<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Rowe, George Clinton, 1853-1903</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Rowe, George Clinton, 1853-1903</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">rowe george clinton 1853 1903</field>
      <field name="author_text">Rowe, George Clinton, 1853-1903</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1890's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_aap/uvaGenText/tei/chaap_D091.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240349</field>
      <field name="date_text">1890</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey African-American Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey African-American Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:410272</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Our Heroes ; Patriotic Poems on Men, Women and Sayings of The Negro Race</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- African American authors</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- African American authors</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Our Heroes ; Patriotic Poems on Men, Women and Sayings of The
</field>
      <field name="title_display">                            Negro Race</field>
      <field name="title_facet">our heroes</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">our heroes</field>
      <field name="title_text">Our Heroes ; Patriotic Poems on Men, Women and Sayings of The
</field>
      <field name="title_text">                            Negro Race</field>
      <field name="year_display">1890</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1890</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1890</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:410272&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:410272&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Rowe, George Clinton, 1853-1903&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;rowe george clinton 1853 1903&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Our Heroes ; Patriotic Poems on Men, Women and Sayings of The</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Negro Race&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;our heroes&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1890&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1890&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Rowe, George Clinton&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1853&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1903&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Our Heroes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Patriotic Poems on Men, Women and Sayings of The</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Negro Race&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charleston, S. C.&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Walker, Evans &amp;amp; Cogswell Co.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1890&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3865065-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chd091&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;68 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- African American authors&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Our Heroes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Patriotic Poems on Men, Women and Sayings of The Negro</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Race&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 88 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted ; verse reproduced elsewhere in</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">African-American Poetry omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-DatabaseAfrAmPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PREFACE. These poems are all based on historical fact, which, in every case, can be substantiated. The object for which they are presented to the public, is to inform our people that there is much unwritten history, of noble deeds, inspiring sayings, and of true manhood and womanhood, undiscovered; and to create that race pride which is necessary to the growth, progress, and prosperity of any people. Trusting that this volume may prove an inspiration to many; and hoping that the success of this, may warrant the issue, from time to time, of other volumes of a series now in contemplation. I am, for the elevation of the Race, Yours ever, GEORGE C. ROWE. INTRODUCTION. The rapid progress which our people have made in the preparation and publication of books is one of the indisputable evidences of culture and refinement Twenty-five years ago, comparatively speaking, we were in total literary darkness, but now there are thousands and thousands of cultured men and women in all sections of our country striving earnestly for the elevation of an oppressed race. Our scholars are at work in all departments of human knowledge. Many are teaching in our schools and colleges; many attending the sick and dying with more than ordinary medical skill; many with learning and eloquence, pleading at the bar of Justice; many grappling with the abstruse problems of the sciences; historians of marvellous patience and prodigious research are bringing to the light of this century the heroic deeds and wonderful achievements of our ancestors, and the poet, with almost Divine inspiration, has thrown his illuminating rays upon the characters of our heroes, and, with the skill of an artistic hand, has woven the threads into a tale of beauty and melody, at once touching, inspiring and sublime. Parents will do well to put these songs of the poet into the hands of their children. J. H. M. POLLARD, Rector of St. Mark's Church, Charleston, S. C. June 9th, 1890. TO OUR HEROES, COURAGEOUS, PATRIOTIC, NOBLE: THIS VOLUME IS GRATEFULLY DEDICATED. Our Heroes! dead and living: Courageous, noble, pure! In war and peace aspiring! Their memory shall endure! Geo. C. Rowe. OUR HEROES. Muse, record on History's pages, And of noble service tell: That our race, in future ages, May with swelling bosoms dwell On the valor of our heroes, Fearless men of Afric race, Who for justice and for freedom, Fought, and won an honored place. For their history is unwritten, It lies buried in the soil With their generous blood besprinkled, And made fertile by their toil! It lies buried in the City Of the Dead, on hill and plain! With their bones! Ah! God in pity! Grant that they may rise again. Rise and shine on memory's tablet With a lustre dazzling, bright,— Circled with a brilliant chaplet, Radiant as the stars of night! Sound the trump of resurrection! Bid the perished thousands live! Send abroad the proclamation— To the world their record give! Tell of Boston, and of Concord, Lexington and Bunker Hill, Burnish bright the noble record, Fill the pages full, until Not a valiant deed is perished, Not a patriotic word: Heroism must be cherished! Of the brave who bear the sword! Tell of Attucks and of Salem, And of unnamed warriors grand, The five thousand valiant soldiers Five thousand negro soldiers, is the official number reported as bearing arms in the Continental army. Fighting for the native land Of their children—not their fathers! Willing to baptize in blood: Hoping not for earthly honors,— Sacrifice to Freedom's God! CRISPUS ATTUCKS. 'Twas not in vain he lived and died; 'Twas not in vain his blood was shed; His spirit still survives: The brave, of every race and clime— In memory's chamber, for all time— The martyr-hero lives. He died? Nay, laid him down and slept: And angels bright their vigils kept Around the patriot's bed. For love he laid his treasure down— The love of freedom was his crown— He sleeps; he is not dead. Brave Attucks! how his honor's shine! We build for him a glorious shrine! His memory will not fade, So long as History's pages stand, Of this our free and favored land, A tribute shall be paid To Attucks, for his valiant deed; To Attucks brave, his blood the seed First planted in this soil, To nourish freedom, and secure For every man while years endure, Freedom in life and toil. But who was Attucks? Afric's son; Who toiled for years, but never won A freeman's just reward. A man of stature, strong and brave, Yet held in bondage as a slave, By men who worshipped God. By men who felt the galling yoke, Of motherland; whose ire awoke Against the tyrant's power; Who cry—Injustice! when the claim For tax is pressed; and loud declaim— We're robbed of rightful dower! To force her claims, the motherland In ships of war, moored at the strand Of this, her new estate; She stationed men in old King Street. These soldiers insolently treat The people of the State. While men of wisdom gathered round, Seeking to know where might be found, Deliverance from the foe,— How to throw off the British yoke, A swarthy negro fearless spoke— And struck the primal blow. Ah! yes, 'tis Attucks! strong and bold, Like giants in the days of old, Who on to conflict led— “This is the nest! Strike the main guard! Strike at the root!” and strike it hard! No need of fear and dread! Then rushed he forward to the fray, Fearless and swordless, charged that day Upon the British band— To make a way for Liberty, Which he was destined ne'er to see In this heaven-favored land. The blow is struck! and then the sound— The roar of battle shakes the ground! And Attucks is no more! No more? a hero's wreath is thine! Around thee deathless laurels twine, And fame from shore to shore! He lies in state in Faneuil Hall; Yes; there upon the sable pall Lies Attucks, true and brave; And, as the people drop a tear, In gratitude, upon his bier, They cry—He's not a slave! And others fell with him that day. And lie beside,—Caldwell, and Gray. And Maverick, and Carr. They lay them gently in one grave. A constellation of the brave! A bright historic star! 'Twas not in vain our hero died; 'Twas not in vain his blood was shed; His spirit still survives; The brave, of every race and clime— In memory's chamber, for all time— The martyr-hero lives! PETER SALEM. It is a clear and cloudless day, The summer sun is high, The midday-zephyrs gently play Beneath the azure sky; The air is ladened with perfume, Of summer flowers in radiant bloom. The birds are singing joyfully Within the woodland vales; The kine are browsing peacefully Over the hills and dales; It is an hour serene and blest, It seems an hour of perfect rest. While beauty lingers everywhere, The heart of man is sad; All nature has, in beauty rare, No power to make him glad: The foe is standing at the gate! It the nation's day of fate! Behind the trench, on Bunker Hill, New England patriots stand, While in the distant city towers The fairest of the land, Who watch the scene with anxious heart— To-day must many love ones part. Now listen to the sullen roar Of the artillery! And strains of martial music soar To thrill and nerve to die— To smite the foe with valiant hand, To die for home, and native land! The plumes of warriors gaily dance; The banners gleam and wave! The sod o'er which they now advance Will prove ere long the grave Of nigh two thousand stalwart men Who hoped to reach their homes again. The sword is flashing from its sheath, The bristling bayonets gleam; The solid earth the sward beneath, Trembles to tread of men— Of soldiers true, in war array, Marching to doom and death that day! Swiftly upon a gallant steed, A single horseman rides, To ask—“Where is the greatest need.” And where the strongest tides Of war and battle will roll in: “At the redoubts it will begin!” Away he gallops to the post Where special danger lay, To the intrenchments, where a host Impatient of delay, Sternly resolve to do and die, To seal their country's destiny! With fearless step the foe advance— How anxious is that hour!— With musket, bayonet and lance, And mien of conscious power. The order passes down the line:— “Reserve your fire till proper time!” A silence grim o'erhangs the scene, A silence, deep and chill; But a few paces intervene The breastworks on the hill: The order “Fire!” rang clear and loud, And on the instant burst a cloud. Out of that cloud a rain of lead, Which swept the foemen down— There lie five hundred soldiers dead, All heaped upon the ground. They charge the battlements again, They rush to death, and charge in vain! The battle raged on Bunker Hill, With fury, long and wild; And trickling downward like a rill The blood the land defiled; And on the air we catch the breath Of war and carnage and of death! But reinforcements now appear, And quick for battle form, Then proudly, grandly they draw near Amid a leaden storm. It is of moments the supreme— A hero enters on the scene. Towering above the parapets Pitcairn, the major stands: “Come on! the day is ours!” he shouts, And proudly waves his hands. While patriots stood in awe and dread— Brave Salem shot the leader dead! The day has passed full many a year Since Bunker Hill was fought; And 'tis with pride that now we hear No braver deed was wrought By men who in the redoubt lay, Than Peter Salem wrought that day! Warren, we write with special pride, Putnam and Prescott brave. But proudly with them we inscribe Salem, the negro slave! For whom arose bright Freedom's star When he enlisted for the war. A stately shaft on Bunker Hill Withstands the test of time, Proudly it tells, and ever will, To men of every clime, That all who shared an honored part, Are cherished in the nation's heart. Postscript: In eighteen-sixteen he laid down To sleep in mother earth, Within the limits of the town Where he was given birth. At Saratoga, Bunker Hill, Concord,—his spirit liveth still! In eighteen hundred eighty-two The town of Framingham, To keep his memory fresh and new— This patriotic man— Placed a memorial o'er the grave Of Salem true, the negro brave. TOUSSAINT L'OVERTURE. HIS ANCESTRY. A tribe surnamed the Arradas, Sojourned for years, on Africa's Southwestern coast. Men of physique and strength of mind, Excelling others of their kind Among a host. Gaou-Gwinou, the chieftain's heir, Hunting the wild beast in his lair, With ruthless hand, Was seized, and hurried to the hold Of a black ship, thence to be sold By slaver band. For Hayti's Isle, the ship was bound, Which years before the Spaniard's found— Luxuriant, fair. The land was rich in fruit and flower, Mountains and valleys—Nature's dower! Oh! beauty rare! The lofty ridge, the rocky height, Present a most inspiring sight, As tier on tier, Up to the clouds their heads arise Seeming to nestle in the skies, They disappear! These look on flow'ry plains below, Where charming, sparkling rivers flow, And fruits abound. While deep within the woodland glen, Too beautiful for tongue or pen. We hear the sound Of forest songsters, sweet and clear, Singing of joy and freedom here For beast and bird; But man, the image of his God, Must bear oppression's cruel rod, From him is heard The sigh, the groan, the sad complaint, Toiling and striving, sick and faint; Hope dying, dead. With wistful eye he scans the sea, Feeling that ocean's depth would be A grateful bed. Gaou-Gwinou was purchased here By a French prince, and many a year He spent—a slave— Upon the Breda property; And there he reared a family And made his grave. HIS BOYHOOD. His eldest son, Arradas' heir, Toussaint L'Overture, who there Was given birth, In seventeen hundred forty-three, Was destined by the gods to be A man of worth. A slender boy, he grew apace; A Prince-apparent of his race! Most eagerly He sat him down at Learning's feast, His teacher, pious Pierre Baptiste Exultingly Taught him to read and write and pray, Some Latin, French, Geometry; To meditate, Upon the precious word of God, His name to magnify, and laud His high estate. To herd the sheep was his employ— This gentle, silent, thoughtful boy. On mountain-wing With Nature vast his soul communed, His very being well attuned Rich strains to sing. Baptiste explained religious lore, Of many a saint long gone before, Now hid in mist; Of noble martyrs, who had died For Him who once was crucified— Lord Jesus Christ. His father taught of Fatherland, Loved Africa, torn from whose strand. Long years ago, He, in the prime of manhood brave, From freedem, to become a slave, Was forced to go. HIS MANHOOD. Thus, up to manhood he arose, A man of wisdom, strength, repose, Integrity; Beloved by all both far and near, Respected for his character And industry. Then he was married to Suzan, A help-meet true for such a man; For many years The loved companion of his life, Sharing his honors, toils and strife, His hopes and fears. In speaking of the life they led, This famous hero, proudly said: “Upon our way To fields we went nor felt the weight Of toil, for love was our estate, The livelong day. God smiled upon us from above, Our pleasure was to show our love— And grateful be, By helping those around in need— Sweet the reward for kindly deed— “'Tis unto me.” He saw with pain the cruel lot Of Brethren dear, and ne'er forgot To humbly pray, That He, who calms the ocean's wave. Would bring deliverance to the slave, And haste the day. In reading, 'neath his gaze there fell Prophetic words, which long and well, And thoughtfully, He pondered, for in them appear Visions of a deliverer From slavery. “Where is the man whom Nature owes To her vexed children—the negroes? He will appear! With standard raised for liberty. Impetuous as a stormy sea, And conquer here. He shall go forth, clothed on with strength, 'Till Freedom's path, its breadth and length, We plainly trace; And everywhere shall people bless This hero, who shall wrongs redress, For human race!” Ah! little did he realize That there revealed before his eyes, His destiny, Was written with the pen of Truth! Destined a martyr from his youth For liberty! HIS PRIME. The years pass on, and overhead, Portentious clouds of fear and dread, Obscure the sky! No ray of hope for bondmen sad, “Whom gods destroy they first make mad!” Then seize their prey. In seventeen hundred ninety-one, Mid-August at the set of sun, There suddenly Appeared upon the evening sky A ruddy glow; we hear the cry— For liberty! The horror of those days, no pen Can tell, of children, women, men, Hurried to death! The masters tortured, shot and burned; The slaves their hideous crimes returned; The very breath. Of realms infernal filled the air! Nor cry, nor groan, nor pleading prayer. Could stay the hand Of voilence, 'twas deaths mælstrom! It seemed indeed the day of doom Throughout the land! From peaceful toil to take his place, As the deliverer of his race Toussaint came forth. This is the man of prophecy, Who, for a noble destiny Was given birth! A leader-born, in manhood's prime, Called to command in God's own time, When there was need; Large-hearted, pure, magnanimous, His policy was glorious, With noble deed! And brightly shone his prosperous star, Red Mars, the harbinger of war, On many a field! Confronted by the valiant band, Under his firm and steady hand, The foemen yield! His dauntless courage everywhere, His power with men, his wisdom rare, Success assure. An inspiration is his name! With pride his followers exclaim: L'Overture! Yes, 'twas Toussaint L'Overture, L'Overture means—The Opening. Who boldly opened freedom's door To Afric's son, Who met the men of Britain, Spain, In war-array, on hill and plain, And nobly won! To win him o'er the British bring Inducement—“Thou shalt be a king Of great renown!” To serve the race his heart desires! To wreath of Freedom he aspires! The richest crown! The war is over; peace again Discovers fields of fruit and grain, In bounty rare! Prosperity on every hand; Free, happy toil, throughout the land! Oh! vision fair! New laws are made, and order reigns; No more the clank of servile chains; But far and near, With one accord—“Our Governor, Shall be Toussaint L'Overture!” From all we hear. This man is chosen for his life, To govern Hayti, freed from strife, And takes his place, Among the rulers of the earth. Destined to rule e'en from his birth! Again we trace! How peaceful are the scenes that we Behold on every hand! how free The people all! 'Tis Jubilee, the year of rest; Each one with royal bounty blessed, Both great and small. But years pass on. The gathering cloud, The rolling peal of thunder loud, Is seen and heard. Oppression rears his hideous head, That hateful foe; the people's dread Is deeply stirred! In eighteen one, great Bonaparte, Proud conqueror with a treacherous heart, Sent forth the word; “That slavery in the Colonies, And in the French Dependencies, Shall be restored!” Now consternation everywhere, And maledictions fill the air. “For liberty! We'll fight until the latest breath! We'll fight for freedom unto death Or victory!” Then sixty ships from shores of France, On waves of ocean gaily dance, With martial crew. “All France to St. Domingo comes! Ah! we must perish with our homes.” Like morning dew! LeClerc with thirty thousand men, Draws near and slays the garrison Of Liberty. Fort Liberty. Holding the sons of brave Toussaint As hostages, he makes a feint Of Amity. “Surrender: and your sons remain! Refuse, we take them back again! To misery! “Take back my sons!” the chief exclaimed; “I can not pay the ransom named— Our liberty!” Then reigned a carnival of blood! Wild revelry—a crimson flood Was everywhere! The sea was red with human gore, For fifteen hundred blacks, and more Were slaughtered there! No quarter, now, for age or sex! The order is to slay and vex The old and young. The rich and poor, of every race, Are, without warning, called to face Death's fiery tongue! Toussaint with burning eloquence, To deeds of valor in defence, Inspired his men: “Remember that the cause of Right, Of Justice, Truth—a righteous fight— Is sure to win!” 'Twas all in vain! The Frenchmen found On St. Domingo's battle-ground, And Hayti's field, A foe they could not overcome; They fought for freedom and for home! They would not yield! “LeClerc in disappointment sore; His troops discouraged, more and more. Issues decree: “Each one who will refuse to fight, Shall have all privilege and right! He shall be free! Deceived; his brother Paul withdraws, Bellair, and gallant Maurepas Submit to France! But brave Toussaint his aid-de-camps Valiant Christoph and Dessalaines With sword advance! A solemn message is received; The wise Toussaint is not deceived, But fear awakes! To pacify his followers, With chief of Frenchmen he confers, And treaty makes. “Submit, and truly, I declare, Shall rights and freedom everywhere Respected be! In rule my colleague thou shalt be; Full rank, and general amnesty, And lenity.” “I might in mountains still remain, And harass thee on hill and plain With brigand's shield; But constant bloodshed I disdain! I fought our freedom to maintain! To terms I yield!” He now retired to Ennery, Surrounded by his family, For rest and peace. A valley, rich and beautiful Where Nature's gifts are bountiful— A great increase. The French, the aged chief annoyed, The soldiers wantonly destroyed His property. His friends indignant recommend To rise in might, his rights defend— His liberty. He made reply to words of strife; “What if my liberty, my life, Is from me shorn? My country's freedom is at stake! I can not now afford to make My people mourn! A letter couched in language fair, Invites our hero to repair To Brunet's home: “Your welfare and the colony, My highest pleasure e'er shall be; Believe me, come!” Without a thought of treachery: Trusting in his sincerity, Nor doubt, nor fear; For love of country he goes forth, To treachery's hand, this man of worth, From freedom dear! Received with honour and respect, Naught but good-will could he detect— A noble part! His host examined heartily The interests of the colony, With map and chart. 'Tis evening's hour, when suddenly Armed men appear, and forcibly, Before he wist, They seize the veteran with the word: “Surrender! Death at point of sword If you resist!” He rose to meet them in his might! 'Tis useless—an unequal fight! No help is near. Such are Injustice's cruel laws! “Heaven will avenge my righteous cause! My God will hear!” 'Tis midnight. With his wife and child, Breast raging with a tempest wild, A storm of grief; Chained—manacled—the guards beside— Toussaint is hurried o'er the tide, Beyond relief! Gazing farewell unto the shore, His home for years, but his no more, He said, with tears; “They have cut down the noble tree, The tree of Freedom, Liberty! But coming years Shall see these rootlets sprout again! Many and deep on hill and plain, And valley broad!” His trust was in a higher power Than France could wield that treacherous hour, Jehovah! God! Without a charge or just complaint, To Castle Joux they bear Toussaint A captive lone, Upon the verge of Switzerland, On Jura's height the castles stand On summit stone! Here in the dreary dungeon cell The brave Toussaint is forced to dwell In misery! Damp, cold, and hunger, his compeers, Grim loneliness, and hideous fears, Continually! He wrote to General Bonaparte: “I served thy cause with my whole heart— Fidelity, What is my crime? Why do I dwell A prisoner in this loathsome cell? My liberty! To these appeals no answers come; No message from the loved at home Glad news to tell! He sent a message to his wife Which never reached her in this life— His last farewell! Reduced by peril, hunger, cold, By longings that can ne'er be told; With failing breath; He bowed beneath the heavy rod, With perfect trust and faith in God, And slept in death! A warrior true of great renown. A hero, martyr, him we crown! He led the van! His heaven-born soul to God has flown! This world of ours has never known A nobler man! Note.— Toussaint died of starvation and exposure to cold in a cell, in Castle Joux, near the border of Switzerland, in 1803, at the age of 60 years. He was confined there eight months, and France refused to give him a trial or to answer his communications. Madame Toussaint sank under the weight of her great afflictions. Her health became very feeble, and at times her mind wandered. When the power of Bonaparte was overthrown, and a new Government was introduced into France, a pension was granted for her support, and her two sons were released from prison. She died in their arms in 1816, thirteen years after the death of our hero. FORT BLOUNT. 'Twas in the beauteous Land of Flowers, And many years ago: Secreted in the sylvan bowers Where birds flit to and fro, On Apalachicola's bank, Below the Georgia line— Now hid by reeds and rushes rank, And stately Southern pine— There stood, in solitude, Fort Blount; A menace to the foe— The enemy who dare attempt To forage from below. A refuge for the pioneer Pursued by Red Men bold; And all who sought protection here, Secured a safe stronghold. In Revolutionary days, The Fort was garrisoned. Parading there to martial lays, On steeds caparisoned, The gallant courtier and the knight With warlike spirit filled, To be prepared for instant fight, There practiced, fenced, and drilled. After the war of eighteen-twelve, In eighteen and fifteen, When 'twixt the nations all was well, A change came o'er the scene: A little band of fugitives From bondage who had fled, Sought here a refuge for their wives, And for their children bread. This band, full forty years before, Had fled from slavery; Hoping, that when the war was o'er, To hold their liberty. They wandered South and made a home, Among the Cherokees, And back and forth for years they roam With Aborigines. Thus, during nearly forty years Their wanderings we trace. Born where forest monarch rears His head in stately grace; Free as the bird on buoyant wings, Gay, healthy, strong, and bold, Resembling, in their wanderings, The Israelites of old. They find, what seems a place of rest, In nature's vast retreat— Like eagles on the mountain's crest— Repose, serene and sweet, Within the ramparts of Fort Blount, Decide to make a home; “Here in this fortress—Zion's Mount— We'll dwell for years to come!” Within this seeming safe retreat, This band of fugitives Enjoyed their labor, truly sweet, Their simple, happy lives. Flocks roaming in the wilderness, Their gardens rich and green; Each “minding his own business,” A cheerful, restful scene. They wist not that the foe ev'n then Was planning to enslave! That this retreat would prove to them No castle—but a grave! The slaver sought the Government To aid his black design, And readily the President Consented to the crime! From Patterson, then in command Of fleet on Mobile Bay: “Reduce Fort Blount, is the demand! Go forth without delay! Loomis, on this grave enterprise, Entrusted unto thee, Thy future surely will depend, Prove thy ability!” On Apalachicola's tide, War ships of great prowess Advance, in martial pomp and pride, To war on helplessness. They reach the Fort, and make demand: “No longer here remain! We come, the inmates to remand To slavery again!” The messengers convey the word To those within the hold! While hearts with consternation stirred Outspoke a Patriarch bold: “No! no! their order we defy!” Each with united breath And patriotic spirit cry: “Our liberty or death!” The Fleet began the cannonade, Great shot fell thick and fast; But all in vain—no heed is paid; And they resolve at last: “Throw hot shot at the magazine! That will break up the nest!” It was a most infernal scheme! How shall I tell the rest? The hot shot reached the magazine! Within no thought of fear! Those sturdy heroes little dream Eternity is near! Hark! hear that sound! it rolls, and rolls! Destruction's heated breath! Alas! three hundred valiant souls Find liberty in death! Note.— The number killed by this explosion, officially reported by the officer in command, Executive document of the 13th Congress, was 270. It must have reached at least 300, as there were 315 souls within the fort, and only 15 of that number were captured and returned to slavery. At the 3rd session of the 25th Congress of the United States, twenty-two years after this event, a bill was reported by a Representative from one of the free States, giving 5,000 from the Public Treasury, as a token of gratitude for the success of this enterprise, passed both Houses, was approved by the President, and became a law on the Statute Books. G. C. R. BISHOP D. A. PAYNE. Hail! thou aged Christian hero! Whither goest thy command? “Marching in the pathway narrow— To our King, Immanuel's Land.” What has been thy earthly mission? Tell the tale of hope and fear: “Study, teaching, exhortation, Preaching Gospel far and near.” Where began thy great commission? When was set an open door? “In my native city, Charleston; Eighteen hundred thirty-four; Where I labored to establish Privileges of the school, Every day advance accomplish, Faithful service, was my rule. I succeeded in this calling, In my school on Anson Street. But, alas! the foe is planning, All my efforts to defeat. Said a measure, which was drafted, In the Legislative hall: Negroes must not be instructed.” Ah! 'twas darkness, like a pall! ‘Fare ye well! my lovely children! Seek God's wisdom, grace and love! Brighter scenes will surely open, Through the Father's hand above!’ Then, my preparation season, For God's work—the ministry; Which, with earnest aspiration I have served with constancy. Prospered by the Lord, my Father; Upheld, strengthened by His hand; Bringing lost ones to the Saviour, Here and there throughout the land. Laboring in the North, the Southland; Laboring in the East, the West: Working for the heavenly restland— All my efforts have been blessed. Early call to rule, a Bishop, “Not sufficient!” I confess; Bowed I down in tears and worship, Feeling my unworthiness! Still my Father has upheld me, All along my pilgrim way. Steadily his hand doth lead me Toward the realms of endless day.” Hast thou wearied on thy journey— Where the thorns and thistles prick? “Fifty years I've served my country, In the School, Church, Bishopric. I would serve God ages longer: I would fight and win the crown! For with age my faith grows stronger: I would fight 'till sun goes down!” Hail! thou faithful Christian soldier! Leading proudly thy command: Journey on! in faith and vigor! Thou shalt reach Immanuel's Land! Thou hast done a work that ages Cannot dim on memory's page, Though the storm, the tempest rages, It shall live from age to age! In that land of Heavenly splendor, Where the pure in heart shall reign; Thou shalt there be crowned—a conqueror! Daniel Alexander Payne! MRS. FRANCES ELLEN HARPER. Faithful Frances Ellen Harper! Truly noble are thy deeds! Using pen and voice with vigor, Thou hast scattered precious seeds! Seeds of truth, of holy living, Seeds of wisdom, temperance; Waking virtuous aspirations; Building up a sure defence, Round our homes, our wives and mothers; Teaching lessons of great worth; Leading on our sons and daughters, In the path of virtue—truth! Lecturing in many a city, With a tongue of living fire! Pungent, eloquent and witty, Thou dost reason and inspire! With thy pen, in happy measure, Thou hast sung the poet's song; Thou hast given us many a treasure— Rich and beautiful and strong! We admire thy noble record, From thy spirit impulse take! Earnestly contending upward, Every day real progress make. Long live Frances Ellen Harper! Voice and pen instruction give! Live thy earnest spirit ever! May thy work forever live! When complete thy earthly missions And from toil thou art at rest: Still, may coming generations Testify, and call thee blest! THE OLD FLAG. “The old flag never touched the ground!” The Sergeant cried, with beaming face; He heeded not the flowing wound,— That noble hero of our race. “The old flag never touched the ground!” Amid the shower of leaden rain, He dragged his wounded limb along, Unmindful of the stinging pain. “The old flag never touched the ground!” He cried with pride, exultingly; Admiring comrades gathered round, And cheered the hero heartily! “The old flag never touched the ground!” Brave Carney's words shall ever live! Adown the ages shall resound, A charm, and aspiration give! “The old flag never touched the ground!” Ah! patriot, hero, brave and pure! With pride we tell the tale around; Thy fame and honor shall endure! Honor to gallant Fifty Fourth! Honor to color-sergeant, brave! O'er all our country—South and North, May stars and stripes forever wave! “The old flag never touched the ground!” With joy the golden motto write! True courage lingers in the sound, And inspiration in the sight. Note.— Sergeant W. H. Carney, of New Bedford, Mass., was very severely wounded when the famous Fifty-fourth Regiment attacked Fort Wagner; but he resolutely held up the stars and stripes, as he dragged his wounded limb along, amid a shower of bullets; and when he reached his comrades he exclaimed exultingly, “The dear old flag has never touched the ground, boys!” BISHOP CAIN. Arrayed in the armor of his God, To war our hero went; In haste the path of Duty trod, On the King's business sent. He wore Salvation's helmet, For sandals Heavenly peace; Above his heart the breastplate Of Truth and Righteousness. To quench the fiery darts of ill, Of wickedness and doubt, The shield of Faith he carried still To keep the tempter out. Proclaiming messages of love, Pointing to mercy seat! “Exhort, rebuke, instruct, reprove,” The order.—No retreat! His forte was burning eloquence, His trusty sword the pen; He fought for truth and temperance— To save the souls of men. Of heroes who have bravely fought, To bring Immanuel's reign, Are none who grander deeds have wrought Than Bishop R. H. Cain. GENERAL SMALLS. It was in Charleston Harbor, Nigh thirty years ago, That the gallant steamer Planter With grace plied to and fro, Ladened with ammunition And food for Boys in Gray, Within the forts, that for defence, Surrounding Charleston lay. There was among the sailors A negro, good and true, Who much preferred to Southern gray A uniform of blue. He worked within the wheel-house; He knew the signal calls And he resolved to run the lines— His name was Robert Smalls. Before the other sailors He doth his plan unfold, And all but two think liberty Dearer than life or gold. And so they make arrangements: “No matter what befalls, We'll make a run for freedom!” Said the heroic Smalls. The ship lies at its moorings Near the “City by the Sea;” The officers to spend the night And with companions be, Have left the ship well ladened With guns and cannon balls, Four sailors true, the engineer And pilot, Robert Smalls. The night was dark and lonely, The hour was three o'clock; When quietly the Planter Was steamed up to the dock. Aboard their wives and children In haste the leader calls; It is an hour with danger fraught For hero, Robert Smalls! Now, out upon the Harbor He steers with steady hand; The shores look dark, forbidding, As he gazes to the land. They reach the point, Fort Sumter, Attention! signal calls; Promptly he blows the whistle 'Tis all right! Pilot Smalls. He steams past Morris Island, The signal answers back; But Sumter signals “Something wrong! Arrest her in her track!” The guns from Morris Island, With ready cannon balls, Send forth a shower of iron hail At Pilot Robert Smalls. But he is out of danger! 'Tis an heroic feat! With all his power he urges Out to the Union fleet! But they mistake his signal— A storm of heavy balls Are ready now to deal out death! To gallant Robert Smalls! Oh, joy! they see his signal, And not a whit too soon! To save a tragedy that night Under the rising moon! But 'twas a happy moment As e'er to mortal falls! When the Union fleet received that ship From hero, Robert Smalls! They've reached the Port of Freedom. This gallant little band! They sought the ground enchanted— To them earth's promised land! For they had felt for many years, Grim slavery's crushing power! It is a time supreme and blest— It is a triumph hour! Detailed blockading pilot He served the cause with pluck! A guide to the Crusader, The Stono,—Keokuk. He made repeated trips along The river, near the shore, Removing the torpedoes thence Which he had sunk before. Sailing through Folly Island creek, Under Confederate gun, The Planter then was in command Of Captain Nickerson,— Commander was demoralized As the leaden shower falls, Fearless he takes the Captain's place— Promoted! Captain Smalls! He served the Union 'till the end Of the great civil strife; Then, as a leader of his race, He entered public life. With honor served his native State As Representative. His work within the Senate will For generations live! And in the State militia He filled an honored place, First Colonel, then a Brigadier, He served with skill and grace; Then Major-General of the troops— This title to him falls. These places with distinction Are filled by General Smalls. At National Convention, In eighteen-seventy-two He votes for Grant and Wilson, Those noble men, and true! In seventy-six and eighty He's called upon again, To stand by Hayes and Wheeler; For Logan and for Blaine. And then he served in Congress, With faithfulness, six years: A sturdy man, of common-sense, Consistent, without fears! We feel in him peculiar pride, As his record to us falls; For he has acted well his part— Honest Congressman Smalls. He failed of re-election But not from failing vote; Because the honest (?) Democrats Counted our hero out. But he is not defeated— To him our ruler calls! The message: You're appointed Collector, Robert Smalls. In canvassing for General Smalls A good Republican Said—“I believe in all the world Smalls is the greatest man!” “Who's greater?” “Why, the Lord, of course, His match was never met!” “Ah!” he replied, triumphantly; “Smalls is a young man yet!” Postscript He stood before the altar, And, standing by his side, A noble woman, good and true, A loving, trusting bride. He trembled when he said “I will;” And perspiration falls,— This man of war, and Congress, Our hero, General Smalls. “I knew the General, 'fore the war For fifteen years or more; I'm sure that he was never known To tremble so before!” Well, many a man can calmly face Musket and cannon balls, Who fears to face a lady fair,— No wonder! General Smalls! They gather in his lovely home, At Beaufort's ocean side, His friends and guests, to wish him joy, And see his winning bride. We wish thee all the blessing That mortal lot befalls, Prosperity, and length of days— General, and Mrs. Smalls! MISS LUCY C. LANEY. Note.— Miss Laney is a graduate of Atlanta University, and has taught school for a number of years in various places in Georgia. She left Savannah, Ga. nearly five years ago, where she was receiving a salary of 400.00 a year, and went to Augusta for the purpose of establishing an Industrial Boarding School, without the promise of aid from any one. She rented a large house (505 Calhoun Street,) became responsible for the support of teachers and the Boarding Department, and began work. The first year her school enrolled 140 pupils; the second, 250, and it has steadily increased in numbers, power and influence. A year ago, a benevolent northern lady gave her 10,000 for the erection of a large Memorial School Building. A site was purchased and the building is now approaching completion. She expects to enter it this fall. Any one desiring to communicate with her, can address her at 505 Calhoun St., Augusta, Ga. G. C. R. Not on the height of Bunker Hill Nor Concord's battle ground, Nor on the field of Vicksburg, will Our heroine be found. Not in the annals of the wars That history records: Not in sayings 'neath the stripes and stars Shall we hear her thrilling words! But where the ranks of the coming men And women may be found, With books and slates and ready pen, Lo! there is her battle ground! Not where the din and conflict reach— Nor hideous bugle toot, But where the patient teachers, teach Ideas how to shoot! To reach the top her mind was bent: Patience and faith her rule; To-day she sits as President Of Haines Industrial School! Among the women of our race We know of few, if any, Who fill a nobler, worthier place— Thou earnest Lucy Laney! WE ARE RISING. Among the sayings of our race, Suggestive and surprising, That fills a most exalted place, Is, “Tell them we are rising.” The question came from Doctor Roy— What to the North your greeting? The answer from a negro boy— “Tell them that we are rising!” Within Atlanta's classic halls, This youth, self-sacrificing, Wrote high his name upon her walls, His motto: “We are rising!” Out in the world he makes his mark, Danger and fear despising, E'er soaring upward like the lark, My Brethren: “We are rising!” He meets the foe with voice and pen, With eloquence surprising! Give us a chance, for we are men! Most surely we are rising! Rising to take our place beside The noble, the aspiring; With energy and conscious pride, To the best things, we're rising! Within the class-room is his place, Greek, Latin, criticising, To raise the youthful of his race, And show the world we're rising! Go forth, my friend, upon your way, Each obstacle despising, Prove by your efforts every day, To all that we are rising! In farming, trade and literature, A people enterprising! Our churches, schools, and home life pure, Tell to the world we're rising! Note.— About a score of years since, Dr. Jos. Roy, of the American Missionary Association, on visiting one of their schools in Georgia, asked the children: “What message shall I take from you to the people of the North? An intelligent boy answered promptly: “Tell them that we are rising!” That boy was Richard Wright, of Augusta, Ga., who has since graduated from Atlanta University, ably filled the editorial chair, and is now Principal of the High School, of Augusta, Ga. Indeed, he is “rising!” TEMPLES OF GOD. Build thou with strength and beauty, A temple grand and fair! Foundation—truth and duty; That temple—character! Build thou with strength and beauty, Young friends of Avery School; True wisdom gain through study; Let prudence be thy rule. With care erect the temple For His indwelling meet; Thy character a temple, With pillars all complete. The rock Discrimination, Which stands for truth and right! Faith, based on education— I know, experience light. Faithful in much and little, Steadfast and firm each hour; Through Christ retrieve the battle— Fidelity is power. Note.— Written for, and used as a conclusion to the Baccalaureate Sermon preached to the Graduating Class of Avery Institute, at Centenary M. E. Church, Charleston, June 15, 1890, from the text found in 1 Kings, 7, 22: “On the top of the pillars was lily work.” Sincere in all life's action, A true and steadfast friend! To win sweet satisfaction, Sincerity defend. The pillar of Self-sacrifice, Thy strength to others give; To highest state of manhood rise— In light of virtue live! The pillar of Benevolence, Love for humanity; Encouragement for temperance And sweetest sympathy The pillar strong of Self-control— Lay firm the corner-stone; Let Self-reliance be thy goal; A failure is the drone! Above the pillars lily-work Of rare and rich design; With Oriental handiwork And treasures of the mine. The lily-work of Confidence Of Faith and Gentleness, Of Power and true Beneficence Of Love and Righteousness! Go forth thou class of Ninety, From Avery Institute! Go forth to do thy duty Through good and ill repute. Stand firm among the heroes, The noble of thy race! Fear not life's raging billows Nor enemies to face. Go forth to all life's duty, With purpose strong and true; Live lives of worth and beauty, And faithful service do! Go forth in golden days of youth. And scatter seeds abroad— To live in Virtue, Honor, Truth— Fit temples of our God! HISTORIC TRUTH. Truth sits enthroned within the sacred Word, Since time was born, her accents have been heard, Bringing men peace, enlightenment and joy, Giving the heart and mind a sweet employ. Those who have sought, have found a friend of worth, Gentle, refined, a queen of noble birth. Oh! Truth Inspired! how rich and full thy store! Possessing thee, what can we wish for more? Through thee we trace the way the Ancients trod, How they were led in providence of God; How they expand, are scattered far and wide, After deliv'rance from the surging tide. Following thee in deep humility, Thou dost reveal—oh! depth of mystery! The mighty God, and King of heaven above, Father Divine, in wondrous, holy love, Making with man a covenant of grace, Op'ning the way to save a fallen race. Never again shall He destroy with flood, That He declared at first was very good; And on the clouds, a pledge of Truth Divine, He sets His bow, an everlasting sign. Filled with delight, the father of a race Enters the way, through wine, of dark disgrace; In nakedness before his grandson's eyes, Standeth exposed—how can he but despise One who forgets his spiritual birth? Forgets that God chose him of all the earth, Prophet to be, and priest of righteousness, To preach the truth, and thus the world to bless. But now his lips in malediction move, Anathema, where nought should be but love; And so the child is cursed for grandsire's crime, Himself, and his descendants for all time: “Servant of servants e'er shall Canaan be”— Punishment dire for thoughtless levity. Three sons had Noah: all within the ark Secured a place, in safety to embark Across the flood, that they in joy might see A period new in the world's history. The surname of the elder son was Shem; The appellation of the second, Ham, And Japheth was the third—each with his wife Believed God's word, and thus insured his life. Shem journeyed east to make himself a home On Asia's soil, and there he ceased to roam. Japheth to the north and west his footsteps bent, For him the scenic land of Europe lent Her charms his mind and spirit to beguile, And there he paused and rested for awhile. Ham journeyed southward to the Syrian shore; Arabia's plains his sandaled footprints bore, And Africa, with all its wealth untold, Its precious woods, its ivory and gold— Spread out in unimagined bounty rare, Its gifts to him, its treasures rich and fair. Here settled Ham, and early in these parts, Flourished the noblest sciences and arts; Vast pyramids, construct with wondrous skill, Which stand to-day a questioning wonder still! What men are these, who built this mighty pile, With labyrinths most marvellous in style? What men are these, who fully understand Geometry and mathematics grand? Who, through the summit-opening, afar, Can, ev'n at midday spy the Polar-star? What men are these? Most surely, it is plain, Men of rich culture, intellect and brain. These are the men to whom we look with pride— Our ancestry; in sciences the guide To all the world—no need is there of shame, No reason why we should despise our name! Then let us all scan well the historic page, Tracing the line direct from age to age; Thus gaining light, encouragement and zeal, That in life's work, our hearts may always feel A conscious power, a manhood pure and free, Which is in truth the highest liberty! MOVE FORWARD!</field>
   </doc>
</add>