<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Peacham, Henry, 1576-1643</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Peacham, Henry, 1576-1643</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">peacham henry 1576 1643</field>
      <field name="author_text">Peacham, Henry, 1576-1643</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.0698.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1612</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:463463</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Greek, Modern (1453- )</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Minerva Britanna ; Or A Garden of Heroical Deuises, furnished, and adorned with Emblemes and Impresa's of sundry natures, Newly devised, moralized, and published, By Henry Peacham</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">Minerva Britanna ; Or A Garden of Heroical Deuises, furnished, and adorned with Emblemes and Impresa's of sundry natures, Newly devised, moralized, and published, By Henry Peacham</field>
      <field name="title_facet">minerva britanna</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">minerva britanna</field>
      <field name="title_text">Minerva Britanna ; Or A Garden of Heroical Deuises, furnished, and adorned with Emblemes and Impresa's of sundry natures, Newly devised, moralized, and published, By Henry Peacham</field>
      <field name="year_display">1612</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1612</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1612</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463463&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463463&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Peacham, Henry, 1576?-1643?&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;peacham henry 1576 1643 &lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Minerva Britanna ; Or A Garden of Heroical Deuises, furnished, and adorned with Emblemes and Impresa's of sundry natures, Newly devised, moralized, and published, By Henry Peacham&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;minerva britanna&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1612&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1612&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Peacham, Henry&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1576&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1643&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Minerva Britanna&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Or A Garden of Heroical Deuises, furnished, and adorned with Emblemes and Impresa's of sundry natures, Newly devised, moralized, and published, By Henry Peacham&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed ... by Wa: Dight&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1612&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp2995&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;gre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;[14], 212 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Minerva Britanna&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Or A Garden of Heroical Deuises, furnished, and adorned with Emblemes and Impresa's of sundry natures, Newly devised, moralized, and published, By Henry Peacham&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 245 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted; Latin verse omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Epigramma Authoris. Se dicit Servum modo patre superstite Princeps, Primus at Imperio Servus HIC, IN DE regit. TO THE RIGHT HIGH AND MIGHTIE HENRIE, ELDEST SONNE OF our Soveraigne Lord the KING, Prince of Wales, Duke of Cornwall and Rothsay and Knight of the most noble order of the Garter. VPON THE AVTHOVR AND HIS MINERVA. Pallas thou hast a second champion bred, As great in Artes, as was stout DIOMED In Armes; that gainst enraged MARS could stand, And dar'd to wound faire VENVS in the hand: The ARGIVE fleete his sole Arme could defend, And with the Gods he durst alone contend; All this thy influence gaue, and more desired, Like power thou hast into this braine inspired: Thy champion too, whose Artes are fam'd as farre, As was TYDIDES for his deedes of warre. We know thou art MINERVA that alike Hold'st Artes and Armes, canst speake as well as strike. Tho: Heywood. VPON THE AVTHOVR AND HIS MINERVA. All eies behold, and yet not all alike, Effects, and defects, both are in the eie, As when an obiect gainst the eie doth strike, Th' imagination straightwaies doth implie Shapes, or what else the obiect doth present, Weaker or stronger, as the sight is bent. Within the minde two eies there are haue sight, To iudge of thinges interiour hauing sence; Foresight, and Insight; Iudgment makes them bright And most perspicuous through intelligence. Foresight, foreseeth harmes, that may ensue: Insight, doth yeild to reason what is due. Then let not men deeme all with corp'rall ei'ne, Eies may deluded be by false illusions: Eies may be partiall, eiesight may decline By weakenes, age, or by abusions. Pride, envie, folly, may the sight pervert, And make the eie transgresse against the heart. VVith outward ei'ne first view, and marke this booke, Variety of obiects much will please; VVith inward ei'ne then on the matter looke, Foresee the Authours care, and little ease T' invent, t' imprint, and publish for delight, And for reward but craues your good insight. Peacham my friend, I must confesse to thee, My Insight is but weake; such as it is, I verdict thus, no better worke I see Of this same kinde, nothing I finde amisse, If any fault there be, it is not thine, The fault shall rest in mens imperfect ei'ne. William Segar Garter. Principall king of Armes. TO MASTER HENRY PEACHAM. A VISION VPON THIS HIS MINERVA. Methought I saw in dead of silent night A goodly Citie all to cinders turned, Vpon whose ruines sate a Nymphe in white, Rending her haire of wiery gold, who mourned Or for the fall of that faire Citie burned, Or some deare Loue, whose death so made her sad: That since no ioye in worldly thing she had. This was that GENIUS of that auntient TROY, In her owne ashes buried long agoe: So grieu'd to see that BRITAINE should enioy Her PALLAS, whom she held and honour'd so: And now no litle memorie could show To eternize her, since she did infuse, Her Enthean soule, into this English Muse. E. S. [PART I] Nisi desuper. To my dread Soveraigne iames, King of great britaine. A secret arme out stretched from the skie, In double chaine a Diadem doth hold: Whose circlet boundes, the greater Britannie, From conquered Fravnce, to Thvle sung of old: Great Iames, whose name be yond the inde is told: To god obliged so by two-fold band, As borne a man, and Monarch of this land. Thus since on heauen, thou wholly dost depend: And from aboue thy Crowne, and being hast: With malice vile, in vaine doth man intend, T'vnloose the knot that God hath link't so fast: Who shoot's at heaven, the arrow downe at last Lightes on his head: and vengeance fall on them, That make their marke, the Soveraigne Diadem. Initium Sapientiæ. A poysonous Serpent wreathed vp around In scalie boughtes, a sharpe two edged Sword, Supported by a booke vpon the ground, Is worldly wisedome grounded on gods word, The which vnlesse our proiects doth sustaine, Our plot is nought, and best devises vaine. What ever then thou hap to take in hand, In formost place, the feare of god preferre, Else, like the Foole thou buildest on the sand, By this (the Lesbian stone) thou canst not erre, Which who so doth, his first foundation lay, Contriues a worke that never shall decay. Cui cedet. Two handes togeither heere with griping hold, And all their force, doe striue to take away This burning Lampe, and Candlestick of Gold, Whose light shall burne in spite of Hell for ay: And brighter then the beames of Phoebvs shine, For tis the Truth so holy and divine. Which foule Ambition hath so often vext, And swelling pride of Prælates put in doubt, With Covetuousnes that greedie Monster next, That long I feare me since it had bene out, Did not thy hand (deare Saviour) from aboue Defend it so, that it might never moue. Nusquam tuta. The silly Hind among the thickets greene, While nought mistrusting did at safetie goe, His mortall wound receiu'd with arrow keene Sent singing from a Sheepeheard's secret bowe; And deadly peirc'd, can in no place abide, But runnes about with arrow in her side. So oft we see the man whome Conscience bad Doth inwardly with deadly torture wound, From place to place to range with Furie mad, And seeke his ease by shifting of his ground The meane neglecting which might heale the sinne, That howerly ranckles more and more within. Philautia. A virgins face with Robes of light aray, Why hath (Selfe-loue) our Poets thee assign'd? Philaut: Loue should be young, and fresh as merry may, Such clothing best agreeth with my mind. What meanes that poisonous Serpent in thy hand? Philaut: My bane I breed, by this you vnderstand. I'th other hand say why that looking glasse? Since in thee no deformitie I find, Philaut: Know how in Pride Selfe-loue doth most surpasse, And still is in her Imperfections blind: And saue her owne devises doth condemne, All others labours, in respect of them. Humane traditiones. At last my braunch doth wither and decay, And with the ruine downe my selfe doe fall, Whose pride did loath on surer ground to stay, But needes would raigne as King vpon the wall, To overlooke in scorne the shrubs below, That did (I find) in greater safetie growe. By this same tree, are all Traditions ment, And what else hammer'd out of humane braine, That on the Rocke, to rest are not content, But puffed vp with pride, and glory vaine; Vnto their shame, doe moulder downe, and fall, As doth this Elder growing on the wall. Cuique et nemini. My hope is heauen, the crosse on earth my rest, The foode that feedes me is my Saviours bloud, My name is faith to all I doe protest, What I beleeue is Catholique and good, And as my Saviour strictly doth commaund, My good I doe with close and hidden hand. Nor Heresie, nor Schisme, I doe maintaine, But as christ's coate so my beliefe is one, I hate all fancies forg'd of humane braine, I let contention and vaine strifes alone; If ought I neede I craue it from aboue, And liue with all in Charitie and Loue. Nec metuas nec optes. The Æthiopian Princes at their feastes, Did vse amid their cates, and costly cheere A deadmans head, to place before their guestes, That it in minde might put them what they were: And phillip dayly caused one to say, Oh King remember that thou art but clay. If Pagans could bethinke them of their end, And make such vse of their mortalitie, With greater hope their course let christians bend, Vnto the haven of heavens fœlicitie; And so to liue while heere we drawe this breath, We haue no cause to feare, or wish for death. Isalms David. To the right Reverend Father in god, iohn Bishop of London. To sundry keies doth hilarie compare The holy Psalmes of that prophetique King, Cause in their Natures so dispos'd they are, That as it were, by sundry dores they bring, The soule of man, opprest with deadly sinne, Vnto the Throne, where he may mercy winne. For wouldst thou in thy Saviour still reioyce, Or for thy sinnes, with teares lament and pray, Or sing his praises with thy heart and voice, Or for his mercies giue him thankes alway? Set davids Psalmes, a mirrour to thy mind, But with his Zeale, and heavenly spirit ioin'd. Prius ablue sordes. Who takes in hand to turne this sacred booke, And heavenly wisedome, doth from hence require, His handes be cleane, I wish him first to looke: No Dog or Swine, that walloweth in the mire, Let dare to come, this pretious Iewell nigh, The foe to filth, and all impuritie. But if thou needes wilt launch into this sea, Where Lambes may wade, and Elephants may swimme, Cast all vncleane affections away, And first with heartie prayer call on him, Whose holy Spirit must guide thee in the sence, A thousand times else better thou wert thence. Sic pacem habemus. To the High and mightie IAMES, King of greate Britaine, Twoo Lions stout the Diadem vphold, Of famous Britaine, in their armed pawes: The one is Red, the other is of Gold, And one their Prince, their sea, their land and lawes; Their loue, their league: whereby they still agree, In concord firme, and friendly amitie. Bellona henceforth bounde in Iron bandes, Shall kisse the foote of mild triumphant Peace, Nor Trumpets sterne, be heard within their landes; Envie shall pine, and all old grudges cease: Braue Lions, since, your quarrell's lai'd aside, On common foe, let now your force be tri'de. Quæ plantivi irrigabo. The Thistle arm'd with vengeaunce for his foe, And here the Rose, faire Cytheraeas flower; Together in perpetuall league doe growe, On whome the Heavens doe all their favours power; “For what th' Almighties holy hand doth plant, “Can neither cost, or carefull keeping want. Magnifique Prince, the splendour of whose face, Like brightest Phoebvs vertue doth reviue; And farre away, light-loathing vice doth chase, These be thy Realmes; that vnder thee doe thriue, And which vnite, gods providence doth blesse, With peace, with plentie, and all happines. TO THE THRICE VERTVOVS, AND FAIREST OF QVEENES, ANNE QVEENE OF GREAT BRITAINE. In Anna regnantium arbor. Anna Britannorum Regina. An Oliue lo, with braunches faire dispred, Whose top doth seeme to peirce the azure skie, Much seeming to disdaine, with loftie head The Cedar, and those Pines of Thessalie, Fairest of Queenes, thou art thy selfe the Tree, The fruite thy children, hopefull Princes three. Which thus I ghesse, shall with their outstretcht armes, In time o'respread Europa's continent, To shield and shade, the innocent from harmes, But overtop the proud and insolent: Remaining, raigning, in their glories greene, While man on earth, or Moone in heauen is seene. Fatum subscribat Eliza. To the most excellent Princesse Elizabeth, onely Daughter to our Soveraigne Lord King Iames, King of Great Britaine. Elisabetha Steuarta. Has Artes beata velit. Faire Princesse, great, religious, modest, wise, By birth, by zeale, behauiour, iudgment sound, By whose faire arme, my Muse did first arise, That crept before full lowly on the ground, And durst not yet from her darke shade aspire, Till thou sweete Sunne, didst helpe to raise her higher. Thus since by thee, shee hath her life and sappe, And findes her growth by thy deere cherishment, In thy faire eie consistes her future hap: Heere write her fate, her date, her banishment, Or may she that day-lasting Lillie be, Or Soli-seqvivm e're to follow thee. Auspice cœlo. To the most Christian King lovis, XIII. King of fravnce and navarre. Henricus IV Galliarum Rex. In Herum exurgis Ravillac. Most Christian King, if yet hast turn'd away, Those kindly rivers, from thy royall eies For Fathers losse, this little view I pray Our Muse reserues from his late Exequies: The least of littles, yea though lesse it be, It's thine, and signe, of her loues loyaltie. Which, wheresoe're presented to thy view, (For all thinges teach vs) thinke a heavenly mind Is meant vnto thee, by that cullour Blew, The Gold, the golden plentie thou dost find; The number of thy Heaven-sent Lillies, three, Is concord's ground, the sweetest harmonie. Vnita valebunt. To the high and mightie Phillip King of Spaine &amp;c. To you great Prince, strong stay, and powerfull prop Of Christian state, who by thy feared might, And restles care; the same supportest vp; From neighbour Mahovnds vndermining spight; From thy Gade's pillars, to the west as farre, As Thetis leades vs to the Southerne starre. I offer vp these Arrowes, with the Tree Of thy Grenade, the Symbole long agoe Of great Fernando's famous In the time of King Henry the 7. in memory of which battaile wonne by Archerie, the sheofe of Arrowes is yet giuen on the Spanish coine victorie, What Time he gaue the Moores their overthrow: Though here it may impart, the fruite that springes By Peace and concord of all Christian Kinges. TO THE MOST RENOWNED, AND Hopefull, Henrie, Prince of VVales, &amp;c. ????????????? ?? ?????. henricvs Walliæ Princeps. Par Achillis, Puer vnevinces. Thvs, thus young Henry, like Macedo's sonne, Ought'st thou in armes before thy people shine. A prodigie for foes to gaze vpon, But still a glorious Load-starre vnto thine: Or second Phoebvs whose all piercing ray, Shall cheare our heartes, and chase our feares away. That (once as Phillip) Iames may say of thee, Thy Britaine scarcely shall thy courage hold, That whether Tvrke, Spaine, Fravnce, or Italie, The Red-shanke, or the Irish Rebell bold, Shall rouze thee vp, thy Trophees may be more, Then all the Henries ever liu'd before. E corpore pulchro Grazior. TO THE RIGHT NOBLE, AND MOST TOWARDLY YOVNG PRINCE, CHARLES DVKE OF YORKE. Sweete Duke, that bear'st thy Fathers Image right Aswell in bodie, as thy towardly mind; Within whose cheeke me thinkes in Red and white Appeare the Roses yet againe conioind; Where, howsoe're their warres appeased be, Each, striues with each, for Soveraignitie. Since Nature then in her faire-Angell mould, Hath framd thy bodie, shew'd her best of art: Oh let thy mind the fairest virtues hold, Which are the beautie of thy better part: And which, (braue Charles) shall make vs loue thee more, Then all thy state we outwardly adore. TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE robert, EARLE OF salisbvrie AND LORD HIGH TREASORER OF england &amp;c. ROBERTVS CAE CILIVS. Is cœlebs, Vrit cura. Th' Arabian Phoenix heere, of golden plumes, And bicie brest, vpon a sacred pile Of sweetest odors, thus himselfe consumes; By force of Phoebvs fiery beames, the while, From foorth the ashes of the former dead, A faire, or fairer, by and by is bred. You, you (Great Lord) this wondrous Phoenix are, Who wast your selfe in Zeale, and whot desire, Of Countries good, till in the end your care Shall worke your end, as doth this Phoenix fire. But while you are consuming in the same, You breede a second, your immortall Fame. His servire. To the Right Honourable and my singuler good Lord Henry Hovvard Earle of Northhampton, Lord Privie Seale. &amp;c. HENRICVS HOVVARDVS Comes Northamptoniensis. Pius, Castus huic mentis honor, mere honorandus. A snow-white lion by an Altar sleepes, (Whereon of Virtue are the Symboles plac't,) Which day and night, full carefully he keepes, Least that so sacred thing mought be defac't By Time, or Envie, who not farre away, Doe lurke to bring the saine vnto decay. Great Lord, by th' Altar Pietie is ment, Thus, wherevpon is virtue seated sure: Which thou protectest with deare cherishment; And dost thy best, their safetie to procure By howerly care, as doth this Lion white Tipe of thy mildnes, and thy feared might, Gloria Principum. To the right truely Noble, and most Honourable Lord VVilliam, Earle of Penbrooke. A Ladie faire, who with Maiestique grace, Supportes a huge, and stately Pyramis. (Such as th'old Monarches long agoe did place, By Nilv's bankes, to keepe their memories;) Whose brow (with all the orient Pearles beset,) Begirte's a rich and pretious Coronet. Shee Glorie is of Princes, as I find Describ'd in Moneies, and in Meddailes old; Those Gemmes are glorious proiectes of the mind, Adorning more their Roiall heades, then Gold. The Pyramis the worldes great wonderment, Is of their fame, some lasting Moniment. Ragione di stato. To the right Honourable Sir Ivlivs Caesar, Knight. Who sits at sterne of Common wealth, and state Of's chardge and office heere may take a view, And see what daungers howerly must amate, His Atlas-burden, and what cares accrew At once, so that he had enough to beare, Though Hercvles, or Briarevs he were. He must be strongly arm'd against his foes Without, within, with hidden Patience: Be seru'd with eies, and listening cares of those, Who from all partes can giue intelligence To gall his foe, or timely to prevent At home his malice, and intendiment. That wand is signe of high Authoritie, The Poppie heads, that wisdome would betime, Cut of ranke weedes, by might, or pollicie, As mought molest, or over-proudly clime: The Lion warnes, no thought to harbour base, The Booke, how lawes must giue his proiectes place. His ornari aut mori. To the right Honourable, and most noble Lord, Henry, Earle of Southampton. Three Girlondes once, Colonna did devize For his Impresa, each in other ioin'd; The first of Olive, due vnto the wise, The learned brow, the Lavrell greene to bind: The Oken was his due aboue the rest, Who had deserued in the Battaile best. His meaning was, his mind he would apply By due desert, to challenge each, his prize: And rather choose a thousand times to die, Then not be learned, valiant, and wise. How fewe alas, doe now adaies we finde (Great Lord) that beare, thy truely noble mind. [When Troian youth went out into the field] When Troian youth went out into the field, With courage bold, against the Greekes to fight; With naked Sword they marched, and their Shield Devoide of charge, saue only painted white: Herein the Captaine with his hand did write, (The Battaile done,) some Ensigne of his fame, Who had by valour, best deseru'd the same. Oh Age of Iustice, yet vnlike to this Wherein wee liue, where Mome and Midas share In vertues merit, and th' inglorious is Allow'd the place sometimes in Honours chaire, Wherein Armes, ill, but worser, Artes doe fare, Times hast, be gone, with all the speede ye may, That thus we liu'd, no after Age may say. Fœlicitas publica. To my Honourable Lord OLIVER Lord Saint IOHN of Bletnesho. Foelicitie by Ivlia once devis'd This shape doth beare, a Ladie louely bright With Mercuries Caduceus, enthroniz'd, Her golden haire with flowery girlonds dight: The horne of plentie, th'other hand doth hold With all the fruites, and dainties may be told. For why? content, she raigneth like a Queene; Richest in Quiet, and the Muses skill, Without the which, wee most vnhappie beene The plentie that her horned cup doth fill; Our labours fruite, the which when we possesse Wee haue attaind our worldly happines. Doctrina. Heere Learning sits, a comely Dame in yeares; Vpon whose head, a heavenly dew doth fall: Within her lap, an opened booke appeares: Her right hand shewes, a sunne that shines to all; Blind Ignorance, expelling with that light: The Scepter shewes, her power and soveraigne might. Her out spread Armes, and booke her readines, T' imbrace all men, and entertaine their loue: The shower, those sacred graces doth expresse By Science, that do flow from heaven aboue. Her age declares the studie, and the paine; Of many yeares, ere we our knowledge gaine. Sine refluxu. TO the honourable Lord, the L: Harrington. The Caspian Sea, as Histories do show, (Whome Rocky Shores, on every side surround,) Was never seene by man, to ebbe and flow: But still abides the same, within his bound; That drought no whit, diminisheth his store, Nor neighbour streames, augment his greatnes more. Thus should we beare, one and the selfe-same saile, In what ere fortune, pleaseth God to send, In mid'st of trouble, not of courage faile, Nor be to proude, when fortune is our frend: And in all honest actes, we take in hand, Thus constant, in our resolutions stand. His altiora. TO the honourable the Lord Wootton. Yee Noblest sprightes, that with the bird of Iove, Haue learnt to leaue, and loath, this baser earth, And mount, by your inspired thoughtes aboue, To heaven-ward, home-ward, whence you had your birth: Take to you this, that Monarches may envie, Your heartes content, and high fœlicitie. You, you, that over-looke the cloudes of care, And smile to see a multitude of Antes, Vppon this circle, striuing here and there, For Thine and Mine, yet pine amid their wantes; While yee your selues, sit as spectators free, From action, in their follies tragædie. Sol alter, veritas. To the Honourable Sir Edvvard Coke, Lord-cheife Iustice of the commen Pleas. The fiery Coales, that in the silent night, (When vaile of darknes, all had overspred) With glowing heate, about did giue their light, Since glorious Phoebvs hath discovered Doe loose foorthwith their splendor, at his sight: And of themselues, doe fall to Cinders quite. So traiterous proiectes, while they lie obscure, They closely feede the plotter, with their light, Who thinkes within, he hath the matter sure, Not dreaming how, the Truth that shineth bright; Will soone reveale the secret of his thought; And bring his ripest practises to nought. Rex medicus patria. A Dragon lo, a Scepter grasping fast Within his paw: doth shew a King should be Like Æsculapius, ev'er watchfull plac't; Amongst his subiects, and with skill to see, To what ill humors, of th'infectious mind. The multitude, are most of all inclind. And when he findes corruption to abound, In that Huge body, of all vices ill, To purge betimes, or else to launch the wound, Least more, and more, it ranckles inward still: Or when he would, it bring to former state, Past all recure, his phisick comes to late. Protegere Regium. While deadly foes, their engines haue prepard, with furie fierce, to batter downe the walles, My dutie is the Citie gate to guard, And to rebate their Rammes, and fierie balls: So that if firmely, I do stand without, Within the other, neede no daunger doubt Dread Soveraigne IAMES, whose puissant name to heare, The Turke may tremble, and the Traitor pine: Belou'd of all thy people, farre and neere: Bee thou, as this Port-cullies, vnto thine, Defend without, and thou within shalt see, A thousand thousand, liue and die with thee. Ilies et ingenium. To the worthie Ladie the L: E: W. The feircest natures; whome in youthfull prime, Nor counsel good, nor reasons rule, could tame, Are by their owne experience, and in time; To order brought, and taught themselves to frame, To honest courses, and to loath the waies; So well they liked, in their youthfull daies. Why then dispaire yee Madame, of your sonne, Whose wit, as in the sappe, doth but abound: These braunches prun'd, that over rancklie runne, You'le find in time, the bodie inward sound: When Dullard sprightes, like fenny flagges belowe, Or fruictles beene, or rot while they do grow. Labor viris convenis. TO the most Honorable Lord, the L: Dingwell. Who thirsteth after Honor, and renowne, By valiant act, or lasting worke of wit: In vaine he doth expect, her glorious crowne, Except by labor, he atcheiveth it; And sweatie brow, for never merit may, To drousie sloath, impart her living bay. HAMILCARS sonne, hence shall thy glory liue, Who or'e the Alpes, didst foremost lead the way, With Cæsars eeke, that would the onset giue, And first on foote, the deepest foor'ds assay: “Let Carpet Knightes, of Ladies favours boast, “The manly hart, brave Action loveth most. Ex malis moribus bonæ leges. To the most iudicious, and learned, Sir FRANCIS BACON, Knight. The Viper here, that stung the sheepheard swaine, (While careles of himselfe asleepe he lay,) With Hysope caught, is cut by him in twaine, Her fat might take, the poison quite away, And heale his wound, that wonder tis to see, Such soveraigne helpe, should in a Serpent be. By this same Leach, is meant the virtuous King, Who can with cunning, out of manners ill, Make wholesome lawes, and take away the sting, Wherewith foule vice, doth greeue the virtuous still: Or can prevent, by quicke and wise foresight, Infection ere, it gathers further might. To the right worshipfull Sir Thomas Chaloner, Knight. Est hac almus honor. Thomas Chalonerus. Heere Virtue standes, and doth impart a scroule, To living fame, to publish farre and neere: The man whose name, she did within enroule, And kept to view, vnseene this many yeare, That erst me thought, she seemed to envie, The world his worth, his fame, and memorie. But since she sees, the Muse is left forlorne, And fortune fawning, on the worthles wight, And eke her selfe, not cherisht as beforne. She bringes Mœcenas once againe to light: The man (if any else) a frend to Artes, And good rewarder, of all best desertes. Virtus Romanaet antiqua. To the right worshipfull Sir DAVID MVRRAY Knight. Thvs HERCULES, the Romanes did devise, And in their Temples, him a place assignd: To represent vnto the peoples eies, The image of, th' Heroique virtuous mind: Who like ALCIDES, to her lasting praise, In action still, delightes to spend her dayes. Within whose hand, three apples are of gold, The same which from th' Hesperides he fetcht, These are the three Heroique vertues old, The Lions skinne, about his shoulders stretcht, Notes fortitude, his Clubbe the crabbed paine, To braue atcheiuements, ere we can attaine. Sic vtile dulci. Ad generosissimum et opt: spei iuvenem Nobilem D.C.M. in Italiane nuperrime profectum. The Spartan virgines, ere they had composed; Theire Girlonds, of the fairest flowers to sight: The wholesom'st herbes, they heere withall inclosed, And so their heades, full iollily they dight, In memorie of that same leach they wright: Who first brought simples, and their vse to light. So ye braue Lord, who like the heavenly Sphære, Delight in motion, and aboute to roame: Must learne to mixe in travaile farre and neere, With pleasure profite, that returning home; Your skill, and Iudgment, more may make you knowen; Then your French suite, or locke so largly growen. For who's he, that's not ravisht with delight, Farre Countries, Courtes, and Cities, straung to see; To haue old Rome, presented to his sight: Troy-walls, or Virgils sweete Parthenope. Yet nothing worth, vnles ye herewith find, The fruites of skill, and bettering of your mind. Tandem divulganda. The waightie counsels, and affaires of state, The wiser mannadge, with such cunning skill, Though long lockt vp, at last abide the fate, Of common censure, either good or ill: And greatest secrets, though they hidden lie, Abroad at last, with swiftest wing they flie. Ope mutua. To the right worshipfull and my singuler good frend Mr: ADAM NEWTON Secretarie to Prince Henry. The Laurel ioyned to the fruitefull vine, In frendly league perpetually doe growe, The Laurell dedicate to wits divine, The fruite of Bacchus that in clusters growe, Are such as doe enioy the world at will, And swimme in wealth, yet want the muses skill. This frendship should inviolate remaine, The rich with Bountie should rewarde the Artes, The living muse should gratefully againe, Adorne Mœcenas with her learned partes: And when his branch is drie, and withered seene, By her support, preserue him alway greene. Salomonis prudentia. To the right worshipfull Sir DAVID FOVLIS Knight. The meanes of wisedome, heere a booke is seene, Sometime the glory of great Salomon, A Cedar branch, with Hysope knotted greene, The heart and eie withall, plac'd herevpon: For from the Cedar saith the Text he knew, Vnto the Hysope, all that ever grew. The eie and heart, doe shew that Princes must, In weightiest matters, and affaires of state, Not vnto others over rashly trust, Least with repentance they incurre their hate, But with sound iudgment, and vnpartiall eie, Discerne themselues twixt wrong and equitie. Vicinorum amicitia. Svch frendly league, by nature is they say; Betwixt the Mirtle, and Pomegranate tree, Who, if not planted over-farre away, They seeke each others mutuall amitie: By open signes of Frendship, till at last, They one another haue with armes embrac't. Which doth declare, how neighbours should vnite Themselues together, in all frendly loue; And not like Tyrants, excercise their spight, On one another, when no cause doth moue: But letting quarrels, and old grudges cease, Be reconcild, to liue, and die, in peace. To the right worshipfull Sir Edmund Ashfeild Knight. Edmund Ashfeild. I fledd vnshamed. The clouded Sunne, that westward left our sight, And for a night, in THETIS lap had slept, Againe's return'd, with farre more glorious light, “To cheere the world, that for his absence wept: His beames retaining, vncorrupt and pure, Although he lay imprison'd and obscure. So, Sir, although the cloudes of troubles, had A while conceald you, from your louing frendes; You doe appeare at length to make them glad, And so much higher still your name ascendes, By how much Envie, seeketh to oppresse, And dimme the splendor of your Worthines. Prœmio et pœna. The vernant Bay, with liuing fame shall crowne, Victorious Cæsar, or sweete Maro's brow, As due reward of Learning, and renowne: To Iustice hand, we do the Sword allow: For by these two, all common-wealthes doe stand, And virtue is vpheld in every land. For Honor, Valour drawes her sword to fight, Devoide of feare, or cuts the foamy surge: The Muse for glorie labours day and night, To braue attempts, yea this doth cowards vrge: When Iustice sword, th' inglorious and the base, Vnworthy life, pursues with all disgrace. Quæ pondere maior. Behold a hand, extended from the sky; Doth steddilie a peized ballance hold, The dreadfull Cannon, in one scale doth ly, The Bay ith'other, with a pen of Gold; Due to the Muse, and such as learned are, Th'other Symbole, of th'art Militar. Though MARS defendes the kingdome with his might, And braues abroad his foe, in glorious armes, Yet wiser PALLAS guides his arme aright, And best at home preventes all future harmes: Then pardon Soveraigne, if the pen and bay, My better part, the other downe doe wey. Hibernica Respub: ad Iacobum Regem. While I lay bathed in my natiue blood, And yeelded nought saue harsh, &amp; hellish soundes: And saue from Heauen, I had no hope of good, Thou pittiedst (Dread Soveraigne) my woundes, Repair'dst my ruine, and with Ivorie key, Didst tune my stringes, that slackt or broken lay. Now since I breathed by thy Roiall hand, And found my concord, by so smooth a tuch, I giue the world abroade to vnderstand, Ne're was the musick of old Orpheus such, As that I make, by meane (Deare Lord) of thee, From discord drawne, to sweetest vnitie. Pœnitentia. Heere sits Repentance, solitarie, sad; Her selfe beholding in a fountaine cleare, As greeuing for the life, that she hath lad: One hand a fish, the other birch doth beare, Wherewith her bodie, she doth oft chastize; Or fastes, to curbe her fleshly enimies. Her solemne cheare, and gazing in the fount, Denote her anguish, and her greife of soule, As often as her life, she doth recount, Which Conscience doth, with howerly care enroule, The cullor greene, she most delightes to weare, Tells how her hope, shall overcome dispaire. Dolus. Of simple looke, with countenance demure, In golden coate, lo heere DECEITE doth stand, With eies to heauen vpcast, as he were pure, Or never yet, in knau'ry had a hand, Whose nether partes, resemble to our sight, The figure of a fearefull Serpent right. And by his side, a Panther close you see, Who when he cannot easily catch his pray, Doth hide his head, and face, with either knee, And shew his back, with spots bespeckled gay To other Beastes: which while they gaze vpon, Are vnawares, surprized every one. Crimina gravissima. Vpon a Cock, heere Ganimede doth sit, Who erst rode mounted on IOVES Eagles back, One hand holdes Circes wand, and ioind with it, A cup top-fil'd with poison, deadly black: The other Meddals, of base mettals wrought, With sundry moneyes, counterfeit and nought. These be those crimes, abhorr'd of God and man, Which Iustice should correct, with lawes severe, In Ganimed, the foule Sodomitan: Within the Cock, vile incest doth appeare: Witchcraft, and murder, by that cup and wand, And by the rest, false coine you vnderstand. Virtutem aut vitium sequi Genus. A Familie in Libia's said to be, For prowesse, farre renown'd aboue the rest: With whome no wholesome diet can agree, But easilie, all poison they digest: The Aspe, the Adder, and the vipers broode, Are said to yeeld their ordinarie foode. To these infected races, I resemble, Of Traitors vile, as Gourie and the rest, To tell whose legend, each good heart may tremble, While Psilli-like, they suck from Mothers brest, The poison of the sires infected mind, Transmissing it, to theirs that come behind. Vos vobis. The painefull Bee, when many a bitter shower, And storme had felt, farre from his hiue away, To seeke the sweetest Hunny-bearing flower, That might be found and was the pride of May: Heere lighting on the fair'st he mought espie, Is beate by Drones, the waspe and butterflie. So men there are sometimes of good desert, Who painfully haue labour'd for the hiue, Yet must they with their merit stand apart, And giue a farre inferior leaue to thriue: Or be perhaps, (if gotten into grace) By waspish Envie, beaten out of place. Sic opibus mentes. The Hyosciame, that about the plaines Of Italie, doth in abundance grow, Doth beare a flower, wherein a seed remaines, Of Birdes the most desir'd, (as Herballs show:) Which tasted by them, giddie downe they fall, And haue no power, to flie away at all. To this same fruite, I riches doe compare, Which though at first, with sweetnes they bewitch: Within a while, they breede our bane of care, Or else we surfet, cloid with overmuch: Or with their poison, breede out frantique fits: Or with their losse, bereaue vs of our wits. Vndique flamma. Who ever dost a Roiall Scepter sway, Or sit'st at sterne of publique gouerment, So beare thy selfe, that all Inferiors may, Behold thee as, a bright example sent; From God aboue, and clearest light to show, The virtuous pathes, wherein they ought to goe. For people, are like busie Apes inclin'd, To imitate the Soveraignes manners still, And to his Actions, frame their varieng mind: So that he standes, as Torch vpon a hill, In open view, and ever shining bright, In good or ill, to thousandes giuing light. Regia liberalitas. Of all the vertues, that doe best beseeme; Heroique valor, and high Maiestie, Which sooner loue, and Honor winne, I deeme, None may compare, with Liberalitie: Which well the mightie ALEXANDER knew, As by this Impre'se following heere I shew. Ere to the charge, he did himselfe advance, His purse by giving he would emptie quite; And cause the same be borne vpon a launce, Throughout the campe, in all the armies sight: And heerewithall proclaime, see, all is gone, “We liue in hope, to purchase more anon. In actione consistit. The Dread-nought Argo, cuts the foaming surge, Through daungers great, to get the golden prize, So when our selues, Necessitie doth vrge, We should avoide ignoble Cowardize, And vndertake with pleasure, any paine, Whereby we might our wealth, or honour gaine. For all in vaine, our partes we keepe within, Vnlesse we act, or put the same in vre: Or hope heereafter, Fame our frend to winne, If can no labour, constantly endure: Which from aboue, is with aboundance blest, When slothfull wightes, by nature we detest. Humilibus dat gratiam. The Mountaines huge, that seeme to check the sky, And all the world, with greatnes overpeere, With Heath, or Mosse, for most part barren lie: When valleis low, doth kindly Phœbus cheere, And with his heate, in hedge and groue begets, The virgin-Primrose, or sweete Violets. So God, oft times denies vnto the greate, The giftes of Nature, or his heavenly grace, And those that high, in Honor's chaire are set, Doe feele their wantes, when men of meaner place, Although they lack, the others golden spring, Perhaps are blest, aboue the richest King, Candor immunis erit. The burning glasse, that most doth gather fire, While Sirian Dog doth parch the meddowes greene, Doth never burne (a thing we much admire) The cloth, or stuffe, that perfect white is seene: But soone enflames, all cullors else beside, The black, the blew, the red, and motley pide. To this same glasse, I slaunder still compare, That by degrees, doth subtilly gather heate, And doth not with malicious envie spare, The good, the bad, the little or the greate, Who though she hath, o're other vertues power, The conscience cleere, she never shall devoure. Scripta non temere edenda. By worke of wit, who thirsteth after Fame: And by the Muse, wouldst liue a longer day, What ere thou writ'st, see carefully the same, Thou oft peruse, and after pause, and stay; Mend what's amisse, with ARGVS hundred eies, I meane advice, and Iudgment of the wise. For as in Children, easily we behold, Some neere resemblance of the mouth, or eie: Of Parents likenes: so our workes vnfold, Our mindes true Image, to posteritie. Beside, lew'd lines, our loues, and leasinges vaine Doe die: when wise wordes ever doe remaine. Pulchritudo fœminea. A Virgin naked, on a Dragon sits, One hand out-stretch'd, a christall glasse doth show: The other beares a dart, that deadly hits; Vpon her head, a garland white as snow, Of print and Lillies. Beautie most desir'd, Were I her painter, should be thus attir'd. Her nakednes vs tells, she needes no art: Her glasse, how we by sight are mooud to loue, The woundes vnfelt, that's giuen by the Dart At first, (though deadly we it after prooue) The Dragon notes loues poison: and the flowers, The frailtie (Ladies) of that pride of yours. Nil inde insipidum. A silver Salt, heere on the Table standes, On which the peace-full Turtle Doue doth sit, Who at the bord, a silent tongue commaundes: The Salt, that we should season still with it Discourses honest, not with idle tongue, Speake what we list, to doe another wrong. Some men there are, whose glorie's to depraue, With ill report, a man behind his back, And then suppose, their credits best they saue, With slaunders vile, when they anothers crack: When wisedome staid, will let such leasinges rest, And speake even of, her enimie the best. Ni vndas ni vientos. Who wouldst dispend in Happines thy daies, And lead a life, from cares exempt and free, See that thy mind, stand irremoou'd alwaies, Through reason grounded on firme constancie, For whom opinion doth vnstaiedly sway, To fortune soonest, such become a pray. Ye loftie Pines, that doe support the state Of common wealthes, and mightie government, Why stoope ye soon'st, vnto the blast of fate, And fawne on Envie, to your ruine bent: Be taught by me, to scorne your worser happe, The waue by Sea, or land the Thunderclap. In alÿs tempestivè consulentes non sibi. They tell me Tusser, when thou wert aliue, And hadst for profit, turned euery stone, Where ere thou cammest, thou couldst never thriue, Though heereto best, couldst counsel every one, As it may in thy Husbundry appeare, Wherein a fresh, thou liu'st amongst vs heere. So like thy selfe, a number more are woont, To sharpen others, with advice of wit, When they themselues, are like the whetstone blunt, And little care, to keepe or follow it: Eeke heere I must, the careles Pastor blame, That teacheth well, but followes not the same. Quicquid delirant Reges— It was the Custome of the Thracians once, Ere they would ore a frozen river passe, To take a Fox, and turne him for the Nonce, Vpon the Ice, to try how thick it was, Who to the streame, by laieng downe his eare, Could heare the noise, and know the thicknes there. Which if he found to tender for his weight, He back returnd, and thankt them, he would none, Which sheweth vs of some, the subtile sleight, Who hazard first, the poore, and weaker one To serue their turnes, whome God preserueth oft, When they themselues, within the pit are caught. In timidos et iactantes. The Fenny Bitter, that delightes to breede In thickest sedge, by moore, and river side, By thrusting low his bill into a reede, All summer long, at morne and eventide: Though neere, yet makes farre seeming such a sound That oft it doth, the Passenger astound. This Figure fits, two sorts of people base, The Coward one, that will with wordes affright, When dares not looke, true Valor in the face: The other is, the proude vaine-glorious wight, Who where he comes, will make a goodly show Of wit, or wealth, when it is nothing so. Deos inprimis placandos. The Romane Ladies, yearely did present Their Iewells, and the best attire they wore To Delphos, which were by commandement Into a Goblet turnd, and plac't before The Pythian God, as offring for the sinne Of loathed pride, they fear'd they liued in. A mirror for such wightes, as will allow Religion, or the church, the least of all, Nay, from the same purloine they care not how, Till Church perforce, hath stript them out of all: This also tells our gallant Dames beside, No vice offendes the Lord, so much as pride. Deus vltimum refugium. To the right worshipfull, Mr: D: Laifeild, sometimes my Tutor in Trinitie Colledge in Cambridge. When Priam saw his Citie set on fire, At once and drowned, in his Peoples blood, To pacifie the heavens enkindled ire, (Since humane helpe, doth faile to do him good:) Creusa warnes him to the Altar flie, Although he were assured there to die. The ease is every christians in distresse, Who to the Lord, himselfe should recommend, As who can best the wrongfull cause redresse, And patiently t' abide, what he shall send: Fall'n into handes of foes, our freedome thence, Or glorious death, to crowne our innocence. Allah vere. i. Deus dabit. Provde Empresse, of the prouder Tyrant mind, Of Soliman's high boundles-swelling thought: When like the Ocean, boyling with the wind, Of vaine Ambition, all in vaine he wrought, To vndermine our Christian happie state, And drowne her in, a deluge of his hate. But as our God, hath giu'n the Sea his bound: So (Pagan) scatterd he, thy froathy Ire: And while thou dream'st, of compassing this round, Thy Snuffe went out, and yet thou want'st no fire: Not that same which, thy fat Ambition fed, But that of Hell, that eates thee, liuing-dead. —Nec te quæsiveris extra. Althovgh the staffe, within the river cleere, Be straight as Arrow; in the Persian bow: Yet to the view, it crooked doth appeare, And one would sweare, that it indeede were so: So soone the Sence deceiu'd, doth iudge amisse, And fooles will blame, whereas none error is. This staffe doth shew, how oft the honest mind, That meaneth well, and is of life vpright, Is rashly censur'd, by the vulgar blind, Through vaine Opinion: or vile envious spite: But if thou know'st, thy conscience cleere within, What others say, it matters not a pinne. Fit purior haustu. If that the Well we draw, and emptie oft: The water there remaineth sweete and good: But standing long, it growes corrupt and naught, And serues no more, by reason of the mudde, In Summer hot, to coole our inward heate, To wash, to water, or to dresse our meate. So, if we doe not excercise our wit, By dayly labour, and invention still: In little time, our sloth corrupteth it, With in bred vices, foule and stincking ill: That both the glories of our life deface, And stoppe the source, and head of heavenly grace. Tutissima comes. Lo Pallas heere, with heedefull eie doth leade; Vlisses in his travaile farre and neere: That he aright, might in his Iourney treade, And shunne the traine of Error, every where: N' ought had Vlisses, ever brought to passe, But this great Goddesse, his directresse was. Though Homer did invent it long agoe, And we esteeme it as a fable vaine: While heere we wander, it doth wisely show, With all our actions, Wisedome should remaine; And where we goe, take Pallas still along To guide our feete, our eares, and lavish tongue. In dilapidantes sibi credita altena. The Houndes, sometimes the Fox had put in trust, From Towne, to Towne, to beg for their releife: Who was a while in's office very iust, But shortly after, proou'd an errant theife: By eating, or embezling, of the best, And casting to, the sterued Houndes the rest. Of Regnards kind, there is a craftie crew, Who when at death of frendes, are put in trust, Doe robbe the Church, or Infantes of their dew, Disposing of anothers as they lust: Whome being bound, in Conscience to preserue, They suffer oft, in open streete to sterue. Patientia læsa furorem. Who lightly sets his enimie at nought, And feares him not because he is too weake: Or that he is thy pray, alreadie caught, Within such net, he cannot eas'ly breake: Repents him often, and doth prooue too late, No foe so dang'rous, as the desperate. Wherefore saith one, giue passage to his Ire, Abuse him not with too much insolence: Least hopeles backe, he doth againe retire, With Furie arm'd, in stead of Patience: And prooues the Victor, when with cunning skill, Thou might'st before, haue rul'd him at thy will. Te aspicit vnam. Ad Sidoniam virginem nobilem. Thov greeu'st Sidonia, that I thus divide, My Loue so largely, to a severall frend: While thou, thou think'st, remainedst vnespi'de: Or takest thy fortune, at the latter end: And certes who his loue, impartes to all, Affectes but coldly, nay loues not at all. With wonder rapt, though much I doe admire Some Starres for lustre, and their glories best: You are that Arctick; most I doe desire, Whereon my hope, hath wholly set her rest: And who (sweete Maide,) when others downe do slide, To vnknowne Fate, must be my surest guide. Maior Hercule. Two Columnes strong, heere little Loue doth beare, Vpon his shoulders bare: though Lillie white, As if another Hercules he were: And would erect them, in a deepe despite, Of that Colosse, or Pharos fiery bright Th' Egyptian Piles, proude Mausolæus toombe Spaines Pillars, or great Traians, yet in Roome. Nor may you lesse imagine Cupids might: Though (Ladies) he, but seeme a child in show, Since hand to hand, himselfe in single fight, Hath giuen the great'st Hero'es their overthrow: Ne could the wisest man avoide his bow: Whose Trophees, &amp; braue triumphes, were they showne Thy Sonne Alcmena, never had beene knowne. Erit altera merces. Ad amicum suum Iohannem Doulandum Musices peritissimum. Iohannes Doulandus. Annos ludendo hausi. Heere Philomel, in silence sits alone, In depth of winter, on the bared brier, Whereas the Rose, had once her beautie showen; Which Lordes, and Ladies, did so much desire: But fruitles now, in winters frost, and snow, It doth despis'd, and vnregarded grow, So since (old frend,) thy yeares haue made thee white, And thou for others, hast consum'd thy spring, How few regard thee, whome thou didst delight, And farre, and neere, came once to heare thee sing: Ingratefull times, and worthles age of ours, That let's vs pine, when it hath cropt our flowers. Cui candor morte redemptus. The Ermin heere, whome eager houndes doe chase, And hunters haue, around environ'd in, (As some doe write) will not come neere the place, That may with dirt, defile his daintie skinne: But rather chooseth, then the same should soile, Be torne with dogges, or taken with the toile. Me thinkes even now, I see a number blush, To heare a beast, by nature should haue care, To keepe his skinne, themselues not care a rush, With how much filth, their mindes bespotted are: Great Lordes, and Ladies, turne your cost and art, From bodies pride, t' enritch your better part. Status humanus. Fower Captiue Kinges, proud Sesostris did tie, And them compeld his charriot to draw, Whereof the one, did ever cast his eie Vnto the wheele: which when the Tirant saw, And ask'd the cause, the chained King repli'de, Because heerein, my state I haue espi'de. For like our selues, the spoke that was on high, Is to the bottome, in a moment cast, As fast the lowest, riseth by and by, All humane thinges, thus find a change at last: The Tyrant fearing, what his hap might be, Releas'd their bandes forthwith, and set them free. Cum severitate lenitas. Of orient hew, a Rainebow doth containe, An hideous shower, within her Circlet round, Resembling that great punishment of raine, The Lord inflicted when the world was drown'd: The Rainebow, of his Mercy, heere a signe, Which with his Iustice, he doth ever ioine. For though we howerly, doe the Lord provoke, By crieng Sinnes, to bring his vengeance downe, The salue he tempers, while he strikes the stroke, And ioines his favor, with a bitter frowne: To let vs know, that wrath he keepes in store, And grace for such, as will offend no more. Sine pluma. This warlick Helme, that naked doth appeare, Not gold-enchased, or with Gemmes beset, Yet doth the markes, of many a battaile beare, With dintes of bullets, there imprinted yet, No featherie creast, or dreassing doth desire, Which at the Tilts, the vulgar most admire. For best desert, still liveth out of view, Or soone by Envie, is commaunded downe, Nor can her heauen-bred spirit lowly sue, Though t'were to gaine, a kingdome, and a crowne: Beside it tells vs, that the valiant heart, Can liue content, though wanteth his desert. Vmbra tantum. The Platane Tree, that by the bankes of PO, With gentle shade refresheth man and beast, Of other Trees, doth beare the goodliest show, And yet of all, it is the barrenest: But Nature though, this tree of fruite bereaues, It makes amendes, in cooling with the leaues. This Platane Tree, are such as growe aloft, Ore-dropping others, with their wealth or might, And yet, they of themselues, are barren oft, Wanting th' endowments, of the meaner wight: Who many times, in vertue doth excell, When these but haue, the shadow, or the shell. Vita tota dies vnus. Of all our life, behold the very summe, Which as this flower, continues but a day: Our youth is morne, our middle age is come By noone, at night as fast we doe decay, As doth this Lillie flowring with the Sunne, But withered ere, his race be fully runne. Wherefore our life's resembled to a shippe, Which passeth on, though we doe what we please, A shade, a flower, that every frost doth nippe, A dreame, a froath, a waue vpon the Seas, Which hath a while his being, till anon, Some else intrude, and hee's forgot and gon. Divitiæ. The country Swaines, at footeball heere are seene, Which each gapes after, for to get a blow, The while some one, away runnes with it cleane, It meetes another, at the goale below Who never stirrd, one catcheth heere a fall, And there one's maimd, who never saw the ball. This worldly wealth, is tossed too and fro, At which like Brutes, each striues with might and maine, To get a kick, by others overthrow, Heere one's fetch't vp, and there another slaine, With eager hast, and then it doth affront Some stander by, who never thought vpon't. Arbiter ipse mei. Vnto his life, who lookes with heedie eie, And labors most to keepe a conscience pure, And doubtes to treade, in errors pathes awrie: That man is blest, and deemed happie sure: When vicious persons, even vnto their graues, Are lewde affections, and their vices slaues. For as the Lion, that hath slipt his band, Or shear'd the chaine, that did his courage hold, Doth not in awe, of churlish keeper stand, But since is waxen, more couragious bold: The righteous man, so from hells bondage free, Hath heartes content, ioind with his libertie. Vulnerat ille medemar. This Sword, a Symbole of the Law, doth threate Perpetuall death, to all of Adams race: But yet th' Almightie, of his mercie greate, Sendes, after sentence, pardon of his grace: For when he found vs, maimed on the ground, With wine, and oile of grace, he heald the wound. Our partes it is; since by the Law we see, The fearefull state, and daunger we are in, To doe our best, then to his mercie flee, And new againe, our sinfull liues begin: Not trusting to our deedes, and merits vaine, Since nought but death, doth due to these remaine. In prodigos. The watry willow, growing by the shore, Of trees the formost, forth her fruite doth send, But laden with her bee-desired store, Ere ten daies fully come vnto an end, Her Palme's so sweete, we lou'd and look't vpon, With Boreas breath, are blowne away and gone. To this same tree, did Homer once compare, Such heires as straight, their Patrimonie wast, In ri'tous wise: and such as Artistes are, Who getting much, doe let it fly as fast: Eeke such of wit, or wealth, that make a show, In substance when, we find it nothing so. Te Duce. The Partrich young, in Foulers net ycaught, Too late the error of their damme repent, For why? her call them into daunger brought, And taught at first, the heedeles way they went: Heereby are kinges our common nurses ment, When to their lustes, themselues become a pray, And by example, thousandes cast awaie. Not heerevpon, as may of most be thought, We should our Prince, like Rebells disobey, When they be Tyrants, or with vices nought, Do hasten others, and their owne decay: But to the Lord, like Christians rather pray For mercie, who hath in his anger sent Such wretches vile, to be our punishment. In salo sine sale. To the Hon: and most worthy Ladie, E: L: The frendly Dolphin, while within the maine, At libertie delightes, to sport and play, Himselfe is fresh, and doth no whit retaine The brinish saltnes of the boundles Sea Wherein he liues. Such is the secret skill, Of Nature working, all thinges at her will. So you great Ladie, who your time haue spent, Within that place, where daungers oft abound, Remaine vntainted of your Element, And to your praise; yet keepe your honor sound Diana-like, whose brightnes did excell, When many starres, within your climate fell. Vna dolo Divûm. To the most Honorable and worthie Ladie the Ladie Alicia D: And ye great Ladie, that are left alone, To merc'les mercie, of the worldes wide sea, Behold your faire, though counterfeited stone, So much you ioi'd in, on your wedding day, And tooke for true, how after it did prooue, Vnworthy Iewell, of so worthy loue. Ah how can man, your sexe (faire Ladies) blame, Whose brests, are vertues pretious Carcanets, When he himselfe, first breakes the boundes of shame, And dearest loue, and loialtie forgets: Yet heerein happie, ye aboue the rest, Belou'd of Heauen, and in your children blest. Paulatim. By violence who tries to turne away, Strong natures current, from the proper course, To mooue the Earth, he better were assay, Or wrest from Ioue, his thunderbolts perforce, Bid the Sphæres stay, or ioine by art in one, Our Thames with Tyber, Pinde with Pelion. For nought at all heerein prevailes our might, With greater force she doth our strength withstand, The River stopt, “his banke downe-beareth quite, And seldome boughes, are bent with stubborne hand: When gentle vsage, feircenes doth allay, And bringes in time, the Lion to obay. Sic vos non vobis. To my worshipfull and kind frend Mr. William Stallenge, searcher of the Port of London, and first Author of making Silke in our Land. These little creatures heere, as white as milke, That shame to sloth, are busie at their loome. All summer long in weauing of their their Silke, Doe make their webs, both winding sheete and toombe, Thus to th' ingratefull world, bequeathing all Their liues haue gotten, at their funerall. Even so the webs, our wits for others weaue, Even from the highest to the meanest, worne, But Siren-like it'h end, our selues deceiue, Who spend our time, to serue anothers turne: Or painte a foole, with coate, or cullors gay, To giue good wordes, or thankes, so goe his way. Tyranni morbus suspicio. When valiant Richmond, gaue the overthrow T'vsurping Richard, at that fatall feild Of Bosworth, as our Histories doe show, This Embleme he devised for his sheild, (For when the battaile, wholly was his owne, He found his crowne, within a Hawthorne throwne.) Whereat he sigh'd they say, and vttered this, A Kingdome easeth not, the guiltie mind, Nor Crowne contents, where inward horror is, Withall it showes, how I am like to find, With Honor, and this dignitie I beare, My part of greife, and thornes of heavie care. Innocentia muninem tutissimum. The Lion once, whome all the Beastes did dread, Doth in a thicket deadly wounded lie, About whose carkas, yet not fully dead, Doe flock the Vultur, Puttock, and the Pie, And where the woundes are greene, and freshly bleede, They light thereon, and most of all doe feede. Such carrion Crowe, thinke thou thine enimie, Who seldome dare assault thee being sound, But where he doth thy guiltines espie, With eager hate, he præies vpon thy wound: But wisely if thou lead'st thy life vpright, He leaues thee then with sterued appetite. Amor coniugalis æternus. To my Louing and most kind frendes, Mr Christopher Collarde, and Mrs Mabell Collarde his wife, of St Martines in the feildes. Mabella Colarde. Bella, alma corde. Dearest of frendes, accept this small device, Wherewith I would your curtesies requite, But that your loues invaluable price, Must hold me debter, while I view this light, Nor can my heires, these papers dead and gone, Repay the favors for me, you haue done. A Turtle heere, vpon an Oliue sits, Vpon whose branch, depends a Ring of gold, As best the loue of Matrimonie fits, Thus ever endles, never waxing old, The branch and bowes, the fruite that from you spring, The Doue your selfe, your wife that golden Ring. Temperantia. Heere Temperance I stand, of virtues, Queene, Who moderate all humane vaine desires, Wherefore a bridle in my hand is seene, To curbe affection, that too farre aspires: I'th other hand, that golden cup doth show, Vnto excesse I am a deadly foe. For when to lustes, I loosely let the raine, And yeeld to each suggesting appetite, Man to his ruine, headlong runnes amaine, To frendes great greife, and enimies delight: No conquest doubtles, may with that compare, Of our affectes, when we the victors are. Servire nescit. The Princely Faulcon, that hath long beene man'd, And taught to stoope, vnto the tossed lure, Is now escaped from his Maisters hand, And will no more such servitude endure, But better likes the feilde, and forrestes spray, And for himselfe, in elder age to pray. The virtuous mind, and truely noble spright, Can seldome brooke, in bondage base to serue, But most doth in his libertie delight, Still rather choosing, by himselfe to sterue, Then eate some caterpillar's envied bread, Or at anothers curtesie be fed. Vis Amoris. Alcides heere, hath throwne his Clubbe away, And weares a Mantle, for his Lions skinne, Thus better liking for to passe the day, With Omphale, and with her maides to spinne, To card, to reele, and doe such daily taske, What ere it pleased, Omphale to aske. That all his conquests wonne him not such Fame, For which as God, the world did him adore, As Loues affection, did disgrace and shame His virtues partes. How many are there more, Who hauing Honor, and a worthy name, By actions base, and lewdnes loose the same. Vini vis. Heere Bacchus winged, midst his cups doth sit, With Mercuries Caduceus in his hand, As God of wine no more, but God of wit, And Eloquence, which he hath at commaund, (Since he hath drawne, his bowles and bottles drie,) Wherewith he seemes, to mount aboue the skie. For when his liquor hath possess'd the braine, The foole himselfe, the wisest thinkes to be, And then so giues his lavish tongue the raine, You'ld sweare ye heard another Mercurie, For lies of Ladies loues, or travailes farre, His birth, his woundes, or service in the warre. Honos venalis. Who seekst Promotion through iust desert, And thinkst by gift, of bodie, or of mind, To raise thy fortune, whosoere thou art, This new Impresa take to thee assignd, To warne thee oft, such labour is in vaine, If heereby thinkst, thy merit to obtaine. For now the golden time's returned back, And all's kept vnder, by th' Athenian Cat, Whose helpe, and favour, whosoere doth lack, May coole his heeles, with Homer at the gate: Such is our age, where virtue's scarce regarded, And artes with armes, must wander vnrewarded. Divinitùs. To the thrice famous and farre renowned Vniversitie of Oxford. Deare Sister of my ever-loued Mother, From whome this little that I haue I drew, Cambridge and heerein Trinitie Colledge. Ingratefully greate light I cannot smother, Some lesser sparkes, which I deriu'd from you, Which first enflam'd to this, my duller spright, And lent in darke, my Muse her candle light. Faire Academe, whome Fame and Artes conspire, To make thee mirror to all mortall eine, Within our Sphære, that Europe may admire, The gratious Lampe that on thy brow doth shine: And shewes the Trvth around by land and sea, Directing thousandes erring, in their way. Atheôn exitus. The Atheists vile, that Giant-like attemptes, To bandie faction with Almightie IOVE, And thinkes this fraile worlds priviledge exemptes, All Faith, and Feare, due vnto heauen aboue: Vnto his terror, let him heere behold, What Histories of IULIAN haue told. For after that he had his Lord defi'de, And wounded deadly lay in deepe dispaire, Thou, GALLILÆAN now or'ecom'st, he cri'de, Wherewith he cast his blood into the Aire: A fit example, for the faithles wight, And such as in prophanenes doe delight. Sic et Ingenium. The Roses sweete, that in the Garden grow, If that not often drest where they abide, Become as wild as those, we see doe blow In every feild, and hedge-row as we ride: And though for beautie, once they did excell, They now haue lost, both cullor and the smell. So many men, whome Nature hath endu'de, With rarest partes, of bodie, or the mind, Do in themselues by Sloth, grow rancke and rude, Not leauing any memorie behind, Saue that they liued heere, and sometime were, A needeles burthen which the Earth did beare. PART II. The Author to his Muse. Now strike wee Saile, and throw aside our oare, My wearie Muse, the worst is well nie past: And take a while, our pleasure on the shore, Recounting what wee overcame at last: To what deepe danger were our fortunes cast: What Rocks, the greatest, &amp; vnknowen shelues, We dar'd to touch, and yet did saue our selues. HENRY, who art both Load-stone, and the starre, Of Heartes and Eies, our wished Loue and Light: By thee conducted, we arriue thus farre; That now OPINIONS vttermost despight, Nor ENVIE, that the iustest one doth bite, We doubt at all; but forth into the maine, With doubled courage, put our selues againe. And you great PRINCESSE, through whose Christall brest, ELIZAS Zeale, and Pietie doe shine, Heire of her Name, and Virtues, that invest You in our Heartes, and Loues immortall shrine: Oh send from that pure Maiestie of thine, Those beames againe, from whence (as PHOEBUS bright) Our feeble Muse, deriues her life and light. Eeke pardon (PEERES,) that heere my ruder verse, Vnto your worthes, and greatnes dares aspire; Or out of course, if I your rankes reherse: But as i'th Presence, twixt the Lord and Squire, (He neere the state, the other by the fire,) Small difference seemes; so heere most Honord traine, Ye take your lots about your Soveraigne. And whatsoever EIE shalt else peruse, These ruder lines, devoid of skill and Art; Reserue thy good opinion of our Muse, That may heereafter worke of worth impart: And though she tastes of Countrey and the Cart, Sinicinatus a noble Romane, cald from his plough, to the Dictatorship. (As that DICTATOR) all in time she may, Within the Citie beare a greater swey. Presidium et dulce deciis. Illustrissimo et potentissimo Principi ac Domino, D: Mauritio Hessiæ Lantgravio, Comiti in Catzenellen bogen Dietz, Zigenhain, et Nidda &amp;c This most noble Prince beside his admirable knowledge in all learning, &amp; the languages, hath exellent skill in musick. Mr Douland hath many times shewed me 10 or 12 severall sets of Songes for his Chappel of his owne composing. To you great Prince, who little neede be knowne, By me or by my worthles Poësie, Since those admired virtues of your owne, Haue made you obiect of the worldes wide eie, Your bounteous mind, your matchles Pietie, Your languages, and learning in all artes, That gaine you millions of remotest heartes. I consecrate in gentle Muses name This Monument, and to your memorie, Which shall outweare the vtmost date of Fame, And wrestle with the worldes Eternitie: For as Artes glorie is your GERMANIE, For rar'st invention, and designe of wit, So ye braue Maurice are the pride of it. Distantia iungo. To the thrice Noble, and exellent Prince: Ludowick Duke of Lennox Nor may my Muse greate Duke, with prouder saile, Ore-passe your name, your birth, and best deserts: But lowly strike, and to these cullors vaile, That make ye yet belou'd in forrein partes, In memorie of those disioined heartes: Of two great kingdomes, whom your grandsire wrought, Till Buckle-like, them both in one he brought. Mild Peace heerein, to make amendes againe, Ordaines your daies ye shall dispend in rest, While Horror bound, in hundred-double chaine, At her faire feete, shall teare her snakie crest, And Mars in vaine, with Trumpet sterne molest Our Muse, that shall her lostiest numbers frame, To eternize your STEVVARTS Roiall name. Nostro elucescis damno. The Steele and Flint, doe heere with hardie strokes, And mutuall hewing, each the other wast: While vnderneath the open Tinderboxe, Vnto his gaine, consumes them both at last: And to the backs, when they are spent and worne, He throwes them by, for he hath seru'd his turne. So, when the Paisant with his neighbour warres, They weare awaie themselues, in golden sparkes; The Boxe, are Pettifoggers from their Iarres, Who walke with Torches, vsher'd by their Clearkes: While blind by Owle-light, Hoidon stumbling goes, To seeke his Iune, the Windmill, or the Rose. Ex Avaritia Bellum. The hand that gripes, so greedily and hard, What it hath got by long vnlawfull gaine; Withall for Battaile ready is prepard, Still to defend, what it doth fast retaine: (For wretches some, will sooner spend their bloods, Then spare we see, one penworth of their goods.) Of Avarice, such is the nature still, Who hardly can endure, to liue in Peace; But alwaie prest, to quarrell, or to kill, When sober mindes, from such contention cease: And seeke no more, then quiet and content, With those good blessinges, which the Lord hath sent. [The glorious Sunne, that cheeres vs with his light] ??? ???????? ????. The glorious Sunne, that cheeres vs with his light, And giueth life, and growth to every thing: Can brooke no peere, to check his soveraigne right, But onely will remaine, the Heauens sole king: When lesser starres, that borrow from his light, Doe keepe their course, in numbers infinite. So fares it with the vulgar that doe goe, In loue, and mutuall concord most secure, When Paritie procures the overthrow, Of Monarchies, that else might well endure: And like moe Sunnes in skie, portendeth still, The Princes ruine, or a worser ill. Non invicta recedo. To my Scholler Mr. Hannibal Baskervile. This Indian beast, by Nature armed so, That scarce the Steele can peirce his scalie side: Assaulteth oft the Elephant his foe, A Rhinoceros was s?t to Rome by Emanuel king of Portingal who fought with it c?ming on land thorough Provence: but by the waie, by hard fortune it was drowned neere Porto Wenere: seeking a long time to save it selfe am?g the Rocks. Paulus Iovius. And either doth the conqueror abide, Or by his mightie combatant is slaine, For never vanquisht, he returnes againe. So you that must encounter Want, and Care, To overcome your hard, and crabbed skill, Take courage, and treade vnder foote dispaire, For better hap, attendes the vent'rous still: And sooner leaue, your bodie in the place, Then back returne, vnletter'd with disgrace. Non Honos, sed Onus. Vaine man who think'st, that happines consistes, In great commaund, and Roiall dignitie; And Kinges with Scepters hold within their fistes, The perfect summe of all Fœlicitie: No no, their Crownes are lin'd with pricking thorne, And sable cares, with crimson Robes are worne. Who list describe the motion of the Sphære, Another, some rare, beauteous modell draw; With Eloquence, let him goe charme the eare, Thy onely art, must be to keepe in aw, And curbe with Iustice, the vnrulie crew, To favor skill, and giue the good their due. Quem timuisti, timet. Ad BRITANNIAM. With haire dishevel'd, and in mournefull wise, Who spurnes a shippe, with Scepter in her hand: Thus BRITANE's drawen in old Antiquities, What time the Romanes, overran her land: Who first devis'd her, sitting in this plight, As then their captiue, and abandon'd quite. But what can long continue at a stay, To all thinges being, Fates a change decree: Thrice-famous Ile, whome erst thou didst obey, Vsurping Roome, standes now in aw of thee: And trembles more, to heare thy Soveraignes name, Then thou her Drummes, when valiant Cæsar came. Eo magis caligat. Why doth vaine man, with rash attempt desire, To search the depth, of Misteries divine: Which like the Sunne vpon his earthy fire, With glorie inaccessible do shine: And with the radiant splendor of their ray, Chase all conceipted Ignorance away. What mortall man might ever comprehend, Gods sacred essence, and his secret will, Or his soules substance, or could but intend, Least while to view, this glorious creature still: Be wise in what the word doth plainely teach, But meddle not, with thinges aboue thy reach. Piorum vita luctuosa. To the modest and virtuous minded, Mrs. Elizabeth Apsley, attending vpon the most exellent Princesse, the Ladie Elizabeth her grace. While that the Mavis, and the morning Larke, Doe cheerely warble their delicious straines, The Turtle likes the shade, and thickets darke, And solitarie by herselfe remaines, Recording in most dolefull wise her woe, Letting the pleasures, of the season goe. The godly wight, whome no delight of Sinne, Doth with vaine pleasure draw: or worldly care, Esteemeth not, these fleeting Ioies a pinne: But to the Lord, in private doth repaire, With quiet Conscience; when the wicked oft, Are in the mid'st, of all their pleasures caught. Coniugÿ Symbolum. Behold a Storke, betweene two Torches plac'd, Of milkie hew, with winges abroad displaide; In aunchient time, the marke of wedlock chast, Because this Bird, a deadly foe is said T' Adulterie, and foulest foule Incest, The Vestal maide, the fire beseemeth best. Chast Loue, the band of everlasting Peace, The best content we haue, while here we liue, That blessest Mariage, with thy sweete encrease, And dost a pledge, of that coniunction giue Twixt Soule, and Body, eke the mutual Loue, Betweene the Church, and her sweete Spouse aboue. In eos qui cum amicis fruantur, vti nesciant. This simple Foole, that here bestrides the bow, And knowing well, the daunger vnderneath, Yet busilie doth saw the same in two, Like idle Ape, though to his present death: Which if he had forborne, and let it grow, He free from harme, had scapt the pikes below. To this same Idiot, such we liken may, Of trustie Frendes as doe not know the vse, But while they are their props, and onely stay, Will cut them off, by this, or that abuse; Or loose their favor, by behaviour ill, Who otherwise, might haue vpheld them still. Sic nos Dÿ. The Tennis-ball, when strucken to the ground, With Racket, or the gentle Schoole-boies hand, With greater force, doth back againe rebound, His Fate, (though senceles) seeming to withstand: Yea, at the instant of his forced fall, With might redoubled, mountes the highest of all. So when the Gods aboue, haue struck vs low, (For men as balls, within their handes are said,) We cheifly then, should manly courage show, And not for every trifle be afraid: For when of Fortune, most we stand in feare, Then Tyrant-like, she most will domineere. Par nulla figura dolori. The device of the late Honorable, Earle of Essex. Wee eas'ly limme, some louely-Virgin face, And can to life, a Lantscip represent, Afford to Antiques, each his proper grace, Or trick out this, or that compartement: But with the Pencill, who could ere expresse, The face of griefe, and heartie pensiuenes. For where the minde's with deadly sorrow wounded, There no proportion, can effect delight, For like a Chaos, all within's confounded, Resembling nothing, saue the face of night, Which in his sheild, this noble Earle did beare, The last Impresa', of his greife, and care. In repetundos, et adulatores. Of Virgins face, with winges, and tallants strong, Vpon thy table, PHINEUS here behold, A monstrous Harpie, that hath præied long, Vpon thy meates, while thou art blind, and old, And at all times, his appetite doth serue, While vnregarded, thou thy selfe dost sterue. The Courtes of Kinges, are said to keepe a crew Of these still hungry for their private gaine: The first is he, that carries tales vntrue, The second, whome base bribing doth maintaine, The third and last, the Parasite I find, Who bites the worst, if Princes will be blind. Salomone pulchrius. Let Courtly Dames, their costly Iewells boast, And Rhodopis, in silkes and sattens shine; Behold the Lillie, thus devoid of cost, In flowery feildes, is clothd by power divine, In purest white, fair'st obiect of the eie, Religions weede, and badge of Chastitie. Why should ye then as slaues to loathed pride, And frantique fooles, thinke ye are halfe vndone, When that ye goe not in your cullors pide, Or want the grace, of newest fashion: When even the Lillie, in glorie doth surpasse, The rich, and roiallst King, that ever was. Soboles damnosa parenti. The Husbandman, in depth of winter feld, An aged Willow, fewell for to burne, But wanting wedges, Grandsire was compeld, To rend with bowes, the bodie for his turne: And while the Willow, now was rent in twaine, It gaue a grone, and thus seem'd to complaine. Oh greife, of greifes! that thus I should be torne, And haue my heart, by those asunder rent, That are my fruite, and of my bodie borne, Who for my stay, and comfort, should be sent: You Parents good, your selues behold in me, Whose Children wicked, and vngratious be. Innocentiam iniurÿs maximè obnoxiam esse. The Cat, the Cock held prisoner in her paw, And said of Birdes, he most deseru'd to die, For that contrarie vnto Natures Law, His kindred he abus'd incestuously: His Mother, Sisters, and a noise did keepe, With crowing still, when others faine would sleepe. In his defence, heereto repli'de the Cock, My fault of lust, is for my maisters gaine, I am for crowing, call'd the Plowmans clock, Whome I awake betime, to daily paine: No doubt (quoth Pusse,) of reasons thou hast store, But I am fasting, and can heare no more. Humanæ miseriæ. See here our humane miseries in breife, That doe our life, vnto the last amate, And sawce the sweete, with feare, and howerly griefe, Diseasing oft, the high, and happiest state: A Rod, the world, a Woman, Ages greife, Which fower, the wisest doe account the cheife. His childish yeares, the Rod keepes vnder still, His youth with Loue, and strong affectes is vext, That headlong force him, pliable to ill, A retchles wife, and worldly cares are next: And when both youth, and middle age be past, Diseases straunge, doe end him at the last. Vireo tamen. The Some would haue it the Orpine. Semper-vivum, though from earth remoou'd, His leafe with flower, are fresh and growing seene, And many times, as by experience proou'd, It will abide, in sharpest winter greene, As faire, and full of life, vnto the view, As if abroad, in fertil'st soile it grew. So many men, of rarest partes there are, Who though the world afford them not a foote, Yet doe they thriue, within the emptie aire, As well as they, that haue the richest roote: Yea, when as some, that are vpheld like Hops, Doe droope, and die, even vnderneath their props. Dÿ laboribus vendunt. The slothfull man, that loues in idle seat, And wanton pleasures, to dispend his daies: The Scripture plaine denieth for to eate, And lawes severe, doe punish many waies: And never Heavens, with their bountie blesse, The hand addicted vnto Idlenes. On th'other side, when for our sweatie paine, To sale they set vs, all the pretious thinges, The Earth within her bosome, doth containe, Gemmes, Herbes of virtue, Diadems of Kinges, All sortes of Girlondes, and the Quill of Fame, To keepe aliue, the honor of our name. Gloriæ lata via. Thovgh life be short, and man doth as the Sunne, His iourney finish, in a little space, The way is wide, an honest course to runne, And great the glories of a virtuous race, That at the last, doe our iust labors crowne, With threefold wreath, Loue, Honor, and Renowne. Nor can Nights shadow, or the Stygian deepe, Conceale faire Virtue, from the worldes wide eie, The more opprest, the more she striues to peepe, And raise her Rose-bound golden head on high: When Epicures, the wretch, and worldly slaue, Shall rot in shame, aliue, and in the graue. Tu contra audentior. The valiant heart, that feeles the vtmost spight, Of envious Fortune, who with Sword and fire, Awaites his ruine, with redoubled might, Takes courage to him, and abates her ire, By resolution, and a constant mind, To deede of virtue, evermore inclin'd. Whose sp'rite, a sparke of heavens immortall fire, Inglorious Sloth, may not in embers keepe, But spite of hell, it will at length aspire, And even by strawes, for want of fewell creepe: When fearefull natures, and the mind vnsound, At every blast, is beaten to the ground. Huic ne credere tutissimum. Sweete Bird, who taught thee here to build thy nest? (In greater saf'tie then MEDEA's shrine,) Did Hap, or that thou knew'st a Crowne the best, From iniurie to shelter thee and thine? How much I did thy happines envie, When first I saw thee singing, hither flie. Your glories Type, even so ye sacred Kinges, In highest place, the weaker one to sheild, Thus vnder that sweete shadow of your winges, Best loues the Artes, and Innocence to build: And thus my Muse, that never saf'tie knew, With weary wing, great HENRIE flies to you. To the Honorable, Sir Thomas Ridgewaie, Knight, and Baronet: Treasurer at warres in Ireland, and one of his Maiesties Privie Counsell there &amp;c. Thomas Ridgewaie. Mihi gravato Deus. The Camell strong, with burthen great opprest, Is forc'd to yeeld vnto his loade at last, And while he toiles, himselfe enioies the least, Of all the wealth, that on his back is cast: For why? he must the same, to those impart, Whose due it is, by Fortune, or desert. So honor'd Sir, you, as your Camell, beare A Treasures charge, that pulls you on your knee, And though that thousandes, aske it here, and there, To those that ought, and best deseruing be, You only giue, their wages, and their due, The while the care, and perill lies on you. Melancholia. Heere Melancholly musing in his fits, Pale visag'd, of complexion cold and drie, All solitarie, at his studie sits, Within a wood, devoid of companie: Saue Madge the Owle, and melancholly Pusse, Light-loathing Creatures, hatefull, ominous. His mouth, in signe of silence, vp is bound, For Melancholly loues not many wordes: One foote on Cube is fixt vpon the ground, The which him plodding Constancie affordes: A sealed Purse he beares, to shew no vice, So proper is to him, as Avarice. Sanguis. The Aierie Sanguine, in whose youthfull cheeke, The Pestane Rose, and Lilly doe contend: By nature is benigne, and gentlie meeke, To Musick, and all merriment a frend; As seemeth by his flowers, and girlondes gay, Wherewith he dightes him, all the merry May. And by him browzing, of the climbing vine, The lustfull Goate is seene, which may import, His pronenes both to women, and to wine, Bold, bounteous, frend vnto the learned sort; For studies fit, best louing, and belou'd, Faire-spoken, bashfull, seld in anger moou'd. Cholera. Next Choller standes, resembling most the fire, Of swarthie yeallow, and a meager face; With Sword a late, vnsheathed in his Ire: Neere whome, there lies, within a little space, A sterne ei'de Lion, and by him a sheild, Charg'd with a flame, vpon a crimson feild. We paint him young, to shew that passions raigne, The most in heedles, and vnstaied youth: That Lion showes, he seldome can refraine, From cruell deede, devoide of gentle ruth: Or hath perhaps, this beast to him assign'd, As bearing most, the braue and bounteous mind. Phlegma. Heere Phlegme sits coughing on a Marble seate, As Citie-vsurers before their dore: Of Bodie grosse, not through excesse of meate, But of a Dropsie, he had got of yore: His slothfull hand, in's bosome still he keepes, Drinkes, spits, or nodding, in the Chimney sleepes. Beneath his feete, there doth a Tortoise crall, For slowest pace, Sloth's Hieroglyphick here, For Phlegmatique, hates Labour most of all, As by his course araiment, may appeare: Nor is he better furnished I find, With Science, or the virtues of the mind. Ad Iesum Christum opt: Max ?? ?????. ?? ? ???. Thou art that sheepe. The sillie Lambe, on Altar lieth bound, Prepared readie, for the Sacrifice, Who willingly awaites his mortall wound, Without resistance, or helpe calling cries, To mooue the tender hearted to relent, Or heauens to heare a dieng Innocent. Thou art (deere Lord) this Lambe, who for our guilt, Forsook'st the Throne, of highest Maiestie, And gau'st thy blood, for sinners to be spilt, Frend to thy foes, high in humilitie: And is this creature innocent, and dumbe, Till Lion-like, thou shalt to Iudgment come. Nec amicis, nec cognatis fidendum. The Partrich building in the ripened wheate, Did charge her young, (while she abroade did flie, With tender care, to search about for meate,) To marke the talke, of those that passed by: Ere long there came, the owner of the corne, Who said by frendes, next day it should be shorne. There is no daunger, quoth the old one yet, Be still a while, I once abroade againe, Then heard they, he his kinsmen would intreate, Without delay, to fell that feild of graine: Some feare there is, quoth Damme, but if he saies, Hee'le come himselfe, then time to goe our waies. Matrimonium Who loueth best, to liue in Hymens bandes, And better likes, the carefull married state, May here behold, how Matrimonie standes, In woodden stocks, repenting him too late: The servile yoake, his neck, and shoulder weares, And in his hand, the fruitefull Quince he beares. The stocks doe shew, his want of libertie, Not as he woont, to wander where he list: The yoke's an ensigne of servilitie: The fruitefullnes, the Quince within his fist, Of wedlock tells, which SOLON did present, T' Athenian Brides, the day to Church they went. Sed frigida pulchra. Ad Lesbiam. Lesbia, that dost th' Elysian Rose excell, Or Cyprian Goddesse, for a beauteous grace; Forgiue me, here that I so plainlie tell, My loues long errors, wandring in thy face: Thy face that takes, like that Dædalian maze, All eies thereon, that shall with wonder gaze. Though fairest faire, thou beest yet like the Snow, Or shamefast Rose, thou inwardly art cold, Nor can the beames, that gentle Loue doth throw, Exhale the sweete, thy bosome doth enfold: As thou art faire, so wert thou Lesbia kind, My wronges had di'de, and none had knowne thy mind. Veritas. A beauteous maide, in comly wise doth stand: Who on the Sunnes bright globe, doth cast her eie: An opened booke, she holdeth in her hand, withall the Palme, in signe of victorie; Her right foote treadeth downe the world belowe: Her name is Trvth, of old depainted so. Her nakednes beseemes simplicitie: The Sunne, how she is greatest frend to light: Her booke, the strength she holds by historie: The Palme, her triumphes over Tyrants spite: The world she treads on, how in heaven she dwels, And here beneath all earthly thing excells. Etiam hosti servanda. Of Concord firme, the Romans in their coine, This symbole gaue, their peace about to make, That as their hands, in one their hearts should ioine, And sooner first, they would their liues forsake, Then treachr'ously, their vow and promise breake, Though to their foe, if they the word did speake. For lo, the Lord who secrets all doth knowe, With vengeance most, doth plague the faithles wight: As that same “Card'nall, prou'd not long agoe, Who in the feild against his faith would fight: With God and man, the truth accepted is; Oh! let not heathen, vs excell in this. Iustitia militaris. When SCAVRVS forth the Roman youth did lead, To proue their valour on the common foe: Within his Campe, in authors as I read, A peare tree laden with the fruit did grow, Which at's departure, kept the wonted store, As full remaining as it did before. A mirror for commaunders in our age, Who deeme it honour, and a souldiers guise, To vse on foes all villanous outrage: Rapes, murders, rapines, burnings robberies: And greatest part of valour to consist, Like savage bruites, in spoyling what they list. Regum Maiestatem non imminuendam. The auntient Romans by their Temples vs'd, To paint a serpent, or such hideous thing: That holy places, might not be abus'd By children, whom they told, that these would sting: And made beleue they liu'd, to that intent, To Sacred things they should be reverent. Vile Traytor, of some Hyrcane Tiger bred, Such Serpents still, thy Soveraignes crowne do guard: But think not as the other, these are dead, Like child or foole: but that they are prepar'd, With mortal stings, to be reueng'd on them, That shall abuse, tha'nointed Diadem. Dolis minime fidendum. The Cat and Foxe, while that a lone they sate Consulting, Regnard thus began to boast, And soberlie to tel vnto the Cat, His shiftes, when danger did assaile him most: The Cat said, one is proper vnto me If worst should come, that is to take a tree. Meane time of hounds, there came a yolping crew, Who found the Foxe: Pusse trusting to her clawes, And seeing him torne in peeces, in her view, Said to her selfe, after alitle pause; One honest shift is better now I see, Then all thy cunning in extremitie. Vigil vtrinque. A Beacon standing on the Rocky shore, Vpon whose top, a cock to sit you see: Gods Ministers doth shew, should evermore, Stand Sentinell; and howerly watchfull be, Vpon their flock, defending every port, Whereto the foe, is likeliest to resort. For many are the stratagems of sinne, And Sathan labors still with might and maine, Within our soules, a landing place to win: It is your partes, with fervent prayer againe; And faith the spirits sword, and all yee may, To keepe his malice, from your flocks away. Vindicta Divina. While sinfull Sodome dreades the heavenly fire, And Nero trembles at his shadowes sight: This booke, the Herald of th'Almighties Ire, Doth on the howse, of every swearer light: To punish iustly, so prophane a sinne, With all the plagues, that are containd therein. A warning good for swearers, and for those, That think such sinne, their actions only grace: And him the man, that can with fearefull oathes, Blaspheme the Lord of heaven vnto his face: But know prophane, ere many yeares be past, A plague will come, with winged speede at last. Eternitas. A Virgin faire, purtraicted as you see, With haire dispred, in comelie wise behind: Within whose handes, two golden balls there be: But from the brest, the nether partes are twin'd Within a starrie circle, do expresse, Eternitie, or Everlastingnes. ETERNITIE is young, and never old: The circle wantes beginning and the end: And vncorrupt for ever lies the gold: The heaven her lightes for evermore did lend, The Heathen thought, though heauen &amp; earth must passe, And all in time decay that ever was. Hei mihi quod vidi. Looke how the Limbeck gentlie downe distil's, In pearlie drops, his heartes deare quintescence: So I, poore Eie, while coldest sorrow fills, My brest by flames, enforce this moisture thence In Christall floods, that thus their limits breake, Drowning the heart, before the tongue can speake. Great Ladie, Teares haue moou'd the savage feirce, And wrested Pittie, from a Tyrants ire: And drops in time, do hardest Marble peirce, But ah I feare me, I too high aspire, Then wish those beames, so bright had never shin'd, Or that thou hadst, beene from thy cradle blind. Sic audaces fortuna. Lysimachvs adiudged once to die, By sentence iust, for that he poisoned, CALISTHENES his maister privilie, And lieng long in dungeon fettered To end his daies, did in the end request, He might be throwne, vnto a savadge beast. The which was straight of ALEXANDER graunted, And naked he vnto a Lion cast, But hauing one arme closely arm'd, vndaunted, By th'vpper Iaw, he holdes his foe so fast, That downe his throate, that armed arme he sendes, And even the heart-stringes, from the bodie rendes. Which bold attempt, when ALEXANDER knew, Thy life is thine, LYSIMACHVS quoth he, Besides I giue, (as to thy valour due,) My frendship here, my Scepter after me: For thus the virtuous, and the valiant spright, Triumphes o're Fate, and Fortunes deadliest spite. Et minimi vindictam. Wee doe adore by nature, Princes good, And gladly as our Parents, them obey, But loath the Monsters, that delight in blood, And thinke their People sent them for a prey: To whome the Lord, doth in his Iudgment send, A loathed life, or else a fearefull end. Once NERO'S name, the world did quake to heare, And ROME did tremble, at DOMITIAN'S sight: But now the Tyrant, cause of all this feare, Is laid full low, vpon whose toombe do light, To take revenge, the Bee, and summer Flie, Who not escap't sometime his crueltie. Ex vtroque Immortalitas. Ad pÿssimum Iacobum magnæ Britanniæ Regem. Bvt thou whose goodnes, Pietie, and Zeale, Haue caus'd thee so, to be belou'd of thine, (When envious Fates, shall robbe the Common weale, Of such a Father,) shalt for ever shine: Not turn'd as Cæsar, to a fained starre, But plac'd a Saint, in greater glory farre. With whome mild Peace, the most of all desir'd; And learned Muse shall end their happie dayes; While thou to all eternitie admir'd, Shalt liue a fresh, in after ages praise: Or be the Loade-starre, of thy glorious North, Drawing all eies, to wonder at thy worth. Icon Peccati. A young man-blind, black, naked here is seene, Ore Mountaine steepe, and Thornie Rock to passe, Whose heart a Serpent gnawes with furie teene, Another's wound about his wast; alas, Since ADAM'S fall, such our estate hath bin, The liuely picture of our guilt and sinne. His age denotes youthes follies and amisse, His blindnes shewes, our want of wisedomes sight; Sinnes deadly waies, those dang'rous stepps of his, His nakednes, of grace depriued quite: Hell's power the Serpent, which his loines doth girt, A Conscience bad, the other eates his heart. Inconstantia. Inconstancie with fickle foote doth stand, Vpon a Crab, in gowne of palie greene, A shining Cressaunt shewing in her hand, Which as her selfe, is changing ever seene: That cullour light, she borrowes from the Sea, Whose waues continue, never at a stay. Forward, and backward, Cancer keepes his pace, Th' inconstant man, so doubtfull in his waies, The private life, one while will most embrace, In travaile then, he listes to spend his dayes: Which was the Kitchin, that he makes a Tower, Then downe goes all togeither in an hower. In Amicos falsos. Two frendes there were that did their Iourney take, And by the way, they made a vow to either, What ere befell, they never would forsake, But as sworne brethren, liue and die togeither: Thus wandring thorough deserts, here and there, By chance they met, a great and vgly Beare. At whome, amazed with a deadly feare, One leaues his frend, and climbeth vp a tree: The other, falles downe flat before the Beare, And keepes his breath, that seeming dead to be, The Beare forsooke him, (for his nature's such, A breathles bodie never once to touch.) The beast departing, and the daunger past, The dead arose, and kept along his waie: His fellow leaping from the tree at last, Askt what the Beare, in's care did whispring say, Quoth he, he bad me, evermore take heede, Of such as thou, that failst in time of neede. Levitas. A youth arraid, in sundry cullors light, And painted plumes that overspred his crest: Describes the varieng and fantastique wight, (For like our mindes, we commonly are drest:) His right hand holdes, the bellowes to his eare, His left, the quick, and speedie spurre doth beare. Such is Capriccio, or th'vnstaied mind, Whome thousand fancies howerly doe possesse, For riding post, with every blast of wind, In nought hee's steddie, saue vnstablenes: Musitians, Painters, and Poetique crew, Accept what RIPA, dedicates to you. Adhuc mea messis in herba. Ad D. M. L. nobilem quandam Italam Mediolanensem quinquagenariam, quæ puero vix 15. annos nato non ita pridem nupsit. Iocosum. Pasquini. Admired Ladie, I haue mused oft, In silent night, when you haue beene in bed, With your young husband, wherevpon you thought, Or what conceipt possest your carefull head, Since he we know, as yet had never seene, His tendrest yeares, amounted to fifteene: No question but you grieued inward much, As doth the Miser, in a backward yeare: When others reape, to see your harvest such, And all your hopes, but in their blade appeare: Ladie, let henceforth nought disease your rest, For after-crops doe sometime prooue the best. Somniorum Dea. What louely Goddesse do mine eies behold? That powers such plentie with her bounteous hand: Her name is BRYSVS, whome the Greekes of old, As Queene of dreames ador'd within their land: Whome if they seru'd, devoutly as they should, They made no doubt, of hauing what they would. And well may BRYSVS, be a Goddesse thought, So many who with fancies vaine deceiues: Whome when she to fooles Paradice hath brought, For golden Apples, scarce she giues them leaues: To visions vaine, and dreames then take no heede, Which had in Christ, their ending as you reade. Libidinis effecta. The Viper when he doth engender, loe, Thus downe the females throate, doth put his head, Which of she bites, as learned Authours show, And ne're conceiues, before the male be dead: Eke when she forth, her poisonous broode doth send, Her young ones likewise, bring her to her end. Of Beastly lust, th' effectes herein perceiue, How deadly, and how dangerous they be, Of life and soule, that doe at once bereaue, Turning abundance into beggery: Daughter of Sloth, vile cancker of the mind, Leauing repentance, and foule shame behind. Sors. A wofull wretch, that languisht in dispaire, Withouten frendes, and meanes of living here, A halter tooke, to make an end of care, The while beneath hid treasure doth appeare: Which to his lot assign'd, by fortunes doome, He takes, and leaues his halter in the roome. The owner after missing of his pelfe, For deadly greife, his heapes and hopes were gon, The others halter takes, and hanges himselfe: Fortune thus dallies ever, and anon O're-swaieng all, with Scepter in her fist, And bandieth vs, like balls which way she list. Inani impetu. The Crocodile along th' Ægiptian NILE, That lurkes to make the passenger his pray, The most of all delightes, to robbe and spoile The Hunny-hiues, were he not kept away By Saffron planted, round on every side, Which this slie theife, could never yet abide. This Crocodile, I count the Ghostly foe, Who evermore lies watching, to devoure Our Hopes encrease, that in the soule doth grow, Did not the grace divine, this Saffron flower (Most wholesome herbe) prevent his deadly spight, And guard the Garden, safely day and night. Secundus deteriora dies. When as TIBERIVS CÆSAR past along The streetes of Rome, by chaunce he did espie A Lazar poore, who there amid the throng, Did full of sores, and loathsome vlcers lie, About the which, so busie was the flie: That moou'd with pittie, CÆSAR willed some, Stand by to kill them, as they saw them come. Whereat the wretch, did suddainely replie, These flies are full, pray let them yet alone, For being kill'd, a fresher companie, More hunger pincht, would bite me to the bone: So when the wealthy Iudge, is dead and gone: Some starued one succeedes, who biteth more, A thousand times, then did the full before. Silentÿ dignitas. Loe SOLON here th' Athenian sage doth stand, The glorie of all GRECIA to this day, With courage bold who taketh knife in hand, And with the same, doth cut his tongue away: But being ask'd of some, the reason why, By writing thus he answer'd by and by. Oft haue I heard, that many haue sustained, Much losse by talke, and lavishnes of tongue, Of silence never any yet complained, Or could say iustly, it had done him wrong: Who knowes to speake, and when to hold his peace, Findes fewest daungers, and liues best at ease. Vini Energia. The husbandman, laid sometime to his vine, To make it beare, the donge of sundry beastes, Whose virtue since, hath quite possest the wine, As may appeare, at many drunken feastes: One Lion-like, doth quarrell with his host, Stares, sweares, breakes windowes, or behacks the post. Ape-like you see, the second merry still, Or whot with lust, he never thinkes of sleepe: Another swinish, feeles his stomach ill: The fourth is soft, and simple as the sheepe: A Romane sage, did sometime thus expresse, In briefe th' effectes, of loathsome Drunkenes. Nec igne, nec vnda. Amid the wanes, a mightie Rock doth stand, Whose ruggie brow, had bidden many a shower, And bitter storme; which neither sea, nor land, Nor IOVES sharpe-lightening ever could devoure: This same is MANLIE CONSTANCIE of mind, Not easly moou'd, with every blast of wind. Neere which you see, a goodly ship to drowne, Herewith bright flaming in a pitteous fire: This is OPINION, tossed vp and downe, Whose Pilot's PRIDE, &amp; Steeresman VAINE DESIRE, Those flames HOT PASSIONS, &amp; the WORLD the sea, God blesse the man, that's carried thus away. Præcocia non diuturna. While gentle Zephire, warmes the tender spring, And Flora glads all creatures at her sight: The Almond-trees, ere any leaues they bring, Vnfold their pride, their blossomes red and white: But withered soone, vnto the ground they fall, Or yeild their fruite, the least and last of all. So many children in their tender yeares, Doe promise much by towardlines of wit, From such, yet seldome any fruite appeares: When as some plodder, that below doth sit, Of whome both frendes, and maister did dispaire, As hindmost hound doth soonest catch the Hare. Ira Principum: Quocunque ferar. By rash attempt, who iniures mightie men, Or by base deede, incurres the Princes Ire, Doth often wish, it were to doe agen, And that his hand, perhaps were in the fire, That fought against him, or with Libell base, Sedition sow'd, or slaunder in disgrace. For as this Engine, where the same doth light, Like IOVE'S swift-thunder, merciles it strikes, And by the roote, rends vp rebellion quite: The wiser man, will then aware the pikes, And frame himselfe, to liue without offence, First God to serue, and afterwardes his Prince. Vlterius durabit. The Monuments that mightie Monarches reare, COLOSSO'S statües, and Pyramids high, In tract of time, doe moulder downe and weare, Ne leaue they any little memorie, The Passenger may warned be to say, They had their being here, another day. But wise wordes taught, in numbers sweete to runne, Preserued by the liuing Muse for aie, Shall still abide, when date of these is done, Nor ever shall by Time be worne away: Time, Tyrants, Envie, World assay thy worst, Ere HOMER die, thou shalt be “fired first. Pro Regno, et Religione. The Monarches good, that doe deserue the name Of “Countrie Parents, by their loue and care Of common-wealth, and to defend the same From publicque harmes, by wise foresight, prepare: By louing heartes, are guarded surer farre, Then some vnweldie SWIZZE, or IANIZAR. HENRY this once, thy Royall Imprese stood, To shew, thy foe should find thee readie prest, For Church, and Country, to dispend thy bloud, When daunger, or occasion did request, And further, though the Trumpet sterne did cease, Thus evermore, to goe prepar'd in PEACE. Non Nubila tangant. The godly mind, that hath so oft assaid, The perils that our frailtie here amate, Through heauenly wisedome, is no more afraid Of Fortunes frowne, and bitter blastes of Fate: For though in vale of woes, her dwelling be, Her nobler part's aboue vntouch't and free. For mortall thinges doe find their change below, And nought can here defend vs from the shower, Now greatest windes doe threate our overthrow, Our golden morne anon begins to lowre: And while our hopes, are yet but in their sap, Their buds are blasted by the Thunderclap. Ordo. The Common-wealth, whose Base is firmely laid On evenest ground, of Iustice and the right, By time or chaunge, in vaine we see assaide, But where affection overswaies with might: Confusion there, all vnto havock bringes, And vndermines, the thrones of mightiest Kinges. The Imprese of King Stephen. Our English STEPHEN, did take vnto him this Faire falling Plume, resembling best of all, The new establsh't goverment of his, Whereas each feather keepes his ranck and fall: So should that state, (let Fortune doe her worst,) As faire, and firme, as ever at the first. His graviora. The valiant mind, whome nothing can dismay, The losse of frendes, of goods, or long exile From natiue countrie, perils on the Sea, Night-watchings, hunger, thirst, and howerly toile, Takes courage, and the same abideth fast, With resolution, even vnto the last. Such shew'd himselfe, ÆNEAS vnto those Of his poore remnant, on the Tyrrhene Seas; When even dispaire, their eies began to close, We greater bruntes, haue borne (quoth he) then these: And God, (my Mates,) when he shall please will send, Vnto our greatest miseries an end. In vos hic valet. Nicolas VVhite. Who striues to keepe a heart and conscience pure, Devoide of vice, and inward guilt of Sinne: Is guarded by his Innocence more sure, And witnesse of an honest mind within, Then if he were in compleate armour clad, Or Bow and quiver of the Moore he had. For Innocence resembled by the WHITE, And manly courage by the constant heart, Way not a straw the force of SLAVNDERS might, DEATHES Ebone shaft, or CVPIDS golden dart: When, whome Affection, or their guilt doe wound, Even at the first, are stricken to the ground. Nitor in adversum. The Cipresse tree, the more with weight opprest, The more (they say) the braunch will vpward shoot, And since the bodie doth resemble best, A Columne strong and stately from the roote: The Auntients would, it should the Imprese be, Of Resolution, and true Constancie. Though Fortune frowne, and doe her worst to bend, Th' vndaunted spirit with her wearie weight, His vertue yet, doth ever vpward tend, And he himselfe, standes irremooued streight, Laughing to scorne, the paper blastes of Fate, That would remooue, or vndermine his state. Vanæ merces. In Naupalum. Rich NAVPALVS, hath secretly convaid, Our English fleece so long beyond the sea, That not for wit, but for his wealth tis said, Hee's thence return'd a worthy Knight awaie, And brought vs back, beades, Hobbie-horses, boxes, Fannes, Windmills, Ratles, Apes, and tailes of Foxes. And now like IASON, vp and downe he goes, As if he had th' Hesperian Dragon slaine, And equaliz'd in worth, those old Heroe's, That in the ARGO cut the Grecian maine: Honour thou didst, but doe his valour right, When of the fleece, thou dubbest him a Knight. Haud conveniunt. I much did muse, why Venus could not brooke, The savadge Boare, and Lion cruell feirce, Since Kinges and Princes, haue such pleasure tooke In hunting: haply cause a Boare did peirce Her Adon faire, who better lik't the sport, Then spend his daies, in wanton pleasures court. Which fiction though devisd by Poets braine, It signifies vnto the Reader this; Such exercise Loue will not entertaine, Who liketh best, to liue in Idlenes: The foe to vertue, Cancker of the wit, That bringes a thousand miseries with it. Zelus in Deum. To my Father, Mr. Henry Peacham, of Leverton in Holland, in the Countie of Linc: With Breast enflam'd, and longing heartes desire, Thus winged Zeale, to heauen-ward castes her eie: And loathing what the world doth most admire, Vpborne by Faith, ascendes aboue the skie: Whereby Oh God, thy misteries we learne, And all beyond, our reasons sight discerne. And as the Hart embos't, doth long to tast The pearly-trickling streame, or Christall fount, Even so the soule, by Sinne pursu'de and chas'd, Thee, thee, (oh Lord) desires, who dost surmount All treasures, pleasures, which we here possesse, The summe and substance, of our happines. Sanctitas simulata. There is more pride, vnder one of their black Bonnets, th? vnder Alexanders Diademe. King Iames in his Bisilicon Doron: Earle Gourie one of the greatest Puritanes of his time in Scotland, in his travailes thorough Fraunce and Italie, vsed with his Diamond, (for the most part) to draw in his Ch?ber windowe, a man in armour, with a Sword in his right hand, pointing towards a Crowne, adding this or the like word, Te solum, which yet r?aines in many places to be seene, what he meant hereby it might easily haue to bin ghessed. Vpon a Crowne with pretious Iemmes beset, Say what's the reason thus a hat we see, Since Diadem's of Princes ever yet, From base controule, haue beene exempt and free: There is a sect, whome PVRITANS they call, Whose pride this Figure fitteth best of all. Not such I meane, as are of Faith sincere, And to doe good endevour all they can, Would all the world of their religion were, We taxe th' aspiring factious Puritan: Whose Paritie, doth worst confusion bring, And Pride presumes to overlooke his King. De Morte, et Cupidine. Death meeting once, with CVPID in an Inne, Where roome was scant, togeither both they lay. Both wearie, (for they roving both had beene,) Now on the morrow when they should away, CVPID Death's quiver at his back had throwne, And DEATH tooke CVPIDS, thinking it his owne. By this o're-sight, it shortly came to passe, That young men died, who readie were to wed: And age did revell with his bonny-lasse, Composing girlonds for his hoarie head: Invert not Nature, oh ye Powers twaine, Giue CVPID'S dartes, and DEATH take thine againe. —Latet abditus agro. The valiant mind that once had most delight, By sea and land to make his prowesse knowne, And in defence of King, and countries right, So much his valour, and his vertue showne, Some wished port, doth at the last desire, And home whereto in age he may retire. For infinite's the summe of world affaires, Nor new, nor straunge, that doe afflict the mind, And shew before the day our silver haires, Yea even before we can experience find: That frailest man, by course of nature dies, Even at his first beginning to be wise. Sine Cerere et Baccho. Say Cytharæan maid, why with thy sonne, Both handes and feete thon warmest at the fire? Who wont your selues, t'enkindle many a one, With gentle flames, of kindly loues desire: I ghesse cause BACCHVS is not present heere, With mirthfull wine, nor CERES with her cheere. Where Temp'rance and Sobrietie do raigne, There lustfull vice, and pleasure frozen are: And vertue best, there liketh to remaine; When often times th' effectes of daintie fare, And drunken healthes, are quarrelles and debate, Blaspheming, whoredome, oathes and deadlie hate. Laboris effecta. To the no lesse vertuous then faire, Mrs. Anne Dudleie. é l' nuda DIANA. Anna Dudleia. Diana chast, doth eagerly pursue With swiftest houndes, the aiery-footed Stagge: And while they keepe, the merry chase in view, The woodes with Eccho's thundring, Loue doth lagge Behind the thickets, and with arrow keene, Doth lie in waite, to wound this maiden Queene. But all in vaine he doth his shaftes bestow, For Labour did this Goddesse faire defend, And sau'd her harmelesse from his deadly bow, And pois'nous dartes: so if thou dost intend, To overcome the force of Cupids might, Flie Idlenesse, and then he leaues thee streight. Gratis servire lîbertas. The gentle Merlion, wearied long with flight, While on the spray in shadie groue she sleepes, With tender foote, a Larke she holdeth light, Which till the morning carefully she keepes, Then lets it goe, and least she should that day Præie on the same, she flies another way. Such thanckfullnes in bird and beast we find, By Natures first instinct obserued still, When worser, man in benefits is blind, Nay oftentimes, for good will render ill: And rather seeke ingratefully his blood, That sau'd his life, or daily gaue him foode. Hìne super hæc, Musa. Henricus Peachamus. Bid now my Muse, thy lighter taske adieu, As shaken blossome of a better fruite, And with VRANIA thy Creator view, To sing of him, or evermore be mute: Let muddy Lake, delight the sensuall thought, Loath thou the earth, and lift thy selfe aloft. Repent not (though) thy time so idlely spent, The cunning'st Artist ere he can, (we see) Some rarest Modell bring to his Intent, Much heweth off in Superfluitie: And many a pretious hower, I know is lost, Ere ought is wrought to countervaile the cost. Movére levissima sensum. So quicke of sense as hath experience taught, The Tortoise liues within her armed shell, That if wee lay the lightest straw aloft, Or touch that Castle wherein she doth dwell, Shee feeles the same and quickly doth retire, A worke of Nature we do most admire, So many men are in theire Nature prone, To make the worst of matters vaine and light, And for a straw will take occasion, In choller moou'd to quarrell and to fight, Then meddle thou the least for feare of wrong, But most of all beware a lavish tongue. Negatur vtrumque. What shall we doe? now tell me gentle Muse, For we welnigh haue finished our taske, Thy tender hand could never Mattock vse, Full well I wot, nor canst thou humblie aske At greatnes gate, or for reversions sue, As beggars, and the basely minded doe. Desire of God but this, when thou art old, To haue a home, and somewhat of thine owne, To keepe thy selfe from hunger and the cold, And where thou maiest in quiet sing alone: For thinke it hell, to liue as bird in cage, At others curt'sie, in thy latter age. Sorte, aut Labore. If neither art, by birth, nor fortune blest, With meanes to liue, or answere thy desire, With cheerefull heart, on labour set thy rest, To bring to passe the thing thou dost require, For lot, or labour, must our calling giue, And find the word, that all doe seeke, TO LIVE. Though thousands haue beene raised by their frendes, By death, by dowries, even when least they thought, The Lord a blessing, still to labour sendes, When lightly come, doth lightly goe as oft: And goodes ill got, by vse, and wicked gaine, Doe seldome to the second heire remaine. Amicitiæ effigies. There was in Rome a goodlie statue fram'd Of youthfull hew, arraied all in greene, Which of the people was TRVE-FRENDSHIP nam'd: Winter and Sommer, on his brow were seene: Within his breast, his heart did plaine appeare, Whereon these wordes were written, Farre, and Neere. Vpon his skirt, stoode LIFE and DEATH below, To testifie in life and death his loue, That farre and neere, with open heart do show, Nor place, nor space, true frendship should remoue: Winter and sommer, whatsoever came, In faire or foule, we should be still the same. Nulli penetrabilis. A shadie Wood, pourtraicted to the sight, With vncouth pathes, and hidden waies vnknowne: Resembling CHAOS, or the hideous night, Or those sad Groues, by banke of ACHERON With banefull Ewe, and Ebon overgrowne: Whose thickest boughes, and inmost entries are Not peirceable, to power of any starre. Thy Imprese SILVIVS, late I did devise, To warne the what (if not) thou oughtst to be, Thus inward close, vnsearch'd with outward eies, With thousand angles, light should never see: For fooles that most are open-hearted free, Vnto the world, their weakenes doe bewray, And to the net, the first themselues betray. Vnum, et semel. A garden thinke this spatious world to be, Where thou by God the owners leaue dost walke, And art allow'd in all varietie, One only flower to crop from tender stalke, (As thou thinkst good) for beautie or the smell, Or some one else, whose beautie doth exell. This only flower, is some one calling fit, And honest course wherein to leade thy life, Thy selfe applieng carefully to it, Or else the heedie choosing of thy wife: Wherein thou wisely dost thy selfe preferre, Or to thy ruine ever after, erre. In Requie, Labor. Exesse we loath, of want we most complaine, The golden meane we prooue to be the best, Let idle fits refresh thy daylie paine, And with some Labour exercise thy rest, For overmuch of either, duls the spright, And robs our life, of comfort and delight. If that thou wouldst acquaint thee with the Muse, Withdraw thy selfe, and be thou least alone, Even when alone, as SOLON oft did vse, For no such frend to Contemplation, And our sweete studies, as the private life, Remote from Citie, and the vulgar strife. Rura mihi et silentium. Wert thou thy life at libertie to choose, And as thy birth, so hadst thy beeing free, The Citie thou shouldst bid adieu, my Muse, And from her streetes, as her infection flee: Where CHAOS and CONFVSION wee see, A swell of language, as of differing heartes, A bodie severed in a thousand parts. Thy solitarie A wood neere Athens, wherein the Phylosophers vsed to studie. Academe should be Some shadie groue, vpon the THAMES faire side, Such as we may neere princely RICHMOND see, Or where a long doth siluer SEVERNE slide, Or AVON courtes, faire FLORA in her pride: There shouldst thou sit at long desired rest, And thinke thy selfe, aboue a Monarch blest, There moughtst thou sing thy sweete Creators praise, And turne at quiet ore some holy booke; Or tune the Accent of thy harmelesse laies Vnto the murmur of the gentle brooke: Whiles round about thy greedy eie doth looke, Obseruing wonders in some flower by, This bent, that leafe, this worme, that butterflie. Where mightst thou view at full the Hemisphære On some faire Mountaine, in a Summers night, In spangles there embraudered is the BEARE, And here the FISH, there THESEVS louer bright, The watry HYADS, here deceiue our sight, ERIDANOS, and there ORION bound, Another way the silver SWANNE is found. Or wouldst thou Musick to delight thine eare, Step but aside into the neighbour spring, Thou shalt a thousand wing'd Musitians heare, Each praising in his kind the heauenly King: Here PHILOMEL, doth her shrill Treble sing, The THRVSH a Tenor, off a little space, Some matelesse DOVE, doth murmur out the Base. Geometry or wishest thou to learne, Obserue the Mill, the Crane, or Country Cart, Wherein with pleasure, soone thou shalt discerne The groundes, and vse of this admired Art, The rules of NVMBRING, for the greatest part, As they were first devis'd by Country Swaines, So still the Art with them entire remaines. If lou'st thy health, preferre the Country Aire, Thy Garden fore the Pothecaries shoppe, Where wholesome herbes, shall it at full repaire, Before a Quint'sence, or an oily droppe: There groweth the Balme, there shooteth Endiue vp: Here Pæonte for th' Epilepsie good, There Dill, and Hysope, best to stanch the bloud. The cooling Sorrell, and the Perslie whot, The Smallage, for a bruise, or swelling best, The Mercurie, the formost in the Pot, The Lavander, beloued for the Chest, The Costmarie, to entertaine the guest, The Rosemarie, and Fenel, seldome set, The lowlie Daisie, and sweete Violet. Nor Princes richest Arras may compare With some small plot, where Natures skill is showen, Perfuming sweetely all the neighbour aire, While thousand cullors in a night are blowne: Here's a light Crimson, there a deeper one, A Maidens blush, here Purples, there a white, Then all commingled for our more delight. Withall (as in some rare limn'd booke) we find, Here, painted Lectures of Gods sacred will, The Daisie, teacheth lowlines of mind, The Camomill, we should be patient still, The Rue, our hate of vices poison ill, The Woodbine, that we should our frendship hold, Our Hope, the Sav'rie, in the bitterst cold. Yet loue the Citie, as the kindly Nurse Of all good Artes, and faire Civillitie: Where though with good, be intermix't the worse, That most disturbe our sweete Tranquillitie: Content thy selfe, till thine Abillitie, And better hap, shall answere thy desire, But Muse beware, least we too high aspire. Omnis a Deo Sapientia. The Poets faigne, IOVE to haue beene with child, But very straunge, conceiu'd within his head, And knowing not, his burthen how to yeeld, Lo! MVLCIBER doth bring the God abed, By cutting with an Axe, his skull in two, When issueth PALLAS forth, with much adoe. By PALLAS, is all heavenly wisdome ment, Which not from Nature, and our selues proceedes, But is from God, immediately sent, (For in our selues, how little goodnes breedes) That threefold power of the Soule againe Resembling God, resideth in our braine. Some wits of men, so dull and barren are, That without helpe of Art, no fruite they bring, Whose Midwife must be toile, and endlesse care, And Constancie, effecting every thing: And those who wanting Eloquence, are mute, Some other way like IOVE, must yeeld their fruite. Divina misericordia. The greedie Eagle here, vpon the tree, PROMETHEVS heart with teene doth præy vpon, But this example doth admonish thee On wretches poore to haue compassion: To pitie those, on whome doth fortune frowne, And Tyrant-like, not more to crush them downe. This pleaseth God, this Pietie commaundes, Nature, and Reason, bids vs doe the like, Yea though our foes, doe fall into our handes, Wee should haue mercie, not in malice strike: Who helpes the sick, and pities the oppressed, He liues to God, and doubtlesse dieth blessed. Homo Microcosmus. Heare what's the reason why a man we call A little world? and what the wiser ment By this new name? two lights Cœlestiall Are in his head, as in the Element: Eke as the wearied Sunne at night is spent, So seemeth but the life of man a day, At morne hee's borne, at night he flits away. Of heate and cold as is the Aire composed, So likewise man we see breath's whot and cold, His bodie's earthy: in his lunges inclosed, Remaines the Aire: his braine doth moisture hold, His heart and liver, doe the heate infold: Of Earth, Fire, Water, Man thus framed is, Of Elements the threefold Qualities. And as we fitly INFANCIE compare Vnto the SPRING, so YOVTH we liken may To lazie SVMMER, whot devoid of care: His middle Age to AVTVMNE, his decay To WINTER, snowie white, and frostie gray, For then his vigor failes, his heate is cold, And like the saplesse Oake he dieth old. Vini natura. Best BACCHVS Ivie thy faire brow befits, Thy winges withall, that proud Gorgonean horse: Because thou addest vigor to our wits, Heate to our blood, vnto our bodie force: Mirth to our heartes, vnto the dullard spright A quick Invention, to the Sence delight. Vnum alam. The Husband good, that by experience knowes, With cunning skill, to prune, and when to plant, Must lop the Tree where ranck abundance growes, Aswell as helpe the barren in her want: Else happilie, when Summer season's past, With leaues he may goe satisfie his tast. Even so the wit, that ranckly doth abound, With many fancies but it selfe deceiues: And while it seemes in sundry Artes profound, In no one good it's fruitfull, but in leaues: Then some one calling choose, whence good may growe, And let the rest, as needelesse branches goe. Terminus. A pillar high, erected was of stone, In former times, which TERMINVS they nam'd: And was esteem'd, a God of every one: The vpper part, was like a woman fram'd, Of comely feature downe vnto the brest, Of Marble hard a Pillar was the rest. Which when IOVE passed by, with sterne aspect, He bad this God remooue, and get him gone, But TERMINVS as stoutly did neglect His heste, and answer'd, I giue place to none: I am the bound of thinges, which God aboue Hath fixt, and none is able to remooue. Fortuna maior. Heere Povertie, doth conquered Fortune bind, And vnder keepes, like HERCVLES in aw, The meaning is, the wise and valiant mind, In Povertie esteemes not Fate a straw: And though a while this angry Goddesse frowne, She vtterlie shall never cast him downe. If Wisdome haue but what the corpes doth craue, Convenient foode and raiment for the back: And libertie to liue, not like a slaue Here in this world, she little else doth lack: But can contented in her cottage sing, In greater safetie, then the greatest King. Nec in vna sede morantur. The awfull Scepter though it can compell By powerfull might, great'st Monarches to obay: Loue, where he listeth, liketh best to dwell, And take abroade his fortune as he may: Ne might, or gold, can winne him thence away, Whereto he is through strong affection led, Be it a Pallace, or the simplest shedde. But VENVS Infant, dred of all beneath, Imperious feare from my sweete Saint remooue, And with thy soft Ambrosial kisses, breath Into her bosome meeke, and mildest Loue With melting Pitie, from thy Queene aboue: That she may reade, and oft remember this, And learne to loue, who most beloued is. Super terram peregrinans. Nor house, nor home, hath wretched man on earth, Ne ought he claimeth iustly as his owne: But as a Pilgrim wandring from his birth In Countries straunge, and Deserts wild vnknowne, Like RECHABITE, or those Tartarian Companies of Tartars, and subiects of the great CHAM, liuing in Tentes in the wildernes, without Civilitie, togeither with their wiues, children, and cattle, never abiding in one place, but ranging and robbing vp and downe where they list. HORDES, Whose vastest Region but a Tent affordes. Betime hence learne we wisely to supplie Our inward wantes, ere hence we flit away: And hide in Heauen, that treasure carefully, Which neither Moth, nor Canker shall decaie: In following state, eke not to spend our stock, Where oft for merit, we but gaine a mock. Sapientiam, Avaritia, et Dolus, decipiunt. Ah pitie PALLAS, who hath thee enwrapt? And in a snare, thus brought thee to distresse: The wisest now I see may be entrapt, And Vertue stoope to Fortunes ficklenesse: Nor Scholler-ship, or wit, at all times can From sad disaster, keepe a mortall man. The loue of Money, and Dissimulation, Hold thee MINERVA tangled in their snare: For now the world, is growne to such a fashion, That those the wisest, that the richest are, And such by whome the simpler should be taught, Are in the net, like PALLAS soonest caught. Personam non animum. The Hypocrite, that doth pretend in show, A feigned Zeale of Sanctitie within, Eschew betime, nor haue with such to doe, Whose hoodes are but the harbour of their Sinne, And humblest habits, but a false disguise, To cloke their hate, or hidden villanies. No HIRCAN Tyger, ERYMANTHIAN Beare, So arm'd with malice, thirstie after blood, To high estate aspiring, as they are, The worst of men, nay man it is too good. Where LVCIFER did openly rebell To God, these Traitors even within the Cell. Honores isti aliunde. The cheifest good, (ah would so good it were) That most imagine Honours bring with them, We pick from others praises here and there, So patch herewith an Indian Diadem Of Parrats feathers, vocall favours light, And Plumes indeede, whereto we haue no right. He is not honourd that Discents can show, Nor he that can commaund a numerous traine, Nor he to whome the vulgar lout so low, Nor he that followes Fashion light and vaine, Saluting windowes, and around doth wheele, Like VRSA MAIOR, starres from head to heele. We honour him, whose Actions not deface, The Glories which his Ancestors haue wonne, By Cowardise, or vicious liuing base, Ne wrong for Passion, or Affect hath done: In whome at once, Artes, Bountie, Valour, dwell. Contending each which other should excell. Non alit, enecat. The Laurel greene, that long in safetie stood By PENEVS streame, the Muses chast delight, Oft water'd by the NAIAD'S of the flood, And oft reviued by her PHOEBVS, whome the Poets feigne to haue loued the Bay, vnder the name of DAPHNE. Louer bright, The Waue assaileth with her swelling might, And overthrowes in time, (but who doth know Their miserie, that neere to Greatnes grow.) This sacred Bay, is Learning and the Artes, In former times that flourished at will, Now wash'd and worne by some, even to the heartes, Who should haue succour'd and vpheld them still, Who eate the Corne, but throw the Chaffe to Skill: And what the Church had once to holy vses, Serues them to pride, and all prophane abuses. Minimus in summo. If that thy Fortunes haue their heigth attain'd, And bid thee not on greatnes BASE to feare, Let not with that preferment thou hast gain'd, Vnwonted Pride, or Insolence appeare: But how much higher thou art plac'd in sight, So much the lesse affect thy state and might. For Honors, know, but lend Ambition winge, And like false mirrours, make vs seeme too greate, Vpborne by vulgar breath, (the vainest thing,) Till all be melted by the Soveraigne heate: That left abandon'd, in a trustlesse aire, We drowne within an Ocean of dispaire. Nil viribus impar. First trie thy strength, and ponder well the end, Ere thou attempt'st a buisines of weight, By triall made of wit, thy wealth, or frend, Who can advise, or iudge of thy conceipt: Thou else but hastest, to thy losse and shame, While abler Iudgments, beare away the game. Hence noblest houses, their decay haue knowne, And greatest Clerkes in vaine opinions err'd, And wits too heavy-rancke beene overthrowne, Who else in time, mought well haue beene preferr'd: Withall we taxe, the glorious foole that crakes, Yet good at nothing, that he vndertakes. Sic bellica virtus. The valiant mindes, that doe delight a farre, By vertuous deede to make their prowesse knowne, Who not of Fathers Actes ambitious are, But of the braue Atcheiuements of their owne, Thus as their Ensignes folded vp vnshowne, In Peace reiected, or forgotten lie: Till new Alarmes, advance them out on high. But Wisedome ever armed with Fore-sight, Then rateth Valour at her weight in gold, For though the ease-full world her merit slight, She seees aloofe the storme. How Malice old Plaies loose a while to get the better hold, And bids vs arme, when least we thinke of knocks, For A Proverbe well knowne in the low Co?tries Foes asleepe, (they say) the Divell rocks, Tantó dulcius. The mortall strifes that often doe befall, Twixt louing Bretheren, or the private frend, Doe proue (we say) the deadliest of all: Yet if The first Discord here taken is from the elev?th to the tenth, that is from b fa b mi, vnto alamire, a tenth to f fa vt in the Base, The second from the ninth, or second to the 8, or vnison. compos'd by concord, in the end They relish sweeter, by how much the more, The Iarres were harsh, and discordant before. How oft hereof the Image I admire, In thee sweete MVSICK, Natures chast delight, The Banquets frend, and Ladie of the Quire; Phisition to the melancholly spright: Mild Nurse of Pietie, ill vices foe; Our Passions Queene, and Soule of All below. Per far denari. The worldly wretch, that day and night doth toile, And tire himselfe in bodie and in minde, To gather that by all devises vile, He must be faine ere long to leaue behinde: All shapes like PROTEVS gladly entertaines, No matter what, so that they bring the gaines. Abroade Religion, Flatterie at the Court, Plaine dealing in the Countrie where he dwells, Then Gravitie among the wiser sort, Where Fooles are rife, his Follie most excells: Thus every way transforme himselfe he can Saue one, in time to turne an honest man. Aula. With mightie men, who likes to spend his prime, And loues that life, which few account the best, In hope at length vnto his heigth to clime, By good desert, or thorough Fortune blest, May here behold the Modell of his blisse, And what his life, in summe and substance is. A Ladie faire, is Favovr feign'd to be, Whose youthfull Cheeke, doth beare a louely blush, And as no niggard of her courtesie, She beares about a Holy-water brush: Where with her bountie round about she throwes, Faire promises, good wordes, and gallant showes. Herewith a knot of guilded hookes she beares, With th' other hand, a paire of Stocks she opes, To shew her bondage: on her feete she weares Lead-shoes, as waiting long vpon her Hopes: And by her doth the fawning Spaniel lie, The Princes bane, the marke of Flatterie. The Authors Conclusion. As then the Skie, was calme and faire, The Windes did cease, and Cloudes were fled, AVRORA scattered PHOEBVS haire, New risen from her Rosie bed: At whose appoach the FLORA sometimes a famous Harlot in Rome, and after Goddesse of flowers, in whose honour they kept their feastes called Floralia. Harlot strew, Both meade, and mountaine, with her flowers: While ZEPHYRE, sweetest odours threw, About the feildes, and leavie bowers. The Woods and Waters, left their sound, No tend'rest twigge, was seene to mooue, The Beast lay couched on the ground, The winged People perch'd aboue, Saue PHILOMEL, who did renew, Her wonted plaintes vnto the Morne, That seem'd indeede, her state to rue, By shedding teares vpon the Thorne. When I as other taking rest, Was shew'd (me thought) a goodlie plaine, With all the store of Nature blest, And situate within the Maine, With Rocks about environ'd quite, But inward round, in rowes there stood, Aswell for profit, as delight, The Trees of Orchard, and the Wood. The builder Akorne long agoe, To DODONÆAN IOVE adioin'd, And there the loftie Pine did grow, That winged flies before the Wind: LEVCOTHOE that wounded bleedes, Nor wanting was, nor that same Tree, That beares the staine, in fruite and seedes, Of THISBES woefull Tragœdie. The Elme embracing BACCHVS stood, And there the Beech was also plac't, That gaue the golden Age her foode: Though we esteeme it, but as mast; The Walnut, praised for her hew, The Ash, the best for helue, and staues, The Eugh, vnto the bender trew, The Sallow soft, that water craues. Th' vnblasted Bay, to conquests due, The Persian Peach, and fruitefull Quince: And there the forward Almond grew, With Erasmus in his Commentaries vpon St. Hierom affirmeth Cherries to haue been knowne to these partes of Europe little aboue two or three hundred yeares, being first brought from Cerarasvntis a Citie of PONTVS, wh?ce they haue their name. Cherries knowne no long time since: The VVinter-Warden, Orchards pride, The The Filbert so named of PHILIBERT a king of France, who caused by Arte, sundry kindes to be brought forth, as did a Gardiner of OTRANTO, in Italie by cloue Gilliflowers, and Carnations, of such cullours as we now see them PHILIBERT, that loues the vale, And red Queene-Apple, so envi'de, Of Schooleboies, passing by the pale. With many moe, of me forgot, Vpon the which the Aëry crew, Each in his kind, and order sat, And did his wonted note renew; The long-liu'd Eagle, IOVE forsooke, And hither in a moment flew, Who to the Oake, himselfe betooke, As King, his multitude to view. And IVNOS Bird, not farre away, Displaid her ARGVS hundred eies; By him sat perched on a spray, The Swanne, that sweetly singing dies: The Crane, who Centinell hath stood, The Herne, high'st soarer in our sight, The Pheasaunt fetch'd from PHASIS flood, With Faulcon for the Kings delight. The Turtle here to each did tell, The losse of his beloued mate, And so did THRACIAN Philomel, In sweetest tunes, her bitter Fate: Ne wanted there the envious Stare, The theevish Chough, and prating Iay, The Raile, and frostie Feldefare, And Larke abroade by breake of day. Within there was a Circlet round, That rais'd it selfe, of softest grasse, No Velvet smoother spred on ground, Or Em'rald greener ever was: In mid'st there sate a beauteous Dame, (Not PAPHOS Queene, so faire a wight) For Roses by, did blush for shame, To see a purer, red and white. In Robe of woven Silver fine, And deepest Crimson she was clad: Then diaper'd with golden twine, Aloft a Mantle greene she had, Whereon were wrought, with rarest skill Faire Cities, Castles, Rivers, Woods; And here, and there, emboss'd a hill With Fountaines, and the Nymphes of Floods. A massie Collar set with stones, Did over all, it selfe extend, Whereon in sparkling Diamonds, SAINT GEORGE, her Patrone did depend; A Crowne Imperial on her head, One hand a bright drawne Sword did hold, The other (most that made her dredd,) Three Scepters of the finest gold. While proudly vnderfoote she trod, Rich Trophæies, and victorious spoiles, Atchieued by her might abroad: Her name is EMPRESSE OF THE ILES: There Charriots were, that once she wanne, From CÆSAR, ere she was betraid, With standards gat from Pagans, whan She lent the Holy Land her aide. Here saw I many a shiver'd launce, Swordes, Battle-axes, Cannons Slinges, With th' Armes of PORTVGAL, and FRAVNCE, And Crownets of her pettie Kinges: High-feathered Helmets for the Tilt, Bowes, Steelie Targets cleft in twaine: Coates, Cornets, Armours richly guilt, With tatterd Ensignes out of SPAINE. About her now on every Tree, (Whereon full oft she cast her eie,) Hung silver Sheildes, by three and three, With Pencill limned curiouslie: Wherein were drawne with skilfull tuch, Impresa's, and Devises rare, Of all her gallant Knightes, and such As Actors in her Conquestes were. Eke some of Queenes, and Ladies too, As pleased their Invention best, (For wit of woman, much can doe;) Were fastned vp among the rest, In sundry tongues, whose Motto's old, And names, though scarcely could be read, She wishd their Glories mought be told, To after times, though they were dead. Great Edvvard third, you might see there, With that victorious Prince his sonne: Next valiant Iohn of Lancaster, That Spaine, with English overran: And those braue spirits Marshalled, The first that of the Garter were, All Souldiers, none to Carpet bred, Whose names to tell I must forbeare. Fourth Henries Sunbeames on the Cloude, Fift Henries Beacon flaming bright, Yorkes Locke, that did the Falcon shroude, Was here, so were his Roses white: The Marshal Movbraie Norfolkes Duke, Yet liuing in great Hovvards blood, With valiant Bedford, Symboles tooke As pleas'd them, to adorne the Wood. By whome the Beavchampes worne away, And noblest Talbot, scourge of Fravnce, With Nevills whome could nought dismay, Left Reliques of their Puissance: The loyal Vere, and Clifford stout, Greate Strongbovves heire, with Bovrchier, Gray, Braue Falconbridge, and Montacvte: Couragious Ormond, Lisle, and Say. With other numberlesse beside, That to haue seene each one's devise, How liuely limn'd, how well appli'de, You were the while in Paradise: Another side she did ordaine, Charles E: of Nortingham L: Admiral. Thomas E: of Suffolke, and L: Chamberlaine. George E: of Cumberland. L: Willowghby. Sir Philip Sydney Sir Ihon Norris. &amp;c. To some late dead, some liuing yet, Who seru'd Eliza in her raigne, And worthily had honour'd it. Where turning, first I spide aboue, Her owne deare Phoenix hovering, Whereat, me thought, in melting Loue, Apace with teares mine eies did spring; But Foole, while I aloft did looke, For her that was to Heauen flowne, This goodly place, my sight forsooke, And on the suddaine all was gone. With griefe awak'd, I gaz'd around, And casting vp to Heauen mine eie, Oh God I said! where may be found, These Patrones now of Chivalry, “But Vertue present and secure, “We hate, when from our knowledge hid, “By all the meanes we her allure, “To take her dwelling where she did. Now what they were, on every Tree, Devises new, as well as old, Of those braue worthies, faithfullie, Shall in another Booke be told. FINIS. 1612.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Epigramma Authoris. Se dicit Servum modo patre superstite Princeps, Primus at Imperio Servus HIC, IN DE regit.</field>
   </doc>
</add>