<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Moffett, Thomas, 1553-1604</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Moffett, Thomas, 1553-1604</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">moffett thomas 1553 1604</field>
      <field name="author_text">Moffett, Thomas, 1553-1604</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">16th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.1088.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1599</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:463728</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Greek, Modern (1453- )</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Silkewormes ; and their Flies: Liuely described in verse, by T. M. [i.e. Thomas Moffet] a Countrie Farmar, and an apprentice in Physicke. For the great benefit and enriching of England</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Silkewormes ; and their Flies: Liuely described in verse, by T. M. [i.e. Thomas Moffet] a Countrie Farmar, and an apprentice in Physicke. For the great benefit and enriching of England</field>
      <field name="title_facet">silkewormes</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">silkewormes</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Silkewormes ; and their Flies: Liuely described in verse, by T. M. [i.e. Thomas Moffet] a Countrie Farmar, and an apprentice in Physicke. For the great benefit and enriching of England</field>
      <field name="year_display">1599</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1599</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1599</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463728&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463728&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Moffett, Thomas, 1553-1604&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;moffett thomas 1553 1604&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Silkewormes ; and their Flies: Liuely described in verse, by T. M. [i.e. Thomas Moffet] a Countrie Farmar, and an apprentice in Physicke. For the great benefit and enriching of England&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;silkewormes&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1599&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1599&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Moffett, Thomas&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1553&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1604&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Silkewormes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;and their Flies: Liuely described in verse, by T. M. [i.e. Thomas Moffet] a Countrie Farmar, and an apprentice in Physicke. For the great benefit and enriching of England&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed ... by V. S. for Nicholas Ling [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1599&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp2710&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;gre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;75 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Silkewormes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;and their Flies: Liuely described in verse, by T. M. [i.e. Thomas Moffet] a Countrie Farmar, and an apprentice in Physicke. For the great benefit and enriching of England&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 165 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To the most renowned Patronesse, and noble Nurse of Learning MARIE Countesse of Penbrooke. Great enuies Obiect, Worth &amp; Wisedoms pride, Natures delight, Arcadia's heire most fitte, Vouchsafe a while to lay thy taske aside, Let Petrarke sleep, giue rest to Sacred Writte, Or bowe, or string will breake, if euer tied, Some little pawse aideth the quickest witte: Nay, heau'ns themselues (though keeping stil their way) Retrogradate, and make a kind of stay. I neither sing Achilles baneful ire, Nor Man, nor Armes, nor Belly-brothers warres, Nor Britaine broiles, nor citties drownd in fire, Nor Hectors wounds, nor Diomedes skarres, Cease country Muse so highly to aspire: Our Plaine beholds but cannot holde such starres: Ioue-loued wittes may write of what they will, But meaner Theams beseeme a Farmers quill. I sing of little Wormes and tender Flies, Creeping along, or basking on the ground, Grac't once with those thy heau'nly-humane eies, Which neuer yet on meanest scholler fround: And able are this worke to æternise, From East to West about this lower Round, Deigne thou but breathe a sparke or little flame Of likeing, to enlife for aye the same. Your H. euer most bounden. T. M. [Sydneian Muse: if so thou yet remaine] Of the Silke wormes and their Flies. Sydneian Muse: if so thou yet remaine, In brothers bowels, or in daughters breast, Or art bequeath'd the Lady of the plaine, Because for her thou art the fittest guest: Whose worth to shew, no mortall can attaine, Which with like worth is not himselfe possest: Come help me sing these flocks as white as milke, That make, and spinne, and die, and windle silke. For sure I know thy knowledge doth perceiue, What breth embreath'd these almost thingles things: VVhat Artist taught their feete to spinne and weaue: What workman made their slime a robe for kings, How flies breed wormes, how wormes do flies conceiue: Fr? natures womb, how such a nature springs, Whereof none can directly tell or reede, Whether were first, the flie, the worme, or seede. A time there was (sweete heau'ns restore that time,) When bodyes pure to spotlesse soules first knit, Deuoyd of guilt, and ignorant of crime, Vpright in conscience, and of harmelesse wit, Disdain'd to weare a garment nere so fine, As deeming coates and couers most vnfit, Where nothing eie could see, or finger touch, Which God himselfe did not for good auouch. Gen. 1.verse 31 Yea, when all other creatures looked base, As mindful onely of their earthly foode: Or else as trembling to behold the place, Where iudge eternall sate, and Angels stood: Then humane eyes beheld him face to face, And cheekes vnstain'd with fumes of guiltie bloud, Desir'd no maske to hide their blushing balles, But boldly gaz'd and pried on heau'nly walles. The breast which yet had hatcht no badde conceat, Nor harbor'd ought in heart that God displeaz'd, Did it for silken wastcotes then intreate? Sought it with Tyrian silks to be appeaz'd? No, no, there was no neede of such a feate, Where all was sound, and members none diseaz'd: Nay more, The basest parts and seates of shame, Were seemely then, and had a comely name. Gen. 3.But when selfe-will and subtile creepers guile, Made man to lust, and taste what God forbad, Then seem'd we to our selues so foule and vile, That straight we wisht our bodies to be clad, Seeing without, and in such great defile, As rest our wittes, and made vs al so mad: That we resembled melancholique hares, Or startling stagges, whom euerie shadow scares. Then Bedlam-like to woods wee ranne apace, Praying each tree to lend vs shade or leaues, Wherewith to hide (if ought might hide) our face From his al-seeing eyes, who al perceaues, And with ful-brandisht sword pursues the chace, Traitors of rest, of shade, and al bereaues: Permitting men with nothing to be clad, But shame, dispaire, guilt, feare, and horror sad. These robes our parents first were deckt withal, Then fig tree fannes vppon their shame they wore: Next, skinnes of beasts, (to shew their beastly fall) Then, hairy cloathes, and wooll from Baa-lambs tore, Last, Easterne wittes, from mane of Camels tall, Plin. lib. 12. ca. 10. &amp; lib. 24. cap. 12. Made water-waued stuffe vnseene before, But til the floud had sinners swept away, Nor Flaxe, nor Silke, did sinful man array. For so it seemed iust to Iustice eyen, Defiled men to weare polluted things: And Rebels not to clothe in Flaxe or line, Which from the sacred loines of Vesta spring, Cleane, knotlesse, straight, spotlesse, vpright, and fine, VVhose floure is like fiue heau'nly-azurd wings, Whose slime is salue, whose seed is holsom food, Whose rinde is cloth, whose stuble seru's for wood Plut. lib. de Isid[illeg.] &amp; Osir. Or if A most famous spinner in Lydiæ, of whom Ouid 6 metam. Arachne erst made sisters threed, Was it thinke you, for euery man to weare? Or onely for the sacrificers weede, VVho of th'immortall priest a type did beare? Wearing not aught that sprang from brutish seed, But what from out it selfe the earth did reare: Exodus 28.So that till holy priesthood first began, VVe neuer reade that linnen clothed man. Yet some conceiue when Orpheus a most famous Poet. Ouid II met. Theban singer wanne, VVood-wandring wights to good and ciuill life, (Which erst with beares and wolues in desarts ran, Knowing no name of God, law, house, or wife) That then his brother Linus first began The Flaxmans craft (a secret then vnrife) Deuising beetles, hackels, wheeles, and frame, Wherwith to bruse, touse, spin &amp; weaue the same. But Silke (whereon my louing Muze now stands) Was it the ofspring of our shallow braine? Spunne with these fingers foule? these filthy hands, Tainted with bloud, reuenge, and wrongful gaine? Ah no, who made and numbreth all the sands, Wil teach vs soone that fancie to be vaine: Farre be it from our thoughts, that sinfull sence, Should make a thing of so great excellence. Ne neede wee yet with Hironimus vidas, Bishop of Alba. lib. 1. de Bombyce. Tuscane Prelate flie, To fictions strange, or wanton Venus eyen: Who seeing Pallas taught from Saturne hie, To clothe her selfe and hers with weaued line, Yea all the Nimphs and Goddesses in skie, To weare long stoles of Lawne and Cambrick fine: Fretted to see her selfe and boy new borne, Left both to heau'n and earth an open scorne. Reuenge she cri'de vnto the sire of Ioue, As she lay hidde vnder th'Idalian tree: Affoord some rayment from thy house aboue, If but to hide the shame of mine and mee. So may thou learne from vs The art of Loue, Whereby to winne each Ladies heart to thee. But grumbling Chuff reiected still her prayre, Whereat lamented heau'ns and weeping aire. Then Cyprian Queene perceiuing that no cries Could pierce the leaden eares of sullen Sire, Straight lodg'd her sonne in faire Oceanus his daughter, a most braue virgin. Ouid 6 met. Phillyraes eies, And caus'd him thence to darte vppe such a fire, As had consum'd the very starres and skies, Yea melted Saturnes wheeles with hot desire: Vnlesse that very houre he had come downe, And beg'd her aide, on whom he late did frowne. How often, as his loue on Pelion hill Stoopt downe to gather herbs for wounds and sores, Strew'd he before her Tutsan, Balme, and Dill, Long Plantaine, Hysope, Sage, and Comfrey moares? Offring besides, the art and perfect skill, Of healing bloudy wounds and festred coares: How oft (I say) did he each day descend, And bootelesse al his vowes and wooings spend? He lou'd, she loath'd, he liked, she disdain'd: He came, she turn'd, he prest, she ranne away, Neither by words, nor gifts shee could be gain'd, (For onely in her eies the Archer lay) Regarding nought but (wherein she was train'd) VVounds how to cure, and smartings to allay: As for the wound of Loue, she felt it none, And therefore litle heeded Saturns mone. Thus thus perplext the chiefe and grauest God, (Or rather God supposd of highest place) Toucht now, nay throughly scourg'd with Cupids rodde, Sent from the eyes but of a mortal face, Flewe downe forthwith where Venus made abode, And prostrate lying at her feete for grace: Promis'd the richest clothing for her Art, That now she did, or could desire in hart. VVho earelesse of reuenge, and innely grieu'd, (True beauty aye is ful of rueful mone) VVas neuer wel til Saturne was releeu'd, His inward griefes asswag'd, &amp; sorrowes gone. And finding him, of hope, and helpe, bereeu'd, (For still Phillira was more hard then stone) Sith that, quoth she, the virgin scorns thy loue, Try whether craft and force wil make her moue. Transforme thy selfe into a Courser braue, (VVhat cannot loue transforme it selfe into?) Feede in her walkes: and in a moment haue VVhat thou hast woo'd to haue with much adooe: VVhereto, consent the auncient Suter gaue, In Coursers clothes, learning a maide to wooe, Filling ech wood with neighs and wihyes shrill, VVhilst he possest his loue against her will. For lesson which, his Mistris to requite, Not with vaine hopes in lieu of friendly deeds, By Maiae's Mercurie, postmaster to Iupiter. sonne (before it grew to night) He sent a Napkin ful of little seeds, Tane from the tree where Thisbes soule did light, To make her selfe and boy farre brauer weeds, Than Pallas had, or any of the seu'n, Yea, then proud Iuno ware the Queene of heau'n. Withall, by him he sent the mysterie Of weauing silke, which he himselfe had found, When chac'd from heau'n by sonnes owne trechery, Hee was compel'd to wander here on ground, Where, in the depth of griefe and pouertie, The height and depth of Arts he first did sound: Yet would he this to none but her reueale, By whose deuise hee did Phillyra steale. What? shall we thinke, that silke was a reward. Bestow'd on craftie dame for aide vniust? Would men, nay, ought they haue such hie regard, Of that which was the lone and hire of lust? Not so, what ere th'Italian Bishop dar'd To faine for true, and giue it out with trust: Yet sith silke robes the blessed High-priest wore, They were not sure the first fruits of a whore. Vespasians Plinius Secundus, lib. II. cap. 2. Scribe affirmes in Cean Ile, Latous Called Pamphia, a most princely Damsell. daughter, quicke of eye and wit, Hunting abroad, times trauaile to beguile, Chaunc'd at the length vnder a tree to sitte, Where many silken bottoms hangd in piles, One by another plac't in order fit. Shee tooke one downe, and with her faulcon eye, Found out the end that did the rest vntie. Looke how the hungry Lambe doth friske and play, With restlesse taile, and head, and euery limbe, When it hath met his mother gone astray, Who absent blear'd and tear'd as much for him: Or as Aurora leapes at breake of day, Seeing her louely brother rise so trim, No lesse that Princesse triumph't (if not more) Finding out that which was not found before. Loues Schoolemaster Ouid lib. 4. Metam. records a tale most sweete, Of louers two that dwelt at Babilon, Equall of age, in worth and beautie meete, Each of their sex the floure and paragon, Next neighbours borne on side of selfesame streete, For twixt their parents houses dwelled none, Him Pyramus, her Thisbe men did call, Coupled in heart, though seuered by a wall. As neighbours children, oft they talke and view, That neighbourship was formost steppe to loue, Loue, which (like Priuie plants) in short time grew, Pales, wals, and eues, yea houses and all aboue, Nay Hymeneus feasts were like t'ensue, And sacred hands giue ring and wedding gloue, Had not vnhappie parents that forbad, Which to forbid, no cause but wil, they had. If louers spake, it was now all by lookes, None deign'd or durst be trouchman to their mind, Paper was barr'd, and penne, and inke, and bookes, Not any helpe these parted prisoners find, But of a rift along the wal that crookes, (A wall of flint, yet more then parents, kind) Which, were it old or new, none it espies, But louers quicke, al-corner-searching eyes, This rift they vsde, not onely as a glasse, Wherein to see daily each others face, But eke through it their voyces hourely passe, In whispring murmurs with a stealing pace: Sometimes when they no longer durst (alas) Send whisprings through, when keepers were in place, Yet would they shift to blow through it a breath, Which fed &amp; kept their hoping harts from death. Enuious wal (sayd they) what wrong is this? Why doth not loue or pittie make thee fal? Or (if that be for vs too great a blisse) Why is thy rift so narrow and so small, As to deny kind loue a kindly kisse? For which we neuer proue vnthankful shal, Although in truth we owe inough to thee, Giuing our eyes and voyce a way so free. In vaine thus hauing plaind in place distinct, When night approacht, they ech bad ech adew, Kissing their wal apart where it was chinckt, Whence louely blasts and breathings mainely flew: But kisses staide on eithers side fast linckt, Seal'd to the wal with lips and Louers glue: For though they were both thick and many eake, Yet thicker was the wal that did them breake. Rose-fingred The morning, Homer. Iliad 4. Dame no sooner had put out Nights twinckling fires and candles of the skie, Nor Phœbus The Sunne. brought his trampling steeds about, Whose breath dries vp the teares of Vestaes The earth. eie, But swift and soft, without all noyse or showt, To wonted place they hasten secretly, Where midst a many words muttred that day, Next midnights watch, each vowes to steale away. And lest when hauing house and cittie past, They yet might erre in fields, and neuer meete, At Ninus Which was without the gates of Balilon, towards the forrest. Sabell. Enneiad. 1. cap. 6. tombe their Rendes-vous is plac't, Vnder the Mulb'ry white, and hony-sweete: Growing hard by a spring that ranne at waste, With streames more swift then speedy The swift riuer of Donawe. Isters feete. There they agreed in spite of spite to stand, Wh? The Charles waine. Monarchs teame had past The great star following Vrsa maior. Bootes hand. Consent they did, and day consented too, Whose Coach ranne downe the seas in greater hast, Then euer it was wont before to doo, Loue-louing night approched eke so fast, That darknesse leapt, ere twilight seem'd to go, Wherat though some gods frown'd, some were agast, Yet Lethes Sleep the brother of forgetfulnesse. Cio. lib. de nat. deorum. brother did the louers keepe, Chaining their guard with long and heauy sleep. How feately then vnsparred she the doore? How silent turn'd it on the charmed cheekes? And being scap't, how glad was she therefore? How soone arriu'd where she her fellow seekes? Loue made her bold, loue gaue her swiftnesse more Then vsually is found in weaker sexe, But all in vaine: nay rather to her ill, For haste made waste, and speede did speeding kil. The grisly wife of brutish monarch strong, With new slaine prey, full panched to the chinne, Foming out bloud, came ramping there along, To siluer spring, her thirst to drowne therein, Whereat the fearefull maide in posting flung, (For The Mooneshine. Lucines eye bewrayde the Empresse grimme) Into a secret caue: and flying, lost A scarfe (for Pyrams sake) beloued most. When sauage Queene had wel her thirst delayde, In cooling streames, and quenched natures fire, Returning to the place where late she prayde, To eate the rest when hunger should require, In peeces tore the scarfe of haplesse maide, With bloudy teeth, and firie flaming ire, Whilst she (poore soule) in caue plaid least in sight, Fearing what should her loue befall that night. Who comming later then by vow he should, Perceiu'd a Lions footsteps in the sand, Whereat with face most pale, and heart as cold, With trembling feare tormented he doth stand. But when he sawe her scarfe (wel knowne of old) Embru'd with bloud, and cast on either hand? O what a sigh he fetcht? how deepe he gron'd? And thus, if thus: yea, thus he inly mon'd. Shalt thou alone die matelesse, Thisbe mine? Shall not one beast be butcher to vs both? What? is my Thisbe rest of life and shine? And shal not Pyram life and shining loath? Mine is the cursed soule, the blest is thine, Thou kep'st thy vow, I falsified mine oath, I came too late, thou cam'st (alas) too soone, Too dangerous standing, by a doubtfull moone. O Lions fierce (or if ought fiercer be, Amongst the heards of woody outlawes fell) Rent, rent in twaine this thrise-accursed me: From out your paunch conuey my soule to hell: Whose murdring slouth, and not the sisters three, Did Thisbe sweete, sweete Thisbe fowly quell: But cowards onely call &amp; wish for death, Whilst valiant hearts in silence banish breath. Then stooping, straight he took hir scarfe fr? ground, And bare it with him to th'appoynted place, Kissing it oft, watring each rent and wound, With thousand teares, that trailing ranne apace. Salt teares they were, sent from his eyes vnsound, Yea salter then the sweate of Oceans face: At last (hauing vnsheath'd his fatall blade) Thus gan he cry, as life beganne to fade. Hold earth, receiue a draught eke of my bloud, (And therewith lean'd vppon his sword amaine) Then falling backward from the crimsin floud, Which spowted forth with such a noyse and straine, As water doth, when pipes of lead or wood, Are goog'd with punch, or cheesill slit in twaine, Whistling in th'ayre; &amp; breaking it with blowes, Whilst heauie moysture vpward forced flowes. The Mulb'ry strait (whose fruit was erst as white As whitest Lilly in the fruitfull field) Was then and euer since in purple dight, Yea euen the roote no other staine doth yeeld, With blackish gore being watred all that night, In morneful sort, which round about it wheel'd, Onely her leaues retaind their former hue, As nothing toucht with death of louer true. No sooner was hee falne, and falling, freed Of perfit sence: but she scarce rid of feare, Returnes againe to standing fore agreed, Not dreaming that her loue in kenning were, Her feete, her eyes, her heart and tongue made speed, To vtter all things lately hapned there, And how she scap't the Lionesses clawes, By letting fall a scarfe to make her pawse. But when she vewd the newly-purpled face Of Berries white: that changing chang'd her mind, New signes perswade her, that is not the place, By either part to meete in fore assign'd. Thus doubting whilst she stood a little space, She heard a flittering carried with the winde, And viewed somewhat shake in quiu'ring wise, Which straite reuok't hir feete, but more her eies. Her lippes grew then more pale then palest Boxe, Her cheekes resembled Ashwood newly feld, Graynesse surpriz'd her yellow amber locks, Not any part their liuely lustre held: Yea euen her vent'rous heart but faintly knocks, Now vp, now downe, now falne, now vainly sweld, Tost like a shippe when One of the Northwest windes. Corus rageth most, That ankers hath, and masts and master lost. But when she knew her faithfull fellow slaine, O how she shrikt and bruz'd her guiltlesse arme, Tearing her haire, renting her cheekes in vaine, On outward parts, reuenging inward harmes, Making of teares and bloud a mingled raine, Wherwith she Pyram drencht, &amp; then thus charmes: Speake loue, O speake, how hapned this to thee? Part, halfe, yea all of this my soule and mee. Sweete loue, reply, it is thy Thisbe deare, She cries, O heare, she speakes, O answere make: Rowse vp thy sprights: those heauie lookers cheere, At which sweete name hee seemed halfe awake, And eyes with death opprest, againe to cleere. He eyes her once, and eying leaue doth take, Euen as faire Bellis The white Daisy. winkes but once for all, When winters Haruest. vsher hastneth summers fall. When afterwards she found her scarfe al rent, His iu'ory sheath voide eke of rapier gilt: And hath this hand (quoth she) thy soule hence sent? And was this bloud by this thy rapier spilt? Vnhappy I: but I no more lament, But follow thee euen to the vtmost hilt. I was the cause of al thy hurt and crosse, Hold, take me eke a partner of thy losse. Whom onely death could from me take away, Shal death him take from me against my will? Not so, his power cannot Thisbe staye: Who euen in death wil follow Pyram still, His blade (yet warme) then to her brest she laye, And falne thereon thus cri'de with crying shrill: Parents vniust which vs deny'd one bed, Enuy vs not one toomb when we be dead. And al you heau'nly hostes allot the same: And thou O tree, which couerest now but one (One too too hot, for Pyramus signifieth as much as fiery.so imports his name) But couer shalt two carcasses anone: Weare signes of bloud from both our harts that came In mourning weed our mischiefes euer mone. She dead: Tree, Sires, &amp; Gods gaue what she praide, Black growes the fruit, and they together laide. Since which time eke some other Natal. Com. lib. vlt. Mytho. Authors faine, Their humming soules about these haplesse trees, To be transported from th'Elysian plaine, Into the snowy milke-white Butterflyes: Whose seedes when life and moouing they obtain, How e're they spare the fruit of Mulberies, Leaue yet no leaues vntorne that may be seene, Because they onely still continude greene. Yet that there might remaine some Pyramis, And euerlasting shrine of Pyrams loue, When leaues are gone, and summer waining is, The little creepers neuer cease to moue, But day and night (placing in toyle their blisse) Spinne silke this tree beneath and eke aboue: Leauing their ouall [illeg.] bottoms there behind, To shewe the state of eu'ry Louers mind. For as in forme they are not wholly round, As is the perfit figure of the skie, So perfit loue in mortals is not found, Some little warts or wants in all we spie, Nay eu'n as fine and course silke there abound, The best beneath, the worst rold vp more hie, So sometimes lust o're-lieth honest loue, Happy the hand that keepes it from aboue. Againe, as these fine troupes themselues deuoure, Spinning but silken herses for their death: VVhich done, they dye therein, (by Natures power Transform'd to flies that scarce draw one months breath) So louers sweet is mingled stil with sower, Such happe aboue proceeds or vnderneath, That still we make our loue our winding sheete, VVhilst more we loue, or hotter then is meete. Others Plin. lib. 6. cap. 17. report, there was and doth remaine A neighbour Called Seres. people to the Scythian tall, Twixt Taurus mount and Tabis fruitful plaine, Most iust of life, of fare and diet, smal, Louers of peace, haters of strife and gaine, Graye ey'd, redde cheek't, and amber-headed all, Resembling rather Gods then humane race, Such grace appeard in words, in deeds, and face. VVhose righteous life and iustice to requite, (Whether with wind or raine, no man doth know) God sent vnto them silke-wormes infinite, In Aprils wane when buds the mulb'ry slow, Which here and there in euery corner light, With sixe white feete and body like to snow: Eating each leafe of that renowned tree, The matter of these silken webbes we see. These webbs for wares they on their coast exchange: For alien none must come into the Land, T'infect their people with religions strange, And file their temples with polluted hand: Neither do they to other nations range, New fashions, rites or manners t'understand: Better they haue at home, where euery slaue Weares silks as rich as here our Princes braue. These be the tales that Poetizers sing, Of Silken-worme, and of their seed and meate: Sweete, I confesse, and drawn from VVherof only the muses drank, as Poets imagine. Helique spring, Full of delighting change, and learning greate, Yet, yet, my Muse dreames of another thing, And listeth not of fictions to entreate. Saye then (my Ioye) say then, and shortly reede, wh? silk was made, &amp; how these silkworms breed. Was it think'st thou found out by industry? Inspir'd by vision or some Angells word, When first the name of sacred Maiesty, Was giuen from heau'n to Melchisede[illeg.] Salems priest and Lord? Did not before tenne thousand Silk-worms lye, And hang on euery tree their little cord? Yes, but (like Hebrues harps on Babels plaine) Vntoucht and vse-lesse there it hang'd in vaine. Before, most men liu'd, either naked quite, Or coursly clad in some beasts skinne or bide: The best were but in linnen garments dight, Wherein themselues the greatest men did pride: Yea afterward in time of greatest light, Mat. 13. When chiefe Baptizer preach't in desart wide, Where said he, silken robes were to be sought, But in kings courts? for whome they first were wrought. Though whether worme or flye were formed first, No man so right can tel as wrong presume: Yet this I hold. Till all things were accurst, Nothing was borne it selfe for to consume. No Caterpillers then which venture durst, To rauish leaues, or tender buddes to plume: For onely life and beauty liu'd in trees, Til falling man caus'd them their leaues to leese. The earthly heards and winged posts of skye, And eu'ry thing that mou'd on Eden ground, Fed first on hearbs (as Duke of Moses. Horeb hie, Author of Natures story most profound, Sets downe to vs for perfit verity, (Gaines aide of none but fooles and wittes vnsound) When for mans foode trees eke allotted were, Gen. 2. verse 29 Which from themselues, did fruit or berries beare. Durst then the finest worme but touch the meate, Or dish which for his soueraigne was ordain'd? Durst they figges, nuts, peares, plummes or mulb'ries eate Before their lord with treas? foule was stain'd? No certs no, but when ambitious heate, Reuok't the blisse which sinnelesse Sire had gain'd: Then wormes in common fed with vs, and tore Our trees, our fruits, yea eu'n our selues therefore. Say Romanes heau'nly-humane Herod. Act. 12. Orator, Whose words dropt sweeter then Hymettus dewe: Say Antiochus Epiphanes. Salems scourge and Iudaes tormentor, Whose very name doth pomp and glory shewe: Say Plato, who died eaten of lice, as Diogenes Laertius writeth. thou whose writtes men as diuine adore, Inspir'd from heau'n with knowledge giuen to few: What are you now? what liuing were you then But worms repast, though wise and mighty men? Foule-footed bird, that neuer sleepest well Nor fully, but on highest pearch do'st breathe: Whose outward shreeks bewray an inward hell, Whose glistring plumes are but a painted sheathe: Whose taile, though it with pride so lofty swel, Yet hides it not thy blacknesse vnderneath. Tell me: what hast thou got by climing thus, But to thy selfe a shame, and losse to vs? To vs alone? nay stowtest Okes likewise, Hard-harted willowes by the water side, Sweete Cedar wood which some thinke neuer dies, And The Bay. Daphnes tree though greene in winters tide, Yea stone, and steele, and things of highest prize, From natures womb that flow in greatest pride: What are they al but meate for wormes and rust? Two due reuengers of ambitious lust. Before thou wast, were Timber-worms in price, Called Cossi which being fat, were counted a most daintie dish in Rome. Cæl. Sec. lib. 28. An lect. And sold for equal weight of purest gold? Fed Tit[illeg.]nise. creeping birds one barke-deuouring lice? Were silk-worms from The first and principall place whence they were brought into Europe. Polyd. virg. lib. 11. de inuent. &amp;c. Sorinda brought and sold? Deuoured they the leaues of tree most The Mulbery is called the wisest tree, because it neuer buddeth till all danger of cold be gone. wise, With fury such as now we do behold? Rather beleeue as yet they were not borne, Or onely fed on grasse, on hearbs, or corne. For sith their chiefest vse is to arraye This little breathing dust when time requires, VVith gallant guards and broydred garments gaye, VVith scarfs, vales, hoodes, and other soft attires: VVhose sense from sense is fled so farre away? Whose mind to beare so wrong a thought conspires, As once to deeme these Silken-mercers sent, VVhen nakednesse was mans chiefe ornament? But sith they are, and therefore framed were, Which first was fram'd? the egge? the worme? or flie? No doubt the flie, as plainely shall appeare, To all that haue but an indiff'rent eye, Though twoo Euangelus in Macrobius lib. 4. sat. cap. 3. &amp; Firmius in Plutarch. lib. 2. symp quest. 3. great Clarks contrary thoughts did beare, And sentence gaue, without iust reason why, That egges were made before the hardie Cocke Beganne to tread, or brooding henne to clocke. Pretend they did, that least and simplest things, (Which none train'd vp in reasons schoole gainsay) Of things compounded are the formost springs, Eu'n as a lumpe of rude and shapelesse clay, Into the mould a Moulder cunning brings, And by degrees compels it to obey: Forming by art what he in mind fore-thought, Out of a masse that iust resembled nought. So eke though egges seeme things confused quite, And farre vnlike what afterwards they prooue: Yet formost place they challenge by their right, For who e're saw a cock or henne to mooue, Till first they came from out the yolke and white, And time, and heate, and place, and sitters loue, Had formed out a nature from the same, Deseruing wel anothers natures name? Springs not from egges that huge The VVhale Leuiathan, The Tortesse eke, and bloudy Crocodile? Fish, Lyzards, Snakes, and Locusts or grashoppers. Skippers African, VVhose hurtful armies waste the coasts of Nile? Nay if with one fitte word the world we scanne, May it obtaine a fitter name of stile, Then that we should a common egge it call, VVhich giueth life and forme and stuffe to all? Nay, did not once that cheerefull brooding sp'rite, Before the earth receiued forme or place, Gen. 1. verses. Sitte closely like a henne both warme and light, Vpon the wauing nest of mingled masse, VVhilst yet nights torches had obtain'd no light Nor Sunne as yet in circled rounds did passe? Yes, yes the words are so apparant plaine, That to deny them, were but labour vaine. These some do vse with other arguments, To proue that seede and egges were first in time. VVrested from quires of sacred Testaments, And those of heathen wittes the chiefe and prime: VVhich for authentique held by long descents, If I gainesay, perhaps may seeme a crime: Yet rather would I carry crime and scorne, Then falsely thinke, imperfect things first borne. For reason saith, and sense doth almost sweare, Natures entire to be created furst: Bodies t'haue beene before the members were, The sound before the sicke, the whole, the burst, That confidence had time when lacked feare, That blessed state fore-went the state accurst: Briefely, al bodyes that begotten beene, Were not before created bodies seene. Now what are seedes and egges of wormes or foule, But recrements of preexisting things, The bodies burden voyd of life and soule? Yea, from themselues corruption onely springs, Vnlesse by brooders heate (as from the whole) They changed be to belly, feete, or wings: Resembling them now metamorphosed, In, by, and from whose essence they were bred. Diphilus and Senecio, their arguments against Firmius and Euangeliuss, of whom at large in Macrobius and Plutarke.Yea, vsual phrase such dreames confuteth quite, For neuer man, this is an egges henne sayd, But this a hennes egge is, shewing aright, That egges are things by former natures layde, Begotte of mingled seede by day or night, Neither with skinne, nor shell, nor forme arrayd, Till long they haue abode in natures nest, And wearied womb be with their weight opprest Againe, to thinke that seede was made before, The substance whence it is ingendered, (Namely from out much nutrimental store, Thorough excesse of humours perfited) Or else to ghesse it formed was of yore, Ere pipes were laid through which it should be shed, What is it but to dreame of day or night, E're darknesse were, or any shew of light? Sith eke all winged creatures by one day, Gen. 1. verse 20 &amp; 24. Are elder then the heards that crawle and creepe, Conclude with truth and confidence wee may, All flies were made ere wormes beganne to peepe, Both they which all day long at base do play, And night once come, do nothing else but sleepe, And these which onely liue to leaue a seede, From whence the neuer-idle spinsters breede. Silke-flies I meane, which not one breast alone, But all throughout, on head, wings, sides, and feete, Besides pure white, else colour carry none, For creatures pure, a colour thought most meete, Martial'd the first of all in glorious throne, Whereon shall sit the Lord and Sauiour sweete, Who with tenne thousand Angels all in white, Shal one day iudge the world with doom vpright No spotte on them, as els on eu'ry flye, Bycause in them no follies euer grew, No crimson redde doth for reuengement crye, No wauering watchet, where al harts be true: No yellow, where there is no Iealousie: No labour lost, and therefore voide of blue: No peachy marke to signifie disdaine, No greene to shew a wanton mind and vaine. No orenge colour, where there wants despight, No tawny sadde, where none forsaken be: No murry, where they couet nought but light, No mourning black, where al reioyce with glee: In briefe, within, without, they are al white, Wearing alone the badge of chastity: Bycause they onely keepe themselues to one, Who being dead, another chuse they none. True Turtles mine, begotten with the breath, Not of a lewd lasciuious mortal Ioue: Whose lawe was lust, whose life was worse then death, VVhose incests did defile both wood and groue, But with the breath of him who vnderneath Rules Stigian king, and heau'nly hosts aboue, Assist me if I erre in setting forth Your birth dayes story; and surpassing worth. Assoone as light obtain'd a fixed seate, (which equally was first spread ouer all, Genesis 1. Giuing alike, both glistring, shine, and heate, To euery place of this inferiour ball) Two master-lamps appear'd in welkin great, Th'one king of day, whom Poets Phœbus call, And th'other Phœbe, soueraigne of the night, Twinnes at one instant bred and borne of light. Him heau'nly Martiall high, in Pallace plac't, Built all of cleere and thorough-shining gold, With columnes chrysolite most brauely grac't, And flaming rubies, glorious to behold, Wearing about his yellow-amber wast, A sloping belt, with studs twise six times told, Wherein were grau'n most artificially, Twelue stately The twelue signes in the zodiake. Peeres of curious imagery. About him, as in royall Coach hee sate, Attended Houre, Day, Minute, Month, and yeare, Spring, Summer, Haruest, Winter, Morning, Fate, With Instancie, who then was driuer there, Whipping his fiery steedes from For it was then ful harvest and not springtime, as the vulgar sort do hold. Libraes gate, Not suffring them to stand still any where, Saue once in Gibeon when fiue kings were slaine, By first-made Iosua cap. 10. Champi? with their faithles train. His sisters court built al of siluer tri'de, And Iu'ory charret set with Diamons, Embost with Orient pearles on either side, Wheeld al with Saphires, shod with Onyx stones, Declar'd in what great pompe she first did ride Amongst the other twinckling Paragons, Before her honour suffred an eclipse, Through serpents guile, and womans greedy lips. Her handmaids then were perpetuity, Constant proceeding, and continuance: No shew of change or mutability Could iustly then themselues in her aduance: Her face was ful and faire continually Not altering once her shape or countenance, Till those lights chang'd for whom al lights were made, And with whose fall the heau'ns began to fade. Yet still on her wait Oceanus is the king, &amp; his wife Thetis is counted the Queene of the seas. Ocean and his wife, Nais The Lady of the riuers. the faire, and al the watry crue, Nights, Riuers, Flouds, Springs, hauing else no strife, Then who may formost proffer seruice due: Bloud, choller, phlegme, (the rootes and sappe of life) Are at her beck, waining or springing new, According as from throne celestiall, She deignes to shine in measure great or small. When they were crowned now in royall thrones, And entred in their first and happiest race, Amongst those glistring pointed Diamons, Which cut out times proportion, lotte, and space: Behold the earth with heauy burden grones, And praies them both to eie and rue her case: And with their friendly hands and meeding art, To hasten that which ready was to part. For eu'n next morne the All-creating Sire Had sent abroad, I know not I, what word: Gen. 1. Much like to this, Let Sea and earth conspire All winged troupes the world for to afford: Wherewith the aire: euen to the desart fire, So called by Pyndarus, because nothing liues in it. Was so with great and little flyers stor'd, That none but winged people sawe the eies, Of any star or planet in the skies. O how it ioyes my hart and soule to thinke Vpon the blessed state of that same daye? When at a word, a nodde, yea at a winke, At once flew out these winged gallants gay, Tide each to each in such a friendly linke, That eu'n the least did with the greatest playe: The doue with hawks, the chickens with the kite. Fearelesse of wrong, rage, cruelty, or spite. Pert marlins then no grudge to larkes did beare, Fierce goshawkes with the Phesants had no warre, Rau'ns did not then the Eagles talens feare, Twixt Cuckoes and the Titlings was no iarre, But coasted one another eu'ry where In friendly sort, as louers woonted were: For loue alone rul'd all in eu'ry kind, As though all were of one and selfe same mind. How safely then did these my Turtle-soules Disport themselues in Phœbus cheerefull shine? How boldly flew they by the iayes and owles, Dreadlesse of crooked beakes or fiery eyen? Nay, who in all the flocks of winged foules Said once in heart, This pris'oner shal be mine? When none as yet made other warre or strife, Then such as A Poeticall God, and supposed instructor of brides and bride-groomes. Hymen makes twixt man &amp; wife. But since the fall of parents pufft with pride, Not onely men were stainde in viciousnesse, But birdes, and beasts, and wormes, and flies beside, Declining from their former perfitnesse, Did by degrees to imperfections slide, Tainted with pride, wrath, enuie, and excesse: Yea, then the husband of one onely henne, Was afterwards contented scarse with tenne. Hence, gowts in cocks, and swelling paines appeare, Hence, Partridge loynes so feeble we do view, Hence, sparrow treaders liue out scarce a yeare, Hence, leprosie the Cuckoes ouergrew: Breefely, none did in true loue perseuere: But these white Butterflies and Turtles true, Who both in life and death do ne're forsake Her, whom they once espoused for their make. They choose not (like to other birds and beasts) This yeare one wife, another wife the next, Their choyse is certaine, and still certaine rests, With former loues their mindes are not perplext, Hee yeeldes to her, she yeelds to his requests, Neither with feare nor ielosie is vext: She clippeth him, hee clippeth her againe, Equall their ioy, and equall is their paine. Remember this you fickle hearted Sires, Whom lust transporteth from your peereles Dames, To scorch your selues at foule and forraine fires, Wasting your health and wealth in filthie games, Learne hence (I say) to bridle badde desires, Quenching in time your hot and furious flames, Let little flies teach great men to be iust, And not to yeeld braue mindes a prey to lust. When thus they were created the first day, Alike in bignesse, feature, forme and age, Cladde both alike in soft and white array, And set vppon this vniuersall stage, Their seuerall parts and feates thereon to play, Amidst the rest of natures equipage: Who then suppos'd (as since some fooles haue thought) That little things were made &amp; seru'd for nought. Diswitted dolts that huge things wonder at, And to your cost coast daily ile from ile, To see a Norway whale, or Libian cat, A Carry-castle or a Crocodile, If leane Ephesian Heraclitus, that euer wept. or Democritus that euer laughed at the worlds folly. th'Abderian fat Liu'd now, and saw your madnesse but a while, What streaming flouds would gush out of theyr eies, To see great wittols little things despise? When looke, as costliest spice is in small bagges, And little springs do send foorth cleerest flouds, And sweetest Called Onis in English. Iris beareth shortest flagges, And weakest Osiers bind vp mighty woods, And greatest hearts make euer smallest bragges, And little caskets hold our richest goods: So both in Art and Nature tis most cleere, That greatest worths in smallest things appeare. What wise man euer did so much admire Neroes Made by Zenodorus: of which, and also of Theodorus image, more in Plin. lib., 4. cap. 7. &amp; 8. Colossus fiue score cubits hie, As Theodorus Image cast with fire, Holding his file in right hand hansomly, In left his paire of compasses and squire, With horses, Coach, and footmen running by So liuely made, that one might see them all? Yet was the whole worke than a flie more small. Nay, for to speake of things more late and rife, Who will not more admire those famous Fleas, Made so by art, that art imparted life, Making them skippe, and on mens hands to seaze, And let out bloud with taper-poynted knife, Which from a secret sheathe ranne out with ease: Th? those great coches which th?selues did driue, Made by Gawen Sn[illeg.] Anno. 1586. With bended serues, like things that were aliue? Ingenious Ioannes Regi montanus of whom Ramus as large in Proem. lib 2. Math. Germane, how didst thou conuey Thy Springs, thy Scrues, thy rowells, and thy flie? Thy cogs, thy wardes, thy laths, how didst thou lay? How did thy hand each peece to other tie? O that this age enioy'd thee but one day, To shew thy Fleas to faithlesse gazers eye! That great admirers might both say and see, In smallest things that greatest wonders bee. Great was that proud and feared Philistine, Whose launces shaft was like a weauers beame, VVhose helmet, target, bootes, and brigandine, VVeare weight For they weied 6000 Shekles of brasse. sufficient for a sturdy teame, VVhose frowning lookes and hart-dismaying eyne, Daunted the tallest king of Israels realme: Yet little shepheard with a pibble stone, Confounded soone that huge and mighty one. Huge fiery Dragons, Lions fierce and strong Did they such feare on cruel Pharaoh. Tyrant bring, VVith bloudy teeth or tailes and talens long, VVith gaping Iawes or double forked sting, As when the smallest creepers ganne to throng, And seize on euery quicke and liuing thing? No, no. The Egyptians neuer Yet for feare of them they honoured their Gods in the forme of cats. Plaut. lib. de Is. &amp; osi. feared mice, As then they feared little crawling lice. Did euer A most famous trumpeter. Plin. lib. cap. 56. Piseus sound his trumpet shrill So long and cleere, as doth the summer Gnat, Her little cornet which our cares doth fill, Awaking eu'n the drowziest drone thereat? Did euer thing do Cupid so much ill, As once a Anacreon in one of his latter Odes. Bee which on his hand did squat? Confesse we then in small things vertue most, Gayning in worth what they in greatnesse lost. But holla, Muse, extol not so the vale, That it contemne great hilles, and greater skie, Thinke that in goodnesse nothing can be small, For smalnesse is but an infirmitie, Natures defect, and ofspring of some fall, The scorne of men, and badge of infamy? For still had men continued tall and great, If they in goodnesse still had kept their seate. A little dismall fire whole townes hath burnd, A little winde doth spread that dismall fire, A little stone a carte hath ouerturnde, A little weede hath learned to aspire, The little Ants (in scorne so often spurnd) Haue galles: and flies haue seates of fixed ire. Small Indian gnattes haue sharpe and cruel stings, Which good to none, but hurt to many brings. And truely for my part I list not prayse These silke-worme-parents for their little sise, But for those louely great resplendant rayes, Which from their woorks and worthie actions rise, Each deede deseruing well a Crowne of bayes, Yea, to be grauen in wood that neuer dies: For let vs now recount their actions all, And truth will proue their vertues are not small. First, though fiue Males be brought to Females ten, Yet of them al they neuer chuse but fiue, Each takes and treads his first embraced henne, With her he keepes, and neuer parts aliue: And when he is enclos'd in Stygian penne, Desireth she one moment to suruiue? No, no, but strait (like a most louing bride) Flies, lies, and dies, hard by her husbands side. Anno. Dom. 1579. when I was in Italy.In Tuscane towres what armies did I view One haruest, of these faithful husbands dead? Bleede, O my heart, whilst I record anew, How wiues lay by them, beating, now their head, Sometimes their feet, and wings, &amp; breast most true, Striuing no lesse to be deliuered, Then Thisbe did from vndesired life, When she beheld her Pyram slaine with knife. But whilst they liue, what is their chiefest worke? To spinne as spiders do a fruitlesse threed? Or Adder-like in hollow caues to lurke, Till they haue got a curst and cankred seed? (Whose yong ones therfore, with dame Natures fork, Iustly gnaw out the wombs that did them breed:) Or striue they Lion-like to seize and pray, On neighbours herds or herds-men by the way? Delight they with strange Of wh? Pliny writeth, lib. II. cap. 31. Ants &amp; Griphins strong, To hoord vp gold and eu'ry gaineful thing? Liue they not beasts, and birds, and men among, Committing nought that may them damage bring? O had I that fiue-thousand-versed song, Which Thamyris, who wrote 5000. verses of the worlds creation Zetzei, 7. chilchistor. 108 Poet prowd did once with glory sing, That whilst I write of these same creatures blest, In proper words their worth might be exprest. What wil you more? they feede on nought but aire, As doth that famous bird of Paradice, They liue not long, lest goodnesse should empaire, Or rather through that Atropos. Hagges enuious eyes, That sits, and sitting, cuts in fatall chaire That threed first off, which fairest doth arise: Affording crowes and kites a longer line, Then fliers ful of gifts and grace diuine. When maker said to eu'ry bodied soule, Gen. 1. Encrease, encrease, and multiply your kinde: What he or she of al the winged foule So much fulfill'd their soueraigne-Makers minde, As these two flies? who coupled three dayes whole, Left on the fourth more seeds or egges behind Then any bird: yea then the fruiteful wrenne, Numbred by tale a Sometimes, more, seldoms fewer. hundred more then tenne. Which donne, both die, and die with cheerefull hart Bycause they had done al they bidden were, Might we from hence with conscience like depart, How deare were death? how sweet &amp; voyd of feare? How little should we at his arrowes start? If we in hands a quittance such could beare Before that iudge, who looks for better deedes, From men then flies, that spring of baser seeds. Go worthy soules (so ???? is all one name in Greeke for a soule and a butterflie. witty Greeks you name) Possesse for aye the faire Elisian greene: Sport there your selues ech Lording with his Dame, Enioy the blisse by sinners neuer seene: You liu'd in honour, and stil liue in fame, More happy there, then here is many a Queene: As for your seeds committed to my charge, Take you no care: I'le sing their worth at large. Weepe not faire The Lady of the plaine. Mira for this funeral. Weepe not Miraes daughter. Panclea, Miraes chiefe delight, Weepe not Gentlewomen attending vpon Mira and her daughter. Phileta, nor Gentlewomen attending vpon Mira and her daughter. Erato tall: Weepe not Gentlewomen attending vpon Mira and her daughter. Euphemia, nor Gentlewomen attending vpon Mira and her daughter. Felicia white: Weepe not sweete Gentlewomen attending vpon Mira and her daughter. Fausta. I assure you all, Your cattels parents are not dead outright: Keepe warme their egges, and you shall see anone, From eithers loynes a hundred rise for one, FINIS. The second booke of the Silke-Wormes and their Flies. O thou whose sweet &amp; heau'nly-tuned Psalmes The heau'ns th?selues are scarce inough to praise! Whose penne diuine and consecrated palmes, From wronging verse did Royall Singer raise, Vouchsafe from brothers ghost no niggards almes, Now to enrich my high aspiring layes, Striuing to ghesse, or rather truely reede, What shall become of all this little breede. This little breede? nay euen the least of all, The least? nay greater then the greatest are: For though in shew their substance be but small, Yet with their worth what great ones may compare? What egges as these, are so much sphericall Of all that euer winged Natures bare? A comparisen of the Silkeflies egges with other egges. As though they onely had deseru'd to haue, The selfe same forme which God to heauens gaue. From Lybian egges a mightie The Ostrich. bird doth rise, Scorning both horse and horsemen in the chace, With Roe-bucks feete, throwing in furious wise, Dust, grauell, sand and stones at hunters face, Yet dwels there not beneath the vauted skies, A greater foole of all the feathred race: For if a little bush his head doth hide, He thinkes his body cannot be espide. From egges of The Eagle. her whose mate supporteth Ioue, And dares giue combate vnto draggons great, With whom in vain huge stagges and Lions stroue, Whose onely sight makes euery bird to sweate, Whom Romanes fed in Capitole aboue, And plac't her Ensigne in the highest seate, What else springs out but bloudy birds of praye, Sleeping al night, and murdering al the daye? From egges of famous Palamedian foules, And them that hallow Diomedes toomb, In bodies strange retaining former soules, VVise, wary, warlike, saging things to come, VVhose inborne skil our want of witte controules, Whose timely fore-sight mates our heedlesse doom, Comes ought but cranes of most vnseemly shape, And diuing Cootes which muddy chanels scrape! Yea Peacocks. you vvhose egges Hortentius sometimes sold, At higher rate then now we prize your sire: Proud though he be, and spotted al with gold, Stretching abroad his spangled braue attire, VVherby, as in a glasse, you do behold, His courting loue, and longing to aspire: VVhat bring ye forth but spectacles of pride, VVhose pitchy feete marres al the rest beside? Thrise blessed egges of The Pelicane. that renowned dame, Who bleeds to death, her dead ones to reuiue, Whome enuious creepers poyson ouercame, Whilst she fetcht meate to keepe them stil aliue, How wel befits her loue that sacred Lamb, That heal'd vs all with bleeding issues fiue? Yet hath your fruit this blotte, to ouer-eate, And glutton-like to vomit vp their meate. VVinters Robbin-red-brest. Orpheus bloudy breasted VVrenne, Queen, Sommers sweete solace, nights Nightingale. Amphion braue, Linus Linnet. delight, Canaries clad in greene, All Pies, parra[illeg.], stares, &amp;c. linguists eke that beg what hart would craue, Selling your tongues for euery trifle seene, As almonds, nuttes, or what you else would haue: Ofsprings of egges, what are you but a voice? Angring sometimes your friends with too much noyse. Victorious The house-cooke. Monarch, scorning partners all, Stowt lions terrour, loue of martial Site, True farmers clocke, nights watchman, seruants call, Pressing stil forward, hating to retire, Constant in fight, impatient of thral, Bearing in a little breast a mighty fire: Oh that thou wert as faithful to thy wife, As thou art free of courage voice and life! Chaste is the Turtle, but yet giuen to hate, Storkes are officious, yet not voide of guiles, Hardy are Haggesses, but yet giuen to prate, Faithful are Doues, yet angry otherwhiles, The whitest swimmer nature e're begate, Suspition blacke and iealousie defiles: Briefely, from egges of euery creature good, Sprang nought distainted but this little broode. As for that Called by Alchimists Ouum Philosophorum, the Philosophers egge. egge conceiu'd in idle braine, Whence flowes (forsooth) that endlesse seed of gold, The wombe of wealth, the A medicine famous in Homer to extinguish all kinde of griefes and paines. Nepenthes of paine, The horne of health, and what we dearest hold: I count it but a tale and fable vaine, By some olde wife, or cousning friar told: Supposed true, though time and truth descries, That all such workes are but the workes of lies. For when the Sire of truth hath truly saide, That none can make the couering of his head, These slender haires, so vile, so soone decaide, Of so smal worth though nere so finely spread Shal any witte by humane art and aide, Transforme base mettals to that essence redde, Which buies, not only pearles and precious stones, But kingd?s, states, &amp; Monarchs fr? their thrones? Ah! heau'ns forbid (nay heau'ns forbid it sure,) That euer Art should more then Nature breede, Curse we his worke whose fingers most impure, Durst but to dare the drawing of that seede, Yet when they haue done al they can procure, And giuen their leaden God a golden weede: Zeuxis his painted dogge shal barke and whine, When Ioue they turne to Sol or Luna fine. Sisyphian Sisyphus was one of king Æolus sonnes, delighted in robbing and causening of his neighbours, wherefore this punishment was enioyned him, to roule a stone continually to the top of a Pyramidall and most steepe hil, til it rested there, which was an impossible thing to performe, because he could neuer pitch it. Ouid 3. met. soules, bewitched multipliers, Surcease to pitch this neuer pitched stone, Vaunt not of Natures nest, nor Orcus fires, Hoping to hatch your addle egge thereon: Restraine in time such ouer-prowd desires, Let cre'tures leaue Creators works alone: Melt not the golden Sulphur of your hart, In following stil this fond and fruitlesse art. Record what once befel great Acols Salmoneus, another sonne to Æolus, who for counterfetting thunder, was turned (as Seruius conceiued) into a Salmon. sonne, For counterfetting onely but the sound, Of heau'nly Canoniers dreadful gunne, That shakes the beams and pillers of this round: A fiery boult from wrathfull hand did runne, Driuing false forger vnder lowest ground: Where stil he liues stil wishing to be dead, Spotted without, within al staind with redde. Remember eke the Vulture gnawing stil, That euer-dying eue-liuing Prometheus, sonne of Asia &amp; Iaphet, who enterprising (as Paracelsus doth) to make man, was tied vppon mount Caucasus in chaines, thereto be eaten euerlastingly by Vultures, and yet neuer to die. Ouid 10. Metam. wretch, VVho stealingly with an ambitious will, From Phœbus wheeles would vitall fire reach, Thinking to make by humane art and skill, His man of clay a liuing breath to fetch: Beware in time of like celestiall rods, And feare to touch the onely worke of gods. But if you still with prowd presumptuous legges, VVill needes clime vppe the fiery-spotted hil, Pilfring from Ioue his Nectar voyde of dregs, And that immortal meate Called Ambrosia. which none doth fill, If ye wil needes imbesill those faire egges, VVhich in her child-bedde did their Leda, who being gotten with childe by Iupiter in the forme of a swanne, brought forth two egges, out of the one came Castor and Clytemnestra, out of the other Pollux and Helveta. Hesiodus. mother kil, Yet say not, that for gifts and vertues rare, They do, or may, with these my egges compare. Cie, 2. de diuThese, these, are they, in dream which Romane spide Clos'd in a slender shell of brittle mould, Holding within, a white like siluer tride, VVhose inward yolke resembleth VVhence Salomon fetcht gold euerie three yeares, which wisedome would neuer haue permitted him to haue done, if he had knowne (as some imagine) how to make the Philosophers stone. Ophirs gold, From out whose centre sprang the cheefest pride, That e're Latinus, or his race did hold, Exchanging in al countries for the same, Meate, drinke, cloth, coyne, or what you else can name. Here lies the Of which Calx, water, and oyle, you may reade more than enough in Libautus: Epist. de [illeg.] Philosophorum, &amp; the troubling Turba Philosophorum, &amp; the reuerent, D Dee. in Monad. Hierogl. Calx of that renowned shel, Here flotes that water permanent and cleere, Here doth the oile of Philosophers dwell, Stil'd from the golden Fleece that hath no peere: In midst of whose vnseene and secret cell Dame Nature sittes, and euery part doth steere, Though neither opening shop to euery eie, Nor telling As one or two fooles haue done. Cæsar she can multiply. Al-working mother, Foundresse of this All, Ten-hundred-thousand-thousand-breasted nurse, Dedalian mouldresse both of great and small, As large in wealth, as liberall of purse, Still great with childe, still letting children fall, A description of Nature. Good to the good, not ill vnto the worse, VVhat made thee shew thy multiplying pride, More in these egges, then all the egges beside? VVas it, because thou takest most delight, To print the greatest worth in smallest things? That they, the least of any seede in sight, Might clothiers breed to clothe our mightiest kings? O witte diuine, O admirable spright! VVorthie the songs of him that sweetest sings: Let it suffice that I adore thy name, VVhose works I see, and know not yet the same. But damsels, ah: who rustleth in the skie? Methinks I heare Erycthean Ladyes Boreas, who by force rauished Orythyia King Erictheus daughter. Ouid 6 Metam. foe, Blustring in fury from the mountaines hie, Looke how he raiseth cloudes from dust below, Harke how for feare the trees do cracke and crie, Each bud recoyles, the seas turne too and fro: O suffer not his breath-bereauing breath, To slay your hopes with ouer-timely death. Therefore assoone as them you gathered haue, Vpon the whitest papers you can find, In Boxes cleane your egges full closely saue, From chilling blast, of deadly nipping winde, Let not that hoary Hjems or winter. slaue So much preuaile, to kill both stocke and kinde: Farre be it from a tender Damsels heart, On tendrest seedes to shew so hard a part. The seedes or egges of Silkeflies are to bee kept neither too cold, nor any thing hot.Yet keepe them not in roomes too hot and close, Lest heate by stealth encroch it selfe too soone, And inward matter ripening so dispose, That spinsters creepe ere winters course be done, Whilst woods stand bare, &amp; naked ech thing grows, And Thisbes sap for aide be inward runne: For as with cold their brooding powre is spilde, So are they then for want of herbage kilde. Th'Arch-mason of this round and glorious bal, Of creatures created Man the last, Not that he thought him therefore worst of all, (For in his soule part of himselfe he cast) But lest his wisedome might in question fall, For hauing in his house a stranger plac't, Ere eu'ry thing was made to please and feast, So great a Monarch and so braue a guest. Vnder whose feete where e're he went abrode Vesta The Earth. spread forth a carpet voide of art, Softer then silke, greener then th'Emerode, Wrought al with flowres, and eu'ry hearb apart, Ouer him hang'd where e're he made abode, An azur'd cloth of state, which ouerthwart Was biast (as it were) and richly purld, With twelue braue signes &amp; glistring stars inurld Vppon him then as vassals eu'ry day Stowt Lions waited, tameles Panthers eke, Fierce Eagles, and the wildest birds of pray, Huge whales in Seas that mighty carricks wreake, Serpents and toades: Yea each thing did obey, Fearing his lawes and statutes once to breake: Yet wherto seru'd this pompe and honour great, If man had wanted due and dayly meate? The seedes or egs of Silkeflies are not to be hatched till the Mulberie tree be budded.Trace you Gods steppes, and til you can attaine Wherwith to feed your guests when first they shew, Haste not their hatching, for t'wil prooue a paine, Filling your hearts with ruth, your eyes with dew, As when th'vntimely lambe on Sarums plaine, Fallne too too soone from winter-starued ewe, To pine you see for want of liquid food, Which should restore his wants of vitall blood. Attend therefore, when farmers The Mullery ioy renues Her liuely face, and buddeth all in greene, For Hyems then, with all his frozen crues, Is fully dead, or fled to earths vnseene, Corne, cattell, flowers, feare then no heauie newes, From Northern coasts, or Boreas region keene: Birds sing, flies buzze, bees hum, yea al things skip To see the very blush of Morus lippe. Let swallowes come, let storkes be seene in skie, Let The Nightingale. Philomela sing, let The Wrenne. Progne chide, Let Larkes. Tory-tiry-leerers vpward flie, Let constant Cuckoes cooke on euery side, Let mountaine mice abroad in ouert lie, Let euery tree thrust foorth her budding pride, Yet none can truely warrant winters flight, Till she be seene with gemmes and iewels dight. O peerelesse tree, whose wisedome is far more Then any else that springs from natures-wombe: For though Pomonaes All kinde of round fruit. daughters budde before, And forward The Almonde tree. Phillis formost euer come, And Persian Peaches: brought first out of Persia, as Columella, writeth. fruit yeeldes of her blossoms store, And Aprils signe. Taurus hotte succeedeth March his signe. Aries roome: Yet all confesse the Mulbery most wise, That neuer breedes till winter wholly dies. Such is her wit: but more her inward might, For budded newe when Phœbus first appeares, She is full leaued e're it grow to night: With wondrous crackling filling both our eares, As though one leafe did with another fight, Striuing who first shall see the heau'nly spheares, Euen as a liuely chickin breakes the shell, Or blessed Soules do scudde and flie from hell. Yet witte and strength her pittie doth exceede, For none she hurts that neere or vnder grow, No not the brire, or any little weede, That vpward shootes, or groueling creepes below, Nay more, from heauenly flames each tree is freed That nigh her dwels, when fearful lightnings glow: For vertue which, the Romanes made a law, So writeth Pliny, lib. 10. hist, nat. To punish them that should her cut or saw. Reade Pliny. lib. citato.I leaue to tell how she doth poison cure, From adders goare or gall of Lisards got, VVhat burning blaines she heales and sores impure, In palat, iawes, and al enflamed throte, VVhat canckars hard, and wolfes be at her lure, What Gangrenes stoop that make our toes to rotte: Briefly, few griefes from Panders boxe out-flew, But here they finde a medcine, old or new. Her bloud retourn'd to sweete Thisbean wine, Strengthneth the lungs and stomacke ouer-weake, Her clustred grapes do proue a dish most fine, VVhose kernels soft do stones in sunder breake: Her leaues too that conuerted are in time, Which kings themselues in highest prize do reake: Thus giues she meat, and drink, medcine, &amp; cloth, To eu'ry one that is not drownd in sloth. Bragge now no more perle-breeding Taprobane, Of Cocos thine, that So Monardes calleth it. lib. de arb. Ind. all-supplying foode, Vaunt not of Dates thou famous Leo Afer. Africane, Though sweete in taste, and swift in making bloud, Blush Syrian grapes, and plums Armenian, Ebusian figges, and fruit of Phillis good: Bad is your best compared with this tree, That most delights my little flocke and mee. But wil you know, why this they onely eate? Why leaues they onely chuse, the fruite forsake? Why they refuse al choise and sortes of meate, And hungers heate with onely one dish slake? Then list a while, you wonder-seekers great, Whilst I an answere plaine and easie make: Disdaine you not to see the mighty ods, Twixt vertuous worms and sinful humane gods. I thinke that God and nature thought it meete, The noblest wormes on noblest tree to feede: Why Silkewormes eate only Mulberie leaues. And therefore they else neuer set their feete On any tree that beareth fruit or seede: Others diuine, that they themselues did weete No other tree could yeelde their silken threede. Iudge learned wittes: But sure a cause there is, VVhy they else feede vpon no tree but this. Ne eate they all, as greedy Kafers do, But leaue the berries to their Soueraigne: Religiously forbearing once to bloe Vpon the fruit, that may their Lord maintaine. Nay, if these leaues (though nothing else doth growe In Eden rich their nature to sustaine) Had erst bin giuen for other creatures meate, They would haue chusde rather to starue then eat. VVhy Silkewormes feed only vpon one meate.In that they onely feede vppon one tree, How iustly do they keepe dame Natures lore? Who teacheth eu'n the bleare-eyde man to see, That change of meates causeth diseases store: The gods themselues (if any such there be) Haue but one Called Ambrosia. meate, one Called Nectar drinke, and neuer more, Whereby they liue in health and neuer die, For how can one against it selfe replie. Dualitie of meates was sicknesse spring, With whom addition meeting by the way, Read PlutarkBegate varietie of euery thing, Sympos, quæst. 1Who like a whore in changeable array, With painted cheekes (as did Philinus sing) And corall lippes, and breasts that naked lay, Made vs with vnitie to be at warres, And to delight in discords, change, and iarres. Wherefore assoone as they beginne to creepe, Like sable-robed Ants, farre smaller tho, Blacke at the first, like pitch of Syrian deepe, Yet made in time as white as Atlas snow, Send seruants vp to woods and mountaines steepe, When Mulb'ry leaues their maiden lippes do shew: Feede them therewith (no other soule they craue, If morne and eu'n fresh lefage they may haue.) The first three weekes the tend'rest leaues are best, The next, they craue them of a greater size, The last, the hardest ones they can disgest, As strength with age increasing doth arise: After which time all meate they do detest, So that they eat not in all aboue nine weekes. Listing vp heads, and feete, and breast to skies, Begging as t'were of God and man some shrowde, Wherein to worke and hang their golden clowde. But whilst they feede, let al their foode be drie VVhen their meate is to bee gathered. And pull'd when Phœbus face doth brightly shine, For raine, mist, dewe, and spittings of the skie, Haue beene ful of the baine of cattle mine: Stay therfore, stay, til dayes-vpholder flie, Fiue stages ful from Easterne Thetis line: That is to say, till the sunne be fiue houres high Then leaues are free from any poysned seede, Which may infect this white and tender breede. Keepe measure too, for though the best you get, In what quantitie they are to be dieted. Giue not too much nor little of the same, Satiety their stomacks wil vnwhet, Famine againe wil make them leane and lame: Lend Witte the knife to quarter out their meate, As neede requires and reason maketh clame: Lest belly break, or meagernesse ensowe, By giuing more or lesse then was their due. Varietie of meates is naught for them.Ne ch?ge their food (as some haue thought it meet) For Mulb'ries though they are of double kind, The blacker ones are yet to them most sweete, From out their leaues most pleasing sappe they find, Boreas, the Northwest windBut wh? they faile whilst Scythi? krime I doth fleete, (Turne heau'nly hosts, O turne that cruell wind) White Mulb'ry leaues, yea tender Elming bud. May for a shift be giuen in steede of foode. Their table is to be kept cleane.Sweepe eu'ry morn ere they fresh vittailes see, Their papred boord, whereon they take repast, With bundled Time, or slippes of Rosemary, Leaue nought thereon that from their bellies past, No not th'alf-eaten leaues of Thisbes tree, And when their seates perfumed thus thou hast, Remooue them back againe with care and heede, To former place wherein they erst did feede. The sleepe of Silkewormes.Oft shalt thou see them carelesse of their meate, Yea ouer-tane with deepe and heauie sleepe, Like to that strange and Epidemian sweate, When deadly slumbers did on Britons creepe: Yet feare thou not, it is but natures feate, Who nethelesse hath of peerelesse spinsters keepe, And makes them thus as dead to lie apart, That they may wake and feede with better heart. Thrise thus they sleep, and thrise they cast their skin, The latter stil farre whiter then the rest, How oft they change their skinnes. For neuer are they quiet of mind within, Til they be cleane of blacknesse dispossest, Whether because they deeme it shame and sinne To weare the marke of blackish fiend vnblest: Or that their parents wearing onely white, They therefore in that onely would be dight. As they in body and in greatnesse grow, How they are to be distributed when they grow greater. Diuide them into tribes and colonies, For though at first one table and no mo (Smal though it be) a thousand wormes suffice, Yet afterwards (as proofe wil truly show) When they proceede vnto a greater size, One takes the roome of tenne, and seemes to craue A greater scope and portion for to haue. The loft wherein their tables placed be, VVhat manner of roome their tables must stand in, Must neither be too full, nor voide of light, Two windowes are inough, superfluous three, Plac't in such sort that one regard the light Of Phœbus steeds vprising as we see: And from the other when it drawes to night, We may behold them tired as it were, And limping downe the westerne Hemisphere. Glasde let them be, or linnen-couerd both, To keepe out fell and blacke Ants or Emets. Monopolites, The Myrmedonian crue, who voide of sloth Do wholy bend their forces, toile, and wittes To priuate gaine, and therefore are ful wroth To see this nation any good besits: Working themselues to death both night &amp; day, Not for themselues, but others to array. The greedy imps of her that slue her sonne, Pandions Wrennes and Robins. daughter, bloudy harted Queene: The winged Sparrowes. steedes in Venus coach that runne, Inflam'd with filthy lust and fires vnseene, Pursue this flocke, and wish them al vndone, Bycause they come from parents chaste and cleane: O therefore keepe the casements close and fast, Lest quellers rage your harmelesse cattle wast. If also carelesnesse haue lest a rift, Or chincke vnstopped in thine aged wall: Where-through a noysome mist, or rayny drift, Or poysned wind may trouble spinsters small, Mixe lime and sand, deuise some present shift How to repel such cruel foe-men al: Small is the charge compared with the gaine, That shal surmount thy greatest cost and paine. If any seeme to haue an amber coate, How the sicke are known from the whole, &amp; in what sort to bee vsed. And swell therewith as much as skinne can hold, Wholy to sloth and idlenesse deuote, Tainting with lothsome gore the common fold, Of deadly sicknesse t'is a certaine note, VVhose cure, sith none haue either writte or tolde, VVisedom commands to part the dead and sicke, Lest they infect the faultlesse and the quicke. Colde sometimes kills them, sometimes ouer-heate, Raine, oyle, salt, old and wet, and musty foode, Outward causes of their sicknesse The smel of onyons, leckes, garlick, and new wheat, Shrill sounds of trumpets, drums, or cleauing woode: Yea some of them are of such weakenesse great, That whisprings soft of men or falling floud, Doth so their harts and senses ouer-wheele, That often headlong from the boord they reele. Forbeare likewise to touch them more then needes, Skarre children from them giuen to wantonnesse, Let not the fruit of these your precious seedes, Die in their hands through too much carelesnesse: VVho tosse and roule and tumble them like weedes From leafe to leafe in busie idlenesse, Now squatting them vppon the floore or ground, Now squashing out their bellies soft and round. Signes of their readinesse to worke.Thus being kept and fed nine weekes entire, Surpriz'd with age ere one would thinke them yong, With what an ardent zeale and hot desire To recompence thy trauels do they long? They neither steepe, nor meate, nor drinke require, But presse and striue, yea fiercely striue and throng, Who first may find some happy bough or broom, Whereon to spinne and leaue their amber loome. They must scoure themselues two daies before you set them to worke.Then virgins then, with vndefiled hand Seuer the greatest from the smaller crue, For al alike in age like ready stand, Now to begin their rich and oual clue, (Hauing first paid as Nature doth command, To bellies-farmer that which was his due) For nothing must remaine in body pent, Which may defile their sacred monument. So being clensde from al that is impure, Put each within a For that is the best and safest way to loose none of them. paper-coffin fine, Then shal you see what labour they endure, How farre they passe the weauers craft of line, VVhat cordage first they make and tackling sure, To ty thereto their bottom most diuine, Rounding themselues ten thousand times &amp; more, Yet spinning stil behind and eke before. None cease to worke: yea rather all contend How they work not aboue nine daies. Both night and day who shall obtaine the prize Of working much, and with most speede to end, Whilst rosie The sunne. Titan nine times doth arise From purple bedde of his most louing Aurora, the morning. friend, And eke as oft in The westerne sea. Atlas vally dies) Striuing (a strife not easie here to find) In working well, who may exceed their kind. Yea some (O wofull sight) are often found Striuing, in worke their fellowes to excell, Lifelesse in midway of their trauerst round, Nay those that longest here do work and dwell, Liue but a while, to end their threed renownd, For I haue seene, and you may see it well, After that once their bottoms are begunne, Not one suruiues to see the tenth dayes funne. Go gallant youths, and die with gallant cheere, For other bodyes shortly must you haue, Of higher sort then you enioyed here, Of worthier state, and of a shape more braue, How they are turned into flies when Dogge daies end, or thereabouts. Lie but three weekes within your silken beere, Till Syrian dogge be drownd in westerne waue, And in a moment then mongst flying things, Receiue not feete alone, but also wings. A description of the Silk-flies.Wings whiter then the snow of An exceeding high hil in Asia Taurus hie, Feete fairer then Venus Paramour, sonne to Cinara, king of Cyprus, by his owne daughter Myrrha. Adonis euer had, Heads, bodies, breasts, and necks of Iuory, With perfit fauour, and like beautie clad, Which to commend with some varietie, And shadow as it were with colour sad, Two little duskie feathers shall arise From forehead white, to grace your Eben eyes. VVhen the silke is to be winded from the bottomThen neither shall you see the bottome moue, Nor any noyse perceiue with quickest eare, Death rules in all, beneath, in midst, aboue, Wherefore make haste you damsels voyd of feare, Shake off delay, as ere you profit loue, In boxes straite away your bottoms beare, Freed from the coffin wherin late they wrought, To gaine the golden fleece you so much sought. In what sort the silke is to bee winded.First pull away the loose and outmost doune, As huswiues do their ends of knottie towe, That which lies vpmost is of least renowne, The finest threed is placed most below: Threed fitte for kings, vnmeete for euery clowne, On Natures quill so wound vp rowe by rowe, That if thine eye and hand the end can find, In water warme thou maist it all vnwind. Three sorts there are, distinct by colours three, How many sorts of silke there be. The purest like to Phaesusa &amp; Lampetia Phaetons sisters. Ouid 2 Metam. their resplendant haire, Who weeping brothers fal from coursers free, Their teares were turn'd to yellow amber faire. The second like Phillis, Demophoons spouse turned into an Almond tree. her whom impatiencie Made of a spouse a tree most solitary: The last more white, made by the weaker sort, Not of so great a price, nor like report. From out al three, but chiefly from the best, Are made, not onely robes for priests and kings, The vse of all sorts of silke. But also many cordial medcins blest, Curing the wounds that sullen Saturne brings, Which being drunk, how quiet is our rest? How leaps out hart? how inwardly it springs? Speake you sad spirits that did lately feele, The hart-breake crush of melancholies wheele. Nay euen the doune which lies aloft confusde, Makes Leuant stuffe for country yonkers meete, Though it of court and cittie be refusde, And is not worne in any ciuill streete, But tel me yet, how can Diogenes that dogge, who with his dirtie shooes trode downe Platoes silken Quilt (as Laertius writeth) in greater pride then Plato euer vsed it. he be excusde, VVho trampled eu'n the best with mired feete, And in a moment marr'd al that with pride, For making which, tenne thousand spinsters dide? The first made bottoms are best to be reserued for seede.Now if of these your bottoms you require, Some to reserue for future race and seede, Chuse out the eldest, for their forward fire Makes inward flye the sooner spring and breede: Whereas the latter ones haue least desire, And lesser might to perfit Venus deede: For why, their pride is dul, and spirits colde, Borne in the quarter last of The walking Moone. Iune olde. Wind none of them, which you for breede allot, In watrie bath, nor else in wine, or lye, Lest outward moisture innly being got, Surrounding, drownes the little infant-flye, And cause both strings and secundine to rotte, So that before it liues it learnes to dye: Or if you haue them drenched so for gaine, At sunne or fire to dry them take some paine. Singled, then laye them on a table neate, Couered al o're with white That is to say, white paper, for the first writing paper was the inner rinde of a certaine reede or cane, into which Phillira was transformed. Com. Mat in Mithol. Within 12 daies after the bottoms finished, the silkeflies are disclosed. Philliraes skinne, Stay then againe till Phœbus chariot great In Oceans bath hath twelue times washed bin, And you shal see an admirable feate, This form'd and yet transformed broode within: From which new shapes new bodies do arise, And tailes to heads, and worms are turn'd to flies. Whereat to wonder each man may be bold, When seely worms themselues new fliers made, Whilst one anothers face they do behold: Muse how, and when, &amp; where, this forme they had, How new hornes sprang fr? out their foreheads old, Whence issued wings, which do them ouer-lade: Silkeflies feede on nothing but aire. For they recording what they were of late, Dare not yet mount aboue their former state. As studying thus they stand a day or more, Offring to feede on nought but onely aire, Lothing the meate so much desir'd before, I meane the leaues of Thisbes tree most faire: Disdaining eke to taste of Nais store, A day or a little more after disclosing, they couple togither. To quench the heate that might their harts impaire: At length they know themselues to be aliue, And fal to that for which our wantons striue. Both long, and longing skud to Venus forts, How long they are coupled togither. To stirre vp seed that euer may remaine, He runnes to her, and she to him resorts, Each mutually the other entertaine, Ioynd with such lincks and glue of natures sports. That coupled stil they rest a day or twaine: Yea oftentimes thrise turnes the welkin round, Ere they are seene vnlocked and vnbound. When they die after discoupling.So hauing left what e're he could impart, Of spirits, humors, seede, and recrement, Willing yet further to haue throwne his hart Into her breast, to whom he all things ment, He formost dies and yeelds to fatal dart: Ne liues she long, but strait with sorrow spent, (Hauing first laide the egges she did conceiue) Of loue and life she shortly takes her leaue. Smal egges they be, in bignesse, colour, shape, Their egges in colour and bignesse, are likest of all things to Millet seede, wherewith Parrachitos are fed.Like to the meate of Indian Parrachite, Lesse farre in view then seed of garden rape, In number many, yet indefinite: For when the females womb begins to gape, And render what the male got ouer night, Now more, now fewer seeds drop from the same, As they were short, or longer at their game. VVhat number of egges they lay.Yet seldome are they than a hundred lesse, Sometimes two hundred from their loynes do fall, Round, smooth, hard-shell'd, and voide of brittlenes, Whited alike, and yellow yolked all, Whose vertues great no man did yet expresse, Much lesse can I whose knowledge is so smal, Though sure I am hence may we find a theame, Able to drink vp The water or riuer wheron all the Muses drinke. Aganippes streame. O keepe them then with most attentiue heede, How, the egges are to be preserued. From Boreas blast and Aeols insolence, From menstruous blasts &amp; breathing keep th? freed, Auoide likewise the mil-dewes influence, Pray heau'nly Monarch for to blesse your seede, Helping their weaknesse with his prouidence. So may your milk-white spinsters worke amaine, When Morus lippes shal bud and blush againe. And An exhortation to all Farmers and Husbandmen to plant Mulberies. thou whose trade is best and oldest too, Steward of all that euer Nature gaue, VVithout whose help what can our rulers doo, Though gods on earth appareld wondrous braue? Behold thy helping hand faire virgins wooe, Yea nature bids, and reason eake doth craue Thy cunning, now these little worms to nurse, VVhich shal in time with gold fill full thy purse. In steed of fruitles elms and sallowes gray, Of brittle Ash, and poyson-breathing vgh, Plant Mulb'ry trees nigh euery path and way, Shortly from whence more profit shal ensue, Then from Made and planted by Ægle, Arethusa, &amp; Hyperethusa, King Atlas daughter. th'Hesperian wood, or orchards gay, On euery tree where golden apples grew: For what is silke but eu'n a Quintessence, Made without hands beyond al humane sense? A commendation of this silke, with that which commeth from the Ossereans, as also with that which is made by the Indian wormes.A quintessence? nay wel it may be call'd, A deathlesse tincture, sent vs from the skies, Whose colour stands, whose glosse is ne're appalld, Whose Mulbr'y-sent and sauour neuer dies, Yea when to time all natures else be thralld, And euery thing Fate to corruption ties: This onely scornes within her lists to dwell, Bettring with age, in colour, glosse, and smel. So doth not yours (you Of these Osserians or Lords of the wood, read Bonfin. lib. 1 Decad 1. Hung. Hist. Lordings of the woode) Growing like webbs vppon the long-haird grasse, Along the Aureleanus surnamed the Liberall, liuing 274 yeares after Christ, in whose time a pound weight of silke was sold for the like wright in fine gold. Vopiseus. Osserian bancks of Scithyan floud, Which into Caspian wombe doth headlong passe. No, no: Although that silke be strong and good In outward shew, and highly prized was, When bounteous Cæsar ruled citties prime, Yet soone it fades, and yeelds to rotte in time. If Pausanias bookes. bookes be true, there is an Indian worme, As bigge as The Dorbeetle. he that robbs the Eagles nest, Shap't like The Spider. Arachne that doth tinsels forme, And nets, and lawnes, and shadowes of the best, Fed with The Reede or cane. her locks, who yeelding stands in storm, VVhen The hie oakes. woods-surue yours lye on earth opprest) From out whose belly, broke with surfetting, VVhole clews of silk scarse half concocted, spring. Yet that compar'd with this is nought so fine, Ne ought so sweetely fum'd with daintie sent, Nor of like durance, nor like powre diuine: Mirth to restore, when spirits all are spent, If it be steept in sweet Pomanaes The goddesse of apples. wine, Till colour fade, and substance do relent: Nay, nay, no silke must make that Called Confectio Alkermes a most singular Electuarie against Melancholie, if it be rightly made. Antidote, Saue onely which from spinsters mine is got. Whereof, if thou a pound in weight shalt take Vnstaind at all (as Amiens Io. Fernelius. lib. 7 qui est de composaned. floure doth write) And with the iuce of Rose and pippins make A strong infusion of some day and night, Adding some graines of muske and Ambres flake, And seething all to hony-substance right: O what a Balme is made to cheere the heart, If pearle, and gold, and spices beare a part? What neede I count how many winders liue, How many twisters eke, and weauers thriue Vppon this trade? which foode doth daily giue To such as else with famine needes must striue: What multitudes of poore doth it relieue, That otherwise could scarce be kept aliue? Say Spaniard proude, &amp; tel Italian youth, Whether I faine, or write the words of truth. Not euer were your princes clad so braue, Not euer were your wiues deckt as they be, Much lesse was silk then worne of euerie slaue, And artists, sprung from base and low degree, That Heliogabalus, for so writeth Lampridius. rioter whose belly diggd his graue, Clothd all in silke, the Romanes first did see: VVhen the seede of silke-wormes was first brought into Europe.Before whose time silke wou'n on linnen threed, Was thought braue stuffe for any Princes weed. So Po[illeg.]dor virgil writeth out of Procopius, saying that this happened 555. yeares after Christ, lib. 3 cap. 6. de ret. inuent.But afterwardes, when holy Palmers twaine From out A citie of east India. Serinda brought these worms of fame, And plauted Mulb'ry plants on hill and plaine, Wherewith to fatte and foster vppe the same: How rich waxt Italy? how braue was Spaine? In Sattin fine, how braggd each man of name? Yea, euery clowne, that euen as now, so then, Habites did scarce discerne the states of men. Vp Britaine blouds, rise hearts of English race, Why should your clothes be courser then the rest? Whose feature tall, and high aspiring face, Aime at great things, and challenge eu'n the best. Begge countrymen no more in sackcloth base, Being by me of such a trade possest: That shall enrich your selues and children more, Then ere it did Naples or Spaine before. No man so poore but he may Mulb'ries plant, How easie and chargelesse a thing it is to keep silkworms. No plant so smal but wil a silke-worme feede, No worme so little (vnlesse care do want) But from it selfe wil make a clew of threede, Ech clew weighs down, rather with more then scant, A penny weight, from out whose hidden seede, (After the winged wormes conception) What ouerplus there is in profite by keeping them. A hundred spinsters issue forth of one. Diuine we hence, or rather reckon right, What vsury and proffit doth arise, By keeping well these little creatures white, Worthy the care of euery nation wise, That in their owne or publique wealth delight. And rashly wil not things so rare despise: Yea sure, in time they wil such profit bring, As shall enrich both people, priest, and king. Concerning pleasure: who doth not admire, How great pleasure there is in keeping them, both to the eies, eares, nose, and hands. And in admiring, smiles not in his hart, To see an egge a worme, a worme a flier, Hauing first shewd her rare and peerelesse art, In making that which princes doth attire, And is the base of euery famous Mart? And then to see the flie cast so much seede, As doth, or may, an hundred spinsters breede. Againe to view vppon one birchen shredde, Some hundred Clewes to hang like clustred peares, Those greene, these pale, and others somewhat red, Some like the locks hanging downe Phœbus cares: And then, how Nature when each worme is dead, To better state in tenne dayes space it reares: Who sees all this, and tickleth not in minde? To marke the choyse and pleasures in each kinde. Eye but their egges, (as Grecians terme them well) And with a penne-knife keene diuide them quite, Behold their white, their yolke, their skin, and shel, Distinct in colour, substance, forme, and sight: And if thy bodies watchmen do not swell, And cause thee both to leape and laugh outright, Thinke God and nature hath that eye denied, By which thou shouldst fr? brutish beasts be tried. When they are worms, mark how they color ch?ge, From blacke to browne, from browne to sorrel bay, From bay to dunne, from dunne to duskie strange, Then to an yron, then to a dapple gray, And how each morne in habites new they range, Till at the length they see that happy day, When (like their Sires and heau'nly angels blest) Of pure and milk-white stoles they are possest. Lay then thine eare and listen but a while, Whilst each their foode from leafage fresh receaues, Trie if thou canst hold in an outward smile, When both thine eare and phantasie conceaues, Not worms to feed, but showrings to distil. In whispring sort vpon the tatling leaues: For such a kind of muttring haue I heard, Whilst herbage greene with vnseene teeth they teard. When afterward with needle pointed tongue, The Flies haue bor'd a passage through their clewes, Obserue their gate and steerage al along, Their salutations, couplings, and Adieus: Heare eke their hurring and their churring song, When hot Priapus loue and lust renewes, And tel me if thou heardst, or e're didst eye, Like sport amongst all winged troupes that flye. Tis likewise sport to heare how man and maide, Whilst winding, twisting, and in weauing, thay Now laugh, now chide, now scan what others saide, Now sing a Carrol, now a louers lay, Now make the trembling beames to cry for aide, On clattring treddles whilst they roughly play: Resembling in their rising and their falls, A musicke strange of new found Claricalls. The smel likewise of silken wool that's new, To heart and head what comfort doth it bring, Whilst we it wind and tooze from oual clew? Resembling much in prime of fragrant spring, When wild-rose buds in greene and pleasant hue, Perfume the ayre, and vpward sents do fling, Well pleasing sents, neither too sowre not sweete, But rightly mixt, and of a temper meete. As for the hand, looke how a louer wise Delighteth more to touch Astarte slick Then Hecuba, whose eye-browes hide her eies, Whose wrinckled lippes in kissing seeme to prick, Vpon whose palmes such warts and hurtells rise, As may in poulder grate a nutmegge thick: So ioy our hands in silke, and seeme ful loth To handle ought but silke and silken cloth. Such are the pleasures, and farre more then these, Which head, and hart, eies, eares, and nose, and hands, Take, or may take, in learning at their ease, The dieting of these my spinning bands, VVhose silken threede shal more then counterpeise, Paine, cost, and charge, what euer it vs stands, So that if gaine or pleasure can perswade, Go we, let vs learne the silken-staplers trade. But list, me thinkes I heare Amyntas sayne, That shepheards skill wil soone be quite vndone, Behold faire Phillis scuddeth from the plaine, Keeping of silke-wormes hindreth not the keeping of sheepe nor Sheepheards. Leauing her flocks at randon for to runne, Lo Lidian clothier breaks his loomes in twaine, And thousand spinsters burne their woollen spunne: Ah! cease your rage, these spinsters hurt you nought But wil encrease you more then ere you thought. For carde an ounce of silke with ten of wooll, How fine, how str?g, how strange a yarne doth rise? Make trial once, and hauing seene at ful, Your new found stuffe, chaffred at highest prize, Then blame your idle heads and senses dull, Trust not conceit, but credite most your eyes: Laughing as much, or more, th? ere you mourn'd, When feare you see to ioy and vantage turnd. Laugh now (faire Mira) with thy Virgins white, For why your egges committed to my care, Are growne so much in bignesse, worth, and sight, That Kings and Queens to keep them wil not spare, Yea Queen of Queenes, for vertue, witte, and might, Perhaps wil hatch them twixt those hillocks rare, Where al the Graces feede and Sisters nine, Who euer loue, and grace both thee and thine. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>