<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Deloney, Thomas, 1543-1600</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Deloney, Thomas, 1543-1600</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">deloney thomas 1543 1600</field>
      <field name="author_text">Deloney, Thomas, 1543-1600</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">16th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.1517.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">1588</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464084</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Queenes visiting of the Campe at Tilsburie ; with her entertainment there [by Thomas Deloney</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Queenes visiting of the Campe at Tilsburie ; with her entertainment there [by Thomas Deloney</field>
      <field name="title_facet">queenes visiting of the campe at tilsburie</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">queenes visiting of the campe at tilsburie</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Queenes visiting of the Campe at Tilsburie ; with her entertainment there [by Thomas Deloney</field>
      <field name="year_display">1588</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1588</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1588</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464084&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464084&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Deloney, Thomas, 1543?-1600&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;deloney thomas 1543 1600&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Queenes visiting of the Campe at Tilsburie ; with her entertainment there [by Thomas Deloney&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;queenes visiting of the campe at tilsburie&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1588&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1588&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Deloney, Thomas&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1543&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1600&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Queenes visiting of the Campe at Tilsburie&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;with her entertainment there [by Thomas Deloney]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Imprinted ... by Iohn VVolfe for Edward White&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1588&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp1078&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;[1 sheet]&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Queenes visiting of the Campe at Tilsburie&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;with her entertainment there [by Thomas Deloney]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 20 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Queenes visiting of the Campe at Tilsburie with her entertainment there To the Tune of Wilsons wilde. Within the yeare of Christ our Lord a thousand and fiue hundreth full: And eightie eight by iust record the which no man may disanull. And in the thirtieth yeare remaining, of good Queene Elizabeths raigning. A mightie power there was prepared By Philip then the king of Spaine: Against the maiden Queene of England, which in peace before did raigne. Her Ryall ships to sea she sent, to garde the coast on euerie side: And seeing how her foes were bent, her realme full well she did prouide. With many thousands so prepared: as like was neuer erst declared. Of horsemen and of footemen plentie, whose good harts full well is seene: In the safegarde of their countrie, and the seruice of our Queene. In Essex faire that fertill soile, vpon the hill of Tilsbury: To giue our Spanish foes the foile. in gallant campe they now do lye. Where good orders is ordained, and true iustice eke mantained. For the punishment of persons, that are leude or badly bent. To see a sight so straunge in England, t'was our gracious Queenes intent. And on the eight of August she, from faire Saint Iames tooke her way: With many Lords of high degree, in princely robes and rich aray. And to bardge vpon the water, being King Henryes royall daughter. She did goe with trumpets sounding, and with dubbing drums apace: Along the Thames that famous riuer, for to view the campe a space. When she as farre as Grauesend came, right ouer against that prettie towne: Her royall grace with all her traine, was landed there with great renowne. The Lords and Captaines of her forces, mounted on their gallant horses. Readie stood to entertaine her, like martiall men of courage bold: Welcome to the campe dread soueraigne, thus they said both yong and old. The Bulworkes strong that stood thereby, well garded with sufficient men: Then flags were spred couragiously, their cannons were discharged then. Ech Gunner did declare his cunning, for ioy conceiued of her coming. All the way her Grace was riding, on each side stood armed men: With Muskets, Pikes, and good Calceuers, for her Graces safegarde then. The Lord generall of the field, had there his bloudie auncient borne: The Lord marshals coulors eke, was carried there all rent and torne. The which with bullets was so burned, when in Flaunders he soiourned. Thus in warlike wise they martched euen as soft as forte could fall: Because her Grace was fully minded, perfectly to view them all. Her faithfull souldiers great and small, as each one stood within his place: Upon their kneees began to fall, desiring God to saue her Grace. For ioy whereof her eyes was filled, that the water downe distilled. Lord blesse you all my friendes, she said, but doe not kneele so much to me: Then sent she warning to the rest, they should not let such reuerence be. Then casting vp her Princely eyes, vnto the hill with perfect sight: The ground all couered she espyes, with feet of armed souldiers bright. Whereat her royall hart so leaped, on her feet vpright she stepped. Tossing vp her plume of feathers, to them all as they did stand: Chearefully her body bending, wauing of her royall hand. Thus through the campe she passed quite, in manner as I haue declared: At maister Riches for that night, her graces lodging was preparde. The morrow after her abiding, on a princely paulfrey riding. To the camp she cam to dinner, with her Lordes and Ladies all: The Lord generall went to meete her, with his Guarde of yeomen tall. The Sargeant trumpet with his mace, and nyne with trumpets after him: Bare headed went before her grace, in coates of scarlet colour trim. The king of Heralds tall and comely, was the next in order duely. With the famous Armes of England, wrought with rich imbroidered gold: On finest veluet blew and crimson, that for siluer can be sold. With Maces of cleane beaten gold, the Queenes two Sargeants then did ride Most comely men for to behold, in veluet coates and chaines beside. The Lord generall then came riding, and Lord marshall hard beside him. Richly were they both atired, in princelie garments of great price: Bearing still their hats and fethers, in their handes in comely wise Then came the Queene on pranceing steede atired like an Angell bright: And eight braue footemen at her feete, whose Ierkins were most rich in sight. Her Ladies likewise of great honor, most sumpteously did waite vpon her. With pearles and diamonds braue adorned, and in costly cales of gold: Her Guarde in scarlet then rid after, with bowes and arrowes stoute and bold. The valiant Captaines of the field, meane space them selues in order set: And each of them with speare and sheelde, to ioyne in battaile did not let. With such a warlike skill extended, as the same was much commended. Such a battaile pitcht in England, many a day hath not beene seene: Thus they stood in order waiting, for the presence of our Queene. At length her grace most royally, receiued was and brought againe: Where she might see most loyally, this noble hoast and warlike traine. How they cam martching all together, like a wood in winters weather. With the strokes of drummers sounding, and with trampling horses than: The earth and aire did sound like thunder, to the eares of euerie man. The warlike Armie then stood still, and drummers left their dubbing sound: Because it was our Princes will, to ride about the Armie round. Her Ladies she did leaue behind her, and her Guarde which still did minde her. The Lord generall and Lord marshall, did conduct her to each place: The pikes, the colours, and the lances, at her approch fell downe apace. And then bespake our noble Queene, my louing friends and countriemen: I hope this day the worst is seene, that in our wars ye shall sustaine. But if our enimies doe assaile you, neuer let your stomackes faile you. For in the midst of all your troupe, we our selues will be in place: To be your ioy, your guide and comfort, euen before our enimies face. This done the souldiers all at once, a mightie shoute or crye did giue: Which forced from the Assure skyes, an Ecco loud from thence to driue. Which fild her grace with ioy and pleasure, and riding then from them by leasure. With trumpets sound most loyally, a long the Court of guarde she went: Who did conduct her Maiestie, vnto the Lord chiefe generals tent. Where she was feasted royally, with dainties of most costly price: And when that night aproched nye, her Maiestie with sage aduice. In gracious manner then returned, from the Campe where she soiourned. And when that she was safely set, within her Barge, and past away: Her farewell then the trumpets sounded, and the cannons fast did play, T. D. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>