<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Heywood, Thomas</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Heywood, Thomas</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">heywood thomas</field>
      <field name="author_text">Heywood, Thomas</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.2306.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1639</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464644</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The life and death of Queene Elizabeth</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">The life and death of Queene Elizabeth</field>
      <field name="title_facet">life and death of queene elizabeth</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">life and death of queene elizabeth</field>
      <field name="title_text">The life and death of Queene Elizabeth</field>
      <field name="year_display">1639</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1639</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1639</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464644&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464644&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Heywood, Thomas&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;heywood thomas&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The life and death of Queene Elizabeth&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;life and death of queene elizabeth&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1639&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1639&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Heywood, Thomas&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The life and death of Queene Elizabeth&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by Iohn Okes&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1639&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp1747&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;[43] p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The life and death of Queene Elizabeth&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 51 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only poem by Heywood included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">[Ayde, all you Sisters of the two fair Hil] Ayde, all you Sisters of the two fair Hil, A Phœnix worth deserves a Phœnix quil To set it forth, and every wit and sence, Of Art, or highest Natures influence, And all the Poets, that have liv'd before Or doe now live, (too many and too poore) If I had all their learnings, (much admir'd) And were I with their severall veines inspir'd, Yet all that cunning, into me compacted Were like a Play ill written, and worse Acted: All would not serve to write the life and death, Of Englands Glorious Great Elizabeth; Her Royall parentage, her birth and breeding, Her dangers and her troubles still exceeding: Her thraldome, freedome, her humility, Her patience, piety, and constancy, Her happy preservation from the hates Of home bred treacheries and forraine States: Her mind with heavenly vertues fully stor'd, Her life admir'd and lov'd, her death deplor'd; Of her most blessed and triumphant Raigne, And what a government she did maintaine, These have beene often written on, but yet, Those writers well spent industry and wit; Have all come short of the renowned Fame Of that Magnificent Illustrious Dame. Her praise is like the Ocean (unexhausted) It is a Theame twice fifty yeers hath lasted, and though it be no work for mortall men, 'Twill be the subject of each worthy Pen; Then why should my poore Muse presume to flie, To touch the hemme of such high Majesty? Ther's many reasons that my mind doth move, I serv'd her, and her memory I love. Besides, her goodnesse partly I relate, That others may her vertues imitate. Moreover this new way which I have gone, I doe imagine very few have done. I know that my presumption hath offended, And that I shall be justly reprehended: But yet I doubt not, but that some there be, That in good part will take this worke of me, Though Iustice justly every fault coverts, Yet favour will connive at small defects; Then from the Birth unto the Sepulchre Of blest Eliza, Englands brightest Star, Of her my watry Muse, with flagging Plumes A lofty pitch in lowly verse presumes; Her Parentage was Royall, she did spring From th'eight Henry, Englands puissant King. Her Mother was Anne Bollein, (beauties pearle) Daughter to Wiltshires and great Ormonds Earle, Sir Godfrey Bollein, her great Grandsire, and (When sixt King Henry rul'd this famous land) He was Lord Mayor of London, and did give One thousand pounds, the poores wants to relieve. 36. Of Henry the 6. 1457. In Henries heart Anne Bolleines love was stated, She Marchionesse of Pembrooke was created, September the 1. 1532. In Ianuary after, which wee call, Ianuary the 25. 1533. The day of the conversion of Saint Paul, This Lady wedded was to Englands King, And crowned Queene in Aprill following, Aprill the 12. Anno 1532. Which then was Easter-Eve; then Gods blest eye Of mercy saw this Kingdomes misery, And made faire Anne so fruitfull to bring forth A daughter better then the Kingdomes worth. Elizabeth was borne, O happy birth, Her Sexes Mirrour, wonder of the Earth, The seventh day of September borne was she, (One thousand and five hundred thirty three,) On Sunday, that most sacred day of Rest, With that great blessing was this Nation blest; Her birth was much remarkeable in this, 'Twas Maries birth Eve (Mother of our blisse) Lady Elizabeth borne 1534. Sept. the 7. (the Eve of the birth of the blessed Virgin Mary) it Greenwitch, and she dyed at Richmond on the Eve of the Annuntiation (or salutation) of the Virgin, March 24. 1602. And sure her death deserves commemoration, For 'twas the Eve of the Annuntiation; Ere two yeeres age she had accomplished, Her faire disastrous Mother lost her head, Her Vnkle (Bollein) the same fortune tride, An Axe his soule and body did divide. Sir George Bollein Lord Rochford the Queenes brother, and the Queene both beheaded, in May the 19. 1536. and Francis Weston, Henry Norrice, Mark Smeaton, William Briecton, all beheaded. And thus the wrath of the incensed King, Vnto Queene Anne, untimely death did bring; This Royall Babe Elizabeth thus left, Vntimely of her Mother thus bereft, The next day after faire Anne Bollein dyde, A mother in Law King Henry did provide, Iane Seymor, (vertues beautious Cabinet) Sole Sister to the Duke of Sommerset, Was Englands Queen; but er'e two yeers were past, At Hampton Court, (she childing) breath'd her last. King Henry at that time both lost, and won, (A loving Wife, and a most hopefull Sonne) King Edward the 6. borne October the 12. 1537. Young Edward born a Prince more good th? great, With love, faith, zeale, and piety repleat; Then faire Elizabeth, and her young brother Both simpathiz'd in love, did love each other; And each of them beyond their ages knew Grace and Religion, and as still they grew, They grew in favour both with God and men, Admired and extold with tongue and pen. Two men well known, for learning and good fame, (Grave Doctor Cox, and Sir John Cheeke by name) They were appointed by the King and State, Those Imps to Tutor and Initiate, And by their labours (through th'Almighties grace) Those Princes waxed learn'd in little space. To plant and water they did seldome cease, And God was pleas'd to give a blest encrease; The Princesse Mary was their Sister deare, Mary was borne at Greenwitch the 11. of February, 1516. and was 18. yeeres old at Edwards birth: Elizabeth was 3. yeers older than Edward. At Edwards birth (of age was eighteene yeare, She under other Tutors up was brought, The Romish Doctrine she too much was taught. When they were borne she was at womans stature, She was a Princesse of a gentle nature, But forced teaching her good mind did sway, Quite from Elizabeths and Edwards way. King Henry left this mortall pilgrimage, His Sonne and Heire about nine yeers of age was crown'd, and straight Elizabeth was sent From Court, to taste the Countries sweet content, There she exprest her Christian conversation, In studying forraine Languages and Tongues. In learning what to manage State belongs, She understood and spake 8. severall languages, so that no Embassador that did ever come to her Court, but she understood him, and answered him in his owne Language. In reverend reading sacred Mysteries, In viewing strange and English Histories; And like a painefull Bee she labour'd so, That honey seem'd this Land to overflow; Sixe yeers belov'd she in the Country staid, Till Royall Edward in his grave was laid. Straight was she sleighted and discountenanc'd: When Mary was unto the Crowne Advanc'd, Then Englands woe, and her's at once began, Romes tyranny the Kingdome overran. Stephen Gardner Bishop of Winchester, Cuthbert Tonstall Bishop of Durham, and Bonner Bishop of London, all releas'd from prisons. For Gardner, joy'nd with Tonstall, and with Bonner, (All three in high Ecclesiastick honour) These three the new reformed truth withstood, And made this woefull land a field of blood, A meere Acheldema, a vale of mone, More hot and fiery then the burning Zone: He that durst be a Protestant, was then Accounted worthy not to live with men; All such as would not then the Masse embrace, In England could not have a resting place, Scarce any day did passe, but that some dyde In burning flames their faiths repurifi'd. The Clergies zeale, made many thousands mourne, And many hundreds did to Ashes turne, That 'twas more safe to be a miscreant, Then be suspected for a Protestant, All that were found, were punish'd (without faile) With hanging, burning, whipping, or a Iayle. Elizabeth, in this tormenting time, Her innocence was held as bad as crime; She was expulst the Court, and sent from thence To Ashridge, where she kept close residence, And then her enemies began to show, What poysoned spleene did from their malice flow; The chiefe was Gardner, Englands Chauncellor, And Bishop of the Sea of Winchester, She was accus'd by Romish Iesuits, Base lurking Locusts, false Iscariothites, With Machivillian sleights and pollicies, With Romish undermining treacheries, With glorious guilded varnish'd Arguments, With labyrinth meandring documents, With cursed banning Bulls, and fiery threats, And all that was religious counterfeits, Elizabeth, was round about beset, Like to a Bird encompast with a net. But still th'All-seeing eye of providence, Did guide and guard her spotlesse innocence, Her foes did spare no malice, to remove Her from her Soveraigne Sister Maries love, And further still their mischiefes did extend. To bring her to an Ignominious end; She was accus'd to be of Wiats faction, To lend him money to support his action, And so with foule aspersions sought to draw, Her life within the compasse of the Law, Thus when of yeeres she scarcely was fifteene, She was accus'd for treason 'gainst the Queene, Then Sir Iohn Williams, (a good Lord of Thame.) From out the Country fetch'd this Royall Dame, Arm'd with a warrant full of feare and dread, To bring her up to Court alive or dead; According to command she up was brought, Kep't close by such as her destruction sought, Sent to the Tower, (and to encrease her cares) Inforc'd to take land at the Traytors staires, And though much sicknes then, her health had troubled By these strange usages her griefes were doubled. Yet still my Lord of Tame did doe his best, To give reliefe unto her mind opprest: And Noble Sussex Earle did venture still To shew to her his duty, and good will. These two did hazard dangers manifold, To doe her the best service that they could: For when she to the Queene a Letter writ, Vndaunted Sussex dar'd to carry it. Thus in the Tower she was close Prisoner shut, And all her trusty servants from her put. And more (to vexe her) to adde wrong to wrong, A Masse was in her Chamber said and sung: But all those tricks and practices could never Her Gracious heart from true Religion sever. King Philip, who was marryed to Queene Mary, Perceiving well how malice things did carry, God made him a most Royall Instrument For preservation of the Innocent: He for the Princesse oft did intercede, Request, seeke, sue, write, speake, intreat, and plead, And sure the Queene did beare a Christian mind, And to her Sister kindly was inclin'd, But that false tongues abus'd her Princely eares With slandrous tales, lyes, fables, doubts, and feares. The Constable o'th' Tower, (Lord Chamberlaine) Not suffred her one servant to retaine, But Common Souldiers, of meane Ranke and place, Did beare her meate, and waited on her Grace. Thus was she guarded closely with that Rout, Forbade to op'e a Cazement, or looke out. But good Lord Shandoys humbly su'de, that she Had leave to walke within the Gallery. A Warrant for her Deaths sad fixed Hower Was brought to the Lievtenant of the Tower: But Master Bridges, (who that Office beare) Mistrusted foule play, and with speedy care He hasted to the Court and Queene, to know Whether she sign'd the Warrant, yea, or no: The Queene was angry, and deny'd the same, Nor gave she order such a Writ to frame. But yet she blamed Bishop Gardner much, And others, whose malicious haste was such. Soone after from the Tower she was releast, And sent to Woodstocke, (an imprisoned Guest) Thus dayly was she travers'd to and fro, From wrong to injury, from griefe to woe. The Constables dismist from her, and than Sir Henry Benningfield, a harsher man, A man of manners and condition course, Who on her miseries had small remorse: She fear'd him, and her feares did more abound, With armed Souldiers she was guarded round. A rugged fellow was the Keeper then Of Woodstock-house, he watch'd occasion when To kill her, but his damn'd device was vaine, Th'Almighties power that mischiefe did restraine. Then Hell another cursed Plot conspir'd, Her Chamber in the Night was suddaine fir'd, And She (when sleepe possest her carefull head) Was likely to be burned in her Bed: But then, and ever, God was her defence, And guarded her untainted Innocence. Yet by this suddaine fiery accident She was strook into danger imminent, Affrighted, into grievous sicknesse fell, That in foure Moneths she scarce recover'd well. Her foes still seeking how they might destroy her, And missing still, devised to convoy her By Marriage to some Stranger, forraigne Prince, And so for ever send her packing hence. But God ordain'd her for some better end, And she a Virgins life, her dayes will spend. Soone after that, one Basset combin'd With twenty more (all Hounds of Hell by kind) To murder her, (in privy Coats all arm'd) But Heaven preserv'd her, that she was not harm'd; For by the Watch, (in darknesse of the Night) Affrighted, all the villaines tooke their flight. These dangers well escap'd and over-past, Shee was sent for unto the Court in haste, Where she (for seven dayes space) was closely pent, Lock'd in her Chamber, full of discontent: But still Lord William Howard did his best To comfort her, &amp; ease her mind opprest. Then was she brought before the Queene, who said, That she in prison had beene detain'd and stay'd On strong presumptions, that she favour'd Wiat, In troubling of the Queene and Kingdoms quiet, And that she was attainted on suspicion; Let her confesse her fault, and have remission. She humbly on her knees did thus reply, Dread Soveraigne, here before Gods Majesty And yours, who are his Substitute on Earth, I never thought on Treason since my Birth: And if by meanes I Wiat did protect By acts, or wayes direct, or indirect, Then let me be depriv'd, and quite bereaven Of your high favour, and the hope of Heaven. The Queene beleev'd her, and with griefe did seeme To hold her Loyalty in high esteeme, And told her, that her truth she did perceive, And so the Princesse humbly tooke her leave. But afterwards she did the Queene desire That she into the Countrey might retire; Which suite was granted, and now Fortunes wheele 'Gan turne, and make her Enemies to reele. King Philip won Saint Quintins Towne in France, And Englishmen lost Callais, (by mischance.) The losse of Callais pierc'd Queene Maries heart, Griefe brought her Death, who with impartial dart Inevitable strikes just and unjust, And layes all worldly honour in the dust. The Queenes decease poore England did deliver From a Quotidian Romish burning Feaver. Elizabeth, who long had beene inur'd To taste sad woe, her sorrows now were cur'd: God (in his mercy) heard this Kingdomes mone, And rais'd his humble hand-maid to her Throne. Thus was her Meeknesse and Humility Mounted unto the Seate of Soveraignty, Through Poysons, Pistols, &amp; deaths dreadful jawes, Through witnesse false, and danger of sharp Lawes, And from perfidious plots of wicked men Preserv'd, like Daniel in the Lyons Den Was blest Elizabeth, (quite lost accounted) And suddainly to Majesty was mounted: Yet was her Royall Seate, no Seate of pleasure, Her Treasury almost quite bare of Treasure. Her friends but few, and those few weake in power; Her foes were many, mighty to devoure. Three mighty Kingdoms, Scotland, France, &amp; Spain Made Warre against her, and disturb'd her Reigne. The Spanish King at Antwerp Armour stayd, For which good Queene Elizabeth had paid. The Scottish Queene did with the Daulphin wed, French Armes and Armies Scotland overspread, Assisted with the mighty Duke of Guise, (On purpose England (that way) to surprise.) And to exasperate her foes the more, The Bull of Pius Quintus' 'gan to rore; That Popish Bull did proudly curse all those Who were her friends, and sweetly blest her foes She then from Rome was excommunicate, Her Crowne and Scepter, Kingdome, and her State Given to the Scottish Queene to winne, and she Caus'd Englands Armes with Scotlands joyn'd to be. Elizabeth, with cares thus compast round, Curst by the Pope, threatned to be uncrown'd; Proclaim'd an Heretick, depriv'd of all Such meanes as man may earthly comforts call: Then she (most glorious) did victorious stand, Supported onely by th'Almighties hand. For shipping she had none, or very few, Of Ordnance she not many had to shew. Kings (e're her Reigne) hir'd Vessels for the Sea From Hamburgh, Lubeck, Dantzick, Genoa, But she a Royall Navy built in haste, Brasse and Ir'ne Gunnes she caused to be cast, Pikes, Shot, &amp; Armours were with cost out sought, And bought, and out of Germany were brought. And as base Brasse for Coyne went currant here, She 'xpulst it, and no money did appeare But Gold and Silver, all her golden Reigne. And (for her best of workes) she did ordaine That Gods pure Service might be said and sung In England, in the well-knowne English tongue. Erroneous superstition she supprest, And she was with aboundant blessings blest. She honour'd God, and God did honour her, That though her foes about her kept a stir, He still preserv'd her from the overthrow, And (in her weaknesse) he his power did show. From Scotland, that was vexed with divisions, Her force did bravely beate the French &amp; Guissians. The Scottish King was then scarce one yeare old, She did protect from perills manifold, Whereby this Land was blest with rest and peace By his just Reigne, (succeeding her decease. The seventeene Provinces (or Neatherlands) Were then afflicted with Spaines warlike Bands: They did pretend that Covenants were broke, To make them slaves unto the Spanish yoke. They cast themselves into our Queenes protection, (Who to oppressed men bore such affection) That she continuall succours still did give them, And with good men and Coine did so relieve them, That Spaines great power, whilst she did weare the crown, Could never c?quer, harrow, or beat down. By which meanes (till this day) they doe persist Spaines mighty powers and forces to resist. But if they thanklesse be to English men, 'Twere just they bore the Spanish yoake agen. To trouble England more, the Duke of Guise New Plots and Projects dayly did devise: First Arthur Poole, (from Clarence line descended) Ioyn'd with one Forteskue, Englands harm int?ded To land in Wales, and with hostility T'invade and spoyle that Principality. The Traytors were surpriz'd, and plot confest, And pardon'd, and Rebellion was supprest. Before Nine yeares she ruled had this Land, King James was giv'n us, (by th'Almighties hand. King Iames borne the 19. of June, at Edenburgh. 1566. Two mighty Earles, Northumberland combin'd With Westmerland, who madly were inclin'd To warre against their Soveraigne and to reare The Masse, which had bin banish'd hence 12. yeare. That hot Rebellion was no sooner done, But mighty warres with Scotland was begun, And thither was the Earle of Sussex sent, By whom that Kingdome was so torne and rent: Three hundred Townes and Villages were burn'd, And fifty strong wall'd Castles overturn'd. At that time Ireland stiffely did rebell, Conducted by a Traytor, Shan Oneale; The Duke De Alua, with great powers from Spain, Striv'd to molest Eliza's happy Reigne. Mendoza, Spaine, the Pope, all joyn'd in one To raise (in Ireland) new Rebellion, And still in all the troubles God hath beene Still pleas'd to guard her from malicious spleene. Prince Ericus, Sonne to the King of Swed, Su'de with our good Elizabeth to wed: Alansons Duke, Great Francis of Valois, And Brother to the French King, he made choyce Of Englands Queene, to be his wedded Pheare, But she refus'd him, with adieu Monsiere. Thomas and Edward, th'Earle of Darbies sonnes, Into most dangerous plots of mischiefe runnes, Ayded by Thomas Gerard, Rolston, Hall, But still Elizabeth was sav'd from all. 1570 Then Thomas Stukely, (by the Popes perswasion) Attempts to winne all Ireland by invasion: But Stukelyes Treasons into ayre was blowne, And he in Barbary was overthrowne With three Kings, on the Mauritanian Plaine Was Englands traytrous valiant Stukely slaine. The Pope at Rome a Colledge did ordaine Our English Fugitives to entertaine. The Duke of Guise in France the like did doe, To harbour Traytors that repair'd thereto. These Colledges were built for Schooles, to teach To lye, equivocate, and over-reach; To write seditious Pamphlets, to disgrace Their Soveraigne, to make Rimes &amp; Libells base: T'withdraw her Subjects hearts, and to alure Men to reject Gods Word, sincere and pure; To fill mens braines with whimsies and vagaries, Those were the vertues of these Seminaries. In these have Parsons, Campion, Allen, Lane, And divers English practis'd Englands bane, And still, like Arrows that were shot upright, Their plots upon the plotters heads did light. Campion was catch'd, and (in a Rope) did cleare His score, and made full satisfaction here. A Popish Pamphlet taught John Somervill And Edward Arden, Englands Queene to kill: But Somervill (selfe choak'd) in Jayle did dye, And Tyburne ended Ardens Tragedy. Thus God unto destruction brought all those That were Elizabeths and Englands foes. Thockmorton, with a venom'd Traytors minde, Seduc'd by Spaines Bernardinus Mendoza. Embassador, combin'd With Spanish powers this Kingdome to distresse, And (from the Crowne) the Queene to dispossesse. But he was taken, and his chiefest gaines Was drawne &amp; hang'd, &amp; quarter'd for his paines. One Chreighton, a Scots Jesuite, was sent By Englands foes for Englands detriment: Pursu'd at Sea, he had of Letters, some To France, to Spaine, and some to Rome. When Chreighton did perceive he ta'ne must be, He tare his Letters, because none should see Their secrets, and then cast them over-boord: But God such favour did to us affoord, That as he threw them t'ward the Ocean Maine, The wind did blow them in the ship againe. The peeces were together set, and joyn'd, Whereby Sir William Wand did quickly finde Their dangerous meaning: then the Queen &amp; State Thus warnd, were quickly arm'd against their hate. Next Parry, twice to kill the Queene assay'd, But still (by Power Divine) his hand was stayd, And from the Tower, to Westminster was brought, Drawne, hang'd, &amp; quartred, as all Traitors ought. William Parry was executed the 2. of March. 1585 Soone after that, some well-borne Gentlemen, (All fill'd with treason from Hells damned den) Fourteene in number, all conspir'd the death Of Englands gracious blest Elizabeth: They promis'd each of them his helping hand To bring this Kingdome under Spaines command: To raise sedition here, and Civill warres, And fill this Kingdome with domestick jarres. Their names were Ballard, Tichborne, Abington, Jones, Barnewell, Bellamie, Gage, Babington: Dun, Traverse, Tilney, Savage, Salisbury, Charnock, all Gentlemen, and well reputed, Untill foule Treason had their minds polluted. Neare Lincolnes Inne they all to death were put, Drawne, hang'd, and bowell'd, and in quarters cut. They suffered in Lincolnes Inne-fields the 20 and 21 of September, 1586. These dangers past, a French Embassador Entic'd one Stafford to goe murder her: But Stafford did reveale the treachery, Which then the Embassador did flat deny: But proofes apparant shew'd the matter plaine, And so the fault was hudled up againe. 1587. Soone after this, two Captaines of great fame, Call'd Yorke and Stanley, (of a noble Name) They both did from their Queenes true service fling, And fought against her for the Spanish King. Lopez, (a Doctor) borne a Portugall, In Physick great in skill, in Truth too small: He was arraign'd, found guilty, that he sought By poysons venome the Queenes death t'have wrought, For which at Tiburne he did make an end, Meete for all such as Treason doe intend, And to all Traytors God such fortune send. Roderick Lopez suffer'd the 7. of June, 1594. Anno 1588. Then came the yeare of wondrous Admiration, England was swallow'd downe in expectation By Spaines Leviathan-like, huge Armado Invincibly call'd in their Bravado. Spaine, Portugall, Castile, Sicilia, Granada, Naples, and Vallencia; Leon, and Aragon, (nine Kingdomes) all Combind to bring Elizabeth in thrall. With these the Pope and Clergie did comply, And Princes, and great Lords of Italy: Besides the Duke of Guise and Parma's power All joyn'd, our little England to devoure, One hundred thirty Ships for War compleat, That Neptune groan'd to beare a load so great, Of Ordnance neere three thousand, and beside Twelve thousand Marriners the Ships to guide, Land souldiers twenty thousand of great skill, To manage Horse, Pike, Launce, Gun, Blade, or Bill; To adde to these they had still fresh supplies, Of Frigots, Drumlers, Victlers, Barkes and Hoyes, With Carvells, Brignadines, and Pinnaces, To spoyle this land with braves and menaces. Seem'd as they floated on the raging flood, A mighty wildernesse, or swimming wood. The Prince of Parma's power to adde withall Were Ships three hundred forty great and small, But all these preparations could not meet, And joyne together with the Spanish Fleet. Our English Ships one hundred numbred were, Man'd with such men as scorn'd all slavish feare, In all 102. whereof 16. were of the Ships Royall. Who all, on Iulyes one and twentieth day, With Spaines Armado fought a mortall fray, Englands Lord Admirall, most valiantly, Bath'd his White-Lyon in a crimson dye, Lord Charles Howard Admirall his crest the White-Lyon. Of Spanish blood, such fame he gain'd that day, Which malice cannot blurre, or time decay. Spaines mighty terrour, (brave Sir Francis Drake) Did their Vice-Admirall, Don Pedro take, And th'English Navy, (after foure dayes fight) Did overthrow the great Armado quite. Some taken, and some sunk, and many burnd, That sixty of them never home return'd, And those threescore, (like Maps of desolation) Were rent and torne, almost past reparation, Thus to the world apparantly was seene, That God preserv'd this Kingdome and the Queen, Heaven arm'd her still with Noble instruments, Most valiant Captaines, for her strong defence. Such as were able both by sea and land, To lead her men to fight, and to command. Most Noble Howard, Oxford, Hawkins, Drake, Grenvill, and Essex, who made Spaine to quake: Vere, Norris, Cavendish, Northumberland, Montjoy, Gorge Willoughby, and Cumberland; With Seimour, Rawleigh, Gerard, Frobusher, With Cecill, Gilbert, Christmas, Uavasor, With Ghidley, Mansell, Mounson, Chauncelor, And Ratcliffe, Winter, Baskervill and Fenner, Brave Wingfield, Williams, Gifford, &amp; stout Bingham, Renowned Sidney, and the famous Windham; All these were brave Commanders in Queene Elizabeths Raigne. Thus was she serv'd with brave experienc'd men For War, and likewise she was blest agen With grave and honour'd Counsellors of State, That wisely could foresee, prevent, debate; And one thing more her happinesse did prove, Her Commons all were joyn'd to her in love. These former dangers past, one Edward Squire, Our good Queenes death did wickedly conspire, Squire did practise to poyson the pommel of the Queens saddle, that she by laying her hand on it, and touching any part of her face or body with the said hand or glove, might be envenomd deadly. But he was taken, and his sentence past, At Tyburne worthily he breath'd his last; And this base treason was the last of all, That were attempted for her timelesse fall, She having past a dangerous Pilgrimage, Decai'd in strength, and seventy yeeres of age, Thus was she guarded, by th'Almighties might, From treasons heere, and from all forraine spight, By uncontrolled right, she liv'd and raign'd, Faiths great def?dresse, she Christs faith maintain'd, With absolute command Imperiously. She was the glorious Star of Soveraignty, Of Principality th'Illustrious mirrour, Glory of Royall Majesty, and terrour To all her foes, joy of the Christian world, For through the Universall world was hurld (Blowne by the Trumpet of unspotted fame) The glorious life of this rare matchlesse Dame, The Diamond amongst Princes, and report And fame of her due praise was ever short: For after she had rightly gaind the Crowne, She Empresse was, and Impresse of Renowne, For state, magnificence, and piety, For beauty, wisedome, prudence, policy, For constant courage, learning, and true zeale, The glory of the whole worlds Common-weale, With justice, mercy, temperance, fortitude, And with all vertues else she was endu'd. She was a Patrone, and a Patterne too, To shew all Princes what and how to doe. She made the mighty Potent power of Spaine, To feele her force in her triumphant Raigne: She brought both Armes and Armour in request, And to th'opprest she was a friend profest. She aided Scotland with men, coyne and horse, She succour'd France, &amp; made peace, force perforce She sav'd all Belgia from the Spanish yoake, She made Romes Reliques vanish hence like smoak, Rebellion she in Ireland curb'd and tam'd, She was, and is, and shall be ever fam'd. She was a Pallas, a Minerva, and Bellona, fourty foure yeers in this land, A good age she surviv'd, and full of dayes, Encompast round with universall praise, Belov'd of God and men she did decease, And crownd in glory with eternall peace. Vpon the removing of her body to the Palace of White-Hall by Water, were written these Passionate dolefull Lines. The Queen was brought by water to White Hall, At every stroak the Oares Teares let fall; More clung about the Barge, fish under water Wept out their eyes of Pearle, and swum blind after: I thinke the Barge-men might with easier thighes Have row'd her thither in her peoples eyes. For howsoe're, thus much my thoughts have scand, Sh'ad come by Water had she come by land.</field>
   </doc>
</add>