<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Woodhouse, Peter, poet</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Woodhouse, Peter, poet</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">woodhouse peter poet</field>
      <field name="author_text">Woodhouse, Peter, poet</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.1717.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1605</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464215</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The flea ; [by Peter Woodhouse</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">The flea ; [by Peter Woodhouse</field>
      <field name="title_facet">flea</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">flea</field>
      <field name="title_text">The flea ; [by Peter Woodhouse</field>
      <field name="year_display">1605</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1605</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1605</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464215&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464215&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Woodhouse, Peter, poet&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;woodhouse peter poet&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The flea ; [by Peter Woodhouse&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;flea&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1605&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1605&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Woodhouse, Peter, poet&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The flea&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;[by Peter Woodhouse]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Iohn Smethwick [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1605&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp4392&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;[40] p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The flea&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;[by Peter Woodhouse]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 55 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Sic parua componere magnis.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">In laudem Authoris. Homer (the glory of the learned Greekes) To wright of Frogges &amp; Mice did thinke no scorne Th'admired Roman Maro also seekes With his sweet songs the little Gnat t'adorne. Great Orpheus Harpe layd by, they'l fill their cheekes As other Shepherds done with pypes of Corne: Yet can at will lay by their Oaten reedes, And sing of battailes and of knightly deedes. One tels vs of a metamorphos'd Asse, An other Folly highly doth commend; He proues nath'lesse, his wit vnchanged was, And this his time oft time could better spend. Neither of those but at his pleasure, has Matter of worth with good aduisement pend. Either of those (the wonder of his age) Vnder base subjects shadowe matter sage. Now let who list this as a toye dispise, Such worthy Patrones since thou hast in store: What though thy subject be of little price? Thy wit appeeres thereby to be the more, Then let thy Flea step forth, since Frogges and Mice And little Gnats haue led the way before. Feare not though Momus brood still carping bee, He snarl'd at Homer, let them barke at thee. R. P. Gent DEMOCRITVS his Dreame. OR, The Contention betweene the Elephant and the Flea. VVhen Titans Carre in th'Ocean was drencht &amp; Phœbus burning heat by Tethis quencht And Arcas through the skye did driue his Teame, My restlesse sprite met with this merry Dreame. Democritus (me thought) chancing to meete Weeping Heraclitus, thus did him greete. What madnes doth possesse thy better parte, That wilfully thou cat'st vp thine owne harte? Call backe thy thoughts, and veiwe this wide worldes stage, Beholde (with me) the follyes of each age. Marke for what trifling toyes, young men doe sell Their wealth and strength, Heraclite marke them well: And see againe when th'one foot's in the graue: The lesse men need, how still the more they craue. This markt, with laughter sure thy sides will burst, Or else I holde thee of the Gods accurst. Not so (quoth he) I knowe I am a man, Needes must I greiue to see mens follyes than. That man is voyde of all humanitie, Who is not toucht with others miserie. Can one be such as you your selfe professe, And see the shape of man proue reasonlesse? Can he see this, and yet his eyes be drye? He is no true Philosopher think I, Reason's the forme of man, he who wants this, May well be like a man, but no man is. Marke this with me; and then I make no dout, Thou'lt laugh no more, but weep thine eye-balles out. Th'art much deceiu'd (Democritus replyes) To think that this could make me wet mine eyes, Vnles much laughter caus'd some teares distill; Should I so farre pertake an others ill As hurt my selfe, for seeing him so doe? He playes the foole, should I be foolish too? But see how mightye men weake ones dispise, See how rich fooles contemne the poore, though wise. And see againe, how in their owne conceit, The least will not giue place vnto the great: See this and laugh; if this too little seeme, I'm sure thou'lt laugh if thou but heare my dreame. To heare of these disorders makes me weep (Quoth he) let's heare what mirth comes fr? your sleep List then: Me thought a christall streame did glide Alongst a valley, by a Forrest side: Through which an heard of Elephants did swimme, From forth the desart, to the hither brimme: Me thought it did me good (euen as I slept) To see the goodly order that they kept. The elder had a care, till all were o're To keep the weake and yongest still before; For so with lesser perill might they passe, whilst yet the quiet streame vntroubled was. And if that any danger hapt beside, For their defence they better might prouide. No sooner had the last set foot on land, But all the rest about him make a stand: When thus the big bone'd beast the rest bespake: Perceiue you not how all the Forrests shake When I doe passe along? how eu'ry tree Doe bend their tops (in dutie) vnto me? What beast in desart can with me compare: I speake not now of the sex-chaunging the Mars is said by Aristotle &amp; Pliny to be one yeere male, another femal Hare, Th'earth deluing Coney, or the subtill Fox, The nimble Ape, nor of the labo'ring Oxe, The watchfull Dog, nor of the long-lyu'd Hart: For most of these at their owne shadowes start. My awfull presence casts into a feare The glut'nous Wolfe, and the sleep-fatted Beare: The swift-foot Tyger, and th'adulterous Parde (Which yet to wrong the Lordly Lyon dar'de) Feares mine aspect: the spotted Panther too Doth stand in dread, and so all th'others doe. Why should I place vnto the Lyon giue? I knowe there is not any Beast doth liue Who dare compare with me in any thing: But all would giue their voyce I should be King. Content thee sonne (his Mother then replide) Though thy great strength can no way be denide Misgouern'd strength (ô this too well I knowe) Often procures his owners ouerthrowe. Then bragge not of thy strength, ô would t'were lesse! Thy too much strength may work thine owne distresse: Though Can and Will not be a noble thing, A Subjects can 's not gratefull to his King. Keep thee within thy bounds, and then thy might Will glad thy freinds, and will thy foes affright. Tush, tush, quoth he, leaue off your talke I pray, Ther's no Beast dares my peerles worth denay. But all this talke a little Flea did heare, Which sate close feeding vnderneath the care Of a poore Sheapheards Curre, the which for feare, Was crept into a bush and hid him there. The Swaine himselfe (when he these beasts did see) Did (for his safetye) climbe into a tree. But the bolde Flea (not any whit agast) To his proud speech, this answer made at last. How long shall vncontrouled arrogance Exalt itselfe? how long shall pride aduance, Without or checke, or curbe, his hatefull crest? Let Flyes then harbour in the Eagles nest: Let little starres compare them to the Sunne, Let all to th'first confused Chaos runne. Who euer thought such insolence to finde, In this huge lumpe of folly, this bace hinde? Thou thought'st perhaps, my vaunts now no beast heares: Yes; know that fieldes haue eyes, &amp; woods haue eares. Is there no beast who can with thee compare? Yes very many, who both can and dare. Euen I my selfe (though of a thousand least) Doe estimate my selfe a nobler beast Then thou, or any of thy lumpish race: And feare not so to tell thee to thy face. The Elephant hearing a little noyes, Said thus: my friends fr? whence proceeds this voyce? Towards the bush he casts his scornfull eyes, Where the poore Curre halfe dead for feare he spyes. Alas, why should he feare (Heraclite said) He trespast not, why should he be affraid? But (quoth the other) he releiu'd his foe, Did he not wrong him (think you) doing so? No, what he did was done against his will, The minde doth make the fact, or good or ill. I, but (quoth he) the thought we cannot see, As is the fact, so must our iudgement bee. What though the Dog had done no fault at all, Yet if the other pleasde it so to call, He durst not stand to iustifie the deed. For why? we see the slender-yeilding reed Doth stand, when as the sturdye Oake doth fall. For mightie men must not be striu'n withall, To fawne &amp; crouch, and tell a softe smooth tale Doth often speed, when force will not preuaile. This knewe the Dog who better dayes had seene, (for in his youth he had a Courtier beene) With faithfull seruice he to please did striue: But honest faith, takes not the way to thriue. But why doost weep? Heraclites then wept, Yet listning to his speech, he silence kept. I weep (quoth he) to heare, that flatterie Should often better speed then veritie. I weep to see how rich ones take delight To entertaine each plump-cheekt Parasite. All doores stand ope to euery claw-backe lout, Whilst honest truth is forc'd to stay without. How wisdome findes but slender entertaine, Whilst doltes and fooles doe licke vp all the gaine. No meruaile quoth the other so let bee Dawes best with dawes, like with their like agree, Then forward with your Dreame (Heraclite faid) You left where as the dogge was sore affraid, Then thus: forthwith out of the bush he cralles, Before the Lordly beast he prostrate falles. He humbly lickes his feete, and then him prayes To weigh with fauour his distressed case. Most mightie Lord (quoth he) I hope you see, That gainst my will this villaine dwels with me: Betwixt my teeth I soone would crush the patch, If I could finde the meanes the dwarfe to catch. But good my Lord no more of this (quoth he) (Leaning his mightye limbes against a tree) I pardon thee: but where is that bolde squire Who durst compare with me? I much desire To see that caytiffe, that presuming else: Heere am I (quoth the Flea) and shew'd him selfe. Heere am I (quoth the Flea) ready to proue What erst I said, and downe he throwes his gloue: Then trye the quarell, when and how thou dare; Thou hear'st I dare my selfe with thee compare. The Elephant (then smiling in disdaine) Said thus: know wretch, I count thy vaunts but vaine. For why? if to this strife I should agree, I should disgrace my selfe and honor thee. Alas, what glory should I thereby gaine. If thou, and all thy eluish race were slaine? But t'were a credit for thee for to dye, Slaine by so great and mightie beast as I: The nimble Flea, thus interrupts his speach, Thou striu'st in vaine my worth for to impeach: This is a cowards common vsed pretence, It stands not with mine honour: this defence, Serues for a sheild to shelter cowardise, But is derided of such as be wise. What? doe I not esteeme my life as deare As thou thine honour? nothing but pale feare Doth daunt thy courage onely fear's the let, Then th'Elephant, thou dost thy selfe forget: For (each one knowes) vnstaind nobilitie Keepes vs aliue, although our bodyes die. Doe I forget my selfe (the Flea did say) But who did then forget him selfe I pray, When this vnweildie masse of thine, did dare Vnto the Lyons grace it selfe compare? Doe I forget my selfe? I doe thee right: I offer thy huge bulke the single Fight. Thou standst vpon thine honor: I tell thee I'le prooue my selfe the nobler beast to be. Thy blood is stayn'd by this vilde traytrous act: Admit it were not, thou'lt denay the fact. I'le proue when that thou wert the best of all, Thy worth (compar'd to mine) would be but small. And let what Beasts thou wilt, iudge in this case, Till when, I will not yeild to thee an ace. Each Beast in his owne cause is partiall, And in his owne conceit, each dwarffe seemes tall. (Quoth th'Elephant) By others, let's be tride, Let others censure, this debate decide. Who feares the tryall, doth his cause mistrust; So doe not I, knowing that mine is iust. Chuse thou an arbitrator for thy part, And promise from his censure not to start. Ile doe the like: let this be done with speed. See yonder Bull which heer belowe doth feed, Shall be my days-man, if that he agree. And (quoth the Flea) yon The Eleph?t standeth in feare of y? mouse for that she will run vp his truncke &amp; throgh it into his head somtime. Mouse shall be for me. Why dost thou start? why art thou so dismaid? What (on the suddaine) makes thee so affraid? The Mouse (quoth he) shall neuer iudge my cause: He is mine enemye, wherefore the lawes Permit me from his censure to appeale, With that vile vermin I will neuer deale. Is this the beast (quoth he) vaunted euen now, Each other beast would at his presence bow? And see! a little Mouse doth make him quake: No meruaile though the very trees did shake For awfull feare, as he along did passe. Is this the beast? sure it some other was. But since the little Mouse (which I did chuse) (For that he is thy foe) thou dost refuse: I'le name an other, though I might defend Me from the Bull, because he is thy freind. Thy freind said I? you'r of one kindred all: For Wh? Pyrrhus King of Epirus warred against y? Rom?s he had Elephants in his army which the Rom?s hauing neuer seen any of th? before, termd Buls of Affrica. Plutarch in the life of Pyrrhus. Bulles of Affricke some folke did you call. I refuse none, from greatest to the least, And loe, the Wesell, that same Princely beast, Who (arm'd with Rue) aduentrously dares fight With the soule Basiliske, which killes with sight; He dares encounter that same poys'nous breath, Which vnto many mortalles causeth death. That Prince shall be my dayes-man (if he please) I choose him arbitrator for the Fleas. Imagine all agreed, the dayes-men set, Bent to decide the cause for which they met. The Elephant did first the silence breake, (For't was his lot that he the first should speake) The arbitrators had such order tane, That either should his owne cause first explaine, Without all interrupting, or impeach, If th'one then could except gainst th'others speach He briefly should declare wherein, and why: And they would giue their censure by and by. The Elephant (by lot) the first place wins, And thus with bolde erected lookes begins. My Lords (who set to arbitrate our cause) I hope you shall not need longtime to pause, To passe your censure, when both partes you heare, For I shall make it very plaine appeare, This little Skip-iack beast, his worth is small. Why grace I him so much? no beast at all. For eu'ry beast produceth his owne kinde: But Fleas to breed of sweat and dust we finde, As his beginning is obscure, and bace, So of his life is the whole course and race. Yet graunt he were a beast, graunt him so much: What judgement is so blinde to thinke him such, As that he may be likened vnto me? Whose breath oreturnes ten thousand such as he. Looke on our statures, see what oddes there is, Such difference is there 'twixt my worth and his. His person's little, little is his worth: What acte praise-worthy can such dwarffs bring forth You see my limbes are large, my ioynts are strong, Able to further right, or right my wrong: Let me speake boldely, ther's no beast in field But that (for strength) to me will easely yeild. Beholde (my Lords) this Castle-bearing backe, And thinke what strength is in this dwarfish iack. Yet durst the else prouoke me to the fight; Well might the world henceforth contemne my might If with this atomye I should contend. But too much time in that's well knowne I spend. Leauing the bodye, let's come to the minde: How many vertues therein shall you finde? My fortitude in this most plaine appeares, That man (who rule ouer all creatures beares) Haue often vs'de my seruice in the warres. Euen Kings of men, in their most bloudy iarres, One gainst an other, vs'de my help and ayde. Who euer (in their warres) the Fleas help pray'de? The Kings of wealthy Indye vs doe chuse As their chiefe champions, and our help vse In all their battailes: and in vs doth stand Their confidence, and hope of all their band. And not without great cause: for I haue beene Whereas my father fighting I haue seene, His The like was doone by the Eleph?t of K. Porus in his war against Alexander but this was after y? time of Democritus who is supposed to dreame this dream rider being downe and almost slaine, He with his trunke did set him vp againe: And forth his bleeding wounds the arrowes drewe, Did neuer Flea like haughtye courage shewe: Nay more, we fought (ô let me vaunt of this) Gainst the worlds wonder, proud Semiramis. Gainst her we fought, gainst her we did preuaile, When as the King of Ind' she durst affaile. Let my foe shewe when he wan such a field, And I the victory to him will yeild. He turnes his feeble might against his friend, And suckes their bloud who doe him harbour lend. But I conuert my force against my foes, The wakefull Dragon, and Rhenoceros Arm'd with strong scales, and with a peircing horne Vpon his wreakefull nose, who holdes in scorne But once to speake to such a wretch as thee: Yet both their forces cannot conquer mee. To proue my fortitude this shall suffice, Because I knowe (my Lords) you both are wise. Now if my dyet you will estimate, (I dout not) you will graunt me temperate: For temperance consisteth (as I thinke) Cheifly in th'vsage of our meat and drinke, And Venus sports: in these (this vertue's plaste) He's temperate, who sober is and chaste. My food is such as from the earth doth spring, I liue not by the death of any thing. I feed not (as the Flea) on others blood, But the greene grasse contents me for my food. My drinke is such as the cleere Fountaines giue, And thus doe I (not harming others) liue. As for the vsage of the acte of kinde, Not any beast more temp'rate shall you finde, We bath our selues both before coiture, As likewise when 'tis done: thus are we sure T'auoyd vncleannes; and our selues suffice To vse this whilst we liue but twise or thrice. In our liues length our temp'rature appeeres, For many of vs liue three hundreth yeeres. Whilst such as thou (the truth if you'l confesse Shorten your lines with ryot and excesse. Xenoph? Libr. 1. de Instit: Ciri.Phisitians which can botch vp your health, Like vultures (whilst you liue) pray on your wealth, As garments which are rent, botchers peece ore: Your crazie bodyes (they) with drugges restore. Thus are your liues a liuing miserie, And death's procur'd by some extremitie. But I with temperance my life prolong, And ne're (with Phisicke) doe my body wrong, My hope of health in mine owne guiding stands, I list not put my life int'others hands. O thrice vnhappy he, whose good or ill, Stands in th'aduenture of anothers skill. Now will I speake of prudence: which in deed Should haue bene spoke of first, but I'le proceed: Religion (which should be naturall As meate and drinke) as common vnto all: Though it of some slightly regarded be, Yet is esteem'd and practised by me. Of prudence this I holde the cheifest part, From seruice of the Gods no whit to start. And to be briefe, I carry such a braine, Of Letters I the knowledge can attaine. What would you more? euen this same excellence Betwixt vs two declares the difference. Heer might I speake of iustice: I wrong none, But giue that which is due to euery one. Of curtesie heere might I something say, How when I meere one straying from his way, I doe direct him how his course to bend, And him from force of hurtfull beastes defend. I could say more, but what need more be said? I onely this will adde: all beastes were made To serue the vse of man, who doth this best, In this approues him nobler then the rest. My strength auailes him much: and when I dye, I leaue my teeth which men call Iuorye. Aliue or dead the Flea doth nothing else But troubleth euery one whereas he dwels. If this be true; as I in nothing li'de, Why pause you to giue sentence on my side? Thus did the Elephant lay ope his case, And then with silence to the Flea gaue place. What (quoth Heraclite) did he gaine his suite? What said the Flea? was he not quight strucke mute? Tell me Democritus what said the else? Euen thus (quoth he) he answered for him selfe. Graue arbitrators, now your selues haue tride This beastes proud arrogance and daring pride, But heare me plead (with patience) for the Fleas, Then may you giue your censure as you please. Th'one part vnheard, who lets his verdit passe, Though he iudge right, no vpright iudge he was. I knowe you doe reserue th'one eare for me, Though not so great a beast, aswell as he. Indeed I was not hid as in a Tombe For two for so l?g time is it reported y? Elephant going with young. yeeres space within my mothers wombe. Yet lookewhat oddes is betweene slyme and dust: Such difference is twixt our beginnings iust. At first the earth did eu'ry creature breed, Yet he contemnes the earth as impure seed. Proud beast who dares our common mother call Impure and bace, th'earth's mother of vs all: But he triumphes in his vnweildye masse, Let this goe currant, it will come to passe That you (my Lords) and all beasts else saue he, Yea euen the Lyons selfe despis'd shall be. He would ore crowe me, for I am so small, Let this be suffred, hee'l out-braue you all. Vertue consists not in the quantitie, But rather is an inward qualitie. We more esteeme the little Rhemora Then the huge Whale; this little fish can stay A Ship that's vnder sayle, in her swift course: In a rough storme, gainst winde and waters force. Who makes a dout but little Philomel' The yron stomackt Estridge doth excell? And though faire Ladyes much esteeme her coate, Shee more delights them with her sugred noate. The Ceder then the Vine is much more tall, And yet the Vine is more esteem'd of all. What wants in stature (oftentimes we finde) Nature repayes it double in the minde. But with his mightye strength he doth me presse, Gainst which I set mine actiue nimblenesse. If that he fall, he cannot rise againe, But like a logge he lyes vpon the plaine. By this meanes is he made the hunters praye, When with a halfe cut tree they him betray. In that great The Bat in this fray tooke parte with beasts &amp; therfore after the victory was inio?d this punishm?t neuer to fly but by twilight. battaile and that bloudie fraye Betwixt the beasts and birds: we lost the day, Not through their str?gth (as they themselues confesse) But rather through their actiue nimbleneste. My seruice that day to you all's well knowne, And therefore need not vauntingly be showne. Then was I well esteem'd of great and least, Who then made dout if that I were a beast? I see a Soldiers seruice is forgot, In time of peace the worlde regards vs not. But to proceed; he prates of fortitude, And, that he's valiant would faine conclude. He counts strength valour, but he judgeth wrong Who faith the Oake hath valour: yet 't is strong. But he (he saith) hath many battailes fought, I, but true valour neuer danger sought. Rashnes, it selfe doth into perill thrust: That's onely valour where the quarrel's iust. But when as vnsought danger doth betide, His prowesse then true valour will not hide. For such as without all foresight are bolde Foole hardye, and not valiant we holde. Let this great warriour, I pray you shewe For what iust cause these warres he did pursue? What, is he mute? then I the cause will tell, For that his Lord to fight did him compell. He saith that man his help doth ofte times craue, It's false, he doth commaund him as his slaue. No, doe not thinke such judgements to delude, Amongst some fooles vaunt of thy seruitude. Men vse your seruice often to their cost, For one day 's wonne through you, there are three lost. Not warre alone, but other fearfull things, (And chiefly such as death ofte with it brings) Are fortitudes true objects heerin lyes His cheifest force these perrils to despise. When man with pressing nayle seekes me to kill, My guts about my heeles, I march on still. And though in this great broyle I was neere slaine, The daunger past, I boldely bite againe. Was thy Syre's valour (thinkst thou) like to this, When as thou fought gainst proud Semiramis? Hast thou no The Eleph?t being wounded, rageth against all y? come in his way, &amp; so doth more hurt on his owne party wound? may be thou wilt not start, But I fight hauing lost my hinder parte; Euen halfe my body being tane away, I flye not but dare still maintaine the fray. I dare aduenture in each dangerous place, And beard the boldest Ruffen to his face: What dare I not? I knowe that I am free, And doe enioy most perfect libertie. He brags that he is entertain'd of Kings, And so am I, but yet for diuers thinges. He as a drudge or as a sturdie slaue, My company at bed and boord they'l haue. The fayrest Ladyes that doe liue in Court, Will sometime entertaine me in such sort; As he would hang himselfe to finde the grace, But once to harbour in so sweet a place. O, this is such a sweet felicitie, That men enuying my prosperitie, Ouid.Haue wisht to be transformed into Fleas, That so they better might their fancie please. By this desire of theirs is plainly showne, They thought my state was better then their owne: And therefore men (for all thy haughty vaunts) Neuer desire to become Elephants, For if they so were chang'd, they plainly see: Their state should be made worsse, not betterd bee My shape they wish for, thereby to obtaine This libertye which else they cannot gaine. The coyest dames in Citie or in Court, Affoord the Flea free scope him selfe to sport In their softe bosomes: and without denay, At his best pleasure he may lower stray. I say no more of this least I be blam'd, But thus conclude, I am a Courtier fram'd. My face and legges, will suite a Prince his hall, For th'one I knowe is smooth, the other small. Vaunt on and spare not of thy mighty foes: I will reioyce I haue such freinds as those. Much of thy sober dyet thou doost preach The Fox hates grapes when they'r out of his reach. So needy beggers speake of pouertie, And gelded men vaunt of their chastitie. Thou neuer knewst what better dyet ment, And therefore arte with such base stuffe content Man, who deuoures both birds, and beasts, and fish, Will spare his bloud for me to be my dish. Thus I reuenge the bloud of beasts are slaine To feed his paunch; and shed his bloud againe. I thinke in this thou quit'st vs free from lust, In that thou saist we breed out of the dust. Thou tel'st vs also of thy curtesie, Are these the markes of thy nobilitie? These vertues which thou nam'dst may gentrie trye, But wherein art thou nobler yet then I? That thou canst learne to knowe a Letter? tush: I count that learning hardly worth a rush. To what good purpose canst thou this applye? But I am skilfull in Astronomye. I can foretell what weather shall ensue, And thereof before hand by signes I shewe. When I bite sore, the Plow-man knoweth plaine (Foretolde by me) he shortly shall haue raine. When he doth snort secure, I him awake, That to good thoughts himselfe he may betake. Thus doe I wisely things farre off foresee, And not such onely as before me bee. Art thou religious? I am so too, For looke what men awak't by me shall doe Is mine: mine are their vowes and prayers all; What good they then shall doe, I may mine call. And to be briefe, thus I conclude in fine: All that they thinke, or say, or doe, is mine. Thou saist thy teeth are good, they are: but when? When thou art dead: they'r neuer good till then. What good thou liuing doost, that is thine all: But good done after death, scarce ours I call. How long thou liu'st I care not, nor can tell, How long we liue it skils not, but how well, And for mans seruice I come not behinde. He proffits but the bodye, I the minde. Thus haue you heard (my Lords) both him and mee, And both of vs awaite for your decree. If that he doe except against my speech, With fauour heare mine answer I beseech. Thus did the Flea (me thought) conclude his Theame, At which I heartily laught euen in my dreame. How now Heraclites, doost not laugh yet? At what quoth he? me thinks this tale should set Teares from the hardest flint: laugh I doost aske? What, to see vice thus put on vertues maske? To heare a villaine tell so smooth a tale, And hipocrites set vp so full a saile? To see how great ones still would greater be, And none contented with their owne degree? How lightly others vertues some doe weigh, Whilst that selfe loue doth beare so great a swaye, O, when I heare that beasts vse reason, then I weep to thinke beasts liue in shape of men. But on, I pray you on, your dreame pursue, And let me knowe what verdit did ensue. Nay stay, (quoth he) you are too forward, fie: First pray you heare the Elephants replye. My Lords (quoth he) before you further goe, I pray you heare me speake a worde or two. Mine enemye thinkes with a glozing tongue And smooth filde speech, to boulster out his wrong. Thou tels how great ones doe thee entertaine, And yet euen those thy company disdaine. But doe they harbour thee, and giue thee food The more vngratefull thou to sucke their blood. This is the wicked custome of our dayes, To seeke their ruyne who first did them raise. Foule sinne hath set her markes vpon thy backe, And (like her selfe) hath cloathed thee in blacke. Doe Ladyes harbour thee? thou doost them wrong: They all would rather haue thy roome then throng Too many such intruding mates we haue, Who boast how Ladyes doe their presence craue. Thou rau'st gainst great ones, tail'st against their life, Such foule mouth'd curres are now adayes too rife. So vse base groomes seeking themselues to raise, Discredit others, others doe dispraise Wanting desert, he to your fauour flyes: But heerin (as I thinke) true bountie lyes, That you may be enforced to wrong none For that you doe entend to giue to one. For many often-times such gifts doe make, They are inforst from others for to take. The enuye of my greatnes makes him speake, He must haue vent, or his swolne heart will breake As shadowes still attend vpon the Sunne, So glory yet could neuer enuye shunne. Where as fire is, there alwayes will be smoake, Enuye will euer seeke vertue to choake. Thus haue you heard in briefe what I can say, Thus ends my speech, I for your censure stay. But then the Flea; yet heard me a fewe words (According to your order) reuerent Lords. He sayes, mongst great ones I my selfe intrude, And then doth charge me with ingratitude, O see how well his speeches doe agree: Obserue them well, you'l finde them contrary. Either their entertaine must willing be, Or from ingratitude acquit me free. Am I in debt to him who did me good? Yet to his power alwayes the same withstood? The wise oft-times reap profit from their foes, Yet who accounts them bounden vnto those? If that turne good which for my hurt was ment, Ile thanke my fortune, and not his intent. But was he willing? then I may conclude, He wrongs me much, who faith I did intrude. Fauour and force, neuer so well agree, That both at once can in one subject bee. But when he sawe his speech truth's colour lacke, He wrangles at my colour, cause tis blacke. Mislikes he blacke? heerat much meruaile I: He neuer could abide his It is written of the Elephant, that he c?not away with y? sight of white colour. contrary. He knowes not well what 't is stands in his light, He neither can away with blacke nor white. I enuye not thy greatnes, for with all, Such as thou art (I knowe) will be thy fall. Little I am, and little will I say, But heere I end, and doe your verdit pray. Heroclit said shewe what their censure was, I long to heare on which side it did passe. Then must you lose your longing (ile be plaine) Or else must stay vntill I dreame againe. I thought (to heare the verdit) to drawe neate, And so awak't, and thus my dreame you heare. What dost not laugh? thou art no man at all; Laughter to man is alway naturall, And to We read how y? Crocodile will weep by nature: the hyena will counterfet mams voyse &amp; vomit, but no creatur (saue man) can laugh by nature. man onely: if thou bee'st not such, Though thou laugh not, I will not meruaile much. No man quoth he? why, dost thou count him none Who is not toucht with each affection? Well, be it so; although I laugh not now, I could (if I see cause) as well as thou. But heere were rather greater cause to weepe, If cause of either can proceed from sleepe. For when as all these foggie fumes are spent, Which to the braine, were from the stomacke sent. Our restlesse phantasies repeat things ore, Which we imagined the day defore. For nothing comes in our intellgence, Which was not let in by the doore of sence. The seu'rall thinges which we awake recite, In dreames our fancies oftentimes vnite. As when of golde and mountaines hath bene tolde, Our dreames present vs mountaines all of golde. We talke of horses, and of flying things, And then we dreame of horses that haue wings. Tis like of beasts, and strife, hath beene thy theame, And that from thence proceedes this idle dreame. Idle doost call it? quoth Democritus) Yet rather had I thou shouldst terme it thus, Then to interpret, or to wrest it, so As curious and busie heads would doe. What by the Flea? what by the Dog was ment? What by the Elephant, was his intent? They'l ayme at this, and that perticuler, And each thing as it pleaseth them transfer. Such fooles as these would descant on my dreame, And it interpret, as it best shall seeme To their weake wit, and blunt capacitye, Censure each worde, each sentence misapplye. If I should light on such a giddie asse, I'd scorne to answer him, but let him passe. But vnto thee an answer must be sought, You say dreames doe repeat but things forethought, In such 't is true, as sleepe free scope affoord, But such as I vse sleepe, not as a Lord, Not suffring it to rule, but serue our need, And thus from this same sorte of dreames are freed. Such dreames as these on morning sleepers creep, And hap to such as glut themselues with sleep. In sleep our soules So saith Cici. in his book de senectute, alleaging it out of Xenophon de exped, Cyri vse their diuinitie, And hence we proue their immortalitie. For whilst we sleep, our bodyes are as dead, And then they stand our soules in little stead. And yet most perfect in her workes is shee, Whilst that she thus is from the body free. Her faculties now can she vse so well, That thinges to come she sometime can foretell And since she life doth to the body giue, We knowe she can without the body liue. To such as doe their soules vncombred keepe, The Gods reueale their secrets in their sleepe. Thus vnto me perhaps the Gods haue done, And therefore Ioelon (God somnus sonne) Shew'd me this vision, thereby to taske Some vice, which thus in shape of beasts did maske. The Elephant, the Flea; termes generall: So eu'ry one of either kinde we call Some kinde of faultes, and not some faultie men Are heerby noted it appeareth then. Why make you this Apologie (quoth he) I hope you take me no such foole to be Thus to coniecture; how so ere it seeme, I let it passe knowing 'twas but a dreame: The Gods haue something else to doe beside, What man? Democr, held opini? that there were many worldes, We Alexander the greate hearing of, wept, because hee had not fully conquerd one of th?. you say th'aue many worlds to guide. Thinkst thou the Gods will leaue their heavenly ioyes, And thus molest themselues with such like toyes? No, no, they are but idle fantasies, Which from thy mirth-deuoted thoughts arise. No, no, fond man, these wordes be weeping spake, This same name (man) makes me all mirth forsake. For what is man? nought else but miserye: No sooner borne, but he begins to dye. Hee's weeping borne; which proues hee's borne to weep, And all his life's or spent in woe, or sleep. Nay this his misery doth proue most plaine, That not one man could become young againe. On this condition to repeat o're, Both th'woes and pleasures which he had before. O no, there is no man so fond, but knowes That for one pleasure, he had twenty woes. Heere teares did drowne his speech (which fast did fall) Thinking to comfort him, I wak't with all. A shadowe of a shadowe thus you see, Alas what substance in it then can bee? If any thing herein amisse doe seeme: Consider 'twas a dreame, dreamt of a dreame. FINIS. [Many, many things have written] Many, many things have written, When th'ad better still haue sitten. Peraduenture so had I: Yet I knowe no reason why. It's a foolish toy I write, And in folly most delight: Then (I hope) it will please many, And not be dislikte of any, Euen from tales of Robin Hood, Wise men alway picke some good. None (I trust) offend I shall, So I take my leaue of all. Peter Woodhouse.</field>
   </doc>
</add>