<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Bowles, William Lisle, 1762-1850</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Bowles, William Lisle, 1762-1850</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">bowles william lisle 1762 1850</field>
      <field name="author_text">Bowles, William Lisle, 1762-1850</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1820's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_2.2049.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1823</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:465800</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Charity ; A Poem. By the author of "Letters on Prejudice," "Sermons on Christian responsibility," &amp;amp;c. [i.e. by W. L. Bowles</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Charity ; A Poem. By the author of "Letters on Prejudice," "Sermons on Christian responsibility," &amp;c. [i.e. by W. L. Bowles</field>
      <field name="title_facet">charity</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">charity</field>
      <field name="title_text">Charity ; A Poem. By the author of "Letters on Prejudice," "Sermons on Christian responsibility," &amp;c. [i.e. by W. L. Bowles</field>
      <field name="year_display">1823</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1823</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1823</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465800&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465800&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Bowles, William Lisle, 1762-1850&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;bowles william lisle 1762 1850&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Charity ; A Poem. By the author of "Letters on Prejudice," "Sermons on Christian responsibility," &amp;amp;c. [i.e. by W. L. Bowles&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;charity&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1823&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1823&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Bowles, William Lisle&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1762&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1850&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Charity&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Poem. By the author of "Letters on Prejudice," "Sermons on Christian responsibility," &amp;amp;c. [i.e. by W. L. Bowles]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by Richard Cruttwell&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1823&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0513&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;15 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Charity&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Poem. By the author of "Letters on Prejudice," "Sermons on Christian responsibility," &amp;amp;c. [i.e. by W. L. Bowles]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 15 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">“CHARITY NEVER FAILETH.”</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE following Lines were written under the impulse of sudden feeling, and without the most remote view to publication. If any apology be deemed necessary for their present appearance, the Writer has only to plead her desire of being useful to a cause, which she has not just now the means of assisting more effectually than by this very humble contribution.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHARITY. OH Charity! thou fairest birth Of heavenly Mercy! sent on earth To heal the wounds that sin has given, To point the Christian's path to Heaven; To mitigate affliction's smart, And to bind up the broken heart; The balm of sympathy to pour On Poverty's neglected sore; The cup of med'cine to supply To the dry lip and fainting eye; The hand of pity to extend, And to the friendless guide a friend;— The naked clothe,—the hungry feed,— And scatter the prolific seed Of moral and religious truth Upon the opening soil of youth, Unblasted yet by passion's breath; Untainted by the gale of death; Unshackled by the frost of years, Unchok'd by earthly thoughts and cares! Or in thy higher, holier aim, The sounds of Mercy to proclaim To an enslav'd, apostate world, And with the banner broad unfurl'd, That erst the Christian heroes bore To Palestina's sacred shore,— But in another spirit sent, Upon another warfare bent, With other panoply supplied; And for the military pride Of shield and helmet, lance and mail, And plumage dancing in the gale, And floating scarf, and charger proud, And doubling drum, and trumpet loud, Presenting fair the open'd page, Where, through the “everlasting age,” Inscrib'd in characters divine, The glories of the Godhead shine; And to the scope of mortal eye The brightness of his Majesty, Soften'd by Mercy's tender grace, Presents a mild and genial face, With healing wings his radiance shades, With love and peace the heart pervades, Fair in a Saviour's form appears To raise man's faith, and calm his fears; And o'er a darken'd world's distress, Shines forth the Sun of Righteousness! While harps celestial hymn the strain That floated soft o'er Judah's plain; And Angels in loud chorus sing Glory to Heaven's Eternal King, And every attribute divine In solemn eulogy combine— Justice and Mercy, Truth and Love, And peace on earth, and joy above. Meet Herald of a theme so high, And on thy glorious embassy Attended, not with vulgar state, Or pageants that on monarchs wait; But leading forth a gen'rous band, Prompt to resign, at thy command, Life's dearest pleasures, tend'rest ties, And all that common mortals prize; And, with a holy zeal inspir'd, With a sublime ambition fir'd, Ready with life itself to part, And patient bear the keenest smart Of skies inclement, toils intense, And (harder still to human sense) Firmly to brave the pang severe Of the loud scoff and bitter sneer; While in his sacred steps they tread, Who “to the smiters” bow'd his head; The thorny crown submissive wore, And sharpest taunts of malice bore, And for his foes his life-blood gave, The scorn of those he died to save! Spirit of Heavenly Love! whose voice First bade the smiling world rejoice, When in transcendent beauty form'd, And with life's genial spirit warm'd, It sprung from chaos, at the word Of Nature's universal Lord; Who, as he view'd the wondrous frame, Pronounc'd that all was good and fair, Ere pain and sorrow, guilt and shame, Had yet obtain'd an entrance there. Nor in that dark and fatal hour, When Sin and Death assum'd their pow'r, When God's fierce indignation burn'd, And songs of joy to mourning turn'd, Didst thou forsake man's wretched race, Their only hope, their only grace: Thine arm the sword of justice stay'd, Thy love the mighty ransom paid; Thy voice proclaim'd the captive free; Thy pity taught the blind to see; Thy breath the Martyr's prayer inspir'd, And through the world thy zeal untir'd, From age to age, from shore to shore, The tidings of Redemption bore. Thy hand the flag of peace unroll'd, Thy tongue the tale of mercy told; Thy strength the Missionary band, From Paul to Schwartz, led by the hand, With energy divine sustain'd, And in their Master's love constrain'd, “That which was lost to seek and save,” To snatch the victim from the grave; From clime to clime, from pole to pole, Speak pardon to the contrite soul, And turn the nations, with their word, From Satan's bondage, to the Lord! Say, “Ministering Angel!” say, When shall we hail the glorious day, When thy celestial form, display'd In native loveliness, array'd In the bright beams of heavenly truth, Perennial love, perennial youth, Shall, from behind the murky cloud That in impenetrable shroud Now veils thy beauties from our sight, Shine forth in unobstructed light; And, with the torch of conscience pure, (A guide infallible and sure,) To Mis'ry's dwelling point the way, And gild it with Compassion's ray? Single in motive, act, and plan!— The will of God, the wants of Man, The only principle to guide, The sole criterion to decide, In the discharge of that high trust, With such emphatic warning given, That if in indolence 'tis lost, It leads to forfeiture of heaven; Talents imparted to be used, And wealth bestow'd to be diffused! Hark! from the skies a voice I hear— Deep fall its accents on mine ear,— While a bright vision, part reveal'd, And part in wreathing clouds conceal'd, Breaks radiant on my wond'ring eyes, And thus in solemn tone replies:— “Not yet can mortal eye sustain The brightness of my glorious reign. Not yet can mortal virtue prove The fervour of my boundless love! Not till the Book of Life shall stand, Alike in promise and command, The guide and oracle of all Who on its glorious Author call:— Not till a spring of action pure, And principles defin'd and sure, Supply, in every doubtful choice, Their aid to Nature's feeble voice; Man's wand'ring fortitude sustain, The path of duty to maintain; And, as along this vale of tears He journeys his allotted years, Still o'er his every thought preside; In every step his progress guide; And bracing his determined soul, And pointing to his heavenly goal, Cheer his probationary way With promise of a brighter day! “Nor even then, shall human eye Sustain the dazzling brilliancy Of love unbounded, faith unmoved, And hope to certainty improved. “Longer, yet longer, must it be, Ere Virtue, from corruption free, In all her native lustre bright, Shall burst resplendent on the sight; Not till the earth's extended bound Shall echo the triumphant sound Of loud Hosannas to the name Of Him, who from the right hand came Of Heavenly Majesty, to heal The sinner's agonies; to feel For sin the sinner's curse, and save His faithful servants from the grave; Not till his kingdom shall begin, And poverty, and pain, and sin, From a regenerate world shall fly, And tears be wip'd from ev'ry eye, And perfect faith, and perfect love, Shall raise the Christian's heart above All meaner interests and cares; All earthly hopes, all earthly fears! Not till the welcome call be given To wing his joyful way for heaven; Not till the grave's dark gulf be cross'd, And Death in Victory be lost!” FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>