<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">West, Gilbert, 1703-1756</field>
      <field name="author_facet">West, Gilbert, 1703-1756</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">west gilbert 1703 1756</field>
      <field name="author_text">West, Gilbert, 1703-1756</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1740's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_2.1736.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1742</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:465604</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">French</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Institution of the Order of the Garter ; A Dramatick Poem [by Gilbert West</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Institution of the Order of the Garter ; A Dramatick Poem [by Gilbert West</field>
      <field name="title_facet">institution of the order of the garter</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">institution of the order of the garter</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Institution of the Order of the Garter ; A Dramatick Poem [by Gilbert West</field>
      <field name="year_display">1742</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1742</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1742</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465604&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465604&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;West, Gilbert, 1703-1756&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;west gilbert 1703 1756&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Institution of the Order of the Garter ; A Dramatick Poem [by Gilbert West&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;institution of the order of the garter&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1742&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1742&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;West, Gilbert&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1703&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1756&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Institution of the Order of the Garter&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Dramatick Poem [by Gilbert West]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for R. Dodsley&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1742&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp4245&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;fre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;64 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Institution of the Order of the Garter&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Dramatick Poem [by Gilbert West]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 112 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">—Lectos ex omnibus Oris Evebis; &amp; meritum, non quæ cunabula quæris, Et qualis; non unde satus: sub teste benigno Vivitur; egregios invitant præmia mores. Claud</field>
      <field name="fulltext">HONI SOIT QUI MAL Y PENSE.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">[Hither, all ye Heav'nly Pow'rs] Dramatis Personæ. Edward the Third, King of England, &amp;c. Philippa, Queen of England, &amp;c. Edward, Prince of Wales. John, The Order of the Garter was instituted on St. George's Day the 23d of April 1350. King John came into England in 1357. I have taken the Advantage of the Licence usually allowed to Poets, of departing a little from Chronology; and have postponed for a few Years the Institution of this Order, for the sake of rendering that Solemnity more August, by introducing King John of France; who, tho' a Prisoner, was treated both by Edward and his Son the Prince of Wales with all the Regard due to the Quality and Virtue of so great a Prince. To alleviate his Captivity, Edward entertained him and the other French Prisoners with Diversions of various kinds: among which a Tournament be held at Windsor on the 23d of April, to Solemnize the Feast of Saint George, the Patron of the Order of the Garter, held the chief Place; and was, as Rapin tell us, the most Sumptuous and Magnificent that had ever been seen in England. The Duke of Brabant, with several other Sovereign Princes, and an infinite Number of Knights of all Nations were present, and splendidly entertained.King of France, &amp;c. Spirits. Genius of England. Bards, Druids. Heralds, Attendants, &amp;c. SCENE, Windsor Park with a Prospect of the Castle. Flourish of aërial Musick at a distance; after which the following Verses are sung in the Air by Spirits, while the Genius of England descends. First Spirit. Hither, all ye Heav'nly Pow'rs, From your Empyreal Bow'rs; From the Fields for ever gay, From the Star-pav'd Milky Way, From the Moon's relucent Horn, From the Star that wakes the Morn; From the Bow, whose mingling Dyes Sweetly chear the frowning Skies; From the Silver Cloud, that sails Shadowy o'er the darken'd Vales; From th' Elysiums of the Sky, Spirits immortal, hither fly! CHORUS of Spirits. Fly, and thro' the limpid Air Guard in Pomp the sliding Car, Which to his Terrestrial Throne Wafts Britannia's Genius down. Second Spirit. Hither, all ye Heav'nly Pow'rs, From your Empyreal Bow'rs! Chiefly ye, whose Brows divine Crown'd with starry Circlets shine; Who in various Labours try'd, Once Britannia's Strength and Pride, Now in everlasting Rest Share the Glories of the Blest! Peers and Nobles of the Sky, Spirits immortal, hither fly! CHORUS of Spirits. Fly, and thro' the limpid Air Guard in Pomp the sliding Car, Which to his Terrestrial Throne Wafts Britannia's Genius down. Third Spirit. Hither too, ye tuneful Throng, Masters of inchanting Song, Sacred Bards! whose rapt'rous Strains, Sooth the toiling Heroe's Pains, Sooth the Patriot's generous Cares; Sweetly thro' their ravish'd Ears, Whisp'ring to th'immortal Mind, Heav'nly Visions, Hopes refin'd; Hopes of endless Peace and Fame, Safe from Envy's blasting Flame, Pure, sincere in those Abodes, Where to Throngs of list'ning Gods, Hymning Bards, to Virtue's Praise, Tune their never-dying Lays. Sweet Encomiasts of the Sky, Spirits immortal, hither fly! CHORUS of Spirits. Fly, and charm the limpid Air, While the softly-sliding Car, To his Sea-encircled Throne, Wafts Britannia's Genius down. Chorus of Bards descends, drest in long flowing Sky-colour'd Robes spangled with Stars, with Garlands of oaken Boughs upon their Heads, and golden Harps in their Hands, made like the Welsh or old British Harp. Before they appear, they sing the Chorus, and afterwards, as they descend, the following Songs; at the last Stanza of which, the Chariot of the Genius appears, and descends gradually all the while that and the grand Chorus is singing. CHORUS of Bards. Gentle Spirit, we obey; Thus along th'Ætherial Way, We attend our Monarch's Car; Thus we charm the silent Air. SONG. First Bard. 1 Ye Southern Gales, that ever fly In frolick April's vernal Train, Who, as ye skim along the Sky, Dip your light Pinions in the Main, Then shake them fraught with genial Show'rs, O'er blooming Flora's Primrose-Bow'rs: 2 Now cease a while your wanton Sport, Now drive each threat'ning Cloud away; Then to the flowry Vale resort, And hither all its Sweets convey; And ever as ye dance along, With softest Murmurs aid our Song. SONG II. Second Bard. But lo! fair Windsor's Tow'rs appear, And Hills with spreading Oaks imbrown'd! Hark! hark! the Voice of Joy I hear, Sung by a Thousand Echoes round; And now I view a glittering Train, In Triumph march o'er yonder Plain. Grand Chorus of Spirits and Bards. Hail mighty Nation! ever fam'd in War! Lo! Heav'n descends thy Festivals to share; To view those Heroes, whose immortal Praise, Celestial Bards shall sing in living Lays. At the Conclusion of this Chorus, the Genius alights from his Chariot, the Front of which resembling the Head of a Man of War, is adorned with a carved Lyon, holding before his Breast the Arms of England, as they were borne by Edward. Behind, on a rais'd Seat sits the Genius, leaning upon an Anchor of Silver, and bearing in his Right-hand the Vindicta, or Wand of Enfranchisement, and in his Left a Roll of Parchment, upon which is wrote, in large Letters of Gold, Magna Charta. On his Head is a Corona Rostrata, or Naval Crown; and his Robe, of a Sea-green Colour, is embroider'd with Cornucopiæ's and Gold Tridents. Genius. Disdain not, ye blest Denizons of Air, To breathe this grosser Atmosphere awhile, Your Service I shall need; mean time resort To yon Imperial Palace, and in Air Draw up your Squadrons in a radiant Orb, Suspended o'er those lofty Battlements, Like the bright Halo, that invests the Moon, Or Saturn's lucid Ring: Thence shed benign Your choicest Influence on the noble Train, There on this solemn Day assembled round The Throne of British Edward: I awhile Must here await th' Approach of other Spirits, Sage Druids, Britain's old Philosophers; Fetch'd by my Summons from the Western Isles, That, scatter'd o'er the rough Hibernian Flood, Seem like huge Fragments by the wild Wave torn From stormy Scotland, and the Cambrian Shore. There, from the World retir'd, in sacred Shades, Chiefly where Breint and Meinai wash'd the Oaks Of ancient Mona, their Academies And Schools of sage and moral Discipline They held; and to the neighb'ring Britons round, From their rever'd Tribunals, holy Mounts, Dispens'd at once their Oracles and Laws. 'Till fierce Paulinus, and his Roman Bands, Them and their Gods defying, drove them thence To seek for Shelter in Hibernian Shades. Yet still enamour'd of their ancient Haunts, Unseen of mortal Eyes, they hover round Their ruin'd Altars, consecrated Hills Once girt with spreading Oaks, mysterious Rows Of rude enormous Obelisks, that rise Orb within Orb, stupendous Monuments Of artless Architecture, such as now Oft times amaze the wand'ring Traveller, By the pale Moon discern'd on Sarum's Plain. But hence, Aërial Spirits: lo, they come! Here the Spirits and Bards, together with the Chariot of the Genius reascend, and at the same time the Druids enter, cloath'd in dark-colour'd coarse stuff Gowns, which before hang no lower than the Knee, but behind almost touch the Ground. The Sleeves of these Gowns reach down below the Elbow, and from behind comes up a sort of Hood or Cowle, which hangs loose about the Head and Forehead. From the left Shoulder hangs in a String a kind of Pouch or Scrip, and rests on the right Hip. In their Right-hands they hold a Staff, and in their Left an Oaken Branch. Their Beards are very large and long, reaching below their Waists. Their Legs are naked, and their Feet shod with Sandals, which are fastened by Thongs wound about the Foot and the Small of the Leg. See a Cut of the Chief Druid, in Rowland's Mona Antiqua reflaurata, taken from a Statue. Page 65. Enter DRUIDS. Chief Druid. Inform us, happy Spirit, protecting Pow'r Of this our ancient Country, wherefore now From our sequester'd Vallies, pensive Groves And dark Recesses, thou hast summon'd us To wait thy Orders on this flow'ry Hill? Genius. A great Event, sage Druids, that no less Imports than this your ancient Country's Fame, From Contemplation, and your silent Shades, Calls you to meet me on this flow'ry Hill. Know, in yon Castle, whose proud Battlements Sit like a Regal Crown upon the Brow Of this high-climbing Lawn, doth Edward hold This Day his solemn Session, to receive The Pleas of all th'aspiring Candidates, Who, summon'd by the Edward having communicated his Intention of Instituting the Order of the Garter to the great Council of his Realm, and having receiv'd their Approbation, dispatch'd his Heralds to several Parts of Europe, to invite all that were eminent for Military Virtue, &amp;c. to be present at its Institution. And his Queen Philippa, on her Part, assembled a Train of 300 of the fairest Ladies to grace the Solemnity, and add to its Magnificence.Herald's publick Voice, To Windsor, as to Fame's bright Temple, haste From every Shore; the Noble, Wise, and Brave, Knights, Senators and Statesmen, Lords and Kings: Ambitious each to gain the splendid Prize, By Edward promis'd to transcendent Worth. For who of Mortals is too Great and High In the Career of Virtue to contend? Of these, selecting the most glorious Names, Doth England's Monarch purpose to compose A Princely Brotherhood, Himself the Chief, And worthy Sovereign of th'illustrious Band; A Band of Heroes, listed in the Cause Of Honour, Virtue, and Celestial Truth, Under the Name and holy Patronage Of Cappadocian George, Britannia's Saint. Such is the Plan by gen'rous Edward form'd; A Plan of Glory, that beyond the Reach Of his own conqu'ring Arms, shall propagate The Sovereignty of Britain, and erect Her Monarchs into Judges of Mankind. But from this Day's Decisions, from the Choice Of his first Colleagues, shall succeeding Times Of Edward judge, and on his Fame pronounce. For Dignities and Titles, when misplac'd Upon the Vicious, the Corrupt and Vile, Like Princely Virgins to low Peasants match'd, Descend from their Nobility, and soil'd By base Alliance, not their Pride alone And native Splendor lose, but Shame retort Ev'n on the Sacred Throne, from whence they sprung. So may the Lustre of this Order bright, This Eldest Child of Chivalry be stain'd, If at her first Espousals, her great Sire, Caught by the specious Outsides, that deceive And captivate the World, admit the Suit Of vain Pretenders, void of real Worth; Light empty Bubbles, by the wanton Gale Of Fortune swell'd, and only form'd to dance And glitter in the Sun-shine of a Court. Begin we then with Edward; first let him At his own high Tribunal undergo The rigid Inquisition—I for this Have left my lucid Star-encircled Throne: For This, immortal Sages, have requir'd Your wise and prudent Ministry, well skill'd In various Science, and the Human Heart. Search Edward's to the Bottom: sound the Depths And Shallows of his Soul; if he possess That first of Regal Talents, to discern, With quick-ey'd Penetration, thro' the Veil Of Art, each Character's intrinsick Worth, And all the Lab'rinths of the Human Mind. Nor blush for this good End yourselves to wear Fallacious Forms, to plead the Cause of false But specious Merit; at his Throne appear In borrow'd Shapes, and there with artful Guile, When the shrill Trumpet cites the Candidates, Urge your Pretensions: all the Pow'r employ Of Wit and Eloquence: Edward, I trust, The Trial shall abide; which shall but tend To manifest, that not from Arrogance, But conscious Virtue, hath he thus assum'd Above all other Kings, to be the Judge And great Rewarder of Heroick Deeds. Nor wholly unassisted will I leave My Royal Charge, but with blest Influence clear His Intellectual Eye from the dim Mists It haply hath contracted from a long Unebbing Current of Felicity, Unhop'd, unequall'd Triumphs, from the View Of Captive Monarchs, and the glitt'ring Throng, Who at his Summons from all Climates come, To take, as from their Sovereign, Honours new. When Heav'n tries Mortals in unusual Ways, 'Tis fit it shou'd afford unusual Aid. Now, Sages, to yon spreading Oaks retire, There wait my Summons; and mean time advise How best to execute the Task enjoin'd. Exe. Gen. and Druids. The Scene Changes to a large Room in the Castle (St. George's Hall) at the upper End of which is a Royal Canopy with the Figure of St. George and the Motto of the Garter, Honi soit qui mal y pense, beneath it embroider'd in Gold. Under this Canopy appears seated on an Elevation of two or three Steps King Edward in the Habit of the Order of the Garter, with a Scepter in his Right-hand and a Globe in his left. On his Left-hand is seated Queen Philippa with a Crown upon her Head, and dress'd in a Royal Mantle of Crimson Velvet, powder'd with embroider'd Garters, and an enamel'd That the Ladies of the Knights of the Garter wore this Ensign of the Order upon their left Arms, may be seen in Ashmole's History of the Garter.Garter bound like a Bracelet upon her left Arm. By her stand a great Number of Ladies very richly dress'd. On Edward's Right-hand is seated King John, in the Imperial Robes of France; and on the same side, but a Step lower, sits Edward the Black Prince, in the Robes belonging to the Prince of Wales. Next to Queen Philippa are seated the rest of Edward's Children; and next to the Black Prince, on the other side, stand the French Prisoners, and a great Number of Lords, &amp;c. richly dress'd. On the Floor at some distance stands Garter King at Arms in the Habit of his Office, holding in his Hand a Garter, with the Grand Collar of the Order. Near him stand other Heralds, Ushers, Attendants, &amp;c. Flourish of Trumpets, Kettle-Drums, &amp;c. After which Edward rising up from his Throne, addresses himself to the Assembly. Edward. That hither from your distant Residence, By solemn Invitation, noble Guests, I have entreated your illustrious Train, Misconstrue not to Levity and Pride, Or ostentatious vain Magnificence, Unworthy the grave Majesty of Kings, Unworthy your Attention, my Renown. This bright Assemblage of the Wise, the Brave, The Noble, the Magnificent, the Fair, The Ornaments of Europe, have I sought To grace the Pomp of Virtue, to adorn With noblest Offerings her unspotted Shrine, Attracting thus to her divine Commands The awful Veneration of Mankind. This was the Cause, great Princes, this the Call, The Voice of Virtue, not of England's King, That with respectful Zeal ye heard and follow'd: From Burgundy's rich Vineyards, from the Meads Of Hainault and Brabant, the rocky Wave Of Danube, from Germania's warlike Tow'rs, Imperial Mother of an Hundred States; From Spain, long exercis'd by Moorish Arms, From Italy's fair Princedoms, and the Walls Of Sea-wash'd Venice, Adria's haughty Spouse. With me then, all ye Virtuous, by what Stile Recorded in the Registers of Fame, Knights, Senators, or Soldiers, Ermin'd Lords, Or Sceptred Princes; from whatever Clime Ye come, ennobled by Heroick Acts, With me unite the Splendor of your Names To dignify th'Erection of a New And Noble Order, which to Heav'n's high Praise, And to Heav'n's Champion, Cappadocian George, On this his holy Festival I mean To found, a Recompence for worthiest Deeds. Thus as the Orient Sun, ador'd of old By prostrate Persia, ow'd his Deity Less to that genial and benignant Heat That cherishes and warms the Seeds of Life, Than to those gorgeous Beams, that deck with Gold And Crimson the gay Portals of the Morn; So shall this rising Order owe its Fame And brightest Lustre to the splendid Train Of Lords and Purple Princes, who are met This Day to usher and adorn its Birth. Nor deem that to allure Heroick Minds, My Private Interests partially to serve, To list the Valiant in Ambition's Cause, And form a League of Conquest, I have laid In subtle Policy this great Design: Edward being engag'd in a War with France, for the Obtaining that Crown, in order to draw into England great Multitudes of Foreigners, with whom he might negotiate either for their personal Service, or Aids of Troops to assist him in that Undertaking, ordered, during the Truce that then subsisted between the two Crowns, Publication to be made of a great Tournament to be held at Windsor; an Expedient says Rapin, which could not fail of Success, because it was intirely agreeable to the Taste of that Age. Accordingly many Persons of Distinction came over, to all of whom he gave an Honourable Reception, caressing them in such a Manner, that they could never sufficiently admire his Politeness, Magnificence, and Liberality. To render these Entertainments the more Solemn, and to free himself also from the Ceremonies, to which the Difference of Rank and Condition would have subjected him, he caused a Circular Hall of Boards to be run up at Windsor, 200 feet in Diameter. There it was that he Feasted all the Knights at one Table, which was call'd the Round Table, in Memory of the Great Arthur, who, as it is pretended, instituted an Order of Knighthood by that Name. Next Year he caused a more solid Building to be erected, that he might continue Yearly the same Diversions. During that time he treated with these several Lords about the Aids, wherewith each could furnish him, in proportion to his Forces. His Rival King Philip could not see without Jealousy, Spaniards, Italians, Germans, Flemings and Frenchmen themselves flock to England to assist at those Tournaments. He suspected some hidden Design in these Entertainments, and to break Edward's Measures, caused the like to be published in his Dominions; which meeting with Success proved a Countermine to Edward's main Design, so that he did not long continue to keep up his Round Table. From thence, however, it is generally agreed, he took the first Hint of Instituting the Order of the Garter. But as his Purpose in erecting this Order was very different from that which had induced him to revive Arthur's Round Table, as he had in this no private Views, no ambitious Scheme of engaging such as should be admitted into this Fraternity to assist him in his Wars, he thought proper, in order to obviate the like Jealousies and Suspicion as had alarmed. King Philip, to signify by his Motto the Purity of his Intentions, and to retort Shame upon all those who should put any malignant Construction upon his Design in Instituting this Order. This therefore I take to be the true Meaning and Import of the famous Motto, Honi soit qui mal y pense. The not understanding the Purport of which, gave rise in all probability to that vulgar Story of the Countess of Pembroke's. Garter, rejected by all the best Writers.Asham'd be He, who with malignant Eye So reads my Purpose: And be He accurst Whoe'er in After-times shall so pervert This Sacred Institution. To the World I here consign it, to the Good and Great Of every Age and Clime, and Them alone. Now sound the Trumpet; bid the Candidates With Confidence appear, and urge their Claims. Flourish of Trumpets, &amp;c. which is answer'd by another Trumpet from without; then enter a Grandee of Spain, magnificently attir'd in the Spanish Habit, holding in his Hand the Pedigree of his Family, and preceded by Heralds, &amp;c. bearing Atchievments, Banners, Coats of Armour, Helmets, Gauntlets, Spurs, &amp;c. Spaniard. Illustrious Monarch! Emperor of the Isles! My Name is Guzman—from those Heroes sprung Who with Pelagio mid th' Asturian Rocks, Against th' Invasion of unnumber'd Moors, Maintain'd the Fame and Empire of the Goths, And founded at Oviedo once again The Spanish Monarchy and Catholick Faith, Transporting from the Mountain's dreary Womb To glittering Temples her most holy Altars. Thence on the bordering Moor their valiant Sons Waging incessant War, e'er long regain'd Their Ancient Realms of Leon, Arragon, And rich Castillia: in which great Exploits My brave Progenitors, by Valour, Zeal, And Loyalty distinguish'd, from their Kings Gain'd those high Honours, princely Signories, And proud Prerogatives, which have extoll'd The Name of Guzman to such envy'd Grandeur, That scarce above it towers the Regal Throne. These Honours undiminish'd, undefil'd, To me deliver'd down, might well content A vulgar Mind; but Spirits highly born, Are full of generous and aspiring Thoughts; And use the vantage Ground of Rank and Pow'r But to ascend still higher. Thus I come Thy Garter to sollicit; pleas'd, great Prince, With Thee to be enroll'd thy Brother Knight, And fearing no Repulse. Nobility, As nearest in her Orbit, first receives The Beams of Majesty; alone can bear The Fulness of that Glory, which o'erpow'rs Inferior Natures. Virtue's self wou'd blush, Did she at once approach too near the Throne. But the young Eagle born amid the Blaze Of glancing Lightnings, with undazled Eye Soars to the Courts of Heav'n, and perches bold On the bright Sceptre of Imperial Jove. The greatest King is he, that is the King Of greatest Subjects. Seek'st Thou to advance The Glory of thy Order? To thy self Associate those, whose high-exalted Names, For Ages past from Envy's self have forced Habitual Veneration, never paid To new and upstart Merit. Such am I, Whose pure and generous Blood, descending down From Noblest Fountains, in its Course enrich'd By glorious Mixtures with each Royal Stream That fair Iberia boasts, might ev'n pretend To thy Alliance, Edward. View this Scroll, The faithful Blazon of my ancient Line, A Line of Potentates, whose every Son Deserv'd to wear the Garter I demand. In me their Representative, the Heir Of all their Honours, Son of their Renown, Do thou reward their Virtues: In their Names I claim, and on hereditary Right, The Right of Monarchs, Edward, rest my Plea. Edward. The high Desert of thy renown'd Fore-fathers Well hast thou shewn; but hast thou therefore prov'd Thy self deserving to be call'd their Son? To thee their prosperous Virtues have indeed Transmitted lineal Rank, and Titles proud, By them more hardly gain'd; for which thou stand'st To Custom and th'Indulgence of the Country Indebted, Guzman, in a large Account; Which thou must first discharge by noble Deeds, E'er thou canst stile those Dignities thine own. This if thou hast not paid, why dost thou seek, Like thriftless Prodigals to swell the Debt, And overwhelm thy self with Obligations? Virtue is Honour, and the noblest Titles Are but the publick Stamps set on the Ore To ascertain its Value to Mankind. It were a kind of Treason to my Crown, To mark base Metal with the Royal Impress, And put off lazy Pride in Virtue's Name. Wou'dst thou attain my Garter? Seek it there, Where thy Heroick Ancestors acquir'd Their glorious Honours, in th' embattled Field Among the Squadrons of the Warlike Moors: Or in the Council of thy King, by Truth And Wisdom equal to th' important Trust. Be what thy Fathers were, and then return To ask the Pledge of Merit from my Hand, And be the fit Companion of a King. Exit Spaniard. Flourish of Trumpets, &amp;c. which, as before, is answer'd by another Trumpet from without; then enter an Usurer and Senator of Genoa (at that time the Bank of Europe) dress'd in his Senatorial Gown of black Velvet, profusely, but awkwardly adorn'd with Jewels, Pearls and Diamond Necklaces, Pendents, Bracelets, Rings, such as he may be suppos'd to have receiv'd as Pawns, and to wear rather as Marks of his great Riches, than as Ornaments of his Dress. He is attended by a large Train of People of every Profession, appearing to be his Debtors, by their abject and timid Countenances, at the Head of whom, and next to the Usurer, marches a Scrivener bearing a large Bundle of Bonds, Mortgages, &amp;c. Genoese. From Genoa the Opulent, the Bank And Treasury of the World, most puissant King, Invited by thy Heralds, am I come To claim the Honour by thy Promise due, Due by thy Justice to superior Worth; Due then to me, great Edward, who possess That Object of the Toils, the Cares, the Vows Of all Mankind, that comprehensive Good, Source of all Pow'r and Grandeur, boundless Wealth. Behold yon glitt'ring Train, whose sumptuous Pride, Bright with the Treasures of each precious Mine, Invests with Glory thy Imperial Throne: Whence is their Dignity? The Ray august, That awes and dazles the respectful Croud, Proceeds it from Nobility, from Virtue Their Wisdom, or their Valour, or their Fame? Comes it not rather from the beaming Ore? The Diamond's star-like Radiance? Wealth, O King, Wealth is the Sun that decks the gorgeous Scene; That cherishes, adorns, and calls to View These Princely Flowers of Honour, Virtue, Fame, Which in the Shade of Poverty were lost. Whatever Men desire or venerate On Wealth attends; ev'n Empire's self is bought. Nor cou'd the mighty Julius have attain'd By Wisdom or by Valour Sovereign Pow'r, Had not the Gold of vanquish'd Gaul subdued The Liberties of Rome. On wretched Want Contempt, and narrow-soul'd Dependence wait. Ev'n Kings, of necessary Wealth depriv'd, In Pow'rless Indigence lose all Respect, All Homage from their Subjects: While the Rich, Like Gods ador'd, o'er every Neck extend Their potent Sceptres, and in Golden Chains Fierce Faction and rebellious Freedom bind. The Glory, Strength, Importance of a Realm Is measur'd by its Riches: Venice thus, Thus Genoa's petty State out-balances, In Europe's Scale, the boundless Wilds that cloath With Tributary Furs the Russian Czar. With like Pre-eminence exalted shines In every Land above the proudest Names, The blest Possessor of all-worship'd Gold. My Birth or Rank I boast not here, though born A Senator of Genoa. The Desert, On which I found my Claim, is all my own; To have adorn'd and dignify'd the State Of my declining House with greater Wealth Than e're my thriftless Ancestors possess'd: Whose richest Acquisitions were but Sprigs Of barren Laurel, or the flaunting Rags Of some torn Ensign, to their needy Son A worthless Heritage. Yet not to swell My narrow Fortunes wou'd my Soul descend To the base Methods of ignoble Trade, And vulgar mercantile Pursuit of Gain. Mine were the nobler Arts of raising Gold From Gold, of nursing and improving Wealth By gainful Use; Arts practis'd heretofore By Senators and Sages of Old Rome, Illustrious Crassus, and wise Seneca. Thus have I grac'd the Splendor of my Name With suitable Possessions; thus I hold In firm Subjection to my Will the Poor Of ev'ry Rank and Order, Soldier, Priest, The vent'rous Merchant, and the sumptuous Lord, Who in a lower Vassalage to Me, Than to thy Sceptre, Edward, bow their Heads, Pledging their Lands and Liberties for Gold. Hence am I bold to stand before thy Throne A Candidate for Glory's highest Prize: And let me add, that Policy alone Shou'd teach thy Prudence to approve my Claim; Shou'd teach thee in thy Subjects to excite, By Honours on superior Wealth bestow'd, A useful Emulation to be Rich: Which once inspir'd, thy Albion shall become The first of Nations, Thou the first of Kings. Edward. Hadst Thou by opening to thy Native Land The golden Veins of Commerce, by employing The useful Hands of Industry in Works Of National Advantage, by uniting Remotest Regions in the friendly Bands And honest Intercourse of Mutual Trade; Hadst Thou by these humane and generous Arts, Which thy mistaken Pride so much disdains, Enrich'd at once thy Country and thy self, Then not unworthy hadst thou been to wear The brightest Marks of Honour; but thy Wealth, The base-born Child of sordid Usury, That Foe to Commerce, Nurse of Idleness, Stains and degrades thee from thy noble Birth; Nor in the Usurer can I discern The Senator of Genoa.—To enlarge The Mind with gen'rous Sentiments, to raise Its Aims by Virtuous Emulation, here I sit; but not to gild with Honour's Beams That selfish Passion which congeals the Heart, And stops the Streams of sweet Benevolence, Mean Avarice, the Vice of narrowest Souls, Incapable of Glory—Wealth, thou say'st, Can buy ev'n Empire, and to Julius gave Dominion o'er his Country—Fatal Gift, And ruinous to both! but what to Rome, What to that Cæsar's Successors avail'd The boundless Treasures of the ravag'd World, When they had lost their Virtue? Did not soon The valiant Sons of Poverty, the Goths, The Huns and Vandals, from their barren Hills And rugged Woods descending, to their Steel Subject the Roman Gold? Yet I deny not The Pow'r and Use of Riches: To the Wise And Good, in publick or in private Life, They are the Means of Virtue, and best serve The noblest Purposes; but in the Use, Not in the bare Possession, lies the Merit. Shew me thy Merit then, thy bounteous Acts, Publick Munificence, or private Alms, The Hungry and the Naked, and the Sick Sustain'd and cherish'd by thy saving Hand; Plead this, and I allow thy worthy Claim, For this is Virtue, and deserves Reward. Exit Gen. Flourish of Trumpets, &amp;c. which is answer'd by a Symphony of Flutes, Violins, &amp;c, playing a light amourous Air; then appears a Neapolitan Courtier, a Favorite of Queen Joan, who then reign'd at Naples, and whose Court was the most debauch'd and dissolute of that Age. He comes in with a gay and affected Gesture; and is dress'd in loose silken Robes, rich, but finical and effeminate; on his Hair, which is curl'd and spread all over his Shoulders down to the Middle of his Back, he wears a Chaplet of Roses, and is attended by a Train of beautiful Boys, habited like Cupids, and Musicians, who, as he marches towards the Throne, continue playing their soft and wanton Airs. Neapolitan. Not on my Wealth, nor on my noble Blood, Shall I presume to claim thy Royal Gift, Auspicious Prince, but on the Skill to give That Splendor to Nobility and Wealth, That Elegance of Taste, from which alone Their Value they derive; of this to judge, This to direct, I boast, fit Arbiter Of all refin'd Delights—But chief to Kings My happy Talents I devote; on them My Genius waits with duteous Care, and wafts The Golden Cup of Pleasure to their Lips, Like Ganymede before the Throne of Jove. And who indeed would wish to be a God Only to Thunder, and to hear the Pray'rs Of clam'rous Suitors? 'Tis the Nectar'd Feast, The Dance of Graces, and the wanton Charms Of Venus, sporting with the Smiles and Loves, That make the Court of Heav'n a blest Abode. Far happier were the meanest Peasant's Lot, Who sleeps or sings in careless Ease beneath The Sunburnt Haycock, or the flow'ry Thorn, Than to be plac'd on high in anxious Pride, The Purple Drudge and Slave of tiresome State, If to superior Power superior Means Of Joy were not annext, and larger Scope For every Wish the lavish Heart can form: If the soft Hand of Pleasure did not wreathe Around the Royal Diadem, whose Weight Oppressive loads the Monarch's aching Brow, Her fairest Growth of ever-blooming Flow'rs. On Thee, victorious Prince, propitious Fortune Hath pour'd her richest Gifts, Renown and Wealth, And Greatness equal to thy mighty Mind; One only Bliss is wanting to thy Court, Voluptuous Elegance, the lovely Child Of Ease and Opulence; that never comes, But like a Bird of Summer to attend The brightest Sunshine of a glorious State. To her, and her alone belongs the Task, By learned Delicacy to remove, What yet remains in this thy ancient Realm Of Gothick Barbarism, the Rust of War, And valiant Ignorance—Her artful Hand, Thy rugged Britons shall refine, and teach More Courtly Manners, to their Sovereign's Will Politely pliant: Do but thou command Thy willing Servant, with thy Favours grac'd, From fair Joanna's ever-smiling Court, Under whose happy Influence I was train'd, From polish'd Naples, her delightful Seat, The blooming Goddess to transport, with all Her Train of Joys, and fix them here beneath Thy great Protection—But perhaps thou fear'st The Voice of Censure, and the grave Reproof Of Moralizing Dullness: Idle Fear! The Vulgar Herd indeed, Religious Craft, And Policy of State have well confin'd With wise Severity to rigid Laws: Else would that headstrong Beast the Multitude Forget Obedience, and its Rider's Voice Disdain. But shall the Rider put a Curb In his own Mouth? The Laws that Kings have made, Shall they restrain the Makers? Edward, No! For Thee indulgent Justice shall relax Her harsh Decrees, and Piety shall wait To give her Reverend Sanction to thy Will, 'Tis thine to rove at large thro' Nature's Field, Crop every Flow'r, and taste of every Fruit; By sweet Variety provoking still The languid Appetite to new Desires. Nor useless to thy Pleasures, happy Prince, Shall be my faithful Service; nicer Joys, Joys of a quicker, more exalted Taste, Than ever ripen'd in this Nothern Clime, The Growth of softer Regions, shall my Hand By skilful Culture in thy Britain raise. To them, whose gross and dull Capacities Are fit to bear the Burthens of the State, The lab'ring Mules, that thro' the Mire of Forms Draw the slow Car of Government along, Gladly the Task of Bus'ness I resign. Be mine the brighter Province, to direct Thy Pleasures, Edward, Minister Supreme Of all thy softer Hours: To serve the King Be Theirs the Glory, let Me serve the Man. But shou'd thy sterner Genius, only pleas'd With Arms and Royalty's important Cares, The Duties of a King, my gentle Arts Too lightly Prize, and thence reject my Suit: Permit at least, that to Philippa's Ear, Divine Philippa, Thine and Beauty's Queen, And her Attendant Graces, I may plead The Cause of Bliss, a Cause so much their own: They will approve my Claim, to whom the Cares The Labours of my Life, my Head, my Heart Are all devoted—Let me from their Hands Receive the Garter, and be call'd their Knight. Philippa. Permit me, gracious Edward, to reply To this irreverent Flatterer, who presumes Before a Matron and a Queen to plead The Cause of Vice, and impudently hopes To find in her a Fautress of his Suit. But know, pernicious Sophister, my Heart Hath learn'd from Edward's Love, and this high Rank Which I partake with Him, a noble Pride, That ill can brook the too familiar Eye And sawcy Tongue of Riot and Debauch; In whose unmanner'd light Society, Nor Majesty, nor Virtue can maintain That Dignity, which is their proper Guard. Thy vile Refinements, and luxurious Arts, Miscall'd Politeness, I detest; and feel, In the soft Duties of a virtuous Love, Such pure, serene Delight, as far transcends What thou stil'st Pleasure, the delirious Joy Of an intoxicated feverish Brain. Behold my Royal Lord, the First and Best Of Kings, the Love and Wonder of Mankind! Behold my Children, worthy their great Sire, The general Theme of Praise and Benediction! These are my Pleasures: Can thy Skill bestow Superior Bliss? Ah no! the vain Attempt Wou'd only bring Disgust, Remorse, and Shame. Edward. That I have lov'd, Philippa, and esteem'd thee More for thy Virtues than those Female Charms, Which this vile Flatterer deems singly worth His Panegyrick, be thy Happiness And Glory, as it is thy Edward's Pride. With the like Spirit have I also woo'd And wedded Sov'reign Pow'r; not weakly caught With outward Pomp, or seeking to my self A Privilege to riot uncontroul'd In sensual Pleasures, and behind the Throne To laugh securely at Restraint and Law. No: I embrac'd her as the Child of Heav'n, Dowr'd with the ample Means of doing Good; From whose Espousals I might hope to raise An Offspring, worth th' Ambition of a King, Immortal Glory; to a generous Mind As far surpassing all the wanton Toys, Which he calls Pleasure, as thy faithful Love (The sweet O'erflowing of Heart-felt Delight) Excells, Philippa, the lascivious Smile Of common Prostitutes, caress'd and loath'd. Hence from my Sight with thy detested Arts, Base Minister of Luxury, the Bane Of every flourishing and happy State: Presume no more within my Court to sing Thy Syren-Song, nor soften into Slaves And Cowards my brave Subjects—I disdain That Elegance, which such as Thou can teach, Virtue alone is Elegant, alone Polite; Vice must be sordid and deform'd, Tho' to adorn her every Art contend. And rather wou'd I see my Britons roam Untutor'd Savages, among their Woods, As once they did, in naked Innocence, Than polish'd like the vile degenerate Race Of modern Italy's corrupted Sons. [Exit Neap. Trumpet sounds, and is answer'd from without by another Trumpet, which sounds a March, accompanied by Kettle-Drums and other Warlike Instruments: Then enters, preceded by Soldiers playing upon Fifes, and others bearing tatter'd Ensigns, Standards, and Trophies, a Leader of Mercenary Bands compleatly arm'd from Head to Foot, and carrying in his Right-hand a Baton or Truncheon. On each side of him march his 'Squires, one bearing his Launce, the other his Shield. Behind him, as his Attendants, comes a Train of Officers and Soldiers maimed, and their Faces all seam'd with Scars. Soldier. Nor Riches, nor Nobility of Birth, Nor the soft Arts of base effeminate Ease, Which justly thou rejectest, valiant Prince, But thy own darling Attribute I boast, Undaunted Courage, try'd in many a Field, In every Clime, and under every Banner, That for these Forty Summers hath been wav'd O'er Europe's Plains, by Isther, Rhine and Po, Hungarian and Bohemian, Flemish, French, Venetian, Spanish, Guelph and Ghibeline: Whence in just Confidence secure I come This Military Honour to Demand, Due to my Toils and Service, to my Wounds, My Laurels, and that generous Love of Glory, Which without any Call, or publick Cause, Or private Animosity, alone Rais'd my strong Arm, and drew my dreadful Sword. Wherever Mars his crimson Flag display'd, That was my Country, thither swift I bore My ready Valour, and the dauntless Band Of various Nations, under my Command, Prepar'd to sell their Blood, their Limbs, their Lives: Nor where the Right, nor where the justest Cause, Deign'd we to ask—Those intricate Debates We left to lazy Penmen in the Shade Of Coward Ease; while our impetuous Fire Still bore us forward, ardent to pursue Thro' Danger's roughest Paths the Steps to Fame. On such a Spirit should thy Favour smile. But let me wonder, Edward, that so long Thy Ear the vain Pretensions cou'd endure Of Men unknown to War, Attendants meet On some luxurious Asiatick Court, Or Female Distaff-Reign; but suiting ill The Presence of a Monarch great in Arms. Hadst thou to those inglorious Sons of Peace Thy Martial Order giv'n, the Warriour-Saint Had blush'd to see his Image so profan'd, Which on my manly Breast, indented o'er With many a noble Scar, will fitly shine. But wherefore stand I thus haranguing here, Unskilful as I am in smooth Discourse, The Coward's Argument? On Force alone I rest my Title: Let the glorious Prize Be hung on high amid the listed Field, And let me there dispute it; there my Launce Shall plead my Cause far better than my Tongue, If any dare deny my rightful Claim. Edward. Not for the Brave alone have I ordain'd This Institution, but for all Desert, All publick Virtue, Wisdom, all that serves, Improves, defends, or dignifies a State; Tho' first indeed to Valour, as the Guard Of all the rest, when in the publick Cause With Justice and Benevolence employ'd. But Thou, base Mercenary, canst thou dare The glorious Name of Valour to usurp, Who know'st no publick Cause, no Sense of Right, Nor Pity, nor Affection, nor Remorse? Who under any Chief, in any Quarrel, Canst stain with Gore thy prostituted Arms. Call it not Love of Glory; That is built On Acts for the Deliverance of Mankind; On generous Principles, and noble Scorn Of sordid Interest: Call it cruel Pride, And Savageness of Nature, that delights To conquer, and oppress, afflict, insult; Or call it Love of Plunder, that can draw Unauthoris'd, uninjur'd, unprovok'd, The Sword of War; that Bravo-like can lift For Hire the Venal Hand to perpetrate Assassinations, Murders, Massacres. But Thou hast serv'd with Courage: be it so— Thou hast thy Pay, and with it thy Reward; Pretend no farther, nor compare thy Deeds, Dishonour'd by the mean Desire of Gain, With His, who for his Country and his King Resigns his Ease, his Fortune, or his Life. Those Battles thou hast fought, those forty Years Of Blood and Horror, which thy vaunting Tongue So high hath sounded, are indeed thy Crimes, Flagitious Crimes; for which th' Impartial Bar Of Reason wou'd condemn thee, as the Foe Of Human Nature, did not Custom screen By her unjust Esteem thy guilty Head. But hope not Honour or Employment here. Unsafe and wretched is that Monarch's State, Who weakly trusts to Mercenary Bands, The Guard or of his Person, or his Realm: Unfaithful, insolent, rapacious, base He soon shall prove them, and become himself Their Slave, to hold his Kingdom at their Will. For this within my Britain have I sought, To raise a Martial Spirit, and ordain'd These new Incitements, Honours, and Rewards, To virtuous Chivalry, that never King Who wears hereafter my Imperial Crown, May need to stoop to the precarious Aid Of venal Foreign Swords; but in the Hearts Of his brave Subjects find a stronger Guard, Prepar'd with Zeal unbought, and English Valour, His Rights to vindicate, and save their own. Exit Soldier. Trumpet sounds, to which another from without replies: Then enters an Italian Politician, habited like a Venetian Nobleman, who advancing with a solemn and important Air towards the Throne, makes a low Reverence to King Edward, and proceeds. Politician. Well has thy sovereign Wisdom, Royal Judge, The Suit refus'd of these Pretenders vain, And, by rejecting them, embolden'd Me. For Valour, and Nobility and Wealth, Though by their proud Possessors vaunted high, Are but subordinate, the Slaves and Tools, Not the Companions, and the Counsellors Of Godlike Monarchy; whose awful Throne By darksome Clouds envelop'd, far beyond The Ken of vulgar Eyes, supported stands On that deep-rooted Prop, the Craft of State, Mysterious Policy.—Who best hath learn'd Her wily Lessons, best deserves to share The Honours, Counsels, and the Hearts of Kings. By Him instructed, even the meanest Prince Shall rise to envy'd Greatness, shall advance His dreaded Pow'r above Restraint and Fear, And all the Rules, that in fantastick Chains Inferior Minds confine. Thus Milan's Dukes, Thus Padoua's Lords above their Country's Laws Have rais'd their Heads, and trampled to the Dust The Pride of Freedom, that essays in vain Their high, superior Genius to controul. These were my Masters, mighty Prince; beneath Their Rule, and in their Councils was I form'd To know the false corrupted Heart of Man, His every Weakness, every Vice, and thence To tempt, or break his Passions to the Yoke: To scorn the Publick as an empty Name, And on the helpless Multitude impose The Adamantine Bonds of Fraud and Force. Thus was I train'd, thus fitted to conduct The Fate of proudest Empires; thus I come To claim thy Garter, Edward, the just Meed Of Worth præeminent, and in Return My Services to offer, which no doubt Thy Wisdom gladly will accept: For who So fit to serve the Majesty of Kings, As He, who slighting every meaner Tye, Friends, Parents, Country, to advance their Pow'r Devotes his Toil, Experience, Fortune, Fame, Nor other Favour courts, nor Refuge hopes But in their high Protection?—Led by me, Thou, Royal Edward, shalt attain that Height, That glorious Summit of Imperial Pow'r, Which not thy mightiest Ancestors have reach'd; Where in a freer Air, a more enlarg'd Horizon, bounded only by thy Will, Thou shalt exalted sit, and view beneath, In humbler Distances and safer Bounds, Those Subjects, who presumptuous now approach Too near, and with rude Hands profane thy Throne. Nor let weak Scruples check thy Manly Soul In the bright Task of Glory; know, great Prince, A King's Divinity is Sovereign Pow'r, The only God, before whose Shrine the Wise Their Incense offer; whence inspir'd, they draw Divine Ambition, and Heroick Scorn Of Vulgar Prejudices, Vulgar Fears. Virtue's the People's Idol, and by them Rewarded well with popular Applause, That idle Breath, the Gift and Prize of Fools. 'Tis thine to Govern, not to Court Mankind, Nor on their Smiles precarious to depend, But nobly force them to depend on Thine. O sacred Sir, can Virtue give thee This, This bright Supremacy? Trust not her Boasts, Her idle Pageantry of barren Praise: Reject her sawcy Claims, importunate, And self-supported; nor admit her Train, Proud Independency, and publick Zeal, Those factious Demagogues, the Foes of Kings. Edward. Are Virtue then and Love of publick Good The Foes of Monarchy? and are Deceit, Injustice, and Oppression, Qualities Becoming, and expedient in a King? Then know I not to govern; but have nurs'd For twice these Fifteen Years even in my Heart, A poisonous Viper; nay unking'd my self, By yielding to restrain my Sovereign Pow'r With Laws and Charters of Enfranchisement, Not due, it seems, from Monarchs to their Slaves. But know, vile Counsellor of Infamy, That I disclaim thy Politicks, those false And shallow Politicks, by which my Sire, Weak-judging Edward, was betray'd to Shame And foul Destruction, while to such as Thee His Ear and Heart incautious he resign'd, And was indeed their Slave, not England's King. By Maxims different far have I sustain'd The Strength and Splendor of my Regal State, On the broad Basis of true Wisdom fix'd With solid Firmness. By encouraging The generous Love of Virtue and of Fame, That Source of Valour, Pledge of Victory. By granting to my Subjects, what indeed Is their inherent Right, Security, The chearful Father of Content and Peace, Of Industry and Opulence, which fills With smiling Multitudes the Land, and pays In willing Subsidies that Prince's Care, Who lays up Treasure in his People's Hearts. By holding with a firm impartial Hand The steady Scale of Justice; not alone Betwixt my Subjects in their private Rights, But in the general, more important Cause, Betwixt the Crown and Them, the different Claims Of Freedom and of just Prerogative: Transgressing not myself by boundless Pow'r, Nor suffering others to transgress those Laws, That in their golden Chain together bind, For common Good, the whole united State. But more than all by guarding from Contempt Or impious Violation, that Supreme Protectress of all Government and Law, Religion; in whose Train for ever wait Obedience, Order, Justice, Mercy, Love, A Guard of Angels plac'd around the Throne. Her sacred Counsels have I still rever'd, Her high Commands enforc'd, her Pow'r implor'd, O'er all my Subject Nations to call down From Heav'nly Wisdom, her Eternal Sire, A fix'd secure Felicity, beyond The Force of human Prudence to attain. These are my Arts of Government, those Arts By which my British Crown I have advanc'd Above th' Imperial Diadem, above The pride of Africk's or of Asia's Thrones. I wou'd not tell Thee this, but that Thou seem'st A Stranger to my Fame, as to my Realm, And to the real Greatness of a King: Whose sacred Dignity, by thee traduc'd, Much it behoves a King to vindicate; Not by rejecting only with Disdain Thy Arrogant Pretensions, but in Thee Dishonouring and branding with Reproach Thy Tenets also, the pernicious Lore Of Tyrants and Usurpers, which thy Tongue, Blaspheming Justice, Government, and Law, Hath in a Land of Freedom dar'd to vent. Hence! from my Kingdom, with thy quickest Speed, Lest the Revenge of an insulted King With sudden Ruin intercept thy Flight. Exit Politician. King John. Permit me, Edward, to thy Royal Voice To add my Suffrage also, and with Thee Protest against this Coward Policy, That meanly skulks behind opprobrious Fraud, And low unprincely Artifice; I feel A Virtue in my Heart, a generous Pride, That tells me Kings were cloath'd with Majesty, Encircled with Authority, rever'd And almost Deify'd, to teach them thence That Goodness and the saving Attributes Of Heav'n become their Office, Justice chief, And Truth, the Virtue of heroick Minds, Which, were it banish'd from all other Breasts, Should dwell for ever in the Hearts of Kings. Aërial Musick, upon which re-enter the Five Druids who personated the Grandee, &amp;c. in their Original Characters and Habits of Druids, the Chief of whom advancing towards the Throne, addresses himself to King Edward. Chief Druid. Behold in Us, great King, the Ancient Priests And Judges of this Land, the Druids old: Who late in borrow'd Characters have stood Before thy sage Tribunal, to prefer The Claims of Valour, Wealth, Nobility, And those soft specious Flatterers, who beneath The Rosy Wreaths of Pleasure and of Love Conceal the sickly and disgustful Brow Of Riot and Debauch, and often win From weak unmanly Princes the rich Prize To Virtue due and Wisdom, not to These The Cankers of a State; but least of all Due to that Traytor to his King and Country, Who lab'ring to build up the Regal Throne Beyond its due Proportion, and the Strength Of those Foundations which the Laws have laid, O'erwhelms the People, and at once o'erturns His Royal Master, places him at best On an uneasy tottering Pinnacle, The Mark of Execration and Reproach. These Claims hast thou rejected; like a King Discerning in Mankind, and knowing well The Value of his Favours: Like a King Deserving the high Office of the Judge And Arbiter of Europe; like a King Equal to his great Fame, and worth the Care Of those immortal Spirits, who this Day Have quitted their Celestial Residence To view and to approve thy glorious Deeds. But Edward, be not thou amaz'd to find That those, who lately for thy Favour sued Were not the Personages they assum'd. O King! Thou art beset with Counterfeits The very Opposites to Us, who seem Far better than they are. For Flattery, Chameleon-like, accommodates with Care To the Court-hue his changeful Countenance. And when a Prince is Brave, Magnanimous, And high in Spirit, then Ambition wears A Face of Dignity, and nothing breathes But lofty Enterprizes, Conquest, Pow'r, And Schemes of Glory to the Sovereign Ear, Pretending Love and Care for his Renown With more than duteous Zeal.—Of these beware! For as the Theban Queen, in Fables old, Was, by the specious Guile of fraudful Jove, In her Amphitryon's Form to Guilt betray'd, So by these Counterfeits are Kings seduc'd, Ev'n in the most belov'd suspectless Shapes, To take a Traytor to their Royal Arms. But Thou shalt know them, Edward, by their Works. And of this Truth be most assur'd, that He, Who in his private Commerce with Mankind Is mean, dishonest, interested, false, Can ne'er be true to Thee, nor can he love His Prince, who feels not for his Country's Good. Thus warn'd we leave Thee, mighty Prince: be firm, Be constant in the Paths of fair Renown. Think it thy Duty to revere thyself The Sacred Laws of Chivalry, the Wise Injunctions by thy Order laid on all The Garter'd Knights; so shall thy Fame remain The great Example of all Future Kings. Farewel! for lo! the Genius of thy Realm With all his Pomp attended, comes to share, And grace the Glories of this signal Day. These Clouds of Fragrance, that far-beaming Blaze Of Heav'nly Brightness, his approach declare. Druids vanish. Flashes of Light, and Symphony of Aerial Musick. Genius of England descends in his Chariot attended by Spirits and Bards, then alighting he advances towards the Throne, and addresses himself to Edward. Genius. From the gay Realms of cloudless Day I come, Where in the Glitter of unnumber'd Worlds, That like to Isles of various Magnitudes Float in the Ocean of Unbounded Space; On my invisible Aerial Throne I sit, attended with a radiant Band Of Spirits immortal, whose pure Essences, While clad in human Shapes on Earth they dwelt, Thro' the dull Clay of gross Mortality Disclos'd their heav'nly Vigour, and burst forth In godlike Virtues and heroick Deeds, Their Albion gracing with as fair a Growth Of Fame, as e'er enrich'd Imperial Rome. Thence ripe for Heav'n and Immortality, To Me, the Genius of this happy Isle, They fly, and claim the Meed of their Desert, Celestial Crowns, and ever-living Praise Recorded in the Songs of Heav'nly Bards, That round my Throne their Hymns of Triumph sing, Attuning to the sweet harmonious Spheres, Their undiscording Lyres and Voice divine. Nor thus remov'd to Heav'n, and thus employ'd In ceaseless Raptures, wont they to forget Their Native Country, and the Publick Weal, To which on Earth their Labours and their Lives They once devoted; but persuing still The Bent and Habit of their Souls, with me They watch the British Empire, still intent To check alternately th' incroaching Waves Of Regal Pow'r and popular Liberty: I, chief attentive near the Royal Throne, Take up my watchful Station, to infuse My sage and moderate Counsels in those Ears, Which Wisdom hath prepar'd and purify'd To relish honest, tho' unpleasing Truth. Thus am I always, tho' invisible, Attendant, Edward, on thy glorious Deeds. But on this solemn Day have I vouchsafed To manifest my Presence; to declare, Not in those Whispers which have often spoke Peace to thy conscious Heart, but audibly And evident to All, th' Assent of Heav'n To the great Business, which hath gather'd here This Troop of Princes from all Nations round. Hence all may know that Virtue hath a Train More bright than Earthly Empire can command: Know, that those Actions which are great and good, Receive a nobler Sanction from the free And universal Voice of all Mankind, Which is the Voice of Heav'n, than from the highest, The most illustrious Act of Regal Pow'r. This nobler Sanction, Edward, in the Name Not of this Age alone, but latest Time, Here do I solemnly annex to each Of thy great Acts, but chief to this most wise Most virtuous Institution, which extends Wide as thy Fame, beyond thy Empire's Bound, A Prize of Virtue publish'd to Mankind. Ye Registers of Heav'n, record the Deed. Bards. Now tune, ye Bards, the British Lyre; Now wake the Vocal String; While Heav'n and Earth in Edward's Praise conspire, Join to the general Voice your sacred Quire, And on your soaring Wing, From Time and Envy waft his glorious Name, And place it in the Shrine of incorruptive Fame. Begin; the listening Echoes round Shall catch with Joy the long-forgotten Sound, And warbling thro' each Grove the British Strain To Windsor's smiling Nymphs, recall their Arthur's Reign. Ye Nymphs of Windsor's bow'ry Woods, Ye Pow'rs who haunt yon glist'ning Floods, That with reluctant fond Delay Around yon flow'ry Valley stray; Say, from your Minds hath time eras'd The pleasing Images of Glory past? Review ye now those Scenes no more? When nobly stain'd with Saxon Gore, From Badon's long-contended Plain Great Arthur with his Martial Train To Windsor's chosen Shades repair'd, And with his Knights the festive Banquet shar'd. Then first exulting Thames beheld The Triumphs of the listed Field; Beheld along his level Meads Careering Knights, encount'ring Steeds, Heroick Games, whose Toils inspire The Thirst of Praise, and kindle Martial Fire. Fair Peace in War's bright Mail array'd, With Smiles the glorious Lists survey'd; So shou'd the Brave (she cry'd) prepare Their Hearts and sinewy Arms for War: Such Combats break not my Repose, Such Sons best guard my Rights from daring Foes. Then too in feastful Hall or Bow'r, Attendant on the genial Hour, The British Harp sweet Lyrists strung, And Albion's generous Victors sung: While valiant Arthur's copious Fame Incessant fed the bright poetick Flame. But Mortals erring in Excess, O'erwhelm the Virtue they caress. Thus Arthur his great Story mourn'd, By too fond Praise to Fable turn'd: Mourn'd the Companions of his Toils, Mock'd with false Glory and fantastick Spoils. 'Till thro' the dark Romantick Tale, Thro' Superstition's magick Veil, Sage Edward piercing view'd, and own'd The Chief with genuine Lustre crown'd: View'd the great Model, and restor'd The long-lost Honours of his Martial Board. Hail British Prince! These faithful Lays, Eternal Records of Heroick Worth, Shall reassert thy ancient Praise And from the Cloud of Fiction call thee forth, In Glory's Sphere thy Orbit to reclaim, And at great Edward's Beam relume thy dark'ned Fame. But see! in Heav'nly Panoply array'd, Whose streaming Radiance skirts the Clouds with Gold, I view Pendragon burst the veiling Shade, And all his blazing Magnitude unfold! O'er yon broad Tow'r he takes his airy Stand, And pointing, Edward, towards thy Royal Throne, To his fam'd Knights around, a laurel'd Band, Shews on thy Knee the bright Sky-tinctur'd Zone. Virtue, he cries, (th' ætherial Sound Thy gross material Organ cannot hear) Virtue on Earth by British Edward crown'd, Her reverend Throne once more shall rear. To Her own self-applauding Breast Forc'd for Reward no longer to retreat, She sees her awful Charms by Kings caress'd, Sees Honour woo her for his Mate. Honour, her Heav'n-elected Spouse, From her Embrace by lawless Pow'r with-held, Now at yon Altar plights his holy Vows, Vows by assenting Edward seal'd. And now the fair Angelic Bride Gathering her Noble Train from every Land, To her late-wedded Lord with decent Pride Presents the venerable Band. The great Procession Edward leads; I see yon hallow'd Dome with Heroes throng'd: Incessant still the white-plum'd Pomp proceeds, Thro' Time's eternal Course prolong'd. And you, dear Partners of my Fame, Your ancient Honours now again shall boast; This Noble Order shall retrieve our Name, In visionary Fables lost. This from our Martial Board deriv'd, These for our Brethren let us proudly own, More pleas'd to view our Deeds by Thee reviv'd, Than griev'd, Great King, to be outdone. CHORUS. Hail British Prince! these faithful Lays Shall reassert thy ancient Praise. Nor Thee, O Windsor, shall I pass unsung, Mansion of Princes, and fit Haunt of Gods, Who frequent shall desert their bright Abodes, To view thy sacred Walls with Trophies hung: Thy Walls by British Arthur first renown'd, The early Seat of Chivalry and Fame; By Edward now with deathless Honour crown'd, Illustrious by his Birth, his Garter, and his Name! Genius. Conferring just Rewards, most worthy Prince, Is the first Attribute of Sov'reign Pow'r, And That which best distinguishes a King: For Punishment, and all the nice Awards Of Civil Justice, by the Laws are fix'd, And Kings but execute what they decree. While in rewarding Merit, uncontroul'd, Unguided, unassisted is the Hand Of Majesty; The Prince himself alone There judges, and his Wisdom is the Law. Well does thy Court, great King, with every Worth And every Virtue fill'd, this Wisdom shew In thee transcendant; well hast thou approv'd Its Force in this great Trial, which my Pow'r Commanded, in no common ways to prove Thy Royal Mind.—But that a Father's Name May not restrain thy Justice in the Choice Of the first Knights-Companions of St. George, Myself here take upon me to present A Candidate, whom, were he not thy Son, Thou wouldst thyself select from all Mankind. His Modesty compells me to declare That Candidate is Edward, Prince of Wales. Prince Edward. Inhabitant of Heav'n! I not presume To deprecate or question that high Will, To which it best becomes me to submit. But, gentle Spirit, be propitious to me; And Thou, my gracious Liege, if I request That this illustrious Monarch, whose Desert Is equal to the Grandeur of his Crown, May stand before me in this List of Fame. King John. Oh generous Youth! in vain thy Goodness strives To raise thy Captive thus above his Fortune. The King that is not free, is not a King; Nor can thy bounteous Favour reconcile Honour and Bondage.—To thy conquering Son Do thou, great Edward, give this Noble Mark Of prosperous Virtue; ill becomes it me, To wear at once thy Garter and thy Chains. Though by my former Dignity I swear, That were I reinstated in my Throne, The Throne of Capet and of Charlemagne, Thus to be join'd in Fellowship with Thee, Would be the first Ambition of my Soul, A Ray of Glory I wou'd sue to gain, And prize it equal with my Diadem. Genius. Wisely thou hast determin'd, worthy Prince, For Thine and Edward's Honour, and hast fix'd Its proper Value on his Royal Gift, Which, as the Meed of Merit, may become The proudest Monarchs, by this Garter mark'd For something more than Monarchs, Virtuous Men. This be the Glory of thy Order, Edward. And Besides the great Persons of our own Nation, that have been admitted of this Order, the English Reader may be glad to be informed that in the Annals of the Garter are found the Names of Charles V. Emperor of Germany; of Francis I. and Henry IV. Kings of France; and of Gustavus Adolphus King of Sweden.never shall it want the greatest Names Of all succeeding Times to grace its Annals. France, Sweden, Poland, Germany and Spain, Each Realm of Europe's wide-extended Bounds, Shall count among thy Knights its mightiest Lords, And see, in Emulation of thy Fame, New Royal Founders of like Orders rise. Proceed then, mighty King, and set the World The Precedent of Glory: Thou begin The radiant List of Sovereigns, while thy Son, Like a young Bride, that on her Nuptial Morn Leads on with modest Pride the Virgin-Choir, Herself the brightest, heads the shining Band Of Knights-Companions, nobly seconding His Father's glorious Deeds with equal Fame. Edward. The Testimony of Heav'n to thee, my Son, Thus gloriously accorded, renders vain All farther Trial.—To my People's Voice, By this their Tutelary Pow'r declar'd, With Pleasure I consent, directing still By theirs my Choice, my Judgment, my Desires. Approach then, my belov'd, my Noble Son, Strength of my Crown, and Honour of my Realm; In whom my Heart more joys, and glories more, Than in the highest Pride of Sovereign Pow'r. The Prince of Wales advances to his Father, and kneels; while the King, taking the Garter from the Herald, buckles it round his left Leg.Thus I admit thee, Edward Prince of Wales, First Founder of the Order of St. George; In Evidence whereof, about thy Knee I bind this Mystick Garter, to denote The Bond of Honour, that together ties The Brethren of St. George in friendly League, United to maintain the Cause of Truth And Justice only— The Sense, and almost the Words in the Verses of this Speech, mark'd thus“, are taken from the Admonitions read to the Knights, at the time of their receiving the Garter and the Ribbon or Collar of the Order. Vide Ashmole's History of the Order of the Garter.“May propitious Heav'n “Grant thou may'st henceforth wear it to his Praise, “The Exaltation of this noble Order, “And thy own Glory.”—With like Reverence, My Son, receive and wear this Golden Chain, “Graced with the Image of Britannia's Saint, “Heav'n's valiant Soldier, Cappadocian George; “In Imitation of whose glorious Deeds “May'st Thou triumphant in each State of Life, “Or Prosperous or Adverse, still subdue “Thy spiritual and carnal Enemies; “That not on Earth alone Thou may'st obtain “The Guerdon of thy Valour, endless Praise, “But with the Virtuous and the Brave above, “In solemn Triumph, wear celestial Palms, “To crown thy final noblest Victory. [Embraces Pr. Edw. Prince Edward. Accept, my Sovereign Liege, my grateful Thanks, That thou hast thus vouchsaf'd to place thy Son First next thy self upon the Roll of Fame, As he indeed is first in Filial Love, And Emulation of thy Royal Virtues. And may thy Benediction, gracious Lord, May thy Paternal Vows be heard in Heav'n! That He, whom thou hast listed in the Cause Of Truth and Virtue, never may forget His vow'd Engagements, nor defraud thy Hopes, By soiling with dishonourable Deeds The Lustre of that Order, which thy Name Shou'd teach him to respect and to adorn. ODE. Bards. STROPHE I. Celestial Maid! Bright Spark of that Ætherial Flame, Whose vivid Spirit, thro' all Nature spread, Sustains and actuates this boundless Frame! O by whatever Stile to Mortals known, Virtue, Benevolence, or publick Zeal, Divine Assessor of the Regal Throne, Divine Protectress of the Common-weal, O in our Hearts thy Energy infuse! Be thou our Muse, Celestial Maid, And, as of Old, impart thy heav'nly Aid To those, who warm'd by thy benignant Fire, To publick Merit and their Country's Good Devoted ever their recording Lyre, Wont along Deva's sacred Flood, Or beneath Mona's Oaks retir'd, To warble forth their Patriot Lays, And nourish with immortal Praise, The bright heroick Flames by Thee inspir'd. ANTISTROPHE I. I feel, I feel Thy Soul-invigorating Heat; My bounding Veins distend with fervent Zeal, And to Britannia's Fame responsive beat.— Hail Albion, native Country! but how chang'd, Thy once grim Aspect! how adorned and gay Thy howling Forests! where together rang'd The naked Hunter and his Savage Prey: Where amid black inhospitable Woods The Sedge-grown Floods All cheerless stray'd. Nor in their lonely wand'ring Course survey'd, Or Tow'r, or Castle, Heav'n-ascending Fane, Or lowly Village, Residence of Peace And joyous Industry, or furrow'd Plain, Or lowing Herd, or silver Fleece, That whitens now each verdant Vale; While laden with their precious Store Far-trading Barks to every Shore, Swift Heralds of Britannia's Glory, sail. EPODE I. These are thy shining Works: this smiling Face Of beauteous Nature thus in regal State, Deck'd by each Handmaid Art, each polish'd Grace, That on fair Liberty and Order wait. This Pomp, these Riches, this Repose, To thee, Imperial Britain owes. To thee, great Substitute of Heav'n, To whom the Charge of earthly Realms was giv'n; Their social Systems by wise Nature's Plan To form, and rule by her eternal Laws; To teach the selfish Soul of wayward Man To seek the publick Good, and aid the common Cause. So, didst thou move the mighty Heart Of Alfred, Founder of the British State: So to Matilda's scepter'd Son, To him whose Virtue and Renown First made the Name of Edward great. Thy ample Spirit so didst thou impart: Protecting thus in every Age, From greedy Pow'r and factious Rage, That Law of Freedom, which to Britain's Shore From Saxon Elva's many-headed Flood, The valiant Sons of Odin with them bore, Their national, ador'd, inseparable Good. STROPHE II. Runny Mead near Stains, where the Grand Charter was sign'd by King John.On Yonder Plain, Along whose willow-fringed Side The silver-footed Naiads, sportive Train, Down the smooth Thames amid the Cygnets glide, I saw, when at thy reconciling Word, Injustice, Anarchy, intestine Jarr, Despotick Insolence, the wasting Sword, And all the brazen Throats of Civil War, Were hush'd in Peace: From his imperious Throne Hurl'd furious down, Abash'd, dismay'd, Like a chas'd Lion to the savage Shade Of his own Forests, fell Oppression fled, With Vengeance brooding in his sullen Breast. Then Justice fearless rear'd her decent Head, Heal'd every Grief, each Wrong redrest; While round her valiant Squadrons stood, And bade her aweful Tongue demand, From vanquish'd John's reluctant Hand, The Deed of Freedom purchas'd with their Blood. ANTISTROPHE II. O vain Surmise! To deem the Grandeur of a Crown Consists in lawless Pow'r! to deem them wise Who change Security and fair Renown, For Detestation, Shame, Distrust and Fear! Who, shut for ever from the blissful Bow'rs, With Horror and Remorse at Distance hear The Musick that inchants th'immortal Pow'rs, The heav'nly Musick of well-purchas'd Praise, Seraphick Lays, The sweet Reward On Heroes, Patriots, righteous Kings conferr'd. For such alone the heav'n-taught Poets sing. Tune ye for Edward then, the moral Strain, His Name shall well become your golden String. Begirt with this ætherial Train, Seems he not rank'd among the Gods? Then let him reap the glorious Meed Due to each great heroick Deed, And taste the Pleasures of the blest Abodes. EPODE II. Hail, happy Prince! on whom kind Fate bestows Sublimer Joys, and Glory brighter far Than Cressy's Palm, and every Wreath that grows In all the blood-stain'd Fields of prosp'rous War; Joys that might charm an heav'nly Breast, To make dependent Millions blest, A dying Nation to restore, And save fall'n Liberty with Kingly Pow'r; To quench the Torch of Discord and Debate, Relume the languid Spark of publick Zeal, Repair the Breaches of a shatter'd State, And gloriously compleat the Plan of England's Weal; Compleat the noble Gothick Pile, That on the Rock of Justice rear'd shall stand In Symmetry, and Strength, and Fame, A Rival of that boasted Frame Which Virtue rais'd on Tiber's Strand. This, Edward, Guardian, Father of our Isle, This God-like Task, to Few assign'd, Exalts Thee above Human-kind, And from the Realms of everlasting Day Calls down Celestial Bards thy Praise to sing; Calls this bright Troop of Spirits to survey Thee, the great Miracle of Earth, a Patriot-King. Genius. Now reascend your Skies, Immortal Spirits! Th' important Act, that drew ye down to Earth, Is finish'd. Spare we now their mortal Sense, That cannot long endure th' unshrouded Beam Of Higher Natures. Well hath Edward laid, Under your happy Auspices, the Base Of his great Order: Let him undisturb'd, But not unaided by the Heav'nly Pow'rs, Compleat th' illustrious Work, which future Kings, Struck with the Beauty of the Noble Plan, Shall emulously labour to maintain. And may thy Spirit, Edward, be their Guide! In every Chapter Thou henceforth preside, In every Breast infuse thy Virtuous Flame, And teach them to respect their Country's Fame. Genius and Spirits reascend to a loud Symphony of Musick. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>