<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Sherburne, Edward, Sir, 1618-1702</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Sherburne, Edward, Sir, 1618-1702</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">sherburne edward sir 1618 1702</field>
      <field name="author_text">Sherburne, Edward, Sir, 1618-1702</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_2.0226.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1648</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464813</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Seneca's Ansvver, to Lvcilivs ; His Qvaere; Why Good Men suffer misfortunes seeing there is a Diuine Prouidence? Written Originally in Latine Prose, And Now Translated into English Verse, By E. S. [i.e. Edward Sherburne</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">Seneca's Ansvver, to Lvcilivs ; His Qvaere; Why Good Men suffer misfortunes seeing there is a Diuine Prouidence? Written Originally in Latine Prose, And Now Translated into English Verse, By E. S. [i.e. Edward Sherburne</field>
      <field name="title_facet">senecas ansvver to lvcilivs</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">senecas ansvver to lvcilivs</field>
      <field name="title_text">Seneca's Ansvver, to Lvcilivs ; His Qvaere; Why Good Men suffer misfortunes seeing there is a Diuine Prouidence? Written Originally in Latine Prose, And Now Translated into English Verse, By E. S. [i.e. Edward Sherburne</field>
      <field name="year_display">1648</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1648</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1648</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464813&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464813&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Sherburne, Edward, Sir, 1618-1702&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;sherburne edward sir 1618 1702&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Seneca's Ansvver, to Lvcilivs ; His Qvaere; Why Good Men suffer misfortunes seeing there is a Diuine Prouidence? Written Originally in Latine Prose, And Now Translated into English Verse, By E. S. [i.e. Edward Sherburne&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;senecas ansvver, to lvcilivs&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1648&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1648&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Sherburne, Edward, Sir&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1618&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1702&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Seneca's Ansvver, to Lvcilivs&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;His Qvaere; Why Good Men suffer misfortunes seeing there is a Diuine Prouidence? Written Originally in Latine Prose, And Now Translated into English Verse, By E. S. [i.e. Edward Sherburne]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Humphrey Moseley [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1648&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp3535&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;30 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Seneca's Ansvver, to Lvcilivs&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;His Qvaere; Why Good Men suffer misfortunes seeing there is a Diuine Prouidence? Written Originally in Latine Prose, And Now Translated into English Verse, By E. S. [i.e. Edward Sherburne]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 61 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Calamitas, Virtutis occasio.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TO His most Sacred MAJESTY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SENECAS ANSWER, TO LUCILIUS HIS QUÆRE, &amp;c. PART. I. Argument. To prove there's Providence were vaine, Since it's Effects Wee see so plaine. Thou asks't of me (my Deare Lucilius!) whence, (If this World govern'd be by Providence,) So many Evills should good men befall? This would, in our works Context, (where we shall Prove, that a Providence doth all things steare, And that God's present with us ev'ry where) Be fitlier answer'd: but since pleas'd thou art, That from the Whole I should divide this Part; And cleare this seeming Contradiction, Letting the rest of the Dispute alone; I willingly to this shall condiscend, And easily the Gods just Cause defend. 'Twill seem but needlesse to be here maintain'd, That this great Fabrick cannot be sustain'd Without some Guardian, or that the set Dance, And certaine Motions of the Stars, by Chance Are not incited, nor distracted run In a wild, loose, Arietation. Or that Heav'ns swift, un-interrupted Course Moves b'an eternall Lawes preord'red force. Or that that Cause which constant Influence To all things doth, in Earth, and Seas dispence; And those bright Sparkes (like Gems in Rings of Gold) Wee in their sev'rall Spheares inchac'd, behold; Is not the Order of some wand'ring Power. That if these things to some rash Coiture Had their convention ow'd, they had not then With such rare Artifice disposed been. That heavy Earth unmoved should behold The flying Heav'ns about her swiftly rowl'd. That Seas through Vallies spred, moisten the ground. That they t'admit increase are never found By that Accesse their Wat'ry Tribute brings From all the In-land Rivers, and fresh Springs, That from small Seeds such Mightie Bodies grow, That none ev'n of these things, which have least show Of Certaintie and most confused seeme, (As Wee, Clouds, Raine, and Thunder-Claps esteeme, Fires which with Horror blaze from Mountaines split, Earth-quakes, when she seemes shook with a Cold fit. And those tumultuous Motions, which appeare So often rais'd about this Earthly Spheare) Without a reason, (though they're thought by some The Births of suddaine violence) doe come. But have their proper Causes, well as those Which Wee, 'cause strange, Miraculous suppose. As Warme Springs are which gellid streames surround, And Islands from the Sea new rising, found. Then if one marke how the retiring Maine The shore discloses, and conceales againe; He'le thinke that the distracted Waters run As 'twere, with a blind volutation, In't one another, and againe from thence With a swift Course, and furious violence Breake forth, and with augmented Streames, retreat Unto their wonted Home, and Proper Seat. When they indeed doe by degrees increase, And to a day, or houre, grow more, or lesse, As the Moones Influence doth them despose; Govern'd by which, the Ocean ebbs, and flowes. But these Wee leave untill their due Time; since Thou doubt'st not, but complaint'st of, Providence. I'le reconcile thee to the Gods above, Who best, unto the Best of Mortalls prove. For ev'n by Natur's lawes it is withstood That good things should prove hurtfull to the Good. 'Twixt God and Good men there's a friendship layd Still Firme, by virtu's Mediation made. Did I say Friendship? An inforcive Tye Or likenesse rather, and a Sympathie. Since a Good man differs from God alone In time; his amulous Scholler, and his owne Legittimate Issue: whom that Royall Sire (Who virtuous Acts severely doth require) As Austere Parents (who make their's indure Labour and toyle) to hardship doth inure. If then the Good, (Men after Gods owne will,) Thou shalt behold to toyle, sweat, climb the Hill, And see the bad to sport with Wanton Pride Floating in Pleasures at a high Spring Tide. Thinke with thy selfe, that Wee delight to have A Modest Child, though a licencious slave. That this, too severe disciplin's restrain'd, Whilst that, in his bold liberti's maintain'd. The selfe same course thou may'st observe God take, He does no darling of a Good Man make; But tryes, and hardens, makes him Proofe 'gainst Ill; And brings him to the Bent of his owne will. PART. II. Argument. God doth good Men, (like a severe Father,) Afflictions learne to beare. Quest. How comes it that Adversitie doth then So often happen to the Best of Men? Ans. No Ill to a good Man can er'e befall, Since Contraries can never mix at All. For as the Land so many fresh Streames powres Into the Sea, the Heav'n so many showres, And yet the Saltnesse of the Ocean Can neither change, nor lessen: so, nor can His fixed Resolutions alt'red be Though storm'd on All sides by Adversitie, He's still the same, and whatsoe're ensue Be't good, or Bad, he brings to his owne Hue. Since he's above all outward Accidents; Not that I meane of these he hath no sence, But that he masters them; and with a State Compos'd, beares up against the Tyde of Fate. Counts Crosses Exercises of the Mind: For where's that man, to honest things inclin'd, Affects not lawufll labour? And's not prone To good Imployments though with hazard, knowne? And to a Soule Industrious, what lesse Then a tormenting Paine, is Idlenesse? Wee see that Wrastlers least their strength impaire, T'incounter with the strongest still prepare. Before the Combat craving from their Foes That they would them with their whole strength oppose. Enduring Stroakes, and Gripes; and if too weake One Foe they find, they more Opponents seeke. Vertue without an Adversary, pines. Then she alone in her true greatnesse shines, Then doth her value, and her strength appeare, When she by suffering shewes what she can beare. And know from me, this is a Good Mans State, Not to feare Crosses, nor complaine of Fate, Who should what ever happens to him, take As sent for good, and his advantage make. Not what, but how we suffer, is the thing. See'st not how Fathers, unlike Mothers, bring Their children up? they with an early care Them for their studies, and their Books prepare, Nor suffer them though on a Holy-day. (A time for liberty and ease) to play; But exercise in some laborious course, Sweat from their Browes, Teares from their eyes, inforce. When Mothers hug them in their Bosomes laid, Nor suffer them to stirre out of the shade, Teares, sadnesse, toyle, are things they must not know. God to Good men a Fathers minde doth snow, And loves with a more strong affection. “Let them (sayes he) that would for mine be knowne, “Bee with griefe labour, and with Crosses try'd, “That so they may be truely fortifi'd. Full Bodies languish through dull Idlenesse; Whom toyle, and their owne weight alike oppresse. Unhurt Felicity, no wound can bide; When with her Crosses she hath been us'd to chide; Then through all Injuries that Chance doth lay T'obstruct her Passage she doth force her way; Yeelds to no ills, though over-power'd by might, But on her knees, though downe, maintaines the fight. Obj. Thou wondrest God that so the Good doth love, Who would they should the best of Mortalls prove, And the most excellent, should yet by's will Make them the Exercise of Fortune still. Answ. I wonder not, if Gods with pleased eyes See great men combate with Calamities. 'Tis to our selves sometimes a pleasing sight To see a Youth with an undaunted sprite, The rough assault of some fierce Beast oppose, Or fearelesse with a raging Lion close. And so much more delightfull is the sight, As the Youth's comely, who performes the fight. These are not spectacles for Gods to see, But childish Scones of humane vanity. Behold a sight, on which as if intent On its chiefe worke, Heav'ns eye may well be bent. A sight worth Heav'n indeed; to see a minde Firmly resolv'd to adverse Fortune joyn'd; As that he scorned Fury, seem'd to brave. What nobler spectacle great Jove could have On Earth, I know not, would he daigne to looke, Then to see Cato all his Partie broke, Upright yet midd'st the Publique Ruines stand. “Though All (sayes he) now stoope to ones Command, “Though Legions guard the Land, Navies the Sea, “And 'fore our Ports Cæsar intrenched be, “Cato hath yet an Exit from all These. “And with one Hand can wheresoe're he please, “Make his rode Way to libertie. This Blade, “With blood of Civill Warre ne're guiltie made, “A brave and Noble Act at length shall doe; “On Cato now that Libertie bestow “It could not on his Country. Now the Fact “My Soule! So long premeditated act. “And snatch thy selfe out of Humanitie. “By this time Juba and Petreius be “Dispatch'd; and lye, slaine by each others Hand. “A brave, and valiant End! Yet does not stand “With our great-sould resolves: Cato his Death “As much from any scorns to aske, as Breath. Sure no small joy it in the Gods did move, Whilst they beheld him his owne Rescue prove, And as it were for others safetie lay The ground, and trace for their Escapes the Way. Whilst that last Night his studies he pursu'd. And in his sacred Brest his Sword imbru'd. Whilst h'his extracted Bowells threw about, And with his owne undaunted Hand, drew out His pious Soule, too worthy farre to feele, Or be contaminated by rude Steele. And therefore I imagine that the Wound No sure, nor Efficacious Issue found, Cato but once to see, could not suffice: The high Immortall Powers. His Faculties, And vertue therefore, still retained were, That in the hardest part they might appeare. For 'tis an Act lesse high, and great, our Breath At once to force, then to repeat our Death. Nor with unwilling Eyes, doe I suppose They saw their Son so gloriously close His Memorable Tragedy; Death then, Is but the Consecration of good Men. Whose brave and gallant Exit, justly drawes From those that tremble at it, as Applause. PART. III. Argument. Ills are not Ills to good Men meant. But are by God as Tryalls sent. Now shall the Progresse of our Worke make cleare Those are no Ills at All that so appeare. For those things you, harsh, cruell, horrid call, Were first ordain'd for them on whom they fall, And next for all Mankind, which is Heav'ns Care Farre more than any Individualls are. Next, that these things falls not against their Wills, That, did they, they deserv'd to suffer Ills. To these I'le adde that they from Fate doe flow, And to the good, by the same Rule they're so, Doe happen; therefore I perswade thee shall Never to pittie a good Man at All. He miserable sometimes may be said, But never can be miserable made. But that which We did at the first propose, Of All the rest, to prove, the Hardest showes, Which is; That for those Men, ev'n that's by Fate Ordain'd, which Wee abhorre, and tremble at. But thou wilt say, was't for their sakes ordain'd They should be banish'd? be to want constrain'd? Of Children be deprived, and of Wife? Slander'd? debarr'd the Meanes to strengthen life? If thou think'st strange this should appointed be For any; thou wilt wonder then to see Lancings, and Fire, Famine, and Thurst, to some The Instruments, and Meanes of Cure become. But when thou shalt consider that t'obtaine A Remedy; some doe indure the Paine To have their Bones be scal'd, their vaines pull'd out, And limbs lopt off, when the whole Frame's in doubt; Thou then wilt easily to this Assent, That Ills for those, on whom they fall are meant. And are for them as fit, and proper thought, As those things, which with eager longing sought, Are contrary to those they doe delight. As the raw, drunken surfets of the Night, And such like Like Luxuries, which while W'in joy Our Ruine prove, and while they please, destroy. 'Mongst All those high Expressions of his Mind Which by our good Demetrius left I find, This voice above the rest, me thinks I heare Still fresh; and smartly sounding in my Eare. “Nought then that Man can more unhappy be “Who never tasted Infelicitie. He ne're could come to try himselfe, though All Ev'n at his Wish, nay 'fore his wish befall, Yet the Impartiall Gods, of him esteem'd But hardly: that Man was ne're worthy deem'd That he should vanguish Fortune, which still flies From the most dull unactive Enemies. As though sh'had said; make him m'Antagonist, Will straight throw downe his Armes, and quit the List? Wee need not use our strength; Our threats shall chace Him hence; He dares not looke us in the face. Let's with some other Combatant joyne Hands, With one who ready to be vanquisht stands, 'Tis shame t'incounter. Gladiators will Thinke it a scorne, with those in strength and skill To them Inferiour, to contend, who know That's held but an Inglorious Overthrow Is without danger giv'n: Fortune the same Doth doe; and seekes out Combatants of Name. Passes by others in a Scorne, and slight, And the most resolute, and most upright Incounters with. On Mucius fire doth try, Upon the stayd Fabricius Poverty. By Exile 'gainst Rutilius would prevaile, And Regulus with Tortures doth assaile. Upon wise Socrates she Poison tryes, And against Cato Death it selfe imployes. All Great Examples, are b'Ill Fortune sought. Shall therefore Mucius be unhappy thought. 'Cause middst the Hostile Flames his hand he thrust? And his owne Error did conceive it just Himselfe should punish? What? 'Cause with that Hand He could not arm'd with Steele, when burnt t'a Brand, He made Porsenna flye? Or should he be Thought happier in his Mistris Brest if he His hand had cherisht? Is Fabricius found E're the lesse happy, 'cause he digg'd his ground When free from State-Affairs? Doubly ingga'd, Who warre at once with Wealth, and Pyrrhus wag'd And supp'd upon those Boots his Weeded Field Did him an aged Triumphator yeeld. Or had he more Felicitie injoy'd If with strange Fish, or forraigne Fowle h'had cloy'd And stufft his Emptie belly? Or, if t'excite The Dulnesse of his queasie Appetite H'had rak'd the upper, and the lower Sea For Shell-Fish? Or, if in large Hortyards, he Beasts of the Noblest kind had clos'd, were ta'ne With losse of many a bold Hunter slaine? Or is Rutilius unhappy? 'Cause He was condemned by the unjust Lawes And Power of those, who for that Act shall be Condemn'd themselves to all Eternitie; Cause with an ev'ner Mind he underwent His Doome, then Freedom from his Banishment? “Cause he alone great Sylla durst deny, And when call'd home againe, did farther flye? “Let those (saith he) whom thy Felicitie “Inslaves at Rome, a bloody Deluge see “I'th' Forum; and, 'bove the Servilian Lake, “(For in that Place they us'd the Spoile to take “Of those whom Sylla had proscrib'd) behold “The Heads of Senators; and Troopes of bold, “Desp'rate Assassinates, run every where “Along the streets; and thousand Romans there “After Faith giv'n, and Pledge of thy right Hand, “Nay, against Faith, butcher'd at thy Command. “Let those that cannot endure Banishment, “Be with such horrid Spectacles content. What then? Is Sylla e're the happier thought, “Cause to the Roman Forum he was brought, Guarded with Swords? and Heads of Consulls slaine He caus'd to be suspended? and the Gaine And Price of his dire Massacres he tooke By Publique Tables, and the Questors Booke? Yet All these things unquestion'd does that Man Who first brought in the Law Cornelian. Come Wee to Regulus; what hurt had he By Fortune? that, him wh'of Fidelitie The Great Example was before, she now Hath made the Arche type of Patience too Nailes pierce his skin, and though he turne him round, His wearied Body rests upon a Wound. Nor can his Eyes in sleepe be ever clos'd But to perpetuall Wakefulnesse expos'd. How much the greater Torture he sustain'd, So much the greater Glory thence he gain'd. Would'st be assur'd he not repents his Fate, To have priz'd Vertue at so high a Rate? Refresh him, send him to the Senate, there, You'l still from him the same Opinion heare. Now, does the great Mecænas therefore seeme The happier of the two in thy esteeme, 'Cause, Vext with jealous love, griev'd at the life Of his Imperious and fantastick Wife, (Which ev'ry day threaten'd to leave him) he With Musicks most delicious Harmony, Eccho'd from farre, in soft, and melting Straines, In pleasing slumbers sought to charme his Braines? Though he in flowing Bowles his sences steepe, And with the Fall of Waters, court his sleepe, As farre from rest yet on his Downe he lies, As he in Midd'st of all his Agonies. This, from his Miseries a Comfort drawes, In that he suffer'd for an honest Cause. Whilst t'other, with his lusts, and Pleasures spent, Sick of a Surfet of too much content, The Cause and Reason of his suff'rings paines Farre more, then All that he for that sustaines. Men who not yet so much inthrall'd to Vice, But if the Gods should put them to their Choice There would be more with Regulus his Fate Then to be borne unto Mæcenas state. If there be any yet dares say that he, Rather then Reg'lus, would Mæcenas be, That Man, (though to confesse it he be loath) Had rather be Terrentia, then e'm both. Do'st Socrates but hardly us'd, suppose, 'Cause he tooke off his publique-mixed Doze As 'twere a Cup of Immortalitie? And with a firme unmoved Constancy Of Mind, disputed, and discourst of Death Untill that came, and stop'd his learned Breath? Was he ill dealt with 'cause his Ice-turn'd Blood Unactive in it it's frozen Channells stood? How much more to be envy'd is his State Then their's who served are in Jewel'd Plate, To whom some old, and out-worne slave, that's brought To be at all Turnes, to beare All things taught, Poures melted Snow from out a Golden Ewre That may A Fresco to their Wine procure. Those what they drinke shall vomit up at last, And 'gainst their Wills their bitter Choller taste. When he to no such surfetings inclin'd, Shall take downe Poyson with a willing Mind. Enough of Cato; whom all Men confesse To have attain'd the hight of Happinesse. A Man whom Nature seem'd to choose, by whom She might the Worst of Terrors overcome. Of powerfull Men, heavy's the Enmitie. Yet hee'd to Pompey Cæsar, Crassus be Oppos'd: 'tis a sad thing, to see Men goe 'Bove us in Honours, in deserts below. Yet can he see Vatinius preferr'd. To be ingag'd in Civill Warres, is hard And grievous: Yet o're the whole World for Right Stoutly, though sure of Ill successe, he'd fight. To part with life seemes grievous to most Men, Yet should he do't: By this what would I then? That All might know, these are not to b'esteem'd Ills, of which, Catos selfe I worthy deem'd. PART. IV. Argument. Vertue by being opprest, is showne, Those Wee thinke Miseries, are None. Prosperitie, and happy Fortune, finds Out base, Plebean, and ungenerous Minds: But 'tis the Propertie of a Great Soule Crosses and humane Terrors to controule. To live still happy, and ne're feele no Smart, Is not to know of life the other Part. Thou'st a stout Man: But how shall this be knowne, It by some Chance thy Valour be not showne? But thou wilt say, thou went'st to play thy Prize And wert at the Olimpicke Exercise; But none besides thy selfe. The Garland gain'd Thou hast, but not the Victory obtain'd. Not as a strong Man thee I gratulate, But as if one to the Pretorian State; Or Consulship, that is arriv'd at length; Thou art increast in Honour, not in strength. The like to a good Man may be apply'd, If by no Crosses, nor Afflictions dy'd. I count thee wretched, that thou ne're were so. If ne're in all thy Life thou knew'st a Foe, None thy Abilities can judge; nor you Your selfe; can tell what 'tis your selfe can doe. Man to the knowledge of himselfe, must bring Experiment all Proofes; Triall's the Thing By which Wee learne our Strength. Some have bin known Of their owne selves t'have sought Affliction; That so their Vertues, without Exercise Obscuring, might with renew'd splendour rise. For in Adversitie Great Minds delight No lesse, then Valiant Souldiers doe in Fight. I'h've heard a Fencer in Great Caijus Raigne Thus of the scarcenesse of Rewards complaine. “How faire an Age, saith he, is lost and gone! Vertu's with greedinesse to Perills is prone. Her Race, not suff'rings, 'tis she minds: since those Th' Accomplishments of Glory are she knowes. Wounds are the Souldiers praise; who take a Pride To shew their Armes in their owne Bloods bedy'd, In some successefull Fight; And though perchance That man as much might doe, as farre advance Receiv'd no hurt, yet Wee the Wounded prize, And he it is on whom Wee fix Our Eyes. God as it were studies the good of those To whom he some fit matter doth oppose To try their Valours on. T'which we with paine And difficulty sometimes scarce attaine. A Pilot is in stormes and Tempests showne, A Generall is in a Battell knowne. How shall I know thou canst beare Poverty When thou still flow'st with Riches? Whence shall I Know with how constant, and compos'd a state Thou canst brook slanders, and the Peoples Hate, If in the Generall Plaudit thou grow old? If an affection not to be controul'd And popular opinion, and good Will Inclin'd to favour thee, attend thee still? How shall I know with what an even minde Thou Childrens losse canst beare, if none thou finde Of all thy Race impair'd? I h've heard thee, when Thou comfort'st others; but would gladly then Have seen thee to thy selfe like comfort give Or heard thee then forbid thy selfe to grieve: Be not possest with Terror of those things, Which Gods apply as the Minds spurs, not stings. Misfortune's vertues Opportunity. All men those wretched thinke deservedly, Who languish on the bed of Happinesse, Benum'd with the Torpedo of Excesse. Whom dull Tranquility, and stupid ease, Detaine like Vessells in becalmed Seas. What e're to such befalls, will strange appeare; Men unexperienc'd, Crosses hardly beare. With paine the Yoak the tender neck doth brook; Pale at the thought of Wounds raw Tyro's looke. When the old Souldier with a dauntlesse eye Viewes his owne Wounds, nor turnes his Head awry. As one, by whom that Maxime's understood He oft proves Victor who resists to bloud. Those then, whom God approves, and loves, he tries, Chastens, and hardens in Adversities. Whilst others; whom he seemes t'indulge and spare For future Miseries reserved are Thou err'st to thinke there's an exemption; Ev'n the long happy hath his Portion: Who seemes dismiss'd, is but deferr'd. Object. You'll say Why yet does God still on the best Men lay Sicknesse and Crosses? Answ. Why in Camps are put Most dangers still, on the most resolute? To beate up Quarters, Scout, or Enemies By nightly Ambuscadoes to surprize, The choicest still are sent; nor of those, one, Thinks himselfe lesse in the Opinion Of his Commander; or by that debas'd; But that his Merits are more highly grac'd. So may those say, who are those Ills design'd T'endure, seem horrors to a timerous Minde; “Worthy the love of Heav'n we now are meant, “Which by our suff'rings would experiment “How much t'is humane Nature can sustaine. Fly from enerv'd Felicity, and vaine Delights which as it were dissolve, and steep Th' inebriated Minde in a long sleep. Unlesse by chance some intervening Fate A monitory give of humane state. Whom still glasse Windowes skreen from cold and wind, Whose feet still warm'd are kept; whose roomes are lin'd With the stoves subtile circumfused Heate; To such, the aires least breath doth danger threat. Though all extreames doe hurt, there's no excesse So dangerous as that of happinesse. This foyles the understanding, and with vaine Delusive Fancies does distract the Braine; And 'fore our blinded eyes a mist doth send, They cannot Truths from Falshoods apprehend. Is it not then farre better to abide Perpetuall Crosses which to vertue guide, Then to be broken with th' excessive weight Of a too great, and a too happy state? To leaue, spare Bodies, Death scarce seems a paine; Tormenting Crudities the the Grosse sustaine. Heav'n with good men, observes the selfe same rule As Masters doe with Schollers in the Schoole; Who greater Paines, and harder Taskes on those That are the hopefullest esteem'd, impose. Think'st thou the Spartans lesse their children love Cause they by publick stripes doe use to prove Their youthfull dispositions? Parents there Their Sons exhort with courage blowes to beare Of lashing whips; and though halfe dead with paine, To persevere, and wounds on wounds sustaine. If God then, Generous spirits with severe Rough Trialls proves, why should it strange appeare? In all the Book of vertue there's not one Soft Document, or easie lesson knowne. With Fortunes whips though we be lasht, and rent, Let's bear't; 'tis our Triall, not our Punishment. Which the more often 'tis we undergoe The more prepar'd, and harier still we grow. Of all the body, that part's most obdur'd And sollid, is to constant Toyle inur'd. We should to Fortune be expos'd, that we Against her selfe, arm'd by her selfe might be. To be her equalls us in time she brings, Contempt of dangers from try'd dangers springs. So Mariners endure the Sea, and so The Plow-mans hands with labour hard'ned grow. So Souldiers learne to throw their Darts with force; So Racers prove the nimbler for the Course: Perfection and Solidity doth rise From constant and assiduous exercise. So is the Minde by Patience brought at last Contempt upon the Power of Fate to cast. Whose force we well may guesse upon the minde, When how much labour can performe, we finde In poore, and naked people, whom we see Assuming strength ev'n from their poverty. Do but consider all those Nations round, Which to the Roman Peace, prescribe a bound; I meane the Germans, and those People spread Along the Banks of Ister to his Head. To lowring skies, and Winters lasting cold Subjected still; to whom the barren Mold Scarce Food affords? to whom a Shed of Boughes A homely shelter from the Raine allowes. Who on the frozen Ister, or the Rhine Doe slide, and on the hunted Quarry dine. Dost count these men wretched in thy esteem? No Natu'rall Habit can e're wretched seem: Time by degrees does those things pleasant make, Which from Necessity their Births did take. No Houses there, no resting Place to those But such as toyle, and wearinesse impose. No food though vile, but what their Hands procure Though horrid be their Climes intemperature, Yet they goe naked; and this you suppose A Misery, is yet the Life of those. Why dost thou wonder if thou good men see Shook with the stormes of Fortune? since that Tree But weakly rooted is, nor solid growne, Hath not the frequent shocks of Tempests knowne: Which firmer still, and deeper rooting findes, The more 'tis tost and vexed with the windes; Whilst those which in the Sunny Valley grow Are weak and brittle. Good men therefore, so Are exercis'd in matters full of feare, That they might terrors without terror beare: And with calme Mindes, those things might undergoe No Ills are, but those endure them so. PART. V. Argument. For good of others, sufferers be The Good; All stoop to Destiny. And now, 'tis for the Generall end, the Best Should war, and by their Deeds their lives attest. Since 'tis God's aime, and a Wise-mans, to prove That those things which the vulgar feare, or love Are in themselves nor good, not Ill at all: For if by Heaven's Decree they doe befall To a good man, their good; but bad they are, If they're allotted to a bad mans share. Blindnesse were detestable, did we finde None lost their eyes, but those the Law made blinde, Then Appius and Metellus may want eyes. We doe not Riches as a true good prize; Ellius the Bawd may then be rich, and we, When in the Temples sacred Treasurie W'have offer'd up our consecrated gold, The same in the Burdello may behold. God cannot more mens longings vilifie Then those, the basest grant, the best deny. Obj. But you will say it seemes to you unjust The good should be opprest, imprison'd, trust. When you behold the Bad still living free In all Delights, and Sensualitie. Answ. Is it not yet as much unjust, and hard, That valiant men in Armes should nightly guard The Campe? and for defence thereof, decline No wounds, but with their Bloods make good the Line, Whilst safe i'th' Citie the spruce Gallant lies, Glor'ing in his profest Adulteries? I'st not unjust that noblest Virgins rise At Midnight, to their sacred Exercise, Whilst dissolute, and inquinated Minds, Soft, pleasing sleepe, in silken Fetters binds? Labour and Travell, still the Best assayes: The Senate oft in Councell sit whole dayes. Whilst in the Fields the meanest Groome doth please Himselfe, or in the Taverne takes his Ease, Or insome other Passe time spends his Houres. 'Tis the same in the Worlds Common Wealth, as ours. Good Men there toyle, and labour still; nor by Fortune are hall'd, but follow willingly. And keepe pace with her, and if they had knowne Her mind, perhaps they had before her gone. That gallant Speech I here to Mind recall, Did once from the great-Sould' Demetrius fall. “Of this, (you Gods!) Doe I complaine alone, “That I before, your pleasures had not knowne; “For sooner then should I have made m'Appeare, “Unto those things, which now I'm call'd to beare, “Would you my Children have? they are your due, “They were begot, and bread by me for you. “Would you some Limbe? (what here my Vow assures “Is no great thing) strait my whole Body's yours. “Would you my Soule? I shall no whit delay, “But gladly what you gave me shall repay. “What e're you aske I give you willingly, “An offering rather then Delivery. “What need y'have forc'd them from me? Now you may “Receive them; no, nor now shall take away. “Since nothing from that Man can e're be ta'en, “Who of himselfe seekes nothing to retaine. “Nought 'gainst my Will, am I compell'd to beare, “To God in love l'assent, not serve in feare. “Since I know all things move by a decree, “Sure, and enacted from Eternitie. W'are led by Fate; and his first Houre of Breath, Unto each Man prescribes his Houre of Death. Cause upon Cause depends, and all are drawne. By a long-link't Concatenation. Which therefore We should beare with courage, since Nought falls by chance, but comes by Providence. Our Joyes, and Sorrowes were long since decreed, And though the life of each Man, seeme indeed With much Varietie distinguisht; yet, There is to All, one common Period set. All W'have receiv'd is subject to decay, And Wee our selves must one day passe away. Why then doe We complaine? or fret with scorne And Indignation? We for this were borne. Nature may doe (by whom We all subsist) With her owne Compositions, as she list. Yet let us cheerefully with Minds prepar'd Thinke, that there's nothing of our owne impair'd. Quest. What is it best befits a good Mans State? Answ. To yeeld himselfe into the Hands of Fate. 'Tis no small comfort, that W'are rapt, and hurl'd About, with the same Course as the whole World. That which commands us to live thus, thus dye, Binds Heav'n by the same Necessitie. And all things humane, and Divine, doth force Along in an irrevocable Course. Who made, and rules this All, to Fate prescrib'd Lawes, yet himselfe ev'n by those Lawes is ty'd. And that which his Commands did once deliver, Now to observe he stands oblig'd for ever. Quest. Why yet by God i'th' distribution Of Fate, seemes there so much Injustice showne? That Povertie, wounds, cruell Deaths, he shov'd Assigne still for the Portions of the Good? Answ. The Workman cannot new his Matter cast; That hath the Lawes of it's Creation past. Some things will not be seperate, nor leave Others, but, as if Individualls, cleave. Those heavy Soules, who still in slumbers steepe Their drowsy Braines, and seeme awake, to sleepe; Of dull, and grosse Materialls framed are. But to the making of a Man that's rare An abler Fate's requir'd, he must not goe The plaine way, but must travell high, and low. He must with tossing stormes acquainted be, And guide his Vessell in a high-swolne Sea. Must shape his Course 'gainst Fortune; to him, shall Many a hard rough Accident befall: Yet such as he himselfe with some small paine May bring to a soft smoothnesse and make plaine. The best of Mettalls, gold, the Fire doth try; The best, and Valiant'st Men, Adversity. See but what Steeps Vertue climbs up, and sure You'l then confesse, she cannot goe secure. PART. VI. Argument. No Joyes the Bad can happy make, Nought from the good their Joyes can take. Quest. VVhy yet does God by his Eternall Will, Permit good Men to suffer any Ill? Answ. Know, he permits them not; for by his Care All evills farre from them removed are. Flagitious Crimes, foule thoughts, corrupt Desires, Blind lust, and Avarice that still aspires To be Possessor of another State; He them doth both defend, and Vindicate. Sure there is no Man at Gods hands exacts That he should beare their Budgets, and their Packs. Ev'n they themselves acquit God of that Care; By whom, all outward things contemned are. Democritus his Riches cast, since they He thought were Clogs to a good Mind, away. Wond'rest thou then if God t'a good man, shall Permit that, which himselfe desires might, fall? Obj. Of Children they're depriv'd; Answ. Why not? Since they Are mortall, and must dye themselves one day. Obj. They are exil'd: Answ. Why not? Since they sometime, Forsake ne're more to see't, their Native Clime. Obj. They're slain, Answ. Why not? Since Wee have knowne that some Unto their Deaths by their own Hands have come. Quest. Why suffer they Adversities? Answ. That so They might teach others them to undergoe. They're for Examples borne; Thinke that you heare “God say, What Cause have you that you should e're “Make your Complaints of me, you, who in Right, “And in Integritie, have tooke delight? “Others with seeming Goods I've but enrich'd; “And with a long and flattering Dreame, bewitch'd “Their vainer Minds. Gold, Silver, Iv'ry's seene “T'adorne their outsides, but no good within. “Those you count happy Men, (could but that side “Which they conceale, as that they show be spy'd) “Most miserable, filthy, sordid, are. “And like their Walls, onely on th' outside faire. “'Tis no sincere, solid Felicitie, “But thinly crusted over to the Eye. “Whilst therefore they stand sure, and as they list “Doe shew themselves; they shine as through a Mist “With larger Orbs: but if ought come that may “Disturbe their Quiets, and them open lay, “Then will appeare how much of base impure “Filth, their false boasted splendor did obscure. “True, reall Goods, and such as shall abide “I have on you bestow'd, which the more try'd “By you they shall be, and be search'd more neare, “They better still, and greater shall appeare. “Minds have I giv'n you Terrors to despise; “And loath, what most, affectionately prize. “Yours is no outward tinseld Braverie, “The goods which you adorne, turn'd inward be. “So doth the World his outward Parts despise, “And with his inward Beauty please his eyes. “The happinesse which you 'bove all possesse, “Is not to stand in need of happinesse. Ob. “But many sad, and dreadfull Accidents, “And oft intolerable Fate presents. Ans. “Since you from these could not exempted be, “I h've arm'd your mindes against adversitie. “Beare all things stoutly, by which meanes you may “Walke before God in his appointed way. “Without the suff'rance of Miseries “He is, and you, above their suff'rance rise. “Want and low Poverty, contemne, and scorne, “There's no man lives so poore as he was borne. “Dolour, and paine contemne; 'twill have an end, “Or at the worst, it you to yours will send. “Fortune despise; whose Power I have confin'd; “She hath no weapon that can wound the minde. “Nay Death it selfe; which ends, or doth translate “Your bad condition, to a better state. The few following Lines in the Close of the Originall, (being a Stoicall Exhortation to the Anticipation of Death) are purposely omitted. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>