<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Wrangham, Francis, 1769-1842</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Wrangham, Francis, 1769-1842</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">wrangham francis 1769 1842</field>
      <field name="author_text">Wrangham, Francis, 1769-1842</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1790's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.1350.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">1795</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466742</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Greek, Modern (1453- )</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Hebrew</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Italian</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Poems ; By Francis Wrangham</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Poems ; By Francis Wrangham</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poems</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poems</field>
      <field name="title_text">Poems ; By Francis Wrangham</field>
      <field name="year_display">1795</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1795</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1795</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466742&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466742&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Wrangham, Francis, 1769-1842&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;wrangham francis 1769 1842&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Poems ; By Francis Wrangham&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poems&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1795&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1795&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Wrangham, Francis&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1769&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1842&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poems&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By Francis Wrangham&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Sold by J. Mawman&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1795&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp4414&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;gre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;heb&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;ita&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;vii, 111 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poems&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By Francis Wrangham&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 88 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted; poems by other authors omitted; translations omitted; Latin verse omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">?????? ?????? ?????? ?? ????? ??????? ??????????.? (Tweddell. Prolus. viii.)</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SE questa materia non è degna, Per esser più leggieri, D'un huom che voglia parer saggio e grave, Scusatelo con questo; che s'ingegna Con questi van pensieri Fare il suo tristo tempo piu soave: Perchè altrove non ave Dove voltare il viso; Che gli è stato interciso Mostrar con altre imprese altra virtue, Non sendo premio alle fatiche sue. (Machiav. Mandrag. Prol.)</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ON these light strains should rigid Wisdom frown, And scorn a page not lustrous as her own; Ah! let her think the Muse with toys like these Sooth'd cheated care, and taught dull life to please: Think that the Bard, by fortune's hand confined, Play'd in a narrow circle of the mind; Ran all the course assign'd his powers by fate, And seized the little—when denied the great. Charles Symmons.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE RESTORATION OF THE JEWS. THE SECOND EDITION. ?Nec numina sedem Destituunt.? Claud. Bell. Get. 508. TO BASIL MONTAGU, ESQUIRE, A TRUE FRIEND (FOR HE HAS BEEN TRIED IN ADVERSITY) AND AN HONEST MAN; THE FOLLOWING POETICAL ATTEMPT IS INSCRIBED, WITH SENTIMENTS OF THE MOST-SINCERE GRATITUDE AND RESPECT, BY THE AUTHOR. ARGUMENT. Invocation:—History of the JEWS from the Exodus, under Moses; —and Joshua:—Their general depravation—followed by the Babylonish;—and the Crucifixion,—by the Roman Invasion:— Their sufferings during,—and after the siege of Jerusalem (by Titus);—and present condition.—Their fate different from that of Egypt,—Babylon,—Tyre,—and the four successive Monarchies— Assyrian, Persian, Greek, and Roman.—The question examined— whether the prophecies, relating to their Restoration, are to be figuratively,—or literally understood;—and reasons assigned for adopting the strict interpretation.—Their return:—The distinction of tribes superseded by the coming of the MESSIAH.— Conclusion.To that great day—when, link'd in holy bond Fraternal, Idumæa's favour'd tribes Their Salem shall revisit; from the dust In prouder state to rear the fallen dome, And bid th' aspiring pinnacle o'ertop Its antient elevation—I attune Th' ambitious string. Thou, Moses (as of yore Through Egypt's parting waves with heaven-lent power Thou bor'st the chosen multitude, what time His cumber'd wheel along the faithless track Busiris urg'd; while round his troubled host, Scath'd by JEHOVAH's terror-flashing eye, The watery ruin roar'd) Thyself a bard, Inspire the Muse; that with prophetic strain Would hail their second Exodus, and wake For future years the high triumphant song. Fain would the Poet tell, what oft his ear Has caught with rapture, how by Thee convey'd Twice twenty summers they their long array Wound through the intricate and perilous path; When with impendent pillar, 'mid the wild Unbroken solitudes, the daily cloud And flame nocturnal mark'd th' uncertain way Alternate: Gushing from the riven flint, In lavish pride, how new-born torrents pour'd Their liquid health; and, by circumfluous night Shrouded from glance profane, th' ALMIGHTY trac'd With his own finger on the two-leav'd stone His double law: Upon its Lord's descent How th' empyréan bow'd, and 'neath his feet Spread darkness: while the consecrated hill, Guarded by death, even to its rocky base Shook with strange weight; and lurid lightnings, hurl'd In awful splendour through the deep obscure, Announc'd a present Deity: How vain This prodigal magnificence of Heaven; Its record soon by novelty's young hand Ras'd from man's careless heart: How two alone Caleb and Joshua, Numb. xiv. 30. xxvi. 65. Surviv'd the lingering maze; and Thou, even Thou, As burst the glorious vision on thy view Of Israel's destin'd heritage, wert doom'd To sleep within an undiscover'd tomb; Though six-score winters fail'd to chill thy blood, And quench thy beaming eye:—O'er all this field, Sown with bright miracles, the verse would range; If verse were equal to the dazzling toil. Keen was the sword, and more than mortal proof, That Joshua wielded when from their huge cliffs He swept the Anakim: The Sun stood still, His punctual course remitting in mid sky; And night's pale Sovereign check'd her rapid orb, To aid the mighty task. Before him sunk Devoted Canaan, with unhallow'd gore Moistening the ground: Not infancy its years, Nor kings their purple rescued; undiscern'd, Amid the common carnage, they expir'd By hostile hands—unsung, unwept, unknown. As some tall vine, whose blushing fruitage glows Beneath the lustre of the noon-tide ray, Long Israel flourish'd; 'till, by gradual shade Darken'd to deepest crimson, guilt provok'd Th' OMNIPOTENT's accumulated ire, And urg'd his bolt. Upon the double throne Sat rash Rebellion, ever prompt to burst From duty's guidance: Sion's dames were fair, But frail as fair; such, Albion, thine (if thine Rightly the bard hath noted) mirror-taught To roll th' obedient eye, and court the glance Of staggering triflers, or with zoneless waist Rouse the lascivious fire: The following Sonnet was written soon after the poem made its first appearance; and, notwithstanding the terrible denunciation of a friend (viz. “that it might perhaps make my peace with one of “the sex, at the expence of irretrievably offending all the rest”) I am unwilling to omit this opportunity of introducing it. To MYRA. What! Though of Albion's dames the Poet sung That, frail as fair, with artificial glance They roll'd th' obedient eye; and 'mid the dance Guileful upon the staggering trifler hung: He then nor knew, fond bard! the modest grace Of Myra's frame; nor haply then divin'd That Nature e'er had link'd so fair a face, In bond harmonious, with so pure a mind. Ah! Had he still in error persever'd! Still cherish'd his mistake! Now doom'd to pine, By viewing in that angel form of thine A more than angel's chastity inspher'd, Fatal discovery! from thy bright eyes And brighter soul he learns his guilt—and dies. There Avarice ground The face of Indigence; the Slanderer there Wove the false tale; and rob'd Devotion paid The homage of the lip, intent with prayer To mask or hallow crimes. Then GOD's wak'd wrath, Gigantic and impatient of delay, Sped its vast vengeance from the eastern sky: Onward by Jordan's stream in mournful line The exiles move, with oft-reverted look Sadly solicitous once more to view Deserted Salem; ere her lessening hills With dubious image cheat their earnest sight: The haughty Babylonian stalks around, And in proud mockery taunts the patriot tear. But happier They, who on the bending tree Hung 'mid the victor's scoffs the silent harp, Than Those who stoop'd beneath the arm of Rome! When seventy suns had fill'd their annual course, Chaldæa's vassals saw the righteous shrine Flame with its wonted incense: On their sons, Mark'd out for heavier woe, more fiercely rose The Flavian Star, and glar'd with redder fires. Oh! Might the Muse attempt the lofty theme Of Glory's King on Calvary for man Offering Himself (nor less than He could make Th' accepted sacrifice) while Nature mourn'd The monstrous guilt; and Earth in wild alarm Receiv'd within her agitated breast Its transient Inmate!—Hopeless wish! Dismay'd From the bold flight she turns, nor dares advance Her pinion to the sun: Else would she sing Th' offence, with all the sorrows which ensued; Sorrows so merited, that even the Youth Of proverb'd Titus, for his humanity denominated Deliciæ humani generis. Suet. in Tit. I. mercy steel'd his gentle breast. Swift as the eagle, The circumstantial agreement of the Mosaic prophecies (particularly Deut. xxviii. 49,57.) with the events, as detailed by Josephus in his narrative of the sufferings sustained by the Jews during the siege, has not escaped the observation of Bishop Newton; who remarks, in his Dissertations on the Prophecies, vol. i.p.102, &amp;c. that, though a great part of those predictions was accomplished at the time of the Babylonish captivity, they were all more amply fulfilled under the Roman invasion. Of the famine indeed of the latter period, the Jewish Historian has left us a very dreadful account; and, from its exact concurrence with prophecy, we know to how much faith it is entitled. minister of Heaven, He comes; with meagre Famine ???????? ???? ??????, ??? ?????? ???????, ??? (?? ???????????) ??????? ?????? ????????? ?? ????? ??? ???????? ??? ??????. Joseph. Bell. Jud. v. 10. 3. ??? ?? ??? ??? ????? ??????????? ???? ??? ????? ??????? ??? ?????? ?? ??????. vi. 3. 3. in his train, And fire-rob'd Desolation. Faint and pale, In his poor boy th' unnatural father sheaths His frantic blade: And, deed of sadder note! She, whose proud foot disdain'd the vulgar ground, Deut. xxviii. 56, 57. — ??? ????? ??? ??????? ????????? ????????, ?? ??? ????? ?????????? ?? ?? ?????? ???????????? ?????????. Id. ib. vi. 3. 4. Grasping her infant (with far other joy Than other days bestow'd) in its young heart Plunges the murderous knife, and glows afresh With guilty health. Twice fifty myriads fell— ??? ?? ??????????? ???? ????? ??? ??????????(???????)???????? ?????? ??? ????. Id. ib. vi. This account is confirmed by Zonaras and Jornandes, who agree in relating that 1100000 (men, women, and children) perished during the siege by famine, disease, and the sword. Omnes (says Lipsius in his notes to Tacitus, Hist, V. 13.) undecies centena millia periisse obsidione illâ clarè tradunt, fame, morbo, Jerro. Happy ???? ???? ?????? ????????????, ???? ??? ????? ??????? ????? ?????? ????? ??????????????? ????????, ???? ??? ???? ??? ????? ????? ??????? ?????????????. Joseph. vi. 3. 4. and vii. 8. 7. to lose in death the maddening sense Of Hebrew ignominy! They nor saw The Latian spoiler revel on the wealth Of their sack'd fane (as from the holy gold For his own Deities with curious zeal He cull'd the votive gift) nor, 'mid the crash Of sinking palaces, with anguish heard The shriek of female frenzy: Who surviv'd, Doom'd to transmit beneath another sun The attachment of the Jews to their country, so pathetically described in the hundred and thirty-seventh Psalm, is confirmed by Tacitus (Hist. V. 13.)—ac, si transferre sedes cogerentur, major vitæ metus quàm mortis. Hereditary servitude, beheld In long succession rising to the view Unpitied millions destin'd to bewail Paternal crime and errors not their own. Still as the lucid harbinger of day Gives to their anxious eye his courted beam, They sigh for evening; with the eve's wan star Comes its peculiar sorrow. Numerous still Of their present numbers Basnage (who has written a history of the Jews, as a supplement and continuation of the history of Josephus) observes—“that it is impossible indeed to fix it; but “that we have reason to believe there are still near 3000000 of “people who profess this religion, and (as their phrase is) are “witnesses of the unity of God in all the nations of the world.” As sands, which pillow Ocean's hoary head, They thrive by grief and grow beneath the sword. Past is the fame of Egypt; whose pale son Erst by the midnight lamp, with learned toil Skilful to wind the hieroglyphic maze, Por'd on the treasur'd page by double fate The library of Alexandria was founded by the first Ptolemies, and gradually enlarged to 700000 volumes; 400000 of which were lodged in that quarter of the city called Bruchion, and the remaining 300000 within the Serapeum. The first part was casually destroyed by fire, when Julius Cæsar was making war upon the place; but restored in number by Antony's munificent present, of the Pergamean library, to Cleopatra: the whole were afterwards burnt by the command of Omar the Caliph. Denied to future times. With prone descent Great Babylon is fallen; amid the dust, Vainly inquisitive, the traveller pries In fruitless search where Syrian Belus rear'd His idol form: No human trace around Bishop Newton proves (vol. i. pp. 174. 177. &amp;c.) by copious extracts from six or seven modern writers of eminence that the present desolate state of Babylon, Egypt, Tyre, &amp;c. fulfils, with a melancholy degree of exactness, the prophecies of the Old Testament relative to their ultimate condition. Instructs his doubtful step; no friendly tone Breaks the disastrous silence. At the hiss Of serpents haply rustling through the brake, As parch'd by tropic fire and wild with thirst Their sanguine eye-balls Postquam exusta palus terræque ardore dehiscunt, Exsilit in siccum; et flammantia lumina torquens Sævit agris, asperque siti atque exterritus æstu. Virg. Georg. III. 432, &amp;c.???????????? ?????????? ?? ??????.44 Æschyl. Sept. contra Theb. 383. flash, his sinking heart Beats with thick fear: Meanwhile the bittern moans In hollow-sounding note; and the lone owl, Dusky and slow, with inauspicious scream Adds horror to the gloom. Beneath the waves Old Tyre is whelm'd, and all her revelry: Those hosts, who barter'd Israel's sons for gold (The Traffickers of blood) no more renew Th' abhorred merchandize; no more with glance Of keen remark compute the sinew's force, Or weigh the muscles of their fellow-man. And thou bethink thee, Albion, ere too late, Queen of the isles and mart of distant worlds, That thou like Tyre (with hands as deep in blood, Warm from the veins of Africa, and wealth By arts more vile and darker guilt acquir'd) Shalt meet an equal doom. The day will rise, If Justice slumber not, when those proud ships— The grace at once and bulwark of thy coast, That now 'mid baffled tempests range the globe— Unequal to a foe so oft engag'd, So oft subdued, shall through their yawning sides Receive the victor main; and in th' abyss Thy cliffs shall sink, their chalky tops alone Extant above the brine: While, as from far Across the wintry waste the seaman views The humid net outspread, his piteous heart (Piteous, though rugged) sorrows o'er thy fate. This traffic is however still patronised by the British Senate; and its continuance was voted, March 16, 1796, by a majority of—four!!!! The following lines, by an anonymous writer, upon that event (transcribed from the Cambridge Intelligencer, March 19.) possess very considerable merit:Did then the bold Slave rear at last the sword Of vengeance? Drench'd he deep its thirsty blade In the foul bosom of his tyrant Lord? Oh! Who shall blame him? Through the midnight shade, Still on his tortur'd memory rush'd the thought Of every past delight—his native grove, Friendship's best joys, and liberty, and love: All lost—for ever! Then remembrance wrought His soul to madness: 'round his restless bed Freedom's pale spectre stalk'd, with a stern smile Pointing the wounds of slavery; the while She shook her clanking chains, and hung her head. No more he pours to heaven his suppliant breath, But sweetens with revenge the draught of death. With angry beam the conquerors of mankind, Like woe-denouncing comets, blaz'd awhile In evanescent glory. He, whose foot Trampled upon Assyria's subject neck, Fled from the Greek: To Rome's imperious race Greece bent the suppliant knee: The Roman bow'd Before the Goth: On rude Germania's brow Shines Cæsar's diadem; and priests preside Where war's stern child, his limbs in steel encas'd, Frown'd fierce defiance on th' embattled world. Nor Thou with sceptic arrogance enquire Where Israel's relics rest; or how, recall'd To repossession of their native seat, His dissipated tribes the glad behest Shall hear, and how obey: So may'st thou dare To question GOD's omnipotence, and ask How wake the dead. The same Almighty Word, Which summon'd into being and dissolv'd The hallow'd polity, in pristine form (At his appointed time) When the times of the Gentiles shall be fulfilled (Luke xxi. 24.) or—as St. Paul expresses it—when the fulness of the Gentiles shall be come in, the fulness of the Jews also shall come in, and all Israel shall be saved (Rom. xi. 12.25.26.) that is, says Newton, II.70. when the times of the four great kingdoms of the Gentiles, according to Daniel's prophecies, shall be expired, and the fifth kingdom (or the kingdom of CHRIST) shall be set up in their place; and the Saints of the Most High shall take the kingdom, and possess the kingdom for ever, even for ever and ever (Dan. vii. 18.) But these prophecies have not yet received their full and entire completion; our SAVIOUR hath not yet had the uttermost parts of the earth for his possession (Psalm xi. 8.) All the ends of the world have not yet turned unto the Lord (xxii. 27.) All people, nations, and languages, have not yet served him (Dan. vii. 14.) neither are the Jews yet made an eternal excellency, a joy of many generations (Isai. lx. 15.) The time is not yet come, when violence shall no more be heard in their land, wasting and destruction within their borders (18.) GOD's promises (Ezek. xxxviii. 21.25. xxxix. 28,29.) are not yet made good in their full extent; however, what hath been already accomplished is a sufficient pledge and earnest of what is yet to come. We have seen the prediction of Hosea, who prophesied before the captivity of the ten tribes of Israel (iii.4.5) fulfilled in part, and why should not we believe that it will be fulfilled in the whole? 1,137,138. This event will take place (Newton afterwards observes, II. 395, &amp;c.) about the time of the fall of the Othman empire (denoted by Ezekiel's Gog and Magog) and of the Christian Antichrist (referred to Dan. xi. 46. and xii. 7.) Then, in the full sense of the words, shall the kingdoms of this world become the kingdom of our Lord, and of his Christ; and He shall reign for ever and ever (Rev. xi. 15.—See also xx. 4. &amp;c. and Dan. vii. 26, 27.) About the particulars of that kingdom our prudence and modesty are equally concerned to forbear inquiry; as they are points which the HOLY SPIRIT hath not thought fit to explain, and of which the perfect comprehension may perhaps constitute a part of the happiness of that period. shall re-unite Its scatter'd parts; No feebler power may raise The ruin'd pile. This hapless Julian knew; When urg'd by pride the rash Apostate toil'd, With puny effort, so perchance to thwart MESSIAH's plan: Him hurl'd from central depths By arm divine the conglobated fire Repell'd Vid. Julian. Epist. xxv. ???????? ?? ?????. Ambitiosum quoddam apud Hierosolymam templum, quod post multa et interneciva certamina obsidente Vespasiano posteaque Tito ægrè est expugnatum, instaurare sumptibus cogitabat immodicis:—Metuendi globi flammarum propè fundamenta crebris assultibus erumpentes fecêre locum, exustis aliquoties operantibus, inaccessum; hocque modo elemento destinatiùs repellente, cessavit inceptum. Amm. Marcell. xxiii. 1., as oft his daring hand resum'd Th' abortive work. Whether (as some suppose In light conjecture) the prophetic song, Glittering with eastern metaphor, expect Its certain end in New Jerusalem— Holiest of cities; or (as others frame The surer inference, with scripture's voice Combining circumstance) shall in the Old Meet strict accomplishment: For still Vide Hartley's Observations on Man, p. 11. iv. §.2. Prop. clxxxii. where, besides these two arguments in favour of the Restoration of the Jews to Palestine, viz. I. That the predictions have never yet been adequately fulfilled of any Jews; and II. That the ten Tribes or Israelites, carried away captive by Shalmaneser (II Kings xviii.2.) have never yet been restored at all, he alleges III. That a double return seems to be foretold in several prophecies; IV. That the prophets, who lived since the return from Babylon, have predicted a return in terms similar to those who went before; whence it follows that both classes must refer to some Restoration yet future; and, V. That the Restoration of the Jews to their own land seems to be foretold also in the New Testament. To these arguments, drawn from prophecy, he adds some concurrent evidences suggested by their existing circumstances: 1. That they are yet distinct from all the nations amongst which they reside; 2. That they are to be found dispersed in all the countries of the known world; 3. That, having no inheritance of land in any country, their property (money and jewels, &amp;c.) admits of being easily transferred to Palestine; 4. That they are treated with contempt and cruelty every where; 5. That they correspond with one another throughout the world; 6. That most of them, by the Rabbinical Hebrew, have an universal medium of communication; and, 7. That they still hope and expect themselves to be RESTORED This Restoration (he subjoins) may alarm mankind, and open their eyes; while, by affording an opportunity of a careful survey of Palestine, it may prove the genuineness and divine authority of the Scriptures. Pistorius, a Norwegian (in his notes and additions to Hartley, i. p. 706. &amp;c.) after expressing his doubts of the destruction of all the present powers of the earth “by a fifth Monarchy or Millen-“nium,” &amp;c. proceeds to vindicate the expectation of a future general Conversion and gathering of the Jews into the Church of CHRIST; proving, by many incontestable arguments, that Rom. xi.26. cannot be understood of a spiritual Israel, or as having happened long ago: About their Restoration to Palestine he is less certain. they lack Completion; Shalmaneser's captives still, Haply in Arsareth with frequent prayer Solicit Heaven to guide their wandering foot To human haunt II Esdr. xiii. 40,41. 45.&amp;c.: Still, though dispers'd, distinct— So GOD pronounc'd—by no mild offices Of Gentile courtesy attach'd abroad, With wealth unfasten'd to an alien soil, They still articulate Judæa's tones; Still pant in patriot sympathy; and still The hope of Restoration gilds the gloom Of present banishment: With brighter hues Glows the gay vision 'mid their long dark night, And borrows brilliance from surrounding shade. And see! They come! Survey yon sweeping bands; Countless as Perfian bowmen, who beset Freedom exulting on her Attic rock; When Asia rous'd her millions to the war, And sunk in all her pomp before the foe Her vengeance fondly doom'd. With ranks as full, But with more prosperous fates and purer joys Than swell the warrior's breast, their destin'd march The Hebrews bend, from where Hydaspes rolls His storied tide; or cleave with holy prow Th' Atlantic main, whose conscious surge reveres Its buoyant load. No Spaniard plunderers they, Allur'd by gold (whom will not gold allure?) With dauntless foot to traverse new-found realms, And plunge the wondering savage in the mine, Where—guiltless then—the unsunn'd mischief slept: No mad crusaders, by the Roman priest Baptiz'd Invincible, with impious zeal To combat Hali's turban'd race; and wade A second time to Palestine through blood: But call'd by GOD or from the western stream Of Plata, or where Ganges pours his urn, In love-knit league they throng. With guardian hand MESSIAH, erst their nation's deadliest hate, Guides the returning host; and high in air Waves the bright ensign of the Cross, that once Led on th' Imperial Christian to the sight, And to his shrinking legions gave the field. Separate no more their tribes: His scepter'd pride Judah resigns; and Levi's hallow'd sons Renounce the ephod, prompt in earlier times To purge the public stain: For now they own Their SHILOH come; nor longer, idly vain, Assert the useless privilege of birth. Then shall some patriot bard, to cheer their way, With magic touch explore the trembling strings, And breathe the sacred harmony around; While, with past solitude contrasting still Present society (so sweeter deem'd) He cheats the summer day of half its hours: Oft, to the harp in tuneful concert join'd, Swells the glad voice; and oft, as on the ear The music falls, they move in measur'd step Responsive; while the joyous sounds deceive Their lifted foot, and steal it from its toil. Then too, as bursts upon his age-worn sight The dazzling blaze of prophecy fulfill'd, Shall some rapt Simeon raise the grateful song And hail th' accomplishment: “LORD, now dismiss'd “In peace thy servant sleeps; his eyes have seen “ISRAEL restor'd, and all thy people bless'd.” THE DESTRUCTION OF BABYLON. ?Sævior armis Luxuria incubuit.? Juv. Sat. vi. 292. TO GEORGE SMITH, ESQUIRE, AS A TOKEN OF GRATITUDE FOR FAVOURS (AT ONCE GREAT AND SEASONABLE) WHICH THE AUTHOR FEARS HE MAY NEVER BE ABLE TO ACKNOWLEDGE IN ANY MORE EFFECTUAL MANNER, THE FOLLOWING POETICAL ATTEMPT IS RESPECTFULLY INSCRIBED. ARGUMENT. Exordium.—Time of the Destruction of Babylon (seventy years after “the carrying away of the Jews”)—Cyrus conquers Sardis; —and diverts the Euphrates.—Belshazzar's Feast.—The army of Medes and Persians, under the conduct of two Babylonians (Gobryas and Gadatas) enters the city, along the channel of the river.—The capture—and present state of Babylon.—Address to Rome,—and London.—Conclusion.And art Thou then for ever set! Thy ray No more to rise and gild the front of day, Far-beaming The classical reader will not be sorry to find a conjecture of the learned Gilbert Wakefield, on the passage (Isai, xiv. 12.) whence this metaphor is taken, transcribed from his notes on Virg. Georg. ii. 97. which reflects great credit upon his ingenuity and erudition. “—Thou that didst subdue the nations!” —Quâ proprietate de stellâ matutinâ prædicari potest, illam subigere nationes: Nos sanè—quibus Hebræi textûs (præsertim in Prophetis et Hagiographiâ) penè infinitas corruptiones, veterum versiones tractantibus, notare contigit—minimè dubitamus errorem sublatere, ab inverso literarum ordine (ut solet) profluentem; quod minùs illi mirabuntur, qui L. Capelli de his rebus librum evolverunt. Pro voce [HEBREW], quæ nihili est, substituimus [HEBREW] vel [HEBREW], mittens, quæ mittebas; aut etiam [HEBREW], mittebaris. ???? ? emendationis nostræ fautores tibi exhibemus, qui habent ? ?????????? ??? ????? ?? ????? Hi igitur in exemplaribus suis legisse videntur [HEBREW], qui mittebas per omnes gentes. Ad hunc demum modum totam clausulam libentissimè refingeremus (et harum rerum æquos æstimatores fortiter appellamus; cæteros enim, in Hebræis literis planè hospites, nihil moramur nec nucis vitiosæ facimus) [HEBREW] qui lucem mittebas per omnes gentes. Nihil elegantius, aut quod Hebraicæ poësis concinnitatem pleniùs sapiat: nihil denique Prophetâ maximè sublimi dignius, &amp;c. Babylon? Those massive gates, Through which to battle rush'd a hundred states; That cloud-topt wall, along whose giddy height Cars strove with rival cars in fearless flight— What! Could not all protect thee? Ah! In vain Thy bulwarks frown'd defiance o'er the plain: Fondly in antient majesty elate Thou sat'st, unconscious of impending fate: Nor brazen gates, nor adamantine wall, Could save a guilty people from their fall. Was it for this those wondrous turrets rose, Which taught thy feebled youth a scorn of foes? For this that earth her mineral stores resign'd; And the wan artist, child of sorrow, pin'd: Destin'd, as Death crept on with mortal stealth, And the flush'd hectic mimick'd rosy health; 'Mid gasping crowds to ply th' incessant loom, While morbid vapours linger'd in the gloom? Silent for seventy years, its frame unstrung, On Syrian bough Judæa's harp had hung: Deaf to their despots' voice, her tribes no more Wak'd Sion's music on a foreign shore; But oft, his tide where broad Euphrates rolls, Felt the keen insult pierce their patriot souls: And still, as homeward turn'd the longing eye, Gush'd many a tear and issued many a sigh. Yet not for ever flows the fruitless grief! Cyrus and Vengeance fly to their relief. Mark where He comes, th' Anointed of the Lord! And wields with mighty arm his hallow'd sword. Reluctant realms their sullen homage pay, As on the heaven-led hero bends his way: Opposing myriads press the fatal plain, And Sardis bars her two-leav'd brass in vain; Her secret hoards the hostile bands unfold, And grasp with greedy joy the cavern'd gold. Then to new fields they urge their rapid course, And rebel states augment the swelling force: Firm to their end 'mid scenes of rural love, Unsoften'd by those scenes, the victors move: And, as in lengthening line their ranks expand, Spread wider ruin through the ravag'd land. But Babylon th' approaching war derides, And shakes the harmless battle from her sides. In vain the ram its vigorous shock applies; The mines descend, th' assailing towers arise: Till Treason comes the baffled chief to aid, And briefer arts succeed the long blockade. With hardy sinew Persia's labouring host Wrest the huge river from his native coast; And bid his flood its wonted track forego, 'Twixt other banks through lands unknown to flow. The task is done; and with obsequious tides Euphrates follows, as a mortal guides: His surgeless channel, now a pervious vale, Invites the foot where navies spread the sail; And soon no barrier, but the eastern main, Shall bound the conqueror's progress or his reign. Thus, when from heaving Ætna's restless caves Impetuous Fire precipitates his waves, The flaming ruin rushes on the plain; And art and nature rear their mounds in vain. Should some high-rampir'd town obstruct his course, The red invader rises in his force: Swells with dread increase o'er the adverse towers, Then furious on the prostrate city pours; And scornful of the check, and proudly free, Extends his blazing triumph to the sea: With refluent stream the straiten'd billows flow, And yield new regions to th' insatiate foe. Yet naught devoted Babylon alarms; Domestic treason, or a world in arms. 'Mid her gay palaces and festal bowers Flutter'd in sportive maze the rose-crown'd hours: Loud burst the roar of merriment around, While wanton dance light tripp'd it o'er the ground; When, bent the long-drawn revelry to spy, Hush'd in grim midnight Vengeance hover'd nigh. Nor vain her care; by wine's soft power subdued The courtly troop with gladden'd eye she view'd: The frantic mob in drunken tumult lost, The drowsy soldier nodding at his post, The gate unclos'd, the desert wall survey'd; And called her Cyrus to unsheath his blade. Quaff then, Belshazzar—quaff, Imperial Boy, The luscious draught and drain the maddening joy; To equal riot rouse thy languid board, And bid the Satrap emulate his Lord. With pencil'd lids —???????????? ??? ???????? ???????? ??? ???????? ???????? ?. ?. ?. Xenoph. ?. ?. ? Ambitiosam hanc ornatûs rationem gentes Orientales, in luxum effusiores, excogitârunt. Ita olim Jezebelem, ut regiam præ se ferret gravitatem, oculos fuco ornâsse legimus, II Reg. ix. 30. Ad quem locum lxxii. habent ??????????? ???? ?????????, i. e. stibio depinxit: Hoc enim lapide ideò in pingendis oculis homines decoris nimiùm studiosi utebantur, quòd eos non nigravit tantùm sed etiam dilatavit: &amp;c. (Hutchinson. ad loc.) —“Ob vim nempè astringendi (?????????) contrahebat palpebras, et adeò oculos ipsos dilatabat.” Zeun., the scandal of their race, Thy crowded halls a thousand princes grace: Ill on such legs the warrior greaves appear, Ill by such hands is grasp'd the deathful spear; Fitter 'mid Syria's harlot train to move, And wage in safer fields the wars of love. Alternate rang'd (with faces not more fair, Nor hearts more soft) that harlot train is there: The virgin's wish her half-clos'd eyes impart, And blushless matrons boast th' adulterous heart; On ardent wing the rank contagion flies, Sigh heaves to sigh and glance to glance replies. Let these th' achievements of thy Gods rehearse, Raise the lewd hymn and pour th' unholy verse; Proceed! With sacrilege enhance thy wine! Let the vase circle, torn from Salem's shrine. Empire and wealth for thee unite their charms; For thee bright beauty spreads her willing arms: Who shall control thy raptures, or destroy? Give then the night, the poignant night, to joy. Ha! Why that start! Those horror-gleaming eyes! That frozen cheek, whence life's warm crimson flies! That lip, on which th' unfinish'd accents break! Those hairs, erect with life! Those joints, that shake! The wondrous hand, which stamps yon wall with flame, Speaks the fear just that labours in thy frame; As round it sheds self-mov'd the living ray, Which mocks the lustre of thy mimic day. Haste! Call thy seers; or, if their skill be vain, Let Daniel's art the threatful lines explain: Haste! For the prophet bring the scarlet vest; If so, seduc'd, his words may sooth thy breast. Ah! no: That phantom with the style of fate Inscribes the doom of thee, thy race, thy state. In curses then, rash Youth, the hour upbraid; When first, by pleasure's meteor beam betray'd, From virtue's path thy heedless foot declin'd, And whelm'd in sordid sense the devious mind. In vain! Even now is wrought the deed of death: This moment ends thy glories and thy breath! Above, beneath thee feasts th' insatiate worm; Completes the murderer's rage, and dissipates thy form. See where, twin sons of Vengeance and Despair, March Gobryas and Gadatas: Hold, rash pair; 'Tis parricide! Can nothing then atone Your private wrongs, save Babylon undone? As monarchs smile or frown, shall patriot fire With docile fervour flourish or expire? No: When th' insulting Mede is at your gates, And your pale country shakes through all her states; For her your cherish'd enmity forego, To wreak its fury on the public foe: Renounce the hoarded malice of your breast, And only struggle—who shall serve her best. Hark! 'Tis the cry of conquest! Full and clear Her giant voice invades the startled ear; With death's deep groans the shouts of triumph rise: The mingled clamour mounts the reddening skies. From street to street the flames infuriate pour, Climb the tall fane and gild the tottering tower: In cumbrous ruin sink patrician piles, And strew amid the dust their massive spoils; While, with stern forms dilating in the blaze, Danger and Terror swell the dire amaze. Now yield those Gods, whom prostrate realms ador'd: Though Gods, unequal to a mortal sword! In awless state th' unworshipp'd idols stand, And tempt with sacred gold the plunderer's hand. Now bend those groves, whose sloping bowers among The Attic warbler trill'd her changeful song: Their varied green where pensile gardens spread, And Median foliage lent its grateful shade: There oft, of courts and courtly splendour tir'd, The fragrant gale Assyria's “Amyitis, the wife of Nebuchadnezzar, having been “bred in Media (for she was the daughter of Astyages, king “of that country) had been much taken with its mountainous and “woody parts, and therefore desired to have something like it at “Babylon; and, to gratify her herein, was the reason of erecting “this monstrous piece of vanity.” (Prideaux's Conn. of Hist. of O. and N. Test. I. p. 102. For an account of these hanging gardens, the walls, tower, &amp;c. of Babylon, see Id. ib. pp. 94-105.Queen respir'd; With blameless foot through glades exotic rov'd, And hail'd the scenes her happier prime had lov'd. Now stoops that tower, from whose broad top the eye Of infant Science pierc'd the midnight sky; First dar'd 'mid worlds before unknown to stray, Scann'd the bright wonders of the milky way; And, as in endless round they whirl'd along, In groups arrang'd and nam'd the lucid throng: Nay, in their glittering aspects seem'd to spy The hidden page of human destiny! Vain all her study! In that comet's glare, Which shook destruction from its horrid hair, Of her sage train deep-vers'd in stellar law Not one his country's hapless fate foresaw; No heaven-read priest beheld the deepening gloom, Or with prophetic tongue foretold her doom. Vocal no more with pleasure's sprightly lay Her fretted roofs shall Babylon display; No more her nymphs in graceful band shall join, Or trace with flitting step the mazy line: But here shall Fancy heave the pensive sigh, And moral drops shall gather in her eye; As 'mid her day-dreams distant ages rise, Glowing with nature's many-colour'd dies: Resound the rattling car, th' innumerous feet, And all the tumult of the breathing street; The murmur of the busy, idle throng; The flow of converse, and the charm of song Sir Brook Booth by in his Answer to Burke, speaking of the reflections that will suggest themselves upon the view of Versailles in its present condition, has the following fine passage: “The silence “will be disturbed by sounds, that are no longer heard; and the “solitude peopled by the brilliant forms, that shall no longer glide “over its polished floors.”:— Starting she wakes, and weeps as naught she sees Save trackless marshes and entangled trees: As naught she hears, save where the deathful brake Rustling betrays the terrors of the snake; Save, of the casual traveller afraid, Where the owl screaming seeks a dunner shade; Save where, as o'er th' unsteadfast fen she roves, The hollow bittern shakes th' encircling groves. Hear then, proud Rome, and tremble at thy fate! The hour will come, nor distant is its date (If right was caught the prophet's mystic strain, Which aw-struck Patmos echoed o'er the main) The hour, which holy arts in vain would stay, That prone on earth thy gorgeous spires shall lay; And, with their vain magnificence, destroy Thy long illusion of imperial joy. And thou, Augusta, hear “in this thy day;” For once, like thee, lost Babylon was gay: With thee wealth's taint has seiz'd the vital part, As once with her, and gangrenes at the heart. Profusion, Avarice, flying hand in hand, Scatter prolific poisons o'er the land; The teeming land with noxious life grows warm, And reptile mischiefs on its surface swarm:— Like hers, or deaf or faithless to the vow Of honest passion are thy daughters now: With well-feign'd flame th' obedient maidens wed, If wealth or birth adorn the venal bed; —“I understand that in this island of Great Britain, at the time “I am now writing, Birth is the first virtue and Money the “second: Some indeed may dispute the precedence; but all will “allow that one or both are sine quâ nons, without which virtue is “not.” Hermsprong, II. p. 205. The novel whence this description of female interestedness is taken, exhibiting Man as he is not, proceeds from the same pen which about four years ago produced Man as he is: They are both works of extraordinary merit. In this character even their “twenty thousand fair readers” (notwithstanding the above extract) will, I doubt not, feel themselves disposed by the innocent bribery of a more conciliating quotation to concur very cordially: —“We are, like unhallowed satirists, involving in one promiscuous “censure all the fair daughters of men. Let us be more just. They “are our equals in understanding, our superiors in virtue: They “have foibles, where men have faults; and faults, where men have “crimes: In the gaiety of conversation it may be allowed (and— “the author might have added—in the fervour of poetry, of which “Synecdoche is a principal figure) at least it will be assumed, to put “the whole for a part, perhaps a small part; but it would be wise in “man, when he makes the errors of woman his contemplation, not “to forget his own.” II.p.175. For the subjoined sonnet on The Corruption of Manners, which seems not inapposite to this place, I am indebted to the friendship of C. Marsh, Esq. of the Temple. TYRANT of pomp, and pride! Chill'd by whose sway Youth's blossoms fade; and all that fancy wrought— The towering fabric of exalted thought; And human mind, that cleaves to heaven its way: Thou smil'st, that Britain's nervous race decay; Tho' once in virtue's brightest fields they fought, Tho' once their blood a nation's blessings bought: Now, the frail insects of a summer day, They fly regardless of the coming storms; Those storms shall come! Nurs'd in yon lurid sky Soon shall they sweep away the sickly forms, That now dissolv'd in perfum'd slumbers lie: Heedless alas! that, while the sun-beam warms, The blast that chills their little lives is nigh. Then—ere a second moon, more fix'd than they, With changing beam the jointur'd brides survey— Madly they fly where appetite inspires, Dart the unhallow'd glance and burn with real fires. Thy sons like hers, a fickle fluttering train, Th' illustrious honours of their name profane; Stake half a province on the doubtful die, And mark the fatal cast without a sigh: Their heavier hours th' intemperate bowl beguiles, Wakes the dull blood and lights lascivious smiles; Then in the stews they court th' impure embrace, Drink deep disease and mar the future race. Far other Britons antient Gallia view'd, When her dead chiefs the plains of Crecy strew'd; Proud of such heroes, and by such rever'd, In that blest age far other dames appear'd: Blest age, return; thy sternness soften'd down, Charm with our better features and thine own! Come; but resign those glories of the field, The gleaming falchion and the storied shield: Renounce the towery menace of thy brow, Which frown'd despair on vassal crowds below; And true to order, and of all the friend, To varied rank unvarying law extend. Ah! In the snowy robe of Peace array'd, Led by the Virtues of the rural shade, Return, and let advancing Time behold Regenerate man, and other years of gold. Then shall no feuds our triple realm divide, No traitor point the dagger at its side; But each with patriot toils his hours shall crown, And in his country's welfare find his own.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SMALLER POEMS, &amp;c. Tempore quo primùm vestis mihi tradita pura est, Jucundum cùm ætas florida ver ageret, Multa satis lusi: non est Dea nescia nostri, Quæ dulcem curis miscet amaritiem. Catull. lxvi. 15. [“Much on my early youth I love to dwell,”] “Much on my early youth I love to dwell,” When by my father's side, a stripling boy, I paced with steps unequal; fain to tell Of some new-practised game, some new-bought toy. How oft with bliss, which later days deny, My prattling tongue its story would repeat! Bounding beneath his tender smile, how high With blameless pride my filial heart would beat! O for those hours of extasy again, Which thus on life's sweet prime their lustre shed! The radiant season I invite in vain, With second beam to gild this orphan head: It comes not twice. Nor boots it to repine; I with his ashes soon may mingle mine. TO THE POST-CHARIOT OF A FRIEND, GOING ABROAD. O may Auriga's A considerable star in this constellation, called Capella, is designed (one would suppose) for the guidance of those, who traverse mountains chiefly known to the goat. lucid star, Direct thee, Chariot, on thy way; Whose whirling wheels from England far To southern climes my friend convey: And may no shock his ease invade From snapping spring, or linch-pin lost; No crack, save those by post-boys made, Till Bernard's ice-crown'd cliff be crost. Steel were his nerves, his sinews brass, Who first with vaulting footstep rose Sublime; and from the virgin-pass Look'd down upon eternal snows: Who, by the raving storm unscared, 'Mid Alpine precipices strode; The thundering mass unflinching heard, And dauntless traced the desperate road. In vain, to chariot-wheels denied, The crags their glittering horrours raise; If skittish mules may climb their side, And plod secure the air-hung ways. But man forbidden paths will tread: Columbus thus, of Japheth sprung, From virtue's simple sons convey'd The fire, whose name would taint my song. Hence the shrunk shank, and carious bone, Accelerate Nature's slow decay; And Death, no longer hobbling on, His ancient crutches flings away. Montgolfier thus, thro' vacant air, Elate on buoyant pinion soar'd; And Spalding thus, too prompt to dare, Old ocean's wreck-strew'd bed explored. To wildest flights wild man aspires: Here Paine would scale th' eternal walls; And there, as Franklin points his wires, Disarm'd th' indignant lightning falls. [With rapid wing our fairest years move on] With rapid wing our fairest years move on: I sigh, my Myra, as again I sing— Our fairest years move on with rapid wing, Till all the loveliness of life is gone. Few are our joys, and fleeting; ere they fly, Seize their brief grace! Not distant is the date (Trust me, dear maid) when even thy bloom shall die, Or scathed by chance, or chased by hurrying fate: Too soon that “eye's blue languish” will expire; And mute too soon will sleep that tuneful tongue, On whose soft sounds entranced attention hung, As with its melody it shamed the lyre. Then, ah! my Myra, ere those charms decay, Give them to love: Even now they haste away! SONG. [Say, fond lover, is thy mind] I Say, fond lover, is thy mind By the gentle Muse refin'd? Hast thou skill to strike the lyre With thine own Apollo's fire?— Think not so the maid to move; Hopeless is a Poet's love: Rich and high-born dotards tear From thine arms the venal fair. II Haply health's unborrow'd hues O'er thy cheek their bloom diffuse; And thy graceful limbs outvie Phidian forms in symmetry:— Ah! To Albion's sordid train Youth and beauty sue in vain: Rich and high-born dotards tear From thine arms the venal fair. III Though the Muse inspire thy breast; On thy face though wonder rest, Wildly gazing; and thy frame Rival Græcia's proudest fame;— Sigh unheard, unpitied pine, If nor rank nor wealth be thine: Rich and high-born dotards tear From thine arms the venal fair. [When first the siren Beauty's face] —Deus crudeliùs urit, Quos videt invitos succubuisse sibi. Tibull. I. viii. 7. When first the siren Beauty's face My wandering eye survey'd; Unmov'd I saw each fraudful grace, That 'round th' enchantress play'd: And still, with careless mien elate, Defied the Paphian's wile; As ambush'd in a look he sate, Or couch'd beneath a smile: And still to rove I madly vow'd Along the dangerous way, Secure—where other boasters bow'd Before the tyrant's sway. Nor learn'd my breast to heave the sigh, Or pour the secret heart; 'Till Myra from her beamy eye Dispatch'd th' unerring dart: “Fly, fatal shaft” (with cruel zeal The conscious murderess cried) “And teach yon haughty boy to feel “The anguish due to pride.” To sooth the soul-subduing pain Awhile I fondly strove; But combated, alas! in vain, Th' omnipotence of love. Then ah! at length, stern power, forbear; Thy wrath at length forego: Enough my youth has felt of care, Enough has tasted woe; Or if, ordain'd by stubborn fate, I drag th' eternal chain; Doom'd, as I bend beneath its weight, To court relief in vain: To Myra equal toil impart, On her thy pang bestow; Thrill with love's agony her heart, And bid her suffer too. [By many sorrows pierc'd before] Quæritis, undè mihi toties scribantur amores? Undè meus veniat mollis in ora liber? Non mî Calliope, non hæc mihi cantat Apollo; Ingenium nobis ipsa puella facit. Propert. II. i. 1. By many sorrows pierc'd before, In early youth I bow'd; Nor least the pang my bosom bore, When love's first fury glow'd: 'Till her harsh medicine Despair, Severely kind, apply'd; Tugg'd at the shaft with friendly care, And wrung it from my side: Stern is her art, but sure to heal Love's woes (those woes abound!) If memory with officious zeal Vex not the closing wound. And shall again insidious Hope With siren voice beguile? Twice must I with the terrors cope, That throng a woman's smile? Upon that fair and faithless main, Where my young heart was tost, Shall I embark—to be again In second ruin lost? O yes. I reck not, let it come; Love's tempest I defy: With conscious rashness court my doom, And dare—although I die. ON LEAVING A FAVOURITE RESIDENCE. ?, farewell! And with thee too adieu, Joys left as soon as tasted! They are gone, Even like some pleasant dream by hasty dawn Scar'd from the lover's pillow: Fast they flew, And long will they be absent. I meanwhile (Sooth'd by the memory of the white-arm'd maid, With whom among thy moonlight scenes I stray'd) With melancholy minstrelsy beguile The lonely hour. But me whate'er betide, Whether on life's tempestuous ocean tost Hopeless I view the still-retiring coast, Or my frail bark propitious Tritons guide Through smiling seas—on Her may prosperous fate, With its long train of changeless raptures, wait! ON THE SAME SUBJECT. Groves, that of late I lov'd so well, adieu! Dear to my soul, accept its parting sigh: Yet oft shall Memory your lost shades review, Still shall you flourish to her faithful eye. There was a time when through your bowers to rove, And with untutor'd fingers touch the lyre; My breast unvisited of other love, Than such as Phœbus and his train inspire, Delighted me. Ah! Time of bliss, return With healing on thy wings!—In vain I cry: Destin'd in hopeless misery to mourn, In vain I roam beneath another sky; And 'mid new scenes the fugitive explore: For joy shall solace this sad heart no more. WRITTEN AT MATLOCK. Matlock, as through thy cliff-sprung woods I rove (Still pausing, while I muse on Youth's brief day: How fast his shadowy raptures fleet away; How oft his heart, that seat of faithful love, Is doom'd to love in vain) my anguish'd mind Sighs to behold in spiral eddies round Thy foliage, scatter'd by the wild Northwind, With faded verdure strew the sallow ground. —But 'tis the season's wreck: Not unforeseen, The deepening tempest howls in Autumn's ear; Me the storm blasted, ere I learn'd to fear Its fatal rage, while yet my leaf was green: Scarce had my May begun her soft career, When stern December clos'd the hasty year. SONG. [In times so long past (though I still am but young)] In times so long past (though I still am but young) That I scarcely their transports can trace, Enraptur'd I caught the soft lisp of thy tongue; And totter'd—for then I but totter'd—along, To clasp thee in childish embrace. As we grew up together, each day I beheld, With feelings unkindled before, Thy yesterday's beauties by new ones excell'd; Nor, boy as I was, from those beauties withheld My heart:—Could I offer thee more? Even now, when the fever of youth is gone by, And I glow with more temperate fire, Delighted I dwell on thy soul-beaming eye; And, heaving perhaps still too ardent a sigh, Survey thee with chasten'd desire. Oh! come then and give me, dear Maiden, thy charms; For life is alas! on the wing: Our summer ere long will be fled; in these arms Let me shield thee, my Fair One, from winter's alarms: Oh! listen to love, while 'tis spring. ADDRESSED TO A LADY, WITH A PRINT OF CORNELIA. When Rome was yet in antient virtue great, Ere tyrant Cæsars had unnerv'd the state; Proud of her toilette's wealth, a modish Fair The costly hoard to fam'd Cornelia bare: And, having press'd it on her cold survey, With conscious triumph claim'd a like display. Soon as from school her boys, the Gracchi, came; “Behold my jewels (cried the happy Dame) “These are the gems a mother most should prize, “These glitter brightest to maternal eyes.” Her inmost soul confounded at the view, The self-admonish'd visitant withdrew. Such were the matrons virtuous Rome admir'd: From such sprang patriots who, by toils untir'd, Even to the last despotic sway defied; And, vanquish'd in the noble conflict—died. One such I could, but may not name (for she, Blind to herself, would deem it flattery) One who, Cornelia-like, each hour employs Sweet labour! 'mid the sphere of filial joys: To courtiers leaves exhausted India's store; And, rich in living diamonds, asks no more. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>