<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Costello, Louisa Stuart, 1799-1870</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Costello, Louisa Stuart, 1799-1870</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">costello louisa stuart 1799 1870</field>
      <field name="author_text">Costello, Louisa Stuart, 1799-1870</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1850's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.1093.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">1856</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466582</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">French</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Lay of the Stork ; By Miss Louisa Stuart Costello</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Lay of the Stork ; By Miss Louisa Stuart Costello</field>
      <field name="title_facet">lay of the stork</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">lay of the stork</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Lay of the Stork ; By Miss Louisa Stuart Costello</field>
      <field name="year_display">1856</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1856</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1856</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466582&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466582&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Costello, Louisa Stuart, 1799-1870&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;costello louisa stuart 1799 1870&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Lay of the Stork ; By Miss Louisa Stuart Costello&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;lay of the stork&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1856&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1856&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Costello, Louisa Stuart&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1799&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1870&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Lay of the Stork&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By Miss Louisa Stuart Costello&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Dublin&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;William and Frederick G. Cash&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Hodges and Smith&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1856&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0898&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;fre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;131 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Lay of the Stork&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By Miss Louisa Stuart Costello&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 159 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INTRODUCTION. The incident which gave rise to this poem, may be thus briefly told. A young German lady of eighteen, had a fancy, a few years ago, to discover to what region the Storks repaired on quitting a Northern climate, and for that purpose attached to the neck of a tame one a letter, in which she begged for an answer from whoever found it, informing her of the place where the bird alighted, and any other particulars attending it. The bird was shot by an Arab, in Syria, and her letter, copied by him, without understanding its language or import, was sent to the Prussian Vice-Consul, at Beyrout, who courteously addressed the desired communication to the young lady. The correspondence which followed is given in the Appendix, with a copy of the original letter. L. S. C. Chaumière d'Estrées, March, 1856. THE LAY OF THE STORK. PART I. THE NECKAR. Sunset! on the plain that spreads Onward to the glowing Rhine: Sunset on the purple heads Of Alsatia's Alsatia.—“Alsace est l'ancien pays des Tribocs dont il est parlé chez César, Strabon, Ptolomée et Ammian, et dont Stras-bourg ou Argentine, a été faite capital. B. Rhenanus dit que le nom d'Alsace est nouveau et il veut qu'il ait commencé sous le regne de Charlemagne qui en parle dans une charte pour le Prieuré du Val de Liévre sous le nom de Pagus Alsaticus. Jacques Chiflet soùtient que cette province emprunte son nom de la rivière d'Elle, d'où on a formé le mot latin Elsatia, Elisatium, Alisatium.”—(Origine de la Maison de Lorraine. 1704. A Toul.) mountain line: Red sunset on the vines that creep, Far along the rocky steep, Till those giant forests rise Dark against the clear, broad skies, All streak'd and fleck'd with sunset's glow, Down to the river's banks below. Silver Neckar! crimson'd o'er With the beam, from shore to shore, Silver Neckar! devious still, Doubling, turning at thy will, Circling through the meadows' maze, Joyous in the golden blaze, Till thy waters, full and free Swell the Rhine's majestic sea. Odenwald! in misty grey Fade thy crowding heights away: But fair Heidelberg stands out, All her ruins girt about With a diadem of gold, Such as crown'd her once of old, When two royal lovers stood, The Elector Frederic the Fifth, and Elizabeth of England, of whose attachment and misfortunes every stone of the Castle of Heidelberg is a relic. Gazing from this charmèd grove, Blest in tender solitude, Till ambition conquered love. Velleda! Keysler says, “Velleda was celebrated as a prophetess amongst the Germans. Tacitus names her and Auriniæ as objects of worship in the time of Vespasian. Women were believed, by the ancient Germans, to possess the gift of prophecy. The priestess Jettha dwelt in a temple, some fragments of which still existed when Frederic built the new palace of Heidelberg.” The name of the mountain has been derived from its Pagan temple (Heiden) by the learned: the peasantry derive it from the bilberries with which it abounds: Heidel. prophetess, whose fane Gave place to these abodes of joy, Didst thou foretel—alas!—in vain! What fate their glories should destroy, And this fair temple be as lone As desolate,—as erst thy own? Ah! in the changes wrought by Time, Whose sullen waves roll fiercely on, What boots, amidst his course sublime, A race of Kings—or Prophets—gone! THE STORK. Recluse, in yonder silent bay, Where the rose-hued rock The beautiful rose-colour of the rocks on the banks of the Neckar is remarkable, and must have been observed by every traveller. has caught Richer colours in the ray, Till its peaks seem fairy-wrought, Lila's shelter'd castle lies Scarcely mark'd by curious eyes. If, perchance, a stranger skiff Pause beneath the ruddy cliff, Then the ling'ring boatman tells Dreamy tales, in soften'd tone, Of an orphan maid, that dwells In those lofty towers—alone. See, where, on the terrace wall, Just beneath the turret's shade. Sits a bird, demure and tall, Buffon, with his usual poetical grace, gives the most minute and interesting particulars of the Stork and its habits. He describes the white variety as loving domesticity, while the black is solitary and seeks desolate places: he speaks of the welcome that attends the familiar bird, and of its content amidst crowded cities, where the noise and bustle are as indifferent to it as to the sparrow. “The body is of a brilliant white, but the wings are black, with reflections of violet and brown. The Greeks derived its name from its colour. It makes long voyages, even in stormy weather: arrives in Germany as early as the 9th or 10th of May, and sometimes, in Alsace, appears in March: it always returns to the same nest after absence.” Watching for the gentle maid. White his breast, and on his wings Glowing lights the sun-set flings: Now, his supple neck he twines, Casts his head his wings between, “When in the attitude of repose, the Stork throws its head backwards, reposing on the shoulders.” Lila's form, amidst the vines, By his rapid eye is seen. He will feel her fond caress, Hear her voice, so softly sweet, Thoughts, in tender words, express, For a happy lover meet: —But that bird alone may prove The happiness of Lila's love. “Do not suitors, at her gate Trembling for the signal wait That shall bid them enter in Free to woo her, and to win?”— —“No: though wealthy, young and fair, Never suitor enters there; Shrined in holy purity, Given to lore and musings high, She can interpret all the lays The small birds sing in summer days, She knows what to the waving grass The breezes whisper as they pass: And what the babbling waters say When on the glitt'ring sands they play. Well she knows each herb and flower, Every star by name can call: For, 'tis said, some mystic power Gives her knowledge over all. —But, that may not be—for nought To our curious doubts is known, Save that, in the realms of thought, Lila lives—apart—alone.— She prizes not her beauty's fame, —A beauty soul and thought bestow— Her friends and kindred vainly blame, A world is hers they cannot know. If sometimes courtly maidens seek Her towers, an idle hour to chase, 'Tis then the bloom deserts her cheek And pensive shades pass o'er her face: They note her lowly joys with scorn, Or pity the recluse forlorn. Perchance she checks a rising sigh, A tear one moment dims her eye, But, bending from her tow'r, she sees Yon hamlet 'midst the clust'ring trees; She meets some bright-ey'd child's salute, And sorrow in her heart is mute. That village, where the sunbeams play, Whose white walls gleam beneath her tower,— From Lila caught the quick'ning ray That changed a dungeon to a bower: Once, buried in yon gorge, it lay With malady in ev'ry blast; There pined the peasant, day by day, And sank in penury at last. She chose that spot of pleasant ground,— —Health breathes in all the airs that blow,— She scattered smiling dwellings round, And lured the victims from below. Now age and youth and childhood there,— —Plenty and ease at length their own,— Name Lila, with the truest pray'r, That ever sought th' Eternal throne.” The palace glows—the dance is gay, Where beauties smile, and hands are prest, And, as they whirl the time away, The hermit Lila is their jest. 'Tis for their speed they prize the hours, The subtle sands shake o'er and o'er; And trampling on the heart's fresh flowers, Can wonder that they rise no more! Whilst Lila, on her mission bent, Smiles on the work—and is content. But yet her smile has not the light Of joys that careless youth engage— The knowledge comes with withering blight That brings to youth the thoughts of age! So brief the moments time can give Of sunshine to our winter cold, Ah! who would wish the young to live In sad experience like the old! If Lila's yearning heart has borne The chill that on hard form attends, Int'rest but feign'd and secret scorn From those the careless world calls “friends;” Perchance at ev'ning, pale and still, Bent sadly o'er the terrace wall, She strives her wounded mind to fill With hopes these gentle scenes recall But still the vain futilities,— The busy coil—that worldlings make,— Come as a swarm of glitt'ring flies Disturbs the calm of some bright lake: “Alas!”—she sighs—“'tis wise to fly A world that has no room for me, Who, the frail forms of vanity With vision too unclouded, see. Oh! soaring bird! how happy thou, Whose nest is on the swaying bough; Whose path is through the blue, broad sky, At liberty!—at liberty! Hail eve and silence!—sages say The mind, by fasting, can descry —From worldly clamour turn'd away— The Secret Presence ever nigh. “The mind,” says Fenelon, “has no less need of fasting than the body: it has also its intermissions. The fast of silence, recollection and prayer, is essential, as is also the cessation, occasionally, of external action and whatever distracts the soul.” Fenelon remarked to one who conversed with Jansenists: “You are too much accustomed to mental application, which leaves your interior void, and prevents you from remembering the Secret Presence of God. This propensity to argument is greatly to be feared. The people whom you frequent are infinitely dry, argumentative, critical, and opposed to the true interior life. Make your greedy mind fast, make it keep silence: lead it to rest. God will then work more within it.” I would avoid the startling jar Of notes that yield but empty din:— Let me have rest from wordy war And feel the spirit-life within! I ask for Truth, without reply, And cling to vague philosophy: But, like to him Socrates was said to be “weary of the sight of human error.” who turn'd aside, Sick of man's error and his pride; When I have sought and heard my fill, I sigh with disappointment still That man is vanity alone, Conjecture—doubt—with nothing known. And still with credulous content We nurse the fond belief—‘we know’— While all, beneath the firmament, Is falsehood and imperfect show: We see the rain drop, shining bright, But worlds are there that mock our sight! Mountains and plains, with space between Glide to new changes, nearer seen; A speck of sand, that whirls around Holds myriad beings in its bound. On the Existence of Acari in Mica. By Sir D. Brewster.—“While examining with a microscope a thick plate of mica, from Siberia, about five inches long and three inches wide, he was surprised to observe the remains of minute animals, some the 70th of an inch, and others only the 150th of an inch in size. Some of these were inclosed in cavities round which the films of mica were in optical contact. These acari were, of course, not fossil, but must have insinuated themselves through openings between the plates of mica, which afterwards closed over them.”—British Association for the Advancement of Science, reported by “Athenæum,” October 6, 1855. “Dans la moindre portion de matière se trouvent enfermés une infinité de corps tous plus petits les uns que les autres: tous decroissant par des amoindrissemens infiniment petits.” —Leibnitz. What seems the smallest object sought Diminishes beyond our thought; What seems to fill the widest place Circles, still larger, through all space!— Ah! should not man's confession be An infant knows as much as he? And how shall feeble woman dare The height from whence the learned fall? Shall she, who may not even share His solemn vigils—seek at all? The will to crush, to immolate, All pangs to bear and to conceal, Is woman's long accepted fate,— She shrinks not back in woe or weal: But, if she hope and strive alone, No light upon her way, to shine, —The star that beckoned onward gone— Will not her strength at last decline? And all her visions, great and high, Vanish in chill reality! When shall I find the help I seek? Must then these aspirations fail! My hope too wild, my power too weak, My eager wishes all too frail? I would that those with hearts like mine, Whate'er their place, whate'er their state, In one great interest should combine, A new existence to create, To banish falsehood, hatred, strife, And give the world another life. I would the mighty truth once taught, In simple words to simple man, Were not by sophistry o'erwrought— Until the wide and ample plan Altered, and left to slow decay, Has all the faults it swept away! Friends!—yes—they tell me ev'ry hour There is no happier lot than mine; That youth is bliss, that wealth is power, And I—the last of all my line, Can, at my will, a world command, And hold a sceptre in my hand, Because in gold such spirits dwell Can bind all creatures to its spell. I hear these boasts, but heed them not, They pass, like winds, and are forgot: But listen still one word to hear, Sought, sigh'd for, waited for in vain: All others fall upon my ear Like discord in some minstrel's strain: All else is meaningless—is weak— But that one word they do not speak! Yet, in my heart's profound repose, Where thoughts lie deep, a treasured store, Whose sealèd fountain ever flows, That word is whispered evermore! Oh flowers! alive with radiant hues— Oh meadows! rich with jewell'd dews— Oh mountains! fading in the skies— Why do I love your mysteries? Why strive your secrets to attain, And fill with hopes my heart and brain? Why, but because ye may possess The treasure I for ever seek, May know the spell of happiness And that one word have power to speak! I make me friends of things like these, Watch the frail flow'rs and tend them well, Lie dreaming beneath waving trees, And fix my eyes on stars that tell Of wonders in a world of light Beyond my bounded mortal sight. Stars!—ay, what mysteries are those!— Whose depths when we would understand, The vase of science overflows And burns the sage's trembling hand. Placed, one, in that vast dazzling line, Awaiting the Eternal sign, Our planet glimmers—none so small,— Yet this we place above them all! No: 'tis too full of sorrows drear, Too sear'd with crime, too stain'd with blood, That our's should be the chosen sphere Which the Great Master said ‘was good.’ Who, gazing on that host sublime— Whose distance we can mark alone,— By measured space and counted time Shall teach what ages keep unknown? While I behold ye,—worlds! we dare To name as realms all void—all vain!— My soul still questions in despair While ye shine on, in cold disdain. And then come thronging visions fast, Glowing and bright'ning—seen—and past! Past! but leaving in their track Beams that will not pass away, Bringing crowding mem'ries back, Of a by-gone, vanish'd day, When the life I seek in vain Seem'd my own, though mine no more, And that one dear word again Voices whisper o'er and o'er. Ah! 'tis fled! earth closes round, Gone the ray, and hush'd the sound! Far off echoes long repeat Melodies surpassing sweet! Names that once I knew—they seem Syllables that haunt a dream; Stirring thoughts of joy and care, Father—mother—where? oh where? Dies each tender, melting tone— 'Tis the orphan's knell alone! Yet still friends—what friends?—protest, Lila is—or should be—blest! Had I all the wealth that fills The veins of yonder sunlit hills— Had I fabled gems that lie In deep caves that waters bind, All were worse than poverty To the treasure in my mind! Treasure, barren though it be, Shrouded in a secret urn, Till a spark shall set it free, And its precious flame shall burn, Bearing to the clouds above That one word—its being—Love! Love, the perfume of the flower, That, when others sweetly share, Loses neither charm nor power But blooms on, more softly fair. If a vision, let me live In that vision's spell divine, Feel the joy its mem'ries give, Though no other may be mine! All I know of love on earth Shows me shadows of the truth, Every object gives it birth, Glowing with the sun of youth: But I feel that far away Shines the true, the living ray. All things promise love around. I can prize, can cherish all; But, amidst this charmèd ground Nothing answers when I call, And my heart shrinks back once more, Waiting, shrouded as before. Eighteen years the summer sun Has renew'd both flower and leaf, Since my life, in tears begun, Learnt, at once, the way to grief. Kindred had th' unwelcome care Of my youthful father's heir: All of duty, duly paid, Each one's task is fairly o'er, And the wealthy orphan maid Thanks them, and demands no more, Asks for tenderness from none, And is left to dream alone! Alas! when happy for awhile, With all that nature yields to please, I can, like those around me, smile, And feel my yearning heart at ease,— Even then will wake the mournful thought, Subdued, repress'd, but ever nigh, Like some sad chord that comes unsought Amidst a cheerful melody, And, sounding once, no other strain Can echo in the heart again. Because I shrink, appall'd to view The cruel pomp of selfish state, While woe and sordid cares pursue Those worthier than the rich and great; They deem me an enthusiast lost, And smile, with silent scorn, to see The follies and the joys they boast, Are held as crimes by such as me. Yes—crimes—while poverty and woe Are pleading, trembling at their gate, Their only care is—not to know,— They dare to bid the wretched—wait! And yet they talk of woman's place As all too lowly for her soul, And bid her quit her narrow space And strive for mast'ry and control. They crush the glow-worm at their feet While reaching to the stars above, And slight, for power undue—unmeet— Mercy and tenderness and love! The world's great sea has threatened long, And brings some changes every tide; But pride and luxury and wrong, Still reckless on their height abide. But these poor worthless weeds and shells, The relics of an infant's play, When once some mighty billow swells, Will to the depths be borne away: And, where they cumbered all the land, Rich pearls shall strew the sunny strand; But no mean power must check the ill, Or pearls will be but pebbles still. Vain is it to be lifted high, If, from the gems that light the sky, No beam upon the earth is thrown, And those who gaze, admire alone, Nor hope nor feel a ray can cheer; So great the distance from their sphere. Pride, or of birth, or wealth, or mind— Though death each moment points and warns! Keeps each at variance with his kind:— One grain of dust another scorns! I ask what boots it thus to feel,— Content to pity and advise, Leave others all these wrongs to heal, And waste life in mere sympathies? Does not some power in Nature lie To teach my heart the remedy? Tell me, gentle bird, that came, Wild at first—now sweetly tame, When the breath of early May The arrival of the Stork in Europe takes place in the Spring. In Seville it is very common; but according, to the Prince of Canino, it is very rare and only an accidental visitor near Rome. Though so common in Holland, it very rarely arrives in Britain. The ground drainage of our marshes may have something to do with this; but it is hardly sufficient to account for so striking a difference in the migratory distribution of the bird, more especially as it proceeds to higher latitudes; for it regularly visits Sweden and the north of Russia, and breeds there. The winter is passed by the bird in the more genial climates of Asia, and in the northern parts of Africa, Egypt especially. Those who have seen these birds in the act of migration, speak of their numbers as very large: thus Belon remarks, that the Storks are never seen in flocks except when they are in the air; and he relates how, being at Abydos in the month of August, a great flight of Storks came from the north, and when they reached the commencement of the Mediterranean Sea, they there made many circuitous turns, and then dispersed into smaller companies. When Dr. Shaw was journeying over Mount Carmel, he saw the annual migration of those which had quitted Egypt; and he states that each of the flocks was half a mile in breadth, and occupied three hours in passing over. The black Stork (Ardea nigra), passes the winter in the southern parts of Europe, and in spring advances to high northern latitudes to spend the summer. Maillet (says Buffon,) speaks of seeing Storks descend at the end of April, in Higher Egypt, and pause on the Delta, which, however, the inundation of the Nile soon forced them to leave. They appear to quit all countries when the heat becomes excessive and the banks of rivers overflow and allow no fishing on the banks. Storks are met with in Turkey and Persia. Bruyn remarked their nest represented on the ruins of Persepolis; indeed, all over Asia they are seen, except in the desert. Lorraine and Alsace are the provinces of France where flocks in great numbers are seen to pass, and there is scarcely a village in which they do not make their nests in the belfries. “It is of a mild nature, neither shy nor savage, and is easily tamed. It has generally a melancholy and pensive aspect, but sometimes has been known to forget these attributes, and join in the sports of children when surrounded by and accustomed to them.” —Notes to Buffon. The Mahommedans call the Stork bel-arje, and hold it in great esteem and veneration. It is nearly as sacred with them as the Ibis with Egyptians. Shaw says those are held as profane who should kill one or use it ill. Chas'd our snowy clouds away, Wherefore restless every year? And, when winter chills us here, Spreading wide thy wings for flight Speedst thou from my dazzled sight? Thrice, when I had wept thee fled, I have hail'd thee back once more, And our summer lives we led, Careless, as they pass'd of yore: But, the cloudy season come, Thou wilt seek another home; That far Eastern home, the source Of all knowledge, great and high, Where the rivers in their course Roll through realms of mystery: Where the sun receives his light, And to holy faith is given Mighty lore, that reads aright Hidden secrets, kept by Heaven. Myst'ry on thy path attends: Those who Nature's wonders know See thee and thy wand'ring friends As, in countless ranks, ye go Trooping from the icy North To some realm for ever bright, Where no fear of winter's wrath Comes between you and delight. Then, dividing, some speed on Back to Nile's majestic waves, Some to Asian rivers lone, By wild sculptur'd rocks and caves, In Col. Todd's interesting “Travels in Western India,” may be read accounts of the shrines and temples of a multitude of deities. The loftiest of the peaks of Abo is called Guru Sikra: here is a cavern before which is a block of granite, impressed with the feet of Data Briga, (an incarnation of Vishnoo), which is an object of pilgrimage. The Pudda-ca, or footsteps of Rama Nanda, is a shrine also held in great veneration. The Agori or man-eater, is a horrible human creature, living on carrion and impurities of all kinds. Where the footsteps of a God Mark the granite path he trod; And by secret coonds The fountains in Upper India are called coonds.—Tod. and wells Where the gaunt Agori dwells; And where Rama's shrines aspire Proudly, as they rose of yore,— Though the bright, misleading fire Lights the Demon fane no more:— Where the Deity, half seen, Frowning, darksome boughs between, Rears some shape of hideous might, Lovely in his vot'ries' sight; They, whose foul belief in ill Crimes confirm, and frauds secure, They who crouch and worship still, In Moultan's hot groves impure. The cause assigned for the heat of Moultan is to be found in the legend of the Saint Shumsi Tabreezee, who is said to have caught a fish, and, having no fire by which to cook it, he brought the sun by his prayers near enough to roast it in his hand.—Tod. But, when scorching burns the sun, Once more is thy flight begun Where the waves run cool, at rest, And the fresh breeze fans thy breast. Restless seeker! can thy lore Teach thee to what realm to fly, When, thy quest of spring-tide o'er, Thou shalt pause eternally? Thy wings have not the radiant dyes Of those bright, gem-like birds, that shine Amidst the flow'rs of tropic skies, Warm with the colours of the mine. Thou hast no voice of melody To soothe and charm, to melt or fire, Nor pheasant step, nor eagle eye:— Yet can thy simple form inspire A tender interest in the heart, Because a loving guest thou art. Thou lov'st our homes: the lane—the street— And, perching on the belfry oft, We smile thy kindly shape to greet Where, motionless, thou sit'st aloft; We feel thou lov'st us, and we hail Thy yearly visit to our land Leading thy rapid, feathery band, And know thy presence will not fail. Cities and people thronging all Welcome ye loud from tower and wall, Crying, with joy to mark your track, “The Stork!—Spring's messenger, comes back!” Who, like thy race, of love can speak? For whom twice o'er Their year is composed of two summers. Belon assures us that the Stork lays its eggs twice in Egypt. the season comes, When other birds, with busy beak, Make for their young their downy homes. What bird so faithful to his mate? So pious to his parents old? Whose cares upon her nestlings wait, Whose wings their forms so warmly fold? And who has won so high a fame As the fond bird that, legends say, When in a city girt by flame, Pow'rless to fly her young ones lay, Rather than quit her burning nest, There is a tradition of a Stork, whose nest being in a building which took fire, the mother bird, finding it impossible to save her young, after flying about in despair, returned at length, and perished with them in the flames.—Notes to Buffon. Died, as they cower'd beneath her breast? Thy very name, in sacred tongue Chasida, In hieroglyphics the Stork signifies piety and benevolence, virtues which its name expresses in one of the most ancient languages, viz: Chasida in Hebrew. is a word of grace, And bards have of thy virtues sung That, to some secret ocean place, The old and feeble of thy race Are borne, by spirits that have power, To cast their feathery garb aside, When—human from that favour'd hour— They step as man in all his pride! “Alexandre du Myndes dans Ælien, dit que les cigognes cassées de veillesse se rendent à certaines isles de l'ocean et là, en recompense de leur piété sont changées en hommes.” Ælien assures us that the reason of their worship in Egypt rose from their great moral qualities. In the Levant, some of the old respect is shown for the Stork. —See Notes to Buffon. “Great moral virtues are attributed to this bird: temperance, conjugal fidelity, filial piety and paternal tenderness. They will carry their young ones on their wings before they can fly, and have been known to die with them rather than abandom them. The well known extraordinary attention they pay to their aged parents sound fabulous when told.” —Idem. Thou, friendly bird, can'st serve me well: Let me to thee my hopes confide; Spread thou the story far and wide, And to all earth my message tell. Speak thou of tenderness and care, Proclaim, wherever thou shalt fly, That love is watchful, and can bear A Northern clime, a cloudy sky, And sends a messenger in thee From shore to shore, from sea to sea. Speed o'er Mount Carmel's peaks of light, Go, where the Delta's isles invite, And rest thee where, 'neath Persian skies, Persepolis in ruin lies. Speed to the groves of far Japan, Kœmper says that the Stork lives all the year round in Japan, which is only the country it so favours. Where Spring—not dwindled to a span— To lure thee to her gentle sphere, Holds her mild sway throughout the year. In every place where thou shalt rove Let thy bright presence tell of love. Safe, in all regions, shalt thou be, A charmèd life is thine, Those who thy rapid voyage see Shall deem thee half divine: For where thy pure feet touch the ground, No venom'd creature may be found: Storks were held in esteem by the ancients, because they purged the land of serpents and other venomous things.—Notes to Buffon. Before thee all things evil flee, Leaving the land to Spring and thee. Thou hast a mission, sacred bird! Above thy kind for this preferr'd. Go: say that woman's sympathy Breathes in each place where'er thou art— That love has taught thy wing to fly, The magnet set to guide thy heart; That, though conceal'd, obscur'd and lost, Yet, even on the remotest ground, By storm delay'd, by tempest tost, Love can exist—and may be found. Bid those who mourn the lost revive, And say, there is no death in love; Bid those who weep no longer strive The pangs of mem'ry to remove. Invisible, love hovers near The couch where wounded heroes lie; No cave too dark, no spot too drear, —All space is filled with sympathy— The radiant spirit roams through earth, Though now by error's veil conceal'd: Yet it has shone, a Heavenly birth, A blessed miracle reveal'd, And, once descended to our sphere Its influence rests for ever here. Come, when the Lybian bird The Crane takes longer voyages than any other bird of passage. Is known in Sweden, Scotland, Orkneys, and all Northern countries. In autumn goes to France, where seeds are just sown, and in marshy places; then on to more Southerly climes, returning in Spring, and takes the way to the North, and thus makes a circle of voyages in a circle of seasons. The ancients called the Crane, bird of Lybia, and bird of Scythia, as it arrived from both these extremities of the then known world. The Crane cries loud in the air; its tumultuous clamours announce a storm. At the first cold of Autumn, the Cranes are warned to change the climate. Those of the Danube and Germany pass to Italy. They linger long in France if the autumn is mild. —Buffon. returns, Who, like thee, flies the winter's chill; But, when the Eastern Summer burns, Asks for our temp'rate region still: Stay not in that soft clime The people of Japan call them tsuri, and never speak of them but as o tsurisama, ‘my lord the Crane.’ —Kœmpfer. The Crane and Tortoise are of good omen in Japan. where she Is nam'd with awe, and held a queen; But bring her home in Spring with thee, When winds are still, and Earth is green. Linger not 'midst Numidian maids, The Demoiselle de Numidie.—“On a donné á ce bel oiseau le nom de Démoiselle a cause de son élégance, de sa parure et des gestes mimes qu'on lui voit affecter; cette Démoiselle-oiseau s'incline en effet par plusieurs révérences. se donne bonne air en marchant avec une sorte d'ostentation et souvent elle saute et bondit par gaité comme si elle voulait danser.” —Buffon. Aristotle calls it the comedian. Plutarch also talks of its acting, and calls its movement pantomime. The ancients speak of it as an actor and copyist of man; it has so much vanity that it prefers showing off its graces to eating. A party of Démoiselles are described as dancing like gypsies. —See Buffon's notes. Aristotle talks of their dancing opposite each other. Seduc'd by their attractive grace, When, gliding in the perfum'd shades Of Afric's groves, the dance they trace, And, plum'd and dress'd with dang'rous art, Use every wile to catch the heart: For thee such charms must have no lure, Far different love thou shalt secure. And when, borne far from shore to shore, My joyous message thou hast spread, Return, dear wanderer, once more, And tell my heart how thou hast sped.” Then Lila—half in jest—has bound A scroll the Stork's white bosom round; A purse the treasured words defends, By Lila's skilful fingers made, That by a silken cord depends, Amidst the fluttering feathers laid. There, closely hidden, shall it rest Secure within that downy nest. The Stork, obedient, seems to feel The myst'ry that his plumes conceal: His lofty step more stately grows, And his bright eye with ardour glows, Her hopes and wishes proud to share, And fond caresses thank her care. THE LETTER. “One, who in solitude has plann'd A world of virtues, great and high, Asks aid from ev'ry stranger's hand To make her dream reality, To all she sues, to all she pleads. To him, who first this message reads, A blessing and a pray'r she sends, And ranks him as her first of friends: All noble aims, all thoughts that soar, She bids awake, to sleep no more. Obey the call of one unknown Whose heart is throbbing like thy own, Think thou behold'st her, hear'st her speak, And grant thy help, where she is weak. Where mis'ry strives, be there to cheer, And weep with those who ask a tear: Where sickness pines be ever nigh To tend with healing sympathy: Shrink not from error, or from crime, But seek and aid—and save—in time. 'Tis true that ill creeps on apace To choke the garden where it grew; But good can spring in any place And, by its strength, the weeds subdue. And never grows there herb or flower But weeds start up within an hour; Yet, if protecting hands secure, The worthless changes to the pure. Is it not idle to complain Of the world's errors and its pain, And yet refuse the help that all Alike can give, however small? Let each but labour as he can, His part of good is gain'd to man None have so little power but one Is guided by that slight control, And though his will be weak—alone, The grain he casts may swell the whole. It is but false and selfish lore That bids us in cold silence rest: Nor add the trifle of our store While yet one being is unblest. The truth to find, and vanquish ill May never be our blissful chance; But to strive on is virtue still— Not to fall back is to advance. The dews that softly fall around May sink perchance in barren ground; But if a fading flower they meet Fresh beauties spring beneath our feet. Heaven sheds on all alike its rain, Strive then—nor fear to strive in vain. If thou would'st know who thus sends forth This bird that quits the icy North, But to return in glowing Spring, And back thy answering message bring, 'Tis Lila: more than this to say Were idle; but, whoe'er thou art, Who shall her fond desire obey, Be sure she holds thee in her heart. Inscribe thy name upon the scroll: —Her messenger will faithful prove,— Give hope to distant Lila's soul Whose wish would fill all earth with love.” PART II. The first dry leaves are borne away From the tall linden's verdant crown; And clust'ring coral berries weigh The bow'd acacia's branches down: The vines a crimson tinge reveal, The grape has caught a ruddier die, The thick woods shiver as they feel Amidst their boughs the North wind's sigh. On the wide plain a fluttering band Of shining plume and dusky wing, Descends, and all expectant stand, Till yon dark cloud its freight shall bring: It pauses, and fresh troops alight Till the broad space is snowy white. The Stork has call'd her armies forth Retreating from the icy North, Bills clang, and clattering seem to cry, —“The time is come!—'tis Winter!—fly!” Then some advance, each other greet, As questioning, with air discreet, Of tardy stragglers, whom they hail, Come sweeping onwards strong and fast; But woe to him whose pinions fail, Who drops, with flagging pace—the last. No mercy, by their law, extends To him who dares desert his friends: In vain his struggles and his cries, Pierced by their jav'lin-beaks—he dies! The Storks when assembled are said to be very severe to the last comer who has retarded their departure. They usually sacrifice him to their fury, by pecking him to death with their sharp bills.—Pliny. When all are marshall'd,—duly met, Till fifteen times the sun has set, From day to day a sage divan They have been observed to meet in large flocks that covered a plain for fifteen successive days, apparently holding a council or divan, to arrange their flight.—See Shaw. Consults and ponders o'er their plan; Till one, with high majestic pace, Steps slowly forth amid the press, And, gazing round the crowded space, Seems the vast concourse to address:— And who shall say the thought is vain That gestures speak a language plain?— Although of old the poets feign That careless Nature did them wrong, And left the Storks without a tongue. The ancients believed the Stork to be without a tongue, because of its general silence.—Notes to Buffon. Deem not such simple fables sooth:— —Tho' poets sometimes tell us truth,— Nor credit vain Italian tales, That oft, on Como's silver lake, While the calm fisher gently sails, His nets, by sudden force, will break, And, as in dreamy thought he lies, And on the unwonted burthen broods, Deep in the waters he descries One naturalist asserts that at the bottom of the Lake of Como, multitudes of Storks in a torpid state have been found by fishermen. Buffon considered as error the belief in the self-immersion of swallows and other birds in lakes; the instances cited by others, in support of that opinion, being, he conceives, merely exceptions or accidents. His chapter on the subject is extremely amusing and curious, full of candour, but resolute for facts, in spite of the poetry which he loves, and the traditions which he delights to allude to. The Storks in countless multitudes; As others say the Swallows hide Conceal'd, till Summer, in the tide. But the White Stork his mission knows And scorn on sland'rous legends throws. The Black Stork seeks desert places, perches in the woods, frequents isolated marshes, and makes its nest in the thickest part of forests. The white species, on the contrary, chooses our habitations as a domicile, establishes himself on towers, chimneys and the roofs of houses: the friend of man, he shares his dwelling, and even his grounds; he fishes in our rivers, hunts in our gardens, places himself in the midst of our towns, without being startled by the noise, &amp;c.—Buffon. Not these the tribe of sable wing, Morose and sad, that cherish gloom, In arid deserts lingering, And making cheerful earth a tomb. They, though the race a kindred claim, Are all unlike, except in name. No social virtues make them dear, Unbending, haughty and severe. Borne on the highest bough that crowns The aged fir's dark, solemn crest; Conceal'd where sullen Nature frowns, They build a secret lonely nest; Flying to marshes far remote, On whose cold breast no lilies float; But where, on pools of waveless sloth, Flit winged things in hideous play, Whose shapes, if fram'd of huger growth, Would scare the sight with strange dismay. Things—that like glitt'ring vices shine, Ever in motion to and fro, Coloured with many a radiant line, Skimming the slime for prey below; Dazzling, in starry splendour drest, But dim and monstrous if at rest. Yet, such cold caution marks the race, Man's lore is weak their course to trace: Some deem they linger on our shore And wait in darkness for the Spring, While far those silver pinions soar, To pleasant places wandering: For scenes, by the fair race enjoy'd, Their envious kindred most avoid: Passing above, with scornful flight, Nor pausing when the rest alight. Jealous their snowy plumes to view That gives their own a duskier hue. Ah! fatal error! wherefore fly, Nor seek, nor cherish sympathy! Even those dim wings, if touch'd by light, And not in murky gloom conceal'd, With sapphire, emerald hues unite, And to the sun new beauty yield, Tinted with e'en a richer glow Than those, eclips'd by breasts of snow. But each, with crimson-circled eyes, Looks on his rival in despair, And hurrying past, with clamour flies From joys he still disdains to share. —“Boast, oh white tribes! your plumage fair, The Black Stork has a world elsewhere!” Go then, ye wanderers, worlds explore— Seek, if ye will, that sphere unknown Thro' many an age to Eastern lore, The feathers of the black Stork, which is only called black to distinguish it from the white kind, are very beautiful in the light, catching violet and golden-green reflections on the dark brown ground of the wings. A very red skin surrounds the eyes. It is wild and solitary, and loves the oldest firs, choosing the highest branches on which to perch. A species called Jabiru, of the same family, is found on the banks of the Amazon and Orinoco. It has sometimes in its fishing excursions to combat large serpents, and is furnished by nature with arms to defend and attack its foes, having a powerful and trenchant bill, inserted like a hatchet into its large head, and a thick and nervous throat. The Jabiru is found in Brazil, and in Guiana is called Negro. It feeds generally on the insects it finds in lonely marshes and beside rivers. The black Stork avoids the spots frequented by the white sort, and shuns society with its species. It flies in small parties, or in pairs, and never in large flocks like the others. Buffon adds—“We are not assured that it travels in the same manner as the white Stork, and are even ignorant whether the time of its migration is the same: nevertheless, there is every reason to believe so.” Whose rivers, lakes, and forests lone Show marvels Nature's wild caprice Bids in her secret depths increase, Till giant creatures, sprung to birth From dawning time, encumber earth. There ye may meet congenial pride, In hermits, to your race allied; There Negro flocks in hostile ranks, Roam sadly by the gloomy banks; Their trenchant bills, for combat made With serpents, ghastly in their strength, That haunt each poisonous nook and glade, And triumph in their scaly length, Amidst Guiana's swamps and reeds, Where their arm'd foe undaunted feeds. Go: leave this pure unsullied race A happier lot and narrower space, Nor heed the summons that exhorts The friends to seek their Spring resorts. “Prepare! prepare!—why ling'ring stay, When other flocks have led the way? The crested Huppo, The Huppo.—This bird bears quite a poetical character amongst ancient naturalists, its qualities being supposed to resemble those attributed to the Stork, with whom it is frequently seen in company. It was held as a good harbinger by the Egyptians, who constantly repeat its form in their hieroglyphics, and consider it, like the Stork, an emblem of filial piety. There are several species, all remarkable, and of few birds have more fables been recounted: amongst the most famous is its supposed power of breaking evil charms, and its singular knowledge of the occult virtues of herbs. In England and in Sweden, it was held as a bird of ill-omen. It leaves Northern climates at the same period as the Stork, and is generally found in the same regions. though she shares Our love of man, deserts him now; Past are the temp'rate Summer airs, And howling winds the forests bow. She seeks, like us, the banks of Nile, Land where she learnt those mystic spells, Pow'rful alike for good or guile, That make her fear'd where'er she dwells: But well the Pious Bird is known To us for virtues like our own. Has not the Swallow's The Swallow generally precedes the Stork in his annual migrations. Of this bird there are many traditions in the East. In the notes to Buffon occurs the following:— “This year (1779) there was no snow during winter: never-theless, the swallows did not arrive in Burgundy till the 9th of April, and at the Lake of Geneva till the 14th. It is related that a shoemaker of Bâle, having put round the neck of a Swallow a collar, on which was written: ‘Hirondelle, Qui est si belle Dis moi, l'hiver où vas-tu?’ received, the following Spring, this answer to his question:— ‘A Athènes, Chez Antoine, Pourquoi t'en informe tu?’ To this story the witty naturalist adds the following comment: “Ce qui est le plus probable dans cette anecdote c'est que les vers ont été fait en Suisse. Quant au fait il est plus que douteux.” beck'ning wing Warn'd us to verdant Egypt's Spring? Wise bird! whose skill the herb can find That gives back vision to the blind! Than ours her pinions far less strong, For favouring winds she waited long. And see, the enamell'd Halcyons Buffon says that this beautiful bird, though originally from a warm climate, has become habituated to the cold of ours. It may be seen all the winter beside the frozen streams, often plunging beneath the ice, and re-appearing with its prey: it is called, for this reason, in Germany, eisvogel. The most superstitious ideas were attached to the Halcyon: that it had the property of preventing thunder, of augmenting hidden treasure, and, though dead, could renew its plumage at the accustomed time. “It communicates,” says one ancient author, “to whoever carries it, grace and beauty: gives peace in a house: calm to the sea: attracts the fish, and renders the season abundant.” “Ces fables,” adds Buffon, “flattent la credulité mais malheureusement, ce ne sont que des fables.” The Halcyon is the most beautiful bird of our climate, from the brilliancy of the colours of its enamelled plumage. It is sometimes called “the Nymph,” from bearing the name of Alcyone, the plaintive daughter of Eolus, so often named by the poets Euripides, Ovid, &amp;c. Ariosto speaks thus: “S'udir l'alcioni alla marina del' antico infortunio lamentarsi.” The nightingale is sometimes meant in these poetical allusions, as in those of “sad Electra's poet.” come! Return'd to find their winter home, For that same season, chill and drear, That makes us exiles, lures them here. Beautiful nymphs! One species of halcyon is named by Cuvier as remarkable for two long feathers, which are prolonged beyond the rest of its tail, and have at their extremity a bright blue mark. This kind Seba called, from its beauty, “Nymphe de Ternate.” whose glance can bless Even snows with grace and happiness! Prepare!—nor rise with clamour loud, Like the wild Cranes—a noisy crowd— Nor let the idle watcher see Our solemn hour with vacant glee. Few such as he, methinks, can boast He mark'd us leave our trysting ground, He turns a moment—we are lost, Plung'd far in space, without a sound. They who the Storks in air behold Storks fly without noise or uttering cries, and leave the North the latter end of August. So rapid is their flight, when once settled in conclave, that, as they make no clamour, like many other birds, they are lost to sight instantly. —Buffon. The flight of the Stork is powerful and sustained, like all birds that have broad wings and a short tail. As he flies he carries his head stiff and forward, and his claws extended backward as if to serve as a rudder. —Idem. May marvel at the height we gain, —The ample wings, spread broad and bold,— Powerful and steady moves our train: The firm head pointing, forward sent, The claws, our rudder, backward bent, Piercing the clouds with lightning force: What mortal eye shall trace our course! Above, our hovering pilot see, Tradition gives a pilot to the flocks of Storks, in the form of a Crow, which is supposed to be their guide to countries they are seeking.—St. Basile and Isidore. His form a dark speck in the sky: He waits our signal to be free, The time is come!—'tis winter—fly!” Long Lila gazes, as away The last swift wing is sweeping by, She deems, amidst the wild array, Her fav'rite she can yet descry: And fancies on his snowy breast She sees her crimson ribbon rest; But, careless of her fond adieu, He passes—and is lost to view. Where the full Danube's forests sweep Down from the mountain's highest steep, And plunge their branches in the wave As the proud river winds his way, Now doubling near some gloomy cave, Now circling round some ruin grey, Dreary and grand and desolate, As though it bore to sudden fate The bark, that on the solitude Of its lone region dares intrude: A moment gleaming as they pass Within the sullen river's glass, Thousands of shining wings move slow, As glittering in the air they go; The shade of all those snowy flocks Deepens the gloom along the rocks; One moment, and—the shadow gone— The lonely Danube murmurs on. The swift-wing'd band speed fast and far, Where Inn maintains his foamy war, By beetling cliff and startled town Pouring his restless torrent down, But—Martinswand and Innspruck past— On speeds the army—far and fast. “Hold, gondolier! what streaks of white Mark the canal with waving lines? It is the rising sun, more bright, That o'er awaking Venice shines? It flashes, vanishes—too soon— That meteor on the blue lagoon. Ah! now I know—I see them fly— The storks!—the storks are passing by.” Not even Venice tempts to stay: St. Mark's gold domes fade fast away, Fade all the rose-hued palace towers Of fairy fret-work, all the isles, And left, amidst her roofs of flowers, Alone, fair Venice sits and smiles. Where a bright Asian city lies, As if by genii planted there, To dazzle Europe's wondering eyes With all the East can boast of rare, Gleaming, two silver seas between, And guarding both, with lofty mien: There pause awhile the winged band, —Their ranks, as if by chiefs, review'd,— In groups they form—await command, —The word is given—the flight renew'd. Yon straits are past, and Europe's sky: All Asia's plains before them lie. No more compell'd through space to roam, The Storks have reached their winter home. Free may they linger now, and choose The spot they love on Syria's strand, Ere yet the hot sun fade the hues Of countless flowers that hide the sand And deck the Desert's carpet rude, —A Paradise of Solitude! Buds, dry and dusky, in an hour, Wak'd by the dews, burst forth in flower, The scarlet amaryllis hastes To throw her mantle o'er the wastes, Striving the roses to subdue In soft perfume and brilliant hue. Narcissus opes his starry eyes, Carnations, rich in odour, rise, Pure lilies lift their lances tall, And feathery palms o'ershadow all. Wild, glittering streamlets, murmuring tell Where gliding finny tenants dwell: And ev'ry river, swelling o'er, Invites the fisher to the shore. Even Lebanon's dark cedars bring New leaves to greet the smiling Spring: And on the myrtle's hardy stem Is hung a snowy diadem. What bird, whose search is earthly bliss Would stray from such a scene as this? And Lila's truant, like the rest, Builds in this bower her second nest. But some, dispersed, far onward fly, Where marvels, in an age gone by, Mark'd sites with awe and solemn dread, Where now unnoticed ruins spread! Jaffa the Beautiful—where stood Sad Noah, ere his ark began That voyage on the surging flood Which should destroy the homes of man: And where—his fated journey past— The world's preserver slept at last. Tradition names Jaffa as the burial-place of Noah, and where the ark rested on its return. 'Tis here, as Pagan minstrels sing, Andromeda's dark rock and ring Are seen above the angry wave That foamed before the monster's cave. The rock and the ring to which Andromeda was supposed to have been chained, are imagined to have existed on this coast. —Chateaubriand. But such unhallowed fables all Before the chosen warriors fall Who came in myriads from the North, To thrust such idle legends forth. Well, if old evil crush'd, a new And purer creed could ill subdue! They came, even then, in mercy's name, But on destruction built their fame. PART III. The embroidered carpet is unroll'd Beneath a sycamore's broad shade, The silken cushions, wrought with gold, And jewell'd pipe, are ready laid. It is the Scheik's accustom'd hour: The breeze flows fresh from Syria's sea; And Kh?lid, from his castle tow'r, Will seek, at eve, his fav'rite tree. The Arabs, as his step draws nigh, Retire, nor mar his privacy: They know, his mind with projects fraught, He wants not rest, but quiet thought. No braver leader have they known, And in his fame they hail their own. Ask not of race, nor lineage high, But mark his step and mark his eye. That eye, though dark, has not the glow That flashes from an Arab lid; Though scorch'd his cheek, a skin of snow Beneath his robe is scarcely hid: And, though his language is their own, A tongue that well becomes the Scheik, The accents have not all the tone That, in their tents, the Arabs speak. They call him Kh?lid, The name of K?led means Happy, according to the celebrated poem of Antar, as quoted by M. de Lamartine. “Kaled n'est plus bien nommé depuis que jele cherche.” This is a line in the song of Antar, when, excited by the desire of Abla, to whom he is devoted, he departs, resolved to emulate the marvellous doings of K?led-Eben-Mohareb, to obtain the hand of his cousin Jida. K?led on the day of his marriage killed a thousand camels and twenty lions, the latter with his own hand, and served up the flesh of the lions to the three tribes invited to his wedding, who feasted on it during three days. Antar resolves to conquer this famous chief of the tribe of Beni-Zobaid. for they tell The name of “Happy” suits him well, Who never in the battle-field One foot of ground was forced to yield, And who, since first he led them on, Has glory gain'd and conquest won. Allah, amidst the tribe's despair, —When fell their Scheik, a chief of fame,— Had heard and, granted to their pray'r, Kh?lid, the Happy Stranger, came. He aids the gen'rous Franks, who fain To crush the treach'rous Russian's pride, Leave island home and flowery plain, To fight upon the weaker side. Now he attends the Pasha's word, Prompt to attack the Tartar horde:— But listless wears the anxious day When warriors wait, and chiefs delay. 'Tis said, when in the fountain's wave The Prophet bent, his head to lave, The manner in which Mohammed was caught away and carried through the Seven Heavens, is one of the questions which has been much discussed and disputed. Some thinking he went bodily and returned the same night; others contending that his journey was only in a vision. Some say it was begun and ended while a vase full of water, was in the act of being overturned, before all had fallen to the ground.—See Koran. His soul went on for countless years, Throughout all space, through all the spheres, From world to world, from pole to pole, And learnt the mysteries of the whole. He saw how rubies have their birth, And how the acorn grows in earth, How pearls are formed in Ocean's breast, How builds the Auk her giant nest: Saw all the caves where tempests lurk, And how the hot volcanoes work; Yet—to attain such wondrous lore, Some believers assert, that the Prophet's vision took place at the moment he was making his ablutions, and that all occurred while he plunged his head in a vase of water. This legend is frequently repeated in Eastern Tales. Seem'd but one plunge, and nothing more! So thought through past and future speeds Nor space, nor time, nor motion needs. The Scheik inhaled that drug of price Haschish.—“By the Indians called Bhang, the Persians Bang, and the natives of Barbary, I believe, Fasukh. The Hottentots use it; and even the Siberians, we are told, intoxicate themselves by the vapour of this seed thrown upon red-hot stones. Egypt surpasses all other nations in the variety of compounds into which this fascinating drug is taken, and will one day probably supply the Western world with ‘Indian hemp,’ when its solid merits are duly appreciated. At present in Europe it is chiefly confined, as cognac and opium used to be, to the apothecary's shelves.”—Notes to the word “Haschish,” in Burton's Pilgrimage to El Medinah and Meccah, vol. i. p. 64. Of the terrible and bewildering effects of the opiate called haschish, Mr. Radcliffe relates that the sense of hearing “becomes, occasionally, so developed, that a word pronounced low, or a slight movement, sounds like a peal of thunder.” He says further:— “In the state induced by haschish, the singular and fantastic forms which those under its influence, and the parties surrounding them, have appeared to undergo, are of great interest. ‘The eyelashes, writes one gentleman, ‘lengthened themselves indefinitely, and rolled themselves as threads of gold on little ivory bobbins which turned unassisted, with frightful rapidity. . . . I still saw my comrades at certain moments, but deformed, half men, half plants, with the pensive airs of an ibis standing on one foot, of ostriches flapping their wings, &amp;c.’—‘I imagined that I was the parroquet of the Queen of Sheba, and I imitated as well as I was able the cries of this praiseworthy bird.’” The same gentleman “thought he could look at will into his stomach, and that he saw there, in the form of an emerald, from which escaped millions of sparks, the drug he had swallowed.” That changes Earth to Paradise, But can transform to foul from fair, If careless hands the charm prepare. His thoughts fled far for many a day, Through all his fortune's devious way, What he had sought and won and lost, Mistaken hopes, an endless store! Vain strivings—expectation crost, And joys and pleasures—prized no more. And, to his bosom's smother'd sigh, These words, within his heart, reply. —“And I—with tender visions still That peace on earth at length might reign, Who would not cherish fears of ill, But idly hoped the end to gain, Which trusting sages, from the first, By love have taught, by precept nurs'd, That Truth should like a Phœnix soar And war and hatred rule no more; I—leader of a savage band, Who but obey my strange command Because, by superstition driv'n, They deem their chief by Allah giv'n! I—yielding to the power of chance, Give up my aspirations high, And, where they blindly rush, advance, And, like them, follow destiny! The hopes my eager childhood caught, The truths those gentle fathers taught, Are they then vain when glory calls, Or linger but in convent walls? Are love and peace but fables all, And must men strive like beasts of prey, But fall to rise and rise to fall, Struggling and wrestling day by day, The end for ever farther thrown, And the world's good—a cloud alone! Strange Fate!—my Eastern mother's star Has kept me from the region far Of my lost father's lineage high; A region all to me unknown, Which he forsook, new realms to try, And had no spot of earth his own. Dying, he gave me but his sword: And she, the Syrian bride he won, A few brief fleeting years adored, Slept in his tomb—and left her son. The Pasha's pity did the rest, And men called Kh?lid's fortune blest! Oh, Northern clime! that in my dreams Comes to my soul in sunny gleams! The meanest hind that leads his flock On thy free soil has better state Than all the gauds, our dearth that mock, And on our savage pride await. Oh happy! on some river's side To hear the ever-murmuring tide, And see the barks glide gently on As meet for peaceful freights alone. And, if some heart at length were found To yield me room wherein to dwell, And lead me to enchanted ground And teach—what nought beside can tell— Ha!—see, it floats—the Pasha's sign! Away! no hopes like these are mine!” THE SONG OF THE ARABS. “Is there a brighter sea or sky Than this beneath the eagle eye Of Lebanon, whose cedars throw Their shadows on eternal snow? Is there a valley half so sweet As this our river loves yet leaves?— With roses blushing at our feet, And many a gentle bird that grieves, And tunes so wild, so soft a song, We can but wish his sorrows long. Where vines upon the branches lean, And hang their grapes the trees between: And where, beside our fountains cold, The maidens dress their long dark hair With shining coins of graven gold, And flow'rs, not half so fresh and fair. Look not to yonder desert lone, 'Tis sand, hot sand, though fair its hue, Look to the deep sea, bright and blue, And those light skiffs that dance thereon: On our white tents beneath the shade, By cedar, pine and laurel made, Where orange flowers, of rich perfume, With starry eyes peep through the gloom. Look on our steeds of fairy feet, Whose light forms breeze-like, fawn-like, move, As if the softest air they meet Would all too rough a lover prove For fragile beings such as they: But, see them furious in the fray, See them the flying Tartar chase,— The light'ning lags behind their pace! And ask if Allah's blessed face Turns ever from the Arab race! But wherefore linger we so long? To war the sword—to peace the song.” As fair as those the Arabs' lays, Proud of their beauty, loved to praise, Had Saba been, who sits alone, Pale, motionless, as turn'd to stone— When first she came, young Youssouf's bride, He for whose love the maidens sigh'd: —The boldest fisher and the best. And both were fair, and gay, and blest. For, safe from storms, secure from ill, His prosp'rous bark came laden still: Till once the skiffs all reached the shore, But Youssouf's?—came that day no more! Since then how faded Saba's cheek! Her heart has left one only joy, Her son, whose smile delights the Scheik, Her Youssouf still—her orphan boy. See where he sports, intent and glad, His aim is true, his eye is keen: His pensive mother, veil'd and sad, Watching his careless step and mien. The tribe look on, and see with pride The skill they cherish fairly tried, And each can tell some wond'rous tale How “Youssouf's hand, that cannot fail, Commands the plain, commands the sky, Soon as his touch obeys his eye. And, would he daunt the wildest steed That ever serv'd an Arab's need, Scarce has he met the angry glance, Scarce towards the mane his hands advance, Than the proud flash of living flame That made all pause, he knows to quell, And the fair creature, soft and tame, Steps, gentle as a maid's gazelle.” Ha! why that shriek?—the bird is prone, Close at his mother's feet it lies: Could he have gained a fairer prize? “Ah! hapless child! what hast thou done! Alas! the sainted bird that came The Arabs home and care to claim!— This deed my cup of anguish fills— Woe! woe to him a stork who kills!” Loud grows the wail—far sweeps the cry— And echo speeds each fierce reply. —“Away! young fated one—away! Nor in our tents one moment stay, Ill chance on all attends where fell The holy bird Heaven loves so well!” Buffon says that this beautiful bird, though originally from a warm climate, has become habituated to the cold of ours. It may be seen all the winter beside the frozen streams, often plunging beneath the ice, and re-appearing with its prey: it is called, for this reason, in Germany, eisvogel. The most superstitious ideas were attached to the Halcyon: that it had the property of preventing thunder, of augmenting hidden treasure, and, though dead, could renew its plumage at the accustomed time. “It communicates,” says one ancient author, “to whoever carries it, grace and beauty: gives peace in a house: calm to the sea: attracts the fish, and renders the season abundant.” “Ces fables,” adds Buffon, “flattent la credulité mais malheureusement, ce ne sont que des fables.” The Halcyon is the most beautiful bird of our climate, from the brilliancy of the colours of its enamelled plumage. It is sometimes called “the Nymph,” from bearing the name of Alcyone, the plaintive daughter of Eolus, so often named by the poets Euripides, Ovid, &amp;c. Ariosto speaks thus: “S'udir l'alcioni alla marina del' antico infortunio lamentarsi.” The nightingale is sometimes meant in these poetical allusions, as in those of “sad Electra's poet.” The Scheik look'd up, nor listened long, Dark grew his brow, he glanced around, Then strode to where, amidst the throng The bird lay bleeding on the ground: And, menaced by the hostile band, Flush'd but unshrinking in the fray, Held by his mother's trembling hand, His fav'rite Youssouf stood at bay. “Stand off!” he cried—and, at his word The crowd fell back—they own'd their lord. —“Take up the quarry, and on me Fall all the ill—if ill there be: But, idle thought! God guards his own, And made all things for man alone. This foolish bird, even like his kind, Was for our food or sport design'd. Give praise to Allah! all beside Is but man's error or his pride. Well shot—dear Youssouf—thou wilt show Such prowess on the Russian foe. The hour is come—on yonder height Waves free our signal for the fight, The Pasha's sign—who shrinks may fly: Yonder our path to victory!” Forgotten Youssouf and his prey, At once the variable throng Renew the shout, the word obey, And hail the mandate, hoped so long. —“Lead Kh?lid, lead once more to fame!” And the skies ring with Kh?lid's name. Still by the bird pale Saba kneels, His dying agonies she feels: Her Youssouf's fate in his she fears, And bathes the victim with her tears. Would she could staunch the purple tide That gushes from his snowy side! Ah! Lila,—all his wand'rings o'er, Thy messenger returns no more! —“'Tis strange! a scroll the feathers hide, Some sacred message it may prove, Sent to the Scheik the war to guide, For still he thrives in Allah's love: Oh! bear it to him straight, his power Is great to read the words aright,— Averted is the evil hour, And we shall conquer in the fight!” Once more they shout—the loud acclaim Bears to the skies young Youssouf's name: —'Tis he, by Allah's gracious will, That gives us good instead of ill!” Scant time has Kh?lid now to scan The secret of that talisman; Enough the treasure to receive That with grave awe and care they bring, He knows they rev'rence and believe The written page a sacred thing, The Mahommedans hold all written words as Sacred as the name of Allah may possibly be contained in them.—See Koran.— And, even though bound in error's thrall, Yet solemn is belief in all.— Enough to place it in his breast As something precious, to obey, That, when for aid and counsel prest, This scroll divine may guide his way: So deem the tribe, and more and more Their chief, by Allah sent, adore. Plunged deep in Asian wilds remote Where lances flash and banners float, And the shrill trumpet's clamorous note Frights nature's stillness,—and where roar Loud thunders, that are not of Heaven!— Where lightnings blast the forests hoar, And torrents, from the mountains driven, Sparkle and foam, not as of yore By long accustomed tempests tost— But roll full tides of crimson gore And mangled forms, from either host, Hurl'd down, and in abysses lost— Kh?lid leads on: and never yet Had chief a band more wildly brave, Ardent and true, but who forget Or scorn to pity or to save: Bearing all ills with minds unmoved, Making e'en famine's self a jest: Casting by life, as if unloved, And slaught'ring with untiring zest! And he must urge, command—nay force His victims to this desp'rate course, With Lila's message in his breast, Where beats a heart as soft and kind As ever pitied the distrest, And throbb'd to succour all mankind. Oh accident! that chains us still Who talk of power, and boast of will! It was alone, within his tent, With toil o'erworn, with struggles spent, —A moment's pause the time allowed, Freed from the tumult of the crowd; First from the little purse he drew The scroll the sacred charge that bore, Followed the lines, with eager view, And read them, trembling, o'er and o'er. —“To me! such holy words of bliss, And read in such a scene as this!— The Dove, that braved the flood alone, And held a leaf of Paradise, Brought promise to a world undone— But, can a star for me arise, Before whose path dark torrents run?— And waiting till to-morrow's sun Shall still on newer horrors shine, The voice that rouses carnage—mine! This angel music sounds too late, It cannot charm the force of Fate!” PART IV. Tidings!—from that pleasant river Where the long-leaved willows bend, And in Spring white hawthorn blossoms With the air their fragrance blend; That, escaped its velvet borders, Hastes its bosom to expand, Bearing onward to the ocean Fleets that may the world command: From fair Thames are tidings coming That shall swell the startled heart, And awake the soul that slumbers To assume its noblest part. Tidings!—from its lucid brother, Winding through a fertile land: Palaces and tall cathedrals Crowding thick on either hand: From gay Seine is heard the summons,— Though the voice is soft that falls, It shall wake a thousand echoes, 'Tis for help in need it calls! From the Rhine and all its castles, From the Danube and its gloom, To the Neckar, gently flowing, Have the rapid tidings come. If within the heart of woman Springs the holy fire of love, Now, behold! the hour of danger All her constancy shall prove. If her boasted thoughts of duty Are not phantoms of the mind; If she dream of deeds of mercy And some glorious task would find: Let her quit all joy and pleasure, All the triumphs beauty gave, Home and quiet, power and leisure, And go forth—to help and save. War is on the earth again, War, subdued and charm'd so long— War, in all its dread and pain, All its suff'rings, grief and wrong: Ghastly war his chain has riven, And all earth to ruin given!— In the East, where rose the star Beaming rest and peace divine, Flashes far the meteor war And the nations mark its sign. “Sisters! there your brothers lie: Mothers! there your sons are prone: Wives! your husbands mangled die, Bleeding—fever'd—crush'd—alone! Not a hand to smooth the pillow, Nor the humble couch prepare: Not a voice to still the murmur: Not a word to soothe despair! Yet ye pity—weeping, wailing, Shudd'ring as the news goes round,— Rise! your feeble hands have vigour, Rise! for power your will has found.” See! they come—they crowd—they muster, Time is pressing—no delay! Where they pass the coldest welcome,— Nations speed them on their way. Prompt and steady, faithful, daring, Scorning all but truth and right, Never beamed a holier vision On some sainted hermit's sight: Than that band of pilgrims blest, Speeding onward to the East! Yon cape, that covered by the pall The deep dark cypress forests spread, Closed in by many a fair white wall, Reveals the mansions of the dead: Look! where the mosques and slender tow'rs O'er Scutari advance in air: No palaces or rosy bowers Are those that gleam at distance fair; There lie the sick on beds of pain, Unconscious of the scene, all light, The sparkling shore, the gardens bright, They may not hope to view again! The rash, the coward and the brave, The foe and friend, the low, the high, The gen'rous Frank, the Tartar slave, The Turk, the Arab, mingled lie. And round them flit an angel band That seem all wants, all pains to know: With noiseless step and tender hand As on from couch to couch they go. One fairy being hovers near A fainting hero's bed of pain, Dragged from a heap, and wounded sore, Scarce breathing,—many a bloody stain Is on his breast, as marble white, Seam'd with deep scars—a piteous sight! One arm hangs pow'rless, but her care Has bound it well—she watches now That sleep descending at her prayer, May calm the fever of his brow. He moves uneasily—his hand Presses his heart, as if in pain— She stoops, perchance that crimson band May his faint breath too much constrain. —She starts—why grows her cheek so pale? Why burst those tears she would control? Tells to her heart some mystic tale That silken purse—that crumpled scroll? Ah Lila! when those lines were traced No blood that snowy page defaced! Ah Lila! this lorn couch may tell Thy bird has done his mission well! But who is he, the brave distrest? So strangely thrown beneath her care Who cherish'd thus, even in his breast The words she wrote—how came they there? She knows that, leading on his band Where dangers most appall'd, he fell, That conquest followed his command, And those who mourn'd revenged him well. The day was won, and loud acclaim Hail'd victory, uncertain long: The air resounded Kh?lid's name Sought vainly by th' exulting throng: At length they found the mangled chief, Prone, where as thick his Arabs lie As lie in Autumn leaf on leaf The scattered blossoms left to die. Pierced through, but in his arms prest fast A boy lay dead, whose dauntless brow Told of the fatal struggle past For whom he died—alas! and how. Weep, Saba! many a widow's tear Shall flow like thine for sons as dear, Warm from their mother's parting kiss— Too young for glorious death like this! Joy, Lila, through thy tears may shine, For mingled bliss and pain are thine; Kh?lid's last hour thy eyes may see, But he may live—and live for thee! But not now may visions rise Gleaming in life's rapid tide; Kh?lid all unconscious lies, And his nurse has cares beside. Others ask her ready aid, And the debt to all is paid. Strange! the talisman that lay On his heart a shield had been, It had turn'd the blade away Glancing off, its folds between. And secure she keeps the spell That his life could guard so well, Till at length, his murmur'd pray'r Asks his treasure from her care. Long and sad her vigils grow; Still new terrors, day by day: Pain and agony and woe Fill each moment with dismay. Death, as seldom human eye Saw him in his horrors stand, Claims his own unceasingly, Grasping victims from her hand. Oft he paused where Kh?lid lay— Paused and glared—then strode away. Still the outstretch'd arms appal Still they reach—but do not fall. Till her watchful eye and hand Scares the vulture from his stand. Once more to breathe, to feel, to think! What rapture runs through ev'ry vein. The stricken chain sends, link by link, New hopes, new joys from heart to brain! Kh?lid looks up in wild surprise— An angel gazes in his eyes, A fairy arm is round him thrown, Life and its marvels—all his own! Sweet fall his words on Lila's ear That ask the cherish'd scroll again, And bid his nurse the story hear Of how the faithful bird was slain. How Youssouf's fate and his he found Circled within that narrow bound. —“How does a son of Syria's sky Our Northern speech thus understand, And to my questions make reply In accents of our Fatherland?” —“Know, gentle nurse, my father's line, Where Neckar flows, were lords of yore; And some neglected tower is mine Left, when he sought far Syria's shore. For angry words his kindred spoke, And his proud soul disdain'd the yoke. Methinks, nay, thou the tale may'st know, There is a mount, that long ago, Was famed for woman's truth and skill, When from past grief and present ill She rescued, by a hallowed jest, The tradition of the Weiber-Treue is well known. The castle of Weinberg being besieged, was defended by the women as well as the men within it. When forced to surrender at length, the victors generously gave permission to the females, who had shown so much courage, to carry off with them whatever treasure they prized the most. The robust heroines each shouldered her husband, and marched down the mountain triumphantly. The ruins of this famous castle are near Heilbronn, on the Neckar. ‘The treasure that she loved the best?’ —“Even so—the record still survives— The Mountain of the Faithful Wives. The castle there in ruin falls: Long arms of ivy clasp the walls. Deserted, and the heir unknown, The state, at length, will claim its own.” —“It may be that to me they come; And there the wand'rer finds a home. I feel these all too feeble hands Unmeet awhile to draw the sword, I dare not trust our scorching sands, And Northern climes may strength afford: And if I gain a heritage, 'Twill be a refuge for my age; And, gentle nurse, be sure for thee My castle gates shall open free!” He smiled—an answering smile to hide Lila has turn'd her head aside: “Go then,” she said, “and health and peace Shine on thy path, thy wand'rings cheer, But, till these fatal contests cease, My duty and my home are here.” PART V. THE CONTRAST “After hard struggles, pain and strife, Hostile to thought, destroying rest, Unwilling, cast in times unblest To battle on with feverish life; Midst savage foes, and friends as rude— Joy!—joy!—at length in solitude! “For the dread cannon's voice of fate, Quelling the earth, rending the sky; For blazing towns and shrieks of hate; And the spent hero's rallying cry; For plains, thick strewn—yet desolate— Where mangled forms, like sandheaps, lie— These to exchange, as in a dream, —A dream of terrors first, that cease And give the sleeper scenes that seem Glimpses of Heaven and radiant peace— For this bright wood and sunny sky, Roaming in careless liberty! To follow where the steep path leads Deeper and deeper in the shade, By fluttering, whispering branches made, To many a sudden-opening glade, That to the mazy wild succeeds: “Upon the soft, dry turf to lie Gazing upon the shining sky That gleams, a starry space between, Through flickering leaves of tender green: And, almost with a lover's look, To watch the fairy things that nod And quiver in this silent nook, Spangling the elastic velvet sod. “Harebells in groups, and many a cup That from its bank looks coyly up: White flowers with open eyes of day, And feathery grasses—all at play: Enamelled lizards glancing bright: Transparent creatures feathery-light, Humming and flitting to and fro As the soft breezes come and go: With nothing mute of all this throng Moving and wavering to song, But to the softest chords subdued To suit such fairy solitude. “And this the Northern summer time! And these the flowers a Northern clime All perfume and all bloom bestows? Methought our glowing crimson rose, Our tender nightingale alone Could in their fabled charms be known, Where the rich East, in jewelled pride Looks from her throne, a peerless bride. “Sweet nurse! how had it been with me, But for thy mercy and thy care? “This—this, and more, I owe to thee, Yet canst thou not my pleasure share! Thou gav'st me life and liberty, But no soft air, no birds, no flowers, Revive thy cheek and please thine eye— Sad watch is thine for countless hours; Scarce thanks, scarce notice dost thou gain, For all thy goodness, all thy pain! “And seldom will thy heart recall The thought of one—where many claim The aid thou giv'st alike to all, Heedless of rank or birth or fame: Working for pity's sake, alone, Unnamed, untalk'd of, and unknown!” Thus Kh?lid, health and strength renew'd, Of lost domains acknowledged heir, The past and all its pains review'd, And blest the present gleaming fair Why, o'er the azure of his sky Pass'd, ever and anon, a cloud? Why came a voice, that whisp'ringly Sigh'd softly first, then murmur'd loud, Still asking him if Lila's will Allows the time for selfish joy; If other's good and other's ill Like her's his anxious thoughts employ, Or if the high appeal sent forth Is cast aside as nothing worth? —Ah mandate, surely too severe, With youth and hope and pleasure here! Days went and came, and wand'ring still, Unsated with the charm of health, He felt his veins new vigour fill, And greedy of fond Nature's wealth, He sought her in wild woods and fields, And blest her for the good she yields, But even idle toil will tire, Pursued beneath an August sun: And, once, when, mounting ever high'r, He through the mazy woods had run, He came, just where a Druid stone, By some strong tempest's rage o'erthrown, Had formed an arch, as prone it fell, On two huge blocks whose granite might Upheld a temple on yon height Famed for the shrine of pagan Bel, But altar, temple, swept away, Wreathed with bright flowers the ruins lay. The peasant-legends whispered tales Of danger in that pleasant spot, But Kh?lid all unconscious hails The cool retreat and tranquil grot. Here, listless, at his ease he lies, In happy, dreamy, weariness, Watching the painted butterflies Whose quivering wings the leaves caress. Through the tall arch, beneath he sees The city's spires and palaces, The river, gliding gaily by, Blue as the bright tint of the sky, With snowy vessels dotted o'er; The lofty bridge from shore to shore: Rich walnut groves and woods of pine, Gardens and trellises of vine, Shining below in light and heat, While all is shade in his retreat, And the fresh breeze with whisp'ring tone, Comes rustling, sporting, whirling on. Sudden—a ringing laugh awakes The silence of the leafy brakes, And Kh?lid turns his half-shut eyes, Startled, at once, to strange surprise. Above, and peering curiously, Two bright blue eyes have met his own, A sweet face blushing—arch but shy, And white arms, clinging to the stone: Ringlets of sunny hair, thrown wild, A form of woman—yet a child, Is watching in gay, jesting mood This stranger to her native wood. And, nothing daunted by the gaze Admiring—rapt—her beauty drew, She still looks down, in sweet amaze, And claps her hands and laughs anew. A band of shining ivy twined Amidst the locks it could not bind, This from her graceful head she throws, And the wreath rests on Kh?lid's brows. He starts—a pleasure wild and new, His heart, his brain is rushing through. She speaks: “Art thou the stranger guest Sent to our shores from farthest East, Who, wand'ring in our wilds alone Hast slept beside the Druid's stone?” The same, sweet questioner—and where Dwell'st thou?—in wave or cloud or air; Or are these woody glades so blest To give a bird like thee her nest?” —“Yes,—yes,”—she wildly laugh'd—“to me These woods are, as these mountains, free; And I can lead thee, far and wide, Where never foot of man has been, Over the foamy torrent's side, —Down, headlong, thro' the deep ravine. If thou hast courage, come with me, And fairer marvels thou shalt see Than all the East has shown thee yet, And, in our Fatherland, forget Whatever made thee sad before; But, for a twelvemonth and a day Thou shalt my ev'ry sign obey, And think upon the past no more.” —“Bright vision! can I see those eyes Nor to thy wishes grant thee all? Oh teach me then thy mysteries, And take me as thy willing thrall Who, with a present like to this, Would look back to the past for bliss!” One instant as he spoke, a cloud Came o'er his heart, and Lila's pray'r Gleamed,—then was cover'd with a shroud— And the bright form rose lightly there. —“Better,”—she smiling said, “to live In all the joy that life can give, Than muse beneath a Druid stone And waste the hours of youth—alone.” She beckoned onward—and he stood Beside her, far beyond the wood. —“Tell me how to call thee, maiden, For thou fli'st so fast and far, 'Twere as easy for a mortal To o'ertake a shooting star.” Then she laugh'd, till every echo Sent the mirthful tidings round, —“Those who know me call me Minnè, Many seek, but few have found: Well my name they understand Minstrels of the Fatherland.” Minne in German signifies love. The Minne-Singers were minstrels of love.— —“Sweet Minnè—wherefore fly so fast? Wait till the heat of noon be past: Sweet Minnè!—yield one fond embrace!” —Again in yonder distant place, Perch'd on a height he sees her stay, As if she chid his long delay. Oh! what a wild pursuit—in vain— Midst flow'rs and sunshine, toil and pain, Hopes, wishes unfulfill'd, he strove To reach the goal of Minnè's love! Long earnest in the useless chase Deceived, but trusting in his speed, Following her sign, from place to place,— With her light laughter for his meed. Till, after twelve months and a day Beside the Druid stone he lay; And, as awakening from a dream Look'd down on city, forest, stream. Turn'd, where bright Minnè smiled before, But saw the lovely shape no more. THE VINTAGE. Red leaves on ev'ry terrace twine, And sunny clusters bend the vine, Boats, crowded with their luscious freight, On the swift river's margin wait, Then, with their store, row gaily home, For the full vintage time is come. All day the pleasant work goes on, And the broad moon looks smiling down On dances and on songs that cheer And welcome in the plenteous year. Joy! joy to all; but chief to these Of yon white village midst the trees; Not in their vintage only blest, But happy, above all the rest. For Lila's lonely castle grey Puts forth its welcome to the day; On every tower a pennon flies Gazed on by eager tear-bright eyes. Yet 'tis not that, the contest past, Peace comes with all her gifts at last; That nations, tired of strife, agree To grant to force what reason claim'd, And the spent world, a moment free, Looks on the angry past—ashamed:— For mighty interests that quell Empires and kingdoms little move The rustic race, content to dwell In their small world of strife and love: Whatever chance, of war or woe, Their mountains rise, their rivers flow. And Kh?lid mused: “How short the wings Of Fame and Glory!—paltry things! Unworthy to disturb the cheer A plenteous vintage gives us here. But why that pennon?—it may be Some chief return'd, perchance like me. Well is he loved for whose return Those joy bells ring, those joy fires burn!” —“Yes, loved indeed! but not to greet A chief we gaze from roof and wall, A young and gentle maid to meet Is the fond care that stirs us all: 'Tis Lila—we have ask'd in vain, Her weary absence none explain; Nor how, nor whence she comes is known, Enough—she is once more our own.” —“Lila!—that name all tongues repeat— Strangely it falls upon my ear, Till my heart's secret pulses beat With springing hope and sudden fear— If it should be!—but why create New hopes to be the jest of fate!” And will not yon bright stedfast star That shines on Lila's castle lone, Tell him he sought the treasure far That once before his path was thrown, And while his dreams the semblance crost, The truth was seen, yet sought—and lost. LILA'S RETURN. “Good Bernhard, who so well supplied My absence, with thy bounty large, Say, what has chanced of time and tide, Since truant Lila left her charge? Hour swell'd to day, and month to year— But she resumes her duties here.” —“The first long year had just declined When old Schloss-Adler's ruins grey, Assumed an aspect strangely gay, And whisper'd rumour, scarce defined, Spoke of the long-lost heir restored— He came, at length, the youthful lord, And, in his lofty brow and mien The ancient race was plainly seen. Though young, 'twas said already fame Had as a hero's shrined his name; 'Twould seem some valiant pagan band Had fought beneath his high command; His followers spoke of this, and told Of wild attacks, as fierce as bold;— Of rivers cross'd, where waters roll'd High as his breast, while cannon pour'd Its deadly hail to stop his course, Yet onward, with resistless force He cheer'd his warriors through the ford. A town besieged and famine-prest, By numbers girt, and sore distrest, By his prompt courage, strength and skill, Defended and triumphant still. At length struck down when fate decreed Conquest to one immortal day, Chance saved him in his utmost need, Mangled and dying as he lay. These tales we heard: and saw him pale And weak, at first, as oft his skiff Close by these walls at eve would sail And pause beneath the rosy cliff. He loved the wood, the rock, the glade, And, day by day, he roam'd alone; Till once—in evil hour betray'd, He slept beneath the Druid stone. 'Twas from that time a change was seen In the young Baron's mind and mien: The gayest of the idle gay, The theme of fashion's empty praise, Our modest maidens turn'd away Nor cared to meet his hardy gaze. But the light fair, whose lives pass by In butterfly variety, Hail'd the bold stranger in their train, As fickle as themselves—and vain! Condemn him not—but hear the rest. For me, I thought within his breast Some gen'rous spark would make us yet The error of wild youth forget. A year pass'd by—deserted, hoar, Frown'd old Schloss-Adler as of yore. At length, how altered!—back he came, Again his cheek was pale with care, But in his eye a brighter flame, For pity, tenderness, were there. Then knew we that the spell was past That for awhile his star o'ercast: And since— but, look on all around— His virtues in his deeds are found. Where Heilbronn lay, inert and still, Her quays destroy'd, her commerce lost, New towers, new mills, new vessels fill Her streets and wharfs with pride and cost, The poor no longer pine for bread, Fresh fields are till'd, fresh vineyards plann'd, Gardens along the rocks are spread, And plenty smiles upon the land, Ask who these prosp'rous changes made, From whence the help, the counsel came, Ask for the peasant's friend and aid, And hear young Baron Wilhelm's name.” —“Thanks, faithful Bernhard, for thy tale: Now haste, for ere the daylight fail, And the first ray of moonlight falls, My boat must reach Schloss-Adler's walls, That I may clasp that stranger's hand, And thank him for our Fatherland.” —“Alas! I had not told thee yet— Of late some evil chance he met, His wounds, they say, have bled again, And sick he lies, in dole and pain.” Like dews that fall on Syria's sea And change to pearls beneath the wave An Eastern Tradition attributes to the sea of Syria, the power of changing into pearls the drops of dew that fall into its waves. So Lila's tears fell fast and free, —But she can hasten—and may save. The sun had sunk; a soft, clear gloom Shrouded the sick man's silent room, And, as he mark'd the daylight die, He turn'd him, with a weary sigh. “Enough!”—he said:—“the task is done,— If late obedience can atone For follies past and wasted time, Lila may yet forgive my crime, Unless, like Minnè, but a shade Of promise to my fancy made! —At least, of good this dream is still— The other leading but to ill: Vainly on either may I call Frail hopes—that Death can cancel—all!” The young moon rising fair and new That moment sent a radiant stream Flooding the dusky chamber through: And—standing in the silver gleam, Close at his side a form is shown, And a soft hand has clasp'd his own. —“Kh?lid!—thy nurse is near thee yet, Be still—be calm—all care forget: 'Tis her's to tend thee and revive— Thine to obey her, and to live.” —“Oh, my sweet nurse, my guide, explain: Is this a fevered dream again? Cam'st thou in yonder moonbeams clear, My couch to watch, my soul to cheer? Art thou, in truth, a saviour sent, To hear my latest, lorn lament?” —“I come from one whose name alone An echo in thy heart,—is known: Who bids me well a brother tend— Who waits to greet and call thee friend. Revive, repay her care and mine, And Lila's—and my thanks are thine.” —“She is a vision, but thou art The truth—the life-spring of my heart! The name I have not ask'd or known Thy virtues and thy beauty own: But all I dreamt of good or wise Speaks in thy voice—shines in thy eyes: Holy and high let Lila be— But thou—oh, be thou all to me!” —“When first I knew thee—sick—in pain— 'Twere worse than vain to question then, And I, the nurse of wounded men, Foretold not we should meet again: To tend my charge with pious zeal Was all the care befitting me: Perchance some grateful throbs to feel Was all the thanks I ask'd of thee: Now—fortune smiles upon thy lot, And Lila's handmaid suits thee not.” —“Speak not of station or of state Those are but toys to minds like thine, Thou know'st the good alone are great, Thou know'st the only boon that Fate Can yield me is to call thee mine!” A bright flush pass'd o'er Lila's brow, Her heart thrill'd to a whispered word: “He loves me! 'tis no vision now. Oh, happy heart! the truth record!” Then with a smile of sweet disguise, She turn'd away her beaming eyes: —“No more: when we together sail, Where on yon cliff the moonlight falls, And Lila's lonely turrets hail, And stand within her castle walls: If thou forsake her love for mine, —And she has loved thee many a day— If she her cherish'd dream resign, Perchance I may not say thee nay.” Contentment is a leech of power, When tender eyes are watching too: And Kh?lid felt, from hour to hour, What hope and happiness can do. And soon, on silver Neckar's tide A bark with joyous freight shall guide Its course to where yon little bay Lies, with its rose-hued sentinel, Guarding that lonely castle well, The beacon of their onward way: The vales are filled with golden haze Rolling and twining wreaths of cloud, The peaks are flashing in the blaze That pierces through the misty shroud, And catch, upon their lances bright, The earliest gleam of morning's light— When the fresh wave it cleaves so fast Casts off the boat, and glitters past. Two wanderers climb the rocky stair, And on the shaded terrace rest,— —Above, the Stork's deserted nest Hangs quivering in the waving air. Then Kh?lid mark'd with soft surprise, Lila's bright cheek and glistening eyes, As on his arm she gently laid Her hand caressingly,—and said: “Dear Wilhelm! if no other come To bid thee welcome to thy home, Wilt thou regret at last to see Lila—thy dream—thy own, in me!” REWARD. And this—of all the wondrous throng Of visions that beset the mind, And lead, through devious mazes long, The striving heart at length may find, To crown life's ceaseless search for bliss, One love, one faith, one trust—like this! And the reward enough shall prove To those whose goal was truth and love: Who saw in all an object meet For pity and for sacrifice, Who wash'd the weary pilgrim's feet, Nor towards the banquet turn'd their eyes, Who strove, who serv'd, who bore, who wrought, Nor praise, nor power, nor triumph sought, No guerdon and no prize would claim, But blest the Giver when it came. Happy! who have not sought in vain For hearts that answer to their own, And happy too who nothing gain, But, patient still, work on alone Without dismay, without regret In the hard task by conscience set. Happy who find the open gate, But happy too—“who stand and wait.” L'ENVOYE. Flow, lovely Neckar!—winding—winding— Rejoicing in thy beauty's pride, The young and loving heart reminding What sunny tales thy legends hide. And let the minstrel, musing lonely, Amidst thy Paradise of flowers, Pouring his song for solace only, Like the wild bird within thy bowers: Long keep the record of the stories That cling to those fair heights of thine, Lost, almost, in the ancient glories Of yonder full and stately Rhine. And, if his solitary numbers One noble deed may yet inspire, Blest were his fever'd broken slumbers, And blest the tears that check his lyre! Oh that the world's great soul's requiring, Would lead to more than poet's dream! Even as fair Lila's high aspiring Is not a visionary theme. APPENDIX. Copy of the Paper attached to the Stork's neck, as transcribed by the Arab who shot the bird:— See Introduction. “Etent tues (étant toute) curieuse de savoir où nos cigognes passent le tems qu'elles nesont pas chez nous, j'ai eu l'idée de mettre à celui-ci ce colier et j'espère qu'il tombera dans des mains qui vondront bien medonner des renseignements que je désire et je vous prie de m'écrire par la poste sous l'adresse suivante, A Mademoiselle la Comtesse O. de G., à T. Silesie Prussienne, en Europe. Oh que je me rejouis de recevoir une lettre de l'Afrique, ou de l'Asie mais l (il) faut qu'elle soit très detaillée; vous me direz dans quel paysvous de meurez, quel est votre sauvveroin votre re ligion votre langue etsurtout votre som (nom) etvotre adresse. J'écris enfrancais parceque i est la ngue (il est la langue) la plus repandue dans le monde. On á seulem, ent pas fallu tier. (Il ne faut pas seulement tuer ?) This sentence was probably not grammatical in the original. The young lady evidently intended to say that the Stork was not to be killed for the sake of its collar. la pauvre bete a cause de son colier; je l'aime car etant petit il a passé deux jours dans ma chambre; parcequ' letait tomb (parce, qu'il était tombé) du nid, qui se trouve sur notre ecurie de mort (demi-mort?) ons. Celui qui lira cette lettre trouvera l'idée bien bizarre et surtout pour une jeune fille mais cest un desir que j'ai eu long tems et que je saurai enfin satisfaire a dieu lecteur de cette lettre j'espevous ne ferez (j'esperè que vous me ferez) le plaisir de me ri pon dre (répondre) Comtesse de G. O. (Signature of the Arab,) AABRAIM AALOSS. Letter of the Aunt of the young Countess to the Prussian Vice-Consul at Beyruth, in Syria. Monsieur, Permettez que ce soit moi qui vous exprime Monsieur le Consul! notre reconnaisance, de la grande bonté, avec la quelle vous avez bien voulu répondre à une petite étourderie de ma niéce la Comtesse O. de G. en Silesie. C'est fort heureux, que sa lettre soit tombée en des mains si bienveillantes, et soyez persuadé, Monsieur! que nous savons en aprécier tout le prix. Dans le nombre d'occupations importantes, vous donnez non seulement du tems, mais encore une amiable attention á la curiosité d'une campagnarde, qui étoit trop jeune pour entrevoir les consequences possibles de la mission de sa cigogne, entreprise sans conseil Losque' à mon arrivée cet êté en Silesie, elle m' en parla, et me montra toute heureuse, la réponse qu'elle avoit recu de Beyruth, dattée du 7 Mai, 1846, je fus tentée de croire que quelque voisin, instruite de cette singulière correspondance, lui avait fait parvenir une réponse imaginaire. Je l'ai promis de prendre ici à mon retour, les informations possibles, et que si elle répondoient essentiellement au contenu du récit de Beyruth, je me chargerois de vous priér, Monsieur! de confirmer ou desavouer, si c'est réellement a vous, que nous devons les détails du sort de la cigogne, qui ne se doute par de l'interêt qu'elle s'est attiré en Asie tant en Europe. Veuillez donc Monsieur! ajouter à vos bontés celle de me répondre ici par la voie de l'Ambassade Prussienne, qui veut avoir la complaisance de vous faire parvenir le courant. Votre réponse qui, j'espère ne sera pas retardée par les circonstances comme la mienne, est attendu avec impatience, et si elle contient la confirmation que c'est vous Monsieur, qu avoit reçu avec une indulgence vraiment paternelle ce dont cette pauvre cigogne était chargée, je vous assure une reconnaissance bien sentie et vous prie Monsieur le Consul d'en agréer l'expression, ainsi que de celle de la haute considération que vous inspirez à Votre trés obéissante servante, Barone de H., Nee Comtesse de G. Vienne, le 20 Oct 1846. Answer of the Young Countess to the Vice-Consul. T—, 25th March, 1847. Sir, It is a great pleasure to me to be able to answer you in your own language, which I hope you will like better than French. I must begin with begging your pardon for a great many faults you will find in this letter; but it is only a short time that I am learning the English language. I am very obliged to you for your letters, which I received both, and they afforded me the utmost pleasure and surprise, as I never thought of the possibility to get an answer to my note, which I feared would be loosed. You will surely be astonished that I not wrote before, but there were so many of my acquaintances who confirmed me in the idea that it was a joke, and only now my aunt at Vienna writes me, that the letters are indeed from you, I took the resolution to write to you. Accept, therefore, my thanks for your letter. I got what I was longing for in sending away the stork, news from a distant land. I also received a letter from Monsieur de Wildenbruck, The Prussian Minister at Constantinople. who tells me that my dear stork has been shot, and this difference in his letter and yours, in which I found that it was still living, made me believe that all was a joke from somebody. I (it) was very cruel of me to sacrifice an animal I loved so much, and I should not have forgotten that I (it) is impossible to get a message without killing the messenger, and never should console myself if not the bird's death had given me news from you, which pleased me infinitely. Now, my honoured sir, I have nothing more to add; I fully pronounced to you the pleasure and satisfaction I had, when receiving your letter, so that I hope you wont fail to renew the correspondence when something interesting happens in your country; you know my curiosity, though satisfied at present by your kind amiability, is a thing that must be fed now and then, else it is getting impetuous if it comes to this point again, I shall take the liberty of sending another messenger, but I don't tell whether it shall be by air, steam, or water; air has proved successful, so perhaps I shall try the other powers. Till then, believe with high respects for your punctuality and kind regarde for your complaisance, Sir! Your very obliged, O. Countess G. A Monsieur O., Vice-Consul de sa Majesté le Roi de Prusse, à Beyrout. That Lila's yearning for the unknown is no fiction, the following anecdote, supplied by the Crimean Correspondent of the Morning Herald newspaper, and published while this poem was passing through the press, furnishes additional proof:— “You are well aware of the donations to the British soldiery sent out from the fair sex in England, from the lowliest cottager to the very highest lady in the realm. Among the presents were some flannel shirts. One of these fell to the lot of Sergeant— the other day (I am requested not to print the name, but I know the man well); this shirt he opened, and then, inside it, he discovered, carefully pinned, a lock of hair and the following letter, which I subjoin verbatim. The letter is directed thus:— “‘This is for you And I hope it is A young man if not Give it tou won.’” Inside, the words run thus:— “My dear Friend,—I write those few lines to you hoping that they Cheer you A little. I think you are dull, but God will hulp you. I am A young woman And I hope that you are A young man, this is my hire (sic. for hair) Keep it for My sake “from “Mary. “You are now lafing, it is bad writing.” So ends the letter. Neither country nor town is mentioned in it. It was wafered, not sealed, and the stamp on the envelope is a “forget-me-not.” The lock of hair enclosed is light brown in colour, and plaited in three, tied with blue and yellow silk threads. Who is Mary?”</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Copy of the Paper attached to the Stork's neck, as transcribed by the Arab who shot the bird:— See Introduction. “Etent tues (étant toute) curieuse de savoir où nos cigognes passent le tems qu'elles nesont pas chez nous, j'ai eu l'idée de mettre à celui-ci ce colier et j'espère qu'il tombera dans des mains qui vondront bien medonner des renseignements que je désire et je vous prie de m'écrire par la poste sous l'adresse suivante, A Mademoiselle la Comtesse O. de G., à T. Silesie Prussienne, en Europe. Oh que je me rejouis de recevoir une lettre de l'Afrique, ou de l'Asie mais l (il) faut qu'elle soit très detaillée; vous me direz dans quel paysvous de meurez, quel est votre sauvveroin votre re ligion votre langue etsurtout votre som (nom) etvotre adresse. J'écris enfrancais parceque i est la ngue (il est la langue) la plus repandue dans le monde. On á seulem, ent pas fallu tier. (Il ne faut pas seulement tuer ?) This sentence was probably not grammatical in the original. The young lady evidently intended to say that the Stork was not to be killed for the sake of its collar. la pauvre bete a cause de son colier; je l'aime car etant petit il a passé deux jours dans ma chambre; parcequ' letait tomb (parce, qu'il était tombé) du nid, qui se trouve sur notre ecurie de mort (demi-mort?) ons. Celui qui lira cette lettre trouvera l'idée bien bizarre et surtout pour une jeune fille mais cest un desir que j'ai eu long tems et que je saurai enfin satisfaire a dieu lecteur de cette lettre j'espevous ne ferez (j'esperè que vous me ferez) le plaisir de me ri pon dre (répondre) Comtesse de G. O. (Signature of the Arab,) AABRAIM AALOSS.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Letter of the Aunt of the young Countess to the Prussian Vice-Consul at Beyruth, in Syria. Monsieur, Permettez que ce soit moi qui vous exprime Monsieur le Consul! notre reconnaisance, de la grande bonté, avec la quelle vous avez bien voulu répondre à une petite étourderie de ma niéce la Comtesse O. de G. en Silesie. C'est fort heureux, que sa lettre soit tombée en des mains si bienveillantes, et soyez persuadé, Monsieur! que nous savons en aprécier tout le prix. Dans le nombre d'occupations importantes, vous donnez non seulement du tems, mais encore une amiable attention á la curiosité d'une campagnarde, qui étoit trop jeune pour entrevoir les consequences possibles de la mission de sa cigogne, entreprise sans conseil Losque' à mon arrivée cet êté en Silesie, elle m' en parla, et me montra toute heureuse, la réponse qu'elle avoit recu de Beyruth, dattée du 7 Mai, 1846, je fus tentée de croire que quelque voisin, instruite de cette singulière correspondance, lui avait fait parvenir une réponse imaginaire. Je l'ai promis de prendre ici à mon retour, les informations possibles, et que si elle répondoient essentiellement au contenu du récit de Beyruth, je me chargerois de vous priér, Monsieur! de confirmer ou desavouer, si c'est réellement a vous, que nous devons les détails du sort de la cigogne, qui ne se doute par de l'interêt qu'elle s'est attiré en Asie tant en Europe. Veuillez donc Monsieur! ajouter à vos bontés celle de me répondre ici par la voie de l'Ambassade Prussienne, qui veut avoir la complaisance de vous faire parvenir le courant. Votre réponse qui, j'espère ne sera pas retardée par les circonstances comme la mienne, est attendu avec impatience, et si elle contient la confirmation que c'est vous Monsieur, qu avoit reçu avec une indulgence vraiment paternelle ce dont cette pauvre cigogne était chargée, je vous assure une reconnaissance bien sentie et vous prie Monsieur le Consul d'en agréer l'expression, ainsi que de celle de la haute considération que vous inspirez à Votre trés obéissante servante, Barone de H., Nee Comtesse de G. Vienne, le 20 Oct 1846.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Answer of the Young Countess to the Vice-Consul. T—, 25th March, 1847. Sir, It is a great pleasure to me to be able to answer you in your own language, which I hope you will like better than French. I must begin with begging your pardon for a great many faults you will find in this letter; but it is only a short time that I am learning the English language. I am very obliged to you for your letters, which I received both, and they afforded me the utmost pleasure and surprise, as I never thought of the possibility to get an answer to my note, which I feared would be loosed. You will surely be astonished that I not wrote before, but there were so many of my acquaintances who confirmed me in the idea that it was a joke, and only now my aunt at Vienna writes me, that the letters are indeed from you, I took the resolution to write to you. Accept, therefore, my thanks for your letter. I got what I was longing for in sending away the stork, news from a distant land. I also received a letter from Monsieur de Wildenbruck, The Prussian Minister at Constantinople. who tells me that my dear stork has been shot, and this difference in his letter and yours, in which I found that it was still living, made me believe that all was a joke from somebody. I (it) was very cruel of me to sacrifice an animal I loved so much, and I should not have forgotten that I (it) is impossible to get a message without killing the messenger, and never should console myself if not the bird's death had given me news from you, which pleased me infinitely. Now, my honoured sir, I have nothing more to add; I fully pronounced to you the pleasure and satisfaction I had, when receiving your letter, so that I hope you wont fail to renew the correspondence when something interesting happens in your country; you know my curiosity, though satisfied at present by your kind amiability, is a thing that must be fed now and then, else it is getting impetuous if it comes to this point again, I shall take the liberty of sending another messenger, but I don't tell whether it shall be by air, steam, or water; air has proved successful, so perhaps I shall try the other powers. Till then, believe with high respects for your punctuality and kind regarde for your complaisance, Sir! Your very obliged, O. Countess G. A Monsieur O., Vice-Consul de sa Majesté le Roi de Prusse, à Beyrout.</field>
   </doc>
</add>