<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Trench, Herbert, 1865-1923</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Trench, Herbert, 1865-1923</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">trench herbert 1865 1923</field>
      <field name="author_text">Trench, Herbert, 1865-1923</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1920's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.1832.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1924</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:467051</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Poems with Fables in Prose ; By Frederic Herbert Trench</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Poems with Fables in Prose ; By Frederic Herbert Trench</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poems with fables in prose</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poems with fables in prose</field>
      <field name="title_text">Poems with Fables in Prose ; By Frederic Herbert Trench</field>
      <field name="year_display">1924</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1924</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1924</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467051&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467051&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Trench, Herbert, 1865-1923&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;trench herbert 1865 1923&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Poems with Fables in Prose ; By Frederic Herbert Trench&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poems with fables in prose&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1924&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1924&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Trench, Herbert&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1865&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1923&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poems with Fables in Prose&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By Frederic Herbert Trench&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Jonathan Cape&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1924&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp3971&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;2 v.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poems with Fables in Prose&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By Frederic Herbert Trench&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 394 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I:NARRATIVE POEMS DEIRDRE WEDDED This narrative poem, published some years before the plays, “Deirdre” of Synge, or the “Deirdre” of W. B. Yeats, does not cover any of the ground touched by these poets. In fact the episode of thirty hours, narrated by the Three Voices, does not, with the exception of two incidents, occur in any of the versions of the famous “Tragical Tale of the Sons of Usnach.” The manner of Deirdre's wooing of Naois is, however, based on an occurrence in a Gaelic version of that tale, in which, on a day (although not, as in this narrative, her marriage day) Deirdre and her women companions “were out on the hillock behind the house enjoying the scene and drinking in the sun's heat. What did they see coming but three men a-journeying. Deirdre was looking at the men that were coming, and wondering at them. When the men neared them, Deirdre remembered the language of the huntsmen, and she said to herself that these were the three sons of Usnach, and that this was Naois, he having what was above the bend of his two shoulders above the men of Erin all.” The three brothers went past without taking any notice of them, and without even glancing at the young girls on the hillock. “What happened but that love for Naois struck the heart of Deirdre, so that she could not but follow after him. She trussed her raiment and went after the three men that went past the base of the knoll, leaving her women attendants there. Aillean and Ardan had heard of the woman that Connachar, King of Ulster, had with him, and they thought that if Naois their brother saw her he would have her himself, more especially as she was not married to the king.” They perceived the woman coming, and called on one another to hasten their steps as they had a long distance to travel and the dusk of night was coming on. They did so. She cried three times, “Naois, son of Usnach, wilt thou leave me?” “What cry is that which it is not well for me to answer, and not easy for me to refuse?” Twice the brothers put him off with excuses. “But the third time Naois and Deirdre met, and Deirdre kissed Naois three times, and a kiss to each of his brothers.” The other incidents in the episodic poem “Deirdre Wedded” are new. They are grounded on knowledge of the localities named. Fintan; Urmael; Cir These were old bards. A tomb like that of Cir, caverned through a hill-ridge, has been found and explored not far from Eman and Armagh, just as it is described in the poem. But the curious may rediscover it for themselves. Connachar This king, or terrestrial divinity, is generally known as Conchobar, or Conor, King of Ulster (Uladh) and Arch-King of Ireland. He is chronicled as reigning about the time of the incarnation of Christ. Eman Eman, or Emain Macha, was the chief palace of Connachar. It is still seen and named in the “Navan Ring”—enormous earthworks on a hill about two miles west of Armagh. The people from the town and countryside still go up to dance there on holidays. Traces of the Lake of Pearls—into which jewels were cast on a sudden flight—lie in a marsh under Eman. The Callan, or “loud-sounding” river, runs not very far off. Dun Aengus A pre-historic stone fortress—singularly vast —on the edge of the cliffs of Arran Môr, one of the Aran Islands in the Atlantic, west of Galway. The walls are very massive, and were originally built half-cricle-wise, as though half of the ring had broken off and fallen into the sea. I: THE CHANTERS I I stood on the Hill of Time when the sun was fled, And my vision sought where to rest, till it knew the plains Of my country, the Night's harp, and the moonless bed Of rivers and bristling forests and sea-board chains. II And from many a chanter's mound—none is nameless there— Could I hear, amid rumour eternal, the voice ascend. With the bones of man endureth his floating hair, And the song of his spirit on earth is slow to end. III Speak to me, speak to me, Fintan, dark in the south, From the west Urmael, and Cir, lying under the pole, Some chant that ye made, who never spake mouth to mouth, But over the ridge of ages from soul to soul! IV And a strain came out of Dun Tulcha, the yew's shores, From Fintan, the elder than yews, the too old for tears, “Let us tell him of Deirdre wed, that his heart's doors Resound, as when kings arrive, with the trees of spears.” 2: VOICE OF FINTAN Out of the First Century O sightless and rare-singing brotherhood! It was the night when Connachar, high king Of the four kingdoms, took to wife at last Deirdre, the wise one, the thrice-beautiful; It was the night of marriage. Word had sped, Tokens gone out to every rath and ring And every pasture on the woody knolls Green about Eman, of the slaughter blithe Of sheep and boar, of badger and of stag, Reddening the ways up to the kingly house— Of sheep and goats and of the stintless food That should be poured out to his beggary By Connachar, that all time should remember The night he wed the girl from the elf-mound. Yonside of Assaroe his swineherd found her Bred in a peaty hillock of the west By one old crone. Though tribeless she and wild— Barefoot, and in the red wool chasing cattle Connachar saw and took, biding his time, And let queens give her skill the winter long In webs and brews and dyes and broideries Up to this night of marriage. Fabulous, O friends, and dark, and mighty, was his house, The beam-work in its dome of forest trunks— They that had been the chantries of the dawn To blacken songless through a thousand years:— But never since they sway'd buds in the glens Or spun the silken-floating violet gleam Had those spars groan'd above so fierce a breath Rich with the vapour of the boar! For now Hundreds with ruddy-glistening faces ran Jostling round the nine shadows of the blaze And spread with skins the lengthy beds of men And soused warm spice of herbs in ale. Here—thither— Was rousing of age-slumber'd horns, arranging Smooth banks throughout the house, strawing of rushes, And cauldrons humm'd before the empty throne Set high in the shadow of the wall, and bubbled Inaudible, impatient for the king. But while outside the black roof on the mount Wide-wafted sank the sun's divinity On swooning wings, the Lake of Pearls far down Curdled beneath the unseen seed of rain. Ramparts run there that by-gone prisoners Bore once in bags of slime up from the lake For barriers of the house they most abhorr'd. And on the hill-side, where that rampart old Dips lowest to the lakeward, Deirdre stood, Hearing from distant ridges the faint bleat Of lambs perturb the dusk—bleats shivering out Like wool from thorns—there the young Deirdre stood, Like the moon whose climbing beauty pales the world, Looking far off on hills whence she was come. Mountains that lift the holiness of Fire! Fortitudes, ye that take the brunt of fate! Send her across the bog a little cloud Full of the ancient savours, full of peace, And for its drops she will hold up her heart, O ye that stand in heaven, far removed! She ask'd aloud, Wherefore were greens so bare That but an hour ago shook with the thud Of racers and of hurlers? Was it late? The wrinkled nurse replied, Had the child eyes? Back from a hosting and a desperate prey For corn and mares and rustless brass and beeves Naois, with the rest of Usnach's sons, Had come. She had seen him weary go but now Heavily up the steep through the king's hedge. Now on the hill-top, while the woman spoke, So chanced it. Hanging on the young man's lips The hosts sway'd round him, and above the press Connachar, glittering all in torques of gold And writhen armlets, listen'd from the mound Of judgment, by the doom-oak at his door. His beak'd helm took the sunset, but he held His flint-red eyes in shadow and averse. And when before him, dark as a young pine, Unmoved the son of Usnach had told all; How half his folk had perish'd in the task By plague or battle, and how poor a spoil Was driven home, the king cried: “Paragon! We must go griddle cakes in honey for him! Bring lavers of pale gold to wash off blood So precious to us!” Since for many moons This champion had forsworn the face of softness And stretched his hungers to the sleety rock, Call in the smile of women to unlatch From his grim ribs the iron:—Faugh! Away! Let Usnach's sons take out again that night Their broken clans, their piteous cattle thence; Defeated men should see his gates no more. The son of Usnach turn'd and went. He ran Down hill and to the loch to wash his wounds Chanting—his dark curls waver'd in the wind— Chanting he strode, tossing a brace of spears, Lest we should think him humbled. Halfway down The shapes of women loiter'd in the dusk And one held backward out her arms to take The latchets of her cloak. But as Naois Pass'd by them, closely as is heard a sigh— His vehement flood of soul fierce for the mere— Glancing not right nor left, O then I saw The foot of Deirdre stricken motionless— I saw the stiff cloak many-colour'd sink Slow to the grass, wrinkling its blazon'd skins Behind her. Gloom suck'd in the banqueters; And from the warmth of drinking at his feast Connachar sent forth to the women's house; And heralds bade bring also the grey seer, Cathva, though Cathva had not will'd to come. But hardly had those erranders gone out When rose the door-hide: the grey seer came in Noiseless. He was of fog the night hath spun, Earth in his hair and on his meagre cheek, Consumed and shaking, ragged as seaweed, And to the throne he cried: “Why hast thou called Me to carousal? Is this bed my work? Nay—too great clearness underneath the thunder Shew'd insupportably the things to be. Too long have I, with glamours, drops and runes Shook round her cabin low my skirts of storm, Far hence, round her peaty hillock in the west, To shield thee from that devastating face. My fault is only that I slew her not. Know! it was I that, seeing those cradled limbs Bright with disaster for the realm and thee, When she no more was than a litling babe Flung her away among sea-warding Mountains. But Muilréa to Ben Gorm said:What is this? What glee is this disturbs our desolation? I hear another than the wild duck sheering Sidelong the wind. Tall as a rush is she, Sweet as the glitter of the netted lakes! And Ben Gorm answer'd:We are sick alone: Let us distil the heavens into a child! Yea, let our bones appear, the black goat starve Upon our heads, yet shall this wafted seed Superabound with ripeness we forgo. Dark space shall come to heart—silvers of mists— And thou, blue depth of gorges! Connachar, I heard the plotters, but I let her live!” And the king ask'd, “Hath any seen her there?” And Cathva answer'd, “Till thy herdsman found her She knew not that men were.” Then Connachar Commanded yet again, “Bring us in Deirdre!” Straightway a woman like the claw of birds, Decrepit, bright of eye, and innocent, Stood up beyond the fire. Her fingers play'd— Play'd with a red stone at her breast. He ask'd, “Who gave thee, hag, the jewel on thy bosom?” Now every drinker from the darkest stalls Perceived the brooch was Deirdre's, and a gift To her from Connachar. Aghast, the woman Fumbled at her sere breast, and wept and said, “It was a gift to me, O Connachar, This night.” And he, consummate lord of fear, Our never-counsell'd lord, the Forest-odour'd, That kept about his heart a zone of chill, Smiled, though within the gateway of his fort A surmise crept, as 'neath a load of rushes Creeps in the stabber. “Fix the pin, Levarcham, For she that loses such a brooch will grieve. Why comes not Deirdre?” “Sir, she is not yet Duly array'd, and so is loth to come.” O, then, believe me, all the floor was hush, But a mad discordancy like fifes, drums, brasses,— Bondmen of old was on the winds released— Shook every beam and pillar of the house; And the king said—“Thou hear'st out of the marsh Scream of my stallions mounting on the gale?” And she said, “Yea.” “Thou knowest round these walls How many chariots now are tilted up?” And she said, “Yea.” “Then, woman, bring with haste Deirdre, thy charge, into this presence now, Or limb from limb upon the pleasant grass Those wheels shall parcel thee at dawn!” And she, Levarcham that was nurse to Deirdre's childhood, Lifted her hands and closed her eyes and sang: “She will come back, but I, I shall not bring her! O rainbow breathed into the dreadful pine, Why art thou gone from me? Dearer to me Than the sobbing of the cuckoo to the shore, Why art thou gone from me?” She bow'd and wept. And Connachar came from the throne, and grasping, As if he felt no heat, the cauldron's brims, Lean'd through its steams, watching the nurse and said, “Will these afflicting tears bring Deirdre in?” But she look'd up and said: “How shall I bring her? Look now outside thy door, O Connachar! The black oak with the vision-dripping boughs Whose foot is in thy father's blood of pride Stagger'd as I came up in the night-blast. In vain it stretches angers to the sky: It cannot keep the white moon from escape To sail the tempest; nor, O king, canst thou!” The cheek of him that listened grew thrice-pale And his thick nostrils swell'd, his half-shut eyes Fang'd sheen, and slow dilated; stubbornly He clutch'd to steady his convulsive frame The sea-full cauldron; quick, with efforts vast, Upheaved and swung and pillar'd it on high— And hoarsely bade, “Take torches!” Every man Kindled in silence at the hearth divine. Then Connachar pour'd out upon the blaze The flood within the vat. The roofs were fill'd With darkness foul, with hissings and with smoke. . . . 3: VOICE OF CIR Out of a Century more remote, but unknown As a horseman breaks on a sea-gulf enwombed in the amber woods Where tide is at ebb, and out on the airy brim Glass'd upon cloud and azure stand multitudes Of the flame-white people of gulls—to the sky-line dim All breast to the sun,—and his hoofs expand the desolate strait Into fevers of snows and ocean-wandering cries: Even so, chanters divine, in some woman's fate At coming of him to be loved do her dreams arise. And Deirdre, the exquisite virgin, pale as the coat of swans, Took the flame of love in her heart at the time of dew, And clad her in ragged wool from a coffer of bronze, And walked in the chill of night, for her soul was new. “Why thick with the berries of sweetness, ye barren thorns of the spring? I could drink up this tempest cold as a burning wine. Why laugh, my grief, for art thou not bride of a king, And the drinkers drink to a couch array'd to be thine?” Where the wounded toss without sleep in the warrior's hive of stones— The house Bron Bhearg—she laid her cheek to the wall And bless'd them by stealth, with no pang at the sound of groans, Having that in her rich heart which could heal them all. To the fortress-gate on the steep that looketh toward Creeve Roe She fled, and spied, not a sling-cast off, the flare Of a torch, and the skull fixed over the gate. And lo, To the right hand watchmen paced by the water there. And the shag-hair'd guard, with a mock, laid spears in their passage house Athwart; for who was this phantom over the grass Like a filcher of food? And Deirdre uncover'd her brows And cried, “I am Deirdre!” And sullen they gave her the pass. And towards Creeve Roe the dip of the cuckoo's vale was dark To blindness. She pluck'd her steps on that miry road Through copses alive with storm, till at length a spark Shew'd the forge where the smith on the heroes' way abode. Now Culann, the smith, was wise; and leaping her spirit stirr'd With the soft roar of his hide-wing'd fire as it soar'd: “Has the son of Usnach pass'd?” “Yea, gone back!” With the word He smote on a ribbon of iron to make him a sword. And the argentine din of anvils behind her steadily dwindling The woman fled to the wastes, till she came to a Thorn Black, by the well of a God, with stars therein kindling And over it rags fluttering from boughs forlorn. And she knelt and shore with a knife a lock of her deathless hair, And leash'd the black-shuddering branch with that tress, and pray'd: “Sloe-tree, thou snow of the darkness, O hear my prayer, And thou, black Depth, bubble-breather, vouchsafe thine aid; “From Connachar's eyes of love let me hide as a grey mole, Sons of the Earth's profound, that no weeper spurn! I have look'd on a face, and its kindness ravish't my soul, But deliverance pass'd; unto you for escape I turn.” And loud as the sloven starlings in winter whistle and swarm Came the banish'd of Usnach nigh, thrice fifty strong, As they drove from Eman away on that night of storm; And Naois spoke with his brothers behind the throng: “O Aillean, O Ardan, hark! What cry was that? For some cry Rang on my soul's shield; hark! hear ye it now?” But they rein'd not their weary chariots, shouting reply: “It was fate, 'twas the curs't hag that is crouch'd on a bough!” Tossing they drove out of sight, Naois the last, and his hood Rain-dripping mantled the wind. One ran like a roe, And call'd on that great name from the night-bound wood: “Stay, long-awaited, stay! for with thee I go!” And his brothers cried, “Halt not! the host of the air makes moan, Or a gang of the wild geese, going back to the lake!” But Naois rear'd up the deep-ribb'd Sr?n: “Good Sr?n, Thou and I needs must turn for our fame's sake.” And he heard a voice: “Son of Usnach, take me to be thy wife!” He bent from the withers, the blaze of her, trembling, drew The breath from his lips and the beat from his heart's life; And he said, “Who art thou, Queen?” But himself knew. And he mutter'd, “Return, return, unto him that I hate! For know, Him least of all I rob, least of all that live!” But she cried: “Am I then a colt, that ye snare from a foe With a bridle's shaking? I am mine own to give!” “Thy beauty would crumble away in the spate of my wild nights, And famine rake out thine embers, the lean paw Of jeopardy find thee. He is not rich in delights Whose harp is the grey fell in the winter's flaw!” And she laid her arm round the neck of Sr?n: “Hast heard, Horse swollen-vein'd from battle, insulter of death— Whose back is only a perch for the desert bird— Whose fore-hooves fight—whose passage is torn with teeth: “And dost thou not shudder off the knees of a master deaf To the grief of the weak?” And the lad, deeply-moved, rejoins, “Mount, then, O woman, behind me!”—and light as a leaf Drawing her up from his foot to the smoking loins Shook loose the ox-hide bridle. Even as the great gull dives From Muilréa's moon-glittering peak when the sky is bare, Scraped naked by nine days' wind, and sweepingly drives Over night-blurred gulfs and the long glens of the air, And feels up-tossing his breast an exhaustless breath bear on Spouted from isleless ocean to aid his flight— So fiercely, so steadily gallop'd the sinewy Sr?n, Braced by that double burden to more delight. Though his mane wrapp'd a wounded bridlehand, fast, fast As giddy foam-weltering waters dash'd by the hoof Flee away from the weirs of Callan, even so pass'd Dark plains away to the world's edge, behind and aloof. And the rider stoop'd and whisper'd, amidst the thunder of weirs, Such sweetness of praise to his horse in the swirl of the flood, That Sr?n twitch'd back for an instant his moonèd ears Strain'd forth like a hare's, as his haunches up to the wood Wrested them. Beaks of magic, the wreckage of time, came out, And talon'd things of the forest would waft and sway; But Naois raised unforgotten that battle-shout That scatters the thrilling wreath of all fears away. So they measured the Plain of the Dreamers, the Brake of the Black Ram, Till the Crag of the Dances before them did shape and loom, And the Meads of the Faery Hurlers in silver swam; Then up to the Gap of the Winds, and the far-seen tomb White on Slieve Fuad's side. By many a marchland old And cairn of princes—yea, to mine own bedside— They adventured! Think ye, sweet bards, that I could lie cold When my chamber of rock fore-knew that impassion'd stride? Had I, too, not pluck'd the webs of rain-sweet drops from the harp, And torn from its wave of chords an imperishable love To sleep on this breast? For here through the mountain sharp My grave-chamber tunnell'd is, and one door from above Westward surveys green territories, gentle with flowers and charm; But forth from the eastern face of the ridge is unquell'd Wilderness, besown with boulders and grass of harm. Even in my trance could I feel those riders approach, and beheld Naois assault the ridge, to the wilderness setting his face Expectant, unconscious, as one whom his foes arouse; His heart was a forge, his onset enkindled space, He shook off the gusty leagues like locks from his brows. What should he reck of Earth save that under his wounds he felt Stolen round him, as dreamy water steals round a shore, A girdle, the arms of Deirdre, clasp'd for a belt That terror of main kings should unlock no more? I was caught from the grave's high gate as that spume-flaked ecstasy drew Upward, and wing'd like the kiss of Aengus, strove For utterance to greet them—encircling their heads that flew— But who lops the whirlwind's foot or outdreameth love? He wheel'd round Sr?n on the crest. Abrupt he flung back a hand And spoke: “Dost thou know the truth? Look where night is low! Soon the ants of that mound shall shake the ledge where we stand; Now the tribes are summon'd, the Night prepares his blow; “Now wrath spurts hot from the trumpet—the main beacon flares— Now tackle the arrogant chariots-dogs in their glee Hang on the leash-slaves, numb in the cockcrow airs. Why, out of all that host, hast thou singled me?” I heard her behind him breathe, “Because out of all that host Aptest art thou in feats, held in honour more Than any save bright Cuchullain!” He turn'd as one lost: “Is this time a time to mock? Are there not four-score “Better at feats than I; my masters, the noble teams, The attemper'd knights of the Red Branch every one? Nay, though I knead up the whole earth in my dreams, Nought to such men am I, who have nothing done!” I heard the blowings of Sr?n, and then lasting words: “I choose Thee—wherefore? Ah, how interpret? Today on the slope Where first by the wall I saw thee at gloam of dews I knew it was fated. It was not some leaf of hope “Eddying. Thou wast the token—half of the potter's shard— That a chief beleaguer'd cons in his desperate camp Pass'd in by some hand unseen to the outmost guard, And fits to the other half by his wasted lamp. “Seeing thee, I knew myself to be shaped of the self-same clay— Half of the symbol—but broken, mayhap to serve As language to them of the night from powers of the day!” By the path of the throbbing curlew no step may swerve Where they rode through the Gap; and at last she murmur'd, “Dost grieve at me still?” And he said: “Glorious is it to me that behind us pursuit Shall be wide as the red of the morning; for thou art my will! To the beach of the world of the dead, and beyond it to boot, “Let me take and defend thee!” In silence the hearts of the twain were screen'd; But crossing the mires and the torrents I saw strange ease Afloat, like a spark, on the woman's eyes as she lean'd Forth, and a shadow betwixt her lips like peace! 4: VOICE OF URMAEL Out of the Sixth Century The slender Hazels ask'd the Yew like night Beside the river-green of Lisnacaun: “Who is this woman beautiful as light Sitting in dolour on thy branchèd lawn, With sun-red hair, entangled as with flight, Sheening the knees up to her bosom drawn? What horses mud-besprent so thirstily Bellying the hush pools with their nostrils wide?” And the Yew, old as the long mountain-side, Answer'd, “I saw her hither with Clan Usnach ride!” “Come, love, and climb with me Findruim's woods Alone!” Naois pray'd. Through broom and bent Strewn with swift-travelling shadows like their moods, Leaving below the camp's thin cries, they went; And never a tress, escaping from her snoods, Made the brown river with a kiss content, So safe he raised up Deirdre through the ford. Thanks, piteous Gods, that no foreboding gave He should so bear her after to the grave, Breasting the druid ice, breasting the phantom wave! “O, bear me on,” she breathed, “for ever so!” And light as notes the Achill shepherd plays On his twin pipes, they wanton'd light and slow Up the broad valley. Birds sail'd from the haze Far up, where darkling copses over-grow Scarps of the grey cliff from his river'd base. Diaphaneity, the spirit's beauty, Along the dimmèd combes did float and reign, And many a mountain's scarry flank was plain Through nets of youngling gold betrimm'd with rain. But when an upward space of grass—so free— So endless—beckon'd to the realms of wind Deirdre broke from his side, and airily Fled up the slopes, flinging disdains behind, And paused, and round a little vivid tree The wolf-skins from her neck began to bind. Naois watch'd below this incantation; Then upward on his javelin's length he swung To catch some old crone's ditty freshly sung, Bidding that shoot be wise, for yet 'twas young. With gaze in gaze, thus ever up and on Roved they, unwitting of the world outroll'd, Their ears dinn'd by the breeze's clarion That quicks the blood while yet the cheek is cold; Great whitenesses rose past them, brooks ran down, And step by step Findruim bare and bold Uplifted. So a swimmer is uplifted, Horsed on a streaming shoulder of the Sea, Our hasty master, who to such as we Tosses some glittering hour of mastery. They heard out of the zenith swoop and sting Feathery voices, keen and soft and light: “Mate ye as eagles mate, that on the wing Grapple—heaven-high—hell-deep—for yours is flight! Souls like the granite candles of a king, Flaming unshook amid the noise of night. What of pursuit, that you to-day should fear it?” Pursuit they reck'd not, save of wind that pours Surging and urging on to other shores Over the restless forest of a thousand doors. “Deirdre,” he cried, “the blowings of thy hair Uncoil the clouds that everlasting stream Forth from the castles of those islands rare, Black in the ragged-misted ocean's gleam, And glimpsed by Iceland galleys as they fare Northward!” But in her bosom's open seam She set the powder'd yew-spring silently; “Speak not of me nor give my beauty praise, Whose beauty is to follow in thy ways, So that my days be number'd with thy days!” In the high pastures of that boundless place Their feet wist not if they should soar or run; They turned, at earth astonish'd, face to face, Deeming unearthly blessedness begun. And slow, 'mid nests of running larks, they pace Drinking from the recesses of the sun Tremble of those wings that beat light into music. There the world's ends lay open; open wide The body's windows. What shall them divide Who have walk'd once that country side by side? She mused: “O why doth happiness too much Fountains of blood and spirit seem to fill? The woods, over-flowing, cannot bear that such An hour should be so sweet and yet be still. Even the low-tangled bushes at a touch Break into wars of gleemen, thrill on thrill. O, son of Usnach, bring me not thy glories! Bring me defeats and shames and secret woe; That where no brother goeth I may go, And kneel to wash thy wounds in caverns bleak and low!” “Here, up in sight of the far shine of sea,” (He sang) “once after hunting, by the fire I knelt, and kindling brushwood raised up thee, Deirdre, nor wist the star of my desire Should ever walk Findruim's head with me, Far from a king's loud house and soft attire. Fain would I thatch us here a booth of hazels, Thatch it with drift and snow of sea-gulls' wings; And thy horn'd harp should wonder to its strings, What spoil is it to-night Naois brings?” “Listen,” quoth he, when scarce those words were gone (A neck of the bare down it was, a ledge Of wind-sleek turf, the lovers roam'd upon, And sent young rabbits scuttling to the edge Of underwoods beneath), “I think that you Some beast—haply a stag—takes harbourage.” And Deirdre at a word come back from regions Of bliss too nigh to pain, snatch'd with no fear Out of his hand the battle-haunted spear And, questing swiftly down the pasture sheer, Enter'd the yew's black vault. Therein profound Green-litten air, and there, as seeking fresh Enemies, one haunch crush'd against the ground The grey boar slew'd, tusking the tender flesh Of shoots, his ravage-whetted bulk around: But, when his ear across the straggling mesh Of feather'd sticks report of Deirdre found, He quiver'd, snorted; from his jaws like wine Foam dripped; the brawny horror of his spine Bristled with keen spikes like a ridge of pine. Mortals, the maiden deem'd that guise a mask— Believed that in the beast sate to ensnare He of the red eye—little need to ask The druid-wrinkled hide, the sluttish hair: This was to escape—how vain poor passion's task!— Connachar of the illimitable lair! He crash'd at her! she heaved the point embrown'd In blood of dragons. Heavily the boar Grazed by the iron, reel'd, leapt, charged once more And thrice in passage her frail vesture tore. As when a herd-boy lying on the scar (Who pipes to flocks below him on the steep Melodies like their neckbells, scattering far, Cool as the running water, soft as sleep) Hurls out a flint from peril to debar And from the boulder'd chasm recall his sheep— So with a knife Naois leapt and struck. Strange! in the very fury of a stride The grey beast like a phantom from his side Plunged without scathe to thickets undescried. Naois sheathed his iron with no stain, And laugh'd, “This shall be praised in revels mad Around Lug's peak, when women scatter grain Upon the warriors! Why shouldst thou be sad Pale victory?” But she, “Ah, thus again Ere night do I imperil thee, and add Burden to burden!” And he strove to lead her From grief, and said, “What, bride! thy raiment torn?” “Content thee, O content thee, man of scorn, I'll brooch it with no jewel but a thorn!” They seek down through the Wood of Awe that hems Findruim, like the throng about his grave, Dusk with the swarth locks of ten thousand stems In naked poise. These make no rustle save Some pine-cone dropt, or murmur that condemns Murmur; bedumb'd with moss that giant nave. But let Findruim shake out overhead His old sea-sigh, and when it doth arrive At once their tawny boles become alive With gleams that come and go, and they revive The north's Fomorian roar.—“I am enthrall'd,” He said, “as by the blueness of a ray That, dropping through this presence sombre-wall'd, Burns low about the image of a spray Of some poor beech-spray witch'd to emerald. Wilt thou not dance, daughter of heaven, to-day Free, at last free? For here no moody raindrop Can reach thee, nor betrayer overpeer; And none the self-delightful measure hear That thy soul moves to, quit of mortal ear!” Full loth she pleads, yet cannot him resist And on the enmossèd lights begins to dance. Away, away, far floating like a mist To fade into some leafy brilliance; Then, smiling to the inward melodist, Over the printless turf with slow advance Of showery footsteps, makes she infinite That crowded glen. But quick, possess'd by strange Rapture, wider than dreams her motions range, Till to a span the forests shrink and change. And in her eyes and glimmering arms she brings Hither all promise, all the unlook'd-for boon Of rainbow'd life, all rare and speechless things That shine and swell under the brimming Moon. Who shall pluck tympans? For what need of strings To waft her blood who is herself the tune— Herself the warm and breathing melody? Art come from the Land of the Ever-Young? O stay! For his heart, after thee rising away, Falls dark and spirit-faint back to the clay. Griefs, like the yellow leaves by winter curl'd, Rise after her—long-buried pangs arouse— About that bosom the grey forests whirl'd, And tempests with her beauty might espouse; She rose with the green waters of the world And the winds heaved with her their depth of boughs. Then vague again as blows the beanfield's odour On the dark lap of air she chose to sink, As, winnowing with plumes, to the river-brink The pigeons from the cliff come down to drink. Sudden distraught, shading her eyes, she ceased, Listening, like bride whom cunning faery strain Forth from the trumpet-bruited spousal feast Steals. But she beckon'd soon, and quick with pain He ran, he craved at those white feet the least Pardon; nor, till he felt her hand again Descend flake-soft, durst spy that she was weeping, Or kneel with burning murmurs to atone. For sleep she wept. Long fasting had they gone And ridden from the breaking of the dawn. It chanced that waters, nigh to that selve grove, From Sleep's own lake as from a cauldron pass; He led towards their sound his weary love And lay before her in the fresh of grass Resting—the white cirque of the cliffs above— Against a sun-abandon'd stem there was. Spray from the strings of water spilling over The weir of rock, their fever'd cheeks bewet; And to its sound a voiceless bread they ate, And drank the troth that is unbroken yet. Out in the mere, brown, unbesilver'd now By finest skimming of the elfin breeze, An isle was moor'd, with rushes at its prow And fraught with haze of deeply-mirror'd trees; And knowing Deirdre still was mindful how The boar yet lived, that she might sleep at ease Naois swore to harbour on that islet. Nine strides he waded in, on footings nine Deep, deeper yet, until his basnet's shine Sank to the cold lips of the lake divine. Divine; for once the sunk stones of that way Approach'd the pool-god; and the outermost Had been the black slab whereon druids slay With stoop and mutter to the water's ghost, Though since, to glut some whim malign, the fay Had swell'd over the flags. Of all the host Few save Naois, and at sore adventure, Had ta'en this pass. But who would not have press'd Through straits by the chill-finger'd fiend possess'd To bear unto that isle Deirdre to rest? “Seal up thy sight! My shield of iron rims Unhook; cast in this shatter'd helm for spoil!” 'Twas done, and then with rush of cleaving limbs He swam and bore her out with happy toil, Secret and fierce as the flat otter swims Out of the whistling reeds, as if through oil. And Deirdre, whiter than the wave-swan floating, Smiled that he suffer'd her no stroke to urge. At length they reach the gnarl'd and ivied verge And from the shallows to the sun emerge. She spreads her wolf-skins on the rock that glows And sun-tears wrings out of the heavy strands Of corded hair. He, watching to the close, Sees not the white silk tissue as she stands Clinging bedull'd to the clear limbs of rose. She turn'd and to him stretched misdoubting hands: “Tell me, ere thou dissolve, O wordless watcher, Am I that Deirdre that would sit and spin Beside Keshcorran? Dost thou love me? Then I touch thee. For I, too, have love within.” O sacred cry! Again, again the first Love-cry! How the steep woods thirst for thy voice, O never-dying one! That voice, like the outburst And gush of a young spring's delicious noise Driven from the ancient heights whereon 'twas nursed! Yet, as death's heart is silent, so is joy's. His mouth spake not; for, as in dusk Glen Treithim Smelters of bubbling gold brook not to breathe Reek of the coloured fumes whose hissings wreathe The brim, he choked at his own spirit's seethe. Sternly he looked on her and strangely said: “What touch is thine? It hath unearthly powers. I think thou art the woman Cairbre made Out of the dazzle and the wind of flowers. Behold, the flame-like children of the shade, The buds, about thee rise like servitors! It seems I had not lipp'd the cup of living Till thou didst stretch it out. Vaguely I felt Irreparable waste. Why hast thou dwell'd Near me on earth so long, yet unbeheld?” Chanters! The Night brings nigh the deeps far off, But Twilight shows the distance of the near; And with a million dawns that pierce above Mixes the soul of suns that disappear; To make man's eyes approach the eyes of love In simpleness, in mystery and fear. All blooms both bright and pale are in her gardens, All chords both shrill and deep under her hand Who, sounding forth the richness of the land, Estrangeth all, that we may understand. So still it was, they heard in the evening skies Creak as of eagles' wing-feathers afar Coasting the grey cliffs. On him slowly rise, As to Cuchullain came his signal star, Out of the sheeted rivers, Deirdre's eyes. And who look'd in them well was girt for war, Seeing in that gaze all who for love had perish'd: The queens calamitous unbow'd at last— The supreme fighters that alone stood fast— Fealties obscure, unwitness'd, and long past; Cloud over cloud—the host that had attain'd By love,—in very essence, force, heat, breath, Now, now arose in Deirdre's eyes and deign'd Summons to him—“Canst follow us?” it saith— Till from that great contagion he hath gain'd An outlook like to conquest over death. Then he discerns the solemn-rafter'd world By this frail brazier's glowings, wherein blend Coals that no man hath kindled, without end Born and re-born, from ashes to ascend. And face to face to him unbared she cleaves Woman no more—scarce breathing—infinite, Grave as the fair-brow'd priestess Earth receives In all her lochs and plains and invers bright And shores wide-trembling, where one image heaves, Him that is lord of silence and of light. Slow the God sigh'd himself from rocks and waters, But in his soft withdrawals from the air No creature in the weightless world was there Uttered its being's secret round the pair. Ah! them had Passion's self-enshrouding arm Taken, as a green fury of ocean takes, Through the dense thickets smitten with alarm To the islet's trancèd core. And Deirdre wakes, Lifting hot lids that shut against the storm, Lying on a hillock, amid slender brakes Of grey trees, to the babble of enchantments From mouths of chill-born flowers. The place was new To rapture. Branchèd sunbursts plashing through After, had laid the mound with fire and dew. Naois cuts down osiers. Now he seeks A narrow grass-plot shorn as if with scythe And over two great boulders' wrinkled cheeks Draws down and knots a hull of saplings lithe, Well-staunch'd with earthy-odour'd moss and sticks Known to the feet of birds. This darkness blithe He frames against the stars for forest sleepers. The living tide of stars aloft that crept Compassion'd far below. No wavelet leapt; And deep rest fell upon them there. They slept. Long, long, the melancholy mountains lay Aware; mute-rippling shades that isle enwound. Naois fell through dreams, like the snapt spray That drops from branch to branch—that stillest sound!— And while from headlands scarce a league away The din of the sea-breakers come aground Roll'd up the valley, he in vision govern'd His ribbèd skiff under Dun Aengus sweeping, Triumphing with his love, and leaping, leaping, Drew past the ocean-shelves of seals a-sleeping. But over starr'd peat-water, where the flag Rustles, and listens for the scud of teal; Over coast, forest, and bethunder'd crag Night—mother of despairs, who proves the steel In men, to see if they be dross and slag Or fit with trusts and enemies to deal Uneyed, alone—diffusing her wide veils Bow'd from the heavens to his exultant ear: A questioner awaits thee: rouse! The mere Slept on, save for the twilight-footed deer. “Those antler'd shadows of the forest-roof Nigh to the shore must be assembled thick,” He thought, “and bringing necks round to the hoof; Or being aslaked and crouching, seek to lick The fawns. Some heady bucks engage aloof, So sharp across the water comes the click Of sparring horns!” But was it a vain terror, Son of the sword, or one for courage staunch, That the herd, dismay'd, at a bound, with a quivering haunch Murmur'd away into night at the crack of a branch? And Deirdre woke. Reverberate from on high Amongst the sullen hills, distinct there fell A mournful keen, like to the broken cry From the House of Hostage in some citadel Of hostages lifting up their agony After the land they must remember well, “Deirdre is gone! Gone is my young one, Deirdre!” And she knowing not the voice as voice of man Stood up. “Lie still, lest thee the spirit ban; O vein of life, lie still!” But Deirdre ran Like the moon through brakes, and saw, where nought had been, On the vague shore a weather'd stone that stood; Faceless, rough-hewn, it forward seem'd to lean Like the worn pillar of Cenn Cruaich, the God. She cried across, “If thou with things terrene Be number'd, tell me why thy sorrowful blood Mourneth, O Cathva, father!” But the stone Shiver'd, and broke the staff it lean'd upon, Shouting, “What! livst thou yet? Begone, begone!” 5: VOICE OF FINTAN Again, out of the First Century Let my lips finish what my lips began.— Then to the two amidst the island's boughs The third, across the water, cried: “Confess! Though the earth shake beneath you like a sieve With wheels of Connachar, answer me this: Naois, could she understand his hate Whose servant and whose iron flail I am— Whose arm requiteth—far as runs the wind— By me, that blow away the gaze and smile From women's faces; O could Deirdre have guess'd— Mourning all night the losing of her kingdoms Fled like a song—what means, a banished man: That he and I must hound thee to the death; That thou shalt never see the deep-set eaves, The lofty thatch familiar with the doves, On thy sad mother Usnach's house again, But drift out like some sea-bird, far, far, hence, Far from the red isle of the roes and berries, Far from sun-galleries and pleasant dúns And swards of lovers,—branded, nationless; That none of all thy famous friends, with thee Wrestlers on Eman in the summer evenings, Shall think thee noble now; and that at last I must upheave thy heart's tough plank to crack it— Knowing all this, would this fool follow thee?” Then spoke Naois, keeping back his wrath: “Strange is it one so old should threat with Death! Are not both thou and I, are not we all, By Death drawn from the wickets of the womb— Seal'd with the thumb of Death when we are born? As for friends lost (though I believe it not), A man is nourish'd by his enemies No less than by his friends. But as for her, Because no man shall deem me noble still,— Because I like a sea-gull of the isles May be driven forth—branded and nationless,— Because I shall no more, perhaps, behold The deep-set eaves on that all-sacred house,— Because the gather'd battle of the powers Controlling fortune, breaks upon my head,— Yea! for that very cause, lack'd other cause, In love the closer, quenchless, absolute, Would Deirdre choose to follow me. Such pains, Seër, the kingdoms are of souls like hers!” He spoke; he felt her life-blood at his side Sprung of the West, the last of human shores Throbbing, “Look forth on everlastingness! Through the coil'd waters and the ebb of light I'll be thy sail!” Over the mist like wool No sound; the echo-trembling tarn grew mute. But when through matted forest with uproar The levy of pursuers, brazen, vast, The thick pursuing host of Connachar, Gush'd like a river, and torch'd chariots drew With thunder-footed horses on, and lash'd Up to the sedge, and at the Druid's shape Their steamy bellies rose over the brink Pawing the mist, and when a terrible voice Ask'd of that shape if druid ken saw now The twain,—advanced out of the shade of leaves Nor Deirdre nor Naois heard reply; For Cathva waved his lean arm toward the north And mounted with the host, and signed them, “On!” Pity had seized him for that hidden pair; And like a burning dream the host, dissolving, Pass'd. On the pale bank not a torch remain'd. They look'd on one another, left alone. THE ROCK OF CLOUD From Youghal, where gulls take harbour, Youghal, the strand of yews, We stood away, off Brandon, Three nights out on the cruise. And thick cloud came over the deep The third day out from land That none could see his shipmate's face, Nor the helm in his own hand. Now bitterer than the mild sea-mist Hath ship no enemy; But we heard a chanting through the mist On the cold face of the sea That night, and lay upon our oars Amazed that this should be. Hark! was it a hoarse demon trolled? Or was it man? But one We knew had such a sea-rough voice— The Clockgate-keeper's son. We throng'd up close into the bow, And hail'd with might and main, “What hell-spawn or what spirit thou?” And the hoarse voice came again, Rang as of one so evil-starr'd That he hath done with grief, A voice of dread, and harsh and hard As the bell swung from a reef: “I am a man—But were I none Row hither! ye may hear Yet shall not save, nor bring me home, Seek ye ten thousand year!” “Keep a stout hope!” “I keep no hope!” “Man alive . . .” “Spare your speech—” “We are upon thee!” “Nay, no rope Over the gap will reach.” “Who art thou?” “I was helmsman once On many a ship of mark: Through many a pitchy night I steered, But there came a night too dark. “In the middle watch we struck—we sank, I reached this Rock of wings Whereby from every boulder's flank The brown sea-ribbon swings. “Here, while the sole eye of the Sun Did scorch my body bare, A great Sea-Spirit rose, and shone In the water thrill'd with hair. “She lay back on the green abyss, Beautiful; her spread arms Soothed to a poise—a sob—of bliss Huge thunders and alarms. “Her breasts as pearl were dull and pure, Her body's chastened light Swam like a cloud; her eyes unsure From the great depths were bright. “There was no thing of bitterness In aught that she could say; She called my soul, as down a coast The Moon calls, bay beyond bay, And they rise—back o' the uttermost— Away, and yet away:— “‘Ichose thee from the sinking crews, I bore thee up alive; Now durst thou follow me and choose Under the world to dive? “‘O here the wreckful heavens do scant Thy Godship, by some spell! But there thy heart shall have its want, And there shall all be well. “‘Come! we will catch, when stars are out, The black wave's spitting crest, And still, when the Bull of Dawn shall spout, Be washing on abreast! “‘Swim with me now, and I'll waft thee, Who hast known no happy hour, Through coral gulfs, over the lip Of islands like a flower, And fresh thee in the drench of youth Beyond an April's power. “‘Spring we up sun-lasht waterfalls Cauldron'd in giant vallies— To hang high as the rainbow hangs Or bask among sea-lilies! “‘My headland temples keen with light, Such as men know not here, Shall make thy senses infinite— Shall let thy heart be clear. “‘Or thee a flame under the seas Quivering with rays I'll hide, Deathless and boundless and at ease In any shape to glide. “‘All waters that on Earth have well'd At last to me repair,— All mountains starr'd with cities melt Into my dreamy air! “‘Shall I all women be to thee— As thou to me all men? Thou shalt have all the souls in me To gaze with. Haste thee then! “‘Set on thy peak under the brink I'll show thee storms above, The sands of kingdoms;—they shall sink While thou dost teach me love; On beaches white as the young moons I'll sit and fathom love!’” And we cried, “By God, 'twas hard for thee At that song not to go And let thy heart take heed no more When the Spirit called thee so!” “Ah! 'twas not any word she sang, But what she did not say, Suck'd griefs out of the colour'd world, And time out of the day.” “What saidst thou then?” “From over sea I felt a sighing burn That made this wrathy rock to me More delicate than fern; “And when like moth-wings I could hear Them heave, that stand in line By the mud-banks of Blackwater, The many-voicèd pine, “Great laughter seized me naked here, That I clung against the ground, Shaking in utter folly, while Myself was like a wound. “And I cried out sore, sore at the heart For her that sleeps at home, ‘Brightness, I will not know thine art, Nor to thy country come!’ “Straightway she sank—smiling so pale:— But from the seethe up-broke— Never thrashed off by gust or gale— White, everlasting smoke. “By stealth it feels all over me With numbness that appals; It laps my fierce heart endlessly In soft and rolling walls; “A mist no life may pierce, save these Wave-wing'd, with puling voice; Stars I discern not, nor the seas—” “O, dost not rue thy choice?” “Rue it? Now tell me, what ye are?— For I doubt if ye be men.” And to us from the cloud-breathing deep No answer came again. We knew the voice! We called his name! We pulled on, weeping loud, All night in earshot of the rock, But never through the cloud. And the gulls across from Brandon, Ere we had done the cruise, To the wall'd town of my mother's folk, Youghal, the strand of yews, And the women waiting on the quay, They carried back the news. THE QUEEN OF GOTHLAND to M.S. I Ho! Ho! the Count was not of those That care for treasure-trove! Ploughland and forest, quarry, fell, Castle and pleasure-grove. All that his house had heaped, he took And shared among his mountain folk, And wasted as they throve; Then flung the rest, all that he had, Round the white neck of love! Ay, in pearls for his young love. Make no mistake! the squanderer knew Shrewdly may be as I or you The virtue that's in gold; But this despotic man we lost Had faults and manifold. He had a something in the brain Never could bide his proper gain; He was not of the Clan of Take, The Clan of Get and Hold! There, in a savage discontent, The Count would sit receiving rent: He took the silver that you brought And thrust you back the gold. “I'd hew with you down to the rock, Down to the rock!” he cried, “Then could you know the man that's stript And working at your side!” Well, he stript himself, he showed his thew, he bared himself in pride, He dared with you, he shared with you, And you for him had died! And you heard his simple gusty laugh, And felt, and you were sure, 'Twas thirsting for the fire of life That made and kept him poor; And that he would keep the fire of life As pure as fire is pure! So impetuously, so seriously, Then grimly, nigh deliriously, He fought, he played, for love; But he lost, and vanished utterly. II Naught that shy beauty promised him, Merry had watched him crave: And the day she married Gothland's King When her father's town was brave With flags, drums, seething battlements, After a duel for her sake Wounded and nigh the grave, (Think you that could his spirit break Or force the Count's head on his breast Like any quivering slave?) He arose, lean in his uniform, Pulse not a stroke too fast, Waited her brilliant-eyed approach, And saw her start aghast, And she, the drawn face and the frown. On gallant knee downcast He tendered her his secret gift, The poor enthusiast! Out of his square palm's brawny foil She took the pearls. Faint gems entoil Clasp-opals of their massy coil. Then, with a jibe, he passed. . . . She stood, she sighed, she took the gift Because it was the last; Took that amazing gift of pearls (Unweeting all he gave) Thrice-pityingly, reluctantly, As 'twere a soul to save. That night she wore the coil of pearls With her bride's diadem, And she locked away that coil of pearls With many a holy gem In a casket in her chambers high, And thought no more of them. Ah, dark towers! Fort of faerie, Steep as Jerusalem! III Three years; and one night there was found Up to the heather drawn, The Count's boat, lying on the moor— Like a young seal that tries to flee Inland, instead of out to sea— But no boat there at dawn! Some said he had appeared that night, Dour as a thunderstroke, And asked her for no more than this, That she should slip the yoke: Make off then in the dawning dim Came she but in her smock to him, And for kingdom, share his cloak! Told how she seized a riding-whip And slashed across his bearded lip The hardy libertine. But who puts faith in such a tale? What eye the Count had seen? No! . . . Winters wore. The King grew bald. All Gothland was serene. IV But at last the lady pale, so pale, Who never could take rest, She stept down from the bed of kings And rode to south and west. From the lightly-faithful bed of kings She rode, they say, and drest In her white silken wedding-gown Alone through many a drowsy town; Hardly she drew the rein by night For the fire within her breast. About the peak'd and stormy towers At the corners of her keep Had marched a music old and proud For the waking of her sleep, But the rousing voice she listened for Was the sea's against the steep. “Take him away, your nimble hawk That comes again to hand! Bring me the bird that shows the pass Into a blither land, And the tune I never heard before Is the tune I understand! “O where shall I now pin my faith Who greatly have believed? And whither shall I fly, my heart, That so hath been deceived? It does no good to speak aloud, Save to the wind, save to the cloud! “Make room, thou southland mountain-top, Make room for my disdain! Make room, Ægean-breathing Dawn! Cypress above the plain, I will inhabit silence; then I shall begin to reign. “I had a cousin—a mad king— Why mad? He had a play Played out for him, and him alone. I'll have, ‘The Death of Day!’ The boards are bare, the footlights lit, The house fills, tier on tier, The vasty arch bedazzles. . . . Now Among the oaks and deer, With every grass-blade lustred through, What tragic gods I hear! “As Muse I'll listen. My thick hair Night-heavy, my sole crown, Falls round me like a close despair And veils me on the throne. See! The Players change as quick as kings!— The eve-mist changes. So I'll waver with unstable things, And go with things that go! “I will go wander like a wave And lash me to the mast, And sail by many a siren cave Till peril's charm be past. I'll wash this gaze in gaze of flowers In some Greek olive glen, And listen till I find my soul In places far from men. “O the world's ill, if even I Whose whimsies none resist— Who, satiate with all-yieldingness, Can change lands as I list, Yet find Death sweetest of all tales Of Life the rhapsodist! If I too sharp-set find the yoke Of earth's monotony, Then for these poor and common folk What must it be, what must it be? “I will forget them. I am wronged. How can I give them ease? I will forget them—play the Muse Of all bright ironies. Since what I asked the gods refuse, I will have Glory's kiss! Failure that's great—among great things At least deny not this! “Now for the prey I cannot kill, The hound that comes not back, The horse I cannot break at will, And a leap to end the track! My soul it shall be hunting still Though the night it may be black. “I am a queen, and round a queen Rumour hath ever rung; But rather than such honour grant Me, Glory, to die young, Full of the passion thou didst plant, Sure that I could have shaped the chant Woman hath never sung! “Blood of grapes stretch me not to drink, But juices more sublime! I'll see the world's green acre shrink While life is at the prime! I'll lift my horse up on the brink As he had wings to climb, And pledge thee, Glory, ere I sink Into the night of time!” V She rode resolvèd and amain, She rode for many a year, A vagabond and scholar queen Whose body knew no fear (Her fear was of the spirit pent For madness dogged her as she went), She chose the foam for outrider And the wind for cavalier. Became she poet? She became Empress, and in a line Of oldest lineage she was first Of ladies that must shine; To her deserted spouse returned— Returned, at what a cost!— Mute, mute she wore her dazzling thorns, But all dear things she lost. For chance among her nearest kin Strange havoc did contrive; In blood of all whom she held dear The gods made horror thrive; Brothers and sons were shamed and shot, Or sisters burned alive. She stared into Fate's eyes accurst And, seeing no glint divine, Closed her wise tragic lips, this first Of ladies that must shine. Ah, dolour that might never speak! . . . Yet as the herd-boy on the peak Gathers the forest's roar and shade Into the pipe he idly made, So in this ditty even I Would murmur all that mighty sigh! VI At last, in a grove of ilexes Off Epirus, in the sea, She built a Grecian pleasure-house Altar'd to poetry And Heine. (May the clan that own The palace now adore his stone As piously as she!) “Here, an old woman, I will rest,” She said: and from the north Sent for a girl's toys, jewelries. But lo! when they come forth In that clear Adriatic morn, On the cold imperial bed The coil of pearls, so long unworn, Lay lustreless and dead. “Tell me now, Monks of the sea-crag, Men wise in country lore, Whose bee-hive cluster of white cells Juts on the Corfiote shore, Where shall I sain them back to white And how sick pearls restore?” . . . And one looked up from his lentil pan, Like an olive, silvery-hoar, This Monk they sent her for a guide To row her out at the ebb-tide. He rowed her in a little boat That secret place to learn, His wrinkled hands pulled on the loom, His eye serene and stern, A Charon in the boat of doom, Unblinking, taciturn. There was gold broom on the sun-bright hills, The plash of oars in chime, And came a smell from the rocky bays Of lentisk-bush and thyme. They rowed along the rosy crags Sea-gnawn, with bouldered base, “O can you see yon headland high With the slant cave in its face? Deep down within it runs the pool Where your sick pearls must lie; At its mouth is the sea-otter's hole And a slant slit is the sky. The walls aloft are green with slime, And the sea-birds' dung is soft with time Along the ledges high.” And by that cranny darkly down They went the sea-birds' way Into the cavern's foul descent; Above, the roofs of mountain leant That plunge down to the spray. At last they heard a black wave wash, The subterranean channel plash, That never sees the day. She took the pearls from her sere breast, Felt them all, long unworn, And in the gloom, swift and unseen, She kissed those pearls as they had been The love-babe never born; And dropt them in the salt, salt wave With tears of the forlorn. A voice cried: “Long, O long lie there, Beneath the break of foam! Far have ye wandered, suffered much; To that ye wandered from We give you back, thrice-noble pearls, Until ye shall become Perfect again and pure again In that which is your home!” And swift came rushings through the air Of cold and wingèd things Alarmed escaping from their lair, Blasts and torch-flickerings. “Who art thou, visionary Monk, That speak'st this requiem?” “One that sees peak'd and stormy towers Steep as Jerusalem, Battlements grey, and over all One window like a gem, And a young girl, weeping on the wall, That wears a diadem!” In the cavern darkness where they stand She takes the high torch from his hand To search till she discerns That manèd visage, trace by trace,— The solemn-sounding mountain's base Rough'd to a humorous savage face Wherein the granite burns. . . . “How sharp,” he said, “that last, last hour Of departure's sick delay Prints on the warm, cleft, trembling soul The thing it takes away! Stamped how imperishably clear Your northern night dwells in me here! In my Greek island cell How oft I shut my eyes and smell Your sweetbriar by the northern shore And hear that fountain play! Its spouted rabble of loud drops Hangs in the evening still! November woods becloud the turf By the dove-house squat and chill. All's hush; and a ragged thunder-storm Comes up over towers and wood; White doves beat in a throbbing swarm Against the thunder-cloud As though they had thy transport been— The yielding of my flame-foot Queen! We pace together up the sward As they circle over the firth; The moonfall on thy coifless hair Makes glamour of the earth. . . . And then, leaning on the parapet, ‘Ah!’ thou say'st, ‘before passion's voice All, all is overset:— But what's a madman's passion worth?’ . . . Well, hast thou learnt it yet? “Why, great one, never kneel to me! We are too wise and old; Thou hast brought back the young man's pearls Before his heart is cold! . . . Calm, calm's for all such agonies As happened long ago! Calm is the Earth, though from its side A moon was torn! What woe! Yet time hath filled the wound with salt And solitary flow. “We were too dream-intent and hard To mingle each with each. Thou hadst to be thyself—to become Thyself the last, high, tragic song Of this our piercèd Christendom, Too high, too sad, for speech! . . . Saved in some vessel we see not, Some dark urn of the Lord, Is shed this everlasting loss, This waste of spirit poured. “For me, more than I need is mine; Labour of the hands is mine; Content, among my lentils here, And the obscurity divine.” VII Well, she went back, she faced her fate, Her tasks, without demur; Amid the shining cares of state Were lentils grown for her. But not long had the pair to wait, O not long to endure! A year thence, at the hour she fell, Stabbed by some crazy boor, The old Monk in his convent died The death of the obscure. And the pearls? Ah, blithe rejoicing pearls, Snapt is your rusty chain! Sucked out to the sea-darkness fresh, Released and born again, Somewhere beneath that ruddy crag, That blue Ionian main, Freely (for who shall seek the fort, Angelokastron?) there Unknown of all men ye may now Beauty and sheen repair! APOLLO AND THE SEAMAN I: APOLLO'S COMING Apollo through the woods came down Furred like a merchant fine, And sate with a Sailor at an Inn Sharing a jug of wine. Had sun-rays, spilled out of a storm, Thither the God conveyed? Or green and floating cloudlet caught On the fringes of a glade? For none had known him by his gait Descending from the hills, Though far and wide before him blew The friendly daffodils; No shepherd had discovered him On upland pastures bare By dew-pond or green Roman camp: No voice aloft in air Along lone barrows of great downs With kine in rolling combes, Where bells blow up from all the plain To headlands spring perfumes, Proclaimed him to those combes and folds Of little lambs unyeaned, Or sung him to the billowy woods With spray of buds begreened, Where spreads in haze the snowy maze Of orchards deep-ravined— Telling the dingles of the thrush To overflow with sound, Warning the grassy commons all In vales for miles around: “Wake, shady forest coverts wide! Wake, skylit river-sward! Chases and meres and misty shires Be ready for your lord!” But he would not stay nor tarry there On the blithe edge of the down, To the sea-coast his errand was And the smoke-hanging town. Far off he saw its harbours shine, And black sea-bastions thronged With masts of the sea-traffickers For whom his spirit longed. Far off he heard the windlass heaved And creaking of the cranes, Gay barges hailed and poled along, And rattling fall of chains, Till by the windows of that Inn He sate and took his ease Where bowsprits of the swarthy ships Came thrusting to the quays. 2: THE RUMOUR Apollo “And why are you cast down, sailor? And why are you cast down? With lapfuls of the guineas light Come you not back to town? Your feet that must have run in air Aloft the slippy mast Are they not glad to land, my lad, On steady ground at last?” Up from his brown rope-harden'd hands A heavy chin he raised, And sidelong through the harbour bluffs Looked out like man amazed. Seaman If you had cruised as I have cruised Abroad for many a year, Your blood like mine it would have struck At the strange news I hear. The Moon went riding high last night And the dance along the quays, But I could not find it in my heart To care for shows like these; While still I felt the rollers' lift Bear on through the dark land, And little houses here still rock And sway—they would not stand— I heard them calling in the streets That the ship I serve upon— The great ship Immortality— Was gone down, like the sun. . . . 3: THE SHIP Apollo And whence did that craft hail, sailor, Of which you seem so fond? Seaman It was some harbour of the East, Back o' beyond, back o' beyond! Apollo What shipwrights' hammers rang on her, The stout ship and the leal? In what green forest inlet lay Her cradle and her keel? Seaman I think some arm of the sea-gods Framed us her stormy frame, And ribbed and beamed and stanchioned her, And gave her strength a name. Never, Sir Traveller, have you seen A sight the half as fine As when she hove up from the East On our horizon-line! Apollo I have seen a dead god on the Nile Paddled by tribes of bronze, Under mud-built villages of palms Glide, statelier than swans, And Isis' frail moon-golden skiff Restore him to that barque of life Whose years are millions. I have seen Jason and his men Into bows of Argo piece Oak of Dodona, ere she slid To find the golden fleece: Ay, and triremes of the marble isles Pursue from Salamis. I have seen master-galleys rise Dipping in mass the oar, And centaur-carven caravels, And galleons big with ore, Dromonds, and mountain'd argosies That sack the globe no more: Great sails, like yellow weeping clouds, Heap'd thunder, roaring squall— And their fadings, like the fleet of stars That floateth over all. Seaman Well—ask all navies such as these— Was she not more divine Who, challenged by Death's muffled drums, Gave Death the countersign? Ah, to serve on her in time of war! It set aflame your blood To feel her in the slack of peace Come booming up the flood, Thousands of wings about her bows As she cast away the deep, The morning star swung from a spar And every sail asleep. Her masts! Land-locked and shut away From the sea-winds' scud and psalm, Her masts, they trembled in a leash— You laid on them your palm— They quivered over with great life That never could be calm. No frothings in your purple wake On the lone path to the pole, White as the spread of sail on her That lent wings to your soul— Apollo What was her build, that boat of yours So proud upon the sea? What was her make of hull and deck, What suit of sails had she? Seaman Her stretch of sail so white, so white, By no man's hand unfurled, Was Heaven! Apollo And the decks you kept so bright? Seaman For us, this bustling World. Apollo And the hold and cockpit out of sight, Pitch dark and ill to smell, Full of the friends of your delight? Seaman That was the pit of Hell! 4: THE TIDINGS Seaman How think of her, gone down, gone down! How think of her decayed! Or that the maker of that ship Could let his creature fade! More unbridled—unforgettable—was never creature made. Gone by the board, those swinging spars That seemed through storm to climb! Sent down, like any cockle-shell To tangle and to slime! Did he that takes the narrow sounds His monstrous hands between Whirl her among his crazy locks Into an eddy green? Was it fog-bound, on a foul coast, With not enough sea-room, Or clear of land that she was lost, Where hard gales can blow home? Was it ice-floe in the sheeted foam Ambushed her? or some ledge Of false lights—or uncharted reef— Broke her back upon its edge? Perhaps even she was seized at last Off an island precipice With weariness, like man's weariness, Of everything that is, And stranded so, till the fresh flood That through the channel swings Crumbled that side like a sea-cliff, As one crumbles little things. Apollo Her end was none, my lad, of these! But first, if you must know, Mutiny of those friends of yours In irons down below. Seaman And how got you, Sir Merchantman, This news—or bitter jest? Apollo “Sir, my trade is bringing light to all From the East unto the West. Nay, he that built your famous boat From the old coasts to fly And bear you ever out and on Was I, and none but I!” With that the sailor clutch'd the board; Wine spilt out of his glass Dripp'd to the floor; but not a sound From his parch'd mouth would pass. 5: THE TALE OF APOLLO Apollo (musing) There was no whisper out of space, Scarcely a ripple ran From thine incommensurable side O dim leviathan, When from afar I came in flight, Rumours 'gainst thee to probe, Leaving afar, engraved in shade, Many a dreaming silver globe, And approached thee on the middle sea Wrapt in my darkling robe. That Ship becalm'd, that triple-tier'd Of Heaven and Earth and Hell, Spread strange commotion as I near'd Over the starred sea-swell. Arcturus, I remember, shone— That rebel! mirror'd bright, And Saturn in his moat of moons Glass'd in unsounded night: The million-litten vault below Breathed, in a slumber light. As in a mountain forest-glade When frosts ere dawn are brisk And early spring boughs knitted close Across the red moon's disk, The rimy turf rings hard to hoof Of light branch-feeding deer, One sees upflushing some glen's brow Camp-fire of mountaineer Bivouack'd below; shag-bearded pines All gnarled, loom down estranged At wanton fire about their knees With moon-fire interchanged— So strange her gaunt dishevelled spars Loomed down out of the sky; Sails that had drunk Earth's soul immense Hung pierced and slung awry, My inwoven eternal blazonries An idle tattered shame. Was this the keen fire-spirited prow Ark of the heaving flame, That sun-stampt and illumined ship, That keel of mystery, Loosed, after toilings beyond count, To plunge from the Daedalian mount To stem futurity? Now since mine own insignia badged Each white celestial vail, Rage seized me, like your emperor Trajan—how goes the tale?— Who on Tigris, twice defeated, tore His gold wolves from the sail. . . . And as from forge doors in her decks Escaped, lulled, rose again, Confused blasts—insolent uproar From torch'd and naked men, As 'twere some wind from Africa's Tropic and demon'd fen. Beast-like shadows ran and flashed; Knotted at grips they swayed And writhed. Unkennelled Hell was loose And swarmed in escalade. Hard-pressed my righteous stood at bay, But when Hell's desperate brood Saw me, they shouted, “Lord of Light, Release!” Ruinous strew'd, Fell on their faces on the decks That breathless multitude. Their leader, with inverted torch, Stepp'd through them. Stern he comes, Stirring their night-bound forest hearts Like distant savage drums, He cries aloud, “In this, in this— Shaking his torch—is peace! Not thou, tardy deliverer, But I, confer release! “Mighty shall be the golden flame! Superb the funeral pyre Of Heaven and Earth! . . . Kindle it Hell, To glut this God's desire!” He paused, with arms distorted, black, Rear'd, long before the crash— Like hollow oak that long outliveth Coil of the lightning's lash; Then fell. Majestic enemy, Time with thy falling rang! He, first of all the ship, was free And fled without a pang. Out of the throng'd expanse, skull-bare Heads rose, and dropped again. They quailed, they flinched before my gaze, My light to them was pain! Shadows of wreckage on the masts Went streaming down the main. Stooping above one cowering shape, I raised it by the chin, Upturned the pallid chronicle And read the tale therein; Read the thing purposed, by the bone, The thing done, by the skin. The lecher, wan, with eyelid lined, Heavy-soul'd, torn with vice, The murderous, with the flitting smile, The drunkard, blue as ice; Incomplete and colourable things, Whose breathings must be lies. All the sweet neighbours that men take Within their breasts to thrive Had blown like glass the body's case Or stamped its clay alive. I mused—(All hung upon a hair!) Why need the dead survive? In one face, stony, white and bleak, Had passions scooped their bed; Old lavas down the rigid cheek, Meseemed, were still unshed; I read the eyes of him athirst Only for things beyond; Whose strata, tossed in molten dreams, Would never correspond With things about him, for he willed To die unparagoned. Unseen above them so bowed down Like beaten, sodden corn, How cast them with derision back, That throng of the forlorn, Herding them with derision cold As with a hand of steel, Condemn them to endurance back And still to think and feel, While tears that might not fall for them Did on my cheek congeal? And in that pause their mournful hope, Swelling like undertone That dins within the wildest gale, Utter'd aloud mine own. Blindly they stretched their scarry hands, Their piteous hands, to me: “Since bonds we cannot bear, nor sight, Be thou our sanctuary! Open again the narrow gate— Let us no longer be!” Then lo! my righteous, whose wounds still With bitter conflict bled, Veer'd in their wrath, hoarsely unjust, Arraigned me for these dead— Spat on their own high bliss, and craved To stand in Hades' stead! Had all white-priested Egypt, then, Not taught thee to perdure, My Boat of Years? Lo, in man's dust So mixed—so long impure— Came light! I summoned up each soul And round its neck secure Fastened this token: “Fudge thyself!” That justice might be sure. Aloft, long since, I saw, had fled That viewless sanhedrim Of presences starry-cresseted Who erst through waters dim Had breathed the towering sails along, My faithful seraphim. I turned about in mournfulness Steadfastly to behold Bulwarks charred, ay, drunken masts And slow deep-labouring hold, And heeling of age-crumbled beams And helmless spars divine— Beheld the horror of those decks Bloodied with mystic wine; Even the little fluttering Genius reft From the wrecked and flameless shrine, And I cried to the white shape on the prow Ascendant by my skill, “O wingèd Ardour, headless now, To sound what wild sea-victory Swing'st there, triumphant still? Why spared they wholly to shatter thee? Thy rippling veils from feet to breasts Winds from the future fill, “But I know my handiwork outworn, This bolted fabric vast That disciplined through many wars Man's courage in the past,— And well, well, hath she served her Lord— Unseaworthy at last!” Then from ocean's frothy hazardous Dream-element I caught Her crew—every half-foundered soul Wherewith her hold was fraught; I sang them back to steady Earth After their wanderings long, Both quick and dead. Hangs on thy breast The token of my song? (He fumbled in his hairy breast, Yes—the “Judge thyself” hung there) Remembering then their mad outburst Of quaint hope and despair, Who deemed each puny life should last, When nothing else escapes, And the nations and the planets melt Like breakers on the capes, From laughter, from tears unquenchable, Scarce able to forbear, I smote the great hull to a ghost,— The mighty masts to air. . . . Seaman What! is there not even left enough Of that so noble craft, A gang-board or a plank or two, To lash into a raft? Apollo No, lad: you shall not ride in her; But then you shall not weep; Nor hear aloft her pipes of cheer Nor the wail under the deep. Yet sometimes, like the Northern Lights, Hull-down—a radiance dim— Loftier than air of Earth, up-sprung To planes beyond its rim, At hours when you are fever-struck A phantom you may see, Derelict—drifting out of hail— Lost Immortality! 6: THE REBUKE When the man knew the ship he loved Had melted to a lie He fronted him upon his feet As who should Gods defy— Syllables choked not in his throat, He met him eye to eye. Refreshed was he through long forborne Anger. His spirit swelled Manful—the stronger in his grief By all that he had quelled. Seaman “This is your world-discovery! This is the great landfall! This coil of warehouses and quays And taverns—this is all! Well was it that we trusted thee! Else—how had we achieved Good luck? But then we had a friend Wholly to be believed. “This is the country we have gained, This land of milk and balm! For this our innocent took wounds And died without a qualm, Drawn on as by a ghost, that ends Like a catspaw in a calm! “Stay! I have heard, how in action's heat A captain in his tent Sealed a despatch; the rider died That with the letter went; The letter—saved—was found a blank! Thine was the message sent, Say, how wilt thou now make amends For what was vainly spent?” Fell off, fell off the enshrouding furs— The beamwork of the room To its last crevices was lit; So terribly illume The God's eyes—all his presence seemed Outwardly to consume; As though all burning sovranties And throbbings of the mind, Condensed into a single flame, Across that board confined Shot the human shade, a skeleton, Clean on the wall behind The man. Apollo Ah, fragment of my soul, When I invented thee To utter Mind, as guest and mate Of a voiceless family, And gave thee selfhood, barred with sleeps, On yon ship's heaving shelves, Selfhood that never can contrive— However lightning-like it strive— To escape, in its inmost, deepest dive My Self beneath your selves, I built through demiurgic powers Myriad human hopes and fears, And laboured at this shipwright's task A hundred thousand years. Think'st thou I framed a vessel vain As earthly ships of wood? Or that thy voyage never was And wasted all your blood? What! Hast not felt the invisible Nor faintly understood? Thou hast seen armies serve a name, A rag, a tomb forlorn; The tides of men obey a ghost, The ghost of the unborn. Thou hast felt passions' blindest roots Quake up man's silly crust, And rock thy reason from its state And crack its towers to dust. Thou hast seen Gods figure forth races, Surging out of the vast On crest of wave after wave, for aye To sweep till time be past:— Feel'st thou no wind behind those waves All washing on one way? Organs of the invisible Yes, thou hast felt their sway! Deem'st those old faceless images, “Truth,” “Justice,” “Liberty,” Heralding symbols thou employ'st? They are employing thee! Organs of the invisible Yes, thou hast felt their sway, The buried city of thy heart Knows thou art less than they. But now get back upon high seas Unknown and drear indeed, Thou, the adventure of my cloud, The sailing of my seed! Seaman “Lord, I confess the things unseen Closer the fountain-head Than this wood table in my grasp Or yonder loaf of bread; But must we, ever-living one, Go out when we are dead? When the arms that held us close and dear, When the love that we are used To mingle with, are wrenched away And the body's kiss is loosed?” The God smiled, and with 'haviour soft Leaning across the wine Heavily took those shoulders young Into his grasp divine. Apollo Hearken! I put you to the touch— My son, my prodigal— Since every brave song hath its close Your own life, end it shall; Yes, utterly shall meet an end. Be it heroical! And, born aboard, my rover stark, Dread you to die aboard? To lay you down beside your love With the sunset on your sword? . . . 7: THE NEW SHIP Apollo (continuing) Voyage after voyage, how else, how else Should I Man's soul prepare For the new venture, bolder yet, On which he now must dare? See! from the voyage whence you come now You come not back the same! Behind the door of your dull brow Have sprung up doubt and blame— Defiance of me. That I praise. This once low-cabined pate Hollows deep-chambered—is become Tribunal—hall of state For the assembled thrones of angels—roof For an assize of fate! Thou hast forgotten, whom I took From lap of things inform And flung to embraces of the sea Caresses of the storm! Now electrified, subtler-energied, Starker-willed, battle-warm, Thou comest, thou comest again to me! . . . Son of tumult, gloom enorm, I have new jeopardy for thee And new eyes yet to form! O wrestler into consciousness Stand upon Earth! Away! Long hath the journey been by night, But roseate breaks the day; Like a scroll I unfold the mountain-tops And the windings of the bay. Awake! Already on the cruise Thou shalt not see its end. Earth is the ship. Thou shalt have time To find the Earth thy friend! Seaman Is there a hand upon her helm? Apollo Weigh thou thine own heart-fires, Her wash of overwhelming dawns, Her tide that never tires— Her tranquil heave of seasons—flowers— All that in thee aspires! How like an eagle on the abyss With outspread wing serene She circles!—thought rolls under her, The flash from the unseen. Here's to her mission, wingèd rock, Bluff-bowed and heavy keel'd Through the night-watches swinging on Still under orders sealed! No crystal gives a peep, my son, Of her errand far and surgy; No witch's magic brew of sleep, Nor smoke of thaumaturgy; But, if thy former priestly ship Failed of the port assigned, The overwhelming globe takes on Her altar-flame of mind. See that the oils that feed the lamp Fail not! Seaman What are those oils? Apollo Heroic, warm, abounding souls! These are the sacred oils On fragrant thin-flamed thymele Lost on the deep like melody— They who, as I My Self disperse In them through the tragic universe, Scatter themselves in toils. And I shall stream into their life Waking—sense after sense— New understandings—endless, no, But more and more intense. Till joy in the Will that wafts the world Buoyant as swimmers be Makes thee divine, perhaps at last Wholly delivers thee. Seaman The man exclaimed, “Delivers me! How, if this death descends? I am a man and not a race. What matters, if self ends? Speak! quick, my brain is worn and cold, Little it comprehends.” Apollo “I shall tell thee, but as music tells. . . . I too, like thee, have striven. I too am launched from the profound And past; I too am driven In turn upon the stream of storms From fountains beyond heaven; To me, too, light is mystery, The greater light half-given. Ah, how make plain the goal obscure Of thy journey but begun?” Again the God smiled on the man And asked, “Hast thou a son?” He nodded. “And never yet hast guessed That thou and he are one! “Leaf shall of leaf become aware On the self-same bough and stem, Whose branches are murmuring everywhere And the heaven floods all of them! . . . Between you—between all that live— Runs no gulf wide nor deep— But a sheen'd veil, thinner than any veil, Thin as the veil of sleep. “Through the death-veil—looming silverly— The self-veil's subtle strand, Dawns it not? For that dawn thy heart Hath eye—shall understand; Before its seeing rock-walls melt And cracks the mortal band. “When once the whole consummate strength Of thy slow-kindling mind Can see in the heart's light at length All strange sons of mankind, Then Earth—that else were but a strait Rock-sepulchre—is new: Of what account to it is death? Its glowing, through and through, Moveth, alive with a God's breath, Translucent as the dew!” 8: THE EMBARCATION The last words in the rafters rang, The bright haze sounded on; Walls, air and shadows vibrant still, The God himself was gone. Was the thing dreamed? The Tavern wall Solid? Still it rang. Feverish he threw the lattice back; Outside fluttered and sang Trees of a tract of narrow yards Behind dark tenements, The nearest garden vacant—rope Eked out its broken fence. Naked it lay—brown mould bestrewn With refuse crockery—yet A pear-tree in its darkest nook Bowered it in delicate Whiteness. Beyond its further pale Above a wall-flower bed Women were hanging linen out— One stoop'd a kerchief'd head. In lime-trees idle rooks were cawing; Even to his upper room Came wafted from some distant plot Fragrance like thyme's perfume; Adrift from zigzag chimney-stacks And ancient courtyards, soft Blue smoke was breathed amongst the trees; Dazzling clouds moved aloft; Here, in the window where he stood A cherry stretched its limb, Half the diaphanous clusters clear Enlumined, and half dim. Green swift immortal Spring was here— Spring in her lovely trim— And whether it were ship or no, The Earth seemed good to him. Had he been Greek, or nurtured well In lore of sages gone, He would have felt her like that ship Ascribed to Hieron, Which, beside its deck-house luxuries Of baths and bronzes fine, Carried a pergola's green walk, Shade-galleries of vine, For awnings, fruit-espaliers From buried urns in line. Quitting the Inn, he made for home; By many a cobbled wynd Behung with mariner's wares, uphill He strode with seething mind. Above in the shady market-place Unwonted silence reigned. Under their patched umbrella stalls Few flower-sellers remained; But one, with old face like a map Wrinkled by good and evil hap, Stretched forth her palm. It rained. Ah, yes, it rained—sudden acold The sky loured overcast. Soon pavements leapt with plashing drops; And as he hasty passed He heard a burst of chanted sound, And glanced up at the vast Shadow that over huddled roofs Loomed, pinnacled and grey. . . . The spired cathedral thunderously And widely seemed to sway; Like Earth upon her pilgrimage Buffeting on from age to age, It still was under way. And on he trudged with peace at heart, Rain pelting on his cheek, But the shower half-ceased before he found The bourn he seemed to seek, A small house in a by-way dark Beneath that April cloud, And nigh the doorway he looked up Keen-eyed. He could have vowed, Yes, 'twas his wife stood shining there, Yonder, where lintels dripped! With soft, profound, familiar look Low-laughing forth she slipped. Her mute nod warned him (while her hair Released bright drops that fell) And bade him watch, but not disturb A happy spectacle. Now vapour'd were the cobble-stones; The runnel where they stood Fleeted adown the middle street, Rays gleaming on its mud, When lo! he saw a child, their son, Squatted beside the flood, The city's sole inhabitant And lost to aught beside. Wholly absorbed, aloof, intent; Upon that ruffling tide The boy embarked a faery ship Of paper, white and gay; And watched, with grave ecstatic smile, Its glories whirled away. II:SHORTER POEMS Night under Monte Rosa ODE FROM ITALY IN TIME OF WAR On the mountain Mottarone; written in April 1915, before the entry of Italy into the European War. I We will go up for help unto the hills. Since in their tent together by a sword The nations sleep divided; since the seas Of memory sever; and the cauldrons formed Of old time make wind-craters full of tongues Opposed, and zones of different decrees; Since hatred trembles in the singing chord, And in ourselves still the old savage throngs Lurk on, cave-dwellers in the gentle breast; Since stone-age man sits as our right-hand guest, And secular coils of chthonian energies, Dark trains of purpose script will never know, Involve in wrestlings blind the polities And interlock the peoples to their woe; In soul, aim, stature diverse, we are stormed By battle yet, and are the sport of fears Through the rushing of unstable atmospheres; Since thus, thus, thus, and thus we fail, And enmities exhaustless us assail, Is it in vain for innocence we strive— In vain that we are now alive? We are earth creatures. If essential strife Be stampt in the very make of the globe itself, What help, to look for help unto the hills? Yet will we go. We will go up and wrestle with the hills; Not for their blessing, but their utterance. Speak they our weal or woe, or naked'st Chance— Until they speak we will not let them go. II Our dearest, our young sons, have gone to slay. But we, denied with them to march and die, Angry-mooded yet at being disused, Racked by the fray— The wound in Europe's side from shore to shore— To-night have climbed up from the plains confused To foothills that look forth on Lombardy, To the mountain of the herdsmen, prow Of Mergozzòlo, flanked by torrents hoar, Ship of granite and of porphyry, Which, anchored between deep gulfs, keeps its bow Toward Ossola's mighty vale's debouching snow, Whence glaciers primordial southward pressed. Stark ship of granite and of porphyry! It clove the invading glaciers on its breast, So that one branch Orta scooped, and one the lake Maggiore. Darkness falls. We have come far By goat-foot path, shrine, ridge far-seen, Round steep flanks dyked with rills, Up from soft chestnut-woods to fell and scar; Scaling the forest-dark ravine— Where the mountain's ancient passion yields its tones Dash'd broken, young and pure, against the stones— To see the dawn from the cloud-bearing hills Of shepherds, and with herdsmen to take rest. III The herd of glaciers from these brooks has run; Huge boulders mark the sway Of their moraines, rude confines of a day. Through the same gates, fore-goers of the Hun, Goth, Carthaginian, pressed and passed away. We now, the riper peoples, rightly sure We must withstand the harsh and immature, The bitter-hearted, toss'd from dream to dream, Fiercely unstable—in all things extreme— These overlordship-seekers; we intent That the spirit of every folk shall take its bent Sunward, and wayward in experiment Adventure,—each small nation stand uncurbed— We shall put down the aggressors, unperturbed. . . . What is life's enemy? Not they But the sense of human life's futility. The vainness of ourselves, as of our foes— To that swift passage what can Man oppose, Who, brawler between two lights, God and Death— Sun-marshall'd and moon-tended—journeyeth? What natures clear, enduring, can Enter the hot and childish discord, Man? Flowing or floating—what of worth can be Establish'd? Courage, Awareness, the pois'd Soul. The rooted forest-people's polity Profound; of forest verdure that stands true And rooted in its own slopes' golden bowl Spreads free. Here, every happy mead Hath windflowers of a different hue; And sun-born Love, the mountain flower, is bred, And, family by starry family, Spreads chalices, whereof each petal young Is a new life: fresh Awareness—tenderly swung And diffused, as moveth a breeze over grasses and trees— Of more: all other men's lives, all other men's ease. . . . Guard we this new Soul against tyrannies! The soul is end enough, it nought else is To come to flower against the precipice. Yonder in Brescia bronze-wing'd Victory Doth still in her subalpine temple stand, Holding a vanish'd shield beneath her hand: Her sons will not to the north's menace yield. Rather than live unworthy of their land Some will forgo existences and fames,— Theirs will be written with the unknown names Inscribed for ever on the vanish'd shield; The viewless shield itself, their souls shall be! IV Therefore, O Latin barrier, when day breaks, Far as your sea-republics and faint shapes, Floating islands, divine cities luminous, Defiant nursed under the Rhaetian capes, We, strangers, fast in spirit your allies— Have you not framed, have you not founded us?— Now will take counsel of your heads of white, Snowy conclave of the arena bounded By the Alps, the amphitheatre of peaks; Pelasgian and Ligurian hear,—sea-races Still surging, murmuring, creating, round your bases Since Pytheas joined them to the Orcades; That, when the silver tubes of Dawn are sounded Over Sesia and the shining tributaries, Congiora and the tribes of promontories, From Resegone to the Graian wall— Padua to Monte Viso—when outleap Cataracts of pure fire into the lakes, And eyelids of the land Hesperia Uplift, we also may shake off our sleep, Put off the dark barbaric spell, Arise, and thinking of the risen glow When Hellas thrilled with rays the vine of night Hesperia, watch her great plains boil with light, As an olive holds her wide cup to the sun In endless battle-furrows of that glebe: And stand to hearken what yon silent say, Tongues of white fire, immarcescible; And grow to calm, if calm may be attained And clear-soul'd Justice from on high be deigned. V The kine-herd's pipe comes home beneath the hill Along Vergente's upland valley Blocked by the snowcapt mountains; kine and sheep Tawny and dark, slow following, graze their fill, Neck-bells wander round the bastions steep, Wandering fingers teach the stops at will Melodies cool as water, soft as sleep. . . . Dark heavens, that take no part in all our stir, Dark heavens, that arbiter The fellow vault of fire, the brain of man, Now from that height and depth—your fastness Confer on the ephemeral your vastness! O stream of time, the sunrise-colour'd flood Alive with tremour of ten thousand stars Dissolved therein like memories in the blood, Arouse us at this dawn to wake indeed! But for the instant a street-door unbars And lets be heard the storming multitude Trampling the unjust fortress-prison doors, Make us alive to those whom we succeed! Make us alive to our inheritors! We must not fail the hour for which they bleed, But hear, within, the Pure and the Outlasting Blow their sharp summons through the soul, To become, in our turn, paean and forecasting. Now on our ears, through gates of Death and Pain, Let the rhythms incommensurable roll,— And change. When we too must take up the strain We join, above the tempests and expanses That blindly move in ecstasies and trances, Into an inner rite, which is not blind, Where equanimity may reign, The grave and the fraternal rite of Mind. VI We cast off blankets, we who have not slept, And cold grope forth uphill. Night, fever-charged, numb, watchful Night, has crept, Uneasy dying, towards tremendous Day. Dawn is not yet: all's chill, Cloud on drench'd grass, clouds washing round the fells, Forth over battlements and deeps A sea of curdled fugitive cloud— Filmy panic-pale hordes, all in flight One way—the ice-floes of an arctic strait; But, through fissures, darknesses untold below. Of the cordon of main Alps—no sign. . . . From cloud a threatening tor outswells; From far abyss one glimpsèd outlier Couchant, of vassal buttresses; and lo! White Horn, or Tagliaferro's rigid spine Slanted, intense, along his ledges sheer. . . . Ah, brothers, brothers, who could have believed It cost so much that this wall should be heaved? Writ in these fulgural archives Of conflicts settled, of denuded hate, Folded together are the hostile lives. Here they are twinned, who strove to dominate! How closely clasp'd, the writhings of the ridges! Behold, the horror of the upturned edges— Together the torn strata seek the sky! VII Not all in vain ye die Whose veins of blazing granite forge the lime To marble, and the mean to the sublime. Embraced, each fierce antagonist Takes in the other's virtue, and so locked Become they fountain-heads, on hard foundations, That might not, but for your ambitions blocked— Your gorges with the muddied glacier choked— Your beautiful strengths, wasted on death—subsist, To slake the thirsts of the divided nations. VIII And what do we deserve? By far Better it is our generation perish, Perish, till we remember what we are. Better it is that Earth be purged of us; She hath need of purer eyes. We have forgot, in our inequities, Our part in the selfless harmonies. A sudden breeze lifts, rending off the pall— Darkling Italy's white coronal Appears. Crest of all the barrier Wrathborn, unearthly in his fixèd mood, Detached from multitude, That struggler now so still, Monte Rosa, in the lightless atmosphere. IX Alone he dreameth, ghostly sovranty— A servant, fetter'd more than we, But by acceptance free; A tenuous presence, rime-cold, pale as rime, Above the band of European cloud Submerging like a slumber Italy, The seven lakes, the cobweb cities proud, The shadow Lombardy, the silt of time, The march and countermarch of history— The mountain waiteth, even as we. Strahlhorn, Alphübel, Dom, and Allelin, Phantom alps to the northward, shrink withdrawn Away from orisons none dare disturb. Southward his wilderness, tossed line beyond line— Darkly surmised through heavy veil on veil— Of toothèd basalts, bare of snow and pine. Out over Orta's blind chasm giddily Wings waver forth. No insect chirp sounds here, No shred of whisper. What clash of cymbal armies now again Noised upward from their golden plain On wings of victory released, could fill Time with an exultation like that hill While unto space the hill lifts up his voice? Though his desolation put no vesture on Of light, the memory of fire, nor emerges The faintest brilliance from beyond the verges, He keeps night-measure with the vanished sun, And answers, to a yet immenser poise. Now shall our soul-mate, Liberty— The rock-bred daughter of the lightnings—she Cradled in welter of these peaks at war— Conceive, at the arising of a star? He waiteth, that grey shape, far up, aloof: As the night-watchman, ten years on the roof Of Agamemnon, till the beacons' joy Mutter'd from sea to sea the fall of Troy— The mountain waiteth, even as we. X And now, upon that watcher in the air, Outpost Promethean, Earth's protagonist, That nothing saw beyond our realms of mist, Slow from the zenith is downbreathed the rose. (Hush, the world's candle!—every star grows pale) Until the nine-peak'd ocean-mantling mass Lit—every cleft and cranny of his snows And sea-curved crystals into which arose The groaning precipices—with peace superb Becomes the altar of the soul of Dawn. Prostrate night-vapours travel down each vale In darkness, the obscurers, and the frail— But the ancient iron summit in his shroud Of radiance, every pike and bastion dour Belted with awe of glacier and crevasse, Floats up, transfigured, at this limpid hour, A walled and heavenly city, clear as glass— A new acropolis of mourning rosed, Aerial, lighter than a branch in flower— An absolute, but of our strifes composed. Requiem of Archangels for the World Hearts, beat no more! Earth's Sleep has come, All iron stands her wrinkled tree, The streams that sang are stricken dumb, The snowflake fades into the sea. Hearts, throb no more! your time is past; Thousands of years for this pent field Ye have done battle. Now at last The flags may sink, the captains yield. Sleep, ye great Wars, just and unjust! Sleep takes the gate and none defends. Soft on your craters' fire and lust, Civilisations, Sleep descends. Time it is, time to cease carouse. Let the nations and their noise grow dim! Let the lights wane within the house And darkness cover, limb by limb! Across your passes, Alps and plains, A planetary vapour flows, A last invader, and enchains The vine, the woman, and the rose. Sleep, Forests old! Sleep in your beds, Wild-muttering Oceans and dark Wells! Sleep be upon your shrunken heads, Blind, everlasting Pinnacles! Sleep now, most dread high-shining Kings, Your torrent glories snapt in death. Sleep, simple men—sunk water-springs, And all the ground Man laboureth. Sleep, Heroes, in your mountain walls— The trumpet shall not wake again; And ranged on sea-worn pedestals, Sleep now, O sleepless Gods of men, Nor keep wide your unchallenged orbs. These troubled clans that make and mourn Some heavy-lidded Cloud absorbs, And the lulling snows of the Unborn. Make ready thou, tremendous Night, Stoop to the Earth, and shroud her scars, And bid with chanting to the rite The torches of thy train of stars! Gloriously hath she offered up From the thousand heaving plains of Time Her sons, like incense from a cup, Souls, that were made out of the slime. She darkens, and yet all her dusk Is but the sigh of him that breathes; The thing unborn bursts from its husk, The flash of the sublime unsheathes. They strove, the Many and the One, And all their strivings intervolved Enlarged Thy Self-dominion; Absolute, let them be absolved! Fount of the time-embranching fire, O waneless One, that art the core Of every heart's unknown desire, Take back the hearts that beat no more! SONG OF THE VINE IN ENGLAND Man Ovine along my garden wall Could I thine English slumber break, And thee from wintry exile disenthral, Where would thy spirit wake? Vine I would wake at the hour of dawning in May in Italy, When rose mists rise from the Magra's valley plains In the fields of maize and olives around Pontrémoli, When peaks grow golden and clear and the starlight wanes: I would wake to the dance of the sacred mountains, boundlessly Kindling their marble snows in the rite of fire, To them my newborn tendrils softly and soundlessly Would uncurl and aspire. I would hang no more on thy wall a rusted slumberer, Listless and fruitless, strewing the pathways cold, I would seem no more in thine eyes an idle cumberer, Profitless alien, bitter and sere and old. In some warm terraced dell where the Roman rioted, And still in tiers his stony theatre heaves, Would I festoon with leaf-light his glory quieted And flake his thrones with leaves. Doves from the mountain belfries would seek and cling to me To drink from the altar, winnowing the fragrant airs; Women from olived hillsides by turns would sing to me Beating the olives, or stooping afield in pairs; On gala evenings the gay little carts of labourers Swinging from axles their horns against evil eye And crowded with children, revellers, pipers and taborers Chanting would pass me by. . . . There go the pale blue shadows so light and showery Over sharp Apuan peaks—rathe mists unwreathe— Almond trees wake, and the paven yards grow flowery— Crocuses cry from the earth at the joy to breathe; There through the deep-eaved gateways of haughty-turreted Arno—house-laden bridges of strutted stalls— Mighty white oxen drag in the jars richspirited, Grazing the narrow walls! Wine-jars I too have filled, and the heart was thrilled with me! Brown-limbed on shady turf the families lay, Shouting they bowled the bowls, and old men filled with me Roused the September twilight with songs that day. Lanterns of sun and moon the young children flaunted me, Plaiters of straw from doorway to window cried— Borne through the city gates the great oxen vaunted me, Swaying from side to side. Wine-jars out of my leafage that once so vitally Throbbed into purple, of me thou shalt never take: Thy heart would remember the towns on the branch of Italy, And teaching to throb I should teach it, perchance, to break. It would beat for those little cities, rock-hewn and mellowing, Festooned from summit to summit, where still sublime Murmur her temples, lovelier in their yellowing Than in the morn of time. I from the scorn of frost and the wind's iniquity Barren, aloft in that golden air would thrive: My passionate rootlets draw from that hearth's antiquity Whirls of profounder fire in us to survive— Serried realms of our fathers would swell and foam with us— Juice of the Latin sunrise; your own sea-flung Rude and far-wandered race might again find home with us, Leaguing with old Rome, young. Epitaph on an Infant House upon the Earth, be sad, Lacking me thou might'st have had!. . . Many aeons did I wait For admission to the Gate Of the Living. But to see Much was not vouchsafed to me, Dazzled, in my little span. I, that hoped to be a man, Like a snowflake incarnated Seem for three days' light created. I saw two Eyes, and break of Day, Gold on spires of Nineveh. But, ere I one comrade made, Or with a fellow Beastling played— Even while voices I forget Called from cloud and minaret Men to wake—I stood once more With the Dreams, outside the door. Song of the Larks at Dawn I Shepherds who pastures seek At dawn may see From Falterona's Falterona is the highest peak of the Apennines. Camaldoli is a monastery of silent monks at the foot of the mountain. peak Above Camaldoli Gleam, beyond forests and wildernesses bleak, Both shores of Italy. Fallen apart are the terrible clouds of the morning And men lift up their eyes. II Birds that have circled and wound Through the chasms below Disappear into belts profound Of fleet cloud, hail and snow. The stripling land they behold not, nor high sea-bound; Out of harsh ravines they know, Out of night—the Earth's own shadow from orbèd morning— They fear, they fear to rise. III Heaven's troubled continents Are rifted, torn: Thunders in their forest tents Still seethe and sullenly mourn, When aloft, from the gulfs and the sheer ascents, Is a music born. Hark to that music, laggard mists of the morning, And, men, lift up your eyes! IV For scarce can eye see light When the ear's aware That virginals exquisite Are raining from the air— With sun and pale moon mingling their delight— Adorations everywhere! The grass hears not, nor the stony summits of morning, But men lift up their eyes. V Eddy of fiery dust— Halo of rays— Thrilling up, up, as they must Die of the life they praise— The larks, the larks! that to the earth entrust Only their sleeping-place, From rugged wolds and rock-bound valleys of morning The larks like mist arise. VI Earth sends them up from hills, Her wishes small, Her cloud of griefs, her wills To burst from her own thrall, And to burn away what chains the soul or chills In the God and fount of all. Open your gates, O ye cities faint for morning, And, men, lift up your eyes! VII Open, Night's blue Pantheon, Thy dark roof-ring For that escaping paean Of tremblers on the wing At the unknown threshold of the empyrean In myriads soft to sing. Give way before them, temple-veils of the morning, And, men, lift up your eyes! VIII O throngs, caught unaware, Whose glee is finding The sun your father—who dare, On the dark gales upwinding, Spill out on burning air your gossamer Of songs heaven-blinding— Who beat the bounds and the wild marches of morning, And take as yours the skies! IX They ascend, ere the red beam On heaven grows strong, Into that amazing stream Of Dawn; and float along In the future, for the future is their dream Who roof the world with song. Open your flowers, O ye mountains spread for morning, And, men, lift up your eyes! X They hang above the wave, And are the voice Of that light for which we crave, They flee from poise to poise, They have forgotten the forgetful grave, In garlands they rejoice; They dance upon the golden surge of morning That breaks our brooding skies. XI Hark! it grows less and less, But nothing mars That rapture beyond guess, Beyond our senses' bars; They drink the virgin light, the measureless, And in it fade, like stars. They have gone past, the dew-like spirits of morning, Beyond the uplifted eyes. XII Between two lamps suspended Of Life and Death, Sun-marshalled and moon-tended Man's swift soul journeyeth To be borne out of the life it hath transcended Still, still on a breath. For a day we, too, are the wingèd sons of the morning, To-day we will arise! Bitter Serenade VENICE, 15? (He speaks, touching the chords) Lanterns of silk down the lagoons are vanished, Brilliance, uproar, and sweep of masquerade; Their eddies swell—the firefly world is banish'd, All your canal is shade. Magnolia-bloom is here my only candle, White petals wash, and break, along the wall; That clumsy lute, the lute with the scorched handle, Is here to tell you all. Do you remember—yes, you will remember— The ballad of a lute of curious tone, Wrought—a charr'd log—out of a great hearth's ember? The great hearth was your own. Firelight was all our light. Your endless gazes— Contemptuous of all living—forth would float, Half-terrible in beauty, down those mazes As in a flame-winged boat. Urania's locks, with horror in their starkness, Enlapt you, pale as an Aegean gem, Enwound your ears with silence, and of darkness Made you a diadem. What eyes were yours that made the witless falter, The beating of the heart forget to beat, Some Arab prisoner's on a desert altar, And sleepless with defeat. Yet with that smile that seemed no smile of woman Frowningly once—floating on light—you cried As in a vision: Friend, not like your Roman Cynthia, by the roadside Would I be tomb'd—close to the dust and rumbling— But childless, by some playground; that at hours Oft I may hear the wicked children tumbling Forth, like a tide of flowers! . . . By God! to the chords wherewith you then endowed us (Something in you gave frame and strings a voice) Now you must listen, in the hours allowed us, Listen, you have no choice! . . . (He sings) THE SONG O heart thrice-noble, to the quick bereavèd, In beauty wasted, and in weakness dire Maintaining 'gainst the Gods that have deceivèd Such cold unwavering ire! The very stars grow dread with tense forefeeling Of dawn; the bell-towers darken in the sky As they would groan before they strike, revealing New day to such as I. There comes a day too merciless in clearness, Worn to the bone the stubborn must give o'er; There comes a day when to endure in nearness Can be endured no more. A man can take the buffets of the tourney, But there's a hurt, lady, beyond belief; A grief the Sun finds not upon his journey Marked on the map of grief. Fate smote you young. Death young would now frustrate you. I have but lived—as alchemists for gold— In my mad pity's flame to re-create you, Heavenly one, waning, cold! Planet dark! Strange and hostile desolation Whereto no ray serene hath ever gone Nor touched with the one kiss of evocation— You might have loved and shone! Was I not bred of the same clay and vapour And lightning of the universe as you? Had I the self-same God to be my shaper, Or cracks the world in two? It cannot be, though I have nought of merit, That man may hold so dear, and with such pain Enfold with all the tendrils of the spirit, Yet not be loved again; It cannot be that such intensest yearning, Such fierce and incommunicable care Starred on your face, as through a crystal burning, Is wasted on the air; It cannot be I gave my soul, unfolding To you its very inmost, like a child Utterly giving faith—no jot withholding— By you to be beguiled; It cannot be to look on us, despising, That yonder great-puls'd Sun englobes the wave With crocus fire—releasing and arising— To break upon the slave; No. In rich Venice, riotous and human, That shrinks for me to sandbanks and a sky, You hold the love I bear you a thing common. Enough. So let it die, Die from your waves away—O, pale, pale wonder! The gaunt ships out—toss'd petals—to the main Be suck'd—the iron bands be snapt asunder! But Night, Death, you—remain. (He ceases to sing; and speaks, touching the chords) In the outer flood, and plunging at his tether, One sullen hulk complains against the quays; Rusty, and timbered ill for such fine weather, He thinks on the high seas. My hand forgets the strings. May be for travel It trembles to be gone, to steer the fleet! There's the secret of the Indies to unravel, And then the Turks to beat! The Challenge Not from a Godlike State Of iron laws Set above right as Fate Our strength, our wisdom draws; But from things weaker than straws, From childish hands and love left desolate. And as one shall walk at ease On battle bent Who knows the battle frees In him the great event— Sing we, with deep consent, The ancient cause, the never-ending cause! No cavern'd foe can hide. Now sharp and clear The bulks of storm divide, The combatants appear; Between that grasp of Fear, And Freedom, lies the unresolvèd cause! The thinking tyrants all That kept not troth Struck falsely, to forestal; The thinking tyrants loathe The invisible forest's growth, The quickening roar in its sea-summits wroth. Like falcons from the wrist They toss'd afar On sleepers in the mist To plunge from Alp and scaur Giant-minded vultures—War's Foul chasm-born Hungers,—Hates that men resist. How shall that Cyclops state Whose subtilty Upheaved the fields, create A murderous sovranty? Pure must our wisdom be, Innocence keep the keepers of our gate. O World, this is our Fire, Our highest Name, Wherein we do aspire And all our temples frame, Freedom of soul's the flame— The guarded hearth of our organic cause! For this we founded States Time shall inherit, To grow to rule our fates— The joy of the free spirit For all! Let them that fear it Declare their vision of a higher cause! We would be free to know, Yea, free to make Finelessly on—to grow More free for freedom's sake: Let us fail, let us mistake, But let Earth's undiscover'd springs outbreak! One spirit, Lord of Life, Beauty, Truth, Deed— Is ventured on this strife Commanding us, “Be freed!” Spirit, our battle lead, Be thou, against the oppressors, all our cause! The nations are thy boughs, The dead, thy seed— The dreamers are thy vows, The fighters are thy deed! By them 'tis Thou art freed— Moving in them thy passion and thy cause! Therefore let him beware, Beneath the sea, Or hung in middle air, Who now opposes Thee! Breath of humanity, Uplift us in that cause, which is thy cause! August 1914. MILO LINES TO A CERTAIN NATION, WRITTEN DURING THE BATTLE OF VERDUN I Milo, the wrestler oiled, whom victories— Six times the Pythian, six the Olympian—crowned, Could shoulder a bullock, run the stadium round, And in a day devour the beast with ease. Thrice-happy too, in philosophic strength, Showed sumptuous ladies paths to Hera's shrine And crushed his fellow-Greeks of Sybaris, Haling their treasure to Crotona. In fine This subtlest of protagonists at length Taught his folk, force was all, and all force his. Sybaris was thy kin. Why then, Crotona, Did Milo lead thee to crush Sybaris? Why tortured he the men of Sybaris? He coveted their golden port, Crotona! At sunfall as the titan athlete went, His mighty self-love nursing discontent, By a forest path, some Dionysian storm Of impulse spurred him to a feat enorm. Cresting the Sila's granites, a strange tree— A boulder wedged its cloven trunk—to sea Spread limbs of shade forth, westward, north, south, east. Its high fantastic-rooted talons capt The granite. It stood desolation-wrapt. Mysterious, wounded, long, long had it stood Deep-rifted, but a kindly fortitude. . . . And Milo's pride of thew, restless, on edge, Heaved out the boulder, made himself the wedge, Thrust the gap wider—that old wound increased— (Faint shivers running through the foliage) Until the great bole writhed, sprang, caught him fast, One arm locked in the yawning of the wood, No more out of its shade to be released;— Unless he transmigrate into this tree His body turns to a fetter, a prison, a grave! Could such dumb wills, outside his will-to-be, Have their own wounded being? Or did he rave? That grip was real. Skywards without end Its branch'd nerves did most curiously extend, As they might be the fibrils of a brain— Stood he within the ganglions of some brain? With what a movement strange the whole tree moves, In thick-running waves of umbratility! The heavy-fronded murmurer of the groves Is dash'd by sudden inward beams—it moves, And lo! a pattern in its vapoury Spirals unwreathing, spirals without end Shaped into glimmering lights, a scatter'd train, Corollas luminous, green nebulæ. . . . Beneath stood Milo, prisoned. To the last, Madness and ghostly wolves approaching fast, Still in delirium, still defiantly, Milo bragged on, shouting up boughs divine, “Who, then, art Thou, whose hold outwrestles mine?” Silence fell round him, that for him was worse Than mortal. But to You (whose name Verse will not utter, lest it darken verse), Who were a greater Milo by your fame, But a Nation, that, before the Multiverse Fountain of souls, seems one whom nothing awes,— To You, light-headed with your own applause, Taunting the world whose agony You cause— Crying with the lips of Milo still the same Insult—“Who art thou, to imprison me?” Immense boughs whisper back, “Humanity!” Innumerable leaves, “Humanity!” II For with a movement strange the whole tree moves, That hath its roots down in the kingdoms pale Of Hela, and whose boughs do overspread The highest heaven. We ripen, we are shed— But lo! a pattern in its vapoury Spirals unwreathing, spirals without end Shaped into glimmering lights, a scatter'd veil, Corollas luminous, green nebulæ Whirled up in figured dance, each soul in station (This fan-like rise of petals seems of souls) Ascending, throbbing—systoles—diastoles— By generations! Old Pythagoras These may have numbered in his secret glass— These, carrying up the spirals of creation; These, that alone change forces into loves! These glowing cores, the chaliced families, What suns draw from a source deeper than these— Nebulæ, wreathing upwards from their fount, Majestic in their dreams and in their traces? They throw off paler confraternities, The temple-guilds, religions of the races, Formed but to echo their august vibration— Image forth perpetually their solemn rise! Floating up warm from narrow native ground Even in the very need of each man's toil And the very pang that bids defend his soil, They become aware of other chalices, Until with sense of all the rest inwound They break, towards one will, within their bound, And feel themselves as one, nation by nation, Enlarging so the spirals of creation:— But neither in men themselves, nor what they change Or make, do lie the centres of the strange Movement, wherewith the whole tree moves Spacing men's mind to measured harmony. Its centres lie in little glowing cores, Them that alone change forces into loves. Warm Bask the Vines, Light-thrilled I Warm bask the vines, light-thrilled, along your steeps, Azure the fleet of islands hangs in azure, On lichen'd rock the wrinkled lizard sleeps— The shore's pine-odour, lifting, sighs for pleasure, Telaro, Telaro! Telaro is a little village between Lerici and Viareggio. Nets, too, festooned about your elfin port Rough-carved out of the Etrurian mountainside, Ripplings from golden luggers scarce distort The image of the belfry where they ride. Yet, on a black volcanic night long gone, That bell-tower on the mole Summon'd, while smouldering heaven with lightnings shone, Scared and half-naked sleepers by its toll And choked, delirious in its monotone, All the narrow channels of your hamlet's soul. II Why beats the alarm? Fire? Shipwreck? Treachery? Is it for some gang that from the macchia springs— For Genoa's raid—the oppressor's piracy— Or the Falcon of Sarzana that it rings, Telaro, Telaro? Is the boat-guild's silver plunder'd? Blood shall pay! Hard-won the footing of your fishers' clan, The sea-cloud watchers. Clash'd above the spray That stinging iron cry, the appeal of man— Enough, enough, the jeopardies of day— Washes through tempest on! And blood is up, and searchers seek to slay— The tower shows empty! By the lightnings wan They find no human ringer in the room. The bell-rope quivers, out in the sea-spume. III A creature fierce, soft, witless of itself, A morbid mouth, circled by writhing arms, By its own grasp entangled on that shelf Has dragged the rope and spread your deathalarms, Telaro, Telaro! From murk deeps light-forgotten, up from slime, From ambush of sea-chasms issuing for prey Submerged, hath used men's language of dismay; The spawn of sunken times hath, late in time, Clamber'd, and griefs upon man's grief imposed Blindly. But fishers closed The blind mouth, and cut off the suckers cold! Two thousand fathoms your disturber rolled From trough to trough into the gulf Tyrrhene; And fear sank back into its night obscene. IV Yes, though 'twill surge again, this monstrous Past To lash the ramparts of our little town— Upheaves the despot, with his tangles vast, Or fell Chance rises and the floods drag down, Telaro, Telaro! From cliffs of light our noblest in its coil— Here the wild breakers closed over Shelley's head, Pale furies swift, unconscious of their spoil, Flung on your sea-cave's floor the dreamless dead— Yet Power, elder than Time, terrible, bright, Dwells in our race of care. On the breast of Chance we are not parasite; When the multiverse ungovernable Might Confronts itself with dark bale and despair, Then the Spirit of Man, pure spirit, shineth bare! Advance on the Somme I Wild airman, you, the battle's eyes, Who, hovering over forest air, Can every belt of cloud despise And through them fall without despair, No cannon's sound to you can rise. But, say, how goes the battle there, As they advance? II Be dumb, choked heart! for they are dumb— Our men advancing. All's at stake! The woods are bullet-stript—with hum Of cannon all the pastures shake; And some will cross the crest, and some Will halt for ever in the brake, As they advance. III The ground is bubbling—pit and mire— And blackened with the blood of sons. Death rains on every yard; and fire Shuttles the veil with woof of guns. Dread is flag those weavers dire Unroll to shroud our gallant ones As they advance! IV They followed once—who rode so well— As brave a hunt as e'er blew horn: And now through warren'd woods of hell They follow till the fateful morn. And them the mudstain'd sentinel Shall watch, and see an age newborn As they advance! July 1916. Three Hours, O Christ Three hours, O Christ, Us to set free Did thy body hang On the bitter tree. Longer, Prometheus, Thou! Age-long Did the ridge of Asia Support thy wrong. But Man, whom ye loved— Man, in whose dream Ye did deliver, Ye did redeem— Whose weightless body At last hath wings, Leaves not the mount Of your sufferings:— Of his own creatures Become afraid, Gnawn by the vultures Himself hath made; Man, in whom vision Outsoars the will, To Earth, war-weary, Is nailèd still. August 1914. Battle of the Marne This action was in truth a chain of five battles in a curved line. Those who know the ground will recognise in this poem the middle battle. “Attila's namesake, the young prince,” refers to Eitel Friedrich, son of William II. His private correspondence was found in a trench in a low plantation on the plain under Mont Aout, between Broussy and La Fère Champenoise. The name of Attila was transformed by German chroniclers and bards into Atli, Azzilo, Ezzilo, and, in the Nibelungenlied, Etzel. Now the name Etzel, sometimes written Aiezelin, is derived from the Celtic root aidu, meaning “fire,” and refers to purity of race (Förstemann, Altdeutsches Namenbuch, vol. i. Personennamen, pp. 43, 45). Eitel, from a common root (cf. the stem eit, meaning “fire,” and eiten, “to burn”; and the Latin aedes, that is, “firestead,” “house,” “hearth”), also means “of high, or fire-pure, race” (Grimm, vol. iii. p. 384); and was attached to princes of that house and other houses before the year 1400 (Stokvis, Manuel d'hist., de généalogie et de chronologie, vol. iii. p. 166). No more than this is implied by the words, “Attila's namesake.” I Sing we of that whereof all song hath sense, That sovran mystery unnamed That makes a nation in its just defence So stern in confidence, Stronger by far than it is bodily, A thing not with the body to be tamed. Beaten Antaeus-like to ground It springs up like a forest tree. Marne knows it not, impetuous for the sea, But well ye know it, ye Deep-minded, formidable listeners, O Forests of the Marne! II Marne's stately water, That melancholy many-winding river, Hath many a battle known Since by her island of the beechen copses, Boar-hunting palace of the Merovings And full this month of autumn-glancing wings, Pale Fredegonda drowned her lover's son— But like this battle, none. Marne, who beneath this chalky spur From woods of Gault and forest of Traonne, Herself doth milky tribute rivers drain,— Marne, the far-wanderer, Stretches not wide as this day's battle line. Now from this bosky mountain spur Beneath the ruined castle Mondement Look down, look there, Towards Champenoise La Fère, Over moon-barren heaths, the vast chalk plain, Bald moors of high Champagne Scattered with spindling woods of birch and pine By the straggled marsh-belt of Saint Gond,— By Reuves and Broussy, Oyes and Bannes, Little marsh-villages with scarce a name, There hangs your lot and mine. Nightlong the marshfire Death hangs flickering Above the pale-lipp'd middle of the line, Watching—from Verdun wall to Paris wall— Whether we stand or fall, Whether the European liberties Pass into dust Like a thing temporal That dureth no long while Or shall outlast us all. These are the claims august, And this the fate that shall be settled there. III Here, Forests of the Marne, Where still your birds are calling, Your streams of light in all directions falling On floors with ivy sheen'd, room beyond room, Your stems, the elder brothers of our house, Would chant with pillar'd ever-budding boughs, Of France our mother, she that drains The wild cloud from the shoreless height Of suns, in your twice-dropping rains, Staunches your heavings day and night— Nerves you against the tempest's strains And soothes the lightning from your veins, Dark rivers of the light. But now is light forgot, Forests of Gault, Traonne; Here lightning is that she soothes not, Lightning from human fears. Blasted and wreckt The zigzag mire of trenches runs, About the ruin'd castle Mondement, Amid your glades blood-fleck'd That tremble all with guns. At Charleroi defeated France hath retreated, Whelm'd are her wise and tomb-embedded walls Inwrought with statues in heroic fragments, Founded on famous written stones; Beauty's time-chartered capitals, Her royal towns, Reims, Soissons, Laon, Are fallen. What else falls? And what though Attila was check'd And headed back to the Hercynian wood From these same Catalaunian fields Where shattered were his waggon forts and shields, Never, since Autumn was, Hath tempest strown the grass Nor charged the spirit-life of atmospheres With ruin rich as this tremendous Year's— For here the soul of France Hath baulk'd the great advance Of all their cannoniers. IV And here your armies, leopard-like, well shielded, Leaf-strewn and shadow-mottled in the dews As the moths that shower about their torch-lit blades, Are couch'd in the wet glades, The young men in their flower Lying in their shoddy coats of shabby blue; And heavy on their hearts Lies all that ground of France that they have yielded. From her they ask no thanks, They who to-day will choose That they must die. They know How lovely is the world that they must lose: This bracken smell, these rivulets floating by, Yet word is passed along the ranks; A surge of joy along the endless ranks— The bayonets rise, the young men rise and go. V France watched that ordered nation Its miracle perform— Saw Germany transform Her summer veil of spies To a tempest of horses and of guns. Though France be loved with fire and fear, With what allies can France confront them here? Can flesh and blood resist The whining ever keener Of that blast out of the east, And the heavy undertone Of yon wheeling symphony of storms? You shall see the world's substructure Laid bare unto the bone, Yet by the high demeanour Of the chief protagonist What mighty forms live on. But how near her breath was gone! To her sons, as they retreated, “Fall back,” she cried, “to Aisne, To Marne, to Aube, to Seine, Ere I can strike again And my battle be completed!” Unshaken was her strain Though near her life was gone. VI And trembling masses of the reeds In the marshes of Saint Gond— Like their holy eremite Retreated waist-deep to these waters cold, Thirsting for desolation here That they might only hear The frog's lone flute Amidst their shivering maze, Or cry of wild duck sheer Down the still waterways,— Hear now exchange of salvoes rolled From Mont Aout to Toulon La Montagne, Cannon from the scarped vineyard-crests Of Congy's northern height That look on the bleak plain. And who would guess the embrace Of conflict for man's soul? The alder covert's trysting-place Of wood-wren and of oriole Still on the marshy bank's short grasses Hoopoe or little bittern passes To hunt food for their young. In the brown reeds, reed-warblers great and small Flit and yet flit. But why Makes he such scrutiny, Attila's namesake, the young prince, Knelt in the white and shallow pit Beside the marshes and stunt pines? Steadily gazing into the sky He sees the harrier-hawk, to feed his mate Fluttering below him in blue air, Let the clutcht lizard fall. Tumbling, six feet below in air, Backward she catches it And bears off to her tussock'd nest In the reed-beds of Saint Gond. The young prince smiles to see them play So featly with a prey. Nine armies lie behind him on the crest Along that line of scarpèd heights Of Congy and of La Chenaille; From Verdun wall to Paris wall Swooping wing-shadows of the eagle fall Who drops to his mate to-day The shrivell'd lizard France. Not even the ruin'd castle Mondement, Warden of all the marshes' realm, Remembers that beyond The rushes, in those waters of Saint Gond, Beneath the she-hawk's tussock'd nest Sleeps Attila's lost golden helm. . . . Cloaking Man's long misdeeds Hold they their gentle bitter colloquy Remote, the ceaselessly Trembling masses of the reeds. VII Even should She perish, stunned, Why for this patch of ground While vintaged suns are blithe And dancing in the glass, Now should it come to pass That men must drop before the scythe, Bound by the same religion as the grass? What, after all, is France? 'Tis she who since Rome's wane Hath been man's leader these two thousand years. She, always first to bear the throe Europe must after undergo, Who beneath the centralising touch of pain Winces into control by brain— Her very hurts become for her an eye— Who first among the nations seems to attain Most near to conscious personality; Until her rudest sea-washt frontier-part Is yet repeated at her heart, And something of her wingèd whole Glass'd upon every Pyrenean herdboy's soul. She, who at Gergovia Rallying the bare clans of the plaided Gael, Alone defeated the great Caesar's dint; She, who at Alesia Massed on her long green mountain's table head, Took for all time the noble Caesar's print Of valour rein'd, and wisdom humanised, And conquest by compassion fortified. Steadfastly to diffuse Her simple hearth-gods use She to expanding thought from Hellas wins, And, beside the freedom she extols, She to imagine law for souls Through the Roman and the Christian disciplines; Slow pinnacle by feudal pinnacle Hath laboured ages without stint To make the many-chambered habitation Of her exalted spirit swell, And by many an anchoret's faint-candled cell, Or flame-lit vestal, like her vestal Joan, Hath from the Alban mount brought down Into your wild green commonwealth of trees The sacred fire familial, And let it on her nation's altar dwell To raise for mother and child a roof sublime. VIII To knit this fabric out of chivalries Her reason charmed so well, By sheer enchanting measure to enthral She chained as Orpheus by a spell Intense, the stubborn'st rock of adversaries, Gascon, Burgundian, Breton, Provencal, Into the very substance of her wall, To be its buttresses, nay, pillars vast, Projecting on the future the brave past, That she by grace and force reciprocal Their countervailing valours did subsume. Her lifting voice Ensheaved these mighty rebel strains to poise Into a nation, ruling us and time. IX By gift of the life communal she reigned Who never yet to Christendom played false Nor yet the light belied, Belying that through which she had attained. Yet, still unsatisfied, France, the propylon of the west, Forecourt of ecstasy's imaginings, With crowded front of half a thousand kings And saints, like Reims's doors eternal, Rose-window'd, deep-recess'd, Hath raised her triple portal— Free, equal, and fraternal— Yet is herself unsatisfied; Long as her state body from soul divide She knows her state is but the destined portal Into another that shall make more free. Leader is she to us Because with such a self unsatisfied; And, she being perill'd thus, Voices not ours in her defence (Like some troubled and illumined sense Exchanged between the sun's and the earth's desire) Descend and call on us To defend, and to fulfil. X Ah! Forests of the Marne, Forests of Gault, Traonne, Of what avail is all your stubborn toil, Of what avail is hers, Rising resistant through so many years, If now, from coast to coast, This noble France be lost? If now this golden France from beach to beach, Her women, sisters of the race of Rome, Her mothers, and that Mother divine, her soil, Be wrest from us by force? We have no need for speech. Harden'd are we by Life: its iron pains, Its shunless endings, do we know; But since She—who is all we have, And so much more— Since she that bore, that fed us with the Earth's Breast-love, before we heard of chains Or guess'd the pangs of birth, Save us, hath now no more resource;— Since she whose shining colour'd plains, Streams, fresh leaves, fire and dew, Ran in our eyes and veins When we ourselves were new And ran about with flower-like breath Before we ever knew There was a thing call'd Death— Herself is like to die,— She, the convergence of our rays, The Eternal smiling on our days,— To pass from us, to die!— Silent as you, O Forests of the Marne, In her defence Our deaths must be our eloquence. XI Some message flies through all, Men are made integral, We lay down cares, we bid good-bye, Embrace in the public eye, Stoop to the children, and depart. Stranger to stranger passing by Opens his long-forgotten heart, Each with amazèd weeping hears The ineffable stark simple truth. The lads and maidens in their throngs Outbreaking like the mountain waterfalls Beneath the breach'd Republic's walls Flood by, singing the old songs Of equal, free, fraternity. Men march out through the barriers To the last infrangible frontiers, And the old men with the step of youth. Some message, fusing all, Moulds and makes integral; Men feel again after their perfect wholes, Arise the maimed and scattered members Of all this wounded ground of France. Out of the plain the leaves that seemed September's Are gathered by a great wind that controls, There comes a sob of flame upon the embers— A wordless breathing on the coals Passes by; Man remembers The unity of souls. And with whose overruling Form do we entwine, Sparks from the forges, blown through space? Or that thou, rising evermore Whirl'd leaf, art becomes a sign, That the chill husk becomes a core And the strange mask, a face, And the one man, a race, And that race, a thing divine? It is the soul of France That stems the great advance Of all their cannoniers. XII “Continue, O continue,” cry her dreams, And the very fibres of her stems; Floating forest voices bode And break like a sea over the continents, “Continue, O continue,” cry her faiths, Her wisdoms, savour of continuity, Sweeping from node to node Her mounting sap, her sapience, Like her green glens Of brooks that pour the sky from fall to fall Her grave religions to the labourer call, “Thou art required, infinitesimal! Now comes the day of pang Of which thy fathers sang, When at the edge of death Thou must pass on That high contagion, Her life, that gave thee breath.” “Continue, O continue,” cries her noble Reason, “Thy life but serves, creating in due orders The floating judgments of the invisible Hearths, throng'd within my borders; And for the free play of the soul's Most intimate loneliness and fire! Upon their counter'd voices, joined, depend All judgment, and all justice, in the end.” 'Tis thus the soul of France Hath stemm'd the great advance Of yonder cannoniers. XIII Four nights along the marshy zone of mists The sleepless line of France resists; And four nights end those days With apocalyptic blaze, Uncertain darkness shot with rays, And golden smoke Rolls out over the thick reeds Deepening the mystery of those dead waters. The eyeless Chateau Mondement, Towering and hollow guard, That like another Lear Stands at the marshes' end and narrow gate, Upon his bosky mountain spur By Poirier's hill white-scarr'd— Besieged and lost By either host, Lighteth no more for the marsh-wanderer Upon his naked-rafter'd turret spire, The kindly signal fire That he for centuries was wont to raise. Summon'd in vain to be strife's arbiter He with insane dark gaze Nightlong upon his plateau listens Smitten with gun on gun, And feels beneath his trembling woods, And about his deep-ravined and dusky base, The arms of great and little Morin run Thrilled with the fate of all that they embrace. XIV Four nights doth parching battle sway Towards the fourth inexorable day; Then outbreaks autumn tempest, rain and hail Towards evening of the day. And, with the rising of that sunset gale, When at last the long-awaited Forty-second Division rode down to Corroy Everywhere then came leapings of the heart! Whisperers strange upstart, Leaf-hosts in whirl'd careers Down Marne's cliffs, willow'd reaches, swollen weirs, Over the bridge of Lagny's foundered piers And St. Rémy's cannon-lighted heart; From vineyard, marsh, heath, copse, Caught up to mix above the forest tops, And blazon'd on a hundred winds to dance Upon the glowing misty airs With low and feverish cries Whirls the whole realm of leaves. And the young men, lifting up their fierce exhausted eyes Above the woods of Gault and forests of Traonne, And from the seven poplar'd roads Threading the marshland zone, Behold the voyage of those torn leaves And, launched above their spiral rise Out of all her deep and stubborn families, They see ascend the wingèd feet of France Terribly to repel. “Behold her,” cry the leaves and winds eternal, “Thrice holy, the maternal, Thrice holy, the son-shaper, Herself our radiant eddy of star vapour Out of whirlwinds of the planet, plant and shell, Emerging to repair her wounded cell.” They remember her, red leaves, and with no fears. Not in the day serene, In cities of the vintage proud, Plainly by them was this Immortal seen, But now, against the midnight thundercloud, Above the shell-pits of our field of dead. Her lineaments are clear, devoid of dread, The glories of her wings are bow'd To us, when our light fails And to the inconsolable her face unveils. The soul of one called France— A secret spirit—far Stronger than any France— Hath turned the tide of war And baulk'd the great advance Of yonder cannoniers. XV By the first hour of dawn Up Congy's steep vine-glades Retreat the tunics grey, And through forests of Compiègne Northwards by stealth, by night, The enemy his rearguards hath withdrawn— The wolf's jaw broken by the bite— To camp upon the brows of Aisne. Then, as a Chinese juggler standing far away Will shower his volley'd blades Round a pale woman's patient face And delicate throat, leant back, unscored By the fringe of knives fixed quivering in the board, He rains from the hills his fire On Reims, the sea of house-roofs round the base Of the mountainous Basilica twin-towered, And spares it in the midst, crushing them all, To be his witness and memorial Of skill and grace. XVI The birds flit unafraid Through the great cannonade; And, O Cannoniers, though ill The forests take your skill, And as by winter nipp'd Scatter leaves bullet-stript Down the shell-ravaged road— Still in its dark abode, In the branches of God, The Soul sings on alone. You may blow the dead from their crypt— Not the dream from its throne. XVII They shall conquer who become Chasm—leaping flashes, spirits self-transcendent— Transmitters of the harmonies of honour Breaking familial from the wasted Earth. XVIII We are not last, we are not highest, Upon the topless scale of being. Closing above our heads, Like you, the many-fountain'd forest, With crests beyond our seeing, (That may be real, and yet may never be) Arise, with lighted chalices, The things in truth most dear to us— Forms of the half-seen sacred Families Bearing, and yet unborn— Seeking, and ever seeking, the perfect flower! And within their cells translucent As in a second womb Our whole lives rise and pass; Each petal in its station, Each body in its sheath. For above, around, beneath The narrow and clear-lighted ring Of each work-day intelligence, There hangs in deep penumbra Whence only beauty speaketh, The Will that upward seeketh, Tossing the pattern of our streaming wills Up hotly from our childhood's plains and hills In ever-widening spiral sweep That yet its steady core doth keep. It is the race creates our soul By touches many-fingered. It is our land that makes the soul to sing, In beauty like the forest's murmuring. As prisoners speak from cell to cell By beatings on the wall, So speaks to us out of her shrine, This sea-beat France, this Gaul, As a god might speak unto a vine Travelling across his temple wall,— By impulse from the divine, Upheaved through the familiar ground— Throbbings of our own heart-beats, our own nation. And Beauty is that language of the race, O beauty is the tongue, In which—be it lived or sung— With utter selflessness of mood, Into the daring instant's time and place The small immediate life is flung With the careless gesture of infinitude. Thus is upheaved the Nation, Like you, the many-fountain'd forest, Closing above our heads— Content that, while we sink, it spreads Abroad on the sunn'd wave of Time Wider its flowering incandescences; A many-voiced, a many-thirsted thing— As full of eyes as heaven hath stars—a thing Ascending to the future like a song Moulded of fineless will and meditation.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SHORTER POEMS The Strait Ah, sleepless race, Ye that a thousand years sail'd to destroy Past Lemnos Isle and Samothrace The cloud-rebuilded pirate fort of Troy— Who perish'd not for Helen's face To keep for kings her beauty's joy, But died to burst the Asian robbers' gate And send Athena sailing thro' the iron strait On lifted shield,— Sleep now in pride! Asia shall yield to you to-day once more When beak'd ships of the freemen ride Past Holy Wisdom's wave-wash'd templedoor! Across the Hellespont's astride Power darker than the Minotaur. But in your Goddess Virgin's battle-wake Again shall we the sea-path into freedom break That you reveal'd. 1917. Who art Thou, Starry Ghost Who art thou, starry ghost, That ridest on the air At head of all the host, And art so burning-eyed For all thy strengthlessness? World, I am no less Than She whom thou hast awaited; She who remade a Poland out of nothingness, And hath created Ireland out of a breath of pride In the reed-bed of despair. 1917. Lines from Salonica On the Pass up from the plain In the land of Macedon We halted and drew rein, And, looking backward down, Beheld Amphipolis, Vast-ruined, in Thracian valleys Where to-day's village is A rat's nest in a palace. And gazing on that scene We trembled, and were dumb. O, great as Man has been Can he become? Hellenes may hold that pass In the land of Macedon And walk where Plato was, But Plato's soul—has gone. What are our minds, to his— And what are we become? Even as Amphipolis That filled the Thracian valleys Where to-day's village is A rat's nest in a palace. 'Twas then, O spirits bow'd, Snow-shoulder'd Rhodope Sent a keen wind from her cloud That called to us aloud: Russia is free! Spring, 1917. Thou Stream Thou Stream of immortality and fire Embank'd in crumbling bound, Splendour of impulse and desire On through the blue profound! Thy human atoms break, for ever fleeing. But still through them unrolled In waves, and loves, and purposes of being, Through them made manifold, Doth Life beyond thy seeing Bear on, not waxing old— Flood on, not growing cold. Deep in a High Valley Deep in a high valley, soft-footed, lonely, Guarded by happy snow-hung woods for him only, (Slopes of the green combe were in flower with the cherry,) Danced, on an oak storm-fallen, one that was merry. Look at the boy aloft, with one finger to stay him, Toss'd on a frail bough wildly to weigh him, Lording, on one bare foot, old Kronos occulted, Long that had lain uprooted, stript, and insulted. Up and down, the young villain, giddily swinging, Gusty with creaking flight and the soar of singing, Higher and higher yet his balladry launches Skyward, last carol to float from its branches, Until grey-weather'd Cotswolds, themselves not sorry, Ring with his small glee, quarry by quarry! O heavenly flowering orchards, that one who peruseth The song of Prometheus freed, cunningly chooseth To rove in at early dawn, bold downs and mazes Of milk-white alleys, rising to far blue hazes Of Stratford—a valiant barefoot master bestrides you! As 'twere that lost truant, that hedger and ditcher Escaped us, horseboy sage and the world's bewitcher. His is the flood that churns in amongst woods to deliver— Rocking in under us, mighty as Severn river. Upheave, ye foaming shires, at sound of his coming! Awake and arise, white canyons, fluttering and humming, Again the abundant genius of joy betides you— Loose, magnificent Spring in this brown whelp rides you! Flame-footed Youth Flame-footed youth, have you a mind To follow Ecstasy— To woo pale Ecstasy for friend? Is that the crock of gold you'd find Under the rainbow's end? The wooing-wisdom they reap so Who win from fever free, 'Tis not a crop that fools may scorn— But do you know, boy, do you know How late true love is born? First-love's a star will flare to nought— Will fall and coasting flee— Escaping, as it falls, like fire; But true love's old—a singing thought More lovely than desire. On the State Of Man, from Woman's knees, No great state shall remain, Until the woman sees And helps with equal brain And as radiant energy To build the walls of Rome; And to make the laws of Rome Just, as her loves at home. All else is frailty. TO AROLILIA O might I only leave the song More beautiful than silence! I: A SONG TO AROLILIA, DWELLER BY THE FOUNTAIN When you were born, the Earth obeyed; (Call her, Echo!) Fragrancies from the distance blew, Beanfields and violets were made, And jasmine by the cypress grew— Jasmine by the cloudy yew— (Call, her, Echo! (Call Arolilia by her name!) When you were born, despairs must die, (Call her, Echo!) Sweet tongues were loosened from a spell— Snow mountains glistened from on high And torrents to the valleys fell— A song into Man's bosom fell— (Call her, Echo! Call Arolilia by her name!) When you were born, hid lightning's shape (Call her, Echo!) Took up the poor man's altar coal, His green vine throbbed into the grape, And in the dastard sprang a soul— Even in the dastard sprang a soul! (Call her, Echo! Call Arolilia by her name!) When you were born, all golden shot (Call her, Echo!) Fountains of daybreak from the sea, And still, if near I find you not— If steps I hear, but you come not— Darkness lies on the world for me! (Call her, Echo! Call Arolilia by her name!) 2: THE CROCUS I On mountains the crocus Ere hollows be clear In the bed of the snowdrift Will rise and appear; Aloft the pure crocus Born under the snow In the sun is left trembling, All bare to his glow, Like the heart of the woman who listens to love in the forests below: II “O light-born, how oft Shall I drink in, like wine, Thy body cloud-soft, Earth's marvel, yet mine? How oft shall I dare, Unabsolvèd by death, In the flood of thy hair, In the flame of thy breath? From the incense-boat Sun hast thou wandered, a dream from a time beyond death?” III She yearns to respond To that strain out of reach, To that glowing and subtle Stream-spirit of speech. But she weeps—ah, too childish— For love is the span Of the half-bestrung lyre Of the language of man; She breathes the sun-song of the crocus,— reveal it, repeat it, who can! In the Jura, June. 3: THE NIGHT I put aside the branches That clothe the Door in gloom; A glow-worm lit the pathway And a lamp out of her room Shook down a stifled greeting. How could it greet aright The thirst of years like deserts That led up to this night? But she, like sighing forests, Stole on me—full of rest; Her hair was like the sea's waves, Whiteness was in her breast. (So does one come, at night, upon a wall of roses.) As in a stone of crystal The cloudy web and flaw Turns, at a flash, to rainbows, Wing'd I became—I saw, I sang—but human singing Ceased, in a burning awe. Slow, amid leaves, in silence, Rapt as the holy pray, Flame into flame we trembled, And the world sank away. 4: THE REPARATION When Man was hounded from glens of Eden, a rover, By reason of her, his mate, And under the pair lay the stone of the world, and over Terrors of Night and Fate, O then did the sorrowful hands of the Woman discover A roof against despair, And spread for the rebel head of her dreaming lover The shadow of her hair. 5: THINE EYES IN MINE EYES Thine eyes in mine eyes Swift though the flame dies Each to each, mirror-wise, Open infinities. Freely without end Light may the soul spend. Rings of the pool blend; So thou and I, friend. 6: COME, LET US MAKE LOVE DEATHLESS Come, let us make love deathless, thou and I, Seeing that our footing on the Earth is brief— Seeing that her multitudes sweep out to die Mocking at all that passes their belief. For standard of our love not theirs we take; If we go hence to-day Fill the high cup that is so soon to break With richer wine than they! Ay, since beyond these walls no heavens there be Joy to revive or wasted youth repair, I'll not bedim the lovely flame in thee Nor sully the sad splendour that we wear. Great be the love, if with the lover dies Our greatness past recall, And nobler for the fading of those eyes The world seen once for all! 7: SONG ON BLACKDOWN Since it was love of you that first revealed Rapture of glens and blown dance of the sky, The march of storm and rivers in the field And hanging blaze of ocean, how should I Without your presence feel that spirit strong That kissed my soul to song, And showed me the moon's race, of dreamy nights, When through the pearly reefs she foams along Zoned with a flame athwart the wine-dark heights To build about the night-paths of the summer Her sunken palaces of silver lights? Come, come, and climb with me to this great Down Where the sea-roar of pines puts care to sleep, And 'midst the blaeberry and heather brown Watch far below resistless shadows sweep The Wealden plain whose villages ray fire From many a chanted shire— Walk with me now above the plains and seas, Ere in us both the springs of life expire— And leave with hearts flung open to the breeze Self-muttering cities, that have lost horizons, To sink behind the mountains and the trees! 8: THERE IS A PLANT THAT BLOSSOMS AT MIDNIGHT There is a plant that blossoms at midnight And fosters in itself a sombre dawn; And some in passion only find delight Leaping to sorrow, like seed furnace-drawn; But thou upon the forces that enslave Breakest like light, where the deep chasms immure, For thou art of the race of them that save, And where thy footstep passes it makes pure. Like the first hour of morning, sleep-washed, free, When every pulse of man's collected soul Ascends to be what it was born to be, Returning like the needle to the pole, Noiselessly as a perfume or a prayer, Or lake-born cloud, the flame that in thee lies Unseals over the mountains of dense care The welling golden water of sunrise. Gignese, above Lago Maggiore, 1912. 9: SHE COMES NOT WHEN NOON IS ON THE ROSES She comes not when Noon is on the roses— Too bright is Day. She comes not to the soul till it reposes From work and play. But when Night is on the hills, and the great Voices Roll in from sea, By starlight and by candlelight and dreamlight She comes to me. 10: A SONG Her, my own sad love divine, Did I pierce as with a knife, Stabbed with words that seemed not mine Her more dear to me than life. And she raised, she raised her head, Slow that smile, pale to the brow: “Lovely songs when I am dead You will make for me; but how Shall I hear them then?” she said, “Make them now, O make them now!” 11: REQUICKENING VOICE Tired with the day's monotony of dreamèd joys I turn to a requickening voice, A voice whose low tone devastates with nightly thrill The cities I have wrought at will: Stone forts depart, and armies heroic flee away Like the wild snow of spray, Deep down the green Broceliande's branch'd corridors That voice of April pours; Light as a bird's light shadow fled across my pages A touch disturbs the ages, And the crags and spears of Troy and the courts of Charlemain, Odin, and the splendid strain Of Cuchullain's self, that with his heart's high brother strove,— Fade at the low voice I love! 12: TO-NIGHT DARK SEAS AND LANDS To-night dark seas and lands Between us lie And, to taunt these graceless hands, Stern mountains high. Yet to-night your voice from home Most soft, most clear, Over the gulfs hath come Straight to mine ear. Still chain'd between two poles Must mortals move Fronting with Janus souls On war, on love? Descend on them that steer it— Our ship ill-guided— Descend, sweet-counsell'd spirit, On Earth divided! Long since, in the desert's heat, I swooned, I fell, To find your love at my feet Like the desert's well; Now, loftier and more profound Than the Dawn at sea, Your spirit, like heavenly sound, Delivers me. 13: TO AROLILIA, URGING HIM Not laurels,—were they lying at my feet! Let hot-foot boys hunt the gold leaves of Fame. Received at thy hands, once they had been sweet, But not now; less than silence is a name. Fame! When thy thousand graces ask no praise— When all that perfect soul shall disappear, And leave no footprint of thy lovely ways Save in the desperate heart that held thee dear! Namelessly still, and yet all Fame surviving Beyond Death's baulk thy very self shalt move— All that's most thou in thee light on the living, Never to hear of thee, nor of thy love. We once found, where the Alpine forests blow, Columbine floating, heavenliest dreamer there; Nothing of its own beauty could it know, And for nothing less than for our praises care. That chalice would not last! O, had it choice 'Twould drain at once the whole illumin'd sky That enters it in rushing light and voice, To change into an “I” greater than “I”! Thy leaves ask not to last! Too close, too fine, That glow of the Absolute, inhung, they feel; The quick breath-sweeping thrill of the divine— Its very warmth left fresh on thee for seal! What's Fame to me, when thou wilt smile and pass Dew-like? For mean lives trumpets shall be blown; Thou wilt go wandering through the gate of grass, And thy place after thee be all unknown. Stanzas to Tolstoi in his Old Age This Ode was printed in an English Review, and received by L. Tolstoi, many years before his attempted pilgrimage and death. I Is this some glowering Titan, inly bright, Angered that summer grasses bloom and seethe Only to taunt him—strange to the upper light— Born at the mouth of Tartarus to breathe And lodged where vapour-dripping chasms ensheathe The groping ire of his tremendous hands? Are these the thews that kept in swaddling bands The wingèd Reason, and would now compel Beauty, that Spirit clear, And every art wherein the few excel Under a peasant's smock to serve as drudges? Is it one forgetful of a long career Through many wars and loves, who now begrudges To youth its fair love-season—one who quarrels With all not abject—one whose mood would bind Under one law the wearers of the laurels With feet upon the uplands, in the wind? II Or may this peasant demiurge not mask Mimir himself—the friend of right in hell, Him that gave Odin on his awful task Water of insight from the world-deep well, And stayed as the god's hostage, and so fell? Perhaps this soul, half-savage, half-divine, Is some freed ghost—the slave from Palestine, Grim Christopher, who strove as he had sworn To bear through the mid-flood That little Child—so hardly to be borne?. . . No, no, this is the prophet of the poor! That face is theirs—that heart hath understood Their piteous certainty in things unsure. And stay!—those shaggy brows, and haunting them Unrest, unrest—O in the Dolorous Street Have I not seen thee in Jerusalem, With sheepskin coat and hat and dusty feet, III Like a poor herdsman, pilgrim from the snows Far north of Volga, where his little hut Lay warm, who on some glittering night arose And blessed his old wife in the dark, and shut On her the door, and took his newly-cut Staff from the eaves—a sapling iron-shod— And set forth for the sepulchre of God? Yes, thence by great plains, Taurus passes bleak And fire-lit caravanserai On, on—though fever sapped his bony cheek Month after month, intent and still unbaulked, Counting the dawns that met his wind-clear eye, Thousands of miles to find it had he walked! But now—since thou hast kissed the very stone, Why restless still, gaunt shepherd, come so far? Why mourn because the ray that led thee on Shines from a long-annihilated star? IV The Man upraised on the Judaean crag Captains for us the war with death no more. His kingdom hangs as hangs the tattered flag Over the tomb of a great knight of yore; Nor shall one law to unity restore Races or souls—no staff of thine can urge Nor knotted club compel them to converge, Nor any backward summit lead them up: The world-spring wherein hides Formless the God that forms us, bursts its cup— Is seen a Fountain—breaking like a flower High into light—that at its height divides; Changelessly scattering forth,—in blaze and shower— In drops of a trembling diaphaneity— Dreams the God-breathings momently upbuoy To melt a myriad ways. Those dreams are we, Chanted from some unfathomable joy. V What! Wouldst to one conception mould mankind? Hast thou not felt—on thy lone mountain track Seeing, from some ridge of forest-rushing wind Where the oak-boughs overhead wrestle and crack, Night-plains be-starred with cities mirror back The naked deeps of stars—hast thou not felt The whole high scheme wherein we move and melt With the swift world—that its last secret is Not Good, nor Immortality, But Beauty,—once to behold the immensities Filled with one soul, then to make room and die? Hence the true faith:—to the uttermost to be Thyself—to follow up that ecstasy Compelling—to let being take its course, Rise like a song, and like a dream be free, Poised on the breath of its own soul and source: Enough—the Fountain will re-gather thee! VI Rejoice then, Master, at the multitude Of wills in the many-coloured nations—yea At the clouds of destinies distinct—the flood Of exploring visions—all the radiant spray Of hostile forces on their upward way, Spirals of the interweaving elements And species, these are but the long ascents Of the self-poised waters of the Universe Opening like a rose, Ingathering all it loses—to disperse Its soul in fragrance on the night's abyss, Yet to build for aye the rainbow as it flows; Rejoice that we have spectacle of this— Of the Fountain opening, opening like a rose, And Eternal Wisdom rising from its core; For the light increases, and the rapture grows, And the love, in them that perish, waxes more. Stanzas on Poetry Here in the Pentecostal woods are seen Mid glens of floating odours, shifting sheen, Motionless yews and scintillating green Of birches young; and here in wandering mood Our feet brushed through the drifts of listless leafage When quick and flame-like Spring was on the bough. Distinct each budding tongue could tell its tale And underfoot the tide of flowers, that pale Firmament, so eternal and so frail, Powdered the woody bosoms of the combes, And everywhere infinity was hinted, Stealing in clouds of gems into the air. And here, in stillness of this stately place, I asked my musing friend to lift the grace On me of her immortal speech and face, And to reveal how in this roaring world A man may tune his lips, and she replied: “So sing, that nothing of thee shall grow old! “This is your end, and this is your reward, To become attuned to the universal chord Wherein all life makes answer to its Lord. O spectator of the sun and night and sea, Great waters with a song-born ocean-sighing Revolve their everlasting floods through thee! “Lift up thy head! tear off the servile mask, Salute the dead, and take on thee their task! In thee man's sleeping powers assemble. Ask! Choose—wilt thou like a cow-boy ride savannahs? Attend the Delian high solemnity? Unbury Egypt, or by Newton kneel? “Be thou, thrice-hot forewafted heart and sight, A wingèd creature, questing for delight, Released from bonds, and by augurial flight Before the gaze of the earth-hungering horde Show thou the pass over Caucasus, the barrier! Or divine thou the sunk waters of the moon! “Chant like the head of that slain king they found The night after the battle by sweet sound In a cluster of rushes on the battle-ground, That sang at his beheaders' feast such truth They would kneel to the pallid lips upon the pillar For saving wisdom and clear prophecy! “Inscription on the lightless dungeon be! Far trumpet that may set the prisoner free! Ray from the battleship on Futurity! Soar, thou blue mosque of lapis-lazuli Whose mortar with rare incense hath been mingled, Fragrant for ever at the sultry noon! “In thee Man's choir assembles, and finds tongue! Thy soul like Roland's horn of echoes flung Must seize the mountains that it gropes among, Must strike and must betray the Invisible— Black peaks that like a crowd of humbled Gods Attend the benediction of the Dawn!” “Goddess,” I cried, “the task is far too great! Spare, overwhelming energies of Fate! Turn aside—shoulders cannot bear your weight; Descend not on us weaklings, us the living!” “I speak to Man!” she said. “The millwheel turns: Between thee and thy son lies but a sleep. “Is not the statue inwardly impaled On iron, when 'tis set aloft and hailed For beauty? Smiling have my noblest failed! Playful as Socrates, the ungainly seer, Or the glorious Persian, whom, when Balkh was stormed, Turanians at his blackened altar slew. “There is no light except the light they saw! There is no song except that song of awe, The slow-unscrolling palimpsest of Law, Where here and there a mighty word ye read (O rushlights seeking on the battlefield!) In haste, by the hasty taper of yourselves! “Thy song shall be imperfect, never fear, Seeing but the half, the half of it is here; Yet fall'n to the heart out of the atmosphere (If the symbol in thy hands ring metal true) Flake soft electric touches of that Life Whose heart-beats are sun-rises, slow and clear. “Do not thy windows every morning hail The sheen of Thames, curved in the forest vale? What splendour, though its reach from vision fail! More than a brief arc you may never scan Of the sweep o' the world, or the destiny of man, Yet now begins to dawn on you the curve— The sense of scale, the orbit's formula. “Love, Courage, Truth, these are; and, while these stand, Who can say Gods inhabit not this land? If wise men sifting light from Saturn's band Discern the rainbowed metals there, what wonder If these passions in your dust shine back to Saturn, If the Soul, regnant in you, reign everywhere! “And if the chorded metals and the fine Elements, in ethereal discipline, Be spaced about the orchestra divine So thou canst gauge a gap, and prove the curve Celestial—even unveil the dark companion Of devious orbs—may not thy soul intense “In its unfrontier'd and illumined mood Hear, far beyond its borders, as it would, At the due interval, with certitude, Transcendent harmony, transcendent Good? The Gods themselves are pipes in one great organ Wherethrough the nations send their shuddering breath; And, were they mute, that music is eternal.” Prelude to a Masque Written as a prelude to a Masque of Ben Jonson's given at the Coronation Gala Performance at His Majesty's Theatre, June 27, 1911. In the audience were representatives of many countries. The “Prelude to a Masque” was first spoken by Mrs. Patrick Campbell in June 1911, at His Majesty's Theatre. Princes, behold a Masque, a vizored Image of things— A merry shadow of things eternal—dust of a Rose Gathered, three centuries gone, for a merrymaking of Kings: Life it hath still and fragrance, infinity and repose. Swift as the flame of a Cloud, a summer Cloud high-hung, Mock you not our poor Masque for the transiency of its sweetness. Our time's a time for Symbols—who can with fullness of tongue Utter this widening World to-day with the old completeness? Not as a Play that is played out orderly, clear to the end, Rounded from simple beginnings, unveils the Show universal. All's but a dim-lit Fragment, a fragment with much to amend, Much to rehearse and excuse. The whole crude World's a Rehearsal! And so some Dance like a wind, some snatch of a Song or a Stave, Is our time's best incarnation—all we can humbly demand Who feel a power through the ages thrilling, wave upon wave, Each wave by a greater that follows compelled to expand, expand! For lo! by the lyric touch of some God behind the scenes Are the walls of this Players' house, like a rude shell, sounded! And the tears that surge in you are the tears of ancient Queens, And by the soul in your eyes shall the Future be founded! I see the Earth, outscrolled like a glittering Map, lie here, Her Indian snows and seas, her minarets, palms and isles, And Time, from his last generation, his topmost encircling Tier Looks down on the glittering Map, and salutes . . . and smiles. The Playhouse itself enlarges, seems to transcend, surpass, Melt into the scene of the World. And shall there be the ultimate close? Or wave-like shall Man, enkindled, and, mirrored from glass unto glass, Become at length aware of an audience divine? Who knows? An Ode to Beauty I Beauty, thou secret lamp, awake! Tremble into sound! Burn in me now, as thou didst break Those glooms profound When with laughter of Olympians we Marched to a song, Vagabonds young, vagabonds free, Up the mountains long. Our road over roots of Apennine Wound up, star-proof, For the thick-enwoven forest pine Made it a roof Trebled for the foot-weary wight— The knapsack bowed— By shade of precipices, night And brooding cloud. Came a yellow diligence flashing down Cheerily jingling, Rocking from side to side, and soon With the valleys mingling; And we overtook a team up-hill, Some woodman's load, Struggling though halted, breasting still The invisible road. Long after, his whip's crack and cry And axle's plaint Followed us up the forests high, Submerged and faint. II We sang no more; each aching sense Craved silence, caring But to climb on, on—forgetful whence Or whither faring. Cold sweat dript from us as we marched, Grim fancies smote, Imprisoned grew the spirit—parched The stifled throat. O for a breath up the ravines To rift and rend This muffling web of branchy screens That never end! Dulness, even melancholy, stole From friend to friend As we left the dark high-road where whole Forests impend And took the path up the cliff's face, Brushwood and stones, Clambering up from base to base On the Earth's bones. . . . So hour by hour, until the escape. At last—look back! Low in the gorge 'twixt cape and cape Battalion'd, black, Creeps radiance: a flush aureoles Yon crag! It bridges Veiled chasms—floods the expectant souls Of sombre ridges. . . . Hail to thee, Moon! Sudden she surged, Far out and sheer Over vague plains immense, and purged Our spirits clear, Bathed our dust-heavy eyes with awe And scope untold— All sleeping Italy we saw Fold beyond fold. . . . We watch'd far down one cloudlet curl Glimmering and frail, Opal and green and blue and pearl Swam on its veil; And about us rocky pastures spoke In herds of bells, And hark! the waterfalls like smoke Blown from the fells; And aloft the fading arch of all The stars, whose pouring Maketh no thunder in its fall Nor any roaring. III And then, ah then! while in the bliss That yet is fear Ranging with thee the great abyss, O lovely Sphere, Did I remember, by some wand Invoked from sleep, Another lamp, rising beyond Another deep. . . . How I, a wandering lute of verse, When grapes grew heavy Had lodged in France with vintagers In a tavern leafy, And in a vine-dark corridor Of that rude inn Had glimpse through a half-open door Of an arm within, A woman's arm—bare, simple, pure, Holding a light Shielded (herself the while obscure) In exquisite Fingers translucent as a grape, Bird-wings or wine, Enshading in soft blood-hued shape The candle-shine. . . . A poise, a ray, a moment's gleam, But, when they went, Against the wall as in a dream Witless I leant, Knowing by that divine contour Of warmth and bloom Some thought immortal lit that poor Rough-paven room. Some eddy of the Infinite Wave on its way Had caught that arm and moulded it In mood of play; That curve was of the primal Will Whose gesture high Waved forth the choir of planets, still In ecstasy; And the rhythm of its dreamèd lines Shall still flood on Through souls beyond to-day's confines When we are gone, Shall bear to the unborn without name The inurnèd light Secret as life, signal as flame, And in that flight— Vaster than Moon's o'er Apennine's Sepulchral doors When from the breathless gap of pines Golden she soars— To the tranced rock, deep-sunken, dumb, Shall murmur, shall smile, “Glorious the dance of passions! Come To life awhile! I, Beauty, travelling heaven on the hoar Faint-phosphor'd wave Of Being, charge ye to explore And dare the grave!” Camaldoli. A Silver Birch I Muse, I will show thee, on a grassy mound Moving with tufted shadows, albeit bare Herself, for yet young April primes the air And bloom snow-laden boughs, the tree I love. London doth compass it with shores of sound And thrills the buds when there's no breath above To shake its fountain beauty. Thus I came Along the courtly mere of thicket isles, And Spring entoil'd me in a hundred wiles, Bringing the heart content without a name. Broods, russet-plumed and emerald, steer'd on With arrowy wake adown the placid tide, And in that gloomy pool there rode enskied, Aloof, the stately languor of a swan. But now the lake sets hither with a breeze And crooks the peel'd bole of its planes.—Ah there Thou shalt find audience—yon's my shadowy love!— O'er head a rose-grey pigeon beat his wings About his 'lighted mate and wooed the bough, And passion born of sight of mortal things In warmth of living, moved and moves me now As from the careless height that sways above Floateth his voice, the soul of greening trees! II Approaching 'twixt the herald saplings pale Whose light arrayment is a whirl of green, Of flamelets dropping for a virgin veil, I come. Though Hades' crocus-jets are stayed, Soft! for a golden troop instead upsprung Gossips apart in yon unfooted glade. Broke we on earshot of that frolic tongue Straightway would all be husht, they being afraid To sing't to simple ear of mutest maid. III But thou, still silver Spirit, unappall'd Standest alone, and with thy senses dim Feeling the first warmth fledge the unleafèd limb Hearest no tread of mine, O Sun-enthrall'd! What buried God conceived thee, and forestall'd In the dull depth thy white and glistening graces— That fume of netted drops and subtle laces And listening statue-air, by men miscall'd? Shower o'er the blue, and sister of blown surf! Dream-daughter of the silences of turf! Couldest thou but waken, and recall the Mind Lifts thee to image, then could I reveal Wherefore thou seem'st remember'd, and I feel In thee mine own dream risen and divined! IV Surely the hymn that charm'd thee from the grass Fashion'd me also, and the selfsame lyre Sounded accords that out of darkness pass And in thy beauty and my song conspire? The drum of streets, the fever of our homes, Clangours and murk metallurgy of gnomes, All are by thee unheard, who dost ignore The wisdom of the wise, in dead pasts now Dungeon'd, as never to ascend; but thou Whose being is for the light, and hath no care To know itself nor root from whence it sprang, Would'st only murmur, in the heavenly air, “The sun, the sun!” if but thy spirit sang! V O might I show thee, by the lute's devising, Man, from thy soft turf, flown with light, arising Him, too, doth hope, the boon without a pang, Summon with thrilling finger forth to hang— To cast a heaving soul to the wave of wind, Sun-passion'd and earth-lodged. Ah, Tree serene, Dilating in the glow of the unseen, We and our roofs and towers magnifical, Our Fame's heroic head against the sky, Our loves, and all That, with our briefness perfect, bloom and die,— Like thee must find Beauty in a besieging of the dark; Our glories on expectancy embark, And the height of our ecstasy, The touch of infinity, Is blind! Woman's Song for a Soldier From spans of the rosy cloud spread wide and clear, (Sing aloft, rare bugles!) From Atlantean headlands and seas aglow The moon uplifted her cold, enchanted sphere, And ghostly cruisers rode in the straits below. “I had rather this moment's bliss than to bide in story Famous ten thousand years on the lips of man, And this light touch of thee, than the kiss of Glory!” But I bade, “Go!” for his heart to the battle ran, “Go, lover and mate!” Glory shall know him not nor his memory save, (Peal, ye gay camp-bugles!) Gone like the marsh-bird's shadow over his sleep. The kiss that I gave him then was the last I gave, And the cruisers are strown and crumbling in many a deep. But they who at nightfall pierce and wax not dim, And clouds, the white-fire-spirited flood of forms, Who shine for ever, shall gather in dance for him, The daughters of light and the hearts full of noble storms. Hail, lover and mate! Let them that are weariless wander there into thee, (Sound on, on, rare bugles!) Let the white and exultant-spirited flood of forms, Let the veils of the lightning assemble and dance for thee, And the daughters of light and the mothers of noble storms. Dark powers in whose veins runs blood of the sunrise Arose for thee, so that thy proud ear was filled With the beat so great that who obeys it dies, And the chant so high that whoso sang was killed. Hail, my lover and mate! Song for the Funeral of a Boy Written in memory of the twelve-year-old son of Mr. Douglas Freshfield, the explorer. I On stems from silver woods Carry him, young companions, to the glen Where white Olympus broods. Flushes of rustlers shall precede you then By bush and glade Low-thrilling and afraid; And, as along its curve of shore ye pass, The dark tarn ruddied with the pine shall glass, Moving to hymns out of its lonely ken, The boy's light bier, with beaded rushes laid. II In beeches shall the fawn An hoof suspend, to learn from that clear sound His eager mate withdrawn For ever unto free and sylvan ground. Up in her hold The wide-wing'd Azure cold Mantling in gyre on gyre shall mark him come By paths root-paven borne, and great bee's hum Swing through your brief procession, winding round The endless alleys up that Mountain old. III In some low space of green Where fleecy mists, bright runnels newly rain'd And springing wands are seen, But nothing yet to gnarlèd eld attain'd, Let his head nigh The chrisom violet lie; And put at hand the sling to him most dear, The sheaf of arrows light, the dauntless spear The lute untroubled on the heart unstain'd; Then, taking hands around him, sing good-bye! IV Praise limbs that robb'd the cloud Of vengeful eagles, and for this rough nest, This egg, embraced the loud And everlasting sea-crag's salty breast! Praise to the face That smiled on nothing base! Hymn ye the laughter of his happy soul— His secret kindness to your secret dole; The heavenly-minded brook shall mourn him best When ye have kiss'd his cheek, leaving the place. V This ditty from the brake, This rainbow from the waters, fades; and Night That little pyre shall take In flame and cloud; but O! when the bloom of light With breathless glow Along the tops of snow Tells out to all the valleys Night is done,— Think of the boy, ye young companions bright, Not without joy; for he hath loved and gone As dews that on the uplands shine and go! Chant Sung in Darkness An early poem. I Though the fool—the old gainsayer— The passionate inveigher Whose passion is a prayer To one beyond his view, Said, “Is He dumb? Defy, then! Art thou indignant? Die, then, Bowed down and battle-writhen, But never stoop to sue!” Yet Man, although he grieveth And the pride of him upheaveth Still in that God believeth, Still in a goal whereto Those heaven-plunging horses Whose neck no rein enforces, Unspent as from the sources Of light and life they flew, Sweep the earth-chariot. (Never Shall the Charioteer's endeavour Govern them—Man for ever Must bide what they may do!) And though the breast maternal Of the stream of lights eternal Bears down a gorge nocturnal Our little raft and crew, And always wider, dimmer, The coasts recede and glimmer, And colder yet and grimmer Unfold to oceans new— Not here my wonder halteth To trust Whom it exalteth, Not here my soul defaulteth To pay its worship due; Yet, yet it mounteth fearing Voices of darkness, rearing Challenges persevering That nothing can subdue:— II “The evil and offenceless Thou smit'st, and both are senseless, Against thine eye defenceless The false man and the true; Our simplest, our sublimest, Our bravest and our primest, Are in thy hand who climbest The heavens without a clue; Crush these, the brazen-throated, But these, the self-devoted, The deep-loved and unnoted, Why dost Thou crush them too? Speak, Thou, who Earth evolvest And the globe of stars revolvest And the night of life dissolvest, Solve us this riddle too:— Why to our young committing The faults of the unwitting Dost Thou award as fitting Irreparable rue? Is not Thy justice deathless? Why let ten thousand faithless, Wise and unclean, go scatheless But not the faithful few? Thy face in cloud enswathing Why visit'st Thou with scathing The child, the beast our plaything And them that never knew?” III And God saith, If ye hear it, This weeping of the Spirit For the world which ye inherit, Do I not hear it too? Arise, and to your stations, Ye lighted living nations! These be my dark foundations— To raise them is for you. To a Dead Poet Lines written at request on the previous day, read at a public banquet in London to commemorate the birth of Edgar Allan Poe. I If the meteor mind, swift-ranger, Destroyer and all-changer, Must die on earth a stranger Leaving a trail Of brilliance frail, A portent and a danger, Hail, Death—thou kindly goader, Most subtle-cloak'd corroder, Whom Man, the blind foreboder, Who feels thee come With footfall dumb, Holds ever in malodour— Hail! friendly overthrower, Sifter of fames, foreknower, Before whom eyelids lower And droop away The gods of day; Death, thou art sight-bestower! For all men's fames, O sternest Deific priest, thou burnest On altars deeply furnaced. Aloft the peak All climbers seek Thou winnowest, thou discernest! And when thy embrace uncloaketh The false and true it yoketh, When slow libation smoketh, And all the host That wronged him most The singer's urn convoketh, How utterly remouldeth The flame that all enfoldeth! No more the arrainger scoldeth, One would have said Some God were dead; He worships who beholdeth. Then, then, the crowd bemoaneth As though such grief atoneth The beauty it dethroneth; It shrines the pen The mantle then, The man himself it stoneth! Night sinks unto the verges, Dull hate no longer urges, Foe beside foe emerges, The wild beasts slake At one fell lake The desert in their gurges. Now by the brain they blunted, Now by the heart they hunted, Now by the soul they stunted Even here to-night, In the banquet-light, The cowards are confronted! And at last the songs confuted Of this vagabond wild-luted, Celestial, persecuted, Mad mystagogue, Or drunken rogue, Are by the world saluted. Ah, wise and worldly legion! Unearthly pride took siege on The brow ye thrust prestige on; This star-lit pall Disdains us all And Earth's discordant region. II When I think of him, comes gliding A perfume strange, abiding, Of a flower I saw when riding One summer night In the Dolomite When stars did all the guiding. Earth shone an ice-cold planet With never an eye to scan it And no God's breath to man it, And below me fell Heights, sheer to hell, One gloomy wall of granite. Dismounted, I leaned over And the dim chasm did discover Far down, where eagles hover, On a footless place In the precipice-face Sky-coloured flowers, in clover. As I gazed down, fear-dissembling, Their moon-lit bells, assembling Azure virgins, resembling Exquisite dancers, Waved me up answers Out of that gulf of trembling. So 'mid inhuman splendour Chaotic, bleak, untender To all that skies engender In giddy air These poems rare Do flutter, wild and slender. III Therefore we hail him, wingèd poet undated, Backward-gazer, seer Chaldean belated, Hymning Terror and Chaos, as Earth in her vagrance Leaves long behind her in space wild tresses of fragrance,— Hymning all wonder, as momently grey Earth breaketh Still into spaces new, and new-eyed awaketh! He floats in the ivory boat he hath carven for pleasure, On, down a faery gorge, as one treads a measure, Bound for the paradise still where his heart hath treasure. Deep-wombed valleys delight him, ambrosial clouded, Clear streams wan with lilies and forestshrouded, Walled by autumnal mountains, all sunsetlustred, Streams that mirror the cypress, dark, cedarclustered. Down the mid-flood he bears through a vaporous Rhineland Borne in his plumèd shallop by pool and vineland (Strange and phantasmal country!) by towers enchanted Ablaze with his enemies' souls or by demons haunted. Broideries droop no longer from keep or casement, Ruins honeycombed with horror and foul abasement. Rats swim off in the water—dead shoulders welter— Cold on the bulwark, lo, a dead hand craves shelter. No, he must hasten past, this poet unfriended, He, too, is shelterless, cold, till this voyage be ended. Melodies dark he sings, low-toned, melancholy, He, too, has wrestled with Gods in his radiant folly, He, too, has felt the breath of passion too near him, Still the lost ecstasy clings, and lost arms ensphere him. O high houses crumbling down to the water, He seeks one lost and gone, the heaven's wise daughter! Named under many names, although none recalls her— Ligeia or Berenice, ah, what befalls her? Valleys and forests and cities that Time enchanteth, Have they not marked her passing for whom he panteth? “None hath gone by, O Genius serene and sombre! Whom dost thou still pursue, through waking and slumber?” “I seek one face alone on my soul's arrival At Hades' glimmering wharves, one divine survival!” “Lo! thy lost one is she, who in airs above thee Urges thy faery sail with the lips that love thee! She takes thy sore heart hence, and shall heal its bruises Far in the deathless country, the land of Muses. . . .” IV Glory unto thee, high Beauty, light in the drearness, Poised fragility, pure with the spirit's clearness! Strengths ungauged, unguessed, in thy petals shining, Blown from the deeps of God through the heart divining. Again and again for ever to Beauty returning Back must the eyes revert, and the ears be yearning, Panting we pause, for a sibylline whisper reigneth; By its perfection only the song enchaineth. Here at the tempest's core is that windless zone Of poise. . . . Here the wave of Beauty, spreading its tone Bell-like, the light Uranian, ringing unknown Wider than the wave æthereal, murmurs alone. . . . Fraternity LINES WRITTEN AT ASSOUAN ON THE NILE I In your amphitheatres of flood-worn rock, Granite escarpments that the desert rings Of quarries whence grey Egypt hewed her kings— Hail! stark beginnings that the fool can mock— Sun-obelisks half-hewn, prone architraves— Hail to you, every scarred and prostrate block! And hail to you, poor plot of English graves Ranked in the sun, a little martial flock! What sudden-quencht, impossible command Say, were you uttering to this drift of sand For England? Your command shall be fulfilled. A temple housing kingdoms doth she build Whose beams are ye, and whose foundations wide The bones of sons; and you therein shall bide! II There shall be lifted from the Earth at last One Temple, O my soul, consummate, fair, Whiter than lightning, rock-set, and so vast That the hopes even of the young may enter there! Round shall it be as that horizon old About its steeps and clear dominions seen, And girt with columns in the antique mould, And doors, one for each nation, stand between Statues heroic—doors, yea, numberless And open. Yellow hands and black and white Shall cast them—so that every race may press Up always to that altar never cold! III There shall be none cast out—nor any fears Fraternal. Unknown music shall aspire About that altar, nor shall human tears Quench the high flame, or still the trembling choir Of man ascendant. Chiefest symbol there, Whereon the eyes of all the host shall wait, The wingèd chalice of the holy sun Lifted above the dome from gate to gate. Its only priesthood thoughts, that range on high In the soft and changeful vestures of the sky; And the slow-built, straggling village of this ball Thither shall mount to worship One, the All; And every soul find there, ere it depart, That thing which fills the craving of its heart. 1888. Adam Outside the Gate “Be not afraid: it was some wise Dæmon amid that glade of Fate Tore off the bandage from our eyes And stamped us mate and mate. I am all yours. I kneel, I burn— Feel every naked rushing nerve And tendril of my being yearn For you; for you I starve! I am all yours. What creature else Exists but you? Passion divine, Pursued through half-a-thousand hells, I make, I keep you mine! Endless you yield what else none gives, That torturing, acutest bliss That quenches self-hood while it lives Enheavened in your kiss. So as the eagle on his ledge Ponders and broods above his prey Eternal terrors in me rage Lest some one take away; Lest I be not the universe For you (as you, my mate, for me) Of every sense—all that confers This fearful ecstasy. None other living shall feel thus The blaze consummate light the breast, For like Death I am covetous Of this too perfect zest; None shall share what possesses us Nor what I have possessed!” Since I have given Thee all my very Heart Since I have given thee all my very heart, Since I have staked so deep and dangerously All that I have of hope till breath depart, And flung my little kingdom on a die; Since now there streams over my land and sea This dread Love—strange as light—beyond recall, I am thy prisoner; yes, and thou art free With but a touch to lay in ruin all. Far off, may be, the Heart's Eyes shall Behold You Far off, may be, the heart's eyes shall behold you. A year ago it would have groan'd unseen, “O could I once attain to you and hold you The world might perish then!” But now I cry to you (as ghost to ghost), “All the world's harvest is not crush'd to this: ‘That you love not.’ Apart! Each to his post! No sob—no sigh—no kiss!” I would not be your master; nor with chiding Embitter our deep music as it fades. In the throng'd forest one can hear no griding Save when tree, tree invades. The error old, that error infinite Even at this hour shall not be made by me! I will not take my passion for my right. Be free, be free, be free! The Questioners I A man made a journey once over half the world To come at the journey's end to no more than this: The cottage where he and another had long been happy; But lilac-bushes had closed right over the path, And the stones of the place, it seemed, had become alive. II Threshold, familiar Threshold, may I not pass? Not till thou tell me my name! Stone of wonder, on thee were the wedding flowers When I bore in to my hearth a silken-haired stranger— Strange unto me was her heart, strange to her mine, And soft and doubtful she trembled, like the blue eve. . . . Pass on, pass on! III Naked and sounding Stair, may I not pass? Tell me my name! Stair of meeting, where nightly I called the call Of the exultant, the earth-engirdling, the nightingale, And she from the stairhead, infinite-eyed and slow, Came down in her gliding brightness into my soul. . . . Pass on, pass on! IV Window, O far-seen Window, may I not pass? Tell me my name! Window of parting,—here would my proud one stand Arrayed in dreams and roses, —here, if by chance Any that she loved much, in going looked not back, Stooped she to mingle sighs and tears with the rose. . . . Pass on, pass on! V Chest, O thou oaken Chest, may I not pass? Tell me my name! Coffer of vision, with bloom upon far mountains, With rays upon ocean isles when their thunders were still, With these did she weave her dresses, simple and secret, Fragrant and here compacted, sealed even from me. . . . Pass on, pass on! VI Table, ah! merry Table, may I not pass? Tell me my name! Table of honour, here in the vast evening On the head of that pale companion, that more than friend, A man I remember inflicted his lordly anger In words that return, return, return to him now. Pass on, pass on! VII Cradle, O Cradle, wilt thou not let me pass! Tell me my name! Other children she bare, but this, the beloved one, This was taken from her, this that most needed care, And the eyes of her turned from earth, and she rose and followed it At dawn, when the birds and the young children sing. . . . Pass on, pass on! VIII Bed, thou snow-silent Bed, may I not pass? Tell me my name! Ask him not, terrible image, ask not, for she The woman by whom he lay down to whisper “Forgive!” Sings here no more, but only in thoughts of friends— Sleeps here no more, but heaven'd in the souls of children. . . . Pass on, pass on! The Requital “What shall I give you, woman dear? Kiss for your eyes, pearl for your ear, Praise to requite you, Toils to delight you, Or trophies that shall leave your name Canopied by outlasting fame?” Ah no! much less! Give me, O give me faithfulness! “Kindness I'll give—with sovran care Harbour you like some temple fair, With care that shields Your way through fields Flower-soft, and makes the wise of ages Only your ministers and mages . . .” Nay, would you bless, Give me, O give me faithfulness! “Take this instead—this throbbing rose, Passion, whose cloudy cups disclose, Core within core, Sea-and-moon-lore, The breath of lovers, whose exchange Of being and worship still is strange . . .” Fair it is, yes . . . But give, O give me faithfulness! 'Tis true, you came with silvery zone All the world's dayspring in your own; True that you gave All he could crave; True, on your bosom warm and pure His children smile in sleep secure; But no! Ask less— He will not give you faithfulness. To a Nightingale heard upon a Hilltop before Dawn The “traveller” mentioned is Colonel Younghusband. The “clansmen” on the heights under the mountain range Elburz (or Elbrûs) are the Kysty tribe of the Tchen Tchen. Yes, Nightingale, I lie awake And wondering hear thee sing Over the deep world from thy brake While every other thing Sleepeth—the deep world like a lake Stirred round thee, ring on ring! More than the chanters of the light Thy passion men confounds Because like ours 'tis born in sight Of that which hath no bounds: How the dark-streaming infinite Wells in those golden sounds! Some traveller once in Himalay Chanced on a tribe so lone, So dungeoned from the world away, They deemed it all their own. And any human race but they Incredible, unknown. But up, up where the snowy crest Of Elburz mounts the blue And Caucasus sinks east and west Precipitous, some few Clansmen are found, high on its breast Where half the earth's in view; And these by that great prospect thrilled Perhaps, in joy or fear, Poor hunters wild and rudely skilled, Have raised an altar there “To the God Unknown”; and this they build Of horns of goat and deer. Their humble, dark, and lofty song Where shining gulfs expand Beyond the Caspian—Death, Time, Wrong That few can understand— Is launched, and low and clear and strong Floats out to all the land! In Summer when the Vales are clear In summer when the Vales are clear And lowland hedges toss their flowery lights, How oft the great Alps disappear And mists invade your foreheads, O ye sovran heights! But when midwinter's bitterest power Must be endured, and the chill rose is done And little farms in valleys cower, Ye, everlasting summits, do abide in sun! The Horn of the Moon “Iroofed my roof-tree at the wane of the moon That nothing might warp it or burn it, And wished a deep wish at the new of the moon And sealed it where no man should learn it. We stood by the oak at the full of the moon Where all the far country was clearest, The bird of the forest kept singing a tune— The word I would say to my dearest. She branded my heart at the new of the moon And the hurt grew a harm beyond measure, And I sent her soft gallant, that begged for a boon, A blade that was red, for his pleasure. Bright my love's tresses at full o' the moon, Nothing in beauty shone rarer, Sleeping her fill in the face of the moon— Never a footfall to scare her! But these hands that slew her at rise of the moon Did mix him with night everlasting . . . The bird of the forest keeps singing abune That mine is a care there's no casting. Hang my powder-horn on the horn o' the moon! The deer of the bracken may flout me, The hunt shall be up at the pale of the moon And the lordings go hunting without me!” Mounting the Hill Mounting the hill I found it long Until I met a merry song That kissed mine eyes to blind me; It mocked at me and turned and fled But played on, fluttering overhead, Till I forgot I went footsore And the dusty road that rose before Was the blue hill far behind me! The Shepherd In this poem the author owes a line and a half to Hale White (“Mark Rutherford”). I When I am worn amid the burning dust Of high wall'd cities, round the milltrack drear Bearing the beam and yoke, as mortals must Who by their lower selves win lodging here, Oft, as among some ancient desert horde Their King flung up the netted bird on high Whose flight should show the nearest pass whereby To cross the mountains from the sands abhorred, Even so cut I the cord, Dismiss my soul on its delirious wings Spurning the dull den where the body dwells In yon green cabinets of grass to stray, Along the liquid mirrors to delay, Yonder, in the wishèd land of wells, By the throbbing of full waters, gleamy springs! II Distilled out of the swift enormous skies But nursed in darkness old, inscrutable, 'Twixt Sinodun and its twin mount Harphill By Thames I know a Wood-Spring takes its rise, Azured and overbough'd, a margin still Untainted, only known to beasts and birds, And alive, like all things wholly beautiful, Exquisite, deathless, seeming self-engendered. Sand-pulses, bubbles, are its only words; How wide the region of the mountainous earth Cistern'd for the making of that little pool! And there what spirit-freshness comes to birth! Thither I voyage, to a dream surrendered, And rays are golden there, and noon is cool. III Or I, a Shepherd, am in Thessaly; And the twilight village cries, “Hath he not come On the last scented load of myrtle home?”. . . He sits in the great valley green and still Blocked by the snow-capt Mountain, and his sheep, Tawny and dark, roam far and crop their fill In the wide pastures, by the river deep; His wandering fingers teach the stops at will Melodies cool as water, soft as sleep. IV And once to him the Mountain spake, “Climb! Here canst larger music make! I know thy heart, and all its ache! For, since thy craving is and ban Conquest of earth to plan, And to come up as if by right All the kingdoms of earth to scan With the soul and the sight of a seraph, The strength of a man, Therefore, lest it should break, Thy heart for my arch-lute I take; My tarns and ghylls shall sing through thee All Olympus and all Thessaly!” V And lo, on a peak above the peaks am I! Above the waves of forest, vale and fell, Above the torrent's voice, the clink of bell, The flock, the scythe, of sparse humanity; Above the earth-enflamèd ring of sky That hems our footing; so I stand alone Isled in the last and dreadful light on high And sovran silence of the air and stone . . . Slowly the plains, those warm and breathing plains, The hearth-lit villages that sleep and play, Whose ceaseless blood and its in-dwelling pains In volumes of sea-darkness surge and sway In the heart most solitary, sink away. . . . Nothing but starred immensity remains. Chilly withdrawals yours, vast Light, vast Love! Though the skies swarm with tremblers faintly bright We are exiles in this glimmering infinite; For centuries Man may see but stars above! Yet shall those summits of scarred ages burn Afresh, and all those lights be quenched in One! Pure new breath shall arouse Our sunk horizons and our sapless boughs! The wrinkled Æons brood on that return, And seal'd in's prison-house The changeless blood keeps memory of the Sun. VI And so when Night hath rolled away undone, Joyful my foot is bounding down the peak; Rich-memoried, I am eager for the yoke, Like some young torrent swollen white with rains How willing then my strength rejoins the plains! “Where is our Shepherd?” cry the villagefolk. . . . He sits in the great valley green and still Block'd by the snow-capt Mountain, and his sheep, Tawny and dark, roam far and crop their fill In the wide pastures, by the river deep; His wandering fingers teach the stops at will Melodies cool as water, soft as sleep. O Dreamy, Gloomy, Friendly Trees Odreamy, gloomy, friendly Trees, I came along your narrow track To bring my gifts unto your knees, And gifts did you give back; For when I brought this heart that burns— These thoughts that bitterly repine— And laid them here among the ferns And the hum of boughs divine, Ye, vastest breathers of the air, Shook down with slow and mighty poise Your coolness on the human care, Your wonder on its toys, Your greenness on the heart's despair, Your darkness on its noise. Lindisfarne Our Seer, the net-mender, The day that he died Looked out to the seaward At ebb of the tide. Gulls drove like the snow Over bight, over barn, As he sang to the ebb On the rock Lindisfarne: “Hail, thou blue ebbing! The breakers are gone From the stormy coast-islet Bethundered and lone! Hail, thou wide shrinking Of foam and of bubble— The reefs are laid bare And far off is the trouble! For through this withdrawal As soft as a smile, The isle of the flood Is no longer an isle. . . . “By the silvery isthmus Of the sands that uncover, Now feet as of angels Come delicate over— The fluttering children Flee happily over! To the beach of the mainland Return is now clear, The old travel thither Dry-shod, without fear. . . . “At last, at the wane, When foundations expand, Doth the isle of my soul, Lindisfarne, understand She stretcheth to vastness Made one with the land!” The Shell I am a shell out of the Asian sea, But my sad Pearl is gone, Risen to be Goddess—Venus green is she— And I cast up alone. Yet some night shall her brilliance stoop and take Unto her ear this shell, And hear the whisper of her own heart-break . . . All that I serve to tell! Old Anchor Chanty First Voice With a long heavy heave, my very famous men. . . . (Chorus. Bring home! heave and rally!) Second Voice And why do you, lad, look so pale? Is it for love, or lack of ale? First Voice All hands bear a hand that have a hand to len'— And there never was a better haul than you gave then . . . (Chorus. Bring home!) First Voice Heave hearty, my very famous men . . . (Bring home! heave and rally!) Second Voice Curl and scud, rack and squall—sea-clouds you shall know them all . . . First Voice For we're bound for Valparaiso and round the Horn again From Monte Desolado to the parish of Big Ben! . . . (Bring home!) First Voice Heave hearty, my very famous men . . . (Bring home! heave and rally!) Second Voice Bold through all or scuppers under, when shall we be back, I wonder? First Voice From the green and chancy water we shall all come back again To the Lizard and the ladies—but who can say for when? . . . (Bring home!) First Voice Heave and she's a-trip, my very famous men . . . (Bring home! heave and rally!) Second Voice When your fair lass says farewell to you a fair wind I will sell to you . . . First Voice You may sell your soul's salvation, but I'll bet you two-pound-ten She's a-tripping on the ribs of the devil in his den. . . . (Bring home!) First Voice Heave and she's a-peak, my very famous men . . . (Bring home! heave and rally!) Second Voice You shall tread, for one cruzado, Fiddler's Green in El Dorado . . . First Voice Why, I've seen less lucky fellows pay for liquor with doubloons And for 'baccy with ozellas, gold mohurs, and ducatoons! . . . (Bring home!) First Voice Heave and a-weigh, my very famous men . . . (Bring home! heave and rally!) Second Voice And drop her next in heat or cold, the flukes of England they shall hold! . . . First Voice Ring and shank, stock and fluke, she's coming into ken— Give a long and heavy heave, she's a-coming into ken. . . . (Bring home!) First Voice Heave and in sight, my very famous men . . . (Bring home! heave and rally!) Second Voice With her shells and tangle dripping she's a beauty we are shipping . . . First Voice And she likes a bed in harbour like a decent citizen, But her fancy for a hammock on the deep sea comes again. . . . (Bring home!) First Voice Heave and she's a-wash, my very famous men . . . (Bring home! heave and rally!) Second Voice O never stop to write the news that we are off upon a cruise . . . First Voice For the Gulf of Californy's got a roller now and then, But it's better to be sailing than a-sucking of a pen. . . . (Bring home!) Chorus at the Green Bear Inn Traveller “Ruddy old Shepherd, blithe of cheer,” Chorus (Here's to the leg that's lusty!) Traveller “When comes to you the pick of the year?” Chorus (Mark what he says . . . he's trusty!) Shepherd “When I watch yon Fire in the chimney roar . . .” Chorus (What in the embers dreamt he?) Shepherd “And sparks flee up from the embers' core . . .” Chorus (Fill up his can—it's empty!) Shepherd “While out on the moorland gale I hear . . .” Chorus (Here's to the woes we bury!) Shepherd “Some Fiddle, ranting and rovering near! . . .” Chorus (Hail to that fiddler merry!) Shepherd “Yon Fire, so great and so quick with glee . . .” Chorus (Here's to the world so stormy!) Shepherd “Is Love, the breath o' the world, you see . . .” Chorus (Here's to the mother that bore me!) Shepherd “And . . . hark to the Fiddle! . . . That's Hope! Play on . . .” Chorus (Fiddle, we send a chorus!) Shepherd “Idling and wheedling, and come and gone! . . .” Chorus (Long may it march before us!) Daughters of Joy I Long, subtle-floating, the choir Of strings—soft floods of tone— In pleading dance-measure, invades Cloud-like the pavement, where, With the night wind's vast lament in mine ears, I am walking alone. II You, from the dance yonder? In tears, at this street-corner? “I am going home, my friend. (Strange, that you knew me!) Dances are not for the sore heart, nor lights for the scorner.” III How came you to live so, sister! “Jealous was he I cared for— False, but jealous—he died— Flung himself into the river; And then a child . . . no matter! What should the child be spared for? IV “What mattered? What matters in London But the play of the iron mill? It is full of women who smile, And heroes live upon them. There, if a love rise in your heart, 'tis that that you must kill. V “Smile under the lamp glare! To laugh cracks your painting— There's no place to weep in there Or bow the head in silence: Under an archway the clever children mock at a woman fainting. VI “Sick, hie to the almshouse— Lie in your shroud, thinking! Soiled before you have loved, When you have loved, betrayed; And is there, once betrayed, a better end than drinking? VII “O wiser ones will save— And then there may be marriage; After precipitous years Settling down (with your past Always to take the opposite seat) in a well-padded carriage!” VIII Through Asia sweeps that voice, Through Christendom and Jewry. Look up at the tavern-door— See! A phantom peering in, The smile of a daughter of joy on the drawn face of a fury. IX Down the dark ancient vale Whirling like leaves, O Daughters Of Joy, gash'd priestesses, Night-bound, hectic, marred, Ye that were lovely once as clouds mirrored in waters, X To what dominion dire Flag your fierce wings, till they Glide through the dense realms lit Only by eyes of prey? Whither, sister-spirits beautiful, sink ye away? XI “Back to the Past we sink, Whence the human would be soaring, To deep-pent Chaos back— Hold out no hand to us— Rushing disharmonies, lost, past deploring! XII “Our blazing rout shall coil Unnumbered down for ever, Our foul shall breed the foul, The heavenly heights be far, While man knows not of love, and cannot curb his fever.” The Gemless Ring Ah, hoop of gold that binds the maid Within thy faery circuit strayed! No gem of murdered blood divine, No dragon green of jasper's thine, No piping shepherd-boy and flock Drowsed on the Ethiopian rock And sovran 'gainst the Bacchic mist Sleeps in thee, shut in amethyst; Nor Isis in chalcedony Protecteth, floating fadelessly. Why hast no serpent-wreathen wand Bescored on thee by diamond? No Wingèd Foot, departure's mark, Treading out Life in garnet dark, Or signed in gloomy emerald Where stands Serapis pedestal'd 'Mid sceptred Æons plumed and starred? No name they write on Indian sard Nor dreaded word from Dian's zone Legends thee, seal without a stone! Yet, seeing no mage since time began Hath found a greater talisman, Since puissant was thy gleaming pure Both to preserve and to allure, Destroyers of this amulet May look back, and lament thee yet! Thou hast outweathered many an age Hid in the missal's burning page; Queens unto Christ in pilgrim guise Tossed thee, with prayer for paradise, And felt thee rained from Zion's gate Back to the cold hand laid in state! Over the fiord of spirits gone I hear great harpers harp thee on! . . . But who shall now thy bond endure? Farewell! thou art too plain and pure! Chinese Drinking Song The old Bards leapt into the fiery Mountain, And your wizard Herb-seller was caught away— The old Seers drank at the Immortal Fountain And took their flight. But where are such to-day? Life like a violet flash of lightning blinds us, And before our eyes recover is gone past, The Earth and Sky grow giddy, Winter finds us— Our childish faces wrinkled—far too fast. Come, friend, whose shaky fist is on the wine here, Why hesitate to drink? For whom do you wait? What dancing-girls do you expect to dine here, Or halt their chariot-wheels before our gate? O Birds of the Air Obirds of the air— Wild birds, buoyant, vagabond, light— Streams may have taught you a stave; But how are ye born so sure of your flight Hence over worlds of the wave? Whose mind remembers in yours as it weaves Subtlest of houses to sway with the leaves? We have forgotten the land out of sight— We build no house but the grave! Almond, Wild Almond Almond, wild almond, Give counsel to me, And hush thy fierce lover The wind in the tree! Along the night pasture I've come through the dew To tell thee, wild almond, The old songs are true! Like the flower on thy branches The heart in me springs With airs and upliftings And hundreds of wings! I, too, have a lover . . . Keep, keep it from them— The wise ones that eye me— Thou whispering stem! I deal with him coldly— I dash him with pride: Yet he comes of evenings, And stands at my side. O had he entreated I could have said nay, But he, he says nothing, And then goes away! Ah, loves he for ever? . . . And loves me alone? . . . These things that men say not How can they be known? He may, but he may not— And I would be free:— Now play not, now sway not, Thou little black tree, Almond, wild almond, Give counsel to me! In Summer-time when Mary bathes In summer-time when Mary bathes And floats along as in a sky, O might I be the stream that swathes Her beauty with infinity! O might I be that stealing song The brown bird sings her from above While in the dark wood, late and long, She listens, and forgets to love! Or else the rose, the rose that bends To Mary, all its soul to give, And on her dreamy bosom spends The only day it has to live! Byron Byron, what clash in thee of sea and wind, Wrecking and squandering all we treasure most, What riches of ungovernable mind Washed up along some bleak despairing coast! Rare liquor doth besiege the furious capes, The iron steeps are splashed with blood of grapes, All the perfumed cargo of thy heady wine Flung to inhabitants of rocks and fogs To grope for, and get drunk out of their clogs While fades the chaos-tingeing fiery juice divine. . . . In the Roman Amphitheatre, Verona AFTER SUPPER AT CAN GRANDE'S Two architects of Italy—austere Men who could fashion nothing small—refused To die with life; and for their purpose used This dim, this topless Amphitheatre. Caesar, trenching an orbit of ellipse, Shaped of sun-temple blocks cyclopean His marbled crater, whence the world would scan, From tier on roaring tier, fighters and ships. I, Dante, having raised, as dreamer can, Like moon-pale Alps those walls immutable, Sole in the night-arena, grow aware I am myself the thing spectacular Seized by the ever-thirsting gaze of Hell, Here, on the voiceless sand, a banish'd man. Shakespeare If many a daring spirit must discover The chartless world, why should they glory lack? Because athwart the skyline they sank over, Few, few, the shipmen be that have come back. Yet one, wrecked oft, hath by a giddy cord The rugged head of Destiny regain'd— Who from the maelstrom's lap hath swum aboard— Who from the polar sleep himself unchain'd. And he, acquainted well with every tone Of madness whining in his shroudage slender, From storm and mutiny emerged alone, Self-righted from the dreadful self-surrender: Rich from the isles where sojourn long is death, Won back to cool Thames and Elizabeth, Sea-weary, yes, but human still, and whole— A circumnavigator of the soul. There comes a Moment of the Twilight There comes a moment of the twilight, The red-forged Orb at his vastest Sinking (how swiftly!) behind black-ridged Intricate harbourage of trees, When brilliant beds of flowers, amid the dimness Of warm lawns silently resplendent, Armies of sapphires and of purples, Flame-cups of red gold, quietude Of dusky companies of lilies, Burn with a light not theirs. They utter, they give off a singing vapour, Discompose into rumour as of voices, A troubled ground-swell, every chalice Steamy with a yearning murmur After the descended sun! Something of the late huge riot Of cloud-light, to them bequeathèd, Dwells on, confused, in them, Thousand by thousand awaiting, Frail-hung lanterns of some gala Invisible. Even so are ye, All standing now at such a moment Smoulderers objectless, uncertain, Artists and priests of all religions, Shapers of clay, sound, colour, Shapers of perfection and of symbol, Shapers of passion and of awe! Hath it gone, last hem of all that glory For which we came to be? 1900. Schiehallion Far the grey loch runs Up to Schiehallion. Lap, lap the water flows Where my wee boatie rows, Greenly a star shows Over Schiehallion. She that I wander'd with Over Schiehallion,— How far beyond your ken, Crags of the merry glen, Stray'd she, that wander'd then Down from Schiehallion! Sail of the wild swan Turn to Schiehallion! Here where the rushes rise Low the black hunter lies; Beat thou the pure skies Back to Schiehallion! Jean Richepin's Song The idea of this little song comes through the French from the Finnish. I Apoor lad once and a lad so trim, (Fol de rol de raly O! Fol de rol!) A poor lad once and a lad so trim Gave his love to her that loved not him. II And, says she, “Fetch me to-night, you rogue,” (For de rol de raly O! Fol de rol!) And, says she, “Fetch me to-night, you rogue, Your mother's heart to feed my dog!” III To his mother's house went that young man, (Fol de rol de raly O! Fol de rol!) To his mother's house went that young man, Killed her, and took the heart, and ran. IV And as he was running, look you, he fell, (Fol de rol de raly O! Fol de rol!) And as he was running, look you, he fell, And the heart rolled on the ground as well. V And the lad, as the heart was a-rolling, heard, (Fol de rol de raly O! Fol de rol!) And the lad, as the heart was a-rolling, heard That the heart was speaking, and this was the word— VI The heart was a-weeping and crying so small, (Fol de rol de raly O! Fol de rol!) The heart was a-weeping and crying so small, “Are you hurt, my child, are you hurt at all?” Maurya's Song Rushes that grow by the black water When will I see you more? Land of the green, green shore! When will the field and the small cabin See us more In the old country? What is to me all the gold yonder? She that bore me is gone. Knees that dandled and hands that blessed me Colder than any stone. Stranger to me than the face of strangers Are my own In the old country! Vein o' my heart, from the lone mountain The smoke of the turf will die, And the stream that sang to the young childer Run down alone from the sky: On the door-stone, grass,—and the cloud lying Where they lie In the old country! Killary I When all her brothers in the house Were lying asleep, my love Ran before me under the bend of boughs Till we looked down from above On the long loch, On the brown loch, On the lone loch of Killary! II Together we ran down the copse And stood in the rain as close As the birds that sleep in the soft tops Of the tree that comes and goes When the morn moon, When the young moon, When the morn moon is on Killary! III In tremblings of the water chill Swans we saw preen their coat, Biting their plumes with stoop'd bill And quivering neck, afloat On the brown shade, On the deep shade, The shade of hills on Killary. IV “Why pale, my belovèd, now When the first light 'gins to beat? No sun of autumn is rich as thou, And honey after thy feet Shall rise from the grass, From the wet of the grass, The brow of the grass over Killary!” V “My grief it is only that thou and I Must part, like swans of the flood That rise up sorrowful into the sky; For one goes over the wood, And one oversea, And one oversea, And one oversea from Killary! . . . VI “Ah, the little raindrops that hang on the bough, Together they may run, But never again shall I and thou Meet here in the morning sun. . . . We shall meet no more, We must kiss no more, We shall meet no more by Killary!” Connemara. You were Stay'd You were stay'd in heart on heaven, I by none but you forgiven,— You unto your Light are taken, I of all, in you, forsaken. Where the night is never broken, Where for long no speech hath spoken, There the ears no longer hearken, There the eyeballs wane and darken. Yet at hours my soul, so bounded By that gloom like blood surrounded— Sees an ancient daylight burning— Hears departed feet returning. Musing on a Great Soldier Fear? Yes . . . I heard you saying In an Oxford common-room Where the hearth-light's kindly raying Stript the empanelled walls of gloom, Silver groves of candles playing In the soft wine turned to bloom— At the word I see you now Blandly push the wine-boat's prow Round the mirror of that scored Yellow old mahogany board— I confess to one fear; this, To be buried alive! My Lord, Your fancy has played amiss. Fear not. When in farewell, While guns toll like a bell And the bell tolls like a gun, Westminster towers call Folk and state to your funeral, And, robed in honours won, Beneath the cloudy pall Of the lifted shreds of glory You lie in the last stall Of that grey dormitory— Fear not lest mad mischance Should find you lapt and shrouded Alive in helpless trance Through seeming death-beclouded: For long ere so you rest On that transcendent bier Shall we not have addressed One summons, one last test, To your reluctant ear? O believe it! we shall have uttered In ultimate entreaty A name your soul would hear Howsoever thickly shuttered; We shall have stooped and muttered England! in your cold ear . . . Then, if your great pulse leap No more, nor your cheek burn, Enough; then shall we learn 'Tis time for us to weep. Inscription for the Scabbard of a Sword of Honour Engraved on Havelock's sword, presented to Field-Marshal Sir George White, V.C. Draw me not! Let your laurels round me wreathe— You that have kept, since you began to breathe, The soul within you ready to unsheathe! I Seek Thee in the Heart alone Fountain of Fire whom all divide, We haste asunder like the spray, But waneless doth Thy flame abide Whom every torch can take away! I seek Thee in the heart alone, I shall not find in hill or plain; Our rushing star must keep its moan, Our nightly soul its homeward pain. Song beyond thought, Light beyond power, Even the consumings of this breast Advance the clearness of that hour When all shall poise, and be at rest. It cracks at last—the glowing sheath, The illusion, Personality— Absorbed and interwound with death The myriads are dissolved in Thee. The Rider on the Shore As on the Iberian shore wanders some priest of Atlantis, Son of a vanished race, seek I my own land here. Ranging to and fro, ranging between the cliffs and the surges, Carry me whither thou wilt, my galloping beast! But no, Rocks are at either end, no gate, no gate to the landward; Gates to the seaward have sunken, what thousands of years ago! Where, O horse, shall we find the love and the lands that sink not? How bear this lamp and spear to the foot of the wingèd sun? “Ride we, master, the reinless foams of the travelling wave! Ride thou the fierce gulfs and torn streams of the sea! “And as a veil over Earth shall be drawn her absolving waters, By the passage of thy hooves shall the new lands be reborn!” Fantasia on Claviers at Night To Arnold Dolmetsch. Iwatch'd a withered Figure at the keys Pause, with a smile, in the great galleries, And heard his tender fingers, as he went, Muse on the heart of each blind instrument. SPINET “Shoaling through twilight to my silver tinglings The great-ruff'd ladies beset with pearl Come out with the gallants in gems of Cadiz, In lofty capriols, with loud spur-jinglings, In Roman galliard and in blithe coranto Learnt in far Otranto Brought home in the galleys of the Earl— Storm-riding galleys of the haughty Earl— To English valleys. They come With reverences stately at meeting, In mockeries sedately retreating, And stomachers and buckles and rings Shake a maze of jewels to the measured strings, Of trembling jewels. Ay, moonlight's fair in yew-clipt alleys, And young Love fledges His shafts 'twixt cypress hedges. Follow the rout, and watch in gentle wind The springing moonbeam of the fountain sway'd Like to a mountain maid Who turns with poisèd jar From bubbling hollow cool. ‘Behold, how't tosses rain of star-drops hither Into main blackness of the pool— Rings ever shimmering out and sheen reborn; So, thou and I, lady, must die, To wake, as echoes wake, of yonder horn With volcelest over the hills of morn. Ah, satin-quilted kirtle, Ah, pearlèd bosom, Let slip one flake of blossom, Deign but a sprig of myrtle, To the poor Fool, panting on his bended knee!’ But silent grow the long swards cedar-shaded Where the young loves were sitting; And lo, in the silver-candled hall The bat is flitting, flitting, The tapestries are dusk upon the wall, And the ladies bright, brocaded, All, with their blushes, faded!” HARPSICHORD “Now ye, the delicate patterers of the hush, Birds, hither! Scarce-rustlers of the sere involvèd leaf Who mourn for summers past with elfin grief, Ye who can hear along the inmost lawn Ebbings and flowings shrill When subtle ballads net the rime-cold daffodil And drift over the blue turf so nigh dumb They startle not from's gloom e'en the airy fawn. Old Antony on his Nile-barge at dawn Caught your deck-walkings, countless overhead, And eased with ye a heart eclipsed and dead. Come swift, come soon, Drift, like a veil over the moon, And rising round this crumbling Keep Shed ye, upon the sleepless, sleep!” CLAVICHORD “‘Wherefore, poor Fool, dost lie— Love, cap and bells put by— On thy pallet-bed so stark?’ ‘I am girt, soul and limb, 'Gainst horror dim. Ear tense to hark Mine eyeballs strain and swim Drowning in foamy dark. Comes no shock Nor earthly foot But the heart's blood, ebb'd with the chill tower-clock To a single beat, Clots to a fear That God may appear— None other eye being near— And bare of His mantle of law Stand, a giant Spirit beautiful, Sombre, pale, in avenging mail, Wings folded, on this planet's skull; And before Him dropping like fine rain, A veil o' the cloud o' the dust of kings Noiseless descending the old Abyss. . . . Ah then, after this How gentle through the dark paths of the brain Comes the faint noise of outer things; The whirr and shower of wings— Satin shufflings of ivy leaves Ranging like bees the leaden pane— Jolting of carters, cries of falconers— The blessed courtyard stirs That do in mercy say Thou hast another day!’” The Man Digging The isle was barren. Far as hawk may scan Slabb'd ledges heaved up to a headland bare Save for one narrow patch, by ceaseless care Sumptuous with corn. Against the sky a Man Digging the waste I saw, —bow'd veteran A stubborn spade he drave in stubborn ground And root and rock flung sheer without a sound Over the bleak edge. . . . Then anew began. “You, who have lodged in the teeth of the abyss Your cabin low, and triumph rich as this Wrung from the ocean-bitter mountain-side, What help'd you most to bring such treasure out?” He stood, and after scrutiny replied, “The thing on which I lean, the spade of doubt.” The Bloom Who are these ancients, gnarl'd and moss'd and weigh'd This way and that, under the sluggard blue And shine of morning—these whose arms are laid Low to the grasses and the sheets of dew— These bowers ruggèd within and thickly knit, But feather'd over with a roseate white So frail that the breeze's touch dismantles it And brings from cradled nurseries in flight— Snow-soft—the petals down In shadows green to drown? We are the matrons. Bent are we and riven Under such years of ripeness manifold, But unto us a special grace is given— To wear a virgin's beauty being old. Noiseless we wear it; round us in the croft These whisperers are leaves of other trees, Babblers that have not learn'd by fruitage oft To shade the heart with wide serenities On tendons knit to bear Sweetness in stormy air. Holmwood. A Winter Song TO ALICE MEYNELL Lady, through grasses stiff with rime And wraith-hung trees I wander Where the red sun at pitch of prime Half of his might must squander. Narrow the track As I look back On traces green behind me— I go alone To think upon A face, where none Shall find me. Birds peal; but each grim grove its shroud Retains, as to betoken Though the young lawn should wave off cloud These would have Night unbroken— Desire no plash Of the Lake awash— No gold but gold that's glinted In still device From the breast of ice Whose summer cries Have stinted. But in a great and glittering space The black Elm doth restore me To you. Empower'd with patient grace Musing she stands before me; Her webs divine Ghosted with fine Remembrance few can capture; Her very shade On greenness laid Is white,—is made Of rapture! Fragment An early poem. Isleep. The panoply of sense, The buffetings, the din, The breasts of love, the battle dense, The roaring drive I know not whence, The riot curbed within, Cease, and in dreamless innocence The Self forgets its sin; Forgets, unloosing like a robe, The body and its grief, Till at the Dawn over the globe (That soft and silver thief!) It wakes; nor ever eye can probe Where it has found relief. I die. The treasure-ships I sought, The glories and the glee, The lives wherewith my own was wrought (As in some tapestry gem-fraught) Nearly and tenderly, And the tune mine ear had almost caught, All sink away from me. Dreamless the aeons interpose. The gap, perchance, is long. Will the Self wake to strains it knows? Will the vast star-lit throng Take up, renewed by deep repose, The full theme of the song? The Nutter I I am the Autumn. Rising from the throne I watch the pageant of my courtiers pass; Chestnuts' canary-feather'd beauty strown— The lime's gold tribute at his foot amass— Fragile jewels from larches blown Enrich with disarray the trembling grass, Until the beggar'd elms, too proud to bend, Emblaze a hundred winds with my rash kingdom's end. II But look! within the beech's burning house Some Nutter, deaf to shouts of fellow-thieves, Hath flung him with his crook to dream and drowse Flush-cheek'd alone, upon the mounded leaves. The squirrel headlong from his eaves Creeps curious down: then drops with sudden souse; The still-come culvers burst away; and flits The beechmast-feasting multitude of shadowy tits. III Where are thy friends? Gone on to sack the glades, My rooms of tatter'd state, not to return. No moth-bright brambles and no rainy braids Of ivy, 'mid the sheen and smoke of fern, Could trammel-up for long their raids. Up, boy! pursue them down the misty burn! But on his bosom tann'd, in slumber fast, Patters the mimic shower of ever-dropping mast. IV What, lads? The last of my poor banquet lose To thy wild kin of air? For them the dell O'er-briar'd hath lean rose-berries and yews And scarlet fruits of ash, that, ere they swell, The missel-thrushes, fluttering, choose; Privet is theirs and briony as well, And redwings wait for the frost-mellow'd sloe, Their orchard is the spinney-side—Awake, and go! V Leaf-driven, my young October in a while Awoke bemazed; on ragged knee arose, Snatch'd at his crook, and hid a shamèd smile Vaulting the ruddy brambles. As he goes I hear his voice; so freshet flows Warbling to wander many a forest mile— So Dryad may the rooty pool forsake Afraid, or antler'd shadow melt into the brake. VI And I go too,—ah! not with mortal things Naked of riches here to flutter down— I soar and tremble in a million wings Above the fen, the coastland, and the town, By dark sea-sunken islands boune Sweeping to choir Apollo where he sings Unslain! The lighthouse lamp, that hears the sky Roaring all night with passage, knows that it is I! Romney Marshman's Love Song On Romney Marsh at sunrise We heard the curlew call, And the young lambs crying to the sheep Within the old sea-wall; The bleak tree that the sea-wind strikes Is bowed across the lilied dykes, All heaven drifting with the lark, The lark that sings for all. You gathered mushrooms from the grass, The newborn mushrooms white; And stooped about with tender cries That come of pure delight. The sheep-lit pastures run for miles With distant villages for isles, And Lympne's grey castle on the down Beholds us from the height. Ah, was your stirring beauty more Than mortal man can bear, Or was it that your tresses streamed Enchantment on the air? I old the winds how we had lain With heart to heart laid bare, In sublimation of desire, Like a singing and outsoaring fire A-poise in slumber there, High on the night-world's shaken breast Hearkening the beat of seas at rest, You and your worshipper; Sang of the region beyond song Where no pale death devours, Yon light-impassion'd vast of bliss Whence falls upon us both the kiss Of new awakening powers. O'er-vaulting golden cloudlets race Eastwards, and leave us time and space; Strange winds and clouds and falls of sheen Mix'd at this birth of flowers; We are breakers-in upon some scene Meant for new eyes like ours. In rich rebuke of mantling pride I saw your bosom move. “Bring it not down to earth!” you cried. “Keep it in shade, that great exchange Of life and joy—that rare and strange And glowing awe of love. Be it remembered, treasured, sighed, Be it remembered, dreamed and sighed, But never spoken of!” Shall then the very core of life Rouse on the harp no string? Shall they be dumb, those radiances, That have so fleet a wing? Shall it awake, the great sunrise, To perish, all unheard, And the soul's wide flights of melodies Fail for a narrow word? Since we must forth, like gallant ships, Far from the haven'd land, Since we must melt like sandy smoke That blows along the strand, Since we must bow and part in grief, Like the rushes or the driven leaf, O put not on my singing lips The proud seal of your hand! Were the deep heaven's golden hosts Beneath our feet like these— Had we outswept the shade of Earth And the long sound of her seas, Our wingèd feet for ever meant Through a thousand lives to run, Each with a new-dawned firmament, Breaking from sun to sun— How well with thee were I content, Thy mute companion, Only with thee and beauty blent Always to journey on! But, lovely Silence!—voices parting, Answering,—through light we breathe In clearness and in glory once,— Are all we can bequeath. E'en mad winds joy—all that have breath Arise and break to flame; Hour ineffaceable as death Shalt thou not have a name? Exquisite Spirit, in whose eyes Floats the unseeing ray, Though utterance scorch between us two Let my fierce spirit reach to you, Be silence torn away! Now wave meets wave; and dull grief's weight, O'erwhelming time, ascends, Now the shaken soul's half-agony For an instant comprehends, Now all things travel to a voice— We see, as from a shore; Let the heart speak, while yet we see, Lest it have sight no more. I Heard a Soldier I heard a soldier sing some trifle Out in the sun-dried veldt alone; He lay and cleaned his grimy rifle Idly, behind a stone. “If after death, love, comes a waking, And in their camp so dark and still The men of dust hear bugles, breaking Their halt upon the hill, “To me the slow and silver pealing That then the last high trumpet pours Shall softer than the dawn come stealing, For, with its call, comes yours!” What grief of love had he to stifle, Basking so idly by his stone, That grimy soldier with his rifle Out in the veldt, alone? A Charge If thou hast squander'd years to grave a gem Commissioned by thine absent Lord; and, while 'Tis incomplete, Others would bribe thy needy skill to them— Dismiss them to the street! Shouldst thou at last discover Beauty's grove, At last be panting on the fragrant verge, But in the track, Drunk with divine possession, thou meet Love— Turn, at her bidding, back! When round thy ship in tempest Hell appears, And every spectre mutters up more dire To snatch control And loose to madness thy deep-kennell'd Fears— Then to the helm, O Soul! Last; if upon the cold green-mantling sea Thou cling, alone with Truth, to the last spar— Both castaway And one must perish—let it not be he Whom thou art sworn to obey! How shall I find . . . How shall I find that friend Of the rare friends, the deep-hearted? When the delicate revels end And the masquers have all departed, At a sudden hour and a drear, For the sweet hour is the sternest, Thou shalt know who held thee dear, Whose hand was thine in earnest. Then unguess'd at thy side Ere Terror's ban be lifted, Though few, few, shall abide Of the many that are sifted, Some bugle's charge may wake Upon thy soul to seal them— Some battling dawn may break And eye to eye reveal them. Yet, yet, should no eye then Its light or fealty send thee, No voice of sons of men Across the wastes befriend thee, Stand by thyself, for prayer. For the very God will waken, When thou shalt shake despair Out of a heart unshaken. Starlight Distilleth Tree by tree filleth, What do they sigh at? Field by field thrilleth, Low comes the fiat, “Let him that willeth Cease from his riot. Starlight distilleth; O World, be quiet! “Night the tremendous Grasps thee and veils thee; Slow thy stupendous Intelligence fails thee. “I, the star-crowded, Outsoar and outsink thee; No more care-clouded Need'st thou bethink thee! “Let my primordial Stupor that seizes Cure, with the cordial For all thy diseases.” Field by field thrilleth— Tree by tree filleth, Fled is all riot. Sleep the soul filleth, Man no more willeth, Starlight distilleth; All Earth is quiet. What Bids me Leave . . . What bids me leave thee long untouch'd, my lute, Hanging so dusty, still and mute? Too many dreams behind these worn eyes throng, And sight too great for song. When I was young how quick thy passions pour'd— Wave on wave, chord on chord— All simple wingèd transport and high strain Of Earth made Heaven again. But I have seen the world, for all its wit, Dangling on fire over the pit; And I must dream what taught our dreamless dead To save Man by a thread. III:LEVIA The Unhappy Marriage Germany Tell me but why—since you left and reproved me— If you respected, you never have loved me? Tell me but why. Italy Merely because of a point you neglected: If you have loved me, you never respected. Tell me but why. A Rude Song of the Switzer and his Pine I The Pine shall be the Switzer's glee, The Pine shall be his “chanson,” The Pine that takes an awkward Point For Foemen to advance on. The Pine it was the Ragged Staff That took an iron lance on When Charles of Burgundy was pricked In such a haste from Grandson! II The Pine-tree bred the Switzer bold, The Pine-tree is his Dwelling, His Hearth it cracks with Pine-tree Stacks— And what is sweeter smelling? The Pine-tree is his jagged Hedge, His hollow trough and Fountain; The Pine it is the Switzer's Sledge To horse him down the Mountain. III Of Pine are his haymaking Prong, His Steeple and his Flagon; Of swarthy Pine shall be his Song, While four Stems make a Waggon! The brown Cones for his Fruit descend, The red Trunks for his Harvest. O Switzer, with a Pine to Vend There's little fear thou starvest, For into Bears thy patient Friend (And cuckoo-clocks) thou carvest! IV As the round-shoulder'd Hero clumps About his steep possession With something of a Pine-tree Stump's Dispassionate Expression, O Switzer, seldom in the Dumps, To thee I'll make confession: Thy Gains are Wood, thy Brains are Wood, At wooden Pins thou Poundest; But if the heart in thee is Wood, 'Tis Pine, and of the Soundest! V The Pine it is the Switzer's Cheer, The best this World affords him, And when his Lodging's ended here The Pine it takes and Boards him— They nail him in the friendly Pine When Slumber sound rewards him. Multatuli Remoulded Once lived a Man who from a Rock broke stone— For little wage, great labour. Hear him groan, “O to be rich, and lounging on a bed With sleepy silken curtains at my head!” And there came an Angel, saying, Be it so! And he was rich, and on a bed at rest Of silk as soft as roses. From the west The King came by with horsemen and patrolled That land, beneath his canopy of gold. And the Newly Rich gazed from his lattice:“Why Have I no kingdom and no canopy? Happy I were with just one little thing: I would have honour! I would be a King!” And there came an Angel, saying, Be it so! And he was King, with horsemen for a screen And cloth of gold to fringe his palanquin. But one day, riding in a desert place, The King grew angry. The Sun scorched his face. “What is this Sun that doth my face devour— Heedless of princes at their height of power? Had I his room, and the arrows of his pride Vast as the air, I should be satisfied!” And there came an Angel, saying, Be it so! And he became the Sun. Jovial he sent Arrows abroad to search the firmament And bake the fields. Everywhere did they pass And scorched the brows of Princes like the grass, Till came a Cloud, that darkly overmisted The plains, and all his sheen of rays resisted. Long, long he battled, but at last avowed, “My light is conquered; I would be that Cloud!” And there came an Angel, saying, Be it so! And he became a Cloud of gloom and rain That cooled and made green pastures of the plain, Till the floods rose. Houses and herds were swept Away in rivers, and the homeless wept. And the Earth became a wholly flooded field, Save for one Rock therein that would not yield. Wildly the streams beat; it withstood their shock. Then the Cloud, sullen, yearned to be that Rock. And there came an Angel, saying, Be it so! And the Cloud became a Rock. Stark he remained Still, whether summer riped or winter rained. And there came a Man into his solitude With pickaxe and with hammer; one that hewed Stones from the Rock. And the Rock groaned oppressed, “Whose heavy Hammer strikes so sore my Breast?” And prayed at length, “Deliver me who can! Make me a hammer-wielder—make me Man!” And there came an Angel, saying, Be it so! And he became a Man, old, feeble, bent, Who for small wages and long labour spent Broke stones under a Rock, and was content. Then the Earth-Spirit, an Enchanter wise, Charmed at complete success of his device, Approached, rubbing his hands in genial wise: “See now the empty Bubbles that enamour You, the Enactor of my Fable, Man! Since you have ended just where you began Confess how futile was the wish to rise!”. . . And the Stone-breaker pushed up, in mild surprise, His spectacles, that Questioner to scan: “Not so! The World's a Bubble, and mere Glamour; But just to have been the round, and learned the grammar, Contents me with my Sitting-pad and Hammer!”</field>
   </doc>
</add>