<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Browne, Moses, 1704-1787</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Browne, Moses, 1704-1787</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">browne moses 1704 1787</field>
      <field name="author_text">Browne, Moses, 1704-1787</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1720's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_2.0385.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1722</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464912</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Richmond beauties</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Richmond beauties</field>
      <field name="title_facet">richmond beauties</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">richmond beauties</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Richmond beauties</field>
      <field name="year_display">1722</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1722</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1722</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464912&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464912&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Browne, Moses, 1704-1787&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;browne moses 1704 1787&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Richmond beauties&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;richmond beauties&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1722&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1722&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Browne, Moses&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1704&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1787&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Richmond beauties&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for E. Curll [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1722&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0590&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;32 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Richmond beauties&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 16 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted, only verse by Browne included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Pulchrâ faciat te prole Parentem. Quilleti Callip.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE RICHMOND BEAUTIES. A POEM. Whilst the glad Muse exults her Strains, And Sings the humble, peaceful Plains: The Meadows, that Refreshing grow; The Streams, that by the Meadows flow; She Paints the Scene in Artless Lays, Nor simple Nature strives to Raise. But when She tells Immortal Things, Of Heroes Slain, or Conqu'ring Kings; Or Virtue's Sacred Path defines, She Sings in stronger, abler Lines. When Truth to Vice, She matchless shows, And strives the Guilty to expose: To aid the mighty Song, She brings Her boldest Notes, and tuneful'st Strings; The Bad to Plunge in lasting Shame, And crown the Innocent with Fame. Near RICHMOND stands the lonely Cell, Where erst did Jenny Seyton dwell: With Ease sufficient was She bless'd, With Riches, full enough, possess'd. The ancient Dame wou'd for her Meat, Wild Sorrel from the Meadow get: Her Drink She from the Cow did draw, Her Bed was on the cleanly Straw: And for her Mirth, She oft wou'd Sing Of Jane The Ballad of Jane Shore, and King Edward IV., beloved by a King. Her Cave contain'd a wooden Stool, And an old Wheel, to spin her Wool: A Spoon, and Knife, as useless thought, Were never in the Confines brought. She, like Diogenes, believ'd, No useless Thing shou'd be receiv'd: And therefore, as Historians say, Her Spoon, and Knife, She threw away. Had She but Virtue's Paths pursu'd, And with her State contented stood; No black Disgrace wou'd now remain, Her hated Memory to stain; Nor her base Guilt, or conscious Cell, Had seen so many Virgins fell. But She to Vice alone inclin'd, Nor thought upon the Woes behind; How once the fond, deluded Fair, Wou'd curse her guilty, fatal Snare: When they forsaken shou'd Complain, And look upon their Woes in vain. With artful Tales wou'd She persuade, Each Lovesick, easy, yielding Maid; Entice each Beauty to be kind, Inflame the wanton Virgin's Mind: Point out the Bliss, and wing the Dart, And send it thro' the burning Heart. O! Maids, said She, if you wou'd know, Where Peace, and Joys, and Transports flow; Before the rising Sun appear, Attend upon your Fortune here: Here court her Smiles, assist the Charms, And call her to your wishing Arms. The yielding Maids obey her Pray'r, And early to the Shade repair; But Jenny had contriv'd the Snare. She calls their Lovers to the Prey, The Youths the welcome Call obey: The Maids they find, the Maids they seize, The Maids grow kinder, by degrees: When each alone, in private, Charms Her Lover, with her open Arms. Her open Arms the Youth surprize, In his, the strugling Wanton lies: Fir'd, with the soft bewitching Bliss, They join in many an eager Kiss. When each, with mutual Promise made, To meet at Ev'ning in the Shade; Swift o'er the parting Cause-way run, And wish'd for the declining Sun. Long did not thus the Pleasure stay, Soon fled the Youths, and Joys away: Too late, the Maids their Guilt perceive, Too late, at their Misfortunes grieve: In vain, they Jenny Seyton blame, In vain, they wou'd escape their Shame. Forsaken, to the Shades they fly, The Shades themselves, relief deny: And once the Solace of their Care, Now but increase their wild Despair. What shall they do?—Ah! hapless Tale! Could'st thou but in their Cause prevail: And wipe away from future Times, The Stain of their unhappy Crimes. Then gladly shou'd thy Numbers flow, And the great Gift with Joy bestow. O! may their Fate a warning be, Dear Chloe, gentle Maid, to thee: And whilst thou see'st the mournful End, That such unhappy Ways attend; With Pleasure turn thy Eyes, and view What Joys a virtuous Love pursue. To the same cool and silent Shade, For Privacy and Pleasure made: Each Ev'ning constantly repair, The more refin'd and modest Fair. Not These to meet alone, and Walk, Or spend the Time in useless Talk; But solid Wit, and Arts to trace, And how to shun supine Disgrace. Three QUEENS The Young Princesses. did over these preside; Three fairer, never Pallas spy'd: When He, in Ida's Solemn Shade, Three Sacred Goddesses survey'd. These more with Charms, by Nature blest, Commanded, and outshone the rest. Their Looks, like Nobleness and Fame, Spoke the Great Line from whence They came: And in each Heavenly Face alone, Was the Great Line's Perfections shown. These, from a Sire, as matchless too, Their pious, beauteous Beings drew: Their Mother's Wit, and Virtue blest, Each pious, beauteous, tender Breast. Whilst each improv'd, adorn'd, refin'd, Promis'd a Race above Mankind. To These, the Fair, Obedience paid; These oft wou'd they Invoke for aid: And with submissive Knees implore, That Joys, a long and shining Store, Might on Their virtuous Actions wait, Might sweeten, and inrich their Fate; That Hymen's Torch, and Holy Shrine, This Lighted, that Adorn'd Divine, Might in the gentle Shade be plac'd, And with Their own blest Nuptials grac'd. For this, They often wou'd relate The Blessings of the Nuptial State: And what fix'd Bliss, and settled Peace, Upon the Equal-Pair increase. How ev'ry Day fresh Joys betide, The constant Swain, and loving Bride: Whilst Those, who to their Lusts betray'd, By Shame and Guilt, are wretched made; Unpity'd Mourn, unsuccour'd Cry, Unblest, and unlamented, Die. O! when shall happy Britain view, Illustrious Princesses, from You; A fair, and num'rous Issue, grown, To Serve the State, and Grace the Throne? That GEORGE, Immortal in his Race, May Rule thro' Time's unmeasur'd Space. And whilst our unborn Sons obey Your Lineage, in a future Day: To You, fresh Honours, they may give, And see You, in Your Children, Live. Hail, RICHMOND! happy, gentle Seat, The Royal Father's mild retreat: O! when shall Thy delightful Shade, Be happy, glorious, joyful made? And Hymen bounteous Blessings spill Upon Thy fragrant, Sunny Hill. Hail, Great AUGUSTUS! doubly Hail; O! never may Thy Off-spring fail: Endow'd with Charms, and Native Fame, May They adorn the British Name: That when some Bard Their Worth shall see, And trace Their Annals down to Thee: That Thou may'st stand, with CHARLOTTE, there, A matchless, Royal, chosen Pair: Remember'd, Honour'd, doubly crown'd, And, like the Living Race, renown'd. O! when hereafter I shall Sing, A virtuous, brave, unhappy King: Alluding to a Play, which will Speedily be brought on the Stage, call'd,—The Tragedy of REFAN, Prince of Kent. If the unkind, and Iron Age, Uphold Him on the Tragic Stage: And whilst they hear Him there relate, His sad, forlorn, and cruel Fate. If then some piteous Tears shou'd flow, At His relentless, pressing Woe: O! may the Audience, with surprize, Look up to Thee, with Blessing Eyes; And their loud Joys to Heav'n display, That sav'd Thee till a happier Day. When Peace and Fortune round Thee wait, And Britain Shines thro' ev'ry State: Superior to the World She stands, And Triumphs in AUGUSTUS Hands.</field>
   </doc>
</add>