<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Talfourd, Thomas Noon, Sir, 1795-1854</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Talfourd, Thomas Noon, Sir, 1795-1854</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">talfourd thomas noon sir 1795 1854</field>
      <field name="author_text">Talfourd, Thomas Noon, Sir, 1795-1854</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1810's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.0741.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">[1811]</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466375</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Poems, on various subjects ; Including a poem on the education of the Poor; an Indian tale; and the offering of Isaac, a sacred drama [by T. N. Talfourd</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Poems, on various subjects ; Including a poem on the education of the Poor; an Indian tale; and the offering of Isaac, a sacred drama [by T. N. Talfourd</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poems on various subjects</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poems on various subjects</field>
      <field name="title_text">Poems, on various subjects ; Including a poem on the education of the Poor; an Indian tale; and the offering of Isaac, a sacred drama [by T. N. Talfourd</field>
      <field name="year_display">[1811]</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1811</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1811</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466375&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466375&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Talfourd, Thomas Noon, Sir, 1795-1854&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;talfourd thomas noon sir 1795 1854&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Poems, on various subjects ; Including a poem on the education of the Poor; an Indian tale; and the offering of Isaac, a sacred drama [by T. N. Talfourd&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poems, on various subjects&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;[1811]&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1811&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Talfourd, Thomas Noon, Sir&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1795&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1854&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poems, on various subjects&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Including a poem on the education of the Poor; an Indian tale; and the offering of Isaac, a sacred drama [by T. N. Talfourd]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Reading&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by A. J. Valpy ... Sold by Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme, and Brown&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Rusher&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;[1811]&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp3849&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;244 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poems, on various subjects&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Including a poem on the education of the Poor; an Indian tale; and the offering of Isaac, a sacred drama [by T. N. Talfourd]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 100 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted; verse drama omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ON THE EDUCATION OF THE POOR. The greater part of this poem was written some time ago, very hastily, and, by Mr. Lancaster's friends, printed and circulated pretty widely. It is here presented with considerable corrections and additions. Addressed to Mr. Lancaster. No fields of Death, no hero's deeds I sing, No splendid conquest, no victorious King; My humble muse a peaceful strain essays, And sings a far more useful victor's praise— Here shall the world no tyrant's sword deplore, No warrior dip his plumes in human gore; Nor purple banners mock the dusky air, Fann'd by the doleful offspring of despair— 'Tis mine to hail the dawnings of the ray, Which glads the world with hope of brighter day, Shines beaming thro' the thickest gloom of night, And puts the deepest shades of woe to flight; Bids Superstition hide her odious head, And raises thousands number'd with the dead. 'Tis mine to sing Religion, Virtue, Truth, Implanted on the minds of British youth, By thee, whose lib'ral deed and fruitful mind Proclaim thee—Benefactor of Mankind. The wants of pining mis'ry to relieve, To wipe the tear away from those that grieve; The trembling wretch from deepest woe to raise, And bid his falt'ring tongue resound with praise; With soothing hand to ease the aching head, And on the cheerless bosom comfort shed; The aching heart with sweet support to fill, Or bid the angry passions—Peace, be still; To soothe the anxious brow of wrinkled care, And watch beside the bed of dark despair, With sympathetic tears each couch to steep, Relieve the poor, and weep with those that weep,— Bespeak the Christian's liveliest grace confest, With God's own image stamp'd upon his breast. Thus Godlike Howard travers'd ev'ry land, Thro' icy regions and thro' tracts of sand, O'er mountains hid in clouds, and capp'd with snow, To benefit mankind, and lighten woe: In dungeons darksome, where the solar ray Had never shone, or brought a glimpse of day, The captives shouted when his voice was heard, And balm flow'd freely from each cheering word; The prisoners' mind began with joy to glow, And tears of pleasure from their eyelids flow— He eas'd their chains, dispell'd their sore dismay, Submission taught, and wip'd their tears away; The darksome caves the godlike Briton trod, And made the old in vice submit to God; Thus, when on mercy's errands from the skies, On balmy wings, a heav'nly seraph flies, Preserves, assists, relieves, and cheers mankind, Supports the body, or directs the mind, Stands o'er afflicting sickness' weary bed, Counts ev'ry groan, and wipes the aching head, Stops ev'ry pain, and hushes all the sighs, Then bear the blissful spirit to the skies. So, in each region where the good man came, His praise was echo'd by the trump of Fame, Exalted monarchs saw their with'ring bays, Their honors dropp'd, and stoop'd to sound his praise; They rode indeed triumphant o'er the plain, Bestrew'd with mangled corps of heroes slain, Tears mark'd the progress of their dreadful sway, And captives sigh'd to see the banners play; But he made wretchedness and grief to cease, His spirit breath'd good-will to man and peace; Zeal ardent thro' his veins and bosom ran, Which glow'd with Love to God, and Love to Man. As solar rays dispel the gloom of night, He put their transient glories all to flight; And when, 'mid works of Love his spirit fled, The hearts of thousands wrung with sorrow bled; Man saw him fall a Martyr to his cause, And nature rang with sorrow and applause: Long as mankind shall be, will stand his fame, And rolling time add lustre to his name. Nor less in thee, O ardent friend of youth, We hail the spread of Knowledge, Virtue, Truth; To teach the poor in virtue's paths is thine, And raise their aims from human to divine. From ignorance impiety begins, And the long train of woes, misfortunes, sins; The youth forlorn, without a teacher's care, Expos'd to wint'ry blasts and chilling air, Without a beacon or a friend to guide, Toss'd to and fro, beset on ev'ry side, To pleasure or to av'rice falls a prey, And press'd by vice's reign and passion's sway, Falls grov'lling on the earth, nor tries to rise, Unhappy, useless lives, and wretched dies.— But 'tis thy noble—thy ingenuous plan To raise the pow'rs of uninstructed man, To form his mind, direct to God on high, And teach him how to live and how to die; Bid ev'ry breast with Love and Joy to glow, And teach the sympathetic tear to flow, Exalt the mind, and give it force to rise The glorious path, that leads it to the skies. Oft are the pow'rs of many a noble mind, To shades eternal, and to night consign'd, By adverse fortune or by woe deprest; In vain with pow'rs immortal heaves the breast; Chill'd by the hand of penury and care, Or only blooms to please a desert air; But, may we hope in future years to see, Arise from those who once were taught by thee, Some Chatham, heaving big with empires' fate To raise his arm, and save a sinking state; Some Milton start aloud in deathless strains, And raise the glory of Britannia's plains; Some ardent warrior form'd her state to save, And by his own, prevent a nation's grave; Resolv'd the fate of bloody war to try, Like Nelson conquer, or like Nelson die; Some Newton thro' the realms of space to soar, Discover suns and worlds unknown before, Show what more hangs on Heav'n's Almighty nod, And raise mankind still nearer to their God; Some Howard give the captive wretch release, Or whisper in the ear of torment—Peace, Turn man from earth, his being's end display, And teach him upwards to direct his way; Bid war and outrage, lust and rapine cease, And bless the world with universal peace. In deepest shades of Heathen darkness hurl'd, Long lay the nations which adorn'd the world; Wise in the arts, in various knowledge wise, They nothing knew beyond these lower skies. 'Mid darkest shades condemn'd in grief to roam, Jehovah's name and attributes unknown; They knew not whence their being, what their end, Whom they should pray to, or on whom depend; In vain they strove to dissipate the gloom— The bound'ry of their knowledge was—the tomb. At length, increasing from a glimm'ring ray, The light burst on us in a flood of day; The word of God brought mortals heav'nly aid, Our being's nature, cause, and end display'd, Show'd us the future worlds beyond the grave, The glorious plan devis'd mankind to save. 'Tis this has brought upon the nations light,— Take this away,—and all is dark as night.— Still rapt in ignorance ten-thousands lie, Think but to err—and only live—to die, Nor view the brightness of Jehovah's love, Nor know their charter to the realms above; Unhappy men! we sicken'd at the view— Our tears once fell—we now rejoice for you; Soon light shall shine with one unclouded ray, And darksome night give place to perfect day; Soon shall the dawn dispel the fatal gloom, And free mankind, and burst their iron tomb. O! if the soul of man, from flame divine, And heav'nly essence sprung, transcendent shine! Above ten thousand orbs that gild the sky,— If when compar'd with this they empty fly— Creation's wond'rous pow'rs as trifling seem, A grain—an atom or an empty dream; O what a work! ten thousand souls to save, And catch them sinking from th' eternal grave; Teach all the way from earthly things to rise, And hope for endless bliss beyond the skies. What! tho' on earth the fairest joys must fade, And fairest prospects vanish like a shade; If sweet Religion taught in youth remain, A solace here we find from ev'ry pain; Soon may we see these noble blessings spread, And heav'nly knowledge, heav'nly comfort shed— Then when disease shall grieve the pallid frame, And quiv'ring lips scarce speak Jehovah's name, Sweet comfort banish fear and dark dismay, And heav'nly angels wipe each tear away, The happy man for thee shall bless his God, Smile at thy name, and humble kiss the rod. For thee shall pray, and fix'd in Faith and Love, Exalt thy name amidst the hosts above.— Britannia, mistress of the azure main, Beholds her fleets and armies fight in vain; Oft when a trophy o'er the dead she rears, Her laurels bought with blood are wet with tears; In Education all her hope relies, Not courage now, but virtue, gains the prize; O hear her join thy honor'd name to praise, And add new lustre to thy peaceful bays; Hark, the glad shouts thro' all the nation ring, And speak their wishes by their patriot king, (Yes, may his name for ever mildly shine, And gain new bays from those he plants on thine) May ev'ry child the word of Promise read, And Britain's happy shores are bless'd indeed; Then Peace shall reign and heav'nly blessings fall, From him who sees, directs, and orders all; Our's be the praise to set the captives free, And fill the world with joy and Liberty, Each virtue florish, ev'ry art succeed— And Britain's Isle by Heav'n be bless'd indeed. Yes: may kind Heav'n assist with aid divine, And great success, in all thy plans, be thine! May ev'ry blessing on thy head descend, Thy country's glory, and thy nature's friend! May, thro' thy means, war, sin, and woe decrease, And earth be hush'd in universal peace. See Superstition with her bloody hand; Nerveless she falls and grimly bites the sand! Whilst Heav'n's glad tidings 'mongst the heathen shed, The wounded heal, and animate the dead! Bid India sing aloud in noblest lays, And Afric join Jehovah's name to praise; Loose ev'ry clime, and plant sweet Sharon's rose On barren deserts and 'mid endless snows; Haste the glad period when the Saviour's fame Shall make all Earth re-echo with his name; When Peace thro' ev'ry Empire shall prevail And universal Justice lift her scale; No more the darts, conveying death be hurl'd, But Wisdom, Truth and Peace shall bless the world; Yes; may these prospects soothe thy life's decline, And heav'n's best comforts, Lancaster, be thine; These soothe the struggles of thy dying breath, And cheer thy spirit on the bed of Death; And when on Seraphs' wings thy spirit flies, To seek its native seat beyond the skies, Then may thy soul with ten-fold pleasure glow, To see the good thy plans have done below; And when the destin'd years revolving 'round, Shall burst the graves and bid the trumpet sound, And nations rising from the dreary tomb Shall start to life and hear their final doom, Then, favor'd man! ten thousand mayst thou meet At God's right hand beside the judgment seat, Thy form rever'd with rapt'rous joy to see, And date their bliss, transporting thought! from thee, Thro' all Eternity in deathless lays, To join the shouts of their Redeemer's praise. ON A TEAR. Emblem of our sad condition, Proof of woe and mis'ry drear; Loudest voice of fair contrition, Sorrow's offspring—trickling tear. Often thou thy station keeping, Join'd with sobs and heaving sighs, Washest cheeks of beauty weeping, Wan the face and dim the eyes! Disappointment, grief, and pleasure, Call thee forth and bid thee flow, Lovely—far exceeding measure When thou fall'st for others' woe; Then the beauteous cheeks adorning, Thou diffusest sweetest gloom, Lovelier far than dews in morning, Washing flow'rs of fairest bloom. Often when Life's billows rolling 'Mid the darkness beat and roar, No kind hand the storm controlling, Harbor none, nor star, nor shore: Thou canst come our griefs relieving, Ease the bosom full of care, Make us cease to grieve—by grieving Spend the force of black despair. Tend'rest pledge of soft affection When for those we love we weep, When faint smiles amid dejection, Speak we know—they only sleep.— Yes; the blush of life declining, Paints a rainbow o'er the tomb, That thro' shades of darkness shining Robs the grave of all its gloom. Whence that blush the west adorning, And the last expiring ray, Speak a far more beauteous morning, And a more delightful day; Then, the constant virtuous lover, Then the friend, the parent dear, Those they lost shall glad recover Ne'er to shed the parting tear. She whom many a loss bereaving, Forc'd her children to deplore; Shall embrace them—ceas'd from grieving Meet them there—to part no more. For eternity beginning, Endless joy, immortal day, Weeping, then, shall cease with sinning, Ev'ry tear be wip'd away. ON THE DEATH OF A POOR, BUT EXCELLENT MAN. Spirit! from thy clay ascending, Seek thy native seat above, Angels thro' the air attending To the God of Grace and Love! Long have sin and woe combining, Haggard care and pallid fear, Show'd thy patience calmly shining, Caus'd the sigh, the groan, the tear. Oft the storms of sorrow roaring, Beat upon thine aching head, Oft we saw thee guilt deploring All thy path with thistles spread: Still amid each dread commotion Thou on God thy hope hast stay'd, When the loud tempestuous ocean Made the stoutest heart afraid. Now thy soul, its prison leaving, Finds the harbor wish'd for long, Ceas'd thy woe and ceas'd thy grieving, Join'd the blest angelic song. Round thy couch in deep dejection Stood thy wife and children dear; All the anguish of affection, Wrung the sad, the silent tear; Still we saw, thy Saviour aiding, Tears did ne'er thy cheeks bedew; Endless bliss and joy unfading, Open'd on thy raptur'd view. Thou couldst leave thy friends with pleasure, Leave them to the God of Love, Haste to take thine endless treasure, Haste to join the hosts above. Tho' no sculptur'd stone, adorning, Show the place where goodness sleeps, There affection daily mourning, With sincerest sorrow weeps. Softly blow, ye breezes, cheering, Breathing sweetly 'round the grave, Where he lies no evil fearing, Let the stream the verdure lave. Constant bloom, ye blushing roses, Cast around your sweet perfumes, Where his dust in peace reposes, Who, like you, in glory blooms. Violets lowly beauteous blowing, Gilded o'er with drops of dew, Florish here, your sweets bestowing, He was humble, pure as you! Gently pass'd the spirit joying, Angels kiss'd the soul away, Songs of praise their harps employing Bore aloft to endless day. Sweetest music softly playing, Charming songs, melodious glee, Whilst the soul in robes arraying Heav'n-like chanted victory. Spirit! from thy blissful pleasures, Look on those who once were dear, Turning from thy heav'nly treasures, If thou canst, bestow a tear.— Whilst to heav'nly joys ascending, Thou attain'st the blissful skies, May we thither onward bending, Catch thy mantle as it flies!— May we, Heav'n, this blessing giving, Meet like thee with aid divine, And like thee, in virtue living, Death obtain as sweet as thine. PROLOGUE TO CATO. Oft has the Muse, from heav'nly essence sprung, The laurel'd deeds of mighty heroes sung, Oft touch'd the chords that string her golden lyre, And warm'd the soul, with more than mortal fire, To give to conq'ring chiefs eternal bays, And gild Ambition's horrid deeds with praise; Oft twin'd the wreath to grace the hero's head, By slaughter nurtur'd, and with carnage red; Her pow'rs debas'd to serve a shameful cause, To give to despots undeserv'd applause; To sing with heroes strew'd th' ensanguin'd plain, Where furies rage, and Discord holds her reign; Earth shaking wide with woe and wild affright, And Nature's self obscur'd in thickest night: But tear these laurels, strip the hero bare, And hear the sighs that pierce the dusky air; Before the eye the mighty victors stand, The scourge, the grief, the ruin of the land, Like fell volcanos filling earth with dread, Whilst clouds of wrath divine hang heavy o'er their head. Not thus, with tinsel robes and guilty hands, The great, the God-like Cato nobly stands; Amidst a nation's vices lifts his head, And speaking fills a guilty world with dread; Poor—yet respected in a wealthy state, In Justice awful—unsubdued by Fate; He spake: and courts withdrew their dazzling blaze, Lov'd by the good—the bad conspir'd to praise, Vice, like a flood, o'erspread the wretched world, He virtue's banners in the midst unfurl'd; Dauntless he stood—not knowing how to dread, Whilst darts fell harmless round his sacred head. When angry Fortune on his prospects frown'd, Red lightnings flash'd, and thunders roar'd around; And pour'd their torrents on his dauntless head, His son—his friends—his country's freedom bled; Like steady Atlas reaching to the skies, Whose foot the waves, whose top the storms defies, He boldly stood, guilt knew him not from fear, Nor did he give to Nature's pangs a tear: Calmly he view'd the raging storm around, And laugh'd at Fortune's efforts—when she frown'd: Nobly he struggled in his Country's cause, For Freedom fought, and gain'd her foes' applause, For this he all the storms of fate defied For this he struggled, and for this—he died! Ah pause and name it not! ascend ye sighs! Let tears suffuse the feeling Christian's eyes; Mistaken, dark, and fill'd with Heathen gloom, He found a shameful passage to the tomb; No Gospel cheer'd his mind with heav'nly ray, And pointed out the road to brighter day; No kind Religion gave the patriot aid, And taught him consolations ne'er to fade, Greatly he liv'd—for light and virtue sigh'd, He practis'd this—for want of that he died. Thanks to our God for brighter, fairer times, When clearest light, with noblest lustre shines, Beneath Religion's mild and gentle reign, In happy Britain's ever favor'd plain.— Let Cato's noble spirit all admire, And strive to catch the ancient patriot's fire, Still hasting on in virtue's path's to rise, Ascend the road that leads us to the skies. What! tho' around the Christian's dauntless head, The clouds of adverse Fortune black'ning spread; Tho' vivid lightnings flash amidst the gloom, Embitt'ring all his passage to the Tomb, The Rock of Ages shall support him there, And angels waft him from this world of care; Secure, and with eternal pleasures blest, And 'midst the wreck of suns and worlds at rest— O! had but Cato known this glorious aid He still had stood undaunted—undismay'd— Cæsar had shudder'd at the good man's sight, And all his boasted glories sunk in night— Rome still had stood by Cato's dauntless plea, And all the nations of the earth been free. Hence let us learn to quell our coward fears, And mourn our nature's feeble state with tears; Let gratitude our ardent breasts inflame, To join a Briton's with a Christian's name; Let us enraptur'd catch the virtuous fire, At once be thankful—pity and admire. SPECIMENS OF A Didactic Poem, ON THE UNION AND BROTHERHOOD OF MANKIND. ARGUMENT. The Author here presents to the Reader some fragments of a poem of very considerable length on those common ties and sentiments of nature, which cement mankind into one family which remain, notwithstanding they are broken by divisions; obscured in the shades of ignorance, and rotted by the general corruption of the human race, still speaking man's present connection and future union into “one fold under one shepherd.” Should these fragments be approved, the whole poem shall be laid before the public. Book the 1st, endeavours to show, that the principles of natural religion are universal; such as the belief of the Being of a God—the probability of a future state—the voice of conscience, &amp;c. and comprehending various episodes, concludes with a display of the superior light of Christianity. Book the 2nd, attempts to show that Man, in every place, has the same natural affection—the same passions—hopes and fears—sympathies and loves, desires and aims. Book the 3d, shows that the principle of resistance to oppression—the daring assertion of the rights of man— the love of freedom, and detestation of bondage, are principles as widely extended as the human race. Book the 4th, endeavours to prove, that in all nations and ages, the powers of the mind have displayed the same force, and appear equally sprung from the essence of Deity—Concluding with an anticipation of the millennium, and an incitement rationally to endeavour the conversion of the heathen. NATURAL RELIGION UNIVERSAL. INTRODUCTION TO BOOK THE FIRST OF THE INTENDED POEM. What Muse, my soul, awakes thy trembling lyre, And fills my ardent breast with conscious fire, Prompts thee, thro' fields unknown, untried to soar, And all the myst'ries of the mind explore? O may it prove that all thy daring plan Is form'd from Love to God and Love to Man; Form'd from the flame, for others' joys that glows, And sheds the tear benign for others' woes; Indignant rouses from the tyrant's rod, And bends in homage to its Maker, God! Then shall thy breast new ardor dauntless find, To sing the noblest feelings of thy kind. Still weeps the Muse, our state forlorn to view, Her voice is hush'd, and tears her cheeks bedew; She sees each breast humane with sorrow wrung, Silent her lyre neglected and unstrung; With down-cast looks she sable-rob'd appears, Her grief—too great for words—but speaks in tears, She sees mankind with sin and woe distrest, With clouds of deepest gloom and shades opprest; Sees how mankind by mutual discord bleed, And ev'ry band of kindred's burst indeed; Still, 'mid the darkness shines a glimm'ring ray, Which speaks a foretaste of a brighter day; Hope, pleasing Hope, still holds her gentle reign, And shows the bands of union still remain; Those common feelings—aims and views we see, Which ne'er can cease—till man shall cease to be; The bands of love from heav'nly mercy sprung, Remaining still, tho' broken—snapp'd—unstrung, Which seem to promise or to whisper peace, And bid us hope the direful strife shall cease; Those gentle rays of truth which dimly shine, Thro' thickest shades—tho' faint—yet still divine, Which 'mid the darkest night their beams display, And give some hope—at least—of brighter day; These, which from Heav'n in ev'ry bosom spring, With all their blessings and their sweets, I sing. Who form'd the earth, who nature's wond'rous plan, Or in his image made the creature Man? Who stretch'd the heav'ns of yon etherial blue, Or fill'd the sky with orbs we dimly view? Who Nature's wond'rous works and wheels controls, Or plants his image in his creatures' souls? Ask India's savage in the desert drear, His bosom beats with love, and throbs with fear; His grateful heart will give the just reply, Or if too full—will point you to the sky— When cheering sun-shine warms the placid day, The breezes rise and cooling zephyrs play, When 'mid the deep'ning woods the roses bloom, Each breeze wafts gladness, and each gale perfume; His grateful heart shall burst in joyful lays, And speak exulting his Creator's praise; When gath'ring storms obscure the azure sky, And rush the sudden whirlwinds from on high, When thunders roar and vivid lightnings glare, He shudd'ring cries aloud—that God is there; Calls on His name, who reigns above the skies, Returns His love, or from His anger flies. See where the scorching sun with piercing ray Shines o'er the burning sands with torrid day, In wildest beauty Afric Nature rise, And worship Him who form'd her cloudless skies; Shake wildly all her locks of jetty hue, Lave her parch'd limbs with drops of early dew; Point to the Nile and Egypt's fertile lands, Or rear her head 'mid rocks and burning sands; The simple robe around her shoulders roll'd, Mock ev'ry rule of art sublimely bold, See her assert her rights and noblest claim, And prove mankind in ev'ry state the same; Spurn then the vile oppressor's cruel rod, And cry for vengeance to her guardian—God, Rise thro' the burning field and barren shore, And claim her rights with weapons dipp'd in gore, Shake in the struggle all the azure sky, And lead her sons to conquer, or to die. Thro' pathless plains where ocean rivers flow, Lave fields untill'd, unknown, with current slow, Reflect the Heav'ns within their bosom fair, And cool the breezes of the sultry air; Or down the craggy rocks stupendous sweep, Foam thro' the air and seek the bottom deep; Where serpents scaly rule the desert land, And hiss tremendous thro' the fiery sand; Taint all the sultry air with baneful breath, And ev'ry step is big with woe and death; There, Man, (if human footstep dare to tread, Where deaths encompass and where Nature's dead) Shall spurn, with sturdy arm, th' oppressor's claim, And leap exulting at his Maker's name— Turn now, Humanity, thine heav'nly eye, To see yon wretched man in anguish lie; His fetter'd hands are worn with grief and care, And thro' his dungeon howls the chilling air; Torn from his friends, his country, and his all, Here doom'd, a wretched captive, soon to fall; Without a crime, of ev'ry good bereft, No earthly hope—no earthly solace left, His sullen groans re-echo thro' the air, And melancholy brooding feeds despair: Say is his mind subdued?—or will he kneel To kiss the rod, and own the conquror's steel? No; still his spirit rises in his heart, Still would his feeble arm direct the dart; Say cans't thou see, amid the darkness drear, One sign of weakness or one glist'ning tear? No; still revenge hangs quiv'ring on his tongue, His heaving breast with direst tortures wrung; He calls on Heav'n to thunder from on high, And bid the lightnings flashing rend the sky; From God's own thunderbolts with anger red, To bring down vengeance on the tyrant's head; And as in thought he sees the monster die, His pains, his fetters, and his tortures fly; Some comfort darts amidst the darksome gloom, A refuge shows; that refuge is—the tomb; There shall he lay his weary limbs to rest, Where robbers come not, which no fiends infest; Hope upward turns with joy his pallid eye, And whispers. . . . thou shalt live beyond the sky— There cease despair, be banish'd ev'ry woe, And human breasts with nobler joys shall glow; There meet thy much-lov'd wife—thy children dear, Where angels' hands shall wipe the falling tear; Yes; rest secure, on yonder peaceful shore, And live for ever blest—to part no more. In savage lands 'mid wastes and deserts drear, Oft sad affliction calls the tender tear; For well, too well, alas! we weeping know, That man is but another name for woe; Whilst sighs of anguish burden ev'ry breath, And speak some friend's, some near relation's death; Say, does no twinkling ray disperse the gloom, No hope of life, and ray beyond the tomb? No cheering thought to bind the broken heart, And whisper “you shall meet no more to part;” Yes; tho' uncertain, dark, and mix'd with fear, The rays of hope may shine on ev'ry tear; Half stop the sigh and ease the aching breast, The grave shall give, at least, repose and rest. See, with her savage plaints and bosom bare, Yon anguish'd mother fill, with shrieks, the air; Whilst o'er her infant's tomb, with chaplets hung, She speaks her agony with falt'ring tongue; Drops all the garlands wafting sweet perfume, And falls, half senseless, on the lowly tomb,— Is there no comfort to remove despair, No hope....no angel near to sooth her care; Raise, from the ground, suffus'd with tears, her eyes, And give some hope of realms beyond the skies? Yes; life's last beam shall then, with cheering ray, Afford a glimpse, tho' small, of brighter day; Tho' faint, obscure, by clouds and shades o'erspread, Still by her aching heart the hope be fed; “Yes;” she exclaims, with pleasure in her eye, “Soon will it be, like thine, my lot to die; “Then in some happier isle, some safer shore, “Where tempests beat not—where no billows roar; “No ruffians make our sons and husbands slaves, “And drag them far, and far across the waves; “There may we meet, no more by fears distrest, “And thou shalt press again thy mother's breast— “And if—which Heav'n forbid!—this hope untrue, “This is indeed my last, my long adieu; “Death shall remove my pain; with thee to lie! “Thy loss forget!—O joyful thought—to die! “I'll bless the day when here I cease to be, “And, in the grave shall lie, my child with thee. INDIAN TALE. Where Ganges' sacred stream, with forests crown'd, Laves fields unknown, and cheers the torrid ground; Where craggy rocks and cloud-capt mountains rise, With woods untrodden crown'd that touch the skies; Where tall cocoäs spread their branches wide, And plantains stand with rude, majestic pride; Lies deep a lowly vale with woods embrac'd, A gem of beauty, beaming in the waste; There spicy groves embosom all the plain, And birds of varied plumage sing in vain; Abodes of peace! where all around is still, Save the calm murmurs of the crystal rill, Save where the distant cat'racts deaf'ning roar, With sound like distant thunder fills the shore, Awes with its noise the silent deserts drear, Which dies in murmurs on the list'ning ear; Here oft the aged fisher will relate, Whose whiten'd locks proclaim his lengthen'd date, The only relict of the lowly vale— With tears of sympathy, the tragic tale; Lay down his nets, his anxious toils forego, To tell, with quiv'ring lips, the tale of woe; Point to each spot, with fond remembrance now, And weep reclining on the whiten'd brow. The Muse shall here in simple strains relate, The fisher's tale of young Acasto's fate— Unknown to all the shining rolls of fame, It shows that Man in ev'ry land's the same; Same in his hopes, his aims, his griefs and fears, At least, that all have fellowship in tears. In calmest form the face of nature lay, As fair Aurora usher'd in the day; In clouds of varied forms and tints embrac'd, The eastern sun display'd the sandy waste; Ting'd all the hills with specks of deepest blue, And spread the flow'ry lawn with drops of dew; Awak'd the rising bird in joyful lays, And bade the woods resound their Maker's praise; When old Acasto tears of pleasure shed, And, early rising, left his rustic bed; O'er his experienc'd head wav'd ringlets grey, With mingled smiles and tears, he hail'd the day; Oft had his arm with firmest sinews strung, The jav'lin darted and the discus flung; Roam'd, prey to find, the sultry desert round, And fix'd some panting savage to the ground; Now, here retir'd, life's evening calm he spent, And, t'wards the tomb his tranquil footsteps bent; Now by his cottage 'mid the tufted wood, In grateful joy with lifted hands he stood; His heart burst forth aloud in thankful lays, And thus to heav'n he pour'd his transport and his praise— “Parent of all, the Lord of earth and air, “Where'er thou dwell'st—accept my humble pray'r; “Thou who can'st pierce the thickest gloom of night, “And liv'st 'mid seraphs in the realms of light; “Bend from on high my grateful tear to see, “Approve that heart that burns and pants for Thee; “Thou know'st this tribute of my praise sincere, “Warm from a bosom fill'd with love and fear— “Thee, tho' but dimly known, I'll here adore, “Till life shall end, and I shall breathe no more; “To thee, in joy or sorrow will I flee, “My source of joy—and all my hope's in Thee.” “This day my son, if thou our wishes speed, “His much-lov'd Zara to the fane shall lead, “Blest by my wife now wrinkled o'er with age, “His heart and hand in ties of love engage; “O from above thine aiding hand extend, “And be the father's and the husband's friend; “Here scatter blessings casting sweet perfume, “And let me rest my head within the tomb; “Then, full of age, with pleasure there I'd lie,— “But let me see them blest before I die; “Then shall they sing thy name in grateful lays, “And infants, yet unborn, shall lisp thy praise.” He ceas'd, and upwards turn'd his aged eye, Which weeping pointed to the cloudless sky; When young Acasto from the garden's shade, Led by the hand, with joy, the charming maid; Who ev'ry grace and lovely charm possest, The auburn tresses swept her beauteous breast; Sweet innocence and ev'ry bashful grace, Shone in her eye and varied in her face; Oft on her spouse her timid eyes she turn'd, Whose raptur'd breast with purest passion burn'd; Around his father's neck his arms he threw, Whilst tears of joy the sage's cheeks bedew; On both by turns, his aged arms he press'd, And clasp'd them silent to his joyful breast; “Yes,” when his swelling heart gave words, he cried, “Long may you live, the valley's boast and pride; “May heav'nly bounty noblest blessings shed, “When I am number'd with the silent dead; “All—all that virtue's hand obtains—secures— “All that I wish—but cannot speak—be your's!” Now from the house, with steps infirm and slow, Whilst tears of pleasure from her eyelids flow, The mother comes suffus'd with tears of joy, And hastes, beyond her strength, to bless her boy: He leaves his bride upon the rustic seat, And melts in love before his mother's feet; Her blessing, with a heart o'ercharg'd, he hears, And with affection sinks dissolv'd in tears; She lifts her eyes, which tears of transport shed, And calls down blessings on her darling's head.— O sweetest passion of our varied mind, Which leaves in force all others far behind; Which nature's self inspires in ev'ry clime, Uncheck'd by space and unimpair'd by time; Thy tears as pure, as fine as temper'd steel; Thy love as chaste as holy angels feel, Alike in fortune's noon, affliction's night, Which storms affect not—which no dangers fright;— Sent to the heart from heav'nly flames above, Heav'n's noblest blessing—pure maternal love. My soul no feeling sings in fancied strain— But one whose pow'r she owns in ev'ry vein; With grateful song, this tribute here she pays, To her who first inspir'd her feeble lays;— To thee, my mother, grateful strains I pour, From love which ne'er shall cease till life's no more; Thee, whose dear image, present to my view, Bids sweet affection's tears my verse bedew; Whose image, time nor woe nor death shall part, Nor joy, nor grief, tear from my glowing heart; Yes; here from fiction and from coldness free, These grateful lines my Muse shall yield to thee. Now nearer drew the time when Hymen's bands Should bless the lovers' hearts and join their hands; When all the pleasing prospect open'd fair, And spicy odors gladden'd all the air: A fatal calm—that breeze whose lovely breath Now gladden'd all—was soon to echo death; Thus when the ocean hush'd in calms is laid, And nature smiles and pleasant lies the glade; Too oft the scene, the sudden tempests shroud And lightnings flash, and thunders roar aloud; When God, his fiery arm for vengeance bare, With fiercest whirlwinds mingles earth and air; Thus oft the calm, that reigns o'er mortal's hearts Precedes the rolling thunder's fiery darts, The gentle breezes soon to storms shall rise, And clouds of woe obscure the fairest skies. Whilst o'er the verdant altar garlands bloom, And dew-dropt roses waft a sweet perfume; The crowding virgins all in white array'd, Stand round the bridegroom and the blushing maid; The rite just finish'd—and the parents' kiss, Crowns all their joy with more than human bliss; Shouts—distant shouts of dread assail the ear, Break off the joy—and fill the mind with fear; Half-fainting Zara hides her fading charms, And sinks affrighted in her husband's arms; Dismay'd—in silence dread, the parents stand, Whilst nearer shouts re-echo o'er the sand; Plainly they seem to hear the missile dart, At ev'ry sound—at ev'ry breeze they start; Scarcely they dare to draw their feeble breath, These were the sounds of woe—of war—of death; As when amid the cheerful village train, Whose cheerful sports enliven all the plain, The scaly monster of the tow'ring wood, Glides on and hissing chills the circling blood; Shrieking they fly in wildest haste away, Or stand opprest with horror and dismay; Thus stood the bridal train aghast—distrest, The heart forgot to beat in Zara's breast; Nerveless she sunk upon the verdant shore, And all was terror that was joy before; When from the hill a swain with breathless speed, Whose face declar'd he told some dreadful deed; From distance, loud in quiv'ring accents, cries, “Acasto, arm! from dreams of peace arise; “A fierce invader fills our shores with death, “And swift destruction hangs on ev'ry breath.— “Soon must your fields lie waste, your cottage fall, ‘Fight for your bride—your parents and your all;” Rous'd from their dreams with sight of present woes, The bridegroom's breast with ardent passion glows; But not to glory all his thoughts resign'd, Love gives him ardor and inspires his mind; Tears after tears his mother's cheeks bedew, Around his father's neck her arms she threw; While wildly Zara rolls her downcast eyes, Nor hears her mother's groans, her husband's sighs; “Yes,” he exclaims, and throws his griefs aside, “For thee, alone, I'll fight, my blooming bride; “For thee, the ranks of bloody war I'll try, “For thee I'll conquer—or for thee I'll die: “Then, since I go, whate'er my lot may be, “May Heav'n support thee when thou think'st on me; “Thy lovely form from keen affliction save, “And bless thee till we meet beyond the grave.” He said, and bending kiss'd her faded cheek, She rais'd her eyes, and thrice essay'd to speak; Thrice did the griefs, that all her bosom wrung, Check the fond accents of her quiv'ring tongue; Thrice did her eyes behold the cheerful light, And thrice they clos'd, opprest with thickest night. Meantime the father brings the quiver dread, And presses 'neath a casque his hoary head; Embrac'd his wife, his son, with fury wild, Gaz'd on his bride, now frown'd, now sobb'd and smil'd. Oft they look back, till, reach'd the summit high, The dusky plains of discord meet the eye, Where rapt in clouds of smoke the armies lay, Lost 'mid the dust that hid the face of day; The sun reflects each sabre's dazz'ling rays, And 'mid the dust the spears like lightning blaze; Then fitting on their arms and jav'lin's bright, The ardent warriors seek the field of fight.— Meantime fair Zara wakes, her grief to know, And wailing silent, strives to hide her woe; Her blooming cheeks are clouded o'er with care, And on her brow is painted deep despair; Her young companions quake with anxious fear, Sigh answers sigh, and tear is shed for tear. In closest fight, the adverse armies rage, And poison'd darts in dusky air engage; No thought of life, no hope from death to fly, They bravely stand to conquer or to die; When thro' the air a jav'lin wings its way, And darts like lightning on its destin'd prey; Acasto's breast receives the poison'd dart, Shades spread his eyes, and quickly beats his heart; Still ardent rage his dying breast inspires, Breathing defiance, greatly he expires; Full on his son, his piercing eyes he cast, And striving yet to speak, he breathes his last. Fix'd in amaze and grief, his offspring stood, Bent o'er the corpse and fondly suck'd the blood,— There on his father dear his body threw, And, 'mid the battle, sigh'd his last adieu; There 'mid contending hosts he chose to lie, And with his much-lov'd father glorious die; Till thought of Zara bade him nobly rise, Her image mournful swam before his eyes; He calls his friends—of youths a noble band, With these he marches o'er the burning sand, Assails the force—spreads war and death around, Till prest with wounds he grimly bites the ground; His faithful friends his fainting body bear, Far from the sights of death to purer air; He seeks the wood, where agoniz'd he lay, Forlorn and friendless, to the close of day— His father's image, present to his view, Oft bade the tears his manly cheeks bedew; But Zara's woes with deeper grief distrest, And fill'd with speechless agony his breast; His only wish, once more her face to view, And speak one last, one sad, one fond adieu! To die while gazing on her lovely charms, And breathe his last, repos'd in Zara's arms. The sun had quench'd his rays in western seas, Low thro' the woodlands crept the cooling breeze; The western tints in slow progression fade, And darkness veil'd the earth in ebon shade; Save that the moon, 'mid clouds of fairest white, Shed mildest rays amid the gloom of night; A solemn stillness held the fields of death, And Peace had hush'd each voice, each whisp'ring breath; When Zara, rising from her grassy bed, Love's softest tears in quick succession shed; Mourn'd thro' the vale and sought the deathlike plain, Fearless 'mid crowds of dead she dar'd complain; Sought for her lord and fear'd to find him there— Her groans re-echo thro' the silent air; “Unhappy youth,” with quiv'ring tongue, she cries, “This hand must never wipe thy tearful eyes; “No Zara near to soothe thy dying breath, “And close, in peace, thy youthful eyes in death; “Now from this scene of blood and woe I'll flee, “And pray to die, my dearest spouse, with thee.”— She said, and sought the wood's embow'ring shade, Where her lov'd spouse in anguish long had laid; He starts and calls, she panting to reply, Speaks not for joy, to find her husband nigh; But rushing onwards with disorder'd charms, Receives his dart, and sinks within his arms. Amazement seiz'd his breast and dire dismay— 'Twas wounded Zara in his bosom lay; The moon just beaming on her pallid face, Display'd her features cold in death's embrace; The blood ran cold about his breaking heart, 'Twas Zara wounded by—Acasto's dart. “And is it you my spouse!” she feebly cries, “Then am I blest, that thus your Zara dies; “Sweet is the wound your healing weapon gave, “Farewell—we soon shall meet beyond the grave: “Think, sometimes think on this my last adieu, “Yet recollect not—Zara bled by you.”— She said, and sunk upon the verdant shore, With her Acasto fell—to rise no more; Scarcely his lips can give the parting kiss, Or speak his hope to meet in endless bliss; Embracing, fondly thus they yield their breath, And safe united, seek the shades of death. Peaceful they rest, and mingle in the tomb, Where join'd with woodbines, dew-drench'd roses bloom; There ev'ry swain the tender tear bestows, And ev'ry maiden's heart with pity glows; There, whilst the seasons change, the maids shall bring The choicest beauties of the op'ning spring; There shall they oft with tears the garlands steep, And pure affection's tend'rest feeling weep. THE SUPERIOR ADVANTAGES OF CHRISTIANITY, STATED AND EXEMPLIFIED. Hush! let the mind be sooth'd and calm'd in peace, Each worldly care, each angry passion cease; Imagination's fairest forms decay, Unrivall'd Reason hold her boundless sway; Whence and what are we? Whither do we tend? Where shall the varied course of mortals end! Must all our pow'rs engross'd by joys of earth, Forget for ever their etherial birth? No; Heav'n forbid!—the restless, tow'ring mind Strives hard, a nobler place of rest to find; Whilst heav'nly flames inspire the conscious breast, Which seeks—but seeks in vain its native rest; Defil'd by sin, distrest by grief and woe, Asserts its claim more solid joys to know; Still pressing onward looks beyond the tomb, And starting, fearful views eternal gloom. Yes; speak ye spirits of the mighty dead, Ye, whom the hope of heav'n rejoicing led; Ye shades of Plato, Socrates, and you, Who find, we trust, that rest ye never knew; Did not your struggling souls impatient fly, Beyond the earth, and pant for realms on high? Did ye not feel some hope of future good, “Tho' dimly seen and faintly understood;” And did no fears your anxious thoughts infest, And say—the grave may be your only rest; And melancholy wrapt in deepest gloom, Say—all your pow'rs may vanish in the tomb? Yes; thus perplex'd in darkness long you lay, With many a feeble glimpse of brighter day, Till death did all your hopes and fears destroy, These chas'd in flight—those crown'd with endless joy. In strains seraphic, godlike Maro sung, While mingled fears and hopes his bosom wrung; These all his soul arous'd with heav'nly fire, Those hush'd, in tears, the poet's tuneful lyre Imagination lent her friendly aid, And painted fairest prospects soon to fade; Describ'd some fancied state of joy and woe, Then paus'd and hop'd some state of bliss to know; Till all his comfort in the maze o'erthrown, His Orpheus' griefs might seem the poet's own. See sweetly touching on the tender strings, Orpheus, unhappy bard, with tears he sings; With vent'rous step forsaking earth and light, To tread the dreary shores of hell and night; Afflicted love inspir'd the hero's strain, Nor was the force of love and music vain; His strains thro' Pluto's frigid bosom thrill, The furies weep,—“Ixion's wheel stands still,” The wand'ring shades the notes seraphic hear, Now swell with joy—now weep, now start with fear; Grim Cerberus with wonder licks his feet, Those hearts which never glow'd, with pity beat; The tortur'd find relief—the monarch hears, And hell transported sinks in gentlest tears; The bard o'ercomes—and ravish'd Pluto yields, Whilst shouts re-echo thro' Tartarean fields; Opprest with bliss the poet speeds his way, Whose heart o'ercharg'd forbids the joyful lay; His wife he holds—her pulse begins to glow, And Orpheus' tears with sweet impatience flow; The day now gleaming, shows surrounding gloom, The awful portals of the dreary tomb; A sudden joy the husband's heart possest, With quicker transport beats his glowing breast; Impatient now, he lifts his longing eyes, Ah see! her color fades, she falls, she dies!— His piercing shrieks the ear of hell might move, If hell could pardon, or if hell could love; “And now farewell!” she cries with quiv'ring tongue, “My breast again with hellish tortures wrung. “Farewell! our union cruel Fate forbids, “And second death sits heavy on my lids; “Alas! redeem'd in vain, I hasty go, “'Mid wretched shades where Stygian waters flow; “My quick departure now the fates ordain, “No longer here I stretch my arms in vain; “I hear them call! shades wrap mine eyes in night, “And thy dear image flits before my sight; “The clay-cold tyrant stops my feeble breath; “Again I sink and close my eyes in death!” She speaks and flies an empty shade in air, And leaves her husband fill'd with deep despair; Who stands as struck by Heav'n's command to stone, While thrice Avernus echoes ev'ry groan. Then raves in anguish round the darksome cave, Then stands as silent as the dreary grave; Eurydice! with falt'ring accents weak, Thy name is all the wretched bard can speak; Still sighing thee, he keeps the darksome way, And loves the shades, impatient of the day; Here, long he wept, thro' all his youthful prime, Till death dismiss'd his shade to join with thine. Thus wrapt in deepest clouds of error's gloom, Lay all the earth, as dreary as the tomb, Save where the glimm'ring stars, that beam'd between, Gleam'd o'er the horror of the dreadful scene; Save from the east some feeble ray display'd Its partial beams to show the deeper shade; The mind then sought in vain a place of rest, The wisest only knew their darkness best; Till o'er the hills arose the radiant morn, Smil'd on the world, a dreary waste forlorn; Angelic hosts the glorious advent sung, And Heav'n resounding with the chorus rung;— Then Truth celestial like a seraph bright, Chas'd all the clouds, and put the shades to flight; Shook o'er the joyful earth her azure wing, And breath'd around an universal spring; Pour'd on the darksome mind her quick'ning ray, And made mankind rejoice with perfect day; Disclos'd to mortal minds th' Almighty's plan, Heav'n stooping here, and God redeeming man; Display'd the worlds beyond the narrow tomb, And gave us prospect of a Life to come; Religion meek diffus'd her joys around, And bade new flow'rs adorn the barren ground; Then gloomy Superstition took her flight, And slowly sought her native caves of night; Envy and Malice shudd'ring, grimly fled, And Vice and Rapine, Lust and Folly bled; O'er ev'ry flow'r she pour'd a deeper bloom, Increas'd the fragrance of each sweet perfume; Caus'd hearts long sunk in deep despair to sing, Brought equal joys to subject or to king; Hush'd all the clangor of unruly strife, And conq'ring Death display'd Eternal Life; The grave o'ercame—bade all their foes forgive, And told the grief-worn wretch, believe and live; Made all the earth resound Jehovah's love, Joy here below, and endless bliss above. Speak ye who long opprest with griefs and fears, Pierc'd night with sighs and steep'd your couch in tears; Ye, who have known a mind with guilt opprest, And felt the struggles of an aching breast; Whose wounded hearts Religion's balm hath heal'd, Who taste the blessings of the Truth reveal'd, Say, would you change your state for Eastern pride, For all the di'monds India's mines supplied; Would ye for all that regal pomp supplies, Resign your title to the blissful skies?— Tho' show'rs of wealth, of fame, of glory fall, For one calm moment ye would scorn them all; Smile if ye saw your earthly comforts flown, And fix'd secure, rely on Heav'n alone. Yes; now we dare to look with placid eye, On all the varied pageant passing by; 'Mid ev'ry storm and ev'ry tempest trust A God most holy, merciful, and just; He who will bend from Heav'n his list'ning ear, To hear the suppliant sigh, and mark the tear; The feeblest wish—the lowest groan to know, And bid the lab'ring breast with comfort glow; The force of vengeance and of war disarm, And soothe the angry passions to a calm; The burden of the weary saint to bear, Or joyful hear the lisping infant's pray'r; Th' opprest, the wretched, captive to defend, To prove the orphan's, and the widow's friend; On weak or strong, alike His blessings fall, The God, the Father, and the Friend of all. Far in the shades that glad the lonely vale, Where flow'ring shrubs with fragrance scent the gale; Behold, within the humble cottage shed, The youthful tribe with care and labor bred; No costly banquet trembling slaves prepare, No di'monds blaze, no rubies sparkle there; Tho' friendless, poor, neglected, and unknown, Religion there erects her humble throne; There, e'en 'mid want dwells happiness sincere, There flows Affection's simplest—fairest tear;— Grateful they live and own their God in all, Meet at His throne and at His footstool fall; And when they sing in simply grateful lays, E'en angels listen and approve the praise. No pomp, no splendid temple glistens here, But filial love is mix'd with holy fear; No dazzling splendor of accursed gold, But nobler gems their purer rays unfold; Where ev'ry virtue's noblest lustre shines, Beyond the transient blaze of earthly mines; See parents grey, and youthful children weak, Join in the wild, their Maker's praise to speak; And Heav'n gives all the Happiness it can, The noblest bliss, the fairest lot of man; Its sure protection 'mid the darksome shade, And daily joys which never pall or fade; Love, peace, a heart that's ne'er with anguish rent, Love toward their God—with gratitude—content. Joys pure as those celestial seraphs know, Which give delight and Heav'n begun below; But see Affliction's offspring nobly die, And own Religion's mounts beyond the sky; Where the good father in life's joyful prime, (Like a fair flow'r cut off before its time), Extended lies, on bed of sickness weak, Whilst clammy drops bedew his pallid cheek; His tott'ring frame with Death's dread tortures wrung, And the last words just quiv'ring on his tongue; Whilst near his bed, his still attentive wife, Her children clasping, begs her husband's life; Watches each sigh, and counts each heaving breath, With tend'rest cares beguiles the pains of death; Calm resignation sits upon his brow— Where, dreaded Death, are all thy terrors now? He smiles and calls thee—then on all that's dear, He thinks, and drops for them one tender tear; Kisses each drop from ev'ry friendly eye, And raptur'd cries—“and is it thus to die? “Weep not for me, the pang that rends your heart, Is all that now I feel of death's cold dart; “Soon shall we meet again, to part no more, “When death and sin, and grief shall all be o'er;” Celestial spirits stop the dying breath, And gently close the eyes in welcome death; Cherubic harps the spirit call away, And bid it mount to realms of endless day. O happy state! Life's fretful fever past, He sweetly sleeps—and silent rests at last; For him the lovely garlands blushing blow, To deck his tomb where living waters flow; With all the earliest chaplets of the spring, Beneath the shading seraph's watchful wing; Who pleas'd stoops down the orphan's sigh to hear, And views with sympathy affection's tear. Speak ye proud sceptics, laughing Heav'n to scorn, Poor wretched outcasts splendidly forlorn; Say, do like this your proudest triumphs please, Are all your fancied joys as fair as these? Will flatt'ry, or will prouder Science save, Or snatch you sickly from the yawning grave? When on the trembling verge of life you shrink, And views eternity's detested brink; Can all the pow'rs of reason or of sense, This blest serenity of soul dispense; Will all your pow'rs of reason, fancy, wit, The spirit for eternal pleasures fit? When all the mist dispers'd, your weeping eyes Behold the punishments you dar'd despise; Each hope delusive from your bosom swept, Of each pretended friend, and joy bereft; When God, a righteous judge appears in ire, And fills you now with half infernal fire; What would you give to see him mildly nod, And know the Rock of Ages for your God? O, 'tis for you I weep, for you I pray, Leave woe for gladness, night for perfect day; Believe and live—arise and taste of Heav'n, Your penitence received—your sins forgiv'n. Celestial spirit, wave thy azure wings, And shed those odors seldom shed for kings; Sent from the blissful regions of the skies, To watch the ground where fair Eliza lies; Where 'mid the weeping cypress' shading gloom, Youth, virtue, beauty, find an early tomb; O give me something of that strain divine, Which equals her's, angelic, rivals thine; Then would I paint her death in plaintive strain, Nor try to move the sceptic's heart in vain; But I forbear—to pierce that heart of stone, Almighty Spirit, is thy work alone! Didst thou from heav'nly hosts avert thine eye, O shade belov'd, to hear the friendly sigh? Didst thou behold the last endearing kiss, And drop a tear—“if souls can weep in bliss?” When borne on cherubs' wings aloft to Heav'n, Would not one sigh, one sorrow be forgiv'n? Too fair a flow'r to blossom here below, Death snatch'd her hence in heav'nly fields to blow; Forgive the fond, yet cruel, soft desire, At once we envy—pity and admire; But this our wish, our pray'r, our efforts be, O lovely shade to live and die like thee!” O were thou here the sceptic's soul to move, And bid his bosom warm in heav'nly love; Then should his bosom glow with love divine, And viewing thee should learn to envy thine; And whilst thy actions all thy words approv'd, Love thy Religion, while thy deeds he lov'd; Then see how Revelation's clearest light, From Nature's self removes the cloud of night, Displays Heav'ns guardian arm and noblest plan, Reviving Nature and redeeming Man. See where the moss-grown arch o'erhangs the plain, Where desolation holds her dreary reign; Where statues half effac'd now mould'ring lie, And bid the passing swain prepare to die; Warriors who once had drench'd the world in gore, And tyrants lie—to harm mankind no more; Within the ruin'd abbey's awful shade, In lowly tombs the humbler poor are laid; Here death and time their conq'ring powers evince, And here a beggar lies, and there a prince; That bard whose soul was warm'd with heav'nly fire, Now clay-cold lies, nor strings his crumbling lyre; Where o'er some lowly tomb affection weeps, And unlamented near Ambition sleeps; Virtue and vice's contests here are past, Man's pow'rs are lost and scatter'd by the blast, The hand of death has stopp'd each tuneful tongue, O'erthrown the good, the bad—the old, the young; Alike they equal sleep—no sound is heard, None but the croaking of some lonely bird; Where 'mid the silent walls and list'ning trees, Despair seems hanging on each whisp'ring breeze; Stops the affrighted trav'ller's heaving breath, And chills his soul with images of death; With deep reflections, Nature sable-clad, Invites the soul to be sublimely sad, And ignorant of heav'n's extended plan, To mourn the weakness and the woes of man; Or else no kindred griefs, no joys he knows, The hard insulter of his nature's woes; To see man's hopes and pow'rs, and passions sleep, E'en he at length self-satisfied shall weep. Oh when we see Ambition's raging hand, Bathe in the blood of myriads o'er the sand; See ev'ry hour some laurel'd robber plan The curst invasion of the Rights of Man; Revenge some rousing, big to deeds untold, Some lure of pleasure, and some thirst for gold; And these triumphant hold their reckless sway, Bid Virtue yield, and Honesty obey; Injustice triumph—Virtue made her slave, To pine in chains or find an early grave; See all the noblest, just arise, then fall, Behold the fatal tomb prepar'd for all; Genius which scarce infinity could bound, Lie cold in death, and quenched in the ground; That spark which promis'd to a flame to rise, More large than earth—just glimm'ring falls and dies; When scarce the laurels for the poet bloom, Their only office is to—deck his tomb; Our darken'd eyes must turn upon the ground, Our hearts afflicted with a piercing wound; Whilst Heav'n the tender sympathy approves, And owns the feelings that it gives and loves, Still must the smart afflict e'en breasts of steel, And those the best who most acutely feel. But see, celestial Truth with balmy wings, The clouds dispers'd, a healing cordial brings, Lifts the dark curtain of the dreary tomb, And darts a heav'nly ray 'mid endless gloom; Shows Sin and Death eternal captives bound, And Nature rising from her deadly wound; Forbids our constant tears for man to flow, And bids us calm behold our nature's woe; Shows that for good the plans of ill succeed, And calm a Gracchus sees, or Cato bleed; Here good and bad alike must yield to fate, But all requited in a future state; When wisdom, justice, mercy crown the plan, And Heav'n's mysterious paths are known to man; Soon fell Ambition waking now for good, Shall cease to rage and bathe her sword in blood: Unruly passions waking now his will, Shall own his sway who speaks—and all is still; The hardest heart shall humbly bow to Heav'n, And chang'd shall melt in love—and be forgiv'n. Such pleasing scenes Heav'ns gracious word displays, That pleasing light that guides the Christian's ways, Faith, Hope, and Joy, descending from above, Its noblest object, Universal Love; A God descending to repair our fall, To shed his blood to raise, to ransom all; And thus give worlds to know Heav'n's noblest plan, Is peace, and love and happiness to man, And all our woes and passions rightly scann'd, The gentle scourges of a Father's hand. Sons of Ambition, Cruelty and Lust, Behold your God, thus mercifully just; Tho' steel'd like Tigers in the Lybian sands, Or tawny Lions fed in savage lands, Who ever warring in th' ensanguin'd field, Have felt your hearts to love and mercy steel'd; Draw heav'nly feelings from a Saviour's love, And melting fix your hopes on realms above. Let he, whose eyeballs roll'd with wild despair, Long worn by guilt, nor dar'd to rise in pray'r, Melt in contrition at the glorious view, Let tears of love his pallid cheeks bedew; Behold the offer'd rest, vouchsaf'd by Heav'n, Fly to the cross—be humbled—and forgiv'n! Now raptur'd Nature seeks her rank again, For all are brothers here, and all are men; And from all nations, hasting to the skies, Let one eternal song of praise arise; Be banish'd sin and woe and guilt and fear, When Love shall twine unfading garlands here! Hark! 'tis the final trump, that rocks the ground, Thro' all infinity its notes resound; Now Nature pale thro' all her systems shakes, Death shudders, and the slumb'ring dust awakes; The grave gives up his countless myriads dead, And sea sends thousands from her azure bed; Ten thousand nations from the earth arise, And borne on dusky air ascend the skies; The clouds retire at Heav'n's almighty nod, And Death and Hell in chains obey their God; When from the darkness springs a seraph bright, And pours amid the gloom a flood of light; Sweeps systems, suns, and worlds, which feebly glare, Like glitt'ring sparkles from his waving hair; And while all sink before th' Almighty throne, And Nature heaves her last convulsive groan; He, while a rainbow veils his radiant head, In thunder speaking, fills the worlds with dread; Swears, while he heaves the oceans and the sky, “Here Time shall end his course, and Death shall die;” Then heav'n obeys, suns, systems die away, And sink dissolv'd in God's ætherial day, Absorb'd as dew-drops die before the sun, Their thousand glitt'ring stars absorb'd by one; Lost and forgotten—at th' Almighty nod, While myriads “tremble at the throne of God,” And while His righteous hand the thunders forms, To blast his foes with wrath's eternal storms; And angry Justice frowning by his side, On clouds of flame bids all his seraphs ride, To crush mankind, or with revengeful breath, To sweep them all to everlasting death; The Saviour comes, his wounded side displays, He pleads his blood—and wrath divine obeys; The storms are hush'd—and all the terrors fly, And Love sits ruling in the cloudless sky; The shouts of joy thro' all creation ring, And men and angels hallelujahs sing; Heav'n's deep foundations start with wild amaze, And worlds and suns resound with love and praise. Scenes rise on scenes of joy and glad surprise, New worlds, new heav'ns adorn the glorious skies; When the last flame that o'er the system hangs, Gives sweet oblivion to ten thousand pangs; One object, next their God, their minds employs— The long perspective of eternal joys. But stop my ardent mind—be humbled here, And sink in gratitude, in love and fear; Be this my object, hope, and end and pray'r, To tune my lyre to nobler measures there; Bid strains of heav'nly love and praises flow, Secure, when here this breast shall cease to glow; When Time shall hurl these worlds to Chaos' womb, And buried 'neath them find an endless tomb; Sink with the suns he conquer'd far away, And fall absorb'd in one eternal day. END OF THE FRAGMENTS. These have been selected almost wholly from the First Book.—They form, however, distinct Poems, and would be much abridged in a correct and connected form. HOSPITALITY. Lives there a man whose harden'd soul Ne'er felt soft Pity's kind control; Ne'er learn'd for others' joys to glow, Or shed the tear for others' woe; Whose spark of pure celestial fire Too soon was quench'd in base desire; And, once of pure celestial ray, The mind's best virtues die away. I bid him turn his tearless eye, Since Fancy's wing so far can fly; And view Arabia's desert plains, Where pure unfetter'd Nature reigns; 'Mid sultry wastes and deserts drear, The sand reflects affection's tear; And all the soul, from fetters free, Dissolves in Hospitality. Behold the friendless trav'ler roam These sandy deserts far from home; And see the deadly whirlwinds rise, Tremendous sweep the crimson skies; Heave flaming columns from the ground, And hurl them all the desert round; Then fall half smother'd on the sand— A stranger in a desert land. See on the torrid ground he lies, And scarcely lifts his feeble eyes; While pangs oppress his heaving breast, And death's dark cave his only rest; No wife, no child, no parent near, To raise his head, and wipe the tear; No pillow and no fountain by, His only refuge seems—to die. But when the whirlwind's rage is o'er, And peaceful lies the sandy shore; The savage smiling hastes to see, The beam of sweet tranquillity; The helpless stranger griev'd shall view, And tears his manly cheeks bedew; For him a sigh to Heav'n shall send, And own a brother and a friend. He softly raises then the head, His eyes the tears of sorrow shed; While friendly, yet discordant sounds, Pour balm in all his inward wounds; Bid once again the pulses glow, The veins with crimson torrents flow; The savage shall embrace a guest, Shall bid him welcome to his breast. At length the trav'ler glad shall rise, And casting round his grateful eyes; Shall call the savage nature's child, The guardian angel of the wild; And to the tent in peace convey'd, Shall welcome glad the sacred shade, And while he views each favor free, Bless purest Hospitality. ON THE TOMB OF AN INFANT. Thrice happy they, who early fall, Who scarcely draw their feeble breath, Just view the gloom that frowns on all, And sweetly sink in friendly death. No pain, no grief, no fears they know, Nor wasting sickness, want, nor care; Releas'd e'er yet they taste of woe, Nor bade life's thousand ills to bear. Ne'er doom'd remorse's pains to feel, In death their tears and sorrows cease, E'er vice their glowing hearts congeal, 'Tis their's to sweetly sleep in peace. As crystal dew-drops, pure and fair, Adorn the flow'rs at break of day, Drank by the sun, disperse in air, And shine on Iris' varied ray; So they as pure, as fair, as sweet, Just smile, and scarcely learn to sigh; Heav'n's favor then, with mildest heat, Transports them gently to the sky. They know not Death's dissolving pangs, Which softly set their spirits free; And while his friendly arrow hangs, Give life and immortality. Why then should flow affection's tear, Why crystal drops suffuse the eye? Why mourn him, innocent and dear, So lately lifted to the sky? While heav'nly cherubs watch the tomb, Where lies the dust in placid sleep; Why will ye mourn his early doom, Why bending o'er the chaplets weep? Celestial spirit! wipe the tear, Chase ev'ry gloomy thought away; Still love the breast that mourns thy bier, And cheer with thoughts of endless day. Soon shall thy body, fair and bright, Start from the tomb thy soul to meet, Rise to the realms of endless light, To bow before the mercy seat. Then seek thy Saviour's glowing breast, And raptur'd thy Redeemer view; His bosom oft young children prest, He liv'd—he died—he rose for you. There pillow'd on his bosom lie, When suns shall quench their lamps in night, When Time shall end and Nature die, And day shall shine with endless light. Then cleaving quick the balmy air, A cherub grown in endless day, Thy Saviour's noblest image wear, And in Hosannahs melt away. Yes, let thy parent dry her tears, And own the stroke in mercy giv'n; Taste comfort from thy early years, And bless the hand that snatch'd to Heav'n. A softer bed than she could give, The grave upon thy dust confers,— To die—is but more glad to live, And Jesus' bosom kind as her's.</field>
   </doc>
</add>