<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Burges, James Bland, Sir, 1752-1824</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Burges, James Bland, Sir, 1752-1824</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">burges james bland sir 1752 1824</field>
      <field name="author_text">Burges, James Bland, Sir, 1752-1824</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1780's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_2.1524.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1780</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:465560</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Heroic epistle from Serjeant Bradshaw ; in the Shades, to John Dunning, Esq. [by James Bland Burges</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Heroic epistle from Serjeant Bradshaw ; in the Shades, to John Dunning, Esq. [by James Bland Burges</field>
      <field name="title_facet">heroic epistle from serjeant bradshaw</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">heroic epistle from serjeant bradshaw</field>
      <field name="title_text">Heroic epistle from Serjeant Bradshaw ; in the Shades, to John Dunning, Esq. [by James Bland Burges</field>
      <field name="year_display">1780</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1780</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1780</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465560&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465560&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Burges, James Bland, Sir, 1752-1824&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;burges james bland sir 1752 1824&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Heroic epistle from Serjeant Bradshaw ; in the Shades, to John Dunning, Esq. [by James Bland Burges&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;heroic epistle from serjeant bradshaw&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1780&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1780&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Burges, James Bland, Sir&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1752&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1824&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Heroic epistle from Serjeant Bradshaw&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;in the Shades, to John Dunning, Esq. [by James Bland Burges]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for G. Wilkie [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1780&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0622&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;14 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Heroic epistle from Serjeant Bradshaw&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;in the Shades, to John Dunning, Esq. [by James Bland Burges]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 23 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">HEROIC EPISTLE FROM Serjeant BRADSHAW, in the Shades, TO JOHN DUNNING, Esq. Pride of the wondering Bar! whose potent art Can guide the judgment, or mislead the heart; Prince of Chicane! deep versed in every wile, To circumvent a Judge, and Mobs beguile; —Whom crowded Senates fondly list'ning hear, While Kings themselves thy declamation fear; Thee Bradshaw hails; his truest, dearest Son, Bradshaw, a Lawyer, was chosen President of the High Court of Justice. Even according to the principles which, in such a situation, he was perhaps obliged to adopt, his behaviour in general will appear not a little harsh and barbarous; but when we consider him as a subject, and one too of no high character, addressing himself to his unfortunate Sovereign, his style will be esteemed to the last degree audacious and insolent. Hume's History. And bids thee snatch the palm which once he won. What boots it, Dunning! with unceasing toil To rack thy brain, and waste thy midnight oil; To store thy mind with learning's dull parade, And all the tasteless jargon of the Trade, If not some object thou aspir'st to gain, To crown thy labors, and reward thy pain? Various the points to which Ambition tends, And hard the struggle which in Greatness ends; But when Success has crown'd our bold essay, When Fortune leads us on, and points the way, Labor grows pleasant, Disappointment flies, And Exultation joys to snatch the prize. Such as Thou now art, Dunning! I was once, Sought by each client, dreaded by each dunce: Nursed in the lumber of the legal school, I learn'd the art to make mankind my tool; Thence, step by step, to eminence I rose, Shifted the scale of Justice as I chose, 'Till last, disdaining meaner paths, I turn'd To politics, and as a patriot burn'd: Slave to dominion, tyrant in my soul, I felt my meanness, yet despised controul; Too proud my rightful Sovereign's power to own, With savage hand I pluck'd him from his throne; As a foul felon, dared my King to try, King Charles I. was impeached as a tyrant, traitor, murderer, and a public and implacable enemy to the Commonwealth. Hume's History. And judged anointed Majesty to die. On Thee Democracy now calls for aid, Pants to behold her flag again display'd, And marks in Thee another Bradshaw rise, With royal sacrifice to feast her eyes. Hail the glad moment, Dunning! spread the sail, And catch, while yet it blows, the fav'ring gale: Fame greater far than mine the deed shall crown, And hand to endless ages thy renown. What tho' my sentence doom'd my King to bleed? The Publisher is sensible it may appear inconsistent for Bradshaw to advise his pupil to tread in his steps, when the exigencies of the times differ so widely. But he trusts the Reader will consider, that consistency is by no means the characteristic of Patriots, either in their apprenticeship, or when they have set up for themselves: and that they will not scruple to acknowledge Don Quixote to have been a more thorough and redoubtable Knight Errant, than any of those whose examples he followed; as they were contented to love the mistress, or engage the giant, which fortune threw in their way; while he, who might have lived comfortably at home, chose to go out of his way, create a mistress for himself, and turn a windmill into a giant, that he might enjoy the satisfaction of knocking him on the head. It might not be improper for our modern Don Quixotes and their Squires to recollect, that he sometimes met with a cudgelling, and that Sancho was not the only Squire who may be tossed in a blanket. Charles gave pretence to justify the deed: Illegal taxes drain'd the murmuring land, Indignant Senates heard his harsh command; Prerogative advanced with dangerous stride, And grasp'd dominion which the laws denied. Resistance then was just.—But when the throne Has fix'd the legal power like it's own, Has ne'er infringed the rights of free debate, Or rose despotic o'er a falling State; How greater far thine art! how worthier praise! With fostering breath the fainting flame to raise, To govern crowds obedient to thy call, And shake St. James's, as I shook Whitehall! The iron is red hot, strike boldly now, And tear the circle from the regal brow; Pluck up each fence which guards the sacred tree, And nip the bud of blooming Majesty: Let no remorse invade thy purposed mind, But to one standard level all mankind. Fix'd in assurance, and with faction loud, Inculcate maxims on the gaping crowd Maxims are a kind of propositions, which have passed for principles of science; and which, being self-evident, have been by some supposed innate. Mr. Locke ventured to expel them from his philosophy, asserting, that disquisition and proof were the test of truth; and that whatever would not stand their touch, must be considered as base metal. Mr. Dunning reprobates this doctrine, and roundly asserts in his late famous speech, “That the facts he advanced were incontestible propositions of an abstract nature, which could not be discussed, truths self-evident, which it would be absurd to attempt to prove.” Let dire Court influence in each period roll, 'Till boding terrors rack the hearer's soul. Swear, you alone your country can redeem, And clothe with quaint device the glorious theme: New-fangled modes of eloquence invent, Where words supply the place of argument. If wrong your premises, increase the cry In just proportion to the falsity: Let abstract propositions stun the ear, Which strike at once, and free discussion fear; And truths, self-evident, which stand aloof, Abhor debate, and dread the touch of proof: Then argue stoutly, every doubt remove, And facts unproveable from Pamphlets prove. Methinks I see Thee, rising in thy place, Great Demagogue! Epitome of Grace! Display thy stores of elegance and ease, Till thrice three hems thy captive voice release: Made vocal now, it sounds the fearful tale, And runs thro' every note of faction's scale. Like his, who erst, with love of glory warm, Bellowed orations to the gathering storm, Thy voice grows stronger from opposing sound, While Order! Hear him! thro' the House resound: There Gordon reprobates a Popish Court; Here Luttrell weeps the loss of Milbourne Port; Burke's Fury blows her horn, shakes Snowdon's base, The Publisher is conscious that the Serjeant's poetry is by no means so poetical as the Orator's prose. He wishes to do the latter all imaginable justice, and therefore takes the liberty of transplanting the beautiful flowers from the Orator's hot-bed into his own garden.—“Since the invasion of King Edward, and the massacre of the Bards, there never was such a tumult, and alarm, and uproar through the region of Prestatyn. Snowdon shook to its base; Cader Edris was loosened from its foundations. The fury of litigious war blew her horn on the mountains. The rocks poured down their goatherds, and the deep caverns vomited out their miners. Every thing above ground, and every thing under ground, was in arms.” Barbara, Celarent, Darii, Ferio, Baralipton! And moves old Cader Edris from his place; Barre and Pitt to swell the concert join, And Bamber loudly calls his troops to dine; Laughters, unheard till now, complete the brawl, Some of the young Gentlemen of the House of Commons, who have had the good fortune to receive an University education, fortunately recollecting that definition of man, that he is animal risibile, have availed themselves of this noble faculty, to prove that they are of the human species, and to confound those arguments by laughter, which they could not confound by reason, to the very great edification of the lobby and galleries, and to the honour and satisfaction of their constituents. Thy obligato voice surmounts them all! Who is there, lost to every sense of shame? Who in superior vice has fix'd his fame? Or who, with empty purse, has passions yet, Pants for the stew, or stakes the darling bet? These are thy tools; these, moved with dextrous skill, Can raise a storm obedient to thy will: Poor servile Puppets, fit for every use, For treasons, riots, votes, or foul abuse: Most harmless in themselves; but well applied, May shake the basis of Old England's pride; With savage joy impel her headlong fate, And, more than Catilines, destroy a state. But, is there one whom real virtue fires, With purer thoughts and more refined desires, With temper'd warmth, and manly spirit bold, Whose honest palm ne'er itch'd for sordid gold; Whom titled Honor stamps with justice great; Whom Fortune marks for influence in the State; Whose nicer feelings make him shun a Court, The mart of principle, and knave's resort; But which alike restrain his cautious tread From those mad schools where Patriot boys are bred? Our phlegmatic forefathers were satisfied with enjoying the gifts of nature in their proper season; and accounted a length of beard no mean index of the understanding of the wearer. Our gardeners, however, now forestal our markets with forced cucumbers and asparagus, and beardless boys sprout up Patriots and Statesmen. If such there be, invite not him to join; Deem him unfit for purposes like thine. He ne'er, to aid a Democratic cause, Will stoop to falsehood, or pervert the laws; He nobly firm will stem the boist'rous flood, And with Carmarthen plan his Country's good. But thousands still remain; the reign of Vice Has stamp'd on every venal front its price: Some pant for honors, some for riches cry, And some for indolence and pensions sigh. Strike but with plastic hand the proper note, True to the touch, the nice-tuned Patriots vote; Pursue the charm, the mighty work is done, And madness ends what headstrong zeal begun. F?x, whose drain'd coffers no resource afford, Who lost his all at Brookes's magic board, Frantic beholds the fleeting moments fly, And dreads the prospect of futurity. Judgments, annuities, and bonds compose A terrible sum total of his woes; Christians and Jews, a long expecting band, In double file to seize the moment stand: A dissolution must complete his fate, And shift his lodging to the King's Bench-grate: For Patriots, steady in the smallest things, Hate the King's Bench because it is the King's. Him Faction claims her own; his pen, his tongue, Ring every change, so oft by Patriots rung. End how it will, he still must be a winner, Secure election, and procure a dinner. Great Poverty! 'tis thou compell'st the deed; 'Tis fit the hungry Senator should feed, Pick up enough to pay the Tavern's score, And purchase Freedom for seven winters more. Should Mr. F?x succeed in his present design upon the Westminster Freeholders, it is much to be apprehended, that he would soon forget in St. Stephen's Chapel what he said in Westminster Hall; and mistaking once more the House of Commons for Brookes's, cry out by a sort of natural impulse, Seven's the main. Behold another candidate for glory! Not less recorded in Rebellion's story: He quits his flock, his duty, and his God, And rules Associations with his nod: A second Horne, he grasps the wreath of Fame; A second Horne, admiring crowds proclaim! May the same fate attend the virtuous pair! The same reward their wondrous worth declare! Fame! swell thy loudest note, tell all the earth, Faction now gives a second Saviour birth; Repeat the strain, let all her Sons rejoice, And hail great Wyvill with exulting voice! Son of a Pensioner, whose hoary head Bows to the Minister for daily bread; A Footman's grandson now directs the State, While truckling Peers his high behests await. Fain would my feeble pen attempt to raise Some lasting monument to Norton's praise: But ah! too arduous and sublime I deem So great, so good, so virtuous a theme: Let him be herald of his own applause, And boast himself the Hero of the laws. What tho' Patrician riches he enjoys, Places for life, and pensions for his boys, The Public feels, therefore can hardly want reminding, that this Right Honourable Gentleman is in possession of many thousands per ann. Perhaps they may not so generally know, that his eldest son, the quondam Minister to the Swiss Cantons, finding his situation disagreeable, thought it expedient to return home; where he has enjoyed for these seven years a pension of 1000l. per ann. “till he can get something better.” Thankless he grumbles yet, aspires at more, And bites that generous hand he lick'd before. Proceed, great Speaker! stop the warm debate, Thy modest worth and high pretensions state; Produce thy witness to inforce thy tale, And swear 'tis true, when gentler methods fail. E'en I, grown grey in insolence, cry hush! And my cheek reddens, which ne'er knew a blush; While Satan smiles triumphantly to see His own ingratitude revived in thee. Tho' worth like thine on earth be ill-repaid, Here, be assured, a difference will be made; Here shalt thou flourish, here direct the helm, The Lord Chief Justice of th'infernal Realm. Such are the tools thy glorious work to form, To sweep the billows, while thou rulest the storm: Like winds broke loose, all obstacles they brave, Rush o'er the plain, or swell the angry wave; Deform with rude confusion Nature's face, And with one ruin mark their direful trace; Their mighty Ruler Thou, with potent sway, To urge their fury, and direct their way. Proceed then, Dunning! in thy bold career, Make Premiers tremble, and their Masters fear: For thee shall Fame her noblest wreaths entwine, In Faction's temple foremost shalt thou shine, And future Humes shall dignify thy pains, And hang thee up in strong historic chains. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>