<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Blundeville, Thomas</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Blundeville, Thomas</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">blundeville thomas</field>
      <field name="author_text">Blundeville, Thomas</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">16th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.0055.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1561</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:463013</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Three morall Treatises ; no lesse pleasaunt than necessary for all men to reade, whereof the one is called the Learned Prince, the other the Fruites of Foes, the thyrde the Porte of rest [by Thomas Blundeville</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">Three morall Treatises ; no lesse pleasaunt than necessary for all men to reade, whereof the one is called the Learned Prince, the other the Fruites of Foes, the thyrde the Porte of rest [by Thomas Blundeville</field>
      <field name="title_facet">three morall treatises</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">three morall treatises</field>
      <field name="title_text">Three morall Treatises ; no lesse pleasaunt than necessary for all men to reade, whereof the one is called the Learned Prince, the other the Fruites of Foes, the thyrde the Porte of rest [by Thomas Blundeville</field>
      <field name="year_display">1561</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1561</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1561</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463013&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463013&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Blundeville, Thomas&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;blundeville thomas&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Three morall Treatises ; no lesse pleasaunt than necessary for all men to reade, whereof the one is called the Learned Prince, the other the Fruites of Foes, the thyrde the Porte of rest [by Thomas Blundeville&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;three morall treatises&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1561&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1561&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Blundeville, Thomas&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Three morall Treatises&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;no lesse pleasaunt than necessary for all men to reade, whereof the one is called the Learned Prince, the other the Fruites of Foes, the thyrde the Porte of rest [by Thomas Blundeville]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Imprynted ... by Wyllyam Seres [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1561&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0464&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;[140] p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Three morall Treatises&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;no lesse pleasaunt than necessary for all men to reade, whereof the one is called the Learned Prince, the other the Fruites of Foes, the thyrde the Porte of rest [by Thomas Blundeville]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 112 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To the Queenes highnes Of all the bookes that euer Plutarke wrote, More mete is none, when they haue time &amp; space, For Prynces all to rede and well to note: Then this, whiche heare I offre to your grace. For lyke as he, the good doth iustly praise, The euill their faultes, so, plainlye dothe he tell, And whilst he doth consider both their wayes: He shewes wherein a Prince ought most texcell. That is to saye in learnynge, wytte, and skill, To tame affectes, and folowe reasons lore, Whose steppes doe fle the wayes of froward will: And treades the pathes of iustice euermore. And though this Boke, your highnes oft hath redde, In Grekyshe prose as Plutarke did it wright: My rurall muse, for that, yeat, had no dredde In Englysh verse, agayne the same tendight. Presuminge of the fauor whyche she fownde, When that she sange, what fruites of foes might ryse And that your grace, gaue eare vnto the sownde Of suche rude ryme, as she did then deuyse. Wherfore now harke my liege and souraigne Quene What Plutarke sayeth of Prynces good and badde Who yf he were alyue to Iudge: I wene, Of all the Quenes in honour to be had, Your learninge, and your vertues pondred well, He would your grace, should onely beare the bell. Your maiesties most humble Subiecte Thomas Blondeuille. The learned Prynce. The Cyrens once made greate request, That Plato wolde vouchsafe to wright such lawes, as he for th? thought best, Their state therby, to rule vpright. But Plato tho, dyd cleane refuse, So hard a thynge to take in hande, Who knewe, they woulde good lawes abuse Which had such welth within their lande. For nothing is more hard tentreate, More proude, ne worse to deale wythall, Than is that man, in wealthye state Which thinkes to stande, and fearth no fall. Wherfore it is to harde for suche As others rule, and beare the swaye, To suffer lawes to rule to muche, Lest than, their power should sone decaye. For reason as their Cheffe to take, They doe abhorre: lest Princely might, They should then forced be to make A slaue: to Iustice trueth and ryght. As men alas which doe not knowe, What Sheopony the Spartan duke Sayd to his wife with voyce full lowe, When she obiected this rebuke. For whereas he dyd fyrst of all To royall power, Tribunos adde: She sayd thou bryngst thy Sonne, in thrall, To leaue lesse powre, then thou hast hadde. No rather yet, then aunswerde he I shall hym leaue so muche the more For nowe his powre shall stronger be Then euer myne was heretofore. And thoughe this Prynce hymselfe depryud Of that whiche he to geue thought good: As thoughe small brookes he had deryud Out of a goulffe, or flowinge floud: Remyttynge yet the riguor greate Of royall powre whiche none can beare He dyd auoyde all enuyouse hate: And leadde his lyfe cleane out of feare. Yf reason gotte by wysedomes lore Assist the Prynce: she gardes his health, For ryddynge thill awaye before She leaues the good tencrease his wealth. But many Kynges that folyshe are To masters rude that karue in stone And haue no arte, I may compare So lytle diffrence is or none. For they their Images do Iudge Then best to make: when that they shape them arms &amp; thighes with legges most hudge and ougly mouthes full wyde to gape. Unprudent kinges euyn so I saye By frowning lokes, bigge voyce, disdayne, and keping closse in, all the daye, Great maiestye do thinke tattaine. Like Images in outward showe UUhich do pretend some goodly one Yeat inwardlye if you wyll knowe they onely are but earth or stone. In one thinge yeat they disagree. For Images throughe that their waight and heauy poyse, fast stablisht bee: Ne do they moue but stande vp straight. UUhere foolishe kynges vntaught I saye For that within they are not sounde Ne truly waide they swarue and swaye and oftimes fall vnto the grounde. For why vnles to place thou wylt In suer wise, thy Principall: UUhat euer shall theron be buylt: In breffe must nedes to ruyne fall. But as the Craftsman should forsee His rule be right and trulye made UUithout all fault before that hee In any woorke do further wade: A Prince likewise ought first to kno Hymselfe to rule and rightlye guyde And then to frame his subiectes so As in good rule they may abyde. For whye it is a thinge vnmete A feble man to take in hande to set vp others on their fete UUhen he himselfe can scantly stande. Ne likewise can it decente be That he should teache whiche hath no skill Or order men in eche degre In whom doth raigne disorder still. Ne should that man commaunde of right UUhich reasons rule doth not obaye Though fooles him count of greatest mighte UUhich subiecte is no kynde of waye. The kynge of Perce, did all men take To be hys slaues and lyue in thrall His wife excepte whom he should make His will tobaye, aboue them all. But some perhappes would nowe demaunde QuestionUUho ought to rule a Prynce or Kynge? answere.The lawe as Quene, who doth commaunde Both Gods and men, as Poets synge. I meane not that whiche is exprest, In bokes of paper, wodde, or stone, But reason graft within his brest, To guyde his doinges euerychone. The Kynge of Pearce was wont to haue A chamberlane whome day by day UUh? mornyng came he strayght charg gaue That he to him these wordes shoulde saye. Aryse thou Kynge and slepe no more But carefull be to do ryght sone Suche nedefull thynges as heretofore Mesoromasdes woulde haue done. But Kynges that wyse and learned are Haue alwayes one within theyr mynde More prompt to tel them of theyr care Then any man that they can fynde, Polemon sayde that Cupyde was A seruaunt to the Goddes aboue From place to place with spede to passe To seke what dyd yonge laddes behoue. But one more rightly yet might saye Gods ministers that Prynces bee To take the charge of men alwaye And eke their wealth to well forsee. That like as God do lette them haue Those godly giftes which they enioye Some part euyn so they still shoulde saue And wiselye ought the rest temploye. UUe see the ample heauen howe he, UUith liquid armes do thearth embrace: UUho first sent downe the sedes whiche she UUith fruit bringes forth in euery place. Some growe by raine, and some by winde, By glittringe starres some norissht are And some the Moone wyth moystures kinde To foster vppe, hath onelye care. And finallye the louelye Sonne UUhose shyning beames adorneth all His frendly course doth dayly ronne And shewes like loue to great and small. These godly gyftes yeat can we not Ne rightlye vse ne well enioy Onles also it be oure lot To haue a Prynce Iustice and Ioy. For Iustice is of lawe the ende And lawe the Prynces woorke I saye The Prynce gods lykenes doth portende UUho ouer all muste beare the swaye. And neadith not the skilfull hande Of Phidias, or Policlette, Of Miron eke or suche lyke bande Of those that Carue and colours sette. For he himselfe by vertue canne Hymselfe to God moste lyke descrye An Image pleasinge eurye manne And noble to beholde with eye. And lyke as God in heauen aboue The shyninge Sonne and Moone doth place In goodliest wise as beste behoue To shewe his shape and lyuelye grace: Suche is that Prynce within his lande UUhych fearinge God, maintayneth ryght, And reasons rule doth vnderstande, UUherin consistes his porte and might. And not in Scepter, or in Crowne, In thunder bolt, or glyttringe swerde, wherby some thinke tobteyne renowne Synce than, they shoulde be greatlye ferde. UUheras in dede, for that they seme That none to them maye haue accesse: They are enuied, and wise men deme Suche porte to be greate foolishnesse. For God offended is wyth those His thundringe power that imitates: But he delightes in suche as chose In clemency to be hys mates. And doth promote them more and more And of his owne benignytye: Doth make them partners of his lore Of iustyce, trueth, and equitye. UUhiche thinges in dede are more deuyne Than fyar, light, or phebus course, Than starres that rise or downe declyne Ye endles life it selfe, is worse. For why longe life is not the cause That God moste happy counted is But prince of vertue is the clause UUheron dependeth all his blis. UUhen Alexander sorye was For Clytos death whome he had slayne: Then Anaxarke, suche wofull cas To mittigate: to hym gan sayne. To Clito hapt but Iustice tho, UUhich doth assiste the goddes alway That what soeuer Princes do, Should rightfull seme without denaye. UUhich sayinge was ne right, ne good, For where the kinge bewaild his cryme: This semd to egge him in lyke moode, To do like act an other tyme. But if for men it lawfull were Such thinges texamyne as them liste: Full quickly then, it would appeare That Iustice doth not Ioue assiste. For Iustyce euyn it selfe to be, Almightye Ioue we ought to take: A lawe of most antiquitye UUhich neuer dyd the trueth forsake. The old men also plainlye saye It passeth Ioue his poure and might UUhen ladye Iustice is awaye: A kyngdome for to rule vpright. UUho as Hesyode hath vs tought A virgyn is immaculate, A shamefast maide, which neuer wrought But modestlye wyth eurye state. And hereof kinges surnamed are Right reuerent, and dredefull aye: For those in whome doth dwel least feare, Ought to be feared moste I saye. But it behoues muche more a kynge To feare to do, then suffer ille, For of the one the other sprynge, So do so haue is Iustice wille. This Princely feare a Prynce lykewyse Should alwayes haue: Unwares that lest To hym, for lacke of carefull eyes: UUith wronges his subiectes be opprest. For so the dogges that watche the folde UUhen they the cruell wolfe do heare: Not for themselues which are full bolde, But for their charge haue onely feare. Epamynond the Theban knight His subiectes tendinge feastes and playe UUould all alone both day and night Kepe watche and warde and oftymes saye, That he dyd aye lyue soberlye And watchfull was to that intente That others myght more quyetlye Be dronke, and slepe, as they were bente. UUhen Cezar hadde at vesque towne, to Cato yeuen the ouerthro: the reste vnslayne, then Cato downe Did call: vnto the sea to go. And hauinge sene them safelye shipte and wysht them well to passe the sea: as one with fewer cares beclipte, Retourned home himselfe to slea. By which ensample Cato heare, Doth teache all Princes that be wise, Of what, they should haue greatest feare, And what againe, they should despise. But on the other part beholde Clearchus cruell kinge of Ponte, Howe lyke a Serpente layde in folde In chest closse shut to slepe was wonte. Full lyke Taristodeme therefore UUho in his dyninge chamber hadde A closette with a fallynge dore And eke with beddynge fynelye cladde. UUherin his concupyne and he UUere wont all nyght to take their rest, And to thintente that none should se Ne come to vexe them in their nest: The mother of the damsell should The stayer cleane from thence remoue And set it, theare against they would come downe next mornynge from aboue. Howe moch thynke you would this man flee A Palays, Courte, or Feastynge place UUhich of hys chamber as you see A prison made to kepe his grace. Thus trew kynges haue no feare in dede But aye for those, on whom they raigne: But Tyrantes for theym selues haue drede Lest for their vice they shoulde be slaine. The greater powre, the greater feare, The more to rule, that they obtayne: The more as foes to them appeare, UUherby they growe in more disdayne. UUyth matter apt all shapes to take And subiect aye to sondry chaunge Of god some would a mixture make and hyde hym theare which is full straunge. But Plato sayith God dwelles aboue And there fast fixt in holy sawes: From trueth he neuer doth remoue Ne swarues from natures stedfast lawes. And as in heauen lyke to a glasse The sonne his shape doth represente: In earth, the light of Iustyce was By hym ordeynd: for lyke intente. UUhich shape all wyse and happy men To counterfete employe theyr payne Full busuly wyth wysdomes pen The chefeste blis therby tattaine. But nothing can this habit brede In vs so sone, as reasons lore Got out of wysdoms schole in dede: To guyde our doynges euer more UUhen Alexander hadde well tryde The prompt wytte of Diogenes And sene his stoutnes great besyde: He marueyled, and sayde, doutles: If I not Alexander were, I woulde become diogenes, As one that vertue woulde fayne leare: But princely powre dyd hym oppresse. UUhich would not graunt him time tapply? The thinge so muche estemed aye For lacke whereof he did enuy? The Cinickes scrippe, and pore araye. UUherewith he sawe the Cinicke made At all assayes more stronge and stoute: Than he hymselfe when to inuade Of horse and men had greatest route. Thus in desiar and good will Diogenes the kinge might be And yeat in dede remayning still In princelye state and highe degre. Yea, he, more nede had in this cas To be diogenes aryght: In that he Alexander was An emprour great of powre and might. UUho hadde in fortunes seas to stryue UUith cruell stormes and rockes besyde UUheron his shippe might easlye dryue Onles he had the better guyde. For priuate men of lowe degre That others can offende no waye Thoughe they taffectes oft subiect be Their greues yeat are but dreams I saye. But whereas powre is ioynd vnto Euill ordred life, thear thinke it true That such affectes will cause also Great grefe in dede for to ensewe. The chefest fruit that Dionise Dyd of his empyre take: it was, (He sayde) what he dyd than deuise, UUith spede to haue it brought to passe. A thyng most peryllouse therfore It is, vndecent thynges to wyll: UUhen he that wylleth, euermore Hath powre, the same for to fulfyll. For powre doth malice quickly moue, UUith euyll affectes the mynd to streke As enuy, wrath, aduowtry, loue, Mens goodes also, and lyues to seke. And then the worde nys soner sayde, But wo to hym that is suspect Toffende in that to hym is layde, For sentence there, must take effect. Of nature, such as searchers be: Do hold that after thunder clapp The lyghtnyng coms, yeat do we se The same before we heare the rapp. The bludd lykewyse before the wound To vs most commonly appeares: For sight doth mete the light, wheare sound Is fayne to come euin to our eares. In kyngdoms so, some men we fynde Taue suffred care, thaccused were And sentence yeuen to wrath inclynde Before due profe of cryme appeare. For wrath nought hable is twithstand The powre of malice when she list, As is the anker fixt in sande UUhich can the cruell sea resist. Onles that reason with her wayght Presse downe such powre, and kynges abyde To marke the sonne, in greatest hayght Howe he hymselfe doth wysly guyde. For when he mownted is aloft To Cancers ryng, he semes to stay, In that he goeth so fayre and soft UUherby he doth assure his way. But this by dayly profe we knowe UUhere powre and malyce do abyde: There, malyce nedes, her selfe must showe, And can her face no long tyme hyde. If those that haue the fallyng yll At any tyme take colde I say, They can not stand but stagger styll UUhich playnely doth theyr grefe bewray. Euyn so thunlearned sort you see UUhen fortune chaunce them to addresse To honor, wealth, and hyghe degree, They shewe full sone their folishnesse. For why no soner vppe, but lo They readye are agayne to fall, For fortunes whele they do not kno UUhich turneth rounde as doth the ball. To trye if that an emptye potte Be sound or cracked anye wheare Let fill the same, and eurye plotte That faultye is will sone appeare. Euyn so corrupted myndes that are Not hable princelye power tabyde, To broken pottes I may compare That flowe with anger wrath and pride. But why should these thinges heare besayde Sithe lesser crymes and faultes most small To noble Prynces haue ben layde By suche as haue them noted all. To Cymon wyne, to Scipio Much slepe as faultes obiected weare: Lucullus noted was also For that he loued costly cheare. Howe happye than is Britan lande UUhich dothe enioye so noble a Quene As reasons rule doth vnderstande UUherby no vyce in her is sene. For why she fearith God aboue UUhose lawe is written in her harte So good affectes in her to moue As wicked thoughtes haue there no parte. A wyse and learned Quene is she And wholly bent to maintaine right, Ne wrathfull tyrante can she be In clemencye which doth delyght. UUho sekes her lawes and ordinaunce To execute with Iustyce aye All vertuous men she doth auaunce And chaste the proude that nill obaye. Of speche full meke, and mylde of cheare To whome all poore men haue accesse, UUhose plaintes she willinge is to heare And eke their wronges for to redresse. UUhat care she hath her subiectes all And Realme to make both riche and stronge By dedes appeare it doth and shall In wordes I nede not to be longe, But only wysshe and dayly craue Of god to graunt, that ouer vs Long tyme of raigne her bygones haue UUhich is so good and gracious. Finis. The fruytes of Foes. Newly corrected and cleansed of manye faultes escaped in the former printing. Anno domini. M.D.LXI. Roger Ascham Secretory to the Queenes maiestie, for the latin tongue, in praise of the booke. Of English bokes, as I could find, I haue perused many one: Yet so wel done vnto my mind, As this is, yet haue I fo?d none The woordes of matter here doe rise, So fitly and so naturally, As heart can wishe or witte deuise In my conceit and fantasie. The woordes well chosen and well sette, Doe bryng suche light vnto the sense: As if I lackt I woulde not lette, To bye this booke for forty pense. To the Queenes highnes Such Newyeres giftes as most m? do prepare To geue your grace, it passeth far my powre. For golde ne pearle, ne such lyke costly ware, Can I possesse: sith fortune styll doth lowre. As she on me hath hereto euer done, UUhich had me brought at length to great distresse But that the hope, which in your grace alone I alwayes fixt: my griefes did oft redresse. UUhich hope I say, euen now doth make me bolde Your royall state, with this so small a queyre For to present: yea more, that hope me tolde, From this day forth, I should no more dispeire. For loe, (saith she) the golden worlde at hande, And Iustice raignes again within this lande. Your maiesties most humble seruant. Thomas Blundeuille. The fruites of Foes. By Plutarks lore of mortal foes, Learne ye y? list some fruit to take, For fruits inough, he doth discloes UUherof I wil, you partners make In olde time past, m? only sought, The hurtfull beastes, their foes to kyll, Of other spoyle, they nothyng thought, But so to saue themselues from ill. But others came then afterwarde, UUhose sleight was such, those beastes to slay: As they thereto had small regarde, Except they myght obtaine some pray. Their fleshe to eate, they vsde therfore, And with their wolle, themselues to cladde, Their milke and galle they kept in store: To heale suche griefes, as sicke men hadde. And of their hydes, they harnes made, Themselues to arme, on euery syde: That they might aye in safety wade Against all force, that might betyde. Loe thus by foes, no hurt to take, It did not them at all suffise, Except they might such great gaine make: As they themselues could best deuise. If thou therfore, without some hate, Here cannot liue in quiet rest: Inuent some way of such debate, To leaue the worst, and take the best. No tylman can by arte deuise, Eche tree to spoyle, of nature wilde: Nor huntsman eke, be he right wise, Can tame eche beast, that roons in fyelde. UUherfore they haue right wisely founde, The meane tapply such beast and tree, To other vse, which doth redounde, Unto their great commoditee. The water of the sea, we see, Is salte, and hath vpleasante taste: Yet cheffly thence, I say haue wee, The fishe, our foode, which we do waste. Yea, more then that, thinges of great price, The shipps by sea to vs do brynge, Both pleasant silke, and holsome spice, And many other nedefull thinge. The brightnes of the flaminge fire, Appearing in the Satirs sight: Straight waies, so kindled his desire, That it timbrace, he toke delight. Prometheus, then loude can crie, Beware he saide imbrace none suche, For that it hath the propertie: To burne all those, that doth it tuche. It was not made to colle, and kisse, But heate, and light, alwaies to yelde: The very meane also it is: UUhereby craftes men, their artes doe welde. Hereby therfore, we may perceiue, That of our foe right perilous, In this our lyfe we may receiue, Suche fruites as be commodious. For though some thynges be very ill, To those, to whom they appertaine, Yet vsde they may be, with suche skyll: As losse shall easily turne to gaine. As loe for proofe, some sickly corse For easementes sake, sekes quiet rest. UUhere some againe, to win their force, To trauell oft, do thinke it best. Diogenes and Crates chaunce, Do well declare, how banishmentes And losse of goodes, doe some auaunce To knowledge great, which them contentes. UUhen Zeno heard, that tempestes gret, In raginge sea, his ship had lost: He mourned not ne yet did fret, But made as though it lytle cost And thus gan say, to fortune tho, Howe dearely doest thou me entreate: Me thus to force, againe to go, In wysedoms schoole, to fynde a seate. Some beastes we see, such stomakes haue As serpentes cause full soone disgeast, Both woode and stone, they also craue Suche kynde of foode, them hurteth least. But some againe, so deinty bene That they oft loth, the finest bredde, And purest wine, that can be sene: UUherwith they myght be alwayes fedde. Euen so fares fooles, that frendship ioyes, Do aye destroye, but to the wyse: Of hatefull strife and spightfull toyes, Great wealth, and gaine, dothe oft aryse. UUherefore, me thinkes, where in thy foe Doth seme to geue the greatest grief: Thou mayst thereof, receiue also Muche greater gayne to thy reliefe. And if thou aske, how that may be, I saye to thee, consider then, UUhat care he hath, thy workes to se, UUith whom, to whom, what, where, &amp; when. UUith Linx his eyes, he doth beholde, Thy lyfe, thy frende, and seruaunte aye, Thy dedes, and thoughtes right manifolde, Thy name to harme, if that he maye. Thys profyt eke, by foes we haue Our frendes oft tymes, we doe not minde, They may be sick, and layde in graue, Unwares to vs, lyke men vnkinde. But of oure foe, both day and night UUe thinke and dreame, such is our choyse, His grief, or bane, to haue in sight: UUhich onely doth, our mindes reioyce. If thou be sick, or much in det, Falne out with wife, with mayde, or man, Yea, no mishap can thee beset: But, it, thy foes, eft sone knowe can. Lyke rauening birdes, that putryd fleshe, And not the sounde, far of can smell, So they thy illes, to spye be freshe, And all thy griefes, with eye full fell. UUhat greater gaine may be than this, Hereby to learne, in suche a sort Our life to leade, as none there is: That ill therof may once report. For as sicke men that wary be, In meates and drinkes, that may offende: In wordes and dedes, euen so doe we Take hede that they the best pretende. UUherby we come in schole to dwell, Of customes good, and excellent, For reason rules thaffections fell: UUherto our myndes be alwaies bent. Yea, through long time, and exercyse, It bredes in vs, such stedfastnes: That learne we can none other guise, But aye to liue in holynes. The townes that long haue bene beset, UUith enmies stout on euery side: Haue derely learnde, by losses gret, To kepe good watche in euery tide. And eke their lawes and ordinaunce, To execute with iustice aye The humble sort for to aduaunce: The proude to chast, that nyll obay. Euen so fare those that forced bee, Through spightfull foes, both negligence, And slouthfulnes alwaies to flee UUhereby they liue without offence. For custome shall them bring with spede, To suche a trade of doyng well, That if they goe as reason lede: In errour none, they can long dwell. UUhen minstrels of one sute and bande In open place doe musicke make: UUithout all feare, and care they stande, And to their play, no hede doe take. But when their skyll, they doe compare UUith straungers, that professe lyke art: They sharpe their wittes, and haue great care, That euery one may doe his part. Of instrumentes, and eke of stringes, They seke where they maye haue best choyce, And oft doe proue, how with suche thinges May best agree, both hande and voice. Euen so it fares with him, whose lyfe And honour bothe, muche spighted is By those that sekes, with hatefull strife Hys thinges to blame that be amis. Full ware is he in busines, And eke foresees therof the ende, For when we erre: malitiousnes Regardes the foe, more than the frende. UUhen Carthage was all torne and rent, And Greece subdude, the Romaines thought Themselues full safe, their foes thus shent, They were all gladde, and feared nought. But Scipio did then repreue, In perill most be we (quoth he) UUhen no foe is, that may vs greue, UUhose feare should make vs slouth to fle, One asked once Diogenes How he might best reuenged bee Of all his foes, both more and les, That from all care he mighte be free. Diogenes right wisely tho To him gan saye, no dent of knife Can greue so much thy cruell fo: As for to see thy perfit lyfe. UUhat grudge, what griefe, the common sort Conceiues to see, the goodly horse And coursing dogges, which but for sport, To kepe: their fees do litle force. UUhat playntes, what sighthes, &amp; dolfull sownds Their spightfull breastes to heauen do yelde, To see their pleasant garden growndes, Or store of corne to growe in fielde. How much more then, would they lament, To see their foe to be full iuste? In worde and dede, to vertue bent, Of sober life, and free from lust. And eke to budde out of his brest, That fraighted is, with holynes Such domes, and councels, as are best, To ease eche heart in heauynes. The tonges of them, that conquerde bee, Are bounde from speache, saith Pindarus: And yet these wordes, as you shall see, To all be not approbrious. But only do suche men reproue, As nedes must yelde, vnto their foes, In all those vertues, that behoue, A perfit man for to disclose. For suche thinges saith Dimosthenes Do binde the tonge in torment aye, And stoppes the mouth of them doutles That thinkes more ill, then they dare saye. Enforce to shewe thy selfe therfore, Sith in thy power it doth consist: Thy lyfe to guide by vertues lore, Their wicked tonges for to resist. And when thou wouldst faine put thy foe, In great dispaire, take not the waye By haynous wordes, as others doe, His name to persecute I saye. Ne beastly man, ne filthy foole Doe thou hym call, but rather seke, In suche a sort thy selfe to schoole, That none thy doynges maye misleke. Be true thy selfe, in woorde and dede Be modest styll, and chast also Shewe curtesy in tyme of nede To suche as haue with thee to do. And if it shoulde so come to passe, That nedes, thy foe thou must reproue For any fault: yet in that case, See first thy selfe thou doe wel proue. Examine eke with diligence, Thine in ward partes if they be free, From all suche vice and negligence: as in thy foe, thou semste to see. For els perhaps thou maist geue cause, To some ill tonge, that standes thee by: UUith voyce full soft, to saye this clause, Recited in a Tragedie. Beholde I saye this foolishe man, That takes in hande the woundes to cure Of other men: and yet nought can His owne redresse, I you assure. But if he call thee ignoraunt, Learne wisedome then by industrie Thy faynty heart, if he doe taunt Let stoutnes shew thou wilt not flie. If he thee checke for lecherie, Auoide eche sparke of filthines, Out of thy breast full spedilie, and learne to liue in holines. More foule or grieuous nothing is Then for a man suche faultes to checke As all the shame therof ywis Againe shall turne vpon his necke. For as rebounde of glittering light, The feble sight doth moste offende: Euen so most grieuous is the spight, UUhich trueth beates back, fr? whence it wende. The mistie cloudes vnto the winde, that blowes Northeast, doe aye resort, The wicked life euen so we fynde To her doth drawe all ill report. If any man in Platoes sight Had vilye done, straight thence would he, And softly say, may any wight, Such one as he, me force to be? But when thou haste with wordes of ire Thy foe yprict, for his offence: Beholde thy self, and eke desire Thy lyfe tamende, with diligence. Of spightfull wordes so shalt thou drawe Muche fruite, to thy greate welth and gaine Though some it thinke, ne right ne lawe, To vse such wordes, of great disdayne. The common sort, do laughe, and smyle, UUhen any balde or crooked man, Do others taunt, and oft reuyle, For such defectes, as themselues han. UUhat greater scorne, then woulde it bee, If thou suche faultes shouldst reprehende: As one with worse, might aunswer thee UUhich thou in no wyse couldst defende. As once, did Leo Bizantine, UUhen one that had a crooked backe, Hym cast in teeth his bleared eyne alas (quoth he) this is no lacke. A humaine thing this is, I say, But why alas canst not espye: Howe on thy backe thou bearest alway, That goddesse fell, dame Nemesye? Nemesis Goddesse reuenge. Aduouterer, see none thou call UUhilst fouler lust in thee dothe raigne: Ne yet reproue the prodigall, If auarice thy lyfe dothe staine. Alemeon when he did reuile, Adrastus, king: of kin thou art (Quoth he) vnto that woman vile: UUhiche carft with knife, her husbandes hart. Adrastus then, him aunswerd loe, UUith that whiche did him touche at quicke Suche beastly wrathe in thee did floe Thy dame to slea ere she were sicke. UUhen Dyonise did Crassus skorne, For that he wailde, his Lampreys cas, By crewell death, then all forlorne, UUhiche in his ponde, long fostred was. Then Crassus said, rebuke not mee Sith that from thee no teares did fall The death to see, of thy wiues three Nor felst no grief, therby at all. UUho so delightes to checke or taunt, No rybalde, knaue, or foole must bee: UUith bragging woordes, hymself to vaunt, But rather should from vyce be free. UUherfore, none semes more bound tobay, Apollos woorde (thine own self know:) Then those that are most prompt alway To rayle, to iest, to mocke, and mowe. For hap, it may, saith Sophocles, That whilst they taunt, as them likes best: To them again, is said doubtles: That whiche to heare, they couet lest. In tauntyng thus our foes, we finde No litle fruit, but more we gaine, UUhen they likewise, with wordes vnkinde, Our faultes to taunt, do not refraine. Anthistines said well therfore, That lyfe, in safety to encloes Man ought to haue alwaies in store: Right perfit frendes, or bitter foes. For faithfull frendes wyll vs reforme UUhen that we erre: our foes againe UUyll so muche rayle, and out of forme, That nedes from vyce, we must abstaine. But syth that now true frendship is Of free speche spoylde, and flattry bent To chatte, and prate of thynges amysse Good counsels eke must nedes all stent. And therefore nothing now remaines For vs to doe: but to abide, The trueth to heare, to our great paynes, By spightfull foes, that nought wyll hyde. UUhen Telephus his festred wounde Could no wise heale: with thenmies speare UUhich first him hurt louelyfe, him bound, To launce the same without all feare. Euen so must they of force agree To byde reprofe of spightful foes: UUhere wanteth frendes their faultes to see, And frankly wyll thesame disclose. Nor in this case, we should behold Our foes intent, when they so rayle, But if such thinges as they haue tolde, Be true in vs, or els doe fayle. Prothemeus of Thessalie A grieuous sore had in his breast: UUhiche one that was his enemie, Did cure by chaunce againste his heast. For when he thought to haue him slain, By dent of sword he brake the sore, UUhich festred was to his great pain, And so hym helde for euermore. Euen so full oft it comes to passe, That wordes yspoke for ill intent, Do greatly helpe, some one that was His fault tamend: ful negligent. But most men when they are reuilde Haue no regarde, if with such vice, As is them tolde, they be defilde: But sekes reuenge, by lyke aduice. UUhere reason would that suche as are By foes rebukte, for their offence: Should afterward thereof beware, And seke redresse with diligence. Yea, more then that, without desart, Though they vs check, for any thing: To seke yet then, it is our part, The cause wherof the same did spring. And eke to feare lest eare we thought, UUe haue the same or such lyke don For one suspect, hath many brought To shame, and great derision. As thargiue kyng sir Lacydes, Because he was so nice of gate And eke his heere would finely dresse UUith finger aye, was poynted ate. And cald a man effeminat, The lyke to Pompey dyd befall, For that he vsde his hedde to scrat: UUhen he no hurt, dyd thinke at all. For none did more then he, despyse Such wanton lust and tendernes, UUho aye was bent to enterprise: Thynges great of weight and hardines. So Crassus eke to tell you plaine, Suspected was through suche lyke tale, For that he did as some men fayne, Frequent full oft, a maide vestale. And yet in dede his connyng nas, For any hurt or ill intent: But certain land to bye, in cas, He could obtayne her free concent, Posthumia through mirth and playe, And hauntyng oft without respect Mens company, her name I saye UUith infamy dyd sore infect. For whiche she cited was tappere, As one that had in lecherie: Abusde her selfe, with kinsfolkes nere: And yet she dyd no villany. UUhom though that Spurius, whiche hight Manutius, then bishop hye, Of that ill fame, did cleane acquight, He warnde her yet thus fatherly. Posthumia, sith that thou haste, In holy workes, thy lyfe aye ledde, Lest wanton talke, thy name may waste I counsell thee haue lykewyse dredde. Themistocles, none ill had wrought, UUhen he so often letters sent: To Pawsanye, yet some folkes thought To traye the realme, was his intent. If any man thee charge therefore, UUith thynges vntrue in euery part, Be negligent no whit the more, Nor lightly let them from thee start. But take good hede, lest thou or thyne, Hath geuen some cause, of suche ill fame, UUhiche once founde out, thy selfe enclyne, To learne, thencefoorth to flee the same. For such ill happes as comes vnwares Do oft times teache, what is for vs, Most mete to doe, in such lyke cares, As Merop saith in writing thus. UUhen fortune did me cleane depriue Of that, whiche I estemed most: To muche more wit I did arriue Albeit full dere it did me cost. By maisters then of cheaper price UUhiche be our foes, why should we steke In thynges vnknowen to take aduyce, UUhiche with such cost we sometyme seke. For they in vs doe knowe and see A thousande thynges, whiche frendes reiect, Because by loue they blinded bee, UUhere foes are full of great respect. UUhen Hierons foe did hym reproue, For that his breth did sauer ill: Then to his wife, and best beloue, UUith spede went he to chide his fill. And sayde to her, why hast thou not, To me declarde this fault of myne? Because (quoth she) I thought god wot, That all mens brethes had bene as thine. Thus may you see, that frendes most deare Our faultes nought can, so soone out fynde As foes that aye, both farre and neare: Fayles not to kepe suche thynges in mynde. One vertue more, and that full goode By foes also we maye obtayne: UUhiche is, our tonges in angry moode, By reasons bytte for to refraine. For vertues such wyll not be hadde, Except we learne in tyme to tame, Our fierce affectes, and rageing madde, UUherby oftimes, we come to shame. As loe, beholde, the wrathfull man, For lacke of wyt and temperaunce, His foolish woordes, to stay nought can: UUhereof doth spring muche variaunce. This fault therfore, as Plato sayes, Both god and man, dothe chast doubtles: For that the rest at all assayes, It doth excede in peuishnes. But silence is, without all harme, And tonges to heare, that lewdly raue UUith stoutnes such, it selfe doth arme: As Socrates was wont to haue. Yea rather more as Hercules For as they say, no wordes of spight, Coulde once offende his hardines: But as a flye them wayde so lyght. UUhat thynge therefore more graue may be, Then styll to be, whilst foes do rayle, As when we woulde take hede to fle: Some fearefull rocke, wherby we sayle Besydes all this, thou shalt thus leare, Thy brawlynge wyfe, and chydinge frend Thy brothers faultes with ease to beare, Howe muche soeuer they offend. I only speake of these, I say, Because I do my selfe assure, Thy parentes woordes and stripes alway, UUithout all grudge thou wilt endure. For what intent dyd Socrates His frowarde wyfe, Zantip by name At home retayne, but patientnes To learne: abrode to vse the same. Muche better wert suche pacience To learne by suffryng aye thy foe: UUhose spightfull woordes with ill pretence Do count as wynde, and let them goe. In enmitie, thus you may see, That pacience mylde hath greatest grace But frendship sekes simplicitee And frendly dedes doth most embrace Nor it deserues so great a prayse Thy faithfull frende to gratefie: As it is foule when nede assayes Of frendly helpe, hym to denye. Our foes offence if we set lyght, UUhen iust reuenge in vs doth lye: It demed is in eche mans sight A dede, whiche doth our vertue trye. But most renowne to him is due, UUho, as his owne, his foes disgrace UUith wofull heart doth wayle and rue, And hym to helpe doth hast a pace. And eke his prompt to doe no lesse UUhen that he seeth his wife or chylde, His man or maide in great distresse And praying ayde with woordes full mylde. For stony heartes haue they ywis That would not praise so great a grace: And thinke him worthy all mens blisse, That mercy suche wyll than embrace. UUhen Cesar made the Pictures faire, Of Pompey to be set againe, That downe were caste out of their chayre, Muche praise thereby he did than gayne. For Tully sayde, O worthy wight, By tendring thus, thy foes renowne Thou haste thyne owne, so well yplight: As neuer power shall throwe it downe. UUherefore I say thy mortall foe UUhich doth deserue to haue great laude Depriue thou not vniustly tho: By spyghtfull meanes, or wicked fraude. Sythe that the more thou doest him prayse, The greater prayse thou shalt obtayne, Besides beliefe, when to dyspraise Thou shalt disposed be agayne. For no man than, wyll iudge or deme, That thou doest hate his personage: But rather as doth best beseme, Dost hate his vice, and yll vsage. The best yet is, that by this way Non enuye shall in vs remayne: Ne shall we grudge to heare men say Our frende to be full iust and playne. Or all men els texcell and passe, In this or that good qualite, UUherat the spightfull hearte alas, UUoulde freat, and ryght sore moued be. UUhat vertue than more profitable Or goodly, may our myndes retayne Than this, wherby, we be made hable: To purge the venome of disdayne. In common weales, some ill decrees, Ill custome doth so well approue That thoughe therby some lose their fees: Yet none with ease maye them remoue. In enmite lykewyse we see Be many faultes, as hatefull spight, Of others grieues right gladde to bee Besides suspect both daye and night. The callinge eke of wronges to minde, And many other hurtfull vyce, As frawde, and guyle, and meanes to finde, To traytours traynes our foe tentyce. UUhich thinges full oft to vse with foes UUe take it as none ill doutles: And whilst our mindes we so dispose, Our faultes remaine without redresse. For if we neuer vse tabstaine, Against our foes such partes to play: Ill custome shall vs eke constrayne, Our frendes to dresse in like aray. Pithagoras did men denye, To hunt, to hawke, or birde to slea And fishe in net would often bye, To cast againe into the sea. No bruit beast eke, of gentle race UUould he haue slayne in any wise Lest fierce affectes we should imbrace Through such a cruell exercise. More goodly, yet it were to flee Such euill affectes throughe sufferaunce And shewing oft our selues to bee Right iust to foes in variaunce. So shall we vse no kynde of guyle Ne fraude with frendes in their affares But shall be playne and thinke it vyle One worde vnkinde, to speake vnwares. UUhen Scaurus at the lawe did sewe, Domitius his mortall foe: Domitius a slaue vntrewe, Had then with him that fled him fro. UUhiche slaue forthwith to Scaurus went, His maysters secretes, to disclose, But Scaurus seeyng his intent: His eares full fast, dyd stop and close. And nought would heare against his foe, By suche a wretche, as woulde hym tray, Yea, more he bound hym fast also: And home agayne hym sent straight way. UUhen Cato lykewyse matter sought Against Muren to fortefie Thaccusement late before hym brought, He nothyng dyd maliciously. For suche as after hym dyd goe, (As was the wont) to heare and see: If that selfe day, dyd aske hym tho, The matter shoulde discussed be: To whom when he had once sayde nay, They by and by did all depart, And thought it true whiche he did say, Suche faith of hym was in their hart. But Simond saith, as euery larke, Of force must haue his coppid creast: So natures gifte, yf ye well marke, Some spight doth brede, in eche mans breast. For whiche emongest light frendes, it were Right good, as Pyndar doth suppose: Of ill affectes, our myndes to cleare by powring them into our foes. And as a sinke our foes temploy Our filthy faultes to kepe in store, The stenche wherof might els annoy Our faithfull frendes, and grieue them sore. In Syo sprang one tyme suche strife That all the towne in factions twaine Deuyded was: then was in lyfe, Onomadem, a man full playne. And curteous eke to euery wight, UUho chaunced on that side to be That wan the fielde by force of fight, To whom he gaue this counsell free. Expell not all (quoth he) your dede That did resist: but some retayne, Lest lacke of foes, may hatred brede, Emongst our selues, vnto our payne. Hesiode sayth, wheras lyke arte Nigh neighbored, or kyndred is The good successe of eyther parte, Eche one tenuye it wer amisse. But yf you can none other waye From spight abstayne, accustome than The welthy state and good araye Of those your foes, to curse and ban. For lyke as gardeners good of skyll, The garlyke stronge: by rosis soote Do vse to set, all sauors yll, From them to drawe, euen from the roote. Our foes euen so that do receiue Our frowarde faultes, our mindes full fell Doe ridde of griefe, whiche we conceyue, To se our frendes to prospere well. UUith foes therfore we should than striue, For honor, rule, and true got gayne, And not to freat when that they thryue, Or more than we, do chaunce tattaine. Ye rather more we should obserue Their doinges all in euery case, And howe they did such thinges deserue, That learne we might them how to passe. Themistocles was wont to tell He could not slepe for thinking on The victorie, that whylome fell Milthiad to, in Marathon. It is a slouthfull grudge and hate, The vertues of thy foes to spight: And none of them to imitate Because thou thinkest they passe thy might. But where as hate thy iudgemente clere Corrupteth not his diligence: And industrie doth then appere, UUhich driues away thy negligence. But if he seme in Prynces hall, Or common weale, right hygh estate To haue hym got by seruice thrall Or flattring meanes, reioyce thereat. And thinke thy selfe an happy wight, For that thou mayst thy honest lyfe: Compare with his in all mens sight And win great praise withouten strife. For Plato saith, no golde on earth Or vnder earth, ne precious ston: One sparke of vertue can be worth, UUhiche passeth all comparison. Ne Solon eke, would chaunge his state In vertue fixt for vain renowne Ne did he care to be check mate UUith noble men in euery towne. He stemed not the peoples prayse UUhose wandryng wyttes are lyke the wynde Nowe heare nowe there at all assayse Their yea, with nay, full sone tonbynde. No worthy state that semes to bee, Can worthy be, in verye dede Except the meanes therto perdee Of worthy actes dyd first procede. But lyke as loue, doth louers blynde Euen so we spye, the faultes of foes Much farther of, than we can fynde The faultes of frendes before our noes Reioyce not than with ioye in vayne Because thy foe doth chaunce toffende, Ne take no griefe without some gaine, To se what good his workes pretende. But ponder well these cases twayne, His vice and vertues both I say And first his vyce from vyce tabstaine And therin passe him farre away. His vertues than thou shalt doe well To imitate in their degree: And though thou canst not hym excell Yet see thou be not worse than hee. Finis. [Lyke as the mightie Oke whose rootes] Lyke as the mightie Oke whose rootes, In thearth are fixed fast: Is hable to withstande eache winde, That blowes most boystrous blast. Euen so eache frowarde Fortunes happe That euer maie betyde: The constant minde with vertue fraught is hable to abyde. To the true louers of Wisedome Iohn Asteley, mayster of the Queenes Maiestyes Iewell house, and Iohn Harington Esquier Thomas Blundeuille, greeting. UUhilst plutarks works, I gaue my self to rede So pleasant fruit me thought, I could none f?d As is in y? which rightly shewes in dede The waie tappease, and still thunquiete minde. For wheras since false flattring hope with wh? I trauelde had, long tyme full painfully, Of comforte voide, alone me leaft to rome The barrein coste of wretched miserye: In stead of helping me the seas to passe Of worldly ioyes, amongst the happy sorte, In ship full fraught with fortunes giftes: as was Her vowe when first to me she did resorte: The restles muse had made my feble brayn The forge of care, and therein daily wroughte Such dulfull domps &amp; dreadful dreames as cleane From mirth my mind vnto despaire had brought. That boke did yeld such glistring beames I say, Of comfort great and ioyfull quietnes: As draue those dumpes and sorowes all away My heauy heart which helde in great destres. So as in dede from that time foorth me thought I coulde not chuse but nedes contented rest And though before vaine hope much griefe hadde wrought Yet now to think y? al was for the best. UUhich comfort though it grateful was to me In my conceyt yet did it not suffise: Onlesse that you my faithfull frendes might be Eke partners of the same some kinde of wise. For as the grief of one frende dothe decreace His other frendes, when they therof partake His ioye euen so he shall the more encreace If of the same, he doth them partners make. Into our tunge therfore this litle quaire I turned haue, and termd the port of rest And wishe eche wight, therto for to repaire with troubled sprite that feeles himself opprest. For as the mariner, in sea whose bote UUith cruel stormes and tempests hath been beat And drieu? twixt whaues &amp; feareful rocks to flote Though al that while dispaire his mind did freat: Yet wh? y? winds their boistrous blowing ceace And he to hauen is safely come at last He than reioyceth with himself in peace And cleane forgeates al those his daungers past: Euen so eche man within this litle port That shall vouchesafe at times more ydley spente To harborough a while: himselfe to sport UUhen he perceiues his minde to sorow bent: To warrant him I dare be bolde I saie That though he be in passing heauines Yet he thereby shall quickly learne the waie To rid his minde of all vnquietnes. Ne shall he feare the losse in time to come Of frendes, of goodes, of lyfe, or lyke distres But lyue and dye, by helpe of reasons dome In suche assured holde of quietnes: As neyther frowarde fortunes sharpe assaultes, Nor death himself, for all his dreadfull name Ne malice eke with all her forged faultes Shall be of power to ouerthrowe the same. To you therefore to whom I am muche bounde And tall the rest, lo here nowe for your sake Of this my paine suche fruite as hath redounde In frendly wise I doe a present make. UUhose relles though it be not halfe so swete Ne hath suche sappe of eloquence in dede As those thinges haue whereon (as meates most mete For deintie mouthes) you wonted are to fede. Yet doubt I not but that vouchesafe you wyll, To take it well in woorth, and speciallye, Sithe Budes woordes in all this treatise styll I folowd haue in deede moste faithfullye, UUhose stile I founde to be more graue then gaye And harde to turne into our vulguer speche, Yet as it is refuse not when you maye To taste thereof I humbly you beseche. For though it hap not deintye mouthes to please UUeak stomakes yet thereby may find much ease.</field>
   </doc>
</add>