<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Boyse, Samuel, 1708-1749</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Boyse, Samuel, 1708-1749</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">boyse samuel 1708 1749</field>
      <field name="author_text">Boyse, Samuel, 1708-1749</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1740's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_2.0351.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1742</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464895</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The praise of peace ; A poem. In Three cantos. From the Dutch of M. Van Haren, one of the Deputies of the Province of West-Friesland in the Assembly of their High Mightinesses the States General [by Samuel Boyse</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The praise of peace ; A poem. In Three cantos. From the Dutch of M. Van Haren, one of the Deputies of the Province of West-Friesland in the Assembly of their High Mightinesses the States General [by Samuel Boyse</field>
      <field name="title_facet">praise of peace</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">praise of peace</field>
      <field name="title_text">The praise of peace ; A poem. In Three cantos. From the Dutch of M. Van Haren, one of the Deputies of the Province of West-Friesland in the Assembly of their High Mightinesses the States General [by Samuel Boyse</field>
      <field name="year_display">1742</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1742</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1742</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464895&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464895&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Boyse, Samuel, 1708-1749&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;boyse samuel 1708 1749&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The praise of peace ; A poem. In Three cantos. From the Dutch of M. Van Haren, one of the Deputies of the Province of West-Friesland in the Assembly of their High Mightinesses the States General [by Samuel Boyse&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;praise of peace&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1742&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1742&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Boyse, Samuel&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1708&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1749&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The praise of peace&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A poem. In Three cantos. From the Dutch of M. Van Haren, one of the Deputies of the Province of West-Friesland in the Assembly of their High Mightinesses the States General [by Samuel Boyse]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for A. Dodd [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1742&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0528&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;[6], 44 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The praise of peace&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A poem. In Three cantos. From the Dutch of M. Van Haren, one of the Deputies of the Province of West-Friesland in the Assembly of their High Mightinesses the States General [by Samuel Boyse]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 82 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Et nomen Pacis dulce est &amp; ipsa res salutaris, sed inter Pacem &amp; Servitutem plurimum interest. Pax est tranquilla Libertas, Servitus autem malorum omnium extremum non modo bello, sed etiam morte repellendum. Cicero.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">? Non ante revellar Quam te exanimem spectem Roma, tuumque, Nomen Libertas, &amp; inanem prosequar umbram! Lucan.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TO THE Right Honourable George Montagu-Dunk, Earl of Halifax.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE Praise of PEACE. CANTO I. O nimium cælo, &amp; Pelago confise sereno, Nudus in ignotâ, Palinure! jacebis arenâ. Virg. Æn. V. Daughter of Jove! Calliope divine, Round whose fair Brow ambrosial Flowrets shine! Descend, bright Muse, display thy radiant Face, And teach the Lyre to sing the Sweets of Peace! Let others paint th'exalted Hero's State, Alike in Conquest, or Misfortune great; A more distinguished Theme attracts my Choice, Celestial Freedom animates my Voice; To warn my native Land from Perils shown, To shew that Peace is Liberty's alone! To bid her eye the gathering Storm afar, And timely wise prepare for distant War: For Belgia's Sake I tune th'historic Lyre, Nor ask a dearer Motive to inspire; My sole Ambition is the Patriot's Name, My Country's Welfare,—all I ask of Fame! But hark! what martial Sounds my Ear surprise? What dreadful Shouts! and intermingled Cries! Why waves Destruction her infernal Brand? And scatters wild Affright thro' Europe's Land! Scarce has she felt an Interval of Rest, When new Commotions heave her troubled Breast! Or is the Age of Cadmus Cadmus is said to have sow'd the Earth with Dragon's Teeth, from which rose arm'd Men, who destroy'd each other. come again? When iron Harvests blast the verdant Plain. 'Tis wild Ambition, deaf to Nature's Call, 'Tis she, curst Goddess, is the Cause of all! No social Ties can bind her lawless Force, No Faith, no Justice stop her furious Course! From Beauty's Arms reluctant Mars she wakes, His Helm she braces, and his Spear she shakes; Then bids the God in Blood his Wrath asswage, And o'er the World relentless pour his Rage! Did not bright Pallas, with her temper'd Shield, Stop his Advance,—and half dispute the Field. All-ruling Heav'n, to plague a guilty Earth, First gave these arbitrary Nimrods Birth; Who, deaf to Pity, see a World in Flame, And millions bleed to raise one Madman's Name! See! while the Trumpet eccho's from afar, And mad Bellona wakes the rising War! The Rhine and Danube, in their oozy Beds, Retiring creep, and hide their frighted Heads! While banish'd by the noisy Cannon's Roar, Fair Themis The Goddess of Justice. flies, and seeks the Asian Shore; Where calm Euphrates rolls her Silver Flood, Or Tygris flows unstain'd with human Blood; There reaps the Native his abundant Grain, Nor sees Invasion spoil his peaceful Plain. Heav'ns! shall th'invidious Cock The Cock alluding to France. the Eagle plume? While the pale Crescents The Crescent is the military and religious Ensign of the Turks. double Light assume: Or shall divided Europe tear her Breast, And leave an easy Conquest to the East? No,—rather let religious Madness reign! Rage holy Wars! Crusados flame again! To Syria's Strand let other Godfreys go, Crusados, ridiculous as they have been represented, were less prejudicial to Europe than the Wars at present are. And waste their Vengeance on the Arab-Foe! Wild tho' the Fury, unprovok'd the War, Yet better it should vent its Force so far. Then might rich Lombardy unwasted The present Seats of War in Europe. smile, And fair Bohemia bless her fertile Soil; Then should the Swede, content with Freedom's Charms, No more provoke the potent Russian's Arms; Nor Gallic Gold its wicked Influence boast, And raise Hostilities on every Coast. While thus dread Mars, from his ensanguin'd Car, Pours wild Affright, and animates the War: Pollutes the Earth, and taints the chrystal Flood, With lawless Havoc, and with human Blood; Pleas'd in his Progress as he looks behind, To see the Ruin suit his savage Mind; To view the chearful Marks of Labour broke, The Harvest vanish, and the Village smoke: Only the Peasant left,—spar'd to deplore His cruel Fate, and curse the Hand of Pow'r. While thus the God extends his potent Sway, From Elbe to Rhine, victorious in his Way! Say Heav'n-born Peace, say where dost thou reside? What Nations bless thee? or what Regions hide? Where shall the Muse discover thy Retreat, And pay her willing Homage at thy Feet: But hark! what pleasing Sounds salute my Ears? Methinks fair Belgia to my Sight appears; Rais'd from her sea-green Couch,—a Matron-form! In Freedom great,—and braves the threat'ning Storm; “Hither, (she cries with a majestic Air) “Let the Distress'd and Desolate repair! “Here Peace invites, sole Partner of my Throne, “And calls these happy Provinces her own: “This Halcyon Clime no rude Alarms infest, “Here exil'd Virtue finds a welcome Rest; “Peace guards my Limits with her olive Wand, “And Arts and Riches rise on every Hand; “The gladsome Peasant tills the fertile Plain, “Assur'd in Safety to enjoy the Gain; “My wealthy Merchants trust their annual Store, “To the known Flag, rever'd by every Pow'r. “My Citizens, like those of antient Tyre! “Behold ev'n Kings their Amity desire: “My People all one general Union prove, “Deriv'd from Liberty, fair Source of Love! “Hence Commerce, beauteous Commerce! smiles to flow, “As far as Ocean rolls, or Winds can blow! “She spreads my Fame to either India wide, “She brings back Treasures each alternate Tide! “And long as Winds can waft, or Seas can flow, “That Fame shall brighten, and that Plenty grow! Fair sounds this Language as the Syren's Strain, But to Precaution's Ear it sounds in vain! Experience ushers Doubt into the Breast, And whispering, asks—“Is Belgia quite so blest? “Or if no Phantom dress'd in fair Disguise, “Instead of real Peace deludes our Eyes? A Shade there is, Security her Name, That oft misleads the most sagacious Aim; Lulls in false Rest the Rulers of a State, And leads them blindfold on the Shelves of Fate! So to th'unhappy Palinurus' Palinurus was Pilot to the Trojans in their Voyage to Italy under Æneas, and was drown'd on the Coast of Naples. Eyes, Appear'd the shadowy Shore, and painted Skies; No more his steddy Rudder rul'd the Deep, Heav'n seal'd his Eye-lids in eternal Sleep! Nor had the Trojans touch'd th'Etrurian Realm, If wise Æneas had not kept the Helm! Peace is the Daughter of celestial Morn, Whom Virtue, Truth, and Liberty adorn! Security, the base-born Child of Hell, With whom Corruption, Fraud, and Ruin dwell. In Scythia's The Situation of this Abode of the God of Sleep, and the making Silence his Queen, is highly poetical, and well imagin'd. Waste beneath the polar Skies, Conceal'd from Day, a dreary Region lies! There Pines dark-shading form a double Night, Impervious to the smallest Glimpse of Light: Eternal Clouds enfold the gloomy Plain, And threaten to descend in Floods of Rain. No Mortal e'er approach'd the dismal Seat, Ev'n Beasts of Prey avoid the dread Retreat; Where two immortal Pow'rs their Empire keep, And Silence The Situation of this Abode of the God of Sleep, and the making Silence his Queen, is highly poetical, and well imagin'd. reigns the consort-queen of Sleep. Full in the Midst, an ice-crown'd Mountain's Head O'er Zembla's Ocean casts its lengthen'd Shade; Where in a spatious Cave's incircling Breast, The God compos'd, enjoys eternal Rest! There no Alarms his downy Slumbers wake, Infest his Quiet, or his Visions break; For watchful Silence, Guardian of his Bed, Stills every Sound that might his Ease invade! While Morpheus hov'ring, with retentive Breath, Spreads round the Dome the Solitude of Death! Beneath his Feet, unfading Poppies bloom, And grateful shed their lulling mild Perfume; Round which innumerous Dreams in millions play, Busy as Bees in July's Noontide Day! Here they resort, and from the potent Juice, The visionary Scenes of Life produce; But soon as chirps The Owl. the solemn Bird of Night, Morpheus with Ebon Wand directs their Flight; Softly he drives them thro' the darksome Port, And sends them o'er the peopled Earth to sport; They fly,—no Obstacles retard their Way, Thro' Walls they penetrate, thro' Keyholes stray! Nor miss a Place where restless Mortals dwell, Down from the crowded City to the Cell. Of these some chuse to haunt the Domes of State, And smile to see the Troubles of the Great; To show that Grandeur is a wretched Thing, Their rebel Hands dethrone the scepter'd King; While others sportive to his envy'd Place, Exalt the Clown, tho' born of lowly Race; The Monarch sighs!—he feels the Want of Pow'r, The Peasant smiles,—and is a Wretch no more! Others to Friendship's Aid propitious move, And bless a Passion which they most approve; These wake the Dead, and to the mental Eyes, Bid the lost Parent, Wife, or Brother rise! With Joy we view the well remember'd Face, The Voice we hear,—the Shadow we embrace! So well these airy Players act their Part, That Dreams are effected by the Interposition of Spirits is a Notion the Reader may see largely explained and defended by a modern Philosopher, the ingenious Mr Baxter, in his excellent Treatise on the Immortality of the Soul. Not Truth more vivid Pleasure can impart; They know how feeble Mortals judge of Things, They sound our Hearts, and touch their tenderest Strings! Our Hopes and Fears alternate others raise, And pain at will th'impassion'd Mind, or please; These the fond Lover's anxious Thoughts beguile, And paint a Chloe's Frown, or Cælia's Smile; Here point a Grace, diminish there a Charm, And Beauty's Pow'r or heighten, or disarm; To the despairing Youth in sweet Disguise, They bid the dear disdainful Daphne rise; No more her Form forbidding Terrors shroud, Nor thinks th'Ixion that he grasps a Cloud! What swelling Joys his raptur'd Heart o'erpow'r? How soft the sweet Delusion of an Hour! But see to Damon, Delia looks severe! How starts the Lover at the alter'd Fair? To see the Maid his tender Suit repress, With whom his waking Vows still found Success: Objects like these the am'rous Sylphs The Sylphs are, according to the Doctrine of Rosicrucius, the most agreeable and friendly of the four Orders of Spirits that inhabit our Atmosphere. They are composed of aerial Particles unmix'd. delight, And form th'important Business of the Night! To Courts the active Salamanders fly, The Salamanders are composed of Fire, and have few Females amongst them. (The boldest Spirits that frequent the Sky) Sworn Foes to Peace! thro' Palaces they creep, And-fire ev'n Monarch's in the Arms of Sleep; There paint Ambition, all in Glory drest, And lodge the Syren in the Royal Breast; Sudden her Poison all the Mind inflames, And Conquests rise in sanguinary Dreams! The Hero wakens—with disclosing Light, Summons his Troops, and meditates the Fight; The Arsenals their deadly Treasures pour, Destruction smiles to see th'infernal Store! Bellona scents the Carnage from afar, And hastens to enjoy the Spoils of War! But of the Swarms, that haunt the Scythian Dome, The most pernicious is the artful Gnome; These bred to Fraud, each varied Shape assume, Bask in the Sun, or glide along the Gloom! Children of Earth, from their parental Mine, They borrow Gold to tempt, The Gnomes are made of terrestrial Effluvia, and inhabit the subterraneous Parts of the Globe, as Mines, &amp;c. They are of a dark malicious Disposition. For a further Account of these see Mr Pope's Rape of the Lock, and the Count de Gabalais. or Gems to shine; In Wisdom's Dress their Purpose oft disguise, And cast a Mist before the Patriot's Eyes; Or else in Flattery's painted Garb appear, And lisp Infection to the Sovereign's Ear! Nor are Republicks from these Demons free, They strive to taint the Springs of Liberty; Restless as Wasps that vex the peaceful Hive, On popular Credulity they thrive; To raise Distrust and Jealousy delight, Or set true Merit in invidious Light; Till public Virtue firm oppose her Shield, And drive the Fiends, victorious from the Field. Or if the Guardians of a Free-born State, Neglect the weighty Charge assign'd by Fate; If those in whom the publick Weal resides, Or Interest sways, or lawless Pow'r misguides; If deep Corruption latent Venom sheds, And threatens Ruin, as the Gangrene spreads; Sudden, these busy Spirits shew their Art, And fly to take the ministerial Part: “Were ever Rulers (they exclaim) so just? “Were ever Senators more worthy Trust! “Safe may you rest in Confidence and Ease, “When blest with watchful Ciceros, Cicero's Vigilancy defeated the most dangerous Conspiracy Rome was ever threaten'd with. like these: So Grave harangue the Crowd, these wicked Elves, But Men of Sense are Judges for themselves. If Union is the Blessing of the State, If Concord makes a happy People great; That Bliss to undermine, and blast the Joy, These hellish Engineers their Skill employ.— They whisper—“Freedom is a tender Thing, “A Stadtholder This alludes to the Motives alleged by the French Party in Holland against the Promotion of General Officers. may rise,—and grow a King; “Or what if you exclude the O?e Race? “If petty Tyrants lord it in the Place! Does Honesty such envious Shafts repel? They call up Discord from her noisy Cell, And bid the Fury, with her poison'd Brand, Drive heav'nly Peace from the distracted Land. Of all the Plagues that speak a Nation curs'd, A False-Security is sure the worst! Freedom, like Sampson, in her lewd Embrace Sinks to Repose, nor sees his own Disgrace: In vain the blackening Clouds the Skies deform, In vain the wakening Winds forebode a Storm! In vain the piercing Clarion sounds to Arms, Th'insensate Sleeper slights its loud Alarms! “Peace, Peace (she crys, and falters in her Voice) “Eternal Peace for ever be my Choice! “Approach no martial Sounds my quiet Ear, “The noblest Triumphs cost the World too dear! “What tempts you to unsheath the cruel Sword? “Repose with me, and take a Neighbour's. Word: “What tho' The Assurances of France, to draw the States into the proposed Neutrality. his numerous Squadrons rise in View? “He promises—he means no hurt to you! “Then spare your Toils, compose your troubled Breast! “And taste with me the endless Sweets of Rest! She speaks,—when see a specious Phantom rise! Whom all the Attributes of Peace disguise: Her Olive Branch she waves with formal Air, The Cap of Freedom hangs upon her Spear! Around her all the busy Demons throng, And sound her Praises as she moves along! “Belgians, (they cry) your Guardian-Goddess bless! “This, this is Peace,—the Cause of your Success! The cheated Crowd the shadowy Form adore, Delusion smiles to see her growing Pow'r! But soon to Scythia's Waste the Phantom flies, Truth clears the Mist that veil'd the vulgar Eyes! And rous'd by the awakening Hand of Fate, The People mourn their Error when too late! The End of the first Canto. CANTO II. “Hei mihi! qualis erat? quantum mutatus ab illo “Hectore? quiredit exuvias indutus Achilleï, “Vel Danaum Phrygios jaculatus puppibus ignes! Virg. Æn. II. Who rashly slights the Torch's friendly Ray, And chuses in the darksome Night to stray! Is neither more or less, by Wisdom's Rule, Than half a Madman, or almost a Fool. Instructed Belgian shun the blindfold State, Bid Reason guide thee thro' the Rocks of Fate! Fair Lamp of Heav'n, let her directing Light, Thy Steps illumine, and conduct thee right! Then see if Peace displays her heav'nly Beam, Or if no vain Usurper boasts her Name! Let no false Colours your Enquiry blind, Be Truth your Guide! Peace, real Peace, to find. As the chaste Virgin, who with down-cast Eyes, At Love's first mention reddens with Surprize; Differs from the experienc'd frontless Dame, Whose Eyes confess a Messalina's Flame; So learn from Peace, Security to know, And guard your Safety from the wanton Foe! Rome scarce o'er ruin'd Carthage rais'd her Head, When with her Manners first her Fame decay'd; No longer blameless Poverty her Boast, Her Faith grew dubious, and her Honour lost! Then first her rising Glory felt a Shade, Her Valour cool'd:—No Rivals to invade. Self-Interest grew, increasing Vice prevail'd; Prosperity her heavy Eye-lids seal'd; And she who rose in Arms and Virtue great, Sunk the vast Prey of Luxury and Fate. 'Twas then Security,—a deadly Guest, First stood beneath her Capitol confess'd: “Romans (she cry'd) enough of War is pass'd, “Let Peace your happy Altars bless at last; “Commerce and rich Abundance both are mine, “I give the Earth to smile, the Sun to shine! “Safe in my guardian Care yourselves repose, “Rome is too great to dread the Name of Foes; “Her's be the Sweets of Riches and of Ease! “Queen of the Earth, and Empress of the Seas! Had Asia's Sons such Sophistry believed, No Wonder if th'Impostress had deceiv'd! But when such Sounds deluded Rome could hear, Rome! that deriv'd her Majesty from War! What Blushes, Mars, must have obscur'd thy Face? To see the Shame of thy degenerate Race! Yet see, how sooth'd by these inchanting Arts, The curs'd Contagion spreads thro' Roman Hearts! A feeble Frontier show'd her waning Pow'r, Arms were forgot, and Glory was no more! Her Tribunes in the Senate chose to jar, Security awak'd domestic War: No more her Consuls rose in Virtue great, Wealth nurs'd Ambition; and Ambition State; To rise to Honours by the purchas'd Voice, Or make some distant Government their Choice; Where the proud Prætor might the Nations fleece, And glean the Spoils of Asia, and of Greece! These were the Arts the Roman Youth were taught, To buy, then sell the venal Herd they bought: Those Limbs each manly Exercise disdain'd, Now Vice enfeebled, and Dishonour stain'd; Then foreign Eunuchs from the Memphian Shore, Imported Rites obscene, unknown before. And Virtue, Guardian of the Roman State, Averse withdrew:—and left the rest to Fate! The Veteran, then in Arms untaught to yield, If pensive as he cross'd the Martian The Field of Mars was the Place where all publick Exercises were performed. Field; From the lewd Sons of Wantonness and Ease, Was forc'd to hear satyric Taunts like these. “Go, useless Warrior! hide that batter'd Face, “Thy Looks the Roman Elegance disgrace! “Peace, and her softer Arts our Manners suit, “What is the Soldier but a fighting Brute? “War is no more!—we know no hostile Land! “The beardless Boy our Legions may command; “With harmless Pomp their Ensigns now may flow! “What is an Army paid for, but for Show? “Go bear thy Murmurs to the Thracian Pontus, in the Euxine Sea, whither most of the worthy Romans were banish'd by Julius and Augustus. It was the Place of Ovid's Exile. Shore, “Where Discord reigns, and Waves eternal roar; “There to the savage Natives point thy Scars! “And teach Barbarians all thy boasted Wars; “Recount thy Deeds, relate the tedious Fight; “We want not to be valiant,—but polite! “Or hast thou got a Hoard of Punic Gold? “Go buy a Post,—for Posts are to be sold! “Else—glad obey the Stripling you despise, “This is no Age, my Friend, for you to rise! The Roman now, who once with scorn could view, The Pomp of Kings, himself as sumptuous grew! Then first prevail'd Magnificence and Dress, And Luxury was heighten'd to Excess. To please her Taste, and spread her costly Board, Each Clime was plunder'd, and each Sea explor'd; As when at Athens Cotys or the Goddess of Pleasure had a Temple at Athens, where her Mysteries were celebrated by Night in a most infamous Manner. the Cottyttian Rite In lawless Pleasure wak'd the tiresome Night, While ruddy Bacchus shew'd his glowing Face, And Venus wanton'd in the lewd Embrace. So Vice at Rome triumphant rear'd her Head, And every Shape of boundless Licence spread. Had Curius Curius, one of the antient Heroes of Rome. from th'Elysian Fields return'd, How had his Breast with Indignation burn'd? To see a powder'd, dancing, motley Race, Effeminacy mark'd in every Face! Methinks I hear him, with a conscious Frown, Ask, “Where is Rome's primæval Virtue gone? Alas! their Ears are Strangers to its Name, Their Silence speaks their Ignorance and Shame. In early Days that bless'd the Roman State, 'Twas virtuous Poverty confirm'd her great: But now Security has wrought her Bane, And Wealth and Pride have darken'd all the Scene; As sordid Interest sways your Passions move, And Av'rice has expell'd the publick Love! No Nation now can on your Faith rely, When all is sold—your Idol-Gold can buy! If Truth a Quintus Roman Consuls, whose Valour and Integrity are well known. or a Decius praise, You cry'—such Patterns suit not modern Days! “Those simple Manners Sabines might become, “But ill befit the Majesty of Rome! “A mere Chimera is the Patriot's Name, “Ambition be our Guide! and Wealth our Aim! “Riches each happy Quality include, “Wit, Courage, Learning, Honesty, and Blood “And he whom Lands or Pow'r distinguish great, “Has all the Virtues useful to the State. Thus publick Good by private Int'rest sway'd, Neglected pin'd,—and dwindled to a Shade; Corruption as it gain'd the venal Post, Strove of its Bargain still to make the most; Av'rice the wealthy Province chose her Prey, Exaction, Rapine, liv'd beneath her Sway: And the lax Sinews of a feeble State, Were Marks of Rome's inevitable Fate. Oh dire Effects of long lethargic Ease! Did ever Peace produce such Ills as these? Not War itself worse Dangers could create, Not greater Mischiefs spring from a Defeat! If Peace indeed attend such dreadful Harms, Quick let the glorious Trumpet rouse to Arms! Uncertain tho' the dubious Chance of Fight, It throws the Dye, Jacta est alea said Cæsar when he passed the Rubicon. A hazardous War is certainly preferable to a fatal Security. and Fate may turn it right! Better at least in Arms the Life to lose, Than dream it thus away in dull Repose! While Senates sleep regardless of your Fame, And Magistrates make Interest all their Aim: Tribunes to rust in Indolence are paid, And ev'n your Priests make Piety a Trade; While Crimes unpunish'd are with Pride declar'd, And Merit starves, unnotic'd by Reward; While Impudence her brazen Front displays, Sure the corrupt Majority to please! Or if one Cato Victrix Causa Diis placuit, sed victa Catoni. rise to stem the Tide, And combat single on the juster Side, Envy pursues him with her secret Arts, And whispers Jealousy to wing her Darts! “Believe him not (the vile Detractress cries) “His selfish Heart the Patriot Tongue belies! “He only makes the publick Good his Theme, “To catch the Vulgar, and to gain a Name! “But when Preferment shall the Mask remove, “You see how high he rates his Country's Love; So snarls the Fiend,—till Truth victorious shine, And gilds Integrity with Beams divine! Pale Envy then recedes,—compell'd to yield, And leaves fair Virtue Sov'reign of the Field! O Rome! who in thy Glory's cloudless Morn, Couldst view the Tyrants of the Earth with Scorn! When Kings beheld thy Senators with Awe, And thy least Mandate gave the Nations Law! Dejected now from Virtue's radiant Height, Crush'd by thy own corrupted monstrous Weight, See, like a dying Lamp, thy Freedom glow; And wait Ambition's meditated Blow! Far sooner would I tread Catanea, a City in Sicily at the Foot of Mount Ætna, which has often suffered by the Eruptions of that Volcano, particularly in 1669. On the Coast between this and Syracuse the Spanish Fleet was destroy'd by Sir Geo. Byng, Anno 1719. Catanea's Shores, Where Ætna all her fierce Explosions pours; Than longer chuse, degenerate Rome, to rest, A hopeless Native, in thy fatal Breast! When Virtue once her sacred Sense withdraws, Weak is the Rev'rence paid to slighted Laws! Where Pow'r but courts the first advent'rous Hand, Soon Liberty forsakes the dangerous Land; So once the headstrong Courser breaks the Rein, No Skill his boundless Fury can restrain; O'er Earth he flies, impetuous as the Wind, And leaves the Car in Fragments far behind! If fell Diseases close besiege the Heart, Self-preservation calls the Aids of Art; So when bad Symptoms threat the publick Peace, 'Tis Time to bid all private Quarrels cease; With Caution to consult the Common-weal, And seek each great Restorative to heal; Lest Civil-War, with Rage pleuretic rise, And spread its Conflagration to the Skies! Or wild Invasion like a Deluge sweep, And bury all in its devouring Deep! Happy had Rome those useful Maxims known, While yet her Strength and Vigour were her own; But lull'd in false Security she lay, And dos'd fair Freedom's last Remains away, Till, not one Spark of Virtue left to save, She sunk in Death,—Corruption dug her Grave! Then Clouds of Civil Discord thick arose, Plagues follow'd Plagues, and Woes succeeded Woes! Romans on Romans turn'd th'avenging Sword, And millions fell, that one might be the Lord! Till Cæsar, Victor on Pharsalia's The Battle of Pharsalia determined the Fate of Rome, and put the last Period to her Liberty. Plain, Beheld the World subjected to his Chain; And Rome enslav'd, discover'd to her Cost, That Peace was fled, when Liberty was lost! The End of the second Canto. CANTO III. Hanc olim veteres vitam coluere Sabini, Hanc Remus &amp; Frater, sic fortis Etruria crevit, Scilicet &amp; rerum facta est pulcherrima Roma. Virg. Geor. II. But close the Muse to darker Scenes her Eyes, While fairer Views in pleasing Prospect rise! Where Peace resides, and forms her subject State, In Liberty serene, in Virtue great! As when the Pilot sees the clouded Air, He marks the Compass with attentive Care; Studious his well-directed Course to keep, And guide his Bark in Safety thro' the Deep! So guardian Peace one steddy Aspect wears, And for impending Danger calm prepares! Respect abroad secures her from Alarms, Freedom inchains domestic Faction's Arms! All are her Friends, whose Justice makes no Foes, And Truth and Virtue watch her fair Repose! But does the Goddess ever cast a Ray On Lands that dwell in arbitrary Sway?— Belgia the Question wants not to decide, Who views her drest in all her radiant Pride! And while her Presence makes her Days serene, Wishes to know no greater,—fairer Queen! Let venal Bards record Augustus' Praise, And to the Tyrant slavish Altars raise! So the poor Wretch, who starves where Nile o'erflows, May sing to Rocks the Comfort of Repose, Alas! 'tis all the Happiness he knows! But let the Belgic Muse with nobler Aim, Arrouse the Patriot's never-dying Flame! To freeborn Minds the happy Maxims trace, How to preserve the balmy Sweets of Peace: That not the Arts of Fraud, nor Tyrant's Frown, May force the Goddess to desert the Throne! On Education chief depends a State, To rise for Wisdom fam'd, or Valour great; Learn then with Care to form the rising Youth, To Virtue's Dictates, and the Rules of Truth; Show, not for Self alone was Man design'd, But giv'n to serve his Country, and his Kind; Born for Society's important Ends, To guard that Peace on which his own depends; In vain, where Principles like these prevail, Av'rice would tempt, or Lust of Pow'r assail; Since Precept and Example both unite, And steddy Reason shews her constant Light! While to the Son, the uncorrupted Sire Points all that can his Country's Love inspire: Tells, how for Freedom his Forefathers stood, In Fields of Death, and lavish'd all their Blood! How placid Orange The first Prince of Orange, who greatly defended his Country from the Spaniards, and was assassinated by a Burgundian; he lies buried at Delft. brav'd the Dart of Death, And bless'd his Country with his dying Breath! How Trompe Van Trompe, famous for his naval Exploits. He was kill'd in an Engagement with the English Fleet under Blake in 1654. see his Epitaph, Gentleman's Mag. Vol. X. p. 618. her Fame to distant India spread, How Essens triumph'd, Van Essens and Van Galen, two Dutch Admirals, who died in the Service of their Country. and Van-Galen bled; Or godlike Nassau, K: William III. who saved his Country on the Brink of Ruin in 1672, and in 1688 rescu'd Britain from the Danger of arbitrary Power. on the Verge of Fate, Another Scipio rose to save the State, Names dear alike to Liberty and Fame, Whose lasting Virtues endless Honours claim; As the skill'd Artist, in the glowing Mold, First pours, and then extracts the minted Gold; Which if neglected, till the Heat o'erpass, Would still continue an unsightly Mass. So virtuous Education forms the Mind, And leaves for Life the beauteous Stamp behind! Then to your Children in their early Days, Inculcate with Esteem the Patriot's Praise! Place these as Models to your manly Youth, And let your own Example prove the Truth: So shall your fair Posterity arise, Firm, uncorrupted, gen'rous, just and wise! Whose Steps their free-born Ancestors shall trace, Nor shame your Counsels, nor their Fame disgrace; To such (when Age shall summon to the Grave,) With Joy your Rights intrusted shall you leave; Which thus to latest Days delivered down, Your Mem'ry shall with spotless Honour crown! While Peace preserv'd by your distinguish'd Toil, Gilds with her placid Beams the Belgic Soil. Bless'd is the Land, where Rules like these obtain! Where Peace and Freedom social Sway maintain: Where chief the Welfare of the Whole's persu'd, And every Passion yields to publick Good. There Luxury in vain her Charms displays, Or mad Ambition sheds her fatal Blaze! Calm Temp'rance smiles the Syren to repell, Integrity the Sorceress drives to Hell! There Virtue joys Authority to trust, That helps the Innocent, and crowns the Just! Protects from Wrong, relieves the Poor distress'd, But punishes the Tyrant who oppress'd: There Sov'reign Pow'r in Goodness mild array'd, Wants no external Forms of Pomp to aid; Blest in itself, demands no vain Supplies, Is it attack'd? a grateful People flies! Prepar'd and willing at its slightest Word, The Purse to open, or unsheath the Sword. So when Eclipses blot the radiant Sun, With eager Zeal Barbaric Nations run; The Cymbal beat, each mystic Rite employ, The God to succour, and the Foe destroy: Till bursting thro' the envious. Veil of Night, He shines with Lustre prevalently Bright! As when the Eagle courts the solar Ray, The timorous Hawk at Distance eyes her Way! So hellish Discord still withdraws her Face, And hides her from the hateful Beams of Peace: In vain th'infernal Hag would try her Arts, On Minds well-principled, and generous Hearts. Where Equity, with an impartial Hand, Administers the Laws that bless the Land; Where heav'nly Reason with her temperate Light, Teaches th'unbiass'd Mind to judge aright; There Property secure enjoys her own; There Conscience sits untroubl'd on her Throne; For every lawless Passion sprung of Night, Is aw'd by Virtue,—and abhors the Light. See in yon distant Shade, all fierce with Scorn, Pale Tyranny her fruitless Projects mourn! Hear how she howls! distracted with Despair, To see her fancy'd Triumphs lost in Air! Vain is thy Rage, detested Monster! vain; Peace views thee not with Pity,—but Disdain! Her Smiles are destin'd for the virtuous Brave, A Title never yet that grac'd a Slave: Should there in Belgia be one Native found, Deceived by thee, who trod the injur'd Ground, The Wretch that Hour should yield his forfeit Breath, And expiate his Disgrace by shameful Death. Where guardian Wisdom in the Senate shines, In vain Conspiracy prepares her Mines; One watchful Tully A wise and vigilant Administration is seldom troubled with Conspiracies. at the Helm of State, Can still a thousand Cataline's defeat. When Justice is to Rank or Favour blind, And guilty Greatness can no Mercy find; Then Vice discourag'd quits the dangerous Ground, Nor is the Villian, or the Traitor found; If Tyranny her baffled Arts withdraws, And fires some hair-brain'd Monarch in her Cause; Who while the specious Name of Friend he wears, Already black Invasion's Storm prepares; Clear-sighted Peace the Artifice discries, Disdains the Flattery, and the Threat defies; Nor trusts her Safety to such dubious Things, The Word of Statesmen, or the Faith of Kings; Whom History from long Experience knows, The Enemies of Freedom and Repose! Tho' cautious thus against impending Harm, Peace never arms, till long provok'd to arm! To Treaties just, she sees not all the same, Nor can her Truth, a faithless World reclaim; Yet when some neighb'ring Prince prepares for Fight, And Troops assembling gather in her Sight! Soon she advances with determin'd Air, And asks the Motives of the purpos'd War; If Silence speaks her Apprehensions just, In righteous Jove, the Goddess puts her Trust; Assumes like Pallas her celestial Shield, And issues out undaunted to the Field! While Virtue thus gives Resolution Force, Injustice stops her meditated Course; Till Fear and Interest, pow'rful Reasons! join, And whisper her to drop the rash Design. As when some Diamond in Perfection fair, Conceal'd the Owner keeps, with watchful Care; Least tempted by the Sight, some Hand unknown, Might snatch a Prize intended for a Crown! So Freedom over Peace intent presides, And in her Breast the dear Palladium The Palladium was the Image on whose Conservation the Safety of Troy depended. hides. For her the Merchant grateful parts his Store, Assur'd her Bounty can repay him more: For her the Farmer braves the doubtful Fight, Whose Smile alone his Toils can best requite; Each Age, Condition, Sex her Cause maintains, Bless'd while she's safe, and happy while she reigns; All fly to aid, to save her in Distress, And Pray'rs unnumber'd rise for her Success! Thus when the Goddess grows by Insult warm, No Arts can sooth her, no Bravade disarm! Firm she persists to guard the publick Good, And if she sets,—she sets in Seas of Blood! Or chain'd Ambition captive at her Car Dejected glooms, and mourns the threaten'd War! For soon Injustice, Opposition breaks, And Slav'ry shrinks, when Liberty awakes. In pathless Woods where Beasts of Prey reside, And unmolested range the Forest wide, Did ever Fox presume on Wolf to prey? Or Bear attack the Lyon on his Way! No:—conscious they confess superior Pow'r, And seek whom Nature gives them to devour! So when with fiercest Rage Ambition beams, Virtue's Repulse soon cools her lawless Flames; From base Subjection, Pow'r tyrannic grows, But shrinks abash'd, if Freedom firm oppose. Her Voice the Demon with Aversion hears, But let her hate it, welcome The Motto of Caligula applied, Oderint dum metuant. so she fears! But give to false Security the Rein, Soon Servitude creeps in with all her Train; And if that Poison once the State infest, 'Tis only Death can give the Subject Rest. Thus heav'nly Peace from every Danger guards, Protects from Faction, from Invasion wards; With thoughtful Care the State of Things she eyes, “And marks what Stars of Empire set and rise; This Line is taken from Mr Waller. Observes which shine with kind, or baneful Light, And by their Course directs her Conduct right; True to her Faith, she keeps her plighted Word, Averse to Blood,—she draws the righteous Sword; But when her antient Friends Assistance claim, Those who upheld This alludes to the generous Support the States received from our great Q. Elizabeth in their first Struggles for Liberty. her Infancy of Fame! In spite of Art, and every false Disguise, In spite of Force she to their Succour flies; She knows, that Probity once left behind, No longer shines Integrity of Mind! Virtue was only giv'n to bless the Brave, Fear is of Guilt:—the Coward is still a Slave! Why then these close Intrigues,—these artful Snares? Why meddle Foreigners with The Intrigues of the French Embassador, the M. of Fenelon. at the Hague. our Affairs? If dark Ambition link the destin'd Chain, Quick let us arm, and make her Labour vain; Let Vigilance each latent Ill oppose, An Hour of Freedom is too much to lose! If we must fight, 'tis for the noblest End, Peace to preserve, and Property defend; Nor grieve we, tho' our dearest Blood should flow, To guard the highest Blessing Man can know! Thus when ensanguin'd Mars retires to Rest, And Venus lulls the Warrior on her Breast, Tho' no Alarms the troubled Nations shake, Yet Prudence bids experienc'd Peace awake! Nor in her Limits give the Demon Place, Whose deadly Arts occasion'd Rome's Disgrace. Impartial Justice guards her gentle Sway, The Laws which all advantage, all obey; Peace ne'er bestows her delegated Trust, But on the wise, the honest, and the just: Her Favours Fraud and Interest sue in vain, And Impudence she treats with calm Disdain! While modest Merit from its silent Shade, She calls to set in Honour's Light display'd: Nor are her Sons more known for Manners chaste, Than Learning's Stores, and Elegance of Taste: In all her Councils Pallas still presides, Directs her Measures, and her Conduct guides; Which, like the faithful Needle to the Pole, Directive points the Welfare of the Whole! There boundless Commerce spreads the busy Sail, And rich Abundance swells each friendly Gale; Sloth hides abashed her discontented Head, While Industry and Manufactures spread; There potent Gold serves no unrighteous End, Nor Wealth despises Virtue for its Friend; Prosperity with Equity combines, And each with fair Effulgence gently shines: Pow'r smiles in clear Integrity array'd, And Honesty renews the Life of Trade: The Lawyer there defends no wrongful Cause, Nor to By-Ends the Priest Religion draws! Those happy Climes ne'er civil Discord found, Nor social Blood e'er stain'd the spotless Ground! The Peasant, as he ploughs with calm Delight; No Bones (the Marks of former Slaughters) fright; But when the Harvest comes, with joyful Eyes He sees the plenteous Gifts of Ceres rise! And all the Care his peaceful Bosom knows, Is where to lodge the Plenty Heav'n bestows. Thrice happy Land! where Peace distinguish'd reigns, And gilds with Happiness the smiling Plains; Oh favour'd People! while no Clouds impend, Precaution'd, against future Ills defend. When all the Sky a chearful Aspect wears, The careful Pilot for the Storm prepares. So while no Woes th'untroubled State alarm, Let Discipline preserve your Virtue warm; That so Invasion if she comes unseen, May stand repell'd,—and leave your Bounds serene. Like Arms with cankering Rust no longer bright, Let not your Laws unactive shed their Light; Still let the Punishment the Crime attend, Nor Wealth corrupt, nor Pow'r itself defend! So shall your Foes, your steddy Virtue dread, More than if Plains your numerous Armies spread; Nor let Security, empoison'd Guest, Infold your Eyes in her destructive Rest! What Sight can penetrate th'Event to come, Or tell dark Fate's irrevocable Doom? Oft have I seen in Autumn's cloudless Day, When Earth appear'd in all her Splendor gay! With sudden Rage, impetuous The Motto of Caligula applied, Oderint dum metuant. Æölus rise, Unchain the Winds, and darken all the Skies! Rapid as Light, th'invading Storm came on, And from th'astonish'd Eye eclips'd the Sun; Who as displeas'd to see the Ruin made, In gloomy Clouds, abhorrent veil'd his Head, While rattling thick o'er the benighted Plain, Dissolv'd the Tempest in a Flood of Rain! The mournful Peasant from his Hut surveys, The wild Uproar with Horror and Amaze; Marks how the Inundation gathering spreads, And sweeps his Cattle from the level Meads! While o'er his Head the awful Thunders shake, Thro' the thick Gloom redoubled Light'nings break! Each Beast of Prey affrighted seeks his Cave; Then guilty Breasts with conscious Terrors heave; And while Jove's angry Bolts tremendous roll, Celestial Vengeance awes the Tyrant's Soul! But Peace, preventive, wards th'approaching Storm, Her Face no Fears disturb, no Clouds deform; Delighted Nations bless her Guardian Sway, “She gives a double Pleasure to the Day! This Line is taken from Mr Waller. For her rewarded Labour grateful toils, And every Muse-like Art encourag'd smiles; Gay looks the World, as when bestow'd of old Saturnian Years their radiant Courses roll'd; So when the April Show'r with balmy Dews, The Spring awakens, and the Earth renews; Each verdant Flow'r uprears its chearful Head, And Zephyrs mild th'ambrosial Odours spread! While the fair Sun declining to the Main, With inexpressive Charms adorns the Scene; A conscious Pleasure steals upon the Breast, Composing every anxious Care to Rest: Majestic Nature shows her beauteous Face, And wafts around the Joys of heav'nly Peace! The End of the Poem.</field>
   </doc>
</add>