<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Rands, William Brighty, 1823-1882</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Rands, William Brighty, 1823-1882</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">rands william brighty 1823 1882</field>
      <field name="author_text">Rands, William Brighty, 1823-1882</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1870's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.1706.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1871</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466979</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Lilliput Lectures ; By the author of "Lilliput Levee" [i.e. W. B. Rands</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Lilliput Lectures ; By the author of "Lilliput Levee" [i.e. W. B. Rands</field>
      <field name="title_facet">lilliput lectures</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">lilliput lectures</field>
      <field name="title_text">Lilliput Lectures ; By the author of "Lilliput Levee" [i.e. W. B. Rands</field>
      <field name="year_display">1871</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1871</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1871</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466979&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466979&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Rands, William Brighty, 1823-1882&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;rands william brighty 1823 1882&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Lilliput Lectures ; By the author of "Lilliput Levee" [i.e. W. B. Rands&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;lilliput lectures&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1871&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1871&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Rands, William Brighty&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1823&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1882&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Lilliput Lectures&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By the author of "Lilliput Levee" [i.e. W. B. Rands]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Strahan &amp;amp; Co.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1871&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp3271&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;155 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Lilliput Lectures&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By the author of "Lilliput Levee" [i.e. W. B. Rands]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 30 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted; verse extracted from prose text.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">[Great, wide, beautiful, wonderful World] Great, wide, beautiful, wonderful World, With the wonderful water round you curled, And the wonderful grass upon your breast— World, you are beautifully drest. The wonderful air is over me, And the wonderful wind is shaking the tree, It walks on the water, and whirls the mills, And talks to itself on the tops of the hills. You friendly Earth! how far do you go, With the wheat-fields that nod and the rivers that flow, With cities and gardens, and cliffs, and isles, And people upon you for thousands of miles? Ah, you are so great, and I am so small, I tremble to think of you, World, at all; And yet, when I said my prayers to-day, A whisper inside me seemed to say, ‘You are more than the Earth, though you are such a dot: You can love and think, and the Earth cannot!’ [Wild, wandering clouds, that none can tame] Wild, wandering clouds, that none can tame, Shake the sweet rain out to the ground! The sky beyond is still the same, Beyond you hangs the clear blue round. Come, Night, and bind the world again With sevenfold darkness as with bars! Upward, the path will still be plain; The pathway lighted by the stars. [Into the skies, one summer's day] Into the skies, one summer's day, I sent a little Thought away; Up to where, in the blue round, The sun sat shining without sound. Then my Thought came back to me. Little Thought, what did you see In the regions whence you come? And when I spoke my Thought was dumb. But she breathed of what was there, In the pure bright upper air; And, because my Thought so shone, I knew she had been shone upon. Next, by night a Thought I sent Up into the firmament; When the eager stars were out, And the still moon shone about. And my Thought went past the moon, In between the stars, but soon Held her breath and durst not stir, For the fear that covered her; Then she thought, in this demur: ‘Dare I look beneath the shade, Into where the worlds are made; Where the suns and stars are wrought? Shall I meet another Thought? ‘Will that other Thought have wings? Shall I meet strange, heavenly things? Thought of Thoughts, and Light of Lights, Breath of Breaths, and Night of Nights?’ Then my Thought began to hark In the illuminated dark, Till the silence, over, under, Made her heart beat more than thunder. And my Thought came trembling back, But with something on her track, And with something at her side; Nor till she has lived and died, Lived and died, and lived again, Will that awful thing seem plain. [All in the morning early] All in the morning early, The Little Boy in Blue (The grass with rain is pearly) Has thought of something new. He saddled dear old Dobbin; He had but half-a-crown; And jogging, cantering, bobbing, He came to London town. The sheep were in the meadows, The cows were in the corn; Beneath the city shadows At last he stood forlorn. He stood beneath Bow steeple, That is in London town; And tried to count the people As they went up and down. Oh, there was not a daisy, And not a buttercup; The air was thick and hazy, And Blue Boy gave it up. The houses, next, in London, He thought that he would count, But still the sum was undone, So great was the amount. He could not think of robbing, He had but half-a-crown; And so he mounted Dobbin, And rode back from the town. The sheep were in the meadows, The cows were in the corn; Amid the evening shadows He stood where he was born. [‘Strong-builded world, of ancient days] ‘Strong-builded world, of ancient days, Shown to me for a dwelling-place, With heights and depths and many a treasure,— Come, I will count, and weigh, and measure, And know you, house in which I live! And what your chambers have to give;— And far more sure and far more swift Shall grow my use of every gift; From land to land, from age to age, Larger shall grow my heritage. ‘And you, great over-bending roof! You rolling lights that shine aloof For ever! I will know you too, And why you shine, and what you do; And when I know your paths and ways, That too shall help me through the days, Across the seas and round the land, As if God led me by the hand. ‘He leadeth me. He makes me care For every pang his creatures bear! I will arise, and ask aloud Of every pain that cries to God, How it has come. And I shall know, I shall, I shall,—God tells me so And many a pain shall pass away, Like darkness in the light of day.’ Amen! Thus spake the soul of man In every age since time began; And louder grew, and clearer grows, That voice Divine since first it rose:— ‘Wisdom and Love, not Wrath and Chance, Showed me this fair inheritance; And till I know it as I ought, I know not all they meant and thought, When first they showed my world to me, Nor all that I was meant to be:’ Thou gracious voice! go sounding on, Till all the inheritance be won! [The lad and lass were forced to part] The lad and lass were forced to part, They kissed and went along; The sight went into the poet's heart, And it came out a song. The sun, down-sloping in the west, Made gold the evening air; The sight went into the painter's breast, And grew to a picture fair. The mother murmured to her child, And hushed it yet again; The sound, as the musician smiled, Grew music in his brain. The damsel turned, her hair to bind, A flower was in her zone; There grew from out the sculptor's mind, A damsel carved in stone. The song was said, the tune was played, The girl in marble stood, The sunset in the picture stayed, And all was sweet and good. And God, who made these things to be, The damsel and the sun, Colour and sound, and you and me, Was pleased to see it done; And all the angels would be glad If, in the world He built, Although there must be some things sad, No drop of joy were spilt, But all the beauty in the earth, And skies, and hearts of men, Were gently gathered at its birth, And loved, and born again. [How is the world kept going] How is the world kept going Like a river always flowing? The people go hither, The people go thither; They are all alive, Like bees in a hive; They work and they strive, And buy and sell— But who is to tell How the great world is kept agoing? The horses with loads Travel on the roads; On rivers the barges Convey their charges, And all the ocean With ships is in motion, The ships with sails, That carry great bales; And the world is kept going, Like a great river flowing— But how there is not any knowing. The North has granite, And iron; nor can it Grow citron, and melon, and the pleasant limes; The North, too, has firwood, And the East has her wood, Cedar, and sandal, and the trees of the climes; There are grapes in the South, And, cool to the mouth, The red-gold orange; and then there is cork! There is cotton in the West, For the people to work; And everywhere meat; And, all in the heat, There is sago, and rice, and sweet bamboo; And as for the rest, In the Earth's deep chest There is salt, and the gold and the silver too: One country has furs, And another is no worse, Having plenty of wool that is warm and true; Ginger grows in the sun, And cinnamon; And the different things keep going on, Like a river in flowing, Or a wind in blowing, But how there is never any knowing. There are many things extra, But, to end this lecture, There is manufacture In many a texture, And likewise in iron, and tin, and wood; And in all this range The people exchange One thing for another, as to them seems good. For what are things made for? To be bought and paid for In money or in kind, As is plain to the mind; And the best of it all Is this,—that when sending, And selling, and lending All round this ball Are finished and over, The world is in clover, And need never have any fears For ever so many years, Because there is more than enough for us all! [Toys, and treats, and pleasures pass] Toys, and treats, and pleasures pass, Like a shadow in a glass, Like the smoke that mounts on high, Like a noonday's butterfly. Quick they come and quick they end, Like the money that I spend; Some to-day, to-morrow more, Short, like those that went before. Mother, fold me to your knees! How much should I care for these Little joys that come and go If you did not love me so? Father, now my prayer is said, Lay your hand upon my head! Pleasures pass from day to day, But I know that love will stay. While I sleep it will be near; I shall wake and find it here; I shall feel it in the air, When I say my morning prayer. And when things are sad or wrong, Then I know that love is strong; When I ache, or when I weep, Then I know that love is deep. Love is old and love is new, You love me and I love you; And the Lord, who made it thus, Did it in His love for us. [I saw the beauty of the world] I saw the beauty of the world Before me like a flag unfurled, The splendour of the morning sky, And all the stars in company; I thought, How beautiful it is!— My soul said, There is more than this. I saw the pomps of death and birth, The generations of the earth; I looked on saints and heroes crowned, And love as wide as heaven is round; I thought, How wonderful it is!— My soul said, There is more than this. Sometimes I have an awful thought That bids me do the thing I ought, It comes like wind, it burns like flame, How shall I give that thought a name? It draws me like a loving kiss— My soul says, There is more than this. I dreamed an angel of the Lord, With purple wings and golden sword, And such a splendour in his face As made a glory in the place; I thought, How beautiful he is!— My soul said, There is more than this. That angel's Lord I cannot see Or hear, but He is Lord to me; And in the heavens, and earth, and skies,— The good which lives till evil dies,— The love which I cannot withstand,— God writes His name with His own hand. [One Lord there is, all lords above] One Lord there is, all lords above, His name is Truth, his name is Love, His name is Beauty, it is Light, His will is Everlasting Right. But, ah! to Wrong, what is his name? This Lord is a Consuming Flame To every wrong beneath the sun: He is One Lord, the Holy One. Lord of the Everlasting Name, Truth, Beauty, Light, Consuming Flame! Shall I not lift my heart to Thee, And ask Thee, Lord, to rule in me? If I be ruled in other wise, My lot is cast with all that dies, With things that harm, and things that hate, And roam by night, and miss the Gate,— The happy gate, which leads to where Love is like sunshine in the air, And Love and Law are both the same, Named with an Everlasting Name. [I saw a new world in my dream] I saw a new world in my dream, Where all the folks alike did seem; There was no Child, there was no Mother, There was no Change, there was no Other, For everything was Same, the Same; There was no praise, there was no blame; There was neither Need nor Help for it; There was nothing fitting, or unfit. Nobody laughed, nobody wept; None grew weary, and so none slept; There was nobody born, and nobody wed; This world was a world of the living-dead. I longed to hear the Time-Clock strike In the world where the people were all alike; I hated Same, I hated For-Ever, I longed to say Neither, or even Never. I longed to mend, I longed to make, I longed to give, I longed to take, I longed for a change, whatever came after, I longed for crying, I longed for laughter. At last I heard the Time-Clock boom, And woke from my dream in my little room; With a smile on her lips my mother was nigh, And I heard the Baby crow and cry. And I thought to myself, How nice it is For me to live in a world like this, Where things can happen, and clocks can strike, And none of the people are made alike; Where Love wants this, and Pain wants that, And all our hearts want Tit for Tat In the jumbles we make with our heads and our hands, In a world that nobody understands, But with work, and hope, and the right to call Upon Him who sees it and knows us all. [Now, mother, a sweet strong kiss] Now, mother, a sweet strong kiss That will go to the heart very straight! But tell me, mother, who is this, That cometh from the door of heaven, With beautiful garments, from the gate, This that is glorious in her apparel, Travelling in the greatness of her strength? As the strength of seventy times seven Is her strength, and endless the story Of those she hath vanquished in quarrel: For the lands are full of her glory. Her glory hath gone all abroad. For this is the Daughter of God; Men call her sweet Charity, And gentle and sweet is she; As the heart of a rose is her heart, As soft, and as fair, and as sweet: The words of her lips, when they part, Are blessèd: the fall of her feet Is kindly as bells when they beat With joy over wedded true lovers. Yea, Daughter of God. She discovers The ache, and the sin, where it lies, The hunger, the anger, the hate, The madness, the wound, and the want;— She comes, ere it yet be too late. Say, what will ye hide from her eyes? She shall see from afar and arise! She will come with the cup from the font, And the hand that shall heal; and her breath Shall be as the breath of the skies; And down the dusk valley of death, Where the perishing wanders and cries, Her garments shall shine, as she saith, ‘Behold!’ when he thinks that he dies. Nay, the perishing shall not die yet; He shall see of the glory of God, Because that her fair feet are set (Her feet shall be swift on the road) To seek him, and show him the glory. Go to, will ye tell me her story?— In the face of the Lord, where the gold Of the high-columned heaven is uplit, Her story at last shall be told— I will wait, for the end is not yet. [An angel with a golden rod] An angel with a golden rod Measured the City fresh from God; What angel from the heavenly land Measures the place in which I stand? Or counts the souls I see therein With all the good, and all the sin? As stars, as sand beside the sea, The people are that wait with me. The vision is not clear to sight; How should I speak it forth aright? But all the air is soul's desire, And overhead are tongues of fire. Thou mighty rushing wind! what word, What message bear'st thou from the Lord? I hardly see, I hardly hear, For sound of hearts that beat so near. I see that Ancient One who bore To the returning conqueror The bread and wine, the hero's food, And blessed his deed, and called it good. I see the undaunted three who tread The seven-times-heated furnace red; A fourth, beside those saints, I see, And like the Son of God is he. The Ark is here, the Cross, the Dove, And all the flags of heavenly love; I know that at the break of day They come to lift the stone away. I hear a voice from heaven, which saith, ‘He never shall be held of death:’ Write, Angel with the golden rod!— ‘The Son of Man is Son of God.’ What board is this they spread, what feast, Whereat the greatest are the least? What old-new wine is this? what bread? What words of fellowship are said? ‘Oh, join these deeds and days, that part, With life-blood out of Love's own heart! Beyond the Hill of Sacrifice The golden City waiting lies!’ Yea, in this place are pain and sin, Yet Life, I know, is Lord therein; So let the organ blow, and then We each will follow, with Amen! ‘All people that on earth do dwell,’— Thou dear old organ, loudly swell! Whilst all the windows, 'midst the din, Let the gay morning-glory in. The day is here, the night will fall, The ox will slumber in the stall; The night will pass, the day will break, And rested eyes will sweetly wake. So goes the time, so roll the years, With wake and sleep, and smiles and tears, While in the heavens, beyond the Mount, The Lord abides, who keeps the count, And drives the lightning down the skies, And sees when the small sparrow dies; Creator, Saviour, Guide—but stay! Now is the time Amen to say. So let us speak it with a shout, Whilst the old organ plays us out, And we shall know it shakes the floor, Though we have passed beyond the door.</field>
   </doc>
</add>