<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Arnold, Edwin, Sir, 1832-1904</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Arnold, Edwin, Sir, 1832-1904</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">arnold edwin sir 1832 1904</field>
      <field name="author_text">Arnold, Edwin, Sir, 1832-1904</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1880's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.2356.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">1888</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:467423</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Poems national and non-oriental</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Poems national and non-oriental</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poems national and non oriental</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poems national and non oriental</field>
      <field name="title_text">Poems national and non-oriental</field>
      <field name="year_display">1888</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1888</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1888</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467423&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467423&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Arnold, Edwin, Sir, 1832-1904&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;arnold edwin sir 1832 1904&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Poems national and non-oriental&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poems national and non oriental&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1888&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1888&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Arnold, Edwin, Sir&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1832&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1904&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poems national and non-oriental&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Trübner&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1888&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0119&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;viii, 375 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poems national and non-oriental&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 44 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Majority of verse reproduced elsewhere in The English Poetry Full-text Database; only unique items included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Square brackets denote editorial insertions or emendations The Four Crowns. [Written upon the death of the Prince Consort.] Throned before the people Queen of land and sea, While from tower and steeple Crashed the clangorous glee; First of four—enamelled All with kingdoms round— The crown of this our England Upon thy brow was bound. Next, in happiest hours, Came the crown of life; Love's fair wreath of flowers Diademed thee Wife: Hailed, Princess and Woman, Honoured, Queen and Spouse, Half the golden burden Lightened on thy brows. Yet a crown came after, Waiting thee to wear; Little children's laughter Rippled in thine ear. At thy knee, most Noble! Learning how to reign, Princes and princesses Grew—a gracious train. Then, that coronation, Grander than of Queen, Making highest station Higher than had been, Did betide thee! binding On thy drooping brow Sorrow's thorny circlet, Death hath crowned thee now. O our Queen! our Mother! Thou, of all, know'st all; Joy or sorrow—other Cannot hence befall. Sad, imperial Forehead! Sceptred, weary Hand! Widowed Heart! the Greatest And Loneliest in the Land! 1862. To H. R. H. the Princess of Wales ON HER FIRST ARRIVAL IN ENGLAND. Fierce, brown-bearded, enclad in the spoils of wolf and of wild-cat, Keener in ravin than wolves, than wild-cats wilder in onset, Came, in the days gone by, the Danes to the shore of the Angles, Came on an errand of blood—to beleaguer, to burn, and to ravage. Ploughing up furrows of foam on the grass-green meads of the North Sea Steered the old Vikings their course, one hand on the helm of their galley, One on the helves of their axes: and when from Flamborough's foreland, Shading his eyes from the glimmer of sunrise, the watcher beheld them Holding right on for the coast, with the signs and the standards of battle, Loud through the wolds rang the cry, “The Dane! the Dane cometh hither!” Flickered with warning flames the crests of the hills, and the cressets, Mothers and maidens fled inland—fast gathered the bowmen and billmen. Grim the welcome awaiting those strangers!—such greeting as arrows Carry on wings of wrath, such kisses as edge of sword renders;— All their room in the land as much as the length of their lances, Nay, or beneath its turf, the length of the Chieftains who bore them. Fair, golden-haired, and glad with the joy of her youth and her beauty, Daughter herself of a Prince, of a Prince the loved and the chosen, Comes in these happier days the Dane to the shores of the Angles, Comes on an errand of love, to the music of soft hymenæals. Over the silver-green seas, which kiss the keel of her vessel, Bending their foreheads on this side and that to the Maiden of Norseland (Rightfully Lady of Waves by her Father's right and her Husband's), Speeds the sweet Princess to land; and all the voices of gladness Tell that she is arrived whose hand the Prince of the English Takes in the sight of God and man for the hand of his consort— Consort in splendours and cares, in the gloom and the glitter of ruling. Warm the welcome awaiting this lovely and winning invader! Such as men give with the lips when the heart has gone forward before them; Such as a nation of freemen, not apt to flatter for fashion, Make, when the innocent past is a pledge of the happy to-morrows. Princess! weak is one voice in the throng and clamour of voices, Poor one flower in the rain of the roses that shower at thy footsteps, Faint one prayer in the anthem of litanies uttered to bless thee; Yet to thy young fair face I make an Englishman's greeting, On thy path to the altar I lay this wreath from a singer, I—of the men whose fathers encountered thy fathers with battle, I—of the men whose mothers turned pale at the galleys of Denmark, Heralds of happiness now, sea-birds that bring from the Norland Unto our Prince his Bride—and to England omens of gladness. The First Distribution of the Victoria Cross. To-day the people gather from the streets, To-day the soldiers muster near and far; Peace, with a glad look and a grateful, meets Her rugged brother War. To-day the Queen of all the English land, She who sits high o'er Kaisers and o'er Kings, Gives with her royal hand—th'Imperial hand Whose grasp the earth en-rings— Her Cross of Valour to her worthiest;— No golden toy with milky pearls besprent, But simple bronze, and for a warrior's breast A fair, fit ornament. And richer than red gold that dull bronze seems, Since it was bought with lavish waste of worth Whereto the wealth of Earth's gold-sanded streams Were but a lack, and dearth. Muscovite metal makes this English Cross, Won in a rain of blood and wreath of flame; The guns that thundered for their brave lives' loss Are worn hence, for their fame! Aye, listen! all ye maidens laughing-eyed, And all ye English mothers, be aware! Those who shall pass before ye at noontide Your friends and champions are. The men of all the army and the fleet, The very bravest of the very brave, Linesman and Lord—these fought with equal feet Firm-planted on their grave. The men who, setting light their blood and breath So they might win a victor's haught renown, Held their steel straight against the face of Death, And frowned his frowning down. And some that grasped the bomb, all fury-fraught, And hurled it far, to spend its spite away,— Between the rescue and the risk, no thought,— Shall pass our Queen this day; And some who climbed the deadly glacis-side, For all that steel could stay, or savage shell; And some, whose blood upon the Colours dried Tells if they bore them well; Some, too, who, gentle-hearted even in strife, Seeing their fellow or their friend go down, Saved his, at peril of their own dear life, Winning the Civic Crown. Well done for them; and, fair Isle, well for thee! While that thy bosom beareth sons like those “The little gem set in the silver sea” Shall never fear her foes! 1856. In Memoriam. [On the death of Lord Raglan.] Ah! not because our Soldier died before his field was won; Ah! not because life would not last till life's long task were done, Wreathe one less leaf, grieve with less grief;—of all our hosts who led Not least in work and worth approved,—Lord Raglan lieth dead. His nobleness he had of none, War's Master taught him war, And prouder praise that Master gave than meaner lips can mar; Gone to his grave, his duty done; if farther any seek, He left his life to answer them,—a soldier's,—let it speak! 'Twas his to wield a blunted sword,—to fight a fated field, While idle tongues talked victory, to struggle not to yield; Light task for placeman's ready pen to plan a day for fight, Hard work and hot with steel and shot to win that day aright. Tears have been shed for the brave dead; mourn him who mourned for all! Praise hath been given for strife well striven, praise him who strove o'er all, Nor count that conquest little, though no banner flaunt it far, That under him our English hearts with Frost and Plague waged war. And if he held those English hearts too good to pave the path To idle victories, shall we grudge what noble palm he hath? Like ancient Chief he fought a-front, and 'mid his soldiers seen, His work was aye as stern as theirs; oh! make his grave as green. They know him well,—the Dead who died that Russian wrong should cease; Where Fortune doth not measure men,—their souls and his have peace; Aye! as well spent in sad sick tent as they in bloody strife, For English Homes our English Chief gave what he had,—his life. 1853. Florence Nightingale. If on this verse of mine Those eyes shall ever shine, Whereto sore-wounded men have looked for life, Think not that for a rhyme, Nor yet to fit the time, I name thy name,—true Victress in this strife! But let it serve to say That, when we kneel to pray, Prayers rise for thee thine ear shall never know; And that thy gallant deed, For God, and for our need, Is in all hearts, as deep as love can go. 'Tis good that thy name springs From two of Earth's fair things— A stately city and a soft-voiced bird; 'Tis well that in all homes, When thy sweet story comes, And brave eyes fill—that pleasant sounds be heard. Oh voice! in night of fear, As night's bird, soft to hear, Oh great heart! raised like city on a hill; Oh watcher! worn and pale, Good Florence Nightingale, Thanks, loving thanks, for thy large work and will! England is glad of thee— Christ, for thy charity, Take thee to joy when hand and heart are still! 1854. Congratulatory Address. [Recited in the Sheldonian Theatre at Oxford, on the Installation of the Earl of Derby as Chancellor of the University.] Thrice welcome to the seat thy worth hath won! Proud in her grief sad Isis hails her son; Welcome! but question not the tear that starts From the sealed sorrow of a thousand hearts. Welcome! but ask not why in Sheldon's hall The voice must falter, and the greeting fall; Greeting as warm, and joy as deep and proud, As though that greeting and that joy were loud, And faith as firm, and love as true we bear, Though Past and Present mingle smile and tear. We weave two wreaths, we twine two garlands now; One of bright olive for thine honoured brow, And one of cypress for the mighty dust, Who is our memory, as Thou our trust: And therefore mourn we, therefore we rejoice, Shaping glad welcomes with a chastened voice, Because to-day great Arthur's seat we see Vacant of him,—held worthily of thee. Sad and remindful task it were to say What hope and gladness graced the festal day, When, diademed with victory's brightest bays, As knight that entereth after herald's praise, Hither he came; whose fame had come before From Spain's sierras, and the Belgic shore; When Learning's self, forgetting doubt and dread, Unclasped the helmet from her warrior's head, Ungirt the good steel sword his thigh displayed, And wiped the bloody honour from its blade: Nor held unfitting, nor unworthy thought That gentle work her timid fingers wrought, For holiest is the war that winneth peace, And best the strife that biddeth striving cease. And now, (alas, but for our hopes in thee Too dark and mindful were such memory!) The sword that stayed not till the fight was won, The heart that failed not till the right was done; Firm heart and faithful sword, their work is o'er, And the great Captain resteth evermore. But Peace hath victories of deed and word, Won with a subtler weapon than the sword: And civic wreaths a greener gleam display Than the stained garlands of the finished fray: Peace hath her battle-fields, where they who fight Win more than honour, vanquish more than might, And strive a strife against a fiercer foe Than one who comes with battle-axe and bow. And this was thine! War's tempest fled away, Leaving thy destinies a fairer day; The eagles slept, the lion-flags were furled, No battle-thunder shook the weary world, No steel-clad legions, merciless of mood, Stained the sweet meadows with their mowers' blood; But Peace, yet bleeding from the lance of War, And Trust, and Truth, and Plenty, frighted far, Learning, uplooking from her lettered scroll, And Science, starting at the drum's deep roll, And angry Justice, with white spreading wings, Leaving for ever earth and earthly things; These to win back, to comfort, and to calm, Till War's wild pæan sank to peaceful psalm, And English homes, untenanted no more, Held hopes, and loves, and laughter, as before; Senates to sway, and councillors to lead, With earnest eloquence and ready deed, And, sailing o'er a deep and dangerous flood, To watch one guiding-star, thy country's good. To hold to honour, for dear honour's sake, Till Faction envied what it might not shake; The right to succour, and the wrong subdue;— This was thy triumph, these thy Waterloo! Well through that bloodless fight thy virtue bore The Stanley's banner, stainless as of yore, The silver shield that wears no trait'rous blot, The legend of the faith that changes not. The motto of the Stanley family is “Sans changer.” Then once again, glad greeting! once again Joy dries the tear, and Pleasures banish Pain; The stream-girt city of the tower and dome Bids thee high welcome to thine early home,— Thou hear'st from tongue to tongue the tributes borne, Where thy first laurel-wreath was won and worn; Here, in an old and well-remembered scene,— Here, where thy verse hath rung, thy voice hath been, Oxford, who sent thee forth, receives in pride, Once her young son, now her grown guard and guide. Bold in thy love, and steadfast in thy strength, Hope hath won Memory to smile at length:— Only, in other days, if need there be To tell our grief for him, our love for thee, Be this the sign:—that when we sorrowed most, Mourning at once our Bulwark and our Boast, To solace best a deep and anxious grief, And best to honour England's buried chief, We chose no meaner name, no lower line To grace his seat, and guard her fame, than thine. 1854. The Order of Valour. Thus saith the Queen! “For him who gave His blood as water in the fight, So he from Russian wrong might save My crown, my people, and my right; Let there be made a cross of bronze And grave thereon my queenly crest; Write valour on its haughty scroll, And hang it on his breast.” Thus saith the Land! “He who shall bear Victoria's cross upon his breast, In token that he did not fear To die, had need been, for her rest; For the dear sake of her who gives, And the high deeds of him who wears, Shall, high or low, all honour have From all, through all his years.” February 1856. On the Death of the Princess Alice. [It will be remembered that Her Royal Highness died of diphtheria, contracted from the caresses of her little son, whom she was nursing.] Tender and true! whose virtue was thy crown! Whose royalty was royally to live! Death, sent to fetch thee, laid his arrow down, And prayed that Love the bitter call would give; But Love, who could not stop such gentle breath, Whispered thy child to give the Kiss of Death! Havelock in Trafalgar Square. The foot set firm! the hand upon the hilt! The warrior-gaze, as innocent of fear As any maid's of shame! which, past the guilt, And blood and battle, sees the triumph clear; Stand so in bronze! large to thy levelled eye, In the supreme imperial peril dawning, “Hoc signo vinces” shines upon the sky; And, calm as one who knows his Master's warning, Stand thou in bronze! stand, what thou wert, a Rock, Whereon Rebellion's yeasty billows breaking Drove wave on wave—dashed high—and from the shock Fell back in shattered foam; thyself unshaking: So stand!—the busy feet of men go by thee, Each one to-day the safer for that sword; Meeanee's just and valiant chief is nigh thee, Palmerston, Beaconsfield, the great Sea-lord,— Well met in some far-off serenest session, The unimpassioned rest of great men gone; And here together set—love's poor profession!— In storied effigy and sculptured stone. Ah! speaking stone and bronze, cunningly graven To show these Champions of the English name, Are men's hearts such, that knave and fool and craven Can pass ye daily, and be still the same? But, true and faithful servant! somewhere plaining That labour multiplies and wage is none, Read Havelock's history, and thereby gaining The comfort of his courage, copy one Who all life's chilly spring and summer dreary Wrought in pure patience what he found to do, Possessing his own soul—not once a-weary— Content, because God was contented too. Wherefrom he hived that honey which is sweetest, The fruit of all the flowers of all a life, A wisdom so perfected, so completest, Great soldiers gave him place to stem the strife: Which never given, Havelock's highest glory Had lacked our knowledge, not his Master's praise, One splendid page been lost from England's story, But not one leaf from his immortal bays. Go to! and work—God's servant—serving men; Bethinking how the ranks closed up, and cried, “Way for the General!” and his answer then,— “You have made way, my lads!”—fair time for pride! Adelaide Anne Procter. “ILICET.” In Roman households, when their dear ones died, Thrice by his name the living called the dead; And, silence only answering as they cried, Ilicet—“go thou then!”—the mourners said. Ilicet! let her part! the Poet's child, Herself a mistress of the lyric song: Ilicet!—to a world so sad and wild To wish her back were far less love than wrong. Ilicet! hard the word for those to say Who know what gentleness is gone from earth; Harder for those whose dwelling, day by day, Shone with her presence—echoed to her mirth: Yet, if He wills it—whom she soars to meet, The Lord of this world's vineyard—shall we ask, Who toil on, in the burden and the heat, A later wage for her—a longer task? Ilicet! let her go! though it were brave,— In the hot vintage, where the strongest fail, Weeding God's grapes from thistles—still to have Her silver hymns o'er weariness prevail! To hear her gentle, certain spirit of ruth Share its great sureties with less happy brothers, And—from eyes bright with Heav'n's light—teach the truth Of “little children pleading for their mothers.” Ilicet! Otherwhere they need those strains, Sounding so true for men—albeit low; A throne was vacant (though its steps were pains), For a soul, tried, pure, perfect—let her go! Sigh not “so young!”—“such promise!”—“ah! a flower That longer life had sunned to fruit of gold.” Be still and see!—God's year, and day, and hour, By lapse of mortal minutes is not told. Who go are called—ilicet! let her go! Though a sweet harp is silent in the land, A soft voice hushed—and, never more below, Poet and poet's child join song and hand. Ilicet! ilicet! nos ibimus!— To that divinest region of the skies, Whence with clear sight she sees, knows, pities us, We shall attain!—Vex not the dead with sighs. To America. [Dedication of a Volume of Poems.] Thou new Great Britain! famous, free, and bright! West of thy West sleepeth my ancient East; Our sunsets make thy noons; Daytime and Night Meet in sweet morning-promise on thy breast. Fulfil the promise, Lady of wide lands! Where, as thine own, an English singer ranks: I, who found favour at thy sovereign hands, Kiss them; and at thy feet lay these, for thanks. Armageddon. A WAR SONG OF THE FUTURE. Marching down to Armageddon— Brothers, stout and strong! Let us cheer the way we tread on With a soldier's song! Faint we by the weary road, Or fall we in the rout, Dirge or Pæan, Death or Triumph!— Let the song ring out! We are they who scorn the scorners— Love the lovers—hate None within the world's four corners— All must share one fate; We are they whose common banner Bears no badge or sign, Save the Light which dyes it white— The Hope that makes it shine. We are they whose bugle rings, That all the wars may cease; We are they will pay the Kings Their cruel price for Peace; We are they whose steadfast watchword Is what Christ did teach,— “Each man for his Brother first— And Heaven, then, for each.” We are they who will not falter— Many swords or few— Till we make this Earth the altar Of a worship new; We are they who will not take From palace, priest, or code, A meaner Law than “Brotherhood”— A lower Lord than God. Marching down to Armageddon— Brothers, stout and strong! Ask not why the way we tread on Is so rough and long! God will tell us when our spirits Grow to grasp His plan! Let us do our part to-day— And help Him, helping Man! Shall we even curse the madness, Which for “ends of State” Dooms us to the long, long sadness Of this human hate? Let us slay in perfect pity Those that must not live; Vanquish, and forgive our foes— Or fall—and still forgive! We are those whose unpaid legions, In free ranks arrayed, Massacred in many regions— Never once were stayed: We are they whose torn battalions, Trained to bleed, not fly, Make our agonies a triumph,— Conquer, while we die! Therefore, down to Armageddon— Brothers, bold and strong— Cheer the glorious way we tread on With this soldier's song! Let the armies of the old Flags March in silent dread! Death and Life are one to us, Who fight for Quick and Dead! To Matthew Arnold. [“FROM EDWIN ARNOLD.”] Suffer that—as thou takest boat to cross Grim Charon's tide, on voyage, heavy loss To England—but to thee gain manifold— I pluck thee by the shroud, and press thy cold Forgetful hand; to lay this obolus Into its honoured palm! Ah! think on us In thy new walks upon the Asphodel; Nor quite forsake the sad sphere where we dwell, Fighting thy battle, lending our small stress To “stream which maketh unto Righteousness!” Now, that thou better knowest friends and foes, Good Friend! dear Rival! bear no grudge to those Who had not time, in Life's hard fight, to show How well they liked thee for thy “slashing blow;” How “sweet” thy “reasonableness” seemed; how right Thy lofty pleading for the long-dimmed “light!” Thou, that didst bear my Name, and deck it so That—coming thus behind—hardly I know If I shall hold it worthily, and be Meet to be mentioned in one Age with thee— Take, Brother! to the Land where no strifes are, This praise thou wilt not need! Before the Star Is kindled for thee let my funeral torch Light thee, great Namesake! to th'Elysian Porch! Dead Poet! let a poet of thy House Lay, unreproved, these bay-leaves on thy brows! We, that seemed only friends, were lovers: Now Death knows it! and Love knows! and I! and Thou! April 15, 1888. Song of the German Soldiers in Alsace. In Alsace, over the Rhine, There lives a Brother of mine; It grieves my soul to say He hath forgot the day We were one land and line. Dear Brother, torn apart, Is't true that changed thou art? The French have clapped on thee Red breeches, as we see; Have they Frenchified thy heart? Hark! that's our Prussian drum, And it tells the time has come. We have made one “Germany,” One “Deutchland,” firm and free; And our civil strifes are dumb. Thee also, fighting sore, Ankle-deep in German gore, We've won. Ah! Brother dear, Thou art German—dost thou hear? They shall never part us more. Who made this song of mine? Two comrades by the Rhine;— A Suabian man began it, And a Pomeranian sang it, In Alsace, over the Rhine. 1871. Berlin.—The Sixteenth of March. [On the Burial of the Emperor William.] Thunder of Funeral Guns! Deep, sad Bells! with your boom; Sorrowful voices of Soldiers and Folk! Whom lay ye here in the Tomb? “Whom?” the Cannons reply— Baying like Dogs of War Whose Master is gone on a path unknown— “Our Glory, and Lord, and Star!” “William, Kaiser and King, For him our iron throats yell; Victor we hailed him on many a field, We make to his soul farewell!” “Whom?” say the slow-swinging bells— “William, pious and dear! Ofttimes he knelt to the King of Kings Where now he lies on his bier!” “He took from his God alone The Crown of the Fatherland; And now he hath given it back undimmed To Death's all-masterful hand!” “Whom?” shout the serried ranks— Guardsmen and Jagers and all— “The lordliest Lord and the kingliest King That ever raised battle-call!” “At his word we thronged to the Field, Sure of success to betide; Sure that the Kaiser would fight for peace, Sure of Heaven on our side!” “Whom?” sigh women and men, And fair-haired Germany boys, And girls, with eyes of his cornflower's hue, “For our Father we raise our voice!” “William the Emperor dead! Lo! he made us one Land! Thanks to him and his chosen chiefs, Strong and secure we stand!” “Steadfast from birth to death, Whatso was Right he wrought! Duty he loved, and his people, and home! Now to dust he is brought!” Thunder of Funeral Guns! We hear you with English ears; In English breasts it echoes—sad bells! This tiding your tolling bears! Warriors, stalwart and fierce! We see you are tender and true; We are come of a kindred blood, we share This sorrow, to-day, with you! Folk of the Fatherland! Our hearts for your grief are fain! God guard your Kaiser Frederick, And give ye good days again!</field>
   </doc>
</add>