<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Breton, Nicholas, 1545-1626</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Breton, Nicholas, 1545-1626</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">breton nicholas 1545 1626</field>
      <field name="author_text">Breton, Nicholas, 1545-1626</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_P10032.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1613</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:467608</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The vncasing of Machivils Instructions to his sonne ; VVith the Answere to the same</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">The vncasing of Machivils Instructions to his sonne ; VVith the Answere to the same</field>
      <field name="title_facet">vncasing of machivils instructions to his sonne</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">vncasing of machivils instructions to his sonne</field>
      <field name="title_text">The vncasing of Machivils Instructions to his sonne ; VVith the Answere to the same</field>
      <field name="year_display">1613</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1613</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1613</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467608&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467608&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Breton, Nicholas, 1545?-1626?&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;breton nicholas 1545 1626 &lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The vncasing of Machivils Instructions to his sonne ; VVith the Answere to the same&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;vncasing of machivils instructions to his sonne&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1613&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1613&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Breton, Nicholas&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1545&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1626&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The vncasing of Machivils Instructions to his sonne&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;VVith the Answere to the same&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Thomas Bushell&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1613&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp5021&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;28, [23] p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The vncasing of Machivils Instructions to his sonne&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;VVith the Answere to the same&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 110 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CONTENTS. Machiauils rules doe whet the purest wits, And doe expell them from their idle fits: To wisemen they shewe the worlds follie, With notice of preuenting deedes vnholie: Which is the true intent of the Authors meaning, How euer fooles their iudgements are bestowing. Though the beginning doe of harshnesse taste, And many things are hudled vp in hast: And though there be instruction to ill, Good vnderstanding the same doth kill, And turnes those words vnto the truest sense, Which for those faults doth make a recompence. As the Answere by degrees plainly showes, What duty to Vertue each creature owes. Condemne not all, till all be throughly past, If first be worst, the best is kept till last. THE VNCASING OF MACHIAVILS INSTRVCTION TO His Sonne. Com hither sonne &amp; learn thy fathers lore: It is not now as it hath bin before; For in my youth would no man reade to me, That now in age I can deliuer thee. If thou wilt be a man of much esteeme, Be not the same what euer so thou seem; Speak fair to al, be gentle, curteous kind, But let the world know nothing of thy minde: Let slip no time may be for thine auaile, Nor trust no friend, for faith begins to faile. Refuse no gift to fill thy coffers full; The wisest poore man passeth for a gull. Be temperate in affect, sober in talke, And often make a solitarie walke: Tickle conceits, commit to memorie; For written lines may lie in ieopardie. Affect no follies, do no quarrels moue, And if thou loue thy selfe fall not in loue: Haue care for all men, conferre with few, And count faire wordes to be but as a dew. Follow the time, finde humours, flatter pride, And praise the Groome, but only please the Bride. Promise enough, but not performe too much, But with thy betters euermore keep touch. Striue not with great ones, meddle not with small, For trifles trouble not thy selfe withall. Frequent the Church, make shew of great deuotion, And be not bashfull to receiue promotion. Looke big at Beggers, weare thy clothes neat, And spend not too much money at thy meat. Saue thy Horse charges at thy cousins stable, And take thy trencher at anothers table. Breake iests on cowards, but take heed of knaues, And loue no Bawdes for they are beastly slaues. Be perfect in Arithmeticks close art, In all accounts to make a sauing part. Stand not to stare vpon a Peacocks taile; Who if he see his legges, will stoup his saile. When Iack-dawes chatter let their language goe, Better be silent then to prattle so. Obserue the Lion, but do not stirre the Beare, And loue the Wolfe but onely for his haire: Learne of the Asse to beare, the Dogge to wait, And of the Ape, to counterfeit conceit. Catch not at Flies, they are but Swallowes food, But loue the meate that nourisheth the blood. Feed like a Wolfe on blood while it is warme, He is a foole that feeles anothers harme: Yet seeme as kind as she that seemes to crie, To see him sicke that she could wish to die. Take heed of interest, gage no land, And from assurance euer keepe thy hand. Take no mans word, for coine is hard to get, And 'tis a custome now to pay no debt. Learne to get riches by the beggers purse: The Fox fares best when Geese begin to curse. Worke all the weeke for profit euery way, Keepe conscience onely for the holy day. Prie into trades to traffique, traine, and tricke, And liue not by the dead but by the quicke. And if thou be a Courtier, know thy place, But do not serue for onely shew of grace: But let thy profit answer thy expence, Lest want do proue a wofull patience; And thou doe proue the prouerb often tolde, A carelesse Courtier young, a begger olde. If that thou be a Scholar and canst preach, And knowest how the vnlearned sort to teach, Let neuer conscience at thy profit knocke, But share the Sheepe, and fleece another flocke: For be thou poore, what e're thy preaching be Thy Parish will not care a pin for thee. If that thou be a Souldier serue for fame, But let thy golden pay maintaine the same: For he that spends more then he gets in fight, Will be a begger though he be a Knight. If that thou be a Lawyer know thy right, But keepe thy Client in a cunning plight: For how canst thou a heartie pleading hold, If that thy tongue be not well tipt with gold? And rich attir'd, thou shalt haue roome to stand To plead thy cause what e're thou hast in hand; But barely clad, and in a poore aray, Thou may'st perhaps haue hearing at Doomes day: For though the Law be right, and Iudge be iust, Yet with the rich the begger must not thrust. If that thou be a Merchant know thy trade, And of thy wares what reckning may be made; And be not lauish in a leaud expence, Lest bankrout proue a bad experience. If that thou be a Crafts-man know thy paines, And let no Alehouse eat out all thy gaines; For if expence aboue thy gettings goe, Thou wilt be quickly in the beggers rowe. What saies the crafty Clowne in clowted shooes; Time was ordain'd to get, and not to loose. VVhat though the poore lye staruing in the ditch? It is the dearth of Corne makes Farmers rich. Weare not thy shooes to short, not cloake to long, Vse thy friend well, but doe thy selfe no wrong. Abandon fooles, make much of cunning wits, But fauour most, that most thy profit sits: Sit not vp to late, except it be for gaine; For want of sleepe is hurtful for the braine. Goe not to Sea, whiles thou mai'st liue on land, Lest scaping rockes, thou fall vpon a sand. Be sociable in euery company, But haue no hand in any villany. “If thou finde humors to passe reasons race, “Depart in time, let others take thy place, “Such companions better lost then found, “Vaine humored wits cannot be very sound: “Though for thy gaine, thou kindly dost entreat them, “Yet know thy time, when, and how to reiect them. Be conuersant with strangers, learne languages, Sound their estates, and note their carriages, Know their seuerall wares, their worth, and prises, But trouble not thy head with vaine deuises. “Do thou seuerely looke to euery action, “And let their errors yeeld thee satisfaction, “That thou by them mai'st easily seeke to rise, “In doing this, the rich will hold thee wise. Aime still at profit, howsoe're it growes, Make the winde serue, wheresoe're it blowes “Then cheerely hoist vp saile, and on apace, “Labouring so that thou arriue with grace: “Then welcome home, if crownes thou hast good store, “But wanting that, respectlesse euermore. “No pennie, no Pater noster men crie, “And that pouertie parts good companie. “These prouerbs old, thou seest are very true; “If thou hast wealth, what miserie can insue? “All men will then grace thee with cap and knee, “And praise thy life how vilde soe're thou be: For 'tis this wealth, this profit, and this gaine, That dyes the colour euermore in graine. Learne thou the Physitians and the Lawyers fee, And for thy profit speake as faire as hee: Promise the one good speed, the other good health; In any course 'tis good to gather wealth. “Men must not liue these dayes by foolish pittie, “In getting coyne accounted very wittie. Learne all diseases and their seuerall cures, And care not what the patients heart endures; But giue him one day griefe, another ease, Not as his patience, but as his purse doth please. “It is not sighes, nor sobs, nor pinching paine “Thou must respect, when that thou seek'st for gain. “Let them grieue, chafe, and euermore be fretting, “So thou by them may'st happily be getting. Learne Cards and Dice, and euery cheating play That may bring in thy profit any way. Learne thou to stop a Card or cogge a Die, But shift it cleanly from the gamesters eye. At Ruffe and Trumpe note thou the dealers rubs, There is no pack without the Knaue of Clubs. “Pittie not when thou hast caught the connie, “Oh how sweet it is to share the monie! “It makes good cheere, and welcomes many a guest “Vnto a stately house, a stately feast, “And brings content while pittie sits and pines, “In griefe and paine, and many hungrie signes, “When louely wealth in Iouiall spirit sings, “Soaring aloft with richest golden wings; “Commanding all those vassals poore and base, “And euer seated in the highest place, “With pleasure feeding on the daintiest faire, “And all delights accounted very rare, “With Musicke sweet, much mirth and iollitie, “With gallant sports and merrie companie. “Thinke on these, and do but rightly weigh them, “Thrice happy he, so happie hath them: “Be carefull then that something may come in; “Though some repine thou need'st not care a pin: “For when those meanes vnto thy coffer sends, “A Pot or a Pinte makes a foole amends; “Yet bestow not this nor any else vpon him, “Except to gaine some greater matter by him. “Seeke any meanes or course that may inrich thee, “The richest sort then kindly will embrace thee. Dandle the childe, grow inward with the Nurse, And thinke no beggerie base that fils the purse. “Be not ouer-nice nor coy amongst proude ones, “Humor them, and flatter thou the small ones; “That they as instruments may serue thy turne. “Stand farther off when thou begin'st to burne: “Haue conference with as many as require it, “And be merrie with those that desire it. “But still be sure to keepe thy tongue from prating, “Which is most base, and breedeth euer hating: “Trust not too farre, though promises be made, “Lest that the substance turne vnto a shade. “Great dangers lie in shewes of seeming kinde, “He is a foole lets all men know his minde: “First trie, then trust, according to thy pleasure, “Be pleasing to all, yet all within a measure. Laugh with the Leacher, at maidens bashfulnesse, And with the chaste, at fleshes filthinesse. And with the Spend-thrift, at the Misers bags, And with the Miser, at the beggers rags; “And with the Glutton, at poore hungry c heare, “And with the hungry, at a pleanteous yeare; “And with the learned, at a simple wit, “And with the foolish, at a frenzie fit; “And with the crafts-men, when they are deceiuing “So that something to thee may be sharing. Learne all Religions, be of euery Sect, And chiefely to thy profit haue respect. “Let conscience knocke, care not for that at all, “If thou hast coine, no matter who doe fall? For this same conscience is so poore and bare, That most shee shifts amongst the beggers share. “Induring hunger, cold, and bitter stormes, “Reprochful termes, with many hurts and harmes; “Coursely clad, all rags, and worne asunder, “And worst of all, basely still kept vnder. “In meane estate helplesse still remaining, “Of better sorts euermore disdaining. In summe, of what estate so ere thou be, Learne to be rich, for that will hold with thee, “What matter though men point at thy folly, “Thou mai'st with the purest seeme as holy: “With yea and nay, verely and indeed, “With demured looke wish them good speede, “Which is a cloake sufficient for thy euill, “Almost able to deceiue the Deuill. “And accuse them, that say thou offerest wrong, “Such cruell deedes to wicked doth belong. “This is the course, in humoring euery sect, “A better meanes thy profit to respect. “Of these pure-ones, learne to dissemble so; “Thine shall be the profit whosoe're the woe. Perswade a slaue he is halfe a Gentleman, Though he doe drop out of of a dripping pan: It is no matter if his purse can beare it, His rascall pride will neuer blush to heare it. “Extoll a foole, and he will still be grinning, “No matter what, so thou by him be winning. Perswade a Clowne that he is halfe a Knight, And that his wealth deserues the place aright: And his Maid marrian with her wain-scot face, Might be a Lady but for lacke of grace, And make her thinke that she is halfe a Queene, Or scarce on earth is such an other seene, For vertue, beauty, wit, shape, and feature, Though God he knows, that she is no such creature But if she doe applaude it, 'tis no matter, He is a foole, for profit cannot flatter. Time is now to trifle or dandle, For gaine, fore the Diuell, hold a candle: And hold it as a deed that's wisely done, Or as as a prize that's brauely wone. Commend a Souldier when he is in Crownes, And sweare a Knight must gouerne ouer Clownes; In many a Campe how he his Caske did beare, Although poore Coward he did ne're come there. But yet thy flattery be sure so to frame, Thine may be the gaine, though his the shame. “If thou findest him simple with money store, “I hope thou wilt finde wit to make him poore. “Then smiling say, I pitty your estate “It is with you now, as 'twas of late: “But be content, no doubt but God will send, “With this depart, his monies thine to spend; “Then see thou meete him not in any case, “Nor come not in where he shall be in place, “Lest to expence, he after seekes to driue thee, “Or by some meanes borrowes mony of thee: “Tut: let him shift, say thou thy mon'is gone, “Care not thou at all, though he make his mone: “But wish him well, as most men now doe vse, “Finde any meanes that may thy purse excuse. “Let men be lauish, and commend them too, “Say 'tis brauely done, but feed on them too: “Be sure of this, and do't in any case, “Looke well about, that thou hast time and place; “Lest that some Machiauill chance to spie it, “Discloseth all, to gaine something by it. Commed the Lawier, and his studious reading; Admire his iudgements, but extoll his pleading: But flatter so, that if he get a fee, Thou mai'st haue out a share as well as hee. “Be plotting so, that still thou maist bee getting; “Few Lawiers grieue at their Clients fretting. “To sue in Forma pauperis, 'tis in vaine, “VVhen most Lawers poore sutors doe disdaine. “They must be humored, sued, and sought to still, “And all things else, obedient to their will. “That this is true, thou daily mai'st behold, “How deearely they, esteeme a fee of gold. Follow a Bishop with a world of praise, And make him as a Load-starre of the daies; Admire him and extoll him to the skies; But so that thou mai'st get a Benefice. A good Vicarage, Cure, or some such, As will returne thee profit small or much. “Looke to't in time, strike whiles the Iron's hot, “Vse no delay where wealth is to be got. “You know that seruice is no heritage: “VVhat bootes a man to stand on parentage? “But look to the maine chance, t'is that must hold, “He's accounted well borne, that hath much gold, “To serue in hope, is but a Beggers fee, “And such rewards most masters vse you see: “Or after two or three yeeres seruice turne thee off, “And for thy seruice done bestow a scoffe: “Or if perhaps, thou serue till thou grow olde, “Happy if an Almes-house thine age can hold. “This is the flinty course of this our age, “This is the time brings humors in a rage. “Then list in time, serue not except for gaine, “Let masters feele the toile of seruants paine. “Serue not those, whose senses haue no feeling, “Or those that with leaden hands are giuing. “Applaude them not with courteous reuerence, “When they are so farre from due beneuolence. “Scorne his blew Coate, his Cogniscence, and all, “That shall reioice in a poore seruants fall. Commend a Merchant, honour his aduenture, Who gets his welth by danger not endenture: Commend his trade, his traffike and his truth, The honour of his age, and toile of youth: “Say how you haue heard him much commended, “And with worthy Art himselfe defended, “Gainst forraine foes by Land and Seas, “And smoothly slipt it off, himselfe to please. But withall be sure to flatter so, That to thy purse, some peece of mony growe: Or on his boord thy trencher to be laid, Or borrowed money neuer to be paid. And tell (what lackeye) that he lackes no wit, And for his head that he deserues to sit On higher seats then Church-wardens stooles, For he hath more wit then a world of fooles; But yet in feeding of his idle vaine, Be sure to picke out some od priuie gaine. “It is a follie then to stand on nicenesse, “For that at such times is counted basenesse. “Thou must boldly looke vp and seeme merrie, “When profit comes in who can be wearie? “Refuse nothing that comes in any way, “It is a bad thing serues not another day. A Rapier, Dagger, Stockings, Bootes or Shooes, Somwhat doth well thogh beggers must not choose. “If one giue thee Venison, what need'st thou care “How he came by it so it mend thy fare? “Stand not to question in any case; “He may thinke thou mean'st to seeke his disgrace, “By telling abroad to strangers vnknowne, “How he had Venison, though more of his owne. “Alwayes looke to thy tongue, no more but mum, “Euer be silent so any thing come; “Yet know thy time when to speake, when to spare, “Keeping this course accounted very rare. Tell mistresse Minkes, she that keepes the shop, Shee is a Ship that beares a gallant top; Shee is a Ladie for her louely face, And her countenance hath a Princes grace, “And that her beautie hath inthral'd thee so: “Except she yeelds remorse shee workes thy woe; “Then cast thine eye vpon her beautious cheeke, “Protesting that thou neuer saw'st the like: “Her smooth forehead, and her comely dressing; “Her louely Breasts cause loues increasing; “Her Iuorie teeth, her lip and chin; “Her snow white hand, the like was neuer seene; “Her legge and foote, with her gate so comely; “Her apparrell worne so neat and seemely. “Thus o're worne with care thou mai'st seeme to be, “Till thou hast made her proude her selfe to see. “Then she nods the head with smiling fauour, “That thou should'st bestow such loue vpon her: Then bite the lip, winke and hange the head, And giue a sigh as though thy heart were dead, And shew strange passions of affections sence, That she may pittie loue sir reuerence: “Wishing her selfe worthy of thy fauour, “Which is a meanes to gaine something by her. Thus let the issue of this cunning be, That from her purse some comfort come to thee: A piece of Sattin, Fustian, or some Stuffe, A Falling-band, or a three-double ruffe, A Hat, a Shirt, a Cloake-cloth, or a Ring, Kniues, Purses, Gloues, or some such prettie thing; Somewhat hath some sauor, 'tis this gaine That still inuention giues his sweetest vaine. “It cheeres a bodie weake, and comfort sends “To any one that's ill or voyde of friends: “It brings the infant vp, for want might pine, “Else charitie small comfort would resigne. “To middle age it nourisheth the blood, “And giues them all, and all that may be good; “And aged men it luls them fast asleepe, “Whose youth took care this pretious gem to keep. “Be carefull then how thou keepe this by thee, “Lest when thou wantest it quite forsake thee; “And leaue thee to wander, still reiected: “My boy looke too't and seeke to preuent it. VVhy tell a Cobler he is halfe a King, VVhen on his patches he can sit and sing, And knock his Last, and whet his cutting knife, There is no Kingdome to a merrie life: “A light heart lightly beares the bell away, “When mightie men find cares, though clothed gay; But yet in telling of this idle tale, Be sure at least to get a pot of Ale, “Or something else that hath a feeling sense, “Take any thing as part of recompence, “And seeme very thankfull till better comes, “Sith many small things adde to greater summes. For this same Nothing brings no world about, Better play small game then be cleane shut out. If that thy wife be faire, and thou but poore, Let her stand like a picture at thy doore; VVhere though she do but picke her fingers ends, Faire eyes fond lookes will gaine a world of friends: “Taske her not to worke if she be prettie; “Bid her forbeare, her toyle makes thee pittie: “She may with ease haue meanes for greater gaines, “VVith rich rewards and pleasure for her paines. Play at bo-peepe, see me and see me not, It comes off well that is so closely got, And euermore say, aye well fare the vent That payes the charges of the house and rent. “Come, come, 'tis no matter, be rul'd by this, “The finest Dames doe sometimes do a misse: “Yet walke demure like puritans indeed, “And early rise to a Sermon for a neede; “And make great shew of deuoutest prayer, “VVhen she onely goes to meet her louer, “Turning backe poore foole, desires the text, “She tels him any thing that cometh next: “And turning o're the leafe to reade the verse, “Scarse for laughing one word can rehearse: “But prettily turnes it off with some iest; “He beares with all, he knowes it is his best. “If that thy wife be olde, thy Daughters young, “And faire of face, and of a fluent tongue: “If by her sutors siluer may be had; “Beare with small faults, the good will helpe the bad. “Be not too seuere, time may mend their faults; “He is a foole before a cripple haults: “Or he that findes a fault where gaine comes in, “'Tis pittie but his cheekes should e're looke thin: “What though thou knowst that vice do gain it all; “Will vertue helpe when thou beginst to fall? “This is no world for vertuous men to thriue, “'Tis worke enough to keepe thy selfe aliue. “Let wife and daughters loue to make thee wealthy; “Thou knowst that gold will seek to make thee healthy. If thy maid seruants be kind hearted wenches; And closely make kinde bargaines on the benches, “Let them haue libertie, loue, and pleasure: “All these are helpes to bring in thy treasure. “Let them laugh and be merrie, it yeelds content, They'll humour all till all their coyne is spent. If by their pleasures may thy profit grow, Winke at a wanton, who hath not beene so? Make loue to twentie wenches in one day, But let no poore lasse leade thy heart away: “For that's in vaine, thy labour then is lost; “Such idle loue can neuer quit thy cost: “It brings a charge, and sends a heauie clog, “And makes thy life as seruile as a dog: “From house to house thou shalt be haunted then, “And cleane exempt from the loue of men. “A plague that's worse; shee's iealous euermore: “This the true course of a loue that's poore. “Or if by chance her husband wealth doth gaine, “She straight growes proud, which is a beastly vaine. “Thus wealth and ease cannot with such agree: “Then let them passe my sonne, be rul'd by me: But where thou find'st good store of land or gold, There lay closely to purchase a Free-hold. “Clap her aboord, and brauely hoist vp saile, “Shoot her in the poop, Ducke haue at thy taile: “The prize is thine owne, thou hast got it faire, “Thou must be briefe then in getting an heire: And be not so squeamish at a nice conceit, That may perswade thee from a pleasing bait. “Stand not like a Woodcocke sneking in the cold, “But set it out with a grace, and be bold. “To make thy selfe simple with a shew of want, “Or that thy meanes at all grow very scant, “God-night Nichole, thy friends will be packing; “Or by vilde disgrace thy credit cracking. “These are the pleasures of a poore estate, “Be rich then if thou can'st possible hate, “Keep good clothes on thy backe, and neatly weare them, “What want soeuer comes doe not pawne them: “For once being gotten in the Diuels iawes, “He will surely keepe them in with his pawes. “If thy apparrell be something cleanly, “Though in thy purse thou hast ne're a pennie: “Men may in some measure yet esteeme thee, “And a farther grace happely giue thee. “Doe not seeme base though penilesse thou art, “But looke about of whom to get a part: “Then make much of that and keepe it closely; “Seeke for treasure and keepe it wisely. Get all contentment that the world can giue, For after death who knoweth how we liue? Strange things are spoken, and beleeue the best, And leaue the worst, I leaue thee to the rest. “Stumble not at a straw nor leap o're a blocke: “Leaue not things at randome, keep all vnder locke: “Things may be missing, but when 'tis gone “It is a common speech, That they saw none: “Be finding still, but let thy losse be small, “Yet haue respect vnto thy selfe withall. “Be not amongst Theeues, but when thou find'st them sharing, “Nor with a miserable wretch that's sparing. “Come not neere a Brothell house for lecherie, “Those damned queanes are full of trecherie. “Part not a fray except thou find'st great reason: “Goe not ill shod in a winter season: “Be not too forwards to goe in the raine “Except it be for profit or for gaine. “When sickenes comes, few friends are euer found; “Looke to thy selfe that thou be whole and sound, “And be not carelesse which way thou doost walke, “Nor care too much with idle braines to talke. Come not within the verdict of a Iurie, Nor yet neere a tyrant in his furie. “Giue faire words to the watch they'l let thee passe; “Giue the Constable thankes, thinke him an Asse. “Promise mony when thou passest through the gate, “But on my blessing let him neuer h'ate. “Beare with a Tapster though his Cans be frothie, “But raile on a Broker whose clothes are mothie. “Carmen and Porters are—approued, “And most Watermen are very dogged. “Yet giue them faire words if thou canst gaine them, “Else bid Deri—say Lord haue mercie on them. “What though thy horse by the Ostler is nipt? “It is a true Ostler that hath not so beene tript: “But to make him amends run in his score, “If thou payest him, Ile counsell thee no more. “Bayliffes and Sergants; keepe without their reach, “And without the verge of a priuie search. “Auoyde warrants, they are dangerous things; “Looke to thy profit that some comfort brings. Plot for a Pudding or a peece of Souce; The slie Cat would not watch but for the Mouse. The Foxe would neuer hunt but for his pray, And workemen but for gaine would play all day. It is this wealth, this profit, and this gaine That makes the labourer sing away his paine. “It makes widows forget their husbands lately dead, “It is the cause they so soone againe do wed. “If thou woo'st a widow, in time begin, “Or else thy wooing is not worth a pin. “If thou be slow to speake, as one I knew, “Thou would'st assure thy selfe my counsels true; “Hee (too late) finding her vpon her knees “In Church, where yet her husbands coorse she sees. “Hearing the Sermon at his funerall, “Longing to behold his buriall. “This sutor being toucht with inward loue, “Approched neare, his louely sute to moue, “Then stooping downe, he whispered in her eare “Saying, he bore her loue as might appeare “In that so soone he shewed his loue vnto her, “Before any else did appoch to woo her. “Alasse (said she) your labour is in vaine, “Last night a husband I did entertaine. “Yet your kind offer I take in good part, “And had entertain'd you with all my heart, “If you had come in any time vnto me, “But he at my husbands death did woo me. “Then speake in time if profit comes thereby, “Or else many dangers therein may lie. If thou be rich and hat'st anothers pride, That he may goe on foot while thou dost ride; Finde meats to feed his swelling humour so, That high conceit may aboue compasse goe; Till fortune frownes his follie so doth checke, That male-content may after breake his necke. Then lay in for his lands, his goods and place, But still be sure to keepe thy selfe in grace. “There are many rubs twixt thee and the Iacke, “Therefore throw home thy cast and be not slacke: “Yet out-throw it not, lest thou lose the cast, “So standers by will reioyce at thy haste; “And betting say, that thou shalt lose the game, “Which is to thy disgrace and vtter shame. “Looke to thy selfe thou be not wrong'd by any: “Promote thy selfe though thou displace a many: But if thou be'st not vp but seek'st to rise, Step by degrees, and in thy steps be wise: “Doe not desire to stride two staires at once, “Diuers men will suffer thee for the nonce, “And will reioyce to see thee breake thy shin; “Then thinke how men reioyce when that they win: “Standers by discerne more then gamsters can: “Disdaine not the kindnesse of any man: “Thou may'st as easily speak faire words as foule, not? “Be not a foole when that thou makest the shot: “Foule words corrupt good manners it is said: “Of backe-biting slaues euer be affraid: “Regard not their kindnesse though it be great, “That shall hit thee in teeth with a meales meat: “Thinke him not true that such basenesse doth hold, “Whose secrets in corners loues to vnfold. “Auoyde them in time, their hate is much, “Yet they will seeme as though they were not such; “And no doubt giue faire words vnto thy face, “Alas, alas, it is a heauie case. “Preuent them then, and care not for their hate, “It boots not to see the fourme where she sate: “Had I wist comes too late, hold time before, “Runne not too deepe in thy Hostes score; “Depart in time when she the shot is making, “And faine some businesse at thy departing. “'Tis good to offer to pay when that thou hast it, “If once offered backe, looke that thou keepst it, “And giue him thankes vntill the next meeting “Thus by degrees still thou must be getting. Refuse no seruice be it ne're so base, By any meanes may bring thee into grace, And make no conscience to attend on sin, To keepe the doore where Diuels dance within. “Mongst all kinde of people (for gaine) men thrust, “Loue no Iron blades, they will but rust, “And turne the edge when thou should'st vse them; “I prethee be wise, and learne to refuse them. Finde a rich Sier, and note his disposition, How he is giuen to basenesse or ambition, And with thy bending lay his land aboord, That he may be thy slaue, thou his Lord: “Yet beare in hand as though thou wish't him good; “There's more wayes then one to goe to the wood. If that thy friend do lacke a little wit, And in his humour frame an idle fit; To take a wife, and vse thee for his wooing, Speake for thy friend, but for thy selfe be doing: “If thou find'st her worth the catching, take her; “If not, let thy friend be sure to haue her. For euery friend is to his friend a debter, To loue him as himselfe, but not no better. But for thy selfe; if thou hast got a wife, Make shew to loue her dearely as thy life; Though for thy quiet thou could'st be content A little money were at her buriall spent, And let that charge be of thy griefe the ground; For many wiues are better lost then found. “Take heed (my Son) how &amp; where thou do'st woo, “For widowes are wanton, and maidens too. “She that hath had many husbands cannot loue, “She that nere had none, who knows how she'l proue? “Great chance but yong wenches are tried before, “And middle age must needes pay the olde score: “Olde women hold out whiles a stump doth last, “Sweet meats to olde folkes haue a gratious taste: But if thou come vnto the second matching, Haue carefull heed for feare of conicatching; VVho in their hole will vndermine so fast, They'le leaue their Lordship like the land of wast: “For manie priuie banquets must be had, “VVhich being known, wold make a man stark mad. “They must haue pleasure, tut, let the world slide, “Sit fast for falling when thou mean'st to ride, “It is no iesting matter my friend, quoth he, “To ride a gauld cut Iaded thou shalt be, “VVho will wince and kicke, and lie in the dust: “Follow not an old Iade that loueth lust, “That is a plague that's worse then all the rest, “Though she be rich, yet her filth detest, “Doe not delight, in an old gresie slut “Whose loue is to fill a greedie gut. “She'll ne're be satisfied, vntill the earth; “Receiues her corps, and stoppeth vp her breath, Suspect thy will be wearie of thy will Then learne to spare, but neuer learne to spill, Part with no coyne but vpon conditon, With humble countenance shadow ambition, “Muffle thy selfe sometimes to keepe vnknowne “For by a knaue thou maist be ouerthrowne, “Take heed of the Counters, tis a great greefe “To lie in Prizon without releefe, “Be not a Pandor, for then thou art sham'd “Take heed of a wild Coult thats neuer tam'd “Yet of all these, if thou canst gaine by them “Haue eare vnto, but be not seene in them “Let simple wits carrie away the blame. “The reproch, the rumours and all the shame, “When thou with slie countenance maist be sure “Of some profit let them the paine indure, “Let all be doone, with shew of humblenesse: “So shalt thou receiue profit with thankfulnesse. Creep, Crouch, and kneele, vntill thou be aloft But then, sit fast, for feare thou fall not soft. “The stately Streames that kindly begins to flow “Affords content, in spight of whom sayes no, “The pleas?t Spring, faier morn's of pleasure sends “And to each Creature pleasant gifts extends: “The louely Birdes, on branches sits still singing; “Reioicing at those stately flowers then springing, “But see how time turnes backe, and crosseth all “Those dates expir'd, begins a heauie fall, “Those flowing streames, that gaue that kind consent To ebbe is turned, and all their strength is spent. “Those mornes of May, where Flora shin'd so bright “Are now forlorne, made darke by winters night, “Those Birds whose chearful tunes did pleasure giue “Are now inforst to seeke them holes to liue, “Where mournfull tunes record their heauy state, “That enuious time hath altered thus their fate. “Behold in this, and all that's called pleasure, “How it is crost by times euill measure. “Who would seeme rich, although he hath store, “But closely keep his treasure euermore, “And to himselfe be euer such a friend, “That to himselfe he may his money lend? “Be circumspect still when thou art in grace; “Let not vaine toyes thy honor then disgrace. Be rich I say, nay boy be rich and wise, Gold is an actious mettle for the eyes. Why rich men haue much money and gay geare, And goodly houses, and most daintie cheare, Faire wiues, fine pictures, playes and Morris-dances, And many cheats, that come by many chances; Fine Ciuet boxes, sweet perfumes and waters, And twentie other such kind of matters. While the poore man that pines for want of friends, May sit and sigh, and picke his fingers ends, And euery morning wash his face with teares, And wipe his blubbered cheeks with sheualed heares. “It is a heauie sense where coyne is wanting, “At such a time of care friends are scanting. “When needie guests com to a feast to dine, “They must content themselues, and drinke no wine, “Small beere must suffice aye, and say 'tis well, “Wine must be kept for Diues going to hell: “This slender care of pouertie is had, Which doth inforce them euer to be sad, And walke abroad for sorrowes recreation, Or starue himselfe, or feed on contemplation: “Sorrowes companion, and all forlorne; “And of euery creature held in scorne: “His head hangs downe, his armes lockt one in one; “To none but hilles and ecchoes makes his mone. “Resounding care, a heauy dolefull breath: “No better pillow then his mother earth, “Speaking to the ayre as to a friend “That should his miserie some comfort send, Make courtesie to the shadow of any food, And glad to get a looke or halfe a word; Blush and fall backe when gay folke come in place And start to looke a Ladie in the face, Talke to the ayre, where no man list to heare him, Or plod alone where no man will come neare him. “Despaire is all his food to nourish bloud, “A fearefull state, hard to be vnderstood “What grieuous hell is want afflicting still, “A hungrie heart, a hungry soule to kill? “What woe is want, where no man will relieue “A poore distressed soule that still doth grieue? And thus recording of an heauie care, He feeds perhaps vpon an hungry fare: Till that some good Knight, or learned Gentleman That will not be a Machauillian, But can make vse of afflicted braines, And gather profit from their toyling paines, May hap to grace him with his countenance Giue him a blew coat and a cognizance, An olde cast doublet, or a paire of boots, Feed him with browne bread, small beere, hearbs and roots; And now and then perhaps a peece of meate, That scarce a man would giue a Dogge to eate: Or after happily some good seruice done, Make him tutor, to his yongest Sonne. Laugh at those Beggers, speake in scorne of pelfe: Care thou for nothing, but to inrich thy selfe. For truth reports, that doltes of thriftie intreat, If thou be rich, thou quickly mai'st be great “Why? then thou shalt bee sought vnto and prais'd, “And manie wayes to dignities be rais'd “Thy name shall be extold by Poets Pen; “And brauely attended on by Seruing men. “Bookes shall be dedicated to thy worth: “To aduance thy glorie, thy fame set forth. “Thou shalt be wise, and plac'st in iustice to, “Though thou want will, all this thy wealth can doe. “Thinke no man wise, but he that gathers wealth, “And keep the diet that preserues the health. “Doe not with gluttons feed, though they woe thee, “Nor with Drunkards vse, though they pay for thee, “If thou be with a glutton at a feast, “He'll wish thee choked, if thou feed on the best, “And eye thee too, and thinke thou do'st him wrong. “To eate one bit, that to his chops belong, “Let gluttons grease their dogs alone for thee “They are not for thy profit, take that of me, “Drunkards are vilde, but not so ill as those “Hee like a braue bully cheares vp his nose “With a rich colour, set with pearles and stone, “Whiles Glutt?s hungry chaps make clean the bones. “He'll call his neighbour in, and make him drinke “A glutton like a beast, doth beastly stinke, “Of any ill, the least is to be chused: “Yet best of all, when all is quite refused “With good aduice, manage so thy doings: “That thou be not troubled much with loosings. Trauell with ease, take heed of taking cold, And next to God take comfort in thy gold. Commit no secrets to thy second selfe, For neuer it was Ape but plaide the Elfe: “To womens trust, t'is paine to trust vpon, “Greatest secrets, from them are soonest gone: “Their closets cannot hold a thing forbidden; “Yet desires to know a thing that's hidden: “Their nature's verie weake, their frailties much; “Thei'l loue him very well that is exceeding rich. Set snares for Woodcocks, pitfales for small birds, And catch a foole with nothing but faire words. Kill not a fly and let a flea alone, That sucks the blood, and neuer hurts the bone. File not thy fingers with a filthie slut, And ride not often on a gald backt Cut. “Keepe not a Curre, that no good profit yeeldes; “A lurching Dog will range about the fields. Feare not a shaddow, but auoid a danger: And keepe not a iade at racke and manger, “Which will quite eat thee out of house &amp; home; “Thy selfe remaine a dunce, a very mome, “With ridiculous termes thou shalt be scoft, “Thy lodging cold, in the streetes very oft. Perswade no Prince, from his choice of pleasure, Nor a rich man from his loue of treasure. “For if thou with Monarkes meddle to farre; “It must perforce procure a mightie iarre, “Or if thou prie but neere a rich mans chest; To him rhou shalt be an vnwelcome guest: But if he be rich, whatso'ere he be, Seeme in thine honnur, to be iust as he. If he be poore, then let him beg alone, It is a trade that few grow rich vpon. “The best Beggers are accounted idle, “Riding a stumbler hold fast the bridle. “A Souldiers wants these daies hath seldome ayde; “To follow warres it makes men much dismaide: “Though ventering life &amp; goods, with losse of lims: “What rich Domesticall a man esteemes, “At his returne, his worth though nere so great; “Scarce giue a looke, or scarce a bit of meat, “If such worthie men shall want deseruing this, “Looke not thou for comfort in distresse? “Keepe thou at home, as home-bred slaues do vse, “Whose cankered hearts bright honour doth abuse, “And feeding fat; like lubbers take their ease. “Let those that list attempt to crosse the Seas: “When Diues loue is onely in his wealth; “When toyling Lazers counted naught but filth: “Grieuous vnto all, horror 'tis to see; “Delight in gold as these else shalt thou be. Learne to know Kingdoms, Nations, &amp; their natures, Their laws, their iudgments, male &amp; female creatures And how their wealth doth grow by warre or peace, And how their quarrels grew, and how they cease, How they may be offended or defended, And how their states begun, and which way ended: But in all notes, note this of all How thou may'st rise, who euer hap to fall. “Let thy Religion be of what sort it will, “Be thou of that sect, seeke to humour still, “Do not with a shamefac'd bashfulnesse do it, “But with a manly courage run through it; “As if to such sects thou had'st beene euer bred, “By which meanes thou may'st be the better fed. If thou hast a partner in thy stocke, And both your wealths do rest vnder one locke, And if thy partner ride abroad for pleasure, And put thy faith in trust with all his treasure; At his returne doe vpon quarrels stand: When thou hast got his wealth into thy hand, Say in accounts he hath deceiued thee, Although thou know'st no such matter bee. “Seeme exceeding earnest and speake aloud; “No maruell though of late you were so proud; “Must needs my purse be thus at your command? “'Tis true, you haue made a faire hand. “Thus raile at him that he may shame to heare thee, “Act it well, he may begin to feare thee. When if he will not take what thou wilt giue him, To course of law, for his best comfort driue him, Where while he railes on thy ill conscience, Thy patience closely will put vp his pence. “Raile thou still on his ill husbandrie, “So men may thinke he spent lasciuiously: “Commending thee that thou lookst to't in time, “Raysing on him abroad a grieuous crime. But whatsoeuer honest mindes surmise, Wealth with the wealthy makes the wealthy wise. Be rich therefore, I say, be rich my Sonne, For wealth will sway the world when all is done. “If these counsels will not make thee rich, “Nor procure thy further profit small or much, “By preuenting mischiefes that may befall thee “VVhat counsell then shall I further giue thee? “The courses of the world I shew thee plaine “As in a Mappe, all dangers to refraine: “VVhich had they beene in time foretold to me “I might auoyde that which now I see, “Headstrong youth in promotion cannot sit “Their fickle age hath manie an idle fit. “Following those humours that please them best, “Which is a hinderance to their quiet rest: “But things foretold, may easily be past. “It is not good to thrust things vp in haste, “Be happy then in learning of this good: “Want is the meanes that partes kind brother-hood. “Thou seest enough, if reason may suffise, “All is laid open heere before thine eyes, “As in a glasse thou rightly mai'st behold, “How thy state stands, if thou wantest gold: “Then on my blessing learne these rules of mine; “Another day surely it will be thine. FINIS. THE ANSWER TO Machiavels vncasing. Bvt now my sonne, that thou hast learnd this lore, Vppon my blessing looke on it no more, Except it be by ill to know the good: But yet take heed it be misunderstood. Be that thou seem'st to be in word and deed, Least Pater noster put thee from thy Creed. Faire speech is good, but keepe not a fowle mind, For hollow hearts are of a hellish kind. “Backbiters and dissembling tongues are vilde, “From heauens happinesse by heauen exilde, “Against such horrid deeds is woe pronounc'd, “A wofull state from blessednesse renounc'd. A good beginning makes a blessed end, And hold him for a dog that hath no friend, “His case is ill when no man will respect him, “But worst of all, when vertue doth neglect him. Receiue no bribes to fill a rustie chest, A quiet conscience is a kingly feast. “Content doth shine where vertuous men doe dwell. “A vicious life deserueth nought but hell. “Labour not by vnlawfull meanes to gaine, “When meanes vnlawfull breeds a wofull paine. And 'tis a heauie sence in sorrowes roule, To saue the bodie, and to kill the soule. Affect the wise, and with the learned talke, And with the learned often make a walke. “And such as thy companions shall be, “Euen such rewards shall be bestowed on thee. “Where grauity remaines, there still resort, “Where modesty doth dwell, with such consort: “So shalt thou be, beloued still of all, No scandals then shall seeke to worke thy thrall, Remember nothing that thou dost not write, For danger doth but fearefull hearts affright: “And with charity loue thy neighbour so, “That by no meanes thou seekst his ouerthrow: “Haue carefull eare, to euery man giue right, “Regard kinde words, in kindnesse haue delight; In honors cause maintaine thy reputation, And hold loue good for reasons recreation. Sooth no ill eares with idle flattery, Honor the Bride, but doe the Groome no rye. Performe thy word, but promise not too much, With rich and poore, be carefull to keep touch. With great and small be sure to keepe measure, And scorne no trifle that may doe thee pleasure: “For he that scorneth much, deserueth hate, “An infamie that nee'r expireth date; “Such long lasting euils (my sonne) refraine, What losse so ere it be vnto thy gaine. Frequent the Church with faith and true deuotion, And doe not step too fast into promotion; For farre more greefe is in a headlong fall, Then if thy care, had neuer climde at all. “Be content with such meanes that god doth send, “A patient heart doth gaine a happy end. “Why shouldst thou toile thy selfe for pelth, “When death ends all approching still by stealth, “And crops the blossomes of our whole delight, “By winter stormes, by time and darkesome night? “What bootest then to burthen thus thine age, “With heauy clogs, for which thy soule's at gage, “Where in woe and thraldome still remaining, “Except by Christ thou purchase thy redeeming. Be wisely kind to euery quallity, And euer keepe good hospitallity. “A miserable house is vilde men say, “Ill gotten goods, are quickly spent away: “Those that so nerely scrapt their welth together, “Another throwes it about, and cares not whether. At thy owne charge, keepe thy Horses stable, And seeke no banquet at a beggers table: For a true minde had rather starue then eate, Where Churles and seruants grudge a stranger meat. “Come not to a hungry house for diet, “Where spies and teltales bring all out of quiet; “Rather for thy quiets sake, liue with bread, “Then mongst talemongers seeke to be fed. “What is thine owne to eate, none can grudge, “A backebiter must needes be a drudge, “Whose owne reports disgraceth him at last, “Cause he himselfe hath made the greatest wast. “Be free from this; great danger lies therein, “To men offence, to God a greeuous sinne. Iest not with cowards, for they will but crie, And as for Bawdes pitty their beggerie: “Lament the wofull state wherein they stand, “And rightly note, the poison in their hand; “Which soone breaks forth, and makes the body foule, “But tenne times worse, it putrifies the soule. Arithmeticke is in euery trade, But true accounts are to be made: For when the last count reckning is cast vp, Then shall the crafty take their poysned cup, “And tast the iuyce of that they haue deserued, “For which deedes, by doome it is reserued: “Where no woe or horror shall be wanting, “Though gold to them on earth was not scanting. “Desire no gaine, where vice doth leade the ring, “It is a profit that thy paine doth bring. For Lions, Beares, Wolues, Apes, and Asses, Learne them to figure honors looking glasses, And haue a care to carry so thy selfe, No storme may driue thy ship vpon a shelfe. “Many dangers lies hid to thee vnknowne, “No corne comes vp sometimes where seed is sowne. “Enuious men sowes tares the Scripture saies, “Auoid them then, and quite forsake their waies: “Let not earths pleasures leade thy heart away, “Which is transitory, will soone decay, “And still doth passe on earth, from hand to hand, “Neuer constant, nor neuer firme doth stand. Swallowes doe feed on flies, but light they fly, Whiles Epicures in too much feeding dye, “Wallowing in the sinke of sinnes filthines, “Loathsome to behold, o're growne with beastlines: “Spuing out the rankor of selfe delight, “Which hath bred a cankor of endlesse spight. By others harmes seeke not thy priuate good, A bloody feast, is an vnkindly foode. And to dissemble loue, is such an euill, As nearest shewes the nature of the Diuell. “To feede on blood a murtherers delight, “If thou dissemble, thou yeelds no man right. “To gaine by others fall a curse growes on, “A heauy case when infants make their mone. “The widowes note is heard, reuenge shee cries, “For those ill gotten goods, which made thee rise. To helpe thy friend, doe not forbeare thy hand, And for thy credit, sell both goods and land: “For he that helpes his friend, in time of neede, “It is in heauen inrold a friendly deed. “When that with truth of heart, tis friendly done, “No deed on earth is like to that, my Sonne, “Be constant still in friendshippe euermore, “And of a true friend make thy chiefest store. “What end wert thou inricht, with goods and lands, “But to the end thou shouldst be free from bands: “Respect it not aboue the heauens pleasure, “Which is the chiefest chiefe of all thy treasure. Denie no friend when he doth friendly craue it, For honest mindes will pay when that they haue it. “A small mattor sometimes doth helpe so much, “That by such meanes a poore man may proue rich, “Which else might bring a man vnto despaire, “When for his helpe, he findeth nought but ayre, “At wants instant, be helpefull euermore, “And God will giue a blessing to thy store. “Be doing this, but doe not boast a whit, “For that dimmes all, and shewes thy lacke of witt: “Or how canst thou haue grace, for this thy good, “If thou backbitest in any angry moode? “Reporting this thy kindnesse done to any, “It is not worth a pin though nere so many, “And those that heare it will thinke thou maist lie, “When that thou whisperest things so priuily. Let care of conscience guide thee euery way, To giue thee comfort on the holliday. “Pry not at all in trades to offer wrong, “Such basenesse vnto rascalls doth belong: “Those men deseruing it, are fit for gaine, “And fit'st of all to reape the pleasure of their paine; “The dead in peace doth rest, yet liue they may; “In endlesse comfort, and in endlesse ioy. “Kinde charity amongst men, and loue to all, “May make vs ready for this heauenly call: “That liuing here, wee die to liue againe; “In heauenly blisse, euerlasting to remaine. And if thou be a Courtier know thy grace, And seeke in heauen to haue a dwelling place. And if on earth, such seruice profit brings, What shall he haue that serues the King of Kings? “Let vertues care, so guide thy conscience still, “Thou neerely looke to all, but none to ill; “What though the prouerbe old, be proued true; “Or that some crosses on this earth ensue; “Or that the destinies doe frowne on thee, “Or that no rich reward will come neere thee? “Yet if thou be free from vices folly, “Thou art in heauen as pure a Saint as any. “Which is a Court, where thou shalt haue a place, “Where none shall seeke thine honor to deface. And if thou beest a scholler and canst preach, With simple truth thy simple audience teach: “With feruencie of heart seeke to wooe them: “To Gods true knowledge, seeke still to bring them. “Be not carelesse of a thing so weighty; “Giuen thee by the God Almightie. But feed thy flocke, thou hast in hand to keepe, Least that thou proue a wolfe vnto thy sheepe. Feeding on them, that should haue food from thee; “In bad estate their case is like to be. “Attempt not thou at all a labor so diuine, “Except thou canst this earthly state resigne; “And liue to loue thy God, thy flocke, thy sheepe; “So will thy care be good thy flocke to keepe. But whatsoeuer here be thine estate, There is none poore, but he that God doth hate, “Hee's poore indeede, his case of all is worst; “No ill so vile, of all ils most accurst. If that thou be a Souldier sucke no blood, To knightly mindes, vnknightly food; “With conscience let poore Souldiers haue their pay, “Then they will follow thee with loue and ioy: “But if too nerely thou dost pinch or poule, “It may be burdensome vnto thy soule, “And want of pay is the death of many, “Yeeld them due, and nere accus'd for any. Of honors title, who doth truly hold, Shall finde it in mercie, not in gold. If that thou be a Lawyer iudge the right, And let no briberie blinde a blessed sight, For thou shalt finde it written in mercies roule, Better a thredbare gowne, then a thredbare soule. “Tis pittie that right should be ouercome, “Or pouerty to pleade to want a roome: “Alas how heauie is their case in this, “For want of fees a rightfull case to misse? “Yet haue (thou) some conscience, be rul'd by mee, “Pitie poore sutors in necessitie. “Let not mightie men oppresse their right, “Nor ouerthrow their states by power and might. “In doing this thou shalt haue double fee, “A heauenly Paradice thy reward shall bee. “Besides on earth thy fame shall spread abroad, “What curtesie to poore thou didst affoord, “This cannot chuse but bring thee into grace, “And by desert obtaine a higher place. “The law is iust, on reason wisely grounded, “Wanting it our state is soone confounded. And if thou be a Marchant, know thy cares, And doe not wound thy conscience with thy wares, Least in repentance all too late thou finde, The gaine is lost that feedes a greedie minde. “What boots thy toyle and traffique on the Seas, “Thy hazard of life, disturbing of thine ease, “Thy boysterous blasts, and stormes so cold, “Which thou endur'st, thy selfe by time made old, “Thy riches, when happie returnes are made, “Those pretious pearles, whose colours neuer vade, “When that thy conscience shall be working so “How thou mayst worke thy brothers woe, “By thy ill wares, trusted at such a rate, “By which meanes his paiment oft proues late? “Then to suit of law thy conscience cries, “Hee's in a heauie case in such danger lyes. “But farre more worse is thine in time to come, “When that thou doest cast vp the totall summe. “When all deceiptfull gaines to losse shall turne, “Where vicious pleasures shall haue time to mourne, “A measure in gaine with quiet truly got, “Is a perfect treasure that faileth not. “For truth: light gaines doth make a heauy purse, “Vnconscionable gaines a heauy curse. “Then take thy choise, but wisely chuse the best: “Corrupted hearts euermore detest, “Their wares are braid, yet fairely shewes to th'eye; “But he thats rotten at the heart must die. In briefe of what estate so ere thou bee, Let truth and conscience euer gouerne thee. Let Clounes clap on their clouted shooes, Seeke thou no earthly gaines the heauen to loose. Let garments fit thy body, not thy minde, And to thy friend, as to thy selfe proue kinde. “Looke so wisely to euery action, “That it may be thy soules satisfaction. “And doe not seeke to rise by others fals, “Be well prepared when the Angell cals; “Doe not thou stand on rich mens fauors here, “But loue thy Christ, his loue is passing deare; “And make the winde serue to a good intent, “And know to what end thy riches are sent. “Hoyse vp saile to heauens happinesse, “Where thou shalt arriue with great blessednesse; “There thou maist be welcome though wanting gold: “And not by earthly wants thy ioyes controld: “No pouerty shall part thee from that society, “But bring thee to thy ioyes eternity: “Though wealth doth die the colour here in graine, “In heauen tis held most base in great disdaine. “Phisitians and Lawyers are men of fame, “And experience doth auer the same; “Whose labors doth deserue their proper gaine, “No patient can be cured without some paine, “If thou dost learne diseases and their cures; “Be carefull what thy patient endures: “Haue due respect vnto thy cures, and be free, “From corrupted thoughts, then happie shalt thou be. “Delay no cures, but doe thy best for ease, “Which both thy patient, and thy God doth please: “Pittie the heauie cares of those in paine, “And be not too greedie to seeke thy gaine: “Let measure guide thy hand in all thy deeds, “Thinke on the greeued heart with paine that bleeds. “Thinke vpon his case, say that it were thine, “How hard it were, for want of helpe to pine. “Learne no vnlawfull games thy state to raise, “That by deceipt may profit thee any waies, “What though thou shift it from the gamesters eye? “It is beheld by him that sits on high: “He doth behold your dealings euery way, “How securelie so ere you thinke you play. “Goods gotten by deceipt, is quickelie gone, “By getting so, better nere get none: “But rather well to keepe thine owne first learne, “The better how to gaine thou maist discerne. “What though this vicious gaine, so vainelie got, “With plentie seemes to replenish the pott? “It is but a feast, or sport thats passing away, “And the least crosse of all brings it to decay. All Cards and Dice, and all such idle play; From thy delight, discard and cast away: For deale or rub, whose hap so ere it be to haue, The knaue of Clubs will euer be a knaue. Flatter no mistris Fubs, or Ione anods, Nor honor golden calues nor wooden gods: Nor puffe a pesant vp with rascall pride, A rascall will but like a begger ride. Be carefull of the words that thou dost talke, “And be not desirous with a knaue to walke: “Be carefull how thou dost thy secrets disclose, “Backebiters are full of wrong thou maist suppose: “Doe not with the letcher seeme to reioyce, “It is but a loathsome and a hatefull vice: “But rather perswade them from their follie, “And from the loue of a deed so vnholie. “Doe not with spendthrifts smile at pouerty, “Least thou thy selfe come to necessity. “Doe not with Epicures reioyce and say, “With meaner fare thou couldst not well away. “Nor doe not triumph ouer simple wits, “And lament the state of those frenzie fits. “Doe not by any meanes learne to deceiue, “That will but vertue from thy conscience driue, “And disanull thee of thy quiet rest, “Exceeding ioyes, of all things else is best. “Aime at no profit with a poisned breath, “Lest it be paid thee in the second death. “Though conscience here be poore and meanely clad, “No meanes but from the Baggers to be had; “Yet time shall come, it shall be well respected, “When prodigality shall be neglected. “There shall shee finde a house adornd with state, “When Diues repents but all too late. “There shall shee finde fine and dainty cheare, “When gluttons in horror shall appeare, “Her raiment then shall be euerlasting, “When her foes their bitter cup are tasting; “Then let conscience gouerne thy state aright, “That thou maist behold this euerlasting sight. An honest minde in euery trade doth well, The winde blowes ill that blowes the soule to hell. “Doe not before the Diuell a Candle hold, “Seeke no corrupt meanes for siluer or gold. If that thy wife be faire, be thou not foule, To let her play the Ape, and thou the Owle. “Winke at no faults, it is but misery, “By bestiall meanes to releefe necessity; “If thou be a Husband gouerne so thy wife, “That her peeuish meanes worke not thy striue; “Giue her not too much lawe, to run before, “Too much boldnesse doth bring thy ouerthrow: “Yet abridge her not too much by anie meane, “But let her still be thy companion. And to thy daughter proue a better sire, Then like a hacknie let her out to hire. “What a greeuous case were this for thee, “To extoll thy selfe to prosperity. “By such insatiat meanes, a heauy sense, “Deseruing nought but hell for recompence. “Like a kinde father loue thy children deare, “Yet to outward view let not loue appeare, “Least too boldly they presuming on thy loue, “By audacious meanes doe audacious proue, “Seeme not a companion in any case, “To thy children, learne them know who's in place; “That due obedience to thee be done, “The end must needes be good, that's well begonne. “Thus may thy children be at thy commaund, “With willing heart, still helpefull at thy hand. “Familiarity contempt doth breed, “By no meanes doe thou stoope vnto thy seede: “Whilst the twig is yong, bend it as thou list, “Once being growne, thei'll stubbornely resist; “Caring not for parents nor their talking, “Commending their owne wits, age is doting. “Looke well to youth, and how their time is spent, “Least thou by leasure afterwards repent: “What thogh thy child grow rich, thy self grow poore. “Wilt thou afford him reuerence therefore? “Imperfection to thine age that doth show: “Let children expresse what dutie they owe, “And not be blinded with a selfe conceipt; “To wise men hate, to fooles a pleasing bait. “Let thy care be great, for Childrens good, “It is a charge thats hardlie vnderstood: “Vse no corrections in an angry vaine, “Which will but vexe thee much, increase thy paine: “And rashnes euermore repentance cries, “Giue due correction, therein be wise: “The greefe is thine, when children goe astray; “Giue them not too much libertie to play, “Least that they doe to a custome bring it; “And euer after forbeare to leaue it. “Vrge not with violence thy childrens woe, “As cruell parents many times doe so; “Which to despaire may carelesly driue them, “When that their care doth carelesly leaue them, “To run at randome shifting as they may, “Alas, it is a heauie case I say. “Let not children vrge their parents vnto ire, “But with dutie doe what they shall require. “With obedient hearts obedience show, “Such true obedience to them you owe. “Thinke it not a trifle to forbeare it, “When Gods commandement doth require it. “A blessing great, besides he hath reserued, “Whose dutie hath this due deserued. “Honour thy parents, long may be thy daies, “Happie in all, and blessed are thy waies. “Be not stubborne at all, it breeds disdaine, “That which they forbid thee, that refraine. “This is the course, that thou their loue maist haue, “Wise parents, childrens hurt will neuer craue. “But with fatherly care admonish them so, “That selfe conceipt, worke not thy ouerthrow: “Which now adaies doth raigne too much in all; “No maruell then so many youth doe fall, “When parents counsell is thus reiected, “And their hourely care so much neglected. “Salomon saies, smile not on thy daughter, “Least thou repent it euer after. “Then to sonnes and daughters let care be such, “That thou and they in vertue may be rich. “Seeme not to laugh at any vnseemely iest, “A meane in all, in all is euer best. And for thy seruants, let no Belly swell, A baudy house is but an earthly hell. “Keepe not an eye seruant within thy doore, “Which will but seeke to vexe thee euermore. “And scoffinglie answere with taunting words, “A beastlie tricke is all a iade affoords. “If that thou findst a tell tale in thine house, “Be watching still as a cat for a mouse. “Such seruants can neuer be true nor iust, “Who backebites in secret, such neuer trust. “Much discord by such is bred oft times, “When most themselues deserueth greatest crimes. “Be not familiar with seruants in anie case, “But let them with dutie respect their place. “Giue but an inch, they'll quickelie take an ell, “A wise tale to a foole, 'tis vaine to tell. In Lawe and Phisicke haue a conscience, In making gaine of thy experience. Least that thy Clients crie and Patients death, Doe make thee crie out in the hell beneath. “Where greeuous horrors shall still affright thee, “Let vertues loue euermore delight thee, “Which is a gaine sufficient for thy store, “A perfect ioy delightfull euermore. By wicked plots doe not proule for pelfe, Let thy soules care be nearest to thy selfe. “So shall all thy waies prosper and be free, “From thraldome want and great necessitie. “No woe shall once approch where vertue shines, “What needes thou care, though vicious men repines. “Their blasts as bubbles, soone doth passe away, “Themselues in little time comes to decay. “If thou be rich abandon wicked pride, And doe not on the horse of Enuie ride, “Least he carrie thee with an easie way, “Vnto thy ouerthrow and great decay. Seeke not the well deseruing to disgrace, Nor put the vertuous spirit out of place. And sooth no humors in an euill minde, For poisned breath is of a poisned kinde: And though to hurt a few to hurt a many Be good, it better not the hurt of any. “What boots small gaines when greater losse doth fall? “By such measure, seeke not to get at all. “Be patient and wise in extremitie, “Thou maist the sooner come to prosperitie. “As gentle dewes, kindly cause flowers to spring, “Patience gaines content, though misery be long. “Let truth in euery thing be thy companion, “And vice ore thee shall neuer get dominion: “Thou hast a bulwarke that defends thee, “And a trusty friend that treasure lends thee: If that thy friend doe trust thee with his loue, Vnto his trust doe not a traitor proue; Least he that seeth thy ill gotten treasure, Doe pay thee home with an euill meaten measure: “Though thy gaines be small and trauell great, “Thou art certaine to come to iudgement seat. “To receaue a guerdon due to thy deeds, “A blessed food, that blessed creatures feedes: “Neuer wanting but still possest with store, “Which makes thee rich, though seeming nere so pore. Be faithfull to thy wife, firme to thy friend, And constant in religion to the end. “Doe not humor euery sect for priuat gaine, “It is a greeuous sinne a greeuous paine; “Against the holy ghost a sinfull deed, “Then vse it not, what euer bee thy neede: “Religion is sacred pure diuine, “It is a heauenly map, a heauenly signe. “It is that burning lampe that shines so bright, “Being with truth receiued a true delight. “Seeke not thou to depraue religious truth, “Least thou increase thy paine and endlesse ruth. “For chiefest learning thereon is grounded, “And all errors from thence quite confounded. Be rich and wise, in this good wit my boy, That death nor hell, nor Diuell can destroy. “Let thy chiefest pleasure be to seeke that gaine, “That afterwards may neuer turne to paine. “Who so, but for the present time doth care, “Oft times is inforst to be poore and bare. “And when those present pleasures past and gone “As much the neere, if he had nere seene none. “Then time to accompt doth call this follie, “Checking him for all those deeds vnholy. “How he his time, so loosely spent in vaine, “Which being spent, can nere be had againe. “Then with ifs and ands he begins to say, “Had I knowne this fore time had past away, I had preuented that which now I finde, But time is past, and thou tookst hold behind. “Where naught remaines but a scul death portraiture, “(As time doth passe,) it is of all most sure. “To spend this precious time it is a woe, “Without regarding how the howres doth goe. “When time makes ful the howres of times accompt, “Asking how much the totall doth amount. “Then all ill times by time vntimelie spent, “Shall by that time, haue time then to repent. “But all to late, sith time was once refus'd, “And time so deerely lost, so much abus'd. “The date is out, 'tis true: the Clocke hath strooke, “Time kindly offered all, when all forsooke. “This gem of worth most pretious is to youth, “But their selfe-wils hates knowledge of the truth, “Which should bring their tender age vnto blisse, “The right way to that perfect happinesse. “Which wold shew th? how they should spend the day, “With due respect how to spend the time away; “Not by idlenesse, or foolish fansies, “Subiect to many vitious mischaunces. “Which luls their age with pleasure fast asleepe, “Such pleasures they were better lose then keepe. “Tell thou the Clocke, as howres doth passe away, “And thinke how time doth turne all flesh to clay. Serue God, thy King, be to thy countrie true, Liue till thou diest, then bid the world adue. “But liue in that sort, that thou diest with fame, “That after death men giue thee a good name. “Which as Chronicles may last for euer, “In liuing thus thy life endeth neuer. “If to thy King thou prouest vntrue vniust, “Who will afterwards giue thee any trust? “Then to thy Prince, giue due obedience, “And to thy betters seemely reuerence. “So shall thy fame on earth be had in store, “And heauenly blessings giuen thee euermore. “If to Countrie thou hast a trechers heart, “Thy words are worse then a deepe venom'd dart. “Swine eats the flowres, then nusles vp the roote, “And none but beastly mindes will surely doo't. “Or offer to spoile that, by which they'r bred, “Or betray the Country, in which they'r bred. “How manifest it is, of such mens liues, “How their courses euermore baselie thriues. “Some themselues vntimely death doth bring, “Others, in greefe of conscience still mourning. “Some wandring here, some there in wofull greefe, “Others pining in streets, and wants reliefe. “Some starke mad doth run, quite distract of all, “Others, in vaine, for comfort out doth call. “Some, in forraine countries desires a place, “But gnawing conscience brings them to disgrace. “Some with audacious face doth faine excuse, “But God cries vengeance gainst so vild abuse. “Some to Magistrates will sue for fauour, “But poisned hearts doth of poyson sauour. “And all that to such vildnesse bends their courses, “Are left comfortlesse without remorses. Machiauels rules let Machiauels reade, Loue thou thy God, his spirit be thy speede. “His loue is richer then siluer or gold, “His home is Paradice the surest hold. “His promise is sure, for euer iust, “And tis the surest hope that thou canst trust. “Thy Ancor being cast vpon that shore, “Thy cable will hold fast for euermore. “Loue not the world, to leaue true vertues loue, “Least to thy destruction, it after proue. “The worldes loue, is but faire fancies flower, “Though seeming rich, yet wanting richest power. Taxe no mans name in any euill matter, But like a Christian pray for euery creature. “Charitably wishing well to men, “The like rewards shall come to thee againe. “Let no mans name at all be wrong'd by thee, “The worsest euill, euer thine will be. “When infamies thou raisest on thy brother, Be sure, gainst thee thou shalt receiue none other. “Such measure as thou meatest to thee is giuen, “He liues vprightly that keeps all euen. “But by good indeuour it may be gaind, “Hate vice, the onely meanes it is obtaind. “To be free from euill speach, a Christians care, “Be a louer of vertue, vice forbeare. Be sorrie for the euill thou hast done, And goe on with the good thou hast begunne. “A heart that's penitent true comfort findes, “To finde remorse, the heauenly lawes it bindes. “If thou beginnest any good, then proceed, “Thou shalt finde it to be a blessed deed. Pray for thy faith, that it may faile thee neuer, So if thou diest, yet shalt thou liue for euer. “Then shalt thou be brought to vertues pallace, “To receiue the true comfort of thy solace. “And for thy paine thou didst indure here, “Thou euermore shalt finde a plenteous yeere. “Where neither hunger cold nor any want, “Shall hinder ioyes, or make thy pleasures scant. “This is the benefit of a vertuous life, “This is true vertues force, to end all strife. “This is vertues garden full of flowres, “Though on earth shee had many pinching houres. “This is vertues path, rightly leades to blisse, “This is vertues gift, his friends doth neuer misse. “This is vertues harbor voide of cares, “This is vertues bountie who neuer spares: “This is vertues pallace, adorn'd with state, “This is vertues gift, neuer comes to late, “This is vertues Parke, infoulds her deare, “This is vertues care, who will not loose a haire, “This is vertues armes, incircling round, “This is vertue which now her right hath found, “This is vertues walkes, whose aire's euer sweete, “This is vertue her friends doth kindly greete, “This is vertues Citty, whose gates are fast “Gainst all that of her name made spoile or wast, “This is vertues banket house, feeding all, “This is vertue that heares the poore mans call, “This is vertue that lou'd her parents kind, “This is vertue that loue to all resign'd, “This is vertue, releeuing friends in want, “This is vertue whose loue was neuer scant: “To any one that pouertie did respect, “Who neuer will such kindnes once reiect, “But kindly seeke such kindnes to requite, “And all her friends shall haue their due and right. “No cankered churles shall seek to crosse her of her wil “But in her place shee remaines as Empresse still. “Then seek (my Son) to serue this Goddesse pure diuine “Be howerly offering gifts vnto her sacred Shrine, “Doe not leaue her seruice, for the worlds treasure, “Esteeme her paine aboue the chiefest pleasure, “Her paines are short, her ioies for euer lasting, “Her loue is deare, her hate to sorrowes hasting, “With reuerence (my child) kneele for her grace, “Sue by petition in any case. “And neuer rest till thou hast got her fauour, “And it will bee double worth thy labour; “For thou such a mistres shalt haue of her: “That for her seruants good none comes neare her: “Shee giues her seruants old good meanes to liue, “When vice her seruants out of doores doth driue, “Shee helpes her seruants in sicknesse and in health, “On such preferments shee bestowes her wealth. “Then be true seruant to such a mistris, “Who at all times with willing hart releeues distresse. “Be mindfull of my words, giuen out of loue, “And happy to thy Father thou wilt proue. “What in the beginning I did declare, “Was but to shew thee what vaine courses are, “That by the knowledge of them thou mightst beware “How thou art caught in any vicious snare. “Make vse of them, and wrest them to the best, “And thou shalt find it yeelds thee quiet rest. “By any meanes doe not to vaine humors growe, “Least that it quickly seeke thy ouerthrow. “Yeeld praise to God, in his lawes seeke to liue, “And at his pleasure he will all things fitting giue. “If thou find'st any thing written here “That may to thy comfort anie way appeare, “Ti's all that I craue or heart requireth, “Who only for thy chiefest good desireth. “If thankes thou wilt bestow, thou seemest kinde, “If vnthankfull, thou hast a churlish minde, “Sith all my labor is onlie for thy good, “Desiring that it bee well vnderstood: “Which if thou doest thou shalt be still my Sonne, “Be true of heart what miserie soeuer come. “First to God giue praise, to Prince and Country true, “Thy Parents reuerence, and so my Sonne adue. “Machiauels rules deny, yet vse them as thy pleasure, “False harted friends defie, in all haue equal measure. “Vse all these to good intent, and boldly say, “Thou maist with vertue, euermore keepe holiday. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>