<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Overbury, Thomas, Sir, 1581-1613</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Overbury, Thomas, Sir, 1581-1613</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">overbury thomas sir 1581 1613</field>
      <field name="author_text">Overbury, Thomas, Sir, 1581-1613</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.0147.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1622</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:463075</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">His wife (1622</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">His wife (1622</field>
      <field name="title_facet">his wife 1622</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">his wife 1622</field>
      <field name="title_text">His wife (1622</field>
      <field name="year_display">1622</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1622</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1622</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463075&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463075&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Overbury, Thomas, Sir, 1581-1613&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;overbury thomas sir 1581 1613&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;His wife (1622&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;his wife 1622&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1622&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1622&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Overbury, Thomas, Sir&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1581&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1613&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;His wife (1622)&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Laurence Lisle and are to be sold by Henry Seile [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1622&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp2922&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;[410] p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;His wife (1622)&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 34 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse by Overbury included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To the Reader.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">A WIFE. The Method. First, of Marriage, and the effect thereof, Children. Then of his contrary, Lust; then for his choyce, First, his opinion negatiuely, what should not bee: the First causes in it, that is, neither Beauty, Birth, nor Portion. Then affirmatiue, what should bee, of which kinde there are foure: Goodnesse, Knowledge, Discretion, and as a second thing, Beautie. The first only is absolutely good: the other being built vpon the first doe likewise become so. Then the application of that woman by loue to himselfe, which makes her a Wife. And lastly, the only condition of a Wife, Fitnesse. Each Woman is a briefe of Womankind, And doth in little euen as much containe, As, in one Day and Night, all life we finde, Of either, More, is but the same againe: God fram'd Her so, that to her Husband She, As Eue, should all the world of Women be. So fram'd he Both, that neither power he gaue Vse of themselues, but by exchange to make: Whence in their Face, the Faire no pleasure haue, But by reflex of what thence other take. Our Lips in their owne Kisse no pleasure finde: Toward their proper Face, our Eyes are blinde. So God in Eue did perfit Man, begun; Till then, in vaine much of himselfe he had: In Adam God created onely one, Eue, and the world to come, in Eue he made. We are two halfes: whiles each from other straies, Both barren are; Ioyn'd, both their like can raise. At first, both Sexes were in Man combinde, Man a Shee-Man did in his body breed; Adam was Eues, Eue Mother of Mankinde, Eue from Liue-flesh, Man did from Dust proceed. One, thus made two, Mariage doth re-vnite, And makes them both but one Her maphrodite. Man did but the well being of his life From Woman take; her Being she from Man: And therefore Eue created was a Wife, And at the end of all her Sex, began: Mariage their obiect is: their Being then, And now Perfection, they receiue from Men. Mariage; to all whose ioyes two parties be, And doubled are by being parted so, Wherein the very Act is Chastitie, Whereby two Soules into one Body goe. Which make two one; while here they liuing be, And after death in their posteritie. God to each Man a priuate woman gaue, That in that Center his desires might stint, That he a comfort like himselfe might haue, And that on her his like he might imprint. Double is Womans vse, part of their end Doth on this Age, part on the next depend. We fill but part of time, and cannot dye, Till we the world a fresh supply haue lent, Children are Bodies sole Eternitie; Nature is Gods, Art is Mans instrument. Now all Mans Art but only dead things makes, But herein Man in things of life partakes. For wandring Lust; I know tis infinite, It still begins, and addes not more to more. The guilt is euerlasting, the delight, This instant doth not feele, of that before. The tast of it is only in the Sense, The operation in the Conscience. Woman is not Lusts bounds, but Womankinde; One is Loues number: who from that doth fall Hath lost his hold, and no new rest shall finde; Vice hath no meane, but not to be at all. A Wife is that enough, Lust cannot finde; For Lust is still with want, or too much, pinde. Bate lust the Sin, my share is eu'n with his, For, Not to lust, and to Enioy is one: And more or lesse past, equall Nothing is; I still haue one, Lust one at once, alone: And though the woman often changed be, Yet Hee's the same without variety. Marriage our lust (as twere with fuell fire) Doth, with a medicine of the same, allay; And not forbid, but rectifie desire, My selfe I cannot chuse, my wife I may: And in the choyce of Her, it much doth lie, To mend my selfe in my posterity. O rather let me Loue, then be in loue; So let me chuse, as Wife and Friend to finde, Let me forget her Sex, when I approue, Beasts likenesse lies in shape, but ours in minde: Our Soules no Sexes haue, their Loue is cleane, No Sex, both in the better part are Men. But Physicke for our lust their Bodies be, But matter fit to shew our Loue vpon: But only Shells for our posteritie, Their soules were giu'n lest men should be alone: For, but the Soules Interpreters, words be, Without which, Bodies are no company. That goodly frame we see of flesh and bloud, Their fashion is, not weight; it is I say But their Lay-part; but well digested food; This but twixt Dust, and Dust, lifes middle way: The worth of it is nothing that is seen, But only that it holds a Soule within. And all the carnall Beauty of my Wife, Is but skin-deepe, but to two senses knowne; Short euen of Pictures, shorter liu'd then Life, And yet the loue suruiues, that's built thereon: For our Imagination is too high, For Bodies, when they meet, to satisfie, All Shapes, all Colours are alike in Night, Nor doth our Touch distinguish foule or faire: But mans imagination, and his sight, And those, but the first weeke; by Custome are Both made alike, which differed at first view, Nor can that difference absence much renew. Nor can that Beauty, lying in the Face, But meerely by imagination be Enioy'de by vs, in an inferiour place. Nor can that Beauty by enioying we Make ours become; so our desire growes tame, We changed are, but it remaines the same. Birth, lesse then Beauty, shall my Reason blinde, Her Birth goes to my Children, not to me: Rather had I that actiue Gentrie finde, Vertue, then passiue from her Ancestry; Rather in her aliue one vertue see, Then all the rest dead in her Pedigree. In the Degrees, high rather be she plac't, Of Nature, then of Art, and Policie: Gentrie is but a relique of time past, And Loue doth only but the present see; Things were first made, then words: she were the same With, or without, that title, or that name. As for (the oddes of Sexes) Portion, Nor will I shun it, nor my aime it make; Birth, Beauty, Wealth, are nothing worth alone, All these I would for good additions take, Not for Good parts; those two are ill combin'd, Whom, any third thing fr? themselues, hath ioyn'd. Rather then these the obiect of my Loue, Let it be Good; when these with vertue goe, They (in themselues indifferent) vertues proue, For Good (like fire) turnes all things to be so. Gods image in Her Soule, O let me place My Loue vpon; not Adams in Her Face. Good, is a fairer attribute then White, Tis the mindes beauty keepes the other sweet: That's not still one, nor mortall with the light, Nor glasse, nor painting can it counterfet, Nor doth it raise desires, which euer tend At once, to their perfection, and their end. By Good I would haue Holy vnderstood, So God she cannot loue, but also me, The Law requires our words and deeds be good, Religion euen the Thoughts doth sanctifie: And she is more a Maid that rauisht is, Then She which only doth but wish amisse. Lust only by Religion is withstood; Lusts obiect is aliue, his strength within; Morality resists but in cold bloud; Respect of Credit feareth shame, not sinne. But no place darke enough for such offence She finds, that's watcht by her owne conscience. Then may I Trust her Bodie with her minde, And, thereupon secure, need neuer know The pangs of Iealousie: and Loue doth finde More paine to doubt her false, then know her so: For Patience is, of euils that are knowne, The certaine Remedie; but Doubt hath none. And be that thought once stirr'd, twill neuer die, Nor will the griefe more milde by custome proue; Nor yet Amendment can it satisfie, The Anguish more or lesse, is as our loue: This miserie doth Iealousie ensue, That we may proue her false, but cannot True. Suspicions may the will of Lust restraine, But Good preuents from hauing such a will, A Wife that's Good, doth Chast and more containe, For Chast is but an Abstinence from ill: And in a Wife that's Bad, although the best Of qualities; yet in a Good the least. To barre the meanes is Care, not Iealousie: Some lawfull things to be auoyded are, When they occasion of vnlawfull be: Lust ere it hurts is best descryde a farre: Lust is a sinne of two; he that is sure Of either part, may be of both secure. Giue me next Good, an vnderstanding Wife, By Nature wise, not Learned by much Art, Some Knowledge on Her side, will all my life More scope of conuersation impart, Besides, Her inborne vertue fortifie, They are most firmely good, that best know why. A passiue vnderstanding to conceiue, And Iudgement to discerne, I wish to finde: Beyond that, all as hazardous I leaue; Learning, and pregnant wit in Woman-kinde, What it findes malleable, maketh fraile, And doth not adde more ballast, but more saile. Domesticke Charge doth best that Sexe befit, Contiguous businesse; so to fixe the Minde, That Leasure space for Fancies not admit: Their Leasure 'tis, corrupteth Woman-kinde, Else, being plac'd from many vices free, They had to Heau'n a shorter cut then wee. Bookes are a part of Mans prerogatiue, In formall Inke they Thoughts and Uoyces hold, That we to them our solitude may giue, And make Time-present trauell that of old. Our life, Fame peeceth longer at the end, And Bookes it farther backward doe extend. As good, and knowing, let her be Discreet, That, to the others weight, doth Fashion bring; Discretion doth consider what is Fit, Goodnesse but what is lawfull; but the Thing, Not Circumstances; Learning is and wit, In Men, but curious folly without it. To keepe their Name, when 'tis in others hands, Discretion askes; their Credit is by farre More fraile then They: on likely-hoods it stands, And hard to be disprou'd, Lusts slanders are. Their Carriage, not their Chastitie alone, Must keepe their Name chaste from suspicion. Womens Behauiour is a surer barre Then is their No: That fairely doth denie Without denying; thereby kept they are Safe eu'n from Hope; in part to blame is shee, Which hath without consent bin only tride; He comes too neere, that comes to be denide. Now since a Woman we to Marrie are, A Soule and Body, not a Soule alone; When one is Good, then be the other Faire; Beauty is Health, and Beauty, both in one; Be she so faire, as change can yeeld no gaine; So faire, as Shee most Women else containe, So Faire at least let me imagine Her; That thought to me is Truth: opinion Cannot in matter of opinion erre; With no eies shall I see her but mine owne. And as my Fancy Her conceiues to be, Euen such my Senses both, doe Feele and See. The Face we may the seat of Beauty call, In it the rellish of the rest doth lye, Nay eu'n a figure of the Minde withall: And of the Face, the Life moues in the Eye; No things else, being two, so like we see, So like, that they, two but in number, be. Beauty in decent shape, and Colours lies, Colours the matter are, and shape the Soule; The Soule, which from no single part doth rise, But from the iust proportion of the whole, And is a meere spirituall harmonie, Of euery part vnited in the Eye. Loue is a kinde of Superstition, Which feares the Idoll which it selfe hath fram'd: Lust a Desire, which rather from his owne Temper, then from the obiect is inflam'd: Beauty is Loues obiect; Woman Lust's; to gaine Loue, Loue Desires; Lust only to obtaine. No circumstance doth Beauty beautifie, Like gracefull fashion, natiue Comelinesse. Nay eu'n gets pardon for Deformity; Art cannot it beget, but may encrease; When Nature had fixt Beauty, perfect made, Something she left for Motion to adde. But let that Fashion more to modestie Tend, then Assurance: Modestie doth set The face in her iust place, from Passions free, Tis both the Mindes, and Bodies beauty met; But Modestie, no vertue can we see; That, is the Faces only Chastitie. Where goodnesse failes, twixt ill and ill that stands: Whence tis, that women, though they weaker be, And their desires more strong, yet on their hands The Chastity of men doth often lie: Lust would more common be then any one, Could it, as other sinnes, be done alone. All these good parts a Perfect woman make, Adde Loue to me, they make a Perfect Wife, Without her Loue, Her Beauty should I take, As that of Pictures; dead; That giues it life: Till then, Her Beauty like the Sun doth shine Alike to all; That makes it, onely mine. And of that Loue, let Reason Father be, And Passion Mother; let it from the one His Being take, the other his Degree; Selfe-loue (which second Loues are built vpon) Will make me (if not Her) her loue respect, No Man, but fauours his owne worths effect. As Good, and wise; so be she Fit for me, That is, To will, and Not to will the same, My Wife is my Adopted-selfe, and shee As Mee, so what I loue, to Loue must frame. For when by Marriage, both in one concurre, Woman conuerts to Man, not Man to her. FINIS. The Authors Epitaph written by himselfe. The Span of my dayes measur'd, heere I rest, That is, my body; but my soule, his guest, Is hence ascended, whither, neither Time, Nor Faith, nor Hope, but onely Loue can clime; Where being now enlightned, She doth know The Truth of all, men argue of below: Onely this dust doth here in Pawne remaine, That, when the world dissolues, she come againe. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>