<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Arwaker, Edmund</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Arwaker, Edmund</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">arwaker edmund</field>
      <field name="author_text">Arwaker, Edmund</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1700's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_2.0035.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1705</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464710</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Birth-Night ; A Pastoral. By Mr. Arwaker</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Birth-Night ; A Pastoral. By Mr. Arwaker</field>
      <field name="title_facet">birth night</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">birth night</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Birth-Night ; A Pastoral. By Mr. Arwaker</field>
      <field name="year_display">1705</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1705</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1705</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464710&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464710&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Arwaker, Edmund&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;arwaker edmund&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Birth-Night ; A Pastoral. By Mr. Arwaker&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;birth night&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1705&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1705&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Arwaker, Edmund&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Birth-Night&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Pastoral. By Mr. Arwaker&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for H. Bonwicke at the Red-Lion in St. Paul's Church-yard&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1705&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0130&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;13 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Birth-Night&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Pastoral. By Mr. Arwaker&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 22 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE Birth-Night, A PASTORAL. MENALCAS and AMARILLIS. AMARILLIS. Defensive Folds our Midnight Flocks inclose On Woolly Beds our fleecy Lambs repose. Our Lowing Herds in dozing Slumbers lye, Their Couch the Grass, their Canopy the Skye. The Lark, whose flight is Heav'n, and Earth his Nest, From Lofty Toil is laid at Humble Rest. Th'industrious Bee in thriftless Quiet dwells; No murm'ring Swarms surround their waxy Cells. No Rangers rob the Flow'rs t'inrich their Hive, Nor from full Stores unactive Idlers drive. Alike the lazy Drones and lab'ring Bees Are lull'd in Sloth, and are dissolv'd in Ease. Man's all compos'd, his Passions all serene; No troubled Thought disturbs his setled Mien; His careless Limbs in peaceful Rapture spread, Like Death his Sleep, and like the Grave his Bed. MENALCAS. The glimm'ring Moon expands her Silver Beams To paint the Meadows, and to gild the Streams: She shines on tall Augusta's tow'ring Spires, Whose pale Reflections shew like distant Fires: Her partial Rays aspiring Monatains gild, While prostrate Vales with dusky Gloom are fill'd. She forms with softest Shade and smoothest Light The pleasing Landskip of the lovely Night. An awful Hush in solemn Grandeur reigns, All calm the Skies, and all sedate the Plains; Round the still World the noiseless Stars make haste: O happy World! by circling Heav'n embrac't. AMARILLIS. But hark! the Nightingale begins her Moan; She grieves, if Melody be Grief, alone. A pointed Thorn awakes her Nightly Strains, With Pain she sings, and with Delight complains, ‘Come, walk my Love, and as we move along, ‘Charm the pleas'd Pastures with a sweeter Song. Come, my Menalcas, to yon River side: Thro' spacious Groves her spread Meanders glide. The Pine and Elm in ranges crown her Banks; Those Sons of Earth invade the Sky in Ranks. Her Glassy Surface shews th'adjoyning Wood, And Heav'n surveys its Image in her Flood. Come, let us trace the Maze thro' which she roves, Wind round the Hills, and wander thro' the Groves. With leisure pace, her flowry Margin tread By twining Streams thro' wooddy Lab'rinths led; ‘And as she flows, and as we move along, ‘Teach me, lov'd Shepherd, some instructive Song. MENALCAS. Thee, only thee, my Strains desire to move, And all that I wou'd teach thee, is to love. But haste, my Amarillis, We forget The Rural Youth at Past'ral Pastime met. ‘This solemn Night they spend in dutyous Mirth: ‘Blest Night, that gave great Galatea Birth! ‘No heavy Tax her free-born People grieves: ‘We pay her Tribute in the Joy she gives. Amidst yon Beachy Grove's a level Green, Whose Oval Plan surrounding Arbors screen The Country Theatre of harmless Sport, Where active Swains and sprightly Nymphs resort; The verdant Center bears a spiral Pine Whose waving Boughs with flaming Torches shine. Where am'rous Pairs in Rosie Garlands crown'd, On Moss-green Carpets dance an artless Round: In Viney Grotts; where languid Shepherds woo, And billing Doves on bending Myrtles coo; Where tuneful Youths contend in Rival Lays To Galatea's Fame, and Pollio's Praise. The listning Pan a Rustick Gambal leads, And grinning Fauns frisk o'er the bord'ring Meads. In lonely Caves dissolving Silvans sigh, And thro' soft Æther tender Echoes fly. Pæan the Prince of Musick and of Day, Hastes to o'ertake the Shepherds at their Play. Come, darling Nymph, come like the dawning Morn, Whose Eastern Robes th'inlighten'd World adorn The fullest Joy will own a kind Increase From thy wish'd Presence, my lov'd Shepherdess. All shall address their Homage to your Face; Each Youth his Chaplet, and each Fair her Place. ‘This Night from Kings who reach from Heav'n to Earth. Great Galatea took her Royal Birth. ‘No heavy Tax her free-born People grieves; ‘We pay her Tribute of the Joy she gives. AMARILLIS. Tho' I forgot th'Occasion, yet I thought Heav'n put not on such Ornaments for nought. A Birth-night Garb rejoicing Nature wears; New Flow'rs the Pastures, and new Stars the Spheres. This Night the Spring, ambitious to be gay, From gawdy Summer steals her best Array; The Oaks their Leaves, the Vines their Grapes disclose: Each Thorn a Berry, and each Brier a Rose. ‘The Spring, like Galatea, takes her Birth ‘At once to cherish, and to grace the Earth. In Fields our Herds, and in their Folds our Sheep, And in their Hives our Swarms their Revels keep. The Nightingale no more her Rape bewails, But sings glad Io's thro' the ravish'd Vales. Her wakeful Joy needs no alarming Thorn; This Night the Goddess of her Song was born. ‘Haste to the sports, and as we move along, ‘Sing the Great Monarch in a nobler Song. MENALCAS. Their gilded Heads Augustean Turrets raise, And seem, like Rockets, as they rise to blaze. No borrow'd Light to palefac'd Heav'n they owe: Their Gates with Stars, their Streets with Comets glow. With joyful Peals their stately Temples ring, And in each Spire ten thousand Pleasures sing. The warbling Sounds on hov'ring Pinions stretch, But tire and languish e're these Plains they reach. ‘This solemn Night is spent in dutyous Mirth, ‘Blest Night, that gave great Galatea Birth! ‘No heavy Tax her free-born People grieves: ‘We pay her Tribute of the Joy she gives. AMARILLIS. But hark! the Satyrs o'er the Brambles prance, The Shepherds pipe, and Shepherdesses dance. Thro' sounding Woods dispersing Murmurs pant, And call Menalcas, for 'tis him they want. Come, my lov'd Swain, to sporting Herdsmen come, All shall with Wonder and Respect be dumb. Thy Tunes shall all their Faculties imploy In silent Transport and attentive Joy. All shall address their Homage to thy Art, Each Youth his Laurel, and each Fair her Heart; While smiling, I with haughty Pleasure see The Nymphs admire a Swain reserv'd for me. ‘Haste, Love, and as we trace these Streams along, ‘Sing the best Monarch in the sweetest Song. Thy Serenades shall echo thro' the Deep Where snowy Nymphs on Chrystal Couches sleep. Thy tempting Strains the wat'ry Pow'rs shall rouse From Thrones of Coral, and from Beds of Owse. The beaut'ous Naids deck'd in Pearly Shells, Shall leave their Fountains, and forsake their Wells, With naked Limbs to glide thro' yielding Weeds In fond pursuit of thy alluring Reeds. Thy Notes shall pierce the Thicket of the Boar, And thorny Wilds where shaggy Satyrs snoar. Tho' lustful Pan were bent in hottest Chace Of some coy Goddess of the Sylvan Race. Drawn by Resistless Pow'r of Magick Sound, He after thee, she after him shall bound. Both shall forget the cause of their Career, The God his Passion, and the Nymph her Fear. Each Savage shall approach to hear thee play, Pow'rless to leave thee, tho' afraid to stay. Each docile Bird upon his dwelling Tree Shall court his Mate in Notes he learnt of thee. MENALCAS. This joyful Night our Hero's recent Ghosts On Hockstean Plains extend their adverse Hosts; With dreadful Joy repeat the daring Fight, In Charges sport, and in Attacks delight. Immortal Youths of various Nations ride In scarlet Glory, and in feather'd Pride. Ethereal Flags in native Skies unfurl'd, Urge the sharp Contest of th'expecting World. From smoaking Brass emitted Thunders kill, And roar, as if they mourn'd the Blood they spill. When Airy Pow'rs dispute their wide Controul, Such Flames they brandish, and such Bolts they roul. The Roman Souls of past success despair, Because Camillus lives and is not there. Thrice they attack, but thrice attempt in vain; The steady Foe the weighty shock sustain. Mean time Marcellus scorning to furvey His Parents Arms confess a doubtful Fray. The Golden Gate of Saphire Heav'n unbars, Stoops to the Conflict, and forsakes the Stars. Alexis from the Clouds his Prince attends, Both valiant Youths, Hereditary Friends. O Death! how hast thou blasted in their Spring A blossom'd Hero and a blooming King! Before their Swords without Distinction fall, The Rebel Hun, and the perfidious Gaul. Affrighted Squadrons seek the Danube's Shore, And safe Retreats from River Gods implore. The plunging Troops in foaming Surges broke, Expire amidst the Numens they invoke: The Victors o'er the Bridges of the Dead, Destroy the Flying, and pursue the Fled. In bloody Harness o'er the blushing Waves, With hideous Cries distracted Slaughter raves. The wounded Danube whips his scaley Steeds, Roars to the Sea, and as he flys he bleeds. Proud Gaul no more exalted Banners boast, Thy faded Lilies load the German Coast. Thy humbl'd Colours lie: thy Fun'ral Sheets Predestin'd Trophies of Augusta's Streets. The stain'd Arena glows with massie Spoil, And breathless Striplings spread th'embroider'd Soil. Old Warriours fam'd for num'rous Conquests past, Here meet a Victor first, and breathe their last. With pannick Fear a mighty Army yields, Unus'd their Swords, and unimploy'd their Shields: Resounding Tubes expiring Mars excite Whose dead Alarms the neighb'ring Towns affright. The Villagers with dread behold from far The fantom Troops at visionary War. This joyful Night delighted Ghosts engage With real Pleasure and dissembl'd Rage. ‘But haste, my Dear, the Night dissolves in Mirth: ‘Blest Night that gave great Galatea Birth. ‘No heavy Tax her free-born People grieves: ‘We pay her Tribute in the Joy she gives. AMARILLIS. So well you paint, methinks I bear in sight The order'd Onset and the scatter'd Flight. I see each Wound, and I perceive each Stroke By Fleaks of Lightning thro' the Clouds of Smoke. Thy sweet Canores on dismal Themes forbear: For tho' with pleasure, I with terror hear. Sing Neptune's Courts where Ocean Gods reside, And Tritons dance in triumph o'er the Tide: ‘Where summon'd Rivers from th'extended Earth ‘In joyful Conflux keep the Royal Birth. The sev'ral Streams in diff'rent Songs relate Their Tyrants Vices or their Monarchs State. Let Gallia's Seine her Lords Oppressions tell, His Rage the Po, his Rapines the Moselle. While Ship-crown'd Thames informs the wondring Main Of glorious Galatea's gentle Reign; That subject Seas who willing Tribute pay, May prize the more the Sov'reign they obey. ‘Or sing the Heav'ns where Kings who sway'd the Earth ‘In perfect Rapture keep their Offspring's Birth. . . Or, sing the Seats, if thou canst raise thy Voice, Where Galatea and her Nymphs rejoyce. MENALCAS. Describe th'Illustrious Mansions, sacred Muse Which Galatea and her Graces chuse. Speak Goddess, speak, and tell me, hast thou seen The lovely Dwellings of the Paphian Queen: Or spangled Cœlum where attending Pow'rs Surround great Juno in the Starry Bow'rs. If thou hast seen all this, my Muse, report A feint Idea of her glitt'ring Court. The Radiant Chambers of her bright Aboad With Joys are hung, and with Delights are strow'd. A Galaxie of Beauties form her Train, And each lov'd Nymph beholds a Fav'rite Swain: A Virgin Sign adorns the Azure Waste: With nobler Maids this happier Zodiack's grac't. Each Gorgeous Fair a splendid Rival vies, In Sparkling Jewels and Refulgent Eyes. But All, with ease, Camillus's Race confess, Excel in Beauty, and Exceed in Dress. So Waring Culv'rins shining Flames display, And Great Alcides made the Milky Way. Here brave Camillus charms his Constant Bride, His Smiles put on, his Thunders layd aside. Mars Woos his Goddess so, when Tumults cease; And whilst he Sports, permits the World a Peace. With chearfull Mien the high-born Pollio stands, And Battles dire to Seas remote Commands. No boist'rous Storms can ruffle Thetys's God Tho' Spouts and Hurricanes observe his Nod. Stay, Muse, forbear the Majesty to draw; 'Twill own her Lustre, and confess thy Awe The dimmest Gem, that spots her fulgent Locks Wou'd buy our Fields, our Cottage and our Flocks. No duller Stars to livelyer Eyes compare; To brighter Curls no Berenice's Hair. No Tyrian Dye to her Imperial Robe, Nor to her emblem Orb the heav'nly Globe. Be silent Muse, for Silence will express Her Pomp the greater, and thy Skill no less. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>