<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">O'Shaughnessy, Arthur William Edgar, 1844-1881</field>
      <field name="author_facet">O'Shaughnessy, Arthur William Edgar, 1844-1881</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">oshaughnessy arthur william edgar 1844 1881</field>
      <field name="author_text">O'Shaughnessy, Arthur William Edgar, 1844-1881</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1870's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.0459.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1874</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466223</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">French</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Lays of France ; (Founded on The Lays of Marie.) By Arthur O'Shaughnessy. Second Edition</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Lays of France ; (Founded on The Lays of Marie.) By Arthur O'Shaughnessy. Second Edition</field>
      <field name="title_facet">lays of france</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">lays of france</field>
      <field name="title_text">Lays of France ; (Founded on The Lays of Marie.) By Arthur O'Shaughnessy. Second Edition</field>
      <field name="year_display">1874</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1874</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1874</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466223&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466223&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;O'Shaughnessy, Arthur William Edgar, 1844-1881&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;oshaughnessy arthur william edgar 1844 1881&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Lays of France ; (Founded on The Lays of Marie.) By Arthur O'Shaughnessy. Second Edition&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;lays of france&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1874&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1874&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;O'Shaughnessy, Arthur William Edgar&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1844&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1881&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Lays of France&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;(Founded on The Lays of Marie.) By Arthur O'Shaughnessy. Second Edition&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chatto and Windus&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1874&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp2918&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;fre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;293 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Lays of France&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;(Founded on The Lays of Marie.) By Arthur O'Shaughnessy. Second Edition&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 363 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">LAUSTIC; OR, THE LAY OF THE NIGHTINGALE. ‘This olde gentil Bretons in here daies Of divers aventures maden laies, Rimyden in her firste Breton tonge, Whiche laies with here instrumentes thei songe, Other elles redden hem for her plesance, And one of hem have I in remembrance Which I shall seie with goode wil as I can.’ Chaucer: Prologe to the Frankeleyne's Tale. ‘Une aventure vus dirai Dunt li Bretun firent un Lai; Laustic ad nun ceo m'est avis, Si l'apelent en lur païs: Céo est reisun en Franceis, E Nihtegale en dreit Engleis.’ Marie: Lais. MS. Bibl. Harl. No. 978. Fair ladies, give me leave to sing: God will I may die serving you And finding ever some sweet thing To praise your beauty and renew The soft enchantment of your love: Now let my singing please your ears, Or gentle pity in you move, Bringing your eyes the grace of tears, Yet never grieving you too sore With any lay of mine or tale; Yea so: for I shall say no more Singing a fair thing, ere I fail, Of lovers and a nightingale. In Brittany a goodly town Is Bon, and there indeed befell What I shall show, and had renown. Two knights who loved each other well Through many a year were come to dwell In that fair town at length; good fame In all France very wide and far They twain had earned for deeds of war; And their whole living had no blame Of any, but before and then Right noble seemed they to all men. Now this befell, and was the fate: One of those knights wed with his hand A lady, who was fair and great— Yea, rather, throughout all that land Fairest and greatest in good sooth: In all the riches of sweet youth She was quite perfectly arrayed, With every grace that flowers have Of spring, or beauty that a maid May have or that a man may crave To look on for his love. Great pride It was to woo and win that dame; Yea, so to take her for man's bride It was a thing for which knights came Full many and from far and wide In France; but soon they all had shame Because of this one of renown Who came and took her for his own. How shall I say she was so fair? But truly God did her compose Of the same colours as the rose, Which of all flowers he does declare The fairest: this way she was fair: First pale she was, all delicate— Like the first sweetest leaf that shows Frail texture, and lets penetrate Through its pure secret, to the flows Of inner feelings intricate That change and glow,—so was she, too, Pale and most tender; you might trace The heart and all its yearnings through Her virgin colour: as she grew, The perfect inner soul began To rise to many a purple place Of blushes on her changing face, Or on her neck that shamed a swan Or snow for white: at length her skin Was all fair fading, all fine hue; And her eyes held the fairest blue That is not in God's heaven above. She was a goodly bride to win! She wedded ere she knew what love Can and doth do; what right he hath To rule in all; to change and move All things that are; to make a path For all hearts whither they shall go: She wedded ere she well could know. And, alas! for it did befall Of sad fate to that gentle dame, She could not love with love at all The husband to whose hand she came; But love the rather did intend A thing most crooked; day by day See knew not of his subtle way, Thought truth and cared not to defend Her heart with any sort of arm; So day by day grew up the harm. That other knight, her husband's friend Seemed fair unto her eyes; and fain Her heart grew of his sight, till pain And tears it was to miss his smile That seemed such healing; for no fear Bade her withhold when he was near Her heart; but sweetest was the while He, sitting nigh, touched her almost, Or gold edge of his garment crost Her own robe; no doubt did defile Her thought, to think that there was sin, Or that in such way could begin Love's ill; but precious seemed the eve, When so they sat, and he was singing Some song to bid her bide the night In peace; the music, too, would leave Soft sighing echoes, 'mid the clinging Of many a balm of rich delight, Stored in the soul through that fair hour —The purples of some closing flower, Thin distant scents of thyme or musk Faded or finished far away 'Mid the dim blightings of the dusk. And so, in many a subtle way, Her heart was wholly leaguered round And poisoned with a sweet love-wound; And so she learned love day by day. Alas for her again! She loved Deep in her heart, before she knew Aught of the ill that love should do To her own heart and him she loved. But in good time this thought did grieve —All for the ancient love that had Those knights—in secret communing Her lover: yea, it made him mad To think that he should e'en deceive That friend of his in such a thing. So for his honour he was moved To have good care; and, sorely rueing, With many a penance he reproved His heart, and sought some straight undoing Of all this toil love's craft had made; Who held both of them in his hand; Whose fingers were like fetters laid About their hearts. And to withstand Truly in this design, he plann'd That he would seek no more her face To see, nor covet to draw near For sake of her in any place: And this he vowed, with many a tear, To do in all faith for a year. Fair ladies, think not any shame; For love ye know hath longing feet, Yea, it hath ever been the fame— To walk in strange paths of deceit; I pray you, therefore, think no shame; For surely it must be the same As long as love: so be content; And I shall set me to repeat The whole thing for your ravishment, And truly, for the tale is sweet. The houses were together quite; The roofs and all the window places Drew nigh with yearning to unite; They were quite like two lovers' faces, Leaving just space enough for sighs And fair love looks and soft replies; You could just see the blue above, You were just far enough for breath Indeed, or near enough for love; There lay a little turf beneath Where a few sickly flowers grew, Chilled by the shadows of the eaves, Warmed by the light that trembled through; A rose all white and with no leaves, Slender and like a maid that grieves, And other flowers one or two. But round about and from the sides, At every moment you could hear A pleasant noise of wind that glides Among thick boughs; for very near There was a garden, and a wood Full of sweet-scented trees that stood Shivering for pleasure in the sun, Whose shadows rustled on the wall; There through the day, one after one The sweet birds sang till even-fall; And then they ceased, and the night long, Sang that one sweetest of them all— The nightingale, O many a song, Or all one song that could not pall Of love luxurious and long. And heavy hazel boughs shut in The souls and scents of all the flowers, The noon, the night and the fair hours; And kept the place all dim within, A pleasant place for love's sweet sin. The noon fell almost to twilight Under the heavy hazel boughs; And the great shadow of each house Growing made dark the other quite; There the dim time was very sweet; And hours between the noon and night Were slow to pass, with lagging feet And wings full-loaded; tarried late, Till long fair fingers from the deep Dark wood came forth to separate Leaves, lights from shades and love from sleep, And the moon, like a dreamed-of face Seen gradually in the dark, Grew up and filled the silent place Between those houses wan and stark. After a year that she was wed And had well striven with this love, Thought shame of it, well purposèd To slay it, yet, for all she strove, Loved with a love she could not quell; After a year, that lady fell Quite weak in heart because of it; She was like one on whom some spell Ill and mysterious hath lit To work great harm; she could not tell Her beads at night the holy way Her wont, nor any more compel Her pining feeble heart to pray; But silently she used the day, Mourning within, and weeping kept The night, and scarcely now she slept. One night in the full summer's tide, —Throughout the house no sort of stir, —For sleep lay heavily on all Though love most heavily on her, She left her lord's bed; from his side Rose softly, with no thought to fall Indeed to any sin; but all To quench and quell the heart she had, The heat within that made her mad. She threw the casement open quite, And let the summer air come in: Have you not stood, the summer night At windows; felt with soft delight The air come from the balmy land Play in your bosom with no sin, Play in your bosom like a hand? She stood and felt it on her brow, Like a kiss straying here and there, Like light lips playing in the hair; She felt it on her neck, and now Creeping through every loosened fold Of the night garment, more and more To slake her body with some cold Sweet touch of dews it thirsted for. The night so softly treated her, And, fair and fond, the moon so sought To lure with smiling; every stir, Or breath, or sound, or silence, taught So pure a peace, they cheated her Almost of bitterness and thought; They strove to heal the heaviness And that most secret sore distress Of her long ailment for love's sake; And all the night-sounds could not make Her fear for all the loneliness; Nay, for hard by her in the glade Of hazels was the nightingale; And his known singing did not fail, Like a fount babbling in the shade, Or music of familiar tale. All the sweet day things were in sight; And, with the wandering of her gaze, She sought them now in the changed light, Knew them in each inconstant phase, Found them in each familiar place; She counted all the flowers plain Under the house;—she could see quite The frail rose-petals with the stain Of their scarce love-tint in each vein, Tender and shrinking, almost white: There had she looked on them for hours; It was like dreaming the most sweet; A flower she was among those flowers, And soft light touchings of the air For lips of love seemed with full greet Kissing around her, faint and fair, Over her bosom and her hair. But it befell that she was stirred Out of the stillness of her dreaming; A sudden shadow crost the streaming Moonlight: some faint sound was heard; Sure one with step or touch did scare The deep night musings. She aware, With sweet forebodings that went through Her secret soul, scarce her eyes moved For dread, until she saw and knew The face of him who was so loved. He was before her in full light; And the great steady moonbeams made The narrow window-ledges bright About him; but a thickened shade Hid all the chamber; he was leant Such way against the inner wall Deep in the dark, that scarce at all She saw the uncertain lineament Of a dim drapery that let fall About him many a changeful fold; Maybe sometime his heart was told That she had felt his look on her; He was as one that could not stir; Their eyes met: then they seemed to touch At length with eyes and lips and face; For soul yearned forth to soul with such A might of yearning, all the space Seemed to yield fast between them, yea Grew rather to a perfect way. O 'twas a feast in every feeling So long a-hungered; sudden balm, All a long fever slowly healing And reaching quickly with its calm Each inmost lurking place of pain, That knew those lovers, seeing plain Each other after so long loss; Eye sated eye, face answered face; And so their looks did interlace They made a shining path across The moonlight in that silent place: For heaped-up floods of long desire Were loosened, and there was no power In all that tender midnight hour To hold or stand against them,—nay, But rather all things did conspire, Moonlight and nightingale and flower, In a sweet aid to help that they Should yet meet love, cheating the day And all their niggard fate's hard stress. So the night found for them a breast Of dreams and dews, and safe indeed Under her hair's dark shining tress, Full of sweet quietness and rest, Where they might have their love and lead Its luscious hour without molest. They both were pale, and bore long trace Of sorrow; each one read with fears, Looking upon the other's face, Great written histories of weeping, Great woven tapestries of tears; Saw the dim stains love cannot hide Under each wan white eyelid keeping Piteous record; found out beside Full many a passage of plain teen, And in a writing true and wet Of what heart's pain and feeling's fret Through the long desolateness had been; For, lo! on either face was cast Some shade of the long bitter past. They lingered, learning all these tender Secrets, and loved them as they learned; So each to each, with sweet surrender Of such sad lore as was hard earned Through so much labour of long grieving, Yielded at length past all deceiving The soul's bare surface; quite revealed Its inward secret of remorse And yearning, that had grown but worse Lying all fearfully concealed. But soon their weak hearts did revive With fertile bliss; and love did thrive A pure and spiritual flower Fit to inhabit the soft soils And regions in that holy hour Of midnight, fain indeed to live For subtle and mysterious joys; A tender flower, whose sense recoils From coarser climes of the day's noise, And sights and shreds of sunlight. Then, Their souls made compact to renew, Apart and secret from all men, Love-interchangings long and true; And love's own mystery was done, That silent hour, a way that none But the nightingale and the moonlight knew. Love lasted through the summer time; And had a language all its own, Of separate sighs and wordless rhyme, Of communing looks and kisses thrown; And had no need for lustier clime Than the unearthly midnight; grown Estranged at length from all the things Whose life sleep steals, but nigh of kin To the dim unviewed hoverings Of sweet things shadowy and thin That traverse moonlight with pale wings Of amber, when on blinded eyes Of men some heavy dream-death lies. —For, soon as, with all stealthy creep Of rays, the moon came forth again To touch each hostile sight with sleep In aid of lovers, not in vain Released, they two did haste to reap The great fresh harvest of each heart, Grown up through lonely hours unculled: Their lives indeed day tore apart And left a-dying; but each night Came just in saving time, annulled The hard day's spell and bade re-plight Love's broken bonds with new delight. No moment longer could they sit With day-long agonies that strove To bring on night desiring it, Ere from those window-places, lit With smiling of the moon, they wove Some mesh of intermingling looks That felt and fastened to each place Of beauty, crept to and took hold In all the shadowy nestling nooks Dimmest where love could ever trace Love; and in measure manifold They soon paid back all stolen peace; And with new presence soon consoled All pining; till the whole disease Of sorrow, in each sundered breast Begotten, was divinely cured With rapture of most new and blest Communion. Such sweet time, assured Of all love's joy, they could consume Serenely in a long-drawn leisure, Fulfilled with many a tranquil bliss, Born as mere transitory bloom Upon a branch, for the mere pleasure Of fragrance; many a tiny way, Almost as pleasant as a kiss, They found for making a sweet play Of love; they had continual treasure Heaped in their hearts; things fair to say With looks or tokens; to relate All quaint sad reveries of the thought In loneliness, and through what state The time had brought them; what new task Or pastime loneliness had taught Their fretting fingers; so to ask And so to render little treats Of trusting. Often they had wrought, Seeking such precious toil as cheats Love-languishment, some fair device In work of tapestry most fine; Or on a scroll dainty and nice Set forth most delicate conceits, Written in many a pleasant line Of sweet love-poesy: and ways Full easy found they to exchange Their gifts and messages athwart The white path of the thin moon-rays,— For love did strengthen every art, And, with his charm, subtle and strange, Prospered them, as he doth always,— Yea, so they learned a pleasant skill To cast those things each unto each, And could e'en send them at their will: And truly they failed not to reach Fair interchange with wafted sign Of kissing, or prolonged embrace Of looks; such way they could combine That many a moment they half felt Touchings sweet; as of face on face, When lips drain lips and eyelids melt And meeting tears make soft the place. And, more and more, this thing became To them a custom, the most sweet In all the heart; and so the dame Beloved it, she forgot to chide Her heart for all this fond deceit; Yea, she forgot or cast aside Such thought and that it was half sin. No man can otherwise abide In life but love must enter in: This thing—do what she would—God knew She could not help with all her care, Nor change; for love will have his due;— And before God she was most fair, And wise and good in all her way: Himself shall pardon and forbear In all things, as His mercy may. So when the night was, and her lord Lay in the bed beside her sleeping, She made no stir nor uttered word, But, while the nightingale was heard, And all the tender spells were keeping Silence and safety, rose and went To greet that lover; and so stayed, Nor thought that many an hour was spent, Ere she returned once more and laid Her down beside her lord, with fear He might have sought her and been wrath Not finding her; yet, all so dear And needful are the needs love hath, That many a time she rose again And left him; who, when he perceived She was so oft away, was fain To chide her somewhat; but believed Her true, and that she had at most Some fantasy of wayward mood, To see, maybe, the trees dark-leaved By the pale moonlight shadows crost, Or sickness of some hidden brood Of nameless longings unallayed, Wherein he nothing might avail, But whereunto some soothing made The still night and the nightingale. She was so fair indeed and good, And to his word in all so meek, In heart he could not, by the Rood, Find chiding for her harsh to speak; But he did pray her, for the fear He had she might attain to ill Through some chance spell of all the drear Strange magic of the night, to still Her sad unrest and wanton will; Yea, that she should not, for that bird, Forsake her lord so and her sleep; Whereto she promised with fair word; And yet from love she could not keep. But, on one day, he came, withal, And did bespeak her otherwise— Reproaching, and with wrath in all He said,—that he indeed was wise Of her whole doing and deceit, And of that love she had so sought To cover with all seeming meet; And for this wrong of will and thought She did his life, he bade her take Fair shame; because himself was true In all his way with her, nor brake His faith at all.—This he would do, He said, because of his love's sake,— He would still bear with her, and hide Her fault from men—yea, still renew Some trust in her; no more to chide Or tell her of that thing again; If she would truly do her part For right, and spare not toil or pain In striving till she freed her heart From all this grievous bond and stain. O when his voice that way she heard, Alas, she could do nought but weep; For very shame of her deceit She fell down in a sorrow deep; Amid her tears she spake no word And looked no look that could but meet With him her husband; yet she quite Desired to touch him and entreat The most of pardon that he might For the great wrong of will and thought She e'en had done his life; yea, now She purposed with herself to smite And slay this evil love had brought Into her heart; and, with a vow To Mary without sin, she said She would make true her living now, And of her love make recompense To him her husband; so she prayed, Through her whole grief and penitence, God might forgive her that offence. But lo, as the man went away, He took into his heart that day To do a hard thing; for he hailed His servants all, yea, the whole band Who served with willing heart and hand, And briefly spake to them, nor failed To tell them all there was a cause Of sore displeasure and unrest To her, whom each with service best Of love and honour, holding dear Did serve; wherefore, should each man pause In his own labour and forbear From doing other far or near, Until he might bring death to pass On such as wrought this ill. Alas, For then he said the nightingale, He was the doer of the thing; For that no fowl at all he was, But a magician who, for bale And mischief on them all to bring, Out of his witcheries did sing So sweetly faining all the nights That he could lure with his delights Their mistress from her lord and sleep; Yea, for the singing he did keep All night was truly not of bird, For sweetness new and magical Such as no man had ever heard, But an enchantment was it all. And so, he said, was come to ail The gentle lady whom all loved, Yea, she was grown quite wan and pale; All men had seen it as he told, How she became as one sore moved With witcheries; disease she had, A kind that no man could unfold With any leechcraft; fallen and sad She was of face and faint of eye; Her head like any rose's head When it is even come to die; Her hand too, like a dwindled leaf In autumn time, quite thin and wan; You might see all the tender thread Of the veins through, it was so thin;— And this came all of some mischief And not her fault; for sure no man Stood there to give her word of sin. He said too, he was full of fear And very heavy sorrowing, To think some ill fate might be near Unto them all; but most to bring Great woe upon his house and shame, Or losing of his wife so dear. But having heard, all in God's name They joined them to him with a will; And did devote themselves to do The thing he said; yea, in God's name, That no man should take rest until So fared he, that he brought or slew Some certain way that bird of ill And all his magic overthrew. Then took they many a kind of arm That might such quest of theirs assure; Nor spared they any sort of lure Man makes, that he may take or harm In any way of sport the free Wild birds that are in field or tree: And, lest some chance should be to save, By all his swiftness or his craft, That bird from death through snare or shaft Wingèd of skill from bow,—they gave A care made perfect through long toil To make a lime most deadly sure, Yea, so that never bird could foil The death of it; for without cure The touch and poison of it were, And the clinging of it most sore: And, truly, this was such a snare As fowler never had before. And he who moved them to this thing, He led them; and, when all was made, He tarried not their steps to bring Into the garden and the glade Where that sweet bird was wont to sing: There soon, with voices harsh and rude, They startled all the tender shade, And broods of mysteries that lay Of long time in that solitude, Woven among the leaves alway: For there he brought them on that day, In a great troop and multitude, The nightingale to take or slay. In truth they had small care or grace; They trode down all the tender flowers, Of whose short sweetness was that place Made fit to serve the short sweet hours That pass and come no more in life; They wrought a ruin in short space; And hasted in unseemly strife With the fair boughs and branches all, And cast their leaves down on the ground, And wounded them with many a wound, And many fair trees they made fall. But very soon it did not fail, Before they had done half their care, And purpose, that they had in snare That craftless bird the nightingale; Who was so free from stain of sin That way they thought that he was in, He fell to them quite unaware It was his death they sought to win. They took and brought him in their hands, The life yet in him, to their lord; Who, when he had him, with fair word Praised their good care of his commands; Then each man went forth to his lands. But straight into the house came he, That good knight, when the men were gone; Yea, he was even in a haste, And sought his wife where she might be; For yet the thought of the wrong done To him in time so little past Lay surely bitter at his heart; So, when he found her there alone, He spake her thus and without art: See, wife, he said, here is that bird —For well I trow that this is he— Who strangely and so long hath stirred Thy rest in nights past; yea, full sore, With all his song and witchery, Hath troubled all thy sleep and me; But now I think he shall no more, Nor may a song of his be heard, For I have taken him in snare; From him and evil everywhere May we have peace for evermore. So with that word, yea, as he spake, He took him in his hands, and hard He wrung him, so the neck he brake And took the life away with ease; And cast him to her afterward; She could no way to save him make, The bird fell dead upon her knees. She was in middle of her grief; Striving to take her leave of love, And weeping all the while she strove; But this new woe stole like a thief Her heart, and the sad power to move Her tears: first took she scarce belief That it was truly and indeed The singing nightingale she had; Yea, no time had she seen him lead Life in the body of a bird; And for his song, holy and sad And never with another heard, Angel of God him might she call Or something not to die at all. She took him; in her hand she took His body; and the life was scant Within it, and his blown plumes shook All in a palsy wofully; In his breath too there was no pant, And no stir at his heart nor look Of pleasant living in his eye; Surely his soul had broken plight With sweet frail life and left to die That relic. To such wretched sight Her tears came quickly, and the thought It almost was her love, so brought Before her slain and faded quite To wanness and sad autumn hue, The death colour of leaves: she knew Thereby, that, in her life, no more Should be that summer colour of love To purple it; and all the sore Of thought within her filled with pain, And grew such burden that she strove If, with lips seeking, she might gain —Yea, even out of that bird's bill, A part of death. But, in the end, She was turned to another will; She thought it would be sweet to send Unto her lover such last sign Of sorrow, and that they must kill Both of their hearts and unto deaths Indeed quite equal them resign; For that the harder part and fate Of life prest with prevailing breaths Bitter upon them, governed, gained, And laid such snare for all that late Their fairest, most indulged, their near Real seeming dream, that now remained For this no longer any state Or place at all,—but love was clear A thing unrealmed, a prey attained By the hard fastening hounds of grief: So she would send that bird—their dear Familiar—as a sign of brief Sad parting and of death all shared. And now to do this she prepared, And made soon, fair with many a lace, A little wallet tapestried Within of stuffs the richest dyed; Full daintily she did enchase The outer part; and worked it all With broideries symbolical; And, in the midst, she wrought a place For that slain bird; the body there Lay fitly covered up and prest Upon warm purples; in a nest It seemed, wings folded smooth and fair, And the head sleeping on the breast A grievous gift was this indeed For love to give.—But, with all speed, She did fulfil the thing and dare Its piteousness: it was conveyed That trackless way which love had freed Across the unconfessing air. Then she said sorrow was all made, To fill her life's long after-year With the full burden she might bear Of loneliness and of regret, And sharp thoughts with an inward fret Gnawing some remnant of a Past, Which should not give them ease while yet At heart the very life might last. She thought how wave of water feeds Upon some oasis of earth, Where hath been greenness and the birth Of flowers;—how it takes the reeds One after one, and with its lips Sucks in the lilies, makes sweet prey Of all at leisure, and in sips Dissolves the whole of it away: She deemed that it should be like this With those thoughts ever in her heart, Feeding upon each separate bliss That once grew in the fragrant part Of life called love: she would find store Of faded relic and perfume, To the most waste and meanest bloom That love's great time for her once bore; And sure the heart should be no more Ere such as this might all consume. She thought, too, how that flower the Rose, —After that it hath filled all June Full of its beauty, as man knows,— How it doth e'en begin to lose Softly its colour; and then soon To let the leaves and petals fall, But with such falling gradual As you may count them one by one, Yea, till it droppeth of them all: And with her heart so it should be, Yea, with that flower of her heart;— Full long should be the atrophy And falling of it part from part; And, for it was in the true core And richest soil of memory, Beauty of it should not depart, Nor fragrance of it be quite o'er, Till death's own snow for evermore Were fairly laid on all the heart. Ah, when the knight, her lover, found And knew that last of gifts from her; Such time now as he slow unwound The broidered bindings one by one, His heart within made many a stir Trembling, many a time it swooned With half foreboding what was done To their hearts equal: soon he read, And could not fail to understand The tender silken hieroglyph; And knew it written with her hand, That both had better have been dead Than to have loved so; and that life Had used up sweet and had instead No balm but death.—O then he sought Indeed for death, that balm,—quite caught And conquered of a great mad sorrow That would no healing, while he thought And knew that there should be no morrow For him to look once on her face, Or worship her in any place; That rather, with his heart's great sore Of love, he should go far and near About the world for evermore, And get no joy from year to year! Ladies, when he had thought and wept And gazed on that gift many a day, For it he found a casket bright Of finest gold; therein he kept That treasure, and with him alway: And then he went with many a knight To save the tomb where Jesu slept: In Palestine, so is the Lay, He fell and died in holy fight. THE LAY OF THE TWO LOVERS. O Love, where is the bed we made In scented wood-ways for sweet sin? The sun was with us and the shade; The warm blue covered us in: All men their curse on us had laid— Finding had slain us both therein; But, summer with us, not afraid Were we to love and sin. O Love, the crushed place is quite fair; Leaves have sprung back and flowers grown there; The blithe trees no long record bore; The flown bird knoweth no more; The hard one never found our lair;— We are not slain, love,—we are fair, And love, ay, as we loved before: —Let us go back once more! Lady, is there indeed no place Beyond the world for thee and me? Where we may love a little space, And joy as any flower or tree That loves the sun; and half forget That life our enemy hath been, And fate a bloodhound keenly set To hunt us on through waste and green And night and day and year and year, Lest we should hallow and make dear One spot of bitter earth with bliss? Is there indeed, beyond the day, Beyond the eve, beyond the sun, No dreamed-of place where we shall kiss, Ay, kiss and put all fear away, Death tarrying till our kiss is done? Since I have loved thee, I have known Their hard irrevocable doom— Ah, love,—mine henceforth and thine own— Whose lives are re-born in the womb Of love: it seems all common food That erst might feed them shall no more Bring to them any taste or good; But they shall go in hunger sore, Seeking some manna that scarce falls On earth; and, surely, their lives long, Full of sad secrets the world calls By names of shame, shall seem a wrong To them and to the world. For, sure, Both I and thee, whom this fair bower And frail night spells somewhile secure, Whom a thin heaven of scent and flower Doth feebly part from outer deaths Awaiting sore and manifold With stings of hate and long fierce breaths Of cursing,—small share do we hold Of any meanest privilege To have and use our common lives With joy; but, rather, this love drives Our doomed days cowering to some edge Of loveless strong humanity; And we are kin with some who lie Slain shamefully on bitter grounds Where grew their furtive flower of sweet; And some who, foiling the strong hounds Of tracking hate, have fled for meet Safe cover where the trees held shade, Or grass and thornbush knew the feet Of many a hunted thing afraid Of the sun's smile; who, through great plight With death and very choice to die, Have rapturously cared to buy One little year, one day, one night Of their lives' confiscated own, Wherein to taste indeed of love The great forbidden good unknown,— Yea, these may call us nought above Brother or sister; and take hands Of us and lead us, as they shall, Joined ever to their fameless bands Who, of all ages and all lands, Do bear one sad memorial That here love hath no heaven at all. My love, I have a lay well fit For me to sing and thee to hear; For they of whom I find it writ Did long time, amid hope and fear, Love secretly; having of fate The seeming fair things and good state Dull men are mocked with; but no place Or liberty, by day or night, To look upon that other face Life had for them shedding strange light Upon their inward thoughts. In fair Green midst of mountain-lands they dwelt, In Val de Pistre; for 'twas there A certain king had sometime built His castle. She, of whom I sing, Was e'en the princess and his child, Whom he would marry, coveting To strengthen by harsh means or mild His hated sway, to some hard lord Of neighbouring hosts. But love had wrought So fair a miracle and taught Such strength to her, that no sharp sword Might have compelled her to this thing. And now a year was he besought Of many, who, with pitying, Beheld her beauty and the death Love surely did intend to bring Upon her, yea to the last breath, That he would even let her wed The fair youth, whose, alive or dead, She could not fail to be. Alas, He grew the harder, and took rage Against them: so it came to pass Their two lives, full of sad presage, And faint with thoughts despairing fret, Were leaguered round about with fear;— Yea, fear was as a demon set About their steps both far and near In every moment, in the dark And in the day: the future year, That once had glimmered from afar With many a beacon-ray and spark, Like distant heavens of some star, Was changed and faded now—yea, changed, As though with long dim ambushed gleams Of deaths in shadowy phalanx ranged Against their coming days: their dreams Were very heavy with the clank And echo the chained days still made Around them; and oft-times they shrank From sleep, as though hard hands were laid Upon the wide unguarded heart To read each open thrill and start. They had been happy, yea, in truth A few sweet hours of precious youth, Ere the world found them. Once and more, The rich effusion of some kiss Had warmed shy scents the roses bore, Making the full heart of some noon Their own most strangely, in a bliss No summer knew or felt before They loved; and, once and more, the swoon Of eve had lengthened out some joy Of theirs, delaying the hard chill And dim affright that would destroy Too shortly such a day, until The blithe eternal nightingale Had seen and known, and did not fail To sing that, though hard fate should kill The twain that midnight, they had taste Of sweet, for one rich day of life. Many a garden place was rife With tender record of fond waste Of hours and broken words and sighs, In the long innocence when love Kept fearful fetters on their eyes And lips and hearts, the more to prove His strong life-filling flower, one day A bursting blossom not forborne. But now the fair earth turned away Her summer from them: on no morn Did shy beams, stealing from the sun, Bring early promise of joy born To fill them till that day was done In some close paradise of bloom, Where love had made them a fair room With unbetraying bird and tree And sleek scared fawn.—O but to see The warm bright chambers under leaf Sun-streaked and gilded morn and noon; The burrow under the arched sheaf Whose crowned heads nodded to some tune Of wordless wavy motion, dim And dense with harvest scent that drew The brown bee blundering o'er the rim To drone about them the noon through! O but to see, yea, once again, Though but to weep, the bed they left Of prest and tumbled leaves with stain Of fair crushed flowers, the day he reft The first long willing bliss from her, And she felt safe to touch and stir The strange and gracious hair he had That once so lured her, as a thing Whereon love's blessing seemed to cling!— Ah, she had said, it would be sad For her, then in the world, when time Were come that she could no more touch His warm drooped head, nor draw the rhyme Of soft words from his lips once more, Watching and loving overmuch Each passionate corner of his mouth: And now 'twas almost come, that sore Too bitter time of her heart's drouth. Their place was no more in the bloom; All ruined was it; and their doom Was a thing sung of by the bird That long had caught his rhapsody Straight out of their charmed thinking, heard And felt like some strong melody The corn or trees made, wordless, wild, Most wonderful: in the grey shade, The searched and trampled solitude Still bore the curses that defiled Its echoes; all the mournful glade Had heard dread shouts and voices rude; Yea, the whole country no more had One shelter of sweet green, one wood, One safe path bright for them, not one; But bitter seemed its smile, and sad And like an alien land it grew, That put scorn of them in its sun, And death lurked in its shade they knew. And now Death only let them draw Each unto each, when most they drew Nigh to himself: he only saw Dread lonesome places where they came In the dark, beautiful and white Beyond their wont; oft-times blue flame Quite clothed the marsh plants, and the night Down there felt horror, seeing that one So clasped and revelled on the slight Soft splendours of a woman—death Hard over him as a prey won— Death stretching to him with armed hands Nigh clutching at the throat where breath Quivered so rapturously. Ah, love, There was no path to other lands, Save only by the mountain steep And desolate, that stood above A mighty way and seemed to sleep On through the year in storm or rain. And yet, thou must be sure, so vain The fair world seemed, they oft would pray Their tenderest fate might show them plain, Through some safe chasm, the merest way To any desert of the earth, Far from that country of their birth Where they were aliens. Many a hope Had fallen from them. Fearful seemed That mountain in the distance; slope On slope of green they counted high Upon its side—down which there streamed Whole rivers fallen from the sky: But, sometimes, they had even dreamed There was a way to heaven, past The topmost crag and precipice; Often a golden cloud was cast Across it bright, and like a piece Of purest heaven it floated there And faded not: but in the fair Angelic moonlight quite a strange Most holy smile seemed resting wide Upon its height, working some change Of snowy mystery: one noontide They saw high up there, nigh the sun, Fair arched paths, gleaming every one As though the winged angels trod Them oft-time going up to God. Then, for no better thing they yearned,— Seeing the whole green world below, Yea, and as far as they might go Fleeing for ever, was all turned Against their love,—than to be there, Quite saved above the ken and reach Of any man, where each to each Might yield some latest hour more fair Than all life past, and truly will The utter breath to love, until Some charmed sleep, wonderful and soft, With deep strange soothings and long dreams Of wings and golden miles of light, Should take them; wherefrom, perhaps, oft Awaking before death, warm gleams Of the same sun would show them, bright, The unchanged earth beneath them yet, Their two selves, and the broad waste green, Full of light singing wind and hum Ineffable, where to forget All but one love they twain were come. And now that love of theirs, I ween, Had even brought them, through fond sin, Past many a death that land decreed; And the king strove a while between A voice at heart that entered in Like a returning bird indeed By disused unfamiliar ways, With pleading overmuch of days When she, now scorned and half condemned, Seemed yet his child fair and unshamed, A perfect promiser of joys;— And the loud whisper of the land And the unanswered urging voice Of many a counseller who planned This way and that to save the law: But day by day could only draw One thing the nearer to them—death. Yea, as I singing of this lay, —Knowing myself e'en such as they Of whom I sing, one changed and filled And lifted by a great pure love, That is much stronger than aught willed By me, and seemeth much above This world,—as I do feel my heart Rise many a time and glow and yearn Like a thing doomed and set apart For perfect sacrifice,—I say As one who learneth and shall learn, Those lovers and their love so fair Had condemnation from the day The bitter world began; both there, And in all lands beneath the sun, And here as there, and now as then, Other than this had not been done By the world unto them: for lo, They be few women and few men, —Of thousands here that come and go, By life-long ways named virtue, shame Sin, innocence, mightiness or fame, Whither I know not,—few they be That reach or touch, conceive or see, Through all mock strivings, kisses, prayers Cold passions, measured lusts of theirs, This one love—led to every way; Which whoso winneth, from that day Hath heavens within him all unfurled And clear sights of the other side Of death. But half loves in the world, And lusts, the dead roots that divide From the spurned cast off flower, are great, And many as mankind, crouch down Timid and loathsome, without fate Or hope or pang or passionate crown, Dying among the deaths and days. And these ignobly safe, being shorn Of all the measureless curse or praise Of love's unmeasured futures—born Inevitably to the whole True daring venture of the soul Eternal through its chosen hell Or chosen heaven,—these do possess The altered earth, first peopled well By love's first self; now to oppress His straggling offspring, like some rare And wingèd alien, having share Of unknown being with the blue And supernatural places fair. —O Lady mine is this not true? Were it not better I and you Had found some straight way long ago Up to the place we seem to know With all our mingled being, hard by In new parts of our destiny, Or even dwelt in, as doth seem, In parts so far they form a dream Within and round us?—Mistress mine, Since here the charmed space of a vine, A few leaves shade, is all love's bower, And all the time one reckless hour Of treacherous night, wherein a cry Too sharp amid our ecstasy Must surely doom us; and since now, Ay, more and more, we do avow No wild wide earth were wide enough, But the immenseness of our love Must have its ending in some star,— Were it not even better far We had found freedom the first days, And earned with our first kiss's breath Some easy momentary death? O to wake strangely in fair ways Past every bar of death and birth, Launched high above all law and hate Or memory of the finished fate Of sloughed pasts in a cast off earth,— And bare and shameless through the whole Eternal unreprovèd soul, To lead on, formed into its form And fated with its fate, this strong Compelling passion, great and long, And one in me and thee!—The storm Of all the blind divine first things, Whose vast eternal wills and wings Bear them fulfilling, age on age, The nameless elemental rage Of the same lusts, loves, hungers, thirsts, That God who gave can ne'er assuage— The storm of the great universe, With all its tidal throes and bursts Of passionate being and excess, Should set us free of fate and curse And shame and tyranny and stress Of day and night—me to possess Thy soul and body for no less Than thine and mine eternity, And thee to give thyself to me Through all thou art or hast to be. I wonder, Love, in what sad way Of sudden bitter pang or shame, The world, that calleth by a name Of sin this love of ours, shall slay, Thinking to end us?—On that day, Shall we have dreamed of death at all?— Shall we be sundered for the space Of some blind fearful moment, face Unsoothed by face, so that we fall Alone through the first dreary waste, Amazed with sickening doubt of death And love and fate?—Or shall the breath Of our two beings, in their blithe haste Escaping, meet, ere yet the taste Of holy agony hath ceased? Ah, well could I desire that they— The twain whose one love was released In Val de Pistre, years gone by, Of whom I sing now—lest we try This perilled hour with too much bliss— Were e'en ourselves. Lady, one kiss,— And I will finish now my lay. Though men and women in their land Did wear the lure of softened looks, And spake love-speeches, and laid hand In wedded hand, and read in books Much gracious and real lore of love;— Yea, though they were right fair withal, And bore rich outward shows enough To cheat love's self with welcoming,— Yet dwelt they, men and women all, In hells of their own fashioning, Where golden good of life was turned To each foul contrary, and love The true god, some rare day returned In stainless perfect semblance bright, Looked shamed and hideous in the light Of long age-honoured lies, above One heart's weak will to change or break. Long years ago some fatal snake Had crept among their hearts, and shed The venom of false shames and dread Between them all; and now the heart Lied back unto the heart that lied; And life lived false with life and died Faining a faithless sanctity: Yea, so that now, for each man's part In life and good, God's changeless sun, The green gay earth, the blithe blue sky That spake unchanged of love did lie. And, therefore, very few or none Of all those men and women, framed, As even they two and as we, To know love and be known unshamed Of love, had eyes at all to see Or hearts to feel or voice to cry That these were very far from sin And had done nought that they should die Like caitiffs: rather all could say Some slight thing treasured up within, Condemning them from some past day When they but used the sun and bloom And rapture of their frank fair world, And knew not that its least perfume And lightest joy were long become Things chained and confiscate. Back-hurled Upon their hearts in cruel hard Accusing, knew they now e'en some Of their own sweet words, whispered low Where they were fit, for skies fair starred And guileless birds and leaves to know And take for music, not for ears Of those who turn sweet words to spears Against the heart from whence they flow. And, truly, since the king had set His utter curse upon the twain, And would not have the law be let From punishing, they had been slain With common sinners the first day— None finding in his heart a way To save them,—only for this thing, That she was daughter of the king And might not fall beneath the hand Of any subject in the land. So, many a hopeless day, meantime, Was added to their numbered days. At last spake some one that their crime Should be for God to take the right To punish or forgive, in ways Of some ordeal in the sight Of all. And being nigh the year's Great day of meeting and of sports, When trials many and of sorts Most various did engage all fears And hopes,—the king made this decree; That, whosoe'er the man might be That claimed the princess for his love, He should that day be man enough To bear her strongly in his arms Quite up the mountain, and again To bring her back,—as through all harms And o'er steep mountains of the pain Of life a man must truly bear The woman whom he hath:—for clear It seemed, the toil, so far, alas, All simple strength of man did pass, None other could have heart to try But he whose love to live or die With her was equal. On the night Before that day, the common voice Of folk who scarcely had a choice, So they beheld the morrow's sight, Between the ending well or ill Of these, did on all sides declare That, unless God should take the will To save those lovers, and prepare Some wondrous miracle to show His mercy on them, by their sure Disaster, quickly all must know Their way was neither good nor pure. But, on that night, without a fear, As though sure happiness were near, The two who loved vowed each to each The extreme day left or the year Of life to come; and death could teach No unknown grief to them it seemed; But rather many sweet things dreamed Should be accomplished to them then: And, on the other hand, there gleamed, As though from no short lives that men Had power to trample out and end, The clear untroubled heaven within Each soul, that love had made descend— An inextinguishable part Of some eternity, akin To nothing that took change and death Of earth: more wonderful at heart The great resplendent secrets grew, That could not find a word or breath To bear their telling, while they two Sat fated in the darkening world That one night before fate: and, free, The thoughts for which strange lives shall be Hereafter, entered and unfurled Their depths and passed between them free. And through an unrecorded hour, Wherein the multitudes of men, With the amassed tyrannic power Of all their laws, became again As in the ancientness, when earth Held not one place of death or birth,— It came to pass indeed that they, With nought belonging to the day Of common life upon them, whole In the eternity that soul Did give to soul, sat quite alone, As a man doth the hour unknown Before his death, in the great bare Unalterable midst of hell And heaven. And then were they aware Of being severed from all kin, And alien from the ill or well, And the law making good or sin To any creature: only they, —Henceforth together—should begin One new almighty spirit, free With its own good and evil way And power to end itself or be For ever. Such a distant sight They had, beyond the daily haze Of bounded vision, at the height And depth of endless destiny That love's inevitable ways Had wrought for them,—they little knew, That eve, how tenderly the blue, Richer with many a memory Out of their open hearts, gave birth To every rapturous burning star; Nor with what perfumed hands the earth Made miracles of sweetness far Into the yielding night: and, ere The yet unbroken chains of their Short sundered being drew back each soul To fill and feel the rest of fate This side of death, alas, this whole Accursèd world, where lusts and hate Have tracked and slaughtered love, lay drear In dews of chill tears hardening sore To add to cruel days one more And not yet be consumed; while, near, Their own yet unattainable, Gleamed only fair the heaven where dwell Love's saved ones deathless, night and day Itself transfigured with the spell That took their first life's tears away. Ah, and the rest is strange enough To common earth-folk, whose cold faith Is coined out of some bitter lie Of their polluted lives; whose wraith Goes downward to the dung and dust They worshipped in the stead of love: But—Love of mine—if thou or I Should doubt love's miracle, whose trust Is in his heaven for which we die Dishonoured in our lives,—then, mad And hopeless were our hearts, and we In all thrice wretched, and this sad World-exile thrice a hell! —Now She Who came unto them on the morn That brought their fate, and, in the ear Of multitudes whose ready scorn Turned to amaze, said she was near Among a kin that held them dear, From time ere unseen hands had torn Their ways asunder,—to the dull And jeering folk she seemed a crazed Long widowed woman used to cull Strange herbs at night time: but there blazed At once, unshrouded, on the twain The beauty in her and the might Of a love-angel long in light; And gathered on no pallid plain By moonlit magic were the charms She gave them: for straight into arms Of tripled strength the lover took His love—to win her so or look His last upon the world that day. O sweet and swift was the first way: —Bearing her from the one dark place In all God's universe where still She was not his: winning her more At every step; mere earthly space And ruggedness between the chill Man's hand that severed and the thrill Of God's that should unite! Grass bore The blithe steps gratefully; and wings Of hurrying wind, outstripping, fanned And fretted many a mile of green That waved with gracious murmurings To the brink of the seeing; keen Delicious scent was in the land; And every little joy that sings Close to its parent clod, unseen In minute mystery, rang out That morn its perfect rapturous chime: And, far behind, the human shout Fell faint and fainter every time, Baffled and wavering about The mazes of the upward way. And then they entered on the fair And fearful solitudes that day And night made in the mountain,—air Immeasurable, and light and space, And burning breadth of heaven, and steep Interminable slopes that face The blue and lead up to the blue. It was the very dream that sleep Had oft beguiled them with, made true And mightier far; the green sheer side Of earth rose boundless, unbeheld Of any living thing beside Themselves: the equal infinite Of heaven uncomprehended held The other dazzling half of light, Endless and fathomless; and both Seemed worlds to them where they might choose To wander out their lives and lose Rich unrecorded days, in troth With some indulgent death that left The lips belovèd with the lips That loved, and, ending them, scarce reft More from them than, with honied theft, Some love-sleep steals of bliss, that nips An agonizing joy in twain. And here they knew that they were fain To cast away all hope and fear; And pass unnamed from men, and near To none affranchisement more blest Than that first licence the mere breast Of an untrodden earth and drear Desired solitude did hold To lure them to ignoble rest. Calm was the never ending wave Of wild mysterious wind, that rolled Through changeless ages there,—that brought Nor good nor evil thing and wrought No change: and peaceful, as a grave Without the memory of a man Or knowledge of a god, the dim Grey grass immeasurable ran, Receding ever, to some rim Where shone, all brandished in the blue, Its coarsely golden heads; and here It seemed indeed that God scarce knew The hoary age of Time or where Was ending or beginning. And it was wonderful, yea, past The loveliest bewildering Of dreams, all suddenly, at last, In such an endless fearless place— Where was no least remembering Of sweet or bitter—for the first Illimitable moment's space, To feel the loneliness of face With yearning face, and love with love, And passionate soul with soul that durst All depth and height of passion. Above Their infinite will that moment reigned No law, but such as the wild wills And endless energies of storms And seas, and all things unrestrained Rule themselves with for aye; and vast, As the most fatal force that thrills Through endless chaos and reforms The earth and heavens, was all desire Of their two spirits—now, at last, In irrepressible ways to blend, Fulfilling heaven or adding fire To hell—one spirit to the end. Wherefore, indeed, face tempted face With a long fatal look, that wore The haggard irresistible grace Of utmost yearning; and no more The eager passionate heart forbore The heart's temptation, for the sake Of any false faith in the earth Left bitterly; but sweetest lures That, perishably perfect, take Imperishable loves of birth That robs or peoples heaven, did tempt And take their souls. Lust, that endures While only the alluring hair Hath the world's sun in it, exempt From aught of the world's change; while, fair In the world's fickle thought, the snare Of lips and limbs and eyes doth hold The glitter of its fading gold,— Knoweth not wherefore they forsook The safe returning paths that day, And such remaining fate as lay Among mankind, and, with a look Mirroring the immensity Of blue above them, mutely took Unknown irrevocable doom Among all endless creatures, high As stars or lowly as the bloom Upon the humble earth: but love That gave an earth knew well what love Gave heaven; and either lover's soul Knew to God's judgment day, the whole Loved story of the other's soul. So they went upward, still, to learn The mystery of the mountain. Day On day, they ever found some way Higher and stranger, past return, Leading up through the solitude They sought. And, one by one, earth's rude Horrific semblances, that hold Mere changeless secrets of a love The world has grown unworthy of, Half fearless for the holy gold Within them, laid by many a veil,— Seeing, that, more and more, the might Of love eternal did enfold And change and beautify with light Those wanderers. And one day they knew There was another wanderer too In that fair mountain; for the pale World-angel Death did haunt it through; Many times, midmost of some waste Quite pathless; or on narrowest place Precipitous, had they even met With wondrous and mysterious trace Of him, that stayed the very haste Of their freed feet, and turned the thought Within them to a dream as yet Beyond their bearing: and they caught, Oft-times, some little sound of his, Coming unearthly as a sharp And rending cry up the abyss, Or taken for the sudden hiss Of a snake near them. But at night They heard him, when that mountain, wild With hollow ways, became a harp Whereon he poured the fearful might Of an immense strange music, full Of storms and thunders, sometimes mild And bringing the delicious lull Of an unearthly dream, but great, And hundred voiced and all his own For ever. Then they saw that lone And mighty one—that savage mate Of solitude; yea, once, afar, And turned from them, and making way Tremendous on the height where lay The snowy shroud of moon and star; Then once again; then many a time Descried they him, scarce nigh, in pose Of thinking thoughts that no man knows; Or fearful in his haste to climb Some distant craggy way of peak And precipice, hung between hell And heaven. At length, spite of the sun, Nigh every day they saw him well, Crouched sullen, or in hideous freak Out on the sunny ledges sheer And glittering. Scarce he seemed to shun The sight of them; though dark and lost And heedless seemed he if he crost Their path; but, now and then, would peer Intently at them from behind Some rugged hiding, with no mind To bring to pass on them his change In any bitter sort. And so, They were a distance great and strange Above the world: they knew no more The shadowy place of it, below The silver of the closing clouds That spread beneath them like a floor; Slowly too, had they felt that shrouds Of fearless sweet forgetfulness, Gathering all within, did hide And shut off from them, and make less And less the knowledge of their tried Hard being in the past. Their love Was growing with them as the light Made in the sun's clear central mine, That long hath burnt a way through shred Of vapoury veil; so they did move And live in it, and, in the bright Transfigurement thereof, did shine Wondrously each on each, and wed Their perfect emanating bliss In ways of an eternal kiss. I cannot find a subtle sound Of words, in which it can be said, How the great tides of glory roll, Over some unperceived last bound, Inward upon the open soul For ever. Softly, while each way And want and manner of the earth —Disused, relinquished,—fell away And ceasèd from them, did they change, Scarcely with dying or with birth— Into the endless element Begun within, the day there went The first love-lightning, swift and strange, Between them, in that lower land Where love's elect are a small band. Yea, even as now their feet had made Ever an upward way that led From the dull earth, from the cold shade, Ever toward some higher height, Where yet their spirits should be fed Upon unearthlier air and light, And yet more perfectly fulfil The high and deep law of their love,— Yea, even as now they went and still Found there was love and light above, And shining changes yet to teach Their souls, and loftier joys to reach— So, when at length, upon the last Chill summit of the earth they stood, And all the earthliness had passed Fairly away from them, a good And never-ending sight they had Of heaven and higher heaven; and, free, With winged feet that were bright and glad To walk upon the silver sea Of airy cloud and air, no stay They made, but upward a great way Went ever, loving ever, yea, And drawing nigh to Love. And now, Alas, that neither I nor thou Can know the full and perfect fate They have; nor where at length they are; Nor for what fairer thing they wait, If yet they have not come to be All things divinely.—But yon star, That doth not seem indeed so far, Hath all this lore; yea, and each free Undefiled flower in the grass Knows and sees plainly in the glass Of heaven: and we know not, alas! Yet shall their fate, whate'er it be, Come very soon on me and thee! Would I might go far over sea, My Love, or high above the air, And come to land or heaven with thee, Where no law is and none shall be Against beholding the most rare Strange beauty that thou hast for me. Alas, for, in this bitter land, Full many a written curse doth stand Against the kiss thy lips should bear; Against the sweet gift of thy hand; Against the knowing that thou art fair, And too fond loving of thy hair! CHAITIVEL; OR, THE LAY OF LOVE'S UNFORTUNATE. Fair yellow murderess, whose gilded head Gleaming with deaths; whose deadly body white, Writ o'er with secret records of the dead; Whose tranquil eyes, that hide the dead from sight Down in their tenderest depth and bluest bloom; Whose strange unnatural grace; whose prolonged youth— Are for my death now and the shameful doom Of all the man I might have been in truth— Your fell smile, sweetened still, lest I might shun Its lingering murder, with a kiss for lure, Is like the fascinating steel that one Most vengeful in his last revenge and sure The victim lies beneath him, passes slow, Again and oft again before his eyes And over all his frame, that he may know And suffer the whole death before he dies. Will you not slay me? Stab me; yea, somehow Deep in the heart: say some foul word to last And let me hate you as I love you now: Oh, would I might but see you turn and cast That false fair beauty that you e'en shall lose, And fall down there and writhe about my feet, The crooked loathly viper I shall bruise Through all eternity!— Nay; kiss me, Sweet! Ladies and lovers, may ye dwell In joy; yea, now and after me; And, for all I shall sing or tell, Hold me but one who loveth well, And singeth of mere joy to see His lady's golden loveliness,— Yea, joyeth, and may scarce repress The song he hath for every tress Her hand hath braided or set free— The rush of rapturous words that break Frail wings against his lips and take A songless death, for mere delight In that fresh miracle of white And perfect red and perfect gold Each new day brings him to behold Renewed and yet unchanged in her. Whence are the rosy seas that stir With richly glowing wave of thin Ethereal fire, alway within, Alway about her heart—all day Flooding the extreme flower of lip And finger-tip and bosom-tip,— As summer, flooding in such way Earth, air and heaven, will seem to stay Gathered up richly in the last And least of the last rose?—O whence Is all her wonder, never past, Nor ever dwelt with and possest Quite through, bewildering the sense With loving, looking and suspense Of loving;—shapeless shades and swift Transfigurement of heavens that drift Ever with glory giving place To glory on her form and face?— Yea, infinite of change and light And wide uncomprehended sight Seems every way his lady's grace,— As seemeth to the day and night Some infinite world of flowers, transformed By unseen wands of wind. And he, Beholding, loves; but may not see Or know whence aught of her may be: Only, beholding, he hath formed, Ah, many a song for very love Of her and wonder. But, above, —Yea, quite beyond the rapturous days He leads with her, he thinketh well Some heaven with fair untrodden ways Shall ever be for him to dwell Rejoicing in her, learning praise More passionate of her, winning whole Immortal knowledge of her soul. Ladies and lovers, will ye see How gold hair hath its perjury? And how the lip may twice or thrice Undo the soul; and how the heart May quite annul the heart's own price Given for many a goodly part Of heaven? How one love shall be fair, And whole and perfect in the rare Great likeness of an angel,—yea, And how another, golden-miened, With lovely seeming and sweet way, Shall come and be but as a fiend To tempt and drag the soul away— And all for ever? Listen well: This is a lay of heaven and hell: Listen, and think how it shall be With you in love's eternity. Some age ago, Love's splendid lures Through the enchanted world made fair Each woman's soft enamouring snare; And the contagion that endures Among men's hearts spread everywhere Love's ailing that love only cures; And, far as the unblemished fire Flooded down joyous from the sun Caused rapturous living and desire Unearthly in the earth, not one Of fair mankind was free to shun The sudden endless fate of flame Caught in the hazard of a look Crossing a kindled look. The same Frail human life it was that shook With the immortal burning soul Of love traversing it, consumed With bearing inwardly the whole Of some celestial joy, or sole —In fair midst of the world that bloomed Or withered—through the long sharp throe Of some inexplicable woe Reaching out to a shoreless sea Of sadness after death. The earth Was beautiful with flower and tree, And full of the delicious mirth And low soft endless jubilee Of bird and nameless creature free To feel the sun; and, where the grave Saddened and broke the last year's green, There most was this year's summer brave With glorious flower and fresh with keen New scent. And men and women, thrilled With their own passionate thoughts unseen, Went fair about the fair world, filled With wondrous joy or misery Killing them at the heart; beheld The sun, and looked upon the sky, And saw the flowers, and felt go by The summer; and were not changed, but held Their secret of eternity Within them. And the earth was glad, Whether the heart was blithe or sad. But Sarrazine, of whom I sing, Had shut her soul up from each thing That once with all her soul she knew Sweet in the earth, bright in the blue; And, joyless, in the midst between Fair blue of heaven and green earth's green, Lived now this lovely Sarrazine With passionate thinking and unknown Most secret flowering of her lone And infinite beauty. All amazed She was, and fearfully she gazed Into each dismal future year, The while it ceased not that a tear, Born of her thought right wearily, Found its way backward to the drear Dead ashes of some memory In a sweet fatal reckless past Love had made recklessly and cast Against her soul. She did not die, But dreamed and lived, and bade the gray Of grieving, more and more each day, Gather around and steal away Her hidden fairness, that was bloom More white and wondrous in that tomb Where the sun touched it not, and sight Should never worship, and delight Flower not of it day or night. The slow cloud found it sweet to rest Over each shadow-haunted tower Of her lone castle, and to remain Low brooding over that domain Of deep autumnal wood and plain And mirroring lake that she possest; The sun and summer owned no flower Down in the deep and wayward ways Ruined and lost about her bower, Whose desolation was the nest Of a strange plaintive bird with crest Of tarnished fiery feathers. Haze Of changeless morn and noon was blue Above the still blue of the lake, Where, year by year, some long dream grew More and more wonderful, and threw A stranger spell over wild brake And dripping mile of sallow sedge— Where the dark bittern and the crake Answered with lone unearthly cry, Or spectral, on the oozy edge, Some tall grey egret with wide eye Stood slumbering. Not a troubled thought Of toiling in the world, or deeds Of living men, was ever brought To break such magic as dreams wrought In that dim region; but the reeds, And redolent snakelike flowers, and weeds Trailed in the wave, and songless bird, With many a shadow thinly seen And many a strange unseen thing heard To wander up and down between The desolate sedges with drear sound— All were become unearthly, bound In the enchanting solitude Of some vast supernatural mood Of sadness. All had learned the heart Of Sarrazine; and every sore Bewailing thought of hers was part Of burdens that the silent things Of wave and fen and feather bore, On languid leaves and drooping wings, In the blue stillness more and more The haunt of cloud and dream. And for his sake—who quite possest, In short blind life upon the earth, The whole irrevocable gift Of her sweet body's passionate worth— Whose soul was ever strong and swift To seek her shaken soul and wrest Some irremediable word Out of its troubled speech to drift Onward eternal and be heard Among the destinies,—for him, She now had given up to grief, To let grief ruin it and dim And waste it as worms do a leaf, The rich continual flowering Of each white unregarded limb, Yea, and the whole of that rich thing, Her woman's loveliness, that love Would perfect secretly and bring To many a marble grace above His wont. O how grief slew each day With deadliest remembering Of some first day the cruel past Held golden with joy torn away For ever! Snake-like, how he cast His sickly and bewildering coil About her life, holding his prey, Her heart, with fierce fang of regret, And making poisoned thought to spoil Her desolate fairness with lone fret! Now she would weary out the days, Joylessly looking on the white Slim wonder that she was, whose praise Henceforth must be omitted quite Out of men's praising mouths; whose sight Should ne'er strike sudden with amaze One other heart fain to have crost That solitude, where she must be Evermore as a flower lost Or nameless unto men. To see The wild white lilies, passionless And lonely, wasted in the rank Green shadowy shallows of the bank, Was to see many a loveliness— No more rejected and left out, As a thing none cared to possess Of love and time—than, past all doubt, Her joyless form and face were now Till death. Was the world whole without One need of her, one thought of how Love prospered making her—one look At the short perfect miracle His passionate hands wrought when they took The rare sweet elements, the fine And delicate fires, and wove the spell Of her rich being? Did days yet shine, And men love boundlessly and well In the fair world, beyond that cell Of grey thoughts shutting out the sun Her life seemed brought to? yea, since none Set living heart upon her more, And all she was and all she bore, Of rare and wonderful lay known To the worms only left alone With faded secrets in the core Of dead men's hearts? Time was so bare, —Her heart at solitary feast Of sorrow sitting unreleast For ever, wasting slow the hair Of gold, the plenteous form of white Unconquerable flower, through night And day, that emptied year and year Of sullied summers, drawing near To death scarce more a winter;—yea, And one last chosen tomb seemed, day And night, so little comforted With summer given or true tear shed— There might have been—her heart now said Sometimes all softly—even for him, That earlier lover, lightly slain Without the touch of her for dim Delicious dreaming after vain, Void life, the guiltless recompense Of more love than he sought to save His soul; yea, though he had gone hence, Telling the worms they should but have Hair's gold that once had been his bed, And dust that love for once had wed To his glad dust, when death made her Some next year's spoil! O who would stir In sleep down there, and think he missed Aught of the faultless mouth that kissed His life all through? For, verily, —He who had all—was not his day, E'en to death softened endlessly With love, filled to the full and more With sweet of hers? And, where he lay, Was not the grave o'erbrimmed with store Of perfect memories and rich ore Of a life rich in love? And, now, It seemed all bitter to avow That one most gracious should have gone Uncheered to death, who had lived on Right rapturously, if once his brow Had felt her lips; if once his hand Had revelled on her, and his heart Filled itself with one lovely part Of loveliness, the rotting sand Of time alone should use with kiss Joyless for ever. Would not this— To weigh the lost wealth of her hair Once in his hand, as one might poise Some weight of gold—have seemed right fair To him, amid the few sad joys He thought it well to die for? Yea, And now the whole sweet, that he lay Evermore thirsting for, was there At waste for ever, out of care Of any; and no man came back To call it his. And, since to her No man returned; since no more lack Of her gave any strength to stir The very grave-stone and come back; And he whose soul's least word of love Seemed a love-fetter strong enough To bind eternity to whole Eternity,—since now his soul Having content of her, or quite Forgetting, left her, as a thing Not owned, and never jealous sting, Caused him to care now, day or night, What chance might happen to the white Unblemished beauty or the heart His empire:—ah, as houseless wraiths And unhoused creeping beasts would glide Back to a house the day he died Who cast them forth,—so, from each part Of her annulled past, full of faiths Abjured and fruitless loves and loss, There came back to her heart the host Of memories comfortless; the ghost Of every lover now might cross Its threshold when he would, to scare And grieve her with his tears, or bare The great wound in his heart, or make Long threat of unknown things for sake Of some forgotten heedless word. It seemed now as a sad thing heard But yesterday, how, bearing still Fair vow of hers, wherefrom the will Of other love had wrenched her, yea, Relying ever on each fair Uncancelled word, and, night and day, Bound, with her gift of golden hair, To hold hers only heart and hand, For ever,—one in Paynim land Died loving her. The intense flower Of waving strange-leaved trees that sang His dirge with voices wild and soft, Wafted her perfume that had power To shake her heart; warm air, that rang With ends of unknown singing, oft Broke in upon her, as though space Of cold climes and cold seas between Were dwindling, and she should have seen That fair unconsecrated place, Golden in sunlight, green in shade Of many a palm and mighty blade Of monstrous herb. Yea, these were three Whose lives and deaths were hers; and she Had only given good to one; And all were with her now, to share And haunt her thoughts quite to the bare Lone end of living. There was none Among sweet women whose ripe heart, Full of the perfect precious part Of many a love, was a deep tomb Where fair dead lay in goodly gloom More royally than these, whose fate Was filled and ended in her, lay In her proud heart, disconsolate And lonely, turning from the day Into its own rich grieving gray. But in the separate place that death Had found for him, to rest from life, To dream upon it, or to wait, Each of her lovers held the breath Of his strong dauntless spirit rife With memories; or content with late Fair kisses on his mouth; or sure Of heaven because of some sweet lure Of looks or pledge or perfect vow She made him,—doubting her not his For ever in fair destinies. He who ne'er felt upon his brow The perfect blessing of her kiss, Stayed his long thirst with thinking how Some early and far-reaching smile, That looked on many a distant mile Of golden promise, seemed to bind His love to follow her and find Dim outskirts of her life to cling With solace in; and, where the chill And changeless dark spread covering His patient soul, he thought it still Her shadow on him; and a thrill That was not joyless turned the sting Of death. And he who, in the fair Rich Paynim place, with the ripe glare Of foreign summers gilding palm And poisonous fruit about him, calm And mighty, rusted in red steel— Not merely barren did he feel Death's prison and the silent gloom Around him; but, within, the tomb Was opulent with glimmering gold; For the slim tress that once was hid Upon his heart, was grown to fold On fold that many times had rolled About him; and he lay amid The splendours of it, and thought well That he should have her soul for hell Or heaven. But he who had all sweet Latest and longest of her,—day And night and many a year he lay, Enthralled, past knowing cold or heat Or hearing thunder or the feet Of armies, in a long deep dream Of her sweet body, full of joy And magical amaze and gleam Of endless excellence: there nought Might reach his spirit or destroy Its passionate raptures of long thought, —Save only if, beneath God's sky, One other creature should draw nigh To touching her whom his soul bought. Tranquil, and holding it enow Each of them had his hope or bliss Or memory of her; and with this He lay alone there,—as I trow, Thinking that she was only his. —O men and women, Love is king Upon the earth; summer and spring Will serve him in the year to come With all new rapture, when the blast Of many a long-drawn autumn day, Made golden with fair thought and dumb Remembering of the perfect past, Shall have swept utterly away The dry dead leaves of summer and spring That spent themselves with worshipping His latest godhead perfectly: His realms are all the lands that lie Beneath yon distant unknown sky— Where only freed souls go unseen To different dooms: his are the green Of grass, the blue of seas, the red Of passionate roses,—each frail life Of rose and bird and slight thing rife With sunlight is but sweetly led By him to its sweet life and death. But, more than all, while ye have breath And rosy relic of the rose Born with you—men and women, lo, Your rich eternal hearts that grow Like widening flowers that cannot close Their leaves—are Love's, to turn and use, And work upon as he may choose. Do ye not feel how love pursues Your full hearts ever with his new Inconstant summer—to convert And steal them from the thing they knew Their own,—to cause them to desert Their piteous memories and the few Fond faiths of perfect years? Alas, He careth not how he may hurt The dead, or trouble them that wait In heaven, so he may bring to pass Ever some new thing passionate And sweet upon the earth: his sun Hath need of you; and, if he takes Last year's spoiled roses and remakes Red summer with them, shall he shun To steal your soft hearts every one, O men and women, to enrich His fair new transitory reign? Are ye mere flowers to love again With each fresh summer, knowing not which Hath had the ripest of your bloom?— Nay, but, for you, there is a doom For ever making in the fair Unalterable world above The blue, unknown to your new love, Irrevocable in your own Sweet word:—O women, have a care What if two come to claim your hair Of God?—what if two shall have thrown Their strong arms round your body, quite Belonging with an equal right To each for ever? Would the place, That bore so long the lovely grace And wayward grief of Sarrazine, Had never lost the tender spell Of the half death that seemed to dwell Out of time there on what was green Of leaf and what was grey, on bird And sleepless wraith;—would none had stirr'd The gloomy magic making there Some lone eternity to scare Untoward striving fates and save Her soul and body in one grave Of safe sleep unresponsive. Yea, For, at the last, I cannot say What thing fell on her, when my lay Hath told you of this Chaitivel, Whom his fate made to love her well And seek her, knowing nought of those That held her on the other side Of death. May this man's woe abide With God for ever, among woes Some heaven of his—some mystic kiss Of Mary sweet shall turn to bliss! It may be, still, for many a year Sarrazine counted tear on tear To soften death unto the dead; And many a thing, that they might hear Sometimes all faintly in the bed Of earth and leaves about them, said —To touch them, if she might, and set Some late desire of her at fret Within them;—and, if, day or night, The grave had let them, fair and white, And far more wondrous as she was Than in their memory, she would quite Have hailed that one who should have earned To come to her in any pause Of death, with words that long had burned Her breast, and love that had long turned To fair earth near their hearts. But now, The graves grew winterly, and how It fared with them in that long sleep She knew not: and they lay and dreamed, Each one his dream, that he should keep And hold her his for evermore. Then Love, who rules the bright world, deemed That, all too well indeed, she bore Such sorrow for the dead who seemed No longer worth one's caring for; And, so, I ween, he sent one day This Chaitivel—who was a man Most goodly, full of all the gay And thrilling summer-time that ran Once more with rapture through the earth. Alas, for her who gave him birth, And put indeed, upon his face And form, somewhat of her own grace To make men love him, and her smile Like magic in his mouth! No guile Was in her; and she saw him fair And stayed with him, maybe a while, For the mere joy to see his hair Grown lovely with youth's golden crown, And to behold his perfect bloom, As of a flower that she had sown: And, having loved indeed and known His heart, she left him to the doom Another woman's love should make:— Alas, for her down in the tomb! Was there no little deadly snake Curled on the threshold, for her sake, To save him with its fiery fang? Nay, but he entered; and this sad Too lovely Sarrazine, all clad In clinging robes, with voice that sang The piteous music of lone thought Most luringly, is unto him, As 'twere some fatal serpent, slim And gracious that hath softly caught His soul twining about it close, Sinking it into ways of woes Past saving. But his coming brought The new strange miracle of love Upon her; and her heart, estranged From all that once had seemed enough, Sprang sudden at him as a bird Breaking a snare, or as a free Blithe butterfly some second birth Lifts in the air, no more to be The joyless worm it was on earth. And, lo—once, when the night was sore, And the world, for a faint space, bore The bitter nearness of its dead Unwontedly, and every pore Of the chill graves seemed free to shed The white and ghastly dews long bred In lone laborious agonies Of those on whom the death-sleep lies Uneasily,—she said or sang, Mourning one last while, words that rang With their full farewell in the ear Of those her listening lovers,—clear With poignant doom of anguish, straight Awakening them to fight with fate For ever. Wheresoe'er ye be, Forgetting or remembering me, She sang,—I bid you now farewell: Surely, I think, you shall not tell Hard things of me in heaven or hell: I pray God, that the grave be sweet About you,—yea, and, if ye keep Some sort of love of me through sleep,— May the worms cease not to repeat My sweet words lest ye wake and weep: Only, if before God we meet, I pray you, lovers, that no more Ye tell me of the things I swore; I loved you: may all death be sweet, And peace be with you evermore. O lover, who had all delight In winning me,—'tis many a night, Since, through the sweet hours lovingly, I lay by you and you by me; And now, perchance, if you should see My flowerless beauty, loved by you, Wasted to white and kissed all through With sorrow,—scarcely might I seem Your love of lost days or your dream Down there in charmed sleep; and, to-day, Why need I take your dream away? —Sleep on; and think of me, I say, Whatever sweet thing lets you lie Content with death; I have made rich Your grave indeed with tear and sigh; And, many a night hath been, through which I prayed to God that I might die And go down softly to you. Dear, I do believe you would not hear; You would not know or feel me near; And, though I kissed you, till you saw My wan face, I should never draw One warm kiss from your lips, or thaw The hard ice at your heart! What song Of mine hath ever reached you? Long Mad nights I lay awake, and wrought My sorrowing heart to such a plaint Of lone imploring words, I thought Some of them surely must have brought Your soul quite to me, roused with faint Most piteous murmurings that made way Through earth and leaves to where you lay. And, if indeed death had not set Some cold and very mighty spell Upon you, making you forget My face, yea, and your love, to dwell With some unearthly dream, or rest Dreamless and joyless in his breast For ever,—O you had not failed To steal up somehow, wearying night, Death, dreams, and mystic ways of sight And sound, till one fair path availed To make you known to me. And now, It seems we both who made the vow Of love have fallen on either side Somewhat away; and I, who chide Thee never for it, hold, maybe, At length the greater memory. 'Tis as though both of us had died I think; and that lone grave of thine Is scarce a harder place to pine And gnaw the inmost heart and shed Unsolaced tears in, than this bed, Lonely and waste and white, where grief Hath held me buried, years wrought sore With sorrowing. No fair hope made brief The agony it was, no more To see one loved face bring relief Of love: the hollow darkness bore No dream to comfort; and the sight Of the yet fair unruined white Of my forlorn lost beauty pained My spirit, showing me but chained To so much more of death. Farewell: Memory or sleep shall hold their spell Unchanged upon you, till the name Or thought of Sarrazine shall dwell No more with you; and though, at last, She winneth any sweet the past Knew nothing of, she will not cast The tenderness of many a day Quickly and utterly away: And, though quite other she became, Surely the grave will feel the same. But he who, living, had possest Her peerless body—who, till then, Rapt in sweet thought, had never known How death grew chill and cold earth prest And walled him in, nor felt the stone Lie heavy between him and men,— But he who, giving his soul's best Of heaven and God's eternal good, Had won that woman to be his And change not: in mere solitude Of death he woke, without a kiss, And knew that fate was false;—the hiss Of a fell serpent seemed to bring The words that woke him to his ear, Bitter with endless echoing, And one long agony stretched clear Out to his soul's eternity. Then, in the hollow of the tomb, Where his speech thundered into doom, He answered her: Woman, said he, Why have you been so false with me? Was it the waste thought of a day I gave to you?—was it to win A wanton hour, I cast away My untried heavens and slew straightway My greater unknown self within? Was it to shrivel, with the sin Of mere rich revelling to dull My fallen soul once beautiful Because of love, sharing the hell Of harlots, that I chose to sell Usurious fate so much of vast, Yea boundless, that lay known between Me and God only? So, at last, Not half way into doom, I find This fails me,—this that should have been All heaven, this love that was to blind So richly, I should ne'er have seen The depth I dwelt in nor the height I forfeited; now, all behind, At once I see as many kings As golden seeming days, with light And lustre fading on them; bright Imperial crowns and goodly things Fall from them hastily; they sit Dishonoured spectres of me, bare In the bare past, abhorring it. If I could go back and repair One hour, one moment, to make fair Eternity,—O I should seem Not quite denuded of some dream To keep my soul unshamed before The fiends and angels: but, indeed, I am too distant from that shore Of life already; and no seed Is left for sowing any more. Henceforth, a weed among much weed Of foundered love and life, my soul Shall drift upon dark waves and waste Upon the ceaseless seas that roll Through the lone Infinite. Ah, haste To live thy false life through, that I May have that wrecked thing I did buy —A body for a soul!—for mine I think you shall be, since I hold A vow for every hair of gold, And destinies and all divine Unalterable things of old Witnessed your pale frail body bound To me immutably.—Ah, white And worthless blossom, for delight Of the lips only: Ah, the round Quite faultless fashioning of slim And sinuous side and shapely limb: Ah, the delirious abyss Of the mouth fainting in a kiss:— Ah, all this, yea, though merely this,— Can make a goodly hell for him Who loses heaven. And I grow sick Of waiting since I am no more Than one to kiss your bosom sore For ever. Wherefore now the thick Polluted darkness? Wherefore gloom And lonely wakings in the tomb? Sin all, and, as you are, come quick And share my sin down here. How long Have I endured to dream among The worms in faithful wretchedness— Sure you would come and lie along Beside me and be sweet no less Than I believed you? You would bless Some fond way for it all, and set Your mouth upon my mouth and let The dreamed-of heaven begin: and, quite So noble was I with my faith,— But for these sad words, I felt bite The ground through to me—O I might Have ceased not trusting the sweet wraith Of word and kiss and memory, Of what I left you, endlessly! Here, in my place among the things That change not, I myself, in all, A changeless spirit past recall, With life's supreme rememberings Unshaken in me,—here I feel And shudder at your shameful word. O woman, think you no fates heard, When, passionately, beyond repeal, You bade them know you mine and seal Your life and death so? See the blue— The sight you have up there with you Most near to heaven,—and, if you can, Believe there is a God to let You change the word you would forget, And quite revoke the doom a man Hath lived and died in! Change; and yet You cannot change, but earth and sky And death will keep you mine: and I— Do not I live for ever? And it befell, another day, When earth, well ravished of the gay Turbulent summer, fell to swoon Under the perfume of the noon,— That Sarrazine, now rich at heart With love's fond thinking, felt a part Of tender pity that must go And find the grave out there beyond So many a sea, where, lone and low, Beneath the palms, that Pharamond Lay buried, with his love of her, And bound as though he might not stir, In meshes of soft growing gold. And him, believing death must hold So rigorously his heart and hands That no fair singing in those lands Had ever soothed him,—now she named; And, murmuring softly of him, framed Her last thought of him in a song; Singing it idly to the birds, And finding as she went along Mere wanton music in the words: Hath any loved you well, down there, Summer or winter through? Down there, have you found any fair Laid in the grave with you? Is death's long kiss a richer kiss Than mine was wont to be— Or have you gone to some far bliss And quite forgotten me? What soft enamouring of sleep Hath you in some soft way? What charmed death holdeth you with deep Strange lure by night and day? —A little space below the grass, Out of the sun and shade; But worlds away from me, alas, Down there where you are laid? My bright hair's waved and wasted gold, What is it now to thee— Whether the rose-red life I hold Or white death holdeth me? Down there you love the grave's own green, And evermore you rave Of some sweet seraph you have seen Or dreamt of in the grave. There you shall lie as you have lain, Though in the world above, Another live your life again, Loving again your love: Is it not sweet beneath the palm? Is not the warm day rife With some long mystic golden calm Better than love and life? The broad quaint odorous leaves like hands Weaving the fair day through, Weave sleep no burnished bird withstands, While death weaves sleep for you; And many a strange rich breathing sound Ravishes morn and noon: And in that place you must have found Death a delicious swoon. Hold me no longer for a word I used to say or sing: Ah, long ago you must have heard So many a sweeter thing: For rich earth must have reached your heart And turned the faith to flowers; And warm wind stolen, part by part, Your soul through faithless hours. And many a soft seed must have won Soil of some yielding thought, To bring a bloom up to the sun That else had ne'er been brought; And, doubtless, many a passionate hue Hath made that place more fair, Making some passionate part of you Faithless to me down there. But Pharamond heard that sweet sound, As the one strange thing waited for Through death; and, waking at the sore Inconstant words, his hands unwound The shining chain and tress that bound His limbs; and, in the glorious gloom Of that unconsecrated tomb, He rose up, dumb and mighty,—pale And terrible in blood-stained mail, And the gold on him as a belt,— He rose up,—a great soul that felt Death ended ere a word from God: And, going forth, he once more trod The waste ways of the human earth; And, terrible, and giving birth To wide dismay, he crossed all lands, Mountains and forests, and the sands Of deserts, and the pathless seas, And where suns burnt or snows did freeze The summer,—going back to take Her soul for vows she could not break. And yet again, the last rich eve —Ere, for this Chaitivel, whom woe Lay waiting for, she thought to leave The past for ever, yea, and go. Through earths and heavens that ne'er should know Other than her new love of her,— Fearing not that the dead should stir Nor fate remember,—as they stayed, Having used up their words and sighed To soften hours that yet delayed Their souls from mingling to divide No more for ever,—Sarrazine, Making her voice sad as might be Some bird's last singing in the tree It nested in, said: As I lean This way upon your bosom, love, Dreaming how it shall be above, —Yea, when we go from star to star, Finding innumerable ways To heaven,—a little thought flies far Behind me, to the piteous days Of one whom no soft memory stays, Maybe, from cursing me down there To death—who might have made life fair And death less bitter, with one care; One fond angelic word: O you, Whose love quite governs me and finds No will in me but your will binds And turns it all to serving you— You might have hated, if you knew How I was sterner than the death That gave him ease of the last breath, Watching him hollow out his grave In his deep boyish love of me! I had a thousand ways to save And strengthen him and make him flee; Nay, but I rather chose to see His passionate face from day to day Consuming near me, knowing well The different thoughts that made their prey His heart, having a word to say —A word unsaid yet!—ah, what spell Of peace should I delight to weave Over his grave there! I would take The very waste the autumns leave Upon it, thinking, for his sake Who lies there, no one stays to grieve, And I would change it into flowers Forced up and fostered in my heart, So I might soften the least part Of death, and make him quite forgive And never hate me for the hours That made death sweeter than to live. Ah, love, but, now, I feel, as though I may forget all this, and say It was another woman, yea, And not this Sarrazine; for, so Your love hath changed me, I may throw The past into a grave, and shrink From ever looking o'er the brink To see the dead in it and see A mouldering form of one like me. And he who never had a joy In life because of her,—he heard Quite plainly; and she did destroy His slender hope with every word. And, in the silence, his soul prayed That she might never take away The little joy it was to stay Not far off in the place she made Her heaven, to steal there unbetrayed, And only see her from some shade. But that night, ere they bade farewell, A fear of unknown sadness fell Between them; and her lover went To wait for joy, with such a heart As if an omen had been sent Sorrow would come to take joy's part. And when he sought her the next morn, Lo, there was one who sat forlorn In the room with her,—a mute, pale, Uncertain semblance of a man Dreary and wasted past the span Of mortal sorrow; with a frail Still passionate look he haunted her, As though his pain changed with each stir Her hand or body made;—and, lo, When, fearful, with a voice that burned His heart, he asked concerning him, And why he came to her,—she turned And trembled, looking to and fro, And said, indeed, it was not so; Only a chill mist seemed to dim Her sight; but surely none was there Beside himself and her. Then, straight That other answered him from where He stood: a voice lent by mere fate It seemed to be, and, thin as air, The void form seemed to vacillate, As though sound shook it through and through: —O lover, loved of her whom I Must love unloved for ever,—you Have nought to hate me for; e'en death Found little he might purify, When he divided the last sigh I gave her with an earthly breath; And now I have long learnt to take Content in ways that could not break Your peace or hers: none hindereth My soul from loving of her still: I pray God keep her from the chill Of seeing me; and only this— Which he hath granted for my bliss Shall all suffice me—to traverse Quite after her his universe And dwell in the enchanted place Her shadow filleth with her grace: Do thou not grudge me this I pray; And this she cannot take away. The phantom flickered as a flame Blown blue and rent about by wind; It seemed that every word became A second agony like death Racking a soul caught and confined In the strained film of some last breath; But, when the utterance ceased, the same— A cheerless wraith of form and face Shrinking into the room's far place Of shade—that semblance did abide Before the living man who held That living woman for his bride: And still when, stricken with amaze, He said: that other hath his gaze Upon thee and but now he held The speech thou must have heard, she grew As one whom many deaths pursue, Pale and affrighted, but averred She nothing saw neither had heard At all one speaking. And, behold, As they sat speechless through the day The spirit of the boy did stay Saddening them both and making cold Their hearts; he stirred not from the gloom Of the far corner of the room, Crouched like a phantom in a tomb. But a more fearful thing befell Ere night; and they have done full well To call this man the Chaitivel— The wretched one. For when, at eve, He went to her, and did believe God and her love for evermore Had power to make her his,—before He could have taken her or laid A trembling hand on her,—there past One between her and him. A blast Brought him in fearfully and made Unearthly winter chill the place; A torn grave garment seemed the last Earth-relic on him; form and face Were mysteries where no man could trace A part of former man,—within, Without, he was become what sin His soul invented; for, intense, He bore the hell of it. And this Was he who thought to buy the bliss Of holding one frail woman his For ever, yea, at the expense And loss of half his soul. Mere flame His thought seemed as he stood between, Finding a voice that might have been A man's: and then, in God's great name, He said:—Touch not her body, thou! Mine only hath it been; and now I come and hold her for her vow Mine only! Then he took her, fair And deathly, fainting in the clutch Of his grim darkness, with her hair Sweeping the ground, and all her bare Delicious beauty free from touch Borne desolately. Her lover there Could find no way to strive at all With that appalling shape of dim Illimitable darkness:—him No sword reached; but the blow did fall On Sarrazine: then, with a yell Unearthly, which no tongue could tell The horror of, that spectre fled Bearing the body of her dead, Dragging it inward to his hell For ever. But her soul did stay: Amazed with knowledge, and aghast To see, that moment and too late, The real eternities and vast Terrific truths of love and fate. The Wretched one sank down, and lay Knowing and suffering no more, As though he struck some dark closed door At the blank end of being and ceased Against the darkness.—Who can say If one may die so, rent away From life and after-life, and eased At once from destiny? How long He felt not: but he felt again The irremediable pain Recall him; and he woke among Dread repetitions of the plain And reeking horror: then his sight Met all things uttering the vast Relentless record: then, at last, Beheld her soul remaining white And whole and beautiful, no blight Or ruin cleaving on it. Free Of the torn frame now would she be, And all acquitted! And the drear And clanging night subsided near And far; and holy stillness grew. There, after all, remained they two Together: death's mere subtle change Dividing. And a new voice—strange, Ineffable in the night,—it seemed One in a distant star were heard Singing celestially,—brought word Revealing more than he had dreamed Of love about him: for the speech Of her rapt spirit gazing straight Into the veilless face of fate Was heard there; seeming to beseech Unyielding destinies and strive With angels. Only, visible there, In the clear wonder death did give The face of her unfading soul, She seemed an angel, thrice more fair Than she had seemed a woman. Yea; But now, for many a league away, Where he was wandering by day And night, through many a land beyond The seas and deserts,—Pharamond Beheld her in that hour: and, whole Immeasurable miles between, Across the dark, her soul had seen And trembled at him. Strong and loud And dreadful were his feet that trod Thundering on mountain or on cloud— Traversing earth and sea and air— With vehement will defying God To take her; for the golden hair Gleamed like a flaunted robe of flame Through earth and hell and heaven. He came With no help of the wind or storm, Or miracle by sea or land, Or deathly terror: in the form Of one most mighty, with the brand Of blood upon stained steel he bore Till doom, and blood upon his hand, And burning badge of one who swore To bear his love for evermore, He came on through the night. And hate A long way off did emanate And fly before him, making felt The coming of a fiend. And, lo, Vengeful, a great way off, he dealt Defiance with his voice. I know This only: that, as one might go Against one's death, the Chaitivel Went against Pharamond that night And met him; and the two did fight Out on the moor. And some can tell How, while they fought and neither fell, The fiend did mock the man and said: How long wilt thou contend with me, A day, a year, a century?— That thou art come to me arrayed In this frail garb of flesh and blood, And with these arms, as man to strive For some dull perishable good With man; or, thinkest thou to drive Back to the grave this soul of mine That brake the grave asunder? Yea, Look on my soul and think if thine May fight for an eternal thing With me eternal? And they say That, wrestling with the fiend, the man Replied: O Pharamond, I can; And we must go on combating, My soul and thy soul to the end! Then Pharamond's red sword did rend The swart air; and they saw him smite The man; and, ere the man was dead, Once more a great voice shook the night Saying: Come up and let us fight Unto the end, as thou hast said; And, peradventure, thou or I May vanquish some day in the sky; Or after ages have been spent, Fighting through every element; Or in the place where shadows dwell; In thy far heaven or my far hell; Or never; till some final gloom Shall end all things and God entomb Eternity!— And so they two fight on till doom. THE LAY OF ELIDUC. Combien que j'aie demouré Hors de ma douce contrée Et maint grant travail enduré En terre maleurée, Pour ce n'ai-je pas oublié Le dous mal qui si m'agrée, Dont jà n'en quier avoir santé S'en France ne m'est trouvée! Guillaume de Ferrières. I went to her who loveth me no more, And prayed her bear with me, if so she might, For I had found day after day too sore, And tears that would not cease night after night; And so I prayed her, weeping, that she bore To let me be with her a little; yea, To soothe myself a little with her sight Who loved me once, ah many a night and day. Then she who loveth me no more, maybe, She pitied somewhat: and I took a chain To bind myself to her and her to me; Yea, so that I might call her mine again: Lo, she forbade me not; but I and she Fettered her fair limbs and her neck more fair, Chained the fair wasted white of love's domain And put gold fetters on her golden hair. O the vain joy it is to see her lie Beside me once again; beyond release, Her hair, her hand, her body, till she die, All mine for me to do with as I please! —For after all I find no chain whereby To chain her heart to love me as before; Nor fetter for her lips, to make them cease From saying still she loveth me no more. Hard is the banishment from thee, Fair France! And, like a minstrelsy, The very naming of thy lands Rouseth the heart, and eke the hands Of any son indeed of thine, In any land of the sunshine Where his feet tarry or are held; For, but to think of thee, is spelled With all his joy or all his woe, As he shall come again, or no, To die thy rose gardens among, Thou land of roses and of song! This Lay is of Sir Eliduc And all his warfare, and the luck He had of love; bitter and sweet: Ladies, it is a thing full meet For minstrelsy; whereof indeed Fair singers have well taken heed In times before; but, first of all, In many a stead and castle-hall, In Brittany it was a lay, And such as all could sing or say. He was in honour of his king; And rich, and crowned with every thing, That, through the hardest years of war A knight may yearn and battle for, To be his guerdon and his pride: Yea, for at length, right far and wide, He was the most beloved of knights For valorous deeds, restoring rights To all oppressed, both mean and fair; And him all voices did declare The very saviour of his land And king from the strong growing hand Of bitter enemies, whose might Had brought to many an evil plight The shrinking borders of the realm, —Whom Eliduc did overwhelm With such a swift and perfect stroke In all their quarters, that he broke Their utter strength, and put in fear All other foes that might be near. And now, for many a great emprise; And, because, also, he was wise As any elder, and his word In every council was most heard, His name was grown the highest name Of theirs who in the king's hall came; And through the whole land he was known Next to the king; and, for his own, He had a palace like the king's, Royal and served with sumptuous things. Yet, for the envying of some, To see how great he was become In places where they once had part But now scarce stood with any art, —For this sad cause, or else for none, Since man more noble than this one Was ne'er in any place at all— Sir Eliduc came to his fall. Even he saw how, leaguered round With false tongues and the feigning sound Of courtiers, who made constant wile To work him ill with all their smile, The king's face fell indeed from him, And the king's smile at last was dim And his trust fencèd round with doubt: Then from the king's house he went out, Saying a proud word to them all, To wit, they should have need, and call Some fair way on him, ere again He should be there in that king's reign. But, surely, in the court that day, There was full many a one to say That this should never have been so— To let that goodliest of them go, And with so little thank at last For all his serving in time past; Yea, for he held their hearts long while, He had so fair and free a smile; Half soft, yet sharp and grey like steel His eyes were; and from head to heel Shaped fair he was; and, or with sword Or gentler wielding of fair word, Could win his will in everything Through field or court, with queen or king; Yet was there no man certainly Knew aught of him but loyalty. But swift was he to ride that day Back to his lands and castle grey, Vast lands of meadows fair and green, Over whose last swell there was seen The blue sea,—castle grey, with moat, And walls that many an axe had smote, Upon a hill set, strong and high With thronging towers against the sky. There came his people all to seek His face; but when they heard him speak With changed voice, and beheld his brow Where heavy thoughts like clouds were now, —O they were silent; and, made sad, Spoke not of tithe or harvest glad, Nor of their fortunes bad or good; But all with downcast look they stood, Thinking of him their fair good lord, Whose praise in each man's heart was stored. Then he more saddened them with speech, Yea, deeply in the heart of each; For now he bade them, till some while, Farewell, and spoke of hard exile; For wrath was in him, and his pride Let him not any more abide In any realm of that his king Unthankful; but he chose to bring The glory he was wont to bear And service of his sword somewhere To nobler patron over seas, Where valour of a knight could please And any fair thing was to do; Yea, so he bade them all adieu. And on that very day, at noon, To his dear wife he came full soon, These bitter wrongs of his to tell, And this last heavier thing as well. He found her fair indeed that day, Where she was sitting, robed and gay, In lonesome coloured chamber high Over the blue sea; there were nigh Her jewelled lute with golden strings, And many fair wrought golden things, And bright quaint tapestries did lie On floor and wall, of various dye, Wrought out in painted histories Of fair women in every guise; And, while she sat in listless mood Sweetening that fair solitude, She read an open book of rhyme, Or heeded most the gay noontime Out on the sunny coloured bar Shedding in showers many a star Or like bright scales of glittering gold Wondrous and lovely to behold. All there was fit to serve her heart With pastime; while the greater part Her thoughts were tuned in sad accord, Mourning for him their distant lord. And now full red it made her cheek To hold him there and hear him speak, And have so soon of his return All sweet for which her heart could yearn. Ah, quick return that brought, alas, A word whose grief was long to pass! Ah, sweet—the hardest bought of all Her heart's rare sweet! Soon hearing all The evil tale of change and fate —That now she should indeed but wait, Might be long years, with no fair sight Of him or coming of delight, —Her hope all unassured and long, Uncertain striving mid a throng Of dismal fears and thought of foes Innumerable, and distant woes Already being wrought perhaps, —Forefeeling through the doubtful lapse The bitterness of many days,— She fell a-swooned; and, in all ways Of sorrow, passed from thought to thought, Despairing of all good; nor sought Too much to turn him from the will To do that bitter thing; for still She knew he loved her, and not vain Could be his deed, while he had pain As much as hers at heart for it. So all that eve they twain did sit Together, losing not a space; Each gazing on the other's face, To fill each other's heart right well With treasure of its love, a spell Against long parting and all crime Of falseness through the bitter time. Full many a vow she had of him That evening in the twilight dim, That, in what lands or with what men His fate were, all his joy, as then, Should be in holding her most fair And thought of soon returning there. Natheless, upon the morrow morn There was a blowing of the horn All round about that castle grey; Not later than the first of day That came up from the hills behind All cheerless; while the chill new wind Fretted between the sea and shore, And pale lights changing more and more The dim land and the grey cold sea Gleamed on fair warriors who should be Embarked in that day's enterprise; And all men were not slow to rise And get them forth to see the start, Grieving or envying at heart. So Eliduc, with warriors ten, His most beloved, well-chosen men And tried, his friends in many a fight, Stood by the ship in the pale light; And ere the halo from the day Was fallen, or the misty spray Gleamed wholly silver in the sun, Their hardy voyage was begun. Fair is the south of England's isle: There the sun maketh a full smile On broad sweet grass of mountain side, Or through great woods where birds abide Full cheerily till summer wanes; And, in the quaint long pleasant lanes, —Whose hedgerows gleam with bindweed bells And fragile particoloured shells— At warm noontide, quite dries the dews From narrow footways lovers use A-wandering hand in hand till eve; And there indeed the folk believe In holy Christ and Mary sweet, Yea, and are fairly wont to meet In gentle tournay; not unlearned Of chivalry; but some have earned In all of Christendom good name, Whereof indeed the greatest fame Had Arthur and that Launcelot Of whom is song that ceaseth not. But, all before and after these, The folk hath had but little ease From evils dire and manifold; For in the forests dark and old Was ever many a lurking harm Of foe unseen; and a strong arm Of weird enchantment too hath been Stretched over that land fair and green. Now, longwhile, in a goodly town Reigned hereabout, with all renown, A king both wise and valorous, And happy too in all his house; For in his time, full many a year, The land had peace from every fear, And was quite easeful now become With heaped-up wealth in every home. Bright was the palace that he built, With carven walls and work of gilt, In every part wrought at command By many a Southern craftsman's hand; And treasure he had now well stored In many a hidden guarded hoard; Noble he was and served with love Of all that folk he reigned above, Honouring all things fair and free And caring well for chivalry. Yet after some long while that thus All men were living prosperous In happy peace at home, and fain To think not else should be again Their lot, yea to forget well-nigh The old hard Past and dream to die Even beneath that sunny fate Of joy; and so were grown elate With pride indeed of all;—I say, After somewhile it was this way, There happened many a sudden strange And fearful omen of sad change And terror coming surely soon. But lo, the Princess Guilliadun —Fair I shall show her as I may, Of whom indeed is all this Lay— Before the eyes of men she stood Filling her year of maidenhood; And now, for all her wealth, and e'en For her fair beauty that was seen, Her hand was sought of many a king, Who came with goodly offering To that rich court her father had, And thought to be made rich and glad With love of her and greater far Than any other, helped in war With mighty aid of him her sire. And with the rest there did aspire A certain king, no way the least; Who, past the forests, to the east Had realms and cities counted fair; But rude he was, and took no care Of much that well beseems a knight In bearing him; nor to the sight Seemed other than some rugged lord And leader of outlandish horde. When he with little grace was heard Among the suitors, nor preferred In any way by the king's hand Above the lowest who for land Paid tribute,—wroth, he left the court, Leave-taking after no smooth sort, But threatening vengeance quick and great; And now he sought his wrath to sate. And it befell that, in no fair And knightly order of warfare, But, in his way barbarian, —Lurking in wait with many a man And marking well the fitting while When was no dream of foe nor guile,— He came upon that town and wrought No little panic while men sought, Bewildered in the strange turmoil Their arms; and, with much precious spoil, He 'scaped them, ere their hands were strong To do great battle with that throng Of ravagers made greatly bold For sake of many a prize of gold. Alas, there was an evil sight At morn in all that city bright, And every head with grief was bowed; For many a dwelling-house or proud Fair treasury, or holy place Was now made poor of store and grace; And the great crowd of spoiling feet Had trodden through the gardens sweet And made a wreck for all that year; And little was there held most dear Of king or townsmen that was found Unruined all the city round. So but beginning was their woe; For now was strengthened every foe At hearing only what was done; And with them fought full many a one Of those contending kings at length, Ending their strife for common strength To make their single vengeance sure: And long the warfare did endure With various fate on either hand; But so their foes grew in the land, Pressing upon them more and more, That, in a year, they scarcely bore Against them any equal part; And were become quite faint of heart, Because they saw at length small chance Or hope of new deliverance. So, while the thing was in such state, —Ordered of God's own will and fate, There came to help those failing men Sir Eliduc with his knights ten. When he was come into that land, And learnt what king there had command, And, verily, what evil plight They now were in, he deemed it right To bear him to the palace straight; And there, before the guarded gate, Full hardily to stand and crave To enter in with his knights brave. And when the king of his intent Knew perfectly, right glad he sent A chamberlain to show them grace And bring them all before his face. Then, surely, he beheld how fair And goodly knights those strangers were, And most what person of high mien Was Eliduc; and, having seen, He joyed at heart such guests to know And prayed them now no further go In quest of knightly toils, but stay And be right welcome many a day, And help him if they would at need; Therewith he bade his folk take heed Those strangers should be nobly served According as their rank deserved, And in a mansion of the town Be straight regaled with all his own. Right royally with wine and meat He made them fare, and all things sweet Was fain unto them to have done: But Eliduc spake everyone His knights, and gave them this command; That they should take nought of his hand, But use their own in every way; And this until the fortieth day. And now, when through the leaguered place The fame of these was spread apace, And their fair vows of timely aid, A new and warlike heart was made In breast of every warrior there, And strength again to go and dare The legion of oppressors rude; And, day by day, more grew the mood, As through the street was fairly seen The comely and undaunted mien Of those fair foreign knights, all clad In ready arms, yet wholly glad And fain of laugh and merriment, The while an idle time they spent, As though there were no foes indeed Or war at hand: scarce in more heed Seemed he—the leader of the band— Who with a free and careless hand Kept feast-time there right bounteously. No longer did men think to die, But felt again all goodly pride; And every day were fain to ride Hotly against the lurking place Of that ignoble banded race Of praiseless fighters with the sling And treacherous shaft, whom none could bring To open battle in the field; But now would Eliduc not yield His word for battle or foray, Until, upon a wished-for day, Was told him how along the plain The foe was seen to rise again, Coming up in a phalanx dim From the low dusky forest rim. Then he caused blast of horn and shout To clamour all the town about; And the roused warriors, strong and bright In ready mail, came to his sight From every dwelling in the town; With a great clangour they came down, More knights than men knew in that realm To wield bright lance or wear hard helm, For so almighty was the sound Of those who stood on high and wound The brazen brilliant clarion there, No youth or old man could forbear. But when he turned and led them all To battle past the city wall, I ween already far away The foe was struck with their array, Where sunshine on the gleaming gold And glittering silver fell and rolled In a proud wave that far and near Broke on some plumèd head or spear Wrought of the hard and threatening steel: So eager was each man to deal His vengeance on those robber bands, The spoilers of his wealth and lands, That all with spur and eager rein Set forward to the midmost plain; And there they met them, and soon paired With lance against round shield, and cared Not much, in all their perfect mail, For stone or javelin or fierce hail Of fluttering arrows; but right close They smote among them there with blows Of mighty battle-axe and sword; And, while the war grew up and roared Around them, each one did rejoice To hear the great undaunted voice Of Eliduc, and knew no fear; And not long could the spoilers bear Such rage as theirs; but, while they fell Slain more than any song can tell, With backward steps along the plain They strove a safer place to gain Among the trees, where, so pursued, The hoof-delaying underwood Might aid and give them yet a hope. But still, that some might be to cope Against them in the place they sought And bring them utterly to nought, Sir Eliduc gave quick command, And straightway chose him out a band Of swordsmen lithe of limb and keen To follow, without horse, between The close and thronging trunks a space; Till they should wholly turn their face, And be past hope or power more. O, on that day he smote them sore; And left them dying far away Out in the forest! And when gray Of evening fell, he turned him round; And with much spoil and prisoners bound Led back that troop of his elate, And came before the city's gate. So with a golden victory He saved the king and set him free. Now is it time indeed and right To tell of Guilliadun the fair. Sweet was her head with woven hair, A tender colour to behold Between the beauty of fair gold And some soft palour of fair brown; Lovely she was past all renown; Her face was of no tint one knows, Save only that of the Primrose, With all its strange rare seeming too That charmeth so in the spring new After long waiting. Now, in truth, All in a tender year of youth, She moved in her scarce maidenhood— Like any Lady to be wooed In bower and served of lord or knight: Upon her neck and her arms white Was many an ornament vermeil Or filigree of gold-work frail; And in rich vestures of a queen All amply broidered she was seen; Yea, in a robe of silk most fine Inwrought with many a gem to shine On train, or in fair shapely sleeve Of fabrics such as women weave. So was she; and scarce knew her state, And fair things done to her of fate; The while, about her form and face, Gracious beginnings of all grace Wrought their most subtly fashioned spell; And within her was seen to dwell Some spirit of bright thoughts and new, Swift glancing out of deep eyes blue. Her beauty was as sweet a thing As is the primrose in the spring. She wondered whether she should die And ne'er find out the mystery Of Love; but daily more and more She sought out all his gentle lore; And, like a maiden pure and bright, She wooed him, many a day and night, With her chaste worship all apart, And many an offering in her heart Of happy blushing thoughts made mute, And with the music of her lute. She had a sweet bright-coloured bower Hidden with many a leaf and flower; Wrought all beneath the gay sunshine With leaf and flower of eglantine, And branches green upon the side. There was her heart set open wide, To heed the marvels of sweet sound Of the trees singing all around, Moving like many a shapen hand Their leaves,—all shining as some band Of goodly armoured men of war What time the sun his light doth pour On their clashed coats of glittering steel; And she would hear each sound reveal Some omen spoken to her heart, And, in each sight familiar, start At some new sense or strangeness caught Making an answer to her thought. And there, between the leaves and leaves, In yellow summer noons and eves, When thousand sorceries of sweet In strange enchantment seemed to meet, She took fair sprays of flowers and wove Her many a destiny of love; And prayed love would bless this and this, Seeking yet more some further bliss; Or after all, forgetting these, Would dream of fair loves over seas, Thinking of Tristan and Ysolde And many another story told, And almost hear the rich lute strain From many a royal tented plain Or golden barge on waters blue: So she would tempt indeed and woo Love's self, and much her thought would err Dreaming what he should do with her. God, in all things that He hath made, Full many a jewel hath inlaid; For first He hath set all on high That fair enamel of the sky, Brilliant of blue and eke of white; Then He hath shed the pearl of light, And made that jewel-work the seas: Nor less a gem indeed than these I count His miracle the Rose, To love more precious than all those: But now—a fairer jewel yet— In every woman He hath set Her heart, some sort of precious stone; He shall know perfectly alone —Who all the stars of heaven can call— The worth and number of them all. Most are they given away, or sold For so much love or so much gold, Yea, no man knoweth of their cost; But well I ween that some are lost, And some are of small worth I say, And some are broken and cast away. It is the fairest thing you can, Ladies, to give this to a man —This precious jewel that God gave: One such is all a man may crave. Now when the Princess Guilliadun Had heard what things were done; and soon, How gracious was that foreign knight And wonderful in all men's sight,— She was but fain some way to seek His presence, so to hear him speak, And win some tale from him perchance Of foreign wonder and of France: So with all salutation meet And many a goodly word and sweet, On the first morrow of that day She sent her Chamberlain to pray Sir Eliduc, of courtesy That to her presence he would hie When so he might, and gain her meed Of praise for all his noble deed. And, soon as she at length beheld That chivalrous man of court and field, Fair, with fair locks unhelmed, and face Changed from all sternness to all grace, Yea, found what smiles in him were stored, Knowing him such a perfect lord In foreign courts of kings,—alas She thought some dream were come to pass Of Love's own sending: with his kiss He touched her hand; nor less than this Fair salutation did he make With many a sweet word for her sake; Then even to her side he came, And told her many a thing of fame, Sitting anigh her on a couch. But, while he heeded not her touch, Nor what fair hanging of her sleeve Or robe upon his own might cleave— O she was feeling in her breast A spell she knew not, breaking rest And thoughts too sweet for shame or fear Making a strange new trouble there, Shaking her breath with many a start; And very colours of her heart Did ofttime rise upon her cheek, Until she scarce knew what to speak; And now the more on him she gazed The more within that sight she praised, And knew that she could love him quite; Yea, sooth, if any were her knight, Sir Eliduc—it might be he. Thereat so weak at heart fell she, Troubled a way she could not hide With him there sitting at her side, It surely had not failed at last But on his breast she there had cast Her head quite weeping.—O, what lack Of wiles to hide the sore heart-rack Beginning all love's secret woe, Yea, of such wiles as women know, —What lack I say was here!—to sigh And let the thoughts come up so high Out of the heart; yea, as it would, To let the heart beat unwithstood And do its pleasure with the cheek! Love was so strong and she so weak. But not like one unskilled I ween Was Eliduc, when he had seen The trouble of her breast and eye, And her breath striving with its sigh; Nay, surely, for he was well taught, Oft having seen how love had wrought With many a queen and lady fair; So of his tokens had good care: That day he left her with a bland And sweet leave-taking of her hand. Now all the toil of war was done; And joy it was to everyone To rest that morn in garden sweet, Or wander through the idle street; Or, as though foe had never been, To seek fair wood and meadow green And feel the sun's rich hour of glow; That day, as in time long ago, Came round the yellow smile of noon Bringing the easeful shadows soon. And now this knight, whom all men blest —In fair pavilion full of rest, Made sweet with many a perfumed thing— He lay, half glad, half sorrowing. Amid the silken curtains there Tarried the soft-lipped summer air, With many a murmurous tiding brought From woodlands far of sweet things wrought Under the cool leaves all that day, Or from the blue sea far away. Yea, he was glad indeed awhile, All through the sorrow of exile; For now, no thought of war at hand, Full of new pleasure seemed that land; Like soft enchantments in a dream Under fair floating blue did seem The summer colours, where, in woods Of quaint-cut golden leaves, sweet broods Of pied birds and the painted jay Flouted with clamours strange and gay; Or where, in wilds of forest grass, Through sun and shade was wont to pass The shrinking spirit-slender herd Of roes; and, far as his sight erred, The straitened particoloured mead Was like some fair mosaic indeed: And there, for many an hour of rest, His heart of all things counted best The thought of goodly Guilliadun; And—through such soft times of the noon When most is pleasant need to steep The sense in dreamy wines or sleep— Remembered all her beauty fair, And fragrance of her presence, rare And haunting as some flower's is;— The blue of pale anemones Her eyes were; and her bosom's white, With every changing hue and sight That love or shame could make of it; And with what grace it did befit Her hands,—their toying with the lace On her rich vest's embroidered place. Then on warm mountain side was seen Full many a broadcast shadow green, And, from the homesteads deep among The thronging trees, some strain was sung Such as the shepherds make at eve; And soon the unseen hands, that weave The sweet spell of the summer night, Were changing softly each fair sight In all the pleasant world; and soon The long pale fingers of the moon Touching all weary things with sleep Through flower-land and forest deep. How many a magic Love doth quite Perform in one short summer night— Wherein is scarcely space for dreams, While, on each side the world, it seems The days nigh join with amber hands, Over the dimly gleaming lands, Where under thin-veiled shifting sky Gleams many a flower with white eye Unclosed!—On moonlight paven path How many a meeting place Love hath— Where dreams, or yearning thoughts that thrill, Parted in vain, may find their will, And come together as they range, And fall into sweet interchange Like waves with waves, whereof some sign Felt at the trembling ripple-line Of either brimming heart doth bring A rich unwonted comforting! Not else I ween, nor without aid Of love's sweet miracle, now strayed The restless seeking thoughts that brake The breast of Guilliadun, for sake Of things some hand of fate had brought So near, yet thereof left her nought But loss and love, and like a sore Filling the heart up more and more: And her sighs, full of that fair ill, Set free, drew near, I think, at will E'en to the breast of him they sought, And there a sweet contagion wrought: Else, in some way no man can tell, Love did renew with greater spell All heart-enthralling memories Of Guilliadun and her fair eyes; And cherished still the slender strain Of her last words; and wrought again, From all the balmy pores of night, The very perfume and delight It was to be at her fair side; For over him a charm did glide: And through the fair hours came a dream Of her beside him; she did seem Still hearkening, with her hands at fret, As in the same fair trouble yet; The while almost upon his own The tremor of her arm seemed known, And in her breath a short half sigh Hung fluttering; and his heart felt nigh To some rich living flower—stood still For fear of breaking some rich thrill. Then, it seemed, all their words had been Of nothing else than love; and e'en Their trouble, that they could not say How sweet it was, and in what way It wrought with each of them at heart;— For, now, it seemed, he, for his part, Loved most because of the sweet hue Her eyes held, purer than all blue; And now for ways her neck was curved; Or for some secret sweet reserved In her curled smiles; but now, in truth, 'Twas only for her body's youth, And the whole strangeness of the grace Belonging to its every place. So, a long time, athwart his trance, Such thoughts love's power did all enhance. Yet afterward came with a tear The memory of his own wife dear, And of her love through all time past, And of her words and grief at last: Yea, now he thought, and with it wept, Of the church where his fathers slept In the midst of the grey sea town, In the land where they had renown, And he was honoured with them all, When, under shield armorial, He stood, on holy day and seemed Before his folk all things they dreamed Noblest and highest to attain. Alas, his heart had been nigh fain To fall away from all that state; And, for some fair uncertain fate In alien land, to bear no more, Laid up in many a precious store, The thoughts of what had quite made fair All fates of many a former year, The long rich pasts of love and fame; —So at length, till his very name Should weary on the lips of men, And in his home among his kin Should come to be no more a boast, And he to seem as one quite lost Or one quite false. Thereof he thought Full bitterly, till he was wrought To utter grief; and in his breast His erring heart at length confest The treason love had there begun; And how it had well nigh undone His constancy; and did intend Surely no honourable end, But to bring on him shameful stain In sight of all men who were fain To call him noble,—yea, to cast Him wholly from their praise at last, As one scarce true with heart and hand To king and love and fatherland. But soon, for all such shame, he found That love had made indeed a wound Already inmost in his heart; And that it was quite hard to part At once from the so sweetened sting, Whereto the aching thoughts would cling Right fondly, spite of all his strength: Then thought he with himself at length, That neither had he needs take heed —Like a mere youth unskilled indeed, To fly a straight inglorious flight Because of such first simple sight Of love—that snarer of man's heart, Nor yet should he forget with art To be full armed, so in the end To foil the harm love did intend. For surely, with no spell or snare Should he be taken unaware, Who had well known all subtle ways Wherein that enemy most lays His ambush, yea, and of long time Seen many an one fall in fair crime Of love, trapped most unwittingly; —Himself in Love's court held to be A very courtier above all: —Yea, little need he fear to fall Through aught of love's familiar guile! Verily, too, love hath some wile Laid deeply in the sweet sunshine And woven in the tissue fine Of the mere light and floating air; And in the purest place his snare Is surely set—in field or home Or wheresoe'er a man may roam About the world, in day or night, In moods of sadness or delight, In crowds or solitudes sought out Or dreams;—so must He go quite out Of all the pleasant world, and joy No more in living, or destroy The very heart,—whoso would flee Where no more taint of love shall be. Moreover, in his exile sad, I ween, some kind of sweet he had, Dwelling in any thought or dream Of love; and so alone did seem Softened at all his utmost fate In that far foreign land; for great Indeed Love's power is to charm, And he can stretch a magic arm Over all sadness to prevail. Then, after all, it doth not fail —Yea, Ladies, as ye know, I say,— But there be many a sweet half way, Wherein is pleasantness enough, That one may quite come nigh to love, And e'en accomplish some fair part Of longing, and regale the heart Ofttimes with many a tender bliss, Or feast of passionate looks or kiss; Yea, many a rapturous thing begin Whereto shall cleave no word of sin. Now Guilliadun was grown quite weak Against her love; and ways did seek To break the spells of silence set Hard over all her thoughts; while yet She sought how, without shame or sin, She might most favourably win To some new solace-giving sight Of fair Sir Eliduc her knight. She took the fairest ring she had, And scarf embroidered from Bagdad, —Of silk it was, rich to behold, Crimson and wrought upon with gold; These gifts,—that therewith she might send Some message written with her hand To pray him be her knight indeed, And come and learn some present need She had of succour: so she fained, And tenderly her will explained In words most delicate and meet To win all things they did entreat. Then one day,—while, each day's long round, Full of a fond expectancy, Yet heavy at her heart, and nigh Foreboding sore was Guilliadun,— Failing not still to importune Each barren hour that brought not peace— He came; and made at once to cease The bitter pulse of fear and doubt That racked her heart; for there, about His waist, was girded that sweet thing The scarf her gift, and the fair ring She saw upon his finger set: O, her heart joyed, and did beget A pleasant trust in all its fate. That day the company was great About the King, in good array; For many a noble kind of play The guests were met; but when the name Of Eliduc among them came, The King went to him in mid-hall And gave him welcome before all. Anon, he took him, with all grace, And brought him straightway to the place Where stood the Princess Guilliadun; And bade that soon might be begun Her favour to so great a knight, As she would show forth her delight In nobleness and valorous deeds. —O, as some music strain that leads The enthralled sense, on willing feet, Through new discoveries of sweet, And leaves it dreaming in some heaven Of half found rapture,—O, as even All simple solace-giving things, Proved now that sweet word of the King's, Heard in the heart of each of these, Wherein it healed one same disease Of restless yearning: and, long pent In many a secret languishment, Some inmost thought of Guilliadun —She could not stay it now—too soon It rose up like a flood with rush Out of her heart, and sent its blush Of rapture to the fairest place Upon her bosom and her face. Into a chamber now they came, Apart, where no one was to shame The fair fruition that they took At once in many a mingling look. Ah, to their hearts that place seemed sweet, A fitting place wherein to meet One's love indeed. Rich to the eyes It showed, with couch and tapestries Wrought all of precious stuffs and new From conquered East,—rich with a hue Of changeful purples; and therein Gleamed many an ornament of thin And precious filigree of gold, And marble things fair to behold Through the dim shadows of noontide: There, too, the casement, open wide To many a pleasant singing breeze And moving shadow of fair trees, Let in the balmy breath all day, From many a lovely garden way,— Ay, fair that chamber was, and sweet For lovers such as they to meet. Long time love kept their hearts too faint For words; and all a sweet restraint They suffered, daring scarce to dream The joy they had, that still did seem Too fair for trusting: then they broke That precious spell, and words they spoke,— Such gentle words as knight or dame May alway, without sin or shame. And, first, Sir Eliduc would please That lady's fancy, at her ease, With all the wonders of the war; And tales of fair deeds done afar In harsh fight with her father's foes, Who so long time oppressed with woes And bitter dread that pleasant land; He told her how the heathen band Cried out at sight of the fair line Of pointed spears; and how, in fine, They turned and fled, and were most left A-dying on the field bereft Of all their arms and spoil, or died Fleeing about the forests wide; And how not such a foe, he thought, Should now for many a year be brought From any land of theirs again. Then too, to tell her he was fain Some foreign history of kings And knights, whereof the minstrel sings Already many a fair romance: And much he said indeed of France And of its royal court, with fame Of many a noble and bright dame. Meanwhile not less seemed very dear To him that time while she was near; Yea, and amid such fair discourse The depth of many a troublous source Of feeling came well nigh to break Its false restraint, yearning to slake In many a warmer spoken word Its passion; and each time he heard Her breath in many a liquid sigh, Scarce fain he was to let it die Unculled upon her lips; nor less Was touched indeed to sweet distress His heart, with heeding many a staid And gentle wooing her eyes made Right piteously amid their fear; Yea, bitter seemed it to forbear From satisfying the least part Of the great longing of the heart, With any exquisite delight Of touch, wrought on the flower white Of hand or shoulder, where the sin Of sight made well nigh to begin Some rosy shame: yea, bitter seemed To let the moments, unredeemed With aught of love's sufficing gain, Fall from the precious present, vain— To pass and dwindle fruitlessly Into a vanishing memory, As of frail dreams, dissolving deep And far away in clouds of sleep. But when again some space was wrought Heavy through silence, with the thought Of each, that added burdens more To every throbbing of the sore And anguished heart,—he did renew Fair chosen speech in praise most due For the rich gifts her hand had sent; And, more, for the full favour meant In every gracious word she wrote; And, thanking her, his heart he smote And said that he was ready now —Yea said and sealed it with a vow— Both with his hand and all he was To serve her straight in any cause, Unto the utmost of all right, As he was now indeed her knight. O rich the moments were with joy, Such as no future could destroy— Strange, wrought through many an inward throe And miracle of feeling. Lo It was the noon; and you might hear Now, from the open casement near, Faint sounds that came through sun and shade; And the mysterious rapture made Among the leaves and flowers and things Each rapid summer moment brings Richly to life. But, on that day, The garden flowers from far away,— Yea, even from her own bower apart, Where so long wearily the heart Of Guilliadun was wont to dwell,— They seemed to have a subtler spell Inwoven with their wafted gift Of sweetness; and she could not lift Some urging hand, that seemed to press Upon her heart and with sore stress Compel it to some passionate thing Through many a fearful shuddering: And love's great magic seemed to meet With silence of that time, and sweet, And many a long remembered vow That urged its true fulfilment now Out of the lonely maiden past Of waiting: yea some league at last Was surely made against her there; And hard it was for her to bear. —And, that she could no more withstand, Full well her fluttering lily hand Betrayed; and, troubled with its sighs, Her breast beneath its broideries; And even her tender foot was seen To tremble, scarcely hid between The silken folds wherein it dwelt. In all her soul a fear she felt; For she thought, on that summer day, Sure Love was either come to slay Her heart that moment, or must do Some miracle to save her through At once, what way He only can. And then, indeed, her lips began All in a passionate way, and spake Quite blindly, as the heart did break Straight into many a beautiful word Of love; the which, when she had heard, Seemed fearful with some direst sin That leaves a rankling stain within And dread for ever. Other far, And but the sweetest words that are, They seemed to Eliduc I think; And scarcely fain was he to shrink From one of them: but when, aghast, She ceased,—softly he took at last Her hand, that, like a bird quite faint With fluttering, failed of all restraint, And lay in his, so white and fair That his lips did not long forbear From kissing out their love on it: Nor after did they quite omit Their pleasant lore of eloquence; Nor did the heart in any sense Fail to suffice their utmost need. For, in that place, beset, indeed, With every sweet conspiring spell, His heart withstood no more; but fell, Past saving, into such deep snare And passionate sin of love, that bare Of joy seemed any former place Of rapturous vows, and dim the face That any earlier lover bore; And with his lips he quite forswore —Yea, now, with praise of that hour's bliss, All former spoken rhapsodies. Of all the things a man may have Before he cometh to the grave— Of all the joys that he may win Through any toil or any sin, This is the richest: to possess One yearned-for hour in loneliness Beside one's love, in some fair clime, In some fair purple Autumn time; For quite shall be forgotten then The pains and labours among men, The bitter things of thought and fear; The bitter ends of hope; and, near, Quite at one's side, yea, on one's heart, Yea, touching, with no more to part The yearning hands or looks that meet, Shall seem the often dreamed-of sweet Much more than all the glowing things To which the fondest memory clings— Much more than any rapturous past Or future in fair heaven at last. And this—the fairest moment, sure, In each man's life—it shall endure Some noon; while creeping twilight dims Slowly some flower's purple rims, Or some green distance suffers change Fading before us: then this strange And precious rapture—it shall pass, And never come again, alas! Nay, for there shall be bliss and bliss, And love and love, and kiss and kiss, And many a pleasant touch of hands, And place for love in many lands, And communings of heart with heart, Much to be gained much to impart,— All these; but, surely, never more Doth any time at all restore That faded purple of delight, And the same sweet and the same sight As when one's love in that fair place Blushed with strange crimson, face to face With every inward passionate thought Into real living blisses wrought, And the heart, through some mystery, Seemed filling earths and heavens to be —Yea, things and spaces dimly known— With endless feelings of its own. Hereafter, surely I may say, That, many an hour in night or day, Those lovers knew some precious part Of all the joy that heart with heart Can so beget. Often they came, And found that silken place the same In purple growing glooms at eve; And sat while pleasure would deceive Their thoughts with many a changing dream Wrought of each momentary gleam Of the unearthly twilight blue, That seemed to make the world anew, Like some enamelled picture fair With jewelled stars and leaves: now there, And now in wanderings amid The pleasant flower-paths, half hid Beneath safe shadows of the trees, They dreamed some dream enough to please All silently; or, one by one, In their own soft and murmurous tone, Spoke all the spells that love hath set In wild sweet words, that ever fret The lips of lovers, till his gold And honied secret be all told. So, of his exile, day by day, This joy took many an hour away: It seemed to Eliduc, perchance, Like some fair love in some romance, Passed wholly in strange foreign land And beneath some presiding hand Of magic.—At his heart did lie The amulets of memory In unsought places falling dim, Till the past was nigh lost to him: And yet, somewhile, amid this sweet, The voice within him would repeat The living vow his heart had made To sacred loves, and the words said; And the face of his own wife dear Some days was with him everywhere Between the times of that strange love; As though from far away she strove; And her face, pleading speechless, bore Great shadows and forebodings sore; And often, through the silent night, She seemed to come with the moonlight; And, with one known look, holding him In fair arms to her bosom dim Through many a tear-stained broidery, Mutely some importunity She seemed all earnestly to keep —Yea through the hours of his sad sleep, And quite until the strange wide morn Was opened yellow and the horn Of foreign huntsmen filled the land. Sometimes he could not well withstand The yearning fairly to behold Her face and know what it foretold Of dim calamity; or still Within him grew some weaker will To visit now and see how fared His lands, and whether any cared For what was his, and if perchance, Saved from the evil governance Of plotters vile, the king were turned Again to him so wrongly spurned. Meanwhile it had but come to pass, His king,—sore grieved, finding, alas, How, with deep traitorous intent, Those false reviling ones had bent His mind to a wrath all unjust Against one worthiest of all trust; And further, for that he was pressed Right hotly now in lands possessed Upon a border, by hard foes;— He sent an embassy of those His noblest, who the most were dear To Eliduc; and bade them bear A royal word of full regret Praying him wholly to forget His wrong and exile, and to bring His unmatched sword back to his king. But lo, no sooner had he heard Than he was glad of every word. Yet was he troubled other way; And held his heart still day by day From seeking such a bitter thing As his free parting from that king Who had so soothed his hard exile With perfect favour of his smile: But, more than all, for the fair sake Of Guilliadun, and fear to break The very life within her heart At the first seeking to depart; For this, full many a bitter thought Most deeply in his bosom wrought, Stirring the love within him straight; And all the tenderness that late Had gathered in the inmost core Of feeling, now it made right sore The very soul of him within. —O Ladies, when you will begin With love, you know scarce on what dark And eddying stream you do embark A skiff so frail and rudderless As this poor heart! nor can you guess How soon, and in what subtle way, Love will procure you for his prey, Quite trapped sometime at unawares In dire entanglement and snares Past all your own wit to undo: Yea, but ye know that this is true: And now ye see that noble knight Sir Eliduc, holy and right Before all men, is come to fall, And so without his fault at all, In such a perilous strait indeed, Of love, between two ways that lead Each to some equal ill,—I deem That well before him it must seem A hard and hopeless thing to live For any day, now he must strive In seekings or forsakings sore: I pray you pity him therefore.— And when he found that Guilliadun Fell in her sorrow nigh to swoon At word of parting from him so,— And that no joy again could grow In her sad bosom for the sake Of other love, but she would take At once some inward death for him, To waste her body and quite dim Her sad remainder of life's space— When this he saw upon her face, Knowing her trust and truth in love, He could not quite forbear; but strove To soothe her heart with promise fair, That, surely, no toil would he spare To win some near day of return, Whereto he ne'er should cease to yearn. So Guilliadun beheld him go; And stayed her sorrow and her woe; For she could love him all the while Waiting, and think of his last smile; And trust his tender uttering, And dream of the fair future thing. Then in his land he did arrive; And made the joy of all to thrive With sight of him, whom all men knew Long time so noble and so true, And now again their very strength And saviour; for no foe at length Endured before his armèd hand: Right soon he beat them from the land. A year he was in field and court; And now his honour fell not short Of anything a king may give; And, save the king, no man did live So royally in all men's eyes. But, after all the hard emprise And triumph of the war were past, He did become as one downcast With some o'er-measured weight of things Sad in some memory that clings Speechless about the heart. And slow, Against his will he seemed to go To tilt or tournay or fair sport; So that, for him, in all the court, Was truly now great heaviness, And many an one would strive to guess What thing so ailed him. Then again He did return—as one most fain Of solitude—to his own place. There they were right glad of his face; And there, maybe, he stayed awhile In such fair peace as would beguile The living sadness that he bore, And thoughts that should not evermore Be slain or ended; there, maybe, In his grey castle by the sea, The pleasant holy pasts renewed Awhile their hold on him, and sued About his heart not all in vain; Or it seemed precious to regain Each old accustomed thing and mode, And find for him there still abode Unchanged the honourable love; And many a time he sought to move, With sudden tenderness new felt, Some little memory that dwelt Far away in its hidden place Among the rest; or on the face Unchanging sweet of his true wife, Fair with the love of all his life, He would find still, and prize it best, Some likeness of the tenderest And first love-look. —Alas, I say, For afterward he fell away From all this; ah, his bitter fate— It could but have him soon or late! And sadness and the utter strength Of thoughts divided, and, at length, The whole real passion of strange love, Foregone awhile, rolled back and drove His soul to its sweet sin again. But still he lingered, as though fain He would deny the thing, and deem That some mere false and evil dream Were but defrauding him awhile With strange delusion; a sad guile Taught him to do in every way His wont; nor ceased he any day From chace with hounds or falconry; And yet when there was none to see He ceased maybe from all, subdued At once with some most bitter mood Of thoughts that chimed not with his deed; And, as though inwardly did bleed Some sudden wound, he reined up short, In very middle of the sport, In any lonely wood or place Of cover,—heeding not his chace Nor yelping of his hounds returned Sadly about him. But he spurned Long time such weakness and forbore; Yet more the weakness grew and more; Until he could not bear the day, So irksome seemed to him his way, So bitter was this inward strife. The very sweetness of his wife And every tender silent look Became a thing he dared not brook And harder than the hardest taunt Against his falseness.—In no haunt Familiar with the fair times past And lost, for him now could there last Repose or peace; but he would flee Long dreary miles beside the sea In rough paths of the rocks, and dare Some solitude no man knew where, And battle all day with that foe, His fate of passionate sin and woe. But, one night, in a ship well manned With speedy oarsmen, to the land Of Guilliadun once more he sped. Darkness and storm were overhead; And there, apprised some secret way He took her—glad through her dismay At any sight of him at last And end of bitter waiting past. And through the night upon his breast Love made indeed her terror rest; Till on the morrow the pure sun Seemed mindful of no wild deed done. And now that all the sky above Was blue and their hearts full of love; And all about them fell a sound Of golden waves like laughs around Their rapid keel; the while, afar, To the fair coloured distant bar Of the bright ocean, gleamed the hue Of halcyon hours,—ah, now they two Joyed in great silent overflow Of loves: for them, the very glow, And myriad-woven sounds of wind, And mingling sounds of waves combined In many a mystery of sweet; And, in accomplishment complete Of some ineffable thing dreamed, With secret inmost soul they seemed To touch now wholly; and a thrill Of inward rapture did fulfil The long desire of every look, So that their thoughts now scarcely took The weary and imperfect ways Of words, as in those fainter days When they were sadly bound to speak Their hearts in repetition weak, Or in an agonised embrace To kill some doubt or to efface The constant marring bitterness. Now, in the mute and pure caress Of liquid looks and secret thought, As though at length all love had wrought Some miracle of peace, they lay, Voyaging in their bark made gay With many a coloured pennon bright And canopy beneath the light Floating in silken folds; and near, Time after time, they loved to hear The silver sound of oars, and oft The music of the lutes, played soft About the prow, and like a song Fallen from some æolian tongue Of zephyr. All about them came A strange sweet pleasure above name Or word or thought: and things around, In living sight or living sound, Grew in mysterious sort akin To every feeling sense within Their hearts; and many an unseen kiss Seemed to be covering them with bliss; For the most trivial noise, that thrilled From the sail fluttering or filled With breath from some rich unseen lip, Or the least murmur of the ship Came to them changed some way, and fraught With strange enchantment or strange thought —Fell into accents at their heart With tenderness enough to start Their pleasant tears. And, as they went, Sometimes a little wonderment Would move them, or they thought, perchance, That they were fallen in some trance Of joy too perfect to endure: For, now, the world seemed all so pure Down through the waves or far above Through heavenly blue, and, for their love, Breaking in colours fair and oft Like smiles ineffable and soft Out on the calm, and all for them, Breaking in many a flower and stem Of wonders beautiful with light, Revealing liquid depths of sight Under each amber-coloured wave. —So joyed they. Ladies so I crave, Yea, so I pray Love keep for me Some halcyon hour upon the sea With one most loved,—some hour all brief Between the sins and all the grief Of love,—between the day and night Of bitter life, one hour's delight! Alas! for they had come perchance Now even to the land of France; But ere they touched it, and with feet Quite saved from all the sea,—the sweet False wand of their enchantment fell; And sudden broken was the spell Which love had laid on all their fate To blind them: and the treacherous state And smiles of the dissembling sea Changed fearfully to many a free And foamy utterance of wrath. Sudden before them all their path Showed horrible with writhing sight Of restless billows without light Athwart the feeble ruling tides, With bounding backs and seething sides, Urging their wild tumultuous way, Lolling out forkèd tongues of spray: Then, with a quick and rushing blast, The dismal tempest clouds were cast All ruin-filled across the face Of heaven, marring each sweet space, And rending all the false fair blue. Quickly each sudden peril grew. And soon the wind and stormy noise Broke forth above them—a great voice In torrent menaces of death; And soon, from greatest depths beneath, The monstrous multitude of waves Came up from all the darksome caves Ploughed over by their goading keel, And stood around them, harsh as steel, Brandishing many a fearful point And whitening crest, above dark glint Of cloven seas that opened wide Vast mouths of waters on each side. And when there was no sort of peace, But dread did utterly release The trembling ribald tongues of men —Thinking that surely they were then To deal at once with death,—there grew A fearful thought among that crew Of fated men, and through the ship A murmur went from lip to lip. And, at last, one man from the crowd Came forth, and bitterly and loud He cried that hard upon the head Of each of them was punishèd The grievous sin of one alone; And that the wrath of heaven was shown Now clearly for Sir Eliduc, And all they had this evil luck Because that, foully, in despite Of every law and holy right, He bore that maiden to the land Where yet one, wedded with his hand, Lady and wife, dwelt sweet and good: And surely none could change the mood Of heaven; and, till their souls were seen Quite purged from all such guilt and clean, This hand of punishment so sore Would not depart; but the dear shore Of that their native land would quake Beneath them and reject to take Them so polluted anywhere. So cried he loudly, coming there To Eliduc, heeding no threat, And, ere indeed he yielded yet, One word had wrought its bitter sting —One word that told an evil thing; Launched fatal, like some wingèd dart, It struck unerringly the heart Of Guilliadun, pale where she lay, Half fainting in the mere dismay At thought of death in midst of bliss; The sense thereof she could not miss. The sense of all the treacherous woe That fate and love had made her know. Then, with a wound, upon her smote The pang of all her life remote, To distant days made full of grief, And to all days beyond relief, Yea, while she yet lived Guilliadun. And so at once as in a swoon Or death she fell. O all in vain Was any leech to bring again The precious throbbings of her heart, Or any kiss to melt apart Her sealèd lips and from beneath Draw forth the spirit of her breath. But Eliduc, half mad was he, And would not have that this could be Her death; and now, in all men's sight, He strove with the full passionate might Of kisses and entreaties hot, Wrought breathlessly upon each spot Where lingered yet the tender hue Of her scarce life: so burning too With rage and vengeance was each word He said, no man of them that heard Durst come before him now for dread, No man durst say that she was dead. —But lo, such sudden way appeased Was all the wrath of heaven, and ceased From any troubling of them more; And very soon they came to shore.— Then wholly taken up with grief —With all the growing thought of grief— Sir Eliduc he did not stay For help or vengeance on that day; But himself from the bitter shore That tender Guilliadun he bore. And quickly to a hidden place, Hidden and hard for steps to trace, Athwart the pathless forest dim He brought her. There all known to him A little sanctuary stood Hallowed in middle of the wood, A silent place deserted quite; And there upon the altar white He placed her, beauteous with closed eyes, A perfect lover's sacrifice. It seemed as though the forest made For that white place a deeper shade; And there the trees all vast and old Stood with their secrets manifold All shrouded up in shadowy thought, Between broad leaves together brought, Like vast hands folded in repose. It was the place some hermit chose To solemnise with all his tears; And of his strivings through long years, And all the penitence he did, And all the holy life he hid, —The leaves and flowers, of all these things, Cherished maybe rememberings, —Kept tender secrets of the ways He lived and hallowed all his days, The tears he shed, the sighs he sighed, And the sweet spot on which he died. There was a holy sort of gloom As though most certainly a tomb Were hidden thereabout somewhere, With scarce a sign, but very dear To all the flowers and to God: And certainly the perfumed sod Seemed consecrated all around. So Eliduc a place had found, A place quite sweet and lone enough To make an end of such a love —Not ineffectual at the last, But, out of all its short sweet past, Furnishing some great fund of tears And memories to enrich long years With many a secret rhapsody: So the real flower of love should be, —O flower unearthly, over-rife, Too frail for any soil of life!— Henceforth some immaterial bloom Of ever-lingering perfume; So he should keep that precious sin A thing henceforth all hid within The heart, not judged of any man: Let Him judge Eliduc who can! But, while he had her there alone, A little season, to atone, With many an utterance agonised Of tears and utmost grief unprized, —Before the bitter silences Of fates, that hearkened pitiless, Weighing nought of the words and sighs, Gazing from cold futurities Immutable with doomful gaze, —And more than all before her face Silent more fearfully indeed,— Truly she did not fail to plead Fairly with him for all her wrong; Yea, piteously indeed and long, Her whole face, with no smile beneath, Made seeming sad for aye with death, Reproached him with an endless look; The very mouth from which he took Its kiss, seemed now, in some clear way Its own, to form what it would say, And in a wordless whispering Absolve itself from everything That left him solace after all: Seeming with pressed lips to recall The spirit from each little kiss Denying all the past of bliss. And this was more than to have heard The vengeance of some poisoned word Or seen one look of sad adieu And disavowal,—this, to sue For ever, with remorseful cares And penitential pain and prayers, Her face, that seemed still to retain A sad account of every stain His sinful passionate touch had wrought,— Her face that seemed in holy thought, Beyond relenting the least while Into the faintest, purest smile. In truth he had her fallen there, As though she were some flower fair, Ruined with eager wanton hand, So that no man should understand The mystery of its sweetness—now Dissolved in the sad overthrow Of petals yielding to each breath Their passionless unfruitful death: So a mere bitter fruitless thing At length, after all suffering Of love and long desire and sin, It was in such a sort to win That shadow of possessing her, That joyless liberty to stir The fallen blossom of her face, To put her hand in any place, And weary of each wondrous touch His heart had coveted so much: Now indeed there was none to care What he should do with her sweet hair; But he could wind it as of old Around her head, or loose its gold In lavish waste upon her neck; And all the gems that used to deck The fair white place above her breast, The jewelries upon her vest, And starry rings that made her hands Like flowers on which a fair dew stands, Piercing the light with sudden hues, —All these were his to touch and use; Sad playthings now were they, alas, Pastimes for grief that could not pass. How false a solace was it, so To smooth her hair aside, and show, Pale as a pearl shed on some flake Of snow, her ear; to touch and take Its ornament of filigree, And never win therewith to see One kindled change in any place Of tender feeling on her face! How sorely earned a right was this To know the tender mysteries Of her apparel, intricate In all its fragrant mazes, late So pure a marvel of sweet guile Enamouring long his heart; the while Around him, dwindling less and less The faint blown fragrance of her dress, Seemed like some thinnest part of all Her spirit fading past recall! O for some long and bitter space, Weeping beside her in that place, I ween, not otherwise he sought To fill his heart, but with sad thought And fantasy of grief like this, Feeding the fountainous abyss Of tears. —And like some watery blast, Brought from the whole warm west and cast Upon the rotting summer woods, That sweeps with constant rage of floods Down all the wild and rainy way The undergrowth of many a day, And mighty wounded limbs of trees Torn from them writhing, and, with ease, The timid multitude of leaves Falling with every sigh that heaves The trembling forest; and, at length, Sated in all its tyrant strength With ruin of the beauteous year, Leaves the whole forest still and drear With tall trees leafless letting through The skies of winter calm and blue: —So was that torrent of his tears From all the heaped-up source of years And gushing springs of thought within: It washed away much love and sin, Yea, from the deep grounds of his heart, And left him like a man apart, Henceforth, from all man's fitful fate Of stormy feelings passionate. The grey cold sadness of his eyes Was very like the winter skies; And now that all the tears were past He rose; and felt some peace at last, To think that love had surely done His worst there, and would even shun That heart of his for evermore, Leaving the precious dust it bore In every tortured place of thought, Leaving the tarnished treasure brought Through bitter paths of memory; And that no future could deny, Through any new uncertain fate, These things he held in such sweet state Of memory—eternal so, This passionate past of joy and woe. There, as he found her day by day, Her beauty did not pass away; But Death seemed tenderly to touch Her cheek, quite slow to wither much Her tender hue; quite fain to spare The semblance of her spirit fair In her face fading flowerwise. And, when, from looking on her eyes He could not stay sometimes his love, But in some tremulous way did move One of the fringed and perfect rims, There seemed not such a death as dims Even the innermost frailest hue Of living; but still, looking through Pale glistening waters warm and deep, Seemed all her soul there, as in sleep, Or smiling through some fond deceit, And seeing truly fair and sweet The great blue heaven above her spread, And the bright branches overhead, And all the place indeed and him: Yea, as though all were some fair whim! And, often through the long golden noon When the day's summer seemed to swoon, And the rich sunlight far and wide Transfigured and so glorified The forest, passing to and fro Like a blonde angel; and the glow Grew wondrous and the place was thrilled, And fervid purple flowers filled More mightily the place with bloom, —O then it seemed some blessèd doom Of peace was still pronouncèd there; Or some past mystery of prayer Was hallowing the silence yet; Yea, so that death might there forget, Or be in wonder, tarrying long, Or come quite changed there from the throng Of flowers, in some perfumed way, And with no envy of decay: O it was good to be there then With her, and all so far from men! And sometimes, after he had wept, With strange and holy feeling crept A greater peace into his heart Than came of any dream or art Of thought,—a part of some long calm Quite after death—a mystic balm Of saving shed from some fair vase In heaven, in such pure way as awes Through the full sunshine everywhere: O it was blessèd to be there! Or sometimes all the heart fell faint With inward thinking of the Saint; And, dying some pure death of trance, Or purified past all hindrance Of each participating dross Of sense, beheld His spirit cross One of the gleaming ways and melt Into the light; beheld or felt And knew Him walking through the place, And all his presence like a grace Working that miracle of peace. —So Eliduc came to great ease At length in all his soul within, Like one whom all his mortal sin God hath forgiven. Who can tell How great a holiness and spell Shall be and evermore abide In the place where a saint hath died! Then one day, through God's grace above, —While he was looking on his love, And thinking how it had been sweet If before death they two could meet, And for some little space so live Without sin, God should quite forgive— This miracle was wrought for him: A little ermine swift and slim And purely white with spirit eyes, Out of the forest came; and thrice, In a strange fearful way like light, It ran across the bosom white, Yea, and the upturned face as well Of Guilliadun; and then it fell Straight to the ground and would have fled; But as it fell it lay there dead. And while he wondered much thereat, Another ermine, white as that, Came from the wood seeking its mate; Then, in a way disconsolate, Finding it stark and with cold eye Dazzled with death, a sharp sad cry He gave, and ran back as he came, And brought a strange bright flower like flame Or redder than the hue of blood, Gathered in some place in the wood, And set this with an unknown care In the mouth of the other there, Upon the loosened languid tongue: And, after this, it was not long Before that great and simple charm Worked potently against all harm, And, by its virtue, did renew In all the body the quick hue And litheness of the life again; And then those ermines were so fain Of their fair life sportive and sweet, That with the swiftness of their feet Straightway they fled and entered quick The forest mazes cumbered thick With flowers. —Eager at this sight Was Eliduc, to try what might There yet were in that wondrous spell: Nor was he doubtful, feeling well Some holy purpose in the thing, Above his fond imagining; And so he found without delay The fallen flower, where it lay Redder indeed than any flame; And, praying well in Jesu's name, He wrought the charm as he had seen. And as that flower touched between The deathless lips of Guilliadun, It broke the mystery of her swoon, And let her open blithe and wide Her eyes from which no thought had died, And gave her mastery of her breast To wake out of their fit of rest The fitful happy tides of breath; All through her body, which no death Had sullied nor availed to chill Went many times the blush and thrill Of pleasant living; and, at length, Her spirit, summoned by the strength Of all the charmed and yearning gaze Of her real love, through many a maze Of half-sighs faltering, was brought, From bodiless abodes of thought, Back to the perfect summer light, To flush her whole face with delight, Finding each kiss of love there still. O what like love can cure the ill Of love? That moment overthrew All timorous thinking; and they knew Henceforth for ill no sort of name But Death; for all the world became Their own; and trivial seemed all fear, And light all other things to bear, While they could each the other find In any place of life, and bind Their souls together in such wise. And so, beneath those summer skies, Full of their hearts, that did begin Most overflowingly within A fresh fertility of bliss; —Delayed I think by many a kiss, And ofttimes by such fervid tide Within their hearts as would abide No long restraint indeed or loss Of perfect interchange,—across The flowering forest paths they came, In all this rapture without name; And tenderly their steps would cling To each delicious wandering; And many a soft delay they found, Where with new smiles the forest ground Lured them to press its printless soils Of yielding mosses; or where coils Of festal flowers held their feet, Or rose up fairly to entreat And half compel them to abide, Would not be alway thrust aside. And they—scarce in a haste were they: Lo, now I leave them on the way. Alas, for here I have to tell Of all the sickness that befell Unto a lady worth all love: Surely there was none fair above That lady Eliduc called wife, None fitter for one's love in life; And now that she is gone, I say, Even from all this life away, And with her love and holiness Saved from that time of her distress For ever,—as it came to pass— Who shall be like her now alas? O in the early day when she Was left, but first not utterly, But with a false fair thought of joy And hope, bright seeming, to destroy The burning canker of despair,— Her heart made promise to forbear, Indeed, from any bitter grief Or doubt of fate, and took relief In golden seeming of the sweet Fair days that brought the future fleet. And in that chamber, where she dwelt Most with the thought of him, she felt —O many a tender ecstasy, In lonely noontime when the sea Glowed and made music from afar, Or in the twilight when the star Of Venus sweet came out to rule The dreams and fancies beautiful Of lovers; and if any sight Or time or thing gave her delight, Yea, if the golden time or dim She loved, it was because of him. And when,—amid the changeful round Of deeds wherein her fancy found Some consolation or pastime, Through precious toil or chanted rhyme Of song, that many an hour made full Of solace,—in delicious lull His voice would reach her, and the tide Of the soft parting words would glide Through the calm space of thoughts and sighs Her heart was,—she would dearly prize That moment: And she had no fear That he—the only one she loved— Could be of any other moved To real forgetting. Many a way She found to keep her heart half gay, And pleased with every wanton thought The hope or memory of him brought. Then there was ever and again Upon her lips the happy stain His kiss had left there like a touch Of flowers,—a little thing, not much In telling, but indeed a charm Quite potent to keep off the harm Of many a doubt and bitter fret Of sorrow, yea, to soothe her yet. But in some little while, despite Her joyous will and the thoughts bright, That ever like a little rill Of tender laughter sought to fill Serenely all the quiet day,— But in some little while, I say, Her inward love failed not to start Oft in such trouble at her heart, Suffusing with such purple glow Her bosom emulous of the snow For peace and whiteness, that she learned Almost with trembling how she yearned To have him back, e'en but to speak Some mightier word than all words weak Her tenderness had found before. Then when, a day long waited for, She held him in her arms, and gazed Upon the face her heart so praised, And saw a strange new shadow there; And when she felt his voice forbear From touching many a wonted tone Whose meaning was best loved and known; And, wondering, she must confess Now wholly foiled and powerless Each tender magic she could make, That, all about her, used to take His looks, in many a guiltless snare Her fond inventing would prepare, —That day, when such a thing she found, Her heart took a great bitter wound Of doubt and poisoned thought within. Yea, after that, she did begin —O through the dreary ways untold Of sorrow, secret, unconsoled— To fall away from all her place In that fair heaven of love and grace Which she had so long held her own, Whose precious state had even grown The very custom of her life; Yea, spite of all the hidden strife Her heart in all its meekness made, She must behold now change and fade Away from her that gilded light Of the known love that made so bright Her life around her; she must miss That air which seemed to hold a kiss Dwelling about her evermore, That mute look seeming to adore Her very presence everywhere. Maybe, she could not quite despair At first, and with some clinging hope, Maybe, her fondness sought to cope Against this hidden woe and strange That did so desolate and change Her husband's all belovèd look: For very hard it was to brook The sight of him, whom all men's eyes Saw bearing secret miseries Of thought, and heavy all the day And weary of his former way, —For her with whom had ever been His heart, it was right hard, I ween, To see this, and, in no hour dim, Draw more than others nigh to him. —Ah bitterly she learned the truth That he could no more turn to her And leave it to her hand to stir The sadness from about his thought. Then she found how for her he wrought A very sad and cruel guile, A piteous semblance of a smile, As though he deemed she should not know How she was served with feigning now. Alas, he marked not her sweet ways, And grieved that charmer of his days! But when she quite believed, at last, She was from all sweet love outcast, A quick disease and mortal sort Of sorrow took her, to make short The bitter time she could not bear. Her golden chamber grew most drear; And now, about her so forlorn, The sweetest things there seemed to mourn, And all the spells of pleasantness Were changed to working her distress; Her precious playthings seemed to reach For her a plaintive kind of speech, Holding a language all day long Together, like a funeral song; And from her lute there broke a sigh, Or like a sob when none was nigh, Appalling her, as though she heard Her own voice uttering some great word That broke her life's sharp chord of ill: There, more and more, she felt the chill Of fate's mysterious encroach; And shuddered now from all approach Of the rough outward stir of life; Her eyes made tremulous weak strife With the once fair familiar light Of day, that now seemed over-bright, With never any tempered gleam Fit for the sadness of her dream; At length, when twilight made that room Most dim, there seemed no place of gloom So dim as the dim place she sought To hide the shadow of her thought. And Eliduc was far away, No man knew where or till what day He tarried, but alas, all vain For her was now his face again: Since she was nothing at his side, What mattered it how soon she died? For, now that all within her felt So sure of change, and well nigh dwelt With death already in her dreams, To the most tender summer gleams, The blue skies, and the sunniest sights Of life—to these her heart held rights No longer; but, without complaint, Her dreams would bear her spirit faint To sunless places, far away In some wild forest, where the gray And ancient leaves, each like a whole Dead shrivelled remnant of a soul Withered and shrunk away at last From every part of a life past, Their nameless sort of burial found, In shifting graves upon the ground, Or frittered the long hours of death Away with every changeful breath That swept them from their shallow tomb. So did her soul forefeel some doom Grey cold and unremembering, And more and more seemed hovering On borders where the dim mists dwell, Nigh within feeling of the spell. And ever weaker grew the thread That held her from among the dead, And could recall her painfully To any bleeding memory Of the defrauded life she left. Truly, with her, sorrow had reft, Quicker than any ailment can, The right of that short summer span Her life from her; and, in quick space, The conscious fading of her face Foreswore its emulous coloured sign: Yea, quickly, as the flower most fine Sudden disheartened may forsake And shed its purple flake by flake In one short day, till with pale head It stands disrobed as do the dead. At length, one day, some seeking her Entered, and found her not astir; And knew death's touches everywhere And, at once, all that chamber fair Deflowered and quite transformed with death; For gone was the most magic breath, And all the eloquent sights were mute: Only, as though upon her lute A hand smote passing, was there still In all the silence some sad thrill Of the last sobbing musical Of broken chords. There, after all, They felt fulfilled the inward thought Which daily in their hearts had taught Such shadowy fear; and, where they now Beheld her sitting, need—I trow— Was small for one to touch her hand, Or e'en her lips, to understand The truth of the pale change they kept. Then surely each one of them wept That Eliduc was still away: And, now,—alas, for him I say; For, surely, when he doth return Sir Eliduc shall have to mourn. Has summer come without the rose, Or left the bird behind? Is the blue changed above thee, O world? or am I blind! Will you change every flower that grows, Or only change this spot— Where she who said, I love thee, Now says I love thee not? The skies seemed true above thee; The rose true on the tree; The bird seemed true the summer through; But all proved false to me: World, is there one good thing in you— Life, love, or death—or what? Since lips that sang I love thee Have said I love thee not? I think the sun's kiss will scarce fall Into one flower's gold cup; I think the bird will miss me, And give the summer up: O sweet place, desolate in tall Wild grass, have you forgot How her lips loved to kiss me, Now that they kiss me not? Be false or fair above me; Come back with any face Summer; do I care what you do? You cannot change one place— The grass, the leaves, the earth, the dew— The grave I make the spot, Here where she used to love me, Here where she loves me not. THE LAY OF YVENEC. ‘Maleit seient tut mi parent, E li autre communalment, Ki à cest jalus me donèrent, E de sun cors me marièrent. A forte corde trait e tir, Il ne porra jamès murir. Quant il deust estre baptiziez, Si fu al flum d'enfern plungiez. Dur sunt li nerf, dures les veines, Qui de vif sanc sunt tutes pleines. Mut ai sovent oï cunter Que um suleit jadis trover Aventures en cest païs Qui rechatouent les pensis. Chevaliers truvoent puceles, A lor talent, gentes e beles; E dames truvoent amans, Beaus e curteïs e vaillans: Si que blamez n'en estoient, Ne nul fors eus nes veeient: Si ceo peot estre e ceo fu, Si onc a nul est avenu, Deu ki de tut ad poeste, Il en face ma volenté.’ Marie: Lai d' Yvenec. MS. Bibl. Harl. No. 978. Since I have e'en begun to sing Full many a tender and sweet thing Of love and lovers; half to ease My heart's great woe of yearning thought, That many a love indeed hath brought Against me, yea, that shall not cease This side of death; and half to please Your gentle ears, if so I may; Shall I end adding lay to lay, Having yet in my heart unsung, Strangest and loveliest among The treasured tales that Marie sang This tale of the fair love that sprang Wondrous, and like a flower unsown In the sad desert of a lone And hopeless life? Ah, miracle! —That visitest so secretly The straight, the joyless inward cell Of many a soul that hath to dwell Chained to some unknown misery Of thought and unattainable dream Of heavens: unearthly do they seem Unreal and distant as a star Until thou, soft and sudden—light And glory filling day and night With splendid rapture—dost unbar Some unimagined golden gate Of love! How excellent they are— The clear transfigurements that wait Throughout the world for thee, O Love, As for the lifting of a veil That shows blithe souls that feigned of late Most funeral faces! how above The sky of any former pale And faultless dream becomes the earth That thou hast touched, the blessèd air That thou hast breathed in and made fair With smiles! The cruel stones give birth To rich unheard-of blooms; and worth The great blue side of heaven seems now The white wall of a prison, if thou Hast let the sunlight in. And, lo, Henceforth, there is no kind of woe To reach the hidden heart and stay The ecstasy that night and day Makes lone immense sweet singing there. —For some, indeed, may love, and lay Their great resplendent joys quite bare Before the world,—unshamed and glad And glorious as they walk from birth To death, proclaiming they have had Such fair wealth all their way, such mirth Of very passionate delight— Love himself coming to them clad In some new saffron day and night— That, truly, all hath been most sweet, And nothing goodlier need they meet In heaven: but some, indeed, must keep A tyranny on lip and look; And eyes that fain would smile must weep, And voice, that fain would ofttimes leap Into great singing, must all brook To speak the set words of some book, Lest it should sing the secret out That gilds each thought and glorifies The infinite innermost that lies Dissembled; and no man shall doubt The pained white of the patient face, That long it hath been painless,—nay, Nor dream the long detested way Of servitude hath got the grace Of some invisible flower set Sweetening it wondrously all through. —Ah, live and bear a little yet The grey days of your life,—O you— Grieving in some unlovely gloom A captive, in some martyrdom Of most intolerable fate, Wed for the heartless outer part Where yet love never wed you;—late, Perchance, it shall be, and your heart Shall have closed every outer gate That let love enter from the world: O bear a little yet and wait: Ere God hath ceased from you and furled Away from you the great fair blue, That paints eternity,—your true, Your dreamed-of love shall come to you. His face shall never have lost light For all the dismal years: his smile Shall dawn insuperably bright Upon some long and lonely eve, When, maybe, you have ceased some while To weep and almost to believe. And the night shall not come; but, then, The endless undivided day Of the long heaven, and mile on mile Of a vast and delicious way Shall gleam out from the ways of men That hour before you: O to see His great immortal look, shall be A perfect end to the long years Of waiting: O to fill your ears With the world of each wondrous word, Shall more than put away your tears; For you shall know he never erred That he came not to you: perchance, Somewhat unearthly shall enhance His head with glory, and unknown So long a while, he shall have grown Almost an angel, in the length Of coming to you, heaping strength To win you with! Ah, do you think That, merely your immaculate Lone excellence, should never link Your soul to his, above all fate Of days that hold you separate? What is the fastness he shall shrink From overcoming with some burst That frees and makes you his, for whole Requital of his soul athirst In the dry distance for your soul? —Though one hath chained up all the ways In the fair world; though, nights and days Fall down hard-fettered in some blank Forgotten dungeon, where a clank Follows each footstir and subdues Each daunted word;—did Love ne'er use His irresistible might and spell In such-like way as I would tell In this same story?—Yea, full oft; And many a cruel fate is soft With his rich secret, unbetrayed In the deep dwelling he hath made Within; and few have told or writ The splendid simple prodigy They knew; and none, believing it, Have doubted love so secretly Was foiling the hard world their strong Oppression had kept hard so long. No dame was fairer in the land Than Bertha, loved of knight and bard; And great was he who held her hand But loved her not,—he was so hard So churlish unto love,—and made No softness for her, but betrayed Her sweet bride's faith. He, of his pride Presumptuous, lusted that the might And wealth and territory wide, Which he had gotten through unright And stealthy dealing, or by strength Tyrannously, were made sure plight Unto some heir of his at length —To be left full and unaccused For ever; and no other dread, Of trampled worth or right refused Vexed the man now; but only this Had power frustrating all his bliss, That men should come when he was dead And curse him, for a late redress Of ancient wrong. Therefore he wed; And thought most surely to possess His utmost hope; but heaven foreshowed Its meaning sternly to upbraid His memory for rich costs unpaid, And the whole life-long debt he owed To vengeance. So the thing he prayed Withholden was, and that he vowed Unvisited. And, sorely gnawing His patience inwardly, two years He bore; at length, the third year drawing Fast to its close, no better wears His straining hope; and now with fears Grown bitter, he complained and e'en Condemned that gentle dame, and hid No longer his ungenerous mien, But daily taunted her and chid Her gentleness.— His crabbed age, Fallen past reasonable hope Of all renewal, would assuage Its envy chiding her, and grope, Unshamed, amid foul jealousies, Gathering new resentments still. He had a sister of like will, Who with foul infamies and lies Prompted his ready thoughts to ill: She was a mean and heartless crone, Whose life had never flowered in truth With love or any balm of youth, But preyed on envyings alone And cankered to the very bone; Yea, she quite hated the heart's tint And the rose flush of lips and health Of love's own life, accounting wealth In these things as some dismal stain, For souls to starve out by sheer stint Of joy, accounting all men vain And born for penances and pain. Therefore, with every harsh endeavour She did promote her brother's mood To tyranny, devising ever Cruel coercions, and such rude Restraint as made poor Marie hate Her youth, which constantly renewed Sick sources to her bitter fate. And one day, in all love's despite, —For jealousy, and for great fear, Lest the all-pitiable sight Of her more perfect for each tear Should sometime, with a sudden might Moving men's hearts to learn the blame, Plead of their villany; and then The hideous thing begetting fame, No honour should be theirs, but shame And hate in all the hearts of men: They made some most deceitful tale,— How, for soul-penance sorely done, Bertha was fallen sick and pale, And ailed to be a space alone And for a space be seen of none. And, through their wiles, it did not fail But she was moved to their deceiving, And that herself performed the thing With scarce a thought or murmuring, Full of her early inward grieving. And lo, they lured her from her bower, And e'en from all the sick sweet ways Her tears had worn, and weary days Found full of soothings, faint and mute, But fit as lullings of a lute; And in a lone and distant tower They left her wounded life to swoon And wither, like a sapless flower, Seen only of the midnight moon Or of the sun at noon. The chamber was most chill and drear A place where you might die of fear; And, from the casement's irksome height, You scarce could snatch a mistful sight Of the far lands of Brittany: And other solace none was near, Saving to moan and make complaint All day and night, or else to hear Some dolorous deed of monk or saint, Some dull and hideous litany. So did this lady live forlorn A weary space of weary years; And day to night and night to morn No solace brought, save fruitless tears, And a new fever of desire Like to a famine at the heart For death, or with some deadly fire To burn the fair and youthful part From the sick life: yea, there was given No liberty in any wise, Saving to pasture her faint eyes Upon a blue sweet space in heaven. Now all the tender things create In earth and heaven did surely ache Unceasingly for her sweet sake, And pined for pity of her fate; Yea, for the sun wept tears of amber; And, stealing silently about The shrouded lands, the stars did stain Pure silver tears upon the plain; And every night the moon did clamber Up the steep dark, and o'er her chamber Hung, like a great breast lolling out, Heavy with pity of her pain. Sometimes, in the long solitude, Her thoughts would weary out their wings, Despairing of the thing pursued, And turn their fruitless flutterings Back to her bosom void: aghast With dreaming, sometimes, they traversed Strange wastes where, touching mystic springs, They gathered timorous forecast Of futures; sometimes they rehearsed Sad echoes of the vain sweet past. Most when the sun was nigh its setting And all the distant lands lay bright, She would beguile her soul, forgetting Its irremediable plight With sorrow, hour after hour Striving to reach some distant strain Of horns, or see some goodly sight Of hounds and men, or fill again Her life with perfume of some flower. Until one day—one summer day, When birds were singing blithe and loud In all the world, and not a cloud Was anywhere in heaven: O day Most sweet—most sorrowful! she lay Half swooned upon her bed, and heard The music under distant trees, And the close pants of life that stirred Around her prison, and the breeze Making a long sweet sigh for pleasure, And such a low and tender measure In all the pulses of the air, That she most bitterly at heart Strove to be choked with her despair— To be quite broken with some sigh— And lay quite still and would not part Her eyes dull lids, but longed to die, Beseeching God the time were nigh. And when the cold and withered maid Came to her couch, and, in harsh tone, Bade her to rise and be arrayed, She feigned great weariness and prayed She might be left all day alone; Then lay and kept her eyes quite closed, And spake not, feigning she reposed; Till, with no tender uttering Or pity for her ill, the crone Departing, fell to muttering Her crabbed litanies alone. Then to her thoughts free way she gave And did devote herself to die. And with full yearning did apply Her prayers to God; who—all to save Her heart—for pity that not yet Her time was come to die,—instead, Gave her in deep sleep to forget Her sorrow, dreaming she was dead And lying happy in her grave,— Feeling that little sighs did crave To have her spirit back again, And all as though a hand were fain, Parting leaves here and there, to stir With tremulous fingers seeking her: Yea, feeling still the constant wane Of all her sickness and life-pain, And how the angels, while she slept, For her continual healing, wept Such tears as touched her night and day, Washing her body all away. But, while she lay and was at rest, Dreaming this dream that she was dead, The sweet contagion of her spread Sweet fever in the airs at play And pasture on her brow and breast; Yearning through all that summer day Soft summer longings to allay In little ineffectual sips; Till, chafing for perpetual thirst The coverlet, they made a way, To ravish with their sudden lips Her luscious limbs, and with the burst Half waking her, she did behold What luxury and gracious mould Of breast she had; what pure expanse And most serene exuberance Of limb, which languor of her mood In all its fairness did enhance; And how the slowly blushing blood Lay in a sweet voluptuous waste Throughout her body wan and chaste, Or, wayward, with inconstant flow Made blue tracks wantonly, to ooze Adown each perfect limb, and lose In such delicious wastes of snow Its purple life. Yea, she did gaze, Still steeped in trance, and with half haze About her, till a weary tide —With slow recurrence brought again Her conscious life, and sad amaze Flooded her heart to see belied The dream of death: O she was fain To dream it back; but with her eyes She read how little word of Death Was written in her, and grew wise —She thought—of some hard bitter will Of God to her, that, not until Some true embrace, some fruitful breath Of love were come upon her breast, Would he take ransom for her death, To let her die and be at rest. Then—while her memory confest How she had heard the minstrels tell That many a lady, so opprest As she was, had been holpen well, By miracle of God or man, To solve her fate; and she began To commune how, if she were pure And altogether good in thought, Such saving wonder might be wrought For her,—that hour it did befall That a vast rush of wing was heard, And the great shadow of a bird Came darkly over couch and wall. And all before her heart, for fear What sudden omen might be near, Quicker beat thrice, there came, with noise Of clashed plumes entering on poise Of pinions sure, a falcon; fine His mien and cresting; wholly keen His gaze; all noble in the line Of the straight sunbeams he was seen, Fierce and without constraint or fault Of wing, to enter straight, nor halt Till forward pouncing, with a sound His talons clashed like clang of steel Sudden flung down, or spurrèd heel From stirrup lighting on the ground. Then, seeking, breathless at her heart, Some imminent future, she apart Held her white lips; and, all aghast, Beheld at length how, from the cast Constraint of plume and talon, rose The spirit of a noble knight, Perfect in bearing and bedight With goodly armature and close Raiment of mail. And soon the light Fell from his eyes and with a flame Touched her heart's snow: pleading he came, And showed with what surpassing power Of saintly labours he had earned Of God this thing for which he yearned; That he might come to her, what hour Her own heart, so betrayed, should crave And cry out for its sweet redress Of fate, and that she too might have Love for her love. Then, with a vow, His faith in God he did confess With all religion; and, to ease In all things to the uttermost Her soul, he prayed that God would show Some perfect token of His peace: So, at his prayer, the blessèd Host Was presently made manifest Miraculously, to attest Him pure, and that he had God's peace. But, when this holy thing was done, She made no further doubt, nor strove Longer to stay her heart from love; But vowed that she would cleave alone To this God gave her to redress Her long restraint and barrenness, And all the purpose of her years And faith so long betrayed to tears. Thereat her heart was wholly freed; And, quickened straight in all its seed With love's full tender lavishment, Most rapturous fulfilment bore; Yea, from recesses at its core, Gushed forth, and sudden ravishment In all her body showering, Made sweet amends for the long drouth: As doth some tardy luscious growth Forced sudden into flowering By late relenting of the South. So, for a while, those lovers lay Revelling in a sweet excess Of restless rapture—lovers' way Limb over limb; content to press Each other's speechless lips, or twine Each other's arms in listless play, Or feed to a soft weariness Each other's look,—then to combine The fainting breath in a low sigh, And swoon asleep and think to die At once so blessedly; but pine Full soon to ravish with new strength Each other's lips and looks,—at length Insatiate. It was a pain To lose each moment, though there grew Some further bliss; it was a pain —Though perfectly her lover knew His mistress' every tint and mood Or flush that in her face could linger, —Knew well, oft tenderly retraced With rapturous and erring finger, All fair ways fretted by the blood And every dimple of her waist— It was a pain one bliss to lose Changing it for another bliss; It was a pain one kiss to lose, Yea, one kiss for another kiss. So they prolonged their sweet enlacement Till there was nothing left of day; And the faint glimmer of the room, Or a most scarce uncertain ray From distant stars over the casement Lit them each other's looks; and gloom Was shed on them; but all their pleasure Sufficed them still, with soft delay, To stay their hearts, and, at love's leisure, To heap them up great store and treasure Out of each other's look and way, Savour of lips, and voice, and aught Of fair remainder for support And solace in long hours of blight, Long seedless fruitless hours unfraught With any comfortable sight Or touch of love: and when, compelled At length, O miserably they quelled Their rich souls, sundering them unquenched, Most cruel each from other wrenched Some uncompleted bliss. Alas, poor Bertha could not keep Dissembled quite her change at heart, And that she did not pine or weep Or languish more; she could not part At sudden will from all the bliss That lingered in her; nor efface The dimple that full many a kiss Left on her features or her brow Too plainly, and in many a place Upon her breast conceived of snow. She could not quite disarm or tame Her lips great fervour to deliver Their burden of her lover's name, Nor with whole patience sit and sever Her thoughts from him, whene'er the dame Plied her with long constraint or task Of prayer: but she was fain for ever In one of his known looks to bask Silent; and with no perfect mask Of meekness could perform her task, Keeping at fast her utmost soul And longing. And, whene'er an hour Laxed that most rigorous control, She would array the passionate power Of all her heart, beseeching him, Through the long silence with his name Grown to a murmur reaching him Perpetual: anon he came Prone to her summons. Long, with pain Her tyrants, jealous, sought to guess What sort of ravishment could bless Her life so secretly; but vain Was all their striving; and, with vile Mistrust and most unquiet wonder They marked her; ceasing not to ponder Divers deceits. But, all the while, The woman set herself with guile To reach and ravel out the thing. And this way: On one morn, deceived, Bertha too easily believed Her feigned departure, hastening Her heart, scarce patient to abide The door's pretended fastening, And the safe sound of steps outside Descending; then with rapturous start Let loose her longing, flinging wide The casement; and from all her heart In mad foretaste precipitate Summoned her Love. And when they knew, Embraced again, no thought of hate And guile so near, but did renew The long drained sources of their bliss The woman lurked; and, not to miss Her treacherous purposes, kept still, Yea, saw and listened and kept still, Stemming her vengeance, more to fill The craving after, and make wise Her way thereto; so she discerned The mystic stratagem and guise With aid of which that lover earned His entry arduous; and perceived Completely all; then, vowing harm With cold and grave intent, she gave Her brother tidings; and conceived With him how best, and with what arm Or ambush they should work to have Their vengeance. So, at length, they made A weapon many-bladed, fell And harsh with clustered points, most keen And deadly: this—for trap, was laid Most deftly, and its purpose well Assured, with some sufficient screen, Upon the window's ledge,—that none Entering could escape or foil Death manifold. The thing was done At night; and, long ere dawn, the toil Was perfect. Then, without recoil Of conscience, they arose and spared No moment; but, with great turmoil, And marshalling sounds of men and mail Rife for some service, and such tale Fitly conceived, they quite ensnared Their captive—saying her lord was prest To absence on a distant guest Of warfare. So the thing prepared Fell out; that when the distant arms And clarions of the troop departing Sent no more sound, and all alarms Were far away a space, so spared Favoring of heaven it seemed,—upstarting, No further tolerant of the load Of longing, she straightway unbound Her heart, most urgently to goad The lagging silence to create Some presence or fulfilling sound, For the known bliss importunate. Then came the dawn with soft delays Of light, and rapturous restraint Reluctant; with flushed feet in ways Voluptuous; full of rich reserve For passionate noons, the golden taint Revealing gradual: then elate, Unerring, on surpassing curve Of faultless wing, with furious aim And constant zest, the falcon came Impetuous; and all his fate, Wretched and sweet of life and heart, Wretched and sweet, delicious part Of love and penalty most dread Relentless drew him on. And she Instant her passionate purpose sped, Redoubling urgent the decree With all her heart's might; feeling too Him all inevitable through The distance reach her with a keen Response of coming; feeling too In all the harassed air between The close beats of his wings; and still The latest moment of reprieve Bearing most niggardly; until, With harsh plunge and uncertain heave Of weak wings faltering to compel His faint course, seeking her, he fell Wounded of life; and sank and shed His gentle blood upon the bed. A little while he baffled Death; And with incessant fluttering Contended for some sweet delay, That he might hold enough of breath For one last passionate uttering; But life fell fast within him, yea, So that he made a piteous plead Of looks all silently instead, And panted all his heart away. But she, in uttermost amaze Painfully held was still intent To see her lover's image raise Its stained and dabbled mask; and couched Expectant, with whole tortures pent At heart a moment's respite, touched Her full woe tenderly;—nay bent Against it her full will and strength Of soul resisting: but at length It broke her quite; and she confessed The silence and the grey cold hue, And gathering death all wan and blue That filmed the eye; anon, she pressed Her bosom to that spoil of love, That bitter wreck of all her love. But lo, once more she was aware Of something pleading sick and faint About her heart,—a speechless plaint Broken like sighs upon the air Stirring her sorely; then a hand Was laid upon her heart and wielded Mysteriously her will; she planned Nor purposed any course, but yielded Meekly as in a dream. And so She rose, all inwardly impressed, And, from the cell with little toil Released, she lingered not to go; Soon the cold corridors confessed, Whispering with a frozen wind, Her steps: but her swift footsteps foil Their echoes; and the conscious floors Betray not, stricken dumb behind Her feet; anon, the dismal doors, Touched with her passionate touch, recoil, Melted in all their irksome mail Of bolts and iron frowns—recoil Setting her free; and as they part There cometh in a long low wail —Half of the wind, and at her heart The hand more heavy doth prevail. And when before the moat she came, The bridge stood ready in her way, As though some traveller that day Had passed quite recent; and the same She thought, where on the fields she found A narrow footway, like a stain Of steps all recent on the ground. Then through lands many, green and fair, Woodlands and many a weary plain And rugged mountain land, a league Full hardily she fled; despair Great in her heart against fatigue. And ere the day yet threatened night, She found a city silent and wide, Silent and wide and full of light. None stirred in all the street beside Herself. She entered by the gate A palace. There with barren state The voiceless walls were tapestried Damask and purple; sullen pride Of pillar frowned; and shapes of stone Stood ponderous, and all hard-eyed Beheld her; and a long low moan The waste winds made in this great dwelling Desolate. Yet, her soul compelling, No fear turned back her feet; but loud The hollow place with harsh repeat Bore witness of her ardent feet,— Until she found a chamber proud With pomp of funeral array: A gilded gloom stupendous lay Upon the walls; and a great shroud In midst upon a regal bier, With a vast pall upon the ground Wide trailed: but on that bier she found Her lover. Still he seemed but near His death; and told her how his soul Choked with the slaughtered life, too weak Had struggled for a voice to speak Farewell, in words that should console Her sorrow; and at length, bound back To fill its twofold death, had yearned And waited, praying God to slack His extreme hand, and sorely earned Prolonging death this sweet reprieve. Anon, he bade her to believe A piteous thing; praying thereby That she would heal her heart, to grieve Not too devotedly; and saying, That surely he should never die Quite to his inmost heart; but, staying Deep in his grave her sorrow too Would most torment him, throbbing through His sleep and evermore delaying His peace and keeping wide the wounds; Yea, with sick longing to regain Sweet pasts unfinished, full of sounds Fallen and broken, would reproach Pure present peace; bringing again The faded endings of old pain And crushed world-sweetness to encroach In the old hollows of the heart; So still some bitterness should burn And burn, and he should never earn His rest of God; ay, never part Wholly from this great slough of life And love turned to this dust, this death Charred and yet chafing. Never life Shall light again this dust he said; Nor can love ever with a breath Touch me down there where I am laid: O there shall be a load for this Upon the very heart of fate; And something too shall be to miss From God's full purposes of bliss And God Himself be all too late To mend or mourn; for mine shall be In earth a place most desolate, Where never flower shall grow nor tree Hang with sweet shadow,—desolate, But very peaceful for a grave, And very fitting so for me. —Ah, who can say if love may have Some heaven yet,—some second earth, Some long revenge for this ill life, Some sort of death redeeming birth? —Ah, who can say?—I feel a strife Of hands about my heart; I thrill Beneath the shadows of new fates That cover me; I have a chill Like death; and yet some touch creates A warmth like life too; I have sights Most hard, of lights mingling with lights; And yet, methinks, I feel but sleep,— Smell a faint fragrance of dead leaves, Or of the dust that I shall heap About my heart: my heart believes No more—no more than this, and cleaves O dying, on thy hands my Love! It was the midnight. His last look Was fading in the fervid gloom; And many an aching echo shook The pauses, moving like a moan; And dying words' sad monotone Lasted about the silent room. She was alone with all her doom; But knew not yet she was alone; For all these things, the looks, the words, Thronged at her heart, foiling dim swords That stood inevitable, keeping A short space charmed with the slow heaping Of thought, rich with each lingering sound,— Ere all fell sickened into weeping And the whole bitterness were found. But soon, out of the distant street Came murmurs; and the growing hiss Of half-hushed voices; and a beat Of steps and steps of other men; And fate fell on her heart; and then With all her load of broken bliss, She fled to seek out some retreat In all-abiding night. The moon Began all wearily to wane: And she—she lay upon the plain Weary, and fell into a swoon; Then heard most dismally the toll Of death-bells, heavy with the soul Of him her lover; and his doom Throbbing across the muffling gloom Attained her to the very heart; And gradual there, in every part, Grew forth the desolating root Of sorrow, piercing shoot by shoot The soft soil where a rose's stain Lay recent; and, where any bliss Had been, wherever love had lain, Grew now some seed and fruit of pain Rich with the rotting memories. Then a new wonder, like a thought Strove with the death in her, and wrought With inward accent promising Half-sweet, an unimagined thing. And at last from the bitter ground She rose, and forward through the night Her feet miraculously found A constant guidance, and a might To go and meet that future fate, Which yet in such strange manner bound Her soul to live indeed and wait. If any saw her in her way, Passing along the meadows gray With deep unlifted shrouding still, Surely they knew not; but beheld Amazed and with a doubtful thrill: And, by her shining robe that trailed Through the dank night; and by the sheen Of all her raiment, and hair seen Wondrous, unsoiled, as though availed No longer spell of day or night On her; and by the rustlings light That startled the deep earthly sleep Along the meadows in her path; —Surely she seemed to them some wraith Walking the world on straight intent Of unaccomplished doom, or sent To work the purposes of God, Whereof no man the knowledge hath. So was there none in all her way To shame her steps; and ere the day Betrayed, her feet returning trode The marble floor of her own hall And silent passage ancestral Of that cold place where she abode. She might not speak at all nor weep; But such great mystery did cling Upon her face, that seemed to keep Knowledge of some most holy thing, No man found ways to try her more With base reproof or questioning. And lo, in due time, and before Her grief of secret thought was done, With many an inward holy thrill And wondrous sign of grace begun Already plain, God did fulfil His miracle of love ere long; So that she bore a goodly Son; And lying showed each evil tongue That spoke her barren of His grace. Her child—he had a wondrous face, In which was written many a dear And lovely word with God's hand clear, In lineament that she could trace More and more through the smiling grace, To many a noble thing foretold Of help and blessedness to her: So she would read, for days and days, His holy smiling that consoled Her heart, and bade her thoughts to err Free in all sweet and hopeful ways: And afterward there grew much praise Of him, for he is named in lays Yvenec, the Deliverer.</field>
   </doc>
</add>