<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Akenside, Mark, 1721-1770</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Akenside, Mark, 1721-1770</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">akenside mark 1721 1770</field>
      <field name="author_text">Akenside, Mark, 1721-1770</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1850's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_2.1509.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">1855</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:465546</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The poetical works</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The poetical works</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poetical works</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poetical works</field>
      <field name="title_text">The poetical works</field>
      <field name="year_display">1855</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1855</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1855</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465546&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465546&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Akenside, Mark, 1721-1770&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;akenside mark 1721 1770&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The poetical works&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poetical works&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1855&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1855&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Akenside, Mark&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1721&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1770&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The poetical works&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;New York&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;George Routledge and Co.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1855&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0017&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;xl, 234, 118 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The poetical works&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 64 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only poems by Akenside included; verse reproduced elsewhere in The English Poetry Full-text Database omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ODES ON SEVERAL SUBJECTS. IN TWO BOOKS. BOOK I. ODE I. PREFACE. I On yonder verdant hillock laid, Where oaks and elms, a friendly shade, O'erlook the falling stream, O master of the Latin lyre, Awhile with thee will I retire From summer's noontide beam. II And lo, within my lonely bower, The industrious bee from many a flower Collects her balmy dews: “For me,” she sings, “the gems are born, For me their silken robe adorn, Their fragrant breath diffuse.” III Sweet murmurer! may no rude storm This hospitable scene deform, Nor check thy gladsome toils; Still may the buds unsullied spring, Still showers and sunshine court thy wing To these ambrosial spoils. IV Nor shall my Muse hereafter fail Her fellow labourer thee to hail; And lucky be the strains! For long ago did Nature frame Your seasons and your arts the same, Your pleasures and your pains. V Like thee, in lowly, sylvan scenes, On river banks and flowery greens My Muse delighted plays; Nor through the desert of the air, Though swans or eagles triumph there, With fond ambition strays. VI Nor where the boding raven chaunts, Nor near the owl's unhallow'd haunts Will she her cares employ; But flies from ruins and from tombs, From Superstition's horrid glooms, To day-light and to joy. VII Nor will she tempt the barren waste; Nor deigns the lurking strength to taste Of any noxious thing; But leaves with scorn to Envy's use The insipid nightshade's baneful juice, The nettle's sordid sting. VIII From all which Nature fairest knows, The vernal blooms, the summer rose, She draws her blameless wealth: And, when the generous task is done, She consecrates a double boon, To Pleasure and to Health. ODE XVI. TO CALEB HARDINGE, M.D. I With sordid floods the wintry Urn Hath stain'd fair Richmond's level green: Her naked hill the Dryads mourn, No longer a poetic scene. No longer there thy raptur'd eye The beauteous forms of earth or sky Surveys, as in their Author's mind: And London shelters from the year Those whom thy social hours to share The Attic Muse design'd. II From Hampstead's airy summit me Her guest the city shall behold, What day the people's stern decree To unbelieving kings is told, When common men (the dread of fame) Adjudg'd as one of evil name, Before the sun, the anointed head. Then seek thou too the pious town, With no unworthy cares to crown That evening's awful shade. III Deem not I call thee to deplore The sacred martyr of the day, By fast and penitential lore To purge our ancient guilt away. For this, on humble faith I rest That still our advocate, the priest, From heavenly wrath will save the land: Nor ask what rites our pardon gain, Nor how his potent sounds restrain The thunderer's lifted hand. IV No, Hardinge: peace to church and state! That evening, let the Muse give law: While I anew the theme relate Which my first youth enamour'd saw. Then will I oft explore thy thought, What to reject which Locke hath taught, What to pursue in Virgil's lay: Till hope ascends to loftiest things, Nor envies demagogues or kings Their frail and vulgar sway. V O vers'd in all the human frame, Lead thou where'er my labour lies, And English fancy's eager flame To Grecian purity chastise: While hand in hand, at Wisdom's shrine, Beauty with truth I strive to join, And grave assent with glad applause; To paint the story of the soul, And Plato's visions to control By Verulamian laws. BOOK II. ODE XIV. THE COMPLAINT. I Away! away! Tempt me no more, insidious love: Thy soothing sway Long did my youthful bosom prove: At length thy treason is discern'd, At length some dear-bought caution earn'd: Away! nor hope my riper age to move. II I know, I see Her merit. Needs it now be shown, Alas, to me? How often, to myself unknown, The graceful, gentle, virtuous maid Have I admir'd! How often said, What joy to call a heart like hers one's own! III But, flattering god, O squanderer of content and ease, In thy abode Will care's rude lesson learn to please? O say, deceiver, hast thou won Proud Fortune to attend thy throne, Or plac'd thy friends above her stern decrees? THE VIRTUOSO; IN IMITATION OF SPENSER'S STYLE AND STANZA. “? Videmus Nugari solitos.” Persius. The Latin inscription (Poem V) has been omitted. Whilom by silver Thames's gentle stream, In London town there dwelt a subtile wight; A wight of mickle wealth, and mickle fame, Book-learn'd and quaint: a Virtuoso hight. Uncommon things, and rare, were his delight; From musings deep his brain ne'er gotten ease, Nor ceased he from study, day or night; Until (advancing onward by degrees) He knew whatever breeds on earth, or air, or seas. He many a creature did anatomize, Almost unpeopling water, air, and land; Beasts, fishes, birds, snails, caterpillars, flies, Were laid full low by his relentless hand, That oft with gory crimson was distain'd: He many a dog destroy'd, and many a cat; Of fleas his bed, of frogs the marshes drain'd, Could tellen if a mite were lean or fat, And read a lecture o'er the entrails of a gnat. He knew the various modes of ancient times, Their arts and fashions of each different guise, Their weddings, funerals, punishments for crimes, Their strength, their learning eke, and rarities; Of old habiliments, each sort and size, Male, female, high and low, to him were known; Each gladiator-dress, and stage disguise; With learned, clerkly phrase he could have shown How the Greek tunic differ'd from the Roman gown. A curious medallist, I wot, he was, And boasted many a course of ancient coin; Well as his wife's he knewen every face, From Julius Cæsar down to Constantine: For some rare sculpture he would oft ypine, (As green-sick damosels for husbands do;) And when obtained, with enraptur'd eyne, He'd run it o'er and o'er with greedy view, And look, and look again, as he would look it thro'. His rich museum, of dimensions fair, With goods that spoke the owner's mind was fraught: Things ancient, curious, value-worth, and rare, From sea and land, from Greece and Rome were brought Which he with mighty sums of gold had bought: On these all tides with joyous eyes he por'd; And, sooth to say, himself he greater thought, When he beheld his cabinets thus stor'd, Than if he'd been of Albion's wealthy cities lord. Here in a corner stood a rich 'scrutoire, With many a curiosity replete; In seemly order furnished every drawer, Products of art or nature as was meet; Air-pumps and prisms were plac'd beneath his feet, A Memphian mummy-king hung o'er his head; Here phials with live insects small and great, There stood a tripod of the Pythian maid; Above, a crocodile diffus'd a grateful shade. Fast by the window did a table stand, Where hodiern and antique rarities, From Egypt, Greece, and Rome, from sea and land, Were thick-besprent of every sort and size: Here a Bahaman-spider's carcass lies, There a dire serpent's golden skin doth shine: Here Indian feathers, fruits, and glittering flies; There gums and amber found beneath the line, The beak of Ibis here, and there an Antonine. Close at his back, or whispering in his ear, There stood a spright ycleped Phantasy; Which, wheresoe'er he went, was always near: Her look was wild, and roving was her eye; Her hair was clad with flowers of every dye; Her glistering robes were of more various hue, Than the fair bow that paints the clouded sky, Or all the spangled drops of morning dew; Their colour changing still at every different view. Yet in this shape all tydes she did not stay, Various as the chameleon that she bore: Now a grand monarch with a crown of hay, Now mendicant in silks and golden ore: A statesman now, equipp'd to chase the boar, Or cowled monk, lean, feeble, and unfed; A clown-like lord, or swain of courtly lore; Now scribbling dunce in sacred laurel clad, Or papal father now, in homely weeds array'd. The wight whose brain this phantom's power doth fill, On whom she doth with constant care attend, Will for a dreadful giant take a mill, Or a grand palace in a hogsty find: (From her dire influence me may Heaven defend!) All things with vitiated sight he spies: Neglects his family, forgets his friend, Seeks painted trifles and fantastic toys, And eagerly pursues imaginary joys. AMBITION AND CONTENT. A FABLE. “Optat quietem.” —Hor. While yet the world was young, and men were few, Nor lurking fraud, nor tyrant rapine knew, In virtue rude, the gaudy arts they scorn'd, Which, virtue lost, degenerate times adorn'd: No sumptuous fabrics yet were seen to rise, Nor gushing fountains taught to invade the skies; With nature, art had not begun the strife, Nor swelling marble rose to mimic life; No pencil yet had learn'd to express the fair; The bounteous earth was all their homely care. Then did Content exert her genial sway, And taught the peaceful world her power to obey; Content, a female of celestial race, Bright and complete in each celestial grace. Serenely fair she was, as rising day, And brighter than the sun's meridian ray; Joy of all hearts, delight of every eye, Nor grief, nor pain appear'd when she was by; Her presence from the wretched banish'd care, Dispers'd the swelling sigh, and stopt the falling tear. Long did the nymph her regal state maintain, As long mankind were blest beneath her reign; Till dire Ambition, hellish fiend, arose, To plague the world, and banish man's repose: A monster sprung from that rebellious crew, Which mighty Jove's Phlegræan thunder slew. Resolv'd to dispossess the royal fair, On all her friends he threaten'd open war: Fond of the novelty, vain, fickle man, In crowds to his infernal standard ran; And the weak maid, defenceless left alone, To avoid his rage, was forc'd to quit the throne. It chanc'd as wandering through the fields she stray'd, Forsook of all, and destitute of aid, Upon a rising mountain's flowery side A pleasant cottage, roof'd with turf, she spied: Fast by a gloomy, venerable wood Of shady planes, and ancient oaks, it stood. Around a various prospect charm'd the sight; Here waving harvests clad the fields with white; Here a rough shaggy rock the clouds did pierce, From which a torrent rush'd with rapid force; Here mountain-woods diffus'd a dusky shade; Here flocks and herds in flowery valleys play'd, While o'er the matted grass the liquid crystal stray'd. In this sweet place there dwelt a cheerful pair, Though bent beneath the weight of many a year; Who wisely flying public noise and strife, In this obscure retreat had pass'd their life; The husband Industry was call'd, Frugality the wife. With tenderest Friendship mutually blest, No household jars had e'er disturb'd their rest. A numerous offspring grac'd their homely board, That still with Nature's simple gifts was stor'd. The father rural business only knew; The sons the same delightful art pursue: An only daughter, as a goddess fair, Above the rest was the fond mother's care; Plenty; the brightest nymph of all the plain, Each heart's delight, ador'd by every swain. Soon as Content this charming scene espied, Joyful within herself the goddess cried; “This happy sight my drooping heart doth raise; The gods, I hope, will grant me gentler days: When with prosperity my life was blest, In yonder house I've been a welcome guest: There now, perhaps, I may protection find; For royalty is banish'd from my mind; I'll thither haste: how happy should I be, If such a refuge were reserv'd for me!” Thus spoke the fair; and straight she bent her way To the tall mountain, where the cottage lay: Arriv'd she makes her chang'd condition known; Tells how the rebels drove her from the throne; What painful, dreary wilds she'd wander'd o'er; And shelter from the tyrant doth implore. The faithful, aged pair at once were seiz'd With joy and grief, at once were pain'd and pleas'd; Grief for their banish'd queen their hearts possest, And joy succeeded for their future guest; “And if you'll deign, bright goddess, here to dwell, And with your presence grace our humble cell, Whate'er the gods have given with bounteous hand, Our harvests, fields and flocks, our all command.” Meantime, Ambition, on his rival's flight, Sole lord of man, attain'd his wish's height; Of all dependence on his subjects eas'd, He rag'd without a curb, and did whate'er he pleas'd: As some wild flame, driven on by furious winds, Wide spreads destruction, nor resistance finds; So rush'd the fiend destructive o'er the plain, Defac'd the labours of the industrious swain; Polluted every stream with human gore, And scatter'd plagues and death from shore to shore. Great Jove beheld it from the Olympian towers, Where sate assembled all the heavenly powers; Then with a nod that shook the empyrean throne, Thus the Saturnian thunderer begun: “You see, immortal inmates of the skies, How this vile wretch almighty power defies; His daring crimes, the blood which he has spilt, Demand a torment equal to his guilt. Then, Cyprian goddess, let thy mighty boy Swift to the tyrant's guilty palace fly; There let him choose his sharpest, hottest dart, And with his former rival wound his heart. And thou, my son, (the god to Hermes said) Snatch up thy wand, and plume thy heels and head; Dart through the yielding air with all thy force, And down to Pluto's realms direct thy course; There rouse Oblivion from her sable cave, Where dull she sits by Lethe's sluggish wave; Command her to secure the sacred bound, Where lives Content retir'd, and all around Diffuse the deepest glooms of Stygian night, And screen the virgin from the tyrant's sight; That the vain purpose of his life may try Still to explore, what still eludes his eye.” He spoke; loud praises shake the bright abode, And all applaud the justice of the god. THE POET —A RHAPSODY. Of all the various lots around the ball, Which fate to man distributes, absolute; Avert, ye gods! that of the Muse's son, Curs'd with dire poverty! poor hungry wretch! What shall he do for life? he cannot work With manual labour: shall those sacred hands, That brought the counsels of the gods to light; Shall that inspired tongue, which every Muse Has touch'd divine, to charm the sons of men: These hallow'd organs! these! be prostitute To the vile service of some fool in power, All his behests submissive to perform, Howe'er to him ingrateful? Oh! he scorns The ignoble thought; with generous disdain, More eligible deeming it to starve, Like his fam'd ancestors renown'd in verse, Than poorly bend to be another's slave,— Than feed and fatten in obscurity. —These are his firm resolves, which fate, nor time, Nor poverty can shake. Exalted high In garret vile he lives; with remnants hung Of tapestry. But oh! precarious state Of this vain transient world! all powerful time, What dost thou not subdue? See what a chasm Gapes wide, tremendous! see where Saul, enrag'd, High on his throne, encompass'd by his guards, With levell'd spear, and arm extended, sits, Ready to pierce old Jesse's valiant son, Spoil'd of his nose!—around in tottering ranks, On shelves pulverulent, majestic stands His library; in ragged plight, and old; Replete with many a load of criticism, Elaborate products of the midnight toil Of Belgian brains; snatch'd from the deadly hands Of murderous grocer, or the careful wight, Who vends the plant, that clads the happy shore Of Indian Patomack; which citizens In balmy fumes exhale, when, o'er a pot Of sage-inspiring coffee, they dispose Of kings and crowns, and settle Europe's fate. Elsewhere the dome is fill'd with various heaps Of old domestic lumber: that huge chair Has seen six monarchs fill the British throne: Here a broad massy table stands, o'erspread With ink and pens, and scrolls replete with rhyme: Chests, stools, old razors, fractur'd jars, half full Of muddy Zythum, sour and spiritless: Fragments of verse, hose, sandals, utensils Of various fashion, and of various use, With friendly influence hide the sable floor. This is the bard's museum, this the fane To Phœbus sacred, and the Aonian maids: But oh! it stabs his heart, that niggard fate To him in such small measure should dispense Her better gifts: to him! whose generous soul Could relish, with as fine an elegance, The golden joys of grandeur, and of wealth; He who could tyrannize o'er menial slaves, Or swell beneath a coronet of state, Or grace a gilded chariot with a mien, Grand as the haughtiest Timon of them all. But 'tis in vain to rave at destiny, Here he must rest, and brook the best he can, To live remote from grandeur, learning, wit: Immur'd amongst th' 'ignoble, vulgar herd, Of lowest intellect; whose stupid souls But half inform their bodies; brains of lead And tongues of thunder; whose insensate breasts Ne'er felt the rapturous, soul-entrancing fire Of the celestial Muse; whose savage ears Ne'er heard the sacred rules, nor even the names Of the Venusian bard, or critic sage Full-fam'd of Stagyra: whose clamorous tongues Stun the tormented ear with colloquy, Vociferate, trivial, or impertinent; Replete with boorish scandal; yet, alas! This, this! he must endure, or muse alone, Pensive and moping o'er the stubborn rhyme, Or line imperfect—No! the door is free, And calls him to evade their deafening clang, By private ambulation;—'tis resolved: Off from his waist he throws the tatter'd gown, Beheld with indignation; and unloads His pericranium of the weighty cap, With sweat and grease discolour'd: then explores The spacious chest, and from its hollow womb Draws his best robe, yet not from tincture free Of age's reverend russet, scant and bare; Then down his meagre visage waving flows The shadowy peruke; crown'd with gummy hat, Clean brush'd; a cane supports him. Thus equipp'd He sallies forth; swift traverses the streets, And seeks the lonely walk. “Hail sylvan scenes! Ye groves, ye valleys, ye meand'ring brooks, Admit me to your joys,” in rapturous phrase, Loud he exclaims; while with the inspiring Muse His bosom labours; and all other thoughts, Pleasure and wealth, and poverty itself, Before her influence vanish. Rapt in thought, Fancy presents before his ravished eyes Distant posterity, upon his page With transport dwelling; while bright Learning's sons, That ages hence must tread this earthly ball, Indignant, seem to curse the thankless age, That starv'd such merit. Meantime, swallow'd up In meditation deep, he wanders on, Unweeting of his way.—But ah! he starts! With sudden fright! his glaring eye-balls roll, Pale turn his cheeks, and shake his loosen'd joints; His cogitations vanish into air, Like painted bubbles, or a morning dream. Behold the cause! see! through the opening glade, With rosy visage, and abdomen grand, A cit, a dun!—As in Apulia's wilds, Or where the Thracian Hebrus rolls his wave, A heedless kid, disportive, roves around, Unheeding, till upon the hideous cave Of the dire wolf she treads; half-dead she views His bloodshot eye-balls, and his dreadful fangs, And swift as Eurus from the monster flies: So fares the trembling bard; amaz'd he turns, Scarce by his legs upborne; yet fear supplies The place of strength; straight home he bends his course, Nor looks behind him till he safe regain His faithful citadel; there spent, fatigu'd, He lays him down to ease his heaving lungs, Quaking, and of his safety scarce convinc'd. Soon as the panic leaves his panting breast, Down to the Muse's sacred rites he sits, Volumes pil'd round him; see! upon his brow Perplex'd anxiety; and struggling thought, Painful as female throes: whether the bard Display the deeds of heroes; or the fall Of vice, in lay dramatic; or expand The lyric wing; or in elegiac strains Lament the fair; or lash the stubborn age With laughing satire; or in rural scenes With shepherds sport; or rack his hard-bound brains For the unexpected turn. Arachne so, In dusty kitchen corner, from her bowels Spins the fine web; but spins with better fate, Than the poor bard: she! caitiff! spreads her snares, And with their aid enjoys luxurious life, Bloated with fat of insects, flesh'd in blood: He! hard, hard lot! for all his toil and care, And painful watchings, scarce protracts awhile His meagre, hungry days! ungrateful world! If with his drama he adorn the stage, No worth-discerning concourse pays the charge, Or of the orchestra, or the enlightening torch. He who supports the luxury and pride Of craving Lais; he! whose carnage fills Dogs, eagles, lions; has not yet enough, Wherewith to satisfy the greedier maw Of that most ravenous, that devouring beast, Yclep'd a Poet. What new Halifax, What Somers, or what Dorset canst thou find, Thou hungry mortal? break, wretch, break thy quill, Blot out the studied image: to the flames Commit the Stagyrite: leave this thankless trade; Erect some pedling stall, with trinkets stock'd, There earn thy daily halfpence, nor again Trust the false Muse: so shall the cleanly meal Repel intruding hunger.—Oh! 'tis vain, The friendly admonition's all in vain: The scribbling itch has seiz'd him; he is lost To all advice, and starves for starving's sake. Thus sung the sportful Muse, in mirthful mood, Indulging gay the frolic vein of youth; But, oh! ye gods, avert th' impending stroke This luckless omen threatens! Hark! methinks I hear my better angel cry, “Retreat, Rash youth! in time retreat! let those poor bards, Who slighted all, all! for the flattering Muse, Yet curs'd with pining want, as landmarks stand, To warn thee from the service of the ingrate.” A BRITISH PHILIPPIC: OCCASIONED BY THE INSULTS OF THE SPANIARDS AND THE PRESENT PREPARATIONS FOR WAR. 1738. Whence this unwonted transport in my breast? Why glow my thoughts, and whither would the Muse Aspire with rapid wing? Her country's cause Demands her efforts: at that sacred call She summons all her ardour, throws aside The trembling lyre, and with the warrior's trump She means to thunder in each British ear; And if one spark of honour or of fame, Disdain of insult, dread of infamy, One thought of public virtue yet survive, She means to wake it, rouse the generous flame, With patriot zeal inspirit every breast, And fire each British heart with British wrongs. Alas the vain attempt! what influence now Can the Muse boast! or what attention now Is paid to fame or virtue? Where is now The British spirit, generous, warm, and brave, So frequent wont from tyranny and woe To free the suppliant nations? Where, indeed! If that protection, once to strangers given, Be now withheld from sons? Each nobler thought, That warm'd our sires, is lost and buried now In luxury and avarice. Baneful vice! How it unmans a nation! yet I'll try, I'll aim to shake this vile degenerate sloth; I'll dare to rouse Britannia's dreaming sons To fame, to virtue, and impart around A generous feeling of compatriot woes. Come then the various powers of forceful speech, All that can move, awaken, fire, transport! Come the bold ardour of the Theban bard! The arousing thunder of the patriot Greek! The soft persuasion of the Roman sage! Come all! and raise me to an equal height, A rapture worthy of my glorious cause! Lest my best efforts, failing, should debase The sacred theme; for with no common wing The Muse attempts to soar. Yet what need these? My country's fame, my free-born British heart, Shall be my best inspirers, raise my flight High as the Theban's pinion, and with more Than Greek or Roman flame exalt my soul. Oh! could I give the vast ideas birth Expressive of the thoughts that flame within, No more should lazy Luxury detain Our ardent youth; no more should Britain's sons Sit tamely passive by, and careless hear The prayers, sighs, groans, (immortal infamy!) Of fellow Britons, with oppression sunk, In bitterness of soul demanding aid, Calling on Britain, their dear native land, The land of Liberty; so greatly fam'd For just redress; the land so often dyed With her best blood, for that arousing cause, The freedom of her sons; those sons that now Far from the manly blessings of her sway, Drag the vile fetters of a Spanish lord. And dare they, dare the vanquish'd sons of Spain Enslave a Briton? Have they then forgot, So soon forgot, the great, the immortal day, When rescu'd Sicily with joy beheld The swift-wing'd thunder of the British arm Disperse their navies? when their coward bands Fled, like the raven from the bird of Jove, From swift impending vengeance fled in vain? Are these our lords? And can Britannia see Her foes oft vanquish'd, thus defy her power, Insult her standard, and enslave her sons, And not arise to justice? Did our sires, Unaw'd by chains, by exile, or by death, Preserve inviolate her guardian rights, To Britons ever sacred! that their sons Might give them up to Spaniards?—Turn your eyes, Turn ye degenerate, who with haughty boast Call yourselves Britons, to that dismal gloom, That dungeon dark and deep, where never thought Of joy or peace can enter; see the gates Harsh-creaking open; what a hideous void, Dark as the yawning grave! while still as death A frightful silence reigns. There on the ground Behold your brethren chain'd like beasts of prey: There mark your numerous glories, there behold The look that speaks unutterable woe; The mangled limb, the faint, the deathful eye, With famine sunk, the deep heart-bursting groan Suppress'd in silence; view the loathsome food, Refus'd by dogs, and oh! the stinging thought! View the dark Spaniard glorying in their wrongs, The deadly priest triumphant in their woes, And thundering worse damnation on their souls: While that pale form, in all the pangs of death, Too faint to speak, yet eloquent of all, His native British spirit yet untam'd, Raises his head; and with indignant frowns Of great defiance, and superior scorn, Looks up and dies.—Oh! I am all on fire! But let me spare the theme, lest future times Should blush to hear that either conquer'd Spain Durst offer Britain such outrageous wrong, Or Britain tamely bore it— Descend, ye guardian heroes of the land! Scourges of Spain, descend! Behold your sons; See! how they run the same heroic race, How prompt, how ardent in their country's cause, How greatly proud to assert their British blood, And in their deeds reflect their fathers' fame! Ah! would to heaven ye did not rather see How dead to virtue in the public cause, How cold, how careless, how to glory deaf, They shame your laurels, and belie their birth! Come, ye great spirits, Ca'ndish, Raleigh, Blake! And ye of latter name, your country's pride, Oh! come, disperse these lazy fumes of sloth, Teach British hearts with British fires to glow! In wakening whispers rouse our ardent youth, Blazon the triumphs of your better days, Paint all the glorious scenes of rightful war In all its splendours; to their swelling souls Say how ye bow'd th' insulting Spaniards' pride, Say how ye thunder'd o'er their prostrate heads, Say how ye broke their lines and fir'd their ports, Say how not death, in all its frightful shapes, Could damp your souls, or shake the great resolve For right and Britain: then display the joys The patriot's soul exalting, while he views Transported millions hail with loud acclaim The guardian of their civil, sacred rights. How greatly welcome to the virtuous man Is death for other's good! the radiant thoughts That beam celestial on his passing soul, Th' unfading crowns awaiting him above, Th' exalting plaudit of the Great Supreme, Who in his actions with complacence views His own reflected splendour; thence descend, Though to a lower, yet a nobler scene; Paint the just honours to his reliques paid, Show grateful millions weeping o'er his grave; While his fair fame in each progressive age For ever brightens; and the wise and good, Of every land, in universal choir, With richest incense of undying praise His urn encircle, to the wondering world His numerous triumphs blazon; while with awe, With filial reverence, in his steps they tread, And, copying every virtue, every fame, Transplant his glories into second life, And, with unsparing hand, make nations blest By his example. Vast, immense rewards! For all the turmoils which the virtuous mind Encounters here. Yet, Britons, are ye cold? Yet deaf to glory, virtue, and the call Of your poor injured countrymen? Ah! no: I see ye are not; every bosom glows With native greatness, and in all its state The British spirit rises: glorious change! Fame, virtue, freedom, welcome! O forgive The Muse, that ardent in her sacred cause, Your glory question'd; she beholds with joy, She owns, she triumphs in her wish'd mistake. See! from her sea-beat throne in awful march Britannia towers: upon her laurel crest The plumes majestic nod; behold she heaves Her guardian shield, and terrible in arms For battle shakes her adamantine spear: Loud at her foot the British lion roars, Frighting the nations; haughty Spain full soon Shall hear and tremble. Go then, Britons, forth, Your country's daring champions: tell your foes, Tell them in thunders o'er their prostrate land, You were not born for slaves: let all your deeds Show that the sons of those immortal men, The stars of shining story, are not slow In virtue's path to emulate their sires, T' assert their country's rights, avenge her sons, And hurl the bolts of justice on her foes. HYMN TO SCIENCE. ‘O Vitæ Philosophia Dux! O Virtutis indagatrix, expultrixque Vitiorum.— Tu Urbes peperisti; tu inventrix Legum, tu magistra Morum et Disciplinæ fuisti: Ad te confugimus, a te Opem petimus.” —Cic. Tusc. Quæst. Science! thou fair effusive ray From the great source of mental day, Free, generous, and refin'd! Descend with all thy treasures fraught, Illumine each bewilder'd thought, And bless my labouring mind. But first with thy resistless light, Disperse those phantoms from my sight, Those mimic shades of thee: The scholiast's learning, sophist's cant, The visionary bigot's rant, The monk's philosophy. O! let thy powerful charms impart The patient head, the candid heart Devoted to thy sway; Which no weak passions e'er mislead, Which still with dauntless steps proceed Where reason points the way. Give me to learn each secret cause; Let Number's, Figure's, Motion's laws Reveal'd before me stand; These to great Nature's scenes apply, And round the globe, and through the sky, Disclose her working hand. Next, to thy nobler search resign'd, The busy, restless, Human Mind Through every maze pursue; Detect Perception where it lies, Catch the Ideas as they rise, And all their changes view Say from what simple springs began The vast ambitious thoughts of man, Which range beyond control, Which seek eternity to trace, Dive through the infinity of space, And strain to grasp the whole. Her secret stores let Memory tell, Bid Fancy quit her fairy cell, In all her colours drest; While prompt her sallies to control, Reason, the judge, recalls the soul To Truth's severest test. Then launch through Being's wide extent, Let the fair scale with just ascent And cautious steps be trod; And from the dead, corporeal mass, Through each progressive order pass To Instinct, Reason, God. There, Science! veil thy daring eye; Nor dive too deep, nor soar too high, In that divine abyss; To Faith content thy beams to lend, Her hopes t' assure, her steps befriend, And light her way to bliss. Then downwards take thy flight again, Mix with the policies of men, And social Nature's ties; The plan, the genius of each state, Its interest and its powers relate, Its fortunes and its rise. Through private life pursue thy course, Trace every action to its source, And means and motives weigh: Put tempers, passions, in the scale; Mark what degrees in each prevail, And fix the doubtful sway. That last best effort of thy skill, To form the life, and rule the will, Propitious power! impart: Teach me to cool my passion's fires, Make me the judge of my desires, The master of my heart. Raise me above the vulgar's breath, Pursuit of fortune, fear of death, And all in life that's mean: Still true to reason be my plan, Still let my actions speak the man, Through every various scene. Hail! queen of manners, light of truth; Hail! charm of age, and guide of youth; Sweet refuge of distress: In business, thou! exact, polite; Thou giv'st retirement its delight, Prosperity its grace. Of wealth, power, freedom, thou the cause; Foundress of order, cities, laws, Of arts inventress thou! Without thee, what were human-kind? How vast their wants, their thoughts how blind! Their joys how mean, how few! Sun of the soul! thy beams unveil: Let others spread the daring sail, On Fortune's faithless sea: While, undeluded, happier I From the vain tumult timely fly, And sit in peace with thee. LOVE, AN ELEGY. Too much my heart of Beauty's power hath known, Too long to Love hath reason left her throne; Too long my genius mourn'd his myrtle chain, And three rich years of youth consum'd in vain. My wishes, lull'd with soft inglorious dreams, Forgot the patriot's and the sage's themes: Through each Elysian vale and fairy grove, Through all the enchanted paradise of love, Misled by sickly hope's deceitful flame, Averse to action, and renouncing fame. At last the visionary scenes decay, My eyes, exulting, bless the new-born day, Whose faithful beams detect the dangerous road In which my heedless feet securely trod, And strip the phantoms of their lying charms That lur'd my soul from Wisdom's peaceful arms. For silver streams and banks bespread with flowers, For mossy couches and harmonious bowers, Lo! barren heaths appear, and pathless woods, And rocks hung dreadful o'er unfathom'd floods: For openness of heart, for tender smiles, Looks fraught with love, and wrath-disarming wiles; Lo! sullen Spite, and perjur'd Lust of Gain, And cruel Pride, and crueller Disdain; Lo! cordial Faith to idiot airs refin'd, Now coolly civil, now transporting kind. For graceful Ease, lo! Affectation walks; And dull Half-sense, for Wit and Wisdom talks. New to each hour what low delight succeeds, What precious furniture of hearts and heads! By nought their prudence, but by getting, known, And all their courage in deceiving shown. See next what plagues attend the lover's state, What frightful forms of Terror, Scorn, and Hate! See burning Fury heaven and earth defy! See Dumb Despair in icy fetters lie! See black Suspicion bend his gloomy brow, The hideous image of himself to view! And fond Belief, with all a lover's flame, Sink in those arms that point his head with shame! There wan Dejection, faltering as he goes, In shades and silence vainly seeks repose; Musing through pathless wilds, consumes the day, Then lost in darkness weeps the hours away. Here the gay crowd of Luxury advance, Some touch the lyre, and others urge the dance; On every head the rosy garland glows, In every hand the golden goblet flows The Syren views them with exulting eyes, And laughs at bashful Virtue as she flies. But see behind, where Scorn and Want appear, The grave remonstrance and the witty sneer; See fell Remorse in action, prompt to dart Her snaky poison through the conscious heart; And Sloth to cancel, with oblivious shame, The fair memorial of recording Fame. Are these delights that one would wish to gain? Is this the Elysium of a sober brain? To wait for happiness in female smiles, Bear all her scorn, be caught with all her wiles, With prayers, with bribes, with lies, her pity crave, Bless her hard bonds, and boast to be her slave; To feel, for trifles, a distracting train Of hopes and terrors equally in vain; This hour to tremble, and the next to glow, Can Pride, can Sense, can Reason, stoop so low? When Virtue, at an easier price, displays The sacred wreaths of honourable praise; When Wisdom utters her divine decree, To laugh at pompous Folly, and be free. I bid adieu, then, to these woful scenes; I bid adieu to all the sex of queens; Adieu to every suffering, simple soul, That lets a woman's will his ease control. There laugh, ye witty; and rebuke, ye grave! For me, I scorn to boast that I'm a slave. I bid the whining brotherhood be gone: Joy to my heart! my wishes are my own! Farewell the female heaven, the female hell; To the great God of Love a glad farewell. Is this the triumph of thy awful name? Are these the splendid hopes that urg'd thy aim, When first my bosom own'd thy haughty sway? When thus Minerva heard thee boasting, say, “Go, martial maid, elsewhere thy arts employ, Nor hope to shelter that devoted boy, Go teach the solemn sons of Care and Age, The pensive statesman, and the midnight sage: The young with me must other lessons prove, Youth calls for Pleasure, Pleasure calls for Love. Behold, his heart thy grave advice disdains; Behold, I bind him in eternal chains.” Alas! great Love, how idle was the boast! Thy chains are broken, and thy lessons lost; Thy wilful rage has tir'd my suffering heart, And passion, reason, forc'd thee to depart. But wherefore dost thou linger on thy way? Why vainly search for some pretence to stay, When crowds of vassals court thy pleasing yoke, And countless victims bow them to the stroke? Lo! round thy shrine a thousand youths advance, Warm with the gentle ardours of romance; Each longs to assert thy cause with feats of arms, And make the world confess Dulcinea's charms. Ten thousand girls with flowery chaplets crown'd, To groves and streams thy tender triumph sound: Each bids the stream in murmurs speak her flame, Each calls the grove to sigh her shepherd's name. But, if thy pride such easy honour scorn, If nobler trophies must thy toil adorn, Behold yon flowery antiquated maid Bright in the bloom of threescore years display'd; Her shalt thou bind in thy delightful chains, And thrill with gentle pangs her wither'd veins, Her frosty cheek with crimson blushes dye, With dreams of rapture melt her maudlin eye. Turn then thy labours to the servile crowd, Entice the wary, and control the proud; Make the sad miser his best gains forego, The solemn statesman sigh to be a beau, The bold coquette with fondest passions burn, The Bacchanalian o'er his bottle mourn; And that chief glory of thy power maintain, “To poise ambition in a female brain.” Be these thy triumphs; but no more presume That my rebellious heart will yield thee room: I know thy puny force, thy simple wiles; I break triumphant through thy flimsy toils; I see thy dying lamp's last languid glow, Thy arrows blunted and unbrac'd thy bow. I feel diviner fires my breast inflame, To active science, and ingenuous fame; Resume the paths my earliest choice began, And lose, with pride, the lover in the man. TO CORDELIA. JULY, 1740. From pompous life's dull masquerade, From Pride's pursuits, and Passion's war, Far, my Cordelia, very far, To thee and me may Heaven assign The silent pleasures of the shade, The joys of peace, unenvied, though divine! Safe in the calm embowering grove, As thy own lovely brow serene; Behold the world's fantastic scene! What low pursuits employ the great, What tinsel things their wishes move, The forms of Fashion, and the toys of State. In vain are all Contentment's charms, Her placid mien, her cheerful eye; For look, Cordelia, how they fly! Allur'd by Power, Applause, or Gain, They fly her kind protecting arms; Ah, blind to pleasure, and in love with pain! Turn and indulge a fairer view, Smile on the joys which here conspire; O joys harmonious as my lyre! O prospect of enchanting things, As ever slumbering poet knew, When Love and Fancy wrapt him in their wings! Here, no rude storm of Passion blows, But Sports, and Smiles, and Virtues play, Cheer'd by Affection's purest ray; The air still breathes Contentment's balm, And the clear stream of Pleasure flows For ever active, yet for ever calm. SONG. [The shape alone let others prize] The shape alone let others prize, The features of the fair; I look for spirit in her eyes, And meaning in her air. A damask cheek, an ivory arm, Shall ne'er my wishes win; Give me an animated form, That speaks a mind within. A face where awful honour shines, Where sense and sweetness move, And angel innocence refines The tenderness of love. These are the soul of beauty's frame; Without whose vital aid, Unfinish'd all her features seem, And all her roses dead. But ah! where both their charms unite, How perfect is the view, With every image of delight, With graces ever new: Of power to charm the greatest woe, The wildest rage control, Diffusing mildness o'er the brow, And rapture through the soul. Their power but faintly to express All language must despair; But go, behold Arpasia's face, And read it perfect there.</field>
   </doc>
</add>