<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Davies, John, 1565-1618</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Davies, John, 1565-1618</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">davies john 1565 1618</field>
      <field name="author_text">Davies, John, 1565-1618</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.0531.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">[1605?]</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:463349</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Wittes Pilgrimage ; (by Poeticall Essaies): Through a VVorld of amorous Sonnets, Soule-passions, and other Passages, Diuine, Philosophicall, Morall, Poeticall, and Politicall. By Iohn Davies</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">Wittes Pilgrimage ; (by Poeticall Essaies): Through a VVorld of amorous Sonnets, Soule-passions, and other Passages, Diuine, Philosophicall, Morall, Poeticall, and Politicall. By Iohn Davies</field>
      <field name="title_facet">wittes pilgrimage</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">wittes pilgrimage</field>
      <field name="title_text">Wittes Pilgrimage ; (by Poeticall Essaies): Through a VVorld of amorous Sonnets, Soule-passions, and other Passages, Diuine, Philosophicall, Morall, Poeticall, and Politicall. By Iohn Davies</field>
      <field name="year_display">[1605?]</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1605</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1605</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463349&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463349&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Davies, John, 1565?-1618&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;davies john 1565 1618&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Wittes Pilgrimage ; (by Poeticall Essaies): Through a VVorld of amorous Sonnets, Soule-passions, and other Passages, Diuine, Philosophicall, Morall, Poeticall, and Politicall. By Iohn Davies&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;wittes pilgrimage&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;[1605?]&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1605&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Davies, John&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1565&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1618&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Wittes Pilgrimage&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;(by Poeticall Essaies): Through a VVorld of amorous Sonnets, Soule-passions, and other Passages, Diuine, Philosophicall, Morall, Poeticall, and Politicall. By Iohn Davies&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Iohn Browne [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;[1605?]&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp1057&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;[168] p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Wittes Pilgrimage&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;(by Poeticall Essaies): Through a VVorld of amorous Sonnets, Soule-passions, and other Passages, Diuine, Philosophicall, Morall, Poeticall, and Politicall. By Iohn Davies&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 377 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Iucunda vicissitudo rerum.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To the Right noble, and Highly honored Lord Phillip Herbert, Earle of Mountgomery and Baron of Shurland. &amp;c. Not for thou hadst a Prince vnto thy Sire, Nor, for thou hast a Monarch to thy friend, Nor for thou dost to Honors heigth aspire, Nor, for thou shouldst my Booke, or me defend, Do I appropriate the same to Thee: But, to this end, that while it liues, it may Divulge how deere thou wert to worthlesse mee, That tasted to thee this lov'd-lothd Essay. Yet, if therein be ought that stirrs thy bloud To boile with heat for thy wisht health vnfitt, I haue it mixt I hope with so much good As thou shalt haue no hurt by tasting it: For, I would taste a great part of my Bane Ere thou shouldst taste what should thee least depraue: Sith thou helpst all (thy nature's so humane) That (sick in mind) seeke what they ought to haue. And where some Spirits, that rise from Holes obscure, To Glories height, as proude, as scornefull proue, (Till hate of all (Prides hire) their falles procure) Thou GREATNESSE bearst as thee it could not moue. Shewing the diff'rence t'wixt the highlie borne (As noblie bredd) and those, in either, base: For, HONORS Children do hir grate adorne: But, Basenesse Brattes Hir glorie quite disgrace. Well knew that King, and great Philosopher (Whose Armes of Loue, and Pow'r vphold thee will) That Hee, on Thee did Honor well conferre, Sith, with his grace, thou dost him honor still. Long may (much hono'rd Earle) that grace to Thee Attaine increase, till the extremity With vnremoued fauoure staied bee: The surest Staie of Earthes felicitie: That after Ages may report, and see, Kinge Iames made One, that God made greate to bee. The Booke to his Patrone. If I thy Bloud do kindly warme, or moue, Warme my Sires Bloud with comfort of thy loue. The most free, bounden, and vnalterable humble louer of your Honor, Name, and Family. Iohn Dauies of Hereford. Againe, To the same truelie-noble Earle, and his most honorable other halfe Sir Iames Haies knight, &amp;c. Sith God and King, and your mindes sympathie Hee is truly liberall and magnanimous vvhich delights more in good renovvne then money. Seneca. Haue made you Two, an vndeuided One, (One, as of two loue makes an Vnity,) I cannot giue a Guift to one alone: For (will I, nill I) if to one I send A token of my loue, or loues desire, That sending to the other must extend, Sith loue doth make your Vnion so intire! Your Soueraigne (that with Iudgments Sharpest Eye Transpearceth all that is oppos'd to it) Saw ye were made for loue of Maiestie, Sith carelesse yee were of more That bounty and beneficence that stands in trauaile &amp; dilig?ce is both more honest and also spreades further, &amp; is able to profit more. Cicero. benefit. O they are worthie to be Minions To God, and King that loue but for their loue: Who, to them both, and their dominions, Yeeld fruites of sweete Affects for bothes behoue. No Sunne ere saw two Fau'rites of a King (For, for the most part, such hurt Great, and small) More deere to al, for their Place mannaging, Then your (deere Paire) prest to do good to all! In loue contending who, for Uertues sake, (O blessed Strife excelling Vnitie!) Shall do most good, &amp; most As the touch-stone trieth gold so gold trieth men. Plato. men bounden make To you, to whom the World it selfe would tye: Hold on rare Spirites; this emulation Is such as, with fine force, your fames aduance Beyond the compasse of Confusion, And reach of Enuy, Sclander, and Mischance. O striue you still to show the World yee scorne To turne such publicke grace to priuate He is a vicious person saith S. Augustine that attendeth only his ovvne profit. gaine: (As if you were for your selues onely borne) Sith all, but Uertue, is as vile as vayne: And if I liue, you, liuing thus, I may Legend your liues in Liues that scorne decay: And, Skill shall faile me but Ile place yee neere Cestor, and Pollux in the Heau'nly Spheare. The sinceare louer of your heroicall vertues Iohn Dauies. The Booke to Grauitie. Thou that dost knitte the Brow to austere lookes, At what but seemes; or else is lewde or light; And lookst for wisedome oft in witlesse bookes, (Sterne Grauity) auert from me thy sight. I am the Issue of a labring braine, Wherein all kind of Fancies, breeding bee: Good, bad, indifferent, all, of either Straine Some as vnfitte, as some are fitte for thee. I probablie presume thou canst not loue, Sith Saturne sits aboue faire Venus swaie Then I am not for thee, for I do mooue But in her Spheare that beares the world awaie. Yet if (vnlike thy selfe) thou long'st to see What, who, and whence I am, then smooth thy fr?t And looke on That which I haue good in mee Aud for that good hold me in good account: For, if (but like a flesh-flie) thou wilt light On nought but Sores, and shun the soundest parts Then nought sublunarie can thee delight: For all haue faults though som haue perfect parts I grant my Lines reache not to those Respectes That touch Religion: State, or Policy. I meddle not with Causes of Effects Farre greater then Loues large capacity: But in round rimes (with Reason Biac'd) I Do runne those Points that ponit at loues delight: And if some Rubbes do make me run awry Yet may I, on this Ground well runne aright: But, howsoere I runne, stoppe not my Race, That tends but to the Mistris full of grace. The Author to his Muse. VVhy makst (fond Muse) a mixture so vnmeet Of good, and bad in this thou hast composd Sith good and bad, do marre all where they meete, If they, in one by armes of Art be clos'd? Is it because thou so woulest Simbolize The nature of the All, in nature bred, Whose good doth bad, and bad doth good comprize So as they scarce can be distinguished? Or ist sith thou wouldst please the good and bad, And so (like Sinne) a people-pleaser bee? Elce ist because that vice &amp; Vertues trade Is measurd by the rule of Vanity? What ere it be it is farre out of Square, If it be tride by true Decorums Squire; Yet skils it not: sith out so all things are That made are of Earth, Water, Aire, and Fire! Then these, of Wits fire made, for Aire of Fame, (Yet some are Earthly, or with folly flow) The fire is faultie, and the Aire too blame: Yet heat and moisture maks young things to grow But yet if these grow great, and swell with praise more then with numbers, or inuention, Then good and badd, conioynd' in these Essaies, Doth please the World, best pleasd with both in one. Yet what is got by pleasing one so base But high'st displeasure of the High'st of all, Abuse of Nature, Arte, Witt, Time, and Grace, Abuse to please ABVSES Generall: Then take this for a vantage, World, for I Will please thee so no more, but liue, and dy Thy fained frend, or open Enemy. Of my selfe. VVhat meane I miscreant my Braines to beate To forge these Fancies light as Leuity, To set the World on fire which amorous heate, That now lies drowned in such vanity? I know I should not do it, and I know This knowledge much exaggerates my blame: Why do I then my science herein show, Where greatest skill doth merit greater shame? And who doth loue this vaine of fancy vaine But vainest men? then, ô how vaine am I That thus the powers of my wit doe strayne, To please vaine Skums with skumme of vanity? Here VVit it self (though wit it selfe I had) Wants skill to coyne excuse the faults so fowle: Then, Reason run right, whether dost thou gad? VVilt thou misleade the blind, thy Queen, my Soule? To please base Earth, wilt thou the Heauens displease, That knowest so well the Earth yeeldes nought but dust? Seekst thou for fame with my whole mannes disease, That worst all fame, but vertues is vniust? Or yet (by Faith instructed) knowst thou not (For, Faith, in Truth, knows more th? thou canst know) That names of famous men away shall rot, If from such gracelesse Grounds theyr fames do growe? Art thou my guide, and yet dost me direct To labyrinthes of loue, where we are lost? Dost thou (most wise) cause this most fond effect? Or' crossest me, sith thee I oft haue crost? Ah Reason wilt thou now to Passion turne, That wast the Prince predominating it? Shal thy Slaue (fraile Affection) thee oreturne? And, mad to make me, wilt thou straine thy wit? VVilt thou instruct mee so to please the sence That none but sensuall men shall like my Lines? And misinforme the best Intelligence, That paies beliefe to thee, and thine assignes? O Reason weigh thy selfe in thine owne Scales, Ponder thy power which is as good, as strong: Be thou thy selfe, though thou art wrongd by Fools, And right that wrong with Iustice, not with wrong I see thou hearst me, for thou teachest me, To teach thee what we both should learne and doe: Thou prompst me now, wherein I erd through thee; And bidst me those light Lines againe vndoe; And tye them to the lasting Lord of loue, VVith such a knot as nere shall be vndone: Those Lynes will draw, and hold, and stay, and mooue. Sith they are by the hand of Vertue spunne. Then Reason I acquite thee from disgrace, Sith thus thou promptst me what I ought to write: Lett Tyrant shame with bloud stil fil my face. For so abusing thy right ruling might. My frinds (though fraile as I am) pres me stil To presse these lines (more fraile) to publike view: If I should saie it is againste my will I shoulde speake truly, and yet most vntrue: For my wills fixt my fast friends stil to please: But yet still wauers thus, to publish these, Yet sith, in wauering wise, thus fixt, it stands Fames wind, Wits weather-cocke, my will, commands. (1) [Ore those faire Alpes, thy Brests, (that naked lie] Ore those faire Alpes, thy Brests, (that naked lie Towards the blushing heau'n of thy bright face) When as I trauell with my wandring Eye The Snowes twixt Them, and That, do let her pace: For, passing through the Valley of thy Neck Mine Eie there sticks, as drowned in those snowes, Yet, thy kind heate the same doth countercheck: So, to thy Chins faire Cliffe, on Milk, she flowes! Where, being come, she breathes, and looketh back, Dazled to see those passed-Beauties Deepes! So, there she rests, as on the rock of Wrack: With sense whereof twixt Feare, and Hope she weepes: And, dares not higher looke, sith thine Eyes Beames Draw clouds thereto, and turne those clouds to Streames. (2) [VVeearie of Rest, thus resting in the Clift] VVeearie of Rest, thus resting in the Clift Of this faire Cliffe (thine Alablaster chinne.) She now begins hir selfe aloft to lift, But ends hir course, soone as shee doth beginne: For, hauing scal'd, the neighb'ring hill, thy Lipp, There soundly sleepes she, drunke with Cherry-wine; From it (being moist, and slippie) she doth slipp, To thy faire Teeth, which whitest white refine. From whence (awakt by thy words siluer sound) She steales through the sweete Rose-banks of thy face; Where shee is caught, and at their pleasure bound, Til thine Eye-beames the Bond breake through their grace: To which cleare Sunnes (thus drawne,) therein she spies Loues heau'n: and still there, drownd in blisse, she lies! (3) [Yet, by the accidentall rising-fall] Yet, by the accidentall rising-fall Of one Haires glitt'ring Sunne-beame, on thine Eyes, Mine Eye lookt ouer that Heau'ns Christall wall To see from whence that bright Beame should arise: And, as shee lookt beyond the milky Waie That leads to loues high Court, she might discrie Ten thowzand Sunne-beames, rang'd in faire array, With Loue, and Wonder to surprize the Eye: To which, being drawne by those pure Threddes of Gold, Shee, (as the Flie is by the Spider wrapt) Stirring to go, the more They hir infold; So, there she restes, with Loue, and Wonder rapt: Where, being blinded with those radiant Raies, I could not see the Rest, the rest to praise. (4) [Grace of that Goodnesse which it selfe doth grace] Grace of that Goodnesse which it selfe doth grace: Vertues rare beauty, in thick Darknesse bright, Life of those Lines that meate the loueliest Face And perfect Period of true Loues delight: The Tearmes that bound thy' vnualuable price Are Words of Wonder, wondring at thy Worth! Archtype of of Beauty! Antitype of Vice! LOVES Holy-Land, that brings His Manna forth! Whose Mouth breathes foorth such Vapor, in suche Cloudes, As straite dissolues to Nectar fluentlie! Whose Brest the Treasure of hidd Wisdome shrouds: Which makes Thee most resemble the most Hie! Then, high'st Loue bounding to the High'st of all In the rebound, on Thee, his Forme must fall! (5) [Dread Maiestie! that shin'st through Beauties Skies] Dread Maiestie! that shin'st through Beauties Skies Regard me, cold Glasse, burning with thy Beames; Which lighting on the Christall of mine Eyes, Do burne my Hart, through Them, with Heates extreames! To whose amazing Light when I draw neere I freeze, with Feare, and flame in Loues desire: Then, lett thy Fauours glaunces thawe this Feare: And, quench, with deerest Dropps of Grace, this fire. Yet in these sacred Flames Ile sacrifize The harte of my poore Harte, to grace thy pow'r; So thou, with Loue, wilt grace that exercize, And, giue me hart, when flames my Hart deuoure: I gaue thee mine, ô then giue thine to me That Mine, and Thine, bee One twixt Mee, and Thee! (6) [Ev'n as the Persians aunciently were v'sd] Ev'n as the Persians aunciently were v'sd With reu'rence to salute the rising Sunne, And as his Beames were more in't them infus'd The more Deuotion did their Soules orerunne: So, when Thou risest in Loues Hemispheare Desire saluts Thee with a mild aspect: But, to His Zenith, when Thou drawest neere, Thou Him enragest with Beames more direct! I do desire Thou should'st looke right on me, Although those Lookes doo but enrage Desire: Yet if that rage may rest it selfe in Thee, Let all thy Beames sett all myne All on sire: Where, if I burne to Sinders, yet I shall Burne in thy loue, more deere then all that All. (7) [VVithin thine eyes (the Mirrors of my minde)] VVithin thine eyes (the Mirrors of my minde) Mine eies behold themselues, wherein they see (As through a Glasse) what in my Soule I find; And so my Soules right shape I see in thee. This makes me loue thee, (for our like we loue) Which makes me loue in thine Eies still to prie; Because I see, in Thine, how mine do mooue, And, mine do mooue (as thine doe) louingly. Then, looke in mine, and thou shalt see thine Eyes Attest, for thee, what mine for me protest: Then, let thie tongue no longer subtilize, But, saie thou lou'st me (as I loue thee) best: For, if we see the Hart-Roote in the eyne Thy eies are false or It is truly mine. (8) [Some say they wonder how so well I write] Some say they wonder how so well I write, (Although my lines to no greate wonders stretch) Sith Art, my skill, of Theft cannot indite; Yet, I endite with skill aboue my reache! Loue learnes me Art, which Art inspires my Muse: For Grammer, Logicke, Retorick: and the rest: (Mnsicke especially) Loues arte doth vse: For, loue, vntun'd, in Tune, is best exprest! Loue, most diuine, makes men do miracles: And, most humane loue, Woonders doth produce: But, Beauties loue, in vertues Spectacles, Makes men do woonders most miraculous! Then, they a woonder do not vnderstand That woonder, sith an Angell guides my hand. (9) [VVhen first I learnd the A, B, C of loue] VVhen first I learnd the A, B, C of loue, I was vnapt to learne; and sith, a Crosse Crost my way to them, I was loth to prooue That learning that might tend but to my losse. The Vowels (Looks) that speld mute Consonants I hardly could distinguish what they were; And, sith the rest to them were Disonantes To make them ioyne with Vowels, cost me deere! The Mutes, and Consonants, being Deedes, and Words, Were harsh without sweet vowels, (sweetest Looks) My youth was spent (for age such skill affoords) Ere them I knew with, and without, my bookes: But (Teares) the Liquides, still being in my Eyes, I saw, through them at last, Loues misteries. (10) [The Partes of all Loues speeche, are eighty eight] The Partes of all Loues speeche, are eighty eight, (A fatall number, but more fatall speeche) And, long it is ere we men learne the sleight; But Women straite do learne, and we men teache. If eight, to eighty eight be multiplide, Loues language doth more Verbes then Nownes embrace: Then, full of Aduerbes is the same beside, Of Swearing, Flattring, Choosing, Time, and Place. Why eighty eight Parts iust: no more, nor lesse? This speeche is figuratiue, A few, for more: For, all the parts, Speeche neuer can expresse, Sith euer they increase in strength, and Store! Then, if Time raise his armes aboue his bounds, Loues speech will Towre, til Error it confounds. (11) [Forbidden Hopes ô why were yee forbid] Forbidden Hopes ô why were yee forbid, Since yee direct your aime at Blisse of Blisses; Which is most euident, yet most is hid Apparant on hir lips hid in hir kisses? Can labour of the lips deserue such meede? Or, bodies trauell earne such recompence? That, with but scarce a view, each sence doth seede And with a touch reuiues the buried sence? Is Sence made capable of such high grace? And yet forbid to hope the same to haue? Is Heauen most conspicuous in her Face? Yet must not Sense there hope it selfe to saue? Ah what is this, but sense to Sense to glue To make it feele in death, what tis to liue? (12) [Forbidden hopes? (the comforts of my Care] Forbidden hopes? (the comforts of my Care, Yet Care that kils all comforts cheering me) I am no more my selfe the whiles you are: And, yet much more then so, the whiles you be. If ye stay with me, from my selfe I runne: If you part from me, past my selfe I fly; Stay, or part from me, death I cannot shun: With, or without your helpe, I needs must dy. I needs must dy, for life-inspiring you: And dy, if dy you do by whom I liue: I do decay when I do yee renew; I grieue with you, but more without you grieue: O then what choise remaines to wretched me But to be nought, or not at all to Be. (13) [Forbidden-Hopes, the Heauens of my Hell] Forbidden-Hopes, the Heauens of my Hell, O ceasse your Heau'nly-Hellish Regiment: My Hart (the Hellish Heau'n wherein you dwell) You rule at once with ioy, and Dryryment! Sith Contradictions ye do then maintaine And that they Reas'n resist that suche defend, Then ô part not my single Hart in twayne, To make it double, for this double end. The ioyes you yeeld, are forg'd but by Conciete; The griefes you giue haue euer reall byn: Your pleasures are accomplisht by Deceite; Which, with their ending, endlesse Woes begin: Sith endlesse Woes your ending pleasures giue, Dy, dy (damn'd Hopes) and let me die to liue. (14) [Forbidden-Hopes, why flutter yee in Aire] Forbidden-Hopes, why flutter yee in Aire, Aboue the Compasse of your Spheare assign'd? More Fitt (how ere vnfitt) were deepe dispaire, Then Hopes forbidden to the mounting Minde. Forbidden-Hopes why gaze yee on the Sunne, (Like Bastard Egletts) that quite blinds your Eyes? For Iustice Sonne such Hopes hath oft orerune, And molt those Hopes forbidden in their rise. Forbidden-Hopes, whie do yee impe your Winges With Feathers culled from the Birdes of Loue? Sith Doues are harmelesse without Gall, or Stings: But both at once yon make your Subiect proue: Then, ô from whence haue such strange Hopes their being, That see by blindnesse, and are blinde by seeing! (15) [If those translucent Lamps thine heau'nly eyes] If those translucent Lamps thine heau'nly eyes Shall stretche their beames of comfort to my passion I still will gaze on thy Cheekes (Beauties Skyes) With, eyes of Wonder, Loue, and Adoration! For, if the Gods their Heau'ns haue made in Starrs Thine Eyes, bright Starres, containe right Deities; Who are the Presidents of Peace, or warrs, And either cause, as either fall, or rise Then may I (with no Godlesse Nations) take Those Starrs for Deities, and them adore, They hauing pow'r or Peace or Warre to make To make my peace, sith warr hath made me poore: For, loues hott wars Lifes Store haue wasted quite Then grace the Foile, thus soild to grace thy might. (16) [VVhen well I weigh thy Fassions, and thy Forme] VVhen well I weigh thy Fassions, and thy Forme, (Both being of Celestiall temp'rature, Which no Change can endammage, or deforme) My loue becomes, like Them, as firme, as pure! Thy Soule vpon so sweet an Organ plaies As makes the Parts, she plaies, as sound, as sweete; Which sounds the heau'nly Setters, and thy praise; The Close wherof with groundlesse blisse doth meet! This makes desire, in me, (vnlike Desire) Like Christall, cold, and cleare, through heat, and colde; This makes me flame, like Sol, with heau'nly fire, Which fructifies mine Earth, as vertue would: Then, what I am, at best, I am of Thee, Vertues best Instrument to fashion mee. (17) [Thy nere too much priz'd Person (deerest Deer)] Thy nere too much priz'd Person (deerest Deer) The, past most pretious, sacred Temple is, Wherein pure Chastity, and Beauty cleere, Espoused are to Loue, and Louers blisse: Thy mildnesse makes Pride poore, and Meeknesse ritch: Thy looks raise Hope, yet staidly keep it downe Within the compasse of a modest pitch: Wherein thy highest grace, with grace, is showne. Thou art a Pearle which nothing can relent But Viniger made of Deuotions Teares: If it be counterfet, or euill bent, For it thou hast, nor Hart, nor Eyes, nor Eares: But, Hart, and Eyes, and Eares thou hast for myne, Whose Hart, and Eyes and Eares, are ruld by Thine. (18) [To touch on Sylla, yet to scape the same] To touch on Sylla, yet to scape the same, And yet be drowned in the Hauens mouth, Is of all griefes the great'st, and greatest blame To Fortune, or Discretion, Paines, or Slouth. But I, that scapt the Gulphe and Rock of Wrack, (VVhich in the Ocean of my boundlesse loue I found to draw me on, and put me back) Am like, in my Hopes Haun, the like to prooue; For when I hopt I had Thee as myne owne (O too too credulous!) am like to those That loue, by which for mine, thou long wast knowne, Through winds of misreport, which Enuie bloes: But, if these bitter blasts thee from me beare, My Hopes sinke, causelesse, where there was no feare. (19) [The Stoicks, in their strange Philosophie] The Stoicks, in their strange Philosophie, Make All, and Nothing, nothing but all one: VVho say that this World Is: but yet deny That it hath any Essence of the owne, But, in our loues (deere Loue) the same is true: For, Thou, being All, art mine, that Nothing am? I Nothing am that is not All thy due, So, All and Nothing's nothing but the same! Then, sith my Nothing and thy All all's one, Thou, All, I, Nothing, make an Vnity: For, All to Nothing hath conuersion; And, Nothing, vnto All, by sympathie: Then, neede I (Nothing) Thee (All) nothing feare But All, and Nothing still shall One appeare. (20) [VVho cannot loue without to lust it runne] VVho cannot loue without to lust it runne Or els to Passions that as wild appeare, Are like ill Eyes, that cannot brooke the Sunne: Or most weake Braines, that strong wine cannot beare. But, in high Loue (whose Base on vertue rests) Ther's no distemprature of Flesh, or Spritie: The Mouth of true Loue sucks true Pleasures Brests: VVhich it augments with pure (not grosse) delight. Hence flow all Nectard Sweets into the Soule That Heau'n, or Earth, (in highest height) can yeeld; As sweet and faire, as Lust is sowre, and fowle, And doth (at pleasure) Pleasures Passions weld: But, he that is impatient in desire, (As Clogd with flesh) cannot this Heaun aspire. (21) [O that I could (as willingly I would] O that I could (as willingly I would By breathing on thy lips my Soule infuse Into thy beauteous Body; then, it should Make Thee (as still it doth) on It still muse? For muse I do, and nought but muse alone, Because it makes my Muse to make my Loue Vnto such only Beauty only knowne (By waight and measure) so, thy Soule to mooue: Moue Soule (sweet Soule!) Soule of my sweetest Sweet!) VVith equall motion moue, as moues my Soule: Which moues to Thine, then let Thine with It meet It to embrace, in loue, not It controule: But yet if so thou moue, thou shalt (Deere Sweete) Controule it still when it moues ought vnmeet. (22) [So looks an Angell on Heauns Christall Wall] So looks an Angell on Heauns Christall Wall As looks my Saint, or Angell in her Glasse: Each see in each, they are Celestiall; Hir flesh then, being Heaunly, is not Grasse: Grasse! no: ô no, though Grasse doth glad the Eie With Ey-delighting Greennesse, its too darke To be like her diuine Serenity That, of highst GLORY, is a flaming Spark! Which sets the World on fire, and al therein, Like Phaetons Pride (the Proude should know that Story) No Eye sees it but would lose fight to win That Light, by which Eyes see, Sight dimd with glory! O might mine Eies be dimd stil, with that Light I would be nought but Eies, yet blinded quite! (23) [Stir'st thou me vp to loue? yet me restrain'st] Stir'st thou me vp to loue? yet me restrain'st From that thy stronge perfections stirr me to? Frown'st thou in ernest? or els frowning fain'st, Sith thee, in ernest, ernestly I woo? If thou can'st be thine owne true Antitype, (That's most deform'd, sith most well form'd Thou art!) If thou can'st rotten be, now, thou art ripe, Then, can I ceasse to sue, but not to smart: For, smart I should no lesse for thy disgrace Then I do smart for loue of (gracefull) Thee: Then, let me loue thee, in thy better case, That in thy worst, so much should greeued be: But, if thou wilt not haue me woo, nor loue, Then, either cease to Bee, or cease to moue. (24) [So, art thou (Cruell!) like a Ballance-Scale] So, art thou (Cruell!) like a Ballance-Scale For, when I sinck with Bale, thou mount'st with Blisse; And when I rise with Blisse, thou sink'st with Bale: So, stil thou art myne Opposite by This And whie all this? (o froward Faire!) ô whie In myne annoy dost thou so much delight? Can I not liue, but thou fourthwith must die? Or doth my death giue thy life, life, and spright? Ther's no necessity herein at all, Vnlesse Thou be the same: Who, (Parchas-like) Dost neuer rise, but by anothers fall: That is, their Threede of life quite off to strike: For while I waighe them wounded by thy Beames Their number, rising, falls into Extreames! (25) [Loue, like a Center, in a Circle standes] Loue, like a Center, in a Circle standes As neere to Beggars as Hee doth to Kings: And like a Kinge them both, alike, Commands, As Hee commands, likewise all other Things! What Hart is of such st'eely temprament (Or much more hard:) for, Steele the Magnes loues) But gently bowes, when it by Loue is bent? Onely thy Heart (hard Heart!) Hee nothing moues! Nature nere made what hath no grace in it; Then, thee she made not, that art so vnkinde: So, thou art nothing, sith all Beeings fitt The Endes, to which, as Meanes, they were assign'd: Women, are Meanes that Men Bee, bee not then As Nothing, but with Something, bring some Men. (26) [The sweetnesse (Sweete) which in thy loue I feele] The sweetnesse (Sweete) which in thy loue I feele, Sweetens the sorrow which, through it, I tast: It mee vpholds, as It doth make me reele; And, doth enlarge my Heart, which It doth wast. LOVE, though Thou kill me, yet, I must confesse Thou hast disbur'sd my Loue where it is due: And though it boundlesse be, yet is it lesse Then to my Loues worth doth, 'of right, accrue! And though thou bee a Spectacle, through which Each grace seemes greater then, in deede, it is: Yet, setled Iudgment mounts hir prices Pitch: For, Heau'n and Earth do offer faire for This! Then, sith Thou art more Faire then Eyes can see, Ile offer Thee as faire (my Soule) for Thee, (26) [By Nature, when wee are most cold without] By Nature, when wee are most cold without (As in the Winter) wee are hott'st within: And, hott'st without, when cold'st the Hart about: Thus, in, and out this Hott, and cold do ryn: The truth here of I know, too well, you know To question it; Then, why do you suppose My Loue is cold within, sith so in show, When that Show showes you how within it glowes? Wilt thou distrust Affections Miracle (I per se I) so rauisht with thy Loue: As now I am Loues Forces Spectacle, Which Cold, and Heate (yet cleere in both) do proue? Then ? looke through my cold-cleere Eyes and see, My Hart still sacrific'd in flames to Thee. (27) [Let not (deere Sweete) the wheeling of the Spheares] Let not (deere Sweete) the wheeling of the Spheares (That spight thy Christaline translucencie) Winde vp thy lifes-Threed on the Spowle of Yeares Ere thou dost as thy Mother did for Thee: Least that thy Glasse thy beauie doo accuse Before the soueraign'st Sence, for being deflowr'd By Time; which Thee, as thou did'st, Him, abuse: Which by thy Beautie will be ill endur'd. Why mak'st an Idoll of Diuinitie (Thy Beauiie!) and with It the Pagan play, By off'ring vp thy selfe, to It, and dy In Flames, but of Selfe-loue, condempn'd eache waie? Then, better thou hadst nere bin borne, sith birth Thy diuiue Beauty so condempnes to Earth. (28) [If (as the Pithagoreans do beleeue)] If (as the Pithagoreans do beleeue) The Sea be nought but one of Saturnes Teares Its not vnlike sith still I, weeping grieue That myne Eyes, Seas should shed, in many years. This is the seaunth Sunne hath seen my loue As firm, as flaming towards thy Beauties Heaun, Yet ouerthwartly that Heauns Sunnes do moue Through euil Signes that to no grace are giun, Nere did they shine on me but to exhale A Sea of Teares from my stil-springing Eyes Or els to parche my Bloud, and make me pale: So, fall my Teares, that still do falling rise: And, if those Sunnes thou Cloude still with disdaine, Myne eyes shall end the World with endlesse Raine! (29) [Some say the Weezel-masculine doth gender] Some say the Weezel-masculine doth gender With the Shee-Weezel only at the Eare And she her Burden at hir Mouth doth render; The like (sweet Loue) doth in our loue appeare: For I (as Masculine) beget in Thee Loue, at the Eare, which thou bearst at the Mouth And though It came from Hart, and Reynes of me From the Teeth outward It in thee hath growth. My Mouth, thine Eares, doth euer chastly vse With putting in hot Seed of actiue Loue; Which, streight thine Ear conueyeth (like a Sluce) Into thy Mouth; and, there but Aire doth proue: Yet Aire is actiue; but, not like the fire Then ô how should the Sonne be like the Sire? (30) [If Fire hath oft Barbarian Honors done it] If Fire hath oft Barbarian Honors done it By reason it resembles so the Sunne Yet scarse is seene when his Raies ouer-runne it) What would Barbarians to thine Haire haue donne? Which (ô faire-Sweete!) oreshines Fire, Sunne, and all; Whose rare resplendance no Eyes can behold That are not (like it) most Angellicall, And being so, will them, in wonder hold. Then sith that Nature Crown'd Thee with such Light As makes all Eyes, adoreing, wonder at, Bee not, ô bee not then, in loue, so light As makes thee darke by being This, to That: My speach is darke; yet what by light I meane Is more vnconstant, then it is vncleane. (31) [It is as true, as strange (els Triall faines)] It is as true, as strange (els Triall faines) That whosoeuer in the Moone-shine sleepes Are hardly wak't, the Moone so rules the Braines; For Shee is Soueraigne of the Braines, and Deepes: So thou (faire Cynthia) with thy borrowed Beames, (Borrow'd of Glories Sunne, great Lord of Light!) Makst me still sleepe, in Loue, Whose golden Dreames. Giue Loue right Currant, sith well-Coyn'd, Delight. I cannot wake, while thou, on me, dost shine, Thy shyning so, makes mee so sweetly Dreame: For, still me thinks I kisse those lippes of thine: And,—nothing els, for, I will not blaspheame: But thought is free, and Dreames, are Dreames, and so. I dreame, and dreame, and dreame, but let That go. (32) [Lvst is a Tyrant, Loue a Seruant Is] Lvst is a Tyrant, Loue a Seruant Is: This is the Sentence of Proofes euidence: For, I nere see you (Sweete!) but feele by This Both Cold and Heate, through Loue, and reuerence, VVhat Eye can look, through cleere Loues Spectacle, On Vertues Maiestie, that shines in Beauty, But (as to Natures diuin'st Miracle!) Performes not to It all subiectiue dutie? BEAVTIES Diuinitie none dare prophane That are of Humane, or of Brutish Kinde But when Its full, where Vertue's in the wane: VVhere a faire Body hids a filthie Minde? But were thy Mind and Bodies beauty one, Twere Natures Maiesties diuinest Throne! (33) [Ynough (fell Faire!) for, thou hast donne the Deede] Ynough (fell Faire!) for, thou hast donne the Deede That thou hast longe bin doing, which doth make Thy mercy lesse, for that, to kill with speede Shewes more remorce then they that leasure take. How? and how longe hast thou bin mart'ring mee To make my Deathe beyond my death to stand? Who haue bin so Anatomiz'd by Thee That eu'ry Nerue hath felt thy Rigors hand! Out of my Hart, and Braines that Hand hath squiz'd The Spirits that either Life, or Sence maintaine: For, I am all as dead, as vnaduiz'd: Only, for Thee, I Life, in show, retaine: And if thou wilt haue That, sith That's for Thee Then take Thou All, and leaue the rest for mee. (34) [O memorie (the Relicke of my Sence)] O memorie (the Relicke of my Sence) Whie yet remainst, to make me yet remaine A Relike of my Fancies sowle offence, That lov'd for hate, and woo'd, but for disdaine? Carowse of Lœthe, make thie Cuppe, my Scull, Vntill thou bee dead-drunke; then, like the Blest, I shall bee full of rest, as thou art full Of that forgetfulnes which myndes but rest. And thou relentlesse Diamond, too deere, (Too deere for mee, that offer'd mee, for thee) Shal, to the World, in woorth the lesse appeare Sith thou proust nothing woorth to, wronged mee: Then, sith thou art nought woorth, but in th' Exchange, I will not mee, for thee, now, interchange. (35) [Now plaies my Mind vpon hir Instrument] Now plaies my Mind vpon hir Instrument, (Thought-wasted Body, Organ of my Minde) No Parts but such as wholy discontent, My Parts are so vntun'd, by Thee, Vnkinde! My Longues (the Bellowes) draw in nought but Aire, That filles my Wind-pipes but with harshe Complaints Tending to Diapassons of Dispaire, Which often die, for, that Winde often faints. My Hart, and Braines (the Stoppes, that cause the Moode) Do often stopp: sith oft such Moodes they cause As by the Pangs of Death are oft with-stood, Through which the Organs Voice doth, sinking, pause: But if thou (SWEET) wilt haue It sweetly rise Then, breathe sweet Aire into It as It dies. (36) [In the' Abstract Nature is immutable] In the' Abstract Nature is immutable; But, in the Subiect it doth varie still: My Loue, each way, is to It sutable; In th' Abstract firme, the Subiect varie will. Whie wilt thou varie (Subiect of my Loue, More sweete then Sweetnesse!) whie wilt alter Sweete? Is it because thou wilt a Tyrant proue? Or scornst Subiection? or, thy Match to meete? If so it bee (ô fayrest Faire!) then, know I am thy Subiect, though thou subiect bee To my high Loue, that makes me subiect so: Then, thy Subiection giues thee Sou'raigntie: Sith so it is: then, firme to me remaine, Whose Loue doth make thee Subiect: so, to Raign! (37) [If two Sunnes should, at once, adorne the Skies] If two Sunnes should, at once, adorne the Skies All, in Combustion, would bee soone beneath: Then, tis no wonder though thy Sunne-bright Eyes (O most faire-Faire!) make all to burne that breath! For, in thy Faces midd-heau'n so they shine As comforts Nature in her workes of grace: Yet makes It flame, with furie (oft) Diuine, While it as Heaun'ly doth adorne thy Face: Then, sith I am great Mother Natures Sonne, Let thine Eyes comfort mee, with grace, to moue, (As if I were all flaming, in the Sunne) Vnto the endlesse Orbe of thy bright loue: Wherein, if quite thou melt me, I shalbe That which I wishe: that is, A parte of Thee. (38) [As great paines are not durable, at most] As great paines are not durable, at most: So, long Griefes are supportable, at least: For, nought is violent but ends in post: And that which dureth Nature may digest. This is most true, els lies Philosophy; And I would say she lyes, in mine owne proofe, Were she not Hand-maide to Diuinity: Which makes the Ly to keep the more aloofe. But ah, the smart I haue endurd through loue Hath (like that Loue) bin long, and extreame great And all for thee (too Sweet) which sowre I proue, Which woundst me while thou dost me well intreate: If Ioab ô had plaid that part alone Thou shouldst in Deed and Show, haue bin mine owne. (39) [VVhen I assaie to blaze my louely Love] VVhen I assaie to blaze my louely Love And to expresse Hir al in Colors quaint I rob Earth, Sea, Aire, Fire, and all aboue Of their best Parts, but her worst parts to paint: Staidnesse from Earth, from Sea the cleerest part, From Aire her subtilty, from Fire her light From Sonne, Moone, Stars the glory they impart So, rob and wrong I All to do her right. But if the beauty of her Mind I touch (Sith That before toucht, touch but parts externe) I ransack Heaun a thousand times as much Sith in that mind we may that Mind discerne Thats all in All that are or faire, or good; And so shees most diuine in Flesh, and bloud. (40) [Now Taper-pointed Night began to pierce] Now Taper-pointed Night began to pierce The bending forehead of our Horizon, When as I tooke my Pen in blackest verse, To shadow foorth my blacker Passion. I told thee then, in Words as dark as Hell, The Torments (Sweet) I for thy Loue abide; And gaue thee light to see their Substance well By Lynes that were al flame thy Sence to guide. Yet canst thou not or rather wilt not see The White whereat, in this dark-light I driue: Then know (deer Sweet) directly it is thee: Lo, knowst thou now? no no thou stil wilt striue Against thy knowledge not to know the same, Yet know thy Fashion puts me out of Frame. (41) [There was a Time when the most sacred Saint] There was a Time when the most sacred Saint That euer wedded was his Wife did woo, And with loue-passions did hir Eares acquaint, To moue hir mind to Loue and mariage too: VVhen he would not haue thought it mortal sin, (If so he could) to haue lynd out his loue In mouing measures so her loue to win. For, all that measure well of force must moue. He did, or would haue told her his desires (And measurd them in Numbers) were alone Those, Edens out-casts left vnto their Heirs By marriage Rights for Generation: Then sith that Church, and Common weale encrease By This, should Lynes that lead to this, surcease? (42) [If Speech, the noblest action of the wil] If Speech, the noblest action of the wil, Be turnd to Silence (Loues best speech) in me, If wit be quickned, or made good, of ill By that good will which I do beare to thee: Then what auailes good Wit if it be mute More then good will, that want good words to show it? Suters speed not, that cannot shew their sute: So, sue I to Thee but thou wilt not know it. Yet Dumb-men do, and may, wed lawfully; But, wed they do not without first they woo: Then, let me (dumb through Loue, that speaks therby) Do as, by Lawes of Heaun and Earth they do: They woo, then Wiue, I woo, then let me Wed; For, Words in Deede, best fit the mariage bed. (43) [My Mind to me a mighty Kingdom is] My Mind to me a mighty Kingdom is; Which I possesse, but not enioy in peace; For if I did, I were a King of This, But Loue, my right, doth force me to release, If thou (great Loue) vsurpe anothers Right Thou art a Tyrant; and thou must resolue By fight to keep, what Thou hast got by fight; If so of force, Thou must thy force dissolue: For with Thy force thou canst not winne from me My Mind, vnlesse Her force Thou quite defeate; VVhich, if Thou do, it is the worse for thee: For, thon defeatest That, that makes thee Great: Then, ô be not too fell, but let that Shee For, and by whom I liue, raign there with Thee. (44) [Cannot that fire that burns me warm thy Hart] Cannot that fire that burns me warm thy Hart: Art thou turnd Salamander in desire To liue in my Harts flames and feel no fire? But rather takst thou pleasure in my smart? My hart is little, and the flames are great: Its litle made by thy great cruelty: The Fuel spent (as now the same is ny) The fier needs must lose both hold, and heat. My Hart (the fuel) is not Adamant, That can indure the fury of this flame: But it is Flesh, and soon melts in the same, VVherof I wot, thou art not ignorant: Then if thy knowledge wil not help my Hart I wil condemn thy VVil, and curse thyne Art. (45) [Some say they loue, because their Loues are faire] Some say they loue, because their Loues are faire; And other some, sith they are wise and kind: The first, loue but the hue of Flesh, or Haire: But the last, loue the beauty of the Mind. But, my loue kindled is at both those fires: For, VVit and Beauty in my Loue doth flame Without al noisom Smoake of dark Desires: So, bright she is in Beauty, Wit, and Fame. If all these do concur to cause my Loue, That Loue, so caus'd, shold bring forth rare effects: And so it doth, for me it so doth moue As I do rest in restlesse rare Affects. Then, sith (deer Sweet) thy Graces and my Loue Are like, alike, let our Affections moue. (46) [They write, and speak wel, that can wel expresse] They write, and speak wel, that can wel expresse, (In either kind) what Fancy doth suggest: But I the more I fancy, speake the lesse: So, in my Hart, my hartlesse Tongue doth rest. But, ô deer Hart, sith thou art Lord of life, On paine of death, command my Pen to make Ynk of thy bloud, to Chronicle the strife Which thou endurest for thy true loues sake. And, thou my Fancy so thy selfe bestir (Who stir'st about the Center of my Loue) That future Times, in loue, may pitty hir, Sith graces such, vnpittiful should proue: And, make my Pen (in lasting Colours) paint The Picture of my Loue, and sullen Saint. (47) [The fatall beames thou dartest from thine Eyes] The fatall beames thou dartest from thine Eyes (Like Basilisks work on me, in effect: Yet from them doth my remedy arise By glassing mine, in thine, them to reflect: For, in mine Eyes, shouldst thou thy self but see Thy Beames would make thee in self-loue to burn Then, harm me not and I wil not hurt thee: Els on thy selfe thy Beauties Beames ile turne. Thinke not because thy Hart is Adamant That thy bright Raies wil but thereon rebound No, to thy selfe thei'l make thee mercy grant, And loue that grace that hurts &amp; heals the wound: Then let thine Eye-beames grace infuse in mine Or, for thy plague, ile riuet mine in Thine. (48) [Pardon me Loue, sith what for Thee I do] Pardon me Loue, sith what for Thee I do (Although it breaks thy Precepts (oft too strict) Is to attaine what to attaine vnto Thou sholdst no Course, how ere crosse, c?tradict For, shee I loue is too too like a Saint, But that shee's most vnlike, in hir disdaine; Who loues: but loues to cause my iust complaint, As if her pride tooke pleasure in my paine: Then though my prostrate old Deuotion I do forbeare, forbeare to blame my Course: For some do climb to high'st promotion By scorning Scorne, and offering Fury force: She's stiff, and I am strange, but yet I see My strangenesse makes hir seem lesse strange to me. (49) [A time there was when Loue alone did liue] A time there was when Loue alone did liue Within the Brest of Heau'ns eternall Light: But since that light did light to Planets giue Light Venus, in light Harts vsurpes his Right: So, Shee's an Idol made and daily serv'd With that Deuotion which to him belongs: Whose Motions are much more then his obseru'd So, He the Author seems of his own wrongs! He made hir first but to incline the Sence: But since, She seems much more then to constrain, Sith Mad She makes Men with her influence, If ought from hir, their Sences do restraine: But why ò Lightnesse, lov'st thou so this Star Whenas the Sun of Glory's brighter far! (50) [Loue, leaue thy Lodge (my Hart) and enter Hirs] Loue, leaue thy Lodge (my Hart) and enter Hirs Who plac'd thee there; that she may know what paine: Thou hast in pleasures, and what rest in Stirs, Which being done, returne to mine againe: For, though, at once, thou glad, and grieue the same, Thou griu'st It so, as still It would bee griu'd, So Hits might still bee melted with His flame: And so made One till they bee life-depriu'd. Or, if not so made one, that Odds should cease, Yet Odds might light bee made, by mutuall Loue: Then, in that Warre wee might enioy sweete peace: So, wee should thinke Warre sweete, and so It proue: But if she loue not too, ô Loue thou art Hart to my griefe, and griefe vnto my Hart. (51) [Of Loue, whie write I, sith such hate I proue] Of Loue, whie write I, sith such hate I proue As is of force to make Loue Loue to hate? How, how (poore Man) should I haue lust to Loue Whose Loue, and Life are so vnfortunate? My scornefull fortunes my Loue scornfull make: Who Looks on mee as on Disgraces Glasse: While I such hate, and wrongs beare for hir sake, As able were to make a Man an Asse! And yet such bearing shee forbeares to stile With vertuous Title, yet if force I vse She saith it's brutishe: Thus, shee doth defile My fame, though yet, herein, I her excuse Sith, shee hates one that loues his owne Disgrace That is, Hee loues hir that doth him debase. (52) [Fortune, and Loue (each other to disgrace)] Fortune, and Loue (each other to disgrace) Striue who should make mee Slaue to eithers might; And, being blinde, fight without shifting place: So, I am made the Barre ore whom they fight. The Blowes of either often fall on mee; And, much more often sith they both are blinde: But, Fortune strikes me sure, as shee could see; And, Loue doth wound me sore, with Blowes more kinde! Fortune, doth chippe me out, and takes away All outward Things: but Loues impetuous Blowes Nere cease to sinck till in my Hart they stay, Thus, is my Spoile the Triumphe of these Foes: But, more I yeeld to Loue, then Fortunes might, Sith I can Liue, in Loue, in Fortunes spight. (53) [Fauours, are so farre sweete as there remaines] Fauours, are so farre sweete as there remaines Place for requitall; but, if past that Place They grow, to great Harts, but to bee great paines; Which lothe such Loue, and grudge at so much grace. This happily (deere Sweete) you thinke vpon When your deere graces on me dropping bee: Who make them fall with small effusion, Lest they should cause the like effect in mee. But, you (ô me!) do quite my Hart mistake: For, you haue made it poore, and hardly liues: Which loues you more, the more of It you make: For, Fauours excesse hardly it reuiues: Then ô, wise-Faire, my poore Hart fauour still, Sith still it liues, by hope, that so you will. (54) [Shee comes, Shee comes, mount, mount my Soule] Shee comes, Shee comes, mount, mount my Soule Vnto the height of Admiration! See how the Sunne him selfe begins to scoule To see a fairer Sunne the Earth vpon! O glorious Light (which makes our Hemispheare Like Iupiters Starre-Chamber with thy Raies!) How dost thou mee confound with Loue, and feare? What praise but Wonder, can thy Wonders praise! Stand, stand a loofe, come not to neere mine Eyes: For, thou wilt make them lightlesse with thy Light! O mee! my Hart, how with thy Beames, it Fryes! What mean'st (ô Miracle!) to melt mee quite? Hold, hold; no more: thy Beames from me auert, Vnlesse, from them, Thou hide me in thy Hart. (55) [If Sunne-Beames spring, by kinde, from Heaun'ly Ground] If Sunne-Beames spring, by kinde, from Heaun'ly Ground, If Voice, diuining Eares, from Angells comes, If breath that yeelds as sweete a Sent, as Sound Celestiall bee, and Sence, with ioy, ore'comes: Then, Face, and Voice, and Breath of my sweet Saint Are most Celestiall: and, if so they bee, The Spirit of Science did this Picture paint By Coppy of his owne Diuinity! If so, she is most mercifull, and iust: Sith Hee, in both is most, most infinite; Which makes vs feare, and yet, in Him, to trust; And so shee doth, in Wisdome exquisite: Which oft, in Iustice, humbles daring Men And then, in Mercy, liftes them vp agen. (56) [If Fauour comes by suff'ring, not by force] If Fauour comes by suff'ring, not by force, And wilde-fire quenched bee with Milke, or Mire; If yeelding Woll resists the Bullets course, And gentle Oile doth quench Lime set on fire: If that the higher wee desire to builde, The lower wee our ground-worke ought to lay: If all these Truethes so naturall are held That their cleare euidence doth question staie: Then questionlesse you are vnnaturall (Sow're Sweet) who though I, at your feet, am thrown Yea, make my selfe your verie Pedestall, Yet, you insult the more, and keepe me downe: If then my lowlinesse your scorne increase You are Perfections vnkinde Master-peece. (57) [Its easie to blaspheame the name of Loue] Its easie to blaspheame the name of Loue, And say its but the worke of Idlenesse: The Slipps of Fancie, which oft mortall proue, The Mothe of Strength, and strength of Foolishnesse: These, and such like, or els farre woorse then these, Might Hate disgorge gainst Loues Diuinitie: And with such Yells Dispaire hir Soule might ease, Whose sweetest ease is bitt'erst Blasphemie: But I, that know the powre of Loue too well, To well do worde him to bee vs'd so ill: For, hee hath dam'd me to his lowest Hell Where Hee torments my Reason, VVitt, and VVill: But, Reason, Witt, and Will in humble wise Do pray for him, and wishe he had his Eyes. (58) [Your Fauors filling my torne Hart with Hope] Your Fauors filling my torne Hart with Hope, Hope, raising lustlesse Loue, and Loue, Desire, Desire rests not but in, Deer you, his scope; Whose flames: stil mount to you, his Spheare of Fire. Then, if to my desire you will giue rest, It must be in your staid Loues purer flames: Then, with his Element, Desire inuest, Sith his fire compound is, and him vnframes. Feeling mounts not to Pleasures firmament, But through this subtill Spheare of simple fire: Nor Loue attaine the Heau'n of true content, But by this sweet Repose of his Desire: Then, if you loue me, as it seems you do, Rest my Desire, and I will rest yours too. (59) [Ha! there Shee goes, that goes away with me] Ha! there Shee goes, that goes away with me; And here stand I, that haue her in my Hart: She flees from me, and yet I with her flee: For no Diuision can vs wholy part. Faire fall thee buxome Aire that yet dost hold The sent of her late presence, for thy grace: Thou dost sweet Aire, but what the Heauens wold, If they so happy were it to embrace. Who breaths this Aire, their breath most sweet must be, Though it, before the Aire made most vnsweet: On It Ile liue, till She returne to me, To take the aire which from hir first did fleet: And then in Words she shall receaue the same That shall be sweetned with hir praise, and Name. (60) [Parhaps I doo, though you thinke otherwise] Parhaps I doo, though you thinke otherwise, Loue in the tenderst Bowels of my Soule; But what? Can I not loue; vnlesse there lies Loue in my Front, while yours, in hate, doth scoule? If no faith in the Front doth lie; no loue Lies where no faith is; for, loue liues thereby: Then, the Fronts Arguments doo nothing proue But showe of trueth inuolu'd in Falacie. And if the Front saie true, and true it bee That Womens Naies are euer double Yeas; Then, your Front euer giuing Naies to mee, Doo giue me twice as many yeas, by These: But, in true loue, I hold that Skill vnfit, That discontents the Will to please the Wit. (61) [VVill you (your Will be done) haue me loue so] VVill you (your Will be done) haue me loue so, That by my Looks the same you best may see? And wil you loue in Deed, and hate in show? Do as you will, your wil is law to me. Yet Show hath much deceite, but Substance none; Then, most substantiall is the truest loue: The foreheads falshood is more seen then known, Yet known of most, that least thereof approue. Then, sith the Front's so full of Falacy, I cannot trust yours, more then you can myne: But if you would our Harts should open lye Change Harts with me, or let vs them combine: Then, feelingly, our harts we so shall kno, To This (Sowr Sweet) say double yea, or No. (62) [My Tongue, is turn'd to Eyes, mine Eyes, to Eares] My Tongue, is turn'd to Eyes, mine Eyes, to Eares In the dread presence of my deeerest Loue: Who, while shee speakes, my very seeing heares; Hir Tongue, and Bodie do so sprightly moue! My Tongue, &amp; Eares are deaff, &amp; dumbe the whiles, Orewhelm'd with Loue, and Ioy, and Hope in each; Only my Lookes applaude hir Words with smiles, As if they onely heard, and saw Their reache. And sith with hir I cannot interpleade But meerely by the meane of speaking-Lookes, Sith Lookes alone must stand me then in steade My Lookes shalbe Loue, and Witts record Bookes, Wherein shee still may reade what I conceaue Of her sweete words, and what replies I giue. (63) [Saie you (deere Sweete) my Lines are labour'd sore?] Saie you (deere Sweete) my Lines are labour'd sore? My Lines, I know, will tell you no such thing: Though euery Line doth laboure more, and more, Till they my Griefe, conceal'd, to light do bring. But, for my Lines themselues, they labor'd are With no more paine then paine in pleasure takes: Sith they my Hart vnburden of much care, That yet, for want of better yssue akes. A Labour'd Line's too busie for my Braine, That is well neere distracted, with muh Thought: Let those Lines laboure, that by Lines do gaine; For, I haue labour'd Lines, too longe, for nought: Sith my best labour'd Lines you still reward With saying, tushe this paines might well be spar'd. (64) [VVhile Words I weigh, in Scales of my Conceite] VVhile Words I weigh, in Scales of my Conceite, To know their weight that merit most respect, And, while I vse some Arte (without Deceite) To place them where they may haue most effect, I finde the weightiest Words are farre too light To weigh the Will resolu'd not to be waid; And, though their place make infinite their might, Yet stirre they not a Mind peruersly staid: Then, whie seeke I to mooue you by my Words? I know not I, because I know so much: Yet this lost labour my Loue you affords, Which, if It draw not, shall your hardnesse touche: For, were you Steele, the Magnes of my Loue Would draw you too't; but harder you I proue. (67) [Your Soules rough Calmes, that neither hate, nor loue] Your Soules rough Calmes, that neither hate, nor loue, Your Minde vnmou'd with praises, or reproofe, The lesse they moued are, the more they moue My froward loue, to stand the more aloofe. Yet looks it back, when it is well-ny gone, Supposing It should not so giue you or'e: Then tries some other kinde Conclusion, Which speeds no better then those tride before. You hate me not; for, well you vse me still: You loue me not; sith you feele not my paine: This (like your mortall hate) offends my Will; Yet, this is all the loue my Loue doth gaine: What Mettell are you off? sure, fleshe, and Blood Are not so staid, that nought can moue their moode! (66) [Where shall I hide me from Loues Pow'r? ô where?] Where shall I hide me from Loues Pow'r? ô where? If to th'Antipodes from him I fly Hee Pricks his Flights at me, and hitts me there: If neere at hand, his Torche my Flesh doth fry. In Earth, his Shafts haue all subdu'd to Him; The Sea's his Mothers Contrie; and beside He naked is, and so can faster swymme: And, through the Aire, he on his Wings doth glide. If to the Fire I flie, its to himselfe: Then, Heau'n, and Hell, (if Poetts fable not) Haue felt the great force of the little Elfe: Thus, all, in all, are subiect to his Shot: Then sith no where I can be safe from these, Ile hide me no where: That is, in mine ease. (67) [Bvt This, and then my Pen shall make aboade] Bvt This, and then my Pen shall make aboade In endlesse Rest: For, euen now the same Goes, stradling, vnderneathe a heauie Loade: For, Heauinesse his forme doth quite vnframe. Who sheddeth sable Teares, well mixt with Bryne, To rue his owners sorrowes bitter state: And maketh happlesse Blotts in eu'ry Line To Simbolize his Loue vnfortunate. The sincking Paper makes them, spreading, runne, As Griefe runnes, spreading, in his sincking Hart: Pen, Ynke, and Paper, then, are quite vndone, (As is their Master) with sad Sorrowes smart: And all that smart I feele through your disdaine, Who wounds my Hart, with loue, yet scornes my paine. (68) [VVorke on my Hart, sterne Griefe, and do thy worst] VVorke on my Hart, sterne Griefe, and do thy worst: Draw it togeather till his Strings do crack: My Minde will nere be whole till they bee burst: Then, breake, breake Hart, ere broken bee my Back. Which vndergoes a VVorld of heauie Harmes, That well might breake It, and an Hart of Oke: Then, Griefe extend the vigor of thine Armes To crush his substance into Sighings smoke. Hope, thou dost hurt It with thy helping Hand: Who (Ape-like) kilst it with a kind embrace: Thy Charge, wan Hope, yeeld to pale Deaths Command, That Hee my vitall Spirits may haue in Chase: For, sith good Lucke proues lucklesse in my Loue, Go hange thee Hope, yet stay, lest I it proue. (69) [Giue mee (faire-Sweete) the Mapp, well coulored] Giue mee (faire-Sweete) the Mapp, well coulored, Of that same little World, your selfe, to see Whether those Zones of hott Loue, and cold Dreade Bee so extreame in you, as th'are in mee. If on the Hart (that small Worlds Center greate) Such Heate, and Cold their vtt'most Powers imploy, No Thoughts could dwell therein for Cold, and Heate; Which my distem'pred-dismall Thoughts annoy. But, if I finde the Climes more temperate In your World then in mine, Ile thether send My Thoughts by Colonies,, in wretched State, Sith there, for'th with, they cannot choose but mend: And by your temp'rance, when they betterd bee If you'l transplant Them, Them re-plant in mee. (70) [No, I deny it; and my negatiue] No, I deny it; and my negatiue Salbe made good with two affirmatiues Yea, I affirme: it which Affirmatiue Shal be auouched with two Negatiues: I do deny I faine, yea, yea I do, As you accuse me, and withal affirme I loue you for your selfe, for whom I woo: And cannot loue no loue that is too Firme. I cannot loue no loue, nor loue that loue That's like Priuation, drawing neer to nought: That loue is nothing, and can Nothing moue, But such a Som-thing as should not be sought: What That is, guesse (if it be not your hate) It is that I would flie as evil fate. (71) [VVhat boots Complaint (if it be made alone)] VVhat boots Complaint (if it be made alone) To him whose help without himself doth lye? But to cause Mone effect more cause of moane, Or make Dispaire wan hopes best remedy: Sith now, ó Tirant Griefe, thou long hast had The sack of my subdued hartie Cheere, Rest, rest awhile let no new fires be made Vnto thy Spoiles that are consumed neere. O Reason what cleer Eyes hast thou to see Our Euils! &amp; how blind in shunning them! My Reason sees my Griefs extremity Yet sees not how to make it lesse extreame: For, since I loue you (Sweet) I can but grieue, To see you raze the hopes which me relieue. (72) [Deer Sweet (who in a bright face Definite] Deer Sweet (who in a bright face Definite (Being a Spark inflaming Worlds of loue!) Containes an Heau'n of Beauty infinite: To which my Thoughts, on Wings of Hope, do moue) Sith that the Sunne (Heau'ns most maiestick Eye) Disdaines not to behold the basest Worme, To glad his Soule and grace his vility, Let your Heau'ns Sunnes the like on me perform. Grace is a Spark of that immortall Flame Which, being from Heau'n descended knew not where (In Earth) to enter in a mortall Frame, But in your Corpse, wherethrough It shineth cleere: Then, sith Grace glorifies you Forme, and Face, Grace me with looks, that glorifie your grace. (73) [Thy Beauties blush, like fairest Morne in Maie] Thy Beauties blush, like fairest Morne in Maie, (Faire-Honied Sweet) doth so intrance mine Eies That while thou dost those Roses rich display They see Heau'ns hue through thy skins Christal skies, And did my fault nor thine enforce the same I stil could wish to see that Heau'nly Blush: Yea, I would see that glory to my shame, So that my faces shame would cause that flush. Then blame me not if (when thy Cheeks I see Died in a Tincture that is so diuine) My Cheeks in selfsame Colour Dyed be To make thine spread their Dy, by dying mine: Then, blush thou not, for blushing in this wise Sith that Hue from, and for thy grace doth rise. (74) [Some, blaze the pretious beauties of their Loues] Some, blaze the pretious beauties of their Loues By precious Stones; and, other some by flowrs; Some, by the Planets, and Celestiall Powres; Or, by what els their Fancy best approoues. Yet, I, by none of these, will blazon mine; But, onely saie hir selfe, hir selfe is like: For, those Similitudes I much mislike That are much vsed, though they be diuine. In saying she is like hir selfe, I say Shee hath no like; for, shee is past compare, Then, who, aright commends this creature rare, Must say Shee is: and there, of force, must staie, Because, by words, Shee cannot be exprest; So, say shee is; and, wondring, owe the rest. (75) [VVee read that Gelon and Pisistratus] VVee read that Gelon and Pisistratus Vsurpt tyrannicall dominion By meanes as violent as vicious: Yet rul'd with loue, and admiration: But, loue (that rules the Kingdome of my minde) Comming in Peace, aright, to that Command Doth rage therin, and either burne, or binde The Powres therof, that none escapes his Hand: Then would he Gelon were, for gouernment, Though he had got the same with sword, and fire: Then, should I be Loues Kingdome of Content, That am the flaming Forge of his Desire: But, rule more mildly, Loue, lest my Minds Powres Conspire to quench that Flame with thy blouds Showres. (76) [Bodies, bee neither Light, nor Heauy found] Bodies, bee neither Light, nor Heauy found So longe as they are in their proper place; But being out, they shift to It apace, Bee it aboue, or els beneath the Ground: Then, Loue, it seemes, is not in his right Spheare, That in my Hart doth rest in such vnrest; Who shifteth still to you, he loueth best; Then, must he rest in you, or els no where. Receaue my Loue (Deere Loue) then, to that rest, Sith Diuine Nature made you for the same; Proue not disloyall to that roiall Dame, But let vs eache of other be possest: And, if your vertue simple were before Thus, beeing purely mixt, it wilbe more. (77) [The Polipp Fishe sitts all the Winter longe] The Polipp Fishe sitts all the Winter longe Stock-still, through Slouthe, and on him selfe doth feed So, through the cold of feare I do, in deede, Whereby the Libertie of Loue I wronge. But they do perishe, pittilesse, that weare (Through slouthe) away, that might bee fatt, and Faire By honest Labour; hie Promotios Staire: So, do I perishe, pittilesse, through Feare. Yet, can I not but feare your scorne, dread Dame, If I should labour to disclose my Loue, Sith your high fortunes myne are farre aboue, This maks me, through my slouthe, to worke my blame: But, lest I should my selfe so quite consume To say I loue you, let my loue presume. (78) [So shootes a Starre as doth my Mistries glide] So shootes a Starre as doth my Mistries glide At Midd-night through my Chamber; which she makes Bright as the Sky, when Moone, and Starres are spide; Wherewith my sleeping Eyes (amazed) wake. Which ope no sooner then hir selfe shee shutts Out of my sight, awaie so fast shee flies; Which me in mind of my slack seruice putts; For which all night I wake, to plague mine Eyes: Shoote Starre once more, and if I bee thy Marke Thou shalt hit mee, for thee Ile meet withall: Let myne Eyes once more see thee in the darke, Els they, with ceasslesse waking, out will fall: And if againe such time, and place I lose (To close with thee) lett mine Eyes neuer close. (79) [Deere, if thou wilt that I shall call thee Deere] Deere, if thou wilt that I shall call thee Deere, (Who art most deere how euer thou-art cald! Endeere mee to thy Loue, past price, and peere, By louing mee that to thy loue am thrall'd. Yet feare I Freedome, as I feare thy hate: For, nought but thie, fixt hate can make me free: And, though relict, Ile be no Reprobate To gentle Loue, nor yet to cruell Thee! Ile bee thy Vassall, though free-borne I am, Sith they are highe-borne whome thy loue sustaines: Then let me liue to beare thy Vassalls name, Yet liue to make thee labour for my paines: That by that paines, and laboure, thou, and I may gett our Like, to liue in when wee dy. (80) [The Romaines, in their Temples, plac'd, of olde] The Romaines, in their Temples, plac'd, of olde, Neere to the Graces, well-Tongu'd Mercury; To note that Speeche in vtt'ring will catch cold, That lights not on a gracious Eare, and Eye: So, though my Tongue were most Angelicall, And, could make Eares to heare of Stone, or Wood, Yet, if your Eares turne Hony into Gall, As good no Speech, as speaking for no good. Bee not (deere Sweete) ô bee not so peruerse, Your Eares are fleshe, and so your Hart should bee: Then, stone them not, to Coole my charming Verse, That seekes to turne your Eares, and Hart to mee: But, by that Turne, if you do feare a fall, Ile hold you vp, or breake my Neck withall. (81) [If the Egyptian, and the Troglodite] If the Egyptian, and the Troglodite Ouer whose Heads the Sunne directly stands But one meere Moment, daily, in his height, Do hardly scape quite burning by his Brands, How then should I (bright-Faire!) not quite bee brent With those bright Beams, shott fr?, those Sunnes, thine Eyes, Sith still they are to me directly sent As from my Zenith, iu thy Beauties Skies? O! with those Raies exhale from Mercies Seas Some Dropps of Grace, &amp; showre th? downe on me, To coole the firie heate of my Disease, That so my Sore, and Salue maie come from Thee: If not, yet shall those Cloude-dissoluing Beames, Melt my Care-Clouded Eies to cooling Streames. (82) [VVhiles that this Aire I breath to coole my Heart] VVhiles that this Aire I breath to coole my Heart, My Hart's inflamed so with loues desire That Aire to Fire it doth thereby conuert: So liues my Hart in Hel, or quenchlesse fire! Then, canst thou Goddesse full of outward grace, (In whom I hope, sith thee I loue and serue) Still feed these flames with Beames sent from thy face And martyr him thou shouldst from paines preserue: Then may I say, by Kind th' art glorious made, But by vnkindnesse thou thy selfe dost mar: Thou mar'st thy selfe; That is, thou mak'st me vade, Who, then thy selfe doth loue thee better far: And yet thou lov'st thy self too well for me Sith so thou lou'st, because I so loue thee. (83) [No more but so? Why then false Hopes farewel] No more but so? Why then false Hopes farewel Why, why so long haue you deluded me? Saie you (false Faire!) you hate to loue too well? Although too wel, true loue can neuer be? Then, too well haue I lou'd you for such loue That thinks true loue too wel loues what it likes: Which speech doth you as fond as fickle proue; And through your tender reputation strikes. Hate you to loue too wel that lothed Hate: But hate not true loue kindly to imbrace: Your grace to loue, my Mind did animate And can you loue, too wel such loue of Grace? If so you can, Grace, too well, loues your Frame Who makes it famous, while you It defame. (84) [Lamia the witch (as Poets featlie faine)] Lamia the witch (as Poets featlie faine) Still in a box, at home puts vp her Eies: But going abrode shee put them in againe Their propper holes, wherewith each Mote she spies: So, thou at home, (that is, thy selfe within O hellish Cerces that bewitchest me) Pul'st out thine Eies: that is, seest not thy Sin; But yet abrode thou mine too wel dost see. Thou saist I haue deceau'd thee in thy loue By other Loues; and so, thou me dost hate Vpon a meer surmise: but I can proue Where thou thy Chastitie did'st vulnerate: O no, I lie, thou stil didst keep it sound But others gaue, and it receau'd the wound. (85) [It may be as you say: but yet say I] It may be as you say: but yet say I It should be otherwise then stil you do: You saie you Loue, I wil not saie you lie, Because you Loue, and Loue to linger to: For, if you lou'd me could I loue so long, For meer Delaies disguizd in Loues Araie Could I, for so much right reape so much Wrong, If you lou'd not alone to show delay? Delaie, in Loue, is daungerous you know: Then It you loue sith mine that daunger is: Who seeing loue wears me in Deed, and Show, You loue Delaie, to wast me quite, by This: But, if you loue to wast me so, by That, Hate me, another while, to make me Fat. (86) [Bee not, ô be not careleslie vnkinde] Bee not, ô be not careleslie vnkinde To him (sower-Sweet) whose care is all for thee: Looke in my Hart, through windows of my minde, And nought but thine owne Image thou shalt see. Sack not the Temple then, where thon art shrinde A glorius Monumente of Excellence! The Shrine's immortal, sith so is my Minde, Yet maist thou it deface, by plaging Sence. Thou plaugst my feeling, sith through thee I feele The hatefulst plagues that Loues Fire can inflict: My Hart (where thou dost dwell, with Hart of Steele;) Sill flaming, burnes, yet thee it not afflicts: But wert thou not lesse sensible then Steele Thou coulst not choose but feele the paines I feele! (87) [It's saide and knowne, (and, so, it's held for true)] It's saide and knowne, (and, so, it's held for true) That Arethusa, and Alphëus are Two Riuers that, each other so persue As noughte can let their Course, or water marre: For sweete Alpheus doth throug Thetis glide, Free from her saltnesse, (though, Lais-like shee steere) Vntill he meete vpon the other side, With his loue Arethusa, fresh and cleere. Then, if that sencelesse Riuers (which by kinde Are most vnstaid) in loue so constant bee, Let me not you (Faire Nimphe) vnconstant finde, Sith through all wrongs, I runne, arighte, to Thee; Then, sith to thee I runne through Sorrowes Seas, Let mee in thy cleare Hart, and Armes haue ease. (88) [Down, down proude Hart, to Loues Lures, stoop, ô stoop] Down, down proude Hart, to Loues Lures, stoop, ô stoop She Lures, that loues, shee loues, that can alure; Then, downe, ô downe, yet not so low as droupe; Sith shee, beeing gracious, is as kinde, as sure! Hir glancing Eye, through Loue, in, State is staid, Which stands with constant grace, and Maiesty: Both which, in, loue deserue to be obaide By hatefull harts, that are as hard as hie: Then melt, melt Hart, in hott affections flames, If thou be not more hard then hardest Stones: For, Harts, but of that temper, shee vnframes In fire of Loue, and makes them tender ones: Then (Sweet) sith now mine melts for loue of you, Let it run into yours, to Mould it new. (89) [There was a time (to speak, wherof I faint] There was a time (to speak, wherof I faint Sith That that was, nere lou'd the ducking Frir'e) When I might pray to you, as to my Saint, And you wold grant, or further my desire. But, you reiect (as superstitious) The praiers which I now do make to you And (tearming them as vaine, as vitious) You bend from me, when I to you do bow. If I with you commit Idolatry It is an easie error sith you be An Image but too like the Deity For Fleshy Eyes the difference to see: But, if you would haue me my Conscience kill Bid me not loue you, that wil do your will. (90) [In Nature are two supreame Principles] In Nature are two supreame Principles: As namely, Vnity, and Binarie: The first doth forme all Beauties Miracles: The last's the Fount of all Deformitie. The Forme of Number is this Vnitie: (Number, the Matter: Vnitie, the Forme) Confusion, springeth from Duality: Which doth the frame of Nature quite deforme: Then sith that Vnity hath so great grace, And that Duality bee so deform'd: Lett's not bee two (faire Sweete) but fast embrace The Meane whereby wee may bee still conform'd: Or, if wee shall bee Two (ô fairest Faire!) Let you, and I make but one perfect Paire. (91) [Ha, ha, ha, ha, you make me laugh, I sweare] Ha, ha, ha, ha, you make me laugh, I sweare: And yet I laugh as some, in ioy, do weepe: To see you double, like a Hare, for feare, Lest I should smell where now, in loue, you creepe. Well, Wanton, well: I see your Harebraind Course, Though, with the Catt, I wincke at what I see: You now turne Taile to mee, no force, no force, You shew your beastly manners as they bee. Double no more, no more Ile hunt for you: Vnlesse I open, sith you now I winde: Ile freely spend, your fame still to pursue, Sith it is blinde before, and lame behinde: Yet though some wide mouthes call a Iade, a Iade, Ile speake more spuce, yet call a Spade, a Spade. (92) [Looke from the Turret of thy high disdaine] Looke from the Turret of thy high disdaine (Wherein I see thee, though thou seest me not) On mee (fell Faire.) flat lyeng on the Plaine Of Lowlinesse, like the least little Mote! Yet if thy heaunly faces Sunnes do shine (In grace,) on my great Smallnesse I, poore I, Shall, shining, mount, as if I were Diuine, Like Motes in Sunne, who, shyning, mount thereby. But if thou Cloude thy faces Heau'n with ought That may those Sunne-beames lett to shine on mee, Ile steepe my selfe in Teares till I be nought, That I thus brought to nought by cruell Thee, May charge thee with my fall, when I shall rise To meet thee, to haue iustice, in the Skyes. (93) [O proudly-chast, and Louely-coy, deere Sweete] O proudly-chast, and Louely-coy, deere Sweete, Why takst thou pleasure to impeach thy fame With name of Cruell, for thy Sex vnmeete? To keepe good name, wilt thou lose thy good name? Its mercy to thy selfe to be most fell To those (I graunt) that seeke thine Honors foile; But, vnto him that makes thy praise excell It is no prayse to tryumph in his spoile. The pure respect thou bear'st thy Chastity First made me loue thee with all pure respect: Then, sith pure loue, is perfect Piety, And chast Desire is sacred, in effect, Requite my pure Loue, and my chast desire With like, to like, till wee become intire. (94) [Finding my selfe (before I would be found)] Finding my selfe (before I would be found) Neer lost in Laborinths of haplesse loue, I got me to a melancholy groue To descant on Loues-griefs to heauy Ground: Where whilst I coucht me to performe the same, The Flies, and Gnats, without still vexed me; And Grief, within, as busy as a Bee, Vnto my treble grief, made double game: So, while I sought to descant on my Harmes, My Harms did descant on That which I sought: For, while I thought on't I was vext in thought; And, in my Flesh afflicted with these Swarms: Then thought I Louers were like idle Drones Whom Stingers follow, to augment their mones. (95) [Gods me! what will you? soft, what do I dreame?] Gods me! what will you? soft, what do I dreame? Do I heare reall words? or think I do? Or can it be that beauty so extreame Should be so fowly false, and brag ont to? Sure, I had rather say my Sences lye, Then think you can, be so vnlike to you: Sith in the sam's no possibility, How ere you seem to you, and me vntrue. Say what you wll, I will not wrong you so To think (much lesse to say) that you fair, Sweet, VVill plight me faith; then, me and It forgoe: And vaunt (ô past beleef!) how you did fleet: But, this I sweare, if yon rest so vnsound, That such crackt Ware is better lost then found. (96) [He that would faine reduce an high-borne Wife] He that would faine reduce an high-borne Wife Vnto the Compasse of his meane estate, Must not at first, stick for a little Strife, To make his peace to haue the longer Date: For, as some Curtall ouer-lusty Mares, Then Water them, wherein they seeing it, Let fall their Crest, sith their Tail so ill fares, That Fooles, and Asses ride them without Bit: So, from the Colon to the Period Of this Similitude, what should ensue Is eas'ly gest: But ah, I am forbod By high-borne Wiues, low matchd, to tell it you: But, by their leaues this must I needs affirme, A Ring, too wide, wel bow'd doth sit more firme. (97) [Foole that I am, to seem so passionate] Foole that I am, to seem so passionate In that which Wiues, and Woes, and Years haue cal'md Bigamus. Why, now should Venus know my Bodies State? Or, with her Balsamum my Wounds be Balm'd? No more, no more: it is ynough that I Haue won Repentance, with the losse of Tyme, In running o're these Rules of Vanity: And not repeate them, erst in Rules of Rime. Now, many Winters haue Frost-bit my Haires, Congeal'd my Bloud, and cool'd my vitall Hear, I, Youthful-follies should ore'flow with Teares: And, make a Rod of Rue my selfe to beate: But, trust me Loue, how ere I write of Thee, I am in hate with thee, and thou with me. (98) [If I dare call Loue Rogue, and Runnagate] If I dare call Loue Rogue, and Runnagate, Its like I am resolu'd to loath his loue: But, so I cal Him and the cause of Hate; VVhich to my grief, in mine owne Soule I proue, I hate as hel, His meer rememberance Much more the Fauours he hath done to me: And hold his loathsom loue the fowl'st mischance That can befall Men that most haplesse be. It is the Scurge of God to plague Mankind: The Conflagration of a World of Lust: The Match whereat Hel-fire it self doth tynd: The Heate that soonest turnes our Bloud to dust: And (so I might not seem of bloudy Mind) VVould's Braines were beaten out, as he is blind. (99) [The Tyrant loue, that martyrs stil the Mind] The Tyrant loue, that martyrs stil the Mind, VVe make a God, to which our Pens &amp; Tongus Do sacrifice their Labours, il assign'd; And so ore-right the Author of our VVrongs: Then, this Affections floud we ought to turne Into the Channel of Celestial Loue; Sith Angels swim stil in that blessed Boorn (Leauder-like) to Grace by whom they moue! VVhere Light of truth (the Land-mark) nere goes out, And stil the Current runs as calm, as cleare: Where no misfortunes Flawes, Feare needs to doubt: Sith holy Loues smooth Floud, excludeth Feare: This Loue alone, (did our Muse rightly sing) Should be the Plaine-song of hir descanting. (100) [VVhy sing I then in this too louing Straine] VVhy sing I then in this too louing Straine When Loue, and I do so vnkindly iar? This Vaine in me, may seem as light as vaine; Who stil turnes Coward in Loues hottest War. Besides, my state of Fortune, Body, Mind, Are all aduerse to light Loues amity: How is it then I am to loue so kind As to seem subiect to his Empery? The Canse is weak, though strong in strange Effects, VVhich Men, how staid so ere, by Wind doth moue: Some cal it Fame, that nought but Aire respects, And, sooth to say, for It I sing of Loue: And though they write best, that write what they feel Yet, edgd by Fame, I fetch Fire out of Steele. (101) [Thus far may Speculation help a Wit] Thus far may Speculation help a Wit Vnapt for loue, to write of Loues estate: Thus far can Art extend hir Benefit Past Natures Bounds, in shew of Loue, or Hate. These Loue-tricks are not myne, though mine they be As they are thus drawne out in louing Lines: These Passions are too weak to passion me, Although my strength from ought to nought declines. But whist my Muse, Hypocrisie is sin; Make me not seem more holy then I am: My Marrow-bones lie Flesh and Bloud within, All which, by nature, burnes in Beauties Flame; But, say I am, sith Grace to me is good, Free from vnkind desires of Flesh and Bloud. (102) Inuentions Life, Death, and Funerall. Busie Inuention, whie art thou so dull And yet still doing? Are no Conceits ensconst within thy Scull To helpe my woing? Canst not, with Iudgments aide, once sally out with Words of power My Ladies dreaded Forces to disrout and make way to her? Or, can'st thou vse no Stratagem of Witt That may entrappe her? To yeeld vnto Conditions faire, as fitt els loue enwrappe her? Fy, fy, thou lin'st my hedd-peece to no end Sith by thy Lyninge I cannot, in Loues warres, my Witt defend from foule declyning. Doth Loue confound thee, that thy Founder is, (Bewitcht Inuention?) Can she which can but make thee pregnant, misse of hir intention? The powers of Witt cannot defend thee then from Shames confusion; But thou must die, with shame, and liue agen By Hopes infusion. Hope, hold my Hart, and Head; for, they are sick Inuention dyeth: Loue-sicke they are and neede an Emperick which Loue denieth. Inuention, now doth draw his latest breath for comfort crying, Hee dies, and yet, in dying, striues with Death (To liue still dying! Ring out his Knell, for now he quite is dead Ding, dong, bell, well ronge! Sing out a Dirge for now hee's buried Farewell Hee, well songe! This Epitath fix on his senslesse Head, Here lies Inuention That stood his louing Master in no steade In Loues contention. Yet, for his Soule (lest it should quite bee dam'd) Some Dole bestow yee; Giue my poore Witts (which he hath fowly sham'd) what he doth owe me. So, Mortus, et sepulcus now, he is, Heau'n graunt his rising, Bee not to vtter darknesse, but to Blisse of highe Deuising. (103) [Die, die Forbidden Hopes, ô die] Die, die Forbidden Hopes, ô die; For, while you liue, in Death liue I: Sith from Forbidden Hope Death first had life; and scope, (Ambitious hope, forbidden:) Then, if thou liu'st, needes die I must; For, Death doth liue in hope vniust: Or at the least Dispaire, Whereof Death is the Haire; Then die, or still liue hidden. (104) [Now, to this Sea of Cittie-Common-wealth] Now, to this Sea of Cittie-Common-wealth (Lymittlesse London) am I come obscur'd; Where twofold Plagues endanger may the health Of Soule, and Bodie of the most securd: The Bodies Plague's an Ill which God can do For, is Ill in the Cirtie hee doth not? But Synne (the Plague which doth the Soule vndo) He cannot do, though how he well doth wott. Then, now my Soule stand stiffly on thy guard Sith many mortall Dangers thee surround Lett Grace, thy guide, thy House still watch, &amp; warde To keepe thy Habitation cleane, as sound: And, if thou canst, with Love, liue chastlie here Angels will fetche thee hence when Plagues are neere. Other Sonnets vpon other Subiects. (I) The Trinity illustrated by a three-square perspectiue Glasse. If in a three-square Glasse, as thick, as cleare, (Be'ing but dark Earth, though made Diaphanall) Beauties diuine, that rauish Sence, appeare, Making the Soule, with ioy, in Trance to fall, What then, my Soule, shalt thou in Heau'n behold, In that cleare Mirror of the TRINITY? What? ô It were not THAT, could it be told: For, tis a glorious, yet dark Mistery! It is THAT which is furthest from description; Whose beaming-beauty's more then infinite! It's Glories Monument, whose Superscription Is, Here lies LIGHT, alone indefinite! Then, ô Light, limitlesse, let me (poore me) Still liue obscure, so I may still see Thee. (2) [I loue the life that Loue doth most mislike] I loue the life that Loue doth most mislike: That is the life which is most like to Death: On Lifes Hart-strings when Death at last, shall strike Soules Organs then do sound with sweetest breath! The Discords of this Life annoy their Eares Where but Faithes Concords onely sweetly sound: From Discords, Dangers rise: from Dangers, Feares: Which Three, these Three, the Soule, Minde, Body, wound! I would therefore, liue dead to such a life Within the Graue of most obscure estate: So, dead, to liue as farre from State, as Strife, To check those Lusts that would giue Loue the Mate: But ô this Faith (fraile faith, and Loue (selfe-Loue) Be dead, sith they but liue for selfe-behoue. (3) [Time, faster then my Thought away doth hast] Time, faster then my Thought away doth hast; Who thought not to haue lost It, but for gaine: But, as that thought was present, Time was past; So, left mee but to thinke that Thought was vaine. While I am musing how my Time to spend, Time spends It selfe, and me: but how, I muse! So, still I muse, while Time drawes on mine ende: Thus; Time doth me, and I do it abuse. I thinke, and while I thinke, I id'ly, acte: (Yet Thought's no idle action of the Minde) So, idle actions Time, and mee haue wrackt Yet, in these Ruines, I my making finde: For, I am made, by musing, what I am That's one that lynes the Ornaments of Fame. (4) [Sith Rest, and Labour weares this Life away] Sith Rest, and Labour weares this Life away: (For, Rest doth toile, as Toile doth fatigate) Sith Payne, in Laboure stirres, and rests in Play: (For, Laboure paines That, Rest doth satiate) What maruell though the Hoast of Animalls Do (groning) longe to bee Life dispossest: Sith their whole Pow'r by Natures forces falles Into the life of Laboure, Death of Rest. Then how should Man but longe to leaue that Stage Where Paine doth plaie in Rest, and Rest in Payne: Sith Rest's his Home, and Payne's his Pilgrimage, Who cannot rest, where hee cannot remayne? It then remaines that wee this Life detest Sith it doth rest in Toile, and toile in Rest! (5) [Sith glorious Princes like to Mirrours are] Sith glorious Princes like to Mirrours are, (As cleare, as brittle) how dare they contend: Sith when they meete, and light vpon the bare, They may see their beginnings, in their ende? And, sith base Vp-starts like to Bladders bee (Pust vp with winde which maks them stiffe, as stout) Mee thinkes each bound they should rise heauily: Sith That which makes them mount, may let It out. Lastlie, sith Men to Bubbles are compar'd (Then which no Being's neerer kin to Nought) Why from ill Thoughts do they their Wills not warde Sith they may bee extinguisht with a thought? It is sith Bubbles do but weake appeare: So, in their VVeaknesse, Men to Nought are neere! (6) [VVorke on, my Soule, while Sleepes Soule takes hir rest] VVorke on, my Soule, while Sleepes Soule takes hir rest, And, Sence held idle by hir heauy hand; Acte in Dumbe-Showes, which idle Spirits detest, That Wit, thy Will, thereby, may vnderstand. Let Fancy offer to Intelligence The Shade of Shapes, whose Substance thou dost loue; So, Sence shall see, without the Seeing Sence, (When Reason is rest) how thou dost moue. Mount thee vppon thy Wings of Witt, and Will, Vnto the height of thy Wills true desires: There worke thy pleasure, bee it good, or ill, That (wakeing) Will may worke what Witt requires: For, tis VVitts worke in sleepe, VVills worke to spy, That wakfull VVitt may right what is awry. (7) [The Match is double made, where Man, and Wife] The Match is double made, where Man, and Wife, Of diuese Bodies, make one perfect Minde; Striuing to bee as farre from Hate as Strife: In kindnesse constant of a diuerse kinde. Hee, gladd of hir, Shee of his selfe, more gladd; Sith as hir better halfe, shee Him doth hold! Each giues, to each, yet haue more then they hadd! For, loue, and wealth so growes more manifold! Doubling one life, sith they of Two, make One, Where Loues Desires rest pleased, in vnrest: For true Ioy rests, vntir'd, in motion, And by their motions that is still exprest: He rules sith Shee obaies, or rather Shee Obaying, rules: Thus, Soules may married bee! (8) [VVere Mannes Thoughts to bee measured by Daies] VVere Mannes Thoughts to bee measured by Daies Tenn thouz?d Thoughts t? thous?d Days should haue: Which in a Day, the Mynd doth, daily, raise: For, still the Mind's in motion like a Waue! Or, should his Daies bee measured by Thought Then Times shortst Moment they would faster flee: Yet, Thought doth make his life both long, &amp; nought; That's nought, if longe, and longe, if nought it bee. If longe it bee, for being nought, (though short) The shortest thought of longe life is too longe: Which thinkes it longe in laboure,, short in sport, So, Thought makes Life, to bee still old, or yonge: But sith its full of thought, sith full of Synnes Thinke it may ende, as thought of it beginnes. (9) [Search all the Sonnets set Loue wealth to wynne] Search all the Sonnets set Loue wealth to wynne, And you shall see (how euer darkly donne) That lightly with the Eye they do begin As if Loues heate, and Witts, came from that Sunne. And I, as if the Eye bewitched mee, Oft sett my Sonetts Seane iust in the Eye Of beaming Beauty, that it, so, may see Wherein consists Loues Comick-Tragedie. Thus is the Sences Sou'raignes Subiect, made Loues Sonetts Subiect, in faire Paper-Reames; Sith with Loues fire it doth the Hart inuade: For, that cold Christall burnes with Beauties Beames. Then ô the Eye, the Eye! I, I, that's it Wherein men see their want of Grace, and Wit. (10) [VVisedome, and Vertue cannot (if they would)] VVisedome, and Vertue cannot (if they would) Misguide the Soule to whom they stil are Guides: They guide to Glory going but on Gold: And all that Earth doth pretious hold besides. Or, if ill Times should (with iniurious hand) Oppresse Them in their Course, or Crosse theyr way, Yet must He needs aboue Times Compasse stand That, with such firm Vp-lifters, falls away. The ayme of Wisedome, yea and Fortunes too, Is at one White, to make bright whom they loue: Ne can Crosse Fortune Wisedoms Friends vndo, Sith their vndoings do their makinges proue: The Stars rule Fools, both ru'ld by Wisemen are: So, ech Mans Manners do his Fortunes square. (11) [When, with my Minds right Eye, I do behold] When, with my Minds right Eye, I do behold (From nought, made nothing lesse) great Tamburaline, (Like Phaeton) drawne, encoacht in burnisht Gold, Raigning his drawers, who of late did Raigne I deem me blessed in the Womb to be Borne as I am, among indiffrent Things: No King, nor Slaue but of the meane degree Where I see Kings made Slaues; and Slaues made Kings. When, if my Meannesse but one Thought conceaue That minds but Mounting, this Thought keeps it downe: And so I liue, in Case, to take or giue, For Loue, or Meed, no Scepter but a Crowne: Yet Flowres of Crownes, for Poesies expence, Poets might take, and giue no recompence. In praise of Poesie. Thou that, by force of All-commanding wordes, Makst all Affections follow thy Commands, To whome the High'st such height of powre affords As fully with his grace, and glory stands, To thee sweet Poesie offer I this Mite Of Forcelesse words deriu'd from lesser might. Thou that dost scorne Commers with muddy Braines Or with oughte lesse then Spirits Angelicall, Who chaunt inchaunting Soule bewitching straines Whereof but some includes the Summe of All To thee I sacrifice these Laudes to leane In flames of zeale that farre surmount the Meane: For ô Thou scornst so base as Meane to beare Sith that the Meane, in Thee, is held but base, Though other Arts the Meane doe highly reare Thou holdst the Meane to bee an high disgrace Then ô with what high Raptures should my Braynes Entraunced bee to ope thy vertues Vaines? Which, while I striue to do my Braines do beate As if they would worke out their Freedome so Who doe attempt to leaue their narrow Seate, As if they scorn'd to be the Crowne below But would be compast in an Angels Crowne To make thee Angell-bright in deere renowne! Sweet Helicon, my Braines quite ouerflow: So shall thy Nectar them intoxicate And with a firy Wreathe bind thou my Brow, That mak'st the Muse in Flames to fulminate: While She, with voice, like Thunder, rattles forth, The Peales of Praises due to Poesies worth! From this Foundation might my Muse transcend The ten-fold Orbs of Heau'n; eu'n to his Throne That's all in All, there should these praises end, That higher praises might be His alone: But, such Transcendents are too high to climb. For my tir'd Muses Wings, that Lets do lime. Yet in my Sconce ó make your Rendeuous All words that may wing Praise with Angels Plumes And Iudgement ioyne them fast with Arts Mouth-glue That they may hold past Time that all consumes: But ò my Wilfull Words hath ouershot Then, let my silence praise what Words cannot. (13) [Whiles in my Soule, I feel the soft warme Hand] Whiles in my Soule, I feel the soft warme Hand Of Grace, to thaw the Frozen dregs of Sin She, Angell (arm'd,) on Edens Walls doth stand To keep out outward Ioyes that would come in: But, when that holy Hand is tane away And that my Soule congealeth (as before) She outward Comforts seeks (with Care) each way And, runs to meet them at each sences Doore. Yet they, but at the first sight, only please; Then shrink, or breed abhor'd Satiety: But, diuine Comforts (far vnlike to These) Do please the more, the more they stay, and Be: Then, outward Ioyes I inwardly detest, Sith they stay not, or stay but in vnrest. (14) [It's not Cocytus, Riuer of sad teares] It's not Cocytus, Riuer of sad teares: Nor ought besides that may sense most torment Doth cause the feare of death, or life indeeres, In Epicures, that sensually are bent: But tis the relaps into Nullity, Which of all griefs and miseries is chiefe To those that scoffe at immortalitie, Sith in Not-being's Beings greatest griefe: For, what ioy is so great but the conceipt Of falling to his Infinition (Of blacke Non-essence) will confound it streight In those that thinke this life their Portion? Sith then their Heau'n on their fraile life depends, Their Heau'n must melt when they do minde their ends. (15) [Men, (Worlds of Mould, that fil the great Worlds Mold)] Men, (Worlds of Mould, that fil the great Worlds Mold) Creep (like vile Wormes, in whom is nought but Slime) To find some Hole, wherein to make their Hold; VVhich found, they fil; then (restlesse) straite they climb: Til hauing rais'd themselues aboue the Ground They open lye to be to dust dissolu'd: As litle, by great Clods, to Dust, are ground: So, Clods resolu'd to climb, are soone resolu'd: For, litle Worlds, that would deuour the great, Break, sith they cannot that huge Masse containe; For, they that Eat the Earth, the Earth wil eat: So, Earth to quick, is quickly dead againe. Then, in the Earth, if Men wil be secure, They must like Wormes, straite Holes or death indure. (16) [VVhen Will doth long t'effect hir own desires] VVhen Will doth long t'effect hir own desires She makes the Wit (as Vassall to the Wil) To do what she (how ere vnright) requires, Which Wit doth (though repiningly) fulfill. Yet, as well pleas'd (ô temporizing VVit!) He seems t'effect hir pleasure willingly; And all his Reasons to hir Reach doth fit; So, like the World, gets loue by flattery. That this is true, a Thousand VVitnesses (Impartial Conscience) wil directly proue; Then, if we would not willingly transgresse Our Will should swayed be by Rules of Loue: VVhich hides the Multitude of Sins because, Hir Sire, thereby, to him his Seruants drawes, (17) [It is no easie skill to rule aright] It is no easie skill to rule aright; The Helm of State one Hand can hardly sway: They must needs vse the left, as wel as right, That in a right Course, wil a Kingdome stay: For, like as Hercules (as Poets faine) VVas gotten in a Night as long as two, Because that Phebus did his horses raigne Till Iupiter that Deed, did throughly Do: So, a right statseman must of force be bred In a long Night of Silence, and sad thought; And in deep skill should hide his subtil Head. Til his skill be Herculean as it ought; And then, though Atlas on him Heu'n impose, He that huge Burden, staidly under-goes! (18) [VVhen Verity and Vertue be at one] VVhen Verity and Vertue be at one with Peoples-loue (cald Popularity) They (like a forewind in the Poop) driue on The Owner to sway Kingdoms easilye: But, if this tripple Vnion be at ods The lack of one may cause the wrack of al, Although the lackers were terrestrial gods Yet wil theyr ruling reel, or reeling fall. I grant, a time vice may haue good successe, And rule at wil, by rules of Policy; But in Conclusion twill haue nothing lesse, If true the Rules be of Diuinity: For, who doth rule by Rules that vertue lack, In Vices spight his Rule shalbe his wrack. (6) [Men ouertoild in Common-VVealth affaires] Men ouertoild in Common-VVealth affaires Gett much Tantalian wealth by wealthie paines; VVhich they enioy not through vncessant Cares: So, all their Comfort is in Care, and Gaines. Good reason then, that they should care to gett, Who gett great Cares, by getting great C?mands: That will not let them sleepe, sith sleepe they lett: For, who sleepes well in Bands, though golden B?ds? VVell fare they then with glittering Miseries, Though they fare costly, yet they coldly fare: That feede on nought, but what doth feede the Eyes, And cloy their Stomackes with consuming Cate. Care for such Gaudies who so list for mee, Sith Commons much more Common better bee. (20) [Dam'd Auarice (like a slie greedie VVhore)] Dam'd Auarice (like a slie greedie VVhore) Stirrs vp Desire, and pleasure doth for didd: And makes hir Louers starue amiddst their Store, As Midas with his golden Viands did. All other Lusts them selues helpe euery way: For, who's a Glutton that will spare to feede? Or who are carnall that forbeare the plaie Vpon an appetite to acte the Deede? But wealthie Misers haue not what they hold: And, money vse not, through desire of it: As, wee should Clothes forbeare for being cold: And, for wee hungrie are, eate not a Bitt. This is an Ill that Good doth most abuse, Because it loues the good, it hates to vse. (8) [A time there was when as thee Moone desird] A time there was when as thee Moone desird The Sunne to make hir a fitt Peticote; Who did refuse to doe what shee requir'd, Sith hee in hir suche often change did note: So, can no wisedome well proportion out To these Phantasticks (uarious, as vaine) A rate of Wealth to bring the yeare about, Sith now they loue, what straight they lothe againe. These, of all light Things, burden most the Earth; Of whome there is no helpe, no hope, no vse; Whose Mothers labored idly in their birthe, To beare such idle Things, for Things abuse: Each Slaue to vice may vs'd bee in his Kind, But ther's no vse of the vnconstant Mynd. (22) [The ignorance of the Omnipotent] The ignorance of the Omnipotent, Into two Branches doth it selfe diuide, Atheisme, and Superstition, either bent From Truth, and in their backward bent abide. The first, incountring Natures stiff, and hard, Begetts in them scorne of Religion: The last, with supple Natures, more afeard, In them ingenders Superstition. These, to Religion, are the two Extreames; Twixt whome she rests, a Vertue most Diuine! Crowned with three in One rare Diadems, By Heau'ns great Thre in One, or single-Trine! These Two bewitche the World; for, at this daie Most pray amisse, or els they misse to pray. (23) [Pleasure with Profitt is the Pynn whereto] Pleasure with Profitt is the Pynn whereto Best Penns direct their best directed ayme; Which if they splitt, they do as they should do; And iustly for it Glories prize they claime. Now from my Will (well-bent as I suppos'd) (With Shafts of the indeuors of my Witt) I haue roud at this Point, and them disposd As the Winde sate abrode, the Pynn to splitt. If I haue shott too much on the left hand, I (as not weather-wise) the Winde mistooke: Yet I considred both the Aire, and Land; But, though my Shafts can neither of them brooke, I loost them right, though light mine Arrowes were Yet some being weightie, I must needs bee neere. (24) [Plato putts difference these Tearmes betweene] Plato putts difference these Tearmes betweene A Man Is not, and is that hath no Beeing: For, in the first a Nullity is seene, Which with nor Sence, nor Substance hath agreeing. The other showeth but the difference Betweene the Cause, and Matter; or, more plaine, Betweene the Pow'r, and Passion; wherein Sence Perceaues that Odds doth really remaine: For, This distinguisheth twixt that which Is (Yea, of It selfe Is, euermore the same) And That which of another's That, or This, Yet holds nor This nor That, but alters Frame: So, Man, compared with his constant Cause, No Beeing hath at all, by Natures Lawes! (25) [Since first I came to yeeres my selfe to know] Since first I came to yeeres my selfe to know, To know my selfe, I haue done what I can: Who am not as I am in outward show, And yet I seeke to show my selfe a man: For, sith of Soule, and Body I consist, And that my Body for my Soule was made, I ought, in searching of that Soule, insist; Sith that's my selfe, that Is, and cannot fade: Shee Is: that is, (Like hir Originall) immortall, and inuisible: that is Past comprehention of Witt naturall, So, still I search, to know, to know I misse: Then, if my knowledge bee but this to kno That I know nothing, I am humbled so. (26) [The Accademicks held it better farre] The Accademicks held it better farre Quite to distrust th' Imagination, Then to beleeue all which it doth auerre, Which breeds more false, then true opinion: Then, sith the case so stands with this Soules Powre, We should suspend our Iudgment, sith Things seeme, Not as they bee (though Sence the same assure) But, bee (but in Conceite) as them we deeme: For, through the Sences Chanells that doth runne, That is conuaid to the Intelligence: Then, Sence (as in the greatnesse of the Sunne) Beeing deceau'd, deceaues eache inward Sence: O then, for Men, who seeke but good to show, How long ought wee suspect they are not so? (27) [So long as Vnity retaines hir might] So long as Vnity retaines hir might She is but only One: the Number Two Breeding but diffrence: so indefinite Doth stil deuide, that so it may vndo; Eu'n so a VVord, or Speech whil they abide But in the Thought, It's cald a Secret right: But if put foorth, forthwith abrode it glydes: For, words haue wings as swift as Thought in flight. A Ship, vpon her wings (the Sailes) may be In roughest winds stayd by her Anchor hold When she would into wel-known dangers flee And so the same from vtter wrack withhould: But speak a word, and nought shal let it hie Oft to the wrack of him that let it fly. (28) [Then, if we show (what vnshown haue we would)] Then, if we show (what vnshown haue we would) To any other, we bewray thereby We ween theil keep that closer then we could: So, shew our Secrets for more secresie. But, do the Geese, that into Cicily Ouer the mountain Taurus fly by night, Gag them with Stones, for Gaggling as they fly, Lest Eagles breeding there should stop their flight? And shall men haue lesse Wit then witlesse Geese To make that known that Wit wold close conceal And put no Gag into their glib Mouth-peece, But (like tame Guls) by gagling it reueale? Then, if my Tongue were of this twatling kinde, It should more tast my meat, then feel my mind. (29) [They that haue skil to keep, and nourish Bees] They that haue skil to keep, and nourish Bees Do hold that Hiues wherein most noyse they make To be the best, or with them best agrees Who, to the same, most honied Riches rake: But they that haue the Charge of humane Swarmes: Do hold them happiest when they quietst be: And furthest off from vproares, and Alarms, As hauing honied Sufficiency! Sufficiency, the Nurse of Rest, and Peace: For excesse breeds excesse of Sin, and Shame: And Sin, and Shame do wars, and Woes increase: VVhere Wasps make honied Ritches spoile, their game: Then, in our treble Hiues of treble Realmes, VVe want no peace, because we want Extreames. (30) [The Frosty Beard, inclining al to white] The Frosty Beard, inclining al to white, The Snowy Head: or Head more white then Snow, The Crow-foot neer the Eyes, Browes, Furrow'd quite, With Trenches in the Cheeks, Experience show. These are the Emblems of Authority; Which ioynd to those do much augment her might: These are the Signes of Reasons Soueraignty, And Hyerogliphicks spelling Iudgement right. These are the Trophies rear'd by Times left hand. Vpon the spoile of Passion, and her Powres: We, by these Symbols, Wisedome vnderstand: That vs directeth, and protecteth ours: All these in me begin to come in sight, Yet can I hardly rule my selfe aright. (31) [All Dignities that sodainly begin] All Dignities that sodainly begin, And gloriously increase, in hast, post hast, So orerunne Enuie that shee cannot synne, Nor synne before; for, straight hir pow'r they past. If Flax on fire bee put, it makes no smoke, Because it, in a Moment, falls to flame: No more can Enuy, Pompe to fume prouoke, That on the soddaine blazeth on the same. But Greatnesse gotten slowlie by degrees Lies most expos'd to Enuies crueltie; Those Beames are faint, and, vs'd thereto, shee sees Them at the brightest, with a banefull Eye: Then, blessed They that are from State exempt That lies expos'd to Enuy, and Contempt. (32) [The more vnlike to God, the worse the Man] The more vnlike to God, the worse the Man; Things most like Gods vnlike, are most vile things: God Brightnesse is, with Him it first began; The Deuill is darkenesse, and from him it springs. Who's bright, or loueth brightnesse, is like God: Who's darke, or Darkenesse loues, is like the Deuil: Who then in Darkedesse liues, or makes abode, Doth liue like Gods vnlike, the Fount of Euill. To liue, or die alone, it is all one; Saue that, of both extreames, to die is best; The Beasts most brute, delight to liue alone: And whosoe liueth soe, liues like a Beast: I cannot thinke that Men such Beasts will bee: For, Men, and Beasts lyue with their like we see. 5. Sonnets in ppaise of Emincacy or a publike Life. (33) [VVealth of Heau'ns Heau'n, and want of Hell of Hells] VVealth of Heau'ns Heau'n, and want of Hell of Hells: Angells renowne, and Mens euangeliz'd: The Summ, of all their All imparadiz'd; Glorious Elier, that it selfe excells! Blacknesse, Antipodes: Fowlenesse, Opposite: Mindes ioye, Ioyes blisse, and Blisses blandishment: Laudes Crowne, Crownes pompe, and Pompes best ornament: Kynnet of Darknessr, lightly turning it. Deathes death, Lifes life, and life of Lifes, liues Life Eyes eye Witts eye, Soules eye Eye of all Eyes: Fames pride, Prides foile, yet Foiles doth scandalize: Gods glory, Glories God, and stay of strife! This is obscure, and yet tis extreame Light, Manns Summum bonum, and Gods Soules delight! (34) [To Liue alone, alone is not to liue] To Liue alone, alone is not to liue, To die alone, alone is not to die: For, Death is Life to such a liuelesse one That liues alone, and lothes all Company. Who liues alone, alone doth lyuing Die, Who dies alone, alone doth dying liue: For, Life gaue life for sweet Societie, And Death, for Life, and Life, for Death did giue. Earth's not alone, for, Earthlings creepe vpon it; And Water's not alone, for Fish liue in it: Ayre's not alone, for Sprights liue in, not on it: And, Cricketts Liue with Fire, as all haue seene it: Since these are all, from whence all Creatures spring, Who Liues alone, liues not like any Thinge! (6) [Then least alone, when I am most alone] Then least alone, when I am most alone, Quoth one that least, loud most Mens Company: But what was hee? a Ruler; such a one Oft liues alone to keepe Societie: For, Kings (whose cares are how from cares to keepe Their Subiects liues: in Lifes Communion.) Oft liue alone, and wake when sound they sleepe, That he with them may sleep when theirs is gon. But priuate Men, if they too priuate are, Are most iniurious to mens publike good; And who are such, liue past all kind of Care; So liu'd not Hee, that for Men spent his bloud: If hee (Kind Lord) had lou'd to liue alone Hee had not died, and wee had liu'd vnknowne. (36) [Martha, and Mary (two of his belou'd] Martha, and Mary (two of his belou'd That was the Sonne of Mary, mother Maide) Chose diffrent liues (by grace, and Nature mou'd) Contemplatiue, and Actiue (as its said) Mary, the first, the last, did Martha choose: The first, preferred was before the last. By Him, for whome she did the last refuse, Through whom she was, therfore, with glory grac't If glorified she were, then not obscure: And if with Him shee were, then not alone: Alone she was with Him, vpon whose powre All Creatures rest, yet still hee rests all one: But such a one, as euery One attends Who liues alone then, liues not like his Frends. (37) [I cannot say but Beauty is a Guift] I cannot say but Beauty is a Guift: But, to fewe giuen that haue other grace: For, it the Minde aboue it selfe doth lift Although the Minde and Body bee but base. Beauty is bright, then, then tis light lightly And if too bright, too light, too oft, it is: Yet tis the Signe where Grace doth vse to lie. But, if thrust out, the Inne is most amisse. And most amisse, to misse what most adornes, And hath but meerely stained-painted Walls: Which Vice doth honour much: but Vertue scornes: Sith It, to Vice, from grace, and Vertue falls: Then Beauty if thou bee not Graces Inne, Grace, suing to thee, sueth but to Sinne. (38) [Yet what a precious Pearle, in Worlds account] Yet what a precious Pearle, in Worlds account, (Pearle in the Worldes Eyes, that doth blinde those Eyes) Fraile Beautie is, appeares by Beauties woont, That Coulors now hir faults with Forgeries. Did euer Sunne (bright Eye of Heau'n!) yet see Complections in our Streets set (Cried) to sale Before these Times made them so vtter'd bee, Which makes chast thoughts good cheape, as being stale? If euer, neuer was there such a Sunne Vnlesse the Deluge, (springing) saw the same: If then they coulord, twas by it ore'runne, To better it, because it was too blame: Those Waters varnisht it, and made it cleane, So wishe I varnisht euerie painted (?.) (39) [Bvt mad, or desprate Muse what meanst thou thus] Bvt mad, or desprate Muse what meanst thou thus To touch this Couloring with this hard Touch, Sith that thou knowst some, somwhat vertuous, Do vse to Colour-somwhat more then much? Some, good, as great (but neither great, nor good: For, Greatnesse scornes hir goodnesse so to blot) Do make their bloud dissemble with their bloud: Which (for a Colour) seems what it is not. Still worse, worse, ceasse, ceasse foole-hardy Muse, Thou art too biter so such Sweets to grieue: Thinkst thou that those, which thou dost so abuse, Will euer grace thee, much lesse thee relieue? But, ô did all as thou dost, they should rest Rewards vnto themselues, and please the best. (40) [Late in a Lodging, where I vs'd to lie] Late in a Lodging, where I vs'd to lie, A Picture, pincht hung therein, in my walk: Which, one way, had a faire-Maides Phisnomy: The other way, an Apes, which seemd to talk: So, that Face had two Faces, in one Hood: A faire Maides, and an Apes: which seem'd to me The Painter was not mad, in mirry mood: That, vnder mirth, hid graue morrality: For, to my Thoughts (that may with his agree) He seem'd to touch our Apish painted Dames, Who counterfet the Beauty, which they see, And make the Boords, their faces: to their shames: But, Wainscot Faces cannot blush, a whit, But when they lay on Red, which feemeth It. (41) [Sweet Beauty beare this bitterest abuse] Sweet Beauty beare this bitterest abuse: If thou abuse thy selfe, why should not he? Of whom thou hast, in this Tract, made good vse (In gaudiest Colours) by out-painting Thee. Thou canst not hurt me more then by thy Looks Then thy good Looks I need not much to waigh: My sight thy Back, then Forepart better brooks: Then, when thou seest me turne some other way: Vnto mine Eyes thou art a Cockatrice, Who dost infuse, through them, into my Hart, The vertue of thy powr, which doth (like Vice) Wholy confound my single-double Part: Then, if thou wilt damn me for myne offence Look well on me, to plague my Soule, and Sence. (42) [Sith Good thou lou'st (ô God, Goods only Drift!] Sith Good thou lou'st (ô God, Goods only Drift! Why giu'st thou me a Mind which Ills depraue? If Grace I cannot haue, without thy guift, Why plagu'st thou me for that I cannot haue? Can my powr make thy Powr obedient be, (Myne being so fraile, and Thine so infinite) That, maugre thine, I might wrest Grace from Thee, And, with strong hand, to rend from Thee thy Sprite? O no! it cannot: but, its in my powr To Sin, and so, to thrust thy Spirite from myne: Then, ô thou Fonnt of goodnesse, on me powr (What's farre aboue my reache) that Spirit of Thine: If not, I can but feare, that can but fall: So, can despaire, but cannot do withall. (43) [Sorrow, the Salue, and Sore of deadly Sin] Sorrow, the Salue, and Sore of deadly Sin, Sister of mercy, Mother of Remorce, Who by thy being lost, dost Being win: And, through thy strengthes decay, augmentst thy force. Who, while thou hurt'st, thou healst (together both) So, takst away thy Beeing, with thy Beeing, Who loath'st to loue, because thou lou'st to loath, That which doth giue thee sight, or blinds thy seeing: O thou sweet-Sowr-sowr sweet, (each way too true!) Sweeten, that Sowr that sowrest death doth seek: Make sweet, sowr Sin, by making Death (hir due) Dy, sith I liue, by Sin, made truly meek: For, when-as Ill, by Grace, makes good our Mood, Grace lets Ill Bee, that so, it may be good! (44) [True loue is Charity be gun to Be] True loue is Charity be gun to Be, Which Is, when Loue beginneth to be true: But, to the high'st growes louing-Charity When she the High'st alone doth loue to view. O Charity! that euermore dost flame In that dread Maiesties eternall Brest. When, by thy heate, shal my Loue lose hir name, And made to flame, like Thee, in restlesse rest? Well featut'd Flesh too base a Subiect is For Sou'raign Loues diuine, ay-blest, imbrace: The Loue of Flesh loues nought but flesh, but this Loues nought that sauors of a thing so base: Then, be the Priest, and as an Host, Ile dy Offerd to Heau'n in flames of Charity. (45) [Sith Truth it selfe cals this life sowr, as vaine] Sith Truth it selfe cals this life sowr, as vaine, What is lesse sensible then Sence, that deemes It Sweet, sith so to sensual Sence it seems, Which not a thought in one state doth remaine. I see it such, with Obseruations Eyes That ey the inside of all outward Showes; Which cleerly showes, Life ebs the more it flowes, And when it longst hath lyued soonest dyes. A King this Moment, that Kings adorate, The next, a Corse, Slaues loath to look vpon: Then, was he King but in opinion, Which alters with the altring of his state; O then sith Life is but a dreame of breath, In this lifes Dream Ile nought but dream of deth. (46) [The Seas vnfit to saile on, if too calme] The Seas vnfit to saile on, if too calme: As it is when it is too turbulent: Then, the meane motion sets it so a walme As doth the Sailors Eare, and Eye content: So, neither too calme, nor too rough a Mind Giues Vertue VVay whose waies are in the Mean: In Loue, if Passion do not Reason bind Their Action to the Clouds commends the scean Hatred, and Ire makes way, (and Lets putback) For Iustice, and for Prowesse t'act their Parts: Courage is cold, and Iustice is but flack If Ire and Hatred did not stir their Harts, Then, sith Loues passion, may with Reason hold Good reason we should loue as Reason would. (47) [If Nature cannot make Desire to cease] If Nature cannot make Desire to cease In Compasse of the Meane, let Grace thy Guest Giue head, where Excesse is the meane to peace, And the Extreame the midst of endlesse rest. For, Grace hath Passion giu'n for Natures aide VVhile they in Vertues Compasse walke the Round: And moue to Goodnesse when themselues are staid: But otherwise, they do their Stay confound: For, as excesse of Vertue is but Vice, And, too much of the best, becomes the worst: So, extream Passion doth much preiudice And make them who haue most, the most accurst: Then if thou wouldst be passionate, and blest Passion must stir thee, but in peace, to rest. (48) [To draw such Lines as will not hold the straine] To draw such Lines as will not hold the straine (If they be stretcht vpon the Rack of Wit) Is labour no lesse vilifide, then vaine: And, for Times grac'd by finding fault, vnfit: But, such to twist vpon the Wheele of Thought, As may hold stretching though all Racks them straine, Do grace their VVorker sith they are well wrought, And drawne of matter that drawes out the Braine. Such Lines will reach, if to the vtmost streind, Aboue Delight, short of Saciety: And are so strong that Enuy is constraynd To say thei'l hould beyond hir pow'r to trie: For, when the Sunne doth in our Zenith light He makes no Shade his Beames descend so right. An amorous Colloqui twixt Dorus, and Pamela. In a Garden rich of Flowres Walld with Baies, and Hawthorn Towres, In a Towre the rest forsaking, Wo kept Philomela waking. Here heard Dorus and his Saint This Birds musicall Complaint: VVhile they harkned to her singing Their hands were each other wringing. When their Eares were cloid to heare Notes that neuer cloie the Eare? Sith Hands, Harts did so discouer, Dorus thus did Woo his Louer. Sweet you see, and feeling see, How our Hands, and Harts agree And sith Hands, and Harts conspier, Let vs likewise in Desier. Time, and Place vs both do woo, To do that we needs must do, If we will be linkt for euer VVith the Knot that none can seuer. Time, once past, returneth not: Place, once lost, is hardly got. Then sith both attend our Pleasure, Let vs waite vpon their leisure. Think not Lust corrupts my loue, Though effects of both I proue Sith that Lust, aloue, seems acting Where Loue, only, is Compacting. This Coniunction I desire Not to quench vnhallowed fire, But sith I would onely owe thee, I, in loue alone, would know thee. Of himselfe Loue iealous is, Lest he should in duty misse, Sith it is his bounden duty To do seruice still to Beauty. Bound, nay treble bound I am, By thy Beauty, Grace, and Fame, That no Right should be neglected Due to one so much affected! Sith Loue can no better doo, Then to make still One, of Two: That Loue, Loue is best acquiting That comes neerest to vniting. My Soule from my Lips would flie, And, of Thine to Thine would hie, That their Powres they might be mixing In desire of faster fixing. Sith our Soules (through Loues desire) Labour thus to be intire, O! then let our Bodies being Make one Essence, through agreeing. So to be, is to be One: Which is by Coníunction: One in Spirit, and Flesh, and either Made by Coupling fast together. This I long for, but not long That this should thy Vertue wrong: Sith its vertue in affection, That desires to make Connexion. When desire hath had hîs will Thou shalt be what thou art still: Myne owne life whose fame I tender, More then what my life can render. My Loue's Loue, whose Obiect is Vertues beauty, Beauties blisse; Nere made poore for Fleshes pleasure, Sith her Meanes are without measure! Loue it selfe it selfe doth hate Till it be incorporate With his deere beloued Obiect, Raigning in It, to It subiect. O then, Deere (more deere to me Then my lifes felicity) Yeeld, ò yeeld, without gainesaying Sith that Danger's in delaying. This he said, and saying straue To enioy what he would haue Warrd with Fire, and Sword of Louers While hir Forces he discouers. Forces put in Beauties hand, Which rare Vertues did command: Wherewith She him so restrayned As the sight grew more vnfained. Loth she was to put him back, But more lothd hir Houorr wrack, Thus while Resolution houerd, Resolution He discouerd Spare, ò spare my deerest Deere (Quoth she to him (Victor neere) Let me die ere liue deposed Of my Trust in Thee reposed. Thee my Loue doth so obay That it hates to say thee nay, Did not Vertue, bid myne Honor Charge my loue to waite vpon hir. Tis no scruple loue doth make That thou shouldst such Tribute take; Sith thou art my loues true owner, But I feare the foile of Honor. Sweet, deere Sweete, let be let be: VVrong not Right thou hast in mee: O! forbeare vnciuill action, Which procureth ciuil faction. If the best bloud of my Harte VVould but ease thy easiest smart, I protest I would effuse it, That thou mightst, at pleasure, vse it. Can my Dorus feele annoy And Pamela ease enioy? No, the smarte of thy least finger Galls my Soule lik Conscience Stinger Arte thou Rackt? thy Rack constraines The convulsion of my vaines: Wherein flovves the Sanguine Humor That fr? thee should vvash fovvle Rumor. Loue me (Sweet) but loue me so That me, faultlesse, thou maist kno So to know me, is to know mee Worth the loue which thou dost ow me. My Hart shrines thy louing Hart, Still in me thou bideing art: Do not then polute thy Temple With the filth of fowle Example. Thou shalt haue me how thou wilt When such Hauing Hath no guilt: Bvt if now I should yeeld to thee, I should feare I should vndo mee. Sith I should seem most obscene In thy Soules Eye pure, and cleane: If not, I should ban my Folly To loue such a soule vnholy. Do what ere thou wilt with me, So thou make me meet for Thee: Thou art good, none can mistake Thee (Being Noble) good, then, make me. Ile be Thine while good I am, Neuer Thine with euill name: Let me glory but in glory Brightning our Affections Story. Yet (deere Sweet) these Lips of mine Shall still Labour more then thine VVith sweet VVords and sweeter Kisses To misse no ioy but Amisses. I will melt with feruor free, And infuse my selfe in thee, That thou shalt possesse me wholy, So thou wilt possesse me holy. I, perhaps do wish that done VVhich in Loue, we haue begun: (Blamelesse) so to blesse thy Fortune VVith what, now, thou dost importune. But, till then (as Reason would) Hold thou all that I do hold, Thou shalt haue all (said shee weeping) But what is in Honors keeping. O then, Sweet, perswaded be Witnesse be my Teares with me How loath I am to displease thee, If with honor, I could please Thee. Hereupon in Dorus Eyes Teares of ioy, and griefe did rise, And while words were issue seeking, Hands, hard wrong, exprest their speking. Yet at last, when Passion had Ceast, in being VVoe, and glad, Louing Dorus his Tongue tried To vnfold what it denied. While (quoth he) Pamela deere I thy charming Reasons heare I am so inchanted by them As I want will to deny them. But let me, ô let me take The deere offer thou didst make VVhich was, harmlesse kindest kissing Sith it is my greatest blissing. Herewith he her Body clips Sucking Sucket from her Lips, Twixt whose sucking all his Speaches Were as sweet, as full of breaches. Though quoth he (and then he kist) Sweet, I should (and then he mist Of what he was then in speaking Kisses still his Speaches breaking) Though, I say (said he) yet then Lips fore Tongue, and VVit did ren) My Lips nere should ceasse to kisse thee My Lips nere shold too much blisse thee. Should I life, and breath consume In thy blisfull Breaths perfume I could neuer too much loue Thee Sith, as good as kind I proue thee. For, as in a Glasse, I see What I ought to be, in thee: Sith thou dost my faults Discouer Making me a perfect Louer. I will loue thee as I should That is, so as Reason would: Reason would such diuine Graces Should be loud with chast Embraces. Come, the Rector of my Soule, VVhich Commands by thy Controule Who hast giun hir Reason power Ore sweet Sin, and Passion sower. Come then (Sweet) let vs from hence Walke in Loues Circumference: Till we may (within the Center) Do these Rights without aduenter. The picture of Formosity. Who would my LOVES diuine Idea see (So to diuine his humane fantasie) Looke in these Lines which her delineate And see an heaunly Forme in earthly state! Haire.Hir Haire, Golds Quintessence, ten times refind, (In substance far more subtill then the Wind) Doth Glorifie that Heauns Diuexity Head.(Hir Head) where Wit doth raigne inuincibly. Forehead.Her Front's the Field wherein, in loue, contends True Grace and Grauity for gracefull Ends; Whose doubtfull Conflict giues vndoubted grace Face.To Loues extreamst Horizon, hir sweet face. On the declyning of this vpper Plaine (Where Modesty in Maiesty doth raigne) Eybrovve.An heaunly Hemispheare ore Canopies Eyes.Two Sunnes, the Lights of earthly Paradise: Who, with the force of their faire influence, Delight Mens inward, light their outward sense. In which faire Mirrors all Eyes loue to prie, Sith there themselues they glad and glorifie. Cheeks.Hir Cheekes! Lyllies, and Roses are too fowle For Similies, t'xpresse true Beauties Soule: For, there that Soule imparadized lies Like Grace, alone, that made it ioy of Eyes! Two Dimples, like two Whirlepits, there appeare, More beauty to deuoure then Flesh can beare! Nose.Hir Nose, the Gnomon of Loues Diall bright, Doth, by those Sunnes, still shadow out that light That makes Times longest howres, but Moments seeme: For Months but Minuts Senses, ioyd, esteeme. Lips.Hir Lips! blush Cherries, Currall, Rubies blush: For your Prim's far inferior to their Flush: Theil gaine the Prize if you, with Them, contend, Whose Beauty's more then Hues can comprehend! Hir Teeth, A Row of rarest Margarites, Teeth. Impale a Tongue that giue all Tongues their Rights; Tongue. From whom their Dialect deriues such grace, As Eares it drawes with it from place to place: VVho, when she lists (with Balme-breaths Ambrosie) Shee it enaíres in Prose, or Poësy; That flow so boldly from her fluent Tongue As if they could not, though they would, go wrong. But ô her Voice! ô fie I wrong the same, Voice. To call much more, no more but by that name; But, briefly thus; It is That of those Quires That wonder rap diuine, and humanes Eares! VVhich when she tunes to Siluer-sounding strings, Hir voice much more then Siluer-sounding rings; So that though she thereto her Voice doth fit Yet sweetest Strings she makes but foiles to it. Hir Chin (where GRACE hir glory brings about) Chin. Is like a Promontory iutting out Into a Sea of Sweets, hir Neck, and Brest, Neck and Brest. Paps. Where Beauties Neck. Billowes rest still in vnrest? Whose seemly Swellings beating on this Point Doth Beauties Deluge seem to disappoint: So, BEAVTY sits in Dimple of this Chin To ouersee the Sweets this Sea within: Who can but touch this Cape (Cape of good Hope) The way from thence, to Pleasure lieth ope, Which lieth on hir Lips, which if Lips touche Pleasure her selfe will at that pleasure gruche. Fall from these Eaues of BEVTYES heaunly house (Where Grace, and Nature are miraculous) Along the Christall Bozome. Columne that it staies, Then Mount my Muse and fly ore Pleasures Belly. Seas Into Desires delicious Continent, Where Loues Desire liues, couertly, content: Hir Belly bounds the life of Loues desire, With all the Comforts, that it can require: There is the Milky waie that doth direct To Ioues hid Court, the Court of LOVES Elect. Is is th' Olimpus where Sense-pleasing sweetes In actiue games to striue for glory meets: Vpon the Toppe whereof Joues Alter lies, Nauel.Where zealous Thoughts their Children sacrifize In flames of lawfull Lust, to Lawlesse LOVE, Where they, with ioy, sweete Martirdomes do proue! Iust at the foote of this my Muses Mount, There lies, but what! that doth my Muse surmount, T'expresse It as It is, without offence, Such is this Secrets vnknowne Excellence! But, at Olimpus Foote runns Helicon; Then thinke what makes good my Comparison (With purest Thought) and so perhapps yee shall Neere gesse from whence Loues Helicon doth fall. Thighes,Hir Thighes, bee snowy Standards, gracefully great, Which are (strange Paradox) congeal'd with Heate! Whose Bases, lifted vpwards, hold on hie That Mount, and Fount of Earthes felicitie; And, growing downwardes, small, or Taper-wise, Two Pirameds, reuersed, make hir Thighes: VVhose Pointes, depending on a Bony Bowle, With motion meete them to, and fro doth rowle. Apple of the knee. Knees,The Biace of which Boowles doth make the Knees From whence Loues lightest Muses take their veeze To leape into those Seas, which Cares destroy, Where to be drown'd is to be drunke with ioy. Those well compacted Knees (vnknowne to all Saue knowne by measures-Geometricall) Are Beauties Hinges: which each Legge, and Thighe VVith nimble-wel made Ioynts togeather tye: So, that faire Frame which on these Hinges playes Doth, by a Consequent, implie their praise. Leggs.Then, from hir Knees slide downe hir Leggs alonge (Dull Muse, that dost hir Partes perfection wrong, And right them in Discription of this Parte VVhich, in a worde, surmounts Discriptions Arte!) Foote.Vnto hir Foote, Perfections Pedestall, No more, nor lesse then keepes hir Corpes from fall: VVhich, for the quaint proportion, doth perswade It rather is imagined, then made! Now, from hir Heele, to Head, climbe back my Muse Alonge hir Back-Parts and those Parts peruse, VVith forwards backwardnesse, because they are More Common to hir Kind though no lesse rare: Hir Butt, but ô! quick VVitt lend me a Worde Buttocks, That fairely may that Part a name afforde Fitt for the fairenesse of hir fowlest Parte, But thinke what tis to spare new words of Arte: To call them Hanches were but to prophane Their names that are for Globes-Celestiall tane: For, they are so composd by Natures Skill That Agent, mixt with Azure, them do fill! But, leaue these Partes (lest partlie some perceaue That I am lothe these pleasant Partes to leaue) And scale Beauties Meridian which doth lie hir back. Ribbs. Rigebone. Vpon theis Christall Heauns pluralitie. There Lock the Side-railes of this totall Frame VVithin a Propp, that vpright holds the same: And, for that Propp of many Ioyntes consists It seemely stands or bowes which way shee lists. She bows to all, yet none can make hir bowe: For, with the high, Shees high, and low, with lowe. VVhose Back beares witnesse that hir Brest is such That stifly stands, or bows, still more then much! The holous of the back bone A Trench, wise Nature, in the same hath Cutt Where all the hottest Shot of Loue are shutt, That can orecome what ere their force withstand And, though by Loue commaunded, Loue C?mand. Vpon the Margins of this Trench do lie (That slowlie, by degrees, mount meanely highe) Beauties faíre Walkes, or Daízie-couerd Downes The outward hollounes of the back. Whereto She flíes, for solace, when She frownes: And all alonge downe to the Posterne Gate Where Nature thrusts out that which shee doth hate. Beauties do runne at Bace, and kindlie take Each other Prisners for sweete Beauties sake! Hir Shoulders broade; whereto hir Armes are knitt, Shoulders Within whose Circuit Ioy doth sadly sitt: Because, that Ioy shee will impart to none But vnto Fames Superlatiues alone! Along those Armes (like Armes of Seas, and Brooks] Armes. R?ne the blew Vaines, with many branching Crooks; Vaines. VVhich, in a Soile, with Milk cleane ouerflowne, Do darkly make those Riuers Channells knowne. But ô hir Hand! (which my Muse Captiue holds And drownes hir in drie-moisture in the Folds) Is a meere Laborinth of Faries, farre sought, That yeelds no comming out t'a wandring Thought. That Hand, in faire Hands, can so show hir mynd That in that show Witt may Witts Substance finde: And handles so eache praised Instrument As Shee of them had supreame gouerment. What should I speake of other Qualities Done by that Hand (the Hand of Sciences) Sith no Skill that doth Greatnesse glorifie But hir Hand can, their rarenesse, rarifie! Table of the h?dThe Tables of those Hands LOVES Tables are; FingersHir fingers are the Points, both whitest Ware: Whose Sides are edged with the sweetest Aire, So to distinguish them, more sweete, pure, faire! Here LOVE at Tick-tack plaies, or at Queens-game; But, Irishe hates, for hauing Trickes too blame: Here Hee casts Doublets, Double Points to take, (The Hart, and Hand) both which an end do make Of all LOVES Games, saue when the Vies are paid Hee playeth with the Prize, for which he plaide, But to paint out hir Part these Parts within I might much more then Zeuxis glorie winn: But, as he drew a Vaile vpon that Parte Hee could not show by Coulors, nor by Arte: So must I do, and say, nay sweare, it is Vertue Contracted, to abstracted Blisse! For, all hir Parts are the true Properties Of diuine Grace, and Princlie Qualities! O Dull Inuention how dost thou abuse This Queene of Beauty Subiect of my Muse? For that too base is eache Comparison Arte yeelds too blaz on Natures Paragon. Then, ô Inuention make my Muse confesse Shee's more then Arte, and Nature can expresse. So, not as I began, my Songe I ende, My LOVES Idea none can comprehend. In Loue is no Lothsomnes. If but no more then base Bum-fiddling Respected were in Loues delicious Sceane, Then, at the Close, such irksome piddling Would make the Acte as odious, as obscene: For, might my Muse, with modestie, demaund VVhat pleasure takes fraile Sense in? In's ynough, To point at That which all do vnderstand A sport, if sport it bee, as rude, as rough. And what feeles Flesh, but Fleshe? and what is that (Though made in height of Natures Arte, and pride) But Dunge, and Dust (bee it or leane, or fatt) And who to fall to such Filth can abide? To stire vp throughly the stincking puddle of the filthie manners of vv?tons, it would turne vp the stomackes of the honest and chast bearers through the hatefull &amp; villanous sound therof. Pitha. But say that Mother Nature doth procure (For procrertions sake) hir fleshly Broode To ioyne together in this Acte impure, Yet is it farre lesse gracefull, then its good: For, did not Adams Aples iuyce infect Our perfectst bloud in being ming'd with it, VVee should not this affect, nor scarse effect, As beeing, for pure Saints Edenizd, vnfitt. Then should no ioy-pain'd tickling of the Sense (Like that of Arme-pitts, payning vs with pleasure) Haue drownd our Feeling with the Confluence Of lustfull pleasures flouds, sunck in Displeasure. VVee should not then lie soaking in Shames Soile, And melting inlaciuious Extasie; Nor should, with heat of Lust, our Liuers boile Till our life-bloud bee quite drid vp thereby. Nor should the Marrow-Malady, consume That Oile of life that makes vs strong, and freshe; Nor should wee neede our Garments to parfume To cloke the stinck of our still-rotting Fleshe. No, Loue hath in it vertue more Diuine, And the Beloud more Cause of deere delight! Where Vertue sits enthrond in Beauties Shine, To make each others splendor double bright. There Modesty to Maiesty is knit, And Uenus Dian Claspes, with chast embrace There stayed Wisedom's matcht to nimble Wit And Nature Chequers vp all gifts of Grace! Now, in such Confluence of Diuine graces (That do beheaun the Hart, entrance the Mind!) How can base flesh, once mind fleshly embraces When fleshly Motions these stayd Vertues bynd. VVere Flesh perswaded that an Angell were In Womans Forme within hir Couerture Could she desire to know a Thing so cleere With other knowledge then diuine, and pure? No no, she could not though she were inflamd With Fire that kindled Zodoms hellish fire; She could not, no, though she sought to be damd (Through hir desires) so damd a deed desire! No more can Loue haue mind of hatefull Lust, When as hir Obiect is Angelicall; But then it doth embrace (as needs it must) That Obiect with Armes supernaturall: This is the highest Heaun of humane Loue, Which none but diuine Creatures seeke to proue! Essaies vpon certaine Sentences. Amans quid cupiat scit, quod sapiat non videt. Wouldst thou (wise Husband) haue thy mariage Bed Solon the excellent Lavv-giuer would haue men keepe c?pany vvith their vviues in bed but thrice a moneth. that live as Cities &amp; States vse after a certaine time betvvene to renevv their leagues, &amp; confederacies one vvith another: So hee vvould haue loue to procure the man to be a continuall vvoer to the vvife to keepe avvay the Monster Saciety. (Without Saciety, to glut Desire? Then Thou, and It must oft be sundered, VVith Loue, and leaue to make Loue more intire: For, no ioy vnder Heau'n, but satiates; The more it is, the lesse while it endures: And, the lesse vs'd, the more it consolates; The truth whereof, too wel-knowne proofe assures. Too much of what so ere, producd by Nature, Makes Nature too too much disordered: Too much of Uenus lessens strength and stature, In the Ingendrers and Ingendered. And Fire, and Flax must flame, if they do touch, And Men, and Women ioyne that (bare) embrace: Who then do seldome part before too much Their deerst Embracements doth too much debase. To wed a wife, and not to Bed her too VVere too vnkind a part for Grooms to play: To woo, and not vse that for which we woo Were Faith, and Hope, through strange Loue, to betray But yet to Bed hir, and to Lie still by her Is more vnkindly done then not to Bed hir: And better were it, for Thee, quite to fly hir Then not to vse hir well, when thou hast wed hir. And well thou dost not vse hir, she may deeme, If well thou dost not then thy selfe approue: And though of Action she may carelesse seeme, Yet may she feare thy slouth is sin in loue. Then must Temptation on thy weaknesse work If still thou Bed, or rarely Bed thy Wife: In each of which, Temptation still doth lurke; And all Temptation tendeth but to Strife. Then they, from strife, are free, that can, and will In marriage Duties vse the Golden Meane: For so their Loue is without Measure still, And Soules, and Bodies are as stronge, as cleane! But, all that married are haue not the Guift So to Deuide themselues, sith Bedds some haue But for them selues (poore Soules) wherewith they shift) Who, being One, haue Two, but on's their Graue. In reason these should be togeather thrust, Sith they are onely rich in cold Desire, Who lie togeather more for heate, then Lust, Heate, that comes only from Afflictions fire. Fleshe these do touch, as oft as Fleshe they tast, That's seld [God wott] so Flesh, and they are Two: A blessed odds that makes the Striuers chast, And makes them liue well, though it them vndoo. Now, if this Lore dislikes some youthfull Blouds That still do boyle with heate of Loue, or Lust, [Which must bee coold (still) in Lusts running Floudds,] Then must they do, perforce, what needs they must. Yet let them know, to know each other so Both Grace, and Nature thereby takes offence, A man may make his Wife, well, lett that go, The name of Whore fitts not Obedience. But Marriage is by Heau'n, aucthorized, Sith, by the Heau'n-wright, wrought in Paradice: Then, who defiles Hir vndefiled Bedd, Makes hir not vertuous, but a Vaile for Vice. And Ouer-much, doth ouer much Defile That blessed Bedd, which Grace doth purifie: Then lett not Sinne oremuch it selfe beguile To think that Bedd, so much doth sanctifie. And if that any man a wife hath gott That lookes but for so much, accurst is Hee: And Wiues that haue, like Husbands, to their Lott, Are like vccurst, so, both accursed bee. The one, by Heau'n, accurst, by Happ, the other; So, both are curst, though in a diuerse Kinde But, blessed Father, and a blessed Mother Those curst, by Happ, may make, if blest in mind. Then, if wee ought, before a Friend we choose, To eate much Salt with him, him all to tast Wee neede to eate ten times as much with those Whose All wee make our All vntill our last: For in that Match our selues wee make or marre; Then had wee neede to leaue, before wee take: That's leaue our Choise, by choosing better farre: Then, leaue our life, ere faith, or Choise forsake. Now, you that yet are free, must needs bee bound, To him that hath thus freed you (ere this Tye) From casting Anchor where you may bee drownd In Seas of Lust, and waues of Miserie. Bee sure of Sea-roome ere these Surges swell, That may lie hidd in deep'st profundities Keepe well that Compasse that may guide you well, In mists of Loue to cleere Felicitie. The fairest Face hath not still fairest grace; Nor yet the Black, in show, still black in Deede: Who oft are bright in Mind, though black in Face. And oft the fairest Flowers beare blackest Seede. Then lest faire Coulor, coulor fowlest Vice Iudge thou of Coulors by cleere Iudgments Eye: If Coulor should to death thy life entice, Die, without Coulor, ere for Coulor die: So shalt thou liue (and neuer coulor dying Which show of life) thy life still glorifying! Be not ielous ouer the wife of thy bozome, neither teach hir by thy meanes an euill Lesson Ecclus. 9. 1. You that do choose your Wiues as sometimes I Haue chosen Kniues: That is, for Beauties sake, And in your Choise mind but Carnalitie You make a Match to marre, and marre, to make. Yee marre your selues by making such a Match: Yet marre your selues, to make your selues but Beasts: Then, in your turning Beasts, oft Hornes yee catch, Which the Head beares, how ere the Hart disgests, For, if you needs will VViue for VVantonnesse Then needs you must haue VVantons to your VViues: And if your selues so well loue Lusts excesse Its fitt They loue what you loue as their liues. But were they good by Kinde, their Kinde you change, And make them ouerkinde, so, ouernought. You learne them strange Tricks, and they teach as strange To others, that do learne but what you taught. Therein (like good Wiues) they divulge your Skill Because you should bee knowne to be good Dooers: Then blame them not sith they, for meere good-will, Do show their Husbands Conning to their Wooers. Nor, will they take to teach, but giue, to learne Some other Tricks of others, skild therein: Wherewith to please their Husbands, and to earne Their Liuing if neede bee, for Slouch is sinne. These Good-ones are made so, by teachers ill (Too good at all things that are good for nought) If their meanes fail; yet can thee liue by Skill; Which being Light shall lightly well be wrought. But ô fraile Fleshlings, Husbands, Hard-heads, Bawdes, Note but the end of your laciuious Match: Your Wiues gett, Emralds, Rubies, and such Gawdes, Which you, of them, and they, of others, catch. Shame, and Confusion (with a Pox) Disioynes Your dam'd Coniunction, which doth quite deuide From Heau'n, your Soules, from Health, your lothsome Loynes, To teach eache Groome to choose a better Bride: For, whosoeuer drownes his Spirit in Fleshe VVhen hee doth handle Flesh, to fitt his gripe; Shall serued bee with Trickes still fresh, and freshe Vntill he stinck, as stale, or rotten-ripe. And in thy Choise, thy Choise to handle so Thou maist so well be seru'd; and serued well Thou art, by hir, which thou didst Loue, to kno, Not know, to loue, or loue, as knowen well. I speake not of the Bralls, and Discontents (That Ielousie, which still doth Lust belott, Doth breede, twixt them, through their misgouerments) Though they Want not; That is, they want them not. Then lett thy Mistris bee what likes hir best [Though Lust loues not to serue best Mistrises] But let thy Wife (in whome thou wouldst be blest) Bee farre from Trickes, and Toyes, and Fantazies. And looke not in hir Eyes for Lookes t'alure (Except thine Eyes b'alurd with modest Lookes) But looke to see, through them, hir Spirit pure; So maist thou coniure Spirits vp by those Bookes, That may thy Hart to pure affection moue, And in Loues Compasse, Compasse endlesse Loue! Non est eiusdem &amp; multa &amp; opportuna dicere. Erasmus Chiliad: Sith all my Thoughts are but my Mindes Conceits And my Conceits but motions of my Mind, How is it that my Minde in hir Receits Takes not, for Currant, Thoughts well Coynd, by Kinde? Is it because their Mettall is but meane Sith they are forgd but by fraile Fantasie? Or, els because their temper is vncleane? Or, all, in one, their value vilifie? What ere it bee it makes my Thoughts to muse That (beeing stampt by Arte, and forgd by Kinde) My Minde should yet (as base) the same refuse; Or, naile them vp, where they no passage finde. The cause, I thinke [which Thought may Currant runne] Is, [sith shee is a Queene of Fleshe, and Bloud] Shee will haue nought [lest all should bee vndone] Alow'd by hir that is not great, and good! Then how escape these counterfet Conceits [Base for ther Stuff, and rugged for their Stampe] Out of hir Mynt, [alow'd by Iudgments Weightes?] They scape through Passions Mist, and Errors Dampe. But can a fault excus'd bee by a fault The lesser by the greater farre? ô no Then this excuse, sith downe-right it doth halt, For Currant, with the Vpright cannot go. But ist a fault to Loue, as tis to hate? Nor, Loue nor Hate are faultie, being iust: But, tis a fault to loue (if too too late) Because such loue looks too like hatefull Lust; Then, if I loue (as Loue is vnderstood) My Vnderstanding much misguides my Will: Which of hir selfe [though blind] still goes to good, If blind Intelligence lad her not ill. Then tis the blame of blind Intelligence, And whats the cause Intelligence is blind? It blinded is by misreport of Sence: For, that doth blind the Soule, and lame the Mind. But must I sensuall seeme, to seem excus'd, Then, worse and worse falls out mine ill excuse: Twere better say, by Loue I am abusd, Sith I, to loue, haue offred much abuse. Abusd by Loue, without my Lusts consent! That is too strange a strength for Loue, or Lust: And eithers powr in me, is impotent: For, how boiles Bloud, that long since is addust? Wel, be it as it may, it seems my might Giues way to what it would, not what it should: Which on the bent of my Minds Motions light Puts these right Lines of Loue which long will hold. But if they breake when my Mind is vnbent Now shal they breake, for I eu'n now repent. Qualis vir talis oratio. Faces do not more varrie in their Formes Then Wits in shapes, though most be shapelesse Wits: For, breeding base, oft well-shapt Wit deformes; So, that it comes off comly, but by fits, And the most part are better fed, then bred; (But, they that feeding want, want Wit, and Wealth:) Then, most Mens Wits ate most il-fauoured, And what they show, by Wit, they show by stealth. Yet many Members of that Block-head Body (The Multitude) write idly, without stint; And he that's not in Print they hold a Noddy Because themselues are Noddies still in Print. Some Ryme, in rage; which rage puts Reason downe; Yet puts not Reason downe in their Rymes rage: These Arrs run rough, but their Rimes (if their owne) With reason runne like a thwart Marriage.. Yet if too smooth be this smart Simily (Although it be as rough as Rage, or VVrack) Their Rymes and Reason then, runne like a Cry Of brayning Beasts, that Rime, and Reason lack, Yet; will they force Minerua, not by Arte, But force, or feare, of their wittes strength, or stature (For, so these Asses weene) to take their part; So (like the Giants) fight gainst God and Nature. Some make, in Prose, greate Tomes their witts t'intomb, To bee as Monuments of Witt, for euer: Yet (sith those Monuments no Witt enwombe, (Being quite consumed) they continue neuer, The mor's the pitty that such stately Tombes (That oft haue gilt Couer gold without, though drosse within] Should bee gazd on by Learnings drugging Gromes And, by their Engin, razd; ô deadly sinne! Minerua blesse my Booke, Witts Monument, (A little Monument for lesser Witt] From such vsurping Beauclarkes violent, Lest they pul out Wittes eies their turnes to fit. Yet will I leaue it them, while fearelesse, I To lury goe in expedition, To trie their truth, or taste their Tyranny; The worst is Eylesse deposition: And if it happ, I hope Ile Sion gaine, Sith I the Cause of Sion will maintaine. When the ritch man speakes, euery man holds his tongue and what he saith is praised vnto the Clouds, &amp;c Ecclus. 13. 24. The Tongue oft uth hath said [then true it is) Though Indigence could speake like Salomon, The VVorld is mute, or saies he speakes amisse Sith but the golden Asse speaks well alone. Thus, golden Asses clawd by Claw-backs are Where they do ytch, (and but for clawing, itch) Yet (like Iades) pinch each other, being bare, And so the Ritch are praisd by poore and ritch; So, from the Wings of Sun-bright Seraphins Pull we our Pens, and make them Nectar flow Yet if we be not gilt, like Cherubins Our fame shall soare, in deed, but sink in show. This Curry-fauoring World is wise herein. (Though wise herein more then most wickedly) It knowes Detraction is esteemd no sin So that the great be greatly praisd thereby. And they are greatly praisd when all but Theirs Dispraised is (how lawdable soere) Their fruits (though Crabs) are sweet with Apple squires Who praise for Loue, and Loue for meed, or feare. They may be bold they wot well with the poore; Who, like pack-horses, beare when Asses bray: They well may wince, but they can do no more, And for their wincing They on them may lay. But heers the comfort, vpright after Times (Vpright, sith that which Is not, no way bends) Will Lawrell-Crowne them for their roiall Rimes: For Enuies selfe Desert, if dead, commends. Then, Rimes, how ere vnroial, run you on You may, in time, perhaps come neer that Crowne Meane while look for no Coronation But such as Enuy giues high-borne Renowne: Yet with your Wit, those after times perswade That some were mard perhaps ere al were made. Upon Apparitions in the Night. Ye grizly Ghosts that walk in shades of Night Like Shades whose Substance (though quite Matterlesse) The dayly fowle Offender doth affright Why make ye Darknesse Paper for your Presse? Do you imprint in Blacknesse, blacker formes Of matters worse? or in our Fantazie Impresse ye Figures raising Horrors stormes Or how in darknesse come you to the Eye? Do you but show? or show in Substances? Thicken you Aire (and so a Shape assume?) Or creepe you in some Corprall Essences? Or els the Sight deceaue with lesse then Fume? And why ô Hell hounds range you in the Night Out of Earthes Center, (your infernall Hold?) Lothe ye the Sunne? a or is the day too light, To do your deeds of Darknesse as ye would? Can ye dead Bodies truly actuate? And so such Bodies borrow of the Saints? Or can ye Wicked Bodies animate: So, take from God the cause of his Complaints? For if you Soules infuse into the ill You are the Father of their Spirites, and God Complaines without cause that they crosse his Will, Nor are they vnder naturally his Rodd. But He it is, alone, that Soules creates, Without whome nought was made that made hath bin: And Bodies good, and Badd he animates, Only he made not Death, first made by Sinne. And what is Sinne, but only meere Defect? So Sinne is nought: then nought hath Death begott; And Nothing should, in sense, haue no effect: So, Sinne, and Death Nought made, and Nought Is not. I would it were not, but, too true, it is, But is as Canker doth to Siluer cleaue: So, you; fowle Fiends, that loue such Filth as this Do leaue no Sinners, that no sinne do leaue. The purest Places you do hold an Hell; And Places most impure you Heau'n esteeme: The one do plague, the other please you well; And so of deeds, of either Kinde, you deeme. To be among the the deads Graues you are gladd; Wherein you seeke their senslesse Bones to griue: And loue to rattle them in signe you had The Conquest of Mankind through Adams Eaue. So by a Woman (your familier.) Y'are now familier with Men night, and Day: And which of both Familiers worse do warre With Men, and Reason, it is hard to say. These femine Familiars, but too oft Torment vs men as if you (friends) they were: Whose hard harts plac'd in their faire Bodies soft Plague whom that Beauty doth to them indeere. Yet some so filthy are that they are best When they are worst; that is, when fowle defame With vse of trading ill, their Trade, hath ceast, Then (with a Pox) they liue Chast to their shame. Thus haue we got double Familiars, Women and Diuels by a VVomans pride: Both vvhich familiarly, vvage secret vvars VVith Men, poore Men, that still the Brunt abide. But yet ô Passion tax not All, for Some: Some are so far from being Fiends, that they Are Saints and Angels, yet such so become Through Grace (not Nature) which their Natures sway. Many a vertues Virgin Grace hath made; The chief whereof was that wife full of grace: Who was a Mother-maide, which may perswade All womens foes their friendship to embrace: Yet many Maries full of Fiends there be, But no such Maries as this Saint we see. Suum cuique pulchrum. Why Self-conceit canst thou not brooke to see Or heare, or read, or scarce once think vpon The Parts which in another praised be? Wouldst like God, only wise, be praisd alone? And why so praisd wouldst be? for being blind Seeing not thy selfe on whom alone thou lookst? Or els for clawing thine own itching Mind? Or, which is worse, sith thou thy selfe mistookst? If these (besides which, I know nought thou hast) Be them for which thou wouldst be lawded so Thy Wits are gone, and thou thy selfe, art past For these do fleet, where staied Wit doth flo. Thou art but blind, yet scornst thou other guide: But leadst thy selfe in VVays most hard to hit: So, thou thy selfe still leadst thy selfe aside VVhere Error robs thee of Grace, Art, and VVit. Yet can the witty hardly shake thee off So hardly to their Headpeece thou dost cleaue: That though thou blindst, thou makst them see to scoff, Yet hardly take, what they so freele giue. Thou lou'st the Learned, sith they loue thee wel Yea, makst them oft to dote for loue of thee Thou makst them ween their Art doth Art excell VVhen they see not they deepe Arte cannot see: For, thou and enny (ay Consociates) VVill not admitte that Arte her selfe should show By others fingers; but the mynde inflates, VVhich scornes to looke for highest Arte so lowe. VVell, take thi pleasure, so thon me displease Displease me, as tho loust me, sith thou art A mental pleasant ticling damnd Disease And Ile loue that thou hatst this louing part Hang not aboute me, tempt me not too much: For I, though fraile doe hold vp hangers on VVhile I can stand, if me in loue théie touch, Though some such oft seeke my subuersion; And rest assur'd if me thou wilt not leaue Ile muse on nought but thy hopes to deceiue. Stultus stulta loquitur. Thoughts wel conceiued and words as faire, as fitt Al souldred with substancial semitry Best showes the life of Iudgement, Arte and Wit, Which best Pens haue worst labor to discrye. This is a grace that glorifies the Pen: That imps Fames wings to make her further flee, This is (like god) but seldome seene with men: Though in men by his power, and grace he be. Yet al suppose (thot cân but draw a Line That they can drawe the picture of this Power And that their workmanship is so diuine That like that Grace, it euer should endure. And through that self-conceit That is conceaud Which they do daily labour (in great paine) To bring to light, which by the World recean'd, Makes her Armes wery long it to sustaine. It often proues such spritelesse heauy Stuffe (As much mishapt as black, or Mistical: Yet ween they, They giue Rudenesse such a Cuff As turns him round, and breaks his neck withal: For Self-conceit will not perswaded be But that hir Bird is fairst, though black and fowle; Cheifly if she in night of Mystery See best abrode to wander like an Owle. Pens, whither will you? whither will ye flee Aboue the Compasse of your natiue powr? O senselesse Things! will you still Doing be The Muses, to their shame, thus to deflowr? Cease, or take Nectar out of Helicon, And let it flow from you as from that Fount; Such, only such, do Fames Wings pynion, But others make but gaggling Geese to mount. Yet, if you ween you were for Motion made, And were in motion while in Wings you were Fall to a Notary, or Scriuners Trade, Then may you moue right being in your Spheare. But ô! to register the Acts of Wit Forbeare, deer Pens, that make your selues so cheape; Sith for that Office you are far vnfit, And for your Laboure sowne, but Laughter reape: But if you'l needs be Lyning, yet take breth Least all the World do laugh your Lynes to death. Candidæ musarum ianuæ Among the faults we fell to by our fall No one diuides vs more from Piety Then doth self-Loue, which is the sum of all The fowl Deformities we caught therby: Hence flow our Follies, and crimes-capitall; This Fount (wherein, [Narcissus-like] we looke) Drownes vs in Blame, which Heaun, nor Earth can brook. Hence is it that we others glorious Guifts Do hold as base; and ours [though meer Defects] We do adore: and vse all cunning shifts To haue them held for glorious Effects! To this tend all our [Wit-purloyning] Drifts, Which we in others, held nor Wit, nor Sense: But, being Ours (stolne) both haue excellence. Hence is it that we can no more endure Anothers praises, then our owne dispraise: Hence, seek we others blemish to procure, That, on their foile, we may our glory raise: We cannot shine directly being obscure: Then, indirectly do we send some Beames Of glory-vaine, on Self-loues vainer Streames. Hence, Men of Art depraue each others Skill, Sith it they view with Luciferian Eyes: Hence, Poets do each others praises kill With keen Inuectiues that from hence arise: Hence, spare thay none whom they haue powr to spill: And they haue powr to spill themselues, and all [If they be great] that stand but neer their fall. That Poets should be made to vomit words] (As being so rawe Wittes Mawe could not disgest] Hath to Wittes praise, bin as so many Swords To kill it quite in earnest, and in Iest: Then, to vntrusse him [before Knights, and Lords] VVhose Muse hath power to vntrusse what not? VVas a vaine cast, though cast to hitt a Blott. O Imps of Phœbus, whie, ô why doe yee imploy the Pow'r of your Diuinity (Which should but foyle Vice from which we should flee?) Vpon impeaching your owne Quality? O grace the gracelesse, you that glorious bee: Who cannot grace your selues more then to give, A large allowance poore wittes to relieue. Written to my deere Friend Maister Nicholas Deeble. I am about it, good Will giue me leaue; Stirre mee not faster then my Witt c? moue: What though Hee bee my selfe, my selfe must giue My selfe, some time, to show my selfe my loue. Show? oh how Show? with Worthlesse Pen, an' ink Alas poore Show! No, Nic, it shall not bee: And, yet it must, my Pen must drinke, or shrink Sith it doth thirst so sore to write to Thee! Then, Ynckpott by your leaue, a Draught, or two Of gaully Liquor you must yeeld my Pen, Which (like a Potion drunke) will make him do His busnesse kindlie: A Hall Gentlemen. Now on, spruse Pen, fall now into your Measures, But stay, let me first number them in Minde: You are too hastie: soft, bee rul'd, take leysure: Now, Single, well sedd, now, thy Motion's Kind. Beware thou double not, a single friend Cannot endure suche Trickes: but, let thy Feete Bee plac'd to please, yet please not to offend, And in their motion Rime, and Reason meete. I loue Thee for thy Loue, lo, ther's my Reason: Nay, didst thou hate mee (as thou maist in time) Yet should I loue VVitts Salt, which Thee doth season, And, thy rare other Guifts, lo, here's my Rime. Thus farre, in measure, hath my prancing Pen To Thee approcht: Pen, homage now, why so: So should it bee, for, still the worser men Must paie the better, reurence which they owe. Now Sir, if my rude Pen may fetch your sin After the manner of a Cooshin-dance Leaue when you will, and, as you list begin, Your Discords to mine breede no variance: But, how so ere your Feete bee placd, they shall In Loue, iumpe with my Feete, Hands, Hart, and all. Bee thou my Damon then, and I will bee, At least a Pithias (if not more) to Thee! An Epitaph, or what you will, on the death of Maister Meece an harmelesse professed Foole who shall decease, when it shall please God, and him, made at his ernest request. Here low he lies that sate still with the Hie, For foolish Witt, and honest Knauerie. Neuer poore-Foole him selfe more wisely bare: For, hee gott loue of All, and tooke no care! Then, neuer Foole, on this World reeling Stage, Plaid his Part better, till forescore of age: Then, Time, and Death on him their force did proue, And tooke him from this Life, but not our loue. Now, make Wormes mirry, Meece, as Thou mad'st Men, Vntill in endlesse Mirth Wee meete agen: For, to that Mirth if now thou be not gon God knowes what is become of Salomon! Who, though Hee knew much Good, and did it to, Yet knew much Ill, which hee (much worse) did doo. But Thou, (like Adam (Meece) in innocence Knewst not so much as how to giue offence, Or, if thou knewst, thou did'st conceale the same; So, like a wise-Foole liudst thou with-out blame! Then, Meece sith Death doth play the Foole with Thee Showing his Teeth, laughing ill fauour'dly, Put on his Pate, thy Capp; and on his Back Thy pide-Coate put, with eu'rie foolish Knack: And say (sith hee sittes quite beside the Stoole) Looke on the Foole that cannot kill a Foole! For I poore Meece, that was a Foole, to Death, Haue made Death now my Foole, eu'n with a Breath: Sith I haue Cousnd him with only That That made mee to bee mockt, and laughed at: Namely, but with mine onely outward The outvvard garment of his Flesh suppressing the Soules vnderstanding. Weede Whereof poore naked Snake, hee stood in neede And, I, beeing wearie of it, gaue it, then, When I was like to liue with God, and Men. For what hath the wise-man more then the Foole Eccles 6. 8. Other Essayes vpon more serious and sacred Subiects. Mortall Life compared to Post, and Pare. When well I weigh the state of mortall Life, Mee seemes it seemes but too like Post, and Pare: Where eache Man seekes to winn, by ciuill strife; While most make show of more then what they are. One, vies it, beeing but a Knaue, perchance, Against a King, or Queene, or Paires of both, Our-brauing Cowardize, and Ignorance: And, others part Stakes, that to lose are loth. Some, Nothing seeme, to gett Some-thinge by it, These some, passe all, to goe beyond the rest: These, better their Good-fortunes by good Witt, Who crouch, as being worst, till they are best. Some, some-what giue, to fetch some others in, That so, at last, they may bee furthest out: These, little giue, by small guifts, much to winne, Yet oft so loose they all, to winne a Flout. Some, beeing Pa-riall, dare to do, what not? Vy, and re-uy and weene they all shall winn: When some One other better Cards hath gott, That they are furthest out, when furthest in! Some Elders, for re-uies, passe Pare, and Post, When lo, the Yonger shares, or Doubles it: Then fretts the VVinner, for his wynning, lost, Sith foolish Fortune Conny-catched VVitt. Some, vy, and reuy faceing, so, to foile; That haue no Games, but game some seem, with griefe: The while the rest haue game to see their spoile, Who yet, out-brau'd, do blush, sith they were chiefe. Some, being Cock, like Crauens giue it ore To them that haue the worst Cards in the Stock: For, if the one be ritch, the other poore The Cock proues Crauen, and the Crauen, Cock! Some, hauing lost the double Pare and Post, on in direct helpes Make their aduantage on the Purrs they haue: Whereby the Winners winnings all are Lost, Although at best, the other's but a Knaue. Pur Ceit deceaues the expectation Of him, perhaps, that tooke the Stakes away; Then, to put Tant hee's in subiection: For, Winners on the Losers oft do play. Flush is ore-borne oft by a better Flush: And Kings do conquer Kings but by the hand: As Stronger do the weaker euer crush: And still win of them Glory Goods, and Land. Some, look awry to see if they can spie Anothers Cards, thereby to make their game, Then on a Nineten times, perhaps they vy Knowing the other's blind, though they are lame. Some Pack, and others Cut, to breake the Pack: Some, shuffle cunningly, and shift thereby: Some, take a Card, and some a Card put back More then they should, to back their vice, and Vie. Some, haue Confedrates of the Lookers on: Who look as friends they were to all alike: Then with a signe of least suspition They note the Conny which they meane to strike. And if the Gamsters do play ouer-long, All, drawne, by all, the Butlers Box doth drawe: As Lawiers gett all bee it right, or wronge That's wonne, and lost, if Men bee long in Lawe: Thus properlie we may this Life compare, Vnto the bragging game of Post, and Pare. My Corollarie. Wealth, like a Pegasus, doth runne, or Flee, (As swift as Thought) especially from those That nere are gladd, but when at game they bee, Though all their Wealth thereby, in Post, they loose: And so when Wealth away is posted quite They runne away, or else play least in sight. Written to the Right Noble, and well-accomplished Ladie the Countesse Dowager of Pembroke. I grace inuoke, which had would make me pray, To Thee (great Ladie, greate, and glorious to:) I pray to Thee, as to a Comforts Staie, Then, lett my comfort still, bee tyde thereto. To Thee my whole Man is dyaphanall; The Raies of whose Witts Eyes pierce through mee quite; Who (like a Goddesse) seeth all in All Which in me is, or Fowle, Faire, Wrong, or Right. If ought be Faire, or Right in mee, it is Not mine, but Thine, whose Woorth possesseth mee: But if ought fowle bee in mee, or amisse, I hate for That, for, that its not for Thee: If I bee All amisse, I All assigne To Shame, and Sorow sith no part is Thine. Your Honors, while he is worthie of that Honor, I. D. Againe to Hir. Faine would I write that Witt nere yet concea'ud, But abiect Witt withstands my highe Desire: So diuerse write, and weene, yet are deceaud, For, Follies Flawes make light Witt so aspire. Then, cease to write. Then, is Desire displeas'd. Better Displease Desire, then Witt disgrace. Disgrace on VVitt hath at this Instant seisd. VVherefore? for halting. Then VVitt post apace Vnto the Point: now, now, thy quicknesse show: For, Fowrteene Lines thy Lymitts are, and They Are at a Point. VVhat if they bee? I know The more's my meede if now I VVitt bewray. The last Line next ensues: your praise, &amp; VVitt's behind, For,M mayA allR raiseY: yourP PriceE exceptM MenB beeingR rudeO ofK kind. Written to the right Honorable, and most iuditious Lord William Earle of Pembrooke that now is. Looke Lord with those sharpe Eyes of thine, with which (though larely open) In seeing thou see'st the least ore sights old, new, or done, or spoken: Looke on this Seale of simple Zeale, which though but courslie Carud, Containes the Impresse of thy praise thy vertues haue deseru'd. Truthes H?ds, VVealths Armes, VVits Eyes, Artes Tong, &amp; wised?s listning Eares Preuent Times Course, yonge yeares, conceiuing, bring forth many yeares! Faire featurd Soule! well-shapen Spright! in which subsisting bee, Grace, Goodnesse, Glory: Three in one, and One including Three! Grace, goodnesse giues, to Glory guides, such Guift, such Guide, such Glory God gaue, you haue, yet hauing hold vnsure, to shunne Vaine-glorie. So, so (sweete Lord) so should it bee; so was true Sapience Sourse, More wise then all, most wise in this, knew Things had but their Course. Who goes to Glory, Glorie shunes so shunes, so goes,, that yet Uaine-glorie shund, true glorie gaind, may him in glorie sett. Reade, Note, Search, Trie, Know, Show, Muse, Mount, aspird, againe descend; The lower Soules sinck in themselues, the higher they ascend! Tell mounting Witts thats too too light that Wisedome makes not weightie; Tell Motion it is worse then madd whose Motors not Almightie. Tel World its but the wayward Maze where Man is mazd and lost; Tel State it stands on Airy Propps, by Stormes still turnd and tost. Tel Wisedome shee is base if Shee mounts not aboue the Moone, Tel Humors, and tell Humoristes, their Humors change too soone. Tel Learning it is darke as Hell not mixt with light of Grace, Tel Councell, and tell At Lavv. Councellors they oft mistake the Case. Tel Bookes, though euer-blest some bee, yet are they but Informers, Tel them they should more blessed bee if they were still Reformers. Tel Artes they aske too much for Arte in asking all our time, Tel Armes they do but worke their Harmes, by Armes, and Harmes that climbe, Tel Earthlie Hopes they make vs seeke for that wee cannot finde, Tel, tell Worlds-Blisse it wanteth force to breede true Blisse in Mynd. Tel Sport it spoileth pretious Time, tell Time hees falslie true, True in his Course, ins Custome false, away steales, yet pursues! Tel Keasars (though they Cæsars are) their Nostrils Bound their breath; Tel Life (though during like the Sunne) it subiect is to death. Tel Wealth it wasts with earthlie Pompe, tell Pompe its but a Puffe, Tel Glory shee must bide the girde of Enuies Counterbuff. Tel, tel Fair-wordes, from fowle Mouthes sent, they feede, but fatten Fooles Tel Friends true Frindshipps no where learnd but in true Vertues Schooles. Tel, Loue that Hee an Idoll is; found, forgd adord by Fancie, Tel Flesh-enraging Lust shee is a Soule-confounding Frenzie: Tel Fauours they are Copper-gilt, vncertaine true, if true: Tel Fooles when Shadowes come before, their Substance nill ensue. Tel Lookes, where Loue in Triumph Tilts against vnfenced Eyes, They Lookes alure, by Lookes like Lures, which seeme true, yet are lies. Tel All that al is (al in All] beneath the Heaunly Coape, A Dreame, a Shade, a toile of Spirite, a base betraying hope. And lastlie tel thy Thoughts [sweet Lord] they in an Harr must rest That Honor holds for Life, and liues to dy ere dispossest. Here Sus Mineruam maist thou say, its true; yet say not so, Because it comes from him that liues to dy vpon thy Foe. I. D. Deus, ad quæ nos tempora reseruasti? Policarpus. Meete not an Harlot, least thou fall into hir Snares. Ecclus. 9. 3. Who so will keepe his Soule, and Body chast From Womans haunt, he must him selfe retire; Yea, though they seeme religious, and shamefaste: For, blushing VVomen most inflame Desire. Stand not vpon thy strength (though it surpasse) Nor thy fore-proued Chastnesse stand thou on. Thou, art not Holier then Dauid was? Nor wiser then was most wise Salomon? And aske the Prince of Earthlie Paradise, (Who, in perfection, was made most compleate) What power a Woman had him to intice To make him his owne bane, and ours to eate! If wee stand neere a Fall, wee stand vnsure, If neere the Fire wee warme, though Yee we were: VVe cannot striue with Death and longe endure; Nor Liue with VVeaknesse, but must weake appeare. To bee with VVomen still, yet know them not Is no lesse strange then to stand falling still: VVe cannot handle Pitch without a Spott, Although we handle it with Care and skill. Then, if thou wouldst bee safe, in saftie, feare; Sith feare doth make thy saftie more secure: For, too much trust is too much danger neere; And in the midst of Dangers none are sure. In greenest Grasse a Snake doth often lie And Loue begun in Spirit, oft ends in flesh: Flesh talls in smoothest Opportunity; And when she (drunken) reels, Sin riseth fresh. The Fiend, hir foe-like friend, doth neuer sleepe But wakes to tempt hir still with Time, and Place: In sweetest Hony he doth Poison steep, Which maketh Nature work in show of grace: Then, if thou wouldst not slide, from Women slip: For, Ill oft raignes in such good fellowship: Gratious is the end that ends all our paines. When, when, ô when shall I bid life farewell Wherein my Soule, and Body so ill fares? My Soule within my Body, Loathes to dwell Sith it doth dwell in such a World of Cares. Wherein the best are Briers, that scratching, hold What ere they catch vnto anothers harme: Whose Tenter-hookt Armes do, in Loue, infold No one but whom they spoile, and quite disarme. Where Men loue Men, not for that Men they are But simply for themselues; all whose respect Is swallowed vp with self-respecting Care, And commonly the Common good neglect. Where Fashions are, then Formes, more various: (Though scarse among a Million two are like) Where the most iust are lest iniurious Though Iustice their iniustice doth dislike, Where Faces want no graces to allure The Mynd to loue, so to betray the Mind: An holy kisse, in show, showes to assure The rather to faile Hope that seeks to find. Where oft Religion palliates Policy, And Saints are made a Sacrifice for State: Yea, heaunly Powres for Earthly Maiesty, Away goes all that lets Ambitions gate. Where holy Fathers do vnholy Deeds While yet they blesse their Sons that cloak their shame: And so the Hart of Piety still bleeds Because Hypocrisie still wounds the same. Where all is seeming, and Nought reall is: For all do couet only but to seeme: Ill seemeth good, and sorrow seemeth Blisse, And Men, but by their show do men esteem. Where the whole frame of Natur's out of frame, And at the point to be dissolued quite: Where VVit and Learning are both blind, and lame, Yet scorne, through pride, a Guide to leade them right. VVhere no man hath an Eare to heare, sith Eares Are now turnd all to Tongues, or Teeth, to gnaw: If one haue Eares none but himselfe he heares, As bound thereto by self-loues lawlesse law. Where Loue, and Lordship can no Riualls beare, That yet should beare with all that Grace doth brooke, Where euery thinge amisse is euery where And nought found good vnlesse it be in looke. Where vertue is despised though bright she bee, Yf she be bare; Yet Venus, bare, is lou'd: Where nought hath tast els, that is bare to see Yea, Truth it self if bare, is not approud. Where all and some make but the sum of al Vainst Vanities; for so at best they be: VVhere each one riseth by anothers fal, Yet mounts in vaine, for quickly fal must he. So on this Sorrowes Sea, [this VVorld of VVoe] Al falls to Earth, that riseth from the same: And so all Earthly Things do ebb and flo, And ebb in nature, as they flow in name. Then ô haue I not reason to desire My Natures dissolution, sith it is VVith these Ills conuersant, which do conspire To make it [like them] more then most amisse? Then, Death (the end of Il vnto the good) Enshore my Soule neer drownd in flesh, and bloud. Quotidie est deterior posterior dies. How many piercing Pens haue launct the Vaines Of this vaine World, to let her humors out? How many Satyres beate their tried Braines How, from this Ioynt sick Age to bite the Gowt? And yet like those anoyd with that disease, These Times haue rather rest then helpe thereby: For they displease them that do them displease; So rest renengd, but toild in malady. And oft those Surgeans are as humorous As are the Aches which they seek to heale; Who hauing Teeth, as sharp as mumerous, Through others, bite themselues, which seld they feele. Because themselues are senselesse of their Ills Which this obseruing World perceiuing well Measures their Medicines by their wicked Wills So loths their Corsiues, and themselues doth quell. But he that looks with well-discerning Eyes Into the worlds ineuitable woes Shal see it sick of mortal maladies; And wil (as from the plague] flie far from those. I see them well (though wel I canot see Sith I am Hood-winckt still with darke desires] And I confesse the World's the worse for me Though to the best my Spirit at worst aspires. Faine would I leaue this fardle of my Flesh In Fastings Charge; the lighter so to flye From these still following plagues which are most fresh When we are weariest of their company. But, lo the World still rounds me in the eare With Wind that sweetly in that Organ sounds, Which me alures to loue mirth, ioye and Cheare: So downe it beates my wil when it rebounds. Thus the Worlds heauy and vnholy hand My Sprit suppresseth that would faine aspire; And with my Flesh, conspires it to withstand With whom the Diuel ioynes in that desire. Thus do I rest in that Church militant, Which still with stands these three stil fighting Foes Stil warring with them til that strength I want To gard, with grace, their most vngratious Blowes. Then through my weaknesse am I forcd to yeeld VVho then, like Tyrants, triumph in my spoile And wrack my Hopes best haruest in the Field VVhich they haue got, so, feareful make my foile: And thus twixt good, and euil, Sin, and grace, I stil do, striuing, run a tedious Race! Enuy is blind and can do nothing but dispraise Vertue. The best conceit that euer Braine did breede (Though better borne then bred, or first conceau'd, May in good birth, yet haue such euil speed, That scarse the spirit of life may be perceaud: For, Emulation hath no patience (No more then Ignorance) to stand vpon The narrow search of strict Intelligence But dooms it dead, sith it liues so alone. That liues alone that singularly liues VVhich is the life of Singularity: To liue that life stil Emulation striues Or to obserue his skill that liues thereby. Enuy seemes pois'ned with anothers praise, Which as those praises swell, swells more, and more; Who, worne to nought, hir selfe (yet) only waighes, And weighes no others woorths, vnlesse too poore. But that shee seeketh to enrich alone, Not of Deuotion, but of damd desire To make the greater woorth the lesser knowne: For shee doth most ecclipse what is most cleir. Whie toile we then? or lose our golden Sleepes To g?ine (with golden Time) more glorious praise? Sith basest Enuy, highest Honor keepes, By whose dispight hir glorie oft decayes. It is because the longer after Death Our Fames do flee, the longer breathe they shall: For, Enuies winde doth vanish with our breath; And when our harts breake, broken is hir Gall: Then this doth comfort all that merit fame Vertue liues when Enuy dies with shame. Vincit qui pætitur. To seeke for ease where wee are borne to toile Is but to rest in toile, and toile in rest: To toile for ease where Slouth may worke our spoile, Is but, by ease, to bee ease dispossest: They fish, and catch a Frogg, which so do fishe That, saue the Soules repose, catch all they wishe, Its better farre to giue our Soules to rest In Patience, then in Pleasures, sith they doo Sweetly (like rubbings of an Ytch) molest, But, Patience gladds vs while Paines us vndoo; Then, giue mee Patience, and let Pleasure go, As that which workes, in sport, our ouerthro. That comfort I detest that takes from mee Vncessant sorrow, for vncessant sinne: Nor, loue I that sharpe sight that all doth see Saue onely That which is my selfe within: That Knowledge is as coorse as counterfett, That makes Men vtterlie them selues forget. Giue mee an Hell of paine, so I may haue The Heauen which a Conscience sound doth giue: Sith hee is but vncessaunt Sorrowes Slaue, That, sick in Soule, in pleasures Heau'n doth liue: If Patience Hiue the Soule in Sorrowes Swarmes, She Heau'n enioyeth in an Hell of Harmes. Who rightlie knowes him selfe, him selfe contemns: And though men clappe their hands in his applause, Yet hee their praises, with him selfe, condempnes By euidence of Conscience, &amp; hir Lawes: The cause why others flatter vs, with ease, Is, wee our selues our selues too wel do please. How much the more our knowledge al surmounts So much the lower we in in Hel shal fal, If, when we come to make our last accounts, Our vertue be not found much more then al: And simply better t'were from Sinne to flee, Then cunningly Define what Sinne should bee, With brightest Knowledge to liue most obscure Is to find Hea'n, which in that Light doth lie: Yet like the Sunne, through thick Clouds couerture, To light the World that Men may walke thereby: So, doth the Highst obscure him selfe from sight While all that see, do see but by his Light. What neede wee seeke quaint words, &amp; Phrases fine Sith by one Word all Truth is knowne alone; Which Word made al things by his pow'r Diuine: So, all things by that VVord are only knowne: Then, they that learne this onelie World to know Know more then World, or Witt it selfe, can show. All other Knowledge doth but vex the Sp'rite, Though hir it makes much more intelligent: In it, alone, is Knowledge, with Delight; Sith it the Witt, doth cleere, the Will, content; Then they that know this single-simple Worde Do know much more then Knowledge can afforde. No State so holie, nor no Place so Sole (Much more no Science) but is full of Doubt: Cares, creeping, fill each solitarie Hole; And many more vexations swarme without: And till wee leaue the World, or wayward Will, Wee beare with vs a VVorld of trouble still. Then, tis not shun'd by flight, vnlesse wee could Flie from our selues, (our aduersaries chiefe:) For, while our selues our selues haue fast in hold, Wee hold our selues to Sinne, and so to Griefe: For, they that griue not when they do transgresse, Short pleasures feele, not extreame wretchednesse The lack of VVill in faith still fixt to bee Is the sole cause wee want our true repose: For, who so blinde as they that will not see, And, who more subiect to hard ouerthrowes: Ineuitable Sorrowes still attend On none but on the wilfull, past their end! To shunne the Tempter wee must shut the Gate Of our Intelligence against his Charmes; Or, lest he should our Will predominate, Repulse him from our VVitt, by force of Armes: If yet he stands, vpon him straight Discharge Truthes double The old, and nevv Testam?t. Cannon, with a double Charge. Then will he flie, or if he stands, he falls; For, nothing can resist his Ordinance VVho makes the meekest Mindes his Generalls That, yeelding, fight, and foile by sufferance: O tis a wondrous Conquest when a Foe By ouercomming hath the ouerthro! The longer wee forbeare him to withstand The weaker are wee when wee do resist, And much the stronger is hee to commaund; For, Thoughts are actiue when they do persist: Because Thoughts trauell, with Delight, in paine, Till He bee borne, and they conceaue againe. Greate Troubles well are borne, by bearing small As Milo bare a Calfe, turn'd Bull at last; They in the roughest Tempests needs must fall That are orethrowne with eury little Blast: In Summe, the Summe of all our earthlie ioy Is in our patient bearing all annoy. Againe. [If Hope and Patience did not hold the Hart] If Hope and Patience did not hold the Hart From being squiz'd to nought with gripes of griefe It could not bee, by Nature, nor by Arte, But Death would hold that Seate of Life, in chiefe: For, in this Life Deathes do so multiplie (Or Dolors, at the best, farre worse then Deathes) That wee do liue no longer then wee die. VVho lyuing die, and breathing spend our breathes. So that in patience, only wee possesse The Soules we haue, which haue the Liues we hold; And Hope sustaines the Soule in heauynesse: So patient hope is fraile Lifes strongest Hold. If both those vertues then in one must ioyne To make our Soules, and Bodies ioyne in one (Els Death, and Dolor, will fraile Life purloyne VVho ioyne to vnioyne that Coniunction.) VVee must inuoke the Heaun's to giue vs Hope VVell arm'd with Patience, sith wee liue thereby Secur'd in Dolors, which to Death lie ope, And makes vs liue, when Death and Dolors die. Then, patient Hope, the Soule of our Lifes Soule, Arme thou my Soule thereby to gard hir life, And Passions furie with thy pow'r controule; So shall I striue in rest, and rest in strife: For no way looke I, but my sights annoyd VVith Troopes of Sorrowes, menacing my wrack; And, in my spacious Mynd, no place is voyd For Campes of Cares that seeke my Soule to Sack: For if I liue, I can but liue in sinne: And if I sin (I ioy) I can but grieue, So when sin ends, my griefs and Cares begin And cease not til I cease to sin, or liue, Yet, what I would He knows that knowes my wil, Which [though peruerse] is prest his grace to serue: Which Grace ingenders Hope on my Good wil And makes me patient, sith I ill deserue. Thus patient Hope, by Grace got on my Will, Doth make me wel to liue, in spight of Ill. In vindicando criminosa est celeritas. Whhat gaine gets witlesse Courage but the losse Of Life, or Limb, Lands, Contry, Goods, or fame, Or to the Gallowes goes by weeping Crosse, And, desprate, dies to his Soules death, and shame. Would any that had Courage, Wit, and Grace (As point to part this life) Mans life bereaue To make a crying Sin his Soule to chase, And neuer, till she dies, the Chase to leaue? None would that would be wise and valiant: Then so we ought to liue, as dying stil, Sith of our death our life is ignorant Then who (but Fiends) would liue in Hel, to kil? Admit in priuate Quarrels (fist to fist) Thou hast slaine al that durst thy powr oppose: Nay say that no man durst the same resist Sith like a God, thou couldst of life dispose, Were it humane? much lesse were it diuine To glory but in bathing but in bloud? Were it not sauage, and too Leonyne For any that would faine be great, and good? O Then what Quarrell but the publike one Can make a wise, and valiant man to fight? What staine takes honest reputation By taking wrong, to make it selfe more right? Can but the Lye (one silly Sillable) (By Time made much more hainous then by Truth) Make great men make their Humors sutable, To Horsleaches, that haue, by bloud, their growth? Or can the Loue but of an hateful Queane [For such no better be, though Queens they are] Broche pretious bloud, as if that were the meane To measure out sound Loue for such crackt Ware? Can but an od Looke, or a simple Smile (Which may be taken wel as wel as ill) Make men their Harts and Hands with bloud defile: So, bloud (like water) for but Looks to spil? Then Men are Monsters, Monsters! al too good Is eu'ry name that is too monstrous For such as liue, alone, but to suck bloud, Which al do hate, that are magnanimous: For all great Minds desire such things to do That are as good, as great; els, scorne the same For Valor theyl be prais'd, and Vertue too, Els Valor they esteem the price of Shame. And no where can the same so wel be showne As with offensiue Armes in Contries right: And with defensiue, guard the ouerthrowne From the Oppressors mercilesse despight. Els Fights vnciuil, sauage, and too bad For Beasts, much more for Men, whom Angels serue, All Quarrels els, are monstrous, moody, mad, And mortal hate of God and man deserue. Yet by such sucking bloud we see some swel Vnto that Greatnesse that they scarce can hold; On Gore they ground great Howses where they dwel VVhich often sink, in bloud, as Reason vvould, Many that haue nought els but daring Harts And leafe their Liues, for Nothing to Dispaire On this Worlds Stage, do oft play Princes parts, To which they climb by Bloud, a slppry Staire, And desprate Resolution so is held Vp by the Chin, while it doth bath in bloud (By Greatnesse, of smal worth) that it doth weld, The world at wil, and seld, if ere, withstood. Yea, oft it makes Authority to shake Sith they owe others liues that loath their owne; And so it doth his owne Conditions make As if it could at wil put vp and downe. This Ladies loue; for, this doth Ladies win, (Faint Hart they say, (Ile ow the rest for shame) This is a VVorld-commanding gracefull sin In the Conceit of each conceited Dame! He that dares ioule together highest Heades (Though he may faile in that too high attempt) The High his haughty Resolution dreads, VVhile he, as Crauens, holds them in Contempt. Lo thus may Reason reason gainst a Wrong That Passion doth approue, and vse, as right: I vs'd [the more my vice] this vertue long If it be Vertue vitiously to fight. VVhat now! vaunts VVit, and vailes the same with skil? Would it be knowne it was to Courage knit? Do I condemn, yet glory in mine ill? So, crack of Courage with, and without Wit? Here lie I open to Wits priuy Nips, Or open Thumps, lay on, Wit spare me not: And Ile oreturne as thou shalt offer Trips Sith through my weaknesse thou the best hast got. Yet stay thy Wisedome, wit, and hold thy hand, Vse thou the Conquest like a Conqueror: That is, foile thou the ill which thee withstand; But, let the faultlesse neuer feel thy powr, For tis not simply ill a truth to tell, (Though it perhaps be told for scarce good end) And doubtful words, with Letters Loue doth spel That alwaies only, doth the best intend. But sith al those that know me, knew me such As once I was, my Lines are of lesse force (Vnlesse my hate, of what I was, I touch) To dravv Sword-dravvers to a quiet Course. For stealst thou Theefe, and yet exhorst to Truth? Or Kilst thou Butcher, yet dehortst from Bloud? Shal he perswade vs who reuenge pursuth That mercy is the best reuenging mood? I am turnd Crauen, and am held therein By Loue, which holds for true diuinity, That Faiths Deuotion is but deadly sin If it be not deuout in Charity. Then he that makes his life a lasting Brall And seems to feed on nought but Wounds, and Gore May pray for grace, to change his life withall, But, other praiers make his sins the more, And they that loue their sins to multiply Stil let them pray in Hate, and thirst of Bloud: So shal they liue (while they make others die) To dy the death of Dogs, in damned moode. Now, if this Charme of Words want violence To make these brauing Spirits lesse bloudy-bold And bring them into Loues Circumference, Sufficeth me I Coniur'd as I could: But, if thereby they wax more turbulent I can but rue, but they shall more repent! Blessed is the Man that doth meditate honest things by Wisedome. Ecclus. 14. 21. Did Wisedome write, or speake the world to please Shee were not wisedom in a pleasing Sence: Then who doth please with any one of these Doth please vnwisely, but the World, or Sence. Then are they worldly wise, or sensual That doe soe write or speake; but none of those Can be in them whose words can sweeten Gall Which Sweets do rest where sweetest Soules repose. And they repose but in the Sweet of Sweets [God only wise] or Bodies of the Blest: In whom true Wisedome, Grace and Nature meets, Whose gracefull VVords are naturally exprest. If VVords inchaunt the Sense, and not the Soule That Charme of VVords coniures no holy Spright: For, Such, such VVords (not Such, such VVords) controule: Soule-pleasing VVords must, then, bee rare, and right. Yet though a Sonnet bee as right, as rare For Number, Measure, VVaight, or Noueltie, Yet, if it sounds so, but to Senses Eare, The Soule, as harshe, doth hold that Hermonie. Then all our Straines that relishe double Loue, (Sweet double-Relishe, worthie treble praise) To Soule, and Bodie) Soule and Body moue. (VVith ioy) to listen, as to Angells Laies! These bee the Aires that gett the Aire of Fame, [Of Fame whose Aire, diuinely is refinde] That feeds, with purest praise immortall Name; Fitting the nature, of each mightie Minde. And, they are only mightie that disdaine, All that, that disagrees with Mightinesse: As is light Loue, fraile Fancies, Shadowes vaine, VVeake VVitt, base Blisse, VVorlds weale, or VVretchednes. Then [as to Nature curst, but kind to Grace] I here haue made a Rodd my selfe to beate, VVhose highest reach in Straines of Loue, is base, Sith Lightnesse measures them with heauie Feete. Yet if this Lightnesse heauy make the Light In Summing vp my Numbers totall Summe, I hope the weight thereof, will bee of weight Their Lightnesse [if it rise] to ouercome: For, they are too Light that in Those but waigh VVhat Lusters, not what Louers ought to say. Sic transit gloria Mundi. Life, stay; or if thou wilt not, let my Soule Moue with thee to the Rest, Thou mouest to: The Twyne, by which thou hangst, Time vp doth rowle On Heau'ns round reeling Spheares, which thee vndoo: Then ô my Soule let Truth thy Vertues woo. To ioyne their Force t'inforce th'infirmitie Of this Lifes excesse in Deficiency, For, truth to say, wee Bee, and Bee not bothe; Wee Bee, in show,, but Bee not as wee ought: If then wee Bee not but in show, in sooth, Wee Are as if wee Were not, Ought, and Nought, Dying as soone as wee to Life are brought: Twixt Generation, and Corruption The Meane inclines but to destruction. And, if we straine the Circle of our Thought To comprehend some Essence of the same, It is as if to catch a Shade we sought, Or clos'd our Fist to hold the blast of Fame: Yet, that is Aire, but Man is but in Name: Then, looke how much a Name hath beeing found, So much hath Man, which is a Sound, vnsound. Vnsound it is: for, were it sound it were That which fraile Man is nothing lesse then like: For, Sounds haue Beeing: yea, they plaine appeare, And, on the Organs of our Hearing strike: Of which those Organs are, with vs, to seeke: For, while the Sound resoundeth wee are gonne: So, are wee So?ds that haue not Time, nor Tone! Then, Reason seeking for a reall Thing Of Humane-nature, fowly is deceau'd: Because the same hath no continuing, But runnes hir Race ere really perceau'd: Whose Life, of Life, is instantlie bereau'd: A Dreame? a Shade? ô no: its not so much, A shadow of a Dreame, at most, is such. That's the Similitude the Lord of Life Doth vse to show our Liues vnbeeing Beeing: What! in the World, where all things are so rife, Is nought but Nothing to the same agreeing? Which not appeares, nor scarse suppos'd by Seeing! And, beeing scarse supposed: then it is To Nothing next, or Nothing's like to This, And, as we cannot bathe twice in one Brooke Sith still it runnes the same and not the same: So, twice on our Estats wee cannot looke And see it One, so soone it alters Frame: Wee are and are not straite, like Light'nings Flame: At once wee go, and come ye, go, ere come, VVhich is the Summe of all of All, and Some! And, if wee liue long Lifs extremitie VVee die as many Deathes as Ages liue: The Life of Youth, is Death of Infancie: The Death of Youth, doth Life to Manhood giue, So, of the rest Death rests in Lifes Depriue: To Day dies Yesterday, to Morrow shall This Day bee dead, and Night's their funerall! VVee change each Day as Dayes do rise, and fall: And, what is chang'd continues not the same: If not the same, the same Is not at all: For, Change transformes the Nature, and the Name, Our Passions are as fickle, as too blame: Now This, then That, then next to This, and That, Still changing, well I wott, t'I wott not what. Thus, is our Sence deceaud, mistaking that Which but appeares, for that which is, in deede, And so our Sence, our Sence, doth Captiuate To mis-conceit, Corrupting Fancies Creede, VVhich taks Not-beeing in true Beeings steede: For, that is truly-false what ere it is, That is but true in Show, and so is This. To BEE, in deede, æternall is to Bee, To Bee æternall, is to Bee alone: To Bee alone, excluds the Pronowne, VVee, Yet VVee do stand by that Trin-Vnion, Though wee therewith hold no Comparison: And yet wee looke most like that Trinity In Vnderstanding, VVill, and Memorie! Tim's like a Leaking Vessell which containes Both Generations, and Corruptions: The Fates (like Danaus daughters) take the paines To fill the same, as oft as out it runnes; From whencè do flow Times daughters, Slaues, and Sonnes: And these are Tearmes that to Times Turnes agree Before, and After; Hath byn, and shall Bee. Which show that no Time (but Æternitie) Hath Beeing; for, wee cannot say that Is Which yet, is not; and, Now, doth cease to Bee; Or if wee say Time Is, Time shrinks at This; Which cannot stand to proue that Terme for His: For, NOW (the Notion, which Denoteth Time) Is Past, while Present, and is Last, while Prime! Then, if Time Bee, it is Past, or Future; The Past, Is not; the Future, Beeing wants: Because it is to come, and most vnsure, For, Time still houers where no Beeing haunts, Sith Time, and Beeing still are Discrepants: Then, That (as erst was said) Eternall is Which Is, in Deede, and only ONE is This! Of whome it cannot properly be sayd Hee Hath Byn, or Shall Bee: These Turnes of Time Can neuer stand with That that's euer staid, Yet farre aboue Times highest Turnes doth climbe, And, is the First, and Last, and lasts in Prime: Who by this NOW, spreads his Æternitie Vnto the boundlesse Bounds of Deitie! For, hee is ONE, and One Is, and no more! For, as what Is, ought to bee onely ONE: So, onely ONE ought to Bee euermore, Which Is, still Is, Is, only, and alone The Cause of All, And caused is of None! To Him, alone, that Is, and only Is Bee only Praise, sith Praise is only His! Non est mortale quod opto. Respice finem. When as I heare Times sober Tongue (the Clock) Call on me eu'rie howre to minde mine end. It strikes ny hart with feare at eu'rie stroke Because so ill Time, Life, and Breath I spend. Then straight resolue I, to bestow them all Vpon that Lord of all, that gaue them mee When lo, the World vpon mee straight doth call And bids me look to it, left poore I be, Twixt these two Calls I parted am in twaine: The first my Spirit, the last my Flesh attends: So twixt them two my pleasure is but paine: For each the other euermore offends. Sin tenders me al Ioyes, that rauish Sence, And Sense doth pine if from Them It be held: Grace offers Ioyes of much more excellence, And faine my Spirit would with Them be fild. But in fraile Flesh Sense such a Cæsar is That It Commands it to withstand the Sprit, While it doth feed the Flesh with Earthly Blisse: And so, my Sprite is vext with that delight. Thus, while I am distracted in desire Time (in his Language, after some Howrs pawse) Tels me he flies, and bids me to retire Before Confusion catch me in his iawes. O Time (that thus endeerst me to thy loue) I constantly adore thy ficklnesse, That neuer mou'st, but dost my Sences moue To mind thy flight, and this lifes trickelnesse. O that I could make thee Æternity! And honor thee, for this, vvith state diuine That with the God of Glory, thou and I Might, like the Sun and Moone, for euer shine! Teach me, ô learned long-experienc'd Time To glorifie thee with some heaunly Art, Whose humble Muse would to thy Temples climb To Lawrel-Crowne them, ere from Thee I part. O let me be the Triton of thy praise: Teach me to Trumpet foorth thyne Excellence: Let me [though most vnworthy] grace thy Dayes With all that may delight Intelligence. Let me by thee [deer Time] be brought to Death Ere I abuse thee in the least degree. For, he wins Blisse that doth but lose his Breath To be still found, from Times Abuses free. Then now, ô now, (sith novv my Daies decline) Let me this Moment enter in the Way Of Vertue, Grace, and holy Discipline, And being in, thence, let me neuer straie Procrastination doth but Plagues protract, Due to protraction of Conuersion: Then, Time with Plagues my wayward Will Coact To turne to Grace, ere my subuersion. Let it suffice that I haue thee abusd Since I was borne, in Wrongs not to be borne: Then be thou, by me, hence foorth rightly vsd, Or let me, by Thee, die, or liue forlorne: For, I am wery, now of wronging Thee, Then let me flee from Vice as thou dost Flee. A blind man cannot see the default of his Eyes. Well, what of this? this restlesse toile for State, What is the end of that which Care begins? And, without Worlds of Guifts, gets Worlds of Hate, Is this the All Pride (at All casting) wins? Must Truths Disciples, Graces Officers, Sacred Apostles (Saints by calling) striue For Headship by vnciuill ciuil Wars Though they beleeue they meanly ought to liue? Nay, but for this, if those resplendant Spirits That do surround the highst Celestiall Throne Aduance themselues aboue their place, and Merits For which they worthily were ouerthrowne, Then, Iudgement where dost thou enthrone thy State That should be in the Kingdome of the Braine? Dost thou that Seate (sith Pride vsurpes it) hate? And only in the Humble dost thou raigne? Then, where are they? true Iudgement tel me where? If neither with the Angels, Saints, nor Men They may be found, (as it doth well appeare) Where shall we seek for these so humble then? Or is the totall Summe of All, but One Who was made truly humble for vs all? And dost thou rest in him (meek Lamb) alone Leuing vs to our selues to rise, or fall? Then, woe to vs that mad are for thie want, And doe we wot not what in what we doe: Who seeke, for nought, each other to supplant: For, Lordships haue their Lodes made fast thereto. We striue for That which bringeth vs but strife With griefe and care among, oft wrack vvithall: We venter life, to win a vveary life; And rise, by all meanes, by all meanes to fall. So vve be vp but for a day, vve deeme Our Neck vvel broken; ô its vvorth a Neck But for an howre a King to Be, or seeme Vnto his Mates before to giue the Check. If vve can catch a place aboue our Peers (Although vve come thereby by peerlesse sin) We vveen vs no small fooles (as it appeares) When vve [alas the vvhile] stark mad haue bin. Such is our Iudgement, snch our temperance, And such the stare of those that State affect; Whose State, and Staie hath such continuance As they that seek it; no time in effect! Then, ô my Soule since thou canst thus discourse (As many can whose Courses are stark nought) Be better staid, or run a better Course Far from the rise of any mounting thought. Look in the Inwards of these outward Things; And note the Lyning of the roialst Robe; Its powdred Ermyne, pepperd to vvith Stings That, like a Nettle, makes the vvearer rub. If thou affect a Kingdome, let it be Heaun, or the happy Kingdome of CONTENT: Which blessed Kingdomes are ordaind for Thee If thou affect but thine owne gouernment. Be Queen but of thy selfe and thou shalt be In Heaun Crownd vvith Immortality, Where Saints, and Angels shall stil honor thee, For swaying vvel thy little Signiory. And sith thy Pilgrimage is almost past Thou needst the lesse Viaticum for it: For, being tird to lode thy selfe at last, With needlesse Trashe, would show nor grace, nor witte. Care for no more then thou maist beare, with speede, To beare thy Charges through this Vale of woe. Superfluous things giue others that haue neede, The lesse thy Lode the better thou shalt goe. Little serues soone-suffized Necessity [Whose Stomack, smal and cold disiests not much) But nothing can Opinion satisfie, Which beeing more then ful for more doth grutche. The greedy-ritch doe Jnstructa inopia est in diuitijs cupiditas. want the wealth they hold Who pine with Tantalus amidst their Store; And (Midas-like) eu'n famish with their Gold, The more they haue, their misery th? more. The next degree to Nothing Nature serues Sith she wth lesse then Little is content, The Hedge-rowes meate, the Riuer drinke reserues To keepe her in good plight, and better bent, The Birds finde meate for seeking euery where, The Highest hand stil strowes it in their way; And so may temprate men stil finde it there Where ere the Birds doe finde their stomack Staie. For Cresses, Rootes, Hippes Havves, Sloes, and such Cates, Are Common, (as the Aire) to take, and eate, This meate serues Nature though it serue not States, And longest liuers had no other meate. Let Gluttons glutt their Gutts vntil they crack With all the Kickshawes Cookrie can deuise; And let them lay on lode vpon their Back Of gaudy Geare; thou needest none; then be wise. Puft-panch doth soon'st the Kite a pudding yeelde; Full Gorges belk, if not much rather spue, Most fulsomely: for being ouerfilled, It selfe with hate doth then it selfe pursue. At Best; these ful Ones can themselues but stretche Vpon their Iuory Bedds, or feede their lust: For, they must still be feeding til they catche That which wilfeede on them til they be dust. And what's a costly Cote but comberous Vnto the Maker and the Wearer too; To keepe off cold and heate we Clothes shoulde vse, Which Howse-wiues cloth doth Without more a doo. And so the same be sound, and sweet, we may In Clothing of that kind best stir, or stand; When as these Garments ritch, and ouer gaie Do rather vs, then vve do them, command. If Garments must distinguish needs, Degrees [Though Vertue makes the plainest Coat to shine] Yet more then needs with no Degree agrees: So saith King Iames, so saith the Word diuine. No more of this; ynough, if not too much (But nere too much against too much is sed) Is sed hereof, and Great ones will but grutch Sith with their Busines I am busied: They hird me not: then, profferd seruice stinks, No more my Muse; thy Lady on thee winks. There is no greater plague then Boldnesse and Powr, when they are accompanied with Ignorance. When Heaun and Earth, and al their Furniture, Were made, their maker made Man last of al; As being his Master-peece, chiefe Creature, For whom the rest were made: He, Generall. To whom such perfect Wisedom was assignd That without Learning He knew all that was: And namd each Thing according to their kind VVhich Names, to vs (as we) from Him, do passe. VVho being thus made (made, I may double say, Sith He was double made, made Man, and Great: Great, like his God, Gods Creatures all to sway) And, in an Earthly-Heaun, held his Seat: VVheras He would, He liud: so in his VVill Rested His life, or death, His VVeale, or VVo: And, while His VVil his Makers did fulfill So long he knew but what he ioyd to know, Hee knew al that was made was perfect good. But knew, saue God, nought vnmade, perfect Euill) And so He knew not, or misvnderstood, The name and nature of the craftie Diuel. He liu'd as free from VVant, as Wickednesse As long as in his Good-wil was no want: Then Earth bare fruit, vntill'd, in blest excesse: For God himselfe the same did sow, and plant. Riuers of Nectar ran an golden Sand (With siluer-cleerenesse) through that Pardice; That, had he thirsted, Drinke was strait at hand, And all that might him free from preiudice. The Tree of Life (to keep off Age, and Death,) Ther stil did florish, in eternal springe: So, like to Gods, immortall was His Breath: For, all he Fedd on Health to Him, did bring, So, his Flesh, health: His Spirit, tranquilitie Enioyd, in height of highest excellence, Which height came neere the high'st Felicitie: For, with Him God still made his residence. Hee naked was, and yet Hee knew it not: For, Cold, or Heate could tell Him no such thing; Much lesse could Shame: for, Shame of Ill's begott; And Ill hee knew not, nor whence It did spring. The Spring of ioy (the High'st) did euer feede His passing pleasures Streames, with fresh supply: So, still hee was as farr (in show, as Deede) From want of Ioy, as ioyes sacietie. The Cause whereof, in Him wrought rare Effects, Who, without Labour, his Lords Heasts could keepe: Whose Heart burnd, like a Beacon, with Affects that show'd, in Danger, he did neuer sleepe. Who if hee stirr'd, and exercis'd his Limbes, T'was not for neede, but them to recreate: Which stirr'd not till in Pleasures Seas he swimms: For, still he bathd therein, in restfull state! And yet the more those boundlesse Seas to make With new Spring-Tides of Ioy, [as yet vnfelt) God, of his Ribb, a fleepe, makes him a Make, On whome, (awake) for ioy, his Hart doth melt. And seeing Hir [for all he saw he knew] Bone of my Bone, Flesh of my Flesh (said he) This Creature is: for, in my selfe the grew, And as my selfe Ile loue, hir while we Be. This! nay (alas) This naught is to the Good That He enioyed in that earthly Heaun, Which by Mans Thought cannot be vnderstood. Whereof [alas] we through him are bereaun: For, He was warn'd but one Tree not to touch, The Tree of Knowledge, by which well he knew He naked was, and sham'd to know so much: For Shame doth Euil euermore ensue. Then euil was it that he knew, and did, When through his serpentine seduced wife He tasted of The Tree which was forbidd: So, Lost wee, with Him, Paradice, and life, None otherwise then by our Lawes wee see The Sons plagu'd for the Sires successiuely; For, if the Sire a proued Traitor be Hees plagu'd him selfe, and his Posterity. Which with highst Iustice, iust proportion holds; So wills the Highst, whose Will giues Iustice forme Whose Grace true Iustice euermore infolds Then neither can or will he It deforme. Hence comes it that from Loue we fall to Lust (Fowle Lust thats but the Excrement of Loue) And hence it is we proue in both vniust When Lust another Way our Mind doth moue. Thus was a Woman made the Instrument Wherewith the Deuil did mans Eare allure To heare the Syren Sins first Straines consent, Which drue him on to Death, which vve endure. And vvhat but Wo-men cause our Sonnetting. Wherein we show vvhat languishnes vve haue Within our Soules for them, which often bring Our Minds to naught, and Bodies to the Graue? Whose Tongues drue vertue from the Tongue of Eue (If it be Vertue vvhich to Vice doth draw) To make vs loue, then, What they List, belieue: For, Lou's as free from Reason, as from Law. O VVo-men (that vvere made, but for Mens sake To helpe, and comfort them in weale, and wo) Why do your selues your selues their plaguers make, And Crosse the Cause of your creation so? Do not, o do not so degenerate: From what ye should be, by creation: You giue vs life, and life abbreuiate: So make and mar our Generation: But if you wil be like your Mother Eue. When you haue vs vndone, helpe vs to liue. In iudicando criminosa est celeritas. To cut off life by Law of such whose Crimes Fall out as euill, from an hopefull good May proue, though iust, iniurious to the Times Wherein they liue, in deed, or likelihood: For, Iustice though she equall be to all Yet, by aduice of Prudence she doth spare Hopefull Delinquents though they fowly fall Only because they oft most hopefull are: For had Miltiades at first bin slaine When he in Chersonesus tyranizd, Where had the Battaile bin got on the Plaine Of Marrathon, that's so immortalizd? Or els had Cimon, or Themistocles Bin done to death for their lasciuious life (For vvhich proscribd was Alcibiades) How had the Athenians conquest been so rise? The Battailes neere the flood Eurimedon Had not bin gaind to their past, gaineful good; Nor from the Mountaine Artemision Had they sent streaming downe their Foe-mens Bloud: For, royall Mynds, greate Harts, and actiue Hands (With nimble Wit among) can nought effect But what with wonder (if not glory) stands, Sith meane Attempts they do (as base) reiect. Nor can their Natures motion idle be That is so restlesse quick, and violent, (Still working like a Billow of the Sea) Til it bee staid in some moode premanent. But as vnskilfull Husbandmen reiect, The fattest Grounds sith they beare Weeds, or worse: When expert'st Husbands those in chiefe ellect Sith well they wott, fatt Grounds make fatt their Purse. So do, at first, greate Witts, and haughtie Sprights Produce strange fruits that feede but leane Decay Which wee detesting weene they had their rights To bee cut off, and ridd out of the way: Which doth proceede from iudgment most deprau'd, Though in desire that Iustice might take place, Sith if those Men had bin in mercie saud They for that mercie might their Countrie grace: For when with Iudgments best-discerning Eye Wee see good matter in an euill Man, As Courage, VVitt, and great actiuitie Wee long must hope, he will do wel, that can: For, Age with Vertue is Cooperatiue. Youths prone to Vice, sith Vice doth cocker it: So they, in time, great matters may achiue That may their King, and Kingdome benefit: Then each wise Iudges iudgment hath this scope To spare the hopelesse Felon full of hope. Fortuna vitrea est, quæ cum splendet, frangitur. Publi. O greatnesse what great Good dost thou containe, T'allure the VVill to bee in loue with thee? Ist souraigne-Good to bee a Soueraigne VVhen high'st degree of Ills threats that Degree? VVho buyes a Crowne with neuer-ending Care Buyes Gold too deere by al that Life is worth: For, Care doth nought but Life to Death prepare, Yet, vnprepard to meet Death flieth foorth: For, Kingdoms Cares so many are, and great, That they constraine the Thought but them to mind; That though vntimely Death they do beget, Yet Thought [though free] from thought thereof they bind! Then, ô my Soule, poore Soule! ritch in Conceit, (Which dost conceiue Kings glittering misery To be (as tis) false pomp, true perils Baite) Suffice thee still with meere Sufficiency. Make me aswell content to be the least As others are well pleasd the Greatst to be; Sith Man in honor liues, and dies a Beast: For, Men proue oft base Beasts in high degree. Let mine ambition reach but to Content, And that Content reach but the Mean to touch: Thats All; sith its omni-sufficient More meet for richest Mynds then more then Much There may I sitt by Vertues surest side, (For in the Meane shee doth hir selfe install) Secure from wrack, while those that Scepters guide Do find no meane betweene their Rise, and Fall, VVhere I may, all vnseene, see all the rest Of this Worlds Reuolutions; and make vse Of Best, and VVorst discreetly for my best And store my Mind with Matter for my Muse: Like a Spectator that doth sitt at ease Secure vpon the Shore, and thence doth see, How others are neere sincking on the Seas In ceaslesse Stormes that full of danger bee: Or like a looker on a Tragedie VVithin the Middle Roome, among the Meane, I see the fall of State and Maiesty VVhile mongst the Presse t'a Piller sure I leane:) So see I others sorrowes with delight Though others sorrowes do but make me sadd: But plagues to see, which on our selues might light, Free from their fall, makes Nature, grieuing, gladd. VVhere while I see some Phaeton striue to guide The Sunne of Souraigntie, I see him set All, in Combustion; so dissolues, through pride, All Mouers causing his Ambitions heate. Where I may see but late-Court-Minions Liue like to Spunge [hard squizd] aliue, and dead Through change of Kings, or Kings opinions: For, when their Heads fall off! off falls their Head. Or if they find more grace in Fortunes Frownes To liue (as in an Hell) a Liuing Death They well may Chronicle what holds in Crownes Which turne about (like Fanes) eun with a Breath. There may I Nobles see vnnobly striue Who shall be greatst in grace, for want of grace, Who by the damage of each other thriue And grace themselues b'each others great disgrace. While (vnperceaud) I laugh to see how thay (Like Fiends) each other restlestly torment, And, blesse my state that on their Plagues may play In my Minds mirry Kingdome of CONTENT. In few, there may I see how all Estates That lifted are aboue the myrry Meane Do, falling stand twixt Dangers and Debates, Whiles of their Falls I make a swelling Sceane. So that this World, the Sea of misery, Becomes my Helicon, and Streames affords, To make my Muse to flow, stil swelling hie, In matter far aboue the reache of Words. Then, you that, shouldring, buckle for the best Holding the Meane [the best of all] the worst] Rest you, or else my Muse shall neuer rest To make your States, and Strifs lothd as accurst. And you, ô you vnpassiond peacefull Harts That with me liue secure in meane estate, Be ioyfull though you play but simple Parts Ye simply play the best, blithst, freest from hate. And though these great Ones scorne our Case, and Cote, Let vs laugh at them sith we know they dote. A Dump vpon the death of the most noble Henrie late Earle of Pembrooke. Death, hath depriud me of my deerest friend; My Deerest friend is dead, and laid in Graue: In Graue He rests vntill the World shall end: The World shall end, and end shall all Things haue: All Things haue end, on Earth, that Nature wrought; That Nature wrought shall vnto Dust be brought: To Dust be brought the worthiest Wights on Ground: On Ground who liues, in Ground consume he must: Consume he must whom Sorrow doth confound: Sorrow doth confound the Mind that Care doth rust: That Care doth rust, full soone Care will deuour: Care will deuour where Care hath greatest powr: Where Care hath greatest powr it frets the Heart: It frets the Heart, and doth perplex the Spirit: The Spirit perplext procures the Bodies smart: The Bodies smart doth quite expell delight: Expell delight, then Life is like to Death: To Death I yeeld, yet cannot lose my Breath: My Breath, why did it not forsake me than: Me than, eun then, when that my friend deceast: My friend deceast, eun as my Ioyes began: My Ioyes began, eun as my Ioyes surceast: My Ioyes surceast eun as my friend did dy. My friend did die, and so would God might I. J. D. I said vnto Laughter, what art thou mad? And to Mirth what dost thou? Eccles. 2. 2. Among the Baites Sinne laies for heedles Flesh (Though Lust be more attractiue in her powr] None takes so soone [sith It doth it refresh] As Myrth; For, Myrth doth ioy, and health procure. The Graue, and Light wil, lightly, mirry bee Mirth so doth tickle Spleenes of either kinde For recreation, one; the other, glee: And both, because the rein they pleasure finde. It is Earths Heauen, yet It doth hale to Hell: But so doth hale, as, with bewitching Arte It makes them willing whome it doth compel To ioy in Pleasure: which procureth Smart. When Fortune smiles who then laughs not outright? And oft (mad mirry] plaies not with each straw? Makes Pleasure, all their paine; their care, Delight? These, Mirth, with Ropes of Vanity, doth draw. These, in the Night, think how to spend the Day [If thinking-sad Ambition let them not] In pas-time, so, Time passeth with ill play Til they lose All, and He the same hath got. In Weale, we flote on Pleasures Streams, with ease, In sugred satisfaction of our Sense: And often seeke to sound those sensual Seas With the decep'st reach of our Intelligence. Then wee embozom all that Myrth can yeeld: Musutions, Plaiers: Buffons, Birds and Beasts Do, at their pleasure, vs (most wanton) weeld: And, deerer then our Wisedomes deeme their Iests. A Zane (farther off from Wit, then Grace (And yet as farre from Grace, as Grace, from Synne) That can at Feasts, prate with a brazen face) (When sober Witt's kept out) must needs come in. Our Dainties will not downe with out some such, A Shamelesse-gracelesse, wittlesse Thing wee gett To make vs Fatt, as fooles, with Laughing much And on his follie feede, to make vs eate. My Lady shee will laugh as madd shee were (Lord! why should Mirth make sober Ladies madd?) If shee but see Him, like an Asse, to fleere; So shee (kind Mule) to see an Asse is gladd. And when such Buffons ball, and Cornetts sound (The Ghests loud-Laughing) Who can then bee heard That speakes like Phillpps Page, as shrill, as sound, That Voice hath then no grace and lesse regard? And, if one sober Soule, amonge the rest, Do mind the rest of their Excesse, in This Some seeming wise man makes him straight a Iest, While all, as at a Goose, like Geese do hisse. Then one Goose (that seemes reason most t'affect) Yeelds him a reason for their hissing so: And saith that Wisedome doth hir selfe reiect, When shee comes out of season ought to do. This Diu'l with reason, dammnes Diuinity; And, with his Wisedome, stopps selfe Wisedomes Mouth: Which saith, all Seasons wee should mortifie Our Eares, to heare the liuely Word of TRVTH! Paule, hold thy peace; thou blessed Saint be still: (Though if thou preach not, thou saist, wo to Thee) Lest they do hisse thee too, for thy good will; Who hold all Geese that not madd-mirry bee. Tell them they ought in season, and without To heare the Word of Life: they, dead in sinne, Will, for thy zeale, requite thee with a floute; For so to quite such zeale they vs'd haue bin The most voluptuous ouer-wanton Rigge Proud Plentie, scornes meeke Pieties VVoman-hood: And, swelling Supra-aboundance lookes so bigg That nought it sees so Low as Sober-moode. Variety of Crownes, Robes, Mirth, and Meate And all that rauish, Sense, with sweet'st delight These are the Heau'ns desired of the GREATE VVho weene no Heau'n nor Hell is out of sight. Frolicke great, great Ones, while these Heauns you hold Sith you will not attend true VVisedoms VVords, Laugh and bee fatt, sith al you touch is Gold, Though that foode your Soules famishment affordes. Soule? tush, what Soule? how idly dost thou chatt, Madd Muse, that now [they thinke] dost Poetize: There is no Soule, nor no such Thing as that; These are but Fictions, Law-confirming Lies, VVhat resurrection? Pish, who euer came From Death, to Life? VVho can Cadaueres raise? Some say a Nazarite once did the same, But Tacitus nor Machiauel so saies. These were wise Men, in deede, and known for such, If such had said it, we might trust their VVorde: But, sow'r poore Fellowes poorely it doth touch, That often with themselues do scarse accord. VVho had no action in the Common-weale No Office, no Command, nor no great Braine, Yet wee [for sooth] for vaine Soules only Heale Must credit them in all their prattle vaine. These are the damnd discourses of these Diuells; Thus, their blasphemous Tongues deride the Truth; Whose greatest gooddesse is in greatest Euills: And growing Greate, through Mischiefe, haue their growth. Great Witt should haue great Grace the same to guide; Or Witts owne greatnesse will it selfe oppresse, Or make it runne to rage, it selfe beside; And sinck the Owner in the deep'st distresse. If Witt, and Wealth concurre, to Hell they runne, If Grace, in mightie measure, stay them not: Who are vndone, if they be not vndone Before they do receiue their later Lott: For, Frolick Fate is most vnfortunate If sanctified Discretion hold not in Vnruly Nature, then, in sober gate: For, from Aboundance, springs aboundant Sinne. In Wealthes excesse to be most continent Is most miraculous, and seldome seene: For, Appetite is then most violent, And Passion, with high-hand, growes Reasons Queene. Then Pleasur's Actiue, and most Passiue, Sense: Madd-Mirhes rude-hand the Soule a sunder teares: Which is distracted by Ioyes violence, Aswell as by Griefes Gripes, or sodaine Feares. If hee that doth the happiest State possesse Looke well within him, and without him too Hee lightly shall see cause of heauynesse, Seeing All to threaten him quite to vndoo. But hardly shall hee sinde a cause of myrth (Though hee sought all the World the same to finde) Sith Sorrow only is our tight of Birth, With Laboure of our Body, Soule, and Mind. O Myrth (strong Strumpett!) Whore to Worldly-Weale, O Laughter (Light Thing!) Baude to both those Beasts, Why do you not your Luxury conceale But that bewray which Modestie detests? It is because yee are madd; as are those That willinglie still rest at your dispose. Omnium rerum vicissitudo est. Terence. As I me sate vpon a Riuer side And markt the Water how it past away, And how that past, with like, was straight supplide, That still is past, and still held at a stay, Mee thought t'was like this the Sea of Sorrowes Tide, Wherein the Race of Man-kinde runneth so: For, downe the Streame of Days, to Death we glide, And still Some come, as fast as Others go. And as the Streame with many Reaches runnes: So runnes our Course, with many way-ward Reaches: This, Ill it runnes to, and that Good it shunnes; And, to runne out of Course, makes many Breaches. Then, with my selfe I thus discourst, at last, I, with the rest, am running downe this Streame: Here now, there then, then, presently am past, Like Streames swift Course, if not much more extreame: For, ah, I cannot think how swift I flee But I flee swifter then that Thought, to Death: For, Times least Partes, then Thoughts much breefer bee, Which Thought, with thought, my short time shorteneth! I am orewheldm'd in Thoughts, as deepe as Hell And high as Heau'n; when thus my state I waigh: And twixt those Thoughts I (as intraunc't) do dwell, While Time drawes mee to Death the neerest way: For, Thought breedes Melancholie, which doth breede The Enemies of Health; and, they do sow (In Fleshes Earth) our Dissolutions Seede, That vs dissolues when it begins to grow. If from my selfe I do my selfe diuide (The longer, so, to keepe my selfe intire) And giue my Sense delight, my Thoughts to guide To Mirth, abroade for health: they straite retire: And, sooner can long married Men forgett They married are, then I forgett the Thought To which I owe my selfe, as duest Debt, Since I was matcht to Ill and knew it Nought: For, if I lett my easi-moouing Minde (With lightest shock turne from his weightie Point) It rests no where, but in this Point, by Kinde; So, Lightest Purposes doth disappoint. The Elements, though still at Warre in mee, Do yet, in firme accord, mine ende conspire: For, It they hasten, sith they disagree; Which well agrees to make me vnintire. Then, ô why should I add sadd care, to Care When one's of pow'r, the Pow'res of Life, to foile? Why should I care to spend, and care to spare, To spare a Life which sparing doth but spoile? Why should I care to liue, sith die I should If I would liue quite free from Thought, and Care? For, Thought's the Deede by which this life we hold, Which yet determines Life, ere Thought beware, Suppose with cark, past Care, I could obtaine A golden Crowne (but better t'wrere of Baies) And with Hell-paines a tripple One attaine, What gott I but more Care to ende my Days? And were Time staid, and Life most stedfast too Such endlesse Kings, had gott but endlesse Cares: And so the longer Life, the more adoo: The more adoo, the Dooer worser fares. While thus my Thoughts are temp'ring, lo, with Time, Time hath stoll'n on mee, to steale mee away: Awaie, with Time, I go: hark, hark, the Chime Saith Musicks charming Notes Time cannot stay: And, if not Musick, no Mirth vnder Sunne Hath pow'r to stay Him; but, Mirth Pas-time is: By It, the sooner, Time away doth runne: Then, Life is wretched both in Bale, and Blisse! If it be wretched, lothsome is it then; If so, then so wee are, to loue it so: Men-Beasts wee bee, that reason want of Men, To Loue our Prison, perill, paine, and wo. Thus while, with healthfull breath, I breathe out This I can contempne this Life, and those condemne That are in Loue with it, as with their blisse, But, were Death neere, I might be one of Them. Yet, let me not my dying Heart bely (Which dyeth as it liues, in thought of Death) It nought (but Heau'n) desires more then to dy; And, yeeld, to endlest rest,, my weary breath. Weery, I well may tearme it, that still toiles, To keepe a toilesome Life from endlesse rest: So, wrongeth Life the more, the more it moiles: Which is at worst, when it is at the best! O Breath, fraile Breath! (base-Daughter of the Aire) Flie to thy Mother, me no longer griue: Nor, would I dy, because I do dispaire But dy, because I hope, in rest, to liue. Here is but Toile, and thou holdst mee to It; Which I abide, sith Thou abidst in mee: So, but losse wynn I, by thy benefitt, The losse of Rest, that restlesse am through thee: Yet, till thy Giuer take thee, make no hast: For, I was borne to toile, for rest, at last. Difficilia quæ pulchra. The Coæternall, consubstanciall WORD, Self-WISDOMS wisedome, Image of the HIGHST, Sole KING of Kings, of Lordes the onely LORD And, heaunly HEAD of CHRISTIANS, IESVS CHRIST, In compleate Time, tooke FLESH, by MIRACLE, Of a pure VIRGIN, through HIS Work that was The Prompter of each sacred ORACLE, That did fore-show how THIS should come to passe: VVith his vnualued Wonder-working BLOVD, To manumise vile Man, a Slaue to Sin, Was borne in Beth'lem without, Liuelihood; And, without all that State doth glory in. His THRONE, a Manger, and, a Crach; his Cradle: His ROBES, course Ragges, poore Reliques of meane Lynnen. His WAITERS Beasts, his COVRT, a stinking Stable: That worse no Begger euer borne had been in: Where, yet, foorth-with, by Angels glorifiyng, Sheepherds agnition, worship of the WISE, The guiding STARRE Old Symeons Prophecying, And Doctors wondring, ALL, HIM GREAT Agnize, Who, in his youth, grew quickly old in grace With GOD, and Man; for GOD, and Man was HEE: Baptis'd by him which made and gaue Him place, That HEE to all might Pieties Patterne bee: Conquering his FLESH with fasting, unconstrain'd, The World with meeknesse, and the Fiend, with Prai'r: And when the WEEKS of DANIELL end attaind Hee taught and sought RIGHTS Ruines to repaire: Sometimes, with Words, that wonder-mazed men, Sometimes, with Deedes, that Angels did admire: With mercy, still, with Iustice, seldome when) He made (as HEE was) God and man entire. He tought EARTH, Truth: and HELL, to know her error: He showed the MEEDE ordain'd for Good, and Bad: Then to confirme All [to Alls ioy, and terror) Hee calm'd the Elements: reform'd the madd: Heald all Diseases: brought, to life the Dead: The quickt' obedience: secret thoughts, to light; To Sinnes restraint, or to be banished, And lastly to the Deuil, feare and flight! These [Notwithstanding) and much more then these, (For, all the World the Books would not comprise That of his Acts should hold the working-Seas, Which to a boundlesse Magnitude do rise! Hee was, (alas, when he had vnder-gon All Paines and Passions (Sin all onely saud) Proper to Man [yet had his God-head showne) By his owne People scorned: and depraud! Yea, by his owne (his owne chiefe Officer Iudas, betraying Him) He was accusd, Arraignd, condemnd, bound, scurgd, hald here, and there, With Thorns, Crownd, crucified, and worse abusd! So He, (All being fulfild: the Sun obsurd, The Earth, all, quaking, Graues self-opening, And, NATVRES Frame dissoluing] Death, endurd: Life, thereby, to his Enemies, to bring! Then, being interd, loost Hell: and, rose againe In triumph, hauing conquerd Death, and Sin: And forty Daies, (with HIS) on Earth did raigne A Man-GOD glorifid, without, and in! And, of his age, the three and thirtith Yeare, He, in the sight of his Saints, did assend To Heaun, with glory, triumph, ioy and cheere, And sits on his right Hand that Him did send! From whence [being now our Spokes-man] He shal come (When all this All shall melt in funerall fire) On Quick, and Dead to giue his finall Doom: When, as their Works shalbe, shalbe their Hire. Then, Good, and Bad diuided, endlesly, The Worle refind, and all things put in frame, To this greate Iudge, the totall EMPERY Shalbee giu'n vp, of this Great-double FRAME! To whome Celestiall, and Terrestriall Knees, And Knees infernall, shall for euer bow: And, eu'ry Tongue confesse, and Eye that sees, That HEE is All, in All, in High, and Low, Vnto His glory that VVas, Is, and shall (In all Æternity) bee ALL, in All! I long for Life, vnlike to Death. So runnes the Tenor of the Treble Ills Existing by the Meane of three fel Foes, The Flesh, the World the Deuill euer spills Vs miserable miserable Men with mortal Bloes, Yet, like Fiends, taking pleasure but in paine, [In paine that to noe perfect profit tends] We seeke to rule, and if we can to raigne; And rule, and raigne but for vnruly Ends, O Rest [the Image of that Saboth sweete Wherein sweete Saints do from their Labours rest! O riche repose of Spirit, for Angells meete!] How do I toile to bee of Thee possest? Then Slouth it is not that delights my VVill, Nor, would mine Vnderstanding idle bee; But, both desire to bee in Action still, Yet rest in action like the Trinitie! The Date of my lifes Lease is neere expird, Yet labour I for life, sith still I swimme In Sorrowes Seas, as one as neerely tride As hee is neere the Bottome, or the Brym. I scarse can keepe me Head aboue the VVaues VVith all my Laboures my Starres are so crosse! Yea, vnder VVater oft my Science saues From Death, my Life, which Stormes of Troubles tosse. But as the Deluge, swelling more, and more, Made th'Arke thereby to Heau'n-warde mount a pace: So, when Afflictions VVaues increase their Store They lift me vp thereby the more to Grace. Yet, as they multiplie, their struggle so That they turmoile my Bodie, toyle my Mynd: For, both in anguishe flote when Sorrowes flo; And, sorrowes flow from Fortunes Ebbe, by kind, So, that I cannot yet that Rest attaine Which my poore Soule, and Spirit so requires; I, longing, labour for it, yet in vaine: For, base Defect withstands my high Desires. And by how much the more for it I longe So much the more I do Worlds weale neglect; Wherein my selfe and my Desires I wrong: That are the more supprest by that Defect. I was not moulded, sure in earthlie Mould, (Though of the Filth thereof my Fleshe was fram'd) For, if I were, then sure it fitt mee should; But, nothing lesse, whereof I am asham'd. I see some Men (who when wee weigh their Witt, Wee, as miraculous, their wealth admire] To this Worlds Mould do make them selues as fitt As if their VVitt, and Mettall were all Fire! Yea some meere Blocks, that are as blunt, as base, Rise from still lying but in Dutt, and Dung, To high estate [which standeth with therir Case] Though Fate, through too much right, them too much wrong! Yet I [whose Braines are plac'd in better Cells And haue the influence of clearer light) Can compas nothing by Wits magick-Spells [These charming Numbers] but mine ovvne delight. I stoln am from my self, by nine svveet Queenes [Who do predominate my Witt, and Will) While Time steals from me both my Life, and Meanes; And leaues mee nought to liue with, but my Skill. Yet from Times Wings I steale his blackest Plumes (The Night) to rest in motion of my Muse; And til my Witt by Health of Time consumes, In spight of VVant, this wealth of VVitt Ile vse. And with Aurora [raiser of the Muse] Ile wake if Rests friend [Sleepe] should rest mine Eyes: To steale from Time, what I may iustlie vse, So to supplie Times want with's owne Supplies! And for the Stuffe whereof Ile draw my Lines It shall bee such as from his Throne shall come, VVhose Muse-immortalizing Spirit them twines, And (Silke worme like) Ile worke me in my Tombe. VVhere, though I, poore VVorme, from my Labours rest My VVorks well wou'n by some more dextrous VVitt May line perhapps the Note-bookes of the best; Yea, for Apparrell of the Mind be fitt. And though the Viperous Iron Teeth of Time May gnaw away, to wrack, through my VVorks VVombe, Yet if my Spirit, thereby aboue Him climbe Lett my Lines ruynd bee, to giue Him Roome: For, though content, I could bee, dead, to liue In Fames strongst Fort (though Paper be the VVall, And Sense of Fame my life cannot suruiue) Yet if I rise thereby lett my Fame fall: For, what feeles Naso that a VVorke compos'd That liues, and shall, till Time bee Toothlesse quite, Sith hees disposd, where now hee's indisposd To feele a VVinde that is so vaine, and light? Yet heers the VVinde that beares the VVorld away Though it bee weaker then the lightest Mynd: Then, weake is That so weake a Winde doth swaie; And die they ought that liue but for such Winde. But, Vertue for hir selfe (and not for Fame That as an Hand-maide hir attendeth still) I chiefly do desire, and let my name Die in hir life, so shee may make my Will, And, with hir leaue, to giue (and make no waste) My Time to draw Diuine Lines to the last. An Ode in commendation of Musick. O Sacred Musick, Nurse of Raptures highe, Which feedst the Soule with diuine Symphony, What Words can prayse Thee? Whose Vertue tunes the discord of the Spheares, And ties therto Diuine: and Humane Eares; Then can Winde raise Thee? Whose sweetest Aires do breathe foorth Wonders Winde, Which mounts, aboue it selfe, the heauiest Minde In spight of Nature: Whose holie Accents are so full of force As can the Soule from Body quite deuorce Of sullenst Creature! VVhat is so dull of Sprite that hath but life That loues thee not? Or who so full of strife To hate thy Concords? Sith thou art Shee, who, with Soule-pleasing Straines, All peruerse Passions of the Mind constraines To cease their Discords! Our Soules (whome some suppos'd but Musicke were, Because they moned are as It doth steere) Do glorifie Thee! The sacred Quires that ring about the Throne Of that more sacred ESSENCE, Three, in One, Do sanctifie Thee! That Holy, Holy, Holy which They crie That are Sub-chaunters of Heau'ns Hermony Records, thy glory; VVhat shall I say? both Heau'n, and Earth conspires To raise the same past reach of what aspires If transitorie! And, in a VVorde, if I might censure Thee That, next my Neerest, art beloud of mee) Thou art that Pleasure, VVho, in thy sweetest Notes, (as well I note) Hast [like that Blisse that by sweete Concord's got] Nor Meane, nor Measure! Nihil tam bene dictum, quod non fuit dictum prius. Were all the VVits that mortall Braines immure (By supposition, or in Deed) made one, Yea though they vvere most subtile made, and pure, By al the Helpes that Wit can think vpon, They could not [though they did themselues distract VVith strayning hard] a new Inuention frame: For, each new Deed doth turne into some Act [In some yeares compasse] past, before the same, Our Actions, and Inuentions are fast fixt. Vnto the Spheare of Vniformity: Though oft the same, with Diffrences, be mixt, Yet they, with Like, past, hold conformity: For, as the heaunly Orbs, in vvheeling, cause The Stars to meet in oft coniunction, For, from the like, the like Time often drawes That rightest vvere in opposition: So, do our Words, and Deeds, vvith Turnes of Time, Turn in't themselues: then, out, then in againe; And, as a VVheele doth roundly fall, and climb: So, Fashions, out of vse, come in amaine. VVe cannot think of that hath not bin thought: For, our more studious Ancients straind their Braines Beyond ours reache, though vve in vaine, haue sought To straine our VVits beyond their VVisedoms Straines. To instance vvould but breed satiety; But, breefly, Lett vs cite some fevv, For All: VVho hath past Plato, in Philosophy? VVho Homer for the Arte Poeticall? In Oratory Craft, who hath out-stript The Facher of the Romaine-eloquence! Whose Tongue, and Pen were so in Hony dipt That now we lick him, to make sweet our Sense. Then, for the Mathematicks, who compares With Archimedes (Wonder of all Times.) And who, for Musick, with Amphion dares Play for the Prize, whose fame past Wonder climbs! What Painter will not blush a Line to draw With Zeuxis; whose bright name, bright Fame doth dim? What Imager would not seem rude, and raw Before Pigmalion, if he wrought with him? By this small Touch, we well may tast the Whole Huge Body-politick of Arts-men past: Which is a like through-out; which Bodies Soule Holds all that All are learning, to the last. We may suppose w'haue lighted on a Vaine Without this Body, when out Muse doth flo In some Inuention, past the modern Straine; But, Self-conceit makes vs imagin so: For, read All extant, and if some, or all Of thy Conceit were not comprizd in some Thou art a Spirit, and no Man Naturall Who speaks as he is taught, or els is dumbe. This, idle-painfull-foolish-witty Worke Pardon mee Patience to call it so] I may conceaue in no Conceit did lurk Before, from mine, it (thus made run) did flo: But, God doth know on whose Vaine I haue lighted, I know not, sith, I know, I know non such: Yet, for inditing, I may be indited For taking That which I ought not to touch. If so I haue, it vvas through ignorance Of vvhat right Others had, to what I haue; And if Theirs be my Wits poore maintainance Proue it; and I am theirs, to spill, or saue. But, some there are that take most greedily From the old Store, sith they know Nought is new: If then they vvrite both vvel, and speedily They but engrosse the Deeds that others drew. Yet, sooth to say, howeuer some may vaunt They scorne to steale, yet They, yea, and their Heires Take [by their leaues] and yet the World inchant VVith coniuring VVords, to think it only Theirs! Old Pictures well refresht, do seem as new: And none but Artists know them to be old: Then, they earne praise, as those that first them drew, VVho make them, newly, their old beauty hold. Thers nothing new: no, not so much as Sin: For, what sin now is done, but hath bin done VVhen the VVorlds Face was vvasht for soile therein VVhich from most fowle, to Filthier far did run. And though the VVorld doth vvax stil worse and vvorse, Its since that Deluge, vvhich then scowrd hir Scums: And so it must grow vvorse and vvorse, perforce, Vntil hir second, and last clensing comes, Which, being by Fires (as erst vveake VVaters) Mean, It, euer after, shalbe nevv, and cleane! Inough's as good as a feast. Wee Bowes vnbend and flack the Viols Strings? That vsed so, wee them may longer vse: Then, if our Muse be euer on her VVings She wil the lesser while flye like our Muse. The body by repletion, compotent, And by Euacuation, fit for it Successiuely, doth Nature most Content: So, must we vse the Minde, the Muse, the Wit: Then, here, an end of that which we began On no Foundation that had any ende But such as makes our Muse an Artizan, That can, in euery Kinde her self transcend: But, ô, light Rimes, bee darke to all but those That can your Rime, and Reason wel dispose. Jucundum nihil est nisi quod reficit varietas. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>