<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Sherburne, Edward, Sir, 1618-1702</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Sherburne, Edward, Sir, 1618-1702</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">sherburne edward sir 1618 1702</field>
      <field name="author_text">Sherburne, Edward, Sir, 1618-1702</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1960's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_2.0222.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">1961</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464810</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Greek, Modern (1453- )</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Italian</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The poems and translations of Sir Edward Sherburne (1616-1702 ; excluding Seneca and Manilius Introduced and Annotated by F. J. Van Beeck</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The poems and translations of Sir Edward Sherburne (1616-1702 ; excluding Seneca and Manilius Introduced and Annotated by F. J. Van Beeck</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poems and translations of sir edward sherburne 1616 1702</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poems and translations of sir edward sherburne 1616 1702</field>
      <field name="title_text">The poems and translations of Sir Edward Sherburne (1616-1702 ; excluding Seneca and Manilius Introduced and Annotated by F. J. Van Beeck</field>
      <field name="year_display">1961</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1961</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1961</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464810&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464810&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Sherburne, Edward, Sir, 1618-1702&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;sherburne edward sir 1618 1702&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The poems and translations of Sir Edward Sherburne (1616-1702 ; excluding Seneca and Manilius Introduced and Annotated by F. J. Van Beeck&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poems and translations of sir edward sherburne 1616 1702&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1961&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1961&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Sherburne, Edward, Sir&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1618&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1702&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The poems and translations of Sir Edward Sherburne (1616-1702)&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;excluding Seneca and Manilius Introduced and Annotated by F. J. Van Beeck&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Assen&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Van Gorcum&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1961&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp3538&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;gre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;ita&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;xlix, 202 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The poems and translations of Sir Edward Sherburne (1616-1702)&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;excluding Seneca and Manilius Introduced and Annotated by F. J. Van Beeck&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 316 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and editorial matter omitted; Latin verse omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">POEMS AND TRANSLATIONS 1651Sqaure brackets denote editorial insertions or emendations. EROTICA SALMACIS BY Signeur GIROLAMO PRETI, Out of Italian. Where cleer Pactolus glides through Phrygian Lands Tween Banks of Emeralds, on golden Sands, And in his Course does Lydia's Confines trace With humid feet, and with a slippery pace, The Bed-rid Earth, to ease her self (opprest With her own weight, and crampt with her long Rest) Her vaster Limbs first stretches to a Plain, Then to a Mountain lifts her head again; A Mountain; such for height, as if 'midst those Which to scale Heaven by the bold Giants chose (Pelion, Olympus, Ossa,) plac'd it were, Would like a Cedar 'mongst low shrubs appear. So far above the Clouds his head doth rise That his green Locks no Summer dripping spies With Rain, his face no Winter does behold Mask'd with a snowy Muffler 'gainst the cold. The proud Usurper seems as if he meant, Scorning his low and baser Element, To make the Airy Region his own, And plant for Juno an Imperiall Throne. Or like some new Briareus he stands Arm'd with more large-spred Oaks than he with hands, And menaces the Stars; his Sides and Back, Woods which ne'r shade, fields which ne'r verdure lack, With a green Mantle cloath, whose fringed Base A hundred Brooks with Streams of Silver Lace. At foot of this tall Rock, a Cave disclos'd It self; a Cave, shady and dark; suppos'd The sole design of Nature, as th'Effect, Where She both Workman plaid, and Architect. Over whose gaping Mouth, her hand had hewn Out of the living Rock a Lip of Stone Cut like a bending Arch; whence for more grace (As 'twere the native Porter of the Place) Green Ivy wreath'd in many a subtile knot Hung dangling: Fore the entry of the Grot With streams of liquid Pearl, (the humid Son Of some large Torrent) a small Brook does run, Which on the Pibbles as it purling plaies, Does so harmonious a murmur raise, Tun'd to so just a Pitch, as dares defie The Birds sweet Noats, and with the Lute may vie. I'th'midd'st of this vast Cave, (which seems to prop With it's arch'd back th'whole Mountain) tow'rd the top Opens a spacious Vent; through which, it's flight, The damp Air takes, Entrance, the Suns warm light. The rude Walls Ivy, creeping round about, With a green Suit of Tapp'stry hangs throughout. The Goddess which in Heavens third Orb does shine Did to these shades her amorous thefts confine. Here her delights secur'd; whose Passions prove Her more the Servant, than the Queen of Love. Here Mars to war oft taught she in Loves field With other weapons than with Spear and Shield; Whil'st 'bout his Sinewy Neck her Arms she wound, And his rough Limbs in those soft Fetters bound. Here once three naked Goddesses ('tis said) With censuring Eyes the Phrygian Swain survayd; Whose judgement in that memorable strife Gain'd him the beautious Hellen for his Wife, And gave to lovely Venus uncontroll'd The Prize of Beauty, and the fruit of Gold. And here at last the winged Son of Jove And Maija, sported with the Queen of Love; Who, in these shades (if Fame have Truth reveal'd) And her soft Bosome, long time lay conceal'd. Mean while great Jove, wondering at his neglect, (Who of some Message did return expect) Thus with himself discours'd 'bout his long stay: Sure he lies lurking for some hop'd-for Prey, Or his light Wings, (doubtless h'had else return'd:) He in the Sea hath wet, or fire hath burn'd. True, Jove; he lurking lay, but in the shade Of Venus Arms; whil'st on her Lips he preyd. His Pinions he had sing'd; but with Loves Torch, Which not so much his Plumes as heart did scorch; Drench'd too he had, and wet his lighter Wing, Not in the Seas salt Waves, but Loves sweet spring. And now seaven times the Sun with quickning Ray Had lighted in the East the Lamp of day; As oft the humid Night had wrapt the Skies In her black Mantle, wrought with Stars like Eyes: And yet no Day goes by, no Night e'r passes, But sees these Lovers link'd in close Embraces. But from those Arms (where long a Pris'ner held) The loyt'ring God now to return compell'd, Unwillingly their dear Embrace declind: Yet left a growing Pledge of Love behind. Nine times already had the Moon (constrain'd By Course) her Orb into a Crescent wain'd; As oft, (her horns spred to a round) had run With Light that seem'd to emulate the Sun; When a sweet Boy (so geniall Stars dispos'd) Fair Cytheræa's pregnant VVomb disclos'd. In their warm Laps new born the Graces laid him, And with their softer Arms a Cradle made him. Beauty first suckled him at her white Breast And her Idea in his Looks imprest. About him did like little Anticks play, Laughter, and mirth, and smil'd his Cries away. No noise, but light breath'd from his Lips of Roses, Such as the Sky no Thunder heard discloses, Nor like to other Childrens, seem'd his Eyes Two springs of Tears, but like two Suns to rise: VVhence all presag'd that they in time should prove No less the Food than the sweet fire of Love. His Beauty with his years did still increase; VVhil'st his fair Mother, longing to impress The Image of her self in his lov'd face, Did every day add some Celestiall Grace. Now grown a Youth, behold him, with the Darts Of his bright Eyes, subduing Female Hearts: The living Picture of his Parents; where Their mixed Beauties seem t'have equall share. From Father both and Mother Name he took, From Father both and Mother his sweet Look. All the feign'd Beauties of the VVorld, seem'd met In him as in their living Counterfeit, VVhere Nature (like Apelles) the best Graces (To add to his,) cull'd from a Thousand Faces. Upon his Ivory Front you might behold His curled Tresses flow like VVaves of Gold, And as enamoured on his Lovely Face, That with their soft and twining Arms embrace. Then like loose VVantons 'bout his Neck to twist, Glad that they might by its warm snow be kist. View his fair Front, and thou'lt say that displays A clear Horizon deckt with Morning Rayes; And as we see beneath the dawning Gleams O'th'Morn, the Sun shoot forth his brighter Beams; So here might you perceive alike to rise In's Front the Morn, the Sun in his bright Eyes. His melting Lips, Speeches Vermilion Gate, Soft Seat of smiles, blushes so sweet dilate, As seem at once to ravish the pleas'd sight, And to a Kiss the longing touch invite; Through which a fragrant Zephyrus transpires, That Fans and kindles both Loves flagrant Fires. Nor can one tell (no grace in either missing) VVhich best becomes them, speaking, smiling, kissing. Look on his tender Cheek, and there thou'lt spy The Rose as in a Throne of Majesty, 'Midd'st a white Guard of Lillies, proudly grow; Or blushing Pinks set in a Bank of Snow: His Habit, and his Looks did both express A kind of sweet becomming carelessness. VVhom all so much more Beautifull esteem By how much he less beautifull would seem. VVhil'st thus he manifests in every Part, What Art there is in Beauty void of Art. One Day by Chance 'twixt him and Cupid grew This æmulous Contest; which of them Two (Since he in Beauty so surpast the other) The God of Love should be! he, or his Brother? When Venus Arbitress of the Debate On a Sublime Tribunal thron'd in State, (Fixing upon the Lovely youth her Eyes) Thus spake: My Deer, this Doom 'twixt you denies All further strife; a Bow Cupid and thou Shalt bear; he at his side, thou in thy Brow. The same your Weapons; Love's inflaming Brand Thou in thy Looks shalt bear, he in his hand: Both too shall shoot at and wound humane Hearts, Thou with thine Eyes (sweet Boy) he with his Darts. This lovely Youth, with divine graces crown'd, As yet three Lustres scarce had seen go round, When in his Mind a Resolution grew Of bidding Phrygia, and the Cave adue. Desire of knowledge, and the Love of Fame, For Travell his aspiring thoughts inflame. How oft he wish'd his Fathers Wings? that so He might each clime the Sun enlightens know: And view what e'r the Earths vast Bosome holds, Or in its watry Arms the Sea infolds. The Lycian Realms he view'd; and there survay'd The Hill, within whose dark, and dreadfull shade The triple-shap'd Chimæra once did dwell That animated Ætna, living Hell, Which from three sooty Jaws, us'd to expire A sulph'ry Deluge, and belch Floods of fire. To Caria next his Course he bends; where he Through that well-peopled Land doth wondring see The numerous Villages like shrubs to rise, The Cities towre like Cedars to the Skies; Whose fertile Borders with its winding waves Tow'rd the cold North the fam'd Meander laves; Which (like a Traveller on some strange Coast, Having his first Path, his Directress, lost, VVith devious steps, now in, now out doth wind, Flies what he seeks, and meets what he declin'd, Lost in the Errour of ambiguous waies) Its self imprisons in a watry Maze. At length he to that fatall Place arriv'd VVhere envious Love his sad Revenge contriv'd. So pleasant and delightful was the Place, That Heavens great Eye in its Diurnall Race Yet ne'r beheld another like unto't, Of all 'twixt Ganges head, and Calpe's foot. There to a round which a fair Prospect lends, Its flowry surface a large Plain extends; A hundred little Brooks its Bosome trace, And with their streams of Quicksilver enchace; VVhich with sweet vernall Dews supply'd, still yeeld Life to the Flowers, and Verdure to the Field; That may, with odorous Jewels thus aray'd, A heaven of flowers, or field of stars be said. And what more Pleasure adds; this pleasant Ground, Tall Trees, as with a leavy wall surround, And 'bout it seem like a green-work to run As if to sconce it 'gainst the scorching Sun. And as sometimes the Airs soft breath we find, Crisps the smooth Sea; so here a gentle wind, (VVhose softer wing the Flowers does lightly brush) Curles into trembling waves the fields green Plush. I'th'midd'st of this fair Plain, the tumid Earth, (As if impregnate with a fruitfull Birth) Swels gently up into an easie Hill: VVhere crown'd with sweets the spring sits smiling still. And, as from thence she sheds her balmy showres, The ground with grasse enamels, that with flowers. VVhose pregnant VVomb a Chrystall issue teems; VVhich as it glides along with purling streams, (That settle in a verdant Vale;) does make Of a small Rivolet, an ample Lake; In which no Weeds their muddy dwelling have To stain the native cleerness of the Wave. But as the Sun pure Christal by its light Transpierces; so the penetrating sight May through the Water here, the bottom spy, Checkerd with Pibbles of a various dye: And see how the Mute People of the Floud, With Ebon Backs, and Silver Bellies scudd. The Flowers which on its fertile Borders grow, As if in Love with their own Beauties shew: Bending their fragrant Tops, and slender Stems Narcissus-like, to gaze on the clear Streams. Where limb'd in Water Colours to the Life They see themselves; and raise a pleasing strife In the deluded Sense at the first View To judge which Flowers are Counterfeit, which true. On the left hand of this transparent Floud, Fringing the Plaines green Verge, there stands a Wood Where Lovers Myrtles, and the Poets Bays, Their spreading Tops to native Arbors raise: From whose tall Crowns like a black Vaile the shade Falling, the Lakes cleer Bosome does invade. So thick the Trees are they exclude Heavens sight, And make a leavy Skreen 'gainst the Suns Light. Whose close-weav'd Branches a new Heaven present And to the Sight form a green Firmament: In which like fixed Stars one might espie Gold-colour'd Apples glitter to the Eye. Which though no Motion Circular they run, Want not yet that of Trepidation. No vulgar birds there make their mean Abodes, But winged Heroes, Musicks Demy Gods, Whose Plumes like Gems, with various Colours shine, Their Beaks of Orient Hew, their Notes Divine: Whilest this sweet Place seems a retired Cell, Where Love and Flora with the Muses dwell. VVithin these dark, yet pleasant Coverts bred, Close by the Lake, a Nymph inhabited: A Nymph; her Breast more snowy, Looks more fair, Her Eyes more Diamonds, and more Gold her Hair, Than ever Nymph could boast that hath been seen To haunt the VVoods, or press the flowry Green. The Chace she lov'd not, nor with Hound or Spear VVould charge the tusked Bore, or savage Bear. Nor at a Mark or Quarry Bow would bend: Nor in a Race with other Nymphs contend. To her the Naiades would often say, Fair Salmacis, fair Cynthia's Laws obey: Her sports pursue; and in thy hand a Spear, Or at thy side a painted Quiver bear. But she who other Pleasures had in Chace, As the proud Mistris of so proud a Place, Disdains to set a Foot beyond the Bounds Of those lov'd shades, or tread on meaner grounds. There with its liquid streams the neighbouring Lake A Luke-warm Bath for her fair Limbs did make. The Neighbouring Lake; which oft it self discovers, Swell'd by the Tears of her forsaken Lovers. In whose unflattering Mirrour, every Morn, She Counsell takes how best her self t'adorn. There she sometimes her looser Curles unwinds, Now up again in Golden Fillets binds, Which makes (which way soever them she wears) For amorous hearts a thousand catching Snares. A Robe, like that of Day, now wears she, white, Now one of Azure, starr'd like that of Night. Now curious Sandals on her feet doth slip, In Gems, and Gold lesse rich, than Workmanship. Now in a carelesse Dress she goes; her Hair Spred 'bout her shoulders, and her Ankles bare. And gathering Flowers, not all alike doth pick, But such alone doth in her Bosome stick, Whose leaves, or Milk, or Scarlet, does invest, To suit in Colour with her Lip and Brest. And if a Flower she pull, strait from its Root Another rises up to kisse her Foot; Thus whether more she take or give none knows, Whilst her Hand gathers what her Foot bestows. By chance she then was gathering Flowers, when she The Son of Venus spi'd, and Mercury: On whose bright Looks her wanton Eyes she bent, With which her longing Thoughts mov'd with Consent, VVhil'st both her Sight, and Thoughts by seeing bred, VVith pleasure on so sweet an Object fed. But she sucks in Loves poyson with desire, VVhich through her Eyes glides like a stream of fire Into her Brest; where, with Ætnæan VVaves Firing her Heart, the scalding Torrent raves. And now she forward goes like a bold Lover, Her flames to him that caus'd them, to discover. But coming neer, she saw in's eyes there plaid A wantonness with Modesty allayd: VVhich though the Gazers Heart it set on Fire, Quench'd yet the heat of a too bold Desire: VVhence though Love spurr'd her on, fear held her back, And though her heart did fly, her pace did slack. Yet she observ'd to lighten in his Look I know not what Majestick Grace, which strook Her Eye not with more Terrour than Delight, And lesse did dazle than it did invite. VVhence fir'd with hope, yet freezing with despair, She nearer fearfully approach'd; and there Sent him by the light waftage of the VVind, A sigh, an Ah Mee, Nuncios of her Mind. And now her Passion gaining vent, affords Her Tongue the liberty and use of words. But lame, and broken; yet that serve t'imply, 'Twas this she meant, Be kind, or else I dye. “Sweet Stranger! if a Soul lodge in thy Brest “Fair as thy outside, hear a Nymphs Request: “That begs thou'lt take thy Inn up in this shade. “(And Gods their dwellings in the woods have made.) “Here on this Bank may'st thou repose thy Head, “Or on my Bosome make thy softer Bed: “The Air here still is sweet, still cool; if by “My sighs inflam'd it be not, or thy Eye. “That Eye which quick as lightning Flames does dart; “And sooner than I saw it, scorch'd my Heart. “O more than happy wert thou, Salmacis! “If he (but dream not of so great a Bliss) “Should prove so kind to lay thee by his side, “Not as his Mistris only, but his Bride. “But if that Joy another do possess, “O let me, as her Rivall ne'r the less “(Since here is none that may the Theft reveal) “From thy sweet Lips a kiss in private steal. “But should some Goddess nourish in thy Brest “A nobler fire; deny not a request “To one that dyes; if more I cannot move, “A kiss for pitty grant, if not for Love. “Or if too much that seem; pray let me have “What Sisters yet may from their Brothers crave. Here ceast to speak; and with that forward prest To have joynd Lip to Lip, and Brest to Brest. But the shy youth coyly repulst her still, As cold in Love, as deaf unto her will, Dying with Blushes of a deeper stain, The native Crimson of his Cheeks, in Grain. (For a bold Suter, of a cold denier When he the heart cannot, the face will fire) At last with a coy look, thus mov'd, he spake. “Fair Nymph be gon, or I the place forsake. “You but deceive your self to think my Mind “Will to such wanton Follies be enclin'd. At which (with his desires glad to comply, Yet loath to lose the pleasure of her Eye) She sadly creeps behind a bushy Skreen, There closely skulks to see, and not be seen. And now the Planet worship'd in the East, Rid on the Back of the Nemæan Beast; And from the inflam'd Meridian that bends Like to a Bow, his Beams like Arrows sends. When this fair Traveller, with heat opprest, And the days Toyls, here laid him down to rest Where the soft Grass, and the thick Trees, displaid A flowry Couch, and a cool Arbour made. About him round the grassy spires (in hope To gain a kisse) their verdant heads perk'd up. The Lilly, the fields Candidate, there stands A Suter for the favour of his hands: And here the blush-dy'd Amaranthus seeks, And finds it selfe outrivald in his Cheeks: Whil'st the enamoured Trees t'embrace him, bend Their shady Crowns, and leavy Arms extend. Mean time from his fair Front he rains a showre Of shining Pearl-drops, whilst his bright Eyes powre On the Nymphs Heart (that melts through hot desire T'enjoy what she beholds) a Flood of Fire. This Place at length he leaves, rous'd by the Call Of the neer waters sweetly murmuring fall. Where, on the Bank his Sandals off he slips, And in the Christal streams his Ankles dips. Whil'st the cleer Lake, as his pure feet he laves, Feels Love's warm Fires mix with its colder VVaves. And now, not his fair feet content alone To kisse, desires, (an amorous VVanton grown) (That she might nearer to her wish aspire) Her Bottom deeper, or her VVaters higher. VVhich (to their power) to rise when moved seem, As if they long'd to bath each curious Limb. The Youth with pleasure on the Floud doth gaze, And in that watery glasse his Face survaies, Admiring, with a Look stedfastly set, His reall Beauty in his Counterfeit. And sure he with himself in Love had fell, Had he not heard of fond Narcissus tell, VVho from cold streams attracting fatall fire, Did, to enjoy what he possest, expire. Then stooping, he with hands together clos'd, Hollowing their joyned Palmes, a cup compos'd Of living Alablaster; which when fill'd VVith the sweet Liquor the cleer Spring distill'd He gently lifts it to his head, then sips, Both bath and Beverage to his Looks and Lips. Mean time with ravish'd thoughts the Nymph doth view The sportive Lad, and whil'st he drinks, drinks too, But in a different Manner: from the Lake He his, her draught, she from his Eyes doth take. His slacks his Thirst, hers more inflames desire, He sucks in VVater, but she drinks in Fire. And now, invited by the heat, and took VVith the alluring Temper of the Brook, Himself disroabing, the rich spoyl he throws Away, and his pure Limbs all naked shows. And like a new Sun with a darkening Cloud Invested, casting off the envious shroud, He round about his beautious Light displaies, And makes the Earth a Heaven with his bright Raies. The Nymph at this freezes at once and burns, And fire with Love and Ice with wonder turns. At length cries out; Ah me! what see I here? What Deity leaving his heavenly Sphere Is come to sport him in these shades? sure by His wounding Look, and his inflaming Eye It should be Love; but no light Wings appear On his fair shoulders; strange he none should wear! No; those he lent my heart; which from my Brest Its flight hath took, and now in his doth rest. Ah me thou living Ætna! cloath'd in snow, Yet breathing flames, how lovely dost thou shew? Cruell, yet cunning Archer! that my Heart Thou sure might'st hit, t'allure me with the Dart. But now from the green Bank on which he stood, Fetching his Rise, he leaps into the Floud. Whose fall, (as him the breaking Waters take) With a white foame all silvers o'r the Lake. Where, as he swims, and his fair Arms now bends, Now their contracted Nerves again extends, He the Nymphs Heart (that peeps behind an Oake) Wounds from that Ivory Bow at every stroak. Into another Form he then converts The Motion of his Arms, and like to Darts, Now this, now that, through the cleer Waves does shoot, His Hand in Motion answer'd by his Foot. For as he this Contracts, he that extends, And when this forward, that he backward sends. Whilst through the streams his purer Limbs, like snow Or Lillies through transparent Chrystall show. His flowing Hair, floating like that rich Fleece Which the first Ship from Colchos brought to Greece. The Nymph at this stands as of sense quite void, Or as no Sense but Seeing she enjoy'd. At last from her full Brest (of its close fire The sparks) these broken Accents did expire. “O why (as Arethusa, or the Joy “Of Galatea) cannot I (sweet Boy) “Melt to a floud for thee? then (my fair Sun!) “Thou might'st (to bath thee) to my Bosome run. More would sh'have said: but her full Passion stopt Her Door of Speech, and her Eyes Floodgates op't. Struck with Despair so dead, she scarce appears To breath, or live, but by her sighs and tears; Yet though her silent Tongue no Words impart, Her speaking Thoughts discours'd thus with her heart. “Fond Salmacis! why flag thy hopes? thy Mind “What fears deject? on; nor be e'r declind'd; “But boldly thy fair Enemy assail. “See! thy desired Prey's within the Pale: “And Love (perhaps in pitty of thy Pain,) “Offers what was deny'd thee by disdain. “Be resolute; and him whose conquering Eyes “Made thee his Captive late, now make thy Prize. “Fear not; for pardon justly hope he may “Who plunders him that does deny to pay. Thus she, rekindling her half-quench'd desires Her Cheeks with Blushes, heart with boldness fires. Then forward moves a little; and anon Full speed, unto the Lake does madly run. But in the mid'st of her Careere, repents, And stops; suspended 'twixt two cross intents Like to a wavering Ballance; on, afraid, Back, loth to go, and yet to either sway'd. Now she advances; then again retreats: Her fears now conquers, then her hopes defeats. Struck with Loves powerfull Thyrsus, at the last (True Mænad-like) her lighter Robes off cast, She hurries to the Lake, then in she skips; And in her wanton Arms th'unwilling clips. He, who Loves Fires ne'r felt in his cold Brest, With fear at such a strange surprize possess'd, For help began to cry; when she at this, Ah, peace, saies; and his Mouth stop'd with a kiss. Yet strugg'ling he her Wishes did deny, And from her shunn'd Embraces strove to fly. But whil'st he labours to get loose, t'his Brest She faster cleaves; and his Lips harder prest. So when Joves Bird a Snake hath truss'd, his Wings The more that plies, the more that 'bout 'em clings, And leaves it doubtfull to the Gazers view, To tell which more is Pris'ner of the two. Fearfull to lose yet her new-gotten prize, The Nymph to heaven (sighing) erects her Eyes. “And shall my Love (saies she) triumph in vain, “Nor other Trophy than a bare kiss gain? “O Jove! if what Fame sings of thee be true, “If e'r thou did'st a Bulls fierce shape indue, “And on thy Back from the Phænician shore, “Through Seas thy Amorous Theft in Triumph bore, “Assist my Vows; and grant that I may prove “As happy in this Conquest of my Love: “No force let our Embraces e'r disjoyn; “Brest unto Brest unite, our souls entwine; “Tye heart to heart; and let the knitting charmes “Sweet kisses be; the Fetters, our soft Arms. “Or if thou hast decreed that we must part “Let that Divorce divide life from my Heart. Jove heard her Prayers; and suddenly as strange, Made of them both a mutuall Interchange; And by an undiscern'd conjunction, Two late divided Bodies, knit in One: Her Body straight a Manly Vigor felt, And his did to a Female softness melt. Yet thus united, they with difference Retain'd their proper Reason, Speech, and Sence. He liv'd and she appart; yet each in either; Both one might well be said, yet that One, neither. This Story by a Rivers side (as they Sate and discours'd the tedious hours away) Amintas to the coy Iole told: Then adds; O thou more fair, in Love more cold Than he, Heaven yet may make thee mine in spite, That can such differents, Ice and fire, unite. This with a Sigh the Shepheard spake; whilst she With a coy smile mock'd his simplicity. But now the setting Sun poasting away, Put both an End to their Discourse and Day. FINIS The Metamorphosis of LYRIAN and SYLVIA, by St Amant. Out of French. Under that pleasant Clime, where Nature plac'd Those Islands, with the name of Happy grac'd, There liv'd a young, and gentle Shepheard late, And had he never lov'd, too fortunate; His Name was Lyrian, she whose looks enthral'd His amorous heart, was the fair Sylvia call'd. The Natives there, 'mongst whom still lives his Name, (Nor shall the Waste of time impair it's Fame) Report, he bare for sweetness of his Song, The Prize from all Apollo's learned Throng. Yet nor his Voice, nor Worth that did exceed, And ev'n in Envy Admiration breed, Could e'r move her that o'r his heart did raign, To pleasing Joys to turn his amorous pain. The Cheerfull fields, and Solitary Groves, (Once loyall Secretaries to his Loves) Are still the Witnesses, and still shall be, Of his chaste thoughts, and firm fidelity. For they alone were conscious of his Grief, They only gave his Wonded Soul Relief, When with the Weight of his sad Woes opprest, They pittying, heard him ease in Plaints, his Brest. Ye Gods! how oft resolv'd he, yet declin'd, (Although he felt his heart with flames calcin'd) Before those Eyes h'ador'd so, to display His Griefes! Such Modesty his Soul did sway. And though h'had learn'd, and knew to suffer much, Yet were his Manners and Discretion such, Silence should first in death have quench'd his flame, E'r he'ld have rudely voic'd it unto fame. Nor had it yet to any (had not Stone And stocks discover'd it) been ever known. Which, (for on them he us'd his Plaints t'incise) By chance presented it to Sylvia's Eyes. This seen, in her does Scorn and Anger move; O heavens! is't possible that such a Love She should despise; and him who had profest Himself her Captive, as her Foe detest? Or that Love's Magick Characters his hand Had grav'd, should in her Eye for Cyphers stand? Or she should read them yet with so much spight, Ne'r more to see them, 'less to raze them quite? Ah 'tis too true! nor's that sufficient, Unless her Tongue to her hard heart consent, And 'gainst her faithfull Love, with cruell Breath Pronounce the rigid sentence of his Death. What said he not his Passion to excuse? What flourishes us'd not his willing Muse, To prove, his Love (of which the noble ground Was her Perfections) could no Crime be found! If neither Reasons self, nor Justice, ought (Those for which Heaven is lov'd) as Crimes be thought. That the Worlds Soveraign Planet which the Earth And Mortals Fates does govern from their Birth, By firm Decrees inrolled in the Skies Had destin'd him a Servant to her Eyes. And could his Will be lead another way, Yet being forc'd he could not disobey. So that his Soul in this her Captiv'd state Did only yeeld to her impulsive Fate; Not that (said he) he murmur'd at his Chains, But pleas'd, sat down and blest his rigorous Pains; Not but his Yoak so willingly he bare That Liberty a greater Bondage were; Not but in spight of his malicious fate, (In crossing all his Joys so obstinate) He should unforc'd, ev'n to the Grave affect That Beauty which his Love did so neglect. Yet these his Reasons, so well urg'd, so fair, With her that will hear none, no Reasons are. They more incense her: yet for fear she might Be softned, she betook her self to flight. Such were the winning Graces of his Tongue, Proving his Love did not her Beauty wrong. How oft since that, by all fair means he tri'd (Whil'st he the Gods with Sacrifices ply'd) To bring the humorous Nymph unto his Bent, And make her too obdurate Heart relent! His Passions, Sighs, and Tears were ready still, As the officious Agents of his Will, To work her to a sense of his hard State; But 'lass! his hopes grew still more desperate. Nay ev'n his voice, of so divine a strain, So moving! mov'd in her nought but disdain. Six years he liv'd perplex'd in this distress, Without the least Apparence of success; When he by chance (as he a Stag pursu'd) Encounter'd her: who e'r the Queen hath view'd Of Wood-Nymphs, (Cynthia) a hunting goe After the Bore, arm'd with her shafts and Bow, May then imagine the diviner Grace, The Looks, the Habit, Stature, and the Pace Of beautious Sylvia, as she tripping came Into the VVoods, pursuing of her Game. Soon as poor Lyrian, half dead with Love, Had spy'd her in that solitary Grove For whom his wounded heart so long had bled, He with these words pursues her as she fled. Art thou resolv'd then (Sylvia) 'gainst my Cries Thine Ears to close, and 'gainst my Verse thine Eyes? That Verse which Fame unto thy Life does give; And must I dye, 'cause I have made thee live Eternally? Seven years expired be Since I've been tortur'd by thy Cruelty; And dost thou think that little strength supplies My heart, for everlasting Torments will suffice? Shall I for ever only see thee stray 'Mongst these wild VVoods, more senseless yet than they? Alas! how weak I'm grown with Grief! I feel My feeble Legs beneath their Burden reel; O stay! I faint, nor longer can pursue, Stay, and since Sense thou lack'st, want Motion too. Stay, if for nothing else, to see me dye. At least vouchsafe stern Nymph to tell me why Thou cam'st into this Dark and Gloomy Place? VVhere Heaven with all its Eyes can never trace Or find thee out. VVas't thy Intent, the Light Of thy fair Stars thus to obscure in Night? Or seek'st thou these cool shades, the Ice and Snow That's 'bout thy Heart to keep unmelted so? In vain Coy Nymph thou Light and Heat dost shun, VVho e'r knew cold or shade attend the Sun? Ah Cruell Nymph! the Rage dost thou not fear Of those wild Beasts that in these VVoods appear? No, no, thou art secure; and mayst out-vy Both them and all the VVorld for Cruelty. Oh thou that gloriest in a heart of stone! VVilt thou not stay? yet seest (as if my Moan They pittied) each rough Bramble 'bout thy foot Does cling, and seems t'arrest thee at my Sute? Ye Gods! what VVonders do you here disclose? The Bramble hath more sweetness than the Rose. But whether fly these idle VVords? in vain Poore, miserable VVretch, thou dost complain; After so many Ills, (of which I bear The sadder Marks yet in my heart;) Now hear Ye Gods at last! and by a welcome Death A period put unto my wretched Breath. Ah me! I faint; my spirits quite decay; And yet I cannot move her heart to stay. Ye hellish Deeps! black Gulphs where Horror lies, Open, and place your selves before her Eyes. Had I Hippomenes bright Fruit, which stay'd The swifter speed of the Schenæian Maid, They would not profit me; the VVorlds round Ball Could not my cruell Fugitive Recall. She is all Rock, and I who am all fire,, Pursue her Night and Day with vain desire. O nature! is it not a Prodigie To find a Rock than fire more light to be? But I mistake: for if a Rock she were Shee'd answer me again as these do here. Thus tyr'd with running, and o'rcome with VVoe, To see his Mistris should out-strip him so, Poor Lyrian yeelds himself as sorrows Prize, His Constancy and amorous Fervor dies, Bloudy dispair entring his captiv'd Soul, Does like a Tyrant all his Powers controul. Then in the height of VVoe to his Relief He cals the Gods, yet in the mid'st of Grief All fair Respect does still to Sylvia give, To shew that ev'n in Death his Love should live. He who for Daphne like Regret did prove, And the horn'd God (who breathless, thought his Love The fair-hair'd Syrinx in his Arms he clasp'd, And slender Reeds for her lov'd Body grasp'd) So far, (remembring their like amorous Fate) His unjust sufferings commiserate, That both straight swore in Passion, and disdain, To punish the proud Author of his Pain: Their powerfull Threats alike effect pursues; See! that proud Beauty a Trees shape endues. Each of her Hairs does sprout into a Bough, And she that was a Nymph, an Elm is now. VVhilst thus transform'd, her feet (to Roots spred) stuck Fast in the ground, she was at last o'rtook By panting Lyrian; happy yet, to see Her he so priz'd within his Power to be; Ye Gods then saies he! who by this sad Test Have 'fore mine Eyes Natures great Power exprest, Grant that to this fair Trunk which Love ne'r knew My heart may yet a Love eternall shew. This having said, unto the yet warm Bole He clings, (whilst a new Form invests his Soul) VVinding in thousand twines about it, whence Hee's call'd of Love the perfect Symbole since. In brief, this faithfull Lover now is found An Ivy Stock; which creeping from the ground About the loved stem, still climbing is, As if he sought her Mouth to steal a Kiss: Each leafe's a heart; whose colour does imply His wish obtain'd, Loves Perpetuity; VVhich still his strict Embraces evidence. For all of him is lost but only sence, And that you'ld swear remains; and say (to see The Elm in his Embraces hugg'd) that he VVilling to keep what he had gain'd at last, For fear she should escape, holds her so fast. FINIS Forsaken LYDIA. Out of the Italian of Cavalier Marino. In Thunder now the hollow Cannon roar'd, To call the farre-fam'd Warriours aboard, Who that great feud (enkindled 'twixt the French And German) with their bloud attempt to quench. Now in the open Sea they proudly ride, And the soft Chrystall with rude Oares divide; Perfidious Armillus at once tore His Heart from Lydia, Anchor from the shore. 'Twas Night, and Aged Proteus had driv'n home His numerous Heard, fleec't with the Seas white fome; The Winds were laid to rest, the fishes slept, The wearied world a generall silence kept, No noise, save from the Surges hollow caves, Or liquid silver of the justling waves, Whilst the bright Lanthorns shot such trembling light, As dazled all the twinkling eyes of Night. The faire Inamorata (who from farre Had spy'd the Ship which her hearts treasure bare, Put off from Land; and now quite disembay'd, Her Cables coiled, and her Anchors weigh'd, Whilst gentle gales her swelling sailes did court To turn in scorn her Poop upon the Port) With frantick speed from the detested Town To the deserted shore comes hurrying down. As the Idæan Shepheard stood amaz'd, Whilst on the sacred Ravisher he gaz'd, Who snatch'd the beautious Trojan youth away, And wafted through the yeelding Clouds his prey; Or as that Artist whose bold hand durst shape Wings to his shoulders (desperately to scape A loathed servitude) through untrac'd skies Creets King pursu'd with fierce, yet wondring Eyes: The flying Navy Lydia so beheld, Her Eyes with Teares, her Heart with Passion swell'd; In sighs to these she gave continuall vent, And those in brinish streames profusely spent: But tears and sighs alas bestows in vain, Borne by the sportive Wind to the deaf Main; The Main, who griefe inexorably mocks, As she her self is scorn'd by steady Rocks. O what a black Eclipse did straight disguise In Clouds the Sunshine of her lovely Eyes! She tore her Cheeks, Hair, Garments, and imprest Marks of his falshood on her guiltless breast. She cals on her disloyall Lovers Name, And sends such sad loud Accents to reclame The Fugitive, as if at every cry Her weary soul forth with her voice would fly. Whither, ah Cruell! There, full grief represt Her Tongue, and taught her Eyes to weep the rest; Whither, ah Cruell, from the hollow side Of the next Rock the Vocall Nymph replied. In Tears and Sighs the Water and the Aire Contend which in her sorrowes most shall share; And the sad Sea hoarse with incessant grones Wakens her faint grief, and supplyes her mones. Oh stop kind Zephyre but one minutes space, (She cries) the swelling Sailes impetuous race, That my expiring groanes may reach the eare Of him who flyes from her he will not heare. Perhaps, though whilst alive I cannot please, My dying Cryes his Anger may appease, And my last Fall, Trophey of his Disdain, May yeeld delight, and his lost Love regain. Receive my heart in this extreme farewell, Thou in whom Cruelty and Beauty dwell, With Thee it fled; but what alas for me Is it to lose my Heart who have lost Thee? Thou art my better selfe; Thou of my heart, The soul, more than the soul that moves it, art: And if thou sentence me to suffer death (My Life) to Thee let me resign my breath. Alas I doe not aske to live content, That were a blessing me Fate never meant; All that my wishes aime at, is, that I (And that's but a poore wish) Content may dye; And if my heart, by Thee already slain, Some reliques yet of a loath'd life retain. Oh let them by thy pitty find release, And in thy Armes breath forth their last in Peace. No greater happinesse than Death I crave, So in thy dearest sight I death may have; And if thy hand, arm'd with relentlesse Pride, Shall the small thread of my poor Life divide, What Pleasure than that Sorrow would be higher? VVhen I in Paradice at least expire; And so at once the different Arrowes prove, Of Death from thy hand, from thy Eyes of Love. Ah! if so pleas'd thou art with Wars alarmes; If that be it that cals thee from my Armes; If thou aspir'st by some advent'rous toiles To raise proud Trophyes deckt with glorious spoiles, Why fondly dost thou seek for these elsewhere? Why leav'st thou me a pris'ner to despair? Turn; nor thy willing Captive thus forsake, And thou shalt all my Victories partake. Though I to thy dear Eyes a Captive be, Thousands of Lovers are no lesse to me. Unhappy! who contend and sue for sight Of that which thou unkindly thus dost slight; Is't not a high attempt that can comprize Within one Act so many Victories; To triumph over Triumphs, and subdue At once the Victor and the Vanquish'd too? But if to stay with me thou dost refuse, And the rude Company of Souldiers choose, Yet give me leave to goe along with Thee, And in the Army thy Attendant be. Love, though a child and blind, the Wars hath known, Can handle Armes, and buckle Armour on; And thou shalt see, my courage will disdain (Save of thy Death) all fear to entertain. I will securely 'midst the arm'd Troops run, Venus hath been Mars' his Companion; And though the heart in thy obdurate Breast Be with an Adamantine Corslet drest, Yet I in Steel (to guard thee from all harm) With my own hands will thy fair body arm, And the Reward Love did from me detain In peace, in War shall by this service gain. And if it fortune that thou undergoe Some dangerous hurt by the prevailing Foe, I sadly by thy side will sit to keep Thee company, and as thou groan'st will weep. My Sorrow with thy Anguish shall comply, I will thy Bloud, and thou my Tears shalt dry: Thus by an equall sympathy of pure Affections we each others wounds will cure. Perhaps when he this sweet effect of Love Shall see, the happy President may move The stubborn Enemy more mild to grow, And to so soft a yoak his stiffe neck bow, Who by himself gladly betraid to thine, Shall willingly his own Command resigne. So by a way of Conquest strangely new, Thou shalt at once Love, Armes, and Soules subdue. Ah most unhappy! he to these sad cries Inexorable his deafe eare denies; And far more cruell than the rough Seas are, Laughs at my sighs, and slights my juster Prayer. See, whilst thou spreadst thy sailes to catch the Wind, What a sad Object thou hast left behind. Of War alas why dost thou goe in quest? Thou leav'st a fiercer War within my Breast. Thou fly'st thy Country and more happy state, To seek in some strange Land a stranger Fate; And under forraign Climes and unknown Stars, T'encounter hazards of destructive Wars; Eager to thrust thy self (lavish of breath) Upon Disasters, Dangers, Bloud and Death, Changing (ah too unwary, too unwise) Thy certain Joyes for an uncertain Prize. Can it be true thou more thy self should'st please With busy troubles than delightfull ease, And lik'st th'enraged Deeps rough toiles above The calmer pleasures and sweet sports of Love? Canst thou from a soft bosome fly (ah lost To gentlenesse!) to be on rude Waves tost? And rather choose in Seas a restlesse Grave, Than in these Arms a quiet Port to have? With furrowing Keel thou plow'st the foming Main, And (O obdurate) hearst not me complain; Too swift thou fly'st for Loves slow wings t'oretake, Love, whom perfidiously thou didst forsake; And all the way thou swell'st with Pride, to know The suff'rings for thy sake I undergoe, Whilst the mild East to flatter thy Desires With his soft Breath thy flagging Sail inspires. Go faithlesse Youth, faithlesse and foolish too, Thy Fate, or folly rather, still pursue; Go, and now thou art from my Fetters free, Never take care who sighs or dyes for Thee. Oh! if the Heavens are just, if ever they With Eyes impartiall humane wrongs survey, Heaven, heaven my tears implore, to Heaven I cry, Avenge my suff'rings, and his Treachery. Be Seas and Skyes thy foes! no gentle gale Blow on thy Shrowds! destruction fill thy Saile! No Star to thee (lost in despair and Night) When thou invok'st, disclose its friendly Light. To Scythian Pyrats, (such as shall despise Thy fruitless tears) mayst thou become a Prize, By whose inhumane usage mayst thou be Spoil'd of the Liberty thou took'st from me. Then thou the difference shalt understand Betwixt the shafts shot from a Thracian hand, And Lovers eye; the odds betwixt a rude Insulting Foe, and Loves soft servitude: The Breast his golden Darts not pierc'd, shall feel The sharp Impression of more cruell steel, And thou enslav'd, which are the stronger prove The fetters of Barbarians, or of Love. Ye Seas and Skies, which of my amorous care The kindly faithfull Secretaries are, To you my crying Sorrows I addresse, To you the witnesses of my distresse: Shores by the losse of my fair Sun forlorn, Winds who my sole delight away have born. Rocks the Spectators of my haplesse Fate, And Night that hearst me mourn disconsolate. Nor without reason is't (alas) that I To Stars and Sands bewail my misery; For with my State they some proportion bear, And numberlesse as are my woes appear. Heaven in this Quire of beautious Lights doth seem To represent what I have losse in him; The Sea to whom his flight I chiefly owe, His heart in Rocks, my tears in Waves doth show. And since to these Eternall Fires whose Light Makes Sleep's dark Mansion so serenely bright I turn; what one amongst them shall I find To pitty me above the rest inclin'd? She who in Naxos when forsook did meet A better Spouse than him she chose in Creet, Though all the rest severely are intent To work me harm, should be more mildly bent. Oh Thou who guild'st the Pompous train of Night, With the addition of thy glorious Light, Whose radiant hair a Crown adorns, whence streams The dazling lustre of seven blazing Gems: If that Extremity thou not forget, If thy own sorrows thou remember yet, Stop at my sighs awhile, and make the Crue Of thy bright fellows stay and hearken too. Thou know'st the like occasions of our Fate, Both circumvented by unkind Deceit; A cruell I, a Love ungratefull Thou Didst follow, both to equall suff'rings bow, In this to thine a near resemblance bears, The Cause that dooms me to eternall Tears; I now am left as thou wert heretofore Alone upon the solitary Shore. But howsoever our misfortunes share The same Effects, their Causes diff'rent are; I my poor self no other have deceiv'd; Thy Brother was through thee of Life bereav'd. Sleep thy Betrayer was, but Love was mine, Thou by thy short Eclipse didst brighter shine, And in the Skyes a Crown of Stars obtain, But I on Earth (forsaken) still remain. Fool, to whose care dost thou thy grief impart? What dost thou talk, or know'st thou where thou art? She midst a dancing Bevy of fair Lights Trips it away, and thy misfortune slights: Yet happy may she go, and her clear beams, Whilst I lament, drench in the Brinish streams; Perhaps the Sea, to my afflicted state, Will prove then her lesse incompassionate. But how on Seas for help should I relye, Where nothing we but Waves and Rocks can spye? Yet so small hopes of succour hath my grief, That of those Rocks and Waves I beg Relief. Down from these Rocks, of Life my troubled Breast, By a sad Precipice may be releast, And my impurer soul in these Waves may Quench her Loose Flames, and wash her stains away. Ah Lydia, Lydia, whither dost thou send Thy lost Complaint? Why words so fruitless spend To angry Waves? to Winds where horror roars? To Rocks that have no ears? to sencelesse shores? Thou giv'st thy grief this Liberty in vain, If Liberty from grief thou canst not gain; And fond presumption will thy hopes abuse, Unlesse thou grief and life together lose. Dye then: so shall my Ghost (as with despair Laden it flyes) raise in the troubled Air Tempests more lowd than Thunder, Storms more black Than Hell or Horrour, in curl'd Waves to wrack His Ship and him: so (and 'tis just) shall I And my proud Foe, at least together dy: On him who first these bitter Sorrows bred, Seas shall avenge the Seas of Tears I shed. This said, she makes a stop; and with rash hast (By violent despair assisted) cast Her self down headlong in the raging Sea, Where she beleev'd it deepest; Now to be Sadly by her enrich'd; whilst from her fair Vermilion lips, bright eyes, Phæbeian hair, Corall a purer tincture doth endue, Chrystall new light, Pearls a more Orient hue. Such was the haplesse fate of Lydia, Who in those Waves from which the King of Day Each morn ascends the blushing East, in those From which the Queen of Love and Beauty rose, A second Queen of Love and Beauty perish'd, Who in her Looks a thousand Graces cherish'd; And by a sad Fate (not unpittied yet) A second Sun eternally did set. Sweet Beauty, the sad wrack of ruthlesse Seas, And ill plac'd Love, whom cruell Destinies Have food for Monsters made, and sport for Waves, With whom so many Graces had their graves, If vain be not my hopes, If no dead fire These Lines devoted to thy Name inspire, Though buried in the Seas salt Waves thou ly, Yet in Oblivions Waves thou shalt not dy. FINIS The Rape of HELLEN out of the Greek of Coluthus. Ye Trojan Nymphs! Xanthus fair Progeny! Who on your Fathers Sands oft laying by Your sacred Armelets, and Heads reedy Tires, Ascend to dance on Ide in mixed Quires; Quit your rough floud; and tell the Phrygian Swains Just verdict: how the Hills he left, the Main's New Toyls to undergo: his Mind what prest With fatall Ships both Sea, and Land t'infest; Whence did that unexpected strife arise, Which made a Shepheard judge 'twixt Deities: What was his bold Award; how to his Ear Arriv'd the fair Greek's Name; for you were there: And Paris thron'd in Ida's shades did see, And Venus glorying in her Victory. When tall Thessalian Mountains the Delights Witness'd of Peleus Hymenæall Rites, Ganymed Nectar at the sacred Feast By Jove's Command fill'd out to every Guest; For all descended from cælestiall Race, That day, with equal forwardness, to grace Fair Thetis (Amphitrite's Sister) strove. From Seas came Neptune, from the Heavens came Jove, And Phœbus from the Heliconian spring, Did the sweet Consort of the Muses bring. Next whom, the Sister to the Thunderer Majestick Juno came: nor did the fair Harmonia's Mother Venus stay behind; Suada went too, who for the Bride entwin'd The Wedding Garland, and Love's Quiver bare. Pallas from Nuptials though averse, was there; Aside her heavy Helmet having laid. Apollo's sister, the Latonian Maid, (Though wholly to the savage Chace apply'd) Her Presence at this Meeting not deny'd. Stern Mars, not such as when his Spear he shakes, But as when he to lovely Venus makes His amorous Address, (his Shield, and Lance Thrown by) there smiling mix'd in a soft dance. But thence unhonour'd Erys was debarr'd; Nor Chyron her, nor Peleus did regard. But Bacchus shaking with his golden Hair His dangling Grapes, lets Zephyre's sportive Air Play with his curled Tresses: like some young Heyfer, (which by a furious Gad-fly stung Quitting the Fields, in shady Forests straies) Whilst madded Erys roams: seeking alwaies, How to disturb the quiet of the Feast. Oft from her rocky Cell (with rage possest) She flings; now stands, then sits: still up and down Groaping on th'Earth, yet could not find a stone: For Lightning shee'd have strook: or by some spell The bold Titanian Brethren rais'd from Hell VVith hostile Flames to storm Jove's starry Fort; Though thus enrag'd, she yet does Vulcan court, Whom Fire, and Malleable steel obeys: She thought the sound of clatt'ring shields to raise, That so the Gods affrighted with the Noise Might have run forth, and left their Festive Joys. But fearing Mars, She does at last incline To put in Act a far more quaint Design: She cals to mind Hesperia's golden Fruit; Whence a fair Apple of dire VVars the Root, Pulling, the Cause of signall strifes she found: Then midst the Feast, Dissentions fatall ground Casts, and disturbs the Goddesses fair Quire. Juno, of Joves Bed proud, does first admire The shining Fruit, then challeng'd as her due: But Venus (all surpassing) claims it too As Love's Propriety: which by Jove seen, He calls, then thus to Hermes, does begin. Know'st thou not Paris, one of Priam's Sons? VVho, where through Phrygian Grounds smooth Xanthus runs, Grazes his horned Heards, on Ida's Hill, To him this Apple bear: say 'tis our Will, As Arbiter of Beauty, he declare VVhich of these Goddesses excells in rare Conjunction of arch'd Eyebrows, lovely grace, And well-proportion'd roundness of the Face; And she that seems the fairest in his Eyes, To have the Apple, as her Beauties prize. This charge on Mercury, Saturnius laies, VVho humbly his great Sires Commands obeys; And with officious care Th'Immortals guides: VVhilst each her self in her own Beauty prides, But as they went: Loves subtle Queen, her heads Rich Tire unloosing, with gold Fillets breads Her curious Hair; then thus, with Eyes intent On her wing'd Sons, her troubled thoughts does vent. The strife is neer; deer Sons your Mother aide! This day must crown my Beauty, or degrade. And much I fear to whom this Clown will give The golden fruit: Juno, all men beleeve To be the Graces reverend Nurse: to Her The gift of Scepters they assign, in War A powerfull Goddess is Minerva deem'd: But We alone are of no Pow'r esteem'd. Nor Empires We, nor Martiall Arms bestow: Yet why without a cause thus fear We? though Minerva's spear We have not, We yet better Are with our Cestus arm'd, sweet Loves soft Fetter, Our Cestus: that our Bow is, that our sting, Which smart to Women, but not death does bring. Thus rosie-finger'd Venus on the Way To her attending Cupids spake, whilst they, With dutious Words, their drooping Mother cheer. And now they reach'd the Top of Ida; where The youthfull Paris neer Anaurus head, His Father's sheep in Flocks divided fed: Here of his roving Buls he count doth keep, And there he reckons o'r his well-fed sheep. Low as his Knee, a Mountain Goats rough hide Hung from his shoulders flagging by his side: In's hand a Neatheards Goad: such to the Eye (As slowly to his Pipes soft Melody He moves) appear'd the gentle Phrygian Swain: Tuning on's Reed, a sweet, though rurall strain. I'th'solitary stalls oft would he set Himself with Songs delighting; and forget The care both of his Heards and Flocks; the Praise Of Pan and Hermes subject of his Layes, (With Shepheards most in use: whose sweeter Note No Dogs rude Howl, no Bulls loud-bellowing Throat Disturbs; but Eccho only, that affords An artless sound in unarticulate Words. His Oxen cloy'd with the rank Grass, were layd, Stretching their fat sides in the cooler shade; Under th'Umbrella of a spreading Tree Whilst he himself sate singing: but when he Spy'd Hermes with the Goddesses; afraid, Upstarting. from their sight he would have made: And, (his sweet Pipe among the Bushes flung) Abruptly clos'd his scarce commenced Song. To whom, amaz'd, thus Heavens wing'd Nuncius spake: Cast away fear: a while thy Flocks forsake, Thou must in Judgement sit; and freely tell Which of these Pow'rs in Beauty does excell, And to the fairest this fair fruit present. Thus he: when Paris, with Eyes mildly bent In amorous Glances, of their Beauties took Exact survey: which had the gracefull'st Look, The brightest Eyes, whose Neck the whitest skin, Not leaving ought from Head, to Heel, unseen. To whom Minerva first her self addrest, Then, taking by the hand, these Words exprest. Come hither, Paris! leave Jove's Wife behind: Nor Venus President of Nuptials, mind. Pallas of Valour the Directress praise: Intrusted with large Rule and Power, Fame saies, Thou govern'st Troy: Me chief for Form confess, I'll make thee too its Guardian in distress. Comply, and 'gainst Bellona's dreadfull Harms Secur'd, I'll teach thee the bold deeds of Arms. Thus Pallas courted him: she scarce had done When with fair Words, and Looks, Juno begun. If me the Prize of Beauty thou'lt assign, The Empire of all Asia shall be thine; Slight Wars, what good from thence to Princes springs? Both valiant men and Cowards stoop to Kings. Nor doe Minerva's Followers oft rise high, But Servants rather to Bellona dy: This glorious Proffer stately Juno made. But Venus (her large Veil unloos'd) displayd Her whiter Bosome; nor at all was shy; But did the honied Chain of Loves unty: And, (whilst to view she her fair Breasts disclos'd) Thus spake; her Looks into sweet smiles dispos'd. Our Beauty, Wars forgot, our Beauty prize, And Empires and the Asian Lands despise. We know not Wars, nor use of Shields can tell; In Beauty, Women rather should excell; For Valour, I'll to thee a Wife commend, Stead of a Throne fair Hellens Bed ascend. A Spouse, thee Troy and Sparta shall behold: Scarce had she ended, when the fruit of Gold To Venus, as her Beauties noble Prize, The Swain presented; whence dire Wars did rise. Who in her hand as she the Apple weigh'd, Did Juno, and Minerva thus upbraid. Yield me the Victory, yield me fair Friends! Beauty I lov'd, and Beauty me attends: Juno they say thou gav'st the Graces Life, Yet they have all forsook thee in this strife, Though thou to Mars and Vulcan Mother art, Nor Mars nor Vulcan did their Aid impart; Though this in Flames, that glory in his Spear, Yet neither one nor other helpt thee here. How thou braggd'st too, who from no Mothers wombe But Jove's cleft Skull, the Birth of Steel, didst come? In Armour how thy Limbs are drest? how Love Thou shunn'st, and dost the Toyls of Mars approve? Alike to Peace and Wedlock opposite. Minerva! know, that such for glorious Fight Are much unfit, whom by their Limbs, none well Whether they Men, or Women be, can tell. Sad Pallas thus, proud of her Victory, She flouts, and her, and Juno both puts by, Whilst she the fatall Prize of Beauty won. Inflam'd with Love, hot in pursuit of one To him unknown; with inauspicious Fate, Men skill'd in Architecture, Paris strait To a dark Wood conducts; where, in a Trice, Tall Oaks are fell'd by Phereclus Advice, Of Ills the Author, who before to please His fond King Ships had built; whilst for the Seas Paris does Ida change; and on the shore With frequent Pray'rs, and Sacrifice, implore His kind Assistant, Queen of Marriage-vows; Then the broad Back of Hellespontus ploughs. But sad presaging Omens did appear: Seas rising to the Skyes, did either Bear Surround with a dark Ring of Clouds; whilst through The troubled Air a showring Tempest flew. With stroaks of active Oars the Ocean swell'd: And now, the Trojan Shores forsook, he held His Course for Greece, and born with winged hast, Ismarus Mouth, and tall Pangæus past. Then Love-slain Phyllis rising Monument, And of the Walk which oft she came and went, The Ninefold Round he saw; there she to mourn Did use, while her Demophoon's safe Return, She from Athenian Lands expected: then Coasting by Thessalies broad Shores, in Kenn The fair Achaian Cities next appear'd. Men-breeding Phthia, and Mycene, rear'd High, and wide built; when the rich Meadows past Water'd by Erymanthus, He at last Spies Sparta, lov'd Atrides City, plac'd Near cleer Eurotas, with rare Beauties grac'd: Not far from whence, under a shady Wood, H'admiring saw how sweet Therapnæ stood. For now but a short Cut he had to sail, Nor long was heard the dash of Oars: they hale The Ship to shore, and with strong Haulsers ty'd; When Paris with cleer water purifi'd, Upon his Tiptoes lightly treads, for fear His lovely feet he with the Dust should smear, Or going hastily, his Hair which flows Beneath his Hat, the Winds should discompose. By this, the stately Buildings, drawing nigher He views, the Neighbouring Temples that aspire, And Cities splendour: where with wondring Eyes The Statue of their Pallas he espies, All of pure Gold; from which, his roving sight Next Hyacinthus Image does invite; The Boy with whom Apollo us'd to play: VVhom lest Latona should have rapt away (Displeas'd with Jove) the Amyclæans fear'd. Phœbus from envious Zephyre, who appear'd His Rivall, could not yet secure the Boy: But Earth t'appease the sad Kings Tears, his Joy, A Flow'r produc'd; a Flow'r, that doth proclame Of the once lovely Youth, the still-lov'd Name. Now near Atrides Court, before the Gates, Bright in cælestiall Graces Paris waites. Not Semele a Youth so lovely bare: (Your Pardon Bacchus! though Joves Son you are) Such Beauty did his Looks irradiate. But Hellen the Court doors unbolting strait, VVhen 'fore the Hall the Trojan she had seen And throughly mark'd, kindly invites him in, And seats him in a Silver Chair; her Eyes VVhilst on his Looks she feeds, not satisfies. First she suppos'd he Venus Son might be, Yet when his quiver's Shafts she did not see She knew he was not Love; but by the shine Of his bright Looks thought him the God of VVine. At length her VVonder in these VVords did break. VVhence art my Guest? thy Stock, thy Country speak; For Majesty is printed in thy Face: And yet thou seem'st not of the Argive Race. Of sandy Pylos sure thou canst not be, I know Antilochus, but know not thee. Nor art of Phthia which stout Men doth breed, I know all Æacus renowned Seed; The glorious Peleus, and his warlike Son, Courteous Patroclus, and stout Telamon: Thus Hellen curious to be satisfi'd, Questions her Guest; who fairly thus reply'd. If thou of Troy in Phrygia's utmost bound, By Neptune, and Apollo walled round, And of a King from Saturn sprung, who there Now fortunately rules, didst ever hear, His Son am I; and all within his sway, To me, as chief next him, subjection pay. From Dardanus am I descended, he From Jove; where Gods, immortal though they be Do oft serve Mortals: who beguirt our Town Round with a VVall, a VVall that ne'r shall down. I am great Queen! the Judge of Goddesses, VVhom though displeas'd, I censur'd, and of these The lovely Venus Beauty did prefer: For which, in noble Recompence, by her Promis'd a VVife, her Sister, Hellen nam'd, For whom these Troubles I through Seas sustain'd. Since Venus bids, here let us solemnize Our Nuptiall Rites; Me nor my Bed despise; On what is known, insist we need not long. Thy Spouse from an unwarlike Race is sprung: Thou all the Græcian Dames dost far outvy, Beautious thy Looks are, theirs, their Sex belye. At this she fix'd on Earth her lovely Eyes, And doubtfull, paws'd a while, at length replies. Your Wals my Guest! by hands Cælestiall rais'd, And Pastures, where his Heards Apollo graz'd, I long to see: to Troy bear me away. I'l follow thee, and Venus will obey; Nor, there, will Menelaus anger heed; Thus Paris, and the beautious Nymph agree'd. Now Night the ease of Cares, the Day quite spent, Sleep brought, suspended by the Morns Ascent, Of Dreams the two Gates opening: this of Horn, In which the Gods unerring Truths are born. T'other of Ivory: whence couzening Lies, And vain Delusions of false Dreams arise. When from Atrides Hospitable Court Paris through plough'd Seas Hellen does transport, And in the gift of Venus proudly joy; Bearing with speed the Fraight of War to Troy. Hermione, soon as the Morn appears, To Winds her torn Veyl casting, big with Tears, Her Loss bewails; and from her Chamber flying, With grief distraught, thus to her Maids spake, crying. Whither without me is my Mother fled? Who lay with me last Night in the same Bed? And with her own hand lockt the Chamber door? Thus spake she weeping: All the Maids deplore With her their Mistress absence; yet assay With these kind Words her Passion to allay. Why dost thou weep sweet Child! thy Mother's gon, But will return soon as she hears thy Moan. See how thy Tears have blubber'd thy fair Cheeks! Much weeping the divinest Beauty breaks. She 'mongst the Virgins is but gon to play, And comming back perhaps has miss'd her way: And in some flowry Medow doubtfull stands; Or in Eurotas bath'd, sports on his Sands. The weeping Child replyes; the Hill, Brook, Walk, And Fields she knows; doe not so idly talk: The Stars doe sleep, yet on cold Rocks she lies; The Stars awake, and yet she does not rise. O my dear Mother! where dost thou abide? Upon what Mountains barren Top reside? Hath some wild Beast alas! thee wandring slain; (Yet from Joves Royall Blood wild Beasts refrain) Or fall'n from some steep Precipice, art layd An unregarded Corse in some dark shade? And yet in ev'ry Grove, at ev'ry Tree, Search have I made, but cannot meet with Thee. The Woods we blame not then; nor doe profound Eurotas gentle streams conceal thee drown'd: For in deep Floods the Naiades doe use, Nor e'r by them their Lives doe VVomen lose. Thus poor Hermione complaining wept, Then tow'rd her shoulder her head leaning, slept. (Sleep is Deaths Twin, and as the younger Brother, In every thing doth imitate the other; Hence 'tis that VVomen often when they weep, O'recharg'd with their own sorrows, fall asleep) VVhen in a Dream, her Mother (as she thought) Seeing, she cries, vex'd, yet with fear distraught: From me disconsolate last night you fled, And left me sleeping in my Fathers Bed. VVhat Hill, what Mountain have I left untrac'd? To Venus pleasing Ties mak'st thou such haste? To whom fair Tyndaris this Answer made: Daughter! though griev'd, me yet forbear t'upbraid: That treacherous Stranger, who the other Day Came hither, carry'd me by force away. Thus she: at which out strait Hermione flies. But finding not her Mother, louder cries; VVing'd Issue of th'Inhabitants of Air, Ye Birds! to Menelaus strait declare, One late arriving at the Spartan Port, Hath rob'd him of the Glory of his Court. Thus to regardless VVinds did she complain, Seeking her absent Mother, but in vain. Mean-time, through Thracian Towns, and Helles strait Paris arriv'd safe with his beautious Fraight, VVhen from the Castle, viewing on the shore A new guest Land, her hair Cassandra tore. But Troy with open Gates her welcome shows To the returning Author of her VVoes. FINIS</field>
      <field name="fulltext">LUDICRA THE SYRACUSIANS, OR ADONIS FESTIVAL Theocrit. Idyl. 15. Gorgo, Eunoa, Praxinoe, two strangers, an old Woman. Gorgo. Pray, is Praxinoe within? Eunoa. What, Dear Gorgo! how great a stranger? yes, shee's here. Prax. I'th' name of wonder, what's the news with thee? Fetch her a Stool and Cushion. Gorgo. Not for me. Prax. Nay sit. Gorgo. Well fare a stout heart yet: I thought I scarce should er'e alive to thee have got Through such a throng of men, and Coaches: All The streets are set with Guards, and every stall Crowded with gallants; and thou know'st beside From hence to our house is no little stride. Prax. My Goodman Dotard (thank him) at th'worlds end Hath found this hole for Me; lest any friend Should e'r come at Me: Mischief on his Care That's onely bent to cross me. Gorgo. Dear, beware To talk thus 'fore the child: See how his eye Is set upon thee! Prax. I, 'tis my good boy; We speak not of thy Father. Gorgo. Now by'r Lady The Child does understand—Dad's a fine Daddy. Prax. Well, this fine Dad, (for we in private may Say what we please) being spoke to th'other day, Ceruse and Merc'ry at the shops to buy, Brings me home salt: this Dunce twelve Cubits high. Gorgo. Just so my Diocleides does; that Grave Of money! Yesterday, a Crown he gave For a few Dag-locks coarser than Doggs hair; Five Sheep-skins too he bought: most precious ware! But let that pass: come, make thee ready strait; And let's to Court, to see them celebrate Adonis Feast: the Queen intends (they say) To make a gallant shew on't. Prax. Great ones may Do great things: tell them this that nothing see. Gorgo. Faith, dress thee straight, and go along with me: With loyterers t'is alwaies holiday. Prax. Fetch me some water hither, Eunoa: D'ee hear, Joan Cleanly! high you, make more haste; Quick; The Cat loves a Cushion: see how fast She comes with it!—pour forth: not so much (Drone!) Yee idle slut, why hast thou wet my gown? Hold!—W'are e'en washt after a sort, as please The Fates:—lock the great chest, and bring the keys. Gorgo. That gown does thee exceeding well become. How much might the stuff cost thee from the Loom? Prax. I pray thee do not ask Me: 'bove one Pound Or two, the weaving: but the yarn I found. Gorgo. Troth it does mighty well. Prax. And well y'have sed. Reach me my Kirtle, wench; and help me spread My scarf.—Child, you must stay at home: there's sprites Where we are going, and a horse that bites. Nay, cry (and th'woo't) as long as thou canst scream, I care not: dost thou think I'le see thee lame? Come,—take the boy, and play with him: d'ee hear! Call the Dog in, and make the dore fast.—Dear What a huge crowd's here! how shall we get by? They swarm like Ants. O noble Ptolomy! Many a good deed since thy Fathers daies We ow thee thanks for. Free are now the waies From Thieves and Murtherers: no Rogues flock together To act their cheats now, like birds of a Feather. But which way now? there's the Horse-guard before us. Pray friend be fair condition'd; don't ride or'e us. O, he curvets; 'tis a fierce horse that Bay; Hee'l throw his Rider, let's get out o'th'way: Run Eunoe:—I'm glad yet I have made The boy keep home. Gorgo. Come, courage; ben't afraid: They'r past us now. Prax. And so's my fright: good Lord! A Horse and Snake are two things I've abhorr'd Even from a child:—but haste, or else another Shole will or'etake us. Gorgo. Come you from Court, Mother? Old Woman. Yes, my good Daughter. Gorgo. Pray, may one get in? Old Woman. The Greeks did Troy by their endeavours win: Endeavour will do all things. Gorgo. Sli'd th'old Crone Speaks Oracles. To woman what's unknown? How Jove wood Juno they can tell. But see, Before the Gate what store of company? Prax. A world! Gorgo, thy hand: Eutychides, Lend Eunoa thine, least she be lost i'th' press. Let's all crowd in together: Eunoe, Be sure you keep your hold. Gorgo, Ah me! My scarfe's rent quite in two: good Sir, for love Of Heaven, help save my scarf there. Stranger. 'Tis above My power to do it: yet I'le do my best. Prax. They thrust like Swine: how vildely are we prest! Stranger. Come, come, w'are well now: take a good heart. Prax. May it be ever so with thee, that art So kind to us: an honest civil man: But O, they crowd as bad as e're again. Help, help alas! thrust Eunoa for thy life. So, now w'are in, as the man said to's wife. Gorgo. Come, look upon these Hangings first; so fair, As if the handy work of Gods they were. Prax. Bless me! what Artist made them of so fine A Woof? what Painter could so well design? They seem to move: sure they're alive, not wrought: Lord! Lord! the wit of man surpasses thought. But see how lovely on a silver bed (His tender cheeks with a soft down o'respread) Adonis lies! how admirably fair! With whom the powers of Hell enamour'd are. 2?. Stranger. Peace, foolish tatling women; hold your prate: Your wide mouth'd Dorick here is out of date. Gorgo. Gup: who art thou? what is our talk to thee? Correct your maids, not us of Sicilie: Yet (would you knew't) we are from Corinth sprung, As was Bellerophon: our Mother Tongue Peloponnesian is: nor is it scorn That they speak Dorick, who are Dorick born. Prax. More Lords then one, Sir, we disclaim: so short! Ye need not faith: here's those care little for't. Gorgo. Whist! whist Praxinoe! The Hymn let's hear: This is the maid that did from Sperchis bear The Prize. I know shee'l sing anon, she hums Unto her self such sweet Præludiums. The Hymn. Thou who in Golgos, and Idalia tak'st Delight, with lofty Erix; who gold mak'st Thy joy: sweet Venus! see the soft pace't hours Thy dear Adonis from th'Infernal powers Have brought again at the years end to thee! Though slowest of the Deities they be, Yet they come wish'd for, and with something fraught Alwaies to all. Thou whom Dione brought To light, fair Cypris! Berenice's said, Mortal, by thee to be Immortall made, And fed with sweet Ambrosia: wherefore now, Her daughter (to make good her grateful vow To thee) her Daughter (who for form may be A second Helin) fair Arsinoe, To thy Adonis choisest gifts assigns; O thou, that gloriest in thy numerous shrines! The several fruits which laden Top-boughs yeild Beside him lie: here flowers of every field In Silver Baskets: there Gold Boxes stand Full of Assyrian unguents: on his hand, All sorts of rare Confections; and with those, What e're of Oyl or Hony we compose. All Fowls, all beasts for food: green Arbours drest With soft Dil branches, where Loves make their nest: And like young Nightingales that have but now New try'd their wings, flutter from bough to bough. O the golds splendour! the pure Ivories too! The Eagle with Joves Cup-bearer that flew! And Purple Carpets then sleep softer! may The wondring Samian, and Milesian say. Here on a rich Bed doth Adonis lie; And lovely Venus on another by. Soft are his kisses, and his lips still red; Venus, now joy in his regained Bed. For we to morrow, e're the dew's exhal'd, With hairs unbound, loose garments, brests unveild, Him to the foaming waves that wash the shore, Shall bear from hence, and with sad songs deplore. The way from Hell (Adonis) unto thee Is ever open, though to none else free Of all the glorious Heroes (as they tell) This ne'r t'Atrides, Ajax ne're befel. Not Hector, chief of Hecub's numerous Race, Patroclus, Pyrrhus, those of elder daies, The Lapithites, Deucalions issue; nor The Sons of Pelops, (Princes fam'd in War) Nor Argive Kings could er'e to this attain. Be now appeas'd: and the next year again Bring gladness with thee: still propitious prove, And as thou cam'st, return to us in love. Gorgo. O deer! what a rare woman's this? what choice Of knowledge hath she? and how sweet a voice? But go:—My husband's fasting still, and then He eats his own Gall: Fear a hungry man. Fare-well Adonis for this time; and when The year's done, come, and make us glad agen. THE SUN-RISE Thou youthfull Goddess of the Morn! Whose blush they in the East adore; Daughter of Phœbus! who before Thy all-enlightning Sire art born! Haste! and restore the day to me, That my Loves beautious Object I may see. Too much of time the night devours, The Cocks shrill voice calls thee again; Then quickly mount thy golden Wain Drawn by the softly-sliding hours: And make apparent to all eyes With what Enamel thou dost paint the skies. Leave thy old husband, let him lie Snorting upon his downy bed; And to content thy Lover, spread Thy Flames new lighted, through the sky; Heark how thy presence he conjures, As leading to the Woods his Hounds, he lures. Moisten the fallow grounds before Thou com'st, with a sweet dewie rain; That thirstie Ceres having ta'ne Her Mornings draught, that day no more May call for drink; and we may see Spangled with pearlie drops each bush and tree. Ah! now I see the sweetest dawn! Thrice welcome to my longing sight! Hail divine beautie! Heavenly light! I see thee through yon Cloud of Lawn Appear; and as thy star does glide, Blanching with raies the East on every side. Dull silence, and the drowsie King Of sad and Melancholie Dreams, Now flie before thy cheerful Beams, The darkest shadows vanquishing: The Owl, that all the night did keep Ahouting, now is fled and gone to sleep. But all those little Birds, whose noats Sweetly the listning ear enthrall, To the clear waters murmuring fall, Accord their disagreeing throats, The lustre of that greater Star Praising, to which thou art but Harbinger. 'Bove our Horizon see him scale The first point of his brighter Round! O how the swarthie Æthiop's bound With reverence to his light to veil, And love the colour of his look, Which from a heat so mild, so pure he took. A God perceivable is he By humane sense, Natures bright eye, Without whom all her works would die, Or in their births imperfect be: He Grace and Beautie gives alone, To all the Works of her Creation. With holie Reverence inspir'd, When first the day renews it's light, The Earth, at so Divine a sight, Seems as if all on Altar fir'd, Reeking with Perfumes to the skies, Which she presents, her Native Sacrifice. The humble Shepherd to his Raies, Having his Rustick Homage paid, And to some cool retired shade Driven his bleating Flocks to Graze; Sits down, delighted with the sight Of that great Lamp, so milde, so fair, so bright. The Eagle in her Airy sitting Spreading her wings, with fixed eye Gazes on him, t'whose Deitie She yields all Adoration fitting: As to the only quickning fire, And Object that her eye does most desire. The Salmon (which at Spring forsakes Thetis salt Waves) to look on him, Upon the waters top doth swim: And to express the joy he takes, As sportingly along he sails, Mocks the poor Fisher with his silver Scales. The Bee through flowrie Gardens goes Buzzing to drink the mornings tears; And from the early Lillly bears A kiss, commended to the Rose; And like a wary Messenger, Whispers some Amorous story in her ear. At which, shee rowsing from her sleep, Her chaster Flames seems to declare To him again (whil'st Dew her fair And blushing leaves in tears doth steep) The sorrow which her heart doth waste, That shee's so far from her dear Lover plac't. And further seems, as if this plaint In her mute Dialect she made: [“]Alas! I shall with sorrow fade, [“]And pine away in this restraint, [“]Unless my too too rigorous Fate, [“]My Constant faithful Love commiserate. [“]Love having gain'd the victory [“]Over my soul, there acts his harms, [“]Nor Thorns so many bear my Arms, [“]As in my heart now prickles be: [“]The onely Comfort I can give [“]My self, is this; I have not long to live. [“]But if some courteous Virgin shall, [“]Pitying my Fate, pull my sweet flowre, [“]E're by a sad and fatal hour [“]My Honours fade away and fall; [“]I nothing more shall then desire, [“]But gladly without murmuring expire.[”] Peace sweetest Queen of Flowres! now see Sylvia, Queen of my Love, appear: Who for thy Comfort brings with her What will thy wishes satisfie; For her white hand intends to grace thee And in her sweeter Brest, sweet flower to place thee. The Night: OR, The fair Mourner. This fair, and animated Night In Sables drest; whose Curls of Light Are with a shade of Cypresse veil'd; Not from the Stygian Deeps exhal'd, But from Heaven's bright Balcone came; Not dropping Dew, but shedding Flame. The blushing East her smiles display, Her beauteous Front the Dawn of Day; The Stars doe sparkle in her Eyes, And in her Looks the Sun doth rise. No mask of Clouds and Storms she wears, But still serene and calm appears: No dismall Birds, no hideous Fiends, Nor charming Hag on her attends; The Graces are her Maids of Honour, And thousand Cupids wait upon her. Dear Flames! still burning, though you are Supprest: Lights, though obscur'd, still fair! What Heart does not adore you? who But sighs, or languishes for you? Heaven wishes, by your shade outvy'd, It's milky Path in Ink were dy'd: The Sun within an Ebon Case, Longs to shut up his golden Face: The Moon too with thy sad Dresse took, Would fain put on a mourning Look. Sweet Night! and if th'art Night, of Peace The gentle Mother! Cares Release! My Heart, now long opprest, relieve; And in thy softer Bosome give My weary Limbs a short Repose; 'Tis but a small Request, Heaven knows: Nor think it shame to condiscend, For Night is stil'd the Lovers Friend. But Muse, thou art too loud I fear, The Night loves silence, Muse forbear. I SOSPIRI. Sighs. Sighs! light, warm spirits! in which, Air, And Fire, possesse an equall share: The Souls soft Breath! Loves gentle Gales! Which from Griefs Golfe (when all else failes) Can by a speedy Course, and short, Conduct the Heart to it's sweet Port: Ye flattering Zephyrs! by whose Pow'r, Rais'd on the Wings of thought, each How'r From the Abysse of Miseries To her Lov'd Heav'n the freed Soul flies. True lively sparks of that close Fire, Which Hearts conceal, and Eyes inspire: Chast Lamps that burn at Beauties shrine, Whose purer Flames let none confine: Nature a warmth unto my Heart, Does not so kind as yours impart; And if by Breath preserv'd alive, By your Breath only I survive. Loves faithfull Witnesses! the Brief, But true Expresses of our Grief! Embassadors of mute Desires! Dumb Rhetorick which our Thoughts attires! Grief, when it overloads the Brest, Is in no other language drest; For you the suffering Lovers Flame, Sweet, tounglesse Orators, proclame. A numerous Descant upon Sorrow! Which sweetnes doth from sadnes borrow, VVhen Love two differing Hearts accords, And Joy, in well-tun'd Grief, affords. The Musick of whose sweet Concent, In a harmonious Languishment, Does softly fall, and gently rise, 'Till in a broken Cloze, it dies. Nature, and all that call her Mother, In Sighs discourse to one another: Theirs, Nightingals, and Doves, in Tones Different expresse; this sings, that grones: The Thrush, his, whistles to his Hen; The Sparrow chirps out his agen; Snakes breath their amorous sighs in Hisses; This Dialect no Creature misses. The Virgin Lilly, bashfull Rose, In Odours their soft sighs disclose; Theirs, sportive VVinds in whispers breath; Earth hers in Vapours doth bequeath To her cælestiall Lover; He, Touch't with an equall Sympathie, To fann the Flame with which she burns, In gentle Gales his sighs returns. Yee glowing Sparks of a chast Fire! Now to those radiant Lights aspire, The fairer Nests of my fair Love, And the bright Spheres where you should move. The Surprise. There's no dallying with Love Though he be a Child and blind; Then let none the danger prove VVho would to himself be kind: Smile he does when thou do'st play, But his smiles to death betray. Lately with the Boy I sported; Love I did not, yet Love feign'd; Had not Mistress, yet I courted; Sigh I did, yet was not pain'd; 'Till at last this Love in Jeast, Prov'd in Earnest my Unrest. VVhen I saw my fair One first, In a feigned fire I burn'd; But true flames my poor Heart pierc't, VVhen her Eyes on mine she turn'd: So a reall VVound I took For my counterfeited Look. Slighted Love his skill to show, Strook me with a Mortall Dart; Then I learnt that 'gainst his Bow, Vain are the weak Helps of Art: And thus captiv'd, found that true Doth dissembled Love pursue. 'Cause his Fetters I disclam'd, Now the Tyrant faster bound Me; VVith more scorching Brands inflam'd, 'Cause in Love so cold he found me: And my sighs more scalding made, 'Cause with VVinds before they playd. None who loves not then make shew, Love's as ill deceiv'd as Fate; Fly the Boy, hee'l cogg and wooe; Mock him, and he wounds thee strait. Ah! who dally boast in vain; False Love wants not reall Pain. Chloris Eyes and Breasts. Chloris! on thine Eyes I gaz'd; When amaz'd At their brightnes, On thy Breasts I cast my Look; No lesse took With their whitenes: Both I justly did admire, These all Snow, and those all Fire. Whilst these Wonders I survay'd, Thus I said In suspence; Nature could have done no lesse To expresse Her Providence, Than that two such fair Worlds, might Have two Suns to give them Light. Love's Arithmetick. By a gentle River laid, Thirsis to his Phillis said; Equall to these sandy Grains, Is the Number of my Pains: And the Drops within their Bounds Speak the sum of all my Wounds. Phillis, whom like Passion burns, Thirsis Answer thus returns: Many as the Earth hath leaves, Are the Griefs my heart receives; And the Stars, which Heaven inspires, Reckon my consuming Fires. Then the Shepheard, in the Pride Of his happy Love, reply'd; With the Choristers of Air Shall our numerous Joyes compare; And our mutuall Pleasures vy With the Cupids in thine Eye. Thus the willing Shepheardesse Did her ready Love expresse: In Delights our Pains shall cease, And our War be cur'd by Peace; We will count our Griefs with Blisses, Thousand Torments, Thousand Kisses. Cælia weeping. A Dialogue. Lover. Say gentle God of Love, in Cælia's Brest, Can Joy and Grief together rest? Love. No; for those differing Passions are, Nor in one Heart at once can share. Lover. Why grieves hers then at once, and joyes, Whilst it anothers Heart destroyes? Love. Mistaken Man! that Grief she showes, Is but what martyr'd Hearts disclose Which in her Breast tormented lye, And Life can neither hope, nor dy. Lover. And yet a showre of Pearly Rain Does her soft Cheeks fair Roses stain. Love. Alas! those Tears you hers surmise, Are the sad Tribute of poor Lovers Eyes. Chorus. Lover &amp; Love. What reall then in VVomen can be known! When nor their Joys, nor Sorrows are their Own? The Vow. By my Life I vow, That my Life, art Thou: By my Heart, and by my Eyes: But thy Faith denies To my juster Oath t'encline, For thou say'st I swear by thine. By this Sigh I swear, By this falling Tear, By the undeserved Pains My griev'd Soul sustains. Now thou may'st beleeve my Moan, These are too too much my own. Ice &amp; Fire. Naked Love, did to thine Eye, Chloris, once to warm him, fly; But it's subtle Flame, and Light, Scorch'd his Wings, and spoyl'd his sight. Forc'd from thence he went to rest In the soft Couch of thy Brest: But there met a Frost so great, As his Torch extinguish'd strait. When poor Cupid, thus, (constrain'd His cold Bed to leave) complain'd; 'Lass! what lodging's here for Me, If all Ice and Fire She be. Novo Inamoramento. And yet anew entangled, see Him, who escap'd the snare so late! A Truce, no League thou mad'st with Me False Love! which now is out of date: Fool, to beleeve the Fire quite out, alas! VVhich only laid asleep in Embers was. The Sickness not at first past cure, By this Relapse despiseth Art: Now, treacherous Boy, thou hast me sure, Playing the VVanton with my Heart, As foolish Children that a Bird have got, Slacken the Thread, but not unty the knot. Cælia's Eyes. A Dialogue. Lover. Love! tell me; may we Cælia's Eyes esteem Or Eyes, or Stars? for Stars they seem. Love. Fond, stupid Man! know Stars they are, Nor can Heaven boast more bright or fair. Lover. Are they or erring Lights, or fixed? say. Love. Fix'd; yet lead many a Heart astray. The Resemblance. Marble (coy Cælia!) 'gainst my Pray'rs thou art, And at thy Frown to Marble I convert. Love thought it fit, and Nature, thus To manifest their severall Powers in us. Love made me Marble, Nature thee, To express Constancy and Cruelty. Now both of us shall Monuments remain; I of firm Faith, thou of Disdain. Love once, Love ever. Shall I hopeless then pursue A fair shadow that still flies me? Shall I still adore, and wooe A proud Heart that does despise me? I a constant Love may so, But alas! a fruitless shew. Shall I by the erring Light Of two crosser Stars still sail? That do shine, but shine in spight, Not to guide, but make me fail? I a wandring Course may steer, But the Harbour ne'r come near. Whilst these Thoughts my Soul possess, Reason, Passion would o'rsway; Bidding me my Flames suppress, Or divert some other way: But what Reason would pursue, That my Heart runs counter to. So a Pilot bent to make Search for some unfound out Land, Does with him the Magnet take, Sailing to the unknown Strand; But that (steer which way he will) To the loved North points still. The Pendants. Those Aspes of Gold with Gems that shine, And in Enammel'd Curles do twine, Why Chloris in each Ear Dost thou for Pendants wear? —I now the hidden meaning guess: Those Mystick signs express The stings thine Eyes do dart Killing as Snakes into my Heart: And shew that to my Prayers Thine Ears are deaf as theirs. The sweet Meat. Thou gav'st me late to eat A sweet without, but within, bitter Meat: As if thou would'st have said, Here, taste in this What Cælia is. But if there ought to be A likeness (deerest!) 'twixt thy gift and thee, VVhy first what's sweet in thee should I not taste, The bitter last? Violets in Thaumantia's Bosome. Tvvice happy Violets! that first had Birth In the warm Spring, when no frosts nip the Earth; Thrice happy now; since you transplanted are Unto the sweeter Bosome of my Fair. And yet poor Flowers! I pitty your hard Fate, You have but chang'd, not better'd your Estate: What boots it you t'have scap'd cold Winters breath, To find, like me, by Flames a sudden death? The Dream. Fair shadow! faithless as my sun! Of peace she robs my Mind, And to my sense, which rest doth shun, Thou art no less unkind. She my Address disdainfull flies, And thou like her art fleet; The reall Beauty she denies, And thou the Counterfeit. To cross my innocent desires, And make my Griefs extreme, A Cruell Mistris thus conspires With a delusive Dream. An old Shepheard to a young Nymph. Scorn me not Fair because you see My Hairs are white; what if they be? Think not 'cause in your Cheeks appear Fresh springs of Roses all the year, And mine, like Winter, wan and cold, My Love like Winter should be cold: See in the Garland which you wear How the sweet blushing Roses there With pale-hu'd Lillies do combine? Be taught by them; so let us joyn. Beauty encreased by Pity. 'Tis true; thy Beauty, (which before Did dazle each bold gazers Eye, And forc'd even Rebell-Hearts t'adore, Or from its conquering splendour fly) Now shines with new encrease of Light, Like Cynthia at her full, more bright. Yet though thou glory in th'Increase Of so much Beauty deerest Fair! They err who think this great Access, (Of which all Eyes th'Admirers are) Or Art, or Nature's gift should be: Learn then the hidden Cause from Me. Pitty in thee, in me desire First bred; (before, I durst but aime At fair Respect) now that close fire Thy Love hath fann'd into a flame: Which mounting to its proper Place, Shines like a Glory 'bout thy Face. Weeping and Kissing. A kiss I begg'd; but smiling, Shee Deny'd it Me: When strait, her Cheeks with tears o'rflown, (Now kinder grown) What smiling shee'd not let me have, She weeping gave. Then you whom scornfull Beauties aw, Hope yet Relief; For Love, (who Tears from Smiles) can draw Pleasure from Grief. The Dilemma. As poor Strephon (whom hard Fate Slave to Chloris Eyes decreed) By his cruell fair one sate, Whilst his fat Flocks graz'd along: To the Musick of his Reed, This was the sad Shepheards Song. From those tempting Lips if I May not steal a Kiss (my Dear!) I shall longing pine and dye: And a Kiss if I obtain, My Heart fears (thine Eyes so near) By their lightning 'twill be slain. Thus I know not what to try: This I know yet, that I dye. Change defended. Leave Chloris, leave, prethee no more With want of Love, or Lightness charge Me: 'Cause thy Looks captiv'd me before, May not anothers now enlarge me? He, whose misguided Zeal hath long Pay'd Homage to some Stars pale light, Better enform'd, may without wrong Leave that, t'adore the Queen of Night. Then if my Heart, which long serv'd thee, Will to Carintha now encline; Why term'd inconstant should it be, For bowing 'fore a richer shrine? Censure that Lover's such, whose will Inferiour Objects can entice; VVho changes for the better still, Makes that a Vertue, you call Vice. The Microcosme. Man of himself's a little VVorld, but join'd VVith VVoman, VVoman for that end design'd, (Hear cruell fair One whilst I this rehearse!) He makes up then a compleat Universe. Man like this sublunary VVorld is, born The sport of two cross Planets, Love, and Scorn: VVoman the other VVorld resembles well, In whose Looks Heav'n is, in whose Breast is Hell. The Defeat. Gainst Celinda's Marble Brest All his Arrows having spent, And in vain each Arrow sent, Impotent, unarmed Love, In a shady Myrtle Grove Layd him down to rest. 'Soon as layd, asleep he fell: And a Snake, in (as he slept) To his empty Quiver crept. VVhen fair Chloris, whose soft Heart Love had wounded, (and its smart Lovers best can tell) This Advantage having spy'd; Of his Quiver, and his Bow Thought to rob her sleeping Foe: Softly going then about To have seiz'd upon them; out Strait the Snake did glide. With whose Hisses frighted, she, (Nimbly starting back again) Thus did to herself complain: Never cruell Archer! never (Full, or empty) does thy Quiver Want a sting for Me. Amore secreto. Content thy self fond Heart! nor more Let thy close Flames be seen: If thou with covert Zeal adore Thy Saint enshrin'd within, Thou hast thy Feast, as well as they That unto Love keep open Holy-day. In his Religion, all are free To serve him as they may. In publick some, and some there be Their vows in private pay. Love that does to all Humours bend, Admits of severall Waies unto one End. Yet wilt thou not repining cease! Still dost thou murmurs vent? Stubborn, Rebellious Zealot, peace! Nor sign of Discontent So much as in one sigh afford; For to the Wise in Love, each sigh's a Word. A Maid in Love with a Youth blind of one Eye. Though a Sable Cloud benight One of thy fair Twins of Light, Yet the other brighter seems, As 't had robb'd its Brother's Beams; Or both Lights to one were run, Of two Stars, now made one Sun. Cunning Archer! who knows yet But thou wink'st my Heart to hit! Cloze the other too, and All Thee the God of Love will call. The broken Faith. Lately by cleer Thames his side, Fair Lycoris I espy'd With the Pen of her white hand These words printing on the Sand: None Lycoris doth approve But Mirtillo for her Love. Ah false Nymph! those Words were fit In Sand only to be writ: For the quickly rising Streams Of Oblivion, and the Thames, In a little Moments stay From the Shore wash'd clean away What thy hand had there imprest, And Mirtillo from thy Brest. Complaint on the Death of Sylvia, to the River. Cleer Brook! which by thy self art chac'd, And from thy self dost fly as fast, Stay here a little; and in Brief Hear the sad Story of my Grief: Then, hasting to the Sea, declare Her Waves not half so bitter are. Tell her how Sylvia (she who late Was the sole Regent of my Fate) Hath yeelded up her sweetest Breath, In the best Time of Life, to Death: Who proud of such a Victory, At once triumphs o'r Love, and Me. But more (Alas!) I cannot speak; Sighs to my sadder Accents break. Farewell kind Floud! now take thy Way, And like my Thoughts, still restless, stray: If we retarded have thy Course, Hold! with these Tears thy speed inforce. A Shepheard inviting a Nymph to his Cottage. Deer! on yond' Mountain stands my humble Cot, 'Gainst Sun and Wind by spreading Oaks secur'd; And with a Fence of Quickset round immur'd, That of a Cabban, make't a shady Grot. My Garden's there: o'r which, the Spring hath spread A flowry Robe; where thou may'st gather Posies Of Gilliflowers, Pinks, Jelsomines, and Roses, Sweets for thy Bosome, Garlands for thy Head. Down from that Rocks side runs a purling Brook In whose unsullied Face (Though thine needs no new Grace,) Thou mayst, as thou think'st best, compose thy Look. And there thine own fair Object made, Try which (judg'd by the River) may be said The greater Fire, That which my Brest feels, or thy Eyes inspire. Sogno, a la sua donna Once unto my amorous flame, Dear, thou dreamd'st thou didst consent; But that dream of truth fell short, 'Cause it from the Ivory Port Of thy white bosom came. But if thou wouldst what that meant Now a real truth should prove, (Dearest Love) Thy old bedfellow forsake, And a new and better take; And thou'lt find 'twill then return By the other Gate of Horn. To Ligurinus. Horat. Carm. l. 4. Od. 10. Paraphrasticè. Cruel, and fair! when this soft down, (Thy Youths bloom,) shall to bristles grow; And these fair Curls thy shoulders crown, Shall shed, or cover'd be with snow: When those bright Roses that adorn Thy Cheeks shall wither quite away, And in thy Glass (now made Time's scorn) Thou shalt thy changed Face survey. Then, ah then (sighing) thou'lt deplore Thy Ill-spent Youth; and wish, in vain, Why had I not those thoughts before? Or come not my first Looks again? The Penitent Murderer. Theocrit. Idyl. 31 [30]. ??? ?????? ??????. VVhen Venus saw Adonis dead, His Tresses soyl'd, his Colour fled, She strait her winged Loves commands To bring the cruell Boar in Bands. They, the Woods nimbly ranging, found The pensive Beast, and brought him bound: This drags along the captiv'd foe, That pricks him forward with his Bow. With trembling steps the Boar drew nigh, For he fear'd angry Venus Eye. —T'whom thus she spake: O thou the Worst, Of all wild Beasts, and most accurst! Was't thou with wounding Tusks didst tear This whiter Thygh? thou kill my Dear? To whom the Boar reply'd, I swear By thy self Venus, by thy Dear, By these my Bonds, these Hunters, I Meant to thy Love no Injury: But gazing on him, as some fair Statue, unapt the flames to bear Desire had kindled in my Brest, To kiss his naked Thigh I prest; And kissing, kill'd him: wherefore these, These murd'ring Tusks, doom as you please. (For why alas! Teeth do I bear That useless and enamour'd are?) Or if a punishment too small You yet think that, take Lips and All. But Venus, pittying the Beast, Commands that strait he be releas'd; Who to the Woods ne'r went again, But liv'd as one of Venus Train: And coming one Day near a Fire, Quench'd there the flames of his Desire. The Shepheard. Theocrit. Idyl. 21 [20]. Fair Eunica I sweetly would have kist, But was with scorn, and this reproach dismist. Hence! what? a Shepheard, and yet hope from Me For such a Grace? We kiss no Clowns, saith she. My Lips I would not with a kiss so vile As thine, so much as in a Dream defile. Lord! how thou look'st? how like a Lubber sport'st? What fine discourse thou hast? how sweetly court'st? How soft thy Beard is? and how neat thy Hair? Thy Lips like sick mens blush, and thy hands are White as an Ethiops: fogh! thou stink'st, out, quick, Carrion! be gone; lest thy smell make me sick. Then in her Brest thrice spitting, me a skew (Mumbling t'her self) from Head to foot doth view. Such Pride in her self-flatter'd Beauty takes, Whilst in Derision Mouths at Me she makes. This scorn my bloud inflam'd, and red I grew With anger, like a Rose new bath'd in Dew. She went her way, and left me vext, to see I should by such a Huswife slighted be. Say Shepheards! am I not a handsome Lad? Or hath some God transform'd, and lately made M'another Man? for once I'd a good face: And that (as Ivy Trees) my Beard did grace; My Locks like Smallage 'bout my Temples twin'd; And my white Front 'bove my black Eye-brows shin'd. My Eyes more lovely than Minerva's were, Than Curds my Lips more soft, and sweeter far My Words than Honey: play too, would you knew't, I sweetly can, on Pipe, Shalm, Reed, and Flute. There's not a Country Lass but likes, as passes, And loves me too: all but your City Lasses; Who, 'cause a Shepheard, me without regard (Forsooth!) pass by, alas! they never heard How Bacchus on the Plains did Oxen tend, And Venus to a Shepheards Love did bend, And his fat Flocks on Phrygian Mountains kept, Or lov'd in Woods, and for Adonis wept. VVhat was Endymion but a Shepheard? whom The Moon affected, and from Heaven would come To lye whole Nights on Latmus with the Boy. A Shepheard (Rhea) too was once thy Joy: And oh, how many scapes Jove didst thou make From Juno's Bed for a young Shepheard's sake? But Eunica alone doth Swains despise, And 'bove those Goddesses her self doth prize. Venus no more thou with thy Love may'st keep In Town, or Hill; alone thou now must sleep. The Pastorall Wooing. Theocrit. Idyl. 28 [27]. Daphnis, and Shepheardess. Daphnis. Paris the Swain, away coy Helen bare: And I, a Swain, am kiss'd by one more fair. Shepheardess. Brag not rude Hind; Kisses are empty things. Daphnis. From empty Kisses yet sweet pleasure springs. Shepheardess. I'l wash my mouth, wipe off thy Kisses stain. Daphnis. Wip'st thou thy Lips? then let us kiss again. Shepheardess. Go kiss your Cows; you fit to kiss a Maid! Daphnis. Be not so proud: your youth will quickly fade. Shepheardess. Grapes though they're dry, yet still are Grapes we see, And Roses although wither'd, Roses be. Daphnis. Let's sit and talk beneath this Myrtles shade. Shepheardess. No; your smooth Tongue me once before betraid. Daphnis. Beneath these Elms then sit and hear me play. Shepheardess. Play to your self; I not your Musick weigh. Daphnis. Take heed lest thou the Wrath of Venus find! Shepheardess. Venus her worst; be but Diana kind. Daphnis. Oh say not so: lest her excited Rage Thee in unextricable Snares ingage. Shepheardess. Do what she can, find we Diana's Grace. Hold off your hands, or else I'l scratch your Face. Daphnis. Love, which no Maid e'r did, thou must not fly. Shepheardess. By Pan I will: why dost thou press so nigh? Daphnis. I fear he'l make thee stoop to thy first Love. Shepheardess. Though woo'd by many, none I did approve. Daphnis. Amongst those many, here, behold! I sue. Shepheardess. Why, my kind Friend, what would'st thou have me do? The married Life with troubles is repleat. Daphnis. No Cares, Joys only Marriage doth beget. Shepheardess. They say, Wives of their Husbands live in fear. Daphnis. Of whom do Women? rather domineer. Shepheardess. But thought of Child-bed Pains makes me afraid. Daphnis. Diana, whom thou serv'st, will be thy Aid. Shepheardess. But bearing Children will my Beauty wrong. Daphnis. In Children thou wilt see thy self still young. Shepheardess. What Dowry wilt thou give if I consent? Daphnis. My Flocks, my Groves, my Fields, be thou content. Shepheardess. Swear, that, when married, thou wilt ne'r forsake me. Daphnis. By Pan I will not, so thou please to take me. Shepheardess. Thou'lt give me Beds, and House, and Sheep to breed? Daphnis. Both House, and Beds, and the fair Flocks I feed. Shepheardess. What shall I to my aged Father say? Daphnis. He, when he hears my Name, will soon give way. Shepheardess. How art thou call'd? for Names do often please. Daphnis. Daphnis my Name, my Father's Lycidas, My Mother's Nomæa. Shepheardess. Of an honest Line Thou com'st, nor we of no more mean than thine. Daphnis. Yet not so great to make your Pride aspire, For, as I tak't, Menalcas is your Sire. Shepheardess. Shew me your Stalls, and Groves. Daphnis. Come let thine Eyes VVitness how high my Cypress Trees do rise. Shepheardess. Feed Goats whilst I survay the Shepheard's Bounds. Daphnis. Graze Bullocks whilst I shew the Nymph my Grounds. Shepheardess. VVhat do'st? why thrust'st thy hand into my Brest? Daphnis. Thus thy soft, swelling Bosome should be prest. Shepheardess. Help Pan! I faint; Swain, take thy hand away. Daphnis. Fear not sweet Nymph; nor tremble with dismay. Shepheardess. 'Twill spoyle my Coat should I i'th'durt be thrown. Daphnis. No: see! on this soft hide I'l lay thee down. Shepheardess. Ah Me! why hast thou loos'd my Virgin Zone? Daphnis. To Venus this will be an Oblation. Shepheardess. Heark! see! some body comes; I hear a Noise. Daphnis. The Cypress Trees are whispering of our Joyes. Shepheardess. Th'hast torn my Cloaths, and me quite naked layd. Daphnis. I'l give thee better. Shepheardess. VVords no deeds e'r paid. Daphnis. Would I could send my soul into thee now! Shepheardess. Oh Phœbe, pardon! I have broke my Vow. Daphnis. A Calf to Love, a Bull to Venus burn. Shepheardess. A Maid I came, a Woman shall return. Daphnis. And be a Mother-Nurse to pretty Boyes. Thus intertalk'd they 'mid'st the active Joyes Of close Embraces; when at length they rose, And being up, to feed her Flock she goes With blushing Face, but with a lightsome Heart, Whilst to his Heards he no less pleas'd doth part. On the Picture of Icarus in Wax. Marino. What once did unto thee impart The means of Death; by happy Art Now thee restores to life again: Yet still remember to refrain Ambitious Flights; nor soar too nigh The Sun of an inflaming Eye; For so thou may'st, scorcht by those Beams, In Ashes dye, as once in Streams. On a Marble Statue of Nero, which falling kill'd a Child. Marino. This Statue, bloudy Nero does present; To Tyrants a sad Document. Though Marble, on his basis yet so fast He stood not, but he fell at last. And seems as when he liv'd, as cruell still, He could not fall, but he must kill. On Paula. Mart. l. 9. Epig. 5 [6]. Fain shee'd have Priscus; and who blame her can? But hee'l not have her: and who'l blame the Man? On an Ill Husband and Wife. Mart. l. 8. Epigr. 34 [35]. Since both of you so like in Manners be, Thou the worst Husband, and the worst Wife she, I wonder, you no better should agree. On Candidus, a rich Miser. Mart. l. 3. Epig. 26. Alone thou dost enjoy a fair Estate, Alone rare Myrrhine Vessels, golded Plate; Alone rich Wines dost drink; and hast for None A Heart, nor Wit but for thy self alone. None shares with thee, it is deny'd by no man: But Candidus, thou hast a Wife that's Common. On Bassus a Pittifull Poet. Mart. l. 5. Epigr. 53. VVhy writ'st thou of Thyestes, Colchis hate, Andromache, or Niobes sad Fate? Deucalion (Bassus!) better far would fit, Or Phaeton, believe me, with thy Wit. On a Boy kill'd by the fall of an Icesicle. Mart. l. 4. Epig. 18. VVher streams from Vipsan Pipes Port Capen pow'rs And the Stones moystned are with constant show'rs A drop congeal'd to a sharp Icesicle On a Child's Throat that stood beneath it, fell, And when the Wretches Fate dissolv'd it had, Melted away in the warm VVound it made. VVhat may not cruell Fate? or where will not Death find us out, if VVater Throats can cut? On Nestor a whisperer. Mart. l. 3. Epig. 28. Thou wonder'st Marius Ears should smell so Ill: They may thank thee; thou whisper'st in 'em still. On Martinia, an old, old, leacherous— Mart. l. 3. Epigr. 32. VVhat? canst thou not with an old VVoman bed Thou criest?—yes: but thou art not old but dead. VVe could with Hecuba, or Niobe Make shift, but then (Martinia!) it must be Before the one Into a Bitch be turn'd, t'other to Stone. On Philomuse, a needy Newesmonger. Mart. l. 9. Epig. 35 [36]. To gain a Supper, thy shift (Philomuse!) Is to vent lies, instead of Truths, for News: Thou knowst what Pacorus intends to do, Can'st count the German Troops and Sarmats too. The Dacian General's Mandates dost profess To know, and Victories before the Express. How oft it rains in Ægypt, thou as well, And Number of the Lybian Fleet, canst tell. VVhom Victor in the next Quinquatrian Games Cæsar will crown, thy knowing Tongue proclames: Come, leave these shifts: thou this Night (Philomuse) Shalt sup with Me; but, not a word of News. On Aulus a Poet-Hater. Mart. l. 8. Epig. 63. Aulus Loves Thestius; him Alexis fires; Perhaps he too, our Hyacinth desires; Go now, and doubt if Poets he approves, When the Delights of Poets Aulus Loves! On Lentinus, being troubled with an Ague. Mart. l. 12. Epig. 17. Lentinus! thou dost nought but fume, and fret, To think thy Ague will not leave thee yet. Why? it goes with thee; bathes as thou dost do, Eats Mushromes, Oysters, Sweet-breads, wild Boar too, Oft drunk by thee with Falern Wine is made, Nor Cæcub drinks unless with snow allay'd: Tumbles in Roses dawb'd with unctuous sweets, Sleeps upon Down between pure Cambrick sheets, And when thus well it fares with thee, wouldst thou Have it to go unto poor Damma now? To Priscus. Mart. l. 8. Epigr. 11 [12]. VVhy a rich Wife (Priscus) I will not wed, Ask'st thou?—I would not have my Wife, my Head: Husbands should have superiority; So Man and Wife can only equall be. On Phœbus that wore leather Caps. Mart. l. [12]. Epig. [45]. VVhilst thou a Kidskin Cap putt'st on To hide the Baldness of thy Crown, On jested wittily, who sed, Phœbus, that thou hadst shod thy Head. On Horace a poor fellow. Mart. l. 4. Epigr. 2. Horace alone, 'mongst all the Company, In a black Gown the Plays did lately see. Whilst both the Commons, and the Knights of Rome, Senate, and Cæsar all in white did come; When strait it snow'd apace; so he the sight Beheld as well as all the rest, in white. On a Swallow torn in Peeces by her Fellowes. Mart. l. 5. Epig. 67. VVhen for their winter Homes the swallows made, One 'gainst the Custome in her old Nest staid. The rest at Spring return'd, the Crime perceive, And the offending Bird of Life bereave. Late yet she suffer'd, she deserv'd before, But then when she in Peeces Itys tore. To Apollo pursuing Daphne. Auson. Throw by thy Bow, nor let thy Shafts appear, She flies not thee, but does thy weapons fear. De Erotio Puella. Mart. l. 5. Epigr. 38 [37]. She, (who than down of aged Swans more fair, More soft was than Galæsian Lambkins are; More beautious than those Shels Lucrinus shews, Or Stones which Erythræan Waves disclose; Smooth as the Elephants new polish'd Tooth, VVhiter than Lillies in their Virgin Growth, Or Snow new fallen; the colour of whose Tresses Outvy'd the German Curles, or Bætick Fleeces; VVhose Breath the Pestan Rosaries excell'd, The hony in Hymættian Hives distill'd, Or chafed Ambers scent: with whom conferr'd The Phænix was but thought a common Bird) She, she, in this new Tomb yet warm, doth lye, VVhom the stern hand of cruell Destiny In her sixth year, e'r quite expir'd, snatch'd hence, And with her all my best Joyes: yet 'gainst all sense Pætus perswades me not to grieve for her; Fye, saies he, (whilst his hair he seems to tear) Art not asham'd to mourn thus for a Slave? I have a Wife laid newly in the Grave, Fair, rich, and noble, yet I live you see. O what than Pætus can more hardy be? No sorrow sure a heart like his can kill, H'hath gain'd ten thousand Pounds, yet he lives still. On Mancinus a Prating Braggart. Mart. l. 4. Epig. 61. Thou mad'st thy Brags that late to thee a Friend A hundred Crowns did for a Present send: But four days since (when with the Wits we met) Thou saidst Pompilla too (or I forget) Gave thee a rich Suite worth a thousand more, (Scarlet of Tyre with gold embroyder'd o'r:) And swor'st that Madam Bassa sent thee late Two Em'rald Rings, the Lady Cælia, Plate. And yesterday, when at the Play we were, At comming forth, thou told'st me in my Ear, There fell to thee that Morning, the best part Of Fourscore Pounds per Annum next thy Heart. What wrong have I thy poor Friend done thee, that Thou thus should torture me? Leave, leave this Chat For pitties sake; or if thou'lt not forbear, Tell me then something that I'd gladly hear. On Picens. Mart. l. 8. Epig. 62. Picens the Backside of his Book doth fill With tedious Epigrams; yet takes it ill Phœbus should shew himself his Back Friend still. On Caius, one of large Promises, but small Performances. Mart. l. 10. Epig. 16. If not to give, but say so, giving be, Caius! for giving we will vie with thee. What e'r the Spaniard in Gallician Feilds Digs up, what the gold Stream of Tagus yields, What the tann'd Indian dives for in the deep, Or in its Nest th'Arabian Bird doth keep, The wealth which Tyrian Caldrons boyl; receive All this, and more; but so as thou dost give. To Posthumus, an Ill Liver. Mart. l. 5. Epigr. 58. Still, still thou cry'st to morrow I'l live well: But when will this to morrow come? canst tell? How far is't hence? or where is't to be found? Or upon Parthian, or Armenian Ground? Priams, or Nestors years by this 't has got; I wonder for how much it might be bought? Thou'lt live to morrow?—'tis too late to day: Hee's wise who yesterday, I liv'd, can say. To Thelesinus. Mart. l. 3. Epigr. 40. Thou think'st th'hast shewn thy self a mighty friend, 'Cause at my Sute thou fifty Pounds didst lend: But if thou, rich, for lending, may'st be said So great a Friend: what I, who Poor, repaid? On Cinna a bold Suter. Mart. l. 3. Epigr. 60 [61]. Thou say'st 'tis nothing that thou ask'st me; Why, If thou ask'st nothing, nothing I deny. The happy life. To Julius Martialis. Mart. l. 10. Epig. 47. Those things which make life truly blest, Sweetest Martial hear exprest: Wealth left, and not from Labour growing; A gratefull soyl, a Hearth still glowing; No Strife, small Business, Peace of Mind, Quick Wit, a Body well inclin'd, Wise Innocence, Friends of one Heart, Cheap Food, a Table without Art; Nights which nor Cares, nor Surfets know, No dull, yet a chaste Bedfellow; Sleeps which the tedious Hours contract; Be what thou mayst be, nor exact Ought more; nor thy last Hour of Breath Fear, nor with wishes hasten Death. Epitaphium Glauciæ. Mart. l. 6. Epig. 28. Here Meliors Freed-man, known so well, Who by all Rome lamented, fell, His dearest Patrons short-liv'd Joy, Glaucias, beneath this Stone doth lye, Neer the Flaminian Way interr'd: Chast, modest, whom quick Wit preferr'd And happy Forme, who to twelve past, Scarce one year added; that, his last. If Passenger thou weep'st for such a Loss, Mayst thou ne'r mourn for any other Cross. To Sextus. Mart. l. 2. Epig. 3. You say y'ow nothing; and 'tis true you say; For he ows only, who hath means to pay. To Maximus. Mart. l. 7. Epig. 72 [73]. Th' Esquiliæ a House of thine doth show, Mount Aventine, and the Patrician Row. Hence Cybells Fane, thence Vesta's thou dost view; From this th'Old Jupiter, from that the New; Where shall I meet thee? in what Quarter, tell? He that does every where, does no where dwell. To Stella. Mart. l. 7. Epigr. 35 [36]. VVhen my poor Villa could not storms sustain, Nor watry Jove, but swam in Flouds of Rain, Thou sent'st me Tyles, wherewith to make a Fence 'Gainst the rude Tempests sudden violence. We thank thee Stella: but cold Winter's near, The Villa's coverd, not the Villager. On Parthenopæus. Mart. l. 11. Epig. 87 [86]. Thy Doctor, that he may asswage the Pain Of thy sore Throat, which a sharp Cough doth strain, Prescribes thee Hony, sweet-meats, luscious Pies, Or what e'r else stills fretfull Childrens cries: Yet leav'st thou not thy coughing: now we see 'Tis no sore Throat, but sweet Tooth troubles thee. On Philænus. Mart. l. 10. Epigr. 102. If how Philænus may be stil'd A Father, who ne'r got a Child Thou'd'st know; Davus can tell thee it, Who is a Poet and ne'r writ. The Choice of his Mistris. Mart. l. [11]. Epigr. [100]. I would not have a VVench with such a VVaste As might be well with a Thumb-Ring embrac'd; VVhose bony Hips, which out on both sides stick, Might serve for Graters, and whose lean Knees prick; One, which a saw does in her back-Bone bear, And in her Rump below carries a Spear. Nor would I have her yet of Bulk so grosse That weigh'd should break the Scales at th'market-cross; A meer unfathom'd lump of Grease; no, that Like they that will; 'tis Flesh I love, not Fat. To Sextus. Mart. l. 2. Epig. 55. Sextus thou will'st that I should show Thee Honour, where I love would ow; And I obey since 'tis thy will, By Mee thou shalt be honour'd still: But Sextus if thou'lt honour'd be, Thou shalt not then be lov'd by Me. On Baucis, an old drunken Crone. Antholog. Græc. Baucis the Bane of Pots, what time she lay Sick of a Feaver, thus to Jove did pray; If I escape this Fit, I vow to take These hundred Suns no drink but from the Lake: Wanting her wonted Cups, (now past all doubt Of Danger) she one day this shift found out, She takes a Sive, and through the bottome pries; So she at once a hundred Suns espies. On Captain Ansa, a bragging Run-away. Casimire. VVhilst timorous Ansa led his Martial Band 'Gainst the Invaders of his Native Land, Thus he bespake his Men before the Fight: Courage my Mates, let's dine, for we to Night Shall Sup (saies he) in Heaven: this having said, 'Soon as the threatning Ensigns were displaid, And the loud Drums and Trumpets had proclam'd Defiance 'twixt the Hoasts; he, (who ne'r sham'd At Loss of Honour) fairly ran away, When being ask'd, how chance he would not stay And go along with them to sup in Heaven? Pardon me Friends (said he) I fast this Even. To Fuscus. Mart. l. 1. Epig. 55. If Fuscus thou hast room for one Friend more, (For well I know thou every where hast store) Let me compleat the List; nor be thought e'r The worse 'cause New; such once thy old friends were: But try if he you for your New Friend take, May happily an old Companion make. On Marcus Anton: Primus his Picture. Mart. l. 10. Epig. 32. This Picture, which with Violets you see And Roses deckt, askst thou whose it may be? Such was Antonius in his Prime of Years, Who here still young, though he grow old, appears. Ah! could but Art have drawn his Mind in this, Not all the World could shew a fairer Peece. Horat. [Carm. l. 1. Od. 9.] Seest thou not, how Soractes Head, (For all it's Height) stands covered With a white Perriwigg of Snow? Whilst the labouring Woods below Are hardly able to sustain The Weight of Winters feather'd Rain; And the arrested Rivers stand Imprison'd in an Icy Band? Dispell the Cold; and to the Fire Add fuell, large as it's Desire; And from the Sabine Casque let fly (As free as Liberality) The Grapes rich blood, kept since the sun His Annuall Course foure times hath run. Leave to the Gods the rest, who have Allay'd the Winds, did fiercely rave In Battail on the Billowy main, Where they did blustring tug for Raign. So that no slender Cypress now, It's Spirelike Crown does tott'ring, bow: Nor aged Ashtrees, with the shock Of Blasts impetuous, doe rock. Seek not to morrow's Fate to know; But what day Fortune shall bestow, Put to a discreet Usurie. Nor (gentle youth!) so rigid be With froward scorn to disapprove The sweeter Blandishments of Love. Nor mirthfull Revels shun, whilst yet Hoary Austerity is set Far from thy greener years; the Field Or Cirque should now thy Pastime yield: Now nightly at the Howre select, And pointed Place, Loves Dialect, Soft whispers, should repeated be; And that kind Laughters Treacherie, By which some Virgin closely layd In dark Confinement, is betrayd: And now from some soft Arm, or Wrist, A silken Braid, or silver Twist, Or Ring from Finger, should be gain'd, By that too nicely not retain'd. Ad Puellam edentulam. Mart. l. 2. Epig. 41. Smile if th'art wise; smile still, fair Maid! Once the Pelignian Poet said; But not to all Maids spake he this, Or spake he to all Maids I wisse, Yet not to thee; for thou art None. Thy bare Gums show three Teeth alone, Scal'd o'r with black and yellow Rust: If then thy Glasse or Me thou'lt trust, Thou laughter shouldst no lesse abhorre, Than rough Winds crisped Spanius, or The neat-drest Priscus the rude Touch Of boisterous hands, and feare as much As Cælia does the Sun; or more Than painted Bassa does a showre. Looks thou shouldst wear more grave, and sad, Than Hectors Wife, or Mother had: Never at Comedies appear; All festive Jollities forbear; And what e'r else doth laughter cause, And the clos'd Lips asunder drawes. Thou Childlesse Mothers shouldst alone, Or Brothers haplesse Fates, bemoan: Or follow still some mournfull Hearse, And with sad Tragedies converse. Then rather doe as I advise, Weep (Galla) still, weep, if th'art wise. Epitaph on an old drunken Crone. Ex Antipatr. Sidon. This Tomb Maronis holds; o'r which, doth stand A Bowle, carv'd out of Flint, by Mentor's hand: The tipling Crone while living, death of friends Ne'r toucht, nor Husbands, nor dear Childrens Ends. This only troubles her, now dead; to think, The Monumentall Bowle should have no drink. On Bibinus, a notorious Drunkard. Scaliger. The Sot Loserus is drunk twice a day; Bibinus only once; now of these, say, Which may a man the greatest Drunkard call? Bibinus still; for hee's drunk once for All. On poor Codrus, who though blind, was yet in Love. Mart. l. 3. Epig. 15. None in all Rome, like Codrus trusts I find; How, and so poor! he loves, and yet is blind. FINIS</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ETHICA Ausonii Ludus septem Sapientum. The Prologue. The seven Wisemen, (that Name Times past apply'd To them, nor hath Posterity deny'd) Themselves this Day unto your view present. Why dost thou blush Gown'd Roman? discontent That such grave Men should on the Stage be brought! Is't shame to us! 'twas none to Athens thought: Whose Councell-Chamber was their Theater. True; here for Busines sev'rall Places are Assign'd, the Cirque for Meetings, Courts to take Enrollments, Forums in which Pleas to make: But in old Athens, and all Greece, was known No other Place for Busines, but this One, Which later Luxury in Rome did raise. The Ædile heretofore did build for Playes A Scaffold-stage, No work of Carved stone; So Gallius and Murena did, 'tis known: But after, when great Men not sparing Cost, Thought it the highest Glory they could boast, To build for Playes a Scene more eminent, The Theater grew to this vast Extent; Which Pompey, Balbus, Cæsar, did inlarge; Vying, which should exceed for State and Charge. But to what End all this? We came not here To tell you who first built the Theater Or Forum, or who rais'd this Gallery; But as the Prologue to a Comedy, In which act Heaven-lov'd Sages; who in Verse Their own Judicious Sentences reherse, Known to the Learned, and perhaps to you: But if your Mem'ries shall not well renue Things spoke so long since; the Comedian shall Who better than I knows them, tell you all. Enter Comedian. Athenian Solon, Fame sings, wrote at Delphis ????? ???????; whose sense, Know thy self, is. But this for Spartan Chilons many take. Whether this Chilons be, some question make, ????? ??? ? ?????? ????: Is't hard? Wee'l english't: Th'End of a long Life regard. But this (say some) to Crœsus Solon sung. From Lesbian Pittacus this Motto sprung, ???????? ??????; that's Know-Time: But He By ?????? here means Opportunitie. ?? ???????? ?????, Bias, did proceed From thee; that is, Most Men are Ill. Take heed You not mistake him; for by Ill Men here He means the Ignorant: the next you hear Is Periander's ?????? ?? ???; That is, Thought's All in All; a Thought-full Man! But Lyndian Cleobulus does protest ??????? ??????; Mean in All is best. Thales, ????? ??????? ?? ??? cries. Upon a Surety present Damage lies. But this, 'fore those who gain by it, to tell, May 'chance displease: Now Solon comes, farwell. Exit. Enter Solon. Loe! on the Roman Stage is Solon come, Clad in his Græcian Ornaments: To whom Fame gave the prize of Wisdome from the rest; But Fame is not of Censure the strict Test. Nor first nor last I take my self to be, For there's no Order in Equalitie. Well did the Delphick Prophet sport with him Who ask'd, which first of the VVise-men might seem, Saying; if on a Globe their Names he writ, None first, or lowest he should find in it. From midd'st of that learn'd Round come I; that so, VVhat once I spake to Crœsus, All here now Might take as spoken to themselves; 'Tis this: ???? ????? ?????? ????; which is In English, Mark of a long life the End; 'Till then your Censure of All Men suspend: Nor Miserable These, nor happy Those Esteem; for None are such till their last Close. The Ground of this wee'l in few Words display. Crœsus, the Tyrant King of Lydia, Happy, and rich even to Excesse! (who wall'd The Temples of his Gods with pure Gold) call'd Me from my Country to him: We obey His Royall Summons, went to Lydia, Willing his Subjects by our means might find Their King improv'd, and better'd in his Mind. He asks Me whom I thought the happiest Man? I said Telana the Athenian, Who his life nobly for his Country gave; He pishes at it, will another have. I told him then Aglaus who the Bounds Ne'r past in all his life of his own grounds; Smiling, he sayes, what think you then of Me? Esteem'd the happyest in the whole World? We Reply'd, his End could only make that known. He takes this Ill: I, willing to be gon, Kisse his hand, and so leave him: For some Ends Meantime, 'gainst Persia he a War intends; And all Things ready, does in Person goe. How speeds? hee's vanquish'd, Prisoner to his foe, And ready now to yeeld his latest Breath, (For by the Victor he was doom'd to death) Upon the Funerall Pile rounded with Flames And smoak, he thus with a loud voice exclames. O Solon! Solon! now I plainly see Th'art a true Prophet! thrice thus naming Me. Mov'd with which words, Cyrus, (the Conquerour) Commands the Fire be quencht, which, by a showre Of Rain then falling, happily was layd. Thence to the King by a choice Guard convay'd, And question'd who that Solon was? and why He call'd so on his Name? He, for Reply, In Order all declares: Pitty at this The Heart of Cyrus moves; and Crœsus is Receiv'd to grace, who in a Princely Port Liv'd after, honour'd in the Persian Court. Both Kings approv'd, and prais'd Me; but what I Said then to one, let each Man here apply As spoke t'himself; 'twas for that end I came. Farewell: your liking let your hands proclame. Exit Solon. Enter Chilon. My Hips with sitting, Eyes with seeing ake, Expecting when Solon an End would make. How little, and how long you Atticks prate! Scarce in three hundred Lines one word of Weight, Or a grave Sentence! how he lookt on me At going off?—Now Spartan Chilon see! Who with Laconian Brevity commends To you the Knowledge of your selves, kind Frends! ????? ???????, carv'd in Delphos Fane. 'Tis a hard Work, but recompenc'd with Gain. Try your own strength; examine what 'tis you Have done already, what you ought to doe. All Duties of our Life, as Modestie, Honour, and Constancie, included be In this; and Glory th'Idoll of these dayes. I've said: Farewell: I stay not for your Praise. Exit. Enter Cleobulus. I Cleobulus, though my Native Seat Be a small Isle, am Author of a great And glorious Sentence; ?????? ???????; A Mean is best: You Sirs that sit upon The fourteen middle Benches next unto Th'Orchestra, best may judge if this be true. Your Nodd shows your Assent: We thank you; but We shall proceed in Order: Was it not Your Afer (though a Man he of late Time is) That said once in this Place, Ut ne quid Nimis? And hither does our ????? ???? aime. The Dorick and the Latine mean the same. In speaking, being silent, or in sleep, In good Turns, or in bad, a mean still keep. In study, Labour, or what else so e'r. I've said: and that a Mean I keep, end here. Exit. Enter Thales. I'm Thales, who maintain (as Pindar sings) VVater to be the originall of Things, And on the Stage (as those before) am come T'assert the Truth of my own Axiom. Perhaps by some 't may be offensive thought: But not by those by sad experience taught. ????? ??????? ?? ???, say we, Be Surety, and be sure a loser be. A thousand Instances I could produce To prove Repentance is the only use That can be made of it, but that We here Examples by their Names to cite, forbear. Make your own Application, and conceive The Damage, Men by this sole Act receive. Nor this our good Intention take amiss. You that like, clap, you that dislike it, hiss. Exit. Enter Bias. I am Priænean Bias, who once taught ?? ???????? ?????, That most men are naught. I wish 't had been unspoke; for Truth gains Hate. But by bad Men, I meant Illitterate, And those who barbarously all Laws confound, Religion, Justice; for within this Round I see none but are good: believe all those Whom I proclame for bad amongst your Foes: Yet there is none so partially apply'd To favour Vice but with the good will side: VVhether he truly be such, or would fain Of a good man the Reputation gain: The hated name of an ill Man, there's none But flies: if y'are all good, your praise: I'm gone. Exit. Enter Pittacus. I'm Pittacus, who once this Maxime penn'd, ???????? ?????? That's Time apprehend. But by Time we meant Time in Season, as, In tempore veni is your Roman Phrase. And your own Comick Poet Terence, he, Chief of all things makes opportunity, Where Dromo comes unto Antiphila I'th'nick of Time: consider what I say. And mark how many Inconvenience Sustain, for want of this sole Providence! But now 'tis more than Time we should be gone; Farewell: and give your Approbation. Exit. Enter Periander. Now on the Stage see Periander move! He who once said, and what he said will prove ?????? ?? ???. Thought is all in all. Since him a perfect Agent we may call Who first considers what he undergoes; For we should still forecast, as Terence shows, Th'Event of Business, whether good, or bad, E'r w'undertake it: where may best be had Conveniency for Planting, where to build, When to wage War, and where to pitch a Field: Nor unconsiderately take in hand Or great or small Things; for that makes a stand In the free Progress of all new designs; In which, there's nothing Policy injoyns Like Consultation; hence it is that they Who use it not, Chance does, not Counsell, sway. But I retire; whilst you with better Fate Imploy your Thoughts how to uphold your State. The Sentences of those seven Sages, comprehended in as many Septenaries. Bias Prieneus. What's Man's chief good? a Mind that right doth know. What's his chief Ill? Man, his own greatest Foe. Who's rich? he who's contented. Who poor? He Who covets. A Wives best Dowr? Chastity. What VVoman's chaste? whom Fame dares not belie. VVho's the VVise man? who can, but doth no Ill. The Fool? He who cannot, yet hath the VVill. Pittacus Mitylenæus. None knows to speak, who knows not to refrain. 'Fore many bad, one good Man's Praise retain. He's mad who envies others happiness. So's he who joys in other Mens distress. The Laws thou dost impose, thy self obey. VVhen Times are prosperous store of Friends provide: VVhen they are bad, but in a few confide. Cleobulus Lindius. The more thou canst, 'less wish to do. The spite Of Fortune oft doth on the guiltless light. None long is happy in Impiety. In others much, nought in thy self pass by. The good Man's Friend is still the bad Man's Foe. Our Fathers' merits want of their due Fame. And oft our Childrens Portion is but shame. Periander Corinthius. Decent and Profitable ne'r dissent. The happier Man's still the more Provident. 'Tis ill to wish, 'tis worse to fear Death, we Should make a Virtue of Necessity. He who is fear'd by many, many feares. VVhen Fortune's kind, dread thy advanced height: And scorn to sink yet when she shows her spight. Solon Atheniensis. Life then is happy, when 'tis consummate. VVed with thy like; Disparity breeds hate. Confer not Honours casually. A friend Convince in private, publikely commend. 'Tis more to be, than be made Noble far. If Fates decrees are sure, in vain We fly them; If they are not, in vain We fear to try them. Chilo Lacedæmonius. Feard by Inferiors, nor by betters scorn'd Let me not live. Oft of thy Death be warn'd, And Health: Misfortunes, by thy own, defeat, Or friends Advice. The good thou dost, forget, But that which thou receiv'st, remember still. Age that resembles Youth doth gratefull come. Youth that resembles Age is burdensome. Thales Milesius. About to sin, thy self, though none else, fear. Life dies: the glory of a good Death, ne'r. What thou intend'st to do, forbear to tell. To fear what thou canst not o'rcome's a Hell. A just Reproof does good though from a Foe: But a false Praise does harm, though from a Friend. Nil nimium satis est bids us here end. Amphion, or a City well ordered. Casimer. Forraign Customes from your Land, Thebans by fair Laws command: And your good old Rites make known Unto your own. Piety your Temples grace; Justice in your Courts have Place: Truth, Peace, Love, in every Street Each other meet. Banish Vice, Walls guard not Crimes. Vengeance o'r tall Bulwarks climbs: O'r each Sin, A Nemesis Still waking is. Truth resembling craft, Profane Thirst of Empire, and of Gain, Luxury, and idle ease, Banish all these. Private Parsimony fill The Publike Purse: Arms only Steel Know, and no more: Valour fights cold In plunder'd Gold. VVar, or Peace do you approve, VVith united Forces move: Courts which many Collumes rear Their falls less fear. Safer Course those Pilots run VVho observe more Stars than One. Ships with double Anchors ty'd Securer ride. Strength united firm doth stand Knit in an eternall Band: But proud Subjects private hate Ruins a State. This as good Amphion sings To his Harps well-tuned strings, It's swift Streams clear Dirce stopt, Cytheron hopt, Stones did leap about the Plains, Rocks did skip to hear his Strains, And the Groves the Hills did crown Came dancing down. VVhen he ceas'd, the Rocks and VVood Like a VVall about him stood; VVhence fair Thebes, which seven Gates close Of Brass, arose. Vertue improv'd by suffering. 'Tis but the Body that blind Fortunes spight Can chain to Earth; the nobler Soul doth slight Her servill Bonds, and takes to Heaven her flight. So through dark clouds Heaven lightens (whilst the shade Is as a foyl to its bright splendour made) And Stars with greater Lustre Night invade. So sparkle Flints when strook; so Metals find Hardness from hammering, and the closer bind: So Flames increase the more supprest by VVind. And as the Grindstone to unpolish'd Steel Gives Edge, and Lustre: so my Mind, I feel VVhetted, and glaz'd by Fortunes turning VVheel. To Mr Stanley, on his unimitable Poems. The Stagirite, who Poesie defines An Imitation, had he read thy Lines, And thy rich Fancy known, he would have then Recall'd the learned Error of his Pen, And have confest, in his convicted State, Nought those could equall, this would imitate; VVhich from no forraign Supplement doth spring, Nor any Stand, but its own Height, take VVing. And but that We should seem so to misprise The influence of Chariessa's Eyes, VVe should not think Love did these Flames inspire, Rather, that thou taught'st Love this noble Fire: And, by a generous VVay thy hopes t'improve, Shew'dst her before thou didst, how thou could'st love; And the old, common Method didst invert, First made her Mistris of thy Brain, then Heart, Some Phant'sies growth may from their Subjects take, Thine doth not Subjects find, but subjects make; VVhose numerous strains we vainly strive to praise 'Less We could ours, high as thy Phant'sie, raise. Large Praise we might give some, with small Expence Of Wit, cry Excellent! how praise Excellence? The Painters Fate is ours, his hand may grace, Or take a bad, scarce hit a beauteous Face. Nor can our Art a fitting value sit Upon thy noble Courtesie of Wit; Which to so many Toungs doth lend that store Of pleasing sweetness which they lack'd before. Th'Iberian, Roman, and the fluent Greek; The nimble French, and the smooth Thuscan, seek For severall Graces from thy Pen alone, Which that affoords to all these Toungs, in One. Whose forraign Wealth transferr'd, improv'd by thine, Doth with a fair Increase of Lustre shine Like Gems new set upon some richer Foyle, Or Roses planted in a better Soyle. If 'bove all Lawrels then thy Merits rise, What can this Sprig (which while 'tis offer'd, dies) Add to the Wreath that does adorn thy Brows? No Bayes will suit with that but thy own Bowghs. On his Translation of Oronta. Flames rescu'd fair Oronta from the Pow'r Of an insulting Thracian Conquerour. The Fame of which brave Action, Preti's Rime Freed from the greater Tyranny of Time: Yet in that Freedome she less glories, then In beeing thus made Captive by thy Pen. To M? James Shirley, on his Way of Grammer explained in English Verse. Grammer, which taught the Poet first to write, Is by the Poet now taught to delight; And Poesy, which once unto the School Ow'd it's Instructions, now, to that's a Rule. Thy gratefull Pen, to Science does impart Civility, and requites Art, with Art. Yet not like some, who think they hardly shou'd Be thought to understand, if understood, Do'st thou the Minds of weaker Tiro's vex, Or, as perplex'd with th'Art, the Art perplex; But what e're seem'd therein obscure, mak'st clear, Brief, what prolix, smooth what did rough appear; That so the Art to Learners now is seen As in a Flat, which Hill, and Wood did skreen. How should they erre their Journey's end in view, Their Way so pleasing, and their Guide so true! Rest then secure of Fame; nor think thy Worth Can by a private Hand be well set forth. Attempts, which to the Publick Profit raise, Expect, nor merit lesse than Publick Praise.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SACRA To the Eternall WISEDOME: Vpon the Distraction of the Times. O thou Eternall Mind! whose VVisedome sees, And rules our Changes by unchang'd Decrees, As with Delight on thy grave Works We look, Say; art thou too with our light Follies took? For when thy bounteous Hand, in liberall Showres Each where diffus'd, thy various Blessings powres; VVe catch at them with strife as vain to sight, As Children, when for Nuts they scrambling, fight. This snatching at a Scepter breaks it; He, That broken does e're he can graspe it, see. The poor World seeming like a Ball, that lights Betwixt the hands of Pow'rfull Opposites: VVhich while they cantonize in their bold Pride, They but an Immaterial Point divide. O whilst for VVealthy Spoyles these fight, let Me, Though poor, enjoy a happy Peace with Thee. Draw Me, and I will follow Thee. Through devious Paths without thee, Lord! I run, And soon, without Thee, will my Race be done. Happy was Magdalen, who like a Bride, Her self to Thee by her fair Tresses ty'd. So she thy Presence never did decline, Thou her dear Captive wert, and she was Thine. Behold another Magdalen in Me! Then stay with Me, or draw me after Thee. If a Man should give all the substance of his House for Love, he would value it as nothing Cant. 8. Love I'd of Heaven have bought; when He, (this who VVould think?) both Purchase was, and Seller too. I offer'd Gold; but Gold he did not prize. I offer'd Gems; but Gems he did despise. I offer'd All; All he refus'd yet: why, If All wo'nt take, take what is left, said I. At this he smil'd, and said; in vain divine Love's Price thou beat'st; give nothing and shee's thine. And they laid him in a Manger. Happy Cribb! that wert alone To my God, Bed, Cradle, Throne, VVhilst thy glorious vilenesse, I View with divine Phant'sies Eye; Sordid filth seems all the Cost, State, and Splendour, Crowns doe boast. See! Heaven's sacred Majesty Humbled beneath Poverty. Swadled up in homely Rags, On a Bed of Straw and Flags. He whose Hands the Heavens displayd, And the VVorlds Foundations layd, From the VVorld's almost exil'd, Of all Ornaments despoyl'd. Perfumes bath him not, new born, Persian Mantles not adorn: Nor do the rich Roofs look bright VVith the Jaspers Orient Light. VVhere O Royall Infant! be Th'Ensigns of thy Majestie? Thy Sires equallizing State, And thy Scepter that rules Fate? VVhere's thy Angell-guarded Throne, VVhence thy Laws thou didst make known? Laws which Heaven, Earth, Hell obay'd; These, ah these, aside he layd; VVould the Emblem be, of Pride By Humility outvy'd. On the Innocents slain by Herod. Go blessed Innocents! and freely powre Your Souls forth in a Purple showre. And for that little Earth each shall lay down Purchase a Heavenly Crown. Nor of Originall Pollution feare The Stains should to your blouds adhere; For yours now shed, e're long shall in a Floud Be wash'd of better Bloud. Christo Smarrito. Sighing, her sad Heart fraught with Fears, Whilst from her Eyes gush streams of Tears, Seeking again how to retrive Her little wandring Fugitive, Each where with weary Steps doth rove, The Virgin Mother of lost Love. Like a sad Turtle, up and down She mourning runs through all the Town: With searching Eyes she pries about In every Creek; within, without. Sticks at each Place, looks o're and ore; Searches, where she had search'd before: Old Joseph following with sad Face, A heavy Heart, and halting Pace. Thrice had the Day been born i'th'East, As oft been buried in the West, Since the Dear Comfort of her Eyes She miss't; yet still her Search she plyes. Each where she seeks with anxious Care To find him out, yet knows not where. When the third Morn she saw arose, And yet no Beam of Hope disclose; Looking to Heaven, in these sad Words She vent to her full Grief affords. O my dear God! Son of my Wombe! My Joy, my Love, my Life, for whom These Tears I shed, on thee I call, But oh! thou answer'st not at all. For thee I search, but cannot find thee: Say (Dear!) what new Embraces bind thee? What Heart, enamour'd on thy Eyes, Enjoyes what Heaven to Me denies? Daughters of Sion! you which stray With nimble feet upon the Way, I beg of you, (if you can tell,) To shew me where my Love doth dwell: Whose Beauty with Celestiall Rayes, The Light of Paradise displayes. Perhaps to you he is unknown; Ah! if you wish to hear him shown, I'l tell y'him: Snow her whiteness, seeks, Vermilion, Blushes, from his Cheeks: His Eye a light more chaste discloses Then amorous Doves, his Lips then Roses. Amber, and Gold shine in his Hair (If Gold, or Amber may compare With that,) a Beauty so Divine, No Tongue, Pen, Fant'sie can design. Why break'st thou not (my Soul) this Chain Of Flesh? why lett'st thou that restrain Thy nimble Flight into his Arms, VVhose only Look with gladness charms? But (alas!) in vain I speak to thee Poor Soul! already fled from Me; To seek out him in whose lov'd Brest, Thy Life, as mine in thee, doth rest. Blest Virgin! who in Tears half drown'd, Griev'st that thy Son cannot be found. The time will come when Men shall hear thee Complain that he is too too near thee. When in the midd'st of hostile Bands With pierced Feet, and nailed Hands Advanc'd upon a cursed Tree His naked Body thou shalt see As void of Coverture, as Friends, But what kind Heaven in pitty lends, Thy Soul will then abhor the Light, And think no Grief worse than his Sight. But loe, as thus she search'd, and wept, By chance she to the Temple stept, Where her dear Son with joyfull Eyes Set 'mongst the Rabbins she espies. And as the Light of some kind Star To a distressed Marriner, So his dear sight to her appears, Tost in this Tempest of her Fears. But O what tongue can now impart The joy of her revived Heart? The Welcome, spoke in mutuall Blisses Of sweet Embraces, sweeter Kisses! Muse, since too high for thy weak Wing It is, contemplate what thou canst not sing. Christus Mathæum &amp; discipulos alloquitur. Leave, leave converted Publican! lay down That sinfull Trash; which in thy happier Race To gain a Heavenly Crown Clogs thy free Pace. O what for this pale durt will not Man do! Nay even now, 'mongst you (For this) there's One I see, Seeks to sell Me. But Times will come hereafter, when for Gold, I shall by more (alas) than One, be sold. Conscience. Internall Cerberus! whose griping fangs That gnaw the Soul are the Minds secret Pangs: Thou greedy Vulture! that dost gorging Tire On Hearts corrupted by impure desire. Subtle, and buzzing Hornet! that dost ring A Peal of Horrour, e'r thou giv'st the sting. The Souls rough File that smoothness does impart! The Hammer that does break a stony Heart! The Worm that never dies! the Thorn within, That pricks, and pains: the whip, and scourge of sin! The voice of God in Man! which, without rest Doth softly cry within a troubled Breast; To all Temptations is that Soul left free, That makes not to it self a Curb of Me. And she washed his Feet with her Teares, and wiped them with the Hairs of her Head. The proud Ægyptian Queen, her Roman Guest, (T'express her Love in Hight of State, and Pleasure) With Pearl dissolv'd in Gold, did feast, Both Food, and Treasure. And now (dear Lord!) thy Lover, on the fair And silver Tables of thy Feet, behold! Pearl in her Tears, and in her Hair, Offers thee Gold. Good Fryday. This Day eternall Love, for me Fast nail'd unto a cursed Tree; Rending his fleshly Veyl, did through his side A way to Paradise provide. This Day Life dy'd; and dying, overthrew Death, Sin, and Satan too: O happy day! May sinners say: But Day can it be said to be, Wherein We see The bright Sun of celestiall Light O'rshadow'd with so black a Night? Mary Magdalen weeping under the Cross. I Thirst, my dear, and dying Saviour cryes: These Hills are dry: O drink then from my Eyes. On the Receiving of the blessed Sacrament. Then Nourishment our Naturall Food imparts, When that into our Flesh, and Blood converts: But at this heavenly Banquet, I Then find of strength a spirituall supply, When (as by Faith the sacred Food I eat) My Soul converts into the Meat. The Message. Dear Saviour! that my Love I might make known To thee, I sent more Messengers than one. My heart went first, but came not back; My Will I sent thee next, and that staid with thee still. Then, that the better thou might'st know my Mind, I sent my Int'lect; that too staies behind. Now my Soul's sent: Lord! if that stay with thee, O what a happy Carkass shall I be! The Fountain. Stranger, who e'r thou art, that stoop'st to taste These sweeter streams, let me arrest thy haste; Nor of their fall The Murmurs, (though the Lyre Less sweet be) stand t'admire: But as you shall See from this Marble Tun The liquid Christall run; And mark withall, How fixt the one abides, How fast the other glides; Instructed thus the Difference learn to see, 'Twixt Mortall Life, and Immortality. FINIS</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PRINTED POEMS from Books by Various Authors To his Ingenious friend Mr. Charles Aleyn, on this his learned Poem. ? Sume Superbiam, Quaesitam meritis ? Thinke not that these my weaker lines can raise Or to thy name or to thy work a praise. Yet give me leave to write, and let these be The Testimonialls of my love to thee. They're no true Leigemen, whosoe're disclaime Tribute of Prayse unto thy Henries name. Who now by thee instated lives, more high Than in the joyes of former Royalty; And from thy hand receives a better Crowne Than was his Kingdomes Transitory one. By thee he conquers Death and Time, thy words Yeeld him his honour, more than could his swords, And gaine a Nobler victory than he Obtained o're usurping Tyrannie. Great Henry, whom wise heaven did ordaine, To blesse this Realme with thy most happy reigne. No more, dull Chronicle thy worth shall hold Or sullen prose thy Noble acts infold. Behold! the shrine wherein thy reverend story Shall ever be preserved, and thy glory, Fresh to all Ages; then 'tis just we give Praise to his name, 'has made thine truely live. Ed. Sherburne To his loving brother M. John Sherburn on his Translation of OVIDS Heroicall Epistles. Wert thou like those whose works and selves; depend For praise, on the fond largesse of some friend; My verse might here a welcome room obtaine: Which now perhaps, will name of flattery gaine. Tis hard to write when praises may offend; And such my fate were, should I here commend. I am too neare. Yet know thy paines shall live; What I cannot, others thy worke will give: Thy worke which shall to after-times endure 'Gainst Sciolists, and Zoilists secure. Ed. Sherburne. To the unfading Memory of the Lord Horatio Veere deceased. If you would be resolv'd whose Dust lies here Know 'tis the remnant of that Noble Veere Whose tall Atchivements fill so large a room, As Europe is too narrow for their Tombe, And He can never perish in His Name Whilst there is such a thing abroad as Fame. Iust Belgia had cause enough to boast, That He alone was her confiding Hoast; Who singly when the Army was away Suppli'd the place of the Militiæ. And had unto her Seventeen Provinces E're this, united the Antipodes; And future times will deem that Land to lie Entrench'd in teares that fell when He did dye, And it will be Impiety to make It firme, but rather drown it for His sake, For the Low-Countries by His Deeds shall be Preferr'd in Story to High-Germany. But Thou hast so out-fought Thy selfe that time, Will thinke such Actions could be none of Thine, And whil'st Thou did'st Thy Vertue so advance, 'Twas not a Truth but a well fainde Romance, And I, preserving of Thy Honour, feare Thou wilt be thought no Lord having no Peere. E. S. The Graces, or Hieron Theocriti Idyll. 16. Translated by Sir Edward Sherborn, above forty years ago. The Muses, and the Muse-inspired Crew, This always, as their best-lov'd Theam, pursue The Honour of immortal Gods to raise, And crown the Actions of Good Men with Praise. For Deities the Muses are, and use (As such) to give to Deities their Dues. We Poets are but Mortals, sing we then The Deeds of god-like, tho but mortal men. None kindly yet our Graces entertain, But send them unrewarded back again. This made the Girls, when bare-foot they came home, Chide me, for idly sending them to roam On sleeveless Errands: wearied here to stay, They sigh their melancholy Souls away. They loath their sordid Lodging, fume and fret 'Cause for their Labours they can nothing get. For where's the generous Mortal now a-days That loves to hear a Poet's well-tun'd Lays? To find one such I know not; some, 'tis true, Love to be prais'd; none a good Deed will do. They value not their Honours, as of old But are meer Slaves to Avarice and Gold. Just or unjust, all Practices they try For heaps of Treasure, but will rather dye Than part with the bare Scrapings of its Rust, To satisfie a needy Poet's Gust. If any chance a Boon of them to beg, They cry, My Knee is nearer than my Leg. Of what is mine, my self alone shall share, For their own Poets let the Gods take care. Who to another's Pray'r now lends an Ear? Not one. This truth Homer to all makes clear; The best of Poets! tho the best he be, He gets not yet one single Cross from me. Mad men! what's Wealth, if still the hoarded Gold From others under Lock and Key you hold? None wise thinks this is the true use of it, Some part for proper Interest we should fit, And some apply to the Support of Wit: Some to our near Allies we should allow, To Strangers some, some to the Gods should vow, Set some for Hospitality a-part, To treat our Friends with open hand and heart: But chiefly to maintain the Muses Quire; That when to the old Grave thou shalt retire, Thou may'st among the living gain Renown; Nor mourn inglorious near sad Acheron, As some poor Ditcher with hard brawny hand, That cannot heavy Poverty withstand. The great Antiochus in plenteous measure Supply'd his Subjects Wants from his own Treasure, So King Alevas; many fat Droves went Into his Stalls, and from his Stalls were sent. Infinite Flocks large Pastures did afford To furnish Crion's hospitable Board. No Pleasure yet from all this Princely store Could they receive, were their Souls wafted o're In Charon's Boat to the dark Stygian Shore. But in obscure Oblivion they would lye, Depriv'd of all their Superfluity, 'Mongst wretched Souls whom no Time can, nor Age From their sad Miseries e'er disengage, If the great Ceian Poet had not been, And with his Praises made them live again. Ev'n the swift Coursers at th'Olympick Game Are registred in the Records of Fame. Who of the Lycian Princes e're had heard? Of Cyrnus with his flaxen Hair and Beard, Or Priam's Sons? forgot they had been long, Their Wars their Battels, had not Poets sung. Ulisses, who full six score Months was tost, And Time and Wealth 'mongst several Nations lost; Who went to Hell alive, and by a slight From the fierce Cyclops Cave, made his safe flight, Had never been remembred but for us, Nor poor Eumæus or Philætius His Shepheard, and his Herdsman. Who had known That to great-Sould Laertes he was Son? Had not the Ionian Bard his Acts and Name Inroll'd in the eternal Book of Fame. Glory on men is by the Muses spread, The living waste the Treasure of the dead: But easier 'tis for me to reckon o're The Waves which the Wind drives against the Shore, Or wash a Blackmoor white, then e're perswade To good, a Slave to Avarice once made. Then farewel such vile Scoundrels! let them lye Obscur'd in base Illiberality: Doating upon their vast, and ill-got store, Still vex'd with restless care of getting more. A good man's Love to me's a greater Grace Than many Mules or Horses for the Race. Yet willingly a man I'd seek, would make Me, and the Muses welcome for my sake: But those sweet Singers, without Jove's Advice, Will find the way too difficult and nice. Yet has not Heaven left off to turn its Sphears, Or ceas'd to measure time by Months and Years; And happily there will a Man arise May need our Verse, nor will our Songs despise; One, that in Actions greater may engage Than Ajax did, or stout Achilles wage In Simois Fields; within whose Plains extent Of Phrygian Ilus stands the Monument. And now a Punick Race, near the Sun's set From Libia's Confines Wars dire horrors threat. Now Syracusians their short Javelins try, And Wicker Targets to their Arms apply. And 'mongst them, Hieron, equal to the best Of ancient Hero's, stands in Armour drest, A Horsemane shadowing o're his glittering Crest. Oh mighty Jove! Father of Gods! Heav'ns King! And thou who from his midwiv'd Brain did'st spring Honour'd Minerva! and thou Proserpine! With Mother Ceres! under whose divine Protection still the mighty City stands, First rais'd by wealthy Ephyrean hands, Near Lysimelia's Lake, dread Pow'rs! expell Sicilia's Foes: That they return'd may tell Their Wives and Children how their slain friends fell; And let the Towns by hostile Arms destroy'd, By former Dwellers now be re-enjoy'd; That they may dress their fertile Fields and breed Numberless bleating Flocks therein to feed. Let their horn'd Heards, call'd home at night from grass, Urge lazy Travellers to mend their pace. Let now the fallowed Fields be sown again, And freshly flourish with fair Crops of Grain, Whilst labouring Mowers the rich Meadows share, Shrubs ecchoing with the shrill-voic'd Gras-hopper. Let ev'n the Name of War in all Mouths cease, Be no Arts cherish'd but the Arts of Peace: Let Spiders rusty Arms in Cobwebs dress, Let Poets Hieron's glorious Acts rehearse, And spread his Fame throughout the Universe; 'Mongst whom I'll sing for one; tho I not reach So high as some whom Jove's fair Daughters teach; Who love Sicilian Arethusa's Name To chant, and Hieron's valiant Acts proclaim. On the publication of the Posthume Poems of M. William Cartwright, sometime Student of Christ-Church in Oxon. How subject to new Tumults is this Age! With War lesse vex'd now, than Poetick Rage! Were not State-Levellers enough! that yet We must be plagu'd with Levellers of Wit? Delvers in Poetry? that only skill To make Parnassus a St George's Hill? The Cyrrhan Grove's almost disforrested To furnish Wreaths for each bold Rimers Head; The Muses fear a Rape, or a Surprize, So Phæbus might, but He their Fury flies. What Pow'r may we invoke then, to withstand This growing Plague? behold! a courteous Hand, A kind, and timely Succour doth dispence: CARTVVRIGHT comes forth; blush Sons of Impudence, And Little Wit! CARTVVRIGHT; the Muses Fame, Just Envy of best Poets, but your Shame. EDVV: SHERBURNE Esq. On Ælian his Various History, Translated into English by M? Thomas Stanley, the hopeful and onely Son of my dearest Friend Thomas Stanley of Cumberlow, Esquire. ÆLIAN, as if affecting to be known To others in a Language not his own, This Curious Piece thought fit at first t'express, Though native Roman, in a Grecian dress. You, kind to him and us, what lay conceal'd In a learn'd Tongue, have in our own reveal'd; And taught our generous Youth by this Essay, T'improve those hours they vainly cast away. Your blooming years forth early Vertues shoot, And ere we Leaves expected, shew us Fruit; Such, and so various, as must needs invite The dull, and please the curious appetite. Not to know what was done ere we were born, Is to live Children still; the too-just scorn Of many an aged head: This slothful crime Your industry refells; looks back on Time, And shews as present in old Ælian's Glass What-ere of rarest note long since did pass; And that transmitted in a style and phrase As pleasing as the Tempe it displaies. Goe on (dear Sir,) Goe on, and nobly trace (Iulus-like) though with unequal pace, Your learned Father's steps, who does engage By so much Worth this too ungrateful age: And think it still your best concern, you shou'd Be like him in Variety of Good. Edw. Sherburne.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">MANUSCRIPT POEMS, FRAGMENTS, DRAFTS. [Lines on Wood's Athenæ Oxonienses] Time who the Births of All Things brings to Light Devowres Them likewise with Saturnian Spight. As if his aged Stomach To feast it on his own Varieties: This Boulemie away thy Skill hath tooke, Disarmd Him of his was[tf]ull Syth, and Hooke. And given us like Another Hercules The Gold Fruits of Old Brut[es] Hesp[erides.] Of what high Worth may be that Worke esteemd Which Works of lost Creations hath redeemd. Methinks Old Carews Cornewell does appeare With Burton his Elaborate Leice[s]tershire, Industrious Dugdales Warwick crownd w?? fame, Grave Thorotons revived Nottingham, Wrights Rutland and Plotts Oxford with Its Twin The well-writt Staffordshire; who All begin To celebrate w?? gratefull Eulogies The Accession of thy learn'd Antiquities, Which I would too; had I a Lute well-strung To sound the Places Praise from whence I sprung. But Phæbus warnes Me, tis in vaine to strive To play the Poet well at Eighty five. [Fragment I] [And now the Sun his All oremast'ring Ray] And now the Sun his All oremast'ring Ray With Luminous Force broke through the yeilding Day. [So dying Swans in Heliconian Plaines] [Lucretius, De Rerum Natura, IV, 545–546] So dying Swans in Heliconian Plaines From their sweet Throates raise melancholy strains. [Epigram I] [Well does He give, and let me add, much too] Well does He give, and let me add, much too, Who his free Guift does with kind looks persue. [Fragment II] [In Streams thy Life did close; so in the Maine] In Streams thy Life did close; so in the Maine Starrs set, yet freshly rise from thence againe; And so mayst Thou maugre Deaths vaine surprize From Waters 'bove the Empyræum rise. [Christ Crucified] Fond Muse in vaine thou seekst a mourning dresse: Art hath no passion can our greifs expresse. Sighs w??out meane teares w?? no measure know Come yee; our Plaints in numbers will not flow. Davids sweet Lyre might play the freindly Theife And steale from his lov'd Jonathan his greif. The Noble Prophet mids Sad Elegies may humane greifs reherse And common sorrows mourne in measurd Verse, But never hope in numbers to comprize A Death w?? all Example far out vies. What sing in neat composures, 'whilst I see My sacred Lord hang on a cursed Tree? Ah better I (as greife my Soule doth fill) Into a flood of endlesse Tears distill Or teach my Eyes drop blood as he did poure From his transfixed Limbs a purple showre. And Thou who readst, mingle thy tears w?? mine: Who ere, if Man, the sad concerne is thine. Nor blame the Jews alone; all have our shares: His Deaths dire Cause We gave, the hand was theirs. Yet if thy Zeale so great a Passion beares Fond Muse! go, sing the prelude to our tears, Sing though in Vaine: after my Saviours death So great a Losse! 'tis none to loose thy Breath. [Epigram II] [Pardon his Error &amp; forgive his fault] Pardon his Error &amp; forgive his fault Whose Crime was onely doing what he ought. [Take Dardan what from dying Dido past.] [Ovid, Heroides, VII, 1a-1b] Take Dardan what from dying Dido past. The words Thou read'st are Hers; of Hers the last. So when Fates call. &amp;c. The Beginning of Virgils Third Booke Heaven having pleas'd to exterminate in fine The Asian Realms, and Priams Guiltlesse Line, Proud Ilium fall'n, Troy fumeing on the Ground, Exile and Lands Deserted We propound By Auspice of the Gods to seeke; provide At old Antandros, under Phrygian Ide A Fleet and Men to raise; uncertaine yet Where Fates would steere our Course, where fix our Seat. Summer was hardly yet begun, when straite Father Anchises bid's Hoyse Sails to Fate. Then native Shoars (Launching into the Flood) With Tears I leave, and Feilds where once Troy stood, Bourn with my Son, and my Associate Traine, Small, and Great Gods, an Exile through the Main. A Martial Land (stout Thracians till the Feilds) To Fierce Lycurgus regal Honours yeilds, A Hospitable Soyle, &amp; People kind To Troy While Fortune [fairly] was inclind. Hither by Fates Malignity I'm driven, Upon whose crooked shore (as Place was given) A Town I soon erect, fence with a Line And give it Name, Æneadæ, from Mine. Rites to my Dionæan Dame, and Powres Auspicious to such New Designs as Ours I pay; and to the Gods Almighty King On shore a white Bull slay for offering. By chance Hard by a Tomb there was w?? round Speare-fourging Corneils, and sad Myrtles crownd. This I approach; and with their Greens whilst I (Some pull'd) my Altar seek to beautify, A horrid and scarce able to be told, A monstrous Miracle, I there behold. For from the first Sprigg which from thence I tore Issu'd forthwith black Dropps of bloody Gore. And stain the Earth: a chilling horrour Shakes My Limbs, and my cold Blood all frozen makes. Againe I strive to pull a tender Sprout, And seek to find the hidden Causes out. Black Blood strait from this other Branch distilld. Much mov'd thereat the Nymphs then of the Feild I venerate; and Mars who Getic Lands And warlike Thracian Colonies commands To make the Vision prosperous, Omen vaine. A Third Time after with more Strength, I straine (My Knees clapt gainst the Ground) up by the Roote To pull another verdant Spearlike Shoot. When from the Tomb (speak shall I or desist?) A voice I heare, with Sighs &amp; Groans amidst, Æneas why strivst Thou a Wretch to rend In Peeces thus: my buried Corps befriend. Forbeare thy Pious Hands to vilify By such a Deed; to Thee no Stranger I. Troy bore Me: nor from those Sprouts flowd the Gore. Ah fly these cruel Lands: this faithlesse shore, For I am Polydore: who here ly slaine. Coverd with Darts, to Trees grown up againe. With Terrors stupified thus strange &amp; new My Haire on End stood, my Tongue speechles grew. This Polydore unto the Thracian Court With a vast Summe of Gold for his support, By Stealth Unhappy Priam sent, to be There bredd, when his Dardan Forces He Saw weaken'd &amp; the Seege close carried on. The Thracian King who found Troys fortune gon Following the Greeks and their prevailing Powre Breaks off All Right, murders young Polydore; And on the Wealth He brought by force lays hold. What will not the Sacred hunger of Gold Force Man to dare? rid of my Terrors, I Convoke the Noblest of my Company Chiefly my Father; unto whom I tell What fatall Prodigies to me befell. And their Opinions what to doe, demand. All give their Votes to quitt th'accursed Land. Fly the polluted Guest-Place, and away. To Polydore then funeral Rites we pay. And on his Tomb a Mass of Earth we lay. Altars to his sad Manes we erect, With sea-greene Wreaths, and Cypresse Boughs bedeckt Whilst Ilian Dames with Haires all loose &amp; torne About Them (as their Country's Custome) mourne. Bowls of New Milk with sparkling Wine a Flood Then Powre We forth, and Streams of sacred Blood. Lastly his Soul downe in his Graves darke Cell We lay, and lowdly bid the last farewell. [Now Night befriending; fir'd with Lust and Wine] [Ælianus, Varia Historia, XIII, 1] Now Night befriending; fir'd with Lust and Wine, Prepar'd to execute their curst Designe These Brutish Savages with horrid Cries Which the Hills eccho to the brasen skies, (Crownd with green Pinetre[e] Bowghs, and in their Hands Like Furies waveing each their flameing Brands, Clasheing their brandishd Swords in rude Essays As Terror might in All Beholders raise Much more a lonely Virgins Heart amaze) Their Course to Atalanta's Grotto bend, Whose Innocence the favouring Gods befriend; For from her Cave lookeing as she admires At th'unknowne Noyse, She sees their blazeing fires. The Virgin quickly guest who They should be; Misdoubting their intended Villany. Yet nothing daunted does not basely try Like those by Womanish feares possest, to fly, But with a nobler Resolution, chose Not to avoyd the Danger, but oppose. Her Bow and Shafts then takeing in her Hand She 'fore the Entry of her Cave doth stand A Guardian to her selfe and that Amaine. The bold Youths now came powtring to the Plaine And fierce Hylæus tossing in the Air His flareing Pine, In Vaine, in Vaine coy Faire! Aloud exclaimes, Thou hop'st in Woods to ly Conceald; or thinkst from our Pursuit to fly. No know What prayers &amp;c Then rushes on. [Haveing past cloudy Nava's rapid Stream] [Ausonius, Edyll. X, 1–44] Haveing past cloudy Nava's rapid Stream, T'admire new Walls of an old Towne I came Where France late did the Latian Cannae foyle And poore Troops, yet unwept for, strow the Soyle. Thence entring pathlesse Forrests on I trace My way, No Footsteps seeing of a humane Race. Leaving dry Densens thirsty Lands, &amp; Those Of fruitful Sauverne, w?? w?? sweet Springs flowes. And Feilds sett out to Sarmate Colonies. Then see in Belgias Skirts Nimegen rise, The famous Camp of holy Constantine. Here Purer Aire and Suns serener shine, In purple Skies. No close weav'd Bows here skreen Th'excluded Day by their caliginous Green. But Sols cleare Beams shew to the freer Ey Through the Transparent Aire a lucid Skie. All things so faire, &amp; pleasing e'en compeld To think 'twas my deare Bourdeaux I beheld. Aspireing Villa's raisd on pendent Rocks Hills cloathd w?? Vines, and Vallies stoard w?? flocks. All pleasd Me strangely, Nothing yet so well As the soft glideing Stream of the Moselle. Haile Flood, the Feilds' Applause! the Plowmans Praise! For whose sake Cæsar Once vouchsafd to raise These Belgian Walls: Sweet Flood! in a sweet Ground! With Bacchus odoriferous Bounty crownd, Thy green Banks still with gawdy flowres Stuck round. As the Sea Navigable; as a River Flowing with downe-prest Waves, yet faileing never. As a faire Lake thy Glasselike streame is deep. And as a Brooke thy trembling Windings creep. Thirst to allay, Thy liquid Waters quaft No gelid spring affords a sweeter draught. Thou hast alone All that Spring, Brooke, or Lake River, or Sea with bivious Tides partake. Thee falling with a gently flowing Wave No Wind makes rough, no hid rock makes to rave. No high rais'd Shores thy winding Course restraine Nor intercepted Ground thy Water Plaine Riseing deformes: or takes from thy just Name The Honour, to make Islands part thy Streame. Shareing thy Course, when fairly flowing on And plyd Oars make thy fixt Banks seem to run. Or when along thy sides the Bargemen goe And lay their stout Necks to the adverse Tow. How often wonderst Thou to see Boats run Up thy streame fast as that drives others downe. [Of an old Law past Times Repeale, Wee read] Angelus Politianus his Sylva entitled Nutritia: in English Verse Of an old Law past Times Repeale, Wee read By Godds, and Mens concordant Votes decreed, By Parent Natures hand incisd in Gold And read by Fate-learnd Themis as 'tis told And wise Prometheus, before crucifyd On Rocks Caucasian: [The Best of Elements is Water; Gold] Olymp. 1. Pindar. The Best of Elements is Water; Gold The Best of Mettles: Which, (as We behold A Mighty Fire illustrating Night's shade) Makes Glorious It's Possessors: and as farr As the Suns Splendour dims by Day each Starr Does Heaven's deserted Vault invade. So if Thou hast a Mind to raise O Muse! of sportful Agons the just Praise None then the Olympick Games among The Rest deserves thy noble Song: Sing then a hymne to mighty Jove A Theme which the Best Witts approve T'whome Hierons Hospitable Court &amp; Board Does Princely Welcome at full Feasts afford. Hieron, who a just Scepter wields In Fertile Sicilies faire Feilds. And from the Rest of Mankind bears The Crowne of []ed Vertues which he wears Well skilld in musicks Artful straines Such as at Friendly Boards We use to try. When noble Raptures fill my Braines Then take thy Dorick Lyre downe from the Pin, It hangs on: And a well-tund Song begin In Praise of Pisa and Pherenicus, If yet the Honour of the Place Or Courser who there won the Race, May in thy willing Muse Now sweet Alacrity infuse By thinking how the Steed in su[] prid[] Whilst by Alphæus Banks as his Lord bravely rides He runs to gaining Victory wi[th] unspurr'd Sides. [Fragment III] [So when a Storme is ceast that vext y? Maine] So when a Storme is ceast that vext y? Maine, The scarce appeased Waves doe yet retaine A grudgeing Murmur still, and fainting gales Loath yet to dye breath in the flagging sayles. To a bull striveing to obtaine the Mastery over another and vanquished. Repulst by his stout foe comes grumbling home, Chafeing to think he should be overcome. [Fragment IV] ['Tis sayd] 'Tis sayd Wee should by Precepts not Examples live But here Examples the best Precepts give. [Epigram III] [A mouse may rouse a Lyon but that don] A mouse may rouse a Lyon but that don There is no tarrying, the mouse must run. [Fragment V] [Now sea and Land y? conquering Rebells held] Now sea and Land y? conquering Rebells held And have y? rifled Kingdomes wealthy spoyles. Like haughty victors w?? successes sweld; Not satisfy'd: still their Ambition toyles. Not satisfy'd? No, were the world their owne. True; for the world hath bounds, Ambition none. The wicked Love of Rule, and change of state Now fires their thoughts. (What will not Rebells dare!) Their bold Intentions now concealem? hate And open Acts their hidden thoughts declare. What! Powre to doe't and yet deferre it still? No; though 'twas once they would, tis now they will. Hell to incite them to such black designes, W?? sence of their dire guilt their soules infests And to all Ills their jealous thoughts inclines With feares their hopes distracting; and suggests There is no meane betwixt their height &amp; fall They must be great still, or not great at all. [Epigram IV] [To make the whole entire] To make the whole entire, Not parts alone, but union Wee require. [Epigram V] [Then to disswade, when Wee have powre to force] Then to disswade, when Wee have powre to force, Shewes a remissenes of y? Mind, or worse. [Epigram VI] [True Valour hath the qualitie of fire] True Valour hath the qualitie of fire And above all corruption doth aspire. That will or bee extinguish'd, or consume And this bee either vanquishd or orecome. [Men from y? Sea, fish from y? Earth might rise] [Lucretius, De Rerum Natura, I, 162–710] Men from y? Sea, fish from y? Earth might rise And Beasts have their Extraction from y? Skies; All Creatures by a Strange promiscuous Birth Alike inhabit every part of Earth. The same trees still should not the same fruit beare But change; and every thing grow every where. For if a proper Seed were not assignd To all, what certaine Parent could We find: But since of such each thing is formd; from thence (As genial Matter gives the difference) They take their Birth &amp; being. Thus We [see] All things produc'd from all things cannot bee, Since every certaine species does Comprise Within itselfe it's proper Qualities. Besides; why Roses does the gentle Spring Produce, Warme Summer, Corne, Grapes Autumne bring? But that of certaine severall seeds composd They in their proper Seasons are disclosd, As them y? kind &amp; gently-fostering Earth Matures, &amp; brings into a perfect Birth. Else everything would in a Moment grow Nor their productions to due Seasons owe. Nor time or space for their Increase would need Would they augment from nothing, as from Seed. Small Infants in a trice would Men become And Trees at once shoot forth, grow up, &amp; bloome. W?? sence confutes; for by Degrees We find Each thing does grow, and growing keeps its kind, To prove from their owne Matter they augment And have from thence their Proper Nourishment. Add unto this that without timely showres Earth cannot bring forth either fruits or flowres Nor Creatures if their dayly food desist Or propagate their kinds, or long subsist. 'Tis better then We severall things surmise From varied common Principles arise (As words from letters formd), then to beleive Any a being can from none receive. Lastly; why should not Nature Men have made So bigg; as might on foot through deep seas wade Levell huge mountaines at a stroake; nor dy 'Till many Ages they had seen go by; But that to each created thing We find A just proportiond Matter is assignd? This for a certaine truth be then decreed That out of nothing nothing can proceed: Since what soever Nature does disclose, To Seminall Matter its Conception owes. Lastly ground manurd, We see the untilld Plaine Excells, &amp; Culture betters fruit &amp; Graine. For Earth does the prime Seeds of things comprize Which Wee by kindly-quickning Exercise Plowing the pregnant furrows up, incite To take a timely Birth &amp; view the light. Were not this true, th'uncultivated Soyle Would of itselfe improve without our Toyle. Next, Nature to their Elementall States All things resolves, but none annihilates. For were there ought whose each part mortall were, That soon would perish quite, &amp; disappeare, Nor any force would need yet to constraine The Dissolution of its naturall chaine. But since all formd of seed Eternall are Till accidentall Violence impaire Their subtle Union &amp; their frames unknit Nature no Dissolution will admitt. Besides, if all that's long since past &amp; gone Have sufferd mere Annihilation, From whence does Venus unto life againe All Creatures bring, or Earth w?? food sustaine. Whence doe clear Springs, &amp; forraigne floods supply The greedy Ocean? how Starrs feeds the Sky? (For all that's Mortall time must needs decay) But if from it's first Birth unto this day The Principles exist of w?? what ere This present Systeme shews created were, Those sure must be immortal &amp; assert That into nothing nothing can revert. In briefe by one &amp; the selfe same Effect, Did not eternall Matter them connect Or more or lesse, all things dissolvd might bee, One single touch inflict Mortalitie, And ruine Nature; But since different Ties Of Principles, and Matter that nere dies Hath each corporeall Substance, that secure, Till some strong force dissolves it doth endure Nor when dissolv'd, does unto nothing fall But the Materiall Principles of All. So showres w?? the great Father of the Sky Powres into Earths Materiall Bosome die And seeming perish; yet sweet flowres &amp; fruit And Trees from thence w?? Leavy branches shoot, Thence food for Man &amp; beast. Thence Towns Wee see Still florish w?? a numerous Progenie. Thence Woods resound w?? birds harmonious Layes Thence Chattell in the fertile Pastures graze Stretching their weary Limbs in sweet repose, Whilst from full Baggs the milky humour flowes. Thence tender Sucklins in a sportive Way Cloyd w?? the Teat, about the Meadowes play. Nothing then wholy perishes Wee see Since Nature by a wise Reficiency So orders all, that in the Birth of things One from the Ruine of another springs. But since from nothing, Nothing (We assert) Can come; nor ought thats borne, to nought revert, Tis fitt, (least thou shouldst doubt that w?? I write, 'Cause Atoms cannot be discern'd by Sight) That Wee in each created Thing declare What kind of Bodies (though unseene) there are. First then, Wind stirrd, to watery Mountains swells The Seas smooth plane, sinks Ships, &amp; clouds dispells, Then hurrying through the Feilds, before him strows Tall trees, makes Hills to tremble, Woods o'rethrows; Threatning Destruction w?? a Rage uncurbd, Whilst the chaf'd Sea, roars to be so disturbed. Winds then are unseene Bodies, w?? do fly Through Sea, &amp; Land, &amp; sweep the clouded Skie. Nor otherwise their Furie Propagate, Then Waters w?? some suddaine showres dilate Fall tumbling like a torrent from some Hill And Vallies w?? the Spoyles of forrests fill, Nor can strong bridges their assault abide: The Rain-swolne Streame w?? an impetuous tide Hurries away what ever does impose And ruine w?? the threatning Deluge flowes; Such in their fury Winds incenst appeare And like a deluge all before them beare, Whilst both their Motion &amp; effects declare That they Corporeall well as Rivers are. Next severall Sents we smell, yet I suppose None ere could see them comeing to his Nose. Who ere did see the Heate, or freesing cold? What subtle Eye did ever voice behold? Yet these are bodies; one sence shews them such For None but Bodies can be touchd or touch. To instance further; the same Cloaths hung ny The shore grow moist, spred to the sun grow dry Yet how the wett comes thether none perceives Nor how the Cloths (dispeld by heat) it leaves. So in the Course of many slideing yeares, A Ring Wee see by onely wearing, weares. So drops peirce Marble, so the Plowghs hard share Does in the feilds through often use impaire. Nolesse the Stony Pavement in the Street Wasts w?? the frequent touch of trampling feet. And brazen Statues w?? some Gate adorne By often handling We perceive are worne. Yet though the Waste be visible the Eye Can nere what Bodies fleet from them descry. Next, those things Which a naturall growth acquire By small degrees insensibly aspire: And whatsoever does by age decay As unperceptibly does waste away. Rocks by the Seas Salt Waves are undermind Yet how they frett away no Eye can find. Nature does then whatever she disclose Of Principles invisible compose. Yet think not Corporeity alone All things invests, they doe a Vacuum owne: Which, if well understood, will usefull bee Nor suffer thee to doubt the Truth, or mee. Vacuum is then a void &amp; empty Space Without w?? nothing e're cann shift it's place For Bodies alwayes Bodies would impede Nor ever could move forward or recede Unlesse some yeilding Principle there bee. But severall things w?? much Varietie Move in the Sea the Earth &amp; Heaven We find As they by different Reasons are inclin'd. Which yet if all Vacuity you wave Nor Motion could nor Generation have: For Matter if on every side opprest Must needs lie stifled in unactive rest. Dense Bodies next &amp; which most solid are You may perceive yet mix'd w?? somthing Rare. Soft Springs from stony Rocks hard Entrails creep And hollowe Caves doe liquid Christall weep. Food in all Creatures when digested flowes Through every Part; Trees thrive, &amp; fruit disclose; The Reason 'cause the Sapp does from y? Root It selfe into the Bole and Branches shoot. Sounds passe through bard up Gates and Walls of Stone And freezing Cold does peirce unto the Bone. Which yet, if there were no Vacuitie For Corporall Transitions ne're could bee. Why should some bodies others next outweigh, Yet in Dimensions not more Large then they? For if of Wool &amp; lead two balls like full Of Atoms were, like Lead would weigh the Wool. But to have Weight, of Atoms is alone The Property; of Vacuum to have none. Hence what hath equall Bulk, but lesse of weight Must more of vacuum needs participate. And those things w?? of equall bignes are Yet have more weight; must lesse of Vacuum share. There is then mixt in every thing Wee see That w?? Wee seek, and call Vacuitie. But here Least from the Truth thou be declind We must oppose what is by some divin'd. Waters say they to scaly fishes yeild A liquid Path; the place they leave still filld By the uniteing Waves; hence they would prove That all things may in a full Medium move. But this is far from Truth; for if no space The Waters yeilded; How from Place to Place Could fishes move? and if not move; how then Could the divided Waters close agen? All bodies then must either Motion want Or you in things a mixed Vacuum grant. Lastly two Bodies by some suddaine force Suppose disjoyn'd. The subtle Aire by Course Must needs fill up the Vacuum thats between Yet that at once can never enter in, Since it must needs possesse place after place And by degrees fill up the empty Space. But if some think that the condensing Aire Does in an Instant the void breach repaire, They erre, for there's a Vacuum first descry'd Was not before; next thats w?? Aire supplyd Which first was void; not can yet I presume Aire move itselfe without a Vacuum. Thus thou (though long disputes may be maintaind) Wilt to confesse it be at length constrain'd. Much more could I alledge in its Defence To take from thee all ground of Diffidence But these small Hints to a sagacious Mind Sufficient are; the rest they selfe may find. For as a well-nos'd Hound, if he the Traile Of some wild Beast discover, will not faile By that to trace him to his shady Layre So, one by one will things themselves declare To thy wise search; through windings of deceit, Till thou hunt truth out of its darke Retreat. And this unlesse [by] sloath from thence declin'd I dare assure thee, thou shalt clearly find Such Streames of Argument &amp; in such store My fluent toung from my full brest shall powre That life I feare would hardly last so long As I could stretch my Philosophick Song. But to returne to our intended Race Nature of these two things, Body and Space Is (as considerd in itselfe) composd, The first in the Last moveing, &amp; inclosd. That there are bodies common Sence does give Which unlesse We as a prime ground beleive No hope remaines for reason to assure The doubting mind in things that are obscure. And if no Space there bee such as Wee call A Vacuum bodies could not move at all. Nor is there any thing thou canst suppose As a third Nature, or distinct from those. For what soever is you must confesse Is either one of these or more or lesse; This, if it take the least Imagin'd touch Mongst Bodies must be rankd, &amp; passe for such. But if untactible, &amp; pervious, It must be what is Vacuum cald by us. Besides; what ever is, or acts alone Or by some media[ting Ac]tion. Or else is such, as others comprehends, And place to be, &amp; space to move in, lends; But none but Bodies act or are imployd And no thing can lend Place but what is voyd. Besides those two then, no third Nature e're By Sence or Reason can be made appeare. For Whatsoever the whole World presents Or conjuncts are of these, or the Events. Conjuncts are such as cannot in their kind Be w??out Ruine to themselves disjoynd, As heat from fire; from Streames Wett; Weight from stone From Bodies touch, from Vacuum to have none. But those whose Presence or whose Absence brings No reall Detriment to Naturall things, As freedome, Servitude, Wealth, Poverty War, peace and such like; these are wont to bee And justly, stil'd Events. Such time; w?? knowes No reall being of it selfe; but flowes From things, on whose mere Notion it depends, For Present, future, Past, Sence apprehends From Motion onely &amp; the Rest of things. Thus when Troys Warr, and Hellens Rape fame sings Take heed least these so force us say, they owne A reall being of themselves alone When they Irrevocably w?? the dead Of whom they were th'Events long since are fledd. For time no Action ever can present But must of things or Place be an Event. In fine were there no Matter nor no space To lend to things and actions fitting place Paris close fires, by Helens Beauty rais'd Into such Hostile flames had never blaz'd. Nor had the wooden Horse, w?? armd Greekes fr[au]ght Destruction to deceived Ilium brought. Thus you see plainly that no Actions past Like Bodies, of themselves subsist or last. Nor can with Vacuum the same Nature share, But the Events of Place &amp; Bodies are. Now, Bodies partly Principles are found And partly such as Principles compound. The first are proofe against all Violence For their Solidity is their Defence. Though it seem hardly credible to find A Body thats so solidly combin'd. For Thunder through thick Walls &amp; Houses goes, So Voice &amp; Sounds; Iron in the furnace glowes. Stones w?? excessive Heat in peeces splitt And gold by fire it's hardnesse doth remitt; Brasse melts in conquering flames; so heat &amp; cold Pearce silver; this, when in our hands We hold A cup w?? water fild to Sence is clear: So far from solid does each thing appeare. Since Reason yet &amp; Nature wills it so, Lend thy Attention while I briefly show That those w?? We for Principles declare Both solid Bodies &amp; eternall are. First then since We a twofold Nature find Of Things unlike, and differing farr in kind, Body and Space: These of Necessitie Each of themselves pure, and a part must be. For where there's Body there no space is knowne And where Space is there body can be none. Prime solid Bodies then no doubt there are Exempt from Vacuum; yet of that a share There is in all that's generated, found. Which therefore solid Matter needs must bound. Nor does it ly in Reason to unfold How things can in themselves a Vacuum hold Unlesse it first be granted, there remaine Somthing that solid is, &amp; does restraine. Now tis of Matter onely the Designe In things the subtle Vacuum to confine. Then Matter form'd of solid Bodies, may For ever Last though all things else decay. Againe, if no such thing as Space were knowne All would be solid; Bodies were there none, All would be Space. But these alternately By each divided are; nor really Is their mere void, or solid; there are then Corporeall Substances that intervene Whose fulnesse does divide the spacious Voyd. These by no outward force can be destroyd, Nor reunited be if once disjoynd, Nor by what Means soe're their Ruine find. For without Vacuum how can ought be broke? Or cut in two, or severd by a Stroke? Suffer by Moisture, heat, or cold? the Ways By w?? each corruptible thing decayes. For how much more of Vacuum all things share So much more subject to corrupt they are. Prime Solid Bodies then from Vacuum free Can nere decay; but must eternall be. And were there no such Matter unto nought What ever is would have long since been brought Or had from thence its birth; yet both w??, mov'd By Reasons dictate, We before disprov'd. There must be then prime Bodies free from waste That all things into them resolv'd, atlast May new supplies againe of Matter Raise For Nature to repaire her old Decayes. The seeds &amp; Principles of things are pure And solid Bodies then, that will endure Through all times changes; without w?? No ground For Natures Reparation can be found. Lastly if Nature had not sett an End How far corporeall fractions should extend, Foregoing times had minc'd all Matter so That nought thence form'd to perfect Age could grow. For all Things sooner We dissolv'd behold Then recompos'd: what therefore dayes of old Diminishd have; and time Successively Continues still t'impaire, that these can be Renewd againe; Experience tells us yet There is a bound to Diminution sett, Since every thing repaird againe We find And time t'acquire their Perfect grow?? assign'd. Next, though most solid bodies We declare The Principles of Matter; Things that are Composd of them may yet be mollified (As Earth, Aire, Vapours, Streams that gently glide) Because there is an Intermixture found Of Vacuum in what ever they compound. But if soft Principles did all things frame No Cause can be assign'd whence Metalls came And harder Flints: For Nature need must bee Without a Ground-Worke of Soliditie. Pure solid Bodies then there are, from whence Things Strength &amp; Substance take, as they condense. Since Nature then to All hath sett an End How far their growth shall &amp; their Lives extend Orderd what can be firm what not; the frame Of Things unchang'd is, Substance still the same (As in y? Plumes of Birds of the same kind Where Spotts though various yet still like We find.) The Ground of Matter likewise must be needs Immutable, for and the simple Seeds Of Things be chang'd, none could for certaine kn[ow] What may be borne, what not; nor Reason show Why to strict Limits Matter hath confin[d] The Powr's of things, &amp; their fixd bounds assignd. Why severall Creatures should from Race to Race, Retaine Their Parents Motions, Manners, face. Now that each bodies extreme Summit flies The Test of Sence &amp; our dim-sighted Eyes Tis 'cause its Nature does no Parts containe But indivisible does still remaine It selfe of others the first Part &amp; Last. Thence (by condensing into order cast) Other like Parts doe bodies consummate Which since they never can as seperate, And by themselves, subsist, they must of force So closely cleave that nought can them divorce. Prime bodies then of simple solidnes Consist: whose minute Parts to Union presse By no strange concourse cimented; but by Their owne innate perfect Simplicity Whose Diminution Nature, that intends Them for her Seminall Reserve, defends. Next, were there nothing least: each bodie might Though ne're so small have Parts yet Infinite For say the halfe from any thing were tane That halfe yet into halfe may part againe By endlesse Sections; what Difference Betwixt the least things then &amp; most immense, If as the greatest Quantities possesse Infinite Parts; the smallest doe no lesse? But since 'gainst this even Reasons selfe protests Nor can it gaine beleife in knowing Breasts Convicted Judgem?? must confese there are Minutest Bodies w?? no Parts doe share Whose Substance No Division can undoe And therefore solid &amp; eternall too. Lastly if Nature w?? does all things frame Into least Parts did not resolve the same Their Diminutions she could nere repaire, For Things w?? of no Parts composed are Must want the various ties, the Motion, Weight Which geniall Matter does participate. If to corporeall Fractions then be sett No bound; there must in things be bodies yet Which from Eternity have still remain'd Nor any Damage hetherto sustain'd. But if a perishing fragility Attends their Nature; they could never be From everlasting; but must needs have faild By times continuall Batteries assaild. Farr then from Truth &amp; Reason they retire Who draw the generall Birth of things from fire: Of w?? alone they dreame the World consists. In whose defense the first that takes the Lists Is Heraclitus, more esteemd among The vainer Grecians for his obscure toung Then valued by the Wise; who seeks not Words But Matter w?? unclouded Truth affords. For the Unwise those things still magnify Which shrowded under darke Expressions ly And think all's Truth w?? a faire Varnish bears Or w?? a pleasing Sound affects the Ears. But what mongst things could such a difference breed If all did from meere fire alone procede? For 'tis all one whether condens'd it bee Or rarifyd if still the Parts agree In Nature w?? the whole: w?? more or lesse But differs by their Want or their Excesse. Beyond w?? Nothing you can ere suppose To come from such a Cause; w?? can disclose (Should they allow what yet their Schoole rejects A Vacuum,) no such various Effects. But these w?? Contradictions meeting, yet Still Loath in things a Vacuum to admitt Whilst they endeavour wholly to eschue A Path thats difficult, they leave the true. Nor see they yet whilst they a Vacuum shun That all must needs condense &amp; be made One. Whence nothing ever can transmitted bee As heat, &amp; Light &amp; smoke from fire, We see, Whose freer Nature does Restraint detest Nor can subsist of parts together prest. But if some think fire by admistion leaves It's proper Body &amp; a new receives, This in the least part granted; wholly brings All fire to nothing, &amp; from thence All things. For what transform'd it's naturall bounds doth passe Is strait the death of what before it was. Somthing must therefore needs remaine entire Least all to Nothing be reduc'd w?? fire And Things not from their Causes be reviv'd But from a meere Non Entity deriv'd. Since therefore certaine Bodies do remaine Which one &amp; the same Nature still retaine Whose presence, Absence, &amp; chang'd order, brings A changed Nature to compounded things Tis cleere these Principles cannot be fire, For though some should be present some retire, Or changd or added be twere yet in vaine If all a fiery quality retaine, W?? save it's like can nothing else create. But thus it seems if I the Truth may state Bodies there are whose Concourse Motion Site Figure &amp; order fiery Births excite, Their Nature by their change diversify'd, By no Resemblance yet to fire ally'd Nor ought that bodies unto Sence subjects Or what (to it applyd) the Truth detects. But to affirme Fire is each thing thats knowne And nothing reall but itselfe alone Is an Opinion farr from Reason held And as it fights 'gainst Sense by Sense refeld; By w?? the Nature of each thing is learnd And fire itselfe by this Wise Greek discernd. Of w?? the judge he makes his Sence &amp; Eyes And yet their Test in things as cleare denies. Which, more then folly, Madnesse seems to Mee; For to know truth from falshood can their be A Rule then Sence more certaine? why againe Do some to heate alone all things restraine As their chief Cause; yet that to fire deny Since either equall folly seems t'imply. Who then to fire alone ascribes the Cause Of this Worlds various fabrick, or who draws The solid Masse of things from subtle Aire Or think that water does all formes prepare Or that [Lines on the Death of Sir Charles Lucas and Sir George Lisle, shot at Colchester on 28 August, 1648] Here lies a Lucas and a Lisle Glory and shame of this our Isle. The first in their brave Lives, all knew The last in their sad deaths, was true. (Though to their Murd'rers what was shame Bee unto them eternall Fame.) Whome since Heaven saw they knew so well To guard an Earthly Cittadell, Advanct to the Celestiall Towres Inrowld among the heavenly Powres. That to distrest Mortalitie They now might Guardian Angells bee. [Lines on Ovids Heroical Epistles] Penelopes chast Love, kind Phillis wrong, Sad Briseis suite, and Phædra's Lustfull fire, The mild Oenones playnts, and praiers among, And Lemnian Queenes distracted Love and Ire, The Lybian Dido's sad and swanlike song, And greife, and Love of desperate Deianire, Lost Ariadnes ruthfull Moanes and cries, Th'incestuous Act of the Æolian paire, The sighes, teares, threates did from Medea rise, And Loyall Laodamias irksome care, What pious Hypermnestra did devise, The Phrygian guest, and beautious Greeke did dare, The streame-divided Lovers mutual flame, Acontius snare, Cydippus heedles vowe, And th'amourous suite of the Learnd Lesbian Dame, In Latian numbers that divinely flowe The soft-sould Ovid ear'st indear'd to fame.</field>
   </doc>
</add>