<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Lee-Hamilton, Eugene</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Lee-Hamilton, Eugene</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">lee hamilton eugene</field>
      <field name="author_text">Lee-Hamilton, Eugene</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1880's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.0530.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">1882</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466268</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The New Medusa, and other poems ; By Eugene Lee-Hamilton</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The New Medusa, and other poems ; By Eugene Lee-Hamilton</field>
      <field name="title_facet">new medusa and other poems</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">new medusa and other poems</field>
      <field name="title_text">The New Medusa, and other poems ; By Eugene Lee-Hamilton</field>
      <field name="year_display">1882</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1882</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1882</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466268&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466268&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Lee-Hamilton, Eugene&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;leehamilton eugene&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The New Medusa, and other poems ; By Eugene Lee-Hamilton&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;new medusa, and other poems&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1882&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1882&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Lee-Hamilton, Eugene&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The New Medusa, and other poems&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By Eugene Lee-Hamilton&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Elliot Stock&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1882&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp2181&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;120 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The New Medusa, and other poems&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By Eugene Lee-Hamilton&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 138 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted; verse reproduced elsewhere in The English Poetry Full-text Database omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I Dedicate THESE POEMS TO MISS A. MARY F. ROBINSON, IN FRIENDSHIP AND ADMIRATION.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">POEMS AND SONNETS. PART I. INTRODUCTION. There was a captive once at Fenestrèl, To whom there came an unexpected love In the dim light which reached his narrow cell From high above. No hinge had turned, no gaoler seen her pass; But when once there, she undisturbed remained; For who would grudge a harmless blade of grass To one long chained? Between the flagstones of his prison floor He saw one day a pale green shoot peep out, And with a rapture never felt before He watched it sprout. The shoot became a flower: on its life He fixed all hope, and ceased of self to think; Striving to widen with his pointless knife The cruel chink. He bore great thirst when, parched, she drooped her head In that close cell, to give her of his cup; And when it froze, he stripped his wretched bed To wrap her up. Naming her Picciola; and week by week Grew so enamoured as her leaves unfurled That his fierce spirit almost ceased to seek The outer world. Oh such another Picciola hast thou, My prison-nurtured Poetry, long been; Sprung up between the stones, I know not how, From seed unseen! This book is all a plant of prison growth, Watered with prison water, not sweet rain; The writer's limbs and mind are laden both By heavy chains. Not by steel shackles, riveted by men, But by the clankless shackles of disease; Which Death's own hand alone can sever, when He so shall please. What work I do, I do with numbed, chained hand, With scanty light, and seeing ill the whole, And each small part, once traced, must changeless stand Beyond control. The thoughts come peeping, like the small black mice Which in the dusk approach the prisoner's bed, Until they even nibble at his slice Of mouldy bread. The whole is prison work: the human shapes Are such fantastic figures, one and all, As with a rusty nail the captive scrapes Upon his wall. But if some shape of horror makes you shrink, It is perchance some outline he has got From nightmare's magic lantern. Do you think He knows it not? Scratched on that prison stone-work you will find Some things more bold than men are wont to read. The sentenced captive does not hide his mind; He has no need. Oh, would my prison were of solid stone That knows no change, for habit might do much, And men have grown to love their dungeons lone; But 'tis not such. It is that iron room whose four walls crept On silent screws, and came each night more near By steady inches while the victim slept, And had no fear. At dawn he wakes; there somehow seems a change; The cell seems smaller; less apart the beams. He sets it down to fancy; yet 'tis strange How close it seems! The next day comes; his narrow strip of sky Seems narrower still: all day his strained eyes sweep Floor, walls, and roof. He's sure the roof's less high: He dares not sleep. The third day breaks. He sees—he wildly calls On God and man, who care not to attend; He maims his hands against the conscious walls That seek his end. All day he fights, unarmed and all alone, Against the closing walls, the shrinking floor, Till Nature, ceasing to demand her own, Rebels no more. Then waits in silence, noting the degrees— Perhaps with hair grown white from that dread doubt— Till those inexorable walls shall squeeze His strong soul out. Siena, July, 1882. THE NEW MEDUSA. A.D. 1620. Grown strangely pale? Grown silent and morose In my three years of travel? Brother John, Oh, once for all, why watch me thus so close? When since my childhood was my cheek not wan, My soul not moody, and my speech not short? As Nature made me, let me then live on. Spare me thy questions; seek such noisy sport As suits thy stronger frame and happier mood, And cease thy preaching of this irksome sort. It suits my whim to hold aloof and brood; Go, medler, go! Forgive me, I recall The word; it was too harsh, for thou art good. O cruel Heaven, shall I tell him all? God knows I need a hand to cling to tight, For on my path all Horror's shadows fall. I am like one who's dogged, and who, as night Is closing in, must cross a lonely spot, And needs some staunch companion in his flight. My enemy is Madness: I have got His stealthy step behind me, ever near, And he will clutch me if thou help me not. Oh, I have sailed across a sea of fear, And met new lands to add to Horror's realms, And shores of Guilt whence none may scatheless steer. A very world of jarring thoughts o'erwhelms My cowering soul when I would tell what's been Since last I saw this Hall, these English elms. Yet must the tale be told, and every scene Gone o'er again. I fear some monstrous thing From my own self, and on thy strength must lean. So listen. I had spent the early spring In Venice, till Ascension Feast—the day On which the Doge casts in his bridal ring; And had embarked, with pleasant winds of May And gentle seas, on a Venetian ship Bound for Palermo, where I meant to stay. All gave us promise of a prosperous trip; Yet, by the second day, mishap began, And 'tween two Turkish sail we had to slip. From dawn to dusk before the Turk we ran, Till, safe and breathless off Illyria's coast, We each thanked God to be a chainless man. 'Twas but the respite of an hour at most; The weather changed with dread rapidity. As in rebuke of Safety's hasty boast, God laid His mighty hand upon the sea, Moulding at once a million liquid peaks That ever round us tossed more furiously. For three whole days the tempest blanched the cheeks Of men whom years of storm had ill enriched, And long familiar with the petrel's shrieks. It was as if the maddened ocean itched Beneath the ship; so desperately it tried To shake it off, and bounded, roared, and pitched, And, like a lion in whose quivering hide An insect burrows, wasted strength and wrath, In rush on rush, by littleness defied. At last, like one who no more hoping hath, It ceased the strife; and we, at dawn of day, Had set the helm to seek our long-lost path, When in the offing, on the lurid grey, Where tossed black waves, as if of ire still full, We saw a something looming far away. It proved to be a small dismasted hull, To all appearance empty, which remained Upon one spot, just like a sea-rocked gull. On closer search we found that it contained A woman, lashed to remnants of a mast, Who seemed a corpse, but, slowly, life regained. Her black, wet, rope-like locks she backward cast, And in her troubled memory seemed to seek; Then strangely, doggedly, concealed the past. Her garb, her features, said she was a Greek, But Tuscan she spoke well; and 'tis that tongue Which she and I in aftertimes did speak. And as she stood amid the wondering throng, And no account of home or kindred gave, A murmur 'mong the sailors ran along. “Keep her,” they cried; “we'll sell her as a slave; She owns no kin that she should be exempt; She's common prize tossed up by wind and wave.” She caught the words, but made no vain attempt To melt their hearts by prayer and sobs and sighs, And looked around her with a queen's contempt. And then it was that suddenly her eyes, Singling me out, were fastened upon mine So searchingly, that all felt huge surprise; And that, like one who by some secret sign Knows that a strange command will be obeyed, She cried, “Lord, buy me;” and I paid her fine. So she my slave, and I her slave was made, She taking eager bondage from that hour, And binding me in chains that never weighed. She seemed contented with a latent power, Keeping slave garb, and took small gifts alone, As might an empress from some love below her. She bade me name her, and I named her Joan, Feeling no wish to pry within her breast, Or learn what name her former life might own. With all the strong lithe beauty, she possessed The noiseless tread of a tame leopardess, Docile, majestic, holding strength repressed. With wondrous insight soon she learned to guess My gloomy temper's ever-shifting mood, And, fierce in love, was chary of caress. Now wisely silent, she would let me brood Until the fit was over; now she cheered With such fantastic tales as tribes still rude Delight to hear, the night till dawn appeared; Now sang unto the lute some old Greek air, Like gusts of moaning tempest wild and weird. And other gifts she had, and arts more rare; For when at Syracuse I once fell ill Of a malignant fever, and her care Preserved my life, she showed a leech's skill In mingling drugs, and knew how to extract From long-sought herbs a juice for ague's cure. Oh she was strangely dowered, and she lacked Nought that can rivet man to woman's side, Nought that can win, or on the senses act. But there were moments when a fear would glide Across my heart, I knew not well of what, And on the secret which her life might hide My mind would work; and yet she daily got A firmer tenure of the love she'd won, And felt each day my kisses grow more hot, Even as those of the Sicilian sun, Which made of winter spring, with fiery love, Long ere the thaw had in our clime begun. She loved, like me, from place to place to move, And seldom we long lingered where mere chance Had made us stop, but sought some lovelier grove, Where, from deep shade, we saw the sunshine dance On the blue sea which lapped the tideless coast, And watched the sails which specked the blue expanse. But when that happened which I dread to reach, We were abiding where the owlet made The night oft sleepless with his lonesome screech. It was a sea-girt castle much decayed, Belonging to an old Sicilian prince With whom, when at Palermo, I had stayed. He loathed the place, would go to no expense To keep it up; but, loving town resorts, Had left it in his youth, nor seen it since. It suited well my mood. The weird reports, The legends which the peasants loved to tell About its empty halls and grass-grown courts; Its garden paths where unpicked flowers fell; Its silent rooms where many echoes woke And fancies came—all made me love it well. Its furniture of carved and blackened oak Looked ghostly in the twilight; while the walls Were hung with shields and swords of mighty stroke. Of mighty stroke? Ay, ay, my tongue forestalls My hesitating thoughts as I relate, And every item that I name appals, As I retread in mind where monstrous Fate Changed love to horror; every look I cast Makes me all love, all horror, re-create. One night—O John, I come to it at last— One night I had a nightmare in my sleep For vividness and terror unsurpassed. Methought I felt a snake's cold body creep About my hand and throat, entwine them tight, And o'er my breast a hideous mastery keep. Awhile I lay all-helpless, in despite Of agony, and felt the pressed veins swell, Then forced a smothered cry into the night. My cry awoke me, waking Joan as well, When, panting still with nightmare fear, I found That the black locks that on her bosom fell Had crept about my throat and girt it round So tightly as awhile to stop the breath, While other locks about my arms had wound. We laughed away my ugly dream of death, And in the silence of the night that waned We heaped up kisses, burying fear beneath. I gave the thing no thought; but Hell ordained That this same dream, before a week was cut, Should be repeated, and its horror strained. Once more the snakes encompassed me about, Once more I woke her with my strangled cry, Once more I found her locks around my throat. Then I began to brood; and by and by Strange things of God's strong chastisement of crime Recurred all vaguely to my memory. I seemed to recollect from olden rhymes Some tale about the hair of those who take A many lives through poison; how at times, When guilt haunts sleep, each lock becomes a snake, While they remain unconscious of the change; And turns again to hair so soon they wake. Smile not, or I will throttle thee. The range Of Nature is so vast that it hath room For things more strange than what we call most strange. I am not mad. I thought with growing gloom How we had met her, tossed alone at sea, And how the Turks who rule those coasts oft doom Their women to strange punishments. Might she, For some great crime, not have been made to brave The winds and waves by some such strange decree? And then I thought what proof she often gave Of skill in medicine and botanic lore; And how that serves to kill that serves to save. I struggled with these thoughts—I struggled sore: With shame and self-contempt I cast them out, And, looking on her beauty, loved her more. But listen, John. A month or thereabout Went by unmarked, and then there came a night Which seemed to put an end to every doubt. I was awake; there was no sound, no light. Yes, there was sound: her breathing met my ear, The breath of dreamless sleep—low, smooth, and slight. But suddenly it quickened, as in fear, And broken words whose sense I could not tell Escaped her lips; my name I seemed to hear. Now listen, John. Methought she lay not well, I stretched my hand to slightly raise her head; But what my hand encountered was, O hell! No locks of silky hair: it met instead A something cold which whipt around my wrist Unholdable, and through my fingers fled. I groped again and felt two others twist About my arm;—a score of vipers twined Beneath my hand, and, as I touched them, hissed. There is a horror which leaves free the mind But glues the tongue. Without a word I slipt From out the bed, and struck a light behind Its ample curtain; then, unheard, I crept Close up and let the light's faint radiance hover Over the Gorgon's features as she slept. The snakes were gone. But long I bent me over Her placid face with searching, sickened glance, Like one who in deep waters would discover A corpse, and can see nothing save, perchance, The landscape's fair reflected shapes, which keep Balking the vision with their endless dance. It seemed to me that in that placid sleep, Beneath that splendid surface lay concealed Unutterable horror sunken deep. And, seeking not to have the whole revealed, I fled that fatal room without a sound, And sought the breeze of night with brain that reeled. How long I wandered 'mid the rocks around, Like some priced outlaw—whether one, or two, Or three whole days I know not—fever bound A veil across my brain, and I've no clue To guide my memory through those days accurst, Or show me what my misery found to do. I recollect intolerable thirst, And nothing more; until the night again Enwrapped the earth, and with it brought the worst. A mighty wish, with which I fought in vain, Came o'er my soul to see once more her face, And dragged me back, as by an unseen chain. Where love and horror struggle, there is place For countless fierce and contradict'ry tides Of Will and Sense within one short day's space. With every hour the gale has shifted sides; The needle of Thought's compass will have leapt From pole to pole, and chance at last decides. So I returned, and like a thief I crept Into the house, where every light was out, And sought the silent chamber where she slept. O brother, brother! I'm in awful doubt. If what I saw, and what shall now be told, Was a mere figment of the brain throughout, Then will the sickened Heaven ne'er behold A deed more monstrous than the deed I've done, Though this old earth should grow again as old. But if the thing was real, if 'twas one Of hell's corroborations of great guilt, My hand was an avenger's hand alone. So wonder not, if, with the blood I've spilt Still on my hand, I fain would have thee think That the great wall, which God Himself hath built Between this world and hell, may have a chink Through which some horror, yet unknown to earth, And over great for us, may sometimes slink. May not such strays from Hell have given birth To poets' fancies which the wise deride, And olden saws of which we now make mirth. Oh who shall have the courage to decide Between the things that are and those that seem, And tell the spirit that the eyes have lied? Watch thy own face reflected in the stream; Is that a figment? Who shall dare to call That unsubstantial form a madman's dream? Or watch the shadow on the sunlit wall, If thou could'st clutch it great would be thy skill; Thou'lt feel a chilly spot—and that is all. So may the spectres which, more subtle still, Elude the feeble intellect of man, And leave us empty-handed with a chill, Be just as much reality. We spend Life 'mid familiar spectres, while the soul In fear denies the rest. But hear the end. The moon was at the full; but o'er the whole Vast vault of heaven was stretched a fleecy tent, Through which her baffled light but dimly stole, Save where the breezes of the night had rent On some few points that subtle woof o'erhead, That men might catch her glances as she went. And as once more I trod with stealthy tread Each silent, vast, and solitary room, Where, through the tiny panes, encased in lead, Of Gothic windows, moonlight broke the gloom So dimly that I scarce could thread my way, I seemed a ghost returning to its tomb. I neared the fatal bed in which she lay; Its sculptured columns had a ghostly look; Its heavy daïs, of faded silk by day, Looked stony in its tintlessness, and took The semblance of the marble canopy Above some Templar's tomb. Yea, every nook Of this strange room bred awe, I know not why, While dim mysterious gleamings seemed to thrill From swords and shields that decked the walls on high. With soundless step, approaching nearer still, I touched the sculptured oak, while love and fear Contesting in my breast suspended will. I saw her shape but vaguely, but could hear Her placid breath attesting, if aught could, A dreamless sleep and conscience wholly clear. Love in my breast was winning, as I stood And watched her thus some moments in her sleep; Her tranquil breathing seemed to do me good. But suddenly it quickened with a leap, Becoming like the fierce and panting breath Of one in flight, who climbs a rocky steep. The soul seemed struggling with the fear of death, While broken utterings in a tongue unknown Escaped at moments through her tightened teeth. I was about to wake her, when the moon Lit up the bed, and let me see a sight Which for a while changed flesh and blood to stone. All round the face, convulsed in sleep and white, Innumerable snakes—some large and slow, Some lithe and small—writhed bluish in the light, Each striving with a sort of ceaseless flow To quit the head, and groping as in doubt; Then, fast retained, returning to the brow. They glided on her pillow; all about The moonlit sheet in endless turn and coil, And all about her bosom, in and out; While round her temples, pale as leaden foil, And fast closed lids, live curls of vipers twined, Whose endless writhe had made all hell recoil. Long I stood petrified; both limbs and mind Refusing in the presence of that face The customary work to each assigned. But, all at once, I felt a fire replace My frozen blood, and unseen spirits seemed To call for an Avenger, and to brace My arm for one great blow. Above me gleamed A double-handed sword upon the wall, Whose weight, till then, beyond my strength I deemed. I seized it, swung it high, and let it fall Like thunder on the sleeping Gorgon's neck Before her eye could see or tongue could call. And, O my God! as if herself a snake Which, stricken of a sudden in its sleep, Coils up and writhes all round the injuring stake, She coiled about the weapon in a heap, But gave no sound, while all the sheet soaked red, Except a sort of gurgle hoarse and deep, Which made me strike again, until the head, Whose beauty death's convulsion seemed to spare, Rolled like a heavy ball from off the bed. I held the dripping trophy by the hair, Which now no more was snakes, but long black locks, And scanned the features with a haggard stare. And, like to one around whose spirit flocks Too great a crowd of thoughts for thought to act, I fled once more along the moonlit rocks. Then Doubt, with his tormentors, came and racked. A BALLAD OF THE PLAGUE OF FLORENCE. A.D. 1348. In some corpse-strewn plain of the sun-baked East Or some foul dark prison, the Plague had arisen, And had leapt on the back of the Wind; For the children of men overmuch had increased, It was time that their crowds should be thinned. And the Wind with the Plague over Florence arrived, As many a tower was striking the hour, For men to seek rest without fear; And a hum uprose, as of bees new hived, From the streets, that was pleasant to hear. And the morrow a many a knell was tolled, Nor ceased the bells to sound the knells, Till the ringers turned black and dropped; Nor the biers to pass by till, relaxing their hold The carriers staggered and stopped. Then neighbour would neighbour suspiciously meet, And would eye him askance with a searching glance, And the sound of men's labour was hushed; Yea, they started aghast, as they passed in the street, If by chance 'gainst each other they brushed. And the lover would shudder on touching the tips Of the fingers fair, or the locks of hair That he loved, but were laden with death; And would shrink from the kiss of Love's blackening lips, As if hell were contained in a breath. And father bade son from his doorstep avaunt, If but gleamed his eye, and would let him die In the streets like a dog, without help; For Fear makes men wild as the wolves that haunt Round the sheepfold at night and yelp. Through a veil of horror the sun seemed black, And the limpid air seemed too dense for prayer To reach to the throne on high; As, faster and faster pursuing its track, The invisible scythe swept by. And high o'er the wail of the trembling crowd, And the cries to Heaven of souls unshriven, Rose strumming, and filthy song, And the rattle of dice, and the laughter loud Of the dying and ghastly throng. O thou great and strong God, cried each strong heart then, Is this guilty Florence Thy eyes' abhorrence? Is it doomed like the Towns of the Plain? Though worse is this rotting and dropping of men Than the falling of fiery rain! But the unseen Mower, with his unseen scythe, Mowed on as through grass, through the populous mass, Till his arm seemed slowly to tire; And of what had been Florence remained but a tithe To relate God's terrible ire. Now just about the time that this selfsame Plague Was preparing to poison the air with its foison, There was living in Florence a dame. She was young and had eyes that were dreamy and vague, And was known as Ginevra by name. And her fame was pure as a pebbly spring, Though by one accord 'twas said that her lord Was harsh and ne'er valued her beauty, And though suffering many a pitiful thing, She but clung all the more to her duty. She lived in a house which is solid still, Though the thick stone wall is blackened all By the centuries five that have flown, With escutcheon on door and sculptured sill In the old, old heart of the town. There, while squandered her husband his time at play, His sweet young wife led her weary life, Secluded from friends and from pleasure (Though her father was rich and her brothers were gay), And had nought but the past as a treasure. As she sat all unkissed in her chamber and wove The tapestry flowers, in long lone hours, She would think of her girlhood and weep; And her thoughts would revert, though against it she strove, To the hopes that lay buried deep. She thought, oh! how different now were her life Had they let her but wed, long ago, instead, Antonio, her early love, Whose dream was to make her the happiest wife In the face of Heaven above. For Antonio had been her father's clerk; And though good his birth and known his worth, His state had been deemed too lowly; And she thought as she wept in the twilight and dark That he now had forgotten her wholly. But Ginevra was wrong; for that love is but hollow Which, robbed of hope, doth flap and drop Like a windless sail on the mast: And his joy was to follow Her life of each day as it passed. He would watch in the aisle of the church, where the streams Of crimson light fell warm and bright, As her prayers on the tombstones she said; And would envy the dead who could hear in their dreams Her whispered words overhead. He would lurk at dusk in the lonely street Till her lamp should be lit and her shadow should flit, Like a restless bird, on the blind; And with painful tightening his heart would beat As he pictured the room behind. And he found a spot whence, with cruel delight, He could see the lady as she walked in her shady Court, which high walls defended; And he scaled them to pluck, like a thief in the night, Some flower her hand had tended. Well, the Plague broke out; and more closely than ever Indoors she was pent, and her dull days spent Till her cheeks' waning roses had died, While Francesco her husband all ties had to sever With the perilous world outside. And he feared for his life, and his fear made him cruel, As death each day swept great crowds away, And all on Ginevra was vented; For he knew of Antonio, and hatred found fuel In wrongs that his fancy invented. And it chanced that he went to her chamber one day, And o'erwhelmed her awhile with language vile; And he struck her a blow as he left, And when he returned in the evening she lay On the ground, of all motion bereft. A waxen mass is more bloodless not Than her face was now; and more cold was her brow Than her pillow the marble floor; While her loosened dress showed a blackening spot On her bosom that heaved no more. And the knees of the coward with terror shook; For the Plague struck even as fast as from heaven Descendeth the fiery fork; He would scarcely approach, but the chamber forsook, And left to his menials the work Of shrouding the body so white and fair, And of closing the bier in haste and fear, As even the great were then buried. And, unfollowed by friend and unhallowed by prayer, To the family vault she was hurried. Then darkness and silence the city surprised; Through the alleys lonely there rumbled only The dead-cart with flickering light; And the silent church, where she lay with the dead, Was more silent than ever that night. The round moon rose, and her white light crept Through the painted panes to the columned lanes Of the aisles with their ornaments pale, And turned the stone garb of the knights who there slept Into something like silvery mail. But all of a sudden the silence ceased, And a sound of sighs and of muffled cries Rose up from the vault below; Then an echo of planks, and a sound which increased, As of movements uncertain and slow. And the door revolved of the steep vault stairs, And a woman staggered, convulsed and haggard, Across the broad nave to the street; And she hid her breast with her long loose hair, And her limbs with a funeral sheet. For Ginevra had risen from out of her tomb, And the plague-spot dark had been but the mark Of the blow that her cruel lord gave; And through ill-closed doors the friendly moon Had helped her to leave her grave. And she threaded her way in her awful plight, Down the stony street with injured feet, To her father's house which was near; And the few whom she met at her white shroud's sight Fled wildly before her in fear. At her father's door she stood and knocked, Till a window at last was open cast, But at once it was slammed with a shriek, And though long she implored, not again was't unlocked, For none cared with a spectre to speak. So she wandered on with a waning strength Till she stood before her husband's door, In her grave-clothes scanty and weird, And shouted and knocked till Francesco at length Himself at the window appeared. And she cried: “Fear not; I am flesh and blood; Ginevra, thy wife; not a ghost, but in life; Though I walk, like a ghost, in a shroud. Oh, open the door!” and she shivering stood, And her prayers grew more pressing and loud. But he, answering nothing, looked down for a while At her bare white feet, and the moonlit street, Which pointed stones did pave; Then he suddenly said, with a sinister smile, “Wert thou not at thy ease in thy grave? “Plague-struck or not thou hast jostled the dead, And trodden the alleys where the great foe sallies, By whom we all fear to be clutched; So seek thou a shelter elsewhere for thy head, For I know not whom thou hast touched.” And the window closed with a quick harsh sound, And opened no more, though, with prayers long and sore, The night of its silence she robbed, Till at last she sat down on the pitiless ground, In her shroud in the moonlight, and sobbed. And as she sat with no counsel nigh, Inert and dejected, and wholly rejected By men and by Heaven above, Her thoughts reverted, she knew not why, To Antonio her early love. And she straightway rose, and resumed her way, Through the sad streets lonely, and halted only At the door of the house where he dwelt. And her limbs as she knocked were as cold as clay, But strange warmth in her heart she felt. And she knocked and called, and Antonio heard, And on seeing her staggered, like a man that's daggered, While her story she hurriedly told. And he led her within, never speaking a word, While she trembled with joy and cold. And he called his mother, and they wrapped her up In blankets of wool, and with hearts over full. He bandaged her feet that were bleeding, And when they were bandaged he gave her to sup, For sorely some food she was needing. And so, till men's courage (the plague being over) Began to revive, and the city to thrive, In the house of Antonio she tarried, When, strange though it seemeth, one morning her lover Led Ginevra to church and they married. And Francesco the husband began then and there A great legal strife to recover his wife In the archiepiscopal courts; Of which, in the archives, such persons as care May find to this day the report. But the lawyers decided, at mighty expense Of parchment and ink (but with wisdom, I think), That Francesco did vilely behave; That Ginevra his wife had been buried long since, And that all are released by the grave. A BALLAD OF THE SACK OF PRATO. A.D. 1512. Said the Spaniards: “By to-morrow, If ye victual us not and well, We will storm the town, and borrow For your use three days of hell.” But the rash, rash Prato people Did not listen, but delayed, And from every tower and steeple Looked to Florence, hoping aid. But the lean and tattered Spaniards Kept their word, and stormed the town, Rich with thriving looms and tan-yards, Like a flood that bears all down, Like a flood whose scummy waters Sweep with hungry, hideous roar Down the streets of busy quarters, Gurgling in at every door. But the waters find a level: There is mercy in the flood; While the Spaniards in their revel Soaked the very roofs with blood; Hunting on the flying dwellers In each house from room to room; Ratting them from out the cellars; Cutting down no matter whom. Then they sought with screw and fire What the rich had hid in haste; Raising their exactions higher For the time they made them waste; And they tightened and they twisted, And they limb from socket drew Unrestrained and unresisted, Till no thumb remained to screw. And they lashed men, gagged and stifled, To the beds where writhed their wives, And in sight of fathers rifled What was dearer than their lives. There were girls on terrace ledges In their fetid, hot embrace, Who, by wriggling to the edges, Dragged pollution into space. And, behind the Spaniards, followed Flame, with red and restless tongue; And a many of them it swallowed With the prey to which they clung. And for three whole days no pity— Plunder, torture, fire, and rape; In the little blood-soaked city Greed and lust took fearful shape. Till it weltered in its horror, Giving night a lurid glow, Like a dying, mute Gomorrah Waiting for God's final blow. Then the scum of Spanish galleys, Gorged with plunder, stained with blood, Ebbed from out its streets and alleys Like the oozing river flood; Dragging with them girls and women Stupid with despair and shame, To such lands as evil omen Doomed to slaughter, sack, and flame. And among these women carried Off from Prato and all things dear, Was an armourer's wife, new married, Who nor sobbed nor shed a tear. Neither did she pine and languish As the seasons rolled along; No, nor learn to drown her anguish In debauchery and song. Nothing showed that while obeying She was writhing under fate; Nothing, save the scowl, betraying Inextinguishable hate For the captain who had torn her From her husband and her child, And had made all Nature scorn her, As its thing the most defiled. Silent, as if God had made her Dumb, but with her teeth clenched tight She endured the blows which paid her For a twice attempted flight. Even as she bore his kisses With a clenching of her teeth, And a silence where abysses Of destruction lay beneath; Like a tigress that hath shaken All the railings of her cage, And has many lashings taken, With a smothered roar of rage, But reserves her spring for later, When her tamer has no help, While her hate grows daily greater With her yearning for her whelp. Seven years through camp and city, In the ravaged Lombard plain, She was dragged, and asked no pity, Letting time enlarge her stain, Till, in one terrific minute, She might wash it out in gore, And see Prato and those in it Pure in spirit as before. And that minute came: the army Far to south, to Parma, went, And the night was dark and stormy, And ill-guarded was his tent. In his drunken sleep, she lashed him With the tent-ropes to his bed, And she took his sword and slashed him Till she severed off his head. And she donned his clothes and, springing On his charger, rode away; With her gory trophy swinging From her pommel, night and day. And she rode and never slackened In a three days' thundering flight, Until towers old and blackened And familiar, were in sight. And she galloped, stained and haggard, Into Prato with reins slackened, On a horse that wheezed and staggered, As she leaped from off his back. Then she tied it to the door-ring Of a cherished dwelling there, Where an armourer's forge was roaring And all smoky was the air. And she cried to him who met her On the threshold, “It is I. I'm not dead; for I'd a better Task before me than to die.” And he started back all trembling, While his sweating brow turned pale, Standing silent, and assembling Thoughts too crowded to avail. “Dost thou see this head, and know it? It's a love-gift which I bring.” And she held aloft, to show it, By the hair, the hideous thing, Saying, as he more recoiled, “Hast thou ne'er a dead dog seen? If I bring my body soiled, Oh, I bring my spirit clean! “To ensure return I waited Seven years ere taking life; I can love as I have hated: Dost thou own me as thy wife?” But her husband, still not giving Any answer to her speech, Scanned the dead and scanned the living, With an equal gloom for each. And at last he said, “I hear thee; I say neither yea nor nay; Thou art fearful, and I fear thee, Though I've mourned thee many a day. “Seven years hast thou been missing; What if wast a willing slave Who did kill him, once his kissing Neither gold nor pleasure gave? “To the market-place I'll take thee, And the people shall decide; And a wife again shall make thee, Or shall bid thee further ride.” And she turned without debating, And he led her to the door, Where her panting steed was waiting, And he bade her mount once more. Then he led her by the bridle, While a mighty, mighty throng, Of the curious and the idle Gathered as they went along. Till the mass of people darkened The cathedral's steps and square, And they knew him, and they hearkened With a thousand headed stare. And he spoke and told the story Loud, that all might understand; And he showed her with the gory, Livid trophy in her hand. And he cried, “See, she has brought me From afar the villain's head, And returned at once and sought me, Shall I take her to my bed?” And the people's heart was with her, And they shouted, “Take her back! None so brave has galloped hither Since the burning and the sack.” And on high the people raised her When her triumph was decreed; And the Tuscan cities praised her For her bold and bloody deed. And the bells from every steeple Rang as when a land's heart beats, As she rode to please the people Through the flower-littered streets. THE IDYL OF THE ANCHORITE. A.D. 1000. [I.] The great firs moaned in the valleys below; But high up in the pass, in the wastes of snow, 'Mid the great lone rocks where no live thing stirred, All was mute, for the torrents had ceased to flow. Save at times when the cry of some travel-spent bird, Or the long, low howl of a wolf was heard; For the wolves in great numbers had traversed the Rhine On the ice that winter, by hunger stirred. The wintry light in its rapid decline Illumined the rocks with a sickly shine; All was stone and was snow; all was dumb and was wan: Of plants no vestige, of man no sign. And yet one human life upon Those crags (if life you could call it) went on, Where even in summer no herb was gleaned, The life of the anchorite, John of Avonne. A lair, half cave, half cabin, screened, Up there where nature had never greened, The man who daily at dawn resumed This long, lone war with himself and the Fiend. His frame, by vigil and fast consumed, Was bent ere age, and his face had assumed A colour more sallow than baker's paste, A look more haggard than corpse exhumed. Six years had he lived on that mountain waste, Which the very stones that his foot displaced, The very waters that bubbled there, Deserted with loathing and headlong haste. Six years had he borne in shirt of hair In summer the sun's terrific glare, In winter great frost, to be nearer to God In a mixture of rapture and dull despair. And not God, but the Fiend on his footsteps trod And tempted him, spite of his scourging rod And his long, long prayer, and his hearth without fire, And the tasteless herb, and the hard wild pod. And whispering devils inflamed his desire For all that men care for, and do and admire; And murmured of riches and pleasure and ease, And made him regret mother, sister, and sire. And others, whose task was to plague and to tease, Took in summer the shape of uncatchable fleas, As he knelt at his prayers, and made his thoughts stray, And in winter they made him to cough and to sneeze. And they stole his dry herbs and made him mislay His beads, and confused him till scarce he could pray, And they sent him to sleep when he still had to kneel, And they left not unplayed any trick they could play. And devils in semblance of women would steal To the side of his bed, till he thought he could feel Their breath on his cheek, and their hot kiss feared, Which should forfeit for ever his heavenly weal. And from under the mat of his cell they peered, And tempted and tickled and beckoned and leered; While their round, rosy limbs to his horror peeped out, And their laughter-filled eyes at his chastity jeered. And they circled him nearer and nearer about, While he trembled with horror with lust and with doubt; And brought him so near the eternal abyss, That all panting he woke with an amorous shout. II. It was winter now, and so cold as this It had never yet been in his cell, I wiss; The night wind had risen, and ceased not to sweep The slopes of snow with an angry kiss. He had lit a fire at last, to keep His soul with his body; and, half asleep, Was telling his beads as he crouched on his mat By the flickering light of the blazing heap. Had you watched him there, as he silent sat, And the work he was sluggishly busy at, You might have felt wonder that God should have made So bloodless and listless a thing as that. It was more than a month since the devils had played Any tricks, and untroubled the anchorite prayed, While sense and sensation began to depart, In numb beatitude unafraid. But all of a sudden he gave a start, The stagnant blood seemed to flow to his heart And he listened awhile to some outer noise With brow contracted and lips apart. For more than six years no woman's voice Had dropped on his ear by his own fierce choice, And now he could hear one imploring outside, And faith made him fear, and nature rejoice. “Let me in! let me in!” the suppliant cried, “Whoever thou art whose blest light I have spied; For the love of God give me shelter and food, I have strayed from the path, and have well-nigh died.” In doubt one moment the anchorite stood Between mercy, and fear, of womanhood; But what conquered was dread of the flesh and its snares, And he stopped his ears with his coarse brown hood. And he knelt once more and resumed his prayer, And placed himself well in the Virgin's care, And, like one who his heart with a strong hand locks, He thanked God that no woman might enter there. But louder and louder resounded the knocks, While she cried in a tone to move stones and stocks “Let me in! let me in! the wolves are near: “I can hear them: they've tracked me since dusk on the rocks.” And he listened, and thought he could distantly hear The howl of a wolf; and in spite of chaste fear He opened the door, and he let her rush by With the icy blast of the night in rear. In a strange, wild way, with a strange, wild cry, She rushed to the fire that still blazed high; And she crouched by the flame as if she would hold The logs and their heat to her bosom more nigh. Her face was so pinched and so warped by the cold That you scarcely could say was she young or old, And her long black hair, which hid partly her cheek, On her shoulders fell loose, by the wind unrolled. He pushed her some food and bade her not speak, But leave him to prayer; and, like those who seek Both shadow and peace, dragged his matting of straw To a corner, and watched her with glance oblique. And, little by little, with terror he saw, As the cold relaxed the icy claw With which it was holding so tightly her frame, And the blood in her veins began to thaw, That from minute to minute she younger became By the steadier light of the higher fed flame, And her form became rounded, her cheek increased, And, from minute to minute, she seemed not the same. And she seemed as her roundness and colour increased, In his eyes, unaccustomed to beauty, at least, To be terribly lovely; his blood quicker ran, And the prayers he was muttering gradually ceased. And a frightful trial of strength began In the breast of the savage and lonely man, Between fear for his soul and the pent up lust, Whose fire her presence had come to fan. He thought how for years, in ashes and dust, He had hungered on herbs of the waste and on crust, And had chastened with scourge and with shirt of hair The flesh that may not, the flesh that must. And had climbed half way up Heaven's desolate stair, Where each step that he took was beset with a snare, And would soon reach the top where he could not fall, To be paid for the ills he had chosen to bear. He tried to do like the bloodless snail, Which gathers up body and horns and tail, And to shrink in his cowl, and escape from her view; But his cowl was no shell, nor would shrinking avail. For an awful force like a magnet drew His senses out, and more terrible grew The more he resisted and tried to be A feelingless thing, and to pray anew. And already he crept on hand and knee, (For still in the posture of prayer was he) When a sudden thought made Austerity win And roused all his fury, while setting him free. He remembered the Fiend had once been let in, In the shape of a girl, by Saint Victorin, And had prayed for a shelter from wolves in his cell, And had tempted him sorely and made him sin. It was he! it was he! Oh, he now knew him well, It was he! it was he! He had come out of hell To make him do sin which no prayer could purge, But, thank God, 'twas still time to refrain and expel. And he sprang from his mat, and he seized his scourge, And, like one whom invisible spirits urge, He let the lash fall on the neck soft and round, Which had brought him so near to destruction's verge. She started and shrank, with no other sound Than a loud, inarticulate cry, like a hound Who feels on his back sudden lashes alight, But understands nought, and lies still on the ground. Then, as faster and faster he ceased not to smite, And bade her avaunt, and begone from his sight, All bewildered with terror, she fled to the door And sought peace in the cold and the darkness of night. III. He fastened the bolt and, alone once more, He knelt on his mat, and repeated a score Of monotonous prayers, while the sobs outside Grew faint in the wind which howled as before. The night was advanced; and the sleep he defied Was numbing his brain, and though hard he still tried To mutter more prayers, his eyelids fell, But his lips their mechanical task still plied. At last his lips stopped, and he dreamt of hell, Which seemed to be somehow encircling his cell, And he heard the damned at his door knock loud With wild entreaty and dreadful yell. They seemed to his fancy a numberless crowd, Whose voice was with infinite horror endowed, While above them the fiends, still more countless than they, Fast scourging and rending them, hung like a cloud. And they shrieked in so urgent and frightful a way That he woke, with a forehead as clammy as clay, And listened in fear; but the wind howled alone, And he turned on his side, and he slept till day. And the bleak light of morning lividly shone On the dreary desert of snow and stone; The clouds hung low, like a great lid of lead, Though the wind still blew with a fitful moan. And the anchorite rose from his hard, mean bed, And he thought, as his long, long prayers he said, How well he had treated the Fiend with his whip Last night, and how quickly the Fiend had fled. And a dull contempt curled faintly his lip As he thought how Saint Victorin let the Fiend slip After letting him tempt him to do what none should, While he had belaboured him, shoulder and hip. And he covered his head with his coarse brown hood, And taking his pail on his threshold stood, And looked out on the waste, ere he went to the spring, But he stared, for the snow was all stained as with blood; And remnants that seemed of a human thing, To which fluttering tatters appeared to cling, On the paw-printed snow had been dragged here and there, While the carrion birds rose with a flapping of wings. And the anchorite gave it a long dull stare; Then he thought: this thing is some new-laid snare Of the wily old Fiend; but he wastes his pains, For I am as cunning, and take good care. And he passed on his way; and the strange re-remains Were borne off by the birds; while the dark red stains Were effaced next day by the thick-flaked snow, Which for many a week seemed, on mountains and plains, As if it would never cease deeper to grow. THE RAFT. He shook his head. “No, no,” he said, “a man Need neither be insane nor wholly bad Who does that kind of thing. I say again, That there are minutes in the lives of all When Satan seems to pass across the heart Just as a shadow flits across the path; And if it happen that we be possessed Of power in such minutes, woe betide Ourselves and others. Bring not yet the lamp, But let the twilight have its way; the fire Is light enough; I have a tale to tell, And care not, as I tell it, to be watched. My children, you shall hear what made me leave, Some fifty years ago, my native land, And seek this colony, then barely formed. I speak at last; for I am old, so old That human justice, even if it cared, Could scarce o'ertake me on the final brink. But human justice cares not; I am safe. All has been long forgotten in that land Whose very language I have long unlearned. I would to God I could forget as well A desperate shriek, which ever and anon Rings in my ears. Now listen. I was born In the Black Forest, on the Upper Murg, A noble torrent, which with rush and roar Fights its way out through many a fir-crowned gorge And rocky pass, till, with diminished strength And slackened pace, it falls into the Rhine. A noble torrent truly: not pale green With silvery shallows, like the rivers here, But with clear coppery gleamings and a grand Voluminous impulsion. Fast as light Across the rapids, down the watery slopes Swoop many rafts—long, narrow, supple— Which men with pikes, one standing at each end, Guide past projecting rocks, to right and left, With perilous dexterity. And then There are the shoots of timber. Once a year All that the ever-sounding axe has felled Of giant trunks for miles and miles around Stored in a mighty mountain reservoir Is hurled into the stream, and rushes down In one terrific and tumultuous race. Ten thousand struggling, rolling, tossing trunks Press like a routed army through the gorge, And, hampered by their number and the rocks, O'erride each other in their desperate flight, Sink, reappear, and sink o'erwhelmed once more; Crashing with splintery crunchings and a roar Like never-ending thunder. So for hours The furious rush continues, and the stream Appears alive with logs. Then by degrees The numbers thin, the crowd contends no more, And single stragglers, leaving far behind Their stranded comrades, gently make their way To distant saw-mills. On the lower Murg, At Ottenau and Gernsbach, where the deal Is stored and sold and floated down the Rhine To Rotterdam, the timber merchants drive A busy commerce—or at least they did; All may have altered. When I did the thing Which changed my life, and made me, like a thief, Desert the country, I was twenty-five. My father was the owner of a mill And well-to-do. We sawed a many plank. The heaps of sawdust in the wide mill yard Grew year by year, the income keeping pace; For sawing is a profitable trade, With small fatigue: the water does the work. I had obtained the liking of a girl, The daughter of a miller higher up, And we were to be married. All men thought That I was over lucky, as my bride Was heiress to her father's mill, and I Would thus inherit two. As I have said, I had a deal of leisure—far too much. My uncle was a ranger of the Duke's; He gave me shooting in the neighbouring hills, And many a roebuck fell beneath my gun. And then I left the fish but little peace. The fish abounded in the shallow runs; You saw the greyling turning on their sides In shoals, like flashing mirrors, and the trout, Large, yellow-bellied trout, leapt at the flies By scores at dusk. It was an August night— Warm, moonlit, still, and breezeless. I had spent The evening at the miller's, and had met, On my way home, a village chum, with whom, Before we parted company, I took A glass of spirits at the village inn. I fear it was not much: I say I fear, Because each single drop that I can plead, When I shall answer for that evening's work, Will be of value at the bar of Heaven. O God Almighty! would I had gone home And sought my bed as usual! But instead The evil powers which obstruct our fate Made me pass on along the riverside, And seek a certain spot, there to rebait Some night-lines which I'd sunk the day before. It was a quiet pool, in which a raft Would sometimes moor and wait for break of day Before it crossed a longish stretch of stream Of ticklish navigation just beyond, Where long, dark slopes of water, which were split By tooth-like points, sucked down the rafts like straws, And called for proven skill, for ready wits, And for good light. Woe to the luckless raft Which lacking these passed in: its fate was sealed. Well, to resume. I reached the shallow pool Above the entrance of the gorge—the place Where I had laid the night-lines; there I found What I had not expected on that night, A raft, with men asleep; three lay curled up, While, in the middle of the raft, a sort Of little cabin served, perhaps, to shield Women or children from the dew; the poles With which they steered the raft were on the bank, Together with an axe; and by ill luck The raft was moored upon the very spot Where I had sunk the night-lines. What to do? The men were fast asleep; the river's roar, Monotonous and ceaseless, drowned my step. I bared my arm, and tried to find the lines Beneath the raft; it was of no avail; Then with the axe I tried to fish them up, But with no more success. Then by the raft I sat me down. I think my mind at first Was with the lines; then by degrees my thoughts Passed to the sleeping men, on whom my eyes Mechanically rested; and I thought How wondrously unconscious were these men Of my existence and my presence there; In what security they slept; while I Was moving, watching, thinking not two yards From where they lay. Something like A sense of power over them began to grow Upon me as I looked. And then it was That Satan's shadow passed across my heart: Together with the power came the wish To play them, in their false security, A sort of monster trick. The single rope Which held the raft was close beside my knee, The axe within my hand. Within myself I heard a voice which seemed to say, “Cut it, and send them spinning. Cut it quick. Thou hast enormous power in thy hands; Thou need'st but raise a finger. What, afraid? They are unconscious: see how sound they sleep, The careless fools. On thee alone depends A mighty wakening. Never will these hills Have seen so great a scamper. Cut it quick; Cut it, I say!” And with a single stroke I cut the tether, and I pushed the raft. It drifted slowly out into the light And left me in the shadow. Suddenly The current caught it, swung it sharply round, So that it struck a rock, and off it shot. There was a shout of men, a woman's shriek, Some figures flitted wildly to and fro upon it As it vanished. I was free To find my lines at leisure. But I stood Upon the bank and trembled. Long I looked Adown the stream, and tried to see and hear; But all was hushed except the water's roar, Monotonous and ceaseless. Then I turned, And, like a man who bears a crushing weight Which may not be set down, and who succeeds Only by rapid staggering straight ahead In reaching to his goal, I staggered home, Crushed and pushed forward and deprived of thought By the great weight of crime which was to rest Upon my head until I reached the grave. What roundabout untrodden path I took I have no notion, nor how long I walked: Next day I found red clay upon my clothes, And there was none for miles. And yet I doubt If what I felt in that first great recoil Was what you call remorse; what crushed my soul Was not the horror of the new-done thing, But its enormity: I was as yet A culprit, not a criminal, and felt Responsible to men, and not to God. Whether or not I slept I cannot tell. I think I must have slept, for I have heard That the first sleep of murderers is deep. A sudden crime exhausts. 'Tis later on, When Fear begins to sit beside your bed, And makes a danger of each sound of night, And at each moment twitches you and cries, “Awake! awake! they come!” 'Tis later on, When from behind your pillow sharp remorse Whispers, “Not yet to sleep, not yet, not yet!” And fills you with self-horror, that you hear The weary striking of the tardy hours, And pray for dawn. I think that when I woke And slowly dressed I had alone a sense That a misfortune had o'ertaken me, that now I had an awful secret to preserve, And that my life was changed. The daily hum, The clatter, and the sawing of the mill, The cackling of the poultry, and the song Of lighter-hearted neighbours, hurt my ear. Then thought began, and I surveyed the deed, But only as we measure the extent Of some great accident. Beyond a doubt Whoever passed the rapids unprepared (Even supposing that the raft should stick, And not be shivered by repeated shocks), Would be swung off or washed away at once. Below the rapids, both to right and left, The banks were high and rocky: no escape. An ugly job, a very ugly job, And inconceivable. But it was done. What most was to be feared was that my looks, When men began to talk, would let it out, And then I prayed an impious prayer to God, That this event might vanish and be lost, Just as the raft had vanished into night; That none might seek or mourn, and that the flood Into whose awful keeping I had given These unknown men and women in their sleep Might be for ever dumb. I heard a step: It was my father bidding me get up, And seek a distant village, down the stream, To settle some transaction for the mill. Down stream! I thought—Oh not for worlds down stream! But he insisted, and I feared to rouse Suspicion by refusal; so I went. The road, at first, was not along the bank, It met it only nearly two miles off Below the rapids, when both road and stream Passed through a gorge. On entering this gorge There fell upon my heart, I know not why, Together with the shadow of the place, A sudden fear: I feared to be alone With this dark river, even as a man May fear to be alone with one whose hand For price of gold had served him over well. The aspect of the gorge was sinister, The road and river both were tightly squeezed To half their width, in Nature's rocky gripe: A sunless home of echoes, where you saw, On looking up, a narrow strip of sky, On which the kites, which circled round and round, Were sharply printed. Rapid, deep, and black, The stream, between two cruel walls of rock, Formed whirling pools, and ever and anon Rolled some huge root, which in the distant gloom Looked like a drowning wretch that none could help. I stopped in doubt; but to retrace my steps Was dangerous; and so I hurried on, Not looking at the river by my side. Half through the gorge, just where it made a bend, The banks were less abrupt; some ridge-like rocks Ran out into the water, shelving down To meet the current. On the first of these Lay something dark. I had to pass close by, And had to look; it was a human form; The body of a woman lately drowned. She lay half in, half out; the circling flood, Which still retained possession of her feet, Gave her strange tugs and twitches, and kept up A lapping and a flapping of her clothes Beyond all measure horrible. Her eyes, Wide open like her mouth, seemed fixed on mine, Drawing me onwards by resistless force. She seemed to be still young—thirty at most. I dared not turn, and yet I dared not pass; At last I passed her quickly, and I fled; And as I fled I shrank as one pursued Who feels a hand descending on his back. I seemed to feel at every step I took Her clammy hand upon me, and to hear Her ever louder and more threatening voice Claim back her stolen life. Beyond the gorge There was a little village, where I heard That fragments of a raft had floated down, And that the body of a man, fresh drowned, Had just been found. I dared not let them know What I myself had seen upon the rock, Lest they should make me lead them to the spot. They'll find the body soon enough, I thought. Not all the riches that the world contained Would have induced me, quaking still with fear, To face that sight or pass that gorge again; And when the business which I had to do Was settled (how I did it Heaven knows), And I returned, it was by rugged paths, Which passed not near the river, but which went Across the fir-clad mountains. One by one The bodies were recovered; they were six: Three men, two women, and a little girl. All went to see them, I alone held back. And soon a rumour spread from door to door That the catastrophe was not the work Of accident; that where the raft had moored, And where the poles were lying with an axe, A bit of rope, sharp severed, had been found, Which tallied with another severed rope, Still dangling from a piece of shivered raft Upon the rocks. But who had done the deed? There was no evidence, and I was safe. If altered looks and habits could convict, I think you might have hung me; for in truth Whate'er I was, I was no hypocrite; And great as was the need, I hid but ill The gloom of guilt. To smile and seem at ease And live as usual was beyond my strength; I held aloof from all my village friends; As you may think, I left the trout in peace; And if, at times, I still would take my gun And wander in the hills, it was because It took me from the river. I was changed. And yet the neighbours, strange as it may seem, Had no suspicion; men are sometimes blind. One person only, almost from the first, Suspected me, and that was my betrothed. I saw it, and I writhed. When once or twice The raft was spoken of, I caught her eye Rest on me for one moment in a way That made me turn aside; and when anon She told me that the match was broken off, I bowed my head, although I loved her still, And asked no explanation. Oh God's hand Was heavy on me then, and I believe, By all that is most holy upon earth, That those whom I had hurried unprepared Into destruction were as well avenged As if the Law had held me in its gripe. Nay, there were moments when the Law's revenge Seemed lighter in the balance; and the dread Of heaping shame upon my father's home Alone withheld me, hounded by remorse, From giving myself up; and there were times (I shudder at the memory) when the stream, Desisting from its old accusing roar, Made wild seductive music in my ears And lured me to its brink. Then, bending o'er Some dark and whirling pool, about to leap, A hideous fear would seize me that the corpse Of the drowned woman might be in its depth Awaiting my embrace. Oh, I repeat, God's hand was heavy on me. When, at night, Great storms would shake the hills, and dazzling shafts Would fall with rattling simultaneous crash Of thunder near the mill, and make it quake Even to its foundations, I would start And, cowering like a craven in my bed, Would think, “It is the messenger of God Who seeks me in the darkness.” Such a life, Had it gone on much longer, would have led Either to madness or to further crime. There came a moment when I felt that nought Could save me but departure and a life Of all engrossing enterprise. And so, Within six months of that most fatal night, And unconvicted, save by God above, I fled my country like a hunted thief, Without a blessing or a farewell wish, Nor have I seen it since. For fifty years, Out here beyond the ocean, I have lived A life of work, acquiring by degrees Both wealth and influence; and have obtained With bitter satisfaction the respect Of men unstained by crime; and I believe That what a man can do to purchase back His self-respect and win a smile from Heaven I have not left undone. But the schools And all the hospitals which I could found Would not bring back again the dead to life. And, like the captives who in former days Were fettered to a heavy cannon ball, Which, if they wished to move from place to place, They had to raise and carry, I am chained To one great load of guilt; the cannon ball Which I have dragged through life has been unseen; But not the less immense has been its weight. ON A TUSCAN ROAD. A SKETCH. Now the white bullocks, in need of no goad, Homeward, at sunset, are coming from tillage; Blithely the labourer carries his load; Creaking and swaying, the wain blocks the road Nearing the village. Slowly the sunset departs from the shrine Close to the road, but still touches the fountain; Fewer are those who pass by with a sign; Dark grow the maize and the hemp and the vine, Blue is the mountain. Foxglove and wallflowers cling to the stone Over the lamp of the shrine that is crumbling; Twilight is falling; the landscape is lone; Save at the grating, where lingers a crone Piously mumbling. Over the valley there creepeth a chill; Slowly, far off, dies the bird's song of gladness; Louder the frogs, with monotonous trill, Croak in the rivulets, seeming to fill Nature with sadness. Then with the mournful and tremulous croak, Even as night by degrees is unrolling Over the lonely plantations her cloak, Mingles a knell of lugubrious stroke Distantly tolling. Suddenly priest-carried tapers appear, Faint in the twilight; their business seems holy; Men who support on their shoulders a bier, Covered with gold and with velvet, draw near Through the corn, slowly Who is the mortal who, freed from his woes, Wends with such trappings from out of the present? Who is the one who so sumptuously goes Out of the reach of his friends or his foes? Only a peasant. Only a peasant, whom peasants are now, After a harvest day, going to render Back to the earth, tilled with sweat of his brow, Decking his bier with a little cheap show, Villager's splendour. Slowly the tapers, with flickering light, Pass, reappear, and are lost in the distance; While, overhead, in the gathering night Twinkling, the stars grow more countless and bright, Taking consistence. Still, for a while, tolls the funeral bell, Breaking the silence of fields that are lonely; Then the frogs' croak, with its tremulous swell, Rising again in the place of the knell, Breaketh it only. THE MANDOLIN. A.D. 1559. Sit nearer to my bed. Have I been rambling? I can ill command The sequence of my thoughts, though words come fast. A fire is in my head And in my veins, like hell's own flame fast fanned. No sleep for eighty nights. It cannot last. The Pope ere long, perhaps ere close of day, Will have a scarlet hat to give away. Good priest, dost hear a sound, A faint far sound as of a mandolin? Thou hearest nought? Well, well; it matters not. I, who was to be crowned At the next Conclave! I was safe to win; And t'will be soon: Caraffa's step has got So tottering. O God, that I should miss The prize within my grasp and end like this! Three little months ago What Cardinal was so robust as I? And now the rings drop off my fingers lean! I have a deadly foe Who steals away my life till I shall die, A foe whom well I know, though all unseen, Unseizable, unstrikable; he lurks Ever at hand, and my destruction works. Thou thinkest I am mad? Not mad, no, no; but kept awake to death, And sent by daily inches into hell. Slow starving were less bad Or measured poison, or the hard-drawn breath And shrivelling muscles of a wasting spell. I tell thee, Father, I've been months awake, Spent with the thirst that sleep alone can slake. O holy, holy Sleep, Thou sweet but over-frightenable power! Thou, whom a tinkle scares or whispered word; Return, return and creep Over my sense, and in this final hour Lay on my lids the kiss so long deferred. But ah, it may not be; and I shall die Awake, I know; the foe is hovering nigh. Attend; I'll tell thee all: I tried to steal his life; and, in return, Night after night he steals my sleep away. Oh, I would slowly maul His body with the pincers, or would burn His limbs upon red embers, or would flay The skin from off him slowly, if he fell Into my hands, though I should sicken hell. The mischief all began With Claudia, whom thou knewest, my own niece, My dowered ward brought up in my own home. I had an old pet plan That she should wed Duke Philip, and increase The number of my partisans in Rome. Oh they were matched; for he had rank and power, And she rare beauty and a princely dower. With infinite delight I saw her beauty come, and watched its growth With greater rapture than a miser knows, Who in the silent night Counts up his growing treasure, and is loth To close the lid, and seek his lone repose. And long before her beauty was full-blown Men called her worthy of a ducal crown. But as her beauty grew Her lip would often curl, her brow contract, With ominous impatience of control; The least compulsion drew Rebellious answers; all respect she lacked; The spirit of resistance filled her soul: She took not to Duke Philip, as the year For marriage neared; and I begun to fear. Give me again to drink: There is a fierce excitement in my brain, And speech relieves me; but my strength sinks fast, The end is near, I think. And I would tell thee all, that not in vain May be thy absolution at the last. Where was it I had got? I lose the thread Of thought at times, and know not what I've said. Ay, now I recollect. There was a man who hung about me ever, One Hannibal Petroni, bastard born, Whom I did half suspect Of making love to Claudia. He was clever, And had the arts and ways which should adorn A better birth; but from the first I hated His very sight, and hatred ne'er abated. He played with rare, rare skill Upon the mandolin; his wrist was stronger Than that of any player I have known; And with his quivering quill He could sustain the thrilling high notes longer Than others could; and drew a voice-like tone Of unexampled clearness from the wire, Which often made me, while I loathed, admire. For 'tis wondrous thing The mandolin, when played with cunning hand, And charms the nerves till pleasures grows too sharp; Now mimicking the string Of a guitar, now aping at command The viol or the weird Æolian harp, The sound now tinkles, now vibrates, now comes Faint, thin, and threadlike; 'tis a gnat that hums. And he would often come On breezeless, moonlit nights of May and June, And play beneath these windows, or quite near, When every sound in Rome Had died away; and I abhorred his tune, For well I knew it was for Claudia's ear; And I would pace my chamber while he played And, in my heart, curse moon and serenade. How came this thing about? My mind grows hazy and my temples swell. Give me more drink! Oh, I remember now. One morning I found out That they were corresponding—letters fell Into my hands. It was a crushing blow; My plans were crumbling. In my fear and wrath I said, “Why wait? Remove him from thy path.” It's easy here in Rome, Provided you are liberal with the price; The willing Tiber sweeps all trace away. Yet ere I sent him home To heaven or hell, I think I warned him twice To go his way; but he preferred to stay. He braved me in his rashness, and I said, ‘Let his destruction be on his own head.” When Claudia learnt his death, What a young tigress! I can see her now, With eyes illumined by a haggard flame, And feel her withering breath, As in a hissing, never-ending flow She poured her awful curses on my name. 'Twas well I kept her close; for she had proofs And would have howled them from the very roofs. It is an ugly tale, And must be told; but what was I to do? I wanted peace not war; but one by one I saw my efforts fail. She was unmanageable, and she drew Her fate upon herself—aye, she alone. I placed her in a convent, where they tried All means in vain. She spurned her food and died. But he, the cause of all, I know not how, has risen from the dead, And takes my life by stealing sleep away. No sooner do I fall Asleep each night, than, creeping light of tread Beneath my window, he begins to play. How well I know his touch! It takes my life Less quickly but more surely than the knife. Now 'tis a rapid burst Of high and brilliant melody, which ceases As soon as it has waked me with a leap. And now a sound, at first As faint as a gnat's humming, which increases And creeps between the folded thoughts of sleep, Tickling the brain, and keeping in suspence Through night's long hours the o'er-excited sense. Oh! I have placed my spes All round the house, and offered huge rewards To any that may see him; but in vain. The cunning rogue defies The best-laid plan, and fears nor troops nor swords; But, scarce my eyes are closed, begins again His artful serenade. Oh, he is sly! And lovest to fool the watchman and the spy. But I should find a way To catch him yet, if my retainers had A little faith and helped me as they ought. I overheard one say, “Mark me, the cardinal is going mad; He hears a mandolin where there is nought.” Ay, that's Petroni's skill. He sends the sound Straight to my ear, unheard by those around! Once, on a moonlit night, I caught a glimpse of him; the villain sat Beneath my window on the garden-wall; And, in the silvery light, I saw his mandolin. Then, like a cat, I crept downstairs, with fierce intent to fall Upon and throttle him. I made a rush And seized him by the throat. It was a bush. But I have talked o'ermuch; And something like a drowsiness descends Upon my eyelids with a languid weight. Oh, would it were the touch Of sweet, returning sleep, to make amends For long desertion, ere it be too late! My fevered pulse grows calm; my heated brow Aches less and less, and throbs no longer now. O sleep, O gentle sleep! I feel thee near; thou hast returned at last. It was that draught of soothing hellebore. I feel sweet slumber creep Across each aching sense, as in the past, And consciousness is fading more and more. I care not to awake again; let death, Whenever sleep shall leave me, take my breath. Give ear! give ear! give ear! I hear him; he is coming; it is he! He plays triumphant strains, faint, far away. Ye fools, do ye not hear? Oh, we shall catch him yet, and you shall see A year of hell compressed into a day. Bring me my clothes, and help me out of bed. Oh, I can stand; I'm weak, but not yet dead. Bring me my scarlet cloak And scarlet stockings. No, they're dyed with blood. Oh, you may laugh! but it's beyond a doubt The dyer's let them soak, In every street, in murder-reddened mud; It is the only dye which won't wash out. The Pope is dead; Caraffa's dead at last. I'm wanted at the conclave: dress me fast. Who dares to hold me down? I'm papable. By noon we must convene; Bring me my clothes, and help me quick to rise. When I've the triple crown Safe on my head, I'll sweep the cesspool clean. What's all that muttering? Speak out loud, ye spies! There's a conspiracy at work, I know, To keep me from the conclave—but I'll go. The Papacy is lost. Lost, wholly lost! The Papal keys, all black With rust and dirt, won't turn the lock of heaven. What's that? what's that? The Host? There's poison in the wafer—take it back! I'll spit it out! I'll rather die unshriven! Help, Claudia, help! Where's Claudia? Where's she fled? They're smothering me with pillows in my bed! A LETTER TO MISS A. MARY F. ROBINSON. A promise is the frailest thing I know: A very soap-bubble which rashness flings On whatsoever breeze may chance to blow; We watch it float, and in its iris-glow See fair precarious things. And you have promised to return and spend A while with us ere Tuscan leaves be sere; Oh break your promise not, nor grieve a friend To whom the Fates but little pleasure send, I ween, from year to year. Come with the dying summer's golden mist; Come with the ripeness of the autumn air; Come when the sun aweary shall desist, And when all Nature, long too fiercely kissed, Lies weak, but not less fair. Come when no more the endless noontide creeps, And each hot tile-roof tremulously steams; Come when no more the shrill cicala keeps Sawing the empty air, and he who sleeps Abhors it through his dreams. Come when no more the vesper bell shall rouse The inmates of each sun-entranced abode; And when no more the peasant shades with boughs His slow, white oxen's fly-tormented brows, Upon the glaring road. Come when the hungry yellow wasp forestalls The vintager, and mars the prosperous grape; And when the vine leaves on the trellised walls Take hectic patches ere the bunches fall In hods of conic shape. Come when the splitting wrapper of the maize The massive golden lump no more can hold; And when the meanest cottage front displays A tapestry of ingots, which outweighs All Eldorado's gold. Come when the chestnut drops with rustling sound, Through scanty leaves, and bursts its bristly husk Just at your feet upon the mossy ground, Where fragrant ferns and flowers wild abound And scent the early dusk. Oh, they are sweet, those chestnut woods where never My foot, alas, can trample down the moss— Those woods where others, full of health, may sever The ferny stems, while I, debarred for ever, Hold all, save strength, as dross. The old, old chestnut-trees, whose trunks uncouth, All gray with lichen and of monstrous girth, Are hollowed out, and gnawed by each year's tooth, Have bright green leaves, like impulses of youth Which in old hearts take birth. They cover the innumerable spurs Of Apennine, the mighty boulders crowned, By village strongholds, walled, and black with years, And penetrate the gullies where one hears The storm-born torrents bound. Which seek the limpid Lima, as it brings Its waters to the Serchio, green and bright, Beneath black bridges where the wall-flower clings, And where the mirrored kingfisher oft wings His straight and rapid flight. And you will see, as through an open door, Where Serchio's gorges suddenly expand; The Garfagnana rich with autumn's store, Where Ariosto held command of yore— A tract of faery land. And watch the stream which, as the sun declines, Winds like a glistening snake whose motion flags Through ripeness-scented fields and reeds and vines, Dividing from the cloud-capped Apennines Carrara's marble crags. But there are times, in later autumn's rains, When that same stream is like no glistening snake, But like a lion tawny flanked, which gains In strength each moment, and whose roar retains The anxious boor awake. Then in its wrath, resistless Serchio tears Through gorge and valley, threatening many a home; Shaking with watery claws the great stone piers Of each old bridge, against whose strength it rears With mane of muddy foam. A desperate hug, which sometimes rips asunder The stoutest arch, though deep the piles be driven; When, with a crack, which fills the hills with wonder, The masonry, out-thundering the thunder, Hurls up the flood to heaven. But I must stop; or else I shall defeat My only object, to attract you here; And at the thought that you perhaps may meet A sudden watery end, you will retreat Elsewhere in haste and fear. Be not afraid; but simply brush away The picture I have held before your eyes. I told you once that you were like a ray Of sunshine; and so long as sunshine stay The river will not rise. AN ELEGY ON THE DEATH OF A LADY Who Died at Florence February 29, 1880. Behold, behold, the joyous spring has come— The spring which she has missed. On every side The mighty wave of sap is bubbling up From deepest rootlet to the topmost twig; On every side the sunny Tuscan fields Are full of large wild tulips, red as flame; The meadows full of daffodils; the woods Are full of rustling, warbling, chirping sounds; The silver poplars fill the air with down, Which floating slowly settles on the path In drifts of mimic snow, while earthy scents Proclaim a recent shower: all is youth And freshness now. But spring, triumphant spring, Which means the strength and jubilee of earth, Means also the incalculable deaths Of all the generations that have been Since life first sprouted on this rocky ball, From insects up to kings. To make this spring The busy populations came and went Of now forgotten cities; and the hosts Of loud exulting conquerors swept by To glory and oblivion, and the whole Of what we call the Past manured the world. And so she too has gone to form a part Of some fair future spring. For I admit No other resurrection: of the earth We mortals are, and to her lap return, Small portions of the ever-shifting whole, Detached, made men, with mean or noble shapes, With mean or noble minds, as fleeting things As are the clouds which rise from out the sea, Take varied forms, are wafted by the winds, Are dull, or glow superbly, and anon Pass off from the horizon, summoned back By their eternal parent. Even so Is she we mourn for, after some brief days Of frail existence and a vivid glow Of noble aspiration, mixed again With elemental Nature: shall we curse Great Mother Earth who calleth back her child? Oh if a fair and gifted human thing Pursued its way, as feelingless and cold As does the cloud which streaks the summer sky, And in its progress through these earthly scenes Knew nought of pain, of undeserved reproach, Of misappreciation, and of hopes Rough trodden underfoot; if it were nought Except a fair appearance sent to charm, And then to vanish, Fate were free from guilt; But ere her birth, nay, ere all years began, The cruel Power which we ne'er behold Affianced her to strong and bitter Death; Decreed a princely dowry of rare gifts And life-endearing instincts, and ordained That in her innocent and tender frame A seed of slow disease should lurk unseen Till early womanhood, to make the gifts Derision, dust. And so it came to pass. Her eye grew lustrous, thin and white her hand, As if some enemy, with muttered spells, Were letting slowly melt before the fire Her effigy in wax: while round and round In ever closer circles hovered Death. And when at last he seized her by the wrist, And bade her come, she cried, “Not yet, not yet! It is too soon to die. Not in the spring— Not when fresh life is poured into the world In measureless abundance.” But in vain. There was small mercy in the God who framed This self-destructive Nature, this great world Which feeds upon itself, and when 'twas made Departed none knows whither, for all time; The Absentee to whom all living things Pay hourly rent in multifarious aches; Who, ere he left, made never-changing laws; Linked Health to Madness, Beauty to Disease, And Genius to Starvation; mingling Good With Evil in a horrible alloy; Now welding them together, as the steel And gold are welded in an Indian blade, Into a beautiful and deadly thing; Now choking good with evil sickeningly In foul contamination, like a pearl Imbedded in the mire; and by a strange And cynical provision, tying up With each great wrong a partial remedy, Perchance opposing to the million sobs Of innocents a tear in pity shed; Or giving man, when doomed to die, The vain conceit of immortality. Death underlies all Nature. See the corn Which stands and ripens in the evening sun, With here and there a poppy in its midst; And cottages beyond, while nought is heard Except the grasshopper and distant shouts Of home-returning children. Who shall say Here, never was a battle lost or won; Here, nought was ever sickled in its strength Except the grain; nought ever trampled down Except the stubble; here no steel has gleamed Except the shining ploughshare? Or, again, Look out upon the sea when all is calm, When o'er the vast extent of lazy blue At most a ripple hovers; when the shore Looks dreamy in the distance, and the sails Of fishing boats are listless: would ye care If that calm sea could be one moment drained, To see the plains and valleys where the ribs Of ships and men are lying, strewn as thick As leaves in autumn woods? Nay, this same breeze Which softly fans the cheek and rocks the buds And strews the almond blossoms on the grass Like flakes of rosy snow, has been at times The all-pervading messenger of death, And, coming laden with the scents of spring, Has thinned the streets of cities. Nature teems With death in every shape—with mighty wars And isolated pinings; with the loud And far-trumped death of heroes, and the still And unobtrusive endings of the poor; The unresisted slaughter of dumb brutes, The rapid tragedies of insect life, The slow decline of flowers; and behold, Beside these deaths, innumerable births, Triumphant renovation, fierce increase, And life for ever winning in the race With silent-footed Death. Behold all round Start up new crops of heroes and new crops Of beauties for the scythe, who for a while Overtop the mass, the nameless, fameless mass, As countless as the new-created swarms Of whirling midges. But to be a mind As noble as was hers, one so akin To those that leave imperishable works; To live awhile upon that purer food, To breathe that purer air, to feel as they, And then be mingled wholly and at once With the forgotten, with the nameless dead; 'Tis hard, 'tis hard! And yet, why ask for more? Is't not enough to be a noble thing Beneath the sun which warms us? Must we live As well on dusty bookshelves and be great? Oh, let not any turn away in scorn From such a grave as this, and ask for fame. She was of those for whom the great exist, She was of those whose wise, sincere delight Out-values all the loud, misplaced applause Of fickle generations, and compels The lasting recognition of the world. She trod not on the stage where Genius stands In presence of the vulgar, but sat high Above both crowd and actors, and enjoyed. And now beneath these Tuscan hills she lies Where friendly sunbeams kiss away the tears Which every passing April cloud lets fall Upon her grave. All through the day Such tears and kisses and the song of birds Have been the gift of spring—the spring she missed. But now the sun is low: before it leaves It sends a slanting ray to kiss the stone. Then pearly twilight settles over all; The cypresses grow black, the air grows chill, The mighty dome of Florence stands distinct, With Giotto's belfry near it, on the sky. Then by degrees they mingle with the night, Like fading ghosts. The city's hum is hushed, And through the dusk there comes the mellow boom Of a great bell, tolled slowly, which brings home A sense of peace in mutability. SONNETS. SOULAC. A lone square house, all time-stained, used to stand Upon the French west coast, where sparse pines keep Their footing ill, while battling sea winds sweep The hillocks of untilled and restless sand. A house? it was the belfry, Norman-planned Of long-lost Soulac's minster, buried deep In sand, which Ocean never ceased to heap For centuries, encroaching on the land. All else was gone. Oh is not such the fate That overtakes the rich and stately pile Which, arch on arch, our youthful hopes create? The Real slowly clogs it, nave and aisle; The arches crash; and we are glad if, late, Some humble vestige shelters us awhile. WAIFS OF TIME. When some good ship has long ago been wrecked, And the repentant waves have long since laid Upon the beach the booty which they made, And years have passed, and men no more expect, The sea will sometimes suddenly eject A solitary waif, defaced, decayed, On which in graven letters is displayed The old ship's name which few can recollect. So, ever and anon, the mighty sea Which we call Time casts up upon our strand Some splendid waif of Greek antiquity. A headless god or Faun with shattered hand, From Art's great wreck is suddenly set free, And stands before us all, serene and grand. WINTER. The month is come when Nature may display Her frosty jewelry in all men's eyes; And when the wind which through the brushwood sighs Brings down her brilliants in a sparkling spray. Like spots of blood upon the snowstrewn way The crimson berries lie, the robins' prize; While in the leafless woods the poor man tries To find some faggots for the bitter day. On every sleeping pool the winter fits With unseen hand a strong and glassy lid; The fish all quaking down below are hid, As overhead the circling skater flits. While hoary Christmas at his banquet sits, Where all whom hunger pinches not are bid. LIFE'S GAME. Life's Evil Genius with the sunless wing And our white Guardian Angel sit and play Their silent game of skill from day to day, Where thoughts are pawns, and deeds are queens and kings. And every move on that strange chessboard brings Some change in us—in what we do or say; Till with our life the winner sweeps The last few pawns to which his rival clings. We seem permitted, ever and anon, To catch a glimpse of that great fatal game By which our soul shall be or lost or won. We watch one move, then turn away in shame; But though we lack the courage to look on, The game goes on without us all the same. LOST YEARS. My boyhood went: it went as went the trace Left by the pony's hoof upon the sand; It fled as fled the stream sought rod in hand; It vanished as the ice on the pond's face. Then went my youth; it went where went the lights Of crowded ball-rooms at the dawn's advance; It died as died the echoes of the dance; It went where go all sorry wasted nights. And now my manhood goes where goes the song Of pent-up bird, the cry of crippled things; It goes where goes the day that unused dies. The cage is narrow and the bars are strong At which my restless spirit beats its wings, While round me stretch immeasurable skies</field>
   </doc>
</add>