<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Alexander, Cecil Frances, 1818-1895</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Alexander, Cecil Frances, 1818-1895</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">alexander cecil frances 1818 1895</field>
      <field name="author_text">Alexander, Cecil Frances, 1818-1895</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1880's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.1632.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1888</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466927</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Poems on Subjects in the Old Testament ; By Mrs C. F. Alexander</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Poems on Subjects in the Old Testament ; By Mrs C. F. Alexander</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poems on subjects in the old testament</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poems on subjects in the old testament</field>
      <field name="title_text">Poems on Subjects in the Old Testament ; By Mrs C. F. Alexander</field>
      <field name="year_display">1888</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1888</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1888</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466927&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466927&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Alexander, Cecil Frances, 1818-1895&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;alexander cecil frances 1818 1895&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Poems on Subjects in the Old Testament ; By Mrs C. F. Alexander&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poems on subjects in the old testament&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1888&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1888&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Alexander, Cecil Frances&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1818&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1895&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poems on Subjects in the Old Testament&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By Mrs C. F. Alexander&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;J. Masters and Co.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1888&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp1872&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;116 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poems on Subjects in the Old Testament&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By Mrs C. F. Alexander&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 135 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted; verse reproduced elsewhere in The English Poetry Full-text Database omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TO MY DEAR FATHER, FROM WHOSE POETICAL TASTE I MIGHT FEAR A MORE SEVERE JUDGMENT THAN I FEEL HIS AFFECTIONATE PARTIALITY WILL AWARD THEM, I DEDICATE THESE POEMS. C. F. ALEXANDER. Derg Lodge, February, 1854. THE CREATION. “Thus the Heavens and the earth were finished, and all the host of them.”—Gen. ii. I. Young heart, impatient of thy powers, Why wilt thou fret to know That knowledge comes with weary hours, And heavy step, and slow? That each thing great in its degree In toil and care begins, And no perfection here may be But that which labour wins? Perchance 'twas writ to do thee shame, That He Whom angels praise Paused o'er His fair creation's frame, And lingered six long days. His word at once had hung them there, Planet, and star, and sun;— Perchance to teach thee patient care, He made them one by one. Think how the great world silent lay, A void and formless place, God's Spirit brooding far away Over the water's face,— Till bursting on that darkness wide The glorious light had birth, And in her beauty and her pride, He made the fair young earth. Three days she hung all cold and still, Wrapp'd in that sunless light, No golden lustre on the hill, No silver moon at night. God made the sun, and in his ray Sprang flowers by stream and meadow, On all her heights the sunlight lay, And on her sward, the shadow.— The graceful moonbeams touched her sod With slanting silver bars, “Shouted for joy the sons of God, And sang the morning stars.” Slowly He wrought, and duly set All things above, below;— Wilt thou, His creature, chide and fret If thine advance be slow? Patience, and zeal, and toil He asks— Then let thine heart be strong, Nor weary of thy lowly tasks, Because the time is long. EDEN. “And the Lord God planted a garden eastward in Eden.” — Gen. ii. 8. Where is that garden of the Lord God planted Eastward in Eden in the days of old, Where the large blossoms and the fruits enchanted That filled the earliest tale our mothers told? Lingers it yet, kept by an Angel warden, Over the purple mountains far away— Untouched, since sinless Adam dressed the garden, And the Lord walked there in the cool of day? Nay, ask not—wherefore should our spirits venture Over the eastern hills—beyond the bars, Where the broad sun girt with his rosy cincture Comes burning up and darkens all the stars? Why should we wish o'er sea and desert going To find the vision true in some far land, To dwell beside the gate—and hear the flowing Of the great river with its golden sand? The font stands yet in many a church's portal, The prayers still echo round where we were made Heirs of an Eden beautiful, immortal, Where never serpent glided through the glade. There flows eternally the gifted river, Whose healing wave is as the crystal clear, There grows the tree of life that sheddeth never Its twelve bright fruits renewed twelve times a year. For us that cooling wave, for us the beauty Of that bright place that has nor sun, nor night, If but by Christ's dear grace, in love and duty, We walk below like children of the light. So may we dream of those invisible bowers, The water's tremulous flow, the flowery sod, Hopeful that Christ's new Eden shall be ours, The home of saints, the Paradise of God. THE TEMPTATION. “She took of the fruit thereof and did eat.” —Gen. iii. 6. “Then the devil leaveth Him.” —S. Matt. iv. II. It was in God's own garden-bowers, The sweetest spot earth ever knew, Eve met the serpent in the flowers— When soft as drops of honied dew, He poured the poisoned words untrue, That lost this world of ours. He said the golden fruit was good, He showed it pleasant to the eyes, He spake of knowledge by that food To make the daring spirit wise: In the full heart of Paradise, She pluck'd it where she stood. It was a wild unlovely place That fed no trees with fruitage crowned, Nor bore upon its barren face Bright blossoms shedding fragrance round, Where Satan erst the Saviour found Who raised our ruined race. In vain His soul with hunger tried He tempted in that lonely hour To make the bread of Heaven denied; In vain he showed earth's pomp and power, And prompted from the Temple tower The deed of daring pride. Him fleshly lusts might not ensnare, Nor gorgeous pomps with pleasure rife That seem to worldly eyes so fair; He heeded not the pride of life, But rose triumphant in the strife, And bruised the serpent there. Lord, by that threefold promise spoken, O'er the baptismal water bright, And by Thine own dear anguish token, We too are pledged to that stern fight. Look on us, help us with Thy might, Nor let our vows be broken. In all our paths the tempter strays, For each a separate snare he knows, The Eden of our happy days— The desert of our lonely woes— Thou that hast fought, and foiled our foes, Lead us in all our ways! CAIN AND ABEL. “And she conceived and bare Cain, and said, I have gotten a man from the Lord; and she again bare his brother Abel. ... Cain rose up against Abel his brother, and slew him.”—Gen. iv. 1, 2, 8. Deem not thine heart by household loves So duly filled, and guarded well, That wrath, and strife, and cruel hate, Shall never reach its charméd cell. Had ever earth a safer nook, Where love might hope to weave a crown Of flowers untouched by envy's breath, Nor by fierce passion trampled down; Than where in Eve's maternal bower, Two boys in rosy childhood lay, Learned love's first lesson from her eyes, And clasped her vesture in their play? The first two babes that ever watched The round sun rise 'twixt awe and mirth, The first whose laughter ever waked The echoes of this great old earth. Each dwelling in a world apart, That had no creature but the other, To share his sport or know his thought, And learning first the name of brother. Alas! full soon the red earth heard The brother's blood that cried to Heaven, And bore upon her shuddering breast The outcast from God's presence driven. Guard well thy spirit's inmost cell, Lest, when sweet love makes music there, Some little envious thought creep in, Untuning all its concord rare. And ask of Him on bended knee Whose love surpasseth brother's love, Whose Spirit filling all thy heart, Is tender as a brooding dove; That close He draw, and closer still, Each chord that kindred love endears, Nor let the strain thy childhood loved Forget to charm in after years. ENOCH. “And Enoch walked with God, and he was not, for God took him.”—Gen. v. 24. Hast thou not seen at break of day One only star the east adorning That never set, or paled its ray, But seemed to sink at once away Into the light of morning? From it, the sage no portent drew, It came to light no meteor fires, But silver shone the whole night through On hawthorn hedges steeped in dew, And quiet village spires. Like him of old who dwelt beneath The tents of patriarchal story, Who passed without the touch of death, Without dim eye, or failing breath, At once into God's glory:— The Patriarch of one simple spot, The sire of sons, and daughters lowly, And this the record of his lot, “He walked with God, and he was not,” For the Lord took him wholly. Like a child's voice in sacred song That trembling rises high and higher, Till lost at last, it peals along, Swelling the anthem sweet and strong Of great cathedral choir:— So year by year, and day by day In pastoral care, and household duty, He walked with God,—nor knew decay, But faded gently, rapt away Into His glorious beauty. There's many a household fair to see By woodland nook, or running river, Where children climb the parent's knee— O, that those homes like his might be Filled with God's presence ever! O, that our thoughts so heavenly were, Our hearts to Christ so fully given, That all our loves, and toil, and care, Might only lead us nearer there, Where He is set in Heaven. THE ARK. “And the ark went upon the face of the waters.”—Gen. vii. 18. Strange thoughts are thine, mysterious ark! A dreary path, a weary motion, A sound of waters falling dark, And all the world one shoreless ocean. Strange ship!—upon a marvellous sea, Without or helm, or compass driven, Fraught with a wondrous company, And lonely as the moon in Heaven. Still rocking to a restless force Of endless endless surges swelling, Upborne along thy silent course Above high hill, and human dwelling. Above the place where year by year Still toiled at his prophetic labour Unmoved by taunts the faithful seer; While sounds of song, and dance, and tabor, From all the mad earth round him came, And laughed in scorn her sons and daughters, Till—reared at last thy mighty frame— There rushed from Heaven th' avenging waters. But more than dread, or warning high, Comes with thy wondrous story blended, Home of the faithful! when the cry Of guilty earth to God ascended. A precious type to us thou art Of Christ's own Church, the safe and holy, The ark that bears within her heart The weak, and strong, the high, and lowly. And sweeter than thy haven wild Upon the purple mountain lying, When through her tears the young earth smiled Like babes that laugh amid their crying: O, sweeter far the haven nest Whereto our ark is ever riding, Though rocking to the world's unrest, And vexed by all her billows chiding. For upward, upward bears she still, And leaves below sin's pain and pleasure, Till, stranded on the Heavenly hill, She yield to Christ His ransomed treasure. THE DOVE. “But the dove—returned unto him into the ark.” —Gen. viii. 9. Bird with soft eye and snowy breast, Whose wild note every echo learns, The first to build thy woodland nest When early spring returns; Along the frost-bespangled lawn I love thy plaintive strain to hear, At breaking of the April dawn Ere yet the day is clear; From out the grove where snowdrop bells Spring underneath the leafless arch, And softly fall the rosy shells, That tip the tufted larch. The skylark's song hath more of fire, The thrush a sweeter note than thine, But none of all doth so inspire The soul with thoughts divine. For art not thou the blessed bird That went forth with the raven dark, When the decreasing waters stirred Around the stranded ark? He rushed along his own wild track; Thou, mindful of our human grief, Didst bear the weary prisoners back The hopeful olive leaf. And was not thine the form of love Wherein the Holy Ghost was shed, When breaking from the cloud above He touched the Saviour's Head? Type of God's grace! in many a fane We read that image pictured fair, Or traced upon the painted pane, Or carved in marble rare. And in our lowly churches yet, We seem to see those wings outspread When baby brows are duly wet, And holy words are said. All song is sweet in sky or grove, But for the blessed thoughts it brings Thy soft low murmur most I love, Bird of the silver wings! ABRAHAM'S CALL. “Get thee out from thy country, and from thy kindred, and come unto the land that I shall show thee.”—Acts vii. 3. Forth from his childhood's sunny home At God's command the Patriarch went; O'er burning sands he turned to roam, From where the wild acacia bent Above the well, whose waters lent A fairy greenness to the glade Around his father's summer-tent, From wild haunts where his youth had strayed, When on the feathery palm the silver moonlight played. To distant Canaan's fertile clime, First pilgrim to that holy land, Where mailéd knights in after time, And warrior kings of many a strand, And many a bold crusading band, Should come from homes beyond the sea, And palmer grey with staff in hand,— A simple herdsman journeyed he, And led his quiet flocks along the desert lea. What though for him, no pastoral nest Lay in those purple hills enisled, Nor spot whereon his foot might rest, Faith's vision on his spirit smiled Of vineyards dressed, and cities piled, Where countless as the bright stars driven, Unnumbered as the sea sand wild, The promised race his God had given, Should hold that favoured land in fief to highest Heaven. For this his pleasant place of birth Where great Euphrates' waters roar, He left—a pilgrim on the earth, A houseless stranger evermore, Nor turned again to that sweet shore, But still to distant Canaan pressed, And passed the burning desert o'er, Type of true faith—who first confessed, He had no country here, but sought a better rest. Christian, that better rest is thine! The land with milk and honey flowing, The land of Eshcol's purple vine, And Jordan's waters westward going, Was but a shadow dim, foreshowing, Beyond death's river dark and lone, The jasper wall like crystal glowing, The rainbow round about the throne— Arise, and hear the call that makes that land thine own! LOT AND SODOM. “And Lot lifted up his eyes, and beheld all the plain of Jordan that it was well watered everywhere, before the Lord destroyed Sodom and Gomorrah, even as the garden of the Lord.”—Gen. xiii. 10. By stately Sodom's palace walls The crimson rose is blushing bright, And silver sweet the Jordan falls Beside Gomorrah's marble halls, Where harp, and song, and festal calls Are sounding day and night. And lovely as a garden fair Lies blooming all the enchanted plain; The purple grapes hang heavy there, The flowers fling out a fragrance rare, And softly wave in perfumed air The fields of golden grain. The river's silver trump has found An answer in the heart of Lot; The lavish beauty breathing round, And those two sister cities crowned, The queens of that well watered ground, Allure him to the spot. Southward he turns from Abraham's tent— Ah venturous man! that could not hear Above the river's murmur sent, Above the town's wild merriment, The cry of sin and shame that went Up to God's patient ear: That dreamed not of the vengeance dire, When those two messengers of Heaven Should call the swift consuming fire, And drag him forth, most wretched sire, From that great city's funeral pyre, In awful mercy driven. O, Christian youth, baptized and blest, God has been merciful to thee, Let not thy soul with sinners rest, Nor make in Sodom's bowers thy nest, Nor choose the fairest, but the best, Thine earthly place to be. The world has songs of Sodom still, And if they needs must vex thy soul, Call God's good angels in to fill Thine home, and heart, and turn in will To Abraham on the eternal hill, Ere fires of judgment roll. A greater guest to thee hath come Than stood in Sodom's street by night— Sure when Christ's trump shall break the gloom O'er that salt sea, her people's tomb, For him shall be a heavier doom, Who sins to grace and light. ABRAHAM'S SACRIFICE. “Take now thy son, thine only son Isaac, whom thou lovest, and get thee into the land of Moriah, and offer him there for a burnt offering, upon one of the mountains which I will tell thee of.”— Gen. xxii. 2. Stood dark and still Moriah's mountain lone,— God's chosen place amid the heathen land— His altar of imperishable stone, Hewn by no mortal hand! Stood dark and still the solitary height— Nor girded then with palace-wall, and tower, Nor on its purple breast the temple white Laid like a marble flower! A deep stern silence held the mountain air; Nor Canaan's songs, nor Kedron's murmur wild Might reach so high; there only whispered there The Patriarch, and his child. The roe-deer hiding in the thicket near Heard a young voice that said, “I see the fire, The knife for sacrifice—the wood is here, Where is the lamb, my sire?” Thou that hast taught thine heart o'erfond to twine Round other heart its every living chord, Who canst not take thy treasure from its shrine, And give it to the Lord! And thou, whose wayward spirit will not learn To bear the little yoke that galls thy pride, Who canst not teach thy soul submission stern— Come to this mountain's side! See faithful Abraham lift his hand to slay The darling of his age, his promised son, See gentle Isaac give his life away Without one murmuring tone. Each high resolve, each shade of self-denial Hath here its type not meaningless, nor weak— The soul that nerves the martyr for his trial— The child's obedience meek. Here too, like murmur of a far off strain, Borne on long echoes through the silent hills, Shall come a shadowing of diviner pain, Till all thy bosom thrills. A thought of Him Who clomb that mountain's face, Bearing with patient arm the cruel wood, True victim Lamb, true Son of Abraham's race, Who won thee with His Blood! He of His grace teach us the path to prove That led His saints and martyrs up to God— He give us Abraham's faith, and Isaac's love, And guide us where they trod. ISAAC AND REBEKAH. “And Isaac brought her into his mother Sarah's tent, and he took Rebekah, and she became his wife.”—Gen. xxiv. 67. I read in God's great holy book The tale of Isaac's bridal tent; And like the murmur of a brook, (That brings to “one in city pent” Gleams of the country far away, Of blossomed orchards in their glory, And clover fields, and scented hay,) Were thoughts that came with that sweet story;— Till I was rapt into a dream Of olden days, and eastern clime, Wherein I saw, (or so did seem) The men of Patriarchal time, The pastoral chiefs who spake with God, The veiléd maid, the comely wife, The rich flocks scattered o'er the sod, And all the charms of tented life. The desert's burning breath I felt, I heard the camel's tinkling bell; And when the faithful servant knelt At even by the city well, I saw his young lord's destined bride— A damsel very fair, and young— Come tripping to the water side, Her pitcher on her shoulder slung. I marked his wonder, as the dew She scattered round the fountain's brink, While in her courteous haste she drew And gave the weary camels drink. I watched what blushes bright and warm To cheek and brow did instant spring, When on the maiden's delicate arm He hung the heavy golden ring. I saw the feast of welcome spread, While loud he praised his master's Lord; I heard how well the wooing sped, How gentle was the kinsman's word, Content—since God had willed it so, That hand and heart the maid hath given, And when she whispered, “I will go,” They blessed her with the wealth of heaven. Another eve—and Hebron lay All flooded with a tender light— The last tints of a rosy ray That lingers somewhere out of sight,— What time, the long day's labour done, Came Isaac from the green well-side Out in the quiet fields alone To meditate at eventide. He saw afar the dust uprise, The camel-driver's song he heard; But who is she that lifts her eyes, Then hides them, like a frightened bird? A trembling thing with covered face Into his mother's tent he led, And set her there, in Sarah's place, And loved her, and was comforted. Sure such a tale, so sweet, so fair, Around our hearts should linger long, Familiar as a household air, And soothing as a cradle song. And we may learn of their meek ways, Their trustful faith in heaven above, Their calm of unambitious days, Their simple truth, and modest love. ISAAC IN THE FIELD. “And Isaac went out to meditate in the field at eventide.” —Gen. xxiv. 63. The fields are rich with golden corn, The fields are bright with flowers; How fair the spangled dew of morn, The blossom of the hedgerow thorn, The woodbine in her bowers! Full oft our feet have brushed away Those drops of diamond light, Full oft we've plucked the blossomed May And watched the sun's last crimson ray Fade softly into night. What thoughts were ours, and whither sent Beneath the sunset heaven? Say, were they good, as his who went Forth from his Patriarchal tent To meditate at even? When, as the light did sudden fade, Above his eastern home, Beside the well for Hagar made, Compare Gen. xxiv. 62 with xvi. 14. And through the palm tree's feathery shade, He saw Rebekah come. So should our walks a blessing bring Out in the meadows near, And we might meet as fair a thing As she who bore the golden ring, And dried the Patriarch's tear. Some blesséd thought might find us there Of what our dear Lord said; The flowers He made our patterns fair, The harvest field, the birds of air, The green trees overhead. All, all, as with a living breath, Speak loudly unto us; For all above us or beneath, He made them types of life, or death, And we should read them thus. ESAU. “Esau, who for one morsel of meat sold his birthright, for he found no place of repentance, though he sought it carefully with tears.”—Heb. xii. 16, 17. Red hunter! lay the quiver down, And set the wingéd shaft aside, Nor seek along the mountain brown The covert where the roe-deer hide. Another hand than thine, to-day Shall find thy father's favourite cheer, And Heaven-appointed bear away The blessing that thou fain would'st hear. He kneeleth by the old man's chair In thine own goodly raiment dress'd, And while its fragrance fills the air, Is blesséd, and he shall be bless'd. In vain thy bitter cry shall break! Not all the tears thine eyes can shower, Not all the vows thy lips can make, Shall bring again that one short hour. The birthright of the eldest born, Thou gav'st to soothe a moment's pain, And blessings once despised in scorn, May never, never, come again. O, thou that bear'st the token high Of better birthright lately given, Whose silver cross is scarcely dry, That signed thee for an heir of heaven, The grace of confirmation time Shall come to seal again thy treasure— See that thou give it not for crime, Nor change it for uneasy pleasure. Nor think for childhood's hours misspent, To give to God thine after day, Nor deem that youth to folly lent An age of tears shall wipe away. Thou wilt not have the same young powers, The fresh warm heart that loves and glows; Who ever saw sweet April flowers Come peeping through December snows? Red Esau roamed a hunter wild, He wooed the daughters of the land, And while the world around him smiled, God's gifts were passing from his hand. He sought in vain with bitter tears, That first best blessing back to win; Beware, beware, lest future years, Should find no time to shrive thy sin! JACOB. “Why should I be deprived also of you both in one day?” —Gen. xxvii. 45. The sunset lies on Isaac's tent, And all the glowing Syrian vale Is flooded with a splendour pale Of gold, and faintest crimson blent. Beside the well the camel waits; Come slowly home the bleating herds, And night by night, the summer birds Sing sweetly from the shadowy dates. But never more at evening's close The quiet voice Rebekah hears That made a concord to her ears More sweet than any music knows. She marks the shadows falling thick, They darken all the blind man's face, And still she sees an empty place, And still her mother's heart is sick. And he that shared her fond deceit, That could not wait th' appointed time, He feels by night the frosty rime, By day, the summer's noontide heat, An exile in another land, And never more his head to rest Upon a mother's patient breast, And never feel her soothing hand. In youth, in age, alike beguiled, So oft deceived for one deceiving, Whose spousal morn was turned to grieving, Who wept for lost his living child. Learn of his sorrow, Christian youth, When tempted sore, when right shall seem To come of wrong, nor ever deem That Heaven has need of thine untruth. Like fountains lost, and traced in vain, That blend at last with ocean blue— Like birds that wander winter through, But find their summer nests again:— God's ways, though dark nor understood, Shall work His righteous will at last. Keep virtue's path, though clouds o'ercast, Nor sin for any seeming good. JOSEPH. “And the Lord was with Joseph.” —Gen. xxxix. 2. The blue old Nile that welters soft and clear Through his own valley rich with flowers and song, Like a proud monarch lingering to hear His people's plaudits as he sweeps along; The great old Nile has seen a youthful brow Such as his Pharaohs wear not, calm, and grave— Has heard his swarthy children as they bow Cry, “honour, honour,” to the Hebrew slave. The merchantment of Midian by the palm Of Dothan bought him, heedless of his grief; They sold him with the spicery and balm, By Memnon's shrine, to Pharaoh's warrior chief. How oft from Egypt's prison towers gazing He dreamed of Shechem's pasture lands again, Of quiet herds in rain-dewed valleys grazing, And the green fig-tree on the tented plain; Or when he watched the azure lotos gleam On the broad bosom of that famous river, Thought of the eyes that haunted, like a dream, His childhood's sleep, then passed away for ever! But God was with him, in his master's hall, And when the false fair woman told her tale, And when like flowers unsunn'd that fade and fall, In the dim prison light, his cheek waxed pale; And all things that he did in home, and tower, The Lord God made to prosper in his hand, And raised him up, and clothed his head with power, And now he rides a ruler through the land. Shall Christian man forget when troubles press, When pain afflicts, or grief, or unjust wrong, One that is with him in his worst distress, If but his heart be true, his faith be strong? Who bringeth him to honour greater far Than aught of earthly state by Pharaoh given, Than purple vesture, or triumphal car,— The long, long life, the glory of high Heaven? Like a sick babe that with averted eye, Tosses unsoothed his little fevered head, Heedless of her who all night watches by, Wets the parched lip, and rocks the cradle bed; So our hearts drooping deem themselves alone, And Christ Himself is with us all the while, Tempers our griefs, and loveth more His own, Than mother hanging o'er with patient smile. JOSEPH A TYPE. “And sold Joseph to the Ishmeelites for twenty pieces of silver.” —Gen. xxxvii. 28. Sold by them that should have loved thee, Prisoner in the heathen's hand, Given by him that best had proved thee To the dungeon and the band:— From the land of flowers, and rain, Borne to Egypt's dewless plain, Leaving tent and pastoral dell And the sire that loved thee well, And the airs on upland breezy Where the scented cedars grow, For the servant's toil uneasy, And the captive's weary woe;— Out of grief to honour risen, Winning rapture for thy pain, And a palace for thy prison, And a sceptre for thy chain:— Ruling with a gentle art, Over many a grateful heart, Melting with a brother's love Those thine anguish could not move— Wearing graciously thy glory Through the land thy wisdom won— How should Christian read thy story, Aged Israel's favoured son? As the little sapling tender Shows the great oak waving proud; As the cold lake burns with splendour From the crimson sunset-cloud; So in sufferings of thine Trace we out a grief divine, And thy sorrows throb and glow With a pulse of heavenly woe! Type thou art of One more holy Who His glory laid aside, Took the form of servant lowly, Stooped to suffering man, and died. He was scorned, and sold, and hated By the men He came to save, With a cruel wrath unsated Followed to His three days' grave,— Not one pitying thought for Him, When His failing eye waxed dim, Not one note in sympathy With that love so full and free, When His tender spirit yearning Wept those tears of Godlike grief O'er the lawless city, spurning Help, and safety, and relief. Now He reigneth high exalted Where the white-robed elders stand By the great throne rainbow-vaulted, Each with golden harp in hand, Thousand thousand hearts adoring, Thousand thousand vials pouring Odours sweet of saintly prayers, That embalm those Heavenly airs, Round the Lamb once slain and wounded Breathing, till that awful hour, When by Heaven's high hosts surrounded He shall come again in power. For behind each image saintly Burns the light of Jesu's Name— As the lines lie dim and faintly In the gothic window frame, Till the sunlight touch the pane, Rising o'er the fretted fane, And each form, and gorgeous hue, Starts to sight distinct, and true. So doth many a sin-stained creature Catch a glory from Christ's face, And a light is on his feature, That our eyes should love to trace. MOSES ON THE NILE. “And she laid it in the flags by the river's brink.” —Exod. ii. 3. Blow gently, wind! beneath the moon Across the river wavelets bright: Make music like a cradle tune Into the mother's ear to-night! Flow, father Nile! unvexed by storm, And softly rock the bulrush ark, Nor whelm the little dainty form,— A lily on thy waters dark. Three months in secret on her breast The faithful mother nursed her boy, And as his smiling lip she press'd, She trembled with a fearful joy. And now the dreaded hour is come, She tears him from her throbbing bosom, She leaves him where the river foam Hangs white around the lotos-blossom. O, mother, when his eyes were shut Better thine hand had slain the child, Than given his delicate limbs to glut The river monster fierce, and wild— Than left to that remorseless stream The rounded form that all the night Lay in thy bosom, like a dream That haunts the sleeper with delight. Nay, but her heart is strong in faith, God's shield is o'er her infant spread, To her his eye a prescience hath, She sees the glory round his head. Dreams that shall visit her full oft, When baby-lips her bosom drain, And ‘baby touches’ pressing soft Thrill to her mother's heart again. For lo! the fated princess fair Comes duly to the water side: Her maids unbind her perfumed hair, And lead her to the sacred tide. She sees him, and her heart allows The claim for love and pity dear Writ on his innocent waxen brows, And speaking through his gushing tear. How many a mother o'er her child Has prayed, and feared, and trembled long, Deeming the world had waves as wild As that broad river rushing strong! To her a holier hand has come, Her twice-born darling back has given, And bade her take the nursling home, And rear him up for God, and Heaven. We, precious charge from Jesus' hands!— We, for whom mother's prayers have gone Borne duly up by angel bands To linger round th' eternal throne!— See that our hearts be mindful still Of holy vow, and heavenly care— What but a child's rebellious will Can mar a faithful mother's prayer! THE PLAGUES OF EGYPT. “I will at this time send all My plagues upon thine heart.” — Exod. ix. 14. Child! when the silent voice within Shall whisper, “Thine intent is sin, That thing thou shalt not do,” And holy text at morning said, Or when the evening sky grows red, Shall speak the warning true; Scorn not the check by conscience given, Nor trifle with the voice of Heaven, That pleads and pleads again— Lest haply wilful in thy crime, There come at last an awful time When it shall plead in vain. For evil habit hardens ever, Like the cold wave of that dark river That touches into stone, And that young tender heart of thine At last may heed no warning line, May hear no pleading tone. Like the stern king on Egypt's coasts Who strove against the Lord of Hosts, And hardened still his heart, By fear and pride alternate swayed, While ten times striking Heaven delayed, And showed the better part. The river rolled its blood-red billow— The child lay stricken on his pillow, By every house a grave,— And still he battled with remorse, Till cold and stiff his swollen corse Lay on the Red-sea wave. More favoured thou by birth and name! Fear lest thy judgment be the same; This is thy day of grace. The sweet dove singeth in thine ear, The book of life is open near, Christ's touch is on thy face. Dread is it when the red right hand That smote of old the Egyptian land, Is lifted up in wrath— More dreadful still if He depart, And leave thee to a hardened heart, To shameless sin and death. ISRAEL'S CRY. “I have surely seen the affliction of My people which is in Egypt, and have heard their cry, and am come down to deliver them.”— Exod. iii. 7, 8. There's many a quiet cottage laid Beneath some elm tree's giant shade, Where oft at eve the speckled thrush Sings from the fragrant hawthorn bush, And rosy children run to greet Their weary sire's returning feet. Light hearts are theirs, untouched by woe, Love's lesson all the lore they know,— The father's hand to spread the board, The gentle mother's soothing word, The week-day's work, the Sunday strain Of sweet bells chiming down the lane. But death may dim the tender light In eyes that love made ever bright, Or sickness come to steal away The strength that laboured day by day, And need may count the lessening store, Where frugal plenty reigned before. Who then shall dry the sufferer's tear O Christian child? what hope shall cheer? Is there no mightier hand to aid If thy worn sire be lowly laid, No better sunshine than there lies Behind thy mother's love-lit eyes? Yea, read how Israel wept of old By Pharaoh's hand to bondage sold. What though around their prison bowers The broad Nile swept his foam and flowers, What though their hands should rear a fane That wondering time would touch in vain, The voice of unrequited toil Rose day and night from that fair soil. The mother's anguish rent the sky For her fair son cast out to die, While the stern king unpitying gave The double task to gall the slave;— But, while unmoved the tyrant heard, A mightier arm in Heaven was stirred, And while that burning southern sun Set hotly on their work half-done, God's ear had heard their anguish strong, God's eye had seen His people's wrong. And lo! like breezes that have lain Asleep on the Atlantic main, And come at even wandering o'er To cool some fainting tropic shore, From lonely Jethro's mountain-home, They see the great deliverer come. Thee too He hears when hunger weeps, When love keeps watch where sickness sleeps, Yea, ev'n beside the new-earthed grave, Thy great Deliverer waits to save. Trust but His love, and seek His care; He never spurns His children's prayer! THE NIGHT OF THE PASSOVER. “It is a night to be much observed unto the Lord, for bringing them out from the land of Egypt.”—Exod. xii. 42. It is a night to be remembered much Unto the Lord, through Israel's hosts for aye, When the destroying Angel by the couch Of Egypt's fairest children,—as they lay Wrapt in their rosy slumber—paused to slay. A night of gladness, and of horror dread, Of eager gatherings, and of wild despair,— In Pharaoh's hall his eldest born lay dead, And the old King rose up, and tore his hair, And bade the people forth ere morn lit up the air. Then were there rapturous thrills, and sudden starts, A tremulous stir in every household band,— And mothers bound their babies to their hearts, And aged men stood up with staff in hand, Whispering young children of the promised land, For through that solemn eve the young lambs dying Had bleated out their sweet lives while they bled, As a child sings itself to sleep with crying: By every hearth the victim blood was shed, On every board the hasty feast was spread. And many a group stood girt for sudden flight, And many a sandalled foot was on the floor, And many a face looked out into the night, Where the destroying Angel passing o'er Cast a bright shadow on the blood-stained door. Now rich with Egypt's golden spoils they go Forth in that broken midnight, through the jar, Like a great river that with even flow, Sweeps on the same 'neath sun and clouded star, To its great sea that roars and raves afar. Go forth, ye chosen heirs of Canaan's coasts, With your loins girded, and your sandalled shoon; Lo! with your banners fights the Lord of Hosts, And brighter far than yon red orient moon, The fiery pillar makes a sunless noon. And was that glorious night alone for ye, Sons of the Jew? Is there no thought that swells The Christian heart—no Paschal memory, Borne yearly where the northern peasant dwells, On the quick chimes of merry Easter bells? Yea, for us too the unblemished Lamb was wounded, For us th' unleavened feast is duly set— We stand with staff in hand by foes surrounded, Bound for a golden Canaan fairer yet Than that sweet land with milk and honey wet. Yea, the destroying Angel has passed o'er, The blood is on the lintels of our heart, Else how from this Egyptian bondage sore, That weighs us down, and makes our tears to start, Should we rise up like pilgrims and depart? Come Paschal thoughts, and soothe us with sweet calm, Oft as we linger o'er the wondrous tale Of those great mysteries—fragrant as the balm Of last year's roses, that all cold and pale Sleep in their vase, yet precious scents exhale. Haunt us, sweet Paschal thoughts! but lead us not Back to the lamb, that died that marvellous night, Staining the door-post with a crimson spot, But to the Lamb Who died on Calvary's height, Whose death redeemed, Whose blood shall wash us white. THE RED SEA. “And the Lord caused the sea to go back by a strong east wind all that night, and made the sea dry land.”—Exod. xiv. 21. O sea! that with thy tinted waves, Now purple dark, now ocean green, Now azure with a silver sheen, Dost cover o'er so many graves— As hoarse and dark thy billow raves, What wonders hath it seen! What tales are on thine iron tongue, That clangs against its rocky coasts The death knell of so many hosts, Of many a gallant heart unstrung— Tales—some to sweeter music sung Than aught Parnassus boasts. I ask thee not of navies proud, Whose oars have swept thy waters brown, With golden spoils from Indian town; I ask not 'neath thy thunder cloud How oft the shriek rose sharp and loud, As shipwrecked men went down. But tell me rather of the day When Israel's hosts stood by thy shore, And saw thy swelling waves before, Behind, proud Egypt's stern array, And cried aloud in wild dismay, Till the Lord led them o'er. Then smitten by that marvellous blast, They saw the unfathom'd waters shrink Back from the wild sea's rocky brink; And down where line was never cast, Mid fretted stones, and weeds they pass'd, And shells of delicate pink. The trembling women held their breath, The men looked up with curdled blood, Where that great wall of waters stood Foam-tipped, like mountains with a wreath Of virgin snow, all blue beneath, As they walked through the flood. They saw the monarch mad with wrath, And all his glittering squadrons sweep,— Chariots, and captains, from the steep, Their horses' flanks were flecked with froth, As they rode down the perilous path, Into the dry sea-deep;— Then closed at once the cloven water Over the leader and his host— The meeting surges raged and toss'd, Above that bloodless field of slaughter— And sang in triumph Amram's daughter O'er horse and rider lost. Or whisper in thy gentlest tone, When airs at even fan thy sea From balmy-breathing Araby, And long soft ripples murmuring on Heave thy blue bosom and are gone, Of what thou art to me. Type of that pure baptismal tide, Where I went down a child unshriven; Ere yet my soul with ill had striven, When the first taint of birth sin died Like Pharaoh and his bannered pride, And I came forth forgiven. Ah me! the great Egyptian lies, Wild sea! full many a fathom deep, Till Christ shall break the sinner's sleep But sins and follies round me rise Staining baptismal purities— I can but turn, and weep. But that deep under song of thine Still rolls to Miriam's measure high, Hymning a glorious victory; It tells a mightier arm than mine, A conquering grace, a strength divine, Lest my soul in me die. THE CAMP AT ELIM. “And they came to Elim, where there were twelve wells of water, and threescore and ten palm trees, and they encamped there by the waters.”—Exod. xv. 27. Rest, weary Israel, rest awhile Where green the feathery palm-trees grow And nestling in their lonely isle The twelve sweet fountains sleep below. Rest, where no sound of foes assailing Shall bid thine heart throb high with fear, No echo of the Red Sea wailing Shall come to vex thy startled ear: But where the long day lingering bright Shall see thy snowy tents uprise, And silent stars shall wake by night To watch them with their golden eyes. Where spicy plants that dwell apart Shall wrap thee round with odorous balms And sweetest quiet fill thine heart By the clear wells, beneath the palms. Past is the Red Sea's perilous hour— The desert path is scarcely trod— Not yet the marvellous manna shower Lies like white daisies on the sod. Not yet to quench thy fiery thirst The rock hath given its fountain free— Here with furled banners linger first Betwixt the desert and the sea. Betwixt thy childhood and thy youth, Christian, there lies a sweeter calm, Where thou may'st drink the well of truth, And lie beneath Hope's shadowy palm. The sea is pass'd, the desert near, Where thou shalt walk with manna fed Scarce trodden yet the path of fear, Not yet for thee the feast is spread; But parents' love and pastoral word, And studious hours are all thine own; And prayers at morn and even heard, Make sweet thy desert island lone, Fill with rich balms thy lowly place— A time for rest and strengthening given, Ere shadowing hands shall bring thee grace For the long strife that leads to Heaven. Oft when the pillared cloud looks dim That guides thee o'er that pathless track, A thought, a text, a holy hymn, Shall lead thy spirit wandering back; Dreaming how good these hours have been, How sweet thy resting by the way, Where Elim's palms grew fresh and green, And Elim's cooling waters lay. MOUNT SINAI. “Go unto the people, and sanctify them to-day and to-morrow, and let them wash their clothes, and be ready against the third day, for the third day the Lord will come down in the sight of all the people upon Mount Sinai.”—Exod. xix. 10, 11. Not to that lonely mountain brown Where the thick cloud was rent asunder, And the trump rang, and rolled the thunder, As the Lord God came down. Not to that mountain with its bound, Where God's own finger wrote the law, And trembling with an intense awe The people waited round. Not to that temple in the wild Where lingered the Lord's presence high, Which whoso touched must surely die, We bid thee, Christian child! But sanctify thy soul even now, And let thy robe be clean and white, The same we gave when for the fight We crossed thy baby brow. Behold! the Mount where we are come,— An awful, holy, glorious spot!— Though there the smoke ascendeth not, The trumpet's voice is dumb. A cross is on that wondrous mount, A place of love, and yet of pain, And we may touch, and touch again, And wash in mercy's fount. The city all of precious stone Is there with jasper girded bright, That hath for light by day and night, The living God alone. 'Twixt earth and heaven that city waits, And up and down bright angels pass Between us, and the sea of glass, Us, and the pearly gates. There are the spirits of the just, Sweet saints that loved us long ago, For whom our poor hearts sorrowed so When they were laid in dust: The holy men of every time, Martyrs to whom the world was loss, And gentle souls who bore the cross Unmarked in many a clime: And Jesus too, our own High Priest, No Moses with the tables twain, Shivered in anger on the plain, Sprinkling with blood of beast— The Mediator that hath stood Between us, and God's angry face, Sealing the covenant of grace With His own precious Blood. Come wash thee in that crimson tide, And make thy garment white as snow, And let us to that mountain go, And linger at its side! Sweet is our high communion there,— The fellowship of Saints is ours, The hope of Heaven's angelic bowers, And Christ's own presence fair. THE ARK A TYPE. “And the Temple of God was opened in Heaven, and there was seen in His Temple the Ark of His Testament.”—Rev. xi. 19. The clouds of night hang dark and dense, An hour before the break of day, Save when one crimson ray intense, Comes peeping round their margin grey; And throbs of red light dimly seen, Like quivering pulses, flash between. But if thine eyes could pass the ridge Of those huge clouds, like molten lead, And pierce beyond their silver'd edge Into the deep unfathom'd red, Where from his bright day never done, Comes round the great unresting sun; And see what corn-rich vales lie steep'd In glowing noon-tide far away, What hills in purple light are heap'd, O'er the green islet's silver bay— What dark woods stand with all their tips Still glowing from his golden lips; If thou could'st see that wondrous orb, Whose crimson shadows fall before, Whose light shall all those hues absorb, That curtain now Heaven's open door, How would'st thou start at once to view Noon's dazzling ray, Morn's roseate hue! Then leave the dew-bespangled lawn, Each drop a diamond on the sod— Come, where the dim prophetic dawn Hangs o'er the old-world works of God; And read them in the perfect light Of Christian noon-tide, clear and bright. For thee the shadow and the type, Wear all their rich reality; Not promise buds, not hopes unripe Are clustering round that mystic tree, That bears for thee on one fair root, At once the blossom, and the fruit. Beneath the Mount where Moses stayed, Wrought well the craftsmen wise of heart, The shittim wood with gold o'erlaid, And carved the work of cunning art, The curtains twined with rare device, And made the incense of sweet spice. Within its tent of scarlet furs, The warrior-leader set the shrine, Where, hidden from the worshippers, Slept ever in a calm divine The law, the bread, the rod unfaded, The mercy-seat, by cherubs shaded. Fair gilded type! where we behold An image brighter than thine own, Of Him Who wears the crown of gold In glory by th' Eternal Throne, Who bore within the law of God, And felt the Father's chastening rod. His heavenly feast, the manna sweet, That feeds us as we walk below— His wounded heart the mercy-seat, Whence God's best words of comfort flow— His light the lamp's undying spark, Himself the Presence and the Ark. Thou journeyedst on from place to place, Till for thy home, the Monarch spread The white dome on the mountain's face;— He had not where to lay His Head, Till raised from death to Him 'twas given To tread the inner courts of Heaven. Lead on, great Ark! where'er we go, As Israel's host was led of yore— Cast down the walls of Jericho, And part the waves on Jordan's shore; Till in God's Temple walls we see, Our Ark at last, and rest with Thee. THE CLOUD ON THE TABERNACLE. “Whether it were two days, or a month, or a year, that the cloud tarried upon the Tabernacle—the children of Israel journeyed not; but when it was taken up they journeyed.”—Numb. ix. 22. Within the Presence-cloud of God, His Ark enshrouded lay; No airs that kiss'd the desert sod, Might breathe that mist away. So wrapp'd their own soft leaves amid, The silver lilies grow. So lies the golden chalice hid Beneath the veil of snow. But when the crescent moon from far Led up her countless train, A brighter light than any star, Glowed on the darken'd plain. The wild beast skulking for his prey, Shunned that unearthly blaze, The desert bird fled fast away, Or shyly came to gaze:— As outcasts wandering to and fro, Pause by the lighted hall, And watch the gleam along the snow From the high casements fall: And eyes as wild, with wistful glance, Watched where that cloud was hung, The warrior leaning on his lance, The Priest with stave unslung, While many a day the banners bright, Drooped listless in the heat, And children in their mother's sight Played down the tented street. It rose, and over hill and dale, The pennons broad were flung— The Levite took the purple veil, The silver trumpets rung. And onward boldly Israel trod Wide plain, or mountain grey, While, silent as the hand of God, It pointed out the way. But more than fire in night's dark face, Than mists when suns are red, The Presence-cloud of love and grace, That Christ doth on us shed:— The cloud that goes before our fears, And conquers every foe, The calm sweet light that glows and cheers, When hearts beat cold and low. Rise up, O Lord! and scatter Thou Our pride, and lust, and hate, The sins that line the mountain brow, And throng the city gate. Return, O Lord! when sad and low Beneath the desert skies, We pause in weariness, or woe, With salt tears in our eyes. Come, gentle as a drooping cloud, Sweet as a summer star, With Thine own Self ourselves enshroud, And lead this weary war. THE INVITATION TO HOBAB. “And Moses said unto Hobab the son of Raguel the Midianite, Moses' father-in-law: ‘We are journeying unto the place of which the Lord said, I will give it you: Come thou with us, and we will do thee good.’”—Num. x. 29. “Come, go with us, the desert path Has many a lone and lovely spot, Where underneath the tall green palm, The silent waters, cool and calm, Sleep in their silver grot. “And those wild eyes shall pierce for us, The unbroken blue that rings us round, And o'er the desert's burning face Along the track that leaves no trace, Shall find their depths profound. “Dark chieftain of the wandering tribe, Come with us! for thou knowest well, (Whose foot hath tracked the desert bird, Whose ear the lion's voice has heard,) What perils round us dwell. “Come with us! we will do thee good, When skies with morning roses blush; Thine hand shall gather angel's food, And for thy cheer the cooling flood Out of the rock shall rush. “For we are journeying to the land Where golden corn, and purple vine, Streak the dark mountain's laden breast. Come with us! and that glorious rest For ever shall be thine.” So sang they to the Arab chief, Along the dewless, desert lea. O Christian youth! that waverest still, With wandering glance, and perverse will, So sing we unto thee. Come with us, dost thou linger yet? The Red sea spray has touched thy brow, And, bright as Israel's streamers fair, Floats far above thee in the air The banner of thy vow. And sweet as odorous plants, their shadow Flinging on some poor wanderer's face, Who kneels beside the fount at noon, On thy bowed head shall fall full soon The touch that winneth grace. Full soon the desert altar wild, Shall bear for thee the fruit divine, The heavenly bread, and that dark flood, Struck from the living rock—the blood Drunk with that mystic vine. And if thine heart have loved too well The songs, and scents of Egypt's bowers, Come with us! and thy youth shall know A holier joy, a purer glow, In this strange march of ours. For many a time the spicy gale Comes wandering round our pilgrim band, And many a shadowy isle of palms, Like a green boat rocks in the calms Of this great sea of sand. Come with us! o'er the hills afar, The promised land lies steeped in glory; But never spy has gone before, And come again, of that fair shore To tell the wondrous story. Their Canaan wore a thousand tints From field, and rock, and flowers that wither; Ours glows and gleams in one still light, From Christ's perpetual presence bright, Come with us, for we wander thither! THE FAITHLESS SPIES. “But the men that went up with him said, ‘We be not able to go up against the people, for they are stronger than we.’”—Num. xiii. 31. “Go not up to that land, though the purple grapes glowing In clusters of beauty hang red by the rill, Though the valleys are green, and the cornfields are showing, Like girdles of gold on the vineyarded hill. “We have searched out its regions of beauty and glory, From Zin where the salt sea beats cold on the sand, By Rehob, and Hamath, to Hebron the hoary, And borne back from Eshcol the fruit of the land. “From Shenir, and Hermon all crested with ices, From Lebanon dark with the cedar and fir, At daybreak we gazed on the gardens of spices, And caught the first breath from the mountains of myrrh. “The roe-deer woke up on the wild hill of Bether, The top of Anana looked red in the glow, The pomegranates blushed in the orchards beneath her, And doves by the lattice were murmuring low. “The figtree and vine by their threshold are twining, But go ye not up with the sword in your hand; The bucklers of brass on their ramparts are shining, The children of Anak are strong in the land.” O false and fainthearted! who looked on the beauty, And tasted the sweetness, but feared to pass in; Who turned back the hosts of the Lord from their duty, Till He left them alone in their darkness and sin. There's a land far away o'er the waste and the river, The desert of life, and the Jordan of death; No foot has gone in there, or come again ever, To bring back the grapes that grow ripe in its breath. No eye ever looked on its heavenly splendour, The light without shadow that sleeps on its sod, No ear ever thrilled to the harmonies tender, That rock there the rest of the people of God. More faithless by far, if in sight of that portal, We turn back to toy with the follies of life; Nor deem that its joys, with its mansions immortal, Were worth all the danger and toil of our strife. THE RED HEIFER. “And a man that is clean shall gather up the ashes of the heifer, and it shall be kept for a water of separation: it is a purification for sin.”—Num. xix. 9. We need not now like Israel's son, The sprinkled ashes making pure; For us a nobler work is done, And we have found a better cure. Forth from the lone camp in the wild, A spotless thing without a stain, They led th' unblemished creature mild, And slew her in the desert-plain. Bring hither what your hands have spoiled, The gold, the silver, and the lead— Or if there be whose robe is soiled, Or one whose hand has touched the dead: Come scatter wide the ashen shower, And let the waters o'er them lie, And that bright sprinkling shall have power From aught unclean to purify. A stainless victim, holy all, Without a spot on soul or frame, Forth from the city's guilty wall, To death our sinless Offering came. And lo! a tide to cleanse, and save, A thousand times more free and wide Than that old purifying wave, Is gushing from His riven Side. That did but touch the outward part, This purifies the soul within; The only tide to reach the heart, The only wave that washes sin. Then if there be, who born anew, Have soiled the robe without a stain, Come hither, and this crimson dew Shall wash it white as snow again; And bring whate'er in studious hour, Whate'er in life's keen strife ye gain, Learning, and wealth, and moral power, Each treasure of the heart and brain. Bring burning thought, and reason strong, The iron of the earnest mind, The golden pen, the silver song, Nor leave one glorious gift behind. And wash them all in Christ's dear Blood, So shall your works be sanctified; For nought is pure, or true, or good, That hath not touched that crimson tide. THE PUNISHMENT OF MOSES. “And the Lord spake unto Moses and Aaron, Because ye believed Me not—ye shall not bring this congregation into the land which I have given them.”—Numb. xx. 12. “Get thee up into this Mount Abarim—yet thou shalt see the land before thee, but thou shalt not go thither unto the land that I give the children of Israel.”—Deut. xxxii. 49, 52. Over the cedars beyond Jordan growing, Come, balmy breeze! and touch the old man's cheek, Come from the land with milk and honey flowing: His eye not dim, his natural strength not weak, He stands and gazes from Abarim's peak, But never shall his weary foot pass o'er Like a glad bird to that desiréd shore. Sweet as the image fair in every part The mother pictures of her babe unborn, Feeling the burden at her happy heart; Dear as his home to wayfarer forlorn; As to the youth his hope of bridal morn; So dear, so sweet had been that old man's dream Of the good land beyond the silver stream. How oft, when Pharaoh's halls were wild with joy, That vision like a strain of music stole O'er the lone musings of the Hebrew boy; How often, like a charm, it used to roll Before him in the desert, when his soul Was weary; and his spirit fail'd within, Vex'd with the people's selfishness, and sin. And now it lies before him, all embalm'd In odours like a garden; and he stands Like a good ship just in the port becalm'd— Her crew hang o'er her sides with idle hands, And see their wives and children throng the sands, Gaze on the outstretch'd arms they cannot reach, And hear their voices murmur from the beach. There lies the golden end of all his hopes, To fancy fair, more beautiful to sight: The blue topp'd mountains with long sunny slopes, And deep green hollows bath'd in purple light; The foam-white streamlets leaping from the height, And stretching far away the chequer'd plain, Red with its grape, and yellow with its grain. But he may never cross the silver river, Because in Kadesh, when the people strove, He sinn'd to the Lord God; and so for ever He turns from the fond dream his childhood wove, His boyhood's eager hope, his manhood's love— Turns with quick quivering lip and streaming eye, And lies down on the mountain top to die. Come, sinful soul, where purple Pisgah dips Her brow in clouds; watch by this dying Saint Once spake he unadvis'dly with his lips, Are not thine full of anger and complaint, Words quick, and light, or with a fouler taint? He once rebell'd—then what of thee whose life Is one long treason, one continual strife? And, O for him, though life's dear hope was blighted, Better that mountain grave by hands undrest, Where soft winds sang, and angel forms alighted; For sweeter far than Israel's promised rest For ever safe to lie down with the blest, And fairer still than Canaan's boasted sod Th' eternal hills, the Paradise of God. BALAAM. “And Balak brought Balaam unto the top of Peor that looketh toward Jeshimon.”—Numb. xxiii. 28. “And Balaam lifted up his eyes, and he saw Israel abiding in his tents,—and the Spirit of God came upon him.”—Numb. xxiv. 2. In Moab's plains the tents of Israel lie, Like cedar trees in many a goodly row. Jeshimon's breezes as they wander by, Bear up her children's songs to Peor's brow. Is it the sunbeam flashing on the rills, That touches the dark mountain into light? Is it the bald old eagle of the hills That claps his wings exulting from the height? No glistening sunbeam on the streamlet shines, Screams from the beetling crag no eagle grey; Why dost thou linger by thy seven shrines, Wild prophet! from the river far away? Why dost thou bid the twice seven victims bleed, Seeking enchantment in thy waywardness, Who knowest well the doom by Heaven decreed, Whose prophet-lip can only part to bless? Fear not, O Israel! in the shadow sleeping Of that great mountain like a fawn at rest, Thy wandering sons are in a safer keeping, How shall God's Prophet curse whom God has blest? He seeks no more enchantments; from the tip Of the blue hill he gazes, and the tide Of glorious blessing gushes from his lip, Like silver water from a dark rock's side. The vision of the Almighty fills his eyes, He looks into the latter days afar, Sees the gold sceptre out of Israel rise, Sees bright from Jacob break the morning star. Fare on, thou favour'd host! not Moab's king Can buy one curse with all his proffer'd gold, Lo! in his ear, red Edom's dirges ring, And Moab's doom, and Amalek's are told. So fareth Christ's dear Church, belovéd much, Through Moab's plains, the desert, and the river; No curse can reach, no rage of man can touch The souls redeem'd she holdeth safe for ever. And that dark seer that like a wild storm-cloud Half light, half darkness, swept o'er Israel's path With God's pure glory burning through the shroud Of his own wilful worldliness, and wrath; A shrine defiled where grace and mammon met, A mystery of knowledge and of sin, Oft as his tranced eye to the desert set, Looms on our thought, and his strong words break in. Fear we the double heart, the service cold, The covetous desire that leads astray, The lust of earthly place, the love of gold, Ask we a single eye to choose the narrow way. THE POSSESSION ON THIS SIDE JORDAN. “We will build sheepfolds here for our cattle, and cities for our little ones, but we ourselves will go ready armed before the children of Israel.”—Numb. xxxii. 16. Where pastoral Jazer stretches wide, Where balmy Gilead slopes away, From fruitful Hermon's mountain side To where the Jordan's waters stray, As drops the dove into her nest, As lies the lamb down in the fold, Manasseh! let thy thousands rest, And warrior Gad, and Reuben bold! For more to you these pastoral dells Where the huge ox unburdened walks, And crushes down the cowslip bells, And daisies on their tender stalks; Than fields of corn that make the plain To ripple like a sea of gold; Than grapes that cast a purple stain, On the dark mountain's bosom cold; Here let your lowly homestead rise, Where the green figleaf thickest twines With lattices for maidens' eyes, And cool verandahs hung with vines. Where, when the mother rests at last, The babe, unwean'd upon her knee, Shall watch the lambs that frolic past, And clap its dimpled hands in glee. But though your hearts be left behind, Still let your arms be strong and brave. The buckler on your shoulders bind, And dip the foot in Jordan's wave. Go ready arm'd before the Lord, Win the good land beyond the river, Then rest ye like a victor's sword That drops into its sheath for ever! Return! and long in peace and joy, Your flocks shall fill these valleys fair, And shepherd-fathers teach the boy The greenest spots embosom'd there. The maids shall chatter at the mill, The sheep-bells tinkle from the height, And when all other sounds are still The nightingale shall sing at night. O precious rest, and duly earn'd, Those grass-rich glades, that clover sod, Where Israel's bloody battle burn'd Afar for Canaan, and for God; For many a year, from Jordan's ford To Arnon's brook all gemm'd with forth, Told lowing kine, and bleating herd, How well the warrior kept his troth. Come then; but not for strain of lute Or cattle bells along the shore. These all are broken now and mute, Their lonely haunts shall teach thee more, Shall teach the truth so oft forgot,— Man lives not for himself alone, He may not hold his own fair lot, Regardless of another's moan. And none of us unmoved may view His brother's strife, or hear him plead; We must go over Jordan too, With many a self-denying deed; We may not turn in joy and health, To homes with peaceful blessings crown'd, And stores of spiritual wealth, While souls and bodies starve around. Their cries on every breeze are borne, God's champions battle in the van. We're every one a warrior sworn, And each must do the most he can, Use all his powers—though faint and few— Give prayers, and soothing words, and alms. Else Hermon hath for us no dew, And Gilead's bowers no precious balms. GERIZIM AND EBAL. “These shall stand upon Mount Gerizim and bless the people— and these shall stand upon Mount Ebal to curse.”—Deut. xxvii. 12, 13 He that hath climb'd Gerizim's steep Has loved to linger on the height, And feel the rapturous thrills that creep Through every sense from ravish'd sight. So fair beneath the glowing scene Of groves and gardens breathing balm, And rich with ever varied green Dark olive bower, and crested palm. And still their tints are most profuse, And still the landscape fairest shines, Where like a snow-drift white Nablous, Modern name of Samaria. Lies nestling in her purple vines. From neighbouring Ebal's summit bare The wild hawk shrieks upon the gale, And sweet songs wrapt in scented air Come wandering up from Leban's vale. But thought too has her inward views, The golden gleams that never fell On visible landscape—shapes and hues To the soul's eye made palpable. So from rich vale and mountain hoary, His wandering eye shall turn within, And many a glorious old time story Shall to a holier rapture win. In Shechem's fields the white flocks stray, The spice-encumber'd camels bear Their rich load up the rocky way, And Joseph's brethren linger there. No more of piping pastoral note That rose at eve by Jacob's well: In the steep pass bright banners float, And loud the brazen trumpets swell. Joy-flushed they come, a glorious band, Elders and priests and warriors all, From Ai's spoil, from Jordan's strand, From Jericho's God-stricken wall. Now hush'd in awe the living tide Rolls, quiet as a silent surge, To either mountain's barren side, And motionless hangs upon its verge. The curses of a broken law In mutter'd storms from Ebal roll; Gerizim, fair in rapturous awe, Speaks blessing on th' obedient soul. Now band and banner fade together, The patient seedsman flings the grain, In a bright noon of autumn weather, Along the fertile Syrian plain. Who sitteth worn with toil, and want, On Jacob's well, by Joseph's grave, While sinful woman scarce will grant The draught His parchéd lip would crave? Hungry, and thirsty, and alone, He rests the wearied human limb, Those mountain-shadows o'er Him thrown, And all their types are found in Him. Fountain of bliss! a thousand fold Richer than aught Gerizim spake; Nor ever curse from Ebal rolled, Dark as He bore for sinner's sake. O weary flesh, and over-task'd; Poor sons of toil in every land! He knew your sorrows ere ye ask'd, And feels your griefs at God's right hand. O laden souls! by guilt press'd down, He bore for you the curse of sin, He earn'd the palm, the robe, the crown, And all Gerizim could not win. Fade gorgeous landscape, tower and tree! Or steep'd in beauty linger still, Where never eye of ours shall see, Beyond the far dawn-crimson'd hill. But still to memory's eye be dear, Still palpable to soul and thought, The weary love that linger'd here, And all the precious truth He taught. SISERA. “The Lord made me have dominion over the mighty.” —Judges v. 13. Forth look'd the mother from her lattice high, To Judah's mountains turn'd her proud dark eye, “Why do his chariot wheels delay so long? Why tarries thus the valiant and the strong? “Have they not sped? have they not won the day? To every man hath been a glorious prey, The gorgeous work by Syrian maidens plann'd, And fair young slaves the choicest in the land. “Sure he will deck his loved ones with the spoil,” In vain she looketh toward that envied soil: With shout and song in peace returning home He cometh not; nor e'er again shall come. Far far away, within the Kenite's tent His brow is bloody, and his head is bent; Where Kishon's ancient waters hurry by On Taanach's plains his trampled warriors lie. For Israel's God hath led the glorious fight, Abinoam's son has conquer'd in His might, And she who sat by Bethel's judgment tree Has risen to chant the song of victory. One woman dwelling in her tent alone In the Lord's Name has slain the mighty one She heard the cry of battle on the blast, She stayed the flying chieftain as he passed. Then say not here on earth are feeble things, Too weak, and mean, to serve the King of kings; The shallow stream scarce noticed in its course Feeds the broad lake, and swells the torrent's force. Prayers of the poor and lowly, heard above, Hang like a charm around the Church we love, And sighs prevail, and simple words have power More than we think, when foes like tempests lour. Weak woman's love when Christ was here below, How oft it served and soothed the “Man of Woe.” And children's voices swelled the loud acclaim, When once in lowly state, to Zion's walls He came. JEPHTHAH'S DAUGHTER. “And she went with her companions and bewailed her virginity upon the mountains.”—Judges xi. 38. Through the woods and pastures comes a crying, A sweet voice that neither fears nor hopes, Mid the ancient oaks of Bashan dying, Dying on green Hermon's sunny slopes. Not the mother, when her grief is sorest For her nest and nestlings torn away, Sends a sadder wailing through the forest, Sitting lonely on her hawthorn spray. Not the wild deer, wounded by the fountain, Gasping out his life with heavy moan, Draws a wilder echo from the mountain, Hath a stranger anguish in his tone. For she waileth, waileth, in the hollows, On the hill-tops rich with many a stripe Of green pasture, where the wild goat follows Shepherd's call, or note of pastoral pipe. Hearken, Gilead! where, with foamy waters, Arnon runneth down to Jordan's shore, In her youth, the fairest of thy daughters Passeth from thy plains for evermore. Hearken, Bashan; where thine old oaks hoary Guard the silver lilies at their feet, When the sunlight crowns them with a glory, Streaming inward where thy branches meet. For the lily that was sweetest, fairest, Shall not blossom next year in thy shades, She, of all thy flowers that was the rarest, Never more shall bloom along thy glades. O wild forest! O ye upland meadows, Like green oceans, tossing to and fro! Ye can only see Heaven's lights and shadows, Can but hear a natural voice of woe, Knowing nothing of the heart's emotion, Nothing of the earnest love that brings All its first, and best, in strong devotion To the altar of the King of kings. But to us, she singeth, singeth faintly, Going up and down that mountain sod, “Nought is grievous to the spirit saintly, Dearest things, and purest, are for God. “Therefore laid I, on the shrine of duty, All sweet flowers that used to bind my brow; So I went down in my youth, and beauty, Went a victim to my father's vow.” RUTH. “It has been fully showed me all that thou hast done—a full reward be given thee of the Lord God of Israel, under Whose wings thou art come to trust.”—Ruth ii. 11, 12. Like one that cometh back again To where his childhood used to roam, And sitteth by the window pane, And listens for the sounds of home, And watches every passing cloud, And thinks how changed is all the scene; Until the brown thrush singeth loud His anthem from the thicket green, Until, perchance, the bells begin To ring from out the old church tower, And all his spirit melts within, Touched with the thoughts of childhood's hour: So is it with that simple tale, Familiar from our earliest time, No church bells on the summer gale Had ever half so sweet a chime. No wild bird, flooding in his glory All nature from the birchen tree, Can thrill us, like that tender story, With such an old time harmony. And like some brilliant foreign thing, From infancy remember'd well; The burnish of a beetle's wing, The rose-tint on a tropic shell; The tinge of Eastern life that clings Around thy gentle tale, sweet Ruth; The simple pastoral tone that brings Home to each heart its stamp of truth. But not alone old memories sweet Of hours beguiled should'st thou record; Or pass us by, like fairy feet, That trace light rings on summer sward. True wife, true daughter, thou hast taught To Christian hearts a holier strain— Fair type of each unselfish thought, The love that fears not want or pain. One of the bright flowers flung of old Along the path the Godhead trod, A link in the long chain of gold 'Twixt David's Son, and David's God. Come, teach us from thine earnest heart, Each depth of true devoted love, And every self-denying art, And cares that noblest spirits move. And leave us with a tender glow, The light flung off from moral beauty Still lingering in our homes below, Pure love, and calm heroic duty. CROSSING THE BROOK. “The king also himself passed over the brook Kidron.”—2 Sam. xv. 23. “When Jesus had spoken these words He went forth with His disciples over the brook Cedron.”—S. John xviii. 1. Like him that doth the picture find Of one beloved but long unseen, And gazes until form and mien Live once again before his mind: So living on the page of truth, Doth many a scene belovéd shine, And we have hung upon the line, And haunts familiar from our youth; And pictured every hill and brook, And looked into the sky above, Till as it is with those that love, We seemed to know their very look. We seemed to see the yellow moon, To watch ourselves the drifting clouds, That hurried by, or hung in shrouds, Across the burning Eastern noon. How many Christian hearts have met Between that city and the hill, And over Cedron's mournful rill, And up the steep of Olivet! How oft that low mount, green and brown To substance and to shape has grown, Filled in with colours of our own, And shadowed from the distant town. Over the brook a weeping king, Behind a weeping host has passed; A long shrill wail comes on the blast, We hear the quivering olives ring. The faithful people go before, Lamenting loud their monarch fled— Barefoot he comes, with covered head, Feeling another sorrow more— The grief that lay all deep and dumb, Behind the grief that sobbed and burned, The father's injured love that yearned Still for his rebel Absalom. Another King has crossed the flood! How many wayward sons had part To wound and break that loving heart, Whose tears were drops of falling blood. And what a pale and weary brow, In that dark olive shade bowed down, The King that never wore a crown, For whom the thorns are weaving now! O mount! where David's bitter tears Fell on the softly-shaded sod, Where David's King, and David's God, Strove with a whole world's weight of fears. O wild dark brook! that heard the cry, A people's mourning on the air, That murmured to the thrice-told prayer Wrung from a deeper agony: Bid our vain hearts some shade to borrow, From that great mystery of grief, Let swelling wave, and drooping leaf, Teach us the worth and depth of sorrow. Tears were in royal David's eyes, Strong tears upon my Saviour's cheek, And shall we shun with spirit weak, All sadder holier thoughts that rise? Musings that mar our lighter strain, Of heaven, and hell, and sinners lost, And of the priceless price they cost, Heart-sorrow, death, and lingering pain? Nay let us find some dark sad hour, When we may weep and think alone Of Christ, and of the Judgment throne, Of death and sin's destroying power. Befits us well the brook of tears, Befits us well the olive-shade, Who have so rarely, coldly, prayed, Have trifled with so many fears. Who shareth thus his Saviour's woe, Shall come as David came again, But to a city where no pain Can enter, and no tear can flow. KING DAVID'S OFFERING. “Nay, but I will surely buy it of thee at a price, neither will I offer burnt offerings unto the Lord my God of that which doth cost me nothing.”—2 Sam. xxiv. 24. When sorrowing David stood of yore, Beside Araunah's threshing-floor, What time the noble Jebusite Bowed in the humbled monarch's sight, And without price had given His oxen for the costly rite, A freewill gift to heaven; The princely penitent forbore The generous donor's offered store, Though kinglike to a king preferred, He turned aside with gentle word, And forth the silver shekels brought— He would not offer to the Lord, Of that which cost him nought. Our love is not like theirs of old, Our hands are closed, our hearts are cold— For choicest gift of wealth and mind We bring the lame, the weak, the blind, For youth's devotion high The few pale flowers that lurk behind When age has dimmed the eye. The broken cup by folly drained, The faded wreath, the garment stained, A little time, a little thought That brings no loss, that costs us nought, A little gold in offering To Him Who our full safety wrought, Is all the gift we bring. Nay, not with things of smallest worth Should Christians serve the Lord on earth; Christ said, “Your daily crosses take, Bear pain, use trouble for My sake, Deny yourselves for Me, Remembering all I bore, to make Your sinful spirits free.” If wealth, so perilous to hold, Be yours, give freely of your gold— Not the poor pittance pleasure spares From luxury's ideal cares; Nor let the poor and low Deem he with his rich brother shares Nought fitting to bestow. Give God that first, best sacrifice, An humble heart's repentant sighs; Give Him some hours that else were spent In sleep or sloth, or merriment, For prayer and holy deed, The praises of a heart content With all by Him decreed. Christ looketh on our inward life; He knows the cost, He sees the strife, Alike accepted in His sight The rich man's thousand talents bright, Given all in quiet lowliness, And the poor widow's single mite, Saved from her hard distress.</field>
   </doc>
</add>