<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Jeney, Thomas</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Jeney, Thomas</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">jeney thomas</field>
      <field name="author_text">Jeney, Thomas</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1890's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.0609.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">1891</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:463399</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Maister Randolphe Phantasey</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Maister Randolphe Phantasey</field>
      <field name="title_facet">maister randolphe phantasey</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">maister randolphe phantasey</field>
      <field name="title_text">Maister Randolphe Phantasey</field>
      <field name="year_display">1891</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1891</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1891</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463399&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463399&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Jeney, Thomas&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;jeney thomas&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Maister Randolphe Phantasey&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;maister randolphe phantasey&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1891&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1891&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Jeney, Thomas&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Maister Randolphe Phantasey&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Edinburgh&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for The [Scottish Text] Society by William Blackwood and Sons&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1891&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp1933&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;lxi, 401, vi p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Maister Randolphe Phantasey&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 64 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only poem by Jenny included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">VOL. I. Satirical Poems. Square brackets denote editorial insertions or emendations. I. Maister Randolphe Phantasey: a breffe calgulacion of the procedinges in Scotlande from the first of Julie to the Last of Decembre. To the reader. Advyse the well (reader) ere thou reprove my restles mevse to theis estates that tendis; arrest thie Judgement for better behove then bewsye brute oft rashelie reprehendes; thie ffrendlie reporte herein lett not to lend; for what apparant in this state I see, my pen presentes It to thie Judginge Eye. Fforweried w?? cares, and sorrowes source supprest, and worldlie woos of sharpe repulse that bredes vnquyet rest, confusd w?? courtlie cares, a seate of slipper stay, that yeldes the draught of bitter swete to such as drawes y? way, In Silent sort I sought, vnwyst of any wight, to attempt some meane howe well I cold my heavy burden light; where eche delight did strive, attendinge for there torne, what fyttest were for feble myndes, and thus the plee begonne: Abrode, q?? my desire, repose the w?? suche rest as may revyve thie pensive thought w?? sorowe so distrest. But tyme bad me retyre, this is no season mete, for feldishe sportes be nowe exempt that might thie sprit? delighte. Q?? fansye: then enforce thie selffe from suche dispaire, assay yf that thie mevses trades may ought dissolve thie care; pervse some pleasunte stile that may delight the brayne, and prove by practyse of the pen to file the wytt? agayne. But reason did conclude, who bade be ruled by me, Devyne Camenes never cold w?? Mavors rage agree, Ne yet Minerva mevse w?? skill was depelie scande, when as Bellona did decree w?? bloody sworde in hande; ffor who dothe wrest his will to wrastle in eche wronge It is as he shold stope the streame, or sporne against the sone. what yeldes no sure hope the wysest men will grutge, for what procedes of suche effect? the gravest wytt? may Judge. mesure by myrthe some meane that may thie greves disgest; Solace the rage of hevmayne cares w??in a gladsome brest. w?? Silence them soyorne, except that y? canst finde a frend on whom thou maist repose thie secretes of thie mynde. but rarenes of suche one may warne the to bewayre, for Kinde have taught It seldome seen that sewgred speech to spaire. suche is the fraude of faith in silent eares that ringe, where greater poyson is not founde w??in thie scorphion stinge. ffor stedfastnes dothe flie w?? winges of often change, a flyinge birde but seldome seen, her nature is so strange. Tho Silence do allay no rage to stormy thoughte, yet is distrust a bankroote gest, and wronge avalethe nowght. Th'unadventured meane do seldome hope reteane: for what attempt but once atchived to countervale the meane? ffor, as the watrye showers delayes the raginge wynde, so dothe good hope clene put away dispaire owt of y? mynde. a toche stone is eche vse that may thie care recure, and weare away in tract of tyme, for nothing may endure. It was when awtum had fild full the barnes w?? corne, and he that eates and emtyes all away had awtum worne, and wynter windes approcht that doth I-bayre the tren, and Saturnes frost?, that steanes the earth, had perst the tend? grene; and dampishe mystes discendes when tempest? work much harme, and force of stormes do make all cold that somer had made warme; whose lustie hewe dispoiled cold not possesse thie place, ne yet abide Boreas blast? that althing? dothe deface. what reason had decreed I whollie was enclynde, I sought by solitarye meanes to recreat my mynde. But solitarynes is, as the sowthfast sayen, hewe of dispaire, ffoo to thie weale and friendlie to eche payne. for Slender are the greves that Silence do vnlade, for who had seen my stepes might Judge what cares was in my heade. my dowbtfull pace bewrayed the weary trace I tryed, for everie stepe did argewe stryffe, to hewmayne myndes affyed. my mevse was not in plight to alter this discourse, but bett my branes w?? bitter bale and woos of worldlie force. The casualls accident to eche state and degree I did debate, and what It was from daunger to be free of Slipper welthe, and howe the worldlie gwiles are sought, that waistes as winde and faster wears then flame w?? fier is wrought; wherew?? my bewsye heade presented unto me Such sowre change, suche sodaine fall, as in this realme had bee; where I attendant lay in porte of princes pay, did linger forthe my painefull yers prorogd from day to day, whereas I might wyttnes this state w?? rufull Eye, from weale to woo, from welth to wast, and worce if ought might be; ffor through that forraigne change my credytt crakt y? string w?? those w?? whom in faythfull league I longe before had bene. I oft bethought howe that Dame Fortune did assay to flatter me, and sett me upp in court to beare a swaye w?? prince of noble fame, whom if I shold discrye, where nature skilfull poinct? do flowe, or bewtie doth supplie, I shold but heare mayneteyne a volume of her price, and so at lengthe Invade by right the boundes of eche devyse; ffor at her onelye name my mevses all do stay: my pen is not in perfytt plight her graces to displaie. and howe Fortune forethought to heape on me that hape, as trustles to her fickle trades to rowle owt of her lappe, That w?? her friendlie chere bewytcht me w?? her wiles, and wone my wytt? as other mo that trust? her when she smiles. I sawe the Quene, whose will, occurant w?? her yeres, was wone to worke oft that she wold by counsaile of her peres. It was the winged boy had perst her tender thought, and Venus Joyes so tickled her that force avaled nought. On Darlie did she dote, who, equall in this mase, sought to assalt the forte of fame, defenst with yeas and nayes; w?? for a while repulst, and had no passage in, but still porsewt did rase the seige that might the fortresse wyne; who, stronglie thus beseiged w?? battry round aboute, at last was forst to yeld the keis: she cold not hold hym owte; But rendered Sacke and spoile vnto the victors grace: so rytch a pray did not the Grek? by Helens meanes possesse. To regall charge of rule she did advaunce his state, and gave the sworde into his hand that bred Civill Debate. This was affection force, that blewe this gale of wynde; This registreth the found pretence w??in a womans mynde; This calls vs to reporte, and proves the proverbe trewe, that wemens wills are sonest wone in that they after rewe. This brede a brutyshe broile and caused cankred spight, to move the myndes of suche as did envy a strangers might. vnder w?? shade was shrowde an other fyrme intente, and so, by color of that change, to doe what he was bente; w?? made muche myserye, and wrought this realme to wrake, and sturde a stiveling sture amongest the muffled contre packe, that mustred eche where in forme and force of warre, and clapt on armo? for the feld as they comannded warre. The rechles rule I sawe reduced to my mynde the slipper state of worldlie wealth that heare on earth we find. ffor those whose grave advice In Judgement semed vpright, Sawest w?? the skill of expert yeres, was clene devorst of might. There faythfull service sounke, and they, exiled clene, and other mo did stire the sterne that had least skill therein; w?? grated but for gayne, and gropt for private pray, wrestinge suche sence of lawes as did there glosing trades bewray. I sawe howe right was rackt, and shadowed w?? wronge, and treason shone in feaned mindes as doth the somer sone. I sawe the auncyent race, from noble bloode extracte, w?? Rigor chast from native shores, there land? and living? sackt, and some I sawe that sought to beare the sway allone, who fayred as tho that they cold gwide a shipe against y? storm; whose practise if were proved in weldinge such a charge, I do beleve have not the skill in calme to stire a barge. And some I sawe sytt still whose wisdome well I knewe as far excedes as Phebus doth Surpasse Awroras hewe; whose goodlie gwyftes are suche, the more they vnderstande, the more they seeke to learne and knowe and take lesse charge in hande. I sawe the ffrendliee ffoo howe he did sytt and smile, and faund vpon the comon gest w?? craft of crocodile; I sawe the ffrendlie man wounde in a volwyshe weede, and howe the faythfull was enforst with procry to procede; I sawe howe trewe report was bankrowt w?? the rest, that hardlie might susteane the force that open wronge profest; I saw Adthole abridge w?? craft to conquere cost, and forge that fact by forraigne foos that his discent might bost; I sawe what Morton ment by shufflinge for his share, Imbrasinge those that shrowdes the shame of his possessed care; I sawe howe Cassells crowcht, affirmynge yea and na, as redyest when chaunce brings chang to drive and drawe y? way; I sawe Crawforde encroche on Slipperie renowne, that curre favell in the court might retche to higher rowme; I saw how Lyddington did powder It w?? pen, and fyled so his sewgred speche as wone the wills of men; I sawe howe Lyndsey Lurkt, vnconstant of his trade, alluding by his duble meanes that might his lust vnlade; I sawe howe Hewme in hope did hoist the sale aloft, and howe he anker weighed w?? those that most for credyt sought; I sawe howe Ruthven reigned as one of gnators kinde, and howe he first prefferd his ple, respondent to his mynde; I sawe what Maxwell mente in kindlinge the flame, and after how he sought newe meanes to choke the smoke agayne; whose dowble Dealinge did argewe vnconstant fayth, and shamefull wayes blowes forthe the brute y? may record his death. w?? feble force I sawe howe Leonox did entende as thristie of a princlie rewle to regestre his Ende; I saw the weake advise that Darlie did aforde, as yonge in wytt as fewe of yeres to weld the Regall sworde; I saw the Quene was bent, w?? Rigorus entente, to subyect to the thristie sworde the blood of Innocente. And sodainelie I sawe howe Balforde credytt sought, and howe from nought he start aloft to beare the freey in court; and sundrye mo I sawe to wrastle for the tyme, to daunte eche Dome, whom they suspect to drawe w??in there lyne. ffor Adthole bare the swindge, w?? feble skill to rule, but who, bolder then blinde byarde, the proverbe doth reveale. ffor, where th'untaught do teach, there hope groves owt of kinde, that is the wracke to worldlie welthe where blinde doth lead y? blynde. Thus slender was there sage of wisdome clene bereft, for eche man prowld for private pray: the publicke weale was left; ffor theis that did awayte to further eche degree, and floryshe in the comon weale, from counsaile they were free. ffor Murray constant fayth and ardent ?eale to truthe had not the grace to fordge and feane y? worldlie wytt? pursewthe. Nor Hamilton cold have no hope to hold his seate, Nor yett Argile to abide the court: the pirrye was to greate. Rothose might not resyst that stedfastnes profest, nor Glencarne cold averde w?? wrong y? Rigor had inc[r]est; Nor Boide wold not attempt the trades of no mystrust, nor Ogletree concure w?? suche as rewled but for lust; Grange wold not grate for grace, no burden he wold beare, whose horye head, expert in warrs, did bred the courtyers feare. By those was right erect, and wilfull wronge supprest, there Judgement? ever vncontrolde did floryshe w?? the best. Theis sought by civill meanes for to advaunce the realme, and ryfflie did reprove such lawes as damaged the same. Theis were the gravest wytt? that ever did awayte by puplishing suche civill lawes as bettred eche estate. Theis were th'afflicted flocke that Rigor did pursewe, w?? bred the bale in suche as did there hevye myshapes rewe. There fame dothe wyttnes this that gives them there dewe prayse, and comon mouthes dothe mysreporte that wold suche men Imbrace. and bewsye brute complaynes vnto eche Silente eare, that want of those shall once enforce a strange estate to appere. I sawe them chast away, the Quene wold not abide there grave advise that counsaled her to watch a better tide. her will had wounde her so to wrastle in this wronge that no restraint might rest her rage her extremes to suborne. I sawe howe fyckle fame do sore from frend to frende, and made there mouths a pray to suche as cold them apprehende; and howe the willinge eare was sowne redust to wronge, yf ought apperde might proffyt hym or serve to his torne. I sawe the willinge man howe glade he was to live fre from Suspect, and that his means might no occasion give to the sedecious sort, where dyscorde dyd attende, how to Impeche the giltles wight vnwillinge to offende. and some I sawe appeald did ha?ered to bee free, and howe that some w?? willinge myndes complande them selves to me, w?? breed me more vnrest, endost from day to daie, that with my will a thousand tymes I wisht my selffe awaye, that my attendaunce heare might not have wytnest this; or termes of yeres might not Import howe sowre dyscorde is that Boiles in noble bloodes, when fyerye hart begwynes to rage and Reve w?? civill wars, that all Impacience bring? In those devyded myndes that thristes for noble bloode, and seek? no Rigor to redresse but by the civill sworde; In spight of all respect runs muffled w?? there will, as mothes vnto there parent? prayse there trades do frete and spill, and clowdes there former fame that shone in there forbears, and caterpillers to there glore that doth perteyne to those that whilome did floryshe and shone w??in this realme, and left no steane vnto there stocke y? myght Impeche there fame. This sawe I clene reyect, regawrde of no myshape Cold once advyse them to prevent the evell successe y?? had; The porpose they profest in comon movthes did ringe that there intent was for no wrong y? might endanger bringe. yett sawe I howe they slackt there Interprise profeste, I sawe th'occasions they lett slipe that might have helped best. But what avaleth this? lett theis debatement? goo, for Gode will shewe his mightie worke and what perteyns theretoo. Remembrance of theis did newe cause of cares encrease, as thoo that force of nature strive howe to confounde my ease; and what my wearie Lyef have wone w?? such vnrest the powdred heires vpon my head can testify It best. No practise I cold vse that might vnlade my paine: the forge of this mysorder so did beate w??in my brayne; and, restles in this rage, to ease my wearye pace, my mevse bade me retyre my selffe vnto my booke a space; whereas I might decerne (w?? rufull Eye) what Bale was incident in everie estate where Tirant? do prevale, where wicked princes rules, and eke what slaughters made, where restles rage of civill wares do cruell hartes Invade. ffor there bloody pretence do spayre ne kythe ne kyn, ne frende ne foo that Rigour may vnto his danger bringe; where I decerned what ruth oft rigor kept in awe, and cruell force had once opprest w?? might of tirant? lawe. Examples there I sawe, a testymonye plaine, that bloodye feict? dothe aske vengiance and thirst? for blood againe. A president hereof was Cirus, whose delight was ever prest in bloody fect? for to declare his might. Tho makeless yet he was in Riches and in might, This gwerdon was alloted him—a scharpe revenge of spight,— his head dismemb[e]red into a vessell fraught w?? blood of those that felte her force the angry Quene she raught, And w?? theis wordes she said: nowe, Cirus, drink y? fill, nowe slake the thrist w?? gore of suche in rage y? sought to spill. Chambises there I sawe, a mirro? of myscheffe, whose handes enbrewed w?? brothers blood did short his wretched lief. his hatefull bloody brest, so salvaged owte of kinde, record? at Lenghe his fatall ende, a iust rewarde assinde; and while he this conspired, bereft of wytt? he founde a sworde that thrust his body throughe, w?? he of Lief benowmbd; and blodye Brutus that his fatall ende might rewe, and Cassius rightlie gorde hym selffe wherew?? he Cesar slewe. and Bessus tratrous hart, armed w?? the murd[r]ers kniffe, w?? bloodye [fect] against his Kinge bereft his m? Lyef. The drerye dewle I rede of mightie Macedoo, when Clitus death (the frendlie man) w?? teares he sorowed soo; who after bent to fane refusinge kinglie foode had queld hym selffe, a giltie end, had not his frend? w??stoode. The prowd Kinge Dionyse, whose Rigor sore opprest his realme, reveales how he him selfe at last w?? dread was strest; wherein Tirant? may see the fyne of forced feare, a mirror eke for magistrat?, in this prowd prince appeare. No garde his cruell hart of Saftie cold assure, for, dreadinge those whom he ought deme of his complice most sure, hym selffe his bearde, his brest w?? bornynge brands wold ceere, of deathe deserved his gwiltie hart so vexed hym w?? feare. me thought this might Suffyce to represent the fyne of Tirant? force, where Royall harts might at there rage repyne, And magistrates might see what feares and what vnrest in Raginge hartes that thrist? for blood is equallie Imprest; and howe the gwiltles blood that is vniustlie shede dothe crave revenge (o dredfull thinge!) vpon the tirant? seade; And what sowre Successe suche bloody mynd? Imbrace, and howe the rage of tyrant? hart? w?? blood rewarded was, that oft I wysht some wold of newe there woos discryve to warne the rest whom frendlie fayte as yet have left alive; And that the fall of those that in this realme have bee might presse abrode amongest the rest, y? forraigne stat? might see That there vnfrendlie fayte are equal w?? the rest, whom frowarde fortune vncontrold w?? bitter hapes distrest; whereas It might appeare, and all estates might knowe howe frutfull warnynge is to suche as wold be free from woo. Thus mewsinge as I satt, I leand my wearye Arme vnto a stay that for a while might ease my Rovinge brayne. But nothinge cold avale, so muche was my mysease, till, tending downe vnto my booke, the watch forsooke my Eyes, And swete slepe did attempt to alter this discourse, that wasted so my wearie corpes w?? rage of worldlie force. whether this restles rage that I cold not vnlade It was, or ells that still perforce the hevmors of the heade did troble me anewe, as fansyes drives by Dreames, or Morpheus mynded I shold have a traunce of suche remaynes as erst I longe foriudged, and so I might constreane to forme a plote as witt cold worke the braunches in my brayne; There sodainelie I sawe one thrust in at the Doore, who said the Quene is here at hand, and bad avoide befoore. w?? that the light? appeared, the waters were at hande, and orderlie prepared a place whereas the Quene shold stand. The great resort that ought to suche estates pteyane made me to deame that was not she y? had so small a trayne. I knewe her at the sight, then reverence made me ryse, and humble me as best became or dewtie cold devyse. she gave a signe as thoo she wold I should attende vnto her tale, where I might iudge to what she might pretende. my Reverence made and done, then Silence did forwarne the standers by, and all was whusht, &amp; thus the Quene beganne: The Quenes Ma??? complante of a mysordered comon weale. W??in thie warpe of this thie woful twyne, that y? entendes (my Randolphe!) to renewe in forraigne forme, first begwyne w?? myne, nowe dryven to drinke as I did brewe: Inwrape my woos w??in thie carefull clewe, That, when the recorde is spred every where, the state of my comber first may appere. for, seinge the prest to pen as a president, that may I Imparte the Scotyshe fall of peres, and rest as a recorde to be residente w??in thie contempt of thie silent eares, I presse forthe first because thy ex[p]ert yeres Dailie attendent may truelie reveale a whole dyscourse how I did prevale. I presse not forthe amongest the rewfull thronge of those that in this wretched realme have bie, whom vnfriendlie fortune have overthrowen, nor yet complayne I of much myserye, that ever impecht my Royal dignitie, ne yett is there cause whie repyne I shold, for all thing? Succeded my will as I wold. I onelie complaine of the myserable state, that this dysorder in my weale have wrought; where no redresse in tyme cold dilate the extreme wronge that Rigor had tought; I ever did deme, the Rokes once vprought that resisted my will, I might purchase peace, and reconcile the rest w?? frendlie grace. ffor, whollie affected w?? th'affyaunce of will— a mist of error that princes do blinde, I wrested such lawes as might my weale spill, rather then ruled as wisdome assynde; I mysliked such meanes as Impugned my mynde, Ledd w?? th'affection, th'onlie springe and Roote, that all godlie Goverment clerelie wroutethe owte. This enraged some in Armes to concurre, that felt my force as after thou shalte heare; This enforced some w?? Silence to demur, that durst not doo that I bad forbeare; This procured some w?? dread to reteare vnto my trayne, that vnwillinge (God knows) in my assistaunce there fayth did repose. Th'unsure faythe that mystrust procures, Th'unconstant trades that dowbtes do reteane appales franke hartes w?? treacherous desyres, that no frendlie brest may them susteane; in o? mysorder this appeared playne, whereto a while yf thou wilt give eare, a whole discourse hereof you shall heare. I hold It nedles to bragg of my birthe, by Loyall dascent endowed a Quene; my ffather doth wyttnes it even to his death, who in this weale most noblie did reigne, and that halffe a Gwyssian by birth I bene, and howe the Frenshe Kinge in marag did endowe me w?? Royall right, a madlie wydowe. But I cold bost of bewtie w?? the best in Skilfull poinct? of princelie attire, and of the golden gwiftes of natures behest, who filed my face of favor freshe and fayre: my bewtie shynes like Phebus in the ayre, and nature formed my feate? beside in such proport as advanseth my pride. Thus fame affatethe my state to the stares, enfeoft w?? the gwyftes of nature devise, that soundes the retreat to others princes eares whollie to resigne me the chefest price: but what doth it avale to vant in this wyse? for as the sowre sent the swete tast do spill, So are the good gwyftes corrupted w?? ill. Merke, Randolphe, heare, for nowe I begwyne: This was the brere that blotted my browe, muffled affection w?? will for to wyne that wisdome forbade me oft for to doo; for as the stronge dothe make the weake bowe, So did my will owtrestle my wytte, w??owt the restreant of a sensuall byte. my ffather in Fawklande yelded his brethe, who warelie did wealde this comon weale w?? gaine; my goodyer in Flowdon was drawen to his death, by the dynt of a sworde of thie contremen; my mother Quene Governo? of the Gwyssian name, who w?? civill warrs this weale did awast, in Edenbrugh castle she breathed her last. nowe ryffe report dothe brute all abroode, that I am a Gwyssian by the sewrer syde, rather given whollie to weld w?? the sworde, then worke that wisdome have firmelie affied, or vse advise w?? reason alyed, that peace propoundeth to purchase me praise, then to persever in theis Rigorus wayes. But, ledd w?? affection affyed w?? trust, first I begonne to wedd as I wold suche one as I demed wold serve my Lust, rather then might my weale well vpholde, whose tender yeres of counsaile was colde, for, prowde of the pray of princelie estate, where I gave the cheke was redye to mate. Then my court encreast w?? costlie recourse, recountinge the pleasures of youthfull desires, and wanton delight of effemynate force, that staned w?? love there lustie attyres; for everie man, wounded w?? Venus desires, was whollie addict to courtlie resyance, where they resigned there whole affyance. I hardened my ears against suche advise, as tendered my state to advaunce my weale; and welded it w?? welth suppressing suche vice as wrathefull awardement w?? wrong did conceale; Suche there advicement I wold not reveale; I reteaned suche counsaile as wold not Invay, but, as a fytt instrewment prest to my pray, ffytlie affirmed what I liked best, in Rigor, in rage, in right or in wronge, Like subtell foxes, for there behest allured my ears vnto there sugred songe; but in this league I Lyngred to Long: The hye sprynginge floudes may not ay abide, but as Tyme apointeth they torne w?? the tide. O pleasinge bayte, y? faire fyled tonge! O craftie crocodile w?? feaned face! O Subtell Syren w?? sugred songe! O treacherous hart w?? flateringe grace! O counsaile corrupt w?? craftie encrease! O poyson apparent, that danger do bringe in everye age like the Scorphion stinge! O cursed advice that tendes to no weale, but for private pray oppressethe the poore! O sugred Synon, that so do reveale thie forged speche vnto thie willinge eare! O froward wytt that will not forbeare to Lysten vnto there duble advyse, that dothe interrupt eche good enterprise! This brede the broile that stirde vs to stryffe; for those that ever tendered my state cold not abide to see this myscheffe; as I pretended to rule in this rate, they ever attendant my wealth did awayte: but, muffled with the myst of Ignorance, I did mystake there faythfull affyaunce; w?? caused Envye, the Rancor of right, w?? fowle pretence to Invade my dome: So did Revenge, the sparke of dispight, that kindlethe the minde against right or wrong. Thus was I provoked rashelie to Ronne to Seke to Subyect all to the sword, that Impugned my will or resisted my worde. ffirst, th'erle of Murray I hoisted to the horne, and divers that were partakers w?? hym I deninced them rebells for ever forlorne, and there retenewe that durst deale therein: I debarde intercessors intreatinge for hym: no meane might serve this Quarrell to debayte; so muche was enflamed my Rigor and hate. The more ye stope streames the higher they flowe, the hastie blastes do oft revive flame; The more ye Lope trees the higher they growe; so It appeared by his mightie trayne assembled w?? force against me to reigne: The more I sought to seperate those the more they clustred on heapes w?? my foos. Then raged I of newe and not w??owt cause, by reason I cold not rule as I list; I ordened Decrees, and proscrybed theis lawes that all men in armes shold me assyst; and so w?? the sworde to clere vpe the myst I waged Sowldgiers to wrastle therein that I my porpose more easylie might wyne. Theis were enduced w?? Murray to Rone, affyinge there faythe to further his force; Duke Shateleraut, next heire to the crowne, whose Lynyall discente I leave to discourse; Th'erle of Argile, whose might I dred worce, abandoned w?? the bloody Iryshe crewe, that who so they take they helples downe hewe. This savage kinde they knowe no lawe of armes; they make not warrs, as others do, a play; they deale not death by the dredfull harmes; yeld or not yeld who so they take they slea. they save no prysonners for Ransome nor for pay; they hold It hopeles of thie bodye dead, except they see hym cut shorter by the heade. Off there complice was th'erle of Glencarne, Th'erle of Rothose and L. Ogletree, Pretcor and Grange and many Arme in Arme, Rone as assistars in there confederacye: Boide and Pretarroo did thereto agree, and sundrye mo was of there consente to further there purpose as they were bente. The dread of no Enemy cold me appaile, nor yett no travell Endaunte my entent, I mustred my men in Armes to assale; to practise my porpose as I was bente: w?? bloody pretence forwarde I wente; No evell Successe of others mens harmes, inexpert thereof, cold me forwarne. howe can the blinde forejudge what is prest, or tred the dowbtfull stepinge vnseen? howe can the deaffe reyoce w?? eche gest, or take delight in the nightingales tune? how can th'unwise w?? wisdome preseume? Those that bluntlie runs may Light in the breres, and put to thir plunge where no dangere apperes. The Lyttle birde do warne vs bewayre that flickereth oft from tree to tree, mystrustinge eche bushe for dread of the snare; The movse shones the bayte that pleaseth y? eye, Dreadinge the trape endaunger to dye: Thes showes what harmes often do lye in suche sewgred bate as deceyveth the Eye. Warre is a welfayre to th'inexperte; I dreaded no daunger of death to ensewe; No Reason might my Rigor reverte, but thristie of blood I did them pursewe; ffrom place to place I sought them of newe: No stormy blastes cold make me retyre; no daunger of death cold dread my desire. The amased lewsarde w?? the fotemans feare from the wandringe gadlinge hastet? a mayne, that by no compulsion will ells retyre, but, tried by the trode of her bendinge trayne, w?? ferefull stinge she tornethe agayne: oft hastie porsewers do happen suche hape, as may Judge the cause by thafter clape. I rested not to rone owt this race: there slender forces durst not abide: for, as the wolffe with Ravenynge grace The sillie shepe do Scater aside, I chast them still, w?? Rigor alyed, but they pretended to puplishe this polycie, in eschewinge my force to attrye my Tirannye. In Glasco towne I entrenched my bandes, and they in Paselee not far dystant from thence, where erelie on the morrowe, west by the sandes, they gave me Larum w?? warlicke pretence: we were in Armes, but they were gone thence; to the ffeldes we marcht in Battell array, expectinge o? foos, but they were awaye. Th'erle of Leonox I ordaned generall, In whom consisted the confidence I had; I gave hym charge and made hym cheffe of all, but th'erle of Morton was discontent thereat: the contencion ryse to have the vangarde: A creditt oblysht by his amycitree to w?? request I wold not agree. The m? Maxwell, somewhat moved w?? ruthe, as It appeared, to reconcile my meane, on his knees entreated me to hear suche truthe as his report cold iustlie maynteyne: his teares appeared to be forged of payne, whose dowble dealinge did after disclose th'unconstant faith that trechers propose. He humblie entreated he might retorne, pretendinge thereby to color his craft; who, semynge vnwillinge to deale in this action, I Lycensed whom frelie to departe: he ran to my foos to maynteyne that parte, where he betrothed his vnsure trust; to whom also after he appeared vnjust. when fame had brought that the Ll? were gone to Edenbrough towne to wage men of warre, to supplie there force and make them more stronge of expert trayns to Joyne in this Jarre, I hasted forwarde to Interrupt them there; but by the way I harde they were gone from Edenbroughe, and had clene left the towne. They fled to the frontyers to further there force, I rased my campe and retyred my bandes Into the ffythe, where w??owt remorse I rested there goodes and disposed there landes; I reatened there forfetures in my owne hand?; Suche as I suspect of there consent or favored there porpose in prison I pent. and some that had Incurred my blame by worde, or wronge, or other like meane, for redye coigne I compounded with them, that I might better my soulgiers maynteyne: Th'unwonted charge that I did susteane was thus considered, in everie Dome, To Surpasse the yerelie revenewe of my crowne. All this effect, even as I wolde, Th'uneasfull Travell that I did susteane bad me retyre whereas I sholde rest for a space, to devyse what meane I might procure most hurtfull for them: contented herew??, w?? my whole trayne To Hollyrowd house I retorned againe. The Secrete dryftes of there pretensed myndes, The whole recounte of theis proceding? past, The great redowbtes that by such meanes we finde consideratelie weighed and depelie forecast, we puplisht decrees and proclaimed in hast that all o? forces shold assemble on a day in payn of deathe to assist vs in o? way. The tyme was come when that eche man might see the barraigne ffeldes w?? Armed men oresprede; The gredye spoiles where suche a trayne had bee made manye a teare w?? rufull Eye be shede; we marched forwarde o? foos to Invade, w?? Eger thrist to put them to flight, and seke there deathes that sought to dash o? dryft. Amidde w?? rowte yf thow thie selffe had bene, and seen howe I my matters did contryve, thou woldest have reckened me the lustyest Quene that ever Europe fostred heare to Live; Yea if Tomiris her selffe had bene alive, who dreaded great host? w?? her tyrannie, cold not shewe her selffe more valiant then I. a Sodaine brute was blowen all abrode that they had Support of th'englishemen; I Somewhat appaled at that comon worde, fordreadinge the daunger that I might Susteane, and this was mystrusted of my whole trayne: the brutyshe sort are oft glade to heare of suche vane reportes as delighteth the eare. we came to Domfreis to attempt o? might, but all was in vane: o? foos were awaie: there was none there that wold vs resiste, nor yett affirme that I did gainesaye: the M? Maxwell appealed that day vnto my favo?, whom I did remytte: Loo! heare th'abvse of a dissembling wytt. They, vnable to abide or resist my myght, entred perforce into th'inglishe pale; in Carlele they all were constrayned to Light, where the L. Scrowpe entreated them all, and th'erle of Bedforde, Leiventen[e]nte generall of th'inglishe northe, whose fervent affection I ever dreaded to deale in this action. whose noble hart, enflamed wth ruthe to see theis Lls thus driven to dystresse, sought the meanes he cold to advance the truthe, and God forgive me yf I do Judge amysse, that thou thie selffe was perciall in this: what racke? Randolphe, thou thie selffe knowes I retorned a victore w??owt any blowes. Theis Lyngrynge broiles by past and forworne, w?? suche Successe as I nede not repyne, Theis troblesome broiles clene overbloen, the mystes gan clere vpe and eke the sone shyne: I Injoyed my will and all was myne; then I resolved to reforme myne vnrest w?? suche delightes as I liked best, Whereas I sawe oft w?? my Rewfull Eye; ffor God endewed me w?? naturall Ingyne To liberallie, that eche man might see howe theis goodlie gwyftes in me did shyne: as well as the wisest I cold those defyne, albeit I was Led w?? muffled affection and evell advise to stirre in this action. The myserable state this mysorder wrought w?? wofull wracke in this my comon weale I sawe, where oft resorted to my thought the sowre myshapes that discorde doth reveale, where devyded myndes may nothinge conceale; but owtbraythinge Envye, debayte, and stryffe entendes nothinge ells but civill myscheffe. The morall sentence of good regymente: Happie is the realme well governed, and is free from th'ambycious consente; where gainefull spoiles are not desired, nor w?? painefull toiles the headie overcharged; but dewe mynystracion of everie charge, dewlie executed by suche as be sage, Enforceth me oft nowe for to Repyne, recountinge this Sentence in my Silent brayne. A tochestone is this where I cold defyne the want of those that once did maynteyne my publicke weale, while I did reigne ffree from eche care that now dothe appeare, and dailie complaintes enforceth me to heare. My restles mewse forweryed with this can nowe adiudge the great Inconvenyence, and howe necessarie a good counsailor is, that can determyne with learned experience, I have bought to Deare to knowe what difference is ever apparant where wise magistrat? regne, and what retchles Successe the blind dot? maynteyne. The tender youthe to Scence whole Imploide accomptes knowledge evell wone w?? there labo?; The wounded man w?? must the greffe abide of steaching vpe or searinge of the soore, Th'onlie meane his health to restoore, Impacyentlie repuynynge to Suffer this smarte, as all to bad reproves the Sorgyons arte. But as the pacyent? greffe and scolers paine cause them deme bad suche as sewre be best, so want of wisdome causeth vs complaine of everie hape whereby we seme opprest; The pore do pyne for pelffe, the rytch for rest, and when th'extremes of such do vs assaile, we curse o? fayte: o? fortune we bewaile. I wishe my skill wold permytt my desyre to frame my tale w?? suche mete Eloquence, as my Devoire in this might aspier to argewe in caus? most fyttyst for a prince; for I can say Somewhat of experyence, what oft is accident in that vnstable stay where th'unadvysed runs wilfullie astray. Randolphe, Randolphe, It is fyttest for a prince, and suche as have the regyment? of realmes, there Subyect? hartes w?? mildnes to convynce, and iustice mixt avoydinge all extremes; ffor like as Phebus w?? his cherefull beames Do freshlie force the flagrant flowres to floryshe, so rulers mildnes Subyect? love do noryshe. Nowe hast thou harde the hole of my vnhape— my chance, my change, the cause of all my cares; and thou hast harde howe fortune doth me wrape w?? world at will to wyne me to her sknare; But I do dread this warnes me to be wayre of greater trobles nowe Lycklie to ensewe, that may enforce me to complaine of newe. Finis. W?? that I start from slepe, the Slomber left my Eyes, fforiudging what I erst forthought, w?? hevy moude I ryse, And what prefixt I see apparant in my dreame, and howe, to answer all my hope, I hard the Quene complaine; I dowbted then my pace, thryse did my trowbled thought Revolt w?? woo the Loukles lott that in this world is sought. I did forecast eche cares that Kyngdomes do resygne, And eke the Sliperie estate of those for fame that clyme; I reckened the rule that peres and princes hold to be a seat that sonest sinck? when fortune waxeth cold; I demed it daungerous in court to beare a sway, for that my yeres forespent might Judge howe some was worne away, whose change and sodaine fall w?? ruthe recordethe this, that shewe by prouffe a paterne prest howe bryttle hono? is; And eke what stepes of stryffe belonge to highe estate, for that oftyme the seate it selffe do purchaise prevye hate; The leaves whereof do fall as fast as sprowtes do springe that cannot last but worne w?? such, It is so vayne a thinge. And howe the clymmynge vpe is dowbtfull to endure, and that the hope of honors hold is fyckle and vnsure. I did foriudge the dread that dothe vnlad eche blame, for eke from hye discend? the bolt, the fulgent flashe of flame. I weighed warelie to shune the shiftes that schrowdes no shame of suche as robes the meanest sort engrossinge but for gayne, And howe in Judgement sytt? Rigor w?? feaned face, Suppressinge some, advansinge those where right nor reason was. And where Envye doth regne and beares the chefest price, where greater poyson is not founde w??in the cokatryce; And howe deceyte doth forge and feanethe eke his woo, and gives the cupe of bitter swete to pledge his mortall ffoo. And this I thought most strange, howe nature doth forsake the bloode that in her wombe was wrought as doth the lothed snake, And howe a feaned frende do powder so his termes, w?? false effect, that truth can try no trades to trust his meanes, And howe that slipper trust dothe lett no losse to lend, and eke the rarenes to Imbrace th'affyance of a frende; And howe fansye abides no longer then she lust, But as the wynde dothe often chang and is not for to trust. And when all this I thus had weighed w?? many moo, and of suche accident? as theis through eche degree that goo, And howe everye estate is Subyect to Rewyn, and sowner sinck? the highest sort than they that live in meane. And howe o? tyme dothe Rone, as sand owt of the glasse, even as ech howre apoincted is from tyme and tide to passe, And that my yeres forespent w?? sporte of youthfull plaies do nowe abridge my losse of gayne w??in my horye herres; And howe the ffeble threede of Lief vertewe dothe spyne, and shewes the end of everie worke before It dothe begwyne. I then said to my selffe: me thinkes this may assure all those that clyme to honors seate, there state may not endure. The hills of highest hight are sonest perskt with sone; The Silver streames w?? somers drowght are letten oft to Rone; The loftiest trees and groves are Ryfest rent w?? winde; the brushe and breres that thikest growe the flame will sonest find; The loftie Rewynge towres there falls the ffeller bee; most ferse dothe fulgent Lightnyng light where furthest we may see; The Gorgyous pallace deckt and reard vp to the skye are souner shokt w?? wynter Stormes than meaner bwilding? bee; Such hape have loftie myndes that sytt? in highest seate, when hatefull hart? disdeane thereat, and envy therat threat. Vpon the highest mount? The stormy wynd? do blowe; The sewer seate and Quyet lief is in the vale belowe; By reason I regawrde the meane estate most sure, that wayteth on the golden meane and harmles may endure. The man that wyselie work? in welthe doth feare no tid?, when fortune failes dispeareth not, but stedfastlie abid?. ffor he that sendeth stormes w?? windes and wynter blast? and steanes w?? hale the wynter face &amp; fils each soile w?? frost?, he slak? the force of cold, he send? the somer hott, he causethe bayle to stormy hart?, of Joy the spring &amp; Roote. Reader, regawrde this well, as I of force nowe must appoinct thie mewse to merke my verse, thus ruffled vp in rust; And Lerne this last of me: Imbrace thie porpose prest, and lett no storme to blowe thie blast?, to lose thie port of rest. And tho thie gale be great &amp; frowarde fortune fayle, againe when wynde do serve at will hoist not to hye the saile. ffor prowffe may toche the stone to prove this firme and plaine, that no estate may countervale the gyld or golden meane. Finit. Jenye.</field>
   </doc>
</add>