<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Pope, Alexander, 1688-1744</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Pope, Alexander, 1688-1744</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">pope alexander 1688 1744</field>
      <field name="author_text">Pope, Alexander, 1688-1744</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1730's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_2.2272.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1738</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:465914</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">French</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">An imitation of the sixth satire of the second book of Horace ; Hoc erat in Votis, &amp;amp;c. The first Part done in the Year 1714, By Dr. Swift. The latter Part now first added, And never before Printed</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">An imitation of the sixth satire of the second book of Horace ; Hoc erat in Votis, &amp;c. The first Part done in the Year 1714, By Dr. Swift. The latter Part now first added, And never before Printed</field>
      <field name="title_facet">imitation of the sixth satire of the second book of horace</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">imitation of the sixth satire of the second book of horace</field>
      <field name="title_text">An imitation of the sixth satire of the second book of Horace ; Hoc erat in Votis, &amp;c. The first Part done in the Year 1714, By Dr. Swift. The latter Part now first added, And never before Printed</field>
      <field name="year_display">1738</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1738</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1738</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465914&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465914&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Pope, Alexander, 1688-1744&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;pope alexander 1688 1744&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;An imitation of the sixth satire of the second book of Horace ; Hoc erat in Votis, &amp;amp;c. The first Part done in the Year 1714, By Dr. Swift. The latter Part now first added, And never before Printed&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;imitation of the sixth satire of the second book of horace&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1738&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1738&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Pope, Alexander&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1688&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1744&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;An imitation of the sixth satire of the second book of Horace&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Hoc erat in Votis, &amp;amp;c. The first Part done in the Year 1714, By Dr. Swift. The latter Part now first added, And never before Printed&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for B. Motte and C. Bathurst ... and J. and P. Knapton [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1738&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp3148&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;fre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;23 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;An imitation of the sixth satire of the second book of Horace&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Hoc erat in Votis, &amp;amp;c. The first Part done in the Year 1714, By Dr. Swift. The latter Part now first added, And never before Printed&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 29 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE SIXTH SATIRE OF THE SECOND BOOK of HORACE. Lines 133–221 are generally attributed to Pope and may be accepted as his without hesitation. Lines 9–28 may be by Pope, but the attribution is uncertain. The remaining lines are attributed to Jonathan Swift. Hoc erat in votis; modus agri non ita magnus, Hortus ubi, &amp; tecto vicinus jugis aquæ fons, Et paulum sylvæ super his foret: auctius atque I've often wish'd that I had clear For life, six hundred pounds a year, A handsome House to lodge a Friend, A River at my garden's end, A Terras-walk, and half a Rood Of Land, set out to plant a Wood. Dii melius fecere: bene est: nil amplius oro, Maia nate, nisi utWell, now I have all this and more, I ask not to increase my store; But here a Grievance seems to lie, propria hæc mihi munera faxis.All this is mine but till I die; I can't but think 'twould sound more clever, To me and to my Heirs for ever. Si neque majorem feci ratione mala rem, Nec sum facturus vitio culpave minorem; Si veneror stultus nihil horum; “O si angulus ille “Proximus accedat, qui nunc denormat agellum! “O si urnam argenti fors quæ mihi monstret, ut illi, “Thesauro invento qui mercenarius agrum “Illum ipsum mercatus aravit, dives amico ldquo;Hercule! si quod adest, gratum juvat; hac prece te oro Pingue pecus domino facias,If I ne'er got, or lost a groat, By any Trick, or any Fault; And if I pray by Reason's rules, And not like forty other Fools: As thus, “Vouchsafe, Oh gracious Maker! “To grant me this and t'other Acre: “Or if it be thy Will and Pleasure “Direct my Plow to find a Treasure:” But only what my Station fits, &amp; cætera, præter Ingenium;And to be kept in my right wits. Preserve, Almighty Providence! utque soles, custos mihi maximus adsis! Ergo ubi me in montes &amp; in arcem ex urbe removi,Just what you gave me, Competence: And let me in these Shades compose Something inQuid prius illustrem Satiris, Musaque pedestri? Nec mala me Verse as true as Prose; Ambitio perdit, nec plumbeus Auster, Autumnusque gravis, Libitinæ quætus acerbæ. Matutine pater, seu Jane libentius audis, Unde homines operum primos vitæque labores Instituunt (sic diis placitum) tu carminis esto Principium. ?Remov'd fom all th'ambitious Scene, Nor puff'd by Pride, nor sunk by Spleen. In short, I'm perfectly content, Let me but live on this side Trent; Nor cross the Channel twice a year, To spend six months with Statesmen here. ? Romæ sponsorem me rapis: eja, Ne prior officio quisquam respondeat, urgue: Sive Aquilo radit terras, seu bruma nivalem Interiore diem gyro trahit, ire necesse est. Postmodo, quod mihi obsit, clare certumque locuto,I must by means come to town, 'Tis for the Service of the Crown, “Lewis, the Dean will be of use, “Send for him up, take no excuse. The toil, the danger of the Seas; Great Ministers ne'er think of these; Or let it cost five hundred pound, No matter where the money's found; It is but so much more in debt, And that they ne'er consider'd yet. “Good Mr. Dean go change your gown, “Let my Lord know you're come to town. I hurry me in haste away, Not thinking it is Levee-day; Luctandum in turba; facienda injuria tardis:And find his Honour in a Pound, Hemm'd by a triple Circle round, Chequer'd with Ribbons blue and green; How should I thrust my self between? Some Wag observes me thus perplext, And smiling, whispers to the next, “Quid vis insane? &amp; quas res agis? Improbus urguet Iratis precibus; tu pulses omne quod obstat, Ad Mæcenatem memori si mente recurras.I thought the D?n had been too proud, “To justle here among a croud.” Another in a surly fit, Tells me I have more Zeal than Wit, “So eager to express your love, “You ne'er consider whom you shove, “But rudely press before a Duke. Hoc juvat, &amp; melli est, non mentiar: at simul atras Ventum est Esquilias,I own, I'm pleas'd with this rebuke, And take it kindly meant to show What I desire the World should know. I get a whisper, and withdraw; aliena negotia centum Per caput &amp; circa saliunt latus.When twenty Fools I never saw Come with Petitions fairly penn'd, Desiring I would stand their friend. This, humbly offers me his Case— That, begs my int'rest for a Place— A hundred other Men's affairs Like Bees are humming in my ears. “Ante secundam Roscius orabat sibi adesses ad Puteal cras. De re communi scribæ magna atque nova te Orabant hodie meminisses, Quinte, reverti. Imprimat his cura Mæcenas signa tabellis. Dixeris, Experiar: Si vis, potes, addit, &amp; instat.To morrow my Appeal comes on, “Without your help the Cause is gone— The Duke expects my Lord and you, About some great Affair, at Two— “Put my Lord Bolingbroke in mind, “To get my Warrant quickly sign'd: “Consider, 'tis my first request.— Be satisfy'd, I'll do my best:— Then presently he falls to teize, “You may for certain, if you please; “I doubt not, if his Lordship knew— And Mr. Dean, one word from you— Septimus octavo propior jam fugerit annus, Ex quo Mæcenas me cœpit habere suorum In numero, duntaxat ad hoc, quem tollere rheda Vellet, iter faciens, &amp; cui concredere nugas Hoc genus; Hora quota est? Threx est Gallina Syro par? Matutina parum cautos jam frigora mordent: Et quæ rimosa bene deponuntur in aure.'Tis (let me see) three years and more, (October next it will be four) Since Harley bid me first attend, And chose me for an humble friend; Wou'd take me in his Coach to chat, And question me of this and that; As, “What's o' clock?” And, “How's the Wind?” “Who's Chariot's that we left behind? Or gravely try to read the lines Writ underneath the Country Signs; Or, “Have you nothing new to-day “From Pope, from Parnel, or from Gay? Such tattle often entertains My Lord and me as far as Stains, As once a week we travel down To Windsor, and again to Town, Where all that passes, inter nos, Might be proclaim'd at Charing-Cross. Per totum hoc tempus subjectior in diem &amp; horam Invidiæ. Noster ludos spectaverat una; Luserat in Campo: Fortunæ filius; omnes.Yet some I know with envy swell, Because they see me us'd so well: “How think you of our Friend the Dean? “I wonder what some people mean; “My Lord and he are grown so great, “Always together, tête à tête, “What, they admire him for his jokes— “See but the fortune of some Folks! Frigidus a Rostris manat per compita rumor: Quicunque obvius est, me consulit; O bone (nam te Scire, Deos quoniam propius contingis, oportet) Num quid de Dacis audîsti? Nil equidem: Ut tu Semper eris derisor! At omnes Dii exagitent me, Si quicquam. Quid? militibus promissa Triquetra Prædia Cæsar, an est Itala tellure daturus? Jurantem me scire nihil mirantur ut unum Scilicet egregii mortalem altique silentî.There flies about a strange report Of some Express arriv'd at Court, I'm stopp'd by all the fools I meet, And catechis'd in ev'ry street. “You, Mr. Dean, frequent the great; “Inform us, will the Emp'ror treat? “Or do the Prints and Papers lye? Faith, Sir, you know as much as I. “Ah Doctor, how you love to jest? “'Tis now no secret—I protest 'Tis one to me—“Then tells us, pray, “When are the Troops to have their pay? And, tho' I solemnly declare I know no more than my Lord Mayor, They stand amaz'd, and think me grown The closest mortal ever known. Perditur hæc inter misero lux, non sine votis:Thus in a sea of folly toss'd, My choicest Hours of life are lost; Yet always wishing to retreat, O rus quando ego te aspiciam? quandoque licebit, Nunc veterum libris, nunc somno &amp; inertibus horis Ducere solicitæ jucunda oblivia vitæ?Oh, could I see my Country Seat! There leaning near a gentle Brook, Sleep, or peruse some ancient Book, And there in sweet oblivion drown Those Cares that haunt the Court and Town. O noctes cœnæque deûm! quibus ipse meique, Ante larem proprium vescor, vernasque procaces Pasco libatis dapibus. Prout cuique libido est, Siccat inæquales calices conviva solutus Legibus insanis; seu quis capit acria fortis Pocula, seu modicis uvescit lætius.O charming Noons! and Nights divine! Or when I sup, or when I dine, My Friends above, my Folks below, Chatting and laughing all-a-row, O quando faba Pythagoræ cognata, simulque Uncta satis pingui ponentur oluscula lardo?The Beans and Bacon set before 'em, The Grace-cup serv'd with all decorum: Each willing to be pleas'd, and please, And even the very Dogs at ease! Ergo Sermo oritur non de villis domibusve alienis, Nec, male necne Lepos saltet;Here no man prates of idle things, How this or that Italian sings, A Neighbour's Madness, or his Spouse's, Or what's in either of the Houses: sed quod magis ad nos Pertinet, &amp; nescire malum est, agitamus: utrumne Divitiis homines, an sint virtute beati: Quidve ad amicitias, usus rectumne trahat nos: Et quæ sit natura boni, summumque quid ejus?But something much more our concern, And quite a scandal not to learn: Which is the happier, or the wiser, A man of Merit, or a Miser? Whether we ought to chuse our Friends, For their own Worth, or our own Ends? What good, or better, we may call, And what, the very best of all? Cervius hæc inter vicinus garrit aniles Ex re fabellas. Siquis nam laudat Arelli Solicitas ignarus opes, sic incipit.Our Friend Dan Prior told (you know) A Tale extreamly à propos: Name a Town Life, and in a trice, He had a Story of two Mice. Olim Rusticus urbanum murem mus paupere fertur Accepisse cavo, veterem vetus hospes amicum; Asper, &amp; attentus quæsitis, ut tamen arctum Solveret hospitiis animum: quid multa? neque ille Sepositi ciceris, nec longæ invidit avenæ: Aridum &amp; ore ferens acinum, semesaque lardi Frusta dedit, cupiens varia fastidia cœna Vincere tangentis male singula dente superbo: Cum pater ipse domus palea porrectus in horna Esset ador loliumque, dapis meliora relinquens. Tandem urbanus ad hunc, Quid te juvat, inquit, amice, Prærupti nemoris patientem vivere dorso? Vis tu homines urbemque feris præponere sylvis? Carpe viam (mihi crede) comes, terrestria quando Mortales animus vivunt sortita, neque ulla est Aut magno aut parvo leti fuga: quo bone circa, Dum licet, in rebus jucundis vive beatus: Vive memor quam sis ævi brevis. Hæc ubi dicta Agrestem pepulere, domo levis exsilit: inde Ambo propositum peragunt iter, urbis aventes Mœnia nocturni subrepere: jamque tenebat Nox medium cœli spatium, cum ponit uterque In locuplete domo vestigia; rubro ubi cocco Tincta super lectos canderet vestis eburnos, Multaque de magna superessent fercula cœna, Quæ procul extructis inerant hesterna canistris. Ergo ubi purpurea porrectum in veste locavit Agrestem, veluti succinctus cursitat hospes, Continuatque dapes; nec non vernaliter ipsis Fungitur officiis, prælambens omne quod assert. Ille cubans gaudet mutata sorte, bonisque Rebus agit lætum convivam; cum subito ingens Valvarum strepitus lectis excussit utrumque; Currere per totum pavidi conclave, magisque Exanimes trepidare, simul domus alta Molossis Personuit canibus. Tum rusticus, Haud mihi vita Est opus hac, ait, &amp; valeas: me sylva cavusque Tutus ab insidiis tenui solabitur ervo.Once on a time (so runs the Fable) A Country Mouse, right hospitable, Receiv'd a Town Mouse at his Board, Just as a Farmer might a Lord. A frugal Mouse upon the whole, Yet lov'd his Friend, and had a Soul; Knew what was handsome, and wou'd do't, On just occasion, coute qui coute. He brought him Bacon (nothing lean) Pudding, that might have pleas'd a Dean; Cheese, such as men in Suffolk make, But wish'd it Stilton for his sake; Yet to his Guest tho' no way sparing, He eat himself the Rind and paring. Our Courtier scarce could touch a bit, But show'd his Breeding, and his Wit, He did his best to seem to eat, And cry'd, “I vow you're mighty neat.” But Lord, my Friend, this savage Scene! For God's sake, come, and live with Men: Consider, Mice, like Men, must die, Both small and great, both you and I: Then spend your life in Joy and Sport, (This doctrine, Friend, I learnt at Court.) The veriest Hermit in the Nation May yield, God knows, to strong Temptation. Away they come, thro' thick and thin, To a tall house near Lincoln's-Inn: ('Twas on the night of a Debate, When all their Lordships had sate late.) Behold the place, where if a Poet Shin'd in Description, he might show it, Tell how the Moon-beam trembling falls And tips with silver all the walls: Palladian walls, Venetian doors, Grotesco roofs, and Stucco floors. But let it (in a word) be said, The Moon was up, and Men a-bed, The Napkins white, the Carpet red: The Guests withdrawn had left the Treat, And down the Mice sate, tête à tête. Our Courtier walks from dish to dish, Tastes for his Friend of Fowl and Fish; Tells all their names, lays down the law, “Que ça est bon! Ah gouter ça! “That Jelly's rich, this Malmsey healing, “Pray dip your Whiskers and your Tail in.” Was ever such a happy Swain? He stuffs and swills, and stuffs again. “I'm quite asham'd—'tis mighty rude “To eat so much—but all's so good. “I have a thousand thanks to give— “My Lord alone knows how to live.” No sooner said, but from the Hall Rush Chaplain, Butler, Dogs and all: “A Rat, a Rat! clap to the door— The Cat comes bouncing on the floor. O for the Heart of Homer's Mice, Or Gods to save them, in a trice! (It was by Providence, they think, For your damn'd Stucco has no chink) “An't please your Honour, quoth the Peasant, “This same Dessert is not so pleasant: “Give me again my hollow Tree! “A Crust of Bread, and Liberty.</field>
   </doc>
</add>