<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Arwaker, Edmund</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Arwaker, Edmund</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">arwaker edmund</field>
      <field name="author_text">Arwaker, Edmund</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1700's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_2.0038.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">1708</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464713</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Truth in Fiction ; Or, Morality in Masquerade. A Collection of Two hundred twenty five Select Fables of Aesop, and other Authors. Done into English Verse. By Edmund Arwaker</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Truth in Fiction ; Or, Morality in Masquerade. A Collection of Two hundred twenty five Select Fables of Aesop, and other Authors. Done into English Verse. By Edmund Arwaker</field>
      <field name="title_facet">truth in fiction</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">truth in fiction</field>
      <field name="title_text">Truth in Fiction ; Or, Morality in Masquerade. A Collection of Two hundred twenty five Select Fables of Aesop, and other Authors. Done into English Verse. By Edmund Arwaker</field>
      <field name="year_display">1708</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1708</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1708</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464713&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464713&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Arwaker, Edmund&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;arwaker edmund&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Truth in Fiction ; Or, Morality in Masquerade. A Collection of Two hundred twenty five Select Fables of Aesop, and other Authors. Done into English Verse. By Edmund Arwaker&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;truth in fiction&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1708&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1708&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Arwaker, Edmund&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Truth in Fiction&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Or, Morality in Masquerade. A Collection of Two hundred twenty five Select Fables of Aesop, and other Authors. Done into English Verse. By Edmund Arwaker&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;J. Churchill&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1708&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0140&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;[8], xvi, 326 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Truth in Fiction&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Or, Morality in Masquerade. A Collection of Two hundred twenty five Select Fables of Aesop, and other Authors. Done into English Verse. By Edmund Arwaker&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 473 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Quicquid agunt homines, Votum, Timor, Ira, Voluptas, Gaudia, discursus; nostri est Farrago Libelli. Juven. Sat. I.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">BOOK I. FABLE I. The Peasant and Hercules: Or, No Pains, no Profit. A Peasant stock'd his Waggon in a Slough, And saw no likely Prospect to get through; Down on a Bank the lazy Lubber lay, And, when he should have Labour'd, fell to Pray: Thus did himself from Toil and Trouble spare, And on the easie Gods cast all his Care: But most to Hercules his Suit address'd, For he was strongest, and cou'd help him best. The God reply'd, You seek my Help in vain, While, for your own Relief, you take no Pain: Fall to your Work, and cease your idle Pray'r; Actions, not Words, must manage this Affair: Your busie Shoulders to the Wheel apply, And when you strive to move it, so will I. The MORAL. ‘Unactive Wishes, slow Concessions find; ‘Heav'n hears no Pray'rs, but with Endeavours join'd: ‘He who from thence hopes to obtain his End, ‘Must, by his own Efforts, himself befriend. ‘The Wretch, who ne'er exceeds a faint Desire, ‘Goes but half-way to what he would acquire. ‘He that to Vertue's high Rewards would rise, ‘Must run the Race, before he gains the Prize. ‘Alcides thus was for his Labours fam'd, ‘His Trophies rose from Monsters which he tam'd: ‘He his Renown by great Exploits enhanc'd, ‘And bore the Heav'n to which he was advanc'd. FABLE II. Jupiter and the Tortoise: Or, Home is Home. Jove treated all his Creatures at a Feast, Only the Tortoise came not with the rest: The angry God resented her Delay, And sent to know the reason of her Stay. She answer'd him, That in her homely Shell She rather wish'd, than in his Court, to dwell. Then on your Back, said he, where-e'er you go, You still shall carry what you value so. The MORAL. ‘The Wise, that are enclin'd to live at Ease, ‘And Reason, more than Appetite, do please, ‘Relish the mean Repasts their Home affords, ‘More than the Dainties of luxuriant Boards: ‘Their Liberty does their coarse Fare digest, ‘And makes each homely Meal a sumptuous Feast. FABLE III. The Ass, Ape, and Mole: Or, Sufferings lightned by Comparison. An Ass, an Ape, and Mole, by diff'rent fates, In joint Affliction made Associates, From the gay Crowd of happy Beasts withdrew, To tell their Grievances, and mourn them too. The Ass, his Ears, as what expos'd him, scorns, And blames his Stars, he was not arm'd with Horns; For so he might himself from Wrongs defend, Repel his Foe, and vindicate his Friend. The Ape reply'd, She thought that Want but slight, Since he was made for Burden, not for Fight; But she had greater reason to repine, Worse us'd by Nature than the filthy Swine; For while on them, a Tail, tho' little, grew, Her Nakedness was made a publick Shew. The Mole, who heard them thus themselves bemoan, And thought their Suff'rings lighter than her own; Desir'd they wou'd their Troubles calmly bear, And turn a while their murm'ring Thoughts to her, Who spent in horrid Darkness all her days, And saw no Objects to dislike, or praise. The MORAL. ‘Men, who their own Misfortunes only weigh, ‘Think none so wretched, so oppress'd as they; ‘But when their Woes with others they compare, ‘With greater Patience their Afflictions bear; ‘And less, the Loads themselves sustain, regret, ‘Because their Neighbours under greater sweat. FABLE IV. The Poet and Clown: Or, Least alone, when alone. A Country Bumpkin, unrefin'd and rude, Disturb'd a Poet's pleasing Solitude; And finding him, as he suppos'd, alone, (Tho' in the noblest Conversation) Ask'd, Why that solitary Life he lov'd, From the Delights of Company remov'd? The Student, thus diverted from his Books, Reply'd, (and back'd his Words with angry Looks) Till you intruded, I was less alone, But find your Company is worse than none. The MORAL. ‘They who in Study do their Time employ, ‘And with their Books, or Thoughts, themselves enjoy: ‘Each pleasing Minute to Retirement gain'd, ‘Are with delightful Converse entertain'd: ‘But when by strong Necessity drawn thence, ‘And forc'd into the World's Impertinence; ‘In Crowds most lonesome to themselves appear, ‘And find their only Solitude is there. FABLE V. The Mule: Or, The Boaster humbled. A pamper'd Mule fat with High keeping grew, And (as 'tis usu'l) was grown haughty too; His Birth and Parentage did highly boast, And what a Price the Horse his Father cost; How often on New-market-Heath he run, How many Plates and Guinea's he had won: Hence the vain Fopling did himself admire, Because he was so like his noble Sire. But, in the height of all his vaunting Pride, He was led out on Bansted-Downs to ride; Where (tho' he vainly to the Course aspir'd,) E're half a Heat was run, he sunk and tir'd. This check'd his Pride; and thus, in doleful tone, The humbled Creature did himself bemoan; I must acknowledge, my Descent was base, And what I call'd an Horse, was but an Ass. The MORAL. ‘Thus prosp'rous Fools, like Bladders newly blown, ‘Swell high, and hardly by themselves are known; ‘Forget the Dunghills whence the Mushrooms grew, ‘And boast themselves to be the Lord knows who: ‘When crush'd by Fate, like Bladders broke, they fall, ‘And sink into their mean Original; ‘Own their Mistake; and all their Vapours past ‘Prove but a noisie and a noisom Blast. FABLE VI. The Fox and Hare: Or, Prize what you have. A Fox and Hare to Jove their Wants make known; Each seeks the other's Parts, and slights his own: The crafty Reynard, Kayward's Speed desires; And nimble Kayward, Reynard's Craft requires. But Jove reply'd, My Favours I dispense To all, according to their Exigence: Reynard, your Craft, your Want of Speed supplies; And Kayward's Safety in her Swiftness lies: Her Head your Craft, your Heels her Speed refuse; Let each the Gift adapted to him use: Or, when your mortal Foes your Lives invade, By wrong Dependance, both will be betray'd. The MORAL. ‘Impartial Heav'n has so its Gifts address'd, ‘That all are favour'd with what suits them best; ‘And in peculiar Ornaments excell, ‘Which, plac'd on others, wou'd not sit so well. ‘In Beauty some, and some in Honour shine; ‘To Labour some, and some to Mirth encline; ‘The Slow are Steady; the Unhealthy, Learn'd; ‘The Homely, Wise; the Simple, Unconcern'd; ‘Wealth keeps the Rich at Ease; Content, the Poor; ‘Each has his Talent, and in that a Store. ‘But where the Lot appointed does not please, ‘Desire of Change, destroys Content and Ease: ‘As when the Shooe too strait, or wide is grown, ‘The restless Wearer's pinch'd, or tumbl'd down. FABLE VII. The Oak and Reed: Or, The Bully slighted. An Oak, that much his Bulk and Stature priz'd, And all his Fellows of the Wood despis'd, Did haughtily a slender Reed defie, And wish'd they might their Strength in Combat try: To whom the Reed (regardless of his Pride, And vain Bravado's) modestly reply'd; The Challenge you have offer'd, I refuse, Contented with the Weakness you abuse; While pliantly I bend to ev'ry side, I all the Rage of fiercest Storms deride; But you who dare their Fury, I shall see Soon levell'd with the Ground, and scorn'd by me. The MORAL. ‘Courage is least in noisie Rant express'd, ‘A modest Silence recommends it best: ‘Insulting Bravo's, who their Prowess boast, ‘Find it least helpful, when they need it most: ‘And they who give Affronts, less Honour gain, ‘Than they who pass them by with wise Disdain. FABLE VIII. The Crab and Fox: Or, Beside the Mark. A gadding Crab, that in the Sea was bred, Rambl'd a-shore, and like a Farmer fed; But, by a Fox unfortunately spy'd, And made his Prey, own'd, she deserv'dly dy'd; She justly bore the Fate she might prevent, Had she not wander'd from her Element. The MORAL. ‘Unsettl'd Fools, who their own Bus'ness quit, ‘Atchieving things for which they are unfit, ‘The Punishment of sure Miscarriage bear, ‘For rash Attempts beyond their proper sphere. FABLE IX. The Daw: Or, Affected Quality exploded. A Daw, in Peacock's pilfer'd Plumes array'd, Thought she a more than common Figure made: She proudly did her fellow-Daws contemn, And to the Peacocks fled, and flock'd with them: But there out-acted what she seem'd to be; None strutted so, or look'd so big as she. The wiser Birds, who knew excessive Pride Did not true Worth express, but Meanness hide, Found the Impostor out, and with disdain, Unrigg'd, and sent her to her Mates again. The MORAL. ‘When Men of Mean Extraction ape the Great, ‘(Tempted by Riches to that vain Conceit) ‘They fondly over-act the Part they Play, ‘And Baseness, in affecting State, betray: ‘While all the truly Noble, free from Pride, ‘The aukward Mimicks, in their Height, deride: ‘Who (thinking Merit is in Pomp express'd) ‘Out-run their Fortunes, and become a Jest. FABLE X. The Crow and Wolves: Or, Service for Self-Ends. While an officious Crow, for private Ends, With diligence a Herd of Wolves attends, She asks to be Partaker of their Prey, As she was their Companion all the Way; Alledging, She did duly on them wait, And bore her Part in all their turns of Fate. The angry Wolves thus her Demands reprove; It is our Booty, not our Selves you love: You, if the Gods our Ruin had decreed, As soon on us, as on our Prey, wou'd feed. The MORAL. ‘Thus Selfish Men their whole Devoir direct ‘To those, from whom they Benefits expect; ‘But, when their Hopes are baulk'd, it will appear, ‘If they are real Friends, or unsincere: ‘Occasion sets them in the truest light, ‘And shews the Knave behind the Parasite: ‘For they, if Fortune did a Turn afford, ‘Wou'd prey on those they seemingly ador'd. FABLE XI. The Dog and Shadow: Or, All covet, all lose. A hungry Dog, that to the Shambles went, Sharp-set, and with felonious Intent, Saw there the Meat was very fresh and good, And found Temptations not to be withstood; Then, on what's next to hand, commits a rape, And takes a Pond, to favour his escape. While there he swam, and bore along his Prey, He saw its Shadow in the Water play; Unwisely this, another Joint he thought, And dropt the true, as at the false he caught. Thus, with vain Hope, pursuing greater Gains, He lost the Purchase of his former Pains; Then vents, in howling tone, this just Complaint, To find himself so cheated by a Feint: Fool that I was, who vainly seeking more, Lost the sufficient Food I had before! Now to my Kennel I must sneaking go, With empty Hopes, and empty Stomach too. The MORAL. ‘Contented Men no Disappointment dread, ‘Their Wishes ne'er Sufficiency exceed: ‘But they, whose vast Desires no limits know, ‘Miss what they seek; and what they have, forego. ‘Ixion-like, baulk'd of their Juno's Charms, ‘They find a Cloud in their deluded Arms. FABLE XII. The Lion superannuated: Or, False Friends, base Enemies. A Lion, that in heat of Youth and Blood, With fierce Exorbitance disturb'd the Wood, Injur'd his Fellows, and provok'd their Rage, Met just Revenge in his declining Age. The Boar and Bull, with pointed Tusk and Horn, Defie his Anger, and his Weakness scorn: Ev'n the dull Ass, to give unusu'l Proof Of active Warmth, insults him with his Hoof. At which Indignity, the gen'rous Beast Thus his Resentment, with deep sighs, express'd: I justly bear return'd Affronts, from those Whom former Injuries have made my Foes; But by this Sluggard to be thus abus'd, Whom I have always serv'd, and kindly us'd, This pierces deeper than the Wounds they give: In what mistaken Measures did I live, That while such pow'rful Enemies I made, I chose no Friends, but who my Choice upbraid? The MORAL. ‘While thou art Great, be Good; on no Pretence ‘Exert thy Pow'r to offer Violence: ‘For injur'd Sufferers will wait a Change, ‘And find their time to take a sharp Revenge. ‘Be therefore cautious to distinguish Friends, ‘Who seek thy Int'rest, who their private Ends: ‘For they who court thee only on Design, ‘Will prove thy Fortune's Followers, not thine: ‘Shadows they are, that, when the Sun declines, ‘Forsake the Things they wait on, while it shines. FABLE XIII. The Ape and her Whelps: Or, The Fondling ruin'd. An Ape, that Twins into the World had brought, Lov'd one, and hated t'other, to a fault: For the Rejected Whelp she took no care; The Darling, from her Arms cou'd never spare: Till, in her sleep, she, by too close a hug, In height of Fondness, Overlaid her Pug. The Dam, thus of her Favourite depriv'd, Express'd some small Concern for him that liv'd; Who soon grew up, and very hopeful prov'd, Because, tho' less, with greater Prudence lov'd. The MORAL. ‘Parents, whose Love to Children oft' is blind, ‘To those they most Indulge, are most Unkind: ‘For Youth, that wants Discretion what to choose, ‘Declines to Vice, when giv'n too great a Loose, ‘Hence the fond Father, by his sad Mistake, ‘Finds his Hopes blasted, and his Son a Rake: ‘But stricter Discipline to Virtue tends, ‘Improves the Child, and gains the Parent's Ends. FABLE XIV. The Elm and Oxen: Or, Involuntary Harms, excusable. A stately Elm, that many Years had stood, And over-top'd his Neighbours of the Wood; Cut down at last, and order'd to be sawn, Was to the Pit, by sweating Oxen, drawn. The Tree believ'd himself unkindly us'd, And of Ingratitude the Beasts accus'd; That they, whom he had fed, and shelter'd long, Unmindful of his Kindness, did him Wrong, And, void of Pity, drag'd him through the Mire, Whose Age, and Love, did more Respect require. The faultless Beasts, to sooth his Woe, reply'd, Our Sighs, our Groans, and ev'ry goaded Side, Shew how in all your Pains we sympathize, Whose weighty Grief on us more heavy lies. This soft, kind Answer, pacify'd the Beam, And he no more griev'd for himself, but them. The MORAL. ‘The Harms which Men, by loath'd Compulsion, do, ‘Are not their Act, nor shou'd we think them so: ‘And all who with unjust Reproach, and Cries, ‘Condemn involuntary Injuries, ‘Their Reason, less than Children whipt, command, ‘Who burn the Rod, but soon forgive the Hand. FABLE XV. The Gnat and Bee: Or, Young Idlers, Old Beggars. An airy Gnat, bred by the Sun's warm Rays, That had no thought of feeling colder days; And no Provision made all Summer long, But trifl'd it away in empty Song; With want of Food, and Winter's piercing Frost, Famish'd, and chill'd, and ready to be lost; From an industrious Bee Relief implor'd, Whose House she saw was plentifully stor'd; And, for the Favour, offer'd to impart To all the Young Ones, her melodious Art. But the more frugal Bee, who well observ'd The reason why this Idler justly starv'd, The pressing Unthrift modestly deny'd, And with this mild, but home Rebuke, reply'd: Elsewhere, my Friend, your vain Instructions try, My Off-spring shall on mine alone rely; Bred to such Work as is its own Reward, And will from Cold and Hunger be their Guard. The MORAL. ‘While early Industry, and timely Cares, ‘Provide Supports for our declining Years; ‘An idle, thriftless Youth, gives sure Presage ‘Of an unpity'd Penury in Age. FABLE XVI. The Sun, and Wind: Or, Virtue heightned by Adversity. Between the boistrous Wind, and scorching Sun, A warm Dispute for Preference begun: And both agreed, the Right on either side, By a decisive Issue should be try'd; That he, whose Influence, with most Success, Cou'd make a Traveller himself Undress, Shou'd be acknowledg'd the Superiour Pow'r, And bear the Trophies of a Conquerour. The hasty Wind begun with blustring Rage, And in a Tempest did the Man engage: But as the Storm with greater fury blew, He closer still his ruffl'd Garments drew; Mended his pace, impatient of the Cold, And, as the Wind encreas'd, kept faster hold. To be thus baffl'd, angry Boreas storm'd, And, since his fiercest Blasts no more perform'd, No longer of his Breath wou'd be profuse, For which his Porridge had more pressing Use. This Disappointment smiling Phœbus saw, And when his Rays had made the Clouds withdraw, Pointed the Vigour of his fiery Beams Against the Man, distracted with Extreams. At first he brought him to a gentle Heat, Then, by degrees, improv'd it to a Sweat; And soon, a Fire, too hot to be withstood, Glow'd in his Face, and swelter'd in his Blood: He panted, breathless grew, began to faint, And sought a Shade to favour his Complaint; Then threw his Cloaths, that burden'd him, away, And gave the Sun the Honour of the Day. The MORAL. ‘When Blasts of adverse Fortune, like the Wind, ‘Wou'd shock the Temper of a steady Mind, ‘The Brave, their firm Resolves, unalter'd, hold, ‘Taught by the rustling Tempest to be Bold; ‘And, in a dark Eclipse, give greatest light, ‘As Stars display their Lustre most by Night. ‘But when Prosperity, with soft'ning Rays, ‘Too warm a Sun-shine round the Soul displays, ‘Its yielding Virtue, less severe and nice, ‘Insensibly becomes dissolv'd in Vice: ‘So Iron, pliant, through excess of Heat, ‘Into all Forms is eas'ly cast, or beat. FABLE XVII. The Fox, and Sick Hen: Or, Self-Preservation natural. A Fox, when visiting the Poultrey's Shed, Observ'd a groaning Hen, that kept her Bed, And, with feign'd Friendship, cloaking deadly Hate, Wou'd fain have felt her Pulse, to know her State. To whom Dame Partlet, almost dead with Fear, Reply'd, I cannot bring my self so near, Through all my Limbs such feeble Shiverings go; But were you gone, the Fit wou'd leave me too. The MORAL. ‘Self-Preservation none neglect, but Fools; ‘'Tis the first Lesson taught in Nature's Schools: ‘From thence we learn all noxious things to shun, ‘By whose Insults we fear to be undone; ‘And restless, at their dreaded Presence, grow; ‘Which, if we are not Sick, will make us so. ‘At thoughts of Dying, we become shagreen, ‘And start at Death, in any Object seen: ‘But such base Cowards just Reproaches bear, ‘Who kill themselves, to shun the Fate they fear. FABLE XVIII. The Kid and Wolf: Or, Mistaken Measures. A rambling Kid, that from his Dam had stray'd, Was by a Wolf an easie Captive made: The trembling Creature, young, and fond to live, Devis'd this Shift, his Freedom to retrieve: Since, Sir, said he, I cannot be repriev'd, Pray let me Die as jocund as I Liv'd: Sing one brisk Air, that I may shew my Skill, And Dance a Fit, then eat me at your Will. Sure of his Prey, the Wolf did soon comply, Nor wou'd so modest a Request deny: But he, whose Voice was hoarse, and Throat was foul, In his Attempts to Sing, began to Houl. A Pack of Hounds, that just were running by, Knew his harsh Note, and follow'd him, Full-Cry. Alarm'd at this, he had no time to stay; (His Safety more concern'd him, than his Prey) He left the Kid, to shake his Heels alone, And rather chose to exercise his own. Freed from his Fear, and of his Fault asham'd, He thus himself, for his Miscarriage, blam'd: Ah, wretched Fool! that such wrong Measures took, To turn Musician, who was bred a Cook! Aiming to Sing, I let my Booty go, And now I may go Whistle for it too. The MORAL. ‘Thus Fools, who indiscreetly slight the Arts ‘To which wise Nature do's adapt their Parts; ‘And Works, for which they are unfit, pursue; ‘Miscarry in their Pains and Credit too. FABLE XIX. The Peacock and Nightingale: Or, Enough's a Feast. The rich plum'd Peacock, kept by Juno's side, (With those Advantages not satisfy'd) Complain'd, That Philomel's melodious Voice Charm'd all the Groves, and made the Swains rejoyce; All list'ned, her delightful Songs to hear, While his harsh Note offended ev'ry Ear. Juno reply'd, You may with this dispense, Since Each has his peculiar Excellence: Her Tunes to more advantage are express'd, But you, my Bird, in nobler Plumes are dress'd. The MORAL. ‘Since Providence do's best for Mortals chuse, ‘Covet no Good reserv'd; none giv'n, refuse. ‘Heav'n largely will our real Wants supply, ‘And not our Lust, but Reason, gratifie. ‘Why shou'd we Grief, at others Joys, express, ‘Who have enough wherein to acquiesce? FABLE XX. The Lion and Frog: Or, A great Noise, a great Nothing. A Lion, by surprizing Noise, alarm'd, Rowz'd; and himself for sharp Encounter arm'd: He thought it a Rhinoceros at least, Or some unknown and more Gigantick Beast: Long time he list'ned, and almost did fear, 'Till he beheld the Enemy appear: But when he found a Frog made all that Noise, A puny Creature, little else but Voice; He spurn'd the slimy Insect with disdain, And said, Thou shalt not tempt my Rage again. The MORAL. ‘When you loud Rant, or noisie Boastings, hear, ‘Despise the Authors, and suppress the Fear. ‘Such Rodomonts can do you little wrong, ‘Whose only dang'rous Weapon is their Tongue. ‘From loaded Cannon Men may dread a Wound, ‘Where Execution still precedes the Sound: ‘But Stent'rophonick Tubes offenceless roar, ‘They do no mischief after, nor before. FABLE XXI. The Wolf disguised: Or, A Saint without, a Devil within. A rav'nous Wolf, addicted much to steal, (That he might better his Designs conceal) In borrow'd Sheep-skin Dress himself array'd, And thus disguis'd, his Pranks securely play'd. The Shepherd, who observ'd his Flock decay, And thought their Number lessen'd ev'ry Day, A stricter Watch about his Folds did keep, And found the Wolf in the dissembled Sheep: He seiz'd the Thief, and hang'd him on a Tree, A sad Example for all Wolves to see. The Neighbours wonder'd what the Man design'd, To hang his Sheep; and said, He sure was blind: For so much Rigour they ne'er saw before, And thought he cou'd not use a Wolf with more. But he reply'd, This Sheep in outward Shew, Prov'd a meer Wolf when he my Weathers slew. The MORAL. ‘No Credit to Appearance shou'd be giv'n, ‘Since harden'd Wretches wou'd impose on Heav'n: ‘Their rotten Hearts with specious Shew they paint, ‘And hide the Dev'l behind the seeming Saint. ‘Unmask the Hypocrites, and look within, ‘Their Virtue goes no deeper than the Skin: ‘And Wise Men never will Appearance prize, ‘But fair Pretences, for foul Ends, despise. FABLE XXII. The Fox and Lionness: Or, Rarity heightens Pleasures. A saucy Bitch-Fox durst her Queen upbraid, That but one Whelp at ev'ry Birth she had. The Lioness reply'd, But One indeed, But that a Lion, and of Royal Breed. The MORAL. ‘We shou'd not Things by their Abundance rate, ‘'Tis Merit gives them their true Estimate: ‘The Firmament do's many Stars display, ‘But 'tis one Sun alone that gives us Day. ‘Tir'd with the frequent Use, we Pleasures slight; ‘Their Rarity inhances their Delight. ‘Tho' from one Sun we Light's great Blessing find; ‘The Favour multiply'd, wou'd strike us blind. FABLE XXIII. The Horse and Ass: Or, Pride must have a Fall. A Horse, with stately Trappings proud and gay, Neighing aloud, and scouring o'er the Way, Was by a burden'd Ass stopt on his Road, And forc'd to wait on the obstructing Load. Enrag'd such Dulness shou'd his Speed arrest, He champt the Bit, and rated thus the Beast: Sluggard, Make Way, or thy dull Sides shall feel My sharp Resentment, from my active Heel. The Ass was frighted so, he durst not Bray, But, with due Rev'rence, gave his Honour Way: Who, in his Course, (straining himself too sore) Soon broke his Wind, and was of Use no more: No more rich Furniture adorn'd his Back, Condemn'd to cary an ignoble Pack. The Ass, arriving at the Carrier's Stage, Beheld him in this homely Equipage, And said, Great Sir, What did this Change produce? Where's your Lac'd Saddle, and Embroider'd Hoose? Where your Gilt Bosses, and your Studded Reins? Can you submit to take such slavish Pains? Can you be with a Pack and Bells content, An Ass's Load, and a Fool's Ornament? Think, when this Burden do's your Shoulders gall, Your lofty Pride deserv'd so great a Fall. The MORAL. ‘Thus Men of Wealth and Honour, vainly Proud, ‘Look with Contempt on the Inferior Croud; ‘But (rifled of their Titles and their Store) ‘Meet just Disdain from those they Scorn'd before: ‘The Insolence which in their Height they shew, ‘Makes them Despis'd, when Fortune brings them Low. FABLE XXIV. The Sick Impostor: Or, Prevarication Punish'd. An Impious Wretch, and Poor, as Wicked too, By Sickness, found Just Heav'n gave Vice its due: He pray'd the Gods, with more than usual Zeal, To spare his Life, and his Distemper heal; And promis'd, if they wou'd reverse his Doom, To load their Altars with an Hecatomb. The Gods, to try how he wou'd keep his Word, Granted his Suit, and former Health restor'd. But he, that had not any Beast to give, Did more to break, than pay his Vow, contrive: With that Design, he trac'd vast Tracts of Ground, And gather'd all the scatter'd Bones he found; And, when the promis'd Number was compleat, Hop'd, with that Sham, the Deities to cheat; Then on an Altar the bare Off'ring laid, And thought his Vow sufficiently was paid. The Pow'rs thus mock'd, on sharp Revenge conclude, To suit his Falshood and Ingratitude: And, by his Bed, appearing in a Dream, Bid him repair to an adjacent Stream; And near its Bank a certain Place assign'd, Where he shou'd dig, and mighty Treasures find. The Fellow, on this sleeveless Errand sent, (Like April-Fool, on Wild-Goose Chase intent) With haste, that wou'd admit of no delay, Went on, but took a Tartar by the Way: Among a Pack of roving Thieves he fell, Who made him Pris'ner, stript, and drub'd him well: To whom the greater Cheat, to buy his Peace, Promis'd a Thousand Pound for his Release. The MORAL. ‘Liars, embolden'd by strange Impudence, ‘Are always ready at a coin'd Pretence: ‘To gain their Ends, all Falshoods they devise, ‘Play foul with Heav'n, and glory in their Lies. ‘But they who with the Gods prevaricate, ‘Are justly punish'd with a proper Fate: ‘The angry Pow'rs infatuate the Cheats ‘To Credit, and to Perish, by Deceits. FABLE XXV. The Hares and Eagles: Or, Every one for Himself. The Hares a Battle with the Eagles sought, And Succours from the wary Foxes sought. They answer'd; We wou'd scarce our selves expose, But that we know your Courage, and your Foes. The MORAL. ‘Some Men on Camps their close Attendance pay, ‘And wait, like Vultures, there, in hopes of Prey: ‘For they (however Victory enclines) ‘By gainful Plunder, compass their Designs. ‘The Needy Wretch, that scarce is worth a Groat, ‘To raise himself, do's baneful War promote: ‘He ventures nothing, yet obtains his Wish; ‘As Anglers best in troubl'd Waters fish. FABLE XXVI. The Wolf and Ram: Or, Suspicion gives Security. A Wolf, that hardly scap'd pursuing Hounds, And cou'd do little else but lick his Wounds, Desir'd a Ram, that at a distance stood, To bring him Water from the neighb'ring Flood: For if he might some help for Drink entreat, Himself, he said, wou'd make a shift for Meat. The Ram, that guess'd what Shift he meant, reply'd, That friendly Office should not be deny'd; But that I fear, if I should prove so kind, The Meat you mean, wou'd not be far to find. The MORAL. ‘Dissembling Villains wou'd, by Art, prevail ‘To gain their Ends, when open Measures fail: ‘But Wise Men (apprehensive of the Cheat) ‘Taught by Suspicion, their Designs defeat. FABLE XXVII. The Mourning Widow: Or, In Dock, Out Nettle. A brisk young Lady, of good Air and Mien, Who had not much exceeded sweet Fifteen, But a whole brace of Weeks had been a Wife, And lik'd the Pleasures of a Marry'd Life; (Nor cou'd she chuse, 'twas yet but Honey-Moon, And Wedlock seldom shews its Sting so soon) Found all her dawning Joys with Clouds o'erspread; Her Husband Dying on his Nuptial-Bed. She Sigh'd, Lamented, and by fits would Roar; (But less had Mourn'd him, had she Known him more) No Med'cine cou'd be found for her Relief; The very Name of Comfort, rais'd her Grief: She kill'd the Birds that in her Windows hung, Not conscious of what past, because they sung. Her Mother, who was griev'd to hear her Cries, And did in all her Sorrows sympathize, The Remedy of good Advice apply'd, And thus, to lessen her Affliction, try'd: Spend not profusely, Child, your precious Tears; Take some Compassion on your tender Years; Be not injurious to those Cheeks and Eyes, Which all who see them (but your self) will prize: You need not long Affliction's Weight endure; The Hand that gives the Wound, will find a Cure: For, if your Dear (which Fate forbid) shou'd die, I have another Husband in my Eye. At this, like one to Bedlam newly brought, She Rag'd, she Swell'd, she Foam'd, she Heav'd, and Wrought; And, when Respiring had restor'd her Breath, Husband! she cry'd; My Husband shall be Death. Thus she continu'd till her Husband dy'd, And Death the Matrimonial-Knot unty'd: But her Affection liv'd to the Deceas'd, And as he Colder grew, its Warmth encreas'd: Extended by his senseless Corps she lay To warm the Lump of abdicated Clay; 'Till Grief exhausted in the wild Extreme, Left her to descant on a sweeter Theme: And, wisely recollecting 'twas in vain To call a Soul Departed back again; She to the Living her best Thoughts affords, With pleas'd Reflections on her Mother's Words, Whom thus she gently whispers in the Ear; What last you said, Pray Madam, let me hear: I will obey your Dictates, if I can, But wou'd be willing first to know the Man. The MORAL. ‘Surviving Wives such to dead Husband's prove; ‘Death, with the Man, annihilates the Love: ‘For who can still desire what is no more? ‘No more the thing for which 'twas lov'd before? ‘And where the Objects of Affection cease, ‘The Passion must by consequence decrease: ‘For, by the stated Rules of Nature's Laws, ‘Effects are hinder'd to survive their Cause. ‘What is a Husband but an empty Name, ‘When he, who bore it, is no more the same? ‘And she, who wou'd his Memory retain, ‘Enjoins her self a wretched Life, in vain; ‘As fondly acts, as one that wou'd embrace ‘A Shadow, when the Substance quits the Place. ‘This only Good to Widows Tears is due, ‘Grief for old Husbands, oft' procures them new. FABLE XXVIII. The Cock and Jewel: Or, Pearls before Swine. As once a Cock of the Plebeian Brood, Scrap'd o'er a Dunghil for his daily Food, He found a Jewel from the Rubbish rise, Of dazling Lustre, and transcending Price: But at this Baulk displeas'd, the Craven said, Why are my Pains with this bright Trifle paid? Some Lapidary might (with real Joy) Have found, and justly priz'd the shining Toy; But I a single Grain of Corn prefer To all the Jewels Eastern Monarchs wear: Let them with fancy'd Worth themselves delight, Give me what feeds my craving Appetite. The MORAL. ‘The Mean-soul'd Wretch, whose low and grov'ling Mind ‘Is to the Dunghil of the World confin'd, ‘In sordid Pleasures centers his Delight, ‘To gratifie his sensual Appetite: ‘While (in their Worth unskill'd) he treats, with Scorn, ‘The Gems that shou'd his nobler Part adorn; ‘They, whose rais'd Thoughts to Virtue's Heights aspire, ‘Its Value know, and, as they know, admire. FABLE XXIX. The Wolf and Lamb: Or, Might overcomes Right. As at a Spring a Wolf his Thirst allay'd, A Lamb, to taste the distant Stream, essay'd; Whereat fierce Isgrim (pleas'd to take Offence) Said, He disturb'd the Fountain-head from thence. The trembling Lamb, with apprehensive Dread, His Pardon crav'd, and did, Not Guilty, plead: For such a Crime, he urg'd, cou'd ne'er be done, 'Till Streams did backward to their Sources run. To whom the Wolf; In vain, presumptuous Thing, Thou do'st to me thy feign'd Excuses bring: Thou art obnoxious; I thy Race abhor; Thy Sire and Dam have wrong'd me heretofore: And now my just Resentment shall be shown On thee, for their Offences, and thy own. The MORAL. ‘Oppressors, bent on wronging Innocence, ‘When Will and Pow'r conspire, ne'er want Pretence: ‘No Arguments from Law or Reason draw; ‘Their Will's their Reason, and their Pow'r their Law. FABLE XXX. The Mouse in a Chest: Or, The World a Wise Man's Home. A Mouse, that in a Chest was born and bred, And there on homely Cheese and Bisket fed, Fell from the Edge, while too intent on Play, And wou'd return, but cou'd not find the Way. Driv'n by her Fear, she sought a safe Retreat; And in her Search, found more delicious Meat. By this she saw she had kept Home too long, And did her Palate and her Freedom wrong: She thought, at first, all Joys to Home confin'd, But, as she chang'd her Station, chang'd her Mind; And bless'd the Chance, that in another Air, Gave her more Liberty, and better Fare. The MORAL. ‘Uncurious Men, fond of their Native Ground, ‘Their whole Desires within its Limits bound: ‘While others, Wiser, for Improvement, roam, ‘And find Abroad a more delightful Home. ‘By Prudence govern'd, and with Sense endu'd, ‘They suit themselves to ev'ry Latitude. ‘These Trees revers'd, by Transplantation thrive, ‘That scarce were, in their Nurs'ries, kept alive: ‘No change of Climate disappoints their aim, ‘Since they, and Heav'n, are ev'ry-where the same. FABLE XXXI. The Young Man and the Old: Or, The Scoffer scoff'd. A Brisk Young Stripling, as an Arrow straight, Who ne'er of Cares or Years had felt the weight, Saw a decrepit Senior bending go, And ask'd, in scorn, if he wou'd sell his Bow. To whom the Sage; Waste not your Stock, to buy What kindly Nature gratis will supply: When you, young Fopling, to my Age are come, You will be furnish'd with a Bow at Home: But, if you are resolv'd to take your swing, You may be sooner fitted with a String. The MORAL. ‘Make not Infirmities of Age your Sport, ‘Which others may on you, in time, retort: ‘For Heav'n has Length of Days a Blessing made, ‘And curs'd the Fools who its Defects upbraid. FABLE XXXII. The Mad-house: Or, Expensive Sports, destructive Folly. A grave Physician, for his Skill renown'd, Had, by long Study and Experience, found For Frenzy an infallible Relief; Frenzy, that is of all Distempers chief: Frenzy, that in the Hypochondria bred, Scorns its mean Country, and affects the Head: And, when, in fact, Possessor of the Brain, Do's there exert an Arbitrary Reign. This Universal Tyrant o'er Mankind, To no Degree, no Sex, or Age confin'd; Is in the Palace and the Cottage found, Among the Old, the Young, the Sick and Sound: Alike its wild, ungovern'd Rage prevails O'er feeble Females, and robuster Males: Alike enslaves the Simple, and the Wise; And whom it captivates, do's still disguise: Who, strangely metamorphos'd into Apes, Act various Follies, in as various Shapes. This fierce, this savage Monster to subdue, Was what the Doctor most profess'd, and knew. His Remedy was this. Within his Court, Accommodated to the vast Resort, He had a spacious, deep, unwholsom Pool; No Common-shore so nauseous, or so foul; Its Filth so nasty, and its Stench so bad, As wou'd make all Men, in their Wits, run Mad. But all who thither Frantick came, were sure In this Bethesda to receive a Cure: Which the wise Doctor, for their quick Relief, Proportion'd to the measure of their Grief. Some, less distracted, he confin'd therein Only above the Ancle, or the Shin: Others, distemper'd to a worse degree, He further drove, and wetted to the Knee. But those, in whom the Frenzy did aspire, He forc'd Chin-deep into the hateful Mire; And, as Occasion did require it most, Gave each a deeper or a shallow'r Post. His fam'd Success, and happy Cures he wrought, A num'rous Concourse to his Bedlam brought; That in his Court appear'd, with mimick Pride, Madness in all its Forms diversify'd: For each, in height of Raving, seem'd intent On that, to which his sober Thoughts were bent. There pining sate the Wretch with Want oppress'd; And there he vaunted, whom kind Plenty bless'd: There was the proud Opiniator found, And still did in his own vain Sense abound: Thither was the Diffiding Mortal brought, Who of himself as much too meanly thought: The Atheist there did Heav'n and Hell despise: There the Enthusiast rag'd in Ecstasies: There he Complain'd, whom Sorrow did destroy; And there he Laugh'd, who cou'd not bear his Joy: There to hoard Treasure was the Miser's Care; And vain Expences pleas'd the thriftless Heir: There the Grave Blockhead made his dull Remark; And empty Jests tickl'd the Witty Spark: The poring Student there was learnd'ly Mad; And there he rav'd, who never Learning had: The Bankrupt Tradesman there design'd his Shop, And there a fancy'd Mistress pleas'd the Fop: The Jilt thought there she had her Cully met; And he did there at Disappointments fret: There the projecting Statesman form'd Intrigues, And, for his Pension, broke, or patch'd up Leagues: The Lawyer there contriv'd to split a Cause, Find Flaws in Deeds, or double Sense in Laws: The Patron there his vacant Livings sold, And still presented leaden Clerks, for Gold: The Parson there the Dev'l and Pope deny'd, Tho' they his Tythe, and Matter too, supply'd: There the great Lord his Chaplain's Service paid With a guelt Parish, and crack'd Chamber-Maid: The Broken Officer did there Parade, And curs'd the fatal Peace that spoil'd his Trade: The Lover there did his Amours reherse; And there the Poet play'd the Fool in Verse: The Merchant there, as shameless as unjust, Sold, at dear Rates, his cheap-bought Goods, on Trust; While there the Fools, undone by that Abuse, Rail'd at ill Bargains, clogg'd with Use on Use: There were the High, the Low, the Rich, the Poor, 'Till the throng'd Mansion cou'd receive no more. Well might the Doctor have enlarg'd his Room, Since all Mankind, in some respect, shou'd come. Among the Crouds, who there their Senses sought, A pert Attorney, for a Cure, was brought; This Spark no mighty stock of Wit had lost, Because his portion was but small, at most; And ev'n when with the height of Madness seiz'd, He had as much as for his Use suffic'd. The Doctor found he wou'd be compos soon, Since half the Bus'ness to his hand was done; He therefore did the slighter Means apply, And launch'd him in no deeper than the Thigh: This cool'd him so, that soon he ceas'd to rave, And sure Prognosticks of Recov'ry gave. The pleas'd Physician freed him from his Hole, And gave him leave about the Court to strole: Then, as he found his Frenzy more abate, Enlarg'd his Limits to the Outer Gate. There, as one day he stood, and gaz'd about, Admiring at the madder Crouds Without, An uncouth Object did his sight engage; A brisk young Gallant, with fine Equipage: Well mounted on a mettl'd Horse he rode, That hardly touch'd the Ground whereon he trod: Two Brace of coupl'd Spaniels ran before, His Fist a Cast of hooded Marlins bore, Adorn'd with Jesses, Varvels, and with Bells, That rung their dying Captives mournful Knells: Behind two Grooms, on able Geldings, came; Their Liv'ries rich, the Cloth and Lace the same. The Mad-man thought the Sight surprizing new, For he forgot what he, e're frantick, knew: (To him the Pond a real Lethe prov'd, And most Idea's of things past, remov'd) Then, as the sprightly Beau approach'd, he cry'd, Fine Thing, let me intreat you to abide: Which done, with twenty Questions he ran on, Without allowing time to answer one. He ask'd, what that was call'd on which he sate; And what they were that did behind him wait: What were the little Things that ran before; And what strange Creatures on his Fist he bore: What was each one's peculiar Use and Trade; And what Advantage of them all he made? The Spark, who guess'd his Case, and thought the Wise Shou'd humour Mad-men in their Fooleries; As soon as he wou'd give him leave, reply'd, This, Sir, is call'd a Horse, on which I ride: The other two, whom you behind me see, Are Grooms that dress my Horse, and tend on me: These on my Hand are Hawks, that, when I please, Will kill me Larks, or Quails, or Partridges: And those, which foremost in the Couples came, Are Spaniels, train'd to range, and spring my Game: All these to my Divertisement conduce; This is their Service, Sir, and this their Use. The Mad-man thought it was no little Charge That cou'd maintain an Equipage so large; And ask'd him what his Game was worth a Year, And what his Annual Expences were? The courtly Gentleman (pleas'd to dispense With his inquisitive Impertinence) Reply'd; My Game's scarce worth Five Crowns, at most; My Sport as many Hundred Pounds do's cost. Tickl'd at this Account, the Man of Laws Laugh'd out, as tho' he just had gain'd a Cause; And said, Since you so dearly buy your Sport, You shou'd be hamper'd in our Doctor's Court: For never was a more egregious Fool Brought to be Compos Mentis in his Pool. Be gone in time; for if this Tale he hears, In sooth, he'll plunge you over head and ears The MORAL. ‘They who on Sports their Time and Wealth bestow, ‘With Cost themselves industriously undo; ‘Consume their Substance by the vain Expence; ‘And waste their Lives in an Impertinence: ‘They need some wise Physician's timely Care, ‘Their broken Brains and Fortune's to repair: ‘Such wild Extravagancies will require ‘The deepest Station in the Doctor's Mire. FABLE XXXIII. The Gardener and his Dog: Or, Save a Thief, and he will cut your Throat. A Gard'ner's Dog, while drinking at a Well, For want of Caution, to the bottom fell. The Owner, troubl'd that his Dog shou'd drown, Ran quickly to his help, and hasten'd down. But the curs'd Cur, suspecting all that Care Was not to free him thence, but keep him there; Requites the Kindness with an ill Amends, And fastens on his Legs, as he descends. The Master, vex'd at such a base Return, Left him to sink, and thus himself did mourn: I justly smart, who did my Pains employ To save a Wretch that wou'd himself destroy. The MORAL. ‘Ungrateful Souls at Benefits repine, ‘And injure those who their Relief design: ‘They from their own ill Meanings learn Distrust, ‘And think all others, like themselves, Unjust. FABLE XXXIV. The Dog and Butcher: Or, Fore-warn'd, Fore-arm'd. A prowling Dog, at Hunger's urgent Call, Snatch'd a fair Purchase from a Butcher's Stall; Then, press'd by Guilt, and apprehensive Dread, Took to his heels, and with his Booty fled. The Butcher, lost in the Surprize, stood mute, No Out-cry made, nor offer'd at Pursuit: But, gaining time for Thought, he rais'd his Voice, And cry'd, Run Thief, and in thy Prize rejoyce: Now thou art safe, and do'st unpunish'd go; Another time thou shalt not serve me so. The MORAL. ‘A Loss receiv'd, do's Men with Caution arm, ‘To hinder or revenge a second harm: ‘Without their fault, they the first Wrong sustain; ‘But, for the next, shou'd on themselves complain. ‘The Stroke that's giv'en us e're we are aware, ‘Shews us our Danger, and awakes our Care: ‘Instructs us where we open lay, and how ‘To ward the Danger of another Blow. ‘Thus, from the Injuries of Foes, we learn, ‘For our own Safety, to shew more Concern. FABLE XXXV. The Ape and Jupiter: Or, The Crow thinks her own Bird whitest. The Beasts were summon'd, by Command from Jove, To try whose Off-spring he wou'd most approve: Among the various Kinds, the Comick Ape, With horrid Visage, and ungainly Shape, Produc'd her aukward Whelps to pass the Test; And thought the God, like her, wou'd judge them best. Tickl'd at so ridiculous a Sight, The Beasts forgot Respect, and Laugh'd outright. Laugh on, said she; Let Jove think what he will, Mother's own Pictures are the fairest still, This put them all upon the second Strain; Nor cou'd ev'n Jove his Gravity retain. The MORAL. ‘Fond of themselves, and blinded with that Love, ‘Men ev'n their own Infirmities approve: ‘But what we are, or what we do, 'tis fit ‘We to more equal Censures shou'd submit; ‘Lest, by our Partiality betray'd, ‘The Judgment shou'd our want of Sense upbraid. FABLE XXXVI. The Peasant and Fortune. Or, Heaven slighted in Prosperity. A lab'ring Peasant, as he Plough'd his Ground, In the deep Furrow a rich Treasure found: Pleas'd with his Luck, he prais'd the fertil Earth, Whose pregnant Womb gave the bright Product birth. Now slighted Fortune, (vex'd at his Neglect, Who took her Gift, and paid her no Respect) Said; See, the thankless Wretch enjoys his Prize, And to my Altar brings no Sacrifice: But when the Blessing, as it came, is gone, He will exclaim, and rail on me alone. The MORAL. ‘When Heav'n on Men has Benefits conferr'd, ‘The Benefactor seldom they regard; ‘'Till the same Hand that did the Gift dispense, ‘Resumes it, to chastize their Negligence: ‘Then (griev'd for what they so deserv'd to lose) ‘They fret at Heav'n, and Providence accuse. FABLE XXXVII. The Boy and Fortune. Or, Self do, Self have. A careless Boy, who wou'd no Bus'ness mind, And more to Sleep, than Labour, was enclin'd, Close on the Brink of an impetuous Stream Securely slept, nor did of Hazards dream: 'Till Fortune, coming timely, to prevent Ris Ruin, which she saw was imminent, Rouz'd him from Sleep, which might have prov'd his last; And thus rebuk'd him for Incaution past: Young Man, you on a dang'rous Bed was plac'd, Which might have cost your Life, and me disgrac'd: Had you been drown'd, Men wou'd of me complain, And not your Negligence, but mine, arraign: The Inquest then, with one Consent and Breath, Wou'd find me only guilty of your Death: Tho', were a Melius Inquirendo sought, Felo de se, shou'd be the Verdict brought. The MORAL. ‘Thus, by the fatal Courses they pursue, ‘Unhappy Mortals oft' themselves undo: ‘But, while they suffer, (to avoid the Shame) ‘Pretend another Cause, and Fortune blame. ‘Their Indiscretion is their Overthrow, ‘And to themselves they each Miscarriage owe: ‘But he who manages with prudent Skill, ‘Leads Fortune bound, and guides her as he will. FABLE XXXVIII. The Sheep and Crow: Or, Easiness invites Insults. On a Sheep's Back a Crow triumphant sate, And fill'd the Plain with her obstrep'rous Prate. The passive Sheep, without Resistance made, Bore the Insult, and no Concern betray'd; But told a Spaniel, that stood grinning by, He wou'd be soundly drubb'd for such a Cry. The Crow reply'd; But I know what I do, And dare make bold with such tame Things as you. The MORAL. ‘Vexatious Knaves, the patient Man despise, ‘And load him with repeated Injuries: ‘But to the Man whose Anger kindles soon, ‘And will not bear Affronts, they offer none. ‘The Passive, by their Easiness betray'd, ‘Are thought, and us'd, as Beasts for Burden made: ‘While mettl'd Souls, who dare Resentment shew, ‘Make bold Insulters their due Distance know. ‘So Fortune do's the yielding Wretch enslave, ‘But stands in awe, and truckles to the Brave. FABLE XXXIX. The Crow and Mule: Or, Distinguish'd Malefactors. A Crow, alighting on a Mule's raw Back, (That had been gall'd by a too heavy Pack) To feast her self, the angry Sore did pinch, And made the restless Creature bray and winch: Which gave rare Pastime to the Muletier, Who twitter'd at the Sport she bought so dear. A Wolf, that saw him in this merry vain, Did of his own Misfortune thus complain: That grinning Fellow, if he did but see, With might and main wou'd quickly fall on me; But while the saucy Crow torments his Beast, Allows it, and is tickl'd at the Jest. The MORAL. ‘Villains, whose only Bent to Mischief lies, ‘Like Beasts of Prey; are Common Enemies; ‘And, tho' not guilty of a present Harm, ‘Where-e'er they come, all honest Men alarm. ‘Such, when by Pow'r enabl'd to do ill, ‘Are justly fear'd; for if they can, they will. ‘Small Rogues, like Crows, can only fret a Sore; ‘And, when they spend their Malice, hurt no more. ‘The Great, like Wolves, make a too bold Effort; ‘They drive the Just too far, and spoil the Sport: ‘And what we slight, or wink at, in a Crow, ‘We hate, and will not in a Wolf allow. FABLE XL. The Eagle and Pye: Or, No trusting Tattlers. A Pye, whose voluble and flippant Tongue, For quaint Harangue, was excellently hung, Fain on the Eagle wou'd her self obtrude, And for a Place at Court had often su'd. She earnestly sollicited her Cause, And spar'd no Rhet'rick in her own Applause: But what did most encourage her Pretence, Was fluent Speech, and pow'rful Eloquence. The Royal Bird, tir'd with her Noise, reply'd; Friend, your Petition shou'd not be deny'd, But that you are so Talkative, I fear You cannot keep the Secrets which you hear. The MORAL. ‘Men, fond of Talk, occasion still Desire ‘To shew the Talent which themselves admire: ‘With Secrets trusted, they are chiefly bless'd; ‘Those furnish Matter, and draw Hearers best. ‘The leaky Fools, whatever they receive, ‘Let out as fast as Water through a Sieve; ‘And still are bursting, 'till they give it vent, ‘As if 'twas Wind in their Intestines pent. ‘Such Echo's are for Prince's Courts unmeet, ‘Who, instantly what's whisper'd there, repeat: ‘There Men shou'd more the Fishes Temper suit, ‘Shou'd be as quick in Bus'ness, and as mute: ‘Manag'd by such, Designs go smoothly on; ‘The Work's accomplish'd e're the Project's known: ‘For they, like Powder, by no Warning-blast, ‘Betray the Aim, till Execution's past: ‘But noisie Blabs, like Drums, alarm the Foe; ‘And what's as loud, must be as hollow too. FABLE XLI. The Lion's Choice: Or, A Friend loves at all times. The Lion, who was vers'd in State-Affairs, And knew how Princes best support their Cares; Order'd his Subjects shou'd at Court attend, That from the Herds he might select a Friend; By whom, when Bus'ness or Diversion pleas'd, He might with Counsel, or Delight, be eas'd: A Friend, to whom he might his Heart disclose, And fear no false Discov'ries to his Foes: A Friend, who wou'd in all his Fortunes share; In Peace, Advise, and Fight for him in War. The Beasts, who all to that high Rank aspir'd, (For Princes Favourites are still admir'd) Paid glad Obedience to their King's Decree; Each urg'd, by hope to be the happy He. Their Sov'reign view'd the vast Assembly round; And what he sought, by piercing Judgment, found: He found what best wou'd answer his Design; And, to their great Amazement, chose a Swine. Then, to declare what thus his Thoughts enclin'd, This weighty Reason for his Choice assign'd: This faithful Creature to his Friends adheres Tho' Life and Fortune run all Risques with theirs. The MORAL. ‘Men may safe Friendship easily pretend; ‘But Times of Danger, only try a Friend: ‘No happy Man is sure he is belov'd, ‘Because his Creatures cannot then be prov'd. ‘They who dare Faith (when hazardous) express, ‘And Wretches, on whom Fortune frowns, caress; ‘Give ample Proof their Friendship is not cold; ‘And are deserv'dly valu'd more than Gold. FABLE XLII. The Elm and Osier: Or, Submit, and Conquer. A Stately Elm, that num'rous Years had stood, And grac'd the Margin of a Rapid Flood; (By its large Bulk, to Vanity betray'd) A neighb'ring Osier's Weakness did upbraid; That still it yielded to the Water's Course, While his fix'd Root withstood its strongest Force. But Pride do's seldom a sure Station know; A sudden Change brought the vain Boaster low: The swelling Torrent, too impetuous grown, O'er-turn'd the Elm, and bore its Trophy down. Thus, by a just Return, its Pride was quell'd, And fell, by what it had been long upheld: While still the pliant Osier kept its ground, And smiling saw its first Despiser drown'd. Then said; You act unkindly, I profess, To leave your Friend and Neighbour in Distress: Why shou'd your Greatness flinch, while I stand fast? Are your Bravado's come to this at last? The MORAL. ‘Wisely the Men, who their own Weakness know, ‘Yield to the Vigour of a stronger Foe: ‘Submission calms and temperates the Rage ‘By which they fall, who dare its Force engage: ‘Resistance causes a more furious Shock; ‘As Waves dash most on an opposing Rock. FABLE XLIII. The Peacock and Crane: Or, Fine Feathers make fine Birds. A Peacock, in his gaudy Feathers, vain, Upbraids, with her more homely Dress, a Crane. The Crane replies; Your Plumes, 'tis true, are fine, But not so useful, haughty Sir, as mine: With them you only o'er low Houses fly, While my strong Pinions bear me to the Sky. The MORAL. ‘Boast not your own, nor others Worth despise; ‘The Rate of Things in their Advantage lies: ‘And they who want what you esteem too well, ‘In some more rare Perfection may excell. FABLE XLIV. The Bear and Bees. Or, Touch One, touch All. Stung by a peevish Bee, a Bear, enrag'd, With angry Paws, the Family engag'd; Flung down their Hive, and all their Combs destroy'd; But in his Fury short Delight enjoy'd. The injur'd Insects round about him swarm, And with their pointed Darts revenge the Harm. He (from their Outrage scarce escap'd with Life) Thus blam'd the Folly that encreas'd his Grief: Since from One Sting I so much Anguish bore, 'Twas Madness to provoke a Thousand more. The MORAL. ‘More wisely Men a single Wrong endure, ‘Than, by Impatience, greater Ills procure: ‘He that, where many potent Friends combine, ‘On one Aggressor do's Revenge design: ‘In vexing him, incenses all the rest, ‘And is with num'rous Injuries oppress'd. ‘United Friends together fall and rise, ‘And, like embody'd Members, sympathize: ‘If ev'n the most Extream receives a Smart, ‘The tingling Anguish runs through ev'ry Part: ‘At his Complaint, all take the quick Alarm, ‘And, for their Fellow's Succour, jointly arm. FABLE XLV. The Wolves and Sheep: Or, Reconcil'd Enemies, seldom Friends. The Wolves and Sheep, that long did disagree, Made Peace, and pass'd a gen'ral Amnesty: For this they mutual Hostages receive; The Wolves their Cubs, the Sheep their Mastiffs give. The easie Sheep, secure by this Exchange, Feed safe, and fearless through the Pastures range: 'Till the false Cubs, (as if the Sheep play'd foul) Taught by their Dams, set up a doleful Houl. The Wolves, that only for this Signal stay'd, With breach of Faith the guiltless Sheep upbraid; And make them feel (upon this slight Pretence) The sad Effects of quitting their Defence. The MORAL. ‘He that's deceiv'd by specious Shews of Peace, ‘And (lull'd in deep Security and Ease) ‘Disbands his Guards; is by himself betray'd; ‘Expos'd to Danger, and depriv'd of Aid. ‘Where open Enmity has been profess'd, ‘To hope for real Friendship, is a Jest: ‘Such Reconcilements are a bare Pretence, ‘And gain Advantage for a new Offence. FABLE XLVI. The Country Fidler: Or, Unseen, Unknown. A Country Scraper, who at Weddings play'd, And was, beyond his Merit, prais'd and paid; Proud of his Parts, wou'd needs himself prefer To grace the Consort at the Theater: But there (when he a Tune or two had play'd) His Impudence, and want of Skill betray'd: And the affronted Audience, in a Rage, Hiss'd the pretending Blockhead off the Stage. The MORAL. ‘So some grave Doctors, who in Schools dispute, ‘And, in conceit, ev'n Bellarmine confute; ‘When they in Paul's or Westminster appear, ‘Make but a dull and awkward Figure there. ‘Learning, without brisk Parts to set it forth, ‘Like hidden Treasure, is but little worth: ‘And the rich Soil, while it conceals the Gold, ‘Is in no more esteem than common Mould. FABLE XLVII. The Clown and Clyster: Or, Invincible Ignorance. A des'prate Head-ach seiz'd a surly Boor, (Rich in his Purse, but in his Spirit poor) To visit him the glad Physicians trot; As Flyes still swarm about a Honey-pot. The Consult held; one wiser than the rest, Or, in his own Opinion so, at least, Prescrib'd a Clyster, to remove his Pain, And did, by Arguments, that Course maintain. But the rude Fellow, to such Cures unus'd, Their Applications, and themselves, abus'd: Be gone, said he; I see your Skill does fail, Who, when my Head's disturb'd, wou'd drench my Tail. The MORAL. ‘Thus rude, and unexperienc'd Fools, despise ‘The best Prescriptions giv'n 'em by the Wise; ‘And, as mistaken Measures, discommend ‘What their dull Reason cannot comprehend; ‘Their Ignorance still keeps them in a Mist, ‘And makes them in their Self-conceit persist. FABLE XLVIII. The Old Weesel, and Mice: Or, Policy beyond Strength. A Weesel, brought, by Age, to great Decay, And grown too feeble to attempt her Prey; Resolv'd some subtle Artifice to try, That might her want of Strength and Speed supply. To compass this, and easie Conquests gain, She lay conceal'd within a Heap of Grain; That, when Marauders did the Corn invade, She might surprize them, from her Ambuscade. The Mice, who saw no Danger to avoid, Came fearless thither, and were all destroy'd. The MORAL. ‘Where Strength, to gain the Point we labour, fails, ‘Our more successful Policy prevails. ‘Precaution'd Men, from open Dangers run; ‘But what are unforeseen, they rarely shun. FABLE XLIX. The Fox and Cock: Or, The Shammer shamm'd. A hungry Fox, in great distress for Food, Came prowling where a lonely Cottage stood; And on the Branches of its shelt'ring Trees, A Cock, at roost among his Misses, sees: With friendly Tone he call'd to Chanticleer, And ask'd the reason he was mounted there, As if he was a Stranger to the Joy, That pleas'd all Hearts, and did all Tongues employ. The Cock reply'd, He liv'd remote from Court, And rarely heard, or listen'd to, Report; But if he ought of Moment cou'd impart, He wou'd give ear to that, with all his heart. Then answer'd Reynard; Know, my noble Friend, All Wrong and Violence are at an end: At Court, a great Assembly has been held Of all the sage Free-holders of the Field; Who have decree'd, Hostilities shall cease, And end in gen'ral Amnesty and Peace: Now ev'n the Weakest may unguarded go, And fear no Danger, for they have no Foe. Pleas'd with the News, I came express away, To celebrate, with you, this joyful Day. The Cock, too wise to be with Words deceiv'd, Knew Reynard was too false to be believ'd: But, not to seem distrustful or surpriz'd, With Complaisance his Jealousy disguiz'd; And said, My Friend, you happy Tidings bring; This Day will make us, O be joyful, sing: Then rais'd his Crest, as if he meant to Crow; But some Concern, that spoil'd his Note, did show. Whereat, the Fox demanding what he saw; Two Hounds, said he, that tow'rds this Mansion draw: With open Mouths, and eager Speed they move; Sure, the same Message do's their Haste improve. The Fox alarm'd, and conscious of his Cheat, Began to think it time for a Retreat; And said, Good Friend, Adieu; I dare not stay; These plaguy Currs have frighted me away. How! said the Cock; Have you forgot the Peace? Are not Hostilities decree'd to cease? 'Tis true, said Reynard; nor do I forget, But fear these Teazers have not heard it yet. The MORAL. ‘Impostors thus (who others wou'd deceive) ‘Suspected in the false Accounts they give, ‘Are justly by a Counter-plot betray'd, ‘And fall themselves into the Snares they laid. FABLE L. The Graceless Son: Or, Unseasonable Mirth. A tender Husband lost a faithful Wife, The kind Support of his declining Life: But when the Bell, before her Fun'ral, rung, His Graceless Son, instead of Weeping, Sung. Displeas'd at such unseasonable Mirth, (When she was lifeless who had giv'n him Birth) The mourning Father did his Folly chide: To whom th' incorrigible Rake reply'd, You hire the Priests to sing, without offence; Then blame not me, who save you some Expence. His Sire rejoin'd, The Priests their Office do; You are too mad, to make a Priest of you. The MORAL. ‘Decorum, that gives every thing its Grace, ‘With Circumstances alters still its Face: ‘The very Act, which we in some approve, ‘In others wou'd our Indignation move. ‘When Parents Die, to Sing at such a time, ‘In Priest, is Piety; in Sons, a Crime: ‘And he who Laughs, when Sorrow claims his Tears, ‘Acts the wrong Part, and just Reproaches bears. FABLE LI. The Hound: Or, Eaten Bread forgotten. A Hound, once stanch, and forward at the Chase As any He of all the Motly Race; But, by his long Fatigue, and Age, oppress'd, Was in the Field thrown off by all the rest. His angry Lord, regardless of his Age, Rated, and lash'd him, with immod'rate Rage. But Kill-buck, whom such Usage did not please, Reply'd, I have deserv'd a Writ of ease; Since now I superannuated grow, And cannot, as in Youth and Vigour, do: But tho' I am unserviceable grown, You shou'd not thus my Service past disown: While I was useful, you was always kind; But now, your Love is with my Strength, declin'd: Tho' sure you shou'd, in Gratitude alone, Respect my Age, for what my Youth has done. The MORAL. ‘How quickly are past Services forgot, ‘Which they, who were oblig'd, acknowledge not? ‘Few People, fac'd like Janus, we shall find; ‘All look before, or very few, behind: ‘And on their present Benefit intent, ‘Where that is found, pay all their Compliment: ‘When Expectations of Advantage cease, ‘Their Kindness fails, and their Respects decrease: ‘Tho' you a Thousand Offices have done, ‘You lose your Thanks, if you omit but One: ‘The first slight Failure wipes out all the score; ‘He has done nothing, who can do no more. FABLE LII. The Fishes: Or, Out of the Frying-pan, into the Fire. Some Trouts, that (apprehending no Deceit) Swallow'd their Ruin with the treach'rous Bait; When from the Brook brought to the Pan alive, Did soon their change of Elements perceive: Impatient of the Heat in which they fry'd, They leap'd among the hotter Coals, and dy'd: And, with their dying Breath, did thus complain; Seeking to ease, we have encreas'd our Pain: For in severer Torments we expire, Who left the Pan, and perish in the Fire. The MORAL. ‘Imprudent Men, while they less Dangers shun, ‘By too much Rashness, into greater run: ‘Their present Sufferings the Wretches force ‘To seek Redress of Grievances in worse. ‘Unskilful Sailors thus do Rocks avoid, ‘And run on Quick-sands, where they are destroy'd. FABLE LIII. The Boor and Wood: Or, Give an Inch, take an Ell. In Happy Times, when Jove's indulgent Care Had made the Forests Vocal ev'ry-where, A Boor the Trees unfortunately press'd To grant a needful, tho' a small, Request; That from some useless, or mishapen, Bough, They wou'd a Handle for his Ax allow. The Wood consented: But the thankless Clown, When fitted, hew'd his Benefactors down. Then they, too late, their Easiness repent, Who ow'd their Ruin to their own Consent. The MORAL. ‘In all Petitions, of Design beware; ‘A poor Request, may hide a fatal Snare. ‘Some, who obtain a slender Grant, with ease ‘(By that impowr'd) command what more they please: ‘Like greedy Leeches, to the Veins apply'd, ‘They may be glutted, but not satisfy'd: ‘When once they taste the Sweets your Stores contain, ‘They'll suck to Surfeit, rather than refrain. FABLE LIV. The Drown'd Wife: Or, Better lost than found. A Man, unhappy in a clam'rous Wife, (That daily led him an unhappy Life) A kind Relief from Fate's Indulgence found; And She, who Ducking oft' deserv'd, was Drown'd. He sought her Corps, and (tho' his true Intent Was not to find it) up the River went. A Neighbour, that observ'd his seeming Pain, Which such wrong Measures needs must render vain, Told him; If what he sought, he wish'd to find, 'Twas a prepost'rous Method he design'd: He rather shou'd the Water's Course pursue, Which soonest wou'd restore her to his view. The Man reply'd; That wou'd be more a Jest, For he was sure (who knew her Temper best) That she, when dead, against the Stream wou'd strive, Who was all Contradiction, while alive. The MORAL. ‘Thus an Ill-humour'd, Peevish Wife, is priz'd; ‘Hated, while living; and when dead, despis'd: ‘One only Good she does; by proving Cross, ‘She saves her Husband's Sorrow for her Loss. ‘Such Helps-unmeet, rather Obstructions prove; ‘Kindle Aversion, but extinguish Love: ‘Their Husbands lose them with a grateful Smart; ‘As Men, for Life, with gangren'd Members part. FABLE LV. The Doves and Kite: Or, A rash Choice, repented. The Doves wag'd War with their old Foe, the Kite, And chose a Hawk to Head them in the Fight: He undertook it, but abus'd his Pow'r, And strove, not to protect them, but devour. The helpless Birds, to greater Harms betray'd, Dearly repent the fatal Choice they made; And rather wou'd the Kite's Insults sustain, Than their new Tyrant's sanguinary Reign. The MORAL. ‘Few Men in any Station acquiesce, ‘But shift, and change, tho' still without Redress: ‘So rarely Heav'n a lasting Blessing finds ‘To gratifie our inconsistent Minds: ‘Manna, tho' suited to each wanton Gust, ‘Cou'd not long silence Isra'l's murm'ring Lust: ‘They Egypt's Bondage, more than Freedom, priz'd; ‘For Leeks and Onions, Angels Food despis'd. ‘This fickle Humour is a wild Disease, ‘Whose raging Fits no Med'cine can appease: ‘Nor is it strange we thus Inconstant prove, ‘Who, with Discretion, neither Hate, nor Love. FABLE LVI. The Ass in a Lion's Skin: Or, Fools betray themselves. An Ass, that fain for Courage wou'd be priz'd, In a dead Lion's Skin himself disguiz'd: The dull Impostor, in that Cov'ring dress'd, Ap'd, with Success, a-while, the Royal Beast: Where he appear'd, the frighted Beasts gave Way, And all to him did low Obeisance pay. While thus he rang'd the Fields, admir'd and fear'd, And thought himself as Brave as he appear'd: He saw a more discerning Fox pass by, And him the Counterfeit resolv'd to try; But had forgot himself, and made a Noise That struck less Terror than a Lion's Voice. The Cheat discover'd, by this lucky Chance, Embolden'd doubting Reynard to advance, And thus accost him; Sir, I was afraid, 'Till, when your Highness meant to Roar, you Bray'd. The MORAL. ‘Fools, while reserv'd, and seemingly precise, ‘Pass, with the shallow Mob, for Grave and Wise: ‘For they read Learning in a formal Face, ‘And find deep Mysteries in strain'd Grimace: ‘But Men of Judgment slight the senseless Tools, ‘Whose hollow Sound proclaims them empty Fools. FABLE LVII. The Wolf and Lamb: Or, No Trust to Fair-shews. A Wolf, that did, with some Displeasure, note A Lamb, that fed close by his Guardian-Goat, Told the young Wanton, He was much to blame, To quit, for that rank Beast, his sweeter Dam: And with sweet Words advis'd him to be gone; In hope to seize him when he was alone. The Lamb reply'd, My Mother's tender Care Has, for my greater Safety, plac'd me here: I will her Counsel, Sir, not yours, obey; For you wou'd eat me, were my Guard away. The MORAL. ‘Do not in ev'ry Man's Advice, confide; ‘A fair Pretence, may an ill Meaning hide: ‘With specious Shews of Friendship, to betray ‘(Since least suspected) is the surest way. FABLE LVIII. The Father and his Sons: Or, Unity, and Security. An aged Yeoman, who much Wealth possess'd, And with a num'rous Progeny was bless'd; Observ'd, with Grief, his Sons did daily Jar, And wag'd, among themselves, intestine War: Nature's soft Voice cou'd not their Feuds asswage, Nor his Commands, or Tears, restrain their Rage. He saw what Ill this did to all portend, And knew their Strife wou'd in their Ruin end: Which (since Advice, and Threatnings, were mispent) He sought, by other Methods, to prevent: And for that good Design, when next they fought, A Sheaf of Arrows, well compacted, brought, And bid them sev'rally their Strength apply To break the Bundle; but in vain they try: For while they in so close a Band were ty'd, The brittle Sticks their baffled Force defy'd. Their Father then (a new Effort to make) Bid ev'ry Son a Single Arrow take, Commanding each on that to try his Hand: And then, with ease, each broke his yielding Wand. This done, the rev'rend Sire thus gravely spoke; United, these were whole; divided, broke: Take then, my Sons, the sound Advice I give, And by this Emblem, learn in Peace to live: Thus you shall baffle all Attempts of Wrong, Secure in Concord, and in Union strong: But by Division, weak and helpless made, To all Insults you will be open laid: And you, who wou'd not, for Defence, combine, By Disagreements, must in Ruin join. The MORAL. ‘Collective Bodies, in close Union join'd, ‘Remain Invincible while so combin'd; ‘But, when divided, are an easie Prey: ‘The Whole do's in its weakned Parts decay. ‘So a compacted Wall, is firm and strong, ‘Maintains its Ground, and braves Time's Fury long; ‘But when one Stone do's from its Station fall, ‘Encroaching Ruin quickly shatters all. FABLE LIX. The Fox and Lion: Or, Familiarity breeds Contempt. When first the Fox the dreadful Lion saw, He trembled all, and stood in mighty awe: The second time he met the Princely Beast, He found his Fear was very much decreas'd: But at next Interview dismiss'd all Doubts, And no more fear'd him, than a Beast of Clouts. The MORAL. ‘Thus Men, unus'd to Dangers, Dangers fear, ‘And represent them greater than they are; ‘But when, by use, familiar with them grown, ‘Despise what they so dreaded while unknown. FABLE LX. The Eagle and Fox: Or, Rage arms the Injur'd. A Fox's Cub too far from Home did stray, And, in his Range, became an Eagle's Prey: The trembling Beast (not without cause afraid) Call'd loudly to his Dam, for speedy Aid. The Dam, who had no Means, but Pray'r alone, Besought the Eagle to release her Son. But the rapacious Bird (deaf to her Cry, And more concern'd for her own Progeny) Straight to her airy, her swift Flight address'd, Pleas'd she cou'd thus her hungry Eaglets feast. The Fox, that found her vain Entreaties fail, Resolv'd to try how Cunning cou'd prevail; And, with a flaming Brand, ascends the Tree That harbour'd her obdurate Enemy: Then, with a Voice that Ruin did portend, She cry'd, Your Young Ones and your Self defend; For to your helpless Off-spring I design No more Compassion than you shew'd to mine. The Eagle, dreading the approaching Flame, Capitulates thus with the angry Dame: Forbear your Rage, since yet no Harm is done; Spare my dear Issue, and take back your own. The MORAL. ‘So ready are the quick Results of Grief, ‘To give the Injur'd Means for their Relief. ‘When sudden Outrages the Weak surprize, ‘Presence of Mind, their want of Strength supplies. ‘The Plunder'd are not destitute of Arms; ‘Rage gives them Weapons to revenge their Harms. FABLE LXI. The Fox and Weesel: Or, Much Wealth, much Woe. A Fox, with tedious fasting, lank and thin, Found Pullets in a Coop, and soon crept in: There, to excess, the Glutton fell to eat, And, till too full, near thought of a retreat. Pleas'd to return, when he cou'd stuff no more, He found the Passage straiter than before: He strove, he stretch'd, and shrunk himself, in vain; But cou'd not Egress now, as Ingress, gain. A Weesel that stood by, and hugg'd the Jest, Cry'd, Sir, you take much Pains to be releas'd: If to get out, as you got in, you mean, Do Penance there, till you become as Lean. The MORAL. ‘Men who Contented in mean Fortunes live, ‘Enjoy the mod'rate Blessings they receive: ‘But when too greedily they covet more, ‘And with pernicious haste improve their Store; ‘They find the Change injurious to their Peace; ‘For, as their Treasures, so their Cares encrease. FABLE LXII. The City Mouse and Country Mouse: Or, Quiet, the best Fare. Tir'd with the Noise and Hurry of the Town, (That scarce wou'd let him call his Life his own) A Cockney Mouse, that wou'd relax his Care, Walk'd to the Fields, to breath the Country Air; And, in his Tour, encountred on the Road, A Rural Mouse, near his retir'd Abode. The wondring Rustick, who had never seen A Mouse of so improv'd an Air and Mien; To the gay Cit, with such Respect did bow, As his more homely Breeding wou'd allow; And pray'd him, since he came to view the Fields, To tast the mean Repasts their Bounty yields. The civil Stranger readily agreed, And to the Farmer's Cottage they proceed. Beneath a Hill the quiet Mansion stood, Shelter'd from Winds by a surrounding Wood; On either hand a double Quick-set grew, And made a fair and graceful Avenue: Through which a pleasing Visto did invite, And to the distant House direct the Sight: Before the Front a Brook ran gently by, Its Surface clear as the reflected Sky: Parterrs and Grass-plots did the Court divide, Where Nature Art's best Mimickry defy'd. When here they were arriv'd, the Stranger-Mouse, By his kind Host, was usher'd to the House: It was a Grott, beneath a Chesnut made, Whose Fruit and Branches serv'd for Food and Shade: The spreading Root was its protecting Roof, And kept it Water-fast, and Weather-proof. The Hall, with Arms (o'erspread with antique Dust) Was grac'd; as they with venerable Rust: Those to the Field his brave Fore-fathers brought, When their fam'd Battle with the Frogs they fought: And the rich Work of Mortlack's finest Loom, Describ'd the Action in the Dining-room. Here Good-man Delver reach'd his Guest a Seat, And begg'd his Patience 'till he fetch'd the Meat. The Hospitable Hind, who thought his Guest Too great and squeamish for a common Feast, Ransack'd each corner of his choicest Hoard, And loaded with Varieties the Board. First came a Scrap of Bacon's sooty Rind, Serv'd up with Beans and Peas of ev'ry kind: Next a Potatoe, whose inviting Meat Wou'd make the Gods wish they were Mice to eat: Then part of a Hog's Seam, whose Tast and Smell Did ev'n delicious Candle-Ends excell: Then Nuts, and Bullace, Crabs, and Mouldy Cheese, For a Dissert that might their Teeth ungrease. When these were on the cover'd Table plac'd, The Host desir'd his courtly Guest to tast; And if his Worship cou'd digest such Fare, He hop'd he wou'd fall to, and never spare. The Citizen (made, by high-feeding, nice) Thought those mean Cates too coarse for Cockney-Mice; And scarce wou'd touch the Bits his hearty Friend Did to his dainty Palate recommend: But thus bespoke him; Sir, I much admire That to this lonely Seat you can retire: And ignorant of those dear Pleasures live, Which we more happy Citizens receive: Our Joys are too sublime to be express'd; Each Day's a Festival, each Meal a Feast: Leave then, my Friend, this homely Place and Fare, And to the Town, the blissful Town, repair; There you will find the Centre of Delight, And (us'd to that) what now you value, slight. The Yeoman, ravish'd with this large Report, Resolv'd to live no longer Alamort; But to the City wou'd the 'Squire attend, And there his Days in Mirth and Revels spend. Soon they the despicable Cave forsook, And the directest Way to London took; Where Cit led gazing Bumkin to a House Enough to daunt a simple Country Mouse; Such Finery he ne'er before had seen, And thought he there, at least, in Heav'n had been. Into the Larder, undiscern'd, they crept, And there absconded 'till the People slept: When all was quiet, each forsook his Hole, And to the Shelves, to taste the Viands, stole: But there such tempting Dishes did abound, As did poor Country's dubious Choice confound: There was Goose, Turky, Capon, Pig, and Veal, Duck, Plover, Pigeon, Partridge, Snipe and Teal; Tarts, Cheese-cakes, Custards, Jellies, Tongues and Ham, (The Ladies fair Pretence to take a Dram) With Pyramids of Sweet-meats, rais'd so high They might almost with those of Memphis vie. Now Peasant, like a Farmer, feeds and gluts, And thinks he ne'er shall fill his craving Guts. But as they feast, they hear the Door unlock'd; Which dampt their Pleasure, and their Courage shock'd; The Cook was coming, with his wonted Care, To see no Cat or Dog was skulking there: He found the Coast was clear, and soon retir'd, While Bamkin, with the fright, almost expir'd: But bolder Cit call'd his Companion out, And bid him rally, and take t'other bout. But trembling Rustick, hardly past his fear, Ask'd him, if such Alarms were frequent there? Cockney reply'd, He had them ev'ry Night, But did the Danger, since familiar, slight: He had a thousand times a Night been scar'd, And still, for shelter, to his Hole repair'd. Nay then, quoth Clod pate, feast alone, for me; I of your City never will be Free: Since a poor Mouse can't here in quiet eat, But such Incursions fright him from his Meat; I'll to my Cave, from this lewd Town, repair, And, with less Danger, feast on meaner Fate. The MORAL. ‘An humble Station is a safe Retreat ‘From all the Toils and Dangers of the Great: ‘Nature with this do's favour'd Mortals bless, ‘Wou'd they but value what they might possess: ‘But they, by Pride and Avarice, misled, ‘Affect their Ruin, and their Safety dread: ‘Vainly to Honour, and to Wealth, aspire, ‘'Till in the rash Pursuit themselves they tire; ‘And find, when they the wish'd Acquest enjoy, ‘What shou'd consummate, do's their Bliss destroy. ‘So lofty Tow'rs the rage of Storms endure, ‘From which the lowly Cottage stands secure: ‘In those, the Guests impending Mischief fear, ‘And Lusts, and Disappointments, spoil their Chear: ‘In this, the Owner solid Joys acquires, ‘While Reason bounds, and answers his Desires. FABLE LXIII. The Lion and Mouse: Or, A Deserved Requital. A Lion, tir'd with long Fatigue and Heat, In a close Thicket sought a cool Retreat: There (while at Ease the dreadful Savage lay) A Herd of fearless Mice did round him play: Rouz'd by whose trampling Feet, the angry Beast Secur'd one Mouse, an Hostage for the rest. The Captive begg'd he wou'd his Wrath asswage Tow'rds one unworthy of his noble Rage. The gen'rous Brute, to shew his noble Mind, Wav'd his Resentment, and his Prey resign'd: But did not the Reward of Goodness lose; (So sure he Pity finds, who pity shews) For soon, entangl'd in the Huntsman's Toils, He was become a Spoil, who liv'd by Spoils. At this Misfortune griev'd, he roar'd aloud, To publish his Confinement through the Wood. The grateful Mouse, that heard, and knew his Voice, Ran quickly, as directed by the Noise; And found him, who so nobly set her free, Confin'd, and in despair of Liberty. The pleasing Image of his Kindness past, (Which still in her reflective Thoughts did last) Induc'd her to return the Benefit, She now with equal Favour cou'd requite. In haste to execute the brave Design, To which her Virtue did her Will encline. She with her Teeth attacks the stubborn Cords, And speedy Means for his Escape affords: Thus, by a Work so gloriously essay'd, She, for her Freedom, his Releasement paid. The MORAL. ‘You that are Great forbear to give Offence, ‘And do not, ev'n the meanest Wretch, incense; ‘Lest you (reduc'd by Fortune's restless Wheel) ‘May want his Help, or his Resentment feel. ‘The poorest Object which you scorn and slight, ‘May Benefits, or Injuries, requite. ‘Strive, by unlimited Beneficence, ‘To find, or to deserve, a grateful Sense: ‘For Gratitude can never want a Place ‘In any Mind, but the deprav'd and base. FABLE LXIV. The Vulture's Treat: Or, A Plausible Decoy. A Vulture, that had long been scarce of Meat, Pretends to keep his Birth-day with a Treat; Invites the little Birds, who fearless fly, To celebrate the Anniversary. Their Welcome he in kind Salutes express'd, But quickly made the Guests themselves his Feast: By his false Arts the slaughter'd Victims fall, And grace his Birth-day with their Funeral. The MORAL. ‘Soft soothing Words, not always friendly prove; ‘Mischief oft' shelters in pretended Love. ‘Fair Speeches, when the Thoughts to Ill encline, ‘Are but the Varnish to a foul Design. FABLE LXV. The Dog and Ass: Or, Nothing against the Grain. A clean, sleek Dog, of more than common Parts, By fawning, and insinuating Arts, Did on his Master's Favour so prevail, That he was stroak'd, whene'er he wagg'd his Tail; And from his Trencher shill was nicely fed, Possess'd his Lap all Day, all Night, his Bed. While an Observing Ass, that saw, and griev'd To find his Service not so well receiv'd, Thought, if smooth Mumper did so hugely please, By idle and unprofitable Ease; 'Twas hard, that He, who heavy Burdens bore, Was wrought and lash'd 'till Back and Sides were sore: Therefore resolv'd he wou'd new Measures take, And, by like Ways, like Friendships hope to make. Pleas'd with this Thought, he hastes, his Lord to meet, And on his Shoulders claps his beastly Feet; And, tho' the dirty Hoofs his Cloaths defile, Fancies himself Obliging all the while. But, at this barbarous Salute, afraid, The Master calls the Servants to his Aid: With Stripes they drive the shallow Monster thence, Whose rude Address had giv'n the foul Offence. The MORAL. ‘Who Nature wou'd out-act, with aukward Grace ‘Makes his Effort, and flies in Nature's Face: ‘But he who knows which way his Talent lies, ‘To that his Mind, with good success, applies. ‘The supple Courtier, of brisk Air and Mien, ‘That can Come o'er a Cudgel, for the Queen; ‘May hope, at Court, to thrive and be caress'd, ‘For there such pliant Limberham's live best. ‘Shou'd the rough Soldier, with his mangl'd Face, ‘Affect to cringe, and strain a skue Grimace; ‘How mal-a-droit wou'd that Attempt appear, ‘Which do's the fawning Plausible endear? ‘A stubborn Manly from the Court shou'd vamp ‘As fast, as prim Sir Courtly from the Camp. ‘Fools only strive to go against the Grain, ‘Which renders all such Undertakings vain: ‘The Proverb will hold good, do what they can, ‘For Jack will never make a Gentleman. FABLE LXVI. The Members and Stomach:Or, One Good-turn requires another. The Hands and Feet, in close Cabal, contrive To starve the Stomach, as their way to thrive: They long had grudg'd, that all their Pains and Sweat Were spent, to find the useless Idler Meat; And plainly told her, with impatient haste, She must betake her self to Work, or Fast. She pray'd them oft', Not to be so Unkind; And urg'd, Themselves the ill Effects wou'd find. But her Entreaties still cou'd do no good, They wou'd no more allow her needful Food. She soon (with Hunger famish'd) sickly grew, And they alike began to languish too. Now, to prevent their Ruin, in her Fate, They fain wou'd be officious, but too late: She cou'd no more her usual Meat receive, But loath'd the Plenty they wou'd freely give. Thus, through Neglect, They (as She feeble grew) With her declin'd, and with her perish'd too. The MORAL. ‘Kingdoms and Bodies, whose Societies. ‘Like Members, with each others sympathize: ‘The Parts contribute to support the Whole, ‘Congratulate its Wealth, its Wants condole. ‘He, who these mutual Offices denies, ‘Deprives himself (in Need) of just Supplies. ‘The Prince's Treas'ry, like the Stomach, shows ‘To which, tho' still the Peoples Tribute, flows; ‘'Tis thence (improv'd by good Digestion) sent ‘To ev'ry Member, for its Nourishment: ‘And they, who scruple to provide the Food, ‘Must want themselves the Circulating Blood. ‘So the kind Sun do's to the Earth retail ‘The Vapours, which his Beams from thence exhale: ‘When rarify'd, he showr's 'em back again, ‘In wholsom Dews, and fructifying Rain: ‘But shou'd the Earth those Subsidies with-hold, ‘No fatt'ning Moisture wou'd refresh the Mould. FABLE LXVII. The Sick Kite:Or, Late Repentance seldom True. A Kite, that long by Rapine had been fed, Was Surfeited with Prey, and took his Bed; Death now (on which before he rarely thought) Star'd in his Face, and in his Fancy wrought: But he who had no mind for Dying yet, Desir'd his Mother wou'd the Gods intreat; For, might he Live, he a New Bird wou'd be, No Dove shou'd shew more Innocence than he. His wiser Dam reply'd; Alas! I fear The Gods but little will regard my Pray'r; Nor to a Wretch be eas'ly reconcil'd, Whose sacrilegious Claws their Altars spoil'd: Tho' of your Crimes you now pretend a Sense, And are all over seeming Penitence; The Gods, whose Eyes pierce deeper than the Skin, And, through your Feathers, see your Soul within, Know you wou'd prove, shou'd they your Health restore, The same rapacious Kite you were before. The MORAL. ‘Vainly to Heav'n Men in Distresses flie, ‘Who, in their prosp'rous State, did Heav'n defie. ‘Wou'd you, in Sickness and in Want, be heard? ‘In Health and Plenty, Heav'n alike regard. ‘Small Credit is to late Repentance due, ‘Which scarce our selves can know if false or true; ‘The True, consists in a Regen'rate State, ‘And on a Death-bed seems begun too late: ‘That Time's too short to bring us to the Test ‘How we wou'd Practise what we had Profess'd: ‘For tho', when Sick, we for past Follies mourn, ‘The Bent to Sin may with our Health return. FABLE LXVIII. The Crow and Fox:Or, Credulity abus'd by Flattery. A Crow, that had some grateful Carrion found, Made all the Forest, with her Joy, resound; Nor cou'd in silence eat her Dainty Fare, But from a Tree proclaim'd aloud her Chear. A subtle Fox, that from his neighb'ring Earth, Perceiv'd the reason of her clam'rous Mirth, Had a shrew'd Plot upon her envy'd Prize: And knowing she was fond of Flatteries, Accosts the Prater thus; Illustrious Dame, I oft' have heard, there is no Truth in Fame; And now I am confirm'd, by seeing you, That Fame's a Lyar, and the Proverb true. Fame, to the World, reports you black as Night, Tho' sure, no Morning is so fair or bright; Your Colour do's the purest Snow excell; And, if your Voice's Charms are parallel, There is no Bird on Earth, that ever flew, But must allow the Preference to you. Corbè, thus wheedl'd, fancies she can sing As well as any Nightingale in Spring: With this Conceit, she strives to raise her Note, But drops her Prey, as she extends her Throat. Reynard, with his successful Flatt'ry pleas'd, Laugh'd at her Folly, and her Booty seiz'd: While her Credulity she justly blam'd, Griev'd at her Loss, and of her Pride asham'd. The MORAL. ‘Thus, Flatt'ry do's Vain-glorious Fools betray ‘To ev'ry Parasite an easie Prey: ‘While Praise, beyond their Merit, they believe, ‘They are fit Tools for Flatt'rers to deceive; ‘Who thus th' Ascendant o'er their Favour get, ‘And pipe the list'ning Boobies to their Net. ‘Keep then, to countermine such dang'rous Arts, ‘A modest Sense of thy applauded Parts: ‘The Man, who of himself ne'er thinks too high, ‘Can all the Pow'r of wheedling Charms defie: ‘In vain the Syrens sing, he shill stands fast, ‘Like Ithacus, leash'd firmly to the Mast.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">BOOK II. FABLE I. The Lion and Goat:Or, Advice for Interest. A hungry Lion, that observ'd, with Grief, A Goat, that brouz'd along a rocky Cliff; Advis'd her, not to take such fruitless Pains, Who might have better Pasture on the Plains. The Goat reply'd; Your Counsel, Sir, is good, But I prefer my Safety to my Food: The Kindness you in this Advice have shown, Is not to ease my Hunger, but your own. The MORAL. ‘False Friends, with plausible Advice, betray ‘The easie Fool on whom they hope to prey: ‘While they his Int'rest speciously pretend, ‘Their own Advantage is the secret End. FABLE II. The Mistress and her Maids:Or, An Ill Disease, a Worse Remedy. An aged Huswife, who did many Years, Divide her Time between her Work, and Pray'rs, And knew how Idleness enclin'd to Vice, Made all her Maidens at first Cock-crow rise; And gave them Tasks to finish e're 'twas Light; For Sleep, she said, requir'd but half the Night. The lazy Baggages, too fond of Bed, Thought this a very weary Life they led; And (that they might lie longer still, and sleep) Destroy'd the Cock, who such ill Hours did keep. But soon they found their wise Contrivance short; For what they meant shou'd lengthen, spoil'd their Sport: Their Dame, not knowing how the Minutes fled, Call'd them to rise, e're they were warm in Bed. The MORAL. ‘Thus, from one Evil, Fools to greater run, ‘And, by their own Devices, are undone: ‘While they contrive to shun what do's not please, ‘The Remedy proves worse than the Disease: ‘Like botching Workmen, they much Skill pretend, ‘But spoil whate'er they undertake to mend. FABLE III. The Sow and Bitch:Or, More Haste, than good Speed. A Sow and Bitch, engag'd in warm Dispute, Whose Womb was most Prolifick in its Fruit: The Bitch affirm'd, She, each revolving Year, Did oft'ner, and more num'rous Litters, bear. The Sow reply'd; Small cause to boast, you find, For all your haste; you whelp your Puppies blind. The MORAL. ‘Some, in few Months, more bulky Volumes write, ‘Than Others in as many Years indite; ‘But, the true Credit, which their Works obtain, ‘Not from Dispatch, but from Perfection, gain: ‘And Books, that pass too soon the Author's Hand, ‘Too long upon the Seller's Shelves may stand. FABLE IV. The Pine and Shrubs:Or, High Stations, insecure. A lofty Pine, some humble Shrubs despis'd, Valu'd his Use, and his Employment pris'd; Boasted his Height, for which he did deserve In Princes Navies, and their Courts, to serve; While the low Brambles, of ignoble Kind, Were for no Use, unless to burn, design'd. The Shrubs reply'd; Tho' you, Exalted Sir, Insult our Baseness, and your Worth prefer; Still our Advantages you have forgot, And what Misfortunes often are your Lot: When the keen Ax shall your large Trunk invade, And all your Honour in the Dust is laid; You will not then our Lowly State abuse, But wou'd our Meanness, with our Safety, chuse. The MORAL. ‘Appendant Ills on Lofty Stations wait; ‘The Lowly, find a more propitious Fate: ‘These rest secure within their humble Sphere, ‘And, free from Danger, are exempt from Fear: ‘But those, expos'd to ev'ry Tempest's Rage, ‘Feel the Misfortunes which their Fears presage: ‘Their Glory, like a Structure rais'd too high, ‘Soon tumbles down, and always stands awry. FABLE V. The Mountain in Labour:Or, A great Cry, and little Wool. A pregnant Mountain long had heaving lain, As if some monstrous Burden caus'd its Pain: The neighb'ring People, in a deadly fright, Flock'd round in Crouds to the prodigious Sight: And while devoutly they Lucina call, Out creeps a puny Mouse, and shams them all. The MORAL. ‘Believe not those who great Atchievements boast; ‘For they who most pretend, deceive us most. ‘When swelling Words have rais'd our Hope, or Fear, ‘The Passions greater than their Cause appear. FABLE VI. The Boar and Ass:Or, Generous Contempt. A sluggish Ass, sprung from ignoble Blood, Had ridicul'd the Vice roy of the Wood. At which the gen'rous Boar, with brave Disdain, Gnash'd his sharp Tusks but scorn'd to rage in vain: More nobly his Resentment was express'd, While, with this Reprimand, he aw'd the Beast: Thy Insolencies dire Revenge provoke; But, Slave, thy Baseness do's divert the Stroke: Go, and oblig'd to thy own Dulness, live, Which 'tis more shame to punish, than forgive. The MORAL. ‘When servile Tongues on Men of Worth reflect, ‘Their best Resentment is, a slight Neglect. ‘Let no unworthy Usage tempt thy Pow'r ‘To a Revenge, that wou'd disgrace thee more. FABLE VII. The Lion, and other Beasts:Or, Unequal Friendships, incompatible. The Sov'reign Lion, vers'd in State-Intrigue, Concerted, with the Subject-Beasts, a League, That they an equal Dividend shou'd make Of all the Game they cou'd, in Hunting, take. Abroad they went on their appointed Day, And soon a lusty Buck became their Prey: Of which a just Partition being made, Each took his Share, and on his Shoulders laid. The Lion, roaring, made his Partners quake, Who saw the Danger of their gross Mistake: For tho' he promis'd Each shou'd have his Part, 'Twas not the true Intention of his Heart: And they who wou'd in Courts securely live, Shou'd not take all that Princes seem to give. One Share, said he, is mine, as I am Best; Another, as my Strength exceeds the rest; A third, because I had the most Fatigue; A fourth, because—if not,—here ends our League. This said, they all in silence slunk away; They did not, for they durst not, disobey. The MORAL. ‘Poor Men, with Rich, in ill-match'd Friendships join'd, ‘Are Gally-Slaves in Golden-Chains confin'd; ‘Who, tho' their Fetters make a splendid Show, ‘Are, at another's Pleasure, bound to Row. ‘The Poor Man, as the Rich direct him, steers; ‘He, hapless Wretch, must have no Will, but theirs; ‘While all the Good his Slavery affords, ‘Is, the bare Smile and Count'nance of his Lords. ‘And tho' the Mighty thus the Mean oppress, ‘They, with less harm, submit, than seek Redress: ‘And, when they have Occasion to Complain, ‘Must Praise the Pow'r whence they the Wrong sustain. ‘Like Flyes with Torches, Subjects deal with Kings; ‘By a too near Approach, they singe their Wings: ‘Free and secure, they at a distance flie; ‘But, if they dally with the Flame, they die. ‘A Prince's Smiles, his Fav'rites shou'd invite ‘T'admire, not grow familiar with, his Light; ‘Lest (as the Sun strikes close Observers blind) ‘In their Encroachment, they their Ruin find. ‘Wou'dst thou, among the Great, in Favour live; ‘The Injuries they do, with Thanks receive: ‘Dissemble Wrongs; seem not their Faults to see; ‘Be thou their Servant, they'll be Friends to thee. FABLE VIII. The Mouse and Frog:Or, The Miseries of Civil War. While the small Empire of a Pool they sought, A Mouse and Frog a bloody Combat fought: A brandish'd Bull-rush was each Champion's Spear; Each, for his Target, did a Mushroom bear. The Fight grew desp'rate, and 'twas hard to find To which Side Victory seem'd most enclin'd. The weaker Mouse, from secret Ambuscade, Did her strong Foe, by Stratagem, invade. The Frog, whose greater Strength Advantage gain'd, By open Force the doubtful War maintain'd: 'Till, from aloft the Clouds, a touring Kite Beheld the Fray, and triumph'd at the Sight: Then, with a sudden Swoop, (while each, enrag'd, Regardless of himself, his Foe engag'd) She seiz'd, and made them both at once her Prey; And did her Thirst for Blood, and theirs, allay. The MORAL. ‘A Fate, like this, contending Factions have, ‘Who, seeking Empire, do themselves enslave: ‘While they their Forces, as their Minds, divide, ‘Their Strength is but by halves on either Side; ‘And they, enfeebled by Intestine Broils, ‘Tempt Foreign Powr's to seize their easie Spoils. ‘The dire Effects of such an ill Dispute, ‘Left Rome Oppress'd, and Cæsar Absolute. FABLE IX. The Bigamists:Or, Divided Couples, Joint-Sufferers. A Man who bury'd one beloved Wife, And, for her sake, admir'd a Marry'd-Life; To lose no Time, (whose precious Worth he knew) Soon took another, and a Widow too. She led him many weary Nights and Days, And teaz'd him still with her first Husband's Praise: While he, resolv'd to fit her in her kind, As often call'd his former Wife to mind. One Night it happen'd that, in moody Pet, She carv'd a Capon, for their Supper set; And, out of no Compassion to the Poor, Serv'd with one half a Beggar at the Door; And with it gave this Charge; Take this half Fowl, And Pray sometimes for my Dead Husband's Soul. The Living Husband, to return the Jest, Call'd back the Man, and gave him all the rest; With this Injunction too, That all his Life, He shou'd remember his Departed Wife. Thus, to upbraid each other with their Dead, The empty Fools went Supperless to Bed. The MORAL. ‘When Discord sep'rates those whom Heaven had join'd, ‘And their One-Flesh grows diff'rently enclin'd, ‘They still like this unhappy Couple act; ‘Ruin their Fortunes, and their Minds distract: ‘While each, to vex the other, grows Profuse, ‘They both themselves to equal Want reduce. ‘Husband and Wife, in their Conjunction, seem ‘Like Oxen yoak'd together in a Team: ‘If they together draw, they still improve; ‘But still lose Ground, if diff'rent Ways they move. FABLE X. The Sick Lion and Fox:Or, No Halting before Cripples. The Lion, seiz'd with Sickness, took his Bed; And now the Beasts no more his Fury dread: They all to him officious Visits pay; Only mis-doubting Reynard kept away. To him the Prince a Letter Missive sent, With Invitations, full of Compliment; Told him, No Company like his did please, Or cou'd so much contribute to his Ease; Pray'd him to come, and bid him fear no Harm; For now his Weakness did his Rage disarm. The Fox return'd; He wish'd his royal Health, With long encrease, alike, of Years, and Wealth; For which with Heav'n he all his Int'rest us'd; But, for a Visit, pray'd to be excus'd: He cou'd not yet dismiss his former Awe, Too much alarm'd by what he daily saw: For Tracts of Beasts, into his Den, were plain, But none appear'd, of coming out again: By which he guess'd, that all who thither went, Were, on his Errand, a long Journey sent. The MORAL. ‘Let not fair Words, which sly Dissemblers give, ‘Thy too secure Credulity deceive; ‘Regard not what they say, but what they do; ‘Their Actions best will their Intentions shew. ‘Learn to distrust: He who suspects a Cheat, ‘Escapes all Cheats, and triumphs o'er Deceit. FABLE XI. The Lapwing:Or, Honour Misplaced. The Eagle did his Feather'd-Subjects Treat, And gave each Quality its proper Seat: But all the Guests express'd a high Disgust, To see the Lapwing next their Sov'raign thrust; Who only was for his Crown'd Head preferr'd, Tho' Mire and Filth the Sloven's Feet besmear'd. The MORAL. ‘The Undiscerning most Regard express ‘For a Gay Out-side, and a Gaudy Dress: ‘But Wiser Men, who dive into the Mind, ‘And its Deformities, or Beauties, find; ‘For them, the Owners honour, or despise, ‘And most the Garment, for the Lining, prise. FABLE XII. The Negro:Or, Labour in Vain. A shallow 'Squire, who had a Negro bought, His Sooty Face too long neglected thought; And, in great hope to make him White and Fair, Had him well Scour'd with wond'rous Pains and Care: But spent his Labour, Soap, and Time, in vain; The Native Black, did still a Black remain. The MORAL. ‘The Characters that Nature has impress'd, ‘Keep their primæval Stamp on ev'ry Breast; ‘And he that wou'd, what's printed there, erase, ‘As well might hope to blanch a Negro's Face. ‘No Pow'r an Innate Quality can sway, ‘That to its Native Bent will force its Way: ‘And still, the more it is diverted thence, ‘Recurrs with more impetuous Violence. FABLE XIII. The Kid and Wolf:Or, Safe and Saucy. A Kid, that in a Citadel was fed, As o'er the Rampart once he rais'd his Head, Observ'd a raw-bon'd Wolf pass gently by, And, with loud Taunts, revil'd his Enemy. The patient Wolf (who knew that strong Defence Encourag'd such unus'al Insolence) With Scorn, reply'd, Your Slights are not Disgrace; For 'tis not You insult me, 'tis the Place. The MORAL. ‘Safety gives Insolence to ev'ry Slave; ‘And Cowards, when secure, insult the Brave; ‘Who, with Contempt, the bold Affronts receive, ‘Which those, unless protected, durst not give. FABLE XIV. The Leopard and Fox:Or, Intrinsick Beauty best. A Leopard, for his outward Beauty, pris'd Himself, and all his fellow-Beasts despis'd. A wiser Fox, that did his Pride disdain, Advis'd the Creature not to be so vain; And told him, 'Tis not in a specious Skin True Worth consists, but Ornaments within: Why then shou'dst thou, conceited Fop, said he, For thy gay Cloathing, look a-skue on me? Heav'n, that this Out-side has to thee assign'd, Gives me th' Advantage of a fairer Mind. The MORAL. ‘Exterior Charms, and superficial Grace, ‘To the rich Ornament of Mind give Place: ‘For Chances may, and Age will, those impair, ‘But these, immortal as their Subject are. FABLE XV. The Hawks and Doves:Or, When Thieves Fall out, Honest Men Thrive. The Hawks Fall'n out, in Civil War engage, And on each other vent their deadly Rage: While the less Birds, no more restrain'd by Fear, Enjoy the Freedom of their Native Air: 'Till (griev'd to see their bloody Feuds encrease) The mediating Doves procure a Peace. The Hawks, thus reconcil'd, new Broils concert, And on the weaker Flocks their Force divert; But treat the Doves at the severest Rate, Who own'd, their Folly did deserve the Fate. The MORAL. ‘Men, who litigious Neighbours reconcile, ‘Oft', by such Measures, do themselves embroil: ‘For Knaves, who love in Brangles to engage, ‘On one or other will discharge their Rage: ‘And Honest Men can only then be free, ‘When Villains, that disturb them, disagree. FABLE XVI. The Mourning Wife:Or, Self-Love most prevalent. A virtuous Wife, who did her Husband prise Above all Objects else that pleas'd her Eyes, Found, by his Sickness, all her Joys allay'd: So soon do Flow'rs of worldly Pleasures fade. She Sigh'd, she Wept, and made continual Moan, And, to redeem his Life, wou'd give her own. Grim Death appear'd, the Ransom to demand, And put the frighted Lady to a Stand: Her hasty Offer she did soon repent, And thought she strain'd too far the Compliment: Wisely consid'ring, (tho' the Fate was hard) Since one must die, he might as well be spar'd: And she, who did for her Old Mate complain, Might, by a New, be comforted again. Since then to either Choice she must be forc'd, And from her Husband, or the World, divorc'd; To part with him, she rather did encline, And not so soon her own sweet Life resign. Resolv'd on this, she gently Death bespoke; Take heed you do not mis-direct your Stroke: You see I am not in the way to die; 'Tis my poor Husband there, is sick, not I; And tho' I gladly his Reprieve wou'd get, I cannot think of making Worms-meat yet. The MORAL. ‘Few Men their Friends to such excess adore, ‘But that their Value for themselves is more: ‘Self-Love outweighs what else they hold most dear; ‘The Skin is nearer, tho' the Shirt be near. FABLE XVII. The Geese, Cranes, and Stork:Or, An equal Guilt, deserves an equal Punishment. Some Geese and Cranes (a most pernicious Breed To new-sown Ground) devour'd a Farmer's Seed: He pitch'd his Net, and with successful Work, Took them, and, in their Company, a Stork. She begg'd the injur'd Hind to let her loose, And pleaded, She was neither Crane nor Goose; But a rare Bird, with noble Parts endu'd, And fam'd for filial Love, and Gratitude. The Man reply'd; This I already know; Love your good Qualities, and praise them too: But, since you did with these Transgressors flie, Your Guilt's alike, and you alike must die. The MORAL. ‘He that does Ill, and he that gives Consent, ‘Justly deserve an equal Punishment: ‘For Accessories to a lawless Act, ‘Incur like Guilt with those who do the Fact. ‘They boast their noble Qualities in vain, ‘When base Confed'racies their Merit stain. FABLE XVIII. The Jealous Husband:Or, No Watch for a Woman. A doating Husband, Jealous of his Wife, For the loose Conduct of her airy Life; His own, and her Dishonour, to prevent, To a try'd Friend the Wanton Lady sent; Profusely promising a large Reward, If he wou'd so the Fairy-Treasure guard, That no Contrivance might his Caution mock, And no False-Key the Cabinet unlock. His Friend (in ev'ry Instance kind and just) Accepted, and was faithful to the Trust; But found The Task wou'd baffle all his Care, To Watch a Woman, volatil as Air; Who did so nicely her Intrigues refine, No Eye or Thought cou'd pierce the close Design. For when a Woman to Deflection leans, What do's incite the Will, procures the Means: Or, shou'd her Body be restrain'd from Sin, What she wou'd be without, she is within. This made the Guardian weary of his Charge, Who, maugre his Inspection, liv'd at large: And he, good Man (whose Faith cou'd not dispense To please her Latitudinarian Sense) Desir'd her Husband wou'd, for both their Ease, Him from his Trust, her from her Guard, release; For her Lewd Wiles wou'd baulk a thousand Spies, Tho' all, like Argus, were stuck round with Eyes. He added too, He wish'd to be preferr'd Rather a Drove of whiffling Fleas to herd, Lead them to feed, and bring them back to sleep; Than one versute Contriving Woman keep. The MORAL. ‘Thus a Lewd Woman is confin'd in vain, ‘No Guards, or Spies, can her Designs restrain: ‘Like Jugglers, she (too nimble for our Eyes) ‘With Slight of Thought, our Caution do's surprise. ‘If Freedom cannot keep her innocent, ‘Restriction less will her light Shifts prevent: ‘That eggs her on to the Forbidden-Meat, ‘And when she Wills it, she finds Means to eat. FABLE XIX. The Geese and Cranes:Or, Poverty and Security. Some Geese and Cranes, by tempting Plenty led, Chose a rich Field, and at Discretion fed; 'Till, by the noisie Cacklings which they made, Their Haunt was to the injur'd Hind betray'd: He soon attack'd them; but the Cranes were light, And shun'd his Fury, by an easie Flight: While, by their weight, the Geese retarded, stay, And, with their Lives, for all the Trespass pay. The MORAL. ‘The Rich, by Fortune too much pamper'd, owe ‘Their Ruin to the Bulk to which they grow: ‘While Wealth's bright Charms invite the Plund'rer's Rape, ‘Its gross Incumbrance hinders an Escape: ‘But Poor Men find, in Indigence, Relief, ‘Their Nothing, baulks the Tyrant and the Thief. FABLE XX. The Fowler and Birds:Or, Something has some Savour. An eager Fowler, big with hopes of Luck, Had spread his Nets, and all his Lime-twigs stuck; And largely scatter'd the deluding Bait, To tempt the Birds the sooner to their Fate. A little Flock to the Refection flew; But those he scorn'd, and thought they were too few: When they had fill'd themselves, they took their flight, And soon another Party did alight. The greedy Fool, expecting better Prey, Let them too unmolested fly away. All Day he waited thus, and cou'd not find A Number suited to his boundless Mind: At last, when tir'd, and Night was drawing on, And all the well-fed Birds to Roost were gone; He saw his Hopes deceiv'd, when they were fled, And thought it time he too shou'd go to Bed: Then drew his Nets, in order to retire, And found but one poor Finch his whole Day's Hire. The MORAL. ‘They who sure Profit slight, because but small, ‘Arrive at Wealth but rarely, if at all: ‘Those sooner are enrich'd, who wisely count, ‘That many Units to a Sum amount: ‘And when those Littles in a Bulk unite, ‘The Purse grows heavy, tho' the Gains were light. FABLE XXI. The Corrupt Judge:Or, Ill gotten, Ill gone. A Judge, whose biass'd Hand, by Brib'ry sway'd, The Scales of Justice oft' unequal made; When sentenc'd to refund his ill-got Gain; What he with Pleasure took, return'd with Pain. One that observ'd his Lordship fume and fret, Made this Remark on his extream Regret: How like the Female-Sex our Judge appears, Conceives in Transports, but Brings forth in Tears. The MORAL. ‘The Wretches, whose brib'd Hands Corruption fouls, ‘And casts a deeper Sullage o'er their Souls; ‘Small Pleasure in their vile Acquests shall take, ‘Which they must leave, or which will them forsake. ‘Heav'n will not let them long enjoy the Gain ‘Which, by perverting Justice, they obtain: ‘What with Delight, tho' basely, they amass'd, ‘They shall as ill, with Terror, quit at last. ‘So Gluttons, who beyond Repletion eat, ‘And clog their Stomachs with Excess of Meat, ‘Find nauseous Crudities their Entrails burn; ‘And what they took with joy, with grief return. FABLE XXII. The Curr and Ox:Or, Dog in Manger. A hard-wrought Ox, that scarce had time to eat, Came to the Crib, to snatch a Chew of Meat: But a cross Messen, that beneath it lay, With envious snarling, drove him from the Hay. To whom the Ox; A Rope your fortune be, Who will not eat your self, nor suffer me! The MORAL. ‘Ill Men repine at what the Good enjoy, ‘And wou'd the Bliss, deny'd themselves, destroy: ‘Worth they malign; and labour to impair ‘What their base Souls allow them not to share. ‘And may they still that Virtue see, with Pain, ‘Which, tho' they envy, they neglect to gain. FABLE XXIII. The Miser and his Bags:Or, Parsimony makes Prodigals. A Miser, whose insatiate Thirst of Gain No Store cou'd satisfie, no Bounds restrain; Who still, amidst his Affluence, was poor, And, as his Wealth encreas'd, still grasp'd at more: Was call'd, by Death, to quit his darling Hoord, Since he wou'd none for Life's Support afford. The Wretch, alarm'd thereat, did sadly weep, And thus took leave of what he cou'd not keep: Tell me, dear Gold, Tell me, my precious Store, Whom thou must please, when I shall be no more? We, said the Bags, shall please your joyful Heir, (Who will in Riot waste what you did spare:) Nor him alone; but the Infernal Pow'rs; Who, by our Means, will have his Soul, and yours. The MORAL. ‘In vain we labour for such useless Gains ‘As we allow not to reward our Pains: ‘In vain, while others our Acquests possess, ‘Encrease our Torments for their Happiness. ‘He who denies himself what Nature craves, ‘Loses the Benefit of what he saves: ‘And what the pinching Father dares not use, ‘Supplies the Son with Means to live profuse. ‘Thus both, their Talents diff'rent Ways mis-spend, ‘But meet and centre in one fatal End. FABLE XXIV. The Lion and Horse:Or, The Dissembler Out-done. A hungry Lion wou'd a Horse devour, But Age had weaken'd, and restrain'd his Pow'r: The Politician, since his Strength did fail, By Stratagem endeavour'd to prevail: Himself an eminent Physician feign'd, And with long Cant his Hearers entertain'd. The Horse, of his Design suspicious grows, Do's Art to Art, and Fraud to Fraud, oppose; Pretends, a Thorn had lately prick'd his Hoof, And of the Doctor's Skill desires a Proof: Who soon consents, but soon his Error feels, He found the Horse too well cou'd use his Heels: With them he struck the Lion almost dead; With them, from his pursuing Vengeance fled. Rewarded thus, his ill Success he mourn'd, But own'd, his Falshood justly was return'd. The MORAL. ‘Dissemblers often desp'rate Hazards run, ‘By those they sham, in their own Arts out-done: ‘While they for others secret Traps prepare, ‘They fall into an undiscover'd Snare. ‘'Tis just, Delusion shou'd that Service pay, ‘Which, by Delusion, others wou'd betray. FABLE XXV. The Shepherd's Boy:Or, A Lyar not Credited. A wanton Boy, that kept his Master's Flock, The Neighbours Care and Kindness us'd to mock: Often he cry'd, The Wolf! The Wolf is come! And brought the friendly Villagers from Home. When still they came, well arm'd, the Folds to guard, They found no Wolf, but the abusive 'Herd. Thus oft' deluded, they observ'd no more His Cry, but let him, unregarded, roar: At last, the Wolf attack'd the Folds indeed; The Boy cry'd out; the People gave no heed: They were so oft', by false Alarms, deceiv'd, They thought he was not fit to be believ'd. The MORAL. ‘A noted Lyar meets this due Reward, ‘That his Reports, tho' true, find no Regard: ‘To gain Belief, he must to Strangers go; ‘For none will trust him, who his Falshood know: ‘But try'd Veracity no Voucher needs, ‘None scruple to believe what thence proceeds. ‘Their own Credentials true Men recommend, ‘And we on them, as Oracles depend. FABLE XXVI. The Shepherd's Dog:Or, Trust betray'd. A Dog, entrusted with his Master's Sheep, And highly fed, the stricter Watch to keep; Not so contented, did his Trust betray, And on the Flock, he shou'd have guarded, prey. His Master, angry at so base a Slur, Justly resolv'd to hang the treach'rous Curr. The Dog alledg'd, He shou'd his Menial spare, And for the Wolf that Scene of Death prepare. The Master answer'd, He's declar'd my Foe, And acts as I expect a Wolf wou'd do: But you, in whom I have repos'd my Trust, Deserve worse Treatment, since you prove Unjust: While specious Shews of Friendship you pretend, You worry those I keep you to defend: This makes Resentment overcome my Grief; Tho' I lament the Dog, I'll hang the Thief. The MORAL. ‘Where Men an open Enmity declare, ‘We Wrongs from them, with less Resentment, bear: ‘But where, with Shews of Friendship, they deceive, ‘'Tis more than human Patience can forgive: ‘And a Foe shelter'd in a seeming Friend, ‘Deserves a Halter shou'd his Treach'ry end: ‘For Enemies profess'd, with ease we shun; ‘'Tis the False Friend by whom we are undone. FABLE XXVII. Jupiter and the Serpent:Or, Sinners Sacrifice rejected. Jove, pleas'd to celebrate his Nuptial Feast, Made ev'ry Animal a welcome Guest: And each, as his Ability allow'd, Some grateful Present on the God bestow'd. Among the Croud the pois'nous Serpent went, And to his Godship did a Rose present. Offended at her Sight, he turn'd aside, And her disdain'd Oblation thus deny'd; Tho' I with Pleasure other Off'rings take, Thy Gift is slighted for the Giver's sake. The MORAL. ‘No Gifts from Men of base Designs receive, ‘For Treach'ry lurks in ev'ry thing they give: ‘And Wise Men, who beyond Appearance look, ‘Beneath the specious Bait perceive the Hook. ‘Heav'n do's Oblations from ill Men despise, ‘And, as their Crimes, detests their Sacrifice; ‘Abhors the Incense whose deceitful Smoak ‘Is rais'd, their blacker Villanies to cloak. FABLE XXVIII. The new Cardinal:Or, The Clerk forgets he was a Sexton. A Man of Sense and Manners, gladly heard His Friend was to a Card'nal's Hat preferr'd; And that he might his Rise congratulate, Went to admire, and to encrease his State. But his new Eminence, with haughty Grace, Seem'd not to know, and ask'd him who he was. To whom his Friend made this jocose Return; My Lord, your high Preferment makes me mourn: Since you in this exalted Station set, Your old Acquaintance, and your self, forget. The MORAL. ‘The Proud, whose Minds do with their Fortunes rise, ‘Their former State, and former Friends, despise: ‘Nor shou'd we wonder they to both are strange; ‘For Men their Manners, as their Stations, change: ‘And, when advanc'd, on others look a-skue, ‘Who, they are sensible, their Meanness knew. FABLE XXIX. The Knight and his Lady:Or, Vice corrects Sin. A Knight, by Birth, and ample Fortune, great, Whose outward Happiness appear'd compleat; To these rich Blessings had a base Allay, A shrewd ill Wife, that plagu'd him Night and Day. This Lady, with a seeming Zeal for Heav'n, Was very much to her Devotion given: But more with her Confessor's Comforts pleas'd, With him her Conscience rather clogg'd, than eas'd: To him, who knew her Secrets but too well, She still, good Soul! had some new Sin to tell: Tho' 'twas her real Bus'ness to make known Her Husband's Failings, and encrease her own. The Holy Father, whom Compassion mov'd, With wont Authority the Knight reprov'd; And, at his Wife's importunate Request, Enjoin'd him soon to come and be Confess'd: That Penance done, and Absolution giv'n, He might be reconcil'd to her and Heav'n. The Knight, who durst not disobey Command, Unless he wou'd the Church's Thunder stand, Next Day to the Confessionary went, In Posture of an humble Penitent: But kneeling mute, the grave Impostor cry'd, Discover all your Sins, and nothing hide! The Knight reply'd, In vain your ill-mask'd Zeal Requires I shou'd, what you well know, reveal: You need not, Rev'rend Sir, my Faults explore, My Wife has often told you all, and more. The MORAL. ‘They who, with false Pretence of Zeal, reflect ‘On others Vices, and their Faults correct; ‘Yet labour under greater of their own, ‘And blush not at the Crimes they act unknown: ‘When once discover'd through the thin Disguise, ‘Meet just Reproof for their Hypocrisies; ‘They find the heavy Censures they inflict, ‘Strongly retorted, and themselves convict. FABLE XXX. The Horse and Ass:Or, Many Hands make light Work. A Carrier, that along the Road did pass, Drove a light Horse, and an o'er-loaded Ass. The Ass, with his excessive Burden tir'd, The Horse's Help to bear a Part desir'd: But he so long the poor Request deny'd, That the o'er-burden'd Ass fell down, and dy'd. The Carrier soon remov'd the weighty Pack, And laid it on the churlish Horse's Back; Then flea'd the Ass, whom Death from Pain releas'd, And, with his Hide, the heavy Load encreas'd. The Horse, oppress'd, thus to his Master cry'd, I am deserv'dly punish'd for my Pride: I, who refus'd to bear a Part before, Am now condemn'd to carry All, and more. The MORAL. ‘When many Shoulders do a Load sustain, ‘No one finds just occasion to complain: ‘The Weight to All is light and easie made, ‘But sinks the Wretch on whom 'tis wholly laid. ‘They who, unmov'd, see Fate their Friends oppress, ‘And will not give them Succour in Distress; ‘May, by that Slight, be brought to want Relief, ‘When they are sunk with more oppressive Grief. FABLE XXXI. The Collier and Fuller:Or, A Man known by his Company. A sooty Collier farm'd a House too large; And, that he might be eas'd of half the Charge, Desir'd a cleanly Fuller wou'd consent To be Joint-Partner in the Tenement. The prudent Fuller modestly refus'd His Offer, and desir'd to be excus'd: For Friend, said he, my Neighbourhood with you, Wou'd spoil my Work, and Reputation too: For what my Art do's Whiten, wou'd be made As Smutty as the Coals in which you trade. The MORAL. ‘With cautious heed beware with whom you sort, ‘For thence proceeds all good or ill Report: ‘The World, that sees who your Associates are, ‘Will, from their Credit, make your Character. ‘If with the Vicious you mis-spend your Hours, ‘Their sully'd Fame will quickly blacken yours. ‘Mankind, that Things by Common Course respects, ‘And knows, One tainted Sheep the Flock infects, ‘Will judge your Morals hardly can be sound, ‘While with your loose, debauch'd Companions found. ‘As Men that from Infected Places come, ‘Must pass Probation, e're admitted Home; ‘So they who live in Vice's pois'nous Air, ‘Waken the Virtuous, and alarm their Care; ‘And e're they can their good Opinion gain, ‘Must undergo a tedious Quarantain. FABLE XXXII. The Nut-Tree and Lady:Or, The Inquisitor silenc'd. A glib-tong'd Dame, who Silence never lov'd, And very much her babling self approv'd; In Woods and Groves was often pleas'd to walk, Where, to the Trees, she cou'd with freedom talk: As she her us'al Tour one Evening made, To give her Clack a Loose to its old Trade; She ask'd a Wall-nut-Tree that fac'd the Road, Why there he chose to settle his Abode, Where he with Sticks and Stones was thumpt and bruis'd, And yet, when batter'd most, most Fruit produc'd? The serious Tree (that rather wou'd dispense With that Abuse, than her Impertinence) Reply'd, Is yet the Proverb strange to you, Which sure Experience has long since prov'd true? Three Things, by Drubbing, most improve, A Nut, an Ass, a Woman: The Cudgel from their Backs remove, They will be good for no Man. At this Reply, the silenc'd Dame retir'd, She now had found more Talk than she desir'd. The MORAL. ‘Such Treatment often busie Medlers find, ‘Who less their own, than others Bus'ness mind: ‘When grown vexatiously Inquisitive, ‘They wou'd into their Neighbours Secrets dive: ‘With some unlucky Answer they are paid, ‘That do's the Folly they betray, upbraid. FABLE XXXIII. The Country Dog:Or, Flight encourages Pursuit. A Country Dog, a very rustick Clown, Follow'd his Master to a Market-Town: Whom, when the Dogs of nicer Breeding, found, They flock'd about him, and survey'd him round: With prick'd-up Ears, and Tails, in figure cock'd, They grinn'd, and (as he thought) his Rudeness mock'd. O'er-power'd with Numbers, and o'ercome with Dread, The daunted Stranger took his Heels, and fled: They, by his Flight, encourag'd to pursue, Still follow'd, 'till the Town was out of view: He then took Courage, turn'd, and fac'd his Foes, And to the Combat did himself dispose: But then, afraid to venture the Attack, They hung their Tails, and all went sneaking back. The MORAL. ‘Thus, when arm'd Legions are engag'd in Fight, ‘They yield the Conquest, who begin the Flight; ‘And, by their dastard Cowardice betray'd, ‘Encourage those of whom they are afraid: ‘Their base Retreat, and Faintness in Dispute, ‘Invite the hostile Troops to close Pursuit: ‘By such Endeavours to escape their Foes, ‘They to their Fury more themselves expose. FABLE XXXIV. The Ape and Fox:Or, Much wou'd have More. An Ape, by human Conversation tam'd, Of her indecent Nakedness asham'd; Desir'd a Fox, from his superfluous Tail To spare as much as wou'd her Bareness veil; And said, The Load that did his Speed prevent, Wou'd serve her both for Use and Ornament. He, whom no Care of others Wants did touch, Reply'd, I never thought I had too much: My Tail shall, 'till it sweeps the Kennel, grow, Rather than make a Cover-slut for you. The MORAL. ‘Unequal Fortune, with a partial Hand, ‘Scatters her Favours through her subject Land; ‘While she do's some with pinching Want oppress, ‘She sends home others laden with Excess: ‘But they who most her lib'ral Bounty share, ‘Will from their vast Abundance nothing spare: ‘Since Men (they see) are valu'd for their Store, ‘An Affluence augments their Thirst for more. FABLE XXXV. The Peacock and Pie:Or, Virtue qualifies a Prince. The Birds, that long unaw'd, and free from Fear, Rambled at pleasure through the spacious Air; Not satisfy'd with that more happy State, To chuse a Sov'reign, in close Juncto sate. The Peacock, of his shining Feathers proud, The Empire claim'd, and was by all allow'd: To whom, with lucky Thought, a chatt'ring Pie, In harsh Address, did thus her self apply: Great Sir, Since, by Unanimous Consent, You are Invested in our Government; If the wrong'd Eagle shou'd resent the Slight, And with just Rage the Injury requite; Can all the gaudy Plumes you value thus, From his Insults protect your self, or us? The MORAL. ‘Nor Pomp, nor outward Shew, nor bold Pretence, ‘But inward Virtue, qualifies a Prince. ‘Courage shou'd arm him who affects a Crown, ‘To guard his Subjects Rights, and keep his Own: ‘And he who cannot nobly both maintain, ‘Ruins his Kingdom by a faulty Reign. FABLE XXXVI. The Eagle and Daw:Or, Good Counsel ill design'd. An Eagle, touring long in quest of Prey, Seiz'd a large Scallop on the Sandy Bay; But found the Shell so strong, and clos'd so fast, She cou'd not reach the Meat she long'd to taste. A pert Young Daw, that saw her strive in vain, Advis'd her thus to supersede her Pain: Bear it aloft, and drop it on a Stone, 'Twill crack the Shell, and make the Meat your own. The Eagle mounts, and, in her airy Flight, Let the Fish drop from the stupendous Height. The watchful Daw, observing where it fell, Pick'd the fat Scallop from its broken Shell; Then with her Booty made a swift Retreat, And left the Eagle to resent the Cheat. The MORAL. ‘Of all Advice, and by whom giv'n, beware; ‘That is not safest, that do's best appear. ‘Designing Men, consulting private Ends, ‘Seek their own Int'rest, and pretend their Friend's. FABLE XXXVII. The Buffoon, and Bishop:Or, Little valu'd, lightly quitted. A loose Buffoon, whose Living was by Shifts, On New-Year's-Day stroll'd round the Town for Gifts; And first attack'd the Bishop, whom he knew A wealthy Prelate, but as greedy too: To prove whose Bounty, he made high Demands, And ask'd a Guinea from his Lordship's Hands. My Lord, who rarely did such Gifts bestow, Judg'd the Man mad, or that he thought him so; And his unreasonable Suit deny'd. The Man, repuls'd, again his Goodness try'd; Yet from his first Extravagance came down, And lower'd his Request to Half-a-Crown: Then, finding that too large a Sum was thought, Became more mod'rate, and requir'd a Groat. Still the close Prelate (whose contracted Heart, With what possess'd it most, abhorr'd to part) Thought that too much. At which the Fellow rav'd, And, to expose him, next his Blessing crav'd. The Bishop, pleas'd to find him thus abate, And glad to scape at such an easie Rate, (Because his Purse no want of that wou'd feel) Did readily comply, and bid him kneel. No, answer'd he, your Blessing I despise, Which at so vile an Estimate you prise: For you, who Heav'ns most lib'ral Gifts abuse, Wou'd that, if valu'd at a Groat, refuse. The MORAL. ‘Thus greedy Priests, who (for the Trust unfit) ‘Love not the Office like the Perquisite; ‘Freely dispense Heaven's Treasure to the Poor; ‘But keep their own, because they prise it more. FABLE XXXVIII. The Peasant and his Kid:Or, Gifts recommend the Giver. An honest Peasant, in his Dealings just, Too good to cheat, to simple to distrust; By crafty and litigious Knaves oppress'd, Fled to the Law, in hope to be redress'd: But wholsom Laws, made to restrain Abuse, Were so perverted from their proper Use, That, by a tedious Suit, he suffer'd more, Than by the Wrongs he had sustain'd before. When thus reduc'd, his Bus'ness to conclude, In forma pauperis he truly Su'd. The greedy Counsel, by the Court assign'd, To such dry Clients was but ill enclin'd: And, when the Pauper came to state his Case, Pretended always want of Time, or Place. He often came, but still was forc'd to wait, And cool his Heels, before the Lawyer's Gate. The Porter, who his Face and Bus'ness knew, And how his Master stood affected too, Said, He was busie still, or not at home, And that 'twas best some other time to come. The slighted Client, guessing, by degrees, His Counsel did not Leisure want, but Fees, Cull'd a fat Suckling from his slender Flock, And recommended thus, made bold to knock: Then pinch'd the Kid, whose Bleating did proclaim, That he who Entrance sought, Full-handed came. The docile Porter, by his Master taught To let in all who grateful Presents brought, Open'd the Gate, and with a fawning Grin, Welcom'd the Man, and pray'd him to walk in. The Peasant smil'd, and pleas'd at this Access, Thus to the Means did his just Thanks address; To you, Dear Kid, my Gratitude is due, For my Admittance was procur'd by you. The MORAL. ‘Prevailing Gifts, that often blind the Wise, ‘Open the Miser's Gates, his Ears, and Eyes. ‘The Men, who back'd with such Credentials come, ‘Force their own Way, and for themselves make Room. ‘Whoe'er with such persuasive Rhet'rick Plead, ‘Must gain their Point, and in their Cause succeed. ‘None can those pow'rful Arguments withstand, ‘Which still the Grants they wou'd obtain, command. FABLE XXXIX. The Ewe and Shepherd:Or, Repining, adds to Misery. A Murm'ring Ewe did on the Shepherd rail: For, tho' her swelling Udders fill'd his Pail, The daily Tribute cou'd not buy her Peace, But ev'ry Year he stript her of her Fleece. The Swain, incens'd at the repining Dam, Slew, in her sight, her tender Infant-Lamb. At which, she cry'd, You now can do no more, You have no greater Punishment in Store. Yes, he reply'd, I can my Rage pursue, And, as I kill'd your Son, can slaughter you; Flea off your Skin, as I your Wool do shear, And throw your Carcase for the Wolves to tear. The Ewe, thus aw'd, and for her Life afraid, No more her pow'rful Master durst upbraid. The MORAL. ‘If Heav'n, that amply do's supply our Wants, ‘To try, or punish us, resumes its Grants; ‘If Riches fail, or hopeful Children die, ‘We humbly must with Providence comply. ‘The Blessings we enjoy are all God's Loan, ‘Nor shou'd we murmur, if he claims his own: ‘Repining can so little give us Ease, ‘That what it seeks to lessen, 'twill encrease: ‘For Murm'ring Wretches do Heaven's Wrath provoke ‘To punish them with a severer Stroke. ‘Whoe'er dares question God's Prerogative, ‘And will not let him take, aswell as give; ‘Draws his resenting Vengeance on his Head, ‘And feels the heavy Blow, alive, or dead: ‘But all who to its Will do theirs resign, ‘And ne'er at its Correcting Hand repine, ‘Lighten the Weight they, with Submission, bear, ‘And find Rewards above, for Suff'rings here. FABLE XL. The Wolf and Crane:Or, Favours lost on the Unthankful. A Wolf, half-throttl'd with a cragged Bone, When he had long, unpity'd, made his Moan; Implor'd Assistance from a neighb'ring Crane, To clear his Throat, and ease his raging Pain: And, to induce her to perform the Cure, Did, for the Service, large Rewards assure. By Expectation of his Bounty led, Unwisely she intrusts him with her Head, While down his Throat she gently thrusts her Bill, Draws the rough Bone, and magnifies her Skill. This done, she for her Work her Fee demands, Expecting Wonders at her Patient's Hands. But he, who did no longer want her Aid, With grinning Scorn his kind Physician paid; And bid her take it for a high Reward, That he her Life, for saving his, had spar'd. The MORAL. ‘Service on thankless Men in Pow'r, is lost, ‘They least reward those who oblige them most: ‘Displeas'd that they for Benefits shou'd owe, ‘They hate the Hand that do's the Gift bestow; ‘And think the Gratitude may well suffice, ‘That binds them to refrain from Injuries. FABLE XLI. The Hart and Fountain:Or, Few know their own Interest. A Hart, that at a Fountain smooth and clear, Quenching his Thirst, saw his Reflexion there; Admir'd his branching Horns, and portly Gate, But scorn'd his slender Legs that bore the Weight. In Contemplation long he had not stood, When a loud Hollow echo'd from the Wood: He soon resum'd his wonted Fear, and fled, With more Dependance on his Heels, than Head: But, as in haste he through a Thicket press'd, Entangling Briars did his Horns arrest: Thus seiz'd, he slighted what before he pris'd, And valu'd now the Shanks he had despis'd; For they, he found, did not his Horns oppose, Wou'd bear him off in safety from his Foes. The MORAL. ‘Our Ruin often in our Wishes lies, ‘And most we suffer by what most we prise: ‘Slighting the better Part, we chuse the worse, ‘Neglect a Blessing, and pursue a Curse: ‘We still are to our real Int'rest blind, ‘And grope for Pleasures which we rarely find. FABLE XLII. The Old Batchelor:Or, Marriage out of Season. A wretched Dotard, who, 'till past Threescore, Had liv'd, and shou'd have dy'd, a Batchelor; For the Support of his Decrepit Life, Took that deceitful, bending Crutch, a Wife: But soon the Dolt his sad Mistake perceiv'd; His Need was not so great as he believ'd: For, howsoever useful she might seem, The Lady had not a Meet-help in him. Asham'd and griev'd at what his Age had done, Since he too late had Marry'd, and too soon; He said, I have but ill address'd my Life To answer my Occasions for a Wife: When fit to Marry, I declin'd the State; But enter on it now, when out of Date. The MORAL. ‘A proper Time to all Things is decree'd, ‘Which they attempt too late, who that exceed: ‘The Day is giv'n for Work, for Rest, the Night; ‘Care for the Old, and for the Young, Delight: ‘And they who will not this Decorum keep, ‘Force Nature's Rule, and wake when they shou'd sleep. ‘So he that Marry's in Declining Age, ‘His Entrance makes when he shou'd quit the Stage. FABLE XLIII. The Fox, Hare, and Hounds:Or, Praise ill design'd. A wily Fox, by eager Hounds pursu'd, Who sought all Means their Fury to elude; Observ'd a Hare close sitting in her Form, And hop'd he might on her divert the Storm: Then to the Dogs he makes her Covert known, Applauds her Flesh, and vilifies his own; Assures them, she is most delicious Meat, And fit for Dogs of Quality to eat. The Hounds to seize the nobler Game prepare, Quit the glad Fox, and start the list'ning Hare; But her light Heels from their Pursuit convey The Doubling Puss, and baulk their Hopes of Prey. Kayward, when free'd, her false Commender meets, And with just Taunts the treach'rous Villain greets. To whom the Fox; Since thus you Praise resent, How wou'd you bluster at Disparagement? The MORAL. ‘Insidious Knaves, who base Designs pursue, ‘Commend the Virtue which they wou'd undo: ‘They raise your Character, to sink your Fate; ‘For Envy waits on Praise, on Envy Hate. FABLE XLIV. The Herd:Or, The Wish recall'd. Missing a Calf intrusted to his Care, The troubl'd Herd sought for it ev'ry-where; And in his Search, from Jove implor'd Relief, With Promise of a Kid, to find the Thief. Led on by Hope, he through a Thicket press'd, And found a Lion preying on his Beast: Then scar'd, and trembling at the dreadful Sight, He thus address'd the God, in dismal Fright: I, who to find the Thief, a Kid did vow, Wou'd give a Bull, I might avoid him now. The MORAL. ‘Instable Mortals, who a Loss sustain, ‘Teaze Heav'n with Pray'rs, till they the Thing regain: ‘When 'tis recover'd, it afflicts them more; ‘Now they grow tir'd, of what they sought before. ‘So Parents oft' Pray for their Childrens Life, ‘Which, more than Death, wou'd aggravate their Grief. FABLE XLV. The Fox and Farmer:Or, The Double-Dealer. A Fox, whose Flight a deep-mouth'd Pack did warn, Took Sanctuary in a Farmer's Barn; And, since no other Remedy he saw, Besought the Boor to hide him in the Straw; With Promises, That, to requite his Care, He wou'd hereafter all his Poultry spare. The Man agreed; and, when the following Cry Of Huntsmen ask'd if Reynard was gone by, Stiffly averr'd, He saw him pass that way; But pointed at the Covert where he lay. The eager Sportsmen, on their Game intent, Knew what his Words, but not his Gestures, meant; And, in belief that what he said was true, Follow'd the Chase, and bid the Boor adieu. The Danger past, the Man call'd forth his Guest, And just Performance of his Promise press'd. The Fox, who did his faithless Carriage see, Reply'd; Yes, Sir, as you perform'd to me: Your Double-Dealing in my desp'rate Case, And Ills design'd, the Kindness done deface. The MORAL. ‘Wisely of Double-Dealing Knaves beware, ‘Whose Words and Actions inconsistent are: ‘With fair Pretence your Ruin they desire, ‘And yet expect you shou'd their Faith admire. ‘But they who with ambiguous Help deceive, ‘Deny the Safety they wou'd seem to give. FABLE XLVI. The Fishermen:Or, Hope the Best, Expect the Worst. Some Fishers, as they drew their Net a-Shore, And felt a Weight they ne'er observ'd before, Believ'd they had a mighty Purchase caught, And hugg'd themselves with the transporting Thought: But when they hal'd the winding Sain a-ground, A pond'rous Stone was all the Draught they found. The Fellows, at the Disappointment griev'd, Which had their Labour and their Hopes deceiv'd; 'Till one, whose Age and Sense surpass'd the rest, His discontented Partners thus address'd: Chear up, my Mates, and grieve not at your Fate; Since Sorrow always do's on Pleasure wait, We shou'd provide for ev'ry Chance, if wise: Expected Storms occasion no Surprize. The MORAL. ‘They who consider Man's uncertain State, ‘Expos'd to swift Vicissitudes of Fate, ‘In all Events shou'd reckon nothing strange, ‘Nor, with their Luck, their Resolution change: ‘Such as Expect the Worst, and Hope the Best, ‘Are ne'er too much Exalted, or Depress'd. FABLE XLVII. The Sharpers and Cook:Or, Nothing hid from Heaven. To a Cook's Shop two needy Sharpers go, With empty Maws, and empty Stomachs too: There busily they cheapen all his Meat, Tho', without paying, they design'd to eat: For while one banter'd the embarrass'd Cook, The other from his Shelf a Capon took; Which privately he to his Friend convey'd, Who wore a Cloak to carry on the Trade. The injur'd Cock, thus of his Fowl bereft, Soon miss'd it, and accus'd them of the Theft. But he who stole the Bird, did stiffly swear He had it not, and therefore must be clear: And he who had it, did Heav'n Witness call, That he was free, and stole it not at all. The honest Man, who cou'd not apprehend What their Equivocations did intend; But knew, tho' both their Innocence did boast, That he, between them, had his Capon lost; Reply'd; Well, Sirs, tho' of the Thief I doubt, Just Heav'n, by whom you swear, will find it out. The MORAL. ‘Villains, that can from Men their Mischiefs hide, ‘The stronger Evidence of Heav'n deride; ‘And their black Crimes with Perjury conceal, ‘Nor fear Omniscience shou'd the Guilt reveal. ‘But Sins that may be skreen'd from human Eyes, ‘All-seeing Heav'n, in the Commission, spies; ‘Observes our secret Faults, with strict Regard, ‘And will close Rogues with open Shame reward: ‘Equivocations then, tho' nicely made, ‘Shall not the Guilt, nor Punishment, evade. ‘Receivers, who're with Thieves in Stealths combin'd, ‘Shall be with Thieves in Condemnation join'd. FABLE XLVIII. The Polygamist:Or, Two Wives, two Woes. A Man of Middle Age, nor Young, nor Old, Whose luke-warm Blood was neither hot nor cold; To sute his Constitution, and his Years, Bore, Countercharg'd, Argent, and Sable Hairs. At this Half-bent he cou'd not live alone, But two Wives marry'd, tho' scarce fit for one: His Linsey-woolsey Temper both did crave; One Young and Gay, the other Old and Grave: Between these two he did himself divide, That warm'd his cold, this cool'd his warmer Side: As if they had a Coat in Blazon been; The Partys They, and He the Pale between. But the two Ladies, of unequal Age, Strove who shou'd most her Husband's Love engage; And, while they diff'rent Humours sought to please, They kept the bandy'd Fool at little Ease: The Elder Wife pick'd his Black Hairs away, The Younger pull'd as busily the Grey; And that they with each other might be ev'n. They left him not a Hair 'twixt him and Heav'n. Which made the Neighbours say, His Skull, no doubt, Within as empty was, as bare without. The MORAL. ‘Men grown in Years, shou'd wisely Wives decline, ‘For they but vex each other when they join; ‘But shou'd unequal Matches most avoid, ‘By which their Peace and Freedom are destroy'd: ‘For where prevailing Humours disagree, ‘That jarring Discord drowns all Harmony. ‘Such hapless Husbands no Proportion hold; ‘Too young for old Wives, and for young too old. ‘He that, while Young, betroths an Elder Wife, ‘Turns Tenant, to a falling House, for Life: ‘And he that takes, when Old, a Younger Mate, ‘Erects a Pile too large for his Estate. ‘When the Match suits, the House nor Wants Repair, ‘Nor Furniture, but what his Stock can spare. FABLE XLIX. The Fox and Cat:Or, One Shift better than Many. A Fox and Cat, bound tow'rds a Wood, for Prey, Shortned, with pleasing Chat, the Time and Way: The Fox began his crafty Wiles to boast, Which still were Help at hand, when needed most: He said, He cou'd the Dogs and Huntsmen gull, For he had Shifts at least a Budget full. The Cat reply'd, She had but one Retreat To save her self, and that ne'er fail'd her yet. While thus they talk'd, and had forgot their Fears, A sudden Cry of Hounds alarm'd their Ears: Tybert to her old Method had recourse, Climb'd a tall Tree, and there defy'd their Force. Reynard, by Shifts, to save his Bacon thought, But whi e he doubted which to try, was caught. The MORAL. ‘He whose uncertain Mind has various Drifts, ‘Trusts to vain Counsels, and deceitful Shifts; ‘Is in a Maze, when most with Danger press'd, ‘And lost, while he demurrs what Course is best. ‘But he who still by one sure Method steers, ‘Is unperplex'd with Doubts, and safe from Fears: ‘He gains his Ends by that secure Effort, ‘As Vessels, by the Compass, make their Port. FABLE L. The Fisher and young Fish:Or, A Bird in the Hand, worth two in the Bush. A Fisher, Trolling with his Baited Hook, Deceiv'd a poor young Native of the Brook. The puny Captive pray'd him to excuse Her Youth, that render'd her unfit for Use; And when she to a larger Size was grown, She pass'd her Word, she wou'd be all his own. The Man reply'd, Forbear in vain to prate, I will not purchase Hope at such a Rate; For shou'd I now your Liberty restore, 'Tis ten to one I never hook you more: Excuse me then, that I your Suit deny; For, Friend, I have no other Fish to fry. The MORAL. ‘Such stolid Mortals are for Bedlam fit, ‘Who Certainties, for Expectation, quit; ‘Or think it can the Rate of Joys inhance, ‘Whose sole Attainment must depend on Chance: ‘Since what we seek, we possibly may miss, ‘Fruition only makes a certain Bliss; ‘We know not what the Future may produce, ‘And of the Present Time shou'd make our Use: ‘Well may his disappointed Hopes grow stale, ‘Who lets a Crampus go, to take a Whale. FABLE LI. Arion:Or, Men worse than Brutes. Of all Musicians by Historians nam'd, Whose celebrated Skill made Lesbos fam'd, Admir'd Arion justly challeng'd Place, None Sang or Play'd with equal Art or Grace; Not the sweet Thracian Bard, whose pow'rful Hand Made Mountains move, and rapid Torrents stand; Nor he whose Harp's attractive Sound did call The hast'ning Stones to form the Theban Wall; Were more renown'd, or more did merit Praise: So soft his Airs, so charming were his Lays. The Inspiration in each Note and String Ravish'd the Heart of the Corinthian King; So highly Periander did admire The conqu'ring Musick of his Voice and Lyre. But this great Artist, whose capacious Mind In narrow Limits cou'd not be confin'd, Resolv'd the Triumphs of his Skill to boast In the Italian and Sicilian Coast; Where he to such advantage Sang and Play'd, That all his Hearers were his Captives made: His influencing Tunes, in either Land, Their Ears and Purses did alike command: So much the Crouds his rare Performance pris'd, That, for its Raptures, they their Gold despis'd. Enrich'd, and laden with the shining Spoil, He wou'd re-visit Corinth's dearer Soil; And hir'd a Vessel, by its Natives Mann'd, To bear him back to the delightful Land. But they, who knew how rich a Fraight they bore, Had scarcely left the hospitable Shore, When, for the Lucre of the tempting Prize, They had design'd his Life a Sacrifice. He begg'd Compassion; but, alas! in vain, His Rhetorick no Favour cou'd obtain: That Voice, whose Pow'r, 'till then, did never fail, Cou'd not on their obdurate Hearts prevail: As soon its Sounds the flinty Rocks might pierce, Or calm the Sea, with which they did converse: All that their conscientious Souls allow'd, Was, not to have their Hands imbrew'd in Blood: He therefore must his own Assassine be, And leap (to save their Guilt) into the Sea. (Tho' this Evasion of their Crime was vain, Not all its Water cou'd remove the Stain.) Since Death was irreversibly decree'd, And no smooth Oratory cou'd succeed; He ask'd their Leave to take his Harp along, And, Swan-like, die with an expiring Song. This small Request they did with ease allow, For, so he was but dead, they car'd not how: And they, who never lik'd his Tunes before, Rejoyc'd to hear what they shou'd hear no more. To lofty Notes he rais'd his Strings and Voice, And took his Leap, not as by Force, but Choice. With Joy the brisk Levalto they behold, Pleas'd they had lost him, and secur'd his Gold; And when they thought him past discov'ring Tales, Before the fav'ring Breezes hoist their Sails. But Heav'n, that Melody with Pleasure hears, And keeps a tuneful Consort in its Spheres; (His Ruin, and their Malice, to prevent) To his Relief a Swift-Finn'd Dolphin sent: Which, by him charm'd, and proud of such a Fraight, Himself presented to support his Weight. Arion, who no better Chance cou'd wish, With active Vigour back'd the yielding Fish; And, mounted thus, o'er the curl'd Billows rode, Safe and triumphant, like a Water-God; 'Till by his scaly Courser's kindly Aid, He was to the Laconick Shore convey'd. When there arriv'd, on Corinth still intent, He to his Patron, Periander, went; And to the wond'ring Monarch did relate The sudden Turns of his surprizing Fate. The King, who scarce cou'd think the Story true, Since History no Parallel did shew, Conceal'd Arion, and the Sailors sought, Who were into his awful Presence brought, And ask'd, If in the Coast from whence they came, They were acquainted with Arion's Fame? They answer'd. He in Italy was well, And did the greatest Masters there excell; With vast Respect and Honour was caress'd, And an Estate, he purchas'd there, possess'd. This false Account conceal'd Arion heard, And, to confront their Impudence, appear'd: Convicted thus, each hid his guilty Face, Tho' harden'd far beyond their Native Brass. The MORAL. ‘Heav'n did to Man, its Noblest Work, impart ‘A yearning Pity, and a tender Heart: ‘This gen'rous Quality, in Tears express'd, ‘Is what adorns, and recommends him best. ‘But Men, with their Creator's Image grac'd, ‘By Cruelty, the Sacred Stamp defac'd: ‘Now Nature's peaceful Laws they disobey, ‘And spoil each other worse than Beasts of Prey. ‘While Beasts, by nobler Principles enclin'd, ‘Abstain (tho' urg'd by Hunger) from their Kind; ‘More savage Men no soft Compassion shew, ‘But, as their Foes, insult their Fellows too: ‘They act Barbarities that Brutes disdain, ‘And nothing Human, but the Shape, retain. FABLE LII. The Thief and Mastiff:Or, Honour and Honesty. A gen'rous Mastiff, to whose try'd Regard His Master trusted all his House and Yard, Was tempted by a Thief to prove Unjust, And, for a hearty Meal, betray his Trust. But he, Great Soul! that wou'd on no Pretence Indulge his Belly, at his Fame's Expence; Reply'd, No, Sir, your base Design I hate; You'd stop my Mouth, to open yonder Gate; That you may safely prey on what you see, And empty all the House, by silling me: But I alike your Bribe and you despise, And less my Life, than Reputation prise. The MORAL. ‘No tempting Profit can Great Souls entice ‘To hazard Fame, of nobler Worth and Price. ‘Who Faith, or Honour, truck for an Estate, ‘Will find it purchas'd at too dear a Rate. ‘They Life o'er-value, who, to save it, give ‘The only Good for which they ought to live. ‘Integrity, above Allurements rais'd, ‘Contemns false Honours, to be justly prais'd; ‘With greatest Pleasure do's its Merit boast, ‘When its untainted Virtue costs it most. FABLE LIII. The Eagle and Crow:Or, Fatal Imitation. A soaring Eagle, from her lofty Flight, Swoop'd a young Lamb, to stay her Appetite: Sure of her Prey, she Homeward did repair, And bore her Burden bleating through the Air. An envious Crow, that her own Parts preferr'd, With vain Ambition, Ap'd the Royal Bird: She soar'd aloft, and made a clam'rous Noise, As if she did at sure Success rejoyce: But in the great Effort mistook her Aim, And made her bold Descent upon a Ram; And in his shaggy Fleece engag'd her Claw, Beyond her Pow'r or Cunning to withdraw. The Shepherd, who observ'd her thus embroild, Of Wings and Tail the flutt'ring Captive spoil'd: And having us'd her in this scurvy sort, Threw her abroad, to make his Children Sport. They, who scarce knew her, in that alter'd Case, Ask'd, of what Species of the Birds she was? The humbled Creature, sensible her Pride Had been her Ruin, with a Sigh, reply'd; I thought I was (e're I my self did know) An Eagle, but now find I am a Crow. The MORAL. ‘When Men, whom pow'rful Means capacitate, ‘Attempt Exploits above the common Rate; ‘The Vulgar, not so qualify'd, mistake, ‘If they such Measures their Examples make. ‘What may be practicable, must be known, ‘Not from another's Virtue, but their own: ‘Lest they, who imitate such noble Deeds, ‘Fail, in attempting what their Pow'r exceeds. ‘For justly we their Vanity impeach, ‘Who dare aspire to Heights beyond their Reach: ‘Unable for the lofty Flight, they fall, ‘Pity'd by none, but ridicul'd by all. FABLE LIV. The Fowler and Owzel:Or, The Multitude of Subjects, the Prince's Safety. An expert Fowler did his Nets prepare For some unwary Natives of the Air. An Owzel, that was on his Work intent, Demanded what his Preparations meant? The Man reply'd, I build a Town for you: And, having finish'd his Design, withdrew. The easie Bird, that his Pretence believ'd, Flew to the Bait, and found her self deceiv'd. When she observ'd the false Deluder come To seize his Captive, and pronounce her Doom; She thus to him her dying Speech address'd, And her true Notion of his Cheat express'd: If this be, Sir, the Town you have design'd, You but a few Inhabitants will find. The MORAL. ‘Tyrannick Princes, who delight in Blood, ‘For private Ends, destroy the Publick Good; ‘And sacrifice to their wild Insolence, ‘Their People's Lives, which are their chief Defence. ‘Then, weaken'd by their Arbitrary Sway, ‘To ev'ry Foe they are expos'd a Prey: ‘And their Dispeopl'd Kingdoms make it known, ‘Their Subjects Safety was no less their own. FABLE LV. The Viper and File:Or, No Striving against the Stream. A Viper, seizing on a harden'd File, Gnaw'd the rough Tool, that did her Hopes beguile; And, in Derision, cry'd, Vain Fool, Forbear; Thy Teeth thou may'st, but me thou can'st not wear: I, that on Brass and Steel am daily fed, From thy soft Grinders no Impression dread. The MORAL. ‘Be always cautious whom thou do'st engage, ‘Lest thou repent thy insuccessful Rage: ‘He who encounters with too potent Foes, ‘Mis-spends his Anger, and himself undoes. FABLE LVI. The Linnet and Boy:Or, Every Man to his Mind. A Linnet, cocker'd by too fond a Boy, (Her Master's only Care, and only Joy) With all his kind Indulgence not content, Made an Escape, and to her Fellows went. He call'd, and ask'd her why from him she fled, By whom she was so highly lov'd, and fed? She answer'd, I wou'd Liberty retrieve, And at my own, not your Discretion, live. The MORAL. ‘Men, to their Native Liberty enclin'd, ‘Disrelish Joys to which they are confin'd: ‘But Freedom do's the meanest Life advance, ‘Its Trouble lessen, and its Bliss enhance: ‘And he, whose Will no Master can dispute, ‘While Kings are Slaves, is truly Absolute. FABLE LVII. The Curate and Sick Man:Or, Godliness for Gain. An Aged Man, and very Ignorant, Labour'd at once with Sickness and with Want: The Wretch, too much addicted to complain, And fretting at his Poverty and Pain; To Patience, by the Curate, was advis'd, Because, whom Heav'n lov'd best, it most chastis'd. Then 'tis not strange, said he, its Friends are few; They daily must decrease, if that be true. The MORAL. ‘Gainful Religion, Men the best conclude; ‘Still Loaves and Fishes draw the Multitude: ‘And they whose Godliness is only Gain, ‘Will, as that fails, their forward Zeal refrain: ‘Rarely their Love to that high Pitch is brought, ‘To serve the Lord, like holy Job, for nought. ‘Few, while his Hand do's heavy on them lie, ‘Beneath their Stripes, keep their Integrity. FABLE LVIII. The Cocks and Partridge:Or, Patience from Experience. A nobleman, who did in Cocks delight, And pleas'd himself to see the Bullies fight; Bought a young Partridge, which he meant to breed, And turn'd the Bird among his Cocks to feed: They did the new-come Guest unkindly treat, Peck'd at him still, and forc'd him from his Meat. He guess'd, his being of a diff'rent Kind, Was the true Cause he did this Hardship find; And griev'd, to think such Usage shou'd be shown To him, that was a Stranger, and alone: But soon did his immod'rate Grief asswage, When he consider'd their intestine Rage; How eagerly they with each other fought, And more than his, their mutual Ruin sought. This made him bear what did before displease; With this Remark he did his Trouble ease: Since they among themselves so ill agree, It is not strange they All shou'd harass Me. The MORAL. ‘He that reads Men, and grows, by Converse, wise, ‘In Fortune's Traverses finds no Surprize: ‘He knows how Mankind's Pulse is wont to beat, ‘And with what Usage they each other treat: ‘Hence Patience arms him to support each Change, ‘And think no Turns or Alterations strange: ‘Without Regret he bears uncertain State, ‘In which he only shares the Common Fate. FABLE LIX. The Fox and Carv'd Head:Or, Fair and Foolish. A Fox, that search'd a Carver's Shop for Food, Found a Man's Head cut to the Life, in Wood: He turn'd, admir'd, and prais'd the Counterfeit, But thought the Block had neither Sense nor Wit: Fine thing, said he, thy Maker play'd his Part, And in thy Sculpture has express'd much Art; But still thou art a stupid Log, I see, And senseless as the Tools that fashion'd thee: How has the Artist lost his curious Pains, Who, with thy Beauty, did not give thee Brains? The MORAL. ‘When Lovely Features want an Equal Mind, ‘And Beauty is not with Discretion join'd; ‘The Body seems an undigested Mass, ‘The Head is Wooden, tho' well Turn'd the Face: ‘But a bright Soul, which meaner Cov'rings shroud, ‘Will gild its Out-side, as the Sun a Cloud. FABLE LX. The Kid and Wolf:Or, Childrens Safety in Obedience. A Goat, by Hunger call'd Abroad to feed, Lock'd carefully at Home her tender Kid; And charg'd the Suckling, as he wish'd to live, He shou'd to none, but her, Admittance give. A Wolf, that near in secret Covert lay, Heard the Command, and saw the Dam away; Then knock'd, and counterfeiting her shrill Tone, Cry'd, in false Accents, Let me in, my Son. The Kid, who, through the Door, perceiv'd the Cheat, Reply'd, I cannot give you Entrance yet: For, tho' methinks my Mother's Voice I hear, By what I see, you are a Wolf, I fear. The MORAL. ‘Children, observe your Parents sound Advice, ‘Your Safety in your just Obedience lies: ‘They know the Ills to which you open lie, ‘And, to prevent them, all their Care apply: ‘But if their wise Commands you disobey, ‘You make them wretched, and your selves a Prey. FABLE LXI. The Bitch and Sow:Or, Reproach improv'd. An angry Sow and snarling Bitch fell out, And had a very eager Scolding-bout. The Sow by Venus swore, that for a Groat She'd dash the Bitch's Grinders down her Throat. What, said the Bitch, do you by Venus swear, You nasty Trull? Are you to her so dear? No Hussy; at her Rites she'll not allow One that e'er tasted such a Beast as you. Fool, says the Sow, this shews her greater Love, She thus do's all, that injure me, reprove: To see me slaughter'd, gives her so much Grief, That she, to save her Tears, preserves my Life: But you, proud Minks, not so well taught as fed, Stink while alive, and feed the Crows, when dead. The MORAL. ‘When loaded with reproachful Taunts, the Wise ‘Improve their Credit, from the Obloquies: ‘They, what their Foes, to their Disgrace, object, ‘Convert to Means of heightning their Respect. FABLE LXII. The Miser robb'd:Or, Hid Treasure useless. A greedy Wretch his Patrimony sold, And turn'd his fruitful Land to barren Gold; And, lest the Sum, by using, shou'd decay, Committed Earth to Earth, and Clay to Clay. His Wealth thus bury'd in a secret Hole, And, with his Bags, his very Heart and Soul; To their dear Tomb he daily Visits made, And at that Shrine his whole Devotion paid. A Needy Fellow, that observ'd his Walk, And guess'd the Ghost did near some Treasure stalk, Came to the Place; and, when he try'd the Ground, The rich Depositum, rejoycing, found: He bless'd his Fortune, and the Booty bore (To spend it safely) to a foreign Shore. The Owner soon return'd to watch his Coin, But found another Hand had digg'd the Mine: Sad Signs inform'd him his Delight was gone, His Yellow-hammers from the Nest were flown. Sunk by this Loss into profound Despair, He beat and tore his guiltless Breast and Hair: His raging Sorrow, in no Bounds restrain'd, Gave a convincing Proof it was not feign'd. A Friend, that saw him in this Transport rave, Bid him his Grief for better Purpose save; And said, You vainly your lost Hoard deplore, Which, since you kept it hid, was yours no more: Bury a Stone where your dear Idol lay, And there, as formerly, your Visits pay; Imagination will Effects produce Of equal Value, since of equal Use. The MORAL. ‘How vainly Men, with restless Industry, ‘Acquire the Wealth they to themselves deny? ‘While what is theirs, they, by not using, want, ‘The Property is insignificant. ‘Riches are lost to them who live in Need; ‘Use, not Possession, makes us Rich indeed. FABLE LXIII. The Lion and Man:Or, Every Tongue its own Trumpet. A Man and Lion held a long Dispute, Which Kind excell'd, the Human, or the Brute. The Man, all further Contests to prevent, Shew'd his Antagonist a Monument, On which the artful Graver's Hand express'd A Man insulting o'er the Princely Beast. The Lion argu'd, That was not enough, For Parties shou'd not be allow'd for Proof. Men, who a Pride in their own Praises take, Might Monuments, to serve their Int'rest, make: But if among the Lions had been known Artists as dext'rous to ingrave in Stone, He wou'd with more, and truer Sculptures, meet, Where Men were prostrate laid at Lions Feet. The MORAL. ‘Men, who their own Atchievements love to boast, ‘To gain their Point, alledge what serves it most: ‘Careless what Truth or Reason may suggest, ‘They chuse what colours their Pretensions best. FABLE LXIV. The Funeral:Or, Mercenary Mourners. A wealthy Man, with two fair Daughters bless'd, By Death, of half his Stock was dispossess'd; And (as if real Woe cou'd find Relief In the false Sounds of Artificial Grief) Did a vast Tribe of Hackney-Mourners call, With their strain'd Notes, to grace the Funeral: Which they perform'd with such dissembl'd Shew, That their feign'd Sorrow soon outvy'd the true. When the surviving Sister heard their Cries, That to a Pitch she cou'd not reach, did rise; She said, Alas! Why are not we as learn'd, To vent our Passion, who are more concern'd? Her Mother answer'd, They may best complain, Whose mercenary Plaints are hir'd for Gain: For diff'rent Reasons we our Tears employ; Ours spring from Trouble, theirs proceed from Joy: Those Counterfeits, by Noise, promote their Trade; For that are better lik'd, and better paid: We need no Witness to attest our Moan; True Mourners grieve in silence, and alone. The MORAL. ‘So some false-Friends, who, for base Lucre's sake, ‘A Profit of their Neighbour's Losses make; ‘With counterfeited Grief his Fate lament, ‘Tho', in his Suff'rings, they find true Content; ‘Hug the Mishaps by which their Fortunes thrive, ‘And best are pleas'd, when most they seem to grieve. FABLE LXV. The Goose:Or, Haste makes Waste. A Goose, well worth her Meat, Lay'd ev'ry Day A Golden Egg, that did her Quarters pay. Her Dame, that thought the Fowl with Gold was lin'd, And hop'd she shou'd, within, the Indies find; Impatient to be Rich, her Death contriv'd, And kill'd the Creature by whose Fruit she liv'd. But when she ript her up, with eager haste, A wretched Bilk did all her Projects blast; She found no Treasure in the Carkass lie, But some Materials for a Giblet Pie: Yet on the right Horse she wou'd lay the Saddle, And own'd, 'twas her own fault her Eggs were Addle. The MORAL. ‘Impatient Fools, not with slow Gains content, ‘By hasty Methods wou'd Heaven's Pace prevent; ‘But, while with luckless Speed they run too fast, ‘Stumble, and miss what did excite their Haste. ‘Such Disappointments justly prove their Fate, ‘Who will not Providence's Leisure wait. FABLE LXVI. The Bull and Mouse:Or, Small Enemies not contemptible. A wanton Bull, that through the Fields did stray, Trod on a Mouse that happen'd in his Way: The little Creature, with Resentment fir'd, Bit him, and quickly to her Hole retir'd. With brandish'd Horns he sought the threatned Foe, But cou'd not find what had disturb'd him so: While she in Safety did his Rage deride, And thus provok'd the Anger she defy'd; Tho' you are strong, and of a bulky Size, Do not, Great Sir, mean Enemies despise; Since a small Mouse, protected by her Cave, Can hurt you, and, unharm'd, your Fury brave. The MORAL. ‘Let not thy Strength make thee Injurious grow, ‘'Tis dang'rous to provoke the meanest Foe: ‘They most may vex thee, whom thou most do'st slight, ‘And scorn thy Pow'r, while they exert their Spight. FABLE LXVII. The Dog:Or, Sweet Meat must have Sour Sauce. A gen'rous Soul, whose Bottle and his Friend Made Life sit well, and did its Cares unbend, Invited, to a Dish or two of Meat, An old Acquaintance, worthy of the Treat. His Spaniel, who the Proverb oft' had prov'd, That, As the Master, so the Dog, is lov'd; An equal Strain of Courtesy express'd, And pray'd his Neighbour-Dog to be his Guest. The ready Curr, that did no Pressing need, To please his Friend, but more himself agreed; And when his Master thought it Time to go, He stretch'd himself, and yawn'd, and travel'd too. He came, was introduc'd by his Comrade, And to the Kitchin his Devotion paid. He saw there was a noble Bill of Fare, And, when his Dishes he had chose with Care, He lick'd his Lips, and wagg'd his Tail, for Joy, To think how well he shou'd his Teeth employ: At last, discover'd by the hasty Cook, Who wou'd not there such loose Companions brook, He found Dame Fortune's Smiles a meer Caprice, His Hopes were disappointed in a trice: He got a Knock or two, without a Bit, And, e're he tasted Roast-Meat, felt the Spit; Then by the Tail was three times hurl'd about, And, like a Dog that Pudding stole, thrown out. Asham'd, and troubl'd that his Stars so lour'd, He yaul'd, betook him to his Heels, and scour'd; But told his Fellow-Currs, (who soon repair'd To know how well their Brother-Scrambler far'd) That he had Eat and Drunk to such Excess, 'Twas past his Skill to tell, or theirs to guess. The MORAL. ‘When Sensu'lists do False-Delights pursue, ‘They lose the nobler Blessings of the True: ‘When on their Lusts their Time and Care they spend, ‘Their fading Joys in lasting Torments end. ‘The Libertines indulge themselves in vain, ‘To buy short Pleasures with eternal Pain. FABLE LXVIII. The Spider and Gout:Or, Delicacy breeds Distempers. A busie Spider, that had long kept Home, And labour'd tightly at her Native Loom; The Web compleated, wou'd relax her Care, And walk'd to view the Fields, and take the Air. To her the Gout, originally Lame, And by a Crutch supported, limping came. Thus join'd, in pleasing Talk they pass'd the Day, And, while intent on that, mistook their Way; 'Till Night approaching, made them recollect, And to next Town in view their Course direct; Resolv'd, that each shou'd for himself provide, As each expected to be best supply'd. The Spider made a Rich Man's House her Inn, And there, tho' tir'd, did a new Task begin; But e're she cou'd compleat her curious Loom, She found the Work demolish'd by a Broom: The cleanly Maids, (to Strangers often rude) From Hole to Hole th' unwelcom Guest pursu'd; And, like Penelope revers'd, their Spight Undid by Day, what she had wrought by Night. Finding no Safety cou'd be there enjoy'd, Where Maids and Besoms were so much employ'd, She left her Lodging, with Regret, to see That all liv'd there in Peace, and Ease, but she. Mean-while her Fellow-Traveller, the Gout, From Door to Door had halted long about, And begg'd Admittance; but, alas! in vain, None wou'd the weary Cripple entertain: 'Till a poor Wretch, more tenderly enclin'd, Part of his Cabin, and his Bed, resign'd: But there the dainty Inmate sadly far'd, His Food was coarse, his Lodging very hard; A dry, brown, mouldy Crust was all his Meat, Which Hunger scarce cou'd tempt a Mouse to eat; His Drink was Puddle, from a dirty Bowl, Which, what shou'd cleanse it, rather help'd to foul: The hard, cold Ground, with Chaff, and thinly spread, Was all the poor Provision for his Bed; Where, vex'd with prickly Awns, and hungry Fleas, Toil was his Rest, and Torment all his Ease: This made his early Haste the Sun prevent, And, when his Legs were dress'd, Abroad he went: Where, as he hopt along the rugged Street, He, and his worthy Friend, Arachne, meet. Good-morrow's giv'n; they to a Porch retir'd, And of each other's good Success enquir'd. Now both, with Grief, alternately relate The mournful Stories of their dismal Fate. The Spider, with their Cleanliness, upbraids The Curious Mistress, and her Dainty Maids. The Gout, in sad Return, his Lodging blam'd, And said, his Feet were more than ever Lam'd. From these Accounts, their Thoughts were next employ'd, How they such future Suff'rings might avoid. The Spider, what the Gout dislik'd, approv'd; And He, what most She discommended, lov'd. Since neither cou'd with his first Lot dispense, They therefore chose to change their Residence. All Day they skulk'd, and when retiring Light Left them the fav'ring Shelter of the Night, The Spider travel'd to the Beggar's Crate, The Gout went boldly to the Rich-Man's Gate; Which soon the ready Porter did unlock, Alarm'd by his Authoritative Knock. His Quality made known, the Lordly Guest Was with the height of Compliment caress'd: The Master treated him with vast Expence, As if he was to entertain a Prince: A costly Bath for his swoln Feet was made, And Velvet Cushions, to support them, laid. The hurry'd Servants, with officious Haste, Strove who shou'd most with his Commands be grac'd: All that nice Palates reckon dainty Chear, From Parts remote was sought, and purchas'd dear: The richest Grapes contributed their Wine To whet his Stomach, and his Blood refine: Swan's softest Down was crouded in his Bed, And light rich Indian Quilts were on it spread: Her utmost Skill the busie Lady try'd, And to his Feet warm Poultices apply'd: She fear'd to hurt him by too rude a Touch, And thought her own soft Hand transgress'd too much: Her Cook'ry too as nicely she display'd, Soops, Caudles, Creams, Tisanes, and Jelleys made: All Things were thought on that cou'd give him Ease, His Wants supply, or wanton Fancy please. While he was pamper'd thus, his happy Friend Did all her Time in equal Pleasure spend; Within the Poor-Man's Hut she liv'd at rest, No curious Dames did there her Work molest: In ev'ry Corner her fine Nets she spread, And on intangl'd Flyes of all sorts fed; She wrought her circling Cobweb free from Care, And fear'd no Breaches but from ruffling Air: Thus she Sole Empress of the Cottage reign'd, And all Insults of Whisks and Brooms disdain'd. The Friends thus pleas'd, an Interview contriv'd, To tell each other in whar Bliss they liv'd: When met, each prais'd what to his Thought seem'd best; The Gout, his Fare, Attendance, Ease, and Rest. The Spider, who enjoy'd what she desir'd, Her Safety, and her Liberty, admir'd. Each did unspeakable Enjoyments find, And to pursue his pleasing Course design'd; To take their Quarters, as they stroll'd about, In Crates the Spider, and in Courts the Gout. The MORAL. ‘Distempers oft'nest on the Wealthy seize, ‘First bred by Softness, then encreas'd by Ease: ‘Where Action least is us'd, they most abound, ‘Like Thistles in uncultivated Ground. ‘But, as the frequent Tillage of a Soil ‘Do's banish Weeds, and all rank Products spoil; ‘So he, whose Fortune craves laborious Pains, ‘Prevents Diseases, and long Health maintains. ‘Nor are high Titles, or abundant Wealth, ‘To Liberty more friendly than to Health: ‘The Great, restrain'd from Life's more easie Rate, ‘Are Ceremonious Slaves, confin'd to State; ‘While Happy Men, in meaner Stations bless'd, ‘Live by no Rules but what are truly best: ‘Govern'd by Nature's Law, and Reason's Sway, ‘(Which 'tis the noblest Freedom to obey) ‘The vain Impertinencies they avoid, ‘With which all Pomp is clogg'd, and Grandeur cloy'd.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">BOOK III. FABLE I. The Old Wife, and the Devil.False Excuses, aggravate a Crime. Men, by their Folly, brought to Grief or Shame, Still on the guiltless Devil lay the Blame; And that they may their faulty selves excuse, No conscience make how they Old-Nick abuse. This he observ'd, and (vex'd to be bely'd) All proper Means for his Purgation try'd: And soon a fair Occasion did present, That justify'd him to his Heart's Content. As he, one Morn, an early Ramble took, He saw a Plum-tree, hanging o'er a Brook, Laden with Fruit, that seem'd delicious Meat, And might have tempted Eve again to eat. Close at the Foot an Aged Beldam stood, Whose toothless Gums requir'd such easie Food; And, eager as a Longing Wife to taste, She clim'd the Tree with an incautious Haste. The knowing Spirit, who foresaw her Fall, To clear himself, did Evidences call: Observe the Hoidon how she climbs, said he, Not instigated to the Fact by me; Yet when she falls, (for soon she will be down, And break her Bones, or in the Water drown) The Blame will wholly at my Door be laid; None will her Folly, all my Guilt, upbraid. This said, she fell, and broke her Collar-bone, And rais'd the Neighbours with her hideous Moan: Who thus alarm'd, and flocking to her Aid, Ask'd, why she had that idle Gambol play'd. Alas! said she, 'twas not my Fault at all, 'Twas the foul Fiend that made me climb, and fall. Satan, (that, undiscern'd, stood by, and heard Himself accus'd) assoon as nam'd, appear'd; And cry'd, 'Tis false, I did not you deceive, 'Twas the old Liqu'rice Lust of Grandam Eve: Here are my Proofs; for, tho' bely'd by you, These honest Men will give the Dev'l his Due. The MORAL. ‘Men, who premeditated Sins commit, ‘With false Excuses wou'd themselves acquit: ‘But conscious Heav'n, that knows the trifling Sham, ‘Without Repentance, will the Actors Damn. ‘Thus our First Parents, with a Fig-leaf Dress, ‘Endeavour'd to conceal their Nakedness: ‘Deluded Adam, of his Crime asham'd, ‘Accus'd the Woman; she the Serpent blam'd: ‘Tho' she, when once enveigl'd to consent, ‘Did his Attempts upon the Man prevent. ‘Nor did the vain Pretence their Guilt excuse, ‘They lost the Trust their Folly did abuse. ‘Prevaricating Sinners miss their Drift, ‘And double the Offence they mean to shift. FABLE II. The Wooden-God.Foul Means must do what Fair Means can't. A man of good Devotion, ill address'd, A Wooden-Idol for his God caress'd; Ador'd the Senseless Stock, and daily Pray'd The Deaf to Hear, the Helpless to give Aid: But still, the more he Supplications made, The more his whole Affairs went retrograde. Incens'd, he shou'd in vain so often call, He dash'd the sacred Block against a Wall; There broke his stupid Logger-head, and found A shining Treasure issue from the Wound: Which gath'ring up, Perverse and False, he cry'd, That, while I honour'd you, your Help deny'd! But since, as you deserv'd, you fell, my Rage, Hath made my future Days a Golden Age. The MORAL. ‘Untoward Wretches, like this stubborn Wood, ‘Are never, but by strong Compulsion, good: ‘When soothing Words, and soft Entreaties, fail; ‘Harsh Language, and rough Usage, must prevail: ‘Their resty Souls thus to Compliance bring; ‘Like Birds, that can, and will not, make them sing. FABLE III. The Petitioners.Envy, its own Tormenter. Two Men, unlike in Mind, and Body too, With vile Intentions, at Jove's Altar sue: One, of large Bulk, whose more extended Mind (Within no reasonable Bounds confin'd) Did on the sordid Wretch, for Gain, prevail To set his mercenary Life to Sale. The other, Meagre-look'd, and Narrow-soul'd, Who did all Pleasure with Regret behold; And with the gnawing Pain uneasie grown, Malign'd his Neighbour's Blessings, and his own. Jove (to avoid their execrable Pray'r) Referr'd the Vot'ries to Apollo's Care: Who let them know, That what they each did want, He wou'd, with this Proviso, freely grant; That whatsoever Boon the one did crave, The other shou'd in double Measure have. The greedy Worldling long demurr'd, to find Demands conform'd to his insatiate Mind; At last, a most prodigious Sum did name, Obtain'd it, and his Fellow twice the same. But he, whose peevish, fretful Soul repin'd, That Heav'n had to his Neighbour been so kind; To do the envy'd Wretch a double Spight, Desir'd one Eye might be depriv'd of Sight. The God (engag'd, what he desir'd, to do) Put out his one Eye, and his Fellows two: And he with Joy perceiv'd its Opticks gone, Since he with t'other saw his Mate had none. The MORAL. ‘The avaricious Wretch, who Wealth admires, ‘And grasps the Globe, in his immense Desires; ‘Tempted by Love of Gain, becomes unjust, ‘Do's Men defraud, and Providence distrust. ‘But Envy, grieving at its Neighbour's Joy, ‘Lessens its own, that it may theirs destroy. ‘So the Old Serpent, grated at the Bliss ‘Our happy Parents found in Paradise, ‘To drive them from that Station to a worse, ‘Became a Sharer in the Fatal Curse. FABLE IV. The Priest and his Dog.Money makes the Mare to go. A priest, possess'd of a fat Benefice, And Wealthier (as oft' it proves) than Wise; By Death was, of a fav'rite Dog, depriv'd, That was his whole Diversion while he liv'd; And, to express his Love to the Deceas'd, In Consecrated Ground interr'd the Beast. His Bishop (fond of Gain) was soon inform'd Of the Offence, and out of measure storm'd: (Not with Concern for the Church-yard's Abuse, But of that Crime to make as ill an Use;) And, more to purge his Pocket than his Soul, Enjoin'd him Penance for a Sin so foul. The Priest, who guess'd what his good Lordship meant, And cast about how he might Shame prevent, Took in his Purse a tempting Sum of Gold, And, back'd with that, his humble Story told: My Fault, My Lord, seems very great, I own; But not without prevailing Reason done: Had but your Lordship known my Ranger's Parts, His pretty and insinuating Arts, You wou'd suspend your Censure on his score, And rather wonder I have done no more: Nor think his Fun'ral-Rites shou'd be deny'd, Whose Zeal enrich'd the Corban when he dy'd; For while he liv'd he had some Treasure stor'd, And at his Death distributed the Hoard: To you, My Lord, for many Favours past, Which he, poor Curr, acknowledg'd to the last, The grateful Creature, with his dying Breath, Did, in Return, this Legacy bequeath. This spoke, with Rev'rence to his Lordship made, He to his ready Hand the Purse convey'd. The greedy Prelate, ravish'd with the Gold, Much the Dog's Thrift, but more his Love, extoll'd; And own'd, That he who that Oblation sent, Deserv'd within the Church a Monument. The MORAL. ‘So little Care of Sacred Things they take, ‘Who only serve the Lord for Mammon's sake: ‘When Lucre draws them in to watch the Fold, ‘The Flock is purchas'd, and the Fleece is sold. ‘They make, by their detested Simonies, ‘The House of God, a House of Merchandize: ‘For impious Ends exert their sacred Pow'r, ‘And, what they were advanc'd to feed, devour. ‘Thus Eli's Sons made Sacrifice abhorr'd; ‘And Judas, tempted thus, deny'd his Lord: ‘In whose foul Steps too many since have trod, ‘Made Av'rice their Religion, Gold their God. FABLE V. The Two Pots.The Weakest goes to the Wall. Two Pots, of diff'rent Size and Matter made, Were swiftly down a rolling Stream convey'd: The larger Vessel, form'd of solid Brass, Did boldly o'er the rapid Water pass: While that, whose Substance was but brittle Clay, Wou'd, for his Safety, give the Stronger Way. Him the Brass-Pot invited to draw near, And said, His Frailty need not cause his Fear; For he, with just Precaution, wou'd prevent The Danger of their justling as they went. The Earthen-Pot, that knew his weaker Frame, Excus'd himself, that he no nearer came; And said, My Friend, if the impetuous Tide Shou'd dash my Clay against your Brazen Side; By the hard Fate of that unequal Stroke, While you are whole, I shall be surely broke. The MORAL. ‘Men safest still in Equal Friendship live, ‘Where they can do no Harm, and none receive: ‘The Strong, by Pow'r, led to insult the Weak, ‘With ev'ry Touch, the brittle Vessels break; ‘While they, Abus'd and Injur'd by the Strong, ‘Must, without Remedy, sustain the Wrong: ‘A just Resentment vainly they express, ‘And perish, by attempting a Redress: ‘For, like weak Ships, that bulge against a Rock, ‘They dash themselves to Pieces in the Shock. FABLE VI. The Bald Knight.Preventive Raillery. Long since, e're Vice was Epidemick grown, And Chaste Mankind grew Bald with Age alone; When Wigs were us'd, not for the modern End, To hide Mens Failings, but their Heads defend: A Knight, whose Crown devouring Time, and Care, Had spoil'd of all its ornamental Hair; With borrow'd Locks the pressing Want supply'd, And gain'd, from Art, what Nature had deny'd. But as he walk'd the Street, a ruffling Wind, Rude to his Person, to his Age unkind; The loose False-Head into the Gutter blew, And left his naked Pate expos'd to View. The Knight, too Wise to be disturb'd, express'd But light Concern, and pass'd it with a Jest: Well may another's Hair, said he, be gone, Since I cou'd find no means to keep my own. The MORAL. ‘Wise-Men, expos'd by any Accident, ‘The Publick Censure, by their Own, prevent: ‘For Malice, that in others Grief is pleas'd, ‘Is tickl'd most, when most they seem diseas'd: ‘But he that at his own Disasters smiles, ‘Forestalls the Market, and the Mob beguiles. ‘So a Gall'd-Horse, that kicks and flings about, ‘Makes special Pastime for the fleering Rout; ‘But when he stands, and quietly is dress'd, ‘Sends the Fools blank away, and bilks the Jest. FABLE VII. Mercury and the Carpenter.Honesty the best Policy. As on a Chrystal River's shady Side, By Mercury belov'd and dignify'd, A busie Carpenter was hewing Wood, His trusty Hatchet dropt into the Flood. The Wretch, who for his Bread cou'd work no more, Griev'd at his Loss, sate weeping on the Shore: To him the God, with Pity mov'd, appears, And kindly asks the Reason of his Tears. The Man had scarce his Cause of Sorrow told, When Maia's Son produc'd an Ax of Gold, Demanding, If for Loss of That he cry'd? But he, Just Soul! the Property deny'd. The God did next a Silver Ax present, And still the Man refus'd the Compliment: But when his own Steel-Hatchet came in view, That, at first sight, the joyful Owner knew; And (better pleas'd with that, than both the rest) Cry'd, This is mine, Sir; This will fit me best. The God admir'd such Honesty to see, And, to reward it, gave him all the Three. The happy Man cou'd not his Joy conceal, But told his Fellows the surprizing Tale: One of the Gang, resolv'd his Luck to try, (Tho' not with such intended Honesty) In the same Place let his old Hatchet fall, And, with feign'd Sorrow, on the God did call. The ready Pow'r appear'd as soon as sought, And in his Hand a Golden-Hatchet brought. Soon the Impostor, tempted with the Sight, Own'd the rich Tool, and claim'd it as his Right. The angry God, who knew his false Pretence, And hated such deceitful Impudence; Nor gave him that, nor did his own restore, But left him, for his Falshood, justly Poor. The MORAL. ‘Thus Heav'n, that do's the Good and Just relieve, ‘Frustrates their Hopes, who by Deceit wou'd thrive: ‘God, in strict Justice, lets such Fools alone, ‘Who slight His Measures, and pursue their own: ‘Nor needs he seek to make their Judgment worse, ‘To want his Blessing, is sufficient Curse: ‘But where he finds a just and honest Mind, ‘That no Acquests by gainful Fraud design'd; ‘The more its Virtue ill-got Wealth denies, ‘The more his lib'ral Hand its Want supplies. FABLE VIII. The Horse-Buyer.Knaves well Met. A Bully, for a Horse in mighty Strait, Resolv'd to purchase one at any Rate: Away the Spark to Smithfield-Market packs, Where soon the Jockies ask him what he lacks: One brought a well-turn'd Nag, that pleas'd his Eyes, And Twenty Guinea's was the Selling Price: He found the Beast too dear by Half a Score, Yet cast to get him, and to pay no more: Without much Chaff'ring therefore he agreed To give the Sum demanded for the Steed; Then paid half Rhino, and the Seller press'd To let him be his Debtor for the rest. The Jocky, pleas'd his Jade so well was sold. Consented, but soon Dunn'd him for the Gold. Friend, said the Chapman, you are fully Paid, If you consider well the Bargain made; To be your Debtor, Sir, I did agree, And so (to keep my Word) I mean to be. The MORAL. ‘The sly Impostor thus himself defeats, ‘And, while intent on Cheating, meets with Cheats: ‘For they who purchase Goods too dear, on Trust, ‘Design, or are constrain'd, to prove Unjust. FABLE IX. The Farmer and River.Smooth Water runs deep. An honest Farmer, who to Market went, To sell his Corn, and pay his Landlord's Rent; Was intercepted in his usual Road, By the deep Current of a new-ris'n Flood: Impatient of Delay, the Stream he try'd, Where the smooth Water with least Noise did glide; But finding there 'twas deeper than he thought, A shallower and safer Passage sought; And where the rougher Torrent most did roar, Found a stanch Ford, and gain'd the farther Shore: Then on his Danger this Reflection made; How soon are Mortals by false Shews betray'd! I in the silent Stream had sure been lost, But found least Mischief where it threatned most. The MORAL. ‘Thus noisie Men their harmless Fury spend, ‘And threaten greater Ills than they intend: ‘While silent Villains their Intrigues refine, ‘And calmly hide the Mischefs they design. ‘Anger, when vented, is a transient Blast; ‘But, when suppress'd, like cover'd Fire do's last: ‘One Menaces, and means no further Ill; ‘The other's Mute, but plotting Mischief still. FABLE X. The Stag and Oxen.Reason betray'd by Fear. A Stag, that from pursuing Huntsmen fled, Took to a Stall where lab'ring Oxen fed; And begg'd their Favour to conceal him there, To shun the Danger, and allay his Fear. They told him, That was no secure Retreat, For soon the Servant wou'd be there with Meat. But he reply'd, He there might safely lie, Wou'd they but kindly promise Secrecy. The Servant came, and fill'd the empty Rack, And, without more Enquiry, soon went back. The Stag, o'erjoy'd, rais'd his dejected Head, And thought he had no Danger else to dread; 'Till a grave Ox, superiour to the rest In Age and Counsel, thus his Joy suppress'd: Boast not too soon, tho' you escap'd with Ease This careless Mole, who nothing heeds, nor sees; Trust me, you will, by dear Experience, find A sharper-sighted Argus yet behind. He spoke; the Master instantly appear'd, Who the Neglects of Servants knew, and fear'd; About the Stall he casts his prying Eyes, The Store, and Goodness of the Fodder, tryes: His searching Hands meet there a branching Horn, Diff'rent from those by his Domesticks worn; By which, discov'ring his absconded Guest, He call'd his Servants, seiz'd, and kill'd the Beast. The MORAL. ‘In Dangers, Safety can be rarely found; ‘For Fortune's Hand that gives, repeats, the Wound: ‘And Men distress'd, in Thought's wild Mazes lost, ‘Want Help and Counsel, when they need it most: ‘Then deep Impressions which their Fear has made, ‘Drive them for Shelter where they are betray'd. FABLE XI. The Fox and Goat.Too late to Repent. By equal Thirst, led to pursue one End, A Fox and Goat into a Well descend; Nor was the Means for their Return their Care, 'Till they had guzzl'd all their Guts cou'd bear: But then the pensive Goat, with knotted Brow, Shew'd he wou'd fain be gone, but knew not how. Reynard, who saw his rev'rend Friend dismay'd, Rais'd his sunk Spirits, with this promis'd Aid: Chear up, my Heart, I have contriv'd a Way, That we no longer in this Pond shall stay; Erect your self, while I your Horns bestride, Make my Escape, and then for your's provide. The Goat obey'd, and soon the subtle Fox Leaps out, and his forlorn Deliv'rer mocks. This scurvy Usage made the Goat complain, And tax his Breach of Faith, but all in vain; Reynard no Pity for his Grief express'd, But rally'd him with this Sarcastick Jest: Were but your Prudence equal to your Beard, You had your Course by wiser Methods steer'd; Your Gravity wou'd first the Means have known How to get up, before you ventur'd down. The MORAL. ‘Wise Men, on any Enterprize intent, ‘Still bear a due Regard to the Event: ‘For where Success do's not the Work attend, ‘There vain Efforts in Shame and Sorrow end. ‘Thus Fools, by rash Endeavours, urge their Fate, ‘And, what they act too soon, repent too late. FABLE XII. The Sick Ass.The Mock-Mourners. An Ass fell Sick, and the Report grew rife, That he, poor Creature, was past Hopes of Life: The Dogs and Wolves, with forward Zeal, pretend To bid Adieu to their Departing Friend: But finding, when they went, the Door was barr'd, They knock'd, and ask'd how their good Neighbour far'd. To whom his Son, through a small Chink, reply'd, Much better, Sirs, than you wou'd wish he did. The MORAL. ‘Thus many, with dissembl'd Tears and Breath, ‘Seem to lament their Friends approaching Death; ‘Tho' from another Cause they truly grieve, ‘Not that they are to Die, but that they Live. ‘The Son believes the Father does him Wrong, ‘And keeps th' Estate, he fain wou'd have, too long: ‘Or if the Parent do's his Succour need; ‘From the Incumbrance wishes to be free'd. ‘The Wife supposes, were her Husband dead, ‘She might be happy in another's Bed. ‘The Husband, whom his try'd Enjoyments cloy, ‘In a new Wife expects improving Joy. ‘Thus, for some Object hated, or desir'd, ‘We of our Friends, or they of us, are tir'd. FABLE XIII. The Crabs.Look at Home. An Ebbing Tide had left the naked Strand, And two large Crabs that crawl'd along the Sand. The tender Mother, and her hopeful Child, Thus by their Native Element beguil'd, Labour'd, the refluous Water to regain, But their slow Pace made their Endeavour vain. While long they rambl'd on the Ouzy Shore, And the young Spark, as nimblest, got before; The Dam observ'd her Son mov'd retrograde: And, tho' her self as ill a Figure made, Condemn'd the Youngster for his aukward Gate, And bid him, angrily, for shame, go straight. The Son reply'd, Pray, Madam, lead the Way, And I will follow whom I must obey. The MORAL. ‘Men with their Neighbours Failings oft' make bold, ‘But scarce their own, tho' greater, will behold: ‘They look abroad, with a too curious Eye, ‘But no domestick Turpitudes espy. ‘Let all who are thus critically Nice, ‘Be first assur'd themselves are free from Vice; ‘Lest, while they others Faults too freely blame, ‘As sharp Returns expose their own with Shame. ‘In those, who with their guilty Selves dispense, ‘And Others tax, 'tis shameless Impudence. ‘He only, that has clean'd his House before, ‘Shou'd blame the Dung-hill at his Neighbour's Door. FABLE XIV. The Old Man and Death.Life is Sweet. A poor Old Wretch, who, to be cloath'd and fed, By daily Labour earn'd his daily Bread; Besides the Burthen of decrepit Age, In bearing Loads of Faggots did engage: But with the Toil fatigu'd, begg'd Death's Relief, To end at once his Being, and his Grief. The ghastly Spectre soon appear'd, to do The grateful Service he was courted to; But such a dreadful Visage did betray, As frighted all Desires of him away. The trembling Caitiff, at this Sight dismay'd, And, ev'n when tir'd of Life, of Death afraid, Did, to excuse his hasty Wish, contrive, (For he wou'd longer, tho' in Mis'ry live) In hope to shun the formidable Stroke, He thus the Executioner bespoke: Sir, I perceive, since your kind Help I sought, I have not such Occasion as I thought: That you shou'd ease my Burden, was my Drift, But now, to bear it, I can make a shift: While I am able, I my self will serve, And for some other Time your Help reserve. The MORAL. ‘So fond are Men, ev'n of Uneasie Life, ‘They wou'd prolong the wretched Scene of Grief: ‘The Tragick Parts they act, can few engage ‘To quit contentedly the tiresom Stage. ‘If they who spend in Trouble all their Years, ‘And bend beneath a Load of Age, and Cares, ‘Find Life sit heavy, and the Burthen own; ‘Why shou'd they with Reluctance lay it down? ‘Why shou'd they hug what do's their Lives molest, ‘And shun the only Means to give them Rest? FABLE XV. The Ass-Teacher.Wise Procrastination. A hungry Tyrant, whose oppressive Reign Did many ways his Subjects Purses drain; Was of a Wealthy Virtuoso told, (And that was strange) who wallow'd in his Gold: Him he resolv'd to squeeze, among the rest: And, since Sir Gim-crack mighty Feats profess'd, Enjoin'd him (with design to make him Bleed) Soundly to Fine, or teach an Ass to Read. The Spark, who knew Refusal was a Crime, Said, That cou'd only be the Work of Time; But if his Grace wou'd Twenty Years allow, To try Experiments what Art cou'd do; He durst engage, his Pupil, by his Care, Shou'd Read as well as any Clerk at Bar. At this Extravagance his Friends grew sad, And thought the daring Undertaker mad. But he, to put them all in better Heart, Bid them Chear up, and not distrust his Art: For, e're so long a Time cou'd be expir'd, If he shou'd fail to do the Work requir'd, 'Twas probable the Prince, the Ass, or he Might be defunct, and then he shou'd be free: And in the int'rim (let what wou'd ensue) He sav'd his Credit, and his Money too. The MORAL. ‘Delay, tho' Dangerous in other Things, ‘In Difficulties kind Assistance brings: ‘And, when Men cannot shun impending Fate, ‘They wisely shou'd the Stroke procrastinate. ‘Wretches Condemn'd, by gaining a Reprieve, ‘Find Means to get their Pardon pass'd, and live. FABLE XVI. The Carter and Wheel.Ease in Complaint. As Hob his Waggon drove along the Road, A crazy Wheel, o'er-burden'd with its Load, Made heavy Murmurs, and did loudly creak, As if its Trouble wou'd have made it speak. Whereat the wond'ring Carter ask'd his Wain, What made that Wheel, more than the rest, complain. To whom the Sage old Cart made this Return; Because 'tis Ease to the Oppress'd, to Mourn. The MORAL. ‘The Wretch, o'er-burden'd with intestine Grief, ‘In outward Marks of Sorrow finds Relief; ‘The Suff'rings he bewails, he gently bears, ‘And his Concern exhausts it self in Tears. ‘For Grief, like Anger, will be quickly spent, ‘When once the tumid Passion finds a Vent: ‘But stifled Woes, like Wounds that inward bleed, ‘Avoid the Cure of which they stand in need. FABLE XVII. The Beam and Oxen.Vicissitudes of Fortune. A heavy Beam, by lab'ring Oxen drawn, And mark'd, in sev'ral Scantlings, to be sawn; Insensible of his own wretched Case, Blam'd the Beasts Sloth, and bid them mend their Pace. The Beasts reply'd, Did you your Fate foresee, You wou'd, Brisk Sir, be less in Haste than we; Nor with Reproach our weary Pains deride, But rather grieve at those you must abide: We of our Load shall very soon be freed, And, when turn'd loose, shall in rich Pastures feed; But you a sorer Burden shall sustain, Shall, more oppress'd, and pity'd less, complain. At this the Beam, in deep Affliction, roar'd With louder Out-cries than the Groaning-Board; No longer he the Oxens Sloth reprov'd, But thought they too precipitantly mov'd. The MORAL. ‘He who insults his Neighbour's wretched State, ‘Forgets how fast Afflictions circulate: ‘And whom they longest Favour in their Course, ‘Attack at last with more oppressive Force. ‘Hence we shou'd Pity, not Upbraid, the Grief ‘That makes our Neighbour court us for Relief; ‘Since we may come to need his Kindness, more ‘Than he, at lowest Ebb, did our's before. FABLE XVIII. The Serpent and Peasant:Or, Injuries long remembred. A Serpent long had settl'd her Aboad Near where a Peasant's Habitation stood; And free from hateful Enmity and Strife, They, like good Neighbours, led a Friendly Life: 'Till the Man's Son, thro' Wantonness, aggress'd, And with a rude Assault provok'd the Beast; Who cou'd not Wrongs so undeserv'd abide, But, in Resentment, stung him that he dy'd. The angry Father, to revenge his Son, And punish her who had the Mischief done; With his keen Ax the Serpent did assail, But miss'd her Head, and cut away her Tail. His Grief and Fury were by this allay'd, And he, for future Peace, kind Offers made: Yet wisely she the proffer'd Terms refus'd, And said, Our Faults can hardly be excus'd: We never shall be throughly reconcil'd, While I regret my Tail, and you your Child. The MORAL. ‘True Reconcilement little Room can find, ‘Where Sense of Injuries afflicts the Mind: ‘The deep Resentment must continue long, ‘While sad Effects still represent the Wrong. ‘E're Foes profess'd in real Friendship live, ‘They must forget the Harms they wou'd forgive. FABLE XIX. The Boor and his Plough:Or, The Sham-Redress. A simple Boor, who, toiling at his Plough, Had tir'd himself, and his weak Cattle too; When he his Labour ended with the Day, Unloos'd his Team, and sent the Beasts away: Then on an Ass the Plough and Harness ty'd, And, mounted over all, did homeward ride. But when the Ass, with too much Weight oppress'd, Began to fail, the Boor (to ease his Beast, That he the better might her Sloth upbraid) The Plough and Gears on his own Shoulders laid; And, without more Concern, was jogging on, As if the Weight, that sunk his Ass, was gone: Then told the Beast, She well might keep her Road, For he, to savour her, bore all the Load. The MORAL. ‘Most Men, affected with the Weight they bear, ‘Of others Suff'rings have no Sense or Care; ‘But vainly think they give their Friends Relief, ‘By Means improper to remove their Grief: ‘Tho' such Sham-Helps can none but Idiots please, ‘To shift the Load, but not the Bearer ease. FABLE XX. The One-Ey'd Farmer:Or, No Jesting with Edg'd-Tools. When Heav'n with Barrenness had curs'd the Earth, And Rates of Corn were heightned by the Dearth; A One-Ey'd Farmer, whose small Stock grew scant, Went to next Market, to supply his Want. A Friend, come thither with the same Intent, Ask'd his old Neighbour how the Market went; What Rate a Peck of Wheat, or Rye, did bear? He, to express how high the Prices were, Return'd, A Peck will cost at least an Eye. Whereat a waggish Boy made this Reply; Then, Gaffer, you have brought too large a Sack, For you can buy but One to carry back. The MORAL. ‘Men, giv'n to Jest, shou'd always cautious be ‘To shun Occasion for a Repartee; ‘Lest others take Advantage of their Sport, ‘And on their own Defects their Jokes retort. FABLE XXI. The Climber:Or, Unseasonable Raillery. A fellow, that had climb'd a Chesnut-Tree, Fell from the Top, and sorely bruis'd his Knee: The Outcries he in height of Anguish made, Call'd in the neighb'ring Peasants to his Aid. A pleasant Wag appear'd among the rest, Who, to divert his Sorrow with a Jest, Said gravely, Friend, If you my Counsel take, You shall no more such ill Elopements make; I have a Rule, and an approv'd one too, Which who observes, shall never fall, like you. The Man, who thought, tho' the Advice was late, It might prevent a more unlucky Fate; With Thanks return'd, desir'd him to impart The Secret of that valuable Art. The Wag reply'd, When next you climb, my Friend, Come down no faster than you did ascend; Thus you shall always be from Danger free, And if you tumble, lay the blame on me. The MORAL. ‘Tho' most Misfortunes Men endure, proceed ‘From their too rash Attempts, and want of Heed; ‘Yet 'tis a Crime to taunt them, when distress'd, ‘And urge their Grief, by an untimely Jest: ‘For an acuter Pain is always found, ‘From Hands that Tickle, than that Probe a Wound. FABLE XXII. The Snail and Jupiter:Or, Live within your self. Jove, willing to supply each Creature's Want, To ev'ry one some pleasing Boon wou'd grant: As soon as any made his Grievance known, Whatever he requested, was his own. The Snail petition'd, That where-e'er she went, She on her Back might bear her Tenement. The God demanded, Why she chose a Load, That wou'd her tardy Motion incommode? She answer'd, Sir, That Trouble I desire; That, when I please, I may from worse retire. The MORAL. ‘The Wise with any Circumstance dispense, ‘That frees them from the World's Impertinence; ‘And when its Bustles and its Cares encrease, ‘Retire within themselves, and live in Peace. ‘This Latent Life secures their Solid Joy, ‘Which nothing from without them can annoy. FABLE XXIII. The Wolf and Sow:Or, Much Courtesy, much Craft. A Sow, that, newly Farrow'd, gladly view'd Her Pains rewarded with a num'rous Brood: To whom a Wolf wou'd fain himself prefer To be the Guardian of her Pigs, and her. But she reply'd; We, Sir, no Safeguard need: Wou'd you retire, you wou'd be kind indeed: I see no Danger, while you are not near; And wish your Absence, to remove my Fear. The MORAL. ‘Justly officious Service we decline, ‘Ev'n when we cannot see through the Design: ‘For he, by whom the forward Offer's made, ‘Expects beyond his Merit to be paid. FABLE XXIV. The Devil and the Sinner:Or, Slow Vengeance, sure. An Old Offender, whose repeated Crimes Had laid him fast in Newgate sev'ral times; Who oft' was Scourg'd, and in the Pill'ry stood, 'Till his more hard'ned Face disgrac'd the Wood: All Punishments, but Death, had undergone, And thought the Gallows ne'er wou'd claim its own: Because the Dev'l, whose Help he always us'd, (To make him Rogue compleat) his Life excus'd; He still, when free, drove on his former Trade, And in new Thefts successful Progress made. At last, discover'd, and confin'd again, He sought his Old Assistant's Aid in vain: Satan, when call'd, was ready, as before; But answer'd, Friend, I cannot help you more: On your vile Errands I've so worn my Pumps, That ev'n my Hoofs are batter'd to the Stumps: Nor have I Cash to purchase me a Shooe; My Stock has fail'd me, and so I must you: Farewell then, and be Hang'd, yet cease your Moans; 'Tis time you Swing, Old Tyburn for you Groans. The MORAL. ‘Let not Impunity, or long Success, ‘Encourage Sinners in their Wickedness: ‘For He, whose sly Temptations draw them in, ‘'Till, past Retrieve, they are ingulf'd in Sin; ‘When He perceives they are entangl'd fast, ‘Will flinch, and leave them in the Lurch at last: ‘Then He will shew them, but, alas! too late, ‘Their loath'd Deformity, and hopeless State; ‘And, in Disdain, upbraid them with the Vice ‘To which his Treach'ry did the Fools entice. ‘While Heav'n, whose injur'd Patience long forbore, ‘To try if they wou'd Turn, and Sin no more; ‘But found them Hard'ned, and grown Old in Ills, ‘And wou'd not make them Good, against their Wills; ‘Consigns them to Eternal Punishment, ‘Because they wou'd not, while they might, Repent. FABLE XXV. The Urchin and Viper:Or, The Supplanting Inmate. An Urchin, by sagacious Instinct taught, Foresaw a Storm, and timely Shelter sought; And since he had not any certain Home, Desir'd a Viper to afford him Room. The hospitable Beast did soon consent To take the Inmate, and as soon repent: He found his Tenant an uneasie Guest, That did the Landlord and the House infest: Restless, he roll'd about from side to side, And wou'd not equally the Room divide; His pointed Bristles pierc'd his Neighbour's Skin, Who sate on Thorns, while he remain'd Within; And at his easie Condescension griev'd, Who such a dang'rous Lodger had receiv'd. At last Vexation conquer'd Modesty, And his tir'd Patience urg'd him to be free: He wish'd his Guest wou'd to new Quarters go, And said, His Hut cou'd scarce suffice for Two. The Churl, whose Soul was rougher than his Hide, With surly Language, and ill Looks reply'd; Let him remove, who is not pleas'd to stay; I will not budge, but, if you will, you may. Thus was the old Proprietor disseis'd, And forc'd from Home, to be of Trouble eas'd. The MORAL. ‘Men, who their Safety, or their Peace, design, ‘With Care, encroaching Part'ners shou'd decline: ‘For all who such vexatious Guests receive, ‘Must quit their Right, or in Disturbance live. FABLE XXVI. The Fox and Eagle:Or, Treachery Reveng'd. A Fox and Eagle, by strong Friendship join'd, To live in social Neighbourhood combin'd; And, by Consent, each was to fix her Rest, Where each might find her own Convenience best. An Oak's thick Boughs, exalted in the Air, The Eagle chose, and Hatch'd her Eaglets there: While at its Foot the Fox a Covert found, Where, undisturb'd, she Litter'd Under-ground. But while the Beast did for her Cubs purvey, And rambl'd far from Home, to hunt for Prey; The Eagle thought she had kept Faith too long, And in the Mother's Absence seiz'd her Young: For she design'd to feast her hungry Brood With them, who were as much in want of Food. The Fox, that lost no Time, return'd with Speed, That, with her Spoil, she might her Litter feed; But found the Treach'rous Eagle had been there, And robb'd her of the Objects of her Care. Griev'd at the Loss, but at the Falshood more, Which she wou'd fain revenge, but wanted Pow'r: She us'd such Means as ne'er the Weakest fail, And at the Breach of Faith did loudly rail. Nor 'scap'd the Injury, unpunish'd, long; The Eagle, enter'd thus in doing Wrong, To greater Mischiefs quickly was betray'd, And did an Altar impiously invade: From thence the sacrilegious Robber stole Some hallow'd Flesh, and, with the Flesh, a Coal; With which she to her Airy did retire, And set the Place, she meant to Store, on Fire. Her unfledg'd Eaglets, by the Danger press'd, Threw themselves headlong from the flaming Nest: Which when the injur'd Fox, with joy, observ'd, She thought their Fate for her Revenge reserv'd; And, to exert the Rigour of her Spight, Devour'd the Off-spring in their Parents Sight. The MORAL. ‘False Wretches, thus, who Friendship's Laws despise, ‘And basely violate its Sacred Ties; ‘Find, (tho' the injur'd Suff'rer's feeble Rage ‘Do's vainly for a just Redress engage) ‘That Righteous Heav'n, with its arm'd Justice strong, ‘Will take sharp Vengeance for the hated Wrong: ‘While from one Mischief, they on worse are bent, ‘The Crimes they act, prove their own Punishment. FABLE XXVII. The Satyr and Traveller:Or, Hot and Cold with a Breath. A Satyr, that in Desart still was bred, And Humane Converse, and its Vices, fled; Found in the Wilds a Wretch that lost his Way, And on the Ground, half-frozen to it, lay. The gen'rous Savage, pleas'd his Life to save, Convey'd him to his hospitable Cave; And there all Means for his Recov'ry try'd, That Pity could suggest, or Care provide. While on the Fire the Host was piling Wood, The Inmate blowing his numb'd Fingers stood: The Satyr saw him on that Work intent, And ask'd what he, by such Sufflation, meant. The Traveller, to answer his Demands, Reply'd, He us'd his Breath to warm his Hands. This pass'd, 'till Breakfast on the Board was plac'd, Which the kind Landlord pray'd his Guest to taste. He soon fell to, but found the Broth too hot; (Too large a Fire did over-heat the Pot) His scalded Lips wou'd let him sup no more, 'Till he had blown it, as his Hands before. The wondring Satyr, who observ'd him puff, Ask'd if the Porridge was not warm enough. He answer'd; Sir, It is too warm, I find, And now my Breath to cool it is design'd. Surpriz'd thereat, the Sylvan strait took Fire, And said, Base Villain, from my Cave retire: This honest Cell shall no such Monster hold, Whose false ambiguous Breath blows Hot and Cold. The MORAL. ‘The Wretch, whose Double-Tongue moves diff'rent Ways, ‘And what it now Commends, can soon Dispraise; ‘Excluded from all Honest Men shou'd live, ‘That he may none, but like himself, deceive: ‘For such a Proteus, one so unsincere, ‘Is truly no-where, while he's ev'ry-where: ‘Whom he, while present, sooths with oily Words, ‘He wounds, when absent, more than pointed Swords. ‘Flee the Infection of such pois'nous Breath, ‘That either Stings, or Tickles you to Death: ‘For no Desert can fix, no Ties can bind ‘A Double-Tongue, mov'd by a Double-Mind. FABLE XXVIII. The Lion disarm'd:Or, Virtue suppress'd by Fortune. While a young Lion, just arriv'd at Age, To hunt for Prey, and vent his gen'rous Rage, Made his first Essay in pursuit of Spoil, He lost his Freedom in a Hunter's Toil. The Man, who there his struggling Captive found, Took the Advantage, while he had him bound; And (to disarm his dreaded Mouth and Paws) Beat out his Teeth, and cut away his Claws: Then the disabl'd Brute, in scorn, releas'd, To spend his harmless Fury where he pleas'd. The Gallant Savage, that did still retain The Native Impress of his Noble Strain; (For that no Rage of Fortune cou'd erase, No barb'rous Hand its Characters deface) By that, to great, to bold Attempts, was led, That as a Lion shou'd, he might be fed. By Courage prompted, he large Beasts assails; (But what can Courage do, when Power fails?) His toothless Jaws, and Paws disarm'd, they dare, His Weakness scorn, and wage Offensive War. He roars, and lashes his stern Sides in vain, In vain he swells, and raves, with just Disdain; He on no Beasts, but of ignoble Breed, Defenceless Lambs, and tim'rous Hares, can feed: Restrain'd from Prey of a more bulky Size, He's forc'd to stoop to what he do's despise. The MORAL. ‘Aspiring Souls, to great Attempts enclin'd, ‘But in mean Fortune's humble Bounds confin'd; ‘Make vain Efforts to soar a lofty Height, ‘While such unkind Restraints suppress their Flight. ‘Virtue, obstructed by a low Estate, ‘It self can very rarely extricate; ‘Whenever to exert her Power she tries, ‘The Burthen clogs, and will not let her rise: ‘She can't to her exalted Centre flie, ‘But, kept below, below must grov'ling lie. ‘So Birds, tho' Wing'd by Nature, and by Age, ‘Pine out their Lives, imprison'd in a Cage; ‘Against whose Sides themselves they rashly bruise, ‘When they their Native Freedom strive to use: ‘Which, since their close Confinement do's restrain, ‘In Tunes compell'd, they of their Fate complain. FABLE XXIX. The Coffee-House:Or, A Man's Credit, is his Cash. At Will's, where Troops of flutt'ring, gaudy Beaus Parade, to pick up scraps of Wit and News; When a whole Swarm in the full House was hiv'd, On the Report of an Express arriv'd: While there they, big with Expectation, sate, The first that enter'd was an old Soldate: His Boots, with Dirt not dry, were spatter'd o'er; His Coat a Brushing 'scap'd some Weeks before; His Hat ill cock'd, his Cravat as ill ty'd; His Wig and Face were a right Piss-burn dy'd; His Rusty-hilted Sword, that seem'd a Load, Was hung on mal-adroit, not a-la-mode: In fine, in this odd Dress, he did appear Some very mean or broken Officer. The Sparks his Equipage divertive thought; Ask'd, whence he came, and what strange News he brought. He told them, He from Flanders newly came, And wonder'd how he had out-posted Fame; Since they seem'd Strangers to the glorious Work Perform'd by Marlborough and Auverquerke: How they had giv'n Old Lewis a fatal Blow, And his best Troops a total Overthrow: And Flanders, which he had by Craft obtain'd, Their Courage, in as short a Time, regain'd. With Patience they the Story let him tell, But not a Man believ'd a Syllable: One, with an Oath, says, I'll not heed a Word He speaks; he can't tell how to wear his Sword. Another (of his Friend's Persuasion) cries, 'Tis such a shabby Curr, I'm sure he Lyes. Fogh! says a third, If ever he was there, He smells as if he ran away for Fear. Hang him, concludes a fourth, 'Tis all a Jest, He has not Din'd, and wou'd be some one's Guest. Thus they, by a wrong Estimate befool'd, The Story and the Author ridicul'd: Yet with such Caution manag'd all their Chat, That he shou'd hear no Noise, nor smell a Rat. Amidst their Sport, comes in a little Prig, Powder'd to th' Eyes, and almost drown'd in Wig: A Golden Snush-Box, with right Vigo fill'd, He, in due Form, between his Fingers held; Whence when he had three graceful Pinches took, With screw'd Grimace, thus the starch'd Coxcomb spoke: Great News at Court, the French are soundly beat, Marlb'rough has giv'n the Dogs a clear Defeat: Flanders is now possess'd by the Allies, And, for its Sov'reign, Charles do's Recognize. This said, without more Scruple, they believe, And all for Gospel from his Mouth receive: Wealth more persuades, than Probability; And One so Rigg'd, they fancy'd cou'd not Lye. The MORAL. ‘Thus, when a Poor-Man, in a Thread-bare Coat, ‘Speaks Truth, his Credit is not worth a Groat; ‘While ev'ry Flutt'ring Gaudy Fop's believ'd, ‘And all his Words for Oracles receiv'd. ‘The thoughtless Mob, whom pompous Outsides sway, ‘To Fools well Dress'd a mighty Def'rence pay; ‘To the Credentials of their Habit trust, ‘But think none meanly Clad are True or Just. ‘Poor Men, they fancy, do the Gods contemn, ‘And are as unregarded pass'd by them; ‘But judge, the Rich their Deities revere, ‘And still to them must equally be dear: ‘Thus they believe too little, or too much, ‘Where only Wealth for Honesty must vouch. FABLE XXX. The Boor and Snake:Or, Charity misplaced. A careful Boor, in tracing o'er his Ground, One Winter's Morn, a Snake half-frozen found: In pity, Home he the numb'd Reptile brought, And all kind Means for its Recov'ry sought. Warm'd at the Fire, it quickly did revive, And gave too certain Proofs it was alive: Its Venom was recruited with its Breath, And now it hiss'd aloud, and threat'ned Death. The Children, frighted at its dreadful Sting, Made all the House with dismal Out-cries ring. Their Father heard, and hast'ning to their Aid, With due Correction did his Guest upbraid; Demanding thus, (with now and then a Stroke) Ungrateful Creature! What cou'd this provoke? Or is thy Life a Favour plac'd so ill, That thus thou wou'dst thy kind Preserver kill? The MORAL. ‘Thus we Oblige Ill-natur'd Men in vain; ‘For no Devoir can their due Thanks obtain: ‘The Favours we misplace, they still pervert ‘To hurt us, and account it our Desert. ‘As if we justly merited their Hate, ‘For giving them the Pow'r to be Ingrate. FABLE XXXI. The Rich Man:Or, The Test of Friendship. A gen'rous Man, by Heav'n with Riches bless'd, Observ'd his Friends still, with his Wealth, encreas'd; Daily he treated them with sumptuous Feasts, And often wanted Room, but never Guests: At last, (to try what Spring their Friendship mov'd, If most his Fortune, or himself, they lov'd; If they, who were Partakers of his Fare, Wou'd, with like Constancy, his Dangers share) He did his usual Company invite (Not, as before, to revel, but) to Fight: Told them, He of Invasion was afraid, And, to repel the Force, desir'd their Aid. But they, whose Stomachs were not half so great To fight his Battels, as devour his Meat, Hung back, and feign'd Pretence to be Excus'd: ('Twas the first Invitation they refus'd) So when he was to March against his Foe, His Num'rous Friends were dwindled down to Two: Their steady Friendship highly he approv'd, And them, as they deserv'd, Caress'd and Lov'd: The rest, unworthy of his Meat and Wine, He vow'd, for him, shou'd with Duke Humphrey Dine. The MORAL. ‘Adversity is the sure Test of Friends; ‘That shews, who Loves indeed, or but Pretends: ‘And he, whose Friendship do's o'er that prevail, ‘Is Stanch, Consistent, and will never Fail. ‘But they, whose Hearts your Wealth alone pursue, ‘If that forsakes you, will desert you too. ‘So Rats in Crouds to a full Hovel crawl, ‘But quit it, if on fire, or like to fall. FABLE XXXII. The Boor and Dog:Or, One Injury borne, invites another. A surly Boor, bit by as cross a Curr, In height of Anguish, kept a fearful Stir; With loud Complaints, and in a mighty Fret, He sought a Cure from ev'ry one he met. A pleasant Droll, that thought his noisie Grief Had little Cause, and needed less Relief; Told him, A Crust sopp'd nicely in his Blood, And giv'n the Dog to eat, wou'd do him Good. Quoth Bumkin, That may be a Remedy; But hang me like a Dog, if e'er I try: For then I shou'd deserve to be run down, Piss'd on, and bit by all the Currs in Town. The MORAL. ‘Tame Suff'rers, who to Injuries submit, ‘And stroke the Currs by whom they have been bit; ‘By passive Easiness, fresh Wrongs invite, ‘And tempt Insulters to exert their Spite: ‘Such giving Ground, makes Insolence encroach, ‘And load them most, who least resent Reproach. FABLE XXXIII. The Ox and Bullock:Or, A Merry Life, a Sad End. An aged Ox, long to the Plough inur'd, Daily his Labour, and his Yoke endur'd; While a young Bullock, never tam'd, or drawn, Fed at his Ease, and wanton'd o'er the Lawn; And, in the height of his exulting Pride, Did the grave Senior, and his Pains deride; Scoff'd his worn Neck, his rough and wrinkl'd Skin, That cover'd nothing but bare Bones within: But boasted, That himself was sleek and fair, Liv'd without Toil, and unconfin'd as Air. The wiser Ox all sharp Replies forbore; But still, the less he answer'd, thought the more: 'Till he observ'd the Steer, so highly fed, (Design'd a Victim) to the Altar led: Then said, Ah! Friend, your soft, Luxurious Life, Has brought your Throat thus early to the Knife: Sure, my safe Labour now wou'd better please, Than the short Joys of your destructive Ease. The MORAL. ‘A prudent Man, by Diligence and Pains, ‘In long Security his Life maintains: ‘But Fools, to Sloth and Pleasure only bent, ‘End their short Riot in a sad Event. FABLE XXXIV. The Tortoise and Eagle:Or, The Higher Flight, the Lower Fall. A Tortoise, that despis'd her humble State, Resolv'd among the Clouds to try her Fate; And pray'd an Eagle to assist her Flight, That she, like him, might soar a lofty Height. The Eagle answer'd, Nature had deny'd The only Means to gratifie her Pride; Yet, tempted by large Promises she made, The Creeping Animal aloft convey'd: But, finding there her specious Offers vain, With Indignation hurl'd her down again. Thus she, who wou'd among the Stars reside, Was, like a Meteor, darted thence, and dy'd. The MORAL. ‘Their meaner Fortune wisely Men endure, ‘And in that humble Station live secure: ‘But, by aspiring to a greater Height, ‘Derive their Ruin from the dang'rous Flight. FABLE XXXV. The Ass and Hare:Or, Small Things help the Great. The Royal Lion wag'd Offensive War Against his Neighbour-Sov'reign of the Air; And all his Subjects, for the Fight array'd, Did at the gen'ral Rendevous parade. The Bear, his Commissary, ask'd his Grace Where he the useless Ass and Hare shou'd place: For, since one cou'd not March, nor t'other Fight, They wou'd the Troops dispirit, not excite. The Prince reply'd, Since they want Strength and Hearts, They shall have Posts adapted to their Parts: The Ass shall Sound the Charge against our Foe; The Hare shall still with our Expresses go. The MORAL. ‘The Meanest Things have their appropriate Use, ‘And to the Service of the Best conduce: ‘The humble Peasant do's the Prince support, ‘And the productive Field supplies the Court. ‘So, in a stately Edifice, we find ‘The ample Roof by little Pins conjoin'd. ‘Minutest Members so the Body serve, ‘And, for their Use, their Station there deserve: ‘Nature do's ev'n Excrescences intend, ‘That they the Parts that bear them shou'd defend. FABLE XXXVI. The Ass and Jupiter:Or, Seldom comes a Better. An Ass, that in a Gard'ner's Service wrought, Tir'd with his Work, another Master sought. Consenting Jove grants him a Tyler next; Where he, poor Slave, was with worse Hardships vex'd. Finding himself thus heavily oppress'd, His Provender retrench'd, his Loads encreas'd, He supplicated for another Change: The God believ'd the Creature giv'n to range; But since his Braying wou'd not let him rest, He to a Currier's Work preferr'd the Beast. When there he had some Time of Trial staid, Enough to understand his Master's Trade; He cry'd, This Service I have bought too dear; Death is not now the only Ill I fear: I, by Experience, see this Heathen Turk Will teaze my Hide, when I am kill'd with Work. The MORAL. ‘Thus Men, who at their present Lot repine, ‘Grow fond of Change, and pregnant with Design: ‘What Providence instates them in, refuse, ‘And for themselves, as better Judges, chuse; ‘But often find they alter for the worse, ‘And Heav'n's too free Concession proves a Curse. ‘So Israel's Lust indulg'd, chastis'd their Fault; ‘Their Souls were famish'd by the Food they sought. FABLE XXXVII. The Physician and Patient:Or, Death in the Pot. A try'd Physician, whose applauded Skill had Cur'd more Patients than some others Kill, On a Sick Libertine long Time did wait, But by no Methods cou'd prevent his Fate. He Dy'd: The Doctor was desir'd to guess The Reason why his Art had no Success. He said, No Physick cou'd the Patient save, Whose own Intemp'rance brought him to his Grave. The MORAL. ‘The Bane of Life, is Riot and Excess, ‘When, what shou'd nourish Nature, do's oppress; ‘And fills (thro' Superfluity of Food) ‘The Brain with Fumes, with Crudities the Blood: ‘But in one Instance do's a Kindness shew, ‘What it uneasie makes, it shortens too. FABLE XXXV. The fable number in the source document has been followed. The Hares and Frogs:Or, Fear brings a Snare. The Forest roar'd, by a fierce tempest shook; The tim'rous Hares themselves to Flight betook; But soon were intercepted in their Way By a large Pond, and there oblig'd to stay. With anxious Care, and doubtful Thought, they stand, By fancy'd Dangers press'd on ev'ry hand; While, to encrease their Terror more, they found, The Frogs within their Native Water drown'd. To lay their Fears, one, wiser than the rest, With grave Harangue, his Fellows thus address'd: Why are we stupify'd with groundless Fear? Courage, my Friends, is most availing here: Speed and Activity we have, I grant; But, what's more useful, Resolution want: Amidst our Dangers, here our Safety lies, That what we cannot shun, we can despise. The MORAL. ‘There's no Defence like Courage, in Distress; ‘That represents impending Dangers less: ‘That do's reverse the Glass, and makes them shew ‘Minute, and distant to the Fancy's View. ‘But Fear, its Objects thro' false-Opticks draws, ‘Heightens it self, and magnifies its Cause: ‘Pushes the Coward headlong on his Fate, ‘To shun the Mormo's his scar'd Thoughts create. FABLE XXXIX. The Shepherd's Voyage:Or, Caution, from Experience. A happy Peasant, rich in fleecy Sheep, Which, with assiduous Care, himself did keep; While he, one Evening, fed the bleating Flock, Observ'd the Ocean, from a neighb'ring Rock: Its smiling Image was all calm and fair, Not wrinkl'd by a Blast of Ruffling Air; And the declining Sun's more radiant Beams Gilded it Surface with reflected Gleams. The Man grew fond of the false Element, And thought his Time wou'd there be better spent; Chang'd his sure Profit, for uncertain Wares, His easie Business, for a Life of Cares; Fraighted a Ship, and, big with Hopes of Gain, Forsook the Land, to traffick on the Main. But there he did not long his Fortune try, E're he perceiv'd its Instability; A frowning Tempest spoil'd its former Grace, And with impostum'd Waves o'erspread its Face. At once the roaring Deep, and lowring Sky, With Menaces of Death and Ruin vie; Shock'd with the Rage of whose contending Force, The shatter'd Vessel scarce cou'd keep her Course: And by the Owner, in this dubious Strait, Was, for his Safety, lightned of her Fraight. Tir'd with the Sea, he soon did Homeward stand, And, with much Difficulty, made the Land; There to his first Employ himself betook, And did with Horror on the Ocean look. Once as he led his Flock along the Shore, And saw the Water wheedling, as before; In vain, he cry'd, you smooth your Treach'rous Brow; Your Falshood, and deluding Arts, I know: You want another Cargo now, I see, But shall no more prevail to Cully me. The MORAL. ‘Wise Men once trick'd, the next Attempt discern, ‘And Caution, from experienc'd Dangers, learn: ‘Their Faith abus'd, they will confide no more, ‘Nor venture on the Rocks they scap'd before. ‘They who have been deceiv'd by Fortune's Smiles, ‘And know how her Dependants she beguiles; ‘No Confidence in her Caresses place, ‘But Ruin dread in ev'ry kind Embrace. FABLE XL. The Fox and Wolf:Or, The Treason lov'd, the Traitor hated. A Wolf, with Prey too plentifully fed, Inclin'd to Rest, lay stretch'd along his Bed. A wily Fox, insidiously bent, Approach'd, and ask'd him what that Posture meant: The Wolf (that had his Den with Plenty stor'd, And smelt a shrewd Design upon his Hoard) Reply'd, He did of longer Life despair, And earnestly desir'd the Fox's Pray'r. Reynard, displeas'd at his successless Train, Betray'd the Covert to a neighb'ring Swain: Who found the Wolf where he supinely lay, And made his Life for former Mischiefs pay. Isgrim dispatch'd, the Fox possess'd his Spoil, Enrich'd, by Treach'ry, without Care or Toil; But e're the ill-got Prize he long enjoy'd, Dy'd by the Hand that had his Friend destroy'd. The MORAL. ‘Men, at their Neighbour's Fortune envious grown, ‘Pursuing his Enjoyments, lose their own; ‘While they on gainful Treachery depend, ‘They meet their due Reward, and miss their End. ‘For they who most the pleasing Treason love, ‘Do most the hateful Traytor disapprove. ‘Since he that will, for Gain, betray his Friend, ‘Wou'd ruin Mankind, for that sordid End. FABLE XLI. The Bee-Master:Or, Friendship misapprehended. While some industrious Bees had left their Home, And, scatter'd o'er the spacious Field, did roam; Where they (in Nature's Chymistry exact) Might rich Elixir from each Herb extract; Which thro' their small Alembicks they distill, And with it their Repositories fill: A pilf'ring Thief, who his own Wants reliev'd By others Care, and on their Labour liv'd; Regardless how they shou'd support their Lives, Came by, and plunder'd the defenceless Hives. Their Owner, who delighted in their Trade, A Visit to their Lab'ratories made; And (with Surprize at the Disaster) found Their Rifled Houses tumbled on the Ground: While he attempts to rectifie the Harm, The laden Bees, returning, round him swarm; They him for the abhorr'd Aggressor take, And, with their Stings, sharp Retribution make. He, so attack'd, for a Cessation sues, And wou'd the jealous Insects disabuse: On me, he cries, your Fury you mis-spend, Who wou'd your Stocks from Injuries defend: You on the Robber, who your Stores destroy'd, To better Purpose had your Stings employ'd: Tho' I am wrong'd, he wou'd be justly serv'd, For his sweet Meat so sour a Sauce deserv'd. The MORAL. ‘A jealous Man, by false Surmise mis-led, ‘Fears not the Enemies he ought to dread; ‘But, thro' his Misconstruction, apprehends ‘His Harms occasion'd by his only Friends: ‘Such wrong Suspicions make him prove unjust, ‘The Guilty free, the Innocent mistrust. FABLE XLII. The Fellow-Travellers:Or, Friends and Sharers. As Two Companions travell'd on the Way, One found an Ax, that there neglected lay; And, as he rais'd his Booty from the Ground, Said to his Friend, See here! what I have found. The other answer'd, Half belongs to me; You shou'd not, Sir, say, I have found, but We. This past, the Owner, who the Hatchet lost, Soon miss'd it, and in quest thereof did post: He found the Person who his Ax possess'd, Seiz'd on the Tool, and did the Man arrest. The Wretch, who saw his Prize, and Freedom, gone, Said to his Friend, Alas! we are undone. His Friend reply'd; We, Sir, you shou'd not cry; For, when you found it, 'twas not We, but I. The MORAL. ‘They who enjoy Heav'n's lib'ral Gifts alone, ‘And in their Golden Days their Friends disown; ‘Deserve, when brought to an oppressive Strait, ‘To bear, unpity'd, and alone, the Weight. ‘For Men that are in mutual Friendship join'd, ‘To share in all Things were by Heav'n design'd. FABLE XLIII. The Bull and Goat:Or, Afflict not the Afflicted. A Bull, to shun a Lion's close Pursuit, Fled to a Cave, and met a greater Brute; A Goat, that Sanctuary there deny'd, And with his threatning Horns the Bull defy'd. He, press'd by Fear, durst not delay so long His present Safety, to revenge the Wrong; But to the Goat said, with a gen'rous Slight, You now, unpunish'd, may oppose my Flight; But, were the Enemy I shun away, For this rude Insolence shou'd dearly pay. The MORAL. ‘He, who denies to succour the Distress'd, ‘Puts off the Man, and represents the Beast: ‘But he, whose Injuries encrease their Woe, ‘Do's a more fierce and brutal Temper show: ‘And, when to him Fate proves alike unkind, ‘As little Pity as he shew'd, shou'd find. FABLE XLIV. The Citizen and his Hounds:Or, None safe, where Merit suffers. A Citizen, who bought a Country Seat, Was much delighted with the sweet Retreat; Nor wou'd remove 'till Winter grew severe, And, by a tedious Storm, confin'd him there. The Man, who found his whole Provision spent, And wanted Food for daily Nourishment; First, with the slaughter'd Sheep his Need supply'd, And, when they fail'd, the lab'ring Oxen dy'd. His Dogs, that saw it, frighted at the Sight, Provided for their Safety, by their Flight: They fear'd their Master wou'd not spare his Hounds, Who kill'd the useful Beasts that plough'd his Grounds. The MORAL. ‘When they, whose Merits claim a just Respect, ‘Are treated with Injustice, or Neglect; ‘What Usage may the less-Deserving fear, ‘Whom no such gaining Qualities endear? ‘Well may they thence their own worse Fate conclude, ‘And shun the Reach of such Ingratitude. FABLE XLV. The Dogs and Ass:Or, Envy, its own Tormentor. The Night was calm, serene, and sweet the Air; The Moon in her full Lustre did appear; All Things to downy Sleep were Captives made, But some loud Currs, that did their Peace invade: At Cynthia's Beams, and their own Shadows, vex'd, They, with vile Houling, all the Town perplex'd. At this, an Ass, wak'd with their Noise, was mov'd, And thus their clam'rous Peevishness reprov'd: Sure, Sirs, much Bus'ness do's your Thoughts molest, That you afford your selves no Time to Rest; Or you suppose you at St. Malo are, And think the Town committed to your Care; Which makes you all this Din and Pother keep, That, while you Wake, your Neighbours may not Sleep. The MORAL. ‘Where Vip'rous Envy frets and gnaws the Mind, ‘The tortur'd Patient no Repose can find: ‘His Sorrow's heightned by his Neighbour's Joy, ‘And their Tranquillities his Peace destroy. ‘The Envious on themselves exert their Spight, ‘And all displeases, that shou'd please their Sight: ‘Misfortunes only give their Pains relief, ‘They Grieve, because they find no Cause of Grief. FABLE XLVI. The Frog and Ox:Or, Never Satisfy'd, never Happy. A Frog, that in a fertile Pasture spies A well-grown Ox, envies his larger Size: To Equal him, she her small Body strains, 'Till, with the Force, she almost burst her Veins. Her wiser Son cries, Mother, Pray forbear; In vain a Frog wou'd with an Ox compare: But he his Counsel and his Breath mis-spent; She wou'd be Great, tho' Death was the Event. Again she strains; again he bids her cease, For all her Pains cou'd not her Bulk encrease; Tho' she shou'd burst, she still wou'd miss her Aim, By Nature stinted to that petty Frame. Yet still she strains, ambitious to succeed; But over-strains her self, and bursts indeed. The MORAL. ‘Wise Heav'n, that suits its Blessings to our Wants, ‘To Each some choice peculiar Favour grants: ‘Hence, some in Beauty, some in Strength, surmount; ‘Some num'rous Friends, and some vast Treasures count; ‘And happy they, who with their Gifts content, ‘Nor envy others, nor themselves torment. ‘For he, who thinks his own Endowment poor, ‘Loses its Pleasure, while he grasps at more. FABLE XLVII. The Trees:Or, Fatal Beauty. A grove of Trees in one Plantation grew, Tall, straight, and smooth, and graceful to the View: Only one Brother, not so kindly thriv'n, Was Dwarfish, Crooked, Knotty, and Unev'n: Him all his haughty Fellows did despise, Him they still loaded with sharp Obloquies. But so it chanc'd, that he who own'd the Soil, Condemn'd his Wood to be the Axe's Spoil; And, to erect a Building on his Land, Fell'd the fair Trees, but let the Monster stand. He, marking how his nobler Brethren far'd, While he, for his Defects alone, was spar'd; Said, I on Nature will no more exclaim, For this my useless and mis-shapen Frame; Since I, by that, my Safety have enjoy'd, While others, for their Beauty, are destroy'd. The MORAL. ‘We shou'd not rashly at those Wants repine, ‘In which kind Heav'n our Safety do's design: ‘A Sickly Body, or a mean Estate, ‘Prevent our suff'ring a severer Fate. ‘Vigour and Wealth make us ill Courses run, ‘And furnish us with Means to be undone. ‘The boasted Beauties of a Charming Face, ‘Expose, what they imbellish, to Disgrace. ‘She who is less admir'd, is more secure; ‘Meets few Assaults, or many can endure. FABLE XLVIII. The Mice in Consult:Or, Impracticable Projects useless. A crew of Mice, that in a Barn were bred, Where they far'd high, and plentifully sed; And, to avoid the injur'd Farmer's Sight, Sculk'd all the Day, and Revell'd all the Night; Were by a Cat made a continual Prey, A Cat more watchful, and as quick as they: For Puss cou'd in the Dark best use her Eyes, And seiz'd the fearless Captives by Surprize. This prompted their Contrivance, to avoid The sudden Fate by which they were destroy'd. The Council sate; a thinking Mouse arose, And to the rest did thus his Sense propose: Since, for our Safety, to find Ways and Means, Is what this grave Assembly here convenes; Because, in spite of all our baffled Cares, Our Foe, Grimalkin, snaps us unawares: To frustrate her Attempts, it may do well, About her Neck to hang a Warning-Bell; By whose shrill Sound, inform'd when Puss is nigh, We may be caution'd, and from Danger flie. This was approv'd, till a considerate Mouse, That had been long the Mouth of all the House, Reply'd; I much approve my Brother's Way: But which of us shall make the bold Essay? The MORAL. ‘Impracticable Projects useless are, ‘But to accomplish, is the Wise Man's Care: ‘Men may safe Methods easily advise; ‘But the main Stress, in Execution lies: ‘If then you cannot what you wou'd atchieve, ‘Will what you can, and you may hope to thrive. FABLE XLIX. The Hermit and Soldier:Or, Involuntary Reformation. A pious Hermit, whose Regard was shown As much for others Safety as his own; Advis'd a Soldier to consult his Ease, And keep his Body and his Soul in Peace; By timely quitting the lewd Camp, which few, Without exposing both at once, pursue. To whom the Man of War, with Thanks, reply'd, Your Counsel, Rev'rend Sir, shall be my Guide: For now the Times are grown so very bad, That neither Pay nor Plunder can be had. The MORAL. ‘Thus freely, Men, when they can sin no more, ‘Renounce the Vices they indulg'd before: ‘The Drunkard, when enfeebl'd by Excess, ‘Do's firm Resolves of Temperance express. ‘The Leacher does in Continence engage, ‘When from his Swinge he is restrain'd by Age: ‘Thus All expect to be accounted Good, ‘Because they cannot act the Crimes they wou'd. ‘But they in vain their Boasts of Virtue make, ‘Who ne'er their Sins, 'till left by them, forsake: ‘For he, whom want of Means with-holds from Ill, ‘Is not Reform'd, but Good against his Will. FABLE L. The Lion, Ass, and Fox:Or, One's Danger, another's Caution. The King of Beasts invited to a Chase A subtil Fox, and an unthinking Ass: The early Hunters well employ'd the Day, Were tir'd with Sport, and laden with their Prey. Their gracious Sov'reign, to reward their Toil, Bid the dull Ass divide the noble Spoil. This inconsid'rate Blockhead, not aware, And eager to be Master of his Share; An equal Tripartite Division makes, And to himself a Third Proportion takes. But soon the Lion, with an angry Brow, Lets him his Error, and his Danger, know; And the imprudent Beast in Pieces tears, To make an Augmentation to the Shares: Then bids the Fox, the Ass's Failure mend, And try to make a fairer Dividend. The cautious Reynard freely did obey, But had no stomach to encrease the Prey; Instructed by his apprehensive Sense, That no Partition, best wou'd please his Prince; He the whole Prize into a Heap did draw, And humbly laid it at the Lion's Paw: Who, pleas'd to see him thus discharge his Trust, Ask'd, where he learn'd to be so nicely Just? To whose Demand the ready Fox reply'd, Sir, The dead Ass has taught me to divide. The MORAL. ‘Wise Men, subjected to a Tyrant's Lust, ‘Who seeks Occasion to become Unjust; ‘By what their Fellows suffer, cautious made, ‘Avoid the Snares that for themselves are laid: ‘And when their Neighbour's House begins to burn, ‘Think how to shun what may be next their Turn. FABLE LI. The Fox and Women:Or, More Bold than Welcome. An Old Eves dropping Fox, a subtle Dog, That us'd to pry in ev'ry Nook for Prog; As he, at Mid-night, through a Village pass'd, Saw Six Fat Gossips round a Table plac'd: As many Pullets, and as Plump as they, Garnish'd with Sausages, before them lay. The tempting Meat made them fall to a-pace, Nor did their Stomachs let them stay for Grace. The Dames so sharp were set, that (which was strange) They did not, for some space, a Word exchange; But a profound surprizing Silence kept, As if their Husbands within hearing slept: (Tho' this was what they cou'd not yet avoid; Their Mouths were now another way employ'd:) But when some hearty Bumpers had gone round, And oil'd their Tongues; they were not Dumb, he found: They grew as Loud, as they were Mute before, And Talk'd so fast, no Pies cou'd Chatter more. Reynard, who envy'd them their Mirth and Fare, Wou'd fain have made an, Are-ye-at-it there? And, since he cou'd not be allow'd a Guest, He lick'd his driv'ling Chops, and spoil'd the Feast. Good Wives, said he, if I had done like you, What Noise of Hounds and Horns wou'd me pursue? Your Dogs, and Husbands (by your Kindness arm'd) Wou'd all, to follow Reynard, be Alarm'd: And you your selves wou'd be too apt to Rail, If I got one poor Pullet by Retail; Tho' you have gormandiz'd, by Wholsale, more Than I have filch'd from you this Month before. To this, a Matron, perter than the rest, Reply'd, What's that to you, malicious Beast? If your Impertinence like us had done, You wou'd have fed on nothing but your own: Learn to do so, and, what is ours, forbear, And much good do't you, Gaffer, with your Chear: We never envy you an honest Meal, Nor grudge at what you eat, but what you steal. The MORAL. ‘Contented with its own, an honest Mind ‘Repines not at the Joys which others find; ‘Nor thinks it can, without affronting Heav'n, ‘Invade the Properties which that has giv'n. ‘Tho', where no previous Right do's Titles grant, ‘Nature leaves Things to the first Occupant: ‘Yet where, by Civil Pacts, the Right's assign'd, ‘They are no longer common, but confin'd. ‘When so enclos'd, to use them at our Will, ‘Is, as the Users differ, well, or ill: ‘In the Proprietors, 'tis Right, and Just; ‘But in Usurpers, Theft, or Breach of Trust. ‘An Honest Man, whose Conscience Justice sways, ‘Without Reserve, all her Commands obeys: ‘Will no Designs, but what he may, pursue, ‘And gives, or wou'd give ev'ry One his Due. ‘Were all Men such, how Happy shou'd we be! ‘From Rapine safe, from all Injustice free. FABLE LII. The Fox without a Tail:Or, The More the Merrier. A Fox, that often had deserv'd a Jail, Was trap'd at last, and taken by the Tail: But he, unwilling to be long confin'd, Made his Escape, and left the Pledge behind. His Freedom gain'd, he next consults his Fame, And casts about how to conceal the Shame: His Project was, to propagate the Mode, Under a fair Pretence of Publick Good: He likes the Thought, assembles all his Friends, And, to their Wisdoms, Docking recommends: Tells them, They carry'd but an useless Load, That did the Bearers greatly incommode; A vain Excrescence, which they well might spare, And better want, than to no purpose bear; But of that Burthen eas'd, they wou'd be light, And fitted either for Pursuit, or Flight; Their Shapes to more Advantage wou'd be seen, Gain a new Air, and a more graceful Mien: Thus they, by quitting this uncomly Part, Might polish Nature's rougher Draught, by Art. This said; a sharper Fox, that smelt his Drift, And found his specious Arguments a Shift, Reply'd, You have your Oratory shown, Not to promote our Int'rest, but your own; And 'tis not reasonable we shou'd join In what was your Misfortune, not Design. The MORAL. ‘Designing Knaves, like Reynard in the Tale, ‘Make the Pretence of Publick Good a Stale; ‘Practise their Villanies, and 'scape the Blame, ‘By drawing others to commit the same. ‘For Many Part'ners in a Crime, when known, ‘Make the divided Guilt seem less in One; ‘Or, by their Numbers, grown too strong, and high, ‘Dare weaker Justice, and the Laws, defie. FABLE LIII. The Miss:Or, The Sponge squeez'd. A Lady of the Town, whose Wheedling Art Had made a Breach in a young Captain's Heart; As Conqu'rors, of the Towns they Storm, dispose, Plunder'd her Slave of all he had to lose: The greedy Wretch scarce left him worth a Groat, Except a Cloak to hide his shabby Coat; Yet he her Pris'ner at Discretion liv'd, Pleas'd with the Fate at which he shou'd have griev'd. At last, the Time for brisk Campaign was come, And he (sad Mortal) must attend the Drum; Tho' with Reluctance, that he shou'd forego A Thing as Noisie, and as Hollow too. Away he sail'd with next presenting Wind, But left his Heart (if he had one) behind. The Jilt, when she perceiv'd him past Retrieve, Did with a more than common Sorrow grieve. Her Consorts ask'd her why she Wept so sore, Who never had appear'd so True before? Ah! she reply'd, My very Heart is broke, To think that I have lost—his Scarlet Cloak. The MORAL. ‘Insatiate Jilts, for mercenary Ends, ‘With Shews of Love, Cajole their Cully'd Friends; ‘'Till they the Substance of their Pockets drain, ‘And then the Sponges they have squeez'd, disdain. ‘Curs'd is the Wretch that on their Faith relies, ‘Who, only for the Gifts, the Giver prise. FABLE LIV. The Smith and his Dog:Or, No Work, no Meat. While a laborious Smith, to earn his Meat, Wrought at his Forge, with daily Toil and Sweat; And, with incessant Pains, himself did tire, For a poor Living, rak'd out of the Fire. His idle Dog, that spent his Time in Ease, Slept undisturb'd by ev'ry thing, but Fleas. But when the Master to his Victuals sate, His Dog sleep vanish'd, and he came to wait; With brisk Devoir he fawn'd, and wagg'd his Tail, And, by his Flatt'ry, did for Food prevail: Thus ready at each Meal he us'd to be, None so adroit, so diligent, as he. All that observ'd his Stomach, wou'd have thought, That he who eat so much, as much had wrought. But honest Smug, who knew the lazy Curr Did only, when the Meat was going, stir; Yet the unprofitable Charge maintain'd, Thus of his Appetite and Sloth complain'd: While I, with early Pains, my Anvil ply, You by my side supinely Sleeping lie; And tho' my Noise the Neighbour's do's molest, 'Tis not sufficient to disturb your Rest: But when my Hands are still, and Teeth employ'd, You quickly hear, and then wou'd Sleep avoid: Whene'er again, with Stroaks, my Anvil groans, Again your Business is, to rest your Bones: Scarce I to Work, e're you to Bed are gone; For when your Belly's full, your Work is done. The MORAL. ‘The Drones who haunt their busie Neighbours Hives, ‘And, by their Pains, support their idle Lives; ‘With just Contempt shou'd be excluded thence, ‘Driv'n to hard Work, or harder Indigence: ‘Labour alone intitles Men to Eat; ‘When Sleep's their Bus'ness, Sleep shou'd be their Meat. FABLE LV. The Swan and Stork:Or, Deliverance in Death. A dying Swan, that with her fleeting Breath, In tuneful Accents, seem'd to welcome Death; Was, by a Stork, that heard her Song, admir'd, When in such joyful Transports she expir'd: That she, who ne'er before unlock'd her Throat, To please her self with any charming Note; Shou'd at grim Death's Approach, which others fear, So gay, so chearful, so serene appear. The Swan reply'd, I well may raise my Voice, And at the kind Relief of Fate rejoyce; Since I for Food shall take no longer Care, No longer dread the Fowler's Gun or Snare. The MORAL. ‘Why shou'd frail Men, at Death's Approach, be shock'd, ‘By whose kind Hand their Prisons are unlock'd? ‘Since, free'd from Troubles which their Lives enslave, ‘They lie at Rest within the peaceful Grave? ‘Embolden'd by their Liberty so near, ‘They need no Tyrant's Frown, nor Fortune's fear. ‘He, whose undaunted Mind can Death despise, ‘All other Foes, and their short Rage, defies. FABLE LVI. The Hawk and Nightingale:Or, Profit, the best Pleasure. A Nightingale was by a Merlin seiz'd, And saw but little hope to be releas'd; Yet, loth to Die, she begg'd the eager Foe To let her pay her Ransom down, and go. The Hawk, who knew she had not much to give, Ask'd, what she cou'd afford for a Reprieve? She answer'd, She wou'd strain her charming Voice, To please his Ears, and make his Heart rejoyce. The Hawk reply'd, Pray, save your fruitless Pray'rs I must indulge my Belly, not my Ears: That calls for Meat, and has been empty long, And will not be contented with a Song: And I, who only live by what I eat, Can want your Tunes, but cannot want my Meat. The MORAL. ‘He, who do's Pleasure, more than Profit prise, ‘Deprives himself of Food, and, starving, dies; ‘While he who only do's his Gain pursue, ‘By getting That, in That has Pleasure too. FABLE LVII. The Dog and Wolf:Or, A Burnt Child dreads the Fire. A Dog lay sleeping at his Master's Gate, And never dreamt of his approaching Fate; When his old Enemy, a Wolf, came near, Just nick'd the Time, and took him napping there. In this Surprize, the Dog for Life begg'd hard, And gave this Reason why he shou'd be spar'd: I have been lately under a Decay, Brought very low, and strangely fall'n away; And now, alas! my Flesh so slowly grows, 'Tis Carrion yet, and only fit for Crows: But my good Master will at Easter Wed, And then I shall be plentifully fed; Then you will find me most delicious Meat, And fit for you, or any Wolf, to eat: If then you please to wait that lucky Hour, You may your Servant, so improv'd, devour. The Wolf believ'd him, and dismiss'd his Prey, And came again at the appointed Day: He found the Dog, not Sleeping, as before, But standing on his Guard within the Door: Isgrim desir'd him to make good his Word; But Spot this Answer only wou'd afford: When next you catch me sleeping at the Gate, Good Mr. Wolf, for no more Bridals wait. The MORAL. ‘Thus prudent Men, when once from Danger free'd, ‘With greater Caution in their Ways proceed; ‘Correct the Errors, and Neglects avoid, ‘Which made them liable to be destroy'd: ‘From former Suff'rings, they Suspicion learn, ‘And proper Means to shun the like, discern. ‘Burnt Children thus are quickly taught the Art ‘To flie the dreaded Fire that made them smart. FABLE LVIII. The Rival Cocks:Or, No Reckoning of Chickens before they are Hatch'd. Two Cocks, that on a Dunghil sought to reign, Did, for the Empire, daily War maintain; Often they strove which shou'd his Foe destroy, And the Seraglio of Hens enjoy: 'Till the first Lord of the rich Soil, by Fate Compell'd to yield, was forc'd to Abdicate: Asham'd thereat, he soon retir'd from Sight, And durst no more appear to claim his Right. The happy Victor, of his Conquest proud, Proclaims his Triumph to the World aloud: Mounts the House-top, and claps his joyful Wings, And, with rais'd Crest, three Iö Bæans sings. But while thus haughty, thus with Trophies pleas'd, An Eagle saw him, and the Boaster seiz'd; Then with her Captive to her Airy flew, And for her Young, the wretched Victim slew. His vanquish'd Rival, who beheld his Fate, Recall'd his Courage, and return'd in State; Was Recogniz'd, resum'd his Rightful Throne, And Trod the Dunghil, and the Hens, alone, The MORAL. ‘Since here we daily Revolutions see, ‘And cannot dive into Futurity; ‘Why shou'd we vainly our Success admire, ‘And, unprovided for a Fall, aspire? ‘Extreams are short-liv'd, and, from Heights of Bliss, ‘We may be plung'd in Sorrow's deep Abyss. ‘A Steady Mind is always on its Guard, ‘And for a Change, in ev'ry State, prepar'd: ‘Hopes for a Calm, when most with Storms oppress'd; ‘And looks for Storms, when with a Calm 'tis bless'd!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">BOOK IV. FABLE I. The Frogs and Jupiter:Or, The Malecontents. The Frogs, a People Uncontroll'd, and Free, But ignorant in prising Liberty; With loud Petitions deaf'ned Jove, to grant A King; a Favour they had better want. Straight the Consenting God throws down a Block, Whose pond'rous Weight the neighb'ring Fens did shock. The frighted Crowds at awful Distance stand, And, with due Rev'rence, wait their King's Command. But when his Silence had dispell'd their Fear, They gather'd Courage, and came boldly near: Then, with dull Majesty familiar grown, They made their King a Stage to sport upon. This did not please, they new Petitions bring, Desire a brisker and more active King. At their Request, the God deputes a Stork, Who stalking through the Pools, made dreadful Work: His Subjects Blood the Tyrant daily shed, And with their Flesh his pamper'd Carcafe fed. Now their wish'd Change of Government they curse, (For if the Log was bad, the Stork was worse;) And of their Grievances again complain, A new Vicegerent ask, but ask in vain: They who the Block's more easie Reign despis'd, By one too Rigid, justly were chastis'd. The MORAL. ‘Restless Desires of Change, our Bliss destroy, ‘We still disrelish Blessings we enjoy: ‘But nothing more betrays our Discontent, ‘Than our Dislike of present Government. ‘Kings of all Tempers are alike revil'd; ‘The Sharp seem too severe, too soft the Mild: ‘We think they hold the Reins too loose, or strait; ‘If that, despise them; if the other, hate: ‘The Mind's unsettl'd with this strange Disease; ‘Heav'n neither can with Rain nor Sun-shine please. FABLE II. The Crow and Birds:Or, Monarchy the best Government. The Birds consider'd, that the Eagle's Care Cou'd scarce extend thro' all the spacious Air; Its Feather'd Natives were so Num'rous grown, They thought the Government too large for One: And, for the better Guidance of the State, Wou'd a Plurality of Kings create. But the wise Crow, disliking that Design, Advis'd, They shou'd the rash Attempt decline; And told them, (for they wou'd his Reason know) A less Expence wou'd fill one Sack, than two. The MORAL. ‘In Common-wealths, where many Lords are found, ‘The Peoples Suff'rings equally abound: ‘But shou'd a Monarch Arbitrary grow, ‘His Subjects still but One Oppressor know: ‘And sure, the Suff'rers less perceive the Harm, ‘To glut a single Hornet, than a Swarm. FABLE III. The Ass and Horse:Or, Sweet Meat has Sour Sauce. An Ass, with Grief, beheld a pamper'd Steed, Who, tho' he never Wrought, did always Feed; And thought him happy in that envy'd State, But murmur'd at his own severer Fate: Pinch'd with hard Fare, with heavy Loads oppress'd, Allow'd as little Time to Eat, as Rest. But while this deep Concern encreas'd his Care, The Trumpet summon'd the proud Horse to War; Who tamely did his Back and Mouth submit To bear the Rider, and endure the Bit: Thus press'd to Battle, from the hostile Side, He soon receiv'd a mortal Wound, and dy'd. The Ass, that saw him fall, no longer griev'd, Nor was with false Appearances deceiv'd; But own'd, the Gods to him had prov'd more kind, Whom they for mean, but safer Use, design'd. The MORAL. ‘The Poor, in judging of his Neighbour's State, ‘Is oft' mistaken in his Estimate: ‘He sees the fancy'd Joy, and that commends, ‘But not the Grief which on that Joy attends: ‘Observes the griping Want himself endures, ‘But not the Quiet which that Want secures: ‘How he, while Cares the Rich-Man's Bliss allay, ‘Can pass the Night in Sleep, in Song, the Day. FABLE IV. The Ass and Calf:Or, A Useful Life, secure. An Ass and Calf in one Enclosure fed, They meant no Mischief, nor did Mischief dread; 'Till an Alarm-Bell rang, which let them know The Watch discover'd an approaching Foe. The frighted Calf cry'd, Neighbour, let us run, For, if we stay, we shall be both undone. The Ass reply'd; You, if you please, may flie, Who are good Meat, and may expect to die: I fear no change of Fortune; come who will, My Work will be to carry Burdens still. The MORAL. ‘Subjects ill us'd, no change of Princes fear; ‘The worst that comes, can only be severe: ‘And rarely Slaves the Axe or Halter dread, ‘Who toil while living, but are free when dead. FABLE V. The Beau and his Cat:Or, Nature unalterable. A brisk young Beau, to airy Mirth enclin'd, Did, with a Cat, unknown Diversion find; For Puss was gay, and sportive too, as he, As Velvet sleek, and white as Ivory; Adorn'd with ev'ry Beauty, ev'ry Grace, And might have look'd a Monarch in the Face: With various Antick Tricks she pass'd the Day, And, with whatever she cou'd find, wou'd play; Or, if she had no other Game in view, In winding Circles wou'd her Tail pursue: All Day she strove to heighten his Delight, And by his Side lay Purring all the Night. These winning Ways did still her Charms improve, And gain'd her the Ascendant o'er his Love; 'Till he esteem'd her at a higher Rate, Than suited with the Merits of a Cat: And now he wish'd (since he was doom'd to burn) That Puss cou'd make his Flame a fit Return: For this his Vows to Venus he address'd; And she (who still helps Lovers, when distress'd) Granted the Boon for which he often pray'd, And metamorphos'd Mouser to a Maid. The Spark, transported at so vast a Bliss, With num'rous Scenes of Love caress'd his Miss; Nothing was wanting that cou'd Joy express, Raise her Delight, or speak his Happiness. But Love's bright Goddess, who enclin'd to know If, with her Shape, her Mind was alter'd too; Resolv'd to try her with her former Game, And sent a cheeping Mouse to tempt the Dame. Scarce had the Animal approach'd the Place, When Madam, with Impatience, gave her Chase; Forgot her Shape, her Quality, and Love, And did as much a Cat, as ever, prove. The slighted Goddess, much incens'd, to find, That Cat (in spite of Fate) wou'd to her Kind; Reduc'd her to the Beast she was before, And vow'd, she shou'd turn Cat in Pan no more. The MORAL. ‘Tho' Men their Climate shift, or cross the Main, ‘They Nature's Tincture ev'ry-where retain: ‘Thus he, whose Temper is to Vice enclin'd, ‘By changing Stations, do's not change his Mind: ‘He cannot his primæval Impress lose, ‘Who takes himself along where-e'er he goes. ‘To alter Nature is a vain Device; ‘Cats will be Cats, as long as Mice are Mice. FABLE VI. The Stag and Sheep:Or, Trick for Trick. A Stag before the Wolf a Sheep conven'd, And falsly did an ancient Debt pretend. The Sheep, (who nothing of the Matter knew, But that the Sum demanded, was not due) Aw'd by the Wolf, durst not the Charge gainsay, But promis'd Payment, and prefix'd a Day. The Day soon came; the Stag made his Demand, And found the Wolf was not so near at hand: The Sheep deny'd, pleaded Duresse and Force, Which void extorted Promises, of course. The MORAL. ‘Reason, and Law on Reason founded, prove ‘That legal Arms shou'd lawless Force remove: ‘Then sure, 'tis just, when false Demands are made, ‘An honest Fraud, a base one shou'd evade. FABLE VII. Mercury and the Statuary:Or, Vain-glory mortified. Ambitious Mercury, grown fond to know In what Esteem his Godship was Below; In Air, resembling Human Form, array'd, His Visit to a Graver's Work house made. This Chapman seen, the Man began to cry, Welcome, Good Sir; What will you please to buy? Pray, what siz'd Figures do's your Worship want, To set in Niches, or on Grass-plots plant? I have of all Sorts, 'tis right Work I sell; Pray, cheapen something, Sir; I'll use you well. The curious Feigner, from Discov'ry free, Desir'd some Statues of the Gods to see. The Workman smil'd, to hear him so inclin'd, For he few Customers for them did find. He had of refuse Stone good store of these, The first Essays of his raw Prentices; That did behind the Door all dusty stand, And long had lain a Drug upon his hand: These he produc'd, and having brush'd them well, Thus, in his usual Cant, began to sell: Here's Jupiter, and very nicely wrought, But yet Dog-cheap; he's yours, Sir, for a Groat: Here's Juno too, and graven to the Life, She'll be a Peny less, because the Wife. The God, with Smiles, deriding their low Rate, For his own Statue call'd, and cheapned that: For, big with Self-conceit, he vainly thought, A Price much higher wou'd for that be sought: But he was baulk'd in his Vain-glorious Pride; The Artist, willing to take Money, cry'd, Sir, if you like to buy the others thus, I'll throw you this in for for an Overplus. The MORAL. ‘Vain-glorious Men, in Self-opinion great, ‘Believe themselves such in the World's Conceit: ‘But, in Attempts to gratifie their Pride, ‘By Disappointments, oft' are mortify'd: ‘They find they are not valu'd as they deem, ‘Their Worth is only in their own Esteem. FABLE VIII. The Wolf and Mastiff:Or, Liberty, the best Enjoyment. A Wolf, that rambl'd out e're Break-of-Day, Met in a Wood a Mastiff sleek and gay; And, after Time allow'd to kind Embrace, Admir'd to see him in such pamper'd Case. The Dog reply'd; My Master's tender Care, That still indulges me with plenteous Fare, And keeps me Nightly in a House inclos'd, Not to th' inclement Air, like you, expos'd: 'Tis that, my Friend, makes me thus Spruce and Clean, And gives me this surprising Air and Mien. Friend, said the Wolf, you're happy, I protest, With such a Master, and such Usage, bless'd: The Gods to me no greater Boon cou'd give, Than in such Plenty, and such Ease, to live. The Dog, who guess'd his Meaning, gave his Word To introduce him safely to his Lord; Provided he, on Honour, wou'd engage To temper and restrain his Native Rage. The Wolf agreed, and tow'rds the House they walk, And on the Way divert themselves with Talk. But soon the Light, which openly reveals The Faults which Night, in friendly Shades, conceals, Appear'd, and shew'd the Dog, that seem'd so fair, Had round his Neck a Circle worn, and bare. The Wolf, that did, with strange Surprize, conclude It was a Badge of hateful Servitude, Ask'd what it meant? To whom the Dog reply'd; My Native Fierceness once I cou'd not hide; But still on Friends, aswell as Strangers, flew, Bark'd at them much, and sometimes bit them too: For which my Lord, my Fury to restrain, Confin'd me to a Collar and a Chain; With strict Command, That I shou'd none molest, But Thieves, or Wolves, that did his Land infest: Thus I was civiliz'd, and what you see, Is the old Mark of my Captivity. At this Relation griev'd, the Wolf withdrew, Return'd his Thanks, and bid his Friend Adieu: You boast, said he, your happy Life in vain, While your High-keeping loads you with a Chain: Believe me, Friend, I will not change my State, To purchase Plenty at so dear a Rate: Enough the bounteous Gods will favour me With meaner Fare, and sweeter Liberty. The MORAL. ‘Prefer a Cottage, and its homely Fare, ‘To Palaces, and all the Dainties there: ‘In that you can no Injury receive, ‘But may secure, and your own Master live: ‘In these you suffer an abhorr'd Restraint, ‘Oppress'd with Wrongs, and not allow'd Complaint. FABLE IX. The Mariners:Or, Devotion misdirected. On the rough Ocean, with a tempest tost, Some Mariners expected to be lost: Their Hopes and Spirits equally grown faint, Each one address'd his own Tutelar Saint; Begg'd his Compassion, and invok'd his Aid, And with great Zeal (for in great Danger) pray'd. But one, more wise, or pious, than his Mates, Reprov'd their vain Petitions in their Straits: Alas! said he, you know not what you ask, While on the Saints you wou'd impose this Task: E're they to Heav'n can represent your Grief, We all shall perish, and be past Relief: Rather, in time, to their Great Ruler pray, Who can both sooner hear, and help, than they. Then to Jehovah they their Pray'rs address'd: Which done, the Billows fell, and Tempest ceas'd. The MORAL. ‘Why shou'd wise Man to Saints or Angels Pray, ‘Who are not to Command, but to Obey? ‘As if the God we serve, was not so near, ‘Or not so ready, and so kind to hear? ‘Those Creatures cannot like Compassion shew, ‘Nor Wonders, as their Great Creator do: ‘He knows our Wants before we vent our Grief, ‘And often helps us e're we ask Relief: ‘And our High-Priest, tho' plac'd above the Skies, ‘Retains a Sense of our Infirmities; ‘It is His Work alone to Intercede, ‘Who can, on our Behalf, His Merits plead. ‘Saints have Defects, which by His Eyes are seen, ‘Those Eyes, in which the Heavens are not clean: ‘And Angels, humbled by their Fellows Pride, ‘With Folly charg'd, their blushing Faces Hide. ‘How then can they on our Account'prevail, ‘Who for themselves, without His Help, wou'd fail? ‘To think a finite Saint, or Angel, hears, ‘At the same Instant, Myriads of Pray'rs, ‘Do's an Omniscience to them impute, ‘And robs Jehovah of that Attribute. ‘To think they can at once be ev'ry-where, ‘(Or else they cannot all Addresses hear) ‘Do's Omnipresence give to finite Things, ‘Which only suits the Boundless King of kings. ‘To think they can all our Petitions grant, ‘Supply, at once, Ten thousand sorts of Want; ‘Is to ascribe to them Omnipotence, ‘Tho' insufficient for their own Defence; ‘And do's th' Almighty of His Right deprive, ‘Who to no other will His Glory give. ‘They who created Beings thus adore, ‘And, in their Maker's Stead, his Works implore; ‘The Guilt of gross Idolatry contract, ‘Profaning him they worship, in the Act. ‘Angels, indeed, our due Regard shou'd have, ‘Because they serve us, tho' they cannot save: ‘And to the Saints just Honour shou'd be paid, ‘Whose holy Lives are our Examples made: ‘Who Worships either, or to either Prays, ‘To Them too much, to Heav'n too little, pays. ‘Let us their GOD, and ours, alone Adore; ‘His Pow'r is greater, and His Goodness more. FABLE X. The Sluggard:Or, Idleness finds Excuses. While early Students with the Sun arose, And to their Studies did themselves dispose: It was observ'd, that one neglectful Youth Indulg'd himself in Idleness and Sloth; And, as if Bed-rid, seldom left that Place, 'Till High-Noon Beams cast Blushes o'er his Face. His Fellows oft' the drowsie Sluggard blam'd: But he, who was not of his Fault asham'd, Reply'd; The Time, you think I lose, is spent In list'ning to an eager Argument: For pleasing Sleep no sooner quits my Eyes, But two in Female-dress before me rise; Brisk active Industry, and heavy Sloth, These both approach, and importune me both; One calls aloud, to raise my drousie Head, And waste no more my precious Hours in Bed, But to some useful Work my self apply: The other blames her Haste, and bids me lie; Where, by kind Warmth, and grateful Ease, secure, I neither Cold nor Labour shall endure: While they continue thus in warm Dispute, Nor can each other's Arguments confute; I, who to both Sides give impartial Heed, Lie unresolv'd, till they are both agreed; So keep my Bed as long as they Contend, In Expectation when the Strife will end. The MORAL. ‘Thus lazy Souls, who lie dissolv'd in Ease, ‘And find no Life, but the unactive, please; ‘Tho' slow to Bus'ness, and profuse of Time, ‘Are ready at Excuses for the Crime: ‘But while such Drones, who all Employment slight, ‘Oblige the Publick with no Benefit; ‘The useless Things are with neglect pass'd by, ‘Unvalu'd live, and unlamented die. FABLE XI. The Clown and Snake:Or, Once Injur'd, still Distrust. A churlish Rustick long a Snake had bred, Warm'd in his Breast, and at his Trencher fed; But, in an angry Mood, with Rage possess'd, He with an Axe attack'd the harmless Beast. Hurt as she was, she did with Life escape, And vow'd no more to venture such Mishap. The Boor reduc'd, believ'd that fatal Blow Had been the Cause of his ensuing Woe: He found the Snake, desir'd her to return, And told her how he for that Wrong did mourn; He promis'd too, she shou'd be better us'd: But wisely she desir'd to be excus'd: Into his House, she said, she durst not come, Who kept so broad, so sharp an Axe, at Home: For tho' kind Time had long remov'd her Pain, The sad Remembrance still did fresh remain. The MORAL. ‘The Injuries which gen'rous Souls receive, ‘They can, with boundless Charity, forgive: ‘But, warn'd by the Insults which first they bore, ‘Will run the Risque of being wrong'd, no more. FABLE XII. The Frogs:Or, Look before you Leap. Two Frogs, all Winter long, a Pool possess'd, And there enjoy'd themselves, and liv'd at Rest; But when the Sun's exhaling Beams grew high, They felt their Residence too hot and dry. Forc'd from this Seat, they for a new one try'd, And sound a Pit with Water well supply'd. The eager Female long'd to taste the Drink, And, with rash haste, was leaping from the Brink; 'Till, by the Heel, her Spouse his Lady caught, And stopt her with a more consid'rate Thought: Forbear, said he; for, shou'd this Water fail, 'Twon'd be our Fate to live and die in Jail. The MORAL. ‘In all Attempts, look forward to the End, ‘Let That the Act discourage, or commend; ‘Lest you, by thoughtless Haste, a Loss receive, ‘Which, tho' you might prevent, you can't retrieve. FABLE XIII. The Fisher:Or, Nothing out of Season. A Fisher, not experienc'd in his Trade, A new Device, for taking Fish, essay'd; With Pipes and Nets he to the River went, And hop'd his Musick wou'd his Pains prevent: Plac'd on the Bank, he sate and play'd a-while, As if that Method wou'd the Fish beguile: But when he found they wou'd not so be caught, He cast his Nets, and took a mighty Draught. The Scaly Pris'ners, as he took them out, Danc'd in the Net, and nimbly frisk'd about: Against whose ill-tim'd Measures he inveigh'd, And, with no little Indignation, said; See how the Fools, that let me Pipe alone, Begin their Galliards now the Tune is done. The MORAL. ‘All Things are, in their proper Season, best, ‘But intempestive Actions are a Jest; ‘And they, who such prepost'rous Works advance, ‘Play out of Time, and, without Musick, Dance. FABLE XIV. The Old-Man loth to Die:Or, Consider your Latter-End. A wretch, that on the World's uneasie Stage Had acted long, ev'n to decrepit Age; At the last Scene, thought he too soon had done; And, when Death call'd him, begg'd he might stay on. He said, His greatest Bus'ness was to do, And hop'd the Fates wou'd not surprise him so; But spare him, that he might Provision make for that long Journey which he was to take. Death ask'd him why he had that Work deferr'd, Since he had warn'd him oft' to be prepard. He answer'd, He had never seen his Face, And hop'd he wou'd allow him Days of Grace. But Death reply'd; You often saw me near, My Face in sev'ral Objects did appear; I have not only your Coævals slain, 'Till but a few, a very few remain; But Young-Men, Children, New-born Infants too, And all to caution and admonish you: All to remind you of your Mortal State, And that my Coming wou'd be sure, tho' late. When you perceiv'd your Eye-balls sink away, Your Hearing fail, and ev'ry Sense decay; When you discern'd your Teeth forsake their Place, Your wrinkl'd Forehead, and your meagre Face; Then you my Visage, in your own, might see, Which ev'ry Day was representing Me. When you observ'd your Blood begin to freeze, Your bowing Body, and your bending Knees; While scarce your feeble Legs your Weight cou'd bear; Did not these Symptoms tell you I was near? And can you yet pretend to be surpriz'd? Then Die, your Folly shou'd be thus chastis'd. If 'till to-morrow I your Life reprieve, You 'till to-morrow will deferr to Live: As you have done, still you, from Day to Day, Repentance and Amendment will delay. The MORAL. ‘Since we must Die, but where, is not declar'd, ‘We shou'd for Death's Approach be still prepar'd: ‘Our Life's uncertain; Time shou'd so be pass'd, ‘As if each Minute was to be our last: ‘Since on the Way in which our Lives we spend, ‘Our future Joys, or Miseries, depend; ‘They best for Heav'ns reserv'd Abodes prepare, ‘Who, Living, keep their Conversation there. ‘They who in Endless Pleasures wou'd on High ‘For ever Live, to Sin must daily Die. ‘If our Repentance we procrastinate, ‘Our good Desires at last, will be too late. ‘Virtue has got the Start in Life's swift Race, ‘And, to o'ertake her, we must mend our Pace; ‘Else, what we shou'd obtain, we ne'r shall find, ‘While she still keeps before, and we behind. FABLE XV. The Dog and Sheep:Or, Gainful Perjury soon swallow'd. A Dog impleads a Sheep, pretends a Debt Of ancient Standing, and not paid him yet. The Sheep denies it, in her own Defence, And bids the Dog produce his Evidence. He brings a Wolf, a Vulture, and a Kite, Who swear point-blank the Dog's Demands are right. Judgment thereon against the Sheep is giv'n; And she, wrong'd Beast! to Execution driv'n: While her Accusers at their Falshood smile, That gain'd them such a rich and easie Spoil. The MORAL. ‘False-Witness strongly backing False-Pretence, ‘Prevails to ruin injur'd Innocence; ‘And Villains soon such Testimonies give, ‘Who by their Perjuries expect to thrive. ‘When Things Untrue, in hope of gain, they swear, ‘They no Voir dire, nor Heav'n's just Wrath revere. FABLE XVI. The Fowler and Dove:Or, Harm watch, Harm catch. A Fowler, led Abroad, in hope of Game, Espy'd a Dove, and at the Bird took Aim; But in the Instant press'd a latent Snake, And lost his Life, while he the Dove's wou'd take: Thus was he justly fitted in his kind, And met the Fate he for the Bird design'd. The MORAL. ‘Thus Villains, to insidious Mischiefs prone, ‘Contriving others Ruin, meet their own: ‘And all the secret Treach'ry they design, ‘Is made abortive by a Countermine. FABLE XVII. The Blind Woman and Doctor:Or, A Rowland for an Oliver. An Aged Matron, who had lost her Sight, Was tir'd with living in perpetual Night; And with a Quack did, for a Sum, agree To be restor'd; but if no Cure, no Fee. The wary Spark, who, for such dubious Gains, Was not content to spend his Time and Pains; Resolv'd he wou'd himself before-hand pay, And still convey'd some Moveable away; 'Till, by his daily undiscover'd Theft, No Utensil in all the House was left. At last the Cure was by the Doctor wrought, But by the Patient still imperfect thought; For tho' he did her former Sight restore, She cou'd not see the Goods she saw before: And therefore, when he claim'd the Promise made, Refus'd him Payment, who too well was paid. His Action brought, she did the Contract own, But pleaded, That the Cure was still undone; And thus did Proof, from seeming Reason, draw, To bite the Biter, and evade the Law: Before my Sight, by Sickness, was destroy'd, I here a well-replenish'd House enjoy'd; Nor were my Goods delusive Fallacies, For then I saw them with these very Eyes: But now this filching Quack pretends I See, They are become invisible to me: And since my Furniture I cannot find, I either am, or had as good be Blind. The MORAL. ‘The sly Designer, that, to gain his Ends, ‘On Knav'ry, and fallacious Arts, depends; ‘Instructs the Men he injures in his Trade, ‘Who learn to Trick him, by the Tricks he play'd. ‘Thus they who Traps for others have prepar'd, ‘Are in their own Contrivances insnar'd; ‘O'er-shoot themselves in all their Policies, ‘And suffer by the Mischiefs they devise. FABLE XVIII. The Ants and Grass-hopper:Or, Provide for your self. Some frugal Ants, that, with unweary'd Pain, Had fill'd their Stores, in Summer-time, with Grain; When Winter's pinching Season was begun, Expos'd their hoarded Treasure to the Sun. A Grass-hopper, that saw them thus supply'd, While he lack'd Food, thro' Idleness and Pride; Besought them to commiserate his Grief, And, from their Plenty, grant him some Relief. The Ants enquir'd how he himself apply'd, When he had Time, and shou'd his Stock provide; Or if in Sloth he the kind Season spent, When he, by Labour, might his Wants prevent. He answer'd them; He then employ'd his Care To chear the Work-man, and the Traveller: The pleasing Melody he made all Day, Shortned one's Labour, and the other's Way. They said, He much Improvidence had shewn, To mind their Bus'ness, and neglect his own; And, since he took no Pains to gather Meat, It was but just, he shou'd have none to eat: He that did others with his Songs revive, Shou'd now, with Dancing, keep himself alive. The MORAL. ‘In Youth and Strength we shou'd our Pains engage, ‘To make Provision for our Feeble Age; ‘That Hoary Winter will require a Store, ‘Which we shall seek too late, if not before: ‘And he that does not for himself provide, ‘Shou'd not by others hope to be supply'd: ‘For what the Diligent, by Labour, gain, ‘Wou'd on a Slothful Wretch be spent in vain. FABLE XIX. The Priest and Apples:Or, Hunger, the best Sauce. A Priest, who in good Eating took delight, And serv'd no God, like his nice Appetite; Was by a Man (who wou'd his Favour win, And hop'd thereby he might more cheaply Sin) Invited to partake a Christmas-Feast, At which he meant to make a hearty Guest. Mean-time he fancy'd Dishes he thought good, And by Anticipation chew'd the Cud; 'Till the wish'd Day of Banqueting was come, And call'd the joyful Epicure from Home. With Expectation big, he went Abroad, And found a Hoard of Apples on his Road: But (tho' for Meat his craving Stomach press'd) He cou'd not such a homely Treat digest: The Delicacies he did soon expect, Made him that mean, tho' present Fare, reject. And, in Contempt, the supercilious Brute Play'd a Dog-trick, and piss'd upon the Fruit. As thence he mov'd to the expected Place, A new-ris'n River stopt his eager Pace: Afraid to drown, he durst no farther ride, But, for his Safety, once his Guts deny'd: Yet sadly at the Disappointment griev'd, That had his Belly and his Hopes deceiv'd. Now his impatient Hunger pinch'd him sore, And made him covet what he scorn'd before: Back in full Gallop to the Place he went Where first the Apples did themselves present; And there the Fruit, on the fame Spot of Ground, In the sweet Pickle he had left it, found. By pressing Hunger urg'd, he long'd to eat, Tho' his nice Palate disapprov'd the Meat: This made him squeamish, and abhor the Food, That strongly recommended it for good: But Hunger, that makes all things relish well, Prevail'd, and, without scruple, to't he fell. The MORAL. ‘While pamper'd Gluttons wholsom Fruit despise, ‘Amidst full Tables, and Varieties; ‘The Men with Hunger pin'd, and thrifty Souls, ‘No poinant Sauces crave, nor Golden Bowls: ‘On what suffices Nature, they can Feast, ‘And relish homely Fare, as meanly dress'd. ‘Necessity, whose Empire all must own, ‘Makes what it recommends, go sweetly down: ‘And in our selves we find the Proverb true, ‘Which lets us know what hungry Dogs will do. FABLE XX. The Birds and Beasts:Or, Once False, still Mistrusted. The Birds and Beasts their Strength in Battle try'd, They press'd, and oft' were press'd on either side: The Bot, who did his Fellows Weakness fear, Deserted to the Beasts, and Listed there. But soon the Birds made their Assailants yield, And, by the Eagle's Conduct, gain'd the Field: Then in Court-Martial doom'd the Renegade, Who basely had the Common Cause betray'd, To live all Day in some dark Hole confin'd, And be no longer reckon'd of their Kind. The MORAL. ‘He who his Friend's Misfortune will not bear, ‘Deserves in his Success as little Share: ‘Such base Desertion, makes his hateful Sight ‘Unfit for Humane Prospect, and the Light: ‘For 'tis a Maxim, Always to Distrust ‘The faithless Wretch who once has prov'd Unjust. ‘Since the base Soul, whom Honour cou'd not bind, ‘No Hostage for his future Faith can find. ‘But he, whose Friendship, free from Selfish Aim, ‘Remains, in all Vicissitudes, the same; ‘(As the sure Needle never fails its Pole, ‘Tho' Tempests rage, and swelling Billows roll) ‘Deserv'dly is by all Mankind approv'd, ‘And as he still is Faithful, still is lov'd: ‘His Steady Soul, in desp'rate Hazards try'd, ‘Makes all secure, who in his Truth confide. FABLE XXI. Mercury's Preparation:Or, A Tradesman, a Lyar. Jove wou'd to each Artificer impart The Mystery of his respective Art; And bid his Chymist, Mercury, with Care, A Lying Powder for that End prepare. The Composition made, and pulveriz'd, He gave to each a Quantum that suffic'd: But had, thro' Haste, the Gentle Craft forgot, Or thought, at least, 'twas what they needed not. However, to atone for the Neglect, And shew it was not caus'd by Disrespect; He swept the Mortar of what stuck behind, And to those Sparks a double Dose assign'd. Hence it proceeds that Tradesmen Lye so fast, But those, of all, go most beyond the Last. The MORAL. ‘The mighty Secret, how to Lye, and Cheat, ‘Makes ev'ry Tradesman in his Art compleat: ‘But most, the Shooe-maker is given to Stretch, ‘And will his Conscience, like his Leather, retch: ‘Will Praise his Work, tho' conscious that he Mocks; ‘Will Swear it Fits them, who are in his Stocks. FABLE XXII. The Farmer and Landlord:Or, Avarice Disappointed. A grateful Farmer, in his Rented Ground, A Tree, well laden with choice Apples, found: He pull'd the Fruit, and, big with pleasing Thought, The Present to his City Landlord brought. Citt found the Apples of a gen'rous Kind, And at his Tenant's Benefit-repin'd: Then Order'd, That the Tree he so approv'd, Shou'd to his City Orchard be remov'd. The Tree, grown old, did not the Soil abide, But, when transplanted, wither'd soon, and dy'd. The Landlord, at this Disappointment, griev'd, And own'd, his Folly had his Hopes deceiv'd: It was enough, (had he his Int'rest known) To eat the Fruit, and let the Tree alone. The MORAL. ‘Thus Men, when blinded by their Avarice, ‘Believe themselves, in their vain Projects, wise: ‘But such Projectors soon their Folly find, ‘Impov'rish'd by the Means for Wealth design'd. ‘But he, who wisely limits his Desires, ‘Seeks what is fit, and, what he seeks, acquires. FABLE XXIII. The One-Ey'd Deer:Or, Fruitless Precaution. While browzing by the Sea, a One-Ey'd Deer, That thought she cou'd from thence no Danger fear, Did, for her Safety, cautiously provide, And tow'rds the Land still turn the Seeing-side. A roving Fowler, whom she did not dread, Found her Blind-side, and shot her thro' the Head. The Beast thus wounded, her ill Fate bewail'd, To find how all her vain Precaution fail'd: Since where she fear'd most Harm, she none endur'd; But suffer'd most, where she seem'd most secur'd. The MORAL. ‘Thus Things, whence most we Danger apprehend, ‘By wondrous Turns, our Fortunes most befriend: ‘While those in which we greatest Trust repose, ‘Deceive our Caution, and procure our Woes. FABLE XXIV. The Fly and Ant:Or, Calumny retorted. A Fly upbraids an Ant, compares their Race, That Her's was Noble, and the Pismire's Base; That She Aloft on active Wings did flie, While T'other on the Ground did grov'ling lie: That She in Courts convers'd; the Other Slave, Born to Contempt, sculk'd in an humble Cave: That She on Choice of costly Dishes fed; The Other meanly far'd, and scarce had Bread: She took no Pains to be thus nobly serv'd; The Other, tho' a constant Drudge, was starv'd. The Ant, the Meanness of her Birth confess'd; But, with that Meanness pleas'd, averr'd it best: The Vagrant Fly, she own'd, rov'd ev'ry-where, But had no Being whither to repair: While She a settl'd House-keeper was found, And never stroll'd from her Paternal Ground: Nor envy'd She the Fly's Ragoo's and Wine, Who cou'd, more pleas'd, on Pulse and Water dine; And was delighted with the Pains and Care She took to get her self that homely Fare: Whereas the Fly was Insolent and Rude, Did into ev'ry Dish and Cup intrude; The Emblem of detested Sloth was known, That liv'd on other's Labour, not her own: She was caress'd, commended, and belov'd, And her Example by the World approv'd: She never found her mean Provision scant, And, as she ne'er Abounded, ne'er did Want: But the unthrifty, idle, useless Fly, In Winter wou'd be forc'd to Beg, or Die: Tho' she was now too hot and haughty grown, She then wou'd find her Courage cool'd, and down; Then unregarded, and despis'd, wou'd fall, As nauseous as her vile Original. The MORAL. ‘While Noisie Fools their own Indowments vaunt, ‘And, in Contempt, upbraid their Neighbour's Want; ‘The Loose-tongu'd Blabs, who, without Wit or Fear, ‘Speak what they shou'd not, what they wou'd not, hear: ‘Recrimination do's their Malice foil, ‘And their Invectives on themselves recoil. FABLE XXV. The Prodigal and Swallow:Or, A Dream of a Dry Summer. A rich young Spend-thrift, left his Father's Heir, (Who bought the Fortune, he bequeath'd him, dear) In the high-road to Poverty made haste, And, what was long a gath'ring, soon did waste: His whole Estate he threw away at Dice, (The Fools first In-let to all other Vice) The Ord'naries and the Groom-Porter's us'd, 'Till to one thread-bare Sute he was reduc'd. Thus Shabby, and thus Moneyless, the Spark, Instead of Dinner, took the Air o'th' Park; Where, walking pensive, and lamenting sore, (Not that he lost so much, but cou'd no more) Before him an untimely Swallow flew; And, from her Flight, he good Presages drew; Dreamt of Warm Weather, and that very Day To Gaming fell, and play'd his Coat away. But soon he found himself in a Mistake, And that One Swallow do's no Summer make; He found the Bird too soon had left her Home, And a Reserve of Winter was to come; Then, numb'd with pinching Frosts, and piercing Winds, In as bad Plight he the false Omen finds, Pleas'd, that she, by her self, so ill was serv'd, Since he, by her delusive Hast, was starv'd. The MORAL. ‘So Fools, who by fair Promises are fed, ‘And into mighty Expectations led; ‘Their little Stock, in hope of greater, spend, ‘While some deluding Courtier they attend. ‘Thus, in Pursuit of Wealth, to Want reduc'd, ‘And, by Pretence of Kindnesses, abus'd; ‘When with Dependance and Attendance tir'd, ‘And ne'er the nearer to the Boon desir'd: ‘Deceiv'd by faithless Words, they miss their Aim, ‘And find it all their Comfort to Exclaim: ‘Then they, with heavy Heart, and, what is worse, ‘The greater Burden of an empty Purse; ‘To their obscure Abodes make their Retreat, ‘Ruin'd, by trusting to a specious Cheat. FABLE XXVI. The Horse and Stag:Or, Liberty resign'd. A Horse and Stag a desp'rate Combat fought; The Horse, o'er-pow'r'd, a Man's Assistance sought: Thus reinforc'd, again he took the Field, And soon the Vanquish'd made the Victor yield; But found small Pleasure from his Conquest grow, By his Ally worse us'd, than by his Foe: He was compell'd for ever to submit To a rank Rider, and a servile Bit. The MORAL. ‘Thus he, who wou'd afflicting Want avoid, ‘By more oppressive Plenty is destroy'd; ‘And while, with eager Haste, he Wealth pursues, ‘Is made a Slave to what he dares not use: ‘But do's too dearly the Enjoyment buy, ‘For which he must resign his Liberty. FABLE XXVII. The Trumpeter:Or, Abettors share the Guilt. A Swoln-cheek'd Trumpeter, whose fatal Breath Had oft' excited others to their Death, While he aloft, and free from Danger, stood, And thought himself not guilty of their Blood; In Fight, by the prevailing Enemy, Was made a Pris'ner, and Condemn'd to Die. The trembling Captive pleaded Innocence, And strongly urg'd, He had not giv'n Offence; Since he in Blood and Wounds took no Delight, And his Employment was, to Sound, not Fight; Nor cou'd they sure to him impute their Harms, Whose hurtless Trumpet was his only Arms. To whom the Foe; This Subterfuge you use, Do's aggravate the Guilt you wou'd excuse: Since you, who own you are not us'd to Fight, Do others to the bloody Field excite. The MORAL. ‘They who advise the Ills which others act, ‘An equal Guilt, a diff'rent Way contract: ‘As when ill Counsellors misguide a Prince, ‘They bear the just Reproach of his Offence; ‘And err as much, by leading him astray, ‘As he, who, rul'd by them, mistook his Way: ‘While they persuade him to infringe the Law, ‘They on themselves its heavy'st Censures draw. FABLE XXVIII. The Beasts and Fishes:Or, Remote Alliances, useless. The Beasts, resolv'd they wou'd the Birds invade, A shrict Alliance with the Fishes made; Much in their Scaly Armour did confide, And fear'd no Foe, while they were on their Side. But when the Time to take the Field drew near, The new Allies did not in Camp appear; But from Land-service pray'd to be excus'd, For they had only to the Sea been us'd. This was the Cause their Forces were not sent, They cou'd not Fight out of their Element. The MORAL. ‘Princes in vain seek such remote Allies, ‘Who, in their Need, can send them no Supplies: ‘The safest Treaties, with near States are made, ‘Whose ready Troops can bring expected Aid. FABLE XXIX. Jupiter:Or, Lust and Modesty incompatible Jove, to Compleat his Creature Man, impress'd All requisite Affections in his Breast; But, in the Throng, he had omitted Shame, And knew not how to introduce the Dame: He found, her Presence there was much requir'd; A needful Virtue, tho' not oft' desir'd; And bid her justle in among the Crow'd: Whereat she blush'd, and the Command withstood: But, urg'd by Jove, reply'd; I will Obey, If you will keep that Monster, Lust, away: For he will all the Microcosm inflame With burning Passions, which I blush to name: And if he enters, I must straight retire, As Men from Houses that are all on-Fire. The MORAL. ‘Where Modesty vouchsafes to fix her Seat, ‘Lust must withdraw, or she will soon retreat: ‘The diff'rent Passions will not brook one Sphere, ‘And never in each other's Bounds appear: ‘For an immortal Quarrel they maintain, ‘And Converse, by Antipathy, refrain. ‘Whoever is to Modesty enclin'd, ‘Do's against Lust a strong Cathartick find; ‘And he, whose loose Desires by Lust are sway'd, ‘Do's Modesty, with open Force, invade: ‘Thus as, to either, Men themselves devote, ‘They chuse a Poison, or an Antidote. FABLE XXX. The Impostor-Priest:Or, 'Ware Geese, when the Fox Preaches. A Fox, that long, against his Will, kept Fast, And was in pressing Want of some Repast; Crept to a Hovel where much Poultry fed, But found them safely roosted in their Shed: Tho' his Chops water'd to be at the Fowl, He cou'd not reach them, for his Heart and Soul: In vain he mighty Friendship did pretend, And, with sweet Words, desir'd them to descend. They, who knew all his seeming Love a Cheat, Refus'd, and not a Hen wou'd leave her Seat. Reynard, who found he cou'd not thus prevail, Resolv'd on Measures which but rarely fail: In Priestly Vestments he himself disguis'd, A Garb for which th' unworthy Wearer's pris'd; And then, with Look demure and sanctify'd, He to the Pullen thus himself apply'd: Sisters, My Zeal, which seeks not yours, but you, Has made me seek this pious Interview; That you your Sins may to remembrance call, And I may Shrive you, and Absolve you all: Then leave, ah! quickly leave your lazy Beds, And take my Hands and Blessing on your Heads. Th' unwary Hens, deluded by his Gown, And Sanctimonious Cant, came quickly down; But found the Hypocritick Zealot's Drift, Aim'd rather at their Ruin than their Shrift: And thus the Fools, by his False Shews betray'd, Their Lives, for Hopes of Absolution, paid. The MORAL. ‘Religion, Villany's successful Stale, ‘Do's with its Name, to cheat Mankind, prevail: ‘And a Pretence to Goodness, tho unjust, ‘Extorts Belief, and rarely meets Distrust. ‘Where such dissembl'd Sanctity appears, ‘The chous'd Admirer no Delusion fears; ‘But those, who most deceive him, most do's love, ‘And thinks them honestest, who falsest prove. ‘Hence 'tis that Knaves, for Irreligion's sake, ‘Too often the Religious Habit take; ‘For with that Garb they cloak their Villanies, ‘And, undetected, Sin in that Disguise: ‘So, unsuspected in the Rev'rend Gown, ‘Blood gain'd admittance to, and stole the Crown. FABLE XXXI. The Old Man, his Son, and Ass:Or, No pleasing all Men. An Aged Sire, frosted with Hoary Hairs, And a young Stripling in his Blooming Years, Went to a Fair, where Gazers seldom fail, And drove an Empty Ass, design'd for Sale. The People, who observ'd them on the Road, And saw the useless Beast without a Load; Laugh'd at their Folly, That, since both were tir'd, Each did neglect the Help his Age requir'd: And said, They spar'd in vain the abler Beast, 'Twas reasonable one shou'd ride, at least. The tender Father gave his Son the Place, And by his Side walk'd on with sober Pace: But this the murm'ring Croud severely blames, Condemns the Senior, and the Youngster shames; Since, without just Regard to either's Age, They had misplac'd the Rider and the Page: They said, The Sire shou'd ride, whom Years oppress'd; The Son was stronger, and cou'd foot it best. The Youth alights, and lets his Father ride, And walks, with humble Rev'rence, by his Side: But this as little Satisfaction gave, The fickle Mob the censur'd Parent slave; Say, He shou'd walk, whose Limbs were tough and strong, And mount the Lad, who was but soft and young. The Sire, to please them, takes his Son behind: But at this Course the People more repin'd; And said, The Ass, which with such Weight they tir'd, Was not their own, but borrow'd sure, or hir'd. The Old Man, with their diff'rent Censures teaz'd, Since neither Riding, neither Walking, pleas'd, Nor Mounting both, nor driving both the Ass, Cou'd through the Throng, without Reflection, pass; (In hope they wou'd at last be satisfy'd) The Ass's Feet with Cords together ty'd, And, on a Pole, on both their Shoulders laid, They through the Fair the Raree-Show convey'd. But this ridiculous Attempt, when seen, Extremely tickl'd the Beholders Spleen; Who thus made merry at the Father's Cost, Tax'd both with Folly, but the Father most: For tho' the Boy, in Duty, did submit; They said, The Senior shou'd have had more Wit. He, (vex'd at their Reproach) with just Disdain, Resolv'd no more to humour them in vain; But this last Way, to 'scape their Laughter, found, He in a Pond, the Ass, that caus'd it, drown'd. Thus, striving to please All, and pleasing None, He lost his useful Beast, and was undone. The MORAL. ‘He, who his Actions by Opinion rules, ‘Condemns himself to live a Slave to Fools: ‘To humour those whose Humours disagree, ‘Is to attempt Impossiblity. ‘The Mob, by various Sentiments inclin'd, ‘Is fickle, and uncertain as the Wind: ‘Each has a diff'rent Object of his Love, ‘And some despise what other some approve. ‘Whoe'er himself to sure such Tempers strains, ‘Do's to no Purpose lavish Time and Pains. ‘Let Reason and Discretion guide thy Ways, ‘Thou need'st not care what Fools condemn, or praise. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>