<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Boyse, Samuel, 1708-1749</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Boyse, Samuel, 1708-1749</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">boyse samuel 1708 1749</field>
      <field name="author_text">Boyse, Samuel, 1708-1749</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1730's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_2.0350.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1735</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464894</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Verses ; Sacred to the Memory of the Right Honourable, Charles, Earl of Peterborough, and Monmouth [by Samuel Boyse</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Verses ; Sacred to the Memory of the Right Honourable, Charles, Earl of Peterborough, and Monmouth [by Samuel Boyse</field>
      <field name="title_facet">verses</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">verses</field>
      <field name="title_text">Verses ; Sacred to the Memory of the Right Honourable, Charles, Earl of Peterborough, and Monmouth [by Samuel Boyse</field>
      <field name="year_display">1735</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1735</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1735</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464894&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464894&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Boyse, Samuel, 1708-1749&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;boyse samuel 1708 1749&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Verses ; Sacred to the Memory of the Right Honourable, Charles, Earl of Peterborough, and Monmouth [by Samuel Boyse&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;verses&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1735&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1735&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Boyse, Samuel&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1708&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1749&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Verses&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Sacred to the Memory of the Right Honourable, Charles, Earl of Peterborough, and Monmouth [by Samuel Boyse]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Edinburgh&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by W. Cheyne&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1735&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0527&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;16 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Verses&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Sacred to the Memory of the Right Honourable, Charles, Earl of Peterborough, and Monmouth [by Samuel Boyse]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 22 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">? Non ego te meis Chartis inornatum fileri Totve tuos patiar labores, Impune, Mordantî! carpere lividas Obliviones, fuit animus tibi Rerumque prudens, &amp; secundis Temporibus, dubiisque rectus: Vindex avaræ fraudis, &amp; abstinens Ducentis ad se cuncta Pecuniæ: Consulque non unius anni, Sed quoties bonus atque fidus Judex honestum prætulit utili, &amp; Rejecit alto dona nocentium Vultù, &amp; per obstantes catervas Explicuit sua victor arma. Hor. To Her Grace, HENRIETTA, Dutchess of GORDON. [When press'd by Fate inferior Mortals bow] Thro' all his glorious Life, (one perfect Plan!) Becoming Grace, and proper Action ran; The Piece, by Virtue's equal Hand was wrought, Mix'd with no Crime, and shaded with no Fault. Mr. Prior. When press'd by Fate inferior Mortals bow, The Muse disdains to notice vulgar Woe; Well may the World such shadowy Forms forget, That rise unnotic'd and unheeded set! But when the heav'nly Bodies feel a Shade, When Darkness o'er the Orb of Day is spread; Wide as the Suff'ring flies the vast Concern, Ev'n savage Lands unusual Terrors learn; Benighted Nations join the Loss to mourn, And wish the friendly Planet's kind Return! Illustrious Princess!—whose acknowledg'd Worth, And gentle Influ'nce warms the gelid North; Thro' Nature's Wilds directs its cheerful Ray, And pours o'er Solitude extensive Day! Forgive the Muse—perhaps too fondly rude, That on your justest Sorrow would intrude; Would deck with Flow'rs illustrious Mordaunt's Herse, And with his Name adorn her lasting Verse! Resume, Urania, then, the heav'nly Lyre; Reflect what Notes such Virtues must inspire, As in unrivall'd Mordaunt full combin'd, Produc'd a Hero of the genuine Kind! Wake ev'ry Grace,—enliven ev'ry String! Think what your Theme is,—and to whom you sing! Forgive me, Goddess, to direct your Lays— 'Tis yours the glorious Monument to raise, Sacred to future Fame, and Peterborough's Praise. See Britain!—lovely Mourner! bend her Head, View from her Eyes the pearly Passion shed! Her blooming Charms with sudden Languor veil'd, Her trembling Hand scarce bears her radiant Shield! Distinguish'd Grief!—by which the Goddess owns Her foremost Heroes, and her noblest Sons. How well he merited the mutual Name, Witness the Voice of fair recording Fame! Soon in his Mind the God-like Passion sprung, Warm'd all his Breast, and fir'd his pow'rful Tongue! And which to Africk's arid Wastes of Light, His early Virtue wing'd its piercing Flight; From the dark Herd that never Freedom knew, The lasting Love of Liberty he drew. So the wise Sage, exploring Nature's Pow'r, Extracts from Poison a restoring Cure. His opening Years to riper Mankind trace, And view him emulate his martial Race! Survey the Chief advanc'd by Nassau's Side, In Triumph o'er the smiling Ocean ride! While kind to Britain, the propitious Gale Curls the blue Main, and fills the whit'ning Sail! Till Albion's Cliffs salute his joyful Sight, Firm like his Temper, as his Genius bright! Friend to the Prince, behold him touch the Strand, And joy to aid great William's saving Hand. But Worth like Mordaunt's scorn'd to be confin'd, His Merit was for wider Bounds design'd! Advancing Years display'd a brighter Scene, Expressive of the Day that shone within; All that could for th'heroic Turn of Mind, Valour with Conduct equally combin'd, Goodness with Grandeur amicably join'd, All strengthen'd with the Love of human Kind! When his bright Sov'reign call'd his Virtue forth, To greater Trials and superior Birth; And when she nam'd the Austrian Prince her Son, Bid Mordaunt's Counsels lead him to the Throne. By Fate's Decree and Anna's high Command, He quits the Calmness of his native Land; Arm'd with the Thunder Britain's Navy bears, On proud Iberia's Coast the Chief appears! Rich Barcelone reduc'd, submiss, and low, Trembles and sinks beneath his certain Blow; But from his Goodness taught to fear no Harm, Blesses the Mercy of his saving Arm; Owns the Distinction of the British Sword, And shines to Liberty and Charles restor'd! From thence, how did his all-informing Soul, Active as Light, invigorate the Whole? How did he, calm, the troubled Scene survey, And learn contending Parties to obey! As from Olympus, Jove's inspective Ken Directs, unseen, the busy Ways of Men; From Montseratte so Mordaunt, cool, beheld The Chances of the undecided Field; And, by the secret Force of Wisdom taught, Plan'd all the future Miracles he wrought: Wonders! that, were they justly but reveal'd, Might vie with those of Blenheim's boasted Field, And make Ramillia's lessen'd Glories yield! See the vindictive Gaul collect his Ire, And aim at Mordaunt's Conquest all his Fire. Round Barcelone behold the gath'ring Storm Darken the Ocean, and the Skies deform! Ev'n now, vain Hope! their proud insulting Eyes Survey'd the Monarch, with the Town, their Prize: Ev'n wav'ring Loyalty began to fear! The Help seem'd distant,—and the Danger near! When Mordaunt, like some Guardian-Angel bright, With unexpected Succour came in Sight: Aw'd by that Arm, whose Pow'r too well they knew, Confus'd, dismay'd, the hostile Troops withdrew; Great Lewis' proud Device, th'astonish'd Sun, Eclips'd, on the relinquish'd Camp look'd down: While grateful Charles embrac'd the British Peer, And crown'd with Praise his blest Deliverer! Short is the Boast of the destructive Spear, The Cords of Love outlast the Chains of Fear; Well Mordaunt knew this Heart-alluring Charm, His Virtue gain'd more Triumphs than his Arm! Since God-like Scipio left Iberia's Shore, She ne'er had felt a milder Victor's Pow'r; He, like that Hero, vanquish'd all he saw, By fair Perswasion, Reason's noblest Law; Yet great as was the Roman, good, and brave, His Aim, howe'er disguis'd, was to enslave: While nobler Motives reign'd in Mordaunt's Breast, To save a Land by Servitude distress'd! To spread new Blessings where his Arms had gone, And make each Nation happy as his own! By slow Degrees most Leaders purchase Fame, But Mordaunt carried Conquest in his Name! In his great Actions Fortune claim'd small Share, What War oft desolates, 'twas his to spare: His Trophies still were of the spotless Kind, Britannia's Pride! the Welfare of Mankind! By him inspir'd, how did the Ardour spread? (For Liberty oppress'd but wants a Head) As gently when the Eastern Breeze descends, On fair Sicilia's Coast, the Harvest bends; So mov'd, as Mordaunt's Counsels could inspire, Delighted Nations catch'd the spreading Fire! Scarce twice the Sun perform'd his annual Round, When Mordaunt's Glory seem'd compleatly crown'd. All of Iberia's ever blooming Soil, That feels the rosy Morn's auspicious Smile, To Charles restor'd the British Chief confess'd, And while they felt the Ease, the Donor bless'd. Oh, had the Fates, that watch'd o'er Europe's Good, A longer Date to his Command allow'd! Ne'er Bourbon's Race had fill'd the Throne of Spain, Ne'er British Blood defil'd Almanza's Plain! Ill-omen'd Day!—sad Muse the rest conceal, O'er dark Reflection draw the silent Veil; Like the great Object of thy plaintive Lays, “Forbear to mention what thou canst not praise. Least conscious Britain tremble at the Sound, “And feel the Smart of that eternal Wound! Convey the Chief to fair Hesperia's Shore, With milder Glories drest, and gentler Pow'r: And let the peaceful Olive softly bind The Laurels, Fame had round his Temples twin'd! Let those politer Courts, whose tender Eye In foreign Objects can no Beauty spy, In Mordaunt's Character, reluctant, own Their Clime in Manners, as in Arts, outdone; Confess such mingling Qualities combin'd, The Hero's Truth, and Statesman's Temper join'd, Heighten'd with native Dignity of Mind! So when abroad the generous Eagle flies, And vindicates the Empire of the Skies, The feather'd Tribes submissive bend to Earth, And pay their Homage to superior Worth! Compass'd with Honour and unblemish'd Praise The Hero's justest Recompence is Ease! Return'd, with Glory, to Britannia Home, What Marks of Favour shall his Sovereign doom, For all his Triumphs past, and Toils to come? To Windsor's Dome the gallant Chief she calls, There in great Edward's richly-trophy'd Walls, She gives the azure Band, and bids him wear Her spotless Emblem! the distinguish'd Star! Well did the radiant Mark become his Side, Stain'd with no Guilt, and darken'd with no Pride! The Race of Fame so honourably run, And Cesar's Motto made so oft his own: 'Twas fit that Mordaunt, in Britannia's Breast, Unenvy'd Peace, and learned Ease should taste; (Such as for all her Patriots she ordains, Source of their Toils, and Crown of all their Pains!) While his past Actions shed a placid Ray, And form'd around him Fame's unclouded Day. Oh honoured Pope! to whom indulgent Heav'n Has every Muse-like Art and Virtue giv'n; With all thy Wish, a mod'rate Fortune, blest, Acquir'd with Honour, and with Peace possest. Be yours the matchless Hero's Worth to tell; Well may you picture what you know so well! In tuneful Addison's recording Page Shall Marlbro's Actions live to latest Age? In Prior's Verse shall Nassau's Glory shine? Oh be the Care of Mordaunt's Virtue thine! Be yours his fair Memoirs consign'd to scan, And to the World produce the valu'd Plan; Think this a Tribute to your Country due, Which she can justly hope alone from you! Oft in your Grotto has the Hero stray'd, Modell'd your Gardens, and your Walks survey'd; Pleas'd in your modest Converse to unbend, And own Britannia's Virgil for his Friend. As great Vespasian, when his Fate drew nigh, Pronounc'd a General should in Action die! So the strong Temper of great Mordaunt's Mind Refus'd the lingring Fate of human Kind; By Destinies unerring Impulse led To view the Climes where once his Glory spread; He met, unmov'd, his Life's concluding Hour, And dy'd where he had triumph'd oft before! Proud of the sacred Treasure which they bring, See the chos'n Squadron spread the Canvass-Wing! O'er the dividing Sea protected sweep; Ev'n Mordaunt's Ashes yet command the Deep! Britannia sad surveys the Sails appear, Some secret Presage raises all her Fear; Too soon she finds her well-form'd Terror true, When the selected Vessel comes in View; Never as yet her subject Ocean bore A Charge more precious to her sov'reign Shore; Than Peterborough's ever honour'd Urn, Whose Loss her latest History shall mourn. Contract thy Views, ambitious Muse, forbear, For Mordaunt's Glory asks a nobler Air; Finish the fond, but too protracted Song, Tremble to think imperfect Praise is wrong! Yet if all-gracious Gordon deign to smile, If, candid, she approve the well-meant Toil; If, generous, she the slender Wreath receive, The Muse for Mordaunt's Urn aspired to weave! The lasting Favour shall o'erpay the Pain, And make her own she has not sung in vain. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>