<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Tupper, Martin Farquhar, 1810-1889</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Tupper, Martin Farquhar, 1810-1889</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">tupper martin farquhar 1810 1889</field>
      <field name="author_text">Tupper, Martin Farquhar, 1810-1889</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1850's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.2314.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1854</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:467385</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">A dozen ballads for the times about White Slavery ; By the Author of "Proverbial Philosophy" [i.e. M. F. Tupper</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">A dozen ballads for the times about White Slavery ; By the Author of "Proverbial Philosophy" [i.e. M. F. Tupper</field>
      <field name="title_facet">dozen ballads for the times about white slavery</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">dozen ballads for the times about white slavery</field>
      <field name="title_text">A dozen ballads for the times about White Slavery ; By the Author of "Proverbial Philosophy" [i.e. M. F. Tupper</field>
      <field name="year_display">1854</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1854</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1854</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467385&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467385&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Tupper, Martin Farquhar, 1810-1889&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;tupper martin farquhar 1810 1889&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;A dozen ballads for the times about White Slavery ; By the Author of "Proverbial Philosophy" [i.e. M. F. Tupper&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;dozen ballads for the times about white slavery&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1854&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1854&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Tupper, Martin Farquhar&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1810&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1889&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;A dozen ballads for the times about White Slavery&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By the Author of "Proverbial Philosophy" [i.e. M. F. Tupper]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;T. Bosworth&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1854&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp3993&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;34 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;A dozen ballads for the times about White Slavery&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By the Author of "Proverbial Philosophy" [i.e. M. F. Tupper]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 41 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted; verse reproduced elsewhere in the English Poetry Full-Text Database omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">BALLADS ABOUT WHITE SLAVERY. I. THE FIELD SERF. Galloping out on a drizzly day To see the foxhounds meet And huntsmen take their reckless way Over the newsown wheat, I came to an old man, stricken and grey, In soak'd and tattered smock, Hoeing the turnips out of the clay For farmer Close's flock. And I pull'd up straight, to talk with the man, For it is but a prudent part To show poor folks whenever we can Their betters are blest with a heart: The steward may oppress, and the farmer may grind, And Squire gets all the scorn,— But the natural bent of a gentleman's mind Is ever to help the forlorn. And how the poor fellow's weatherworn cheek Ran down with gratitude there, To hear the voice of kindliness speak, And touch the shilling rare; And yet—he had given to me much more Than I to him could have given, For his story touch'd my heart to its core, And I heard the praise of Heaven! For years threescore, or five or six more,— He didn't know right well,— How he had toiled, and muck'd and moil'd, He couldn't justly tell;— He only remember'd that, young or old, He had ever been, so to speak, In midsummer heat or Christmas cold, Half starved, aweary, and weak! As a ragged urchin scaring the birds With lungs all sore and hoarse, As a farm-lad tending the pigs and herds, And feeding on food as coarse,— As a labourer, earning never enough For bairns, and self, and wife,— And ever with plenty of bitter and rough, But none of the honey of life! No books, no rest, no pleasures, no treats, But aches, and labour, and care, No earthly excitements, nor heavenly sweets, But ignorance bald and bare, In the same dull fields from cradle to grave To spend life's dismal span,— Why,—this is to live as a Cuban slave, And not as an English Man! II. THE FACTORY SLAVE. Pale, and shabby, and looking so ill, Hungry and cold and wet, On a winter's morning going to mill The factory-child I met: All the day long among perilous wheels, His duty it was to tend Spindles and jennies and shuttles and reels, A toil without an end, For iron never grows weary, nor feels, Nor ever made child its friend! One among hundreds was that boy Who never had known of a home nor a toy, But work'd without hope, and liv'd without joy! Stunted, sorrowful, looking so old, Blear-eyed, weary and wan, Though thrice ten years had barely been told, I came to the factory-man: All life long in a poisonous air, Blighting to body and mind, Where health soon turns to be stagnant there, And piety deaf and blind, His lot was a loom and a ricketty chair, And cotton to weave and wind! One among thousands all alike His only excitements were Drink and the Strike, To think of the torch and to dream of the pike! Faded, slatternly, looking so weak, Tho' once a Scotch lassie so braw, —With sin in her eye, and disease on her cheek, The factory-girl I saw: That close dim room was her home for years With all things vile to endure, Irksome labour, and quarrels, and jeers, And words and deeds impure, And so till Death,—amid sorrows and fears, And all without a cure! One of a multitude was that girl Slaving amid the machinery's whirl, Bold, and beggar'd of modesty's pearl! O but how base and shameful a thing Is this, ye getters of wealth,— That your prosperities Ruin should bring On happiness, virtue, and health! Consider the Mind, remember the Soul, Of these poor Bodies take care; If Providence over them gives you control, As stewards to be judged, beware! And you, good men,—ay, good on the whole, No Strikes!—let all be fair. Thus, on a just anti-slavery plan Let each do well, as well as he can, And all will go better with Master and Man! III. THE QUILL, AND THE COUNTER When, O when, shall the life of a Man Be worth a Man's while to live? When, to this old White-Slavery plan Its death shall Liberty give? For, Life was lent to each of us here For more than a living to earn, For duties to bless, and affections to cheer, And plenty to teach, and to learn. But how can yon pale copying clerk, Screw'd down to a desk and a stool Twelve hours per diem at quill-driving work, Go ever to God's own school? No rest, no leisure, no changes in life, But one dull same routine, The pounce and the parchment, the pen and the knife, And—Man as a mere machine! Then,—as to that faint feverish youth So early and late in the shop, Whose mileage of walk by the counter in truth Has rendered him ready to drop, Painfully smiling, and puffing his wares, And tricking the customer well, How sad is his life, and how badly he fares Let too many thousands tell! O tyrannous Fashion, these victims are thine, O Vanity, thine are these souls, O merciless Trade, at thy bidding they pine, And misery over them rolls! Grant them, ye chiefs with the will and the power More leisure for knowledge of good,— The boon of a sensible evening hour For mental and heavenly food. Aye, how many myriads with every day Wake only to worry and pain, Life's beauty and blessedness shredded away, A mockery cruel and vain! And all because Man, tyrannical Man, Wills not that his brother be blest, But fights against Nature's sabbatical plan Of righteous and rational rest. You may talk of the Slave, and the chain and the whip, We have plenty of slavery here; Steep'd in its bitterness up to the lip They grind in a bondage severe! O God! what a heaven this hard earth might be, If men to each other were kind, And bodily industry left a man free To nourish his heart and his mind! IV. THE BRITISH SLAVE'S REPLY TO A POLITICAL ECONOMIST. So! you preach me self-reliance, Emigration,—rights of man? So! you bid me breathe defiance As a freeborn Briton can? Break the fetter, burst the shackle, Let the despot find me still Loose from all constraining tackle, Stout of heart, and strong of will?— Tell the mouse to bell the mouser, Bid the harnessed jade kick out, Be the lion's mean arouser Till his cage he raves about! Say to Lethargy, be stirring, Counsel health to fever's cheek, Preach cold ethics to the erring, Teach gymnastics to the weak! O, good sir! your weighty reason Falls like feathers on a fool; Want has no such leisure season No such chance to go to school: Bitter circumstance has bound me, Everyway its serf and slave, And for these free hands has found me Fetters even to the grave! You have wit, and time to whet it, Feeling, knowledge, station, might, I—my bread it's hard to get it, All beyond is out of sight, Out of hope, and out of heeding; Think you that my stinted soul Can, like yours, on thoughts be feeding, Or be kindled like a coal? What the parson weekly preaches, Pretty seldom understood, What the book of Nature teaches, That's my sum of true and good: Gentlefolks have nobler chances Prizes all, as things of course; But the poor man's Circumstances Bind him down a slave perforce! Emigrate?—to where I know not,— Whilst I cannot break my chain; Rights of man?—my Rights, they show not,— And my Wrongs are shown in vain! And, for what you call “defiance,” If one act, or word, or look Even hinted “Self reliance,” —I'm struck off the Bailiff's book! V. THE WORKWOMAN. “The Song of the Shirt,”—O heart-stirring hymn! How sternly and terribly true The portrait of misery, ghastly and grim, That Bard of Humanity drew: Go, read it once more; none other may paint So touching a picture as this,— For he that imagined it now is a saint At rest in a mansion of bliss! Yet, precept on precept, and line upon line, And effort again and again, This, friends, is a duty of yours and of mine, If we wouldn't labour in vain; And he that would combat White-Slavery-sin Must hit its most hideous blot, To tell how poor womanhood, sickly and thin, Is treated the worst of the lot! This binder of boots, that stitcher of slops, These knitters by night and by day, Are slaves to the tyrants that rule in the shops, Who grind them for pittance of pay; And often the delicate daughters of taste, With needle and need for their goads, Hard-driven by Fashion with murderous haste, Like packhorses die on the roads! O Belle of the ball-room, how little you know Of the pain that has made you so fair; O bride of Belgravia, hunger and woe Have drest you so charmingly there! O buyer of bargains, most cruelly cheap, Consider what sorrow must lurk In toil without respite, that strangers may reap The fruit of such profitless work! Come, Queen of the Fashions, so gracefully calm, And yet with heart throbbing within, Vouchsafe, as you can, some Imperial Balm To cure this old system of sin; Your ladylike milliners,—leave them awhile, And seek out their want-stricken slaves; 'Twere better your Majesty wasted a smile On poor honest girls, than on knaves. And, gentle Society, bargain-befool'd, Ah, think what embroideries cost! Remember, when self-exultation has cool'd, Your gain by some other is lost! It is gambling unfairly,—where virtue and health And labour these workwomen give, While all that you stake is an atom of wealth, Too little for “Live, and let live!” VI. THE OUTCAST. A walk in the city by day;— When rural simplicity stops To wonder at all that is glittering gay Heap'd in the ticketing shops; And oftener too gets stopp'd as it goes By many a sorrow it meets, The sins and the shames, the troubles and woes Found in the flinty streets! In spite of Philanthropy's rules, And all that Exertion has won By Orderly badges, and Ragged Schools,— Alas! how little is done: For an orphaned legion of desperate youth The scum and the lees of the town, Outcasts of virtue, and outlaws of truth, Are prowling up and down! They live—Heav'n only knows how— Uncared-for in body and soul, As foxes in holes, or the rook on the bough, Or scavenger-dogs of Stamboul: Three myriads of such (as they tell us) are known, A homeless and famishing crew Who roam up and down this labyrinth town Like jackals in Timbuctoo!— A stroll in the city by night;— Where sadden'd Humanity's tear Must ever be dropt for a sorrier sight The ruins of Womanhood here! Alas! for their bondage; no heavier chain Has ever poor African worn, Than yon wretched creature, whom pleasure and pain Make equally foul and forlorn! Six myriads (they tell us) of these, Society's commonest slaves, Live only for guilt, and scorn, and disease And pine for the beds of their graves; And profligate men, who from boyhood are curst By daring to sin as they will, Add ever new victims, to live like the worst And to perish like reprobates still! —Who can pretend they are Free? Free to be starved, if they cease By sinning, or stealing, or begging, to be Scabs on the world's increase! Free?—when a network of Circumstance strong Closes them only to Crime, And multiplied evil and manifold wrong Are rife in a Christian clime! O world,—poor travailing world,— When shall your oppressed go free? And Rights be set up? and Wrongs be down hurl'd? Ah, when shall these things be? —Come speedily, Holy One, King of the Just! No power but Thine can save The cruel from treading the meek in the dust, Or ransom the poor White Slave! VII. THE SERVANT-OF-ALL-WORK. Drudgery all the day, Drudgery half the night,— Scolded about and worried away, Begrudged of sleep, and victuals and pay, And always in dread of “what Missus will say,” Thou scared little weary wight,— Alas, for that poor thin face so pale, I read in its features this piteous tale She was a peasant's child In the prison-like Union born; Never on her had a father smiled, And as for her mother, degraded, defiled, By some young reprobate basely beguiled, Deserted and forlorn, She died in giving her little one birth And left the poor babe alone on this earth! So, under workhouse care Somehow the child grew up, Stunted and spare, upon stinted fare Without one gleam of kindliness there, One touch of humanity ever so rare, One drop of sweet in her cup,— An ill-used, cunning, ignorant mind, Blunted and bruised by a world unkind. And thus the years went round, And then to service she went; The stern taskmaster was easily found, The trembling apprentice as easily bound, And so this drudge has been work'd and ground, And still slaves on, content, Too deeply acquainted with sorrow and strife To care to be otherwise all her life! —Nay but, Liberty's Nest! Dear England, home of the Free! So frankly made welcome to strangers distrest, Can thine own daughters, pining for rest, Be thus ground down, unhelp'd tho' opprest, Be thus enslaved in thee? Can woman, or man, or childhood appear So hopelessly, endlessly, desolate here? Bear witness, many a Place Where such bad servitude grinds,— Where Sunday is never a Sabbath of grace, And Toil never reaches the goal of its race, And Cruelty buffets Humility's face, And Thraldom Liberty binds,— And hardships, and evils, and wrongs you may see To rival almost the dark deeds of Legree! VIII. THE COALPIT GNOME. Christmas hearth! Christmas hearth! Bright with the blazing coals, And echoing clear with children's mirth, Goodwill tow'rds men and peace upon earth, And blessing to bodies and souls: Ah, Christmas hearth! a gloomier light Streams from those thy coals so bright While sternly before my musing sight This dark hearse-reverie rolls! The coalpit!—come with me Deep down the perilous shaft— And, how many objects sad to see, Pale abject girls and boys there be Doom'd to this deadly craft: Ah, blazing coals! what labour and pain From earth's hard bowels have torn you amain, By women and men that have sweated like rain, And babes that have never laught! The laden gang creeps on, Women with browbound packs, Up sultry galleries, one by one, Headlong dragging ton by ton These coals upon their backs! And children, aching with ague and cramp, Wearily watching the blue-flamed lamp, Lest death steal by on the breath of the damp, If those tired eyes relax. And blows from merciless men, And dread of the pick or the knife, And nameless wrongs beyond mortal ken Deepen the dark of their noisome den, With terrors, and oaths, and strife: O hard is the fate of this human gnome, The woman, or child, with never a home, Save under the coalpit's Tartarus dome, The home of a miner's life! Good Ashley! thine is the eye To pity and help such a slave; Priest and Levite, both pass by, But this Samaritan still draws nigh, His generous hands still save! And yet, how much remains to be done; For though in a Blue-book the battle be won, —They still drag coal-corves, ton by ton, White slaves from cradle to grave! IX. OUR NATIONAL DEFENDERS. All honour to Discipline!—happy the land Whose soldiers and sailors obey,— Whose captains and colonels are strict in command, And guide their strong steeds with a resolute hand By Order, the rule of the day. All praise to the captain,—whose spirited crew Is ready by noon or by night With cheerful alacrity,—steadily too,— His daring and masculine bidding to do In spite of the storm or the fight! All praise to the colonel,—whose troops well in hand At double-quick rush at the guns, Or like a built wall on the battlefield stand, Or hold without malice an enemy's land As dear British mothers' own sons! But, scorn for yon Admiral, bitter old Salt, Who swears “he'll make hell of his ship!” Who flogs honest Jack for the hint of a fault, And brands the ship's company “Slaves”—to exalt The pride of his heart and his lip. Poor Jack is right ready to watch and to work, And any one's servant to be, All dangers to dare, and no duty to shirk,— But cannot put up with that terrible Turk A quarter-deck tyrant at sea! Give, give him his comforts; for hardships enough Must ever be mates of poor Jack; But his heart is as soft as his bosom is rough And he feels like a woman the curse or the cuff And the mark of the cat on his back! And—General Martinet, one little verse To you and your majors is due: Be kind to your men; for no blunder is worse Than still to be flinging the cuff or the curse At Englishmen honest as you! Don't tease them with pipeclay; nor drill them too hard; Nor shave their moustachios away,— Why shouldn't their beards be “outparding the pard?”— Nor stiffen their stocks on parade, nor on guard; Nor scold them by night and by day. Let Jack and his brother, who fight for us, find They serve under true-hearted men, As officers strict, but as gentlemen kind, And so to each Service good treatment shall bind Our champions most heartily then! X. SLOP-JOBBING. Surely, to labour for what is not bread,— To earn for an egg a stone instead,— Cheap work, with victuals so dear; Tho' skill'd with the hand, and shrewd with the head, To be drudging on still, half clothed, half fed, —Hard lines for the poor man here! The journeyman sits in his garret dim Till his legs are numb'd and his eyeballs swim, At piecework night and day; His sharp Jewish master makes money of him, Sweating his muscles, limb by limb, And coining his life away! The lower he drops in the social scale, Tho' jobs never cease, nor diligence fail, Worse paid is work ever found; That varnish'd chair in the furniture sale Yields only some pence to this journeyman pale, —To his master the rest of the Pound! Those huge jack-boots of the cavalry-swell, These coats that Isaac and Jacob sell So cheap to the full-dress gent,— Their gains to the firm what sum can tell? For the hands that have done their work so well Earn barely a two per cent! Then illness comes; and the crushing load Of debts increasingly hopelessly owed, And all sold up at the last; And Honesty, urged by Necessity's goad, As a Union-pauper at work on the road Breaks stones—but not his fast. On water-gruel he lives, and dies,— For death makes free his soul for the skies; And as for its carcass asleep,— Into his muscles the surgeon pries; For Science claims such cheap supplies, Society's pay for his keep! O pity and shame for such a man's woes! Yet thousands of garrets and cellars disclose Like tale of suffering long; Industry, Honesty,—every one knows What ought to be gain'd by such virtues as those If Right were the rule and not Wrong. XI. BETTER BARRACOONS: OR, PROFITABLE CHARITY. Men of money, shrewd and skill'd In putting capital to nurse, Ready to pull down streets, or build, If either helps to fill the purse, Now let me tell your wit a plan How to reap a royal rent Out of—doing good to Man, Charity, at cent per cent. From Belgravia cease awhile, Cold, repulsive, stern and white, Where each huge palatial pile Frowns the poor man out of sight; From Tyburnia's dreary squares Turn your energies aside,— And look to how the workman fares Who built those stuccoed haunts of pride. In stagnant cellars, dim with stench, In putrid alleys, choked by drains, Or where the reeking gutters drench Some garret, rotten with the rains, Beggar'd of water, light, and air, And every good that gladdens life, The poor mechanic festers there With pallid babes and haggard wife! Can yonder neighbouring flashy shops, Glorious in plaster, glass, and gilt, Where Hebrews ticket showy slops, And bankrupt trade is overbuilt, Can those repay your risk and cost, Or make you half so blest or rich As finding homes for these half-lost Who crowd the dunghill and the ditch? Build a broad street, a hive of homes, Where workmen mostly go and come, —A thousand weekly rented rooms Will make a pretty yearly sum,— Build it for cleanliness and health, And judge it wisdom well to build, Lest—foul miasma blast your wealth, And that—your lodgings may be fill'd. Build it for comfort, ay and pleasure, For winter's warmth, and summer's cool, With reading-room for evening leisure, And—why not chapel, hall, and school? The good mechanic's homestead-college Where, with his homely flock and friends, Work over, he may feed on knowledge Or gather up its odds and ends. Better than shop-fronts, gaudy-gay, Better than mansions, let or sold, Will such a wise investment pay, And prove a mine of good and gold: Of good,—for so shall honest men In healthy dwellings live content; Of gold,—your well-used money then Shall yield the builder cent per cent! XII. THE LIBERATOR. After all said,—how many more Of shames and sorrows by the score Escape without a touch; After all said, how little hope With this world's leprosy to cope In chance of doing much! Good statesmanship's acutest scheme, Philosophy's most perfect dream, Democracy's pet plan, Philanthropy's devoted will, Not all our zeal, nor all our skill Can heal the wounds of Man! With Pleasure's growth, and Wealth's increase, The contrast, Want, shall never cease, And Want secures the Slave; With human nature's cruel mind Dependent Misery to grind What brother's hand can save? Even our sons, the lads at school, Delight with tyranny to rule And beat the lower boys,— Even our daughters, fashion's flowers, Begrudge the early-closing hours, And frown on Sunday joys. There is a Brother,—only One, Whose Spirit does what has been done, And all in secret heals; Who wipes away the mourner's tear, And whispers patience in his ear, And comfort—when he kneels! He, only He, can change outright This wretched state of sin and night For righteousness and day; And when He cometh,—(when He will!) Shall scatter every cloud of ill, And drive all shames away! Meanwhile, it is for you, O Man, To imitate as best you can That universal Friend, To right the Right, and fight the Wrong, Assured it cannot now be long All Thraldom has an end! T.</field>
   </doc>
</add>