<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Garnett, Richard, 1835-1906</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Garnett, Richard, 1835-1906</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">garnett richard 1835 1906</field>
      <field name="author_text">Garnett, Richard, 1835-1906</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1900's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.0197.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1901</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466053</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Queen and Other Poems ; By Richard Garnett</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Queen and Other Poems ; By Richard Garnett</field>
      <field name="title_facet">queen and other poems</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">queen and other poems</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Queen and Other Poems ; By Richard Garnett</field>
      <field name="year_display">1901</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1901</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1901</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466053&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466053&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Garnett, Richard, 1835-1906&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;garnett richard 1835 1906&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Queen and Other Poems ; By Richard Garnett&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;queen and other poems&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1901&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1901&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Garnett, Richard&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1835&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1906&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Queen and Other Poems&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By Richard Garnett&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;New York&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;John Lane, The Bodley Head&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1901&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp1460&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;viii, 11, [53] p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Queen and Other Poems&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By Richard Garnett&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 38 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted; verse reproduced elsewhere in The English Poetry Full-text Database omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE QUEEN I The Century that to the grave is gone, Whose birth was fear, confusion, and lament, Parted in joy, beholding ere it went High jubilee of happy Albion. Another step of Time's long stair is won; O'er widening life an ampler prospect lent; New morning streams o'er isle and continent; Where is the glorious Light that was our Sun? Yet, Britain mine, though chiefly o'er thy coasts The all-eclipsing shade broods dim and blind, And tears more sad from springs more sacred flow, Thine is but one among the mourning hosts. Thy sorrow is the sorrow of mankind, And the wide world is darker for thy woe. II Yea, the wide world is darker for thy woe! What blast of all the many-roaming gales But speeds or thwarts some errand of thy sails, And waves thy Empire's banner to and fro? Where the brief sun shines dim on mounded snow, Where luxury of summer never pales, Where frost with fire is poised in even scales, Hearts beat to bleed, eyes ope to overflow. The great confederate Land decree divine Dissevered from her Mother, so to lend Thy language and thy laws yet wider reach, Droops, what to foe did never yet incline, Her constellated flag; and sighings send The swarthy nations, skilless of our speech. III The swarthy nations, skilless of our speech, Where 'neath the starry Cross the suppliant throng Sue for thy sword to remedy their wrong, And rule humane and equal right beseech:— Or where late laurel veils the baleful breach Where Gordon died, and speed of Nilus strong Rolls on rich wave the liquid life along Thy science stores, thy care divides for each:— Or where from Comorin to Cashmere reigns The British Peace, and fly to gloomy lair The fiends of Plague and Famine overthrown:— Or where new drops for their decrepid veins The dateless empires from thy fount would share:— By these for theirs is thy bereavement known. IV By all for theirs is thy bereavement known! Around earth's circle tolls the heavy bell; In thousand tongues the thousand nations tell Of orphaned multitude and stricken Throne: And prudent Kings and counsellors grey-grown New writing on the wall discern, and spell The silent sign and script irrevocable, And reason of the things that shall be shown. But lost is a nobility from Life Not soon restored, for Time by Time repairs Slowly a cedar-crest of Lebanon. More gravely garbed, with moodier musings rife, The youthful Age upon its journey fares Than that which to the sepulchre is gone. AT A CITY FEAST (SADDLERS' COMPANY. January 20, 1896) As camping hosts at trump of battle blown, All to their feet by common impulse rise; “The Queen!” the ruler of the banquet cries, And all with thundering cheer acclaim the Throne. But one far guest, The Hon. Mr Reid, member of the Legislative Council of Victoria. whose hand had harvest sown Maturing then 'neath blaze of Austral skies, The high health hails; then, soft 'twixt words and sighs, “God bless her,” breathes, so low, I hear alone. Than all the plaudits that with plaudits vied, As shout on shout beneath the rafter rung, Be rather, Queen, that whispering prayer thy choice. Worth, Honour, Wisdom trained and Valour tried Spoke in that clamour, but the heart and tongue Of all thy Empire in the still small voice. VENI, VIDI, VICI ON THE KAISER'S VISIT The message by its brevity so great, Summing in three thrice-memorable words The lightning of the sudden Latin swords, And ruin of base son of Mithridate; This History now, with Fame confederate, Rescribes, old phrase with modern deed accords, Nor lesser than the Roman's praise awards To helmsman of the ship of German State. Compeers in action swift, in vision sure: But widening world and vaster issues bring To Kaiser than to Cæsar nobler part. Old glory by the recent beams obscure: Cæsar came, saw, and smote a Pontic king; Kaiser in triumph leads a people's heart. FIFTY SONNETS I SPARTA AND RHODES “Spartam nactus es, hanc orna.” “Hic Rhodus, hic salta.” Sonnet, as diamond of mine or dew Perfect in form and purity and light, Wherefore, though more aspiring Muse incite, Walk I content among thy retinue? Veiled in the vast and visionary blue This song should soar, companion of their flight Whose pinions effortless unchallenged smite Aerial void where eagle never flew. Epic or tragic laurel would I share, Or his, whose soul streams forth in lyric odes; But yoke of public and of private care With daily lassitude the spirit loads, And to the earth remands her from the air, “Behold thy Sparta,” saying, “and thy Rhodes.” 1895. II TO DANTE “Poet, whose unscarred feet have trodden Hell, By what grim path and red environing Of fire couldst thou that dauntless footstep bring And plant it firm amid the dolorous cell Of darkness where perpetually dwell The spirits cursed beyond imagining? Or else is thine a visionary wing, And all thy terror but a tale to tell?” “Neither and both, thou seeker! I have been No wilder path than thou thyself dost go, Close masked in an impenetrable screen, Which having rent I gaze around, and know What tragic wastes of gloom, before unseen, Curtain the soul that strives and sins below.” VII TIME AND CHANGE Affrighted at his own eternity, Time Change begot, to soothe with curious show Disquiet of uneasy soul below, Bewildered with its being's mystery. Hail, world-renewing Mutability, By whom the unimprisoned waters flow, And the great vault doth darkle or doth glow, And light and shadow course upon the sea! Though worlds arise and pass, like drift of spray Or flake of billow flung upon the shore, And dying suns like dying brands decay: Yet of all change not any change so sore As this the daunted spirit should affray; If Time were ever still, and Change no more. XI PRESIDENT KRUGER My wont it ever was the head to bow When foot of fallen Greatness wended near; Oft sprang into the eye the sudden tear, And the wrung heart bled sympathy—but now? Craft, weaving grimy webs in hoary brow, Pride's vaunting tongue, Presumption's stubborn ear, And Guile and Greed in sanctities austere Profanely draped, sweet Pity disallow. Unchivalrous! thy penury of worth Rivets the hand reluctant to thy throat, And Victory cheats of exquisite reward; To raise, encircled by the arm that smote, The enemy low laid on gory earth, With balmy salve for gashes of the sword. December 1900. XII “FAS EST ET AB HOSTE DOCERI” If doubtful of thy country thou hast been, And shunned at her commandment to inscribe Her patriot roll, regard the hostile tribe, And read her quarrel's justice in their mien. If such her foes, well may she smile serene! Jew-baiter, anarch, cleric, hireling scribe, The Fenian vitriol and the Brussels bribe: —An ark for every beast, except the clean. Yet, from the seething venom canst thou strain Some wholesome drop, be, Briton, not too nice, Dreading with slime thy finger to distain: Romans to tripes resorted for advice; And well for Egypt had her Pharaoh ta'en Hints from the frogs and lessons from the lice. XIV TO A REACTIONARY Unblest, whom tartness of unmellowed eld Doth from thy day's accumulating dower Of thought and lore estrange, which, hadst thou power, Thou wouldst efface, unheard and unbeheld. Warped from her wont, hath Nature then withheld From thee the quickening sun, the tempering shower; Fragrance denied to full expanded flower; Nor with the flagoned vine the vat excelled? Old poet-preacher, deemest thou that Truth, Triumphal treading on her trophied way, Will turn her round to dance unto thy pipe? Not Gods but stones attend Amphion's lay. Intolerance is comedy in youth; But 'tis most tragic to be sour and ripe. XV HELEN'S TOWER (ERECTED BY THE MARQUIS OF DUFFERIN IN MEMORY OF HIS MOTHER, AND CELEBRATED BY TENNYSON AND BROWNING) Love low in earth thy sure foundation laid; Song thy aspiring head with honour crowned; And the green wood rejoicing came around; And the broad sea was thy bright mirror made. Yet not yon restless blue or slumbering shade, Or Scotland's coast in distant purple drowned, Or various Erin's many-tinctured ground,— Thousandfold beauty to one glance displayed— Not these, or laurelled lyres, that, as of old The stars of morning, pealed thy natal lay, Exalt thee most, but choicest praise is thine; That we who this fair Paradise behold Would yield for thy rude granite, scarred with spray, Prospect of earth and sky, and sea divine. XVI TO A FAVOURED POET Minstrel, if I like thee found place and time In field and grove to meditate my lays, Where spinning leaf with whirling eddy plays Feeding the thirsty ear with fluent chime; Or, where thick bees besiege the towering lime, Or the long wood in one green billow sways, With harp attuned might court Apollo's praise, Sight, scent, and sound embalming in sweet rhyme: Not, haply, then should I to thee consign This lonely note like plunging pebble flung Where thy full river widens to the sea. As works her web the spider, I have wrung An arduous music from my bosom; thine Besets thy daily path, as flowers the bee. XVIII THE VIOL TO THE MUSICIAN (PLAYING ON AN INSTRUMENT MADE IN 1525) What time the Friar of Wittenberg was bold To wed his vestal, shaped was I and strung, And wail of vanquished France around me rung For captive King and ranks in ruin rolled. Skill subtler grown, Device of daintier mould, Thrust me aside, in halls of stillness hung, Till touch of Genius came, and I had tongue To tell of love and ruth and triumphs old. O give me life as I shall give thee praise, And mates be we through memorable years By Destiny assigned thee, as I trust. But when the hand the soul no more obeys, And from the stage the artist disappears, Lay me by too, and let me fall to dust. XXI CÆSAR BORGIA'S SWORD AUT CÆSAR AUT NIHIL Well has the graver traced thee, sword of mine! Here Cæsar by the Rubicon's slow deeps Ponders, here resolute to empire leaps, And far and near the smitten waters shine. The vanquished train's interminable line Wends with his wheels up Capitolian steeps; And round the interlacing legend creeps, Cæsar or nothing, saith Duke Valentine. And did I bare thee to the sun, my Blade, Fired at the flash all Italy should thrill, And many a city quake and province bow. Yet is a drop within this phial stayed, That should the might of marching armies still, And stainless sheathe ten thousand such as thou. XXII LAND AND SEA (AFTER MRS C. MURA'S “IDYLL” IN THE ROYAL ACADEMY) A bight of Grecian waters sapphirine, Where woody slopes shelve gently to the seas, And Satyrs ambushed by Oreades Peep forth astonied from the screening pine. For foaming furrows blanch the azure brine Where Tritons plunge and Nereids wheel at ease; And fain the admiring Fauns would be as these, Who would for earth the watery realm resign. Sometimes a Satyr, to the margin crept, Pelts a near-gliding nymph with shell or sand, Or trump of Triton peals an Oread's praise. But Law is Deity, and will be kept; Foot travels not the sea, or fin the land; And scaly folk and sylvan pause at gaze. XXIV THE VESSEL OF THE STATE I am the Vessel of the State, and hence, When sudden from the helm the steersman fails, 'Twere meet some sighs were given to the gales, Which, as in duty bound, I here dispense. Yet other sentiment have I, immense Relief from prow to poop through spars and sails, Which whirlwinds, haply, yet may wreck, or whales, But not the pilot's gross incompetence. Hath he gone down to nether regions dim? No matter, so not longer here he be; But, monarch of the fallen Seraphim, Vast ruth and mighty dole have I of thee; For thou must needs be intimate with him, Whence ruin of thy empire I foresee. XXVI A LETTER FROM AFAR My thought of thee was sadness, as beseems Remembrance of old amity descried Through veils of Time and Space, as through the tide Of sea's abyss a sunken jewel gleams. 'Tis I, not it, behold! have dwelt with dreams. Anew, fond soul, in friend and fate confide; And favourable deep be glorified, And work of Love wrought from the world's extremes. So lamp of Love in Sestian turret lit, Beamed, though Love's planet sank beneath the main, Boldness on young Leander cleaving it. The wizard so, last birth of Shakespeare's brain, The ship “three glasses since we gave out split,” Winged with brave sails to breast the seas again. XXIX DANTE (PREFIXED TO A TRANSLATION OF HIS SONNETS) Thou who like Dian hast in Heaven domain And hell, and worlds that intermediate roll, This slender tribute summed in tiny scroll Seemeth it not thy grandeur to profane? Not so, such offering thou wouldst ne'er disdain, Aware that not from deeper springs of soul Burst the great song the centuries extol Than these clear notes heard once and yet again: Which, if among the spirits unforgiven Thou wentest, or where smites the healing rod, Or didst the path of Paradise essay, Borne in the heart where'er the feet took way, Gave witness that thou hadst already trod Love's land, that comprehendeth Hell and Heaven. XXX PETRARCH (PREFIXED TO A TRANSLATION OF HIS SONNETS) Laurel in right of Laura thou didst claim, Which wreath Apollo with his bay enwound; Nature with flower and Wit with diamond crowned; Thine were the wind, the dawn, the star, the flame. First ever thou, no second comes or came. Worship not fellowship with them is found Whose lyres by rills of Castaly resound, Enkindled and disheartened by thy fame. What first? what last? such lauds unnumbered throng Upon the thought intent to honour thee, That silent panegyric fears to wrong. Yet first, the clear and golden suavity Wherethrough the soul inhabiting the song Is seen, as sitting in her sanctuary. XXXI CAMOENS (PREFIXED TO A TRANSLATION OF HIS SONNETS) What singles my Camoens from the rest? Not gliding flood of silver eloquence; Or phrase of nicest choice; or affluence Of thought severe to one strong line comprest: Not music aye attending at his hest On lute or trump as suits the various sense: All these he hath; but laurel gathered hence Crowns every bard inscribed among the best. But that with lyric vehemence was fraught, Sonnet, by him thy fair amenity, The perfect form perturbing not in aught, But teaching how the flight might fierier be. Tagus yet pealeth with the passion caught From the wild cry he flung across the sea. XXXIII SHELLEY Eagle of Song, whence came such strength to thee, On spacious air launched forth with strenuous wing Thus effortless to glide on voyaging O'er earth's domain and the unfooted sea? Or from Light's portal inaccessibly The lyric torrent of thy soul to fling, With music of the skies discomfiting Earth's little choristers of lawn and lea? Phœbus unfold, for surely not without Some gracious aid it pleased thee to extend, To altitude so vast did Shelley rise. I hope so, says Apollo, but I doubt. Myself in rivalry a lay have penned, But have not published, and therein was wise. XXXIV ROBERT LOUIS STEVENSON Wondrous as though a star with twofold light Should fill her lamp for either hemisphere, Piercing cold skies with scintillation clear, And glowing on the sultry Southern night; Was miracle of him who could unite Pine and the purple harbour of the deer With palm-plumed islets that sequestered hear The far-off wave their zoning coral smite. Still roars the surf, still bounds the herd, but where Is one to see and hear and tell again? As dancers pause on an arrested air Fail the fast-thronging figures of the brain; And shapes unshapely huddle in dim lair, Awaiting ripe vitality in vain. XXXV SYMONDS, PATER, HAMERTON, STEVENSON Child of the great Rebirth, who most of men Didst steep in Italy the English soul: Thou, Phidias of discourse, who couldst control Speech to Form's purity by shaping pen: Thou who all Art didst learn to teach again: And thou whose Art was Nature:—from the scroll Of Life how swiftly blotted:—golden toll Cast to the oarsman of the Stygian fen! Of you who had not said, “Behold in these The strenuous growth Time mellows to endure, More rich, more fair, for annual season found?” O dupes and scoffs of hollow auguries! Still flourishes the weed, the tree mature With stem and bough and fruitage loads the ground. XXXVI SMALL POETS AND GREAT PESSIMISTS Fleas are not Lobsters. —Peter Pindar. “Oysters and whelks avaunt! and all sea-fry Of ignominious brood unapt to smell The sulphur of a lobster-spirit's hell, Viewing the kitchen with prophetic eye! There what avail my sable panoply? Or giant claw whose grinding gripe might well Enforce the Lord of Myrmidons to yell, Till silver Thetis to his succour fly?” “If, brother, thou dost rightly diagnose Thy rank in Nature's scheme, so must it be: Even now the light flame leaps, the furnace glows, The cauldron hisses on the hob for thee: But can the Power like tragedy propose, That made thee not a lobster, but a Flea?” XXXVII JUSTICE When Deities from earth departure made, Justice I found in attitude to soar: No bandage veiled her eyes, no blade she bore, Nor in her hand her wonted balance swayed. Goddess, I cried with tongue and look dismayed, Bereft of thee and thine, how any more Shall Hope allure, or Gratitude adore, Or Faith on Wisdom's prophecy be stayed? Fear not, she said, though far I seem to wend, Who omnipresent am, and whose award Hath course by automatic Law sublime. My bandage blinds the vulgar; on my sword The malefactor falls: my scales depend In nicest balance from the hand of Time. XXXVIII AN EMBLEM OF TRANSLATION Not of one growth the solemn forests are; Not solely is the stately alley made Of towers of foliage and tents of shade, Sturdy, deep-rooted, massy, secular. But briar astray, and bines that ramble far, And cup and crown of Bacchus blend and braid, With all that creeps disabled or afraid To mount by its own might toward sun and star. A lowly birth! yet lovely even so, Through brake and bush it serpenting doth wend, Vagrant with baffled rovings to and fro, Till soaring stem or stooping bough befriend; Then high the vine shall as the cedar grow, And from his summit shall her fruit depend. XL PASSION This flame of Passion that so high in air, By spice and balsam of the spirit fed, With fire and fume vast heaven hath overspread, And blots the stars with smoke, or dims with glare: Soon shall it droop, and radiance pure and fair Again from azure altitudes be shed; And we the murky grime and embers red Shall sift, if haply dust of Love be there. Gather his ashes from the torrid mould, And, quenched with cups of Bacchic revelry, Yield to the Stygian powers to have and hold; And urn Etrurian let his coffin be, For this was made to store the dead and cold, And is a thing of much fragility. XLI VIDEO MELIORA 'Tis not that witchery of Sin hath sway, But that the rock of Will is crumbling sand: The dungeons of the soul so open stand, Well might she issue by her entering way. Heart, thou art not so trodden into clay That ever must thou cower, where once trepanned; Torpor not palsy numbs the inactive hand, And shrouded eye sleeps dreaming of the day. Enough of wooing of estranged delight, Enough of crouching fear and wistful care, And banquet with all sauce but appetite: Leave, Spirit, leave these reptiles to their lair, And rise rejoicing to the golden light Thou canst not miss, for it is everywhere. XLIV OF ONE IN RUSSIA Dove that of old, fraught with the olive-spray, Toldest of Earth arisen from the flood, And how the grove in ancient station stood, And badest man take courage and be gay: Vain for green leaf this January day To search the savage waste of Scythian wood, Yet thither wend, of Clara's ill or good Bringing back tidings on thy westering way. Tell her the flame the brand should blithely fling Dies on the hearth in ashes chill and drear, And season vainly lengthens unto Spring Since she forsook the love that held her here, Sorrow and dread and many a joyless thing Leaving in place of her that was so dear. Jan. 28, 1894. XLVIII THE LAGGARD KNIGHT Too late! The mighty Dragon's crest of gold Lies cloven on the cavern's sparry floor; And flameless now the throat whence never more Shall blighting fume on blast of fire be rolled. But he, my Friend, lies lifeless—in his hold The venomed tongue his dying valour tore For triumph's token—with the monster's gore Sanguine, and stifled in its scaly fold. And diamond and emerald lie blent The ruby and the amethyst amid; And treasury is mine more opulent Than catacomb e'er stored, or pyramid; But ah! the deed illustrious I meant Rebukes the deed inglorious I did.</field>
   </doc>
</add>