<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Hunt, Leigh, 1784-1859</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Hunt, Leigh, 1784-1859</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">hunt leigh 1784 1859</field>
      <field name="author_text">Hunt, Leigh, 1784-1859</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1810's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.2466.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1819</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:467508</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Greek, Modern (1453- )</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Italian</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Poetical Works of Leigh Hunt</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Poetical Works of Leigh Hunt</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poetical works of leigh hunt</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poetical works of leigh hunt</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Poetical Works of Leigh Hunt</field>
      <field name="year_display">1819</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1819</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1819</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467508&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467508&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Hunt, Leigh, 1784-1859&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;hunt leigh 1784 1859&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Poetical Works of Leigh Hunt&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poetical works of leigh hunt&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1819&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1819&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Hunt, Leigh&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1784&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1859&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Poetical Works of Leigh Hunt&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Charles and James Ollier&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1819&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp1879&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;gre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;ita&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;3 v.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Poetical Works of Leigh Hunt&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 185 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted; verse reproduced elsewhere in The English Poetry Full-text Database omitted; translations omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">VOL I THE DESCENT OF LIBERTY Aprite, O Muse, i chiusi fonti, aprite. Cominci omai da questo di giocondo Più che mai bello a rinovarsi il mondo. Celio Magno. DEDICATION. TO THOMAS BARNES, ESQ. OF THE INNER TEMPLE ODE FOR THE SPRING OF 1814. From the Examiner of April the 17th, 1814. The vision then is past, That held the eyes of nations, Swept in his own careering blast, That shook the earth's foundations! No more throughout the air Settles the burning glare, That far and wide, metallic twilight, shone; No more the bolts, from south to north, Leap in their fiery passion forth. We look'd and saw the Wonder on his throne; We raised our eyes again, and lo, his place was gone! Nor did the Shape give way To mightier spirits like him, Nor did upon that final day Elder Corruption strike him. The long-taught world no more Those idle charms explore, Nor call on evil to restore from ill; But heav'n-ward things, that have their birth And shed their early tears on earth, Experience, Truth, and Conquest of the will, These took the Troubler's place, and bade the Plague be still. Never did sweeter sound From discord drop resolving, Than struck the balanced world around Once more set smooth revolving; And princely visions rare, Went stepping through the air, With frank eyes listening to the glassy spheres; The Eagles of the north were seen Sailing the sunny doves between; The Lily whiten'd from its dust with tears; And Hopes with lifted smiles, and holy-minded Fears. And lo, how earth and sky, As if the charm completing, From winter's other tyranny Revive and give us greeting. There's not a joy of spring, But's up upon the wing; The leaves put out their hands into the ray; The bee, that rings the basking hour, Comes for his kiss from flow'r to flow'r; Glad faces are abroad with crowding play, And all creation keeps full-hearted holiday. The soldier sheathes his sword, The statesman breathes from thinking, The freeman feels his hope restored, When most his heart was shrinking. No more the widow bleeds To see the babe that feeds At her dear breast with sudden-stopping moan; But while his earnest task he plies, Smiles in his grave uplifted eyes, Gath'ring his little hand into her own, And feels that in the world she shall not be alone. O Liberty! O breath Of all that's true existence! Thou at whose touch the soul, at death, But leaps to joy and distance; Before thy present call, The very captive's wall, If wrongly round him, like a curtain flies; The green and laughing world he sees, Waters, and plains, and waving trees, The skim of birds, and the blue-doming skies, And sits with smile at heart, and patience-levell'd eyes. THE DESCENT OF LIBERTY. PERSONS OF THE DRAMA. SPEAKERS. Eunomus—an old Nobleman, reduced and living in solitude. Philaret—his son, supposed to be dead. Myrtilla—his daughter-in-law, Philaret's wife. Three Shepherds—reduced to that condition. LIBERTY. Four Genii of the Kingdoms. Phaniel and Mabiel—attendant Spirits. Spring, Peace, and Poetry—Goddesses. The Sable Genius.MUTES. The Enchanter. Painting, Music, and Dancing—Goddesses. Ceres. Ambriel—a Spirit. Visions, and Pageants, &amp;c. PROLOGUE. The scene of the Prologue is nothing but clouds and sky, the former lying in heaps of silvery snow for a ground, and the latter, which is of a deep blue, presenting an occasional planet in motion. A sudden light strikes over the place, and Liberty, with a cheerful step, issues out of it. She is in the bloom of youth, buskined up with an active dress like Diana, her large and airy curls enwreathed with laurel, and a light staff with a cap on it across her shoulder. As she advances she makes a stop, and casts her eyes downwards, as if looking into the distance afar off. LIBERTY. This is the point at which the rolling world Opens upon me. There it is, broad gleaming! O what a sight of loveliness art thou, Earth, my dear care; and what would some of those, Who spoil thee, think if they could see thine orb As I do now, smoothing along the air With full-turn'd face divine, and all the while Serv'd with the beauty of the silver moon! Now the wide waters heavingly come round, Opaque and restless, with a lingering sweep; Fair islands now, and there, my favourite soil, Among them, upon which I first set foot Whene'er I visit earth; and now at last, The suffering land, which I must free to day. With what a clinging darkness is it cover'd! The Enchanter, foil'd in his attempt to force His art beyond it's limits, and to work His fiery magic in the northern snows, Where the rude people, having Nature's help, Scatter'd his wilder'd slaves, and smote him back, Feels that the secret weakness has escap'd him Of art compared with nature, wrong with right; And now, though resolute to dare all chances, Sits wrapp'd in double gloom, listening at times, With half a fear, to catch the expected sound Of numbers coming in their fresh revenge To dash him from his height. This is the hour I look'd for. Four of the most potent spirits, That rule the nations, have I just advised, Each in a morning vision, to combine Their clouds, and following up his wasted strength, Burst with a final thunderclap upon him, At which the world shall startle. Then will I Descend in lustre through the freshen'd air, Met by the flowering Spring; and giving each The laurel he has earn'd,—Liberty's crown,— Summon the triumphs and the joys about me, And lead a lovelier period for mankind. Ye tricksome cherubs, ever at your play, With smile-expanded cheeks and hovering limbs,— Minions of air, born of it's basking leisure,— Break off, my little spirits, some of ye, And with a silver cloud wait on me down. A set of cherubs rise from the back-ground, and Liberty seating herself on one of the clouds, they playfully bear her up with it, the whole going off at the side-scene with a descending motion. SCENE THE FIRST. A secluded spot in a wood, with a cottage on one side, and a little river running under the trees in the background. A kind of twilight is in the air. Enter three Shepherds, looking cautiously about, and listening. 1st Shep. It's wander'd somewhere else:—every thing's quiet. 2d Shep. Hush! Was not that it? 1st Shep. No; there's not a breath: I think it turn'd among the willows there. 3d Shep. Most likely: sound delights itself in water, As I have noticed often:—let's pursue it. 1st Shep. No, better not; remember what a road It led us yester eve;—'twill play no more. These spirits, bad or good (by what I've heard From my old grandam, and have read in books), Seem to delight in playing tricks with us, As if they made them merry with the awkwardness And grave mistakes of our inferior nature. Besides, the stream, you know, runs through the grounds Of fine old Eunomus, who used to set So rare a lesson to the former court, But now shuts up his sorrows in this corner; And 'twere amiss to startle his grey head E'en with a footstep. 2d Shep. 'Twere so: yet methinks He might be pleased to hear of this new sound, The first, of any comfortable breath, Our wood has heard for years. I know not why, But there is such a sweetness in the touch Of this mysterious pipe that's come among us, Something so full of trilling gladsomeness, As if the heart were at the lip that fill'd it. Or went a rippling to the fingers' ends, That it forebodes, to me, some blessed change. There! All. There! (A flourish of a small pipe heard.) 3d Shep. 'Tis overhead—I heard it plainly. 1st Shep. It comes no more. 2d Shep. But it was louder then Than it has ever been;—'twas curious too, It should return just as I spoke of change. 1st Shep. I think, with you, there must be something in it. Feel you no alteration? 2d Shep. What? In the air? 'Tis lighter,—fresher;—I perceived it yesterday. Oh, my dear friends, what if this gloomy weight, That sick and dim, like a disease of nature, Has visited so long our weary land, Should at the last be going? Nay,—to speak it, What if this cursed Enchanter— 3d Shep. Hush! Be cautious; You know what ears he has in every corner. 2d Shep. I care not:—who is there, among us, cares? Has not he robb'd us all of something dear, Some father, brother, son, to go and do His devilish work in countries of all climate, In fainting heats, and powerless, cramping colds, Wasting away in one, stiff'ning in t'other With horrid sleep, besides a world of toils, Of sore and starting bones, fevers, and frenzies, Sharp swords from hands unlook'd for, all the while, Glancing about their ears, and killing thousands? Look at old Eunomus—from first to last A lover of us all both high and low, And one that would have all live well together, The high in rank, the low in liberty, Gracing each other like the trees in spring, The tufted by the tall:—how has he suffer'd? Both his sons gone,—the first one by his death Breaking the mother's heart, the second now Torn from his bride, and dead too as they say,— She only left him to perform all parts, And keep back her own tears to save him his. Let's tell him of this pipe; I do believe, It brings us comfort. 1st Shep. Heaven send it may! At all events, 'twere well perhaps to tell him; For now I recollect, I have heard often, These hovering spirits may not keep their secret From unpolluted men; but when they're by, And the occasion's good, will yield their voices To the still air. I'll knock directly, shall I? All. Do, do. (Goes to knock at the cottage door.) Enter Eunomus with Myrtilla. Eun. How now, my friends? I saw you stop With hush'd and anxious gestures, and was coming To learn your news. Heard ye this sound in the air My daughter speaks of? for of late, my ear Seems closing up to every sound but her's. 2d Shep. We came, Sir, to inform you of it, Since from it's strange delightfulness, and something Of a new freshness in the air about us, We thought it boded good. Myrt. The very things, Dear father, that I told you. Eun. Is it then So very sweet? for my Myrtilla here Has a young fancy, and will convert the sound Of common breath to something exquisite, If evening silence and the trees be round her. 1st Shep. Sir, when I heard it first, and that was yesterday, Standing and looking down the floating stream With oft-returning lapse of distanced eyes, I felt my cheek change colour, it awoke So fairy-like at once; and when it rose A second time, which was near fall of night, As I was lingering at my open door, Fix'd as the calm, the tears came in my eyes Starting for sweetness. 3d Shep. We have heard, Sir, nothing At all resembling it, since fair Myrtilla Sang upon evenings to your— Myrt. (Interrupting him, and making side gestures of caution.) Have you all Perceived it then? 1st Shep. All of us,—some alone, And some together. 2d Shep. But so close to us Never till now; and so, we have remember'd What in sage books is told of reverend men, And of their power to hear celestial things, And voices of the sky; and now you're here,— Pardon us, Sir,—we think that if you spoke to it, It might give utterance, and disclose it's purpose. Eun. I fear, my friends, you think too potently Of an old man, whose heart is yearning still, Not for celestial, but for earthly voices:— But those are past,—and in the hope some day To hear them yet again with other ears, I have not fallen into so much bitterness With my humanity, or such resentment At ill's apparent wonders, as to shut My fancy up in a dull downward sleep, And never think of fair invisible things Or good intended towards us,—good perhaps Brought out and better'd from the taste of woe. If spirit unearthly ever went beyond It's dumb communication with such thoughts, Breaking air's vacancy with shape or sound, Though we, my friends, may not be men to ask it, This is a time when wonders are abroad, And such things might be. (A louder and longer flourish of sweet music than before.) 3d Shep. 'Twas upon the trees there. 2d Shep. 'Tis, Sir, as we supposed, pray speak to it— 1st. Shep. Hush! to the left. (The music shifts to the left with a different strain, and then makes a sudden stop.) Eun. Myrtilla, my sweet child, Frame you a prayer out of your innocent thoughts, And speak for all, something of heav'n is near us. (He takes off his cap, the rest doing it after him.) Myrtilla sings. Gentle and unknown delight, Hovering with thy music near us, If that our request be right, Lean thee tow'rd the earth, and hear us; And if we may yet rejoice, Touch the silence with a voice. By the lingering day forlorn, And the dread of the drear morrow, By the infant yet unborn, Waiting for it's world of sorrow, By youth, forgetful to rejoice, And middle age's failing voice; By the griefs of many lands, And hearts that waste in secret places, By the lift of trembling hands, And the tears on furrow'd faces, Say, shall anguish yet rejoice? Spirit dear, put forth a voice. Spirit sings. To the griefs of many lands, To hearts that waste in secret places, To the lift of trembling hands, And the tears on furrowed faces, To Beauty's and to Virtue's voice, I am come to bid rejoice. Two Echoes. Rejoice! Rejoice! RECITATIVE. 'Tis my brethren of the sky, Couriers we of Liberty, Coming hither, one by one, Like the streaks before the sun. She herself is now not far, But has pass'd the morning-star, And if ye would wish to see What shall help to set ye free, From the greenwood start ye forth, And turn your eyes from south to north. (A symphony of pipes mingles in; and the Spirit sings again.) Elsewhere now I take my voice; Locks of grey! And lips of May! And shepherds all, rejoice, rejoice! Echoes dying off. Rejoice! Rejoice! Myrt. This is deliciousness!—Our friends will go, And bring us word, dear father, of this sight: You must in-doors, and rest your spirit awhile. (Exeunt severally.) SCENE THE SECOND. The confines of a wood with a large plain stretching up the country in the back-ground, and shewing a city in the distance. Over the city hangs a dark cloud. Enter the Shepherds meeting on either side. 3d Shep. Did you remark the strange and sudden mist That parted us? 1st Shep. Ay, and was lost in wonder. 3d Shep. How it came rolling tow'rds us through the trees, And wrapp'd us from each other! 1st Shep. 'Twas like night Visibly passing. All my faculties Seem'd stuff'd and blinded till it had gone by. Yet here we are all met. 2d Shep. Some trick no doubt Of this tyrannic juggler to delude us: It's failure looks well-omen'd. What do you see? 3d Shep. Nothing as yet in the north. 1st Shep. But tow'rds the south There is a streak of light in the dark sky; And the Enchanter in his city seems At troubled work. 2d Shep. That's plain. Heav'n alter him! What choice has his been of these dark vexations, These sullen heights, this flound'ring in Heav'n's worst, This poor and purblind acting of the god, When by the same good gift of understanding Thus devilishly abused, and by applying To books of clearer wisdom, he had been Blessing and blest, and help'd to keep our land In still and shiny peace, it's vital air Pure and at liberty, and it's happy families As numerous, and as smiling, and as rich With joy at heart, as the small orbs that throng Their laughing cheeks together on our vines. What flash was that? Was it not lightning? 1st and 3d Shep. Look, Now the light's coming. 2d Shep. Something flashes thick As from a forge, and spits against the dark: The wind too,—how it musters on the sudden! Now, now! Another cloud, similar to that over the city, emerges from the north after the light, and begins to come slowly onward, the latter meantime shifting it's place a little towards it, and leaving the spires of the city whitening up into the air. 1st Shep. The Enchanter, wrapp'd within his cloud, Seems to await it. Heaven send us good! For after all, my friends, what if this voice We heard delude us, and this other cloud Contain but other evils like himself, Come to dispute with him the power to vex us? 2d Shep. That thought has cross'd me also; but I feel It cannot be; the voice had something in it So frank and kind, I feel assured 'twas true. Besides, those counter-ills have fail'd already:— He is so fixed and potent in his art, They have but furnish'd him with proud occasion To play the master, and bring under him, One after one, the trusters in his trade. No, no; the world is wiser, and has found, Be sure, some nobler art that shall perplex him. The better spirit within us all is roused, The spirit that reddens at an insolent eye, That leaps 'twixt wrong and suffering, that throws up A smile to heav'n ere it's impatience executes, That says to all men, ‘This is right, this wrong, This just and unjust, bearable and unbearable,’ This spirit is roused; and it shall read to his A lesson of such new and finishing thunder, As shall, at once, shake him from out his hold, And purge the air from after pestilence. A fierce gust of wind:—the two clouds wheel nearly together, and hover a little, darting out fires. By this time, a multitude of Shepherds have joined the others, and are gazing with anxiety at the sight. CHORUS OF PART OF THE SHEPHERDS. Moment of all anxious wonder! Hour, about to strike in thunder! Lo, we feel to that dread sound Heaven's own finger travelling round! CHORUS OF OTHER PART OF THE SHEPHERDS. Go not back, thou sacred hand, Hope of every listening land! Strike, strike, and set the nations free, And ring the knell, from clime to clime, of tyranny,—of tyranny! The attacking cloud throws out brighter and thicker flames than the other:—the latter begins to heave, and give way. GRAND CHORUS. See! see! he totters in his cloudy walls! See! see! See! see! He totters, totters, in his cloudy walls! (A vivid flash of lightning.) He falls! A tremendous clap of thunder, the clouds coming in contact; one bursts, and the Enchanter falls headlong, the twilight over the country vanishing. Then to the sound of distant and grand music, the other cloud, turning to a silvery hue, moves into the former's place over the city, and separates into four bright globes, on each of which sits a Genius, with one hand holding a thunderbolt carelessly on the thigh, and in the other lifting an olive-branch. They descend gradually into the city, amidst the far-off sound of bells and artillery. 2d Shep. More wonders yet:—we three will first return To the anxious hearts that wait us in the wood, Then join you in the city. Away, away! (Exeunt severally.) SCENE THE THIRD. A pleasure-ground in the suburbs of a great city laid out in a natural style with wood and turf, the spires and domes appearing over the trees toward the side, and the view opening to the western horizon in front. Voice of a Spirit in the air. Mabiel! Voice of another Spirit out of the trees. Who calls? Phaniel. 'Tis I, Here—two lark-ascensions high, Watching tow'rds the sunny sea To tell the approach of Liberty. Have you done what she desired? Mabiel. Every thing. All spots admired Have I plied my wings about To find the best and greenest out, And on this have fix'd at last, Where the meddling eastern blast Through the myrtle and the bay Shall not force his knify way To nip the sides and shrug the shoulders Of our Lady's fair beholders. Over all the beds and bowers Have I broke my softest showers; And the nearer breath of Spring Is all that's wanting now to bring Courage to their blossoming. Look behind; for by the humming Of the bees, I think she's coming. Phan. Yes,—and is at hand already. Scarcely can I keep me steady For her wanton fays and elves, Who'd have me dancing like themselves. Wags, be off; for though I'm free As suits a sprite of Liberty, You nor all your Lady's beauty Must beguile me from my duty. Mabiel, she's passing now.— Goddess of the sparkling brow, Rosy lip, and springing bosom, Please thee with all whitest blossom, Warmest bud and coolest green, To enrich this destined scene, Where to-day our Lady great, Liberty's to hold her state. (A short flourish of flutes:—the voice of Spring is heard.) Spring. Spirit, I have heard it all, And shall add my service small To content thy queen victorious, Though herself is all that's glorious. But I play not the bestower; 'Tis a gladsome task I owe her; For without her what were I? She it is that makes my sky Happy to the eye that sweeps it, And my bow'r to him that keeps it, And my air to him that takes it, And my verse to him that makes it. Doubly therefore, as I go, Breathe I on the buds below Warmth to set the prisoners free, Peeping red from flow'r and tree; And I shall have parted hence Scarce a moment, ere thy sense Fill with odours, rich and soft, Which their young lips vent aloft. Thank me not; I must be going.— Now, my Joys, your music blowing, Set the breeze, that wafts me, flowing. Soft pipes going off to the gentle bowing of the trees, whose blossoms in the mean while spread forth. Spring and her train are seen to float over at a little distance. Mab. Ha! you have petition'd well, Frank and fine-voiced Phaniel! All around me start, and spread, Bowering blossoms, white and red, Some in frills and curious frets, And some in cups and coronets, While the bees, about their treasure, Hum and pitch with tipsy pleasure, And the coying butterflies, Drest in all their summer dyes, Flutter up from every part, Tickled, as it were, at heart. Never shot so bright a blush! Then the panting leaves are flush With the freshest rainy green, And an amber light between; And the turf lies thick and glowing, Just as from a gentle mowing, Asking a fair foot to press On it's springy mossiness. Never look'd the bay so fit To surmount two eyes of wit, Nor the myrtle to be seen Two white-kerchief'd breasts between, Nor the oak to crown a sword For a nation's rights restored. Then the flowers on all their beds— How the sparklers glance their heads! Daisies with their pinky lashes, And the marigold's broad flashes, Hyacinth with sapphire bell Curling backward, and the swell Of the rose, full-lipp'd and warm, Round about whose riper form Her slender virgin-train are seen In their close-fit caps of green: Lilacs then, and daffodillies; And the nice-leaved lesser lilies, Shading, like detected light, Their little green-tipt lamps of white; Blissful poppy, odorous pea, With it's wings up lightsomely; Balsam with his shaft of amber, Mignonette for lady's chamber, And genteel geranium, With a leaf for all that come; And the tulip, trick'd out finest, And the pink, of smell divinest; And as proud as all of them Bound in one, the garden's gem, Heartsease, like a gallant bold, In his cloth of purple and gold.— But why stay I chattering here To a more instructed ear? Feet approach, my task is done, I must glance me through the sun. Phaniel, if your cloud holds two, I'll come up, and sit with you! Phan. Come along, and share my view. Mabiel flies up across the scene, whisking his coloured wings in the sunshine. The same scene. Enter the Three Shepherds with Eunomus and Myrtilla. 1st Shep. Now, Sir, rest here,—upon this shady bank. Eun. I will:—this heavenly season, and the sight Of my Myrtilla's face against the sun Touch'd with a morning eagerness, inspired me Beyond my strength. (Sits down.) I should apologize Once more for thus— 2d Shep. Pray, Sir, think well of us, We'll take the balmy welcome of the spot. 1st Shep. 'Tis one not to be hurried from. Eun. Well, well, My manly friends, I know what you think requisite To your true pleasures, and shall not dispute. 'Tis a sweet spot. 2d Shep. And with a lady in it Wants no perfection. We have come, I think, Through nothing but sweet spots from first to last. What think you, Madam? Those are not sad tears That flash above your smiling. Myrt. Tears of joy, Sir, To see the world with such a happy look. May you be happy all. 2d Shep. (Aside to the others.) She thinks a moment Of her lost kindred,—but in what a spirit! 1st Shep. O yes,—her heart is full, but love for all Swims at the top, and helps to shake these tears Over the brim. Myrt. (To Eunomus.) Now you will smile at me, And so would our friends too, but that they're younger And cannot yet afford to look such truths At a fair lady,—but you've heard me, Sir, In my young fancy picture out a world, Such as our present-timed, unfinal eyes, Knowing but what they see,—and not even that,— Might gather from the best of what's before them, Leaving out evil as a vexing thorn, Whose use they know not;— 2d Shep. Such a world, you say, This change appears! Myrt. I do; it seems to me, In it's fresh whisper, and delighted eye, And all this burst of out-o'-door enjoyment, Just like a new creation,—Spring and Summer Married, and Winter dead to be no more. Was ever so much horror, at the best, Follow'd by such a time,—change, wonderous change In what has busied all your talk by the way, And with it all this luxury,—flowers, blossoms, And heaps of leafiness on every side About and overhead, with beams between, And quick-voiced birds that steep the trees in music, Green fields, and crystal waters, and blue skies, With here and there a little harmless cloud That only wants a visible cherub on it To ride its silver;—happy human beings O'ertaking us meantime at every step With smile that cannot help itself, and turning, As they pass quick, with greeting of the day, Exchanging blessedness:—Oh Sir, Oh father, There's such a look of promise all about us, A smile so bidding, something that almost Seems to say yes to what the tip-toe heart, Hanging on Nature's neck, would ask of her, Even to the raising of a buried joy, That I could fancy—but—forgive me, pray, For talking of those things. Eun. Talk on, my child, And let the young hope, that is natural Both to thy age and sweetness, come about thee. Me too the season moves—What said you, Sir? (Catching hold of a Shepherd's arm.) My senses quicken at the name you spoke, Or else I'm losing them. 3d Shep. I saw a figure, Leaping the stile just now 'twixt yonder trees, Whom, if I make not miserable error, Was your son Philaret— 1st Shep. This lady's husband,— I saw him too—there!—darting through the limes. 2d Shep. And there!—he knows us, and makes joyful sign With a wild arm;—nay, Sir, you need not rise,— Do not;—dear lady too— Myrt. Tis he! 'Tis he! Risen out of buried thousands to come back to us! Enter Philaret rushing towards his father, and kneeling under his embrace, his arm at the same time clasping his wife. Eun. My boy!—What then escaped!—alive once more!— Come to lay smooth my old locks, ere I die! 3d Shep. (Aside.) Mark how his hand quivers and slips about To grasp his son all close to him. 2d Shep. Hush, hush; It is a sight to make our joy complete. Phil. (Still kneeling.) Let me see both your faces—both at once;— Oh, I see how it was,—you thought me dead, And so!— Myrt. But now! Oh now! Eun. Ay, this quits all;— Yes, all;—I have not, cannot cease to think Of others, but I'm grateful,—and a joy Despair'd of comes to us like Heaven's own message To bid us be content.—And yet I've wanted not An angel with me:—ay, my boy, do thank her;— She need not turn from you, as she was wont To do from me sometimes, her watery cheek; Or manage, with a lovely, pale pretence Of unconcern, to draw from out your sight The ring that slips upon her wasted finger. Phil. Did she do so? Did you do thus, my best And tenderest heart,—my wife?—May Heaven for this, If only this, bring out that cheek again Into it's dimpled outline,—Heaven for this Cool the dear hand I grasp with health and peace, Bless thee in body and mind, in home and husband,— And when old age, reverencing thy looks In all it can, comes with his gentle withering, Some thin and ruddy streaks still lingering on thee, May it, unto the last, keep thee thy children, Full-number'd round about thee, to supply With eyes, feet, voice, and arms, and happy shoulders Thy thoughts, and wishes, books, and leaning-stocks, And make the very yielding of thy frame Delightful for their propping it.—Come, come, We will have no more tears.—My old companions, Generous, I see, as ever, pray forgive me; I had not overlook'd you, but for these; And now for these, as well as for old times, My hand must grapple with you. Ah, Damætas, You've not forgotten your old shake, I find,— The cordial crush that used to lay one's hand up. 3d Shep. Pray take it, Sir, for all the shakes I owe you. 2d Shep. And now we'll leave, Sir, to your better keeping Our happy friends:—we had not staid thus long, But that we fear'd you might have thought us careless. Phil. Nay, if you go, you'll only come again; For as I heard, the pomps were just prepared To leave the city, and strike hereabouts. Flourish of a pipe in the air;—the voice of Phaniel is heard. Ambriel, Ambriel, brother scout, O'er the city looking out, I discern above the sea Light, that dawns for you and me, Of our mistress Liberty. Shoot your slender voice below, And let the pomps and triumphs know. Flourish of a distant pipe; and after a little pause, grand music approaching from the city. Enter the foremost part of the crowd of spectators on each side of the scene, congratulations passing between them; when suddenly, in the midst of the coming music, and to the attraction of all eyes, a purple light rises in the west, with winged cherubs touching away the little coloured clouds on either side; and the figure of Liberty is seen advancing on her cloud of silver. The acclamations of the crowd suddenly burst into a Chorus. 'Tis she! 'Tis she! 'Tis Liberty, Come to crown our wonders; To follow our night With a perfect light, And with airy health our thunders! O Goddess dear, our hearts leap up before thee, And on our feet like men, we best adore thee! By this time the cloud has descended to the back of the front scene, the cherubs seating themselves playfully about it, with Phaniel and Mabiel. The music, which seemed about to enter, suddenly ceases, and Liberty speaks:— Well met, my friends! After long centuries The unprison'd airs here freshen once again, And feel as they were fit for hearts and eyes To breathe and sparkle in. You thank me nobly. Now let the doers of my glorious work, Those Spirits of the Nations, whom I taught The way to conquer for themselves and you, Come in their pride before me, and receive The crowning thanks I owe them. A blast of trumpets. The music strikes up into a Prussian march, and one of the four Genii, or Spirits of the Nations, who overthrew the Enchanter, enters in a low chariot sculptured with instruments of war, and formed after the fashion of those in Homer, that is to say, a mere shell for a standing-place, open at the back, and drawn by a couple of white palfreys. He is habited in a short girdled vest, leaving his arms, knees, and throat naked, with a head of manly curls, a star gleaming on his forehead, and two large and dark wings at his shoulders,—altogether presenting the appearance of an angel in the bloom of manhood,—immortal spirits not being outwardly touched, like men, by the cares of their respective employments. On the front edge of his car is an eagle carved in ebony. Liberty, as he stops in passing, presents him with a crown of laurel, which he holds in his hands while she addresses him:— [Liberty.] Genius of a suffering land, Whom the curst Enchanter's hand Vex'd with bonds and worse disdain, Well have you dash'd off your chain,— Well have you repaid him now, And must wear a laurell'd brow Of a grace and of a hue, Such as Conquest's merer crew Never could have won for you. Only when you take to wing, And return to governing, Recollect for those you rule, What you learnt in Sorrow's school, And acquaint their homes with me, Triumph-teaching Liberty. Seat you now in well-earn'd state, While the pomps we celebrate. The Genius here gracefully making an obeisance moves on towards the side-scene, and then, quitting his chariot, which is borne away, turns round and ascends for his throne a portion of the cloud, which the cherubs roll off for that purpose. When he is seated, he puts on his crown, and Mabiel proclaims,— [Mabiel.] So our Goddess, wise and free, Wills that every crown should be:— This is the true sovereignty. Trumpets as before:—an Austrian march;—enter a similar Genius in a car sculptured with instruments of war and music, a silver eagle standing on the front edge. Liberty in the same manner presents him with a crown, and addresses him:— [Liberty.] Genius of a suffering land, Whom the curst Enchanter's hand Pluck'd from your old towering height, Well have you return'd to light!— Well have you repaid him now, And must wear a laurell'd brow Of a grace and of a hue, Such as Conquest's merer crew Never could have won for you. Only this remember well For your surest counter-spell,— 'Tis not age and height alone Can secure the staidest throne From the reach of Change or Death,— But an eye to all beneath, And an air kept pure for me Life-supplying Liberty. Seat you now in well-earn'd state, While the pomps we celebrate. The Genius takes his seat by the side of the preceding one, and puts on his laurel, upon which Phaniel proclaims,— [Phaniel.] So our Goddess, wise and free, Wills that every crown should be:— This is the true sovereignty. Trumpets as before:—a Russian march;—enter a similar Genius in a car of crystal ice sculptured with instruments of war and with scaffolded cities, a golden eagle standing on the front edge. Liberty presents him with the crown, and addresses him:— [Liberty.] Genius of a rising land, Whom the foil'd Enchanter's hand Reach'd but to recoil with pain, Well have you repulsed his chain!— Well have you repaid him now, And must wear a laurell'd brow Of a grace and of a hue, Such as Conquest's merer crew Never could have won for you. Would you make it nobler still?— There's a land was heap'd with ill By sinning pow'rs that ruled before you, Whose repentant pains implore you, Joining with this free-voiced season, And your own asserted reason, To restore it. Do,—and blest For this good deed and all the rest; Be esteem'd; and may the ray Which you have help'd to clear away, Stretch into your distant sphere, Without the storms that brought it here. Seat you now in well-earn'd state, While the pomps we celebrate. The Genius here moves round the scene, so as to return to the side at which he entered, and seats himself opposite to the preceding one; then putting on his laurel, Mabiel proclaims:— [Mabiel.] So our Goddess, wise and free, Wills that every crown should be:— This is the true sovereignty. Trumpets as before:—‘Britons, strike home;’—enter a similar Genius, but with a laurel already on his head, and a halo of light also about it. He is in a car sculptured with emblems of all the arts, a golden lion standing on the front edge. Liberty smilingly spreads forth her hand at his approach, and addresses him:— [Liberty.] Genius of a glorious land, Whom the vex'd Enchanter's hand Never yet could venture near, Spell-bound with a marble fear, (For he felt a strange impression From your eyes' free self-possession, And the ring of watery light Rippling round your forehead white,) Long have you my laurels worn; And though some under leaves be torn Here and there, yet what remains Still it's pointed green retains, And still an easy shade supplies To your calm-kept, watchful eyes. Only would you keep it bright'ning, And it's power to shake the light'ning Harmless down it's glossy ears, Suffer not so many years To try what they can bend and spoil, But oftener in it's native soil Let the returning slip renew It's upward sap and equal hue; And wear it then, with glory shaded, Till the spent earth itself be faded. Seat you now in your old state, While the pomps we celebrate. The Genius here rides round the scene like the former one, and then takes his seat opposite to the one that entered first, so as to be the nearest on the right hand of Liberty; upon which Phaniel proclaims,— [Phaniel.] So our Goddess, wise and free, Wills that every crown should be:— This is the true sovereignty. A flourish of concluding music from the Genii. Liberty speaks:— [Liberty.] Phaniel and Mabiel, sparkling servants mine, You know what blessing we must first invoke From the clear sky. These noble Spirits here Will join to charm her down. She is all heart, Affectionate and quick, and only waits A tender word to slip from heav'n with smiles. Duet.—Phaniel and Mabiel sing. O wrapping looks and balmy tongue, Sweet as summer air through tree, Remember'd when this age was young, Like sights beheld in infancy,— O Peace, whose very name's a pleasure, Re-appear To bless us here, And light with silken foot upon our leisure! First Genius speaks. By the last tear that hangs to day, For thy kiss to clip away; Second Genius. By the toil of struggling hearts, That rest them from their final parts; Third Genius. By hopes, that wait in rising lands A blessing from thy gentle hands; Fourth Genius. By home-delights, and spirits free, And one full sigh of earth and sea, And victorious Liberty; The two Spirits taking up the song again. Re-appear! Re-appear! Chorus of Spectators. Earth is worthy to regain thee, And hopes it may not always pain thee. A pause of listening silence, and then an exquisite voice in the air:— [Voice in the Air.] Greatest Goddess of our sphere, Elves, and human beings dear, I am here! I am here! A descent of turtle doves, who sweep gently off in pairs on either side, and a couple of snowy feet are discerned treading the air, as it were, softly downwards. The whole figure soon appears, and a strain of flutes welcomes the arrival of Peace. She is habited in white like an angel, with dove-coloured wings, on which she comes hovering down, a sheep-bell hanging on one of the fingers of her right hand, and a wreath of olive and myrtle on her head. As she descends, she spreads her hands hither and thither with gestures of benediction, and alighting at the foot of Liberty, embraces her with upward-looking affection and reverence, taking her seat there in conclusion. The spectators stretch out their hands in an attitude of eager and mute worship. Liberty. I must thank thee, sweet, I fear; For among the voices here Gushes of sweet tears have broken; But how indeed could they have spoken, Who beheld at once in thee Worlds of home felicity,— Hopes come back, that all seem'd gone,— Bosoms, which their griefs lay on? Charm'd they are at ears and eyes, And as with new faculties Seem to look abroad and hear Basking silence wrap the sphere, While the clouds hush off in racks, And in long-left golden tracks Ships to ships on the still sea Glance with broad sail courteously; And on land, for countless miles, Passion rests and Nature smiles, And not a harsher sound is heard Than of nest-resuming bird, With flocks, and streams, and village calls, And bells, that winds fling out o'er walls From joyous towns at intervals. Come; 'tis our's, assembled here, To flush the triumph. Goddess dear, If the tenderness within Has left thy voice, begin, begin, And summon from their waiting climes The pleasures that perfect victorious times. Peace. I obey; and thus commence With one shall freshen unexerted sense. She sings. Holder of the smiles of heaven, Listening eye and forehead even, Who from out the thrill'd air broke, When Love first saw the light and spoke, O Music, mildest, Warmest, wildest, Wind thee down from sphere to sphere, And meet us here! Chorus of Cherubs. Earth is worthy now of thee, And only waits thy harmony. A sweet sound in the air, gradually descending, and growing louder, the winds themselves making a harmony as they swell among the trees. A cloud then appears from the top of the scene, and bursting open with a fullness of fine sounds, Music issues forth in a floating drapery of blue, and playing on a golden lyre, the cloud in the mean time closing under her, and furnishing her with a throne. Ceasing to play, she begins to descend very slowly towards the left hand of Liberty, and again passing her hand across the strings with a hasty prelude, and then waving it commandingly in the air, a concert seems to pour in from all quarters, till it swells into a complete pomp of harmony, the whole closing as the cloud finally mingles with that of Liberty, and Music has taken her seat. Lib. Circler of the ear with bliss, Sweetest Goddess, thanks for this! Now for the eye's rich artifice. The second Song of Peace. Oh many-blushing beauty, born Of Iris and the Prince of Morn, Painting,—Vision's choice completeness, With sweepy shape, and summer lips, And hand, that into roses dips It's careless-playing finger tips, Contrasting sweetness; O wheresoe'er thou look'st from air, Shaping the clouds that purple there, Or shedding landscapes in the fountains, Or showing sights of tow'r and tree In fairy mirror o'er the sea Of wonder-eyed Parthenope, And her red mountains; O sparkler of the sapphire sphere, Visit us here! Chorus. Earth is worthy now of thee, And only waits thy brilliancy. The cloud, on which the celestial visitors are sitting, is suddenly tinged about with the prismatic colours, and a rainbow half appearing towards the side, and pitching it's tip on the right of Liberty, Painting is seen in a mixed habit of purple and yellow, gliding down over it on another cloud. She makes an obeisance to Liberty, and keeps in motion a hand-mirror, which at first only throws out a vanishing light on the objects below, like a jack-o'-lantern, but upon being raised a little higher and held steadily opposite to the horizon in the back-ground, suddenly reflects upon that quarter a clear and exact representation of the whole scene, only rendered more beautiful and gorgeous. Then turning her glass again, the picture vanishes, and having by this time descended, she takes her seat on the right of Liberty, the rainbow relapsing into air. Lib. Filler of the eye with bliss, Brightest Goddess, thanks for this! Now for the thought's free artifice. The third Song of Peace. O best Enchantress, unconfined, Full of all the Mighty Mind,— Lustrous forehead laurel-leaved, Whom Psyche of her love conceived In the voiceful, golden house, When first he came mysterious, O spare us from addressing thee, All accomplished Poetry, And turning quick eye, deep and clear, Glance thee down here! Chorus. Earth is worthy now of thee, And only waits thy witchery. A sudden flash of radiance with sweet sounds and perfumes, and to the transport of the beholders, who all start forward except Liberty, Poetry breaks at once from out the air, lying as it were upon her wings, and looking with bright-eyed earnestness upon the scene. She is in a robe of carnation or flesh-colour, scarfed with green, her wings like the bird of Paradise, her head crowned with laurel and surmounted by a lambent fire, and a magic wand in her hand. After a moment's pause, during which those who had risen reseat themselves, she takes off her crown with an obeisance to Liberty, and then replacing it, and calling up, with a motion of her wand, a portion of the cloud underneath her, reclines in a noble attitude, and recites to an accompaniment of unseen harps the following verses: [Poetry.] From isles that streak the mellowing west, And enclosing bowers of rest, By whose doors pellucid streams Break on pebbled pearl in beams, Hither with a thought am I At call of Peace and Liberty. There I left on rosy beds The poets with their laurell'd heads, Who when on earth gave happy voice To Truth and Right, and now rejoice Each with her he loved the best, Pleasure-eyed, in perfect rest, Till by length of lovely deeds, Such as mortal guess exceeds, Both earn them wings, and hand in hand Start for still diviner land. There too on appointed days, Their opening ears discern the praise, And their far-off eyes the worth, Of those whom they delight on earth, Which all the while, by charm serene, Is amply yet minutely seen In the blue depths rolling green. Then before me they appear, Each with his divinest dear, And in friendly zeal contend, Which of all, to some great end Of good and just, can raise to sight Happiest visions of delight, By themselves perhaps to be After made reality. But I may not fetch ye those.— Come then, old poetic shows, Shadows of abstracted things, That with your different colourings Have in different ages been The pomp and service of your Queen; And with ye come, to close your trains, Those who ruled your several reigns, And best disposed ye, or indued, To charm the thought-struck multitude. Here Poetry waves her wand, and several stately and gorgeous visions pass through the air, the actual back-ground of the scene changing with them. For the first, the back-ground changes into groves, temples, and mountains, such as those of Delphos and Parnassus; and a music striking up, consisting of pipes, lyres, and timbrels, with a smell of incense accompanying, there passes through the air a line of ancient deities, Jupiter, the Muses, Venus, Apollo, Mercury, Cupid and Psyche, &amp;c. who, vanishing all at once, are succeeded by the forms of Homer, Pindar, Theocritus, and the Greek tragedians, all crowned with laurel, and seated on a cloud in chairs of marble. These vanish in the same manner; the back-ground shifts into a delicious scene of gardens and palaces, with castles at intervals and spots of wildness; and the music, after a short and rustic amatory strain on the harp, changes into an ardent flourish of trumpets, when a vision, in two groups, of horse and horsemen appears, part riding with dignity, others with a lightsome ease, others with a forward or rearing eagerness. The horses are variously trapped, but the horsemen all mantled with red cloaks over their suits of armour; and by their banners are recognized, in the first group, King Arthur and his Knights of the Round Table, Launcelot, Tristan, &amp;c. and in the second, Charlemagne and his Peers, Roland, Rinaldo, and others. They are followed by bearded enchanters attired in long cloaks, and riding on griffins and other animals, with wands and books in their hands; when the whole suddenly vanishing are succeeded by the forms of Pulci, Ariosto, Tasso, and Spenser, crowned with laurel and seated on thrones of tapestry. The back-ground then changes, for the third time, to an ethereal scene, in which hangs the Earth like a planet with the Moon moving round it; and to the sound of various and delightful music, a troop of fairies first cross the air with gestures of quaint pretension and tricksome loveliness,—then a company of ordinary human beings from the king to the peasant,—and then again, creatures of the fancy, Ariel, Caliban, Comus, &amp;c. ending with the majestic but melancholy form of Satan, sailing along in a swarthy mist. These vanishing in their turn, are replaced by three Gothic seats, in which are enthroned the shapes of Chaucer, Shakspeare, and Milton, crowned with laurel, and holding globes in their hands,—the first a terrestrial, the third a celestial, and the second a double one of both. The whole then disappears; a tremulous and small music is heard as in conclusion: and while the original scene is returning in the back-ground, Poetry descends on the wing, and seats herself in a reclining posture, on an upper part of the cloud, a little behind the head of Liberty. Lib. Filler of deep thoughts with bliss, Supplying what on earth we miss, Finish'd Goddess, thanks for this! She continues. And now the two great blessings of the time, Whom all may know,—the only true amenders, The builders of glad homes,—let them appear, And strike into our smiles security;— Experience old the one, scar-cheek'd and sage, Whose touch is thought;—the other a fresh knight, Long tranced in Gothic sepulchre, now freed And turn'd to youth again, whom this my champion, The Genius with his ready-laurell'd hair, Brought back to light victoriously, through crowds Of grinning lumps and chattering enmities, Who gnaw'd themselves for spite to view the arm Should drive their ancient darkness,—Education. Enter Experience crossing the stage, a troop of sorrowful spirits sailing before him, and another of joyful ones skimming after, the music shifting from grave to gay accordingly. He is a venerable figure, with a white uncovered head, a touchstone in one hand, a pilgrim's staff in the other, and wearing a grey robe over a suit of battered armour. As he goes by, he salutes Liberty with a gesture of benediction, the Goddess crossing her arms in return, and bending her pleased head in acknowledgment. Education follows from the same side and in the same path; and is a smiling, manly youth, in a succinct habit, with a sheathed sword hanging behind him, and holding up in display a golden book, from which a light strikes on the faces of a troop of boys who precede him in babits of different colours, and who look back upon it as they go lightly along, holding each other's hands at arm's length. Two guardian angels follow on the wing, the one crowned with roses, the other bearing a light yoke on her neck, and resting her arm on her companion's shoulder, who turns affectionately to look at her. These are Pleasure and Duty.—As the youth passes, he bows his head reverently, and takes his benediction from Liberty, as she received hers from his fore-runner. Lib. These for the mind.—Now for the body's blessings, Without whose help the over-conscious mind, Prison'd from power of change, inhabits it Like a sad spirit pent in his own wand,— The thing which he should lightly bear about For his free purposes. Summon them in, Sweet Peace, and smoothe us with another song, Then for my wisest contrast, and so finish. The fourth Song of Peace. O Thou that art our Queen again, And may in the sun be seen again, Come, Ceres, come, For the war's gone home, And the fields are quiet and green again. The air, dear Goddess, sighs for thee, The light-heart brooks arise for thee, And the poppies red On their wistful bed Turn up their dark blue eyes for thee. Laugh out in the loose green jerkin That's fit for a goddess to work in, With shoulders brown, And the wheaten crown About thy temples perking. And with thee come Stout Heart in, And Toil, that sleeps his cart in, And Exercise, The ruddy and wise, His bathed forelocks parting. And Dancing too, that's lither Than willow or birch, drop hither, To thread the place With a finishing grace, And carry our smooth eyes with her. Enter three rustic figures of Stout Heart, Toil, and Exercise, with a band of Reapers and Vine-gatherers, male and female,—the first a manly swain in corderoy with an oaken cudgel, the second in white with a fork over his shoulder, the third in green with a vaulting-staff, and buskined. The rest of the men have sickles and pruning-hooks at their side, handled like swords and hanging from sword-belts;—the women are in short white gowns with rose-coloured boddices, and straw hats with ribands. To them, overhead, enter Ceres, reclining on a horn of plenty, and gliding slowly along on a summer cloud. She is a plump and laughing figure, dressed in a loose green boddice, with bare shoulders, large auburn curls, and a crown of wheat. As she goes along, she makes joyful salutes to Peace and Liberty, and the back-ground breaks into golden fields of corn that wave in the sunshine, while vines run over a hill in the distance, and the trees in front are hung with them like garlands from bough to bough. Trio and Chorus. All joy to the giver of wine and of corn, With her elbow at ease on her well-fill'd horn; To the sunny cheek brown, And the shady wheat crown, And the ripe golden locks that come smelling of morn. Stout Heart. 'Tis she in our veins that puts daily delight; Toil. 'Tis she in our beds puts us kindly at night; Exercise. And taps at our doors in the morning bright. Chorus. Then joy to the giver, &amp;c. We'll sling on our flaskets, and forth with the sun, With our trim-ancled yoke-fellows, every one; We'll gather and reap With our arm at a sweep, And oh! for the dancing when all is done; Exercise. Yes, yes, we'll be up when the singing-bird starts; Toil. We'll level her harvests, and fill up her carts; Stout Heart. And shake off fatigue with our bounding hearts: Chorus. Then hey for the flaskets, &amp;c. By this time Ceres has crossed the scene; and a sunbeam suddenly striking down to the middle of it in front of Liberty, a lightsome figure with wings at her feet and shoulders comes rapidly tripping down it, and, taking a spring before she reaches the bottom, leaps into a graceful attitude of preparation. Chorus of a few voices male and female. And see, to set us moving, here is Dancing here, With the breezes at her ancles, and her winsome cheer, With her in-and-out deliciousness, and bending ear; Nay, trip it first awhile To thine own sweet smile, And we'll follow, follow, follow to thee, Dancing dear. Here Dancing twirls round and makes an obeisance to Liberty, and then taking up the measure of the Chorus, which is that of a dance by a single person, performs a movement of that description, at the conclusion of which, the sunbeam suddenly striking down again, she spreads her wings, and glancingly returns up it. The Reapers and Vine-gatherers then join in a general dance, which is all at once interrupted by a loud noise, accompanied with groans and clashing of chains:—they separate in disorder. Lib. What's this that mars the time's new loveliness With such return of horror? Enter hastily a Sable Genius, with fetter-rings at his wrists, a few of the links not broken off; and prostrates himself in front of Liberty. What again The Southern Genius troubled! What has caused This evil fear in thee, unhappy spirit? Thy hands, though some remains of outrage gall them, Tug not as heretofore, one with the other, In linked anguish:—thou hast freer looks, Spite of this posture, and a firmer presence. I thought the noble heart here on the right,— The ready-laurell'd,—had smoothed all for thee, And left thee to new hopes and safer slumbers Sable Gen. (Rising.) He had, great Mistress, and I bless him for it. But last night, burthen'd I could scarce tell how With drooping recollections and heap'd thoughts, I slept for sorrow; and the searching toil Not having left, as it should seem, my mind Even in that refreshment, I had dreams; And dreams, thou knowest, though they play confused About the grosser faculties of man Like hints of other spheres, are to a spirit Clear and true mirrors of impending fate, Like wells, in which the looker-down perceives What's passing o'er his head, or coming cloud. Methought that on the breathing shore I sat Of the wide sea, looking upon it now With inward-smiling eye, and fresh-blown cheek, And now reverting to the champain green On which the untaught race, whose guard I am, Danced at clear evening to their humming music Midst their low cabins and tall-shafted trees. On both I look'd; and these my brethren great Bless'd in my heart, to think that they had made The watery neighbourhood so sweet and safe, When lo! while heart, and ear, and all was quiet, Just in the pause of the resounding dance, A horrid peal of laughter o'er the wave Came clattering, and from out the liny distance Some of those old and coast-descending monsters, Whom we had all thought quell'd, rose to the light, Swelling their ship's pale wings, and plunging fierce It's hastening breast towards us;—all, at once, Saw them and knew, and struck through knees and heart With fear as with a trembling arrow, stood Lost;—even I, though an immortal spirit With storms familiar, who can catch the lightning, And let the lion's voice lull me to sleep, Felt the old spell upon me, and at thought Of what my sons might suffer once again, Of wives and children from each other torn To glut th' accursed in their distant haunts, Of stripes and sorrows, bitter-turning bloods, Impatiencies, moist-covering agonies,— Or if by death escaping,—suffocations With struggling cheek under the hot pent boards, Or home-sick hearts that break in the mid sea, Was agitated so, and felt the suddenness Athwart my nature with so keen an edge, That I too rose bewildered, and stood staring Till the foul vision to the shore came nigh; With human voice it came, and cried aloud, ‘Twice are ye sold, ye wretches, twice are sold To me and mine: fresh compact has been made, Now that your fellow-creatures have grown happier, Shaking all off in their own loose from care, And I am here again:—bring out your wives, Bring out your wives, ye husbands,—youths, your loves, Mothers, your children,—that I may select My victims, and with their united agonies O'er the far sea return, leaving your eyes And hearts to burst on the impossible shore!’ So saying, the Execrable, coming on, Lifted, as he was wont, the mocking flag That gave pretended colour to his crimes, The ? Lib. Whose device was on that impious remnant? What daring land's? Sable Gen. The land I tread on now:— (A pause; Liberty looks about her with surprise and anger, and the spectators turn down their eyes.) The sight of which, hearing what I had heard, Of joy and freedom to this very land Restored, such active rage flush'd into me, That, turning to the rock by which I sat, I grappled with a crag, thinking to whelm Th' approaching horror in the wave before me, When with the struggle suddenly I woke Clasping my leaping temples, and sprang hither Through the clear wind to come and call upon thee, On thee, O Liberty, and thy great heart. Lib. Thy call shall not be useless.—To be sure, Ye are strange creatures, mortals,—most of ye,— And worth the laughter of immortal spirits, Were fond self-love our sovereign principle, As it seems yours:—but this remembrance checks Both laughter and poor anger, and prevents A wretched wish, to which this fearful dream Had nigh degraded me,—a wish, almost, That I had left th' oppressor to his work. But it must not be so; all human good Mounts by degrees, and those but slippery ones Apt to slide back again, nor must I visit Upon the thoughtless many the vile few. Eun. Blessings attend thee! Lib. Good old man, and thee,— And thine, and mayest thou see deserving joy Complete this land's security, and lead It's proper dance on every lightsome green, Thyself and such as thou sitting cool-hair'd, In golden shade of arm-o'er-reaching boughs. And, to this good end, hear me, Eunomus;— What masters ye may choose for your new lords, New or restored, is left, as best befits The gifts of Liberty, to your free selves:— But should this plague, as from the spirit's dream I fear, again be loosed upon the south, Whether from want of thought, or barbarous habits Left by long war, or fear, self-realized, That yields to evil from despair of good, Or bitterer conclusion still, brought on By diseased sorrow, arguing with itself, Whose argument is it's disease's proof, Wanting the cure of action,—whether this, Or worse than all, whether from rank indifference, Which neither joy nor sorrow, rain nor shine, Can touch with kindliness for other's good, Content to heave it's own gross uselessness Out in the sun, and spoil the soil it swells on,— Whether from this or that, from part or all, It must and shall not be;—from this time forth The few must know their service to the many: Knowledge and I have given the world a voice Fit for it's frame, nor at this special moment, When one huge wrong, contemptuous of mankind, Has been o'erthrown, shall they endure to see Part of it's veriest slaves conspire another. Be it thy task then, wise old man, and all Who would scape blushing for their native land, To spread this warning voice; and should at last The dream come true, I will myself inspire Those noblest of their race, who walk in lustre Beneath the star of this my genius here, To rise once more in their brave scorn, and win One last, preventing, and perfecting triumph. Sable Gen. And shall it then indeed be so? Whither shall I turn to go? Whither turn, or how depart, Scatter'd with delight of heart? But I lose my recollection.— Goddess of all sound perfection, Since thy sons will not forsake me, Back again I now betake me In a light and lifting breeze O'er the lands that bask at ease And the cool up-striking seas, To revive with far-eyed coming Dinning strings and tabors drumming, And to set the fresh-limb'd pleasure Up in many a desperate measure, Till a thousand homely joys Break abroad with giddy noise; And the lover decks his maid In the tall tree's lump of shade; And the babe at the proud breast, Open-lipp'd, goes safe to rest; And all my lightsome race of jet Shall rise in worth and knowledge yet. Here making a farewell and grateful obeisance, the Sable Genius springs backward from the earth, and then turning in the air, goes off at the side-scene. Lib. This thoughtful interruption, though it break Our joy's completeness, gives a double finish To what concludes. Come forth, contrasting shows, And with your moral this time's story close. Enter a Vision of False Glory. The back-ground changes into a city rich with palaces and triumphal arches, a smoky atmosphere rolling from behind it over a plain covered with burning cottages; and to the sound of trumpets and other warlike music, the front of the scene is crossed by a long train of laurelled soldiers, horse and foot. As they move onward, the word Slave is seen worked on their backs. To these succeeds a quantity of treasure in waggons, consisting of money, pictures, statues, &amp;c. and then follows a number of painters, poets, and musicians, with the emblems of their respective arts, and attired in gorgeous robes; but the same word is discovered on them; and as they pass, the three Goddesses, who preside over them, turn down their eyes in disquiet. Lastly, comes a triumphal chariot, drawn by crowned monrachs, and containing the Conqueror dressed in purple, in a haughty attitude, with a crown of laurel on his head, and holding in his hand a globe with a figure of Victory. As he proceeds, a slender gilt chain is discerned reaching from the back of his neck into a dark cloud that follows, behind which are several turbulent, weeping, and indignant shapes, representing the Passions, Misery, Widowhood, &amp;c. the first having hold of the chain, and the figure of Pity closing the whole. Enter a Vision of Real Glory. The back-ground keeps the palaces and triumphal arches, but changes farther back into fields of rural beauty; and the front scene is crossed in like manner by a train of yeomanry or armed peasants crowned with laurel, each bearing a sheathed sword in one hand and a bunch of wheat in the other. These are followed by poets, painters, and musicians, carrying the emblems of their respective arts, but wearing an air of frankness, and treading with a firm step. To these succeed a number of venerable old men, and then a train of marriageable young men and women, two by two, the former crowned with olive and the latter with roses; and after all, in a chariot drawn by white horses, and in a succinct habit of the same colour, appears the Conqueror, crowned with laurel and oak, and holding in his hand upon a globe a figure of Liberty. A snowy cloud follows, behind which are radiant angelic figures, Serenity, Happiness, &amp;c. the whole concluding with the figure of Homage, bearing aloft a heart in his two hands, to which he looks upward with veneration. A snatch of fine music:—Liberty speaks:— [Liberty.] All is finish'd. Now I rise Back to my wide-breathing skies, Where there is no hindering To the heart or to the wing; But the planets, round and free, Lapse about eternally, And the space through which they burn Feels a thrill at my return, And the never-tiring Joy, Rosy and heart-dancing boy, On continual errand runs In and out a thousand suns. There sometimes, when I have ended What my daily task intended, I sit looking, with still eyes, At the many-starred skies, Or go pace the central sun With his gardens, every one, Where the golden light is kept, And the winds are music swept; Or in graver mood take wing Beyond the bounds of every thing, And look in, with half-check'd sight, On the unform'd infinite, Where with his eternal ear Time is listening.—Mortals dear, Think on all I've done and said, And keep my blessings on your head. Here the great cloud, on which Liberty is seated, begins to disengage itself from the others,—Peace and the rest of the Goddesses joining in a Chorus. Call up then in gathering measure All the sounds of lofty pleasure, Pipes of deep continuous blow, Fuming ventage, stately bow, Ivory dint of dancing fingers, Touch that leaves, and voice that lingers, Hands that plunge in panting wires,— Till our own full voice aspires To attend our sovereign Queen, With vows and lifted looks between, Up into the blue serene. The cloud begins to rise with Liberty and her attendant spirits, and all the spectators burst into the Final Chorus. O dear Goddess, wherever we are, We'll never forget thee, we'll never forget thee; Spots may come over our mortal star, But a light must remain upon all who have met thee. Rise, rise; To thine airy skies, With the bliss of good deeds in thy bosom and eyes. Thou hast taught us a lesson our children shall learn, And made the homes happy to which we return. [Exeunt Omnes. EPILOGUE. POETA LOQUITUR. 'Tis done. The vision from my fancy's eye Fades, gleam by gleam, into the closing sky; And the far sounds, touching from sphere to sphere With upward lessening, baffle the fix'd ear. But not directly does the earthly chain, That holds me here, come closing round again; Not instantly the darkening wall comes nigh; The brighten'd spot yet breathes of Liberty; The fine and holier circle charms me still, Drawn by the quickness of the Muse's quill; And Silence, listening as at dead of night, Sits with her finger up, hushing Delight. THE END.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">VOL II HERO AND LEANDER BACCHUS AND ARIADNE AND THE FEAST OF THE POETS Love is too young to know what Conscience is; Yet who knows not, Conscience is born of Love? SHAKSPEARE. HERO AND LEANDER. The hour of worship's over; and the flute And choral voices of the girls are mute; And by degrees the people have departed Homeward, with gentle step, and quiet-hearted; The jealous easy, the desponding healed; The timid, hopeful of their love concealed; The sprightlier maiden, sure of nuptial joys; And mothers, grateful for their rosy boys. All, all is still about the odorous grove, That wraps the temple of the Queen of Love, All but the sparrows twittering from the eaves, And inward voice of doves among the leaves, And the cool, hiding noise of brooks in bowers, And bees, that dart in bosoms of the flowers, And now and then, a breath-increasing breeze That comes amidst a world of tumbling trees, And makes them pant, and shift against the light, About the marble roof, solid and sunny bright. Only some stragglers loiter round the place To catch a glimpse of Hero's heavenly face,— Hero, the loveliest of a lovely train, That did the gentle service of the fane. And now and then, there comes upon their ears A slender step; and some sweet girl appears, Some sister priestess with a rosy crown, Who hastens by, with eyes half looking down, Carrying a golden torch, or ivory casket, Or, on her head, doves in a milk-white basket. But Hero comes not as she used to do; They watch, and watch, and keep the door in view; Till almost all, hopeless of further stay, One after one, drop silently away. At last she comes; yet scarcely has stepped out, And cast, with a quick blush, her eyes about, Than turning back, she leaves them in fresh pain:— Not long however,—for she comes again, Bringing a golden torch;—and so with pace A little slackened, and still rosier face, Passes their looks; and turning by a bower, Hastens to hide her in her lonely tower. The tower o'erlooks the sea; and there she sits Grave with glad thoughts, and watching it by fits; For o'er that sea, and by that torch's light, Her love, Leander, is to come at night,— To come, not sailing, nor with help of oar, But with his own warm heart and arms,—no more; A naked bridegroom, bound from shore to shore. And yet 'twas he that in the porch but now, Had held her, and had kissed, she scarce knew how And after months of mutual admiration Felt more than told, and glancing inclination, (For he was but an ardent youth, and she Of a severe and wealthier family,) Had made her say, or rather look, in spite Of what she said, that he might come that night, And take her for his bride, and plight his truth By Venus, and the waves, and uncorrupted youth. So there she sat; and looking vaguely through The arching trees that at her window grew, Started a moment, as across the sea She saw his bark go homeward airily. But 'twas her wish that he should not remain Waiting, till night, concealed about the fane; And he himself, however loth to go, Preferred returning for an hour or so, To hinder friends from wondering with each other, And above all, to comfort a kind mother. So she sat fixed, thinking, and thinking on; And wished, and yet did not, the time were gone; And started then, and blushed, and then was fain To try some work, and then sat down again; And lost to the green trees with their sweet singers, Tapped on the casement's ledge with idle fingers. Hesper meanwhile, the star with amorous eye, Shot his fine sparkle from the deep blue sky. A depth of night succeeded, dark, but clear, Such as presents the hollow starry sphere Like a high gulf to heaven: and all above Seems waking to a fervid work of love. A nightingale, in transport, seemed to fling His warble out, and then sit listening: And ever and anon, amidst the flush Of the thick leaves, there ran a breezy gush; And then, from dewy myrtles lately bloomed, An odour small, in at the window, fumed. At last, with twinkle o'er a distant tower, A star appeared that was to shew the hour. The virgin saw; and going to a room Which held an altar burning with perfume, Cut off a lock of her dark solid hair, And laid it, with a little whispered prayer, Before a statue, that of marble bright Sat smiling downwards o'er the rosy light. Then at the flame the torch of gold she lit, And o'er her head anxiously holding it, Ascended to the roof; and leaning there, Lifted its light into the darksome air. The boy beheld,—beheld it from the sea, And parted his wet locks, and breathed with glee, And rose, in swimming, more triumphantly. He had not long left home; but at the shore He made no stay; his eye but just ran o'er The hills behind; and stripping him, he laid His clothes within a nook some holm-trees made, And o'er the pebbles, in his naked pride, Trampling the surf, rushed down into the tide. Smooth was the sea that night, the lover strong, And in the springy waves he danced along. He rose, he dipped his breast, he aimed, he cut With his clear arms, and from before him put The parting waves, and in and out the air His shoulders felt, and trailed his washing hair; But when he saw the torch, oh, how he sprung, And thrust his feet against the waves, and flung The foam behind, as though he scorned the sea, And parted his wet locks, and breathed with glee, And rose, and panted, most triumphantly! Arrived at last on shallow ground, he saw The flaring light, as if in haste, withdraw. Again it issued just above the door With a white hand, and vanished as before. Then rising, with a sudden-ceasing sound Of wateriness, he stood on the firm ground, And treading up a little slippery bank, With jutting myrtles mixed, and verdure dank, Came to a door ajar,—all hushed, all blind With darkness; yet he guessed who stood behind; And entering with a turn, the breathless youth Slid round a gentle cheek, and kissed a warm kind mouth. So lingered they awhile; then silent still Went up the stairs; when she, with gentle thrill, A little bashful, yet ashamed to be, Performed the rites of hospitality. His glazy limbs she dried, and dripping locks, And emptied rosy essence from a box; And so restored him to himself again From the faint toil and rankness of the main. Then, on the genial couch, she took his head, And laid her bosom to his cheek, and said,— “Leander, I do love you; you can take So brave a journey for a lady's sake; And you are kind and good,—so that to meet Your very aspect and your mind is sweet; And I could be content (and here she blushed) That you should lie to-night, embraced and hushed, And take your rest after the toilsome sea; Your love alone is such a wealth to me.” But looking up with glad yet reverent eyes, He breathed away the gentle self-disguise; And folding her, with doubled wish to bless, Strained to his heart the cordial shapeliness. Pleasure be with them, and affectionate sleep! I say no more; for foolish men still keep Their vice-creating ways, and still are blindest To what is happiest, loveliest, best, and kindest. Thus passed the summer shadows in delight: Leander came as surely as the night, And when the morning woke upon the sea, It saw him not, for back at home was he. Sometimes, when it blew fresh, the struggling flare Seemed out; but then he knew his Hero's care, And that she only walled it with her cloak; Brighter again from out the dark it broke. Sometimes the night was almost clear as day, Wanting no torch; and then, with easy play, He dipped along beneath the silver moon, Placidly hearkening to the water's tune. The people round the country, who from far Used to behold the torch, thought it a star, Set there perhaps by Venus as a wonder, To mark the favourite maiden who slept under. Therefore they trod about the grounds by day Gently; and fishermen at night, they say, With reverence kept aloof, cutting their silent way. But whether we are things too weak to be Long happy, beyond mere placidity; Or whether we must taste bitterness here, To exalt our relish for a perfect sphere; Or whether there are joys, which when the gods See plucked, as 'twere, from out their own abodes, They say, “Those mortals have discerned a prize, Which they must come up here to realize;” Or lastly, whether like distempered men, Who want their cure from nature's breast again, We talk of griefs and follies, yet lay claim To praise for both, and call it a good name, Hugging our thorns, and taking reverend measures To cut short all offenders who get pleasures, I know not; but if one true joy there spring, The world must have its speedy poisoning,— Must interfere, some way, to make it hard Of getting, or to blast it when not barred; And thus it is, that happiest linked loves Glance and are gone sometimes, like passing doves; Or like two dancers gliding from a green; Or two sky-streaks, filling with clouds between. All we can hope is, that so sweet a smile Goes somewhere to continue; and meanwhile, Hopes, joys, and sorrows link our days together, Like spring, and summer-time, and wintery weather. For autumn now was over; and the crane Began to clang against the coming rain, And peevish winds ran cutting o'er the sea, Which at its best looked dark and slatily. The gentle girl, before he went away, Would look out sadly toward the cold-eyed day, And often beg him not to come that night; But still he came, and still she blessed his sight; And so, from day to day, he came and went, Till time had almost made her confident. One evening, as she sat, twining sweet bay And myrtle garlands for a holiday, And watched at intervals the dreary sky, In which the dim sun held a languid eye, She thought with such a full and quiet sweetness Of all Leander's love and his completeness, All that he was, and said, and looked, and dared, His form, his step, his noble head full-haired, And how she loved him, as might other women, And yet he earned her still with nightly swimming,— That the sharp pleasure moved her like a grief, And tears came dropping with their meek relief. Meantime the sun had sunk; the hilly mark Across the straits mixed with the mightier dark, And night came on. All noises by degrees Were hushed,—the fisher's call, the birds, the trees, All but the washing of the eternal seas. Hero looked out, and trembling augured ill, The darkness held its breath so very still. But yet she hoped he might arrive before The storm began, or not be far from shore; And crying, as she stretched forth in the air, “Bless him!” she turned, and said a tearful prayer, And mounted to the tower, and shook the torch's flare. But he, Leander, almost half across, Threw his blithe locks behind him with a toss, And hailed the light victoriously, secure Of clasping his kind love, so sweet and sure; When suddenly, a blast, as if in wrath, Sheer from the hills, came headlong on his path; Then started off; and driving round the sea, Dashed up the panting waters roaringly. The youth at once was thrust beneath the main With blinded eyes, but quickly rose again, And with a smile at heart, and stouter pride, Surmounted, like a god, the rearing tide. But what? The torch gone out! So long too! See, He thinks it comes! Ah, yes,—'tis she! 'tis she! Again he springs; and, though the winds arise Fiercer and fiercer, swims with ardent eyes; And always, though with ruffian waves dashed hard, Turns thither with glad groan his stout regard; And always, though his sense seems washed away, Emerges, fighting tow'rds the cordial ray. But driven about at last, and drenched the while, The noble boy loses that inward smile. For now, from one black atmosphere, the rain Sweeps into stubborn mixture with the main; And the brute wind, unmuffling all its roar, Storms;—and the light, gone out, is seen no more. Then dreadful thoughts of death, of waves heaped on him, And friends, and parting daylight, rush upon him. He thinks of prayers to Neptune and his daughters, And Venus, Hero's queen, sprung from the waters; And then of Hero only,—how she fares, And what she'll feel, when the blank morn appears; And at that thought he stiffens once again His limbs, and pants, and strains, and climbs,—in vain. Fierce draughts he swallows of the wilful wave, His tossing hands are lax, his blind look grave, Till the poor youth (and yet no coward he) Spoke once her name, and yielding wearily, Wept in the middle of the scornful sea. I need not tell how Hero, when her light Would burn no longer, passed that dreadful night; How she exclaimed, and wept, and could not sit One instant in one place; nor how she lit The torch a hundred times, and when she found 'Twas all in vain, her gentle head turned round Almost with rage; and in her fond despair She tried to call him through the deafening air. But when he came not,—when from hour to hour He came not,—though the storm had spent its power, And when the casement, at the dawn of light, Began to shew a square of ghastly white, She went up to the tower, and straining out To search the seas, downwards, and round about, She saw, at last,—she saw her lord indeed Floating, and washed about, like a vile weed;— On which such strength of passion and dismay Seized her, and such an impotence to stay, That from the turret, like a stricken dove, With fluttering arms she leaped, and joined her drowned love.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">VOL III FOLIAGE Still climbing trees in the Hesperides. —Shakspeare. DEDICATION. TO Sir JOHN EDW?. SWINBURNE, Bart. GREENWOODS, OR ORIGINAL POEMS. I doe not know what their sharpe sight may see Of late, but I should thinke it still might be, As 'twas, a happy age, when on the plaines The woodmen met the damsells. Ben Jonson. ? Bitter shame hath spoiled the sweet world's taste. Shakspeare. Under the greenwood tree Who loves to lie with me, And tune his merry note Unto the sweet bird's throat, Come hither, come hither, come hither. Here shall he see No enemy. Shakspeare. Quel ch'il ciel da se mostra, e la Natura. Lorenzo de' Medici. Questi fuor di città luoghi, ov'adorna Letitia sta, non mai lascianvi al core Spunti la vana Ambition le corna; Ne pur un breve dì, con lei soggiorna L'Avaritia, cagion quì d'ogni errore. Lodovico Paterno. THE NYMPHS. IN TWO PARTS. Dique petitorum, dixit, salvete locorum, Tuque novos cœlo terra datura Deos; Fluminaque, et Fontes, quibus utitur hospita tellus, Et Nemorum Divæ, Naïadumque chori. Ovid. PART I. Spirit, who waftest me where'er I will, And seest, with finer eyes, what infants see, Feeling all lovely truth With the wise health of everlasting youth, Beyond the motes of Bigotry's sick eye, Or the blind feel of false Philosophy,— O Spirit, O Muse of mine, Frank, and quick-dimpled to all social glee, And yet most sylvan of the earnest Nine, Who on the fountain-shedding hill, Leaning about among the clumpy bays Look at the clear Apollo while he plays;— Take me, now, now, and let me stand On some such lovely land, Where I may feel me, as I please, In dells among the trees, Or on some outward slope, with ruffling hair, Be level with the air; For a new smiling sense has shot down through me, And from the clouds, like stars, bright eyes are beckoning to me. Arrived! Arrived! O shady spots of ground, What calmness ye strike round, Hushing the soul as if with hand on lips! And are ye seen then but of animal eyes, Prone, or side-looking with a blank surmise? And do ye hear no finer-fancied words Than the sweet whistle of the repeating birds? And are ye haunted of no lovelier trips Than the poor stag's, who startled, as he sips, Perks up with timid mouth, from which the water drips? O ye whom ancient wisdom, in it's graces, Made guardians of these places; Etherial human shapes, perhaps the souls Of poets and poetic women, staying To have their fill of pipes and leafy playing, Ere they drink heavenly change from nectar-bowls; You finer people of the earth, Nymphs of all names, and woodland Geniuses, I see you, here and there, among the trees, Shrouded in noon-day respite of your mirth: This hum in air, which the still ear perceives, Is your unquarrelling voice among the leaves; And now I find, whose are the laughs and stirrings That make the delicate birds dart so in whisks and whirrings. There are the fair-limbed Nymphs o' the Woods, (Look ye, Whom kindred Fancies have brought after me!) There are the fair-limbed Dryads, who love nooks In the dry depth of oaks; Or feel the air in groves, or pull green dresses For their glad heads in rooty wildernesses; Or on the golden turf, o'er the dark lines, Which the sun makes when he declines, Bend their white dances in and out the pines. They tend all forests old, and meeting trees, Wood, copse, or queach, or slippery dell o'erhung With firs, and with their dusty apples strewn; And let the visiting beams the boughs among, And bless the trunks from clingings of disease And wasted hearts that to the night-wind groan. They screen the cuckoo when he sings; and teach The mother blackbird how to lead astray The unformed spirit of the foolish boy From thick to thick, from hedge to layery beech, When he would steal the huddled nest away Of yellow bills, up-gaping for their food, And spoil the song of the free solitude. And they, at sound of the brute, insolent horn, Hurry the deer out of the dewy morn; And take into their sudden laps with joy The startled hare that did but peep abroad; And from the trodden road Help the bruised hedgehog. But when tired, they love The back-turned pheasant, hanging from the tree His sunny drapery; And handy squirrel, nibbling hastily; And fragrant-living bee, So happy, that he will not move, not he, Without a song; and hidden, amorous dove, With his deep breath; and bird of wakeful glow, Whose louder song is like the voice of life, Triumphant o'er death's image; but whose deep, Low, lovelier note is like a gentle wife, A poor, a pensive, yet a happy one, Stealing, when day-light's common tasks are done, An hour for mother's work; and singing low, While her tired husband and her children sleep. Then, there the Hamadryads are, their sisters, Simpler crown twisters, Who of one favourite tree, in some sweet spot, Make home and leave it not, Until the ignorant axe downs it's fine head, And then the nymph is fled. And there are the Napeads,—names till now Scarce known, I know not how, To the rich bosom of my mother soil; For they in meads and little corner bowers Of hedge-row fields take care of the fresh flowers, Keeping their innocent wealth from early spoil Of beasts and blasts, and other blind mishaps, For little children's laps, And for the poet when he goes to hide him From the town's sight, and for the lass beside him. 'Tis they who nurse in the moist dells The mild primrose, and ring the sky-blue bells To the bee's ear in a grass-gliding breeze; Tis they encourage, and from tearful wet Dry up the grateful-breathing violet; And they that set at ease The sheath-enfolded fans of rosy bushes, Ready against their blushes; And for the Water-Nymphs', their cousins', sake, Lay out the lily on the lake; And teach the gentle cattle, when they sup, To leave the daisy and the buttercup; That when the bright-eyed Sun Looks out in May to see what has been done, The laughing meadows may be bold, And shew their bosoms to him, white and gold. Too far for me to see, the Limniad takes Her pleasure in the lakes; She, that with hills about her, loves to be At once at home and at her liberty. Far off I fancy, 'twixt their bowery isles, Her and her sisters playing their sweet wiles About a boat, which one of them sits in And will not let them win; Till comes a sudden gust, and parts them with new smiles. Nor can I see the lightsome-footed maids, The Oreads, that frequent the lifted mountains; Though by the Muses' help I still might shew, How some go leaping by the laughing fountains Down the touched crags; and some o'er deep ravines Sit listening to the talking streams below; And some in sloping glades Of pines lie musing, or betwixt high screens Of fern and flowers; or, like pavilioned queens Covered from heat of the blue silent skies, Sit perfumed underneath the cedarn shades, Feeding the gazel with his lamping eyes. Elsewhere, from ridge to ridge They lay the tempest-levelled tree for bridge; And help down the poor goat That stands close-footed with his shivering coat On a lone point; and echo the sweet calls The herdsman makes, when singing to their stalls The loitering cows with his home-loving strain, The Ranz-de-Vaches. That sighs, and carols, and then sighs again,— A song the sweeter for a taste of pain: And these are the kind terrors, that with sounds Of groans about the air, or earthly quaking, Or great gigantic shadows, that stand making Gestures upon the fog, warn the low grounds Against the dreadful snow-rocks, that at last Loos'd by the voiceful blast, Burst down from their heaped ices; and come raking O'er the crushed trees and dwellings nestling under, Into the dash'd-up stream, with loads of misty thunder. And O ye sweet and coy Ephydriads, you, Why are your names so new To islands which your liquid lips serene Keep ever green? There, there the Ephydriads haunt;—there, where a gap Betwixt a heap of tree-tops, hollow and dun, Shews where the waters run, And whence the fountain's tongue begins to lap. There lie they, lulled by little whiffling tones Of rills among the stones, Or by the rounder murmur, glib and flush, Of the escaping gush, That laughs and tumbles, like a conscious thing, For joy of all its future travelling. The lizard circuits them; and his grave will The frog, with reckoning leap, enjoys apart, Till now and then the woodcock frights his heart With brushing down to dip his dainty bill. Close by, from bank to bank, A little bridge there is, a one-railed plank; And all is woody, mossy, and watery. Sometimes a poet from that bridge might see A Nymph reach downwards, holding by a bough With tresses o'er her brow, And with her white back stoop The pushing stream to scoop In a green gourd cup, shining sunnily. The rills, a little farther onward, leave The shady hollows; and united, heave A river forth, that looking out as 'twere For his fine way, turns, and with widening fair, Lapses, full-bedded, between lawny brims. Thence, from the dazzling of the noon, he swims With darker sides into the woods, and there Washes the Nymphs, that in sun-sprinkled ease Haunt the white liquid spots, 'twixt shade-reflecting trees. Those are the Naiads, who keep neat The banks from sedge, and from the dull-dropp'd feet Of cattle that break down the fibrous mould. They snap the selfish nets, that, overbold, Cross the whole river, and might trip the keels Of summer boats. Their's are the kind appeals And unseen beckoning, holding baits of grass, That win the sheep into their washing-place; And they too, in their gentleness, uphold The sighing nostrils of the stag, when he Takes to the wrapping water wretchedly; And tow'rds the amorous noon, when some young poet Comes there to bathe, and yet half thrills to do it, Hovering with his ripe locks, and fair light limbs, And trying with cold foot the banks and brims, They win him to the water with sweet fancies, Till in the girdling stream he pants and dances. There's a whole bevy there in that recess Rounding from the main stream: some sleep, some dress Each other's locks, some swim about, some sit Parting their own moist hair, or fingering it Lightly, to let the curling air go through: Some make them green and lilied coronets new; And one there from her tender instep shakes The matted sedge; a second, as she swims, Looks round with pride upon her easy limbs; A third, just holding by a bough, lets float Her slumberous body like an anchored boat, Looking with level eye at the glib flakes And the strange crooked quivering which it makes, Seen through the weltering of the watery glass: Others (which make the rest look at them) pass, Nodding and smiling, in the middle tide, And luring swans on, which like fondled things Eye poutingly their hands; yet following, glide With unsuperfluous lift of their proud wings. And far beyond upon another side, Remembrance almost helps me to discern Their stouter sisters, the great Nereids, turn And toss upon the ocean's lifting billows, Making them banks and pillows, Upon whose springiness they lean and ride; Some with an inward back; some upward-eyed, Feeling the sky; and some with sidelong hips, O'er which the surface of the water slips. Sometimes, when morning runs along the sea In a gold path, they cross it glancingly; Sometimes they may be seen, going along By the red sun-set in a silver throng; And sometimes, when the black clouds send before Their windy voices, they come past the shore, Stooping in haste, and driving through the foam The hunch-backed dolphins home But most they love sleek seas and springy sands Under green rocks, on days of golden weather; And there, in their free beauty, they'll take hands And dance about a boat, which to the shore They helped the night before; Or dress their locks with myrtles or pearl bands; Or sit and make them fans of many a feather Which the gull sheds; or colour, like their own, The parted lips of shells that are up thrown, With which, and coral, and the glib sea flowers, They furnish their faint bowers. I have not told your loves; I have not told Your perfect loves, ye Nymphs! Those are among The perfect virtues only to be sung By your own glorious lovers, who have passed Death, and all drear mistake, and sit at last In the clear thrill of their hoped age of gold. END OF PART THE FIRST. PART II. As I thought thus, a neighbouring wood of elms Was moved, and stirred and whispered loftily, Much like a pomp of warriors with plumed helms, When some great general whom they long to see Is heard behind them, coming in swift dignity; And then there fled by me a rush of air That stirred up all the other foliage there, Filling the solitude with panting tongues; At which the pines woke up into their songs, Shaking their choral locks; and on the place There fell a shade as on an awe-struck face; And overhead, like a portentous rim Pulled over the wide world, to make all dim, A grave gigantic cloud came hugely uplifting him. It passed with it's slow shadow; and I saw Where it went down beyond me on a plain, Sloping it's dusky ladders of thick rain; And on the mist it made, and blinding awe, The sun, re-issuing in the opposite sky, Struck the all-coloured arch of his great eye: And up, the rest o' the country laughed again: The leaves were amber; the sunshine Scored on the ground it's conquering line; And the quick birds, for scorn of the great cloud, Like children after fear, were merry and loud. I turned me tow'rd the west, and felt the air Thinner and soft, yet nimble on my face; The sun was shadowed by the elms; and made A little golden ferment in one place, A strawy fire;—as when within the shade He used to get of old, and harbour him Beside a fountain's brim To wait for some sweet-eyed and shapely maid, Who often looking round, came winding there, Led by the lustre of his beautiful hair. And lo, there issued from beside the trees, Through the blue air, a most delicious sight; A troop of clouds, rich, separate, three parts white, As beautiful, as pigeons that one sees Round a glad homestead reeling at their ease, But large, and slowly; and what made the sight Such as I say, was not that piled white, Nor their more rosy backs, nor forward press Like sails, nor yet their surfy massiveness Light in it's plenitude, like racks of snow Sent strangely from some Alp to cool the glow Of a long summer-time,—but with most fit, And finishing, soul-satisfying show, That every cloud had a bright Nymph to it,— Each for a guide; and so those bodies fair Obeyed a nobler impulse than the air, A bright-eyed, visible thought,—beneath whose sway They went, straight stemming on their far-seen way. Most exquisite it was indeed to see How those blithe damsels guided variously, Before, behind, beside. Some forward stood As in well-managed chariots, or pursued Their trusting way as in self-moving ones; And some sat up, or as in tilted chair With silver back seemed slumbering through the air, Or leaned their cheek against a pillowy place As if upon their smiling, sleepy face They felt the air, or heard aërial tunes. Some were like maids who sit to wash their feet On rounded banks beside a rivulet; Some sat in shade beneath a curving jut As at a small hill's foot; And some behind upon a sunny mound With twinkling eyes. Another only shewed On the far side a foot and leg, that glowed Under the cloud; a sweeping back another, Turning her from us like a suckling mother; She next, a side, lifting her arms to tie Her locks into a flowing knot; and she That followed her, a smooth down-arching thigh Tapering with tremulous mass internally. Others lay partly sunk, as if in bed, Shewing a white raised bosom and dark head, And dropping out an arm. Some who appeared To railly these fair idlers, stoutly steered Their clouds and passed them; some kept bustling round, Moving their shifting racks, as men in boats To summer winds alter the sail's white coats; And some pushed gently at the back, and went On with the launching influence which they lent; And some drew sideways so. Now you might see One with grave settled look, as with sweet vaunt, Riding in front with an upgathered knee, Like the dusk Indian on his elephant: Another on a middle heap was raised As on a camel, who for days has gazed Along the desart's tawny atmosphere With sheep-like mouth and patient step sincere, Hoarding at heart his little watery treasure; And a third rode upon a rounded rack As on the eye-retorting dolphin's back, That let Arion ride him for the pleasure Of his touched harp. The rest had got at play Together, passing to each other's cloud, Or drove them in a crowd, Till, it would seem, some sweet reminding ray Came sparkling 'twixt their talk, and then they broke away. And now there was another wond'rous thing; For this fair troop, instead of holding on Till they were far and gone, Began descending in a growing ring Tow'rds that green standing place of mine, the hill; And then I found a lovelier wonder still; For as they stooped them near, Lo, I could hear How the smooth silver clouds, lapsing with care, Make a bland music to the fawning air, Filling with such a roundly-slipping tune The hollow of the great attentive noon, That the tall sky seemed touched; and all the trees Thrilled with the coming harmonies; And the fair waters looked as if they lay Their cheek against the sound, and so went kissed away. And more remains; (such things are in Heaven's ears Besides the grander spheres): For as the racks came sleeking on, one fell With rain into a dell, Breaking with scatter of a thousand notes Like twangling pearl; and I perceived how she Who loosed it with her hands, pressed kneadingly, As though it had been wine in grapy coats; And out it gushed, with that enchanting sound, In a wet shadow to the ground. But they came on; and I must tell you now How they looked at me smilingly; and how They circled the green mount in a white ring, Making a crown to it, like large, unspread, White, dabbled roses upon Flora's head: For so they did; and thus did they all sing:— Ho! We are the Nepheliads, we, Who bring the clouds from the great sea, And have within our happy care All the love 'twixt earth and air. We it is with soft new showers Wash the eyes of the young flowers; And with many a silvery comer In the sky, delight the summer; And our bubbling freshness bringing, Set the thirsty brooks a singing, Till they run for joy, and turn Every mill-wheel down the burn. We too tread the mightier mass Of clouds that take whole days to pass; And are sometimes forced to pick With fiery arrows through the thick, Till the cracking racks asunder Roll, and awe the world with thunder. Then the seeming freshness shoots, And clears the air, and cleans the fruits, And runs, heart-cooling, to the roots. Sometimes on the shelves of mountains Do we rest our burly fountains; Sometimes for a rainbow run Right before the laughing sun; And if we slip down to earth With the rain for change of mirth, Worn-out winds and pattering leaves Are what we love; and dripping eaves Dotting on the sleepy stone; And a leafy nook and lone, Where the bark on the small treen Is with moisture always green; And lime-tree bowers, and grass-edged lanes With little ponds that hold the rains, Where the nice-eyed wagtails glance, Sipping 'twixt their jerking dance. But at night in heaven we sleep, Halting our scattered clouds like sheep; Or are passed with sovereign eye By the Moon, who rideth by With her sidelong face serene, Like a most benignant queen. Then on the lofty-striking state Of the up-coming Sun we wait, Shewing to the world yet dim The colours that we catch from him, Ere he reaches to his height, And lets abroad his leaping light. And then we part on either hand For the day; but take our stand Again with him at eventide, Where we stretch on either side Our lengthened heaps, and split in shows Of sharp-drawn isles in sable rows, With some more faint, or flowery red; And some, like bands of hair that spread Across a brow with parted tress In a crisp auburn waviness; And mellow fervency between Of fiery orange, gold, and green, And inward pulpiness intense, As if great Nature's affluence Had opened it's rich heart, and there The ripeness of the world was bare. And lastly, after that blest pause, The Sun, down stepping, half withdraws His head from heaven; and then do we Break the mute pomp, and ardently Sing him in glory to the sea. Thus chaunted to me that fair blooming throng Leaning about the hill on silvery beds, And said to me at last,—Go tell our song To such as hang their pale home-withered heads For winter-time, and do our kindness wrong: And say, that they might bear, The more they know us, the moist weight of air, Which stamps upon their fields so fine a green, So glad, so lasting, yet so little seen. Bethink thee oftener too. Yet add, for all The obstinate love and natural, Which thou hast borne us in despite Of all thy sunny dreams of southern places, That thou hast been the first that has had sight Of what is on the clouds, and the kind faces Basking on t'other side: and so we take Our journey up through heaven; and for the sake Of all thy patient looks into the skies, We circuit thee, and kiss thy feverish eyes. So saying, the white clouds a little stirred, Like palfreys after rest; and every cloud Passed close to me; and every lady bowed A little from it's side without a word; And swept my lids with breathless lips serene, As Alan's mouth was stooped to by a queen. MISCELLANIES. FANCY'S PARTY. A FRAGMENT. ?Juvat ire per ipsum Aera, et immenso spatiantem vivere cœlo. Manilius. We take our pleasure through the very air, And breathing the great heav'n, expatiate there. In this poetic corner With books about and o'er us, With busts and flowers, And pictured bowers, And the sight of fields before us; Why think of these fatalities, And all their dull realities? 'Tis fancies now must charm us; Nor is the bliss ideal, For all we feel, In woe or weal, Is, while we feel it, real: Heaven's nooks they are for getting in, When weeping weather's setting in. And now and now I see them, The poet comes upon me, My back it springs With a sense of wings, And my laurel crown is on me; The room begins to rise with me, And all your sparkling eyes with me. Far, far away we're going From care and common-places, To spots of bliss As fine to this, As your's to common faces; To spots—but rapture dissipates The pictures it anticipates.— And hey, what's this? the walls, look, Are wrinkling as a skin does; And now they are bent To a silken tent, And there are chrystal windows; And look! there's a balloon above, Round and bright as the moon above. Now we loosen—now—take care; What a spring from earth was there! Like an angel mounting fierce, We have shot the night with a pierce; And the moon, with slant-up beam, Makes our starting faces gleam. Lovers below will stare at the sight, And talk of the double moon last night. What a lovely motion now, Smoothing on like lady's brow! Over land and sea we go, Over tops of mountains, Through the blue and the golden glow, And the rain's white fountains. What a pleasure 'tis to be Sailing onward smilingly; Not an effort, not a will, Yet proceeding swiftly still! 'Tis to join in one sensation Business both and contemplation; Active, without toil or stress; Passive, without listlessness. Now we pierce the chilly shroud Of a sight-enfolding cloud; And could almost crowd together, As at home in wintery weather: Now we issue forth to light, With a swift-eyed scorning; And with gently stooping flight Slide us down the sunbeams bright, And travel towards the morning. HIS DEPARTED LOVE TO PRINCE LEOPOLD. SET TO MUSIC BY VINCENT NOVELLO. A female voice is heard, issuing forth softly and tenderly. My widowed Love! Recitative of another voice, a man's. Hark, princely mourner! 'tis the voice of her You loved on earth, that with her favourite strings Comes mingling thus, like smiling dreams that stir The lips of day-sweet Patience. Hark! She sings! The voice returns. Look up, look up, and weep not so, My Leopold! My love! Thou touchest me with such a woe, As should not be above. Pray be, as thou wast all along, Affectionate and sweet, but strong. I know, dear love, thou canst not see The face that looks on thine; Thou canst not touch or come to me, But all this power is mine; And I can touch that bosom still; And now I do so, by that thrill! The night I passed thee from my clay, And kissed thy brow's despair, I met upon my moonlight way A hundred spirits fair,— A hundred brides, who all, like me, Died in that first sweet agony. And we inhabit wondrous bowers, Which though they cannot fade, Have sympathy with the sweet powers Of those our smiles obeyed; For as on earth ye spread delight, The leaves are thick and flowers grow bright. Then turn thee to thy wonted will, Dry thine and others' tears; And we will build our palace still, With tops above the spheres; And when thou too art fancied dead, There, there shall be our bridal bed. EPISTLES. TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE LORD BYRON, ON HIS DEPARTURE FOR ITALY AND GREECE. Dio ti dia, baron, ventura. —Pulci. Since you resolve, dear Byron, once again To taste the far-eyed freedom of the main, And as the coolness lessens in the breeze, Strike for warm shores that bathe in classic seas,— May all that hastens, pleases, and secures, Fair winds and skies, and a swift ship, be yours, Whose sidelong deck affords, as it cuts on, An airy slope to lounge and read upon; And may the sun, cooled only by white clouds, Make constant shadows of the sails and shrouds; And may there be sweet, watching moons at night, Or shows, upon the sea, of curious light; And morning wake with happy-blushing mouth, As though her husband still had “eyes of youth;” While fancy, just as you discern from far The coasts of Virgil and of Sannazzar, May see the Nymphs emerging, here and there, To tie up at the light their rolling hair. I see you now, half eagerness, half ease, Ride o'er the dancing freshness of the seas; I see you now (with fancy's eyesight too) Find, with a start, that lovely vision true, While on a sudden, o'er the horizon's line Phœbus looks forth with his long glance divine, At which old Ocean's white and shapely Daughters Crowd in the golden ferment of the waters, And halcyons brood, and there's a glistering show Of harps, midst bosoms and long arms of snow; And from the breathing sea, in the God's eye, A gush of voices breaks up to the sky To hail the laurelled Bard, that goes careering by. And who, thus gifted, but must hear and see Wonders like these, approaching Italy?— Enchantress Italy,—who born again In Gothic fires, woke to a sphery strain, And rose and smiled, far lovelier than before, Copier of Greece, and Amazon no more, But altogether a diviner thing, Fit for the Queen of Europe's second spring, With fancies of her own, and finer powers Not to enslave these mere outsides of ours, But bend the godlike mind, and crown it with her flowers. Thus did she reign, bright-eyed, with that sweet tone Long in her ears; and right before her throne Have sat the intellectual Graces three, Music, and Painting, and wing'd Poetry, Of whom were born those great ones, thoughtful-fac'd, That led the hierarchy of modern taste;— Heavenly Composers, that with bow symphonious Drew out, at last, music's whole soul harmonious; Poets, that knew how Nature should be wooed, With frank address, and terms heart-understood; And Painters, worthy to be friends of theirs, Hands that could catch the very finest airs Of natural minds, and all that soul express Of ready concord, which was made to bless, And forms the secret of true amorousness. Not that our English clime, how sharp soe'er, Yields in ripe genius to the warmest sphere; For what we want in sunshine out of doors, And the long leisure of abundant shores, By freedom, nay by sufferance, is supplied, And each man's sacred sunshine, his fire-side. But all the four great Masters of our Song, Stars that shine out amidst a starry throng, Have turned to Italy for added light, As earth is kissed by the sweet moon at night;— Milton for half his style, Chaucer for tales, Spenser for flowers to fill his isles and vales, And Shakspeare's self for frames already done To build his everlasting piles upon. Her genius is more soft, harmonious, fine; Our's bolder, deeper, and more masculine: In short, as woman's sweetness to man's force, Less grand, but softening by the intercourse, So the two countries are,—so may they be,— England the high-souled man, the charmer Italy. But I must finish, and shall chatter less On Greece, for reasons which yourself may guess. Only remember what you promised me About the flask from dark-welled Castaly,— A draught, which but to think of, as I sit, Makes the room round me almost turn with wit. Gods! What may not come true, what dream divine, If thus we are to drink the Delphic wine! Remember too elsewhere a certain town, Whose fame, you know, Cæsar will not hand down. And pray, my Lord, in Italy take care, You that are poet, and have pains to bear, Of lovely girls, that step across the sight, Like Houris in a heaven of warmth and light, With rosy-cushioned mouths, in dimples set, And ripe dark tresses, and glib eyes of jet. The very language, from a woman's tongue, Is worth the finest of all others sung. And so adieu, dear Byron,—dear to me For many a cause, disinterestedly;— First, for unconscious sympathy, when boys, In friendship, and the Muse's trying joys;— Next for that frank surprise, when Moore and you Came to my cage, like warblers kind and true, And told me, with your arts of cordial lying, How well I looked, when you both thought me dying;— Next for a rank worn simply, and the scorn Of those who trifle with an age free-born;— For early storms, on Fortune's basking shore, That cut precocious ripeness to the core;— For faults unhidden, other's virtues owned; Nay, unless Cant's to be at once enthroned, For virtues too, with whatsoever blended, And e'en were none possessed, for none pretended;— Lastly, for older friends,—fine hearts, held fast Through every dash of chance, from first to last;— For taking spirit as it means to be,— For a stretched hand, ever the same to me,— And total, glorious want of vile hypocrisy. Adieu, adieu:—I say no more.—God speed you! Remember what we all expect, who read you. Hampstead, April, 1816. TO THOMAS MOORE. ??? ????? ????????? ???? ???????? ???????? ? ??? ?? ??? ?????? ??????? ??????????? ? ? ?????? ?? ??? ? ????? ????? ??????. Here, here sweetly murmur the bees, Here talk the quick birds in the trees, And the pines drop their nuts at their ease. Theocritus. Dear Tom, who enjoying your brooks and your bowers, Live just like a bee, when he's flushest of flowers,— A maker of sweets, busy, sparkling, and singing, Yet armed with an exquisite point too for stinging,— I owe you a letter, and having this time A whole series to write to you, send them in rhyme; For rhyme, with its air, and its step-springing tune, Helps me on, as a march does a soldier in June; And when chattering to you, I've a something about me, That makes all my spirits come dancing from out me. I told you, you know, you should have a detail Of Hampstead's whole merits,—heath, wood, hill, and vale, And threatened in consequence (only admire The metal one's turned to by dint of desire) To draw you all near me,—vain dog that I was,— As the bees are made swarm by the clinking of brass. (By the bye, this comparison, well understood,— Is, modestly speaking, still better than good; For a man who once kept them in London, they say, Found out that they came here to dine every day.) But at present, for reasons I'll give when we meet, I shall spare you the trouble,—I mean to say treat; And yet how can I touch, and not linger a while, On the spot that has haunted my youth like a smile? On its fine breathing prospects, its clump-wooded glades, Dark pines, and white houses, and long-allied shades, With fields going down, where the bard lies and sees The hills up above him with roofs in the trees? Now too, while the season,—half summer, half spring,— Brown elms and green oaks,—makes one loiter and sing; And the bee's weighty murmur comes by us at noon, And the cuckoo repeats his short indolent tune, And little white clouds lie about in the sun, And the wind's in the west, and hay-making begun? Even now while I write, I'm half stretched on the ground With a cheek-smoothing air coming taking me round, Betwixt hillocks of green, plumed with fern and wild flowers, While my eye closely follows the bees in their bowers. People talk of “poor insects,” (although, by the way, Your old friend, Anacreon, was wiser than they); But lord, what a set of delicious retreats The epicures live in,—shades, colours, and sweets! The least clumps of verdure, on peeping into 'em, Are emerald groves, with bright shapes winding through 'em; And sometimes I wonder, when poking down by 'em, What odd sort of giant the rogues may think I am. Here perks from his arbour of crimson or green A beau, who slips backward as though he were seen:— Here, over my paper another shall go, Looking just like the traveller lost in the snow,— Till he reaches the writing,—and then, when he's eyed it, What nodding, and touching, and coasting beside it! No fresh-water spark, in his uniform fine, Can be graver when he too first crosses the line:— Now he stops at a question, as who should say “Hey?” Now casts his round eye up the yawn of an A; Now resolves to be bold, half afraid he shall sink, And like Giffard before him, can't tell what to think. Oh the wretched transition to insects like these From those of the country! To town from the trees! Ah, Tom,—you who've run the gay circle of life, And squared it, at last, with your books and a wife,— Who in Bond-street by day, when the press has been thickest, Have had all the “digito monstror” and “hic est,” Who've shone at great houses in coach-crowded streets, Amidst lights, wits, and beauties, and musical treats, And had the best pleasure a guest could befall, In being, yourself, the best part of it all,— Can the town (and I'm fond of it too, when I'm there) Can the town, after all, with the country compare? But this is a subject I keep for my last, Like the fruit in green leaves, which conclude a repast.— Adieu. In my next you'll hear more of the town; Till when, and for ever, dear Coz. Harry Brown. EXTRACT FROM ANOTHER LETTER TO THE SAME. Per me si va nella città dolente. —Dante. Through me you go into the city,—grieving. Would you change, my dear Tom, your old mode of proceeding, And make a dull end to a passage worth reading,— I mean would you learn how to let your wit down, You'd walk some fine morning from Hampstead to town. What think you of going by gardens and bowers, Through fields of all colours, refreshed by night-showers,— Some spotted with hay-cocks, some dark with ploughed mould, Some changed by the mower from green to pale gold,— A scene of ripe sunshine the hedges betwixt, With here and there farm-houses, tree-intermixed, And an air in your face, ever fanning and sweet, And the birds in your ears, and a turf for your feet;— And then, after all, to encounter a throng of Canal-men, and hod-men, unfit to make song of, Midst ale-houses, puddles, and backs of street-roads, And all sorts of rubbish, and crashing cart-loads, And so on, eye-smarting, and ready to choke, Till you end in hot narrowness, clatter, and smoke! 'Tis Swift after Spenser, or daylight with candles, A sea-song succeeding a pastoral of Handel's, A step unexpected, that jars one's inside, The shout-raising fall at the end of a slide, A yawn to a kiss, a flock followed by dust, The hoop of a beauty seen after her bust, A reckoning, a parting, a snake in the grass, A time when a man says, “What! Come to this pass!” EXTRACT FROM ANOTHER TO THE SAME. THE BERKELEIAN SYSTEM. You know, my dear Tom, that the objects we see, Are not, on the whole, what we take 'em to be; And that colour, shape, surface, are modifications, At least more or less, of our purblind sensations. A set now of needles, like certain smooth souls, Are as rough, on inspection, as old iron poles; The sun, to us dim little critics, Lord love us! Seems hardly worth measuring, he's so much above us; And mountains, like lovers, whatever their hue, When kept at a distance, are sure to look blue. The thing is notorious. Nay, as for that matter, To talk about colour is only to chatter; For like a complexion put on for the night, 'Tis all but a business of optics and light; And a pair of red garters, although 'twould be wrong to— Are just, in the dark,—like the girl they belong to. This truth, though it's stale to the present deep age, Had once such effect on a good mitred sage, That mistrusting those brilliant deceivers the eyes, He resolved to put faith in no sort of disguise; And (how he contrived, I don't know, with St. Paul) Concluded there really was nothing at all. Friends, pictures, books, gardens, like things in romances, To him were but fictions,—agreeable fancies; And things not so pleasant, of course, such as aches, Wounds, fractures, and thumps, were but cruel mistakes. Did he cry, “A thought strikes me,” you turn'd round to know What thought 'twas he spoke of, a kick or bon-mot; Had your brains been displaced by a bullet of lead, 'Twas a painful idea had got into your head; And did any one speak of a wreck on the ocean, He fell, as the crew had done, into a notion. SONNETS. WRITTEN UNDER THE ENGRAVING OF A PORTRAIT OF RAFAEL, PAINTED BY HIMSELF WHEN HE WAS YOUNG. Rafael! It must be he; we only miss Something which manhood gave him, and the fair; A look still sweeter and more thoughtful air; But for the rest, 'tis every feature his, The oval cheek, clear eye, mouth made to kiss, Terse lightsome chin, and flush of gentle hair Clipped ere it loitered into ringlets there,— The beauty, the benignity, the bliss. How sweetly sure he looks! how unforlorn! There is but one such visage at a time; 'Tis like the budding of an age new born, Remembered youth, the cuckoo in the prime, The maid's first kiss, or any other thing Most lovely, and alone, and promising. [TO PERCY SHELLEY.] Yet, Percy, not for this, should he whose eye Sees loveliness, and the unselfish joy Of justice, turn him, like a peevish boy, At hindrances and thwartings; and deny Wisdom's divinest privilege, constancy; That which most proves him free from the alloy Of useless earth,—least prone to the decoy That clamours down weak pinions from the sky. The Spirit of Beauty, though by solemn quires Hourly blasphemed, stoops not from it's calm end, And forward breathing love, but ever on Rolls the round day, and calls the starry fires To their glad watch. Therefore, high-hearted friend, Be still with thine own task in unison. TO JOHN KEATS. 'Tis well you think me truly one of those, Whose sense discerns the loveliness of things; For surely as I feel the bird that sings Behind the leaves, or dawn as it up grows, Or the rich bee rejoicing as he goes, Or the glad issue of emerging springs, Or overhead the glide of a dove's wings, Or turf, or trees, or, midst of all, repose. And surely as I feel things lovelier still, The human look, and the harmonious form Containing woman, and the smile in ill, And such a heart as Charles's, Charles C. C., a mutual friend. wise and warm,— As surely as all this, I see, ev'n now, Young Keats, a flowering laurel on your brow. ON RECEIVING A CROWN OF IVY FROM THE SAME. A crown of ivy! I submit my head To the young hand that gives it,—young, 'tis true, But with a right, for 'tis a poet's too. How pleasant the leaves feel! and how they spread With their broad angles, like a nodding shed Over both eyes! and how complete and new, As on my hand I lean, to feel them strew My sense with freshness,—Fancy's rustling bed! Tress-tossing girls, with smell of flowers and grapes Come dancing by, and downward piping cheeks, And up-thrown cymbals, and Silenus old Lumpishly borne, and many trampling shapes,— And lastly, with his bright eyes on her bent, Bacchus,—whose bride has of his hand fast hold. ON THE SAME. It is a lofty feeling, yet a kind, Thus to be topped with leaves;—to have a sense Of honour-shaded thought,—an influence As from great Nature's fingers, and be twined With her old, sacred, verdurous ivy-bind, As though she hallowed with that sylvan fence A head that bows to her benevolence, Midst pomp of fancied trumpets in the wind. 'Tis what's within us crowned. And kind and great Are all the conquering wishes it inspires,— Love of things lasting, love of the tall woods, Love of love's self, and ardour for a state Of natural good befiittng such desires, Towns without gain, and haunted solitudes. TO HORATIO SMITH. With what a fine unyielding wish to bless, Does Nature, Horace, manage to oppose The town's encroachments! Vulgar he, who goes By suburb gardens which she deigns to dress, And does not recognize her green caress Reaching back to us in those genial shows Of box-encircled flowers and poplar rows, Or other nests for evening weariness. Then come the squares, with noon-day nymphs about; Then vines, and ivy; tree tops that look out Over back walls; green in the windows too;— And even where gain huddles it's noisiest rout, The smile of her sweet wisdom will break through, For there, dear Horace, has she planted you. TO BENJAMIN ROBERT HAYDON. Haydon, whom now the conquered toil confesses Painter indeed, gifted, laborious, true, Fit to be numbered in succession due With Michael, whose idea austerely presses, And sweet-soul'd Raphael with his amorous tresses; Well hast thou urged thy radiant passage through A host of clouds; and he who with thee grew, The bard and friend, congratulates and blesses. 'Tis glorious thus to have one's own proud will, And see the crown acknowledged that we earn; But nobler yet, and nearer to the skies, To feel one's-self, in hours serene and still, One of the spirits chosen by heaven to turn The sunny side of things to human eyes. 1816. TO JOHN HAMILTON REYNOLDS, ON HIS LINES UPON THE STORY OF RIMINI. Reynolds, whose Muse, from out thy gentle embraces, Holding a little crisp and dewy flower, Came to me in my close-entwined bower, Where many fine-eyed Friendships and glad Graces, Parting the boughs, have looked in with like faces, And thanked the song which had sufficient power With Phœbus to bring back a warmer hour, And turn his southern eye to our green places: Not for this only, but that thou dost long For all men's welfare, may there be a throng Of kind regards, wherever thou appearest; And in thy home, firm-handed Health, a song Girt with rich-hearted friends, and she the nearest To whom the warble of thy lip is dearest. TO THE SAME, ON THE SAME OCCASION. A liberal taste, and a wise gentleness Have ever been the true physician's dower, As still is visible in the placid power Of those old Grecian busts; and helps to bless The balmy name of Haller, and the address Of cordial Garth; and him in Cowley's bower, Harvey; and Milton's own exotic flower, Young Deodati, plucked from his caress. To add to these an ear for the sweet hold Of music, and an eye, ay and a hand For forms which the smooth Graces tend and follow, Shews thee indeed true offspring of the bland And vital god, whom she of happy mould, The Larissæan beauty, bore Apollo.</field>
   </doc>
</add>