<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Clough, Arthur Hugh, 1819-1861</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Clough, Arthur Hugh, 1819-1861</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">clough arthur hugh 1819 1861</field>
      <field name="author_text">Clough, Arthur Hugh, 1819-1861</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1840's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.2555.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1849</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:467562</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">[Poems from] Ambarvalia</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">[Poems from] Ambarvalia</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poems from ambarvalia</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poems from ambarvalia</field>
      <field name="title_text">[Poems from] Ambarvalia</field>
      <field name="year_display">1849</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1849</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1849</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467562&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467562&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Clough, Arthur Hugh, 1819-1861&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;clough arthur hugh 1819 1861&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;[Poems from] Ambarvalia&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poems from ambarvalia&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1849&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1849&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Clough, Arthur Hugh&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1819&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1861&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;[Poems from] Ambarvalia&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Oxford&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chapman and Hall&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Francis Macpherson&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1849&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0777&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;155 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;[Poems from] Ambarvalia&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 17 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only poems by Clough included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">[Ah, what is love, our love, she said] I. Ah, what is love, our love, she said, Ah, what is human love? A fire, of earthly fuel fed, Full fain to soar above. With lambent flame the void it lips, And of the impassive air Would frame for its ambitious steps A heaven-attaining stair. It wrestles and it climbs—Ah me, Go look in little space, White ash on blackened earth will be Sole record of its place. II. Ah love, high love, she said and sighed, She said, the Poet's love! A star upon a turbid tide, Reflected from above. A marvel here, a glory there, But clouds will intervene, And garish earthly noon outglare The purity serene. [I give thee joy! O worthy word!] I give thee joy! O worthy word! Congratulate—A courtier fine, Transacts, politely shuffling by, The civil ceremonial lie, Which, quickly spoken, barely heard, Can never hope, nor e'en design To give thee joy! I give thee joy! O faithful word! When heart with heart, and mind with mind Shake-hands; and eyes in outward sign Of inward vision, rest in thine; And feelings simply, truly stirred, Emphatic utterance seek to find, And give thee joy! I give thee joy! O word of power! Believe, though slight the tie in sooth, When heart to heart its fountain opes The plant to water that with hopes Is budding for fruition's flower— The word, potential made, in truth Shall give thee joy! Shall give thee joy! Oh, not in vain, For erring child the mother's prayer; The sigh, wherein a martyr's breath Exhales from ignominious death For some lost cause! In humbler strain Shall this poor word a virtue bear, And give thee joy! COMMEMORATION SONNETS. OXFORD, 1844. I. [Amidst the fleeting many unforgot] Amidst the fleeting many unforgot, O Leonina! whether thou wert seen Singling, upon the Isis' margent green, From meaner flowers the frail forget-me-not, Or, as the picture of a saintly queen, Sitting, uplifting, betwixt fingers small, A sceptre of the water-iris tall, With pendent lily crowned of golden sheen; So, or in gay and gorgeous gallery, Where, amid splendours, like to those that far Flame backward from the sun's invisible car, Thou lookedst forth, as there the evening star; Oh, Leonina! fair wert thou to see, And unforgotten shall thine image be. II. [Thou whom thy danglers have ere this forgot] Thou whom thy danglers have ere this forgot, O Leonina! whether thou wert seen Waiting, upon the Isis' margent green, The boats that should have passed there and did not; Or at the ball, admiring crowds between, To partner academical and slow Teaching, upon the light Slavonic toe, Polkas that were not, only should have been; Or, in the crowded gallery crushed, didst hear For bonnets white, blue, pink, the ladies' cheer Multiplied while divided, and endure (Thyself being seen) to see, not hear, rehearse The long, long Proses, and the Latin Verse— O Leonina! thou wert tired, I'm sure. III. [Not in thy robes of royal rich array] Not in thy robes of royal rich array, As when thy state at Dresden thou art keeping; Nor with the golden epaulettes outpeeping From under pink and scarlet trappings gay (Raiment of doctors) through the area led; While galleries peal applause, and Phillimore For the supreme superlative cons-o'er The common-place-book of his classic head; Uncrowned thou com'st, alone, or with a tribe Of volant varlets scattering jest and jibe Almost beside thee. Yet to thee, when rent Was the Teutonic Cæsar's robe, there went One portion: and with Julius, thou to-day Canst boast, I came, I saw, I went away! [Oh, ask not what is love, she said] Oh, ask not what is love, she said, Or ask it not of me; Or of the heart, or of the head, Or if at all it be. Oh, ask it not, she said, she said, Thou winn'st not word from me! —Oh, silent as the long long dead, I, Lady, learn of thee. I ask,—thou speakest not,—and still I ask, and look to thee; And lo, without or with a will, The answer is in me. Without thy will it came to me? Ah, with it let it stay; Ah, with it, yes, abide in me, Nor only for to-day! Thou claim'st it? nay, the deed is done; Ah, leave it with thy leave; And thou a thousand loves for one Shalt day on day receive! [With graceful seat and skilful hand] With graceful seat and skilful hand, Upon the fiery steed, Prompt at a moment to command, As fittest, or concede, O Lady! happy he whose will Shall manliest homage pay To that which yielding ever, still Shall in its yielding sway: Yea, happy he, whose willing soul In perfect love combined With thine shall form one perfect whole, One happy heart and mind! Fair, fair on fleeting steed to see, Boon Nature's child, nor less, In gorgeous rooms, serene and free, 'Midst etiquette and dress! Thrice happy who, amidst the form And folly that must be, Existence fresh, and true, and warm, Shall, Lady, own in thee! Such dreams, in gay saloon, of days That shall be, 'midst the dance And music, while I hear and gaze, My silent soul entrance. As here the harp thy fingers wake To sounds melodious, he To thy soul's touch shall music make, And his enstrengthen thee. The notes, diverse in time and tone, The hearts shall image true, That still, in some sweet ways unknown, Their harmonies renew. The mazy dance, an emblem meet, Shall changeful life pourtray, Whose changes all love's music sweet Expressively obey. Then shall to waltz, though unexiled, And polka sometimes heard, To songs capricious, wayward, wild, Be other strains preferred. The heart that 'midst the petty strife, Whose ferment, day by day, To strange realities of life Converts its trifling play,— The heart, that here pursued the right, Shall then, in freer air, Expand its wings, and drink the light Of life and reason there: And quickening truth and living law, And large affections clear Shall it to heights on heights updraw, To holiest hope and fear. —Ah, moralizing premature! And yet words half-supprest May find some secret thoughts ensure Acceptance half-confest. Full oft concealed high meanings work; And, scorning observation, In gay unthinking guise will lurk A saintly aspiration; No sickly thing to sit and sun Its puny worth, to pause And list, ere half the deed be done, Its echo—self-applause: No idler, who its kindly cares To every gossip mentions, And at its breast a posy wears Of laudable intentions. As of itself, of others so Unrecognised to seek Its aim content, and in the flow Of life and spirits meek. [Look you, my simple friend, 'tis one of those] Look you, my simple friend, 'tis one of those, (Alack, a common weed of our ill time), Who, do whate'er they may, go where they will, Must needs still carry about the looking-glass Of vain philosophy. And if so be That some small natural gesture shall escape them, (Nature will out) straightway about they turn, And con it duly there, and note it down, With inward glee and much complacent chuckling, Part in conceit of their superior science, Part in forevison of the attentive look And laughing glance that may one time reward them, When the fresh ore, this day dug up, at last Shall, thrice refined and purified, from the mint Of conversation intellectual Into the golden currency of wit Issue—satirical or pointed sentence, Impromptu, epigram, or it may be sonnet, Heir undisputed to the pinkiest page In the album of a literary lady. And can it be, you ask me, that a man, With the strong arm, the cunning faculties, And keenest forethought gifted, and, within, Longings unspeakable, the lingering echoes Responsive to the still-still-calling voice Of God Most High,—should disregard all these, And half-employ all those for such an aim As the light sympathy of successful wit, Vain titillation of a moment's praise? Why, so is good no longer good, but crime Our truest, best advantage, since it lifts us Out of the stifling gas of men's opinion Into the vital atmosphere of Truth, Where He again is visible, tho' in anger.</field>
   </doc>
</add>