<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Moore, Edward, 1712-1757</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Moore, Edward, 1712-1757</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">moore edward 1712 1757</field>
      <field name="author_text">Moore, Edward, 1712-1757</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1750's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_2.0730.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1756</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:465102</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Poems, Fables, and Plays ; By Edward Moore</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Poems, Fables, and Plays ; By Edward Moore</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poems fables and plays</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poems fables and plays</field>
      <field name="title_text">Poems, Fables, and Plays ; By Edward Moore</field>
      <field name="year_display">1756</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1756</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1756</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465102&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465102&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Moore, Edward, 1712-1757&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;moore edward 1712 1757&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Poems, Fables, and Plays ; By Edward Moore&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poems, fables and plays&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1756&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1756&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Moore, Edward&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1712&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1757&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poems, Fables, and Plays&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By Edward Moore&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by J. Hughs, For R. and J. Dodsley&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1756&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp2733&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;xvi, 215 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poems, Fables, and Plays&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By Edward Moore&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 241 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To His Grace THOMAS HOLLES, Duke of NEWCASTLE.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE DISCOVERY, AN ODE To the Right Honourable HENRY PELHAM. —Vir bonus est quis? Hor. I Take wing, my muse! from shore to shore Fly, and that happy place explore Where Virtue deigns to dwell; If yet she treads on British ground, Where can the fugitive be found, In city, court, or cell? II Not there, where wine and frantic mirth Unite the sensual sons of earth In Pleasure's thoughtless train; Nor yet where sanctity's a show, Where souls nor joy nor pity know, For human bliss or pain. III Her social heart alike disowns The race, who shunning crowds and thrones, In shades sequester'd doze; Whose sloth no generous care can wake, Who rot like weeds on Lethe's lake, In senseless, vile repose. IV With these she shuns the factious tribe, Who spurn the yet unoffer'd bribe, And at corruption lour; Waiting till Discord Havock cries, In hopes, like Catiline, to rise On anarchy to pow'r! V Ye Wits, who boast from ancient times, A right divine to scourge our crimes, Is it with You she rests? No. Int'rest, slander are your views, And Virtue now, with every muse, Flies your unhallow'd breasts. VI There was a time, I heard her say, Ere females were seduc'd by play, When Beauty was her throne; But now, where dwelt the Soft Desires, The Furies light forbidden fires, To Love and Her unknown. VII From these th' indignant goddess flies, And where the spires of Science rise, A while suspends her wing; But pedant Pride and Rage are there, And Faction tainting all the air, And pois'ning every spring. VIII Long through the sky's wide pathless way The muse observ'd the wand'rer stray, And mark'd her last retreat; O'er Surry's barren heaths she flew, Descending like the silent dew On Esher's peaceful seat. IX There she beholds the gentle Mole, His pensive waters calmly roll, Amidst Elysian ground: There through the windings of the grove She leads her family of Love, And strews her sweets around. X I hear her bid the Daughters fair Oft to yon gloomy grott repair, Her secret steps to meet; Nor Thou, she cries, these shades forsake, But come, lov'd Consort, come and make The husband's bliss compleat. XI Yet not too much the soothing ease Of rural indolence shall please My Pelham's ardent breast; The man whom Virtue calls her own Must stand the pillar of a throne, And make a nation blest. XII Pelham! 'tis thine with temp'rate zeal To guard Britannia's public weal, Attack'd on every part: Her fatal discords to compose, Unite her friends, disarm her foes, Demands Thy head and heart. XIII When bold Rebellion shook the land, Ere yet from William's dauntless hand Her barbarous army fled; When Valour droop'd, and Wisdom fear'd, Thy voice expiring Credit heard, And rais'd her languid head. XIV Now by thy strong assisting hand, Fix'd on a rock I see her stand, Against whose solid feet, In vain, through every future age, The loudest, most tempestuous rage, Of angry war shall beat. XV And grieve not if the sons of Strife Attempt to cloud thy spotless life, And shade its brightest scenes; Wretches, by kindness unsubdu'd, Who see, who share the common good, Yet cavil at the means. XVI Like these, the metaphysic crew, Proud to be singular and new, Think all they see deceit; Are warm'd and cherish'd by the day, Feel and enjoy the heav'nly ray, Yet doubt of light and heat. THE TRIAL OF SELIM the PERSIAN, FOR DIVERS High Crimes and Misdemeanours. The court was met; the pris'ner brought; The council with instructions fraught; And evidence prepar'd at large, On oath, to vindicate the charge. But first 'tis meet, where form denies Poetic helps of fancy'd lies, Gay metaphors, and figures fine, And similies to deck the line; 'Tis meet (as we before have said) To call description to our aid. Begin we then (as first 'tis fitting) With the three Chiefs in judgment sitting. Above the rest, and in the chair, Sat Faction with dissembled air; Her tongue was skill'd in specious lies, And murmurs, whence dissentions rise; A smiling mask her features veil'd, Her form the patriot's robe conceal'd; With study'd blandishments she bow'd, And drew the captivated crowd. The next in place, and on the right, Sat Envy, hideous to the sight; Her snaky locks, her hollow eyes, And haggard form forbad disguise; Pale discontent, and sullen hate Upon her wrinkled forehead sat; Her left-hand, clench'd, her cheek sustain'd, Her right (with many a murder stain'd) A dagger clutch'd, in act to strike, With starts of rage, and aim oblique. Last on the left was Clamour seen, Of stature vast, and horrid mein; With bloated cheeks, and frantic eyes, She sent her yellings to the skies; Prepar'd with trumpet in her hand, To blow sedition o'er the land. With these, four more of lesser fame, And humbler rank, attendant came; Hypocrisy with smiling grace, And Impudence with brazen face, Contention bold, with iron lungs, And Slander with her hundred tongues. The walls in sculptur'd tale were rich, And statues proud (in many a nich) Of chiefs, who fought in Faction's cause, And perish'd for contempt of laws. The roof in vary'd light and shade, The seat of Anarchy display'd. Triumphant o'er a falling throne (By emblematic figures known) Confusion rag'd, and Lust obscene, And Riot with distemper'd mein, And Outrage bold, and Mischief dire, And Devastation clad in fire. Prone on the ground a martial maid Expiring lay, and groan'd for aid; Her shield with many a stab was pierc'd, Her laurels torn, her spear revers'd; And near her, crouch'd amidst the spoils, A lion panted in the toils. With look compos'd the pris'ner stood, And modest pride. By turns he view'd The court, the council, and the crowd, And with submissive rev'rence bow'd. Proceed we now, in humbler strains, And lighter rhymes, with what remains. Th' indictment grievously set forth, That Selim, lost to patriot worth, (In company with one Will P?t, And many more, not taken yet) In Forty-five, the royal palace Did enter, and to shame grown callous, Did then and there his faith forsake, And did accept, receive, and take, With mischievous intent and base, Value unknown, a certain place. He was a second time indicted, For that, by evil zeal excited, With learning more than layman's share, (Which parsons want, and He might spare) In letter to one Gilbert West, He, the said Selim, did attest, Maintain, support, and make assertion Of certain points, from Paul's conversion; By means whereof the said apostle Did many an unbeliever jostle, Starting unfashionable fancies, And building truths on known romances. A third charge ran, that knowing well Wits only eat, as pamphlets sell, He, the said Selim, notwithstanding, Did fall to answ'ring, shaming, branding Three curious Letters to the Whigs; Making no reader care three figs For any facts contain'd therein; By which uncharitable sin An author, modest and deserving, Was destin'd to contempt and starving; Against the king, his crown and peace, And all the statutes in that case. The pleader rose with brief full charg'd, And on the pris'ner's crimes enlarg'd— But not to damp the Muse's fire With rhet'ric, such as courts require, We'll try to keep the reader warm, And sift the matter from the form. Virtue and social love, he said, And honour from the land were fled; That patriots now, like other folks, Were made the butt of vulgar jokes; While Opposition dropp'd her crest, And courted pow'r for wealth and rest. Why some folks laugh'd, and some folks rail'd, Why some submitted, some assail'd, Angry or pleas'd—all solv'd the doubt With who were in, and who were out. The sons of Clamour grew so sickly, They look'd for dissolution quickly; Their weekly journals, finely written, Were sunk in privies all besh—n; Old-England, and the London-Evening, Hardly a soul was found believing in, And Caleb, once so bold and strong, Was stupid now, and always wrong. Ask ye whence rose this foul disgrace? Why Selim has receiv'd a place, And thereby brought the cause to shame; Proving that people, void of blame, Might serve their country and their king, By making both the self-same thing. By which the credulous believ'd, And others (by strange arts deceiv'd) That Ministers were sometimes right, And meant not to destroy us quite. That bart'ring thus in state affairs, He next must deal in sacred wares, The clergy's rights divine invade, And smuggle in the gospel-trade, And all this zeal to re-instate Exploded notions, out of date; Sending old rakes to church in shoals, Like children, sniv'ling for their souls, And ladies gay, from smut and libels, To learn beliefs, and read their bibles; Erecting conscience for a tutor, To damn the present by the future. As if to evils known and real 'Twas needful to annex ideal; When all of human life we know Is care, and bitterness, and woe, With short transitions of delight, To set the shatter'd spirits right. Then why such mighty pains and care, To make us humbler than we are? Forbidding short-liv'd mirth and laughter, By fears of what may come hereafter? Better in ignorance to dwell; None fear, but who believe a hell; And if there should be one, no doubt, Men of themselves would find it out. But Selim's crimes, he said, went further, And barely stopp'd on this side murther; One yet remain'd to close the charge, To which (with leave) he'd speak at large. And first 'twas needful to premise, That though so long (for reasons wise) The press inviolate had stood, Productive of the public good; Yet still, too modest to abuse, It rail'd at vice, but told not whose. That great improvements, of late days, Were made, to many an author's praise, Who, not so scrupulously nice, Proclaim'd the person with the vice, Or gave, where vices might be wanted, The name, and took the rest for granted. Upon this plan, a Champion Author of the Letters to the Whigs. rose, Unrighteous greatness to oppose, Proving the man inventus non est, Who trades in pow'r, and still is honest; And (God be prais'd) he did it roundly, Flogging a certain junto soundly. But chief his anger was directed, Where people least of all suspected; And Selim, not so strong as tall, Beneath his grasp appear'd to fall. But Innocence (as people say) Stood by, and sav'd him in the fray. By her assisted, and one Truth, A busy, prating, forward youth, He rally'd all his strength anew, And at the foe a Letter threw, His weakest part the weapon found, And brought him senseless to the ground. Hence Opposition fled the field, And Ign'rance with her sev'n-fold shield; And well they might, for (things weigh'd fully) The pris'ner, with his Whore and Bully, Must prove for every foe too hard, Who never fought with such a guard. But Truth and Innocence, he said, Would stand him here in little stead; For they had evidence on oath, That would appear too hard for both. Of witnesses a fearful train Came next, th' indictments to sustain; Detraction, Hatred, and Distrust, And Party, of all foes the worst Malice, Revenge, and Unbelief, And Disappointment, worn with grief, Dishonour foul, unaw'd by shame, And every fiend that vice can name. All these in ample form depos'd Each fact the triple charge disclos'd, With taunts and gibes of bitter sort, And asking vengeance from the court. The pris'ner said in his defence, That he indeed had small pretence To soften facts so deeply sworn, But would for his offences mourn; Yet more he hop'd than bare repentance Might still be urg'd to ward the sentence. That he had held a place some years, He own'd with penitence and tears, But took it not from motives base, Th' indictment there mistook the case; And though he had betray'd his trust In being to his country just, Neglecting Faction and her friends, He did it not for wicked ends, But that complaints and feuds might cease, And jarring parties mix in peace. That what he wrote to Gilbert West Bore hard against him, he confess'd; Yet there they wrong'd him; for the fact is, He reason'd for Belief, not Practice; And people might believe, he thought, Though Practice might be deem'd a fault. He either dreamt it, or was told, Religion was rever'd of old, That it gave breeding no offence, And was no foe to wit and sense; But whether this was truth, or whim, He would not say; the doubt with him (And no great harm he hop'd) was how Th' enlighten'd world would take it now; If they admitted it, 'twas well, If not, he never talk'd of hell, Nor even hop'd to change men's measures, Or frighten ladies from their pleasures. One accusation, he confess'd, Had touch'd him more than all the rest; Three Patriot-Letters, high in fame, By him o'erthrown, and brought to shame. And though it was a rule in vogue, If one man call'd another rogue, The party injur'd might reply, And on his foe retort the lie; Yet what accru'd from all his labour, But foul dishonour to his neighbour? And he's a most unchristian elf, Who others damns to save himself. Besides, as all men knew, he said, Those Letters only rail'd for bread; And hunger was a known excuse For prostitution and abuse; A guinea, properly apply'd, Had made the Writer change his side; He wish'd he had not cut and carv'd him, And own'd, he should have bought, not starv'd him. The court, he said, knew all the rest, And must proceed as they thought best; Only he hop'd such resignation Would plead some little mitigation; And if his character was clear From other faults (and friends were near, Who would, when call'd upon, attest it) He did in humblest form request it, To be from punishment exempt, And only suffer their contempt. The pris'ner's friends their claim preferr'd, In turn demanding to be heard. Integrity and Honour swore, Benevolence, and twenty more, That he was always of their party, And that they knew him firm and hearty. Religion, sober dame, attended, And, as she could, his cause befriended; She said, 'twas since he came from college, She knew him, introduc'd by Knowledge; The man was modest and sincere, Nor farther could she interfere. The Muses begg'd to interpose, But Envy with loud hissings rose, And call'd them women of ill fame, Liars, and prostitutes to shame; And said, to all the world 'twas known, Selim had had them every one. The pris'ner blush'd, the Muses frown'd, When silence was proclaim'd around, And Faction, rising with the rest, In form the pris'ner thus address'd. You, Selim, thrice have been indicted, First, that by wicked pride excited, And bent your country to disgrace, You have receiv'd, and held a Place. Next, Infidelity to wound, You've dar'd, with arguments profound, To drive Freethinking to a stand, And with Religion vex the land. And lastly, in contempt of right, With horrid and unnat'ral spite, You have an Author's fame o'erthrown, Thereby to build and fence your own. These crimes successive, on your trial, Have met with proofs beyond denial; To which yourself, with shame, conceded, And but in mitigation pleaded. Yet that the justice of the court May suffer not in men's report, Judgment a moment I suspend, To reason as from friend to friend. And first, that You, of all mankind, With Kings and Courts should stain your mind! You! who were Opposition's lord! Her nerves, her sinews, and her sword! That You at last, for servile ends, Should wound the bowels of her friends! — Is aggravation of offence, That leaves for mercy no pretence. Yet more—For You to urge your hate, And back the church, to aid the state! For You to publish such a Letter! You! who have known Religion better! For You, I say, to introduce The fraud again!—There's no excuse. And last of all, to crown your shame, Was it for You to load with blame The writings of a Patriot-Youth, And summon Innocence and Truth To prop your cause?—Was this for You?— But justice does your crimes pursue; And sentence now alone remains, Which thus, by Me, the court ordains. “That you return from whence you came, “There to be stript of all your fame “By vulgar hands; That once a week “Old-England pinch you till you squeak; “That ribbald Pamphlets do pursue you, “And Lies and Murmurs, to undo you, “With every foe that Worth procures, “And only Virtue's friends be Yours.” ODE TO GARRICK, UPON The Talk of the Town. When I said I would die a batchelor, I did not think I should live till I were married. Much Ado about Nothing. I No, no; the left-hand box, in blue; There! don't you see her?—See her! Who? Nay, hang me if I tell. There's Garrick in the music-box! Watch but his eyes; see there!—O, pox! Your servant, Ma'moiselle! II But tell me, David, is it true? Lord help us! what will some folks do? How will they curse this stranger! What! fairly taken in for life! A sober, serious, wedded wife! O fie upon you, Ranger! III The clergy too have join'd the chat; “A papist—Has he thought of that? “Or means he to convert her?” Troth, boy, unless your zeal be stout, The nymph may turn Your faith about, By arguments experter. IV The ladies, pale and out of breath, Wild as the witches in Macbeth, Ask if the deed be done? O, David! listen to my lay! I'll prophecy the things they'll say; For tongues, you know, will run. V “And pray, what other news d'ye hear? “Marry'd!—But don't you think, my dear, “He's growing out of fashion? “People may fancy what they will, “But Quin's the only actor still, “To touch the tender passion. VI “Nay, madam, did you mind, last night, “His Archer? Not a line on't right! “I thought I heard some hisses. “Good God! if Billy Mills, thought I, “Or Billy Havard would but try, “They'd beat him all to pieces. VII “'Twas prudent though to drop his Bayes— “And (entre nous) the Laureat says, “He hopes he'll give up Richard. “But then, it tickles me to see, “In Hastings, such a shrimp as he “Attempt to ravish Pritchard. VIII “The fellow pleas'd me well enough “In—what d'ye call it? Hoadley's stuff; “There's something there like nature: “Just so, in life, he runs about, “Plays at bo-peep, now in, now out, “But hurts no mortal creature. IX “And then there's Belmont to be sure— “O ho! my gentle Neddy Moore! “How does my good lord mayor? “And have you left Cheapside, my dear? “And will you write again next year, “To shew your fav'rite player? X “But Merope, we own, is fine, “Eumenes charms in every line; “How prettily he vapours! “So gay his dress, so young his look, “One would have sworn 'twas Mr. Cook, “Or Mathews, cutting capers.” XI Thus, David, will the ladies flout, And councils hold at every rout, To alter all your plays; Yates shall be Benedict next year, Macklin be Richard, Taswell Lear, And Kitty Clive be Bayes. XII Two parts they readily allow Are yours; but not one more, they vow; And thus they close their spite: You will be Sir John Brute, they say, A very Sir John Brute all day, And Fribble all the night. XIII But tell me, fair ones, is it so? You all did love him once, Julius Cæsar.we know; What then provokes your gall? Forbear to rail—I'll tell you why; Quarrels may come, or madam die, And then there's hope for all. XIV And now a word or two remains, Sweet Davy, and I close my strains; Think well ere you engage; Vapours and ague-fits may come, And matrimonial claims at home, Un-nerve you for the stage. XV But if you find your spirits right, Your mind at ease, and body tight, Take her; you can't do better: A pox upon the tattling town! The fops that join to cry her down Would give their ears to get her. XVI Then if her heart be good and kind, (And sure that face bespeaks a mind As soft as woman's can be) You'll grow as constant as a dove, And taste the purer sweets of love, Unvisited by Ranby. ENVY and FORTUNE, A TALE TO Mrs. GARRICK. Says Envy to Fortune, “Soft, soft, madam Flirt! “Not so fast with your wheel, you'll be down in the dirt! “Well, and how does your David? Indeed, my dear creature, “You've shewn him a wonderful deal of good-nature; “His bags are so full, and such praises his due, “That the like was ne'er known—and all owing to you: “But why won't you make him quite happy for life, “And to all you have done add the gift of a wife?” Says Fortune, and smil'd, “Madam Envy God save ye; “But why always sneering at me and poor Davy? “I own that sometimes, in contempt of all rules, “I lavish my favours on blockheads and fools; “But the case is quite different here, I averr it, “For David ne'er knew me, 'till brought me by Merit. “And yet to convince you—nay, madam, no hisses— “Good-manners at least—such behaviour as this is—!” (For mention but Merit, and Envy flies out With a hiss and a yell that would silence a rout. But Fortune went on)—“To convince you, I say, “That I honour your scheme, I'll about it to-day; “The man shall be marry'd, so pray now be easy, “And Garrick for once shall do something to please ye.” So saying, she rattled her wheel out of sight, While Envy walk'd after, and grinn'd with delight. It seems 'twas a trick that she long had been brewing, To marry poor David, and so be his ruin: For Slander had told her the creature lov'd pelf, And car'd not a fig for a soul but himself; From thence she was sure, had the Devil a daughter, He'd snap at the girl, so 'twas Fortune that brought her. And then should her temper be sullen or haughty, Her flesh too be frail, and incline to be naughty, 'Twould fret the poor fellow so out of his reason, That Barry and Quin would set fashions next season. But Fortune, who saw what the Fury design'd, Resolv'd to get David a wife to his mind; Yet afraid of herself in a matter so nice, She visited Prudence, and beg'd her advice. The nymph shook her head when the business she knew, And said that her female acquaintance were few; That excepting miss R ?—O, yes, there was one, A friend of that lady's, she visited none; But the first was too great, and the last was too good, And as for the rest, she might get whom she cou'd. Away hurr'd Fortune, perplex'd and half mad, But her promise was pass'd, and a wife must be had: She travers'd the town from one corner to t'other, Now knocking at one door, and then at another. The girls curtsy'd low as she look'd in their faces, And bridled and primm'd with abundance of graces; But this was coquettish, and that was a prude, One stupid and dull, t'other noisy and rude; A third was affected, quite careless a fourth, With prate without meaning, and pride without worth; A fifth, and a sixth, and a seventh were such As either knew nothing, or something too much— In short as they pass'd, she to all had objections, The gay wanted thought, the good-humour'd affections, The prudent were ugly, the sensible dirty, And all of them flirts, from fifteen up to thirty. When Fortune saw this she began to look silly, Yet still she went on till she reach'd Piccadilly; But vex'd, and fatigu'd, and the night growing late, She rested her wheel within Burlington gate. My lady rose up, as she saw her come in, “O ho, madam Genius! pray where have you been?” (For her ladyship thought, from so serious an air, 'Twas Genius come home, for it seems she liv'd there.) But Fortune, not minding her ladyship's blunder, And wiping her forehead, cry'd, “Well may you wonder “To see me thus flurry'd,”—then told her the case, And sigh'd till her ladyship laugh'd in her face. “Mighty civil indeed!”—“Come, a truce, says my lady, “A truce with complaints, and perhaps I may aid ye. “I'll shew you a girl that—here, Martin! go tell— “But she's gone to undress; by-and-by is as well— “I'll shew you a sight that you'll fancy uncommon, “Wit, beauty and goodness, all met in a woman; “A heart to no folly or mischief inclin'd, “A Body all grace, and all sweetness a Mind.” “O, pray let me see her, says Fortune and smil'd, “Do but give her to me, and I'll make her my child— “But who, my dear, who?—for you have not told yet”— “Who indeed, says my lady, if not Violette?” The words were scarce spoke when she enter'd the room; A blush at the stranger still heighten'd her bloom; So humble her looks were, so mild was her air, That Fortune, astonish'd, sat mute in her chair. My lady rose up, and with countenance bland, “This is Fortune, my dear,” and presented her hand: The goddess embrac'd her, and call'd her her own, And, compliments over, her errand made known. But how the sweet girl colour'd, flutter'd and trembled, How oft she said no, and how ill she dissembled; Or how little David rejoic'd at the news, And swore, from all others, 'twas her he would chuse; What methods he try'd, and what arts to prevail; All these, were they told, would but burden my tale— In short, all affairs were so happily carry'd, That hardly six weeks pass'd away till they marry'd. But Envy grew sick when the story she heard, Violette was the girl that of all she most fear'd; She knew her good-humour, her beauty and sweetness, Her ease and compliance, her taste and her neatness; From these she was sure that her man could not roam, And must rise on the stage, from contentment at home: So on she went hissing, and inwardly curs'd her, And Garrick next season will certainly burst her. TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE HENRY PELHAM. THE Humble PETITION OF THE WORSHIPFUL COMPANY OF Pòets and News-Writers. SHEWETH, That your Honour's petitioners (dealers in rhymes, And writers of scandal, for mending the times) By losses in bus'ness, and England's well-doing, Are sunk in their credit, and verging on ruin. That these their misfortunes, they humbly conceive, Arise not from dulness, as some folks believe, But from rubs in their way, which your Honour has laid, And want of materials to carry on trade. That they always had form'd high conceits of their use, And meant their last breath should go out in abuse; But now (and they speak it with sorrow and tears) Since your Honour has sat at the helm of affairs, No party will join them, no faction invite To heed what they say, or to read what they write; Sedition, and Tumult, and Discord are fled, And Slander scarce ventures to lift up her head— In short, public bus'ness is so carry'd on, That their country is sav'd, and the patriots undone. To perplex them still more, and sure famine to bring, (Now satire has lost both its truth and its sting) If, in spite of their natures, they bungle at praise, Your Honour regards not, and nobody pays. YOUR petitioners therefore most humble intreat (As the times will allow, and your Honour thinks meet) That measures be chang'd, and some cause of complaint Be immediately furnish'd, to end their restraint; Their credit thereby, and their trade to retrieve, That again they may rail, and the nation believe. Or else (if your wisdom shall deem it all one) Now the parliament's rising, and business is done, That your Honour would please, at this dangerous crisis, To take to your bosom a few private vices, By which your petitioners haply might thrive, And keep both themselves, and Contention alive. In compassion, good Sir, give them something to say, And your Honour's petitioners ever shall pray. THE TRIAL OF SARAH?, alias SLIM SAL, FOR PRIVATELY STEALING. The pris'ner was at large indicted, For that by thirst of gain excited, One day in July last, at tea, And in the house of Mrs. P, From the left breast of E. M. gent. With base felonious intent, Did then and there a heart with strings, Rest, quiet, peace, and other things, Steal, rob and plunder; and all them The chattels of the said E. M. The prosecutor swore, last May (The month he knew, but not the day) He left his friends in town, and went Upon a visit down in Kent: That staying there a month or two, He spent his time as others do, In riding, walking, fishing, swimming; But being much inclin'd to women, And young and wild, and no great reasoner, He got acquainted with the prisoner. He own'd 'twas rumour'd in those parts That she'd a trick of stealing hearts, And from fifteen to twenty-two, Had made the devil and all to do: But Mr. W, the vicar, (And no man brews you better liquor) Spoke of her thefts as tricks of youth, The frolics of a girl forsooth; Things now were on another score, He said; for she was twenty-four. However, to make matters short, And not to trespass on the court, The lady was discover'd soon, And thus it was. One afternoon, The ninth of July last, or near it, (As to the day, he could not swear it) In company at Mrs. P's, Where folks say any thing they please; Dean L, and lady Mary by, And Fanny waiting on Miss Y, (He own'd he was inclin'd to think Both were a little in their drink) The pris'ner ask'd, and call'd him cousin, How many kisses made a dozen? That being, as he own'd, in liquor, The question made his blood run quicker, And, sense and reason in eclipse, He vow'd he'd score them on her lips. That rising up to keep his word, He got as far as kiss the third, And would have counted t'other nine, And so all present did opine, But that he felt a sudden dizziness, That quite undid him for the business; His speech, he said, began to faulter, His eyes to stare, his mouth to water, His breast to thump without cessation, And all within one conflagration. Bless me! says Fanny, what's the matter? And lady Mary look'd hard at her, And stamp'd, and wish'd the pris'ner further, And cry'd out, part them, or there's murther! That still he held the pris'ner fast, And would have stood it to the last; But struggling to go through the rest, He felt a pain across his breast, A sort of sudden twinge, he said, That seem'd almost to strike him dead, And after that such cruel smarting, He thought the soul and body parting. That then he let the pris'ner go, And stagger'd off a step or so, And thinking that his heart was ill, He begg'd of Miss Y's maid to feel. That Fanny stept before the rest, And laid her hand upon his breast; But, mercy on us! what a stare The creature gave! no heart was there; Souse went her fingers in the hole, Whence heart, and strings, and all were stole. That Fanny turn'd and told the prisoner, She was a thief, and so she'd christen her, And that it was a burning shame, And brought the house an evil name, And if she did not put the heart in, The man would pine and die for certain. The pris'ner then was in her airs, And bid her mind her own affairs, And told his reverence, and the rest of 'em, She was as honest as the best of 'em. That lady Mary and dean L Rose up and said, 'twas mighty well, But that, in gen'ral terms they said it, A heart was gone, and some one had it; Words would not do, for search they must, And search they would, and her the first. That then the pris'ner dropp'd her anger, And said, she hop'd they would not hang her, That all she did was meant in jest, And there the heart was and the rest. That then the dean cry'd out, O fie! And sent in haste for justice I, Who, though he knew her friends and pity'd her, Call'd her hard names, and so committed her. The parties present swore the same; And Fanny said the pris'ner's name Had frighten'd all the country round, And glad she was the bill was found. She knew a man, who knew another, Who knew the very party's brother, Who lost his heart by mere surprize, One morning looking at her eyes; And others had been known to squeak, Who only chanc'd to hear her speak: For she had words of such a sort, That though she knew no reason for't, Would make a man of sense run mad, And rifle him of all he had; And that she'd rob the whole community, If ever she had opportunity. The pris'ner now first silence broke, And curtsy'd round her as she spoke. She own'd, she said, it much incens'd her, To hear such matters sworn against her, But that she hop'd to keep her temper, And prove herself eadem semper. That what the prosecutor swore Was some part true, and some part more; She own'd she had been often seen with him, And laugh'd and chatted on the green with him; The fellow seem'd to have humanity, And told her tales that sooth'd her vanity, Pretending that he lov'd her vastly, And that all women else look'd ghastly. But then she hop'd the court would think She never was inclin'd to drink, Or suffer hands like his to daub her, or Encourage men to kiss and slobber her; She'd have folks know she did not love it, Or if she did, she was above it. But this, she said, was sworn of course, To prove her giddy, and then worse; As she whose conduct was thought levis, Might very well be reckon'd thievish. She hop'd, she said, the court's discerning Would pay some honour to her learning, For every day from four to past six, She went up-stairs, and read the classics. Thus having clear'd herself of levity, The rest, she said, would come with brevity. And first, it injur'd not her honour To own the heart was found upon her; For she could prove, and did averr, The paultry thing belong'd to her: The fact was thus. This prince of knaves Was once the humblest of her slaves, And often had confess'd the dart Her eyes had lodg'd within his heart: That she, as 'twas her constant fashion, Made great diversion of his passion; Which set his blood in such a ferment, As seem'd to threaten his interment: That then she was afraid of losing him, And so desisted from abusing him; And often came and felt his pulse, And bid him write to doctor Hulse. The prosecutor thank'd her kindly, And sigh'd, and said she look'd divinely; But told her that his heart was bursting, And doctors he had little trust in, He therefore begg'd her to accept it, And hop'd 'twould mend if once she kept it. That having no aversion to it, She said, with all her soul, she'd do it; But then she begg'd him to remember, If he should need it in December, (For winter months would make folks shiver, Who wanted either heart or liver) It never could return; and added, 'Twas hers for life, if once she had it. The prosecutor said amen, And that he wish'd it not again, And took it from his breast and gave her, And bow'd, and thank'd her for the favour; But begg'd the thing might not be spoke of, As heartless men were made a joke of. That next day, whisp'ring him about it, And asking how he felt without it, He sigh'd, and cry'd alack! alack! And begg'd, and pray'd to have it back; Or that she'd give him hers instead on't, But she conceiv'd there was no need on't, And said, and bid him make no pother, He should have neither one nor t'other. That then he rav'd and storm'd like fury, And said that one was his de jure, And rather than he'd leave pursuing her, He'd swear a robbery and ruin her. That this was truth she did averr, Whatever hap betided Her; Only that Mrs. P, she said, Miss Y, and her deluded maid, And lady Mary, and his reverence Were folks, to whom she paid some deference, And that she verily believ'd They were not perjur'd, but deceiv'd. Then doctor D begg'd leave to speak, And sigh'd as if his heart would break. He said that he was madam's surgeon, Or rather, as in Greek, chirurgeon, From chier, manus, ergon, opus, (As scope is from the Latin scopus.) That he, he said, had known the prisoner From the first sun that ever rise on her; And griev'd he was to see her there; But took upon himself to swear There was not to be found in nature A sweeter or a better creature; And if the king (God bless him) knew her, He'd leave St. James's to get to her: But then as to the fact in question, He knew no more on't than Hephæstion; It might be false, and might be true, And this, he said, was all he knew. The judge proceeded to the charge, And gave the evidence at large, But often cast a sheep's eye at her, And strove to mitigate the matter, Pretending facts were not so clear, And mercy ought to interfere. The jury then withdrew a moment, As if on weighty points to comment, And right or wrong, resolv'd to save her, They gave a verdict in her favour. But why or wherefore things were so, It matters not for us to know: The culprit, by escape grown bold, Pilfers alike from young and old, The country all around her teazes, And robs, or murders whom she pleases.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">FABLES FOR THE LADIES. FABLE I. The EAGLE, and the Assembly of Birds. TO HER ROYAL HIGHNESS, THE Princess of WALES. The moral lay, to beauty due, I write, Fair Excellence, to you; Well pleas'd to hope my vacant hours Have been employ'd to sweeten yours. Truth under fiction I impart, To weed out folly from the heart, And shew the paths, that lead astray The wandring nymph from wisdom's way. I flatter none. The great and good Are by their actions understood; Your monument if actions raise, Shall I deface by idle praise? I echo not the voice of fame, That dwells delighted on your name; Her friendly tale, however true, Were flatt'ry, if I told it you. The proud, the envious, and the vain, The jilt, the prude, demand my strain; To these, detesting praise, I write, And vent, in charity, my spite. With friendly hand I hold the glass To all, promiscuous as they pass; Should folly there her likeness view, I fret not that the mirror's true; If the fantastic form offend, I made it not, but would amend. Virtue, in every clime and age, Spurns at the folly-soothing page, While satire, that offends the ear Of vice and passion, pleases her. Premising this, your anger spare, And claim the fable, you, who dare. The birds in place, by factions press'd, To Jupiter their pray'rs address'd; By specious lies the state was vex'd, Their counsels libellers perplex'd; They begg'd (to stop seditious tongues) A gracious hearing of their wrongs. Jove grants their suit. The Eagle sate, Decider of the grand debate. The Pye, to trust and pow'r preferr'd, Demands permission to be heard. Says he, prolixity of phrase You know I hate. This libel says, “Some birds there are, who prone to noise, “Are hir'd to silence wisdom's voice, “And skill'd to chatter out the hour, “Rise by their emptiness to pow'r.” That this is aim'd direct at me, No doubt, you'll readily agree; Yet well this sage assembly knows, By parts to government I rose; My prudent counsels prop the state; Magpies were never known to prate. The Kite rose up. His honest heart In virtue's suff'rings bore a part. That there were birds of prey he knew; So far the libeller said true; “Voracious, bold, to rapine prone, “Who knew no int'rest but their own; “Who hov'ring o'er the farmer's yard, “Nor pigeon, chick, nor duckling spar'd.” This might be true, but if apply'd To him, in troth, the sland'rer ly'd. Since ign'rance then might be misled, Such things, he thought, were best unsaid. The Crow was vex'd. As yester-morn He flew across the new-sown corn, A screaming boy was set for pay, He knew, to drive the crows away; Scandal had found out him in turn, And buzz'd abroad, that crows love corn. The Owl arose, with solemn face, And thus harangu'd upon the case. That magpies prate, it may be true, A kite may be voracious too, Crows sometimes deal in new-sown pease; He libels not, who strikes at these; The slander's here—“But there are birds, “Whose wisdom lies in looks, not words; “Blund'rers, who level in the dark, “And always shoot beside the mark.” He names not me; but these are hints, Which manifest at whom he squints; I were indeed that blund'ring fowl, To question if he meant an owl. Ye wretches, hence! the Eagle cries, 'Tis conscience, conscience that applies; The virtuous mind takes no alarm, Secur'd by innocence from harm; While guilt, and his associate fear, Are startled at the passing air. FABLE II. The PANTHER, the HORSE, and other Beasts. The man, who seeks to win the fair, (So custom says) must truth forbear; Must fawn and flatter, cringe and lie, And raise the goddess to the sky. For truth is hateful to her ear, A rudeness, which she cannot bear. A rudeness? Yes. I speak my thoughts; For truth upbraids her with her faults. How wretched, Cloe, then am I, Who love you, and yet cannot lie! And still to make you less my friend, I strive your errors to amend! But shall the senseless fop impart The softest passion to your heart, While he, who tells you honest truth, And points to happiness your youth, Determines, by his care, his lot, And lives neglected, and forgot? Trust me, my dear, with greater ease Your taste for flatt'ry I could please, And similies in each dull line, Like glow-worms in the dark, should shine. What if I say your lips disclose The freshness of the op'ning rose? Or that your cheeks are beds of flow'rs, Enripen'd by refreshing show'rs? Yet certain as these flow'rs shall fade, Time every beauty will invade. The butterfly, of various hue, More than the flow'r resembles you; Fair, flutt'ring, fickle, busy thing, To pleasure ever on the wing, Gayly coquetting for an hour, To die, and ne'er be thought of more. Would you the bloom of youth should last? 'Tis virtue that must bind it fast; An easy carriage, wholly free From sour reserve, or levity; Good-natur'd mirth, an open heart, And looks unskill'd in any art; Humility, enough to own The frailties, which a friend makes known, And decent pride, enough to know The worth, that virtue can bestow. These are the charms, which ne'er decay, Though youth, and beauty fade away, And time, which all things else removes, Still heightens virtue, and improves. You'll frown, and ask to what intent This blunt address to you is sent? I'll spare the question, and confess I'd praise you, if I lov'd you less; But rail, be angry, or complain, I will be rude, while you are vain. Beneath a lion's peaceful reign, When beasts met friendly on the plain, A Panther, of majestic port, (The vainest female of the court) With spotted skin, and eyes of fire, Fill'd every bosom with desire. Where e'er she mov'd, a servile crowd Of fawning creatures cring'd and bow'd; Assemblies every week she held, (Like modern belles) with coxcombs fill'd, Where noise, and nonsense, and grimace, And lies and scandal fill'd the place. Behold the gay, fantastic thing, Encircled by the spacious ring. Low-bowing, with important look, As first in rank, the Monkey spoke. “Gad take me, madam, but I swear, “No angel ever look'd so fair: “Forgive my rudeness, but I vow, “You were not quite divine till now; “Those limbs! that shape! and then those eyes! “O, close them, or the gazer dies!” Nay, gentle pug, for goodness hush, I vow, and swear, you make me blush; I shall be angry at this rate; 'Tis so like flatt'ry, which I hate. The Fox, in deeper cunning vers'd, The beauties of her mind rehears'd, And talk'd of knowledge, taste, and sense, To which the fair have vast pretence! Yet well he knew them always vain Of what they strive not to attain, And play'd so cunningly his part, That pug was rival'd in his art. The Goat avow'd his am'rous flame, And burnt—for what he durst not name; Yet hop'd a meeting in the wood Might make his meaning understood. Half angry at the bold address, She frown'd; but yet she must confess, Such beauties might inflame his blood, But still his phrase was somewhat rude. The Hog her neatness much admir'd; The formal Ass her swiftness fir'd; While all to feed her folly strove, And by their praises shar'd her love. The Horse, whose gen'rous heart disdain'd Applause, by servile flatt'ry gain'd, With graceful courage, silence broke, And thus with indignation spoke. When flatt'ring monkeys fawn, and prate, They justly raise contempt, or hate; For merit's turn'd to ridicule, Applauded by the grinning fool. The artful fox your wit commends, To lure you to his selfish ends; From the vile flatt'rer turn away, For knaves make friendships to betray. Dismiss the train of fops, and fools, And learn to live by wisdom's rules; Such beauties might the lion warm, Did not your folly break the charm; For who would court that lovely shape, To be the rival of an ape? He said; and snorting in disdain, Spurn'd at the crowd, and sought the plain. FABLE III. The NIGHTINGALE, and GLOW-WORM. The prudent nymph, whose cheeks disclose The lily, and the blushing rose, From public view her charms will screen, And rarely in the crowd be seen; This simple truth shall keep her wise, “The fairest fruits attract the flies.” One night, a Glow-worm, proud and vain, Contemplating her glitt'ring train, Cry'd, sure there never was in nature So elegant, so fine a creature. All other insects, that I see, The frugal ant, industrious bee, Or silk-worm, with contempt I view; With all that low, mechanic crew, Who servilely their lives employ In business, enemy to joy. Mean, vulgar herd! ye are my scorn, For grandeur only I was born, Or sure am sprung from race divine, And plac'd on earth, to live and shine. Those lights, that sparkle so on high, Are but the glow-worms of the sky, And kings on earth their gems admire, Because they imitate my fire. She spoke. Attentive on a spray, A Nightingale forbore his lay; He saw the shining morsel near, And flew, directed by the glare; A while he gaz'd with sober look, And thus the trembling prey bespoke. Deluded fool, with pride elate, Know, 'tis thy beauty brings thy fate: Less dazzling, long thou might'st have lain Unheeded on the velvet plain: Pride, soon or late, degraded mourns, And beauty wrecks whom she adorns. FABLE IV. HYMEN, and DEATH. Sixteen, d'ye say? Nay then 'tis time; Another year destroys your prime. But stay—The settlement! “That's made.” Why then's my simple girl afraid? Yet hold a moment, if you can, And heedfully the fable scan. The shades were fled, the morning blush'd, The winds were in their caverns hush'd, When Hymen, pensive and sedate, Held o'er the fields his musing gait. Behind him, through the green-wood shade, Death's meagre form the god survey'd, Who quickly, with gigantic stride, Out-went his pace, and join'd his side. The chat on various subjects ran, Till angry Hymen thus began. Relentless Death, whose iron sway Mortals reluctant must obey, Still of thy pow'r shall I complain, And thy too partial hand arraign? When Cupid brings a pair of hearts, All over stuck with equal darts, Thy cruel shafts my hopes deride, And cut the knot, that Hymen ty'd. Shall not the bloody, and the bold, The miser, hoarding up his gold, The harlot, reeking from the stew, Alone thy fell revenge pursue? But must the gentle, and the kind Thy fury, undistinguish'd, find? The monarch calmly thus reply'd; Weigh well the cause, and then decide. That friend of yours, you lately nam'd, Cupid, alone is to be blam'd; Then let the charge be justly laid; That idle boy neglects his trade, And hardly once in twenty years, A couple to your temple bears. The wretches, whom your office blends, Silenus now, or Plutus sends; Hence care, and bitterness, and strife Are common to the nuptial life. Believe me; more than all mankind, Your vot'ries my compassion find; Yet cruel am I call'd, and base, Who seek the wretched to release; The captive from his bonds to free, Indissoluble but for me. 'Tis I entice him to the yoke; By me, your crowded altars smoke: For mortals boldly dare the noose, Secure that Death will set them loose. FABLE V. The POET, and his PATRON. Why, Cælia, is your spreading waist So loose, so negligently lac'd? Why must the wrapping bed-gown hide Your snowy bosom's swelling pride? How ill that dress adorns your head, Distain'd, and rumpled from the bed! Those clouds, that shade your blooming face, A little water might displace, As nature every morn bestows The crystal dew, to cleanse the rose. Those tresses, as the raven black, That wav'd in ringlets down your back, Uncomb'd, and injur'd by neglect, Destroy the face, which once they deck'd. Whence this forgetfulness of dress? Pray, madam, are you marry'd? Yes. Nay, then indeed the wonder ceases, No matter now how loose your dress is; The end is won, your fortune's made, Your sister now may take the trade. Alas! what pity 'tis to find This fault in half the female kind! From hence proceed aversion, strife, And all that fours the wedded life. Beauty can only point the dart, 'Tis neatness guides it to the heart; Let neatness then, and beauty strive To keep a wav'ring flame alive. 'Tis harder far (you'll find it true) To keep the conquest, than subdue; Admit us once behind the screen, What is there farther to be seen? A newer face may raise the flame, But every woman is the same. Then study chiefly to improve The charm, that fix'd your husband's love. Weigh well his humour. Was it dress, That gave your beauty power to bless? Pursue it still; be neater seen; 'Tis always frugal to be clean; So shall you keep alive desire, And time's swift wing shall fan the fire. In garret high (as stories say) A Poet sung his tuneful lay; So soft, so smooth his verse, you'd swear Apollo, and the muses there. Through all the town his praises rung, His sonnets at the playhouse sung; High waving o'er his lab'ring head, The goddess Want her pinions spread, And with poetic fury fir'd, What Phœbus faintly had inspir'd. A noble Youth, of taste and wit, Approv'd the sprightly things he writ, And sought him in his cobweb dome, Discharg'd his rent, and brought him home. Behold him at the stately board, Who, but the Poet, and my Lord! Each day deliciously he dines, And greedy quaffs the gen'rous wines; His sides were plump, his skin was sleek, And plenty wanton'd on his cheek; Astonish'd at the change so new, Away th' inspiring goddess flew. Now, dropt for politics, and news, Neglected lay the drooping muse; Unmindful whence his fortune came, He stifled the poetic flame; Nor tale, nor sonnet, for my lady, Lampoon, nor epigram was ready. With just contempt his Patron saw, (Resolv'd his bounty to withdraw) And thus, with anger in his look, The late-repenting fool bespoke. Blind to the good that courts thee grown, Whence has the sun of favour shone? Delighted with thy tuneful art, Esteem was growing in my heart; But idly thou reject'st the charm, That gave it birth, and kept it warm. Unthinking fools, alone despise The arts, that taught them first to rise. FABLE VI. The WOLF, the SHEEP, and the LAMB. Duty demands, the parent's voice Should sanctify the daughter's choice; In that, is due obedience shown; To chuse, belongs to her alone. May horror seize his midnight hour, Who builds upon a parent's pow'r, And claims, by purchase vile and base, The loathing maid for his embrace; Hence virtue sickens; and the breast, Where peace had built her downy nest, Becomes the troubled seat of care, And pines with anguish and despair. A Wolf, rapacious, rough and bold, Whose nightly plunders thinn'd the fold, Contemplating his ill-spent life, And cloy'd with thefts, would take a wife. His purpose known, the savage race, In num'rous crowds, attend the place; For why, a mighty Wolf he was, And held dominion in his jaws. Her fav'rite whelp each mother brought, And humbly his alliance sought; But cold by age, or else too nice, None found acceptance in his eyes. It happen'd, as at early dawn, He solitary cross'd the lawn, Stray'd from the fold, a sportive Lamb Skip'd wanton by her fleecy Dam; When Cupid, foe to man and beast, Discharg'd an arrow at his breast. The tim'rous breed the robber knew, And trembling o'er the meadow flew; Their nimblest speed the Wolf o'ertook, And courteous, thus the Dam bespoke. Stay, fairest, and suspend your fear, Trust me, no enemy is near; These jaws, in slaughter oft imbru'd, At length have known enough of blood; And kinder bus'ness brings me now, Vanquish'd, at beauty's feet to bow. You have a daughter—Sweet, forgive A Wolf's address.—In her I live; Love from her eyes like light'ning came, And set my marrow all on flame; Let your consent confirm my choice, And ratify our nuptial joys. Me ample wealth, and pow'r attend, Wide o'er the plains my realms extend; What midnight robber dare invade The fold, if I the guard am made? At home the shepherd's curr may sleep, While I secure his master's sheep. Discourse like this, attention claim'd; Grandeur the mother's breast inflam'd; Now fearless by his side she walk'd, Of settlements, and jointures talk'd; Propos'd, and doubled her demands Of flow'ry fields, and turnip-lands. The Wolf agrees. Her bosom swells; To Miss her happy fate she tells; And of the grand alliance vain, Contemns her kindred of the plain. The loathing Lamb with horror hears, And wearies out her Dam with pray'rs; But all in vain; mamma best knew What unexperienc'd girls should do; So, to the neighb'ring meadow carry'd, A formal ass the couple marry'd. Torn from the tyrant-mother's side, The trembler goes, a victim-bride, Reluctant, meets the rude embrace, And bleats among the howling race. With horror oft her eyes behold Her murder'd kindred of the fold; Each day a sister-lamb is serv'd, And at the glutton's table carv'd; The crashing bones he grinds for food, And slakes his thirst with streaming blood. Love, who the cruel mind detests, And lodges but in gentle breasts, Was now no more. Enjoyment past, The savage hunger'd for the feast; But (as we find in human race, A mask conceals the villain's face) Justice must authorize the treat; Till then he long'd, but durst not eat. As forth he walk'd, in quest of prey, The hunters met him on the way; Fear wings his flight; the marsh he sought; The snuffing dogs are set at fault. His stomach baulk'd, now hunger gnaws, Howling, he grinds his empty jaws; Food must be had, and lamb is nigh; His maw invokes the fraudful lie. Is this (dissembling rage, he cry'd) The gentle virtue of a bride? That, leagu'd with man's destroying race, She sets her husband for the chace? By treach'ry prompts the noisy hound To scent his footsteps on the ground? Thou trait'ress vile! for this thy blood Shall glut my rage, and dye the wood! So saying, on the Lamb he flies, Beneath his jaws the victim dies. FABLE VII. The GOOSE, and the SWANS. I hate the face, however fair, That carries an affected air; The lisping tone, the shape constrain'd, The study'd look, the passion feign'd, Are fopperies, which only tend To injure what they strive to mend. With what superior grace enchants The face, which nature's pencil paints! Where eyes, unexercis'd in art, Glow with the meaning of the heart! Where freedom, and good-humour sit, And easy gaiety, and wit! Though perfect beauty be not there, The master lines, the finish'd air, We catch from every look delight, And grow enamour'd at the sight: For beauty, though we all approve, Excites our wonder, more than love, While the agreeable strikes sure, And gives the wounds, we cannot cure. Why then, my Amoret, this care, That forms you, in effect, less fair? If nature on your cheek bestows A bloom, that emulates the rose, Or from some heav'nly image drew A form, Apelles never knew, Your ill-judg'd aid will you impart, And spoil by meretricious art? Or had you, nature's error, come Abortive from the mother's womb, Your forming care she still rejects, Which only heightens her defects. When such, of glitt'ring jewels proud, Still press the foremost in the crowd, At every public show are seen, With look awry, and aukward mein, The gaudy dress attracts the eye, And magnifies deformity. Nature may under-do her part, But seldom wants the help of art; Trust Her; she is your surest friend, Nor made your form for you to mend. A Goose, affected, empty, vain, The shrillest of the cackling train, With proud, and elevated crest, Precedence claim'd above the rest. Says she, I laugh at human race, Who say, geese hobble in their pace; Look here! the sland'rous lie detect; Not haughty man is so erect. That peacock yonder! lord, how vain The creature's of his gaudy train! If both were stript, I'd pawn my word, A goose would be the finer bird. Nature, to hide her own defects, Her bungled work with finery decks; Were geese set off with half that show, Would men admire the peacock? No. Thus vaunting, cross the mead she stalks, The cackling breed attend her walks; The sun shot down his noon-tide beams, The Swans were sporting in the streams; Their snowy plumes, and stately pride Provok'd her spleen. Why there, she cry'd, Again, what arrogance we see! Those creatures! how they mimic me! Shall every fowl the waters skim, Because we geese are known to swim? Humility they soon shall learn, And their own emptiness discern. So saying, with extended wings, Lightly upon the wave she springs; Her bosom swells, she spreads her plumes, And the swan's stately crest assumes. Contempt, and mockery ensu'd, And bursts of laughter shook the flood. A Swan, superior to the rest, Sprung forth, and thus the fool address'd. Conceited thing, elate with pride! Thy affectation all deride; These airs thy aukwardness impart, And shew thee plainly, as thou art. Among thy equals of the flock, Thou hadst escap'd the public mock, And as thy parts to good conduce, Been deem'd an honest, hobbling goose. Learn hence, to study wisdom's rules; Know, foppery's the pride of fools; And striving nature to conceal, You only her defects reveal. FABLE VIII. The LAWYER, and JUSTICE. Love! thou divinest good below, Thy pure delights few mortals know! Our rebel hearts thy sway disown, While tyrant lust usurps thy throne. The bounteous God of nature made The sexes for each other's aid, Their mutual talents to employ, To lessen ills, and heighten joy. To weaker woman he assign'd That soft'ning gentleness of mind, That can, by sympathy, impart Its likeness to the roughest heart. Her eyes with magic pow'r endu'd, To fire the dull, and awe the rude. His rosy fingers on her face Shed lavish every blooming grace, And stamp'd (perfection to display) His mildest image on her clay. Man, active, resolute, and bold, He fashion'd in a diff'rent mould, With useful arts his mind inform'd, His breast with nobler passions warm'd; He gave him knowledge, taste and sense, And courage, for the fair's defence. Her frame, resistless to each wrong, Demands protection from the strong; To man she flies, when fear alarms, And claims the temple of his arms. By nature's author thus declar'd The woman's sov'reign, and her guard, Shall man, by treach'rous wiles invade The weakness, he was meant to aid? While beauty, given to inspire Protecting love, and soft desire, Lights up a wild-fire in the heart, And to its own breast points the dart, Becomes the spoiler's base pretence To triumph over innocence? The wolf, that tears the tim'rous sheep, Was never set the fold to keep; Nor was the tyger, or the pard Meant the benighted trav'ler's guard; But man, the wildest beast of prey, Wears friendship's semblance, to betray; His strength against the weak employs, And where he should protect, destroys. Past twelve o'clock, the watchman cry'd, His brief the studious Lawyer ply'd; The all-prevailing fee lay nigh, The earnest of to-morrow's lie. Sudden the furious winds arise, The jarring casement shatter'd flies; The doors admit a hollow sound, And rattling from their hinges bound; When Justice, in a blaze of light, Reveal'd her radiant form to sight. The wretch with thrilling horror shook, Loose every joint, and pale his look; Not having seen her in the courts, Or found her mention'd in reports, He ask'd, with fault'ring tongue, her name, Her errand there, and whence she came? Sternly the white-rob'd Shade reply'd, (A crimson glow her visage dy'd) Can'st thou be doubtful who I am? Is Justice grown so strange a name? Were not your courts for Justice rais'd? 'Twas there, of old, my altars blaz'd. My guardian thee did I elect, My sacred temple to protect, That thou, and all thy venal tribe Should spurn the goddess for the bribe? Aloud the ruin'd client cries, Justice has neither ears, nor eyes; In foul alliance with the bar, 'Gainst me the judge denounces war, And rarely issues his decree, But with intent to baffle me. She paus'd. Her breast with fury burn'd. The trembling Lawyer thus return'd. I own the charge is justly laid, And weak th' excuse that can be made; Yet search the spacious globe, and see If all mankind are not like me. The gown-man, skill'd in romish lies, By faith's false glass deludes our eyes; O'er conscience rides without controul, And robs the man, to save his soul. The doctor, with important face, By sly design, mistakes the case; Prescribes, and spins out the disease, To trick the patient of his fees. The soldier, rough with many a scar, And red with slaughter, leads the war; If he a nation's trust betray, The foe has offer'd double pay. When vice o'er all mankind prevails, And weighty int'rest turns the scales, Must I be better than the rest, And harbour Justice in my breast? On one side only take the fee, Content with poverty and thee? Thou blind to sense, and vile of mind, Th' exasperated Shade rejoin'd, If virtue from the world is flown, Will other's frauds excuse thy own? For sickly souls the priest was made; Physicians, for the body's aid; The soldier guarded liberty; Man woman, and the lawyer me. If all are faithless to their trust, They leave not thee the less unjust. Henceforth your pleadings I disclaim, And bar the sanction of my name; Within your courts it shall be read, That Justice from the law is fled. She spoke; and hid in shades her face, 'Till Hardwick sooth'd her into grace. FABLE IX. The FARMER, the SPANIEL, and the CAT. Why knits my dear her angry brow? What rude offence alarms you now? I said, that Delia's fair, 'tis true, But did I say she equall'd you? Can't I another's face commend, Or to her virtues be a friend, But instantly your forehead lours, As if her merit lessen'd yours? From female envy never free, All must be blind, because you see. Survey the gardens, fields, and bow'rs, The buds, the blossoms, and the flow'rs, Then tell me where the wood-bine grows, That vies in sweetness with the rose? Or where the lily's snowy white, That throws such beauties on the sight? Yet folly is it to declare, That these are neither sweet, nor fair. The chrystal shines with fainter rays, Before the di'mond's brighter blaze; And fops will say, the di'mond dies, Before the lustre of your eyes: But I, who deal in truth, deny That neither shine when you are by. When zephirs o'er the blossoms stray, And sweets along the air convey, Shan't I the fragrant breeze inhale, Because you breathe a sweeter gale? Sweet are the flow'rs, that deck the field; Sweet is the smell the blossoms yield; Sweet is the summer gale that blows; And sweet, tho' sweeter you, the rose. Shall envy then torment your breast, If you are lovelier than the rest? For while I give to each her due, By praising them I flatter you; And praising most, I still declare You fairest, where the rest are fair. As at his board a Farmer sate, Replenish'd by his homely treat, His fav'rite Spaniel near him stood, And with his master shar'd the food; The crackling bones his jaws devour'd, His lapping tongue the trenchers scour'd; 'Till sated now, supine he lay, And snor'd the rising fumes away. The hungry Cat, in turn, drew near, And humbly crav'd a servant's share; Her modest worth the Master knew, And strait the fat'ning morsel threw: Enrag'd the snarling Curr awoke, And thus, with spiteful envy, spoke. They only claim a right to eat, Who earn by services their meat. Me, zeal and industry inflame To scour the fields; and spring the game; Or, plunging in the wintry wave, For man the wounded bird to save. With watchful diligence I keep, From prowling wolves, his fleecy sheep; At home his midnight hours secure, And drive the robber from the door. For this, his breast with kindness glows; For this, his hand the food bestows; And shall thy indolence impart A warmer friendship to his heart, That thus he robs me of my due, To pamper such vile things as you? I own (with meekness Puss reply'd) Superior merit on your side; Nor does my breast with envy swell, To find it recompenc'd so well; Yet I, in what my nature can, Contribute to the good of man. Whose claws destroy the pilf'ring mouse? Who drives the vermin from the house? Or, watchful for the lab'ring swain, From lurking rats secures the grain? From hence, if he rewards bestow, Why should your heart with gall o'erflow? Why pine my happiness to see, Since there's enough for you and me? Thy words are just, the Farmer cry'd, And spurn'd the snarler from his side. FABLE X. The SPIDER, and the BEE. The nymph, who walks the public streets, And sets her cap at all she meets, May catch the fool, who turns to stare, But men of sense avoid the snare. As on the margin of the flood, With silken line, my Lydia stood, I smil'd to see the pains you took, To cover o'er the fraudful hook. Along the forest as we stray'd, You saw the boy his lime-twiggs spread; Guess'd you the reason of his fear, Lest, heedless, we approach'd too near? For as behind the bush we lay, The linnet flutter'd on the spray. Needs there such caution to delude The scaly fry, and feather'd brood? And think you, with inferior art, To captivate the human heart? The maid, who modestly conceals Her beauties, while she hides, reveals. Give but a glimpse, and fancy draws Whate'er the Grecian Venus was. From Eve's first fig-leaf to brocade, All dress was meant for fancy's aid, Which evermore delighted dwells On what the bashful nymph conceals. When Cælia struts in man's attire, She shews too much to raise desire; But from the hoop's bewitching round, Her very shoe has pow'r to wound. The roving eye, the bosom bare, The forward laugh, the wanton air, May catch the fop; for gudgeons strike At the bare hook, and bait, alike; While salmon play regardless by, 'Till art, like nature, forms the fly. Beneath a peasant's homely thatch, A Spider long had held her watch; From morn to night, with restless care, She spun her web, and wove her snare. Within the limits of her reign, Lay many a heedless captive slain, Or flutt'ring, struggled in the toils, To burst the chains, and shun her wiles. A straying Bee, that perch'd hard by, Beheld her with disdainful eye, And thus began. Mean thing, give o'er, And lay thy slender threads no more; A thoughtless fly or two, at most, Is all the conquest thou can'st boast; For bees of sense thy arts evade, We see so plain the nets are laid. The gaudy tulip, that displays Her spreading foliage to the gaze; That points her charms at all she sees, And yields to every wanton breeze, Attracts not me: where blushing grows, Guarded with thorns, the modest rose, Enamour'd, round and round I fly, Or on her fragrant bosom lie; Reluctant, she my ardour meets, And bashful, renders up her sweets. To wiser heads attention lend, And learn this lesson from a friend. She, who with modesty retires, Adds fewel to her lover's fires, While such incautious jilts as you, By folly your own schemes undo. FABLE XI. The YOUNG LION, and the APE. 'Tis true, I blame your lover's choice, Though flatter'd by the public voice, And peevish grow, and sick, to hear His exclamations, O how fair! I listen not to wild delights, And transports of expected nights; What is to me your hoard of charms? The whiteness of your neck and arms? Needs there no acquisition more, To keep contention from the door? Yes; pass a fortnight, and you'll find, All beauty cloys, but of the mind. Sense, and good-humour ever prove The surest cords to fasten love. Yet, Phillis, simplest of your sex, You never think but to perplex, Coquetting it with every ape, That struts abroad in human shape; Not that the coxcomb is your taste, But that it stings your lover's breast; To-morrow you resign the sway, Prepar'd to honour, and obey, The tyrant-mistress change for life, To the submission of a wife. Your follies, if you can, suspend, And learn instruction from a friend. Reluctant, hear the first address, Think often, ere you answer, yes; But once resolv'd, throw off disguise, And wear your wishes in your eyes. With caution every look forbear, That might create one jealous fear, A lover's ripening hopes confound, Or give the gen'rous breast a wound. Contemn the girlish arts to teaze, Nor use your pow'r, unless to please; For fools alone with rigour sway, When soon, or late, they must obey. The king of brutes, in life's decline, Resolv'd dominion to resign; The beasts were summon'd to appear, And bend before the royal heir. They came; a day was fix'd; the crowd Before their future monarch bow'd. A dapper Monkey, pert and vain, Step'd forth, and thus address'd the train. Why cringe my friends with slavish awe, Before this pageant king of straw? Shall we anticipate the hour, And ere we feel it, own his pow'r? The counsels of experience prize, I know the maxims of the wise; Subjection let us cast away, And live the monarchs of to-day; 'Tis ours the vacant hand to spurn, And play the tyrant each in turn. So shall he right from wrong discern, And mercy from oppression learn; At others woes be taught to melt, And loath the ills himself has felt. He spoke; his bosom swell'd with pride. The youthful Lion thus reply'd. What madness prompts thee to provoke My wrath, and dare th' impending stroke? Thou wretched fool! can wrongs impart Compassion to the feeling heart? Or teach the grateful breast to glow, The hand to give, or eye to flow? Learn'd in the practice of their schools, From women thou hast drawn thy rules; To them return; in such a cause, From only such expect applause; The partial sex I not condemn, For liking those, who copy them. Would'st thou the gen'rous lion bind, By kindness bribe him to be kind; Good offices their likeness get, And payment lessens not the debt; With multiplying hand he gives The good, from others he receives; Or for the bad makes fair return, And pays with int'rest, scorn for scorn. FABLE XII. The COLT, and the FARMER. Tell me, Corinna, if you can, Why so averse, so coy to man? Did nature, lavish of her care, From her best pattern form you fair, That you, ungrateful to her cause, Should mock her gifts, and spurn her laws? And miser-like, with-hold that store, Which, by imparting, blesses more? Beauty's a gift, by heav'n assign'd, The portion of the female kind; For this the yielding maid demands Protection at her lover's hands; And though by wasting years it fade, Remembrance tells him, once 'twas paid. And will you then this wealth conceal, For age to rust, or time to steal? The summer of your youth to rove, A stranger to the joys of love? Then, when life's winter hastens on, And youth's fair heritage is gone, Dow'rless to court some peasant's arms, To guard your wither'd age from harms; No gratitude to warm his breast, For blooming beauty, once possess'd; How will you curse that stubborn pride, Which drove your bark across the tide, And sailing before folly's wind, Left sense and happiness behind? Corinna, lest these whims prevail, To such as you, I write my tale. A Colt, for blood, and mettled speed, The choicest of the running breed, Of youthful strength, and beauty vain, Refus'd subjection to the rein. In vain the groom's officious skill Oppos'd his pride, and check'd his will; In vain the master's forming care Restrain'd with threats, or sooth'd with pray'r; Of freedom proud, and scorning man, Wild o'er the spacious plains he ran. Where e'er luxuriant nature spread Her flow'ry carpet o'er the mead, Or bubbling streams soft-gliding pass, To cool and freshen up the grass, Disdaining bounds, he crop'd the blade, And wanton'd in the spoil he made. In plenty thus the summer pass'd, Revolving winter came at last; The trees no more a shelter yield, The verdure withers from the field, Perpetual snows invest the ground, In icy chains the streams are bound, Cold, nipping winds, and rattling hail, His lank, unshelter'd sides assail. As round he cast his rueful eyes, He saw the thatch'd-roof cottage rise; The prospect touch'd his heart with chear, And promis'd kind deliv'rance near. A stable, erst his scorn and hate, Was now become his wish'd retreat; His passion cool, his pride forgot, A Farmer's welcome yard he sought. The Master saw his woeful plight, His limbs, that totter'd with his weight, And, friendly, to the stable led, And saw him litter'd, dress'd, and fed. In slothful ease, all night he lay; The servants rose at break of day; The market calls. Along the road, His back must bear the pond'rous load; In vain he struggles, or complains, Incessant blows reward his pains. To-morrow varies but his toil; Chain'd to the plough, he breaks the soil; While scanty meals, at night repay The painful labours of the day. Subdu'd by toil, with anguish rent, His self-upbraidings found a vent. Wretch that I am! he sighing said, By arrogance and folly led, Had but my restive youth been brought To learn the lesson nature taught, Then had I, like my sires of yore, The prize from every courser bore; While man bestow'd rewards, and praise, And females crown'd my latter days. Now lasting servitude's my lot, My birth contemn'd, my speed forgot, Doom'd am I, for my pride, to bear A living death, from year to year. FABLE XIII. The OWL, and the NIGHTINGALE. To know the mistress' humour right, See if her maids are clean, and tight; If Betty waits without her stays, She copies but her lady's ways. When miss comes in with boist'rous shout, And drops no curt'sy going out, Depend upon't, mamma is one, Who reads, or drinks too much alone. If bottled beer her thirst asswage, She feels enthusiastic rage, And burns with ardour to inherit The gifts, and workings of the spirit. If learning crack her giddy brains, No remedy, but death, remains. Sum up the various ills of life, And all are sweet, to such a wife At home, superior wit she vaunts, And twits her husband with his wants; Her ragged offspring all around, Like pigs, are wallowing on the ground: Impatient ever of controul, She knows no order, but of soul; With books her litter'd floor is spread, Of nameless authors, never read; Foul linen, petticoats, and lace Fill up the intermediate space. Abroad, at visitings, her tongue Is never still, and always wrong; All meanings she defines away, And stands, with truth and sense, at bay. If e'er she meets a gentle heart, Skill'd in the housewife's useful art, Who makes her family her care, And builds contentment's temple there, She starts at such mistakes in nature, And cries, lord help us! what a creature! Melissa, if the moral strike, You'll find the fable not unlike. An Owl, puff'd up with self-conceit, Lov'd learning better than his meat; Old manuscripts he treasur'd up, And rummag'd every grocer's shop; At pastry-cooks was known to ply, And strip, for science, every pye. For modern poetry, and wit, He had read all that Blackmore writ; So intimate with Curl was grown, His learned treasures were his own; To all his authors had access, And sometimes would correct the press. In logic he acquir'd such knowledge, You'd swear him fellow of a college; Alike to every art, and science, His daring genius bid defiance, And swallow'd wisdom, with that haste, That cits do custards at a feast. Within the shelter of a wood, One ev'ning, as he musing stood, Hard by, upon a leafy spray, A Nightingale began his lay. Sudden he starts, with anger stung, And, screeching, interrupts the song. Pert, busy thing, thy airs give o'er, And let my contemplations soar. What is the music of thy voice, But jarring dissonance, and noise? By wise. True harmony, thou'lt find, Not in the throat, but in the mind; By empty chirping not attain'd, But by laborious study gain'd. Go read the authors Pope explodes, Fathom the depth of Cibber's odes, With modern plays improve thy wit, Read all the learning Henley writ; And, if thou needs must sing, sing then, And emulate the ways of men; So shalt thou grow, like me, refin'd, And bring improvement to thy kind. Thou wretch, the little Warbler cry'd, Made up of ignorance, and pride, Ask all the birds, and they'll declare, A greater blockhead wings not air. Read o'er thyself, thy talents scan, Science was only meant for man. No useless authors me molest, I mind the duties of my nest; With careful wing, protect my young, And chear their ev'nings with a song. Thus, following nature, and her laws, From men, and birds I claim applause; While, nurs'd in pedantry, and sloth, An Owl is scorn'd alike by both. FABLE XIV. The SPARROW, and the DOVE. It was, as learn'd traditions say, Upon an April's blithsome day, When pleasure, ever on the wing, Return'd, companion of the spring, And chear'd the birds with am'rous heat, Instructing little hearts to beat; A Sparrow, frolic, gay, and young, Of bold address, and flippant tongue, Just left his lady of a night, Like him, to follow new delight. The youth, of many a conquest vain, Flew off to seek the chirping train; The chirping train he quickly found, And with a saucy ease, bow'd round. For every she his bosom burns, And this, and that he wooes by turns; And here a sigh, and there a bill, And here—those eyes, so form'd to kill! And now, with ready tongue, he strings Unmeaning, soft, resistless things; With vows, and dem-me's skill'd to woo, As other pretty fellows do. Not that he thought this short essay A prologue needful to his play; No, trust me, says our learned letter, He knew the virtuous sex much better; But these he held as specious arts, To shew his own superior parts, The form of decency to shield, And give a just pretence to yield. Thus finishing his courtly play, He mark'd the fav'rite of the day; With careless impudence drew near, And whisper'd hebrew in her ear; A hint, which like the mason's sign, The conscious can alone divine. The flutt'ring nymph, expert at feigning, Cry'd, Sir!—pray Sir, explain your meaning— Go prate to those, that may endure ye— To me this rudeness!—I'll assure ye!— Then off she glided, like a swallow, As saying—you guess where to follow. To such as know the party set, 'Tis needless to declare they met; The parson's barn, as authors mention, Confess'd the fair had apprehension. Her honour there secure from stain, She held all farther trifling vain, No more affected to be coy, But rush'd, licentious, on the joy. Hist, love! the male companion cry'd, Retire a while; I fear we're spy'd. Nor was the caution vain; he saw A Turtle, rustling in the straw, While o'er her callow brood she hung, And fondly thus address'd her young. Ye tender objects of my care! Peace, peace, ye little helpless pair! Anon he comes, your gentle sire, And brings you all your hearts require. For us, his infants, and his bride, For us, with only love to guide, Our lord assumes an eagle's speed, And like a lion, dares to bleed. Nor yet by wintry skies confin'd, He mounts upon the rudest wind, From danger tears the vital spoil, And with affection sweetens toil. Ah cease, too vent'rous! cease to dare, In thine, our dearer safety spare! From him, ye cruel falcons, stray, And turn, ye fowlers, far away! Should I survive to see the day, That tears me from myself away, That cancels all that heav'n could give, The life, by which alone I live, Alas, how more than lost were I, Who, in the thought, already die! Ye pow'rs, whom men, and birds obey, Great rulers of your creatures, say, Why mourning comes, by bliss convey'd, And ev'n the sweets of love allay'd? Where grows enjoyment, tall, and fair, Around it twines entangling care; While fear for what our souls possess, Enervates every pow'r to bless; Yet friendship forms the bliss above, And, life! what art thou, without love? Our hero, who had heard apart, Felt something moving in his heart, But quickly, with disdain, suppress'd The virtue, rising in his breast; And first he feign'd to laugh aloud, And next, approaching, smil'd and bow'd. Madam, you must not think me rude; Good-manners never can intrude; I vow I come through pure good-nature— (Upon my soul, a charming creature!) Are these the comforts of a wife? This careful, cloister'd, moaping life? No doubt, that odious thing, call'd duty, Is a sweet province for a beauty. Thou pretty ignorance! thy will Is measur'd to thy want of skill; That good old-fashion'd dame, thy mother, Has taught thy infant years no other. The greatest ill in the creation, Is sure the want of education. But think ye?—tell me without feigning, Have all these charms no farther meaning? Dame nature, if you don't forget her, Might teach your ladyship much better. For shame, reject this mean employment, Enter the world, and taste enjoyment; Where time, by circling bliss, we measure; Beauty was form'd alone for pleasure; Come, prove the blessing, follow me, Be wise, be happy, and be free. Kind Sir, reply'd our matron chaste, Your zeal seems pretty much in haste; I own, the fondness to be bless'd Is a deep thirst in every breast; Of blessings too I have my store, Yet quarrel not, should heav'n give more; Then prove the change to be expedient, And think me, Sir, your most obedient. Here turning, as to one inferior, Our gallant spoke, and smil'd superior. Methinks, to quit your boasted station Requires a world of hesitation; Where brats, and bonds are held a blessing, The case, I doubt, is past redressing. Why, child, suppose the joys I mention, Were the mere fruits of my invention, You've cause sufficient for your carriage, In flying from the curse of marriage; That sly decoy, with vary'd snares, That takes your widgeon in by pairs; Alike to husband, and to wife, The cure of love, and bane of life; The only method of forecasting, To make misfortune firm, and lasting; The sin, by heav'n's peculiar sentence, Unpardon'd, through a life's repentance. It is the double snake, that weds A common tail to diff'rent heads, That lead the carcass still astray, By dragging each a diff'rent way. Of all the ills, that may attend me, From marriage, mighty gods, defend me! Give Me frank nature's wild demesne, And boundless tract of air serene, Where fancy, ever wing'd for change, Delights to sport, delights to range; There, Liberty! to thee is owing Whate'er of bliss is worth bestowing; Delights, still vary'd, and divine, Sweet goddess of the hills! are thine. What say you now, you pretty pink you? Have I, for once, spoke reason, think you? You take me now for no romancer— Come, never study for an answer; Away, cast every care behind ye, And fly where joy alone shall find ye. Soft yet, return'd our female fencer, A question more, or so—and then, Sir. You've rally'd me with sense exceeding, With much fine wit, and better breeding; But pray, Sir, how do You contrive it? Do those of your world never wive it? “No, no.” How then? “Why, dare I tell, “What does the bus'ness full as well.” Do you ne'er love? “An hour at leisure.” Have you no friendships? “Yes, for pleasure.” No care for little ones? “We get 'em, “The rest the mothers mind, and let 'em.” Thou wretch, rejoin'd the kindling Dove, Quite lost to life, as lost to love! Whene'er misfortune comes, how just! And come misfortune surely must; In the dread season of dismay, In that, your hour of trial, say, Who then shall prop your sinking heart? Who bear affliction's weightier part? Say, when the black-brow'd welken bends, And winter's gloomy form impends, To mourning turns all transient chear, And blasts the melancholy year; For times, at no persuasion, stay, Nor vice can find perpetual May; Then where's that tongue, by folly fed, That soul of pertness, whither fled? All shrunk within thy lonely nest, Forlorn, abandon'd, and unbless'd; No friend, by cordial bonds ally'd, Shall seek thy cold, unsocial side; No chirping prattlers, to delight Shall turn the long-enduring night; No bride her words of balm impart, And warm thee at her constant heart. Freedom, restrain'd by reason's force, Is as the sun's unvarying course, Benignly active, sweetly bright, Affording warmth, affording light; But torn from virtue's sacred rules, Becomes a comet, gaz'd by fools, Fore-boding cares, and storms, and strife, And fraught with all the plagues of life. Thou fool! by union every creature Subsists, through universal nature; And this, to beings void of mind, Is wedlock, of a meaner kind. While womb'd in space, primæval clay A yet unfashion'd embryo lay, The source of endless good above Shot down his spark of kindling love; Touch'd by the all-enliv'ning flame, Then motion first exulting came; Each atom sought its sep'rate class, Through many a fair, enamour'd mass; Love cast the central charm around, And with eternal nuptials bound. Then form, and order o'er the sky, First train'd their bridal pomp on high; The sun display'd his orb to sight, And burnt with hymeneal light. Hence nature's virgin-womb conceiv'd, And with the genial burden heav'd; Forth came the oak, her first born heir, And scal'd the breathing steep of air; Then infant stems, of various use, Imbib'd her soft, maternal juice; The flow'rs, in early bloom disclos'd, Upon her fragrant breast repos'd; Within her warm embraces grew A race of endless form, and hue; Then pour'd her lesser offspring round, And fondly cloath'd their parent ground. Nor here alone the virtue reign'd, By matter's cumb'ring form detain'd; But thence, subliming, and refin'd, Aspir'd, and reach'd its kindred Mind. Caught in the fond, celestial fire, The Mind perceiv'd unknown desire, And now with kind effusion flow'd, And now with cordial ardours glow'd, Beheld the sympathetic fair, And lov'd its own resemblance there; On all with circling radiance shone, But centring, fix'd on one alone; There clasp'd the heav'n-appointed wife, And doubled every joy of life. Here ever blessing, ever bless'd, Resides this beauty of the breast, As from his palace, here the god Still beams effulgent bliss abroad, Here gems his own eternal round, The ring, by which the world is bound, Here bids his seat of empire grow, And builds his little heav'n below. The bridal partners thus ally'd, And thus in sweet accordance ty'd, One body, heart and spirit live, Enrich'd by every joy they give; Like echo, from her vocal hold, Return'd in music twenty fold. Their union firm, and undecay'd, Nor time can shake, nor pow'r invade, But as the stem, and scion stand, Ingrafted by a skilful hand, They check the tempest's wintry rage, And bloom and strengthen into age. A thousand amities unknown, And pow'rs, perceiv'd by love alone, Endearing looks, and chaste desire, Fan, and support the mutual fire, Whose flame, perpetual, as refin'd, Is fed by an immortal mind. Nor yet the nuptial sanction ends, Like Nile it opens, and descends, Which, by apparent windings led, We trace to its celestial head. The sire, first springing from above, Becomes the source of life, and love, And gives his filial heir to flow, In fondness down on sons below: Thus roll'd in one continu'd tide, To time's extremest verge they glide, While kindred streams, on either hand, Branch forth in blessings o'er the land. Thee, wretch! no lisping babe shall name, No late-returning brother claim, No kinsman on thy road rejoice, No sister greet thy ent'ring voice, With partial eyes no parents fee, And bless their years restor'd in thee. In age rejected, or declin'd, An alien, ev'n among thy kind, The partner of thy scorn'd embrace, Shall play the wanton in thy face, Each spark unplume thy little pride, All friendship fly thy faithless side, Thy name shall like thy carcass rot, In sickness spurn'd, in death forgot. All-giving pow'r! great source of life! O hear the parent! hear the wife! That life, thou lendest from above, Though little, make it large in love; O bid my feeling heart expand To every claim, on every hand; To those, from whom my days I drew, To these, in whom those days renew, To all my kin, however wide, In cordial warmth, as blood ally'd, To friends, with steely fetters twin'd, And to the cruel, not unkind! But chief, the lord of my desire, My life, myself, my soul, my sire, Friends, children, all that wish can claim, Chaste passion clasp, and rapture name; O spare him, spare him, gracious pow'r! O give him to my latest hour! Let me my length of life employ, To give my sole enjoyment joy. His love, let mutual love excite, Turn all my cares to his delight, And every needless blessing spare, Wherein my darling wants a share. When he with graceful action wooes, And sweetly bills, and fondly cooes, Ah! deck me, to his eyes alone, With charms attractive as his own, And in my circling wings caress'd, Give all the lover to my breast. Then in our chaste, connubial bed, My bosom pillow'd for his head, His eyes with blissful slumbers close, And watch, with me, my lord's repose, Your peace around his temples twine, And love him, with a love like mine. And, for I know his gen'rous flame, Beyond whate'er my sex can claim, Me too to your protection take, And spare me for my husband's sake. Let one unruffled, calm delight The loving, and belov'd unite; One pure desire our bosoms warm, One will direct, one wish inform; Through life, one mutual aid sustain, In death, one peaceful grave contain. While, swelling with the darling theme, Her accents pour'd an endless stream, The well-known wings a sound impart, That reach'd her ear, and touch'd her heart; Quick drop'd the music of her tongue, And forth, with eager joy, she sprung. As swift her ent'ring consort flew, And plum'd, and kindled at the view; Their wings their souls embracing meet, Their hearts with answ'ring measure beat; Half lost in sacred sweets, and bless'd With raptures felt, but ne'er express'd. Strait to her humble roof she led The partner of her spotless bed; Her young, a flutt'ring pair, arise, Their welcome sparkling in their eyes; Transported, to their sire they bound, And hang with speechless action round. In pleasure wrapt, the parents stand, And see their little wings expand; The sire, his life-sustaining prize To each expecting bill applies, There fondly pours the wheaten spoil, With transport giv'n, though won with toil; While, all collected at the sight, And silent through supreme delight, The fair high heav'n of bliss beguiles, And on her lord, and infants smiles. The Sparrow, whose attention hung Upon the Dove's enchanting tongue, Of all his little slights disarm'd, And from himself, by virtue, charm'd, When now he saw, what only seem'd, A fact, so late a fable deem'd, His soul to envy he resign'd, His hours of folly to the wind, In secret wish'd a turtle too, And sighing to himself, withdrew. FABLE XV. The FEMALE SEDUCERS. 'Tis said of widow, maid, and wife, That honour is a woman's life; Unhappy sex! who only claim A being, in the breath of fame, Which, tainted, not the quick'ning gales, That sweep Sabæa's spicy vales, Nor all the healing sweets restore, That breathe along Arabia's shore. The trav'ler, if he chance to stray, May turn uncensur'd to his way; Polluted streams again are pure, And deepest wounds admit a cure; But woman! no redemption knows, The wounds of honour never close. Though distant every hand to guide, Nor skill'd on life's tempestuous tide, If once her feeble bark recede, Or deviate from the course decreed, In vain she seeks the friendless shore, Her swifter folly flies before; The circling ports against her close, And shut the wand'rer from repose; 'Till, by conflicting waves oppress'd, Her found'ring pinnace sinks to rest. Are there no off'rings to atone For but a single error? None. Though woman is avow'd, of old, No daughter of celestial mould, Her temp'ring not without allay, And form'd but of the finer clay, We challenge from the mortal dame The strength angelic natures claim; Nay more; for sacred stories tell, That ev'n immortal angels fell. Whatever fills the teeming sphere Of humid earth, and ambient air, With varying elements endu'd, Was form'd to fall, and rise renew'd. The stars no fix'd duration know, Wide oceans ebb, again to flow, The moon repletes her waining face, All-beauteous, from her late disgrace, And suns, that mourn approaching night, Refulgent rise with new-born light. In vain may death, and time subdue, While nature mints her race anew, And holds some vital spark apart, Like virtue, hid in every heart; 'Tis hence reviving warmth is seen, To cloath a naked world in green. No longer barr'd by winter's cold, Again the gates of life unfold; Again each insect tries his wing, And lifts fresh pinions on the spring; Again from every latent root The bladed stem, and tendril shoot, Exhaling incense to the skies, Again to perish, and to rise. And must weak woman then disown The change, to which a world is prone? In one meridian brightness shine, And ne'er, like ev'ning suns, decline? Resolv'd and firm alone?—Is this What we demand of woman?—Yes. But should the spark of vestal fire, In some unguarded hour expire, Or should the nightly thief invade Hesperia's chaste, and sacred shade, Of all the blooming spoil possess'd, The dragon honour charm'd to rest, Shall virtue's flame no more return? No more with virgin splendor burn? No more the ravag'd garden blow With spring's succeeding blossom?—No. Pity may mourn, but not restore, And woman falls, to rise no more. Within this sublunary sphere, A country lies—no matter where; The clime may readily be found By all, who tread poetic ground. A stream, call'd life, across it glides, And equally the land divides; And here, of vice the province lies, And there, the hills of virtue rise. Upon a mountain's airy stand, Whose summit look'd to either land, An ancient pair their dwelling chose, As well for prospect, as repose; For mutual faith they long were fam'd, And temp'rance, and religion, nam'd. A num'rous progeny divine, Confess'd the honours of their line; But in a little daughter fair, Was center'd more than half their care; For heav'n, to gratulate her birth, Gave signs of future joy to earth; White was the robe this infant wore, And Chastity the name she bore. As now the maid in stature grew, (A flow'r just op'ning to the view) Oft through her native lawns she stray'd, And wrestling with the lambkins play'd; Her looks diffusive sweets bequeath'd, The breeze grew purer as she breath'd, The morn her radiant blush assum'd, The spring with earlier fragrance bloom'd, And nature, yearly, took delight, Like her, to dress the world in white. But when her rising form was seen To reach the crisis of fifteen, Her parents up the mountain's head, With anxious step their darling led; By turns they snatch'd her to their breast, And thus the fears of age express'd. O joyful cause of many a care! O daughter, too divinely fair! Yon world, on this important day, Demands thee to a dangerous way; A painful journey, all must go, Whose doubtful period none can know, Whose due direction who can find, Where reason's mute, and sense is blind? Ah, what unequal leaders these, Through such a wide, perplexing maze! Then mark the warnings of the wife, And learn what love, and years advise. Far to the right thy prospect bend, Where yonder tow'ring hills ascend; Lo, there the arduous paths in view, Which virtue, and her sons pursue! With toil o'er less'ning earth they rise, And gain, and gain upon the skies. Narrow's the way her children tread, No walk, for pleasure smoothly spread, But rough, and difficult, and steep, Painful to climb, and hard to keep. Fruits immature those lands dispense, A food indelicate to sense, Of taste unpleasant; yet from those Pure health, with chearful vigour flows, And strength, unfeeling of decay, Throughout the long, laborious way. Hence, as they scale that heav'nly road, Each limb is lighten'd of its load; From earth refining still they go, And leave the mortal weight below; Then spreads the strait, the doubtful clears, And smooth the rugged path appears; For custom turns fatigue to ease, And, taught by virtue, pain can please. At length, the toilsome journey o'er, And near the bright, celestial shore, A gulph, black, fearful, and profound, Appears, of either world the bound, Through darkness, leading up to light; Sense backwards shrinks, and shuns the sight; For there the transitory train, Of time, and form, and care, and pain, And matter's gross, incumb'ring mass, Man's late associates, cannot pass, But sinking, quit th' immortal charge, And leave the wond'ring soul at large; Lightly she wings her obvious way, And mingles with eternal day. Thither, O! thither wing thy speed, Though pleasure charm, or pain impede! To such th' all-bounteous pow'r has giv'n, For present earth, a future heav'n; For trivial loss, unmeasur'd gain, And endless bliss, for transient pain. Then fear, ah! fear to turn thy sight, Where yonder flow'ry fields invite; Wide on the left the path-way bends, And with pernicious ease descends; There sweet to sense, and fair to show, New-planted Edens seem to blow, Trees, that delicious poison bear, For death is vegetable there. Hence is the frame of health unbrac'd, Each sinew slack'ning at the taste; The soul to passion yields her throne, And fees with organs not her own; While, like the slumb'rer in the night, Pleas'd with the shadowy dream of light, Before her alienated eyes The scenes of fairy-land arise; The puppet world's amusing show, Dipt in the gayly-colour'd bow; Scepters, and wreaths, and glitt'ring things, The toys of infants, and of kings, That tempt, along the baneful plain, The idly wise, and lightly vain, 'Till verging on the gulphy shore, Sudden they sink, and rise no more. But list to what thy fates declare; Though thou art woman, frail as fair, If once thy sliding foot should stray, Once quit yon heav'n-appointed way, For thee, lost maid, for thee alone, Nor pray'rs shall plead, nor tears atone; Reproach, scorn, infamy, and hate, On thy returning steps shall wait, Thy form be loath'd by every eye, And every foot thy presence fly. Thus arm'd with words of potent sound, Like guardian angels plac'd around, A charm, by truth divinely cast, Forward our young advent'rer pass'd. Forth from her sacred eye-lids sent, Like morn, fore-running radiance went, While honour, hand-maid, late assign'd, Upheld her lucid train behind. Awe-struck, the much-admiring crowd Before the virgin vision bow'd, Gaz'd with an ever-new delight, And caught fresh virtues at the sight: For not of earth's unequal frame They deem'd the heav'n-compounded Dame, If matter, sure the most refin'd, High wrought, and temper'd into mind, Some darling daughter of the day, And body'd by her native ray. Where-e'er she passes, thousands bend, And thousands, where she moves, attend; Her ways observant eyes confess, Her steps pursuing praises bless; While to the elevated Maid Oblations, as to heav'n, are paid. 'Twas on an ever-blithsome day, The jovial birth of rosy May, When genial warmth, no more suppress'd, New-melts the frost in every breast, The cheek with secret flushing dyes, And looks kind things from chastest eyes; The sun with healthier visage glows, Aside his clouded kerchief throws, And dances up th' etherial plain, Where late he us'd to climb with pain, While nature, as from bonds set free, Springs out, and gives a loose to glee. And, now for momentary rest, The Nymph her travel'd step repress'd, Just turn'd to view the stage attain'd, And glory'd in the height she gain'd. Out-stretch'd before her wide survey, The realms of sweet perdition lay, And pity touch'd her soul with woe, To see a world so lost below; When strait the breeze began to breathe Airs, gently wafted from beneath, That bore commission'd witchcraft thence, And reach'd her sympathy of sense; No sounds of discord, that disclose A people sunk, and lost in woes, But as of present good possess'd, The very triumph of the bless'd. The Maid in wrapt attention hung, While thus approaching Sirens sung. Hither, fairest, hither haste, Brightest beauty, come and taste What the pow'rs of bliss unfold, Joys, too mighty to be told; Taste what extasies they give, Dying raptures taste, and live. In thy lap, disdaining measure, Nature empties all her treasure, Soft desires, that sweetly languish, Fierce delights, that rise to anguish; Fairest, dost thou yet delay? Brightest beauty, come away. List not, when the froward chide, Sons of pedantry, and pride, Snarlers, to whose feeble sense April sunshine is offence; Age and envy will advise Ev'n against the joy they prize. Come, in pleasure's balmy bowl, Slake the thirstings of thy soul, 'Till thy raptur'd pow'rs are fainting With enjoyment, past the painting; Fairest, dost thou yet delay? Brightest beauty, come away. So sung the Sirens, as of yore, Upon the false Ausonian shore; And, O! for that preventing chain, That bound Ulysses on the main, That so our Fair One might withstand The covert ruin, now at hand. The song her charm'd attention drew, When now the tempters stood in view; Curiosity with prying eyes, And hands of busy, bold emprise; Like Hermes, feather'd were her feet, And, like fore-running fancy, fleet. By search untaught, by toil untir'd, To novelty she still aspir'd, Tasteless of every good possess'd, And but in expectation bless'd. With her, associate, Pleasure came, Gay Pleasure, frolic-loving dame, Her mein, all swimming in delight, Her beauties half reveal'd to sight; Loose flow'd her garments from the ground, And caught the kissing winds around. As erst Medusa's looks were known To turn beholders into stone, A dire reversion here they felt, And in the eye of Pleasure melt. Her glance with sweet persuasion charm'd, Unnerv'd the strong, the steel'd disarm'd; No safety ev'n the flying find, Who vent'rous, look but once behind. Thus was the much-admiring Maid, While distant, more than half betray'd: With smiles, and adulation bland, They join'd her side, and seiz'd her hand: Their touch envenom'd sweets instill'd, Her frame with new pulsations thrill'd, While half consenting, half denying, Reluctant now, and now complying, Amidst a war of hopes, and fears, Of trembling wishes, smiling tears, Still down, and down, the winning Pair Compell'd the struggling, yielding Fair. As when some stately vessel, bound To blest Arabia's distant ground, Borne from her courses, haply lights Where Barca's flow'ry clime invites, Conceal'd around whose treach'rous land; Lurk the dire rock, and dangerous sand; The pilot warns with sail and oar, To shun the much suspected shore, In vain; the tide, too subtly strong, Still bears the wrestling bark along, 'Till found'ring, she resigns to fate, And sinks o'erwhelm'd, with all her freight. So, baffling every bar to sin, And heav'n's own pilot, plac'd within, Along the devious, smooth descent, With pow'rs increasing as they went, The Dames, accustom'd to subdue, As with a rapid current drew, And o'er the fatal bounds convey'd The lost, the long-reluctant Maid. Here stop, ye fair ones, and beware, Nor send your fond affections there; Yet, yet your darling, now deplor'd, May turn, to you, and heav'n, restor'd; 'Till then, with weeping honour wait, The servant of her better fate, With honour, left upon the shore, Her friend, and handmaid now no more; Nor, with the guilty world, upbraid The fortunes of a wretch, betray'd, But o'er her failing cast the veil, Remembering, you yourselves are frail. And now, from all-enquiring light, Fast fled the conscious shades of night; The Damsel, from a short repose, Confounded at her plight, arose. As when, with slumb'rous weight oppress'd, Some wealthy miser sinks to rest, Where felons eye the glitt'ring prey, And steal his hoard of joys away; He, borne where golden Indus streams, Of pearl, and quarry'd di'mond dreams, Like Midas, turns the glebe to oar, And stands all wrapt amidst his store, But wakens, naked, and despoil'd Of that, for which his years had toil'd. So far'd the Nymph, her treasure flown, And turn'd, like Niobe, to stone, Within, without, obscure, and void, She felt all ravag'd, all destroy'd. And, O thou curs'd, insidious coast! Are these the blessings thou can'st boast? These, virtue! these the joys they find, Who leave thy heav'n-topt hills behind? Shade me, ye pines, ye caverns, hide, Ye mountains, cover me, she cry'd! Her trumpet slander rais'd on high, And told the tidings to the sky; Contempt discharg'd a living dart, A side-long viper to her heart; Reproach breath'd poisons o'er her face, And soil'd, and blasted every grace; Officious shame, her handmaid new, Still turn'd the mirror to her view, While those, in crimes the deepest dy'd, Approach'd, to whiten at her side, And every lewd, insulting dame Upon her folly rose to fame. What should she do? Attempt once more To gain the late-deserted shore? So trusting, back the Mourner flew, As fast the train of fiends pursue. Again the farther shore's attain'd, Again the land of virtue gain'd; But echo gathers in the wind, And shows her instant foes behind. Amaz'd, with headlong speed she tends, Where late she left a host of friends; Alas! those shrinking friends decline, Nor longer own that form divine; With fear they mark the following cry, And from the lonely Trembler fly, Or backward drive her on the coast, Where peace was wreck'd, and honour lost. From earth thus hoping aid in vain, To heav'n not daring to complain, No truce by hostile clamour giv'n, And from the face of friendship driv'n, The Nymph sunk prostrate on the ground, With all her weight of woes around. Enthron'd within a circling sky, Upon a mount o'er mountains high, All radiant sate, as in a shrine, Virtue, first effluence divine; Far, far above the scenes of woe, That shut this cloud-wrapt world below; Superior goddess, essence bright, Beauty of uncreated light, Whom should mortality survey, As doom'd upon a certain day, The breath of frailty must expire, The world dissolve in living fire, The gems of heav'n, and solar flame Be quench'd by her eternal beam, And nature, quick'ning in her eye, To rise a new-born phœnix, die. Hence, unreveal'd to mortal view, A veil around her form she threw, Which three sad sisters of the shade, Pain, care, and melancholy made. Through this her all-enquiring eye, Attentive from her station high, Beheld, abandon'd to despair, The ruins of her fav'rite Fair; And with a voice, whose awful sound Appal'd the guilty world around, Bid the tumultuous winds be still, To numbers bow'd each list'ning hill, Uncurl'd the surging of the main, And smooth'd the thorny bed of pain, The golden harp of heav'n she strung, And thus the tuneful goddess sung. Lovely Penitent, arise, Come, and claim thy kindred skies, Come, thy sister-angels say, Thou hast wept thy stains away. Let experience now decide, Twixt the good, and evil try'd, In the smooth, enchanted ground, Say, unfold the treasures found. Structures, rais'd by morning dreams, Sands, that trip the flitting streams, Down, that anchors on the air, Clouds, that paint their changes there. Seas, that smoothly dimpling lie, While the storm impends on high, Showing, in an obvious glass, Joys, that in possession pass; Transient, fickle, light, and gay, Flatt'ring, only to betray; What, alas, can life contain! Life, like all its circles, vain! Will the stork, intending rest, On the billow build her nest? Will the bee demand his store From the bleak, and bladeless shore? Man alone, intent to stray, Ever turns from wisdom's way, Lays up wealth in foreign land, Sows the sea, and plows the sand. Soon this elemental mass, Soon th' incumb'ring world shall pass, Form be wrapt in wasting fire, Time be spent, and life expire. Then, ye boasted works of men, Where is your asylum then? Sons of pleasure, sons of care, Tell'me, mortals, tell me where? Gone, like traces on the deep, Like a scepter, grasp'd in sleep, Dews, exhal'd from morning glades, Melting snows, and gliding shades. Pass the world, and what's behind? Virtue's gold, by fire refin'd; From an universe deprav'd, From the wreck of nature sav'd. Like the life-supporting grain, Fruit of patience, and of pain, On the swain's autumnal day, Winnow'd from the chaff away. Little trembler, fear no more, Thou hast plenteous crops in store, Seed, by genial sorrows sown, More than all thy scorners own. What though hostile earth despise, Heav'n beholds with gentler eyes; Heav'n thy friendless steps shall guide, Chear thy hours and guard thy side. When the fatal trump shall sound, When th' immortals pour around, Heav'n shall thy return attest, Hail'd by myriads of the bless'd. Little native of the skies, Lovely penitent, arise, Calm thy bosom, clear thy brow, Virtue is thy sister now. More delightful are my woes, Than the rapture, pleasure knows; Richer far the weeds I bring, Than the robes, that grace a king. On my wars, of shortest date, Crowns of endless triumphs wait; On my cares, a period bless'd; On my toils, eternal rest. Come, with virtue at thy side, Come, be every bar defy'd, 'Till we gain our native shore, Sister, come, and turn no more. FABLE XVI. LOVE, and VANITY. The breezy and morning breath'd perfume, The wak'ning flow'rs unveil'd their bloom, Up with the fun, from short repose, Gay health, and lusty labour rose, The milkmaid carol'd at her pail, And shepherds whistled o'er the dale; When Love, who led a rural life, Remote from bustle, state, and strife, Forth from his thatch'd-roof cottage stray'd, And stroll'd along the dewy glade. A Nymph, who lightly tript it by, To quick attention turn'd his eye; He mark'd the gesture of the Fair, Her self-sufficient grace, and air, Her steps, that mincing meant to please, Her study'd negligence, and ease; And, curious to enquire what meant This thing of prettiness, and paint, Approaching spoke, and bow'd observant; The Lady, slightly, Sir, your servant. Such beauty in so rude a place! Fair one, you do the country grace; At court, no doubt, the public care, But Love has small acquaintance there. Yes, Sir, reply'd the flutt'ring Dame, This form confesses whence it came; But dear variety, you know, Can make us pride, and pomp forego. My name is Vanity. I sway The utmost islands of the sea; Within my court all honour centers, I raise the meanest soul that enters, Endow with latent gifts, and graces, And model fools for posts and places. As Vanity appoints at pleasure, The world receives its weight, and measure; Hence all the grand concerns of life, Joys, cares, plagues, passions, peace and strife. Reflect how far my pow'r prevails, When I step in, where nature fails, And every breach of sense repairing, Am bounteous still, where heav'n is sparing. But chief in all their arts, and airs, Their playing, painting, pouts, and pray'rs, Their various habits, and complexions, Fits, frolics, foibles, and perfections, Their robing, curling, and adorning, From noon to night, from night to morning, From six to sixty, sick, or sound, I rule the female world around. Hold there a moment, Cupid cry'd, Nor boast dominion quite so wide; Was there no province to invade, But that by love, and meekness sway'd? All other empire I resign, But be the sphere of beauty mine. For in the downy lawn of rest, That opens on a woman's breast, Attended by my peaceful train, I chuse to live, and chuse to reign. Far-sighted faith I bring along, And truth, above an army strong, And chastity, of icy mould, Within the burning tropics cold, And lowliness, to whose mild brow, The pow'r and pride of nations bow, And modesty, with downcast eye, That lends the morn her virgin dye, And innocence, array'd in light, And honour, as a tow'r upright; With sweetly winning graces, more Than poets ever dreamt of yore, In unaffected conduct free, All smiling sisters, three times three, And rosy peace, the cherub bless'd, That nightly sings us all to rest. Hence, from the bud of nature's prime, From the first step of infant time, Woman, the world's appointed light, Has skirted every shade with white; Has stood for imitation high, To every heart, and every eye; From ancient deeds of fair renown, Has brought her bright memorials down; To time affix'd perpetual youth, And form'd each tale of love and truth. Upon a new Promethean plan, She moulds the essence of a man, Tempers his mass, his genius fires, And, as a better soul, inspires. The rude she softens, warms the cold, Exalts the meek, and checks the bold, Calls sloth from his supine repose, Within the coward's bosom glows, Of pride unplumes the lofty crest, Bids bashful merit stand confess'd, And like coarse metal from the mines, Collects, irradiates, and refines. The gentle science, she imparts, All manners smooths, informs all hearts; From her sweet influence are felt Passions that please, and thoughts that melt; To stormy rage she bids controul, And sinks serenely on the soul; Softens Deucalion's flinty race, And tunes the warring world to peace. Thus arm'd to all that's light, and vain, And freed from thy fantastic chain, She fills the sphere, by heav'n assign'd, And rul'd by me, o'er-rules mankind. He spoke. The Nymph impatient stood, And laughing, thus her speech renew'd. And pray, Sir, may I be so bold To hope your pretty tale is told? And next demand, without a cavil, What new Utopia do you travel? Upon my word, these high-flown fancies Shew depth of learning—in romances. Why, what unfashion'd stuff you tell us, Of buckram dames, and tiptoe fellows! Go, child; and when you're grown maturer, You'll shoot your next opinion surer. O such a pretty knack at painting! And all for soft'ning, and for sainting! Guess now, who can, a single feature, Through the whole piece of female nature! Then mark! my looser hand may fit The lines, too coarse for Love to hit. 'Tis said that woman, prone to changing, Through all the rounds of folly ranging, On life's uncertain ocean riding, No reason, rule, nor rudder guiding, Is like the comet's wand'ring light, Eccentric, ominous, and bright, Trackless, and shifting as the wind, A sea, whose fathom none can find, A moon, still changing, and revolving, A riddle, past all human solving, A bliss, a plague, a heav'n, a hell, A—something, which no man can tell. Now learn a secret from a friend, But keep your council, and attend. Though in their tempers thought so distant, Nor with their sex, nor selves consistent, 'Tis but the diff'rence of a name, And every woman is the same. For as the world, however vary'd, And through unnumber'd changes carry'd, Of elemental modes, and forms, Clouds, meteors, colours, calms, and storms, Though in a thousand suits array'd, Is of one subject matter made; So, Sir, a woman's constitution, The world's enigma, finds solution, And let her form be what you will, I am the subject essence still. With the first spark of female sense, The speck of being, I commence, Within the womb make fresh advances, And dictate future qualms, and fancies; Thence in the growing form expand, With childhood travel hand in hand, And give a taste to all their joys, In gewgaws, rattles, pomp, and noise. And now, familiar, and unaw'd, I send the flutt'ring soul abroad; Prais'd for her shape, her face, her mein, The little goddess, and the queen Takes at her infant shrine oblation, And drinks sweet draughts of adulation. Now blooming, tall, erect, and fair, To dress, becomes her darling care; The realms of beauty then I bound, I swell the hoop's enchanted round, Shrink in the waist's descending size, Heav'd in the snowy bosom, rise, High on the floating lappit sail, Or curl'd in tresses, kiss the gale. Then to her glass I lead the fair, And shew the lovely idol there, Where, struck as by divine emotion, She bows with most sincere devotion, And numb'ring every beauty o'er, In secret bids the world adore. Then all for parking, and parading, Coquetting, dancing, masquerading: For balls, plays, courts, and crowds what passion! And churches, sometimes—if the fashion; For woman's sense of right, and wrong, Is rul'd by the almighty throng; Still turns to each meander tame, And swims the straw of every stream. Her soul intrinsic worth rejects, Accomplish'd only in defects, Such excellence is her ambition, Folly, her wisest acquisition, And ev'n from pity, and disdain, She'll cull some reason to be vain. Thus, Sir, from every form and feature, The wealth, and wants of female nature, And ev'n from vice, which you'd admire, I gather fewel to my fire, And on the very base of shame Erect my monument of fame. Let me another truth attempt, Of which your godship has not dreamt. Those shining virtues, which you muster, Whence think you they derive their lustre? From native honour, and devotion? O yes, a mighty likely notion! Trust me, from titled dames to spinners, 'Tis I make saints, whoe'er makes sinners; 'Tis I instruct them to withdraw, And hold presumptuous man in awe; For female worth, as I inspire, In just degrees, still mounts the higher, And virtue, so extremely nice, Demands long toil, and mighty price; Like Sampson's pillars, fix'd elate, I bear the sex's tott'ring state; Sap these, and in a moment's space, Down sinks the fabric to its base. Alike from titles, and from toys, I spring, the fount of female joys; In every widow, wife, and miss, The sole artificer of bliss. For them each tropic I explore; I cleave the sand of every shore; To them uniting Indias fail, Sabæa breathes her farthest gale; For them the bullion I refine, Dig sense, and virtue from the mine, And from the bowels of invention, Spin out the various arts you mention. Nor bliss alone my pow'rs bestow, They hold the sov'reign balm of woe; Beyond the Stoic's boasted art, I sooth the heavings of the heart; To pain give splendor, and relief, And gild the pallid face of grief. Alike the palace, and the plain Admit the glories of my reign; Through every age, in every nation, Taste, talents, tempers, state, and station, Whate'er a woman says, I say; Whate'er a woman spends, I pay; Alike I fill, and empty bags, Flutter in finery, and rags, With light coquets through folly range, And with the prude disdain to change. And now you'd think, 'twixt you, and I, That things were ripe for a reply— But soft, and while I'm in the mood, Kindly permit me to conclude, Their utmost mazes to unravel, And touch the farthest step they travel. When every pleasure's run a-ground, And folly tir'd through many a round; The nymph, conceiving discontent hence, May ripen to an hour's repentance, And vapours, shed in pious moisture, Dismiss her to a church, or cloyster; Then on I lead her, with devotion Conspicuous in her dress, and motion, Inspire the heav'nly breathing air, Roll up the lucid eye in pray'r, Soften the voice, and in the face Look melting harmony, and grace. Thus far extends my friendly pow'r, Nor quits her in her latest hour; The couch of decent pain I spread, In form recline her languid head, Her thoughts I methodize in death, And part not, with her parting breath; Then do I set, in order bright, A length of funeral pomp to sight, The glitt'ring tapers, and attire, The plumes, that whiten o'er her bier; And last, presenting to her eye Angelic fineries on high, To scenes of painted bliss I waft her, And form the heav'n she hopes hereafter. In truth, rejoin'd love's gentle God, You've gone a tedious length of road, And strange, in all the toilsome way, No house of kind refreshment lay, No nymph, whose virtues might have tempted To hold her from her sex exempted. For one, we'll never quarrel, man; Take her, and keep her, if you can; And pleas'd I yield to your petition, Since, every fair, by such permission, Will hold herself the one selected, And so my system stands protected. O, deaf to virtue, deaf to glory, To truths divinely vouch'd in story! The Godhead in his zeal return'd, And kindling at her malice burn'd. Then sweetly rais'd his voice, and told Of heav'nly nymphs, rever'd of old; Hypsipile, who sav'd her sire; And Portia's love, approv'd by fire, Alike Penelope was quoted, Nor lawrel'd Daphne pass'd unnoted, Nor Laodamia's fatal garter, Nor fam'd Lucretia, honour's martyr, Alceste's voluntary steel, And Catherine, smiling on the wheel. But who can hope to plant conviction Where cavil grows on contradiction? Some she evades or disavows, Demurs to all, and none allows; A kind of ancient things, call'd fables! And thus the Goddess turn'd the tables. Now both in argument grew high, And choler flash'd from either eye; Nor wonder each refus'd to yield The conquest of so fair a field. When happily arriv'd in view A Goddess, whom our grandames knew, Of aspect grave, and sober gaite, Majestic, aweful, and sedate, As heav'n's autumnal eve serene, When not a cloud o'ercasts the scene; Once Prudence call'd, a matron fam'd, And in old Rome, Cornelia nam'd. Quick at a venture, both agree To leave their strife to her decree. And now by each the facts were stated, In form and manner as related; The case was short. They crav'd opinion, Which held o'er females chief dominion? When thus the Goddess, answering mild, First shook her gracious head, and smil'd. Alas, how willing to comply, Yet how unfit a judge am I! In times of golden date, 'tis true, I shar'd the fickle sex with you, But from their presence long precluded, Or held as one, whose form intruded, Full fifty annual suns can tell, Prudence has bid the sex farewell. In this dilemma what to do, Or who to think of, neither knew; For both, still biass'd in opinion, And arrogant of sole dominion, Were forc'd to hold the case compounded, Or leave the quarrel where they found it. When in the nick, a rural fair, Of inexperienc'd gaite, and air, Who ne'er had cross'd the neighb'ring lake, Nor seen the world, beyond a wake, With cambrick coif, and kerchief clean, Tript lightly by them o'er the green. Now, now! cry'd Love's triumphant Child, And at approaching conquest smil'd, If Vanity will once be guided, Our diff'rence may be soon decided; Behold you wench; a fit occasion To try your force of gay persuasion. Go you, while I retire aloof, Go, put those boasted pow'rs to proof; And if your prevalence of art Transcends my yet unerring dart, I give the fav'rite contest o'er, And ne'er will boast my empire more. At once, so said, and so consented; And well our Goddess seem'd contented; Nor pausing, made a moment's stand, But tript, and took the girl in hand. Mean while the Godhead, unalarm'd, As one to each occasion arm'd, Forth from his quiver cull'd a dart, That erst had wounded many a heart; Then, bending, drew it to the head; The bow-string twang'd, the arrow fled, And, to her secret soul address'd, Transfix'd the whiteness of her breast. But here the Dame, whose guardian care Had to a moment watch'd the fair, At once her pocket mirror drew, And held the wonder full in view; As quickly, rang'd in order bright, A thousand beauties rush to sight; A world of charms, till now unknown, A world, reveal'd to her alone: Enraptur'd stands the love-sick maid, Suspended o'er the darling shade, Here only fixes to admire, And centers every fond desire.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">A HYMN to POVERTY. O Poverty! thou source of human art, Thou great inspirer of the poet's song! In vain Apollo dictates, and the Nine Attend in vain, unless thy mighty hand Direct the tuneful lyre. Without thy aid The canvas breaths no longer. Music's charms, Uninfluenc'd by thee, forget to please: Thou giv'st the organ sound; by thee the flute Breaths harmony; the tuneful viol owns Thy pow'rful touch. The warbling voice is thine; Thou gav'st to Nicolini every grace, And every charm to Farinelli's song. By thee the lawyer pleads. The soldier's arm Is nerv'd by thee. Thy pow'r the gown-man feels, And, urg'd by thee, unfolds heav'n's mystic truths. The haughty fair, that swells with proud disdain, And smiles at mischiefs, which her eyes have made, Thou humblest to submit and bless mankind. Hail, Pow'r omnipotent! Me uninvok'd Thou deign'st to visit, far, alas! unfit To bear thy awful presence. O, retire! At distance let me view thee; left too nigh, I sink beneath the terrors of thy face! THE LOVER and the FRIEND. O thou, for whom my lyre I string, Of whom I speak, and think, and sing! Thou constant object of my joys, Whose sweetness every wish employs! Thou dearest of thy sex, attend, And hear the Lover and the Friend! Fear not the poet's flatt'ring strain; No idle praise my verse shall stain; The lowly numbers shall impart The faithful dictates of my heart, Nor humble modesty offend, And part the Lover from the Friend. Not distant is the cruel day, That tears me from my hopes away; Then frown not, fairest, if I try To steal the moisture from your eye, Or force your heart a sigh to send, To mourn the Lover and the Friend. No perfect joy my life e'er knew, But what arose from love and you; Nor can I fear another pain Than your unkindness, or disdain: Then let your looks their pity lend, To chear the Lover and the Friend. Whole years I strove against the flame, And suffer'd ills, that want a name; Yet still the painful secret kept, And to myself in silence wept; Till grown unable to contend, I own'd the Lover and the Friend. I saw you still. Your gen'rous heart In all my sorrows bore a part; Yet while your eyes with pity glow'd, No words of hope your tongue bestow'd, But mildly bid me cease to blend The name of Lover with the Friend. Sick with desire, and mad with pain, I seek for happiness in vain: Thou lovely maid, to thee I cry, Heal me with kindness, or I die! From sad despair my soul defend, And fix the Lover and the Friend. Curs'd be all wealth, that can destroy My utmost hope of earthly joy! Thy gifts, O Fortune! I resign, Let her and poverty be mine! And every year that life shall lend, Shall bless the Lover and the Friend. In vain, alas! in vain I strive To keep a dying hope alive; The last sad remedy remains, 'Tis absence that must heal my pains, Thy image from my bosom rend, And force the Lover from the Friend. Vain thought! though seas between us roll, Thy love is rooted in my soul; The vital blood that warms my heart With thy idea must depart, And death's decisive stroke must end At once the Lover and the Friend.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SONGS. SONG the First. I Thus I said to my heart, in a pet t'other day, I had rather be hang'd than go moping this way; No throbbings, no wishes your moments employ, But you sleep in my breast without motion or joy. II When Cloe perlex'd me 'twas sweeter by half, And at Thais's wiles I could often-times laugh; Your burnings and akings I strove not to cure, Though one was a jilt, and the other a whore. III When I walk'd up the Mall, or stroll'd through the street, Not a petticoat brush'd me, but then you could beat, Or if bang went the hoop against corner or post, In the magical round you were sure to be lost. IV But now if a nymph goes as naked as Eve, Like Adam, unfallen, you never perceive; Or the seat of delight if the tippet should hide, You tempt not my fingers to draw it aside. V Is it caution, or dread, or the frost of old age, That inclines you with beauty no more to engage? Tell me quickly the cause, for it makes me quite mad, In the summer's gay season to see you so sad. VI Have a care, quoth my heart, how you tempt me to stray; He that hunts down a woman, must run a d?d way: Like a hare she can wind, or hold out with the fox, And, secure in the cháce, her pursuers she mocks. VII For Cloe I burnt with an innocent flame, And beat to the music that breath'd out her name; Three summers flew over the castles I built, And beheld me a fool, and my goddess a jilt. VIII Next Thais, the wanton, my wishes employ'd, And the kind one repair'd what the cruel destroy'd: Like Shadrach, I liv'd in a furnace of fire, But, unlike him, was scorch'd, and compell'd to retire. IX Recruited once more, I forgot all my pain, And was jilted, and burnt, and bedevil'd again; Not a petticoat fring'd, or the heel of a shoe, Ever pass'd you by day-light, but at it I flew. X Thus jilted, and wounded, and burnt to a coal, For rest I retreated again to be whole; But your eyes, ever open to lead me astray, Have beheld a new face, and command me away. XI But remember, in whatever flames I may burn, 'Twill be folly to ask for, or wish my return: Neither Thais, nor Cloe, again shall enflame, But a nymph more provoking than all you can name. XII This said, with a bound from my bosom he flew; O, Phillis! these eyes saw him posting to you: Enslav'd by your wit, he grows fond of his chain, And vows I shall never possess him again. SONG the Second. Collin. Be still, O ye winds, and attentive, ye swains, 'Tis Phebe invites, and replies to my strains; The sun never rose on, search all the world through, A shepherd so blest, or a fair one so true. Phebe. Glide softly, ye streams, O ye nymphs, round me throng, 'Tis Collin commands, and attends to my song; Search all the world over, you never can find A maiden so blest, or a shepherd so kind. Both. 'Tis love, like the sun, that gives light to the year, The sweetest of blessings that life can endear; Our pleasures it brightens, drives sorrow away, Gives joy to the night, and enlivens the day. Collin. With Phebe beside me, the seasons how gay! Then Winter's bleak months seem as pleasant as May; The Summer's gay verdure springs still as she treads, And linnet's and nightingales sing through the meads. Phebe When Collin is absent 'tis Winter all round, How faint is the sunshine, how barren the ground! Instead of the linnet and nightingale's song, I hear the hoarse raven croak all the day long. Both. 'Tis love, like the sun, &amp;c. Collin. O'er hill, dale and valley my Phebe and I Together will wander, and love shall be by: Her Collin shall guard her safe all the long day, And Phebe at night all his pains shall repay. Phebe. By moonlight, when shadows glide over the plain, His kisses shall chear me, his arm shall sustain; The dark haunted grove I can trace without fear, Or sleep in a church-yard, if Collin is near. Both. 'Tis love, like the sun, &amp;c. Collin. Ye shepherds that wanton it over the plain, How fleeting your transports, how lasting your pain! Inconstancy shun, and reward the kind she, And learn to be happy of Phebe and me. Phebe. Ye nymphs, who the pleasures of love never try'd, Attend to my strains, and take me for your guide; Your hearts keep from pride and inconstancy free, And learn to be happy of Collin and me. Both. 'Tis love, like the sun, that gives light to the year, The sweetest of blessings that life can endear; Our pleasures it brightens, drives sorrow away, Gives joy to the night, and enlivens the day. SONG the Third. I As Phillis the gay, at the break of the day, Went forth to the meadows a maying, A clown lay asleep by a river so deep, That round in meanders was straying. II His bosom was bare, and for whiteness so rare, Her heart it was gone without warning, With cheeks of such hue, that the rose wet with dew, Ne'er look'd half so fresh in a morning. III She cull'd the new hay, and down by him she lay, Her wishes too warm for disguising; She play'd with his eyes, till he wak'd in surprize, And blush'd like the sun at his rising. IV She sung him a song, as he leant on his prong, And rested her arm on his shoulder; She press'd his coy cheek to her bosom so sleek, And taught his two arms to infold her. V The rustic grown kind, by a kiss told his mind, And call'd her his dear and his blessing: Together they stray'd, and sung, frolick'd and play'd, And what they did more there's no guessing. SONG the Fourth. He. Let rakes for pleasure range the town, Or misers doat on golden guineas, Let plenty smile, or fortune frown, The sweets of love are mine and Jenny's. She. Let wanton maids indulge desire, How soon the fleeting pleasure gone is! The joys of virtue never tire, And such shall still be mine and Johnny's. Both. Together let us sport and play, And live in pleasure where no sin is; The priest shall tie the knot to-day And wedlock's bands make Johnny Jenny's. He. Let roving swains young hearts invade, The pleasure ends in shame and folly; So Willy woo'd, and then betray'd The poor, believing, simple Molly. She. So Lucy lov'd, and lightly toy'd, And laugh'd at harmless maids who marry; But now she finds her shepherd cloy'd, And chides too late her faithless Harry. Both. But we'll together, &amp;c. He. By cooling streams our flocks we'll feed, And leave deceit to knaves and ninnies; Or fondly stray where love shall lead, And every joy be mine and Jenny's. She. Let guilt the faithless bosom fright, The constant heart is always bonny; Content, and peace, and sweet delight, And love shall live with me and Johnny. Both. Together still we'll sport and play, And live in pleasure where no sin is; The priest shall tie the knot to-day, And wedlock's bands make Johnny Jenny's. SONG the Fifth. I Stand round, my brave boys, with heart and with voice, And all in full chorus agree; We'll fight for our king, and as loyally sing, And let the world know we'll be free. Chorus. The rebels shall fly, as with shouts we draw nigh, And echo shall victory ring; Then safe from alarms, we'll rest on our arms, And chorus it, long live the king! II Then commerce once more shall bring wealth to our shore, And plenty and peace bless the isle; The peasant shall quaff off his bowl with a laugh, And reap the sweet fruits of his toil. Chorus. The rebels, &amp;c. III Kind love shall repay the fatigues of the day, And melt us to softer alarms; Coy Phillis shall burn at her soldier's return, And bless the brave youth in her arms. Chorus. The rebels shall fly, as with shouts we draw nigh, And echo shall victory ring; Then safe from alarms, we'll rest on our arms, And chorus it, long live the king! SONG the Sixth. I To make the wife kind, and to keep the house still, You must be of her mind, let her say what she will; In all that she does you must give her her way, For tell her she's wrong, and you lead her astray. Chorus. Then, husbands, take care, of suspicion beware, Your wives may be true, if you fancy they are; With confidence trust them, and be not such elves, As to make by your jealousy horns for yourselves. II Abroad all the day if she chuses to roam, Seem pleas'd with her absence, she'll sigh to come home; The man she likes best, and longs most to get at, Be sure to commend, and she'll hate him for that. Chorus. Then, husbands, &amp;c. III What virtues she has, you may safely oppose, Whatever her follies are, praise her for those; Applaud all her schemes that she lays for a man, For accuse her of vice, and she'll sin if she can. Chorus. Then, husbands, take care, of suspicion beware, Your wives may be true, if you fancy they are; With confidence trust them, and be not such elves, As to make by your jealousy horns for yourselves. SONG the Seventh. Damon. Hark, hark, o'er the plains how the merry bells ring, Asleep while my charmer is laid! The village is up, and the day on the wing, And Phillis may yet die a maid. Phillis. 'Tis hardly yet day, and I cannot away, O, Damon, I'm young and afraid; To-morrow, my dear, I'll to church without fear, But let me to-night lie a maid. Damon. The bride-maids are met, and mamma's on the fret, All, all my coy Phillis upbraid; Come open the door, and deny me no more, Nor cry to live longer a maid. Phillis. Dear shepherd, forbear, and to-morrow I swear, To-morrow I'll be not be afraid; I'll open the door, and deny you no more, Nor cry to live longer a maid. Damon. No, no, Phillis, no, on that bosom of snow To-night shall your shepherd be laid; By morning my dear shall be eas'd of her fear, Nor grieve she's no longer a maid. Phillis. Then open the door, 'twas unbolted before, His bliss silly Damon delay'd; To church let us go, and if there I say no, O then let me die an old maid. SONG the Eighth. I That Jenny's my friend, my delight, and my pride, I always have boasted, and seek not to hide; I dwell on her praises wherever I go, They say I'm in love, but I answer no, no. II At ev'ning oft-times with what pleasure I see A note from her hand, "I'll be with you at tea!" My heart how it bounds, when I hear her below! But say not 'tis love, for I answer no, no. III She sings me a song, and I echo each strain, Again I cry, Jenny! sweet Jenny, again! I kiss her soft lips, as if there I could grow, And fear I'm in love, though I answer no, no. IV She tells me her faults, as she sits on my knee, I chide her, and swear she's an angel to me: My shoulder she taps, and still bids me think so; Who knows but she loves, though she tells me no, no? V Yet such is my temper, so dull am I grown, I ask not Her heart, but would conquer my own: Her bosom's soft peace shall I seek to o'erthrow, And wish to persuade, while I answer no, no? VI From beauty, and wit, and good-humour, ah! why Should prudence advise, and compel me to fly? Thy bounties, O Fortune! make haste to bestow, And let me deserve her, or still I say no. SONG the Ninth. I You tell me I'm handsome, I know not how true, And easy, and chatty, and good-humour'd too; That my lips are as red as the rose-bud in June, And my voice, like the nightingale's, sweetly in tune: All this has been told me by twenty before, But he that would win me, must flatter me more. II If beauty from virtue receive no supply, Or prattle from prudence, how wanting am I! My ease and good-humour short raptures will bring, And my voice,like the nightingale's, know but a spring. For charms such as these then, your praises give o'er, To love me for life, you must love me for more. III Then talk to me not of a shape or an air, For Cloe, the wanton, can rival me there: 'Tis virtue alone that makes beauty look gay, And brightens good-humour, as sunshine the day; For that if you love me, your flame shall be true, And I in my turn, may be taught to love too. SONG the Tenth. I How blest has my time been, what days have I known, Since wedlock's soft bondage made Jesse my own! So joyful my heart is, so easy my chain, That freedom is tasteless, and roving a pain. II Through walks, grown with woodbines, as often we stray, Around us our boys and girls frolic and play; How pleasing their sport is the wanton ones see, And borrow their looks from my Jesse and me. III To try her sweet temper sometimes am I seen In revels all day with the nymphs of the green; Though painful my absence, my doubts she beguiles, And meets me at night with compliance and smiles. IV What though on her cheek the rose loses its hue, Her ease and good-humour bloom all the year through; Time still as he flies brings increase to her truth, And gives to her mind what he steals from her youth. V Ye shepherds so gay, who make love to ensnare, And cheat with false vows the too credulous fair, In search of true pleasure how vainly you roam! To hold it for life, you must find it at home. SONG the Eleventh. I Hark! hark! 'tis a voice from the tomb! Come, Lucy, it cries, come away; The grave of thy Collin has room, To rest thee beside his cold clay. I come, my dear shepherd, I come; Ye friends and companions, adieu; I haste to my Collin's dark home, To die on his bosom so true. II All mournful the midnight bell rung, When Lucy, sad Lucy arose; And forth to the green-turf she sprung, Where Collin's pale ashes repose. All wet with the night's chilling dew, Her bosom embrac'd the cold ground, While stormy winds over her blew, And night-ravens croak'd all around. III How long, my lov'd Collin, she cry'd, How long must thy Lucy complain? How long shall the grave my love hide? How long ere it join us again? For thee thy fond shepherdess liv'd, With thee o'er the world would she fly, For thee has she sorrow'd and griev'd, For thee would she lie down and die. IV Alas! what avails it how dear Thy Lucy was once to her swain! Her face like the lily so fair, And eyes that gave light to the plain! The shepherd that lov'd her is gone, That face and those eyes charm no more, And Lucy forgot and alone, To death shall her Collin deplore. V While thus she lay sunk in despair, And mourn'd to the echoes around, Inflam'd all at once grew the air, And thunder shook dreadful the ground. I hear the kind call, and obey, Oh, Collin, receive me, she cry'd! Then breathing a groan o'er his clay, She hung on his tomb-stone and dy'd.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE NUN: A CANTATA. RECITATIVE. Of Constance holy legends tell, The softest sister of the cell; None sent to heav'n so sweet a cry, Or roll'd at mass so bright an eye. No wanton taint her bosom knew, Her hours in heav'nly vision flew, Her knees were worn with midnight pray'rs, And thus she breath'd divinest airs. AIR. In hallow'd walks, and awful cells, Secluded from the light and vain, The chaste-ey'd maid with virtue dwells, And solitude, and silence reign. The wanton's voice is heard not here, To heav'n the sacred pile belongs; Each wall returns the whisper'd pray'r, And echoes but to holy songs. RECITATIVE. Alas, that pamper'd monks should dare Intrude where sainted vestals are! Ah, Francis! Francis! well I weet Those holy looks are all deceit. With shame the muse prolongs her tale, The Priest was young, the Nun was frail, Devotion faulter'd on her tongue, Love tun'd her voice, and thus she sung. AIR. Alas, how deluded was I, To fancy delights as I did! With maidens at midnight to sigh, And love, the sweet passion, forbid! O, father! my follies forgive, And still to absolve me be nigh; Your lessons have taught me to live, Come teach me, O! teach me to die! To her arms in a rapture he sprung, Her bosom, half-naked, met his; Transported in silence she hung, And melted away at each kiss. Ah, father! expiring she cry'd, With rapture I yield up my breath! Ah, daughter! he fondly reply'd, The righteous find comfort in death. SOLOMON, A SERENATA: Set to Music By Dr. BOYCE. PART I. CHORUS. Behold, Jerusalem, thy king, Whose praises all the nations sing! To Solomon the Lord has giv'n All arts and wisdom under heav'n: For him the tuneful virgin throng Of Zion's daughters, swell the song: While young and old their voices raise, And wake the echoes with his praise. RECITATIVE. She. From the mountains, lo! he comes, Breathing from his lips perfumes; While zephyrs on his garments play, And sweets through all the air convey. AIR. Tell me, lovely shepherd, where Thou feed'st at noon thy fleecy care? Direct me to the sweet retreat, That guards thee from the mid-day heat: Lest by the flocks I lonely stray, Without a guide, and lose my way: Where rest at noon, thy bleating care, Gentle shepherd, tell me where? AIR. He. Fairest of the virgin throng, Dost thou seek thy swain's abode? See yon fertile vale along The new-worn path the flocks have trod: Pursue the prints their feet have made, And they shall guide thee to the shade. RECITATIVE. She. As the rich apple, on whose boughs Ripe fruit with streaky beauty glows, Excels the trees that shade the grove, So shines, among his sex, my love. AIR. Beneath his ample shade I lay, Defended from the sultry day; His cooling fruit my thirst assuag'd, And quench'd the fires that in me rag'd; 'Till sated with the luscious taste, I rose and blest the sweet repast. RECITATIVE. He. Who quits the lily's fleecy white, To fix on meaner flow'rs the sight? Or leaves the rose's stem untorn, To crop the blossom from the thorn? Unrival'd thus thy beauties are; So shines my love among the fair. AIR. Balmy sweetness, ever flowing, From her dropping lips distils; Flowers on her cheeks are blowing, And her voice with music thrills. Zephyrs o'er the spices flying, Wasting sweets from every tree, Sick'ning sense with odours cloying, Breathe not half so sweet as she.RECITATIVE. She. Let not my prince his slave despise, Or pass me with unheeding eyes, Because the sun's discolouring rays Have chac'd the lily from my face. My envious sisters saw my bloom, And drove me from my mother's home; Unshelter'd all the scorching day They made me in their vineyard stay. AIR. Ah simple me! my own, more dear, My own, alas! was not my care: Invading love the fences broke, And tore the clusters from the stock, With eager grasp the fruit destroy'd, Nor rested, till the ravage cloy'd. AIR. He. Fair and comely is my love, And softer than the blue-ey'd dove; Down her neck the wanton locks Bound like the kids on Gilead's rocks; Her teeth like flocks in beauty seem, New shorn, and dropping from the stream; Her glowing lips by far out-vie The plaited threads of scarlet dye; Whene'er she speaks the accents wound, And music floats upon the sound.RECITATIVE. She. Forbear, O charming swain, forbear! Thy voice enchants my list'ning ear; And while I gaze, my bosom glows, My flutt'ring heart with love o'erflows, The shades of night hang o'er my eyes, And every sense within me dies. AIR. O fill with cooling juice the bowl! Assuage the fever in my soul! With copious draughts my thirst remove, And sooth the heart that's sick of love. PART II.RECITATIVE. He. The chearful spring begins to-day; Arise, my fair one, come away!RECITATIVE. She. Sweet music steals along the air— Hark!—my beloved's voice I hear!AIR. He. Arise, my fair, and come away, The chearful spring begins to-day: Bleak winter's gone with all his train Of chilling frosts, and dropping rain. Amidst the verdure of the mead The primrose lifts her velvet head: The warbling birds, the woods among, Salute the season with a song: The cooing turtle in the grove Renews his tender tale of love: The vines their infant tendrils shoot: The fig-tree bends with early fruit: All welcome in the genial ray: Arise, my fair, and come away! CHORUS. All welcome in the genial ray, Arise, O fair one! come away! DUET. Together let us range the fields, Impearled with the morning dew; Or view the fruits the vineyard yields, Or the apple's clust'ring bough: There in close-embower'd shades, Impervious to the noon-tide ray, By tinkling rills, on rosy beds, We'll love the sultry hours away.RECITATIVE. He. How lovely art thou to the sight, For pleasure form'd, and sweet delight! Tall as the palm-tree is thy shape, Thy breasts are like the clust'ring grape. AIR. Let me, love, thy bole ascending, On the swelling clusters feed: With my grasp the vine-tree bending, In my close embrace shall bleed. Stay me with delicious kisses, From thy honey-dropping mouth; Sweeter than the summer breezes, Blowing from the genial south.RECITATIVE. She. O that a sister's specious name Conceal'd from prying eyes my flame! Uncensur'd then I'd own my love, And chastest virgins should approve: Then fearless to my mother's bed My seeming brother would I lead: Soft transports should the hours employ, And the deceit should crown the joy. AIR. Soft! I adjure you, by the fawns, That bound across the flow'ry lawns, Ye virgins, that ye lightly move, Nor with your whispers wake my love! RECITATIVE. He. My fair's a garden of delight, Enclos'd, and hid from vulgar sight; Where streams from bubbling fountains stray, And roses deck the verdant way. AIR. Softly arise, O southern breeze! And kindly fan the blooming trees; Upon my spicy garden blow, That sweets from every part may flow. CHORUS. Ye southern breezes gently blow, That sweets from every part may flow. PART III.AIR. He. Arise, my fair, the doors unfold, Receive me, shivering with the cold.RECITATIVE. She. My heart amidst my slumbers wakes, And tells me my beloved speaks.AIR. He. Arise, my fair, the doors unfold, Receive me, shivering with the cold: The chill-drops hang upon my head, And night's cold dews my cheeks o'erspread: Receive me, dropping, to thy breast, And lull me in thy arms to rest.RECITATIVE. She. Obedient to thy voice I hie; The willing doors wide open fly. AIR. Ah! whither, whither art thou gone? Where is my lovely wand'rer flown? Ye blooming virgins, as you rove, If chance you meet my straying love, I charge you tell him how I mourn, And pant, and die for his return. CHORUS of Virgins. Who is thy love, O charming maid! That from thy arms so late has stray'd? Say what distinguish'd charms adorn, And finish out his radiant form?AIR. She. On his face the vernal rose, Blended with the lily glows; His locks are as the raven black, In ringlets waving down his back; His eyes with milder beauties beam, Than billing doves beside the stream; His youthful cheeks are beds of flow'rs, Enripen'd by refreshing show'rs; His lips are of the rose's hue, Dropping with a fragrant dew; Tall as the cedar he appears, And as erect his form he bears. This, O ye virgins, is the swain, Whose absence causes all my pain.RECITATIVE. He. Sweet nymph, whom ruddier charms adorn, Than open with the rosy morn; Fair as the moon's unclouded light, And as the sun in splendor bright; Thy beauties dazzle from a-far, Like glitt'ring arms that gild the war.RECITATIVE. Speaker. O take me! stamp me on thy breast! Deep let the image be imprest! For love, like armed death, is strong, Rudely he drags his slaves along: If once to jealousy he turns, With never-dying rage he burns. DUET. Thou soft invader of the soul! O love, who shall thy pow'r controul! To quench thy fires whole rivers drain, Thy burning heat shall still remain. In vain we trace the globe to try, If pow'rful gold thy joys can buy: The treasures of the world will prove Too poor a bribe to purchase love. CHORUS. The vain we trace the globe to try, If pow'rful gold thy joys can buy: The treasures of the world will prove Too poor a bribe to purchase love.</field>
   </doc>
</add>