<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Blacklock, Thomas, 1721-1791</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Blacklock, Thomas, 1721-1791</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">blacklock thomas 1721 1791</field>
      <field name="author_text">Blacklock, Thomas, 1721-1791</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1770's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_2.1178.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1774</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:465348</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Graham ; an heroic ballad. In four cantos. By Thomas Blacklock</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Graham ; an heroic ballad. In four cantos. By Thomas Blacklock</field>
      <field name="title_facet">graham</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">graham</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Graham ; an heroic ballad. In four cantos. By Thomas Blacklock</field>
      <field name="year_display">1774</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1774</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1774</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465348&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465348&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Blacklock, Thomas, 1721-1791&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;blacklock thomas 1721 1791&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Graham ; an heroic ballad. In four cantos. By Thomas Blacklock&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;graham&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1774&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1774&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Blacklock, Thomas&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1721&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1791&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Graham&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;an heroic ballad. In four cantos. By Thomas Blacklock&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for T. Davies [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1774&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0440&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;vi, 54 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Graham&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;an heroic ballad. In four cantos. By Thomas Blacklock&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 51 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">? Vestra capit discordia finem:— Tros Rutulusve fuat, nullo discrimine habebo. Virg.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE GRAHAM. AN HEROIC BALLAD. CANTO I. I In former days, when Scotia hurl'd Against her sister realm the spear, When on her frontiers war unfurl'd His bloody flag from year to year; When wonder fill'd th'attentive world Her glorious conflicts charm'd to hear, By native virtue sav'd from thrall Whilst wealth and power conspir'd her fall: II Of noble soul and lineage high, Amongst her chiefs was Graham rever'd: But wan his cheek, and dim his eye; Keen smart he prov'd, yet keener fear'd: No Howard echoed sigh for sigh, No plighted maid his bosom cheer'd; His love, his confidence abus'd He deem'd, and thus his soul effus'd. III “Rise winds of heaven, to tempest rise; Flames flash, and cataracts descend!— No storms convulsing earth and skies, Like those which now my bosom rend: Should chaos order's reign surprize, And heaven, and earth, and ocean blend, No anarchy could vex the void, Like sacred peace of mind destroy'd. IV Sweet peace of mind! seraphic guest! How long thy absence shall I mourn? From yon bright mansions of the blest With all thy placid train return: For hell is center'd in my breast, There still its hottest fervours burn. No more, ye tortur'd ghosts, repine, Since less acute your pains than mine. V Of all the ills that rage so rise, (And ha! from ills what state is free?) Of all the plagues that prey on life, God's heaviest curse is jealousy; Of love and hate eternal strife: When shall it cease to torture me? Oh! when shall streams of blood atone For Scotia's wrongs, and for my own? VI Just God! that he, to whom my heart, Accessible as light and air, Was fond its wishes to impart, With whom its inmost thoughts to share, These confines falsely should desert, Tho' prescient of his friend's despair; Unseen desert, and basely steal What, lost, to madness I must feel!” VII Thus Graham; inexorably bent His rival or himself to slay, Then shap'd his course with fell intent To where Northumbria's warriours lay; Nor night his journey could prevent, Nor danger intercept his way; He reck'd not how he sped, nor where: They dread no ruin who despair. VIII Singly (for such was his command) He meant to meet his gallant foe; But chosen men, a worthy band, Who vow'd to share his weal or woe, When he his hardy purpose plann'd Th'important secret chanc'd to know; Remotely these his steps pursue, Unseen, yet keep him still in view. IX Determin'd on revenge or death And guided by a dubious ray, Through many a rough and winding path Th'intreprid hero held his way; Upbraiding much his easy faith, Which arts so flimsey could betray; At length he reach'd the wide campaign Where fix'd Northumbria's tents remain. X And now the genial hours prepare To yoke Aurora's rosy teem; Her blushes ting'd through humid air The rising hill and crystal stream; While with encreasing light more fair, More sweet the opening prospects seem: But souls involv'd in sorrows gloom No landscapes charm, no rays illume. XI When now the hostile camp he spy'd In silence solemn and profound; “Here, here the miscreant rests (he cry'd), Who gave my peace its mortal wound: A while the wretch, who heav'n defy'd, May with success in guilt be crown'd; Yet crimes like these, tho' long secure, At last for vengeance prove mature.” XII No emblematic signs pourtray'd Within its orb his buckler bore; Nor then the variegated plaid Around his manly chest he wore; His name, his form, no mark betray'd, Which jealous caution might explore: Thus thro' the strong and watchful guard He pass'd unquestion'd, undebarr'd. XIII “By all the glories of my race 'Tis Graham himself! (young Howard said); He comes to brave me face to face, He comes to claim the rescu'd maid: So may my soul in heaven find grace When most she needs her powerful aid, As I his challenge shall receive, Since one or both must feast the grave. XIV And thou by early fate remov'd From all that renders being dear, Oh still remember'd, still belov'd, My vow, fraternal spirit, hear! That vengeance, which so tardy prov'd, Scotia at last shall learn to fear, Shall expiate from unnumber'd veins A brother's blood, a captive's chains.” XV He snatch'd his sword, he pois'd his shield, He issu'd to confront the foe, As bickering flames involve a field Where arid heath and stubble grow: His breast, with native courage steel'd, On fear could ne'er one thought bestow: Yet ere his steps could far proceed, The Scot advanc'd and check'd his speed. XVI “Blush, traitor, blush (enrag'd he said), If still susceptible of shame, If benefits with wrongs repaid From heav'n and earth just vengeance claim: But fools and cowards may upbraid, In speeches fierce, in action tame; The righteous pow'r that rules on high, And arms alone our cause can try.” XVII He ceas'd; and Howard thus reply'd: “Impetuous Boy, thy rage restrain! Ere now thy force I had defy'd, But other tasks my arm detain: For know, to mortify thy pride, Thou ow'st thy life to my disdain; Thy country first I meant to quell, Then destin'd thee for death and hell. XVIII How well it suits the heart of Graham To doubt his friend, tho' known sincere! That heart, which base designs inflame, Such base designs may justly fear: From all the various mouths of fame Thy vile suspicions reach my ear. Now if unscourg'd thy crime remains, No more eternal justice reigns. XIX Traitor my soul retorts with scorn On thy opprobious clans and thee. The nymph thou seek'st I found forlon; From base attempts I set her free; When hence by brutal ruffians borne, For aid she call'd on heav'n and me. Where then was that vindictive arm Portending now such mortal harm? XX In vain that rage which bends thy brow, Thy boasts, thy menaces are vain: By heav'n's omnipotence I vow, Nor perjury my soul shall stain; Not all thy country's force, nor thou, The beauteous capture shall regain: Mine now she is, and mine shall be, Indignant Scot, in spite of thee. XXI But whilst in heav'n's unerring scale Our quiv'ring destinies appear, And which shall fall, and which prevail, By no decision yet seems clear; I could unfold a wond'rous tale, Whose lightest word demands thy ear:— But haste we hence where friends nor foes Can in our quarrel interpose.” XXII “Damn'd subterfuge to make me swerve! (Thus Graham resum'd with fervid ire;) These arts for weaker dupes reserve; They raise my indignation higher: When wretches, who in dungeons starve, Nor light, nor air, nor food desire, Then may my heart its wrath suspend 'Till thy insidious tale shall end.” XXIII “Me brand'st thou with evasive fright, (Cry'd Howard with protended steel;) Who for thy fury or thy might Supreme contempt alone can feel! Which heart shall now decline the fight, Which beat with fears it would conceal, Th'impending instant shall display; Hark! hov'ring ravens croak for prey.” XXIV Now front to front the champions stood, And hew'd and lash'd, and thunder'd blows; Whilst thro' th'adjacent hills and wood, The propagated clangor rose; Anna, with eyes in tears bedew'd, Had heard them talk, and seen them close; With pallid cheek, and trembling frame, Between the combatants she came. XXV “For heav'n's sweet sake, ere you engage, Attend to love's, to friendship's call! If blood alone can quench your rage, Mine, mine I offer; take it all. Could I have form'd the sad presage, That one of two so dear should fall, Ere I this cursed hour survey'd, To fate that tribute I had paid. XXVI Oh Graham! in whom for ever dwells Concenter'd all my soul's delight, What frenzy now thy mind impels To urge this inauspicious fight? That fury, which thy bosom swells, May in his blood its conquest write; But say, is this his noblest meed Who rescued me, by Graham to bleed? XXVII While full of thee I lonely stray'd, With tears and anxious vigils spent, To breathe in some sequester'd shade The grief with which my heart was rent, Villains, who lay in ambuscade, And watch'd and wish'd for this event, My person seiz'd, and bore away, To lawless force a feeble prey. XXVIII In vain my eyes with sorrow stream'd; In vain my threats, in vain my pray'r; In vain to heav'n and earth I scream'd, And beat my breast, and tore my hair: But when each hope extinct I deem'd, Extinct in ruin and despair, This Howard, like an angel, came, And sav'd at once my life and fame. XXIX Nor thou, as heav'n supremely good, Refuse my plaints thy gentle ear; Should Graham beneath thy hand subdu'd Expire by destiny severe, Say, can that hand in blood embrued, In Graham's warm blood, to me be dear? Or can the life of him I love To me a grateful offering prove? XXX Now hear my voice, ye chieftans, hear; Eternal fate is in the sound; Let each these hated broils forbear, In leagues of holy friendship bound: Should either lift the hostile spear, And stretch his rival on the ground, First heav'n and hell shall be ally'd Ere I become the victor's bride.” CANTO II. I She ended: and her varying charms A thousand agitations show; When all at once they heard alarms As from a fierce advancing foe: To arms! the camp resounds, to arms! Wide and more wide the tumults grow; From heart to heart contagion flies, And all in wild disorder rise. II What felt the valiant heart of Graham When he descry'd the mad'ning throng? Conflicting passions shook his frame; He knew th'opponent army strong. Rapid as heaven's explosive flame, To stop his friends, he stepp'd along; Whilst rushing on, with tortur'd view, He recogniz'd his faithful few. III “What mean my soldiers! (loud he cry'd) Behold your leader safe restor'd. Would heav'n! in anguish I had died Ere conscious of this deed abhorr'd! Thus unprovok'd, unsanctify'd, What right had you to draw the sword? Rash men! was expiation due For private wrongs to me or you?” IV Thus he rebuk'd, tho' in despair Their gallant ardour to restrain; Lost in th'expanse of turbid air Expostulation prov'd in vain: Discord and havock every where In luxury of triumph reign; The groan of death, th'exulting roar, The suppliant shrieks, heav'ns concave tore. V A storm of lances now they threw, Whilst on each point destruction flies; And starting from th'elastic yew A cloud of shafts obscure the skies.— “Ye hosts of heav'n, what blasts my view! (With voice exerted, Howard cries:) What laurels can these dastards gain, When handfuls fall by myriads slain? VI Hence, execrable cowards, hence! Shrink to your holes, and tremble there! Whose blood is spilt without expence, Whom mercy hardly deigns to spare. This band (so mighty, so immense!) To hungry dogs and fowls of air, My troop alone shall quickly throw: Hear Percy's voice in mine, and go.” VII This Elliot heard; for war renown'd, In danger's front severely try'd: He grasp'd his sword, he groan'd profound, Then with sarcastic smile reply'd: “Yes, if your words like darts could wound, If foes were vanquish'd when descry'd, Trophies from hence you might extort, Like those obtain'd at Agencourt. VIII Such trophies let your annals boast, Their truth I mean not to refute; Yet were those precious archives lost, Our juniors might the facts dispute, Unless your formidable host More recent wonders execute: Yet Edward play'd a safer game, And filch'd a bloodless diadem.” IX He spake: and rear'd his shining blade With mortal prowess to descend; Nor vainly had his might essay'd In death the hero to extend; But by the shiv'ring steel betray'd, His stroke abortive miss'd its end; Yet stunn'd and giddy Howard reel'd, And thund'ring press'd the sanguine field. X Him, stagg'ring, Elliot thus address'd; “If yet unhurt thy life remains, If yet of wonted strength possess'd, Nor wound thy vital current drains, (Advantage o'er a foe depress'd, Tho' in her power, my soul disdains) Arise, thy scatter'd arms resume, Nor prostrate share a vulgar doom.” XI He said; and with extended hand, At once from earth the chieftan rears, Tho' circl'd by a furious band Of foes, with quivers arm'd, and spears. Then fear first Howard's soul unman'd, For Elliot's life; nor vain his fears; An arrow from an unknown bow, Struck deep, and laid the hero low. XII Long torpid o'er the bleeding corse, Howard in silent horror hung; Depriv'd of sense, depriv'd of force, And all his soul with anguish wrung: Not with more exquisite remorse Did guilt e'er feel her bosom stung, Than Howard felt intense regret, Tho' guiltless of the warriour's fate. XIII As fires in some volcano pent, That on its melting inwards prey, With struggling rage explore a vent, And burst resistless into day; So now, impatient of restraint, In tears his anguish found its way: By grief his soul to madness driv'n, Thus wild expostulates with heav'n: XIV “Ye powers that o'er this orb preside! Must worth thus perish premature? Should chance the helm of nature guide, What greater ills could man endure? His hoary sire, his blooming bride, His orphan babes, in hope secure, Shall view him cold and lifeless earth, Then curse the period of their birth. XV Oft of a seer the Scots have told, Before whose heav'n-directed eyes Remote events of things, enroll'd By destiny, successive rise; Why could not he this stroke behold, Which now to heav'n for pity cries? But victims to the future blind, We must pursue the course assign'd. XVI Detested instrument of ill, Into thy sheath, my sword, return! From nature tears enough distill, Condemn'd inherent woes to mourn. O thou! whose dear remains must fill, Instead of mine, th'untimely urn, Would I had fell the sad decree, And yielded up my soul for thee! XVII Yet bear, my soldiers, bear him hence, And, whilst his vital warmth remains, Aid nature, struggling in suspense, And stop th'effusion of his veins; Cherish returning life and sense; For if the chief his strength regains, Honour and wealth on him shall wait, Whose hand retards th'approach of fate.” XVIII As when two adverse blasts descend To strife for empire o'er the main, This way, and that, the surge they bend, While both their native force retain; Thus arms to arms oppos'd contend For conquest on th'empurpled plain; Yet, unfatigued with wounds and toil, Nor these advance, nor those recoil. XIX Still struggling with superior pow'rs, The hardy Scots maintain their ground, Tho' fate its pregnant quiver showrs, And death in carnage wantons round.— While on his forehead vengeance lowr's, Forth Percy issues with a bound; His wrathful eyes perdition dart, And thus he pours his pregnant heart: XX “God's splendour! shall a lawless crew Of vagrant thieves your might restrain? Shall hands so feeble, troops so few, Repel this vast, this martial train? Or do my senses tell me true, Or have enchantments turn'd my brain? Better in death my eyes were seal'd, Then see my country's spirit yield. XXI But you, oh England's spurious race! In other feats distinguish'd shine: The trembling arm and lilied face For other fights their stars design. Vile offspring! destin'd to disgrace Your native soil, your generous line! To heav'n and earth, say, shall I tell, In what atchievements you excell? XXII To gorge the feast, to drain the bowl, To loiter near the blazing fire; To waste the night without controul, Indulging gross or lewd desire: For these, tho' doom'd in flames to howl, To joys no nobler you aspire; These are your sov'reign bliss alone, The heav'n you seek, the god you own. XXIII But if unchastis'd hence you fly, Tho' dogg'd with penitence and shame, The death of cowards let me die, And slander blast my spotless fame. Oh curse, that form should men belie, In visage, not in heart the same! Shall honour, life, and soul at stake, No spark of English valour wake?” XXIV With spirit from their chief inhal'd, Whilst all their might his troops exert, A piercing shriek their ears assail'd, Sad emphasis of female smart. At this the soul of Howard fail'd; Cold horror thrill'd his boding heart, When lo! his swimming eyes explore Their dearest object stain'd with gore: XXV Her rescue nobly Graham essay'd, And interpos'd a massy shield: But impotent his single aid; His hands employ'd, no sword could wield; Nor could his utmost force pervade, Th'embattel'd ranks that throng'd the field. This, torn with anguish, Howard saw, Nor could remain, nor durst withdraw. XXVI “Oh list, for mercy's sake! (he cry'd); Mercy, chief glory of the brave! Suspend your strife by him who died, From endless death your souls to save! Else beauty's blossom, virtue's pride, Scarce blown, must wither in the grave. Oh let me to her aid be gone, Prevent her fate, or seek my own!” XXVII Thus by the sacred name adjur'd, Suspense prevail'd in every mind; Whilst Graham no more by troops immur'd, A passage free, rejoic'd to find: His lovely charge, from harm secur'd, He in a neighbouring tent resign'd; Thence thro' the habitations round, Relief he sought, relief he found. XXVIII Of matrons, now a weeping train, Attended round the fair distrest; With skillfull hand, and care humane, The blood they stopt, the wound they drest. The more they view'd, the less their pain; For slightly was the hurt imprest; And, should her mind serene endure, Susceptible of speedy cure. XXIX By undesigning fury thrown, The weapon, ere it reach'd the fair, Had thro' a spacious distance flown, And idly spent its force in air. When to the rivals this was known, What joy they felt, from what despair! So joy the guilty when from heav'n They hear pronounc'd their sins forgiv'n. CANTO III. I And now in milder tasks engag'd, The wants of nature to repair; No longer war the armies wag'd, Their dead and wounded claim'd their care; In truce their mutual honour pledg'd, Both pleas'd, the common safety share; While Graham and Howard in one tent, The tranquil hour in parley spent. II Thus Graham began: “Let local hate, And jealous rage, be cancell'd here; And now that mystery of fate, Whose lightest word demands my ear, In this calm interval, relate With temper candid and sincere; Each dark event minutely show, And how I stand concern'd, to know.” III To whom his rival: “From my tongue Expect the story but in part: Of Caledonian lineage sprung, Thou deem'st the charmer of thy heart; There thou beheld'st her first when young, There first thou felt'st the pleasing smart, Which since o'er all thy bosom reigns, And constitutes its joys or pains. IV But erst, when urg'd by youthful heat To satisfy a brother's shade, I plung'd myself beyond retreat, Where all its horrors war display'd, And by this conduct indiscreet, To Scotland pris'ner was convey'd; A sire with years and honours grac'd, To me her various fortunes trac'd: V For as by chance our way she cross'd, “Thou view'st (said he) that lovely maid, “Heaven's darling image, nature's boast, “Virtue by beauty's hand array'd; “Yet in the storms of fortune tost, “When heaven's blest beam she scarce survey'd; “Her from the womb no sire embrac'd, “No gladness hail'd, no splendour grac'd. VI “With England's troops, in hostile guise, “A godlike youth adorn'd the field, “Who till he gain'd some high emprise, “His name and pedigree conceal'd: “But partial fortune oft denies “The meed, which bright desert should yield, “Rushing unguarded on the fray, “Too soon depressed by wounds he lay. VII “Him Elliot, hospitable knight, “Convuls'd with pain, and drench'd in gore, “Beheld, and thro' the shock of fight, “Surviving to his mansion bore: “His daughter melting at the sight, “The blooming hero to restore, “Apply'd each salutary art, “And cur'd his wound, but pierc'd his heart. VIII “For in his chamber while confin'd, “And tended by the pitying fair, “With anguish more intense he pin'd, “Than that extinguish'd by her care. “He breath'd the torment of his mind, “Nor she reluctant heard his pray'r: “A priest (unknown to Elliot) came, “And with heaven's sanction crown'd their flame. IX “By honour call'd, impell'd by hope, “Once more in arms the hero rose, “Renown's eternal wreath to crop, “Which high on danger's summit grows “But doom'd with mightier force to cope, “And circl'd by a world of foes; “My life, my love, my hopes, farewel!” “He said; and, crush'd by numbers, fell, X “The father every worth confest, “Which the young bridegroom's soul adorn'd; “Yet, for his country prepossess'd, “All overtures from England scorn'd; “Nor ceas'd the stranger to detest, “Who from his arms his child suborn'd; “Nor view'd with nature's fond regard, “Her soul depress'd, her form impair'd; XI “Her period of gestation o'er, “And nature struggling for relief, “Her orphan babe the mother bore, “Sad heir of indigence and grief! “Then, banish'd from her father's door, “By mandates from the angry chief, “Within a convent's walls confin'd, “Her suff'ring spirit she resign'd. XII “Yet instinct, pow'rful in his breast, “(Tho' with determin'd hate inflam'd,) “The smiling infant he caress'd, “And for his once lov'd Anna nam'd; “His hand her slightest wants redress'd, “His heart her plan of culture fram'd; “Yet would not own the charming maid, “Till nature's debt his daughter paid. XIII “Then 'gan his stubborn soul to melt; “Emotions till that hour unknown, “Thro' all his alter'd mind he felt, “Which injur'd nature might atone; “Still in his breast the parent dwelt, “Now reign'd triumphant and alone; “Transferr'd from fortune's barren waste, “His eyes she charm'd, his mansion grac'd.” XIV “Thus far the chief, nor more he knew; For hid in night's impervious veil, The youth's descent eludes our view, Nor can we gain this sad detail, Where first that vernal blossom grew, Whose ruin hostile eyes bewail: His birth from England all attest, Deep secrecy involves the rest.” XV Whilst thus in Scotland I remain'd A wretched captive on parole, Her charms my raptur'd eyes detain'd, Her virtues conquer'd all my soul: Oh! what is liberty regain'd, When endless chains the mind controul? Fulfil, just heav'n, thy fixt decree, And strike me dead, or set me free! XVI By public sanction thence releas'd, As to our camp I bent my way, With fond anticipation pleas'd, My late dishonour to repay; Each sense the voice of anguish seiz'd, Anguish that could not brook delay; I saw my Anna's struggling charms Encircled in a ruffian's arms. XVII O'Braian of Hybernian race, A robber fam'd and fear'd around, To gain the prize had watch'd the place, And now presum'd his wishes crown'd: Thither, enrag'd, I urg'd my pace, And made the felon bite the ground; His timid train his fall survey'd, Nor to revenge their leader staid. XVIII With indignation and despair, All pale and faint my charmer lay; I rais'd her with fraternal care, And gently sooth'd her deep dismay; I begg'd, nor did she slight my pray'r, But, sweet companion of my way, By my protecting arm sustain'd, At length secure the camp she gain'd. XIX Nor, tho' the maid for thee declares, Let passion joys in prospect feign; Divided hearts, divided cares, Domestic bliss can ne'er maintain: An English heart thy Anna shares; Still in her breast shall England reign: Hence woes entail'd on all thy line, Shall prove a curse to thee and thine. XX But now in heav'n's high vault no star To gild the dark horizon glows; No sound ambiguous, heard from far, Thro' air's, thin texture trembling flows; Nature, fatigued with toils and war, Courts the dear blessing of repose: Soon shall the lights officious glare, Restore the world to grief and care.” XXI While thus their languid pow'rs to cheer, Grateful recess the warriours sought, Thither extended on a bier, An agonizing chief was brought: But as he now advanc'd more near, Elliot, whom dead before they thought, Elliot himself they recognize, And melt in tears, and burst in sighs. XXII “You see me still, though scarce alive; (In groans th'expiring hero said:) From duty, strength my pow'rs derive, To dear departed worth unpaid; This done, with fate no more I strive, But sink beneath its peaceful shade; Enough of life kind heav'n bestows, When fame and virtue grace its close. XXIII Thy audience, Howard, let me claim; To thee my message is addrest; For when my sister's languid frame The bed of death reclining prest, Her long lamented husband's name, To me her dying lips confest; Thy ill-starr'd brother (rashly brave!) To Anna's charms existence gave. XXIV How light these last convulsions seem, That shew my mortal crisis near! But nature's voice in this extreme, Her pleading voice, what heart can bear! This, this is agony supreme; Ten thousand deaths are less severe: Great God! whose smile is more than life, Console my tender babes and wife. XXV How long shalt thou, my country! smart, For whom my blood spontaneous flows! Thrice happy could my pangs impart A lasting cure for all thy woes; These plagues, benignant pow'r, avert, And grant sincere, tho' late repose; Where wrath and devastation sway, Let arts of peace their charms display!” XXVI For me, my friends, your sorrows spare; I go in regions more sublime, A nobler destiny to share, Above the sphere of chance and time. Howard, be Anna's bloom thy care In this inhospitable clime.” His parting soul, while this he said, Angels to bliss in heav'n convey'd. CANTO IV. I Now with immortal splendor gay, The sun his wonted course resumes, To pour th'exhaustless flood of day, Which heaven's majestic arch illumes: From every bush the vernal lay, From ev'ry opening flow'r, perfumes Impregnate wide the sportive gale, And joy exults in hill and dale. II Not so the hosts on yonder plain: Their hearts of comfort felt no ray; For conquest each had toil'd in vain, Nor hop'd the dear decisive day: Sadden'd with labour, want, and pain, Th'interminable prospect lay; But chief in ev'ry English soul Sedition rag'd without controul. III Thus to his mate each soldier cries: “What curse this fruitless war extends! At home each field uncultur'd lies, On which our daily bread depends: Alike the Scot his wants supplies, Where'er his devious course he bends.” Mov'd by such views, their heralds came, A new cessation to proclaim. IV “Ye quiver'd Scots, our words attend; Pacific overtures we bring: Shall groans and carnage never end? Shall blood from rills perennial spring? Let either nation envoys send, For peace to importune its king.” The hosts for peace exclaim around; Peace heav'n, and earth, and sea resound. V In holy fervour now entranc'd, From Scotia's bands a rev'rend sage, Half way between the troops advanc'd, In all the dignity of age: With ardent eyes, on both he glanc'd, That lightned with prophetic rage, Then on a point of empty space, Their beams directing stopp'd his pace. VI “The God! the flaming God! (he cry'd:) I feel him all my pow'rs controul. Oh! gently on my spirit glide, Nor into nothing flash my soul! O'er heav'n and earth one boundless tide Of glory sweeps from pole to pole: Inscrutable to grosser eyes, The book of fate expanded lies. VII Two chiefs I see of noble name, Whose hearts in friendship once were join'd, Competitors for love and fame, Now glow with passions more unkind; Whilst cold suspicion, mutual blame, Embitter each dissever'd mind: Such ills on human spirits prey, By cruel error led astray. VIII To truth eternal and severe, Howard, thy docile ear incline! Nature's great interdict revere; For nature's mandate speaks in mine: By kindred blood ally'd so near, To kindred love thy wish confine; Else shall thy days in anguish flow, And God and man pronounce thee foe. IX Thee, Graham, of Anna's charms possest, My soul's enlighten'd view surveys: Each night shall give thee sacred rest, Each day to light thy joys shall blaze: With all a father's transports blest, I see thy offspring fix thy gaze; And with ineffable delight, Behold your lovely forms unite. X Dispatch'd from heav'n's etherial height, By her eternal father's smile, Fair Peace accelerates her flight, To bless this long distracted isle; Fell Anger and corrosive Spite, No more inur'd to war and spoil, In adamantine fetters bound, With clamour shake their cells profound. XI But as with desultory fire Along th'aerial current borne, When scarce its lusture we admire, The meteor leaves our sight forlorn; So, blasted, Peace shall soon retire, And Britain still by faction torn, Shall mark with horrors ev'ry age, And glut with civil blood its rage. XII Where am I wrapt, eternal pow'r! What extacies my soul dilate! Emerge thou bright auspicious hour, Elude the slow results of fate. The rose, gay summer's fav'rite flow'r, No more with tumid pride inflate; Shall throw each prejudice aside, And with the thistle be ally'd. XIII By sanguine proof, ye nations, taught What various ills from discord rise, Discord with all the curses fraught That earth can feel or hell devise; With sacred vigilance of thought, Your union cultivate and prize; Union, eternal source of joy, Which nought can lessen or destroy. XIV England! for industry and toil, Wisdom, and polish'd arts, renown'd, Whose happy clime and grateful soil Diffuse exhaustless plenty round; So from thy shores may foes recoil, Involv'd in shame, and grief profound, As thou behold'st with placid eyes Thy sister kingdom's glory rise. XV Scotia! to earth's remotest verge, By each conspicuous virtue known, Whose glorious deeds, whose talents large, Enrich all climates but thy own; To him thy duty first discharge, From whose paternal hand alone Thy blessings, which no measure know, Thy freedom, wealth, and safety, flow. XVI Nor let seductive Pleasure's charms, From Wisdom's ways thy soul allure, Nor quench thy gen'rous thirst of arms, Nor all thy recent fame obscure: Thy breast, while noble ardour warms, For sacred faith, and virtue pure, Till heav'n and earth shall pass away, Thy glory ne'er shall feel decay. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>