<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Middleton, Christopher, 1560-1628</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Middleton, Christopher, 1560-1628</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">middleton christopher 1560 1628</field>
      <field name="author_text">Middleton, Christopher, 1560-1628</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">16th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.1068.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">1596</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:463723</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Historie of Heaven ; Containing the Poeticall fictions of all the starres in the firmament: gathered from amongst all the Poets and Astronomers. By Chrystopher Middleton</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">Historie of Heaven ; Containing the Poeticall fictions of all the starres in the firmament: gathered from amongst all the Poets and Astronomers. By Chrystopher Middleton</field>
      <field name="title_facet">historie of heaven</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">historie of heaven</field>
      <field name="title_text">Historie of Heaven ; Containing the Poeticall fictions of all the starres in the firmament: gathered from amongst all the Poets and Astronomers. By Chrystopher Middleton</field>
      <field name="year_display">1596</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1596</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1596</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463723&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463723&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Middleton, Christopher, 1560?-1628&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;middleton christopher 1560 1628&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Historie of Heaven ; Containing the Poeticall fictions of all the starres in the firmament: gathered from amongst all the Poets and Astronomers. By Chrystopher Middleton&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;historie of heaven&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1596&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1596&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Middleton, Christopher&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1560&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1628&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Historie of Heaven&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Containing the Poeticall fictions of all the starres in the firmament: gathered from amongst all the Poets and Astronomers. By Chrystopher Middleton&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Clement Knight [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1596&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp2635&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;38 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Historie of Heaven&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Containing the Poeticall fictions of all the starres in the firmament: gathered from amongst all the Poets and Astronomers. By Chrystopher Middleton&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 65 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To his very good friend master Robert Traps, C. K. wisheth health. The Historie of Heauen. When from a chaos of confused things Was fram'd the compasse of this christall skie, The subiect which my home-borne muse now sings, Though farre vnfit to reach a note so hie, As is the musicke making course of it, Whose lowest streame orereaches euery wit. Then when perfection in her course did bring The hidden knowledge of those god-like arts, That worlds faire frame, which heauen-borne Poets sing, Was made to memorize great mens desarts: Where, by succeeding ages should be seene The wonders that in oreworne worlds haue beene. This true vnstainde record not spangled then With euerlasting characters of gold, Where now is writ the workes of gods and men: The stories that time long agoe hath told, Was then vnfurnisht of those glorious lights, That now makes day time of the darkest nights. This is the circuit which some please to call, The glorious starrie spangled firmament: Others imagine it that golden wall, That compasses the heauens continent: And of those nine fayre Orbs great iudgements write: This is the highest obiect to our sight. Whose motion formes these elementall frames, Quickens the naked shapes that nature makes: Sorts euery subiect to the seuerall names, And workes what Gods intended for our sakes, Turnes backe perforce the motion of the sunne, Makes morning, euening, night, and cheerefull noone. The first that in this monument of fame [illeg.]Next to the Articke pole supplies a place, Is faire Calisto, famous by that name: Descended from th'Arcadian kingly race, Whom for her beautie Cynthia did intertaine, That she might waite vpon her maiden traine. This Nymph once bathing on her in a brooke, To coole her bodie in the chrystal glide: Where to that end her fellowes she forsooke, By Iupiter was lucklesly espied: Who with her sight set suddenly on fire, Gins studie how to compasse his desire. Long time his wauering thoughts did run about, Orelabouring of themselues to finde the way, That from this labyrinth might leade him out, And yet himselfe thus loath for to bewray, Transformes his substance to Dianaes shape, By that meanes thinking to obtaine her rape. Where, with the damsell vnderneath a shade, He spends that pleasant day in sweet delight: Offring to shew himselfe: yet halfe afraide, Least with his sudden change he might afright His fearfull Loue, not yet come to his call, And by that meanes lose labour, Loue, and all. Gins like a nibling fish that halfe mistrusts The golden shew of an intising baite, Makes many offers for the thing she lusts, Daring to deale with that she deemes deceit: So playes this amorous God, with his faire prize, Whom loue and lust bids boord, but shame denies. At last as swelling tides breakes downe their bounds, That all this while hath kept them in perforce, Orelying forcibly their neighbour grounds, And loath to come into their former course: So driuen to the deede with strong desire, He gins to make a flame out of his fire. Which when the shamefast naked Nymph gins see, How subtilly she poore soule was oretaine, With modest words defends her chastitie: Alleaging what an euerlasting staine Would cleaue vnto her soule for this offence, With which nor Gods nor mortall men dispence. When like a subtill Syren he begins To tell her it was credit to offend With mightie men, their credit cloakes their sins, What they misdoe, their might doth straight amend: And therefore was Achilles weapon saide, To heale the wound that it before had made. At last with his perswasiue tongue he wonne The castle of this maidens constancie: They melt with words as waxe against the sunne: So weake is many womens modestie, That what sometimes they most would seeme to shield, Another time vnaskt poore soules they yeeld. On her this wanton God begot a sonne, Whom she calde Archas, at whose luckles birth Diana (for this trespasse she had done) From her sweet seruice doth expell her forth, Plaguing Calisto with this rigorous law, That her mishap might hold the rest in aw. And ielous Iuno, that had seene all this That her escaping husband had done here, Inflicts a heauier doome on her amis, Changing her bodie to an vgly beare: And makes her now perforce poore soule to dwell In desart dungeon, groues thrice worse then hell. Where after many yeares she had oreworne, Grieuing at that, hard hap had brought to passe, Changde from the shape wherein she first was borne, And saue her mind, naught left of what she was: The fates yet more to crosse her wearie will, Inflicts vpon her now a greater ill. For whil'st her stripling sonne ranging abroad, To seeke amongst the shadie trees some game, Whereas his wofull mother made abode: Thither by chance her careles ofspring came, Who seeking to pursue some beast or other, Was first of all incountred by his mother. She willing to interpret her intent, For that her tongue denies to take his turne, With fawning friendship tels him what she ment, And would say how (poore soule) her heart did burne With the incessiue ioy, a mothers eye Surfets vpon her childrens safetie. Thus standing at a bay, the foolish boy Misconstering her motherly good will, Cheeres vp his heart with ouer cloying ioy, He had found a beast he was in hope to kill. And casting from his hand a harmfull dart, Pierces his mother through her tender hart. Which murder that it should not here remaine A wondring president for times to come, How in despite of God, his Loue was slaine By her owne ofspring, and his base got sonne: To heale this harme and make all iniuries euen, He takes them vp and places them in heauen. Where in the Isie frozen Artick clime, Turnde into starres in likenes of two Beares: This mother and her sonne since spends their time, Keeping continuall motion with the spheres: Seuen of which starres that in their shapes remaine, Are by our common people called Charles waine. But Iuno for to crosse them he had blest, Compounds with Neptune God of watrie seas, That where all other starres doe take their rest, These two should neuer taste that quiet ease: Gainst whom this God opposes such great lets, That in all Europe these starres neuer sets. Next them compounded of thirteene fayre starres, [illeg.] A hidious Dragon circles most of these, He that kept safely with his watchfull warres, The golden garden of the Hesperides: Whom the right rendring Gods haue placed there, For to requite the toyle that he tooke here. Then stands Cephæus, sometimes Egypts king, Husband to Cassiopeia the faire: [illeg.] From whom Andromeda Perseus Loue did spring: Vpon whose stock the Gods had such a care, That at his beautious daughters happie birth, They swore none of that kinde should waste in earth. Bootes next, on whom the Gods haue plast, [illeg.] To keepe the Beares that Ioue here dignifies: Least Iuno in her egar wrath should cast Her husbands darling from the azured skies, And quit the fault before he had misdone, Vpon this wretched mother and her sonne. Then of nine siluer starres is made a Crowne, [illeg.] A garland beauties Goddesse once did twine, And gaue to Ariadne for a boune: When as she matcht with Bacchus God of wine: After vngratefull Theseus fled away, And left his Loue to perish and decay. Which Bacchus in remembrance of his Loue, Plaste in the heauens as too good to dwell Beneath with men, but with the Gods aboue, Where it should neuer wither, but liue well, And be the trophees of their nuptiall pride, Which Venus gaue him for to grace his bride. [illeg.]Next them, the labouring conqueror of kings Alcides is, whose lookes yet menace wrath To the succeeding issue of those things: Monsters and men that here he put to death, Arm'd at all poynts there this worlds captaine stands, With his victorious weapon in his hands, He from his wife, whom long he had not seene, Receiued for an intermissiue good A poysoned shirt, that by her meanes had beene Stain'd in the venome of a Centaures blood: Whom once himselfe bereaued of his life, For offring wanton daliance with his wife. Which he suspectles puts vpon his backe, And proude of his wiues fauour he was in, Wore it, till it began to worke his wracke, And forcibly did pierce his skarles skin, Eating his strong made limmes and ioynts asunder, Whose might was to the world a matchles wonder. Which treason when too late he now perceiues, How thus vntimely he was made away: Vrg'd with the poysoning paine, he madly raues, Disdaining that the world of him should say, How he which ransackt hell, and conquerd earth, Should by a womans meanes be brought to death. So on a mountaine making vp his nest, Where Phœnix-like he now intends to die, And bring his haples soule to hopefull rest, By this vndoing of his miserie: Casts his decaying limmes into the fire, Where death had quickly finisht his desire. But for of seuerall substances combinde, Begot vpon Alcumena by great Ioue, His mothers earth to earth he there resignde. His godhead that the Gods doe hold aboue, As loath their substance thought it here discend, Should with mortalitie make here an end. Next that, the golden Harpe whose well toucht strings [illeg.] Could moue the massie stones with melodie: Raise rooted trees, and stirre all liueles things To follow on her heauenly harmonie: Make riuers turne their streames another way, And come vnkindly for to heare her play. Some say the riuer Nylus ouerrun, To water the black burnt Egyptian plaine: When time calde backe her streames whence they begun, To keepe their course into the sea againe, There with innumerable fishes more, It left a Tortoyse sprauling on the shore. Which dried with the moysture drawing sunne, Young Mercurie, as once he passed by, Stroke it with his staffe: whereat the shell begun To make a musicking murmuring melodie. Which the young God takes vp with an intent, To make of it a formall Instrument. And to that sweete tungde Poet that did sing Such pleasant Poems in the iawes of Hell: The Gods decree to giue this heauenly thing, For that his arte could exercise it well: After whose death their deede they did reclaime, And fetcht this Harpe to heauen backe againe. [illeg.]Then sits a siluer Swanne, vnder whose shape The wanton God obscur'd his deitie, When as he purchasde louely Ledaes rape, And reuelde in a ritcher treasurie Then was combined vp in Paris ioy, Whose sun-bright beauty burnt faire blowming Troy. Whilome inamoured Ioue with her faire eyes, Consorts with wanton Venus for his will: She like an Eagle, he in the disguise Of a white seeming Swanne, seekes to fulfill His hungrie hope that sets his soule on fire, With neuer dying flames of hot desire. And as the Ladie sitting by a brooke, Vnder a broad bloom'd Rose sweet smelling shade, Apollo for to glut him with her looke, Stops the strong passage his proude coursers made: Wishing tenne thousand times in Thetis sted, This beautie were conueyed to his bed. When these beguiling birds, as though by hap The Swanne had fled his furious foe for feare: He for his refuge takes this Ladies lap, And courteous she content to keepe him there, Sits her downe further vnderneath the shade, For to preuent the meanes the Eagle made. And looking louely on this beautious bird, Smoothing his siluer plumes with her soft hand, His silke-like feathers here and there she stird, He with his wings the sweete fumed aire fand, For to alay the ouersmoothering heate, That valed her angels face with pearlie sweate. Thus lyes this God in beauties proudest bed, Couered with curtaines of her iuorie armes: Her snow white breasts are pillowes for his head, Her sugred words intising heauenly charmes, Whose siluer sound were able to asswage Warres furious God in hottest of his rage. At last, intising sleepe perswades her eyes To feede her idle sences with content: Which this loue armed God, straightwaies espies, And takes that time to practise his intent: When in her slumber softly there he wrought The full content of his inueagled thought. For which good turne, to gratifie his friend, Vnder whose couert he contriu'd his lust, And brought his hopeles thoughts to happie end, In quenching of his drie desirous thirst, Plac'd her within this compasse mongst the rest, Where for that deede for euer she is blest. Then comes faire Cassiopeia Egypts pride, That with her beautie brau'd those peerles dames, Nereides the sea Nymphs that abide Vpon the watrie worlds still mouing frames, Tripping like summers Deere from place to place, Vpon the dancing waues faire gilded face. For which contempt, the censuring Gods decree, She should be changed to her deepe disgrace Into some starres: where for her miserie Here they appoynted her abiding place: And in the motion of the heauens still, She's backward drawne as though against her will. Next is her husband Perseus, Daneas sonne, Whom Iupiter beguil'd with golden shoes: Dazeling her eyes (vntill the deede were done) With present pleasures which breede after woes, Raining into her lap so sweete a showre, As would haue wonne a thousand women more. From that deceitfull daliance Perseus sprong, Who after prou'd Heauens champion in their warres, Against Medusa that durst offer wrong To Gods and men with her disturbing dares: Whose monstrous face orehung with snakie haire, Made Heauen tremble and kept earth in feare. This souldier armed with Mineruaes shield, Plum'd with swift Mercuries aire-beating wings, And his bright sword now readie for the field: Proud that the Gods would vse him in these things, Cuts through the emptie aire and vnseene way, That brought him downe where fierce Medusa lay. Where in that single combat she orecom'd, Humbles her selfe vnto his conquering hand: He takes her head, and leaues her bodie numbd With deaths cold comfort sprauling on the sand: Then with that purchase backe againe he flies, To be eternizde for his deare bought prize. When as he towring in the emptie aire, Sees in the sea a maiden weake and pale, Whose semblance seemed that she had been faire: Though feare had now oreshadowed in a vaile The faire vermillion tincture of her face, And left her there the conquest of disgrace. This was Andromeda, the Gods had bound Vpon a ruthles rocke to be the pray Of a fierce fish, by whom she must be found, And for her mothers pride should there decay, Proude Cassiopeia that durst hold plea With the faire ofspring of the foming sea. Whom Perseus from her painfull prison frees, And then at libertie he pleades his loue: For whose requitall she straightwaies agrees, Vowing her fancie neuer should remoue, Vntill diuorcing death to both their paine, Should separate their vnited soules againe. Thus as these new met louers homewards hies, Proud Perseus to his sole commander tels The hidden vertue of his hidious prize, How with her lookes all humane power she quels, And metamorphizes her gazers on, To an vnpenitrable senceles stone. At length vnto Sariphus Ile they come, Where Perseus grandsire old Acrisus meetes him: Glad that his nephew had so happily wonne This hopeles conquest, kindly comes and greetes him. But looking wishly on the monsters face, Turn'd to a stone he stands still in that place. When Perseus grieuing at his grandsires death, Brought by his meanes to this vnhappie end: Casts downe his conquest to the cursed earth, And vowes in sorrow his sad dayes to spend: Whose hap to helpe the powerfull Gods agree, To take him vp amongst this companie. Then comes Auriga or the Wagoner, [illeg.] Whom Poets say is young Hypolitus, Who fled his mothers lust: and for the care The Gods requites his continencie thus: That sensuall sinners by this meanes may see, How heauens remunerats his chastitie. By him stands Capra Iupiters kind nurse, Who by his mother Ops conueide away From th'execution of his fathers curse: To whom the Delphion Oracle did say, That by his owne sonne, Saturne should be driuen From his great kingdome of all-keeping heauen. When Iupiter conueyed from his rage, Was by this she-gote fostred in a downe, Vntill he came to strength and able age, And had depriu'd his father of his crowne: Then he rewards his nurse to her content, By placing of her in the firmament. [illeg.]Next vnto him a mans faire picture stands, Composed of xxiiii. glorious starres, Holding a wreathed Serpent in his hands, Striuing as though they two were still at iarres. This Esculapius is Apollos sonne, That could bring life againe when life was done. He when Hippolytus was all to torne By the foule flesh-fed iades that drew his carre: Setting his limmes againe as they were borne, Reuiues them all as erst before they were. For such his cunning was in Phisicks skill, He could expell deaths danger at his will. Whereat the Destinies incenst with wrath, Complaines to Iupiter how they were wrong'd By mortall men, whose might could conquer death, A thing which solely to themselues belong'd. Telling him he must curb these forward men, Or their aspiring minds would orereach them. At which the angrie God shaking his head, Throwes downe a thunderbolt, that with his weight Hits Esculapius, and so strikes him dead. But Phœbus hardly brooking of that sight, Takes vp his sonne, and spite what Ioue can doe, Sets him in heauen for to ease his woe. Mynos the Cretane King had one sole heire Nam'd Glaucus, louely like the Gnidian Doue, [illeg.] Straight as the new sprong pine tree, and as faire As faire Adonis Cythereas Loue. But hungrie death that all things doth deuoure, Cuts vp this bud of beautie fore his flower. Whom Esculapius for his former cure, Was by constraint inioyned to regaine: And to that end the King did there immure This Artist where he now must needes remaine, And either bring him back againe his sonne, Or let death glorie in the deedes he had done. When the poore scholler copte vp with the course, Brooking but badly his imprisonment: Beguiles the tedious time with a discourse Of wisedomes rule and wils fond gouernment, How wisedome this worlds soule should be combinde, With a fond wilfull ouerruling mind. At last he finds will stronger of the two, But wisedome the director of his might: For proofe whereof, he sees how great beasts bow And humbly casts themselues at wisemens feete. Then thinkes he to himselfe, it cannot be Will should haue now such conquest ouer me. But then he found it how it came to passe, Authoritie that will was sometimes in: Ietting like Æsopes moralized Asse, Vnder the couert of a Lyons skin: This is the wofull thing (quoth he) that still Must keepe Gods wisedome subiect to mans will. When to breake off his solitarie muse, A Serpent comes to him whereas he sits: Which with a staffe he commonly did vse, He strikes at, and his stroke so surely hits, As piercing of the poysoned Serpents head, His foe fals downe and at his feete lyes dead. Then suddenly from forth another place, A second Serpent brings in a faire greene leafe: With which, touching his fellow, straight doth chase Triumphant death, and brings lost life reliefe. Which done, the wormes makes haste to get away, And leaues the leafe where the dead Serpent lay. At which strange sight the man now halfe amazed, Takes vp the leafe and layes it on his skin: At whose soft touch the child againe was raised, By working of the like effect in him. Which Serpent, Phœbus for this deed she had done, Places in heauen with his happie sonne. There is the strong steel'd arrow that did kill [illeg.] The Griph that fed vpon Promethæus hart, Chain'd to the top of Caucasus cold hill, Whom Hercules released from that smart The Gods had cast vpon him in their wrath, For fetching fire from heauen downe to earth. The Eagle's next that Iupiter did send [illeg.] To steale away the wanton smiling boy, Whose neuer matched beautie still did lend More meanes of pride to peacock plumed Troy, That in the summer of her fayre sprong flower, Thought she had robd the Gods of all their power. He with abundance surfetting his minde Of womans fading pleasure quickly spent: Turnes his affections to another kinde Of lasting loue that was more permanent. For such is the effect of too much store, It makes them lothe that which they lou'd before. This Eagle in the searching flight he made, Sees this earths wonder by a bubling well: Wooing Narcissus like his owne faire shade, That in his owne conceit did farre excell The mixture, which to womens foule disgrace The Gods had shadowed in this wantons face. Nature, when as this god-like boy was borne, Taunted by Venus that he was too rare: Sayd she had fram'd his face in heauens scorne, Whose Angels sparkling eye-bals were so fayre, As they should draw men from their chiefe resort, And make proud women lose their best priz'd sport. Thus at himselfe as wondring all alone, The carefull foole did softly take him vp: And to her master quickly gets her gone, Who takes him for to waite vpon his cup: Where he for euer, as old writers say, Seru'd Ioue with Nectar and Ambrosia. Orion that did first of all inuent The siluer Lutes sweet trembling harmonie, Stor'd with abundant riches, as he ment To saile towards Lesbos from sweet Italie, The Saylers, for the wealth he there had stor'd, Determin'd for to drowne him ouer boord. Whom he intreates to let him touch his strings, Before they worke their pitiles intent: The which they graunt, and then the Poet sings The tragick tale of his disparagement, Sighing (poore soule) it was his owne mishap Now in his age to dye in dangers lap. A floating Dolphin that had hard all this, Houers about the ship to heare some more, Orion straight leapes out vpon the fish, And the poore creature proud of that he bore, Passes with pleasure through the surging maine, And sets him safe in Italy againe. Which curteous deede the Gods doe thus repay, Placing this fish within the firmament: Where his remembrance neuer shall decay, As long as they keepe in this Continent. For with the Gods good deedes are so regarded, As that they neuer perish vnrewarded. Young merrie Bacchus when his idle head, [illeg.] amongst his cups, was out of frame: Gets him a little easie paced steede, That [illeg.] might conuey him whence he came: After whose death the pleasant God obtained, His horse in heauen might be intertained. After Medusaes conquest, of her blood The ingendring sunne another monster breedes: A flying horse that long time stoutly stood, Refusing to be curbd like other steedes: Vntill Bellerephon deuisde a way To bring this stubborne courser to his bay. But he intending for to shape a course With his winged Palfray vp vnto the skies, Amidst his iourney tumbles from his horse, And in the seas like Icarus he dies. But vp to heauen the horse still kept his way, Where euer since he holds a certaine stay. Next that, Andromeda young Perseus wife, To whom the heauens promisde at her birth, They would extend her euerlasting life, After she had run her mortall race on earth: And carefull for to keepe their promise sure, They plaste her there where she doth still indure. Ceres in loue with fruitfull Cicilie, [illeg.] Whose soyle did euery yeare affoord more corne, Then from her neighbour countries treasurie Could in a long deuouring time be worne: Craues of the Gods, that with them still might stand, The three squar'd forme of this thrice luckie land. All these abides within these Artick climes, [illeg.] And keepes continuall motions with the spheres: Now followes these diuiders of our times, The Signes, through whom the sunne makes vp our yeres, And in twelue months drawes out his motion euen, Going through euery seuerall signe in heauen. The first is Aries, the golden Ramme, [illeg.] That carried Phixius and his sister ouer The surging Hellespont, from their curst damme, Ino old Athmas wife their second mother. Whose dangerous iourney Iupiter requites, Turning this Rammes rug'd shape to heauenly lights. This was the Bull the God transform'd him to, [illeg.] When as he stole Eutropa by a wile, Carrying her ouer where she would or no, To dallie with his Loue in Candies Ile. Whose losse old Agenor long time bewayl'd, Till when he saw his wayling naught preuayl'd. Within his forme seuen starres which Poets call Old Atlas seuen fayre daughters, whom we reade The immortall Gods did companie withall: And to requite their Lemmans for this deede, They liberally thus rewards their Loue, By placing of them with themselues aboue. But fayre Electra eldest of those seauen, That night when wofull Troy was ouerturned, Pluckt back her head, and would not see from heauen The flames wherein that ancient citie burned: Since which time this seauenth sister hath not beene Amongst her other sisters euer seene. [illeg.]Next him the Twins which Iupiter begets On louely Leda in his Swans disguise, Castor and Pollux, whom their father sets In heauen as obiects for our mortall eyes: For the requitall of his former scape He made in compassing their mothers rape. [illeg.]Then comes the backward creeping Crab that went On Iunos message to that masse of men Alcides, whom before herselfe had sent To warre with Hydra in foule Lernaes fen: Where when she came as strongly as she might, She bites his heele, thinking to crosse his fight. But Hercules when Hydras heads were done, Looking about him who should doe this deede: Oretakes the sloe paste shell-fish as she run, And beates her selfe borne-house about her head. When Iuno pitying of her seruants paines, Takes her to heauen where she now remaines. The furious Lyon in Numeas groue, [illeg.] Iuno inioyn'd her husbands sonne to kill: With whom great Hercules a long time stroue, For he could bring the beast vnto his will This Ioue when as their wearie warres were done, Placed in heauen for to grace his sonne. Then Iustice comes the last of all the Gods, [illeg.] That left her residence here on this earth: For lacke of whom the world grew all at ods, And man to man curses each others birth: For then vsurping wrong succeeded straight, That no man knew how long to hold his right. Then cals the world for Iustice backe againe, Complaining how they now were ouerrun: And they would suffer any scourging paine, In penance for those sinnes themselues had done: For that their wickednes did force this power, To leaue the seate whereas she sate before. Whereas the Gods did in their court decree Iustice should be transformed to these starres, Where foolish men might euery minute see Her, that should helpe these miseries of theirs. But stand like Tantalus within those brinks, Where he sees water, but yet neuer drinks. Next her the Ballance stands, wherein she had The vnequall deedes of mens vnruly liues, Which Iupiter there saw to be so bad, As for their sakes for euer he depriues The world of Iustice, which they had before, That spar'd no rich men, nor opprest no poore. [illeg.] Orion proudly boasting of his strength, There was no monster that he could not kill: The earth brought forth a Scorpion at the length, To trie what this proud bragger could fulfill, Whom this impoysoned Serpent with her sting Killed, before their combat could begin. For recompence whereof, the Gods did take This Serpent vp againe from of the earth, And of his substance there a signe they make, To let men know they should not deeme their worth More then the power of heauen: for they can Quickly controll the strongest stomackt man. Faire Epheme that nursde those sacred dames [illeg.] The learned Muses authorises of Arts, Whose wits all kinds of heauenly cunning frames, And liues eterniz'd for their great desarts In many a golden line, that will preuaile When all deuouring time it selfe shall faile, Had to her sonne faire Crocus, that did sup The milke those learned sisters left behind: Whom Iupiter at their requests takes vp To dwell amongst this metamorphiz'd kind: And for his knowledge did exceede compare, The Gods haue thus determin'd of him there: Like to a Horse they frame his hinder parts, To shew his knowledge in braue martiall deedes: His vpper limmes tels vs the skill in Arts, Wherein all other men he farre exceedes: Fram'd like an Archer, that the world might know His sharpe wit by his arrow and his bow. The giant Tiphon, heauens greatest foe, [illeg.] When as he menac'd all the Gods with warres, They for to plague him for disturbing so Their quiet kingdome with his churlish dares, Sets themselues readie all in battaile ranks, Vpon the bordering plaines to Nylus banks. When subtillie by their foe intrapped there, And no meanes left them for to scape away: Disguisde themselues in other shapes for feare, Where Pan the shepheards God, as writers say, Was glad by turning of his former coate, To shew like halfe a fish and halfe a goate. Whereas the God setting himselfe to swim, For feare his foe should circumuent his shape, Ioue by great chance in this sort seeing him, Gins wonder at the strangenes of his shape: And when the Gods were all come from these warres, They place this shape of Pans amongst the starres. This is young Ganimed the Troian boy, Whom Iupiter fetcht for to be his page, And rauisht all his beating vaines with ioy, Sucking the sweet taste of his tender age: Whom afterwards the God did here set vp, Powring in Nectar to a golden cup. Venus and louely Cupid on a day, Seating themselues by Euphrates faire glide, Spending the time in dallying wanton play, Was by the giant Typhon there espide, Compassed them about where they were set, As once black Vulcan tooke her in his net. For feare whereof the Goddesse was constrain'd, Clasping her young sonne in her siluer armes, To take the water, where they were sustain'd By fishes that conueyd them from those harmes: Whom afterwards the Goddesse thus requites, By turning of these fishes to fayre lights. Thus haue we run this Circle round about, Wherein the daily Sunne still keepes his course: From whence his fierie teame neuer broke out, But wholly rul'd young Phaeton by force. Now to the Southerne climates are we led, To tell what stories there are chronicled. Next to the Signes is plaste a mightie Whall, [illeg.] By which Andromeda should haue been slaine: Whom Perseus vndertooke to fight withall, To free his Loue Andromeda from paine. For the remembrance of which victorie, She is recorded in this Registrie. Iupiter, Neptune, and young Mercurie, [illeg.] Trauailing in humane likenes vp and downe, Were by Hyreus welcom'd curteously: Which to requite, the bid him aske a boune: Of whom the man desir'd he might haue A sonne before death brought him to his graue. Then doe the Gods command him bring the skin Of a young oxe that was but newly slaine: Wherein they pist, and puts it straightwaies in The earths cold wombe, bidding him raise't gaine When as the tearme of ten full months were done, And of that vrine he should haue a sonne. Which charge he kept: and when the time was past He takes it vp, within whose folds he found Orion, from the vrine they there plast Growne in the bellie of the hard cold ground: After whose death in memorie of this thing, Him and the hide to heauen they did bring. Eridanus or Padus is the next, Within whose streames young Phaeton was drencht: At whose offence great Iupiter being vext, Strikes him straight downe, whereat the fire was quencht. And in remembrance of this Riuers name, It stands in heauen for quenching of that flame. And at his feete they plaste a fearfull Hare, For that he most delighted for to view it, Whil'st on this earth he was conuersing here With mortall creatures, and there would still pursue it With two fierce dogs, that there doe also stand Readie attendants at their masters hands. The ship in which proud Iason came from Greece, [illeg.] Stoutly attended with a luckie traine To Colchos, for to winne the golden fleece, Which by Medeas loue he did obtaine: For her successe the Gods doe dignifie, Next to Orion and his companie. Apollo on a time would needes inuite [illeg.] Iupiter for to be his welcome guest, And sends the Crow wherein he did delight, To fetch him some faire water for his feast, Sending him with a golden cup away, [illeg.] And charg'd him straitly for to make no stay. The Crow as he was flying to the spring, Spies a faire fig-tree standing by the way, And then forgetting what he was to bring, Determins there awhile to make his stay: Where sore he goe this seruant meanes to see The yet greene figs full ripened on their tree. After long time when he had eate his fill, He then too late remembers what was past: And taking a dead Serpent in his bill, [illeg.] Backe to his angrie master flies he fast: To whom the sillie foule begins to tell How that soule Serpent kept him from the well. At which the angrie God chafing to see Himselfe abused by a simple fowle, Meanes with an euerlasting miserie, His too bold misdemeanour to controule, And into heauen to his shame takes vp Himselfe, the Serpent, and the golden cup. [illeg.]Next them the man that was so famous, Chiron the Centaure for his famous arts, Chiefe schoolemaster to Esculapius, Achilles, and Alcides, whose desarts Wonne with the Gods such an exceeding fauour, As that they plaste him here to liue for euer. [illeg.]Next him a woolfe, which heauens to this end Plaste there besides him, for he was deuout: The fame of his deuotion should extend Vnto all times, and nere be blotted out: Holding a sacrifice within his hands, To offer on an Altar that there stands. Next that, the Wheele that wrought Ixions paine, [illeg.]For offring daliance to the heauens Queene, Whereon in hell long time he did remaine, Till pitie mou'd the Gods for to redeeme This cursed creature from his punishment, And place his rack within the firmament. The last that's in this monument of fame, [illeg.] Is a fayre fish whom they tearme Venus daughter, Transformed in the sea, and for her name These starres continued there euer after: Where she and all the rest are fixed fast, As long as heauen moues and earth shall last. Thus did the Gods with fauours still regard The dutifull demeanes of earth-bred kinds, And gaue to euery deede his due reward. Such is their equall iustice rendring minds, That no affections drawes away their fauour, But euery thing's rewarded for his labour. The weake they doe not ouerpresse with weight, Nor feare they what the mightie man can do: The rich man with his close fist golden sleight Cannot corrupt their rightfull iudgements so. Thus without hope of gaine, or feare of might, They rendred vnto euery man his right. But when the world, orecloyed with this good, Began to surfet in intising ill, Then turn'd they downe the wheele where Fortune stood, And lets them reape the fruits of their owne will: So that these after times as Poets tell, Are for their follies registred in hell. Where now they show not in faire fixed starres, But shadowed in foule mists and frying fire, With fiends and furies keepes continuall warres, From which their wearie soules shall nere retire. So was the first world blest with heauenly fauours, And the last curst with painfull hellish labours. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>