<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Laurence, French, 1757-1809</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Laurence, French, 1757-1809</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">laurence french 1757 1809</field>
      <field name="author_text">Laurence, French, 1757-1809</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1870's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_2.0928.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1872</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:465196</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Poetical remains (1872</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Poetical remains (1872</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poetical remains 1872</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poetical remains 1872</field>
      <field name="title_text">Poetical remains (1872</field>
      <field name="year_display">1872</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1872</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1872</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465196&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465196&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Laurence, French, 1757-1809&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;laurence french 1757 1809&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Poetical remains (1872&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poetical remains 1872&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1872&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1872&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Laurence, French&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1757&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1809&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poetical remains (1872)&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Dublin&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1872&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp2168&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;172 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poetical remains (1872)&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 97 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse by French Laurence included; Latin verse omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TO THE HONORED MEMORY OF TWO BROTHERS, SOME OF WHOSE LIGHTER PRODUCTIONS ARE HERE PRESERVED, THIS SMALL VOLUME IS GRATEFULLY INSCRIBED BY ONE WHO FEELS TOO LATE HOW MUCH HE HAS OWED TO THE FAMILY OF WHICH THOSE BROTHERS WERE DISTINGUISHED ORNAMENTS. HENRY COTTON. The Poetical Triumvirate. Written at the age of 15. O lyre divine, harmonious frame! To whom shall I attune thy string? What god, or god-like son of fame, What hero shall I sing? Hence, ruthless tyrants, nor accuse The scornful silence of the Muse. Hence, ye destroyers of mankind, Who bade the blood-stained throat of war to roar, In vain your murd'rous swords the world have thinn'd. The Muse's pinions shall not blush with gore; The Muse her sons shall sing, the boast of Albion's shore. Avon exult! for thou didst hear Immortal Shakespear's voice divine; What time he stayed thy waters near, Communing with the Nine. Shakespear, of more than magic skill, With horror every breast can thrill: The night owl shrieks! I see Macbeth! Aghast with wild affright his fix'd eyes stare, His sheathèd dagger reeks from Duncan's death, While guilty fear erects each conscious hair, And hasty faltering words his breast confused declare. Thou monarch of the soul! my bosom owns thy reign, I sigh, I glow, obedient to thy strain. When, by his children spurned, Lear's sorrows flow, We feel the pleasing sympathy of woe. Ah, dearest Regan! wilt thou too conspire To drive to madness a fond helpless sire! But when with rage the monarch glows, Forgetful of his woes, Revenge each panting bosom warms. In such a cause who dreads the clash of arms? Shakespear! 'tis thine to look around From some high cliff, untouched with fear, Tho' constant thunders rock the ground And lightnings fire the air; Tho' the loud howling whirlwinds sweep The surface of the raging deep. But by the side of Mulla's stream Far calmer joys would gentle Spenser seek; There oft, when hapless damsel was his theme, His heaving breast was touched with pity meek, And softly stole the tear adown his sorrowing cheek. Oft would he sing of warlike fays Encountering fierce with Paynim knight. Ah me! that in fair Virtue's ways Such dangers men must fight. Oft would he sing of princely maid By Archimago vile betrayed. False traitor! how couldst thou ensnare And make such virtue and such truth thy prey? Yet deem not heaven withdraws its guardian care; His conquering shield brave Arthur shall display,— That shield which Virtue gives to every godlike fay. Away, ye fairy songs! The harp of Zion bring, To Milton's praise I strike the sounding string. Milton like some high towering eagle flies, And soars unwearied to his native skies. Milton! 'twas thine to view with stedfast gaze The throne that pours intolerable rays. To thee the angel Michael came And touched thee with the holy flame. Straight with new rapture burned thy breast, And all thy strains th'inspiring god confest. Then bright in adamantine arms, Bold Satan durst defy his God, While all heaven shook with war's alarms: With fury Michael glowed, Like lightning blazed his angry steel, On Satan's crest the tempest fell. Great Cherubim, I see thee now! High on the wings of winds I see thee ride, Pointing destruction at the trembling foe; I see thee in thy rage confound their pride, And with uprooted hills their horrid engines hide. Lo! like the raging torrents roar, The living chariot shakes the sky, Resistless whirlwinds howl before, And angry lightnings fly. Stern frowned Messiah from His car, And withered all the strength of war. Not so His frowns, when from above Serene He comes to judge the guilty pair: His looks breathe justice softening into love, Afraid to drive the wretched to despair. His presence Adam fled, for then he first knew fear. Ode on the Witches and Fairies of Shakespear. Written at the age of 15. STROPHE I. O guardian of that sacred land, Where Avon's wood-crowned waters stray; Thou, whose all-powerful magic wand The throng'd ideal train obey; Who dartest on swift eagle wings, Beyond the flaming bound of things: O Fancy, hear!—'tis thine alone, High-seated on a radiant throne, Fast by the lyric Muse, Her listening offspring to inspire, And, ere they strike Apollo's golden lyre, In their big breasts to pour Castalia's genuine dews. ANTISTROPHE I. Deem not my lips profane would praise A name unknown to thy chaste ear: No! Shakespear now demands my lays,— Shakespear to thee, to Phœbus dear. And oh! how at that mighty name My swelling breast hath caught the flame. Come then O Fancy, bend thy bow; With me the Muse's arrows throw At Avon's favored streams; For thee full oft thy secret feet Nightly have trod thy darling son to meet, And wave before his eyes thy gaily glittering dreams. EPODE I. At Shakespear's happy birth With fire ethereal Jove his soul endow'd, Then bade him spurn the narrow bounds of earth, And sordid wishes of the grov'ling crowd, That chain the free-born mind; and “Take,” he said, “This sacred charge, O Fancy: to his sight, “Glancing in all their colours, be displayed “The airy forms that sport in thy pure fields of light; “For his vast mind, with innate wisdom fraught “Beyond what taught “The bards of yore, “Thy trackless regions boldly shall explore, “I guiding;—thus, O goddess, have I sworn: “And now is come the fated hour; “Earth now shall see and own thy power “Forth-beaming in thy son. Be Shakespear born!” STROPHE II. So spake the god. With eager joy Thou didst prevent his high behest, And gazing on th'immortal boy, Thrice snatch him fondly to thy breast; Then, rushing from the heavenly height, The winds to Avon bore thy flight; There in old Arden's inmost shade, Far from the sun, thy spirits laid The heaven-entrusted child; And as before his purgèd eyes Thou badest oft their sportive train arise, With silence fixed he saw, looked up to thee, and smiled. ANTISTROPHE II. Where tripping light with wanton tread The Fairies marked the mazy green: While some the blighting cankers kill, And bless the tender plants from ill; Some drive the clamorous owl away, That nightly wonders at their play; Some pant in nobler war T'invade the hostile Rear-mice crew, And, sheathed in glittering arms of filmy dew, Their spears of thorn erect round Oberon's nutshell car. EPODE II. But oh! what sudden gloom, What horror overcasts the lowering day? How yawns that shagged cave, whose dreary womb Ne'er felt the genial sun's enlivening ray; Black, noisome, cheerless. Lo! how all around With feeble cries the gliding spectres throng! Hark, now I hear, with hollow, tremulous sound, The solemn mutter'd spell, and horrid magic song! Save me! What wither'd forms my soul affright? By the pale light Of yon blue fire I know their scowling fronts, their wild attire. See! thro' the glimmering darkness of the cave, By Padoke warned, their rites they sing, And slowly walk in dismal ring Around the charmed cauldron's bubbling wave. STROPHE III. What howling whirlwinds rend the sky! How shakes that ivy-mantled tower! The conscious sun turns back his eye, And nature trembling owns their power. For whom, at yonder livid flame, Do ye the deed without a name, Ye secret hags? Whence breathes this sound? Why sinks that cauldron in the ground? Why do these thunders roll? Tell me what means that armed Head? Why comes that bloody Child?—The hags are fled! They vanished into air.—Amazement wrung my soul! ANTISTROPHE III. Whither, ye beldames, do ye roam? Love ye wild Lapland's Gothic night? None now shall tread that cavern's gloom, Nor spy your dreadful mystic rite: None now shall see in yonder plain The gambols of Titania's train. No more the elves, with printless pace, The ocean's ebbing waters chase, Or fly the swelling tide: Nor over the wide-watered shore Sit listening to the curfew's sullen roar; Nor, nightly, mushrooms make along the mountain's side. EPODE III. Ariel! who sees thee now Upon the bat's wing sail along the sky? Who sees thee sit upon the blossomed bough, Bask on the rose, or in the cowslip lie? No more shalt thou upon the sharp North run, Or pierce into the earth, or tread the main; No more with clouds bedim the mid-day sun, Or fire the angry bolts, or pour the rattling rain. For who can wield like Shakespear's skilful hand That magic wand, Whose potent sway The Elves of Earth and Air and Sea obey? Yet, Fancy! once again on Britain smile; Yet choose some favorite son again, O'er all thy boundless realms to reign: Oh! give another Shakespear to our Isle. Elegy on the Death of a Father. Written at the age of 16. We must submit—Why then with grief opprest? Why sinks my soul beneath her load of woe? The voice of wisdom cannot calm this breast, Nor dry those tears which nature bids to flow. All-fost'ring sun! vain is thy genial power; Thou shinest but for him from sorrow free. In vain spring paints each blooming fragrant flower, Their bloom, their fragrance, all is lost to me. Ye dear companions of my sports, with you How late I mixed, as thoughtless and as gay. Vain sports that charmed my happier hours, adieu! Adieu, ye fields, where once I loved to stray! Ah me! Then all was joy. Yon echoing mead Beheld me foremost of the youthful train: Each pleasing toil yon hill beheld me lead; When, when, blest days, will ye return again? I now must weep among the lonely woods, Which ne'er the hateful eye of day pervades; Where, sadly, silent melancholy broods, “Breathing a browner horror on the shades.” Oh! may no foot intruding mark this place! Leave me unseen, unpitied, here to mourn! For he is lost to a young orphan race! O heavy, heavy loss! O race forlorn! Thou best of fathers! Where ah! where was I When on thee fell the ruthless arm of death? Why, why, did heaven this little boon deny; Thine eyes to close, and catch thy struggling breath? Why did I not embrace thy limbs, yet warm, And follow with slow steps thy mournful bier? Why did I not the last sad rites perform, And o'er thy grave indulge the pious tear? Hadst thou no parting kind farewell to give, When o'er thy face a wife distracted hung? Hadst thou no blessing on thy race to leave? Cruel disease! Why didst thou chain his tongue? Cruel disease! and am I left behind? Why do I call on thee, O Death, in vain? What is life now? What can this aching mind Of joy or solace feel? All here is pain. When, absent long, with many a fond caress My raptured mother smiles away her care; When round with eager love my brothers press; How shall I meet that love? Thou art not there. In vain round every scene my eyes I roll, Scenes that could once wake transport in my heart; They but recall thy image to my soul, While from my eyes the tears unbidden start. No more can Bath with all her treasures charm; No more the waving fields, the verdant lawn, The distant lowing herd, the sheltered farm One cheerful thought can raise: for thou art gone. In serious converse joined, the mountain path (Where feed the woolly flocks) full oft we wore; And, as we trod the flowery vale beneath, Thy tongue oft formed my mind to virtue's lore. And art thou dead? Who shall direct my youth? Who my rash feet from pleasure's snares defend? Who shall point out the steady paths of Truth? Like thee, my Guide, my Guardian, Father, Friend! And art thou dead? Oh! to what friend sincere Shall thy defenceless orphan children fly? Who shall protect them? Who shall wipe the tear That streams incessant from affliction's eye? To Thee alone we look, thou Sire of all! 'Tis thine to shield the helpless orphan's head: 'Tis thine to listen to affliction's call, And on our wounds the balm of comfort shed To Myself. Written in a melancholy mood on my 18th birthday. O'ercome by grief's oppressive weight My soul in anguish lies; Lamenting follies past, too late She breathes these hopeless sighs. But what avails the pensive hour, The nurse of secret woe? O'er moments gone no tears have pow'r, To bid them backward flow. Then let not care's corrosive smart Upon my vitals prey; Infusing poison in that heart, So blythe erewhile and gay. Too gay alas! for my repose; Thence spring what I endure; Sad thoughts of unavailing woes, Which time alone can cure. Yes! Time shall bid these streaming tears, These struggling murmurs, cease; Shall dissipate my doubts and fears, And all again be peace. How have I wasted eighteen years! For now I must reflect; Alas! the dreary space appears One blank of long neglect. Farewell to vain and empty mirth! Ye giddy flights, adieu! Since noise and folly gave you birth I'll think no more of you. Come Resignation, meek eyed maid! Thy soothing influence lend To one who now implores thy aid His weakness to befriend. But whence this change? Why is my heart With sudden grief opprest? Why do these new objections start? These doubts again molest? My wonted pleasures please no more; They aggravate my pain: From books, which charmed me so before, I seek relief in vain. From thought I fly:—for much I fear To know whence this proceeds; That why, tho' I so gay appear, My heart in secret bleeds. Then rest, my griefs:—alone display'd To that All-seeing mind Who knows the creature which He made, And dooms in justice kind. To Miss Allen. 1775. As the pure sentimental platonical friend, To his Platonist mistress his picture may send, And not give the most rigid old damsel a handle, From thence on their friendship to throw any scandal; Tho' I've well weighed the matter, I cannot as yet see, Any reason why I should not send mine to Betsy. Yet think not I mean to a painter to sit, With my elbows trussed down like a goose for the spit; Or, in languishing style with my head o'er one shoulder, Be drawn sweetly smirking at every beholder. In my own way of painting, in plain black and white, With my pen for a pencil, my picture I'll write, And since my face, mien, and in short my whole person, Is scarce worth the wasting such excellent verse on, This sketch of myself, to the traits of my mind, Tho' perhaps scarce more lovely, shall all be confined. My mind then resembles the month I was born in, As changeable just as an April fine morning; One moment with clouds on a sudden o'ercast, The next 'tis all sunshine, the tempest is past. In my studies too carrying the very same farce on, One half a physician and one half a parson. Each scheme that in prospect so charms for a time, I give up to jingle the sheep-bells of rhyme: Then lazily sport in such trifles as these, And have vanity too to conceive they may please. To politeness attached, though disqualified quite, By my freedom of temper, from being polite, Whatever occurs at the moment I say, So perhaps contradict myself ten times a day. With parts so capacious, they render me idle, In all wanting more of the spur than the bridle. I have sense some few faults of my own to detect, Without resolution those faults to correct. Thus am I this weak, vain, soft fickle creature, With indolence still the predominant feature. But lest you should think, in thus reading my picture, That I've too plainly dealt with myself in this stricture, E'en touch up the beauties you chance to discover, Throw in some new lights, and varnish all over. It may then perhaps serve as a match for your own: Or stay;—you had best let these touches alone; Its shades, as they are, will improve to the view, The lights that must shine thro' each copy of you! On going to Oxford. Adieu, O ye thoughtless gay train! That tread pleasure's flowery path, Where sloth, idly busy, in vain Ever seeks fresh enjoyments at Bath. Adieu! That from you I retire, No tear shall swell into my eye; Nor, pining with hopeless desire, For your joys shall I heave one loud sigh. Adieu, O ye seats still so loved! Dear scenes of my childhood, adieu! Ye vales, too, where happy I roved, Ere the sharpness of sorrow I knew! No more on his willowy shore Avon sees me lone-wandering at eve; Avon hears me deep-musing no more;— These meads, and these plains, I must leave. Hark! Isis now calls me away; “Haste! spurn these soft pleasures,” she cries; “Oh! why dost thou fondly delay? “Oh! why turn so often thine eyes? “Amid the bright circle to shine, “Each varying fashion to guide, “To warm the fair breast is not thine; “Haste, spurn these soft pleasures aside. “If yet the green mead can delight; “If Philomel sweetly can sing; “If the distant stream glittering bright “Amid the gay landscape of spring; “Or the spires, that high-bosom'd in trees “Reflect the sloped sun's golden ray, “Have yet aught of beauty to please; “O haste, to my banks haste away. “Say, where smile the meadows more green? “Where does Philomel warble more sweet? “What stream rolls more pure through a scene “Where Spring's various treasures so meet? “O say what can Avon compare “To the towers that crown my proud side? “Or when did the muses sport there? “When deigned Phœbus to bathe in his tide? “Erewhile thou to Phœbus wast dear “When Itchin was calmed by thy strains; “And fondly I deemed I should hear “Thy pipe echoing shrill through my plains. “Go, Corydon, throw that pipe down; “Thy lips now no longer it breathes: “Go, Corydon, pluck off that crown; “Those laurels ill brook pleasure's wreaths.” Oh Isis! thy taunts are in vain; Far other cares tear my sad heart! Nor can Phœbus e'er soothe my fix'd pain:— Ah me! love but laughs at his art. In vain nature pours o'er the ground Her beauties,—no beauties to me; If, wherever I roll them around, These eyes can no Maryanne see. Sonnet, Addressed to a friend, A. B., and candidate for a fellowship in one of the Universities. That hood, so late your wish, in monkish beauty Flows from your shoulders now long, black, and furry. Were you but Fellow then!—yet why this hurry? Before you stand, read this, and learn your duty. Learn, if untufted wit and worth salute you, To frown impatience while they cap and sir ye: With titled Vice and Folly favour curry, Nor blush if ill your awkward flattery suit ye: Sin you: but tolerate no younger sinner: Teach them to rise, be sober and grow clever; Snore you till noon, and every night be mellow: Pray seldom; then be last; be first at dinner: Walk, ride, and dress; read sometimes, study never. This will you swear? Enough: admit him Fellow. Epigrams from the Greek. On marble tombs let no rich essence flow, No chaplet bloom, no lamp suspended glow; Vain cost! while yet I live, these honours pay: Wine can but moisten ashes into clay. Mindful of many a tear and many a sigh, My prudent heart from Anna bids me fly: In vain! too weak my resolution proves: This prudent heart, that gravely bids me,—loves. His shafts, the terror of the skies, No more the god of Love discover; Now from fair Anna's azure eyes With surer aim they wound the lover. For Venus he mistook the maid, And laughing, ran his arms to give her: The bow she bent; her skill essay'd; And emptied at my heart the quiver. If a kiss so offend you, dear maid! And to punish the insult you burn; Let affront with affront be repaid, And kiss me ten times in return. On a Beautiful Bath at Smyrna. The Graces, bathing on a day, Love stole their robes and ran away; So naked here they since have been, Ashamed in daylight to be seen. From the Greek of Julian, PREFECT OF EGYPT As a garland once I made, In a bed of roses laid Love I found; with eager joy, By the wings I seized the boy; Crowning then an ample cup, In a bumper drank him up. Now along my veins he swims, Fluttering, tickling, through my limbs. What, whence, am I? why came I? but to go. Where all is doubt, how little can I know? From nothing I began; in nothing I Again shall end. Man is but vanity. Come live then, while you live. A bumper fill. This cordial is a cure for every ill. Epigrams from the Greek. Blest he who sees; who hears thee, trebly blest; Thy kiss is Paradise: and Heaven the rest. To make the boy a scholar, to my care An advertising Doctor gave his heir. We got to Homer; and “that wrath, the spring “Of woes unnumbered,” soon he learnt to sing; Then in due course “To Pluto's gloomy reign “Hurl'd many a gallant soul untimely slain.” But now he came no longer. In the street It shortly was my luck the sire to meet: And “Thanks, my friend,” he cried, “but, to be free, “What you were teaching he may learn of me. “I, ere their time, hurl many a soul below; “Yet not one word of Homer need to know.” Hymn. TO HARMODIUS AND ARISTOGEITON. With myrtle will I braid my sword; Such as the brave Harmodius bore, When Athens hailed her rights restored, And proud Hipparchus was no more. Nor art thou, dear Harmodius, dead! Thine are the islands of the blest; Where heroes old, stout Diomed, And the swift son of Peleus, rest. My sword with myrtle will I braid, Such as Aristogeiton bore; When, at Minerva's shrine, the blade Dropped with the victim-tyrant's gore. Dear patriot pair! your fame shall bloom Immortal in the poet's strain; Who, by the tyrant's righteous doom, Bade Athens flourish free again. On the Death of Heliodora. (From the Greek of Meleager). These tears be thine, O lost in early bloom! (All, all that now affection can bestow.) Tears wept in anguish; o'er thy honour'd tomb Love, in fond memory, pours the stream of woe. Yes, my dead Heliodora, ever dear! Long, long for thee shall Meleager grieve: Still shall thy shade, while yet he lingers here, These empty gifts to Acheron receive. Ah! where is now my lovely blossom? Torn, By Death untimely torn, in dust to fade: But this fair flower, which all admire and mourn, O Earth fold softly, in thy bosom laid! Translations. Italian Sonnets of Milton III. [As duly, when chill evening darkens round] As duly, when chill evening darkens round, O'er the wild uplands the young shepherd fair Fond hies, some beauteous plant to foster there, Some stranger plant, that, ill, with blossoms crown'd, Pines for it's native suns and mother-ground. So on my tongue fond Love, with fostering care, Wakes the strange flow'rs of many a Tuscan air, While thee, O nobly graceful, I resound In lays of words to British ears unknown, And change fair Thamis for fair Arno's plain. Love will'd it so, and well my strains have shewn, Tun'd to new laws, that Love wills not in vain. Ah! could this breast be cold, this heart be slow, To him who plants the joys of heav'n below. IV. [Charles, I will tell, though wondering while I speak] Charles, I will tell, though wondering while I speak, How I, who Love rebellious wont to scorn, And mock his bonds as but by cowards worn, Am caught, where wiser have been caught as weak. Yet not or tress of gold, or vermeil cheek, Me dazzled so: less vulgar charms adorn My wondrous maid, to bless the lover born; A decent state, a brow whence mildly break The beams serene of amiable black, A speech with not one language only grac'd, A song, whose magic from her airy track Might sweetly force the labouring moon to haste, And eyes, whose glances such keen light'ning dart, In vain our ears we seal to guard the heart. V. [A simple youth, a lover little tried] A simple youth, a lover little tried In lover's arts, irresolute to fly, His heart, O Lady, brings thee: nor deny, As light, the gift. This heart shall still abide, True, constant, firm, with presence still supplied, Generous of sentiment, and good: from high When roars the vast, and lightnings fire the sky, In adamant self-arm'd on every side: As safe from envy, and each hope, each fear Of vulgar souls, and far o'er Fortune plac'd, So with the muse, and lyre of sacred sound With genius and with worth superior grac'd; One part alone there weaker will appear, Where Love infix'd th'immedicable wound. The Smile. (From the Italian of Chiabrera.) Beauteous Roses, not with morn From the thorn Scattering sweet but transient pleasures; You, whom round the lips display'd, Love has made Guardians of his pearly treasures! Dear to Love, sweet Roses! tell, If I dwell, Fondly those bright eyes beholding; As I gaze, and gazing sigh, Tell me why You expand in smiles unfolding? Conscious, I could ill sustain Your disdain, Seek you thus my life to cherish? Is it that you feel delight In the sight Of the pangs by which I perish? Beauteous Roses, be your joy To destroy Or to save, since thus you show it; Still will I in novel lays Sing your praise, But oh! smile upon your Poet. If at dayspring, as we pass Through the grass, Murmur rills and whisper breezes; If, with flowers the mead looks gay, Sooth'd we say, How the smiling landscape pleases! When his foot blithe zephyr laves In the waves, That with gently-gliding motion Hardly rippling on the sand, Kiss the strand; See, we cry, how smiles the ocean! Veil'd in gold and round her hair Lilies there, Here each blushing blossom piling, If, on wheels of sapphire drawn, Mounts the dawn; Lo! we say, the sky how smiling! True, in mighty Nature's mirth, Heaven and earth Deck with smiles their jocund faces; True, they smile; but, smiling so, Cannot show Half your soul-enchanting graces! The Frown. (From the Italian of Chiabrera.) When with soft and winning air Comes my fair, By her guard of Loves surrounded; And a smile benignly bright, Beams delight On the heart which they have wounded; Such the charms which she displays, All who gaze Wish her ever thus alluring; Nor again dare hope to meet Sight so sweet, Spite of Love himself assuring. But the pearls, whose lucid hue Wonder drew, If in serious mood she closes; And the look, that gaily glanc'd, As entranc'd In reflected thought composes; Suddenly behold we now On her brow Pride enthroned in awful beauty. Pride? ah no!—but where, my Muse Wilt thou chuse Words to satisfy thy duty? When abroad on orient wings Eurus springs O'er the summer seas to revel, And their feet in rapid race Print their trace Where he skims the watery level; Curling waves with murmuring sound Form around; Yet no storm of wrath collected Speaks that sound, the sign but shows Ocean knows How to make her power respected! Thus we on that brow discern, Sweetly stern, Terrors which no pain occasion: 'Tis not anger that is shown; 'Tis alone Beauty daunting bold invasion: And that gentle look severe Charms endear So transporting to the lover, Not one thought he more employs On the joys Which her beauteous smiles discover! Sonnet. ON THE DIVINE PROVIDENCE. (From the Italian of Filicaja.) As some fond mother views her infant race, With tender love o'erflowing while she sees, She kisses one, one clasps in her embrace, Her feet supporting one, and one her knees; Then, as the winning gesture, speaking face, Or plaintive cry explain their different pleas, A look, a word, she deals with various grace, And smiles, or frowns, as Love alone decrees. O'er man, frail kind, so Providence Divine Still watches; hears, sustains, and succours all, With equal eye beholding each that lives. If Heaven denies, oh! let not man repine! Heaven but denies to quicken duty's call, Or feigning to deny, more largely gives. The Tenth Epistle of the First Book of Horace Imitated. To you, who think St. James's stairs The way to happiness—not cares, One, whom retirement pleases better, Sends his best wishes with this letter. Like, as two eggs, the one to t'other's, Our souls would, if not twins, seem brothers: But that our taste here disagrees; You love a bustle,—I love ease. Yes! form'd upon the sober plan, I'm never so much my own man As when to rural peace and leisure I fly from all which you call pleasure. Be yours your bustle, smoke and noise; Be mine far simpler, soberer joys: At morn, at eve, secure to rove, Or tread at noon the upland grove. Thence view the verdant vales around, The hills with waving corn embrown'd, The streams, that, dancing as they run, Glitter beneath the chequering sun, While here and there a bosom'd grange Completes the beauteous interchange. If, as they tell us in the Schools, We ought to live by nature's rules, Where would you build? What properer ground, Than the sweet country can be found? There Pleasure has not learnt the way With Judas' kisses to betray; And Health—in town a very prude, By rule and method to be woo'd— There runs herself into your arms; A hoyden, liberal of her charms. Where is that self-tormentor, Spleen, In dull November's gloom less seen? Where breathes a purer breeze t'assuage The fiery dog's enfevering rage? Where are you safer from the heap Of Macbeth cares that “murder sleep”? What Persian carpet can exceed The velvet of a flowery mead? What couch can be so soft, but moss May very well supply that loss? Though gentle gales through London streets Whisper from whom they stole their sweets, Has Warren's warehouse one perfume Superior to a bean in bloom? Can Cælia's crimson cheek disclose A softer blush than paints the rose? Can the mix'd blaze of gems surpass The dewdrop sparkling in the grass? Can any water be so clear, So pleasing to the pensive ear, When hissing through the bursting lead, As rippling down its pebbly bed? Indeed amidst your squares one sees, A few poor straggling scrubbed trees, That nodding seem to ask each other In whispers, “How came we here, brother?” Or gardens, plots of grass, or basons Scoop'd in burlesque of lakes by masons, Where, sleeping o'er a common sink, In state the happy mud-nymphs stink. Then if your garret window yields A yard of prospect to the fields, “Well, what a charming view! how pretty! “Here's quite the country in a city!” Thus Nature, use what force you will, Ejected, turns upon you still, Nor ceases, till, at length replac'd, She share at last the throne of Taste. Propertius. LIB. II., ELEG. VIII. Along the shore Pelides idly roved While regal force detained the maid he loved, No more could war no more could glory charm, To plaintive lyres he bent his strenuous arm; And wooed the tender muse in shady bowers, While Hector's flames consumed the Doric towers. The Greeks beheld through many an anxious tear, Degrading rust corrode the Pelian spear; And while his arms divine neglected lay, His bleeding country chid her hero's stay. He saw unmoved,—nor lent his friendly hand,— His loved Patroclus gasping on the sand, Unmoved great Hector's glorious deeds could view, For love prevailed o'er fame and friendship too. But when the fair was to his arms restored, Great Hector fell beneath his conquering sword, Again the Trojans saw his vengeful spear Their flying ranks confound, and thunder on their rear. Sonnet. [Thrice hath the sun his annual circle rolled] 1778. Thrice hath the sun his annual circle rolled And now is hastening to the goal again, Since Love within my bosom fixed his reign, And, joined by reason, lorded uncontrolled. Yet never dared my lips, too fondly bold, To speak what language can but ill explain; And if to conscious Heaven I breathed my pain, In faltering sounds the timorous wish I told. Ah! then in livelier signs than words exprest, In softly languid looks, and stealing sighs, Read, gentle maid, my tender woe confest. And Thou to whom is known, O Power all-wise, Each unborn purpose labouring in the breast, So hear my faltered vows, as pure they rise. Sonnet. WRITTEN AT MR. THISTLETHWAITE'S. 1779. Oh! sprung of virtuous and of gentle race! Sweet buds of infancy, whose secret roots Together spread their intermingled shoots, Tho' now ye branch dissever'd from th'embrace. As now the bloom unfolding on the face With glad presage my friendly muse salutes; So may your minds too blossom: may the fruits Of Wise and Good your riper season grace. Oh brothers! whom, as yet unborn, ye lay, Nature united! may no treacherous wiles Of foes divide you, no domestic strife. Strive only which shall best with love repay Her love, who fondly gazing on your smiles Forgets in joy the pangs that gave you life. Sonnet. WRITTEN AT NORMAN COURT (MR. THISTLETHWAITE'S). 1779. As Nature fondly viewed, with conscious pride, This airy brow with waving forests crowned, Th'expanse of varied green and hills that bound The rich domain, Mine be the praise! she cried. Not thine alone, my sister, Art replied; I clothed in livelier green the varied ground, And here with woods the circling vale embrowned, There spotted with thin shade the mountain side. Yes, Nature said, with thee that praise I share; But view these beauties where alone I reign, Where Art has added, and can add, no grace. Her haughty rival with th'insulting air Of mockery turned; but when upon the plain She saw Selina, blushing veiled her face. To a Lady. SENT WITH HAMMOND'S LOVE ELEGIES. Let costly presents win the fickle fair, Let heaps of wealth the sordid bosom move; To thee, my Marian, no such gifts I bear, I have no wealth, no treasure—but my love. Yet take (all I can give) these tender plaints That breathe from Hammond's sweetly mournful tongue; Such as, beyond what Fiction feebly paints, Nature inspires, and her Tibullus sung. Oft shalt thou steal to read in secret here, When from all else but love thy thoughts are free; Oft shalt thou drop the sympathising tear, And, while thou pitiest Hammond, think of me. Oft too, whilst I in sorrow waste my youth, A wretched exile, far from thee and bliss; Thou'lt kiss, perhaps, these pledges of my truth: O Heaven! that I could intercept that kiss! Oh! whilst on earth she bends her modest eye, That I could gaze upon those blushing cheeks! That I could, fixed in silent rapture by, Fondly devour each nectar'd word she speaks! O ineffectual vows! O cruel doom, From all my soul holds dear so soon to part! Meantime, perhaps, some lovelier youth may come, And drive me hopeless from my Marian's heart. Yet rest, too credulous heart! my Marian swears That none but I shall in her bosom reign; Farewell then! now farewell to all my cares! Farewell to love-lorn Hammond's plaintive strain. Sonnet. [Pulteney! the fourth young Spring now clothes the earth] Pulteney! the fourth young Spring now clothes the earth, Since my rude muse with laureate wreaths essayed To deck the sacred spot where he is laid, Who formed my genius, and who gave me birth. Yet o'er my gayest hours of social mirth Oft still his absence casts a sadd'ning shade: Oft still to him my secret tears are paid, While memory fondly dwells upon his worth. Hence mindful, who most shared his grateful love, By many an act of gen'rous kindness won, This page I mark, O Pulteney! with thy name: Happy, if so I draw thee to approve The pious gratitude which warms the son, Howe'er thy nicer taste the poet blame. Sonnet. [Ye gales, that gently soothe the smiling sky] Ye gales, that gently soothe the smiling sky, And, stealing from the flow'rs their nectar'd dews, In many a wanton blandishment diffuse The balmy shower of odours, as ye fly; Ye verdant vales, ye springs that murmur by, Fit haunts, which amorous sorrow well might choose. Who bade so oft your echoes to my muse? Each hope, each fear, that ruled the song, reply. Those conscious echoes I no more to tales Of tender woe shall wake: since o'er my mind Again firm reason holds her calm control. Yet, though no more to lonely grief resigned I wander here to weep, not less my soul This cool, these murmurs loves, and verdant vales. Odes. ODE I. ON THE APPROACH OF SPRING, 1777. Stern Winter not perpetual sounds The alarm that calls his hosts to war. Encircling blithe with frolic bounds The Sun's ascending car, Their tresses wreathed with budding flowers, Again advance the rosy Hours, That bade the timorous steps of Spring, Yet coy, her bosom to display, Tho' in fond dalliance round her way Young Zephyr wave his wing. O wayward daughter of the West! Whom, second from one parent source, Fair Spring in Albion bore, comprest By Winter's amorous force! April! if dimly on thy face The dawning smiles of Spring we trace. Yet many a tear still rising drowns In woe thine eyes of dewy light, Nor seldom on thy brow, now bright, Dark scowl thy father's frowns. And see, e'en now less powerful, stream Thro' scattered clouds the solar fires, Till faint and fainter every gleam Now whelm'd in night expires. Mute are the groves, save where in drops The shower sounds stilly on the tops: To heaven the patient heifers gaze; While idly, on his staff upstayed, The shepherd from yon hawthorn shade The increasing storm surveys. With him awhile my moral Muse Shall feed her melancholy mind, As wide the drear expanse she views, Then sighs for human kind. O Heir of misery! man! tho' fair, Through the thin mists of childhood's care Unvex't by every ruder blast, Thy morning shine, the sickly sun Of joy, ere half thy course be run, Shall sorrow overcast! But from yon oak, whose giant height, Lonely before the embattled shades, Towers in proud confidence of might, What transports wake the glades! The winds around his airy seat Unbridled rush, and tempests beat, The storm-bird there his song pursues: Secure that rosy-bosom'd May Shall soon bid gentler breezes play; Soon shed more genial dews. Not stern affliction's lifted scourge Can shake with fear the virtuous soul, Tho' black she sees the sweeping surge Of death around her roll. Unmoved amid the storms of Fate Virtue still holds her customed state; Save that, as o'er her anchor bent, Hope points to where the distant skies Gleam opening, on her cheek arise Meek smiles of calm content. Cease then, my Lyre! thy partial woes: Again bright breaking through his veil The sun a purer radiance throws; The groves his presence hail; The heifers bound; and o'er the meads His flock the whistling shepherd leads. Whate'er of anguish mortals know Heaven well permits; that so the breast Of Joy, from Memory doubly blest, With livelier sense may glow. ODE II. [Why doubts thy foot, too timorous maid] The metre of this ode is similar to that of the fourth, with this difference only, that this is of the kind, which, to borrow the language of ancient prosody, we may call Iambic; the other is Trochaic. Why doubts thy foot, too timorous maid, T'explore this shade? To bowers, deep-bosom'd in the centre Of this o'er-arching gloom from sight, The paths invite That here in devious labyrinths enter. There freely fond caresses play, While coy delay Feigns from their search desire to cover; And bold-eyed sports, and arch-eyed wiles, Which mock the smiles Ill-masked in mimic anger, hover: There pointing now, where blind and mute The branches shoot, Now beckoning laugh's secure occasion; Thither if any curious rove, The sounding grove Gives early signal of the invasion: There, when bright noon inflames the day, The dubious ray But half reveals, in dim illusion, The rudely-rising breast, and cheek Where blushes speak Wild passion awed by soft confusion. And now still Evening holds again Her sober reign, Her dusky banners widely spreading; And now serenely beams above The star of Love, Sweet influence thro' the silent shedding. Yes! Delia feels, O sacred hour, Thy tender power; Beneath the vaulted verdure lying; Her eyes that with moist languor shine She lifts to mine, Then sinks upon my bosom sighing. Hence, Evening, oft my grateful muse Thy name shall chuse To grace her gently falling measures But when thy bounty too, O Night, Shall she requite In songs more glowing, like thy pleasures? ODE III. [The sabler shades of night prevailing] The sabler shades of night prevailing, Ungenial fall the dews and chilly: And now with hollow murmur wailing, Now wildly shriek the blasts, and shrilly: High then pile the flame and higher; Wake to social joy the lyre; And with cups to beauty crowned Warm the loitering pulse to bound. Wandering in lonely woe, the lover Moans to the conscious moon his story, Whose orb the driving clouds discover In dreary gleams of sickly glory. Me, where festal tapers shine, Eloquence that glows with wine, Eyes that speak, and looks that dare, Me more please,—and more the fair. Now gusty beats the shower descending, Now drops in tears of sober sorrow, Thus o'er our joys may storms impending In various ruin rush ere morrow. Let the morrow frown or lour, Fate indulgent gives this hour. Wise then, what ye may, secure: Pleasures past alone are sure. ODE IV. INVOCATION OF THE ZEPHYRS. Ye, before whose genial breath Hovering Death, Girt with troops of pale diseases, Quits th'usurp'd domain of air; Where, oh! where, Linger ye, propitious breezes? Hither, where my languid maid Wooes your aid, Come, with balmy spirit blowing; Gentle harbingers of Spring, Hither bring Health in rosy beauty glowing. Bright-eyed Joy to Youth allied At her side, While with giddy gesture after Trip gay sport of wilder glance, Jest, and Dance, Dimpled Smiles, and sleek-browed Laughter. Joy-born Mirth shall lead the train, Soon again Her each sprightlier Love shall follow; All who from the brow defy, All who lie In the dimple's treacherous hollow. So my song your praise shall tell; So my shell Pour to you the liquid measures; Soft, as when your downy wings Fan the strings, Murmuring sweetly pensive pleasures. Ah! no such reward ye seek O'er that cheek, Blushing if she meets my gazes; O'er those beaming orbs of love, Free to rove, Little ye regard my praises. Yet, if to my sober ear Ever dear Sound your voices, sadly sighing, Where from lonely shades my grief Courts relief, To your airy woe replying: As in fondly frolic-play, Boldly gay, Thus around her charms ye hover, Oh! in whisper'd sighs reveal What I feel, What to you alone discover. ODE V. TO A YOUNG LADY ON HER ATTAINING HER 21st YEAR. The dawn, from whose auspicious light Her flowing years my Laura numbers, Now glows in ruddy beauty bright. Awake, my lyre! thy debt to pay, Prevent the day, O sunk in long-inglorious slumbers! So may the approaching maid be won To smile, and emulate the morning; For half-discovered now, the sun Scatters around his jocund beams, With golden gleams Yon airy waving pines adorning. But o'er his orb what shadowy grace That amber-skirted cloud diffuses! So let awhile thy lovelier face The gloom of not unpleasing care, O Laura! wear: The moral wisdom of the muses. This hour demands. In flattering charms Comes Liberty, by Love attended. But yet alert with just alarms Behold them in this anxious hour, Where ends the power That held thy doubtful choice suspended. Dangerous is Beauty! Her, while new, We court with many a fond profession; And self-deceived, may think them true. Yet hope not, if no purer fire Refine desire, That love will grow beyond possession. In glittering hues, to dazzle youth, Opinion paints the untried condition: But Time shall sober into truth Her gaudy coloring. He shall show What specious woe Heaven well denied to thy petition. Or, if sincere his faith remain, Whom long, his country's call obeying, Far distant climes from thee detain; Time, when thy wanderer he hath tried, To thee shall guide, With joy, tho' late, thy grief o'erpaying. Nor be the white-wing'd minute long! Then, Laura, with glad zeal officious, Again the matin lark my song Shall join, to hail in livelier lay The auspicious day, Above this sacred light auspicious. ODE VI. TO A YOUNG LADY. (The metre of this little Ode is borrowed from Chaulieu.) Why thus decline my troubled eyes? Whither their mild lustre bending, Those azure orbs to meet me rise? Why thus, with thee conversing, dies My voice in broken murmurs ending? Yet dawning from my looks distrest, Yet wooing in the coy expression Of faltering sounds, that, half supprest, In sighs ill-stifled breathe the rest, Read, ah! too dear, the fond confession. In vain!—What these soft tumults show From thee yet new to love is hidden, Untaught thy wishes yet to know, If sighs ascend, if blushes glow, What means the sigh, the blush unbidden? But hope not, ever thus secure, To dart thy wildly wandering glances: How fated soon in charms mature, What others feel for thee, t'endure, On hasty wing thy youth advances. O skilled in every lovelier art, That adds a polished grace to beauty! Be mine the pleasing cares to impart That best refine the gentle heart; Be mine to teach the tender duty. ODE VII. To Fancy. A PRIZE AT LADY MILLAR'S. O thou whose empire unconfined Rules all the busy realms of mind, The slow-eyed cares thy mild dominion Confess;—if thou thy rod extend, No more the sharp-fanged sorrows rend, While hovering round on frolic pinion The laughing train of Joys descend. To soothe the woes of absent Love, Come, Fancy, now what time above The full-orb'd moon, that rose all glowing, Begins her lifted lamp to pale; What time, to charm the listening vale, In liquid measures fondly flowing, Laments the enamoured nightingale. In softly-pleasing light the Queen Of heaven arrays the blue serene; Yet lovelier beams the gentle glory In Anna's azure eyes displayed. Sweet is the Poet of the shade, Yet sweeter than his warbled story. Each sound from Anna's lips conveyed. Nor haply shall I ever find That tongue to me alone unkind, On every grief but mine so ready To bid the balm of comfort flow; Nor shall that eye, which every woe But mine can melt, thus ever steady, To me alone no pity shew. Like mine, her bosom now can feel The tender melancholy steal, Tho' maiden modesty dissemble; And now while memory brings again The muse that first revealed my pain, The involuntary tear may tremble, And own the triumph of the strain. So whispers Hope. By Fancy led She comes. With rosy wreaths her head, With rosy wreaths her sacred anchor, Love intertwines in vain employ: For lo! behind the exulting boy, With stifled smiles of patient rancour, Creeps Mockery, watchful to destroy. Ah! still, tho' whispered to deceive, Thy flatteries, Hope, let me believe; Content from grief one hour to borrow: Ah! still, if round my distant way, As thro' the path of life I stray, Hang gathering clouds of future sorrow; O Fancy! gild them with thy ray. ODE VIII. [Till graver years, O wisdom, stay!] Till graver years, O wisdom, stay! Awhile delay Thy sober lessons: come not hither. Too soon alas! each pleasure cloys; Our budding joys Let not thy frozen aspect wither. Now half a rebel to thy cause, Thy sacred laws, As too severe my heart accuses; And now I chide the preaching sage Whose cautious age To Youth it's lawful joys refuses. No more, O Wisdom, haunt these plains, Where Pleasure reigns; But let me careless of the morrow, Still linger in her flowery road And sweet abode, Unconscious of impending sorrow. Soon reason cries,—Mistaken youth, This holy truth In Fate's eternal law is written: Ne'er shall the wreath of fair renown His temples crown Whom these fantastic joys have smitten. His feeble mind shall ne'er explore The sacred store Of science, who, dissolved in pleasures, With sluggish hand the page unrolls: For nobler souls Her bright reward the goddess treasures. Farewell the gay convivial scene! And ye fair train, With wanton smile my glances wooing; O if I pass in silence by, Nor meet the eye That sweetly tempts me to my ruin, Forgive the wrong: for many a throe My heart will know Ere I can calmly slight your favour; And oft, averse to wisdom's laws, Between her cause And yours my treacherous heart shall waver. Song. [Love! I am thy slave confest!] Love! I am thy slave confest! Pardon thou the wild opinion Which my frantic mind possest: O forgive the foolish breast That abjured thy just dominion. Once indeed I fondly thought Love grown weaker, reason stronger; But experience I have bought, Me my folly Chloe taught; And alas! I boast no longer Beauty I can calmly view, And defy the charming treason; Wit alone I promise too Never shall my heart subdue, Nor deceive my watchful reason. But when wit and beauty blend In a fair so good and tender, How shall I myself defend? To thine altar, Love, I bend, And my vanquished heart surrender. Elegy. [Now sunk in dumb despondence on the thorn] Now sunk in dumb despondence on the thorn, Where, nightly perch'd, she pours her solemn lay, Sad Philomel beholds the gradual morn Bright and yet brighter kindle into day. Sweet child of sorrow! With regret, like thine, I too the gold, which skirts the dapple, see: No joy the gleams, that now more ruddy shine, Dear as the joys that fly them, bring to me. Yet then again, ye slumbers, on mine eyes Descending soothe my troubled soul to rest; And yet again, ye pleasing visions, rise, In all my Delia's gentle graces drest. And tho' through every semblance ye can range, Well might ye choose my Delia's form to wear; Secure that to no lovelier ye can change, No mien more winning, and no face more fair. In vain I call! Obedient to my will No visions rise, no slumbers o'er me creep; And now in glory from yon Eastern hill The sun ascending bids me wake to weep. Ah gentle Sun! So will I bless thy beams, Though thy return but grief returning brings: With cautious reverence steal, where hovering dreams O'er Delia's pillow wave their busy wings. Oh! could I stand with trembling duty nigh To guard, and guarding gaze upon the maid! No ruder ray should dare intrude, no fly In murmuring error her repose invade. And if, while thus I gazed upon her cheek, One smile of haughty scorn should haply dawn; And if one amorous sigh should haply break, Deep from the involuntary bosom drawn; Now, would I cry, she proudly deigns to smile, While at her feet I seem my suit to press; Now ill concealed by many a female wile Her mutual flame these amorous sighs confess. And can I so the flattering tale believe, Which Hope, too ready, whispers in mine ear, And can I so this simple heart deceive, That still my Delia holds thy memory dear? She now can wander in the conscious grove, Nor think how there I wandered by her side; In dreams her fancy now can freely rove, Nor hear me talk, nor see my shadow glide. Yet be she false; her falsehood shall but show How fixed the firm foundation of my truth; For her alone I nurse perpetual woe; For her in silence drooping waste my youth. For here, when lingering through the extended plains Their hurried train the waves of Isis wreathe, The tuneful sorrows of these tender strains With many a hope, and many a fear, I breathe. And oft the while my head, in grief declined, Wistful I raise to watch the journeying sun; Sigh as I mark the distance yet behind, And bid his westering wheels more swiftly run. Then, fondly kind, in visionary charms Propitious night my Delia may restore; Then I again may fold her in these arms; O! be the vision true!—I ask no more. Fragment. [Father of being, who, before all time] Father of being, who, before all time, Of happiness immutable Thyself Within Thyself possest, yet with Thy Son, The eternal Reason, counselling in time, By that efficient cause, the Third, from both Proceeding, mad'st whatever lives below, Each in his kind, of thy great attribute His due degree to enjoy; when, gracious God! When shall this exile of her native heaven, Imprison'd in this mortal, with blind search No longer trace, through matter dimly seen, Those forms original, which dwelt in Thee From the beginning; but with piercing glance Catch universal beauty to the view At once in all her various charms displayed? When shall this Soul, of Thee derived, to Thee Again united, from Thy presence drink In beatific vision perfect joy Surpassing human thought? But Thou, Supreme, Hast placed me here, with natures like my own Surrounded, that, while gladly to their wants I minister, by giving I may gain That happiness, which I from Thee, O Just As bountiful! solicit. Connal and Crimora. From the Erse Language, versified from a prose translation.) Now Autumn clouds the face of day; With rising mists the hills are grey; The winds conflicting howl around, While the dark stream, with thundering sound Rolling thro' the narrow plain, Pours its rapid tide amain. There yon lone tree, with spreading shade, Marks the sad spot where Connal's laid. Oft when the bleak winds loudly blow The whirling leaves his grave bestrew: Oft, as with solitary pace The musing hunter leaves the chase, He starts to see with feeble cry The airy forms glide swiftly by. Come, Connal! come, in all thy might, Clad in thy wonted arms of light! Thou to Crimora o'er thy tomb (So breaks the moon thro' midnight's gloom) In all thy beauty shine confest, Thy golden locks, thy snowy breast. Illustrious warrior! who shall trace The triumphs of thy war-worn race? Long grew thy house; like some tall oak, The pride of Morven's wood-crowned rock; Uninjured long the blast it meets, Around its head the tempest beats, Long beats in vain,—but now o'ercome It bows, it falls, in Connal's tomb. Who now, with Connal's courage steeled, Shall lead us to the embattled field? Here fierce war blew its loud alarms Mid dying groans and clashing arms: Here, mightiest of the mighty slain, O Connal! thou didst press the plain. Thy lifted arm in tempests fell; Like lightning blaz'd thy angry steel; High as a rock thy stature rose; Thine eyes shot flames amid thy foes; Loud as when hoarse waves lash the shore Thy voice inflamed the battle's roar; And where thou turnedst on the heath Warriors resistless sank in death: As when some boy in wanton play Lops the tall thistle's stalk away. With fury Dargo's bosom glowed, Dark as a storm he onward strode: His hollow eyes he threw around, Then full on Connal bent, and frowned. High-waved their bickering falchions flashed, While loud the pierced hauberk crashed. But lo! amid the thickest fight, Sheathed in old Rinval's arms of light, Crimora stood: her hair behind Loose floated on the heaving wind; A bow she bore; with decent pride A quiver rattled at her side: Thus, like some warlike youth arrayed, By Connal fought the lovely maid; And now on Dargo's breast she drew With erring hand the faithless yew; Unhappy love! the fatal dart Stood quivering in her Connal's heart. What shall she do? his swimming eyes Are closed! he faints! her Connal dies! Wildly she roams the desert hill, And weeps, and calls on Connal still; Till, spent with grief, she faintly sighed Her Connal's name;—then bowed and died. Here, in thy lap, O Earth, is laid The bravest youth, the loveliest maid. Tho' now the creeping moss hath grown Around their monumental stone; While softly sighs the passing wind, Their memory rushes on my mind. Unhappy pair! yet here ye rest; Here none your lonely tomb molest. A Fragment, WRITTEN AT BEACONSFIELD BEFORE MR. BURKE'S DEATH. 1797. Yes! down this grassy bank as now I stray, Beneath these oaks as now I bend my way, Where'er I turn, familiar to my eyes The lawn expands, woods wave, and uplands rise. Thy church, sweet Penn! in simple beauty plain, That from yon brow beholds this fair domain, More widely looking on the distant side, Where Thames in mazes rolls his wandering tide; The beechen shades, that stretch along the hill, Sweep down the slope, and half the valley fill; The scattered cottages, that here and there Skirt the green spot, yet sacred from the share; The neighboring grange, which through the trees I catch, Bright in the splendors of the recent thatch; These sheep close nibbling, and the youthful steed, That round his mother, sporting, tries his speed; Those sober herds that ruminate reclined, Or, grazing slowly, thro' the pasture wind, While some retired, the sultry day to cool, Seek in that bushy dell the limpid pool; These groves of verdure rich in various hues, Whose walks of pleasing gloom invite to muse, Where bordering shrubs, and sheltered seats imply, To Fancy's curious search, the mansion nigh; And here the thickened mass of darker green, Where the tall pines that well-placed mansion screen, All I remember:—still in all I trace The charms that smiled before on Nature's face. All I remember:—where content I found, Pleased with each rural sight, each rural sound. Yet not within the same emotions spring. To me no more these scenes familiar bring The joy which here I knew in happier years: The smiles of Nature but provoke my tears. In every bush, at each green alley's end, I see the form of some departed friend: If Zephyr fan the leaves, in every breath I hear some voice, for ever mute in death. Alas! though drenched in dews from Lethe's lake The Memory sleep, if Sorrow bid her wake, How exquisite in torture, she employs Alike her hoard of miseries and joys! How present grief revives long-buried woes! From what past trifles new-born anguish grows! Nothing so light, that played around the heart, But, like the feather, deeper drives the dart. There, on that hillock, where, with whirling sails, The busy mill collects the passing gales, As now I cast my pensive view behind, Thy image, Reynolds! rushes on my mind. There I beheld thee stand, with lifted eyes, That sparkled quaint delight and feigned surprise; Unseen I saw, and marked within thy soul The wayward fancies of Cervantes roll; How Quixote's giants worked upon thy thought, And the squire wondering as the master fought. For thine was playful elegance of taste, And humour thineTHE END.</field>
   </doc>
</add>