<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Newcastle, William Cavendish, Duke of, 1592-1676</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Newcastle, William Cavendish, Duke of, 1592-1676</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">newcastle william cavendish duke of 1592 1676</field>
      <field name="author_text">Newcastle, William Cavendish, Duke of, 1592-1676</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1950's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.0854.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1956</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:463566</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Phanseys of William Cavendish Marquis of Newcastle ; addressed to Margaret Lucas and her Letters in reply: Edited by Douglas Grant</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Phanseys of William Cavendish Marquis of Newcastle ; addressed to Margaret Lucas and her Letters in reply: Edited by Douglas Grant</field>
      <field name="title_facet">phanseys of william cavendish marquis of newcastle</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">phanseys of william cavendish marquis of newcastle</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Phanseys of William Cavendish Marquis of Newcastle ; addressed to Margaret Lucas and her Letters in reply: Edited by Douglas Grant</field>
      <field name="year_display">1956</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1956</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1956</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463566&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463566&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Newcastle, William Cavendish, Duke of, 1592-1676&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;newcastle william cavendish duke of 1592 1676&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Phanseys of William Cavendish Marquis of Newcastle ; addressed to Margaret Lucas and her Letters in reply: Edited by Douglas Grant&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;phanseys of william cavendish marquis of newcastle&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1956&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1956&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Newcastle, William Cavendish, Duke of&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1592&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1676&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Phanseys of William Cavendish Marquis of Newcastle&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;addressed to Margaret Lucas and her Letters in reply: Edited by Douglas Grant&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;The Nonesuch Press&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1956&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0686&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;xxxiii, 194 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Phanseys of William Cavendish Marquis of Newcastle&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;addressed to Margaret Lucas and her Letters in reply: Edited by Douglas Grant&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 108 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Phanseys of the Marquesse of Newcastle. Sett by him in verse att Paris These following Verses to M??. Margaret Lucas before hee Married her. 1 The universall Confest Beuty I will not say that love in you discloses A mingl'd Bath of Lillies and of Roses In Eyther Cheeke; or Else so lovely borne For conqueringe Hartes, all other Bewties scorne; Or that you'r all well shap'te; and Even length Converts love's Infidells beyond their Strength, And makes an Athist to God Cupid more Pious then Ever love did know before. At your sacred Alter's lipes lovers kneelinge, Offringe Thoughts, Kisses, for prayres without feelinge: All these you know too well your selfe is true, But I must tell you somethinge more of you. Love heretofore still diffringe in Each minde, Wondringe att one another, thought love blinde; And so he was, but since all Ages wooe You for love's Goddesse; Men of busnesse too Confessinge you love's Center without Sinne; Mankinde Enamor'd Circlinge you within; How can you scape? not Impudence denies Where all agrees, you've given Cupid's Eyes A perfect sight; but love sick we are all, And love is growne now Epidemicall: Must die for love of you, then bee't your will That I may bee the last that you will kill. 2 Love's Consideration of his Mistres' Picture When View'd your Picture, so divine, And did consider Every line, The Figure, and each mingl'd Colour, That life it selfe could not be fuller; So Pensil'd by the Paynter's Arte That att my Eyes it struck my Harte; And all Love's Passions it did move That ever yett was knowne in Love. Then thought to touch that parte, then this, And then to steale a gentle Kisse; But check't those thoughts as Sinne, and then, Turn'd all to Eys, look't on't agen. The more I look't, that Urg'd Each thought To thinke a kisse now not a falte, Nor Rudenesse in my Lips att all On your twinnes temptinge lips to fall; Since their magnettick power did drawe Mine to them by love's, Nature's, lawe. When Kiste, then sigh'd and drop't a teare Because my touch found you not there; T'was not your Picture I did see Drawne by the Paynter, but in me By first Impressions; and this newe Picture those motions did renewe. Those Speties, cousinnge, glidinge passe Like 'Sissus in his water Glasse; But truly all thinges doe obtaine Nothinge but motion in our Braine. Since touch not pleas'd but onely sight, I'le winke, so please my Touch delight. 3 Love's Thoughts Thus I doe thinke, t'is strainge I never heard From my deare love so longe; is the way barr'd? Or doth the State of France thinke it their gaine By partinge Us the better to beate Spaine? Or Els our Sacred Queene thinkes our intente Somethinge gainst her by Us for Parliament? For Else we sure should meet. Is ther no hope? Doth Digby hinder it now from the Pope, Or doubts our meetinge may perchance miscarry The Grand Duke's Sister with our Prince to marry: Madamosell, or Prince of Oringe's Daughter? What is the cause wee mett not? who's the Author? It is so longe, so longe agoe, since mett, I doubt you will me Utterly forgett; It is now how longe? it is, lett me see, Since I had letter, or did heare from thee, I Vow it is, protestinge here I may, T'is since I heard from you, T'is one whole day. Oh, Gods, oh, Gods, how it doth greeve my Sole Longer then sixe month's day att Eyther Pole; Methusalem, from's Death to's Youth and Prime, To this longe day was not a minute's tyme; Adam his dayes to this poore dust and Earthe So shorte to ours as strangl'd in his birthe. From the Creation, reckon day and night, When God Commainded, now lett there be lighte, Not so much tyme consum'd as in our day; Nor Nature in that made so much decay. Pray you then come, or write, or send, that that We may doe somethinge; but if I know whatt I am a Villan; what I thinke of thee Is still too bigg to bee Exprest by mee. Here by our Love I sweare that it is true, Methinkes so longe since I did heare from you That Almenackes are falce, so lay them by; And all that tells me otherways doe lie. They say t'is but a day, but doth inrage Me so because to mee it is an Age. Wee'le have new Efemerides and make Love's Almenacks from them for our Each sake; And houer-glasses, whose least droppinge Sand Heape hills of houers, nay, for yeares shall stand, When parted; but when mett Tyme shall stand still, Observinge Us and waytinge of our will. 4 Love's Answer When one doth aske, what news, I pray you Sir? I answer yett I did not heare from her. S'ounds, I meane Bristoll, says he, can you tell? I answer, I doe hope that shee is well. The Peace is made in Ireland they say? I tell him, I doe thinke shee'le send to-day. Are the Scotts turn'd Unto the Kinge? pray speake. If she not love me then my harte will breake, Say I. Says he, your Answers mad doe make me. I sweare I love her, Else the Divell take me. What's this to what I say or doe Enquier? T'is true, I tell him, her I doe admire Of all the world, and will doe whilst I live. Says hee, the straingest answers you doe give; Pray God you'r well, says he; what doth you move? Are you awake? I tell him, I'm in love. Oh, crie you mercy, says he, since you please To tell mee that, for that is a disease. And now I see Lovers all things refraine But whom they love, and that fills all their Braine. The Brayne is hearinge, thinkinge men do find; So love is deafe, too, now as well as blinde. 5 The unexpressable Love dispising both Venus and Cupid Alas, poore Cupid, you are quite Undun, Though Heaire to Venus, and her onely son. Poore Queene of Love, your mother, never knewe The height of Love, in that as blinde as you. Goe still to Courts, there flatter, Cogg, and Lye; Drop a false teare, a windy Sith, and die As lovers Use to doe; then pale and tremble; With folded Armes, in love doe thus dissemble. Or shoote your Arrows in the Citty, than The Mistresse may provoake the Jorney man; Or his head Prentise, in some lovesick houer, Steale marrige with his daughter att the Tower, Lawfull Unlawfully there to committ The Sinne of Matrimony with no witt. Or Else a Codlinge Heaire Inflaminge made To throw himselfe away on Chambermayde. Or Else fall lower with your love that's stale; Practise your love tricks att a Whitson Ale, And strike Up Love in Hornepipe, Couplinge all On Circl'd Greene boute painted Maypole tall; There drown'd in love and wassill, that's love's streame; Her Joynture, Apples; Portion, Curdds and Creame. Or Joyne with Robin goodfellow, thy Doome To fright the Mayds by stealinge of the Broome; If the Harthe not swept cleane, or potts like newe By rubbinge cleane, lett Faries pinshe them blewe. Thus Joyne your forces; with these still alonge Enamore Shepards with the Milkemayd's Songe; Or from a frumpe of Darymade, you finde, Th'inraged Carter whip till's horse breake winde. These petty Artes, God Cupid, you must Use, And sporte your selfe by others to abuse. Poore Child, but did your boyship ever knowe The height of love, and how far it can goe? Then I will teach you manners; you shall finde You'l wishe your selfe as deafe as you are blinde Before I've done with you. What say you, Sir, Unto a Woman? but t'is onely her: A spotlesse Virgin, full of Love and truthe, Freshe as is Morning's day, or her owne youthe; Modest beyond the newcom'd budds that's faire, That dares not looke Upon the gentle Ayre For feare of Scandall, so shrinkes still within Gainst Nature's lawes, doubtinge that law's a Sinne. So Innosent, or if she grow att all, Like Oringe trees, in her owne Pott and wall. In her love's Climate and more bewty hides Then all the world of Bewty hath besides; And all her all, love's quintesence, t'is such T'would serve all women kinde, nay, be too much, And doth but Justly fitt her; with the least, For shee is shee, is not to be Expres't. Something beyond our Nature that doth move, Or bove the Angells, t'is a purer love; Tis more then love; from Heaven sure it came; We all confesse it, yett it wants a name; Too bigge for Language, like God it is so; A thinge wee worship still but do not know. Worship's Religeon, lett me live and die With all my prayrs Unto your Diaty. Settle our Church and State, that now hath none, For to agree in one Opinion; Converte the Independents, you will drawe Them to Dependents all by your Love's lawe. Since so many Opinions we have gott Amongst our selves, from Irishe and the Scott, We'le sett Up for our selves love's Church, no lesse; I worship: that's the Church, You my Goddesse. Wee'le be no more; lett all the rest condole; Thus by our faythe and workes save our Each Sole, For more would damme Us: I begg then of thee, As thee I onely love, love onely me. 6 Love's Creature I Now sitt downe with Penne and Inke and Paper, Invoake my Muse by my dimme single Taper. Faire as your selfe; for ther's nothinge so faire, Your Skinne is sulli'd with Transparent Aire; Well favour'd like your selfe; it must be so, For there is nothinge like you that I know. Here is no Simulisinge, you must know it; And if not that, why then you spoyle a Poett. Then your discription is, to do you righte, No Sircumscription, beinge infinite. Incomprehensible you are, oh, then To comprehend you how can Mortall Men? Then some Unexpressible thinge thou arte, That fills my Immortallity and Harte With over joye; but whether that or this I can not call it, or know what it is. But there it is, somethinge as farre above Man's kindnesse, or all Mortall Humayne love, As Infinite to finite thinges; wee'r lesse, Since we poore Creatures att you cannot guesse. Sweare by thy selfe then; and so for my parte To tell what thou art, thou art what thou arte. I sweare by thee, all other Oaths refrayne, That I will never take thy name in Vaine: As I love thee, and thou lov'st onely me, Thy thankefull creature I will Ever bee. 7 Hymen's Ancorett Like an old Soldier in Queene Venus' warres, My wounds of love turn'd all to mangl'd Scarrs, Love's broaken speere and bowed sworde doe meet As offrings att your Sacred Alter's feete. My discharg'd Pistoll, Rusty Armes, though stronge, Dismounted Cannon, here doth lie alonge; And all Love's Magazine, that's thought divine, I Sacrifise here att love's flaminge Shrine: As all sweet powders, Essence, sweet balls, Oyles, Rich Cloaths, Fethers, Ribbans, and all Love's Spoyles I here give Up; all Poetry renounce, Gainst phansi'd Ryme or Verse I here pronounce. Though your maim'd Soldier, Venus, scorne to begg So much of you to buy a woodne legge, Nor Pention from love's County; I'le be stript Starke naked first, so to my parishe whipt. You have a Shrine but are no Saynte, they say; I have a Hymen's Saynt to whom I'le pray. A Glorified body shee doth holde, So Purslaine-like, so Cristall-puer her molde, As not a spott of Sinne on her doth faule; Most thinkes shee's free of what's Origenall. There dropinge Hymen's beads, with homage bowe And Sacrifise my Pious harte; there Vow Your holy Ancorett to be alone Within your Marrige walls, thus two's made one; And so with holy rights more pleasure have Then Soles that's damn'd for it, yett ours Wee'le save; So have two Heavens by Infused grace, See you heere, and so God there, face to face. Beatificall Vision, thus wee'le doe, Sav'd by you here, and in the next world too. 8 The Easterne Ayre: Love's Shepperdesse: The Divine Nature: Love's Ballsum, or the Spotlesse Lover Ther's none so hayted as yourselfe, no thinge, No, not the Parliment against the Kinge, So much as all Mankind is against you; Thinke what you please now of your selfe, t'is true. It is confest fayre as Unshadow'd Light, Your lilly Skinne, not fallinge Snow so white; Softer then softest silke, Bevor, or Downe, Your thinner Skinne, for your plumpe fleshe your Gowne; So porous as still issuinge a Dewe, Sweeter then is the Balsum of Perue. Your Breath more fragrant then the Easterne Ayre, More odoriferous then flowers are. Attired like the Graces, or your dresse Like to a modest, simple shepperdesse, So farre above all women of Each Nation As women hate you out of Emulation. No spott of Sinne Upon your Soule att all, Some thinkes you have not what's Origenall; Above the Angells is your heavenly Nature, So sweete that t'would doe good to Every Creature. Nothinge offends you, whatsoere they say: So Innosent, lookes just like Equall day Upon Mankinde, and is a runninge flood, A Cristall streame, to what may be cal'd good; Freshe as the Springe, or Summer's greene, a Calme Perpetually in your Brest, sweet as Balme. So faire, well favour'd, and of shape so fine, Made Up of morrall Virtue and Divine, You have not Virtue but is it, tis true; Then that's the Cause makes Mankinde so hate you: Not all; 'Cause handsomest, and best, I doe Love you, and onely love you for those two. 9 The Savinge Love Deere, you nor none else know Why you should love me so; Ther's nothinge that can be Worthy of you in mee; To you a greate reproach To see mee neare your Coach; To love me, tis high treason Against your State and reason; Therefore I dare not wooe you For feare I should Undoe you. Love me no more, my sweete, I begge it att your feete. Your Love it doth amate me; My love would have you hate me; As I love you, t'is true, I am so fraide of you. Then some Unkindnesse send me That presently might Ende me; Though never would I wave thee, Yett glad to die to save thee. 10 Love's Excuse My Deere, how can I thinke that you love mee? In what, or how, can I thinke that should bee? Did you e'ar once enquier how I doe? Yes, but that kindnesse I provoak't you to. Or Ever sent? your woman too did flie me, Although in Towne yet shee would not come nigh me. Swarmes of your Courts make Visetts heere, not know For all that whether you doe live or noe. Well natur'de Tom sweares that his Mistresse chid him For offringe but to see me, so forbid him. Cruell of Cruelty, your love, I finde, Will not your selfe nor servants lett be kinde. What should I say in your behalfe? oh, now I can Excuse you, and I'le tell you how: My love to you so much, it lefte no roome For any from you Unto me to come; My Love did ply you so with Prose and Rime, That my love never would give your love tyme; My love made such assaults, did you surrownde, That you had much adoe to keepe love's grownd; My Love such Volleys gave, such Noble fier, By my Inflam'd affection and desire. So I confesse, t'is my faulte and not thine; So aske you pardon att your sacred Shrine. I've Won love's battle, yet your Prisner yeeld; Though I have Conquer'd, you have won the feeld. 11 Love's Troubles Our Love grows Troublesome, I doubt too true; So troublesome, both troubles mee and you. It is both peace and Warre, all State affairs Of Comonwelths, and drownds all other Cares; All Greefe Expresses, and Expresses Pleasure, The height of both; is poverty and Treasure. Divinity and Story I can drawe Out of our love, and Newse too, and so Lawe; What not? so Under our love all things fall, All things is our love, and our love is all. Such greevous pleasure, troublesome delight, So painfull pleas'd, with and without your Sight; All att one Tyme, those Passions mingl'd power, Just as is sweet things mixt with those that's Sower, So to love's taste; yett pleasure drownds the Payne, Pleasure by Greefe, more pleasure doth remayne. Such mingl'd Motions Variously doe move My Panntinge Harte and tremblinge Brayne: that's love, And love of you; I sweare by love t'is so. It is, it is some thing I doe not know; And yett it is so fully Exprest in that, That it is somethinge, but I know not what: Like the greate hiddne Secrett of our ball, Eternall matter mov'd, that moves our all And yett is nothinge; Motion, Accedent, Forme's Various Shapes, call'd things by Us, thus meant. And yett, me thinkes, we both know love so well In fayth, yett neyther of Us it can tell. Thus troubled least you thinke I doe neglect you, And you are troubled that I thus respect you. How shall we helpe our trouble? it will Ease Us: When our love's mett together, sure will please Us. 12 Love's Heaven I wishe I'd never seene you, seene you never; Or Else I wishe that I had seene you Ever. If never seene you, then in love my Fate As other folkes, lov'd att the Common rate, Litle or nothinge; some small passions mov'd, To greeve and morne, and thus like Turtles lov'd; A litle sadd and Melancholy, finde A Showre of Teares to lay Love's siths of winde. If Ever with you, love's Paradise true; In love there is no heaven sure but you; There is no hopes, no wishes to desire, But Everlastinge Joyes cannot mount higher; All height's delights, Various offer'd not sought, All present, permenent, and prevents thought. There is no tyme to come, or what is past, All present Joyes, those Joys for ever last; No tyme, no Age, no Seasons, heate or Cold, Beyond all wishes with you grows not old. No Violence, with renu'd Joyes we lie, That's Unexpressible, thus can not die. Oh, you Unexpressible thinge, to parte: That teares and kills my Sole, nay, my sole's harte, And makes my immortality Condole; Thus murders my Sole, you sole of my Sole, And makes my Sole a body; thus doth bringe Mee now to thinke it a poore mortall thinge. Infuse that Spiritt once againe to mee, Make it immortall by your Company. 13 Love's Transmigration If livinge can not meete, then lett Us trie If after death wee can; Oh, lett Us die. By Transmigration bodys still doe rainge In thousand things, in one another chainge: In Roses you, for finer Poseys fitt, I, winding Silke, your tender stalkes to knitt, And so Imbrase you; or you, heaven's due, Fallinge on me, a dead leafe, may renue With honey'd kisses; you, lillies newly gott, And putt in me, turn'd now a Purslaine pott; Or Sweeter Grapes, whose squees'd Juce is divine, Minglinge our selfes, makinge but one pewr Wine; Or wholsom Salletts, mingl'd to our wishe, Thus may be Joyn'd both in one Sallett dishe; Our Norrishment turn'd to the quintesence Of what makes man, and is his first Essence. Aptly dispos'd by Hymen, wee may then Bee gott, brought forth two twinnes, be Us againe. In spight of fate, death, Grave, still joyned thus, Wise Nature still will make Us both, both Us. 14 A Songe [All my Misfortunes they are gone] All my Misfortunes they are gone Now wee are one; Dispise the greatest Monarks' frownes And all their Crownes; And triflinge of all. What's mankinde? Like Various winde, Like Boys that fethers blow, these be Compar'd to thee. What's Court's dissembling? lett them lie; Or what's Digby? Or Greatnes of our great Frenshe Queene? Or Mazerine? Or our Queen? doe all shee can, Jerman's Jerman. Not picking Strawes, hee, shee, or hee, Compar'd to thee. 15 Love's Sole's Conversation Were we both blind, though that were much, Wee could both live and love by touch; If onely Deafe, and that our beinge, Wee could discourse our love by Seeinge; If onely Dum, Each lovinge Brest Our love by musick so Exprest; Wantinge our taste, not barr'd love's tellinge, Discourse by flowers' Various Smellinge; Wantinge our Smellinge, love not wasted, Our minds Exprest when lipps were tasted; Though wanted touch, love's cheefest Joy, Platonick love thinkes that a Toye; If sensles were our Senses' holes, Wee could converse our Purer Soles. 16 Love's Vision Deere, lett Us two each other spye: How curious in Each other's Eye Wee're drawne to life; and thus wee see Our selves att once, both thee and me; Distinctly two, yett not alone; Incorporated, that's but one. My Picture in your Eys you beare, I yours, as much as myne you weare; T'is not our Speties can not passe, Or Shininge makes a lookinge glasse, Nor Picture; Really wee lie Contracted Each in other's Eye. When that our milke White purer lawne, Our Eylid Curtaynes, when they're drawne, Soft Sleepe, made with sweet Vapors' rayne, To coole Us shrinkes into Each Brayne, Rejoyseinge with love's runninge Streames, Which groser Lovers calls but Dreames. Because wee two must never parte, Wee move downe to Each other's harte; And there, all Passions turn'd to Joy, Our lovinge harts feeles no annoy; Delated, least our Soles out skipps With Joy, kisse quickly, stopp our lipps. 17 Love's Conjuration Love's Magick strainge, for now I see you are, Venus, a Witch, your Sonne a Sorserer; So conjur'd in love's Circle can not sturre, Or thinke a thought but onely, onely her. When Reverent Witches goes with staves for propps, Yett oynted flies out of the Chimney topps, Danses on Ayre, not fetter'd are their Mindes, And foots it to Stormes of Boystrous windes, And posts on blacker clouds, on them they stride, Those winged Vapors to Every place they ride. Though Jove a God, their Post boy to our wonder; No light but lightning's flashe, their horne, his Thunder; Darkens the world, as darke as is their Hell; Workes still their will, thus with a fatall Spell. But lovers seperated never meete But by the dull Soles of their duller feete. Banisht by fate, what helpes then can ther bee? Onely Love's thoughts, weake Comforts Unto mee. Phansy doth flatter mee to thinke I'm there, Onely where you are, but, alas, I'm heere; Then I imagine you are heere with me; Findinge it false, falles in love's Extasie, Of all love's Passions read in love's recordes, Pale Siths, sad teares, Greefs, Groanes, with sadder words. With you, not with you, att one tyme, I Vow Love conjures well when none can tell me how; And yett t'is so, nor find that I am mee, But I, and all things Else, are onely thee. You knowe it, Cupid, though you can not see't; Unconjure Us, or prethee, lett Us meete. 18 Love's Thoughtes Love is the pretiest pleasinge thinge, The sweetest thoughts doth bringe, And makes me thinke my self so wise All Else I do dispise As fooles; how can I thinke them less, Havinge other busnes? For ther is nothinge Else, in fayth, But what she doth or Sayth; For all the rest are but meer toys To love, her solid Joyes; And wonder, by my troth, I doe, How most doe live without it too, And thinke they're well; alas, alas, I pitty their poore case; For all things in love's armes are hurl'd, Then wee are all the world. 19 Love's Resolution For to contract my lovinge Minde I winke, because love should be blinde. Such Various thoughts Sight makes, you know, It dissepates our love's soles so, Scattring in Atoms love so much As love is lost; forgettinge touch. Nor in my Mouth have Comfetts felt, Delightfull in that Oven melt; My Toung to tickle with that taste, And make my other pleasure waste: I'le onely heape Up heere love's pleasure, Reckon no Ritches but her Treasure. I'le stop myne Eares, as well as sight, From sweetest musick her delight; Bee't warblinge Voyce, or Soft toucht Stringe, Or your discourse, that's ravishinge: Not tempt my love for to goe lesse, I'le onely minde Cupid's busnes. Nay, more; I'le tell you what I'le doe: I'le stopp my clearer Nostrills too, For feare puer touch I should refrayne; Your Balsome dewe perturbe my Brayne: Of Senses five, I'le have no more But Touch; lett any take the foure. 20 The only Love, or Love's Philosophy To all but you I finde Cupid hath struck me blinde; All others I refrayne; The sight is in the Brayne. If touch and not know when, Touching is nothing then; None Else I heare, t'is so, For hearing is to know. Ladies' perfumes are dead, Not Vapor'd to my head; And kisses taste in Vayne, Not movinge of my Brayne. So all my Senses bee Devoted all to thee; No Speties can come in, For you fill all within. Your Motions' figur'd Coler, My Brayne can not be fuller; Thus there can be no roome For others then to come. Thou fill'st to where thou art All Pattion in my hart; And makes it pantinge move You onely for to love. 21 The onely Shee Were all that can be cal'd true bewty sitt, Plac'd and Inthron'd in one face, you have it; Or best of featurs, crusht into one forme, T'is your face still; others looke like a Storme. Gras't like a Goddes, borne by Angells' wings, All your Sex Else, such wretched mortall things. Shap't beyond best of Pensill's Arte, So fine, Such Even length; not Humayne but Divine: When Unbeleevers thinke this cannot bee, Lucas but nam'd converts them, onely Shee. Sweetest of Nature, Virtu, you are it; Cerenest Judgment, Phansey for a witt; So confidently modest, so discreet, As Lust turnes love, love homage att your feet, Saint-like Religeous, not for shew but true; And Honor's Height onely belongs to you. So affable, yet keeps your State, all say; Strikes such respect as none dares thinke hee may: Your youth as freshe as Morning day we see; And all this all is Lucas, that is shee. 22 Love's Torture When you are sad, oh, then such paynes I feele: Stretcht on the Rack, or Broaken on the wheele; Hung by the Thumbs, my body's weight thus borne; Or by wilde horses all in peeces torne; Pincht with hott Pincers, peece by peece; nay, more, Striding the Cannon, fier'd though shee roare; Imprison'd in the firy brason bull; Or Else Strappado'd, out my Joynts to pull. All these were pleasurs, and would make me glad, To my love's Tortures when you seeme but sad. Should you be sick, and on your bed but lie, Your Sicknesse more then myne would make me die. My love our Bodys chaing'd, and so Each will, My love to yours; thus bee before hand still. 23 Love's Dieing Lethergie When you'r displeas'd, my Body's all within As if benuminge Campher taken in; Or Else blood chillinge Hemblock I had ta'en, Melancholy Night Shade, or liver's bane; Or in dull Lethe my Eye lids did steepe, Or colder Opium lul'd them fast asleepe; As if my Unstrung Nerves by Lettice fedd, And moist Emultions Vapor'd to my head; As Moone wort, or as adder's tonge, did rayne Their poyson'd Vapors on my Unmov'd brayne. Thus in Love's Lethergie I lie, as dead; The Niter'd grownd my Pillow and my Bed; From my sad Eyes a Sea of teares doe flow, Conjeal'd to Ice, but first was turn'd to Snow. If your least frowne such power hath, oh, then Give but a smile, and I shall live againe. 24 Love's Ghoste When you leave lovinge me I'le die, and then My Ghost shall haunt you, for I'le rise againe Att Curfu tyme; and att the dead of Night I will appeare, your Contious Sole to fright; Make signes, and becken you me still to follow To sadder Graves in Church yards, ther will hollow; To Darker Caves, and solitary woods, To fatall Whirlepooles, and Consuming floods, I'le tempt you; then passe by th'unluckye Ewe, Blasted with cursed dropings of Meldue; Under an Oake that ne'ere bore leafe, my moanes Shall there be told you, by the Mandrake's Groanes, Such horrid things, and Crueltys by thee; The winds too sithing tell, thou murder'd'st mee. Yett loath to leave you, havinge love's desier; But forst to Vanishe in a flashe of fier. 25 Love's Murder When your least sadder looke on me, it still Doth make me thinke which way my selfe to kill; Then Melancholy Vapors presse my Brayne; Feeds on dispare all Comforts, Joy disdayne. Phansies a Valte, darke, Under ground, like hell, Hung all with black; and with a fatall Spell Invoakes th'infernall Speritts, as they're Divells, For to appeare, and counsell mee with Evills; But their advise so childishely did tell As I did kick and Cudgell them to hell. Thoughts multiplyinge thoughts, how to discover The next way to Cruelty for a lover: Sent for a Glorious burning Taper bright, Though a darke deed, durst doe it by the light; Pul'd off my Dublett, all my Shert did teare, To see my naked brest, and, without feare, With my drawne sword wounded that Very Parte That led Unto my more then wounded harte; And furiously my blood gusht out, but found Your name it writt still as it fell o'th' Ground, Till it droun'd that and me, being all ore; Delightfull bathinge thus in my owne gore. My last breath nam'd you, but did not repent; Your purer Name to heaven thus I sent. So parted with you; thus have sevrall fames; You sav'd, and I to Everlasting flames. 26 Love's Fate My Love, my Deere, my Joy, Cupid's a foolishe Boy To put such thoughts in to my brayne, That I can not refrayne But still must thinke of you, you know, Whether I will or noe; So that I can not chuse, Take this, or that refuse; So that in Love I'm bound Up still, Necessitated with my will. The softest whisper such, The Gentlest looke, or touch, Nay, smother'd sithes, they all doe wayte Of that thing cal'd our fate; Strivinge for our Ends without doubt, Though we bringe hers about; Ne'ere see't, we are so blind, Nor her comands doe finde: We must obay thus in a mist, Thinke doe, when not doe, what we list. 27 Love's Providence Some talke of Providence, and some of fate, Of fortune, and predestination's State; Some calls it luck, and some the Gods do mock; And some they say, lapt in their mother's smock Necessitated some; others free will; Some thinke the Gods take care of Mankind still; Others thinke not att all, but doe advance Their heavenly busnes, leaves mankind to Chance. Unknowinge man Unknowne things thus disputs; Poore wretches, one another still confutes, So remayns Ignorant; sayes that or this, But man shall never know shure what it is. I thinke my fate, if rightly Understood, Is all in your hands; what we may call good: A ruine better I doe Understand By you, then sav'd by another's hand. So Eyther pleases me; I'me Never sad So you the Auther; still you make me glad. 28 The Knowne Love Lord, how we strive in love; shall we so still? You know without you I have not a will; Pray you command me then, both night and day, Since my will is, still your will to obay. I can not live contented, pleas'd with thee, Except you totally doe governe mee; Pray you now doe. Alas, tis but a toy; Can you not doo't, my deer? sweet, doo't, my Joy. For my sake pray you grant it; then, wherfore, For that your bounty, I'le ne're aske you more, For all is sayd in that; then agree still But with your selfe; we havinge but one will Shall still agree, since that will too is thyne; Soles married thus, as bodys doe Combine. This is not weaknes; Wisdome I dare owne; Thus two is justly, onely thus made one. For my love thus you need no fayth, t'is true, No false fayn'd words; thus you know I love you. 29 The Mariage Songe Wee'le Singe and all rejoyce, Made happy by your Choyce; Nature, wee finde, Rob'd all your kinde, Wee know tis true, To make Up you. So Women since doe paint and Curle, Forst to art's dresse, with finer Purle: What Nature wants they now supplie with arte, So for to Cosen a poore lover's harte. But now, in spite of fate, When lost was all my state, What did you then? Restor't againe. Thus by your Love I onely move, And have my beinge and my life; Thus by your bounty now my wife: You first and great Example, we may call, Of Love, to ruine thus your selfe of all. Venus, you may begon, Of your love wee'le have non; Nor such a toye As is your Boye. Then you must knowe Wee scorne his Bowe And Arrow; though his swiftest flight, His love is blinde, ours sharpe of Sight: His love is built of Nothinge but of folly; Ours Virtue, Goodnesse, and all what is Holy. Now you'r in bedd With tremblinge Maidenhed, T'is Civell to begone. As the Preest made you one, Make your selves so anone; So all this plesant Night Bee Love's Hermofredite, And wee will out of sight: Blest be the knott of holy Hymen That thus in lovinge Nuptialls tie men. 30 Our Love dispiseing both Venus and Cupid Who thinkes there is a Cupid, His brayne is Very Stupid; No paynted Winges or Bowe, Ther's no such thinge I knowe; Nor Lawne before his Eyes, They are but Poett's Lyes; Nor no such thinge as Ever A glorious Silver Quiver, Or Arrow's goldne Head Makes Us Enamored: Ther's no such thinge about him, Then we will love without him. Neyther his mother Venus, The Poetts there did meane Us; Nor yett her milke white doves, All that is but our loves; Nor is it a Reproach To say shee hath no Coach, Or Chariot, which some name it, All gilte, for so they fame it, Drawne in the purer skie; In it the Poetts Lie: Our love for that, instead Of it, wee'le lye in bedd. Birds wooe and Kisse and Bill Without a Cupid still; And Beasts heapes Up love's treasure And asks not Venus' pleasure; Fishe, plants, too, never die, Lives in their Proginie. As theirs your love and myne; They make no lofty Line, Or in their love rehearse A sad or witty Verse: This is their love, t'is such; Could we love halfe as much! 31 Love's Snake To say wee'r like one Snake, not Us disgrases, That winds, delights it selfe, with selfe Imbrases, Lappinge, Involvinge, in a thousand rings, It selfe thus tieinge by love's phansy'd winges; And so doe wee. Cutt her in peeces all, Throw them away, those peeces ne'er so small, They'le come together, whersoe'er they light, And glu'de so fast, such force hath love's delight, And thus made one; and so are wee, and then Wee, but a word, peeces made whole agen. Ther is no wee, but one thinge still doth move, One Matter still, the purer parte of love, And that for grosser braynes is still cal'd wee, For none but puer Soles sees this Misterie. Thus like one Snake, batinge her Venum; true, Instead of that, our's balsum of Perue: Love hath no Venum, Poyson, in't att all, But is all sweetnes and Balsamicall. 32 Love's Repentance I meane now by your leave, my deere, For to be bold with your own sheer: In Essex, all men tell me soe, Ther is a Towne ther call'd Dunmoe, Wher is hung Up, if not mistakne, An Unrepentant flitch of Bakne; For married folks thither are sent To Eate of that, if not repent. Sweet hart, then I must lett you know When married wee will thither goe; For I have such a Marrige Itch To take away their Bakon's flitch, No married man att all shall Eate On Collop, with his Egs for meat, Of this, our sacred flitch wee'le call: Onely to Us belongs itt all. But stay, it is longe since t'was quick; I doubt the tast would make you sick: No Lady meate, Itt shortens lives, Refused by Pease-porrige wives; And for my selfe, itt ne'ere did wishe, Nor none can lay it in my dishe; For I repent, Repentance store, Cause did not marry you before. 33 The Heaven's Moulde So streight, so slender, and so tall, But that's not all: A face out of the Comon Road, With smiles so stroad, To grace that feature and that forme Without a storme. You, Heaven's mould, sent downe so fresh and new; None can be handsom that's not thought like you. So Bewtifull you are, so fayre, Transpayrent Ayre Doth sully and doth stayne your skinne; It is so thinne, The Gentlest blushe no where can hide, So soone tis spide; And your Each curled hayre those locks doth grace, Like pensil'd shadows for your lovely face. You doe Excell, Nature thought fitt, So too in witt, And Judgment too; wher you doe come Wee'r all struck dumme, Amas'd with your discourse; when heare Ravisht Each Eare: So Orfious' Harpe doth stringe your tongue of love, And when you Play makes trees and Rocks to move. 34 Love's Flowers From your lipps I will Pluck Freshe Roses, Kisses suck, And blow those budinge leaves; Robb you, and so disseaves Those Odoriferous Fragrant love's flowers thus. It is no theft, for when I kisse, you tak't agen; And doth your lipps renue With your owne hony'd dewe And Naturall showers, gott From your tongue's water pott. When my Lipps, heated, seekes Love's cooler Walkes, your Cheekes; Or wandringe loves to Roave In thicketts, your hayr's Groave; Or on love's Mounts that's fayre, Your pantinge brests, gives Ayre; Or Bayth me in love's poole, My heated love to coole; Or in love's Grotto shunne Your Eys, Each a hott Sunne; Freshe fountayns there will please me, With sweet fan'd Ayre to Ease mee. 35 Both Love's Sicknesse and Love's Cuer Love's Radient Streames With your Eys' Beames Hath Rob'd me of my sight; And my Each Eare Now can not heare Your Musick's speech delight. Wher you doe come I'me struckne dumme, This all the world can tell; Love's Power such, Have lost my touch; And now I can not smell. Unconjure mee: The blind to see, And make the dumme to talke; Of Nostrill Cleere; The deafe to heere; The Palsied man to walke. A looke that's kinde Will cure the blinde; A gentle kisse the Numme; Hope's whispers dropp, My Eares Unstopp; And make my Tongue not dumme. 36 Love's Constellation Wilde Phansey, goe possesse some younger Sole, Whose giddy humor suffers no controll; Whose Minde yett hath no bounds settl'd att all, No Pale about him, Hedg, or Ditch, or wall; Who hath no Center, cause not Circkl'd in; Bridles no Passion but is loose to Sinne, Takes lust for love, runnes over Woman kinde; Lookes for Contentment, never doth it finde; His food Inconstancy, and Various winde; Nothinge like Love about him, but what's blinde; Such a selfe lover, yett this doth not see. Thinkes greatest Ladys prostitute must bee Unto his will; though Under honor's locks, Courts these, but with a whoore doth gett the Poxe; Or Els his high ambition Ends in stenche, Lays his great fury with a Kitchinge wenshe; Or Else doth worse for to save charges, and Like a good husband makes for whoore his hand. Nay, his Vayne glory spoyl'd, growne wretched tame, Misseinge to lye with a greate lady's fame, Which was his Second Plott; so all his Payne To loose his labour, all his dresse in Vayne. Poore Various Color'd fethers now is lost, Ribbans att knees, Under his waste; the Coste Is to no purpose; nor Each ribban'd boote, Like a Ruff footed Pigion in Each foote; Nor his greate bunshe of Ribbands in his hatt, Which hee did buy full deare, hee knows for whatt; And so do I, some lady to defame her, When I dare sweare hee knowes not how to name her. Thus wee will leave him and his weaker Crimes, Not Wonder att the follys of these tymes. Hymen makes mee these follys to forbeare; I move and onely move in my owne Spheere, Inlightn'd by the holy flame of love; In my owne Circkle onely I doe move, Virtue my Orbe; seal'd with a sweeter kisse, Makes quiett sleepe still softer then it is. After Religious rights that peace doth bringe, As my cleer Contience is without a Stinge; No frowny clouds, darknes, or what is night, But when I'm out of her beloved sight. Or, like the Sunne, that powre shee now hath gott To Inflame others, yett herselfe not hott; A Presedent of Virtue, shininge bright; Who lives as good must borrow from her light; And mortall lovers, waken'd from their dreames, Can live and love but by our scatter'd Beames. But Purity of love, they all will say, Is onely our love, that perpeatuall day; Our love's Eternall, when our bodys die Wee'le make one Constellation in the Skie; And then wee'r Joyn'd againe by pure desire. Our Soules made one, thus married wee'l mount higher, And, what so Ever living heer we are, After our death both bee one fixed starre. To all Posterity, when shee is nam'd, Love's Miracle shee shall be call'd, so fam'de; Love's Diety, so pray'd to shee shall bee: I lost that starre call'd Lucas, that is shee. 37 The Country Cupid A Country Cupid I have gott That prieinge Courtiers spie him not; So poor disguis'd they will not minde him, Cause hee his quiver left behinde him, And all his Arrows and his Bowe: Those would discover him, you know. So wee Imploy him though a God; Being a Child hee fears our Rodd; Hee does not thinke we doe abuse him, Though for a footman wee doe Use him; And Hackin'm out like hier'd Carmen From Paris, with love, to St. Jermyn. 38 Love's Cristall River Wee'r like two fountayne Cristall Riv'letts cleer, With Serpent Windings runninge here and ther; With sadder murmerings still as we goe At the strict Jelous bankes, least overflow. Spight of Earth's Carefull, watchfull, porous Eys, Wee swell our Channells, higher wee doe Rise, And in our lovinge Course we still advance, Mauger our Mother Earth; thus gett a glance. Findinge we can not Joyne as yett att all, In pearled drops we downe againe do fall; But plyeinge still as they their watry feet, At last we Joyne; made one as they, so meete: Love Traffick now a Navigable River; Parted againe, till death, we shall be never. 39 The Lovely face, a Songe You, Goddesse, With your lovely face: Your sweet Eys' Beames doth Conferr grace Wher they doe shine, They're so divine. But Grace doth fade Iff make a shade; And in a wofull, sinfull state Wher you looke not, a Reprobate. So when I wante your Eys' Sunn's light, It is with mee perpeatuall Night; Wantinge your Eye I'm sure to die; And all my station Is but privation: So sadder Death and darker Night Is nothinge so from your sight. 40 Love's Preparation Just like a Penitent that doth Prepare For to receave, washing his Sole with Prayre And sadder teares; repentance rubbing sinne, All spotts thereof, so cleane, though it be thinne: A better Imortality t'will bee T'Injoy my Heaven, which is onely thee; Which makes me now, in hopes for to be thine, To purge me cleane, fitt for your holy shrine. Thus be your living Arke, and to mee drawe Your Virgin rodd, blest Manna, and your lawe, And keepe them sacred; and with nothing fedd But with pure Marriage, your shew holy bred. In me your Consecrated Arke shall lie, No sinfull hand shall touch Us but shall die. So Cristall pure I'le be; for you I'l boast, Fitt to preserve you, my love's holy Ghost. When Joyfully receave you, I dare say That may be Justly cal'd my Easter's day, My Resurection; and you too shall see My blest assention when I am with thee. But a long lent I've had, and doe beleeve Before our Easter had too long an Eve, Which Crusifi'd me to my onely losse, My darke Good friday, and my shamefull Crosse. Old and new Testament, some thinkes Us neyther; Sure wee'r love's Bible When wee'r bound together. 41 Love's Fluide Soles When happily Wee mett, all did admire To see our fluid Soles turn'd all to fier, Whose sublim'd suttle motion none did doubt, Feeding one another, could not goe out. Minglinge our selves thus, still must be the same, Each living still Eternally in flame; But, parted, gross thick melancholy Vapors Extinguisht light, putt out our loving Tapers; And where before two sunns when wee wer mett, Disjoyn'd, turn'd now Each to a dull Planett. In whirlepooles moving to meet; if so, then Love will inflame Us both to sunnes agen. 42 Love's Muster I'le Muster Up my senses with delight; My taste, my touch, my smell, Hearing, and sight, All att one tyme; height's pleasure shall obtayne, With gentle stroakes Upon my Ravisht Brayne. Best Various Pictures wee will have; nay, more, The Roofe with story fill'd, and all gilt o'er. All Rareties heightninge Us when wee meete; The richest Pertian Carpetts for our feete; With Antick Romayne Plate, that shall be bought Fill'd with Puer wines, more Various then is thought; Numberlesse meates so drest, and Banquetts flowinge, To please our Gustaes, shouringe Just like snowinge. To Cossen tyme, and passe away the houers, Robb Nature of her Choysest, sweetest flowers, Strow'd on the Ground with Spainishe sents that's rare; Fanninge our selves with this perfumed Ayre. With such amasinge Musick wee'l obtayne, Our Soles still ravisht in Each pleased Brayne; For all the Passions musick can Expresse Rules our Immortalls, att this none can gesse. Spight of your Envious Kinde, though they thinke much, Silke, downe, and Beavor not like you for touch; You are so smooth, so soft, so Very fine, Beyond Expression, something that's divine. Now all the Senses att one tyme wee'll measure, And fill them till they all runn o'er with pleasur; And danse the hay with Various sweet delight: Touch moves to hearing, hearinge moves to sight, Sight turnes to smellinge, smelling then doth haste To be converted to her Neyghbor Taste; And thus they chainge, and danse so quick a Strayne, And foot it all Upon the moving brayne, Or Else t'wer nothinge. Nerves, they are the strings That to the senses all the Pleasure brings. When touch is satisfi'd, thus t'is related, Then all the rest of senses are abated: So all the rest wayts of her pleasure still; Likes or dislikes all following her will. 43 Cupid's Murder Oh, Cupid, I am slayne, I bleed amayne, Struck with thy cruell darte; No Skinne is broake, yett wounded is my harte. Alas, I know Her Eye browes bent, that is your bowe; Her sparklinge Eys your Arrows shott Into both myne; speake, is it not? Methinks this Cruelty should make me hate her. So deadly wounded is my Pia mater, No Surjon can be gott to cuer this; But from your dewey lips a balsum kisse Dropp, Dropp that sweeter shower, love's softer rayne, Into my Lips, 'twill cuer my wounded brayne. 44 The Gentle Soule My gentle Soule breath'd in thine Eare, Love's Mase, with winding heer and there, Will beat a Parly on your Drumme Softly to tell you I am come To Chainge Harts' Pris'ners. Myne hath longe Suffer'd Extreams, and had much wronge From you, that is a dunjon deepe; With sadd thoughts fetter'd, could not sleepe; Siths Manackl'd a lover's breath; Fill'd with dispayre, that's worse then death; Greefe my Companion; this I beare Can not bee Eased with a Teare. Famisht, oh, Famisht shall I die? I onely feed of your Each Eye; And when my thirst did still renue, Quensht it with thoughts of your lips' dewe. Pray you, releeve mee; sett mee free, And then your Prisner more I'l bee. 45 Love's panting Harte Oh, Cupid, you have Conjur'd mee By the witchcraft spell of a shee, And by her Image in my Brayne, That now doth play so sweet a strayne Upon my Nerves' strings, that doth move My panting hart's sole for to love. That Motion's Passion now doth Ayme To turne me to a liveing flame; Kindl'd att first by love's desier, Increast Unto a mighty fier By Vapors of your love; without Tis fedd, and so can ne'ere goe out. My heate, that drawes it thus to me, And my beames doth Inlifen thee; I do begett, produce love's birth: I am the Sunne and you the Earth, Cold and sterill; but for my light You would be dead, Eternall Night. 46 Love's thankfull Harte Though in Night's darkenesse from you, do not feare, Since your Beames' favor gilds our Hemisphere, And dissepates our blacker Cloudes, despayre, Turnes Melancholy Vapers to a Cleer Ayre; Turning our sad thoughts' mist and foggs away, Chainginge our darker Night to a Cleer day. But, soft, 'cause from you, methinks yett t'is Night, Though with your sweetnesse Starrifi'd with light. Your Devine Nature my Misfortunes tames, Lights my darke sole, my thankefull harte inflames. Thus by you I have light within, without mee, But no inlifeinnge warmth att all about me Till I'm with you: greate Goddes, all can tell Wher you are, heaven is; wher not, my Hell. 47 Love's Emulation Pale Envie, with her Venum'd, hissinge Snakes And Poyson'd tayles with stings, now Undertakes, With sick hatred and Emulation store, To parte our loves, that wee should love no more. Spight of Each witchcraft, sorsery, and spell Of Courte Divells, in their dissemblinge Hell, And Subtlest Spiritts, with their blacker artes, Can not Untye th'affection of our Harts. Incorporated so, not two but one; Halves are not two, but shews love's Union. Love is Immortall, can not suffer death; Wee chaing'd our Soules, with kisses, by our breath. Prethee, take heed; be carefull then of myne, And I will looke as carefully to thine. No, t'is not so; not two, they're still but one; One is together, thus wee'r ne'ere alone. In spight of fate, wee never can be two, But still United, what e'er they can doe: Theirs Is not hatred but pewre love, you'l see; For all the men lov'd you, the Women mee. 48 Love's Sunne Oh, can we love and live? praye, lett Us die If liveing can not meete; I'l tell you why: When dead we may both of Us turne to Ayre, So meete in Higher regions that is faire, Thus have a Calme; or turn'd to waters sweete, Postinge downe Rivers, in the Sea to meete; Or Else, our subtle Motions Ayre, mount hier, Our heated love Inflame Us to one fier, And there we'er Joyn'd: one Sunne, your love and mine, On Mortall Lovers here Ever to Shyne. 49 The Unexpressible love My love to you Is so much, nay, tis more Then Ever lovers yett did know before; Theirs no Proportion, theirs is so much lesse; Myne more then any language can Expresse. Iff a new Alphabett was made, too small T'expresse least parte of our love; how then all? Nay, Algebrase, Arethmatick all o'er, Will still fall short; our love will still be more. Not the World's Heroglificks for ours stand; Our love's small partes, more numerous then the sand. Poore lady Venus and her Son, that youth, All fictions, farre too litle for our truth. We must finde out some new way how to move The greatest Witts to gesse but att our love. Love, that word's too litle, like motes to the Sunne, Love, forty years agoe, serv'd Doctor Dunn, But wee'r beyond it farre; our wise delight Is what wee know, not know that's Infinite: Then tis a God to all love Else; then thus All Lovers as our Creaturs worship Us. 50 The Confeste Love You are the fayrest, all the world can tell; Why you are so, is cause you love mee well. The Comliest too, sweetest and best behavior, Best favor, cause that I am in your favor. Your witt and Judgment best, when tis Exprest Exceeds mankinde, cause you love mee the best. And Every thing that thus Excells in thee Is, I dare sweare, because that you love mee. But stay, I doubt Erronious that will bee; Is it not, Deare, because that I love thee? No, None of these reasons att all the Cause, For you are Justly those by Natur's lawse; For could you hate Mankind, Mankinde hate you, You and they both must needs confesse t'is true. 51 Love's Immortality You Silly lovers, you Imbrase But things, Skinne deepe Upon the face; For Bewty like the movinge Ayre Fades, Withers, staynes, corrupts though fayre: Blasted like morning's flowers soone; The[n] Gayther'd, dyes before tis Noone. The best of Shape, and Comliest Creature; The Purest, best, fast molded feature; Ther's such assaults from Natur's Pressinge, Brings a decay for all her dressinge: Like Romayne Theaters that fall, Nothing but Ruine left att all. So hee whose love is built of this Is as short liv'd as her lipps' kisse; If an assault Upon her face By some disease, it to disgrase, His love grows sick too, Will not stay, But dies with her buties' decay. Our love's Immortall, still kept whole, Wee love by one another's Sole; Our love triumfant still doth sitt, Pleas'd by sweet Phansies of her witt, And Serean Judgment what to doe; With her sweet melting Nature, too. With flames of love sweet Passions make, Siths coolinge love's flames for Each sake; And Chainge our lovinge Soules, and then Not know them when they come agen, Beinge but one; thus wee will doe: Love heere, and in the next world too. 52 Love's Petition Love me, I prethee, love mee; as I live, I'd have thee love mee more then love can give. Thou must not be now as before thou wast; Can'st thou not give mee more love then thou hast? That's Very strainge and, methinks, so Unkinde, Not to give mee more love then thou can'st finde. Why, when you've writt all your love in a letter, Before tis seal'd you finde you love mee better; And Evry Minut thinke can love no more, Yett the next Minut's love scornes that before. Then take Up love before hand, pray you, doe; I'l pay love's Principall, and Int'rest too, For I am rich in love; my love's not scant, I'le sweare for my love you shall never want; And if in love a Bankrout, can not Paye, I'le quitt your debt, give you love Evry day: What a rich Match to you then shall I prove; You'l have ten thousand pounds a yeare in love. 53 The unparalel'd Love The Princes Mary Marrys Kinge of Poland, And you, my Deer, do marry Prince of Noland. Shee hath a Portion, I hope you have non; Shee hath a Dower, but your Dower's gone. Theirs are but rich Externall shews, that move Like love, not it; ours pure Internall love. She doth imbrase all this world's full delight, And you take mee to bidd the world good Night. Shee will possesse what height of Courts can be, But you take Up your Crosse to follow mee; Leaves Court, your Parents, Brothers, Sisters, freinds, Onely for mee, and hath no other Ends. Could all the Love that Ever was on Earth Be reckon'd Up, or all from Cupid's Birth, Or from his Lady Mother's, nine years old, And all the Gods' love, more then can be told Is yours, and onely yours; these never knew This way and height of Love, that fitts but you. Who could do this but you? and onely you. Is't not a dreame, a fiction? no, tis true, Beyond Example, or what fayn'd; therefore, Since none E'er did soe, none shall E'er doo't more. All femall loves to this, how short they've been, Male freindships to the height of Masculin. So farre above them your Eternall fame, I wishe for my sake I could giv't a Name; Beyond Expression, that doth make mee morne; T'is beyond Words, or deeds, to make returne; Thus I'm inslav'd. All other love still tends Onely for bargains, and such petty Ends. Some might give bounties, and then sickly lie; Or in their love's pil'de fun'ralle flames ther die, Surpris'd with Sorrow, or a sudden Passion, Or a Vaine Glory, like a Woman's fashion; Or Madd for love is nothing lesse to die. But for to dare to live in Misery, That's love and Corage; all things Else refus'd That is not mee, and mee thus onely Chus'd That's wholly ruin'd; that you know's my State; And yett will love mee thus, in spight of fate. Thus Miseries opresse me, makes me bowe; I ne'er knew greefe nor Misery till now. Oh, you are Cruell, such love you might give As might oblige mee not in slavery live. To manacle mee thus makes mee condole, Thus to imprison and chaine Up my Sole; My Immortallity thus is not free, But made your Vassell by this Crueltye. Honour, Virtue Noble, too litle; say, Nay, sweare, you've putt mee downe in my owne way. Oh, fie, you love too much, pray you love lesse; Some fine and litle love I might Expresse: Your snow white Skinne, and then my Muse to seeke Lillys and Roses for your Eyther cheeke, So Simulise you all; but I do know it, Ther's nothing like you, so you spoyle a Poett. Pray you love lesse; how shall we doe with Us? Yett love no other; Ignorance might thus Make him Emperious; pray, doe not trie; He may perchance think't your Simplicity. Or if you tooke some fine rich Ayre with land, Whose obligation could not Understand. Ther's No Unhappy, happy fate but myne, So fitt a Subject for your love to shine. Tis too much love; for now my thankefull harte Is loath to ruine you, yett will not parte. You over love; know, pray you, what you doe; You've ruin'd mee with love, and your self too, Mee for your sake. Else Height of love's Content; Since tis our Soles' Choyse, we shall ne'er repent. 54 The Orientall Pearle The Oriental'st Pearle, had I my wishe, I'd robb the Richest of the Sea-shel'd fishe For pendents for you; Necklases not deck But serve for foyles, worne by your whiter Neck. So richest Dimonds: who would not dispise Their luster when compar'd Unto your Eyes? The Rubie of the rock, who would now seeke When they're putt downe by blushes of your cheeke? Such plump and Azure Vaynes belongs to you, As the best Saphir seemes not to be blewe. What Juell then are you, such Treasure bringes Beyond the wealth of Welthiest, richest Kinges? And all this you have given mee: before Nothinge I was, and now I wishe no more. 55 Love's Musick Your silke and danglinge Tresses of best die, When on your whiter Satten Skinne doth lie, With love doth so amase mee Unto death, When wav'd with your sweet perfum'd breath. And then your Sun-like Eyes doth make me proud When shines on mee, and breakes through your hayr's Cloud. So shap't, strikes Poetts dumme; they can not speake, And Paynters in dispayre their Pensills breake. Your words Unto my Soule such Musick brings, Makes Voyces hoarse, Instruments breake their Strings. Not Downe or Beaver like you for soft touch, But none dare offer that; no, not so much; So sithinge dies for greefe, since there is none But one that must Enjoy you, I that one. Oh, happy I; my fate makes mee rejoyce, Bove all Mankinde made happy by your Choyce. 56 Love's Commission T'is love's Commission, Justly it may call; For Hymen's onely Use, you have mee all. Your words such Harmony, my Eares doth feele All Musick Else scrapt Trenchers, Ungreas'd wheele. Your plump fleshe with your Nature Robe, so thinne, All others ruffe like a Beare's or a seale's skinne. Ambrosia, Nector, nautiously should caste When hope but on your temptinge lips to taste. The fresher flowers, Spannishe sents, they stinke, To your Balme's dewe, like Privie or our Sinke. The Hansom'st of your sexe to mee appears, Compar'd to you, like men of fowre score yeares, Not Women. Since I've left them all for you, And they for that left mee, your love is due: In Justice for to love mee, and love so As love no other; Else I'me lost, you knowe. 57 A Songe [Oh, come, oh, come, my dearest] Oh, come, oh, come, my dearest, Most Joy Unto mee when neerest; And then wee will kisse; No pleasure we will misse That belongs to Cupid's sportinge. Then when, oh, when our faces Are look't on, with love's Imbrases, Although we seeme sad, Wee are both of Us glad; Too serious it is for laughinge. When thus, oh, thus wee'r Lieinge As if wee were both adieinge, Our bodys are felt As if they both did melt, And our Soules to one sweet Jelly. 58 A Songe [Sweet harte, we are beggers; our Comfort's, t'is seene] Sweet harte, we are beggers; our Comfort's, t'is seene, That we are Undunne for the Kinge and the Queene; Which doth make Us rejoyce, with Royall braggs, That now we doe foote it with Royall raggs. Wee can not borrow, nor take Up of Trust, So water wee'le drinke, and bite a hard Cruste: Lett Care goe kill Catts, what Comfort's in Sorrow? Therfore lett to Morrow care for to Morrow. In a Gray Morning's dew thy Coates thou wilt dagg, Whilst thou bearest the bottle and I beare the bagg; And then when the wether growes cold and rawe, Wee'l in to the Barne and Tumble in Straw; And when the Springe on our love setts an Edge, Wee'l kisse and wee'l play Under Evry Hedge: Though Nothinge we have, yett nothing we lack; A Staffe in your hand, A Child att your back. This Diett will make Us both looke pale and wanne. Your Hatt band of Inkle, and buttermilke Canne; Or for a doale att a great man's gate Sitt, Expectinge the Porter, your Stockings ther knitt; Whil'st his Inrag'd black staffe ther some rapps, Bee thou then busie in stealinge of Scrapps: And when our Olio of Alme's tubb is cleere, Our hands be our Cupps, the river our beere. For all these blessings lett's Merrily singe: Give God the Prayse, and to Charles our brave Kinge. 59 Love's Matremony There is no happy life But in a wife; The Comforts are so sweete When they doe meete; Tis plenty, Peace, a Calme Like Droping Balme; Love's wether is so fayre, Perfumed Aire; Each word such pleasure brings, Like soft toucht strings; Love's Passion moves the harte On Eyther parte; Such Harmony together, So pleas'd in Eyther; No discords, Concords still, Seal'd with one will. By Love, God man made one, Yett not alone; Like Stamps of Kinge and Queene Itt may be seene; Two figures but one Coyne, So they doe Joyne; Onely they not Imbrase, We face to face. 60 Love's Newyeare's Gifte I must as others doe, appeare For to present you this new yeare: No Mony, or what it can bringe, Not gives, or buy then any thinge. Nor Creditt have I for to borrow, Which for your sake is all my Sorrow; Nor have I left one foote of Land, So much as for one Minut's sande; Weake hopes of some Contingent goods, Faint thoughts of some Potentiall woods; With Remote Phanseys may be fedd, But that will buy Us nowher bredd. What shall I offer then? a harte Swel'd with love's passion; Evry parte So reall, Loyall, and so true; All of it sacrifis'de to you. So all my thoughts cannot refrayne, Still of you, for you, fills my brayne. When you'le not love mee then I'l trie, Tis Easy for your sake, to die; A life I'l give you, for to please you, So from my love I thus may Ease you; I can but give you what I have; All what I am, Unto the grave; And my last sithinge breath shall tell How much I lov'd you; so fairewell. 61 Love's Imagination Oh, Joy of Joys, my love, my Sweet, And doe we meete? Is't not a mist before myn Eyes That flatters mee with Lies? And pleasing Phansys of my Deer, And you'r not heer? Itt is not, cannot be, my fayre. A body of Compounded Ayre? Or body from the Grave did steale, Thinkinge my wounds to heale? A Vision onely to disceave mee, To wound mee more when you do leave mee? Oh, it doth speake; it speakes, I finde, With Trembling Voyce and out of winde. Oh, speake againe; your hand give mee, To know whether that thou art thee. Love's Palsy in myne; prethee, fold it; It shakes so that I can not hold it. Shure you are you; your hart so tremblinge; Your love and myne is no dissemblinge. Oh, doe not weepe, nor Sith, nor Groane; Now I am with you, make no moane. But wee'r not mett; so Joy'de, it Equalls Sorrow: Wee'r foxt in love; let's sleepe and meet tomorrow. 62 The Knowne Angell Long have I now bin told What Angells doe, Their Bewty, favor, goodnesse of Natur too; This is but fayth; beleefe doth make it true; But never sawe or knew any but you. Nay, were those Glories crusht into one forme, Compar'd to yours but a ruff, boystrous Storme. Nay, were their Essence, Virtue's highest prise, Sett but by your's, their Virtues would seeme Vice; Their Soules such sinfull spotted lepars all, With deform'd bodys, ready for to fall; Their Naturs, but compair'd to yours, so Evill, Sinfull dispaire would turne Each to a Divell. Presumption damn'd them first, though it seeme odd That Evry Angell thought to be a God; An Easyer Matter they might thinke to be, Then in their soles and bodys like to thee: So now Dispaire would damn them; pray you, then, Though Angells Damnes, save mee a Mortall man. 63 Love's Joyes More Joy to mee you are, a greater Pride Then Victoryes that's gain'd off Eyther side By Kinge or Parliment; did the warre cease, Not so much Joy as your love, wer't a peace. From Poverty to Riches, could nott feele A Joy like you, should fortune turne her wheele; Not to save Crownes such Joy as your love, when Though Kinge and Queene might so love mee againe. More Joy to mee then when the greatest strife Of Pantinge Soule and body strives for life, Nature's great duell; freinds, lamenting mourn'd, Not Joy'd like mee when they spie health return'd. Not so much Joy is an Unparel'd Soule That's fled to Heaven, and that's Newly stole From the foule shert of fleshe, her spotted Sinne; That with a lively, skipping fayth lept in. Put all the Joys together, from the birth Of Heaven's first Creation and the Earth, Not like the Joy of your love; nay, tis higher Then all Joys shall be, to the world's last fier. 64 Love's Wonder Your sweeter lookes, when View them to my Wonder, Gives mee love's strictest Lawe, yett without Thunder. Your gentle Eys, in Virtue mee still teachinge, They Edifie mee more then any Preachinge; Their kinder Beames, shott from your modest face, Invirtuse mee, just like infused grace. Your Sun-like Bewty's flaminge light, so fayre, Each glimps of Goodnes fills my hart with Prayre; And your Each meltinge worde, what doth it doe? When I receave them, am so thankefull too. Kneeling thus att your Alter and your shrine, Findinge nothinge about mee, but divine; Thus, by reflection of your goodnesse, stole Thus into mee your Soule, thus saves my Soule. Thus consecrated for mee you were sent, Makes mee beleeve Marrige a Sacrement, That thus hath Chang'd mee from what I have bin; Finding nothing about mee now like Sinne, Knows not my selfe, nor thinkes that I am mee; Marrige it could not doo't, not Married thee. T'is thee, and thee, and onely, onely thee; For none Else in the world could have sav'd mee, And sav'd mee so as now my heaven's heere, For beyond you no wishes doe appeare; That's heaven, shure, for heere wishes doth store Us, And Earthly thoughts have wishes still before Us, And I have none but you; I sweare t'is true: I have no heaven then, but what is you. 65 Love's Creatore You Angell-like, for Bewty and for feature, You my Creator, then I am your Creature. Why, pray you then, why not dispose of mee, Since all my beeing onely is from thee? Body and Soule, and all my all, yours still; Am not, nor have, without you, any will. Nothing doth move it selfe, but by another, This Mov'd by that, and that mov'd by the t'other; So I am mov'd by you, you to obay; If I want that, fall to my first bakt Claye. You first breath'd life in mee; itt was your Spiritt, For without that, I nothing could inherritt; And as of nothinge you did make mee, then Without you, faule to Nothing back againe. I begg it not for mee a preservation But for your honor, since I your Creation. Maintaine mee now your worke, lett it not fade; Shew power to preserve what you have made; Else who will thinke you a Goddesse, all-seeinge? Doe but Command, and that Comands my beinge. 66 Love's Contemplations When from you, know not whatt to doe; No busnesse, am so Idle too; But fil'd with thoughts so Vast, Imence, Of greate and Solid Consequence; So Phansy-swell'd, ready to burst. Thus for your Comminge am athirst, To tell you what concernes Us neere: Therfore, oh, com, oh, come, my Deer. When Com'st, I know not what to say, For all those thoughts are gone away, Quite Vanisht; thus your love doth make mee; If I know one, the Divell take mee. Thus am love-Conjur'd, thus by thee, When I am in your Company; When 'parte, and you are gone away, Methinkes much more then have to saye. 67 Upon her takeing Cold Envious Cold, thus to assault A Bewty that's without a faulte; To Close shut Up her porous Skinne That is so white, so soft, so thinne: To stop those holes it is a Sinne. Can nott her sacred body scape From this, thy Unnaturall rape? Appollo will revenge this wronge, And discepate thee E'er't be longe: His powre for thee will be too stronge. Wer't thou not hired by her sexe Her Envi'd bewty thus to Vexe? Thy Cold can not make her more fayre; If wonders doe, condence the Ayre, Pleasur foule faces in dispayre. At Cranis thou get'st slyly in, Till in her Chamber thou'rt within; Then sithinge when thou get'st a sight, Plays with her Neck that is so white: So gives her Cold for thy delight. Thou wert in love without all doubt, For when by warmth thou wer't put out In colder Ayre, within few howres Thou turn'd into sad tears of showres, For to refreshe lovers' sweet bowers. 68 Love's Murmering Brooke When Tytan's hotter Eyes Men's fortunes most Espyes, Walking the world about To finde men's Actions out, I'l hide myne from his sight, Though myne dare bide his light. Pearst by his subtil'st beames, Man's fortune, Waken'd dreames; And not asham'd to tell, Though ruin'd, how I fell; But loath that hee should Eye it; For Princes' sakes, not spie it. A Sollitary Groave, No further wee will roave; Hung all with darke, no sight, Shutt out what's Joy and light. In sadder shade wee'le bee Under a Mornefull tree; Sitt on the Grasse, though die And withers where we lie; A Murmring brooke not stay But flies, and runnes away Fearinge my fate; Nott knows, Yett weepes still as it goes. Siths tellinge make harts Ake Of Stouter Oakes; leaves quake, And trembling thus for feare, When my sad story heare, Though Springe, they almost deafe; Greefe makes it faule o'th' leafe. Siths then Condenst to dewe, Weeping salt dropps, renewe Their woes and greefs to bee Morners for you and mee. In our sad Armes wee lye; They, Claspinge roots, all die. 69 The Ravisheing Voyce Your Voyce, that's ravisheing, so rare, It moves the Cereane panting Ayre, And makes the woods to walke; Hard harted rocks are mov'd to teares, And Earth doth stretch her porous Eares; Rivers leaves murm'ring talke. The Sunne so ravisht in his Eare As will not leave thy Hemispheare; The Fixed Starres now move, And all the Plannetts have no choyce But now are fixed by thy Voyce: Thus all is turn'd to love. Hard Mineralls now liquid flow; Swel'd hills falls into Valleys lowe, Amas'd wher you doe come; The wilder beasts tame, Voyd of feares; And all man's sences, turn'd to Eares; The twatling Echo dumme. 70 The Maydne Gowne Your milke-white maydne Gowne Setts off your Curled browne; Those shaddow'd heares doth grace The Buty of your face: Your Innosent and Virgin die Says onely Virtue there doth lie. Your yallow goldne dress Jelosie did Expresse; The Tincture gave to thee, So when you looke of mee Thought mee so too; then, if you please, T'is love's Jandes, that's a disease. Youre Sables, robe divine, Setts off the sacred Shrine, And shews the saynte that's thee, Still worshipt for to bee. Thus heaven onely sent you downe By Various shapes Virtue to crowne. 71 Love's pale Cheekes Thy Cheekes are pale, What doe they Ayle? Thy blood did slipp Into Each lipp. I wishe it may Ther Ever stay; But as I came them nigh, That rosey scarlett die Did presently mee flie; Div'd instantly, but wher? Looke, looke, oh, it is there, In thy sweet brest; I sweare They blushe for shame. It thither came; What was its Ayme? Was't modesty when spide, Your Virgin blood, when Ey'de, So from me it to hide? Oh, sunke againe, t'is so. Though buri'd ne'er so low I'l finde it, you shall knowe. With motion's heate Enlifne it; Love's Resurrection make it sitt In Triumph: who hereafter seekes, Shall finde it in thy lipps and cheekes. 72 The too serious Love Sweete, lett Us love Enjoy, And play and tick and Toye, And all our Cares will drowne; Smile, laugh, and sometymes frowne; Makes Love's Parenthasis With a sweete melting Kisse. Then Whisper in Each Eare, Love's pretty tales to heare; If wanton, cry, oh, man, And strike mee with your fanne; If offer thee to dandle, Then rap mee with the handle. For all this I'l not misse Thy lipps, but steale a kisse; Cause it is stolen, then I'l give it you againe; Play with your litle hand, And kisse it as I stand. Then, tho' you thinke it much, Wee'l one another touch, As carelesly not knowinge How love is now agrowinge; As if you did not minde it: Yett both of Us will finde it. And speake, too, all the while, But in a lover's stile: Short breath'd with love's omitions, Nonsence in Repetitions. If dare I am a Villan, Take notice you are willinge. Then flatter, kisse, cologe; You say, away, you Rogue. When your Cheekes redd, I'l pull thee, And gently then will cull thee: You say, away, so, so, Too serious you doe growe. 73 The Lyrick Poett The Lyrick Poett Nightingale, With love's songs shee doth never faile To warble forth love's sevrall Passions, With fine Expressions, sundry fashions, To make her love sick Male hopp to her, With love's sighs bowing so to wooe her. The Gentle Natur'd spoted Thrushe Such languadge Utters in her bushe As doth astonish those that heare her; Her lover then drawes somewhat neer her, With homage to her that sitts higher, Not Venter till shee calls him nigher. The Litle Bulfinche doth Expresse That love in her is no whitt lesse; Love's languadge both can speake and singe. Her lover moves with fluttring winge; Dansinge on tender bowes so light, Enamour'd kills him with the sight. The lovely Blackbird in her throate With trilloes sweetens Evry note; Arcadian love discourses then Beyond our high borne Sydne's penne. And I dare sweare, were their loves knowne, Language and witt putts downe our owne. 74 Love's fier I know I'm old, it is too true, Yett love, nay, am in love with you; Doe not dispise mee, or be Cruell, For thus I am love's best of fuell. No man can love more, or loves higher; Old and dry wood makes the best fier, Burnes cleerest, and is still the same, Turn'd all into a living flame. It lasts not long, is that your doubt, When am to ashes all burnt out? A short and lively heate that's pure, Will warme one best, though not indure. When young, wett wood makes but a smoake, And never warmes but doth you Choake; Though with your panting Bellows trie, That litle fier seemes to die; Smother'd in Vapours, dimly lies; Plesant, nor Usefull, spoyles your Eyes; Shivring for cold, Colder dispaire With sighinge in and out the Ayre. Thus Languishinge, take the pure fier That will warme the height of thy desier: Meeting in one, thine flame, thus seated, Continue longe, both warme and heated.</field>
   </doc>
</add>