<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Todhunter, John, 1839-1916</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Todhunter, John, 1839-1916</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">todhunter john 1839 1916</field>
      <field name="author_text">Todhunter, John, 1839-1916</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1910's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.2380.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1918</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:467446</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">From the Land of Dreams ; By John Todhunter. With an introduction by T. W. Rolleston</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">From the Land of Dreams ; By John Todhunter. With an introduction by T. W. Rolleston</field>
      <field name="title_facet">from the land of dreams</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">from the land of dreams</field>
      <field name="title_text">From the Land of Dreams ; By John Todhunter. With an introduction by T. W. Rolleston</field>
      <field name="year_display">1918</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1918</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1918</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467446&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467446&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Todhunter, John, 1839-1916&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;todhunter john 1839 1916&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;From the Land of Dreams ; By John Todhunter. With an introduction by T. W. Rolleston&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;from the land of dreams&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1918&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1918&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Todhunter, John&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1839&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1916&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;From the Land of Dreams&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By John Todhunter. With an introduction by T. W. Rolleston&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Dublin&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;The Talbot Press&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;T. Fisher Unwin&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1918&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp3940&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;xxii, 115, iv p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;From the Land of Dreams&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By John Todhunter. With an introduction by T. W. Rolleston&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 127 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted; verse reproduced elsewhere in The English Poetry Full-text Database omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DEDICATION I For all my fellow-countrymen, And women, East or West, For every kindly Irish heart Within an Irish breast; II All exiles for the Old Land who long, And those whose destinies Have held them in that Land of Dreams, Knowing no other skies; III For all abroad, and all at home, My songs to every wind I breathe, in hope one song of mine One Irish heart may find. LYRICS AND BALLADS AN INVOCATION O Memory, Nurse of Dreams, out of the night Steal to my hearth, and by the autumn fire Crouch like a Fairy woman, and fan the turf, Fan the sweet Irish sods until they glow! Then lay thine ear close to thy sounding shell, And listen, till within its winding caves The words of mystery wake; and to my spirit, Roaming the shadowy halls of lonely thought, Where deep it dwells, lamped by a sibylline star, Come visions of the never dying past. A golden youth flames in thy hoary hair And withered cheek, and all the world grows young In the soft shining of thy dream-lit eyes. Thou art the grave Recording Angel, calm As a bright cloud of dawn, and in thy voice The eternal deep that lies behind me calls To the eternal deep that lies before. DREAMS IN EXILE I LONGING I Oh! the sunshine of old Ireland when it lies On her woods and on her waters, And gleams through her soft skies Tenderly as the lovelight in her daughters' Faithful eyes! II Oh! the brown streams of old Ireland, how they leap From her glens, and fill their hollows With wild song, till charmed to sleep By the murmuring bees in meadows where the swallows Glance and sweep! III Oh! my home there in old Ireland, the old ways We had when I knew only The ways of one sweet place; Ere, afar from all I loved, I wandered lonely Many days. IV Oh! the springtime in old Ireland! O'er the sea I can smell our hawthorn bushes, And it all comes back to me— The sweet air, the old place, the trees, the cows, the thrushes Mad with glee. V I'm weary for old Ireland! Once again To see her fields before me In sunshine or in rain; And the longing in my heart, as it comes o'er me, Stings like pain. II SPRING I Oh! the flowers, the Irish flowers of my visionary home, In the fields where I wandered, where I wandered as a boy! In the meads where they were growing I could see the Shannon flowing, And growing still I see them, and my heart grows young in joy, In the sunny fields of memory ever in splendour blowing, Where Time's grey wings no shadow cast, the young hours to annoy. II Oh! the primroses with faces that looked from lonely places Wistfully on me, pearly with morning's early dew! When I dreamed, as children dream, by that legendary stream Where, agleam in shining mail, the slender dragonflies, I knew, Served our freaksome Irish fairies for steeds, as through the reeds They flitted on their blazoned wings, in mail of green and blue. III Oh! the cowslips in the grass, where the sunshine seemed to pass Like Spring's young life through all things, in the golden afternoon! Their scent, like Spring's first honey, made all the fields more sunny, And fairy money was their gold, that left me poor too soon Of my wealth gained in the meadows of the Spring, when I was king, With a cowslip crown upon me in the golden afternoon. IV Oh! the daisies, when they came with their stars of silver flame, The baby buds, in green with crimson caps, by fairies drest! Their breath of childhood lingers in my heart, as on my fingers Their smell when first I picked them in the pastures of the West; And when memory moves my longing for flowers of childhood's hours, The Spring comes rushing in my blood—they blossom in my breast. III SUMMER I Over the Wicklow hills the sun's vast blaze Palpitates in the abyss of azure bright; Dim through the splendour, in a pearly haze The glowing woodlands loom. Slow sail the white Swan-breasted argosies the ocean calm Of the blue air, their shadows drowsily Moving like dreams over the fields and flowers; And every field is pasture for the bee, Each flower a blithe voice in the fragrant psalm Antheming earth's delight in summer hours. II Like spirits clothed in light they shine and sing, In heaven's own loom woven are the robes they wear, Angels on every wind grace to them bring, And back to heaven their sweet oblations bear. The basking thyme sheds balm about my feet; The yellow iris o'er the marshy ground Flames, where the river wanders through the dale; The woodbine her grave incense breathes around; Red poppies blaze among the sunburnt wheat, And silver lamps gleam where the bindweeds trail. III But oh! the roses! Here hot afternoon Sleeps with her winds in this lone woodland glade Where shine the roses. Ah! fade not so soon, Sweet flowers, each winsome as an Irish maid. For when your last buds wane, and withered be Your frail immaculate petals red and white, This nook your delicate fragrance makes divine, Will seem the temple of a lost delight; Where, while ye breathe, to breathe is ecstasy, Embalming your brief hours in memory's shrine. IV The sun's heart still throbs through the luminous haze, I wander through the lost land of a dream; Heaven stoops to embrace earth, as she stands at gaze, Wondering at her own beauty in the stream. Summer in triumph comes to celebrate In magic robes her druid mysteries here; I feel the drowsy glamour of her eyes— Time swoons, earth dreams. What ancient gods appear? What mystic rites? What Kings in solemn state? What Bards, what Heroes from their gravemounds rise? V O Land of Dreams! O haunted Innisfail! O Land enchanted for a thousand years! O forlorn Land where sings no nightingale, Counting thy woes on rosaries of tears! Before me, cloudlike, sail wild visions by: High tragedies of passionate love and hate: Battles and festivals; heroic deeds, Orgies of crime. Some unappeased fate Hangs like dumb thunder in the brooding sky, And phantom fears come stalking through the meads. VI I wake—how far away! How long ago I roamed, that summer day, my spirit aflame With youth, ambition, hope, the rapturous glow Of courage born, when to my heart Love came, Singing the song that makes this world of ours Beautiful as a new-created star! Yet still, though Time, the spectre with grey hair, Bears me each day from youth's glad fields more far, I hear that song Love sang among the flowers, And pay no homage to the fiend Despair. IV AUTUMN I Now is the season of rewarded toil, When sunburnt labourers reap to sow again, And each lean handful cast into the soil Waits its rich usury; where the loaded wain, Heavy with harvest, lately left its track; For Mother Earth smiles on each golden grain, Pledge of man's trust in her who gives him back An hundredfold for one spared from her spoil. II What do men reap now in our Land of Dreams? What do they sow? Here, over stubbles, leas, And hills, a sultry mist of sunshine seems Deeply to brood, wakening old memories: Sad, patient eyes, in faces pinched and pale, Haunt me from days when Ireland's enemies, Famine and fever, in the Golden Vale Ravaged and slew, where Suir still flows and gleams. III Those days grow dim, and Ireland wakes at last Out of her Great Enchantment, and her eyes Turn from vain brooding o'er the bitter past, While in her dauntless heart new hopes arise; New songs, like streams outleaping from springs, Fill her glad vales with music, as though her skies With mellower music hearten him who sings; The Nation's blood begins to flow more fast. IV Now is our seedtime, when the sering leaves Whisper low dirges for the days gone by, With their dead children, to each wind that heaves The baring boughs. All things outworn must die, Yet, dying, quicken, as their life they yield, Earth and the air with a new potency; And every seeds finds in the furrowed field, Bare earth to-day, food for to-morrow's sheaves. V WINTER I Oh! those nights, those Winter nights By the fire, when the sweet brown turf-sods glowed; When the punch went round, and uncanny sights I saw in the flickering shadows, while flowed The talk when a neighbour or two dropped in; Or maybe old Tom the Fiddler would come, With: “God save all here!” and glad welcome win To a seat by the hearth, in our farm at home. II “Tom the Rover,” “Tom of the Tongue,” That could reel off stories, cap jest with jest, Tom the crony of old and young, Tom who could hold his own with the best. Oh! the keene, or the lilt of the strings when he played, When the girls came wheedling for “one more tune!” But God help the fools of whom hares he made! Try a fall with Tom, and he grassed you soon. III Oh! the stories I heard from him: Tales of Kings in the days of old, Merrows, changelings, and spectres grim, Tales that made my young blood run cold, Tales of humour, tales of romance, Of faithful lovers at odds with fate, Tales of the Irish Brigade in France, Tales of the horrors of Ninety-eight. IV Strange were the sights old Tom had seen: “The Headless Coach,” and the Leprechaun, And the fairies' court, where he danced with their Queen, When into her magic hill he'd gone. And “beyant by the bridge,” one moonlit night, There crouched the Banshee by the water side, “With a freckled face, an' she all in white, Thryin' over her keene for O'Neill that died.” V Oh! the rambles I had with him! He taught me the ways of beasts and birds; For he loved them all, fly, or walk, or swim, Made me know the lives we but docket with words. If Tom had his dreams he had eyes as well For the world God fashions for man's high school, The world that spins between heaven and hell, And His scholar, Tom, was no book-learn'd fool. VI O Tom, 'twas yourself made me laugh and cry! When our tunes come singing now in my ear, The old days come back, and clear to my eye The old place stands there, and the dead appear. They welcome me home at the door. I grasp My Father's hand, and his hearty voice Breaks on my name; I feel the clasp Of my Mother's arms by that door of joys! VII Ah! that door of joys! it opens for me Only in dreams, and never more Will open on earth, save when memory Brings back the days I have lived before. Ah! the life we lead here from day to day Is but a struggle for life, it seems, That finds us callow, that leaves us grey, Our spirits dwell in the Land of Dreams. VI A FENIAN'S RETURN (Inscribed to the Memory of John O'Leary) I From exile in a Land of the Stranger, I come, as from long voyage, eagerly, To her port with many a scar of many a billow, A ship comes flying, singing o'er the sea; Safe bearing in her weathered hull, storm-battered, Her cargo of things rare, As in my heart, their golden shrine, unshattered, My shipwrecked hopes I bear. II And here I stand, a stranger, yet no stranger, In Ireland, on the soil where first I knew, In the vision and the glamour of life's morning, The silent consecration of her dew; The dreams that came, like angels, in her sunlight, Ghosts in her twilight grey; The mystery and sadness of her moonlight, That was dearer than the day. III The sun fills heaven and earth with his last glory, And, like phantoms, through the veil of golden mist, Loom the Connemara mountains, huge and solemn, Hewn out of heaven's aerial amethyst. Plain and mountain dream, entranced in subtle splendour, Bog and pasture still the same, Gleam through miles of glowing light, and shadows tender In the palpitating flame. IV And the sunset-wind comes wandering out of Dreamland, That Dreamland where I wandered long ago, With whispering in my ear and ghostly singing, Druid words, and dirgelike music, sweet and low, Comes from far away, where lilies white are sailing On waters vast and cool, Comes o'er cotton-grass and myrtle softly wailing, And through rushes by the pool. V In the bog stand three lonely pine-trees, Waifs of fortune, planted there by Fate's grim choice, And the wind wails o'er the bog, and in their branches, And thrills me with solitary voice; Like the Spirit of an ancient Desolation It comes wailing o'er the West, And the burden of its ancient lamentation Is echoed in my breast. VI The wind wails o'er the bog, and in the pine-trees, With an Irish note of sorrow, soft and wild, And old memories of dead days come with its wailing, Till the heart in me is weeping like a child. It wafts to me the smell of turf-sods burning In some cabin far away, And the homelike Irish odour sets me yearning For a hearth—cold many a day. VII Oh! the story of my home, the dismal story, The story of a thousand homes like mine: The four walls in their grave-grass, cold the hearth stone, Dead my kin, or driven like felons o'er the brine! Raise the keene, O wind! for Ireland's ancient sorrow, O'er the desolated West! Raise the keene for our dead hopes of her tomorrow, The pale treasures of my breast! VIII Yet, like sweet, remembered kisses of my Mother, I feel each Irish sight, and scent, and sound; Like her love I feel the tender Irish twilight With gentle consolation clasp me round. Oh! the magical, drear beauty of this lone land, Oh! its welcome, sad and wild! To the Mother's breast of Ireland, of my own land, I come, weeping like a child! VII TIR-N'AN OG TIR N'AN OG. The legend of Tir n'an Og, “The Land of the Young,” is the Irish version of the legend of the Island Atlantis. The Irish tradition is that there was once an Island in the Atlantic, sometimes visible from the West Coast of Ireland. It was inhabited by a race of happy magicians, beautiful and unscathed by evil, who never grew old. Sometimes their Island floated on the surface of the Atlantic, and sometimes it sank under the waters; but when the Sun of the Earth mingled his beams with those of his sunken brother, the Island rose and floated on the waves. And many who saw it went mad, and sailed in search of it; but were lost or shipwrecked. But some who saw the vision were content with that, and became Poets. I On a cliff in the West, the shy wild West, The ecstatic, tender, desolate West, Sits, in a nook where the sea-pink shakes to the surges Thundering far down, a Boy. II Far before him, Thronging the dusk-blue waste of waters, Foam on their way, like untamed sea-horses, Rearing, plunging, the giant waves. Over the waves uncouthly careering Loom in the gleaming amber sky Grey clouds: in their smouldering fringes Fiery embers of sunset, fading, Turn ashen pale. III All alone sits the Boy, and gazes, Dumb, with the wistful eyes of a peasant— Sits, while the memoried blood of Kings, Long lines of legendary Kings, Whispers to his heart that listens Wordless magic lore, as he gazes, Dumbly dreaming. IV Far below him, Landward, with heaving, gleaming shoulders, Charge, with a thousand miles of onset, In crested legions, the ocean-rovers, The huge Atlantic waves. V Bellowing, foaming, the ocean-rovers, The moon-adoring, fanatic waves, Armed with the sea's eternal thunder, Swoln with the sea's mad conqueror's lust, Storm at the bastions of the land, Ever shattered, advancing ever. VI Fresh blows the wind, the wind of the West, The Irish wind! Like a lusty lover He woos on the crags the tufted sea-pink, With sea-salt kisses; And high on the cliff's brow he overmasters With fierce caresses the lissome cliff-grass, That quivers and bends, as she vainly wrestles, Faintly hissing. VII O wizard wind, alchemic wind, Seed-bearing wind of change! O wind whose seeds are dreams! O brine-soaked, soft, caressing wind! The Boy too feels it over him swooping, With downy wing-strokes and gentle buffets, And moan in his ears, as of far sea-music, A vast, invisible owl of the sea; And his Irish blood exults in the wind, And sings in his veins as the wind blows through him. It comes, through sad farewells of day, From the Land of the Sunken Sun, Tir-n'an Og, fathoms down, whelmed by the insolent sea, A thousand fathoms down. VIII But, when the Magian Sun, to walk the Western waters, Dons his enchanter's robe, and pacing the cold waves, From Ireland turns his face, Tir-n'an Og, fathoms down, Feels his faint smile of dawn, and rises dim, and sits A spectre on the waters—the Land no voyage makes, The Land of Youth! IX The West-wind blows, blows Over Ireland, The Land of Dreams, Bearing dreams from the Land of Youth; And the Boy sits there, and dreams Till the spirit of youth within him Goes forth on airy wings, a measureless way, As he dreams—dreams. X Twilight comes, and the stars Shyly peep through the purpling heavens And the lone Evening Star, Thridding the waning, withering clouds, In gentle splendour, slowly, Follows, dreaming, the steps of the Sun; And she casts her silver spell On the roaring waves, and their giant voices Boom with a drowsier thunder. Then, leaving the sea, the ghostly sea-gulls Gleam, and fade, and suddenly vanish; And high in air, unseen, the curlews Pass with a desolate cry; and shyly Sad-eyed seals, brown dogs of the ocean, Sleek from the sea on the rocks come landing. XI And the Boy feels deep within him Longings vague, like eerie harp-notes, Wake at the curlew's whistle bleak, And the soft bark of the seal; and with longing Swells his heart, as he sits and gazes, Alone with his dreams, and the murmuring sea, And the beautiful, sad stars. SONGS MEETING I O come to me in the morning, white Swan of the thousand charms, Or come to me in the passion of day, the rapture of noon, Or come to me in the twilight hour, sweet Longing of my arms, In the hush when day kisses night, our two hearts beating one tune! II Though Time on his owl-soft wings bring parting of our feet, Oh! never my heart from yours will wander, come day, come night. And never my lips forget your kiss that the world made sweet, Or my heart the song of my love in that hour of its young delight! PARTING I You come, and the little rhymes come singing in my heart, And where you are their music wakes trembling in my breast; When you go from me, O my sorrow! they spread their wings and depart, Like birds from a lonely nest. II They fly to where you make summer, and leave me cold, Their nest forsaking, they leave me cold and alone, And my heart is a lonely sorrow, a sorrow not to be told, Its music a weary moan! A SONG OF THE RAIN (A Girl stands at a window) I The rain, the rain, the rain upon the pane, How it spirts and ceases, As the spite of the gale increases, Then pauses and dies again! II The rain-drops fallen out of the skies Hang upon the pane, Gather, and fall slowly, like tears from lovers' eyes When they know their weeping is vain. III The rain, the rain, the rain from over the plain Comes drenching, splashing The pane, as the lightning flashing Leaps out, and is gone again. IV The rain-drops pine for their home in the skies, And vanish from the pane; Yet still my tears are falling slow from these lonely eyes, Though I know my weeping is vain. VOICES I Oh! the voices of the wind, the soft sweet voices, The melancholy voices of the wind, Bear me gently to the peaks of ancient vision, The lone and silent mountains of the mind; And the spirit of old Ireland to my spirit Speaks like solitude, and desolately fills Their silence with the passion I inherit From her valleys and her hills. II Pale Kings, and hoary Druids in procession Pass me sighing, with old sorrow in their eyes; While the wind, the passionate wind, with fitful wailing In his airy tongue of mystery replies. Grave Kings, and Bards, and Druids without number Pass by me with the wind whereon they pass, Sweeping o'er me like a terror felt in slumber, As a windflaw sweeps the grass. III The Danann gods pass by, majestic phantoms, Like shining clouds, bright children of the morn; But the gods of gloom have dimmed their ancient splendour, Where, like wizards, in their tombs they dwell forlorn; Where their beauty they have hidden from derision, Whence they wander, veiled in storm or twilight grey; But their beauty still shines on the peaks of vision, And shall never pass away. IV There the Daghda walks the wind, the great Mor Riga Floats beside him to the hosting of their clan, Angus ?g is there, grey Lir, B?v Derg, and Cleena, VOICES. The Danann gods and goddesses were the descendants of the Daghda (Father) and his wife Dana, The Mor Riga (great queen), who was the war goddess. Angus Og, The Love-god, was the Irish Eros. Lir was a sea-god, like his son Manannan, and Cleena ruled over one of the three magic waves, which roared on the coast of Ireland when danger threatened. Bov Derg was King of the Dananns. Queen of the moaning wave, and Manannan; Their voice is on the winds, their druid power Enchants with youth and love the Land of Dreams, Their beauty and their glamour are the dower Of her mountains, vales and streams. V There is music on the winds and o'er the waters, They are singing still, the wandering Swans of Lir, Silver-pure the voice of love-inspired Fianola, Through the long night of enchantment ringing clear; Like the voice of Ireland's heart she makes the nightwind Ache with wild hopes that in her breast are sore, Till the red wind from the East, her spirit's blight wind, Shall have power to blight to more. VI There are voices on the peaks of ancient vision, They call the dreamers in the Land of Dreams; The young men hear, and wake, and in the morning Go singing through her vales and by her streams; Making music that shall win the world hereafter, Making songs that shall go ringing down the years Of tears that weep within the house of laughter, Of joys baptized in tears. THE LIANAN SHEE THE LIANAN SHEE. “The Lianan Shee” is an evil demon, half siren and half vampire, and is a type of jealousy in the poem that bears her name. She is said to have been originally a Nature Goddess. (A Tragedy of Dreams) I She waits for me upon Death's gloomy shore, Pale, in that pale and lonely grove where dwell Those who have set for portress at Love's door Jealousy, stern and unappeasable. II She sends me bitter and remorseful dreams, That ice the wholesome rivers of my blood, Crawling about my brain on their cold streams, With endless memories in the sluggard flood. III I walk in dreams by a dark raging sea, And she beside me with implacable face, Dead, with wide lids where through gaze wistfully The accusing eyes, and through my heart they gaze. IV I lie in dreams as in a living tomb, And she, death-pale, her cheek with tears long marred, Comes hovering like a vampire through the gloom, Craving some comfort, but my heart is hard. V She hunts my soul in dreams; the hounds of thought Chase me through dense thickets of tangling thorn, The woods of old remorse—till I am caught, And wake, still shuddering, in the ghastly morn. THE NAMELESS ONES I Through the stately Mansions of Endeavour Blow the winds, the sleepless winds of wild desire; And the mansions in their fashion change for ever, Replying to the sighing of the winds of wild desire. II All around the Mansions of Endeavour Flow the waters, deep and strong, of wild desire; And fair dreams out of their waves are born for ever, The daughters of the waters, deep and strong, of wild desire. III Deep below the Mansions of Endeavour Glow the flames, the passionate flames of wild desire; And the building-stones, like opals, change for ever, Their hues, while slow they fuse within the flames of wild desire. IV For the Nameless Ones come building and destroying, In the winds, and rushing waters, and fierce flames of wild desire; And their passion moulds that music, ever changing, never cloying, Which is life in all the worlds, in man's heart a wild desire. THE HOUR OF FATE I Things dead and things unborn are flying, And thinly wail on the wind tonight, Like hungry changelings I hear them crying Round the Dark Moon's den in the wan starlight. II My Saint and Angel have hid their faces, My dead sins daunt me with spells tonight, And sins unborn tempt from unseen places, Their glamour works in the wan starlight. III The past betrays me, the Future thralls me, Fate's hour of power is my hour of blight; My frail soul falters—the dread voice calls me, The deed I hate I shall do tonight. THE SUMMONS O hosts without a name! O unappeasable powers! O wandering forms of Love, and Beauty, and Heart's-ease! Why is it ye disturb with dreams men's fading hours? Why is it still the promise, never the gift, of peace? Your music, your wild singing, came to me out of the air, Alluring, promising, in one mysterious word Of the great Voice that thrilled old Silence in her lair, Ere the stars for their first flight their mighty wings had stirred: One summons from that realm where things unuttered sleep With the unawakened Beauty hidden from desire, Challenging, maddening me, mocking all things that weep, Till my spirit was a wild wind, my heart a wind-blown fire. My heart was an eddying flame, my spirit a rushing wind, Fierce joy, fierce pain, seized me in that mysterious word; My heart consumed my life, my spirit left me lonely, Following your sweet alluring song—left me behind, Knowing not where I was, or went; believing only The vision that I saw, the music that I heard. The sunset's dying glow was paling in the sky, And twilight, from the visionary land where silence dwells, Stole o'er the gleaming fields, shedding tranquillity Like dew, o'er bawn and pasture, o'er woods and ferny dells; But lingering day's farewell grew sad with all farewells. Following the sun's footsteps through the heavens, where yet no star Heralded Night, that now with all her hosts drew nigh, Only the Planet of Love shone in the delicate sky, Only the Planet of Love looked sad from heaven on me; While through the deepening gloam, over the hills afar, Throbbed a faint orange flame. The ancient mystery Of day's decline entranced the earth. Light's quivering wand Drew from the fields of air their tenderest newborn hues, And made the earth divine. There in the hallowing gleam, Beside her cottage door I saw my Mother stand, At peace with age. Numb woe for all things I must lose, Following the airy music, following the flying dream, Troubled my heart. The cows trooped to the milking shed, Lowing; the grave poplars, and the sallies by the stream, Felt the sad spell of the sky; but I was as one dead, And all familiar things I loved phantoms did seem. The old place knew me no more—the solitary ghost Haunting the fields awhile. A robin from a tree Warbled his last sweet rapturous litany. The host Of airy singers calling troubled not him, I knew; But only me. And there, in the sweet twilight hour, My Love was waiting me; whom those wild voices drew Away from home and her! And now their magic power Made me but as a billow when the moon compels; My heart grew drowsy—closed, when closed each innocent flower, My chilling heart shut close. They called—called through Love's hour— They called, and I must follow, lured by their wildering spells; And the farewell of day shone sad with all fare-wells. THE QUEST I The thin rain is falling, With a sigh the reeds quiver, And the cow-herds are calling Beyond the dark river. II There is gloom in the sky, In my heart desolation, As the cold mist creeps by With a dumb lamentation. III Like a bird to her nest I came, weary of roaming, With a fear unconfest I sped on through the gloaming. IV From the ends of the earth Oh! the longing that drew me To the place of my birth, To the fields that once knew me; V To my home! the bare walls Of my dream have bereft me, The chill spectre appals The lone days that are left me. VI There is gloom in my heart, In my home desolation, Like a ghost I depart With a dumb lamentation. FAIRY GOLD (A ballad of Forty-eight) I Buttercups and daisies in the meadow, And the children pick them as they pass, Weaving in the sunshine and the shadow Garlands for each little lad and lass; Weave with dreams their buttercups and daisies As the children did in days of old; Will the dreams, like sunlight in their faces, Wither with their flowers, like Fairy Gold? II Once, when lonely in life's crowded highway, Came a maiden sweet, and took my hand, Led me down Love's green delightful byeway, Led me wondering back to Fairyland. Ah! Death's envious eyes that light on lovers Looked upon her, and her breast grew cold; Now my heart's delight the green sod covers, Vanished from my arms like Fairy Gold. III Then to Ireland, my long-striving nation, That poor hope life left me still I gave, With her dreams I dreamed, her desolation Found me, called me, desolate by that grave. Once again she raised her head, contending For her children's birthright, as of old, Once again the old fight had the old ending, All her hopes and dreams were Fairy Gold. IV Now my work is done, and I am dying, Lone, an exile on a foreign shore, But in dreams roam with my Love that's lying, Lonely in the Old Land I'll see no more. Buttercups and daisies in her meadows When I'm gone will bloom; new hopes for old Comfort her with sunshine after shadows, Fade no more away like Fairy Gold! A MAY MADRIGAL I May comes clad in gleaming gold, The world grows young that was so old, All so sweet, all so fair, Birds are singing everywhere; Come away! Come sing and answer them again, Answer, boys and girls again, And welcome in the May! II Mary guard the woods from teen, Donning now their virgin green! All be fair, all be sweet, Where in the woodlands lovers meet! All who love true Come and charm the woods with song, Glad voices charm the woods with song, And welcome Love in too! MAUREEN I Oh! you plant the pain in my heart with your wistful eyes Girl of my choice, Maureen! Will you drive me mad for the kisses your shy sweet mouth denies, Maureen! II Like a walking ghost I am when I come to woo, White Rose of the West, Maureen; For it's pale you are, and the fear that's on you is over me too, Maureen! III Sure it's one complaint that's on us asthore, this day, Bride of my dreams, Maureen! The smart of the bee that stung us its honey must cure they say, Maureen! IV I'll coax the light to your eyes, and the rose to your face, Mavourneen, my own Maureen, When I feel the warmth of your breast, and your nest is my arms' embrace, Maureen! V Oh! who was the King of the World that day only me, My one true love, Maureen? And you the Queen with me there, and your throne in my heart, machree, Maureen! A DAY OF THE DAYS I Faint red the rowan-berries in the glen begin to turn, The wind is whispering to the woods the rune of their decay, Those woods where once upon my lips I felt your kisses burn, Where we met, and where we parted—it seems but yesterday. II Through all their breathing branches the spirits of the trees Whispered of love that day; and we, breathing their passionate breath, Trembled before the flaming veil that hid love's mysteries— Where now, alone, I bow before the mystery of death. III Martyrs of Love and Hope we stood, and in each other's eyes Read the sweet secret of our love; and that transfiguring day, Which crowned my spirit with grace to bear the sorrow that makes wise, From that spirit's Holy-places will never pass away. ATHLONE I Och wirrasthrue for Ireland, and ten times wirrasthrue For the gallant deeds, and the black disgrace of the tale I'm tellin' you! 'Twill kindle fire inside your heart, then freeze it to a stone, To hear the truth of that bad day, and the way we lost Athlone. II O where was then bold Colonel Grace, and Sarsfield, where was he, When Ginkel came from Ballymore with his big artillery? 'Twas fifty battering guns he brought, and mortars half a score, And our half-dozen six-pounders there to meet him, and no more. III They took from us the English town, yet fighting, breast to breast, We held the drawbridge, one to ten; for we were sorely prest. But we cheered and charged, and they gave us ground, and when their Colonel fell A good half furlong from the bridge we drove them back pell-mell. IV We held them till to the Irish town our rearguard could retreat Across the bridge o'er Shannon's arm, shrunk by the Summer's heat. The fuse we lit, then back we sprang; behind, the drawbridge rose, And the two arches of the bridge blew up among our foes. V We laughed at Ginkel's shot and shell; for St. Ruth came up next day, And it raised the cockles of our hearts to see his grand array; But black the hour when Sarsfield chafed under his high command, For, in his pride and jealousy, he left him no free hand. VI Small help we got from that French Chief, when there he just sat down To guard the fords, and pitched his camp a mile outside the town. Our guns dismounted, shot and shell thinned our undaunted ranks And with our firelocks, four hard days, we kept the Shannon's banks. VII We made a breastwork on the bridge; but they burnt it on us soon With their damned grenades. It blazed like thatch in the hot sun of June— And beams they laid from arch to arch, nailed planks on every beam. They thought to rush our last defence, and cross the Shannon stream. VIII But one we had, thank God!—a bold Dragoon, Custume by name, Sergeant in Maxwell's troop; and now to that hectorin' Scot he came; “Give me ten more to go with me, and by my soul,” says he, “We'll try the job, and, live or die, we'll spoil their carpentry!” IX “Hoots!” Maxwell sneers, “wha volunteers?” Out stepped some two score men. “Fall in then, boys, reserves an' all!” says Custume an' picked his ten. They gave their souls to God, each man his breastplate buckled on, In the hope he'd maybe keep his life till a plank or two was gone. X I'll see till death, as I see him now, Custume, as brave and cool, He schemed for every man his place; for 'twas he was no French fool. Then on the bridge before our eyes a glorious deed was wrought, In vain with our best blood that day Athlone was dearly bought. XI Five plankers ripped the planks away, a sawyer at each beam; We heard the steady teeth at work, saw axe and crowbar gleam; But from the startled English lines arose a sudden yell, From flank to flank the muskets flashed, and sent their hail of hell. XII We answered with our small-arms; but 'twas little we could do, Minute by minute on the bridge they dropped by one and two; But as each man fell a man as good ran out to take his place, And the work went on—my God! 'twas hard they strove to win that race! XIII At last the planks were gone, one beam was loosened in its bed; But man by man fell round it in that murtherin' rain of lead. Custume came there, blood on his face, a crowbar in his hand— O blessed Saints, keep the life in him to launch it from our land! XIV The heel gives—God be praised, it's down! We saw him stagger then: “Work hearty, Boys, an' we'll keep Athlone!” he shouted to his men. But his heart blood gushed with those brave words. The Shannon's waters bright Were his last bed, and in their arms they took him from our sight. XV They worked the lustier for that shout, and the beams fell one by one, But the place was just one slaughter-yard before the last was gone. They shot the wounded where they crawled, to leave their comrades room, Or struggling in the water grasped at the flaggers full in bloom. XVI Each man was killed twice over, and of two and twenty men But two poor boys, as pale as ghosts came back to us again. We scarce could rise a cheer for them; for 'twas like an awful dream; But the last scantling, with our dead, went down the Shannon stream. XVII But what's the use of dauntless men, to make a gallant stand, When all they've won is thrown away by fools in high command? My curse be on St. Ruth, cold friend in our last extremity: “'Tis hanging I'd deserve,” he bragged, “if they took the town on me.” XVIII But they crossed the Shannon's dwindled stream, that left us in their power, And the town we held for ten long days, was lost in one slack half-hour, St. Ruth died well on Aughrim field; but ten deaths could ne'er atone For the shame and the blame of that bad day, and the way he lost Athlone. THE FACE OF DREAMS I Where may I hide my loneliness and sorrow? Where sings the bird that sang upon the tree, When you and I were young, and feared no bleak to-morrow, And trusted Love to lead us through the years that were to be? II The days, the years went by, the days we lived and loved, When you and I were young, and sat beside the river, Glad as all happy things that round us lived and moved, And he heard the blackbird sing, saw the whispering aspens quiver. III The days, the years go by, like eddies in a stream, That seem the same, yet glide from change to change for ever; I feel them pass and change, and still I dream and dream Of one sweet face, that save in dreams comes to me never. A MOMENT I “Was that the wind?” she said, And turned her head To where, on a green bank, the primrose flowers Seemed with new beauty suddenly endowed, As though they gazed out of their mortal cloud On things unseen, communing with strange powers. II Then upon that green place Fell a new grace, As when a sun-gleam visits drops of dew, And every drop shines like a mystic gem, Set in the front of morning's diadem, With hues more tender than e'er diamond knew. III And something seemed to pass— As through the grass The presence of the gentlest wind will go— Delicately through her bosom and her hair, Till, with delight, she found herself more fair, And her heart sang, unutterably low. THE CHILDREN'S WARD 'Tis the Good Shepherd's fold, his holy ground: With genial face, between a smile and tear, Old Father Christmas, bustling on his round, With presents for the children has been here. The Children's Ward: there, in her little cot, Her wasted face wise with long suffering, A little patient girl, a hectic spot Branding each cheek, her soul upon the wing. Poor tiny child! A grave motherly light Veils now her glittering eyes. In mother's pride Clasped to her bosom, lovingly and tight, With one thin arm, her doll sleeps at her side. All sickness now, all pain, all weariness Are lost in love. The dumb thing at her breast Comforts her hungry heart: in that caress Her suffering finds relief, her longing, rest. MEMORIES I Whence, at what summons, what faint-whispered sigh From life's fall'n leaves, what vanished voice's tone, Come ye, the gentle train of Memory, In that sweet hour when thought dreams on her throne? Ye twilight elves who people solitude, And are the undying children of dead hours, My phanton self dwells with your glimmering host, Charmed from night's envious brood; Ye crown my days with amaranthine flowers, And I live on, in ghostly lands a ghost. II I pass into the fairyland of dream, As one might pass into the world we see Deep in lone woodland pool or quiet stream, With tenderer skies and mellower greenery. I tread the mossy silence of dim ways Where sunshine, through the leaves of long ago, Haunts the still glades, and holds in solemn trance Long aisles where bygone days Whisper their tales, and memory's afterglow Clothes my grey past in splendour of romance. III Ah! do ye live in me, or I in you, Memories, that bring me in your phantom hands A sound, a sense, an odour, or a hue; As though the past, eternal in the sands Fallen from Time's glass, and even as they fell, Caught by Death's angel in his hallowing urn, Were garnered there without decay or stain? The day wherein we dwell, Fled with life's pageant, never to return, Is it a dream that may be dreamed again? IV The sweet remembered fragrance of a rose, Long withered, in a garden ruined long, Breathes round me—lo! the cloudy gates unclose! I am there again, and hear the blackbird's song In life's glad morn: a crushed geranium-leaf Sheds balm, and through the old house that stands no more I move, with beating heart, from room to room; And where the eyes of grief Looked in Death's eyes, meet those I loved of yore, Truants from time and change, as from the tomb. V The self within us burns, a lonely star, And knows not its own form, sees not its light, Save mirrored in the shapes passing afar From birth to death o'er the abyss of night, Finding itself in that reflected beam Which kindles in the House of Memory Her pale phosphoric flame. And round that flame, Moths in her lantern's gleam, Appear the ghostly train of things that die, Yet piteously awhile evade Death's claim. VI As feathers shaken from the wings of Time Seem the pale memories whereby we live; Lingering awhile, then melting like the rime. The self we know as frail and fugitive. But in God's House weaves Mother Memory After Death's feet the web of life anew, Creation's dream lives in her arras bright; Where her swift shuttles fly God shines eternal in each drop of dew, All moments live immortal in His sight. VERSES FOR MUSIC WAITING I Lone is my waiting here under the tree, Under our tree of the woods, where I wait and wait; Why loiter those white little feet that would bring you to me, Where are the warm sweet arms that are leaving me desolate, Oona, asthore mochree? II Oona, the woods are sighing—they sigh and say: The wind of summer will pass like a lover's sigh, And love's glad hour as lightly passes away; Come to me then, ere my longing hope of despair shall die, Oona, asthore mochree! A SONG OF THE SPRING I The leaves are springing, The woodlands ringing With birds' love-words in Love's golden tongue; The blue air winging, Glad larks are singing, For Spring is come, and my heart is young. II Oh! the mirth Of the Spring's new birth, The joy that never was told or sung, As round the girth Of the wakening earth She flies, and laughing makes all things young! A COMPLAINT I Like a stone on my heart grief's come to lie, Sadly as phantoms my days go by, Though shines the sun at our cottage door. He gilds the corn with the year's first gold, While through my veins the sick blood creeps cold: My Heart's Beloved comes never more! II Grief my handmaid, I sit and spin, With grief my comrade go out and in, I lay the table, I sweep the floor; But all I do is a senseless dream, And here a stranger myself I seem; For my Heart's Beloved comes never more! III Grief lies awake in my bed with me, Like dim corpse-candles the stars I see, When the moon shines in, as she did before; O mother, mother! her face I dread, 'Tis like the face on my own death-bed, Since my Heart's Beloved comes never more. THE SALLY-TREE I There's a sally standing by the river, Ah Mary! why is it standing there? To make a garland for my hair, For my lover is gone from me for ever; And that's why it stands there! II There's a thrush that sits on that sally-tree, Ah Mary! why is he sitting there? He sings the song of my lonely care For the lover that cares no more for me; And that's why he sits there! III The wind comes keening in that sally-tree, Ah Mary! why is it keening there? It keenes the keene of my heart's despair, For the lover that's gone, that's gone from me; And that's why it's keening there! DREAMS How oft in this mad world we lose our way, Dazed by the glamour of Love's romantic moon, Or young Ambition's meteors, fading soon, In the fierce light of disenchanting day! And yet by dreams we live, our house of clay Haunted by dead men's dreams. Dreamers have hewn Columns for Wisdom's temple, where each June Brings dewy flowers to crown her seers grown grey. The gods reveal themselves in dreams. In dreams We feel the unseen Spirit whose power impels The labouring earth. To dream is still to hope, Hope leads our upward feet. Our dreams are spells To wake the god within. Dreaming we grope After the splendour that before us gleams. BARDIC TALES THE WAVES' LEGEND ON THE STRAND OF BALA I The sea moans on the strand, Moans over shingle and shell; O moaning sea! what sorrowful story Do thy wild waves tell? II Ever they moan on the strand, And my ear, like a sounding shell, Chants to me the sorrowful story The moaning billows tell: III For Bala the Sweet-Voiced moan! Here on the lonely strand Fell Bala, Prince of the Race of Rury, Slain by no foeman's hand. IV Sweet was your tongue, O Bala, To win men's love; your voice Made sigh for you the maids of Eman; But nobler was your choice. V She gave for your heart her heart, Warm in her swan-white breast, Aillin of Laigen, Lugah's daughter, The fairest bird of his nest. VI Their pledge was here by the shore To meet, come joy or pain; And swift in his war-car Bala from Eman Sped o'er the sundering plain. VII He found her not by the shore, Gloom was o'er sea and sky, And a man of the Shee with dreadful face On a blast from the south rushed by. VIII Said Bala: “Stay that man! Ask him what word he brings?” “A woe on the Dun of Lugah! A woe On Eman of the Kings! IX “Wail for Aillin the Fair! Wail for him her feet Were swift to seek on the lonely strand Where they shall never meet! X “Swift were her feet on the way, Till me she meet on her track, A hound of swiftness, a shape of fear, A tiding to turn her back. XI “Swift are the lover's feet, But swifter our malice flies! I told her: Bala is dead; and dead In her sunny house she lies.” XII He scowled on Bala and rose A wrath of the mist, and fled Like a wind-rent cloud; and suddenly Bala, With a great cry, fell dead. XIII So moans the sea on the strand, Moans over shingle and shell. O moaning sea, of many a sorrow These wild waves tell! THE DEATH OF CONLAOCH THE DEATH OF CONLAOCH. This Tale belongs to the last cycle of Bardic Tales, the Ultonian Cycle of the Red-Branch, The Men of Ulster, whose King was Conchobar, “Hound of Help.” Con, or Cu, means a hound, and the great Irish wolfhound was regarded as the noblest of animals, and therefore the word forms a part of the names of many of the Red-Branch Champions. Cuchullain means Hound of Culan, the great smith, who forged armour and chariots for the Ulstermen. Cuchullain when a boy was named Setanta, and once, roving with his hurl and ball, he came to the workshop of Culan, where he was attacked by a fierce dog, who guarded the door. This dog he killed with his hurl; but on hearing the lamentation of Culan over his faithful guard, he promised to take the dog's place and defend the door. Hence his Champion's name. The Champion's vow, laid upon Conlaoch by his mother, is an instance of the strange vows laid upon the Champions when their training in all manly exercises and feats of war was finished, and they “took their spears” from their teachers, or from the King's hand. These vows often produced fatal consequences, as they took precedence of all other obligations. The vow of Fergus, never to refuse a feast, led to the death of the sons of Usna, whom he had promised to accompany to Conchobar's court, and protect them there. THE BARD'S PRELUDE I O Strand of the sorrowful waves! O Strand of Bala! Once more The wind-swept grass of your dunes is my whispering bed, and I hear The songs your sorrowful waves moan always along the shore, The old stories your winds through the grass come whispering in my ear. II They whisper, and all the coast is a druid mist in my eyes, And my heart is a glory of flame, like a dewdrop's heart, when the sun Kindles its heavenly colours; and round me clear visions rise, As the eye within me opens, and my Path of the Seers is won. THE SON OF AIFÉ Among the pines of Alba was the birth Of Conlaoch; when the salt, sad winds of the sea, On a wild night of storm, o'er Scatha's dun Moaned in the branches; and around the house The gulls and curlews cried, ere his first wail Was answered by the bleak roar of the surf. There, by her daughter's couch, with murmured spells To stay his coming till the lucky hour Of birth should look on Aifé and her babe, Sat red-maned Scatha; while, without a groan, The mother lay, hating her child unborn. With loathing and contemptuous bitterness She smelt the balmy fume of magic herbs Cast by the old sorceress on the glowing turf, And heard the birth-rune wrathfully; and thus Storm on the sea, storm in his mother's heart, He passed the gates of birth. But magic herbs And chanted spells are weak to stay the loom Of those grey weavers, in whose gleaming web Dark powers with fateful dyes the threads imbue; And his good hour looked on the boy too late. That Scatha knew; yet cried: “A child is born, Beautiful in his form, and in his heart The seed of valour. Conlaoch be his name— A Hound of War!” So Conlaoch came, the flower Of a noble tree; for when in Scatha's School Cuchullain learnt the mystery of arms: The seven feats of dexterity and strength, The nine great feats of valour, of all there He had the mastery, save of one alone, Aifé, and her he strove with day by day, A year's four seasons, and vanquished her at last; For love had tamed her fierceness, and her proud heart Turned to her conqueror. Short was the delight She had with him. Soon the untarrying morn She hid from in her lover's arms, yet knew With every pulse's beat stole ever nearer, A sorrow on the track of her glad hours Not to be stayed, came swooping from the East On silent wings. It chilled her bodeful heart, And passing looked on her with its bleak eyes, And left joy slain. Cuchullain must go forth To take his champion's arms from Conchobar. Sad was their parting; and there upon the strand Cuchullain took from Aifé's hand a spear Armed with an eastern dragon's venemous teeth By Bolg, the Son of Buan. “Take it,” she said. “I give thee here no spindle of a girl, Wherewith she spins man's comfort in soft wool. Round the red Queen of Carnage, when she weaves The web of death, and spears, her shuttles, fly, No spear so deadly sings above the slain.” The ghastliest love-gift ever woman gave She gave him then. Five were the battle-horns, Stronger than steel and sharp in point and blade, Arming its head, and in its raging breast Lurked the slain dragon's malice. With wistful eyes She looked upon him, saying, “Remember me By this, my gift—my last gift; for I know That, parting now, we part for evermore. No more may thou and I in happy days Meet in these woods, or walk on this white strand. Farewell! That spear will be thy last defence, And keep thy life in many a dreadful hour.” Cuchullain lightly wielded it, and smiled, “The voice of all the rivers of my veins Sings in my heart for this great gift my thanks! A warrior's life, my love, is not his own; But count me fooled by some forgetful spell, Or some rash vow, if I come back no more; Since here I hold death to my enemies Life to myself.” To her he gave a ring, Saying: “Out of the mingling of our blood A proud hope, Aifé, smiles upon us now, A child of joy, in whom our love shall flower In such a flame of valour as never yet Shone where keen blades reap the red sheaves of war. Thou hast taught me how to woo thee as men woo Strong warrior queens; teach him all sleights of arms We used against each other, when we played The glorious game of war, the battle-glee In our fierce hearts. And when the boy is grown, If I live still, send him to me, this ring Upon his hand, that we may meet in joy.” “That will I do,” she said, “though false or true His father prove himself.” She took the ring And fiercely clasped her lover, with a kiss That might have kindled love in a dead heart. So parted they, and Aifé from the shore Waved her sad last farewell, while the swift bark Fled like a gull, vanishing o'er the sea. THE SENDING OF CONLAOCH. Before her child was born, from o'er the sea, In a bad hour, this news to Aifé came: “Cuchullain weds with Emer.” In her ear, And in her jealous heart, that message dwelt, Poisoning the sweet springs of her motherhood While the child grew. Love battling with dark hate Strove in the storms of her breast; yet the boy grew, No blemish on him, beautiful and strong, The child of love, not hate; blithe as a fawn, And fearless as a hound of noble race; Yet gently he endured his mother's moods, And when she raged would coax her from her spleen With some bright roguish answer, deftly shot Athwart her bitter humour, like a ray Of sunshine through the lowering of a storm. As an oak sapling planted by a stream He grew and throve under his mother's eyes— Sad eyes too proud for tears; now soft awhile, Surprised by love; now cold and fierce again, Sternly she trained him in all games of war, Till in the School of Scatha every feat His father did no worse did he, the down Of manhood on his face. But when his thumb Could hold his father's ring, grimly she set That ring upon his hand, and laid upon him Three champion's vows; the first: “Ne'er to go back Before a living man, but sooner die”; The second: “Never to avoid the proof Of battle, though the champion of the world Frowned in his face; but sooner die”; the third: “For any man's fair word, or threat of death, Never to tell his name.” Bitter that day Was Aifé's heart, where, through long waiting years, While never back to her arms over the sea Cuchullain came, the black witch jealousy Sat like a carrion bird, with gloomy spell Blighting the flowers of love, chanting for ever In hoarse monotonous voice one baleful word, “Revenge!” Now, as the mother kissed her son, And sent him forth saying: “This ring will find Thy father,” in her heart she heard that song; And, even when on his hand she kissed the ring, Her eyes hot with the memory of old tears, Out of the dreary cave of her sick brain, Where Love lay on his bier, crept a dark thought, Whispering: “Now let the father slay the son, The son his father, my false lover's wrong Shall be avenged at last, and I can die.” So did they part, and Aifé from the strand Watched Conlaoch's bark over the heaving waves Flee like a gull, and vanish in the sea. CONLAOCH'S CHALLENGE Over the Strand of Bala and the sea A morning of great sunshine filled the sky, Making the fathomless deep of tender air One azure flame, and with soft inward light Flooding the bosom of each sailing cloud That slowly on its way voyaged serene, High o'er the Strand of Bala and the sea. On the broad Strand of Bala white-capt waves, Tripping their ancient measure, up the shore Danced gleefully, and paused, and turning drew The lazy pebbles down with murmurous noise. Green leagues of heaving billows, far away Gleamed in the sunlight, darkened in the gloom Where fell the shadow of a passing cloud. The peace of morn reigned in the sunny sky, Reigned o'er the Strand of Bala and the sea. There on the lonely strand a Warrior Youth Came, landing through the surf: the battle-dress Upon him like the ransom of a King, For splendour; like the glory of the looms In a Queen's house the mantle that he wore. The cathbarr on his head blazed like a star; The beauty of his hair, flame of his youth, Gleamed on his broad shoulders. Firmly he stood On his well-planted feet as a tall pine That grips with its tough root the wind-swept crag; Or moved with springing step like the red buck Who rules the mountain-glens, and keeps his realm Against all foes. Valour and strength and grace He wore upon him, as the rowan-tree, Royal by ancient birthright, in the woods Wears with blithe dignity her coral crown, And knows not her own beauty. So that day Came Conlaoch to the strand. There by the ship He left his crew, and, striding from the shore Shone like a Danann god high on the ridge Of sun-kist sand-hills, terrible as Lugh, When in his eye kindles the battle-glee; Beautiful as young Angus, when he stands Upon on eastern hill, and wakes the day With the far-sounding music of his harp. O Spear of Lugh! for what strange combat now Yearns the relentless fury of thy blade? O sweet-voiced birds of Angus, bringing dreams, What dream fires the Boy's heart, as on his arm He lifts his death-defying shield, and waves His spears aloft, and far before him sends The joy of his voice in that clear challenging shout? Beyond the sandy ridges by the Strand Of Bala, in the lowlands where the cows O'er the green meadows, by the wandering stream Of gently-flowing Fane, pastured in peace, The young men kept the ford for Conchobar; Who, far from ruined Eman, burnt in wrath By Fergus, for the death of Usna's Sons, Reigned sadly in Dundalgan by the sea. Clear to the young men's booth rang that stern shout, And three came forth to meet upon the dunes Young Conlaoch where he stood. Greeting him there, They said: “O Warrior Youth, come you to us This day in peace or war, out of the sea? From what strange land fare you, on what strange quest, Shining in arms against us, and your voice Vexing the air with such a battle-cry? If it be death you seek, these plains can yield Stones for your cairn; if not, you have come astray, Perchance to light on danger.” Cheerily Sounded the northern music of his voice In his bold answer: “Flower of the valorous host Of Conchobar, from no chance-driven ship, Ill-steered, or wandering from her course, I come From oversea, to find my feet astray In your long-famous Land. No fear of death Dismays my heart; for here I come to seek The proof of battle, and one to put me down; And slain will I before him fall, or take His glory from him in fair fight this day.” Smiling in scorn they said: “Grandly must sound Your name upon the tongues of men, fair youth, If you can match the least whose shield adorns Our House of Arms. But shame of ignorance Reddens our cheeks, asking your name and kin. What champion comes over the sea to tame The pride of Connall Cearnach, or mayhap Win glory from the Hound of Uladh now?” And Conlaoch gravely answered: “Vows are on me Never to tell my name, save to the man Who conquers me. Set me before your best, And I will strive with him until I take My death from him, or he defeat from me.” Wondering they heard, and said: “O stranger youth, Great seems your folly, greater still your pride; But welcome be the man whose courage soars A hawkflight over both!” They left the shore, And to the booths beside the ford they came; There gave him food, and water from the well; For mead he would not drink. They staked the field And built of sods cut from the sunny plain The judge's throne; then bade him name his hour And take his rest awhile. So passed the time In courteous talk between them in the shade. THE FIRST BATTLE BY THE FORD The judge was set, the summoning trumpet blew, And Conlaoch took his place. Then from the booth Came Connall Cearnach armed into the field. There courteously they met, and Connall said: “Fair Youth, refuse not now to tell your name To me—to Connall Cearnach.” Brightly shone Young Conlaoch's eyes, hearing that name. He bent His head in reverence ere he answered him; “Great is your grace in meeting one unknown, O Warrior King, whose fame lives on the tongue Of mightiest bards; and for that grace my heart Sings a proud song of thanks. But save to him Who conquers me, I may not tell my name. That is my vow.” “O Youth,” Connall replied, “Your valiant words promise as noble deeds.” Again the trumpet blew; and then was fought Between the two a battle that gave joy To every eye beholding. The swift spears Flew like trained falcons from their hands; and fast They raced like hounds over the field of arms; Now here, now there, parrying with watchful shields, Leaping aside, or catching in their flight The darts of death, to hurl them hissing back. Yet such fine craft they used in their defence That neither took a wound. They breathed awhile And Connall cried, laughing: “This is the game Of boys in Scatha's House, and better none Could play with me than you, O nameless Youth! But now our eager swords, hungry for work, Begin to bite their scabbards. Let us prove Their valour and their guile in combat now!” They drew their swords, and closed upon the green With feint and thrust, meeting with blade or shield Many a fierce onset, many a deadly blow; Until young Conlaoch, baffling with bold sleight A thrust of Connall's closed, and lifting him In his tough arms, flung him upon the ground, Stunned by his fall. Then from the Ulstermen A cry of anger and amazement rose; And Connall as he lay groaned with dull voice: “Youth you have put such shame on me this day As never man before. I am grown old. My happy star pales like a sunset-cloud, And victory flies to perch on younger crests. Slay me then! Death is better than grey years Among the old men, whose names die on the tongue Of palsied age!” But Conlaoch by his side Knelt ruthfully, murmuring: “As soon would I Slay thee as slay my father! Grudge me not My first great hour, or deem thy honour dimmed By one unlucky chance; thou, whose proud name Shines glorious in the everlasting morn Wherein great deeds live in undying song. Where is the man who never felt the spite Of Fortune's treachery? Who dare talk of shame When on a noble head her malice falls?” So Conlaoch strove to comfort him; and he Smiled a sad smile: “Mock me not with vain words; Better the dreams of youth,” he said, “than all Grey memories of brave deeds! I am grown old, My fame lies mouldering like an autumn leaf In winter's fogs. The old fade with their fame. Enjoy thy youth!” Sadly the young men came And bore him thence in silence to his booth. THE SECOND BATTLE BY THE FORD Meanwhile a message to the King was brought By a fleet runner, with the bitter news Of Connall's fall; and ere the day was old Two chariots from Dundalgan to the ford Came racing, swifter than two flames of war. Far off they saw them blaze like angry stars, As the wind-outspeeding stallions rushed like fire Over the plain, and far behind the wheels Long dust-clouds rose like smoke. In one the King Rode with the Archdruid Cathvah, and in one Cuchullain, driven by Laeg, stood like an oak, Grasping his battle spears. Conchobar now, Throned on the seat of judgment, set by him Grey Cathvah, venerable in magic robes. There Conlaoch, lightly sinking on his knee, Made his obeisance, and from the grave King Great was the praise he heard, with flushing cheeks And youthful joy of triumph in his heart; But boldly still refused his name. Once more The trumpet blew. Cuchullain from the booth Come shining to the field, and courteously Greeted the Boy: “O Youth, in feats of war Thou hast shamed us all this day! Tell me thy name, And no dishonour on that name can fall. I am Cuchullain.” Conlaoch answered him: “O Champion of the World, better my death From such a hand than breaking of my vow! That were my black dishonour.” Cuchullain sighed: “That face is like the face of one I knew— Where did I see that face?” A cloud of gloom Fell on him, as he muttered to himself: “Dark is my mind, blind is my groping brain!” Then looked once more on Conlaoch, and sadly said: “Come! Wilt thou prove on me thy valour now?” Fast flew their spears. The champion carelessly Played with him as a master, testing him; Conlaoch with careful heed of his defence Watching his play, made answer with a sleight Fine as his own; and soon Cuchullain saw One worthy of his arms was in the field, And shouted praise. And now, like two red stags Unmatched before, they bounded o'er the grass Fighting for mastery; till the sunny sky Was overcast, and growling from the hills The thunder swooped, as there furiously still They fought, and in Cuchullain's breast the rage Of battle flamed, and dreadful grew his face; Then to the Boy, with wrathful shout, he cried: “Tell me thy name, or die!” From some deep voice In Conlaoch's heart came the revealing word: “This is thy father!” “Know me then by this!” He shouted back. A spear flew from his hand Full at his father's head; but by his art Swerved from its mark, and lightly grazed his brow, And singing past him quivered in the earth. Then on Cuchullain madness fell. The lust Of slaughter darkly blazed in his fierce eyes, And, grasping in his rage his ghastly spear, Armed with the dragon's teeth, he cried again: “Thy hour is come—take from my hand thy death!” And rashly, in fatal madness, from his hand He launched the grisliest horror of the world. Sudden and grim the end its baleful teeth Made of that noble game, superb in skill Beyond all combats fought on Irish grass. Not to be balked or stayed, inevitable, The demon thing flew screaming o'er the plain, Through shield and warcoat rending its fierce way, And Conlaoch fell, pierced by five deadly wounds. Fast following it Cuchullain cried to him: “Tell me thy name!” He lifted his weak hand, And showed the ring, read in the setting sun That gleamed through clouds parted above the plain, As o'er the sea the thunder died away. Cuchullain saw, and knew it. His crime revealed With a swift pang stabbed his remorseful heart. In sudden vision rose the Alban shore, And Aifé waving o'er the sundering sea Her last farewell. Then with a bitter cry: “My son! my son!” he knelt beside his boy, And kissed his blanching lips, and his great voice Tender with tears, and broken with wild sobs, Groaned out: “Oh! why this horror? Why the guilt Of thy dear blood—my own—upon this hand? Did she—? Black fall my curse upon her head, Aifé, thy mother, if she planned this guile!” And Conlaoch, pale with agony, panted slow: “Curse not my mother—though she laid on me The vow that slays me! Curse this worm of pain Your blind desire of victory loosed on me— Base weapon for a champion! Curse the false heart That held my father's eyes from knowing me! Wonder is in my mind you knew me not, When my spear turned from you. Not mine the shame This day, falling before you, magic arms Against me. Never had you put me down Without this plague whose fangs burn in me now.” His tortured eyes looked in his father's face, And saw such love and anguish of remorse, It touched his heart. Faintly he smiled, and said: “The pity and the sorrow of the world Wail in my breast for you, seeing your grief. Take my forgiveness, father—and give me now The mercy of your sword!” Cuchullain groaned And pierced his heart with ruthful steel. The light Fled from his eyes, as his young life gushed forth, Following the blade withdrawn. From his marred flesh His father drew the spear, and shuddering Flung it away; then crouched upon the ground, Pale as the dead, and weak with wild remorse, Moaned o'er his murdered son: “Ochone for thee, Son of my youth! Madness was in my brain, Base wrath in my heart, slaying thee! In thy fall I am fallen below the beasts; the championship Flies these red hands of shame! Curst be the spear That slew thee! Curst am I who gave thee death, And knew not him I slew! I am grown grey In aging grief! An outcast o'er the earth Now must I wander, black upon my brow, Where honour shone, the brand of infamy!” Meanwhile the men who stood by Conchobar, Watching the end in horror and strange fear, Had heard that anguished cry: “My son! my son!” But Conchobar to Cathvah whispered low: “Let us be gone—leave him to mourn his boy While sorrow tames his heart and makes his limbs Weaker than rushes bent before the blast. But when the hour of tears goes by, his grief Eased, as he chants with music of sad words Keening above the dead, madness may fall Again upon him; the raging of his mind Urge him to turn his fury on ourselves, And many deaths may hap, ere he be slain By us or his own sword. Lay thou a spell Upon him. Let him quench his agony Fighting the woundless waves on Bala's Strand.” They left him there with his dead son alone, And sought the booths; while he with many a moan Closed the dim eyes, straightened the cramp-wrung limbs; And from afar they heard him raise the keene. CUCHULLAIN'S LAMENTATION I Ochone, bad are the days Without my son, without my son! Ochone for the days before me, And the love slain in my heart! II My curse on thy Mother, my curse I lay, because in her fury The Kings of my race she slew When she drank the blood of thy body. III My lap sad rest for the head, My arms round the body's beauty, My hands red with the blood Of him I slew in my madness! IV The father that slew his son, I lay my curse on that father, May every spear from his hand Come back, my torture and wounding! V In a bad field I planted This valiant slip of my body, In a bitter field it was nourished, To bring this curse upon me! VI A man's wrath is a flame That burns and is quenched in sorrow; But like venom never cured Is the jealousy of a woman! VII If thou and I, O my son, Were playing war-feats together O Conlaoch, boy of my heart, We would ride on the waves of battle! VIII But now death-pale are thy cheeks, Death-cold is thy fair white body, And the agony of my love Devours my heart like death! IX My grief will go from me never Till my bones in the cairn shall crumble; It feeds upon my heartstrings Like fire in the hoar hill-grasses! X Ochone, bad are my days Without my son, without my son! Ochone for the days before me And the love slain in my heart! He rose, and his red eyes were shot with blood, Ghastly his working face; and dreadful thoughts Raged in his brain. And now he might have turned His sword against himself; save that he found The fatal spear clotted with Conlaoch's gore, And fury seized him. But Cathvah's druid spells Against him sent a cloud of magic smoke, And rushing o'er the sandhills to the Strand Of Bala, there he fought against the waves All the night long, till far into the sea He cast the baleful spear, and the sane mind Came to him once more. Then slow, back o'er the hills He paced in the cool dawn. Three days they kept Young Conlaoch's funeral feast, and where he fell They raised his cairn. Not long Cuchullain lived; But on Murthemny heath, wanting that spear, With spear and sword was basely slain, unarmed, By Lugaid's hand; and Aifé died avenged. THE CURSE OF THE BARD Princess Enna: Truth is not in thee, Brian the Bard, Thy tongue is bitter, thy heart is hard! Because my Father will not strip off From his breast the brooch of sovereignty, Wilt thou dare to curse, wilt thou dare to scoff At the golden gifts he has proffered thee? Brian: Let him keep the pledge that he made to me! Enna: No pledge he has given thee, thou Tongue of Blight! Hence with thy Pot of Avarice—hence! Begone from his threshold; for at his door, Brian the Bard, thou shalt crouch no more, Starving for pride, and cursing for spite. Thy pride and thy wrongs are a vain pretence, Thy curses fall on thy head this night, If now thou drink not, for love of me, The Peace of the Bards, and the end of hate, In this cup of mead I bear to thee, Brian the Bard, is my word too late? Brian: I drink derision for love of thee! King's Daughter, for thee I have borne the spite, While in my heart is a quenchless flame, As here I starve on ye day and night. I crave not gifts, I crave not gold, I crave not the brooch of sovereignty. I crave that here I may die consoled, When here I lie dying for love of thee. Enna: Brian the Bard, thy pride is great! Brian: Kiss then the cup in thy white hand, And kiss my lips ere it be too late, And rove with me, as I rove the land, And I'll pledge in that cup an end of hate. Enna: Brian the Bard, thou art mad with pride! Shall I, a King's Daughter, fly with thee? Shall I wander the world by a greybeard's side? A shameful thing thou hast asked of me! Brian: I tear this beard from off my chin, Fling this patched cloak from off my back; And if thy love I may not win Laugh in my face, and bid me pack! Not Brian the Bard in sooth am I, But Brian, the King of Munster's son, And as thine own is my dignity. As children our fathers pledged our hands, And now thy father his pledge would break, Would kindle strife between friendly lands; But here I lie starving for thy sake, And here I starve till thy heart be won! Enna: A starveling at my father's door Might move my pity, not win my heart; But never a royal suitor before Played with such cunning a madman's part. If thou canst play the prince as well, Thou might'st scape laughter—I cannot tell. Stand up, and look me in the face! In sooth thou seemest in woeful case. Brian: In woeful case for love of thee, And the curse of our fathers' enmity. I dreamed of thee in my father's land; Yet what form was on thee I could not tell, What heart, what mind might in thee dwell, What fate for me was in that white hand. But, now I have seen thee, well I know The Beauty of the World thou art! I have come through foes for the love of thee, I would pass through fire to win thy heart, Rose of the World, wilt thou come with me? Enna: A hostage wouldst thou have me be? Brian: No hostage; but my chosen bride! And if thou wilt not come with me, Here as a hostage will I bide, Whatever my fate I will bide with thee. Take me then to thy father's hall, And let me stand before his face, Whether he free me or hold me in thrall, Whether he slay me or grant me grace: Or kiss the cup in thy white hand, Let me kiss thy lips ere it be too late, And pledge we now an end of hate! Choose now, I bow to thy heart's decree. Enna: Brian the Bold, I will go with thee! NINETY-EIGHT Written 1898 I A hundred years are gone Since Ninety-eight. What has our Nation done Since Ninety-eight? Shines brighter now the sun? What progress, small or great? What victories have we won Since Ninety-eight? II Nine hundred years, upon The waters, desolate, Wept Lir's enchanted Swan, Driven by the Witch's hate. Like that enchanted Swan Driven by the Witch's hate Has Ireland drifted on, Tossed by the storms of fate. III Now brighter shines her sun, Her day of sorrow past, Her long enchantment done, She spreads her wings at last. UNDER THE WHITEBOY ACTS, 1800 An Old Rector's Story Ay, I was once a soldier, as you've heard, A cornet in the Irish Yeomanry. To say what that meant fifty years ago Would seem, thank God! to young fellows like you, Like telling tales about some foreign land In the dark ages. Yes, my memory Has its black chamber, where, whene'er I look, There flicker out, shining with ghastly fire, Some ugly pictures painted on the wall— Bad sights! Now here's a sample: I was once Riding at night along a country road, Patrolling with my troop—one August night. The moon was full, and surely bright and fair As when she rose on Eden's innocence The night before the Fall. What brought us there, Out of our beds? Well, in the peasants' phrase, “The Boys was out.” The Whiteboy scare, in fact, Was in full cry, and Ireland in the grip, Under the Whiteboy Acts, of martial law: Nothing new, mind; the district was proclaimed, And we patrolled it, to repress the crime Of being out of doors between the hours Of sunset and sunrise. Well, there I sat, Loose in my saddle, in a kind of dream, Thinking, I fancy, of the County Ball, A pretty face—I was a youngster then— Had made for me a chapter of romance, To be re-read by that romantic moon. Oh! but 'twas wonderful, that moonlight, mixed With woodbine scents, and gusts of meadowsweet. An Irish boy's first love, a cornet's pride In his new soldiership and uniform! Why, 'twas sheer ecstasy—I feel it still, As I remember how, athwart my mood, The martial noise of our accoutrements, Clanking and jingling to the chargers' tramp, Chimed in a sort of music. The road turned, And a stream crossed it. On the further side There was a man, a scared look in his face, White in that great moonlight. And there he stood, And never ran—the creature never ran, But quavered out some question: 'tis my guess He said: “Is that the sogers?” Then I saw, Like a bad dream, the captain of our troop, (Whom I'll here name “Lord Blank”) ride at him straight, And cut him down. You, maybe, never saw A man cut down? Nor I, till that bad hour. Well, 'twas an ugly sight—a brutal sight. The strangest thing was that the man seemed dazed, Made no attempt to run, or dodge the sword, Shrank rather from the wind of the horse, I thought, His hands held out in a groping sort of way; But never raised, I saw, to guard his head, Till the blow sent him reeling, with a shriek: “O Lord have mercy!” Then he plunged, face down, Clutching and wallowing in a pool of blood. He spoke no more—just moaned. 'Twas horrible, And all the more for something half grotesque; You'd never think a man's last agony Could look so like a joker's antics, played To raise a laugh. Yet no one laughed, I think. We had pushed across the stream. I saw them lift His head, with long grey hair dabbled with blood. The sword had caught him under the right ear, And through the gash his poor, scared, struggling heart Simply pumped out his life. 'Twas over soon. They laid him down, stone dead, with staring eyes; And then I saw it all—the man was blind. Then someone said: “Lord save us! Sure it's Tom— It's ould blind Tom, the fiddler! Sure enough, He lives just here in the boreen beyant.” Another said: “He's due to play to-day In Ballintogher Fair. He must ha' thought 'Twas mornin', an' come here to clane himself, Here in the sthrame. Poor Tom! 'Twas just your luck, Misfort'nate craythur that ye always wor! Well, you'll chune up no more; God rest your sowl!” We found his stick, indeed, beside the stream. Then we rode on and left him lying there Upon a grassy tussock by the road. An ugly business that. I never knew How My Lord felt about that sad mistake: Such things will happen under martial law, And ill-judged deeds, done through excess of zeal, The King's Commission covers in such times. We heard no more of it. But all that night I felt myself next door to a murderer, And rode with a sick chill about my heart. No more pride in my uniform; No more Delight under that ghastly, glaring moon That showed me Tom's dead face. Perhaps you'll think This made me sick of soldiering? Well, not quite. The young mistrust their instinct, sir, when first Thrust forth new fledged into the great rough world. I was shocked, surely; but was half ashamed To be so shocked. Then I saw other things My conscience quite convinced me went beyond The necessary horrors of this life. For me I felt From that time forth the uniform I wore Smother my soul in shame. I changed it soon For this poor cassock, which, though not so smart, I find more comfortable every way. THE SUNBURST I Through the midnight of despair I heard one making moan For her dead, her victors fallen to gain all battles but her own; I heard the voice of Ireland, wailing for her dead With wailing unavailing, and sighing as she said: “In vain in many a battle have my heroes fought and bled, Like water, in vain slaughter, my sons' best blood been shed; For my house is desolate, discrowned my head! II In vain my daughters bear their babes, babes with the mournful eyes Of children without father, soothed by strange lullabies, Rocked in their lonely cradles by mothers crooning low, And weeping o'er their sleeping sad songs of long ago; Whose eyes, when they remember, as the wailing nightwinds blow, Their Nation's desolation in their singing overflow With the overflowing of an ancient woe.” III O Mother, mournful Mother, turn from wailing for thy dead, Grey Sibyl, yet unvanquished, lift up thy dauntless head! O Swan among the nations, enchanted long, so long That the story of thy glory is a half-forgotten song, Lift thine eyes, and bless the living, thy sons who round thee throng, In the hour of their power they shall right thine ancient wrong; For their love is deathless, and their faith is strong. IV Thy leaf of many sorrows, wet with thy tears for dew, Emblem of thy long patience, thy champions brave and true, Knights of the threefold Heart of Green, like saints the Cross, have worn Through their nation's tribulation, through infamy and scorn, We'll blazon with the Sunburst, star of thy destined morn, On our azure's ancient blazure in royal banners borne, To lead for ever the World's Hope Forlorn.</field>
   </doc>
</add>