<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Rodd, Rennell, 1858-1941</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Rodd, Rennell, 1858-1941</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">rodd rennell 1858 1941</field>
      <field name="author_text">Rodd, Rennell, 1858-1941</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1940's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.2151.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">1940</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:467267</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">German</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">War poems with some others ; By Lord Rennell of Rodd</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">War poems with some others ; By Lord Rennell of Rodd</field>
      <field name="title_facet">war poems with some others</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">war poems with some others</field>
      <field name="title_text">War poems with some others ; By Lord Rennell of Rodd</field>
      <field name="year_display">1940</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1940</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1940</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467267&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467267&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Rodd, Rennell, 1858-1941&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;rodd rennell 1858 1941&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;War poems with some others ; By Lord Rennell of Rodd&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;war poems with some others&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1940&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1940&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Rodd, Rennell&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1858&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1941&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;War poems with some others&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By Lord Rennell of Rodd&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Edward Arnold &amp;amp; Co.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1940&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp3368&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;ger&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;32 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;War poems with some others&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By Lord Rennell of Rodd&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 29 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DEDICATION To Britain Dear isle, in whose high service it was by fate decreed That I should work in other lands with men of alien breed, With those who little knew thee or knew but to resent The girdling sea should hold at bay their envious ill-content, Dear isle, whose summer magic now challenged to grim strife Has never seemed more lovely in all my years of life, Words fail to match the patriot pride that makes my soul elate To feel thy sons so one at heart in this dark hour of fate, At home and round the seven seas where Britain's flag is flown, Who have ventured all in freedom's cause and bear the brunt alone. And though the sky be overcast in which my setting sun May sink beyond red battlefields still waiting to be won, I know my people's sword and shield will ransom the oppressed And I can pass with unbowed head serenely to my rest. The Voice of the Empire If my work is over and if in vain I had hoped at the close of life That peace would fall with the evening, not passion and hate and strife, I can still give thanks as my sun goes down for one treasure of passing worth, The faith that was staunch to the motherland of her sons at the ends of the earth, When she called them all into council and their splendid answer came, Their pledge in an issue greater than conquest, profit or fame, That peoples should live in freedom, unfettered in word or thought, And hold the land that their fathers held and the faith that their fathers taught. From the isles of all the oceans, from the north to the tropic sun We have heard the homing voices, and the soul of their voice was one— She has carried the flag of freedom over many an unplumbed wave Saint George's cross at the masthead, to liberate not to enslave. She sheltered us in our childhood. We are nations now full-grown. If Britain must draw her sword once more she shall not draw alone. With a single voice in a common cause we bid the challenger know We stand with the Mother Country, and where she leads we go. To the Dominions Sons of those stout adventurers who set forth long ago To found the vast dominion that marches with the snow, And you whose great forefathers in little ships defied Uncharted seas and tamed wild lands to be our Austral pride, How nobly has your swift response revealed the island breed That rallied to the mother's call in this her hour of need, When those we had armed for left us, who had made their cause our own, On freedom's menaced bulwark to face the spears alone. Not only have you all renounced the peace your sires had won, Accepting with no faltering voice the challenge of the Hun, But warm hearts half the world away of mothers and of wives Prepare kind welcome in their homes to shield our children's lives. We can face the fight in firmer faith who know beyond the sea Your love for Britain still inspires such splendid loyalty. The Degenerates: To Fuehrers and Verfuehrers You deemed our empire overgrown and withering at the root, Its parent city a grand place, your Bluecher said, to loot. We had meant to be good neighbours, we praised your enterprise, And never dreamed that welcomed guests were really well-trained spies. Your aim was world-dominion, and we stood in your way— A sterner fibre nerved us once but we had had our day. Wherefore with specious falsehoods and eyes on our estate Your envious millions were inspired to nurse a rabid hate. You had branded us degenerates, but since we might resist Weak nations first must learn to feel the weight of your mailed fist. And all that man's long effort has 'stablished and reveres You scorned and did not scruple to drown in blood and tears. Half Europe bides your menace now, and only air and sea Where Britain guards the highway can make and keep her free. Though all the rest may falter this People that I knew, With sons and kin from oversea, to Britain staunch and true, Heirs of a great tradition, will not belie her past Upholding freedom's banner rock-steadfast to the last. November, 1939 Out of the vastness traversed by the wave Which brings the messages of lips unseen There came a call to Britain from the Queen, Direct, inspiring, confident and brave. If those clear accents, mightier than the pen In world-wide range, that listening millions heard Appealed to women, none the less her word Enlisted all the chivalry of men. We have a debt of honour to repay, We shall not falter in the manly part, We shall not fail to keep our scutcheon clean, Whate'er the cost, however hard the way; But we shall fight on with a greater heart, Who bear her gage as champions of our Queen. The Nation's Hymn It has stirred me like the voice of home World over, wheresoe'er Assembled Britons chant the hymn That is a nation's prayer. But most my heart has felt its call In mighty battleships, Where solemn unison inspires A thousand fervent lips. Yet, when I heard it yestereve I questioned if before The sense of all it symbolised Had ever moved me more. For first the unseen viol-strings Recalled to hearts oppressed The anthems that are silenced now In nations dispossessed; Then strong, as if atoning, swelled That hymn the British sing Serene with faith undaunted, Our own God Save the King. Finland Hail! Hail, ancient people of the northern sea, In number small, but great in heart and mind, Not envying others, save that they were free, Maintaining long tradition, unresigned To alien rule, impatient for release To live self-centred your own lives in peace! A little nation, shadowed by the strength Of circling millions, they kept sharp their swords, Enduring, not submissive. Then at length The great day dawned, when they defied the hordes Of a vast empire, and alone assailed The old oppression and alone prevailed. But brief was Finland's happy spell, once more That old oppressor in a new disguise, Claimed overlordship of their Baltic shore, Masked in discreet benevolence of lies. Yet those few years had steeled a patriot will And hard-won freedom seemed but dearer still. What though outnumbered more than fifty-fold They faced like men who trusted in their star, Great armies panoplied with stolen gold And murderous engines of unequal war. They, without allies but their ice and snow, Flung back the challenge with a splendid ‘No!’ Hardly, I think, since round Leonidas, Between the flanks of Oeta and the sea, Three hundred Spartans in the narrow pass Dying, immortalised Thermopylae, Have patriot warriors earned so just a claim To share their record on the roll of fame. Free nations of the world, will you endure This people's re-enslavement, or that he, The bandit neighbour, crazy with the lure Of world dominion, should aspire to be Your arbiter, predestined to replace Your code of morals with his claims of race? Will you permit earth-hunger and the lust For mastery to revive the brute in man, And suffer all the wise, the brave, the just Have 'stablished since his upward trend began To count as naught? You that are sane and free Unite, proclaim ‘We will not have this be.’ To the Air-men of France We vaunted many a gallant deed In wars of long ago When rivalries of State decreed A friend should be a foe. But peace restored made swift amends For blows not struck in hate, And ancient foes should be firm friends In this grim hour of fate. If Britain claimed her island due, Dominion on the sea, Nor we nor you were less than true To the code of chivalry. Now, with a menaced world to save We should be proud to share, With wings outsoaring strand and wave, Dominion in the air. Crederit quia Absurdum To the Fuehrer I You say in Mein Kampf, ‘When you have to lie don't lie in a minor key; It would not convince the people, not even coming from me.’ So when you lie for a purpose you lie on a superscale, And the average man will not believe that you could invent the tale. The absurd he will readily swallow. Maybe; but bethink you first, When you lie, of the frog in the fable who swelled so big that he burst. II Wer einmal lügt, den glaubt man nicht Und wenn er auch die Wahrheit spricht. ‘Who once has lied’—I learned in youth The precept in an old refrain— ‘Will never be believed again Not even when he tells the truth.’ But you with purpose to deceive Remodelled that old rhyme To ‘Lie not once but all the time, And many people will believe.’ Hellas In Homage to a Royal Bride There is a land the sun loves more Than other lands of earth Where men revered in ancient lore The cradle of his birth; Where still as when the old world called A Siren voice beguiles The wanderer to abide enthralled Among enchanted isles: A land with scanty wealth to boast Save vines and olive trees On terraced slopes that ward her coast Against encroaching seas. Where that tradition has not died Which welcomes whoso roams With tidings from the world outside In hospitable homes. A land where none may choose but feel More near the soul of things, And nature eager to reveal Mysterious communings; Whose harmonies of tone and form And clear pellucid air First gave ungoverned minds a norm And made man's thought aware; Whose marble cliffs lent their white heart To masters of design, Interpreting in terms of art Their dream of the divine, The land which quickened worlds unborn And sowed for all to reap, And then, forgotten and forlorn Sank in an age-long sleep, While Frank and Moslem hordes displaced The gods they did not know, And uncouth battlements defaced Their shrines, yet, even so The envious fates that know no ruth, The doom long years exact Proved vain to mar her ageless youth, She woke, but one thing lacked To gladden the reviving soul Of living Greece again, A Fairy Princess to control The loyalties of men. So you, endowed of Grace and Muse, Are destined for their land, To claim the love none may refuse When you bestow your hand. Legend No sandal round the cloisters crept, The solemn precinct slept, Since midnight's curtained silence fell Until the matins bell. A single vigilant in prayer Knelt at an altar-stair. His eyes' young blue, his hair's long gold, Were goodly to behold, Although the lamp that lighted him Burned tremulous and dim. He said, ‘I lay my birth right down To sceptre and to crown. The pride of race, the pomp of state, To God I consecrate. I have no need for helm or sword Whom no man shall call lord; The golden spurs are no more meet To deck my unmailed feet, Who barefoot choose as greater gain To tread my path in pain.’ Her statue carved in painted wood Stirred where the Virgin stood, And in the shadowy niche her face Assumed a living grace. The seven swords that pierce her soul Gleamed, and her aureole. The hands unclasped and waxen white Reached out across the night, And on his head she bending down Laid her own red-rose crown. ‘Nay, Blessed Guardian of my vow, No roses decked the brow Of him who had no place,’ he said, ‘In which to lay his head. Give me some other sign, I pray, To bear upon my way. No blooms of earth or paradise Crowned love's great sacrifice: I would renounce, could that but be, As wholly as did He.’ Then as in answer to the prayer From his long golden hair On the cold stone which paved the cell The crimson petals fell, While through the flesh a piercing smart Pulsed to his beating heart; And redder than that rosy rain One print of deeper stain Bore witness that his brows had borne A diadem of thorn. Folk Song From the French Bind the distaff round with white Spin for your true love's delight, Spin a veil to lift aside When he claims you as his bride. Bind the distaff round with blue Spinning for the priest his due, A stole to wear when you two stand By his altar hand in hand. Bind the distaff round with rose Spin, as dawn to daylight grows, Spin to weave white linen, meet For the first-born's cradle sheet. Bind the distaff round with red When you need to spin the thread For a kerchief soft to dry Tears which gather in the eye. Bound with sable let it be When you spin, with few to see, For the shroud wherein to lie We shall fold you when you die. Fresh Woods and Pastures New Here by the forest edge the cuckoo-flowers The border dwellers cluster in the sun. Invading bracken spreads its new green fronds Beside close thorn and hazel, and beyond No ripple stirs the grasses or the wheat; Life seems arrested in the pause of noon. Then from afar a soft wind gathers breath Quickens the tree-tops, quivers the still leaves, Sets all the hazel rustling, bends the fern And breaking silence as it passes brings A message from the infinite to me. And the wind said, yon flowers of the field Born to be beautiful and so fulfil Their part in a great harmony, all those Gold-hearted daisies, wide to drink the sun And poppies on the fringe of last year's corn Hold seed of beauty that is yet to be— But they bloom barren till some breeze like mine Or honey-questing bee may chance to bear The golden pollen to expectant lips. And of these myriad frail existencies,— Despite the scent of kindred blossom near And nature's lavish effort to survive,— How many are terminate in beauty, fade Fast rooted with no favouring wind for friend! And are not we as they are? Though some few Shall be fulfilled of loving ere they die How many wait and dream their dream in vain. Deep in the forest now! where twilight stems Taper in purple to a golden red. But in the solemn silence no bird sings, And if the feet of little fawns should trip Between the tree-trunks you would hardly hear The old moss lies so deep. But you might ask Do not the white clouds whisper to their crests ‘Look through us at the wonderful deep blue’ That so their branches strain to reach the sky. I feel there moves not any harmful thing Through this unbroken solitude of trees. Whose very stillness has a soothing power, Dispelling restless doubtings and desires, Leaving the soul self-centred. It is good To be here with the silence. Very good. My pathway led me to a woodland mere With reed-beds haunted by the dragon-fly, Where the roe drinks at even, and the clouds Reflect a pearl-like image, sailing past. I wonder if the emerald dragon-fly Hovers for memory over lakes and streams Where the life impulse stirred a worm to spin A hanging cradle in the swaying reeds, Its winter prison that the sun broke through To radiate the filmy wings and free A rainbow marvel to the summer air. Then a wide clearing opened; meadow lands In sunshine perfumed by the new-mown hay, A village with red roofs and steepled church, A graveyard at the lifting of a hill, All forest-girdled to assure their peace. Too long have I dwelt in cities, spent my soul In concentration on material ends. Here sense and spirit are in mute accord, Here speaks unchallenged living nature's voice. Beat into mine world's heart and make me feel The magic of the eternal miracle, No more perplexed why others miss the way. Because always the marvels of our earth Lie round them widespread these they hardly heed. They only grasp the fragment and the whole Escapes a vision blind to all beside That use has made familiar. Therefore they Note first the discords in the harmony, Rail at the shadow and forget the sun. Consider the mute lore of little things. What master-craftsman, though he gave long years To match one marvel of our everyday, Scattered in myriads, could have graded so A leaf of any wayside rose that blooms Inevitably beautiful, or mould One simple feather from the wild-bird's wing? Then dimly wondering try to apprehend That which not merely fashioned but conceived Controlled creation, and in that thought daze. And yet assurance, not in words expressed, Not issuing from a presence palpable, But echoed from a world beyond my ken, Convinces some immortal sense in me Of potency to grasp all amplitudes, To outsoar the finite, compassing the whole, An all that is, but for us is not yet, Because God's now is not in time or space. Epilogue To L. R. Ere long on this deserted shore Sea-folk will spread their gear, And stretch the sail and paint the oar Because the spring is near. In a little while seas will be blue And west winds warm again, And I shall want to sail with you To lands beyond the main. We know the lure of sail and spur, The call of the unknown; And why should brain or heart demur When the young birds are flown? A hand that beckoned us to roam Determined you and I Should keep no anchor grounded home But wander till we die. A world yet unexplored extends Past yon horizon's rim, And where the bounded unknown ends The unknowable is dim; But so we pass with unbowed head And eyes towards the sun; We reck not where the tent be spread When the last march is done.</field>
   </doc>
</add>