<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Langhorne, John, 1735-1779</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Langhorne, John, 1735-1779</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">langhorne john 1735 1779</field>
      <field name="author_text">Langhorne, John, 1735-1779</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1760's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_2.2208.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1762</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:465876</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Viceroy ; A poem. Addressed to the Earl of Halifax [by John Langhorne</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Viceroy ; A poem. Addressed to the Earl of Halifax [by John Langhorne</field>
      <field name="title_facet">viceroy</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">viceroy</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Viceroy ; A poem. Addressed to the Earl of Halifax [by John Langhorne</field>
      <field name="year_display">1762</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1762</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1762</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465876&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465876&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Langhorne, John, 1735-1779&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;langhorne john 1735 1779&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Viceroy ; A poem. Addressed to the Earl of Halifax [by John Langhorne&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;viceroy&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1762&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1762&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Langhorne, John&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1735&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1779&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Viceroy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A poem. Addressed to the Earl of Halifax [by John Langhorne]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for H. Payne and W. Cropley [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1762&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp2141&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;xi, 11 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Viceroy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A poem. Addressed to the Earl of Halifax [by John Langhorne]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 14 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ADDRESSED TO THE EARL OF HALIFAX. THE VICEROY. 'Twas on Time's birth-day, when the voice divine Wak'd sleeping Nature, while her infant eye, Yet trembling, struggled with created light; The heaven-born Muse, sprung from the source sublime Of Harmony immortal, first receiv'd Her sacred mandate. “Go, seraphic maid, “Companion still to Nature! from her works “Derive thy lay melodious, great, like those, “And elegantly simple. In thy train, “Glory, and fair renown, and deathless fame “Attendant ever, each immortal name, “By thee deem'd sacred, to yon starry vault “Shall bear, and stamp in characters of gold. “Be thine the care, alone where truth directs “The firm heart, where the love of human kind “Inflames the patriot spirit, there to soothe “The toils of virtue with melodious praise: “For those, that smiling seraph bids thee wake “His golden lyre; for those, the young-ey'd Sun “Gilds this fair-formed world; and genial spring “Throws many a green wreath, liberal, from his bosom.” So spake the voice divine, whose last sweet sound Gave birth to Echo, tuneful nymph, that loves The Muse's haunt, dim grove, or lonely dale, Or high wood old; and, listening while she sings, Dwells in long rapture on each falling strain. O Halifax, an humble Muse, that dwells In scenes like these, a stranger to the world, To thee a stranger, late has learnt thy fame, Even in this vale of silence; from the voice Of Echo learnt it, and, like her, delights, With thy lov'd name, to make these wild woods vocal. Spirits of ancient time, to high renown By martial glory rais'd, and deeds august, Atchiev'd for Britain's freedom! Patriot hearts, That, fearless of a tyrant's threatening arm, Embrac'd your bleeding country! o'er the page, Where history triumphs in your holy names, O'er the dim monuments that mark your graves, Why streams my eye with pleasure? 'Tis the joy The soft delight that thro' the full breast flows, From sweet remembrance of departed virtue! O Britain, parent of illustrious names, While o'er thy annals memory shoots her eye, How the heart glows, rapt with high-wondering love, And æmulous esteem! Hail, Sydney, hail! Whether Arcadian blythe, by fountain clear, Piping thy love lays wild, or Spartan bold, In freedom's van distinguish'd, Sydney, hail! Oft o'er thy laurell'd tomb from hands unseen Fall flowers; oft in the vales of Penshurst fair Menalcas, stepping from his evening fold, Listeneth strange music, from the tiny breath Of fairy minstrels warbled, which of old, Dancing to thy sweet lays, they learned well. On Raleigh's grave, O strew the sweetest flowers, That on the bosom of the green vale blow! There hang your vernal wreaths, ye village-maids! Ye mountain nymphs, your crowns of wild thyme bring To Raleigh's honour'd grave! There bloom the bay, The virgin rose, that, blushing to be seen, Folds its fair leaves; for modest worth was his. A mind where truth, philosophy's first born, Held her harmonious reign: a Briton's breast, That, careful still of freedom's holy pledge, Disdain'd the mean arts of a tyrant's court, Disdain'd and died! Where was thy spirit then, Queen of sea-crowning isles, when Raleigh bled? How well he serv'd thee, let Iberia tell! Ask prostrate Cales, yet trembling at his name, How well he serv'd thee; when her vanquish'd hand Held forth the base bribe, how he spurn'd it from him, And cried, I fight for Britain! History rise, And blast the reigns that redden with the blood Of those that gave them glory! Happier days, Gilt with a Brunswick's parent smile, await The honour'd Viceroy. More auspicious hours Shall Halifax behold, nor grieve to find A favour'd land ungrateful to his care. O for the Muse of Milton, to record The honours of that day, when full conven'd Hibernia's senate with one voice proclaim'd A nation's high applause; when, long opprest With wealth-consuming war, their eager love Advanc'd the princely dignity's support, While Halifax presided! O, belov'd By every muse, grace of the polish'd court, The peasant's guardian, then what pleasure felt Thy liberal bosom! not the low delight Of fortune's added gifts, greatly declin'd; No; 'twas the supreme bliss that fills the breast Of conscious virtue, happy to behold Her cares successful in a nation's joy. But O, ye sisters of the sacred spring, To sweetest accents tune the polish'd lay, The music of persuasion! You alone Can paint that easy eloquence that flow'd In Attic streams, from Halifax that flow'd When all Iërne listen'd. Albion heard, And felt a parent's joy: no more, she cried, No more shall Greece the man of Athens boast, Whose magic periods smooth'd the listening wave Of rapt Ilyssus. Rome shall claim no more The flowery path of eloquence alone To grace her consul's brow; for never spoke Himeria's Viceroy words of fairer phrase, Forgetful of Alpheus' hastening stream, When Arethusa stop'd her golden tide, And call'd her nymphs, and call'd her shepherd swains To leave their sweet pipes silent. Silent lay Your pipes, Hibernian shepherds. Liffey smil'd, And on his soft hand lean'd his dimply cheek, Attentive: “Once so Wharton spoke,” he cried, “Unhappy Wharton! whose young eloquence “Yet vibrates on mine ear.” Whatever powers, Whatever genii old, of vale or grove The high inhabitants, all throng'd to hear. Sylvanus came, and from his temples grey His oaken chaplet flung, lest haply leaf, Or interposing bough should meet the sound, And bar its soft approaches to his ear. Pan ceas'd to pipe—a moment ceas'd—for then Suspicion grew, that Phæbus in disguise His ancient reign invaded: down he cast, In petulance, his reed; but seiz'd it soon And fill'd the woods with clangor. Measures wild The wanton Satyrs danc'd, then listening stood, And gaz'd with uncouth joy. But hark? wild riots shake the peaceful plain, The gathering tumult roars, and faction opes Her blood-requesting eye. The frighted swain Mourns o'er his wasted labours, and implores His country's guardian. Previous to his wish That guardian's care he found. The tumult ceas'd, And faction clos'd her blood-requesting eye. Be these thy honours, Halifax! and these The liberal muse, that never stain'd her page With flattery, shall record: from each low view, Each mean connection free, her praise is fame. O, could her hand in future times obtain One humble garland from th'Aonian tree, With joy she'd bind it on thy favour'd head, And greet thy judging ear with sweeter strains! Mean while pursue, in public virtue's path, The palm of glory: only there will bloom Pierian laurels. Should'st thou deviate thence, Perish the blossoms of fair-folding fame! Even this poor wreath, that now affects thy brow, Would lose its little bloom, the muse repine, And blush that Halifax had stole her praise. The END.</field>
   </doc>
</add>