<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Hayman, Robert</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Hayman, Robert</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">hayman robert</field>
      <field name="author_text">Hayman, Robert</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.1746.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">[before 1634]</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464234</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Mirrour of New Reformation ; wherein Reformers, by their owne acknowledgements, are represented ad viuum, the Beauty also of their handy worke is displayed [by Robert Hayman</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">Mirrour of New Reformation ; wherein Reformers, by their owne acknowledgements, are represented ad viuum, the Beauty also of their handy worke is displayed [by Robert Hayman</field>
      <field name="title_facet">mirrour of new reformation</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">mirrour of new reformation</field>
      <field name="title_text">Mirrour of New Reformation ; wherein Reformers, by their owne acknowledgements, are represented ad viuum, the Beauty also of their handy worke is displayed [by Robert Hayman</field>
      <field name="year_display">[before 1634]</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1634</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1634</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464234&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464234&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Hayman, Robert&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;hayman robert&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Mirrour of New Reformation ; wherein Reformers, by their owne acknowledgements, are represented ad viuum, the Beauty also of their handy worke is displayed [by Robert Hayman&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;mirrour of new reformation&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;[before 1634]&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1634&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Hayman, Robert&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Mirrour of New Reformation&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;wherein Reformers, by their owne acknowledgements, are represented ad viuum, the Beauty also of their handy worke is displayed [by Robert Hayman]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;[Rouen]&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;[Printed by J. Cousturier]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;[before 1634]&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp1691&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;94 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Mirrour of New Reformation&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;wherein Reformers, by their owne acknowledgements, are represented ad viuum, the Beauty also of their handy worke is displayed [by Robert Hayman]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 115 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries, introductory matter and notes omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I. TO THE PROTESTANT READER. I seeke not heere by curious Words and phrase To catch the vaine aire, of vncertaine prayse, Those ends are base: let seruile spirits choake Their best endeauors with that puffe of smoake; I only ayme in all that I haue done, By winning of thy soule, to gaine my owne. II. Another to the same. Read, search, compare, quote, weygh, examine, all I wish thee, is, to be impartiall. III. On the censuring Minister. Me thinkes I see some captious Minister Take vp my booke, and with a thought as farre From vpright iudgement, as my lines from lyes, Viewes euery page, and each citation tryes; But finding all exact, he carpes my stile, Censures my verse, and with a scornfull smile Fy on this Priest (sayth he) what rime is this? What words are heere, this couplet is amisse; That phrase is of his owne inuention, new; This ouer-harsh, that England neuer knew. Haue patience good Aminadab, heer's none Gaynsayes your censure; for to France alone Whose ayre hath fed me from a child, I owe The litle of this litle which I knowe. How then should I in forraine countryes gaine That, to whose height few can at home attaine? I grant my lines are harsh, and do not falle To please your eares, but yet I hope, they galle. IIII. On the same. Although t'were true that these my lines containe No good, no right, or wel applied straine, T'were not my fault, for what good can be wrought; Where the whole subiect of the whole is nought. V. LVTHERS CHANGE To his much honored freind W. T. While in the Romane Church your Luther staid, To tame his flesh, hee fasted, watcht and prayd, Affected true obedience, liued poore, And carefully from carnal acts forbore. All that he did was with a single hart, An vnfain'd zeale, empois'ned on no part With fond vaine glorie, but directed whole T'encrease God's honour and secure his soule. But thence gone forth, he sodainly became So burned with his fleshe's raging flame, As he grew al most madd through lust; eight dayes He now will spend, and neither studies, prayes, Nor writes, disturbed with inflamed veynes Of burning leacherie, and other paines. Say, is not this (speake freely worthie friend) T'begin in th'Spirit and in the flesh to end? VI. Luther no Reformer. Lvther still vaunts himself to be the first, That by Truth's beames the Romish clouds disperst. Yet is it granted, Satan was the cause, Which mou'd him first the sacred Masse t'oppose. Why's Satan then not Reformer? true, He is indeed: Let's giue the diuell his due. VII. The fruits of Protestancie. Protestants tell vs that before the light Of their new Ghospell men were more vpright, Of better life, more truly vertuous, More reall, faithfull, and Religious. And eu'ry way more giuen without compare To all good workes, then in their Church they are. For now, (say they) such as haue late embrac't Our Reformation do repaire more fast To theft, exactions, lying, vsury, Excesse in drinking, swearing, gluttony And such foule vices as from hence proceed, Then did the former t'any vertuous deed. So that (thus still themselues goe on) who would A rable of cheating, factious knaues behold. Let them but vnto any Citty go Posses't by Protestants, and it will shew Whole shoales of such, yea Pagans, Iewes, and Turkes, With other Infidells do better workes, Detest sinn more, shew greater honesty, Are farre more patient and lesse proud then wee. In lieu of fasts wee haunt excessiue feastes Drink healths to make our selues and others beasts, Wrong marriage-beds, haunt stewes, and for our prayer In eu'ry place we curse, blaspheme and sweare. Our children they grow worse, and dare such crimes As were scarse knowne to men of former times. Our Preachers labours, which should bee assign'd Only to Truth, are guided with the winde Of popular applause, attended still With hate and enuy: their malicious will N'er giues them rest, but makes them seek out wayes How they debates and causelesse iarres may rayse. In their disputes they wrest, peruert and lye, Oppresse the Truth, and from the point still flye. Many besides are flatte'rers, and beleeue As please the Prince or country where they liue. But more with their vile wicked life do shame Their Gospels doctrine and themselues defame So that we see, since we reiected Rome The world doth dayly worse and worse become: For n'ere in Flanders was more drunck'nes seen, Th'Italians euer haue lesse wanton been, In Iury n'ere was more Hypocrisy, Turky is freer from impiety, And Tartary lesse wicked is then those, Who euen in England now Rom's Church oppose. All this themselues affirme, this few deny; T'weer not good manners (here) to say, they lye. VIII. An other vpon the same. The question's state we Ministers, to shrowd Our falshood, do with darknes ouerclowd; Things that are plaine we shamelesly deny; Things false wee all maintaine, yet know wee lye. Impious things, we as faith's grounds, propose; And true things still as heresies, oppose; The scriptures we to our owne dreames do wrest; We boast the Fathers, but their faith detest: To cheat, calumniate, glosse, deceaue, and raile Is our cheif practise: soe we may preuaile Gainst our Opponents, all things we auouch But greatly care not what: I think, nor much. IX. ON ZVINGLIVS. When into Zuinglius Satan had infus'd Himself, and by those engines, which he vs'd Before 'gainst Luther, drawn him to forsake Christ, and al true Religion; and betake Himself to Schisme, his neuer setled braine Suting his name, did in a trice containe Such swarmes of Heresies, as one might see, But such a Master could his Master bee. Th'first thing he doth is to correct the lines Of sacred writ: his second worke declines To liberty of life, affirming, all Christs promises were hyperbolicall. The floodgate thus set wide he keeps no measure But frames al grounds of faith to his owne pleasure, As, that original sinne though others please To tearm it sinne, is only a disease. Baptisme is so indifferent as it may Be done, omitted, yea or taken away. The path to heauen is so broad and plaine, As euen Infidels thereby attaine T'eternall blisse: when sinne we do commit God as the Author moues, and forceth it. All Kings and Princes when they are dispos'd To persecute the truth may be depos'd; For which himself assumes the sword and stirres Euen his owne Countrey-men to Ciuill warres: And there an armed rebell feeles the proofe Of treacherie, and dyes; end good enough. X. ANOTHER. Zvinglius, himself in open field did beare Against his Countrey trayt'rous armes, and there Like to a thiefe, hell's sonne, in sinne did die; And Luther doubt's he's damn'd; so do not I. XI. LVTHER'S CATECHISME. Three God's there are; yet like I not the name Of Trinity; my Soule makes full disclaime From (Homousion); the Antientest of tymes Is the true Author of our greatest crymes. Christ, whome I first reuealed, hath euer been Cloath'd with that flesh which here on earth was seene; Yet that was a mere Spirit, while he the rod Of Gods iust wrath felt for vs, Sonne of God He was no more: but of all men the cheife Blasphemer, leacher, murderer, and thiefe. His conscience then was troubled as impure He did being dead Hell's paines, in Hell endure. His God-head suffered, otherwise he ne're Had beene my Christ: nay he a Sauiour were Vile, base, and abiect, not to be esteem'd, Yea a new Sauiour should haue him redeem'd. The reall body and true blood of Christ, According to the substance is compris'd In euery place, yea in the rope which eyes A wretches necke when in despaire he dies. Those bookes we Iob and Ecclesiastes call This rides without bootes, th'other's but a tale. It is a fond and false opinion T'affirme there are foure Ghospels; onely Iohn The onely true prime Ghospell did set forth. Iames his Epistle is of no great worth, T'is strawy, drye, contentious, and vnfit To be accounted an Apostl's writ. Th'Apocalyps is not Canonicall. Moyses his lippes were full of wrath and gall, Nothing delightfull, angry, stop'd, wherein Noe word of Grace was, but of death, and sinne. The more men doe their Soules with vices staine, The sooner they God's fauour shall obtaine. For the iust offend, euen when they seeke to winne God's grace by Prayer; their best good deeds are sinne. The ten Command'ments doe not appertaine Vnto the free state of a Christian, Whose cheefest art and way, is not to know Good workes, nor actiue Iustice, nor the law; For faith vnlesse without good deeds it be, It is no faith, nor doth it iustifie. Let's but belieue, and though by greatest sinnes Wee striue t'be damn'd, our faith such forces winnes As it alone from Hell will set vs free; For there's no sinne but incredulitie. Let's not debase our selues, all Christians are Able in worth and honour to compare With Christ his Mother, Peter and the rest Of heauen's most Saint-like Cittizens, whose best And purest actions, might as well by dogs Haue been performed, or by filthy hogs. A woeman, or a boy, the Priest away, May giue true absolution: only they Whose Conscience fill'd with confused care, Afflicted, troubled, and erroneous are, Doe worthily receiue: who is baptis'd, Vnder the name of Priest is streight compris'd. All Christians may Christs body consecrate; All preach the word, and all administrate Effectuall Sacraments; yea I can shew That, though the Dyuell doe it, it were trew. To fight against the Turk is to oppose Euen God: none can be subiect vnto lawes Of earthly Magistrate, for all men share Like power, like place on earth, all equall are. Besure you haue regarde that none be stay'd When the wife wil not, for to take the mayd; The Magistrate must bridle such a shrew, Yea put her t'death, which if he will not doe, Let th'husband then suppose her to be dead, And slaine with thieues, and streight another wed: Nor is he bounded here, o no he's free To do't, as oft as he shal vrged be; So that one man by this occasion, may Haue ten or more wiues liuing on a day. The offending person if he cannot tame His fleshes pride, may likewise doe the same. Th'Ghospell noe more excludes Poligam Then th'rest of Moyses law, it still is free; This world hath nothing that can equalis A woeman's loue: he who would be so wise As t'liue without one, let him cease to be Of flesh and blood, for t'is as necessarie T'enioy a woeman, as (my self best knowes) To eate, drinke, purge, watch, sleepe, or wipe the nose. When we are dead, our soules must still remaine All cast on sleepe, vntill we ryse againe. And whether then they must, exempt from death For euer liue, it is noe point of fayth. If any Papists doe this doctrine blame, Tell them, a Papist and an asse are th'same. But, if they doe persist and vrge thee still, Make answer that my reason is my will, Whoe am a Doctour greater farre then all Those, who themselues the Roman church do call. My fayth of errour they shall ne're appeach, Nor shall the Angels iudge of what I teach? For I am sure this doctrine is most true. Soe Luther sayth: now, Reader, what say you? XII. Vpon that fearfull Atheisme of Luther, Zuinglius and Caluin, that God is the author of sinne. Some now a dayes, when into sinnes they fall, Like Eue's vndoubted children, first of all Themselues excuse, and without further stay Th'fault on an other, as the inforcer, lay. But who is he, on whom they doe impose Soe great a burden? Eue the serpent chose, Tis not sure he: ô noe, I quake to tell; He's greater then the greatest power of hell: He (though eu'n faythlesse heathen doe disclame From such a thought) whoe all this All did frame Must, as the authour, that they may be cleare From fault, the poise of their offences beare. The egg, whereof this monster first was made Was got in hell, and since by Satan layd, Ould Simon Magus and the Cerdonistes, Th'Marcionistes, Manicheans and Priscillianistes, With the Seleucians, did (the Church to spight) Keepe it, yet n'ere durst bring it forth to light. Th'infernal Sire of this curstrabble, chose His misshap't cubb Florinus, to disclose This poysnous Hydra: he, twas he whoe first Arm'd with audacious pride and malice durst Attenpt to hatch it, and profane the light Of sacred Truth by it's vnhallowed sight. Longe, as vnseene, did vnregarded lye This hellish prodigie, straight sure to die For want of food, had not through curst remorse Of it's iust misery Luther playd the nurse. He carefull fram'd it steppes, he did it drawe T'a haughty passe, as scorning all it sawe. Then Zuinglius takes it, and fordiuers yeares, The charge ther of himself, most ioy full, beares. Till Caluin, much enamoured of it grace, (Soe Apes doe think their yong all creatures passe) Handled the matter with his brother soe As soone he got it, o how it did growe Vnder his hand! in few yeares it became The cheef support of it new Master's name. He brought it to full growth: and, hauing first Aworld of rare destructions rehearst, He sent it forth, where now (alas!) we see Scarse any place from it's infection free. Great Ireneus did soe much dislike Florinus act, as more then heretique He long since censured him: if soe. what may Wee then of these our latter Rabbins say? XIII. VPON MELANCTHON. Melancthon holds there are three Gods, and striues Mainly to proue plurality of wiues. He teacheth that in case of iust diuorce Th'offending party may, without remorse, Againe contract: and vnder zel's pretence Th'inferior powers he armes against their prince The Sonne of God did, eu'en as God (he sayth) Obey his Father, and resist his wrath, Yea pray vnto him; whence he doth inferr He is his suppliant, Priest and minister. About the Sacraments he held——but what? Tis yet vnknowne; for still as well in that As other points soe wau'ring he appeares, As noe side dare securely call him theirs: For which respect eu'en they, whoe most would rayse His name, referre him to the Diuell's prayse: Yea doubt of his saluation. What could frame For such a man a more befitting name, Then this of Black-earth? ô, it sutes him well! For nothing that is whyte, can enter hell. XIIII. VPPON BVCER. Bvcer, as some affirme, was first a Iewe; But doubting that; his mind he did imbew With Christian rites, and, vpon iust dislike Of Iudaisme, became a Catholick; Yet stayd not there, but soone did that reiect For Luther's, then new rays'ed, licentious Sect. Yet that, he held not long, but chang'd againe, And vowd himself a perfect Zuinglian. From hence he back to Luther made repaire; And there, for his offence, by humble prayer He pardon crau'd: but this he soone forgot, And straight resum'd his former Zuinglian's coat Nor want there some, whoe dare auerre for true, That, after this, he dy'd, as first, a Iew. Whoe'l not admire this man? sure he doth misse it, Who his Religion cannot like, what is it? XV. VPON PROTESTANTS Sacraments. Yovr Sacraments, you say doe onely signe, Witnesse, and seale, the promises deuine; And, euen to' him, whoe faythfully repentes, Conferre noe grace, ô gracelesse Sacraments! XVI. THE PROTESTANTES Oath of Alleageance. I A. B. truly from my hart protest That if Priestes be not by the King represt, My self will rayse the people to effect What he will not: and if he doe erect Himself 'gainst God, I'll not regard his place, But, rather then obay him, spit in's face. If he himself giue ouer to the vice Of lust, of riote, pride or auarice, Or willfully infringe our feudall lawes, And play the Tyrant, I will straight dispose, As best I can, th'inferiour Magistrate By peace or warr his fury to abate. Which if, through want of courage, he refuse The people shall attemptit: they shall vse All meanes they can to worke his ouerthrowe, Take him, arraigne him, and depose him to. But if these fayle, we, in our iust defence, Will suppliants be vnto some forraine Prince T'assist vs with his ayd, that pulling downe Our King, he, if we please, may take the crowne. But if yet all these meanes defectiue proue, Then I my self, inspired from aboue, Either by poyson, pistoll, sword or knife, Or such like wayes, will take away his life. A deed soe farr from treason, as I sweare, That he whoe kills a raging Wolf or Beare Deserues lesse pay, for from this acte proceeds Th'whole Kingdom's good; ô't is the best of deeds! For all such kings as doe God's lawes, transgresse, And to the same their fearfull subiects presse, Of their due honour sull depriued be, And th'subiects from their vs'd alleageance free. And then we scourge them may with their owne rod. All these and more I sweare; soe help me God. XVII. TO THE KING'S MOST EXCELLENT Maiesty my dread Soueraigne. Pardon, most gratious Soueraigne, if my verse Distast thy eares: what I aboue rehearse Is not my owne: I onely doe relate The Tenets of such foes vnto the state, As would (if they had power) assayle the crowne, And in thy blood all our best fortunes drowne. My prayers, are (as likwise of the rest Of my deare brethren) that thou mayst liue blest Aboue thy wishes; all disasters chase, And still looke smiling fortune in the face. May peace by thee with that same throne be grac't, Wherin thy royall Father hath her plac't: And all such wretches, as beare any part In hate to thee, put off their traytrous hart, That noe tumultuous or disloyall straine May e're disturbe the quiet of thy raigne. Be forraine and home-bred iniurious scopes A gainst thy person strangled in their hopes: And whoe knowes treason and reueales it not, Be food to beastes, and branded with the note Of Traytor; yea, let those so censur'd be, Whose onely thoughts are false to thine or thee. This, all true subiects wish, this, each implores, Who'll not subscribe to this, is none of ours. XVIII. CALVIN'S CREED. Three Gods there are; noe Father; nor can he, Whoe made of nothing all, allmighty be. Christ is to God, as God, inferiour, And doth, as God, for vs God's ayd implore. He truly was a sinner, not God's Sonne, His birth made Mary, of a Virgin, none. Shee was too busy, of a haughty vaine, And spightfully God's power did restraine. Christ not one onely, but two persons hath, And was endew'd, as other men, with fayth. He, as in yeares, so did in wisdome growe, Yet did not, when at wisest, all thinges knowe. He vs'd noe grounded method to confute The aduerse part, but, when he did dispute, He his opponents either did amuse With farre fetch't similitudes, or els abuse Their fayth by some superfluous inference, Harsh phrase, and words not in a proper sense. To vicious passions he sometymes obay'd, Was disobedient, cowardly, rash, dismay'd; For through base feare he did t'his power denie To be the world's mediatour, and to dye, And more afrayd of death was, then we see Theeues now, or other wicked persons be. Yea he then quite forgot and did not deeme Himself to be, whoe should our soules redeeme. His prayer was not aduis'd, but such as did A more proportioned correction need. Nothing had beene effected if his death Had bene but corporall; for, e're his breath Forsook him, he was truly in despaire, And did the death of more then body feare. His guilty soule was cited for to come Before th'Eternall, to receaue her doome; And was tormented with th'Infernall paines, Which for the damn'd forsaken soules remaines. And, to be breef, no other signes there are In all his death, but tokens of despaire. He went to hell, that is, God did impose Those paines on him, he doth vpon his foes; Whence he became in horror with the fright Of black damnation, and with that did fight. His body dead, aliue againe was made, Not of himself, but by his Father's ayd. He sits at God's right hand; that is, he holdes Next vnder him, cheefrule, and all controlls. Wee need not feare to haue our sinnes awaite For Iudgment, ransom'd at so high a rate. The holy Ghost is God, as I haue showne, Distinct from both, the Father and the Sonne. Tis false to say, the Church can neuer fayle, For then it fell, when Popes did first preuaile. Penance is needles; eu'ry sinnfull falle In baptisme is remitted once for all. It is a foolish madnes to maintaine That after death our flesh shall ryse againe. In heau'en it self no Saints haue yet at all byn. Whoe speakes these words, a Christian? noe; Iohn Caluin. XIX. VPON SAINT PAVL and Luther. Paul in his writings oftymes IESVS names, Luther the Diuel's name more oft proclames. What is the reason? sure, on either part The Mouth speakes from th'aboundance of the hart. XX. Vpon the late peace betwixt the King of France and the Hugonots. Warr's stormes are past, the gentle breath of peace Hath forc't in France all noysome vapours cease. The Rochellers and their adherents now Their humble necks, vnto the King doe bow. They now no more will for Religion's sake Rebellious armes against their Sou'raigne take. Noe more contemne his Edicts, and noe more Against his powers forraine power implore: Hence forth they'l neuer vnder fayre pretence To shew their fayth, come armed to their Prince, Nor armed treate with him, like such as stand To begge an almes with threatning sword in hand. They'l ne're contend by open force againe From him his sacred Churches to detaine: Nor will their Preachers, arm'd with pistols, proue If them to greater treasons they may moue. Religious persons, Abbeys, Monasteries, Preists, Altars, Vestments, Reliques, Images, And whatsoeuer els, may now be free From the profane reach of impiety. They'l cease. But stay; a further clause remaines; I had forgot my self, they'r Puritans. XXI. VPON CAROLOSTADIVS. As Car'lostadius first begin's to preach, The Diuel courteously takes paines to teach, Guide and direct him, and to make him still Better obserue the proiects of his will, He kindly creepes intho him, and directs His tongue to all Hell's most desir'd effects. So that, when e're this Doctour silence breakes, His lips and tongue moue, but the Diuell speakes. And whyle helyes, expecting eu'ry hower To try the force of death's all-forcing power, The Diuel visits him. Monster of men! The Diuel left thee not till death: nor then. XXII. VPON BEZA, BETWIXT HIS Candida, and Andebert. What? is not Beza yet resolu'd? nor yet? Still doth he doubt on whether part to set His spacious lustes, his lustes as hard to fill As is the gulf of his insatiate will. See, see, ô, how he, fearfull to distast Either damnation, his loosse eyes doth cast Alike on both, as if he faine would gleane Equall acceptance both from Boy and Queane. Now her he courts; then, fearing least that act Displease his Ganimed, he seemes t'retract His former errour, and assures the Boy That he alone shall be his onely ioy. His iealous punke at last perceaueth this, And stormes therat; he calmes her with a kisse: Then, to his Boy: thou sweete (sayth he) art myne, Thou art my cheef delight. O rare Diuine! XXIII. VPON PROTESTANT Predestination. Ere Rome, the world's then empresse, did embrace That sacred Truth, whose path she now doth trace, Mettall and stone, her owne workes, she ador'd, And help, of what requir'd her help, implored. The ioyfull reapers of the fruits of Nile Worship't a Cat, Dog, Bull &amp; Crocodile, Ibis and Hawkes; yea offered vp their groanes To Beetles, Aspes, Garlick, and Onyons. Snakes, Adders, Tigers, Skritch-owles, Bats and Trees, Hearbs, Beasts and Birdes are Congo's Deities. To the Diuel Calicute doth prayer assigne, Yea to an Ape, Elephants, and Kine. But bolder Pegu doth in this excell In sacrifice she feeds the Diuel well, And giues him musique: spacious Tartary And fayre Cathaga much deuoted be To a God of Felt, in whose conceit Earth, Fire, Sunne, Water, Starres, the like respect require. The Philippina's doe adore an Oxe Peru a mount of Sand, a Cocke and Foxe An Emerald and Thunder: Mexico Before a liuing Slaue as God doth bow; Yea to a masse of Paste which long hath stood Tempred in Childrens and in virgins blood. The lands betwixt Cambaia and Malabar Th'first thing they meet, after the morning-starre Hath told the Sunn's approach, be't Bull or Boare Or any Creature els, they low adore. Rude misshap't Stones industrious China makes Her Gods, with heauen and Hell-hags wound with snakes. To a Flint Narsinga; th'farthest Moschi fall To an old wiue's shape; Lithuania to a Mall. And in this sottish manner diuers more For their Creatour, creatures doe adore: All foolishly, I grant; yet all hope t'gaine Some good by this their superstitious paine; And think, that in reward each God proceedes With euery one according to his deedes. But Protestants serue such a Tyrant God As doth (say they) inflict the dreadfull rod Of his eternall wrath, no care once had Of any of their actions good or bad: Yea though they be the chiefe in Vertue's schoole, They must be damn'd: Which is the greatest foole? XXIIII. A LETTER TO A MINISTER from one of his Pupills concerning S. Austins Workes. Sir, Since I saw you last, though many a hill Plaines, woods, &amp; groues our bodies doe diuide, Your best part hath beene present with me still, Distance of place, that from me nere could hide. The ghostly good derections, which by you It pleasd' the Spirit to me then impart Straight in my soule to such perfection grew As they nere shall, nor can from thence depart; You taught me then to know Rom's scarlet-whore And other points, which then I held amisse: Wherewith emboldned, now in one thing more Your graue aduice I craue, &amp; this it is. I doubt not but you know in what esteeme With our best Authors Austin's writings are. To some so free from errour he doth seeme As none but Scripture may with him compare. Others doe stile him the profound'st Diuine And great'st of Fathers, since th'Apostles were. Others affirme he did in learning shine Farre aboue all that did or will appeare. Others appeale vnto him, some him call The Fathers Monarch, one more free from taint Of error then the purest of them all And say, he doubtlesse was a Protestant. Yet I perusing of his Workes, can see (Thus much the Spirit hath giu'n me to discerne) Nothing but rules of wicked Popery Nor ought by him but superstition learne. To instance some; he holds the Church-decrees, Which are the bookes we ought true Scripture call. Toby, with Iudith, Hester, Machabees, He, Papist-like, doth hould canonicall. Generall Traditions are to be obseru'd Christ's true Church only called Catholike None must gain-say her; she is still preseru'd From fall; Rom's Church is chiefest, &amp; the like. The holy Sacraments doe grace conferre And with the Crosse's signe applyed be: He doth moreouer seriously auerre, That such are damn'd as vnbaptised dye. He holds the reall presence, which the bad As well as good receiue, and doth it call A sacrifice, whereof he euer had A care noe peece vpon the ground should fall. It ought by all to be ador'd (sayth he:) And holds the Papists now-Confession: Orders besides, a Sacrament to be He shewes, and teaches Extream-vnction. His sentence still against our Fayth proceedes In all these so much controuerted Heads. Iustification, Free-will, Merit of deedes; Which fayth perhaps through him now so farre spreads; In Prayer to Saints, their Worship, Images, Prayer for dead, materiall fire in hell, And Purgatory-paines; he ne're doth cease Our now-held Doctrine to his power t'refell. With our blind Papists a mayne difference Twixt Mortall sinnes and Veniall he vnfolds: A vowed chastity, Fastes, Abstinence From certaine meates on certayne days he holds. In brief what holds he not? scarce doe I know One part of him from superstition free; His doctrine to approue, his rules t'allow Were to reduce expulsed Popery. Which makes me wonder, why we say, that he The iudgement of the ancient Church doth shew; For grant but that, and since we disagree From him our Doctrine must of force be new. Faine would I know, how best I might defend Our faith, if euer Papists should obiect And aske: why, since his writings we commend, We their authority as weake reiect. So hoping to receiue ere long your best And soundest counsell in this case, I rest. XXV. The Minister's Answer to the former letter. Dearely beloued, I haue read your lines, Wherein aboue the common course of youth As in a spotlesse mirrour clearly shines A perfect zeale to search &amp; finde the truth. Now as concerning briefely your demand, Of Hippo's Austin's so much vrged fayth: Why's all he writes pure Ghospell? what command Haue we to credit whatsoe're hee sayth? I but, say you, some doe him much commend, And vnto him as a sure ground appeale. I answer, such appeales too farre extend, They hurt themselues and the true Churche's weale. They giue too great a scope, themselues they shew Too much obsequious to Room's Popish broode, Their cause they iniurie: what haue we to doe With man's inuentions now, with flesh or blood? For though some prayse him, some there also are, Perhaps as zealous of the Word as they, Who will not doubt, before they doe impare The grounds of Truth, his errours to display. Be there not many of our learnd'st Diuines Who in some places of his workes suspect His sincere dealing, &amp; by diuers signes His contradicting of him self detect? One you shall find his reasons disallowes, Another markes his grosse absurdity, Another his vngrounded speaches shewes And some his furthring of Idolatry. Nor want there some who dare affirme, he erres And is corrupt, &amp; vseth quircks; &amp; some Auouch that to belieue what he auerres, Were to set vp the faith againe of Rome. What should I say? how many doe oppose Against him, his authoritie despise, And doubt not, on him this fowle taint t'impose, That leauing Scripture he doth temporise. Nay more then that, some wil not stick to say, His wordes repugnant to the scripture be, And on his back the imputations lay Of rashnes, boldnes, and imprudencie. The sower, or increaser some him call Of seedes not gratefull in the Almightye's sight, Some stile him foole and dolt, and not at all Inspired with the Lord's all-guiding Spirit. If so; why should we on his words rely To find that truth which only Scriptures shew: Noe, let vt this pernicious custome flye If e're we meane th'vndoubted Truth to know. Nor would I haue you from this man alone But from all other Fathers to refrayne, For 'mongst them all scarce can you find me one But doth mayne poyntes of Papistry maintayne. So that as long as we on them insist Still in the self-same errours shall we stay: God's onely Word can onely chase this mist, No Sunne but that, that onely shewes the way. Now to your last demaund; make answer stil Your faith's not tyed vnto each man's tongue; T'Austin y'are ready to resigne your will, As long as he doth to the Word no wrong. Say thus and they are mute: be not intic't To leaue this n'ere-forc't Hold: farewell in Christ. XXVI. A REPLIE TO THE PRECEDENT letter. Yours I haue read, and since you cannot giue Better solutions to my doubts, I grieue To haue so long insisted on the path Of your so much esteemed, so empty Fayth. For, if (as Beza did himself reply To such as did the same with you deny) Austin and other Fathers did maintayne Those poynts for true, which you reiect as vaine; Why, as if you alone could neuer erre Should you your iudgment before theirs preferre, And neuer cease their writings to oppose Against the Scriptures, since they euery clause, No lesse then you, but with a more profound And deeper sight, did on the Scripture ground? The question therefore as I thought before, Is not heere whether we should credit more God's word or them, each child can that decide But whether now Men's iudgments should betyde To what you hold the worde's true sense to be, Or that whereon they iointly all agree. Heere lyes the doubt: when you doe them excell In this, I'le then returne; till then fare well. XXVII. Vpon Peter Martyr. When pale death summond Martyr to appeare Before th'Eternall's dread tribunall chaire, In Brentius heauen, he vow'd he would not come, He long before renounc't the heauen of Rome. In Zuinglius heauen sure he then would stay, With Theseus, Numa, Scipio &amp;c.) where are they? XXVIII. ON OECOLAMPADIVS. Oecolampadius still in outward shew Vow'd himself confident that al was true He either preach't or writ: but in his hart He doubted still of some and no small part. Which priuate doubt (allthough he did pretend Outward assurance) lasted till his end; I meane till Sathan, for his goodly merits, Vouchsaf't to quit him of his vitall spirits. Shame not hereat; Luther thy ancient friend Will tell thee, 'twas an honorable end. XXIX. Vpon the familiarity of Luther, Carolostadius, Zuinglius, Caluin, Beza, and others with the Diuell. Some Protestants, as they themselues rehearse, Haue with the Diuel oft had great commerce. Luther with Diuels oft did lye and walke; With Diuels Car'lostadius oft did talke; Zuinglius receaued from the Diuell his fayth; Caluin on Diuels called at his death; Beza's preferr'd to be the Diuels scribe; And some are full of Diuels. A Diu'lish tribe XXX. The Protestant Iubilie. All you who hate the idle smoake Of Rom's good-workes, and scorne her yoake. You proud disturbers of all peace, You Tyrants, you who neuer cease Of your oppressed subiects still T'exact for law your lawlesse will. You who with traytrous armes withstand Your lawfull Sou'raign's iust command, And to molest and vexe the King Pretend the State's reordering. You wanton wits, you who profane The Sabaoth's rest with seruile gaine, You who attempt by magick spell To your behestes to summon hell: You cut-throat Theeues, you Vsurers, You Forgers, you Extortioners, You disobedient children, You Who in man's blood your hands embrew: You Leacher, Pandar, Bawd and Whore, You who afflict and starue the poore: You froward wretches, You false teachers, You Brib'd Iudges, you Truce-breakers: You who murd'red haue your brother, Stabb'd your father, kill'd your mother: You Drunkards, Gluttons, Sycophantes, You impious scoffers at the Saints, You guile full gamesters, You who be Iustly condemnd of Simony: You false Informers, you who still I' vnmeasur'd pride direct your will: You who sucke after other's bloud, You who enuy your neighbour's good, You Cursers, you who still afford A bloudy oath to eu'ry word: And you by whom are dayly sold Lawes, iustice, right, and all for gold, Lands in lust and riot lauish't, Wiues defiled, Virgins rauish't, The lawfull Rulers had in scorne, Vice ouerpriz'd, false-witnes borne, Seruants wronged, Masters cheated, Tales to others hurt repeated, Churches robb'd, the weake opprest, Widowes, Orphanes all distrest. And finally, all you, whose crimes Exceed the measure of our tymes, Cheere vp yourselues, my noble Geux, And lend your eares: I bring you newes Of a more easy Iubilie Then euer did the Roman See Bestow on hers. For when as shee Presumes to set her Papists free From their offences, first of all They straight forsooth to mind must call Their forepast sinnes, and then stirre vp Themselues to sorrow (ô this cup Hath no good rellish:) then againe All this their labour's spent in vaine Vnlesse they meane with all their might T'amend their liues; I, ther's the spight. Nor will this serue, but they must go, And to a Priest all humbly show. Besids, they must both watch and pray, The world's loosse pleasures cast away, And if their sinnes be greater, then The lighter faults of other men They must be penanc't, and for that Giue almes, fast, and I know not what. All which I'm sure, if that you be Luther's true off-spring, you will see To be but deeds, which may by dogs As well be compass'd, or by hogs. But you my Roaring desp'rate Boyes, Are freed from all these tedious toyes. The great and gen'rall Pardon, which I now proclaime is nothing such. O noe; you may still murder, sweare, Steale, cheate, and still fals-witnes beare, You need not leaue your drunken feastes, You still may vse maides, boyes, yea beastes, Still enuy others, still be proud, Take Vsse by God nor man allow'd, Be mad through rage, vse wanton diet Apply yourselues to slouth or riot, Curse, damne, and haue your magick spells, Your punke, or whatsoeuer els, And yet as soone or sooner winne This gen'rall pardon for each sinne, Then if you left them: for you know Our Luther doth most plainly shew, That th'more we doe ourselues deface With sinnes, we nearer are to grace. This Iewell now, this pretious gemme This costly pearle, this golden streame Of heauenly grace (because I know You wish to haue me shew't, &amp; so Your thirsty hopes at last relieue) Is this, and only this: Belieue XXXI. On Andræas Musculus. Mvsculus held, that Christs diuinity Vpon the Crosse did with his body dye: And in his profane bookes plaine grounds did lay To make the Ghospel giue the Alcoran way; All which he euer did, no lesse then sound And orthodoxall points, on Scriptures ground. How wel his Name his inclination shewes! Who't feed such Monsters, chatters, teares, &amp; gnawes Which such fond glosses, as himself thinkes fit, The sacred volumes of th'Eternall's Writ. For Musculus to all imports the same That little mouse in English: hence thy name Thou takest Musculus. Take heed, and watch Th'infernall Catt; She hath a diu'elish Scratch. XXXII. Looke beyond Luther. Looke beyond Luther: what espy you there? I finde the Fathers then possessed were With the now censur'd doctrines of Free-will Merit of workes, Fastes, Power to fulfill Gods sacred Precepts, Vowes of Chastity, S. Peter's and the Pope his Primacy The Reall presence, Water mixt with wine The Eucharist reseru'd and yet diuine I meane still Reall, Altars, Sacrifice, That Sacraments giue grace, the Church comprise Both good and bad, with Satisfaction, Confession, Chrisme or Confirmation That we may pray to Saints, yea and assigne Vnto themselues, their Images, and shrine Religious worship, that the Crosse may bee Honour'd; with Prayer for dead and Purgatory, With Limbus Patrum, and that Faith alone Produceth not Iustification. But these are Papists Heads: what? then behinde Your famous Luther can we nothing finde Which you may challenge and securely vant To be the true badge of a Protestant? Yes; at his heeles, scortcht in lasciuious fyer, Lies the cast habit of a periur'd Frier. XXXIII. Looke vpon Luther. Looke vpon Luther; what is he? a man Confessedly attended with a traine Of many vices; one that beares a sense By much too deepe, of his self-excellence, The pride of his ambitious minde is such, Yea so vnmeasur'd, as't can brooke no touch. Among his heads of fayth, some doe appeare Deceiptfull, others vaine, some not sincere, Some false, some reprobate, which with the light Both of Gods word, &amp; Christian fayth doe fight; Where he presumes the Scriptures to expound, His errours and corruptions oft are found Like to the Arians, and Marcionites To be both plaine &amp; many: when he writes Like to a scoffing cheater he doth bring Now this, now that, forth of the selfsame thing, Ne're with himself at one: and when he gets Once an opinion, instantly he sets Others at naught; that now to hold he'll trye, Though from himself, or scripture he doe flye. Yea, t'spight his foe, when he the truth hath mist', Against his conscience he will still persist: And yet this man doth still himself preferre, And damnes all those, who with him will not erre. Besides, he is, as sure as God is God, A Diu'lish lyar; yea and allmost mad Through rage of lust: he is as liberall Of his dire execrations vnto all, As frantick men of stones: and still affordes Such stormes of railing, &amp; inuectiue wordes Gainst priuate men, and kings as one would sweare Th'Infernall furies in his speaches were. He Sathan knowes, and Sathan him againe, They are of long acquaintance; through his braine He sometime runnes while as he reades, or writes, Sleepes with him nearer then his Kate: a nights. He hath a Diuell or two, not of the throng Of vulgar Diu'lls, but such as are among Hell's great'st Diuines, on all occasions still Prompt, and obseruant to performe his will. He vseth Scurrill, and immodest wordes Names oft the Diuell, talkes of dung &amp; (?) Beraying, priuyes, durty puddles, sinkes Windy gutt-crackes. Fie take him hence he stinkes. XXXIV. Looke on this side Luther. Looke now on this side Luther, and relate What you can find in his reformed State; Th'inconstant weake Melancthon first I see; Next him that channell of impiety That barb'rous, doltish, ignorant, impure, Possessed heretiq; and Epicure Carolostadius: neare to him do passe That Ape that Cyclops, and two-footede Asse, The Sycophant, the dog Heshusius, And the Eutychian lying Brentius, Next th'heretique Osiander hand in hand With that vnchristian'd wretch, that factious brand. Zuinglius, who had his doctrine from a spright, Which but since death, he knew if black or white; Perfidious fickle Bucer next doth go, Then Iames Andræas, who no God did know But Gold and Bacchus; nor by night, or day, Was euer this Adult'rer seene to pray. Th'Angell of darknes Caluin now appeares, Who on his back the shamefull token beares Of a hot iron, for th'vnnaturall vice Of Sodomy, who after died of lice, And in dispaire exhal'd his hatefull breath, Cursing and calling Diuels till his death. Here comes another of this vertuous tribe That profane bawdy Scurre, that Diuels Scribe Lasciuious Beza, in vndecent sort Betwixt his Candida, and Andebert. Now Allemannus the blasphemous Iew Beza's great freind: then th'Authours of the new And later Arians, the vndoubted Spawne Of Caluin, whence was all their doctrine drawne, Syluanus, Dauid, Gentil Blandrata, Gribald, Seruetus, with the Apostata Bernardin Ochin, ioyned to whome heere lurkes Alciate, with Neuser, circumcised Turkes. With many more such zelous Protestantes All Luthers of spring, yea and all prime Saintes In his new Church. Who'ld not imbrace this faith Which such rare Doctours, such strong pillars hath? XXXV. On Bullinger. Thou writest, Bullinger, (omitting much, Which can noe more then these, abide the touch) That the three Persons in the Trinity Doe differ not in state but in degree. That Christ to hell, his suffrings at an end, Did not in person but in power descend. That Iohn did an Apostata become That infants lying in their mother's womb Are truly iustified: that some now liue In heauen who neuer did in God belieue; And to conclude that any Christian Holding faith's groundes, though he besides maintain Blasphemous poyntes of stiff-necked Iudaisme, Or Infidelity, much more of schisme, May come to heauen. Perhaps thou hast deprau'd This Poynt, to proue that thou thy self art sau'd. XXXVI. THE LYE. Papists doe hold (thus prate all Ministers Whome to the pulpit their glib tongue preferr's) That ther's noe God, that all which Scriptures shew Concerning Christ are fables, and vntrue; That after this, there is noe life; nor must Our flesh, once rot, return againe from dust; The Virgin Mary is their cheifest God; She hath all power, she rules the dreadfull rod Of Heau'ns dread wrath, for her they Christ reiect, And more at her hands, then at his expect. The Saints they doe, in lieu of Christ, implore, Their shoes, cloathes, images, and bones adore. Christ's death, they hold, for men did pardon gaine, Women are saued by one Mother Iane. A man with them, may God's commandments keepe Without his grace: all faith is laid to sleepe When they doe Penance; yea t'is Heresy T'affirme that faith therein is necessary. Noe one of them by Christ, but by bare straines Of mans inuention, vnto heauen attaines. And when they pray noe mention's made of Christ, But of his creatures. Minister, thou ly'st. XXXVII. The reformed Protestant. Lvther pretending clearely to reforme The Roman Church, did raise his firster storme 'Gainst Pardons, Pope, &amp; Monks: but not content With that, he straight his second forces bent Against the Scriptures, Sacraments, and grace, Iustification Works, Freewill and Masse; Yet was he iudged scarce to haue vntyl'd The roofe of Babylon. Zuinglius compyl'd A second Reformation, and complain'd Of diuers things, which Luther still retain'd, As th'Reall presence, with the Crosse to blesse; Saints honour, Purgatory, Images. Yet was he censur'd nothing to haue done But slightly battred superstition. Caluin, with Beza and their fellows try'd To make the Church yet purer, and deny'd Lay persons Baptisme in a needfull case, Saints feasts, Vniuersality of grace, Power of Priests t'absolue the penitent, Church-vestments, ceremonies, Christ's descent To Hell, all Churches Headships to reside In Bishops, and to their wills law's t'be ty'd. Yet did not here this reformation rest, Others condemn'd this, as a second Beast, A fayned church vnto the Harlot built, Reformists all with forged colours guilt, Sinnefull prouokers of th'Eternal's wrath, A fond, new, strange, and Antichristian faith. These say, that th'heyght of reformation, Is to throw all materiall churches downe, Raze Vniuersityes, reiect the prayer Our Lord (we say) did for his church prepare; Neither doth yet this reformation please; To make the church most pure, &amp; from disease Of all corruptions cleare, the Trinity Must be impugned, with Christ his Deity. Stay, stay, great Sages of this wondrous church, Whither at last wil your admired Torch, The Spirit, conduct you? whither will you goe? For what coasts are you bound? ô, now I know; Belike y' are bound with your reformed couple Alcyate and Heuzer, for Constantinople. XXXVIII. On Math. Flaccus Myricus. Thy brethren tearme thee, Flaccus, a profane Foe to all truth; as impudent as Cain, A Dunghill-cock, a Snake, a Dogge, a Scurre, A loathsome Cancer, Fury, Epicure, Vngratefull cuckow, periur'd, wicked, base, Impugner of the vertuous, doltish Asse, Foule grunting sowe, who with her filthy nose, Furrow's all grounds, where any goodnes grow's: Vaine Thraso, faithlesse Sinon, impudent Thersites, Harpax, hayre-brain'd Sycophant Blaster of freindship, kindler of debate, Sower of discords, enuy, iarres, and hate; A full-blowne bagpipe, which when any tryes To presse, or squeeze it, squeaketh nought but lyes; The Diuel's liuely organ, and his sonne, Deseruing, as Christ's enemy, a throne In Hell's damn'd court. If in this manner those Who are thy Brethren, speake, what say thy foes? XXXIX. ON CALVIN. Caluin, in pay of that despairing sinne He laid on Christ, himself did dye therein. And while from forth his vlcerous flesh did burst, Wormes, stench, and lice, still swore, blasphem'd, &amp; curst, And on the Diuell without rest did call; Which argueth his good nature, and that all His wits were perfect: Since so neare his end He had so cleare remembrance of his friend. XL. An other on the same. Caluin, your faith's chief Patriarch, did dye Of wormes, and lice: nor neede you to deny, The truth hereof: great men haue dyed thus, For thus dyed Herod and Antiochus. XLI. The Protestant iarre. No sooner Sectaryes, drunk with the pride Of their owne wits, beginne for to deride Their mother Church, and leaue that steadfast rock, 'Gainst which no power, nor Infernall shock Can e're preuaile; but they beginne to reele, And their small forces, and great weaknesse feele. And like to Cadmus brawling serpent-brood 'Gainst one an other in a frantik mood Conuert their weapons. Hence did Magus first Into Menandrians, and Saturninians burst, With Basilidians: from the Manichees The Catharists and Macharians did aryse: Appellians, Seuerians, Lucianists, Were branches all sprong from the Marcionists Montanus spawn'd th'Phrygasts, Pepuzians, And Artotyrists: The Martyrians, With th'Enthusiastes from Messalus came, As those that doe from Sathan take their name. And from Arius sprong th'Acacians, With Macedonians, and Eunomians. But all these ioyn'd in one shew noe effects Of discord, equal to our moderne sects; They are diuided into Lutherans, And Sacrament-blaspheming Zuing lians And these againe both subdiuided, make More seu'rall branches, then th'Lernean snake Sprouted forth heads: all whose contention spring's About Fayth's grounds, and not in triuiall things. Christ's Natur's, Vnion, and Distinction, His Incarnation, and Ascension, Baptisme, Good-workes, Man's iustice before God, Christ's corporall eating by the good and bad, Iustification, which by their church still Is held the very soule of fayth, Freewill, Christ's Reall presence, his Vbiquity, Th'Ghospel, Law, Sacrament, and Trinity, With many more, which to be brief I spare, Of their distinctions the maine subiect are. Nor be these iarres maintain'd among the base, And common small-shot; they of chiefest place Are the prime agents, and with so great hate Nourish the raging flame of their debate, As they by mutuall sharpe proscriptions Banish each other from their seuerall townes, Seare them with th'odious brands of Heritick, Infidel, Iew, Turck, Diuel and the like, Erect strict Inquisitions, fill the geoale With their susprised bodies, stop the sale Of all their bookes, vnciuilly deny The vsuall rights of hospitality Euen to strangers; take offensiue armes; And in confused and tumultuous swarmes Assayle each others; nor be dead corps free From their ne're equall'd sauage cruelty. And what is most worth note, themselues confesse They haue no meanes these discords to redresse Or hope to be atton'd (for that intent Hauing so many fruitlesse meetings spent.) Before that day, when the Eternall shall All men, all causes, vnto triall call. So as some of them with amazement haue Stumbled thereat, and others for to saue Their soules from shipwrack on such stormy seas, Haue made repaire vnto the calmer Bayes Of Rome's ne're shaken Church. By which wee see That shee alone is from all errour free, Which, void confessedly of all such strife, Show's one, and but one way t'eternall life. So by this meanes the Prouerb's truth is knowne: When Theeues dissent, true men regaine their owne. XLII. ON VAFER. Ingenious Vafer can with speciall grace Sute his religion vnto euery place; When he's in England he himself doth vant, A Parlament-Prince-pleasing Protestant; And Holland holds to be a fertill place Of faithles Hereticks; Bohemia's race Of Sectaries, hath no vnited scope In any point, but how to spite the Pope. 'Mongst all translations of the sacred Word That of Geneua's most to be abhorr'd; Whose factious Ministers not by word' alone But by their deeds teach subiects to dethrone Their lawfull Soueraignes. Those in Scotland are Seditious persons, men who neuer spare Their King or country, troublesome, vnciuill, And restles spirits, yea members of the Diuill. The Puritans in generall are lyars Heady aduancers of their owne desires, Crosse, wayward spirit, prone to loosse delights, Scripture-corrupters periur'd Hypocrites. Detracting Satyrists, dogs, Schismaticks Murmurers, Vultures, yea and Hereticks Equall to th'Pharisies &amp; Donatists, Arrians, Ebionites, and Catharists. Th'Florinians, Beguardins, Pepuzians Apostolicks, and Petrobusians. Yet if to Amsterdam he hence do saile, Or to Geneua go, he then doth raile At th'English Church. The Bishops are (saith he) An Antichristian Popish ministry. Their prescript forme of seruice wholy full Of fond corruptions; from the masse they cull Their new Communion-bookes, dissenting farre From the Lord's word it neuer fayling square. The Sacraments they wickedly prophane Their rites and habits Antichristian. Their ministries are neither Prou'd nor Call'd Nor right according to the Word install'd: The most are Monks, Friars, Drunkards, Dolts, or Boyes They baptisme profane with childish toyes And to conclude, they are, he yet beleeues Soule-murd'ring Hereticks, Sacrilegious theeues. Nor doth he there the Lutherans respect, Them he condemneth for a damned sect Of willfull Hereticks; and still them call's Drinkers of bloud, Flesh-eaters, Canniballs, Auerse from Christian faith, Christ's murderers Destroyers of the Creed, Idolaters, Reiecters of Christs death, Zuenckfeldians, Hang-men, Capernaites, Eutychians, Localists, men prodigiously blind, False, wicked, proud, of an ambitious mind, Impudent Asses, more illiterate fooles Then simple Children, that frequent the shcooles. But from these townes this Rouer scarce is got To Wittenberg, but sing's another note; He now auerr's, and seriously, that they Who from the true faith do with Zuinglius stray, And likewise such as Caluin do respect, Are a most damn'd and execrable sect Of conuict Hereticks; on euery part About their body, and within their hart, Aboue, below, behind them, and before, Obsest with Diuells; men deseruing more To be refelled by the aw-full swords Of ciuill Magistrats, then force of words. They are (he now affirmes) to be restrain'd From holy things, their company refrain'd By all good men, most fitting t'be expell'd From forth the Churches bosome, yea and held Not worthy to be pray'd for, and vnfit That Kings should them into their leagues admit; He vowes they are for either faith, or workes, Nestorians, Arians, Anabaptists, Turkes. And in a word, the worst of men, yea he Proclaimes them damn'd for all eternity. Yet into Frizeland if he take his flight Then th'Anabaptists only teach aright; There, as amongst the Caluinists againe, He against Luther slack's his passion's rayne, And with a quau'ring head, and half-shut eyes As if forsooth of zeale his words did rise, In verity he offers to detect Infinite faultes in now false Luther's sect. With carnall wayes, saith he, their soules they staine, And Christ himself they crucify againe, Blaspheme his spirit, and contemne his grace, Affect faire houses, and a wealthy place; They climbe the pulpit there to preach, yet none Hath either Spirit, Word, or Mission. There will they vtter naught that may appeare At all distastfull to their Princes eare. They idly liue, and to relieue their need On Antichrist's rich spoyles through flattery feed; And to such loosnes all their flocks allure As Turkes and Tartars are by much more pure. But when this man, who with such zeale now burn's Vnto Geneu' or Wittenberg returnes; The Anabaptists straight, vnfit t'be nam'd, Chimera-like of diuerse sects are fram'd, Muntzer, and those who of his doctrine share, No men, but meere incarnat Diuells are. Scarce any one but still dissent's from other And will of errour charge his purest brother. If after this he goe to Rome or Spaine He Proteus-like transformes himself againe Then he's a Roman Catholick, and saith, That Rome's the Mother Church: Her only faith Is Orthodoxall, others doctrines be Most iusty all condemn'd for heresy. Yet after all these changes if he come A new Vlisses, to his natiue home, He layes fasthold againe where he began. Say: Is not Vafer a Religious Man? XLIII. ON FVRBO. Fvrbo the Caluinist doth much complaine On Luther, and his followers railing vaine Against his Church; but yet saith he I thinke, They do not dant vs much, nor make vs shrinke; O no, we pay them home; Then he affords A roll of all their mutuall scurrill words And base inuectiues; and refers it straight To all men's iudgments whether's in the right. Belieue me, Furbo, if without offence I might my iudgement giue, t'auoyd all sense Of partiall censure, and my debt defray To Christian charitie, I sure would say, Not to offend here either them, or you, But to content you both: That both say true. XLIIII. On the Protestants rayling vpon the Apostles and Fathers. If either Father, or Apostle crosse Your Ghospel so, as you can finde no glosse T'inuert their words, their euidence to vaile, Against their writings you, or persons raile. Peter, though he by th'Holie-Ghost had beene Confirm'd, you say, committed mortall sinne, Yea err'd in fayth, which errour did import Th'losse of Christ's grace, and Christian freedome's hurt. Th'Apostle Paul did not a litle slide, He was possessed with immoderate pride; And wallow'd in the durt of slauish sense, Subiect to rashnes, and froward confidence. Iames did produce a wicked argument, Scripture 'gainst Scripture cite, and gaue assent To superstitious vowes, yea moued Paul Into the same erroneous zeale to fall. Mathew not truly still, but from the right Sense of their words, the Prophets oft did cite. Iohn vs'd improper speaches, and became A false Apostata; Mark was the same, And most perfidiously himself bereft Of his great charge, and his vocation left: Yet for their bookes, more credit is t'be showne To him and Mathew, then to Luke alone. Thus you th'Apostles censure, what then are The Fathers? them I doubt you will not spare, Yes, as the former: Ambrose you affirme T'haue writ but meager lines, you Leo tearme A haughtie speaker. Austin did decline To more faultes. Cyprian is a weake Diuine. Basil of no worth, Chrysostome a vaine And simple tatling Rhetorician. Maximus doted. Isidore was rash. Old Irenæus builded straw and trash Vpon Truth's grounds. Bold Epiphanius was A pratling Deacon, and so farre did passe All limits, as he shew'd in what he writ More face then learning, and more tongue then wit. Gregorie, like Peter, knew not what he sayd, And with Fulgentius ioyntly passage made For blinde Idolatrie, yet he alone Was the Architect of superstition. Bernard, ador'd Moozim to his end, And stifly did proud Antichrist defend. Hierome ofright should not reputed be Among the Fathers, since with heresie He is infected, and no iudgement hath, Nor care, nor writeth as he ought of faith. And to conclude, the Fathers blinded were, With wretch'd Montanus spirit, nor did feare To preach false doctrine, all their life they err'd So that, vnlesse before their death they clear'd Their consciences from those erroneous taynts, They were not of the Church, nor now are Saints. Thus do the Churche's glorious Lampes become Subiect to your eu'n Christ-controlling doome. While by the same (more partiall) Protestants Are th'mouthes of Christ, great Prophets, Angels, Saints, Lights of whole Nations, men adorn'd with all Vertue and learning, next to Christ and Paul; Worthie Diuines, whose bookes deserue a place I'th' Churche's Canon, whose learn'd Authors trace Truth's foote-steps, righter, and in faith more sound Then since th'Apostle's times haue yet been found. The ancient Fathers of the Church, you say, Were farre to you inferiour euerie way, In clearing of the Scripture's hidden sense, 'Twixt whom, and you, there is that difference As is 'twixt Sunne and Moone. I know it well, Nay more; As much as is 'twixt Heauen and Hell. XLV. Luther's respect to S. Hierome. While Luther liu'd, he would not to haue gain'd Ten thousand Crownes, haue had his soule so stain'd With sinnes black guilt, as Hierom's was, and be In as great perill to be damn'd as he. Sure now to be but so, he would become More tractable, and take a lesser Summe. XLVI. The dutifull children. Not anie Protestant, but still auowes The Church to be his Mother, and Christ's Spouse; And yet, against the square which cannot erre Of Scriptures, yea and Fathers, they auerre, Shee of her Faith hath so regardelesse been, As since the Apostles shee scarce e're was seen But taynted, and impure; did wholy loose Not only th'Ghospel, but euen Christ her Spouse; No sparck of true Faiths heauenlie fire was cherisht; All was destroy'd extinguisht, buried, perisht, Yea eu'n her soule was ouer-whelmed quite Polluted, and deuoyd of all true light. So that in lieu of being true, say they, And faithfull to her Spouse, shee fell away To fowle adulterie. Did er'e fooles before Striue in this sorte to proue their Mother Whore. XLVII. THE IVDGE. Hvsse holds whole Christ doth in the Eucharist Vnder the formes of bread and wine consist. Luther's opinion is, that we are fed With Christ's true real flesh, but ioyn'd with bread. Zuinglius maintaineth, that the bread and wine Are not Christ's bodie, but a naked signe. Caluin dissenting from the former, saith Tis truly Christ, but to the mouth of faith. All these were learned Doctours, and suppos'd To be by th'Spirit to all Truth dispos'd; These all haue Colledges, and men of name, Yea Townes, or Nations, which maintaine the same; The Scripture's words they did acknowledge all, All vs'd the same endeauours, which they call The best approued way, and meanes most fit To finde the true sense of th'Eternall's Writ; They all had skill in tongues, they all perus'd And weigh'd the Text, they all (they thought) still vs'd Due diligence with prayer, and places hard And doubtfull speaches carefully compar'd: Yet did they all in this and manie more Chief heads of Faith, which I haue toucht before, Dissent so farre, as by a mutuall stile In greatest heat each other to reuile With th'name of Heretick; and still did grudge To be oppos'd by anie: Where's the Iudge? FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>