<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Tynan, Katharine, 1861-1931</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Tynan, Katharine, 1861-1931</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">tynan katharine 1861 1931</field>
      <field name="author_text">Tynan, Katharine, 1861-1931</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1890's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.0341.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1896</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466145</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">A Lover's Breast-Knot ; by Katharine Tynan (Mrs Hinkson</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">A Lover's Breast-Knot ; by Katharine Tynan (Mrs Hinkson</field>
      <field name="title_facet">lovers breast knot</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">lovers breast knot</field>
      <field name="title_text">A Lover's Breast-Knot ; by Katharine Tynan (Mrs Hinkson</field>
      <field name="year_display">1896</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1896</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1896</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466145&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466145&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Tynan, Katharine, 1861-1931&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;tynan katharine 1861 1931&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;A Lover's Breast-Knot ; by Katharine Tynan (Mrs Hinkson&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;lovers breast knot&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1896&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1896&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Tynan, Katharine&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1861&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1931&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;A Lover's Breast-Knot&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;by Katharine Tynan (Mrs Hinkson)&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Elkin Mathews&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1896&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp4034&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;49 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;A Lover's Breast-Knot&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;by Katharine Tynan (Mrs Hinkson)&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 49 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">HEARTSEASE TO HARRY Heartsease you gave me, richer, rarer Than any heartsease blowing, growing. Not Death shall make me less the wearer Of the dear heartsease of your sowing. Heartsease you gave me for a token You took my share of pain and grieving. A charmed heart to bear unbroken Amid Love's sorrow, Love's bereaving. Heartsease for yesterday, to-morrow, And for the dying year and vernal: To make me flowers the winter thorough, For mortal Time and Time eternal. Take for your heartsease purple, golden. Heartsease that bloomed in Love's gold weather, For all in which I am beholden, My heartsease and my heart together! Love's Trouble For you I fear the stabbing rain, The wounding wind; O wandering love, return again, Turn and be kind. The distant thunder in the hills I fear for you; I fear the lightning's spear that kills, Wavering, blue. For you the noonday sun I dread. O noonday sun, Rest quietly on his dear head, My dearest one! For you all evil beasts I fear, All foul affrights With wingèd shadows that creep anear In lonely nights. Dear angels, guard him where he goes, In day and dark; Lest nigh his path, in lily and rose, The serpent lurk. O, sleepless eyes of blessed ones, Watch o'er my love; And wings that shame th' eternal suns Winnow above! Greater Love There is but one sweet Love, one Love unroving, Truer than mine may be; One constant Love beyond all mortal loving, Greater than yours for me. Therefore unto that Love I do commend you, So that when mine shall fail That Love unfailing may wrap round, befriend you, That sea of Love prevail. So that when my poor love is but remembered As some sweet thing foregone, That Love may fill you full with sweets unnumbered, And leave you not alone. O Love eternal, Love supernal, keep him If haply I should go; In all Love's raptures, Love's rewardings steep him, Yea, pay him all I owe! Love's Bird When thrushes rest the weary head, And linnets lie in gold and green, When blackbirds on a downy bed Are silvered with a moony sheen, What voice awakes the emerald house? What love incarnate flies on wings? What passion shakes the trembling boughs? It is the Bird of Love that sings. It is the Bird of Love that sings, Stabbing our silence like a sword, And Love himself that flies on wings. God and enchanter and no bird. Our moon of honey, our marriage moon Rides in the heaven for our delight. The silver world grows golden soon, Honey and gold spilled in the night. The Bird of Love, the Bird of pain, He sings our marriage moon away; Filling the night with golden rain, Betwixt the darkness and the day. Closer and closer, hold me close, For is it Love or Death he sings? And is it Love or Death that goes Through the sweet night with rustling wings? Love's Flight There is a love of earth, Love, A love that flies on wings; The one hath lowliest birth, Love, The other blood of kings. O look, look, my Sweetheart, Where yon skylark flies; So light and bright, my Sweetheart, In the clear skies! He is our love on wings, Love, That flies in sure bliss Beyond the wreck of things, Love, On earth where death is. And yet not all of heaven: He flies back to earth To find his heaven at even Beside his own hearth. O look, look, my own Love, 'Tis our love on wings! But, ah, the wingless love, Love, 'Mid earth's creeping things. Love's Watchfulness When you awake I wake, And when you sleep I sleep. Your lightest sigh will break My sweetest dreams and deep. My heart watches aware Whether I wake or sleep. Though far in dreams I fare, Call, and my heart will leap. The grave is not so low, The way to Heaven so steep, But I should surely know If my Love stirred in sleep. What world, what starry sphere My heart in dreams could keep, If you wanted me, dear, If you should wake and weep? Love's Garden A little garden, great enough To hold Love's wings. Yea, and the sacred Bird of Love, Hark, how he sings! The ardent Flower of Love, likewise, Burns in the brake. Love's wings are set with myriad eyes, Ever awake. Heavy with honey flies the bee From rose to rose; Powdered with gold dust to the knee, He comes and goes. The secret song the nightingale Sang to the moon, It shall be hidden by Love's veil, Now it is noon. The secret thing the golden bee Said to the rose, Though it be known to thee and me, Shall we disclose? Ah no! Love's secrets let us keep, Lest the winged god Angered, go seeking, while we sleep, Some new abode. Love Inconstant After April month and May Love of birds will fly away. After June light loves grown chilly Part, though tarry rose and lily. O alas! such loves should sunder, They who made the world a wonder, Raining from their honey throats Golden notes and silver notes! O in April what unrest Stirs the swallow's sea-born breast For some love of old and golden, Where pale orchards bloom unfolden! For some silent heartstring stirred, Some lost heaven remembered. And the old dream calls him home, Home by trackless skies and foam. O alas, such things should be! Cold as stone are he and she: Empty gapes the nest and wide They two planned with such sweet pride. The sweet nestlings flown as far As the light-winged lost loves are. Love, whose love endures, see then How sweet Love is wronged again! How these birds, from lark to sparrow, Snap his bow and blunt his arrow! Love in Absence I LOVE IMPATIENT Come while the sweet Spring stays, O come! Come ere the nightingale be dumb; While on her eggs his mate doth sit, And all the chestnut lamps are lit. Come, ere the baby leaves grow old. Crumpled and soft, these keep the fold Of tight enswathèd buds, O come! While yet the swallow is new to home. Come while our orchard like a bride Blushes through white, and evening-tide Hangs all the pear tree with such white, Spun from the moon-rays for delight. Come while the yellow moon still shows, A moon of honey, a golden rose. And while all night in rapt content Our garden of Eden spills its scent. Come, ere the cuckoo's song is over, Come in the day of every lover, When every lover still wings for home; Come, ere the nightingale be dumb. II LOVE CONTENT I would not shorten if I might By one sweet hour the hours that stand Betwixt me and my heart's delight. May and the lilac in the land, All rapturous sounds, and scents at night, The days spill out their golden sand. Sweet is the garden, white with bloom, Heavy with honey, drenched with scent, Wherein a bride awaits her groom, In a most measureless content. With gold and white day fills the loom, And soon the moon-gold nights are spent. I would not shorten by an hour The hours wherein I wait for you With Love and all the world in flower. So sweet, so sweet in sun and dew, It is the hour of Love's full power, Yet come, and make my world anew! Home-Coming O passionate pilgrim, was the way So long then, was the day so long From the blue matin till 'twas gray? From morning till the evening-song? Was it so long, love, while you came Nearer each minute? lead-foot, slow, Did the day round to evening-flame? And was the daylight slow to go? And did your eager eyes look far To see the crescent moon rise bright? And Hesper, your home-coming star, Did Hesper tarry long that night? At last the moon rained gold, and lest The moon-gold were too cold, there fell Drifting of bloom about your nest; That night the nightingale sang well. O sweet day full of scent and song, Sweetly it wore from dawn to even; And yet the sweet day did us wrong, Since evening brought the lover's heaven. The Lark in Love The lark that's climbing stair on stair His ladder of light that swings in air, Hath a new note for every rung, The lark's in love and young. But soon the clouds allure no more, No more the silver-damasked floor; In spirals was his outward track, But headlong comes he back. He falls, shot through the burning heart, Yea, through the heart by Love's own dart; Too well the cunning archer knew The arrow he sent was true. But, lark, what wisdom dost thou prove Whose wings, still tethered by thy love, Carry thy song to Paradise, Yet sweeter are her eyes. That was her praise, thy song that poured, And his of wedded lovers, the lord. Io Hymen! Thou happy boy, Drunken with love and joy. Io Hymen! O, speckled breast, Minstrel of thine own wedding feast, Lover and bridegroom, singing still, How Love shall have his will! Love's Carefulness Unto myself I am grown dear, Being dear to you, And fearful with a double fear In all I do, Lest that some evil chance should prove Ruin of that poor thing you love. O this woman will love her girl And that her boy! I keep not even the golden curl Of our dead joy; Now both my loves in one are given Ever to you who make my heaven. If all our palaces were dust Blown on the wind, I might some other woman trust To be as kind, To love as well as I—but then What love could bid you love again? O generous giver, who hast given Once and for aye, For life and death, for earth and heaven, As for to-day, I love myself because you hold Every hair of my head as gold. Love's Summer I CALLING THE BIRDS Who close beside our window pane, Whistles thrice at the dawn of day, And listens for his answer fain? Toujours gai. Who bids the merry din resound, While oaten pipes are silvery gray, Ere chanticleer first turns him round? Toujours gai. Who bids the corncrake, shrill and blithe, Wake up on his sweet couch of hay, And whirr against the mower's scythe? Toujours gai. Who hales the finch from dreams of love, And linnet to his roundelay, And from Love's arms the wooing dove? Toujours gai. Who calls the robin and the starling, And bids the blackbird's flute to play, The thrush to sing: O darling, darling? Toujours gai. Who is it wakes the sparrows' wall, And sets a-tremble every spray, With flutter, and chatter, and trill, and call? Toujours gai. This whistling thing at sweet o' the year, O is he bird, or boy, or fay? Mayhap, some fairy chanticleer. Toujours gai. May he be fed on honey and kisses, And where the undying roses stay, Wake the sweet world to newer blisses. Toujours gai. II SUMMER-SWEET Honey-sweet, sweet as honey smell the lilies, Little lilies of the gold in a ring; Little censers of pale gold are the lilies, That the wind, sweet and sunny, sets a-swing. Smell the rose, sweet of sweets, all a-blowing! Hear the cuckoo call in dreams, low and sweet! Like a very John-a-Dreams coming, going. There's honey in the grass at our feet. There's honey in the leaf and the blossom, And honey in the night and the day. And honey-sweet the heart in Love's bosom, And honey-sweet the words Love will say. III SOUNDS Bees in the white and scarlet cell Of bean-flowers and in beds of thyme; The leader of the sheep his bell Ringeth my even-song and prime; He leads his flock at morning early Out to the dark grass sewn with gold, And when the evening dews are pearly, Back to the fold. Somewhere they mow the grass: the sound Brings with it fresh and fragrant breaths. And little airs all scent be-drowned, Blown from the white and purple heaths. The last bird sings his waning passion. And you, whose love can never fail, Take up the burden and narration Of the sweet tale. IV AUGUST WEATHER Dead heat and windless air, And silence over all; Never a leaf astir, But the ripe apples fall; Plums are purple-red, Pears amber and brown; Thud! in the garden-bed Ripe apples fall down. Air like a cider-press With the bruised apples' scent; Low whistles express Some sleepy bird's content; Still world and windless sky, A mist of heat o'er all; Peace like a lullaby, And the ripe apples fall. Love's Praises Let other ladies name their loves With flushing cheek and bashful eye, And voices as the gentle dove's, Crooning her love-song like a sigh; I know not such sweet ways, in faith, And yet I love my Love till death. When I would tell how he excels All other men my eyes grow dim, My heart shakes and my bosom swells, And only tears I have for him. To my own heart with tears I say His name, and silent turn away. Let other ladies sit and sun Like turtle-doves their shining heads, And tell their lovers every one, Their kindness and their gentle deeds. How this is brave and that is true. Only my tears are praise for you. O secrets we may not impart, Being too tender to be told; And sweetnesses that break the heart, Too great for one poor heart to hold. Silence and tears beseem them best, And hidden eyes in my Love's breast. Love's House O in Love's emerald house Of emerald chestnut boughs, The brown wife broods upon blue eggs and dear, Nor finds the gold days long Hearing her true Love's song Of love and wedding in the sweet o' the year. And in Love's golden house Of golden chestnut boughs, The brown bird to his sweet sings wild and clear; Though little ones are gone, The true Love lingers on, For two old lovers in the fall o' the year. Annus Mirabilis (1893) The year that brought our hearts' desire, The Spring came with a sudden glow; No tender Spring that shyly comes With primroses and apple-blooms, But garbed as with a golden fire Of her own daffodills a-blow. O year beyond all years that were! The Summer followed fast in May; Scarce had the nightingales begun When the red rose out-burned the sun, And scent of ripe fruit in the air Mixed with the honey-breath of hay. That year the Spring came over again, There were two Summers in that year. In August there were bird-nestings And second broods and such sweet things, And on the world a golden rain, And a new blossom on the pear. That year the year was always May. Our year in whose sweet close shall come No winter with a waning sky, Nor sad leaves fall, nor roses die; But roses, roses all the way, And never a nightingale be dumb. Love at Easter Sing to the Lord a new song! Because the Spring comes newly, And every slender sapling Has budded green and red. Sing to the Lord a new song! The skylark sings it truly, Since all in dewy April His love and he are wed. Sing to the Lord a new song! For every bird's a lover, And o'er the purple furrows The green spears nod and wave. Sing to the Lord a new song! Since Lenten fasts are over, And Easter's gone in glory, And Christ has left the grave. Sing to the Lord a new song! A song of love and wedding, For every bird is building His nest in bower and tree. Sing to the Lord a new song! The tufts of soft wool spreading Where a brown wife and babies This April-tide shall be. Of the True Marriage Unto His servant on a day The Lord revealed His hidden way. He said: “Within this city great, Where sin still slays the Lamb of God, What dost thou think I contemplate For comfort when I look abroad?” His servant answered: “Yonder church Crowded at Mass-time to the porch.” The Lord replied: “Not so”; and then, His servant guessed to make Him glad The priest where he sat shriving men; The wounded healed; the orphan clad; The widow's tears wiped off; the poor Fed from another's little store. And then he guessed the saint who died Last night; Fra Leo, vigil-pale, Painting the wings of Heaven; Christ's bride New-wed, beneath her shadowy veil; The grey cross in the market-place With children playing at its base. And many things of earth and heaven: The Convent garden and the doves; The Western sky aflame at even; The mountains and the orange groves; The sea that moaned alway and prayed: And yet the Lord God shook His head. He said: “Lo, in thy city I see A wife and husband, full of love, Whose lives in loving harmony Are set all death and change above. I see: and leaning from my place, I bless them in their hidden grace. Whose love and peace and sweet accord Comfort Me greatly”: said the Lord. LOVE-LIES-BLEEDING TO GODFREY His small hands brought a flower for me, A flower of love and sorrow. Now angels over the gray sea Bid my sweetheart good-morrow. His face was sweeter than a rose,— But O Love's rose is thorny! He nestled in my breast so close Before he went his journey. O days when he and I lay there, O he and I together,— All in a trance of peace and prayer In the rich August weather. I gather from the self-same root My flower of Love lies bleeding. Ah, Love, one wound from head to foot, Past help and interceding! Love Comfortless The child is in the night and rain On whom no tenderest wind might blow, And out alone in a hurricane. Ah, no, The child is safe in Paradise! The snow is on his gentle head, His little feet are in the snow, O, very cold is his small bed! Ah, no, Lift up your heart, lift up your eyes! Over the fields and out of sight, Beside the lonely river's flow, Lieth the child this bitter night. Ah, no, The child sleeps under Mary's eyes! What wandering lamb cries sore distressed, Whilst I with fire and comfort go? O, let me warm him in my breast! Ah, no, 'Tis warm in God's lit nurseries! The Sheepfold The Shepherd of the sheepfold leant Upon his crook, and saw within The fold his milky ewes content, His white lambs innocent of sin. The milky mothers giving suck He saw, and merry lambs at play, Yet, leaning on his shepherd's crook, His eyes, his heart, were turned away. His tender thoughts were turned apart To where his orphaned lambs cried on; Their cries lay heavy on his heart— Poor milkless lambkins and undone. With tears he saw the milky dams Go dropping milk upon the grass; These were the mothers of dead lambs, The mothers of dead lambs, alas! O little lambs that would not live, Your milk runs all to bitter waste, Your milk that makes the Shepherd grieve, Runs out like tears so hot and fast. O comfort, comfort then those sheep, Whose little lovely lambs are dead. The milk that makes the Shepherd weep Runs out like tears, and none is fed. Holy Innocents Gold on gold, snow on snow, Height on height, row on row; Greater in number these Than the sands of the seas. Yea, past all counting far, Flower on flower, star on star, Dimpled shoulder, cheek of peach, As they lean each to each. Golden heads, brows of pearl, O many a boy and girl, O many a girl and boy, Mother's grief, mother's joy. But amid snow and gold, Gathered warm from the cold, Fairer than gold or snow, Should be two that I know. Love's Thanksgiving O how good God is that He sends Stores of unfailing love to me, And work and prayer and praise of friends, Blackbirds and thrushes in the tree, And sheep bells in the fields, and roses And all the sweets of May and June, And lavender and dew and posies, And sun and moon. O how good God is that He sends Bean-rows in blossom, bees i' the hive, Gray dawn and golden evening-ends, And a glad heart to be alive; A grateful mind and quiet fancies, Shade from the sun, and sleep at night, And clumps of brown and golden pansies, And lilies white. O how good God is that He sends A little child to be all ours, Mine and my dearest Love's, and tends Our blossom in the sun and showers, And bids His angels still keep near him Lest that the little feet should miss, And wings of angels still to bear him Ever in bliss. O how good God is that He keeps The child for ever and ever well, Above the tempests and the deeps, In joy no tongue can tell. Our little lamb of God goes straying, By daisied meadows, 'neath dappled skies; Our little lamb of God goes playing Under God's eyes. Love's Winter O if the shortest day were past, Or if it were the shortest day, 'Twere easier to take heart at last To face the outward way. O if above a darling head The snowdrops danced in the wind's play, Then joy might steal in sorrow's tread To meet the hope of May. But now the shortest day is gone, The year of sorrow gone for aye. Ho, traveller, turn and face the sun, For night gives place to day. Ho, traveller, take the outward track, Lift up your heart, give thanks, and pray. God knows some New Year brings you back What Old Year took away. Love's Rose My rose shall have no care at all, While the years rise and the years fall, Shall keep its gold heart folded close In the warm petals of my rose. Winds that deflower may rave at will Round the June rose to work her ill— Scatter her leaves of pearl and peach, O, but my rose is out of reach. In the shut bud the canker-worm Steals to defile her and deform. Near my one rose no ill shall creep, Seeing his plot kind angels keep. The wind that swings him low and high Softer is than a lullaby: The wind that swings him high and low Goes as his cradle used to go. Winter shall never find my Sweet, Nor shall he faint in summer heat, Filled full of dews and bathed in sun, Happy he is, my tender one. God is his gardener, so 'tis plain, God's rose shall never fret again, Never be sad, never be gray, Blooming a bud for ever and aye. Yea, my sweet rose God's eyes shall please; O, what a happy lot is his! Blessed the will that doth accord Me to grow roses for my Lord. Garden Secrets A garden in the Summer, Wherein the birds and I Built nests for some new-comer To swing against the sky. Garden of rose and lily, And dream of dew and scent, Where never a wind was chilly, And hearts were well content. The day smoked like a censer Till evening brought the shade, And leaves grew thicker, denser, And we were not afraid. Ah, birds, so blithe and cheerful, We guessed not how should come The Autumn gray and tearful, The Winter cold and dumb. Ah, building days and brooding! We guessed not how 'twould be With sad rains flooding, flooding, Our ruined nests in tree. The Child in Heaven The refrain of these verses, “The Child in Heaven,” belongs to a poem by the late W. B. Rands,—“Matthew Browne.” At the time I used it I was not aware of this; but the poem had been built up about it, and afterwards anything else seemed less right. The nursery windows were cold and black, The nursery hearth it was gray and sad; She moaned for the child that would never come back, Her heart was broken for her little lad. She had folded his garments and put them away, She had hidden his cradle quite out of sight: But the child was glad in the light of day, While she was caught in the bitter night. He thinks of his mother through all that cheer; He would never forget in a hundred year. The silence ached for the baby's cry. O silence, silence and loneliness! And the thought of the empty nursery Cried at her heart with a keen distress— Knocked at her heart like a ghost of the night, Followed her ever or near or far: But her little boy he is clad in white, In the land that is over the morning star. He thinks of his mother through all that cheer; He would never forget in a hundred year. His bed was soft as a nest of roses, His robes were all of the linen spun, He had taken nought but a handful of posies When he went out on his way alone— When he went out where she might not follow, And left her stricken and cold and bare, His radiant journey by hill and hollow, To the dear God's House in the glittering air. He thinks of his mother through all that cheer; He would never forget in a hundred year. She will come one day to God's nursery, Where His little babies are safe and warm, And lift the little one to her knee, And lose the ache of the empty arm, And lose the ache of the empty heart, And fashion newly Love's empty nest, And kiss his brows and his lips apart, And give him milk from her lonely breast. He thinks of his mother through all that cheer; He would never forget in a hundred year. Love in Heaven The child is rocked on Mary's knees, Her lullaby stills his alarms, Love's cradle gives him happy ease, Love's nest of love within her arms: “Lullaby,” she singeth, “Pretty babe of sorrow, Thy mother comes to stay with thee to-morrow.” One angel hold his basin, one His ewer of golden water sweet, And one his robe to put him on And one his pillow and his sheet. “O mystery,” they cry, “of love and sorrow, Sleep sweet, dear babe, thy mother comes to-morrow.” Immortal angels standing by, Kiss that sweet babe on Mary's knee. “Blessed the woman is,” they sigh, “Whose motherhood hath given her thee. Happy her lot in mortal joy and sorrow Who lost thee yesterday but finds to-morrow.”</field>
   </doc>
</add>