<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Dodd, William, 1729-1777</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Dodd, William, 1729-1777</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">dodd william 1729 1777</field>
      <field name="author_text">Dodd, William, 1729-1777</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1750's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_2.1269.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1750</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:465401</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Greek, Modern (1453- )</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">A New Book of the Dunciad ; Occasion'd By Mr. Warburton's New Edition of The Dunciad Complete. By a Gentleman of one of the Inns of Court. With several of Mr. Warburton's own Notes, and likewise Notes Variorum [by William Dodd</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">A New Book of the Dunciad ; Occasion'd By Mr. Warburton's New Edition of The Dunciad Complete. By a Gentleman of one of the Inns of Court. With several of Mr. Warburton's own Notes, and likewise Notes Variorum [by William Dodd</field>
      <field name="title_facet">new book of the dunciad</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">new book of the dunciad</field>
      <field name="title_text">A New Book of the Dunciad ; Occasion'd By Mr. Warburton's New Edition of The Dunciad Complete. By a Gentleman of one of the Inns of Court. With several of Mr. Warburton's own Notes, and likewise Notes Variorum [by William Dodd</field>
      <field name="year_display">1750</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1750</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1750</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465401&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465401&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Dodd, William, 1729-1777&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;dodd william 1729 1777&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;A New Book of the Dunciad ; Occasion'd By Mr. Warburton's New Edition of The Dunciad Complete. By a Gentleman of one of the Inns of Court. With several of Mr. Warburton's own Notes, and likewise Notes Variorum [by William Dodd&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;new book of the dunciad&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1750&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1750&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Dodd, William&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1729&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1777&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;A New Book of the Dunciad&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Occasion'd By Mr. Warburton's New Edition of The Dunciad Complete. By a Gentleman of one of the Inns of Court. With several of Mr. Warburton's own Notes, and likewise Notes Variorum [by William Dodd]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for J. Payne and J. Bocquet [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1750&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp1134&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;gre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;27 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;A New Book of the Dunciad&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Occasion'd By Mr. Warburton's New Edition of The Dunciad Complete. By a Gentleman of one of the Inns of Court. With several of Mr. Warburton's own Notes, and likewise Notes Variorum [by William Dodd]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 72 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">A Man that hath read without Judgment, is like a Gun charged with Goose-shot, let loose upon the Company.—He is only well furnished with Materials to expose himself, and mortify those he liveth with. Lord Halifax.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The DESIGN. To do honour to a person who hath done the greatest to the cause of Dulness, seemeth to be the sole design of the following Piece: The style of which is such as becometh such a work, (for of the style, courteous reader, we are necessitated to speak:) but of that made use of in the notes, we can say no more than that we doubt not, 'tis excellently well adapted to the several matters it handleth: it must needs be very various, as the things, it treateth of, are so, as well as the writers, or rather annotators, who have honour'd the poem with their remarks. It was once the design of the author to have dedicated this his favourite work to the Hero; but as he conceiveth the whole work is properly dedicated to him, in character of the Hero thereof, he therefore saved himself that trouble, nothing doubting, but he shou'd equally obtain the good-will, and high opinion of his worthy and well-sung patron. Martinus Scriblerus hath kindly promised to write the prolegomena, a thing absolutely necessary in works of this kind, soon as the author publisheth a second edition, and maketh his work complete, which he assureth thee, friendly reader, he shall do; particularly if favour'd with the kind remarks and observations of any choice spirits, or wits of the present times. And a great critic, little inferior to the thundering Ricardus Aristarchus, hath already pen'd a choice dissertation on the Hero, (together with an account of his life and writings) which is a most curious piece of literature, and deserveth the encomiums of all the sons of true criticism: but we cannot prevail with him to supply us with it at present; he too is determined to see what success the poet hath, before he honoureth his labours with so learned and elaborate a piece. I have taken upon me, where other critics had not sufficiently explained my author, to attempt that great work myself: how I may be qualified for the grand business of a critic, I presume not to know: however shou'd I prove deficient, Mr. Warburton's annotations will be of singular use, who is a critic profest; and a very excellent one, as a celebrated divine witnesseth: and as he hath unquestionably shewn himself by his happy edition of Shakespeare. I have much more to inform thee, and that of importance, kind reader, but must wait, 'till we are better acquainted; and I sincerely promise, in my next edition, to give thee full satisfaction with regard to any point, that shall raise the least doubt with thee. Till then think well of me: and from the mighty pains I have taken, and difficulties I have found, I wou'd have the “unlearn'd writer be deterr'd from wantonly trifling with an art, he is a stranger to, at the expence of his own reputation, and the integrity of the text of establish'd authors,”—as our hero (inauspiciously I wot) declareth in his Preface, and very fully proveth in his remarks on William Shakespeare. Thine, &amp;c. J. F. Scriblerus, jun.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ANTI-DESIGN. Scriblerus, jun. is a pedant! 'Tis plain, Luce clarius—he writeth this only to shew his erudition and reading. Who knoweth not Gilbert Cooper, Esq; first used the word Design? Who knoweth not in that Design, he speaketh of his Style very largely? Idle—in Scriblerus; why not give honour where due? Why not own from whence he borrow'd this word and method of writing? ? ???????? ????? ???????, Scriblerorum frontissime Furfur! R. Aristarchus.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">It hath been objected by some critics of profound learning and known abilities, that this is a misnomer, and that our poet stumbleth in the very threshold: since this, being of a nature different from the former, and celebrating another hero, is not properly another book of the Dunciad, but a new Dunciad rather: or I should conceive the poet should, in imitation of the greater poets, have given it a name from the hero, and have added the termination ad to his name, or something similar thereto, whereby he would have sufficiently distinguish'd this poem or Dunciad from any other.—It may be worth while to reflect on the vanity and short-sightedness of mortals, display'd in this hero of our poem, who writeth in his celebrated D?e L?n, amongst various other matters, of the epic poem, and saith, that species being already complete, we henceforth must expect no more, little deeming at that time, he was himself destin'd to be the hero of another heroic poem. J. F. Scriblerus, jun. Imitations. The learned reader is indebted to a celebrated divine for the many choice passages he will find hereafter, collected from ancient authors, which our poet plainly imitateth; but all Greek we have avoided with great and diligent caution, for our own and his sake.A NEW BOOK OF THE DUNCIAD. ARGUMENT. Our poet beginneth, as all writers of the greater heroic are wont, with a proposition, or the whole design in miniature, an invocation, and inscription. He then goeth on to describe the Goddess of Dulness asleep in her cave on a couch, or sopha, composed of the works of her sons, whereof one, more favoured than the rest, maketh her pillow. In this pleasing slumber, she is interrupted by a mixt, and violent noise of her subjects ushering into her cave a new king, namely, one W? W?; and determined to dethrone the old monarch, Cibber. Four booksellers support the monarch elect, and K?n presenteth to the Goddess, now awakened, the complete edition of the Dunciad, which the goddess, receiving with joy, taketh the hero in her arms, and, interrupted by tears of transport, maketh a pathetic speech to him, promising him King Cibber's throne, as more worthy thereof. This speech is received with so great applause, that it awakeneth Cibber from his sleep, who perceiving by instinct a superior genius present, runneth away, and resigneth up the throne. He scarce hath fled, ere four doughty champions come from the crowd to lead their master to the throne; which they, assisted by Dulness, achieve We spell the word as Milton doth. See Book the 2d, ver. 21 of his Paradise Lost, Dr Newton's Edition.. Here he is no sooner seated, than two reverend favourites appear with his crown; the crowd acknowledge the justness of their pretensions, and they put it on his head; after which the monarch stifleth the clamors, and maketh an elaborate harangue, promising to use his utmost endeavours in the support of his Queen's gracious authority; and concluding with a command that an altar of the most favourite pieces composed by his loving subjects, be raised and burnt; and also that a much-reverenced bard, well known there, ascend, and sing a coronation ode. Scarce hath he done speaking, before the bard ascendeth, and K? hasteth to the press with the speech, and the crowd gathereth busily round to raise the pile; the several works that compos'd which, our poet desirng his Muse to relate, in a very interesting point endeth his first book, raising with singular judgment the expectation of the learned reader. Of revolutions Of revolutions—plainly from Milton—Of man's first disobedience. B. I. I. 1. in that state I sing, Where long unenvied Cibber slept a king, Till, by dread W?r??r??n dethron'd, he run, Confess'd the victor, and resign'd his crown. Relate, of Goddess, IMITATION. Relate, O goddess.—Musa! mihi causas memora.—Virgil, B. I. See too most of the beginnings of all Epic Poems. whose inspiring aid Through Shakespear's mangled page thy hero led; Relate what work; each former work outdone, A poetical phrase to outdoe his best outdoings: this work appears line 68 to be the new edition of the Dunciad. See remark there. To such high honour rais'd thy darling son: Oh! whether gladsome prompting at his side Through Pope's unhappy page his pen you guide; Or whether, in concluding labours crost, Moses, with thee, in long digressions A thing our hero is eminent for; witnesses to which truth are those very long digressions to be found, in the work hinted at, of which only a part hath yet appeared; the main scope whereof is well nigh lost in the multitude of other matters, à re, there treated of. lost; Whether new scenes of criticism rise, Or future Julians A curious piece so called, lately published by W. Warburton, equal to his other works: so true is old Flaccus's remark, —Nec imbellem feroces Progenerant aquilæ columbam. Oh! condescend a while thy aid to bring, For thy own cause, and thy own son, I sing. And thou, O Edwards, The author of the Supplement to Mr Warburton's Shakespear, commonly called the Canons of Criticism: “Ill would that scholiast discharge his duty, who should neglect to honour those whom Dulness has distinguish'd; or suffer them to lie forgotten when their rare modesty would have left them nameless. Let us not therefore overlook the services which have been done her cause, by one Mr Thomas Edwards, a Gentleman, as he is pleased to call himself, of Lincoln's Inn; but in reality a gentleman only of the Dunciad: or to speak him better, in the language of our honest ancestors to such mushrooms, a gentleman of the last edition; who, nobly eluding the solicitude of his careful father, very early retained himself in the cause of Dulness against Shakespear, and hath now happily finished the Dunce's progress in personal abuse. For a Libeller is nothing but a Grubstreet critic run to feed.” Scriblerus, or Warburton, in his Dunciad Complete. B. 4. ver. 567. We need make no observations, or Hypercritica, on this curious annotation. envy not my lays A theme so great as thy inspirer's praise. What though unequal to thy pointed wit, To thee his venom'd vengeance must submit? What though he bids loud scandal strike the blow, And lay at once thy hated humour low? What though thy varied ridicule he flies, While at each dart his reputation dies? Yet in compassion hence the vanquish'd spare, Lay by the victor, and refuse the war; This, this his triumph, with thy smiles attend, And thy kind aid to sound his praises lend: Thou too, assume IMITATION. Plainly from the author of the first Dunciad, O thou whatever title please thine ear, Dean, Drapier, Bickerstaff, or Gulliver. The ancients addrest their deities in the same manner, as might be proved by a thousand instances, Sive tu Lucina probas vocari, Seu genitalis. Hor. Ode 2. whatever name you will, Or Abraham Johnson, Richard Roe, or ?; A well known author, who hath favoured the world with two witty and ingenious pieces, wherein he speaketh much to our hero's commendation: and, as the text observeth, treateth right prudently his subject in syllogistical order, according to the manner of the aforesaid heroe. Let him speak for himself! “I mention that gentleman's (Mr W?rb?n's) name, who now unquestionably stands foremost in the catalogue of British writers, with the most profound respect; and it wou'd afford me infinite pleasure, if he wou'd give this subject a discussion in the next Vol. of his Divine Legation, whenever he pleases to oblige the world with that long expected work: or if, by chance, he should happen to have no room for it, being already furnished with his complement of digressions, (see l. 11. foregoing) (and to be sure one book can hardly contain everything) still I have the vanity to expect a letter from him by the first post, to thank me, according to custom, for the honourable mention I have made of him, (see l. 171. and the annotation) and with some compliments on my performance, to make an overture of his acquaintance.”—See Lucina sine concubitu, edit. 1. p. 26, where he hinteth at Mr W?rb?n's skill in chopping logic.—And surely nothing can be imagined more pure and genuine than the applause this most judicious physician bestoweth on our hero! never was so happy a man, as to meet with encomiums from all the learned faculties, law, physic, and divinity! Scriblerus, junior. Thou in thy lov'd protector's cause arise, And croud his blazing virtues on our eyes; In syllogistic form, oh! let them shine, For his that form, most meet that form is thine! Long unmolested, peaceful Dulness Dulness is well conceived by our author to be of large bulk, and he expresseth himself well by calling her carcase a mighty load; supposing she hath much of the vis inertiæ (as the philosophers speak) in her, which absorbeth the divinam particulam auræ, as faith an excellent ancient poet. Scriblerus. See also the design to Mr Warburton's Dunciad. lay, And slept in dead serene her days away: Her gracious sons benign support bestow'd, Whole heaps of lumber held her mighty load; Heroics, It may be proper to defer the particularizing these several pieces, till the account of those which compose the altar, mentioned at the end of the book, is given by the poet himself: and we hear of several other learned persons who are composing heroic poems at this present time, which it will be my duty, as a faithful scholiast, if worthy thereof, hereafter to mention in these my observations explanatory. Scriblerus, sen. odes, adventures, tales, and plays, To form her couch, were twin'd a thousand ways: Her pillow the Divine Legation made, The matter contained in these lines is so well known, that it needeth little explanation: we being determined, in the course of our remarks, to avoid the errors of former commentators, who are copious on well-known matters, but very sparing in such as require their assistance. But one thing it may be proper to observe, that our poet speaketh not of volumes in the common acceptation, but as parts of a work; in which sense the passage is clear. Grand soporific, to compose her head: Two splendid tomes their swelling aid afford, And proudly kept a place to hold the third: Her brow in sleep a smile of joy confest, While close she hugg'd slash'd Shakespear The author of the former Dunciad, speaking of Tibbald's Shakespear, has it, There hapless Shakespear, yet of Tibbald sore. B. 1. L. 131. but our author calleth him slash'd Shakespear, and riseth as much above the expression of the former, as his hero's edition excelleth that of Tibbald; for if poor Shakespear be only just sore from the one, he is slash'd, cut and hack'd all to pieces by the other. J. F. Scriblerus, jun. to her breast; A work so brave made all her slumbers sweet, For there at length she view'd her power complete. Thus on soft sophas in her cave reclin'd, Slept the fam'd goddess of the leaden mind: IMITATION. A common mode of expression amongst poets.—So Thompson,—The goddess of the fearless eye. Liberty, Part 2. When thither tending, danc'd a jovial throng, From whom loud shouts in thund'ring vollies rung: “Down All this speech of the mob is natural enough; 'tis such language as at elections, or any things of that kind, is used by them: huzza, is a word expressing some mode or degree of joy. Warburton. with King Cibber, was the general cry, “Down with King Cibber, all Moorfields reply: “Huzza, huzza, King W?rb?n's our own, “Be he our King, be his King Colley's throne.” Thus in old times the Bacchanalian crew, In madding sort, o'er rocks and mountains flew, They wav'd their Thyrsus, while the rocks around, God save King Bacchus! Absurd: The poet never gave it so. Was not Bacchus a God? What—a God save a God? The blunder of some ignorant transcriber: The author gave it Oh brave King Bacchus! Oh brave is a term expressing great exultation among us; the same as Io pæan with the Greeks and Latins. Bentley. joyously rebound. Rous'd at the mighty din the Queen awoke, Thrice yawn'd, thrice rubb'd her eyes, then snatch'd a look, And through their rheums dull mist in doubt beheld, A chair by W?n's dread grandeur IMITATION. A latinism—So mitis sapientia Læli, for Lælius, besides a thousand more, we cou'd quote, and, if the reader suspecteth our learning, will hereafter; though every school-boy knoweth them. fill'd: Four brawny booksellers sustain'd the freight, And puff'd, and sweat beneath such learning's weight: The dull procession K? pac'd before, And in his arms the work completed Mr Warburton calleth his the Dunciad complete, and so in truth he hath made it. bore: Which, graceful as before the Queen he bends, Rapt'rous she seizes, and with glee descends, Th' alighted hero in her arms she took, Thrice clasp'd her darling, and wou'd thrice have spoke: But thrice IMITATION.Thrice he assay'd, and thrice, in spite of scorn, Tears, such as angels weep, burst forth: at last Words, interwove with sighs, found out their way. Milton. big tears of transport forc'd their way, At length or thus she said, or seem'd to say: 'Twill be worth the reader's while carefully to examine this speech of the Goddess, which, by men of sound erudition, hath been adjudg'd an original of its kind, not only for the sound moral, and just politics it contains, but also for the fine and elegant encomium it bestows on the hero, and that amazingly judicious turn in it, where she triumphs over her great adversary the author of Dunciad the first; and where at length, willing to wrest all things (as all mankind are wont) to her own advantage, she seems to see his design in chusing William Warburton for his commentator, namely, to make her amends for all the disservice he had done her, by giving her all his works with the commentary of that chosen critic.“Oh! born thy mother's glories to maintain, “Last, best, support and honour of my reign; “How shall my fondness all my love express, “Or pay due thanks for thy well-earn'd success? “How paint the blessings by thy labours won? “And all thy zeal exerted for my throne? “Thy glorious triumph with what language hit, “O'er sense, o'er learning, modesty and wit? “Yes, yes, my foe, in triumph I survey “Myself sole umpress of thy every lay: “I joy to pardon what thy envy pen'd, “Nay more than pardon, I can now commend. “Be spit thy venom on my meaner race, “Since in thy sight this chosen son found grace: “And, matchless Commentator, nobly brings, “To me each critick'd piece his poet sings! “Deluded Dulness—Gods! I did not see “Thy kind intention in that choice to me: “Blest foe! nor can my soul enough admire “Thy kind ambition, and thy fond desire “To put He (Mr Pope) was desirous I should give a new edition of this poet, as he tho't that it might contribute to put a stop to a prevailing folly of altering the text of celebrated authors without talents or judgment. And he was willing that his edition should be melted down into mine, as it would, he said, afford him (so great is the modesty of an ingenuous temper) a fit opportunity of confessing his mistakes. In memory of our friendship, I have, therefore, made it our joint edition. Warburton's preface to Shakespear, p. 19. thy friend on such a grand design, “As melting down thy Shakespear into mine. “Oh my best hopes!”—(she adding, closely press'd, 'Midst tears of joy, the hero to her breast) “Oh still go on with matchless Folly fraught, “And nobly puzzle with thy deep no-thought: “Still strenuous employ thy critick skill, “Amend, abuse, and utter what you will; “Wide o'er the world thy own renown extend, “My empire widen, and my rights defend: “And lo,—for thee what honours I design, “That throne where Colley sleeps be henceforth thine!” She spoke, and as at rustic wake or fair, Where crowds on crowds surround a growling bear, If chance Sir Bruin's paws some hero We think it should be spelt hero, without the e. We would have the learned reader observe through our work, once for all, how careful we have been to preserve the proper and original spelling. Somebody. seize, The culprit bellows at the brute's rough squeeze; And as it hugs and mumbles o'er its prize, Mixt shouts of thousands echo through the skies, Applauses ring, and hats ascend in air, All praise the culprit, and all praise the bear: So when IMITATION.—Cunctique fremebant— Cælicolæ assensu vario. —Virg. Poets generally use similies on these occasions. See Milt. B. 2. 1. 284. the Goddess of her speech made end, Eternal peals of loud applause ascend, While tears flow copious down each friendly face, The queen and hero clasp'd in close embrace; While every tongue the grateful praise bestow'd, And W??r??r?n rebellow'd through the crowd. “Hail, hail, Saturnian days of lead restor'd, “Great Dunce the second The disingenuity of poets is amazing: one may perceive how they borrow almost all their works from others, as I have already made clear in my Milton's imitation of the moderns; (which see) “a poet I have now reduced to his true standard, who appears mortal and uninspired, and in ability little superior to the poets above-mentioned, (viz. Cowley, Waller, Denham, Dryden, Prior, Pope;) but in honesty and open dealing, the best quality of the human mind, not inferior perhaps to the most unlicensed plagiary that ever wrote. (p. 160 of my work). I say, 'tis plain how all of them borrow their works from others, (see p. 160 of my work) and yet confess not, or give the least intimation of their having translated or imitated from any author whatever.” In this author I could trace out innumerable passages, which I find a great Divine hath done to my hands; however, these two lines, unobserved by him, supply us with a flagrant instance of it: Hail—is met with in Milton—Hail holy light, and in the Latin, salve or hail, (and I am told in the Greek). Saturnian days, &amp;c. is from Virgil's Pollio—redeunt Saturnia regna—of lead, is from the former Dunciad, as well as almost the whole subsequent line, Great Dunce the second yields to Dunce the third. The first Dunciad.— Still Dunce the second reigns like Dunce the first! “This industrious concealment of his helps is highly ungenerous in our poet, nay, criminal to the last degree, and absolutely unworthy of any man of common probity and honour,”—therefore he will not be angry at my condemning it, since Sua quisque exempla debet æquo animo pati. Pages 163 and 164 of my work. W. Lauder. P. T. C. See a letter concerning this my work in the Gentleman's Magazine for April 1750. p. 155. yields to Dunce the third: “Rejoice great Queen, for now thy foes are flown, “Thy own Dunce reigns: the age is all thy own.” IMITATION.Tuus jam regnat Apollo. Virg. So loud IMITATION.He call'd so loud, that all the hollow deep Of hell resounded. —Milton. they bellow'd their triumphal song, That all the hollow cave resounding rung; And Cibber rous'd, scarce look'd, ere from the throne Half stumbling, sleeping, yawning, he posts down. A greater genius Our poet hath here taken a thought from Shakespear,—where he tells us Anthony's genius was ever rebuk'd by Cæsar's.—See Macbeth, and also Anthony and Cleopatra (in my edition). Now a person who understands Shakespear, as I do, will immediately see, this is the very thing he hints at, when he makes Cibber's genius know mine by instinct, and be so far rebuk'd by its superior excellence, as to run away! Warburton. he by instinct knew, And skulking, trembling, from the rabble flew: Glad, without blood-shed, to resign a throne, Gain'd by his subjects choice, and not his own. Scarce had he fled, ere, bustling from the crowd, Four dauntless forms beside their Hero stood; Whose kindly aid in every cause he tried, Each his support, his patron, and his guide; And now to lead him to the throne they came, His worth's best meed, the summit of his fame. The first was Impudence, with dauntless eye, For a more full account, and lively description, nay, the very original portraits, of these champions, see all our hero's works, courteous reader, if thou can'st throw away so much of thy precious time. Scriblerus. With face of brass, and stare, that look'd a lye: The second Pedantry, whose words profest All skill, all science, and yet none possest: The third Scurrility, whose envious tongue With loud abuse, and scandal ever rung: The fourth proud Vanity, puff'd up with air, With glass reflecting each self-virtue clear; But others worth, or turning to grimace, Or strange effect—admitting there no place. By these conducted, and by Dulness led, Slow to the throne behold the monarch tread; An awful gloom, with philosophic grace, For a complete commentary on these verses, see a Metzotinto print of Mr W?r?t?n, in a very curious and philosophic attitude: For we judge no method so proper to explain the poets, as applying to their sister art; A method beautifully commended, and elegantly pursued by two very great enemies of Dulness—very dreaded names in these parts, Addison and Spence. Spreads its dull horrors o'er his frontless face: And looking scorn on all the herd below, With full complacence in his sneer-clad We judge these compound epithets of great and singular excellence: several of them may be found in the life of Socrates, and in the poem of a certain gentleman, on the peace. brow, Conscious this due reward his worth has won, Behold, behold him seize the promis'd throne! His faithful friends beside him smiling stand, Delighted Dulness holds his dear right hand: Her looks expressive speak her ravish'd soul, Where future triumphs in long order roll. And see! e'en now those triumphs are begun; Two reverend favourites bow before his throne: By their right hands a crown supported view, Enwove with poppy, nightshade, and with yew: Yet on his head or ere that crown they place, Behold their titles to so high a grace. Refulgent M? As we propose to give future critics an idea what we would have all critics be, so we shall here too lay down another rule, very proper to be pursued in explaining difficult matters: namely, that of consulting contemporary authors, when the author's own context will not direct us, and seeing if from them we can throw any light on the passage in question; which we hope in the present passage we have done, as also in the next, very obscure in themselves, and of which we would not predicate any thing; only therefore will we give from two authors a short quotation or two, and if, reader, thou thence can'st draw any conclusion—it will be well for thee. “Upon looking into the history of the works of the learned, to my regret, I found that his remarks (Mr Warburton's on Milton) were continued no farther than the three first books; and what is become of his other papers, and how they were mislaid and lost, neither he nor I can apprehend! but the excellence of those which remain, sufficiently evinces the great loss we have sustained in the others, which cannot now be recovered! He has done me the honour too of recommending this edition to the public, in the preface to his Shakespear; but nothing could have recommended it more effectually, than if it had been adorned by some more of his notes and observations.” Again—“Mr Warburton has favoured me with a few other notes in manuscript: I wish there had been more of them, for the sake of the reader: for the loose hints of such writers, like the slight sketches of great masters in painting, are worth more than the labour'd pieces of others.”—Hear, friendly reader, what the same author thinketh of his Shakespear.—“And as, according to the old proverb, the best guesser was the best diviner, so he may be said, in some measure too, to be the best editor of Shakespear, as Mr Warburton hath proved himself by variety of conjectures, and many of them very happy ones, upon the most difficult passages.”—See Dr Newton's preface to his Milton. Thus, 'tis hoped, some light is thrown on these four lines; our next remark proceedeth in the same way, and desireth the proemium hereto affixed, be conceived at it. J. F. Scriblerus, jun. pleas'd the first display'd, Yet as he look'd, he sigh'd, and shook his head: “Whither, quoth he, ah! whither are they gone? “Weep, world! with me the mighty loss bemoan.” Prick'd with “It appeared then to the writer of these sheets, that it might be of use, if in the opportunities of his leisure he employed some pains in clearing the sense, connecting the method, and ascertaining the scope and purpose of this admired epistle.”—Again—“I chuse therefore to rest on the single authority of a great author, who hath not disdain'd to comment a like piece of a late critical poet. What was indeed the amusement of his pen, becomes, it must be owned, the labour of inferior writers. Yet on these unequal terms it can be no discredit to have aim'd at some resemblance of one of the least of those merits, which shed their united honours on the name of the illustrious friend and commentator of Mr Pope.”—See first and last pages of the introduction to a commentary on Horace's Art of Poetry, by an anonymous writer, who hath been unjustly suspected, from the intrusion of one unlucky metaphysical note, to be a very judicious person, who is, we are assured, much superior to such a work. Had it not been too large, we wou'd have quoted the whole introduction, as it well deserveth a place here: the reader will see we desire him to read it all, by quoting only from the begining and from the end. J. F. Scriblerus, jun. The hypercritica to both these notes unluckily came too late, but they shall be inserted in a future edition.—See Abraham Johnson's Lucina sine concubitu, p. 35, where he hinteth at this writer. delight the second shew'd away, The true design of Arts poetica: “Compos'd by Flaccus, commented by Me, “And there, great friend of Pope, I follow thee.” All with one voice their just pretensions found; They bow'd obsequious, and the monarch crown'd; They bow'd and cried: “Your prince, blest subjects, ken! IMITATIONS. An old word, signifying to behold, view, or see: the next line is from Shakespear.— He was a man, take him for all in all You will not light upon his like again. “Where will ye light upon his like again?” As when a fen-man, from long piece, lets fly 'Midst various mingled lodgers of the sky; 'Midst ravens, crows, A raven and a crow is the same bird of prey: the first name taken from its nature, the other from its voice: we should therefore read, 'Midst ravenous crows and kites. Warburton in his Shakespear, V. 7. p. 84. kites, herons, daws, and pies, All on the wing discordant mingle cries, [Hoarse Though we cannot but commend the author's choice of words here, each being adapted to the language, the several species of birds, he characteriseth, severally speaketh;—yet it is an improper simile for an epic poem—at least these two lines should be thrown out, and therefore we have inclosed them in uncæ or hooks. F. H. croaking, screaking, squawling, cawing, chattering, The brazen welkin is Shakespear's and Milton's: “and we have been the more willing to explain and illustrate our author by similar expressions and sentiments in Shakespear, not only because Milton was a great reader and admirer of his works, but also because we conceive Shakespear and Milton to be two of the most extraordinary genius's, and greatest poets, whom any country or any time has produc'd.” Newton's Milton. with their tumults battering:] So dissonant to view their monarch crown'd, And hear his praise, the subjects joys rebound: 'Twas discord all: but when in act to speak, His head majestic they beheld him shake, In universal silence IMITATIONS. So Milton, when Beelzebub is about to speak, faith, ?His look Drew audience and attention still as night Or summer's noon-tide air.— B. 2. L. 307. round they stood, Not e'en a whisper murmur'd through the crowd: Their King with wide-mouth'd wonder they survey, As stare The hint of this simile is plainly taken from Shakespear: he says, Then nightly sings the staring owl.— Our poet maketh the owls cease, to hear the musick of the ass! These creatures, 'tis well known, are the prime ministers in the state of Dulness.—The author of the first Dunciad informs us, Dulness herself was the dry-nurse of her own owls. Here she nurst her owls— And in various places speaketh much to the laud of these honourable creatures, owls and asses. Scriblerus, jun. the owls, while midnight asses bray: But much 'Tis worth while to observe how judiciously our poet soundeth the praise of his hero; for, in this place, he raiseth him to such a pitch of glory, as even to make him of a species superior to mankind, of a nature elevated beyond human; and yet he doth it so artfully, that our stomachs nothing nauseate the flattery! I remember I once was told our hero, (who is a divine) refused to preach at any time before any common congregation, yea even Mr A?'s at B?, because he could not express himself so as to be understood by the vulgar, the ?? ??????! How like is he to all the great divines since our Saviour's time!— Scriblerus, sen. he hem'd, and hesitated long, Ere he found words to suit the vulgar throng: For, 'midst those thousand blessings he enjoy'd, This, as in sport, his Goddess had deny'd: A gift of language level to mankind, Dark but to Genii, like himself refin'd. At length, while Silence IMITATION. This is prettily imagined: silence sitteth mourning the delay of his speech, and at length is eased—The poet had in his eye Shakespear's passage, Like Patience on a monument Smiling at grief. mourn'd his speech prorogued, Easing her grief, his mind he disembogued. To readers unacquainted with our hero's writings, the following speech will appear somewhat harsh: and therefore for their sakes it is, he hath consented his own annotations on such words or passages as have aught difficult, be added. The speech might be properly divided into three parts: his menace, contained in the first eight lines; his intention, contained in the next twelve; and his command, to the end: in all of which the judicious reader will find little or nothing to the purpose, as it seems the poet—or speaker intended: giving hereby the judicious reader a good notion of the rest of our hero's works, which are all similar hereto! Scriblerus. Long has a race of heroes fill'd the stage. Prologue to Phædra and Hippolitus.“Long has a deedless hero fill'd the throne, “Renown'd for non-activity alone: “But be not overcome, i. e. Deceived. Warburton. as if my Queen, “Like that base Merop's son, i. e. A bastard, base-born. Warburton. I meant to stain: “Fief Fief'd is a word I have introduc'd to Shakespear's acquaintance. See Macbeth Act. I. Sc. 6.— Warburton. to her throne, that throne ill heried i. e. Praised, celebrated; the word is obsolete. Warburton. rule, “And bravely fear-spearse The author has not done me justice here,—my manner of reading a passage in Shakespear is, Th' fear spersing fife. Othello. But this of our poet is much softer than I could wish. Warburton. each inferior fool: “More than ten thousand Maurice-pikes i. e. Pikemen of prince Maurice's army. Warburton. See my Shakespear. o'ercome; “And put down blockheads, as they put down mum. i. e. The fattening liquor so called. So I explain it in my Shakespear, V. I. p. 272. Warburton. “And Queen, since mich i. e. Much. Warburton. Shakespear, V. 7. p. 378. I so thy pow'r shall spread, “Myself will write, till all thy foes are fled: “Those fools who boast of learning, wit and sense, “I'll yield to yon stout champion Impudence: “And those “Indeed there was little or nothing in the work confuted (Dr Rutherforth's Essay on Virtue) but sophistical wrangling and disingenuous tergiversation, embarrass'd by an understanding more than ordinarily condensed with the frigid subtilty of school-moonshine.” See Remarks upon the principles and reasonings of Dr Rutherforth's Essay on the nature and obligation of virtue: publish'd by Mr Warburton, with a Preface. From this curious preface we have taken the above, from whence the reader may judge of the rest, which we assure him is all of a piece. The work itself hath been said to be wrote by an old woman; we believe the writer of the preface is the writer of the whole, or he had not so strongly defended it, and abused Dr Rutherforth; whom we would take upon us to clear from his aspersions, was not that writer's great good-nature, and judgment, solid sense, and extensive learning, so well, so universally known and esteemed, that any applause of this kind would be as unable to assist, as any dispraise of Mr Warburton's to blemish his high character. J. F. Scriblerus, jun. condens'd in moonshine of the schools, “Tergiversating hebetated fools, “Scurrility shall seize; these, these shall fight, “And, when not books, I prefaces will write. i. e. I will exert my utmost endeavours to prejudice all mankind against any thing of taste or learning, that would be likely to do harm to our empire,—by writing prefaces, unask'd, (as I am known to have done, to that hurtful work (to us I mean) call'd Clarissa) and perverting the author's meaning all I possibly can. Warburton. “Myself will trempe This is a word I have restored to Shakespear, where, when the vulgar reading is damp,—I amend that nonsense, and read trempe, i. e. moisten. Warburton. V. 4. p. 97. Jargon and nonsense are words of all others most pleasing to me; for them see almost every page of my Shakespear. the paper the year round, “Jargon confute, and non-sense flat confound; “Hold i. e. My writings shall be as long and unending as that tale from whence the plot of Measure for Measure is taken, which Cynthio begun to write on Dec. 8, and continued writing the whole year round till Nov. 5. So my friend Mr Pope means by his abbreviations of Dec. 8. Nov. 5. Warburton. from December to November breath, “Till all, my Dulness, own, I'th' This is a manner of expression I have introduced to Shakespear's acquaintance, as a trial of skill for future players; and whoever can speak it, I promise them, for reward, to make honourable mention of them, in some of my future commentaries on the remaining part of Mr Pope's works. In Shakespear the text was 'Tis present death. In mine I read it, and I assure you right, I'th' presence 't's death. Vol. 4. p. 489. Warburton. presence 't's death. 'Twere not unpleasing to observe how very plain the hero speaks on a matter where his honour is concerned.—There's not one uncommon word, 'tis observable, to be found there,—except that phrase the hero's self in the next remark taketh notice of, and which is undoubtedly foisted in by some ignorant transcriber.“But hold, 'twere best, or ere Shakespear has an absurd expression of the same sort: I'll speak a prophecy or e're I go. “Or e're I go, is not English, and should be helped thus: I'll speak a prophecy or two ere I go.” And in our poet it should be helped too thus: 'Twere best, before I speak my will. Warburton. I speak my will, “This day's solemnity we straight fulfill: “Quick then, my Queen, thy votaries command, “(Thine and my loyal subjects through the land,) “Of all those works, in our lov'd cause they've pen'd, “They see an altar 'fore i. e. before. We assure you, these abbreviations of words, as 'gin, for begin; 'gainst, for against, and the like are very usual with the best poets,—and are besides very great beauties,—I have shewn this in many of my annotations on Shakespear. Warburton. our throne ascend, “That grateful to thy Goddessship may blaze, “And with its fragrant smoke our nostrils please. “And thou, O bard, There is no conjecturing who this bard may be, there being such a number of words rhyming to spoke: therefore we will not take upon us to determine ought concerning this intricate point from hence. Other marks are given; 'tis not impossible we may smell him out from these: the word Muggletonian, we find, is borrowed from us, in our annotations on the former Dunciad: See B. 2. v. 138; but we presume not to gather ought from hence; however it appears, this bard is an ode-wright; and, from the following account of his subjects, it appeareth to be that anonymous poet, who hath favour'd us with two curious odes already, on Beauty, and Martial virtue.—Pindarics. See 1. 245. Scriblerus, sen. (he beckon'd as he spoke) “Firm friend of Dulness, Muggletonian ?; “O darling of my soul! whose earth-born IMITATION. Is a word of Milton's, Titanian, or earth born;—'tis worth while to observe how judiciously the poet stileth these lays, earth-born, as sprung from the meanest and lowest seat,—and not like Homer's and Milton's descended from Heaven! lays, “Nor tort An old French word, signifying the being in the wrong, is much in use amongst our old English writers, which those who have not read them may collect from its being found in the etymologicon of the judicious Skinner. Warburton, V. 7. p. 267. I been, well suit, thy monarch's praise; “Haste, narrify i. e. Make my encomium. Warburton's Shakespear, V. 6. p. 541. my worth, my laud relate, “An ode of thine deserves a theme so great: “Grateful digression See a pleasing instance of what the hero desireth in the four first stanzas of the Ode on martial virtue: It consisteth of 8 stanzas. in thy songs admit, “Fine i. e. censure. So I would understand it in a nonsensical passage of Shakespeare. Warburton. the no-vowell'd i. e. without sense: as a word without vowels is jargon, and contains no idea. See my Shakespeare, vol. 7. p. 398. Warburton. frippery of wit, “And by thy great example let men see, “The very things I'd have my subjects be.” Scarce had he spoke, the Goddess scarce commends, Ere ravish'd with his praise the bard ascends: While No wonder the bookseller is in such haste to get the speech printed, when Dulness has so many thousand subjects ready to receive it,—for, tho' a famous bookseller told me two years ago; “Oh Sir—“any thing of Mr W?n's will sell!” The tables are turn'd now, and his luck strangely alter'd! K?n, wond'ring who each word devour'd, Strait with the speech precipitately scour'd To ply the press: delighted Dulness sends A thousand imps to aid—and bless their absent friends: From this and the following line, it is plain the elder Scriblerus is much mistaken in his conjecture concerning the bard here notified: For it cannot be the author of the Odes on Beauty, and Martial Virtue, since that learned Gentleman biddeth not Taste to fly, but saith it is his sole endeavour to inform us what true Taste is:—And for that reason, he proposeth himself to give both the precept and example at once, in a series of odes, before which he constantly intendeth to fix certain useful dissertations. See those before the Odes on Beauty, and Martial Virtue.With conscious pride the master sweeps the strings, Bids Taste fly blushing, and of Beauty sings; Of Martial Virtue, and of War's dread God, In loftier numbers swells the daring Ode: To Dulness, Bards at his command submit, The Test at once and arbiter of wit. While thro' the cave his strains triumphant sound, Behold what crowds of authors gather round; Thick as autumnal leaves IMITATION. Thick as autumnal leaves. So Milton. Thick as autumnal leaves— and Virgil. &amp;c. B. I. v. 302. Quam multa in sylvis autumni frigore primo Lapsa cadunt foliis— Thick as the leaves in autumn strew the woods. Dryden. they press along, Wights dull in prose, and Wights more dull in song: Each emulous his favourite brat to see, Oh Dulness! blazing to thy Prince and thee! —Relate Nothing can equal the proper manner in which the poet closes his first book; when our expectations are rais'd to the height.—So he leaves us, and we are anxious to know what heroes are to shine in his future strains! A copious theme; and every day, every hour supplieth new matter; so that, courteous reader, I much fear, if our author deferreth his account much longer, the labour will be too great; and the catalogue so tedious, not even Homer's dread one will equal it.—Yet he telleth me, he hath heart to undertake it, if properly encouraged, and as he doubteth not of many friendly and unfriendly remarks, encomiums, and the contrary on his poem, so he feareth not to find proper matter to compleat the design he hath engag'd in, to the utter ruin of all Taste, and the serene establishment of the throne of Mr. W? and his beloved queen Dulness. Scriblerus, sen., my Muse, their labours, feats and names, Who gave their works to those immortal flames. Say what fam'd Chieftain the foundation lay'd? Who, on the altar last his works display'd? Say, to that grace what treatises inspir'd, And which the pile, that grace obtaining, fir'd? FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>