<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Carew, Thomas, 1595-1639</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Carew, Thomas, 1595-1639</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">carew thomas 1595 1639</field>
      <field name="author_text">Carew, Thomas, 1595-1639</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.1874.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1651</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464345</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Poems, with a maske</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">Poems, with a maske</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poems with a maske</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poems with a maske</field>
      <field name="title_text">Poems, with a maske</field>
      <field name="year_display">1651</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1651</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1651</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464345&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464345&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Carew, Thomas, 1595?-1639?&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;carew thomas 1595 1639 &lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Poems, with a maske&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poems, with a maske&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1651&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1651&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Carew, Thomas&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1595&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1639&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poems, with a maske&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for H. M. and are to be sold by J. Mantin [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1651&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0660&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;221 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poems, with a maske&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 20 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Majority of verse reproduced elsewhere in The English Poetry Full-text Database; only unique items included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To my Lord Admirall, on his late sickness, and recovery. VVith joy like ours, the Thracian youth invade Orpheus, returning from th'Elysian shade, Embrace the Heroe, and his stay implore, Make it their publike sute he would no more Desert them so, and for his Spouses sake, His vanisht love, tempt the Lethæan Lake; The Ladies too, the brightest of that time, Ambitious all his lofty bed to climbe, Their doubtfull hopes with expectation feed, Which shall the fair Euridice succeed; Euridice, for whom his numerous moan Makes listning Trees, and savage Mountaines groan, Through all the Ayr his sounding strings dilate Sorrow like that, which touch'd our hearts of late, Your pining sickness, and your restless pain, At once the Land affecting, and the Mayn, When the glad newes that you were Admirall, Scarce through the Nation spread, 'twas fear'd by all That our great CHARLES, whose wisdom shines in you, Should be perplexed how to chuse a new: So more than private was the joy and grief, That at the worst it gave our soules relief, That in our Age such sense of vertue liv'd, They joy'd so justly, and so justly griev'd. Nature, her fairest light ecclipsed, seemes Her self to suffer in these sad extremes, While not from thine alone thy blood retires, But from those cheeks which all the world admires. The stem thus threatned, and the sap, in thee Droop all the branches of that noble Tree, Their beauties they, and we our love suspend, Nought can our wishes, save thy health intend; As Lillies over-charg'd with rain they bend Their beauteous heads, and with high heaven contend, Fold thee within their snowy arires, and cry, He is too faultless, and too young to die: So like Immortals, round about thee They Sit, that they fright approaching death away. Who would not languish, by so fair a train To be lamented, and restor'd again? Or thus with-held, what hasty soul would go. Though to the Blest? O'r young Adonis so Faire Venus mourn'd, and with the precious showr Of her warm teares cherisht the springing flower. The next support, fair hope, of your great name, And second Pillar of that noble frame, By loss of thee would no aduantage have, But step by step pursues thee to thy grave. And now relentless Fate about to end The line, which backward doth so farr extend, That Antique stock, which still the world supplies With bravest spirits, and with brightest eyes, Kind Phæbus interposing bade me stay, Such stormes no more shall shake that house, but say, Like Neptune, and his Sea-born Neece shall be The shining glories of the Land and Sea, With courage guard, and beauty warm our Age, And Lovers fill with like Poetique rage. On Mistris N. to the green sickness. Stay coward blood, and doe not yield To thy pale sister, beauties field, Who there displaying round her white Ensignes, hath usurp'd thy night; Invading thy peculiar throne, The lip, where thou shouldst rule alone; And on the cheek, where natures care, Allotted each an equall share, Her spreading Lilly only growes, Whose milky deluge drowns thy Rose. Quit not the field faint blood, nor rush In the short salley of a blush Vpon thy sister foe, but strive To keep an endless warre alive; Though peace doe petty States maintain, Here warre alone makes beauty raign. Vpon a Mole in Celia's bosome. That lovely spot which thou dost see In Celia's bosome was a Bee, Who built her amorous spicy nest I'th' Hyblas of her either breast, But from close Ivory Hyves, she flew To suck the Aromatick dew Which from the neighbour vale distils, Which parts those two twin-sister hils, There feasting on Ambrosiall meat, A rowling sile of Balmy sweat, (As in soft murmurs before death, Swan-like she sung) chokt up her breath. So she in water did expire, More precious than the Phænix fire; Yet still her shaddow there remains Confind to those Elizian plains; With this strict Law, that who shall lay His bold lips on that milky way, The sweet, and smart, from thence shall bring Of the Bees Honey, and her sting. An Hymeneall Song on the Nuptials of the Lady Ann Wentworth, and the Lord Lovelace. Break not the slumbers of the Bride, But let the Sun in Triumph ride, Scattering his beamy light, When she awakes, he shall resigne His rayes: And she alone shall shine in glory all the night. For she till day return must keep An Amorous Vigill, and not steep Her fayr eyes in the dew of sleep. Yet gently whisper as she lies, And say her Lord waits her uprise, The Priests at the Altar stay. With Flowry wreathes the Virgin crew Attend while some with roses strew, And Mirtles trim the way. Now to the Temple, and the Priest, See her convaid, thence to the Feast; Then back to bed, though not to rest. For now to crown his faith and truth, Wee must admit the noble youth To revell in Loves sphere. To rule as chiefe Intelligence That Orb, and happy time dispence To wretched Lovers here. For there exalted farre above, All hope, fear, change, or they to move The wheel that spins the fates of Love. They know no night, nor glaring noon Measure no houres of Sunn or Moon, Nor mark time's restless Glass. Their kisses measure as they flow, Minutes, and there embraces show The hower's as they pass. Their Motions, the yeares circle make, And we from their conjunctions take, Rules to make Love an Almanack. A married Woman VVhen I shall marry, if I doe not find A wife thus moulded; I'l create this mind: Nor from her noble birth, nor ample dower, Beauty, or wit, shall she derive a power To prejudice my Right, but if she be A subject born, she shall be so to me: As to the soul the flesh, as Appetite To reason is, which shall our wils unite In habits so confirm'd, as no rough sway Shall once appear, if she but learn t'obey. For in habituall vertues, sense is wrought To that calm temper, as the bodie's thought To have nor blood, nor gall, if wild and rude Passions of Lust, and Anger, are subdu'd; When 'tis the fair obedience to the soul, Doth in the birth those swelling Acts controul. If I in murder steep my furious rage, Or with Adult'ry my hot lust asswage, Will it suffice to say my sense, the Beast Provokt me to't? could I my soul devest, My plea were good, Lyons, and Buls commit Both freely, but man must in judgement sit, And tame this Beast, for Adam was not free, When in excuse he said, Eve gave it me: Had he not eaten, she perhaps had been Vnpunisht, his consent made hers a sinne. A divine Love. 1 Why should dul Art, which is wise Natures Ape, If she produce a shape So farre beyond all parternes, that of old Fell from her mold As thine (admir'd Lucinda) not bring forth An equall wonder, to express that worth In some new way, that hath Like her great work, no print of vulgar path? 2 Is it because the rapes of Poetry, Rifeling the spacious sky Of all his fires, light, beauty, influence, Did those dispence On ayrie creations that surpast The reall workes of Nature, she at last To prove their raptures vain, Shew'd such a light as Poets could not feign? 3 Or is it 'cause the factious wits did vie With vain Idolatry, Whose Goddess was supreme, and so had hurld Schism through the world, Whose Priest sung sweetest layes; thou didst appear A glorious mysterie, so dark, so clear, As Nature did intend All should confess, but none might comprehend? 4 Perhaps all other beauties share a light Proportion'd to the fight Of weak mortality, scatt'ring such loose fires, As stir desires, And from the brain distill salt amorous rhumes, Whilst thy immortall flame such dross consumes, And from the earthy mold With purging fires severs the purer gold. 5 If so, then why in Fames immortall scrowl, Doe we their names inroul, Whose easie hearts, and wanton eyes did sweat With sensuall heat? If Petrark's unarm'd bosome catch a wound From a light glance, must Laura be renown'd? Or both a glory gain, He from ill-govern'd Love, she from Disdain? 6 Shall he more fam'd in his great Art become, For wilfull martyrdome? Shall she more title gain to chast and fair Through his dispair? Is Troy more noble 'cause to ashes turn'd? Than Virgin Cities that yet never burn'd? Is fire when it consumes Temples, more fire, than when it melts perfumes? 7 Cause Venus from the Ocean took her form Must Love needs be a storm? Cause she her wanton shrines in Islands reares, Through seas of tears, O'r Rocks, and Gulphs, with our own sighs for gales, Must we to Cyprus, or to Paphos sayl? Can there no way be given, But a true Hell that leads to her false Heaven. Loves Force. In the first rude t'Age, when Love was wild, Not yet by Lawes reclam'd, nor reconcil'd To order, nor by Reason maun'd, but flow Full-summ'd by Nature, on the instant view Vpon the wings of Appetite, at all The eye could fair, or sense delightfull call: Election was not yet, but as their cheap Food from the Oak, or the next Acorn-heap, As water from the nearest spring or brook, So men their undistinguisht females took By chance, not choyce; but soon the heavenly spark That in mans bosome lurkt, broke through this dark Confusion, then the noblest breast first felt Itself, for its own proper object melt. A Fancy. Mark how this polisht Eastern sheet Doth with our Northern tincture meet, For though the paper seem to sink, Yet it receives, and bears the Ink; And on her smooth soft brow these spots Seem rather ornaments than blots; Like those you Ladies use to place Mysteriously about your face; Not only to set off and break Shaddowes and Eye beams, but to speak To the skild Lover, and relate Vnheard, his sad or happy Fate: Nor doe their Characters delight, As careless workes of black and white But 'cause you underneath may find A sense that can informe the mind; Divine, or moral rules impart Or Raptures of Poetick Art: So what at first was only fit To fold up silkes, may wrap up wit.</field>
   </doc>
</add>