<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Cory, William Johnson, 1823-1892</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Cory, William Johnson, 1823-1892</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">cory william johnson 1823 1892</field>
      <field name="author_text">Cory, William Johnson, 1823-1892</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1850's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.1639.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1859</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466932</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Greek, Modern (1453- )</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Cambridge Prize Poems</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Cambridge Prize Poems</field>
      <field name="title_facet">cambridge prize poems</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">cambridge prize poems</field>
      <field name="title_text">Cambridge Prize Poems</field>
      <field name="year_display">1859</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1859</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1859</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466932&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466932&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Cory, William Johnson, 1823-1892&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;cory william johnson 1823 1892&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Cambridge Prize Poems&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;cambridge prize poems&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1859&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1859&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Cory, William Johnson&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1823&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1892&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Cambridge Prize Poems&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Macmillan and Co.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1859&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp1955&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;gre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;xii, 351 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Cambridge Prize Poems&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 20 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only poem by Johnson included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PLATO, BY WILLIAM JOHNSON, SCHOLAR OF KING'S COLLEGE. 1843. They say the world is on the wane, and some Swear that the age of dwarfish minds is come, That greatness hath no charter as of yore, And men revolt from claims of sovereign lore, And the bold majesty of mental strife Hath lost its force in our distracted life, And though the circles widen, fainter gleam All new emotions on the mirror-stream, A subtle touch—a brave and calm appeal To thoughts that thoughtful men alone can feel; A strong ingenuous plea for what is best, Which scorns the drossy gauds of interest,— Such weapons now are blunt, and praters say That we must fling those time-worn arms away, Content with faint and faltering hands to wield The stones we gather from our battle-field. O Granta! thou that hast the heart of youth Pulsing with genial heat of ancient truth, Whose cloistral peace is vocal to the wise, Whose shadowy rites and fame-lit cemetries Still bear high witness to the wealth and pride Of Grecian reason's glowing summer-tide, Speak for the honour of mankind, and tell The sceptic herd, how willingly and well Thy venturous sons are ever bold to try The sounding depths of bright philosophy. Stretch out thy hand to help the faithful few, Who toil to fill their urns with lustral dew, Wading heart-deep into the brimming stream That glides around the fadeless Academe. On—on—our limbs are nerved, our eyes are keen, The waves we part are glad with tremulous sheen, Where light and shade are quivering evermore, Flung from the plane-trees of yon pleasant shore, And lucent eddies, wreathed on either side, Play round our bosoms—but the stream is wide, The farther bank is steep; and they that lack The sure calm will, are fain to struggle back, And then, disloyal to thy gracious sway, With sneers of baffled hope they turn away. Yet some have won the passage hand in hand, For on that river's marge a duteous band, With dripping raiment and a beaming face, Are beckoning us to seek their resting-place. Lo! the mild company of lordly seers In choral clusters on the bank appears, And round one foremost hierarch, whose voice Breathes like the harping Zephyr, they rejoice. Their footfalls lightly crisp the dimpled lawn, Their smiles are free and radiant as the dawn, Their arms are waving peace—the young gale brings Sweet awful accents from their communings, And far-off listeners reverently stoop To catch the murmurs of that tuneful group, And, when they pause, deep in the ear doth lie Their clinging penetrative melody. A glorious throng! the brave, the meek, the wise, In one admiring glance we recognize Great heirs of human love and human power, Who own'd and used their intellectual dower In nurturing every truth that conscience taught, And taking forms of good from vital thought. Here walk Athenian youths of gentle mien, Moulding high words in colloquy serene— Calm, bright-eyed neophytes with sunny brows, Bearing symposial wreaths of myrtle boughs, With buoyant step, and free lips, and the air Of men with minds to think and hearts to dare. And mingling with that hopeful crowd we see Gray Fathers Clement of Alexandria, Justin Martyr, Origen, &amp;c. of a holier family, Sages who scan these Gentile forms to search For some rare type of the eternal Church, And love with tender faith to contemplate The wondrous image of that model state, Which, though it were but bodied forth in speech, The scope of human wants doth wellnigh reach, And hath a glorious meaning, e'en for us Who gaze on symbols more miraculous. Here too the studious peers, Lorenzo de Medici, Politian, Ficinus, &amp;c. who graced of yore The fair Laurentian haunts on Arno's shore, And 'midst the wakening arts, in classic shade, By urn, and fount, and rose-clad balustrade, Would crowd, like wistful children, to unroll The rescued treasures of some living scroll, These—the enthusiasts of bright Fiesole— Join with the shadowy crowd; and must not she, Lady Jane Grey. Who sat with Phædo's volume on her knee, And, when the blithe hunt was on foot for her, When horns were clamorous, and the woods a-stir, And echoes of the noon-day joyaunce fell On the sweet stillness of her oriel, Just look'd up once to see the merry men, Then bent her frail neck o'er the page again, And, though she loved the forest, dared prefer To talk with Life's and Death's Interpreter,— Must not that second Diotima be Vid. Plat. Conviv., cc. 27, 35. In this high-rapt and tranquil company? Yes, thou great-hearted Plato! few be they Of Wisdom's votaries that disown thy sway; Few souls of beauty ever lacked the sense Which feeds upon thy rich intelligence. Others are names—thou art a living friend, In whom the gifts of earlier teachers blend— And sworn by thy fair memory—sworn to take Thy love-chants' burden, till the world's awake, Aye foremost in the gaze of Time hath stood Thy strenuous and heroic brother-hood. The queenly City of thy love is dead, Thy Greece is of the Past; but thou hast sped Through other lands, like an unwearied breeze, Wandering to tell a tale of Socrates, And ever, where that old man's words have been, Fancy hath grown more fresh and hope more keen. Still live the soft and intricate discourse, The wit, that makes us tolerant perforce, The mystic legend, and the verse that drops As snow-flakes shower on wintry forest-tops, ?)/?? ?????????? ??????? ???????????. —Hom. Il. ?. 222. The questions working wedge-like towards the proof, The threads of prayer from old Religion's woof, The courteous skill of keen rebukes, that chide The learner's folly, and the sophist's pride— With this fair growth encinctured still, thy mind, Like some old dial, stands to tell mankind How the world's day moves on. Thy glorious views Of God's and the immortal Spirit's dues, Thy scheme of law within the law, of grace ??????? ??? ???????? ????? ???? ???? ???? ?? ?? ???? ??????. —Rep. iv. 124. ??? ?????? ??????. 129. Wrought in the fair souls of “the golden race,” Of pure essential art, that will not be The minion of a vulgar fantasy, Of truths that lift themselves to Reason's gaze, Of love which yearns for strength, and toil, and praise, And hath a vivid influence to combine All kindred forms of excellence divine— Such high achievements of thy subtle brain Have taken shape in other minds again, And men, in judgment free, in knowledge ripe, For many a thought borrow thy archetype, Not servile, not ungrateful, but endued With hope to wage on sin thy valiant feud, Or live thy manifold life in solitude. True was thy teacher's dream, “Socrates, nocte priusquam ad se a patre deduceretur [Plato], vidit Cygni pullum ex arâ, quæ in Academiâ Cupidini consecrata fuit, volâsse, et in gremio suo resedisse, et postea olorem illum pennis cœlum petiisse, canore musco auditus hominum deorumque mulcentem.” —Fabricius de Platone, ejusque Scriptis, c. 2. According to Olympiodorus, it is related that, ?????? ??????? ?? ???? ??????? ????? ???????, ??? ????????? ??????????? ??????, ?. ?. ?.. which on the eve Of thy novitiate, boding hopes did weave; When, as he slumbered in the twilight dim, His vision-working Genius shaped for him A forecast of the coming friend. 'Tis said That in a dream he sat with drooping head, Musing, as was his wont; and there did seem From Love's green altar in the Academe To fall a callow cygnet on his lap, And, as he tried in kindly folds to wrap The helpless thing, it struggled to the light, Took plumes of snow, and drest its wings for flight, Then soared with jubilant song of liquid mirth Far—far above the loftiest points of earth, Thrilling all ears in land and sea and sky With long-drawn floods of magic harmony. Oh! keep that rhythmic influence of thought— Still keep for us—for all—that music-fraught And loving soul; still be thy full rich cup For ever and for ever mantling up, Where hearts that faint at many a mournful sight May take a freshness from such deep delight, And they that venture for a freeman's prize May wax the stronger for thy sympathies. Yet, though our homage rises high to speak The debt of love we owe this mightiest Greek, And jealous of the fretful world we break A lance of chivalry for Plato's sake, Were it not well, before the feeble lay, That wooes his memory, hath died away, To check loud praise, and for a moment try The sweet calm whisper of humility? Say we, that he was poor, whose course was run, Though bold and stedfast, yet without the Sun; Say we, he died too soon, ere man was blest With that for which his spirit went in quest, Who built a birth-place for the soul, but brought No general freedom from that home of thought, Felt not, or scarcely felt, in wisdom's dream Our want of one to suffer and redeem, Hoped not that mortal dust to life could rise, And schemed for nought his deep triplicities? There they [Angels] in their trinal triplicities, About Him wait, and on His will depend.— Spenser's Hymn to Heavenly Love, stanza x. Oh! there's a greater knowledge, and a mind By happier sureties, wiser fears consigned, In what some weak unlettered infant feels, When for his bed-side orisons he kneels, A loftier hope—than thou could'st e'er affect, Man of broad ????? ?? ????, ?????????????? ????? ??? ?? ?????, ??? ?????????, ??? ?????????????, ??? ??????????? ??????????. —Olympiod. de Vit. Plat. heart and piercing intellect! O Plato! were it given thee but to hear The chime of treble tongues so silver-clear, When reverent children at a mother's feet The first low words of deathless prayer repeat, And like the birth of early stars, whose light Comes in a moment from the Infinite, The young instinctive thoughts of love and awe Wake at the prompting of a Saviour's law, Then what a gain were thine to take that yoke, To learn the words a Christian weakling spoke, To weep for sin, and sue for grace, and bring To God thy reason, as an offering.</field>
   </doc>
</add>