<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Lamb, Charles, 1775-1834</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Lamb, Charles, 1775-1834</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">lamb charles 1775 1834</field>
      <field name="author_text">Lamb, Charles, 1775-1834</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1870's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.2475.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1874</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:467516</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Mary and Charles Lamb: Poems, letters, and remains ; now first collected, with reminiscences and notes. By W. Carew Hazlitt. With portrait, and numerous facsimiles and illustrations of their favourite haunts in London and the suburbs</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Mary and Charles Lamb: Poems, letters, and remains ; now first collected, with reminiscences and notes. By W. Carew Hazlitt. With portrait, and numerous facsimiles and illustrations of their favourite haunts in London and the suburbs</field>
      <field name="title_facet">mary and charles lamb poems letters and remains</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">mary and charles lamb poems letters and remains</field>
      <field name="title_text">Mary and Charles Lamb: Poems, letters, and remains ; now first collected, with reminiscences and notes. By W. Carew Hazlitt. With portrait, and numerous facsimiles and illustrations of their favourite haunts in London and the suburbs</field>
      <field name="year_display">1874</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1874</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1874</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467516&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467516&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Lamb, Charles, 1775-1834&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;lamb charles 1775 1834&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Mary and Charles Lamb: Poems, letters, and remains ; now first collected, with reminiscences and notes. By W. Carew Hazlitt. With portrait, and numerous facsimiles and illustrations of their favourite haunts in London and the suburbs&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;mary and charles lamb poems, letters and remains&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1874&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1874&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Lamb, Charles&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1775&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1834&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Mary and Charles Lamb: Poems, letters, and remains&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;now first collected, with reminiscences and notes. By W. Carew Hazlitt. With portrait, and numerous facsimiles and illustrations of their favourite haunts in London and the suburbs&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chatto and Windus&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1874&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp2101&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;307, 31 p.; ill.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Mary and Charles Lamb: Poems, letters, and remains&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;now first collected, with reminiscences and notes. By W. Carew Hazlitt. With portrait, and numerous facsimiles and illustrations of their favourite haunts in London and the suburbs&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 16 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">POEMS. LIVING WITHOUT GOD IN THE WORLD. From a MS. in the handwriting of Robert Southey, circâ 1799; formerly the property of Joseph Cottle, of Bristol, and now in the possession of F. W. Cosens, Esq., of Clapham Park. These lines originally appeared in the Annual Anthology. Mystery of God! thou brave &amp; beauteous world! Made fair with light, &amp; shade, &amp; stars, &amp; flowers; Made fearful and august with woods &amp; rocks, Jagg'd precipice, black mountain, sea in storms; Sun, over all—that no co-rival owns, But thro' heaven's pavement rides in despite Or mockery of the Littleness of Man! I see a mighty Arm, by Man unseen, Resistless—not to be controuled; that guides, In solitude of unshared energies, All these thy ceaseless miracles, O World! Arm of the world, I view thee, &amp; I muse On Man; who, trusting in his mortal strength, Leans on a shadowy staff—a staff of dreams. We consecrate our total hopes and fears To idols, flesh &amp; blood, our love (heaven's due), Our praise &amp; admiration; praise bestowed By man on man, and acts of worship done To a kindred nature, certes do reflect Some portion of the glory, &amp; rays oblique, Upon the politic worshipper—so man Extracts a pride from his humility. Some braver spirits, of the modern stamp, Affect a Godhead nearer: these talk loud Of mind, &amp; independent intellect; Of energies omnipotent in man; And man of his own fate artificer— Yea, of his own life lord, &amp; of the days Of his abode on earth, when time shall be That life immortal shall become an Art; Or Death, by chemic practices deceived, Forego the scent which for six thousand years, Like a good hound, he has followed, or at length, More manners learning, &amp; a decent sense, And rev'rence of a philosophic world, Relent, &amp; leave to prey on carcasses. But these are fancies of a few: the rest, Atheists, or Deists only in the name, By word or deed deny a God. They eat Their daily bread, &amp; draw the breath of heaven, Without a thought or thanks; heav'n's roof to them Is but a painted ceiling hung with lamps, No more, that light them to their purposes. They “wander loose about.” They nothing see, Themselves except, and creatures like themselves, That liv'd short-sighted, impotent to save. So on their dissolute spirits, soon or late, Destruction cometh “like an armed man,” Or like a dream of murder in the night, Withering their mortal faculties, &amp; breaking The bones of all their pride.— A PARODY. I found these lines—a parody on the popular, or nursery, ditty, “Lady-bird, lady-bird, fly away home”—officiating as a wrapper to some of Mr. Hazlitt's hair. There is no signature; but the handwriting is unmistakably Lamb's; nor are the lines themselves the worst of his playful effusions. Lazy-bones, lazy-bones, wake up and peep; The Cat's in the cupboard, your Mother's asleep. There you sit snoring, forgetting her ills: Who is to give her her Bolus and Pills? Twenty-five Angels must come into Town, All for to help you to make your new gown— Dainty aerial Spinsters &amp; Singers: Aren't you asham'd to employ such white fingers? Delicate Hands, unaccustom'd to reels, To set 'em a washing at poor body's wheels? Why they came down is to me all a riddle, And left hallelujah broke off in the middle. Jove's Court &amp; the Presence Angelical cut, To eke out the work of a lazy young slut. Angel-duck, angel-duck, wingèd &amp; silly, Pouring a watering pot over a lily, Gardener gratuitous, careless of pelf, Leave her to water her Lily herself, Or to neglect it to death, if she chuse it; Remember, the loss is her own if she lose it. LINES SUGGESTED BY A SIGHT OF WALTHAM CROSS. Time-mouldering crosses, gemmed with imagery Of costliest work and Gothic tracery, Point still the spot, to hallowed Wedlock dear, Where rested on its solemn way the bier That bore the bones of Edward's Elinor To mix with Royal dust at Westminster. Far different rites did thee to dust consign, Duke Brunswick's daughter, princely Caroline: A hurrying funeral, and a banished grave, High-minded Wife, were all that thou couldst have. Grieve not, great Ghost, nor count in death in losses; Thou in thy life-time hadst thy share of crosses A DRAMATIC FRAGMENT. For this little relic I am indebted to the kindness of Theodore Martin, Esq. “Fie upon't! All men are false, I think. The date of love Is out, expired, its stories all grown stale, O'erpast, forgotten, like an antique tale Of Hero and Leander.” John Woodvil. All are not false. I knew a youth who died For grief, because his Love proved so, And married with another. I saw him on the wedding-day,— For he was present in the church that day, In festive bravery decked, As one that came to grace the ceremony,— I marked him when the ring was given: His Countenance never changed; And, when the priest pronounced the marriage blessing, He put a silent prayer up for the bride— For so his moving lip interpreted. He came invited to the marriage-feast With the bride's friends, And was the merriest of them all that day: But they who knew him best called it feigned mirth; And others said He wore a smile like death upon his face. His presence dashed all the beholders' mirth, And he went away in tears. What followed then? O then He did not, as neglected suitors use, Affect a life of solitude in shades, But lived In free discourse and sweet society Among his friends who knew his gentle nature best. Yet ever, when he smiled, There was a mystery legible in his face; But whoso saw him, said he was a man Not long for this world— And true it was; for even then The silent love was feeding at his heart, Of which he died; Nor ever spoke word of reproach; Only, he wished in death that his remains Might find a poor grave in some spot not far From his mistress' family vault—being the place Where one day Anna should herself be laid. THE CHRISTENING. Copies of these verses are still preserved at Enfield. They were written by Lamb to celebrate the christening of the son of Charles and Mary Gisburne May there, March 25, 1829; when Miss Lamb and her brother stood sponsors. Mr. Tuff, the historian of Enfield, writes: “I knew both the families [the Mays and Gisburnes]. The head of the first was Dr. May, who conducted a first-class school for nearly half a century. He occupied the ‘Old Palace,’ hence it was called The Palace School. The Doctor had a brother, Charles May, who married Miss Gisburne, mistress of a ladies' school here many years. The child of Charles and Mary May, for whom Lamb and his sister stood sponsors, was the issue of this marriage. There is nothing in the parish book, beyond the signatures of Charles May and his wife. Dr. May educated, amongst many citizens' sons, the present Baron Bramwell, the eminent judge.” Arrayed—a half angelic sight— In nests of pure baptismal white, The mother to the font doth bring The little, helpless, nameless thing, With hushes soft, and mild caressing, At once to get—a name and blessing! Close to the babe the priest doth stand, The sacred water at his hand, That must assoil the soul within From every stain of Adam's sin. The Infant eyes the mystic scenes, Nor knows what all this wonder means; And now he smiles, as if to say, “I am a Christian made to-day;” Now, frighted, clings to nurse's hold, Shrinking from the water cold, Whose virtues, rightly understood, Are, as Bethesda's waters, good— Strange words! “The World, the Flesh, the Devil.” Poor Babe, what can it know of evil? But we must silently adore Mysterious truths, and not explore. Enough for him, in after times, When he shall read these artless rhymes, If, looking back upon this day, With easy conscience he can say— “I have in part redeemed the pledge Of my baptismal privilege And vow, and more will strive to flee All that my sponsors kind renounced for me.</field>
   </doc>
</add>