<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Pilkington, Francis</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Pilkington, Francis</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">pilkington francis</field>
      <field name="author_text">Pilkington, Francis</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.1804.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1624</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464285</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The second set of Madrigals, and Pastorals, of 3. 4. 5. and 6. Parts ; Apt for Violls and Voyces</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">The second set of Madrigals, and Pastorals, of 3. 4. 5. and 6. Parts ; Apt for Violls and Voyces</field>
      <field name="title_facet">second set of madrigals and pastorals of 3 4 5 and 6 parts</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">second set of madrigals and pastorals of 3 4 5 and 6 parts</field>
      <field name="title_text">The second set of Madrigals, and Pastorals, of 3. 4. 5. and 6. Parts ; Apt for Violls and Voyces</field>
      <field name="year_display">1624</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1624</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1624</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464285&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464285&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Pilkington, Francis&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;pilkington francis&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The second set of Madrigals, and Pastorals, of 3. 4. 5. and 6. Parts ; Apt for Violls and Voyces&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;second set of madrigals, and pastorals of 3 4 5 and 6 parts&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1624&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1624&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Pilkington, Francis&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The second set of Madrigals, and Pastorals, of 3. 4. 5. and 6. Parts&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Apt for Violls and Voyces&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by Thomas Snodham [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1624&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp3711&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;6 parts&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The second set of Madrigals, and Pastorals, of 3. 4. 5. and 6. Parts&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Apt for Violls and Voyces&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 26 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted; music omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Songbooks.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The following poems are scored for music in the source text. Where poems are not stanzaic, no attempt has been made to reconstruct the metrical lines. Variations for different voices have been ignored. Repetition marks have been ignored. TO THE RIGHT VVOR????????, And worthy of much Honor, Sir Peter Leighe of Lyme, Knight. To my approoued Friend, Master Francis Pilkington, Batchelar of Musicke. A Sonnet. Those great Atchieuements our Heroicke Spirits Haue done in Englands old or later Victories, Shall we attribute wholly to the Merrits, Of our Braue Leaders? And faire Industries Which their not-named Followers haue exprest Lie bid? And must the Matchlesse Excellencies Of Bird, Bull, Dowland, Morley, and the rest Of our rare Artists, (who now dim the lights Of other lands) be onely in Request? Thy selfe, (and others) loosing your due Rights To high Desert? nay, make it (yet) more plaine, That thou canst hit the Ayres of euery vaine. Their praise was their Reward, and so 'tis thine: The Pleasure of thy paines all mens: and mine. William Webbe. To Master Francis Pilkington, Batchelar of Musicke. Art's praise, and Skill's high pitch, are not so tyed To bankes of Po, or siluer Thames (we see) But Ioues faire bird may haunt fine streames beside, And chaunt sweet layes on brinkes of Antique dee. Old Chester is not so with Eld ore-laine, That where contention is for praise, shee then Should not her old-borne title still maintaine, And put in, for her claime to chiefe of Men. Witnesse more Instances hereof, then cast Into few lines can be (some larger Quill Shall labour that) Witnesse thy first and last Rare-fram'de composures. And this witnesse will Thy choice for Patron: one for glorious fame, Chiefe in our Clyme, Grace to thy worke, thy name. Thine and the Muses friends of Chester, Henry Harpur. Of 3. Voc. [I. Sou'raigne of my delight] Sou'raigne of my delight Sou'raigne of my delight, of my delight, heare my complaining Flie to her, flie to her, my sad thoughts containing, Beauty by pleasure onely crowned, onely crowned, Now in her selfe lies drowned, by her vnkinde disdaining, by her vnkinde, vnkinde, vnkinde, vnkinde disdaining, now in her selfe lies drowned, now now in her selfe, now in her selfe lies drowned, by her vnkinde disdaining, her vnkinde, vnkinde, vnkinde, vnkinde disdaining. [II. Yond hill tops Phœbus kist] Yond hill tops Phœbus kist Yond hill tops Phœbus kist, at his last nights farewell, This morne the same he blist, in homage to her cell, in homage to her cell, The Nymphs and wood-gods cry'd, Lord Phœbus goe your way, We her, she vs, will haue, she vs will haue, you are too hot to play, you are too hot to play, you are too hot to play. [III. Wake sleepy Thirsis] Wake sleepy Thirsis wake Wake sleepy Thirsis wake, for loue &amp; Venus sake, Come let vs mount the hills, which Zephirus with coole breath, coole breath fills, Or let vs tread new Allyes, in yonder shadie vallies, Rise, rise, rise, rise, lighten thy heauy eies, See how the streames doe glide, And the greene Meads deuide, and the greene Meads, and the greene Meads deuide, But streame nor fire shall part, this and this, ioyned heart, But streame nor fire shall part, this and this, ioyned heart. [IIII. Stay heart, runne not so fast] Stay, stay, stay heart, runne not so fast Stay, stay, stay heart, runne not so fast, from him that loues thee, To her that deadly hates thee, that deadly hates thee, Her sharpe disdain, reproues thee, And worse then ill still rates thee, and worse then ill, and worse then ill still rates thee, Then let her goe and spare not, Hold thou thy selfe contented, and I care not, My loue is gone, and with her goe my sorrow, O vile wretch, thou louedst once, and why now doest thou varry? Then straight away I hast me, And after thee will run, while life shall last me, Ah death his force now tryeth, Flora farewell, farewell, For loe thy Shepheard dyeth [V. Yee bubling springs] Yee bubling springs that gentle musicke makes Yee bubling springs that gentle musicke makes, To louers plaints, with heart-sore throbs, immixt, When as my deare this way her pleasure takes, Tell her with teares How firme my loue is fixt, And Philomell report, report, my timerous feares, Sound, sound my highoes, highoes, in her eares, her eares, But if she aske if I for loue will dye, if I for loue, if I for loue will dye, will dye, Tell her good faith not I. [VI. Your fond preferments are but Childrens toyes] Your fond preferments are but Childrens toyes Your fond preferments are but Childrens toyes, And as a shadow all your pleasures passe, As yeares increase, so waining are your ioyes, Your blisse is brittle, brittle, like a broken glasse, Death is the salue that ceaseth all anoy, Death is the port by which we saile to ioy, Death is the port by which we saile to ioy. Here endeth the Songs of three Parts: Of 4. Voc. [VII. Mænalcas in an euening walking was] Mænalcas in an euening walking was Mænalcas in an euening walking was, With Daphne, his beloued louely lasse, louely lasse, She weepes, and doth of Cupid oft complaine, But comfort Daphne, said the iolly swain, Come kisse me sweet and let vs merry be, and let vs merry, merry be, The gods are crost in loue as wel as we. [VIII. Coy Daphne fled from Phœbus hot pursuite] Coy Daphne fled from Phœbus hot pursuite Coy Daphne fled from Phœbus hot pursuite, Carelesse of passion, sencelesse of remorse, Whilst he complaind his griefes, she rested mute, He beg'd her stay, he beg'd her stay, she still kept on, she still kept on her course, But what reward she had, for this you see, She rests transform'd, a winter beaten tree. But what reward she had for this you see, She rests transform'd, a winter beaten tree. [IX. Chast Daphne fled from Phœbus hot pursuite] Chast Daphne fled from Phœbus hot pursuite Chast Daphne fled from Phœbus, Phœbus hot pursuite, Knowing mens passions, idle and of course, And though he plain'd, 'twas fit she should be mute, And honour would she should keepe on her course, For which faire deed, her glory still we see, She rests still greene, she rests still greene, And so wish I to be. [X. If she neglect me, I doe waile and cry] If she neglect, neglect me If she neglect, neglect me, I doe waile and cry, If she, if she affect me, straight for griefe I dye, For though our sorrow, ioy, and death, and death one be, Yet we in one, yet we in one shall nee'r be ioyn'd I see, So that I cry, I dye, I dye, I dye, I dye, Oh dismall fate, Whether she loue, whether she loue, affect, affect, neglect, or hate. affect, neglect, or hate, neglect or hate. [XI. Palæmon and his Sylivia forth must walke] Palæmon and his Sylivia forth must walke Palæmon and his Sylivia forth must walke, Of passions past, of passions past, and diuers things to talke, He sighes, he sighes, she weepes, they kisse, they kisse, and both complaine, they kisse, they kisse, and both complaine, And both of them would some thing, some thing vtter faine, But voice &amp; words, were to them both denaid, For they had nought to say that was not said, But voice &amp; words, were to them both denaid, For they had nought to say that was not said. [XII. You gentle Nymphs that on these meadowes play] You gentle Nymphs that on these meadowes play You gentle Nymphs that on these meadowes play, You gentle Nymphs that on these meadowes play, And oft relate the loues of Shepheards young, Come, come, come sit you downe, come sit you, sit you downe, for if you please to stay, Now may you heare an vncouth passion song, A Lad there is, and I am that poore groome, That's falne in loue, and can not tell, and can not tell with whom. Here endeth the Songs of foure Parts. Of 5. Voc. [XIII. Chast Syrinx fled, feare hasting on her pace] Chast Syrinx fled Chast Syrinx fled, chast Syrinx fled, feare hasting on her pace, hasting, hasting on her pace, With loosed haire, and teare bedewed face, and teare bedewed face, Wearie God wot, And Pan behinde her, and Pan behinde, and Pan behinde her nye, Pan behinde her nye, She fills the woods with many a drery, drery cry, The gods did see, and seeme her case to mourne, And into reeds, her dainty, dainty limbs transforme, So now she makes, she makes, so now she makes most ioyous, ioyous melody, For ioy she kept her lou'd virginitie. [XIIII. Come Shepheards weeds, attend my wofull cryes] Come Shepheards weeds, attend my wofull cryes Come Shepheards weeds, attend my wofull cryes, come Shepheards weeds attend my wofull cryes, Disuse your selues from sweet Mænalcas voyce, disuse your selues from sweet Mænalcas voyce, Mænalcas voyce, For other be those tunes, for other be those tunes which sorrow tyes, which sorrow tyes, which sorrow tyes, From those cleare notes which freely may reioyce, Then power out plaint, and in one word say this, Helplesse his plaint who spoyles himselfe of blisse. [XV. Crowned with flowers I saw faire Amarillis] Crowned with flowers, with flowers Crowned with flowers, with flowers, I saw faire Amarillis, Amarillis by Thersis sit, Hard by a fount of Christall, And with her hand more white then snow or lillies, on sand she wrote, My faith shall be immortall, But sodainly a storme, but sodainly a storme of winde &amp; weather, Blue all her faith, blue all her faith and sand away together. But sodainly a storme of winde and weather, Blue all her faith and sand away together. XVI. An Elegie on the death of his Worshipfull friend, Master Thomas Purcell of Dunhill, Esquire, in Salop. Weepe sad Vrania, weepe Weepe sad Vrania, weepe, For thou hast lost thy deare, And now must fixe thy sacred loue elsewhere, For he that lately made thy numbers eu'n, for he that lately made thy numbers eu'n, Forsaking earth, is now possest, possest of heau'n, is now possest of heauen, Where he though dead still liues with God on hye, He found, he found, we lost, we lost, He sings, he sings, we sigh and dye. [XVII. O Gratious God, pardon my great offence] O gratious God, pardon, pardon my great offence O gratious God, pardon, pardon my great offence, pardon, pardon my great, my great offence, O pardon my great offence, Increase my faith, renue thy spirit, thy spirit of grace, renue thy spirit of grace, Inuest me with thy Christ his innocence, And from me Lord, turne not away thy face, Let not my sinnes foule, foule, many, many, though they be, they be, Make a diuorse betweene thy grace, and me. [XVIII. Goe you skipping Kids and Fawnes] Goe you skipping, skipping Goe you skipping, skipping, skipping Kids and Fawnes, Exercise your swift carriere, ouer pleasant fields and lawnes, Rousing, rousing, rousing vp, rousing vp, rousing vp the fearefull Deere, fearefull Deere, the feareful Deere, fearefull Deere, Greet them all with what I sing, Endlesse, endlesse, endlesse loue eternizing, eternizing. Greet them all with what I sing, Endlesse, endlesse, endlesse loue, eternizing, eternizing. [XIX. Care for thy soule as thing of greatest price] Care, for thy soule as thing of greatest price Care, for thy soule as thing of greatest price, Made, made vnto the end to tast, to tast, to tast of pow'r diuine, to tast, to tast, of pow'r diuine, Deuoid of guilt, deuoid of guilt, abhorring sinne and vice, Apt by Gods grace to vertue to incline, Care for it so, as by thy retchlesse traine, It be not brought to tast eternall paine. [XX. Drowne not with teares, my deerest loue] Drowne not with teares Drowne not with teares, drowne not with teares, my deerest loue, Those eyes which my affections moue, which my affections moue, Doe not with weeping those lights blinde, Which me in thy subiection binde, which me in thy subiection binde, subiection binde, Time that hath made vs two of one, of one, hath made vs two of one, And forst thee now to liue alone, Will once againe vs revnite, revnite, vs revnite, To shew how she can fortune spight. Here endeth the Songs of fiue Parts. Of 6. Voc. [XXI. Deare Shepheardesse, thou art more louely faire] Deare Shepheardesse, thou art more louely Deare Shepheardesse, thou art more louely, more louely faire, Then the both Roses in the prime of May, Thou art more tender, sweet, without compare, without compare, Then the bright Morning, at the breake of day, But vnto me that doe thy praise declare, More cold and dead, more cold and dead, then the most cold dismay. most cold dismay. [XXII. Cruell Pabrilla with thine angrie looke] Cruell Pabrilla with thine angrie looke Cruell Pabrilla with thine angrie looke, Thou euer, euer hold'st my soule in alteration, And of the pleasure that I whilome, and of the pleasure that I whilome tooke, In my faire flockes, thy threats are depriuation, Thee I more loue then hill or valley brooke, valley, valley brooke, Or thriftie, thriftie, thriftie shadow, shadow, my flocks delectation, But yet my sight, but yet my sight more hatefull is to thee, Then thornes or nettles to thy white feet be. [XXIIII. O softly singing Lute] O softly, softly, singing Lute O softly, softly, singing Lute, O softly, singing Lute, See with my teares, thou Time doe keepe, Yet softly, gentle strings, yet softly, softly gentle strings, Agree with loue, that cannot sleepe, Sorrow hy'st, when as it sings, When teares doe fall, then sighes arise, So griefe oft shines, in most sad eyes, Yea loue, through hart it dies, through hart it dies. [XXV. O Praise the Lord all ye Heathen] O praise the Lord ye Heathen O praise the Lord ye Heathen, O praise the Lord, O praise the Lord all ye Heathen, Praise him all ye Nations, all ye Nations, Praise him all ye nations, all ye nations, For his mercifull kindnesse, for his mercifull kindnesse is euermore towards vs, for his mercifull kindnes, for his mercifull kindnes is euer more &amp; more towards vs, And the truth of the Lord endureth for euer, and the truth of the Lord endureth for euer, &amp; the truth of the Lord endureth for euer, for euer, Praised be the Lord, praised be the Lord, praised be the Lord, O praised be the Lord, O praised be the Lord, O praised be the Lord, praised, O praised be the Lord, praised be the Lord, praised, praised be the Lord. [XXVI. Svrcease you youthfull shepheardesses all A dialogue. ] Svrcease you youthfull shepheardesses all Svrcease you youthfull shepheardesses all, Fond folly, breeding loue so sensuall, Stint then our strife, content'on, be content, Loue in it selfe, maintaines an argument. Loue be propitious, Shepheardesdes sing, Olympus likes and loues our Caroling. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>