<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Lichfild, Henry</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Lichfild, Henry</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">lichfild henry</field>
      <field name="author_text">Lichfild, Henry</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.1820.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1613</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464299</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The first set of Madrigals of 5. Parts ; apt both for Viols and Voyces</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">The first set of Madrigals of 5. Parts ; apt both for Viols and Voyces</field>
      <field name="title_facet">first set of madrigals of 5 parts</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">first set of madrigals of 5 parts</field>
      <field name="title_text">The first set of Madrigals of 5. Parts ; apt both for Viols and Voyces</field>
      <field name="year_display">1613</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1613</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1613</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464299&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464299&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Lichfild, Henry&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;lichfild henry&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The first set of Madrigals of 5. Parts ; apt both for Viols and Voyces&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;first set of madrigals of 5 parts&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1613&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1613&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Lichfild, Henry&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The first set of Madrigals of 5. Parts&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;apt both for Viols and Voyces&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for M. L. I. B. and T. S. [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1613&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp3691&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;[114] p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The first set of Madrigals of 5. Parts&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;apt both for Viols and Voyces&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 17 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted; music omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Songbooks.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TO THE RIGHT HONO????? and most Renowmed Lady for all Honour and Vertue, and my most Noble Lady and Mistris, the Lady Cheyney.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Vpon The Right Vertvovs And Honov????? Lady, the Lady Cheney; and her Court-like House at Tuddington. Vnto that Vale-built Place, of lowely height; Where Ioy, Peace, Loue, make an harmonious Chime; Where ciuill sports. Musique and Court delight, Doe runne diuision on the Houres of Time: Where raignes a Lady crown'd with highest merits, On whom the Muses, and the Graces wayte; Beauty, and Courtship match't with noble spirits, Adore her Presence, and adorne her State: To that bright Fame that makes her Turrets shine, Vpon these new sprung Leaues I spred my wings, And to her Praise, would I could sing diuine, Set to Apollo's Lyre, or Orpheus strings; That Honors webb, my Muse might dye in graine, And make remotest Eares admire my straine. Christopher Brooke. TO THE AVTHOR, vpon his Musicall Muse. Ovr Times so curious, and our wits as nice, And all as changing as the Fashion is; No Art for any certaine Truth hath price; All by Opinion goe: and therefore this Which th' Angell (propper to thy Musicks skill) Hath here expos'd to Fashion, Time, and Wit, Looke not t'haue simply crown'd for Good, or Ill, But as thy humorous Censor shall thinke fit. Fortune in these Things rules; (That all know blinde) As blinde are they that censure out of Humor; But if some few iudiciall in this Kinde, Shall grace thy Muse; force not the idle Rumor: For thy knowne worth, in Their iust approbation, Shall wage with Wit, with Humor, Time, and Fashion. Christopher Brooke. The following poems are scored for music in the source text. Where poems are not stanzaic, no attempt has been made to reconstruct the metrical lines. Variations for different voices have been ignored. Repetition marks have been ignored. [I. All yee that sleepe in pleasure] All yee that sleepe in pleasure, Awake, loose not times faire treasure, For Time doth neuer cease his restlesse turning, O I repent the time I spent in loues sweet burning. [II. Shall I seeke to ease my griefe?] Shall I seeke to ease my griefe? No my sight is lost with eyeing, O shall I speake and beg reliefe? No, my voyce is hoarse with crying, O what remaines but onely dyeing? [III. 1 Part. The shepherd Claius seeing his louely Daphnie flying] The shepherd Claius seeing his louely Daphnie flying, He wept with deepe lamenting, his pore hart tormenting, But oh the shepherd, when they met together, To liue or dye for ioy he knew not whether. [IIII. 2. Part. First with lookes he liu'd and dy'd] First with lookes he liu'd and dy'd, Then with sighes her faith he try'd, After sighes he sent his teares, And all to shew his trembling feares, At last he said a truer hart was neuer, Pittie Daphnie, disdaine me not for euer. [V. Aye me, that life should yet remaine] Aye me, that life should yet remaine, When heart and liuing spirits are bereft me, Aye me, Then thus to liue in paine, It better were no life at all were left me, Then die betimes that when my hart returne, That may dye to, and so I cease to mourne. [VI. O my griefe.] O my griefe, were it disclosed, To her (alas) that scornes my playning, Or were she but disposed, to turne her eyes disdayning, From me that sit in sadnesse, My griefe would turne to gladnesse. [VII. I Alwaies lou'd to call my Lady Rose] I alwaieslou'd for to call my Lady Rose, For in her cheeks Roses doe sweetly glose, And from her lips, she such sweet odours threw, as Roses doe gainst Phœbus morning view, But when I thought to pul't, Hope was bereft me, My Rose was gone, and naught but prickles me. [VIII. O Come, come shepherds all] O come, shepherds all, O come all together, To meet faire Daphnie, comming hether, Tell her poore Claius for her sake, Many, many woes, did vndertake. [IX. Sweet Daphnie stay] Sweet Daphnie stay, thy flying, Sweet Daphniestay thy flying, stay thy flying,And hark to my complayning, hark to my complayning, harke to my complayning, Fly not my deere, Fly not so fast away, so fast away, Sweet, but suffer me with thee to play, but suffer me, suffer me to play, Sweet but suffer me with thee to play, with thee to play, Which if thou shalt deny me, deny me, Of life thou dost depriue me, Of life thou dost depriue me, depriue me, Of life thou dost depriue me, Of life thou dost depriue, depriue me. [X. Alas, alas my Daphnie] Alas, alas my Daphnie, my Daphnie, stay but and heare my moning, my moning, Oh stay or I faint, stay or I faint with groning, with groning, or I faint with groning, Nay you run away, nay you run away, as if you meant to leaue me, Ile set me downe and dye, if thus you grieue me, you grieue me, Adew, adew my Daphnie, adew for euer, Ile tell Apollo how cruell you perseuer, you perseuer, Ile tell how cruell you perseuer, But if you by returning doe reuiue me, Ile sing againe of Daphnie, Ile sing againe, againe of Daphnie, Ile sing againe, Ile sing againe of Daphnie, Ile sing againe of Daphnie, Ile sing againe of Daphnie, of Daphnie, againe of Daphnie. [XI. Aye me, when to the Ayre I breath my playning] Aye me, when to the Ayre I breath my playning, to merry fountaines my disdayning, When to rude rockes and pleasant groues, I tell all my vnhappy loues, They heare me, whilst I thus condole, But with their Ecco, call me foole. [XII. Arise, sweet hart.] Arise, sweet hart, arise, and come away to play, See, see with flowry garlands all the Meades are gay, The pretty Birds are singing, and Ecco sweetly ringing, Then Daphnie pitty mee, or else I dye, If with hard hart, no no you cry. [XIII. 1. Part. When first I saw those cruell eyes] When first I saw those cruell eyes Those eyes, the authors of my cryes, Adoring them for Saints diuine, Placed in such a heau'nly shrine, You told me then to proue me, You would for euer loue me. [XIIII. 2. Part. If this be loue to scorne my crying] If this be loue to scorne my crying, To laugh at me when I lye a dying, To kill my hart with too much grieuing, To flye and yeeld me no relieuing If loue be thus to proue me, O then I know you loue me. [XV. Cruell, Let my hart be blessed] Cruell, Let my hart be blessed, No life is sweet with a hart oppressed, For though my greater griefe be flying, My smile, is turn'd to sighing, And when I would thy praise be singing, I change my note and say, alas my hart is sore with stinging, Yet cruell loue for this woe if thou dost languish, O then I dye, I dye with anguish. [XVI. 1. Part. A Seely Syluan, kissing heau'n-borne fire] A seely Syluan, kissing heau'n-borne fire, Scorched his lips for his so fond desire, I not so fond, but gaz'd whilst such fier burned, and all my hart straight into flames, was turned. [XVII. The Syluan iustly suffered for his kisse] The Syluan iustly suffered for his kisse, His fire was stolne, and stolne things goe amisse, But I alas, vniustly, for to haue her, Her heau'nly fire, the Gods and Graces gaue her. [XVIII. Iniurious houres, whilst any ioy] Iniurious houres, whilst any ioy doth blesse me, With speedy wings you flye, and so release me, But if some sorrow, doe oppresse my hart, You creepe, as if you neuer ment to part. [XIX. Whilst that my louely Daphnie] Whilst that my louely Daphnie, my louely, louely Daphnie, downe from the hils came walking, from the hils came walking, The Nimphs of Diana, Nimphs of Diana in a shade sat talking, This shepherds Queene that there vnseene, This shepherds Queene, this shepherds Queene that there was vnseene, all sodainely in rushed, Lord how the Nimphs then blushed, Lord how the Nimphs, Lord how the Nimphs, the Nimphs then blushed, And al danc'd round about her, with this sweet cry, long liue, long liue my louely Daphnie, long liue my louely Daphnie, louely Daphnie, my louely Daphnie, Long liue, long liue my louely Daphnie, Long liue my louely Daphnie. [XX. My hart opprest by your disdayning] My hart opprest by your disdayning Doth flow in teares by iust complayning, All ioyes from me are quite exiled, Since of your loue I am beguiled.</field>
   </doc>
</add>