<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Middleton, Thomas</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Middleton, Thomas</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">middleton thomas</field>
      <field name="author_text">Middleton, Thomas</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">16th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.1070.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">1597</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:463725</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Wisdome of Solomon Paraphrased ; Written by Thomas Middleton</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Wisdome of Solomon Paraphrased ; Written by Thomas Middleton</field>
      <field name="title_facet">wisdome of solomon paraphrased</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">wisdome of solomon paraphrased</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Wisdome of Solomon Paraphrased ; Written by Thomas Middleton</field>
      <field name="year_display">1597</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1597</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1597</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463725&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463725&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Middleton, Thomas&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;middleton thomas&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Wisdome of Solomon Paraphrased ; Written by Thomas Middleton&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;wisdome of solomon paraphrased&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1597&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1597&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Middleton, Thomas&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Wisdome of Solomon Paraphrased&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Written by Thomas Middleton&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed ... by Valentine Sems [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1597&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp2638&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;[5], 177 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Wisdome of Solomon Paraphrased&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Written by Thomas Middleton&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 309 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">A Joue surgit opus.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To the right Honourable and my very good Lord, Robert Deuoreux, Erle of Essex and Ewe, Vicount of Hereford, Lorde Ferrers of Chartley, Bourcher, and Louayne, Maister of her Maiesties Horse and Ordonance, Knight of the honourable order of the Garter, and one of her Maiesties most honorable priuie Counsell. The Wisedome of Solomon paraphrased [Chapter I.] Uerse 1 Wisedome Elixer of the purest life, Hath taught hir lesson to iudicial views, To those that iudge a cause &amp; end a strife, Which sits in Iudgements seat &amp;c Iustice vse: A lesson worthy of diuinest eare, Quintessence of a true diuinest feare. Vnwilling that exordium should retaine, Her life-infusing speech, doth thus begin, You (quoth shee) that giue remedy or paine: Loue Iustice, for iniustice is a sin. Giue vnto God his due, his reuerent stile; And rather vse simplicity then guile. [Verse] 2 For him, that guides the radiant eie of day, Sitting in his star-chamber of the Skie, The Horizons and hemespheres obay, And windes the fillers of vacuitie: Much lesse shuld man tempt God, when all obay, But rather be a guide, and leade the way. For temting argues but a sins attempt, Temptation is to sin associate; So doing, thou from God art cleane exempt, Whose loue is neuer placde, in his loues hate, He will be found, not of a tempting minde, But found of those which he doth faithfull finde. [Verse] 3 Temptation rather seperates from God, Conuerting goodnes from the thing it was, Heaping the indignation of his rod, To bruse our bodies like a brittle glasse: For wicked thoughts haue still a wicked end, In making God our foe, which was our frend. They muster vp reuenge, encamp our hate, Vndoing what before they meant to do, Stirring vp anger, and vnluckie fate, Making the earth their friend, the heauen their foe: But when heauens guide makes manifest his power, The earth, their frinds, doth them like foes deuoure. [Verse] 4 O foolish men to warre against your blisse, O hatefull harts where wisedome neuer raignd, O wicked thoughts which euer thought amisse, What haue you reapt? what pleasure haue you gaind? A fruite in shew, a pleasure to decay, This haue you got by keeping follies way. For wisedomes haruest is with follie nipt, And with the winter of your vices frost, Her fruite all scattered her implanting ript, Her name decayed, her fruition lost: Nor can she prosper in a plot of vice, Gaining no summers warmth, but winters ice. [Verse] 5 Thou barren earth, where vertues neuer bud, Thou fruitles wombe, where neuer fruits abide, And thou drie-withered sap which bears no good, But the dishonor of thy prowd hearts pride: A seate of al deceit, deceit, deceaude, Thy blisse, a woe, thy woe of blisse bereaude. This place of night hath left no place for day, Here neuer shines the sunne of discipline, But mischiefe clad in sable nights array, Thoughts apparition, euill Angels signe, These raigne enhoused with their mother Night, To cloude the day of clearest wisedomes light. [Verse] 6 Oh you that practise to be chiefe in sinne, Loues hate, hates friend, friends foe, foes follower, What doe you gaine? what merit do you winne, To be blaspheming vices practiser? Your gaine is wisedomes euerlasting hate, Your merit, griefe, your griefe, your liues debate. Thou canst not hide thy thoght, god made thy thoght, Let this thy caucat be for thinking ill, Thou knowst that Christ thy liuing freedome boght, To liue on earth according to his will: God being thy creator, Christ thy blisse, Why dost thou erre? why dost thou do amisse? [Verse] 7 Hee is both Iudge and witnesse of thy deeds, Hee knowes the volume which thy hart containes, Christ skips thy faults, only thy virtue reades, Redeeming thee from all thy vices paines: O happy crowne of mortall mans content, Sent for our ioye, our ioye in being sent. Then sham'st thou not to erre, to sin, to stray, To come to composition with thy vice, With new-purg'd feete to treade the ouldest way, Lending new sence vnto thy ould deuice? Thy shame might flowe in thy sin-flowing face, Rather then ebbe to make an ebbe of grace. [Verse] 8 For hee which rules the Orbe of heauen and earth, And the ineqall course of euery starre, Did knowe mans thoughts and secreats at his birth, Whither enclinde to peace or discords iarre: He knowes what man will be ere he be man, And all his deeds in his lifes liuing span. Then tis vnpossible that earth can hide, Vnrighteous actions from a righteous God, For he can see their feete in sin that slide, And those that lodge in righteousnesse abode: Hee will extend his mercy on the good, His wrath on those in whom no vertues bud. [Verse] 9 Many there bee, that after trespasse done, Will seeke a couert for to hide their shame, And range about the earth, thinking to shunne, Gods heauie wrath, and meritorious blame: They thinking to flye sin, run into sin, And thinke to end, when they do new begin. God made the earth, the earth denies their sute, Nor can they harbor in the centres womb, God knowes their thoughts, although their tongs be mute, And heares the sounds from forth their bodies tomb: Sounds? ah no sounds, but man himselfe hee heares, Too true a voice of mans most falsest feares. [Verse] 10 Oh see destruction houering ore thy head, Mantling her selfe in wickednes array, Hoping to make thy body as her bed, Thy vice her nutriment, thy soule her pray: Thou hast forsaken him that was thy guide, And see what followes to asswage thy pride. Thy roaring vices noyse, hath cloyd his eares, Like foaming waues they haue orewhelmde thy ioy, Thy murmurings which thy whole body beares Hath bred thy waile, thy waile, thy lifes annoy, Vnhappy thoughts to make a soules decay, Vnhappie soule in suffering thoughts to sway. [Verse] 11 Then sith the height of mans felicitie, Is plung'd within the pudle of misdeedes: And wades amongst discredits infamie, Blasting the merit of his vertues seedes, Beware of murmuring, the chiefest ill, From whence all sin, all vice, all paines distill. O heauie doome proceeding from a tong, Heauie light tong; tong to thy owne decay, In vertue weake, in wickednesse too strong, To mischiefe prone, from goodnesse gone astray; Hammer to forge misdeedes, to temper lies, Selling thy life to death, thy soule to cries. [Verse] 12 Must death needs pay the ransome of thy sin, With the dead carcasse of descending spirit? Wilt thou of force be snared in his gin, And place thy errour in destructions merit: Life seeke not for thy death, death comes vnsought, Buying the life which not long since was bought. Death and destruction neuer needs a call, They are attendants on liues pilgrimage, And life to them is as their playing ball. Grounded vppon destructions anchorage, Seeke not for that which vnsought will betide, Nere wants destruction a prouoking guide. [Verse] 13 Will you needs act your owne destruction? Will you needs harbour your owne ouerthrowe? Or will you cause your owne euersion? Beginning with dispaire, ending with woe: Then die your hartes in tyrannies arraie, To make acquittance of destructions pay. What do you meditate but on your death? What doe you practise but your liuing fall? Who of you all haue any vertues breath, But ready armed at a mischiefes call? God is not pleased at your vices sauour, But you best pleased when you lose his fauour. [Verse] 14 He made not death to be your conqueror, But you to conquer ouer death and hell. Nor you to bee destructions seruitor, Enhoused there where Maiestie should dwell: God made man to obay at his beheast, And man to be obayde of euery beast, He made not death to be our labours hire, But we our selues made death through our desart, Here neuer was the kingdome of hell fire, Before the brand was kindled in mans hart: Now man defieth God, all creatures, man, Vice flourisheth, and vertue lieth wan. [Verse] 15 O fruitefull tree, whose roote is alwaies greene, Whose blossomes euer bud, whose fruites encrease, Whose toppe celestiall vertues seat hath been, Defended by the soueraintie of peace: This tree is righteousnes, ô happy tree, Immortalized by thine owne decree. O hatefull plant whose roote is alwaies drie, Whose blossomes neuer bud, whose fruites decrease: On whom sits the infernall deitie, To take possession of so foule a lease; This plant is vice, O too vnhappy plant, Euer to die, and neuer fill deaths want. [Verse] 16 Accursed in thy growth, dead in thy roote, Cancred with sin, shaken with euery winde, Whose top dooth nothing differ from the foote, Mischiefe the sappe, and wickednesse the rhinde: So the vngodly like this withered tree, Is slacke in doing good, in ill too free. Like this their wicked growth, too fast, too slowe, Too fast in slouth, too slow in vertues hast, They thinke their vice a friend, when tis a foe, In good, in wickednes, too slow, too fast: And as this tree decayes, so do they all, Each one copartner of the others fall. Chapter II. Uerse 1 Indeede they doe presage what wil betide, With the misgiuing verdict of misdeeds, They knowe a fall will follow after pride, And in so foule a hart growes manie weeds: Our life is short, quoth they, no tis too long, Lengthned with euill thoughts, and euill tong. A life must needs be short to them that dies, For life once dead in sin, doth weakely liue: These die in sin, and maske in deaths disguise, And neuer thinke, that death new life can giue; They say, life dead, can neuer liue againe, O thoughts, ô wordes, ô deeds, fond, foolish, vaine. [Verse] 2 Vilde life, to harbor where such death abodes, Abodes worse then are thoughts, thoughts worse then words, Wordes halfe as ill as deeds, deeds sorrowes odes, Odes ill inchaunters of too ill records; Thoghts, words, and deeds conoyined in one song, May cause an Eccho from destructions tong. Quoth they, tis chaunce whether we liue or die, Borne, or abortiue, be, or neuer bee, Wee worship fortune, shee's our deitie, If she denies, no vitall breath haue wee. Here are wee placed in this orbe of death, This breath once gone, we neuer looke for breath. [Verse] 3 Betweene both life and death, both hope and feare, Betweene our ioy and griefe, blisse and dispaire, We here possesse the fruite of what is here, Borne euer for to die, and die deaths heire: Our heritage is death annexde to life, Our portion death, our death an endlesse strife, What is our life but our liues tragedy, Extinguishde in a momentary time? And life to murder life, is cruelty Vnripely withering in a flowrie prime; And vrne of ashes pleasing but the showes, Once dry, the toiling spirit wandring goes. [Verse] 4 Like as the traces of appearing clouds, Giues way when Tytan resalutes the sea, With new-changd flames guilding the Oceans flouds, Kissing the cabinet where Thetis lay: So fares our life, when death doth giue the wound, Our life is led by death, a captiue bound. When Sol bestrides his golden mountaines toppe, Lightning heauens tapors with his liuing fire, All gloomye powers haue their diurnall stoppe, And neuer gaines the darknes they desire; So perisheth our name when wee are dead, Our selues nere cald to mind, our deeds nere read. [Verse] 5 What is the time wee haue? what be our daies? No time, but shadowe of what time should be, Daies in the place of houres which neuer staies, Beguiling sight of that which sight should see; As soone as the begin they haue their fine, Nere waxe, still waine, nere stay, but still decline, Life may be cald the shadowe of effect, Because the cloude of death doth shadow it, Nor can our life approaching death reiect, They both in one for our election sit; Death followes life in euery degree, But life to followe death you neuer see. [Verse] 6 Come we, whose olde decrepit age doth hault, Like limping winter, in our winter, sin, Faultie wee know we are, tush, whats a fault? A shadowed vision of destructions gin; Our life begun with vice, so let it ende, It is a seruile labour to amend. Wee ioyde in sin, and let our ioyes renewe, We ioyed in vice, and let our ioyes remaine, To present pleasures future hopes ensue, And ioy once lost, let vs fetch backe againe; Although our age can lend no youthfull pace, Yet let our mindes follow our youthfull race. [Verse] 7 What though olde age lies heauie on our backe, Anotomie of an age crooked clime, Let minde performe that which our bodies lacke, And change olde age into a youthfull time; Two heauie things are more then one can beare, Blacke may the garments be, the body cleare. Decaying thinges be needfull of repaire, Trees eaten out with years must needs decline, Nature in time with foule doth cloude her faire, Begirting youthfull daies with ages twine; We liue, and while we liue, come let vs ioy, To thinke of after life, tis but a toy. [Verse] 8 Wee know God made vs in a liuing forme, But weele vnmake, and make our selues againe; Vnmake that which is made, like winters storme: Make vnmade things to aggrauate our paine, God was our maker, and he made vs good, But our descent springs from another blood. He made vs for to liue, wee meane to die, He made the heauen our seate, we make the earth, Each fashion makes a contrarietie, God truest God, man falsest from his birth; Quoth they, this earth shal be our chiefest heauen, Our sin the anchor, and our vice the hauen. [Verse] 9 Let heauen in earth, and earth in heauen consist, This earth is heauen, this heauen is earthly heauen: Repugnant earth, repugnant heauen resist, We ioy in earth, of other ioyes bereauen; This is the Paradice of our delight; Here let vs liue, and die in heauens spght. Here let the monuments of wanton sports Be seated in a wantonnes disguise; Closde in the circuit of veneriall forts, To feed the long staru'd sight of Amours eyes; Bee this the Chronicle of our content, How wee did sport on earth, till sport was spent. [Verse] 10 But in the glory of the brightest day, Heauens smoothest browe sometime is furrowed, And cloudes vsurp the clime in dim array, Darkning the light which heauen had borrowed, So in this earthly heauen wee dayly see, That greife is placed where delight should bee. Here liues the righteous, bane vnto their liues, O sound from forth the hollow caue of woe, Here liues age-crooked fathers, widowed wiues; Poore, and yet rich in fortunes ouerthrowe; Let them not liue, let vs increase their want, Make barren their desire, augment their scant. [Verse] 11 Our lawe is correspondent to our doome, Our lawe to doome, is dooming lawes offence, Each one agreeth in the others roome, To punish that which striues and wants defence; This Cedar-like doth make the shrub to bend, When shrubs doth wast their force but to contend. The weakest power is subiect to obay, The mushroms humbly kisse the cedars foote, The cedar florishes when they decay, Because her strength is grounded on a roote Wee are the cedars, they the mushromes bee, Vnabled shrubs, vnto an abled tree. [Verse] 12 Then sith the weaker giues the stronger place, The yong the elder, and the foote the top, The low, the high, the hidden powers, the face, All beastes, the Lion, euery spring, his stop; Let those which practise contrariety, Be ioynd to vs with inequallity: They say that we offend, we say they doe, Their blame is laid on vs, our blame on them: They stricke, and we retort the strucken blowe, So in each garment there's a differing hem; Wee end with contraries as they begun, Vnequall sharing of what either wun. [Verse] 13 14 In this long conflict betweene tongue and tong, Tongue new begining what one tongue did end, Made this cold battell hot in eithers wrong, And kept no pawsing limites to contend; One tongue was eccho to the others sound, Which breathed accents between mouth &amp; ground. Hee which hath vertues armes vppon his shield, Drawes his descent from an eternall King: Hee knowes discretion can make follie yeild, Life conquere death, and vice a captiue bring: The other tutred by his mother sin, Respects nor deedes, nor words, but hopes to win. [Verse] 15 The first, first essence of immortall life, Reprooues the hart of thought, the eie of sight, The eare of hearing ill, the minde of strife, The mouth of speach, the body of despight; Hart thinks, eies sees, eares heares, mindes meditate, Mouth vtters both the soule and bodies hate. But Nature differing in each natures kinde, Makes differing hartes, each hart, differing thought, Some hath shee made to see, some follie blinde, Some famous, some obscure, some good, some nought. So these which differeth in each natures reason, Had natures time, when time was out of season. [Verse] 16 (Quoth they) he doth reprooue our hart of thinking, Our eies of sight, our eares of hearing ill, Our minds, our hearts in meditation linking, Our mouthes in speaking of our bodies will; Because hart, sight, and minde do disagree, Heel'd make heart, sight, and mind of their decree. Hee saies, our hart is blinded with our eies, Our eies are blinded with our blinded hart, Our bodies on both parts defiled lies, Our mouthes the trumpets of our vices smart; Quoth hee, God is my Father, I his sonne, His waies I take, your wicked waies I shun. [Verse] 17 As meditated wrongs are deeper plaste, Within the deepe crue of a wronged minde, So meditated wordes is neuer past, Before their sounds a setled harbour finde; The wicked answering to the latter words, Begins to speake as much as speach affords. One tong must answer other tongues replie, Beginning boasts, requires an ending fall; Wordes liuely spoke, do somtimes wordles dye, If not, liue Ecchoes vnto speeches call; Let not the shadow smother vp the deed, The outward leafe differs from inward seed. [Verse] 18 The shape and shewe of substance and effect, Doth shape the substance in the shadowes hue, And shadowe put in substance, will neglect The wonted shadowe of not being true: Let substance followe substance, showe a showe, And let not substance for the shadowe goe. Hee that could giue such admonition, Such vaunting wordes, such words confirming vaunts, As if his tongue had mounted to ambition, Or clim'd the turrets which vaine-glory haunts: Now let his father, if he be his sonne, Vndoe the knot which his prowd boasts haue spun. [Verse] 19 Wee are his enimies, his chaine our hands, Our wordes his fetters, and our hart his caue, Our sterne embracements are his seruile bands, Where is the helper nowe which he should haue? In prison like himselfe, not to be found, Hee wanteth helpe himselfe to be vnbound. Then sith thy father beares it patiently, To suffer torments, griefe, rebuke, and blame, Tis needfull thou shouldst beare equallity, To see if meekenesse harbour in thy name, Help father, for thy sonne in prison lies, Helpe sonne, or else thy helples father dies. Uerse 20 Thus is the righteous God and righteous man, Drownde in obliuion with this vices raigne, God wanteth power (say they) of what we can, The other would performe that which is vaine; Both faultie in one fault, and both alike, Must haue the stroke which our lawes iudgements strike He calls himselfe a sonne, from heauens descent, What can earths force aualie gainst heauens defence? His life by immortalitie is lent: Then how can punishment his wrath incense? Though death her selfe in his arraignment decke, He hath his lifes preseruer at a becke. Uerse 21 As doth the Basiliske with poysoned sight, Blinde euery function of a mortall eye, Disarme the bodies powers of vitall might, Rob heart of thought, make liuing life to die: So doth the wicked with their vices looke, Infect the spring of clearest vertues brooke. This Basiliske mortalities chiefe foe, And to the hearts long-knitted arterie; Doth sometime perish at her shadowes showe, Poysning her selfe with her owne poysoned eie: Needs must the sting fall out with ouer-harming, Needs must the tong burne out in ouer-warming. Uerse 22 So fares it with the practisers of vice, Laden with many venomous adders stings, Sometimes are blinded with their owne deuice, And tunes that song which their destruction sings; Their mischeife blindeth their mischeiuous eies, Like Basiliskes which in their shadow dies. They goe and yet they cannot see their feete, Like blinded pilgrimes in an vnknowen way, Blind in perceiuing things which be most meete, But neede nor sight nor guide to goe astray; Tel them of good, they cannot vnderstand, But tell them of a mischeife, that's at hand. Ve. 23 24 The Basiliske, was made to blind the sight, The adder for to sting, the worme to creepe, The viper to deuoure, the dog to bite, The nightingale to wake when others sleepe; Onely man differs from his makers will, Vndoing what is good, and doing ill. A god-like face he had, a heauenly hue, Without corruption, image without spottes, But now is metamorphosed anewe, Full of corruption, image full of blottes; Blotted by him that is the plot of euill, Vndone, corrupted, vanquisht by the deuill. Chapter III. Uerse 1 Bvt euery cloude can not hide Phœbus face, Nor shut the casement of his liuing flame, Nor is there euery soule which wanteth grace, Nor euery hart seducde with mischiefs name; Life cannot liue without corruption, World cannot be without destruction. Nor is the body all corrupt, or world Bent wholie vnto wickednes assault, The adder is not alwaies seene vncurlde, Nor euery soule found guiltie in one fault; Some good, some bad, but those whom vertues guard, Heauen is their hauen, comfort their reward. [Verse] 2 3 Thrice happy habitation of delight, Thrice happy step of immortalitie, Thrice happy soules to gaine such heauenly sight, Springing from heauens perpetuitie; Oh peacefull place, but oh thrice peacefull soules, Whom neither threats, nor strife, nor wars controls They are not like the wicked, for they liue, Nor they, like to the righteous, for they die; Each of their liues a differing nature giue, One thinkes that life endes with mortalitie, And that the righteous neuer liue againe, But die as subiects to a grieuous paine. [Verse] 4 What labouring soule refuseth for to sweat, Knowing his hire, his paiment, his reward? To suffer winters colde, and summers heate, Assured of his labours due regard? The Bee with summers toile will lade her hiue, In winters frost to keepe herselfe aliue. And what diuinest spirit would not toile, And suffer many torments, many paines, This worlds destruction, heauie laboures foile, When heauen is their hire, heauens ioy their gaines? Who would not suffer torments for to die, When deaths reward is immortalitie? [Verse] 5 Paine is the entrance to eternall ioy, Death endeth life, and death beginneth life, Beginneth happy, endeth in annoy, Begins immortall peace, ends mortall strife; Then seeing death and paines bring ioy and heauen, What need we feare deaths pain when life is giuen? Say sicknes or infirmities disease, (As many harmes hang ouer mortall heades) Should be his worlds reward, yet heauen hath ease, A salue to cure, and quiet resting beds; God maketh in earths world, lament our pleasure. That in heau?s world, delight might be our treasure Uerse 6 Faire may the shadow bee, the substance foule, After the triall followeth the trust, The clearest skinne may haue the soulest soule, The purest golde will sooner take the ruste: The brooke though nere so cleare may take some soile, The hart thogh nere so strong may take some foile. Wouldst thou be counted iust? make thy selfe iust, Oh purifie thy mire-bespotted heart, For god doth trie thy actions ere he trust, Thy faith, thy deeds, thy wordes, and what thou art, He will receiue no mud, for clearest springs, Nor thy vnrighteous wordes for righteous things. Verse 7 As God is perfit God, and perfit good, So hee accepteth none but perfit mindes, They euer prosper, flourish, liue, and bud, Like blessed plants, far from destructions winds: Still bud, nere fade, still flourish, nere decay, Stil rise, nere fall, still spring, nere fade away. Who would not couet to be such a plant? Who would not wish to stand in such a ground? Sith it doth neither fruit nor blessing want, Nor ought which in this plant might not be found; They are the righteous which enioye this earth, The figure of an euer-bearing birth. Uerse 8 The small is alwayes subiect to the great, The yong to him which is of elder time, The lowest place vnto the highest seate, And pale-facde Phœbe to bright Phœbus clime, Vice is not gouerner of vertues place, But blushes for to see see so bright a face. Vertue is chiefe, and vertue will be chiefe, Chiefe good, and chiefe Astræa, Iustice mate, Both for to punish and to yeeld reliefe, And haue dominion ouer euery state: Torghit the wrongs which wickednes hath done, Deliuering Nations from life-lasting mone. Verse 9 Oh you whose causes plungeth in despaire, Sad facde petitioners with griefes request: What seeke you? heeres nor Iustice, nor her heire, But woe and sorrow with deaths dumbe arrest: Turne vp your woe blinde eyes vnto the skie, There sits the Iudge can yeeld you remedie. Trust in his power, he is the truest God, True God, true Iudge, true Iustice, and true guide; All trueth is placed in his trueths abode, All vertues seated at his vertuous side: He will regarde your sute, and ease your plaint, And mollifie your miseries constraint. [Verse] 10 Then shall you see the Iudges of the earth, Summoned with the trumpet of his ire, To giue account and reckning from their birth, Where worthy or vnworthy of their hire: The godly shall receiue their labours triall, The wicked shall receiue their ioyes deniall. They which did sleepe in sinne, and not regarded The poore mans fortune, prostrate at their feete, Euen as they dealt, so shall they be rewarded, When they their toyled soules destruction meet, From Iudges they petitioners shall be, Yet want the sight which they do sue to see. [Verse] 11 That labour which is grounded on delight, That hope which reason doth enrich with hap, That merite which is placde in wisedomes might, Secure from mischiefes baite, or follies clap: Wits labour, reasons hope, and wisedomess merit, All three in one, make one thrice happy spirit. Why set I happinesse fore mortall eyes, Which couets to be drencht in misery? Mantling their foolish mindes in follies guise, Despising wisedomes perpetuitie: Sins labour, follies hope, and vices merit, These three in one, make a thrice cursed spirit. Uerse 5 Vaine hope must needs consist in what is vaine; All foolish laboures flowes from follies teares, Vnprofitable workes proceed from paine, And paine ill labours duest guerdon beares: Their vanities in one, and one in three, Make three paines one, and one vncertaintie, A wicked King, makes a more wicked land, Heads once infected, soone corrupts the feete, If the tree falls, the branches cannot stand, Nor children, bee their parents indiscreet; The man infects the wife, the wife the childe, Like birdes, which in one nest bee all defilde. Uerse 6 The field which neuer was ordainde to beare, Is happier farre, then a still tilled ground, This sleepes with quietnes in euery yeare, The other curst if any tares bee found, The barren happier then shee that beares, This brings foorth ioye, the other tares and teares. The Eunuch neuer lay in vices bed, The barren woman, neuer brought foorth sin, These two in heauens happines are led, Shee fruite in soule, hee fruite in faith doth win: O rare and happy man, for euer blest, O rare and happy woman, heauens guest. [Verse] 7 Who seekes to reape, before the corne be ripe? Who lookes for haruest among winters frost? Or who in greife, will followe pleasures pipe? What mariner can saile vppon the coast? That which is done in time, is done in season, And things done out of time, is out of reason. The glorious labour is in doing good, In times obseruance, and in natures will, Whose fruite is also glorious for our foode, If glory may consist in labours skill: Whose roote is wisdome, which shal neuer wither, But spring, and sprout, and loue, and liue together. Uerse 2 But euery ground doth not beare blessed plants, Nor euery plant brings foorth expected frute, What this same ground may haue, another wants, Nor are all causes answered with one sute: That tree whose roote is found, whose grounding strong, May firmely stand when others lie along. View natures beautie, marke her chaunging hue, Shee is not alwaies foule, nor alwaies faire, Chaste and vnchaste she is, true and vntrue, And some springs from her in a lustfull aire, And these adulterers be, whose seede shall perish, Neuer shall lust and wickednes long florish. Uerse 5 Although the flint be hard, the water soft, Yet is it molifide with lightest drops, Hard is the water, when the wind's aloft, Small things in time may vanquish greatest stops: The longer growes the tree, the greater mosse, The longer soile remaines, the more the drosse. The longer that the wicked liues on earth, The greater is their paine, their sin, their shame; The greater vices raigne, and vertues dearth, The greater goodnes lacke, and mischiefes name; When in their youth no honour they could get, Olde age could neuer pay so yong a debt. Uerse 6 To place an honour in dishonours place, Were but to make disparagement of both, Both enimies they could not brooke the case, For honor to subuert dishonors growth: Dishonor will not chaunge for honours roome, Shee hopes to stay after their bodies doome. Or liue they long, or die they sodainly, They haue nor hope, nor comfort of rewarde, Their hope of comfort is iniquitie, The barre by which they from their ioyes are bard: O olde newe end, made to begin newe griefe, O new beginning, end of old reliefe. Chapter IV. Verse 1 If happines may harbour in content, If life in loue, if loue in better life; Then vnto many happines is lent, And long departed ioy might then be rife: Some happy if they liue, some if they dye, Happy in life, happy in tragedy. Content is happines, because content, Barenes and barrennes is vertues grace, Bare, because wealth to pouertie is bent, Barren, in that it scornes ill fortunes place: The barren earth is barren of her tares, The barren woman barren of her cares. Uerse 2 The soule of vertue is eternitie, All-filling essence of diuinest rage, And vertues true eternall memory, Is barrennes, her soules eternall gage: O happy soule that is engaged there, And pawnes his life that barren badge to weare. See how the multitude with humble harts, Lies prostrate for to welcome her returne; See how they mourne and waile when she departs See how they make their teares her trophees vrne: Being present they desire her, being gone, Their hot desire is turnde to hoter moane. Uerse 3 As euery one hath not one natures mould, So euery one hath not one natures minde; Some think that drosse which others take for golde, Each difference commeth from a differing kinde: Some do despise what others do imbrace, Some praise the thing which others do disgrace. The barren doth embrace their barrennesse, And holde it as a vertue worthy meede: The other calles conception happinesse, And holde it as a vertue worthy deede: The one is firmely grounded on a rocke, The other billows game and tempests mocke. Uerse 4 Sometime the nettle groweth with the rose, The nettle hath a sting, the rose a thorne, This stings the hand, the other prickes the nose, Harming that scent which her sweete birth had borne; Weeds among herbs, herbs among weeds are found Tares in the mantle of a corny ground. The nettles growth is fast, the roses slow, The weeds outgrow the herbs, the tares the corne, These may be well compared to vices show, Which couers for to grow ere it be borne: As greatest danger doth pursue fast going, So greatest danger doth ensue fast growing. Verse 5 The tallest Cedar hath the greatest winde, The highest tree is subiect vnto falles, High soaring Eagles soone are strucken blinde, The tong must needes be hoarse with many calles: The wicked thinking for to touch the skie, Are blasted with the fier of heauens eie. So like ascending and descending aire, Both duskie vapours from two humerous cloudes, Lies withered the glory of their faire, Vnpleasant branches wrencht in follies floudes: Vnprofitable fruites like to a weede, Made onely to infect, and not to feede. Verse 6 Made for to make a fast, and not a feast, Made rather for infection than for meate, Not worthy to be eaten of a beast, Thy taste so sower, thy poyson is so great: Thou mayst be well compared to a tree, Because thy branches are as ill as thee. Thou hast begot thine owne confusion, The witnesses of what thou dost beginne, Thy doomers in thy lifes conclusion, Which will vnaskt and askt reueale thy sinne: Needs must the new hatched birds bewray the nest, When they are nursed in a step-dames breast. Uerse 7 But righteousnes is of another sex, Her roote is from an euerlasting seede, No weake-vnable grounding doth connex, Her neuer-limited memorialles deed: She hath no branches for a tempests pray, No deedes, but scornes to yeeld vnto decay. She hath no withered fruit, no shew of store, But perfect essence of a compleate power, Say that she dies to world, she liues the more, As who so righteous but doth waite deaths hower? Who knowes not death to be the way to rest? And he that neuer dies is neuer blest. Uerse 8 Happy is he that liues, twice he that dies, Thrice happy he which neither liu'd, nor died, Which neuer saw the earth with mortall eies, Which neuer knew what miseries are tried: Happy is life, twice happy is our death, But three times thrise he, which had neuer breath. Some thinkes that pleasure is atchieude by yeares, Or by maintaining of a wretched life, When, out alas, it heapeth teares on teares, Griefe vpon griefe, strife on beginning strife: Pleasure is weake, if measured by length, The oldest ages hath the weaker strength. Verse 9 Three turnings are containde in mortal course, Old, meane, and yong; meane, and old brings age, The youth hath strength, the meane decaying force, The old are weake, yet strong in angers rage: Three turnings in one age, strong, weak, &amp; weaker, Yet age, nor youth, is youths or ages breaker. Some sayes that youth is quicke in iudging causes, Some sayes that age is witty, graue, and wise. I holde of ages side with their applauses, Which iudges with their hearts, not with their eyes: I say graue wisedome lies in grayest heads, And vndefiled liues in ages beds. Verse 10 God is both graue and old, yet yong and new, Graue because aged, aged because yong; Long youth may wel be called ages hew, And hath no differing sound vpon the tongue: God old, because eternities are old, Yong, for eternities one motion hold. Some in their birth, some dies when they are borne, Some borne, and some abortiue, yet all die, Some in their youth, some in old age forlorne, Some, neyther yong nor old, but equally: The righteous, when he liueth with the sinner, Doth hope for death, his better lifes beginner. Uerse 11 The swine delights to wallow in the mire, The giddy drunkard in excesse of wine, He may corrupt the purest reasons gire, And shee turne vertue into vices signe: Mischiefe is mire, and may infect that spring, Which euery flowe and ebbe of vice doth bring. Fishes are oft deceiued by the baite, The baite-deceiuing fish doth fish deceiue; So righteous are allurde by sins deceit, And oft inticed into sinners weaue: The righteous be as fishes to their gin, Beguilde, deceiude, allured into sin. Verse 12 The fisher hath a baite deceiuing fish, The fowler hath a net deceiuing fowles, Both wisheth to obtaine their snaring wish, Obseruing time like night-obseruing owles: The fisher layes his baite, fowler his net, He hopes for fish, the other birds to get. This fisher is the wicked, vice his baite, This fowler is the sinner, sinne his net, The simple-righteous falles in their deceit, And like a prey, a fish, a fowle beset: A baite, a net, obscuring what is good, Like fish and fowle tooke vp for vices food. Uer. 13 14 But baites, nor nets, gins, nor beguiling snares, Vice, nor the vicious sinner, nor the sin Can shut the righteous into prisons cares, Or set deceiuing baites to mew them in: They know their liues deliuerer, heauens God, Can breake their baites and snares with iustice rod. When vice abounds on earth, and earth in vice, Then vertue keepes her chamber in the skie, To shun the mischiefe which her baites intice, Her snares, her nets, her guiles, her companie: Assoone as mischeife raignes vpon the earth, Heauen calls the righteous to a better birth. Uerse 15 The blinded eies can neuer see the way, The blinded heart can neuer see to see, The blinded soule doth alwayes go astray, All three want sight, in being blinde all three: Blinde and yet see, they see and yet are blinde, The face hath eies, buy eyelesse is the minde. They see with outward sight Gods heauenly grace, His grace, his loue, his mercy on his Saints, With outward faced eie, and eied face, Their outward body inwarde soule depaintes: Of hearts chiefe eye they chiefely are bereft, And yet the shadowe of two eyes are left. Uerse 16 Some blinded be in face, and some in soule, The faces eyes are not incurable, The other wanteth healing to be whole, Or seemes to some to be indurable: Looke in a blinded eie, bright is the glasse, Though brightnes banished from what it was. So (quoth the righteous) are these blinded hearts, The outward glasse is cleare, the substance darke, Both seeme as if one tooke the others parts, Yet both in one haue not one brightnes sparke: The outwarde eye, is but destructions reader, Wanting the inwarde eye to be the leader. Verse 17 Our body may be calde a common-weale, Our head the chiefe, for reason harbours there, From thence comes hearts and soules vnited zeale, All else inferiours be, which stande in feare, This common-weale rul'd by discretions eye, Liues likewise if shee liue, dies if shee die. Then how can weale, or wealth common, or proper, Long stand, long flowe, long flourish, long remaine, When wail is weales, &amp; stelth is welths chiefe stopper; When sight is gone which neuer comes againe: The wicked sees the righteous loose their breath, But knowe not what rewarde they gaine by death. Uer. 18 19 Though blinde in sight, yet can they see to harme, See to despise, see to deride and mocke, But their reuenge lies in Gods mighty arme, Scorning to chuse them for his chosen flocke: He is the shepheard, godly are his sheepe, They wake in ioy, these in destruction sleepe. The godly sleepe in eies, but wake in hearts, The wicked sleepe in hearts, but wake in eies; These euer-wake eyes are no sleepie partes, These euer sleepe, for sleepe is hearts disguise: Their waking eies do see their hearts lament, While heart securely sleepes in eyes content. Uerse 20 If they awake, sleepes image doth molest them, And beates into their waking memories, If they doe sleepe, ioy-waking doth detest them, Yet beates into their sleeping arteries: Sleeping or waking they haue feare on feare, Waking or sleeping they are ne're the neare. If waking they remember what they are, What sins they haue committed in their waking, If sleeping they forget tormentings fare, How ready they haue beene in mischiefes making: When they awake, their wickednes betrayes them, When they do sleepe, destruction dismayes them. Chapter V. Uerse 1 As these two slumbers haue two contraries, One slumber in the face, one in the minde, So their two casements two varieties, One vnto heauen, and one to hell combinde: The face is flattery, and her mansion hell, The minde is iust, this doth in heauen dwell. The face heauing her heauie eie-lids vp, From foorth the chamber of eternall night, Sees vertue holde plenties replenisht cup, And boldly stands in Gods and heauens sight: Shee opening the windowes of her brest, Sees how the wicked rest in their vnrest. Verse 2 3 Quoth shee, those whom the curtaine of decay, Hath tragically summoned to paine, Were once the cloudes, and clouders of my day, Deprauers and depriuers of my gaine; The wicked hearing this descending sound, Feare strucke their lims to the pale-clothed ground. Amazed at the freedome of her words; Their tongue-tide accents droue them to dispaire, And made them change their mindes to woes records, And say within themselues, lo what wee are: We haue had vertue in derisions place, And made a parable of her disgrace. Uerse 4 See where she fits enthronizde in the skie, See, see, her labours crowne vpon her head, See how the righteous liue which erst did die, From death to life with vertues loadstarre led, See those whome we derided, they are blest, They heauens, not hels, we hells, not heauens guest. We thought the righteous had beene furies sonne, With inconsiderate speech, vnstayed way, We thought that death had his dishonour wonne, And would haue made his life destructions pray: But we were mad, they iust, we fooles, they wise, We shame, they praise, we losse, they haue the prise. Verse 5 We thoght th? fools, when we our selues were fooles We thoght them mad, when we our selues were mad, The heate which sprang from them, our follie cooles, We find in vs, which we but thought they had: We thought their end had beene dishonors pledge, They but surueyd the place, we made the hedge. We see how they are blest, how we are curst, How they accepted are, and we refusde, And how our bands are tied, their bands are burst, Our faults are hourely blamde, their faults excusde: See how heauens gratulate their welcomd sight, Which comes to take possession of their right. Uerse 6 But oh, too late we see our wickednesse, Too late we lie in repentant tombe, Too late we smoothe olde haires with happinesse, Too late we seeke to ease our bodies doome: Now falshoode hath aduauncde her forged banner, Too late wee seeme to verefie truths manner. The sunne of righteousnes which should haue shinde, And made our hearts the cabines of his East, Is now made cloudy night through vices winde, And lodgeth with his downefall in the west: That summers day which shuld haue bin nights bar Is now made winter in her icie carre, Verse 7 Too much our feet haue gone, but neuer right, Much labour we haue tooke, but none in good, We wearied our selues with our delight, Endangering our selues to please our moode: Our feete did labour much, twas for our pleasure, We wearied our selues, twas for our leasure. In sinnes perfection was our labour spent, In wickednes preferment we did haste, To suffer perills wee were al content, For the aduancement of our vices past: Throgh many dangerous waies our feet haue gone, But yet the way of God we haue not knowne. Uerse 8 9 Wee which haue made our harts a sea of pride, With huge risse billowes of a swelling minde, With tossing tumults of a flowing tide, Leauing our laden bodyes plungde behinde; What trafficke haue we got? our selues are drownd, Our soules in hell, our bodies in the ground. Where are our riches now? like vs consumde, Where is our pompe? decaide, wher's glory? dead; Where is the wealth of which wee all presumde? where is our profit? gone, our selues? misled: All these are like to shadowes what they were, There is nor wealth, nor pompe, nor glory here. Verse 10 The diall giues a caueat of the houre, Thou canst not see it go, yet it is gone, Like this the diall of thy fortunes power, Which fades by stealth till thou art left alone. Thy eies may well perceiue thy goods are spent, Yet can they not perceiue which way they went. Lo, eu'ne as ships sailing on Thetis lap, Plowes vp the furrowes of hard grounded waues, Enforced for to go by Eoles clap, Making with sharpest teeme the water graues: The ship once past, the trace cannot be found, Although shee digged in the waters ground. Uerse 11 Or as an Eagle with her soaring wings, Scorning the dusty carpet of the earth, Exempt from all her clogging gesses, flings Vp to the ayre, to shew her mounting birth: And euery flight doth take a higher pitch, To haue the golden sunne her wings enrich. Yet none can see the passage of her flight, But onely heare her houering in the skie, Beating the light winde with her being light, Or parting through the ayre where she might flie: The eare may heare, the eye can neuer see, What course she takes, or where she meanes to bee. Uerse 12 Or as an arrowe which is made to goe, Through the transparent and coole-blowing ayre, Feeding vpon the forces of the bowe, Else forcelesse lies in wanting her repaire: Like as the branches when the tree is lopt, Wanteth the forces which they forcelesse cropt. The arrow being fed with strongest shot, Doth part the lowest elementall breath, Yet neuer separates the soft ayres knot, Nor neuer woundes the still-foote windes to death: It doth seioyne and ioyne the ayre together, Yet none there is can tell, or where, or whither. Verse 13 So are our liues, now they beginne, now end, Now liue, now die, now borne, now fit for graue, As soone as we haue breath, so soone we spend, Not hauing that which our content would haue: As ships, as birds, as arrowes, all as one, Euen so the traces of our liues are gone. A thing not seene to go, yet going seene, And yet not shewing any signe to go; Euen thus the shadowes of our liues haue beene, Which shewes to fade, and yet no vertues shew: How can a thing consumde with vice be good? Or how can falshoode be are true vertues foode? Uerse 14 Vaine hope to thinke that wickednes hath bearing When she is drowned in obliuions sea, Yet can she not forget presumptions wearing, Nor yet the badge of vanities decay: Her fruites are cares, her cares are vanities, Two, both in one destructions liueries. Vaine hope is like a vane turnde with each winde, Tis like a smoake scattred with euery storme, Like dust, sometime before, sometime behinde, Like a thin fome made in the vainest forme: This hope is like to them which neuer stay, But comes, and goes againe, all in one day. Uerse 15 View Natures gifts, some gifts are rich, some poore, Some barren grounds there are, som clothd with fruit, Nor hath all nothing, nor hath all her store, Nor can all creatures speake, nor are all mute: All die by nature, being borne by nature, So all change feature, being borne with feature. This life is hers, this dead, dead is her power, Her bounds begins, and ends in mortall state, Whom she on earth accounteth as her flower, May be in heauen condemnde of mortall hate: But he whom vertue iudges for to liue, The Lord his life and due reward will giue. Uerse 16 The seruant of a king, may be a king, And he that was a king, a seruile slaue; Swans before death a funerall dirge do sing, And waues their wings agen ill fortunes waue. He that is lowest in this lowly earth, May be the highest in celestiall birth. The rich may be vniust, in being rich, For riches do corrupt and not correct, The poore may come to highest honours pitch, And haue heauens crowne for mortall lifes respect: Gods hands shall couer them from al their foes, Gods arme defend them from misfortunes blowes. Verses 17 18 19 20 His hand eternitid; his arme, his force, His armour zelousie, his breast-plate heauen, His helmet iudgement, iustice, and remorce, His shield is victories immortall steauen: The world his challenge, and his wrath his sword, Mischiefe his foe, his ayde his gospels word. His arme doth ouerthrowe his enimie, His breast-plate, sinne, his helmet death and hell, His shield preparde against mortallitie, His sword gainst them which in the world do dwell: So shall vice, sinne, and death, world and the deuill, Be slaine by him which slayeth euery euill. Uerse 21 All heauen shall be in armes against earths world, The sunne shall dart foorth fire commixt with bloud, The blazing starres from heauen shall be hurlde, The pale-facde moone against the Ocean floud: Then shall the thundring chambers of the skie, Be lightned with the blaze of Titans eie. The cloudes shall then be bent like bended bowes, To shoote the thundring arrowes of the ayre, Thicke haile and stones shall fall on heauens foes, And Tethis ouerflowe in her despayre: The moone shall ouer-fill her horny hood, With Neptunes Oceans ouer-flowing flood. Uerse 22 The winde shall be no longer kept in caues, But burst the iron cages of the clouds? And Æole shall resigne his office staues, Suffering the windes to combate with the flouds: So shall the earth with seas be paled in, As erst it hath beene ouerflowde with sin. Thus shall the earth weepe for her wicked sonnes, And curse the concaue of her tyred wombe, Into whose hollowe mouth the water runnes, Making wet wildernes her driest tombe; Thus, thus, iniquitie hath raignd so long, That earth on earth is punisht for her wrong. Chapter VI. Verse 1 2 After this conflict betweene God and man, Remorce tooke harbour in Gods angry breast, Astræa to be pitifull began, All heauenly powers to lie in mercies rest: Forth with the voice of God did redescend, And his Astræa warnde all to amend. To you I speake, (quoth shee) heare, learne, and marke, You that be Kings, Iudges, and Potentates, Giue ere, (I say,) wisedome your strongest arke, Sends me as messenger, to end debates: Giue eare, (I say) you Iudges of the earth, Wisedome is borne, seeke out for wisedomes birth. Verse 3 This heauenly ambassage from wisedomes tong. Worthy the volume of all heauens skie, I bring as messenger to right your wrong, If so her sacred name might neuer die: I bring you happy tidings, she is borne, Like golden sunne-beames from a siluer morne. The Lord hath seated you in iudgements seat, Let wisedome place you in discretions places, Two vertues, one, will make one vertue great, And drawe more vertues with attractiue faces: Be iust and wise, for God is iust and wise, He thoughts, he words, he words, and actions tries. Uerse 4 5 If you neglect your offices decrees, Heape new lament on long-tosst miseries, Doe and vndoe by reason of degrees, And drowne your sentences in briberies: Fauour and punish, spare and keepe in awe, Set and vnset, plant and supplant the lawe. Oh bee assur'd there is a Iudge aboue, Which will not let iniustice flourish long, If tempt him, you, your owne temptation moue, Proceeding from the iudgement of his tong: Hard iudgement shal he haue which iudgeth hard, And he that barreth others shall be bar'd. Uerse 6 For God hath no respect of rich from poore, For he hath made the poore, and made the rich, Their bodies be alike, though their mindes soare, Their difference nought, but in presumptions pitch: The carcasse of a King is kept from foule, The Begger yet may haue the cleaner soule. The highest men do beare the highest mindes, The cedars skorne to bowe, the mushromes bend, The hiest often superstition blindes, But yet their fall is greatest in the end: The windes haue not such power of the grasse, Because it lowly stoopeth when as they passe. Verse 7 8 The olde should teach the yong obseruance way, But now the yong doth teach the elder grace; The shrubs doe teach the Cedars to obay, These yeelde to winds, but these the winds out-face: Yet he that made the windes to cease and blowe, Can make the highest fall, the lowest growe. He made the great to stoop as well as small, The lions to obay as other beasts, He cares for all alike, yet cares for all, And lookes that all should answere his beheasts: But yet the greater hath the sorer triall, If once he findes them with his lawes deniall. Verse 9 Be warnde you tyrants at the fall of pride, You see how surges chaunge to quiet calme; You see both flowe and ebbe in follies tide, How fingers are infected by their palme: This may your caucat be, you being kinges, Infect your subiects, which are lesser things. Ill sents of vice once crept into the head, Doth pearce into the chamber of the braine, Making the outward skin diseases bed, The inward powers as nourishers of paine: So if that mischeife raignes in wisedomes place, The inward thought lies figured in the face. Uerse 10 Wisdome should clothe her selfe in Kings attire, Being the portrature of heauens Queene, But tyrantes are no Kings, but mischiefes mire, Not sage, but shewes of what they should haue beene: They seeke for vice, and how to go amis, But doe not once regard what wisdome is. They which are Kings, by name are Kings by deed, Both rulers of them selues and of their land, They know that heau'n is vertues duest meed, And holines is knit in holy band: These may be rightly called by their name, whose words and works are blaz'd in wisedomes flame. Verse 11 To nurse vp crueltie with milde aspect, Were to begin, but neuer for to end, Kindenes with tygers neuer takes effect, Nor proffered frendship with a foe-like friend: Tyrants and tygers haue all naturall mothers, Tyrants her sonnes, tygers the tyrants brothers. No words delight can moue delight in them, But rather plow the traces of their ire, Like swine that take the durt defore the gem, And skorns that pearle which they should most desire: But Kings whose names proceed fr? kindnes sound, Do plant their harts &amp; thoghts on wisd?s ground. Uer. 12 13 A grounding euer moist, and neuer dry, An euer fruitfull earth, no fruitlesse way, In whose deare wombe the tender springs dolye, which euer flowes, and neuer ebbes away; The sunne but shines by day, she day and night, Doth keepe one stayed essence of her light. Her beams are conducts to her substance view, Her eye is adamants attractiue force, A shadowe hath shee none, but substance true, Substance out liuing life of mortall corse. Her sight is easie vnto them which loue her, Her finding easie vnto them which proue her. Uer. 14 The far fet chastitie of female sex, Is nothing but allurement into lust, Which will forsweare and take, scorne and annex, Denie and practise it, mistrust, and trust: Wisedome is chast and of another kinde, She loues, she likes, and yet not lustfull blinde. She is true loue, the other loue a toy, Her loue hath eyes, the other loue is blinde, This doth proceed from God, this from a boy, This constant is, the other vaine combinde: If longing passions follow her desire, She offereth her selfe, as labours hire Uerse 15 She is not coyish shee, won by delay, With sighs and passions, which all louers vse, With hot affection, death, or lifes decay, With louers toyes, which might their loues excuse: Wisedome is poore, her dowrie is content, Shee nothing hath because shee nothing spent. She is not woo'd to loue, nor won by wooing, Nor got by labour, nor possest by paine, The gaine of her consists in honest doing, Her gaine is great, in that she hath no gaine: He that betimes followes repentance way, Sall meet with her his vertues worthy pay. Verse 16 To think vpon her, is to think of blisse, The very thought of her is mischiefes barre, Depeller of misdeeds which do amisse, The blot of vanitie, misfortunes scarre: Who wold not think; to reap such gain by thought? Who would not loue, when such a life is bought? If thought be vnderstanding, what is shee? The full perfection of a perfect power, A heauenly branch from Gods immortall tree, Which death, nor hell, nor mischiefe can deuoure: Her selfe is wisedome, and her thought is so, Thrice happie he which doth desire to know. Uerse 17 Shee manlike woes, men womenlike refuses, She offers loue, they offered loue denie, And hould her promises as loues abuses, Because she pleads with an indifferent eye: They thinke that she is light, vaine and vniust, When she doth plead for loue, and not for lust. Hard hearted men (quoth shee) can you not loue, Behold my substance, cannot substance please, Behold my feature; cannot feature moue? Can substance, nor my feature, helpe or ease? See heauens ioy, defigured in my face, Can neither heauen, nor ioy, turne you to grace? Uer. 18 19 Oh how desire swayes her pleading tong, Her tongue, her heart, her heart, her soules affection? Faine would she make mortalitie be strong, But mortall weaknes yeelds reiection: Her care is care of them, they carelesse are, Her loue loues them: they neither loue nor care. Faine would shee make them clients in her lawe, Whose laws assurance is immortall honour, But them, nor words, nor loue, nor care can awe, But still will fight vnder destructions bonner. Though immortalitie be their reward, Yet neither words, nor deeds will they regard. Uerse 20 Her tongue is hoarse with pleading, yet doth plead, Pleading for that which they should all desire, Their appetite is heauie made of lead, And lead can neuer melt without a fire: Her words are milde and cannot raise a heat, Whilst they with hard repulse her speeches beat. Requested they; for what they should request, Intreated they; for what they should intreat, Requested to enioye their quiet rest, Intreated like a sullen bird to eate: Their eies behold ioyes maker which doth make it, Yet must they be intreated for to take it. Verse 21 You whose delight is plac'd in honours game, Whose game, in maiesties imperiall throne, Maiesticke portratures of earthly fame, Releeuers of the poore in ages mone: If your content be seated on a crowne, Loue wisedome, and your state shall neuer downe. Her crownes are not as earthly diadems, But diapasans of eternall rest, Her essence comes not from terrestriall stems, But planted on the heauens immortall brest: If you delight in scepters and in raigning, Delight in her your crownes immortall gaining. Uerse 22 Although the shadowes of her glorious view, Hath beene as accessary to your eies, Now will I shew you the true substance hiew, And what she is, which without knowledge lies: From whence she is deriude, whence her discent, And whence the linage of her birth is lent. Now will I shew the skie, and not the cloude, The sunne, and not the shade, day, not the night, Tethis her selfe, not Tethis in her floud, Light, and not shadow of suppressing light: Wisedome her selfe true tipe of wisedomes grace, Shall be apparant before heart and face. Verse 23 Had I still fed you with the shade of life, And hid the sunne it selfe in enuies aire, My selfe might well be called natures strife, Striuing to cloude that which all cloudes impaire: But Enuy, haste thee hence, I loathe thy eie, Thy loue, thy life, thy selfe, thy company. Here is the banner of discretions name, Aduaunst on wisedomes euer-standing tower, Here is no place for enuie or her shame, For Nemesis, or blacke Mageraes power: He that is enuious, is not wisedomes frend, She euer liues, he dies when enuies end. Uer. 24 25 Happy, thrice happy land, where wisedome raignes, Happy, thrice happy king, whom wisedome swayes, Where neuer poore laments, or soules complaines, Where follie neuer keepes discretions wayes: That land, that king doth flourish, liue and ioy, Farre from ill fortunes reach, or sins annoy. That land is happy, that king fortunate, She in her dayes, he in his wisedomes force, For fortitude is wisedomes sociate: And wisedome truest fortitudes remorce: Be therefore rulde by wisedome, she is chiefe, That you may rule in ioy, and not in griefe. Chapter VII. Uerse 1 What am I? man, oh what is man? oh nought, What am I? nought, yes, what? sin &amp; debate, Three vices all in one, of one life bought, Man am I not, what then? I am mans hate: Yes man I am, man, because mortall, dead, Mortalitie my guide, by mischiefe led. Man, because like to man, man, because borne, In birth no man, a child, child, because weake, Weake, because weakned by ill fortunes scorne, Scorn'd, because mortall, mortall, in wrongs reake: My father like my selfe did liue on earth, I like my selfe, and him, folow his birth. Verse 2 My mothers matrice was my bodies maker, There had I this same shape of infamies, Shape, ah no shape, but substance mischiefes taker, In ten months fashion; months, ah miseries, The shame of shape, the very shape of shame, Calamitie my selfe lament my name. I was conceiude with seede, deceiude with sin, Deceiude, because my seede was sins deceit, My seede deceit, because it closde me in, Hemd me about, for sins and mischiefes baite: The seede of man did bring me into blood, And now I bring my selfe, in what? no good. Uerse 3 When I was borne, when I was, then I was, Borne? when? yet borne I was, but now I beare, Beare mine owne vices, which my ioyes surpasse, Beare mine owne burden full of mischiefes feare: When I was borne, I did not beare lament, But now vnborne, I beare what birth hath spent. When I was borne, my breath was borne to mee, The common aire which aires my bodies forme, Then fell I on the earth with feeble knee, Lamenting for my lifes ill fortunes storme: Making my selfe the index of my woe, Commencing what I could, ere I could goe. Uerse 4 5 Fed was I with lament as well as meat, My milke was sweet, but teares did make it sower, Meat and lament, milke and my teares I eat, As bitter herbs commixt with sweetest flower: Care was my swadling clothes as well as cloth, For I was swadled, and clothed in both. Why do I make my selfe more then I am? Why say I, I am nourished with cares, When euery one is clothed with the same, Sith as I fare my selfe, another fares? No King had any other birth then I, But waild his fortune with a watry eye. Verse 6 Say what is mirth, an entrance vnto woe, Say what is woe, an entrance vnto mirth, That which begins with ioy doth not end so, These go by chaunge, because a changing birth: Our birth is as our death, both barren, bare, Our entrance waile, our going out with care. Naked we came, into the world as naked, Wee had nor wealth nor riches to possesse, Now differ we, which difference riches maked, Yet in the end we naked nerethelesse: As our beginning is, so is our end, Naked and poore, which needs no wealth to spend. Uerse 7 Thus weighing in the ballance of my minde, My state, all states, my birth, all births alike, My meditated passions could not finde, One freed thought which sorrow did not strike: But knowing euery ill is curde by praier, My minde besought the Lord my griefes allaier. Wherefore I prayde, my praier tooke effect, And my effect was good, my good was gaine, My gaine was sacred wisedomes bright aspect, And her aspect in my respect did raigne: Wisedome that heau'nly spirit of content, Was vnto me from heau'n by praier sent. Uerse 8 A present far more worthy then a crowne, Because the crowne of an eternall rest, A present far more worthie then a throne, Because the throne of heau'n, which makes vs blest: The crowne of blisse, the throne of God is shee, Compared vnto heau'n, not earth to thee. Her foot-stoole is thy face, her face thy shame, Thy shame her liuing praise, her praise thy scorne, Thy scorne her loue, her loue thy merits blame, Thy blame her worth, her worth thy being borne: Thy selfe art drosse to her comparison, Thy valour weake vnto her garison. Uerse 9 To liken gold vnto her radiant face, Were likening day to night, and night to day, The Kings high seat, to the low subiects place, And heau'ns translucent breast, to earthly way: For what is golde? her scorne, her scorne? her ire, Melting that drosse, with nought but angers fire. In her respect tis dust, in her aspects Earth, in respect of her tis little grauell, As dust, as earth, as grauell she reiects, The hope, the gaine, the sight, the price, the trauell: Siluer, because inferiour to the other Is clay, which two she in one looke doth smother. Verse 10 Her sight I called health, her selfe my beautie, Health as my life, and beautie as my light, Each in performance of the others dutie, This curing griefe, this leading me aright: Two soueraigne eies, belonging to two places, This guides the soule, and this the body graces. The heart sicke soule, is cur'd by heart-strong health, The heart-strong health, is the soules brightest eye, The heart-sick body heal'd by beauties wealth, Two sunnie windolets of eithers skie, Whose beames cannot be clouded by reproach, Nor yet dismounted from so bright a coach. Uerse 11 What dowrie could I wish more then I haue? What wealth, what honour, more then I possesse? My soules request is mine, which I did craue, For sole redresse in soule, I haue redresse: The bodyly expences which I spend, Is lent by her, which my delight doth lend. Then I may call her author of my good, Sith good and goods are portions for my loue, I loue her well, who would not loue his food, His ioyes maintatiner, which all woes remoue? I richest am, because I doe possesse her, I strongest am, in that none can oppresse her. Uerse 12 It made me glad to thinke that I was rich, More gladder for to thinke that I was strong, For lowest mindes do couet highest pitch, As highest braues proceed from lowest tongue: Her first arriuall first did make me glad, Yet ignorant at first, first made me sad. Ioyfull I was, because I sawe her power, Wofull I was, because I knew her not, Glad that her face was in mine eies lockt bower, Sad that my senses neuer drew her plot I knew not that she was discretions mother, Though I profest my selfe to be her brother. Uerse 13 Like a rash wooer feeding on the lookes, Disgesting beauty apparitions show, Viewing the painted out-side of the bookes, And inward workes little regardes to know: So I, feeding my fancies with her sight, Forgot to make inquirie of her might. Externall powers I knew, riches I had, Internall powers I scarcely had discernd, Vntainedly I learned to be glad, Faining I hated, veritie I learnd: I was not enuious, learned to forsake her. But I was louing, learned for to take her. Uerse 14 And had I not, my treasure had bin lost, My losse, my perills hazard had proclaimde, My perill had my lifes destruction tost, My lifes destruction at my soule had aimde: Great perills hazarded from one poore losse, As greatest filth doth come with smallest drosse. This righteous treasure whoso rightly vseth, Shall be an heire in heau'ns eternitie, All earthly fruites her heretage excuseth, All happinesse in her felicitie: The loue of God consists in her embracing, The gifts of knowledge in her wisedomes placing. Verse 15 I speake as I am prompted by my mind, My soules chiefe agent, pleader of my cause, I speake these things, and what I speake I finde, By heau'ns iudgement, not mine owne applause: God he is iudge, I next, because I haue her, God he doth know, I next, because I craue her. Should I direct, and God subuert my tongue, I worthy were of an vnworthy name, Vnworthy of my right, not of my wrong, Vnworthy of my praise, not of my shame: But seeing God directs my tongue from missing, I rather looke for clapping than for hissing. Uerse 16 He is the prompter of my tongue and me, My tongue doth vtter what his tongue applies, He sets before my sight what I should see, He breathes into my heart his verities: He telles me what I thinke, or see, or heare, His tongue a part, my tongue a part doth beare. Our wordes he knowes, in telling of our hearts, Our hearts he knowes in telling of our words, All in his hands, words, wisedome, workes, and arts, And euery power which influence affords: He knowes what we will speake, what we will doe, And how our mindes and actions will goe. Ver. 17 18 The wisedome which I haue, is heauens gift, The knowledge which I haue, is Gods reward, Both presents my fore-warned sences lift, And of my preseruation had regard: This teaches me to know, this to be wise, Knowledge is wits, and wit is knowledge guise. Now know I, how the world was first created, How euery motion of the aire was framed, How man was made, the diuells pride abated, How times beginning, midst, and end was named: now know I time, times ch?ge, times date, times sho And when the seasons come, and when they goe. Ver. 19 20 I know the chaunging courses of the yeares, And the diuision of all differing climes, The situation of the stars and spheres, The flowing tides, and the flow-ebbing times: I know that euery yeare hath his foure courses, I know that euery course hath seuerall forces. I know that nature is in euery thing, Beasts furious, winds rough, men wicked are, whose thoghts their scurge, whose deeds their iugm?ts sting, Whose words and works their perill, and their care, I know that euery plant hath difference, I know that euery roote hath influence. Verse 21 True knowledge haue I got in knowing truth, True wisedome purchased in wisest wit, A knowledge fitting age, wit fitting youth, Which makes me yong, though olde with gaine of it; True knowledge haue I, and true wisedomes store, True hap, true hope, what wish, what wold I more? Known things I needs must know, sith not vnknown, My care is knowledge, she doth heare for me, All secrets know I more because not showne, My wisedome secret is, and her I see; Knowledge hath taught me how to heare knowne causes Wisedome hath taught me secrecies applauses. Uer. 22 23 Knowledge and wisedome knowne in wisest things, Is reasons mate, discretions centinell, More then a trine of ioyes, from vertues springs, More then one vnion, yet in vnion dwell, One for to guide the spring, sommer the other, One haruests nurse, the other winters mother. Foure mounts, and foure high mounters, all foure one, One holy vnion, one begotten life, One manifolde affection, yet alone, All one in peaces rest, all none in strife: Sure, stable, without care, hauing all power, Not hurtfull, doing good, (as one all foure.) Verse 24 This peacefull army of foure knitted soules, Is marching vnto peaces endles warre, Their weapons are discretions written roules, Their quarrell, loue, and amitie their iarre: Wisedome directorlis, captaine, and guide, All other take their places, side by side. Wisedome deuides the conflict of her peace, Into foure squadrons, of foure mutuall loues, Each bent to war, and neuer meanes to cease, Her wings of shot her disputation moues: Shee warres vnseene, and pacifies vnseene, Shee is wars victory, yet peaces Queene. Uerse 25 Shee is the martiall trumpet of alarmes, And yet the quiet rest in peaces night, Shee guideth martiall troupes, she honours armes, Yet ioyns she fight with peace, and peace with fight: Shee is the breath of Gods and heauens power, Yet peaces nurse, in being peaces flower. A flowing in of that which ebbeth out, An ebbing out of that which floweth in, Presumption she doth hate, in being stout, Humilitie though poore her fauours win: Shee is the influence of heauens flow, No filth doth follow her, where ere shee goe. Uerse 26 Shee is that spring, which neuer hath an ebbe, That siluer-coloured brooke, which hath no mud, That loome, which weaues, and neuer cuts the webbe, That tree which growes, and neuer leaues to bud: Shee constant is, vnconstancie her foe, Shee doth nor flow and ebbe, nor come and goe. Phœbus doth weepe, when watrie cloudes approach, Shee keeps her brightnes euerlastingly, Phœbe, when Phœbus shines forsakes nights coach, Hir day is night and day immortally: The vndefiled mirrour of renowne, The image of Gods power, her vertues crowne. Uer. 27 28 Discretion, knowledge, wit, and reasons skill, All foure are places in one only grace, They wisedome are, obedient to her will, All foure are one, one in all foures place: And wisedome being one, she can do all, Sith one hath foure, all subiect to one call. Her selfe remaining selfe, the world renewes, Renewing ages with perpetuall youth, Entring into the soules, which death pursues, Making th? Gods friends, which were frends to truth. If wisedome doth not harbour in thy minde, God loues thee not, and that thy soule shall finde. Ver. 29 30 For how canst thou be lead without thy light, How can thy eyles soule direct her way, If wanting her, which guides thy steps aright, Thy steps from night into a path of day? More beautifull then is the eye of heau'n, Guilding her selfe with her selfe-changing steau'n. The stars are twinckling handmaides to the moone, Both moone and stars, handmaids to wisdomes sunne, These shine at middest night, this at mid-noone, Each new begins their light, when each hath done: Pale-mantled night, followes red-mantled day, Vice followes both, but to her owne decay. Chapter VIII. [Verse 1] Who is the Empresse of the worlds confine, The Monarchesse of the foure cornerd earth, The Princesse of the seas, life without fine, Commixer of delight with sorowes mirth: What soueraigne is shee which euer raignes, Which Queene-like gouerns al, yet none c?strains? Wisedome, ô flie my spirit with that word, Wisedome, ô lodge my spirit in that name, Fly soule vnto the mansion of her lord, Although thy wings be sindged in her flame: Tell her my blacknes doth admire her beautie, Ile marie her in loue, serue her in dutie. Uerse 2 If marry hel; God is my father God, Christ is my brother, Angells are my kin, The earth my dowrie, heauen my aboade, My rule the world, my life without my sin: Shee is the daughter of immortall Ioue, My wife in heart, in thought, in soule, in loue. Happy for euer hee that thought in hart, Happy for euer he that heart in thought, Happy the soule of both which beares both part, Happy that loue which thoght, hart, soule, hath sought; The name of loue is happiest, for I loue her, Soule, heart, and thoughts, loues agents are to proue her. Uer. 3 Ye parents that would haue your children rulde, Here may they be instructed, rulde and taught: Ye children that would haue your parents schoolde, Feeding their wanton thirst with follies draught; See here the schoole of discipline erected, See here how yong and old are both corrected. Children, this is the Mistris of your blisse, Your schoolemistris reformer of your liues, Parents, you that do speake, thinke, do amisse, Heres she, which loues, and lifes direction giues: She teacheth that which God knowes to be true, She chuseth that, which God would chuse for you. Verse 4 What is our birth? poore, naked, needy, cold, What is our life? poore as our birth hath beene: What is our age? forlorne in being old. What is our end? as our beginnings scene: Our birth, our life, our age, our end is poore, what birth, what life, what age, what end hath more Made rich it is with vanities vaine show, If wanting wisedome it is follies game, Or like a bended, or vnbended bow, Ill fortunes scoffe it is, good fortunes shame: If wisedome be the riches of thy minde, Then can thy fortune see, not seeing blinde. Uerse 5 6 Then if good fortune doth begin thy state, Ill fortune cannot end what she begins, Thy fate at first will still remaine thy fate, Thy conduct vnto ioyes, not vnto sins: If thou the bridegroome art, wisedome the bride, Ill fortune cannot swimme against thy tide. Thou marrying her, dost marry more than she, Thy portion is not faculties, but blisse, Thou needst not teaching, for she teacheth thee, Nor no reformer she thy mistris is, The lesson which she giues thee for thy learning, Is euery vertues loue, and sins deseruing. Verse 7 Dost thou desire experience for to know? Why how can she be lesse than what she is? The growth of knowlege doth from wisdome grow, The growth of wisedome is in knowing this: Wisedome can tell all things, what things are past, What done, what vndone, what are doing last. Nay more, what things are come, what are to come, Or words, or works, or shews, or actions, In her braines table-booke she hath the summe, And knowes darke sentences solutions: She knowes what signes and wonders will ensue, And when successe of seasons will be new. Uer. 8 Who would not be a bridegroome? who not wed? Who would not haue a bride so wise, so faire? Who would not lie in such a peacefull bed? Whose canopy is heau'n, whose shade the aire: How can it be that any of the skies Can there be missing, where heau'ns kingdom lies? If care-sicke, I am comforted with ioy, If surfeting on ioy, she bids me care, Shee sayes that ouermuch will soone annoy, Too much of ioy, too much of sorrowes fare: She alwayes counsels me to keepe a meane, And not with ioy too fat, with griefe too leane. Verse 9 Faine would the shrub growe by the highest tree, Faine would the mushrome kisse the cedars barke: Faine would the seely worme a sporting be, Faine would the sparrow imitate the larke: Though I a tender shrub, a mushrome be, Yet couet I the honour of a tree. And may I not? may not the blossoms bud? Doth not the little seed make eares of corne? Doth not a sprig (in time) beare greatest wood? Doth not yong eu'nings make an elder morne? For wisedomes sake, I know, though be yong I shall haue praises from my elders tongue. Uerse 10 And as my growth doth rise, so shall my wit, And as my wit doth rise, so shall my growth, In wit I growe, both growths grow to be fit, Both fitting in one growth, be fittest both: Experience followes age, and nature youth, Some aged be in wit, though yong in ruth. The wisedome which I haue, springs from aboue, The wisedome from aboue, is that I haue, Her I adore, I reuerence, I loue, Shee's my pure soule, lockt in my bodies graue: The iudgement which I vse, from her proceedes, Which makes me maruelld at in all my deedes. Verse 11 Although mute silence tie my iudgements tongue, Sad secretarie of dumbe action, Yet shall they giue me place though I be yong, And stay my leisures satisfaction: Euen as a iudge which keeps his iudgements mute, When clients haue no answer of their sute. But if the closure of my mouth vnmeetes, And diues within the freedome of my words, They like petitioners tongues welcome greetes, And with attentiue eare heares my accords: But if my words into no limites goe, Their speech shall ebbe, mine in their ebbing flow. Uerse 12 And what of this vaine world, vaine hope vaine show Vaine glory seated in a shade of praise, Mortalities descent, and follies flow, The badge of vanity, the houre of daies, What glory is it for to be a King, When care is crowne, and crown is fortunes sling? Wisedome is immortalities alline, And immortalitie is wisedomes gaine, By her the heauens lineage is mine, By her I immortalitie obtaine, The earth is made immortall in my name, The heau'ns are made immortall in my fame. Uer. 13 14 Two spatious orbes of two as spatious climes, Shall be the heritage which I possesse, My rule in heau'n, directing earthly times, My raigne in earth, commencing earths redresse, One king made two, one crowne a double crowne, One rule two rules, one fame a twice renowne. What heauen is this, which euery thought containes, Wisedome my heau'n, my heau'n is wisedoms heau'n, What earth is this, wherein my bodie raines? Wisedome my earth, all rule from wisedome giu'n: Through her I rule, through her I do subdue, Through hir I raigne, through hir my empire grew. Verse 15 A rule, not tyrannie, a raigne, not blood, An empire, not a slaughter house of liues, A crowne, not crueltie in furies moode, A Scepter which restores, and not depriues: All made to make a peace and not a warre, By wisedome concords Queene, and discords barre. The coldest worde oft cooles the hottest threat, The tyrants menaces, the calmes of peace, Two coldes augmenteth one, two heates one heat, And makes both too extreame, when both encrease: My peacefull raigne shall conquer tyrants force, Not armes, but wordes, not battaile, but remorce, Uerse 16 Yet mightie shall I be though warre in peace, Strong though abilitie hath left his clime, And good, because my warres and battails cease, Or at the least lie smothered in their prime: The sence once digged vp with feares amaze, Doth rage vntam'd with follies senceles gaze. If wisedome doth not harbour in delight, It breakes the outward passage of the minde, Therfore I place my war in wisedomes might, Whose heauie labours easie harbours finde: Her company is pleasure, mirth, and ioy, Not bitternes, not mourning, not annoy, Uer. 17 18 When euery thought was ballanced by weight Within the concaue of my bodies scale, My heart and soule did holde the ballance streight, To see what thoght was ioy, what thoght was waile: But when I saw that griefe did weigh down plesure, I put in wisedome to augment her treasure. Wisedome the weight of immortallitie, Wisedome the ballance of all happinesse, Wisedome the weigher of felicitie, Wisedome the Paragon of blessednesse: When in her hands there lies such plenties store, Needs must her heart haue twice as much and more. Uer. 19 20 Her hart haue I conioyned with hir hand, Her hand hath she conioyned with my hart, Two soules, one soule, two hearts, one bodyes band, And two hands made of foure, by amours art: Was I not wise in chusing earthly life? Nay wise, thrice wise, in chusing such a wife? Was I not good? good; then the sooner bad, Bad, because earth is full of wickednes, Because my body is with vices clad, Anotomy of my sins heauines: As doth vnseemely clothes make the skin foule, So the sin-inked body blots the soule. Verse 21 Thus lay my hart plung'd in destructions mire, Thus lay my soule bespotted with my sin, Thus lay my selfe consum'd in my desire, Thus lay all parts ensnared in one gin: At last my hart mounting aboue the mud, Lay betweene hope and death, mischiefe, and good. Thus panting ignorant to liue or die, To rise or fall, to stand or else to sinke, I cast a fainting looke vnto the skie, And sawe the thought, which my poore hart did think Wisdome my thought at whose seene sight I prai'd, And with my hart, my minde, my soule, I said. Chapter IX. Uer. 1 2 3 O God of Fathers, Lord of heau'n and earth, Mercies true soueraigne, pitties portraiture, King of all kings, a birth surpassing birth, A life immortall, essence euer pure: Which with a breath ascending from thy thought, Hast made the heau'ns of earth, the earth of nought. Thou which hast made mortalitie for man, Beginning life to make an end of woe, Ending in him, what in himselfe began, His earths dominion, through thy wisedomes flow: Made for to rule according to desart, And execute reuenge with vpright heart. Verse 4 Behold a crowne, but yet a crowne of care, Behold a scepter, yet a sorrowes guise, More than the ballance of my head can beare, More than my hands can hold wherein it lies: My crowne doth want supportance for to beare, My scepter wanteth empire for to weare. A leglesse body is my kingdomes mappe, Limping in follie, halting in distresse, Giue me thy wisedome (Lord) my better happe, Which may my follie cure, my griefe redresse: O let me not fall in obliuions caue, Let wisedome be my baile, for her I craue. Uerse 5 Behold thy seruant pleading for his hire, As an apprentice to thy gospels word, Behold his poore estate, his hot-cold fire, His weake-strong limmes, his mery woes record: Borne of a woman, woman-like in woe, They weake, they feeble are, and I am so. My time of life is as an houre of day, Tis as a day of months, a month of yeeres, It neuer comes againe, but fades away, As one mornes sunne about the hemispheres: Little my memory, lesser my time, But least of all my vnderstandings prime. Verse 6 Say that my memory should neuer die, Say that my time should neuer loose a glide, Say that my selfe had earthly Maiestie, Seated in all the glory of my pride: Yet if discretion did not rule my minde, My raigne would be like fortunes, follie-blinde. My memory, a pathway to my shame, My time, the looking-glasse of my disgrace, My selfe, resemblance of my scorned name, My pride, the puffed shadow of my face: Thus should I be remembred, not regarded, Thus should my labours end, but not rewarded. Uerse 7 What were it to be shadow of a king? A vanitie: to weare a shadow'd crowne? A vanitie: to loue an outward thing? A vanitie: vaine shadowes of renowne: This King is king of shades, because a shade, A king in shew, though not in action made. His shape haue I, his cognisance I weare, A smoaky vapour hemd with vanitie, Himselfe I am, his kingdomes crowne I beare, Vnlesse that wisedome change my liuerie: A king I am, God hath inflamed me, And lesser than I am I can not be. Verse 8 When I commaund, the people do obay, Submissiue subiects to my votiue wil, A prince I am, and do what princes may, Decree, commaund, rule, iudge, performe, fulfill; Yet I my selfe am subiect vnto God, As are all others to my iudgements rod. As doe my subiect honour my command, So I at his commaund a subiect am, I build a temple on mount Sions sand, Erect an altar in thy citties name: Resemblances these are, where thou doost dwell, Made when thou framedst heau'n, earth and hell. Uerse 9 Al these three casements were containd in wit, Twas wisedome for to frame the heauens skie, Twas wisedome for to make the earth so fit, And hell within the lowest orbe to lie: To make a heau'nly clime, an earthly course, And hell, although the name of it be worse. Before the world was made wisedome was borne, Borne of heau'ns God, conceiued in his breast, Which knew what works would be, what ages worn, What labours life should haue, what quiet rest: What shuld displease and please, in vice, in good, What should be clearest spring, what fowlest mud. Verse 10 Oh make my sinfull bodies world anew, Erect new elements, new aires, new skies, The time I haue is fraile, the course vntrue, The globe vnconstant, like ill fortunes eies: First make the world, which doth my soule contain, And next my wisdome, in whose power I raigne. Illumine earth, with wisedomes heau'nly sight, Make her embassador to grace the earth, Oh let her rest by day, and lodge by night, Within the closure of my bodies hearth: That in her sacred selfe I may perceiue, What things are good to take, what ill to leaue. Uerse 11 The bodies heate will flow into the face, The outward index of an outward deede, The inward sins do keepe an inward place, Eies, face, mouth, tongue &amp; euery function feede: She is my face, if I do any ill, I see my shame in her repugnant will. She is my glasse, my tipe, my forme, my mappe, The figure of my deede, shape of my thought, My lifes character, fortune to my happe, Which vnderstandeth all that heart hath wrought: What workes I take in hand, she finisheth, And all my vitious thoughts diminisheth. Verse 12 My facts are written in her foreheads booke, The volume of my thoughts, lines of my words, The sins I haue she murders with a looke, And what one cheeke denies, th'other affords: As white and red like battels, and recreates, One doth defend the blowes, the other beates. So is her furious moode commixt with smile, Her rod is profit, her correction mirth: She makes me keepe an acceptable stile, And gouerne euery limit of the earth: Through her the state of monarchie is knowne, Through her I rule, and guide my fathers throne. Uerse 13 Mortalitie it selfe without repaire, Is euer falling feebly on the ground, Submissiue body, hart aboue the aire, Which faine would knowe, when knowledge is not found: Faine would it soare aboue the Eagles eie, Though it be made of lead, and cannot flie. The soule and body are the wings of man, The soule should mount, but that lies drownd in sin, With leaden spirit, but doth what it can, Yet scarcely can it rise when it is in: Then how can man so weake, know God so strong? What hart from thought, what thought from heart hath sprung? Ver. 14 15 We thinke that euery iudgement is alike, That euery purpose hath one finall end, Our thoughts (alas) are feares, feares horrors strike, Horrors our lifes vncertaine course do spend: Feare followes negligence, both death, and hel, Vnconstant are the paths wherein we dwell. The hollow concaue of our bodies vaultes, Once laden vp with sins eternal graues, Strait bursts into the soule the slime of faults, And ouerfloweth like a sea of waues: The earth as neighbour to our priuy thought, keeps fast the mansion which our cares haue bought Uerse 16 Say, can wee see our selues? are we so wise? Or, can we iudge our owne with our owne hearts? Alas we cannot; folly blindes our eies, Mischiefe our mindes, with her mischieuous arts: Folly raigns there, where wisdom shuld beare sway. And follies mischiefe barres discretions way. O weake capacitie of strongest wit, O strong capacitie of weaker sence, To guide, to meditate, vnapt, vnfit, Blinde in perceiuing earths circumfluence: If labour doth consist in mortall skill, Tis greater labour to know heauens will. Verse 17 The toyling spirit of a labouring man, Is tosst in casualties of fortunes seas, He thinkes it greater labour than he can, To runne his mortall course without an ease: Then who can gaine or finde celestiall things, Vnlesse their hopes a greater labour brings? What volume of thy mind can then containe, thoghts, words, &amp; works, which god thinks, speaks, &amp; makes, When heau'n it selfe cannot such honour gaine, Nor Angells know the counsell which God takes: Yet if thy heart be wisedomes mansion, Thy soule shall gaine thy hearts made mention. Uerse 18 Who can in one dayes space make two dayes toile? Or who in two dayes space will spend but one? The one doth keepe his meane in ouerbroyle, The other vnder meane, because alone: Say, what is man without his spirit swayes him? Say, what's the spirit if the man decayes him? An ill reformed breath, a life, a hell, A going out worse than a comming in, For wisedome is the bodies centinell, Set to guard life which else would fall in sin: Shee doth correct and loue, swayes, and preserues, Teaches, and fauours, rules, and yet obserues. Chapter X. Uer. 1 Correction followes loue, loue followes hate, For loue in hate, is hate in too much loue, So chastisment is preseruations mate, Instructing and preseruing those we prooue: So wisedome first corrects, then fauoureth, But fortune fauours first, then wauereth. First, the first father of this earthly world, First man, first father cal'd for after time, Vnfashioned and like a heape was hurl'd; Form'd and reform'd, by wisedome out of slime, By nature ill reform'd, by wisedome purer, Shee mortall life, she better lifes procurer. Verse 2 3 Alas what was he? but a clod of clay, What euer was he? but an ashie caske, By wisedome clothed in his best array, If better may bee best, to choose a taske: One gaue him time to liue, she power to raigne, Making two powers one, one power twaine. But ô maligne ill boading wickednes, Like bursting gulfes orewhelming vertues seed, Too furious wrath forsaking happines, Loosing ten thousand ioyes, with one dire deede: Cain cloud see, but follie strucke him blinde, To kill his brother in a raging minde. Uerse 4 Oh too vnhappy stroke to end two liues, Vnhappy actor in deaths tragedy, Murdring a brother, whose name murder giues, Whose slaying action, slaughters butcherie: A weeping part had earth in that same play, For she did weepe herselfe to death that day. Water distill'd from millions of her eyes, Vpon the long dride carcasse of her time, Her watrie conduites were the weeping skies, Which made her wombe an ouerflowing clime: Wisedome preseru'd it, which preserues all good, And taught it how to make an arke of wood. Ver. 5 Oh that one borde should saue so many liues, Vpon the worlds huge billow-tossing sea, Twas not the borde, twas wisedome which suruiues, Wisedome that arke, that boord, that fence, that bay: The world was made a water-rowling waue, But wisedome better hopes assurance gaue. And when pale malice did aduance her flagge, Vpon the raging standard of despight, Fiends soueraigne, sins mistris, and hells hagge, Dunne Plutoes Lady, empresse of the night: Wisedome from whom immortall ioy begun, Preseru'd the righteous, as her faultlesse sonne. Uer. 6 The wicked perished, but they suruiu'd, The wicked were ensnar'd, they were preseru'd, One kept in ioy, the one of ioy depriu'd, One feeding, fed, the other feeding, steru'd, The foode which wisedome giues, is nourishment, The foode which malice giues, is languishment. One feeds; the other feeds, but choking feedes, Two contraries in meat, two differing meats, This brings forth hate, and this repentance seeds: This war, this peace, this battails, this retreats: And that example may be truely tride, These liu'd in Sodomes fire, the other dide. Verse 7 The land will beare me witnes they are dead, Which for their sakes beare nothing else but death, The witnes of it selfe with vices fed, A smoaky testimony of sins breath: This is my witnes, my certificate, And this is my sinne weeping sociate. My pen will scarce holde inke to write these woes, These woes, the blotted inkie lines of sin, My paper wrincles at my sorrowes showes, And like that land will bring no haruest in: Had Lots vnfaithfull wife beene without fault, My fresh-inkt pen had neuer calld her salt. Uerse 8 But now my quill the tel-tale of all moanes, Is sauory bent to aggrauate salt teares, And wets my paper with salt-water groanes, Making me stick in agonising feares: My paper now is growne to billowes might, Sometimes I stay my pen, sometimes I write. O foolish pilate I, blind-harted guide, Can I not see the clifts, but rent my barke, Must I needs hoist vp sailes gainst winde and tide, And leaue my soule behinde my wisedomes arke, Well may I be the glasse of my disgrace, And set my sin in other sinners place. Ver. 9 10 But why despaire I? heere comes wisedomes grace, Whose hope doth lead me vnto better hap, Whose presence doth direct my fore-run race, Because I serue her as my beauties map: Like Cain I shall be restored to heau'n, From shipwracks perill to a quiet hau'n. When that by Cains hand Abel was slaine, His brother Abel, brother to his ire, Then Cain fled, to fly destructions paine, Gods heauie wrath, against his blouds desire: But being fetcht againe by wisedomes power, Had pardon for his deed, loue for his lower. Uer. 11 By his repentance he remission had, And relaxation from the clogge of sin, His painefull labour, labours riches made, His labouring paine, did plesures profit win: Twas wisedome, wisedome made him to repent, And newly plac'd him in his olde content. His body which was once destructions caue, Blacke murders teritorie, mischiefes house, By her, these wicked fins were made his slaue, And she become his bride, his wife, his spouse: Enriching him which was too rich before, Too rich in vice, in happynes too poore. Uer. 12 Mægera which did rule within his breast, And kept foule Lernas fen within his minde, Both now displease him, which once pleasde him best, Now murdring murder with his being kinde: These which were once his frends are now his foes, Whose practise he retorts with wisedomes blowes. Yet still lie they in ambush for his soule, But he more wiser keepes a wiser way, They see him; and they barke, snarle, grin, and houle, But wisedome guides his steps he cannot stray: By whom he c?quers, and throgh whom he knows The feare of God is stronger then his foes. Ver. 13 14 When man was clad in vices liuery, And solde as bondman vnto sins commaund, Shee shee, forsooke him not for infamie, But free'd him from his harts imprisoned band: And when he lay in dungeon of despight, Shee interlinde his griefe with her delight. Though seruile shee with him; shee was content, The prison was her lodge, as wel as his, Till she the scepter of the world had lent, To glad his fortune, to augment his blisse, To punish false accusers of true deeds, And raise in him immortall glories seeds. Uer. 15 Say, shall wee call her wisedome by her name, Or new inuent a nominating stile, Reciting ancient worth to make new fame, Or new-old hierarchie from honours file: Say, shall file out fame for vertues store, And giue a name not thought, nor heard before? Then should wee make her two, where now but one, Then should we make her common to each tongue, Wisedome shall be her name, she wise alone, If alter olde for new, we do olde wrong, Call her still wisedome, mistris of our soules, Our liues deliuerer from our foes controules. Uer. 16 To make that better which is best of all, Were to disarme the title of the power, And thinke to make a raise, and make a fall, Turne best to worst, a day vnto an houre, To giue two sundry names vnto one thing, Makes it more commoner in Ecchoes sling. She guides mans soule, let her be calld a Queene, Shee enters into man, call hir a sprite, Shee makes them godly, which haue neuer beene Call her her selfe, the image of her might: Those which for vertue plead, she prompts their tong, Whose sute no tyrant, nor no King can wrong. Uer. 17 Shee stands as barre betweene their mouth and them, She prompts their thoghts, their thoghts prompts speeches sound Their tongues reward is honours diadem, Their labours hire with duest merit crown'd: Shee is as iudge and witnes of each heart, Condemning falshood, taking vertues part. A shadow in the day, star in the night, A shadow for to shade them from the sunne, A star in darkenes for to giue them light, A shade in day, a star when day is done: Keeping both courses true, in being true, A shade, a starre, to shade and lighten you. Ver. 18 19 And had she not, the sunnes hot burning fire, Had scorcht the inward pallace of your powers, Your hot affection coolde your hot desire, Two heats once met make coole distilling showers, So likewise had not wisedome beene your star, You had beene prisoner vnto Phœbes car. Shee made the red-sea subiect to your craues, The surges, calmes, the billowes, smoothest wayes, Shee made rough winds sleepe silent in their caues, And Æole watch, whom all the winds obayes: Their foes pursuing them, with death and doome, Did make the sea their church, the waues their tome Uer. 20 21 They furrowed vp a graue to lie therin, Burying themselues with their owne handie deed, Sin dig'd a pit it selfe to bury sin, Seed plowed vp the ground, to scatter seed: The righteous, seeing this same sodaine fall, Did praise the Lord, and ceas'd vpon them all. A glorious prise, though from inglorious hands, A worthy spoile, though from vnworthy hearts, Tosst with the Oceans rage vppon the sands, Victorious gaine, gained by wisedomes arts: Which makes the dumbe to speak, the blind to see, The deafe to heare, the babes haue grauitie. Chapter XI. Uer. 1 2 3 What he could haue a hart, what hart a thought what thoght a tong, what tong a shew of fear Hauing his ship balanste with such a fraught Which calms the euer-weeping oceans tears: Which prospers euery enterprise of warre, And leades their fortune by good fortunes starre. A Pilate on the seas, guide on the land, Through vncouth desolate vntroden way, Through wildernes of woe, which in woes stand, Pitching their tents where desolation lay: In iust reuenge incountring with their foes, Annexing wrath to wrath, and blowes to blowes. Verse 4 But when the heate of ouermuch alarmes, Had made their bodies subiect vnto thurst, And broyld their hearts in wraths-allaying harmes, With fiery surges which from body burst: That time had made the totall summe of life, Had not affection stroue to end the strife. Wisedome affectionating power of zeale, Did coole the passion of tormenting heate, With water from a rocke which did reueale, Her deare deare loue, placde in affections seate: She was their mother twice, she nurst them twice, Mingling their heat with cold, their fire with ice. Uerse 5 From whence receiude they life, from a dead stone? From whence receiude they speach, from a mute rock? As if all pleasure did proceed from mone, Or all discretion from a senslesse blocke: For what was each but silent, dead, and mute? As if a thorny thistle should beare fruit. Tis strange how that should cure, which erst did kill, Giue life, in whome destruction is enshrinde, Alas the stone is dead, and hath no skil, Wisedome gaue life and loue, twas wisedomes minde: Shee made the store, which poysoned her foes, Giue life, giue cure, giue remedy to those. Ver. 6 7 Blood-quaffing Mars, which washt himselfe in gore, Raignde in her foes thirst-slaughter-drinking hearts, Their heads the bloody store-house of bloods store, Their minds made bloody streames disburst in parts: What was it else but butchery and hate? To przie yong infants bloud at murders rate. But let them surffet on their bloody cup, Carowsing to their owne destructions health, We drinke the siluer-streamed water vp, Which vnexpected flow'd from wisedomes wealth: Declaring by the thirst of our dry soules, How all our foes did swimme in murders boules. Uerse 8 What greater ill than famine? or what ill Can be compared to the fire of thirst? One be as both, for both the body kill, And first brings torments in tormenting first: Famine is death it selfe, and thirst no lesse, If bread and water doe not yeelde redresse. Yet this affliction is but vertues triall, Proceeding from the mercy of Gods ire, To see if it can finde his truths deniall, His iudgements breach attempts contempts desire: But oh, the wicked sleeping in misdeede, Had death on whom they fed, on whom they feede. Verse 9 A diudgde, condemnd, and punisht in one breath, Arraignde, tormented, torturde in one lawe, A diudgde like captiues with destructions wreathe, Arraignde like theeues before the barre of awe: Condemnd, tormented, torturde, punished, Like captiues bold, theeues vnastonished. Say God did suffer famine for to raigne, And thirst to rule amongst the choisest hart, Yet father-like he easde them of their paine, And proou'd them, how they could endure a smart: But as a righteous King condemnd the others, As wicked sonnes vnto as wicked mothers. Uerse 10 For where the diuel raignes, there sure is hell, Because the tabernacle of his name, His mansion-house, the place where he doth dwell, The cole-blacke visage of his nigrum fame: So if the wicked liue vpon the earth, Earth is their hell, from good to worser birth. If present, they are present to their teares, If absent, they are present to their woes, Like as the snaile which shewes all that she beares, Making her backe the mountaine of her shoes: Present to their death, not absent to their care, Their punishment alike where ere they are. Verse 11 Why say they mournd, lamented, greeude, and wailde, And fed lament with care, care with lament? Say, how can sorrow be with sorrow bailde, When teares consumeth that which smiles hath lent? This makes a double prison, double chaine, A double mourning, and a double paine. Captiuitie hoping for freedomes hap, At length doth pay the ransome of her hope, Yet frees her thought from any clogging clap, Though backe be almost burst with yrons cope: So they indurde the more, because they knew, That neuer till the spring the flowers grew. Uerse 12 And that by patience commeth hearts delight, Long-sought for blisse, Long far fet happines, Content they were to die for vertues right, Sith ioy should be the pledge of heauines: When vnexpected things were brought to passe, They were amazde and wondred where God was. Hee whom they did denie now they extoll, Hee whom they do extoll, they did denie, Hee whom they did deride, they doe enroll, In register of heau'nly maiestie: Their thirst was euer thirst, repentance stopt it, Their life was euer dead, repentance propt it. Verse 13 And had it not their thirst had burnd their harts, Their harts had cri'd out for their tongues replie, Their tougues had raised all their bodies parts, Their bodyes once in armes had made all die: Their foolish practises had made them wise, Wise in their hearts, though foolish in their eyes. But they (alas) were dead to worshippe death, Sencelesse in worshiping all shadowed showes, Breathlesse in wasting of so vaine a breath, Dumbe in performance of their tongues suppose: They in adoring death, in deaths behests, Were punished with life, and liuing beastes. Uer. 14 15 Thus for a shew of beasts, they substance haue, The thing it selfe against the shadowes will, Which makes the shadowes, sad woes in lifes graue, As nought impossible in heauens skill; God sent sad-ohes, for shadowes of lament, Lions, and beares, in multitudes he sent. Newly created beasts; which sight ne'er sawe, Vnknowne, which neither eye nor eare did know, To breathe out blasts of fire against their law, And cast out smoake with a tempestuous blow: Making their eyes the chambers of their feares, Darting forth fire as lightning from the spheares. Verse 16 Thus marching one by one, and side by side, By the prophane ill-limnd, pale spectacles, Making both fire and feare to be their guide, Pulld downe their vaine-adoring chronicles: Then staring in their faces spit forth fire, Which heats, and cools, their frosty-hot desire. Frosty in feare, vnfrosty in their shame, Coole in lament, hot in their powers disgraces, Like luke-warme coales, halfe kindled with the flame, Sate white and red mustring within their faces: The beasts th?selues did not so much dismay them, As did their vgly eyes aspects decay them. Uerse 17 Yet what are beasts, but subiects vnto man, By the decree of heau'n, degree of earth? They haue more strength then he, yet more he can, Hee hauing reasons store, they reasons dearth, But these were made to breake subiections rod: And show the stubernnesse of man to God. Had they not beene ordain'd to such intent, Gods word was able to supplant their powers, And root out them which were to mischiefe bent, With wrath &amp; vengeance, minutes in deaths houres: But God doth keepe a full-direct-true course, And measures pitties loue, with mercies force. Ver. 18 19 The wicked thinkes, God hath no might at all, Because he makes no shew of what he is, When God is loth to giue their pride a fall, Or cloud the day wherein they do amisse; But should his strength be showne his anger rise, Who could withstand the sunne-caues of his eyes. Alas, what is the world against his ire? As snowie mountaines gainst the golden sunne, For'st for to melt, and thawe with frosty fire, Fire hid in frost, though frost of colde begunne: As dew-distilling drops fall from the morne, So nw-destructions claps fall from his scorne. Uerse 20 But his reuenge lies smother'd in his smiles, His wrath lies sleeping in his mercies ioy, Which very seldome rise at mischiefes coyles, And will not wake for euery sinners toy: Boundlesse his mercies are, like heauens grounds, They haue no limittes they, nor heau'n no bounds. The promontary top of his true loue, Is like the end of neuer-ending streames, Like Nilus water-springs which inward moue, And haue no outward shew of shadowes beames: God sees, and will not see, the sinnes of men, Because they should amend, amend? oh when? Verse 21 The mother loues the issues of her wombe, As doth the father his begotten sonne, Shee makes her lap their quiet sleeping tombe, Hee seekes to care for life which new begun: What care hath he (think then) that cares for all, For aged, and for yong, for great and small? Is not that father carefull, filld with care, Louing, long suffering, mercifull, and kinde; Which made with loue all things that in loue are, Vnmercifull to none, to none vnkinde, Had man beene hatefull, man had neuer beene, But perisht in the spring-time of his greene. Uer. 22 23 But how can hate abide where loue remaines? Or how can anger follow mercies path? How can vnkindenesse hinder kindnesse gaines? Or how can murder bathe in pitties bath? Loue, mercy, kindenesse, pitty, eithers mate, Doth scorne vnkindenesse, anger, murder, hate. Had it not beene thy will to make the earth, It still had beene a Chaos vnto time, But twas thy will that man should haue a birth, And be preserude by good, condemnd by crime: Yet pitty raignes within thy mercies score, Thou spar'st &amp; lou'st vs all, what would we more? Chapter XII. Uerse 1 2 When all the elements of mortall life, Were placed in the mansion of their skin, Each hauing dayly motion to be rife, Closde in that body which doth close th? in, God sent his holy spirit vnto man, Which did begin when first the world began. So that the body which was king of al, Is subiect vnto that which now is king, Which chastneth those whom mischiefe doth exhale, Vnto misdeeds from whence destructions spring: Yet mercifull it is though it be chiefe, Conuerting vice to good, sin to beliefe. Verse 3 Old time is often lost in being balld, Balld because old, old because liuing long, It is reiected oft when it is calld, And weares out age with age, still being yong: Twice children we, twice feeble, and once strong, But being old, we sin, and do youth wrong. The more we grow in age, the more in vice, A house-roome long vnswept wil gather dust, Our long vnthawed soules wil freeze to ice, And weare the badge of long imprisoned rust: So those inhabitants in youth twice borne, Were old in sin, more olde in heauens scorne. Uer. 4 5 Committing workes as inckie spots of fame, Commencing wordes like foaming vices waues, Committing and commencing mischiefes name, With workes and words sworne to be vices slaues: As sorcery, witchcraft, mischieuous deeds, And sacrifice which wicked fancies feeds. Well may I call that wicked which is more, I rather would be lowe than be too hie, Oh wondrous practisers clothde all in gore, To end that life, which their owne liues did buy: More than swine-like eating mans bowelles vp, Their banquets dish, their blood their banquets cup. Verse 6 7 Butchers vnnaturall, worse by their trade, Whose house the bloody shambles of decay, More than a slaughter-house which butchers made, More than an Eschip seely bodies pray: Thorow whose hearts a bloody shambles runnes, They do not butcher beasts, but their owne sonnes. Chief murdrers of their soules, which their souls boght Extinguishers of light which their liues gaue, More than kniue butchers they, butchers in thought, Sextons to digge their owne begotten graue: Making their habitations old in sinne, Which God doth reconcile and new beginne. Uerse 8 9 That murdring place was turnd into delight, That bloody slaughter-house to peaces breast, That lawlesse pallace, to a place of right, That slaughtring shambles to a liuing rest: Made meete for iustice, fit for happinesse, Vnmeete for sin, vnfit for wickednesse. Yet the inhabitants, though mischiefes slaues, Were not dead-drencht in their destructions flood, God hop'd to raise repentance from sins graues, And hop'd that paines delay would make them good: Not that he was vnable to subdue them, But that their sins repentance should renue them. Ver. 10 Delay is tooke for vertue and for vice, Delay is good, and yet delay is bad, Tis vertue when it thawes repentance ice, Tis vice to put off things we haue or had: But here it followeth repentance way, Therefore it is nor sins nor mischiefes pray. Delay in punishment is double paine, And euery paine makes a twice double thought, Doubling the way to our liues better gaine, Doubling repentance which is single bought: For fruitles grafts when they are too much lopt, More fruitlesse are, for why their fruits are stopt. Uer. 11 So fares it with the wicked plants of sin, The rootes of mischiefe, toppes of villany, They worser are with too much punishing, Because by nature prone to iniury: For tis but folly to supplant his thought, Whose heart is wholy giuen to be nought. These seeded were in seede; oh cursed plant, Seeded with other seede, Oh cursed roote, Too much of good doth turne vnto goods want, As too much seede doth turne to too much soote: Bitter in taste, presuming of their height, Like misty vapours in blacke-coloured night. Uer. 12 But god whose powerful arms one strength doth hold Scorning to staine his force vpon their faces, Will send his messengers both hote and colde, To make them shadowes of their owne disgraces: His hot Ambassador is fire, his cold Is winde, which two scorne for to be controld. For who dares say vnto the King of kings, What hast thou done, which ought to be vndone? Or who dares stand against thy iudgements stings? Or dare accuse thee for the nations mone? Or who dare say, reuenge this ill for me? Or stand against the Lord with villanie? Ver. 13 What he hath done he knowes, what he will doe, He weigheth with the ballance of his eies, What iudgement he pronounceth must be so, And those which he oppresseth cannot rise: Reuenge lies in his hands, when he doth please, He can reuenge, and loue, punish, and ease. The carued spectacle which workemen make, Is subiect vnto them, not they to it, They which from God a liuely forme do take, Should much more yeeld vnto their makers wit: Sith there is none but he which hath his thought, Caring for that which he hath made of nought. Uer. 14 The clay is subiect to the potters hands, Which with a new deuice makes a new moule, And what are we I pray but clayie bands, With ashie body, ioynde to cleaner soule? Yet we once made, scorne to be made againe, But liue in sin like clayie lumps of paine. Yet if hot anger smother coole delight, Hee'le mould our bodies in destructions forme, And make our selues as subiects to his might, In the least fewell of his angers storme: Nor king, nor tyrant, dare aske or demaund, What punishment is this thou hast in hand? Uer. 15 We all are captiues to thy regall throne, Our prison is the earth, our bands our sins, And our accuser our owne bodies grone, Prest downe with vices weights, and mischiefs gins: Before the barre of heau'n we pleade for fauour, To cleanse our sin-bespotted bodies sauour. Thou righteous art, our pleading then is right, Thou mercifull, we hope for mercies grace, Thou ordrest euery thing with looke-on sight; Behold vs prisoners in earths wandring race: We know thy pitty is without a bound, And sparest them which in some faults be found. Uer. 16 Thy power is as thy selfe, without an end, Beginning all to end, yet ending none, Sonne vnto vertues sonne, and wisedomes frend, Originall of blisse to vertue showne: Beginning good which neuer ends in vice, Beginning flames which neuer ende in ice. For righteousnes is good in such a name, It righteous is, tis good in such a deed, A lamp it is, fed with discretions flame, Begins in seede, but neuer ends in seed: By this we know the Lord is iust and wise, Which causeth him to spare vs when he tries. Ver. 17 Iust, because iustice weighs what wisedome thinkes, Wise, because wisedome thinkes what iustice weighs, One vertue maketh two, and two more linckes, Wisedome is iust, and iustice neuer straies: The help of one doth make the other better, As is the want of one the others letter. But wisedome hath two properties in wit, As iustice hath two contraries in force, Heate added vnto heate augmenteth it, As too much water bursts a water-course: Gods wisdome too much proou'd doth breed gods hate, Gods iustice too much mou'de breeds Gods debate. Uer. 18 Although the ashy prison of fire-durst, Doth keepe the flaming heate imprisoned in, Yet sometime wil it burne, when flame it must, And burst the ashie caue where it hath bin: So if Gods mercy passe the bounds of mirth, It is not mercy then, but mercies dearth. Yet how can loue breed hate, without hates loue? God doth not hate to loue, nor loue to hate, His equitie doth euery action proue, Smothring with loue that spitefull enuies fate: For should the teene of anger trace his brow, The very puffes of rage would driue the plow. Uerse 19 But God did end his toile when world begun, Now like a louer studies how to please, And win their harts againe, whom mischiefe won, Lodg'd in the mansion of their sins disease: Hee made each mortall man two eares, two eyes, To heare and see; yet he must make them wise. If imitation should direct mans life, Tis life to imitate a liuing corse, The things example makes the thing more rife, God louing is, why do wee want remorce? Hee put repentance into sinfull hearts, And sed their fruitlesse soules, with fruitfull arts. Ver. 20 21 If such a boundlesse Ocean of good deeds, Should haue such influence from mercies streame, Kissing both good, and ill, flowers, and weedes, As doth the sunnie flame of Tytans beame, A greater Tethis then should mercy bee, In flowing vnto them which loueth thee. The sunne which shines in heau'n doth light the earth The earth which shines in sin doth spight the heau'n, Sinne is earths sunne, the sunne of heau'n sins dearth, Both odde in light, being of height not eu'n: Gods mercy then which spares both good and ill, Doth care for both, though not alike in will. Uerse 22 Can vice be vertues mate, or vertues meate? Her company is bad, her foode more worse, Shee shames to sit vpon her betters seat, As subiect beasts wanting the Lions force, Mercy is vertues badge, foe to disdaine, Vertue is vices stop, and mercies gaine. Yet God is mercifull, to mischiefe flowes, More mercifull in sins and sinners want, God chast'neth vs, and punisheth our foes, Like sluggish drones, amongst a laboring ant: Wee hope for mercy at our bodies doome, Wee hope for heau'n, the baile of earthly tombe. Ver. 23 What hope they for, what hope haue they of heau'n? They hope for vice, and they haue hope of hell, From whence their soules eternity is giu'n, But such eternity which paines can tell: They liue; but better were it for to die, Immortall in their paine and misery. Hath hell such freedome to deuoure soules? Are soules so bolde to rush in such a place? God giues hell power of vice, which hell controules: Vice makes her followers bolde with armed face, God tortures both, the mistris and the man, And ends in paine, that which in vice began. Uerse 24 A bad beginning makes a worser end, Without repentance meet the middle way, Making a mediocrity their friend, Which else would be their foe, because they stray: But if repentance misse the middle line, The sunne of vertue endes in wests decline. So did it fare with these, which strai'd too far, Beyond the measure of the middayes eye, In errors waies, lead without vertues star, Esteeming beast-like powers for deitie: Whose heart no thought of vnderstanding ment, Whose tongue no word of vnderstanding sent. Ver. 25 Like infant babes bearing their natures shell, Vpon the tender heads of tendrer wit, which tongue-tide are, hauing no tale to tell, To driue away the childhood of their fit: Vnfit to tune their tongue with wisedomes string, Too fit to quench their thirst in follies spring. But they were trees to babes, babes sprigs to them, They not so good as these, in being nought, In being nought, the more from vices stem, Whose essence cannot come without a thought; To punish them, is punishment in season; They children like, without or wit, or reason. Uerse 26 To bee derided, is to be halfe dead, Derision beares a part tweene life and death, Shame followes her with misery halfe fed, Halfe-breathing life, to make halfe life and breath: Yet here was mercy showne, their deeds were more, Then could bee wipte off by derisions score. This mercy is the warning of misdeedes, A trumpet summoning to vertues walls, To notifie their hearts which mischiefe feeds, Whom vice instructs, whom wickednes exhal's: But if derision can not murder sin, Then shame shall end, and punishment begin. Ver. 27 For many shamelesse are, bolde, stout in ill, Then how can shame take roote in shamlesse plants, When they their browes with shamelesse furrows fill, And plows ech place, which one plow-furrow wants: Then being arm'd gainst shame with shamlesse face, How can derision take a shameful place? But punishment may smoth their wrinckled brow, And set shame on the forehead of their rage, Guiding the forefront of that shamelesse row, Making it smooth in shame, though not in age: Then will they say, that God is iust and true, But tis too late, damnation will ensue. Chapter XIII. Uer. 1 The branch must needs be weake, if roote be so, The roote must needs be weake, if branches fall, Nature is vaine, man cannot be her foe, Because from nature, and at natures call: Nature is vaine, and wee proceede from nature, Vaine therfore is our birth, and vaine our feature. One body may haue two diseases sore, Not being two, it may be ioynde to two, Nature is one it selfe, yet two and more, Vaine, ignorant of God, of good, of show, Which not regards the things which god hath don, And what things are to doe, what new begun. Uer. 2 Why doe I blame the tree? when tis the leaues, Why blame I nature? for her mortall men, Why blame I men? tis she, tis she that weaues, That weaues, that wafts vnto destructions pen: Then being blamefull both, because both vaine, I leaue to both, their vanities due paine. To prize the shadow at the substance rate, Is a vaine substance of a shadowes hue, To thinke the sonne to be the fathers mate, Earth to rule earth, because of earthly view: To thinke fire winde, ayre stars, water, and heau'n, To be as Gods, from whom their selues are giu'n. Ver. 3 Fire as a God? oh irreligious sound, Winde as a God? oh vaine, oh vainest voice, Aire as a God? when tis but duskie ground, Star as a God? when tis but Phœbes choice: Water a God? which first by God was made, Heauen a God? which first by God was laide. Say all hath beautie, excellence, array, Yet beautifide they are, they were, they bee, By Gods bright excellence of brightest day, Which first implanted our first beuties tree: If then the painted outside of the show, Bee radiant, what is the inward row. Uer. 4 If that the shadowe of the bodies skin, Bee so illumin'd with the sun-shin'd soule, What is the thing it selfe which is within, More wrencht, more cleansde, more purifi'd from foul: If elementall powers haue Gods thought, Say what is God, which made them all of nought. It is a wonder for to see the skie, And operation of each ayrye power, A meruaile, that the heau'n should be so hie, And let fall such a low distilling shower: Then needs must hee bee high, higher then all, Which made both hie and lowe with one tongues call. Uer. 5 The workeman mightier is then his hand-worke, In making that which else would be vnmade, The nere-thought thing, doth alwaies hidden lurke, Without the maker in a making trade: For had not God made man, man had not beene, But nature had decayde, and nere beene seene. The workman neuer shewing of his skill, Doth liue vnknowne to man, though knowne to wit, Had mortall birth beene neuer in Gods will, God had beene God, but yet vnknowne in it: Then hauing made the glory of earths beautie, Tis reason earth should reuerence him in dutie. Uer. 6 The sauadge people haue a supreame head, A king, though sauadge as his subiects are, Yet they with his obseruances are lead, Obaying his beheasts what ere they were: The Turkes, the infidels, all haue a Lord, Whom they obserue in thought, in deed, in word. And shall we; differing from their sauage kinde, Hauing a soule to liue and to beleeue, Be rude in thought, in deed, in word, in minde, Not seeking him which should our woes releeue: Oh no deere brethren, seeke our God, our fame, Then if wee erre we shall haue lesser blame. Ver. 7 How can wee erre, wee seeke for ready way, Oh that my tongue could fetch that word againe, Whose very accent makes me go astray, Breathing that erring wind into my braine: My word is past and cannot be recalde, It is like aged time, now waxen balde. For they which goe astray in seeking God, Doe misse the ioyefull narrow-footed path, (Ioyfull, thrice ioyfull way to his abode,) Nought seeing but their shadowes in a bath: Narcissus-like pining to see a show, Hindring the passage, which their feete should goe. Uer. 8 9 Narcissus fantasie did die to kisse, O sugred kisse dide with a poisoned lip, The fantasies of these do die to misse, Oh tossed fantasies, in follies ship: He dide to kisse the shadow of his face, These liue and die to lifes and deaths disgrace. A fault without amends, crime without ease, A sin without excuse, death without aide, To loue the world, and what the world did please, To know the earth, wherin their sinnes are laide: They knew the world, but not the L. that framde it They knew the earth, but not the L. that namde it. Uerse 10 Narcissus drownde himselfe, for his selfes shew, Striuing to heale himselfe, did himselfe harme, These drownde them selues on earth, with their selues woe, Hee in a water-brooke by furies charme; They made dry earth wet with their follys weep?g, Hee made wet earth dry, with his furies sleeping. Then leaue him to his sleepe: returne to those, Which euer wake in miseries constraints, Whose eyes are hollow caues, and made sleeps foes, Two dungeons darke with sin, blind with complaints: They called images which man first found, Immortall Gods: for which, their tongs are bound. Ver. 11 12 Golde was a God with them, a golden God, Like children in a pageant of gay toyes, Adoring images for saints abode, Oh vaine vaine spectacles of vainer ioyes: Putting their hope in blocks, their trust in stones; Hoping to trust, trusting to hope in mones. As when a carpenter cuts downe a tree, Meet for to make a vessell for mans vse, He pareth all the barke most cunningly, With the sharp shauer of his kniues abuse, Ripping the feely wombe with no entreate, Making her woundy chips to dresse his meat. Uer. 13 14 Her bodies bones are often rough and hard, Crooked with ages growth, growing with crookes, And full of wether-chinkes, which seasons marrde, Knobbie and rugged, bending in like hookes: Yet knowing age can neuer want a fault, Encounters it with a sharpe knifes assault. And carues it well though it be selfe-like ill, Obseruing leasure, keeping time and place, According to the cunning of his skill, Making the figure of a mortall face: Or like some vgly beast in ruddy mould, Hiding each crannie with a painters fould. Ver. 15 16 It is a world to see, to marke, to view, How age can botch vp age, with crooked thread, How his olde hands, can make an olde tree new, And dead-like hee, can make another dead: Yet makes a substantiue, able to beare it, And she an adiectiue, nor see, nor heare it. A wall it is it selfe, yet wall with wall, Hath great supportance bearing either part, The image like an adiectiue would fall, Were it not closed with an yron hart: The workman being olde himselfe, doth know, What great infirmities olde age can show. Uerse 17 Therefore to stop the riuer of extreames, Hee burst into the flowing of his wit, Tossing his braines with more then thousand theams, To haue a wooden stratagem so fit: Woodden, because it doth belong to wood, His purpose may be wise, his reason good. His purpose wise? no, foolish, fond, and vaine, His reason good? no, wicked, vild, and ill; To be the authour of his owne liues paine, To be the tragick actor of his will: Praying to that which he before had fram'd, For welcome faculties, (and not asham'd.) Ver. 18 19 Calling to follie, for discretions sence, Calling to sicknes, for sick bodies health, Calling to weakenes, for a stronger fence, Calling to pouertie, for better wealth: Praying to death, for life, for this hee praide, Requiring helpe of that, which wanteth aide. Desiring that of it, which he not had, And for his iourney, that which cannot goe, And for his gaine, her furdrance, to make glad, The worke which he doth take in hand to doe: These windie words do rush against the wall, Shee cannot speake, twill sooner maker her fall. Chapter XIIII. Uerse 1 As doth one little sparke make a great flame, Kindled from forth the bosome of the flint, As doth one plague infect with it selfe name, With watrie humours making bodies dint: So, euen so, this idoll worshipper, Doth make another idoll practiser. The shipman cannot teeme dame Tethis waues, Within a winde-taught-capring anchorage, Before hee prostrate lies, and suffrage craues, And haue a block to be his fortunes gage: More crooked then his sterne, yet he implores her, More rotten then his ship, yet he adores her. Ver. 2 3 4 Who made this forme? he that was form'd and made, Twas auarice, twas shee that found it out, Shee made her crafts-man crafty in his trade, Hee cunning was in bringing it about: Oh had he made the painted shew to speake, It would haue calde him vaine, herselfe to wreake. It would haue made him blush aliue, though hee, Did die her colour with a deadly blush, Thy pouidence (ô father) doth decree, A sure sure way, amongst the waues to rush: Thereby declaring that thy power is such, That thogh a man were weake, thou canst do much. Uer. 5 What is one single barre to double death? One death in death, the other death in feare, This single barre, a borde, a poore bords breath, Yet stops the passage of each Neptunes teare: To see how many liues one borde can haue, To see how many liues one borde can saue. How was this borde first made? by wisedomes art, Which is not vaine, but firme, not weake, but sure, Therfore do men commit their liuing hart, To plancks which either life or death procure: Cutting the stormes in two, parting the winde, Plowing the sea till they their harbour finde. Uer. 6 The sea whose mountaine billowes, passing bounds Rusheth vpon the hollow-sided barke, With rough-sent kisses from the water grounds, Raising a foaming heat with rages sparke, Yet sea, nor waues, can make the shipman feare, Hee knowes that die he must, hee cares not where. For had his timorous heart beene dide in white, And sent an eccho of resembling woe, Wisedome had beene vnknowne in follies night, The sea had beene a desolations showe: But one world hope lay houering on the sea, When one worlds hap did end with one decay. Uer. 7 8 Yet Phœbus drowned in the oceans world, Phœbe disgrast with Tethis billow-roules, And Phœbus firie-golden-wreath vncurl'd, was seated at the length in brightnes soules: Man tosst in wettest wildernes of seas, Had seed on seed, encrease vpon encrease. Their mansion-house a tree vpon a waue, O happy tree, vppon vnhappy ground, But euery tree is not ordain'd to haue Such blessednes, such vertue, such abound: Some trees are carued images of nought, Yet God-like reuerenc'd, ador'd, besought, Ver. 9 Are the trees nought, alas, they sencelesse are, The hands which fashion them, condemne their groth, Cuts downe their branches, vailes their forehead bare, Both made in sin, though not sins equall both: First God made man, and vice did make him new, And man made vice from vice; and so it grew. Now is her haruest greater then her good, Her wonted winter, turn'd to summers ayre, Her ice to heat, her sprig to cedars wood, Her hate to loue, her lothsome filth to faire: Man loues her well by mischiefe new created, God hates her ill, because of vertue hated. Uerse 10 O foolish man mounted vppon decay, More vgly then Alastors pitchie backe, Nights dismall summoner, and end of day, Carrying all duskie vapours hemde in blacke: Behold thy downfall ready at thy hand, Behold thy hopes wherein thy hazards stand. Oh spurne away that blocke out of thy way, With vertues appetite, and wisedomes force, That stumbling blocke of follie and decay, That snare which doth ensnare thy treading corse: Beholde thy body falls, let vertue beare it, Beholde thy soule doth fall, let wisedome reare it. Verse 11 Say art thou yong, or olde, tree, or a bud, Thy face is so disfigured with sin, Yong I doe thinke thou art, in what? in good, But olde I am assur'd by wrinckled skin: Thy lips, thy tongue, thy heart, is yong in praying, But lips, and tongue, and heart is olde in straying. Olde in adoring idolls, but too yong, In the obseruance of diuinest lawe, Yong in adoring God, though olde in tong, Olde and too olde, yong, and too yong in awe: Beginning that, which doth begin misdeeds, Inuenting vice, which all thy body feeds. Ver. 12 13 But this corrupting and infecting foode, This caterpiller of eternitie, The foe to blisse, the canker vnto good, The new accustom'd way of vanitie: It hath not euer beene, nor shall it be, But perish in the branch of follies tree. As her descent was vanities aline, So her descending like to her descent, Here shall shee haue an end, in hell no fine, Vaine glory brought her, vainely to be spent: You know all vanity drawes to an end, Then needs must shee decay because her frend. Uer. 14 Is there more follie then to weepe at ioy, To make eyes watrie, when they should be drie, To greeue at that, which murders griefes annoy, To keepe a shower where the sunne should lie? But yet this folly-cloude doth oft appeare, When face should smile and watry eie bee cleere. The father mournes to see his sonne life-dead, But seldome mournes to see his sonne dead-liu'd, Hee cares for earthly lodge, not heau'ns bed, For death in life, not life in death suruiu'd: Keeping the outward shadow of his face, To worke the inward substance of disgrace. Uerse 15 Keeping a shew to counterpoize the deed, Keeping a shadow to be substance heire, To raise the thing it selfe from shadowes seed, And make an element of liuelesse aire: Adoring that which his owne hands did frame, Whose hart inuention gaue, whose tong the name. But could infection keepe one setled place, The poyson would not lodge in euery brest, Nor feede the hart, the minde, the soule, the face, Lodging but in the carcasse of her rest: But this Idolatry once in mans vse, Was made a custome then without excuse. Verse 16 Nay more: it was at tyrannies commaund, And tyrants cannot speake without a doome, Whose iudgement doth proceed from heart and hand, From heart in rage, from hand in bloudy tombe: That if through absence any did neglect it, Presence should pay the ransome which reiect it. Then to auoide the doome of present hate, Their absence did performe their presence want, Making the image of a kingly state, As if they had new seed from sins olde plant: Flattring the absence of olde mischiefes mother, With the like forme and presence of another. Verse 17 Making an absence with a present sight, Or rather presence with an absent view, Deceiuing vulgars with a day of night, Which know not good from bad, nor false from true: A crafts-man cunning in his crafty trade, Beguiling them with that which he had made. Like as a vane is turn'd with euery blast, Vntill it point vnto the windie clime, So stand the people at his worde agast, Hee making olde new forme in new-olde time, Defies, and deifies all with one breath, Making them liue and die, and all in death, Uer. 18 They like to Tantalus are fed with shoes, Shewes which exasperat: and cannot cure, They see the painted shadow of suppose, They see her sight, yet what doth sight procure? Like Tantalus they feed, and yet they starue, Their foode is caru'd to them, yet hard to carue. The crafts-man feeds them with a staruing meat, Which doth not fill but empty hungers gape, Hee makes the idoll, comely, faire, and great, With well limnd visage, and best fashioned shape: Meaning to giue it to some noble view, And faine his beautie with that flattring hue, Uer. 19 Enamour'd with the sight, the people grew, To diuers apparitions of delight, Some did admire the portraiture so new, Hew'd from the standard of an olde trees hight, Some were allur'd through beutie of the face, With outward eye to worke the soules disgrace. Adored like a God though made by man, To make a God of man, a man of God, Tis more then humaine life or could, or can, Though multitudes applause in error trode, I neuer knew since mortall lifes abod, That man could make a man much lesse a God. Uer. 20 Yes man can make his shame, without a maker, Borrowing the essence from restored sin, Man can be vertues foe, and vices taker, Welcome himselfe without a welcome in: Can he doe this? yea more, oh shamlesse ill, Shamefull in shame, shamelesse in wisedomes will. The riuer of his vice can haue no bound, But breakes into the ocean of deceit, Deceiuing life with measures of dead ground, With carued idols, disputations baite: Making captiuitie cloth'd all in mone, Bee subiect to a God made of a stone. Uer. 21 Too stony hearts had they which made this lawe, Oh had they beene as stony as the name, They neuer had brought vulgars in such awe, To be destructions pray, and mischiefes game: Had they beene stone-dead both in looke &amp; fauour They neuer had made life of such a sauour. Yet was not this a too sufficient doome, Sent from the roote of their sin-oregrowne tong, To cloud gods knowledge with hel mischiefs gloome To ouerthrowe truths right with falshoods wrong: But dayly practised a perfect way, Still to begin and neuer end to stray. Ver. 22 23 For either murders pawe did gripe their harts, With whispring horrors drumming in each eare, Or other villanies did play their parts, Augmenting horror to newe strucken feare: Making their hands more then a shambles stall, To stay their children ceremoniall. No place was free from staine of blood or vice, Their life was markt for death, their soule for sin, Marriage, for fornications thawed ice, Thought for despaire, body for eithers gin: Slaughter did either end what life begunne, Or lust did end what both had left vndone. Uer. 24 25 The one was sure, although the other faile, For vice hath more competitors then one, A greater troupe doth euermore auaile, And villanie is neuer found alone, The bloud-hound folows that which slaughter kild And theft doth folow what deceit hath spild. Corruption mate to infidelitie, For that which is vnfaithfull is corrupt, Tumults are schoole fellowes to periury, For both are full when either one hath supt: Vnthankfullnes, defiling, and disorders, Are fornications and vncleannes borders. Verse 26 See what a sort of rebells are in armes, To root out vertue, to supplant her raigne, Opposing of them selues against all harmes, To the deposing of her empires gaine: O double knot of treble miseries, Oh treble knot, twice, thrice, in villanies. O idoll-worshipping, thou mother art, Shee procreatresse of a he offence, I know thee now, thou bearst a womans part, Thou nature hast of her, shee of thee sence: These are thy daughters, too too like the mother, Black sins I dim you all with inckie smother. Uer. 27 My pen shall be officious in this scene, To let your harts blood in a wicked veine, To make your bodies cleare, your soules as cleane, To cleanse the sinkes of sin, with vertues reine: Behold your cole-blacke blood my writing inke, My papers poysoned meate, my pens fowle drinke. New christned are you, with your owne new blood, But madde before; sauage, and desperate, Prophecying lies, not knowing what was good, Liuing vngodly euermore in hate: Thundring out oathes, pale Sergeants of despaire, Swore, and forswore, not knowing what you were. Ver. 28 Now looke vpon the spectacle of shame, The well-limnd image of an ill-limnd thought, Say, are you worthy now of praise or blame, That such selfe-scandall in your owne selues wrought? You were heart-sicke before I let you blood, But now heart-well since I haue done you good. Now wipe blinde folly from your seeing eies, And driue destruction from your happy mind, Your follie now is wit, not foolish-wise, Destruction, happinesse, not mischiefe blinde: You put your trust in idoles, they deceiude you, You put your trust in God, and he receiude you. Uer. 29 Had not repentance grounded on your soules, The climes of good or ill, vertue or vice, Had it not flowde into the tongues enrowles, Ascribing mischiefes hate, with good aduice: Your tong had spild your soul, your soul your tong Wronging each function with a double wrong. Your first attempt was placed in a show, Imaginary show without a deed, The next attempt was periury, the foe To iust demeanors, and to vertues seede: Two sins, two punishments, and one in two, Makes two in one, and more than one can do. Verse 30 Foure scourges from one paine, al comes from sin, Single, yet double, double, yet in foure, It stayes the soule, it hems the body in, It spills the minde, it doth the heart deuoure: Gnawing vpon the thoughts, feeding on blood, For why, she liues in sin, but dies in good. She taught their soules to stray, their tongs to sweare, Their thought to thinke amisse, their life to die, Their heart to erre, their mischiefe to appeare, Their head to sin, their feete to treade awry: This sceane might well haue bin destructions tent, To pay with paine, what sin with ioy hath spent. Chapter XV. Uer. 1 But God will neuer die his hands with bloud, His heart with hate, his throne with crueltie, His face with furies map, his browe with cloud, His raigne with rage, his crowne with tyrannie: Gratious is he, long-suffering, and true, Which ruleth all things with his mercies view. Gratious, for where is grace but where he is? The fountaine-head the euer-boundlesse streame, Patient, for where is patience in amisse, If not conducted by pure graces beame: Truth is the moderator of them both, For grace and patience are of truest groth. Ver. 2 For grace-beginning truth, doth end in grace, As truth-beginning grace, doth end in truth, Now patience takes the moderators place, Yong-olde in suffering, olde-yong in ruth: Patience is olde in being alwaies yong, Not hauing right, nor euer offering wrong, So this is moderator of Gods rage, Pardoning those deeds, which wee in sin commit, That if wee sin, shee is our freedomes gage, And wee still thine, though to be thine vnfit: In being thine (ô Lord) wee will not sin, That we thy patience, grace, and truth may win. Uer. 3 O grant vs patience in whose grant we rest, To right our wrong, and not to wrong the right, Giue vs thy grace (ô Lord) to make vs blest, That grace might blesse, &amp; blisse might grace our sight: Make our beginning and our sequell truth, To make vs yong in age, and graue in youth, Wee know that our demaunds rest in thy will, Our will rests in thy word, our worde in thee, Thou in our orisons, which dost fullfill, That wished action, which wee wish to bee: Tis perfect righteousnes to know thee right, Tis immortalitie to know thy might. Verse 4 5 In knowing thee, we know both good and ill, Good, to know good and ill, ill to know none, In knowing all, wee know thy sacred will, And what to do, and what to leaue vndone: We are deceiu'd, not knowing to deceiue, In knowing good and ill, wee take and leaue. The glasse of vanitie, deceit, and showes, The painters labour, the beguiling face, The diuers-coloured image of suppose, Cannot deceiue the substance of thy grace: Only a snare, to those of common wit, Which couets to be like, in hauing it. Uerse 6 The greedy lucre of a witlesse braine, This feeding auarice on sencelesse minde, Is rather hurt, then good, a losse, then gaine, Which couets for to loose and not to finde: So they were coloured with such a face, They would not care to take the idols place. Then be your thoughts coherent to your words, Your words as correspondent to your thought, Tis reason you should haue what loue affords: And trust in that which loue so dearely bought: The maker must needs loue what he hath made, And the desirers free of either trade. Verse 7 Man, thou wast made, art thou a maker now? Yes, tis thy trade, for thou a potter art, Tempring softe earth, making the clay to bow, But clayie thou, dost beare too stout a hart: The clay is humble to thy rigorous hands, Thou clay, too tough against thy Gods comma?ds. If thou want'st slime, beholde thy slimie faults, If thou want'st clay, beholde thy clayie breast, Make them to be the deepest centres vaults, And let all clayie mountaines sleepe in rest: Thou bear'st an earthly mountaine on thy back, Thy harts chiefe prison-house thy souls chief wrack. Uer. 8 Art thou a mortall man, and mak'st a God, A God of clay, thou but a man of clay, O suds of mischiefe, in destruction sod, O vainest labour in a vainer playe: Man is the greatest worke which God did take: And yet a God with man is nought to make. Hee that was made of earth, would make a heau'n, If heauen may be made vpon the earth, Sins heires, the ayres, sins plants, the planets seau'n, Their God a clod, his birth, true vertues dearth: Remember whence you came whither you goe, Of earth, in earth, from earth to earth in woe. Verse 9 No, quoth the potter, as I haue beene clay, So will I end with what I did begin, I am of earth, and I doe what earth may, I am of dust, and therefore will I sin: My life is short, what then? I'le make it longer, My life is weake, what then? I'le make it stronger. Long shall it liue in vice, though short in length, And fetch immortall steps, from mortall stops, Strong shall it be in sin, though weake in strength, Like mounting Eagles, on high mountaines tops: My honour shall bee placed in deceit, And counterfait new shewes of little weight. Uerse 10 My pen doth almost blush at this replie, And faine would call him wicked to his face, But then his breath would answere with a lie, And staine my inck with an vntruths disgrace: Thy maister bids thee write, the pen sayes no, But when thy maister bids, it must be so. Call his hart ashes: oh too mild a name, Call his hope vile, more viler then the earth, Call his life weaker then a clayeie frame, Call his bespotted heart, an ashye hearth: Ashes, earth, clay, conioyn'd to heart, hope, life, Are features loue, in being natures strife. Verse 11 Thou mightst haue chose more stinging wordes then these For this he knowes he is, and more, then lesse, In saying what he is, thou dost appease, The foming anger which his thoughts suppresse: Who knowes not, if the best be made of clay, The worst must needs be clad in foule array. Thou in performing of thy maisters will, Dost teach him to obay his lords commaunds, But he repugnant is, and cannot skill Of true adoring, with heart-heau'd vp hand: Hee hath a soule, a life, a breath, a name, Yet is he ignorant from whence they came. Uerse 12 My soule, saith he, is but a mappe of shoes, No substance, but a shadow for to please, My life doth passe, euen as a pastime goes, A momentary time to liue at ease: My breath a vapour, and my name of earth, Each one decaying of the others birth. Our conuersation best, for there is gaines, And gaine is best in conuersations prime, A mart of lucre in our conscience raignes, Our thoughts as busie agents for the time: So we get gaine ensnaring simple men, It is no matter how, nor where, nor when. Verse 13 We care not how, for all misdeedes are ours, We care not where, if before God or man, We care not when, but when our crafts haue powres, In measuring deceit with mischiefes fanne: For wherefore haue we life, forme, and ordaining, But that we should deceiue, and still be gaining? I made of earth, haue made al earthen shops, And what I sell is al of earthy sale, My pots haue earthen feete, and earthen tops, In like resemblance of my bodies vale: But knowing to offend the heauens more, I made fraile images of earthy store. Uer. 14 O bold accuser of his owne misdeedes, O heauy clod more than the earth can beare, Was neuer creature clothde in sauage weedes, Which would not blush when they this mischief hear: Thou toldst a tale which might haue bin vntolde. Making the hearers blush, the readers olde. Let them blush still that heares, be olde that reades, Then boldnes shal not raigne, nor youth in vice, Thrice miserable they which rashly speeds, With expedition to this bold deuice: More foolish than are fooles, whose misery Cannot be changde with new felicitie. Ver. 15 Are not they fooles which liue without a sence, Haue not they misery which neuer ioy? Which takes an idoll for a Gods defence, And with their self-willd thoghts themselues destroy? What folly is more greater than is here? Or what more miserie can wel appeere? Call you them gods which haue no seeing eyes? No noses for to smell, no eares to heare, No life but that which in deaths shadow lies, Which haue no hands to feele, no feete to beare: If gods can neither heare, liue, feele, nor see, A foole may make such gods of euery tree. Uerse 16 And what was he that made them but a foole? Conceiuing follie in a foolish braine, Taught and instructed in a wodden schoole, Which made his head run of a wodden vaine: Twas man which made them, he his making had, Man full of wood, was wood, and so ran mad. He borrowed his life, and would restore His borrowed essence to another death, He faine would be a maker, though before Was made himselfe, and God did lend him breath: No man can make a god like to a man, He sayes he scornes that worke, he furder can. Verse 17 He is deceiude, and in his great deceit, He doth deceiue the folly-guided harts, Sin lies in ambush, he for sin doth waite, Here is deceit deceiude, in either parts: His sin deceiueth him, and he his sin, So craft with craft is mewed in either gin. The crafts-man mortall is, craft mortall is, Each function nursing vp the others want, His hands are mortall, deadly what is his, Onely his sins buds in destructions plant: Yet better he, than what he doth deuise, For he himselfe doth liue that euer dies. Uer. 18 Say, call you this a God? where is his head? Yet headlesse is he not, yet hath he none: Where is his godhead? fled; his power? dead; His raigne? decayed; and his essence? gone: Now tell me, is this God the God of good? Or else Siluanus monarch of the wood. There haue I pierst his barke, for he is so, A wooden god, fainde as Siluanus was: But leauing him, to others let vs go, To senslesse beasts their new adoring glasse: Beasts which did liue in life, yet died in reason, Beasts which did seasons eate, yet knew no season. Ver. 19 Can mortall bodies, and immortall soules Keepe one knit vnion of a liuing loue? Can sea with land? can fish agree with foules? Tygers with lambes, a serpent with a doue? Oh no, they cannot; then say, why doe wee, Adore a beast which is our enimy. What greater foe than folly vnto wit? What more deformitie than vgly face? This disagrees, for follie is vnfit, The other contrary to beauties place: Then how can senslesse heads, deformed shoes, Agree with you when they are both your foes. Chapter XVI. Uer. 1 Oh call that word againe, they are your friends Your liues associats, and your loues content, That which begins in them, your follie ends, Then how can vice with vice be discontent: Beholde deformitie sits on your heads, Not hornes but scornes, not visage but whole beds. Beholde a heap of sins your bodies pale, A mountaine-ouerwhelming villany, Then tell me, are you clad in beauties vale? Or in destructions pale-dead liuerie: Their life demonstrates; now aliue now dead, Tormented with the beasts which they haue fed. Uer. 2 3 You like to Pelicans haue fed your death, With follies-vaine let bloud; from follies veyne, And almost sterude your selues, stopt vp your breath, Had not Gods mercie helpt, and easde your paine, Beholde a new-found meat, the Lord did send, Which taught you to be new, and to amend. A strange disgested nutriment, euen quailes, Which taught them to be strange vnto misdeeds, When you implore his aide, he neuer failes, To fill their hunger, whom repentance feeds: You see when life was halfe at deaths arrest, Hee new created life at hungers feast. Verse 4 Say, is your God like this, whom you ador'd, Or is this God like to your handie frame, If so, his power could not then afford, Such influence which floweth from his name: Hee is not painted, made of wood and stone, But he substantiall is, and rules alone. He can oppresse, and helpe, helpe, and oppresse, The sinfull incolants of his made earth, He can redresse, and paine, paine, and redresse, The mountaine-miseries of mortall birth: Now tyrants you are next, this but a show, And merry index of your after woe. Uer. 5 6 Your hot-colde misery is now at hand, Hot because furies heat, and mercies colde, Cold because limping, knit in frosty band, And cold and hot in being shamefast-bolde: They cruell were, take crueltie their part, For misery is but too meane a smart. But when the Tygers iawes, the Serpents stings, Did summon them vnto this lifes decay, A pardon for their faults thy mercy brings, Cooling thy wrath with pitties sunnie day: O tyrants tere your sin-bemired weeds, Beholde your pardon sealde by mercies deeds. Uer. 7 8 That sting which pained could not ease the paine, Those iaws that wounded, could not cure the wounds To turne to stings for helpe, it were but vaine, To iawes for mercie, which wants mercies bounds: The stings, ô Sauiour, were puld out by thee, Their iawes claspt vp, in midst of crueltie. O soueraigne salue, stop to a bloody streame, O heauenly care and cure, for dust and earth, Celestiall watch to wake terrestriall dreame, Dreaming in punishment, mourning in mirth, Now knowes our enimies, that it is thee, Which helpes and cures, our griefe and misery. Uer. 9 Our punishment doth end, theirs new begins, Our day appeares, their night is not oreblowne, Wee pardon haue, they punishment for sins, Now we are raisde, now they are ouerthrowne: Wee with huge beasts opprest, they with a flie, Wee liue in God, and they against God die. A flie, poore flie, to follow such a flight, Yet art thou fed, as thou wast fed before, With dust and earth, feeding thy wonted bite, With selfe-like food, from mortall earthly store: A mischiefe-stinging food, and sting with sting, Do ready passage to destruction bring. Verse 10 Man beeing grasse is hopt and graz'd vpon, With sucking grasse-hoppers of weeping dew, Man being earth is wormes vermilion, Which eats the dust, and yet of bloudy hue: In being grasse he is her grazing food, In being dust he doth the wormes some good. These smallest actors were of greatest paine, Of follies ouerthrow, of mischiefes fall, But yet the furious dragons coulde not gaine, The life of those whom verities exhale: These follie ouercame, they foolish were, These mercie cur'd, and cures, these godly are. Uer. 11 When poysoned iawes and veninated stings, Were both as opposite against content, (Because content with that which fortune brings,) They eased were, when thou thy mercies sent: The iawes of dragons had not hungers fill. Nor stings of serpents a desire to kill. Appal'd they were, and struck with timerous feares, For where is feare, but where destruction raignes, Agast they were, with wet eye-standing teares, Outward commencers of their inward paines: They soone were hurt, but sooner healde and cured, Lest black obliuion had their minds inured. Uer. 12 The lion wounded with a fatall blow, Is as impatient as a king in rage, Seeing himselfe in his owne bloody show, Doth rent the harbour of his bodies cage: Scorning the base housde earth, mounts to the skie, To see it heauen can yeeld him remedy. Oh sinfull man, let him example be, A patterne to thine eye, glasse to thy face, That Gods diuinest word is cure to thee, Not earth, but heauen, not man, but heauenly grace: Nor hearb, nor plaister, could help teeth or sting, But twas thy word which healeth euery thing. Verse 13 We fooles lay salues vpon our bodies skin, But neuer drawe corruption from our minde, We lay a plaister for to keepe in sin, We drawe foorth filth, but leaue the cause behinde: With hearbs and plaisters we do guard misdeedes, And pare away the tops, but leaue the seedes. Away with salues, and take our Sauiours word, In this word Sauiour lies immortall ease, What can thy cures, plaisters, and hearbs afford? When God hath power to please and to displease: God hath the power of life, death, help, and paine, He leadeth downe, and bringeth vp againe. Uer. 14 15 Trust to thy downefall, not vnto thy raise, So shalt thou liue in death, not die in life, Thou dost presume, if giue thy selfe the praise, For vertues time is scarce, but mischiefes rife: Thou mayst offend, mans nature is so vaine, Thou now in ioy, beware of after paine. First commeth fury, after fury thirst, After thirst, blood, and after blood, a death, Thou mayst in fury kill, whome thou louedst first, And so in quassing blood, stop thine owne breath: And murther done, can neuer be vndone, Nor can that soule once liue, whose life is gone. Ver. 16 What is the body but an earthen case, That subiect is to death, because earth dies? But when the liuing soule doth want Gods grace, It dies in ioy, and liues in miseries: This soule is led by God, as others were, But not brought vp againe as others are. This stirs no prouocation to amend, For earth hath many partners in one fall, Although the Lord doth many tokens send, As warnings for to heare when he doth call: The earth was burnt &amp; drownd with fire &amp; raine, And one could neuer quench the others paine. Uer. 17 Althogh both foes, God made them then both frends, And onely foes to them which were their foes, That hate begun in earth what in them ends, Sins enimies they which made friends of those: Both bent both forces vnto single earth, From whose descent they had their double birth. Tis strange that water should not quench a fire, For they were heating-cold, and cooling hot, Tis strange that wailes could not allay desire, Wailes waters kinde, and fire desires knot: In such a cause, though enimies before, They would ioyne friendship to destroy the more. Verse 18 The often weeping eies of drie lament, Doth powre forth burning water of despaire, Which warms the caues fr? whence the tears are sent, And like hot fumes, do foule their natures faire: This contrary to icie-waters vale, Doth scorch the cheekes, &amp; makes them red &amp; pale. Here fire and water are conioynde in one, Within a red-white glasse of hote and cold, Their fire like this, double and yet alone, Raging, and tame, and tame, and yet was bold: Tame when the beasts did kill, and felt no fire, Raging vpon the causers of their ire. Uer. 19 Two things may well put on two seuerall natures, Because they differ in each natures kind, They differing colours haue, and differing features, If so, how comes it that they haue one minde? God made them friends, let this the answer be, They get no other argument of me. What is impossible to Gods command? Nay, what is possible to mans vaine eare? Tis much he thinkes that fire should burne a land, When mischiefe is the brand which fiers beare: He thinkes it more, that water should beare fire, Then know it was Gods will, now leaue t'enquire. Ver. 20 Yet mightst thou aske, because importunate, How God preserude the good; why? because good, Ill fortune made not them infortunate, They Angells were, and fed with Angells food: Yet maist thou say (for trueth is alwayes had) That raine falles on the good aswell as bad. And say it doth; farre be the letter P. From R. because of a more reuerent stile, It cannot doe without suppression be, These are two barres against destructions wile: Paine without changing P cannot be raine, Raine without changing R can not be paine. Uer. 21 Both sunne and raine are portions to the ground, And ground is dust, and what is dust but nought? And what is nought is naught, with Alphaes sound, Yet euery earth the sunne and raine hath bought: The sunne doth shine on weeds, as well as flowers, The raine on both distills her weeping showers. Yet far be death from breath, annoy from ioy, Destruction from all happines allines, God will not suffer famine to destroy, The hungry appetite of vertues signes: These were in mid'st of fire, yet not harmed, In mid'st of water, yet but coolde, and warmed. Verse 22 And water-wet they were, not water-drowned, And fire-hot they were, not fire-burned, Their foes were both, whose hopes destruction crowned: But yet with such a crowne which ne'er returned, Heere fire and water brought both ioy and paine, To one disprofit, to the other gaine. The sunne doth thaw what colde hath freezde before, Vndoing what congealed ice had done, Yet heere the haile and snow did freeze the more, In hauing heat more piercing then the sunne A mournfull spectacle vnto their eyes, That as they die so their fruition dyes. Uer. 23 24 Fury once kindled with the coles of rage, Doth houer vnrecall'd, slaughters vntam'd; This wrath on fire no pitty coulde asswage, Because they pittilesse which should be blam'd: As one in rage, which cares not who he haue, Forgetting who to kil and who to saue. One deadly foe is fierce against the other, As vice with vertue, vertue against vice, Vice hartned by death his hartlesse mother, Vertue by God, the life of her deuice: Tis hard to hurt or harme a villany, Tis easy to do good to verity. Ver. 25 26 Is grasse mans meat, no it is cattells food, But man doth eat the cattell which eats grasse, And feeds his carcasse, with their nurst vp blood, Lengthning the liues which in a moment passe: Grasse is good food if it be ioynde with grace, Else sweeter foode may take a sowrer place, Is there such life in water and in bread? In fish, in flesh, in hearbs, in growing flowers, Wee eat them not aliue, wee eat them dead, What fruit then hath the word of liuing powers? How can wee liue with that which is still dead? Thy grace it is, by which we all are fed. Uer. 27 28 This is a liuing food, a blessed meat, Made to digest the burthen at our harts, That leaden-weighted food, which we first eat, To fill the functions of our bodies parts: An indigested heape, without a meane, Wanting thy grace, o Lord, to make it cleane. That ice which sulphure vapours could not thaw, That haile which piercing fier could not bore, The coole-hot sunne did melt their frosty iaw, Which neither heat nor fire, could pierce before: Then let vs take the spring-time of the day, Before the haruest of our ioyes decay. Verse 29 A day may be deuided as a yeare, Into foure climes, though of it selfe but one, The morne, the spring, the noone, the summers sphere, The haruest next, euening the winters moone: Then sowe new seeds in euery new dayes spring, And reape new fruite, in dayes olds euening. Else if too late: they will bee blasted seeds, If planted at the noonetide of their growing, Commencers of vnthankfull too late deeds, Set in the haruest of the reapers going: Melting like winter-ice against the sunne, Flowing like follies tide, and neuer done. Chapter XVII. Uerse 1 O flie the bed of vice the lodge of sin, Sleep not too long in your destructions plesures Amend your wicked liues, and new begin, A more new perfect way to heauens tresures: Oh rather wake and weep, then sleep and ioy, Waking is truth, sleep is a flattring toy. O take the morning of your instant good, Be not benighted with obliuious eye, Behold the sunne which kisseth Neptunes floud, And resalutes the world with open skie: Else sleep, and euer sleep: Gods wrath is great, And will not alter with too late intreat. Verse 2 Why wake I them which haue a sleeping minde, Oh words, sad sargiants to arrest my thoughts, If wakt, they cannot see, their eyes are blinde, Shut vp like windolets which sleep hath bought: Their face is broad awake, but not their hart, They dreame of rising, yet are loth to start. These were the practisers how to betray, The simple-righteous with beguiling words, And bring them in subiection to obay Their irreligious lawes and sins accords: But nights black coloured vale did cloud their will, And made their wish rest in performance skill. Uerse 3 The darkesome clouds, are summoners of raine, In being somthing blacke, and somthing darke, But cole-blacke clouds makes it poure downe amaine, Darting forth thunderbolts and lightnings sparke: Sin of it selfe is black, but black with black, Augments the heauie burthen of the back. They thought that sins could hide their sinfull shames, In being demi-clouds, and semi-nights, But they had clouds enough to make their games, Lodg'd in black couerings of obliuious nights: Then was their vice afraid to lie so darke, Troubled with visions from Alastors parke. Verse 4 The greater poyson, beares the greater sway, The greatest force, hath still the greatest face, Should night misse course, it would infect the day, With foule risse vapours from a humorous place, Vice hath some clouds, but yet the night hath more, Because the night was fram'd and made before. That sin which makes afraid, was then afraid, Although enchambred in a dens content, That would not driue back feare, which comes repai'd, Nor yet the ecchoes which the visions sent: Both sounds and showes, both words and action, Made apparitions satisfaction. Uer. 5 A night in pitchie mantle of distresse, Made thick with mists and oppsite to light, As if Cocytus mansion did possesse, The gloomy vapours of suppressing sight, A night more vgly then Alastors pack, Mounting all nights vpon his night-made back. The moone did mourne in sable-suted vale, The stars her handmaids were in black attire, All nightly visions tolde a hideous tale, The scrich-owles made the earth their dismall quire: The moone and stars diuide their twinckling eies, To lighten vice, which in obliuion lyes. Ver. 6 Onely appear'd a fire in dolefull blaze, Kindled by furies, raisde by enuious winds, Dreadfull in sight, which put them to amaze, Hauing before, furie-despairing minds: What haire in reading, would not stand vpright, What pen in writing, would not ceasse to write? Fire is Gods Angell, because bright and cleare, But this an euill Angell, because dread, Euill to them, which did already feare, A second death to them which were once dead: Annexing horror to dead strucken life, Connexing dolor to liue natures strife. Uerse 7 Deceit was then deceau'd, treason betrayde, Mischiefe beguilde, a night surpassing night, Vice fought with vice, and feare was then dismayde, Horror it selfe appal'd at such a sight: Sinns snare was then ensnarde, the fisher cought, Sinnes net was then entrapt, the fouler fought. Yet all this conflict, was but in a dreame, A show of substance, and a shade of truth, Illusions for to mocke in flattring theame, Beguiling mischiefe with a glasse of ruth: For boasts require a fall, and vaunts a shame, Which two vice had, in thinking but to game. Verse 8 Sinne tolde her creditours, she was a Queene, And now become reuenge, to right their wrong, With hony-mermaids speech alluring seene, Making new-pleasing words, with her olde tongue: If you be sick, quoth she, I'le make you whole, Shee cures the body, but makes sicke the soule. Safe is the body, when the soule is wounded, The soule is ioyfull in the bodies griefe, Ones ioy vpon the others sorrow grounded, Ones sorrow placed in the ones releefe: Quoth sin, feare nothing, know that I am heere, When shee alas, her selfe was sick for feare. Uer. 9 A promise worthy of derisions place, That feare shoulde helpe a feare, when both are one, Shee was as sick in hart, though not in face, With inward griefe, though not with outward mone: But shee claspt vp the closure of the tongue, For feate that words should do her body wrong. Cannot the body weepe without the eies? Yes and frame deepest canzons of lament, Cannot the body feare, without it lies Vpon the outward shew of discontent: Yes, yes, the deeper feare sits in the heart, And keeps the parliament of inward smart, Ver. 10 So sin did snare in minde, and not in face, The dragons saw, the hissing serpents sting, Some liu'd, some dide, some ran a fearefull race, Some did preuent that which ill fortunes bring: All were officious seruitours to feare, And her pale connizance in heart did weare. Malice condemnd her selfe guiltie of hate, With a malicious mouth of enuious spight, For Nemesis is her owne cruell fate, Turning her wrath vpon her owne delight: Wee need no witnes for a guiltie thought, Which to condemne it selfe a thousand brought. Uer. 11 12 For feare deceiues it selfe in being feare, It feares it selfe in being still afraid, It feares to weepe, and yet it sheds a teare, It feares it selfe, and yet it is obaid: The vsher vnto death, a death to doome, A doome to die in horrors fearefull toome. His owne betrayer, yet feares to betray, He feares his life, by reason of his name, He feares lament, because it brings decay, And blames himselfe in that he merites blame: He is tormented, yet denies the paine, He is the king of feare, yet loath to raigne. Uer. 13 His sons were they which slept and dreamt of feare, A waking sleepe, and yet a sleepy waking, Which passt that night more longer than a yeare, Being griefes prisners, and of sorrowes taking: Slept in nights dungeon insupportable, Lodgde in nights horror too indurable. Oh sleepe, the image of long-lasting woe, Oh waking image of long-lasting sleepe, The hollow caue where visions come and goe, Where serpents hisse, where mandrakes grone &amp; creep Oh fearefull shew, betrayer of a soule, Dieng each heart in white, each white in foule. Ver. 14 15 A guilefull hole, a prison of deceit, Yet nor deceit, nor guile, in being dead, Snare without snarer, net without a bait, A common lodge, and yet without a bed: A holow-sounding vault, knowne and vnknowne, Yet not for mirth, but too too well for mone. Tis a free prison a chainde libertie, A freedomes caue, a sergeant and a baile, It keepes close prisoners, yet doth set them free, Their clogges not yron, but a clog of waile: It stayes them not, and yet they cannot goe, Their chaine is discontent, their prison woe. Uer. 16 Still it did gape for more, and still more had, Like greedy auarice without content, Like to Auernus which is neuer glad, Before the dead-liude wicked soules be sent: Pull in thy head thou sorrowes tragedy, And leaue to practise thy olde cruelty. The merry shepheard cannot walke alone, Turning sweete Madrigals of haruests ioy, Caruing loues Roundelayes on euery stone, Hanging on euery tree some amorous toy: But thou with sorrow enterlines his song, Opening thy iawes of death to do him wrong. Uer. 17 18 Oh now I know thy chaine, thy clog, thy fetter, Thy freechainde prison, and thy clogged walke, Tis gloomy darknesse, sins eternall detter, Tis poysoned buds, from Acharonticke stalke: Sometime tis hissing winds which are their bands, Somtime inchanting birds which binds their hands Sometime the foaming rage of waters streame, Or clattring downe of stones vpon a stone, Or skipping beasts at Titans gladsome beame, Or roaring lions noyse at one alone: Or babbling Eccho tell-tale of each sound, From mouth to skie, from skie vnto the ground. Uer. 19 20 Can such like feares folow mans mortall pace, Within drie wildernes of wettest woe, It was Gods prouidence, his will, his grace, To make midnoone midnight in being so: Midnight with sin, midnoone where vertue lay, That place was night, all other places day. The sun not past the middle line of course, Did cleerely shine vpon each labours gaine, Not hindring daily toyle of mortall force, Nor clouding earth with any gloomy staine: Onely nights image was apparant there, With heauy-leaden appetite of feare. Chapter XVIII. Verse 1 You know the Eagle by her soaring wings, And how the Swallow takes a lower pich: Ye kno the day is clear, &amp; clearenes brings, And how the night is pore, thogh gloomy rich: This Eagle vertue is which mounts on hie, The other sin which hates the heauens eie. This day is wisedome, being bright and cleare, This night is mischiefe, being blacke and fowle, The brightest day doth wisedomes glory weare, The pitchie night puts on a blacker rowle: Thy saints (O Lord) were at their labors hire, At whose heard voyce the wicked did admire. Uer. 2 They thought that vertue had beene clothde in night, Captiue to darknesse, prisoner vnto hell, But it was sin it selfe, vice, and despight, (Whose wished harbours do in darknesse dwell, Vertues immortall soule had middaies light, Mischiefes eternall foule had middayes night. For vertue is not subiect vnto vice, But vice is subiect vnto vertues seate, One mischiefe is not thawed with others ice, But more adioynde to one, makes one more great: Sin vertues captiue is, and kneeles for grace, Requesting pardon for her rude-run race. Ver. 3 The tongue of vertues life cannot pronounce The doome of death, or death of dying doome, Tis mercifull, and will not once renounce Repentant teares to wash a sinfull roome: Your sin-shine was not sun-shine of delight, But shining sin in mischiefes sunny night. Now by repentance you are bathde in blisse, Blest in your bath, eternall by your deedes, Behold you haue true light, and can not misse, The heau'nly foode which your saluation feedes: True loue, true life, true light, your portions true, What hate, what strife, what night can danger you? Verse 4 Oh happy, when you parde your oregrowne faults, Your sin-like Eagles clawes past growth of time, All vndermined with destructions vaults, Full of olde filth, proceeding from new slime: Else had you beene deformed like to those, Which were your frinds, but now becom your foes Those which are worthy of eternall paine, Foes which are worthy of immortall hate, Dimming the glory of thy childrens gaine, With cloudy vapours set at darknesse rate: Making new lawes which are too olde in crime: Making old-wicked lawes, serue a new time. Uer. 5 Wicked? no: bloudy lawes, bloudy? yea worse, If any worse may haue a worser name, Men: oh no, murdrers, not of mens remorce, For they are shamefull, these exempt from shame: What? shall I call them slaughter-drinking hearts? To good a word for their too ill desarts? Murder was in their thoughts, they thought to slay, And who? poore infants; harmelesse innocents, But murder cannot sleepe, it will betray Her murdrous selfe, with selfe disparagements: One child poore remnant did reprooue their deeds, And God destroyd the bloudy murdrers seedes. Verse 6 Was God destroyer then? no he was iust, A iudge seuere, yet of a kinde remorce, Seuere to those in whome there was no trust, Kind to the babes which were of little force: Poor babes half murdred in whole murders thoght, Had not one infant their escaping wrought. Twas God which breathde his spirit in the childe, The liuely image of his selfe-like face, Twas God which drownd their childr?, which defilde Their thoughts with bloud, their hearts with murders place: For that nights tidings our old fathers ioyd, Because their foes by water were destroyd. Uer. 7 Was God a murdrer in this tragedy? No, but a iudge how bloud should be repaid: Wast he which gaue them vnto misery? No, twas themselues which miseries obaid: Their thoughts did kill and slay within their hearts, Murdring themselues, wo?ding their inward parts. When shines the sun, but when the moone doth rest? When rests the sun, but when the moone doth shine? When ioyes the righteous? when their foes are least, And when doth vertue liue? when vice doth pine: Vertue doth liue when villany doth die, Wisedome doth smile when misery doth crie. Ver. 8 The summer dayes are longer than the nights, The winter nights are longer than the dayes, They shew both vertues loues and vices spites, Sins lowest fall, and wisedomes highest raise: The night is foe to day, as naught to good, The day is foe to night, as feare to food. A king may weare a crowne, but full of strife, The outward shew of a small-lasting space, Mischiefe may liue, but yet a deadly life, Sorrow may greeue in heart, and ioy in face: Vertue may liue disturbd with vices paine, God sends this vertue a more better raigne. Uer. 9 She doth possesse a crowne, and not a care, Yet cares, in hauing none, but selfe-like awe, She hath a scepter without care or feare, Yet feares the Lord, and careth for the lawe: Asmuch as she doth rise, so much sin falles, Subiect vnto her law, slaue to her calles. Now righteousnesse beares sway, and vice put downe, Vertue is Queene, treading on miscchiefes head, The lawe of God sancited with renowne, Religion placde in wisedomes quiet bed: Now ioyfull hymnes are tuned by delight, And now we liue in loue, and not in spite. Ver. 10 Strong-hearted vices sobs haue pierst the ground, In the deepe cesterne of the centers breast, Wayling their liuing fortunes with dead sound, Accents of griefe, and actions of vnrest: It is not sin her selfe, it is her seede, Which drownd in sea, lies there for seas foule weed. It is the fruit of murders bloudy wombe, The lost fruition of a murdrous race, A little stone which would haue made a tombe, To bury vertue with a sin-bolde face: Me thinkes I heare the ecchoes of the vaults, Sound and resound their old-new-weeping faults. Uer. 11 View the dead carcasses of humaine state, The outsides of the soule, case of the harts, Beholde the king, beholde the subiects fate, Beholde each lim and bone of earthen arts: Tell me the difference then of euery thing, And who a subiect was, and who a king. The selfe same knowledge lies in this dead scene, Valde to the tragike cipresse of lament, Beholde that man, which hath a maister beene, That king, which would haue climde aboue content, Beholde their slaues, by them vpon the earth, Haue now as high a seat as great a birth. Verse 12 The ground hath made all euen which were odde, Those equall, which had inequalitie, Yet all alike were fashioned by God In bodies forme, but not in harts degree: One difference had, in scepter, crowne, and throne, Yet crown'd, rul'd, plac'd, in care in griefe in mone. For it was care to weare a crowne of griefe, And it was griefe to weare a crowne of care, The king deaths subiect, death his empires theefe, Which makes vnequall state, and equall fare, More dead then were aliue, and more to die, Then would be buried with a mortall eie. Ver. 13 O well-fed earth with ill digesting food, O well-ill food, because both flesh and sin, Sin made it sick, which neuer did it good, Sin made it well, her well, doth worse begin: The earth more hungry then was Tantall's iawes, Had flesh and blood held in her earthen pawes. Now could beleefe some quiet harbour finde, When all her foes were mantled in the ground, Before their sin-enchauntments made it blind, Their magick arts, their negromantick sound: Now truth hath got some place to speake and heare. And what so ere shee speaks, she doth not feare, Ver. 14 15 16 When Phœbes axletree, was limnd with pale, Pale, which becommeth night, night which is blacke, Hem'd round about with gloomy shining vale, Borne vp by cloudes, mounted on silence backe? And when nights horses, in the running waine, Oretook the middest of their iournies paine. Thy worde ô Lord descended from thy throne, The royall mansion of thy powers command, As a fierce man of war in time of mone, Standing in midst of the destroyed land: And brought thy precept? as a burning steauen, Reaching from heau? to earth, from earth to heauen Uer. 17 Now was the night far spent, and mornings wings, Flew through sleepie thoughts and made them dream, Hying apace to welcome sunny springs, And giue her time of day to Phœbus beame: No sooner had she flowne vnto the east, But dreamy passage did disturb their rest. And then like sleepie-waking harts and eyes, Turn'd vp the fainting closures of their faces, Which betweene day and night in slumber lies, Keeping their wakie, and their sleepie places: And loe, a fearing dreame, and dreaming feare. Made euery eye let fall a sleepie teare. Ver. 18 19 A teare halfe wet from they themselues halfe liude, Poore drie-wet teare, too moyst a wet-drie face, A white-red face, whose red-white colour striude, To make anotamy of either place: Two champions both resolu'd in faces field, And both had halfe yet either scornde to yeeld. They which were wont to mount aboue the ground, Hath leaden-quick-glude sinewes forst to lie, One here one there in prison, yet vnbound, Heart-striuing life and death to liue and die: Nor were they ignorant of fates decree, In being tolde before what they should bee. Uer. 20 There falsest visions shewde the truest cause, False because fantasies, true because haps, For dreames though kindled by sleep-idle pause, Sometime true indices of dangers claps: As well doth proue in these sin-sleeping lines, That dreames are falsest shewes, and truest signes. By this time death had longer pilgrimage, And was encaged in more liuing breasts, Now euery ship had fleeting anchorage, Both good and bad were punisht with vnrests: But yet Gods heauie plague indur'd not long, For anger quencht her selfe with her selfe wrong. Ver. 21 Not so, for heat can neuer coole with heat, Nor colde can warme a colde, nor ice thaw ice, Anger is fire, and fire is angers meat, Then how can anger coole her hot deuice? The sunne, doth thaw the ice, with melting harme, Ice cannot coole the sunne, which makes it warme. It was celestiall fire, terrestriall cold, It was celestiall colde, terrestriall fire, A true and holy praier which is bolde, To coole the heat of angers hot desire: Pronounced by a seruant of thy word, To ease the miseries which wraths afford. Uerse 22 Weapons and wit are double linkes of force, If one vnknit they both haue weaker strength, The longer be the chaine, the longer corse, If measurde by duplicitie of length: If weapons faile wit is the better part, Wit failing: weapons haue the weaker hart. Praier is weake in strength, yet strong in wit, And can do more then strength, in being wise, Thy word, ô Lord, is wisdome, and in it, Doth lie more force, then forces can surprize: Man did not ouercome his foes with armes. But with thy word, which conquers greater harms Verse 23 That word it was, with which the world was framde, The heauens made, mortalitie ordain'd, That word it was, with which all men were namde, In which one word, there are all words containde: The breath of God, the life of mortall state, The enimie to vice, the foe to hate. When death prest downe the sin-dead-liuing soules, And draw'd the curtaine of their seeing day, This word was vertues shield, and deaths controules, Which shielded those which neuer went astray: For when the dead did die, and end in sin, The liuing had assurance to begin. Uer. 24 Are all these deeds accomplisht in one word, O soueraigne word, cheefe of all words and deeds, O salue of saftie, wisdomes strongest sword, Both food, and hunger, which both starues, and feeds: Food vnto life, because of liuing power, Hunger to those, whome death and sins deuoure. For they which liu'd, were those which vertue lou'd, And those which vertue lou'd, did loue to liue, Thrice happy these, whom no destruction mou'd, Shee present there, which loue and life did giue: They bore the mottoes of eternall fame, On diapasans of their fathers name. Ver. 25 Here death did change his pale to purple hue, Blushing against the nature of his face, To see such bright aspects, such splendent view, Such heau'nly paradice of earthly grace: And hid with lifes quick force, his ebon dart, Within the crannies of his meagre hart. Descending to the place from whence he came, With rich-stor'd chariot of fresh bleeding wounds, Sore-greeued bodies, from a soules-sick name, Sore-greeued soules, in bodies-sin-sick sounds: Death was afraide to stay where life should be, For they are foes and cannot well agree. Chapter XIX. Uerse 1 2 Avant destroier with thy hungry iawes, Thy thirsty heart, thy longing ashie bones, The righteous liue, they be not in thy lawes, Nor subiects to thy deepe oppressing mones. Let it suffice that we haue seene thy show, And tasted but the shadow of thy woe. Yet stay and bring thy empty car againe, More ashie vessells do attend thy pace, More passengers expect thy comming waine, More groaning pilgrimes long to see thy face: Wrath now attends the passage of misdeeds, And thou shalt still be stor'd with soules that bleeds. Verse 3 Some lie halfe dead, while others dig their graues, With weake-forst teares, to moyst a long-drie ground But teares on teares, in time will make whole waues, To bury sin with ouerwhelming sound: Their eies for mattocks serue, their teares for spades, And they them selues, are sextons by their trades. What is their fee? lament, their paiment? woe, Their labour? waile, their practise? miserie, And can their conscience serue to labour so, Yes, yes, because it helpeth villanie: Though eies did stand in teares, and teares in eyes, They did another folishnes deuise. Uer. 4 5 So that what praier did, sin did vnd oe, And what the eies did win the heart did loose, Whom vertue reconcilde, vice did forgoe, Whom vertue did forgoe, that vice did choose: Oh had their hearts beene iust, eyes had bin winners Their eyes were iust, but hearts new sins beginners. They digd true graues with eyes, but not with hearts, Repentance in their face, vice in their thought, Their deluing eies did take the Sextons partes, The heart vndid the labour which eies wrought: A new strange death was portion for their toyle, While vertue sate as iudge to end the broyle. Ver. 6 Had tongue bin ioynde with eies, tong had not strai'd, Had eyes bin ioyn'd to heart, heart then had seene, But oh, in wanting eye-sight it betrai'd, The dungeon of misdeeds where it had beene: So, many liuing in this orbe of woe, Haue heau'd-vp eyes, but yet their hearts are low. This chaunge of sin, did make a chaunge of feature, A new strange death, a misery vntoulde, A new reforme of every olde-new creature, New seruing offices, which time made olde: New liuing vertue, from an olde dead sin, Which ends in ill what doth in good begin. Uer. 7 When death did reape the haruest of despight, The wicked eares of sin, and mischiefes seed, Filling the mansion of eternall night, With heauy-leaden clods of sinfull breed: Life sowde the plants of immortalitie, To welcome olde-made new felicity. The clouds, the gloomy curtaines of the aire, Drawne and redrawne with the foure-winged winds, Made all of borrowed vapours, darkesome faire; Did ouershade their tents, which vertue findes, The red seas deepe, was made a drie trod way, Without impediment, or stop, or stay. Uer. 8 9 The thirsty windes with ouertoyling puffes, Did drinke the ruddy-oceans water drie, Tearing the Zones hot-cold, whole-ragged ruffes, With ruffling conflicts in the field of skie: So, that drie earth did take wet waters place, With sandy mantle, and hard grounded face. That way which neuer was a way before, Is now a troden path, which was vntrod, Through which the people went, as on a shoare, Defended by the stretcht-out arme of God: Praising his wondrous workes, his mighty hand, Making the land of sea, the sea of land. Ver. 10 That breast where anger slept, is mercies bed, That breast where mercy wakes is angers caue; When mercie liues, then Nemesis is dead, And one for eithers coarse makes others graue: Hate furrowes vp a graue, to bury loue, And loue doth presse downe hate, it cannot moue. This breast is God, which euer wakes in both, Anger is his reuenge, mercy his loue, He sent them flies in steade of cattels growth, And multitudes of frogges for fishes stroue: Here was his anger shewne, and his remorse, When hee did make dry land of water course. Uer. 11 The sequele prooues what actor is the chiefe, All things beginning knowes, but none their end, The sequele vnto mirth, is weeping griefe, As doth mishaps with happinesse contend: For both are agents in this orbe of weeping, And one doth wake, when other falles a sleeping. Yet, should mans eies pay tribute euery hower, With tributarie teares to sorrowes shrine, He would all drowne himselfe with his owne shower And neuer finde the leafe of mercies line: They in Gods anger wailde, in his loue ioyd, Their loue brought lust, ere loue had lust destroyd. Uer. 12 The sun of ioy dride vp their teare-wet eies, And sate as Lord vpon their sobbing hart, For when one comfort liues, one sorrow dies, Or ends in mirth what it begunne in smart: What greater griefe than hunger-starued moode? What greater mirth than satisfying foode? Quailes from the fishy bosome of the sea, Came to their comforts which were liuing starude, But punishments fell in the sinners way, Sent downe by thunderbolts which they deserude: Sin-fed these sinners were, hate cherished, According vnto both they perished. Uer. 13 Sin-fed, because their food was seed of sins, And bred new sin with olde-digested meate, Hate cherished, in being hatreds twins, And sucking cruelty from tygers teate: Was it not sin to erre and goe astray? Was it not hate to stop a strangers way? Was it not sin to see, and not to know? Was it not sin to knowe, and not receiue? Was it not hate to be a strangers foe, And make them captiues which did them releeue? Yes, it was greatest sin first for to leaue them, And it was greatest hate last to deceiue them. Ver. 14 Oh hungry Canniballes which know no fill, But still do staruing feed, and feeding starue, How could you so deceiue? how could you spill Their louing selues, which did your selues preserue? Why did you sucke your pellican to death, Which fed you too too wel with his owne breath? Oh say that cruelty can haue no lawe, And then you speake with a milde-cruel tongue, Or say that auarice lodgde in your iawe, And then you do your selues but little wrong: Say what you will, for what you say is spight, Gainst ill-come strangers which did merite right. Uer. 15 You lay in ambush, oh deceitfull snares, Inticing baites, beguiling centinells, You added griefe to griefe, and cares to cares, Teares vnto weeping eies where teares did dwell: O multitudes of sin, legions of vice, Which thawes with sorrow sorrowes frozen ice. A banquet was preparde, the fare, deceit, The dishes, poyson, and the cup despight, The table, mischiefe, and the cloth a bait, Like spinners web t'entrap the strange flies flight: Pleasure was strewd vpon the top of paine, Which once digested, spread through euery vaine. Uer. 16 Oh ill conductors of misguided feete, Into a way of death, a path of guile, Poore pilgrimes which their owne destruction meete, In habitations of an vnknowne Ile: Oh had they left that broad deceiuing way, They had beene right and neuer gone astray. But marke the punishment which did ensue, Vpon those ill-misleading villanies, They blinded were themselues with their selfe view, And fell into their owne made miseries: Seeking the entrance of their dwelling places, With blinded eies, and darke misguided faces. Ver. 17 Lo, here was snares ensnar'd, and guiles beguilde, Deceit, deceiu'd, and mischiefe was mislead, Eies blinded sight, and thoughts the hearts defilde, Life liuing in aspects, was dying dead: Eyes thought for to misleade, and were mislead: Feete went to make mis-treads, and did mis-treade. At this proud fall the elements were glad, And did embrace each other with a kisse, All things were ioyfull which before were sad, The pilgrimes in their way, and could not misse: As when the sound of musick, doth resound With changing tune; so did the changed ground. Uer. 18 The birds forsooke the ayre, the shheepe the fould, The Eagle pitched low, the Swallow hie, The Nightingale did sleepe and vncontrould Forsoke the prickle of her natures eie: The seely worme was friends with all her foes, And suckt the dew-teares from the weeping rose. The sparrow timde the larkes sweet melody, The larke in silence sung a dirge of dole, The linnet helpt the larke in malady The swans forsooke the quire of billow-roule: The drie-land foule, did make the sea their nest, The wet-sea fish did make the land their rest. Verse 19 The swans the queristers which did complaine, In inward feeling of an outward losse, And filde the quire of waues with lauing paine, (Yet dauncing in their waile, with surges tosse:) Forsooke her cradle billow-mountaine bed, And hies her vnto land there to be fed. Her sea-fare now is land-fare of content, Olde change, is changed new yet all is change, The fishes are her food, and they are sent, Vnto drie land, to creep, to feed, to range: Now coolest water cannot quench the fire, But makes it proud in hottest hot desire. Uer. 20 The eu'ning of a day, is morne to night, The eu'ning of a night is morne to day, The one is Phœbes clime, which is pale-bright, The other Phœbus, in more light array: Shee maks the mountaines limp in chil-cold snowe Hee melts their eies and makes them weep for woe. His beames ambassadors of his hot will, Through te transparent element of aire, Doth only his warme ambassage fulfill, And melts the icie iaw of Phœbes heyre: Yet those, though firie flames could not thaw cold, Nor breake the frosty glew of winters mould. Ver. 21 Here nature slue herselfe, or at the least Did tame the passage of her hot aspects, All things haue nature to be worst or best, And must encline to that, which she affects: But nature mist herselfe, in this same part, For shee was weake, and had not natures hart. Twas God which made her weake, and makes her strong, Resisting vice, assisting righteousnes, Assisting, and resisting, right, and wrong, Making this Epilogue in equallnes: Twas God his peoples aide, their wisedomes frend, In whom I did begin, with whom I end. A Ioue surgit opus: de Ioue finit opus.</field>
   </doc>
</add>