<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Wither, George, 1588-1667</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Wither, George, 1588-1667</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">wither george 1588 1667</field>
      <field name="author_text">Wither, George, 1588-1667</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1880's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.1998.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1880</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464439</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Vox Vulgi ; A poem in censure of the Parliament of 1661, by George Wither, now first edited from the original MS., together with an unpublished letter from Wither to John Thurloe, by Rev. W. Dunn Macray</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Vox Vulgi ; A poem in censure of the Parliament of 1661, by George Wither, now first edited from the original MS., together with an unpublished letter from Wither to John Thurloe, by Rev. W. Dunn Macray</field>
      <field name="title_facet">vox vulgi</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">vox vulgi</field>
      <field name="title_text">Vox Vulgi ; A poem in censure of the Parliament of 1661, by George Wither, now first edited from the original MS., together with an unpublished letter from Wither to John Thurloe, by Rev. W. Dunn Macray</field>
      <field name="year_display">1880</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1880</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1880</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464439&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464439&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Wither, George, 1588-1667&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;wither george 1588 1667&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Vox Vulgi ; A poem in censure of the Parliament of 1661, by George Wither, now first edited from the original MS., together with an unpublished letter from Wither to John Thurloe, by Rev. W. Dunn Macray&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;vox vulgi&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1880&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1880&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Wither, George&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1588&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1667&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Vox Vulgi&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A poem in censure of the Parliament of 1661, by George Wither, now first edited from the original MS., together with an unpublished letter from Wither to John Thurloe, by Rev. W. Dunn Macray&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Oxford&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;James Parker&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1880&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp4376&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;xi, 35 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Vox Vulgi&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A poem in censure of the Parliament of 1661, by George Wither, now first edited from the original MS., together with an unpublished letter from Wither to John Thurloe, by Rev. W. Dunn Macray&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 53 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries, introductory and editorial matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Square brackets denote editorial insertions or emendations. He that rebuketh shall afterwards finde more favour then hee that flattereth. Pro. 28. 23. Hee that being often reprooved hardneth his neck shall suddenly be destroyed without remedy. Pro. 29. For both they who condemn the Righteous and justify the wicked are abhominable to the Lord. To the right honorable the Earle of Clarendon Lord Chanceller of England. Sir, he that hath nought left, nor ought to do Save only what Occasion tempts him to, Shall need the influence of some such Star As they who mark your motion say you are: And such a light, whereby to steer my course, To mee may vsefull be, lest I make worse (By acting in the dark) what fame I would Make, rather, to be better, if I could. Though, therfor, what I need will seem to be Declard in vaine, to them who need not mee, I now adventer to try what successe God's Providence will give to this adresse, And am resolved no eie henceforth shall veiwe This Welcome-Home till it be seen of you, In hopes 'twill in your sight find so much grace That you unblamd, at least, will [let] it passe, Though not approvd; for, if I may beleive That character which common-fame doth give Of you, and of that prudent moderation Wherby you labour to reduce this nation To better concord, and her wounds as well Vpon the left side as the right to heale, (Which doubtles is the nearest way to bring Content both to the People and the King), I shall presume that both his interest And theirs you essay to mannage for the best, And persevere in acting to that End Whereto God your advancement did intend, Which being well performd, He that begun Vpon the ruines of old Clarendon To raise your house, will raise it more and higher Than I dare say, or you ought to desire. If This, or I, or ought that may appear To be in mee (by what is written here) Shall in your judgment any way conduce To publick service (or to private use Not thereunto repugnant), you of those Are hereby tendered a free dispose, In order hereunto, without regard To any selfends, or of more reward Then opportunities and meanes to do What conscience of my duties calls mee to. Which I shall never want, because to mee Neglects as healpfull as respects will be, And poverty imbitterd with disgrace, No lesse than wealth and powre in honor'd place, Will an assistance bring to cary on What is of mee required to be done. To add more will be needles; for the wise Cann make good use of that which Fooles despise, Or think impertinent. You have on high A worke to do, and so, belowe, haue I. Wee are both servants to one God and King, Although in offices much differing, And, howsoeuer you shall entertaine This my Adresse, it will not be in vaine, For somwhat it hath hinted which doth need Both your, and my, and evry reader's heed. I may be someway fitt to be employd, And by this Nation to be quite destroyd Deserve not, though to God-ward much to blame. But, whatsoere I seem, (my Lord), I am Your honors humble servant, Nec Habeo, nec Careo, nec Curo N? h?, n? c?, n? c?. A Postscript. Your servant on your candor so presumes That since this to your hand in private comes It shall not (if offensive it may seeme) Made vse of be to disadvantage him; For he's as well pleas'd that should be exprest Which showes what's worst in him, as what is best. Et, Fiat Voluntas Dei. VOX VULGI. A Welcome home from the Counties, Citties and Burroughs to their Prevaricating Trustees, with a premised savinge of the honor of the every faithfull and discreet Member of Parliament. “Words are but winde, and when that they are spoken “Work, for the most parte, but like Bladders broken “About mens eares, to whatsoever ends “The Speaker or his hearers them intends. “I'le, notwithstanding, upon some of those “To represent this nation lately chose “Bestowe a fewe words; and resolved am “To speake unto them in the people's name, “Whereof since opportunity I have “Already offred me: Freinds, by your leave, “Stay, and be pleasd to hear without offence “What shall be spoke before you goe from hence.” Wee not a litle troubled are this day To thinck what cause is given vs to say What wee must speake, and how wee may divide Them who have well deservd from those wee chide, For they so intermixt among them are Whose Reputations vnto vs are dear, That neither he who was to cleave in two An apple on his childes head with his bow, Nor he who shott the Centaure without harme Vnto his wife when shee was in his arme, Had much more cause than wee haue to beware That not mislevelled our arrowes are. But wee will runn the hazzard now begun, For, them should none reprove who haue misdone, The world would quite be ouerwhelmd with evill, And all, at last, runn headlong to the Devill. Are you so soon adjornd? and dare you come To shewe your faces here againe, at home? Hold vp your browes, wee pray, that wee may see Whether with brasse or steel they hardned be: So, 'tis enough: Good God! what impudence In them appeareth! and how little sense Seem these to haue of that disreputation Which they haue brought upon this English nation By turning of their glorie into shame, And rendring those partakers of their blame Whose rationall debates and sober voices Were ouerwhelmed by their brutish noises, And whom, wee hope, God will distinguish from Those Brutes who, for the most parte, are become Our Representatives in nothing more Then in those sinns which wee are plauged for. And you, by some effects that wee haue seene, Do rather seeme elected to haue bene Our Hangmen, to haue had our clothes for Fees, Then for our welfare to be made Trustees, For since your meetinge, much a doe to saue vs The King had by the pardon which he gaue vs, And no provision by your means wee had Whereby our Greevances abatement had (?) Which disrespect did wee forbare to veiwe Wee to our selves should be as false as you, And thoughts from question should no more be fre Ere long, then now our words and actions be. Pray, what new title is conferd upon Your Worships, for the service you have done? The Blessed, or the Healing, Parliament You never shall be calld by our consent; Nor were those epithites upon the last With our free vote or approbation plac't, (Although they who ascribed what was thought Then merited, performd but what they ought.) Our wounds (if not inlarged) were left bleeding, So that newe mischeefs evry day are breeding Because they had not learnd to be so wise To know that Mercy more then Sacrifize Doth pacify the wrath of God and man, And tenn times more then extream rigor can. By worthy managing of that great blessing Whereof wee had almost a full possessing, (Or li[ke]lyhoods of timely settling that Which both our King and wee then aimed at), Things might haue that effected long ere this Which would haue much improvd our happines. Whereas, whateuer wee shall now endeavor, A setlement indangerd is for ever, Or so to be obstructed by oure juggling That, like beares in a nett, wee may ly struggling Till we are breathless, or vntill those fewe Who are yet sober grow as madd as you, And make thenceforth both Parlaments and Kings To be reputed despicable things. For carnall polecies the work hath spoyld And faire expedients offred are so foild (As in all former ages and of late They often were, when to a King or State God tendred them), that what shall now be done Our wills or witts dependeth not vpon But only our fate Concuring with celestiall Wee never heard your judgments praised much Or moderation; but that you are such Quickwitted things we heare as haue not bene In any British Parlaments yet seen; For, wheras they consumd much time in stating What was to them proposd and in debating, You, at first hearing, could without dispute All arguments with noise alone confute, And absolutly be resolued too In hardest matters what yee list to do In spight of reason, both to their vexation And wonderment who to more moderation Would faine haue you reducd; to scornfull jeering You more inclined then to patient hearing; Whereon, if that shall to the publike wrong Which may expected be ere long, (sic) They who unborne and unbegotten be To blame you will haue no lesse cause then wee. Your guiltines is great, and so is our Who did such giddy Ratlebraines impowre, Or could beleeue that men of sober wit Might be elected in a druncken fit, Or persons of debauched conuersation Prove vsefull to the wellfare of the nation, Or that they any way advance could bring Vnto the reall honor of the King; For few who know you not can well conceive What men some of you were, much lesse beleive. But peradventure this experiment May henceforth make vs wary to prevent Such oversights, or else make other some To be more wise then wee in times to come. And cheefly to that purpose this was writ That your Repentance to For wee a better principle embrace Then to delight ourselues in your disgrace; And therefor, though your faults we shall not spare, Wee of your names and persons will haue care, So likewise would, had they Of your estates though you had other. Excuse vs though in termes we bitter bee, For men more holy and more meek then wee In such concernements as these are wherin You haue of late prevaricaters bene, When such like attributes haue bene their due Did vilify as rightous men as you. Looke not so bigg vpon vs; neither stare So wide; For wee with much ado forbear To kick you out of Town, when wee well weigh How barbrously the trust you did betray By your endevoring to haue made voyd Our Auncient Charters, and to haue destroyd The selfsame powre wherby to you wee gaue That very powre which you employed haue Ingratefully against vs, for no use Which to the Common welfare could conduce: For, to that end, wee shall be well content Our Priviledges and Infranchisement To wave as need requires; because no Place Or Person should retaine in such a case Prerogatives or Freedoms, no, not Kings Or Parlaments, if it in hazzard brings That Peace, that Honor, or that Interest Wherein a General welfare doth consist. But you had other ends; and, whilst wee live, Forget wee cannot, though wee may forgive, How willfully you prosecuted those To whome your malice only made you Foes; And how, as if yee thirsted after blood, You sought, een in despight of men and God, Of that Indulgence vs to have bereaven Which gratiously the King had freely given, Though not a few of you as guilty be As any, and do need as much as wee The selfsame pardon. Some of you perchance Complide with others meerly for advance In way of profit, or to please their wives By gaining of some Court appellatives, Which is a weaknes whereby wiser men And good are byassd now and then, That wee are plesed to connive in this At you and them; For though you did amisse It may illustrate so the constancy And perseverance of [his] Maiestie In his late Act of Grace, and so much tends Vnto his honor, that it makes amends For that wherein to vs you gave offence, And wee'l ascribe it to God's Providence; Who, if He should to you be so severe As yee vnto your Benefactors were (Or as you are to many a one of those Whome (though your Friends) you still pursue as Foes) You would with shame descend into your graves And your Posterity be voted Slaves. For never would this Nation's wounds be closd If what hath bene by some of you proposd Had tooke effect; or were the King inclind To no more Mercy then as yet wee find In some of you, he might be healped on To act what by a Tirant could be done. So far forth as within your powr it lies, You haue exposed all our Liberties To such a hazzard that they may be lost For euer, if not purchast with more cost Than wee can bear: and you in vs thereby Haue also raised such a Jealosie Of Parlaments, that wee beginn to fear They never will bee better then you are Vntill that Kingdom commeth which will bring All Nations in sub[j]ection to one King, Or, all to make a passage therevnto, God shall chuse one man out of evry two Who into publike trust shall be elected. For what can reasonably be expected From Persons chosen as they lately were But an increase of all Prophanes here, Corrupting Princes of the best condition, Or setling of Iniustice, Superstition, And Wickednes or Tiranny by Lawe? That which should keep the worst of men in awe Affrights the best. The brutish Lusts of men Are more indulged and promoted then The will of God; True conscientiousnes Is either cried downe or favord lesse Then grosse hypocrisy; those wisest are Who take of good or ill lest heed or care, Regarding nothing but to live at ease, Or how their sensuality to please. The greatest number negligent are growne Both of the publike welfare and their owne, Yea therto mischeevus, and had the Peers As forward beene as many Commoners In some particulers by them intended Wee peradventer had bene lesse befreinded. In these times truly sayd it cannot be Of Parlaments, that God, the King, or Wee Their Makers were: For those wee lately hadd Haue, for the most parte, by themselves bene made, Which being well considerd nothing more Hath happned then wee might haue looked for. To do the common work, few men will pay, Intreat, make frends, go, run and ride, but they Who, therein, seek themselues, and looke for fruite Either in profit or in vaine repute: And such as these do in a commonweal Make more wounds and deseases then they heal; Which to prevent, the Romans, who foresaw What mischeevs it begat, ordaind a lawe, And to neglect it when they did begin Corruption and all tiranny broke in. As zealous wee acknowledge these to be As Jehu when he cried out, Come and see. In those Formalities they are devout Which from the holy temple is (sic) shut out Within the fore-court, upon them be By whome [?] the holy Citty is trodd downe. So far forth as the Cause of God, the King, Or of the People, an advance may bring Vnto their Vengance, or to their Ambition, Their Wealth, or any sensuall fruition, They will not in the least punctilio faile To prosecute it with toungue, tooth and naile, Or with those exprobations (?) which their hate Can add, a shewe [of] guilt to aggravate In those whome they disfavour; but no further, Be their crimes treason, heresy, or murther, Shall those crimes charged be then upon them Though others they as justly might condemn. Yea, (as if cheefely it were their designe All bonds of concord, Civell and Devine, To break in peeces) they haue tride this Nation With almost evry kinde of Provocation, Which may occasion either an increase Of Discord or infringment of their peace, Charging the blame of what doth misbefall On them whome they Phanaticks please to call; Though if words, deeds, and clothes them shew vs may, Phanaticks none so truly are as they. Was this the kindnes which to vs you ment When so profusely your estates you spent In druncken Feasts and Banquetts, to besott The Rable, who on Gaudes and Feathers dote, That they in their distempratures might sell Their, and our, auncient Birthrights for a meal Or Dish of drinck? Did you consume your wealth In Bribes for this? and quaff away your health In Drinck oblations to the King, with shewes Of Loyaltie, that you might him abuse And ruine vs? Procurd you from your betters For this end their commendatory letters On your behalues? Did you for this pretend The Peoples weal and slavishly descend To fawne on vs, and to alure them to A hope of what you never ment to do? So seems it. But things past or out of date Now to recall them back it is too late: We therfor must pursue another course, We then were very Fooles, and you were worse, Which being knowne, we hope to be so wise That henceforth Flutter-mice and butterflies Shall never more delude vs: for our sight Beginns to clear, and finde a better light Then was that Ignis ffatuus wherwith you Befoold vs whilst wee did the same pursue. They who can neither vnderstand nor see Reformd perhaps may by ther feeling be. Wee now perceiue it must be rather sense Of mischeeves and of some ill consequence, Then sollid Arguments, which at this season Will make men either capable of reason Or keep them in their witts; And that, unlesse The Kings humanity and prudentnes Shall theirs exceed in whom both hee and wee Confided haue, all at a losse will be; Or rather (as Affaires at present stand) If God Himself setts not His healping hand. For they and wee our Ends have driven on So bedlam-like that wee haue pleased none Or very fewe. Evn they that wisest are, And active in the highst and safest sphear, Are not secure from that which them disturbs By countermotions in the lower Orbes. All Parties are in some respects to blame, And liable to such rebuke and shame As might induce them to forgive each other Before they are destroyed altogether. Dissatisfide men of all judgment are, The Rich, the Pore, the Roundhead, Cavaleer, And they who at the first did in their choice Of such as these much glory and reioice. Yea, Citty, Court, and Cuntry (if wee may Give credit vnto what wee hear them say) So doubtfull are to what their Actings tend That they much wish their powre were at an end, And that (if it were possible) our doome Might from one heart and from one spirit come, To setle Vnitie; For sure are wee An Vniformity cann never be Till all the men on earth are of one feature, Of one Minde, of one Language and one Stature. Tis high time to be sober men, and do To others as wee would be done vnto; For all affaires are strangely interrupted, In manners men are more corrupted, At variance things Divine and Civill be, And none to reconcile them wee yet see; Old Animosities are still fomented, Oppressive Projects are afresh invented, As if it were slipt wholly out of thought What troubles to this Realm they lately brought. Neglected Private wrongs and Suffrers are, As if the Gen'rall Welfare no whit were Concernd in Individualls, though that sinn Made first those Breaches which at last let in That Vengance which inevitable brings Destruction both to Commonweales and Kings. New Greevances are evry day begun, Oppressing those who were before vndone, And sleights devised, as if for the nones When they haue eat our flesh to pick our bones. Yet numbred it will be among our Crimes If wee deny that these are happy times. The Fatt kine are devoured by the pore, Who yet are still as leane as heretofore; So that wee forced are to give Releefs To Publike wants as if it were by breefs Vouchsafd to beggers, and to raise supplies Out of the Peoples sinns and penuries; And many private Famelies, bereft Of all their Livelyhoods, are wholly left By Charity alone to be preserved, Or els to begg, or steal, or to be starved. Both Confiscations and the Warrs of late Made not so many thousands desolate, Breadles and harborles; nor were then more Pore men quite ruinde, or Rich men made [pore] (Nor half so many brought to great destresse) As are at this time, calld a time of peace! Yet wee still fayt, and brave it, sing and laugh, And roare, and whore, and swear, and curse, and quaff, As if in tryumph hither riding in The Skarlet whore vpon the Beast had bene. Those snuffs had not now flashed out so high, Nor stunck so as they will do when they dy, Had all bene but as modest as some were Who had the Title of a Cavaleer; For not a few of them, though they and wee Unhappily did lately disagree By some misprisions, do themselves comply In principles of faith and honesty, Could their disturbers have been moderated, And things proposed in modesty debated; Whereas their Indiscretion whom wee blame Hath unbound and brought all [things] out of frame, That if God plese not to vouchsafe releef These are but the beginnings of our greef: For, doubtles, better fruites haue bene expected Then His great mercy showne hath yet effected. Wee know, [and] what wee know doth vs provoke To speake so boldly that which wee haue spoke, And wee appeal to God and these three nations Whether or no these be false imputations, Or whether iust exceptions may be took To any line or word that wee haue spoke. God blesse the King, and so anoint his eies That he may see wherein his saftie lies, Vouchsafe him such a circumcized eare That he may Truths with approbation hear, And him discerne who really intends His weal, from those [who] seek but their owne ends, Lest they so difficult his ways do make That he cann neither forward go nor back, Or may be brought againe into a wood, And rotten Oke, with tales of Robinhood. Let Civill things with natures Lawes accord, Church-Discipline be squard out by the Word. Permit not any that (?) they step in our consciences to faith [?] Move him to be more mercifull and iust Then they haue bene in whome wee plac't our Trust. His judgment at this present so improve, That by our Failings an increase of Love With honor he may gaine; In time prevent The purposes of men malevolent, And vnto evry faithfull one dispence Justice and Mercy with Indifference. And since God without bloodshed brought him in, Let that which heretofore pourd forth hath bene Suffice for what is past, and let no more In time to come be shed vpon that score. And whome he gives life let him so provide That living them to have died. Thus doing shall his powre and life And turne our mourning to a cherfull (?) song. By him this seems in parte to be begun, And so far also to be caried on As meanes hath bene afforded thervnto, If wee well weigh the works he had to do, And for how many diffring maladies, Dissenting persons, and Antipathies, He must provide a cure. Let us therfor, Vntill God him enables to do more, Attend with patience, and not trouble him In what is to be done; but give him time; For, then, what wee expect he shall fullfill, Or, if that he performe it not, God will. Then, howsoere the waters ebb or flowe, From whatsoever coasts the windes do blowe, Though craggy rock and lofty hill do stand And barr out (as they do) on either hand, Though Armies follow us, and though befor The Redd sea stop our passage at the shore, If wee with faith and meeknes wait on God No stormes, hills, armies, or a sea of blood, Shall make his purposes without effect Or hinder what wee iustly may expect; Or when all other meanes are quite bereaven, There will be still an open passe to heaven. God is our present hope, and more in Him We do confide then in the King or them On whome wee haue confided heretofor; Strengthen this Faith, Lord, and increase [it] more, For therby wee are so well pacifyed That vnto those whome wee began to chide Wee shall be reconcild, if they can be As willing to amend their faults as wee To pardon them; For wee haue all offended, And he thats best hath more to be amended Then to be proud of. The prime diffrence Twixt men and Devills is true penitence, (As to their criminall estate, for they Cannot repent of evill, as we may;) And adds more to the glory of a man Than acting all the morall Virtues cann, For those may counterfeited be; This never. If therfor they will henceforth so endeavor As they would be forgiven to forgive, And (as God shall enable them) to strive To do their duties and to lay aside Their Vengance, Animosities and Pride, That wee may be in hope they will abate Their spleen to persons who are moderate, And shall assist them with a prudent zeal To propagate his and publike weal Whome they pretend to serve (although so headdy They are not, nor so spightfull nor so giddy), Let them so qualified back returne Vnto their Trust, at end of this Adjorne, If them to re-employ the King shall please: For though wee might finde fitter men then these Whome wee reprove, there sit among them some By whose example they reformd become May act more prudently at their next session, And wee do hope they will. On this condition Let all their former Failings, and the blot Which this may cast vpon them, be forgot, And let these checks for euermore hereafter Be turned into merriment and laughter. For such faults now are epidemic[al], And greater siners haue no checke at all. But (notwithstanding to excuse them thus Wee willing are) they with our Scribe and vs Will scarce well pleased be: The polititian Will cry, It tends to scandall or sedition, And they who heed not to what vse, nor from What Spirit these iust Reprehentions come, Will censure them, as, without fear or wit, To be conceivd in a phanatick Fit By some one who had therby an intent To bring a scandall to the Parlament. This may be feard; yet naytheles wee hope When wise men weigh our words and heed their scope It will appear that by a Retroversion Wee free the Parlament from that aspersion Which might be cast upon it. God forbid All should reproched be for what some did! Yet so it oft befalls that Yea's and No's Without a reason, Reason overthrowes. And in such cases evry Member there, Though no way guilty, in the blame doth share; Yea, the whole Parlament receives a blot By that which but a part thereof did vote; Which blemish this expedient wipeth off, And therfore merriteth no harsh reproof. To hear of Parlaments vniustly blamed, Or worthely reprooved and nick-named, Is to this Generation no strang newes, Yet wee our Liberty do not abuse, Although the parasite, to bring on vs A scandall, may repute them scandalus. Neither have these Reproofs or Obiurgations Deserved any such misimputations, For wee haue put large difference betweene Those who haue Guiltles and Blamworthy bene, So that this can applied be to none Save those who scandalously haue misdone. And none but Fooles to anger will be moved When Vice and Folly only are reproved, Considering how to Dovelike Innocence The Serpents art is ioynd to shun offence, Considering too that, no man being namd, No man can iustly say he is defamd, Or, if he do, wee cannot much be harmd, For by the Dove and Serpent wee are charmd. A Man defective born or misbegot To be therfor a Man deny wee not, Nor thinck wee those defects deprive him can Of attributes essentiall to a Man. If he deseased be, dumb, lame or blinde, (Or otherwaies deformd in any kinde,) Wee may (on iust occasions) without blame Assume the boldnes to aver the same If nothing so malitiously be spoken That Rules of Christian Charity be broken. Ev'n so, howere it shall be constituted, A Parlament in being is reputed And ownd by vs as an Authority Whereto wee, actively or passively, Should yeald obedience; yet wee doubtles may Speak thereof all which wee cann truly [say], Which neither violates the common peace Nor renders their Authority the lesse. These things considerd, wee in reason iudge That this infringeth no iust priviledge Of Parlaments; for wee so lay the blame As both prevents an vniversall shame And individuall Blurrs; if what's intended Shall so work vpon those who haue offended That they, these Checks in silence passing over, No further their owne guiltines discover. Wee have herein expressed no whit more Then what wee hear the raging waters [roar] Or murmur out. And if effect this take, It those distempratures perhaps may slake Which yet increase, and improve a powre To act what will be for their weal and our. But whether wee haue done amisse or well We to the Parlament itself appeal When next it meets, and if we haue offended Will ask their pardon, and faults shal be mended. For wee haue hope that after next October Wee that were mad this sumer will be sober, And that this Chymick pill which some suspect Is dangerous will haue a good effect, If they who take it do but drink a cupp Of cheerfull wine and spue their choller up. This Parlament hath doubtlesly effected What could from such [a] medly be expected, And their Obstructers wee will not condemn In all things wherewith some haue charged them. An Acting by or beyond Precedent To blame them for it is not our intent, Though Precedent's no Law nor Warranty Nor Rule at all times to be guided by, And though the things that haue bene done wee owne When done; And, seing likewise vnto vs unknown The Circumstances and the Causes are For which those Novells first enacted were, It may be questionable whether wee As conscientiously obliged be To iterate them; Naytheles, because Sometimes Necessity occasion drawes On men inevitably to despence With what may be compeld by Indigence, Wee know a Parlament may iustly do What such necessity enforceth to, Ev'n without Precedent, so it be that Which Gods nor Natures Lawes may violate. For, without scrupling it, professe do wee The peoples weal the Supream Lawe to be. His Maiesty, wee hear, is well content With whats enacted by this Parlament, And so are wee; for all men it befitts To like of whatsoeuer God permitts. Yet they whome wee reprove deserve no share In those thancks which to them returned are Who did their duty; For that which is best Might haue (no doubt) bene betterd had the rest Discharged their. Deeds are made good or ill, Better or worse, according to the Will. Wee haue tooke speciall notise of the Lawes Enacted now, and wee haue speciall cause. Good heed by vs henceforward shall be tooke Wee speak not what's forbidden to be spoke, Though tis more hardly done then heretofore, Because it makes vs mind it tenn times more, And very often when wee meet together (With wonderment) to question one another How rationally and to what intents Such things enacted are in Parlaments. The King approoves what's for the Bishops done, And displeasd therewithall wee know not one; For we beleeue that shortly he and wee Shall therewith both alike contented be, And that the work which hath bene long begun Will much the sooner by that meanes be done. Yea, when the worst is done that was intended Things which are now amisse will be amended. Wee grudge not that the Military powre (Reputed heretofore the Kings and Our) Is his alone; for when wee singly had it, Destructive to our selues and him wee made it. And so it will hereafter be if vsed As then it was, or otherwaies abused. Whether it be the People or the King Who doth into the Feild an Army bring, No matter; for, who ere aray them shall, The Lord of hoasts will be their Generall, And though their weapons make a dreadfull Ratle He onely giveth victories in Batle, And if they countermarch to His commands Will slay them with the swords in their owne hands. Though powre they add to powre, they shall at length Like old Rome, ruind be by their owne strength, And they by whome the sword is misemployd Shall by the sword be at the last destroyd. When that all Isr'el could not arme one man With sword and spear, saue Saul and Jonathan, And were of their Militia so bereft That in their Borders not one smith was left To make them weapons, God that want supplide, And to break off that yoke did meanes provide, In spight of all their enimies could do, Though they had Armies, Armes, and Giants too. Wee, therfor, hope the King in God alone Confides, and not in ought that can be done By humane wit or powre; For God intends To blast all whereon flesh and blood depends, Yea, all those things wherein they now take pride, Or whereby they hope to be glorified, That they may know the weal of States and Kings Consists but very litle in those things Which they make most account of, in respect Of those which they do most of all neglect. Their lusting things terrestriall to possesse The more the geting the more will still increse, For whoso hath a longing after more Though they had all the world would still be pore. The Leaches which are always crying on Will faile of all they lacke till the're undone, And ere their endles wants cann haue supply, One oxe will drincke the Seas and Rivers dry. Their saftie nor their honor doth subsist In saying or in doing what they list, In wasting or abusing of the Creature Against Gods lawes, their owne, and Lawes of Nature, Or in depressing those who evry way Their Makers image are as well as they, And for whose [good] (not for their owne) they were Inriched and advancd to what they are, By works of Mercy and of Righteousnes To execute the places they possesse. This that our King will do wee hope, and pray Without dissimulation that he may. Then he noe way to need inlarge his poure, For his wee then shall be, and all that[s] our. Wee then shall so be ruld by Grace and Reason That here shall never need a Law for treson; His Throne shall florish then, and wee no [more] Of Kings or Parlaments as heretofore Shall be afrayd, but live in loving awe Of them, and to our selues become a Lawe. Wee now haue spoke what wee thoght fit to say, Let that which will succeed be as it may. They who herin our Judgment shall condemn Think but of vs as wee do think of them. If our Complaints no Greevance cann redresse, Lets mend our selues, and wee need care the lesse. This Welcome home by him the People sends Who is no Foe to them that will be Friends; No stranger this this Nation, but so long With observation them hath livd among And knowes so well their manners, disposition, Their hopes, their fears, the good and sad condition, That much he cannot be deceived in them, Though few for good haue taken heed of him; And if what they would be he so well knew, He might forshew what would to them ensue. Of this Reproof no malice hath bene cause; For their misfeesans or for their applause He cares not much, and is as careles too Whether this shall beleeued be or no; Who at this present keeps his name vnknowne More to prevent their trouble then his owne. For, should they question him, he so well knowes Their Priviledge, their powre, and what he owes To God, his King and Cuntry, that to them Twill bring more disadvantage then to him. And yet twere better (if harme come to any Hereby) that one man suffer should then many, Through want of tendring to consideration Things vsefull to the wellfare of a nation. And, peradventer, somewhat here exprest Will work on those to whome it is addrest. The Author lives without much hope or fear Of any thing that cann befall him here. Tis Autumn now, and Winter drawing on Will come with Stormes assone as that is gone; But when the Sun of Righteousnes comes hither, That will againe revive which now doth WITHER.</field>
   </doc>
</add>