<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Barclay, Alexander, 1475-1552</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Barclay, Alexander, 1475-1552</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">barclay alexander 1475 1552</field>
      <field name="author_text">Barclay, Alexander, 1475-1552</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">16th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.1858.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">[1509]</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464333</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The ship of fools</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">The ship of fools</field>
      <field name="title_facet">ship of fools</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">ship of fools</field>
      <field name="title_text">The ship of fools</field>
      <field name="year_display">[1509]</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1509</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1509</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464333&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464333&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Barclay, Alexander, 1475?-1552&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;barclay alexander 1475 1552&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The ship of fools&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;ship of fools&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;[1509]&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1509&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Barclay, Alexander&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1475&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1552&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The ship of fools&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;[London]&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Wynkyn de Worde&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;[1509]&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0231&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;[229] p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The ship of fools&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 72 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse included; verse extracted from prose text.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The shyppe of fooles. Of bookes inutyle. capitulo. primo. The fyrste foole of the shyppt I am certayne That with my handes dresse the sayles all For to haue bookes I do all my besy payne Whiche I loue not to rede in specyall Nor them to se also in generall Wherfore it is a prouerbe all aboute Suche thynketh to knowe y? standeth in doubte. Of good counseyle. ca. ii. The counsayle the whiche dothe not well conserne His owne estate and grete affynyte And frome others hurte doth not his dyscerne Is well worthy to haue aduersyte And to be deiecte frome prosperyte For he bryngeth the hogge vnto the pyt And afterwarde reuerseth hym in it. Of auaryce and prodygalyte. capitulo. iii. Of the folysshe shyppe there dothe occupye the seconde parte/the auarycyous That wyll not gyue a poore man one peny He is so harde and so malycyous Beynge on his rychesse so curyous That is lente hym for a small ceason The poore at nede to defende by reason. Of newe customes and gyses. ca. iiii. He that desyreth our thynges newe For to begynne amonge poore mem all Parauenture he maye it ones sore rewe Whan he cometh before god eternall There to be Iuged in sentence fynall Where after his deserte he shall haue mede Yf he haue done well/ryght well he shall spede. Of auncyent fooles. ca. v. Alas for all that euer I enclyne To my sepulture both by houre and daye Yet can I not leue the folysshe ruyne That I haue contynued in alwaye And of olde fooles euer haue kepte the laye Wherfore of olde fooles I maye be the chefe For all that is vyce hathe ben to me lefe Of the document of chyldren. ca. vi. He that forgyueth the crymes ryght vycyous Of his chyldren without correctynge And them enduceth not in vertuous gloryous Is well worthy to haue grete tormentynge And eke anguysshe by longe contynuynge For why he seketh all the wayes he can To lyue in sorowe as a folysshe man. Of reportoures and detractoures. ca. vii. Who that maketh bate and also stryfe By fals enuy and double retortynge And he whiche synfully ledeth his lyfe Euer in vyce and synne contynuynge Without remors of inwarde repentynge Bytwene two mylstones his body doth bere There to haue guerdon as ye may se here. Of them that ensueth not good counseyle capitulo. ix. He is reputed a naturall foole That can nothynge dyscerne at no ceason Of his werkes for all he wente to to scoole And that he is so grounded on reason Yet it may happen at some encheason Whan he ploweth the mountaynes and the rockes For his foly to haue many grete mockes. Of folysshe meurs &amp; condycyons, ca. ix. Who kepeth his mayntene vnstedfast And all his gestes nothynge semely With fyers regarde and not shamefaste Lyght and mouable without curtesy And dysdeynous answerynge proudly He serchet wayes a foole to be Drawynge the hode as ye maye se. Of the hurtynge of amyte. ca. x. Who that doth Iustyce and greuaunce Agaynst vertue and equyte And excercyseth his puyssaunce Upon a man with cruelte By his euyll inyquyte Dothe the pyt of his tombe compose For of vertues he hathe no lose. Of the cont?nynge of scrypture. ca. xi. Who wyll byleue eloquacyte Of fooles seynge the scrypture Shewynge our grete felycyte And wyll not in vertues endure Is a grete foole without mesure Wherfore as fooles makynge dyscordes Of our grete shyp they dresse the cordes. xii Who fastneth not the sadle well Upon his horse whan he shall Unto some towne his ware to sell Thynkynge all sure on euery syde Yf he fall in some dyche syde They that passe by maye to hym saye There lyeth a foole without delaye Of vayne and tr?sytory loue. ca. xiii. The fooles that ben bounde with this corde I drawe in to myne excellent toures Bycause that they to me accorde In seruynge me well at all houres As true louers and paramoures For whome that I smyte feruently Can haue no salue but theyr lady Of th? that syn on the mercy of god. xiiii. Who thynketh that god is moued Unto mercy and grete pyte And that of synnes approued He wyll not ones auenged be He is a foole in certaynte For he must Iuge the synnes all And gyue on them sentence egall. Of fooles makynge edyfyces. ca. xv. He that wyll castelles edyfye Or buylde houses with lyme and stone Must not trust in his owne folye Lest he repente or it done For the thyage that is done anone Oftentymes they do repente Whan that theyr monye is all spente xvi Of pouerte the dede and charge Can no lecherous man eshewe That nyght and daye in metes large Euer in one dothe contynewe The daye shall come they shall it rewe For they dampne theyr soules in dede That etcth more than they haue nede. Of rychesse inutyle. ca. xvii. Who that loketh vp his rychsse In chestes alwaye there to lye And helpeth no man in dystresse Thoughe the poore man therfore sholde dye And be destroyed vtterly He is a foole at eche deuyse The poore men so for to dyspyse. Of the seruynge of two maysters. xviii. He that wyll take two hares at ones With one sole grehounde alonely Renneth throughe busshes for the nones Is a foole I you certyfye Shewynge by dede his grete foly For one can not two maysters serue At ones truely thoughe he wolde sterue. xix Who that can well his tongue refrayne Bothe ferre and nere in euery place And another mannes cousayll layne Is replynysshed with grete grace But he the whiche clatereth a pace Doth his propre counsall bewrye As with chatterynge dothe the pye. For to fynde other me?es goodes and not to yelde them agayne. ca. xxi. He the whiche fyndeth ony thynge. And employeth it to his vsage Alwaye of the same dyspendynge Is a grete fole and nothynge sage For the deuyll at eche passage Holdeth hym fast in a bande Go he by water or by lande. Of conscyon of sapyence. ca. xxii. Who delyteth in sapyence That is worthy of grete praysynge Shall growe to moche magnyfycence In the courte of some grete kynge And shall haue heuen at his endynge Where he shall lyue eternally With bryght aungelles gloryously. Of iactaunce and confydence of fortune. ca. xxiii. Who sayth he is well fortuned Bothe of body and of rychesse And that he was neuer greued Of fortunes whele full of rudenesse That casteth many in dystresse And brenneth houses all aboute Whan the poore fooles stande lest in doubte. xxiiii He that procureth by gre payne The werkes of his seruauntes all And leueth his by grete dysdayne Undone and nought yet therwithall A veraye foole men maye hym call For he wyll take mo werkes on hande Than he and his men may withstande Of them that taketh a truste. ca. xxv. He is a foole deuoyde of reason And ones shall be myserable That wyll borowe at eche ceason Golde and syluer transmutable And for to paye is not able Without he shold sell coote and gowne And after go begge in to the towne Of petytycyods and vowes inutyle. xxvi. Who that on handes and fete dothe praye By false dyssymulacyon Cryenge on god bothe nyght and daye That he wolde graunte vnto hym pardon And gyue them clene remyssyon They be fooles that with cryenge Thynketh to opteyne ony thynge xxvii Who wyll not excercyse studye But renne aboute from place to place Is replysshed with foly And is deiecte from all grace For no scyence he wyll purchace Wherfore he shall repente hym sore Bycause he wolde not lerne nomore Of them that speke folysshly agaynst god capitulo. xxviii. If god wolde here fooles prayer After theyr wyll and theyr peasure They wole make it ryght synguler With wepynge eyen ye may be sure Yf that they myght it so procure But god wyll not to them assente Seynge theyr vnhappy entente To gyue iugement on an other. xxix. Some thynketh that they be ryght Iuste And Iugeth other mennes vyse Saynge that to hell go they muste And neuer come in paradyse He is a foole at eche deuyse To Iuge an other mannes mysdede And wyll not of his owne take hede. Of theym that charge theym with benefyces. ca. xxx. Who some euer dothe apppetyte Benefyces by grete plenty And taketh in them no delyte Saue for the rentes alonely He is not wyse I you certyfye For and he bere more than he maye He is lykly to fall by the waye Of them that desyre for to amende them frome daye to daye. ca. xxxi. Who dothe ensue the rauens songe Sayenge I shall amende to morowe And contynueth in it longe Is lyke to fall in to moche sorowe But yf our lorde wyll be his borowe For and he euer that songe synge It shall hym streyght vnto helle brynge Of them that wyll kepe wyues. xxxii. Of this foole sore I meruayll That casteth water in the well And of one withouten say I Wyll kepe the fleen with his mell In the sonne and by them dwell But he is the moost foole of all That wyll kepe his owne wyfe in thrall Of aduoutrye. ca. xxxiii. The man is folysshe and ryght obstynate That seeth his wyse in a dyssolute place Frequentynge mysrule/but her vnclene fate He wyll not se but couereth his face With his hande thorughe his fyngers space He toteth as he wolde playe bo pepe As cat for a mouse faynynge to slepe Of hym that is alwayes folysshe. xxxiiii. The peruers foole is lunatyke That thynketh to haue grete rychesse And that euery man wyll stryke Without a cause in his madnesse He is a foole without sagenesse And hathe ben one all his longe dayes And shall abyde styll so alwayes. Of angre that proceeeth of a lytell thynge. ca. xxxv. Who beteth his asse without mesure And wyll neuer be sacyate He is a folysshe creature To demeane hym in suche astate Upon a beest that can not prate For this foole is dystraught for wo Bycause his asse wyll not fast wo. Of the mutabylyte of fortune. ca. xxxvi. He that thynketh to mount on hye On fortunes whele that is so peruerse He is replete with grete foly Seynge that she is so dyuerse For she wyll lyghtly hym reuerse Up so downe vnder the whele And take hym from his hertes wele. Of the impacyence in sykenes. Ca. xxxvii. yf the syke man be oppressed With maladye full anguysshous And wyll not be well counsaylled By the medecyne gracyous He is a foole vylependyous Wherfore yf he haue aduersyte He is the cause therof truely Of consultacyons to openly. ca. xxxviii. Who dothe openly his wyll shewe And setteth his gynnes to appertly One maye the daunger soone eschewe Be it a man or byrde truely For whan they knowe it they go by As who sayth we be all puruayed Wherfore the foole is euyll appayed How one ought for to be wyse/by experyence of the euylles that they se fooles commyte. ca. xxxix. Who seeth of fooles the grete ruyne And theyr fallynge downe so dadayne And wyll vnto vyces enclyne Is worthy helle for to obtayne With deuylles alwaye to remayne For he wyll not his synne amende Untyll the tyme that he must wende. Not for to haue cure of detraccyons &amp; vayne wordes of euery body. ca. xl. He is a foole ryght varyable The whiche wyll gyue faythe and credence Unto euery mannes fable Whiche are folysshe without sence And knowe they be voyde of prudence Euer reportynge false tydynges Bothe at morowe and at euynnynges. Of subsannatoures/calomnyatours and detractoures. ca. xli. The foole that casteth stones ferre After the wyse man fleenge a pace And doothe euer in that synne erre Is deuoyde clene frome all good grace For in synne resteth his solace Wherfore he wyll not ruled be By ryght reason and equyte. Of the dyspraysynge of the Ioye eternall. ca. xlii. O god how our mynde is mouable Dyshonest false and not loyall For to dysprayse god permanable Withall the courte celestyall And sette at nought his syege royall For he is a foole nothynge wyse The Ioyes of heuen for to dyspryse. Of tumulte and iangelynge ? the chyrche Capitulum. xliii. Who bereth a hauke on his hande In the chyrche walkynge vp and downe And ledeth houndes in a bande That with theyr belles make grete sowne He were better be in the towne For he letteth without delaye Bothe men and women for to praye. Of them that enclyne them voluntaryly to suffre dethe. ca. xliiii. Who that of his owne propre wyll Dothe hange hymselfe by ygnoraunce Or with a guysarme dothe hym kyll Withouten shryfte or repentaunce He is a foole at eche dystaunce So to purchase dethe eternall And so to be in tormentes fynall. Of the felycyte and payne to come/and of the delytes perpetuall. ca. xlv. Dyuers fooles do drawe the carte Full of vyces bothe daye and houre And wyll not ones to god reuerte The be so hote on theyr laboure Dommagynge euer theyr neyghboure That it is pyte for to se How enuyous they to them be. Of the euyll example of the most byggest Capitulum. xlv. If the fader do ony thynge That is euyll and vycyous Before his sone in the mornynge Be it neuer so daungerous Nor vnto hym so odyous yet he wyll put it in assaye To do the same yf that he maye. Of the voluptuousnes corporall. xlvii. Dyurs by voluptuousnes Of women the whiche be presente Be brought in to full grete dystres Forgetynge vertues excellente Of god the whiche is permanente And suffreth themselfe to be bounde In cordes as it were a hounde. Of th? that c?not hyde theyr secretes. xlviii. He that in hym hathe some secrete Let hym kepe it well in his herte And tell it no man vndyscrete Lest he of his payne be coherte And dwell euer in anguysshe smerte He is a foole for afterwarde He shall haue dolours fyerse and harde Of hym that weddeth a wyfe for to haue her rychesses. ca. xlix. The man the whiche dothe wedde a wyfe For her treasour and her rychesse And not for lygnage femynatyfe Procureth dolour and dystresse With infynyte payne and heuynesse For she wyll do hym moche sorowe Bothe at euen and at morowe Of enuye. ca. l. The dartes ryght cursed of enuye Hathe reygned syth the worlde began Whiche bryngeth one euedently In to the bandes of sathan Wherfore he is a dyscrete man That can eschewe that euyll synne Where body and soule is loste ynne Of impacyence in correccyon. ca. li. He that cheseth an instrumene The whiche is vyle and dyshonest And that fooles playe on verament Leuynge the other whiche be best He is a foole for without ren He playeth theron incessyuely Without musyke or melody. Of folysshe physycyens. ca. lii. Who that vseth the arte of medycyne Takynge his knowlege in the felde He is a foole full of ruyne So to take herbes for his shelde Wenynge theyr vertue for to welde Whiche is not possyble for to knowe All theyr vertues bothe hye and lowe Of thy dolorous departynge of the puyssa?ce of heuen. liii. Neuer man yet was so pussaunt Of goodes or of parentage But that mortall dethe dyde hym daunt Byt processe at some strayte passage ye were he neuer of suche aege For he spareth not yonge nor olde Fayre nor foule fyerse nor also bolde. Of predestynacyon. Ca. l.iiii. He the whiche demaundeth the pryce That he dyde neuer well deserue He is a foole peuerse and nyse So to aske for thoughe he sholde sterue And be loste he wyll not obserue The byddynges and commaundementes Haue he neuer so many rentes To forgete hymselfe. ca. lv. He that quencheth the flambes hote Of an other mannes house of fyre And letteth his owne brenne god wote He is a foole so to conspyre His owne hurte by folysshe desyre For he is dygne to haue dommage That wyll not do after the sage Of his owne pleasaunce. Ca. l.vii. Approche you nere all the hole route And beholde this foole full of rage The whiche doth stere all rounde aboute With his ladyll his owne potage And myrreth his vgly vysage In a fayre glasse ouer the fyre For his pleasaunce and his desyre. Of daunces and dysportes. ca. lviii. Who reioyseth hym for to daunce With men and women Iouslye And syngeth by contynuaunce Foule songes full of rybaudre He is a peruers foole truely For therby is moche sorowe wrought Bothe in dedes and also thought Of players of instrumentes. lix. Who gothe aboute euery nyght Playenge on instrumentes swetely And syngynge songes by the lyght Of the mone melodyously Before his ladyes doore truely He a foole endurynge colde Whiche he shall fele whan he is olde Of beggers and of theyr vanytees. ca. lx. I whiche am a poore almes man Haue grete fere to encreace lygnage Bycause that I nothynge get can To helpe my selfe in myne olde aege And my chyldren in theyr domage Goynge aboute from doore to doore gyue your good almesse to the poore. Of condycyons/murmurygnes/&amp; grete vnhappynes of wyues. Ca. lx. Who that in his mynde doth compasse To rule his wyfe after his wyll He maye also soone make an asse Renne a wallap ouer a hyll For she always wyll haue good skyll And also soone do after them As dryue a snayle to Iherusalem Of the puyssaunce of foles. ca. xlii. The fooles saye they haue puyssaunce Bycause theyr tentes is wyde and large Hauynge goodes golde and cheuaunce For to make warre at euery tyde On lordes and knyghtes on eche syde Be it for ryght or elles for wronge They dystroye ech other amonge Of the cure of astronomye. ca. lxiii. He is holden a foole truely The whiche putteth his besy cure To calke the sterres in the skye And all theyr natures to procure In pronostynge as he were sure Of the tyme the whiche is to come That he knoweth not all nor some Of hym that wyll wryte/and enquyre of all regyons. ca. xliiii. He the whiche mesureth the grounde The heuens and the clymates all And the worlde whiche is all rounde With the planettes superyall Dysspraysynge our lorde eternall By comprysynge so folysshly The maners of countrees truely Of hym that wyll not be a foole. Ca. lxv. Mercia the whiche with the sage Doet appollyne ones dysputed Bycause he passed the passage And in the same was poluted For a foole he was reputed But he wolde not therto agre Wherfore he was flayne as ye maye se Of them that can take no playe. lxvi. They the whiche wyll with chyldren playe And fooles the whiche be of one sorte Of mysfortune beware alwaye Bycause ye maye haue good reporte And frome all vyces you deporte For one sholde euer perylles drede And puruaye therfore at a nede Of the impacyence of some that wyll not abyde/but wyll do euyll. lxvii. He the whiche is so varyable He that can not with none agre And hathe his mynde so reasonable In smytynge men of eche degre He is o foole for certaynte And yf he fall after in nede He can blame none but his owne dede Of vnpuruayenge for the tyme to come. ca. lxviii. Who that spendeth his tyme in wast Without lernynge of sapyence To come to god he hathe no haste Whiche is of so hyghe excellence For but in yougthe he make prouydence And in somer gadre and spare In wynter he shall be full bare Of pleaders in iugement. ca. lxix. Who hathe aspecte to dame Iustyce Makynge complayntes dolorous Askynge her ryght whiche is propyce Of all men beynge vertuous Peruers cursed or malycyous But the foole blyndeth her vysage By false sentence full of outrage Of foles abhomynable in wordes. lxx. The vayne wordes dysordynate Foule vnclene and abhomynable Reported by fooles approbate Peruers and vnrensonable Beynge therin insacyable In deseruynge maladyccyons For brekynge good constytucyons Of the estate &amp; abuse spyrytuall. ca. lxxi. Some dothe the goodes spyrytuall Coueyte in aege not couenable But whan they must doo the actuall And with god dyne at his table They be therto nothynge notable For the worlde and his vanyte Draweth them to perplexyte Of players. ca. lxxiii. The players take all theyr solace To playe by an ardaunt courage Nyghte and daye without ony grace Doynge eche other grete outrage By takynge cotes and gownes to gage Hauynge to god no garde at all The whiche is aboue eternall Of fooles surprysed. ca. lxxiiii. I knowe in my booke is paynted A sorte of fooles without delaye The whiche in our shyppe is acquaynted And that theyr asses do with playe Agaynste theyr wyll withouten naye The whiche in laughynge doth conspyre Many oppressyons for Ire Of knyghtes/men of armes/scrybes/and practycyens. ca. lxxv. If the rustykes be oppressed With men of armes and practycyence And be beten and dystressed In dyuerse wyse by influence Without reason or sapyence In takynge more than theyr duyte Of the poore men without pyte Of folysshe legacyons and messengers. ca. lxxvi. I messenger hathe ben full ferre In dyuers londes and regyons Bothe in tranquylyte and warre Berynge worde of prouysyons In castelles and in garnysons Gyuynge my lettres and suche thynge Of whome I haue hadde the wynnynge Of caters and kepers of sellers in houses. ca. lxxvii. Apparell you that ye were here Caters of houses in the towne And for all perylle drawe you nere Our shyppe at the trompettes sowne The whiche to sayle is redy bowne For come on nowe we haue good wynde Or elles ye must all byde behynde Of the excessyue arrogaunce rustyke. lxviii. Yf there be chorles or vyllaynes The whiche dothe coueyte our cordes Let them brynge with them they waynes And they shall haue in them dyscordes Ynouthe/but for good concordes We haue not many for to spare But yf we sholde leue ourselfe bare Of the contempnpnge of pouerte. lxxix. Pouerte gothe in this worlde rounde Decayed by monye and rychesse And lyeth naked on the grounde In paynes sorowes and dystresse Frostes snowes wyndes raynes and coldenesse For there is none wyll them socoure Nor exalte vnto some honoure Of hym that wyll not perseue in goodes. ca. lxxx. Dyuers fooles wyll the carte drawe By whanhope and iniquyte Without reason or ony lawe Lyuynge in grete calamyte Deuoyde of blysse and prosperyte And all thrugh theyr folyswe bobaunce Not folowynge perseueraunce Of the dysprysynge of dethe. ca. lxxxi. O dethe dethe thou arte ryght cruell To destroye all thy humayne lygnage And to sende them to heuen or hell To dwell there with theyr parentage Where ryche nor poore hathe no vauntage For golde nor syluer in no manere Saue of all good vertues in fere Of the grete contempnynge and dyspraysynge of god. ca. lxxxii. Yf that god wyll not punysshe the In thy body withouten fayle He wyll in other thynges truely Ryght sore the punysshe and assayle In thy goodes or in catayle Wherfore please hym daye and nyght That he maye saue the in thy ryght Of them that blaspheme our lorde Ihesu chryste. ca. lxxxiii. O swerers by god omnypotente Makynge hym smarte by othes cruell In terynge his body all shente By blasphemynge as I you tell Leue your othes or ye shall dwell In the tenebres funerall With deuylles blacke in paynes fynall Of the plage and indygnacyon of of god. ca. lxxxiiii. This same foole here meruayleth sore Saynge it is agaynst nature That god sholde put vs euermore In paynes grete for to endure For our synnes and worldly pleasure Wherfore he that lyueth in synne Beware that he fall not therin Of the folysshe permutacyon. ca. lxxxv. Who loueth yll conuersyon Not knowynge good from vycyous And maketh perturbacyon In a countree commodyous He is a foole ryght daungerous For he leseth for lytell thynge The blysse of god euer lastynge To honour fader and moder. ca. lxxxvi The chyldren and eche creatour Is bounde by nature and reason Fader and moder to honoure And them to helpe at eche ceason After theyr myght and encheason And yf they bete them by rudenesse They maye be sure of grete dystresse Of the cauellacyon of preestes in the quere. ca. lxxxvii. We se in this tyme nowe present How preestes serue god neglygently Not praysynge hym as permanent Doynge his seruyce deuoutly For they do but clattre and crye In the quere whyle they sholde synge And gyue to god laude and praysynge Of the grete dem?stra?ce of pryde. lxxxviii. All they that be replete with pryde Folowynge the fende ryght cruell Is worthy with hym to abyde And for euermore with hym to dwell In the horryble paynes of hell There to be rewarded doubtelesse And neuer come in heuens blesse lxxxix All you the whiche ben vsurers That take of men theyr hole substaunce And also you that be synners Lyuynge euer in grete bobaunce Leue your vyle synnes and perturbaunce Or elles ye shall be put in thrall And haue tormentes perpetuall Of the vayne hope to haue &amp; succede. ca. lxxxx. Who trusteth to haue successyon Of others goodes and rychesse Makynge therfore prouysyon Not thynkynge on dethes hardynesse He is a foole voyde of sagesse For to desyre other mennes dethe Eyther for rychesse londe or hethe Of them that obserueth not the sondayes and other feestes. ca. lxxxxi. Who that kepeth not the sondayes And holy festes canonysed But occupyeth them in playes Is a grete fole predestyned And shall be frome god expulsed But yf that he kepe them truely In seruynge good god reuerently To gyue his goodes &amp; after repente hym. Capitulo. lxxxxii. He that gyueth his goodes in haste Unto some man of lowe degree And afterwarde maketh suche wast That he falleth in pouerte Then yf for gyfte he sory be He leseth meryte and guerdon And hathe for his gyftes no pardon Of the synne of slouthe. ca. lxxxxiii. Slouthe hathe nowe the grete sygnorye Of this wretched worlde rounde aboute In oppressynge eche good body Be they neuer so styffe nor stoute By slouthe they be brought in grete doubte And fere of foule dampnacyon If they make longe contynuacyon Of fooles infydeles. ca. lxxxxiiii. The infydels and myscreauntes I haue wylled for to put here Bycause they adoure termagauntes And wyll no holy scrypture lere Nor worshyp chryst by no manere Not withstonde they be not worthy To be put in this booke truely Of our holy faythe catholyke of oure moder holy chyrche. And the inclynacyon of the holy empyre Romayne. lxxxxv. O you my barons of the chyrche That sholde me loue full tenderly In good operacyons loke ye wyrche And serue Ihesu chryste deuoutely That he maye take you to mercy And deiecte clene out of your thought The vayne thynges the whiche is nought Of blandysshees &amp; flatrrers. ca. lxxxxvi. Who blandyssheth a cruell stede Lyckynge the platers of ryche men And faylleth his mayster at his nede Is worthy punysshed [illeg.] to ben In greuous tormentes nyne or ten Bycause of his grete trechery Blandysshynge and flatery Of delayers/&amp; vayne reporters. lxxxxvii. Who byleueth eche mannes sayenge Bothe fooles and men vndyscrete Gyuynge to theyr folyes herynge Is worthy to haue sorowes grete The whiche maye his folysshe herte frete For flaterers he wyll byleue That seketh all wayes hym to greue lxxxxviii Alcumyne whiche is deceytfull Maketh the worlde golde in doctryne But the deceyuer is all full Of malyce rancour and ruyne Neuer sacyate but as a swyne Glouteth the poore folkes rychesse By falsshode and by doublenesse lxxxxix Here maye ye se false antechryste In his estate tryumphauntlye That counterfetteth Ihesu chryste By his foule pryde and trechery Wherfore he shall haue paynes truely With his owne fader Lucyfere And all that byleueth hym here c Who that for drede or for fauour Dothe hyde the trouthe and veryte Or who that for loue or lycour Letteth the dede of charyte He is a foole for certaynte For they be of antechrystes lyne That causeth suche thynges to take fyne To withdrawe the good dede &amp; what it is ca. C.i. Who that wyll let a man prudent To do werkes of honeste Or put ony impesshement Betwene folke of affynyte He is a foole for certaynte So thynkynge to let the good dede The whiche he may not by no spede Of the obmyssyon of good werkes. C.ii. He the whiche hathe his lampe replete With oyle he maye the better se Also he that hathe vertues grete And accomplyssheth them truely He lyueth in grete prosperyte And he the whiche dothe here lyue well Shall neuer come in fyre of hell Of the praysynge of sapyence. ca. C.iii. We nowe take with the ryght hande Bothe palme and the ryche crowne abyde Aud on the lefte syde there doth stande The cap of fooles bothe large and wyde Whiche is strowed on euery syde Leuynge the crowne of sapyence Descended frome the hye essence Of the dispraysynge of his vnfortune. C.iiii He is a foole that fortune dothe se Come on hym whiche is transmutable And maye resyste it in eche degre With sapyence incomperable Folowynge thynges prouffytable And wyll not by no maner of waye Tyll dethe hym take without delaye Of the detraccyon of goodes. ca. C.v. The wyse man that lyueth here well Without fraude or detraccyon And afterwarde hangeth a bell At his cattes necke by correccyon Ho is a foole without dyscrecyon Se at the last for to condyscennde Unto foly and so make an ende Of the immoderate turpytude of the table. ca. C.vi. Now at this tyme we be moued To paynte the grete enormytes Of dronkerdes the whiche is approued In our booke of fragylytees Touchynge theyr foule commodytees Whiche they commyt in euery place As folke that is deuoyde of grace Of fooles dysfygured takynge straunge clothynges. ca. C.vii. Democrytus the sapyent By this that he sawe so grete foly Of fooles that were neclygent He laugheth fast and that on hye Bycause they coude no polycye And Cynycus wepeth ryght fast Bycause that the worlde is not stedfast cviii The wyse man whiche is prudent Dothe moche good where euer he go Gyuynge examples excellent Unto them the whiche are in wo Techynge them in all vertues so That they maye not in to synne fall Yf that they hertly on god call Of the rec?m?dacyon of phylosophy. Cix. At this tyme doctryne is decayed And nought set by in no place For euery man is well appayed To get good with grete solace Not carynge how nor in what place Puttynge tha fayre and dygne sophye Under fete with phylosophye Concertacyon of vertue with voluptuosyte. ca. C.x. O you the whiche is here commysed Beholde beholde my frendes all For I am vertue that is surmyseth With voluptuosyte venyall Thrrughe her demeanour bestyall Wenynge me here for to oppresse Whiche aboue all am empresse Obieccyon of voluptuosyte blamynge vertues. ca. C.xi. Am I not the grete enemye Of vertues that I loue nothynge Warrynge on her with grete maystry Bycause from luste she wolde me brynge The whiche is all my desyr?ge In my gardyn full of pleasaunce Where as I do bothe synge and daunce Of the answere of vertu vnto voluptuosyte. ca. C.xii. O voluptuosyte wherfore Doest thou me put in suche araye Scoffynge with me so vengeable sore Makynge on me so grete a fraye And yet vyle best thou can not saye But that thou arte trasmutable Unchast and abhomynable Of the shyp latyne/or barge socyale. C.xiii. To the fooles in shyppes innumerable Withouten ende and euer furyous We shall be to them euer aydable Bothe in flodes and wawes tempesteous Wherfore ye ought to be gladde and Ioyous Seynge that you are of the myghty stocke Of fooles peruerse whiche is so grete a flocke Of the shyp socyale mecanycque. ca. C.xiiii. The turbe of men full of inyquyte As vnthryfty mecanykes with many mo Playenge on organs by extremyte Getynge theyr lyuynge with playenge to and fro And without ony reason they call our shyppe so That the shyppe redowndeth all of the sowme Comynge in to it as they wolde cast all downe Of the syngularyte of some newe fooles. Capitulo. C.xv. Bycause that we sholde be besy In our shyppe be it ferre or nere And take in other fooles by and by Whiche asprely brynge in theyr gere Thynkynge with vs to go in fere And helpe vs here for to gouerne Bothe at the purse and at the sterne Of th? that do all thynges contrary. C.xvii. He the whiche dothe the contrary To reason ryght and equyte And that euer from them vary Lyuynge in grete perplexyte He is a fole for certaynte For after the sayenge of the scrypture Who lyueth here well of heuen is sure</field>
   </doc>
</add>