<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Stanley, Thomas, 1625-1678</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Stanley, Thomas, 1625-1678</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">stanley thomas 1625 1678</field>
      <field name="author_text">Stanley, Thomas, 1625-1678</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.1571.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1655</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464113</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Greek, Modern (1453- )</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The History of Philosophy ; ... By Thomas Stanley. Containing those on whom the Attribute of VVise was conferred</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">The History of Philosophy ; ... By Thomas Stanley. Containing those on whom the Attribute of VVise was conferred</field>
      <field name="title_facet">history of philosophy</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">history of philosophy</field>
      <field name="title_text">The History of Philosophy ; ... By Thomas Stanley. Containing those on whom the Attribute of VVise was conferred</field>
      <field name="year_display">1655</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1655</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1655</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464113&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464113&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Stanley, Thomas, 1625-1678&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;stanley thomas 1625 1678&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The History of Philosophy ; ... By Thomas Stanley. Containing those on whom the Attribute of VVise was conferred&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;history of philosophy&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1655&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1655&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Stanley, Thomas&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1625&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1678&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The History of Philosophy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;... By Thomas Stanley. Containing those on whom the Attribute of VVise was conferred&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Humphrey Moselay, and Thomas Dring [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1655&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp3758&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;gre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;4 v.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The History of Philosophy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;... By Thomas Stanley. Containing those on whom the Attribute of VVise was conferred&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 161 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The first Volume. TO MY HONOVRED VNCLE JOHN MARSHAM, Esq. Out of his Elegies. Sprung from Mnemosyne and Joves great line, Pierian Muses, to my prayer encline, Grant that my life and actions may call down Blessings from heaven, and raise on earth renown: Sweet to my friends, and bitter to my foes, To these my sight bring terror, joy to those. Riches I wish, not riches that are plac't In unjust means, for vengeance comes at last. Riches dispenc'd by heavens more bounteous hand, A base on which we may unshaken stand. But that which men by injuries obtain, That which by arts and deeds unjust they gain Comes slowly, swiftly by reveng'd pursued, And miserie like a close spark include, Which soon to a devouring flame dilates, Wrong is a weak foundation for effates. Jove doth the end of every thing survey: As sodain vernall blasts chase clouds away. Ransack the bottom of the roaring main, Then swiftly overrun the fervile plain, Ruffling the wealthy ears; at last they rise To Joves high seat, a calm then smooths the skies. The Sun's rich lustre mildly gilds the green Enamell of the meads, no clouds are seen, Such is Joves heavie anger diff'ring far From men, whose every trifle leads to war: They are not hid for ever, who offend In secret, judgment finds them in the end. Some in the act are punisht, others late, Even he who thinks he hath deluded fate; At last resents it in just miseries, Which Nephewes for their Ancestors chastise. We think it fares alike with good and bad; Glory and selfe-conceit our fancies glad Till suffering comes, then their griev'd spirits bleed, Who did before their soules with vain hope feed. He whom incurable diseases seize, Sooths his deluded thoughts, with hopes of ease. The coward's valiant in his own esteem, And to themselves, faire the deformed seem. They who want means, by poverty opprest Beleeve themselves of full estates possest. All is attempted, some new seas explore To bring home riches from a forraign shore: Seas, on whose boisterous back secur'd they ride, And in the mercy of the winds confide: Others to crooked ploughes their Oxen yoke, And Autumn with their plants and setts provoke. Some Vulcan's and Minerva's arts admire, And by their hands, their livelyhoods acquire. Others the fair Olympian muses trace, And lovely learning studiously embrace. One by Apollo is prophetick made, And tells what mischiefs others shall invade: With him the Gods converse, but all the skill In birds or victimes cannot hinder ill. Some to Peonian knowledge are inclin'd, Nor is the power of simples unconfin'd. The smallest hurts sometimes increase and rage, More then all art of physick can asswage; Sometimes the fury of the worst disease, The hand by gentle stroking will appease. Thus good or bad arives as fates design, Man cannot what the Gods dispenc'd decline. All actions are uncertain, no man knowes When he begins a work, how it shall close. Some, who their businesse weigh with prudent care, Oft of the issue intercepted are: Whilst others who have rashly ought design'd, An end successfull of their labours find. There is no bound to those who wealth acquire, For they who are possest of most, desire As much again, and who can all content, Even those full blessings which the Gods have lent, Man variously to his own harm applies, Whom Jove by means as various doth chastice. Again. [Our City never can subverted be] Our City never can subverted be By Jove, or any other Deitie; For Pallas eye surveyes with pious care The wals, which by her hand protected are: Yet the inhabitants of this great Town, Fondly inclin'd to wealth, will throw it down; And those unjust great persons who are bent Others to wrong, themselves to discontent; For their insatiate fancies have not power T enjoy the sweetnesse of the instant hower; But by all wicked means, intent on gain, From hallowed, nor from publick things refrain. Riches by theft and cozenage to possesse, The sacred bounds of justice they transgresse. Who silent sees the present, knowes the past, And will revenge these injuries at last: Causing a cureless rupture in the state, And all our liberties shall captivate. Rouse war from his long slumber, who the flower Of all our youths shall bloodily devour. For Cities which injuriously oppose Their friends, are soon invaded by their foes. These are the common evills; of the poor Many transported to a forraign shore, To bondage there, and fetters shall be sold. Each private house thus shares the publick fate, Nor can exclude it with a bar'd-up gate; For scaling furiously the higher walls, On those whom beds or corners hides, it falls. My soule, Athenians, prompts me to relate What miseries upon injustice wait: But justice all things orderly designes, And in strict fetters the unjust confines. What's soure, she sweetens, and allaies what cloyes. Wrong she repells, ill in the grouth destroyes, Softens the stubborn, the unjust reformes, And in the state calmes all seditious stormes: Bitter dissention by her raign supprest, Who wisely governes all things for the best. Another. [No man is blessed, bad is every one] No man is blessed, bad is every one That feeles the warmth of the all-seeing Sun. Another. [Let me not die unpitti'd, every friend] Let me not die unpitti'd, every friend With sighes and tears my latest hower attend. AUSONII LUDUS septem Sapientum. The Prologue. The seven wise-men, (that name times past apply'd To them, nor hath posteritie deny'd) Themselves this day unto your view present. Why dost thou blush Gown'd Roman? discontent That such grave men should on the stage be brought! Is't shame to us? 'twas none to Athens thought: Whose Councell-Chamber was their Theater. True; here for businesse severall places are Assign'd, the Cirque for meetings, Courts to take Enrolements, Forums in which pleas to make: But in old Athens, and all Greece was known No other place for businesse but this one. [viz. the Theater Which latter Luxury in Rome did raise. The Ædile heretofore did build for plaies A Scaffold-stage, no work of Carved stone; So Gallius and Murena, 'tis well known. But after, when great Men not sparing Cost, Thought it the highest glory they could boast, To build for Playes a Scene more eminent, The Theater grew to this vast extent; Which Pompey, Balbus, Cæsar did enlarge; Vying which should exceed for state and charge. But to what end all this? we came not here To tell you who first built the Theater, Forum, or City Gates, but t'usher in Grave sages, who by Gods approv'd have been. Such as in pleasing and instructive verse, Their own judicious sentences rehearse, Known to the learned, and perhaps to you: But if your Mem'ries cannot well renue Things spoke so long since; the Comedian shall, Who better then I knowes them, tell you all. Enter Comedian. Athenian Solon, Fame sings, wrot at Delphis ????? ???????; whose sense Know thy selfe, is: But this to Spartan Chilon most assign. Some question Chilon, whether this be thine, ????? ?????? ????, The close Of a long life regard: but most suppose That Solon this to Lydian Crœsus spake. From Lesbian Pittacus this motto take, ??????????; that's Know time: But he By ????, here means opportunity. ?? ???????? ()???, Bias, did proceed From thee; that is, Most men are ill. Take heed You not mistake him; for by ill men here He means the ignorant: The next you hear Is Periander's ???????(); That is, Thought's All in All; a Thoughtfull Man! But Lyndian Cleobulus does protest ????? ?????? Mean in All is best. Thales, ?????, ??????? ?? ??? cries. Upon a Surety present damage lies. But this, 'for those who gain by it, to tell, May 'chance displease: Now Solon comes farewell. Exit. Enter Solon. Lo! Solon in his Greeks dresse treads the stage, To whom (as of the seven the greatest Sage) Fame gave the prize of wisdome from the rest; But fame is not of Censure the strict Test. Nor first nor last I take my selfe to be, For there's no order in Equalitie. Well did the Delphick Prophet sport with him Who ask'd, which first of the Wise-men might seem, Saying; if on a Globe their names he writ, None first or lowest he should find in it. From midst of that learn'd Round come I; that so What once I spake to Crœsus, All here now Might take as spoken to themselves; 'tis this: ?? ????? ?????? ???? which is, Mark the end of a long life; till when forbear To say, these wretched, or those happy are: For All till then are in a doubtfull state, The proofe of this wee'l in few words relate. Crœsus the King or Tyrant (choose you which) Of Lydia, happy thought; and strangely rich; Who to his Gods did gold-wall'd Temples build, Invites me ore, I to his summons yeeld. His royall summons went to Lydia, Willing his subjects by our means might find Their King improv'd, and better'd in his mind. He asks me whom I thought the happiest Man? I said Telana, the Athenian, Who his life nobly for his Country gave; He pishes at it; will another have. I told him then Aglaus, who the Bounds Nere past in all his life of his own grounds. Smiling, he saies, what think you then of Me Esteem'd the happyest in the whole world? We Reply'd, his End could only make that known, He takes this ill: I, willing to be gon, Kisse his hand, and so leave him: For some ends Meantime, 'gainst Persia he a war intends; And all things ready, does in person go. How speeds? he's vanquish'd, Prisoner to his foe, And ready now to yeeld his latest breath, (For by the Victor he was doom'd to death) Upon the funerall Pile, rounded with Flames And smoake, he thus with a loud voice exclaimes O Solon! Solon! now I plainly see Th'art a true Prophet! Thrice thus naming me Mov'd with which words, Cyrus, (the Conquerour) Commands the Fire be quencht, which, by a shower Of Rain then falling, happily was laid. Thence to the King, by a choice Guard convay'd, And question'd who that Solon was? and why He call'd so on his Name? He, for reply, In Order all declares: Pitty at this The Heart of Cyrus moves; and Crœsus is Receiv'd to grace, who in a Princely Port Liv'd after, honor'd in the Persian Court. Both Kings approv'd, and prais'd Me, but what I Said then to one, let each man here apply As spoke t'himselfe, 'twas for that end I came. Farewell: your liking let your hands proclaim. [Exit. Enter Chilon. My Hips with sitting, Eyes with seeing ake, Expecting when Solon an End would make. How little and how long your Atticks prate! Scarce in three-hundred lines one word of weight, Or a grave sentence, how he lookt on me At going off?—Now Spartan Chilon see! Who with Laconian Brevity commends To you the Knowledge of your selves, kind Friends! ????? ?????? carv'd in a Delphos Fane. 'Tis a hard Work, but recompenc'd with Gain. Try your own strength; examine what 'tis you Have done already, what you ought to do. All Duties of our life, as Modestie, Honour and Constancie included be In this, and glory, which we yet despise. Farewell, your claps I not respect nor prize. [Exit. Enter Cleobulus. I Cleobulus, though my Native Seat Be a small Isle, am Author of a great And glorious Sentence; ?????? ??????; A man is best: You Sirs that sit upon The fourteen middle Benches next unto Th'Orchestra, best may judge if this be true. Your Nodd showes your assent: We thank you; but We shall proceed in Order: Was it not One Afer (who a man of your own Clime is) That said once in this place, Ut ne quid Nimis? And hither does our ????? ???? aime. The Dorick and the Latine mean the same. In speaking being silent, or in sleep, In good Turns, or in bad, a mean still keep, In study, or what ever you intend. I've said, and that I mean, I keep here end. [Exit. Enter Thales. I'm Thales, who maintain (as Pindar sings) Water to be the best and first of things. To whom by Phœbus Mandate, fishers brought A golden Tripod, which they fishing caught, By him as present to the wisest meant, Which I refus'd, and unto others sent In knowledge my superiors as I thought. From one to th'other of the Sages brought By them again return'd, to me it came, Who to Apollo consecrate the same. For Since to seek the wisest, he enjoyn'd, I Judge no man but God by that design'd. Now on the stage (as those before) I come T'assert the truth of my own Axiom. Perhaps by some t'may be offensive thought: But not by those by sad experience taught. ???()?? ?????? ?? ???, say we. Be Surety, and be sure a loser be. A thousand Instances I could produce To prove Repentance is the only use That can be made of it, but that we here Examples by their Names to cite, forbear. Make your own Application, and conceive The Damage, Men by this sole act receive. Nor this our good intention take amisse, You that like, clap, you that dislike it, hisse. Enter Bias. I am Priænean Bias, who once taught ?? ??()???? ()??, That most men are naught. I wish't had been unspoke; for Truth gains Hate. But by bad men I mean illiterate, And those who barbarously all Lawes confound, Religion, Justice; for within this Round I see none but are good: believe all those Whom I proclaim for bad amongst your Foes: Yet there is none so partially apply'd To favour Vice, but with the good will side: Whether he truly be such, or would fain Of a good man the Reputation gain: The hated name of an ill man all shun. Then (most good Men) your praise, and I ha' done. Enter Pittacus. I'm Pittacus, who once this Maxime penn'd, ????????? That's, time apprehend. But by Time we meant Time in Season, as In tempore veni is your Roman Phrase. And your own Comick Poet Terence, he, Chief of all things makes opportunity, Where Dromo comes unto Antiphila. I'th nick of Time; consider what I say, And mark how great an inconvenience Most suffer through this want of providence. But now 'tis more then time we should be gon; Farewell, and give your Aprobation. [Exit. Enter Periander. Now on the Stage see Periander move! He who once said, and what he said will prove ?????? ?? ???. Thought is all in all. Since him a perfect Agent we may call, Who first considers what he undergoes; For we should still forecast, as Terence showes, Th'event of businesse, whether good or bad, E'r w'undertake it: where may best be had Conveniency for planting, where to build, When to wage War, and when to pitch a Field: Nor inconsiderately take in hand Or great, or small Things, for that makes a stand In the free progresse of all new designes; In which there's nothing policy enjoynes Like consultation; hence we see it cleer, Who use it not, by chance, not counsell steer, But I retire, whilst you with better Fate Imploy your Thoughts how to uphold your State: THE CLOVDS of Aristophanes. Added (not as a Comicall divertisement for the Reader, who can expect little in that kind from a subject so antient, and particular, but) as a necessary supplement to the life of Socrates. Act 1. Scen. 1. Strepsiades, Phidippides, Servant. Streps. Oh, oh, Great Jove, how long a night is this, how endlesse! Will't neer be day? I heard the Cock again, Yet still my servantssnore; 'tis but of late They durst do thus: curse o'this war that awes me, And will not suffer me to beat the Rogues. My good Son sleeps too, wrapt ore head and ears: Well, let me try to bear them company; Alasse, I cannot, so perplext and tortur'd With charges, bills for Horse-meat, interest: All for this hopefull Son, who in's curl'd locks, Aides matches, keeps his Coach, and dreames of Horses, Whilst I (unhappy!) see th'unwelcome Moon Bring on the Quarter day, and threaten use-mony. Boy, snuffe the light, bring my account-book hither, That I may summe my debts and interest: Let's see, twelve pound to Pasia; ha! twelve pound To Pasia, how laid out? to buy Coppatia: Would I had paid this eye for him. Phid. Hold Philo, You'r out of the way, begin again. Strep. I this, This is the misery that ruines me; His very sleeps are taken up with Horses. Phid. How many courses will the manage hold. Streps. Many a weary course thou leads thy Father: But how much more owe I then this to Pasia? Three pound t'Amynias for Chariot wheeles. Phid. Go sirrah, take that horse and turn him out. Streps. I thou hast turned me out of all my means, Charges at Law will eat me up, my Creditours Threaten to sue me to an execution. Phid. Why do you wake all night, and tosse so Father? Streps. I cannot sleep, the Scrivener doth so bite me. Phid. Yet let me rest a little longer. Streps. Do so. All these will one day light upon thy head, Curs'd be the houre when I first saw thy Mother, I liv'd before most sweetly in the Country, Well stock't with Sheep and Bees, Olives and Grapes, Till from the Megaclean house I took This Neece of Megacles out of the City, Well fashion'd, highly bred, and richly cloathed; We married, as I said, and lay together: I smelling strong of Drugs and greasie Wool; But she of Unguents, Crocus wanton Kisses, Of vain expence, dainties, and luxury; I will not tell the idle life she led, And yet she spun that I have often told her, Showing this Coat, you spin a fair thread woman. Serv. Sir, all the Oyle ith' Lamp is wasted. Streps. Ha? Why didst thou put in such a Drunken week? If thou wert neer me I would beat thee. Ser. Why Sir? Streps. Because the week is thicker then the oyl. Well, at last my good Wife and I betwixt us got At last this Son; about his name we differ'd; Shee'd have it something that belong'd to horses, Callippides, Xanthippus, or Charippus; I from his Grandfather) Phidonides. Long time we wrangled thus, at last agreed He should be called Phidippides; this Son She takes, and stroaking kindly, thus instructs him, “When thou art grown a man, frequent the City, “Follow the fashion, keep a Coach and Horses, “Like Megacles thy Uncle. No, said I, “Go in a homely Coat, and drive thy Goats “Into Phelleus, as thy father doth. But my advice prevailed so little on him, That now he wasts my means in keeping horses, Which all this night I have been thinking how To remedy, and now have found the way; To which could I perswade him, I were happy. Phidippides, Phidippides, Phid. Your will Sir. Streps. Kisse me, give me thy hand. Phid. Here Sir. Streps. Dost love me? Phid. By Neptune God of Horses. Streps. Do not name That God, for 'tis from him springs all my sorrow: But if thou lov'st me truly, heartily, O son be rul'd. Phid. In what should I be rul'd? Streps. Change without more delay thy course of life, And do as I would have thee. Phid. What is that? Streps. But wilt thou do it? Phid. Yes by Bacchus will I. Streps. Come hither then, seest thou that little dore? That is the Phrontistherium of wise soules, Of learned men, that tell us Heaven's an Oven, And we the Coles inclosed in the wide arch, They, if we give 'em but a little mony, Will teach us gain all causes, right or wrong. Phid. Who can these be? Streps. Their names I know not good They are, and busied in continuall study. Phid. Oh now I know the wretches that you mean, The meager, wan, proud, bare-foot, begging fellowes, Whose evill Geniuss's are Socrates And Chærephen. Streps. Peace, talk no more so idly; If you'l obey a father, let me see you Give ore your horses, and turn one of these. Phid. Not I, by Bacchus, no though you should tempt me With all Leogoras his breed of Racers. Streps. Dear son be rul'd and learn. Phid. What should I learn? Streps. 'Tis said they have two tongues, and one of them Able to prove any injustice reason; Couldst thou but learn that language, we were made, And might dispute our stubborn Creditours Out of the debts I have incurr'd for thee; They get not then a penny more then words. Phid. I cannot do't, were I so lean and Pale, I durst not look a Jocky in the face. Streps. By Ceres then you stay with me no longer, You, nor your Coach-horse, nor your Samphoras, But all together pack out of my dores. My Uncle Megacles will neither see Me nor my horses want, so long I care not. Exit. Scene 2. Strepsiades, Scholar. Streps. Though I have fail'd, i'l not give over thus, But say my prayers, and go my self to school To learn this Art: but how can I, by Age Dull and forget full, reach such subtleties? Yet on I will, why should I doubt? ho, friend. Schol. A mischief on you, who's that knocks at dore? Streps. Strepsiades, Cecinnian Phædo's Son. Schol. 'Twas rudely done to knock so hard, y'have made My labouring brain miscarry of a Notion. Streps. Forgive me, I was bred far off ith' Country: But pray what notion was't that prov'd abortive? Schol. 'Tis lawfull to discover that tonone But fellow-scholars. Streps. Then you may tell me, For I come hither to be one of you. Schol. I will; so will value't as a mysterie. Socrates t'other day ask'd Chærephon How many of her feet a flea could leap, For one by chance had bit Chærephons eyebrow, And leap'd from thence upon the head of Socrates. Streps. How could he measure this? Schol. Most dexterously. Both feet oth' flea he dipt in melting wax, Which strait congeals to shooes; these he plucks off, And with them most exactly measures it. Streps. Great Jupiter, how subtle are these wits! Schol. If you shouldst hear their other speculations, You would say so indeed. Streps. Pray what was that? Schol. This Charæphon the Sphettian ask'd him once, If a Gnat sounded from her mouth or tail. Streps. And what said he? It had a strait thin gut, At end of it a bladder, into which The air being forc'd, sounded in breaking forth. Streps. Then I perceive that a gnat's tail's a Trumpet; How blest is this Anatomist of Gnats! Sure he can hide himself from purblind justice, That knows so well these dark intestine waies. Why should we cry up Thales any longer? Come open me your Phrontisterium, And quickly let me see this Socrates, I long to learn, open the dore,—O Hercules What strange beasts have we here! Schol. Why do you wonder? Whom do they look like think you? Streps. Like the poor Lacedæmonian Captives tane at Pylus. Why look they so intently on the ground? These seek out things that appertain to Earth! Oh they seek leeks; trouble your selves no more friends, For I know better where are good and great ones. Schol. Come let's go in. Streps. Let's stay a while and talk with 'em. Schol. No, no, they cannot long endure the air. Streps. What's this, for Heavens sake say? Schol. This is Astronomy. Streps. And this? Schol. Geometry. Strop. But what is't good for? Schol. To measure land: Streps. What, arable or pasture? Schol. No, the whole Earth. Streps. A pretty jest indeed. That were a mighty help to husbandmen. Schol. Here's all the world, and this is Athens. Streps. How? I'l scarce believe that, what's become oth' Judges? Where the Cicynians my Countymen? Schol. Here; this Eubæa; see how far 'tis stretch'd. Streps. I, almost stretch'd in pieces betwixt us, And Pericles; and where is Lacedæmon? Schol. Here. Strepss. 'Tis too nigh us, why, with all your skill Do you not help to thrust it farther off. Schol. It is not possible. Streps. No? you will rue't then. But what man's that hangs yonder in the basket? Schol. That's he. Streps. He, what he? Schol. Socrates. Streps. How, Socrates? Call him. Schol. Call him your self, I'm not at leasure. Scene 3. Strepsiades, Socrates. Streps. Ho Socrates Socr. Why dost thou call me mortall? Streps. First I would gladly know what thou dost there? Socr. I walk ith' aire, and gaze upon the Sun. Streps. Why in a basket dost thou view the Gods, Not from the ground? Socr. I could not elevate My thoughts to contemplation of these mysteries, Unlesse my Intellect were thus suspended, Where my thin thoughts melt into air (their likeness) Stood I upon the ground, I should find nothing, Though I sought nere so strictly up and down, For the magnetick vertue of the Earth Would draw away the humour of my brain, Just as we see in nose-smart. Streps. How, hows that? Doth the brain draw the humour out of nose-smart? Come down, sweet Socrates, and teach me quickly The knowledge of those things for which I came. Socr. What camest thou for? Streps. To learn the art of speaking, With debts and usury I'm torn in pieces Tost up and down; forc'd to pawn all my goods: Socr. On what occasion did you run in debt? Streps. By horses eaten into this consumption; And I would learn of you your other language Which teacheth men to pay nothing: for which By all the Gods i'l give you what you'l ask. Socr. By all what Gods? we do not here allow Those Gods the City worships. Streps. How then swear you, By copper farthings like the Byzantines? Socr. Wouldst thou be skilfull in divine affairs. Streps. By Jove (if any such there be) I would. Socr. You must be then acquainted with the Clouds, Our reverend Goddesses. Streps. With all my heart. Socr. Sit down upon this Couch then Streps. Well. Socr. Now take This Garland. Streps. Why a garland? alasse Socrates, D'ee mean (like Athamas) to sacrifice me? Socr. No, these are rites that every one performes At his admission. Streps. But what shall I gain by? Socr. Thou shallt be made most voluble in speech, A very rattle, bolting words as fine As flower. Streps. Th'art right by Jove, I shall be powderd. Socr. silence old man, and listen to our prayer. “Great King, unbounded air, whose armes are hurld “About the surface of this pendant world, “Bright Æther, reverend Clouds, that from your Spheas “Thunder and lightning dart, rise and appear. Streps. Not yet, not yet, till I have wrapt my selfe Close in my Cloak, lest I be wet: twas ill That I forgat to bring my Riding hood. Socr. “Your power, great Clouds, make to this suppliant known “Whether now seated on Olympus Throne, “Or whether you your sacred revells keep “In the wide Gardens of your Sire the deep: “Or of his flowing Christall seaven-mouth'd Nile, “In golden Ewers wantonly beguile: “Or in Mauritian marshes keep your Court; “Or on the snowy top of Mimas sport. “Come, to our servant vowes propitious be; “Grace with your presence our solemnitie. “We humid fleeting Deities, “The bright unbounded clouds thus rise “From our old Sire, the grumbling Flood, “Above the tallest hill or wood, “To those high watch-towers, whence we may “The hallowed fruitfull-ground survey; “Rivers that in soft murmurs glide, “And the lowd sea's rebellious tide; “From thence heavens restlesse eye displaies “The splendour of his glorious raies, “Chasing all dusky mists, that we “In shapes divine may mortalls see. Socr. Thanks reverend Clouds for favouring thus our prayer. Did you not hear'm speak in Thunder to us? Streps. Great Clouds, I worship too, but am so frighted, I scarce can hold from answering your Thunder. Socr. Jest not profanely in such sacred rites: Peace, for the swarm of Goddesses come singing. Chor. “Come virgin Mistresses of showers, “Let's visit Pallas pregnant bowers, “The far renowned Cecroplan plain “Where shines the Eleusinian Fane, “Where are the most retir'd aboads, “Statues and Temples of the Gods: “Where Altars blaze with Incense, where “The holy-day lasts all the year; “Where the brisk Craces every spring, “And youths with virgins dance and sing. Streps. Tell me good Socrates, what things are these That speak so finely? are they Ladies? Socr. No, They're Clouds, the Deities of idle men; From these we have our sense, discourse, and reason, Our high Capriccio's, and elaborate whimseys. Streps. My soul, me thought, did leap, while they were speaking, And now most subtly would dispute of smoak, Sharply confute opinion with opinion: Oh how I long to see them once again. Socr. Look yonder towards Parnes, look how gently They glide to earth. Streps. Where? show me. Socr. See in sholes They creep into the Caverns of the Mountain. Streps. What things are these? I cannot yet behold 'em. Socr. There in the entrance look. Streps. Yet I scarce see them. Socr. Either thou seest them now, or thou art blind. Streps. I do by Jove, great Clouds, for you hold all! Socr. Didst thou not know these Deities before? Streps. Not I, I thought them only mists and vapours: Socr. Thou knewest not then those who maintain the Sophists. Streps. If these be Clouds, how comes it that they look Like women? for the Clouds have no such shape. Socr. No, what shape have they then? Streps. I know not justly; They look like flying fleeces, but by Jove, Nothing at all like women; these have noses. Socr. Answer to what I ask. Streps. Ask me quickly. Socr. Didst ere behold a Cloud shap'd like a Centaure, A Leopard, Bull, or Wolfe? Streps. I have, what then? Socr. The Clouds can take what form they list, as when They see a hairy fellow curl'd like Clitus, They mock his madnesse in a Centaures shape. Streps. And when they see one that defrauds or plunders The Common-wealth, like Sinon, what then do they? Socr. They do resemble him, turn ravenous wolves, This was the reason yesterday, when they Beheld Cleonymus, they fled like deer: And seeing Clisthenes are now turn'd women. Streps. Great Queens, if you ere design to speak to mortalls, Make me acquainted with your rumbling voice. Chor. “All hail old man, who dost on wisdome prey, “And thou the Priest of subtle trifles say, “What wouldst thou have with us, to none but thee, “Of all the Meteor Sophists thus stoop we; “Save Prodicus, to him as grave and wise, “To thee, because thou walkst upright, thy eyes “Rowling on every side, thy look severe “And barefoot many miseries dost bear. Streps. Good heavens, what voice is this, how strange &amp; stately. Socr. These are our Goddesses, the rest are toyes. Streps. Is then Olympian Jove no Deity? Socr. What Jove? there's no such thing; meer fancy. Streps. How? Whence then proceeds all rain? Socr. Only from these. Didst thou ere see a shower without them? take The Clouds away, and heaven must rain fair weather. Streps. By Phœbus thou hast cleer'd it well, till now I thought Jove made water through a sive. But whence comes thunder? when I'me sick, that frights me, These thunder as they tumble up and down. How can that be? Socr. When they are full of water, By their own weight, driven upon one another, They roar and break. Streps. But who is it that drives them, Is not that Jove? Socr. No, an ætheriall whirlewind. Streps. A whirle-wind, hum! I knew not that til now. But whence comes lightning then, that glittering fire Which terrifies and burns us? Jupiter Useth to dart this down on perjur'd men. Socr. And how (thou phlegmatick, dull Saturnine,) If darted on the perjur'd, how comes Sinon, Theorus, and Cleonymus to 'scape it? No, his own Temple, or the Sunian Promontory, Or sturdy Oakes he strikes, did they ere wrong him? Did the Oak ere forswear it selfe? Streps. I know not: That which you say seems reasons; but what then Is lightning? Socr. When the winds are shut up close, They swell the clouds like bladders, and at last Break out with violence and horrid noises; And by contrition kindle one another. But thou who searchest amongst us for wisdom, How happy wilt thou be above all Græcians If thou conceive well, and remember, and Canst suffer much, and never wilt be tir'd Standing or walking, nor have sense of frost, Nor care for dyning, and refrain from wine, From exercises, and all other toyes. Streps. O for a solid soul restlesse with cares, Sparing, self-torturing, one that can feast Upon a dish of herbes, you never could Be better fitted; a meer an vile I. Socr. Dost thou believe no Gods but those we teach, The Chaos, Clouds and Tongue, onely these three. Streps. I'l not so much as speak of any other, Much lesse bestow an offering on their Altars. Chor. “Say boldy then, say what is thy request, “For if thou honour us thou shalt be blest. Streps. Great Queens I sue for a small matter, that I may out-talk all Greeks a hundred furlongs. Chor. “To thee alone this gift we will allow, “None speak such mighty sentences as Thou. Streps. I do not care for mighty sentences, But subtle ones to cheat my Creditours. Chor. “It is not much thou askst, and shalt obtain it, “Learn of our Ministers and thou shalt gain it. Streps. I shall, relying on your promise; forc'd By want, Coppatia and a lucklesse match. Now let'em use me as they list, beat, starve me, Burn, freeze, or flea me, so I scape my debts: I care not though men call me impudent, Smooth-tongu'd, audacious, petulant, abhominable, Forger of words and lie, contentious Barretour, Old, winding, bragging, testy, crafty fox. Socr. Said like a man of courage: if thou learn Of me, thy fame shall spread wide as the Heavens. Streps. What shall I do? Socr. Thou shalt spend all thy time With me; a life the happiest in the world. Streps. I long to see that day. Socr. Thy dore shall alwaies Be throng'd with Clients that will come to thee For Counsell, and discourse of cases worth The wealth of kingdoms, to thy hearts desire. Chor. “Try this old man; first see if he be fit; “Put him toth' test, and sound the depth of's wit. Socr. Come tell me now your disposition, That when I know it I may fit my Machines Accordingly. Streps. You will not undermine me. Socr. No, I would know if you have any memory. Streps. Yes, when another owes me any thing, I can remember very well, but what I owe my self, i'm ready to forget. Socr. Hast thou a naturall faculty in speaking Streps. No, I can mar words sooner far then make 'em. Socr. How wilt thou learn then? Streps. Fear me not, I tell you Wel, when I make some learned deep discourse. Socr. You must be sure to catch't up presently. Streps. What must I snap at learning like a dog? Socr. This is a very fool, an unknown Clown; I am afraid old man thou wilt need whipping. What if thou shouldst be beaten? Streps. Then i'm beaten. Socr. But what wouldst do? Streps. I would take witnesse on't And sue them on an action of Battery. Socr. Off with your Cloak. Streps. Why, how have I offended? Socr. No; but our orders admit none but naked. Streps. I came not hither to steal any thing. Socr. Down with your Cloak, why dost thou trifle. Streps. Now Tell me if I prove apt and diligent, Of all your schollars who shall I come nighest? Socr. Thou maist perhaps be like our Chærephon. Streps. Alasse, alasse! what an Anatomy? Socr. No, no: but if thou wilt be any thing, Follow me without more delay. Streps. I want A Cake for your Cerberus; I go me thinks As if'twere into the Trophonian Cave. Socr. On, on, why stayst thou gazing at the dore. Chor. “Go, for thy courage blest whose aged mind “To wisdom soars, and leaves the young behind. Exeunt. Act. 2. Socrates, Strepsiades. Socr. By Chaos, and this air I breath, I never Met any thing so stupid as this fellow, So clownish and oblivious; easie toyes He learns, not half so fast as he forgets 'em, I'l call him forth; what, ho, Strepsiades; Come out and bring your bed along with you. Str. The fleas will hardly let me bring my self. So. Quick, down with't there; and mark what I say to you. Str. I'm ready. So. What have you most mind to learn, Measures, or Verse, or Rhyme? Str. By all means measures; For I was cheated by a Meal man lately Two pecks. So. That's not the thing I demand; I'de know which you conceive the fairest measure, The Trimeter or the Tetrameter. Str. The fairest measure in my mind's a Bushell. So. 'Tis nothing that you say. Str. What will you lay That your Tetrameter holds not a Bushell. So. Away, away, how dull thou art, and blockish. But thou wilt be perhaps more apt at Rime. Str. What help can rimes afford me in my meal. So. First they wil make thee pleasant in all company. Then thou shalt know which suits with Anapæstick, And which with Dacty les. Str. Dactiles? I know that sure. So. Why what's a Dactyle. Str. What, but this same finger, 'Thas been a Dactyle ere since I was a child. So. Th'art an unprofitable Dunce. Str. I care not For learning these devices: So. What then wouldst thou? Str. That, that unjust and cheating Sophistry. So. But there are things that must be learnt before You come to that; what Creatures are there Masculine. Str. Sure I know that or I were mad indeed. A Ram, a Bull, a Goat, a Dog, a Pigeon. So. See how thou err'st, that call'st both male and female A Pigeon. Str. Right, by Neptune, how then must I? So. Call this a Cock, Pigeon, and that a Hen. Str. A Pigeon, Cock and Hen, ha! by this air, For this sole document, I will replenish Your Cardopus with meal. So. Again th'art wrong; Thou call'st it Cardopus, but 'tis hæc Cardopus, And therefore henceforth call it Cardopa. Next it is fit you know which names are Masculine, And which are feminine. Str. I know well which Are feminine, I'me sure. So. Lets hear. Str. Philina, Cletagora, Demetria, and Lystha. So. And which are Masculine? Str. A world, Philoxenus, Milesias, and Amynias. So. Thou art out. Str. Are not these Masculine with you? So. By no means. How if you saw Amynias, would you call him? Str. Amynia, ho! So. What, make a woman of him. Str. And reason good, h'has thrown away his armes, And will not fight. But to what purpose learn I These common trifles. So. Not so common neither, But come, lie down. Str. What must I do? So. Consider With your selfe the businesse that concernes you. Str. Not in this bed, I thank you, if I must Lie down, Ile meditate upon the ground. So. But heres no room besides. Str. Wretch that I am. How I shall be tormented with these fleas! So. Now think into the depth of thy affairs, Try every turn and winding, every double; And if you stick at any thing: give't ore, And to some other; but be sure you sleep not. Str. Oh, oh. So. How now the matter? Str. I am kill'd By these blood-suckers, these Corinthians. So. Do not torment your selfe. Str. How can I choose When I have neither mony left, nor colour, Scarce life, no shooes, grown almost to a Ghost With watching? So. Now what think y'on, nothing? Str. Yes By Neptune. So. What? Str. I'me thinking if the fleas Will leave a piece of me or not. So. Death on thee. Str. You might have spar'd your curse, I'm dead already. So. Fy, fy, you must not be so tender, cover Your face, and study for some subtle cheat. Str. Would I could learn to cheat these wicked fleas. So. Let's see what does he? what, asleep, ha'ye thought Of nothing yet? Str. What would you have me think on? So. What would you learn? Str. I've told you that already A thousand times; I'd learn to pay no use-mony. So. Come then, cover your self, and subtilize Your thoughts, diffect your businesse into Atomes. Str. Alasse. So. Ly still; and if you stick at anything, Passe by't a while, and come to it again. Str. Ho, my dear Socrates. So. What is't old man? Str. I have found out that will do't. So. As how. Str. First tell me Where I may meet with some Thessalian witch; For I would steal the Moon one of these nights, And having got her, lock her in a chest As charily, as I would keep a glasse. So. What wilt thou get by that? Str. What, if the Moon Ne'r rise again, I'me bound to pay no use. So. How so? Str. 'Cause use you know is paid by th'Month. So. 'Tis well, but I'le propound another businesse; Suppose that you were tyed upon a statute To pay five Talents, could you rase figures? Str. I know not, but I'le try. So. You must not limit Your thoughts so narrowly within your selfe, But like a beetle fetter'd in a thread, Allow them play and flutter in the air. Str. I ha't, I ha't, the rarest way to cancell A deed, as you'l confesse when you have heard it. So. What is't? Str. Did you nere see at any Grocers A clear transparant stone, with which they use To kindle fire? So. You mean a burning-glasse. Stro. The very same. So. What wouldst thou do with it? Str. Whilst that the Scrivener writes the deed, d'ee mark, Thus standing by him with my burning-glasse Against the Sun, I'l burn out every letter. So. Wisely by all the Graces. Str. How I long To cancell thus a bond of fifty pound. So. 'Tis well, now tell me if thy adversary Sue thee, and thou art like to be orethrown For want of witnesses, how wilt thou void His suit. Str. Most easily. So. Which way? Str. Before It comes to judgement, I would hang my self. So. Push, thou sayst nothing. Str. Yes, by Iove there's none Will prosecute a suit against the dead. So. Away, thou fool'st; i'l teach no more. Str. Why dear Socrates, Why? So. Thou forget'st as fast as thou canst learn. Tell me the first thing thou wert taught to day. Str. The first, stay let me see; the first thing say you? How call you that we use to put our meal in? Wretch, Iv'e forget it! So. See, deserv'st thou not Forgetfull to be punish'd for a dunce, Str. Alasse what shall I do? for if I learn not The cheating language, I am quite undone; Good Clouds advise me what course I shall take. Cho. “If an ingenious son thou hast at home, “Thou hadst best send him hither in thy room. Str. I have a son, and he's ingenious too; But will not learn, the more my misery. Cho. And wilt thou suffer't? Str. Of a promising person His mother is a woman of great spirit: Once more Ile try; if he refuse, i'l make No more adoe but turn him out of dores; Stay but a while, I will be quickly back. Act. 3. Strepsiades, Phidippides, Socrates. Str. Now by the Clouds thou staist no longer here? Hence, and go feed in Megacles his stable. Ph. Alasse what fury hath possest you Father? By Jove I think you are besides your self. Str. See, see, he swears by Iove, art thou not mad At these years to believe there is a Jove? Ph. Is truth to be derided? Str. Well I see Th'art still a Child and credit'st old wives tales. But come I will tell thee that shall make thee A man, so you be sure to tell it nobody. Ph. Pretty; what is't? Str. Thou swor'st e'en now by Jove. Ph. I did so. Str. See how good it is to learn; There's no such thing as Iove. Ph. What then? Str. A whirlwind Hath blown Iove quite away and rules all Heaven. Ph: What fooleries are these? Str. They're serious truth son. Ph. Who tells you so? Str. Our Socrates the Melian, And Chærephon, that trace the steps of fleas. Ph. How, are you grown to such a height of madness, As to believe such melancholy dreamers. Str. Good words: defame not men of such deep wisdom And subtle spirits; these live sparingly, Are never at the charges of of a Barber, Unguents, or Baths, whereas thou wasts my means As freely as if I were dead already. Come then, and be their scholler in my room. Ph. What can be learnt that's good of such as they are? Str. All things that are accompted wisdom Boy; And first to know thy self, and what a dunce Thou art, how blockish, rustick and forgetfull. But stay a little, cover thy face a while. Ph: Alasse my fathers mad, what shall I do, Accuse him to the Court of folly, Bespeak a Coffin for him, for he talks Idly, as he were drawing on? Str. Come on now. Let's see, what that? Ph. A Pigeon. Str. Good; and that? Ph. A Pigeon. Str. Both the same? ridiculous. Take heed you make not such mistakes hereafter. This you must call a Cock, and that a Hen. Ph. A Hen? Is this the goodly learning Father You got since your admission 'mongst these earth-wormes? Str. This and a great deal more; but being old, I soon forget what I am taught. Ph. I think 'Twas want of memory made you lose your cloak. Str. No, 'tis hung up upon the arts and sciences: Ph. And where your shooes? Str. Lost for the common good, Like Pericles: But lets be gone and see You learn t'obey me, and to wrong all else. Remember that I bought thee, when thou wert But fix yeers old, a little Cart to play with. Ph. Alasse you'l be the first that will repent this. Str. Take you no care for that; do as I bid you. Ho, Socrates, I've brought my son at last, Though much against his will. So. I, that's because He's rude, untaught, a child of ignorance, And unacquainted with our hungry baskets. Ph. Go hang your self in one of them. Str. How impudence; dost thou talk thus to thy Master? Socr. So go hang, with what a seeming grace was that pronounc'd! How do you think that he should ever learn To overthrow a nimble adversary, Or win a Judges heart with Rhetorick? Str. Fear not, but teach him; he's ingenious By Nature; for when he was but a little one, Hee'd build you houses, and make leather Coaches, And ships, and cut frogs out of apple parings. What's your opinion then? do you not think Hee's capable to learn both languages? Or if not both, be sure he learn the worse. Socr. Well, we shall try what may be done with him. Str. Farewell, and so remember that in all I say that's just, you learn to contradict me. Act. 4. Scœn. 1. Strepsiades. Streps. The fift, the fourth, the third, the second; hum. The most abhord and dreadfull day's at hand, The old and new; all I ow money to Threaten to sue and vow my utter ruine; Yet I require nothing but what is just reason: My friend forbear me till some other time; But they all answer me, words are no payment, Revile me, swear they'l put their bonds in suit, And let 'em, what care I, so my Phidippides Have learnt the art of cheating: I shall know straight; It is but knocking at the school, ho son. Scœn. 2. Strepsiades, Socrates. Socr. Save you Strepsiades. Streps. The like to you. First take this bag of meal, for it is fit We pay our duty to our reverend Master, Now tell me, has my son attain'd the art For which I plac'd him with you. Socr. Yes exactly. Streps. Thanks to deceit, the Queen that governs all things. Socr. Now you may overthrow all adversaries. Streps. What though a witnesse swear that I have borrowed. Socr. I though a thousand swear't. Streps. Iò. Iò. Triumph my boyes, wo to you money-mongers, You and your bonds, your use on use may hang now, You'l trouble me no more! O what a son Have I, that fenceth with a two-edg'd tongue, My Houses prop and Guardian, my foes terrour, Quickly come forth, and meet my glad embraces, Come forth and hear thy Father. Socr. See the man. Streps. O my dear boy! Socr. Away and take him with you. Scœne 3. Strepsiades, Phidippides. Streps. Io my son! O how I joy to see Thy chang'd complexion! Thou lookst now me thinks As if thou wert inspir'd with contradiction I read, crosse questions in thy very face, Thy very eyes me thinks say, how, how's that? Thou canst perswade the world that thou art wrong'd, When thou art, he that does the wrong. I see't, I plainly see't; a very Attick mine; Now let it be thy study to recover Him, whom thou almost hast undone. Phid. Why, what Is that you fear? Streps. The old and the new day. Phid. Can one and the same day be old and new? Streps. I know that: I'm sure my Creditors By joint consent that day threaten to sue me. Phil. They'l loose by it if they do: for 'tis impossible To make two daies of one. Streps. How is't impossible? Phil. As for a woman to be old and young At once. Streps. But law has so determined it Phil. But these men know not what the law doth mean. Streps. Why what's the meaning of it. Phil. Antient Solon Was naturally a lover of the people. Streps. What's that to this? Phid. He did appoint two daies, The last day of the old month for citation, The first oth' new for payment of the money. Streps. But why the last day for citations? Phil. That The debtor having th us one day of warning Might fly and shun the trouble of the next. So. Why do the Magistrates then take all forfeits Upon the old and new day? Ph. They are hungry, And tast their meat before they should fall too. Str. We the fools that sit still and do nothing, We that are wise and quick have done the businesse; Ye blocks, ye stones, ye sheep, ye empty bubbles; Let me congratulate this son of min My selfe and my good fortune in a song. “Now Strepsiades th'art blest “Of the most discreet the best, “What a Son thou hast, now may “All my æmulous neighbours say, “When they hear that he alone “Hath my creditours orethrown. But come my boy, now thou shalt feast with me. Sect. 4. Pasias, Strepsiades, Witnesse. Pas. And must a man be outed of his own thus? Better take any course then suffer this. You must assist me in this businesse neighbour, That I may call my debtor to accompt; There's one friend made a foe; yet I'le not shame My country, ere I do't, I'le give him warning. Strepsiades. Streps. How now, what would you have? Pas. The old and new daies come. Streps. Bear witnesse friend, He nam'd two daies. What summe is't you demand. Pas. Twelve pounds you borrow'd when you bought your Son A Race-horse; with the interest. Streps. A race-horse, You know I neer car'd for 'em in my life. Pas. And swor'st by Jove and all the Gods to pay it. Streps. By Jove? 'twas then before my son had learn't The all-convincing speech. Pas. You'l not deny't. Streps. What have I got but that, for all this learning? Pas. Darst thou deny't, if I should put thee to Thy oath, and make thee call the Gods to witness it? Streps. What Gods de'e mean? Pas. Jove, Mercury, and Neptune. Streps. By Iove? yes that I will I hold thee three pence. Pas. Curse on thee for this impudence. Streps. If thou wert rubb'd with salt, 'twould make thy wit the quicker. Pas. De laugh at me? Streps. Thou wilt take up six bushells. Pas. So help me Jupiter, and all the Gods, I will even be with you for this scorn. Streps. I am extreamly taken with your Gods, And this same Iupiter you swear by, they Are excellent pastime to a knowing man. Pas. Well, you will one day answer for these words. But tell me, whether I shall have my money Or not, give my answer, and I'me gone. Streps. Stay but a little, I will answer presently, And plainly. Pas. Sure hee's gone to fetch the mony. Streps. Where is the Man that comes to ask me mony? Tell me, what's this? Pas. That which it is, a Cardopus. Streps. You ask for mony, and so very a dunce; I'le never whilst I live pay him a penny. That calls a Cardopa a Cardopus. Pas. You will not pay then? Streps. Not for ought I know: You'l stay no longer, pray about your businesse. Pas. Yes, I'le be gone, but in the mean time know I'le have my mony, if I live this day. Streps. You may chance go without it; yet I'm sorry You should be punish'd so for a mistake, For saying Cardopus for Cardopa. Scœn. 8. Amynias, Strepsiades, Witnesse. Amyn. Oh, oh, alasse. Streps. Who's that keeps such a bawling? What art thou? one of Carkinus his sons? Amyn. 'I is I unhappy! Streps. Keep it to thy selfe. Amyn. Unlucky chance, oh cruell destiny, To spoil at once my Cart and all my Horses! Oh Pallas, how unkindly hast thou us'd me? Streps. What hurt did ere Tlepolemus do thee? Amyn. Deride me not, but rather bid your son Pay me the mony which he had of me, For I was never in more need of it. Streps. What mony man? Amyn. That which he borrowed of me. Streps. Then I perceive you're in a sad condition. Am. I had a scurvy fall driving my horses. Streps. Thou dost but jest, 'twas driving an Asse rather. Amyn. I do not jest when I demand my mony. Streps. Upon my word thou art not right. Amyn. How so? Streps. Thy brain me thinks is troubled. Amyn. Either pay me My money strait, or I will trouble you. Streps. Tell me, doth Jove beget and send down rain, Or doth the Sun exhale it from the sea? Amyn. I neither know nor care. Streps. What? are you fit To receive mony, and so ignorant Of these sublime and subtle mysteries. Amyn. Well, if you cannot let me have the principal, Pay me the interest. Streps. Interest, what kind Of creature's that? Amyn. What, but th'encrease of mony By months, and daies, as time runs on. Streps. 'Tis well. And do you think the sea is fuller now Then 'twas at first? Amyn. No, not a drop, it is Not fit it should. Streps. The sea by your confession Is nothing grown; then with what conscience Can you desire your mony should encrease. Go get you from my doores, fetch me a whip there. Witn. Well, I'le bear witnesse for him. Streps. Why de'e not go, will you move Sumphoras? Amyn. Is not this riotous? Streps. Will you be gone? Or shall I lead you in a chain, and make you Shew tricks? if you but stay a little longer, I'le send you, and your Cart and Horses packing. Chor. “Now observe what 'tis to bend “Studies to an evill end “This old man, that is intent “Creditours to circumvent, “Foolishly himselfe hath crost, “And will find so to his cost; “That in this false Art his son “Hath attain'd perfection: “Justice cunning to refute) “That at last hee'l wish him mute. Act. 5. Scene 1. Strepsiades, Phidippides. Streps. O Neighbours, Kinsmen, Countrymen, help, help, I'm beat all all over: oh my head, my back! Thou strik'st thy Father Rogue. Phid. I do so father. Streps. See, see, he stands in't too. Phid. I do indeed. Streps. Thief, villain, Parricide. Phid. More I beseech you, I am much taken with these pretty Titles. Streps. Rascall. Phid. Pray stick me fuller of these roses: Streps. Dost beat thy Father? Phid. Yes, by Jove, and justly. Streps. Oh' rogue what justice can there be in that: Phid. I will demonstrate it by argument. Streps. By argument? Phid. Most easily, which language Shall I dispute in. Streps. Language? Phid. Yes the greater Or lesser? Streps. I have bred thee well indeed If thou canst make this good, that any son May beat his Father. Phid. You'l confesse as much If I so prove it, that you cannot answer't. Streps. Well, I will hear for once what you can say. Scœn 2. Chorus, Streps Phidip. Cho. “Old man it much concerns you to confute “Your son, whose confidence appears to suit “With a just cause; how happen'd this dispute? Str. I shall relate it from the first; as soon As we had din'd, I took a lute and bid him Sing the sheep-shearing of Simonides, He told me 'twas an old and ugly fashion To sing at dinner like a millers wife. Phi. And was not this sufficient to deserve A beating; when you'd make men chirp like Grasse-hoppers? Str. Just so he said within; and added that Simonides was an unpleasant Poet. I must confesse I hardly could forbear him; But then I bid him take a Myrtle branch, And act some piece of Æschylus, that Æschylus Saith he, is of all Poets the absurdest, The hat shest, most disorderly and bumbast. Did not my heart pant at this language think you? Yet I represt it; Then said I, rehearse A learned speech out of some modern wit; He strait repeats out of Euripides A tedious long Oration, how the Brother (Good Heavens) did violate his sisters bed. Here I confesse I could contain no longer But chid him sharply; to dispute we went, Words upon words, till he at last to blowes, To strike, to pull, to tear me. Phi. And not justly? You that would discommend Euripides The wisest of all Poets. Str. Wisest? ah What did I say, I shall be beat agen. Ph. By Iove, and you deserve't. Str. How, deserve it? Ungratefull wretch, have I not brought thee up, Fed and maintain'd thee from a little one, Supplied thy wants? how then can I deserve it? Chor. “Now I believe each youthfull breast “With expectation possest, “That if the glory of the day “Be from the Plantiffe born away, “By this example they may all “Upon the old men heavy fall; “What you have done with utmost art, “To justifie is now your part. Phid. How sweet it is to study, sage new things; And to contemn all fundamental lawes! When I applied my mind to Horse-coursing I could not speak three words but I was out; Now since I gave it ore, I am acquainted With ponderous sentences and subtle reasons, Able to prove I ought to beat my Father. Str. Nay, follow racing still, for I had rather Maintain thy horses then be beaten thus. Phid. I will begin where you did interrupt me, And first will ask, did you not beat me when I was a child? Streps. But that was out of love. Phid. 'Tis very right, tell me then, ought not I To recompence your love with equall love; If to be beaten be to be belov'd, Why should I suffer stripes, and you have none? I am by nature born as free as you; Nor is it fit the sons should be chastiz'd, And not their parents. Str. Why? Phid. You urge the Law, That doth allow all children to be beaten: To which I answer, Old men are twice children, And therefore ought, when they offend, be punish'd As well as we. Str But there's no Law that saies The Parents should be punished. Phid. Was not he Who made that Law, a man as you and I, He form'd a Law, which all the old men follow'd; Why may not I as well prescribe another, And all the young men follow my advice: But all the blowes before this Law was made Must be forgiven without all dispute. Besides, mark how the Cocks and other creatures Fight with their sires, who differ not at all From us, save only that they make no lawes. Streps. Why then if you will imitate the Cocks, Do you not dine upon a Dunghill, and Lodge in a hen-roost? Phid. 'Tis not all one case, Our Socrates doth not approve so far. Streps. Approve not then their fighting, but in this Thou plead'st against thy selfe. Phid. How so? Streps. Because Th'authority I exercise o're thee Will be thine own, when ere thou hast a son. Phid. But if I ne'r have any, then I never Shall have authority, and you will go To th'grave deriding me. Streps. 'Tis too much reason. Phid. Hear now another argument. Streps. I'me lost. Phid. And then perhaps you'l take the blowes I gave you Not halfe so ill. Streps. What good shall I get by them? Phid. I'le beat my mother too. Streps. What sayest thou, thou? Why this is worse then t'other. Phid. What if I Prove by the second language that I ought? Streps. Why then you will have nothing more to do. But prove that you, and your wise Socrates, And wiser language may hang all together. O Clouds, all this I suffer through your means, For I in you wholly repos'd my trust. Chor. “Thy selfe art author of this misery, “Because to ill thou didst thy mind apply. Streps. Why did you then give me no warning of it? You know I was a rude and aged man. Chor. “This is our custome, whensoere we find “Any to malice or deceit enclin'd, “Into some dreadfull mischief such we thrust, “That they may fear the Gods, and learn what's just. Streps. Alasse, this is a mischief, and a just one, For I ought not, when I had borrow'd mony, To seek out wayes t'avoid restoring it. Come then my son, let us be reveng'd Upon that wicked Socrates and Cheræphon, Who have abus'd us both. Phid. I will not wrong My Masters. Streps. Reverence Celestiall Jove. Phid. Celestiall Jove, see how you rave now father: There's no such thing as Iove. Streps. There is. Phid. A whirle-wind Hath blown Iove quite away, and rules all. Streps. No son, he's not expell'd, I was but fool'd To worship in his room a fictile deity. Phid. Nay if you will needs be mad, be mad alone. Scœn. 3. Strepsiades. Streps. Mad that I was to trust in Socrates, And cast off all our Gods; good Mercury Be not displeas'd, or punish, but forgive me, That took such paines, and studied to talk idly, And tell me what I'de best do with these fellowes, Sue them or punish 'em some other way— Th'art in the right, I will not sue them then, But as thou bidst me set their Nest on fire; Come Xanthias, come, a fork and ladder quickly. Get up and pluck the house about their Ears, Quick if thou lovest thy master; one of you Go light a torch, and bring it hither strait: Proud as they are I mean to bring 'em lower. Scœn 4. Scholar, Strepsiades, Socrates, Chærephon. Schol. Oh. oh! Strep. Torch to thy work, set fire apace. Schol. What art thou doing man? Streps. That which I'm doing; Disputing somewhat hotly with your school here. Schol. Alasse, who's this that sets our house on fire? Streps. He whom you cosen'd of his cloak. Schol. Thou kill'st, Thou kil'lst us man. Streps. That is the thing I mean, If my fork hold and ladder, do not fail me. So. How now, what do you make on our house-ridge. Streps. I walk i'th air and gaze upon the Sun. So. Alasse I'm choak'd. Streps. Why dost thou scorn the Gods then? Chær. Oh me I burn; Streps. Now you may calculate The motions of the Moon; tear, pluck, beat, burn 'em. For many reasons they deserve the flame, But most because they did the Gods disclaim. [Bion the Boristhenite] Bion the Boristhenite, By his Birth to Scythia known, Did religious duties slight, Gods affirming there were none. If to what he then profest, Firm he had continued still, Then his tongue had spoke his breast, And been constant though in ill. But the same who Gods deni'd, He who sacred fanes despis'd, He who mortalls did deride, When to Gods they sacrific'd; Tortur'd by a long disease, And of deaths pursuit afraid, Guifts their anger to appease On their hearths and Altars laid. Thus with smoak and incensetries To delight their sacred scent; I have sinn'd, not only cries, And what I profest repent. But unto an old wives charms Did his willing neck submit, And about his feeble armes Caus'd them leather thongs to knit. And a youthfull sprig of bayes Did set up before his gate: Every means and way essaies To divert approaching fate. Fool to think the Gods might be Brib'd with gifts, their favours bought, Or the sacred Deitie Were, and were not as he thought. But his wisdoms titles (now Turn'd to ashes) not avail With stretch'd arms, I know not how, Hail he cried, great Pluto hail. Epigrams. Upon one named Aster. The Stars, my Star, thou view'st; Heav'n I would be, That I with thousand eyes might gaze on Thee. Upon his Death. A Phosphor 'mongst the living late wert thou, But shin'st among the dead a Hesper now. Epitaph on Dion, engrav'd on his Tomb at Siracuse. Old Hecuba the Trojan Matron's years Were interwoven by the Fates with Tears; But thee with blooming hopes my Dion deckt, Gods did a Trophy of their pow'r erect. Thy honour'd reliques in their Country rest, Ah Dion! whose love rages in my breast. On Alexis. Fair is Alexis, I no sooner said, When every one his eyes that way convey'd: My soul (as when some dog a bone we show, Who snatcheth it) lost we not Phædrus so? On Archæanassa. To Archæ'nassa, on whose surrow'd brow Love sits in triumph, I my service vow; If her declining Graces shine so bright, What flames felt you, who saw her noon of light? On Agathon. My Soul, when I kiss'd Agathon, did start Up to my lip, just ready to depart. To Xantippe. An Apple I (Love's emblem) at the throw, Thou in exchange thy Virgin-zone bestow. If thou refuse my suite, yet read in this, How short thy years, how frail thy Beauty is. I cast the apple, loving those love thee, Xantippe yeeld, for soon both old will be. On the Eretrians vanquish'd by the Persians. We in Eubæa born Eretrians are Buried in Susa from our Country far: Venus and the Muses. Virgins (said Venus to the Muses) pay Homage to us, or, Love shall wound your Hearts: The Muses answer'd, take these toyes away, Our Breasts are proof against his childish darts. Fortune exchang'd. One finding Gold, in change, the halter quits, Missing his Gold, 'tother the halter knits. On Sappho. He, who believes the Muses Nine, mistakes; For Lesbian Sappho ten their number makes. Time. Time all things bring to passe, a change creates In Names, in Formes, in Nations and in States. Death. That is a Plough-man's grave, a Sailor's this; To Sea and Land alike Death common is. On one Shipwrack'd. The cruell Sea, which took my life away, Forbore to strip me of my last array: From this a covetous man did not refrain, Acting a crime so great for so small gain; But let him wear it to the shades, and there Before great Pluto in my cloaths appear. Another. [Safely (O Saylors) presse the Land, and wave] Safely (O Saylors) presse the Land, and wave, Yet know, ye passe a Shipwrack'd persons grave. On the Statue of Venus. Paphian Cythera, swimming crosse the Main, To Guidas came her Statue there to see, And from on high, surveying round the plain Where could Praxiteles me spy? (saith shee) He saw not what's forbidden mortall Eyes, 'Twas Mars's Steel that Venus did incize. Another. [Not carv'd by Steel, or Praxitele's fam'd hand] Not carv'd by Steel, or Praxitele's fam'd hand: Thus nak'd before the Judges did'st thou stand. Love sleeping. Within the Covert of a shady Grove, We saw the little red-cheek'd God of Love. He had nor Row nor Quiver, those among The neighb'ring Trees upon a bough were hung: Upon a Bank of tender Rose-buds laid He, (smiling) slept; Bees with their noise invade His rest, and on his lips their honey made, Pan Piping. Dwell awfull Silence on the shady Hills Among the bleating flocks, and purling rills, When Pan the Reed doth to his lip apply, Inspiring it with sacred Harmony, Hydriads, and Hamadryads at that sound In a well order'd measure beat the ground. On the Image of a Satyre in a Fountain and Love sleeping. A skilfull hand this Satyre made so near To life, that only Breath is wanting here: I am attendant to the Nymphs; before I fill'd out purple wine, now water powre; Who ere thou art com'st nigh, tread softly, lest You waken Love out of his pleasing rest. Another. [On horn'd Lyæus I attend] On horn'd Lyæus I attend, And powre the streams these Nayads lend, Whose noise Lov's slumber doth befriend. Another. [This Satyre Diodorus did not make] This Satyre Diodorus did not make, But charme asleep; if prick'd he will awake. On a Seal. Five Oxen grazing in a flow'ry Mead, A Jasper seal done to the life doth hold, The little herd away long since had fled, We'rt not inclos'd within a pale of Gold. The Sonnet. [Love, (whose hand guides my Hearts strict Reins] I. Love, (whose hand guides my Hearts strict Reins Nor, though he govern it, disdains To feed the fire with pious care Which first himself enkindled there) Commands my backward Soul to tell What Flames within her Bosom dwell; Fear would perswade her to decline The charge of such a high design; But all her weak reluctance fails, 'Gainst greater Force no Force avails. Love to advance her flight will lend Those wings by which he did descend Into my Heart, where he to rest For ever, long since built his Nest: I what from thence he dictates write, And draw him thus by his own Light. II. Love, flowing from the sacred spring Of uncreated Good, I sing: When horn; how Heaven be moves; the soul Informs; and doth the World controwl; How closely lurking in the heart, With his sharp weapons subtle art From heavy earth he Man unites, Enforcing him to reach the skies. How kindled, how he flames, how burns; By what laws guided now he turns To Heaven, now to the Earth descends, Now rests 'twixt both, to neither bends. Apollo, Thee I invocate, Bowing beneath so great a weight. Love, guide me through this dark design, And imp my shorter wings with thine. III. When from true Heav'n the sacred Sun Into th'Angelick Mind did ran, And with enliv'ned Leaves adorn, Bestowing form on his first-born; Enflamed by innate Desires, She to her chiefest good aspires; By which reversion her rich Brest With various Figures is imprest; And by this love exalted, turns Into the Sun for whom she burns. This flame, rais'd by the Light that shin'd From Heav'n into th'Angelick Mind, Is eldest Loves religious Ray, By Wealth and Want begot that Day, When Heav'n brought forth the Queen, whose Hand The Cyprian Scepter doth Command. IV. This born in amorous Cypris arms, The Sun of her bright Beauty warms. From this our first desire accrues, Which in new fetters caught, pursues The honourable path that guides Where our eternall good resides. By this the fire, through whose fair beams Life from above to Mankind streams, Is kindled in our hearts, which glow Dying, yet dying greater grow; By this th'immortal Fountain flows, Which all Heaven forms below, bestows; By this descends that shower of light Which upwards doth our minds invite; By this th'Eternall Sun inspires And souls with sacred lustre fires. V. As God doth to the Mind dispence Its Being, Life, Intelligence, So doth the Mind the soul acquaint How't understand, to move, to paint; She thus prepar'd, the Sun that shines In the Eternal Breast designs, And here what she includes diffuses, Exciting every thing that uses Motion and sense (beneath her store) To live, to know, to operate. Inferiour Venus hence took Birth; Who shines in heav'n, but lives on earth, And o're the world her shadow spreads: The elder in the Suns Gloss reads Her Face, through the confused skreen Of a dark shade obscurely seen; She Lustre from the Sun receives, And to the Other Lustre gives; Celestiall Love on this depends, The younger, vulgar Love attends. VI. Form'd by th'eternal Look of God, From the Suns most sublime abode, The Soul descends into Mans Heart, Imprinting there with wondrous Art What worth she borowed of her star, And brought in her Celestiall Carre; As well as humane Matter yields, She thus her curious Mansion builds; Yet all those fames from the divine Impression differently decline: The Sun, who's figu'rd here, his Beams Into anothers Bosom streams; In whose agreeing soul he staies, And guilds it with its virtuous Rales, The heart in which Affection's bred, Is thus by pleasing Errour fed. VII. The heart where pleasing Errour raigns, This object as her Child maintains, By the fair light that in her shines (A rare Celestiall Gift,) refines; And by degrees at last doth bring To her first splendours sacred spring, From this divine Look, one Sun passes Through three refulgent Burning-glasses, Kindling all Beauty, which the Spirit, The Body, and the Mind inherit. These rich spoiles, by th'eye first caught, Are to the Souls next Handmaid brought, Who there resides: She to the brest Sends them; reform'd, but not exprest: The heart, from Matter Beauty takes, Of many one Conception makes; And what were meant by Natures Laws, Distinct, She in one Picture draws: VIII. The heart by Love allur'd to see Within her self her Progeny; This, like the Suns reflecting Rayes Upon the Waters face, survaies; Yet some divine, though clouded light Seems here to twinckle, and invite The pious Soul, a Beauty more Sublime, and perfect to adore. Who sees no longer his dim shade Upon the earths vast Globe display'd, But certain Lustre, of the true Suns truest Image, now in view. The Soul thus entring in the Mind, There such uncertainty doth find, That she to clearer Light applies Her aimes, and near the first Sun flies: She by his splendour beautious grows, By loving whom all Beauty flows Upon the Mind, Soul, World, and All Included in this spacious Ball. IX. But hold! Love stops the forward Course That me beyond my scope would force. Great Power! if any Soul appears Who not alone the blossoms wears, But of the rich Fruit is possest, Lend him thy Light, deny the rest. THE GOLDEN VERSES OF PYTHAGORAS. First, in their ranks, th'Immortall Gods adore, Thy Oath keep; next, great Heroes; then implore Terrestriall Dæmons with due sacrifice. Thy Parents reverence and neer Allies: Him that is first in Vertue make thy Friend, And with observance his kind speech attend: Nor (to thy power) for leight faults cast him by, Thy pow'r is neighbour to Necessity. These know, and with intentive care pursue; But anger, sloath, and Luxury subdue. In sight of others or thy selfe forbear, What's ill; but of thy selfe and most in fear. Let Justice all thy words and actions sway; Nor from the even course of Reason stray: For know that all men are to dye ordain'd, And riches are as quickly lost as gain'd. Crosses that happen by divine decree, (If such thy lot) bear not impatiently. Yet seek to remedy with all thy care, And think the Just have not the greatest share. 'Mongst men, discourses good and bad are spred, Despise not those, nor be by these misled. If any some notorious falshood say, Thou the report with equall Judgement weigh. Let not mens smoother promises invite, Nor rougher threats from just resolves thee fright. If ought thou wouldst attempt, first ponder it, Fools onely inconsiderate acts commit. Nor do what afterwards, thou maist repent, First learn to know the thing on which th'art bent. Thus thou a life shalt lead with joy repleat. Nor must thou care of outward health forget. Such temp'rance use in exercise and dyet, As may preserve thee in a setled quiet. Meats unprohibited, not curious chuse, Decline what any other may accuse. The rash expence of vanity detest, And sordidnesse: A mean in all is best. Hurt not thy self: Before thou act, advise; Nor suffer sleep at night to close thine eyes, Till thrice thy acts that day thou hast ore-run, How slipt? what deeds? what duty left undone? Thus thy account summ'd up from first to last, Grieve for the ill, joy for what good hath past. These study, practise these, and these affect, To sacred virtue these thy steps direct. Eternall Nature's fountain I attest, Who the Tetractys on our soul imprest. Before thy mind thou to this study bend, Invoke the Gods to grant it a good end. These if thy labour vanquish, thou shalt then Know the connexure both of Gods and men; How every thing proceeds, or by what staid, And know (as far as fit to be survay'd) Nature alike throughout: that thou maist learn Not to hope hopelesse things, but all discern. And know those Wretches whose perverser wills Draw down upon their head spontaneous Ills; Unto the good that's nigh them deaf and blind: Some few the cure of these misfortunes find. This onely is the Fate that harms, and rolls, Through miseries successive, human souls. Within is a continuall hidden fight, Which we to shun must study, not excite. Great Jove! how little trouble should we know, If thou to all men wouldst their Genius show? But fear not thou; Men come of heav'nly race, Taught by diviner Nature what t'embrace: Which if pursu'd, thou all I nam'd shalt gain, And keep thy Soul clear from thy bodie's stain. In time of Pray'r and cleansing, meats deny'd Abstain from; thy mind's rains let reason guide: Then strip'd of flesh up to free Æther soar, A death-lesse God, Divine, mortall no more. Plato to Archytas Thee the surveyor of the Sea and Land, And the innumerous sand, A little share of these small dusty grains, Archytas now contains, Hard by the Matine shore: It nought avail'd, Since dye thou must, t'have scar'd Th'aeriall Orbs, or that thy soaring soul O're-run the wheeling Pole. ARCHYTAS answers. And so dy'd Pelop's father, at whose Feasts The gods themselves were guests; And Tithon, who Aurora entertain'd; Minos, whom Jove design'd Admission to his counsells; and again Dark Tartara detain, Panthous son, who, by his Target known, And from the shrine ta'ne down, Attested, that in Trojan Wars he breath'd, And to black death bequeath'd Nothing but skin and nerves, whom thou wilt yield In truth and nature skild. But all men to one endlesse night are led, And once death's path must tread. Some are stern Mars's Trophies; Seas become The greedy Sailor's Tomb. The fates of young and old together crowd, No head is disallow'd By mercilesse Proserpina; and me Into th'Illyrian Sea The wind, which doth Orion's Star pursue, Unruly Auster threw. But grudge not thou, kind Mariner, to spread On my unburied head And bones, some few of these loose sands; so may Fierce Eurus turn away Whatever threatens the Hesperian floods, On the Apulian woods, Securing thee from harm a swelling tyde Of wealth on every side Flow on thee by great Jove and Neptune sent. Tarentum's President If thou neglect, thou maist in future age Thy guiltlesse sons engage In this offence, perhaps fate may return What's due unto thy scorn. Vengeance may on my poor petition wait, And thee nought expiate. The stop is small, as thou sailst on, thou maist Dust thrice upon me cast.</field>
   </doc>
</add>