<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Smith, Horace, 1779-1849</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Smith, Horace, 1779-1849</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">smith horace 1779 1849</field>
      <field name="author_text">Smith, Horace, 1779-1849</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1840's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.1927.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">1846</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:467120</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">French</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Poetical Works of Horace Smith ; Now First Collected. In Two Volumes</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Poetical Works of Horace Smith ; Now First Collected. In Two Volumes</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poetical works of horace smith</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poetical works of horace smith</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Poetical Works of Horace Smith ; Now First Collected. In Two Volumes</field>
      <field name="year_display">1846</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1846</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1846</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467120&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467120&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Smith, Horace, 1779-1849&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;smith horace 1779 1849&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Poetical Works of Horace Smith ; Now First Collected. In Two Volumes&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poetical works of horace smith&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1846&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1846&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Smith, Horace&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1779&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1849&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Poetical Works of Horace Smith&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Now First Collected. In Two Volumes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Henry Colburn&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1846&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp3626&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;fre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;2 v.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Poetical Works of Horace Smith&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Now First Collected. In Two Volumes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 488 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">VOL. I. MISCELLANEOUS POEMS. PREFATORY STANZAS. Talk not to me of Necromantic wights, And dread magicians, Who, by their potent spells, could conjure sprites, Ghosts, apparitions, And raise the dead from the forgotten past, Each in the perfect mould of pre-existence cast. I, though no conjuror, have far outdone Such Archimages, For, as I culled and ponder'd, one by one, These scattered pages, From the dark past, and memory's eclipse, Up rose in vision clear my life's Apocalypse. Mutely each re-creative lay outpour'd Its own revealings; Youth, manhood, age, were momently restored, With all their feelings. Friends long deceased were summoned from the tomb; Forgotten scenes regain'd their vividness and bloom. Again did I recline in copses green, Gazing from under Some oak's thwart boughs upon the sky serene, In reverent wonder; Or starting from the sward with ear acute, To hear the cuckoo sound its soft two-noted flute. Association! thy transcendant power What art can rival? Muse-haunted strolls by river, field, or bower, At thy revival, Return once more, and in their second birth Bring back each former scent and sound of air and earth. In social joys where song and music's zest Made beauty fairer, In festive scenes with all their mirth and jest, Once more a sharer, I see the smiles, and hear the laughter loud Of many a friend, alas! now mouldering in his shroud. So, when the hands are dust that now entwine These prompting pages, Some future reader, as a jest or line His thought engages, Feeling old memories from their grave arise, May thus, in pensive mood, perchance soliloquise: “I knew the bardling; 'twas his nature's bent, His creed's chief feature, To hold that a benign Creator meant To bless the creature, And giving man a boon denied to brute, Loved him to exercise his laughing attribute. “He felt that cheerfulness, when unalloy'd With aught immoral, Was piety, on earth, in heaven enjoy'd; And wished his laurel To be a Misletoe, whose grace should make The mirth-devoted year one hallowed Christmas wake. “In mystic transcendental clouds to soar Was not his mission, Yet could he mould at times the solid ore Of admonition; Offenceless, grave, or gay, at least that praise May grace his name, and speed his unpretending lays.” If such thy welcome, little Book! discard Fears of thine ordeal; Go forth, and tell thy readers that the Bard, With fervent, cordial Feelings of gratitude and hope combined, Bids them all hail, and wafts them ev'ry feeling kind. HYMN TO THE FLOWERS. Day-stars! that ope your frownless eyes to twinkle From rainbow galaxies of Earth's creation, And dew-drops on her lonely altars sprinkle As a libation. Ye matin worshippers! who bending lowly Before the uprisen Sun, God's lidless eye, Throw from your chalices a sweet and holy Incense on high. Ye bright Mosaics! that with storied beauty, The floor of Nature's temple tesselate, What numerous emblems of instructive duty Your forms create! 'Neath cloistered boughs, each floral bell that swingeth And tolls its perfume on the passing air, Makes sabbath in the fields, and ever ringeth A call to prayer. Not to the domes where crumbling arch and column Attest the feebleness of mortal hand, But to that fane, most Catholic and solemn, Which God hath planned; To that cathedral, boundless as our wonder, Whose quenchless lamps the sun and moon supply; Its choir the winds and waves,—its organ thunder,— Its dome the sky. There, as in solitude and shade I wander Through the green aisles, or stretched upon the sod, Awed by the silence, reverently ponder The ways of God, Your voiceless lips, O Flowers! are living preachers, Each cup a pulpit, every leaf a book, Supplying to my fancy numerous teachers From loneliest nook. Floral Apostles! that in dewy splendour “Weep without woe, and blush without a crime,” O may I deeply learn, and ne'er surrender Your lore sublime! “Thou wert not, Solomon! in all thy glory, Arrayed,” the lilies cry—“in robes like ours; How vain your grandeur! ah, how transitory Are human flowers!” In the sweet-scented pictures, heavenly artist! With which thou paintest nature's wide-spread hall, What a delightful lesson thou impartest Of love to all! Not useless are ye, Flowers! though made for pleasure: Blooming o'er field and wave, by day and night, From every source your sanction bids me treasure Harmless delight. Ephemeral sages! what instructors hoary For such a world of thought could furnish scope? Each fading calyx a memento mori, Yet fount of hope. Posthumous glories! angel-like collection! Upraised from seed or bulb interred in earth, Ye are to me a type of resurrection, And second birth. Were I in churchless solitudes remaining, Far from all voice of teachers and divines, My soul would find, in flowers of God's ordaining, Priests, sermons, shrines! ADDRESS TO A MUMMY. And hast thou walk'd about, (how strange a story!) In Thebes's streets three thousand years ago, When the Memnonium was in all its glory, And time had not begun to overthrow Those temples, palaces, and piles stupendous, Of which the very ruins are tremendous. Speak! for thou long enough hast acted Dummy. Thou hast a tongue—come—let us hear its tune; Thou'rt standing on thy legs, above-ground, Mummy! Revisiting the glimpses of the moon, Not like thin ghosts or disembodied creatures, But with thy bones and flesh, and limbs and features. Tell us—for doubtless thou canst recollect, To whom should we assign the Sphinx's fame? Was Cheops or Cephrenes architect Of either pyramid that bears his name? Is Pompey's Pillar really a misnomer? Had Thebes a hundred gates, as sung by Homer? Perhaps thou wert a Mason, and forbidden By oath to tell the secrets of thy trade,— Then say what secret melody was hidden In Memnon's statue which at sunrise play'd? Perhaps thou wert a Priest—if so, my struggles Are vain, for priestcraft never owns its juggles. Perchance that very hand, now pinion'd flat, Has hob-a-nob'd with Pharaoh, glass to glass; Or dropp'd a halfpenny in Homer's hat, Or doff'd thine own to let Queen Dido pass; Or held, by Solomon's own invitation, A torch at the great Temple's dedication. I need not ask thee if that hand, when arm'd, Has any Roman soldier maul'd and knuckled, For thou wert dead, and buried, and embalm'd, Ere Romulus and Remus had been suckled: Antiquity appears to have begun Long after thy primeval race was run. Thou couldst develop, if that wither'd tongue Might tell us what those sightless orbs have seen, How the world look'd when it was fresh and young, And the great Deluge still had left it green— Or was it then so old, that History's pages Contain'd no record of its early ages? Still silent! incommunicative elf! Art sworn to secrecy? then keep thy vows; But prythee tell us something of thyself— Reveal the secrets of thy prison-house; Since in the world of spirits thou hast slumber'd, What hast thou seen—what strange adventures number'd? Since first thy form was in this box extended, We have, above-ground, seen some strange mutations. The Roman empire has begun and ended, New worlds have risen—we have lost old nations, And countless Kings have into dust been humbled, While not a fragment of thy flesh has crumbled. Didst thou not hear the pother o'er thy head, When the great Persian conqueror, Cambyses, March'd armies o'er thy tomb with thundering tread, O'erthrew Osiris, Orus, Apis, Isis, And shook the Pyramids with fear and wonder, When the gigantic Memnon fell asunder? If the tomb's secrets may not be confess'd, The nature of thy private life unfold:— A heart has throbb'd beneath that leathern breast, And tears adown that dusty cheek have roll'd:— Have children climb'd those knees, and kissed that face? What was thy name and station, age and race? Statue of flesh—Immortal of the dead! Imperishable type of evanescence! Posthumous man, who quitt'st thy narrow bed, And standest undecay'd within our presence, Thou wilt hear nothing till the Judgment morning, When the great Trump shall thrill thee with its warning. Why should this worthless tegument endure, If its undying guest be lost for ever? Oh! let us keep the soul embalm'd and pure In living virtue, that when both must sever, Although corruption may our frame consume, Th' immortal spirit in the skies may bloom!— ADDRESS TO THE ORANGE-TREE AT VERSAILLES, Called the Great Bourbon, which is above four hundred years old. When France with civil wars was torn, And heads, as well as crowns were shorn From royal shoulders, One Bourbon, in unalter'd plight, Hath still maintain'd its regal right, And held its court—a goodly sight To all beholders. Thou, leafy monarch, thou alone, Hast sat uninjured on thy throne, Seeing the war range; And when the great Nassaus were sent Crownless away, (a sad event!) Thou didst uphold and represent The House of Orange. To tell what changes thou hast seen, Each grand monarque, and king and queen, Of French extraction, Might puzzle those who don't conceive French history, so I believe Comparing thee with ours will give More satisfaction. Westminster Hall Rebuilt 1399., whose oaken roof The papers say, (but that's no proof,) Is nearly rotten, Existed but in stones and trees, When thou wert waving in the breeze, And blossoms, (what a treat for bees!) By scores hadst gotten. Chaucer, so old a bard that time Has antiquated every chime, And from his tomb outworn each rhyme Within the Abbey; And Gower, and older poet whom The Borough Church enshrines (his tomb, Though once restored, has lost its bloom, And got quite shabby,) Lived in thy time—the first perchance Was beating monks There is a tradition (though not authenticated) that Chaucer was fined for beating a monk in Fleet-street. when thou in France By monks wert beaten, Who shook beneath this very tree Their reverend beards, with glutton glee, As each down-falling luxury Was caught and eaten. Perchance when Henry gain'd the fight Of Agincourt, some Gaulish knight, (His bleeding steed in woful plight, With smoking haunches,) Laid down his helmet at thy root, And, as he pluck'd the grateful fruit, Suffered his poor exhausted brute To crop thy branches. Thou wert of portly size and look, When first the Turks besieged and took Constantinople; And eagles in thy boughs might perch, When, leaving Bullen in the lurch, Another Henry changed his church, And used the Pope ill. What numerous namesakes hast thou seen Lounging beneath thy shady green, With monks as lazy; Louis Quatorze has pressed that ground, With his six mistresses around— A sample of the old and sound Legitimacy. And when despotic freaks and vices Brought on th' inevitable crisis Of revolution, Thou heard'st the mob's infuriate shriek, Who came their victim Queen to seek, On guiltless heads the wrath to wreak Of retribution. Oh! of what follies, vice, and crime, Hast thou, in thine eventful time, Been made beholder! What wars, what feuds—the thoughts appal! Each against each, and all with all, Till races upon races fall, In earth to moulder. Whilst thou, serene, unalter'd, calm, (Such are the constant gifts and balm Bestow'd by Nature!) Hast year by year renew'd thy flowers, And perfumed the surrounding bowers, And poured down grateful fruit by showers, And proffer'd shade in summer hours To man and creature. Thou green and venerable tree! Whate'er the future doom may be, By fortune given, Remember that a rhymester brought From foreign shores thine umbrage sought, Recall'd the blessings thou hadst wrought, And, as he thank'd thee, raised his thought To heaven! SICILIAN ARETHUSA. Sicilian Arethusa! thou, whose arms Of azure round the Thymbrian meadows wind, Still are thy margins lined With the same flowers Proserpina was weaving In Enna's field, beside Pergusa's lake, When swarthy Dis, upheaving, Saw her, and, stung to madness by her charms, Down snatch'd her, shrieking, to his Stygian couch. Thy waves, Sicilian Arethusa, flow In cadence to the shepherd's flageolet As tunefully as when they wont to crouch Beneath the banks to catch the pipings low Of old Theocritus, and hear him trill Bucolic songs, and Amoebæan lays. And still, Sicilian Arethusa, still, Though Etna dry thee up, or frosts enchain, Thy music shall be heard, for poets high Have dipp'd their wreaths in thee, and by their praise Made thee immortal as themselves. Thy flowers, Transplanted, an eternal bloom retain, Rooted in words that cannot fade or die. Thy liquid gush and guggling melody Have left undying echoes in the bowers Of tuneful poesy. Thy very name, Sicilian Arethusa, had been drown'd In deep oblivion, but that the buoyant breath Of bards uplifted it, and bade it swim Adown th' eternal lapse, assured of fame, Till all things shall be swallow'd up in death.— Where, Immortality! where canst thou found Thy throne unperishing, but in the hymn Of the true bard, whose breath encrusts his theme Like to a petrifaction, which the stream Of time will only make more durable? THE SHRIEK OF PROMETHEUS. Suggested by a passage in the second Book of Apollonius Rhodius. Fresh was the breeze, and the rowers plied Their oars with simultaneous motion, When the Argo sail'd in her stately pride By the laurel'd shores of the Pontic Ocean. The island of Mars with its palmy coves, The sacred Mount, and Aretia's strands, And Philyra's Isle with its linden groves, And Ophir's flood with its shelly sands,— Swiftly they passed—till, stretching far, On their right Bechiria's coast appears, Where painted Sapirians, fierce in war, Bristle the beach with bows and spears. At distance they saw the sun-beams quiver Where the long-sought towers of Colchis stood, And mark'd the foam of the Phasis river, As it flung from its rocky mouth the flood. The Argonauts gaze with hungry eyes On the land enrich'd by the Golden Fleece,— Already in fancy they grasp the prize, And hear the shouts of applauding Greece. Jason looked out with a proud delight, Castor and Pollux stood hand in hand, Showing each other the welcome sight; While fierce Meleager unsheath'd his brand. Laocoon bade the rowers check Their oars, as the sun to the water slanted, For Orpheus sate with his harp on the deck, And sweetly the hymn of evening chanted, While the heroes around, at each pause of sound, Stretched their right hands to the god of day, And fervently joined in the choral lay. The Hymn of Orpheus. Twin-born with Dian in the Delos isle, Which after the Ogygian deluge thou Didst first illume with renovating smile, Apollo! deign to hear our evening vow. Chorus. When thou'rt dim, our harp and hymn Thy downward course shall follow: Hail to thee!—hail to thee! Hail to thee, Apollo! God of the art that heals the shatter'd frame, And poetry that soothes the wounded mind, Ten thousand temples, honour'd with thy name, Attest thy ceaseless blessings to mankind. Chorus. When thou'rt dim, our harp and hymn Thy downward course shall follow, Hail to thee!—hail to thee! Hail to thee, Apollo! Thy golden bow emits a gushing strain Of music when the Pythian serpent dies: His eyes flash fire—his writhings plough the plain: Hissing he leaps aloft—then lifeless lies. Chorus. When thou'rt dim, our harp and hymn Thy downward course shall follow, Hail to thee!—hail to thee! Hail to thee, Apollo! Pan of his pipe and rural science proud, Dreamt that his music might with thine aspire; The mountain Tmolus was the judge—and bow'd His nodding woods in homage to thy lyre. Chorus. When thou'rt dim, with harp and hymn Thy downward course we follow. Hail to thee! hail to thee! Hail to thee, Apollo! From bowers of Daphne or Parnassus' Mount, While Delphic girls their Io Pæans sing, The gifted Muses by Castalia's Fount With choral symphonies salute their king. Chorus. When thou'rt dim, with harp and hymn Thy downward course we follow. Hail to thee! hail to thee! Hail to thee, Apollo! God of the golden lyre and laurel wreath, To thee each poet turns with yearning heart And thoughtful eyes, invoking thee to breathe Thine inspiration— With a start The minstrel ceased,—for over all the bark A baleful shadow on a sudden spread! The Argonauts look'd up, and saw a dark And monstrous eagle hovering o'er their head; So vast and fearful, that transfix'd and pale They stood, with wild amaze o'ertaken:— The vessel trembles, and the shivering sail Flaps as if with terror shaken. Entranced they gazed—and silent till Philas, the son of Bacchus seized his bow, And would have aim'd it at the feather'd foe, But Mopsus, gifted with an augur's skill, Gently held back his arm, and bade him wait This dread portent—pronounce no word, Nor dare to challenge Jove's own bird, The minister of unrelenting fate. Extending now his oar-like wings, Twice round the ship the monster swings, As if prepared to pounce upon his prey; His eyes from forth their sable shroud Shot fire, like lightning from a cloud; But with a sudden dart he rush'd away, And clove the northward distance, where The heights of Caucasus their barrier throw, Where crag on crag, chaotic giants bare Their granite foreheads to the sky, and sit In desolate state beneath their crowns of snow. Within these topmost peaks, there is a pit,— A dizzy, gaunt, precipitous ravine, Upon whose rocky floor environ'd round With walls of ice—by every eye unseen, With adamantine chains Prometheus lies bound. Thither the ravenous wonder wing'd his flight, They saw him clear the intervening height, And sink behind it:—every eye Is fix'd upon the spot, and every heart Throbs with expectant agony,— But nought is seen—no sounds impart The secret of that dread abyss:— Still do they gaze, half-willing to dismiss Their fears and hopes, for over plain and hill, And smiling ocean—all is hush'd and still. Gracious God, what a shriek! The monster with his beak Is tearing out his victim's heart! Lo! as that desolating cry Echoes from the mountains high, And throws its fear afar, a start Of horror seems to darken nature's face.— Athwart the quaking deep, Revolting shudders creep, Earth trembles to her very base— Air seems to swoon—the sky to frown— The sun with ghastly glare shrinks faster down.— Hark! what a furious clash of chains! Victim! thou never canst unlock The brazen bolts that root thee to the rock; Vain are thy struggles and convulsive strains. Ah me! what dreadful groans are those Wrung from the very depths of agonies;— Now weaker moanings rise, till, worn with woes, The fainting wretch exhausted lies, And all again is grim repose. But still with throbbing breasts and steadfast eyes The heroes gazed upon the mountain's peak, Till gorged with gore they saw the monster rise With blood-stain'd claws, and breast, and beak: And as above them he resumed his flight, Th'arrested vessel shakes, The flapping main-sail quakes, And all seem'd turned to statues at the sight, All but the son of Bacchus, who With flashing eyes and visage red, Again uprear'd his bow and drew His longest arrow to the head.— When from the eagle's beak a drop of gore, (The heart's blood of Prometheus) fell Warm on his hand! upon the vessel's floor Down fell his bow;—with shuddering yell, And haggard eyes still staring on the drop, He staggers back, clasping the mast to prop His fainting limbs. Upon the pilot's forehead The dews of terror stood, And all in awe-struck mood Ponder'd in silence on that omen horrid. The sun went down, and far into the gloom The monster shot away,—but none Of the bewilder'd Argonauts resume The vessel's guidance as her way she won.— None spake—none moved—all sate in blank dismay, Revolving in their minds this dread portent; And thus, abandon'd to the sway Of the blind wind and watery element, Through the whole night the Argo bore Those throbbing hearts along the Pontic shore. THE BIRTH OF THE INVISIBLE. O scene of enchantment! O vision of bliss! What Paradisaical glory is this! A garden! a garden! O rapturous sight! More stately in beauty, more rich in delight, Than any the Muse, in her leafiest hour, Has fabled of golden Hesperian bower, Or Fortunate Islands, or fields where the blest In Elysium's sylvan beatitudes rest. Lovely or rare, none can compare With this heaven on earth so surpassingly fair! Well, well may its flow'rets thus brightly expand, For they feel the fresh touch of the Deity's hand; And the trees that are rustling their branches on high, Are raising their arms and their voice to the sky, To give thanks to the Lord, at whose fiat sublime They sprung from the earth in maturity's prime; And the newly-born river that flows at their feet, Is lisping an anthem its Maker to greet. Lovely or rare, none can compare With this heaven on earth so surpassingly fair! What odorous incense upsprings from the sod, Which has lately been press'd by the foot of its God! What fragrance Sabæan the zephyrs exhale, Where celestial breath has been left on the gale! Behold! how the fruits deeply blush, where the sun Has stamp'd his first kiss upon every one! And hark! how the birds in sweet choral accord, Send their voices' first offerings up to the Lord! Lovely or rare, none can compare With this heaven on earth so surpassingly fair! No solace is wanting, no charms that dispense A rival delight to the soul and the sense; It is blissful to quaff the nectareous air; To pluck from the branches ambrosial fare; To list to the music of birds and of trees, The chiming of waters, the song of the breeze; To gaze on the Paradise blooming around, And scent the rich breath of its flowery ground. Lovely or rare, none can compare With this heaven on earth so surpassingly fair! The creatures now savage, not then beasts of prey, 'Mid the flocks and the herds fondly pasture and play: The lion lies down with the kidling; the lamb Disports with the tiger; the wolf with its dam; The elephant, twining his trunk round the boughs Of the palm, scatters dates for his friends to carouse; The giraffe plucks the high-growing fruits; and each beast Makes the banquet of Nature a fellowship feast. Lovely or rare, none can compare With this heaven on earth so surpassingly fair! 'Tis the garden of Eden, where joy, peace, and love, Join the creatures below to their Maker above. Behold! from yon verdant alcove, hand in hand, Wander Adam and Eve, till admiring they stand Beneath the resplendent pre-eminent tree Of knowledge, whose fruit is forbidden. And see! In the guise of a serpent, where Satan appears, And whispers melodious guilt in their ears. Lovely or rare, none can compare With this heaven on earth so surpassingly fair! O horror of horrors! the dark deed is done: They have tasted the fruit. Lo! the shuddering sun Rushes out of the sky; all is terror and gloom. The tears of the angels bewailing man's doom, Rain woe upon earth; the wild animals roar, As their fangs, stainless once, are polluted with gore; Flocks and herds fly before them, astounded, aghast; Shrieks of anguish are borne on the terrible blast. Fear and despair are on earth and in air, For thunder has ravaged that garden so fair. Degraded, ashamed, sinful Adam and Eve From its precincts are driven to toil and to grieve; Then earth gave a groan, a soul-harrowing sound, And thrill'd in her depths with a shudder profound, That wither'd each Paradise tree to its root, And shook down for ever and ever its fruit, And scatter'd the rivers,—till all was o'erthrown, That the site of the garden might never be known. And Record is all that is left, since the fall, Its exquisite beauties and bliss to recall. Then, then in the desert's profoundest abyss, Where the winds o'er the waste fiercely whistle and hiss, In the blackness of night, with convulsions and throes, Did Earth her sepulchral recesses unclose, And heave up a monster, the world to affright, Terrific of purpose, tremendous in might, Though his features to none might he ever reveal. Gladness and mirth fled from the earth, When that fearful invisible monster had birth. The hopes and the courage of Adam to daunt, It ceased not, the spectre, his footsteps to haunt; His children it touch'd, and converted to dust In a moment his tenderest objects of trust; Birds and beasts fell around him; where'er Adam walk'd, Before him, in fancy, the murderer stalk'd; More dread to the heart when unseen by the eye, 'Twas vain from the phantom to hide or to fly; Wrinkles and bloom met the same doom,— One touch of the Gorgon sent all to the tomb. It lurk'd in the wave, in the air, in the bower,— An ubiquitous curse, an all-withering power,— Still snatching from Adam his hope and his joy, And scaring with dread when it fail'd to destroy; Till weaken'd with age, worn with sorrow and fear, He felt a cold hand on his heart, and his ear Was chill'd by the spectre's cadaverous breath, As in accents sepulchral it groan'd—I am Death!” THE SANCTUARY. In Israel was many a refuge city, Whereto the blameless homicide might flee, And claim protection, sustenance, and pity, Safe from the blood-avenger's enmity, Until the law's acquittal sent him thence, Free from offence. Round old cathedral, abbey-church, and palace, Did we ourselves a sanctuary draw, Where no stern creditor could glut his malice, And even criminals might brave the law; For judge nor justice in that charter'd verge Their rights could urge. These times are gone; felons and knavish debtors May mourn the change, but who bewails their case? For why should God and King be made abettors Of guilt and fraud, the champions of the base? Never may such a desecration stain Our land again! But all are not divested of their charter; One refuge still is left for human woes. Victim of care! or persecution's martyr! Who seek'st a sure asylum from thy foes, Learn that the holiest, safest, purest, best, Is man's own breast! There is a solemn sanctuary founded By God himself; not for transgressors meant; But that the man opprest, the spirit-wounded, And all beneath the world's injustice bent, Might turn from outward wrong, turmoil, and din, To peace within. Each bosom is a temple; when its altar, The living heart, is unprofaned and pure, Its verge is hallow'd; none need fear or falter Who thither fly; it is an ark secure, Winning, above a world o'erwhelm'd with wrath, Its peaceful path. O Bower of Bliss! O Sanctuary holy! Terrestrial antepast of heavenly joy! Never! oh, never may misdeed or folly My claim to thy beatitudes destroy! Still may I keep this Paradise unlost, Where'er I'm tost. E'en in the flesh, the spirit disembodied, Uncheck'd by time and space, may soar elate, In silent awe to commune with the Godhead,— Or the millennium reign anticipate, When earth shall be all sanctity and love, Like heaven above. How sweet to turn from anguish, guilt, and madness, From scenes where strife and tumult never cease, To that Elysian world of bosom'd gladness, Where all is silence, charity, and peace; And shelter'd from the storm the soul may rest On its own nest! When, spleenful as the sensitive Mimosa, We shrink from winter's touch and Nature's gloom, There may we conjure up a Vallombrosa, Where groves and bowers in summer beauty bloom, And the heart dances in the sunny glade Fancy has made. But, would we dedicate to nobler uses, This bosom sanctuary, let us there Hallow our hearts from all the world's abuses; While high and charitable thoughts and pray'r, May teach us gratitude to God, combined With love of kind. Reader! this is no lay unfelt and hollow, But prompted by the happy, grateful heart Of one who, having humbly tried to follow The path he counsels, would to thee impart The love and holy quiet which have blest His own calm breast. THE POPPY. The man who roams by wild-flower'd ditch or hedge Skirting the mead, Or treads the cornfield path—along its edge, May mark a weed, Whose ragged scarlet gear might well denote A road-side beggar in a soldier's coat. Hence! terms misplaced, and thoughts disparaging! O Poppy Flower! Thou art the Crœsus of the field—its king— A mystic power, With emblems deep and secret blessings fraught, And potent properties that baffle thought. When thy hues catch, amid the growing corn? The traveller's eye, “Weeds! weeds!” he cries, and shakes his head in scorn: But when on high The grain uplifts its harvest-bearing crest, The Poppy's hidden, and the taunt suppress'd. So, when our early state is poor and mean, Our portion small, Our scarlet-blushing moral weeds are seen, And blamed by all; But as we rise in rank we win repute, Our faults gold-hidden, our accusers mute. Why does the Poppy with its chaliced store Of opiate rare, The opium is principally extracted from the white poppy. Flush in the fields, and grace the hovel door, But to declare That, from the City's palaces forlorn, Sleep flies to bless the cottage in the corn? And Oh! how precious is the Anodyne Its cells exude, Charming the mind's disquietude malign To peaceful mood, Soothing the body's anguish with its balm, Lulling the restless into slumbers calm. What tho' the reckless suicide—oppress'd By fell despair, Turns to a poison-cup thy chalice, bless'd With gifts so rare; And basely flying, while the brave remain, Deserts the post God gave him to maintain. Such art perverted does but more enhance That higher power, Which, planting by the corn—(man's sustenance,) The Poppy flower, Both in one soil, one atmosphere their breath, Rears, side by side, the means of life and death! Who, who can mark thee, Poppy, when the air Fans thy lips bright, Nor move his own in sympathetic prayer To Him whose might Combined the powers—O thought-bewildering deed! Of death—sleep—health—oblivion—in a weed! THE MURDERER'S CONFESSION. I paused not to question the Devil's suggestion, But o'er the cliff, headlong, the living was thrown; A scream and a plashing, a foam and a flashing, And the smothering water accomplish'd his slaughter, All was silent, and I was alone! With heart-thrilling spasm I leant o'er the chasm; There was blood on the wave that closed o'er his head, And in bubbles his breath, as he struggled with death, Rose up to the surface. I shudder'd and fled. With footsteps that stagger'd and countenance haggard, I stole to my dwelling, bewilder'd, dismay'd, Till whisperings stealthy said—“Psha! he was wealthy, Thou'rt his heir—no one saw thee—then be not afraid.” I summon'd the neighbours, I join'd in their labours, We sought for the missing by day and by night; We ransack'd each single height, hollow, or dingle, Till shoreward we wended, when starkly extended, His corpse lay before us—Oh God! what a sight! And yet was there nothing for terror or loathing. The blood had been wash'd from his face and his clothing, But by no language, no pen, his life-like wide open Eyes can be painted;— They stared at me, flared at me, angrily glared at me, I felt murder-attainted; Yet my guilty commotion seem'd truth and devotion, When I shudder'd and fainted. No hint finds emission that breathes of suspicion, None dare utter a sound when an inquest has found His death accidental; Whence then and wherefore, having nothing to care for, These agonies mental? Why grieve and why sicken, frame-wither'd, soul-stricken? Age-paralysed, sickly, he must have died quickly, Each day brought some new ill; Why leave him to languish and struggle with anguish, The deed that relieved him from all that aggrieved him, Was kindly, not cruel. In procession extended a funeral splendid, With banner'd displays and escutcheons emblazon'd, To church slowly pass'd, When a dread apparition astounded my vision; Like an aspen leaf shaking, dumfounded and quaking, I stood all aghast! From its nail'd coffin prison the corpse had arisen, And in all its shroud vesture, with menacing gesture, And eye-balls that stared at me, flared at me, glared at me, It pointed—it flouted its slayer, and shouted In accents that thrill'd me, “That ruthless dissembler, that guilt-stricken trembler, Is the villain who kill'd me!” 'Twas fancy's creation—mere hallucination— A lucky delusion, for again my confusion, Guilt's evidence sinister, seem'd to people and minister The painful achievement of grief and bereavement. Then why these probations, these self-condemnations Incessant and fearful? Some with impunity snatch opportunity, Slay—and exult in concealment's immunity; Free from forebodings and heartfelt corrodings, They fear no disclosure, no public exposure, And sleeping unhaunted, and waking undaunted, Live happy and cheerful. To 'scape the ideal let me dwell on the real, I, a pauper so lately, In abundance possessing life's every blessing, Fine steeds in my stable, rare wines on my table, Servants dress'd gaily, choice banquets daily, A wife fond and beautiful, children most dutiful, I, a pauper so lately, live rich and greatly, In a mansion-house stately. Life's blessings? O liar! all are curses most dire, In the midst of my revels, His eyes ever stare at me, flare at me, glare at me, Before me when treading my manors outspreading, There yawns an abysmal cliff precipice dismal. Isolation has vanish'd, all silence is banish'd, Where'er I immew me his death shrieks pursue me, I am hunted by devils. My wine clear and ruddy seems turbid and bloody, I cannot quaff water:—recalling his slaughter, My terror it doubles—'tis beaded with bubbles, Each fill'd with his breath, And in every glass each hisses—“Assassin! My curse shall affright thee, haunt, harrow, and blight thee In life and in death!” My daughters, their mother, contend with each other Who shall show most affection, best soothe my dejection: Revolting endearments! their garments seem cerements, And I shudder with loathing at their grave-tainted clothing. Home and the mercies That to others are dearest, to me are the drearest And deadliest curses. When free from this error I thrill with the terror, (Thought horrid to dwell on!) That the wretch whom they cherish may shamefully perish, Be publicly gibbetted, branded, exhibited, As a murderous felon! O punishment hellish! the house I embellish From centre to corner upbraids its adorner,— A door's lowest creaking swells into a shrieking, Against me each column bears evidence solemn, Each statue's a Nemesis. They follow, infest me, they strive to arrest me, Till in terrified sadness that verges on madness, I rush from the premises. The country's amenity brings no serenity. Each rural sound seeming a menace or screaming, There is not a bird or beast but cries—“Murder! There goes the offender! Dog him, waylay him, encompass him, stay him, And make him surrender!” My flower-beds splendid seem eyes blood-distended, His eyes, ever flaring, and staring, and glaring! I turn from them quickly, but phantoms more sickly Drive me hither and thither. I would forfeit most gladly wealth stolen so madly, Quitting grandeur and revelry to fly from this devilry, But whither—O whither? Hence idle delusions! hence fears and confusions! Not a single friend's severance lessens men's reverence, No neighbour of rank quits my sumptuous banquets Without lauding their donor; Throughout the wide county I'm famed for my bounty, All hold me in honour. Let the dotard and craven by fear be enslaven. They have vanish'd! How fast fly these images ghastly, When in firm self-reliance, You determine on treating the brain's sickly cheating, With scorn and defiance! Ha ha! I am fearless henceforward and tearless, No coinage of fancy, no dream's necromancy Shall sadden and darken—God help me!—hist—harken! 'Tis the shriek soul-appalling he utter'd when falling! By day thus affrighted, 'tis worse when benighted; With the clock's midnight boom, from the church on his tomb, There comes a sharp screaming too fearful for dreaming; Bone fingers unholy draw the foot curtains slowly, O God! how they stare at me, flare at me, glare at me, Those eyes of a Gorgon! Beneath the clothes sinking with shuddering shrinking, A mental orgasm and bodily spasm Convulse every organ. Nerves a thousand times stronger could bear it no longer. Grief, sickness, compunction, dismay in conjunction, Nights and days ghost-prolific, more grim and terrific Than judges and juries, Make the heart writhe and falter more than gibbet and halter. Arrest me, secure me, seize, handcuff, immure me! I own my transgression—will make full confession, Quick—quick! Let me plunge in some dark-vaulted dungeon, Where, tho' tried and death-fated, I may not be baited By devils and furies! THE CONTRAST. [Written under Windsor Terrace, the day after the Funeral of George the Third.] I saw him last on this Terrace proud, Walking in health and gladness, Begirt with his Court; and in all the crowd Not a single look of sadness. Bright was the sun, and the leaves were green, Blithely the birds were singing, The cymbal replied to the tambourine, And the bells were merrily ringing. I have stood with the crowd beside his bier, When not a word was spoken; But every eye was dim with a tear, And the silence by sobs was broken. I have heard the earth on his coffin pour To the muffled drum's deep rolling, While the minute-gun with its solemn roar, Drown'd the death-bell's tolling. The time since he walk'd in his glory thus, To the grave till I saw him carried, Was an age of the mightiest change to us, But to him a night unvaried. We have fought the fight;—from his lofty throne The foe of our land we have tumbled; And it gladden'd each eye, save his alone, For whom that foe we humbled. A daughter belov'd—a Queen—a son— And a son's sole child have perish'd; And sad was each heart, save the only one By which they were fondest cherish'd. For his eyes were seal'd, and his mind was dark, And he sat in his age's lateness, Like a vision throned, as a solemn mark Of the frailty of human greatness. His silver beard o'er a bosom spread, Unvex'd by life's commotion, Like a yearly-lengthening snow-drift shed On the calm of a frozen ocean. O'er him oblivion's waters boom'd, As the stream of time kept flowing; And we only heard of our King when doom'd To know that his strength was going. At intervals thus the waves disgorge, By weakness rent asunder, A part of the wreck of the Royal George, For the people's pity and wonder. THE BARD'S SONG TO HIS DAUGHTER. O Daughter dear, my darling child, Prop of my mortal pilgrimage, Thou who hast care and pain beguiled, And wreathed with Spring my wintry age,— Through thee a second prospect opes Of life, when but to live is glee, And jocund joys, and youthful hopes, Come thronging to my heart through thee. Backward thou lead'st me to the bowers Where love and youth their transports gave; While forward still thou strewest flowers, And bidst me live beyond the grave. For still my blood in thee shall flow, Perhaps to warm a distant line, Thy face my lineaments shall show, And e'en my thoughts survive in thine. Yes, Daughter, when this tongue is mute— This heart is dust—these eyes are closed, And thou art singing to thy lute Some stanza by thy sire composed, To friends around thou mayst impart A thought of him who wrote the lays, And from the grave my form shall start, Embodied forth to fancy's gaze. Then to their memories will throng Scenes shared with him who lies in earth, The cheerful page, the lively song, The woodland walk, or festive mirth; Then may they heave the pensive sigh That friendship seeks not to control, And from the fix'd and thoughtful eye The half unconscious tears may roll:— Such now bedew my cheek—but mine Are drops of gratitude and love, That mingle human with divine— The gift below, its source above.— How exquisitely dear thou art Can only be by tears express'd, And the fond thrillings of my heart While thus I clasp thee to my breast. THE FLOWER THAT FEELS NOT SPRING. From the prisons dark of the circling bark The leaves of tenderest green are glancing; They gambol on high in the bright blue sky, Fondly with spring's young Zephyrs dancing, While music and joy and jubilee gush From the lark and linnet, the blackbird and thrush. The butterfly springs on its new-born wings, The dormouse starts from his wintry sleeping; The flowers of earth find a second birth, To light and life from the darkness leaping: The roses and tulips will soon resume Their youth's first perfume and primitive bloom. What renders me sad when all nature glad The heart of each living creature cheers? I laid in the bosom of earth a blossom, And water'd its bed with a father's tears; But the grave has no spring, and I still deplore That the flow'ret I planted comes up no more! That eye, whose soft blue of the firmament's hue, Express'd all holy and heavenly things,— Those ringlets bright, which scatter'd a light Such as angels shake from their sunny wings,— That cheek, in whose freshness my heart had trust— All—all have perish'd—my daughter is dust! Yet the blaze sublime of thy virtue's prime, Still gilds my tears and a balm supplies, As the matin ray of the god of day Brightens the dew which at last it dries: Yes, Fanny! I cannot regret thy clay, When I think where thy spirit has wing'd its way. So wither we all—so flourish and fall, Like the flowers and weeds that in churchyards wave; Our leaves we spread over comrades dead, And blossom and bloom with our root in the grave;— Springing from earth, into earth we are thrust, Ashes to ashes and dust to dust! If death's worst smart is to feel that we part From those we love and shall see no more, It softens its sting to know that we wing Our flight to the friends who have gone before; And the grave is a boon and a blessing to me, If it waft me, O Fanny, my daughter, to thee! MORAL RUINS. Asia's rock-hollow'd Fanes, first-born of Time, In sculpture's prime, Wrought by the ceaseless toil of many a race, Whom none may trace, Have crumbled back to wastes of ragged stone, And formless caverns, desolate and lone;— Egypt's stern Temples, whose colossal mound, Sphinx-guarded, frown'd From brows of Granite challenges to Fate, And human hate, Are giant ruins in a desert land, Or sunk to sculptured quarries in the sand. The marble miracles of Greece and Rome, Temple and Dome, Art's masterpieces, awful in th' excess Of loveliness, Hallow'd by statued Gods which might be thought To be themselves by the Celestials wrought,— Where are they now?—their majesty august Grovels in dust. Time on their altars prone their ruins flings As offerings, Forming a lair whence ominous bird and brute Their wailful Misereres howl and hoot. Down from its height the Druid's sacred stone In sport is thrown, And many a Christian Fane have change and hate Made desolate, Prostrating saint, apostle, statue, bust, With Pagan deities to mingle dust. On these drear sepulchres of buried days How sad to gaze! Yet, since their substances were perishable, And hands unstable Uprear'd their piles, no wonder that decay Both man and monument should sweep away. Ah me! how much more sadden'd is my mood, How heart-subdued, The ruins and the wrecks when I behold By time unroll'd, Of all the Faiths that man hath ever known, World-worshipp'd once—now spurn'd and overthrown! Religions—from the soul deriving breath, Should know no death; Yet do they perish, mingling their remains With fallen fanes; Creeds, canons, dogmas, councils, are the wreck'd And mouldering Masonry of Intellect.— Apis, Osiris, paramount of yore On Egypt's shore, Woden and Thor, through the wide North adored, With blood outpour'd; Jove, and the multiform Divinities, To whom the Pagan nations bow'd their knees,— Lo! they are cast aside, dethroned, forlorn, Defaced, out-worn, Like the world's childish dolls, which but insult Its age adult, Or prostrate scarecrows, on whose rags we tread, With scorn proportion'd to our former dread. Alas for human reason! all is change Ceaseless and strange; All ages form new systems, leaving heirs To cancel theirs: The future can but imitate the past, And instability alone will last.— Is there no compass left, by which to steer This erring sphere? No tie that may indissolubly bind To God, mankind? No code that may defy time's sharpest tooth? No fix'd, immutable, unerring truth? There is! there is!—one primitive and sure Religion pure, Unchanged in spirit, though its forms and codes Wear myriad modes, Contains all creeds within its mighty span— The love of God, displayed in love of Man.— This is the Christian's faith, when rightly read;— Oh! may it spread Till Earth, redeem'd from every hateful leaven, Makes peace with Heaven: Below—one blessed brotherhood of love; One Father—worshipp'd with one voice—above! MORAL ALCHEMY. The toils of Alchemists, whose vain pursuit Sought to transmute Dross into gold,—their secrets and their store Of mystic lore, What to the jibing modern do they seem? An ignis fatuus chase, a phantasy, a dream!— Yet for enlighten'd moral Alchemists There still exists A philosophic stone, whose magic spell No tongue may tell, Which renovates the soul's decaying health, And what it touches turns to purest mental wealth. This secret is reveal'd in every trace Of Nature's face, Whose seeming frown invariably tends To smiling ends, Transmuting ills into their opposite, And all that shocks the sense to subsequent delight.— Seems Earth unlovely in her robe of snow? Then look below, Where Nature in her subterranean Ark, Silent and dark, Already has each floral germ unfurl'd That shall revive and clothe the dead and naked world. Behold those perish'd flowers to earth consign'd— They, like mankind, Seek in their grave new birth. By nature's power Each in its hour Clothed in new beauty, from its tomb shall spring, And from its tube or chalice heavenward incense fling. Laboratories of a wider fold I now behold, Where are prepared the harvests yet unborn Of wine, oil, corn.— In those mute rayless banquet halls I see Myriads of coming feasts with all their revelry.— Yon teeming and minuter cells enclose The embryos Of fruits and seeds, food for the feather'd race, Whose chaunted grace, Swelling in choral gratitude on high, Shall with thanksgiving anthems melodize the sky.— And what materials, mystic Alchemist! Dost thou enlist To fabricate this ever-varied feast, For man, bird, beast? Whence the life, plenty, music, beauty, bloom? From silence, languor, death, unsightliness and gloom!— From Nature's magic hand whose touch makes sadness Eventual gladness, The reverent moral Alchemist may learn The art to turn Fate's roughest, hardest, most forbidding dross, Into the mental gold that knows not change or loss.— Lose we a valued friend?—To soothe our woe Let us bestow On those who still survive an added love, So shall we prove, Howe'er the dear departed we deplore, In friendship's sum and substance no diminish'd store.— Lose we our health?—Now may we fully know What thanks we owe For our sane years, perchance of lengthen'd scope; Now does our hope Point to the day when sickness, taking flight, Shall make us better feel health's exquisite delight.— In losing fortune, many a lucky elf Has found himself.— As all our moral bitters are design'd To brace the mind, And renovate its healthy tone, the wise Their sorest trials hail as blessings in disguise. There is no gloom on earth; for God above Chastens in love, Transmuting sorrows into golden joy Free from alloy, His dearest attribute is still to bless, And man's most welcome hymn is grateful cheerfulness. MORAL COSMETICS. Ye who would save your features florid, Lithe limbs, bright eyes, unwrinkled forehead From age's devastation horrid, Adopt this plan;— 'Twill make, in climates cold or torrid, A hale old man.— Avoid, in youth, luxurious diet, Restrain the passions' lawless riot; Devoted to domestic quiet, Be wisely gay: So shall ye, spite of age's fiat, Resist decay. Seek not in Mammon's worship pleasure, But find your richest, dearest treasure, In books, friends, music, polish'd leisure; The mind, not sense, Made the sole scale by which ye measure Your opulence. This is the solace, this the science, Life's purest, sweetest, best appliance, That disappoints not man's reliance, Whate'er his state; But challenges, with calm defiance, Time, fortune, fate. THE OLD MAN'S PÆAN. Vainly, ye libellers! your page Assaults and vilifies old age, 'Tis still life's golden æra; Its pleasures, wisely understood, An unalloy'd unfailing good, Its evils a chimæra.— Time's victim, I am victor still,— Holding the privilege at will To seize him by the forelock; On me would he return the grasp, He finds there's nothing left to clasp— Not e'en a single hoar lock.— We blame th' idolatrous divine Who gilds and decorates his shrine, The Deity neglected; Yet our self-adoration blind Is body-worship—to the mind No reverence directed.— Greybeards there are, who thinking art Can conquer nature, play the part Of adolescent friskers; Swindlers and counterfeits of truth, They strive to cheat us by false youth, False teeth, hair, eyebrows, whiskers. While to the frame due care I give, No Masquerader will I live, To no disguises pander; But rather seek to save from blight My mind in all its pristine plight Of cheerfulness and candour. A youthful cheer sustains us old, As arrows best their course uphold Wing'd by a lightsome feather.— Happy the young old man who thus Bears, like a human arbutus, Life's flowers and fruit together. To dark oblivion I bequeath The ruddy cheek, brown hair, white teeth, And eyes that brightly twinkle;— Crows' feet may plough with furrows deep My features, if I can but keep My mind without a wrinkle. Young, I was never free—my soul Still master'd by the stern control Of some tyrannic passion; While my poor body, servile tool! The livery wore of fop and fool, An abject slave of fashion. Thanks to thy welcome touch, old age! Which strongest chains can disengage, The bondsman's manumitted:— Released from labour, thraldom, strife, I pasture in the park of life, Unsaddled and unbitted. If drawn for the Militia—call'd On Juries, where the heart is gall'd With crime, chicane, disaster, “Begone,” I cry—“avaunt! avast! Thank heaven! I'm sixty, and at last Am of myself free master.”— An actor once in every strife That agitates the stage of life, A lover, fearer, hater, Now in senility's snug box I sit, aloof from all their shocks, A passive, pleased spectator.— Free-traders, Chartists, Puseyites! Your warfare, with its wrongs and rights, In me no rage arouses; I read the news, and cry, if hurt At Whigs and Tories throwing dirt, “A plague on both your houses!” Tailors! avaunt your bills and spells!— When fashion plays on folly's bells, No haddock can be deafer;— Comfort and neatness all my care, I stick to broadcloth, and forswear Both Macintosh and Zephyr.— 'Tis but our sensual pleasures' zest That time can dull;—our purest, best Defy decay or capture.— A landscape—book—a work of art— My friends, my home—still fill my heart With undiminish'd rapture.— Fled some few years, old time may try Again to wake my rhyme, when I, Obeying the vagary, May thus subscribe the muse's frisk: “My pensive public—yours!—a brisk Young Septuagenary!” ANSWER TO “AN OLD MAN'S PÆAN.” [Written (invitâ Minervâ) at the instigation of J. H.] Thou greybeard gay! whose muse—(perchance In second childhood's ignorance,) Inspired “An Old Man's Pæan,” Hear how a brother senior sings Sexagenarian sufferings, In strains antipodean! Young, I could take a morning's sport; Play matches in the Tennis Court, So strong was I and plastic;— Dine out, and yet with spirit light And body unfatigued, at night Could sport the toe fantastic. Behold me now!—my limbs are stiff: An open door, an east-wind's whiff, Brings sharp rheumatic touches; A chamber-horse my only nag, I mope at home, or slowly drag My gouty feet on crutches. Once I devour'd whatever came, And never knew, except by name, The heartburn, bile, dyspepsy: Now I must fast—eat what I hate, Or all my ailments aggravate, From ache to epilepsy. How starving Tantalus of old Was punish'd by the Gods, is told In many a classic stanza; And all must recollect the wand That whisk'd the viands from the hand Of hungry Sancho Panza:— Their fate without their fault is mine. Champagne and claret, drinks divine As nectar or ambrosia, I may not quaff, but—(horrid bore!) My sherry from a cruet pour And think of past symposia. At home my wife will supervise Each meal I take. I wish her eyes Were sometimes touch'd with blindness! But no—they move not from my plate: God bless her! how I love, yet hate Her ever watchful kindness. “My dear! you know you're bilious—pray Avoid the turtle soup to-day, And do not touch the salmon; Just take a chicken wing, or leg, But no rich sauce—and let me beg You will not taste the gammon.” Shell-fish—of yore my favourite food, Are now my bane; yet crabs eschew'd, Might make an angel crabbed— No wonder if I quit the treat Of dainties that I may not eat, Half starving and half rabid. Debarr'd by fond affection's care From all my palate yearns to share, A kindness still more cruel Gives me carte blanche in all I loathe— Bread-puddings, sago, mutton-broth, Rice-milk, and water-gruel! INVOCATION. [Written in the neighbourhood of Abbotsford, during the last illness of Sir Walter Scott.] Spirits! Intelligences! Passions! Dreams! Ghosts! Genii! Sprites! Muses, that haunt the Heliconian streams, Inspiring Lights! Whose intellectual fires, in Scott combined, Supplied the sun of his omniscient mind! Ye who have o'er-informed and overwrought His teeming soul, Bidding it scatter galaxies of thought From pole to pole; Enlightening others till itself grew dark,— A midnight heaven, without one starry spark;— Spirits of Earth and Air—of Light and Gloom! Awake! arise! Restore the victim ye have made—relume His darkling eyes. Wizards! be all your magic skill unfurl'd, To charm to health the Charmer of the World! The scabbard, by its sword outworn, repair; Give to his lips Their lore, than Chrysostom's more rich and rare: Dispel the eclipse That intercepts his intellectual light, And saddens all mankind with tears and night, Not only for the Bard of highest worth, But best of men, Do I invoke ye, Powers of Heaven and Earth! Oh! where and when Shall we again behold his counterpart— Such kindred excellence of head and heart? So good and great—benevolent as wise— On his high throne How meekly hath he borne his faculties! How finely shown A model to the irritable race, Of generous kindness, courtesy, and grace! If he must die, how great to perish thus In Glory's blaze; A world, in requiem unanimous, Weeping his praise! While Angels wait to catch his parting breath— Who would not give his life for such a death? THE MOTHER'S MISTAKE. Heard you that piercing shriek—the throe Of fear and agonising woe? It is a mother, who with wild Despairing looks and gasping breath, Thinks she beholds her only child Extended on the floor in death! That darling Babe whose natal cry Had thrill'd her heart with ecstasy, As with baptizing tears of bliss Her nestling treasure she bedew'd, Then clasp'd him with a silent kiss, And heavenward look'd her gratitude:— That darling babe who, while he press'd His rosebud lips around her breast, Would steal an upward glance, and bless With smiles his mother's tenderness; Confining laughter to his eyes, Lest he should lose the teeming prize:— That darling Babe who, sleeping, proved, More than when waking, how she loved. Then was her ever watchful ear Prepared to catch the smallest noise, Which sometimes hope and sometimes fear Would liken to her infant's voice. With beating heart and timid flush, On tiptoe to his cot she crept, Lifting the curtain with a hush, To gaze upon him as he slept. Then would she place his outstretch'd arm Beside his body, close and warm; Adjust his scatter'd clothes aright, And shade his features from the light, And look a thousand fond caressings And move her lips in speechless blessings, Then steal away with eyes that glisten, Again to linger round and listen. Oh! can she bear to think that he Whom she has loved so tenderly, Her only earthly hope and stay, For ever should be wrench'd away? No, no!—to such o'erpowering grief Oblivion brings a short relief: She hears no sound, all objects swim Before her sight confused and dim; She feels each sick'ning sense decay, Sinks shudd'ring down, and faints away! Her child revives,—its fit is o'er; When with affrighted zeal it tries By voice and kisses to restore The mother's dormant faculties; Till nature's tides with quicken'd force Resume their interrupted course: Her eyes she opens, sees her boy, Gazes with sense-bewilder'd start, Utters a thrilling cry of joy, Clasps him in transport to her heart, Stamps kisses on his mouth, his cheek, Looks up to heaven, and tries to speak; But voice is drown'd in heaving throbs, Outgushing tears, and gasping sobs. THE SUN'S ECLIPSE. —July 8th, 1842. 'Tis cloudless morning, but a frown misplaced, Cold—lurid—strange, The summer smile from Nature's brow hath chased. What fearful change, What menacing catastrophe is thus Usher'd by such prognostics ominous? Is it the light of day, this livid glare, Death's counterpart:— What means the withering coldness in the air That chills my heart, And what the gloom portentous that hath made The glow of morning a funereal shade? O'er the Sun's disc a dark orb wins its slow Gloom-deep'ning way, Climbs—spreads—enshrouds—extinguishes—and lo! The god of day Hangs in the sky, a corpse! th' usurper's might Hath storm'd his throne, and quench'd the life of light! A pall is on the earth—the screaming birds To covert speed; Bewilder'd and aghast, the bellowing herds Rush o'er the mead; While men, pale shadows in the ghastly gloom, Seem spectral forms just risen from the tomb. Transient, tho' total was that drear eclipse: With might restored The Sun re-gladden'd earth—but human lips Have never pour'd In mortal ears the horrors of the sight That thrill'd my soul that memorable night. To every distant zone and fulgent star Mine eyes could reach, And the wide waste was one chaotic war; O'er all and each, Above—beneath—around me—everywhere, Was anarchy—convulsion—death—despair. 'Twas noon, and yet a deep unnatural night Enshrouded Heaven, Save where some orb unsphered, or satellite Franticly driven, Glared as it darted through the darkness dread, Blind—rudderless—uncheck'd—unpiloted. A thousand simultaneous thunders crash'd, As here and there Some rushing planet 'gainst another dash'd, Shooting thro' air Volleys of shatter'd wreck, when, both destroy'd, Founder'd and sank in the engulphing void. Others, self-kindled, as they whirl'd and turn'd Without a guide, Burst into flames, and rushing as they burn'd With range more wide, Like fire-ships that some stately fleet surprise, Spread havoc thro' the constellated skies. While stars kept falling from their spheres—as tho' The heavens wept fire, Earth was a raging hell of war and woe Most deep and dire, Virtue was vice—vice virtue—all was strife, Brute force was law—justice th' assassin's knife. From that fell scene my space-commanding eye Glad to withdraw, I pierced th' empyrean palace of the sky And shudd'ring saw A vacant throne—a sun's extinguish'd sphere, All else a void—dark, desolate, and drear. “What mean,” I cried, “these sights unparallel'd, These scenes of fear?” When lo! a voice replied, and Nature held Her breath to hear, “Mortal, the scroll before thine eyes unfurl'd, Displays a soul eclipse—an atheist world.” I woke—my dream was o'er! What ecstacy It was to know That God was guide and guardian of the sky, That man below Deserved the love I felt—I could not speak The thrilling joy, whose tears were on my cheek! LACHRYMOSE WRITERS. Ye human screech-owls, who delight To herald woe—whose day is night, Whose mental food is misery and moans, If ye must needs uphold the pall, And walk at Pleasure's funeral, Be Mutes—and publish not your cries and groans. Near a menagerie to dwell, Annoy'd by ceaseless groan and yell, Is sad, altho' we cannot blame the brutes; A far worse neighbour is the man Whose study is a Caravan, Whence the caged monster ever howls and hoots. Ye say that Earth's a charnel—life Incessant wretchedness and strife— That all is doom below, and wrath above, The sun and moon sepulchral lamps, The sky a vault, whose baleful damps Soon blight and moulder all that live and love. Man, as your diatribes aver, Only makes reason minister To deeds irrational and schemes perverse; Human in name, he proves in all His acts a hateful animal, And woman (monstrous calumny) is worse. This earth, whose walls are stony gloom, Whose roof rains tears, whose floor's a tomb With its chain-rattling beach and lashing waves, Is, ye maintain, a fitting jail Where felon man the woes may wail, From which no prudence guards, no mercy saves. E'en were it true, this lachrymose List of imaginary woes, Why from our sympathy extort more tears? Why blazon grief—why make the Press Groan with repinings and distress, Why knell despair for ever in our ears? Ungrateful and calumnious crew, Whose plaints, as impious as untrue, From morbid intellects derive their birth; Away! begone to mope and moan, And weep in some asylum lone, Where ye may rail unheard at heaven and earth. Earth! on whose stage in pomp array'd Life's joyous interlude is play'd, Earth! with thy pageants ever new and bright, Thy woods and waters, hills and dales, How dead must be the soul that fails To see and bless thy beauties infinite! Man! whose high intellect supplies A never-failing Paradise Of holy and enrapturing pursuits, Whose heart's a fount of fresh delight, Pity the Cynics who would blight Thy godlike gifts, and rank thee with the brutes. Oh Woman! who from realms above Hast brought to Earth the heaven of love, Terrestrial angel, beautiful as pure! No pains, no penalties dispense On thy traducers—their offence Is its own punishment most sharp and sure. Father and God! whose love and might To every sense are blazon'd bright On the vast three-leaved Bible—earth—sea—sky, Pardon th' impugners of thy laws, Expand their hearts, and give them cause To bless th' exhaustless grace they now deny. WHY ARE THEY SHUT? The following Stanzas were composed while the author was sitting outside a Country Church in Sussex, much regretting that, as it was week day, he could not gain admittance to the sacred edifice. Why are our Churches shut with jealous care, Bolted and barr'd against our bosom's yearning, Save for the few short hours of Sabbath prayer, With the bell's tolling statedly returning? Why are they shut? If with diurnal drudgeries o'erwrought, Or sick of dissipation's dull vagaries, We wish to snatch one little space for thought, Or holy respite in our sanctuaries, Why are they shut? What! shall the Church, the House of Prayer, no more Give tacit notice from its fasten'd portals, That for six days 'tis useless to adore, Since God will hold no communings with mortals? Why are they shut? Are there no sinners in the churchless week, Who wish to sanctify a vow'd repentance? Are there no hearts bereft which fain would seek The only balm for Death's unpitying sentence? Why are they shut? Are there no poor, no wrong'd, no heirs of grief, No sick, who, when their strength or courage falters, Long for a moment's respite or relief, By kneeling at the God of mercy's altars? Why are they shut? Are there no wicked, whom, if tempted in, Some qualm of conscience or devout suggestion Might suddenly redeem from future sin? Oh! if there be, how solemn is the question, Why are they shut? In foreign climes mechanics leave their tasks To breathe a passing prayer in their Cathedrals: There they have week-day shrines, and no one asks, When he would kneel to them, and count his beadrolls, Why are they shut? Seeing them enter sad and disconcerted, To quit those cheering fanes with looks of gladness,— How often have my thoughts to ours reverted! How oft have I exclaim'd, in tones of sadness, Why are they shut? For who within a Parish Church can stroll, Wrapt in its week-day stillness and vacation, Nor feel that in the very air his soul Receives a sweet and hallowing lustration? Why are they shut? The vacant pews, blank aisles, and empty choir, All in a deep sepulchral silence shrouded, An awe more solemn and intense inspire, Than when with Sabbath congregations crowded. Why are they shut? The echoes of our footsteps, as we tread On hollow graves, are spiritual voices; And holding mental converse with the dead, In holy reveries our soul rejoices. Why are they shut? If there be one—one only—who might share This sanctifying week-day adoration, Were but our churches open to his prayer, Why—I demand with earnest iteration— Why are they shut? THE LIBELLED BENEFACTOR. They warned me by all that affection could urge, To repel his advances, and fly from his sight, They call'd him a fiend, a destroyer, a scourge, And whisper'd his name with a shudder of fright.— They said that disease went as herald before, While sorrow and severance followed his track, They besought me if ever I came to his door, Not a moment to pause, but turn instantly back. “His breath,” they exclaim'd, “is a pestilence foul, “His aspect more hateful than language can tell, “His touch is pollution,—no Gorgon or Ghoul “In appearance and deeds is more loathsome and fell.” Such stern prohibitions, descriptions so dire, By which the most dauntless might well be dismay'd, In me only waken'd a deeper desire To gaze on the monster so darkly portray'd. I sought him—I saw him—he stood by a marsh, Where henbane and hemlock with poppies entwined; He was pale, he was grave, but no feature was harsh, His eye was serene, his expression was kind. “This stigmatized being,” I cried in surprise, “Wears a face most benignant; but looks are not facts, “Physiognomy often abuses our eyes; “I'll follow his footsteps and judge by his acts.” There came from a cottage a cry of alarm, An infant was writhing in agonies sore, His hand rock'd the cradle, its touch was a charm, The babe fell asleep, and its anguish was o'er. He reach'd a proud mansion where, worn by the woe Of consumption, a Beauty lay wither'd, in bed, Her pulse he compress'd with his finger, and lo! The complaint of long years in a moment had fled! He paused where he heard the disconsolate groan Of a widow with manifold miseries crush'd; Where a pauper was left in his sickness to groan, Both were heal'd at his sight, and their sorrows were hush'd. He sped where a king, sorely smitten with age, In vain sought relief from the pangs he endured; “I come,” said the stranger, “your woes to assuage;” He spoke, and the monarch was instantly cured. Astounded by deeds which appear'd to bespeak In the fiend a benevolent friend of mankind, From himself I resolved a solution to seek Of the strange contradictions that puzzled my mind. “Chase, mystical being,” I cried, “this suspense; “How comes it thou'rt blacken'd by every tongue, “When in truth thou'rt the champion, the hope, the defence “Of the king and the beggar, the old and the young?” “Thou hast witness'd”—he answer'd—(his voice and his face Were all that is musical, bland, and benign), “Not a tithe of the blessings I shed on the race “Who my form and my attributes daily malign. “All distinctions of fortune, of birth, of degree, “Disappear where my levelling banner I wave; “From his desolate dungeon the captive I free; “His fetters I loose from the suffering slave. “And when from their stormy probation on earth, “The just and the righteous in peace I dismiss, “I give them a new and more glorious birth In regions of pure and perennial bliss.” “Let me bless thee,” I cried, “for thy mission of love, “Oh say to what name shall I fashion my breath?” “The Angel of Life is my title above, “But short-sighted mortals have christen'd me Death!” DIRGE FOR A LIVING POET. Written during the last illness of Southey. What! shall the mind of bard—historian—sage, Be prostrate laid upon oblivion's bier, Shall darkness quench the beacon of our age, “Without the meed of one melodious tear?” Will none, with genius like his own, Mourn the fine intellect o'erthrown, That died in giving life to deathless heirs? Are worthier voices mute? then I The Muse's humblest votary, Will pour my wailful dirge and sympathising prayers. Well may I mourn that mental sun's eclipse, For in his study have I sate enshrined, And reverently listen'd while his lips Master'd the master-spirits of mankind, As his expanding wisdom took New range from his consulted book.— Oh, to what noble thoughts didst thou give birth, Thou poet-sage, whose life and mind In mutual perfectness combined The spirit's loftiest flight, with purest moral worth! Behold the withering change! amid the rays That form a halo round those volumed wits, Amid his own imperishable lays In silent, blank fatuity he sits! Seeking a respite from his curse, His body, now his spirit's hearse, Still haunts that book-charm'd room, for there alone Thought-gleams illume his wand'ring eyes, As lightnings flicker o'er the skies Where the departed sun in cloudless glory shone. Oh withering, woful change—oh living death! Lo! where he strays at fancy's aimless beck, On his dementate brow the titled wreath, A mournful mockery of reason's wreck.— Roaming by Derwent's silent shore Or dark-hued Greta's rushing roar, A human statue! His unconscious stare Knows not the once familiar spot, Knows not the partner of his lot, Who, as she guides him, sobs a broken-hearted prayer. Oh flood and fell, lake, moorland, valley, hill! Mourn the dark bard who sang your praise of yore. Oh Rydal-Falls, Lodore, and Dungeon Gill! Down the rock's cheek your tearful gushes pour.— Ye crag-envelop'd Tarns that sleep In your hush'd craters, wake and weep.— Ye mountains! hide your sorrowing heads in cloud: As sobbing winds around ye moan; Helvellyn! Skiddaw! wail and groan, And clothe your giant forms in vapour's mourning shroud. Why make appeal to these? Ye good and wise Who worshipp'd at his intellectual shrine, Ye kindred natures, who can sympathise With genius 'reft of reason's light divine, Ye whom his learning, virtue, lays, Taught, guided, charm'd in other days, Let all your countless voices be combined, As on your knees, ye pour on high This choral supplicating cry— Restore, restore, O God! our poet's wand'ring mind! CAMPBELL'S FUNERAL. He was buried in Poets' Corner, Westminster Abbey, his pall being supported by six noblemen. 'Tis well to see these accidental great, Noble by birth, or Fortune's favour blind, Gracing themselves in adding grace and state To the more noble eminence of mind, And doing homage to a bard Whose breast by Nature's gems was starr'd, Whose patent by the hand of God himself was sign'd. While monarchs sleep, forgotten, unrevered, Time trims the lamp of intellectual fame, The builders of the pyramids, who rear'd Mountains of stone, left none to tell their name. Though Homer's tomb was never known, A mausoleum of his own, Long as the world endures his greatness shall proclaim. What lauding sepulchre does Campbell want? 'Tis his to give, and not derive renown. What monumental bronze or adamant, Like his own deathless lays can hand him down? Poets outlast their tombs: the bust And statue soon revert to dust; The dust they represent still wears the laurel crown. The solid Abbey walls that seem time-proof, Form'd to await the final day of doom; The cluster'd shafts and arch-supported roof, That now enshrine and guard our Campbell's tomb, Become a ruin'd shatter'd fane, May fall and bury him again, Yet still the bard shall live, his fame-wreath still shall bloom. Methought the monumental effigies Of elder poets that were grouped around, Lean'd from their pedestals with eager eyes, To peer into the excavated ground Where lay the gifted, good, and brave, While earth from Kosciusko's grave Fell on his coffin-plate with freedom-shrieking sound. “And Freedom shriek'd as Kosciusko fell.”—Campbell. And over him the kindred dust was strew'd Of Poets' Corner. O misnomer strange! The poet's confine is the amplitude Of the whole earth's illimitable range, O'er which his spirit wings its flight, Shedding an intellectual light, A sun that never sets, a moon that knows no change. Around his grave in radiant brotherhood, As if to form a halo o'er his head, Not few of England's master spirits stood, Bards, artists, sages, reverently led To wave each separating plea Of sect, clime, party, and degree, All honouring him on whom Nature all honours shed. To me the humblest of the mourning band, Who knew the bard through many a changeful year, It was a proud sad privilege to stand Beside his grave and shed a parting tear. Seven lustres had he been my friend, Be that my plea when I suspend This all-unworthy wreath on such a poet's bier. THE LIFE AND DEATH. The Life. Hath Momus descended,—the god of Mirth,— To glad the world with his triumphs thus? Or is it a mortal, who tastes on earth An apotheosis rapturous! While his worshippers hail him with choral cries, And Laughter's reverberant ecstasies! He moves like a mental sun, whose light Scatters around an electric ray, Which every eye that beholds, is bright, And every bosom that feels, is gay,— A sun, (it is own'd by a nation's lips,) That hath ne'er been dimm'd,—never known eclipse! As this Spirit sits on his throne elate, They tender him homage from every sphere: From the rich, the noble, the wise, the great,— Nay, even the King is a courtier here; And, vassal-like, makes his crown submit To the majesty of sceptred Wit.— They press him with flattering words and wiles To honour and grace their lordly halls, And impart by his mirth, and songs, and smiles, A glory and zest to their festivals. For they know that his presence can banish gloom, And give light and life to the banquet-room. On what aching hearts hath he gladness pour'd! In scenes unnumber'd, what countless throngs, From the public stage to the festive board, Have enraptured hung on his mirthful songs! At his wit's incessantly flashing light, What shouts have startled the ear of night! Ask you the name of the gifted man, Whose genius thus could enchant the world; Whose fame through both the hemispheres ran,— Whose flag of triumph was never furl'd?— You ask it not, for you know that none But Mathews alone has such trophies won! The Death. Hark to the toll of the passing bell, Which “swinging slow with solemn roar,” Carries the dismal funeral knell O'er the thrilling waves of the Plymouth shore; And is borne afar by the shuddering breeze, From Wembury's cliffs to Mount-Edgecumbe's trees. Nature appears to have thrown a pall Over that landscape so rich and fair, For a withering gloom and sadness fall Alike upon ocean, earth, and air, And the darkling heights in the distance show Like spectral mourners, grim with woe. The bittern's wail and the sea-mew's cry, Seem to share the deep and wide distress, As their wings they spread, and seaward fly Away from that scene of wretchedness: And the booming moan of the distant surge Falls on the ear like a doleful dirge. Hark! 'tis a female cry—'tis the sound Of a widow's heart with anguish torn; A groan succeeds, and the sob profound Of a sireless son, aghast, forlorn! And oh! how loving and loved they were, Their own 'reft hearts can alone declare. Behold! from St. Andrew's Church appears A funeral train in its sad array, Whose mourners, blind with their stanchless tears, With faltering footsteps feel their way To the bones and mould thrown up in a heap Beside a sepulchre dark and deep.— The coffin is sunk, the prayer is pour'd— “Ashes to ashes, and dust to dust.” They sprinkle earth on the rattling board, And they whose heads o'er the grave are thrust, Draw back at the sound with a shuddering start, For its awful echoes thrill their heart. As if it were sent to reveal and bless, A ray through the lurid vapour beams,— Pierces the sepulchre's ghastliness, And lo! on the coffin's plate it gleams. Th' inscription now may be plainly read— “Charles Mathews”—that's the name of the dead. God! can it be?—is that breath resign'd Which render'd the brightest joy more bright? Does that life of life, and mind of mind, The circle's soul, and the world's delight, Lie stretch'd in the coffin's silence, dark, Cold—lifeless—ghastly—stiff and stark? What proofs of his friendship, wit, and worth, On memory crowd, and recall past years! But I cannot give their record birth, For my heart and my eyes are both in tears: Let me drop the pen,—let me quit the lay, And rush from my own sad thoughts away.— HOPE'S YEARNINGS. How sweet it is, when wearied with the jars Of wrangling sects, each sour'd with bigot leaven, To let the Spirit burst its prison bars And soar into the deep repose of Heaven! How sweet it is, when sick with strife and noise Of the fell brood that owes to faction birth, To turn to Nature's tranquillizing joys, And taste the soothing harmonies of Earth! But tho' the lovely Earth, and Sea, and Air, Be rich in joys that form a sumless sum, Fill'd with Nepenthes that can banish care, And wrap the senses in Elysium, 'Tis sweeter still from these delights to turn Back to our kind—to watch the course of Man, And for that blessed consummation yearn, When Nature shall complete her noble plan;— When hate, oppression, vice, and crime, shall cease, When War's ensanguined banner shall be furl'd, And to our moral system shall extend The perfectness of the material world.— Sweetest of all, when 'tis our happy fate To drop some tribute, trifling tho' it prove, On the thrice-hallow'd altar dedicate To Man's improvement, truth, and social love. Faith in our race's destined elevation, And its incessant progress to the goal, Tends, by exciting hope and emulation, To realise th' aspirings of the soul. TO A LOG OF WOOD UPON THE FIRE. When Horace, as the snows descended On Mount Soracte, recommended That logs be doubled, Until a blazing fire arose, I wonder whether thoughts like those Which in my noddle interpose, His fancy troubled. Poor Log! I cannot hear thee sigh, And groan, and hiss, and see thee die, To warm a Poet, Without evincing thy success, And as thou wanest less and less, Inditing a farewell address To let thee know it. Peeping from earth—a bud unveil'd, Some “bosky bourne” or dingle hail'd Thy natal hour; While infant winds around thee blew, And thou wert fed with silver dew, And tender sun-beams oozing through Thy leafy bower. Earth—water—air—thy growth prepared; And if perchance some robin, scared From neighbouring manor, Perch'd on thy crest, it rock'd in air, Making his ruddy feathers flare In the sun's ray, as if they were A fairy banner. Or if some nightingale impress'd Against thy branching top her breast Heaving with passion, And in the leafy nights of June, Outpour'd her sorrows to the moon, Thy trembling stem thou didst attune To each vibration. Thou grew'st a goodly tree, with shoots Fanning the sky, and earth-bound roots So grappled under, That thou whom perching birds could swing, And zephyrs rock with lightest wing, From thy firm trunk unmoved didst fling Tempest and thunder. Thine offspring leaves—death's annual prey, Which Herod Winter tore away From thy caressing, In heaps, like graves, around thee blown, Each morn thy dewy tears have strown, O'er each thy branching hands been thrown, As if in blessing. Bursting to life, another race At touch of Spring in thy embrace, Sported and flutter'd; Aloft, where wanton breezes play'd, In thy knit boughs have ringdoves made Their nest, and lovers in thy shade Their vows have utter'd. How oft thy lofty summits won Morn's virgin smile, and hail'd the sun With rustling motion; How oft in silent depths of night, When the moon sail'd in cloudless light, Thou hast stood awe-struck at the sight In hush'd devotion— 'Twere vain to ask; for doom'd to fall, The day appointed for us all O'er thee impended; The hatchet, with remorseless blow, First laid thee in the forest low, Then cut thee into logs—and so Thy course was ended.— But not thine use—for moral rules, Worth all the wisdom of the schools, Thou may'st bequeath me; Bidding me cherish those who live Above me, and the more I thrive, A wider shade and shelter give To those beneath me. So when death lays his axe on me, I may resign, as calm as thee, My hold terrestrial; Like thine my latter end be found, Diffusing light and warmth around, And like thy smoke my spirit bound To realms celestial. UNPOSSESSED POSSESSIONS. Whose are Windsor and Hampton, the pride of the land, With their treasures and trophies so varied and grand? The Queen's, you reply:— Deuce a bit! you and I Through their gates, twice a week, making privileged way, Tread their gilded saloons, View their portraits, cartoons, And, like Crusoe, are monarchs of all we survey.— And whose are our Nobles' magnificent homes, With their galleries, gardens, their statues and domes? His Grace's? my Lord's? Ay, in law and in words, But in fact they are ours, for the master, poor wight! Gladly leaving their view To the visiting crew, Keeps a dear exhibition for others' delight.— And whose are the stag-haunted parks, the domains, The woods and the waters, the hills and the plains? Yours and mine, for our eyes Daily make them our prize: What more have their owners?—The care and the cost! Alas! for the great, Whose treasures and state, Unprized when possess'd, are regretted when lost.— When I float on the Thames, or am whisk'd o'er the roads, To the numerous royal and noble abodes Whose delights I may share, Without ownership's care, With what pity the titled and rich I regard, And exultingly cry, Oh! how happy am I To be only a poor unpatrician bard! TO THE FURZE BUSH. Let Burns and old Chaucer unite The praise of the Daisy to sing,— Let Wordsworth of Celandine write, And crown her the Queen of the Spring; The Hyacinth's classical fame Let Milton embalm in his verse; Be mine the glad task to proclaim The Charms of untrumpeted Furze! Of all other bloom when bereft, And Sol wears his wintery screen, Thy sunshining blossoms are left To light up the common and green. O why should they envy the peer His perfume of spices and myrrhs, When the poorest their senses may cheer With incense diffused from the Furze? It is bristled with thorns, I confess; But so is the much-flatter'd Rose: Is the Sweetbriar lauded the less Because amid prickles it grows? 'Twere to cut off an epigram's point, Or disfurnish a knight of his spurs, If we foolishly wish'd to disjoint Its arms from the lance-bearing Furze. Ye dabblers in mines, who would clutch The wealth which their bowels enfold; See! Nature, with Midas-like touch, Here turns a whole common to gold; No niggard is she to the poor, But distributes whatever is hers, And the wayfaring beggar is sure Of a tribute of gold from the Furze. Ye worldlings! learn hence to divide Your wealth with the children of want, Nor scorn, in your fortune and pride, To be taught by the commonest plant. If the wisest new wisdom may draw From things humble, as reason avers, We too may receive Heaven's law, And beneficence learn from the Furze! THE FIRST OF MARCH. The bud is in the bough, and the leaf is in the bud, And Earth's beginning now in her veins to feel the blood, Which, warm'd by summer suns in th'alembic of the vine, From her founts will overrun in a ruddy gush of wine. The perfume and the bloom that shall decorate the flower, Are quickening in the gloom of their subterranean bower; And the juices meant to feed trees, vegetables, fruits, Unerringly proceed to their pre-appointed roots. How awful is the thought of the wonders underground, Of the mystic changes wrought in the silent, dark profound; How each thing upward tends by necessity decreed, And a world's support depends on the shooting of a seed! The summer 's in her ark, and this sunny-pinion'd day Is commission'd to remark whether Winter holds her sway; Go back, thou dove of peace, with the myrtle on thy wing, Say, that floods and tempests cease and the world is ripe for spring. Thou hast fann'd the sleeping Earth till her dreams are all of flowers, And the waters look in mirth for their overhanging bowers; The forest seems to listen for the rustle of its leaves, And the very skies to glisten in the hope of summer eves. Thy vivifying spell has been felt beneath the wave, By the dormouse in its cell, and the mole within its cave; And the summer tribes that creep, or in air expand their wing, Have started from their sleep at the summons of the Spring.— The cattle lift their voices from the valleys and the hills, And the feather'd race rejoices with a gush of tuneful bills, And if this cloudless arch fills the poet's song with glee, O thou sunny first of March! be it dedicate to thee. INVOCATION TO THE CUCKOO. O, pursuivant and herald of the spring! Whether thou still dost dwell In some rose-laurel'd dell Of that charm'd island, whose magician king Bade all its rocks and caves, Woods, winds, and waves, Thrill to the dulcet chaunt of Ariel, Until he broke the spell, And cast his wand into the shuddering sea,— O hither, hither fleet, Upon the south wind sweet, And soothe us with thy vernal melody! Or whether to the redolent Azores, Amid whose tufted sheaves The floral goddess weaves Her garland, breathing on the glades and shores Intoxicating air, Truant! thou dost repair; Or lingerest still in that meridian nest, Where myriad piping throats Rival the warbler's notes, The saffron namesakes of those islands blest,— O hither, hither wing Thy flight, and to our longing woodlands sing. Or in those sea-girt gardens dost thou dwell, Of plantain, cocoa, palm, And that red tree, whose balm Fumed in the holocausts of Israel; Beneath banana shades, Guava, and fig-tree glades, Painting thy plumage in the sapphirine hue Thrown from the heron blue, Or rays of the prismatic parroquet,— O, let the perfumed breeze From those Hesperides Waft thee once more our eager ears to greet! For lo! the young leaves-flutter in the south, As if they tried their wings, While the bee's trumpet brings News of each bud that pouts its honied mouth; Blue-bells, yellow-cups, jonquils, Lilies wild and daffodils, Gladden our meads in intertangled wreath; The sun enamour'd lies, Watching the violets' eyes On every bank, and drinks their luscious breath; With open lips the thorn Proclaims that May is born, And darest thou, bird of spring, that summons scorn? “Cuckoo! Cuckoo!” O welcome, welcome notes! Fields, woods, and waves rejoice In that recover'd voice, As on the wind its fluty music floats. At that elixir strain My youth resumes its reign, And life's first spring comes blossoming again: Oh, wond rous bird! if thus Thy voice miraculous Can renovate my spirits' vernal prime, Nor thou, my Muse, forbear That ecstacy to share,— I laugh at Fortune, and defy old Time. MAN. [Versified from an Apologue by Dr. Sheridan.] Afflicition one day, as she hark'd to the roar Of the stormy and struggling billow, Drew a beautiful form on the sands of the shore, With the branch of a weeping-willow. Jupiter, struck with the noble plan, As he roam'd on the verge of the ocean, Breathed on the figure, and calling it Man, Endued it with life and motion. A creature so glorious in mind and in frame, So stamp'd with each parent's impression, Amongst them a point of contention became, Each claiming the right of possession. He is mine, said Affliction; I gave him his birth, I alone am his cause of creation;— The materials were furnish'd by me, answered Earth;— I gave him, said Jove, animation. The gods, all assembled in solemn divan, After hearing each claimant's petition, Pronounced a definitive verdict on Man, And thus settled his fate's disposition: “Let Affliction possess her own child, till the woes Of life cease to harass and goad it; After death give his body to Earth, whence it rose, And his spirit to Jove who bestow'd it.” SPORTING WITHOUT A LICENCE. There's a charm when Spring is young, And comes laughing on the breeze, When each leaflet has a tongue, That is lisping in the trees, When morn is fair, and the sunny air With chime of beaks is ringing, Through fields to rove with her we love, And listen to their singing. The sportsman finds a zest, Which all others can outvie, With his lightning to arrest Pheasants whirring through the sky; With dog and gun, from dawn of sun Till purple evening hovers, O'er field and fen, and hill and glen, The happiest of rovers. The hunter loves to dash Through the horn-resounding woods, Or plunge with fearless splash Into intercepting floods; O'er gap and gate he leaps elate, The vaulting stag to follow, And at the death has scarcely breath To give the whoop and hallo! By the river's margin dank, With the reeds and rushes mix'd, Like a statue on a bank, See the patient angler fix'd! A summer's day he whiles away Without fatigue or sorrow, And if the fish should baulk his wish, He comes again to-morrow. In air let pheasants range, 'Tis to me a glorious sight, Which no fire of mine shall change Into grovelling blood and night; I am no hound, to pant and bound Behind a stag that's flying; Nor can I hook a trout from brook, On grass to watch its dying. And yet no sportsman keen Can a sweeter pastime ply, Or enjoy the rural scene With more ecstacy than I: There's not a view, a form, a hue, In earth, or air, or ocean, That does not fill my heart, and thrill My bosom with emotion. O clouds that paint the air! O fountains, fields, and groves! Lights, sounds, and odours rare, Which my yearning spirit loves! While thus I feel, and only steal From visions so enchanting, In tuneful lays to sing your praise, What charm of life is wanting? THE QUARREL OF FAITH, HOPE, AND CHARITY. Once Faith, Hope, and Charity traversed the land, In sisterhood's uninterrupted embraces, Performing their office of love hand in hand, Of the Christian world the appropriate Graces. But tiffs since those primitive days have occurr'd, That threaten to sever this friendly relation, As may well be surmised when I state, word for word, The terms of their latest and worst altercation: “Sister Charity, prythee allow me to state,” Cries Faith, in a tone of contemptuous sneering, “That while you affect to be meek and sedate, “Your conduct is cunning, your tone domineering. “In the times that are gone, my world-harassing name, “Received some accession of strength ev'ry hour; “St. Bartholomew's Massacre hallow'd my fame, “And Sicily's Vespers asserted my power. “When martyrs in multitudes rush'd at my call, “To peril their lives for Theology's sake, “Mine too was the voice that cried, ‘Sacrifice all, “‘With gaol and with gibbet, with faggot and stake.’ “When the banner of orthodox slaughter was furl'd, “And subjects no more from each other dissented, “I set them at war with the rest of the world, “And for centuries national struggles fomented. “What are all the great heroes on history's page, “But puppets who figured as I pulled the strings? “Crusades I engender'd in every age, “And Faith was the leader of armies and kings. “In those days of my glory Hope followed my track, “In warfare a firm and impartial ally, “For she constantly patted both sides on the back, “And promised them both a reward in the sky.” Here Charity, heaving disconsolate sighs, That said “I admit what I deeply deplore,” Uplifted to heaven her tear-suffused eyes, Which seem'd but to anger her sister the more. “Nay, none of your cant, hypocritical minx!” She cried in a louder and bitterer tone, “If you feel any fancy to whimper, methinks “You might weep that the days of my glory are gone. “What wreck of my palmy puissance is left? “What bravos and bullies my greatness declare? “Of the holy and dear Inquisition bereft, “All my fierce fulminations are impotent air. “No racks and no pincers—no limbs piecemeal torn, “No screams of the tortured my prowess display; “And to crown all these slights, I am shamefully shorn “Of my own proper triumph, an auto da fè. “The Pope, who could once, in my terrible name, “Spread warfare and havoc all Christendom round, “Is sunk to such pitiful dotage and shame, “That the Vatican thunder 's a ridiculed sound. “Nay, even in England, my latest strong-hold, “And the firmest support of my paramount sway, “(In Gath or in Askelon be it not told,) “All my orthodox bulwarks are crumbling away. “Dissenters, untested, may now, nothing loth, “As municipal officers feast and carouse; “And emancipate Catholics, taking the oath, “O horror of horrors! may sit in the House. “If Erin no longer my altar-flame fann'd, “By ceasing to murder for tithe now and then, “It might well be surmised that my paralysed hand “Had lost all control o'er the actions of men. “And what though each orthodox candidate swears “To my Thirty-nine Articles—'tis but a jest, “Since a bishop (proh pudor!), a bishop, declares “That such oaths are a form,—never meant as a test. “And who is the cause that I'm laid on the shelf, “Disown'd and deserted by all but a few? “My downfall and ruin I trace to yourself, “To you, I repeat, sister Charity—you! “Your looks and your whining expressions of ruth, “Your appeals—ever urged with insidious wiles, “To reason and justice—to love and to truth, “Your tears of deceit, and your plausible smiles, “Have inveigled the bulk of my subjects away, “And have swell'd your own ranks with deserters from mine: “Such conduct is base, and from this very day, “Hope and I mean to leave you and take a new line.” With the look of an angel, the voice of a dove, Thus Charity answer'd—“Since Concord alone “Can prosper our partnership mission of love, “And exalt the attraction that calls her her own, “I would not, dear sisters, e'en harbour a thought, “That might peril a friendship so truly divine; “And if in our feelings a change has been wrought, “I humbly submit that the fault is not mine. “Christianity's attributes, holy and high, “When first, sister Faith, you delighted to teach, “And Hope only wafted your words to the sky, “I seconded gladly the labours of each: “But when, in crusades! you began to affect “A thousand disguises and masquerades new, “When you dress'd yourself up in the badges of sect, “Nay, even of Mussulman, Pagan, and Jew, “And when in each garb, as yourself have just said, “You scatter'd a firebrand wherever you went, “While Hope spent her breath, as she follow'd or led, “In fanning the flames of religious dissent, “I raised up my voice in a solemn appeal “Against your whole course of unchristian life, “Tho' its accents were drown'd in the clashing of steel, “In the clamour of councils, and schismatic strife; “But now when men, turning from dogmas to deeds. “Bear the scriptural dictum of Jesus in mind, “That salvation depends not on canons and creeds, “But on love of the Lord, and the love of our kind, “My voice can be heard, and my arguments weigh'd: “Which explains why such numerous converts of late “Are under my love-breathing standard array'd, “Who once, beneath yours, were excited to hate. “Superstition must throw off Religion's disguise; “For men, now enlighten'd, not darkling like owls, “While they reverence priests who are holy and wise, “Will no longer be hoodwink'd by cassocks or cowls. “If, Sisters! forgetting your primitive troth, “You would still part the world into tyrants and slaves, “What wonder that sages should look on you both “As the virtues of dupes, for the profit of knaves? “You would separate? Do so—I give you full scope; “But reflect, you are both of you naught when we part; “While I, 'tis well known, can supply Faith and Hope, “When I choose for my temple an innocent heart.” WINTER. The mill-wheel's frozen in the stream, The church is deck'd with holly, Misletoe hangs from the kitchen beam, To fright away melancholy; Icicles clink in the milkmaid's pail, Younkers skate on the pool below, Blackbirds perch on the garden rail, And hark, how the cold winds blow! There goes the squire to shoot at snipe, Here runs Dick to fetch a log; You'd swear his breath was the smoke of a pipe, In the frosty morning fog.— Hodge is breaking the ice for the kine, Old and young cough as they go, The round red sun forgets to shine, And hark, how the cold winds blow! THE CHOLERA MORBUS. [On hearing it said that this disease only attacked the poor.] It comes! it comes! from England's trembling tongue One low and universal murmur stealeth;— By dawn of day, each journal is o'erhung With startling eyes, to read what it revealeth, And all aghast, ejaculate one word— The Cholera—no other sound is heard! Had Death upon his ghastly horse reveal'd, From his throat-rattling trump a summons sounded, Not more appallingly its blast had peal'd Upon the nation's ear;—awe-struck, astounded, Men strive in vain their secret fears to smother, And gaze in blank dismay on one another. Now are all cares absorb'd in that of health; Hush'd is the song, the dance, the voice of gladness, While thousands in the selfishness of wealth, With looks of confidence, but hearts of sadness, Dream they can purchase safety for their lives By nostrums, drugs, and quack preventatives. The wretch who might have died in squalid want, Unseen, unmourn'd by our hard-hearted blindness, Wringing from fear what pity would not grant, Becomes the sudden object of our kindness, Now that his betters he may implicate, And spread infection to the rich and great. Yet still will wealth presumptuously cry, “What though the hand of death be thus outstretched? It will not reach the lordly and the high, But only strike the lowly and the wretched. Tush! what have we to quail at? Let us fold Our arms, and trust to luxury and gold.” They do belie thee, honest Pestilence! Thou'rt brave, magnanimous, not mean and dastard; Thou'lt not assert thy dread omnipotence In mastering those already overmaster'd By want and woe,—trampling the trampled crowd, To spare the unsparing, and preserve the proud. Usurpers of the people's rights! prepare For death by quick atonement.—Stony-hearted Oppressors of the poor!—in time beware! When the destroying angel's shaft is darted, 'Twill smite the star on titled bosoms set, The mitre pierce, transfix the coronet. Take moral physic, Pomp! not drugs and oil, And learn, to broad philanthropy a stranger, That every son of poverty and toil, With whom thou sharest now an equal danger, Should as a brother share, in happier hours, The blessings which our common Father showers. O thou reforming Cholera! thou'rt sent Not as a scourge alone, but as a teacher— That they who shall survive to mark the event Of thy dread summons, thou death-dealing preacher! By piety and love of kind may best Requite the love that snatch'd them from the Pest. THE RECANTATION. Young, saucy, shallow in my views, The world before me—free to choose My calling or profession, I canvass'd, one by one, the list, And thus, a tyro satirist, Condemn'd them in succession: The Law?—its sons cause half our ills, By plucking clients in their bills, As sparrowhawks do sparrows; Shrinking the mind it whets, their trade Acts as the grindstone on the blade, Which, while it sharpens, narrows. What makes the Pleader twist and tear Statutes to wrong the rightful heir, And bring the widow sorrow? A fee!—What makes him change his tack, Eat his own words, and swear white's black?— Another fee to-morrow.— A Curate?—chain'd to some dull spot, Even at church he mourns his lot, Repining while thanksgiving. 'Mid stupid clodpoles and their wives, The Scholar's buried while he lives, And dies without a living.— And what are Bishops?—hypocrites Who preach against the world's delights In purple and fine linen; Who brand as crime, in humbler elves, All vanities, while they themselves Have palaces to sin in.— A Soldier?—What! a bravo paid To make man-butchery a trade— A Jack-a-dandy varlet, Who sells his liberty,—perchance His very soul's inheritance— For feathers, lace, and scarlet! A Sailor?—worse! he's doomed to trace With treadmill drudgery the space From foremast to the mizen; A slave to the tyrannic main, Till some kind bullet comes to brain The brainless in his prison.— Physic?—a freak of times and modes, Which yearly old mistakes explodes For new ones still absurder: All slay their victims—disappear, And only leave this doctrine clear, That “killing is no murder.” A Poet?—To describe aright His lofty hopes and abject plight, The quickest tongue would lack words! Still like a ropemaker, he twines From morn to even lines on lines, And still keeps going backwards. Older and wiser grown, my strain Was changed, and thus did I arraign My crude and cynic sallies: Railer!—like most satiric scribes, Your world-condemning diatribes, Smack less of truth than malice.— Abuse condemns not use—all good Perverted or misunderstood, May generate all badness, Reason itself—that gift divine, To folly may be turn'd by wine, By long excess to madness. From the professions thus portray'd, As prone to stain, corrupt, degrade, Have sprung, for many ages, All that the world with pride regards, Our statesmen, patriots, heroes, bards, Philanthropists and sages. Not from our callings do we take Our characters:—men's actions make Or mar their reputations. The good, the bad, the false, the true, Would still be such, tho' all their crew Should interchange vocations. Whate'er the compass-box's hue, Substance, or form—the needle's true, Alike in calms or surges: E'en thus the virtuous heart, whate'er Its owner's plight or calling—ne'er From honour's pole diverges. DEATH. Fate! fortune! chance! whose blindness, Hostility or kindness, Play such strange freaks with human destinies, Contrasting poor and wealthy, The life-diseased and healthy, The bless'd, the curs'd, the witless, and the wise, Ye have a master—one Who mars what ye have done, Levelling all that move beneath the sun,— Death! Take courage ye that languish Beneath the withering anguish Of open wrong, or tyrannous deceit, There comes a swift redresser, To punish your oppressor, And lay him prostrate—helpless at your feet. O champion strong! Righter of wrong, Justice—equality to thee belong,— Death! Where conquest crowns his quarrel, And the victor, wreath'd with laurel, While trembling nations bow beneath his rod, On his guarded throne reposes, In living apotheosis, The Lord's anointed, and earth's demigod, What form of fear Croaks in his ear, “The victor's car is but a funeral bier.”— Death! Who—spite of guards and yeomen, Steel phalanx and cross-bowmen, Leaps at a bound the shudd'ring castle's moat, The tyrant's crown down dashes, His brandish'd sceptre smashes, With rattling fingers grasps him by the throat, His breath out-wrings, And his corpse down flings To the dark pit where grave-worms feed on kings?— Death! When the murderer's undetected, When the robber's unsuspected, And night has veil'd his crime from every eye; When nothing living daunts him, And no fear of justice haunts him, Who wakes his conscience-stricken agony? Who makes him start With his withering dart, And wrings the secret from his bursting heart?— Death! To those who pine in sorrow, Whose wretchedness can borrow No moment's ease from any human act, To the widow comfort-spurning, To the slave for freedom yearning, To the diseased with cureless anguish rack'd, Who brings release And whispers peace, And points to realms where pain and sorrow cease?— Death! THE POET AMONG THE TREES. Oak is the noblest tree that grows, Its leaves are Freedom's type and herald, If we may put our faith in those Of Literary-Fund Fitzgerald. Willow's a sentimental wood, And many sonneteers, to quicken 'em, A relic keep of that which stood Before Pope's Tusculum at Twickenham. The Birch-tree, with its pendent curves, Exciting many a sad reflection, Not only present praise deserves, But our posterior recollection. The Banyan, though unknown to us, Is sacred to the Eastern Magi; Some like the taste of Tityrus, “Recubans sub tegmine fagi.” Some like the Juniper—in gin; Some fancy that its berries droop, as Knowing a poison lurks within, More rank than that distill'd from th' Upas. But he who wants a useful word, To tag a line or point a moral, Will find there's none to be preferr'd To that inspiring tree—the Laurel. The hero-butchers of the sword, In Rome and Greece, and many a far land, Like Bravos, murder'd for reward, The settled price—a laurel-garland. On bust or coin we mark the wreath, Forgetful of its bloody story, How many myriads writhed in death, That one might bear this type of glory. Cæsar first wore the badge, 'tis said, 'Cause his bald sconce had nothing on it, Knocking some millions on the head, To get his own a leafy bonnet. Luckily for the Laurel's name, Profaned to purposes so frightful, 'Twas worn by nobler heirs of fame, All innocent, and some delightful. With its green leaves were victors crown'd In the Olympic games for running, Who wrestled best, or gallop'd round The Circus with most speed and cunning. Apollo, crown'd with Bays, gives laws To the Parnassian Empyrean; And every schoolboy knows the cause, Who ever dipp'd in Tooke's Pantheon. Daphne, like many another fair, To whom connubial ties are horrid, Fled from his arms, but left a rare Memento sprouting on his forehead. For Bays did ancient bards compete, Gather'd on Pindus or Parnassus, They by the leaf were paid, not sheet, And that's the reason they surpass us. One wreath thus twines the heads about, Whose brains have brighten'd all our sconces, And those who others' brains knock'd out, 'Cause they themselves were royal dunces. Men fight in these degenerate days, For crowns of gold, not laurel fillets; And bards who borrow fire from bays, Must have them in the grate for billets. Laureats we have (for cash and sack) Of all calibres and diameters, But 'stead of poetry, alack! They give us lachrymose Hexameters. And that illustrious leaf for which Folks wrote and wrestled, sang and bluster'd, Is now boil'd down to give a rich And dainty flavour to our custard! TO THE LADIES OF ENGLAND. Beauties!—(for, dress'd with so much taste, All may with such a term be graced,)— Attend the friendly stanza, Which deprecates the threaten'd change Of English modes for fashions strange, And French extravaganza. What! when her sons renown have won In arts and arms, and proudly shone A pattern to the nations, Shall England's recreant daughters kneel At Gallic shrines, and stoop to steal Fantastic innovations? Domestic—simple—chaste—sedate,— Your fashions now assimilate Your virtues and your duties:— With all the dignity of Rome, The Grecian Graces find a home In England's classic Beauties. When we behold so fit a shrine, We deem its inmate all divine, And thoughts licentious bridle; But if the case be tasteless, rude, Grotesque, and glaring—we conclude It holds some worthless idol. Let Gallia's nymphs of ardent mind, To every wild extreme inclined, In folly be consistent; Their failings let their modes express, From simpleness of soul and dress, For ever equi-distant. True to your staid and even port, Let mad extremes of every sort With steady scorn be treated; Nor by art's modish follies mar The sweetest, loveliest work by far That nature has completed:— For oh! if in the world's wide round One peerless object may be found, A something more than human; The faultless paragon confess'd May in one line be all express'd,— A well-dress'd English Woman. NIGHT-SONG. Written at Sea. Tis night—my Bark is on the Ocean, No sound I hear, no sight I see, Not e'en the darken'd waves whose motion Still bears me, Fanny, far from thee! But from the misty skies are gleaming Two smiling stars that look, my love! As if thine eyes, though veil'd, were beaming Benignly on me from above. Good night and bless thee, Fanny dearest! Nor let the sound disturb thy sleep, If, when the midnight wind thou hearest, Thy thoughts are on the distant deep:— Thy Lover there is safe and fearless, For Heaven still guards and guides my track. Nor can my dreaming heart be cheerless, For still to thee 'tis wafted back. 'Tis sweet on the benighted billow, To trust in Him whom all adore; 'Tis sweet to think that from her pillow Her prayers for me shall Fanny pour. The winds, self-lullabied, are dozing, The winking stars withdraw their light. Fanny! methinks thine eyes are closing— Bless thee, my love! good night, good night! THE SONG-VISION. Oh, warble not that fearful air! For sweet and sprightly though it be, It wakes in me a deep despair By its unhallow'd gaiety. It was the last my Fanny sung, The last enchanting playful strain, That breathed from that melodious tongue, Which none shall ever hear again. From Memory's fount what pleasures past At that one vocal summons flow; Bliss which I vainly thought would last— Bliss which but deepens present woe! Where art thou, Fanny! can the tomb Have chill'd that heart so fond and warm,— Have turn'd to dust that cheek of bloom— Those eyes of light—that angel form? Ah no! the grave resigns its prey: See, see! my Fanny's sitting there; While on the harp her fingers play A prelude to my favourite air. There is the smile which ever bless'd The gaze of mine enamour'd eye— The lips that I so oft have press'd In tribute for that melody. She moves them now to sing!—hark, hark! But ah! no voice delights mine ears: And now she fades in shadows dark;— Or am I blinded by my tears? Stay yet awhile, my Fanny, stay, Nor from these outstretch'd arms depart;— 'Tis gone! the vision's snatch'd away! I feel it by my breaking heart. Lady, forgive this burst of pain, That seeks a sad and short relief, In coining from a 'wilder'd brain A solace for impassion'd grief. But sing no more that fearful air, For sweet and sprightly though it be, It wakes in me a deep despair, By its unhallow'd gaiety. THE POET'S WINTER SONG TO HIS WIFE. The birds that sang so sweet in the summer skies are fled, And we trample 'neath our feet leaves that flutter'd o'er our head; The verdant fields of June wear a winding-sheet of white, The stream has lost its tune, and the glancing waves their light. We too, my faithful wife, feel our winter coming on, And our dreams of early life like the summer birds are gone; My head is silver'd o'er, while thine eyes their fire have lost, And thy voice, so sweet of yore, is enchain'd by age's frost. But the founts that live and shoot through the bosom of the earth, Still prepare each seed and root to give future flowers their birth; And we, my dearest Jane, spite of age's wintry blight, In our bosoms will retain Spring's florescence and delight. The seeds of love and lore that we planted in our youth, Shall develop more and more their attractiveness and truth; The springs beneath shall run, though the snows be on our head, For Love's declining sun shall with Friendship's rays be fed. Thus as happy as when young shall we both grow old, my wife, On one bough united hung of the fruitful Tree of Life; May we never disengage through each change of wind and weather, Till in ripeness of old age we both drop to earth together! SONG TO FANNY. Nature! thy fair and smiling face Has now a double power to bless, For 'tis the glass in which I trace My absent Fanny's loveliness. Her heav'nly eyes above me shine, The rose reflects her modest blush, She breathes in every eglantine, She sings in every warbling thrush. That her dear form alone I see Need not excite surprise in any, For Fanny's all the world to me, And all the world to me is Fanny. SONG TO FANNY. Thy bloom is soft, thine eyes are bright, And rose-buds are thy lips, my Fanny, Thy glossy hair is rich with light, Thy form unparagon'd by any; But thine is not the brief array Of charms which time is sure to borrow, Which accident may blight to-day, Or sickness undermine to-morrow. No—thine is that immortal grace Which ne'er shall pass from thy possession, That moral beauty of the face Which constitutes its sweet expression; This shall preserve thee what thou art, When age thy blooming tints has shaded, For while thy looks reflect thy heart, How can their charms be ever faded? Nor, Fanny, can a love like mine With time decay, in sickness falter; 'Tis like thy beauty—half divine, Born of the soul, and cannot alter: For when the body's mortal doom Our earthly pilgrimage shall sever, Our spirits shall their loves resume, United in the skies for ever. THE BIRTHDAY OF SPRING. Cry Holiday! Holiday! let us be gay, And share in the rapture of heaven and earth; For see! what a sunshiny joy they display, To welcome the Spring on the day of her birth; While the elements, gladly outpouring their voice, Nature's Pæan proclaim, and in chorus rejoice! Loud carols each rill as it leaps in its bed; The wind brings us music and balm from the south, And Earth in delight calls on Echo to spread The tidings of joy with her many-tongued mouth; O'er sea and o'er shore, over mountain and plain, Far, far does she trumpet the jubilee strain. Hark! hark to the cuckoo! its magical call Awakens the flowerets that slept in the dells; The snow-drop, the primrose, the hyacinth, all Attune at this summons their silvery bells. Hush! ting-a-ring-ting! don't you hear how they sing! They are pealing a fairy-like welcome to Spring. The love-thrilling hedge-birds are wild with delight; Like arrows loud whistling the swallows flit by; The rapturous lark, as he soars out of sight, Sends us sun-lighted melody down from the sky. In the air that they quaff, all the feathery throng Taste the spirit of Spring that out-bursts in a song. To me do the same vernal whisperings breathe In all that I scent, that I hear, that I meet, Without and within me, above and beneath, Every sense is imbued with a prophecy sweet Of the pomp and the pleasantness Earth shall assume When adorn'd, like a bride, in her flowery bloom. In this transport of nature each feeling takes part; I am thrilling with gratitude, reverence, joy; A new spring of youth seems to gush from my heart, And the man's metamorphosed again to a boy. Oh! let me run wild, as in earlier years; If my joy be suppress'd, I shall burst into tears. AN OLD MAN'S ASPIRATION. O glorious Sun! whose car sublime Unerring since the birth of time, In glad magnificence hath run its race;— O day's delight—God-painted sky, O moon and stars, whose galaxy Illuminates the night thro' all the realms of space. O poetry of forms and hues, Resplendent Earth! whose varied views In such harmonious beauty are combined;— And thou, O palpitating Sea, Who holdest this fair mystery In the wide circle of thy thrilling arms enshrined,— Hear me, Oh hear while I impart The deep conviction of my heart, That such a theatre august and grand, Whose author, actors, awful play, Are God, mankind, a judgment day, Was for some higher aim, some holier purpose plann'd. I will not, nay I cannot, deem This fair Creation's moral scheme, That seems so crude, mysterious, misapplied, Meant to conclude as it began, Unworthy the material plan With whose perfections rare its failures are allied. As in our individual fate, Our manhood and maturer date, Correct the faults and follies of our youth, So will the world, I fondly hope, With added years give fuller scope To the display and love of wisdom, justice, truth. 'Tis this that makes my feelings glow, My bosom thrill, my tears o'erflow, At any deed magnanimous—sublime; 'Tis this that re-assures my soul, When nations shun the forward goal, And retrograde awhile in ignorance and crime. Mine is no hopeless dream of some Impeccable Millennium, When saints and angels shall inhabit earth; But a conviction deep, intense, That man was meant by Providence Progressively to reach a higher moral worth. On this dear faith's sustaining truth Hath my soul brooded from its youth, As heaven's best gift, and earth's most cheering dower, Oh! may I still, in life's decline, Hold unimpair'd this creed benign, And mine old age attest its meliorating power! GIPSIES. Whether from India's burning plains, Or wild Bohemia's domains, Your steps were first directed; Or whether ye be Egypt's sons, Whose stream, like Nile's, for ever runs With sources undetected: Arabs of Europe! Gipsy race! Your Eastern manners, garb, and face Appear a strange chimera; None, none but you can now be styled Romantic, picturesque, and wild, In this prosaic era. Ye sole freebooters of the wood, Since Adam Bell and Robin Hood: Kept everywhere asunder From other tribes,—King, Church, and State Spurning, and only dedicate To freedom, sloth, and plunder; Your forest-camp,—the forms one sees Banditti-like amid the trees, The ragged donkeys grazing, The Sybil's eye prophetic, bright With flashes of the fitful light Beneath the caldron blazing,— O'er my young mind strange terrors threw: Thy History gave me, Moore Carew! A more exalted notion Of Gipsy life; nor can I yet Gaze on your tents, and quite forget My former deep emotion. For “auld lang syne” I'll not maltreat Yon pseudo-tinker, though the cheat, As sly as thievish Reynard, Instead of mending kettles, prowls, To make foul havoc of my fowls, And decimate my hen-yard. Come thou, too, black-eyed lass, and try That potent skill in palmistry, Which sixpences can wheedle; Mine is a friendly cottage—here No snarling mastiff need you fear, No Constable or Beadle. 'Tis yours, I know, to draw at will Upon futurity a bill, And Plutus to importune;— Discount the bill—take half yourself, Give me the balance of the pelf, And both may laugh at fortune. LIFE. There are who think this scene of life A frightful gladiatorial strife, A struggle for existence, Where class contends with class, and each Must plunder all within his reach, To earn his own subsistence. Shock'd at the internecine air Of this Arena, they forswear Its passions and its quarrels; They will not sacrifice, to live, All that to life its charms can give, Nor sell for bread their morals. Enthusiasts! check your reveries, Ye cannot always pluck at ease From Pleasure's cornucopia; Ye cannot alter Nature's plan, Change to a perfect being Man, Nor England to Utopia. Plunge in the busy current—stem The tide of errors ye condemn, And fill life's active uses; Begin reform yourselves, and live To prove that Honesty may thrive Unaided by abuses. TO A LADY. [On giving the writer a little bronze Cupid from Pompeii.] Thanks for thy little God of Love, Dug from Pompeii—whose fate 'tis, Henceforth to be install'd above My household Lares and Penates. Oh! could its lips of bronze unclose, How sad a tale might they recall! How thrill us with th' appalling woes Of the doom'd City's burial! Perchance, on that benighted day This tiny imp the table graced Of one whose mansion might display The choicest stores of classic taste. Of some one whose convivial board With all embellishments was deck'd, While her rich cabinets outpour'd A constant feast of Intellect.— Of one who, tho' she ne'er declined In social chat to bear a part, Loved more to fill her house and mind With letter'd lore, and varied art.— Of one who thus could give delight To guests of every mental hue, Whether unlearn'd or erudite,— Of one, in short, resembling You! To the dark tomb, thou Pagan Sprite! For many centuries consign'd, Thrice welcome to this world of light, Where worshippers thou still wilt find.— Methinks thy new abode is one Thou wilt not, Cupid! disapprove, For all my married life has run A lengthen'd course of constant love.— Prompt me, thou type of higher hope! To spread that love from me and mine, Until, in its ascending scope, It soar to social and divine.— So, little Elf! shalt thou be eyed With double favour by thine owner, Both as a tutelary guide, And a memorial of thy donor.— THE CHARMS OF LIFE. What hath life to charm us? Flowers Whose sweet lips have ever sung Carols from the fields and bowers, In perfume's universal tongue. Choral fairies bright and merry! Hark! I hear your silver bells, Chiming from the tufted dells A May-day welcome—hey down derry! Hark again! those jocund calls Are Echo's voice, who loves to mock The laughter of the waterfalls That leap for joy from rock to rock. And now the winds their organ ply, Tuned to the music of the birds, And rustling leaves and lowing herds, Oh! what a thrilling harmony! Joys there are of wider scope,— Our social and domestic ties, Faith, love, charity, and hope, With all their mingled ecstacies. And mental bliss that never cloys, But charms the head and thrills the heart; Life! how grand a boon thou art! Life! how sumless are thy joys! A HINT TO CYNICS. Youth, beauty, love, delight, All blessings bright and dear, Like shooting stars by night, Flash, fall, and disappear. Let Cynics doubt their worth, Because they're born to die, The wiser sons of earth Will snatch them ere they fly. Tho' mingled with alloy, We throw not gold away; Then why reject the joy That's blended with decay? MUSIC. Peace to the tenants of the tomb Whom oft we met in hall and bower, Peace to the buried friends with whom We shared the charm of music's hour; Tho' dead, they are not mute, for still Does memory wake some favour'd strain That makes our yearning bosoms thrill As if they lived and sang again. Health to the friends we still possess; Oh! long and often may we meet, Our yet remaining years to bless With Music's pleasures pure and sweet: And praises to the power divine That gave to man the precious boon, Which makes life's social evening shine As brightly as its morn and noon. THE BARD'S INSCRIPTION IN HIS DAUGHTER'S ALBUM. The thoughtful reader here may see A little world's epitome In turning each successive folio;— Names, drawings, music, poems, prose, From kindred and from friends compose This Album's multifarious olio. Its owner, from her circle wide Of friends, may here survey with pride A cherish'd tributary Cento; And when they're absent,—alter'd—dead— Each contribution will be read With double zest as a memento. Here with a smile will she recall The walk, the concert, or the ball, Shared with the young and merry-hearted;— And here, perchance, while brooding o'er The song of one who sings no more, A tear may drop for the departed. Yet—daughter dear! my heart foretells That thou wilt quit all other spells, Of friends, however loved,—and rather Hang o'er the page that thus records, With feelings ill express'd by words, The fervent blessing of a Father! STANZAS Written for the Bazaar of the National Anti-Corn-Law League, Covent Garden Theatre, 1845. Why with its ring has the connecting sea Married the Hemispheres and join'd their hands, Why has the Magnet's guiding ministry Made paths athwart the deep to distant lands? Why are the winds to our controul resign'd, Why does resistless steam our will obey, Why are all arts, all elements, combined To speed us o'er the ocean-world's highway? That from wide earth, and from the watery waste, Creation's sacred flag may be unfurl'd, Whereon the finger of the Lord hath traced Creation's law—“Free Trade with all the World!” Thus Nature,—her maternal hands untied, Shall scatter fresh supplies of wealth and food, And from each varied soil and clime provide Some separate blessing for the common good. So shall the sever'd races of mankind, Bidding all barriers and restrictions cease, By constant intercourse become combined In one vast family of love and peace. Let no man part whom God would thus unite! They who would speed this high and holy aim, Leagued in the cause of universal right, All factious ends, all party views disclaim. Their weapons, Faith, and Charity, and Hope, Justice and Truth the champions of their cause, Firmly but peacefully they seek to cope With selfish interests and mistaken laws. Ye who love man's advancement,—peace,—free trade, Ye who would blessings win from every land, Oh! give the liberating League your aid, And speed its course with zealous heart and hand! A HINT TO THE FARMERS. Farmers, whose income, day by day, Slides on the Sliding Scale away, Whatever its direction; When favour'd most still most forlorn, Starved by monopoly of Corn, And ruin'd by protection;— Farmers! who dying, seldom see One penny left for Charon's fee, When o'er the Styx ye're ferried, But in your landlord's pocket trace (Like Mecca to the Turks) the place Wherein your profit's buried— Farmers! who find in Cobden's breath, And Bright's harangues, a menaced death For all of yeoman station, And most appropriately brand The Corn-law Leaguers as a band Prone to ass—ass—ination:— When landlords cry, “We must be fed, “Go—grind your bones to make our bread, “From Earth more harvests ravish; “Study Liebig, ye clodpole elves! “Buy Guano—Soda—stint yourselves, “That we may still be lavish:”— Farmers! ye ought to patronise Whate'er improvements may arise To lessen your expenses, So hear my tale—there's little in't, 'Tis merely meant to give a hint For making cheap field fences. Queen Bess—I mean Elizabeth, Favour'd, as the historian saith, The handsome Earl of Leicester, To whom she made large grants of land, For which he doubtless kiss'd her hand, And duly thank'd and bless'd her. These lands were commons, on whose turf Many a cottager and serf Had fed his goose or donkey; And being dispossess'd, the crowd Began to murmur in a loud, I needn't add a wrong key. What cared his lordship! down he came, With carpenters to fence the same, And shut out clowns and cattle; Riding each morn the men to watch, So that no moment they might snatch For drink or tittle-tattle. One day, a peasant by his side Bow'd his grey-head and humbly cried, “I ax your lordship's pardon, “I've got a notion in my nob, “Whereby this here expensive job “Need hardly cost a farden.” “Not cost a farthing, doting clown!” Exclaim'd his lordship with a frown, Half angry and half comic;— “Braggart most vain and over free, “Think'st thou that I can learn from thee “A plan more economic?” “Yes,” quoth the rustic—“yes, my lord, “You needn't buy another board, “Or oaken plank or paling, “Think not my words are brags and boasts, “For if your lordship finds the posts, “The public will find railing!” DISAPPOINTMENT. Joy! joy! my lover's bark returns, I know her by her bearing brave: How gallantly the foam she spurns, And bounds in triumph o'er the wave! Why dost thou veil the glorious sight, In lurid rain, thou summer cloud? See! see! the lightning flashes bright! Hark! to the thunder long and loud! The storm is past—the skies are fair, But where's the bark?—there was but one:— Ha! she is yonder, shatter'd—bare,— She reels—she—sinks—O Heaven! she's gone! THE DYING POET'S FAREWELL. Animula vagula, blandula, Hospes comesque corporis, Quæ nunc abibis in loca? Adrian. O thou wondrous arch of azure, Sun, and starry plains immense! Glories that astound the gazer, By their dread magnificence! O thou ocean, whose commotion Awes the proudest to devotion! Must I—must I from ye fly, Bid ye all adieu—and die? O ye keen and gusty mountains, On whose top I braved the sky! O ye music-pouring fountains, On whose marge I loved to lie! O ye posies,—lilies, roses, All the charms that earth discloses! Must I—must I from ye fly, Bid ye all adieu—and die? O ye birds whose matin chorus Taught me to rejoice and bless! And ye herds, whose voice sonorous Swell'd the hymn of thankfulness! Learned leisure, and the pleasure Of the Muse, my dearest treasure; Must I—must I from ye fly, Bid ye all adieu—and die? O domestic ties endearing, Which still chain my soul to earth! O ye friends, whose converse cheering, Wing'd the hours with social mirth! Songs of gladness, chasing sadness, Wine's delight, without its madness; Must I—must I from ye fly, Bid ye all adieu—and die? Yes—I now fulfil the fiction— Of the swan that sings in death;— Earth, receive my benediction, Air, inhale my parting breath; Hills and valleys, forest alleys, Prompters of my muse's sallies, Fields of green and skies of blue, Take, oh! take my last adieu. Yet perhaps when all is ended, And the grave dissolves my frame, The elements from which 'twas blended May their several parts reclaim; Waters flowing, breezes blowing, Earth, and all upon it growing, Still may have my alter'd essence, Ever floating in their presence. While my disembodied spirit May to fields Elysian soar, And some lowest seat inherit Near the mighty bards of yore; Never, never to dissever, But to dwell in bliss for ever, Tuning an enthusiast lyre To that high and laurell'd quire. SONNETS. Eternal and Omnipotent Unseen! Who bad'st the world, with all its lives complete, Start from the void and thrill beneath thy feet, Thee I adore with reverence serene; Here, in the fields, thine own cathedral meet, Built by thyself, star-roof'd, and hung with green, Wherein all breathing things in concord sweet, Organ'd by winds, perpetual hymns repeat. Here hast thou spread that Book to every eye, Whose tongue and truth all, all may read and prove, On whose three blessed leaves—Earth, Ocean, Sky, Thine own right hand hath stamp'd might, justice, love; Grand Trinity, which binds in due degree, God, man, and brute, in social unity. MORNING. Beautiful Earth! O how can I refrain From falling down to worship thee? Behold, Over the misty mountains springs amain The glorious Sun; his flaming locks unfold Their gorgeous clusters, pouring o'er the plain Torrents of light. Hark! Chanticleer has toll'd His matin bell, and the lark's choral train Warble on high hosannas uncontroll'd. All nature worships thee, thou new-born day! Blade, flower, and leaf, their dewy offerings pay Upon the shrine of incense-breathing earth; Birds, flocks, and insects, chaunt their morning lay; Let me, too, join in the thanksgiving mirth, And praise, through thee, the God that gave thee birth. TO THE SETTING SUN. Thou central Eye of God, whose lidless ball Is vision all around, dispensing heat, And light and life, and regulating all With its pervading glance,—how calm and sweet Is thine unclouded setting! Thou dost greet, With parting smiles, the earth; night's shadows fall, But long where thou hast sunk shall splendours meet, And, lingering there, thy glories past recall. Oh! may my heart, like thee, unspotted, clear, Be as a sun to all within its sphere; And when beneath the earth I seek my doom, May I with smiling calmness disappear, And friendship's twilight, hovering o'er my tomb, Still bid my memory survive and bloom. ON THE STATUE OF A PIPING FAUN. Hark! hear'st thou not the pipe of Faunus, sweeping, In dulcet glee, through Thessaly's domain? Dost thou not see embower'd wood-nymphs peeping To watch the graces that around him reign; While distant vintagers, and peasants reaping, Stand in mute transport, listening to the strain; And Pan himself, beneath a pine-tree sleeping, Looks round, and smiles, and drops to sleep again? O happy Greece! while thy blest sons were rovers Through all the loveliness this earth discovers, They in their minds a brighter region founded, Haunted by gods and sylvans, nymphs and lovers, Where forms of grace through sunny landscapes bounded, By music and enchantment all surrounded. ON A GREEN-HOUSE. Here, from earth's dædal heights and dingles lowly, The representatives of Nature meet; Not like a Congress, or Alliance Holy Of Kings, to rivet chains, but with their sweet Blossomy mouths to preach the love complete, That with pearl'd misletoe, and beaded holly, Clothed them in green unchangeable, to greet Winter with smiles, and banish melancholy. I envy not th' Emathian madman's fame, Who won the world, and built immortal shame On tears and blood; but if some flower, new found, In its embalming cup might shroud my name, Mine were a tomb more worthily renown'd Than Cheops' pile, or Artemisia's mound. ON A STUPENDOUS LEG OF GRANITE, Discovered standing by itself in the Deserts of Egypt, with the Inscription inserted below. In Egypt's sandy silence, all alone, Stands a gigantic Leg, which far off throws The only shadow that the Desert knows. “I am great Ozymandias,” saith the stone, “The King of Kings; this mighty city shows “The wonders of my hand.” The city's gone! Nought but the leg remaining to disclose The site of that forgotten Babylon. We wonder, and some hunter may express Wonder like ours, when through the wilderness Where London stood, holding the wolf in chase, He meets some fragment huge, and stops to guess What wonderful, but unrecorded, race Once dwelt in that annihilated place. WRITTEN IN THE PORCH OF BINSTEAD CHURCH, ISLE OF WIGHT. Farewell, sweet Binstead! take a fond farewell From one unused to sight of woods and seas, Amid the strife of cities doom'd to dwell, Yet roused to ecstacy by scenes like these, Who could for ever sit beneath thy trees, Inhaling fragrance from the flowery dell; Or, listening to the murmur of the breeze, Gaze with delight on Ocean's awful swell. Again farewell! nor deem that I profane Thy sacred porch; for while the Sabbath strain May fail to turn the sinner from his ways, These are impressions none can feel in vain,— These are the wonders that perforce must raise The soul to God, in reverential praise. THE WORLD. Oh, what a palace rare hast thou created, Almighty Architect, for man's delight! With sun, and moon, and stars illuminated; Whose azure dome with pictured clouds is bright, Each painted by thy hand,—a glorious sight! Whose halls are countless landscapes, variegated, All carpeted with flowers; while all invite Each sense of man to be with pleasure sated. Fruits hang around us; music fills each beak; The fields are perfumed; and to eyes that seek For Nature's charms, what tears of joy will start. So let me thank thee, God, not with the reek Of sacrifice, but breathings pour'd apart, And the blood-offering of a grateful heart. TO A ROSE. Thou new-born Rose, emerging from the dew, Like Aphrodite, when the lovely bather Blush'd from the sea, how fair thou art to view, And fragrant to the smell! The Almighty Father Implanted thee, that men of every hue, Even a momentary joy might gather; And shall he save one people, and pursue Others to endless agony? O rather Let me believe in thee, thou holy Rose, Who dost alike thy lips of love unclose, Be thy abode by saint or savage trod. Thou art the priest whose sermons soothe our woes, Preaching, with nature's tongue, from every sod, Love to mankind, and confidence in God. ON AN ANCIENT LANCE, HANGING IN AN ARMOURY. Once in the breezy coppice didst thou dance, And nightingales amid thy foliage sang; Form'd by man's cruel art into a lance, Oft hast thou pierced, (the while the welkin rang With trump and drum, shoutings and battle clang,) Some foeman's heart. Pride, pomp, and circumstance, Have left thee, now, and thou dost silent hang, From age to age, in deep and dusty trance. What is thy change to ours? These gazing eyes, To earth reverting, may again arise In dust, to settle on the self-same space; Dust, which some offspring, yet unborn, who tries To poise thy weight, may with his hand efface, And with his moulder'd eyes again replace. THE NIGHTINGALE. Lone warbler! thy love-melting heart supplies The liquid music-fall, that from thy bill Gushes in such ecstatic rhapsodies, Drowning night's ear. Yet thine is but the skill Of loftier love, that hung up in the skies Those everlasting lamps, man's guide, until Morning return, and bade fresh flowers arise, Blooming by night, new fragrance to distil. Why are these blessings lavish'd from above On man, when his unconscious sense and sight Are closed in sleep; but that the few who rove, From want or woe, or travels urge by night, May still have perfumes, music, flowers, and light: So kind and watchful is celestial love! SUNSET. 'Tis sweet to sit beneath these walnut trees, And pore upon the sun in splendour sinking, And think upon the wond'rous mysteries Of this so lovely world, until, with thinking, Thought is bewilder'd, and the spirit, shrinking Into itself, no outward object sees, Still, from its inward fount, new visions drinking, Till the sense swims in dreamy reveries. Awaking from this trance, with gentle start, 'Tis sweeter still to feel th' o'erflowing heart Shoot its glad gushes to the thrilling cheek; To feel as if the yearning soul would dart Upwards to God, and by its flutters speak Homage, for which all language is too weak. END OF VOL. I.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">VOL. II. COMIC POEMS. THE ENGLISHMAN IN FRANCE. A Frenchman seeing, as he walk'd, A friend on t'other side the street, Cried “Hem!” exactly as there stalk'd An Englishman along the road; One of those Johnny Raws we meet In every sea-port town abroad, Prepared to take and give offence Partly, perhaps, because they speak About as much of French as Greek, And partly from the want of sense. The Briton thought this exclamation Meant some reflection on his nation, So bustling to the Frenchman's side, “Mounseer Jack Frog,” he fiercely cried, “Pourquoi vous dire ‘Hem!’ quand moi passe?” Eyeing the querist with his glass, The Gaul replied,—“Monsieur God-dem, Pourquoi vous passe quand moi dire ‘Hem?’”— THE CULPRIT AND THE JUDGE. The realm of France possess'd, in days of old, A thriving set of literati, Or men of letters, turning all to gold:— The standard works they made less weighty By new abridgments—took abundant Pains their roughnesses to polish, And plied their scissors to abolish The superficial and redundant. And yet, instead of fame and praise, Hogsheads of sack, and wreaths of bays, The law, in those benighted ages, By barbarous edicts did enjoin That they should cease their occupation, Terming these literary sages Clippers and filers of the coin; (Oh! what a monstrous profanation!) Nay, what was deeper to be dreaded, These worthies were, when caught, beheaded! But to the point. A story should Be like a coin—a head and tail, In a few words envelop'd. Good! I must not let the likeness fail.— A Gascon who had long pursued This trade of clipping, And filing the similitude Of good King Pepin, Was caught by the police, who found him With file and scissors in his hand And ounces of Pactolian sand Lying around him. The case admitting no denial, They hurried him forthwith to trial; When the Judge made a long oration, About the crime of profanation, And gave no respite for repentance, But instantly pronounced his sentence, “Decapitation!” “As to offending powers divine,” The culprit cried,—“be nothing said: Yours is a deeper guilt than mine. I took a portion from the head Of the king's image; you, oh fearful odds! Strike the whole head at once from God's!” SONNET TO MY OWN NOSE. O nose! thou rudder in my face's centre, Since I must follow thee until I die,— Since we are bound together by indenture, The master thou, and the apprentice I, O be to your Telemachus a Mentor, Though oft invisible, for ever nigh; Guard him from all disgrace and misadventure, From hostile tweak, or Love's blind mastery. So shalt thou quit the city's stench and smoke, For hawthorn lanes and copses of young oak, Scenting the gales of heaven that have not yet Lost their fresh fragrance, since the morning broke, And breath of flowers “with rosy may-dews wet,” The primrose, cowslip, blue-bell, violet. THE MILKMAID AND THE BANKER. A Milkmaid, with a very pretty face, Who lived at Acton, Had a black Cow, the ugliest in the place, A crooked-back'd one, A beast as dangerous, too, as she was frightful, Vicious and spiteful; And so confirm'd a truant, that she bounded Over the hedges daily, and got pounded: 'Twas all in vain to tie her with a tether, For then both Cow and cord eloped together. Arm'd with an oaken bough—(what folly! It should have been of thorn, or prickly holly,) Patty one day was driving home the beast, Which had, as usual, slipp'd its anchor, When on the road she met a certain Banker, Who stopp'd to give his eyes a feast, By gazing on her features crimson'd high By a long Cow-chase in July. “Are you from Acton, pretty lass?” he cried. “Yes”—with a curtsey she replied.— “Why, then you know the laundress, Sally Wrench?”— “Yes, she's my cousin, Sir, and next-door neighbour.” “That's lucky—I've a message for the wench, Which needs dispatch, and you may save my labour. Give her this kiss, my dear, and say I sent it: But mind, you owe me one—I've only lent it.”— “She shall know,” cried the girl, as she brandish'd her bough, “Of the loving intentions you bore me; But since you're in haste for the kiss, you'll allow, That you'd better run forward and give it my Cow, For she, at the rate she is scampering now, Will reach Acton some minutes before me.” THE FARMER'S WIFE AND THE GASCON. At Neufchâtel, in France, where they prepare Cheeses that set us longing to be Mites, There dwelt a farmer's wife, famed for her rare Skill in these small quadrangular delights.— Where they were made, they sold for the immense Price of three sous a-piece; But as salt water made their charms increase, In England the fix'd rate was eighteen-pence. This damsel had to help her in the farm, To milk her cows, and feed her hogs, A Gascon peasant, with a sturdy arm For digging, or for carrying logs; But in his noddle weak as any baby, In fact a gaby, And such a glutton when you came to feed him, That Wantley's dragon, who “ate barns and churches, As if they were geese and turkeys,” (Vide the Ballad,) scarcely could exceed him. One morn she had prepared a monstrous bowl Of cream, like nectar, And wouldn't go to Church (good careful soul!) Till she had left it safe with a protector; So she gave strict injunctions to the Gascon To watch it while his mistress was to mass gone.— Watch it he did—he never took his eyes off, But lick'd his upper, then his under lip, And doubled up his fist to drive the flies off, Begrudging them the smallest sip, Which if they got, Like my Lord Salisbury, he heaved a sigh, And cried,—“O happy, happy fly, How I do envy you your lot!” Each moment did his appetite grow stronger; His bowels yearn'd; At length he could not bear it any longer, But on all sides his looks he turn'd, And finding that the coast was clear, he quaff'd The whole up at a draught.— Scudding from church, the farmer's wife Flew to the dairy; But stood aghast, and could not, for her life One sentence utter, Until she summon'd breath enough to mutter, “Holy St. Mary!” And shortly, with a face of scarlet, The vixen (for she was a vixen) flew Upon the varlet, Asking the when, and where, and how, and who Had gulp'd her cream, nor left an atom; To which he gave not separate replies, But with a look of excellent digestion, One answer made to every question, “The Flies!” “The flies, you rogue! the flies, you guzzling dog! Behold your whiskers still are covered thickly; Thief,—liar,—villain,—gormandizer,—hog! I'll make you tell another story quickly.” So out she bounced, and brought, with loud alarms, Two stout Gens-d'armes, Who bore him to the judge,—a little prig, With angry bottle nose Like a red cabbage rose, While lots of white ones flourished on his wig.— Looking at once both stern and wise, He turn'd to the delinquent, And 'gan to question him and catechise As to which way the drink went: Still the same dogged answers rise, “The flies, my Lord—the flies, the flies!” “Psha!” quoth the judge, half peevish and half pompous, “Why, you're non compos. You should have watch'd the bowl as she desired, And kill'd the flies, you stupid clown.” “What, is it lawful then,” the dolt enquired, “To kill the flies in this here town?”— “The man's an ass! a pretty question this! Lawful, you booby? to be sure it is.— You've my authority, whene'er you meet 'em To kill the rogues, and if you like it, eat 'em.” “Zooks!” cried the rustic, “I'm right glad to hear it. Constable, catch that thief! may I go hang If yonder blue-bottle, (I know his face,) Isn't the very leader of the gang That stole the cream, let me come near it!” This said, he started from his place, And aiming one of his sledge-hammer blows At a large fly upon the Judge's nose, The luckless blue-bottle he smash'd, And gratified a double grudge, For the same catapult completely smash'd The bottle-nose belonging to the Judge! THE AUCTIONEER AND THE LAWYER. A City Auctioneer, one Samuel Stubbs, Did greater execution with his hammer, Assisted by his puffing clamour, Than Gog and Magog with their clubs, Or that great Fee-fa-fum of War, The Scandinavian Thor, Did with his mallet, which (see Bryant's Mythology,) fell'd stoutest giants;— For Samuel knock'd down houses, churches, And woods of oak, and elms, and birches, With greater ease than mad Orlando Tore the first tree he set his hand to.— He ought in reason to have raised his own Lot by knocking others' down. And had he been content with shaking His hammer and his hand, and taking Advantage of what brought him grist, he Might have been as rich as Christie;— But somehow when thy midnight bell, Bow, Sounded along Cheapside its knell, Our spark was busy in Pall-Mall Shaking his elbow;— Marking, with paw upon his mazzard, The turns of hazard; Or rattling in a box the dice, Which seem'd as if a grudge they bore To Stubbs: for often in a trice, Down on the nail he was compell'd to pay All that his hammer brought him in the day, And sometimes more. Thus like a male Penelope, our wight What he had done by day undid by night: No wonder, therefore, if like her He was beset by clamorous brutes, Who crowded round him to prefer Their several suits. One Mr. Snipps, the tailor, had the longest Bill for many suits—of raiment, And naturally thought he had the strongest Claim for payment. But debts of honour must be paid, Whate'er becomes of debts of trade; And so our stylish auctioneer, From month to month throughout the year, Excuses, falsehoods, pleas, alleges; Or flatteries, compliments, and pledges, When in the latter mood one day, He squeezed his hand, and swore to pay.— “But when?” “Next month, you may depend on't, My dearest Snipps, before the end on't;— Your face proclaims, in every feature, You wouldn't harm a fellow creature,— You're a kind soul, I know you are, Snipps.”— “Ay, so you said six months ago; But such fine words, I'd have you know, Butter no parsnips.” This said, he bade his lawyer draw A special writ, Serve it on Stubbs, and follow it Up with the utmost rigour of the law. This lawyer was a friend of Stubbs; That is to say In a civic way, Where business interposes not its rubs; For where the main chance is in question, Damon leaves Pythias to the stake, Pylades and Orestes break, And Alexander cuts Hephæstion; But when our man of law must sue his friends, Tenfold politeness made amends. So when he meets our Auctioneer, Into his outstretch'd hand he thrust his Writ, and said with friendly leer, “My dear, dear Stubbs, pray do me justice; In this affair I hope you see No censure can attach to me— Don't entertain a wrong impression; I'm doing now what must be done In my profession.”— “And so am I,” Stubbs answer'd with a frown; So crying, “Going—going—going—gone!” He knock'd him down. THE GOUTY MERCHANT AND THE STRANGER. In Broad Street Buildings, on a winter night, Snug by his parlour fire a gouty wight Sat all alone, with one hand rubbing His leg wrapp'd up in fleecy hose, While t'other held beneath his nose The Public Ledger, in whose columns grubbing, He noted all the sales of hops, Ships, shops, and slops, Gums, galls, and groceries, ginger, gin, Tar, tallow, turmeric, turpentine, and tin; When lo! a decent personage in black Enter'd, and most politely said,— “Your footman, Sir, has gone his nightly track, To the King's Head, And left your door ajar, which I Observed in passing by, And thought it neighbourly to give you notice.” “Ten thousand thanks! how very few get, In time of danger, Such kind attentions from a stranger! Assuredly that fellow's throat is Doom'd to a final drop at Newgate, He knows too, the unconscionable elf! That there 's no soul at home except myself.” “Indeed!” replied the stranger, looking grave; “Then he's a double knave. “He knows that rogues and thieves by scores “Nightly beset unguarded doors; “And see how easily might one “Of these domestic foes, “Even beneath your very nose, “Perform his knavish tricks, “Enter your room as I have done, “Blow out your candles,—thus and thus, “Pocket your silver candlesticks,— “And walk off—thus!” So said, so done—he made no more remark; Nor waited for replies, But march'd off with his prize, Leaving the gouty merchant in the dark. THE FAT ACTOR AND THE RUSTIC. Cardinal Wolsey was a man Of an unbounded stomach, Shakespeare says: Meaning, (in metaphor,) for ever puffing To swell beyond his size and span; But had he seen a player of our days Enacting Falstaff without stuffing, He would have own'd that Wolsey's bulk ideal Equall'd not that within the bounds This actor's belt surrounds, Which is, moreover, all alive and real.— This player, when the Peace enabled shoals Of our odd fishes To visit every clime between the poles, Swam with the stream, a histrionic Kraken: Although his wishes Must not in this proceeding be mistaken, For he went out professionally bent To see how money might be made, not spent.— In this most laudable employ He found himself at Lille one afternoon; And that he might the breeze enjoy, And catch a peep at the ascending moon, Out of the town he took a stroll, Refreshing in the fields his soul With sight of streams, and trees, and snowy fleeces, And thoughts of crowded houses and new pieces.— When we are pleasantly employ'd, time flies;— He counted up his profits, in the skies, Until the moon began to shine, On which he gazed awhile, and then, Pull'd out his watch, and cried—“Past nine! Why, zounds, they shut the gates at ten!” Backwards he turn'd his steps instanter, Stumping along with might and main, And though 'tis plain He couldn't gallop, trot, or canter, (Those who had seen it would confess it,) he March'd well for one of such obesity. Eyeing his watch, and now his forehead mopping, He puff'd and blew along the road, Afraid of melting, more afraid of stopping; When in his path he met a clown, Returning from the town.— “Tell me,” he panted in a thawing state, “Dost think I can get in, friend, at the gate?” “Get in?” replied the hesitating loon, Measuring with his eye our bulky wight: “Why yes, Sir, I should think you might— “A load of hay got in this afternoon!” THE BANK CLERK AND THE STABLE KEEPERS Showing how Peter was undone By taking care of Number One.— Of Peter Prim (so Johnson would have written,) Let me indulge in the remembrance;—Peter! Thy formal phiz has oft my fancy smitten, For sure the Bank had never a completer Quiz among its thousand clerks, Than he who now elicits our remarks.— Prim was a formalist, a prig, A solemn fop, an office Martinet, One of those small precisians who look big If half an hour before their time they get To an appointment, and abuse those elves Who are not over-punctual like themselves. If you should mark his powder'd head betimes, And polish'd shoes in Lothbury, You knew the hour—for the three-quarters' chimes Invariably struck as he went by; From morning fines he always saved his gammon, Not from his hate of sloth, but love of Mammon. For Peter had a special eye To Number One—his charity At home beginning, ne'er extends, But where it started had its end too; And as to lending cash to friends, Luckily he had none to lend to.— No purchases so cheap as his, While no one's bargains went so far, And though in dress a deadly quiz, No Quaker more particular. This live automaton, who seem'd To move by clockwork, ever keen To live upon the saving plan, Had soon the honour to be deem'd That selfish, heartless, cold machine, Call'd in the City—a warm man. A Bank Director once, who dwelt at Chigwell, Prim to a turtle-feast invited, And as the reader knows the prig well, I need not say he went, delighted; For great men, when they let you slice their meat, May give a slice of loan—a richer treat. No stage leaves Chigwell after eight, Which was too early to come back, So, after much debate, Peter resolved to hire a hack; The more inclined to this, because he knew In London Wall, at Number Two, An economic stable-keeper, From whom he hoped to get one cheaper. Behold him mounted on his jade, A perfect Johnny Gilpin figure; But the good bargain he had made Compensating for sneer and snigger, He trotted on—arrived—sat down, Devour'd enough for six or seven, His horse remounted, and reach'd town As he had fix'd, exactly at eleven. But whether habit led him, or the Fates To give a preference to Number One, (As he had always done,) Or that the darkness jumbled the two gates, Certain it is he gave that bell a drag, Instead of Number Two, Rode in,—dismounted—left his nag, And homeward hurried without more ado. Some days elapsed, and no one came To bring the bill, or payment claim; He 'gan to hope 'twas overlook'd, Forgotten quite, or never book'd,— An error which the honesty of Prim Would ne'er have rectified, if left to him. After six weeks, however, comes a pair Of groom-like looking men, Each with a bill, which Peter they submit to; One for the six weeks' hire of a bay mare, And one for six weeks' keep of ditto: Together—twenty-two pounds ten! The tale got wind. What! Peter make a blunder? There was no end of joke, and quiz, and wonder, Which, with the loss of cash, so mortified Prim, that he suffered an attack Of bile, and bargain'd with a quack, Who daily swore to cure him—till he died; When, as no will was found, His scraped, and saved, and hoarded store, Went to a man to whom, some months before, He had refused to lend a pound! PIRON, AND THE JUDGE OF THE POLICE. Piron, a Poet of the Gallic nation, Who beat all waggish rivals hollow, Was apt to draw his inspiration Rather from Bacchus than Apollo. His hostess was his deity, His Hippocrene was eau-de-vie; And though 'tis said That poets live not till they die, When living he was often dead,— That is to say, dead drunk.—“While I,” Quoth Piron, “Am by all upbraided With drunkenness, the vilest, worst, Most base, detestable, degraded, Of sins that ever man repented, None of you blames this cursed thirst With which I'm constantly tormented.— Worse than a cholic or a phthisic, E'en now it gripes me so severely, That I must fly to calm it, merely Swallowing brandy as a physic.” To cure this unrelenting fever He pour'd such doses through his lips, he Was shortly what the French call ivre, Anglicè—tipsy; And while the midnight bell was pealing Its solemn tolling, Our Bacchanal was homeward reeling, Tumbling and rolling, Until at last he made a stop, Suffering his noddle, which he could not keep Upright, upon the ground to drop, And in two minutes was asleep, Fast as a top. Round came the guard, and seeing him extended Across the gutter, Incompetent to move or utter, They thought at first his days were ended; But finding that he was not dead, Having lost nothing but his head, They popp'd him on a horse's back, Just like a sack, And shot him on the guard-house floor, To let him terminate his snore. Next morning when our tippling bard Had got his senses, They brought a coach into the yard, And drove him off to answer his offences, Before the Judge of the Police, Who made a mighty fuss and clamour; But, like some Justices of peace, Who know as much of law as grammar, Was an egregious ninny-hammer. “Well, fellow,” cried the magistrate, “What have you got to say for boozing, Then lying in the streets and snoozing All night in that indecent state?”— “Sir,” quoth the culprit to the man of law, “It was a frost last night in town, And tired of tripping, sliding, and slipping, Methought I might as well lie down, And wait until there came a thaw.” “Pooh! nonsense! psha! Imprisonment must be the lot Of such a vagabond and sot. But, tell me, fellow, what's your name?” “Piron.”—“The dramatist?”—“The same.” “Ah, well, well, well, Monsieur Piron, Pray take your hat and quit the court, For wags like you must have their sport; But recollect, when you are gone, You'll owe me one, and thus I shew it: I have a brother who's a poet, And lives as you do, by his wits.” Quoth Piron, “that can never pass, For I've a brother who's an ass, So we are quits.” THE FARMER AND THE COUNSELLOR. A counsel in the Common Pleas, Who was esteem'd a mighty wit, Upon the strength of a chance hit Amid a thousand flippancies, And his occasional bad jokes In bullying, bantering, browbeating, Ridiculing, and maltreating Women, or other timid folks, In a late cause resolved to hoax A clownish Yorkshire farmer—one Who, by his uncouth look and gait, Appear'd expressly meant by Fate For being quizz'd and played upon: So having tipp'd the wink to those, In the back rows, Who kept their laughter bottled down, Until our wag should draw the cork, He smiled jocosely on the clown, And went to work.— “Well, Farmer Numscull, how go calves at York?” “Why—not, Sir, as they do wi' you, But on four legs, instead of two.” “Officer!” cried the legal elf, Piqued at the laugh against himself, “Do pray keep silence down below there. Now look at me, clown, and attend; Have I not seen you somewhere, friend?” “Yees—very like—I often go there.” “Our rustic's waggish—quite laconic,” The counsel cried, with grin sardonic; “I wish I'd known this prodigy, This genius of the clods, when I On circuit was at York residing. Now, Farmer, do for once speak true— Mind, you're on oath, so tell me, you, Who doubtless think yourself so clever, Are there as many fools as ever In the West Riding?” “Why—no, Sir, no; we've got our share, But not so many as when you were there!” THE COLLEGIAN AND THE PORTER. At Trin. Coll. Cam.—which means, in proper spelling, Trinity College, Cambridge, there resided One Harry Dashington,—a youth excelling In all the learning commonly provided For those who choose that classic station For finishing their education: That is, he understood computing The odds at any race or match; Was a dead hand at pigeon-shooting; Could kick up rows, knock down the watch— Play truant and the rake at random— Drink—tie cravats—and drive a tandem. Remonstrance, fine, and rustication, So far from working reformation, Seem'd but to make his lapses greater, Till he was warn'd that next offence Would have this certain consequence— Expulsion from his Alma Mater. One need not be a necromancer To guess that, with so wild a wight, The next offence occurr'd next night, When our incurable came rolling Home as the midnight chimes were tolling, And rung the College bell.—No answer. The second peal was vain—the third Made the street echo its alarum; When to his great delight he heard The sordid Janitor, old Ben, Rousing and growling in his den. “Who's there?—I s'pose young Harum Scarum.” “'Tis I, my worthy Ben, 'tis Harry.” “Ay, so I thought—and there you'll tarry. 'Tis past the hour—the gates are closed, You know my orders; I shall lose My place if I undo the door.” “And I (young Hopeful interposed) “Shall be expelled if you refuse; So prythee”—Ben began to snore. “I'm wet,” cried Harry, “to the skin; Hip! hallo! Ben!—don't be a ninny; Beneath the gate I've thrust a guinea, So tumble out and let me in.”— “Humph!” growled the greedy old curmudgeon, Half overjoy'd and half in dudgeon, “Now, you may pass, but make no fuss, On tiptoe walk, and hold your prate.” “Look on the stones, old Cerberus,” Cried Harry as he pass'd the gate, “I've dropp'd a shilling,—take the light, You'll find it just outside;—good night.” Behold the porter in his shirt, Cursing the rain which never stopp'd, Groping and raking in the dirt, And all without success; but that Is hardly to be wondered at, Because no shilling had been dropp'd; So he gave o'er the search at last, Regain'd the door and found it fast! With sundry oaths, and growls, and groans, He rang once, twice, and thrice; and then, Mingled with giggling, heard the tones Of Harry, mimicking old Ben. “Who's there?—'Tis really a disgrace To ring so loud.—I've lock'd the gate— I know my duty—'tis too late, You wouldn't have me lose my place?” “Psha! Mr. Dashington: remember, This is the middle of November, I'm stripp'd, 'tis raining cats and dogs.” “Hush, hush!” quoth Hal, “I'm fast asleep;” And then he snored as loud and deep As a whole company of hogs: “But, harkye, Ben, I'll grant admittance At the same rate I paid myself.” “Nay, master, leave me half the pittance,” Replied the avaricious elf. “No: all or none—a full acquittance: The terms, I know, are somewhat high; But you have fix'd the price, not I,— I won't take less, I can't afford it.” So, finding all his haggling vain, Ben, with an oath and groan of pain, Drew out the guinea, and restored it. “Surely you'll give me,” growled th' outwitted Porter, when again admitted, “Something, now you've done your joking, For all this trouble, time, and soaking.” “Oh surely, surely,” Harry said; “Since, as you urge, I broke your rest, And you're half drown'd, and quite undress'd, I'll give you—leave to go to bed!” THE MAYOR OF MIROBLAIS. While he was laying plans for getting The honours of the Chapeau rouge, The Cardinal Dubois was ever fretting; All his days and nights allotting To bribes and schemes, intriguing, plotting, Until his face grew yellow as gamboge, His eyes sepulchral, dull, and gummy, And his whole frame a walking mummy.— Meanwhile his steward, De la Vigne, Seem'd to be fattening on his master, For, as the one grew lank and lean, The other only thrived the faster, Enjoying, as he swell'd in figure, Such constant spirits, laugh and snigger, That it e'en struck his Excellency, Who call'd him up, and ask'd him whence he Contrived to get so plump and jolly, While he himself, a man of rank, Visibly shrank, And daily grew more melancholy.— “Really, my lord,” the steward said, “There's nothing marvellous in that; “You have a hat for ever in your head, “My head is always in my hat.” Dubois, too wealthy to be marr'd in all His plots, was presently a Cardinal, And wore what he had pined to win; When pasquinades soon flew about, Hinting his sconce was deeper red without, Than 'twas within.— Perhaps it was, but that's no matter, The Pope, like any other hatter, Makes coverings, not heads; and this With its new guest agreed so well, That he soon wore an alter'd phiz: Ate heartily, began to swell, Recover'd from his ails and ills, And grew quite rosy in the gills. 'Tis strange, but true, our worthy wore Fine robes, and wax'd both plump and fresh, From the first moment he forswore All pomps and appetites of flesh.— His Eminence, on this inflation Both of his stomach and his station, His old Château resolved to visit, Accompanied by one Dupin, A sandy-headed little man, Who daily managed to elicit Jokes from some French Joe Miller's page, Old, and but little of their age; Though they drew forth as never-failing A roar of laughter every time, As if they were as new and prime As those which we are now retailing! To the Château in Languedoc; Whole deputations From the surrounding districts flock, With odes, addresses, gratulations, And long orations; And amongst others, the Préfet Of Miroblais, Famed for its annual Fair of Asses, Began a speech which, by its dull Exordium, threaten'd to be full As long and dry as fifty masses. Dupin, who saw his yawning master Somewhat annoy'd by this disaster, And thought it might be acceptable To quiz the bore, and stop his gabble, Abruptly cried—“Pray, Mr. Mayor, How much did asses fetch, last Fair?” “Why, Sir,” the worthy Mayor replied, As the impertinent he eyed— “Small sandy ones, like you, might each Sell for three crowns, and plenty too:” Then quietly resumed his speech, And mouth'd it regularly through. RABELAIS AND THE LAMPREYS. When the eccentric Rabelais was physician To Cardinal Lorraine, he sat at dinner Beside that gormandizing sinner; Not like the medical magician Who whisk'd from Sancho Panza's fauces The evanescent meats and sauces, But to protect his sacred master Against such diet as obstructs The action of the epigastre, O'erloads the biliary ducts, The peristaltic motion crosses, And puzzles the digestive process. The Cardinal, one hungry day, First having with his eyes consumed Some lampreys that before him fumed, Had plunged his fork into the prey, When Rabelais gravely shook his head, Tapp'd on his plate three times and said— “Pah!—hard digestion! hard digestion!” And his bile-dreading Eminence, Though sorely tempted, had the sense To send it off without a question.— “Hip! Hallo! bring the lampreys here!” Cried Rabelais, as the dish he snatch'd; And gobbling up the dainty cheer, The whole was instantly dispatch'd. Redden'd with vain attempts at stifling At once his wrath and appetite, His patron cried, “Your conduct's rude, This is no subject, Sir, for trifling; How dare you designate this food As indigestible and crude, Then swallow it before my sight?” Quoth Rabelais, “It may soon be shown That I don't merit this rebuff: I tapp'd the plate, and that you'll own, Is indigestible enough; But as to this unlucky fish, With you so strangely out of favour, Not only 'tis a wholesome dish, But one of most delicious flavour!” THE BITER BIT. Jack Dobson, honest son of tillage, The Toby Philpot of his village, Laugh'd and grew fat, Time's gorgon visage braving; To hear him cackle at a hoax, Or new edition of old jokes, You'd think a Roman Capitol was saving. Not Boniface, when at a mug Of ale he gave a hearty tug, Was fuller of his subject-matter; And Dobson had a better plea For boasting of its pedigree; For his was brew'd at home, and he Was infinitely fatter. One cask he had better and stronger Than all the rest—brew'd at a christening; To pass it set his eyes a glistening; In short he couldn't tarry longer, But seizing spiggot and a faucet, He tapp'd it—quaff'd a luscious posset— Then, like a hospitable fellow, Sent for his friends to make them mellow.— Among them he invited one Call'd Tibbs, a simple-minded wight, Whom waggish Dobson took delight To make the subject of his fun: For Nature such few brains had put In neighbour Tibbs's occiput, That all the rustic wags and wits Found him a most convenient butt For their good hits; Though sometimes, as both great and small aver, He gave them Roland for their Oliver. The guests all met, and dinner spread, Dobson first tipp'd the wink, then said, “Well, now, my lads, we'll all draw lots, To settle which of us shall go Into the cellarage below, To fill the pots.” So saying, he adroitly wriggled The shortest into Tibbs's paw, Whereat the others hugely giggled, And Tibbs, obedient to the law, Went down, the beverage to draw. Now, Farmer Dobson, wicked wag! Over the cellar door had slung A water-bowl, so slily hung, That whoso gave the door a drag, Was sure to shower down at once A quart of liquid on his sconce. Our host and all his brother wits, Soon as they heard their victim's tramp, Who look'd half-drown'd, burst into fits, Which in fresh peals of laughter flamed, When Tibbs in drawling tone, exclaim'd: “Isn't your cellar rather damp?” Grace being said, quick havoc follow'd; Many good things were said and swallow'd;— Joking, laughing, stuffing, and quaffing, For a full hour they push'd about The cans, and when there came a pause, From mere exhaustion of their jaws, Tibbs with his nasal twang drawl'd out— “Suppose we now draw lots again, Which of us shall go down to put The spiggot back into the butt.” “Why, zounds!” the farmer roar'd amain— “The spiggot back! come, come, you're funning, You haven't left the liquor running?” “I did as I was ordered, Jack,” Quoth Tibbs;—“and if it was intention'd That I should put the spiggot back, 'Tis a great pity 'twasn't mention'd:— You've lost a cask of precious stuff, But I, for one, have drunk enough.” “Ass! numskull! fool!” the farmer cried,— “What can one get, confound their souls! By asking such half-witted lubbers?”— “This lesson, neighbour,” Tibbs replied,— “That those who choose to play at bowls Must expect rubbers!” THE PARSON AT FAULT. A country parson took a notion Into his head, one Whitsuntide, That it was more like true devotion To preach extempore;—he tried: Succeeded once—twice—thrice—but, lo! His fourth discourse was not forthcoming; Spite of his hawing and his humming, Not a word further could he go; So that the worthy man perforce Was fain to leave them in the lurch, And say, that, since he came to church, He'd lost the thread of his discourse. Whereat a man below exclaim'd, “Lock the doors, beadle! search us round, All, every one, until it's found: The thief should really be ashamed.— Here are my pockets—ransack both! I have it not, I'll take my oath.” BLINDMAN'S BUFF. Three wags, (whom some fastidious carpers Might rather designate three sharpers,) Enter'd, at York, the Cat and Fiddle, And finding that the host was out On business for two hours or more, While Sam, the rustic waiter, wore The visage of a simple lout, Whom they might safely try to diddle, They order'd dinner in a canter— Cold or hot, it matter'd not, Provided it were served instanter; And as the heat had made them very Dry and dusty in their throttles, They bade the waiter bring three bottles Of prime old port, and one of sherry.— Sam ran with ardour to the larder, Then to the kitchen; And, as he briskly went to work, he Drew from the spit a roasting turkey, With sausages embellish'd, which in A trice upon the board was spread, Together with a nice cold brisket, Nor did he even obliviscate Half a pig's head. To these succeeded puddings, pies, Custards and jellies, All doom'd to fall a sacrifice To their insatiable bellies; As if, like camels, they intended To stuff into their monstrous craws Enough to satisfy their maws, Until their pilgrimage was ended. Talking, laughing, eating, and quaffing, The bottles stood no moment still; They rallied Sam with joke and banter, And, as they drain'd the last decanter, Call'd for the bill.— 'Twas brought,—when one of them who eyed And added up the items, cried, “Extremely moderate indeed! I'll make a point to recommend This inn to every travelling friend; And you, Sam, shall be doubly fee'd.” This said, a weighty purse he drew, When his companion interposed,— “Nay, Harry, that will never do, Pray let your purse again be closed; You paid all charges yesterday, 'Tis clearly now my turn to pay.” Harry however, wouldn't listen To any such insulting offer, His generous eyes appear to glisten Indignant at the very proffer; And though his friend talk'd loud, his clangour Served but to aggravate Hal's anger. “My worthy fellow,” cried the third, “Now really this is too absurd; What! do both of ye forget I haven't paid a farthing yet? Am I eternally to cram At your expense? 'tis childish quite; I claim this payment as my right— Here—how much is the money, Sam?” To this most rational proposal The others gave such fierce negation, One might have fancied they were foes all, So hot became the altercation, Each in his purse his money rattling, Insisting, arguing, and battling. One of them cried at last—“A truce!— This point we will no longer moot; Wrangling for trifles is no use, And thus we'll finish the dispute.— That we may settle what we three owe, We'll blindfold Sam, and whichsoe'er He catches of us first, shall bear The whole expenses of the trio, With half-a-crown (if that's enough,) To Sam for playing Blindman's Buff.” Sam liked it hugely—thought the ransom, For a good game of fun was handsome; Gave his own handkerchief beside, To have his eyes securely tied, And soon began to grope and search; When the three knaves, I needn't say, Adroitly left him in the lurch, Slipp'd down the stairs, and stole away. Poor Sam continued hard at work;— Now o'er a chair he gets a fall; Now floundering forwards with a jerk, He bobs his nose against the wall; And now encouraged by a subtle Fancy, that they're near the door, He jumps behind it to explore, And breaks his shins against the scuttle.— Crying, at each disaster—“Drat it! Dang it! 'od rabbit it! and rat it!”— Just in this crisis of his doom, The host, returning, sought the room; And Sam no sooner heard his tread, Than, pouncing on him like a bruin, He almost shook him into ruin, And with a shout of laughter said— “By gom, I've cotch'd thee now, so down With cash for all, and my half crown!”— Off went the bandage, and his eyes Seem'd to be goggling o'er his forehead, While his mouth widen'd with a horrid Look of agonised surprise. “Gull!” roar'd his master, “Gudgeon! dunce! Fool as you are, you're right for once, 'Tis clear that I must pay the sum;— But this one thought my wrath assuages— That every halfpenny shall come Out of your wages!” THE POET AND THE ALCHEMIST. Authors of modern date are wealthy fellows;— 'Tis but to snip his locks and follow Now the golden-hair'd Apollo. Invoking Plutus to blow up the bellows Of inspiration, they distil The rhymes and novels which cajole us, Not from the Heliconian rill But from the waters of Pactolus. Before this golden age of writers, A Grub-street Garreteer existed, One of the regular inditers Of odes and poems to be twisted Into encomiastic verses, For patrons who have heavy purses. Besides the Bellman's rhymes, he had Others to let, both gay and sad, All ticketed from A to Izzard; And living by his wits, I need not add, The rogue was lean as any lizard. Like a rope-maker's were his ways, For still one line upon another He spun, and, like his hempen brother, Kept going backwards all his days. Hard by his attic lived a Chemist, Or Alchemist, who had a mighty Faith in the Elixir Vitæ; And though unflatter'd by the dimmest Glimpses of success, kept groping And grubbing in his dark vocation, Stupidly hoping To find the art of changing metals, And guineas coin from pots and kettles, By mystery of transmutation. Our starving poet took occasion To seek this conjuror's abode; Not with encomiastic ode, Or laudatory dedication, But with an offer to impart, For twenty pounds the secret art, Which should procure, without the pain Of metals, chemistry, and fire, What he so long had sought in vain, And gratify his heart's desire. The money paid, our bard was hurried To the philosopher's sanctorum, Who, somewhat sublimized and flurried Out of his chemical decorum, Crow'd, caper'd, giggled, seem'd to spurn his Crucibles, retort, and furnace, And cried as he secured the door, And carefully put to the shutter, “Now, now, the secret I implore; For God's sake speak, discover, utter!” With grave and solemn air the Poet Cried—“List—oh, list! for thus I show it:— Let this plain truth those ingrates strike, Who still, though bless'd, new blessings crave, That we may all have what we like, Simply by liking what we have!” THE ASTRONOMICAL ALDERMAN. The pedant or scholastikos became The butt of all the Grecian jokes;— With us, poor Paddy bears the blame Of blunders made by other folks; Though we have certain civic sages Term'd Aldermen, who perpetrate Bulls as legitimate and great, As any that the classic pages Of old Hierocles can show, Or Mr. Miller's, commonly called Joe.— One of these turtle-eating men, Not much excelling in his spelling, When ridicule he meant to brave, Said he was more ph. than n. Meaning thereby, more phool than nave. Though they who knew our cunning Thraso, Pronounced it flattery to say so. His Civic brethren to express His “double, double, toil and trouble,” And bustling noisy emptiness, Had christen'd him Sir Hubble Bubble. This wight ventripotent was dining Once at the Grocers' Hall, and lining With calipee and calipash That tomb omnivorous—his paunch, Then on the haunch Inflicting many a horrid gash, When having swallow'd six or seven Pounds, he fell into a mood Of such supreme beatitude, That it reminded him of Heaven, And he began with mighty bonhomie To talk Astronomy.— “Sir,” he exclaim'd, between his bumpers, “Copernicus and Tycho Brahe, And all those chaps, have had their day; They've written monstrous lies, Sir, thumpers!— Move round the sun?—it's talking treason; The earth stands still—it stands to reason.— Round as a globe? stuff—humbug—fable! It's a flat sphere, like this here table, And the sun overhangs this sphere, Ay—just like that there chandelier.” “But,” quoth his neighbour, “when the sun From East to West his course has run, How comes it that he shows his face Next morning in his former place?” “Ho! there's a pretty question, truly!” Replied our wight, with an unruly Burst of laughter and delight, So much his triumph seem'd to please him; “Why blockhead! he goes back at night, And that's the reason no one sees him!” SOUTH-DOWN MUTTON. If men, when in a rage, inspected Before a glass their angry features, Most likely they would stand corrected At sight of such distorted creatures; So we may hold a moral mirror Before these myrmidons of passion, And make ill temper see its error, By gravely mimicking its fashion. A sober Cit of Sweeting's Alley, Deem'd a warm man on 'Change, was what In temper might be reckoned hot, Indulging many an angry sally Against his wife and servants:—(this Is no unprecedented state For man and wife, when, tête-à-tête, They revel in domestic bliss,)— But to show off his freaks before his Guests, was contra bonos mores. Our Cit was somewhat of a glutton, Or epicure, at least in mutton; Esteeming it a more delicious Feast, than those of old Apicius, Crassus' savoury symposia, Or even Jupiter's ambrosia. One day a leg arrived from Brighton, A true South Down legitimate, When he enlarged with much delight on The fat and grain, and shape and weight; Pronounced on each a learned stricture, Declared the joint a perfect picture, And as his eye its outline follow'd, Call'd it a prize—a lucky hit— A gem—a pearl more exquisite Than ever Cleopatra swallow'd; Promulging finally, this fiat— “I'll dine at five, and ask Jack Wyatt.” The cover raised, the meat he eyed With new enjoyment—next the cloth he Tuck'd in his button-hole, and cried, “Done to a tittle—brown and frothy!” Then seized the carving-knife, elate, But lo! it would not penetrate The skin—(the anatomic term is The what-d'-ye-call?—ay—epidermis.) He felt the edge—'twas like a dump; Whereat with passion-crimson'd frown, He reach'd the stair-head at a jump, And threw the blade in fury down, Venting unnumber'd curses on His thoughtless lazy servant—John. His guest, observing this disclosure Of temper, threw with great composure The dish, with mutton, spoons and all, Down helter-skelter to the hall, Where it arrived with fearful clatter. “Zounds!” cried the Cit,—“why, what's the matter?” “Nothing whatever,” with a quiet Look and accent, answer'd Wyatt: “I hope I haven't unawares Made a mistake; but when you threw The knife below, in such a stew, I thought you meant to dine down stairs!” EVENING; AN ELEGY. By a Poetical Carman. Apollo now, Sol's carman, drives his stud Home to the mews that's seated in the West, And Customs' clerks, like him, through Thames Street mud, Now westering wend, in Holland trowsers dress'd. So from the stands the empty carts are dragg'd, The horses homeward to their stables go, And mine, with hauling heavy hogsheads fagg'd, Prepare to taste the luxury of—“Wo!” Now from the slaughter-houses cattle roar, Knowing that with the morn their lives they yields, And Mr. Sweetman's gig is at the door, To take him to his house in Hackney Fields. Closed are the gates of the West India Docks, Rums, Sugars, Coffee, find at length repose, And I, with other careless carmen, flocks To the King's Head, the Chequers, or the Rose. They smoke a pipe—the shepherd's pipe I wakes, Then skittles pleases—me the Muse invites, They in their ignorance to drinking takes, I, bless'd with learning, takes a pen and writes. PATENT BROWN STOUT. A Brewer, in a country town. Had got a monstrous reputation; No other beer but his went down;— The hosts of the surrounding station Engraved his name upon their mugs, And painted it on every shutter; And though some envious folks would utter Hints, that its flavour came from drugs, Others maintain'd 'twas no such matter, But owing to his monstrous vat, At least as corpulent as that At Heidelberg—and some said fatter. His foreman was a lusty Black, An honest fellow; But one who had an ugly knack Of tasting samples as he brew'd, Till he was stupified and mellow. One day, in this top-heavy mood, Having to cross the vat aforesaid, (Just then with boiling beer supplied,) O'ercome with giddiness and qualms, he Reel'd—fell in—and nothing more said, But in his favourite liquor died, Like Clarence in his butt of Malmsey. In all directions round about The Negro absentee was sought; But as no human noddle thought That our fat Black was now Brown Stout, They settled that the rogue had left The place for debt, or crime, or theft. Meanwhile the beer was, day by day, Drawn into casks and sent away, Until the lees flow'd thick and thicker; When lo! outstretch'd upon the ground, Once more their missing friend they found, As they had often done—in liquor. “See!” cried his moralizing master, “I always knew the fellow drank hard, And prophesied some sad disaster; His fate should other tipplers strike: Poor Mungo! there he welters, like A toast at bottom of a tankard!” Next morn a publican, whose tap Had help'd to drain the vat so dry, Not having heard of the mishap, Came to demand a fresh supply, Protesting loudly that the last All previous specimens surpass'd, Possessing a much richer gusto Than formerly it ever used to, And begging, as a special favour, Some more of the exact same flavour.— “Zounds!” cried the Brewer, “that's a task More difficult to grant than ask:— Most gladly would I give the smack Of the last beer to the ensuing, But where am I to find a Black, And boil him down at every brewing?” YORK KIDNEY POTATOES. One Farmer Giles, an honest clown From Peterborough, had occasion To travel up to London town, About the death of a relation, And wrote, his purpose to explain, To cousin Jos. in Martin's lane; Who quickly sent him such an answer, as Might best determine him to dwell At the Blue Boar—the Cross—the Bell, Or some one of the caravanseras To which the various coaches went— All which, he said, were excellent. Quoth Giles, “I think it rather odd he Should write me thus, when I have read That London hosts will steal at dead Of night, to stab you in your bed, Pocket your purse, and sell your body; To 'scape from which unpleasant process, I'll drive at once to cousin Jos.'s.” Now cousin Jos. (whose name was Spriggs) Was one of those punctilious prigs Who reverence the comme il faut; Who deem it criminal to vary From modes prescribed, and thus “Monstrari Pretereuntium digito.” Conceive him writhing down the Strand With a live rustic in his hand, At once the gaper and gapee; And pity his unhappy plight, Condemn'd when, tête-à-tête, at night To talk of hogs, nor deem it right To show his horrible ennui. Jos. was of learned notoriety, One of the male Blue-stocking clan, Was register'd of each Society, Royal and Antiquarian; Took in the Scientific Journal, And wrote for Mr. Urban's Mag. (For fear its liveliness should flag,) A thermometrical diurnal, With statements of old tombs and churches, And such unreadable researches. Wearied to death, one Thursday night, With hearing our agrarian wight Prose about crops, and farms and dairies, Spriggs cried—“A truce to corn and hay,— Somerset House is no great way, We'll go and see the Antiquaries.”— “And what are they?” inquired his guest:— “Why, Sir,” said Jos., somewhat distress'd To answer his interrogator,— “They are a sort—a sort—a kind Of commentators upon Nature.”— “What, common 'tatoes!” Giles rejoin'd, His fist upon the table dashing: “Take my advice—don't purchase one, Not even at a groat a ton,— None but York kidneys does for mashing.” THE HANDKERCHIEF. A Judge of the Police, and Spy, (For both are joined in Eastern nations,) Prowling about with purpose sly, To list to people's conversations, And pry in every corner cupboard, According to his dirty calling, Saw a poor woman passing by, Who wept and blubber'd, Like a church spout, when rain is falling, Which strives in vain to vent and utter The overflowings of the gutter. Our magistrate thought fit to greet her, Insisting on the dame's declaring What caused this monstrous ululation, When she averr'd her spouse had beat her Black and blue, beyond all bearing, Without the smallest provocation. To work the Judge's pen and ink went, Taking the rogue's address and trade, And the next morning the delinquent Was duly into court convey'd: When he asserted, that his wife Was such an advocate of strife, That she would raise a mighty clangour, And put herself into a pucker, For trifles that surpass'd belief; And, for the recent cause of anger, He swore, point blank, that he had struck her With nothing but his handkerchief. The judge, convinced by this averment, Dismiss'd the case without a word; When in the court there rose a ferment, And the wife's angry voice was heard:— “To cheat your worship is too bad! My lord, my lord! do interpose, And stop the knave where'er he lingers; The villain! he forgot to add That he for ever blows his nose With his own fingers!” THE JESTER CONDEMNED TO DEATH. One of the Kings of Scanderoon, A royal jester, Had in his train a gross buffoon, Who used to pester The court with tricks inopportune, Venting on the highest folks his Scurvy pleasantries and hoaxes. It needs some sense to play the fool; Which wholesome rule Occurr'd not to our jackanapes, Who consequently found his freaks Lead to innumerable scrapes, And quite as many kicks and tweaks, Which only seem'd to make him faster Try the patience of his master. Some sin at last, beyond all measure, Incurr'd the desperate displeasure Of his serene and raging highness: Whether the wag had twitch'd his beard, Which he was bound to have revered, Or had intruded on the shyness Of the seraglio, or let fly An epigram at royalty, None knows—his sin was an occult one; But records tell us that the sultan, Meaning to terrify the knave, Exclaim'd—“'Tis time to stop that breath; Thy doom is seal'd;—presumptuous slave! Thou stand'st condemn'd to certain death. Silence, base rebel!—no replying!— But such is my indulgence still, That, of my own free grace and will, I leave to thee the mode of dying.” “Thy royal will be done—'tis just,” Replied the wretch, and kiss'd the dust; “Since, my last moments to assuage, Your majesty's humane decree Has deign'd to leave the choice to me, I'll die, so please you, of old age.” LAUS ATRAMENTI, Or the Praise of Blacking. A New Song. Our Sires were such pedagogue blockheads of yore, That they sent us to college instruction to seek, Where we bother'd our brains with pedantical lore, Law, Logic, and Algebra, Latin and Greek; But now, wiser grown, leaving learning alone, And resolving to shine by a light of our own, Our cares we transfer from the head to the foot, Leave the brain to be muddied, and polish the boot. On the banks of the Isis, ye classical fools, Who with Lycophron's crabbedness puzzle your ear, And ye who learn logarithmetical rules At Cambridge, from tables of Baron Napier, Renounce Aristotle, and take to the bottle That wears “Patent Blacking” inscribed on its throttle; For Napier and Greek are by few understood, While all can decide when your blacking is good. When a gentleman dubb'd by the wight of the brush, Which has set up your foot in Corinthian style, For the rest of your wardrobe you care not a rush, Secure of the public's distinguishing smile. Though your dress may be dusty, and musty and fusty, You're whitewash'd by blacking, and cannot be rusty;— Such errors as these are but venial and small, People look at your boot, which atones for them all. And ye who are struggling your fortune to make By the brief or the bolus, law, commerce, or trade, Your pitiful schemes of ambition forsake, And be makers of blacking, by taunts undismay'd; For what is auguster than giving a lustre To those who without you would hardly pass muster, And by selling your “brilliant and beautiful jet,” A name and a fortune together to get?— Day and Martin now laugh as they ride in their coach, Till they're black in the face as their customers' boots; Warren swears that his blacking's beyond all approach, Which Turner's advertisement plumply refutes; They hector and huff, print, publish, and puff, And write in the papers ridiculous stuff, While Hunt, who was blacken'd by all, and run down, Takes a thriving revenge as he blackens the town. Their labels belibel each other—each wall With the feuds of these rivals in blacking is white; But the high polish'd town seems to patronise all, And the parties get rich in each other's despite; For my own part, I think I shall mix up my ink, In a bottle with lamp-black and beer to the brink, And set up at once for a shiner of shoes, Since I never shall shine by the aid of the muse. THE TWO BRACELETS. A Farmer General, one Monsieur B?, Who dwelt in France when Louis held the throne, Lived like a prince from every trouble free, Except a wife,—(th' exception's large, I own) For she was fat as any marchioness, And given to extravagance in dress.— One day she bought a pair of bracelets—such As few but royal damsels would bespeak; They cost—I cannot recollect how much, But they were quite magnificent—unique,— And having clasp'd them on, away she flies Off to the Opera to show her prize. It happen'd that the Queen was there that night, Just opposite the box that Madame took, And on the bracelets with intense delight Frequently look'd—or else appear'd to look; For she took special care to have them seen, As if on purpose to outvie the Queen. Soon to the box door came a Page, attired In the Queen's proper livery, all in style, And in the name of Majesty required One of the bracelets for a little while, That by her eye she might the pattern take, And order some of the exact same make. Off went the sparkling bauble in a trice, While her rouged cheeks with exultation burn, As, bowing to the Royal party thrice, She patiently awaited its return; But when the Queen retired, and none was sent, Our dame began to wonder what it meant.— A Lord in waiting soon confirm'd her fears: “Oh, that pretended Page I've often seen,— A noted sharper—has been such for years. Madame, you're robb'd,—he came not from the Queen; I knew the rogue, and should have had him taken, But that he slipp'd away, and saved his bacon.” Boiling with anger, Madame called her coach, And drove to the Bureau de la Justice, Where, with loud tongue, and many a keen reproach, About the shameful state of the police, She call'd upon the Provost for relief, And bade him send his men to catch the thief. Early next morn she heard the knocker's din; Her heart beat high, with expectation big, When lo! the Provost's Clerk was usher'd in,— A formal consequential little prig, Who, with a mighty magisterial air, Hemm'd, and began his errand to declare:— “Madame, a man is brought to our bureau, On whom was found a bracelet of great cost, And we are all anxiety to know Whether or not it is the one you lost; Wherefore I'll take the other, if you please, Just to compare, and see if it agrees.” “Dear Sir, I'm overjoy'd,—'tis mine, I'm sure; Such a police as ours how few can boast! Here, take the bracelet,—keep the rogue secure, I'll follow you in half an hour at most; Ten thousand thanks—I hope you'll trounce the spark— Open the door, there, for the Provost's Clerk!” Oh! how she chuckled as she drove along, Settling what pangs the pilferer should feel: No punishment appear'd to her too strong, E'en should the wretch be broken on the wheel; For what infliction could be reckon'd cruel, To one who would purloin so rich a jewel? Arrived at the bureau, her joy finds vent: “Well, Mr. Provost, where's the guilty knave? The other bracelet by your clerk I sent, Doubtless it matches with the one you have; Why, then, outstretch your mouth with such surprise, And goggle on me thus with all your eyes?” “La! bless me, Ma'am, you're finely hoax'd—good lack! I sent no clerk, no thief have we found out, And the important little prig in black Was the accomplice of the Page no doubt;— Methinks the rascals might have left you one, But both your bracelets now are fairly gone!” MARSHAL SAXE AND HIS PHYSICIAN. Fever's a most audacious varlet:— Now in a general's face he shakes His all-defying fist, and makes His visage like his jacket—scarlet; Now o'er surrounding guards he throws A summerset, and never squeaks “An' please your Majesty,” but tweaks The Lord's anointed by the nose. With his inflammatory finger, (Much like the heater of an urn) He makes the pulses boil and burn, Puts fur upon the tongue, (not ermine,) And leaves his prey to die or linger, Just as the doctors may determine. Though this disorder sometimes seems Mild and benignant, It interferes so with our schemes, Imparting to our heads a dizziness, Just when we want them clear for business, That it may well be termed malignant. Of these inopportune attacks, One fiercely fell on Marshal Saxe, Just as his troops had open'd trenches Before a fortress; (what a pity!) Not only did it make his heart ache To be condemn'd to pill, cathartic, Bolus and blister, drugs and drenches, But shock'd his military notions, To make him take unwish'd-for potions, Instead of taking, as he wish'd,—the city. Senac, however, his physician, Soon gave our invalid permission To be coach'd out an easy distance, First stipulating one condition,— That whatsoe'er the when and where, The Doctor should be then and there, Lest any syncope, relapse, Or other unforeseen mishaps, Should call for medical assistance. Saxe gives consent with all his heart, Orders the carriage in a minute, Whispers the coachman—mounts within it, Senac the same, and off they start, Joking, smiling, time beguiling, In a facetious tête-à-tête.— The subject of their mutual chatter is Nothing to us;—enough to state That Marshal Saxe at length got out To reconnoitre a redoubt, Projecting from a range of batteries. Left in the carriage, our physician By no means relish'd his position, When he discover'd they had got Nearly within half cannon shot; Wherefore he bawl'd, with fear half melted, “For God's sake move me from this spot!— Doubtless they've noticed our approach, And, when they recognize your coach, Shan't I be fired at, pepper'd, pelted, (When I can neither fly nor hide) From some of yonder bristling masses?” “It's not unlikely,” Saxe replied; “And war I know is not your trade, So if you feel the least afraid, Pull up the glasses!” STANZAS TO PUNCHINELLO. Thou lignum-vitæ Roscius, who Dost the old vagrant stage renew, Peerless, inimitable, Punchinello! The Queen of smiles is quite out-done By thee, all-glorious king of fun, Thou grinning, giggling, laugh-extorting fellow! At other times mine ear is wrung Whene'er I hear the trumpet's tongue, Waking associations melancholic; But that which heralds thee recalls All childhood's joys and festivals, And makes the heart rebound with freak and frolic. Ere of thy face I get a snatch, Oh! with what boyish glee I catch Thy twittering, cackling, bubbling, squeaking gibber— Sweeter than syren voices—fraught With richer merriment than aught That drops from witling mouths, though utter'd glibber. What way was ever known before To keep the circle in a roar, Nor wound the feelings of a single hearer! Engrossing all the jibes and jokes, Unenvied by the duller folks, A harmless wit—an unmalignant jeerer. The upturn'd eyes I love to trace Of wondering mortals, when their face Is all alive with an expectant gladness: To mark the flickering giggle first, The growing grin—the sudden burst, And universal shout of merry madness. I love those sounds to analyse, From childhood's shrill ecstatic cries, To age's chuckle with its coughing after; To see the grave and the genteel Rein in awhile the mirth they feel, Then loose their muscles, and let out the laughter. Sometimes I note a henpeck'd wight Enjoying thy marital might, To him a beatific beau idéal; He counts each crack on Judy's pate, Then homeward creeps to cogitate The difference 'twixt dramatic wives and real. But, Punch, thou'rt ungallant and rude, In plying thy persuasive wood; Remember that thy cudgel's girth is fuller Than that compassionate, thumb-thick, Established wife-compelling stick, Made legal by the dictum of Judge Buller. When the officious doctor hies To cure thy spouse, there's no surprise; Thou should'st receive him with nose-tweaking grappling; Nor can we wonder that the mob Encores each crack upon his nob, When thou art feeing him with oaken sapling. As for our common enemy, Old Nick, we all rejoice to see The coup de grace that silences his wrangle; But, lo! Jack Ketch!—ah, welladay! Dramatic justice claims its prey, And thou in hempen handkerchief must dangle. Now helpless hang those arms which once Rattled such music on the sconce; Hush'd is that tongue which late out-jested Yorick; That hunch behind is shrugg'd no more, No longer heaves that paunch before, Which wagg'd with such a pleasantry plethorick. But Thespian deaths are transient woes, And still less durable are those Suffer'd by lignum-vitæ malefactors; Thou wilt return, alert, alive, And long, oh long may'st thou survive, First of head-breaking and side-splitting actors! THE HURRICANE AND THE MENACE. Verdant St. Kitt's! thou art indeed a gem, “A precious stone set in the silver sea,” An emerald in Neptune's diadem, An island formed in Nature's poetry; And yet thou art unsung by son or stranger, Save a few passing lines by Doctor Grainger. In his poem of the “Sugar Cane.” The vale of Tempe,—Plato's fabled isle, Hesperian gardens, Enna's classic plain, All, all must yield to that Arcadian smile That thou, in thy unparagon'd domain, Palmy St. Christopher's, the sweetest, fairest Of earthly Paradises, ever wearest.— Wild and romantic are thy breezy mountains, Forth from whose sides, with cane plantations clad, Leap here and there perennial rills and fountains, Making the landscape all so green and glad, That nymphs and sylvans through thy bowers might ramble, And Nereids in thy glassy waters gambol. Contentment with his lot I ne'er could trace In any Negro, save a single soul, And he, poor fellow,—which explains the case— Was a good-humour'd, grinning, brainless droll, Whose nickname, Silly Bingo, presupposes That he was not a Solomon or Moses. Bingo, whose fortune never made him grumble, The banshaw ('tis a rude guitar) could twang, And after work was fain to sing, dance, tumble, As the mere butt of every Negro gang; And yet this seeming simple-witted donkey, In pilfering was as subtle as a monkey. One Mr. Jackson was the overseer Of the estate where Bingo was employ'd; Nor could St. Christopher's produce his peer, For he was honest to the Planter, void Of all oppression, hated whips, loved pardons, And had a taste for rural shades and gardens. Palm Villa, his abode, was sweetly placed Between the sloping mountains and the ocean; An avenue of noble palm-trees graced Its front; while, singing to its own commotion, A stream throughout the shady grounds meander'd, Diffusing coolness wheresoe'er it wander'd. The mansion's rear was shaded by a screen Of lofty tamarinds and cassias sweet; On either side were fragrant gardens seen, Where melons, sabbacas, and citrons meet, Limes, lemons, guavas, sappadillas mellow, The green anana, and the shaddock yellow. Hence, when refreshen'd by the moist Aurora, Incense and balm were wafted all around, And in all seasons, unexhausted Flora Broider'd with richest tapestry the ground; While the gilt humming-bird and cooing turtle Perch'd on each hedge of acassee and myrtle. Nature, however, loves to strike a balance; And he who once has known the venom'd bite Of fierce mosquitoes, felt the land-crab's talons, Or found cockroaches in his bed at night, Knows to his sorrow that the land they breed in Is not by any means a curseless Eden. Here in an arbour I had found a seat Of privet with carnation shrubs entwined, Yielding a fragrant shelter from the heat And persecuting flies of every kind, When divers simultaneous signs accruing, Proved that an elemental war was brewing. The warn'd mosquitoes left the sunny light, The speckled lizards to their holes withdrew, Cockroaches crawled abroad, a loathsome sight! And land-crabs crept from every slope in view; While doves and pigeons, on the roofs collected, Up to the sky their anxious looks directed. A suffocating heat oppress'd the air, Still'd were the lightest feathers of the palm, The sky was coppery, and a blood-red glare Shot from the misty sun;—portentous calm! When Nature's self appears to faint and sicken, And wail her doom, aghast and horror-stricken. The fear-fraught waves came panting to the shore, Usher'd by flocks of scared and screaming birds; While, as they wildly eyed the clouds, a roar Loud-bellowing burst from the bewilder'd herds; And the mazed horse, with sudden fear transported, Snuffing the tainted air, stood still and snorted. To covert fled the Negroes, 'mid the cry Of wailing dogs: at which absorbing hour Did Silly Bingo, judging none would spy His depredations, steal upon my bower, Thinking no doubt that he had found a famous Season for plund'ring the contiguous yam-house. The dog that guarded it had lately died,— Poison'd perhaps, but that was not in proof;— But still the Black with much misgiving eyed The precincts, keeping carefully aloof, Then crouching on as stealthily as Reynard, When he is stealing to attack a hen-yard. Reaching the place, he fill'd his bag, and back The rogue retreated with his shoulder'd prize, Peering with fearful joy around his track, Showing his teeth, and rolling his large eyes,— Just like some great baboon, who, undiscover'd, Steals with his plunder to the nearest covert. The bag within a tangled brake he dropp'd, Then back to his companions would have fled; But suddenly, as if transfix'd, he stopp'd, Scared by the skies so menacing and dread: For now a low'ring hurricane impended, That woe and horror to the isle portended. Up from the westward heaves a mass of clouds, Climbing successively the mountain tips, Which rapidly the whole horizon shrouds In lurid gloom, and fulgurous eclipse; While the dark ridges, as they take position, Seem batteries for the island's demolition. Crash! burst the whole artillery of thunder, Concentrating its force in one explosion, As it would rive the rooted earth asunder, Split the sky's vault, and overturn the ocean; Fierce leap'd the lightning forth, as if with savage Triumph it came, the world to blast and ravage. The prison'd winds break loose, like Furies dire, Rattling their chains, and roaring all amain; Heaven's flood-gates open, water leagues with fire; It might be thought the frantic hurricane, As in its fangs the shrieking isle it seizes, Would shake and tear it in ten thousand pieces. All is confusion, terror, havoc, flight— Plantations, houses, to the ground are hurl'd, The welkin yells with tumult and affright; Huts, canes, and shrubs, aloft in air are twirl'd; And cattle, madden'd with dismay and wonder, Wildly rebellow to the roaring thunder. The stream that lately held its gentle course, Swoll'n to a torrent, devastates the plain, Seizing and sweeping with resistless force, Men, trees, and oxen to the troubled main, Whose shores are strew'd with vessels wreck'd and broken, Of the storm's ravages a dismal token. Tost in the raging waves, mine eye explored One lab'ring ship, whose terror-stricken crew Had cut away her masts, and overboard Into the yawning deep her cargo threw; Though still the sea did but the fiercer wrestle, To swallow up the doom'd and shatter'd vessel. Meanwhile, my looks I did not long withdraw From Silly Bingo, the purloining Black, Whose face depictured, as he heard and saw The dire destruction and the thunder-crack, A rapid change and struggle of sensations, Emblazon'd by the flashing coruscations. Thinking at first that Jackson had let fly This hurricane, the robber to disquiet, He seem'd indignant, and I heard him cry— “Gog! here's a hurly burly and a riot About a bag o' yams, not more dan twenty!— Why for you grumble, Massa? you got plenty.” But when the sulph'rous bolt above his head Shatter'd the cedar-tree 'neath which he stood, Terror possess'd him, and he humbly said, With eyes upturn'd in supplicating mood, “Please Massa cloud, no more make such a clatter! Bingo gib back de yams,—dat end de matter.” Off to the brake reluctantly he stole, The plunder'd bag upon his shoulders took, Crept to the store-house, and replaced the whole, Returning past me with the scowling look Of hungry beasts, when they have been molested, And had their booty from their clutches wrested. Clenching his fist as he the house drew near, This parting menace he pronounced aloud: “Now you remember, Massa Oberseer, Next time you send a great black nassy cloud, Out of his wits to frighten Silly Bingo, I'll throw a stone at it,—I will, by jingo!” THE PLEASANT TETE-A-TETE. The Isle of Saint Eustatia, which the Dutch First colonized, was govern'd long ago— (I mean mis-govern'd)—by the Herr Van Gutch, As great a rogue as one would wish to know, Who should, instead of ruling at Eustatia, Have shared a convict's fate in Australasia. No excellency could the knave pretend to, Save in his title, which the folks about him Lavish'd upon him as an innuendo, Ironically meant to mock and flout him; For he had proved himself in every case Sordid, corrupt, extortionate, and base. Lord Bacon urged that when in bribes he did err, Justice, but not injustice, he had sold; Van Gutch sold either to the highest bidder: So that each criminal possess'd of gold Became, of course, more daring and more harden'd, Knowing beforehand that he should be pardon'd. Our governor was in fact an island Pope, (But not, I ween, Pope Innocent or Pius,) Selling indulgences that gave full scope To him who foster'd any lawless bias, To sear his conscience, so that nought should shock it, By purchased absolutions in his pocket. As he sat waiting for this odious traffic, Ready for hire to pardon or condemn, Smoking his pipe in vacancy seraphic, 'Twixt stupid sottishness and native phlegm, An Englishman, named Tate, made application To buy a pardon by anticipation. “May't please your Excellency,” whisper'd Tate, “I want to horsewhip, kick, and clapper-claw A fellow that I hold in special hate: But as the knave will doubtless take the law, I wish beforehand to enquire the pittance That I must pay to purchase an acquittance.”— “That,” said Van Gutch, “on circumstance must rest; Does the man merit such a deep disgrace?”— “Richly; he stands recorded and confess'd The most notorious scoundrel in the place.”— “Nay, then, I'll not be hard in my condition: I promise, for ten ducats, full remission.”— “Take them,” said Tate, and threw them on the table; Then drew a whip prepared for the occasion, And laid it on as if he would disable His victim from all further malversation, So thick a storm he raised of kicks and lashes, With curses, sandwich-like, between the slashes. Cried Tate, “Your Excellency's the convicted And flagrant knave to whom I made allusion, And this unmeasured scourging I've inflicted, Because your back claims lengthen'd retribution. There!—there's no harm done—all is honest barter: I've trimmed a scoundrel:—you have caught a Tartar.” This said, he bowed politely and departed; Hied to the shore, embark'd and hoisted sail; And in some half hour's space had fairly started From St. Eustatia with a fav'ring gale, Leaving the writhing Dutchman in a fluster Of anguish, rage, oaths, bullying, and bluster. A TOUR TO THE LAKES. If as pleasure you can rank it, To gaze at beauty through a blanket, Go where each lovely lake enshrouds Her charms behind a vale of clouds. Some of our summer tourists seek the Alps, Risking their own to climb the mountain scalps, And if they do not slip, and so Stick midway in some icy nook O'erhanging an abyss of snow; Or that no avalanche down-slides, Engulphing them and all their guides, They write a book, To shew the world what fools they've been, And tell the nothings they have seen. Others there are who can't abide To glide and slide on a glacier's side,— When a trip or a slip may send them to dip, With a hop and a skip, In a bath of snow, where you taste the pleasure Of dying by inches, and freezing at leisure. So, for their consciences' sakes, Eschewing such a clear self-slaughter, They substitute for mountains, lakes, And ramble all on fire for water, Exploring every classic pond, From Pô to Naples, And doating on each muddy moat That boasts sufficient depth to float The ducks of some Italian Mrs. Bond. But if a brace of moping maples Or pining pines o'erhang the bank, Lord! how they laud the fœtid tank; While, ten to one, some rhyming fool Writes stanzas to his “Peerless Pool!” Travellers we have much more John Bullish, Deeming each brother tourist foolish Who his country forsakes, To seek mountains and lakes, When he may get them ready made at home, And so to Westmoreland they roam, Thinking, with all their mights and mains, Of Southey's and of Wordsworth's strains, Of landscapes, picturesque and grand, And crags whose lines are never scann'd, They pierce into the clouds so far,— Of picnic parties, moonlight nights, Boat dinners, and the dear delights Of poetry and potted char! Our lakes, it must be own'd, are pretty things, When one can see them, which is very seldom, For Pluvian Jupiter for ever wings His clouds above them, and Apollo flings His rays so rarely, one would think he held 'em Only for sabbaths, but that not e'en one day In a lake-week deserves the name of Sunday. Maugre this soaking of the scenery, Thither I went last Summer-time (not Summer), A greenhorn gazing for the greenery, And bent, like every undeceived new-comer, To rise by daylight and explore Lake, mountain, valley, tarn, and shore; With which most laudable intent, Having bespoken proper guides For walks and boatings, drives and rides, To bed I went. Up with the sun! and so I might, If I had lain in bed till night! The morning came, at least the hour, But 'stead of light, a darkling shower, That seem'd as if it came to barter us For English weather that of Tartarus. Said I, a shower? Alas! the Lakes Know not the word; for when it takes A falling fit, the rain comes down As if it were resolved to drown All it encounters here and there, Except the prison'd Tourist's care. 'Tis not a storm that spits its spite, Then hurries off, and leaves the scene Enliven'd with a brighter green, And sparkling in the rainbow light: No—'tis a straight unceasing fall Of sullen, dogged, steady rain, Set in to last while you remain, Enshrouding lake, shore, mountain, all, In one impenetrable pall.— After some hours it would subside Into a drizzle drearier yet; For then th' impending clouds were spied, Like monstrous udders—spongy, wet, Flapping and flagging, Lagging and dragging Against the mountain sides, and spilling o'er Whate'er they touch'd their unexhausted store. None could admire such mists, except some scion Descended from old cloud-kissing Ixion. It might be thought the scullions of the sky Had had a washing-day on high, And hung their dish-clout clouds to drain, not dry; While Earth, in a muddle Of pool and of puddle, Assumed a most bedraggled, miry mien; Such slipping and slopping, And dripping and dropping, Save at the Lakes, was surely never seen. Even the ducks one saw the kennel sucking, Appear'd to quake at getting such a ducking,— And, floundering through the slough, each passing man Look'd like a sop in Earth's great dripping-pan. And yet in these diminish'd inundations, (There never were complete cessations,) My guides would quit The taps where they had been carousing, And try to tempt me to a sousing. “It don't rain now, Sir, scarce a bit: We've mopp'd the boat, Jem Thwaites and me: And finer weather cannot be, After those heavy showers and squalls, For seeing both the Waterfalls.”— “Thank you, my friends,” was my reply; “But as I've had from morn till eve, A cataract in either eye, I must be couch'd, with your good leave.” And this was done as soon as said, For off I hurried to my bed. “Doubtless, to-morrow 'twill give o'er,” I whisper'd as I sank to rest; But when the morning stood confest, Zounds! it was wetter than before! The sky had now been used to pour, And seem'd to do it with a zest; For the clouds spouted con amore, And the rain reign'd in all its glory. Oh! how I watched the window pane, Then gazed upon the blubb'ring gutter, Then read the Guide-book through again, And 'twixt my teeth began to mutter Curses upon this most abhorrent And personally spiteful torrent.— My execrations had no force, I could not dam it in its course: Nay, it began to flow the faster, As if to mock at my disaster. E'en the church clock, that toll'd the hours, Appear'd half-smother'd in the showers, So sullenly its muffled knell Boom'd through the heavy air around. Sick of the wet and weary sound, In mere despair I rang the bell:— “Waiter!” said I, “d'ye think this weather Will long continue?”—“No, Sir, no; I shouldn't wonder in the least, If in a week or two it ceased, And gave us two fine days together! Some shifts of wind they sets it going, Others they sets it faster flowing, But still you know, Sir, there's no knowing.” “Pleasant and shrewd! But tell me pray, Have you no public show or sight To which a wretched tourist may Fly from Aquarius's spite?” “Oh yes, Sir, yes; the gentlefolks Goes now and then to Mr. Noakes', Who has a show uncommon fine, Something in the Museum line.”— “Got a Museum, say you? That's A sight I'll see, though Jove's decanter Pour cats and dogs, and dogs and cats. Which is the house? I'm off instanter.” Behold me then, umbrella'd, booted, Great-coated, and envelop'd duly In triple wraps,—in fact just suited To face a Lake-ish day in July, Dabbling and waddling, Splashing and paddling, To the Museum, where I found, A covey of amphibious peasants, Standing in Mr. Noakes' presence, With their dab-chicks all dripping round, And all their mouths and goggle eyes Wide open with profound surprise. “Ladies and gemmen,” said the showman, Raising his magisterial wand, “You'll all be pleased to understand You mustn't chatter-mag, for no man Can tell his story out of hand, If, when he's stating all his factses, You bothers him and questions axes.” “This here (it's number one) that's hung Those Ethiopian birds among, Is an Owhyhee tomahawk.” “Whew!” cries a crone, “It look, good lauk! More like a handsaw nor a hawk. Bees that a hawk?—What say ye, Tommy?” “Naw that it baint, I'm certain, Mommy.” “Silence!” commanded Mr. Noakes; “Please to attend to me, good folks.— This is a whinkam whankam wam, Or statue of the Goddess Isis, Brought from the Islands called the Sandwich; Because the natives are a band which Cut their war-prisoners into slices, As we do ham, And eat them with their bread and butter, A thing most horrible to utter! This here's their bludgeon as they uses In sea or land-fights as they chooses.”— “Why then,” quoth I, “these savages Have got, to give our pride a rub, Their own United-Service Club.” (“Pray, Sir, be silent if you please.”) “This is the Indian calumet, Or pipe of peace, the end on't's broken.”— “Call it,” cried I, “by that same token, (When a new catalogue you get) A piece of pipe, not pipe of peace.”— (“Pray, Sir, be silent if you please.”) “That animal is call'd up there, The great Ant-eater, from Bengal.”— “Lauk!” screamed a child, “the horrid cretur! If he be such a great-aunt-eater, Do pray, Aunt Polly, have a care, Or he may eat you crutch and all! So prythee, prythee, this way hobble, Lest he should gulp you at a gobble.”— “La! Miss,” cried Noakes, and blandly smiled; “He do look just like life, it's true, But don't be frightened, little child! The beast's no more alive than you.— “These crooked horns were all imported Straight from Cape Horn; but how they call The beasts by whom they were supported, I never couldn't larn at all; And hope I needn't make apology For knowing nought of Hornithology. This is a Chinese shoe that pinches A lady's foot within four inches;— Here's a rhinoceros's egg;— This drawing shows you a flea's leg; But whether 'tis the leg behind Or that before, I cannot find, Not being larned in phlebotomy, Nor over skilful in anatomy.— This finger in the bottle's one Of Edward the Black Prince's;—see! It's black as ink itself;—so none Can doubt its authenticity.— This is a Polecat from the Pole, Right underneath the great Equator; And this a Roman painted Bowl: How wondrous are the works of Natur!— Here is a Lynx, whose fiery eyes Have caused us to call flambeaux links; And a Chameleon, changing dyes At will, although it never drinks Nor eats, except a sup of air;— I can't say I should like such fare.— “Now please to open all your eyes; This rarest rarity of all, In the glass-case against the wall, Is Cromwell's head, my greatest prize, With vouchers giving true and full Proof that it is his genuine skull.”— “Softly,” cried I; “I've seen a head At Oxford, which is also said To have been Cromwell's, proved as such By all the certified contents Of most authentic documents, And that was larger,—larger much.”— “What odds, if mine be summat less?” Ask'd Noakes; “this head that I'm a-showing, Might have been his, as any fool may guess, When he was small and hadn't done a-growing.” Thus did he blunder through his task, While I maliciously would ask Questions of Noakes, intended to hoax, And turn into jokes, all he said to the folks, Who, pleased with what they heard and saw, Would burst into a broad Haw! haw! And say, “This chop's a queer one, aint'n?”— “Aw! he's a rare rum codger, baint'n?” The show, though not the rain, was o'er, Which still continued, pour, pour, pour: But wading on through thick and thin, I swam and flounder'd to my inn, Dined, went to bed, and closed my eyes Amid the soothing lullabies Of rain bespattering, windows clattering, The spatter and sputter of every gutter, And all the sounds of liquid clamour That water on the ear can hammer. Next morn the same da capo strain Of everlasting rain, rain, rain. So leaving some more patient fool To wait till doomsday for fine days, I pack'd my luggage, call'd a chaise, And started back for Liverpool; While as they laid their heads together, The waiter to the ostler said, “Why what a flot this chap is, Ned, To coom to th' Lakes and hope to get fine weather!” AN EASY REMEDY. An honest tailor, whose baptismal And patronymic appellations Were William Button, had a dismal Tendency to deep potations; And though, as he was over-mated, Like Jerry Sneak, our snip was fated In spite of all his hungry heavings, To drink the tea and coffee leavings, And eat cold mutton-flaps at dinner; Yet sometimes the rebellious sinner, Asserting his marital rights, Would on the wages-paying nights, Betake him to the public-house, To smoke, and tipple, and carouse; And as with each new dram and sip he Still more and more pot-valiant grew, At last he fairly braved his spouse, Call'd her a vixen and a shrew, A Jezabel and a Xantippe! Returning home one night, our varlet Bold with his wife-compelling liquor, Rattled the knocker quick and quicker, When with fierce eye and face of scarlet His tender spouse appeared, and shrilly Vented reproaches on her Willy. “So, Jackanapes, you've come at last! No doubt the evening has been passed In tippling purl, you drunken sot, Mull'd ale and amber, hot and hot; While your poor wife is left to slave, And drink cold water from the can, Cold water, ye remorseless knave!” “Cold!” cried the husband, who began In turn to wrangle and to storm it,— “Cold! ye poor lazy slattern;—cold! Then why, ye good-for nothing scold, Why don't you warm it?” MADAME TALLEYRAND AND THE TRAVELLER. The famous Talleyrand, who knew The secret of avoiding execution, And kept his head upon his shoulders, through All the convulsions of the Revolution, When heads were cropp'd by the prevailing powers, Like cauliflowers, Till they themselves endured the keen Infliction of the Guillotine, And made way for another faction, To undergo the same reaction:— This Talleyrand possessed a wife, Selected in his humbler life,— A rich bourgeoise of homely breeding, Neither bas bleu, nor femme savante, But rather, as I freely grant, Deficient in her general reading. One day—'twas when he stood elate, Napoleon's minister of state,— Having invited to his house Some literati to confer With a great foreign traveller, The husband thus addressed his spouse:— “My dear, at dinner you will meet A foreigner, a man of note. These authors like that you should quote From their own works; therefore, to greet Our guest, suppose you learn by rote A sentence here and there, that when He prates, like other travell'd men, Of his exploits on land and ocean, You may not be completely gravell'd, But have at least some little notion Of how, and when, and where he travell'd. Take down his book, you'll find it yonder; Its dull contents you need not ponder; Read but the headings of the chapters, Refer to them with praise and wonder, And our vain guest will be in raptures,” Madame resolved to play her part So as to win the stranger's heart, Studied the book; but far from dull, She found it quite delightful;—full Of marvellous adventures, fraught With perilous escapes, which wrought So deep an interest in her mind, She really was surprised to find, As to the dinner-room she tripp'd, How rapidly the time had slipp'd. The more to flatter and delight her, When at the board she took her place, The famous traveller and writer Was seated by her side;—the grace Was hardly said, or soup sent round, 'Ere with a shrug and a grimace, Eager to show her lore profound, A la Française, she raised her eyes, And hands, and voice, in ectasies,— “Eh, Monsieur Robinson, mon Dieu, Voilà un conte merveilleux! Ah, par exemple! it appals The mind to think of your attacks On those terrific cannibals,— Those horrid savages and blacks, Who, if they once had gained the upper Hand, had eaten you for supper, And so prevented your proceeding With that sweet book I've just been reading. Mais, quel bonheur! to liberate Poor Friday from the murd'rous crew, And gain in your deserted state, So lonely and disconsolate A servant and companion too!” The visitants were all astounded; The stranger stared aghast, dumfounded; Poor Talleyrand blushed red as flame, Till having catechised the dame, The mystery was quickly clear'd; The simple woman it appear'd, Instead of the intended book In which she had been urged to look, From the same shelf contrived to take Robinson Crusoe by mistake! PROJECTS AND COMPANIES. “Some were condensing air into a dry tangible substance by extracting the nitre, and letting the aqueous or fluid particles percolate; others softening marble for pillows and pincushions; others petrifying the hoofs of a living horse to preserve them from foundering.”—Gulliver's Travels. A Nation's wealth that overflows, Will sometimes in its course disclose Fantastical contortions: 'Tis like the rising of the Nile, Which fats the soil, but breeds the while Strange monsters and abortions. Better our superflux to waste On peaceful schemes, howe'er misplaced, Than war and its abuses; But better still if we could guide And limit the Pactolian tide, To salutary uses. Our sires, poor unambitious folks! Had but an individual hoax, A single South-sea bubble: Each province our delusion shares, From Poyais down to Buenos-Ayres,— To count them is a trouble. The gold that's sent out ready made To the new world, must be repaid By help of Watt and Boulton, Who from their mines, by aid of pumps, Will raise up ore, and lumps, and dumps, Whence sovereigns may be molten! Others, not roaming quite so far, In stocks and bonds Peninsular, Find all their treasure vanish; Leaving a warning to the rash, That the best way to keep their cash, Is not to touch the Spanish. Gilded by Eldorado dreams, No wonder if our foreign schemes Assume a tint romantic; But e'en at home, beneath our eyes, What ignes fatui arise, Extravagant and antic! Bridges of iron, stone, and wood, Not only, Thames, bestride thy flood, As if thou wert a runnel; But terraces must clog thy shore, While underneath thy bed we bore A subterranean tunnel. Now bursts a fiercer mania—all From every shire, the great, the small For Railroad shares are scrambling: Peers, paupers, countesses, their maids, With equal ardour ply the trades Of jobbing, scheming, gambling. Decoy'd by projects wild and rash, Some find their rail-devoted cash Is lost beyond retrieval; Others, who profitably sold, Will tell you that the age of gold And iron are coeval. With each new moon new bubbles rise, Each, as it flits before our eyes, Its predecessor smashing; All at their rivals freely throw Their dirt, to which we doubtless owe The Company for washing. These are but weeds; the rich manure Of overflowing wealth is sure To generate the thistle:— They who would learn its nobler use, May Pope's majestic lines peruse That close his Fourth Epistle. ELEGY. TO THE MEMORY OF MISS EMILY KAY, COUSIN TO MISS ELLEN GEE, OF KEW, WHO DIED LATELY AT EWELL, AND WAS BURIED IN ESSEX. “They fool me to the top of my bent.”— Shakespear. Sad nymphs of U L, U have much to cry for, Sweet M L E K U never more shall C! O S X maids! come hither and D, o, With tearful I, this M T L E G. Without X S she did X L alway, Ah me! it truly vexes 1 2 C, How soon so D R a creature may D K, And only leave behind X U V E! Whate'er 1 0 to do she did discharge, So that an N M E it might N D R: Then why an S A write?—then why N Or with my briny tears B D U her B R? When her Piano-40 she did press, Such heavenly sounds did M N 8, that she Knowing her Q, soon 1 U 2 confess Her X L N C in an X T C. Her hair was soft as silk, not Y R E, It gave no Q, nor yet 2 P to view: She was not handsome: shall I tell U Y? U R 2 know her I was all S Q. L 8 she was, and prattling like a J; How little, M L E! did you 4 C, The grave should soon M U U, cold as clay, And you should cease to be an N T T! While taking T at Q with L N G, The M T grate she rose to put a: Her clothes caught fire—no 1 again shall see Poor M L E; who now is dead as Solon. O L N G! in vain you set at 0 G R and reproach for suffering her 2 B Thus sacrificed; to J L U should be brought, Or burnt U 0 2 B in F E G. Sweet M L E K into S X they bore, Taking good care the monument 2 Y 10, And as her tomb was much 2 low B 4, They lately brought fresh bricks the walls to 10 (heighten.) PITT'S BON-MOT. Though William Pitt (nick-named the Tory In Morris's facetious story,) Retains the honours of his name As a Debates-man, Who in the House of Commons, “ore Rotundo,” cried up England's glory, Yet as a statesman, Or as a financier, his fame May be compared to his own sinking fund, Which, if not quite extinct, is moribund. Seeing this heaven-born minister's renown In his political capacity, Thus tumbling down, An instance of his smart dicacity Ought in justice to be stated, In order that the reader may bestow Due praise on the defunct for a bon-mot, The only one he ever perpetrated. When the French threaten'd in flat-bottom'd boats, To come and cut our throats, Pitt—then Lord Warden of the Cinque Ports—held A meeting in the town of Dover, To settle, should the French come over, How they might best and soonest be repell'd; Which said assemblage, being fierce and loyal, Declared that England might discard her fears, For they themselves would promise to destroy all The French, if they might form a corps, the Mayor To be commander, and the whole to bear The name of Royal Dover Volunteers. The Premier, when the cheering ceased, Smiled, for he knew the dictum true, That greatest boasters do the least, And whisper'd to himself—“The Dover traders Are most insufferable gasconaders; If any folks deserve an innuendo, By way of a rebuke, I'm sure these men do.” However no remark was made, Until the secretary reading o'er The rules and regulations of the corps, Broke off, and to the chairman said, “Sir, I respectively submit That it were well on this occasion, Among our standing rules and laws, To insert the customary clause, Not to serve out of England.”—“Yes,” said Pitt, “Except in case of an invasion!” HOBBS AND DOBBS. Adrian.—“Your jest is somewhat of the oldest, Master Giles.” Giles.—“Hush! do you think I would offer a new joke, any more than new wine, to your Worship?”—The Unknown. Love in a village, where the parties revel In all the neighbourly civility Of cheerful, social amiability, Is vastly pleasant; But hatred in a village is the devil! Because each peasant Is ever meeting in that narrow circle, The very man on whom he longs to work ill. How sad the pity that our beau idéal Is never real;— That envy, hatred, jealousy, and malice, Should hold their chalice Up to the lips of rustics, who were meant By Nature to be innocent, And harmless as the household dove, That type of love! After this pretty bit of flummery, Or moral sentimental proem, (An apt exordium to my poem,) I must be quick, concise, and summary, And without any more preparative, Commence my narrative. At Oakley, in the Western Riding Of Yorkshire, were two men residing, Named Hobbs and Dobbs, whose constant quarrels, Springing from rivalry in trade, A sort of village warfare made, Which sadly spoilt the people's morals, Splitting them into furious factions, Some warmly advocating Hobbs, While others, both by words and actions, Supported Dobbs. And yet these foolish fellows ought In their two leaders to have found Men of strong understanding, taught With friendly stitches, To patch up, not occasion breaches, And mend the soles of all the rustics round, For they were both shoemakers, and their labours Should have been circumscribed to putting Their friends, and customers, and neighbours, On a good footing. They lived, unfortunately, vis-à-vis, And soon began the work of emulation, By flaming shopboards, where in gilt And lacker'd lustre, you might see The symbols of their occupation, Much paint in blue and crimson being spilt, That each might be more splendid than the other, And win all custom from his baffl'd brother. Hobbs, who had somehow given handle For undeserved reproach and scandal, When he new-dizen'd out his board, Wrote at its foot this Latin scrap— “Mens conscia recti,” which he took From some heraldic motto-book, Meaning thereby to have a slap At his maligners, and afford Proof that his path he still pursued, Strong in a conscious rectitude. This was a source of envious dolour To Dobbs, who, in his first confusion, Knowing his rival was no scholar, Deduced the natural conclusion That “conscia recti” doubtless meant Some article of trade, perchance, Some fashion just arrived from France, And being resolutely bent His hated rival to eclipse, He sent forthwith for Mr. Cripps, Painter and glazier, When thus ejaculated Dobbs— “Paint me a still more flaming board, Of green, and gold, and azure; What! do you think I can't afford To pay for it as well as Hobbs? Be these French kickshaws what they will, I am resolved to beat him still, To which effect I Desire you'll print in gold at bottom, (That folks may fancy I have got'em,) Men's and women's conscia recti!” MONSIEUR LE BRUN. Monsieur le Brun (who must not be confused With the great painter) jointly cultivated Apollo's laurel and the grape of Bacchus, And into médiocre verse translated, Or rather, as the French would say, traduced The odes of Flaccus. The work, I must confess, was badly done, For poor Le Brun, Still scribbling, and unable still to win A living for himself and wife, Was like a rope-maker, condemned to spin Long lines, yet still go backward all his life. Le Brun asserted that an author loses By quaffing with the water-drinking Muses, Wherefore he held in small account Castalia's fount, And not a solitary sip he Ever quaffed from Aganippe, Maintaining that champagne and other wine, With, now and then, a draught of liquor, Produced an inspiration quicker, As well as more delightful and divine.— If to his cups his couplets he had suited, They must have sparkl'd—and 'tis strange to me, That want of life should ever be imputed To poetry inspired by eau-de-vie. But so it was—his poems, every one, Were like a flintless gun, Which won't go off for want of fire; And poor Le Brun who took to deeper drinking Instead of thinking, Sunk daily deeper in oblivion's mire. While swallowing compound spirits, still the faster He lost his own, till he became a prey To hypochondria; and one disaster Another following, his health gave way. His stomach, it was said, had lost its coat, Or thrown it off, perhaps, from being hot, For his old trick he never had forgot, Of pouring ardent spirits down his throat; Which daily system of potation Most deleterious, Brought fever first, then inflammation, When his poor wife, so much his aspect shock'd her, Call'd in the doctor, And now the case grew serious. Bolus, a man of fees, not feeling, Finding his purse was low, though high his fever, Bolted, but sent a priest, who, kneeling, Thus comforted the bibulous believer,— “My son, 'tis clear you have not long to live, So you must quickly use this unction, Confess your sins with due compunction, And freely all your enemies forgive— Bestowing on them, if they're nigh, The kiss of peace before you die!” “Kiss what I hated most—my deadliest foes! Surely, good father, you impose A penance too revolting to be just, 'Tis ten times worse than fasts, hair shirts, and whips; However, if I must, I must; So put a glass of water to my lips!” POETICAL EPISTLE, From Amos Stokes, Esq., of Nashville, United States, to Washington Nokes, Esq., of Liverpool, commencing the Account of a very remarkable Aerial Voyage made in the grand Kentucky Balloon. In ordinary times and moods, dear Nokes, You might for centuries have had to whistle, 'Ere I, the plain prosaic Amos Stokes, Should send you a poetical epistle: But the muse sometimes visits solemn folks, As a flower blossoms even on the thistle, And mine's a theme so startling and sublime, That it affords good reason for my rhyme.— I have been far above the clouds,—and seen Sights unreveal'd before to mortal eye! You know that merry madcap, Harry Green,— Well—he persuaded Ebenezer Guy, A Latin usher—solemn, long, and lean, Whose talk was pompous, polyglot, and dry, And your unlucky friend—(a witless wight!) In Hudson's grand balloon to take a flight. Hudson—long practised in balloons, was meant To steer our bark, and manage every part; In fact, all four were seated—all intent On making quickly an auspicious start, When, leaning to untie the rope, too far, Our clumsy pilot tumbled from the car! As Hudson was a heavy man, of course The loss of his preponderating weight, Made the machine start upwards with a force As if a whizzing rocket went elate. So instantaneous was our earth-divorce, We had no time the crowd to calculate, Or note their shouts, fast dwindling to a hum, When the whole scene grew indistinct and dumb. E'en I, dear Nokes, an unreflecting wight, Felt an awe-stricken, and a solemn mood, In being sever'd from the world outright, And floating upwards thro' th' infinitude Of space; as if, while blessed with life and light, A sort of dissolution had accrued, And I had bid a last adieu to earth, To find, in some new sphere, a second birth. Is that dim mass, methought, obscured with clouds, Looming below, a doubtful vapoury form,— Is that our planet, with its countless clouds,— Its nations, empires, cities? Is the storm Of vice and passion that man's heart enshrouds, The virtues that the female bosom warm, Thrilling and throbbing in that little sphere? Oh! what an ant-hill does the whole appear! And other planets, throng'd like ours, perchance, With beings that seem only born to die; Why do they weave their rotatory dance, Like gnats disporting in a summer sky? Why do they fill the limitless expanse With sepulchres that whirl eternally Around the central fount of life and light, What was their dawning—when will be their night? While thoughts like these were flashing through my mind With lightning speed, adapted to our motion, My comrade, Harry Green, remain'd resign'd To a convulsive laughter, at the notion Of the fat sprawler whom we left behind, Till, having wiped the tears that made a lotion For either cheek, he cried “I can't forget Hudson's own wonder at his somerset.” “Had he been with us, our retarded flight, If we could fly at all—a doubtful case,— Had been no higher than an urchin's kite, Or eagle, towering in its pride of place; And never had we known the keen delight Of soaring thus triumphantly through space, And looking, every moment as we climb, Down on the earth with feelings more sublime.” “Do you remember, Guy, the well-known joke Of singing Dignum at a public dinner, Who, slicing from the pudding, at one stroke, A mass that left it some three quarters thinner, Said, as he moved the dish—‘some pudding, Skinner? ‘Which,’ replied Skinner, as his glances stray From plate to dish, ‘which is the pudding, pray?’” “So I, while gazing on the sphere below, And that above, which, like a silken moon, Sustains our car, am half in doubt to know Which is the Earth, and which is the balloon, How beautiful is this celestial show! Methinks it were an enviable boon Ne'er to revisit Earth, but in the sky, Amid these glorious scenes, to live and die.” “There's little doubt about the last,” replied The hollow voice of Guy, who hitherto, While as with fear transfix'd, he sternly eyed The mass above him, evidently drew Grim auguries he did not seek to hide;— “Prepare for death—you've nothing else to do— Giving false hopes I'll not be a colleague at, For dubiam qui dat salutem, negat. “An endless holiday my school will have,— I never more shall wield the birch or cane; No human agency our lives can save, In this accursed car must we remain, Until it proves—as soon it will—our grave. Our fate is manifest,—the case is plain,— I wouldn't hurt your feelings,—never mind, Mors omnibus communis,—I'm resign'd.” As his affrighted looks the boast belied, We called upon him for an explanation; When, in the same sepulchral voice, he sigh'd— “As Hudson tumbled, in his agitation He caught the string that to the valve is tied, And snapp'd it off—so that no operation Can now let off the gas, and we must rise Till cold or famine kill us in the skies!”— “Nonsense,” cried Harry Green,—who lov'd his joke, Bad as it might be, better than his friend,— “While we thus soar (excuse the équivoque) Into the grave we cannot well descend.”— “So much the worse,” with melancholy croak, Responded Guy, “we shall not in our end Have even decent burial, but be cast to And fro in air—nantes in gurgite vasto,— Until the flesh is wasted from our bones, (Dying of famine, that will soon be done!) When for unnumber'd years our skeletons, Floating in space, may reach at last some zone, Or sphere remote, whose geologic sons, In a glass case may have us clapp'd, and shown As fossils of the air—quis talia fando— But I'll not weep—Fortunæ omnia mando.” At first I thought by climbing up some rope, That we might cut the silk or tear a rent, So as to let th' imprison'd gas elope; But after each had tried th' experiment, In climbings numberless, we lost all hope, For none by grappling made the least ascent; The car hung low,—the cords were small,—and we Had ne'er since boyhood even climbed a tree. Little supposing, when we first went up, That we should spend the morning in the sky, Still less that we should want to dine or sup, We ne'er had dreamt of taking a supply;— Of liquids we had not a single cup, Nor would our solids bear a scrutiny, Consisting of a quince-cake, small enough, Three pears, two apples, and a penny puff.— “We're stump'd, I fear,” said Harry Green, whose mood Changed with his grave and lengthen'd countenance; “But our first duty is to share the food, So as to give to each an equal chance. The puff and quince-cake must not now be chew'd, The pears are three, a lucky circumstance; The apple-sharing I myself will see to, There's one for you two, and there's one for me too.” At first I thought this trite and sorry jest Was merely fun, until he ate the prize, When Guy and I our discontent express'd, Whereat he said decisively—“Be wise, Discard all thoughts of quarrel from your breast, If we fall out we're dash'd to atomies.—” “Humph, a high joke,” quoth Guy; “you little ween, Hi joci in seria ducunt—Mr. Green.” In fact we all look'd serious as he spoke, Eyeing each other with distrust and fear, And none of us the sulky silence broke, For now the sun was setting—night drew near— None had an extra Macintosh or cloak, And the cold grew so nipping and severe, That though no single syllable we said, Our teeth began to chatter in our head. The cold augmented as we soar'd more high, But this, though most distressing, would not bear Comparison with the sharp agony Caused by the rarefaction of the air. We gasp'd for breath as if about to die, As fishes on dry land pant, gulp, and stare, And swell'd as if our blood and bones were thirsting To leave the body by a general bursting. This must have been our dismal fate, indeed, But that our noses, in a copious stream, At the same moment all began to bleed, Which gave us ease—your ministers may deem The pressure from without a bore—agreed! That from within is a far worse extreme, When your exterior seems all turn'd about, And your inside is struggling to get out. Up in that keen attenuated air, Th' evaporation is so great and swift, That we already wither'd, as it were:— Our parch'd and rattling tongues we could not lift, Our eyes were solder'd up—no tears were there; And when that æther rare we breath'd or sniff'd, Our stomach's region, and brain's pia mater, Felt twice as dry as a limeburner's gaiter. The silence, too, so thrillingly intense, Caused a fresh pain: dilated and acute, Our ears ached piercingly, because their sense Could catch no sound—all, all was hush'd and mute; While now the darkness most profound and dense, Might half persuade us Death had won his suit, And struck us all, but that by fits and starts, We heard the feeble beating of our hearts. Oh! there's an awfulness most dread and deep In piercing thus night's topmost atmosphere, And feeling that, however fast you sweep, You never need look out a-head for fear Of running foul of others, since you keep A course that none have ever dared to steer, And have all space before you, all your own, E'en to the wide creation's widest zone. But what!—methought, if like our planet, space— Holds some vast desert,—some Zahara dark, Where the Creator's hand has left no trace, A primal chaos, never cheer'd by spark Of sun or moon, and that our airy chase Should finish by delivering our bark Into that limbo, and so leave us fated, 'Mid nothingness to be annihilated! From this appalling reverie I woke, By seeing in the blazing skies afar, A fearful storm, which suddenly outbroke In the full rage of elemental war, Amid whose lightning flash and lurid smoke, Diminish'd earth, no bigger than our car, Seem'd to sustain a contest most uneven, With all the dread artillery of heaven. Tremendous must have been the thunder's peal, But not the faintest murmur reach'd mine ear, A fact, dear Nokes, which will alone reveal Our measureless remoteness from earth's sphere. As the storm died away I seem'd to feel The darkness that return'd more deep and drear, And nought disturb'd the silence of the sky, Save the mix'd snores and mutterings of Guy. Mumbling his prayers, and dreaming that he heard His boys their Greek and Latin tasks repeat, I caught this galimatias absurd:— “Amo, amas—a dactyle has three feet— God's will be done!—that's not a Latin word— Tupto-tupteis, means—verbero, to beat;” And then he murmured in a tone more drowsy, “Amen!—good night,—tuptomen,—boy,—tuptousi.” Harry, meanwhile, as if he strove no more With adverse fate, began to nod his head, And soon set up a comfortable snore, Like him who, when his bark resistless sped Tow'rds dread Niagara's engulphing roar, Threw down his oar, his cloak above him spread, Stretch'd out his legs, composed himself to sleep, And thus perform'd his last tremendous leap. Our plight, in sooth, was much the same as his, Save that our vortex was a stream of air, Which hurried us to some unknown abyss;— And yet, perhaps, we better might compare Our danger with Mazeppa's wretchedness, For our wild steed no curb or check would bear, And if he would, to dream of it were idle, For in the valve-string we had lost the bridle. I could not sleep; for, through the darkness dense That hitherto had compassed us about, In beautiful and bright magnificence, The constellations, signs, and stars shone out, Like monarchs stepping from their thrones; my sense Ached at their flashing crowns, which made me doubt Whether they were the same whose duller glories I had oft mark'd from Earth's observatories. At length, when all unconscious of the lapse, I sunk into a short and broken rest, It was this vision doubtless—(though perhaps, Mazeppa's horse occasion'd half the pest)— That brought, 'midst many painful after-claps, The nightmare to bestride my lab'ring breast; And conjured up, out of this heavenly glory, a Most diabolical phantasmagoria. The Zodiac's monsters and celestial signs Seem'd to take living bodies, near and far; Their arms they snatch'd, and quitting their confines, Cried “Havoc! and let slip the dogs of war.” The trumpet's clang rang loud along their lines; While shouted fiercely every sign and star,— “Sacrilege, sacrilege! destroy—o'erwhelm The impious wretches that invade our realm!” The roaring Lion, rushing from his lair, Lifted his paw, and bared his snarling teeth; Up, with a growl appalling, sprang the Bear; The hissing Serpent, darting from his wreath, Transfix'd me with his eyeball's fiery glare; And all the forms I saw—(I'm here beneath The mark)—were ten times bigger, every one, Than Doctor Mantell's famed Iguanadon. The Scorpion huge, his shudd'ring prey to reach, Stretch'd out his bristling claws; the Hydra rear'd His furious heads, each horrider than each; Orion with his cries the Dog-star cheer'd; The Twins (not Siamese) with horrid screech, Urg'd on the Crab and Lizard; all appear'd Eager and rampant for the sign when all, With ravening rage, upon their prey might fall. It was not long delay'd. From out her chair Cassiopeia rose, and shouted “On!” Twang! went the Archer's bow, and through the air Claws, teeth, horns, hoofs, and weapons fell upon Our wretched trio; while the startled zone Still more our 'wilder'd faculties to scare, With roaring, growling, grunting, hissing rang, The clash of cymbals, and the clarion's clang. Roused by this charivari, when I woke, Shivering and stupified with cold and fear, The baseless fabric of the vision broke, And all again was silent, dark, and drear, Except when Guy, in mingled mutterings spoke, Or Harry's heavy snorings met mine ear. So pass'd the night;—but oh! with morning's beam, The real sight was ghastlier than my dream!— Gaunt—stiffen'd—pale—desiccated—adust— Our clothes and faces in a gory smear With our nose-blood,—our stony eyes out-thrust, Striving in vain to shed the frozen tear; Harrow'd with horror, sicken'd with disgust, Our teeth's sharp chatter all that met our ear,— We looked like corpses, or three dismal dummies, Hung up to dry till we should turn to mummies. How long we thus remain'd transfix'd and mute, I cannot tell—perhaps an hour or more, Till, pinch'd with hunger, I drew out the fruit Which I had pocketed the night before; So did my friends, all eating with such brute Voracity, that breakfast soon was o'er, Tho' every pear was large and full of juice—(it's The sort that here is called the Massachusets.) O Nokes! how suddenly our frame derives Fresh vigour, sometimes from the scantiest meal! Our moisten'd tongues threw quickly off their gyves, And as his mood relax'd from woe to weal, Cried Hal, “We draw, (to judge by what I feel,) From the first pear a second time our lives!” Whereat Guy, frowning, said, “Don't talk at random, Ne lude sacris, Mr. Green—nefandum!” Alas! our subsequent and dire distress Was but augmented by this short relief, For hunger's gnawings and cold's bitterness Returned with tenfold sharpness; but our chief Torment was thirst, increased by the excess Of dryness in the atmosphere;—in brief I stated, that if others felt as I did, I thought our quince-cake ought to be divided. “Quince-cake!” laughed Harry, with a look of bonhommie, “To tell the truth, I swallowed it last night From pure and abstract motives of economy, Fearing it might evaporate outright; But some concession you have fairly won o'me; So of the penny puff I waive my bite.” “Sir!” mutter'd Guy, “I hate and I despise you, Thus blando fraudem pretexere risu.” To guard against th' extension of this code So treacherous and base, myself and Guy Shared the small puff—no very heavy load For stomachs yearning with inanity; And now, in our most desolate abode, Was left no drop—no mouthful of supply, Whatever crib or cruise we might examine, To save us from th' extremity of famine. Our woes to aggravate, we found, alas! That when the outward pressure was reduced, In its endeavours to escape, the gas Thro' the stretch'd silk had gradually oozed, Until the whole machine's suspended mass, Balanced in equilibrio, refused To rise or fall; affording us the pleasure To starve, or freeze, or wither up at leisure. “Ha!” suddenly cried Hal, “I've found a way, By which we all may shun our threaten'd fate.”— “What is it?” we together cried,—“Oh say!”— “You may jump out,” drawled Harry; “I, elate, Then to some higher habitat may stray, While you a starving death will evitate.” Quoth Guy,—“You should have left these jests, jamdudum, Nec lusisse pudet, sed non incidere ludum.” “'Tis our sole chance,” quoth Hal, “for our career, When lightened thus, will doubtless recommence, And we may soar until some higher sphere Bring us within attraction's influence— Some peopl'd globe, where hospitable cheer May welcome us with glad benevolence: Heaven grant that we may find, for our revival, A smoking dinner waiting our arrival.” His low'ring looks soon darken'd to a stern And fell expression that confirm'd his speech; And thus we sate in silence, each in turn Eyeing his comrade with misgiving—each Holding dark counsel with his thoughts, to learn How he might save himself—and overreach His friends, so lawless in its operation Is that remorseless law—Self-preservation. Heavy and slowly dragg'd the dreary day, Our bosoms rankling with a fiercer ire, As the light ominously died away, And thirst and cold and hunger grew more dire. I hoped some rain or dew-drops might allay Our raging thirst's insatiable fire; But in those altitudes, dear Nokes, there's neither Rain-drops nor dew to damp the parching ether. What horrid thoughts of violence and crime Haunted my comrades in the dead of night, I know not; but the Devil at one time Urged me to grapple Green with all my might, And throw him out; but Hal was in his prime, And, waking, might on me bestow the flight I meant for him. Guy was awake, poor elf! So Satan whisper'd me—throw out thyself! These temptings I resisted, Heaven be praised! And bore my torments till the break of morn, When Harry as his heavy eyes he raised, And marked our looks grim, haggard, and forlorn, Gried—“Gentlemen, you surely must be crazed, To think these pangs much longer can be borne, We'll wait till sunset, then draw lots to know Which of the party overboard must go.” “But it were well (the hint I venture here Is offered to your joint consideration) If one of you would kindly volunteer To act the Curtius on this sad occasion, By leaping in the gulph—a fate, 'tis clear, Better than vi et armis jactitation, And as you're oldest, Guy, I tell you plump, 'Tis your's to make the sacrificial jump. “Mine!” cried the pedagogue, with angry sneer, “In your own idle vein to give reply, I might maintain that as I'm tallest here, And we are doomed to die by inches—I Must perish last;—besides, your loose career Has prematurely destined you to die. Against all suicide I make disclaimer, Quocunque trahant fata nos sequamur.— “Moreover, I've a nephew full of glee, Yet fonder still of learning than of frolics, For all his Latin who depends on me, And has begun translating his Bucolics: On his account I wish my life to be A little lengthen'd—not of course too prolix;— At thought of leaving him my very gorge aches, At least—before he gets into his Georgics.” “Well then,” said Green, “you, Stokes, will not pretend That you have niece or nephew—what say you? Will you jump overboard to save a friend?” “I would,” said I, “but I've a cousin who Is giddy—young—wants watching, or he'll spend His cash too fast. Oh Harry! if you knew My cousin Tom, I ne'er had been expected To leave him cousinless and unprotected.” “As for myself, I own,” said Green, and smiled, “That I am free from every social clog, Have neither kith nor kindred, chick nor child, But I've a poodle puppy—such a dog! He, too, depends on me—is young and wild, And from his home might wander in a fog: You're Christians, gentlemen!—have hearts—confess You would not leave that poodle masterless!” The voluntary principle, we saw, Had no supporters in our coterie, So we resolved, at sunset, lots to draw, And sacrifice one victim of the three. Thus sat we grim and silent, cold and raw, Two destined murderers and one murderee; Eyeing each other, all that day of fate, With scowls most savage, fell, and desperate, As the watch'd sun went down—(it was the last Sunset that one of us was doom'd to view)— An ominous and baleful glance it cast On our most ghastly and sepulchral crew: Our senses swam—our hearts beat loud and fast, And more convulsively our gasps we drew, Clenching our teeth and drawing in our breath, As Green prepared the paper lots of death. There was a leering devil in his eye,— A look of cruelty and craft combined, Which satisfied me that some treachery Lurked in his bosom. My misgiving mind Whisper'd that if he drew the lot to die, Some fraudulent evasion he would find, Or might, in desperation's last resource, Throw overboard myself or Guy by force. Resolved to see fair play, and sell my life As dearly as I could, if thus defied, I kept my hand upon a large clasp-knife In my coat pocket, while I gave, aside, A friendly wink to Guy, in whom the strife Of hope and fear was potent as he cried, “My pangs can't last, one plunge and I shall lose 'em In space profound—profundo—profudi—profusum!” “The hour is come!” croaked Green, and well we knew What was to follow that appalling text, “The hour is come!”—Adzooks! that's very true, 'Tis twelve—the Packet sails at one—I'm vex'd To break off here, dear Nokes!—in haste, adieu! Allow me to refer you to my next, Which will contain a full and true relation Of what next happen'd in our aërostation. SECOND POETICAL EPISTLE. From Amos Stokes, Esq., of Nashville, United States, to Washington Nokes, Esq., of Liverpool, containing the Account of the very remarkable Ascent made in Mr. Hudson's Grand Kentucky Balloon. My last, dear Nokes, convey'd a full account Of our most desperate and horrid plight, When, to compel our poised balloon to mount By rendering it more volatile and light, So that we might approach some stellar fount, And quench our raging thirst—we deem'd it right To fix, by drawing lots of paper, Which of our trio overboard should caper. One after one Green placed them on his palm, And was about to close his hand, when lo! Although it hitherto had been dead calm, A gust of wind snatch'd up those types of woe, And whisk'd them out of sight. Hope's sudden balm Gave to our spirits a reviving flow; For, in this crisis of our sad condition, It seem'd a heavenly interposition. Especially when our balloon, beneath Some new and strong attraction, upwards rush'd, And we drew in, between our chattering teeth, A warmer air, which thro' our system gush'd, Thawing our blood until it seem'd to seethe, While we no longer felt oppress'd and crush'd By th' outward atmosphere, which now was neither Too rare nor cold, but a delicious æther. Hey! presto! pass!—One anxious moment more, And we were compass'd by a vapoury shroud. Another pause, and there began to pour A heavy rain from this dissolving cloud; So that, by holding up the hats we wore, The swelling sides of the balloon allow'd A stream continuous to trickle down, And fill a bumper in the indented crown. Me and my comrades did that magic draught Raise from despair to bliss without alloy, As if we simultaneously had quaff'd Hope, courage, strength, vitality, and joy. Green was no longer truculent:—he laugh'd, And thought no more of whom he should destroy; While Guy kept praying, in his own farrago, Jupiter auctor! tibi gratias ago.” From that most blessed cloud emerging soon, There shot athwart our course a sudden light, As warm as a meridian day of June,— When our three voices, at their topmost height, Set up a choral shout—“The moon! the moon!” And there it was above us, huge and bright; Confounding all my system of astronomy, And notions of the sun and moon's economy. When, as we thought, the balanced element, Kept our balloon in equipoised inaction, We still had made a gradual ascent, Until we came within the moon's attraction. For 'twas the moon indeed to which we bent Our course with so much speed and satisfaction. I tell you simply what I saw, dear Nokes, So don't suppose my history a hoax. After the sun went down brief twilight gleam'd; We were rapt upwards with a rush—and lo! As we approach'd the moon, the morning beamed, And the warm planet sparkled in the glow Of sunshine;—yes, however strange it seem'd, There was no night that night. Guy felt it so, For he exclaim'd,—“A miracle confess'd! Occubuit sol, nox nulla secuta est.” As we drew nearer, still the fairer smiled That lunar garden of delight, until The paradise thus open'd in the wild Fill'd us with wonder, though it could not fill Our maws:—the pangs of Tantalus were mild, Compared to those that made us yearn and thrill, As various fruits we noted, all and each Within our sight, but far above our reach. When we had nearly gain'd the promised land, Some most provoking law of ærostatics Brought our poised vessel to a second stand, And thus we hung suspended in the attics; While the ground floor exhibited a bland Display of warmth to solace our rheumatics, As well as food, which, in our starving langour, Half madden'd us with an impatient anger. Our woes to aggravate, the rustic crew, Who in the fields already were at work, Soon as our floating figures came in view, Brandish'd ferociously scythe, spade, and fork, Or gathered stones, which at our car they threw, Each, with the look of a malignant Turk, Shouting amain—“Hikanah polbob, boo!” Words meaning, when their English garb is put on, “If you alight, you're all as dead as mutton!” Just then some influence of gravitation Brought our balloon still nearer to the ground, When, smitten with a sudden consternation The peasants fled to the defying sound, “Hikanah polbob, boo!” but in their station We marked one maiden as we gazed around, For such we judged her by her curly head, Her figure slim, and petticoat of red. Cried Green, whose spirits had revived, “By jingo! That flaming petticoat and graceful mien Give her the semblance of a red flamingo, But that no beak or pinions can be seen. I wonder whether she can speak our lingo:— Hilloa! Ma'am or Miss! behold our lean And starving state. If you can throw so far, Pray toss a quartern loaf into our car!” Whereat she threw her body back—uprear'd Her fair round arms, and tenderly exclaim'd “Squanch zimzom squish!” How euphonous appear'd Those guttural and Dutch-like words, when named By woman's ever welcome voice, endear'd Tenfold to us, whose hearing was inflamed By long and hungry listening for a sound, While we were prison'd in our silent pound. As speech was useless here, I made a sign, By pointing to my mouth with starving look; Untwisting then a little ball of twine, And fastening to its lower end a hook, I let a basket down until the line Came within reach, which eagerly she took, Untied the pannier in a trice, and, quicker Than any antelope, bore off the wicker. Oh! how we watch'd her flitting o'er the ground, As to the covert of a wood she flew! Oh! how our bosoms thrill'd with joy profound, As her light form appeared again in view! Oh! when the string she to the handle bound, How carefully the basket we up-drew! But oh! (and this beat all the other oh!'s) At sight of its contents what joy arose! Three bowls of milk we saw: I cannot say How mortal cows could yield so rich a draught, Unless they pastured in the milky way;— Imagine with what eagerness we quaff'd! Next were three loaves upon a wooden tray, So far beyond an earthly baker's craft, That from their taste they might have been surmised To be sweet almond cakes celestialized. Not Heliogabalus nor old Apicius, Nor the famed suicidal cook Vattel, Ever concocted banquet more delicious, Or one so eagerly devour'd.—To tell Th' effect of those restoratives auspicious Transcends my power; in short, we felt quite well, And in an access of hysteric gladness, Shriek'd, laugh'd, and jumped with every sign of madness. So kind the maiden, that I felt a hope, Perchance, that she might aid us to descend, So I uncoil'd and lowered down a rope, With a small grappling iron at its end, Making a sign,—(oh! there is ample scope In signs, if people will but comprehend,) That she should stick the hook into the ground, Or fasten it to anything she found. As quick to execute as understand, The tackle to a withered stump she tied, Then lifting up each alabaster hand, She bowed, as if to say “I have complied.” So did we gently pull ourselves to land, And mooring the balloon that it might ride Safely at anchor, out we jumped, enchanted To find our feet on terra firma planted. How shall I paint it—where begin—how frame Language descriptive of a scene so rare? Luxora (so the nymph was call'd) must claim Precedence of my pen. That fairest fair, Bending one knee as to the ground we came, Thrice touch'd her forehead with a reverent air, Then smiling like an opening rose in June, Appeared to give us welcome to the moon. All the Lunarians, you must keep in mind, Are somewhat smaller than the human race, Bearing the same proportion to mankind, That the moon does to earth. In stature, grace, And symmetry, Luxora's form combined All that we dream of sylphs, although her face More round and moonlike than we see on earth, Showed her to be a girl of lunar birth. Yet was it fair, most exquisitely fair,— Her cheeks just beaming with a roseate light, Contrasting with the yellow silken hair That fell in tendrils o'er her shoulders white; Her round ox-eye with Juno's might compare, Save that its hue was moonlike, with a bright Spot in the centre of the purest hazel, More sparkling than the pupil of the gazelle. Her tight-made boddice of a golden thread, The budding beauties of her bust conceal'd, Her petticoat of dark flamingo red, Half of her fair unstocking'd leg reveal'd. No wonder that with such a foot, her tread Was light as gossamer. No nymph lark-heel'd, Nor Dian, Atalanta, nor Aurora, Had legs so lissom as the light Luxora. When I had gazed my fill—no easy task,— I look'd around me on the landscape fair. Oh! what a master's pencil would it ask To paint a scene so beautifully rare, Where the whole face of nature wore a mask That gave her features a diminish'd air, And yet enhanced their charms, as if she sought To prove how well in miniature she wrought. A golden bloom illumed the velvet grass, Whose flowers gave forth a perfume rich and rare, The tinted waters looked like purple glass, Flowing through meads auriferous;—the air Thrill'd with the songs of birds that far surpass Earth's nightingales in summer evenings fair; And when we raised our ravished eyes on high, What lovely visions glorified the sky! Prismatic clouds assumed the form and hues Of a grand gallery of pictures splendid, Where every taste its favourite scene might choose: For here a gorgeous landscape lay extended, An air-drawn Paradise; and there sea-views, With figures, flowers, and cattle-pieces blended. All, when a zephyr wafted them from sight, To form again more beautifully bright. While I stood thus in an admiring trance, Green, who had gather'd and devour'd a mango, Now, bowing, to Luxora would advance, Now twirl around her in a mad fandango, Crying at times, as he increased his dance, “I'll show you, Miss, how rapidly I can go,” And laughing louder as he caper'd round, At poor Luxora's wonderment profound. Guy's wonder was a stupor; every sight And every moment seeming to increase it: His first quotation was a bull outright, “Steterunt comæ, vox faucibus hæsit,”— For he was bald, and spoke.—“Who,” quoth our wight, “Quis tale credat? even when he sees it? Well may the moon be called decus astrorum, Where everything is dulce et decorum.” And now Luxora, tripping o'er the glades That formed its outskirts, led us to a wood, Within whose fragrant and sequestered shades, A small pavilion picturesquely stood, With windows looking down, thro' green arcades, On a far lake, whose waves the zephyr woo'd, Or sped some vessel on its sunny way, That dash'd the waters into sparkling spray. In this retreat, where everything betray'd Simplicity, refined by female taste, Our fair neat-handed Phillis—now our maid And hostess too—(both characters she graced,) A plain repast upon the table laid, Waiting upon us with such looks of chaste And reverent homage in her beaming features, 'Twas plain she took us for celestial creatures. Whene'er we spoke, this answer still we heard— “Squanch zimzom squish,” whose lunar sense implies, “I cannot understand a single word;” But we had little need of colloquies, For what we wanted instantly occurr'd, As if she read our very thoughts and eyes; Such was the intuition of this airy, Brave, gracious, graceful, deferential fairy. Our meal concluded, with her tiny hand Of ivory, she pointed to a door, With signs to open it; at which command We pass'd within and mark'd upon the floor Three couches ready to receive our band; Each at its head a plume of feathers bore, Each was with rushes strewn, and flowers whose balm Inspires a sleep, refreshing sweet, and calm. When we returned, behold! the nymph had fled, Or vanish'd as by magic from the place: We listen'd, but we could not hear her tread; We gazed around, no object could we trace; So to beguile our lonesomeness we sped Forth to the circling forest—not in chace Of the fair fugitive—but just to see Whate'er might move our curiosity. Oft will my memory that stroll renew, So strange and lovely was the woodland show: Each wild flower, shrub, and tree that met our view, Resembled those that in our tropics grow— Palm, cedar, cypress, banyan, bamboo, And many more whose names we did not know, Were laced together in alcoves and bowers, By parasitic plants, enwreathed with flowers. The dove, gold pheasant, humming-bird, maccaw, Swung to and fro upon the high festoons, While, sporting in the lower boughs, we saw Opossums, squirrels, monkeys, and racoons, And all by some mysterious lunar law Had round flat faces just like little moons; Even the animals unknown on earth, Bearing this token of their lunar birth. If they were strange to us, 't was clearer still That we were strange to them; for, as we sped, The birds flew off with startl'd screamings shrill, While quickly disappeared each quadruped; New forms we glimpsed, which scarcely waited till We came in sight, when instantly they fled. We laugh'd at their alarms, but far more pleasant Was the wild panic of a passing peasant. Thus we pursued our fear-diffusing walk Till evening's shadows fell, when home we hied, Of fair Luxora's bravery to talk— The only being who, unterrified, Had faced us, and not only scorn'd to baulk Our hopes of aid, but kindly had supplied Such food and lodging, we could almost fancy The whole some scene of fairy necromancy. We saw the sun behind the mountains set In all th'effulgence of prismatic glory, Then gladly to our couches did we get, To chat awhile of our surprising story, But the flowers soporific would not let Our talk be more than brief and transitory, For we all sunk in balmy slumber soon: So passed our first day's sojourn in the moon. THIRD POETICAL EPISTLE. From Amos Stokes, Esq., of Nashville, United States, to Washington Nokes, Esq., of Liverpool, concluding the Account of a very remarkable Aerial Voyage made in the Grand Kentucky Balloon. Waking next morning, when I raised my head After a slumber sweet beyond compare, I found, as if by magic fingers spread, A ready breakfast of substantial fare: Fruits, milk, and honey, and a sort of bread Resembling ours, but far more rich and rare, Composed the meal, of which our approbation Was shown by its immediate mastication. By her own pure and pious heart deceived, Luxora thought us a celestial crew, Who, in their visit, ought to be received With all the reverence to angels due; And stating to the King what she believed, His Majesty, who deem'd the story true, Next morning sent a solemn deputation, To offer us a royal habitation. The gravest Quaker's gravest pug would bark Had he but seen the pomp and the grimaces, Of these dwarf'd spindle-shanks, without a spark Of animation in their moony faces; Yet proud as Lucifer, if any mark, Or badge, or bearing, gave the smallest traces That they might elevate their pigmy bodies One jot above their brother hoddy-doddies. Some had a maze of horse-hair, saturate With grease and dust, entwisted round their polls, Which dirty dignitaries walk'd in state, As grave as judges. Bless their nasty souls! Some strutted in fantastic robes, ornate With filthy fur of polecats or of moles, Seeming to think that it enhanced their rank, The more the animals that wore them stank. Others, deriving their distinction's germ From baser sources still, displayed a dress Spun from the bowels of a loathsome worm; Others again, like earthly savages, Wore toys and trinkets worthy of the term, Such as sliced vegetables, to express Their rank and honour; these their vests were put on, Or dangled from a coat's conspicuous button. Another class there was, in trappings gay, Fine colours—laces—feathers—ribbons—wreaths, Who let themselves for hire, to kill and slay, For which they carried carving knives in sheaths; Of shoulder-knots, and liveried array, Prouder than any popinjay that breathes; And what was strange, the women seemed to love These men-destroyers other men above. The leader of the party, robed and starr'd, Made a long speech in the terrestrial fashion; Sawing the air, he thumped his bosom hard, With every sign of vehemence and passion, Just to assure us of the king's regard, And to convey the royal invitation, That we should permanently be installed At Phosphan (so their capital is call'd). As in procession we began our march Through groves and fields, and avenues romantic, Green vented his vivacity most arch, In every sort of foolery and antic, Pulling the pig-tail of the leader starch, Who, turning sharply round, with rage half frantic, Cuffed more than once his own astonished folk, Whom he suspected of this shameful joke. But Green's great aim in pulling was to turn Suspicion on the grave decorous Guy, Whose deprecating look of blank concern, (Not to say horror,) language must defy. “You had rather lose,” he cried, in accents stern, “Your friend than joke.” “Why that,” (was the reply,) “Somewhat depends,”—(he sniggered as he spoke,) “Upon the friend, but more upon the joke.” If for a moment, Nokes, you recollect The influence of the moon on people craz'd, How, at its full, it has a marked effect On lunatics, you will not be amazed That here its power, more stringent and direct, Should to a more morbific height be raised. So that the people, to their planet fitted, Are lunatics outright, or else half-witted. Thus their whole architecture's scope and plan, Opposes nature, who, in building trees, Holds out a lesson to masonic man, By suiting them to their localities. Where we require a parasol or fan, And there's no snow to break their canopies, Her boughs she spreads as widely as she can, As in the cedar, cypress, and banyan. In northern climes, where shade we can forego, Her verdant structures take the conic form, As best adapted to shoot off the snow, And bide the pelting of the frequent storm; While the close branches, tapering from below, Support, protect, and keep each other warm: As we discover in the fir and plane, Indigenous to every cold domain. Winter, at Phosphan, is so long and drear, That they've more need of flannel than o shades, Yet they've imported from their southern sphere, A taste for corridors and colonnades, Flat roofs, wide balconies, (to lovers dear,) Projecting porticoes, and cool arcades, Which would appear less thoroughly misplaced, Could they import the climate with the taste. During eight days we led a life serene, Pampered with feasts, and garlanded with roses, But on the ninth a change came o'er the scene, Which ended quickly our apotheosis; The cause of which reverse was Harry Green, Whose frantic course of lunar life discloses Insults most gross—iniquities most daring— And drunken outrages beyond all bearing. Learning these black enormities, the king And council met in secret, made decree That as our crime was such an impious thing, In having claimed a sham divinity, We should, without a formal trial, swing Early next morning on the gallows tree! Which, I submit, was sacrificing us, For their own notions superstitious. How she obtained the secret none can tell, But in the night, Luxora passed our gate, And by her speaking looks and signs, full well Gave us to understand our threatened fate; To shun which doom most truculent and fell, She urged our flight ere yet it was too late, Offering to guide us to the spot where we Left our balloon fast tackled to a tree. In her right hand our fairy guide conceal'd A turning lamp, whose light at times was dead, At times, the glades and copses it reveal'd, Through which in silent fearfulness we fled. And thus we hurried on through wood and field, Till to the moor'd balloon our way we sped, When in we jumped—cut loose—and soar'd together Up in a whirlwind like an eagle's feather. How we should ever re-descend to earth, We hadn't, one of us, the smallest notion; But while our thoughts were struggling for a birth, A moon volcano, in a fierce explosion, Threw out an aerolite, which struck the girth Of our silk globe, and caused a strange commotion— Out went the gas, and down, down, down went we, Shooting through space with dread velocity! All thoughts of life I now resigned, well knowing That if we reached the earth, (and what if not!) At the tremendous rate that we were going, We must be dashed to atoms on the spot. While this sad prospect set my brains all glowing, Whiz! dash! smash! crash! beneath the waves we shot, And down we sank till rising breathless, scared, I oped my peepers and around me stared. A brig I saw upon our starboard bow, The Jane of Boston, Captain Samuel Ford, Who, when he saw us rising from below, Lowered a boat and took us all on board. Both Green and Guy at first were somewhat slow In coming to, but were at length restored, And quaff'd a glass of grog to cure the rum ache Occasioned by the water in their stomach. It seems that we had plunged in our descent Into the Gulf of Mexico—a cast Which saved our bones and lives; so now we bent Our course for Boston, which we reach'd at last, Thence by the diligence we homeward went, Much talking of our strange adventures past, Deeming ourselves all singularly lucky Safely to reach our dwellings in Kentucky ST. GEORGE'S PENITENTIARY. The learned and facetious Dr. Airy Preach'd, 'tother day, a sermon so pathetic, For the St. George's Penitentiary, That it seemed just like giving an emetic To every purse of Christian bowels: Folks sobbed and blubber'd So fast, that handkerchiefs were turned to towels; And the last tear seemed squeezed from out its cupboard. The Doctor smiled (within his sleeve) At these salt tributes to his oratory, Sure that the Institution would receive A sum redounding to his proper glory, From the soul-melted auditory. The sermon o'er, he bent his keen Ear to the tinklings of the plate;— Alas they came with pause deliberate 'Twixt each donation, “Like angel visits, few and far between,” (I like a new quotation,) But, as he caught the sounds, he thought Each had a golden echo, which in fairness Made full atonement for its rareness. “Ay, ay,” soliloquized the preacher, “I told them charity aton'd For multitudes of sins;—they've owned For once the wisdom of their teacher, And, for their many crimes untold, Are doing penance with their gold.” With this auriferous impression, Proud and elate, He moved towards the plate; But ah! how changed was his expression, When, 'stead of the expected prize, Nothing but shillings met his eyes, And those, alas! too few in number Each other to encumber. “Ah!” cried the parson,—“addle-pated Dolts and dunces! when I stated, ‘Love of our species is the just Measure of charity,’ they must Have understood the phrase to be, Love of our specie. Nothing but shillings, shillings still! A strange vagary! Now on my credit, if I had my will, Their Institution's title I would vary, Into the Twelve-penny-tentiary.” Doctor! 'tis my opinion humble, You had not any right to grumble, For he who in this penny age can touch A shilling, gets twelve times as much As other folks;—I state no hoax, But simple fact, devoid of jokes, Or amphibological equivoques; Yes, since the penny banner was unfurl'd, In this two-halfpenny four-farthing world, Have we not thousands who are willing To place unlimited reliance, For learning, news, and science, Upon the twelfth part of a shilling? Have we not Penny Cyclopedias, Penny Magazines and books, Penny Tracts, less good than tedious, For penitents of rueful looks, And penny classics that give scope To boys at penny schools, and misses, To sympathize with poor Ulysses And his beloved Penny-lope? With such economy, Where every cottage is a college, What wonder, in the march of knowledge, That ploughboys understand astronomy? Cries Hodge—“How comes it that the sun, Which nightly seeks the western shore, Rises, as sure as any gun, Next morning where he was afore?” “Spoony!” replies a learned wight, Your ignorance is truly risible; He always travels back at night, And that's the reason he's inwisible.” It was a penny Latinist, who said, In chaos there had been a battle Before the days of men and cattle, Though not set down in Holy Writ, Because in Ovid he had read That was the time when nihil fit. Such tales, (I hope that none have quizzed 'em,) Evince the march of penny wisdom, And might be told ad infinitum, Had we just now the time to write 'em. CHARADE. Sordid and narrow and mean is my First, Where in tenements rank with tobacco and gin, Dwells the toiling mechanic with poverty cursed, 'Mid the breakers of law and the victims of sin. 'Tis gone!—a hall uprises,—view Yon clamorous prize-fighting crew, Wrangling, jangling, sense entangling, Law new-fangling, justice mangling,— 'Tis not Bedlam, but as bad, For money-mania makes them mad. Hey presto pass! a graced saloon behold Where to a brighter star bright stars repair And beauties decked in jewelry and gold, Curtsey to grace and beauty still more rare. From each and all of these, at times, Prison'd within my second's bound, The sick—the sad—the doom'd for crimes, The idle and the gay are found, Swiftly their wingless flight is flown, Their guide a lady's plaything, beckon'd By hand unseen from spot unknown:— What urges thee so fast my second? What hurts the eye, yet mocks the sight, Feels not, yet sighs and makes lament;— As any floating feather light, And yet at times omnipotent. Guarded, my Second, thus, thy might Would seem to challenge fate and death, Yet doom and danger track thy flight, Threat'ning around—above—beneath. See, see, the lightning's angry flash; Hark! what an elemental roar! A shuddering cry—a thunder crash,— My Second's gone—'tis seen no more! Let none but pleasant sights appear, Naught but the turtle-dove be heard, Where Passion-flowers, to lovers dear, Enwreathe an arbour for my Third.— There the heart vents in tender sighs The feeling that no words can reach, Or makes the love-revealing eyes More fond and eloquent than speech. Fulfill'd be all the hopes ye raise, Enamour'd inmates of the bower, And oh! may all your future days Be blissful as the present hour!— [Courtship.] CHARADE. Gin-palace Circe! quit the niche Or den that constitutes my First, Nor from below, thou fair foul witch! Call spirits baleful and accurs'd. She's gone!—Beware! your pouch to pick, Yon crew throws dust into your eyes: Distrust their flowers of rhetoric, They garland whom they victimise. Now to our dearest hopes opposed, My changeful First! thou'rt all we dread; And now, in solid gold disclosed, How eagerly thou'rt coveted! But ah! most fatal art thou when Thou'rt formed beneath the 'whelming wave, Of women fair and gallant men, The Sacrificer and the grave! The friend, the lover, are on thee, My Second! source of many a tear, When their vex'd souls they cannot free From dark suspense, and jealous fear. On thee, within his prison lone, The doom'd assassin or the thief, Vents, in his agony, the groan, Or prays for death as a relief. I see thee speeding overhead, As if thou hadst an eagle's wing, I see thee in the cattle shed, A lifeless and unmoving thing, My Third is fashion'd to enfold Strange implements of war.—Behold Those frames with human features; By time and artificial means They're manufactured to machines For killing human creatures. Obedient moves—east, west, north, south, Up to the breach, or cannon's mouth: Each automatic figure,— 'Gainst friend or foe, whate'er the cause, With equal nonchalance he draws His death dispensing-trigger. Enslaved alike in frame and mind, Life's object for its means resign'd, What gains th'unlucky varlet? Dying, he sleeps on honours couch, And living, flaunts with empty pouch, In outward gold and scarlet. Never were muscles, bones, and will, By such self-sacrificing skill, Made neuter, passive, active. Machine! thou'rt mechanism's pride, But never was its art applied To purpose less attractive! [Barrack.] CHARADE. Oh! what a glorious city!—behold Its obelisks, pyramids, sphinx-guarded fanes, You gaze on Bubastis in Egypt of old, And hark! to those sacred melodious strains! The dulcimer, harp, shawm, and tabret combine With the choral rejoicings and anthems that burst From yon temples august and magnificent shrine, Where prostrated crowds are adoring my First. How strange the conflicting caprices and whims Of blind superstition! some ages are fled, And the object which living was worshipp'd with hymns, And graced with an apotheosis when dead, In Europe is marked for proscription and ban, As leagued with the foul and unsanctified crew Who ply the black art that's forbidden to man, And with spirits of darkness dark courses pursue. And where is my changeable Second display'd? In the belle and the bird, in the damsel and crone, In the foul and the fair, in the mistress and maid, In the dabbler in mud, in the queen on her throne. Who can reckon its changes of form and abode? Arch'd and square, low and dirty, distorted and strait, It is seen in the ditch, on the dunghill, the road, In the huts of the poor, in the halls of the great. It is pure flesh and blood, when from Nature's own hand: Made by man, its diversified substance is found In the fish of the deep, in the beasts of the land, In the trees of the field, in the ore underground. If sometimes 'tis worn unembellish'd and plain, By the wives or the daughters of niggardly churls, At others 'tis deck'd with a glittering train Of diamonds and amethysts, rubies and pearls. In my populous Third what a withering change From the busy Bubastis my first gave to sight: No sunbeam, no moon gilds its desolate range; All is silence profound and perpetual night. It has numberless houses, and each one contains A single inhabitant ever asleep, No footfall is heard in its streets and its lanes, In the midst of a crowd there is solitude deep Here lovers whose union has long been denied, Often meet, but no love-breathing whisper is heard; Here bitterest foemen are placed side by side, But their warfare is over: there's peace in my Third! [Catacomb.] DIAMOND CUT DIAMOND. A RECENT OCCURRENCE. A firm there is, of civic fame, At all events, of notoriety, (Excuse my mentioning its name,) Which crams the public to satiety, With rhyming puffs by shopmen bards, And huge conspicuous placards, Slung on the backs of men and boys, And hobble-de-hoys, Plying all day their devious courses; Or stuck on the tall vans that flare Through every crowded thoroughfare, To cozen asses and to frighten horses. This firm's emporium or bazaar, Near Aldgate pump, is known afar By catchpenny devices manifold, By panes of glass worth many guineas, And all that may attract the ninnies Who think they're buying cheap, and find they're sold. Two clowns, one day, before the shop, In rustic frocks and spatterdashes, Besmirch'd with stercoraceous splashes, Came to a stop; Not to admire the flash habiliments, Which a month's wear would turn to filaments; Not to indulge in talk domestic, But to decide by imprecations, And interchange of objurgations, Some unadjusted feud agrestic. Their flashing eyes and gestures furious Soon show'd that words, howe er injurious, Would not interpret what their rage meant, So they began a fist engagement; And, in the very first attack, One of the rustics, reeling back, Against the window fell slap dash. Zooks! what a crash! 'Twas obvious that the largest pane (If we may speak in Yankee strain) Was sent to everlasting smash. Away the first aggressor hurried, And presently was lost to sight; Out rushed four shopmen, red and flurried, Who seized the window-breaking wight, Aghast and trembling with affright, Dragg'd him into their shop or trap, and Told their master what had happen'd. “It cost ten pounds!” the latter roar'd; “Ten pounds, and you must pay them down, Before your liberty's restored. D' ye hear? hast got the money, clown?” “Ten pounds!” cried Hodge, in blank dismay; “Lord love you, I can never pay. I've got ten shillings and some pence; ('Tis hard to make me such a loser,) But if they'll cover the offence, Take 'em and let me go, now do, sir.” “Blockhead! will such a mite atone? You must make good the whole disaster.” “I've nothing else, sir, of my own; What more I've got belongs to master.” “So you have money then? how much?” “Why, sir, he sent me on a job, To cash a check for fifty pound; 'Tis done, the note is in my fob, Wrapp'd in a paper, safe and sound; But that, you know, I mustn't touch; You wouldn't bring me to disgrace, Wi' loss o' character and place; So don't ye ax me, sir, pray don't; Touch it I mustn't, and I won't.” “Your master, clown, is answerable For your misdeeds, whate'er they be; Down with the note upon the table, And we'll give change and set you free; If not, prepare to go to prison,” “Dang it!” cried Hodge, with face of woe, “What can I do, sir, when you know The money isn't mine, but his'n?” “Stuff!” quoth the magnate of the shop; “Quick! quick! let the police be called, And send him straight to gaol.” “Stop! stop!” Ejaculated Hodge, appall'd, And like a leaf of aspen shaking, Such was his pitiable taking, “Master, if I am miss'd, will say I've robbed him, and have run away It can't be helped—what must be, must.” So saying he fish'd up the note, From the deep fob in which 'twas thrust, And twisted like a papillote, Secured the change, and then departed, Half frightened and half broken hearted, Moaning and muttering, “I fegs! How shall I ever tell my master About this terrible disaster? I'm ruined, sure as eggs is eggs.” Our cits, though chuckling with intense Enjoyment at the clown's expense, Had little cause for mirth, if any. For lo! their banker's clerk appears Next day, and whispers in their ears, “This fifty's forged—not worth a penny!” Such was the fact,—our firm had lost, Besides the broken window's cost, Pounds forty at a single throw: What had they in return to show For such subtraction from their till? A piece of paper, value—nil! Meanwhile the fighting clowns, whose roguery (They were colleagues) the plot had plann'd, By which the tradesmen were trepann'd, Changed their smock frocks for stylish toggery, To Margate steam'd, to take their pleasure, And spent their forty pounds at leisure. THE END.</field>
   </doc>
</add>