<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Sabie, Francis</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Sabie, Francis</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">sabie francis</field>
      <field name="author_text">Sabie, Francis</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">16th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.0241.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1596</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:463148</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Adams Complaint ; The Olde Worldes Tragedie. Dauid and Bathsheba. A Ioue Musa [by Francis Sabie</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">Adams Complaint ; The Olde Worldes Tragedie. Dauid and Bathsheba. A Ioue Musa [by Francis Sabie</field>
      <field name="title_facet">adams complaint</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">adams complaint</field>
      <field name="title_text">Adams Complaint ; The Olde Worldes Tragedie. Dauid and Bathsheba. A Ioue Musa [by Francis Sabie</field>
      <field name="year_display">1596</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1596</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1596</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463148&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463148&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Sabie, Francis&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;sabie francis&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Adams Complaint ; The Olde Worldes Tragedie. Dauid and Bathsheba. A Ioue Musa [by Francis Sabie&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;adams complaint&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1596&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1596&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Sabie, Francis&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Adams Complaint&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;The Olde Worldes Tragedie. Dauid and Bathsheba. A Ioue Musa [by Francis Sabie]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Imprinted ... by Richard Iohnes [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1596&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp3440&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;[52] p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Adams Complaint&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;The Olde Worldes Tragedie. Dauid and Bathsheba. A Ioue Musa [by Francis Sabie]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 95 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To the Right Reuerend Father, Richard by the Prouidence of God, Bishop of Peterborough, F. S. wisheth increase of temporall and spirituall blessings. Learned Mecœnas, fauorite of Muses, Renowned Patron, hater of abuses: Who sitting in Religions golden Chaire, Thou her, she thee adornes with vertues rare. As Phœbe from her Phœbus borrowes light, Wherwith againe she decketh him by night. So likewise thou: She thee with swauity, Thou gracest her with moderne grauitie. Both I my selfe, and Muse will now assay, Our tributorie debt to thee to pay. By dutie bound, vnbound I can be neuer, Vow'd to your Lordships seruice now and euer. Your Lordships at commandment. FRANCIS SABIE. ADAMS Complaint. New formed Adam of the reddish earth, Exilde from Eden, Paradice of pleasure: By Gods decree cast down to woes from mirth, From lasting joyes to sorrowes out of measure: Fetch'd many a sigh, comparing his estate With happie blisse, which he forewent of late. Rowse vp thy selfe (my Muse) a tale to tell, A dolefull tale in sad and plaintiue verse: How man in blisse from happinesse once fell, Although not woont such horrors to rehearse. Oh great Iehouah, heauens great Architect, In this sad worke my fainting Muse direct. With pensiue heart he trac'd the earth new founded, Wringing his hands in lamentable wise: Earth neuer with ground-cleauing ploughshare wounded, Now to the starry globe he cast his eyes, And now to Eden where he erst remained, From which with fiery sword he was detained. O haplesse Adam (quoth he) vnkind father, Vnnaturall Parent, childrens fatall foe: From whence all mankind doe such curses gather: Authour of death, first bringer in of woe. No sooner fram'd of thine al-making God, Then purchasing his sin-correcting rod. Did not Iehouah lend to thee his grace, More plentifull then other liuing things: Who hauing fram'd thee, did prouide a place, Euen Paradice, the shadow of his winges. Amongst a thousand sundry kindes of meat, Forbidding thee one only fruit to eat. Consider birds, beasts, fish, and other Creature, Behold, they all looke groueling on the ground: He vnto heauen erected hath thy feature, That thou maist see his woonders, which abound. Yet thou on whom most louingly he looked, Hast first of all to anger him prouoked. For thee he made heauens Azur-painted cou'ring, Adorning it with starres, with Sunne, with Moone: The blustring windes within the aire be hou'ring, That thou his maruels mightst behold alone. Yet thou his greatest fabricke, with thy sinne To anger him didst first of all beginne. For thee he fram'd earths euen-poysed globe, Hanging it in the aire to humaine woonder: And decked it with fruites, as with a robe, Making the seas deuide the same in sunder. The seas he dight with fish, the earth with beasts For thee, yet thou hast broken his behests. What didst thou want amid that pleasant plot, Prepar'd for thee, by his all-working skill: Thou canst not thinke, the thing thou haddest not, Without all griefe thou liued'st, not knowing yll, Pride, and desire of knowledge made thee taste The fruite, which did indeed thy knowledge waste. Had not thy God sayd, taste not of the tree, The fruit perhaps had still remain'd vntouched: Hencefoorth shall this enormity by thee In minds of thy posterity be couched, Burning desire of secrets which are hidden, And fiery zeal of things which are forbidden. What made thy wife the fruit so to desire, The goodly hue and beautie of the same? What did allure and set thy mind on fire? The glozing words of thy seducing Dame. Henceforth therfore will womens words &amp; beautie Seducers be of mankind from their dutie. Blind Euah, saw'st thou not as in a glasse, How Sathan with his guiles did circumuent thee: Beheldst thou not the brittle world alas, How it with vading vanity did tempt thee. Then how the flesh did combate with the Spirite, And all of heauenly blisse thee to disherite. O certaine type, true figure, perfect map Of future euilles t'all mankind to fall: These still with sleights, as in a subtill trap, Will seeke to make all humaine ofspring thrall. Whilst Sun remaines, &amp; whilst Moon doth endure, These archfoes will their treason put in vre. Wouldst thou in blisse not keep one little law? How wilt thou now a multitude obserue, When many thousand deuils thy mind withdraw, To which thou canst not choose but needs must swerue? And hauing sweru'd, thy conscience plainly saith, That euery sin deserues a seuerall death. Then viewed he the cerule-colored Pole, With pitchy clouds which gan to be obscured, Blacke foggie mists rose from earths lumpish mole, Earths mole by plow-swaine neuer yet manured Ay me (quoth he) this may a token be, That for my sinne my maker frownes on me. Day-guiding Sol with his bright-burning lampe, Obscures his beames, in clowdes his glorie hiding: Night-ruling Luna waxeth pale and dampe, Asham'd of me, my glory not abiding. Star-bearing skies, with your earth-cou'ring valt, For me it is, you frowne for my default. Rain-sending clowdes, poure out your watry showers On earth, vast Orbe, which from the seas you borrow: Cold-causing frosts deface the fragrant flowers With hoarie rymes, true types of future sorrow: Adam now made, his maker hath offended, To whom so many blessings he extended. Ah how Dame Ver the ground with flowers spread, Vauting her selfe amid that pleasant pallace: Foure chrystall lakes distilled from one head: Refreshing hearbs with humor, thee with sollace. Thou didst not sow, no labour didst thou take, The earth bore all things neuer toucht with rake. See now how Sommers beauty-spoyling drought Earth of her party-colloured vestments robs: Transporting all the buds which Ver had brought, To fruitlesse hay, dry straw, and withered shrubs. Then mystie Autumne with his raigne, bereaues The earth of hearbes, the trees of parched leaues. If any Vernall remnant yet be left: By Aestaes heat, and Autumns raine not spoyled: The same by chil-cold Winter is bereft Of vigor: and with hoary frosts defoyled. Frost making earth a Chaos to resemble, For mine offence, wheron to thinke I tremble. The blewish skyes did only me protect, I sought not for a stately brick-built Castle: I needed not a sheltring roofe erect, Against tempestuous windes and raine to wrastle. The sturdie Oake in mountain tops did stand, The stones lay still, I tooke them not in hand. Now Adam stir thee like the nimble pricket, Pursu'd with houndes, ransacke thy Grandams bones, Cut downe the massie Oke from grouie thicket, To forge a tyled roofe for playned stones. Forge thee a shelter, edifie an holde, To shield thee from the rage of winde and colde. As I was made, so liu'd I with my spouse, Both naked were, yet knew it not (O rarenesse) We felt no colde, yet liued in no house, We blushed not one at anothers barenesse. But (out alas) what shamefastnes we suffred. When vgly sinne our nakednesse vncou'red. Learne heer (O all posterities) the shrewdnesse Of Sathan, and his treacherous assaultes: VVho hauing once seduced man to lewdnesse, Exaggerates the greatnesse of his faults, Making him blush like Adam in the garden. Only to bring him in dispaire of pardon. Ye winged birds, send out your wofull quips In leauelesse trees, once glutting you with berries: Cold winter now your tender bodies nips. Depriuing earth of hearbs, and trees of Cheries: Your euerlasting Spring abridged is, And all for Adam who hath done amisse. Four-footed beasts inhabitants of field, Poure out your plaints among the rurall brambles, Now must your hides mans corps from weather shield, Your carkasses hang vp on bloody shambles. Diue in the deep, ye water-hanting Fishes, Now must ye serue to nourish man in dishes. Help to lament, ye water-flowing Fountaines, Congealing Frosts your passages will hinder: Keep in your buds, ye Gote-frequented mountaines. Receiuers of the hoarie frosts of winter. Woods, hearbs, and trees, all terrene things bewayle, Teares ease the mind, though little doe preuaile. Proud Adam not content with thy condition, Blessed estate, and ten times happie calling: Sought'st to atchieue more glory, whose ambition Hath wrought thy fatall ouethrow in falling. Aspiring to the knowledge of thy maker, hast lost that blisse wherof thou wert partaker. This roote of pride (this neuer-withering weed) Prouoker first of mankind vnto follie: Will still attaint and cleaue vnto thy seed, As twinding Yuie on the tender Hollie. Imbracing it, till it hath suck'd it drie, And wanting sap, they both together die. This noysome root in euery ground will spring, The meanest man in thought will still aspire: The Potentate will seeke to be a King, The King to be an Emperour will desire, And he to be more higher in degree, Will also striue, if higher he may bee. I sought moe dainties hauing ouer manie, From hence shall come desire of varietie: Contentment seldome will be found in anie, Lothsome contempt will wait vpon satietie. All men from me will this infection plucke, As Spyders doe from flowers poyson sucke. Fond wretches, who in sinfull follie blinde, Did thinke to hide you from Iehouahs face: As doth the purblind Hare, or fearfull Hind, VVhom yelping hounds doe still pursue in chace. Ah no, ye cannot, his all-seeing eie VVill find you out, where euer you doe lie. Take I to me the south-windes ayrie winges, And in the vtmost coast of earth conuay mee: Take I to me the Dolphins watery sinnes, And in the seas vnsounded-bottom lay mee: Let earth into her secret wombe me swallow, Yet will his glorious eie-beams still me follow. My guilty conscience sayd, I had offended, VVhat sting on earth more hellish can we find, A sore it is which cannot be amended, A worme which alwayes gnawes vpon the mind. Run where I will, into all lands betake me, Yet will a wounded conscience ne'r forsake me. O thundring sayings: terrifying wordes, Heart-taming speaches, cleauing rockes in sunder: Proceeding from the supreame Lord of Lords: VVhich in mine eares resounded like a thunder, Words causing earth an Aspen leafe resemble, Which at the breath of euerie wind doth tremble. VVhere art thou Adam? shamest thou my Deitie, Ay me, needs must I my sinne display: Supposing earst my vicious impietie, That euery shaking bramble would bewray. Thus shall it also fare with all my seede, Committing any detestable deed. How faine would I my guiltie mind haue cleared, Alleadging Eue was causer of mine euill: She to excuse her selfe, as then appeared. Laid all the fault vpon the subtill Deuill. Like clowds which pour their rain vpon hie-waies, They into riuers, riuers into seas, This sayd; he turn'd him to the vntill'd field, VVhere vncoth weeds, and fruitlesse brambles breed, The earth which earst most fragrant hearbs did yeeld, VVith thornes and thistles now was ouer-spread. Oh see (quoth he) the earth for mine yll deeds, Rob'd of braue robes, and clad in baser weedes. Deare Grandam earth, thy fountaine heads set open, Like Chrystall teares, my sorrowes to discouer: Now must thy mole with deluing share be broken: A crooked rake thy tilled field passe ouer. For me these shrubs and prickling thorns thou bearest For me these yl-beseeming weeds thou rearest. The heifar now in fields must not be idle, The seruile Asse must beare an heauy packe: The Courser braue restrained with a bridle, The silly sheep his woolly fleece must lacke. Horse, sheepe, Asse, heifar help me all to mone, I causer am of all your woes alone. Still thought he on this string to tune his woes, And forward went, but loe, three-horned Cattle Neer vnto him amid proud bearing Does, With frowning gesture menaced a battle. At length not able to forbeare him longer, Two weaker ones ran both against the stronger. Th'encountred beast receiuing others stroke, With like assault the one of them requighted, Assault resounding like a falling Oke, Which threw th'one backe, the other fled affrighted. And left his friend distrest, his foe inulted, The victorer triumphantly insulted. Ah see (he sayth) see heer a world of woe, An heap of euils vnto thy seed ensuing: What maladies from lewd desires doe growe, As beasts, so men with sauagenesse induing. Ay me, what dolors, euils, and deeds vnjust Shall not arise to man through sinfull lust. Heer maist thou haue a president of warres, Tumultuous discord, horrible dissention, Blood-shedding horror, disagreeing jarres, Inhumaine murthers, pitifull contention: The mightiest shall be viewed on of all, The poore dispis'd, the weaker thrust to wall. Whilst things go well friends wil be alwayes neer thee Prosperity will loued be of many: But falling downe, thy dearest friends will feare thee, Aduersity not holpen vp of any. The fawning beast doth this presignifie, Who quite forsooke his friend in misery. The small shall subject be vnto the greater, Nobility through strength shall make his entrie: The welthyer will thinke himselfe the better, For couetousnesse will spring, the root of Gentry. Though all sprong from one father and one mother, Yet euery one will striue t'excell his brother. See how the Eagle with his bloody clawes Doth massacre the house-frequenting Sparrow: The lordly Lyon with his murthering jawes, Doth rend the Hind as earth is rent of harrow. The fearfull Whale, that monster in the deep The lesser fish doth in his bellie keepe. Whale, Eagle, Lyon, fitly ye presage Blood-sucking tyrants and inhumaine murtherers, Which will the weaker sort oppresse with rage, Arch-foes to vertue, and to vices furtherers. Blush Adam, blush to name these dreadful terrors, First causer of all maladies and errors. The pleasant Larke delights to mount on hie, The little wren neer to the earth below: The greedy Gleyd betwixt them both doth flie, The Doue in course is swift, the Lapwing slowe. The shew mens sundry callings and conditions, These note mens diuers minds and dispositions. The ayerie-winged blasts as euer mutable, And neuer in one certaine place abide: So mans condition shall be euer changeable, No ground so firme in which he shall not slide. What seat so strong or what so sure estate which shall not subject be to frowning fate. O happie wight, ten times shall he be blest, VVho with the wren dare not presume to mount: VVith meane estate contented who doth rest, And blisse in sole tranquility doth count, Considering that great things are view'd of all, And highest things are soonest like to fall: That highest things are soonest like to fall, The reaching Pine on mountaines doth betoken, which sooner then the shrub or bramble small, with raging blastes of hoysting windes are broken. VVhat mortall things hencefoorth on earth ensuing Shall not be subject to times fatall ruin. Times ruin shall so dyre obliuion breed In men, that noting their so frayle variety, Forgetting me, the cause thereof, my seed Shall faine to Fate an euer-changing deity. Proportraying her vpon a round wheele dancing, Euerting some, and other some aduancing. Alas, no sooner night-expelling morning, Al-hyding heauen from her blacke rug exempteth: But viewing me, and mine offences scorning, Her snowie cheekes with rednes she besprenteth, Disdaining Sols bright beams should long behold me In Sable night bright Hesperus doth fold me. Vile Couetousnes in me first tooke his roote, For moe things thirsting, when no thing I wanted: Still shall it hold my children by the foote, And in the hearts of all my seed be planted. Now shall rush in the greedy zeale of mony, which men will labour for, as Bees for hony. Now shall rush in the fiery thirst of gaine, And golde in bowels of the earth inclosed: Which men by toyle and labour will obtaine, And coffer vp from his darke dungeon losed. By mortall wightes rare mettals will be knocked, Which earth in her close treasure-house had locked. Now shall be found the hurtfull mine of Iron, For which men wil into earths bellie enter: The glittering steele besieged foes t'enuiron, They now will into swords and Lances temper. What mortall thing so hard? or what so geason, Wil not be done and found by humaine reason? The lofty Pine which mountaine top affoords, Cut downe, shall now into a Mast be squared: The yellow brasse nayled to Firre-tree boords, Shall cut the seas, as earth with plough is ared. Sea-Porposses and Dolphins huge shall woonder, To see their Cerule waters cleft in sunder, The ruddie Diamond and the Saphir faire, In th'vtmost coast of earth shall now be sought, The bright Smaragd, the Pearl, and Onix rare, Fetch'd from the East, full dearly shall be bought, O into-what so deepe and huge an hell, Will not the thirst of riches men compell? This sayd, on earth his glowring eyes he fastned, There saw an Ant, a little creeping else, Who dragg'd with her a Barley graine, and hastned Home to her caue, graine bigger then her selfe: O learne he cries, learne Adam of this Ant, To worke in youth, least afterward thou want. Behold the Bee, a silly painfull creature, How wittily shee laboreth in Sommer: Reposing food, she only taught by nature, Least barraine winters penurie should numb her, Her industrie giues to thee an example, how thou shouldst liue, &amp; in what waies to trample. Now Adam must thou labour, ditch and delue, Graft, plant, walke, run, hedge, fence, plow, harrow, sowe Pluck downe, reare vp, set munifie, build shelue, VVeep, laugh, striue, wrastle, bind vp, gather, mowe, Thresh, cary out grind, bake, brue, spin and card, Knock, beat, wash, dry, buy, sell, sleep, watch and ward In sweat of browes and horrible vexation, To get my liuing shall I be constrained: VVhat shall man see but dolefull tribulation, Vnto his death from time that he is wained. Nought shall his race be but a vale of sinning, Fond, sinfull, fraile, in end, midst and beginning. How vaine is wordly pompe? how fraile and brittle? How soon is man of earthlie things bereft: His pleasures passe as swiftly as a shittle Cast from the weauers right hand to the left: His orient hue as vading as a flower, VVhich floorisheth and dyeth in an hower. O wretched man! O life most transitorie! Deceiptfull world, foule sinke of filthy errors: Eye-pleasing shades of vaine delightfull glorie Deepe gulfe of sinne, vast dungeon of terrors, Receptacle of woful tribulations Grand treasure-house of all abhominations. O sea of sorrowes, laborinth of woes, Vale full of cares: abysse of imbecilitie: Thief-harbouring house, field full of armed foes, Stil-turning orb, true map of mutahility. Affoording man as many false yl-willers As woods haue trees, as trees haue Caterpillers. Of lumpish earth Iehouah me created, To th' end I should not glorie in my feature: And I againe to earth must be translated By Gods iust doome, the end of euery creature: Then wherto should I trust on earth abiding, Sith for my fault all earthly things are sliding, When first of all man draweth virall breath And spirite, he to die beginneth then: No worldly thing more certaine then is death, Nor more vncertaine then the hower when. O lend me then a font of springing teares, To weep my fill for mans vnconstant yeares. Ah weladay, me thinks for mine offences, My God sayth still I must to earth againe: O how the thought of death appales my sences, Though end it be of all mans woe and paine. So likewise shall all my posteritie Feare it, though end of all calamity. O great Iehouah, woonderfull in might, How wisely hast thou wrought all things, concealing The certaine houre of death from mortal wight, Yet certaintie thereof to him reuealing. Done surely by thy skilfull prouidence, That man should feare and learne obedience. Me thinks I see (O let me yet diuine) How many of my sonnes will goe astray, Erecting houses, raysing buildings fine, As though they were inthroniz'd here for ay. O let them know that for my foule offence, by Gods just doome all flesh must wander hence. Nor he that shall on earth the longest dwel, Not he that shall in prowesse be the rarest, Not he that shall in wisedome most excel, Not he that shall in visage be the fairest. With wisedome, beautie, age or courage fell Shall able be impartiall death t'expell. O wretched Euah, mankinds deadlie Foe, Accursed Grandame, most vngentle mother, Sin-causing woman, bringer of mans woe, Woe to thy selfe, and woe vnto all other. Thy mighty maker in his iust displeasure Hath multipli'd thy sorrowes out of measure. In paine shalt thou thy seed conceiue and beare, In peril shalt thou of it be discharged: Thou shalt it softer vp with tender care, A thousand wayes thy griefs shal be enlarged: Thou shalt be guided by thy mans direction, He as a Lord shall haue thee in subjection. O cursed worme, O exerable serpent: Blisse-hating Dragon: most abhorred creature. Infectious Adder: venom-breathing verment, The food of enuie, sdeignfull scorneof Nature: Fals-hearted traitor, harbourer of euill: Darke den of spight, foule cabbin of the Deuill. Most lothsome be thou of Iehouahs worke, Enuyed both of man and feeding cattell: In vnfrequented valleyes shalt thou lurke, And with thy stinging tongue still menace battell. Man seeing thee, shall feare and seeke thy bane, As instrumentall author of his paine. For want of feet: through woods and deserts thicke Vpon thy griesllie belly shalt thou slide: And for thy food dust of the earth shalt licke, Such plagues shall thee (O lothsome worme) betide, Such woes on thee Iehouah hath disbursed, Pronouncing thee of all his workes most cursed. The husband-man among the rurall bushes, VVill start, and thinke each moouing twig a foe Still fearing least among the marshy rushes Thou lying hid, shouldst worke his second woe. Thy deadly sting, and golden speckled hew, In false pretence thy glosing words doe shew But thou (O Sathan) proud infernall deuill, Chiefe actor in this dolefull tragedie: Lord of ambition, maister of all euill, Thy fatall fall behold I prophecie: From out the woman shall an issue spring, VVhich will preuayle against thy deadly sting. Between her seed and thee (O fearfull fiend) Shall be continuall enmity and fight: Thou shalt but pricke her heele, she in the end Shall conquer thee, and ouerthrow thy might. Then man reioyce, O Adam cease to waile, Thy conqueror shall now no whit preuaile. O woondrous pittie, vndeserued kindnesse, Of earths-sole founder to the worke he made: Who seeing man cast downe in sinne and blindnesse, So speedily him promisd help and ayd. Ayd, certaine ayd his arch-foe to repell, To conquer death, and conquer conquering hel. Rejoyce then earth, cease frowning heauens to glower, Now broken are hels euer-lasting barres, From whence man tooke by Gods almighty power, Shall mount aloft aboue the twinkling starres: There with the womans seed which promis'd is, For euermore to raigne in heauenly blisse. Ye chirping birds, whose partie colloured plumes With gentle sound the whistling aire doe trouble: In shady dales send foorth your dolefull tunes, Let Ecchoes shrill your dulcid notes redouble. Adam your Lord exil'd from Eden garden By faith and mercy hath obtayned pardon. Harmonious Larke, let neue blushing morning See dankish earth, but mount thou from the ground: And blewish skies with pleasant notes adorning. For mans redemption signes of mirth resound: Sweet Philomene, let neuer Hesper shine Ere thou haue tun'd a thousand ditties fine. Mild Eurus raigne in blustering Boreas place, Leap sportiue fish aboue the Chrystall riuer: Man reconciled to his God by grace, Shall now in heauenly blisse abide for euer. For these glad tydings, frolike tender lambes, In pastures pleasant with your merie dammes. And lastly, Adam, sith it is decreed, That thou must fight ere thou canst win the fort: Fight manfully, trust in the promisd seed, And be most sure thou shalt arriue the port, Port full of joy and heauenly blessednes. Free from all cares, and worldly wretchednes. FINIS. The old Worlds Tragedie. I sing of horrors sad and dreadfull rage, Of stratagems wrought in the former age, Contagious vice, and in conclusion, Of massacres, death and confusion: Vouchsafe my muse, my dolefulst muse to tell What made the King of heauen to be so fell: Sole Architect of earth and earthly landes, So furiously the fabricke of his handes To bring to ruine: can Iehouah then Poure out such fearfull threats on mortall men, Full sixteen hundred years from worlds creation, And fifty sixe by sacred computation: When liuing things replenished the ground. And earth with mortall wights did first abound: A dolefull Tragedie was brought to passe, Earth was the stage whereon it acted was, Vpon the stage first came impietie, Vaunting her selfe against the Deity. She in short time began to growe to hed, And all the earth at length she captiue led. Then came in foule desire and lothsome lust, She in short time seduced euen the just: Who gazing on the beautie of the wicked, Began with lewd concupiscence be pricked, In matrimony to their daughters linking Their sonnes, and at sinnes detestable winking. The Host was ofttimes slaine by lodged stranger, Guest of his hoste stood many times in danger. Vile Auarice all mortall hearts possessed, The weaker lay in euery street oppressed: Men sought by cruell bloodshed gaine to gather, The sonne for riches sought to slay his father: The brother mixed poyson for his brother, She for her daughter: daughter for her mother. Pale enuie left her Adder-haunted den, And rul'd on earth as supreame Queene of men, Aspiring pride with weapons in her hand, To warre against humility did stand, Wherewith in fight she killed her at last, And from the stage all massacred her cast. Then dreadfull wrath met patience at the field, And shortly she compelled her to yeeld. Fals-hearted treason like a faithfull louer, His woluish backe with sheepish skin did couer: And meeting with true friendship secretely, Gaue her the stab (O monstrous villanie) Fidelity lay slaine by treacherie, Pure chastitie by lothsome letcherie. Here lay the seruant by the master killed, There masters blood lay by the seruant spilled. Then might you see man-murthring falshood fiight With verity, and ouercome her quite: Religion by Atheisme proud was banisht, And she forthwith to heauenly kingdomes vanisht: As soone as ere good Conscience shew'd her head, By disobedience she was stroken dead. Then Gluttony vpon the stage made entrance Prodigiously who slew dame Temperance. Excesse appear'd with strange varietie, And fiercelie put to flight Sobriety. Enuious Anger vehementlie assailed Dame Patience, and in the end preuayled. Then mounted on the earth obliuious Sloth, She Industrie and labor conquer'd both, Iniustice lastlie with an hideous rout Of hellish furies trac'd the stage about: Her visage sterne, her hands in blood imbrued Her breast of Iron, vgly Toads she spued: Her standerd-bearer was ambitious pride, And next vnto her went Don Homicide, Next vnto them a ranke of Enuies brood, Begirt with Adders, serpents were their food: Straight after them excesse and gluttonie, Deformed Sloth, and impious Simphonie A thousand other stygian hagges and moe, Then with their Queen impietie did grow. Whom just Astrea seeing in this sort, A sudden feare amaz'd her mean report, And leauing earth with all that hideous crew, Vnto the skies without delay she flew. And now huge Gyants vpon earth remained, with whose vile ofspring al the earth was stained Of them to Damsels faire committing seed, A deuillish kind of people there did breed: A People fierce and of exceeding stature Pestifferous, and prone to sin by nature. These tyranniz'd and liued at their pleasure, Oppressing weaker people without measure. With dreadfull rigor keeping them in awe, Despising iustice, breaking Natures law. These heaped sinne on sinne, and fault on fault, As high as Pelion or Olympus vault: As high as Pindus or steep Ossa either, Were Pindus or steep Ossa clapt together, When suddenly from his most glorious throne, Whereon he sitting guides all things alone. Iehouah founder of the starrie pole, Of waterie seas, and of the earthly mole, Daign'd vpon earth his sacred eies to cast, Eies seeing all things in the world so vast. He saw how vice had growne vnto a head, Injustice all the earth had ouerspread: He saw how sinne and vile impietie Vanted themselues against his Deitie. The Adder-pawed gyants, mounts of euill Touching the skies, base children of the deuill. His sacred head heerat he gan to shake, Wherat the skies, the earth, and all did quake: He sighed, and most sorrowfull he was, That euer mortall man was brought to passe: He grieu'd in heart that euer he created Man, who with sinne was so contaminated. All things (quoth he) wherin remaineth breath, I purpose to destroy with sudden death: This hand which fram'd all mortall things aliue All earthlie things of life shall now depriue, From man to beasts, from birds to things which creep, All flesh shall taste of my displeasure deep. The birds swift winges shall not his body saue, The Lyons force, nor Grants courage braue, Thus am I minded, thus doe I intend, All liuing creatures now shall haue an end. But yet on earth one only man there dwelled All other men in justice who excelled: The third from Enoch was he in discent, Enoch who all his life vprightly spent: Enoch of life who neuer was bereauen, Enoch, who liuing was rapt into heauen. Methushelah who all men did surpasse In length of life, his Grandsire cleped was. It was just Noah, Lamechs sonne vpright: Three sonnes he had, Shom, Ham &amp; Iaphet hight He loued vertue, vice he did eschew, Iehouah therfore fauour did him shew. Againe Earths founder his all-seeing eyes Cast on the world from top of Cerule skies. Againe he saw all wickednes abound, In all the earth no justice could be found. The children bathed in their fathers blood, All nought he saw, and nothing that was good Vast fields of sin, Abysses fraught with lewdnes Realmes full of errors, mountaines huge of shrewdnes. The height whereof vnto his throne ascended, And with their stench his nostrils fore offended Then vnto Noah, Lamechs sonne he spake, An end of all things now I meane to make: All flesh wherin remaineth liuing spirit, Of vitall breath I purpose to disherit. Ah how it grieues me now that I haue framed Man, who with sin the earth hath so defamed. Make thee an Arke of Pine trees verie strong, Three hundred cubits shalt thou make it long. Threescore in breadth, and thirty cubits hie, Make rooms in it where seueral things may lie. Three sundrie stories shalt thou in it frame, And round about with pitch close vp the same: For I vpon the earth a flood will bring, Wherwith I will subuert ech liuing thing, But vnto thee my couenant will I make, My couenant which I neuer meane to breake; Thou with thy wife, thy sons, &amp; thy sons wiues Shal in the arke be shut and saue your liues. Of euery lining creature also twaine, A male and female shall with thee remaine, And lay vp food for thee and euery creature, Euen seuerall food according to their nature. The ark was made, &amp; al things brought to passe As God commanded, so it framed was. Then spake Iehouah vnto him, goe thou Into the arke with all thy houshold now: For seu'n dayes hence shall mighty rain abound Wherwith I mean to couer al the ground. Then Noah with his family also Iust eight persons into the arke did goe, And now the hower was neer, the fatal hower Wherin Iehouah meant to shew his power: Sixetimes Aurora with her blushing hew Had seene the earth all darke with hoary dew. Now pitchie night six times gan dim the skies, Last night of sollace vnto mortall eyes: O Luna still detaine thy blackish horse, Let neuer dismall Tytan run his course, Bright Vesper still continue thou thy race. Let neuer fatall, day-star thee deface. Who can alas, expresse the dolefull ruin, And piteous horror of the day ensuin. Now fro her chamber comes the scowling morning, Her selfe still in a night-gowne blacke adorning: Tytan arose, but yet his glorious head With pitch-resembling cloudes was ouerspread, Blacke foggie mystes rose from the earthly mole, Ascending vp vnto the aery pole. Windes thronged foorth, and stroue in skies aloft, As ciuill warres among them had been wrought, As craggie hils had broken been by charmes, As all Eolia had beene vp in armes. Windes, ayre and cloudes, all meant the ayre to sacke, O now or neuer goes the world to wracke, Then thou (O woe) heauens Architect began To poure thy feareful threats on mortall man: The glowring skies resounded like a thunder, As though heauens sacred vault had cleft in sunder, As though ten thousand Cannons huge discharged Their roaring sounds with fall offorts enlarged. His right hand shoke the earth, his left hand crushed. The clouds, then raine in great aboundance rushed. Raine poured foorth, yet not content, his anger Enforced swelling tydes on earth to wander. Then broken were the heads of watrie fountaines, They gushed from the feet of craggie mountaines. Seas lent them waues their courses to maintaine, Earth made them passage to his vtter bane, Now had the morne still clad in mourning weeds, Thrise open'd gates to Phæbus fiery steeds, Steeds smoking wet, yet from his flaming carre, No light did come, blacke mystes his light did scarre: And now the three dayes raine and flowing flouds Had spoyled quite green hearbs and pleasant buds: And shortly did the husband man complaine, That all his whole years trauell and his paine Were brought to ruin, corne and goodly flowers Were prostrate laid with ouer-flowing showers. The sillie birds with violence of weather In bushes thicke did shroud themselues together: Beasts shrinking vnder grouie hedges stood Halfe drown'd with wet, halfe dead for want of food. By this time waters all the earth did couer, The falling raine and rising flouds ran ouer All champion countries, where men lately plowed Now waters stood, and Scullers might haue rowed. O then on earth was heard a piteous crie, Men crying out, beasts roaring plaintiuely. Then first of all began the Gyants sterne To shake for feare, and flinty hearts to yerne. Raine falling, and seas rising without pittie, Made entrance into euerie house and cittie: As when a Fort or sacked citties walles, With violence of rampir'd engines falles, The furious foe runnes raging through the streets, With bloody weapons killing whom he meetes. An hideous cry and sound arriseth then Of maymed women and distressed men. Men seeing weapons come to worke their bane, Yet could not shun them: O what greater paine? So far'd it with the people of this time, Some vpon roofes and turrets high did clime, One takes the highest mountaine he can see, Another sits a fishing in a tree. One thrusts himselfe into a wherry boat, And desperately vpon the waues doth floate. And euery one did seeke to clyme aloft, For eurie one to shun the waters sought, They saw the waters come to stop their breath, Yet could not shun't, O greater griefe then death. Their dollours might haue been compared well To one that dying heares the passing bell. Some were already drown'd, thus stood the case, He liu'd the longest who had highest place: And now were turrets high and mountaines couered, And leauie trees which in the aire erst houered: O lend me words the dollours to display, The Fatall horrors of this dismall day. There might you see how louingly the mother With her sweet daughter kissed one the other: One piteoussy requesting others help, Yet neither of them knew to ayd himselfe. The dying sonne now at the latest gaspe, About his clasping fathers neck did claspe. And ready now to bid their last farewell, Were snatched both with seas and billows fel: The Lord &amp; seruant both at one time snatched, One furiously hold on the other catched. And still in surging waues together cleft, Till both of breath together were bereft. The tyrannizing Giants bodies grim Now with the criples liuelesse corps did swim. The subject with the scepter-bearing king, The murthring billows spar'd no liuing thing. Some might you see half dead and halfe aliue, Like water-fowles now rise, &amp; now to diue. Some turning round, and violently borne Al headlong downe, their lims in sunder torn. The brisle-bearing bore, and gentle sheepe Swam both together in the surging deep. The silly Lambe was with the rauening Wolfe Drown'd in the vast no-pitie taking gulfe. The liuelesse Lyon in the deep did swim, Nought did the Tygers courage profit him, Nought booted it the Beare to roar and grind, No profit by his swiftnesse got the Hind. And hauing long time with exceeding paine Flowne through the aire, disturbed still with raine, The wearie bird not finding any ground, Fals downe in seas, and at the last is drown'd. And now the Arke where Noah did abide, Was hoisted vp with ouer-swelling tide. One while all hidden to the earth it fell, As though it would haue gone to visit hell, One while againe it seemed to arrise, And suddenly would mount vp to the skies: No sterne it had, no mast, no sayle, no guide, But caried was at pleasure of the tide. Twise twenty dayes as blacke as any cole The murthering raine distilled from the Pole. The tallest mountaines in the world so wide, Now couered were with ouer-swelling tide. The ayrie Alpes and eke Pernassus faire Now hidden were with waues, a woonder rare, Snow-bearing Pindus and Olympus steep, Both at this time lay hidden in the deep. Now first of all igniferous Aetnas caues, And Ciclops flames were quench'd with salt-sea waues, Sweet-smelling Ide and sacered Ismarus, Aspiring Pelion and hard Caucasus, In Scythian mounts, where murthering Tygres hanted: Now vgly shapes of monstrous sea-fish vanted: The Dolphins woonders vnder watrie floods, To see faire turrets and thicke grouie woods. In steed of sacrifice on Altars faire Sit seemly Marmaydes combing of their haire, In Churches eke their Organists now wanting, Melodious Odes and ditties now recanting. The vglie dog-fish and deuouring Whales Gainst pinacles did dash their shining skales: And where the Goat was woont her food to swallow, Foule Porposses and seaish monsters wallow. Now from his glorious pallace heauens creator Look'd downe, and saw the world a sea of water: All was a sea yet wanted it a coast, Then thought he on the Arke and Noah tost: Through all the world and earth, which manie a night Hid vnder seas, had seen no cheerfull light. Foorthwith he charg'd the foggie mysts to vanish, Then all the windes tempestuous did he banish: And then retreyt vnto the water soundes, Commanding it to keepe within his bounds: Commanding it his fountaines to restraine, And them to stop their springing heads againe. Clouds foorthwith fled, and tempestes were appeased, The seas return'd, and running fountaines ceased. The scowling morne now left his mourning robe, And smilinglie blush'd on the watery globe. And shortly might you see meane turrets peepe, And tops of Pine-trees from the flouds to creepe: The fleeting arke which long had cleft in sunder the vast deluge, both caried vp and vnder, Now vnto East, and now vnto the west, At length in mounts of Armeny did rest. Twise twentie times had Phœbus drencht his beames, And Car in graue Oceanus his streames. When as the framer of the subtill Barke, A window did set open in th Arke. And foorth he sent a Rauen thence, to know If waters still the land did ouerflow. Foorth flew she, but returned presently So went and came vntill the earth was drie. Againe, he sends a siluer-winged Doue, To see if still the waters were aboue. Out flies the Doue, &amp; through the aire doth go As swift as any arrow from a bowe. Much aire she cuts, and in the earth not seeing One liuing creature any where haue being. Nor any ground wheron she might remaine, With weary wings returnes to him againe. Then rested he vntill the day-star bright Seuen times remoou'd the canopie of night: Then once againe the Doue he sendeth out, She mounts aloft and flieth round about. And finding much dry ground on earth, presumes To fall theron, and rouse her ruffled plumes, Now shakes her selfe, and with her bill them peckes, Now layes them downe and orderly them deckes. And hauing long time frolik'd at her will, Returned with a green leafe in her bill, By this knew Noah that the Flood decreased, Yet other seuen dayes in the arke he rested: And when bright Vesper in the Welkin pale Had thrise and foure times drawne the clowdy vale, The third time forth againe he sends the Doue, She swiftly in the aire her wings doth mooue: And finding food her body to sustaine, And ground to rest on, neuer came againe. Yet rested Lamechs ofspring in the Arke, Till seuen times againe in Welkin darke Bootes guider of the greater Beare, Had showne himself, and then expelling feare Sets ope the doore, and plainely did espie Floods quite decreas'd, and face of earth all dry. And then the lord commandment to him gaue That he with all things els the Arke should leaue. No stay they made, all things man, bird and beastes, VVhom Titan saw from either of his restes Aliue on earth, came foorthwith from the arke, There stretcht their limmes, vnweldy yet and starke. There Enochs ofspring to his God erected An altar, who from Floods had him protected: And theron for his preseruation Did offer vp a just oblation: The smell wherof vnto his throne arose, And cast a pleasant odour to his nose. Expelling quite that detestable stinke VVhich erst ascended from worldes filthy sinke. Delighted therfore in this pleasant sauour, He blest all mankind with his gracious fauour: Hencefoorth (quoth he) no more my wrathfull curse Vpon the world or man I will disburse. For all his thoughts with wickednes are stayned Euen from his birth, to time that he is wayned. Hencefoorth in season shall he plant and sow, In season shall he after reape and mowe. In his due course hot Sommer will I send And winter, till the earth shall haue an end: Increase aboundantly, bring foorth and breed, And earth againe replenish with your seed. Beholde, your feare all creatures shall appall, Rule thou as Lord and maister ouer all. Whoso shall man bereaue of vitall breath, His life shall be abridg'd with cruell death. Blood will haue blood, whoso shall cut mans life, His also shall be cut with blooudy knife. Encrease aboundantly, bring foorth and breed, The earth againe replenish with your seed. Behold, with thee I make a couenant sure, A couenant which for euer shall endure, With earth, and all thinges which thereon remaine, That I will neuer drowne the world againe, And to confirme my promised decree, A certaine seale therof I giue to thee. This is the seale: a Bowe I meane to shrowde Of diuers collours in a pitchie clowd. This is the seale, and this shall be a token, That this my league at no time shall be broken. And when I shall all-hiding heauen cloake With clouds, foorth-pouring mystie raine like smoke, Then I in cloudes will place my certaine seale, Mine euer-during promise to reueale. With surging billowes and impartiall raine That earth shall neuer be destroy'd againe. And this a signe infallible shall be, Of mine eternall-durable decree. FINIS. Dauid and Beersheba. Svch time as Tytan with his fiery beames In highest degree, made duskish Leo sweat: Field-tilling Swains driue home their toiling teams, Out-wearied with ardencie of heat: And country heards to seeke a shadie seate: All mortall things from seruency of weather, In sheltring shades doe shroud themselues together. Beersheba wife vnto Vrius stout, A Captaine vnder Ioab of renowne: Whom princely Dauid with a warring rout Had sent to beat the pride of Ammon downe. And to besiege and ransacke Rabbah towne, Betooke her selfe into a garden faire, Inricht with flowers, which sent a pleasant ayre. On euery side this garden was beset, With choice of rare delights and Arbors geason: The Lentisk, fig-tree, and Pomgranet great, Grew there in order, far surpassing reason. The ground was deckt with Gyliflowers fine, Carnations sweet, and speckled sops, in wine. There might you heare vpon the pleasant trees, The little birds melodiously to sing: Vpon the blossoms wrought the painfull Bees, Neere was it to the pallace of the King, Within it also was a pleasant spring. Whose liquid humour moystened the same, A garden worthy of so worthy dame. Now gathereth she the sweetest of the sweet, And pretilie from flower to flower trippeth, Soone after to the fountaine turnes her feet, Then daintily her hands of gloues she strippeth, And in the Chrystall waues her fingers dippeth. She likes it well, and calles it passing coole, And minds to bath her bodie in the poole. Then nimbly castes she off her Damaske frocke, Her Satten stole most curiously made: Her Partlet needle-wrought, her Cambricke smocke, And on a seat thereby them nicely laid. And so to wash her in the well assay'd. O shut thine eies Narcissus come not neere, Least in the well a burning fire appeare. Sleep still King Dauid in thy Princely bed, Where now thou takst thine after-dinners nap: O rouse not vp from sleep thy kingly head. Least by mischaunce thou fall into a trap, See heere of mans fragilitie a map: Thou canst not (Dauid) needs must thou vpstart, Thy God will haue thee know how frayle thou art. Now riseth he, and vp in haste he flies, Vpon the highest turret of his tower: There standing, all the Cittie ouerpries Her carued Bulwarkes, and ech goodly bower. But O vnlucky time, O dismall hower! Stop Ishas sonne thine eares, keep sayles on hie, Least Syrens songs doe drawe thy mind awry. Suruaying thus his towne, at length he cast His eye-lids downe, and saw Beersheba naked: His princely heart, which neuer yet did tast Of euill, stroke with burning feuer quaked: A fire he caught, by no waues to be slaked. And as he striues to quench this flaming fire, Still kindles it with bellowes of desire. Much better hadst thou kept within thy pallace, There on thy harpe t'aue fed thy mind with joy: Or entertain'd some pretie pleasing sollace. But are the godly subject to annoy? Must they be ruled by a wanton boy? His eie approou'd, his heart it gaue consent, And both were spurres vnto his bad intent. With washing waues her breast he saw her decke, He cals it Nectar, wherof Angels drinke: With Iuory armes she rubs her milky necke, White Doues which fall on snow he doth them thinke He wisheth he himselfe were at the brinke. But with the candle whilst he thus doth play, At last his wings were burned quite away, And now begins the combatant assault, Betweene the willing flesh and nilling spirit. The flesh alluring him vnto the fault, The spirit tels him of a dreadfull merit. And in the end flesh conquered the spirit. He sends, she came, he wooes, she gaue consent, And did the deed, not fearing to be shent. What hast thou done, O Psalmist? blush for shame, Thinkst thou thy sinne will neuer come to light. No, no, Iehouah will reueale the same, Though thou hadst don't in silence of the night. Yet would he bring it into open sight: T'was he would put thy piety in triall, To see if thou wouldst yeeld or make denyall. Now three times Cynthia in the Welkin bright Her circle full vnto the earth did lend: Thrise had she lost againe her borrowed light, Since Dauid with Beersheba did offend, And now began she feele her wombe extend. What should she doe? her fault she could not couer, Of many dayes she had not seen her louer. And now shee moanes her to the King, and sayes In mournfull sort, shee feeles her selfe with child: His guilty mind disturbed many wayes, (Wit waites on feare) finds out a pretie wild, Wherwith he hopes his maker to beguild. But what? can Prophets then so grosly slide, And from their God suppose their sinnes to hide? He sendeth word to Ioab presently, His true estate in letters to expresse: And therewith send Vrias speedilie, Vrias comes, he readeth their successe, And bids him goe vnto his wife in peace. But see the more he labour'd to conceale it, So much the more God labour'd to reueale it, Vrias would not goe vnto his house, But gathered strawe, and layd it in the yard, And caring not to frolike with his spouse, He laid him down to sleep amid the Gard. As soone as Dauid had these tydings hard, He askes him why he rested not at home, From toyling warres art thou not lately come? No (quoth Vrias) tis for me vnfit To sleep within, whilst Ioab is without: Vnseemly tis to see the seruant fit, And let his maister toyle and run about: What, lyeth not the Arke of God without? I sweare by Dauids crowne and princelie head, Whilst things goe thus, I will not come in bed. And now is Dauid vexed worse and worse, And euery way is forc'd his wits to sift: By this he hath deuis'd a second course, And means to put in vre a pretie shift, To make Vrias drunken was his drift. So thinkes he, hee'ill forget his dutie quite, And mooued be therewith to some delight. He charg'd his seruantes entertaine him well, To giue him store of wine, and comfits daintie: Before the King to banquetting they fell, Sweet syrrops there they had, and wine great plentie: He dranke to twentie, and he pledged twenty. They quaft off flagons full, and spared not, The third sell alwayes to Vrias lot. Heere, heer (saith one) I drinke vnto my brother, Ile pledge him (quoth Vrias) hees my friend: I drinke to such a Captaine (quoth another) And he to all a good carrouse would send: Surcharg'd with wine, he staggerd in the end. He walketh vp and downe the stately hall, But alwaies leanes, and cleaues vnto the wall. Full glad was Dauid now, and hop'd his plot Would take effect, he almost was secure: He heard the souldiour talke he knew not what, He with Beershebas name did him allure, He thought that night would breed contentment sure But what so ere he built, it could not stand, For all his worke was built vpon the sand. Now night was come, all creatures went to rest, Downe lay the Hitthite where he slept before: King Dauid with a sea of cares opprest, Was driuen welnigh to dispaire his doore, Yet still against the streame he labours more. Thus euermore sinne leadeth vnto sinne, A lesser ends, and greater doth begin. Stay sinfull King, looke backe, and aske thy pardon, It boots thee not alas thy selfe to hide: So guiltie Adam hid him in the garden, So Ionah fled vpon the surging tide. Yet quickly had Iehouah them espide. Looke backe (I say) confesse it is much better, To hide a lesser sinne doe not a greater. And now againe hee's driuen to inuent, And vp and downe for pollicies to roue: Yet finds he nothing vnto his content, At length the deuill a deadly plot doth moue, And he thereof doth presently approue. In errour blind still walkes the Letcher further, And thinks to hide adultery with murther. Obliuious Prophet, call to minde thine oth, Thou vowdst to keep the couenant of thy Lord: More sweet thou saydst then combe or honey both, More deare then Gems which Tagus doth afford. Thou brag'dst thou joyedst only in his word. Chose he not thee his tender lambes to keepe? And like a Wolfe wilt thou deuoure his sheep? And now begins this deuilishnesse to bud, He vnto Ioab letters doth indite, O fearfull letters, messengers of bloud, He wils him place him foremost in the fight, And let him die, whilst they escape by flight. And by Vrias sends he him away, he guiltlesse beares a sword himselfe to slay. He guiltlesse beares a sword himselfe to flay, And harmlesse feares no treason to be wrought: So doth the Cony fall into the hay, So is the bird vnto the Lyme-bush brought, So on the hooke the nibling Fish is caught. he to his Captaine doth his letters bring, Who readeth them, and minds to doe the thing. Soone after causd he them the towne to sacke, Next to the walles Vrias preass'd amaine: The Rabbanits came out, Ioab fled backe, And many of his souldiours there were slaine, Among the which Vrias caught his bane. O joyfull tydings to th'offenders eares, Now frolickes he, and no suspition feares. Securely now he layes him downe to sleepe, As he were blemisht with no sinfull spot, As all his sinnes were drowned in the deepe, Or Lethes waues, where all thinges be forgot, As though Iehouah wink'd and saw him not. Till at the last vnto his vile disgrace, Thus Nathan sent, reproou'd him to his face. Ah Churle (quoth he, and sadly tels the tale,) Within a little cittie dwelling was: Much cattell had he feeding in his pale, And pastures faire, which yeelded hay and grasse, None could be seene in riches him to passe. Great store of golde he had, of Gems and treasure, He felt no want, but liued at his pleasure. A very poore man neere vnto him dwelled, One little sheep, who fostered at his manger, To which in loue he mightily excelled And in his bosome shrouded her from danger. Now to this Misers house there came a stranger. And sparing all his owne, vnto the feast He butchted vp, and eat the poore mans beast. Hereat was Dauid verie sore incenst, He chas'd, and rag'd thereat exceedinglie: Without reuenge his wrath could not be quench'd, He swore the man that did the sinne should die, Himselfe would see him tortur'd by and by. Thou, thou (quoth Nathan) art the man indeed That hath commitred this detested deed. Thus sayth thy God, thou wert a shepheards boy, A seruile arte, and feddest sheep in field: Then wert thou subject vnto much annoy, A russet cloake did thee from weather shield. And liuedst of the fruite thy flocke did yeeld. A shepheards hooke vpon thy back thou borest, A lether scrip about thy necke thou worest. Then ioyest thou to gather Filberds ripe, To play at Barly-breake amongst the Swaines: To tune rude Odes vpon an Oaten pipe, Thy feeding heards to follow on the plaines, And driue them backe againe, no little paines From greedy Wolues to shield thy tender Lambes, And meat to fetch vnto their blating Dams, And now thy title low I haue suborned, Made thee my Prophet of a shepheard base: And with a Regall Crowne thine head adorned, I chaung'd thy sheep-hook to a princelie Mace: What earthly man is now in higher place? Thou hadst seuen brethren goodlier in blee. Yet I refusing them, made choise of thee. I ouerthrew Goliah with thy sling, Thou but a dwarfe, and he a Gyant tall, I gaue to thee the daughter of a King, I sau'd thee from the hands of murthring Saulo, I gaue thee wiues, and concubines and all. I made thee feed my people Israell, And all because I loued thee so well. And if in heart thou hadst desired more, More also had I added to thy life: But thou of wiues although thou haddest store, Hast taken vnto thee Vrias wife, And caus'd him to be slaine by Ammons knife. And walking still in this absurditie, Thinkst to conceale this haynous sin from me. Now whilst thou liu'st, for this which thou hast done, The sword shall neuer from thy house depart: And of thy seed thou shalt beget a sonne, Which shall pursue thee with a deadly dart. Now is the Psalmist stroken to the heart. Three sundry times endeuoured he to speake, Three times he sob'd as though his heart would break And now at last begins he to relent, A showre of teares distilled from his eyes: His heart is humbled, fearing to be shent, And lifting mind and hands vnto the skies, Peccaui Deus, manie times be cries Rise vp (quoth Nathan) God doth heare thy crie Thy sin is pardon'd, but thy child shall die. And then in heart as lowly as a childe, Betakes him to his chamber all alone: There weepeth he before his maker milde, And oftimes sobbing, maketh piteous mone, Complayning other help it he hath none. Thus in the end distressed as he stood, He tooke his harpe and warbled out this Ode. DAVIDS ODE. O Great Creator of the starrie Pole, and heauenly things: O mightie founder of the earthly mole, chiefe king of Kings. Whose gentle pardon euermore is nere, To them which crie vnfaynedly with feare, Distrest with sin, I now begin, To come to thee, O Lord giue eare, O Lord look down fr? thy chrystallin throne, enuirond round, With Seraphins, and Angels manie one, thy praise who sound: Such fauour Lord on me vouchsafe to send, As on thy chosen flock thou doest extend. To thee alone I make my mone. Some pittie father on me send. Remember Lord, that it is more then need, to send redresse, My sore will grow (vnlesse thou help with speed) remedilesse. Therfore in mercie looke down from aboue, And visit me with thy heart-joying loue. Alas, I see No cause in me Which vnto pitie may thee moue. With sinne I only haue offended thee, O Lord my God, And therwithall I purchas'd haue to me thine heauie rod: The waight of it doth presse me verie sore, And brings me wel nigh to dispaire his doore. Alas I shame To tell the same: It is before thee euermore. And this is not first time I sinn'd alas, by many moe: Within the wombe in sin conceiu'd I was, Borne was I so. And since that day I neuer yet did cease, From time to time thy highnesse to displease. My life hath bin A race of sin: Me with thy comfort somewhat ease. O why did I offend thy glorious Grace so hainously? Why fear'd I not the presence of thy face who stoodest by? Because I should acknowledge thee most just, And in mine owne vprightnes shuld not trust: Fraile is my fleshs I must confesse, And nought is it but sinne and dust. If thou shalt me asperge with sprinkling grasse, or Hysope greene: As Chrystall pure, or as the shining glasse, I shall be cleane, And if thou wilt me wash with water cleare, More white then Scythan snow I shall appeare Then whitest snow which wind doth blow From place to place both farre and neere. My mind O Lord, infectious and foule, make cleane and pure: Into thy hands I humbly giue my soule to heale and cure. Out of thy booke all mine offences blot, And with thy blood quite take away my spot. So shall my hart Be free from smart, And mine offences quite forgot. Turn back thy face which al things doth behold from heauens vault: Least thou espie my trespasse manifold, and hainous fault. My faults, which are in number many more Then little sands which are vpon the shore, refraine thine ire, I thee desire, And also heale my deadly sore. Within my breast (O Lord) an humble spirit, do thou create: And of thy comfort doe not me disherit, I thee intreat. Let me enjoy the sun-shine of thy face, Take not from me the solace of thy grace, The holy Ghost: My comfort most. Let me retaine in any case. My tongue vntie, my lips (O Lord) resolue, thou art the key: So will my tongue thy mercie great reuolue, from day to day. Then shall the wicked learne by mine example, To keep thy statutes which be sweet and ample And seeing me, shall turne to thee, And in the right way learne to trample. Wouldst thou haue bin with sacrifice content, much fat of Rammes, Much incense sweet on thee wold I haue spent and blood of Lambes: But thou (O God) therto hast no respect, A broken heart thou neuer wilt reject: That sacrifice Is of most price, That onlie with thee takes effect. Be gentle Lord to thy Sionian towne, bow downe thy face, And on thy Shalem send thy mercie downe, and louing grace: Reedifie her bulwarkes like to fall, And vp againe build her decaying wall. Then will I praise Thy name alwayes. And giue burnt offrings therewithall. Thus did the Psalmist warble out his plaints, And ceaseth not from day to day to mone, His heart with anguish of his sorrowe faints. And still he kneels before his makers throne. At midnight sends he manie a grieuous grone. So did his God in mercie on him looke. And all his sinnes did race out of his booke. FINIS. F. S.</field>
   </doc>
</add>