<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Arwaker, Edmund</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Arwaker, Edmund</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">arwaker edmund</field>
      <field name="author_text">Arwaker, Edmund</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1700's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_2.0034.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">1704</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464709</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">An Embassy from Heav'n ; or, the Ghost of Queen Mary. A Poem. By Mr. Edmund Arwaker</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">An Embassy from Heav'n ; or, the Ghost of Queen Mary. A Poem. By Mr. Edmund Arwaker</field>
      <field name="title_facet">embassy from heavn</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">embassy from heavn</field>
      <field name="title_text">An Embassy from Heav'n ; or, the Ghost of Queen Mary. A Poem. By Mr. Edmund Arwaker</field>
      <field name="year_display">1704</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1704</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1704</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464709&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464709&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Arwaker, Edmund&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;arwaker edmund&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;An Embassy from Heav'n ; or, the Ghost of Queen Mary. A Poem. By Mr. Edmund Arwaker&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;embassy from heavn&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1704&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1704&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Arwaker, Edmund&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;An Embassy from Heav'n&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;or, the Ghost of Queen Mary. A Poem. By Mr. Edmund Arwaker&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for, and Sold by S. Malthus [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1704&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0133&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;20 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;An Embassy from Heav'n&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;or, the Ghost of Queen Mary. A Poem. By Mr. Edmund Arwaker&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 44 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">? Me fera jactat Hyems. Ovid de Trist. TO The Right Honourable, THE Countess of DERBY. An Embassy from Heaven. OR, THE Ghost of Queen MARY, &amp;c. Damon and Thirsis from a Mossy Rock, View'd with Delight, and watch'd with Care their Flock: The Lambs securely o'er the Pasture play'd; Secure, by such attentive Eyes survey'd: Nature with Flow'rs embroiders all the Fields, And Tender Food and fragrant Odour yeilds. Thus pleas'd the Sheep, thus pleas'd the Shepherds lay: They with their Sport, and These to see them play. When Damon, all astonish'd, cry'd aloud, DAMON. See, See, what Angel comes on yonder Cloud! Like a descending Star, She leaves the Sky, And her Attendants form a Galaxie: A Thousand Cherubs round her Chariot play, And Seraphs spread their Garments in her Way: A golden Mist's her Canopy of State, And in her Train the Saints by Thousands wait: Had Cyprus so much Grace in Venus seen, They well might make a Goddess of their Queen Immortal Saint, approach not mortal me! My dazled Eye-balls swim with Extasie. THIRSIS. Hark, hark! The Spheres t'enchanting Numbers move Thro' breaking Air She issues from Above; Speak, Angel, speak! Dost thou to Shepherds bring Once more Glad Tydings from th'Almighty King? GHOST. Peace be on Albion: Shepherds, do not fear; Can your MARIA terrible appear? To visit you, She leaves the Plains of Rest, Where Her NASSAU presides among the Blest. THIRSIS. O Heav'nly Queen! more Fair than Cynthia shown, When She to view her slumbring Swain came down; Say on, what Happy Embassy you come: You'd make it happy, tho' it were our Doom: Say, why the Seats of Transport you forgo, While Heav'n attends you to those Plains below; Say, what Commands from JOVE, or from Nassau. GHOST. I come, glad People, to Congratulate The late Successes of your prosp'rous State. NASSAU, and I, and all the Saints, confess, Increase of Rapture at your Happiness; Heav'n's Armies in your Quarrel harness'd stood, When Marlb'rough battell'd at the German Flood; The Bless'd to Bleinheim glided down in Crouds, To view the Conflict from adjacent Clouds; Sure Saints themselves have some Regard to Men, For all our Knees were bent for Britain then; My Hero at th'accustom'd Sight was rais'd, And Marlb'rough's Courage and his Conduct prais'd: Yet view'd his dear-lov'd Host with such an Air, As if once more he wish'd himself was there. Our Eyes on Vict'ry's dubious Motions wait; She, in suspence, expects the Nod of Fate, JOVE gave the Fiat, from the Sky she fled, And crown'd with Palm the Conqu'ring Marlb'rough's Head, It thunder'd, and NASSAU the Lightning threw, Your Foes, who dy'd not, or surrender'd, flew; Confusion rages thro' the scatter'd Rout, The Angels sing, the Danes and English shout. As Moses Israel, Marlborough Britain led; The Waves where both their Foes expir'd were red; The ruddy Sands stain'd the Egyptian Flood, But German Streams were dy'd with Gallick Blood. Heroick Souls the Azure Mansions swell; They rose to Heav'n, who for your Monarch fell; The Good NASSAU His former Friends embrac't, And now they guard Him thro' the Fields of Rest. DAMON. Angel proceed: The Choire of Heav'n ne'er sung Such Harmony, as dwells upon thy Tongue: Say, Does MARIA, and Her Great NASSAU, From Heav'n respect their Britain's Fate below? How justly safe, and happy we're esteem'd, If still you Guard the Land you once Redeem'd. GHOST. Did We from Belgian Shores the Ocean plow, To save your Albion, and forsake her now? Shall Mortals Aid, and Saints Neglect their Friends? Shall We refuse, when Heav'n Assistance lends? No, No, from your Successes you may learn, That all your Actions want not our Concern. We wak'd when Oss'rey's Son to Spain advanc'd, And Rook, like Neptune, on the Billows danc'd; When Gallia's Flaming Fleet did gild the Main, And Ormond took the Golden Gods of Spain: He with their Altars, did their Saints with-hold; For as their Altars, so their Gods are Gold. The Blest ELIZABETH Her Skies forsook, To praise Great Ormond, and encourage Rook; With Drake and Rawleigh, She beheld the Seas, And Troops of Her Old Worthies wond'ring gaze. To see a Spanish, and a French Armado blaze. Ormond and Oss'rey blest their Hero Son, And smil'd to be by None but Him out-done; The Great NASSAU above, rejoyc'd to know Th'Effects of the Design he laid below. Comets were lighted, Saints Laudamus sung, And glitt'ring Heav'n with Hallelujahs rung. THIRSIS. O Boundless Love! O All-forgiving GOD! Have we thy Favour, who deserve thy Rod? Can't all the Sins of this Ungrateful Land, Provoke thee to withdraw thy Lib'ral Hand? Do we, like Israel, feed on Angels Bread, Who do, like Israel, murmur while we're fed? Is not thy Bank of Blessings yet dismay'd, To Lend, where so unthankfully Repaid? We praise not Thee for plenteous Peace at Home, While War and Want thro' Foreign Regions roam: While you would Quench, our Factions we Enflame; And quit Religion, striving for the Name: To bow at All it's Altars, Heaven empowers; We'll let our Brother kneel at none but Ours. We murmur; 'tho', while MARLB'ROUGH leads our Host, England, like Jewry, can a Gideon boast: Speak, Angel, then; how Heav'n persists to bless Where Thanks are small, and where Desert is less. GHOST. Your Fortunes to your God and Queen are due; Jove gave them Her, and ANNE bestows them you: Her Vows so oft' to Him for you were made, He thought he did not Give Success, but Paid. THYRSIS. Behold each Lamb that yonder plays, or feeds, While ANNE gives Peace and Safety to the Meads, Shall pay her Tribute from it's Silver Fleece; Or, were it Golden, like the Ram of Greece. Henceforth, I'll urge my unpresumptuous Prayer, For Her to Heaven, and for my self to Her. DAMON. I saw Her Triumph, thro' Augusta move; Beauties, like Saints, ador'd Her from Above: With such Divinity the Monarch rode, We did Neglect the Pow'r She did Applaud, And all that Day cou'd praise no other God. GHOST. Almighty JOVE, pleas'd with the humble Show, Decree'd on High, a Triumph for NASSAU. THYRSIS. Angel, To poor, but loyal Swains, relate, Th'Exalted Grandeur of their Monarch's State, And fix'd and silent as this Rock, we'll wait. GHOST. Shepherds, I will, tho' I attempt in vain, In narrow Speech wide Notions to contain: Thoughts, like our Souls, are Boundless and Divine, Which Words express like Bodies, and confine. JEHOVAH spoke—Ev'n Day encreas'd its Light, And Heav'n, till then, was never seen so Bright: The glowing Sun in Beams of Splendor danc'd, And flashing Rays from burning Planets glanc'd; The spangled Roof of Heav'n, from both the Poles, In Gilded Scaffolds held surveying Souls: Th'Enamel'd Plains of Happiness out-shone The Gold and Azure of the Lazule Stone. Machines of Air from the high Zenith hung, Where Angels sat and play'd, and Cherubs sung: Wanton (in Clusters) Seraphs flew on High, And seem'd to make the Fret-Work of the Sky, On yielding Clouds whose Fleeces curl'd along, To view the Triumph infant Angels clung. The Gaudy'st Rainbows were like Arches rais'd, On which bright Spoils and flaming Trophies blaz'd; Troops of Arch-Angel Guards, in bright Array, Were rank'd on either Side the Milky Way; On shining Pavements the Procession march'd; And Heav'n it self seem'd for the Triumph Arch'd. JEHOVAH's choicest Musick led the Van, Each Orpheus mov'd upon a Silver Swan; But Purcell drawn by Nightingales, advanc'd; His Notes were play'd, and Heav'n lay all intranc'd. The Souls of Men, whom JOVE himself inspir'd With Sacred Skill, came Gorg'ously attir'd: Here Poetry assum'd the foremost Place, With easy Movement, and Majestick Grace. Her Beauteous Sister, Painting, charm'd the Sight, in party colour'd Robes of various Light. Cowley and Waller here were wreath'd with Bays; The ravish'd Saints held their alternate Lays; Cowley sung David's Fame, and Waller WILLIAM's Praise. Drunkards no more make Songs on either King, But sweetest Bards the best of Monarchs sing; Here Crouds of tuneful Laureats touch'd their Lyres, And Rapture hover'd on the trembling Wires. On Pageants born, above the Painting Throng, Rubens, Vandike and Lilly mov'd along; Each wav'd an Ensign of Etherial Lawn, On which JOVE's Battles, or NASSAU's, were drawn Next, Noble Boyle a Troop of Sages led, By whose Attempts the World has profited: Here the Learn'd Dane, upon his Shoulders bears, Like a new Atlas the Refulgent Sphears; Himself the fairest of the Northern Stars. Ten thousand Virtues next, by Couples came In fiery Chariots, and in Robes of Flame, Too Glorious to describe, too Numerous to name: Each had a modest Air, a lovely Mien; But all these Beauties may on Earth be seen; They meet and shine in your Illustrious QUEEN. Next, march'd in Armour, that out-blaz'd the Sun, The Chiefs that fell at Blienhem, Liege and Bon, Rowe, Mordant, Forbes, Wentworth led them on. DAMON. How Blest are Heros! How Unhappy Swains! I'll change these slothful Fields for active Plains: Farewel my bleating Lambs and warbling Reed; To live in Heav'n, on Earth who wou'd not bleed? O take me hence, I'll all my Flocks forego, To Die for ANNE, and Triumph with NASSAU. THYRSIS. Peace Damon, don't my Ravish'd Soul awake, I of the Bliss, the Saint describes, partake; Such Image my transported Fancy frames, I am in Heav'n, or Heav'n is in my Dreams. Angel, go on; dissolve me as you speak, And let the blest Inchantment never break. DAMON. Pardon, blest Saint, the Rapture you enflame; Pursue, MARIA, your Celestial Theme; To my warm Soul such deep Impression give, That with NASSAU my Thoughts, at least, may live. GHOST. Next, Pious Souls, of all Religions, came; Their Worship Various, but their God the Same. Here Bates and Hammond in Embraces meet, And Baxter joyns in Praise with Stillingfleet; Horneck, and Annesly, and Millions more, Alike are Happy, and alike Adore: All, all is Peace, all Prejudice forgot; From sev'ral Stations, at one Mark they shot: The Just reach Heav'n, altho' by different Ways; God is their Sun, and they his spreading Rays: Tho' at the Circle some are opposite, They meet, and center in Eternal Light. Hast then, my Friends, your causeless Feuds remove; Wou'd you Below, be blest like Us Above? Learn Peace from Us, and learn from Us to Love. Next, follow'd Truth, her Cloathing Rich, tho' Plain; Solemn, yet Pleasing, Awful, yet Serene. A Band of Champions round the Matron clos'd, Who, by Defending Her, Themselves Expos'd: Here, Wickliff, like a Comet on a Cloud, The Emblem of the Age he liv'd in, stood; Calvin, Melancthon, Luther, did appear, Like Stars that rose, to tell Rome's Fall was near: Or, like that Light that led wise Kings the Way To th'humble Place, where Great Messiah lay; O'er their grave Heads protecting Angels glide, And Guardian Cherubs range on ev'ry Side: The Matron's Enemies may learn from hence, That her Defenders never want Defence. Next, came a Troop of Martyr'd Innocents, Light blush'd to see their fairer Ornaments; In Iv'ry Chariots flam'd with Gold, they rode, Gay as the Milky Path on which they trod. Here Gaunt, as if she burnt once more, is Bright; Not in Terrestrial Fire, but Heavenly Light: Lisle do's no more the barbarous Hatchet dread, But Lambent Glory glides about her Head: What divers Fates their Charity has found! Below, 'twas Punish'd; and Above, 'tis Crown'd. ESSEX was wafted on the Wings of Fame; Himself no longer bloody, nor his Name: T'excuse his Murth'rers, he's of Murther blam'd; But Saints his Fall and Innocence proclaim'd. Tho' none but One, by Suff'ring merits Bliss, Sure, Heav'n was due to Injuries like his. Cornish approach'd dismember'd, but in vain; God and his Faith have made him whole again: JOVE, while they triumph'd in his Blood Below, Turn'd his fierce Eyes from the Affronting Show: His Innocence, at his Demand, was known, On Trumpets of resounding Thunder blown: Heav'n back to Earth hot Exhalations hurl'd, To break all Converse with th'abandon'd World; Like the Centurion, then his Foes began To own, too late, he was a Righteous Man. THYRSIS. I mind it well, the Clouds did burst and weep; I on yon Cliff, and in these Meads, my Sheep: It lighten'd; to their Folds my Lambkins made; Damon and I to yonder Laurel-Shade: All Night we lay, the Tempest did encrease, Nor cou'd we reach our distant Cottages: Yon gentle Sea, that now salutes the Shore, Against those breaking Rocks did foam and roar: We hear'd the Cryes from Vessels driv'n to Land; See there the Wrecks lie buried in the Sand: Such dismal Groans thro' all the Valleys ran, As when the Satyrs mourn'd the Fall of PAN. DAMON. Tragick Remembrance! Hold, my Thyrsis, hold; New Griefs will spring from th'Ashes of the Old: Wou'd you, kind Saint, our Joy, not Pain, create, Our Friends Advancement, not their Fall, repeat. GHOST. Next, Sidney, in his inlaid Chariot rol'd; Sidney the Good, the Noble, and the Bold: Sidney, whose Christian Exit did deride The Roman's Rashness, and the Stoick's Pride. RUSSEL, in Pomp, rid o'er the Di'mond Road, And all around him hov'ring Splendor glow'd; His Chariot-Wheels appear'd like fiery Globes, And Comets weav'd their Hair to make him Robes: God-like he liv'd, so like a God he dy'd; Not much more Glorious, now he's Glorify'd: In Costly Gems, from Heav'ns best Wardrobe drest; At length, the Saint Increase of Light confest. Astrea, in the Skies, to which she fled, Wept, when on Earth the Pious RUSSEL bled; She wept such Tears as his own Consort shed: Alike they mourn'd, and as they both design'd To see such Sights no more, they wept till both were blind. Next, Troops of Good and Warlike Princes go, From CONSTANTINE the Great, to Great NASSAU; Each Monarch was attended by a Train Of all the first-rank'd Worthies of his Reign: The Skies amaz'd, admir'd their Sparkling Crowns, And thought, at first, They saw so many Suns. Round the first Edward's Head such Glory twin'd, As in the Face of the meek Prophet shin'd: Both, from one Source, their Laws and Lustre drew; The Legislators this Distinction knew; The One taught Israel, and the Other You. Here the first Edward rests from all his Toil, With Sion's Diadem and Cyprus Spoil, The Brave Redeemer of his Saviour's Soil. Here, the third Edward and his hardy Son, Were Crown'd with Glory which themselves have won. In your Great ANNE they both revive again; She scourges France, and makes a Prince of Spain. What Circling Rays kiss'd the Fifth Henry's Brows, Who first subdu'd Himself, and then his Foes? To vanquish much, to rule the Victor, more; This wreath'd his Head with Bliss, and that with Oar. Here England's Brutus, the Sev'nth Henry Reigns, Who struck your Tyrant Dead at Bosworth's Plains His Robes with Stars, like Roses, Interwrought, Declar'd the Union he to ALBION brought. Behind him Squadrons of his Warriors range, Led by Great Derby, and the Youthful Strange; Derby, who durst prefer his Country's Good To his own Safety, and his Off-spring's Blood! Derby, whose Ancestors were Hero's long; Derby, from whom a Race of Hero's sprung: The Derby's Valour, as their Birth-right claim; Is there a Prince wants Worthies of the Name? Their Derby's Charles and William have beheld, And ANN a Derby boasts at Blenheim's Field. Next Charles the First, rode with his Royal Sons, He was with Glory grac'd, and they with Crowns. Amidst their Train, Ormond and Oss'ry shine, With Murther'd Derby, and his Heroine. So here, on Earth, their Princely Progeny do joyn. Honor herself her Finest Rayment spreads, Wrought with their own Atchievements o'er their Heads. Next Your ECCLESIA was by Angels drawn, Herself all Light, and all her Vestments Lawn; Cherubs above her, Saints around her fly, Her Locks are Constellations in the Sky: Edward the Sixth, the Young, the Good, the Great, At her Right-hand her bright Defender sat; The Spring with Primrose Chaplets Crown'd his Hair, And Sporting, scatter'd Vi'lets in the Air. Elizabeth her left Arm does support, Glori'us as Heav'n, when Shades on Earth are short. Tho' Edward's Morning was Eclips'd so soon, She warm'd World with her enliv'ning Noon. How shall I count the Worthies of her Age, Or, how describe her splendid Equipage? Shepherds, you wou'd have thought, had you been there, The Stars had left their Orbs to follow her. Next Justice came, led by Unbias'd Hales; Cooke bore her Sword, and Littleton her Scales. Next Venerable Tillotson approach'd, The Saints in Throngs, his Sacred Mantle touch'd; Learning and Eloquence, and Rhet'rick strow'd Their choicest Flowr's in his embellish'd Road. Wisdom and Piety the Patriarch led, And MODERATION crown'd his Peaceful Head: Awful as Shade, yet like a Comet bright, Where e'er he past, he shed a stream of Light. Now Aclamations through the Poles resound, Glou'ster does on a foaming Courser bound; A Troop of little Angels rid before, Some his gilt Spurs, some his plum'd Helmet bore; Cherubs aloft look'd down to see him March, And twisting, form'd themselves into an Arch: Seraphs his Brows with Blossoms did adorn, And cloath'd him with the dawning of the Morn: His Guards were blooming Youths, whose hasty Fall, Lamenting Parents do Untimely call. Blanford and Strange, the lovelyest of the Band, Wait next his Person, and his Troops Command. Derby forgive, if I rejoyce to see Dear Partner of my Soul, a part of thee: VVe Revel, whilst Mankind is left Forlorn, Pleas'd with such Sons, for whom such Mothers Mourn. Now, now all Heav'n's Spectators Shout aloud, The eager Angels o'er each other Croud: All their keen Eyes are to one Object bent, The loaded Skies with Peals of Praise are rent. NASSAU, while Lightning sweeps his Starry way, Comes Blazing in the Chariot of the Day; Twelve flaming Steeds, all led by Angels, pranc'd; And trembling Beams on their Gold Trappings danc'd: The Sun himself in his best Liv'ry drove; And 'twas th'Opinion of the Bless'd above, He rul'd that day more steady than before, Taught how to Govern by the Prince he bore: His Golden VVheels on Silver Axles turn'd, His Chrystal Coach in Di'mond Sparkles burn'd: On the cut Jems reflected Lustre play'd, And Light in all its Colours was array'd: Michael attends him with Heave'n's Body Guard, The same with whom the beaten Angels VVarr'd. Jove at the Triumph wou'd himself appear, But that he had decreed none shou'd be there Of greater Glory than the Triumpher. THIRSIS. Blest Saint, for ever on this Subject dwell, 'Tis Heav'n to hear you Heav'nly Stories tell. DAMON. How did our Monarch look? Ah! tell us how; What Stars, or brighter Things, enclos'd his Brow? GHOST. Shepherds a farther Scrutiny forbear, When Angels must not speak, nor Mortals hear: NASSAU's transcendent Lustre struck our Sight, We cou'd not see him for excess of Light. Thus past the Triumph with a Solemn Pace, To Sing Te Deum at the Throne of Grace; Immense I AM, fills the unbounded Place. Apostles, Martyrs, Saints, all melting lay On Golden Thrones of everlasting Day, Cherubs like Atoms in the Glory play. Melodious Joy slides from Seraphick Flutes, And soothing Softness from agreeing Lutes: Our Transports with Eternity revolve, And we in endless Extasie Dissolve: We Pray, we Praise, we Worship, and we Sing, Harmonious Ecchoes round the Convex ring: Jehovah Smiles amidst his Attributes; We sue for Britain, and he grants our Suits. DAMON. O happy Heav'n! O happy Britain too! For whom NASSAU and his MARIA sue; Screen'd by your Pray'rs amidst the Waves and Winds, Where others Danger, She her Safety finds: Her chalky Bulwarks all Invasions fence, Types of her Strength, but not her Innocence. You make each Surge of the Surrounding Sea Kiss her white Feet, and Foreign Tribute pay: Back'd by your Vows, Rook all her Rivals braves; The Navy Her, and He the Navy Saves. Shovel and Fairborne, Drake's Exploits pursue; And mighty Deeds, like mighty Orford, do. Now Saint, since we are Bless'd at your desire, See if our Works are worthy of our Hire. Say if our sad Divisions have not shown, Britain has all Religions, and has none. The Man, whom Heav'n unsought has fill'd, observe; He hears his Brother's Crys, and sees him Starve: Behold, such Lewdness through our Island sways, She rises Queen of Lust from frothy Seas. Ah! see how Vertue pines without Regard! Applause alone is thought too much Reward. To serve my Queen, I once my Lambs forsook, And chang'd, for Warlike Arms, my peaceful Crook; I hop'd to merit some Preferment soon; Thoughtless to Bow, to Bribe, or Importune; Till daily I saw worthless Swains succeed, Who had some Fav'rite Slave or Harlot Feed. Perhaps such Chiefs are best to beat our Foes; I've heard Lucullus by a Strumpet rose: But forc'd by Want to leave the dusty Plain, I quit the Wars, and tend my Lambs again. But who can bear to hear to hear these Realms disown The Glorious things NASSAU for them has done? For us in Heav'n he Prays, on Earth he Fought; 'Twas our Deliv'rance, not our Crown, he sought: Malice has o'er his Tomb her Venom shed, And rak'd the Sacred Ashes of the Dead. GHOST. Malice, that Fiend, has tempted some to say, I took a Parent's Diadem away: But they, in spite of Malice, must confess, None cou'd do more for them, or 'gainst a Father less: But Shepher'ds, you Maria was not sent T'Accuse her Land, but urge her to Repent. THIRSIS. To Heav'n, where you Reside, teach us the Road; Or make these Plains an Heav'n by your Abode: Tho' we hear Moses and the Prophets read, Tho' our meek Prelates guide us in their stead, What can Perswade like bless'd Maria from the Dead? Teach us the Vertues you possess'd alive: And we shall to that Heov'n you Grace, arrive. GHOST. To reach to Heav'n from Paths that led to Hell, Is more than always to have journey'd well: If bright Example can your Isle entice To follow Vertue, and abandon Vice, Let Denmark's Prince teach ev'ry British Man; And all your Matrons, learn from God-like ANN: Their Piety, their Moderation trace; Their Ways all Pleasure, and their Paths all Peace, Must lead to Heav'n, or there is no such Place. But now lov'd Meads, I hence must take my Flight, To seek my Heroe in the Fields of Light: Yet e'er I go and bid my last Farewell, To Albion I will Albions Fortune tell. Marlb'rough shall make the Roman Eagle rise, Fresh as a Phœnix, from its Obsequies: Justice and Vict'ry give to him their Swords, Justly he Conquers, and receives Rewards. Gal'way Impower'd from Heav'n and ANN, is gone; Charles He'll Establish, Philip he'll Dethrone. Gal'way for Worth, for Charity Renown'd, Has all a Prince should have, but being Crown'd: The Lands he Rul'd, his Name with Blessings load, William his Monarch was, and William's God: All might the Kings in the Vicegerents know; Nassau in Galway, and Heav'n in Nassau. The two Great Ormonds bless Irena's State, Him they Obey, and Her they Imitate. Tho' now each willing Land Britannia stiles The Ocean's Mistress, and the Queen of Isles; With no less Title she shall be content, Than Queen of Isles, and of the Continent: New Worlds to her, shall all their Product give, And she shall deign the Homage to receive. As Hallelujahs the Almighty please, And he Accepts, who does not want our Praise, Ierna's Harp with Golden Strings shall shine, And the three Sister-Realms for ever joyn: Then like the Fatal Sisters in their Hands, Shall rest the Fortune of all other Lands: And then Rebellion shall no more preyail, Arm'd by the Vizard of Religious Zeal. The Scotch and English Lions Roar no more, But gentle Tweed waft Peace from Shoar to Shoar. No more Sedition kindle to a Flame, The same your Worship, and your God the same: Gold shall delude you to be Base, in vain; For it shall be the Golden Age again. From ANN, and Denmark's Prince, shall rise an Heir, With all th'Endowments of the Royal Pair: In Pity to Bewailing Mortals given, He'll sway the World, when they are Crown'd in Heav'n. THIRSIS. She Moves! the Cherubs Sing! Stay Angel, stay! Or take us with the Joys you brought, away: Call, Damon! Art thou Speechless? See she flies! See, see, Heav'n meets her through the op'ning Skies! Ah now she glimmers like a distant Star, And wasting Sounds come dying from afar. Now the glad Skies are clos'd; to Heav'n she's bourn, And leaves the World, th'unhappy World to Mourn. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>