<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Grange, John</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Grange, John</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">grange john</field>
      <field name="author_text">Grange, John</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">16th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.0392.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1577</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:463256</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">French</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Golden Aphroditis ; A pleasant discourse, penned by John Grange ... Whereunto be annexed by the same Authour asvvell certayne Metres upon sundry poyntes, as also divers Pamphlets in prose, which he entituleth His Garden: pleasant to the eare, and delightful to the Reader, if he abuse not the scente of the floures</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Golden Aphroditis ; A pleasant discourse, penned by John Grange ... Whereunto be annexed by the same Authour asvvell certayne Metres upon sundry poyntes, as also divers Pamphlets in prose, which he entituleth His Garden: pleasant to the eare, and delightful to the Reader, if he abuse not the scente of the floures</field>
      <field name="title_facet">golden aphroditis</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">golden aphroditis</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Golden Aphroditis ; A pleasant discourse, penned by John Grange ... Whereunto be annexed by the same Authour asvvell certayne Metres upon sundry poyntes, as also divers Pamphlets in prose, which he entituleth His Garden: pleasant to the eare, and delightful to the Reader, if he abuse not the scente of the floures</field>
      <field name="year_display">1577</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1577</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1577</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463256&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463256&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Grange, John&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;grange john&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Golden Aphroditis ; A pleasant discourse, penned by John Grange ... Whereunto be annexed by the same Authour asvvell certayne Metres upon sundry poyntes, as also divers Pamphlets in prose, which he entituleth His Garden: pleasant to the eare, and delightful to the Reader, if he abuse not the scente of the floures&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;golden aphroditis&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1577&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1577&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Grange, John&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Golden Aphroditis&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A pleasant discourse, penned by John Grange ... Whereunto be annexed by the same Authour asvvell certayne Metres upon sundry poyntes, as also divers Pamphlets in prose, which he entituleth His Garden: pleasant to the eare, and delightful to the Reader, if he abuse not the scente of the floures&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Imprinted ... by Henry Bynneman&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1577&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp1547&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;fre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;[140] p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Golden Aphroditis&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A pleasant discourse, penned by John Grange ... Whereunto be annexed by the same Authour asvvell certayne Metres upon sundry poyntes, as also divers Pamphlets in prose, which he entituleth His Garden: pleasant to the eare, and delightful to the Reader, if he abuse not the scente of the floures&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 170 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Habet &amp; musca splenem, Et formicæ sua bilis inest.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To the right Honorable and his singular good Lord the Lord Sturton, Iohn Grange vvisheth health, vvelth, and prosperitie, vvith increase of Honour. To the Courtelike Dames and Ladie-like Gentlevvomen, the Authour sendeth greeting. I greete (but wh??) the glittring stars &amp; troupes of Venus crewe, VVith painefull pen of ranging fiste, bedewde with Ganges dew, So iocundare leades my will, that wanton needlesse toyle Of Courtlike Dames, my pestred wittes declare seekes to foyle. Draw neare therfore ye weried Nimphes, with such Mineruas toyles, And vewe this lading scope, which yeeldes for th? Veneriall foyles. As none so well as Cæsars penne, could Cæsars deedes indight, So none but of Morychus secte could dolor put to flight, Now I who wantes Apollos skill, and eke Dame Pallas witte, Herein to play Morychus parte, haue thought my selfe most fitte. Yet shall you finde an Ape, an Ape, in purple be she clothde, I come not from Trophonius care, for then I should be lothde: Nor from S. Patrickes purgatorie, but play Nepenthes parte, The iuyce whereof perforce will keepe such sadnesse fr? your harte. Thus labour I with tooth and nayle of Lethe force to be: Then with obliuion might I force your carping cares to flee. VVhiche once exilde, the better might the Muses then take place, And barefote might the tripping Nimphs the better shew their grace I ofte haue longde with penne to painte the trade of louers loue, Yet neare cold find what pen deserude, which was not known before. Thus dayly musing, where to finde whereon to wreake my spight, Me thought I harde Apollo sing full sweetely in the night, And play vp? his twinkling harp, whose warbling notes (me thought) Perforce c?straynde my penne to write, what he in songs had tought. VVhich fed full wel my restles reume with Stories somwhat str?ge: Marke now therfore, who liste to know whereon I list to range. It chaunste N. C. a valiant knight, possessed riches store, Yet w?ted whom his goodes shold rule when Clothe yeldes no more. For chaste, and solemne vowe once made, Dianas Nymphe to be, Dame Nature helde hir as content to heare, and not to see. VVherefore as one deuoyde of ioy, and hauing issue none, He oft reparde before the Goddes, with great complaynt, and mone, For that Cibile had transformde into a Lions shape Hyppomenes his cosin deare: for taking yeelded rape, VVithout a reuerence of the place: when beautie prickte his harte, His lust to serue (alas to soone) his hony waxed tarte. A Nymphe likewise of Scyros Ile, adornde with beautie rare, Before the Goddes with earnest sute, full oft she did repare: As for to haue Atlanta fayre to be restorde againe Vnto hir former shape, which once Cilele (to hir payne) Togither with Hyppomenes transformde to Lions route, And set them both at once to drawe hir chariot wheles aboute. Thus fortune frayle doth turne hir whele, to giue ech m? his cha?ce: And fraught their la?cing ships with wiles, Dan Cupids ro?d to da?ce For meeting both (as fortune would) before the Goddes with plaints, Loue gaue assault, the sparkes whereof, his tender harte attayntes. Such beautie (as Apollo sayde) consisted in hir face, That all the Heauens gan cleare to shine, not Phœbus yet in place, VVho, fearing lest the Gods th?selues with loue should be inflamde, Sat all on thorne till she was gone, and was he to be blamde? No, no. Thus I at length, haue founde a texte to stubbe a ganders quill: VVhiche if it proue Elleborus, according to my will, A heauy harte needes must it purge, from care, and pensiue plight, And like vnto Argivus harte inforce it to be light: To laugh indeede where cause is none, as this Argivus did, Yet Aiax rises to frequent, my story doth forbid. And I forbid a carping knight to catche where catche he can, For harde it is one dishe to please the mouth of euery man. VVho spies my fault (as easie) may by suyte I him forbid, To see and turne it to the worst, as Argus whilome did, That simple skill (whiche earst I had) I giue it you to vewe, Not doing as this Argus did, who kepte his vvife in mevv. For, quicquid in buccam venit, the same with haste I pende, No maruell then (deare Dames) if ought herein ye may amende. Thus standing to your curtesie (madames) loade starres of light, The sequele shal my meaning shew here offred to your sight. Tam Mineruæ quàm Veneri. Cuiquam. Marke well my frende this ragged ryme, thrust forth the Elderne pith: Spare not to cut a hasell wande to make a winding with. Seeke forth the grounde of evry thing, esteeme not filed phrase, The pythe, but not the paynting penne doth yeelde the Aucthours prayse. VVhat though I seeke by wantons witte each man for to delight? Shall sense therefore inforced be by myrth to see no lighte? Then is the Readers care but small, what fruyte he reape thereby: And eke the Aucthours prayse, by this, shall seeme in duste to lie. Then who that knovves, so foolish is his penne to take in hande? Sith that the vewers care is more, to reade, than vnderstande. Legere &amp; non intelligere negligere est. C. G. Maister of Arte, in the prayse of the Authour. In wisedomes schoole Apollo, and dame Pallas thought it fit Of al, therin your Aucthour here, in highest rome to sit. Holde there (quoth shee) the Muses all haue lulde thee in their lappe, Not I alone haue giuen thee sucke, but they haue giu? thee pappe. Ganges, thy streames bedewed, his penne thy sandes haue polisht eke, Rare blossomes blowne to mortal men, yet not in him to seeke. Arethusa, thy influence in him it is not skant, Not Polymneia eke hir rules of Rhetoricke doth he want, God guyde thy steps therefore my Grange, and eke what is begunne, Echidmas sting thou onely soughtes by secrete meanes to shunne. Ioue would it so, thou knowest well Pernassus Mounte to clyme Of Momus mates, thou needst not care, nor muttring Mucius slyme: Holde here therefore thy iust rewarde, a crowne of Laurell bayes, Not sounding trumpe, but due desertes, thy flickering fame shall rayse. Gra?t him ye fatall sisters three, old Næstors race to run Renoumedly without default, &amp; cracke of fame to shun. A Grange in deede he may be termde, a Grange for eache delight, Not Grange, nor groue, nor fertile fielde that is in eache mans sight, Grange would I so acco?ted be, but such a Grange I meane, For outwarde mirth and secrete sense as earst hath not bene seene. FINIS. W. S. in commendation of the Aucthor. Of siluer pure thy penne is made, dipte in the Muses well, Thy Eloquence and loftie style all other doth excell: Thy wisedome great and secrete sense diffusedly disguysde, Doth shew how Pallas rules thy minde, and Phœbus hath deuisde Those Golden lines, which polisht are with Tagus glittring sandes. A pallace playne of pleasures great vnto the vewers handes. Thy learning doth bewray it selfe and worthie prayse dothe craue, VVho so thee knew, did little thinke suche learning thee to haue. Here Vertue seemes to checke at Vice, and wisedome folly tauntes: Here Venus she is set at naught, and Dame Diane she vauntes: Here Pallas Cupid doth detest, and all his carpet knightes: Here doth she shew, that youthfull impes in folly most delightes. And how when age comes creeping on, with shewe of hoary heares, Then they the losse of time repent, with sobbes and brynish teares. Thou Ambodexter playste herein, to take the first rebounde, And for to shew thy minde at large, in earth doth the same c?pound: So that Apollo claddes his corps all with Morychus clothes, And shewes himself still friendliest there, where most of al he lothes. FINIS. [Verse extracted from Golden Aphroditis] I. I. his deuice to. A. O. The soaring Hauke beyonde his skill who seekes to soare so hye, That weeried wings shall him anoy before he footing fyndes: The recklesse birde on euery branche that seekes to prone and prye, The sayler of his launching ship the mast which weakly bindes, At length shal breed their bathing bane to scourge th? in their kinds. And though the change of pasture helpes by proofe to make fat calues, Through slickenesse yet, the rolling stone we see can take no mosse. Wherfore sith you will dayly seeke eche thing to part by halues, Think for your part, &amp; for your pains, nought else to gain but drosse For while you seeke a greater gaine, your wittes in vaine you tosse. Your selfe to be the rolling stone, and I your Sisiphus You sought to make, but all in vaine, I learned haue to shunne, The poysoning plagues of Circes cup (as did Prometheus) Which was him sent as sawce, for y? which erst by stelth he won: Wherfore with leysure now repent, with haste what you begon. Sith Socrates vs byd denide one Venus into two, In two likewise Dan Cupid God, loue tormentes to abate: Therfore you wil (as none erst did) hir corps deuide in moe, Which plainly shewes your ch?ge w? choice, your ch?ge I mean of late, Which turnd your frends to mortal foes, by ch?ging of your mate. When Aeolus mindes to raigne, then Boreas nedes must hast, Elleborus hath me purged, I now defie thy crew. By profe I finde an ape an ape, in purple be she plast. Let who list do as Argus did, kepe thee within their mew: Yet who so list, or who so doth shal neuer finde thee true. And sith you thinke your beautie such, as none inioyes the like: To Platos Citie, fairies lande, or to Vtopia wenne: Yea sith you thinke your wisedome such, as no man hath the like: In desertes shrinke (as Tymon did) go seeke some caue or denne, There to inioy your giftes alone, imparted not to men. Perhappes dan Phæbus in the day, Minippus else by night, In sight, which passe Linceus eyes, will spie thee forth at length, With b?ding eyes from sun &amp; Moone, who rauisht with thy sight, In heau? wil place thee as a star, none can withst?d their strength. Thus thou dispising mortall men, the Goddes enioyes at length. Mitto tibi fr?tem Veneris, mediumque Dianæ, Principium lucis quod mare claudat item. Tempus erit quo tu quia nunc excludis am?tes Frigidia disertè nocte iacebis anus. This token herein closed I sende as for my last farewel, Tis Eglantine, which plainly shews where swete there soure lay. My loue at first (most like the leaues) did giue a fragrant smell. But now at last, tis like the prickes most hurtful bearing sway. Yet as the prickes do yeelde no hurt, Unlesse some one abuse the smell: So had my last bene like my first, If thou the first had vsed wel. Hereafter set by none so light, As I haue founde thee set by me: Least they then doe as I do now, Take of thy belles, and let thee flee. N. O. his visitation of A. O. by writing. Nere drownd in d?ps of drowsines, shal Morpheus bind my hed With kercher dipte in Limbo lake? shall drowsy dumps forbed My penne to shewe the zelous loue which I to thee do beare? No no: if Dytis dungeon darke did hedge thee in to feare I woulde not yeelde my liuely spirites: for why? not Tartars denne, Not Cerberus he, Auerne deepe, nor yet the Gorgon fenne, Not Plutoes grisly gates I say, nor yet Megera fierce, The Stygian poole, with thousand more, which now for to reherse It were too long: not Phlegethons flame shuld bar me fro thy sight, But needes I would aduenture all to winne thee in despight. Wherfore accept my willing pen descrying thus my hart, Until my corps doth come in place, and maketh good his part. Thus fare you well my gemme of ioy, the fountayn of delight. Farewell once more, thou wel of lyfe, thus takes my pen his flight. Fil vp my lampe with oyle of grace. N. O. whome I vowe to be, Your loyall he. Adewe. A. O. to hir louer, charging him with an vntruth. With vapourd eyes, &amp; scalding sighes, my tedious steps I trace, w? wailful weeds I clad my corps, salt tears bedews my face: A boiling brest like Aetna hill, subdues my sweltring hart, And ransackt vaines perswades me now to thinke on Cupids darte. I see my heart with inward thoughts hath bathed in good-will, That hounde which seekes by ranging foote a virgins rule to spill. Which lothsom death w? fearful mace c?mands to work my dome, With ayde lykewise of sisters three to finish foorth my tombe. O Ladyes of the Destiny, shal this a guerdon bee In lieu of my good will bestowed? may nought occasion bee To bulwarke my defence in neede? haue I a rolling stone All wrapt in gold, as if it were a gemme that peer had none? Well well N. O. vnlesse you proue your selfe a peerlesse gemme: Unconstancie will me perforce constrayne thee to condemne. By proofe we see, what golden is, the same hath glittering spheares, As Phebus hath his radyant rayes, Pactolus eke that beares His siluerie sands on shore, and Tagus castes his golde to lande Yea Lydius hath his golden streames, and Hermes glittring sande: So Uertue would not lurke vnknowne, if vertue did thee rule, But needs wold shine like glittring beams, though wrapt in Friers cule. Report could not subuert thy fame, if thou y? virgins path Had trode by rule of Uirgins lawe, or bathde thy selfe in bath Of loyall loue. But yet I hope how that Dan Eccho failes, With m?bling voice of foltring song (thogh truth imbark y? sailes.) Wherfore as one deuoide of ioye, and yet would faine reioyce, Imbarke this foming froth of waues, then with of pleasure choyce I may adorne my daisy banke, whiche delectable seemes To those, whose greedie senses seekes the scent which floures teems. And thus, Adieu. From my lodge where I march all with my dumpishe Muse. videlicet Melpomenes. A. O. N. O In his owne defence. Shal Zoilus he, or Momus mates imbash my penne to write? Or shal the want of Homers quill, or Virgils vayne to endyte, I new diffused Chaos make of these my pestred wittes? Not so, though Tritons trumpet shrill on fynned fish that sittes, Hath blased vnto your tentiue eares, what honor might defame, Sith I vnguiltie am thereof, I wil not seeke the same Texcuse, for why? I know that tyme ech thing wil bring to light: And truth it selfe wil come in place gainst falshoodes force to fight. By phrase of filed style you seeme a verdict rash to giue Of prisoner yours to dye, but yet it grauntes my state to liue. By rolling stone, and ranging hounde vnconstant me to be, Your painting penne by art declares: yet shal you neuer see, Nor know my senses, for to know the breath of any wight Saue thou alone, as Biblia, who when Duellus hight Him selfe to haue a stinking breath by open parlance mayde Of Roman dames vnto his face: I haue not knowen (she sayde,) But all mens breath haue bene alike, such was the vestal line Of that hir chosen path, as wel the stories doe define. Wherefore in suspence now let hang, the iudgemente of my dome, Tyl truth through time for falshodes corps hath finisht vp a tome. Thus fare thou wel my iemme of ioy Let not our absence breede anoy. [Ye Muses nine] Ye Muses nine With grace deuine My wittes to shrine Giue not consent, But ayding hand To beare my band Through sea &amp; land For good intent To rime not rayle Hold vp my sayle Let not breth faile the vertuous mode With trumpe to blase The condigne phrase Of hyr who stayed Where vertue stoode. Although of Helicone that well my tongue hath not assayde: And though the Horne of Acheloye his knowledge hath denayde: Yea, though Alcinous Orcharde hath his fruyte denayde my lore, Whereby I might the apter be my landing carme to score: Yet Arethusa, yeelde me thine influence to indite, And Phebus sharpe my willyng penne, expresly for to write The blasing feates displaying wise of Natures darlyng deare, Whome Uertue she with golden mace and trumpe dothe seeke to reare. Yet sithe my selfe by paynting penne I would so fayne disguise, Lucina graunt Apollo may melodiously deuise My filed phrase, so polished with Tagus glittring sandes, Whereby hyr vewyng eyes might thinke she redde of golden landes. Ye Goddes seclude my rurall penne, and yeelde a glosing stile, With curious polished phrase, or with relucent file, Of Tullies famous eloquence To prayse hir worthy excellence. Come yeelde thy leaues thou Laurell tree to make a garland rounde: To Crowne hyr head, and let the trumpe hyr flying fame resounde. Whose features all so many are, so worthie, and so cleare, That of my selfe I dare be bolde to say, she hath no peare. Suche paynting forme, some comely hue consisteth in hyr face, That from the Goddes I well suppose she may define hyr race. Polixene fayre, Caliop, and Penelop may giue place. Atlanta, and dame Lucres fayre, she doth them bothe deface. The precious orient pearle so fayre and gorgeous cleare, Doth testifie vnto hyr mates the whitenesse of hyr leare. Hir lusty, liuely gallant lookes with rosed ruby ruddes, Resembleth right to standers off the pleasant red rose buddes. Hyr sweete and eke hyr sugred lippes, softe, rounded lyke the berrie, Right well to me resemble doe the crimson bloomed cherrie. So that to me poore wretche I counte it were an heauenly blisse, At suche a sweete and sugred mouthe to steale a pleasant kisse. Hyr rounde, fayre, and flanting cheekes moste rosedlyke are paynted, What though dame Fortune caused hir fronte to be attainted? Perforce eche harte with truth must graunt, it can not be denayed, But that this skar vpon hyr fronte was womanly conueyed. Whiche seemeth from a farre To be a radyant Starre Hyr butned, ruby chinne, hir face, and eke hir necke did shine, As though they were with Iuery white all burnisht maruelous fine. Hir prety nose is somewhat shorte, it well bec?mes hyr face, Hir fryseled heare in knotted wise is to hyr fronte a grace. Hir temples smothe, and eke hir vaines stande full of lustie crue. I liken them therefore as likest to Indie Saphire blew. Hir twinckling eyne bothe steepe and grey, they seeme like Christall cleare. Hir siluery teeth, and golden tongue, doe say shee hath no peare. Hir fingers are bothe long and small, hir handes are softe as silke: The palmes thereof are somewhat shorte, yet whiter than the milke. Hir comely sides are long and straight, all shapde in massiue golde. What harte aliue coulde hyr denie with fame to be inrolde? My harte it dothe bothe skippe and ioye to see hir trace the grounde. Hir feete they are so fine, and feate, hir heeles so shorte and rounde. But stay, O Muse, thy golden mace, and Gange now bedewe My paynting penne with siluery streames, that I foorthwith may shewe What feates within this comely corps by parant proofe doth rest, I thanke thee that thou seemst to graunt at first to my request. Hir curteous harte, and lowly minde adornde with vertues rare: Hir sober lookes with brydeled cheere doth shewe she hath a care To trace the chaste Dianas lawes as well by deede as thought, That nought may seeme to scape hyr handes whiche vertue hath not taught. Hir tongue it rolles in Rethoricke termes to giue eche man delighte: Whiche rauisht hath my sencelesse wittes by cancred Cupids spighte. Alas poore wretche what should I say? to looke on hir agayne I may nor can it not abide, though tis a pleasant payne. With hyr aye to remayne, Some hartes ease for to gayne: This blossome of freshe flower Beares Hartes ease for hyr bower. A. O. VVorthie to be in rolde, VVith letters of golde. Car elle vault. [Whiche flower faire and freshe in Adones garden sawe I groe] Whiche flower faire and freshe in Adones garden sawe I groe: The sight whereof hath rauisht me, ill might I it forgoe. But (to my griefe) to winne the same, no way finde out I can: Wherfore this fragrant flower I mighte full iustly curse and ban, The sight whereof and pleasant hue hath forced me to yeelde Unto their lore, as Sirenes, whose songs bothe sweete and milde, Perforce them to doe drawe the saylers by, but none escape Fro them aliue, no more shall I: for whyle with hope I gape My ioyes to winne, my life departes: what do I then preuayle, Unlesse I had Vlisses arte, then might I safely sayle? For while through pleasant outwarde sight I seeke for to obtayne My hartes desire, and winne it not, what ioyes do then remaine? I woulde to God my wit had serude to vse that famous grace Of Percian Kings, who neuer goe abroade with open face, But with some lawne or silken scarfe: then it I had not spyde, The wante whereof dothe force me now in torments to abide. For why? I can not turne my selfe into a golden rayne, Nor to a Bull, as Goddes they can, their pleasure to obtayne. Wherefore thus much, though strange it be, yet iustly may I say, I pleasure take, yet as my foe, it brings me to decay. For whyle I pleasure take to see, the sight doth me confounde: As doth the Gorgon whose fierce eyes do yeelde a deadly wounde. And when I striue to come away, and leaue that pleasant sight, I seeme as though with Hydra fierce that serpent I did fight: Who leesing one of all his heddes, seuen springeth in his ryne, So I through voiding of this sight, seu? times my cares do twine. With lure I play the Faukner kinde, I hallowe, and I whoupe, I shake my fiste, I whistle shrill, but nought will make hir stoupe, Wherefore (though sore against my wil) I finde the prouerbe true, Vnmanned Haukes forsake the lure, whiche maketh me to rue. I see I swimme agaynst the streame, I kicke against a gode, I caste a stone against the winde: my tongue that nere abode To say thee wel, my feete to goe, my handes to do the like, Yet you deniall giue, whiche doth my harte asunder strike. Yet somewhat would my greedy gripes, &amp; eke my carping cares, My griping grieues, my sobbing sighes, and eke my tedious teares Abate, if that but halfe my harte it would returne againe: What doth preuaile c?plainte or none, for nought therby I gaine? Yet Poetes say that Triton can with sounding trumpe inforce Eche thing that hath exceeded bandes receiue his former corce. If this be true, then Triton come retreyte with me to blowe: I call in vaine, there is no such, the Poetes braines did crawe. Yet will I wofull wighte my corps with stedfast colours clad, As Russet decte with Blew, as stedfast suites as may be had To represent my faithfull harte, a banner to be true, And like vnto the turtle Doue whiche changeth not for new. As carped knight thus standes my cace, woe to me wofull wight, Whose harte is like to Aetna hill which burneth day and night. I spende my time in sobbing sighes, from sighes I turne to teares, From tedious teares to pensiue playnt, and thus my life it weares. Yea thus the shell of carping care hath put my ioyes to flight: That ioyfull tunes increase my woe, thus doe I mourne aright. And if by chaunce I heare the sounde of song or instrument, Me thinkes the tune that dolefull is doth helpe me to lament. And as the deare whiche stricken is, dothe drawe himselfe alone, So will I seeke some secrete place where I might make my mone, Secluding ioy, imbracing care, the Incresse trade to vse I will incline, who closde in walles no pleasure can peruse. Eche side inclosde, parte of my graue my nayles shal dayly scrape, In token that my death shall soone rewarde my cursed happe. Yet mayst thou al with ease preuent, if pittie taketh place, If not, then dolefull dumpes approch to rue my wretched cace. N. O. [The fountayne Granus giueth str?gth vnto the weakened bone] The fountayne Granus giueth str?gth vnto the weakened bone, And eke the force of Spawe doth help al those y? haue y? Stone. Who hath the lither Feuer, runnes to Padoa for helpe, And to Veronas well he hies whose wante of bloud doth yelpe. Yet as by proofe Buckestones do stande, to those that here doth dwel, In steede of Grane, and Padoa, of Spawe and Verone well: So mightst thou hartes ease be to me, that al these things do neede, In steede of Buckstones present help, if so it be thy meede. For why? I sinke in Syrtes sandes, through tasting Circes cuppe, Unlesse thou speedy helpe wilt bring by chinne to holde me vp. For tangled thus in Scyllas bandes, and whelmde in Lethe lake, Who can me helpe but thou alone? tis onely for thy sake. If nought may breede remorse, nor make your stony harte relent, Then may I wake, &amp; wayle the night, my bed w? teares besprent. Then may I say as Atlas did, I beare this waighte in vaine. My thirste doth likewise say, I may with Tantalus complaine. Then may I say as Sisiphus, I toyle to none effect, As Theseus, and Ticius, with other of my secte. Then is thy loue a Labyrinth vnto me for my liking: Whome great good will hath grauelled, since Cupid fell a striking. But yet in time I hope to finde such mercie at thy hande: That where thy wrath sometime bore sway, thy friendship once shall stand. If not, Then, What Clotho doth on distaffe place for Lachesis to twyne, Come Atropos with speedy pace to bryng the same to fyne. N. O. N. O. beginning, A. O. followeth, crauing ayde of the Muses and chiefe Musitions. He Now Venus with your ruffling Nimphes Keepe backe Dianas dearlings deare: And Muses graunt your ayding impes, Our strings to tune and notes to reare: With perfect deawe of Helicons well. Where Poetes fayne your Muse to dwell. She Orpheus with thy Harpe in hande, Arion also with the like, Wrinche vp your strings, and make them stande In egall heigth: Amphion strike Thy twinckling Harpe with fingers small, That ioyfull tunes may rise withall. He Me thinkes I heare Apollo graunt Melodiously for to deuise, And Venus bid Minerua vaunt, So that no dolefull dumpes may rise: The Muses likewise (graunting ayde,) Doe bid strike vp, thus none denayde. She What man doth longer thinke, than he, the weary winters nighte, Whose cares forbiddes his eyes to sleepe? what is a greater spighte To him who thinkes he sayles in seas whose waues of honye are, Yet time purloynes his former ioy, and brings him to despayre? He With gasing eyes for him to looke whiche hath no care to come To serue where no acceptance is (as Ladies deale by some) To be in bed and not to sleepe, what greater griefe then this? To die for wante of foode, and yet he feedes on daintie dishe? She To rue and rage, to frie and freese, these are the louers panges: Who dies himselfe and liues in hir his life in suspence hangs. Yet if he liue in after hope his Ladies loue to gaine, Then holdes his harte, and rendeth not by direfull darte in twayne. He Hope looketh for requitance made whiche oftentimes doth fayle, Or else to gayne his harte againe which were a luckie gayle. But lesse than seldome seene it is, what giuen doth not returne, From womens handes, who rather had to frie then else to turne. She But what if neyther seeme to come, and hope beginnes to faynte? Then seeme they all to weept and wayle, and teares with streakes doth paynte Their lether cheekes are (profe declares,) stale nature to prouoke, Whose harte opprest with scalding sighes, their throates doth seeme to choke. He Thus witlesse wightes doe breede their woe: yea, riper yeares and setled heddes Herein doe wante their skoking pointes, whose glauncing eyes by rule forbeddes. Thus trapte they let these wordes to flie: oh get my graue in readinesse, Remedilesse I die, I die, I die remedilesse. Finis. [Lie fatall fooles fat fedde with foode] Lie fatall fooles fat fedde with foode of talped minde and rangyng hed: O talpes, thinke ye to change the moode of buzzyng Bees with Mel so fed? O talped talpes, O buzzing Bees, thinke ye Dame Venus hath no wit To shunne the ginne when she it sees but that she must needes fall in it? Then she and all Uenereall kinde Apollo wanted for his skill To cleare their eyes, whiche were too blinde, if not they coulde withstande your will. Of naughty seede since you haue store, will you it cast on others grounde: Then are they common to foolishe lore, whiche pokes it vp and hath it founde. When Venus listeth for to ride, to decke hyr heeles with your spurres, Hir nature can it not abyde she hath no gappe that wanteth furres. Of ought whereof shee standes in neede, she needeth not to seeke redresse, When Vulcane fayles, Mars stands in steede hyr corps with his for to suppresse. But yet, What needes a mate while Marrowe liues, this is the marke whereat you shoote: To tell eche hole conteynde in siues vnbende your bowe it is no boote. Unmanned Haukes forsake the lure, all whistlying brings them not to fiste: Wherefore with shame put vp your lure, a Hauke will checke still when she liste. [Congealed ayre doth make the starres to shote.] Congealed ayre doth make the starres to shote. But seldome yet tis seene such starres to fal: By earnest suyte not I but all our route We yeelded haue to ayde you when you call. And that you should such call as best can ayde I sende thee here what is eche one hir trayde. But in the Goblet she graued these verses following in the same order as she had done before. I for my parte, loue tragedies to penne. And Cleo notes the worthinesse of menne. Thaleia she delights in cunnyng talke. In soundyng trumpe Euterpes wittes do walke: In Musicke rules Terpsichore delightes. Erato loues Geometry that hightes. Heroicall verse Calliope firste did knowe. Euranea loues Astrologie to showe. And last of all Polymneia shee, Will force thy tongue Rhetoricall to bee. Thus to vsurpe at any time our ayde, Take heede of this, least that you be denayde. [Sith Crasus wealth, with Crassus pompe, &amp; Midas golde is skant] Sith Crasus wealth, with Crassus pompe, &amp; Midas golde is skant, It shall suffice to wishe you well, good will shall neuer wante: Thryce Næstors yeares to liue in age I craue that Clotho graunt, that of your helth good fame &amp; welth, your willers wel might va?t. Alter Atropos and Lachesis with Clotho graunt you the lyfe of Long lyfed Næstor, whose youth not soone being cut off, Aged and hoarte as Hyems who did not call him? Wrinkled, yet sugred in wordes, so who hath not termde him? [Who will the curnell of the nutte] Who will the curnell of the nutte, must breake the shell: Who will the spoyle of any towne, must sacke the walles: Who will the harte of any Dame, must touch hir harpe: Who will the fruyte that haruest yeeldes, must take the payne. [Unfolde your courtesie oh amorous dame] Thus beginneth their song. F Unfolde your courtesie oh amorous dame, Ioyne leagues of amity my deare by name. G Unlace your loyalty, breake vp your loue, For so fidelity it doth behoue. F I can though I vaunt not, G So I though I graunt not, May yeelde thy request. F Dan Cupid constrayneth. G So Venus refrayneth No tyme for to ieste. F I ieste not, G I weste not, F Then it for to trie I vowe this my harte within that doth lie, Thine owne vndefiled and euer to be. G Soone heate, soone colde I see, Soone withered what redresse? F This counsell giue I thee, Suth like for like professe. G My fancie layes liking, oh let thy suyte fall, Withstand Cupides striking, oh giue him a fall. F I ran not, nor will not, it pricketh myne harte, I dare not, I may not, withstand that his darte. G My fancie denayes thee, F But yet sithe I like thee Oh say me not nay. G Affection scholeth F No reason it ruleth To say me denay. G And what then? F Be flatte then. G No likyng I haue, To wedde gaynst liking, your pardon I craue: For good will deserueth good will for to haue. F Then render loue for loue, Els shall I die for woe: G We see how pynes the doue, But yet he dyes not tho. F May nothing purchase grace my ioyes to renewe? Shall pitty take no place? then pleasure adewe. G Tis folly I tell thee you lull in your lappe, It grieues me (beleeue me) that such was your happe. F My bale then delightes me, G Curse Cupid that strucke thee, To like for no gayne. F That will not suffice me, G That loue should so tyce thee, The greater thy payne. F I finde it: G Untwyne it: F A lasse I can not, So Vulcanes nettes twyne me, that not a denay Can force me to leaue thee, though twere my decay. G My fancie biddes auaunte, You spende your winde in vayne. F Though thus you seeme to taunt, I hope your harte to gayne. G Ouer loued soone lost, betroth not your hande: Least you gayne to your cost, a willow garland. F Alas, fancy moues me, to change for no newe, But still for to loue thee, my payne to renewe. G And what though you change not? F The harder were my lotte Thus farre for to range. G Your folly it harmeth: F Is wisedome you warneth, Yet be not to strange. G I graunt it, F I vaunt it, G Then if you fayne not, I vowe vndefiled thine owne for to bee: Thy faith it shall bynde me agayne to loue thee. F My ioyes are vnfayned, And bannish my gryping: G My harte thou hast gayned, In lieu of thy liking. F Then coll me and kisse, whiche arte my delight: Let flaunta, galanta, put sorrowes to flight. G In hope that Dame pleasure vs neuer will fayle, Let flanta galanta stiffe holde vp our sayle. F Then hoyste it and vaunt it: G Yea vaunt it, and graunt it: With huff and with huff. F To sport I beshrowe thee, G To flaunt it beleeue me, I sit in my ruff. F Then vaunt it, G I graunt it, F all So this liketh well: Our sorrowes are squenched, with pleasaunt delight, Huff, huff, let vs huff it, by day and by night. G Let pleasure be hoysted, New fangles deuised, F Yea lette it be roysted, And newe pastyme trysed: All With all a flantare then let vs beginne, Our goodes haue no ending, sing let vs not linne. FINIS. GRANGES GARDEN: Conteyning as well certaine verses vpon sundry poyntes, in Metre, as also diuerse Pamphlets in prose: Pleasant to the eare, and delightfull to the Reader, if he abuse not the scente of the Floures. A valiant yong Gentleman beyng trayned vp in Martiall provves, and allured by euill counsell to womens follies, bewayleth his life in this order. Sometime in Martiall deedes, I set my whole delight: And eke my stedfast eyes did hate, of w?ton dames the sight. But now I take delight, each blasing starre to vewe, My tongue likewise with sugred wordes, inquireth of their mewe. Then thither fast I hie, if hope doth giue me grace, And many wanton lookes I cast, to vewe hir comely face. Thus hath shee wonne my harte, my purse is neuer tide, Good will hath giuen a dasing dente, fro thence I may not bide. In hope I spende my time, in hope to gayne my will, I daunce attendance euery day, in hope to haue my fill. Sometime I haue my wishe, the bensell of hir bowe, Sometime I haue my hartes desire, of certen this I knowe. Sometime againe I wante, what is my hartes desire, Which as dry wood, and kindling coles, doth set my harte on fire. Then I to late repent my want on foolishe eye, Which gussheth forth like springs of teares, my c?st?t hart to trie. Than this, what greater griefe? to spende my winde in vayne, On those who nought regarde my harte, &amp; lesse regard my payne. Then wishe I all to late, that Mars had rulde my will, Then Cupid, he, nor Venus had, not knowen my hart to kill. My goods are wasted whole, and I consumed am, Beware therefore by others harmes, a Tygre seemes a lam. But iudgement here I craue, who greater sorrowes sente, Of him who tyste me herevnto, or hir to whome I lente? If he, then all beware, of me who bought my witte, And shunne the counsell of the naught, a wise mans rule to hitte. If she, likewise eschewe, th' allurements of the nought, And learne by me, for sure it is, I haue my wisedome bought. Though tis a sugred bayte, it is but for the time, And riper yeares lamenteth much, the losse of former time. But youth regardeth not, the things that are to come, Oh would to God I followed had, the sound of trump &amp; dromme. For aged yeares forbid to runne this youthfull race, And warnde me oft, who wold not heare, for lighting in this cace. Yong men thinks old men fooles, but old men knoweth well, Yong men are fooles, and wants the witte, wherein they do excell. Let no man therefore shunne, the counsell of the olde, For he a foole may counted be. whose faultes would not be tolde. Thus happie I him counte, who can right well beware, Of others harmes, least he himselfe, should fall in such a snare. His Poesie. VVhat wisedome warneth marke you well That follie harvesth truth dothe tell. The force of Beauties pryce. As Cæcias winde, hath force the clowdes to drawe: As Geate, or Anuibre, likewise doth by strawe: As Adamant stones, dothe Iron plucke them to: So amorous lookes, hath force the like to do. And as Dan Titan, with his radiant guyse, The withering grasse, doth skorche in smothring wise: Ueneriall Dames, do likewise parche the harles, Of rauening youthes, with there Cupidall dartes. Thus beyng set on fire with masing minde they stande, Of ardent loue, and waues of woe, to see the vpper hande. Tace commoui. A Gentleman reuealeth his former life. When youth was in his prime, and florisht most of all, I set my whole delight to vew, whom gall?t dames m? cal. So wauring was my witte, so wanton was mine eye, That all the day I walkt the streetes, to see who passed bye. And when a crewe I spide, adornd with toppes of pleumes, Such gasing sights did please me wel, and daintie fed my reumes. If hir I did suspect a Curtizan to be, Then would I clap hir on the lippes, though euery man did see. And say all hayle faire dame, I ioye to see your health, You will not know your w?ted fri?ds such is your store of welth. Then she herewith amazde not knowyng me before, Will thinke I come (as one a fresh) acquaintance new to score. If she whome thus I kiste, did sayle in vertues barke, I crie you mercy then I sayde, I did mistake my marke. No harme, she would replie: thus I a kisse would gayne, Of those whome nere I sawe before, else was it to my payne. And when my hand was in, with those whiche were of welth. The tablet hanging on hir necke, sometime I gotte by stealth. Sometime I got hir ring, sometimes hir chayne of golde, Sometime she gaue me mony store, to bye me what I would. Thus making vp my mouth, I made thereof a skoffe, I counte I got it all by stealth, hir mate knew not thereof. If hir by chaunce I met, in presence of hyr mate, I passed by, I knew hir not, nor looked at hir gate. Yet if he marked not, my nobbes a nodde should haue, My Connie she would winke againe, but none should it perceaue. If that she bitte hir lippe, thereby I knew hir harte, I must be logging all in haste, hir husband would not starte. And for a token true, to passe betwixt vs twayne, Yea, for to keepe our hartes in loue, she broke a ring in twayne. If ought I stoode in neede, this token did I sende, At sight whereof she ready was, what might for euer lende. Yea glad she was to bende, least hir I should forsake, Who did hir selfe vnto my lure, so curteously betake. Good cheere I could not wante, when gone he was from home, Nor nothing else which pleasde mine eye (neglecting sillie mome) This got my ranging foote, this got my glauncyng eye, This got I say my trying tongue, whiche tolde hyr many a lye. But now the pryme is paste, the flower of all my ioye, Yea, now my youthful dayes are spent, and fortune seemeth coye. Each thing most freshe of hue, in tyme of Lady Ver, Now Titan with his parchyng beames, beginnes himselfe to ster. Now Autumne he is paste, and Hiems c?mes in place, My goodes are wasted whole &amp; some, wh? should I sue for grace? What should I leane vnto? my pillers now are gone, And eke the trulles whereto I lente, are changed euery chone. Now must I turne my coate, and cleaue vnto my God, Desiring pardon for my crime, that spared hath his rod. This is the common ende, of those whiche vse the game, Happie is he that sees the snare, and can eschewe the same. Compare your former luste, vnto your after witte, For wisedome sayes for Vertues schoole dame Follie is not fitte. And tyme will force thee see, how follie did anoy, For where dame pleasure b?t thy bowe, now fortune seemeth coy. Thus thou at length wilt turne, if vertue giues thee grace, If not, assure thy selfe to burne, where pleasures hydes hir face. His Poesie. Serò sapiunt Phryges. The paynting of a Curtizan. It is a worlde to see, eache feate displaying wise, Of Venus Nimphes, of Curtizans, whom folly doth disguise. Yea, how, and by what meanes, they doe allure the youth, To spend vpon th? all they haue, whose beauty whettes their tooth. Who listeth to beholde, and marke my painting penne, Shall see their garish trickes set downe, wherby they allure the m?. First with their lawnes, and calles of golde beset with spangs, With died, and frizeled perewigs, with hartes fro thence that h?gs, With veluet cappes, and plumes, they doe adorne their heddes, With red &amp; white they painte their face, to tice th? to there beddes. There partlets set with spangs, come close vnto their chinne, There gorgets fairely wrought without, inclose blacke necks w?in. And from their eare there hangs, a pearle and siluer ring, As for a bell, the sounde whereof, such like to hir doth bring. About hir necke likewise, there hangeth many a chayne, Yea, many a costly iem they weare, thats giu? th? of their trayne. Their gownes in fashion are, there vardingales are greate, Their gownes likewise which are so side, do sweepe al?g y? streate. Their pompes most oft are white, their pantables are blacke, Their wosted hose are purple blew, thus nothing do they lacke. Their gloues are all befumde, with pure and perfect smell, Yea, all their clothes which smels of muske, loe here she goes they tel. Their smockes are all bewrought, about the necke &amp; hande, And (to be short) I tell you playne, all things in order stande. They onely walke the streates, to see and to be seene, Their w?ton eyes caste here &amp; there, will tell you what they bene. But if hyr flanting lookes, hath trayned any one, Unto the mewe wherein she keepes, along as she hath gone, They shalbe sure to finde, all kinde of musicke there, And she hir selfe (at his request) to play she will not spare. Whiche doth inflame his harte, with flashing sparkes of heate, To trie with sugred wordes, if so, his harte would cease to beate. Then she to passe the time, at cardes will seeke to play, Or else to tables will they goe, to driue the time away. Then will they vaunt, and graunt, and for affinitie, At cardes they will vye, and reuye, each their virginitie. At Irishe game she will, contrary to the game, At bearing beare more than she should, by proofe I know the same. If that she taken be, with this, that byr foule play, Then makes she straight thereof a ieste (I saw it not) to say But with this ouersight, she doth prouoke the man, To thinke the worste and trie the best, by all the meanes he can. Then must she haue such cheare, as may be got for quoyne, That by the foode of dayntie dishe, hir woes he might purloyne. To spende and make no spare, he must himselfe incline, No quoyne, good cheare, aray, nor gemmes, for cost he may define. For, giue me, and fetch me, this is their dayly song, But yet with this worde Adfer she driues him straight along. This worde for to fulfill, he settes on sale his lande, And nought he seeth hir wante, but buyth it out of hande. His presence doth deserue, remembraunce for to haue, But out of sight so out of minde: good will doth presence craue. And if she grauntes him grace, to mitigate his woes, His handketcher she will bewet, with water of a rose. And then such wanton toyes, she wilbe sure to finde, That he perswades himselfe herewith, to him she is full kinde. Who would requyre more? it full requites his coste. And he likewise (as proude thereof) will make thereof his boste. Yea, yea, she treades so nice, she would not wafers breake, And maulte horse like she beares hir mayne, y? ayre hir armes doth streake. Thus as a floting fishe, she glides along the streete, As la?cing ships she cuts y? seas, hir plumes the sayles doth greete. But if by candle light, she chaunce hir selfe to showe, Hir paynted forme so glistreth, as the starres appearde arowe. Such cousining trickes they haue, each man for to deceaue, That while they credite giue therto, his wordes their wits bereaue. Wherfore let not thine eye, reduce thy wanton woe, Nor giue no credite to their wordes, whiche honie like doe flowe. Light wonne, light lost againe, be sure them thus to finde, For lightly comen, so lightly gone, this is a harlots kinde. Beleue a harlots wordes, and weaue a webbe of woe: No credite therefore giue thereto, beleue it is not so. She will not sticke to sweare she hath not knowen a man, And thou alone hir maydenhed, by filed phrase haste wan. And that no man aliue, could euer gayne his will, When many an one, yea, evry day, of hir hath had their fill, No man hath toucht hir skinne, excepting hande and face, Thus will they lie with euery breath, it is their wonted grace. Take heede therefore betime, least thou too late repent. And curse the time that ere you knewe, thereby what folly mente. Beleeue, my wordes are true, by proofe thou shalt them finde, Adewe at laste, I wishe thee well, take heede of womenkinde. The Authours Poesie. Ne femina, ne tela, non piglia alla candela. A Gentleman seing his brother desirous to goe to the seas, vvrote these verses following, vnwitting to any, and layed them in his brothers vvay. I rue to see the raging of the seas, When nothing may king Eolus wrath appease. Boreas blastes asunder rendes our sayles: Our tacklings breake, our ankers likewise fayles. The surging seas, they battred haue my shippe, And eke mine oares auayle me not a chippe. The ropes are slackte, the maste standes nothing strong: Thus am I toste, the surging seas along. The waues beate in, my barke to ouerflowe, The rugged seas, my ship will ouerthrowe. Yea, driuen I am, sometimes against a Rocke, Sometimes againe a Whale his backe I locke. When Neptune thus, and Eol falles to stryfe, Then stand I most in daunger of my lyfe. And when the winde beginneth moste to rage, Then out I caste (my barke for to asswage) Each thing of waight, and then if sea at will I chaunce to haue, I lesse regard mine ill. If shipwrack once, I suffer in my life, Farewell my goodes, farewell my gentle wife. Adewe my friendes, adewe my children all, For nought prenayles, though on your helpe I call. First goe I to the bottome of the seas, And thrice I rise, but nothing for mine ease. For why? at length, when last of all I fall, My winde doth fayle, wherewith I burst my gall. My body then, so full as it may be With water store, then may each man me see All borne alofte, amid the fomyng froth, And dryuen to lande, if Neptune waxeth wrothe. But yet if so I cunnyng haue to swimme, When first I fall into the water brimme: With streakyng armes and eke with playing feete, My parte I play the water flouddes to grete. And then perchaunce, some shippe comes sayling bye, Whiche saues my life, if me they doe espie. Perchaunce likewise I drowne before they come, Perchaunce the crampe my feete it maketh numme. If so it dothe, then sure I am to die, In this distresse the sea will ayde denie. Wherefore (I wishe) who well may liue by lande, And him forbid the sea to take in hande. The description of the loue of a Gentleman and a Gentlevvoman. In the tyme of Lady Ver, the sweete and fragrant smell Of each delight, it doth a rangyng foote compell. For when the Aprill showers, descende with westerne windes, Each hearbe, ech floure, and plante, doe florish in their kindes. Each leafe vpon the tree, the grasse vpon the grounde, The Hatherne buddes new sprung, on earth what may be founde, Doth yeelde as pleasant scentes, as nature can deuise: All things in lusty greene, appeares displaying wise. And eurye birde that liues, then strayneth forth his voyce: So that of each delight, each man may take his choyce. Thus in this merry moneth, he tooke delight to vewe, Ought that of nature was, most pleasaunt in his hewe. Yea, many a tyme and oft, in springs and groues alone, Himselfe he would apply, as yet where none had gone. There in distilling wise, she tooke delight to see, The chirpyng birdes full ofte, from bushe to bushe to flee. Whose warbling notes him thought, inforced to beleue, That nothing vnder Sunne, such merry liues did liue. In euery bushe againe, the Primerose did appeere, The Uiolet at hande, was prest to be his feere: Which cast such fragrant smelles, amid this pleasant spring, That eury bushe it did, a newe delight forth bring. But walking all alone, in this his whole delight, The Primerose as him thought, and Uiolet did fight. Wherewith as one amazde, at large he them behelde, Hoping at length to see, the one or other yelde. But lighting in a vayne, which fortune had not tryed, Beholde euen neare at hande, a damsell he espied, Whose beauty was so braue, and eke so Christall cleere, That nature could not frame, the like to be hyr peere. Hir peere I neuer sawe, for beautie in the face, The like was neuer seene, such was hir comely grace. And where he tooke delight, before in fragrant scente, Now hir to gaze vpon, his minde was wholy bente. And as good fortune would, he stoode behinde a bushe, Where well he might beholde, and neede not starte the thrushe. For while she tooke delight, to vewe this pleasant fielde, He did obtayne his will, at large he hir behelde. And nought she did suspect, for here he lay vnknowne, Untill such time as loue, his kindling coles had blowne. Hir rounde and cherry lippes, and eke hir skarlet hewe, Hir crymson cheekes was cause, the more he did them vewe. Hir rosed lookes him thought, his tentiue eares forth tolde, The more that them he did, the more he should beholde. So fell it forth at length, he could not haue his fill, The more he did hir vewe, the more he wisht his will. When long he vewed had through many a pleasant tune, Him thought this Aprill month, was turnde to ioly June. For in hir face him thought, the redde rose and the white, In liuely forme did seeme, with other for to fighte. The Columbine likewise, whiche commendable is, With Dasies did contend, that delectable blisse. And as a Marygolde amazde, he hyr behilde, Untill hir dasing dentes, his rufull harte it filde. Then out alasse he cried, but all it was in vayne, His harte fro him was gone, and did with hir remayne. This damsell single was, and eke did wante a mate, And he to feede hyr reume, did wante a dayntie date. But yet his harte was good, and loue did make him bolde, He spared not at length, his meanyng to vnfolde. For hir he went vnto, and greeted in this wise, Alhayle deare dame he sayde, the chiefe of vertues pryse. I see that Lady Ver, with sweete and fragrant scente, Inflames your harte to see, whereto dame nature lente. The Nightingale likewise, with hyr recorded song, Hath giuen you this desire, this groue to walke along. For now each thing that is, doth florishe in his kinde, And is of force (me thinkes) to recreate the minde. And eke no greater health, vpon the earth is founde, Then early and late to walke, vpon this pleasaunt grounde: The scente whereof will so, restore your liuely bloud, That you your selfe will say, therefore tis very good. A thousande fancies more, for to delight the minde, Within this pleasaunt groue, by walking you may finde. A floure by chaunce I spie, whose beautie freshe and gay, Doth force against my will, what I to you doe say. It rauisht hath my wittes, wherefore I craue your ayde, Herewith my garlande make, let me not be denayed. For you the floure are, wherewith agast I stande, And choyce there resteth none, for beautie at your hande. With you my harte shall reste, when as my corpse is slayne, Take pitie on my woe, take pittie on my payne. At which she floode agast, not knowing what to say, She soone with loue was prickte, and coulde not say me nay. So friendly Venus is, so friendly Cupid was, That fancie brought hir soone, vnto my wisshed passe. She answered againe, a floure likewise I see, Wherein the profe declares, my constant harte to be. And where I heretofore, was movde by many a voyce, Yet none my hart coulde gayne, so curious was my choyce. The sap now creepeth vp, and vapors do increace, Lust doth inforce the fleshe, to warre and not to peace. When Ver is in hyr pryme, each one desires a mate: And now the thing doth please, whiche I before did hate. For earst I did detest, to see a gallant dame, But now I take delight, of thee to heare the name. And sithe that none before, did please my gazing eye, Untill such time I did, your presence here espie. So now your loue I craue, my loue for to requite, Least cause I haue to curse, the canckred Cupides spight. Betake your selfe I say, vnto a trustie friende, In me repose such trust, as ye in me shall finde. For why, in you I liue, and in my selfe I dye: Whiche as a rampire is, your loue agayne to trye. My harmes so huge would crie, if it I should not gayne, And none aliue I thinke, should suffer the like payne. But hope a Castle is, for me to winter in, And biddes me not to feare, nor yet my suyte to lin. With this she walked home, vnto hir mansion place: And all the way he sued, of hir to purchace grace. Who fancide him asmuch, as he did fancie hyr, Though it she kept vnknowne, as best was thought to hyr. The end it tried all, such loue to him she bare, He was hir whole delight for him was all hir care. His sight it did hir good, his absence bredde anoye, His presence was hir meate, hir drinke, and all hir ioye. For if he missing were, at most but halfe a day, Hir eyes like springs of teares would runne in like aray. Or else lyke Xanthus streames, hir tricklyng teares ran downe, As salte as brine, and eke hir skalding sighes vnknowne, Most ready were sometimes, to ende hir lothsome life, Or els in haste she callde for Atropos hir knife. Thus nothing was to much for him that was so kynde, And yet the more he sought, the lesse his lucke to finde. Suche peeuishe lucke had he, in vayne to spende his winde, That, looke the more he ranne, the more he came behinde. Ioue would it so, I thinke, dame fortune beyng coye, Delay it daunger bred, and absence bredde anoye. Though eyther was most true, and faithfull eke in harte, If fortune turne hyr whele, then pleasure is but tarte. So quaynte by proofe she was, and totling in hir chaunce, That where Dame pleasure stoode, she rygor did aduaunce. For why? it hapned so, the trumpe of Muse had blowne, Unto hir eares, that he far forth was better knowne To other than to hir, and eke betrothed had His hande, his harte, and faith vnto an other Dame, So that she did dispayre, and yet he not in blame. But farther it was noysde, that he nought else did seeke Of hir, but for to haue his pleasure for a weeke. Whiche though it was most false, and blased in despight, Yet it hir rauisht had of all hir fore delight. For she beleeued straight, how that these wordes were true, And in this wise began to rage and eke to rue. Haue I long fostred vp, a naughtie soaring Hauke. That now forsakes the lure, when I to hir it shake? May whistling nought preuayle, needes wilt thou checke at fiste, Then soare alofte at will, and take thee vp whose liste. In deede thy slicknesse shewed, thou wast a rolling stone, Wherefore adewe my ioy, sith needes thou wilt be gone. Sithe fortune was so quaynte, and nothing could preuayle, With griefe she curste hir hap, and thus began to rayle. An other hath my right, and it inioyes perforce, The Goddes reuenge it wil, for this thy sought deuorce. Take heede ye Ladies all, on whome ye let your loue, See that he constant be, for so it dothe behoue. Too late now am I wise, be warned all by mee, By others harmes, beware the snare ye do not see. The beste that now I can, is others to forewarne, Least they as I haue done, do light in such like harme. Wherefore I wishe you all, whom Cupid doth assault. Him to deuide in twayne, least through your owne default, To late you do repent, the force of Cupids bowe, And curse the time ye wist, what Venus meant to know. And learne each one by me, whiche way to frame your loue, Be constant, iust and true, as is the turtle Doue. But yet beware on whome, ye let your loue to light, Least want of rendring like, both put your ioyes to flight. Know first his nature well, and then repose your trust, Let nothing be to deare, if so yee finde him iust. Spende not your loue on those, that will it not requite, For why? that wante of loue, it can no one delight. Thus ponder well my wordes, let Pallas be your guyde, Least that in wanton lust, your feete beginne to slyde, Adewe my pleasures all, adewe my chiefe delight, Loue hath me wounded now, and put you all to flight. Wherefore. Yee Tigres whelpes vnkinde, and eke yee rauening Wolues, The Stigian poole and eke, the Acherontes gulues. Yea, yea, the Manticors, the Lyons in their rage, Cerborus, Alecto, with the Leopardes sauage. And (to be shorte) drawe neare, yet furies all of Hell, Yee Fayries with the reste, elsewhere where so you dwell. And Clotho now leaue off, thy distaffe aye to hed, Lachesis sitte still, and spinne no longer thred. But Atropos make haste, and with thy shredding knyfe, Asunder cut the threede, which doth prolong my lyfe. For why? Milecian maydes, your steppes I meane to trace, And as Lucrecia did, my lyfe for to vnlace. Wherefore ye dolefull dumpes, and eke ye Ladies all, Come rue the wretched chaunce, whiche did to me befall. Come Heraclitus nowe, to weepe and eke to wayle, And Ladies now to rue, hoyste vp your mourning sayle. Melpomene likewise, now take thy penne in hande, In mourning wise to paint, how fortune doth withstande. Likewise I thee beseeche, Sulpicia of Rome, Some poste to indite, to set vpon my tome. That all whiche heares or sees, may rue my wretched cace, And know the cause wherefore, my life I did vnlace. This sayde, with bloudy hande, she tooke hir dyrefull knife, And to hir harte it thrust, to ende hir lothsome life. Whiche blowne vnto his eares, he rued in raging wise, But nought he could withstande, hir fonde and foolish guyse. Why liue I on the earth, that thus am lefte alone? Why seeke I not to die, and first to make my mone? Alas my gem of ioy, and eke my Dymande deere, Ah fountayne of delight, as dead why liest thou heere. What shall of me become, my ioyes exiled are, My harte with griefe will burst, hope lodged is so farre. Hath Paris, Leander, Pyrame or Troylus, Aye truer bene than I, to thee my prety mus? Pesistratus in fayth, or Romeus in truth? What cause then hast thou had, to fall in such a ruth? These wordes are but in vayne, I do but seeke to drowne Thy crased corps in teares, of certaine this is knowne. It shall not aye be sayde, that thou for me shalt die, For I the like to doe, thy former deede will trie. Bloud shall be shedde for bloud, and life shall pay for lyfe, I haue like force I know, like hande, and eke like knyfe. With lyke, adewe my ghost, adewe my latter breath, Adewe each pleasure that is founde vpon the earth. Yet Ladies thus much graunt, our corpse one tome to haue, One Epitaphe thereon, this onely thing I craue. This sayde, he kiste hir corpse, ten thousand times and more, With teares he fillde those woundes, that greeued him full sore. He callde vpon hir name, ten thousand times and more, But life it yeelded had to cruel death his lore. Hir eyes they were clong fast, prest downe with heauie death, Adewe my deare he saydt, and thus he stopte his breath. A Song whiche the Gentlewoman made, before she slevve hir selfe. O Cupide, why arte thou to me vnkynde? Unequall arte thou in thy raging moode, Why didst thou seeke with loue to make me blynde? By loue to die, it will doe thee no good, Unlesse perchaunce you ioy to see my woe, I gaue no cause to finde you such a foe. Did I offend thy mother any time? Whereby she sought on me to wrecke hir spight, Did I commit at any time a crime, Whiche moued you to put my ioyes to flight? If so I haue, then didst thou serue me well, If not, me thinkes thy nature is to fell. Ioue knoweth all, but I doe feele the smarte, I haue the wounde whiche breedes my endlesse woe, Alas, alas, what meanes that dyrefull darte? It makes me loue whome neither may forgoe. Alas to late I may repent the time, Of my delight, when Ver was in hir pryme. For my delight hath giuen this deadly wounde, Whiche by no meanes agayne may cured be, Alas, alas, loue doth me nowe confounde, By parant proofe each man the same may see. And none aliue dothe rest to cure the same, Thee Cupid now full iustly may I blame. And Lady Ver, thou arte my mortall foe, For thy delights did force my feete to range, Thou arte the cause of all this endlesse woe, Though Fortune coy she seemed somewhat strange. Thus all alike did gyue this mortall wounde, And all alike hath sought me to confounde. If Lethe lake shoulde yeelde vnto my lore, Yet would it want in me his former force. It could not be a salue for suche a sore, For Cresses iuyce it would his wonte deuorce. Wherefore in vayne I crie and looke for ayde, For hope it selfe at neede hath me denayde. Come Ladies now, put on your mourning weedes, Mourne and lament the cause of my distresse, Through want of will my harte it dayly bleedes. For hope denies to yeelde me ought redresse. Mourne and lament each day with dolefull tunes, For I am she whome lingring loue consumes. What woman will in man repose hir trust, And findeth them so oft to be vniust? Worse than a beast is he that plights his troth, And then for to performe the same is loth: But worse is he that giues his faith to one, When long before to others it was gone. Falser art thou to me than Demophon, Theseus, Phaon, Aeneas, Iason: Falser to me, than euer any wight, Who waste my ioy, and eke my whole delight: And of my death thy falshoode is in blame, Whose bloud shall pay the ransome of the same. Come rue therefore with me ye wretched wightes, With dolefull tunes approche yee neare at hande, Weepe now and wayle forbidding all delightes, And pleasures eke at elbow yours to stande. For loue it seekes to make me now a tome, And loue it will me bryng vnto my dome. FINIS. An answere to a letter written vnto him by a Curtyzan. A bottome for your silke it seemes my letters are become, Whiche with oft winding off and on are wasted whole and some. Who nilling other for to finde but through my paintyng penne, Thereto to giue occasion to wryte you will not lenne. And sith you take such great delight my bottomes for to spende, Beholde now grauntyng to your will, an other here I sende. Ne sutor vltra crepidam, I giue this phrase to vewe, Forbidding Sowters to exceede, the clowting of a shooe. Tis seldome seene a Swan to diue, of Morehennes had bene best For you to talke, although you seeme that name for to detest. Dianas troupe it best may blase the Swan of Menander, It best becomes your penne to paynte the Gose and the gander. Whose tongue dothe runne before your witte, and shewes, fooles boltes sone shotte: You would a good Virgillian be, if Vir in place were not. Sometime if Ouid tooke delight to prayse the hasell Nutte, If Virgill vaunting of his Gnat, why doe not I forth put My selfe to paynt thy iuggling trickes? secluding dalliaunce, Who knowes so well thy legerdemaynes with false conueyance. You are Meduse that feendlike mare, no more a Curtizan, You are no more a soaryng Hauke, what then, a chaste Diane? Not so, what then? the rampyng flie, who vauntes on euery dishe Whereon he lightes, and sowes his seedes, a bayte for those that fishe. For with your preuy winkes, and noddes, yea with your smyling lookes, With wanton toyes, and sugred wordes, whiche are your chiefest hookes: With Demi grauntes, and weake denayes, to those that craue good will, Thou doest prouoke the bashfull youthes, a Uirgins rule to spill. For sure such is thy change with choyce, and eke thy choyce to change, That it inforceth many an one his wanton wittes to range. Thy beautie as a trumpet is this Larum forth to sounde, Tantara, tara, Tantara, whiche when it dothe rebounde Intentiue eares, of force it is each man for to delight, And biddes them stoupe vnto thy lure to put their cares to flight. Then Alleluya they crie, with downe, downe, downe, downe, Terlyterlowe, terlyterlowe, pype downe, downe, down, downe, If so the hunte be vp, then sounde, tathane, tathane, inough. I see it is the houndes doe yelpe, bowgh, bowgh, baugh, baugh, baugh, baugh. The game is dead, beate off the houndes, rate, rate, hawe, hawe, dead, dead. They spoyle the hare, tis nothing worthe, they mangle all his head. You know my minde, how beauties pryce contendeth still with lust, Affection yet once sette aside, layes pleasure in the dust. Farewell and thus adewe. Sound trumpe Aleluya, At th' ende of Tatatantara, To ioy my pleasant Dallyda, So clothed with the Lillie. A song of a Louer, wherein he shewes his loue tovvarde his Lady. The feathered foule that flies so hye And floting fishe whiche swimmes so lowe, When as their tyme they doe espye, They take refuge for euery woe. Yet I forlorne a dolefull wight, Who liues in vayne vpon the earth, Doe wishe me set farre from the light: And ridde of this my spyring breath. For that no refuge can I finde, Whiche will abate my raging woe, Whiche forceth me to erre from kynde: And eke from nature quite to goe. If Hobbyes houer in the winde, When as they seeke to get a praye: Then am I sure of suche lyke kinde, Theyr trade in me doth beare suche swaye. My Lady fayre whose shape doth shine And glyster in my vading sighte, Doth force my harte with woe to pine, And biddes my ioyes at noone good nighte. Yet houer I full oft in thayre My Ladies hue whiche hedgeth in: Hoping at length of hir so fayre, The longed loue with ease to win. I stryde the streetes both long and wyde, A stealed sight of hir to haue: Escaping neyther tyme nor tyde, But still I seeke for that I craue. What though hir loue she sayde me nay, When as I cravde it at hyr hande? Of trothfull troth hope biddes me say, That loue hath hedgde me in hir bande. A Prouerbe olde I beare in mynde, The whiche I hope will be full true: The fallyng out of louers kynde, Is fayned wrath loue to renewe. If so it be, I lesse regarde Hir frownyng lookes which fayned are, If not, what then? my lucke is harde, And harte from hope is lodged farre. FINIS. A newe Married man being stung vvith vvedlocke, declareth his minde Cantico more, vpon this texte: Content your selfe as well as I, let reason rule your minde, As Cuckoldes come by destinie, so Cuckowes sing by kinde. When as Aurora in the morne, did buskle vp to ryse, And Lucifer that brode day Star, did vaunce himself in skies. I gan Morpheus to resist, and eke his mace to skorne, Murcea likewise stept aside, and I as one new borne. In stretchyng forth my slouthfull limmes, amid my naked bedde, Began to thinke opprest with care, whiche way my life to leade. For thryce seuen times the Lady Ver, had florisht in hir pryme, And thryce seuen times Dan Estas he, appeared in my time. No lesse likewise had Autumne he, by course me shewed his face, With hoary Hyems at his trayne according to his grace. Which when I saw how Time did passe, and balde he was behind, I thought it best my selfe tapply, his former bushe to finde, And founde, thereon to lay fast holde, bicause he flittes away, For time and tide it tarieth none, nor keepeth at a stay. Thus musing much w? masing mind, which way for me wer best, At length I founde that harde it was, for ought to liue at rest. For if dame Pleasure streake mine oare, in this my youthfull race, Swete meat sharp sauce, I know requirs no iudgm?t in this cace. And what though Venus graunts me grace? nought therby shal I gaine, Such pleasures lasteth but a time, &amp; yet they do aske paine. And then if so affection fonde, within my brest should raygne, A Lion in an Asses skinne my harte it should retayne. Whereof Valerius doth reporte, that Aristophnes once, In templis Acharontijs made prayers for the nonce. That he in Charons ferry boate might passe the Stygian lake, To Plutos grysly gates of Hell: which for his daughters sake He did obtayne, through fayned loue, which he to them did beare, Alecto, and Tisiphone, Megera: these for feare He flattered much, to whome I know such credite did they giue, That they him taught with sops to feede (if so he sought to liue) The Triceps head of Cerberus the porter of his gate, But see within thou stay not long, least forth thou come to late. This councell did he keepe ful well, and as they had him tought He did, and saw what was his will, he founde eke what he sought. But what he fo?d that restes vnknowne, but when he came againe Unto Thatheniensians, he gan to warne them playne, For wanton Lions fostryng vp within the Citie walles, Least while they thinke of Melt to feede, they taste of bitter galles, Thus likyng breedes extremitie, lulld in affections lappe, And looke what others pleaseth moste, therein I finde least sappe. Alas what one can frame himselfe his youthfull race to spende, All in Mineruas comely courte? doth not Diana bende Sometime vnto Dame pleasures lawes? how then c? I withst?d The firie force of Cupides bowe? doth not dame Venus stande At Beauties barre with comly crewes &amp; routes of dayntie dames? Whose smiling lookes &amp; pr?king toyes, doth cast such fiery flames Before my greedy glauncing eyes, that rolleth here and there, That I poore soule do rest betrayde, as doth the fearfull hare. What shall I do poore sillie sotte? make answere in this cace: Where are thy wittes as now become, that arte so wan of face? If so they wandring be abrode, then call them home againe, A counsell generall to holde it asketh them no payne. Therein determine of my life, how I the same shall leade, But yet determine of thy selfe that perfite path to treade, That leades vnto the perfite ioyes, else thou thy selfe beshrowe Mayst soone perchaunce, &amp; vnawares the paine therof shalt know. Thus beyng set in counsell graue, this counsell did they giue, That I my running head to stay, and eke at ease to liue, A wife should wedde (oh waylfull woe) what could haue chaunced wurse? The wedded man best liues at ease, when fast bounde in his purse He hath the tongue of wedded wife, else will she clatter so, Bothe to his face and at his backe, that gladde he is to goe His way and leaue hyr all alone, for why a shrewishe tongue, Is like vnto an Aspen leafe, that nothing vayles to clangue. But yet for this they councellde me a wedded wife to take, That I the fishe of c?mon sewer might whole and cleane forsake. I was content, my wittes did serue, and would me so to doe, To wiue I wente, as bootelesse bente, a goslyng for to shoe. For looke whose wife in beautie braue, doth passe the middle sorte, Each thinkes hir nought, a secrete whore, and giues hir this report. But further yet of wiues to speake, thus much I haue to say, Whose wife in welth hir mate exceedes, she then wil beare y? sway, And treade vpon hir husbandes crowne, as for hir feete to lowe, Thou mightst haue beggde, this will she say (if so she be a shrowe) If not for me, thou knowest full well, thus will she beare the rule, And weare the breeches of hir mate, as wrapt in Friers cule. I did deserue a better man than euer thou wilt be, Why seekste thou then thy whole affayres or ought to hide fro me? Why should not I thy councell be, without restraint of will? So ought it be, and so it shall, till pleasure hath his fill. Then she disdayning of hir matche, some one will soone procure, To pay the boxe, and eke with salue, hir former wounde to cure. To Cuckoldes hall she will him sende, as warden for to be, With grifted hornes vpon his head, as euery one may see. Hir husbandes wealth shall wasted be, vpon hyr bilbowe boyes, Thus ouerfayre, and all to riche, doe wante no tedious toyes. Then who so wiues, whome beauty w?ts, be she ere poore or ritche, He will hir lothe, she can not please, she is not for his pitche. Thus whiche way can a maried man at this day liue at ease, When neyther faire, the foule, nor riche, his fancy fond may please? Yet I a merry meane did finde, which is a berry Browne, Browne and louely (thus they say) she only beares the crowne. If so it be (as Goddes it graunt) then am I all to wedde, For Browne and louely haue I cought, taccompany me in bedde. New married wiues and yong men too, do thinke the day is long, Wherein they wedded be, and wishe for wante of other song The night were come, &amp; so did I, that Phebus to the west, With steedes were drawne on chariot wheles, and there to take his rest. His course was done, &amp; Vesper she with Luna playde their partes, Whiche pleasde vs well, for ioyes approcht, most meete for louing harts, But passing forth this pleas?t night, w? louely tricks I say, Alas to soone dan Phebus he did shewe, that it was day. And with his radiant glittering beames began for to display, It was not meete for louers, yet so timely for to ryse, But for to chat an houre or two, this is their wonted guyse: And playing thus with w?t? toyes, y? Cuckow bad good morow, Alas thought I, a token tis, for me to liue in sorrow: Cuckow sang he, Cuckow sayd I, what destiny is this? Who so it heares, he well may thinke, it is no sacred blisse. Alas (quoth she) what cause haue you, as yet thus for to say, In Cuckow time few haue a charme, to cause his tongue to stay. Wherfore, Content your selfe as well as I, let reason rule your minde, As Cuckolds come by destiny, so Cuckowes sing by kinde. FINIS. The Louer forsaken, bewayleth his chaunce. If euer man had cause to wayle, then haue I cause to mourne, Who ioyes to see my vowed foe, I like and am forlorne. I serue where no acceptance is and haue this seuen yeares space, And thryce seuen in yeares I would hir serue in hope to purchace grace. But all alas it is in vayne, I like but to my coste, For why the loue I haue bestowed I count it is but loste. I take delight to vewe that face whiche yeeldes my deadly wounde, I loue to serue in loyall thrall although no thankes are founde. O gulfes of care, O dolefull dumpes that sore oppresse my harte, Why doe yee runne in ragyng wise, haue I deserude a parte? No no, I see tis bootelesse now for me to call or crye, For none I see doth rest aliue whose ayde I meane to trye. Hir breath alone it doth suffise to ende my lothsome lyfe, For why the Coccatryce tis lyke and I deserue no wyfe. Sith Fortune quaynte hath graunted so, needes must I be content, No way there is for to withstande the chaunce she hath me sent. Sithe tis my hap my ioyes to cease dame Pleasure now adewe, And dolefull dumpes approch at hande my wretched case to rewe. FINIS. I. G. biddeth his friende A. T. good morrovve. Ave madama, good morrow if it please. Bone iour ma mestresse did you lie at ease? Dieu vou done bone iour, will nothing make you speake? What rest haue you taken? your minde to me breake. What nothing but mum? an Almon for parrot, Speake Parrot I pray thee, may nothing be got? Your pillow misliketh, else care hath forbid, Your eyes to be sleepyng, while pleasure is hid. Else saith Murcea, the sleepe is in thine eyes, Disdayne else forbiddeth (through vanities cryes) To bid me good morrowe, if harte will not breake, Then say but Aueto: I like when you speake. Comporte vou maddam? in French you doe excell. Bien fire gramercy, this likes me very well. Ie suis bien aise pour vou voye in bone sante: I am glad to see that your breath is not fainte. And sith that you speake, now for my god morrowe, Ie vou prie de bon ceur, take this that I owe, A verse tis or twayne, wherewith I meane to greete, Your mornings firste flight as loue hath thought it meete. Perliez bien ou perliez rien, you know my minde: Nothing will I speake, whiche shall not seeme full kinde. As hoarie Hyems froste, keepes backe with pining payne, Eache braue delight, till Ver doth shewe hir face agayne: Thy goyng so to bedde doth put my ioyes to flight, Till mornyng doth appeare, wherefore I hate goodnight. For as the fallyng sap whiche creepes into the earth, Disgrace the trees vntill returne of Ver hir bearth: As naked seemes the trees whiche gallant were of hew: So naked seemes the house when layde thou arte in mew. Thy bedde is lyke thy graue, the earth presents the sheetes: The frisking fleas are like, the wormes dead corpse which greetes. But when the liuely sap creepes vp in blowing thorne, And each delight doth seeme to laugh the frost to scorne: As Ver most freshe of hue, sendes forth hir newe delightes, With iust returne, and greetes vs all with pleasant sightes: So doth Aurora seeme, his giftes for to bestowe, Although to Lady Ver he be a gree belowe. For as the spring delights each thing vpon the earth, Whiche moueth them to wishe and call vpon hir bearth: So doth the morne (me thinkes) vnclose and eke vnbinde, Each thing whiche in the night, are closed in their kynde. And nothing greenes me more, than when the night drawes on, For then I know full well we sunder must anone. And then in vayne I wishe the morne for aye remayne, That then my pleasure loste I might enioy agayne. For in the morne (me thinkes) I see the sap creepes vp, Whiche to my will dothe seeke with ioyes to fill my cup. As great is my delight to vewe thy comely face, As is the birdes, to see the Lady Ver in place. And eury morne by course doth shewe me thee agayne, Whereas the night before vs parted hath in twayne. The brydegrome in his course doth take no more delight, Than I doe dayly take, of thee to haue a sight. Aue I say therefore, I ioy to see thy face: Aueto to reply, this poynt I aske of grace: For whyle my life doth last, with thee my harte shall rest, And for thy sake I will, all other choyce detest. For sure it is in time, the brasen walles will starte, And eke the water flouddes the craggy rockes will parte. In time the watrishe droppes, we see doth perce the stone, Wherefore I hope to finde, as yet where loue is none. This salutation print it within thy brest, And (as deserte deserues) therein so let it rest. As tyme it trieth troth, so then repose thy trust, I craue good will for aye, and not to serue my lust. His good night to the same A. T. I brone in griefe my towre of truste to set Morpheus mace: For needes it will deuide vs bothe though for a litle space. Yet can it not so litle be, though for an howre or twayne, But sure me thinkes it is a yeare, asunder to remayne. For goyng to thy naked bedde thou goest to thy graue: And euery thing resembleth right the course whiche death doth craue. Within thy face consistes my ioyes, within thy harte my lyfe, When death dothe call vpon thy corpse then doe I ende my lyfe. At night my ioyes beginne to ende, by cause we must departe: And dolefull dumpes oppresse my minde, so lothe I am to starte. And when of force departe we must, with lingring steppes I goe: For why thy sweete abode I wishe whose wante doth breede my woe. My heauy hart within my corpse loth to departe doth daunce: And in my moning mynde me thinkes whole barkes of care doth launce. Thy mewe it is a hauen of hope whereto I cleaue and holde: Holde Cable ropes, and Ancor faste for hope dothe make me bolde. Sith dryuen by drifte we must departe, Morpheus thus muche graunt, That all the night I dreame on hyr whome in the day I haunt. And that in liuely forme hyr face before me may appeare, So that I may perswade my selfe shee were in presence here. I would imbracyng in mine armes I could my selfe perswade, For sure it were a golden dreame to walke in suche a shade. Shall I not lull thee in my lappe as well by night as day? Though not, I hope thy harte fro mine it will not goe astray. For why I beare thee in my brest and will while lyfe dothe laste, My harte to thyne I vowe by othe it shall be linked faste. And lette one corpse two faythfull hartes shrowde vp yea all in one. We linger time and all in vayne of force we must be gone. Good night therefore, God sende you rest, and eke Hartes ease at will. God graunt your ioyes they may increase, also the worlde at will. In health the Goddes prolong thy lyfe, of wealth to haue thy fill. Good fame I say and good reporte, according to their will. With heauy cheere I bidde good night, tyme calleth vs away: Against my will we must departe, and that without delay. His Farewell to the same. A greater griefe can hardly be, Then faythfull friendes for to departe, Thy tryed friendship biddes me say, That absence thyne will cut my harte. Thou arte my gem of all my ioye, The Fountayne eke of my delight. Thou arte the staffe whereto I leane, How might I misse thee fro my sight? Though space is great and myles are long Whiche seemes to parte our corpse in twayne: Yet distaunce shall not parte our loue, Our hartes alike shall still remayne. O Titus true, O Phenix kynde, How lothe am I to bidde farewell? It grieues me that suche faithfull friendes For aye togither may not dwell. Shall we asunder parted be, Who thus haue livde in tryed troth? If needes we must, then fare you well, Yet to departe I am full lothe. No greater ioye on earth is founde Than faythfull friendes to liue in one. No greater griefe can likewise chaunce, Than when the one must needes be gone. Ten thousand times I rather had A grisly ghost to ende my lyfe: Come Atropos therefore in haste On me to vse thy shredding knyfe. Come lothsome death with fearefull mace, Spare not to worke my latter dome. Make haste, make haste, I liue to long, Breath yeelded hath, bryng me my tome. When thou arte dead, then all the worlde With me is gone, thou arte so kynde: Who would then willyng let thee goe? Suche faithfull friendes are harde to finde. My lingring feete no power haue Fro thee at all for to departe. Eache stone becomes a Mountayne huge My feete to stoppe, O faythfull harte. Loue it hath made mine eyes so blinde I can not see to finde the way No maruell then if so I seeke A bad excuse to make delay. Eache howre I know will seeme a yeare Untill thou doest returne againe. Wherefore agaynst my will adewe, The want of thee doth breede my payne. Returne in haste, omitte no tyme, Thy absence spinnes a webbe of woe. Lothe to departe come let vs daunce, And make no haste away to goe. The time and tyde it tarieth none, Wherefore this suyte is but in vayne. Of force I see away you must, But yet make haste to come agayne. Adewe, farewell my faithfull friende, As deare to me as is my harte. Now griefe, now care, now endelesse woe Drawes on bycause thou must departe. But why seeme I thy steppes to stay? The longer stay the greater griefe: As good at first as at the laste Hope of returne will yeelde reliefe. No worse to thee than to my selfe, Adewe therefore God be thy speede. With faythfull harte and moning minde I wishe the Lorde to be thy guyde. Farewell.</field>
   </doc>
</add>