<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Ravenscroft, Thomas, 1592-1635</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Ravenscroft, Thomas, 1592-1635</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">ravenscroft thomas 1592 1635</field>
      <field name="author_text">Ravenscroft, Thomas, 1592-1635</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.1815.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1611</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464294</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Melismata ; Mvsicall phansies: fitting the Covrt, Citie, and Covntrey Hvmovrs. To 3, 4, and 5. Voyces</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">Melismata ; Mvsicall phansies: fitting the Covrt, Citie, and Covntrey Hvmovrs. To 3, 4, and 5. Voyces</field>
      <field name="title_facet">melismata</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">melismata</field>
      <field name="title_text">Melismata ; Mvsicall phansies: fitting the Covrt, Citie, and Covntrey Hvmovrs. To 3, 4, and 5. Voyces</field>
      <field name="year_display">1611</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1611</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1611</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464294&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464294&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Ravenscroft, Thomas, 1592?-1635?&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;ravenscroft thomas 1592 1635 &lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Melismata ; Mvsicall phansies: fitting the Covrt, Citie, and Covntrey Hvmovrs. To 3, 4, and 5. Voyces&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;melismata&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1611&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1611&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Ravenscroft, Thomas&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1592&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1635&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Melismata&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Mvsicall phansies: fitting the Covrt, Citie, and Covntrey Hvmovrs. To 3, 4, and 5. Voyces&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by William Stansby for Thomas Adams&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1611&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp3717&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;[43] p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Melismata&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Mvsicall phansies: fitting the Covrt, Citie, and Covntrey Hvmovrs. To 3, 4, and 5. Voyces&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 36 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted; music omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Songbooks.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The following poems are scored for music in the source text. Where poems are not stanzaic, no attempt has been made to reconstruct the metrical lines. Variations for different voices have been ignored. Repetition marks have been ignored.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To all delightfull, except to the Spitefull, To none offensiue, except to the Pensiue. TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL THE true fauorers of Musicke, and all vertue M?. Thomas Rauenscroft, and M?. William Rauenscroft Esquires. COVRT VARIETIES. The Courtiers good Morrow to his Mistris. 1. Canst thou loue, and lie alone? Loue is so disgraced. Pleasure is best, wherein is rest In a heart embraced. Rise, rise, rise, Day light doe not burne out, Bels doe ring And Birdes doe sing, Onely I that mourne out. Morning starre doth now appeare, Wind is husht, and skies cleare. Come come away, come come away, Canst thou loue and burne out day? Rise, rise, rise, rise, Day-light doe not burne out, Bels doe ring, Birds doe sing, Onely I that mourne out. The Crowning of Belphebe. 2. Now flowres your odours breath, And all. the ayre perfume, Grow in this honor'd wreath, And with no stormes consume, Hayle, hayle, and welcome her, Thou glorie of our greene, Receiue this flowrie Spheare, And bee the Shepheards Queene O kneele, and doe her homage now, That cals our hearts like fate, Now rise, your humble bosomes bow, And leade her to her state. Mercuries Song, the messengers of the Gods. 3. Haste, haste, post haste, make haste and away; The tide tarieth no man, it makes no delay. Trudge, trudge for thy life; for vertue must flie, These iourneyes are rife with thee, with the poore Mercurie. 4. [Where are you faire maides] Will yee loue me Lady sweete The Courtiers Courtship to his Mistris. Will yee loue me Lady sweete, you are young and loue is meete, out alas, out alas, alas, who then will sport thee, wanton yet in the spring, Loue is a pretie thing, Loue is a pretie thing, Kisse sweete, as louers doe proue, kind to them that woe. The Mistris to the Courtier. Fie away, fie away, fie, no, no, not I, Ile liue a maide till I be fortie, Fie away, fie away, no, not I. A Song of Pages, Cashiered from their Masters. 5. Long haue we bin perplext and vext Long haue we bin perplext and vext, with a life that I lothed, now may we sing, hay ding, a ding, a ding, and leaue to lament any longer, glad to the heart to depart, that I must bid adew to my master, thankes to the heauens will I giue while I liue, for ioye, for ioye, that I leaue him, gone may hee be downe. trole we the Boles, lets in pretie soules, to carrouse with the wenches, with the wenches. with the wenches. Seruants out of Seruice, are going to the Citie to looke for new. 6 Heigh ho, away the Mare Heigh ho, away the Mare let vs set aside all care, aside all care, if any man be disposed to trie, Loe here comes a lustie crew, a lustie crew, that are enforced to crie, a new Master, a new, a new Master, a new, Hay now, weele take small paines, and yet will thriue, hay now. CITIE ROVNDS. [Broomes for old shooes] Broomes for old Shooes, Pouchrings, Bootes and Buskings Broomes for old Shooes, Pouchrings, Bootes and Buskings, will yee buy any new Broome? New Oysters, new Oysters, New new Cockels, Cockels nye, Fresh Herrings. Will yee buy any straw? Hay yee any Kitchin-stuffe Maides? Pippins fine, Cherrie ripe. Hay any Wood to cleaue? Giue eare to the clocke, beware your locke, your fire and your light, and God giue you good night, one a Clocke. [I pray you good Mother ] 8. I pray you good Mother I pray you good Mother, giue me leaue to play with little Iohn, to make his Bed, and combe his head, and come againe anon, or else beate me as you thinke good, for I loue Iohn alone. [My mistris will not be content ] 9. My Mistris will not be content My Mistris will not be content, to take a Iest, as Chaucer meant, but following stil the womans fashion, allowes it, for the new translation, for with the word she would not dispence, and yet, and yet I know the loues the sence. [I lay with an old man ] 10. I lay with an old man all the night I lay with an old man all the night, I turned to him and he to me, hee could not doe so well as hee might, but hee would faine, but it would not bee. CITIE CONCEITES. The Painters Song of London. 11. [1] Where are you faire maides, That haue neede of our trades? Ile fell you a rare confection. Will yee haue your faces spread, Either with white or red? Will yee buy any faire complection? 2 My drugges are no dregges, For I haue whites of Egges, Made in a rare confection. Red Leather and Surfler water, Scarlet colour or Staues-aker, Will yee buy any faire complection? The Scriueners seruants Song of Holborne. 12. My master is so wise, so wise, that hee's proceeded wittall, My Mistris is a foole, a foole, and yet tis the most get-all. Let the Vsurer cram him in interest that excell, Their pits enough to damme him before he goes to hell. In Holborne some. In Fleetestreete some, Where care he come, there some, there some. A Belmans Song. 13. Maides to bed, and couer coale, Let the Mouse Out of her hole. Crickets in the Chimney sing, Whil'st the little Bell doth ring. If fast asleepe, who can tell When the Clapper hits the Bell. The Cryers Song of Cheape-side. 14. O yes, O yes, O yes, If any one at fifteene, hath taken vp and found A pretie, pretie thing, that hath her maiden head vnbound. If any gallant haue with Cater-tray, Play'd the wise Aker, and made all away, Let him come to the Crier, There will bee laide a thousand pound to tenne, That none, (of these) will ere bee had againe. O yes, O yes, If note or line, or word be here let fall, That giues, to any man the taste of Gall, Let him come to the Cryer, I will lay my lips to a fat shrouing Hen, That none of these will be had againe, For this I say and likewise I protest, No arrowes here at shot at any brest, But all are well come to my musicke feast COVNTRY ROVNDS. [He that will an Ale-house keepe ] 15. He that will an Ale-house keepe He that will an Ale-house keepe, must haue three things in store, a Chamber and a feather Bed, a Chimney and a hey nony no. [And seest thou my Cow to day Fowler ] 16. And seest thou my Cow to day Fowler And seest thou my Cow to day Fowler, the Bels ring into Mattens, Bim bome, bim bome. [Kit and Tom chid a ] 17. Kit and Tom chid a, Tom and Kit chid Kit and Tom chid a, Tom and Kit chid, Kit chid Tom, Tom chid Kit, Kit and Tom chid a. [Dery ding, ding, ding Dasson ] 18. Derrie ding, ding, ding Dasson Derrie ding, ding, ding Dasson, I am Iohn Cheston, we weeddon we wodden, we weedon, we wodden, Bim bom, bim bom, bim bom, bim bom. [As I went by the way ] 19. As I went by the way, holom, trolum As I went by the way, holom, trolum, there met I by the way, hazom, gazom, and I had my little companion, I would a catcht, hazom, gazom, and hunge him vpon holum trolum. COVNTRY PASTIMES. There were three Rauens sat on a tree 20. [1] There were three Rauens sat on a tree, Downe a downe, hay down, hay downe. There were three Rauens sat on a tree, With a downe, There were three Rauens sat on a tree, They were as blacke as they might be, With a downe derrie, derrie, derrie, downe, downe. 2 The one of them said to his mate, down adowne hey downe, The one of them said to his mate, with adowne. The one of them said to his mate Where shall we our breakefast take? with adowne dery downe. 3 Downe in yonder greene field, downe adowne hey downe, Downe in yonder greene field, with adowne. Downe in yonder greene field There lies a Knight slain vnder his shield, with a downe. 4 His hounds they lie downe at his feete, downe adowne hey downe. His hounds they lie downe at his feete, with adowne. His hounds they lie downe at his feete So well they can their Master keepe, with adowne. 5 His Haukes they flie so eagerly downe adowne. His Haukes they flie so eagerly with adowne. His Haukes they flie so eagerly, There's no fowle dare him come nie. with a downe. 6 Downe there comes a fallow Doe, downe adowne. Downe there comes a fallow Doe with a downe. Downe there comes a fallow Doe. As great with yong as she might goe. with adowne. 7 She lift vp his bloudy hed, downe adowne. She lift vp his bloudy hed, with a downe. She lift vp his bloudy hed, And kist his wounds that were so red with a downe. 8 She got him vp vpon her backe, downe adowne. She got him vp vpon her backe, with adowne. She got him vp vpon her backe, And carried him to earthen lake, with adowne downe. 9 She buried him before the prime, downe adowne. She buried him before the prime, with adowne. She buried him before the prime, She was dead her selfe ere euen-song time with adowne. 10 God send euery gentleman downe adowne. God send euery gentleman with adowne. God send euery gentleman Such haukes, such hounds, and such a Leman, with adowne. The Marriage of the Frogge and the Movse. 21. [1] It was the Frogge in the well, Humble-dum, humble-dum. And the merrie Mouse in the Mill, Tweedle, tweedle twino. 2 The Frogge would a woing ride, humble dum humble dum Sword and buckler by his side, tweedle, tweedle twino. 3 When he was vpon his high horse set, humble dum, humble dum His boots they shone as blacke as iet, tweedle, tweedle twino. 4 When she came to the merry mill pin, humble dum, humble dum Lady Mouse beene you within? tweedle, tweedle twino. 5 Then came out the dusty Mouse, humble dum, humble dum I am Lady of this house, tweedle, tweedle twino. 6 Hast thou any minde of me? humble dum, humble dum I haue e'ne great minde of thee, tweedle, tweedle twino. 7 Who shall this marriage make? humble dum, humble dum, Our Lord which is the rat, tweedle, tweedle twino. 8 What shall we haue to our supper? humble dum, humble dum, Three beanes in a pound of butter, tweedle tweedle twino. 9 When supper they were at, humble dum, humble dum The Frog, the Mouse, and euen the Rat, tweedle, tweedle twino. 10 Then came in gib our cat, humble dum, humble dum, And catcht the mouse euen by the backe, tweedle, tweedle twino. 11 Then did they separate, humble dum, humble dum, And the frog leapt on the floore so flat, tweedle, tweedle twino. 12 Then came in Dicke our Drake, humble dum, humble dum, And drew the frogge euen to the lake, tweedle, tweedle twino. 13 The Rat run vp the wall, humble dum, humble dum. A goodly company, the diuell goe with all, tweedle, tweedle twino. A wooing Song of a Yeoman of Kents Sonne. 22. I haue house and land in Kent, And if you'l loue me, loue me now. Two pence halfe-peny is my rent, I cannot come euery day to woo. Ich am my vathers eldest zonne, my mother eke doth loue me well, For ich can brauely clout my shoone, and ich full well can ring a bell. Chorus. For he can brauely clout his shoone, and he full wel can ring a bell. My vather he gaue me a hogge, my mouther she gaue me a zow, I haue a God-vather dwels there by, and he on me bestowed a plow. Chor.He has a God-vather dwels there by, and he on him bestowed a plow. One time I gaue thee a paper of pins anoder time a taudry lace. And if thou wilt not grant me loue, in truth ich die beuore thy vace. Cho.And if thou wilt not grant his loue in truth hee'le die beuore thy vace. Ich haue beene twise our Whitson Lord, ich haue had Ladies many vare, And eke thou hast my heart in hold, and in my minde zeemes passing rare. Cho.And eke thou hast his hart in hold, and in his mind seemes passing rare. Ich will put on my best white sloppe, and ich will weare my yellow hose, And on my head a good gray hat, and in't ich sticke a louely rose. Chor.And on his head a good gray hat, and in't hee'le sticke a louely rose. Wherefore cease off, make no delay, and if you'le loue me, loue me now, Or els ich zeeke zome oder where, for I cannot come euery day to woo. Cho.Or els hee'le zeek zome oder where, for he cannot come euery day to woo. A Christmas Carroll. 23. [1] Remember O thou man, O thou man. Remember O thou man Thy time is spent, Remember O thou man, How thou art dead and gone, And I did what I can, Therefore repent. 2 Remember Adams fall O thou man, O thou man, Remember Adams fall From heauen to hell. Remember Adams fall How we were condemned all In hell perpetuall there for to dwell. 3 Remember Gods goodnesse O thou man, O thou man, Remember Gods goodnesse And his promise made. Remember Gods goodnesse, How he sent his sonne doubtlesse Our sinnes for to redresse, be not affraid. 4 The Angels all did sing, O thou man, O thou man. The Angels all did sing Vpon the Shepheards hill. The Angels all did singe Praises to our heauenly King, And peace to man liuing with a good will. 5 The shepheards amazed was, O thou man, O thou man. The shepheards amazed was To heare the Angels sing, The shepheards amazed was How it should come to passe That Christ our Messias should be our King. 6 To Bethlem did they goe, O thou man, O thou man, To Bethlem did they go The shepheards three, To Bethlem did they goe To see where it were so or no, Whether Christ were borne or no to set man free. 7 As the Angels before did say, O thou man, O thou man, As the Angels before did say, So it came to passe, As the Angels before did say, They found a babe whereas it lay In a manger wrapt in hay, so poore he was. 8 In Bethlem he was borne, O thou man, O thou man, In Bethlem he was borne, For mankind sake, In Bethlem he was borne For vs that were forlorne, And therefore tooke no scorn our flesh to take. 9 Giue thanks to God alway, O thou man, O thou man, Giue thanks to God alway With heart most ioyfully, Giue thankes to God alway, For this our happy day, Let all men sing and say holy, holy. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>