<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Hood, Thomas, 1799-1845</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Hood, Thomas, 1799-1845</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">hood thomas 1799 1845</field>
      <field name="author_text">Hood, Thomas, 1799-1845</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1900's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.1454.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1906</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466800</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">French</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The complete poetical works of Thomas Hood ; Edited, with notes by Walter Jerrold</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The complete poetical works of Thomas Hood ; Edited, with notes by Walter Jerrold</field>
      <field name="title_facet">complete poetical works of thomas hood</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">complete poetical works of thomas hood</field>
      <field name="title_text">The complete poetical works of Thomas Hood ; Edited, with notes by Walter Jerrold</field>
      <field name="year_display">1906</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1906</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1906</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466800&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466800&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Hood, Thomas, 1799-1845&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;hood thomas 1799 1845&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The complete poetical works of Thomas Hood ; Edited, with notes by Walter Jerrold&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;complete poetical works of thomas hood&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1906&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1906&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Hood, Thomas&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1799&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1845&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The complete poetical works of Thomas Hood&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Edited, with notes by Walter Jerrold&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Henry Frowde&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1906&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp1801&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;fre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;xv, 773 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The complete poetical works of Thomas Hood&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Edited, with notes by Walter Jerrold&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 277 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries, introductory and editorial matter omitted; verse reproduced elsewhere in The English Poetry Full-text Database omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">MISCELLANEOUS UNCOLLECTED POEMS (1821–1845) FARE THEE WELL Before our banns be published like a tax, Ask'd on the portals of St. Mary Axe, If thou wilt marry me—then prythee tell— Oh now—or fare thee well! Think of old maids of seventy—fourscore, Fourscore old women at the temple's door, Those that can read, and those that learn to spell— Oh now—or fare thee well! Suppose our names a history—suppose Our love forepicked to pieces, like a rose Shed blushing all abroad—my Isabel! Oh now—or fare thee well! ON A SLEEPING CHILD I O, 'tis a touching thing to make one weep— A tender infant with its curtain'd eye, Breathing as it would neither live nor die, With that unmoving countenance of sleep! As if its silent dream, serene and deep, Had lined its slumbers with a still blue sky; So that the passive cheeks unconscious lie, With no more life than roses', just to keep The blushes warm and the mild odorous breath: O blossom-boy! so calm is thy repose, So sweet a compromise of life and death, 'Tis pity those fair buds should e'er unclose, For Memory to stain their inward leaf, Tinging thy dreams with unacquainted grief. II Thine eyelids slept so beauteously, I deem'd No eyes would wake more beautiful than they; Thy glossy cheeks so unimpassion'd lay, I loved their peacefulness, and never dream'd Of dimples; for thy parted lips so seem'd I did not think a smile could sweetlier play, Nor that so graceful life could charm away Thy graceful death, till those blue eyes upbeam'd. Now slumber lies in dimpled eddies drown'd, And roses bloom more rosily for joy, And odorous silence ripens into sound, And fingers move to mirth,—All-beauteous boy! How dost thou waken into smiles, and prove, If not more lovely, thou art more like Love! [IN MEMORIAM] Little eyes that scarce did see, Little lips that never smiled; Alas! my little dear dead child, Death is thy father, and not me, I but embraced thee, soon as he. ODE ‘I'll give him dash for dash.’ J[erda]n, farewell! farewell to all Who ever prais'd me, great or small; Your poet's course is run! A weekly—no, an ev'ryday Reviewer takes my fame away, And I am all undone! I cannot live an author long! When I did write, O I did wrong To aim at being great; A Diamond Poet in a pin May twinkle on in peace, and win No diamond critic's hate! No small inditer of reviews Will analyse his tiny muse, Or lay his sonnets waste; Who strives to prove that Richardson, That calls himself a diamond one, Is but a bard of paste? The smallest bird that wings the sky May tempt some sparrowshot and die; But midges still go free! The peace that shuns my board and bed May settle on a lowlier head, And dwell, ‘St. John, with thee!’ I aim'd at higher growth; and now My leaves are wither'd on the bough, I'm choked by bitter shrubs! O Mr. F. C. W.! What can I christen thy review But one of ‘Wormwood Scrubs?’ The very man that sought me once— Can I so soon be grown a dunce?— He now derides my verse; But who, save me, will fret to find The editor has changed his mind,— He can't have got a worse. ODE IMITATED FROM HORACE Oh! well may poets make a fuss In summer time, and sigh ‘O rus!’ Of London pleasures sick: My heart is all at pant to rest In greenwood shades,—my eyes detest This endless meal of brick! What joy have I in June's return? My feet are parch'd—my eyeballs burn, I scent no flowery gust; But faint the flagging zephyr springs, With dry Macadam on its wings, And turns me ‘dust to dust.’ My sun his daily course renews Due east, but with no Eastern dews; The path is dry and hot! His setting shows more tamely still, He sinks behind no purple hill, But down a chimney's pot! Oh! but to hear the milk-maid blithe, Or early mower whet his scythe The dewy meads among!— My grass is of that sort—alas!— That makes no hay,—call'd sparrow-grass By folks of vulgar tongue! Oh! but to smell the woodbine sweet! I think of cowslip-cups—but meet With very vile rebuffs! For meadow buds, I get a whiff Of Cheshire cheese,—or only sniff The turtle made at Cuff's. How tenderly Rousseau review'd His periwinkles!—mine are stew'd! My rose blooms on a gown! I hunt in vain for eglantine, And find my blue-bell on the sign That marks the Bell and Crown! Where are ye, birds! that blithely wing From tree to tree, and gaily sing Or mourn in thickets deep? My cuckoo has some ware to sell, The watchman is my Philomel, My blackbird is a sweep! Where are ye, linnet! lark! and thrush! That perch on leafy bough and bush, And tune the various song? Two hurdy-gurdists, and a poor Street-Handel grinding at my door, Are all my ‘tuneful throng.’ Where are ye, early-purling streams, Whose waves reflect the morning beams And colours of the skies? My rills are only puddle-drains From shambles—or reflect the stains Of calimanco-dyes. Sweet are the little brooks that run O'er pebbles glancing in the sun, Singing in soothing tones:— Not thus the city streamlets flow; They make no music as they go, Tho' never ‘off the stones.’ Where are ye, pastoral pretty sheep, That wont to bleat, and frisk, and leap Beside your woolly dams? Alas! instead of harmless crooks, My Corydons use iron hooks, And skin—not shear—the lambs. The pipe whereon, in olden day, Th' Arcadian herdsman us'd to play Sweetly—here soundeth not; But merely breathes unwelcome fumes, Meanwhile the city boor consumes The rank weed—‘piping hot.’ All rural things are vilely mock'd, On every hand the sense is shock'd With objects hard to bear: Shades,—vernal shades!—where wine is sold! And for a turfy bank, behold An Ingram's rustic chair! Where are ye, London meads and bow'rs, And gardens redolent of flow'rs Wherein the zephyr wons? Alas! Moor Fields are fields no more! See Hatton's Garden brick'd all o'er; And that bare wood—St. John's. No pastoral scene procures me peace; I hold no Leasowes in my lease, No cot set round with trees: No sheep-white hill my dwelling flanks And omnium furnishes my banks With brokers—not with bees. Oh! well may poets make a fuss In summer time, and sigh ‘O rus!’ Of city pleasures sick: My heart is all at pant to rest In greenwood shades,—my eyes detest This endless meal of brick! STANZAS TO TOM WOODGATE, OF HASTINGS I Tom!—are you still within this land Of livers—still on Hastings' sand, Or roaming on the waves,— Or has some billow o'er you rolled, Jealous that earth should lap so bold A seaman in her graves? II On land the rush-light lives of men Go out but slowly; nine in ten, By tedious long decline,— Not so the jolly sailor sinks, Who founders in the wave, and drinks The apoplectic brine! III Ay, while I write, mayhap your head Is sleeping on an oyster-bed,— I hope 'tis far from truth! With periwinkle eyes;—your bone Beset with mussels, not your own, And corals at your tooth! IV Still does the Chance pursue the chance The main affords—the Aidant dance In safety on the tide? Still flies that sign of my good-will A little bunting thing—but still To thee a flag of pride? V Does that hard, honest hand now clasp The tiller in its careful grasp— With every summer breeze When ladies sail, in lady-fear— Or, tug the oar, a gondolier On smooth Macadam seas? VI Or are you where the flounders keep, Some dozen briny fathoms deep, Where sands and shells abound— With some old Triton on your chest And twelve grave mermen for a 'quest, To find that you are—drowned? VII Swift is the wave, and apt to bring A sudden doom—perchance I sing A mere funereal strain;— You have endured the utter strife— And are—the same in death or life, A good man in the main! VIII Oh, no—I hope the old brown eye Still watches ebb and flood and sky; That still the old brown shoes Are sucking brine up—pumps indeed! Your tooth still full of ocean weed, Or Indian—which you choose. IX I like you, Tom! and in these lays Give honest worth its honest praise, No puff at honour's cost; For though you met these words of mine, All letter-learning was a line You, somehow, never crossed! X Mayhap, we ne'er shall meet again, Except on that Pacific main, Beyond this planet's brink;— Yet as we erst have braved the weather, Still we may float awhile together, As comrades on this ink! XI Many a scudding gale we've had Together, and, my gallant lad, Some perils we have passed; When huge and black the wave careered, And oft the giant surge appeared The master of our mast:— XII 'Twas thy example taught me how To climb the billow's hoary brow, Or cleave the raging heap— To bound along the ocean wild, With danger only as a child, The waters rocked to sleep. XIII Oh, who can tell that brave delight, To see the hissing wave in might, Come rampant like a snake! To leap his horrid crest, and feast One's eyes upon the briny beast, Left couchant in the wake! XIV The simple shepherd's love is still To bask upon a sunny hill, The herdsman roams the vale— With both their fancies I agree; Be mine the swelling, scooping sea, That is both hill and dale! XV I yearn for that brisk spray—I yearn To feel the wave from stem to stern Uplift the plunging keel. That merry step we used to dance, On board the Aidant or the Chance, The ocean ‘toe and heel.’ XVI I long to feel the steady gale, That fills the broad distended sail— The seas on either hand! My thought, like any hollow shell, Keeps mocking at my ear the swell Of waves against the land. XVII It is no fable—that old strain Of sirens!—so the witching main Is singing—and I sigh! My heart is all at once inclined To seaward—and I seem to find The waters in my eye! XVIII Methinks I see the shining beach; The merry waves, each after each, Rebounding o'er the flints;— I spy the grim preventive spy! The jolly boatmen standing nigh! The maids in morning chintz! XIX And there they float—the sailing craft! The sail is up—the wind abaft— The ballast trim and neat. Alas! 'tis all a dream—a lie! A printer's imp is standing by, To haul my mizen sheet! XX My tiller dwindles to a pen— My craft is that of bookish men— My sale—let Longman tell! Adieu the wave! the wind! the spray! Men—maidens—chintzes—fade away! Tom Woodgate, fare thee well! [EPISTLE TO MISS CHARLOTTE REYNOLDS] My dear Lot, There's a blot!— This is to write That Sunday night By the late Coach at eight, We shall get in To little Britain,— So have handy Gin, rum, Brandy A lobster,—may be— Cucumbers, they be Also in season And within reason— Porter—by Gum! Against we come— In lieu of Friday Then we keep high day And holy, as long as We can. I get strong as A horse—i.e., pony Jane tho' keeps boney. How is your mother, Still with your brother, And Marian too— And that good man too Call'd your papa, Miss. After these ah Miss! Don't say I never Made an endeavour To write you verses Tho' this lay worse is Than any I've written The truth is, I've sitten So long over letters Addressed to your betters That—that—that Some how— My pen— Amen. T. Hood. [July 11, 1828.] BIRTHDAY VERSES Good-morrow to the golden Morning! Good-morrow to the world's delight! I've come to bless thy life's beginning, That hath made my own so bright! I have brought no roses, Dearest! Summer lies upon her bier; It was when all sweets were over Thou wert born to bless the year. But I bring thee jewels, Fairest! In thy bonny locks to shine; And, if love seem in their glances, They have learn'd that look of mine! THE SWEETS OF YOUTH ‘Sweets to the sweet—farewell.’ —Hamlet. Time was I liked a cheesecake well enough; All human children have a sweetish taste— I used to revel in a pie, or puff, Or tart—we all were tartars in our youth; To meet with jam or jelly was good luck, All candies most complacently I crumped, A stick of liquorice was good to suck, And sugar was as often liked as lumped; On treacle's ‘linkèd sweetness long drawn out,’ Or honey, I could feast like any fly, I thrilled when lollipops were hawk'd about, How pleased to compass hard bake or bull's eye, How charmed if fortune in my power cast Elecampane—but that campaign is past! ANTICIPATION ‘Coming events cast their shadow before.’ I had a vision in the summer light— Sorrow was in it and my inward sight Ached with sad images. The touch of tears Gush'd down own my cheeks:—the figur'd woes of years Casting their shadows across sunny hours. Oh there was nothing sorrowful in flow'rs Wooing the glances of an April sun, Or apple blossoms opening one by one Their crimson bosoms—or the twitter'd words And warbled sentences of merry birds;— Or the small glitter and the humming wings Of golden flies and many colour'd things— Oh these were nothing sad—nor to see Her, Sitting beneath the comfortable stir Of early leaves—casting the playful grace Of moving shadows on so fair a face— Nor in her brow serene—nor in the love Of her mild eyes drinking the light above With a long thirst—nor in her gentle smile— Nor in her hand that shone blood-red the while She rais'd it in the sun. All these were dear To heart and eye—but an invisible fear Shook in the trees and chill'd upon the air, And if one spot was laughing brightest—there My soul most sank and darken'd in despair!— As if the shadows of a curtain'd room Haunted me in the sun—as if the bloom Of early flow'rets had no sweets for me Nor apple blossoms any blush to see— As if the noon had brought too bright a day— And little birds were all too gay!—too gay! As if the beauty of that Lovely One Were all a fable.—Full before the sun Stood Death and cast a shadow long before, Like a dark pall enshrouding her all o'er, Till eyes, and lips, and smiles, were all no more! THE BALLAD O, when I was a little boy— This print the time recalls— What strips of song there hung along Old palings and old walls! O, how they flaunted in the air, And flutter'd on their strings! I'd heard of Muses, and they seemed Like feathers from their wings— Dim flimsy papers, little fit With Newland's bills to rank; But O! there seem'd whole millions there In notes of Boyhood's Bank! With what a charm of black and white They witch'd the urchin sense! How blest if I could stop and buy! How pensive—without pence! How hard, alas! if forced to pass By that enchanted place, In dismal sort—a farthing short— To long for ‘Chevy Chase.’ One comfort liv'd—if pence were scant, There still was Mary Dunn— So stored with song, she seem'd the whole Nine Muses rolled in one. Her pocket money never went For cheesecake or for tart; She purchased all new songs, I had The old ones each by heart. When Mary set to sing, to read, All sport and play stood still— Her words could lock a waggon wheel, And stop the march to drill. Meanwhile, the tragic tale she told Of Babies in the Wood And gentle Redbreast,—or that bold Cock Robin, Robin Hood, Will Scarlet, and his merry mates, Who Lincoln Green had on— I listen'd till I thought myself A little Little John. O, happy times! O, happy rhymes! For ever ye're gone by! Few now—if any—are the lays Can make me smile or sigh. Perchance myself am changed—perchance I do their authors wrong— But scarce a modern ballad now Seems worthy ‘an old song.’ EPIGRAM ON A PICTURE This picture very plainly shows How little many a painter knows Of colour, though he thinks it. T? herein depicts a view, And underneath gamboge and blue Informs us that T. pinxit. ANSWER TO PAUPER Don't tell me of buds and blossoms, Or with rose and vi'let wheedle— Nosegays grow for other bosoms, Churchwarden and Beadle! What have you to do with streams? What with sunny skies, or garish, Cuckoo songs or pensive dreams?— Nature's not your parish! What right have such as you to dun For sun or moonbeams, warm or bright? Before you talk about the sun, Pay for window-light! Talk of passions—amorous fancies; While your betters' flames miscarry— If you love your Dolls and Nancys, Don't we make you marry? Talk of wintry chill and storm, Fragrant winds, that blanch your bones; You poor can always keep you warm, An't there breaking stones? Suppose you don't enjoy the spring, Roses fair and vi'lets meek,— You cannot look for everything On eighteenpence a week! With seasons what have you to do?— If corn doth thrive, or wheat is harmed?— What's weather to the cropless? You Don't farm—but you are farm'd! Why everlasting murmurs hurl'd, With hardship for the text?— If such as you don't like this world— We'll pass you to the next. Overseer. ODE TO SPENCER PERCEVAL, ESQ., M.P. Oh, Mr. Spencer!— I mean no offence, Sir— Retrencher of each trencher, man or woman's; Maker of days of ember, Eloquent member Of the House of Com—I mean to say short commons, Thou Long Tom Coffin singing out, ‘Hold fast’— Avast! Oh! Mr. Perceval, I'll bet a dollar, a Great growth of cholera, And new deaths reckon'd, Will mark thy Lenten twenty-first and second. The best of our physicians, when they con it, Depose the malady is in the air: Oh, Mr. Spencer!—if the ill is there, Why should you bid the people live upon it? Why should you make discourses against courses; While Doctors, though they bid us rub and chafe, Declare, of all resources, The man is safest who gets in the safe? And yet you bid poor suicidal sinners Discard their dinners! Thoughtless how Heav'n above will look upon't, For men to die so wantonly of want! By way of a variety, Think of the ineffectual piety Of London's Bishop, at St. Faith's or Bride's, Lecturing such chameleon insides, Only to find He's preaching to the wind. Whatever others do, or don't, I cannot—dare not—must not fast, and wont, Unless by night your day you let me keep, And fast asleep; My constitution can't obey such censors: I must have meat Three times a day to eat, My health's of such a sort,— To say the truth in short— The coats of my stomach are not Spencers. ON THE DEATH OF SIR WALTER SCOTT Farewell, Sir Walter Scott, secured From Time,—our greatest of Inditers! No Author's fame's so well assur'd, For all who wrote were Under-writers. A CHARITY SERMON ‘“I would have walked many a mile to have communed with you; and, believe me, I will shortly pay thee another visit; but my friends, I fancy, wonder at my stay, so let me have the money immediately.” Trulliber then put on a stern look, and cried out, “Thou dost not intend to rob me?” ‘“I would have thee know, friend,” addressing himself to Adams, “I shall not learn my duty from such as thee. I know what charity is, better than to give to vagabonds.”’ —Joseph Andrews. I'm an extremely charitable man—no collar and long hair, though a little carroty; Demure, half-inclined to the unknown tongues, but I never gain'd anything by Charity— I got a little boy into the Foundling, but his unfortunate mother was traced and baited, And the overseers found her out—and she found me out—and the child was affiliated. Oh, Charity will come home to roost— Like curses and chickens is Charity. I once, near Whitehall's very old wall, when ballads danc'd over the whole of it, Put a bad five-shilling piece into a beggar's hat, but the old hat had got a hole in it; And a little boy caught it in his little hat, and an officer's eye seem'd to care for it, As my bad crown-piece went through his bad crownpiece, and they took me up to Queen's Square for it. Oh, Charity, &amp;c. I let my very old (condemn'd) old house to a man, at a rent that was shockingly low, So I found a roof for his ten motherless babes—all defunct and fatherless now; For the plaguey one-sided party-wall fell in, so did the roof, on son and daughter, And twelve jurymen sat on eleven bodies, and brought in a very personal verdict of Manslaughter. Oh, Charity, &amp;c. I picked up a young well-dress'd gentleman, who had fallen in a fit in St. Martin's Court, And charitably offer'd to see him home,—for charity always seem'd to be my forte, And I've had presents for seeing fallen gentlemen home, but this was a very unlucky job— Do you know, he got my watch—my purse—and my handkerchief—for it was one of the swell mob. Oh, Charity, &amp;c. Being four miles from Town, I stopt a horse that had run away with a man, when it seem'd that they must be dash'd to pieces, Though several kind people were following him with all their might—but such following a horse his speed increases; I held the horse while he went to recruit his strength; and I meant to ride home, of course; But the crowd came up and took me up—for it turned out the man had run away with the horse. Oh, Charity, &amp;c. I watch'd last month all the drovers and drivers about the suburbs, for it's a positive fact, That I think the utmost penalty ought always to be enforc'd against everybody under Mr. Martin's Act; But I couldn't catch one hit over the horns, or over the shins, or on the ears, or over the head; And I caught a rheumatism from early wet hours, and got five weeks of ten swell'd fingers in bed. Oh, Charity, &amp;c. Well, I've utterly done with Charity, though I us'd so to preach about its finest fount; Charity may do for some that are more lucky, but I can't turn it to any account— It goes so the very reverse way—even if one chirrups it up with a dust of piety; That henceforth let it be understood, I take my name entirely out of the List of the Subscribers to the Humane Society. Oh, Charity, &amp;c. ODE TO SIR ANDREW AGNEW, BART. ‘At certain seasons he makes a prodigious clattering with his bill.’ —Selby. ‘The bill is rather long, flat, and tinged with green.’ —Bewick. O Andrew Fairservice,—but I beg pardon, You never labour'd in Di Vernon's garden, On curly kale and cabbages intent,— Andrew Churchservice was the thing I meant,— You are a Christian—I would be the same, Although we differ, and I'll tell you why, Not meaning to make game, I do not like my Church so very High! When people talk, as talk they will, About your bill, They say, among their other jibes and small jeers, That, if you had your way, You'd make the seventh day As overbearing as the Dey of Algiers. Talk of converting Blacks— By your attacks, You make a thing so horrible of one day, Each nigger, they will bet a something tidy, Would rather be a heathenish Man Friday, Than your Man Sunday! So poor men speak, Who, once a week, P'rhaps, after weaving artificial flowers, Can snatch a glance of Nature's kinder bowers, And revel in a bloom That is not of the loom, Making the earth, the streams, the skies, the trees, A Chapel of Ease. Whereas, as you would plan it, Wall'd in with hard Scotch granite, People all day should look to their behaviours,— But though there be, as Shakspeare owns, ‘Sermons in stones,’ Zounds! Would you have us work at them like paviours? Spontaneous is pure devotion's fire; And in a green wood many a soul has built A new Church, with a fir-tree for its spire, Where Sin has prayed for peace, and wept for guilt, Better than if an architect the plan drew; We know of old how medicines were back'd, But true Religion needs not to be quack'd By an Un-merry Andrew! Suppose a poor town-weary sallow elf At Primrose-hill would renovate himself, Or drink (and no great harm) Milk genuine at Chalk Farm,— The innocent intention who would baulk, And drive him back into St. Bennet Fink? For my part, for my life, I cannot think A walk on Sunday is ‘the Devil's Walk.’ But there's a sect of Deists, and their creed Is D?ing other people to be d?d,— Yea, all that are not of their saintly level, They make a pious point To send, with an ‘aroint,’ Down to that great Fillhellenist, the Devil. To such, a ramble by the River Lea, Is really treading on the ‘Banks of D?.’ Go down to Margate, wisest of law-makers, And say unto the sea, as Canute did, (Of course the sea will do as it is bid,) ‘This is the Sabbath—let there be no Breakers!’ Seek London's Bishop, on some Sunday morn, And try him with your tenets to inoculate,— Abuse his fine souchong, and say in scorn, ‘This is not Churchman's Chocolate!’ Or, seek Dissenters at their mid-day meal, And read them from your Sabbath Bill some passages, And while they eat their mutton, beef, and veal, Shout out with holy zeal,— ‘These are not Chappel's sassages!’ Suppose your Act should act up to your will, Yet how will it appear to Mrs. Grundy, To hear you saying of this pious bill, ‘It works well—on a Sunday!’ To knock down apple-stalls is now too late, Except to starve some poor old harmeless madam;— You might have done some good, and chang'd our fate, Could you have upset that, which ruined Adam! 'Tis useless to prescribe salt-cod and eggs, Or lay post-horses under legal fetters, While Tattersall's on Sunday stirs its Legs, Folks look for good examples from their Betters! Consider,—Acts of Parliament may bind A man to go where Irvings are discoursing— But as for forcing ‘proper frames of mind,’ Minds are not framed, like melons, for such forcing! Remember, as a Scottish legislator, The Scotch Kirk always has a Moderator; Meaning one need not ever be sojourning In a long Sermon Lane without a turning. Such grave old maids as Portia and Zenobia May like discourses with a skein of threads, And love a lecture for its many heads, But as for me, I have the Hydra-phobia. Religion one should never overdo: Right glad I am no minister you be, For you would say your service, sir, to me, Till I should say, ‘My service, sir, to you.’ Six days made all that is, you know, and then Came that of rest—by holy ordination, As if to hint unto the sons of men, After creation should come re-creation. Read right this text, and do not further search To make a Sunday Workhouse of the Church. ODE TO J. S. BUCKINGHAM, ESQ., M.P. ON THE REPORT OF THE COMMITTEE OF DRUNKENNESS ‘Steady, boys, steady,’ —Sea Song. ‘Then did they fall upon the chat of drinking; and forthwith began Flaggons to go, Goblets to fly, great Bowls to ting, Glasses to ring, draw, reach, fill, mix, give it me without water; so, my Friend, so; whip me off this Glass neatly, bring me hither some Claret, a full weeping Glass till it run over!’ —Rabelais. ‘Now, seeing that every Vessell was empty, great and small, with not so much at the Bottom as would befuddle or muddle even a Fly, such as are the Flies of Baieux, I say, seeing this lamentable sight, Gargantua leapt up on one of the Tables, and with Tears in his eyes as big as Cannon Bullets, did pathetically beseech Pantagruel, as well as he could for the Hiccups and the Drinking Cups, and all sorts of Cups, as he valued his precious Body and Soul, one or both, never to drink more than became a reasonable Man, and not a Hog and a Beast. And the Stint of a reasonably reasonable Man is thus much, to wit, seven Thousand three Hundred and fifty-three Hogsheads, twice as many Kilderkins, thrice as many little Kegs, and as many Flaggons, Bottles, and Tankards as you will, beside. A Christian ought not to drink more. As Gargantua said these Words his Voice grew thick, his Tongue being as it were too huge for his Mouth; and on a sudden he turned dog-sick, and fell off the Table a prodigious Fall, whereby there was a horrible Earthquake, from Paris even unto Turkey in Asia, as is remembered unto this day.’ —Rabelais. O, Mr. Buckingham, if I may take The liberty with you and your Committee, Some observations I intend to make, I hope will prove both pertinent and pretty. On Drunkenness you've held a special court, But is consistency, I ask, your forte, When after (I must say) much Temperance swaggering, You issue a Report, That's staggering! Of course you labour'd without drop or sup, Yet certain parts of that Report to read, Some men might think indeed, A corkscrew, not a pen, had drawn it up. For instance, was it quite a sober plan On such a theme as drunkenness to trouble A poor old man, Who could not e'en see single, much less double. Blind some six years, As it appears, He gives in evidence, and you receive it, A flaming picture of a flaming palace, Where gin-admirers sipped the chalice And then, (the banter is not bad,) Thinks fit to add, You really should have seen it to believe it. What is your occupation? My occupation has been in the weaving line; but having the dropsy six years ago, I am deprived of my eyesight. 2734. Did you not once see a gin-shop burnt down?—About nine months ago there was the sign of the Adam and Eve at the corner of Church-street, at Bethnal-green, burnt down, and they had such a quantity of spirits in the house at the time that it was such a terrible fire, that they were obliged to throw everything into the middle of the road to keep it away from the liquor, and it was all in flames in the road; and the gin-shop opposite was scorched and broke their windows; and there was another gin-shop at the opposite corner, at three corners there were gin-shops, and was, from the fire, just like a murdering concern; for you could not get round the corner at all, it was so thronged that a man could not believe it unless he saw it. That he could see such sights I must deny, Unless he borrowed Betty Martin's eye. A man that is himself walks in a line, One, not himself, goes serpentine, And as he rambles In crablike scrambles, The while his body works in curves, His intellect as surely swerves, And some such argument as this he utters, ‘While men get cut we must have cutters, As long as Jack will have his rum, We must have pink, corvette, and bomb, Each sort of craft Since Noah's old raft, Frigate and brig, Ships of all rig, We must have fleets, because our sailors swig, But only get our tars to broths and soups, And see how slops will do away with sloops! Turn flip to flummery, and grog to gravy, And then what need has England of a navy?’ 3893. If temperance were universal, do you think we should need any line-of-battle ships? —It would be very unsafe for us to be without them. Forgive my muse; she is a saucy hussy, But she declares such reasoning sounds muzzy, And that, as sure as Dover stands at Dover, The man who entertains so strange a notion Of governing the ocean, Has been but half seas over. Again: when sober people talk On soberness, would not their words all walk Straight to the point, instead of zig-zag trials, Of both sides of the way, till having crost And crost, they find themselves completely lost Like gentlemen,—rather cut—in Seven Dials? Just like the sentence following in fact: ‘Every Act 1686. Do you mean to infer from that, that the law in all its branches should be in accordance with the Divine command?—I do; every Act of the Legislature should flow over the bed of inspired truth, and receive the impregnation of its righteous and holy principles. Of the Legislature,’ (so it runs) ‘should flow Over the bed,’—of what?—begin your guesses. The Bed of Ware? The State Bed of the May'r? One at the Hummums? Of MacAdam's? No. A parsley bed? Of cabbage, green or red? Of onions? daffodils? of water-cresses? A spare-bed with a friend—one full of fleas? At Bedford, or Bedhampton?—None of these. The Thames's bed? The bed of the New River? A kennel? brick-kiln? or a stack of hay? Of church-yard clay, The bed that's made for ev'ry mortal liver? No—give it up,—all guessing I defy in it, It is the bed of ‘Truth,’—‘inspired’ forsooth As, if you gave your best best-bed to Truth She'd lie in it! Come, Mr. Buckingham, be candid, come, Didn't that metaphor want ‘seeing home’? What man, who did not see far more than real, Drink's beau ideal,— Could fancy the mechanic so well thrives. In these hard times, The source of half his crimes Is going into gin-shops changing fives! 2512. Are they in the habit of bringing £5 notes to get changed, as well as sovereigns?—Very rarely; I should think a £5 note is an article they seldom put in their pockets. Whate'er had wash'd such theoretic throats, After a soundish sleep, till twelve next day, And, perhaps, a gulp of soda—did not they All change their notes? Suppose, mind, Mr. B., I say, suppose You were the landlord of the Crown—the Rose— The Cock and Bottle, or the Prince of Wales, The Devil and the Bag of Nails, The Crown and Thistle, The Pig and Whistle, Magpie and Stump—take which you like, The question equally will strike; Suppose your apron on—top-boots,—fur cap— Keeping an eye to bar and tap, When in comes, muttering like mad, The strangest customer you ever had! Well, after rolling eyes and mouthing, And calling for a go of nothing, He thus accosts you in a tone of malice: ‘Here's pillars, curtains, gas, plate-glass—What not? Zounds! Mr. Buckingham, the shop you've got Beats Buckingham Palace! It's not to be allowed, Sir; I'm a Saint, So I've brought a paint-brush, and a pot of paint, You deal in Gin, Sir, Glasses of Sin, Sir; No words—Gin wholesome?—You're a story-teller— I don't mind Satan standing at your back, The Spirit moveth me to go about, And paint your premises inside and out, Black, Sir, coal black, Coal black, Sir, from the garret to the cellar. I'll teach you to sell gin—and, what is more, To keep your wicked customers therefrom, I'll paint the Great Death's Head upon your door— Write underneath it, if you please—Old Tom!’ 3006. Do you think it would be of good effect, were the Legislature to order that those houses should be painted all black, with a large death's head and cross-bones over the door?—I wish they would do even so much. Should such a case occur, How would you act with the intruder, Sir? Surely, not cap in hand, you'd stand and bow, But after hearing him proceed thus far, (Mind—locking up the bar) You'd seek the first policeman near, ‘Here, take away this fellow, here, The rascal is as drunk as David's Sow!’ If I may ask again—between Ourselves and the General Post, I mean— What was that gentleman's true situation Who said—but could he really stand To what he said?—‘In Scottish land The cause of Drunkenness was education!’ 4502. What are the remote causes that have influenced the habit of drinking spirits among all classes of the population?—One of the causes of drunkenness in Scotland is education. Only, good Mr. Buckingham, conceive it! In modern Athens, a fine classic roof, Christened the High School—that is, over proof! Conceive the sandy laddies ranged in classes, With quaichs and bickers, drinking-horns and glasses, Ready to take a lesson in Glenlivet! Picture the little Campbells and M'Gregors, Dancing, half fou', by way of learning figures; And Murrays,—not as Lindley used to teach— Attempting verbs when past their parts of speech— Imagine Thompson, learning A B C, By O D V. Fancy a dunce that will not drink his wash, And Master Peter Alexander Weddel Invested with a medal For getting on so very far-in-tosh. Fancy the Dominie—a drouthy body, Giving a lecture upon making toddy, Till having emptied every stoup and cup, He cries, ‘Lads! go and play—the school is up!’ To Scotland, Ireland is akin In drinking, like as twin to twin,— When other means are all adrift, A liquor-shop is Pat's last shift, Till reckoning Erin round from store to store, There is one whisky shop in four. 3804. Did you observe the drinking of spirits very general in Ireland?—In Ireland, I think, upon a moderate calculation, one shop out of every four is a whiskey-shop, throughout the whole kingdom. Those who have been unsuccessful in every other employment, and those who have no capital for any employment, fly to the selling of whiskey as the last shift. Then who, but with a fancy rather frisky, And warm besides, and generous with whiskey, Not seeing most particularly clear, Would recommend to make the drunkards thinner, By shutting up the publican and sinner With pensions each of fifty pounds a year? 773. Now suppose we were to give £50 a-year to every spirit-seller in Belfast, to pension them off (and I am sure it would be much better for the country that they should be paid for doing nothing than for doing mischief)— Ods! taps and topers! private stills and worms! What doors you'd soon have open to your terms! To men of common gumption, How strange, besides, must seem At this time any scheme To put a check upon potheen's consumption, When all are calling out for Irish Poor Laws! Instead of framing more laws, To pauperism, if you'd give a pegger, Don't check, but patronise their ‘Kill-the-Beggar!’ 794. We have in our neighbourhood a species of whiskey of this kind, called ‘Kill-the-Beggar.’ If Pat is apt to go in Irish Linen, (Buttoning his coat, with nothing but his skin in) Would any Christian man—that's quite himself, His wits not floor'd, or laid upon the shelf— While blaming Pat for raggedness, poor boy, Would he deprive him of his ‘Corduroy!’ 795. Another description of what would be termed adulterated spirits, is by the vulgar termed ‘Corduroy.’ Would any gentleman, unless inclining To tipsy, take a board upon his shoulder, Near Temple Bar, thus warning the beholder, ‘Beware of Twining?’ Are tea dealers, indeed, so deep-designing, As one of your select would set us thinking, That to each tea-chest we should say Tu Doces, (Or doses,) Thou tea-chest drinking? 789. It is quite common, in Dublin particularly, to have at one end of the counter a large pile of tea-chests for females to go behind, to be hid from sight: but the dangerous secrecy arises chiefly from the want of suspicion in persons going into grocers' shops. 788. It is a well known fact, that mechanics' wives not unfrequently get portions of spirituous liquors at grocers' shops, and have them set down to their husbands' accounts as soap, sugar, tea, &amp;c. What would be said of me Should I attempt to trace The vice of drinking to the high in place, And say its root was on the top o' the tree? 816. Do you ascribe the great inclination for whiskey at present existing among the lower classes, originally to the use of it by the higher classes as a favourite drink? I attribute a very large portion of the evil arising from the use of spirituous liquors to the sanction they have received from the higher classes; the respectable in society I hold to be the chief patrons of drunkenness. But I am not pot-valiant, and I shun To say how high potheen might have a run. 759. What do you mean by the phrase ‘run’?—It means, according to a common saying, that for one gallon made for the King, another is made for the Queen. What would you think, if, talking about stingo, I told you that a lady friend of mine, By only looking at her wine Flushed in her face as red as a flamingo? 4627. A lady informed me lately, that in dining out, although she should not taste a drop in the hob and nob at dinner, yet the lifting of the glass as frequently as etiquette requires, generally flushed her face a good deal before dinner was ended. Would you not ask of me, like many more,— ‘Pray, Sir, what had the lady had before?’ Suppose at sea, in Biscay's bay of bays,— A rum cask bursting in a blaze,— Should I be thought half tipsy or whole drunk, If running all about the deck I roar'd ‘I say, is ever a Cork man aboard?’ Answered by some Hibernian Jack Junk, While hitching up his tarry trouser,— How would it sound in sober ears, O how, Sir, If I should bellow with redoubled noise, ‘Then sit upon the bung-hole, broth of boys?’ 3901. Are you aware of the cause of the burning of the Kent East Indiaman in the Bay of Biscay?—Holding a candle over the bung-hole of a cask of spirits, the snuff fell into the cask and set it on fire. They had not presence of mind to put in the bung, which would have put out the fire; and if a man had sat on the bung-hole it would not have burnt him, and it would have put it out. When men—the fact's well known—reel to and fro, A little what is called how-come-you-so, They think themselves as steady as a steeple, And lay their staggerings on other people— Taking that fact in pawn, What proper inference would then be drawn By e'er a dray-horse with a head to his tail, Should anybody cry, To some one going by, ‘O fie! O fie! O fie! You're drunk—you've nigh had half a pint of ale!’ 4282. Do many young men visit those houses?—A very great many have done, more so than what visit the regular public-houses. I was in one of those places about twelve months ago, waiting for a coach, and there came into the beer-shop twenty-two boys, who called for half a gallon of ale, which they drank, and then they called for another. One certain sign of fumes within the skull They say is being rather slow and dull, Oblivious quite of what we are about— No one can doubt Some weighty queries rose, and yet You miss'd 'em, For instance, when a Doctor so bethumps What he denominates ‘the forcing system,’ Nobody asks him about forcing-pumps! 1211. The over-stimulation, which too frequently ends in the habit of drunkenness in Great Britain in every class, is the result of the British forcing system simply. Oh say, with hand on heart, Suppose that I should start Some theory like this,— ‘When Genesis Was written—before man became a glutton, And in his appetites ran riot, Content with simple vegetable diet, Eating his turnips without leg of mutton, His spinach without lamb—carrots sans beef, 'Tis my belief He was a polypus, and I'm convinc'd Made other men when he was hash'd or minced!’— Did I in such a style as this proceed, Would you not say I was Farre gone, indeed? 1282. Was not vegetable food prescribed in the first chapter of Genesis?—Vegetable food was appointed when the restorative power of man was complete. The restorative power in some of the lower animals is still complete. If a polypus be truncated or cut into several pieces, each part will become a perfect animal. —Vide Evidence of Dr. Farre. Excuse me, if I doubt at each Assize How sober it would look in public eyes, For our King's Counsel and our learned Judges When trying thefts, assaults, frauds, murders, arsons, To preach from texts of temperance like parsons, By way of giving tipplers gentle nudges. Imagine my Lord Bayley, Parke or Park, 975. What happy opportunities, for example, are offered to each Judge and King's Counsellor at every assize, to denounce all customary use of distilled spirit as the great incitement to crime. The proper improvement of such opportunities would do much for temperance. Donning the fatal sable cap, and hark, ‘These sentences must pass, howe'er I'm pang'd You Brandy must return—and Rum the same— To the Goose and Gridiron, whence you came— Gin!—Reverend Mr. Cotton and Jack Ketch Your spirit jointly will despatch— Whiskey, be hang'd!’ Suppose that some fine morning, Mounted upon a pile of Dunlop cheeses, I gave the following as public warning, Would there not be sly winking, coughs and sneezes? Or dismal hiss of universal scorn. ‘My brethren, don't be born,— But if you're born, be well advised— Don't be baptised. If both take place, still at the worst Do not be nursed,— At every birth each gossip dawdle Expects her caudle, At christenings, too, drink always hands about, Nurses will have their porter or their stout,— Don't wear clean linen, for it leads to sin,— All washerwomen make a stand for gin— If you're a minister—to keep due stinting, Never preach sermons that are worth the printing, 4642. When a clergyman gets a new manse he is fined in a bottle of wine; when he has been newly married, this circumstance subjects him to the same amicable penalty; the birth of a child also costs one bottle, and the publication of a sermon another. —By J. Dunlop, Esq. Avoid a steam-boat with a lady in her, 4637. The absolute necessity of treating females in the same manner, in steam-boat jaunts, is lamentable. And when you court, watch Miss well after dinner. 4637. Some youths have been known to defer their entrance into a temperate society till after their marriage, lest failure in the usual compliments should be misconstrued, and create a coldness with their future wives. Never run bills, or if you do don't pay, It (drinking) is employed in making bargains, at the payment of accounts. And give your butter and your cheese away,— 4639. A landlady, in settling with a farmer for his butter and cheese, brings out the bottle and the glass with her own hands, and presses it on his acceptance. How can he refuse a lady soliciting him to do what he is, perhaps, unfortunately already more than half inclined to? Build yachts and pleasure-boats if you are rich, But never have them launched or payed with pitch, 4640. The launching bowl is a bonus of drink, varying from £2 to £10, according to the size of the ship, bestowed by the owners on the apprentices of a ship-building yard at the launch of a vessel. The graving bowl is given to the journeyman after a vessel is payed with tar. In fine, for Temperance if you stand high, Don't die!’ 4638. On the event of a decease, every one gets a glass who comes within the door until the funeral, and for six weeks after it. Did I preach thus, Sir, should I not appear Just like the ‘parson much bemused with beer?’ Thus far, O Mr. Buckingham, I've gather'd, But here, alas! by space my pen is tether'd, And I can merely thank you all in short, The witnesses that have been called in court, And the Committee for their kind Report, Whence I have picked and puzzled out this moral, With which you must not quarrel, 'Tis based in charity—That men are brothers, And those who make a fuss, About their Temperance thus, Are not so much more temperate than others. THE UNITED FAMILY ‘We stick at nine.’ —Mrs. Battle. ‘Thrice to thine And thrice to mine, And thrice again, To make up nine.’ The Weird Sisters in Macbeth. How oft in families intrudes The demon of domestic feuds, One liking this, one hating that, Each snapping each, like dog and cat, With divers bents and tastes perverse, One's bliss, in fact, another's curse. How seldom anything we see Like our united family! Miss Brown of chapels goes in search, Her sister Susan likes the church; One plays at cards, the other don't; One will be gay, the other won't: In pray'r and preaching one persists, The other sneers at Methodists; On Sundays ev'n they can't agree Like our united family. There's Mr. Bell, a Whig at heart, His lady takes the Tories' part, While William, junior, nothing loth, Spouts Radical against them both. One likes the News, one takes the Age, Another buys the unstamp'd page; They all say I, and never we, Like our united family. Not so with us;—with equal zeal We all support Sir Robert Peel; Of Wellington our mouths are full, We dote on Sundays on John Bull, With Pa and Ma on selfsame side, Our house has never to divide— No opposition members be In our united family. Miss Pope her ‘Light Guitar’ enjoys, Her father ‘cannot bear the noise,’ Her mother's charm'd with all her songs, Her brother jangles with the tongs: Thus discord out of music springs, The most unnatural of things, Unlike the genuine harmony In our united family! We all on vocal music doat; To each belongs a tuneful throat, And all prefer that Irish boon Of melody—‘The Young May Moon’— By choice we all select the harp, Nor is the voice of one too sharp, Another flat—all in one key Is our united family. Miss Powell likes to draw and paint, But then it would provoke a saint, Her brother takes her sheep for pigs, And says her trees are periwigs. Pa praises all, black, blue, or brown; And so does Ma—but upside down! They cannot with the same eye see, Like our united family. Miss Patterson has been to France, Her heart's delight is in a dance; The thing her brother cannot bear, So she must practise with a chair. Then at a waltz her mother winks; But Pa says roundly what he thinks All dos-à-dos, not vis-à-vis, Like our united family. We none of us that whirling love, Which both our parents disapprove, A hornpipe we delight in more, Or graceful Minuet de la Cour. A special favourite with Mamma, Who used to dance it with Papa, In this we still keep step, you see, In our united family. Then books—to hear the Cobbs' debates! One worships Scott—another hates, Monk Lewis Ann fights stoutly for, And Jane likes ‘Bunyan's Holy War.’ The father on Macculloch pores, The mother says all books are bores; But blue serene as heav'n are we, In our united family. We never wrangle to exalt Scott, Banim, Bulwer, Hope, or Galt, We care not whether Smith or Hook, So that a novel be the book, And in one point we all are fast, Of novels we prefer the last,— In that the very Heads agree Of our united family! To turn to graver matters still, How much we see of sad self-will! Miss Scrope, with brilliant views in life, Would be a poor lieutenant's wife. A lawyer has her pa's good word, Her Ma has looked her out a Lord. What would they not all give to be Like our united family! By one congenial taste allied, Our dreams of bliss all coincide, We're all for solitudes and cots, And love, if we may choose our lots— As partner in the rural plan Each paints the same dear sort of man; One heart alone there seems to be In our united family. One heart, one hope, one wish, one mind,— One voice, one choice, all of a kind,— And can there be a greater bliss— A little heav'n on earth—than this? The truth to whisper in your ear, It must be told!—we are not near The happiness that ought to be In our united family! Alas! 'tis our congenial taste That lays our little pleasures waste— We all delight, no doubt, to sing, We all delight to touch the string, But where's the heart that nine may touch? And nine ‘May Moons’ are eight too much— Just fancy nine, all in one key, Of our united family! The play—Oh how we love a play, But half the bliss is shorn away; On winter nights we venture nigh, But think of houses in July! Nine crowded in a private box, Is apt to pick the stiffest locks— Our curls would all fall out, though we Are one united family! In art the self-same line we walk, We all are fond of heads in chalk, We one and all our talent strain Adelphi prizes to obtain; Nine turban'd Turks are duly sent, But can the royal Duke present Nine silver palettes—no, not he— To our united family. Our eating shows the very thing, We all prefer the liver-wing, Asparagus when scarce and thin, And peas directly they come in, The marrow-bone—if there be one— The ears of hare when crisply done, The rabbit's brain—we all agree In our united family. In dress the same result is seen, We all so doat on apple-green; But nine in green would seem a school Of charity to quizzing fool— We cannot all indulge our will With that sweet silk on Ludgate Hill, No remnant can sufficient be For our united family. In reading hard is still our fate, One cannot read o'erlooked by eight, And nine ‘Disowned’—nine ‘Pioneers,’ Nine ‘Chaperons,’ nine ‘Buccaneers,’ Nine ‘Maxwells,’ nine ‘Tremaines,’ and such, Would dip into our means too much— Three months are spent o'er volumes three, In our united family. Unhappy Muses! if the Nine Above in doom with us combine,— In vain we breathe the tender flame, Our sentiments are all the same, And nine complaints address'd to Hope Exceed the editorial scope, One in, and eight put out, must be Of our united family! But this is nought—of deadlier kind, A ninefold woe remains behind. O why were we so art and part? So like in taste, so one in heart? Nine cottages may be to let, But here's the thought to make us fret, We cannot each add Frederick B. To our united family. POETRY, PROSE, AND WORSE ‘Esaad Kiuprili solicited in verse permission to resign the government of Candia. The Grand Vizier, Hafiz Pasha, addressed a Ghazel to the Sultan to urge the necessity of greater activity in military preparations; and Murad, himself a poet, answered likewise in rhyme. Ghazi Gherai clothed in Ghazels his official complaint to the Sultan's preceptor. The Grand Vizier, Mustafa Pasha Bahir, made his reports to the Sultan in verse.’ —Vide Von Hammer on Othoman Literature in the Athenœum for Nov. 14, 1835. O Turkey! how mild are thy manners, Whose greatest and highest of men Are all proud to be rhymers and scanners, And wield the poetical pen! The Sultan rejects—he refuses— Gives orders to bowstring his man; But he still will coquet with the Muses, And make it a song if he can. The victim cut shorter for treason, Though conscious himself of no crime, Must submit and believe there is reason, Whose sentence is turned into rhyme! He bows to the metrical firman As dulcet as song of the South, And his head, like self-satisfied German, Rolls off with its pipe in its mouth. A tax would the Lord of the Crescent? He levies it still in a lay, And is p'rhaps the sole Bard at this present Whose poems are certain to pay. State edicts unpleasant to swallow He soothes with the charm of the Muse, And begs rays of his brother Apollo To gild bitter pills for the Jews. When Jealousy sets him in motion The fair one on whom he looks black, He sews up with a sonnet to Ocean, And sends her to drown in her sack. His gifts, they are poesies latent With sequins roll'd up in a purse, And in making Bashaws, by the patent Their tails are all ‘done into verse.’ He sprinkles with lilies and roses The path of each politic plan, And with eyes of Gazelles discomposes The beards of the solemn Divan. The Czar he defies in a sonnet, And then a fit nag to endorse With his Pegasus, jingling upon it, Reviews all his Mussulman horse. He sends a short verse, ere he slumbers, Express unto Meer Ali Beg, Who returns in poetical numbers The thousands that die of the plague. He writes to the Bey of a city In tropes of heroical sound, And is told in a pastoral ditty The place is burnt down to the ground. He sends a stern summons, but flow'ry, To Melex Pasha, for some wrong, Who describes the dark eyes of his Houri, And throws off his yoke with a song. His Vizier presents him a trophy, Still, Mars to Calliope weds— With an amorous hymn to St. Sophy A hundred of pickled Greek heads. Each skull with a turban upon it By Royal example is led: Even Mesrour the Mute has a Sonnet To Silence composed in his head. Ev'n Hassan while plying his hammer To punish short weight to the poor, With a stanza attempts to enamour The ear that he nails to a door. O! would that we copied from Turkey In this little Isle of our own, Where the times are so muddy and murky, We want a poetical tone! Suppose that the Throne in addresses— For verse there is plenty of scope— In alluding to native distresses, Just quoted the ‘Pleasures of Hope.’ Methinks 'twould enliven and chirp us, So dreary and dull is the time, Just to keep a State Poet on purpose To put the King's speeches in rhyme. When bringing new measures before us, As bills for the sabbath or poor, Let both Houses just chaunt them in chorus, And p'rhaps they would get an encore. No stanzas invite to pay taxes In notes like the notes of the south, But we're dunn'd by a fellow what axes With prose and a pen in his mouth. Suppose—as no payers are eager— Hard times and a struggle to live— That he sung at our doors like a beggar For what one thought proper to give? Our Law is of all things the dryest That earth in its compass can show! Of poetical efforts its highest The rhyming its Doe with its Roe. No documents tender and silky Are writ such as poets would pen, When a beadle is sent after Wilkie, Vide the advertisement of ‘The Parish Beadle after Wilkie,’ issued by Moon &amp; Co. Or bailiffs to very shy men. The warrants that put in distresses When rates have been owing too long, Should appear in poetical dresses, Ere goods be sold off for a song. Suppose that—Law making its choices Of Bishop, Hawes, Rodwell, or Cooke,— They were all set as glees for four voices, To sing all offenders to book? Our criminal code's as untender, All prose in its legal despatch, And no constables seize an offender While pleasantly singing a catch. They haul him along like a heifer, And tell him ‘My covey, you'll swing!’ Not a hint that the wanton young zephyr Will fan his shoe-soles with her wing. The trial has nothing that's rosy To soften the prisoner's pap, And Judge Park appears dreadfully prosy Whilst dooming to death in his cap. Would culprits go into hysterics, Their spirits more likely elope, If the jury consulted in lyrics, The judge made a line of the rope? When men must be hung for a warning, How sweet if the law would incline In the place of the ‘Eight in the morning,’ To let them indulge in the Nine! How pleasant if ask'd upon juries By Muses, thus mild as the doves, In the place of the Fates and the Furies That call us from home and our loves! Our warfare is deadly and horrid, Its bald bulletins are in prose, And with gore made revoltingly florid, Nor tinted with couleur de rose. How pleasant in army despatches In reading of red battle-plains, To alight on some pastoral snatches, To sweeten the blood and the brains! How sweet to be drawn for the Locals By songs setting valour a-gog! Or be press'd to turn tar by sea-vocals Inviting—with ‘Nothing like Grog!’ To tenants but shortish at present, When Michaelmas comes with its day, O! a landlord's effusion were pleasant That talk'd of the flowers in May! How sweet if the bill that rehearses The debt we've incurr'd in the year, But enrich'd, as a copy of verses, The Gem, or a new Souvenir! O! would that we copied from Turkey In this little Isle of our own! For the times are so moody and murky, We want a poetical tone! DOMESTIC POEMS ‘It's hame, hame, hame.’ —A. Cunningham. ‘There's no place like home.’ —Clari. I HYMENEAL RETROSPECTIONS O Kate! my dear Partner, through joy and through strife! When I look back at Hymen's dear day, Not a lovelier bride ever chang'd to a wife, Though you're now so old, wizen'd, and grey! Those eyes, then, were stars, shining rulers of fate! But as liquid as stars in a pool; Though now they're so dim, they appear, my dear Kate, Just like gooseberries boil'd for a fool! That brow was like marble, so smooth and so fair; Though it's wrinkled so crookedly now, As if Time, when those furrows were made by the share, Had been tipsy whilst driving his plough! Your nose, it was such as the sculptors all chose, When a Venus demanded their skill; Though now it can hardly be reckon'd a nose, But a sort of Poll-Parroty bill! Your mouth, it was then quite a bait for the bees, Such a nectar there hung on each lip; Though now it has taken that lemon-like squeeze, Not a blue-bottle comes for a sip! Your chin, it was one of Love's favourite haunts, From its dimple he could not get loose; Though now the neat hand of a barber it wants, Or a singe, like the breast of a goose! How rich were those locks, so abundant and full, With their ringlets of auburn so deep! Though now they look only like frizzles of wool, By a bramble torn off from a sheep! That neck, not a swan could excel it in grace, While in whiteness it vied with your arms; Though now a grave 'kerchief you properly place, To conceal that scrag-end of your charms! Your figure was tall, then, and perfectly straight, Though it now has two twists from upright— But bless you! still bless you! my Partner! my Kate! Though you be such a perfect old fright! II [The sun was slumbering in the West] The sun was slumbering in the West, My daily labours past; On Anna's soft and gentle breast My head reclined at last;— The darkness clos'd around, so dear To fond congenial souls, And thus she murmur'd at my ear, ‘My love, we're out of coals!— ‘That Mister Bond has call'd again, Insisting on his rent; And all the Todds are coming up To see us, out of Kent;— I quite forgot to tell you John Has had a tipsy fall;— I'm sure there's something going on With that vile Mary Hall!— ‘Miss Bell has bought the sweetest silk, And I have bought the rest— Of course, if we go out of town, Southend will be the best.— I really think the Jones's house Would be the thing for us;— I think I told you, Mrs. Pope Has parted with her nus— ‘Cook, by the way, came up to-day To bid me suit myself— And what d'ye think? the rats have gnawed The victuals on the shelf.— And, lord! there's such a letter come, Inviting you to fight! Of course you don't intend to go— God bless you, dear, good-night!’ III A PARENTAL ODE TO MY SON, AGED THREE YEARS AND FIVE MONTHS Thou happy, happy elf! (But stop,—first let me kiss away that tear)— Thou tiny image of myself! (My love, he's poking peas into his ear!) Thou merry, laughing sprite! With spirits feather-light, Untouch'd by sorrow and unsoil'd by sin— (Good heavens! the child is swallowing a pin!) Thou little tricksy Puck! With antic toys so funnily bestuck, Light as the singing bird that wings the air— (The door! the door! he'll tumble down the stair!) Thou darling of thy sire! (Why, Jane, he'll set his pinafore a-fire!) Thou imp of mirth and joy! In love's dear chain so strong and bright a link, Thou idol of thy parents—(Drat the boy! There goes my ink!) Thou cherub—but of earth; Fit playfellow for Fays, by moonlight pale, In harmless sport and mirth, (That dog will bite him if he pulls its tail!) Thou human humming-bee, extracting honey From ev'ry blossom in the world that blows, Singing in Youth's Elysium ever sunny— (Another tumble!—that's his precious nose!) Thy father's pride and hope! (He'll break the mirror with that skipping-rope!) With pure heart newly stamp'd from Nature's mint— (Where did he learn that squint?) Thou young domestic dove! (He'll have that jug off, with another shove!) Dear nursling of the hymeneal nest! (Are those torn clothes his best!) Little epitome of man! (He'll climb upon the table, that's his plan!) Touch'd with the beauteous tints of dawning life— (He's got a knife!) Thou enviable being! No storms, no clouds, in thy blue sky foreseeing, Play on, play on, My elfin John! Toss the light ball—bestride the stick— (I knew so many cakes would make him sick!) With fancies buoyant as the thistledown, Prompting the face grotesque, and antic brisk, With many a lamb-like frisk— (He's got the scissors, snipping at your gown!) Thou pretty opening rose! (Go to your mother, child, and wipe your nose!) Balmy, and breathing music like the South, (He really brings my heart into my mouth!) Fresh as the morn, and brilliant as its star,— (I wish that window had an iron bar!) Bold as the hawk, yet gentle as the dove— (I'll tell you what, my love, I cannot write, unless he's sent above!) IV A SERENADE ‘Lullaby, oh, lullaby!’ Thus I heard a father cry, ‘Lullaby, oh, lullaby! The brat will never shut an eye; Hither come, some power divine! Close his lids or open mine! ‘Lullaby, oh, lullaby! What the devil makes him cry? Lullaby, oh, lullaby! Still he stares—I wonder why? Why are not the sons of earth Blind, like puppies, from the birth? ‘Lullaby, oh, lullaby!’ Thus I heard the father cry; ‘Lullaby, oh, lullaby! Mary, you must come and try!— Hush, oh, hush, for mercy's sake— The more I sing, the more you wake! ‘Lullaby, oh, lullaby! Fie, you little creature, fie; Lullaby, oh, lullaby! Is no poppy-syrup nigh? Give him some, or give him all, I am nodding to his fall! ‘Lullaby, oh, lullaby! Two such nights, and I shall die! Lullaby, oh, lullaby! He'll be bruised, and so shall I,— How can I from bedposts keep, When I'm walking in my sleep? ‘Lullaby, oh, lullaby! Sleep his very looks deny— Lullaby, oh, lullaby! Nature soon will stupify— My nerves relax,—my eyes grow dim— Who's that fallen—me or him?’ JOHN JONES A PATHETIC BALLAD ‘I saw the iron enter into his soul.’ Sterne. John Jones he was a builder's clerk, On ninety pounds a year, Before his head was engine-turn'd To be an engineer! For, finding that the iron roads Were quite the public tale, Like Robin Redbreast, all his heart Was set upon a rail. But oh! his schemes all ended ill, As schemes must come to nought With men who try to make short cuts When cut with something short. His altitudes he did not take Like any other elf; But first a spirit-level took That levell'd him himself. Then getting up, from left to right So many tacks he made, The ground he meant to go upon Got very well survey'd. How crows may fly he did not care A single fig to know;— He wish'd to make an iron road, And not an iron crow: So, going to the Rose and Crown To cut his studies short, The nearest way from pint to pint, He found was through a quart. According to this rule he plann'd His railway o'er a cup; But when he came to lay it down, No soul would take it up! Alas! not his the wily arts Of men as shrewd as rats, Who out of one sole level make A precious lot of flats! In vain from Z to crooked S His devious line he show'd; Directors even seemed to wish For some directer road. The writers of the public press All sneered at his design; And penny-a-liners wouldn't give A penny for his line! Yet still he urged his darling scheme In spite of all the fates; Until at last his zigzag ways Quite brought him into straits. His money gone, of course he sank In debt from day to day— His way would not pay him, and so He could not pay his way. Said he, ‘All parties run me down,— How bitter is my cup! My landlord is the only man That ever runs me up! ‘And he begins to talk of scores, And will not draw a cork’;— And then he rail'd at Fortune, since He could not rail at York! The morrow, in a fatal noose They found him, hanging fast; This sentence scribbled on the wall,— ‘I've got my line at last!’ Twelve men upon the body sate, And thus, on oath, did say, ‘We find he got his gruel 'cause He couldn't have his way!’ THE DEAD ROBBERY ‘Here's that will sack a city.’ —Henry the IVth. Of all the causes that induce mankind To strike against themselves a mortal docket, Two eminent above the rest we find— To be in love, or to be out of pocket: Both have made many melancholy martyrs, But p'rhaps, of all the felonies de se, By ponds, and pistols, razors, ropes and garters, Two thirds have been through want of £. s. d.! Thus happen'd it with Peter Bunce; Both in the dumps and out of them at once, From always drawing blanks in Fortune's lottery, At last, impatient of the light of day, He made his mind up to return his clay Back to the pottery. Feigning a raging tooth that drove him mad, From twenty divers druggists' shops He begg'd enough of laudanum by drops T' effect the fatal purpose that he had; He drank them, died, and while old Charon ferried him, The Coroner convened a dozen men, Who found his death was phial-ent—and then The Parish buried him! Unwatch'd, unwept, As commonly a Pauper sleeps, he slept; There could not be a better opportunity For bodies to steal a body so ill kept, With all impunity: In fact, when Night o'er human vice and folly Had drawn her very necessary curtains, Down came a fellow with a sack and spade, Accustom'd many years to drive a trade, With that Anatomy more Melancholy Than Burton's! The Watchman in his box was dozing; The Sexton drinking at the Cheshire Cheese; No fear of any creature interposing, The human Jackal work'd away at ease: He toss'd the mould to left and right, The shabby coffin came in sight, And soon it open'd to his double-knocks,— When lo! the stiff'un that he thought to meet Starts sudden up, like Jacky-in-a-box, Upon his seat! Awaken'd from his trance, For so the laudanum had wrought by chance, Bunce stares up at the moon, next looking level, He spies a shady Figure, tall and bony, Then shudders out these words ‘Are—you—the—Devil?’ ‘The Devil a bit of him,’ says Mike Mahoney, ‘I'm only com'd here, hoping no affront, To pick up honestly a little blunt—’ ‘Blunt!’ echoes Bunce, with a hoarse croak of laughter,- ‘Why, man, I turn'd life's candle in the socket, Without a rap in either pocket, For want of that same blunt you're looking after!’ ‘That's true,’ says Mike, ‘and many a pretty man Has cut his stick upon your very plan, Not worth a copper, him and all his trumps, And yet he's fetch'd a dacent lot of stuff, Provided he was sound and fresh enough, And dead as dumps.’ ‘I take,’ quoth Bunce, with a hard wink, ‘the fact is, You mean a subject for a surgeon's practice,— I hope the question is not out of reason, But just suppose a lot of flesh and bone, For instance, like my own, What might it chance to fetch now, at this season?’ ‘Fetch is it?’ answers Mike, ‘why prices differ,— But taking this same small bad job of ours, I reckon, by the pow'rs! I've lost ten pound by your not being stiffer!’ ‘Ten pounds!’ Bunce echoes in a sort of flurry, ‘Odd zounds! Ten pounds, How sweet it sounds, Ten pounds!’ And on his feet upspringing in a hurry— It seem'd the operation of a minute— A little scuffle—then a whack— And then he took the Body Snatcher's sack And poked him in it! Such is this life! A very pantomime for tricks and strife! See Bunce, so lately in Death's passive stock, Invested, now as active as a griffin, Walking—no ghost—in velveteens and smock, To sell a stiff'un! A flash of red, then one of blue, At last, like lighthouse, came in view; Bunce rang the nightbell; wiped his highlows muddy; His errand told; sack produced; And by a sleepy boy was introduced To Dr. Oddy, writing in his study. The bargain did not long take time to settle, ‘Ten pounds, Odd zounds! How well it sounds, Ten pounds,’ Chink'd into Bunce's palm in solid metal. With joy half-crazed, It seem'd some trick of sense, some airy gammon, He gazed and gazed, At last, possess'd with the old lust of Mammon, Thought he, ‘With what a very little trouble, This little capital I now might double—’ Another scuffle of its usual brevity,— And Doctor Oddy, in his suit of black, Was finishing, within the sack, His ‘Thoughts upon Longevity!’ The trick was done. Without a doubt, The sleepy boy let Bunce and burthen out; Who coming to a lone convenient place, The body stripp'd; hid all the clothes, and then, Still favoured by the luck of evil men, Found a new customer in Dr. Case. All more minute particulars to smother, Let it suffice, Nine guineas was the price For which one doctor bought the other; As once I heard a Preacher say in Guinea, ‘You see how one black sin bring on anudder, Like little nigger pickaninny, A-riding pick-a-back upon him mudder!’ ‘Humph!’ said the Doctor, with a smile sarcastic, Seeming to trace Some likeness in the face, ‘So death at last has taken old Bombastic!’ But in the very middle of his joking,— The subject, still unconscious of the scoff— Seized all at once with a bad fit of choking, He too was taken off! Leaving a fragment ‘On the Hooping Cough.’ Satan still sending luck, Another body found another buyer: For ten pounds ten the bargain next was struck, Dead doctors going higher. ‘Here,’ said the purchaser, with smile quite pleasant Taking a glimpse at his departed brother, ‘Here's half a guinea in the way of present— Subjects are scarce, and when you get another, Let me be first.’—Bunce took him at his word, And suddenly his old atrocious trick did, Sacking M.D. the third, Ere he could furnish ‘Hints to the Afflicted.’ Flush'd with success, Beyond all hope or guess, His new dead robbery upon his back, Bunce plotted—such high flights ambition takes,— To treat the Faculty like ducks and drakes, And sell them all ere they could utter ‘Quack!’ But Fate opposed.—According to the schools, When men become insufferably bad, The gods confer to drive them mad; March hairs upon the heads of April fools! Tempted by the old demon avaricious, Bunce traded on too far into the morning; Till nods, and winks, and looks, and signs suspicious, Ev'n words malicious, Forced on him rather an unpleasant warning. Glad was he to perceive, beside a wicket, A porter, ornamented with a ticket, Who did not seem to be at all too busy— ‘Here, my good man, Just show me, if you can, A doctor's—if you want to earn a tizzy!’ Away the porter marches, And with grave face, obsequious precedes him, Down crooked lanes, round corners, under arches; At last, up an old-fashion'd staircase leads him, Almost impervious to the morning ray, Then shows a door—‘There, that's a doctor's reckon'd, A rare Top-Sawyer, let who will come second— Good day.’ ‘I'm right,’ thought Bunce, ‘as any trivet; Another venture—and then up I give it!’ He rings—the door, just like a fairy portal, Opens untouch'd by mortal— He gropes his way into a dingy room, And hears a voice come growling through the gloom, ‘Well—eh?—Who? What?—Speak out at once!’ ‘I will,’ says Bunce. ‘I've got a sort of article to sell; Medical gemmen knows me very well—’ But think Imagination how it shock'd her To hear the voice roar out, ‘Death! Devil! d?n! Confound the vagabond, he thinks I am A rhubarb-and-magnesia Doctor!’ ‘No Doctor!’ exclaim'd Bunce, and dropp'd his jaw, But louder still the voice began to bellow, ‘Yes,—yes,—odd zounds!—I am a Doctor, fellow, At law!’ The word suffic'd.—Of things Bunce feared the most (Next to a ghost) Was law,—or any of the legal corps,— He dropp'd at once his load of flesh and bone, And, caring for no body, save his own, Bolted,—and lived securely till four-score, From never troubling Doctors any more! ‘NAPOLEON'S MIDNIGHT REVIEW’ A NEW VERSION In his bed, bolt upright, In the dead of the night, The French Emperor starts like a ghost! By a dream held in charm, He uplifts his right arm, For he dreams of reviewing his host. To the stable he glides, For the charger he rides; And he mounts him, still under the spell; Then, with echoing tramp, They proceed through the camp, All intent on a task he loves well. Such a sight soon alarms, And the guards present arms, As he glides to the posts that they keep; Then he gives the brief word, And the bugle is heard, Like a hound giving tongue in its sleep. Next the drums they arouse, But with dull row-de-dows, And they give but a somnolent sound; Whilst the foot and horse, both, Very slowly and loth, Begin drowsily mustering round. To the right and left hand, They fall in, by command, In a line that might be better dress'd; Whilst the steeds blink and nod, And the lancers think odd To be rous'd like the spears from their rest. With their mouths of wide shape, Mortars seem all agape, Heavy guns look more heavy with sleep; And, whatever their bore, Seem to think it one more In the night such a field day to keep. Then the arms, christened small, Fire no volley at all, But go off, like the rest, in a doze; And the eagles, poor things, Tuck their heads 'neath their wings, And the band ends in tunes through the nose. Till each pupil of Mars Takes a wink like the stars— Open order no eye can obey: If the plumes in their heads Were the feathers of beds, Never top could be sounder than they! So, just wishing good night, Bows Napoleon, polite; But instead of a loyal endeavour To reply with a cheer; Not a sound met his ear, Though each face seem'd to say ‘Nap for ever!’ THE OLD POLER'S WARNING Come, messmates, attend to a warning, From one who has gone through the whole; And you'll never set sail, some fine morning, To seek any sort of a Pole. It's not for the icebergs and freezing, Or dangers you'll have for to court, It's the shocks very hard and unpleasing You'll meet on returning to Port. It's joyful to sail up the Channel, And think of your girls and your wives, Of the warming-pans, Wallsend and flannel, To comfort the rest of your lives! But Lord! you will look like a ninny To find, when to shore you have got, That Old England is turned into Guinea, It feels so confoundedly hot! The next thing is coming, in Wapping, To houses you lived at before, And you find there is no kind of stopping Without open windows and door! Then Poll, if dispos'd to be cruel, Or got someone else in her grace, She just chucks on a shovel of fuel, And drives you smack out of the place! There's Tomkins, that took for to grapple With Methody Tracks at the Pole, Is half crazy he can't go to chapel, It's so like Calcutta's Black Hole! And Block, tho' he's not a deceiver, But knows what to marriage belongs, His own wife he's oblig'd for to leave her, Because of her pokers and tongs. Myself, tho' I'm able at present To bear with one friend at a time, And my wife, if she makes herself pleasant, At first I was plagued with the clime. Like powder I flew from hot cinders, And whistled for winds fore and aft, While I set between two open winders A-courting a cold thorough-draught! The first time in bed I was shoven, The moment I pillow'd my head, O! I thought I had crept in an oven, A-baking with all of the bread! I soon left the blankets behind me, And ran for a cooler retreat;— But next morning the Justices fin'd me For taking a snooze in the street! Now, there was a chance for a feller! No roof I could sleep under twice; Till a Fishmonger let me his cellar, Of course with the use of the ice. But still, like old hermits in stories, I found it a dullish concarn; With no creature but maids and John Dories, To listen to spinning a yarn! Then wanting to see Black-Ey'd Susan, I went to the Surrey with Sal; And what next?—in the part most amusin', I fainted away like a gal! Well, there I was, stretch'd without motion, No smells and no fans would suffice, Till my natur at last gave a notion To grab at a gentleman's ice! Then, Messmates, attend to a warning From one who has gone through the whole, And you'll never set sail, some fine morning, To seek any sort of a Pole. It's not for the ice-bergs and freezing, Or dangers you'll have for to court, It's the shocks, very hard and unpleasing, You'll meet on returning to port! STANZAS COMPOSED IN A SHOWER-BATH ‘Drip, drip, drip—there's nothing here but dripping.’ —Remorse, by Coleridge. Trembling, as Father Adam stood To pull the stalk, before the Fall, So I stand here, before the Flood, On my own head the shock to call: How like our predecessor's luck! 'Tis but to pluck—but needs some pluck! Still thoughts of gasping like a pup Will paralyse the nervous pow'r; Now hoping it will yet hold up, Invoking now the tumbling show'r;— But, ah! the shrinking body loathes, Without a parapluie or clothes! ‘Expect some rain about this time!’ My eyes are seal'd, my teeth are set— But where's the Stoic so sublime Can ring unmov'd, for wringing wet? Of going hogs some folks talk big— Just let them try the whole cold pig! CLUBS TURNED UP BY A FEMALE HAND ‘Clubs! Clubs! part 'em! part 'em! Clubs! Clubs!’ —Ancient Cries of London. Of all the modern schemes of Man, That time has brought to bear, A plague upon the wicked plan That parts the wedded pair! My female friends they all agree They hardly know their hubs; And heart and voice unite with me, ‘We hate the name of Clubs!’ One selfish course the Wretches keep; They come at morning chimes, To snatch a few short hours of sleep— Rise—breakfast—read the Times— Then take their hats, and post away, Like Clerks or City scrubs, And no one sees them all the day,— They live, eat, drink, at Clubs! On what they say, and what they do, They close the Club-House gates; But one may guess a speech or two, Though shut from their debates: ‘The Cook's a hasher—nothing more The Children noisy grubs— A Wife's a quiz, and home's a bore’— Yes,—that's the style at Clubs! With Rundle, Dr. K., or Glasse, And such Domestic Books, They once put up—but now, alas! It's hey! for foreign cooks! ‘When will you dine at home, my Dove?’ I say to Mister Stubbs,— ‘When Cook can make an omelette, love,— An omelette like the Club's!’ Time was, their hearts were only placed On snug domestic schemes, The book for two—united taste,— And such connubial dreams,— Friends dropping in at close of day To singles, doubles, rubs,— A little music—then the tray— And not a word of Clubs! But former comforts they condemn; French kickshaws they discuss, They take their wine, the wine takes them, And then they favour us:— From some offence they can't digest, As cross as bears with cubs, Or sleepy, dull, and queer, at best— That's how they come from Clubs! It's very fine to say ‘Subscribe To Andrews'—can't you read?’ When Wives, the poor neglected tribe, Complain how they proceed! They'd better recommend at once Philosophy and tubs,— A Woman need not be a dunce To feel the wrong of Clubs. A set of savage Goths and Picts, Would seek us now and then— They're pretty pattern-Benedicts To guide our single men! Indeed my daughters both declare ‘Their Beaux shall not be subs. To White's, or Black's, or anywhere,— They've seen enough of Clubs!’ They say, ‘without the marriage ties, They can devote their hours To catechize, or botanize— Shells, Sunday Schools, and flow'rs— Or teach a Pretty Poll new words, Tend Covent-Garden shrubs, Nurse dogs and chirp to little birds— As Wives do since the Clubs.’ Alas! for those departed days Of social wedded life, When married folks had married ways, And lived like Man and Wife! Oh! Wedlock then was picked by none— As safe a lock as Chubb's! But couples, that should be as one, Are now the Two of Clubs! Of all the modern schemes of man That time has brought to bear, A plague upon the wicked plan That parts the wedded pair! My female friends they all allow They meet with slights, and snubs, And say, ‘They have no husbands now,— They're married to their Clubs!’ A RISE AT THE FATHER OF ANGLING TO MR. IZAAC WALTON, AT MR. MAJOR'S THE BOOKSELLER'S IN FLEET STREET Mr. Walton, it's harsh to say it, but as a Parent I can't help wishing You'd been hung before you publish'd your book, to set all the young people a fishing! There's my Robert, the trouble I've had with him it surpasses a mortal's bearing, And all thro' those devilish angling works—the Lord forgive me for swearing! I thought he were took with the Morbus one day, I did with his nasty angle! For ‘oh dear,’ says he, and burst out in a cry, ‘oh my gut is all got of a tangle!’ It's a shame to teach a young boy such words—whose blood wouldn't chill in their veins To hear him, as I overheard him one day, a-talking of blowing out brains? Chewing and spitting out (bullocks') brains into the water for ground bait is called blowing of brains. —Salter's Angler's Guide. And didn't I quarrel with Sally the cook, and a precious scolding I give her, ‘How dare you,’ says I, ‘for to stench the whole house by keeping that stinking liver?’ Twas enough to breed a fever, it was! they smelt it next door at the Bagots',— But it wasn't breeding no fever—not it! 'twas my son a-breeding of maggots! I declare that I couldn't touch meat for a week, for it all seemed tainting and going, And after turning my stomach so, they turned to blueflies, all buzzing and blowing; Boys are nasty enough, goodness knows, of themselves, without putting live things in their craniums; Well, what next? but he pots a whole cargo of worms along with my choice geraniums. And another fine trick, tho' it wasn't found out, till the housemaid had given us warning, He fished at the golden fish in the bowl, before we were up and down in the morning. I'm sure it was lucky for Ellen, poor thing, that she'd got so attentive a lover, As brings her fresh fish when the others deceas'd, which they did a dozen times over! Then a whole new loaf was short! for I know, of course, when our bread goes faster,— And I made a stir with the bill in my hand, and the man was sent off by his master; But, oh dear, I thought I should sink thro' the earth, with the weight of my own reproaches, For my own pretty son had made away with the loaf, to make pastry to feed the roaches! I vow I've suffered a martyrdom—with all sorts of frights and terrors surrounded! For I never saw him go out of the doors but I thought he'd come home to me drownded. And, sure enough, I set out one fine Monday to visit my married daughter, And there he was standing at Sadler's Wells, a-performing with real water. It's well he was off on the further side, for I'd have brain'd him else with my patten, For I thought he was safe at school, the young wretch! a studying Greek and Latin. And my ridicule basket he'd got on his back, to carry his fishes and gentles; With a belt I knew he'd made from the belt of his father's regimentals— Well, I poked his rods and lines in the fire, and his father gave him a birching, But he'd gone too far to be easy cured of his love for chubbing and perching. One night he never came home to tea, and altho' it was dark and dripping, His father set off to Wapping, poor man! for the boy had a turn for shipping; As for me I set up, and I sobbed and I cried for all the world like a babby, Till at twelve o'clock he rewards my fears with two gudging from Waltham Abbey! And a pretty sore throat and fever he caught, that brought me a fortnight's hard nussing, Till I thought I should go to my grey-hair'd grave, worn out with the fretting and fussing; But at last he was cur'd, and we did have hopes that the fishing was cured as well, But no such luck! not a week went by before we'd another such spell. Tho' he never had got a penny to spend, for such was our strict intentions, Yet he was soon set up in tackle again, for all boys have such quick inventions: And I lost my Lady's Own Pocket Book, in spite of all my hunting and poking, Till I found it chuck-full of tackles and hooks, and besides it had had a good soaking. Then one Friday morning, I gets a summoning note from a sort of a law attorney, For the boy had been trespassing people's grounds while his father was gone a journey, And I had to go and hush it all up by myself, in an office at Hatton Garden; And to pay for the damage he'd done, to boot, and to beg some strange gentleman's pardon. And wasn't he once fish'd out himself, and a man had to dive to find him, And I saw him brought home with my motherly eyes and a mob of people behind him? Yes, it took a full hour to rub him to life—whilst I was a-screaming and raving, And a couple of guineas it cost us besides, to reward the humane man for his saving, And didn't Miss Crump leave us out of her will, all along of her taking dudgeon At her favourite cat being chok'd, poor Puss, with a hook seow'd up in a gudgeon? And old Brown complain'd that he pluck'd his live fowls, and not without show of reason, For the cocks looked naked about necks and tails, and it wasn't their moulting season; And sure and surely, when we came to enquire, there was cause for their screeching and cackles, For the mischief confess'd he had picked them a bit, for I think he call'd them the hackles. A pretty tussle we had about that! but as if it warn't picking enough, When the winter comes on, to the muff-box I goes, just to shake out my sable muff— ‘O mercy!’ thinks I, ‘there's the moth in the house!’ for the fur was all gone in patches; And then at Ellen's chinchilly I look, and its state of destruction just matches— But it wasn't no moth, Mr. Walton, but flies—sham flies to go trolling and trouting, For his father's great coat was all safe and sound, and that first set me a-doubting. A plague, say I, on all rods and lines, and on young or old watery danglers! And after all that you'll talk of such stuff as no harm in the world about anglers! And when all is done, all our worry and fuss, why, we've never had nothing worth dishing; So you see, Mister Walton, no good comes at last of your famous book about fishing. As for Robert's, I burnt it a twelvemonth ago; but it turned up too late to be lucky, For he'd got it by heart, as I found to the cost of Your servant, Jane Elizabeth Stuckey. THE FORLORN SHEPHERD'S COMPLAINT AN UNPUBLISHED POEM, FROM SYDNEY ‘Vell! Here I am—no Matter how it suits A-keeping Company with them dumb Brutes, Old Park vos no bad Judge—confound his vig! Of vot vood break the Sperrit of a Prig! ‘The like of Me, to come to New Sow Wales To go a-tagging arter Vethers' Tails And valk in Herbage as delights the Flock, But stinks of Sweet Herbs vorser nor the Dock! ‘To go to set this solitary Job To Von whose Vork vos alvay in a Mob! It's out of all our Lines, for sure I am Jack Shepherd even never kep a Lamb! ‘I arn't ashamed to say I sit and veep To think of Seven Year of keepin Sheep, The spooniest Beasts in Nater, all to Sticks, And not a Votch to take for all their Ticks! ‘If I'd fore-seed how Transports vood turn out To only Baa! and Botanize about, I'd quite as leaf have had the t'other Pull, And come to Cotton as to all this Vool! ‘Von only happy moment I have had Since here I come to be a Farmer's Cad, And then I cotch'd a vild Beast in a Snooze, And pick'd her Pouch of three young Kangaroos! ‘Vot chance have I to go to Race or Mill? Or show a sneaking Kindness for a Till; And as for Vashings, on a hedge to dry, I'd put the Natives' Linen in my Eye! ‘If this whole Lot of Mutton I could scrag, And find a fence to turn it into Swag, I'd give it all in Lonnon Streets to stand, And if I had my pick, I'd say the Strand! ‘But ven I goes, as maybe vonce I shall, To my old Crib to meet with Jack, and Sal, I've been so gallows honest in this Place, I shan't not like to show my sheepish Face. ‘It's wery hard for nothing but a Box Of Irish Blackguard to be keepin' Flocks, 'Mong naked Blacks, sich Savages to hus, They've nayther got a Pocket nor a Pus. ‘But Folks may tell their Troubles till they're sick To dumb brute Beasts,—and so I'll cut my Stick! And vot's the Use a Feller's Eyes to pipe Vere von can't borrow any Gemman's Vipe?’ THE BEADLE'S ANNUAL ADDRESS The Curfew tolls the knell of parting day, The lowing herd winds slowly o'er the lea, The ploughman homeward plods his weary way— And this is Christmas Eve, and here I be! Now fades the glimmering landscape on the sight, And all the air a solemn stillness holds, Save where the beetle wheels his droning flight, Save Queen Victoria, who the sceptre holds! Save that from yonder ivy-mantled tower The moping owl does to the moon complain— Save all the ministers that be in power, Save all the Royal Sovereigns that reign! Let not ambition mock their useful toil, Their homely joys and destiny obscure; Nor grandeur hear with a disdainful smile, The Parish Beadle calling at the door! Far from the madding crowd's ignoble strife, Their sober wishes never learn'd to stray; Along the cool sequester'd vale of life, They kept the apple-woman's stalls away! Yet e'en these bones from insult to protect, Some frail memorial still erected nigh; With uncouth rhymes and shapeless sculpture deck'd He never lets the children play thereby. Haply some hoary-headed swain may say, Oft have we seen him at the peep of dawn, Brushing with hasty steps the dews away, To meet the Reverend Vicar all in lawn! One morn I miss'd him on the 'custom'd hill, Along the heath, and near his favourite tree; Another came, nor yet beside the rill, Nor at the Magpie and the Stump was he! The next with hat and staff, and new array, Along all sorts of streets we saw him borne; Approach and read (for thou canst read) the lay He always brings upon a Christmas morn! Large was his bounty, and his soul sincere, Heaven did a recompense as largely send; He gave to misery (all he had) a tear, And never failed on Sundays to attend! No further seek his merits to disclose, Or draw his frailties from their dread abode; Where they alike in trembling hope repose, John Bugsby, Number Thirteen, Tibbald's Road. THE ASSISTANT DRAPERS' PETITION ‘Now's the time and now's the hour.’ —Burns. ‘Seven's the main.’ —Crockford. Pity the sorrows of a class of men, Who, though they bow to fashion and frivolity; No fancied claims or woes fictitious pen, But wrongs ell-wide, and of a lasting quality. Oppress'd and discontented with our lot, Amongst the clamorous we take our station A host of Ribbon Men—yet is there not One piece of Irish in our agitation. We do revere Her Majesty the Queen, We venerate our Glorious Constitution; We joy King William's advent should have been, And only want a Counter Revolution. 'Tis not Lord Russell and his final measure, 'Tis not Lord Melbourne's counsel to the throne, 'Tis not this Bill, or that gives us displeasure, The measures we dislike are all our own. The Cash Law the ‘Great Western’ loves to name, The tone our foreign policy pervading; The Corn Laws—none of these we care to blame, Our evils we refer to over-trading. By Tax or Tithe our murmurs are not drawn; We reverence the Church—but hang the cloth! We love her ministers—but curse the lawn! We have, alas! too much to do with both! We love the sex:—to serve them is a bliss! We trust they find us civil, never surly; All that we hope of female friends is this, That their last linen may be wanted early. Ah! who can tell the miseries of men That serve the very cheapest shops in town? Till faint and weary, they leave off at ten, Knock'd up by ladies beating of 'em down! But has not Hamlet his opinion given— O Hamlet had a heart for Drapers' servants! ‘That custom is’—say custom after seven— ‘More honour'd in the breach than the observance.’ O come then, gentle ladies, come in time, O'erwhelm our counters, and unload our shelves; Torment us all until the seventh chime, But let us have the remnant to ourselves We wish of knowledge to lay in a stock, And not remain in ignorance incurable;— To study Shakspeare, Milton, Dryden, Locke, And other fabrics that have proved so durable. We long for thoughts of intellectual kind, And not to go bewilder'd to our beds; With stuff and fustian taking up the mind, And pins and needles running in our heads! For oh! the brain gets very dull and dry, Selling from morn till night for cash or credit; Or with a vacant face and vacant eye, Watching cheap prints that Knight did never edit. Till sick with toil, and lassitude extreme, We often think, when we are dull and vapoury, The bliss of Paradise was so supreme, Because that Adam did not deal in drapery. LORD DURHAM'S RETURN ‘On revient toujours.’ —French Song. ‘And will I see his face again, And will I hear him speak?’ —There's nae Luck about the House. ‘The Inconstant is come!’ It's in every man's mouth; From the East to the West, From the North to the South; With a flag at her head, And a flag at her stern; Whilst the Telegraph hints At Lord Durham's return. Turn wherever you will, It's the great talk and small; Going up to Cornhill, Going down to Whitehall; If you ask for the news, It's the first you will learn, And the last you will lose, My Lord Durham's return. The fat pig in the sty, And the ox in the stall, The old dog at the door, And the cat in the wall; The wild bird in the bush, And the hare in the fern, All appear to have heard Of Lord Durham's return. It has flown all abroad, It is known to goose-pens, It is bray'd by the ass, It is cackled by hens: The Pintadas, indeed, Make it quite their concern, All exclaiming, ‘Come back!’ At Lord Durham's return. It's the text over wine, And the talk after tea; All are singing one tune, Though not set in one key. E'en the Barbers unite Other gossip to spurn, Whilst they lather away At Lord Durham's return. All the Painters leave off, And the Carpenters go, And the Tailor above Joins the Cobbler below, In whole gallons of beer To expend what they earn While discussing one pint, My Lord Durham's return. It is timed in the Times, With the News has a run, Goes the round of the Globe, And is writ in the Sun, Like the Warren on walls, Fancy seems to discern, In great letters of chalk, ‘Try Lord Durham's return!’ Not a murder comes out; The reporters repine; And a hanging is scarce Worth a penny a line. If a Ghost reappeared With his funeral urn, He'd be thrown in the shade By Lord Durham's return. No arrival could raise Such a fever in town; There's a talk about 'Change Of the Stocks going down; But the Butter gets up Just as if in the churn, It forgot it should come In Lord Durham's return. The most silent are loud; The most sleepy awake; Very odd that one man Such a bustle can make! But the schools all break up, And both Houses adjourn, To debate more at ease On Lord Durham's return. Is he well? is he ill? Is he cheerful or sad? Has he spoken his mind Of the breeze that he had? It was rather too soon With home-sickness to yearn; There will something come yet Of Lord Durham's return. There's a sound in the wind Since that ship is come home; There are signs in the air Like the omens of Rome; And the lamps in the street, And the stars as they burn, Seem to give a flare up At Lord Durham's return! VERSES MISTAKEN FOR AN INCENDIARY SONG Come, all conflagrating fellows, Let us have a glorious rig: Sing old Rose, and burn the bellows! Burn me, but I'll burn my wig! Christmas time is all before us: Burn all puddings, north and south. Burn the Turkey—Burn the Devil! Burn snap-dragon! burn your mouth! Burn the coals! they're up at sixty! Burn Burn's Justice—burn Old Coke. Burn the chestnuts! Burn the shovel! Burn a fire, and burn the smoke! Burn burnt almonds. Burn burnt brandy. Let all burnings have a turn. Burn Chabert, the Salamander,— Burn the man that wouldn't burn! Burn the old year out, don't ring it; Burn the one that must begin. Burn Lang Syne; and, whilst you're burning, Burn the burn he paidled in. Burn the boxing! Burn the Beadle! Burn the baker! Burn his man! Burn the butcher—Burn the dustman, Burn the sweeper, if you can! Burn the Postman! burn the postage, Burn the knocker—burn the bell! Burn the folks that come for money! Burn the bills—and burn 'em well. Burn the Parish! Burn the rating! Burn all taxes in a mass. Burn the Paving! Burn the Lighting! Burn the burners! Burn the gas! Burn all candles, white or yellow— Burn for war, and not for peace; Burn the Czar of all the Tallow! Burn the King of all the Greece! Burn all canters—burn in Smithfield. Burn Tea-Total hum and bug. Burn his kettle, burn his water, Burn his muffin, burn his mug! Burn the breeks of meddling vicars, Picking holes in Anna's Urns! Burn all Steers's Opodeldoc, Just for being good for burns. Burn all Swindlers! Burn Asphaltum! Burn the money-lenders down— Burn all schemes that burn one's fingers! Burn the Cheapest House in town! Burn all bores and boring topics; Burn Brunel—aye, in his hole! Burn all subjects that are Irish! Burn the niggers black as coal! Burn all Boz's imitators! Burn all tales without a head! Burn a candle near the curtain! Burn your Burns, and burn your bed! Burn all wrongs that won't be righted, Poor poor Soup, and Spanish claims— Burn that Bell, and burn his Vixen! Burn all sorts of burning shames! Burn the Whigs! and burn the Tories! Burn all parties, great and small! Burn that everlasting Poynder— Burn his Suttees once for all! Burn the fop that burns tobacco. Burn a Critic that condemns.— Burn Lucifer and all his matches! Burn the fool that burns the Thames! Burn all burning agitators— Burn all torch-parading elves! And oh! burn Parson Stephen's speeches, If they haven't burnt themselves. POMPEY'S GHOST A PATHETIC BALLAD ‘Skins may differ, but affection Dwells in white and black the same.’ —Cowper. 'Twas twelve o'clock, not twelve at night, But twelve o'clock at noon; Because the sun was shining bright, And not the silver moon. A proper time for friends to call, Or Pots, or Penny Post; When, lo! as Phœbe sat at work, She saw her Pompey's Ghost! Now when a female has a call From people, that are dead; Like Paris ladies, she receives Her visitors in bed. But Pompey's Spirit could not come Like spirits that are white, Because he was a Blackamoor, And wouldn't show at night! But of all unexpected things That happen to us here, The most unpleasant is a rise In what is very dear. So Phœbe screamed an awful scream, To prove the seaman's text: That after black appearances, White squalls will follow next. ‘Oh, Phœbe, dear! oh, Phœbe, dear! Don't go to scream or faint; You think because I'm black I am The Devil, but I ain't! Behind the heels of Lady Lambe I walked whilst I had breath; But that is past, and I am now A-walking after Death! ‘No, murder, though, I come to tell By base and bloody crime; So Phœbe, dear, put off your fits Till some more fitting time: No Crowner, like a boatswain's mate, My body need attack, With his round dozen to find out Why I have died so black. ‘One Sunday, shortly after tea, My skin began to burn As if I had in my inside A heater, like the urn. Delirious in the night I grew, And as I lay in bed, They say I gather'd all the wool You see upon my head. ‘His Lordship for his doctor sent, My treatment to begin— I wish that he had call'd him out, Before he call'd him in! For though to physic he was bred, And pass'd at Surgeons' Hall, To make his post a sinecure, He never cured at all! ‘The Doctor look'd about my breast, And then about my back, And then he shook his head and said, “Your case looks very black.” And first he sent me hot cayenne, And then gamboge to swallow,— But still my Fever would not turn To Scarlet or to Yellow! ‘With madder and with turmeric He made his next attack; But neither he nor all his drugs Could stop my dying black. At last I got so sick of life, And sick of being dosed, One Monday morning I gave up My physic and the ghost! ‘Oh, Phœbe, dear, what pain it was To sever every tie! You know black beetles feel as much As giants when they die— And if there is a bridal bed, Or bride of little worth, It's lying in a bed of mould, Along with Mother Earth. ‘Alas; some happy, happy day, In church I hoped to stand, And like a muff of sable skin Receive your lily hand; But sternly with that piebald match My fate untimely clashes— For now, like Pompe-double-i, I'm sleeping in my ashes! ‘And now farewell! a last farewell! I'm wanted down below, And have but time enough to add One word before I go— In mourning crape and bombazine Ne'er spend your precious pelf— Don't go in black for me,—for I Can do it for myself. ‘Henceforth within my grave I rest, But Death, who there inherits, Allowed my spirit leave to come, You seemed so out of spirits: But do not sigh, and do not cry, By grief too much engross'd,— Nor, for a ghost of colour, turn The colour of a ghost! ‘Again farewell, my Phœbe dear! Once more a last adieu! For I must make myself as scarce As swans of sable hue.’ From black to gray, from gray to nought, The Shape began to fade,— And, like an egg, though not so white, The Ghost was newly laid! AN OPEN QUESTION ‘It is the king's highway that we are in, and in this way it is that thou hast placed the lions.’ —Bunyan. What! shut the Gardens! lock the lattic'd gate! Refuse the shilling and the Fellow's ticket! And hang a wooden notice up to state, ‘On Sundays no admittance at this wicket!’ The Birds, the Beasts, and all the Reptile race Denied to friends and visitors till Monday! Now, really, this appears the common case Of putting too much Sabbath into Sunday— But what is your opinion, Mrs. Grundy? The Gardens,—so unlike the ones we dub Of Tea, wherein the artisan carouses,— Mere shrubberies without one drop of shrub,— Wherefore should they be closed like public-houses? No ale is vended at the wild Deer's Head,— Nor rum—nor gin—not even of a Monday— The Lion is not carv'd—or gilt—or red, And does not send out porter of a Sunday— But what is your opinion, Mrs. Grundy? The Bear denied! the Leopard under locks! As if his spots would give contagious fevers, The Beaver close as hat within its box, So different from other Sunday beavers! The Birds invisible—the Gnaw-way Rats— The Seal hermetically sealed till Monday— The Monkey tribe—the Family of Cats,— We visit other families on Sunday— But what is your opinion, Mrs. Grundy? What is the brute profanity that shocks The super-sensitively-serious feeling? The Kangaroo—is he not orthodox To bend his legs, the way he does, in kneeling? Was strict Sir Andrew, in his Sabbath coat, Struck all a heap to see a Coati Mundi? Or did the Kentish Plumtree faint to note The Pelicans presenting bills on Sunday? But what is your opinion, Mrs. Grundy? What feature has repulsed the serious set? What error in the bestial birth or breeding, To put their tender fancies on the fret—? One thing is plain—it is not in the feeding! Some stiffish people think that smoking joints Are carnal sins 'twixt Saturday and Monday— But then the beasts are pious on these points, For they all eat cold dinners on a Sunday— But what is your opinion, Mrs. Grundy? What change comes o'er the spirit of the place, As if transmuted by some spell organic? Turns fell Hyæna of the Ghoulish race? The Snake, pro tempore, the true Satanic? Do Irish minds,—(whose theory allows That now and then Good Friday falls on Monday)— Do Irish minds suppose that Indian Cows Are wicked Bulls of Bashan on a Sunday— But what is your opinion, Mrs. Grundy? There are some moody Fellows, not a few, Who, turn'd by Nature with a gloomy bias, Renounce black devils to adopt the blue, And think when they are dismal they are pious— Is't possible that Pug's untimely fun Has sent the brutes to Coventry till Monday— Or p'rhaps some animal, no serious one, Was overheard in laughter on a Sunday— But what is your opinion, Mrs. Grundy? What dire offence have serious fellows found To raise their spleen against the Regent's spinney? Were charitable boxes handed round, And would not Guinea Pigs subscribe their guinea? Perchance the Demoiselle refused to moult The feathers in her head—at least till Monday; Or did the Elephant, unseemly, bolt A tract presented to be read on Sunday— But what is your opinion, Mrs. Grundy? At whom did Leo struggle to get loose? Who mourns thro' Monkey tricks his damag'd clothing? Who has been hissed by the Canadian Goose? On whom did Llama spit in utter loathing? Some Smithfield Saint did jealous feelings tell To keep the Puma out of sight till Monday, Because he prey'd extempore as well As certain wild Itinerants on Sunday— But what is your opinion, Mrs. Grundy? To me it seems, that in the oddest way (Begging the pardon of each rigid Socius) Our would-be Keepers of the Sabbath-day Are like the Keepers of the brutes ferocious— As soon the Tiger might expect to stalk About the grounds from Saturday till Monday, As any harmless Man to take a walk, If Saints could clap him in a cage on Sunday— But what is your opinion, Mrs. Grundy? In spite of all hypocrisy can spin, As surely as I am a Christian scion, I cannot think it is a mortal sin— (Unless he's loose) to look upon a lion. I really think that one may go, perchance, To see a bear, as guiltless as on Monday— (That is, provided that he did not dance) Bruin's no worse than bakin' on a Sunday— But what is your opinion, Mrs. Grundy? In spite of all the fanatic compiles, I cannot think the day a bit diviner, Because no children, with forestalling smiles, Throng, happy, to the gates of Eden Minor— It is not plain, to my poor faith at least, That what we christen ‘Natural’ on Monday, The wondrous history of Bird and Beast, Can be Unnatural because it's Sunday— But what is your opinion, Mrs. Grundy? Whereon is sinful phantasy to work? The Dove,—the wing'd Columbus of Man's haven? The tender Love-bird—or the filial Stork? The punctual Crane—the providential Raven? The Pelican whose bosom feeds her young? Nay, must we cut from Saturday till Monday That feather'd marvel with a human tongue, Because she does not preach upon a Sunday— But what is your opinion, Mrs. Grundy? The busy Beaver—that sagacious beast! The Sheep that own'd an Oriental Shepherd— That Desert-ship the Camel of the East, The horned Rhinoceros—the spotted Leopard— The creatures of the Great Creator's hand Are surely sights for better days than Monday— The Elephant, although he wears no band, Has he no sermon in his trunk for Sunday— But what is your opinion, Mrs. Grundy? What harm if men who burn the midnight-oil, Weary of frame, and worn and wan in feature, Seek once a-week their spirits to assoil, And snatch a glimpse of ‘Animated Nature’? Better it were, if, in his best of suits, The artisan, who goes to work on Monday, Should spend a leisure hour amongst the brutes, Than make a beast of his own self on Sunday— But what is your opinion, Mrs. Grundy? Why, zounds! what raised so Protestant a fuss (Omit the zounds! for which I make apology) But that the Papists, like some Fellows, thus Had somehow mixed up Dens with their theology? Is Brahma's Bull—a Hindoo god at home— A papal Bull to be tied up till Monday— Or Leo, like his namesake, Pope of Rome, That there is such a dread of them on Sunday— But what is your opinion, Mrs. Grundy? Spirit of Kant! have we not had enough To make Religion sad, and sour, and snubbish, But Saints Zoological must cant their stuff, As vessels cant their ballast—rattling rubbish! Once let the sect, triumphant to their text, Shut Nero up from Saturday till Monday, And sure as fate they will deny us next To see the Dandelions on a Sunday— But what is your opinion, Mrs. Grundy? ON A LATE IMMERSION Long Life and hard frosts to the fortunate Prince! And for many a skating may Providence spare him! For surely his accident served to evince That the Queen dearly loved, tho' the ice couldn't bear him! A BULL One day, no matter where or when, Except 'twas after some Hibernian revel, For why? an Irishman is ready then ‘To play the Devil’— A Pat, whose surname has escaped the Bards, Agreed to play with Nick a game at Cards. The stake, the same that the old Source of Sin From German Faustus and his German cousins Had won by dozens; The only one in fact he cares a pin To win. By luck or roguery of course Old Nick Won ev'ry trick; The score was full, the last turn-up had done it— ‘Your soul—I've won it!’ ‘It's true for you I've lost that same,’ Said Pat a little hazy in his wits— ‘My soul is yours—but come, another game— Double, or quits!’ A REFLECTION When Eve upon the first of Men The apple press'd with specious cant Oh! what a thousand pities then That Adam was not Adamant! ON A ROYAL DEMISE How Monarchs die is easily explain'd, And thus it might upon the Tomb be chisel'd, ‘As long as George the Fourth could reign he reign'd, And then he mizzled.’ THE PURSUIT OF LETTERS The Germans for Learning enjoy great repute; But the English make Letters still more a pursuit; For a Cockney will go from the banks of the Thames To Cologne for an O and to Nassau for M's. EPIGRAM After such years of dissension and strife, Some wonder that Peter should weep for his wife: But his tears on her grave are nothing surprising,— He's laying her dust, for fear of its rising. NIGHT-SONG—WRITTEN AT SEA 'Tis night—my bark is on the ocean, No sound I hear, no sight I see, Not e'en the darkened waves whose motion Still bears me, Fanny! far from thee;— But from the misty skies are gleaming Two smiling stars that look, my love, As if thine eyes, though veiled, were beaming Benignly on me from above. Good-night and bless thee, Fanny dearest! Nor let the sound disturb thy sleep, If when the midnight wind thou hearest, Thy thoughts are on the distant deep. Thy lover there is safe and fearless, For heaven still guards and guides his track, Nor can his dreaming heart be cheerless, For still to thee 'tis wafted back. 'Tis sweet on the benighted billow To trust in Him whom all adore; 'Tis sweet to think that from her pillow Her prayers for me shall Fanny pour. The wind, self-lullabied, is dozing, The winking stars withdraw their light, Fanny! methinks thine eyes are closing, Bless thee, my love! Good night, good night! RONDEAU To-day it is my natal day, And threescore years have pass'd away, While Time has turn'd to silver grey My hairs. Pursuing pleasure, love, and fun, A longish course I've had to run, And, thanks to Fortune, I have won My hares. But now, exhausted in the race, No longer I can go the pace, And others must take up the chase— My heirs! EPIGRAM ON A CERTAIN HERO AND HEROINE In raising names to noble rank Not always true desert prevails; But Honour's self may take delight In hoisting such top-gallant Sales! SKIPPING. A MYSTERY Little Children skip, The rope so gaily gripping, Tom and Harry, Jane and Mary, Kate, Diana, Susan, Anna, All are fond of skipping! The Grasshoppers all skip, The early dew-drop sipping, Under, over, Bent and clover, Daisy, sorrel, Without quarrel, All are fond of skipping! The tiny Fairies skip, At midnight softly tripping; Puck and Peri, Never weary, With an antic Quite romantic, All are fond of skipping. The little Boats they skip, Beside the heavy Shipping While the squalling Winds are calling, Falling, rising, Rising, falling, All are fond of skipping! The pale Diana skips, The silver billows tipping, With a dancing Lustre glancing To the motion Of the ocean— All are fond of skipping! The little Flounders skip, When they feel the dripping; Scorching, frying, Jumping, trying If there is not Any shying, All are fond of skipping! The very Dogs they skip, While threatened with a whipping, Wheeling, prancing, Learning dancing, To a measure, What a pleasure! All are fond of skipping! The little fleas they skip, And nightly come a nipping, Lord and Lady, Jude and Thady, In the night So dark and shady— All are fond of skipping! The Autumn Leaves they skip; When blasts the trees are stripping; Bounding, whirling, Sweeping, twirling, And in wanton Mazes curling, All are fond of skipping! The Apparitions skip, Some mortal grievance ripping, Thorough many A crack and cranny, And the keyhole Good as any— All are fond of skipping! But oh! how Readers skip, In heavy volumes dipping! ????? and ????? ???? and ????? ??? and ????? ???????? All are fond of skipping! A DREAM 'Twas night: the Globe was folded up, (The paper, not the earth,) And to its proper shelf restored The fairest ‘Maid of Perth:’ But still with strange intricacy The things that I had read— The Irish News, the Scottish Tale— Kept running in my head; While over all a sort of mist Began to slowly creep, The twilight haze of Thought before It darkens into Sleep; A foggy land where shady shapes Kept stirring in the gloom, Till with a hint of brighter tint One spot began to bloom, And on the blank, by dreamy prank, I saw a Figure tall, As vivid as from painted glass, Projected on a wall! The face, as well as I could trace, Two sparkling eyes were there, Black as the beard, and trim moustache, And curly head of hair; The nose was straight, the mouth was large, The lips disclosed beneath A set full white and regular, Of strong and handsome teeth— The whiter, that his brow, and cheek, And thick uncover'd gorge, Were ruddy as if baked by heat Of sun or glowing forge. His dress was buff, or some such stuff, And belted at the waist; A curious dirk, for stabbing work, Was in the girdle placed, Beside a sort of pouch or purse Of some wild creature's skin, To safely hold his store of gold Or silver coin therein;— But—suddenly his doublet changed To one of brighter hue, A jerkin fair and superfine, Of cloth of azure blue, Slash'd front and back with satin black, Embroider'd o'er, and laced With sable silk, as used to suit The ancient time and taste; His hose were of the Flemish cut, His boots of cordovan; A velvet bonnet on his head, Like that of Scottish man,— Nay, not a velvet one,—for why, As dreams are apt to deal, With sudden change, as swift as strange, It shone a cap of steel! His coat of buff, or azure stuff, Became a hauberk bright, No longer gay in his array, But harness'd for the Fight! Huge was his frame and muscular, Indicative of strength: His bosom broad, his brawny arms Of more than common length; And well the sturdy limbs might be So sinewy, stark, and strong, That had to wield in battle-field A sword so broad and long! Few men there were of mortal mould, Although of warlike trade, But had been rash to stand the clash Of that tremendous blade; And yet aloft he swung it oft, As if of feather-weight, And cut amid the empty air A monstrous figure eight; Whilst ever as it cleft the wind, A whisper came therewith, That low and clear said in my ear, ‘Behold the Fighting Smith!’ Vide Scott's ‘Fair Maid of Perth.’ And lo! another 'change came o'er The spirit of my dream:’ The hauberk bright no longer shone With that metallic gleam— No ruddy visage furnace-scorched, With glowing eyes, was there, No sable beard, nor trim moustache, Nor head of raven hair; No steely cap, with plume mayhap, No bonnet small or big; Upon his brow there settled now A curly powder'd Wig! Beneath his chin two cambric bands Demurely drooped adown; And from his brawny shoulders hung A black forensic gown. No mail beneath, to guard from death, Or wounds in battle dealt, Nor ready dirk for stabbing work, Dependent at his belt— His right hand bore no broad claymore, But, with a flourish, soon He wav'd a Pistol huge enough For any horse-dragoon, And whilst he pointed to and fro, As if to aim therewith, Still in my ear, the voice was clear, ‘Behold the Fighting Smith!’ Vide ‘The State Trials in Ireland.’ THE CAPTAIN'S COW A NAUTICAL ROMANCE ‘Water, water everywhere, But not a drop to drink.’ —Coleridge. It is a jolly Mariner As ever knew the billows' stir, Or battled with the gale; His face is brown, his hair is black, And down his broad gigantic back There hangs a platted tail. In clusters, as he rolls along, His tarry mates around him throng, Who know his budget well; Betwixt Canton and Trinidad No Sea-Romancer ever had Such wondrous tales to tell! Against the mast he leans a-slope, And thence upon a coil of rope Slides down his pitchy ‘starn;’ Heaves up a lusty hem or two, And then at once without ado Begins to spin his yarn:— ‘As from Jamaica we did come, Laden with sugar, fruit and rum, It blew a heavy gale: A storm that scar'd the oldest men For three long days and nights, and then The wind began to fail. ‘Still less and less, till on the mast The sails began to flap at last, The breezes blew so soft; Just only now and then a puff, Till soon there was not wind enough To stir the vane aloft. ‘No, not a cat's paw anywhere: Hold up your finger in the air You couldn't feel a breath; For why, in yonder storm that burst, The wind that blew so hard at first Had blown itself to death. ‘No cloud aloft to throw a shade; No distant breezy ripple made The ocean dark below. No cheering sign of any kind; The more we whistled for the wind The more it did not blow. ‘The hands were idle, one and all; No sail to reef against a squall; No wheel, no steering now! Nothing to do for man or mate, But chew their cuds and ruminate, Just like the Captain's Cow. ‘Day after day, day after day, Becalm'd the Jolly Planter lay, As if she had been moor'd: The sea below, the sky a-top Fierce blazing down, and not a drop Of water left aboard! ‘Day after day, day after day, Becalm'd the Jolly Planter lay, As still as any log; The parching seamen stood about, Each with his tongue a-lolling out, And panting like a dog— ‘A dog half mad with summer heat And running up and down the street, By thirst quite overcome; And not a drop in all the ship To moisten cracking tongue and lip, Except Jamaica rum! ‘The very poultry in the coop Began to pine away and droop— The cock was first to go! And glad we were on all our part He used to damp our very hearts With such a ropy crow. ‘But worst it was, we did allow, To look upon the Captain's Cow, That daily seemed to shrink: Deprived of water hard or soft, For though we tried her oft and oft, The brine she wouldn't drink; ‘But only turn'd her bloodshot eye And muzzle up towards the sky, And gave a moan of pain, A sort of hollow moan and sad, As if some brutish thought she had To pray to heav'n for rain; ‘And sometimes with a steadfast stare Kept looking at the empty air, As if she saw, beyond, Some meadow in her native land, Where formerly she used to stand A-cooling in the pond. ‘If I had only had a drink Of water then, I almost think She would have had the half; But as for John the Carpenter, He couldn't more have pitied her If he had been her calf. ‘So soft of heart he was and kind To any creature lame, or blind, Unfortunate or dumb: Whereby he made a sort of vow, In sympathising with the Cow, To give her half his rum;— ‘An oath from which he never swerv'd, For surely as the rum was serv'd He shared the cheering dram; And kindly gave one half at least, Or more, to the complaining beast, Who took it like a lamb. ‘At last with overclouding skies A breeze again began to rise, That stiffen'd to a gale: Steady, steady, and strong it blew; And were not we a joyous crew, As on the Jolly Planter flew Beneath a press of sail! ‘Swiftly the Jolly Planter flew, And were not we a joyous crew, At last to sight the land! A glee there was on every brow, That like a Christian soul the Cow Appear'd to understand. ‘And was not she a mad-like thing, To land again and taste the spring, Instead of fiery glass: About the verdant meads to scour, And snuff the honey'd cowslip flower, And crop the juicy grass! ‘Whereby she grew as plump and hale As any beast that wears a tail, Her skin as sleek as silk; And through all parts of England now Is grown a very famous Cow, By giving Rum-and-Milk!’ AN EXPLANATION BY ONE OF THE LIVERY Says Blue-and-Buff, to Drab-and-Pink, ‘I've heard the hardest word, I think, That ever posed me since my teens, I wonder what As-best-os means!’ Says Drab-and-Pink to Blue-and-Buff, ‘The word is clear, and plain enough. It means a Nag wot goes the pace, And so as best os wins the race.’ EPIGRAM ON DR. ROBERT ELLIOT OF CAMBERWELL. Whatever Doctor Robert's skill be worth, One hope within me still is stout and hearty, He would not kill me till the 24?? For fear of my appearing at his party! May 23, 1844. EPIGRAM ON A CERTAIN EQUESTRIAN STATUE Whoever has looked upon Wellington's breast, Knows well that he is not so full in the chest; But the sculptor, to humour the Londoners partial, Has turn'd the lean Duke to a plump City Marshal. EPIGRAM ON THE NEW HALF-FARTHINGS ‘Too small for any marketable shift, What purpose can there be for coins like these?’ Hush, hush, good Sir!—Thus charitable Thrift May give a Mite to him who wants a cheese! EPIGRAM [Charm'd with a drink which Highlanders compose] Charm'd with a drink which Highlanders compose, A German traveller exclaim'd with glee,— ‘Potztausend! sare, if dis is Athol Brose, How goot dere Athol Boetry must be!’ EPIGRAM [When would-be Suicides in purpose fail—] When would-be Suicides in purpose fail— Who could not find a morsel though they needed— If Peter sends them for attempts to jail, What would he do to them if they succeeded? THE LARK AND THE ROOK A FABLE ‘Lo! hear the gentle lark!’ —Shakspeare. Once on a time—no matter where— A lark took such a fancy to the air, That though he often gaz'd beneath, Watching the breezy down, or heath, Yet very, very seldom he was found To perch upon the ground. Hour after hour, Through ev'ry change of weather hard or soft, Through sun and shade, and wind and show'r, Still fluttering aloft; In silence now, and now in song, Up, up in cloudland all day long, On weary wing, yet with unceasing flight, Like to those Birds of Paradise, so rare, Fabled to live, and love, and feed in air, But never to alight. It caused, of course, much speculation Among the feather'd generation; Who tried to guess the riddle that was in it— The robin puzzled at it, and the wren, The swallows, cock and hen, The wagtail, and the linnet, The yellowhammer, and the finch as well— The sparrow ask'd the tit, who couldn't tell, The jay, the pie—but all were in the dark, Till out of patience with the common doubt, The Rook at last resolv'd to worm it out And thus accosted the mysterious Lark:— ‘Friend, prithee, tell me why You keep this constant hovering so high, As if you had some castle in the air, That you are always poising there, A speck against the sky— Neglectful of each old familiar feature Of Earth that nurs'd you in your callow state— You think you're only soaring at heaven's gate, Whereas you're flying in the face of Nature!’ ‘Friend,’ said the Lark, with melancholy tone, And in each little eye a dewdrop shone, ‘No creature of my kind was ever fonder Of that dear spot of earth Which gave it birth— And I was nestled in the furrow yonder! Sweet is the twinkle of the dewy heath, And sweet that thymy down I watch beneath, Saluted often with a loving sonnet: But Men, vile Men, have spread so thick a scurf Of dirt and infamy about the Turf, I do not like to settle on it!’ MORAL. Alas! how Nobles of another race Appointed to the bright and lofty way Too willingly descend to haunt a place Polluted by the deeds of Birds of Prey! SUGGESTIONS BY STEAM When Woman is in rags, and poor, And sorrow, cold, and hunger teaze her, If Man would only listen more To that small voice that crieth—‘Ease her!’ Without the guidance of a friend, Though legal sharks and screws attack her, If Man would only more attend To that small voice that crieth—‘Back her!’ So oft it would not be his fate To witness some despairing dropper In Thames's tide, and run too late To that small voice that crieth—‘Stop her!’ ANACREONTIC BY A FOOTMAN It's wery well to talk in praise Of Tea and Water-drinking ways, In proper time and place; Of sober draughts, so clear and cool, Dipp'd out of a transparent pool Reflecting heaven's face. Of babbling brooks, and purling rills, And streams as gushes from the hills, It's wery well to talk;— But what becomes of all sich schemes, With ponds of ice, and running streams, As doesn't even walk? When Winter comes with piercing cold, And all the rivers, new or old, Is frozen far and wide; And limpid springs is solid stuff, And crystal pools is hard enough To skate upon and slide;— What then are thirsty men to do, But drink of ale, and porter too, Champagne as makes a fizz; Port, sherry, or the Rhenish sort, And p'rhaps a drop of summut short— The water-pipes is friz! THE SURPLICE QUESTION BY A BENEDICT A very pretty public stir Is making, down at Exeter, About the surplice fashion: And many bitter words and rude Have been bestow'd upon the feud, And much unchristian passion. For me I neither know nor care Whether a Parson ought to wear A black dress or a white dress; Fill'd with a trouble of my own,— A Wife who preaches in her gown, And lectures in her night-dress! EPIGRAM ['Tis said of Lord B., none is keener than he] 'Tis said of Lord B., none is keener than he To spit a Wild Boar with éclât; But he never gets near to the Brute with his spear, He gives it so very much law. TO MY DEAR MARIANNE THIS FIRST SONNET If kindly words could warm th' unkindly air To summer clemency, that there might be A constant atmosphere of love with thee, Won by a constancy of tender care,— Then thy most delicate cheek should ever wear An exquisite blush, red-ripening to the glee Of cheerful lips; and my contentment see Its wish so recognised and written there: So much my bosom clings to thee and feels A painful echo of thy bosom pains; The patient paleness of thy cheek so steals With more than chill of Winter to my veins; And conscious sympathy of blood reveals The tender Brother-hood that now obtains! [SONG] [The Summer—the Summer—] The Summer—the Summer— Is beautiful and green;— But when its leaves are fallen off Who'd know that it had been,— Its dewy buds,—its scented flow'rs— Its fair and sunny mien, If honey were not stored up And harvest left to glean? So beauty,—so beauty Will wither and away;— And what is left to charm us when The flower's in decay,— To cheer our hearts and feast our souls And bless Affection's sway,— But that love gave us all its sweets Whilst Beauty had its day? Then Winter,—then Winter But sees us more than kind;— Tho' Age hath soil'd the surface charm Where first the eye reclin'd. But love lies deeper at the core, Like words the woodmen find Deep graven in the hearts of trees That once were on the rind. [WRITTEN ON THE BACK OF THE FOREGOING] Give me a pen that's charg'd with dews Fresh gather'd from the morning rose, And let it stain my page with hues As bright as kernel buds enclose. In common ink shall I indite, With ink that dates the felon's doom, That forges bonds,—no, let me write My bloomy thoughts in tints of bloom. [FRAGMENT] (EVIDENTLY SUPPOSED TO BE SPOKEN BY MRS. REYNOLDS, MOTHER OF THE POET'S WIFE) Mary, I believ'd you quick But you're as deaf as any beedle; See where you have left the plates; You've an eye, and so's a needle. Why an't Anne behind the door, Standing ready with her dishes, No one ever had such maids Always thwarting all my wishes, Marianne set up that child— And where's her pinafore—call Mary, The frock I made her will be spoil'd— Now Lizzy don't be so contrary, Hand round the bread—‘Thank God for what—’ It's done to rags! How wrong of Ann now,— The dumplings too are hard as read And plates stone-cold—but that's her plan now— Mary, a knock—now Hood take that— Or go without—Why, George, you're wanted, Where is that Lotte? Call her down She knows there's no white wine decanted— Put to the door, we always dine In public— Jane take that cover off the greens; Our earthen ware they play the deuce to; Here's Mr. Green without a fork— And I've no plate—but that I'm used to.— SIR JOHN BOWRING To Bowring, man of many tongues, (All over tongues like rumour) This tributary verse belongs To paint his learned humour; All kinds of gabs he talks, I wis, From Latin down to Scottish; As fluent as a parrot is, But far more Polly-glottish! No grammar too abstruse he meets However dark and verby,— He gossips Greek about the streets, And often Russ—in urbe—: Strange tongues whate'er you do them call, In short the man is able To tell you what's o'clock in all The dialects of Babel. Take him on 'Change; try Portuguese, The Moorish and the Spanish, Polish, Hungarian, Tyrolese, The Swedish and the Danish; Try him with these and fifty such, His skill will ne'er diminish, Although you should begin in Dutch And end (like me) in Finnish. FRAGMENTS Jove's Eagle Asleep I saw, through his eyelids, the might of his eyes. River of Life Those waters you hear, Yet see not—they flow so invisibly clear. Night Shedder of secret tears Felt upon unseen pillows—shade of Death! The Sun and Moon Father of light—and she, its mother mild. The Moon Sometimes she riseth from her shroud Like the pale apparition of a sun. Mercury That bantam Mercury, with feathered heels. A Lady She sighed And paleness came, like moonlight, o'er her face. She was like an angel in mosaic, Made up of many-coloured virtues. A friendless heart is like a hollow shell, That sighs o'er its own emptiness. He lay with a dead passion on his face, Like a storm stiffen'd in ice. Sometimes Hope Singeth so plaintively, 'tis like Despair. Her smile can make dull Melancholy grow Transparent to the secret hope below. Morning Surely this is the birthday of no grief That dawns so pleasantly along the skies! The lusty Morn Cometh, all flushed, and singing, from a feast Of wine and music in the odorous East The sun unglues The crimson leaves of Morning, that doth lie, Like a streaked rosebud in the orient sky.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">JUVENILIA THE BANDIT (? 1815–17) CANTO FIRST ‘While the red glaring torches illumine the cave, Bring the wine that was bought by the blood of the brave! No coward's pale lip Of the liquor shall sip While we drink to our comrades that lie in the grave! ‘We gained it in strife, and in danger we won; But we merrily drink now the battle is done! And the goblet we quaff While we merrily laugh, Nor to fill it anew the same danger we'll shun. ‘Then fill the bright goblets—replenish the whole! Pour, pour the rich liquor that gladdens the soul; For remorse we defy When the goblet is by, And conscience and care are soon drowned in the bowl.’ Thus sung the bandit crew, and as they sung, Wildly their harsh, discordant voices rung; And jarring echoes filled the vaulted cave As each harsh voice joined rudely in the stave; And when they ceased, the scoffing jest gave birth To sounds of laughter—loud and boisterous mirth; Or all was hushed in silence round while one Triumphant told of deeds of horror done; Or boasting speech and bitter mockings rose To angry words, and threatenings to blows And bloody contest, till the din swells high With shouts of fury, pain, and blasphemy. But instant sunk the tumult and the din, As suddenly the Chieftain came within; His tall, majestic, and commanding form Had been depressed beneath misfortune's storm; And on his brow care's lineaments uncouth Belie his age and rob him of his youth. And, save when all convulsed, his features show He strives within for mastery with woe; While half his agitated frame reveals The inward agony his pride conceals; His face and form assume the settled air And wonted attitude of calm despair. He was not formed by Nature for the part That he now played—once foreign to his heart. He had been formed to love; but 'twas his fate To meet with none but who deserved his hate. He had been mild, but injuries had fired, And with a savage sullenness inspired; Repeated wrongs had turned his breast to steel, And all but these he had forgot to feel. Apart from all, within a dark recess, He sat him down in gloomy silentness, Where he was wont to sit in gloomy thought O'er dark designs with woe and fury fraught, And his wild brain each frenzied plan revolved, Or acts of daring enterprise resolved; Even now, thus darkly did he meditate One last sad act to signalize his hate— One deed of retribution to be hurled To 'venge the wrongs he suffered from the world! Nor oft the robbers ventured to intrude By careless noise upon his thoughtful mood; And fewer still e'er strive by curious speech The secret purport of his plans to reach. One look—one word—the intrusive speech repressed, And the inquiry hushed, ere scarce expressed; So was he ever feared and held in awe— They crouched to him who spurned at every law! Wolf only to address the Chieftain dared, Nor for repulses oft repeated cared. Next to the Chief they feared and hated him Whose joy was blood and cruelty his whim. His sheathless blade was never known to rust, Nor the fresh gore e'er suffered to encrust; Peace he abhorred, and endless warfare waged, In jarring strife, eternal broils engaged. Ambitious, too,—impatient of control,— Subjection grated on his haughty soul, And made him—spurning at his leader's sway— First to rebel and latest to obey. And now, with angry tone the Bandit spoke, And on the Chieftain's reverie thus broke— ‘Say, do you scorn us, that you shun our feast, For that invites not your contempt at least; Our wine is good, and even Dacre's Lord Scarce sees such venison smoke upon his board. Such is our feast—would it were never worse, Nor more deserving your contempt than us.’ Up rose the Chief in haste, but not a word Implied the discontented speech was heard. ‘To arms,’ he cried, ‘to arms with speed prepare, This night our final enterprise to share, And then we part, for 'mid these wilds I see No firm security remains for me.’ He spoke—they lingered still, and some expressed Their discontent in murmurs half repressed— ‘When steals our wearied limbs repose from toil, While we make merry o'er our hard-earned spoil, This very night we fondly hoped at last To rest and revel after labours past; And, as I live, a feast, 'twas our belief, Would celebrate the accession of our Chief.’ ‘A feast! a banquet! rather let it show In my life's calendar a day of woe! A day that rose in gloom is lowering yet, And soon, I fear, as gloomily will set; And for your calling, think you I have prized Your avocation, nor yourselves despised? Have I your savage, brutal deeds admired, Nor cursed the sordid motives that inspired? No! I have viewed ye as a scourge designed— A plague—a curse—to chasten humankind. As such, as instruments I chose you, then, To wreak my vengeance on ungrateful men! ‘And in your banquets did I ever sip? Your food untasted ever pass my lip? No! I will eat wild berries and wild fruit, Drink of the stream and famish on a root, Couch in a cave and lodge me where I can, Ere I will now hold anything of man! And, hear this truth,—the plainest morsel now, By honest labour, earned with sweating brow, Were dearer, sweeter far, to me at least, Than all the viands in your guilty feast! Enough of this. Time hurries on! Draw near; For once my plan and all its purport hear, That, known more fully, you may judge aright, You join or not my enterprise to-night!’ In deep attention,—hushed without a sound,— With wondering eagerness they circle round; Ne'er had he deigned before one word to hold In converse with them or his plans had told; But now he speaks, for once without command, And the mute robbers, listening, round him stand. ‘Who has not heard the Earl Glenallan's name, And been familiar with his warlike fame? Who, by his king ungratefully repaid, Left courts and kings and sought the rural shade, Till roused from happy indolence he heard The plaint his bondaged countrymen preferred, And heard the summons to his patriot hand To burst the fetters that enslaved his land; 'Twas then reluctantly he drew his sword Against the king for whom his blood had poured, But poured, alas, in vain;—who does not know His combats, victories, and overthrow? Though all his perils, both by land and sea, And sorrows since, are only known to me. ‘Defeated and deserted—under ban— Chased like a tiger by the hate of man; By day through lonely wilds he urged his flight, And couched beneath Heaven's canopy at night. Alone he fled—his tenantry's goodwill And wishes for his welfare followed still; But more they dared not—till, by happy chance, Two boldly aided his escape to France. ‘But ere he went he bade a long adieu To one, the last, the only friend he knew; To him confided his intended wife— His love, his hope, his all, and more than life; And then he hurried from the ingrate strand, But first bequeathed his blessing to his land. ‘In France he covered all his deeds with shame, And, first, for aye resigned the patriot's name. Cursed be the day—the era of his fall— He gave his hand in friendship to the Gaul; Ne'er might his foes so well exult till then, Nor he deserved thus of his countrymen; Ne'er had he raised before his traitor hand Against the welfare of his native land; His deeds were blasted and his shame was sealed. There first he fought and first was known to greet A joyful feeling in his own defeat; Oft had he sighed to join in fight once more With those he led to victory before; But, they victorious,—'twere a coward's deed! He sighed, and left it for the day of need. It came. He marked the Gaul's superior force— Resistless, bursting its triumphant course. He left the conquerors in joyful haste, And fought when ruin and defeat menaced. Again he conquered, and returned once more With hopes rekindled to his native shore, And fondly thought this service might recall His country's love and make amends for all. In vain! His service they remembered not, But all, except his many faults, forgot, And drove him into solitude to find A refuge with the vilest of his kind. And now, to fill the measure of his woe, His friend must strike the last inhuman blow. This night—save we avert the guilty deed, Or his cold heart, like that he tortures, bleed— He weds the hand and heart he basely stole, And whelms keen anguish o'er Glenallan's soul! Love, friendless, poor—yet while my arm is strong, And my blade keen, I can avenge the wrong. Till now I've righted others' cause alone, But now Glenallan shall avenge his own!’ Awhile the robbers paused in deep amaze, And on the Chieftain turned their earnest gaze, Not that they pondered aught unusual now In the dark workings of his gloomy brow; But ne'er before they heard his lofty name, Nor knew they had a Chieftain of such fame. He spoke again: ‘Your guilty hands are red, And blush with blood too often they have shed. Many perchance may feel in after times The woe, the misery that tracked your crimes; But can remorse or conscience now recall One deed as black as this among them all? If so, remain, unworthy of the care To speed the chastening you ought to share. Speak! What so sacred to a Highland breast As is the claim of safety for his guest, And far more sacred if he be distrest? 'Twas thus we hailed the Stuart when he fled, And spurned the gold that hung upon his head: Was there a wretch, a traitor so accurst, A seeming friend who dared betray his trust? ‘Lead on!—We go! The traitor's heart shall bleed, Our hands shall aid, our tongues approve the deed. Long live our Chieftain, and all traitors die!’ They cried—one only joined not in the cry. 'Twas Wolf! ‘I say not so,’ with scornful smile He said, and gazed upon his brand the while. ‘Could this relate the deeds its edge had done,— Lost in amaze ye would forget that one, As each succeeding each you found them still All brighter far, or blacker, if you will,’— And o'er his haggard features as he spoke A scornful smile of exultation broke. All have some passion, pride, or ruling will, And his to be in all superior still; And now he gloried o'er the blood he spilt, That made him paramount, though but in guilt. And now the sign, the bustle, and the din Of preparation reigns without—within; Loud ring the arms, and loud the bugle strain, Recalls the stragglers to the cave again. They came in weary groups, but gaily bring Fresh game and booty for the banqueting, But, lo! deserted is the festive board, And each girds on his armour and his sword, While all their converse and their words imply Some daring enterprise and booty nigh. They marvel and inquire the Chief's intent, And rather give submission than consent. They arm—the order given—the route is known,— They hurry out, and Wolf is left alone. The sun, still lingering in the golden west, Slow sinks behind the purple mountain's crest That rears its head sublime; and far below The lake's calm bosom sparkles in the glow, Save where is seen an undulating shade By frowning rocks and woods and forests made; Or the tall vessel gently seems to glide In silent majesty along the tide, Her white sails wooing the soft zephyr's breath, Scarce rippling in the dancing wave beneath That rolls with gentle murmuring to lave The willow twig that loves to kiss the wave. One bright departing ray of golden fire Still hangs reluctant on the village spire; Like Hope's last dream, it fondly lingers yet, Then leaves the highest pinnacle—'tis set! And now the mountains, blending with the sky, Or, lost in clouds, elude the gazer's eye, And wide and far the lengthened shadows round, Creep slow and silent o'er the darkened ground; And travelling on, obscuring hill and dale, The shades of night enshroud the quiet vale. Now sleeps the peasant, and forgets the while, In sweet oblivion, his daily toil; Now rest the weary, and perchance in sleep The wretched and unhappy cease to weep; Some few in pain, or revelry or woe, Or worldly cares, its influence forego. Perhaps it flies the dark uneasy bed, Where the pale invalid reclines his head; But chiefly Guilt its balmy sweets forsake, And the cursed murderer and robber wake, For Conscience and Remorse, that sleep not, seem To sting when waked and haunt their every dream. CANTO SECOND Through Arden's pile the lighted tapers blazed, The sound of mirth and revelry was raised, And in the mazy dance light bounding feet The sprightly measure of the music beat, The song, the jest, the laugh, the bowl flew fast, And grey-haired Time smiled gaily as he passed; And ‘joy to Arden and his bonny bride!’ Was hymned by joyous tongues on every side; And oft they pledged the fair in sparkling wine, Inspiring wit that better seemed to shine. And there were lovely maids that blushed to hear The grateful praises whispered in their ear; And undisguised, love mingled with the rest,— A welcome, nor an uninvited guest; And there were beating hearts with rapture filled, And throbbing pulses that with pleasure thrilled, And eyes that shone with flames they could not veil, And tongues and lips that oft confirmed the tale, Or strove the avowal but in vain to shun, And all were happy—pleasing—pleased—but one! Clad as a mourner in a sable suit The stranger stood—pale, motionless, and mute, Nought could divert his glaring eyes aside, That gazed reproachfully upon the bride. In vain her supplicating glance she raised; Unmoved, immovable he sternly gazed; But when she wildly clasped her hands of snow He turned aside in pity to her woe. Still where he moved all gaiety was crushed, The dance was ended and the song was hushed, And if, perchance, the speaker's glance had caught His countenance, with woe and fury fraught, He smiled no more—his face unconscious took The gloomy semblance of the other's look, His speech was checked as sudden as his glee, Or ended in the whisper—‘Who is he?’ 'Twas Ulric, on whose brow a sadder shade Half mourned the gloomy change his presence made, And while the dulcet sounds of music stole So soft, so sweetly o'er his stormy soul, His heart half softened, and his fury soothed, As ruffled waves by oily drops are smoothed, Inly he shuddered at himself, who stood To end the scene of happiness in blood! But when he pondered on his own sad fall, That left him dark and lone among them all, Or looked on some exulting at his cost, And revelling in joys himself had lost, Then roused the slumbering Demon in his breast, And mad designs that scarce could be repressed, As suddenly, he laid his eager hand And grasped impatiently the starting brand. Thus terrible he stood, when Arden pressed To view the figure of his stranger guest, And while in that stern countenance, with dread, The well-known features of the Chief he read, A damp, chill shuddering shook his startled frame, His tongue, too, trembled while he spoke the name, And his heart sank as his fixed eye-balls viewed The frowning look and threatening attitude. ‘Yes! I am he—deserted and despised, Whose heart is tortured and whose head is prized! Yes, I am he—your treachery has driven From all his kind—hope, happiness, and heaven; But shall you not sit mocking at my fall, Nor hold your banquets in my father's hall; Nor shall you revel in her beauties now, Nor glory in the false one's broken vow. No! I will act, in just resentment strong, As late avenger in each former wrong; Requite all injuries received of old, And match the justice man has dared withhold.’ Thus spoke the Chief, and from his girdle drew His brazen bugle-horn, and loudly blew: Shrill rung the strain, and instant from without, Responsive rose the impatient robbers' shout, Fierce rushed the ruffian band, and burst within, With mingling curses and terrific din, Like straining bloodhounds round the Chief they stood, And watched the signal for the work of blood. Brandished aloft the robbers' weapons gleam, And, flashing, glance beneath the taper's beam, While partially the broken rays illume Their rugged features, shaded by the plume That o'er each brow imparts a deeper gloom. Pale—trembling now, the ladies start aside, And crowd in fearful groups around the bride; The guests recoil afraid—e'en Arden shrinks, And on his knee a faltering suppliant sinks: ‘Oh! I have wronged you, but in hour like this, When sparkles at my lip the cup of bliss, Can you behold it yet untasted shine And dash it down?’— ‘Thus was it dashed from mine; Thus did you blast each lingering hope, and steal The last sole joy my wounded soul could feel, And thus will I your budding hopes destroy And blight them ere they ripen into joy. Oh, Arden, you have driven me to deeds At which my soul revolts, my nature bleeds, For you have severed the last tie could bind My soul in amity with humankind. Stripped—exiled—deserted—under ban— In you I still possessed one friend in man; But, lo! your treachery has crowned my fall, Stolen my last friend, and made me foe to all. Then look around once more—behold these charms, And that fair bride, now severed from your arms; Mark the late partners of your joy and see The broken wreck of thy last revelry; And this, the scene of thy rejoicings view— Survey all these, and bid them all adieu, And tear from off your brow the bridal wreath Before you meet the cold embrace of death!’ But ere his lingering arm could speed its aim, The trembling Adelaide affrighted came; Pale was her cheek, and tear-drops glistened there Bright as the gems that sparkled in her hair, And her clasped hands expressed a deep distress That ill accorded with the bridal dress, As thus in speechless agony of grief She bent her lovely form before the Chief. On Ulric's brow, each trace of fury flown— The gloominess of grief remained alone. He dropped the fatal point—who could forbear When tears implored and beauty urged the prayer? But still internally his stubborn pride Strove the best feelings of his heart to hide, And still each pang he struggled to conceal, As though he deemed it weakness thus to feel. But Nature triumphed! Though he turned aside Abrupt, his changing countenance to hide, From his dark eyes unwonted tear-drops rushed (So from the smitten rock the waters gushed); Beneath his cloak he sought the drops to shroud, But bursting sighs bespoke his grief aloud. ‘Oh, Adelaide! a joyless wretch I came, With frenzied purpose and infernal aim, To 'venge the falsehood that had caused my woe, And make thy blood as now thy tear-drops flow; But, lo! my heart forgets not that it knew The time, alas! it only throbbed for you, And, loving yet, rebels against my will, And prompts my faltering tongue to bless you still. Be blessed! Forget my love! The solemn vow That with my wretched heart is broken now. But, ah, to you may ne'er its sorrows reach, And I alone feel wretched in the breach; Forget all these! with that unhappy man Who bids you still be happy—if you can!’ Faltering she answered, but her faint reply Was drowned amid the robbers' angry cry, Whose scornful words strove vainly to condemn The Chieftain's weakness as unknown to them; And one more daring seized the kneeling bride— ‘Be this my prize! I claim her first!’ he cried. Surprised and awed, accustomed to his sway, They loudly murmured, but they still obey; Amid them all he stands, unhurt, alone, And all the band submit and crouch to one! ‘'Tis vain. No longer I pretend to wield The sword of justice, or the weak to shield, Or hurl that vengeance which the Final Day More surely and less blindly will repay. Enough! From all your oaths I now release; And this, my last command—Depart in peace. Your Chief no longer, in some private cell, Far from the busy haunts of men, I'll dwell, And strive to wash my many crimes away By sorrowing nights, and sighs and tears by day. Would that ye also left your crimes, and then Were less a scourge and curse to better men!’ As thus he spoke, in bitterness of heart, He, sad and sorrowing, turned him to depart; But, sudden bursting in the hall again, Came Wolf, and led a strong and armed train. ‘Behold our prize! Yon sable plume behold! Seize—seize him! for his head is gold! On, comrades, on!’—At once the robbers poured And seized the Chieftain ere he gained his sword. One only dared to strike in his defence, And smote the assailant, but at life's expense. The Chieftain saw and seized the falling brand, And broke resistless from the circling band; Then, as a lion, when the foes surround, Springs on the first and tears him to the ground, Headlong he rushed—death followed on each stroke— And felled the foremost till the sabre broke. Thrice Arden joining in the unequal strife Had stayed the steel that pointed at his life; But soon a sword too keen—too surely prest— Escaped his zeal and gored the Chieftain's breast. He staggered—sunk—and on the bloody ground Still feebly combated with all around, Then rose again and rushed against the foe— Another effort and a final blow;— With steady purpose and unerring hand He raised the fragment of the faithless brand; On Wolf with violence he pressed the blade, And lifeless at his feet the robber laid! Again he falls—faint, wounded, and beset, He fights exhausted but undaunted yet. More close the circling foes assault him round, From every side he feels the biting wound; Blade after blade the crimson current drinks, And steals his strength—he struggles—wavers—sinks! The broken sabre quits his feeble grasp, And life just seems to hang upon a gasp. Now he can fight no more, but, doomed to die, Gazes on his murderers with angry eye: Loud swells the shout for triumph vilely won, The prize is conquered and the deed is done; But other spoil invites—they turn to where Bright diamonds sparkle 'mid dishevelled hair Blest if no violence should take them there! In vain they kneel, and gentler pity claim, They plead to those who never knew the name. The robbers seize!—but, bursting from the wall, What sudden blaze illuminates the hall? It is the taper, or the robbers' aim, Has set the lighted drapery in flame? All through the robbers burst their fearful way— Perhaps death to go—but never death to stay! ‘Who fired the curtain? 'Twas a foolish deed! Molest them not, but to the cave with speed. Haste, comrades, bear yon body in your arms, Ere yon red blaze the villagers alarms!’ They seize the Chief unconscious of his lot, And wildly hurry from the fatal spot; And wondering villagers collect the while And gaze in terror on the burning pile. With rapid stride the blaze ascends on high, Now gains the roof and blushes in the sky; Each space, each chink, the fiery guest betrays, And through each window bursts the angry blaze, And rocking walls and burning beams impend, And crackling timbers with a crash descend! Downward they hurl, still blazing as they go, And fall, half-smothering the flames below! And lo! the brightest and the last of all— One turret trembles at its threatened fall; In vain through many a long and stormy age It braved the battle and the tempest's rage, Now o'er its frowning crest, that once so proud Looked down exulting o'er the misty cloud, The roaring flames and spiral blazes curl, And fire and smoke in mingled eddies whirl;— It shakes—it totters on its shattered base, And headlong falls with brave Glenallan's race. Soon will the nettle's humble top alone Look proudly down upon the fallen stone; And waving grass will flourish o'er the head Of him who scarcely lingers from the dead. CANTO THIRD Loud crows the cock—the peasant's slumbers cease! He wakes to days of innocence and peace; And with the lark that leaves the yellow corn Begins the matin song and hails the morn, While peering in the East, the rising sun Proclaims a bright, a new-born day begun; Aurora, blushing, hails the god of day, Who comes to kiss the glittering tears away; And opening buds and flowers expanding rise, And blush with colours borrowed from the skies. All wakens into life—the chiding hound And huntsman's horn awake the echoes round, And rouse the stag who listens to the strain, Then starts away and bounds along the plain! Men, horses, hounds, the flying game pursue, And ruddy health attends the happy crew. Where'er they fall the pleasing rays adorn— Now gild the stream, and now the waving corn, On all they glow;—but ah! where'er they strike They gild the evil and the good alike; The cloud that's golden when beneath the ray Is gloomy, dark and ugly when away. The beam that played upon the rosy bower Now gilds the summit of yon dungeon tower, And, through the close and narrow grating cast, Is hailed by the sad captive as his last! With that first ray the fettered Chieftain rose From fearful visions and disturbed repose; For him that sun would never rise again. Towards the grate he dragged his heavy chain. ‘This is my latest day, but ere I die, Fain would I gaze upon the earth and sky. Oh, heavens! how lovely is the new-born day! All Nature smiles, all beautiful and gay, Oh, in my youth, what fairy dreams of bliss Would Fancy picture on a morn like this! When like the buds I felt my soul expand, And pictured love and joy on every hand! When ne'er expecting aught less fair to find, I ope'd my heart in love to all mankind. ‘Ah! thus my fancy in my youth's gay morn Would her bright images of life adorn; Yea—like yon sky-lark that so gaily sings To heaven, aspiring on exulting wings— Would leave this world below and wildly soar To add to that fair heaven one heaven more; Life, like yon firmament she drew serene, Nor clouds obscured—nor storms disturbed the scene, And Friendship, Pleasure, Love, and Hope, were given To shine as stars in her ideal heaven! 'Twas all delusion! What are earthly joys But pleasing dreams our wakening destroys; And I have wakened, yea, to scenes of pain That make me wish that I could dream again. ‘Love is a madness—happiness a dream! And Hope and Friendship things that only seem. I've tried them all, and found them all untrue, And long have bid them and the world adieu; I loved it once, and prized its idle state— Suspected—then despised—and now—I hate!’ Thus spoke the Chief, but now in angry tone He spoke aloud—‘Why am I here alone? Why am I fettered when all else are free, And left to act their crimes at large but me? And greater villains that deserve my fate’— He turned indignantly and left the grate, Where he could see the swallows round him skim, And all in happy liberty but him. E'en thus, a wild enthusiast in all The Chief had been, and it had shed his fall. One he had known—his honourable sire— Such as his heart could cherish and admire, And loved to imitate, and Fancy dressed And with his virtues painted all the rest— Free, open, generous, gay, noble, young, Assailed too often by the flattering tongue; Affected love and proferred friendships fell, He prized too highly and believed too well; Beloved, he thought, by all, and loving too, These were the best, the happiest days he knew; Blest in his blindness! For how blest is he Who sees the world as it ought to be; Who, pressed by want, or misery, or woe, Still finds, or fancies, friends, but not a foe, And with Despair successfully can cope, Buoyed up by frail but never-failing Hope, Though never realized, and blessed at last If the veil drops not and reveals the past. Not so with him, for soon as fortune wore A frowning look, and friends were friends no more, But shunned his woe, not blushing to condemn The very faults that had exalted them; Or rising undisguised as open foes, Scarce deigned to hide they triumphed in his woes; But hailed the fall that left him now too weak Just vengeance for their injuries to wreak! Then from his cheated eyes the film soon cleared, And all the world's deformity appeared. Once he had loved it, and too highly prized, But now as strongly hated and despised He fled its vile contagion with speed— A misanthrope—nor more in word than deed! By Flattery, that with the world began The woes, abasement, and the fall of man; That, demon-like, still ruins and beguiles, And while betraying each sad victim smiles! Thus felt the Chief. How hapless are the great, If such their evils and too oft their fate. Truth they ne'er know divested of disguise, And scarcely see but through another's eyes;— But, knowing other men—and, what is more, Knowing themselves—how happy are the poor; Too oft condemned for vices they have not, And scarce allowed the virtues they have got; None ever flatter them—nor oft they fail Betrayed by vanity or flattering tale. But to my theme. The Chieftain turned away As though he sought to shun the light of day. On his hard couch he threw his limbs once more, All racked with pain, or stiff with clotted gore; And while across his pale and varying cheek The sudden throbs of anguish seemed to speak, His wild and working brain appeared as fraught With far more keen and agonizing thought; Remembrance, perhaps, of gay and happier times, Linked with the memory of after crimes, And keen remorse that shudders o'er the past, With deep regret for joys that fled too fast, And doubtings of the future and his fate, And all the sorrows of his present state, With all their varied pangs, were mingled there, Nor sunk nor settled, but in calm despair. Oh, who can speak that wandering of thought, When, with all varied recollections fraught, In wild confusion the bewildered brain Now turns from woe to joy—from joy to pain; Now sinks and saddens over present woes, And now o'er scenes of former pleasure glows; Regretting joys and means which, once possessed, If better known or valued, would have blessed; Thus boiled the Chieftain's brain, and pondered o'er The scenes of long-lost happiness once more. Yes; 'twas the mansion of his sires he eyed, Such as it had been in the days of pride, Though many a lingering, long, and painful day Since he had left its roof had passed away; Yet could not time nor misery efface Of former joys the long remembered trace. No; though each hope of happiness had flown— Had left the bitterness of life alone; Though deeds of guilt his soul had long bereft Of the last solace to the wretched left; Undimmed the retrospect of happy years Shone bright through times of misery and tears; And oft, as in delusive dream restored, We greet departed friends we've long deplored, His mind forgot the sense of present pain, And dreamed o'er scenes of happiness again. E'en now, abstracted from his present state,— His pain, misfortune, and impending fate,— His mind retraced the ever-pleasing scene Of things, times, pleasures, feelings that had been. But, suddenly, a harsh discordant sound Roused him to consciousness of things around. He started, and strove vainly to recall The fleeting phantoms on the dungeon wall, But they had fled in air like parting breath, And left him with the Messenger of Death! With calm, unaltered voice, unvarying cheek, The fated Prisoner was the first to speak: ‘I know thy message—no unwelcome one To him whose days of misery are done. The time is gone such tidings could impart Reluctance, grief, or terror to my heart. Too long the cup of bitterness I've quaffed Without one hope e'er mingled in the draught To quit this wretched being with regret; And as for Death—why, I can brave him yet;— Nay, as an Angel—Harbinger of Peace— I'll hail the Spectre if he bring release!’— ‘Enough!’— Harsh as the grating hinge, and rough, Responsive rung the keeper's loud ‘Enough.’ Surprised, he turned again—ne'er till that hour, Of all the inmates of that gloomy tower, None had he known who gazed on Death so near With such rejoicing and so little fear. But, lo! he started as he seemed to trace Some dear remembrance in the captive's face; Swift to embrace the prisoner he flew— ‘Oh, heaven!—my lord—my master—is it you?’ Up rose the Chieftain with a sudden start, That voice had struck upon his throbbing heart! ‘Ha! Is it Donald! or a mocking dream? Are these things so, or do they only seem? Am I awake? The gaoler bent the knee— ‘Alas, no dream—dear master, I am he!’ All pride forgotten quite, the Chieftain pressed His former steward warmly to his breast, But rudely bursting from the Chief's embrace He paused, and wildly gazed around the place. ‘Oh, I forgot you lingered here to die. Behold the keys! Oh, take them now and fly: My clothes, perchance, will happily disguise And shroud your person from more careless eyes. For, ah, though Arden kneels before the throne, I fear 'twill change the punishment alone— The gibbet to the block—our nobles hate The noble soul that made you once so great. No hope remains but this—let me implore Your speedy flight.’ The Chieftain frowned—‘No more! Perchance 'tis justice dooms me now to bleed, And you would save me by a traitor's deed! When have I fled my foes or valued life, Or shrunk when Death menaced me in the strife? Perhaps one more in love with life than I Would hail the terms, but now I scorn to fly! Beside your hate and punishment, too sure, Would leave my safety still too insecure.’ Proudly he answered—‘Have you then forgot The loathsome dungeon—once my cruel lot To linger there a sad and joyless time— Misfortune's punishment, and not for crime? Your bounty freed me thence, and now 'tis due From gratitude to pay the same for you. And, ah! my life I cheerfully resign, For many woes—few comforts—now are mine! Oh, add one more—O, hark! The warning bell, One short hour more, it tolls your parting knell. I pray!—I kneel!’— ‘O give me not the pain,’ The Chieftain said, ‘to see you kneel in vain. I am resolved—a solemn oath I swore To leave these hated walls with life no more. That oath I keep; but, would you glad my soul, Bring me a dagger or a poisoned bowl. This last request I urge with latest breath, Oh! spare your Chief an ignominious death!’ ‘Alas, I know Glenallan's word too well To hope to move you now, my Lord—Farewell! I have a dagger, but my heart shall feel Its deepest reach ere you shall use the steel. What! can no other hand but mine be pressed To lend the dagger for my Patron's breast! Ah! it must be! once more, my lord, adieu; My death alone surrenders it to you!’ He raised his hand, but with a sudden clasp The Chieftain caught the dagger in his grasp. ‘Ha! Now I laugh to scorn the feeble chain, The guarded fortress shall not e'en detain. In vain shall vengeful crowds impatient flock To see my head fall streaming from the block; Exulting peers shall not behold me fall, And for their tortures I elude them all. Dungeon and fetters may the limbs control, But what can fetter or confine the soul? Now I am free—live to behold me die, And tell the world Glenallan scorned to fly; And tell with all the courage of a friend No sign of weakness marked my latter end. Live, I command you! say to Arden this— I thank his zeal and pray heaven send him bliss; Tell him to love’—it died upon his tongue, The gaoler's hand in agony he wrung. Each strove to speak, but wept, embraced anew, They only in their hearts could say—‘Adieu!’ Thus had they lingered, but the distant sound Of hurried footsteps broke the silence round. Still nearer comes the noise—they rush apart, A moment more, he aims against his heart— 'Tis missed—he strikes again—too sure the aim— The deathless spirit quits its mortal frame, That still and silent lies amid its gore, And tells to all—Glenallan is no more! Again the bolts recede, the jarring din No more disturbs the prisoner within; He wakes no more, nor can that sound impart One quicker throb of terror to his heart; Too late the lingering voice of mercy calls, And ‘Pardon!’ ‘Pardon!’ echoes to the walls. He hears it not—nor would the tidings give More joy, perchance, or pleasure did he live. But o'er his body hath he still a friend, Who seems in silent agony to bend. All knew his crimes too well, and some had wept The loss of friends where his revenge had swept, But Arden weeps his breathless body o'er, And Donald's tears are mingled with his gore; Together now they pour the sorrowing sigh, Nor let him quite unwept, unpitied die!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPENDIX J. H. REYNOLDS'S CONTRIBUTIONS TO THE ‘ODES AND ADDRESSES TO GREAT PEOPLE’ (1825) LINES TO MISS F. KEMBLE ON THE FLOWER SCUFFLE AT COVENT GARDEN THEATRE BY CURL-PATED HUGH Make a scramble, gentlemen—make a scramble.’ —Boys at Greenwich. Well—this flower-strewing I must say is sweet And I long, Miss Kemble, to throw myself considerably at your feet; For you've made me a happy man in the scuffle when you jerk'd about the daisies; And ever since the night you kiss'd your hand to me and the rest of the pit, I've been chuck full of your praises! I'm no hand at writing, (though I can say several things that's handsome); But that ignorance, thank my stars! got me off, when I was tried for forging upon Ransom. I didn't try to get the flowers, which so many of your ardent admirers were eager to snatch; But I got a very good going chronometer, and for your sake I'll never part with the watch! I've several relics from those who got your relics—a snuff-box, a gold snap; A silver guard and trimmings, from a very eager young chap; Two coat flaps with linings, from a youth, who, defying blows, And oaths, and shoves, was snatching at, and I'm sorry to say, missing, the front rose! One aspiring youth out of the country rushed at the wreath like a glutton, But he retired out of the conflict with only a bachelor's button! Another in a frenzy fought for the flowers like any thing crazy But I've got his shirt pin, and he only got two black eyes and a daisy. The thought of you makes me rich—Oh, you're a real friend to the free trade; You agitate 'em so, and take their attention off—If you'd keep farewelling my fortune'd be made. Oh! how I shall hate to make white soup of the silver, or part with anything for your sake! I'll wear the country gentleman's brooch, on your account it's so very pretty a make! I didn't get a bud—indeed, I was just at the moment busy about other things: I wish you'd allow me to show you a choice assortment of rings— You understand the allusion; but I'm in earnest—that's what I am; And though I'm famous a little—domestic happiness is better than all fame! Well—you're going over the water—(it may be my turn one of these days); Never heed what them foreigners, the Americans, says! But hoard your heart up till you come back, and if I luckily can Scrape up enough, you shall find me yours, and a very altered young man!</field>
   </doc>
</add>