<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Doubleday, Thomas, 1790-1870</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Doubleday, Thomas, 1790-1870</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">doubleday thomas 1790 1870</field>
      <field name="author_text">Doubleday, Thomas, 1790-1870</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1810's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.1109.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1818</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466594</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Sixty-Five Sonnets ; With Prefatory Remarks on the Accordance of the Sonnet with the Powers of the English Language: Also, A Few Miscellaneous Poems [by Thomas Doubleday</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Sixty-Five Sonnets ; With Prefatory Remarks on the Accordance of the Sonnet with the Powers of the English Language: Also, A Few Miscellaneous Poems [by Thomas Doubleday</field>
      <field name="title_facet">sixty five sonnets</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">sixty five sonnets</field>
      <field name="title_text">Sixty-Five Sonnets ; With Prefatory Remarks on the Accordance of the Sonnet with the Powers of the English Language: Also, A Few Miscellaneous Poems [by Thomas Doubleday</field>
      <field name="year_display">1818</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1818</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1818</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466594&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466594&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Doubleday, Thomas, 1790-1870&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;doubleday thomas 1790 1870&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Sixty-Five Sonnets ; With Prefatory Remarks on the Accordance of the Sonnet with the Powers of the English Language: Also, A Few Miscellaneous Poems [by Thomas Doubleday&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;sixty five sonnets&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1818&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1818&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Doubleday, Thomas&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1790&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1870&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Sixty-Five Sonnets&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;With Prefatory Remarks on the Accordance of the Sonnet with the Powers of the English Language: Also, A Few Miscellaneous Poems [by Thomas Doubleday]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Baldwin, Cradock, and Joy [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1818&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp1156&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;124 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Sixty-Five Sonnets&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;With Prefatory Remarks on the Accordance of the Sonnet with the Powers of the English Language: Also, A Few Miscellaneous Poems [by Thomas Doubleday]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 95 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter including prefatory remarks omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SONNETS. I. They know not least, who have most need, of rest, That last, kind refuge from o'erwhelming woes; Thee I invoke then, Sleep, thou friend of those By ill on ill, and wrong on wrong oppress'd, The happiness that sometime I possess'd, Though now bereft me by the craft of foes, Return in pitying visions of repose, And bid me for a time again be bless'd; The while thou mak'st their waking conscience see Crimes that the noise and glare of day can hide; Yes, when that Judge impartial giveth thee O'er his eternal balance to preside, Repel th' o'erweenings of injurious pride, And what thou tak'st from them restore to me. II. Son of the earth, whatever thy degree, Placed in this changeable and troublous sphere, Fix not thy heart on aught that passes here; Neither permit thou unenjoyed to be The few propitious minutes as they flee; Pleasure, because it will be quickly gone Must still be promptly seized, or left alone. Despair shall lay his iron hand on thee! Smile when thou may'st, but hope not it can last. The northern Empress, as the storm drew on, Amid the snows her icy palace placed, A work perfected but to be undone, Nor let the thought her glory overcast That it must sink before the coming sun. III. Attend then, and while lingers still the light O'er ocean, I'll describe her beauty's spells. Her bosom is the silver'd wave that swells In trembling heavings to the moon-beam bright; That cloudless beam her glance; her locks have quite The sea-thread's shine; her teeth pearl'd, tiny shells; The coral plant her lips, where raptured dwells The touch for softness, as for hue the sight; Her voice, her magic song, ne'er heard in vain, Soon chased the transient glooms that doubt would cast, Some white-arm'd sea-maid, pillowed on the main, When evening's crimson clouds are fading fast, Perhaps may pour forth a resembling strain, As her's may lure me and betray at last. IV. Sophronia, when, with lavish harp, I fling Thy beauty's praises to the spreading gale, Say, does my tongue, unmindful, ever fail The loftier graces of thy soul to sing? My love with fondness to thy form will cling, Yet, reverend, bends to bid each virtue hail, And, though he prize the soft, luxurious vale, Can path the heights of bright imagining. He is a wanton yet adventurous boy, With earthly wishes and a climbing mind, Tracking rich fancy's land with feet of fire; But thou would'st have him soar to seek with joy An atmosphere so subtle, cold, refin'd, That he must breathe in pain, and soon expire. V. That truth survives I know, for I am true; That love is more than name, for I adore thee; That it shall live, the flame I cherish for thee, My heart commands my willing tongue to vow. And is it strange I should confide that thou, Who bad'st me think thy heart my sole possession, Had'st made as sooth, as tender a confession, And look to have the precious token now? Nay, never say, 'twas folly to believe thee, Nor soon forget a jest as thou forgot. Let not a transient fitfulness deceive thee To stain thyself with falsehood's cureless blot; Nor think dissimulation can reprieve thee, For, cruel girl, I'll now believe thee not. VI. Still is this firstling love a welcome guest, Tho' pale, cold, sickly, as a spring-time flower, It tells the winter of my heart is o'er, And glad I hail the stranger to my breast; There may it rise, by sighing gales caress'd, Wooed often by the early sun-beams coy, And freshen'd with the softest tears of joy, Till worthy to her bosom to be press'd, She, whose bright glance, with playful witchery, First taught thy fair yet fragile stem to shoot. Thou graceful bud of promise! 'tis by thee I've hope of summer's richness, autumn's fruit, E'en though by suns too fierce should withered be Thy flower, or nipped by frosts thy tender root. VII. Sit thou with us beneath these summer bowers, Nor say we waste the day we give to wine— How ill such saws become that tongue of thine, To bathe our souls in sunny cups be ours. That we should taste all ecstasies, the powers Who gave the means had surely the design; The wildest sprigs our arbours well entwine, And variegate our couch the sweetest flowers. Look, where a tinted rose-leaf, midst our joy, Hath thrown itself into my brimming glass, To give the rich, red juice a brighter zest:— The minutes, thus, thou tell'st us we destroy In wild unthinkingness, are spent the best, Shedding a charm on all the rest we pass. VIII. How vain is human pride! Not stone and lime, Or brass, or marble (though the founder's name Or sculptor's, oft, is lost before the fame Of what he builded), sooner stoop to time, Than do those structures of the mind, sublime, Whence once, perchance, a nation's wisdom came, Or where undying glory seem'd to flame Upon the tripod of immortal rhyme! Ye lights o' th' olden time! now dimly seen, Still with the mist of ages more o'erspread, Scarce known, forsaken; like yon river's bed Your sacred pages to mine eye appear; The lonely chasm, with whiten'd fragments drear, Shows where the some-time mighty stream hath been! IX. Clelia, thy pillar'd form, supremely made, A marble structure, with those lamps of pride Which spread around a downy lustre wide, The polished hardness in their light allayed, What boots it, if, unseemly, to degrade Such loveliness, a soul shall there reside, Foul as the worship'd reptiles that abide Within some Indian temple's column'd shade? Ne'er, on thy heart's ungenial altar, fires More mild than those of rage or hate have lain: For young, adoring troops of fair desires, Its rites the black-robed, impious passions stain; And cans't thou think too, that my wish aspires To join thy madly idolizing train? X. Emma, to tempt thee forth this festal day The fields and skies have put themselves in trim; Full music stirs the woods, while swallows skim, Mixing, like dancers, in their gliding play. I bring a wreath, twined when the early ray First peep'd abroad and made the stars look dim, When dew fill'd every flower-cup to the brim, And birds, just roused, prepared the revelling lay. Come, deck thy brow;—delay no more;—ne'er beam'd Such general smiles to chide thy doubting stay: Thou mak'st me sigh those times are vanish'd quite, When, in the flower-crown'd troop that welcom'd May, To mingle was a sacred duty deem'd, And love's endearment a religious rite. XI. There are some tears that time can never dry; Deep, smould'ring griefs no weight of years can smother: Yet that these lids are moisten'd for another Need not excite in thee th' upbraiding sigh. There is no rivalship.—Believe me, I Regard that buried love but like the mother Of that I bear for thee;—for, were it other, No tear of mine should fall when thou wert by. No scorn of thee doth sully the pure brine, Which thinking o'er past years can ever make Steal on mine eye,—to fond remembrance waking; And, oh! believe, no other heart than thine Might bid me, thus, that buried love forsake, Which still I must deplore, e'en when forsaken. XII. A boundless love of heaven, in mild repose, Slumbers upon thy face; the gentle hair How meekly parted on thy forehead bare; Pure, as they ought, the ivory lids that close O'er those rich gems, where, when uplifted, glows A swimming rapture; the pale face, so fair In Grecian-moulded calmness! wants the glare Of lilies, softened like a faint tinged rose; Thy bosom heaves without an earthly stain; Those liquid tones, which languish on the ear, Sink to my heart;—there, ah, how sadly dear! For could my verse rise like Cecilia's strain, The hope to call were impious as vain, Such angel love from heaven to waste it here. XIII. Though flatt'ry whispers that I might incline Some high-born hand to point me to the road That leads to lofty honour's proud abode, And seat me there, and link itself with mine; And though she paint the glare of riches' shine Doubly illumed, reflecting honour's rays, The hoarse applauses, and the frequent gaze That wait the lordling of a noble line, Alas! 'tis all too poor to purchase thee! No, let the vain, the foolish, and the proud, Exchange their happiness for lures like this, And court the worship of a wretched crowd— Thou canst, alone, afford substantial bliss, And thou my honour, wealth, and pride shalt be. XIV. I will not praise the often-flatter'd rose, Or, virgin like, with blushing charms half seen, Or when in dazzling splendour like a queen, All her magnificence of state she shows; No, nor that nun-like lily, which but blows Beneath the valley's cool and shady screen; Nor yet the sun-flower that with warrior mien, Still eyes the orb of glory where it glows;— But thou, neglected wall-flower to my breast And muse art dearest, wildest, sweetest flower, To whom alone the privilege is given Proudly to root thyself above the rest As genius does, and, from thy rocky tower, Lend fragrance to the purest breath of heaven. XV. Deplore ye not his fate, though he hath dealt In woe, and often shed the bitter rain; He is not luckless though he may complain, And long with ill and poverty hath dwelt; The poet who would make another melt Himself must know well the dissolving vein, And pathos must be purchased still with pain; For he can ne'er describe who hath not felt. Misfortune's torrent, which no courage stems; Despair's stagnation, and distraction's whirl; Insults that fire, humilities that freeze; Are genius' elements;—her purest gems By such extremes are nurtured, as the pearl Itself is but the creature of disease. XVI. The stars are wandering o'er the fields of blue, While earth drinks freely of the cup of sleep;— But I have drain'd love's magic draught so deep, That sleep's is tasteless.—Emma haste;—each hue Is deepen'd, but not lost; these trees ne'er threw A stiller shade; no rude breeze dares to sweep Breathings from flowers which fragrant slumbers steep. —But, list!—more balmy than the odorous dew, Prelusive music of my queen's approach, Of promises of chasten'd raptures full, How soft the whispering voice and footsteps light On the awed silence silverly encroach:— The young enchantress comes, as wont, to cull Pleasure's pure flowers, of mystic power, by night. XVII. Once more that air—such sounds to peace engage The cares that threaten our most blissful leisure; Brightly the faded traces of past pleasure At the soft glow revive on memory's page. Wine of the soul! each sorrow to assuage, Let it flow, harmless, in no stinted measure: It is th' immortal drink,—the much-sought treasure, Can give again his days to hopeless age, And make the time-chill'd soul a youthful lover. Oh! while those strains my willing ears bewitch, What forms, half-shown, on glittering wings, pass over! Pour forth the measured stream deep, fragrant, rich; It is a grateful off'ring around which The shades of joys departed love to hover. XVIII. O woman, thou, who, for an hour of vanity, Oft doom'st another to an age of pain, To mar a heart and cast it back again Favours, soft creature, nothing of humanity; And know, 'tis only reasonless inanity To ask “what tie can bind thee to retain,” And say, “the bondage of thy rosy chain Can little harm the most unstable sanity:” For, as within the gentlest grasp continuing The butterfly assured misfortune brings, So love, alack! is such a tender minion, That if ye hold him, e'en in silken strings, Ye chafe the fragile plumage from his wings, And haply, too, for ever, lame his pinion. XIX. Though thou art cruel and thy scorn rejects me, Though thou art lightsome, and wilt feel no care What fate is mine, the restless love I bear And heed of thee from utter woe protects me; Tho' sorely grief may wear and pride may vex me, I ever will thy devious steps attend, And be, if not the lover, yet the friend, A right, from which no force nor craft ejects me; And when thy fortune's setting beams have left thee, Or gloomy gathering clouds bedimm'd their shine, I'll meet the envious fates that would have chafed thee, And from thy cheeks kiss off the pearly brine, For, oh! thy happiness shall still be mine, However of mine own thou hast bereft me. TO THE DUCHESS OF ANGOULEME. On its being said that she had adorned her chamber with tapestry representing the death of the Admiral Coligni, on the day of St. Bartholomew. That breast, where woman's rancour well unites With woman's folly, what? doth it not hide Fancy enough to paint their blood who died Struck for the cause in which it most delights; Justly, in sooth, thou enviest the sprites Of Charles and that proud matron homicide, To whom 'twas given to revel in the tide Drawn from Coligni's veins! But history writes; And bodying forth the pictures of her pen, Enwoven on thy walls, to the fell steel Thou seest the venerable warrior bow; Console thee then, and think that though to feel Thy harder fate denies as they did then, Thou shalt hereafter feel as they do now! XXI Quick, bring some wine; for as when ebbs the tide, Just like the river's bed are now our souls, Sordid and muddy, till inspiring bowls, Like the returning waves, from side to side, Spread the full, sparkling flow of pleasure wide; See, see, how brightly in the tinging stream, My pale cheeks flush and glow, my dull eyes beam, And in that glass alone I gaze with pride. Foolish Narcissus, o'er the fountain blue To pore, and nurse such fancies in thy breast; I ever shun'd the beverage cold, nor drew Weak watery pictures to disturb my rest; Still in the wine cup, to its promise true, I've found myself, and always thus been blest. XXII. With that soft bloom and dress of glossy green, Thou'rt like some half-blown apple-blossom fair; The bright and bashful beauties peeping there Just make us wish a little more were seen; Thine eyes two dew-drops, brilliant yet serene— What frown o'ercasts the sunshine on thy face? Is this a simile too common-place? Well then, thou art the Fairies' beauteous Queen; Yes, thou'rt Titania, as the Bard in glee Has drawn her; pure, unearthly, as if fed On flowers;—a pretty, conscious majesty Around thy small and dainty form is shed: O give thy love, I care not why, to me, E'en though I gain it with the Ass's Head! XXIII. Think'st thou no milder passion ever warms His bosom; that, although his years be few, As if besprinkled with the marble dew, It is insensible to love's alarms? Thou err'st; for know, that beauty's power disarms That loftiness of nature: he hath knelt To genius cloth'd in brightness, yea, can melt Before the chasten'd glow of virtue's charms: But angel, e'en 'midst angels, must she be, With bosom softer than the sacred dove, With glance like lightning in the summer's even, Who claims his worship for her deity. For sacrifice, so worthy thee, O Love, Tis fit the kindling flame descend from heaven! XXIV. Where yonder lilacs wanton with the air, And no autumnal blasts have blown to fade, If flowers thou seek'st a festive wreath to braid, Bend thy search thither, thou wilt find them there; Not in the arches of the forest, where The branching oaks extend unmoving shade; Of spring's minuter verdure disarray'd The earth beyond their twisted roots is bare; Save where perchance the hop, with tendril curl'd, Or ivy, string'd, may seek and twine around Some stems amidst the forest chiefs that tower:— So, in the mightier landscape of the world, The flowers of joy and love are seldom found At the stern feet of knowledge or of power. XXV. Pour, till the wine peep o'er its crystal pale, And pledge the falter'd name each deemeth best; Most of your loves are in their bud, and drest In comely smiles, and never felt an ail; Oh, my Miranda! yet I not bewail The troubled turmoils that our love opprest; By them was given that keener, finer zest Which can alone with our existence fail. Love is this purple stream; as cloying sweet As this, first summon'd from the bending vine, As little lasting in its tender prime, It is the trying struggles that refine And nurse a juice, for highest hearts most meet, Pure, sparkling, strong, a juice that smiles at time. XXVI. France, in thy bosom place some mountain flower, Whose unprotected and unshrinking form Can breast the sunshine or endure the storm, Still arm'd against the change of every hour; And whether suns shall smile or clouds shall lour, O may the favoring goddess Liberty Breathe on its hallowed leaf, and doom to be Imperishable by the blasts of power. Let not thine eyelids waste their noble dew Upon the cold and purple violet, Nor by th' avenging whirlwind prostrate, yet The stained lily pity, whose chang'd hue ('Tis with the blood of thine own children wet) E'en from thy breast its regal crimson drew. XXVII. Although the silent sadness of thine air, Thy mild blue eyes, to earth serenely bent,— (Eyes that soft, melting Pity might have lent, Or Resignation, dove-like virgin, wear); Altho' the prison'd ringlets of thy hair, In studied but yet modest ornament (The unobtrusive neatness of content), Thy cheek, one knows not if 'tis pale or fair; Thy plaintive melody of voice, but chief That evenness of soul, that seems to turn A placid eye on all, my soul so draws, No sigh of mine shall violate thy grief, For oh! so much I love to see thee mourn, That, for a world, I would not give thee cause! XXVIII. Far off the rook, tired by the mid-day beam, Caws lazily this summer afternoon; The butterflies, with wand'ring up and down O'er flower-bright marsh and meadow, wearied seem; With vacant gaze, lost in a waking dream, We, listless, on the busy insects pore, In rapid dance uncertain, darting o'er The smooth-spread surface of the tepid stream; The air is slothful, and will scarce convey Soft sounds of idle waters to the ear; In brightly-dim obscurity appear The distant hills which skirt the landscape gay; While restless fancy owns th' unnerving sway In visions often changed, but nothing clear. XXIX. Music, high maid, at first, essaying, drew Rude sketches for the ear, till, with skill'd hand, She traced the flowing outline, simply grand, In varied groups to grace and nature true; And this was Melody.—Her knowledge grew, And, more to finish, as her powers expand, Those beauteous draughts, a noble scheme she plann'd; And o'er the whole a glow of colouring threw, Evening's rich painting on a pencill'd sky, Tints that with sweet accord bewitch the sense, 'Twas Harmony: the common crowd, that press Around, prefer the charms these hues dispense, As they, chance-mingled, on the palate lie, To her white forms of undeck'd loveliness. XXX. Fill all your beakers to the very brim, And drink a measure to the absent fair; And who disdains to join the festive pray'r Neglect and sorrow be the meed of him. The soul that gives her eye's delicious swim Soft though it be, our happiness is there; And they who in the dotage do not share Their eyes or wits with wine or age are dim. Behold our vines that smile around; see where The loaded boughs with clust'ring fruit are crown'd; Yet these, without support and fostering care, A certain and a fatal lot had found, And all the inspiration that they bear With the weak stems been trodden to the ground. XXXI. These scenes, that are the dearest to thy heart, Domestic;—the white house; the garden, neat; The shingly walk, well-ending in a seat; The arbour, where a sunbeam dare not dart; The river, seen through where the branches part. Heard gently laving just beneath our feet, Beguiling with its sound the sense of heat, Or boiling down the mound that's built athwart; Use blunts their finer zest—quit them, and then Enjoy the welcome thy return receives, When all seems freshly sweet, and newly feels. Thou shalt see all; hear all; approaching men Whom the cur chides; the dripping water-wheels' Quick dash; the very chirping in the eaves. XXXII. My bowl's a cheerful, home-bred, rustic bowl, That hates the proud patrician wine to see, But hearty greets, with marv'lous open glee, Strong-bodied Ale's brown face and honest soul; And, in good truth, he is a mirthful fellow, And tells o'er all our morning's gallant sporting Through fields and woods; then laughs and talks of courting The bashful country nymphs, as we get mellow. We part in time he knows no tricks o'th' town, And freshly vigorous rise at peep of light, Now wine, who all restraints has pride in scorning, Full soon grows riotous and knocks you down, Gives you a tossing sickness through the night, Perhaps a quarrel to adjust next morning. XXXIII. Days of my childhood, when, where wild flow'rs grew, From morn I've stray'd till twilight gloom'd again, When I recall my long since pleasures, then So sweet, so pure, so simple, and so true, Mine eyes grow misty with regretful dew, To think that like a dream they're gone;—I yearn And sigh for bliss that never can return,— So lov'd when lost—and so unprized when new! And well may I weep o'er the joys that smiled Long past—well linger 'mid the times that were, I who retain the weakness of the child Without the simpleness;—my moments are As wayward, and as wasteful, and as wild, —But oh! not innocent, nor void of care. XXXIV. No walk to day;—November's breathings toss The vaporous clouds in masses; fitter suit The intercourse of minds, social dispute, And wit's pure fire purging the mental dross;— —So, come, my friend; let those delights engross The present hour; and when their voice is mute Then let thy mellow-tongued, persuasive flute, With its sweet utterance, well supply their loss.— Thou shalt have tea, not wine; wine shall not sing With syren pleadings to th' unfetter'd blood; Snug is the shutter'd room; the fire is good; Thy flute its tide of softest sounds shall bring: While quiet pleasure, with a halcyon's wing, Broods and luxuriates on the gentle flood! XXXV. This silent, awful cave, how dimly grand! Surely the mighty Ocean here has led Some nymph beloved, and, all to please her, spread These gorgeous carpets of the golden sand; Bright, watery mirrors; sea-plants green and red, In hues beyond the rose's flower or leaf, Has gemm'd these walls, these deep recesses plann'd; To hide his secret joys; perhaps her grief: These are not brine-drops trickling, but her tears, Nor could the wind so deep a sigh afford; But lo, how jealous of his bride adored Vex'd Ocean, pale with foamy ire, appears; Vain his alarms; she shall not change her lord For one still fickler to increase her fears. XXXVI. Lovers have still their mistresses array'd In every gift and virtue under heaven, And still the less they knew the more have given— Perfections that would crush an earthly maid! What, loved as soon as seen? I am afraid That with his own imagination e'en My sage, sagacious friend has vainly striven, And that th' excelling graces he has laid Upon this paragon, which gem her o'er Like dewy spangles on the downy leaf, May prove as transient, and deceive as much. Though smile I must, yet shall I share thy grief When all these charms,—as we have seen before, Fall off and vanish on the slightest touch. XXXVII. Her heart broke not; but had it for her weal 'Twere best. She breathes, and so do they who lie Tranced in obliviousness; whom pharmacy Can hurt no further if it cannot heal— Oh! see, how Sorrow hath the art to steal The essence that to life its value gives, Yet, as in mockery, still the victim lives, Like those, in restless sleep who move and feel; Poor earthly ghost! whose soul is in the grave; Whose eye no ray of hope e'er more can view; Thou mind'st me, when I look on thy distress, Of flowers that spring within a darksome cave, Sickly, devoid of odour or of hue, The forms of sweetness, faint and colourless! XXXVIII. Thine eyes, those stars, where once I might have thought My being's dearest destinies depended, Oh! frown not that with me their power is ended, That form, from Greece's fabled graces caught; That hue, in nature's delicate richness wrought, Where heavenly tints with heavenly fairness blended, Would seem an angel from the skies descended, Be they by others worship'd, others sought; For, that the gentle fibres of that breast Should ache, to hate or cold neglect a prey, Against the marble of this bosom press'd, Were most unnatural. 'Tis the better way That he thy love who never could have bless'd, Should want the inclination to betray. XXXIX. Those rural scenes that ever have been dear, Though now denied me, fill my fondest dreams: The silent breathing fields; the sportful streams To their own music dancing, which appear Pausing at times, the louder song to hear, Of birds more sportful still, 'mid dappled beams, In sunny woods, profuse; the lake that gleams With stretching lines of light, a mirror clear For bloom-deck'd Nature's face; the shadeless plain Heavy with heat, where, murmuring long, the bee Makes to the shame-faced flowers his courtship free: A landscape smiling at pleas'd heaven again; With humble sports and joys now lost to me, The peasant joys that pay no tax to pain. XL. A drowsy mist hangs heavy on the soul During her short and mournful sojourn here; Yet sometimes her dull vision turns so clear As if a glimpse of future life she stole: Had e'en our hopes by word or holy scroll Still unconfirm'd remain'd, need we to fear But that our race must reach some blissful goal Which shines beyond the tomb's confinements drear. Our frames seem heaven-design'd; waked by the touch Of Fancy's wand in Feeling's high-wrought hour, Or 'mid wild visions in Sleep's shadowy bower, Who but hath felt his earth-freed mind was such? And is it probable, an all-wise Power Denying more, would ever grant so much? XLI. Bright Queen of night's lone kingdom, high in air Thy silvery orb how have I loved to see, Nor dreamt that mighty potency could be In aught so mild, so peaceful, and so fair, Yet, harmless, as thou gild'st my Mira's hair, Or bid'st thy cold beams kiss her beauteous cheek, And look'st like her as radiantly meek! Too well with thine her empire may compare; For as thy influence the wild waters find And still submissive on thy state attend, While, to compell their pride, the angry wind, The nave of heaven, itself in vain might rend, So have her magic charms subdued a mind That tyrant violence could never bend! XLII. While Emma careless saw how much I loved, And met my passion with averted eyes, Listening reluctant to my vows and sighs, Through what wild dreams my busy fancy roved! The colder she, each vision brighter proved; But when, at length, propitious to my prayer, I won to answering smiles the yielding fair, Perversely then the glittering scenes removed; Thus, when Night frowns along the wintry skies, And sternly Frost maintains his rigorous sway, What thousand forms of silvery frost-work rise, With mimic towers and sparkling forests gay; But soon, alas! the fair illusion flies From the warm sunshine of advancing day. XLIII. Urge me no more, for know within this breast There is a gloomy and eternal void, Dark, undefined, uncertain, unemployed, With light unvisited, with joy unblest; An ill so strange, it cannot be exprest, Except by him, who, ever at his side, Beheld a fearful chasm still yawning wide, Grave of his peace, and bane of all his rest! Urge me no more; 'tis not for me to smile, Whom leagued mis'ries ever mock and goad; Whom quiet maddens; pleasure discontents; Whose pain, nor wit, nor beauty, can beguile; Whose wearied spirits just can bear the load Of life, without its cumb'rous ornaments! XLIV. Remember, if my wild and stormy soul Should chafe hereafter, as the ocean waves Ungovernable, when from forth their caves Swift rushing winds th' augmenting billows roll, That this impetuous mood thou didst extol And love, because with all thy sex to choose, It, ardent, deck'd thee in celestial hues, And then adored with passion past control: And think, though Venus from the sea arose (If aught of truth by ancient bards is sung), Yet in his rage when mighty Eurus blows And to the skies the boiling waves are flung, E'en she, all-conquering goddess, to repose The waters cannot charm from whence she sprung! XLV. Crito, how well thy boisterous mirth keeps under The modest men of wit, who must sit dumb; Thou heedest not the disapproving hum At thy forced jokes, but still, lest we should blunder, Out bursts thy laugh, as duly as the thunder, Like it, to tell us whence the flashes come, And then so fiercely shake thy sides at some, That how thy frame endures it is our wonder. The painter Zeuxis, ancient authors say, Was doom'd a strange and humorous death to know: For having drawn a woman old and gray, He with mad laughter brought the fatal blow; Crito beware! thou'lt conjure up, one day, Some stale, old, feeble jest to kill thee so. XLVI. When I saw Borrowdale, and wander'd where The savage rocks begin to beetle high, Proud, like that Titan race who scorn'd the sky, Uncouth, enormous, ragged, dark, and bare, And mark'd the desert heath-flower e'en despair To clothe the granite flooring grey and dry, Musing amid the fragments, heap'd that lie, Fantastic in eternal ruin, there, Methought that nature in her mood had shown, On this same spot how far creative chance Can soar beyond the reach of art, and 'mid Her labour, in a happy petulance Had her tired pencil at the canvass thrown With the same fortune that Apelles did. XLVII. From the unbarring to the shut of day, Aye, oft' times restless in the midnight blind, His loss I mourn; it lies upon my mind Like a thick mist, that will not clear away, But bodes and brings grief's showers. His was a sway Of soul so gentle, we alone might find, Not see its strength; a wit that, ever kind, Would spare the humbled in its freest play. A silent, boastless stream, smooth, clear, but deep; His mighty powers attired themselves so plain They drew no worship though they won the heart: Now he is gone, we waken from the sleep, But, as of visiting Gods the poets feign, We knew him not till turning to depart. XLVIII. I'll not believe that lovely Womankind Have hearts as treach'rous as their brows are fair; And that their breath, sweet as the summer air, Is false and perilous as the wintry wind; That charms inimitable are design'd To fill the hated office of a snare, And all our happiness and all our care Is but upon a bending reed reclin'd. For oh! 'twere pity, if, like yonder skies, Of whitest fleeces dash'd with fleecy gold, Or yonder rainbow, of a thousand dyes, When we inquire what 'tis such charms enfold, The worship of our fool'd, adoring eyes Should prove an aguish heap of vapors cold. XLIX. One noon, while shelter'd from the breezeless heat, I dream'd, when sleeping 'mid a waste of flowers, That, from their cells, bright, dwarfish forms, the powers Presiding here, tripp'd forth their guest to greet; Simplicity, health, peace, contentment, sweet, All who had banish'd from those quiet bowers The fierce and gloomier passions, 'mong the towers And strife of men, that I was wont to meet. Yet in the peaceful train an urchin, arm'd, Would threaten with his needly dart my breast, While smiling, they, as arch he look'd about him, Thus said and mock'd me when I seem'd alarm'd, “Love fear'd so now will soon be most carest And thou, like us, wilt scarce exist without him.” L. Oh! he is bless'd, and ten times bless'd, what though Steep'd to the very lips, and full of grief, Who, quite forsaken, free to seek relief, Amid the shades of solitude may go, And temper disappointment's bitter throe By memorizing every fitful scene, Where all his ills and all his joys have been; Till pleasure strangely takes the place of woe, Compared with him, who, fasten'd to a stake, Asks solitude in vain his grief to 'guile, Who, though his lacerated heart must ache Within his sore and shrinking breast the while, By an unfeeling, selfish world's mistake Is voted happy, and condemn'd to smile! LI. 'Twas here she slept,—beneath this branching shade; Here,—on this bank, with thick'ning flowers bespread; Here,—where mine eyes long linger'd, rivetted Upon the faint impressure still that staid; But, hither when, with morn, my footsteps stray'd, Each ingrate flower had lifted up its head, And every trace where she had been was fled; Oh! would that from this heart e'en so might fade The mem'ry of her form; that, long disused To happiness, my bosom might obtain Again the calm that it, 'ere while, possess'd; And life's first, fairest flow'rs, too rudely bruised, Lifting, like these, their slender stems again, Outgrow the traces of the ill that press'd. LII. Of nature if I ask or nature's laws, Or moralize on conquerors and kings, Or, balancing the tendencies of things, Construct a chain of consequence and cause, Or ever make a calculating pause To sum the profit that an action brings, Then out at once thy unrein'd laughter flings, Tickled to death by sages and their saws. And yet the very man that mocks at me, Whom paradoxes to derision move, Whose lip is still in scorn of system curl'd, Is votary of a strange philosophy, And preaches too, after his master, love, That there is but one woman in the world! LIII. Friends, when my latest bed of rest is made, No empty bowls must ring my funeral knell, But bumpers rouse the gay song's wildest swell, While soft you lay me in my vineyard's shade; And press the ripe grapes till they weep and aid The rites for one that loved them still so well; A goblet on my grave its place may tell; And thus would I be mourn'd, and thus be laid. My vines, close twining round, shall keep away The rains, for water ever pain'd my sight; Haply, as mild departs th' autumnal day, The nightingale, amid their clusters bright, May sit, and sweetly pour for him the lay, Whose song, like hers, was heard so oft at night. LIV. The heart that disappointments ever freeze And hard adversity hath made her own, Welcomes the gloom of surly winter's frown And is congenial with the chilly breeze; Though thou may'st wonder, it shall give me ease To mark th' unnumber'd, feathery store descend, And watch th' accumulating burthen bend The thick-clad branches of the leafless trees: The dark and pitiless storm, howe'er it blows, But imitates thy cruelty, severe, And minds me of thy love, cold as the snows And false as they, which, though they may appear Pure as the candor that the lily shows, Chill the warm touch, and turn into a tear. LV. Shade of my long lov'd Mira, if that e'er Departed souls again on earth might roam, Some vision of thy semblance sure would come This wither'd and deserted heart to cheer. And wherefore cannot such things be, when here, E'en when the animating flame hath died, Its gross and earthly vehicle may bide, A soul-less form, past joy, past hope, past fear, For though this woe-worn frame, as heretofore, To pass among the ranks of men is seen, My bosom is a dark, forsaken cave; Dank, healthless, silent, cold; where pleasure more Shall never dwell; where life hath only been; My spirit is inhumed in thy grave. LVI. 'Tis true her hazel eye, so gently mild, A gentler than itself hath haply seen, Her coral lips, with ivory between, So sweetly smiling, may have been outsmiled; Perchance, her nut-brown tresses, waving wild In many an artless ringlet, may bedeck The graceful roundness of a snowy neck, Than which, though fair, some fairer may be styled: 'Tis true my friend; but not more true it is Than that my Mira, still, of woman kind, Fixed in this heart, to me must dearest prove: And sickliness of fancy call'st thou this, Or imbecile fatuity of mind, Or devilish enchantment? No, 'tis love! LVII. Look, how the trumpet of the loud-voiced gale Has roused the waters from their sullen sleep; Swift rush the banded billows of the deep, While o'er them peers, with visage broad and pale, The moon, in sickly splendor; her black veil Of vapours, shifted by the winds that sweep Along the deep-hued azure, see her keep Her watch on high, list'ning the troubled wail, Viewing the billows heaving from their bed, As if they aimed the hurrying clouds to lave; Like fame presiding o'er the battling brave, She sits, still prompt her fullest light to shed On the proud crest of each ambitious wave That highest in the strife shall raise its head. LVIII. The tribes of earth, the dwellers in the main, Air's light inhabitants, at seasons own The sway of love; but in man's heart alone He holds, though oft unseen, continual reign; Like to that latent fire which will remain Secret, pervading all things, till 'tis shown By some collision, when the flinty stone Can make, in brilliant streams, its presence plain Dear to the flower, as is the cherishing ray, So love comes to the soul, in lustrous might; The plant, gay blushing, gladdens in the day; And should it be denied the influence bright, Will strangely wind a forced and crooked way, Striving to reach at length the needful light. LIX. Oh, could we on this night-wind, dearest maid, Seek some lone islet, with its silver rim Of beating waves, so not a bark might swim Thither our bless'd oblivion to invade; Tranquilly curtain'd in th' unknown shade, No hated chance our hallow'd loves to dim, While nature spreads us, in her choicest trim, Skies never cold, and bowers that never fade: There would our souls together dwell entwined, Bright as the flowers, and gentle as the air, Forgetting in our little world so fair, The rude and adverse one we left behind; Yet, should the thought of some steal o'er our mind, 'Twere but to wish them well, not wish them there. LX. Until the Fates, Anacreon sung, shall close My life, and brandish the abhorred shears; Though age's winter on this head appears In ever whitening and unsummer'd snows, I'll cherish here the sacred fire that glows, Nor blush to say that love my being cheers; For love adorns accumulating years, And is adorn'd, as moss becomes the rose. Grant, Venus, still thy smile; I'll worship thee, I turn me to thy glory, gently bright, That seems so mild, yet darts its beam so far, And recollect, well pleas'd, thou dost delight, And art, in two fold honour, held to be As well the evening as the morning star. LXI. Though she that was thy joy, thy life's sole light, Is snatch'd away for ever from thine eyes, And now forgetting, haply, in the skies Leaves thee to lonely and unstarred night; The bitter blow hath miss'd of half its spite, Grief her own visage, seeing first, denies; Thou canst not feel thy alter'd destinies, Nor for a little space believe them quite! I know too well how slow the shrinking heart Is to admit that overwhelming woe Which mortal bosom can but once sustain; Still some dim, lingering twilight will remain; As, when the sun's retiring rays depart, Darkness comes not at once, though daylight go. LXII. Few are the isles that Heaven has form'd more fair, Pouring more luxury of verdure o'er Than thine oft-sung Ierne; few where more Man's deeds have poison'd what was made so rare; Thy softest scenes a murd'rous aspect wear; We shrink disgusted from the recent gore, As, at the guilty streaks her forehead bore, Conrad turn'd shudd'ring from the bright Gulnare. Falsely, 'mid ornaments of tinsell'd show, Thy praiseful poets, in their flatt'ring strains, Have made the emerald's rich, unsullied glow, A type of thee with thy unwithering plains, They should have chosen the blood-stone, which would show At once the greenness and the sanguine stains. LXIII. “My roving friend, what! married after all?” “Aye, aye,” sighs he, “alas! 'tis but too true; A fluttering fly, to every flower I flew, From the low violet to the foxglove tall; The English rose's sweets at length will pall, To seek the lily fair to France I went, Ah! none but yellow lilies there they knew, Or painted tulips without juice or scent; No slender harebells I in Scotia spied, But, like their thistles, as I soon was taught, A pretty face and stout coarse form were blended; 'Mongst flowers of every clime I've roam'd with pride, Luckless at last in Venus' fly-trap caught, There may I linger till my life be ended.” LXIV. Say must I go, again to meet thee never, To hear, to touch, to gaze on thee no more? And from my all, the angel I adore, Must waves and wilds, without a hope, dissever? If this must be, give o'er the vain endeavour To couple consolation with despair, Where all is dark, which happiness and care, Which hope and fear, have bid adieu for ever! The joys thou speak'st, to thee so lovely seeming, Are but the friends that prosp'rous men await, And, while my paradise thine eyes were beaming, Officious throng'd to hail my blissful state, But now, past hope, past comfort, past redeeming, With thee they fly, and leave me to my fate! LXV. Poppies, that scatter'd o'er this arid plain, Display the barrenness ye cannot cure, Though little may your sickly flowers allure, Their juice deserves because it aids the strain, For not alone it lulls our harshest pain, While, in the dang'rous or th' indulgent hour, The Turk still seeks it, but its wond'rous pow'r Can bring to bear the poet's barren brain; And in blest service, like a Knight of old, It conquers but the monsters of the mind: Oh! poppy-flow'rs, as rude weeds round ye press, E'en you look beauteous, 'mong their colours cold; So, mid the prickly cares of life, we find The sweetest hours—those of forgetfulness. POEMS. ANACREONTIQUE. Fill high our bowls with potent wine, And prate no more of love to me; This goblet shall my mistress be, A brighter, sweeter far than thine! More lively white and pink combine, And this has charms will never flee; Then kiss your cups, with lips as free And ardent as I dwell on mine. Our gallant hearts, the wines that glow In frequent cups, shall ne'er appal; There is a land that takes, we know, A river, at a draught not small! And should the stream for ever flow, The thirsty sand would drink it all. SONG. Thou canst not chide my love away, So never task thy lip to frown; Whate'er that cruel tongue can say By those bright eyes is still undone: Ah! no; not e'en thy power can set This heart from its enthralment free; Nor think to teach me to forget, For I shall never learn of thee! If outcast I am doom'd to be, A wanderer this drear confine o'er, Oh! let my latest look of thee Be sweet as those that went before; I'll drink thy smile; I drank it when 'Twas poison! yes, 'twas rash and blind! But oh! to me, though fatal then, Past hope and help, it now were kind! ANACREONTIQUE. I'll taste thy wine if bright and strong; Trust me, wherever it may roll, Trace up the stream of joyous song, Thou'lt find its fountain-head the bowl; This is true juice!—now, by my soul, Which scorns the water-drinking throng, Castalia's waves may glide along Untouch'd; this cup is worth the whole: And wouldst thou have a strain of fire, I pray thee fill it up again; Nectar will make a bard divine, And, though by many a graver strain, Slack'd are the high chords of my lyre, They'll tighten soon when wet with wine! [A smile will often join and stray] A smile will often join and stray With tear-drops o'er the saddest cheek; A tear espouse at times the ray That from the sunniest eye may break. Though showers be soft, and beams be bright, Still more the plants enjoy the weather, When, in a coy and milky light, The beams and showers are mix'd together. From maiden's lids as they descend To nurse love's bud each gives its power; But when allied they fondly blend, They nourish best the blissful flower. Such moments I the dearest prize; And rapture seems to swim more near, When I behold, in trembling eyes, The marriage of the smile and tear. [I know thee well; at once the zest] I know thee well; at once the zest Of added wealth and soft desires Thou wouldst enjoy, nor thinkst the fires Of love alone can make us blest; While dowry, jewels, and the rest, May feast the eye when beauty tires; So, with the rose, thy wreath requires The marygold's refulgent crest. Gold pippins tempt thee still aside, From chace of her thou lik'st to rove; Choose prudent wisdom then for guide, But call not at his bower on Love: Men yet to pair have vainly tried Minerva's owl with Venus' dove. [I'll pledge thee, Mary, long and deep] “Jam bibe; formosa es: nil tibi vina nocent. “Cum tua præpendent demissæ in pocula sertæ, “Et mea deductâ carmina voce legis, “Largius effuso madeat tibi mensa Falerno; “Spumet et aurato mollius in calice.” I'll pledge thee, Mary, long and deep, And drink at once of love and wine, Aye, and the sacred cup I'll keep Unsullied by a breath but mine: And tenfold shall it fire my soul With inspiration sweet, to sip The noble liquor from that bowl Which once hath met thy dewy lip! Like wine our love may't be, the more We've drain'd the more we'll wish to drain; And may misfortune's heavy hour Ne'er spill the bliss betwixt us twain. While, true to thine, my lip I wet, A draught of Lethe may it be, Joys, sorrows, hopes, may I forget, And centre all my soul in thee;— And when thou'rt false to plighted love And feelst no more the mutual glow, A bowl of poison may it prove, That I thy scorn may never know! [When I shall sink in my latest sleep] “Sepulchri “Mitte supervacuos honores.” When I shall sink in my latest sleep, Let not my poor remains be laid Where yon cypresses funereal weep, Or the yew affords unwholsome shade; But let me rest in the well-known bowers Where life its choicest blessings gave, Where the scented shrubs and springing flowers May lend a grace to my humble grave. Place not a stone for him beneath, Be no memorial taken nigh, But let the gales of the spring-time breathe And the summer sun smile where I lie; And let o'er the spot my mistress dear Bend for awhile with dishevell'd hair, And give to the conscious earth a tear, 'Twill serve me better than pomp and prayer; For there nor baleful blight shall rest, Nor wicked dews be nightly shed, To fade the turf on my mould'ring breast, And mark the grave of the unbless'd dead! There shall nor brooding sprite be roused, Nor sullen ghost, untimely, roam, But I, to a hallow'd couch unused, Shall sleep the sounder laid at home! STANZAS. Yes, I have loved, like thee, what though I live in such wild waste of soul, And still at eve thou seest me go To join the dance or drain the bowl. These are to sorrow but relief, Nor show a mind without annoy; Wretches can revel; for the grief That poisons peace but maddens joy. This heart hath known the pain that wrings The hopeless. Though the name of her Now cannot make me shrink, nor brings My visage in one line to stir, Ere this, though now the time's gone by, That form, whatever joys might call, Though wine was free and beauty nigh, Still stood between and darken'd all. 'Tis past. Yet never thence infer, Albeit, in sooth I do not know If aught could draw a tear for her From eyes that once adored her so. That feeling hath expired, because In ready drops it will not start, For oh! 'tis keen as e'er it was, But sunk more deeply in the heart. E'en so. The grief that never dies Will, when the first wild gust is past, Retiring first from other's eyes, E'en hide it from itself at last; Close coil'd within the breast a snake, In growing torpor slumbering, Which he who bears learns not to wake, And which, unwaken'd, will not sting. [The bloody wreath that warriors wear] “Qualem si cuncti vellent decurrere vitam, “Et pressi multo membra jacere mero; “Non ferrum crudele, neque esset bellica navis.” The bloody wreath that warriors wear To us shall no ambition bring, But scented nard shall gloss our hair, And roses round our temples cling; The ringing goblet's call shall more Inspire us than the trumpet's sound; And for discolour'd fields of gore This juice shall flow our table round; Our flutes shall speak but airs divine That breathe of love; and, better far Than heroes, we'll devote to wine The pomp so misbestow'd on war. TO?. I may not kiss the drops away Which from thine orbs of softness fall, But ah! in vain my lips delay, For my sad spirit drinks them all. And dreary as a chill morn's showers On meads deep-drench'd with heavy dew, To me the flood of sorrow pours Forth from those clouded heav'ns of blue. Let a brief anger rather cast Its glance along my startled soul, There it some flower of hope may blast, But could not sadden thus the whole. They say, and I have deem'd it so, That women oft'ner weep than grieve, Yet, soften'd by the bitter flow, My heart still feels, nor will believe. STANZAS. Hid in the deep recesses of my soul Rests my fix'd scorn of faithless womankind, Increasing with the years which onward roll, The secret, o'ergrown passion of my mind. But ah! Elmira, of this breast forlorn 'Twas thou alone the glittering hope couldst be: Free from the least approach the jealous scorn Preserves secure my treasured love for thee. So the huge snake, which, dimly-volumed, lies In mystic watch, where Indian treasures sleep Deep in some dusky vault, from prying eyes And daring hands, the precious trust will keep. LINES WRITTEN IN A BURIAL GROUND PARTLY DESTROYED BY THE SEA. “But thou, thy very dust is gone.” Lord Byron. When thou to nature paidst the debt I saw that thou must die, And, if e'er my fever'd cheek was wet, I knew not till 'twas dry; But when I saw where the wave had swept, And heard the sea-mew shrill, My bosom choked and my eyes they wept, Though my heart felt lonelier still. I had often thought, nay, loved to think, Although the thought was vain, That when I of the cup of death should drink We here should meet again; On that alone my thoughts would rest, From the pangs of thinking free; Now all is drear within my breast As the deep that covers thee. I trusted that some time I should lie Beneath where now I stand; Where twice a-day now the wave leaves dry The still encroaching sand: And till I saw the Neptune steal Upon this changing shore, I knew not it was possible That I could lose thee more. Yet, though true is the grief that clouds my brow, And my eyes drop faithful brine, I had not lived to mourn thee now Had my love been worthy thine. The grief that lives, lives but to wane; And mine e'en yet may fade, As this sand shall lose my steps, which fain Would trace where thou wert laid. It would have seem'd a baser part Had the storms allow'd thee room, And the sorrow had left my fickle heart While fresh upon thy tomb; And I yet may join a heartless laugh, And thank th' officious tide, That hath blotted out thine epitaph, E're it told me how much I lied! Still, though pleasure ere long may expand her wing, And smiles relight my brow, Of this I am sure, the world can bring Nought so worthy love as thou. Though thy form may fade from my mem'ry quite, Or my tears refuse to fall, Thou art but like the heav'nliest dream of night, Forgotten first of all. THE LILIES OF LOWDORE. On Derwent I have spread my sail And view'd the jaws of Borrowdale, And, when becalm'd beneath Lowdore, Have turn'd me to the western shore, Where mighty Skiddaw, rudely bare, Rais'd high his ridgy back in air, Above his fellows, as when braves Leviathan the mountain waves. Yet nothing could the scene delight As did those lilies, lovely white, That, with their cups reclining, slept Where Granges' glassy current crept. Recumbent on the deep, clear waters, They look'd like Innocence' own daughters, Too pure and heav'nly-sprung for storms To agitate their tender forms. Amid surrounding mountains wild, In meek retiredness they smiled, Soft as the loves which poets prize Amid life's rude realities. Yes.—For that I have dream'd and sigh'd, I love ye, lilies, on your tide, Ye types of that same passion vain, At once our excellence and bane. Like ye, it only bloometh where The heart's pure tide runs calm and clear, And where the stainless flowers abound They still are on the surface found. There they adorn, however deep, The stream beneath, yet seem to weep, Howe'er the upward heav'ns may smile, Still pensive and reclined the while; And, 'mid their leaves, you still may spy Some tiny seeds of yellow dye, As Love, though ev'ry star may bless, Is jealous in its gentleness. But though it seemeth that of them A breath would break the fragile stem, When angry storms have swept the air They still are found unalter'd there, As though some watching sylphs were given To guard them by indulgent Heav'n, To shield them till the blast had blown, And save them from the thunder-stone. —Yet what the waters and the air Are bid, or else have learn'd, to spare, Can scarcely for a breath withstand The hostile touch of human hand. The leaves will fall, as when we shiver The infant ice upon the river, As little fitted to endure, As bright, as brittle, and as pure. And then the drooping bells that bear Enshrined in ev'ry leaf a tear, Though gemm'd with heav'n's own dew before, When violated, weep no more: But earthy ravage shrivels up, And feeds upon each snowy cup, And, as the shrunk leaves drop away, They wither with a dry decay. EPISTLE TO?. Though the deep snows are lying unthaw'd, And the chill blasts forbid us to roam, The season allures me abroad, Since it tells me my friend is at home. Then my limbs I will warmly enfold, And come forth, be the skies e'er so fell; Applauding the climate, though cold, Where friendship can flourish so well! Let thy hearth show a genial flame, Let thy wine sparkle bright as thy glee, And my comrade, in all but the name, Thy cottage a palace shall be! Nay, when Fancy is high in her fit, We'll scorn e'en a king on his throne, Like gods on Olympus we'll sit, And reign in a heav'n of our own! For what in this life shall compare (And surely this life hath its flow'rs), When Bacchus, the curer of care, Looks down upon friendship like ours? The worldly man's wine may be rare, But what's wine if th' enlivening part, If the relish, my friend, be not there, The relish that springs from the heart; For the joys of the palate and eye, Proud luxury trebly refined, All that power, all that riches can buy, Must yield to the feast of the mind; And heav'n, if my prayer thou wilt bless, May I never be destined to stay, Where to hollow and cold politesse True friendship is frittered away; Where Freedom his forehead must shade In the hood of Hypocrisy drest; Where aught by the tongue may be said, But the truth that's approved by the breast. Yes! my days may with anguish be fill'd, Yet may thrice treble vengeance be hurl'd, If I envy the soul that is chill'd By that numbing torpedo, the world. But poesy, best gift of all! That human enlink'st with divine! I would give this terrestrial ball That one spark of thy spirit were mine! Then, my friend, let us call up each scene Ennobled by poesy's strain, Where the sports of our childhood have been, Where the sports of our manhood remain. The hours when delight was in bloom, The moments when ecstasy shone, And picture the days still to come By the brightest of those that are gone! We'll toast the warm hearts that are here In friendship's invincible corps, We'll memorize but with a tear The long lost companions of yore. We'll drink to our damsels of old, We'll drink to our girls in their prime, To the fires of the past that are cold, To the loves yet unsullied by time. Nor need we, my friend, be dismay'd, Though Plutus his smile should refuse, While still we can call to our aid And Friendship, and Love, and the Muse; But, with juice of enspiritment rare, And with these our repast to control, We'll drown the foul harpies of care, And wash off their stains from the soul. THE END.</field>
   </doc>
</add>