<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Caswall, Edward, 1814-1878</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Caswall, Edward, 1814-1878</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">caswall edward 1814 1878</field>
      <field name="author_text">Caswall, Edward, 1814-1878</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1870's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.1482.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1873</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466818</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Hymns and Poems ; Original and Translated: By Edward Caswall ... Second Edition</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Hymns and Poems ; Original and Translated: By Edward Caswall ... Second Edition</field>
      <field name="title_facet">hymns and poems</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">hymns and poems</field>
      <field name="title_text">Hymns and Poems ; Original and Translated: By Edward Caswall ... Second Edition</field>
      <field name="year_display">1873</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1873</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1873</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466818&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466818&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Caswall, Edward, 1814-1878&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;caswall edward 1814 1878&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Hymns and Poems ; Original and Translated: By Edward Caswall ... Second Edition&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;hymns and poems&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1873&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1873&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Caswall, Edward&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1814&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1878&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Hymns and Poems&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Original and Translated: By Edward Caswall ... Second Edition&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Burns, Oates &amp;amp; Co.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Basil Montagu Pickering&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1873&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0678&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;xii, 496 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Hymns and Poems&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Original and Translated: By Edward Caswall ... Second Edition&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 334 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted; translations omitted; hymns omitted; verse drama omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DRAMATIC PIECES. ODES. POEMS Et tamen cum quiesceret corpus Mariæ, vigilaret animus; qui frequenter in somnis aut lecta repetit, aut somno interrupta continuat, aut disposita gerit, aut gerenda prænuntiat. And yet while Mary's body rested, her mind would still be awake; either (as is the nature of the mind) bringing back in dreams what she had been reading, or carrying on what sleep had interrupted, or doing things determined, or foretokening things to be done hereafter. —St. Ambrose, De Virginibus. DRAMA ANGELICUM: A MASQUE OF ANGELS BEFORE OUR LADY IN THE TEMPLE. ANTE TORUM HUJUS VIRGINIS FREQUENTATE NOBIS DULCIA CANTICA DRAMATIS. PRELUDE. An open Court in the Temple of Jerusalem surrounded by cloisters of white marble. In the centre a fountain playing. On the left, resting against a pillar, the Blessed Virgin Mary, as a child, fast asleep; at her side vases containing rose-trees in bloom, and delicate aromatic plants. Angels around keeping watch. Dawn slowly breaks. Distant chant of Priests. ITHURIEL.(Chief of the Angelic Guard). Comrades, our sacred charge, Who all night long upon this marble pavement, Like a pale lily bent, was pouring forth Her most ambrosial sighs into the ear Of her eternal Father, now at length Has yielded her young nature to repose. Morning returns emblazoning with gold Yon eastern pinnacle. The hideous storm Raised by the vagrant spirits of the night, Which seem'd to shake this temple to its base, Is past;—no cloud appears; And through the spicy air softly diffused A halcyon calm is basking, as becomes This day of our young Queen's Nativity, The seventh in its order since she came Immaculate into a world defiled. A day it is well worthy of observance Now as in after-time; and our custom Has been to celebrate it hitherto With song and festal show, in entertainment Of this dear Maid. Now, therefore, Azael, Most bright deviser of our pageantries, Say, what new mystery hast thou prepared For this auspicious morn, which thrills the world With life, and joy, and glad expectancy? Last year thine art was most felicitous, Bringing before our eyes, as I remember, The happy pastoral times; and setting forth, With infinite delight to this fair soul, As in a drama, Abraham's sacrifice Of Isaac on the holy Mount of Vision, Timely averted by an angel's hand. AZAEL. Dread Lord, our mystery of to-day attempts After the manner of a sacred masque, To represent by aid of a Procession, In contrast with unhappy Eva's fall, The glories of this heaven-created Child; Personifying the early Patriarchs, As we remember each in face and garb, While journeying on his earthly pilgrimage, Now in the groves of Paradise at rest. These, as they pass, in turn will homage pay To this new blossom of their ancient tree; Felicitating in triumphant strains The birthday morn of Her, in whom alone The hope of poor mortality is hid. All was prepared, and we were busy choosing Last night our parts, when of a sudden leapt The tempest down, and summon'd us away To the defence of this all-sacred head, From the satanic crew that strove so hard To sweep into the bottomless abyss Our Temple and its Treasure. ITHURIEL. It was well. First among all our duties was enjoin'd us, By Michael the Archangel, our high Prince, Ever by day and night with heedful watch To guard this paragon of innocence From her innumerable relentless foes Headed by false apostate Lucifer. This task ye well perform'd, Angelic powers: Exultingly I mark'd each several deed, While Hell in vain before your serried front Its nether depth upheaved. Now, therefore, go, Ye who this entertainment have in charge, And what remains complete with diligence; For I expect some princely visitors With the first slanting sunbeam, in high state Coming from bright Italia, to salute The Queen of Sion, and perchance to stay As your spectators. We, who here remain, Will sing meanwhile in this fair sleeper's ear Our birthday song of gratulation, Blending and parting in alternate strains. [Exeunt Azael and Companions. Angels' Birthday Song to Mary. Hail to the Flower of grace divine! Heiress hail of David's line! Hail Redemption's Heroine! Hail to the Virgin pre-elect! Hail to the Work without defect Of the supernal Architect! Hail to Her ordain'd of old, Deep in eternities untold, Ere the blue waves of ocean roll'd! Ere the primordial founts had sprung; Ere in ether the globe was hung; Ere the morning stars had sung! Welcome the beatific morn When the Mother of Life was born, Whom all lovely gifts adorn! What a thrill of ecstatic mirth Danced along through Heav'n and Earth, At the tidings of Mary's birth! How was Hell to its centre stirr'd! How sang Hades when it heard Of her coming so long deferr'd! Happy, happy, the Angel band, Chosen by Mary's side to stand As her defence on either hand! Safe beneath our viewless wings, Mother elect of the King of kings, Fear no harm from hurtful things! What though Eden vanish'd be, More than Eden we find in thee! Thou, our joy and jubilee! Enter Herald, with a banner inscribed Roma and surmounted by a golden eagle. HERALD. Most mighty Prince! Foremost among the Chivalry of Heaven! Know that the Angels of Italia, With their high Potentate the Guardian Of world-subjecting Rome, moved by report Of Palestine's new wonder, have arrived; And crave permission of thee to behold The world's young joy. ITHURIEL. They are most welcome here. Enter, in glistening apparel, the Tutelary Angels of Rome and other Italian Cities. TUTELARY ANGEL OF ROME (kneeling to Mary). Hail thou, of love and fear and holy hope Mother that art to be! Hail, woman blest Above all women! Mightier than all Before or after thee! Effulgent Mirror Wholly untouch'd by breath of primal sin! Brightness of light eternal! within whom Nothing defiled hath place. All beautiful! Lovelier than Cherubim or Seraphim! Surpassing all th' Angelic Hierarchies Temple and throne of blazing Deity! Praise, lustre, excellence, of humankind! Through whom celestial dove-like peace returns To the long-ruffled and disordered world! Who shalt on earth ineffably conceive The Lord of Heav'n. Hail, living Fount of Life! From whom the Maker of the Universe, The Father's consubstantial Word and Son, Shall into His eternal Person take Perfect humanity, thenceforth to be Inseparably His for evermore; So with a new regenerated race To fill our vacant thrones! Virgin august! As yet amid celestial sovereignties Only by dim anticipation known, But now, in thy predestinated time, Beginning partially to be reveal'd! [Laying his crown at her feet Never again since I have Mary seen Shall glitter on this humbled brow of mine Great Rome's imperial diadem; hers it is, And mine by right no more. Accept it then, Dear unexampled glory of the world! Unworthy to adorn thy sacred head, Hardly deserving at thy feet a place. ITHURIEL. Most noble Potentate, in the behalf Of this fair Daughter of Jerusalem And Queen of holy Sion, we accept Your loving worship; and the time shall be When Mary to your Rome a hundredfold This homage shall repay; if but aright I read the course of ages faintly traced In prophecy, or by conjecture weigh'd. And now, in grateful token of our thanks, I bid you to a Pageant, each and all, Prepared amongst us in a simple fashion For the diversion of this royal Child; Which presently commencing will conclude As we expect, ere the meridian sun Lies mirror'd on your Adriatic wave. ANGEL OF ROME. We count ourselves most fortunate; already Fame of your Mysteries hath reached our ear. AZAEL (re-entering). All is complete, my Prince: we do but wait For your commands. ITHURIEL. Begin then, Azael; While in their chalices are sparkling yet The dewdrops of the morn. AZAEL. Please you that we Awake our Lady first? ITHURIEL. Nay, as I think, Better she slumber on; for much she needs, After the rabid uproar of last night, Some genial balm. Nor will your Spectacle Less clearly pass before her inward gaze, Than if those sacred eyelids had unclasp'd Their golden fringe; finding an easy entrance, Beneath the semblance of a mystic dream, In that exact proportion best befitting Her present grace and knowledge. Such the power That to angelic ministries belongs. [Exit Azael. The rest arrange themselves for the spectacle behind Our Lady. THE MASQUE. Enter, on the right, personated by Angels, the High-Priest and Priests of the Temple, with censers and silver trumpets, followed by Virgins of the Sanctuary with harps and tabrets. Advancing towards Our Lady all make solemn obeisance. HIGH-PRIEST. Daughter of Joachim and Anna blest! Of David's race the loveliest and the best! Scion of Jesse, in whose stem entwine The sacerdotal and the regal line; In whom with ever-new delight we trace New miracles of still increasing grace; Accept the homage that we come to pay On this thy rosy-dawning natal day. O, how can we enough record Our grateful thanks to Israel's Lord! For sending us, in this the hour Of Juda's fast departing power, Of Juda's shame and Juda's crime, This Promise of an earlier time! This earnest of the Father's love! This pure and spotless Turtle-dove! This Gem above all price! This Flower of Paradise! Not without cause O Virgin pre-elect, Do we auspicious days from thee expect; Remembering how from Anna's barren womb, Child of a vow, thou didst divinely come; What noble gifts of reason, virtue, grace, In thy first dawn of being found a place;— How, hither of thine own accord Thou camest with thy parents dear To be presented to the Lord, And dwell with Him in secret here, While yet, O mystery divine! Only three short years were thine! Nor camest thou by Angels unattended; Myself beheld their guardian wings, O, sacred Heir of Juda's kings! High above thy radiant head The old Cherubic glory shed In mystic rays of pearl and azure blended! Now therefore from prophetic signs most clear Knowing that soon Messias must appear; And having watch'd from day to day Thy soul its hidden wealth display, As from some unfathom'd mine Full of treasures all divine;— Marking thy life of ceaseless prayer and praise; Marking thy various superhuman ways; Marking thy most august humility, That nothing worthy in itself can see;— We judge that thou must be None other but that Virgin long foretold By word, and type, and mysteries manifold, That Virgin promised at Creation's morn, Of whom the great Messias should be born, Whose foot should crush the Serpent's head, And down in dust the pride of raging Satan tread! Hail, then, O Israel's joy! Hail, Orient Gate! Through which the everlasting Increate, The Infinite Almighty King of kings Shall enter on the stage of finite things. Hail, Stair of light! That burst on Jacob's sight, Spangling the vault of night! What time a lonely exile flying, His head upon its stony pillow lying, Beneath Heaven's open door unwitting he took rest And learnt that in his seed all nations should be blest! Stair of cerulean glass, Along whose solemn flights, that tier by tier Scale the blue starry sphere, Angels ascending and descending pass! To whose firm base the earth a floor supplies, Whose soaring heights are lost beyond the skies!— Hail, thou, whose faith to Israel shall restore More than the glory that was hers of yore; From whose most sacred and imperial womb The great High Priest in majesty shall come, Chosen for ever, as the Psalmist spake, After the order of Melchisedech! [Taking a thurible, he solemnly incenses Our Lady as she lies asleep; after which Priests and Virgins arrange themselves as chorus on the right side of the Court, facing Our Lady. SCENE I. The fountain ceases to play; and the Cloister at the end of the Court slowly parting exhibits, as on a stage, a melancholy prospect of rock and desert, veiled in mysterious gloom. Enter Eve, personated by an angel, in a raiment of many colours, grace fully wrought of delicate furs and plumage. EVE. Adam, where art thou? O return, return. Too long hast thou been absent from my side Searching the wild for fruits so scanty here, So plentiful in Eden's happy clime! Adam, where art thou? Ah, in vain I call; No voice responds; and o'er the hideous waste Chaotic silence broods; save when a blast Far pealing from the stormy clarions Of sworded Cherubim, from earth to heaven Reverberates our doom. O misery! O misery of miseries,—to think, But yesterday in Paradise! and now Outcasts of nature, to the wrath exposed Of all creation by our Fall aggrieved! Nor less of furious demons raging round, Unchain'd by our own act. But worse than all, Far worse than outward elemental wrack, Far worse than brutal or Satanic rage, Is this conflicting storm I feel within, Deep in my central being, such as never I felt before in Paradisal days. O loss supreme! O loss unutterable Of grace divine, our Maker's noblest boon To nature superadded! This departed, I feel a very ruin of myself; A strife of inward spiritual elements Each furiously against the other turn'd, And wrestling in the darken'd soul's abyss. Ah, wilful and perverse! who, not content With that unmerited beatitude So freely by creative love bestow'd, Ambitiously must lend an eager ear To the deceiving Serpent; and partake Of the forbidden tree; and break the law Our Maker gave us; and prevail with Adam To break it also; and had no touch of pity For generations to be born of me, Who through perpetual ages shall proclaim Their Mother cursed among all womankind, Partakers of her guilt and penalty. [Casting herself on the sand. O parent earth, receive me! Dust I am, And into dust I must again return; So runs the sentence. Oh, that here it might Find its fulfilment—happier far to die Now in Creation's morning, than live on To be a fount of countless miseries To countless beings through all future time! So might the Lord another Eve create, Another Eve far better than the first, Far better and more wise; who should not sin As the first sinn'd. So might the Lord from her Ordain another race of humankind, Not to be born in sin, as must be born All who are born of me. Ah, what if this Which now I feel,—this faintness stealing o'er me,— Ah, what if this be death! O Adam, Adam! Haste to thy dying spouse; make haste to speak Forgiveness of the past, and to enfold Thy partner in a last embrace of love. [She sinks in a swoon, Solemn silence. Presently a soft Eolian melancholy music springs up, mingled with the distant moaning of wild-beasts, plaintive notes of birds, the sighing of winds, and other doleful sounds. After which Voices overhead, as in a colloquy. FIRST VOICE. Hark, how all creation moans In a thousand piteous tones, Wailing its untimely fall From a state celestial! See for sylvan lawns appear Arid wastes of desert drear! See the world a ruin lie, All through Eve's apostasy! SECOND VOICE. Lord, how long shall be the time Ere the guilt of Adam's crime Shall from nature be removed In the smile of Thy Beloved? When shall justice dawn again? When shall peace eternal reign? When again on earth shall be Truth and true felicity? THIRD VOICE. When his weakness man has shown In his native strength alone; When the world is worn and old; When its faith is dead and cold; When o'er sacred Carmel's head Forty centuries have sped; When a Virgin shall be born, Like the rose without a thorn, Wholly free from Adam's stain;— Then shall justice dawn again; Then again the waste shall bloom As a lily from the tomb; Heaven re-open in the skies, Earth renew its Paradise. [Eve slowly wakes; and gazing round with terror, sobs vehemently. Enter the Archangel Gabriel, bearing an olive-branch and some fruits of the desert. GABRIEL. Hail, Mother of all ages! fontal source Of humankind, who shall from thee become A multitudinous river, surging on, In ever-widening and majestic flood, Into the ocean of eternity! Weep not, O Eve!—I come to comfort thee. In proof of which behold this olive-branch, Earnest of peace restored, and brighter days. Know that, among all miseries, despair Closing the gate of mercy is the worst. Rise, then, and be consoled; and eat of what I bring thee. Little yet suspectest thou How much thy natural frame has been impair'd, Immortal once by grace, and with the help Of life's immortal tree; but now, alas, As left in its own native feebleness, By slightest effort wearied; and throughout Corruptible with latent germs of death. These fruits, less exquisite indeed than those Of Paradise, are yet, so mercy wills, Best suited to repair thy wasted strength. [He offers her fruit EVE (rising). O thou, whose form, So radiantly bright, proclaims thee one Of Heav'n's high Princes, I would eat, but grief Forbids me,—grief, and keen solicitude For woe-worn Adam. At the break of dawn He wander'd forth, leaving me strict command Not to forsake the circuit of these rocks; And now the evening shades are closing round Without a sign of his desired return. What if some beast have rent his tender flesh! Or on his head the vivid thunderbolt Have fallen unawares! or, sadder still, What if in strong aversion he has left His guilty Eve; and sought him out a nook In some far region, there to pine and die Safe from her hateful sight! Say, holy Angel, If haply you have chanced to cross his path Upon the borders of th' inclement waste? For I am troubled at his lengthen'd stay. GABRIEL. But now I came upon him, as he sate, His hands upon his forehead tightly clasp'd, Beneath a solitary juniper, On a high sandy hillock, gazing far Across the plain in meditative mood, And breathing forth his lamentable sighs Upon th' unsympathising desert space, In fond remembrance of lost Paradise. Some comfort, as I think, I minister'd, Bearer of welcome news; and have the same For thee, when thou hast tasted of the fruit He sends by me,—his poor love-offering, Cull'd with laborious and painful search From the rude bosom of the wilderness, Not without wounds from many a prickly thorn. Himself had come, but that his jaded limbs Refused their task. EVE (eating of the fruit). Thanks, heavenly messenger, for those dear words That tell me Adam lives, and still can love The guilty origin of all his ills. And thanks again to Adam and to thee For this repast, too good for fallen Eve. Already, with no small surprise I feel In body as in mind my strength revived. And now, declare, I pray, what consolation Is this thou bringest? How can comfort be, Where all is gloom and blank despondency? GABRIEL. And can it be, then, Eve, thou hast forgotten That promise most august, so lately made thee By thy all-pitying Maker, ‘through the Woman To crush the Serpent's head?’—I fear thou hast; Or whence this hopelessness?—Now, therefore, list To what I here announce. Far distant hence, Behind yon red horizon where the sun Is dipping low, there stands a holy Hill, Upon encircling mountains based sublime, Which men hereafter shall Moria call, Or ‘Mount of Vision;’ now with cedars crown'd, Encircling with their fragrant depth of shade A verdant mead, but in the times to come To be surmounted by a glorious Temple, Of Sion named. For there hath God decreed To set His habitation; there hath fix'd His everlasting love, and firm impress'd The sacred stamp of His Almighty Name. To this most holy and majestic Mount, Know, Eve, that I, in pity of the grief That weighs thy soul, have been enjoin'd to bring thee; And there in mystic vision to disclose, What shall console thee much,—the lovely sight Of that eternally predestined Maid Reserved to spring from thee in after-days, Immaculate in Conception as in Birth, Whose Seed shall be the Saviour of thy race Uniting in one Person, all divine, Two natures unconfused, divine and human, For evermore. There also shalt thou see (As in the mirror of th' Eternal Mind, Which simultaneously with all the times, At once in present, past, and future, lives) In glorious procession sweep along Before thy dazzled gaze, Saints upon Saints,— The Patriarchs of the world,—their homage paying To their and thy fair Daughter, whom on earth They antedate, coeval in the skies, The veritable offspring of thy womb, For ever bless'd among all womankind; And seeing shalt rejoice. EVE. O happiness! Kind Angel, let us go without delay. Lead on; I follow thee. GABRIEL. To Adam first We bend our steps; he also is permitted To see this blissful sight, that so your joy United may be greater. Yet, O Eve, When of these visionary scenes ye drink, Deem not that ye behold the things themselves, Or aught beside a semblance shadow'd forth By angel ministries, beneath the veil Of outward shapes; as suits your fallen state, Whose now beclouded soul, enslaved to earth By its own fatal and rebellious choice, Its heavenly intuitions half-obscured, Henceforth, so long as it inhabits flesh, Must be content by earthly images To picture to its gaze immortal things. Nay Heav'n itself, could it be brought before Your feeble vision, would perforce assume The bulky outline of material forms, Its essence pure escaping human reach. [He leads Eve across the desert. As they advance, the sandy waste begins to assume a verdant tint, blue sky appears, and a balmy breeze springs up. GABRIEL. See, Eve, already how the wilderness Is casting off its late funereal garb, And all in vernal beauty decks itself— Emblem of hope revived, and happier times. Onward! the furthest spot to human speed Is little distant if an Angel lead. [Exeunt Gabriel and Eve. A brilliant mirage rises at the end of the Court, representing, by way of drop-scene, Jerusalem and its Temple as in the age of Solomon; meanwhile the Chorus of Priests and Virgins sings alternately as follows: PRIESTS. On Sion's hill a Temple stands, No toilsome work of human hands: A Temple beauteous in design, Replete with mysteries divine: A Temple of eternal fame; And Mary is its mystic name. VIRGINS. Or ere the skyey dome was rear'd; Or ere the mountain-tops appear'd; Or ere the raging sea was chain'd; The Lord this Temple had ordain'd: And its secure foundations laid Before the Seraphim were made. PRIESTS. Deep in His counsels all divine, In silence grew the lovely shrine; In silence rear'd aloft its head, And like the fragrant cedar spread, That keeps from age to age its throne Upon the heights of Lebanon. VIRGINS. What in the night of times gone by Was ever in th' eternal Eye, Now in the world's reviving morn Begins on human sight to dawn; Our hands have touch'd, our eyes behold, This Temple of pellucid gold. PRIESTS. Still with the tide of onward time Expanding in a growth sublime, Soon shall its heritage extend Throughout the world from end to end, And gather into one embrace The Jewish and the Gentile race. VIRGINS. Hail, sacrosanct intact abode Created for Incarnate God! Hail, shrine incomprehensible, In which the Father's Word shall dwell! Hail, Virgin, free from Adam's curse! Hail, Temple of the universe! PRIESTS. Ah, could we but a moment spy, Thy glorious inner Sanctuary; What miracles would meet our gaze, Exceeding all that earth displays! Such as befit the Palace bright Preparing for the Infinite. VIRGINS. Ah, could we view the altar fair, That glistens so divinely there; Could we but scent the incense sweet That hovers round that mercy-seat; Could we but hear the lovely song, Which evermore those aisles prolong;— PRIESTS AND VIRGINS TOGETHER. Then should we all perforce avow That Heav'n itself had come below; In order that the Lord of grace Might find on earth a fitting place Whence—in depths of ruin hurl'd— To reorganise the world! SCENE II. The mirage dissolving reveals a grassy terrace looking upon an open space, in the midst of which rises Mount Moria. Enter the Archangel Gabriel, conducting Adam and Eve. GABRIEL. Lo, where it stands; the sacred table-land And Mount of Vision promised to your gaze! Behold its fair foundations lifted high Upon the summits of the holy hills; Figure of her, whose sanctity begins Where others terminate. Behold, behold, The Mount of mounts: Heav'n's sacred vestibule, Jerusalem's fair seat in future days, Predestined habitation of the Lord, Where He shall dwell for ages, and well-pleased Incense and holy sacrifice receive; Umbrageous now, and in the glory clad Of late creation; but in after-times, When o'er the world a roaring flood has swept, Far different to appear! There shall ye see, Upon its verdant heaven-embracing floor, Your Child in glory immarcessible Sitting enthroned beneath the mystic shade Of Life's ambrosial Tree—Mother elect Of Life and all who live: and there shall view, Before her with exultant pæans throng, Gather'd from all the onward centuries, The Patriarchal train, of which already As hitherward we came, ye saw the skirts Winding along the valley's further side; And heard its herald note of victory Peal from a thousand trumpets with a blast That shook the realms of chaos and of night. And now, farewell: henceforth ye need me not, O fountain-heads august of all mankind! Sufficient of yourselves to find the way. [He vanishes. ADAM. How sudden was his parting! such the gift Of incorporeal natures. Fare thee well, Bright Messenger of peace! and bear aloft To other worlds the tale of Adam's fall, To be their warning through the tracts of time. Come, Eve, rejoice with me in this fair scene. O contrast exquisite With that interminable desert waste Which late we trod! Ah, what an odorous waft Of Paradisal perfume hither steals From shrubs innumerous, whose circlet fair Encompasses as with a flowery belt The Mount of God. O balm ineffable, At which mine eyes, that seem'd as adamant, In blissful tears dissolve! Hail, sacred hill! Hail, second Eden, fairer than the first! Be quick, my best beloved; let us press on, And mount without delay yon gracious stair Of Heaven-ascending heights, lest with a breath The vision melt before our yearning eyes, And leave us doubly desolate. EVE. Bethink thee, My Adam, with what face can we appear In that most holy vestibule, disrobed As here we stand, of our first innocence? Such is the fear that in my bosom thrills. ADAM. And rightly, had we no sure confidence Elsewhere obtain'd. But, O my timorous Eve, These honourable vestments clothing us, So delicately wrought in fairest form And exquisite variety of tint, Lovely adornments from the loving hand Of God Himself—what else are they but tokens Exterior of a new interior grace, Infused within us through the priceless merits Of Him who is to come? In this array'd, Though of ourselves most wholly miserable, We have no cause for shame. Why, then, delay His counsel to fulfil who brought us hither? EVE. Adam thy will is mine. Too much already Has disobedience cost us. Lead thou on; My heart is burning with desire to see The sacred Virgin to be born of me. [Exeunt Adam and Eve. A mirage as before, representing Rome as in the age of Augustus. CHORUS OF PRIESTS AND VIRGINS. PRIESTS. Ere yet primeval Chaos reign'd; Ere matter yet had form obtain'd; Far in the Empyrean height A vacant Throne of purest light Aloft o'er worlds angelic raised In solitary glory blazed. VIRGINS. The Seraphs, from the topmost tier That girdles Heav'n's eternal sphere, With awe the distant wonder eyed, And vainly to interpret tried; No creature worthy could they see To sit in such high majesty. PRIESTS. But not in vain th' Eternal Mind Hath its eternal scheme design'd; Now, therefore, in the midst of years This Child immaculate appears, Worthy alone of all to fill That Throne so inaccessible! VIRGINS. Hail, Mary, purest Gem of earth! Hail, child of grace before thy birth! Whose path from grace to grace ascends, And in supremest glory ends. Hail, Daughter of th' Eternal King, From whom the Life of life shall spring! PRIESTS. O, how for thee the Angels sigh, Eager to waft thee to the sky! Too long to them the days appear That yet detain thee captive here; Where, quench'd in mists of earth below, Thy rays of glory dimly glow. VIRGINS. Ascend, ascend, Imperial Queen! Forsake this limitary scene; Forsake this lower darksome place Which guilt and misery deface: A higher world invites thee on To splendour and dominion! PRIESTS AND VIRGINS TOGETHER. Ascend, ascend, Imperial Queen! Ascend, and plead the cause of men! Ascend, and reign upon the Throne Predestinated thine alone! Ascend, where none before have trod! Ascend, the Mother of thy God! SCENE III. Summit of the Mount of Vision, exhibiting a spacious flowery mead surrounded by cedars. In the midst, the Tree of Life; beneath which, personated by an angel, appears Mary, as a child, in a raiment of blue and gold, seated on a throne with steps of sapphire, crowned, and sceptre in hand. Enter Adam and Eve. EVE (clasping Mary's feet.) O most Immaculate Maid, Virgin ineffable! Pure child of God! Transcendent marvel of the universe! Beauty and glory of the human race! Effacing all the shame of womankind! See at thy feet poor miserable Eve; And hear the parents to their daughter sue For pardon and for peace. O joy of joys! Felicity unhoped! to see thy face, Who shalt repair the ruin that I made; Else irremediable. By Eva's crime Came sin, came death, came deathly slavery To Satan and to sin; but Eva's daughter, Bridging the cruel gulf her mother made, Opens to all mankind a second path To Paradise and life's immortal Tree. Hail, second Eve, far better than the first! Hail, Virgin pre-elect! Virgin conceived In Adam's nature, not in Adam's sin; That so to all mankind thou mightest be A new beginning of new life in Him Who comes through thee for Adam to atone. Hail, Archetype of all that loveliest is, Sweetest, most perfect, best, and heav'nliest! Of whom our Eden but a figure was. Lily of incorruption! Life in death! Abyss of grace! remember that from us Thou didst that elemental substance take Wherewith thou shalt—O marvel infinite! The Incorporeal with corporeal clothe, And on the uncreated Word bestow A second nature's origin, so becoming Mother of God, and Empress of the world! Remember that to our sad fall thou owest Thy peerless glory; and with gracious eye Look down upon thy parents here before thee, Here as they kneel, most lovely and beloved: And stretch thy gentle hand, and wipe away Their mournful tears; and lift them up again; And whisper in their hearts eternal peace. MARY (rising, and kissing Eve on the forehead). Hail, parents dear! O weep no more, and cease your piteous sighs; And praise with me the goodness of our God; His heights unsearchable Of wisdom and of love; Who on His lowly handmaid gazed; And her from empty nothing raised; And chose her in His grace to be Mother of Immortality; Mother of His Eternal Son: Not for her own sake alone, But for the sake of you and all mankind; For whom, in His omniscient mind, Before the worlds were made, this mercy He design'd. Who, pitying our first Parents' fall, And in their fate the fate of all, The penalty their guilt had earn'd Hath into greater glory turn'd; And deign'd to crush the serpent's head Beneath a feeble maiden's tread. Now therefore, parents dear, Lament no more; but, with a joyful heart, Ascend these steps, and sit beside your child; And know that ye are here most opportunely, To aid her in receiving with due grace The glad Procession now upon its way; Coming, with songs of triumph jubilant, To offer thanks in Sion this fair morn In homage of that love, which, in the depth Of everlasting ages, fix'd on her Its pitying gaze; and chose her from the mass Of old corruption, and predestined her, And called her in the plenitude of times, To be the mother of the Son of God In whom alone is all redemption found. [She embraces our first Parents; and taking them by the hand, makes them sit down on the uppermost step of the throne, Adam on her right, and Eve on her left. A mirage, as before, representing Athens and sea-coast. CHORUS OF PRIESTS AND VIRGINS. PRIESTS. Hail, thou first-begotten Daughter Of th' Almighty Father's love; Temple of eternal glory, Pure and spotless turtle-dove; Mistress of the earth and skies, Choicest bud of Paradise! VIRGINS. Hail to her, whose deep foundations On the holy hills are laid; Joy of endless generations, Loved before the worlds were made; Treasure of believing souls While the wheel of ages rolls! PRIESTS. Garden of divinest odours; Roseate shell of purest ray, Where the priceless pearl of heaven Waited its appointed day, Nestling in repose sublime Down beneath the wave of time! VIRGINS. Cloud of supramundane splendour, Cloud, that in its awful womb Bears the Father's hidden lightning, Bears the thunderbolt of doom; O'er the world in mighty power Comes to shed the Spirit's shower! PRIESTS. Who can count the starry jewels Set in Mary's crown of light? Who can estimate her greatness? Who can guess her glory's height? What can measure its extent Save the depth of God's descent? VIRGINS. Hail, O Queen of nature's kingdoms, Queen of Angels, hail to thee! Greater none have been before thee, Greater none shall ever be: Hail, divine Receptacle Of th' Incomprehensible! PRIESTS. Thee the God of worlds foreseeing In thy dignity supreme, Loved thee, chose thee, gave thee being, Set thee in salvation's scheme; Then with all perfections deck'd, As His Mother pre-elect. VIRGINS. Thine shall be a lot surpassing All that is of glory known In the earth or in the heavens,— Thine, but not for thee alone; God, in whom thy life began, Made thee for Himself and man. PRIESTS. God and man in thee uniting, Death in thee by life o'ercome; Creature with Creator blending, Man remoulded in thy womb;— Such, O peerless Child, shall be Thy prolific history. VIRGINS. Fount of wonders ever flowing! Glory of the sea and sky! How for thee th' eternal mansions Waiting yearn and yearning sigh Envying earth the moments slow That detain thee here below. PRIESTS. Bird of Paradisal beauty, Silver Dove with wings of gold, Pity thy dear native Heaven, And thy fragrant plumes unfold; Quickly, quickly, speed thy flight Up to crystal realms of light. PRIESTS AND VIRGINS TOGETHER. There for poor unhappy mortals Thy immortal Son implore, There in beatific glory Reign with Him for evermore; Through the ages all along Theme of sempiternal song! SCENE IV. Summit of the Mount of Vision as before; Mary on her throne, with Adam and Eve on either side. Peal of trumpets, and enter first part of Procession: Abel, bearing a lamb in his bosom; then Seth, Henoch with his Book, Mathusala, and other antediluvian Patriarchs, with long white beards; last of all Noe, walking as it were in the midst of a rainbow, and carrying a pattern of the Ark in gold, with a dove upon its roof. On arriving before the throne, the Procession stops. HENOCH. Hail, Desire of the first world! THE REST. Hail, Amaze of the ages to come! NOE. Daughter of prophecy and Virgin true, Hope of both worlds—the ancient and the new, Mother of day, and Queen of golden morn, From whom the sole-begotten Son is born! Here, lowly bending at thy feet, behold The Blest who lived before the deluge roll'd; And see before thee, Olive-branch of grace, The second Father of the human race. Ah, why, O Lady dear, On earth's terraqueous sphere So late in time did thy sweet form appear? Hadst thou but earlier come, Not then the first-created world had been Into destruction swept beneath a watery doom; Thy smile had soothed the wrath of God, And stay'd His dread descending rod. Hail, Ark of Life! Floating unharm'd above the surging strife Of Hell and human crime! So to preserve that promised Seed The Hope of after time; From whence shall come a new creation, A holy spotless generation, A race and kingdom all divine, Children of th' eternal Trine; A royal race, with promise sure Through everlasting ages to endure! Hail, Rainbow bright, From the pure Fount of Light In variegated hues of grace array'd; Glistening sublime Upon the verge of time, Where spreads eternity its awful shade! Now, therefore, bend thine ear, O Daughter fair, and hear, And grant this favour we entreat, Queen of Patriarchs, at thy feet;— That, since on earth thy face we might not see While wrapt around in our mortality, Now, in return for our long sighs, Beaming down with thy bright eyes, Thou suffer us to hear that voice At which the circling spheres rejoice; Which all the earth with gladness fills, And through the womb of nature thrills, Robbing with its delicious strain E'en Purgatory of its pain. [Mary smiles a gracious assent; and giving her sceptre to Eve, rises and sings. MARY'S SONG. While I was yet a little one I pleased the Lord of grace, And in His holy Sanctuary He granted me a place. There, shelter'd by His tender care, And by His love inspired, I strove in all things to fulfil Whatever He desired. I wholly gave myself to Him, To be for ever His; I meditated on His law And ancient promises. And oft at my embroidery, Musing upon the Maid Of whom Messias should be born,— Thus in my heart I pray'd: ‘Permit me, Lord, one day to see That Virgin ever dear Predestinated in the courts Of Sion to appear. ‘O blest estate, if but I might Among her handmaids be! But such a favour, O my God, Is far too high for me.’ Thus unto God I pour'd my prayer; And He that prayer fulfill'd, Not as my poverty had hoped, But as His bounty will'd. Erewhile a trembling child of dust, Now robed in heavenly rays, I reign the Mother of my God Through sempiternal days. To me the nations of the world Their grateful tribute bring; To me the Powers of darkness bend; To me the Angels sing. [The Procession moves on. Peal of trumpets, and enter Melchisedech, gorgeously vested as High Priest and King of Salem, bearing a Paten and Chalice of gold; whom follows the Father of the Faithful, attended by Isaac, Jacob, and Joseph; then, between Aaron and their sister Mary, Moses, bearing the two tables of stone; after whom Josue and warriors, succeeded by Ruth and maidens as gleaners. Last of all King David as a shepherd-boy, with his harp. MELCHISEDECH. Hail, Queen of Salem! THE REST. Hail, Vision of peace! DAVID (accompanying himself on his harp). Daughter of a royal line, Noble shoot of Jesse's rod, Flower immortal and divine, First among the works of God! As I watch'd my flock by night, Musing over Israel's woes, Oft of old thy Vision bright, Child of grace, before me rose. Lulling nature's angry storm, Oft I saw with prophet eye Thy imperial radiant form On the moonbeam glancing by; All in robes of orient light, Tinted from the azure skies, Breathing o'er chaotic night Perfume fresh from Paradise. Ah, how then, O Queen of day, I for thee would pour my tears; Mourning o'er the long delay Of a thousand coming years: Yearning with a strong desire Thy vivific birth to see; All my spirit's depth on fire For the times that were to be. Those triumphant days below Not permitted to behold, Waiting long, while, ebb and flow, Restlessly the ages roll'd,— Now at last, in realms serene Of immortal life and love, I salute thee as the Queen Of Jerusalem above; Thee with joy ecstatic greet, Glist'ning in a golden crown, And before thy sacred feet Lay my harp in homage down. [The Procession moves on. Peal of trumpets, and enter King Ezechias, bearing a lily-like flower; succeeded by other Kings of Judah, all royally arrayed; after whom Judith and attendant women, with cymbals and timbrels, moving to a solemn measure. EZECHIAS. Hail, Glory of Jerusalem! THE REST. Hail, Delight of Israel! JUDITH. Jerusalem, Jerusalem! Arise thee now and shine; Put on, put on thy purple robe And diadem divine; For by a woman's feeble arm The Lord hath fought for thee, And in the cause of his elect Hath triumph'd gloriously. Jerusalem, Jerusalem! Thy streets are paved with gold; Thy pearly halls and palaces Are glorious to behold; Thy walls of jasper are inlaid With every precious gem; How pure, how lovely is the sight Of our Jerusalem! Jerusalem, Jerusalem! No tear in thee is known; Thy bright and fragrant courts were made For happiness alone; The Lord alone thy Temple is, And calls thee by His name; The Lamb alone is all the light Of our Jerusalem! Jerusalem, Jerusalem! Thou City of the skies; Dear City of our King and God; Dear object of our sighs! How blest, how blest are thy abodes, And those who dwell in them! Thrice welcome here, O Virgin dear, To thy Jerusalem! [The Procession moves on. Peal of trumpets, and enter to martial music, with banners, escorted by troops of war diversly arrayed, Allegorical Personifications of the Four Great Empires, on triumphal Cars drawn by yoked lions, leopards, and other emblematic animals; then Isaias and the other Prophets; Daniel last, bearing a scroll in his hand. ISAIAS. Hail Virgin who shalt conceive! Alleluia. THE REST. And bear a Son. Alleluia. DANIEL. God who guides the wheeling spheres, Keeping still His promise firm; Lo, the Seventy Weeks of years Speed to their prophetic term. Vainly strove Assyria's pride, Persian wealth, or Grecian power; Vainly each in turn defied Its inevitable hour. Rome herself so strong to-day, Greatest empire of them all, Of her very strength the prey, Marches onward to her fall. Other kingdoms, Lord, than Thine, To eternity pretend; One alone, by right divine, Sees of each in turn an end. One alone, while others fade, Growing with the growing years, Undecaying, undecay'd, Ever in its prime appears! Hail, of that high Kingdom Queen! Fairest Form that earth has trod! Hail, Inheritance of men! Glory of the Church of God! At the end of the procession appear, with palms in their hands, the Hermits of Mount Carmel, conducting six ethereal steeds, which draw after them the Car of Elias, marvellously glistering. Seated in the car is seen the Archangel Gabriel. SONG OF THE HERMITS OF MOUNT CARMEL. Hail to the Flower of pure delight, Blooming on sacred Carmel's height! Flower of Carmel, Flowering Vine, Shed thy sweets On us who are thine! Virginal Mother, Star of the sea; Glory of Heaven, We glorify thee! [On arriving in front of the throne, the Car stops. GABRIEL (descending). O brighter than all brightness, living Altar Of light's pure temple, Joy exuberant Of all the patriarchs, Queen of Palestine, And splendour of the New Jerusalem! Know that in honour of thy birth this day Thy loving Angels and true Guardians hold In Paradise High Feast, which in their name I supplicate thy sceptred majesty With its imperial presence to adorn. In hope whereof, this empyrean car (Once only touch'd by mortal foot, what time It bore Elias through the fields of space) Attends thy bidding. See, its fiery steeds, Already, of their happy task aware, Curvet, impatient for their precious freight. MARY. My soul hath fainted for the living Courts Of my eternal King. Most joyfully I go with you; this only boon entreating, That I may bring with me these sacred Parents Here seated at my side. GABRIEL. Lady, not yet is it permitted them To pass beyond this outer vestibule; But when the long-desired Emmanuel, Of them through Thee hereafter to be born, In his atoning life-blood shall have paid For Thee and them and all of human kind Super-exceeding ransom on the Cross; And re-estated all things in Himself, Opening to life eterne the door long closed; Then shalt Thou have thy will, O Heavenly Bride, And see these Parents ever at thy side. [Mary, with a tender smile of pity and hope embracing our First Parents, ascends the Car, which majestically moves forward, Adam and Eve gazing wistfully after her. EVE. Farewell, O bright Perfection! vain it were To follow after thee. O Adam, mark How o'er our Mount of Vision Dim monitory clouds come stealing down; And all its tinted glories pale away So exquisite before. 'Tis time, methinks, That we descend. ADAM. Yes, it is even so. Dense and more dense the vapour gathers fast, From th' upper air insensibly distill'd, As 'twere a veil let down to segregate From sublunary gaze immortal things. Give me thy hand, O Eve, my sole beloved, And ere within its folds voluminous The storm our perilous descent obscure, Leave we Moria's enigmatic hill, Hereafter by the grace of our dear Heir From Mary born, hoping to be received Into the sacred Sion of the skies, When turn'd in death to our original dust Again from dust we rise, created new For new and more divine felicity (Such my reliance on redeeming love) Than that by disobedience forfeited. At present in the world our portion lies There to toil on in faith and hopeful love Through good and evil mingled; till at length Our lifelong penance o'er we go our way Into the place appointed; there to wait, In patience of subdued expectancy, The joyful coming of Salvation's Morn! [They descend the hill. END OF THE MASQUE. The Masque over, the Cloister reunites as at first, the fountain in the Court begins again to play, and the Chorus of Priests and Virgins withdraws. Enter Azael and Companions. AZAEL (kneeling to Ithuriel). Mighty Prince, our task is o'er, And from phantasy's domain, Through the secret golden door, Hither we return again; And commend our pageantry To this noble Company, Ready to receive for it Praise or blame as may befit. ITHURIEL. Rise, Azael, and for this your Mystery Accept our general thanks to each and all; Scarce could we deem it but a spectacle; So true was each performer to his part; So true your evanescent scenery To nature's subtlest tints and lineaments. See, even yet there lingers on the cheek Of this fair sleeping Maid a roseate smile, As from the fanning of the balmy wings Of some inspiring vision, foretaste sweet Of heavenly joys; such power your masque hath had: Whereof that perfect soul, which evermore Receives of all things in proportion due, Admitted whatsoever for her state Was most expedient. ANGEL OF ROME. We, Azael, too, Render our grateful thanks; in sign of which Accept this ring of purest chrysolite, Which anciently on Numa's finger shone, Numa, of early Rome pacific king. And he, when in his cradle, so 'tis said From the great Sibyl of Cumæan song Received it as the heirloom of his race. A royal province scarce could purchase it. AZAEL. Aught by thy hand bestow'd were high reward, Most noble Potentate. Would that the work Had equall'd but the will; then had there been A spectacle more worthy the spectators. ANGEL OF ROME (to the Angels of Italy). Princes and sacred Peers, the blazing sun, O'ertopping yonder pile of burnish'd gold, And circling with a rainbow diadem The snowy head of this fair cloistral fount, Proclaims our near departure; come then, all, And, kissing each in turn the heavenly feet Of this dear glory of Jerusalem, Let us entreat her blessing on ourselves, And on the cities, shores, and territories Committed to our several custodies. [The Angels of Italy kneel, two and two, before Mary, still asleep, and kiss her feet, singing meanwhile as follows: Age with age contended, At Creation's dawn, Which might see the day When Mary should be born: But the Lord had hidden His decree sublime, Destined to prevail In its appointed time. They who came the foremost Empty sought the skies; And the last of all Has won the happy prize. Hail, thou Age of ages, Light of all the rest! Hail, predestined Era Infinitely blest! Hail, thou bright Aurora, Chasing nature's gloom, Hope of all before, And bliss of all to come! Age of peace on earth! Age of joy in heaven! Age of grace restored! Age of guilt forgiven! Thee the coming cycles Grateful shall proclaim, Germ of all their life, And fount of all their fame. Earth from thee henceforward Shall its date renew, And to thee look back All the ages through; As a pillar shining, From a mount sublime, O'er the tracts of space! And o'er the tide of time! ITHURIEL (to the Angel of Rome). Doubt not, imperial Chieftain, but our Lady Will breathe her supplications to high Heav'n, Omnipotential with the Omnipotent, For every several object of your prayers. And for thy comfort learn, that mighty Rome, Now in the bonds of pagan darkness swathed, Hereafter shall, in reverence to Mary And Mary's Child, exceed your utmost hope. A prophecy there is of ancient date, Unbrokenly preserved from age to age By this high Temple's angel guardians;— That, in the times to come, this holy Salem In ruins laid, must to a holier city Give place, whose name is ‘Strength,’ prepared of old Upon the bosom of th' eternal floods, And lifted on a sevenfold mystic hill; Which in its day predestined shall become The hierarchic centre of the world, (As to the Jews Jerusalem before) Embracing in one faith, one polity, Beneath one Head in Heaven, and one on earth Pontifical, the whole of human kind; With ordinances, priesthood, all things, new, Promised through endless ages to endure. This mystery to thy attentive mind We here commit, in its most certain time To be reveal'd before the universe In sight of all. And now, if go ye must, At least, in memory of your visit here, Accept, celestial Princes, at our hands These parting gifts; for thee, high Potentate, This fair embroider'd piece, the priceless work Of Mary's pearly fingers; which remember To keep for happy Rome in after-days. For thy companions here these flowers new cull'd, [He plucks some flowers from the plants at Mary's side. Children of Mary's care, and like herself Of bloom and fragrance immarcessible, So only they approach no mortal hand; And if, as we entreat, ye shall appear At our festivities another year, There wait you other gifts more precious still, So promises your own Ithuriel. [The Angels of Rome and Italy withdraw. Now, comrades, to your tasks; for, as I think, The eyelids of our Mistress soon will part, And to our wistful gaze reveal anew Their hidden Paradise; the dawn to us Of day, more truly than the golden light That flashes from the kindling Orient. We must be ready at our several posts To wait upon her wishes and fulfil Our daily ministries. Let music sound; Let a celestial perfume breathe around; Let all be sparkling, joyous, and serene, To greet the waking of creation's Queen! THE MINSTER OF ELD. PROLOGUE. Minster of Eld! in thy sweet solemn shade How pleasant is it thus apart to roam! Here for myself a shelter I have made; In thee my pilgrim spirit finds a home. Hither withdrawing from the day's false glare, From earthliness and all that breeds annoy, She hath wrought out a resting-place from care, And drinks unwatch'd from hidden fount of joy; Oh, cruel world that would such happiness destroy! For while in quiet thought I wander on, These peaceful courts along, Too oft its clangours sound And jar the golden chords so finely strung On which my soul had hung; Then sinks the Minster in a depth profound, And alone I seem to stand On some disenchanted land, Lost upon a desert drear, All a blank to eye and ear, Seeking ofttimes long in vain Ere I can return again. Ah me! what time hath pass'd Since here I enter'd last! Almost I seem a stranger here to be, As though no right I had Mine own dear shrine to see. Oh, archetypal Place! Pure mystery of space! Which, as my glance around I throw, Dost into clearer outline grow. Oh, music that above me sweeps Like anthem of uplifted deeps! Oh, roof of roofs sublime, Wrought in the world's young prime! Oh, pillars firm, that seem Vaster than thought may dream! Oh, lights and shades that fall So strange and mystical, Crossing from wall to wall! Oh, tints most rare! Oh, gently-breathing air! Oh, floor so green and fair! Here let me dwell Choosing some holy cell; Here let me sit and sing to solemn chord Thy works O loving Lord! Joying to tell of Thee Who madest all to be; Joying with all creation to proclaim The glories of Thy Name, Great King of kings! Lord of invisible things! Lord of the starry skies, of earth and air and sea! SCENE I. Nave of a vast Minster. PILGRIM. Was it a fancy, or in very truth Did I behold angelic faces near me? And there was music too! It is most strange; Once in my boyhood's morn I had a dream Of a most noble Minster, rear'd aloft Upon the realms of Chaos and old Night, Fair in proportion, full of mysteries, And typical of all creation's scheme; A supernatural glorious edifice Raised by no hand of mortal architect! Most curiously it dwelt upon my mind, And, as I grew, supplied to teeming fancy A subtle food, and to myself I named it Minster of Eld! Now in its very courts I seem to be;—how hither brought From couch of sickness nigh to death, From couch of weary convalescence long, A secret unexplain'd; and as I gaze, Unless my sense deceive, it spreads abroad Wider and wider still its beauteous aisles. How pleasant is this turf, with fairy-rings Of old primeval growth! How delicate This scent of flowering thyme, which as I tread I cannot choose but crush! These gates that stand As entrance to the Nave, are broad and high Beyond imagination, yet not larger Than suits the rest; and yonder seven great bolts That keep them closed in bonds of adamant, Inscribed with hieroglyphics mystical, So massive seem, they well might typify The very bars of Nature which hold fast The Universe in one. Upon the seventh Appears a Runic text, which may afford Haply some clue to my perplexity. [He reads. ‘When the Universe was made, On its hinge this door was laid; Once unbolted hath it been; Once again shall so be seen. When its folds were opened first, Inward the flood of waters burst; When they next apart shall leap, Inward a flood of flame shall sweep. In the midst of that great din Comes the King of glory in, He who at Creation's door Watching standeth evermore!’ Methinks I can decipher me in part The meaning here contain'd. O, joy of joys! And can it then be so in very deed As I somewhile have thought, that here I stand Within that glorious Minster of old time, Which in my boyhood's days Did evermore around me seem to rise, By glimpses caught through the half-opening haze Of nature's outward mutabilities, Then quick withdrawn again, lest I Too narrowly its secrets should espy. Oh, Minster of my youth! How oft on mossy stone Seated alone In the deep woods I heard thine anthem's solemn tone! How oft I saw unfold Around the setting sun thy skirts of gold, And felt mine inmost heart dance with a joy untold! And of thy glories to imbibe did seem, Till thou alone wast real and earth a dream! Brief date had those glad hours, Soon by advancing manhood put to flight; The world with all its powers Came sweeping on before my ravish'd sight, And I with it was borne, as on the waves of night, Far from sweet Nature's face, Too far, my God, from Thee and Thine embrace, Till the fair vision of mine earlier years Faded in mists of tears, And its sweet music found no echo in mine ears! Thrice welcome then, blest place, If so indeed it be, Up whose long avenues with joy I go; And may thy scenes efface Henceforth for me Remembrance of vile earthly things below, Which all too long endures, feeding the heart with woe. [He proceeds up the nave. How soft and pearly is the light that doth Inhabit here! Yon pillars, dimly shown Through swathing clouds, might vie in girth and height With Babel's Tower. This floor is one vast down, On which a thousand herds might feed apart And still leave room for more; and as I see, On yonder mound there sits a shepherd boy Beside his nibbling flock. I will address him. What, ho! good shepherd boy, canst tell me aught About this holy fane? SHEPHERD BOY. Nay, sir, not much Myself, but not so far away there dwells A Hermit of Mount Carmel, who can tell thee All thou shalt choose to ask. If thou art thirsty, Here is a most sweet spring; and I entreat thee Take bread from my poor scrip. Oh, I have seen Strange things upon the plain since I came hither To keep this flock in charge. The Angel Choirs, The same that sang in Bethlehem, oft I've heard Singing o'erhead in the still moonlight hour. If thou wilt go with me, I'll show the way To where the Hermit lives. But I must call My little sister first to take my place, Now absent gathering anemones To weave a necklace for some favourite Among her lambkins. She will hasten back Soon as she hears this pipe. [He plays, and they proceed together. SCENE II. An open plain in the nave. PILGRIM. We have been stepping fast, and must have come A league upon our way. SHEPHERD BOY. 'Tis difficult, I've noticed, to judge here of distances. What seem'd remote but now being often found At hand when least expected; what seem'd near In turn far off; such mystery there is In all that to this Minster appertains. PILGRIM. I have observed it too; and had ascribed it To some rare trick of fancy. But, behold, The curtain of the mist is lifting up Its heavy folds, and shows the massive pillars Clear to their base; the windows, or what may To windows correspond, begin to cast Through their diminish'd cloudy drapery A rainbow tint; and a suffusèd purple Is gathering overhead; while far away Yon screen its range of crested pinnacles Shows like an alabaster glacier Betwixt two mountains piled! [Music. Ah! what a strain Of harmony was there! Never before Heard I such music. Hark! it swells again And rains down like a shower. SHEPHERD BOY. There are strange harps, Pendent at intervals by golden threads Along the nave, whence spring these gracious sounds, As it would seem, spontaneous. Come this way, And I will show thee one. Lo! where it hangs; Would it were near enough for thee to touch! PILGRIM. O beauteous Instrument! O Harp of eld! What symmetry it hath, resembling those Of th' ancient Druids! with a hoary moss Of silver sprouting on its delicate frame! But for the present mute! SHEPHERD BOY. It will begin To sound again, if we but wait. I see Already a vibration in the chords. [It sounds, gradually increasing in depth and variety. PILGRIM. O miracle of tones! O most divine capacity In instrument so slight and delicate! Or is it rather that the music flows Not from the chords themselves, but from the stir Which by some deep affinity they work In the surrounding natural influences? It must be so. For now it sounds afar, Now near, now all around, in height and depth Ascending and descending through the scales Of such a multitudinous harmony, As though within itself it did embrace All the wide compass of creation's tones. Now 'tis the tinkling of a shower—and now The whistling wind—anon the solemn roll Of mountain waves, changing by slow degrees To muttering thunder. Oh, I could stay and listen For ever to the ever-varying strain, So jubilant awhile; and then so sad, Enough to melt the very soul away With its deep hidden pathos! SHEPHERD BOY. I have heard say, The tones of jubilation are the praise Which Nature pays her Lord; the sad her moans For her own fall in Adam; mix'd with yearnings For the great Day of Restitution, When all things shall in Christ be made anew. But see the spot where dwells the holy Hermit I told thee of! PILGRIM. I see it:—a long range Of curious cells scoop'd in the solid rock, With immemorial ivy over-brow'd; In front a sloping sward, on which appears A broken altar of th' old Pagan time, If right I guess. SHEPHERD BOY. Here, then, I leave thee, Pilgrim; My task complete: God's blessing rest on thee! [Exit. SCENE III. Front of a Hermitage. The Hermit is seen carving a Crucifix on the rock. HERMIT. Another touch might mar it. Holy Christ! Who so for me didst die on Calvary, Accept this poor memorial of Thy love, Which here upon my knees I dedicate To th' everlasting glory of Thy Name. PILGRIM, entering. Forgive me, holy Hermit, breaking thus Upon thy solitude. A shepherd boy Guided me here to thee, as one who might Resolve for me the meaning of this place. [Observing the Crucifix. O work of grace! What glorious majesty Sits on the brow, with depth of patient grief Divinely mingled! wonders have I seen Of art, but none like this. HERMIT. No art is here But that of love and contemplation; A longer gaze would show thee sore defects In what at present pleases. 'Tis the work Of hands most rude and inexperienced. But if concerning this our Minster here Knowledge thou seek, I have some certain Rhymes Which to the Pilgrims who go by this way Sometimes I do impart; these will I gladly Rehearse to thee, as best my memory serves; We sitting by yon altar-step the while. [They approach the altar. PILGRIM. This altar hath most excellent proportions, Ionic in its style, and, as 'twould seem, Of purest Parian. Pity that 'tis rent As by some shock of sudden violence. Its dedication still is legible In Greek: ‘to the unknown god.’ HERMIT. This neighbourhood The Pagans of old time did much frequent, Such as with hearts sincere, in nature's works Felt after nature's omnipresent God, If haply they might find Him. These were they Who first began to scoop these hermitages. This altar was their making. Here with rites Of solemn patriarchal sacrifice, Confused with errors of strange ignorance, Did they adore the Almighty Architect, Their God unknown, yearning for clearer light Of Revelation's dawn, as yet withheld: Later there came the Christian anchorites, And multiplied the cells, as now you see. PILGRIM. And this deep-fissured rent;—how came it thus? HERMIT. It is believed that when our Saviour died, That earthquake, which upheaved the sepulchres, Ran also through this Minster in its course, And, among other traces, left behind This shatter'd altar. PILGRIM There is a pleasant moss Upon this bank that faceth to the East; Here let us sit. It hath grown visibly lighter Since I was in the Minster, and the mist Hath much dispersed. How most majestically Doth yonder neighbouring pillar lift its height, So vast it scarcely seems to be a pillar, And in comparison those cells in the rock Appear to be no bigger than the holes Of the sand-martin! I saw Staffa once, And marvell'd; but a thousand Staffas here, Ascending from basaltic height to height, Seem piled upon each other without end. Yonder, across the plain, on the other side Of the broad Nave, a solemn Porch appears, Between which and the Transept I can count The huge Titanic figured capitals Of twenty several columns, peering forth Through their thin strata of aërial cloud, As in the Pyrenees the crested peaks At morning-tide. But I am quite forgetting, Lost in the mighty majesty around, Thy promise, hoary-headed Solitary, Me to instruct in its deep mysteries. HERMIT. O thou, who of this transcendental place Seekest from me th' originals to trace, Know that, coeval with the earth and skies, No less it dates than from creation's rise: Such the tradition which through ages deep Among themselves its angel-watchers keep. For when, according to the eternal plan, The universe from nothing first began, All elements uniting in His name Him to adore and bless from whom they came, Straightway, as from the strings the music flows, From their rich harmony this Temple rose, An emanation from the things we see Unto His praise, who caused them so to be Working His holy will invisibly. To this great Minster, eldest-born of time, Earth gave a floor, the heavens a roof sublime, For pillars firm their heights the mountains rear'd, And windows in the opening clouds appear'd, The stars for lamps themselves in order ranged, The winds into a glorious organ changed, Chanted from side to side with solemn roar The waves from ocean and the woods from shore. This Temple from the first hath standing been, Open to all, yet evermore unseen, Except by such as with a lowly mind Sought in His loving works their Lord to find, To whom, the more they gazed with reverence due, More and more visible its glories grew; While ever from the eyes that peer'd with pride The structure, of itself, itself would hide. But ceaselessly its solemn aisles along Wander'd of angels bright a glorious throng, Transported its exuberance to behold Of ever-flowing wonders new and old. Now of this Minster if thou next desire The archetypal pattern to inquire, Know, that when early in the dawn of days The Son made all things to the Father's praise, Of His own Cross the everlasting sign He stamp'd within Creation's depth divine, Crosswise uprearing on th' abyss of space The world whose scheme thou here dost dimly trace: Thus in primeval Eden we behold Crosswise four rivers flowing forth of old; And still the Cross this Minster doth divide, For all things draw towards the Crucified. Fourfold expands itself the glorious Fane In Nave, and Choir, and mighty Transepts twain; Each with its cloistral haunts and chantries fair, Each with its countless aisles for praise and prayer, And maze of inner wonders half-unknown E'en to the Seraphs that stand round the throne. But if in each such miracles are found, Such grandeurs of creative love abound; Still more the Choir excels the other three In supernatural grace and majesty. Learn then, fast shut within Creation's shrine, A place there is, part human part divine, Made from the first by Him who set the spheres, But open'd later in the midst of years By Him again, when stooping from His throne He drew our human life into His own. Behind yon screen it lies, the portion blest Of Holy Church, secluded from the rest. O place most dear, who can thy joys express, Or paint the beauties of thy loveliness? O place most calm, who can thy shades forget, Where only God's true Israel may be met? Where dwelleth Faith in undisturb'd repose, Where Hope and Charity their sweets disclose, And all our earthly troubles vanish quite In the Communion of the Saints in light! Thus of this holy Temple, as I could, I've traced for thee, my son, an outline rude; More wonders still within its depths there be, A boundless and unfathomable sea; Some for thyself of these thou shalt explore, And some shalt never know for evermore. What else remains but His great Name to bless; Him, Father, Son, and Spirit to confess, Who all things made by His eternal will, Who all things by the same upholdeth still; All things shall once again in ruin pour, All things again shall once for all restore: To Him be praise all days as in all time before! PILGRIM. Thanks kind Interpreter; I now begin Better to comprehend the great design Unfolding all around: yet, oh, forgive, If of yon Porch which in the distance shows So vast and dim, unnoticed in thy Rhyme, I dare to make of thee inquiry brief, Touch'd with a strange and growing interest, Whither it leads, what comes or goes thereby. HERMIT. Know, Pilgrim, then, besides the Western door Thou sawest first, the Minster hath two gates, Which, opening out upon th' unseen abyss, Entrance the one, the other exit gives To nature's forms. Within the Nave they stand, Southward and Northward upon either side, Facing each other, and to each its Porch Attach'd, whereof the Southern one is named The Porch of Life, for thereby entrance find Organic things in their predestined mould Into the world of sense; its opposite, The Porch of Death, and thither all again They tend; for, coming forth from the unknown, And having wrought, each in its several shape, Their task assign'd, straightway they onward go, Absorb'd into their several elements, (Save what of man substantially endures Imperishable by divine decree) Through Death's dread Portal to the gulf again. Yonder it looms, so drear and shadowy, On the left hand, before thy very gaze! PILGRIM. Ah! e'en from here Methinks I feel its chilly influence. And now, as I remember me again Of that sharp fever which I had of late Nigh unto death, and of the wanderings strange Wherein my soul was borne; Within myself I seem to recognise That I to that same Porch In spirit was led on By Sickness, vision pale: And in its solemn vestibule did stand, And there half-open'd spied The unrelenting door; And felt the outer air from the abyss Breathe coldly on my cheek; And in the dimness saw, Where all amid the ever-vanishing crowd Death solitary sate, wrapt in his sable shroud. Ah, then my step Had all but slipp'd, Its footing lost and gone, And I unto myself had said: ‘The world's inhabitants No more shall I behold, Nor Nature's gladsome brow;’ But One to me did reach his hand, And drew me back to light and life again, That I might better serve him, so to win His pardoning grace before I pass away. Now of that other Porch, The Porch of Life, I fain would something know, For it I have not seen. HERMIT. Thou sawest it once And passedst through it, but rememberest not, For it was in thy new-born infancy; A wondrous spot, the womb of all that lives. Upon this Southern side its station is, Beyond our present view: No blasts of winter there Chilling the air; No darkness dwells, nor spectral forms are seen, But evermore an atmosphere serene Thrills on the sense; and a strange stir of joy Admitting nought that grieves Or genders any pain, Prevails, as of unnumber'd opening leaves In a warm hour of April sunshine coy, After the falling rain; While Hope for ever guards the gate, And Angels of the Morn attendant wait. PILGRIM. O Hermit blest, But I would yet one question ask, If me thou wilt not chide. Lo! now from Death's dread Gate Granted for once reprieve, Too certainly I know the day draws nigh When I a second time must thither go, And back return no more To this terrestrial strand, But onward wend across the solemn sea, Whose other shore is our eternal land. Then in the formless deep Plunging without a hold On aught to nature known, What may my soul betide Immortal borne along, Ofttimes I shuddering meditate, Conscious of ill-desert and fill'd with fears untold. Oh, say, if there be not some other door Whereby we may go forth And find a surer way Across the illimitable dim profound? HERMIT. Thou speakest well; such door indeed there is; But in the Choir it stands, Far distant from this spot, Upon the further side of yonder screen, Within the Lady Chapel, at the back Of the High Altar. A postern-gate it is Of pearly semblance, and once open'd leads Right out upon the arch that Heavenward spans Th' impalpable abyss. But so withdrawn it lies, That many pass thereby and see it not. Moreover, though the door was in its place Since first this Minster rose, Yet only of late years Hath it to human effort open been; For ever since the Fall Closed it remain'd by double bolts outside, Which none might draw, there being no way thither Save by a circuit long, First through the Gate of Death, And then all round, coasting the outer edge Of the great Minster wall, Till to the back ye came; And this no man might do: For each no sooner pass'd the gate of death Than down at once he sank In the sheer nameless deep, Quite impotent upon the void to tread; Therefore long time the pearly door was closed. Yet by tradition in part, In part by instinct, to lost Adam's race The secret way was known, And whitherward it led. This prompted men to search, And many were the schemes Which fancy or philosophy devised, Or round the gulf to pass and draw the bolts, Or else the gate to force, Or through the wall to cleave some other road. But all in vain was tried; To Heaven's high pinnacles no path was found, Until Emmanuel came, Predicted of our race, Of Virgin Mother born, Mighty in word and deed, Prince and High-Priest and Sacrifice in one. He of his own accord Did through the grave and gate of death proceed, And entering on the void, Trod with firm foot th' unsearchable expanse, As on the sea of Galilee before; Till passing round, up to that door He came, To th' hinder part, and there both bolts withdrew, Opening the way of everlasting life Thenceforth to mortal man! Oh, day of victory! How with triumphant notes This Minster did resound! What music then was heard through earth and Heaven! Sweeter by far than at Creation's dawn, When all the morning stars sang out for joy! PILGRIM, bowing his head. All praise to Him who wrought this wondrous work, At price of His own Blood! Oh, lead me on, That I at once that heavenly door may see, That arch may climb, and fleet away From earth without delay To the clear realms of immortality. HERMIT. Thy time is not as yet. The Lord hath work For thee below. O Pilgrim, here we part; But let these words sink in thine inmost heart: If thou that door wouldst see Unclose to thee, Long must thou toil, and patient must thou be, And bended oft thy knee; Confiding still in nothing of thine own But in the grace of thy dear God alone. EPILOGUE. Farewell, a long farewell, O Minster green, Dim haunt of olden time! Where with our Pilgrim I have wandering been;— Thou in thy strength sublime Shalt still abide; nor be by me forgot, Though, veil'd from earthly sense, I see thee not. Thee oft the gather'd clouds reposing Over the sunset's crimson closing, Thee oft the forest aisle to mind shall bring; Of thee the mossy cell In lonely woodland dell, Of thee the winds shall tell, Of thee the budding Spring! Thy front of gold Through the faint flush of morn I shall behold; Thy chant shall hear in ocean's roar Still echoing on for evermore! Now to Him who all hath made Everlasting praise be paid. The time for Him it draweth near In His own Temple to appear: All Creation shall be dumb When in His glory He shall come. Who then may stand His face to see? In that day, Jesu, pity me!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ODES. I. TO THE POWERS OF THE UNIVERSE. Benedicite, omnes Virtutes Domini, Domino. Hail, Powers sublime, all hail! Which in the natural or spiritual worlds, Or here, or in far space, Or in the far infinity beyond, His wondrous work perform; Of whom ye are, and whom Inanimate or animate, ye serve! Hail, first to you, Dread armies of the Lord! Ye glorious Seraphim and Cherubim! And Thrones sublime! Ye countless Dominations, Virtues, Powers! Ye Principalities! Archangels bright! And Angels ever blest, In solemn order ranged! Hail, Spirits of the Just, Whose prayer is strength! Prophets, Apostles, Martyrs of all time! Virgins, and Confessors, and Pontiffs good! In purest bliss Reigning with Heaven's high Queen! Next hail to you, Great powers of this our sphere!— Or who in Holy Church, Regents of Christ, His Sacraments dispense, And jurisdiction wield, Priesthood, Episcopate, and higher still St. Peter's central throne— Or who on chair of civil state Seated supreme, High o'er the stormy world Your iron sceptres wave, Types of His reign to come! Hail, too, O ye, Grand movers of mankind! Sages and Poets dear, Heroes of land and sea! Of Art the lords! And under whatsoever name or form, O Genius, all thy sons! Ye! chief of all! Or great as known to fame, Or greater still unknown, Th' Inventors of the world! By whose laborious search High Providence through ever-widening ways This human scheme evolves. Nor of thyself, O Mind, Unmindful here be thou, Nor of thy powers and faculties divine;— Intelligence supreme! Thought, Memory, Will, Conscience, Imagination, Feeling, Sense! Choice flowers of life! By grace yet lovelier made. Ye last, all hail! Dim Forces, which mankind The Powers of nature call, Thou, Instinct deep! Pure mystery of God! Reigning amid the worlds of living things! And thou, great sister Force! Of Gravitation named, Sovereign amid material elements! Nor less ye other kindred Influences Unsearchable in might, And divers in your kinds! Which in the earth and water, fire and air, From hour to hour Your silent task fulfil! All these, and many more yet unreveal'd Or in the book of Nature or of God, Each within each involved, Wheel within wheel in many-mingled maze, (Like that strange vision which Ezechiel saw By Chobar's mystic stream) All these, where'er they be, Confess thine hand, O Lord; And here, or in far space, Or in the far infinity beyond, Not of themselves, But in Thee only, and for Thee exist, Dread emblems of Thyself, who all hast made! Thou the beginning and the end of all! Nor know we aught, Where each its issue finds, Or in the other merges; nor can guess The proper essence of the very least; So dense our ignorance Of that untold, immeasurable abyss, In which Creation moves! Save that at times of some vast scheme We catch the vanishing glimpse, as in a dream; And hear at intervals a tone Wafted down from spheres unknown, Telling of things diviner far Than any that around us are! II. TO THE SKY. Benedicite, cœli, Domino. O sea of thoughts! Wave upon wave Of mystery and wonder without end, Borne in upon my soul! Casting her upward glance on yonder breadth Of unsupported dome In viewless joinings knit; Yon azure firmament, The ocean incorruptible Of space immense, Beyond all suns and spheres, Beyond the starry depth, Beyond attenuate ether's utmost bound, Stretching its onward way! O dreary solitude!—O mystic realm Of primal chaos!—Distance infinite!— Where e'en imagination drops her wing!— O barrier unconceived! Dissever'd equally From spirit as from sense! Blue mirror of bright Heaven! Which from beneath we mortals gaze upon; Whose upper coast,—creation's table-land— Is that great sea of glass Which makes the pavement of th' eternal throne! O void unsearchable of depth and height! Up whose unfathom'd vistas as we glance, The outskirts of dim immortality Loom on the trembling gaze; As when within the eye Searching deep down by mirror's aid, We seem the soul to see Coil'd up and basking in her own eternity! Praise thou the Lord most high, All-spanless sky! Whose everlasting Hand Has, like a tent, thy veil cerulean spread! Praise Him, ye Heavens! Praise Him, ye waters, that above the Heavens Extend your awful shade! Proclaim, proclaim, The glory of His Name, Thou light, that flowest in a flood divine! Declare His praise Through ceaseless nights and days, Ye stars, that like the Saints in glory shine! O that to me were given To blend my voice with your ecstatic song! And through the spheres of Heaven The peal of jubilation to prolong! And what though stars there be, Wandering through space, Rayless and dead, Consign'd to blackest night for evermore? O let not such Be my sad lot, I pray, When on my vision fades this earthly day; But set me, Lord, amid Thy living orbs, Though dimmest there, Though least of all In that vast galaxy; Yet counted Thine, and number'd with Thy Saints! And ever be my place, Not amid heathen constellations old, Arcturus, Pleiads, or Orion huge, But in that saintly cluster of bright stars New found of late in the new hemisphere, Thy Cross, O Jesu! Crowning the arch of night! The glory of the islands of the South! Greeting, in pagan climes unknown, With a thrice welcome and familiar smile, The weary wanderer on ocean tide. III. TO THE EARTH. Benedicat terra Dominum, laudet et superexaltet eum in sæcula. O Earth, from whose dread womb I, after wandering long In faithful miner's charge, With joy at last Once more emerge upon the sunny sward, Weary and travel-stain'd! Declare, declare, Within thy secret depth what marvels dwell, Marvels by us unguess'd, Who walk thine upper shore. For many such thou hast, as well I know, Or spiritual, or of material kind; Dread Angels subterrene, Mighty in works of ill; Brute things, of which In learned book no form or name appears; And wrought in thousand shapes Down thy long avenues of grottoes fair, A hidden growth of secret substances, Whereof our brightest gems but tokens are; And rivers of strange fire, Far underneath, Preparing, day by day, a second flood; And treasures all untold Of virgin gold, Which evermore from man thou dost withhold; And cities underground, A multitude of mansions widely spread, Where rest in sleep profound Th' unbusied nations of the countless dead! A labyrinth sublime, Down whither, through all time, But one alone Descending, hath been known Again in his own strength The re-ascending stair of life to climb. But for marvels why explore, O Earth, thy hidden central core? We but thine outer rind beholding, New wonders see for ever there unfolding. There are the waters gather'd into seas, Broad continents and isles, Rivers and lakes, and ever-shifting breeze Dimpling thy face with smiles. There are the forests tall, The cultured landscape green, Rock, grove, and waterfall, Blue skies serene, And of the seasons blest the gently varying scene. While ever round thee, in their silent flight, Fair day and solemn night Each after each proceed, Unwearied pilgrims, scattering on their way Or sun-bespangled ray, Or dewy darkness answering nature's need; Waking to toil, or folding into rest, Ten thousand peoples shelter'd on thy breast. But chiefly me, O Earth, thy mountains fill With wonder at His power and skill, Who piled aloft their soaring height, As monuments of His eternal might!— Or verdurous with groves, Or bleak with barren crag, Silver'd with snow, or capp'd with roaring flame; All they alike their great Creator Lord proclaim. Hail Etna fair! Hail leafy Apennine and Pyrenees, Athos, and that vast range Carpathian named, Taurus and Caucasus, Olympus, Himalaya, Atlas old, Historic Alps, Andes, and Apalachian heights sublime! Hail, too, O ye The mountains of our God! Which of His glory saw in ancient days! Thou patriarch Ararat! Thou, Mount of Vision, dear for Isaac's sake! Sinai and Hor, Carmel and Lebanon, and many more! And ye, diviner still, Earth's choicest Heights, Whose verdant slopes were press'd By the blest footsteps of the Son of Man, Fair Olivet, with Sion's holy hill, And Thabor's flowery floor, And Galilee's dear Mount without a name, Where Christ new risen to His Apostles came! Thus, O Earth, upon thy face I a thousand wonders trace; Wonders old and wonders new Ever springing into view! And oft in meditative song Musing, as I walk along, On th' interminable design Shown in nature's work divine; Musing upon the tide of times untold, When o'er the mountain tops primeval ocean roll'd, I marvel if, by slow degrees, Thou, Lord, didst into land convert the seas; Or rather in its present state By one sheer act the whole create! Yet this I know, and this proclaim, That unto Thee it was the same, Or in a moment all to frame, Or to elaborate the whole by stages, Through the long growth of million million ages. Wherefore howe'er the work was wrought, All praise be Thine, who all hast made; All praise be Thine, who all hast bought, With the price Thy Lifeblood paid; What time descending from the empyreal height, Thou who creation with Thy finger framedst, Begotten God of God, and Light of Light, The uncreated Word, created flesh becamest! O great Incarnate Lord of earth and sea, What love, redoubled love, thus oweth man to Thee! IV. TO THE HEAT AND COLD. Benedicite ignis et æstus Domino; benedicite frigus et æstus Domino. Ye Heat and Cold! Creatures most opposite! Betwixt you twain ofttimes In a strange doubt I stand, Which out of which proceeds; Nor what ye are, nor whence, Can I at all divine, Unversed in natural things; Yet have I learnt Not to this globe your office to confine, Ranging through space, Beyond where eye can trace, Or thought the goal assign. And each invisible In its own nature seems; Yet hath from God its own investiture And special outward robe, Wherein from ancient days itself it shows: Thou, Heat, in flame appearing; thou, Cold, in ice and snows! All for the sake of our poor mortal being, By mercy's heedful law; Lest we not seeing, Nor of their presence warn'd, too near should draw, And perish quite extinct in their devouring maw! And Heat a docile creature doth appear, Though violent at times; And we abuse her as our bondslave here, And tool of countless crimes; Fashioning thereby a thousand things Which better for our souls had never been: Who, soon unchain'd, shall us and all consume, The partner of our guilt and of our doom. But the Cold dwells apart, Inflexible and stern in his own place, Seated on high, Beneath the upper sky, In regions calm and still, Where evermore he worketh his own will, And changeth not for us his rigid face; Nor unto man himself will bend, Either to be his servant or his friend: Save when in downy snow O'er the raw glebe he deigns his cloak to throw; O power of Love divine to tame him so! That one, who doth for earth so little care, Thus should lend his mantle rare, Earth's tender things to pity and to spare, And of this mantle much I might unfold, Wrought on angelic loom in days of old, How, mindful of its heavenly birth, No stain it takes of earth, But presently returns to Heaven again; On this vile sod That bears the curse of God, Unable to remain: Or how, with curious eye, If we but venture in its folds to pry, Seeking the woof to find Which through its maze doth wind; Scarce with a finger's tip Have we begun the delicate web to trace, Woven in crystal pure, When lo, the skein Beneath our mortal touch dissolves apace, Unwilling to endure Aught that its virgin whiteness might profane! O emblem clear to all Of our sad fall! Oh that of sinful flesh so great should be the bane! V. TO THE DEW AND RAIN. Benedicite, imber et ros, Domino. Ye Dew and Rain! How pleasant is your task, who, hand in hand, Tend the green innocent herbs With your blest ministries! Dear brethren are ye both; But dearer thou, O Dew, the elder born! For later came the rain, Rough in his ways, and sometimes harmful found, As suits a ruin'd world. But the soft dew, it is a patient thing, Quiet of spirit, ever doing good, At no time harm; And pitiful for man and nature's fall; Ministering unseen through midnight hours To fainting mortal things! Offspring of Eden days! In whose clear globe Eden is faintly seen reflected still! Yet pleasant too, art thou, O Rain, at times; And there has been, when I have loved to sit On some high crag, Watching thine armies scour The breadth of vale below; As, troop by troop, they swept With cloudy flags unfurl'd, Muster'd in distant climes, Or wild Norwegia, or Siberian waste, Or melting Polar snows, Atlantic deep, or wizard Egypt's shore, Children of many lands and many tongues, Under one law, United each with each In solemn contract of self-sacrifice, To fertilise the world with their sweet blood! O Dews! O Showers! Praise Him, who you ordain'd; Praise Him with me, and I with you, Friends of my early days! And God forefend Judea's lot be thine, dear British Land! Though stain'd with guilt of deadliest sacrilege, Still not as yet of God forsaken quite. A glorious clime was hers, Nurtured in morning dew and evening shower, The promise of her Lord. But Oh, her children slew their Lord; And evermore since then, Up from the guilty soil His Blood has cried, And year by year her Heav'n hath dried o'erhead, Till all her sky is brass; Nor through long arid months Or dew or rain descend, Save where, in nook forlorn, Faith far retiring The penitent tear outpours For Sion's evil deeds; There still, they say, the golden floweret springs, The rain-drops fall, And balmy dews distil; To show that e'en in vengeance mercy lives! VI. TO THE SEASONS. Benedicite, sol et luna, Domino. What strain was that, Soft as a blossom's fall, Which sang but now at my heart's open door? Came it from earth? Or rather from some Cherub had it birth? Of Spring its burden was, Spring green and glad; Sweet remnant left of happy Eden days: Next of the Summer-tide; Of Autumn next; and then of Winter sere;— Weaving a web of praise all through the livelong year! For lovely are the Seasons in their turn (So went the song)— Lovely, and speak Thy love, O Thou, who all hast made. Lovely the Spring, When forth she trips upon the dewy lawn, With hope and joy irradiant in her smile; And, warbling as she goes, Scatters, with liberal hand, Treasures of Paradise on all around. And lovely thou, O Summer, jasmine-crown'd! Blossom of Spring! Who out of Spring dost bud Into an odorous flower! Unmark'd the transformation, day by day, Till, lo! the Spring is gone, and in her place We see thy jocund face Peeping above the shoulders of bright May! Then would we have thee evermore to stay: But, lo! with solemn tread Stalks Autumn in his robe of many dyes; And, soon as he his magic wand applies, Shade after shade, Nature begins to fade, And into evanescence goes her way, Loveliest of all perhaps, in her decay. Anon comes Winter, and locks up the door, Till Spring returns again, to vanish as before! These are Thy works, O Lord! By Angel-hands Divinely minister'd to this our globe; Thy works in silence wrought; (In silence all great things Do evermore proceed); And still, while earth shall stand, Standeth Thy promise sure, That seed-time, harvest, cold and heat, Sunshine and rain, shall evermore endure, For man to sow his glebe, and reap his grain secure, O gracious love! that no abatement knows, But to unjust and just unceasing mercy shows! And many are the joys beside, Which in their turn belong (So went the song) To all the several Seasons as they glide; God with his goodness garlanding the year, And with all-bounteous art Setting the one against the other part, That so no time may be From grateful praises free. Thus, lest in Winter it should grieve the mind To see the wreck that Summer leaves behind, Lo! then the Saviour's birth comes round, To deck with second Spring the ground. And lest in Spring too much we should rejoice, And make this earth the Eden of our choice, Lo! then Mount Calvary And its dread Cross are present to the eye: Almost we hear Him groan, and see Him die! While in each Season, did we but attend, We might detect the warning of a friend; Each as an Oracle, O Lord, of Thine, Reminding us, in turn, of truths divine:— Autumn, of life's decay; Winter, of death's still tomb; Spring, of the Resurrection Day; Summer, of Heaven's own bloom! VII. TO THE FLOWERS. Benedicite, universa germinantia in terra, Domino. Green things, green things of Earth! Bless the Lord evermore; Him praise who gave you birth, And magnify His goodness o'er and o'er; The bounties undeserved, Which He from age to age doth on his creatures pour. Green things, green things of Earth! Brief is your span In this our latter time; Unlike that earlier state, When first in Paradise your life began In nature's happy prime! For Adam's sake the world a curse doth wear, And in his fall ye share. O, partners in one doom! Betwixt our races twain be friendship true; Give us of your bright blooms To deck our tombs, And we in your short lives will honour you. All honour to all flowers Of every hue! Thou, Heaven! give showers; And thou, O Earth! give dew; Thou, Sun! give heat; thou, Light, thyself distil, Till every tint hath drunk of thee its fill! While I, beneath the sylvan shade Of some deep umbrageous glade, Sitting on the grassy ground, Sing to the Angels all around; Praising the meadows green, With rills that run between, And cowslips' heads just seen: Praising the primrose sweet, And purple violet, And gorse of golden hue, And hyacinthian blue Beneath the forest high Spread like a mimic sky;— Praising their great Creator Lord, Who made them what they are, Whose Love the Heavens outpour'd, And of the smallest daisy hath a care. And ofttimes on His word divine Meditating, line by line, And in the bud's unfolding flower Tracing His eternal power, I praise the rod, which, dead before, Its blooming tufts of almond bore; I praise the hyssop on the wall; I praise the cedar's branching hall; I praise the lily's fair attire Which Jesus bids me to admire, Setting such a lowly thing Above the pomp of Israel's King! Anon before my fancy lie Branches green of palm and bay, Scatter'd thick along the way Where Christ is passing by; And, presently, methinks I see, All in moonlight shadows rise The garden of Gethsemane Slowly before my tearful eyes; O place most mystical and dread! From whence the Lord to death was led; O, place unlike to Eden's bowers, Where life was lost to us and ours! Straightway, O Eden, at thy name My heart is in a flame, And fires with thirst of thine abyss of shade, Long cloister'd alleys green, Cascades half seen, Flower-woven paths for feet immortal made! Oh, for that day of days, When all again shall happy Eden be! When earth shall one triumphant pæan raise; When Paradise shall stretch far as the land and sea! For this, O Lord, creation groans to Thee! Oh, quickly come to save the people of Thy choice! Then shall the grass be glad, and all the trees rejoice. VIII. TO THE WINDS. Benedicite, omnes spiritus Dei, Domino. Sweet Breeze, all thanks to thee, Who, as but now upon the grass I lay, Leaving thy comrades gay, Didst round about me play; And fanning with thy balmy breath my cheek, Didst in mine ear most eloquently speak; Leading me on, as through a meadow bright, With tinted flowers bedight; And still fresh-budding memories didst bring, Cull'd from my boyhood's spring, And lay them at my feet In many a posy sweet, Delighted in my heart of early times to sing. For much I loved the winds in my young days; Whereof thou, Breeze, aware, Didst take my spirit up, And in thy lap transport her back again To times of youth gone by; When in the clouds aloft My swooping kite they bore; Or blew my ship across the mimic waves; Or lull'd me half asleep, With deep Eolian murmurs of the pines; Or swept the thistledown across the plain, Mocking my pursuit void; Or for my pleasure lash'd the cornfields up Into a troubled sea, I gazing down from some hill-side the while! Of these things, then, O Breeze, Most sweetly didst thou sing, From thought to thought Leading me unawares. Nor of thy Mother Air Wast thou without thy tale; Nor of the numerous brethren whom thou hast, Through the world's quarters spread: Far different from herself, As oft in children seen: She evermore the same; A changeful people they! For tranquil is the Air, In her own nature view'd; God's wondrous instrument Of manifold design, Answering to many ends! A harp invisible, Rich with unnumber'd tones! A magic scroll, on which the tongue of man Writes at his will irrevocable words! A mirror of our thoughts By speech reflected forth! Our life-blood's food! A censer laden with all Nature's incense! A treasure-house of dew and quick'ning showers! The fuel of all fires! A crystal screen betwixt the sun and earth, Blending all rays, and melting light's sharp edge! An ocean all unseen, This earth encircling round, Wherein we walk, and know it not, As men upon the bottom of the deep! A globe immense, Receptacle of Nature's divers forms, Abode of countless mutabilities, Itself from age to age The same abiding still! But restless are the winds her progeny, Restless, and full of change; Motion their life, in motion evermore, Strange creatures, and a marvel in their ways! Various their haunts! More various still the tempers they display, Constant alone in their inconstancy! Now freezing cold, From the far wintry pole; Now breathing warm and rich From spicy climes; now sharp with arrowy sleet Of Tartary; now booming loud and long Portentous of the coming hurricane; Now gentle as a lamb; Now rudely blustering, or fiercely vex'd, And now most sweetly sad; Anon quite mad they seem At window-casement heard, As though an entrance forcing for themselves; Wild raving beasts of night! Listening to whom The sick man cannot sleep; Or if he sleep, 'tis vain,— In dreams they follow still. Yet e'en in this they work Thine ends, O Lord; And Thou to each hast given Its immemorial tone; Whereby it preaches to the heart of man, Concerning deeds long past, And Judgment sweeping nigh, Reminding conscience of forgotten things Amidst the midnight storm! IX. TO A SPRING. Benedicite, fontes, Domino. Sweet Fount, that from the bosom of the glebe Dost evermore thy mother-milk distil To the poor fainting babes of vernal things! Bright eye of earth, Always to Heav'n upturn'd, Glistening serene! Thee of all spots around I cherish most; Not for thy purity alone beloved, But for the sake of pleasant musings past Beside thee oft indulged. Here still retiring, In a chance leisure-time, I love to sit upon thy margent green, And watch the dancing of those golden sands, Thy natural hour-glass! For thereby, as I guess, Thy gracious issue dost thou regulate, From year to year Still, hour by hour, Running eterne! O say, dear Fount, O say, Through what strange windings to the upper day Thy limpid waters flow?— For nought of this I know; Save what to me, of wonders there, Truant Fancy may declare; When from wandering at will Down amid thy grottoes still, Back she comes with many a tale Shrouded in a mystic veil, Of the curious works of eld There by her sole eye beheld! How beneath this surface green, In the heart of earth enshrined, Regions lovely and serene Hid for ever from mankind, Regions full of marvels new, Open on her trancèd view, Answering to the upper space, As in water face to face. Where beneath an opal sky, Emerald fields extended lie; Other hills and vales than ours Bloom with other trees and flowers; Silver lakes their mirrors bright Spread in amethystine light; Songs of birds salute the ear, Birds that ne'er on earth appear! Groves a greener foliage show; Roses all in ruby blow; Orchards bend with fruitage fair; Soft and spicy breathes the air; While the verdant lawns between, Dance along in sparkling sheen Living rills of chrystal clear, Changing into water here! Thus in my heart but now, Most limpid Spring! As on thy velvet sward I lay reclined, Did Siren Fancy sing, Rippling the quiet surface of the mind, With the soft wavings of her rosy wing;— But I, too oft As man and boy and child, By her fair tales beguiled, Rather to thy low murmurs would attend, Singing with thee His glory without end, Who set thee on this grassy mound To be a type to all around, Of that perennial love which no abatement knows, But still for ever on, still on for ever flows! X. A VISION OF ANIMALS. Benedicite, omnes bestiæ et pecora, Domino. Farewell to things material, void of sense, Unchanging elements of earth and sky! Welcome the breathing worlds, Of fabric subtler far, In which, O Life and Death, your mysteries dwell! Creatures of blood, With gifts unsearchable, Sensations quick, Instinct divine, Likings, dislikings, pleasure, pain, endow'd. Of such my vision was upon a day In summer-tide, beneath the forest boughs, Listless reclining on the perfumed sward. Endless the scenes, Polar or tropical, that went and came, Courting my vacant gaze; Endless the tribes Of bird and beast, which in those scenes appear'd; While now Norwegia's pines Bending with weight of snow, Now Cheviot's heathery hills before me lay; And now again, in undulations long, The verdant prairies stretching far and wide, Beyond the Western wave; Each with their busy races roaming wild. Endless the scenes; Endless the climates; endless, too, the praise By those unnumber'd denizens outpour'd To Him, their God unknown, In whom they move and live. I saw the cedars tall Of which the Psalmist sings, Glory of thy green haunts, O Lebanon! I saw them cluster'd thick with various birds;— Highest of all, the hern Had poised her stormy nest. Then glistening rose A fair Pacific Isle, With graceful ferns adorn'd, and scented shrubs; Where, amid blossoms of a thousand dyes, The joyous humming-birds, More brightly tinted still, Like gems upon the wing their sport pursued, Glancing from spray to spray, Through the clear sunny ray, In the full zest that springs of natural solitude. Anon the eagle stands High on a jutting crag, That o'er the desert looks: There I espied her, with her savage mate, Their lofty eyry build; There lay her eggs, and hatch her bristly brood. No food has she at hand. But lo, meanwhile, From earth's far ends two hostile armies draw: Prescient of carrion near, She for her starving nestlings feels no fear; Soon all amid the slain are they, Sucking the blood of kings! The peacock next, Fanning his goodly plumes, His aureole display'd. Upon a broken urn, Relic of ancient days, Graceful he stood, the rainbow amid birds! Then came the mystic dove, Her silvery feathers all bedropp'd with gold, Sliding she came, down the smooth circling stair Of yielding atmosphere, nor stirr'd a breath With her becalmèd wing. I look again; And lo, 'tis all a void of blue expanse,— A reach of azure sky, Interminably spread! Then comes a sound of myriad beating wings, And through the thin aerial solitudes, An army strong, The swallows voyage along; In instinct's faith sublime, Seeking another clime, Not knowing whither bent, as he of olden time! All in a rush I see them onward sweep;— Then from far down below, Ascending slow, Swells up the peal of the Atlantic deep! Anon a beauteous range of mountain-tops Courts my delighted gaze, Where the wild goats are seen, Feeding at will Upon the ridges green, Their pasturage of old; While slowly sails the condor overhead. Then on its tide, Like a broad flowing stream, The vision bore me on, And brought me to an English homestead sweet, Long years ago Pictured on memory's page; Where in the yard, Thick laid with wholesome straw, I see four oxen stand, Feeding at early dawn. Hard by, the calf, responsive to its dam, Lows from within the stall; While, from half-open stable-door, Pipes merrily the ploughboy's whistle shrill, Mimic of blackbird's note. Then forth the team is led, Sleeky and slow; and, hardly past the gate, Is met by our old shepherd and his son, From midnight watch Returning, nipp'd and raw, their dog behind. But ah! what sounds of fear Are these that smite mine ear? 'Tis night—the moon is up— And from the forest's dense obscurity, In gusts are borne Howlings of savage beasts, whose fiendish forms, Betwixt the glimmering stems, Glance by at intervals, Fleetly careering After their panting prey. Trembling, I hear and see; but lo, With the first streak of dawn, Each to his den they wend; Or fossil cave—or hollow of the pine— Or ruin'd tower of eld; And there, among their cubs The spoil dividing, lay them down in peace? Then in my sight a tufted palm-tree stood, Shading a grassy track, That by a tinkling rill its course pursued. There, on the pathway green, A dead man in his pool of blood is seen; The sunbeams twinkling with the twinkling leaves Upon his face serene. A saddled ass is grazing at his side;— While o'er him stands erect And motionless the mighty forest-king; His eye in secret fascination set; His tail and shaggy mane Rigid as bronze:—the sun is mounting high, Yet there he stands In the same place; nor hurteth ass or man. Fades the quick-shifting scene; and in its stead A dungeon spreads its gloom; Upon whose floor, Noisome with human gore, Sits holy Daniel, and feels no fear, An Angel watching near; While round and round, without a sound, Lions and lion's whelps in ceaseless maze career. Then lo, a wilderness, Broken in jagged rocks, and all besprent With prickly weeds; where horrid beasts of prey, In the broad light of day, Are roaming terrible as Satan's brood, Tainting with noxious breath that awful solitude; And all amid the howling crew, Victim of day's hot glare, and night's envenom'd dew, One with a thorny crown Appeareth, kneeling down!— Ah! wherefore kneels He there, In fast and prayer? Before eternity outstretch'd her wings, Lord of lords, and King of kings! Next from a vague abyss, up swam Strange shadowy forms Of mystic beasts by ancient Prophets seen; He foremost, erst beheld on Chobar's margin green, With fourfold wing and face, and living wheels between Anon, as in the Apocalypse, I stood Upon a sandy shore; And lo, a beast from out the ocean rose,— Seven heads he had, ten horns, And on each horn a crown; Leopard in form, With lion's mouth, and paw of grisly bear. I saw him mount upon th' horizon's edge, A dim and fearful thing; I saw the nations darken in his shade. Forthwith the serpent coils his slimy way, Enormous stretch'd along In folds without an end. Then fiery coursers smote my sight; And lo, Elias soars, rapt in his car of light! XI. A VISION OF WATERS. Benedicite, maria et flumina, Domino. Sitting within her secret vestibule (Those windows closed through which the outward world Admittance finds) this spirit saw pass by, As on the sheeted surface of a wall, In bright dissolving views, a lengthen'd train Of scenes depicted in prismatic tints By quick Imagination's vivid art; Whereof a portion, reader, for thy sake Shall here be told; the rest is gone from me, Lost in oblivion's colourless abyss. At first, a glimmering mist; then, purring soft Within the secret chamber of mine ear, A murmur as of distant ocean-waves. Whereon the mist disparting shows far down A sea without a shore, o'er which the clouds Are floating high, with veins of ruby tinge Streaking the deep; while gently, here and there, O'er tracts of open sunshine and of shade, A thousand glistening billows rise and fall, Dimpling the face of ocean's solitude. But see, what form is this Which as a moving mountain breasts the waves, Borne without mast or sail? A ship, yet not a ship; Rising in stories tier on tier, And by a shadowy Hand Guided upon its way. Thus as I gaze in wonderment, the clouds Conglomerate into a murky black; Down leaps the hurricane, up rise the waves, Rattles the thunder round, Ocean and atmosphere are blent in one! While towering waterspouts, That each might sink a nation's armament, In broad and foamy tracks Stalk o'er the broken level of the main. Ah, much I trembled then For thee, O Ark, now nearer in my view; For thee and for thy crew, That awful seed, sole remnant of a world, The hope of bird and beast and mortal man. I see thee toss'd upon the shivering waves Up to the clouds, then downward suck'd again Into the sheer abyss; ofttimes from sight Wholly withdrawn, unharm'd thou reappearest Upheaving a broad cataract of wave From thine emerging roof. Around thee swarm Spirits of darkness fresh from yawning hell, Spirtling their fiery insatiate wrath On thy defenceless head. But all in vain; for still that Hand of might (The same that on the Babylonian wall Wrote at a later day) Still o'er the trackless deep it thee upbears Unerringly along, Stemming the fearsome tide. Long do I watch thy track, And oft the rising and the setting sun Salute my anxious gaze; But still thy course is onward as before, Nor swerves one point From its predestined line. At last, from heaven Propitious calm descends, and swanlike sails Over the ruffled deep; All smooth the vast expanse As a bright mirror lies, where lovely Peace Might see her face and smile. Onward, O sacred Ark, thou movest still; Till on a little isle Grounding at length, thou settlest rooted there; A little isle at first— But all around the waters fast subside, And soon into a mountain-peak it soars, And lo, the Ark amid the skies is seen, With a bright rainbow shining o'er its head; While in the place of lately foaming waves A slimy plain appears; Slimy and dead, the ruins of a world! Anon the scene is changed, And other seas appear, and other times. A mighty gulf, Upon whose strand a multitudinous host Gathers of old and young; Arm'd myriads in their chariots of war Pursuing close behind; Then steps a chieftain forth, and with his rod Smites the white crest of an advancing wave; Whereat the trembling deep asunder parts And a broad sandy path is seen Betwixt the cloistering walls of waters green; Enters the foremost host, and passes on Safe to the further shore;— The second follows—and is seen no more! Then rose a gentle lake Before my raptured eye; A gentle lake with variegated shore Of rocky promontory, landscape green, Castles and towers and tranquil villages, With palm-groves here and there Fondling the quiet bays— And in the midst of that same gentle lake, A little ship with fishermen aboard, And One, who lies asleep Upon the pillow at the listless helm. Sudden there bursts a storm Spat from Satanic mouth, And under whirling foam The stricken bark is sinking, as I gaze; Then in their fear they wake that sleeping One, And He forthwith arising lifts His voice, Which o'er the billows onward borne Hushes them straight Into an infant's rest. I look again:— The self-same lake is there, Glistening beneath the moonbeam's silver shower; And lo, far out, He, whom I saw but now, again appears, A solitary shape! Striding across the fleet careering waves, With the same ease As on the green-sward of a quiet lawn! Then for awhile no vision came, as though Some curtain had been drawn; Patient I sit and wait,— When lo, a mass of many-mingled shades! Which slowly breaking up resolves itself Into a second train of ocean-scenes, Wherein the various tenants of the deep Before my curious gaze Their several parts perform. I see the porpoise o'er the stormy wave Wheeling intent along; I see the nautilus Expand her sail of gauze, And spread with mimic armaments the main. I see leviathan with scales of pride Stemming his hoary way. All these and many more Unwieldy sporting upon ocean's breast, Or drowsing in its caves, Or wandering restlessly from pole to pole, In turn attract my gaze; I mark their most exuberant joy of life, I mark their pastimes strange, And own in each a mystery divine. Anon all calm and still Before me lay the bottom of the deep A region unexplored, Where never yet came down The raving upper storms; Stirless abode of solitude profound! O'er whose white floor Strange glistening shells were spread, And gems without a name. There, 'mid the bulky stems of seaweeds tall, Whose ancient growth might antedate the flood, With fear I saw A mighty monster of an unknown fish, Dozing and motionless, Thy wondrous work, O Lord! Thick-ribb'd and strong he seem'd, With skin more rugged than the corky rind; On whom no sooner had I fix'd my glance, Than seems to shoot An Angel down, and whisper in his ear. Forthwith his fins strike out, And, as an arrow from the bow he darts Upon his order'd course. I mark him long through the clear underdepth Sweep on his silent track; Then suddenly to pause, His destined goal attain'd, And close beneath The gently-rippling surface, tranquilly His station taking wait the will divine. Nor waits he long: A storm is on the deep; A straining ship draws nigh; Toss'd from the deck, The Prophet sinks amid engulfing waves; Up springs the monster from his secret lair, And down his ghastly jaws Sucks his appointed prey. Ah, then all hope was o'er For thee, O Jonas, in thy fleshly tomb, Absorb'd without reprieve. I see thee downward borne, Downward and downward through the watery maze; Till on the bars thou touchest Of this compacted globe. Three days, three nights, Thy home is in the deep; Then at thy prayer, the Lord remembering thee, Sheer on the rocky strand The monster spurts thee forth, And to his solitary place returns Beyond the nether pole. Anon the scene is changed, and changed again; Till last of all appears, As at the first, a sea without a shore; Gazing whereon, I hear a trumpet-blast Peal from above; and lo, the ocean parts Like a rent scroll, and through its yawning clefts Up from their watery graves in clouds arise The multitudinous nations of the dead, From age to age Drown'd in the savage depth. In clouds they rise, Thick as autumnal mist; Myriads on myriads borne. Then comes insufferable darkness down, And sits on the abyss; And a voice cries, ‘There shall be sea no more!’ Whereat amid the black obscurity I hear a formless sound as of the deep Departing on its way:—then all is hush'd; Silence and ancient chaos fill the void. XII. THE PAST. Benedicite, noctes et diei, Domino. O Time, thou creature strange, Subtler than air, Who all things dost pervade, All things dost change, And of the whole a record dost preserve, Thyself unseen the while! Lo, as from out the depths Of some far eastern Archipelago Uprises firm, By toiling instinct raised Of million million insects unobserved, The curious structure of some coral-isle;— So thou, O Time, From out eternal deeps A wondrous world hast wrought, The fabric slow Of million million moments unperceived; For every moment lived its tiny life, Then solitary died, And dying, left behind Its fragment of the past; Till upward, lo, Emerging from th' abyss an isle appears, Which, shooting transverse forth, Is into grots and lengthening avenues Of mystic cloisters grown. Halls of the dead! Halls of the Past and Gone! Long corridors of years Mantling the bosom of eternity! Wherein we wander on at will, Led by historic muse along, And wonder at thy matchless skill, Patient heart, and labour long; Who o'er the level of th' eternal tide Hast spread a labyrinth so vast and wide; And built it up in such a wondrous way, Working from age to age by night and day; Nor built alone; but storied every wall With all that did from age to age befall. O registries sublime! O records of all time! What things untold Of new and old Have on your silent tablets been enroll'd! O dim archives of vanish'd nights and days, What thoughts ye raise In those who wander your lone aisles along! A twilight scene O'ergrown with ivy green, Where scarce a trembling ray can shoot between, Fit place for my sad song, For I would sing Of every earthly thing, How speedily it fleeteth to its close; How all our hopes and fears, Our smiles and tears, Thoughts, words, and deeds, With all that thence proceeds, And all that thither flows, In thee converge at last O solemn Past! Borne in a ceaseless flux which none may stay, And so remain, For glory or for bane, Irrevocably stamp'd until the Judgment Day! XIII. THE SOUL. Benedicite, spiritus et animæ justorum Domino. Of God, of Truth, of high celestial things, Methought one night I heard The Angel Watchers singing to themselves; Then sudden changed the strain, And took a mournful tone; As of the soul they sang:— Her origin sublime; How nobler far than elemental fire, Or air, or sea, or first-created light, Or immaterial principle unknown Of the brute race, or instinct's force divine, Or comet's wheeling orb, Or sun, or blazing star, She boasts a heavenly birth, A life immortal, incorruptible, From the pure fontal essence ever blest Of Majesty ineffable derived. O shame, to think that such a pearl of price Should all unvalued to the swine be cast By thankless mortal man! And marvellously was her nature framed, And still a wonder is, With awful powers endow'd; Conscience supreme! Clear Intellect, and Fancy's airy wand! Exhaustless Memory! Skill, and inventive power! Capacious Science which subdues the world! Pity soft-eyed! angelic Sympathies In boundless treasure stored! Genius sublime! Thought, Eloquence, Freewill! ‘O marvel of the world!’ (so went the strain) ‘Great miracle of majesty divine! Image of God, of Angels the high charge By life-blood of Incarnate God redeem'd! Bright ray of Heaven piercing this lower deep! Wherefore so dull become, ethereal soul! Forgettest thou to shine; but, soil'd and dim, Trailest in dust, the prey of earthly things? Ah, well may nature weep For thee her highest crown so lowly laid! Ah, well for thee May Angels mourn and all creation sigh!’ Then of Eternity The hidden warblers sang, Whereat a joyous burst throughout the concave rang; Anon 'twas sadness all, Telling of Adam's fall, Telling of sin and death which us thereby enthral. XIV. THE ANGELS. Benedicite, Angeli Domini, Domino. What honour hast Thou given To these sweet sons of Heaven, Whom for Thyself, O Lord, Thou didst create! What mercies hast Thou shown, Sending them hither down From age to age On gracious pilgrimage; Till Thou Thyself didst come in our estate: Then upon Thee it was their joy to wait! Oft as on them I muse, Revive those pictures bright, My infancy's delight, In ancient Bible cunningly portray'd; Which in transparent vivid hues Their past appearances from age to age display'd.— Now Jacob, pillow'd on his stone; While Angels o'er his head, By light from moonbeams shed, On crystal stair are wending up and down: Now Peter on his prison-floor, At the mid hour of night Waked by an Angel bright, To whom without a touch opens the iron door. Anon before my gaze The sheepfolds lie, all bathed in heavenly rays; While the hymn of Christ's glad birth, ‘Joy in Heaven and peace on earth,’ As once of old it downward stole, Sings in mine ear, and sinks into my soul. Then, all in mists of gray Fading away, The vision changes to a mantling gloom, And shows the dim interior of a tomb; Where on a stone Two Angels sit alone, Watching the hallow'd spot where Christ was laid, When he for human guilt the bloody price had paid. Risen and free, Himself I cannot see; Before mine eyes Folded apart the sacred napkin lies. Ah me, how still they sit, While silently before th' in-flooding Morn Night's shadows flit! One at the head, the other at the feet, Like Cherubim of old beside the mercy-seat! XV. AJALON. Benedicite, sol et luna, Domino. A gorge of green, That downward slopes two mountain crests between, Tranquil and hush'd in evening's lap serene!— Betwixt the heights the sun is sinking slow; While in the vale below The moon begins her silver orb to show, Brightening each moment into clearer glow. Like mists of night descending, In mingled masses blending, What swarms are these that hither downward pour? Conflicting hosts they seem; I catch their serried gleam, I hear, I hear, the distant battle's roar. And now far down the plain In one broad flow, A living sea they go; Pursuers and pursued, the slayers and the slain. Ah, 'tis the Amorrhite host, Beneath th' Almighty's sword By Israel's red hand into destruction pour'd! O quickly sink, thou Sun; Let darkness dun Wrap the world up in night, And hide from wrath divine the perishing Amorrhite! Why standest thou so still, O Sun, on Gabaon's hill; And thou, O Moon, in Ajalon's far vale; Each in your habitation of calm space Transfix'd? While time his race Suspends, and in his stead Eternity its solemn pall hath spread; Forestalling that great Day which brings the Judgment dread. And still the slaughter'd fall, the slayers still pursue, In the broad open day, Where midnight else had sway, Reaping the harvest ripe of deadly vengeance due. Josue, thy glory bright Excels all glory's height! O force of prayer! The sun upon his stair Pauses midway, as fearing to descend; The moon hangs motionless in air, As it were painted there, Till prayer hath wrought its end; Till Israel's foes In heaps of death repose. Then night and darkness to their place again Return, and silent reign; Proving by confirmation strong To all the ages all along, That whom Jehovah loves all nature must befriend; Whom the Creator hates no creature may defend. XVI. THE WORLD. Benedicite, filii hominum, Domino. O world, which evermore As in a swollen river's turbid tide Dost on and onward roll, How long, how long Shalt thou yet flow? How long the sons of Eve Into Hell's dismal ocean shalt thou sweep, An unresisting throng? Oh stream, augmenting ever by our loss! Oh stream, whose surges toss So high, scarce they escape who climb the Cross! As one who, on a rock That o'er the rising Danube looks afar, Planting his steady foot, Beneath him views the broad uproarious flood Resistless whirling its tumultuous prey; So to the table-land Of this calm solitude retired awhile, I, raised above myself, Seem from its sylvan height Thee to behold, O world, far down below; With all thy pomps and specious vanities, In eddies borne along without an end, An evanescent scene. Cities in whirlpools sweeping; Unnumber'd armies from all nations pour'd; Wharfs piled with merchandise; Kings' palaces in marble terraced high; Fountains and glittering domes; Castles and forts Bristling with cannons' teeth; Huge heaps of gold, Prisons and theatres, and crowds of men;— All these and many more, Life's phantom masquerade, Beneath my gaze in mazy circles speed. See in procession long The Pagan world go by, Baal and Astaroth and Remmon's car, With music wild, and shouts of drunken joy; Assyria, Media, Persia, Babylon, Egypt, and ancient Thebes. Ah me, what hideous rites! What fearful orgies drench'd in human blood, Man's blood in hellish sacrifice outpour'd! Such things I saw, and seeing, knew the world For an apostate from its Maker's creed, Though stamp'd on its own heart, And writ on nature's brow. Anon came whirling by old Greece and Rome, With all their arts sublime; Still far from Thee, O Lord. Beauty their idol; her in countless forms Their pleasure to adore; Spurning her Author and first Origin; Sensual their deeds, with a false glory crown'd. Long was the train That follow'd in their wake. Then seem'd the globe To spin upon its axis as I gazed; While land and sea together blent in one Like a broad ribbon show'd. So quickly time Coursed on its way. Anon 'twas darkness all; Which, presently dispersing, usher'd in The light of modern days,— The light of Intellect, false reason's ray! Upward from earth it came, Not downwards from on high: And lo, beneath its pale and haggard beam Sweeps roisterous along A democratic rout; Uproar and anarchy set loose from chains. Oh woe was me, what blasphemies I mark'd! Science run mad; Mammon in triumph borne; And nature's law set up in place of God. Methought the end was near; That surely Antichrist must now appear. Vanish'd the rabble rout in distance far, Borne on thy stream, O world; And now before me swam all pleasant things,— Mansions and fragrant groves; Arcadian lawns With groups of dancers fill'd; Banquets in halls of state; Bright throngs of revellers, enchanting forms Of youth and beauty, music's joyous bands, All sweets of this vain world, All pleasures, glories, riches, dignities. And ever as I gazed, within me rose A yearning strange and most insatiable, A yearning and an emptiness profound, Which nought of all I there beheld could fill. ‘O foolish heart,’ I thought, ‘that ever once You could have dreamt to find in these your rest! All in a restless scene; All amid phantom things That come and go, and go and come again, Fata Morgana of this fleeting world! Poor shreds of time, while thou eternal art! Adieu, adieu, Illusive pageantry! Adieu, adieu, False fleeting airy show! Speed on thy way, and with insidious smile Thy wretched victims into ruin sweep; But I, thy treacheries taught By sad experience, spurn thee from my breast, And thy allegiance evermore renounce, Insensate, heartless, empty, perjured world!’ Such were the thoughts, O Solitude divine, Which, as I sat upon thy mountain height Beneath a cloister of umbrageous pine, Upon me stole, what time before my sight The mists of eve were passing in review, Marshall'd far down the vale. Meanwhile the moon, Pale-glistening with a solemn-tinted hue, Above the forest lifted her fair head; Faded away the sunset-dyes, and soon, Dim spreading to the far horizon's verge 'Twas twilight all. Then in melodious swell, Inviting requiems for the faithful dead, Came floatingly, like some aerial dirge, The peal of ancient monastery bell, Rising and falling soft o'er distant flood and fell. XVII. THE SANCTUARY OF THE CHURCH. Benedicat Israel Dominum, laudet et superexaltet eum in sæcula. Farewell, a long farewell, Ye pomps and vanities of this false world, Vain-glorious systems and perverted ways! Welcome, ye shades serene, As by some heavenly screen Shut off from earth and earthlings' empty gaze! Welcome, true Israel, Where peace and justice dwell; Where in low cloister'd cell, Remote from scenes of pride, Faith, Hope, and Love may hide; Where prayer and praise are pealing evermore, While through the spacious ever-open door, In distance view'd, Appear th' eternal hills, glistening and golden-hued! Welcome, thou Church sublime, Founded from olden time, Far out upon the world's tempestuous tide; Which surging all around, Stirs not the rock profound, Rooted whereon thou dost from age to age abide! O place most blest, Foretaste of Heaven's own rest! Port where no billow rolls! True home of human souls! O Sanctuary rare of all creation, Worthy of endless praise and admiration! How oft thy glorious aisles along Vibrating with ecstatic song, Lost in Elysian dreams, I glide, Forgetful quite of all beside; Seeking with Jesus there to meet, And cast me down before His feet. How oft amid thy cloisters dim I seem to walk alone with Him, Marking His every word and deed, Of which in Holy Writ we read, In living colours ever new Set before th' entrancèd view! O place most bright, O'erflooded from the Fount of living Light! O place most sweet, For gentlest musings meet, And whispering with the tread of sainted feet! O place of pure repose, Which the world never knows; Where peace and penitence their joys disclose; Where whatsoever good was lost before Is found again, and found for evermore! All hail, new world of grace, That fillest up the space From man to Angel in th' ascent of things! Hail, sacred palace of the King of kings! Great mystery from generations hid, Outdating Egypt's eldest pyramid; Chantry kept secret since the world began In silent darkness seal'd; But now, according to th' eternal plan, To Faith reveal'd! Ah, what a waft divine Steals from thine inner shrine, As with hush'd step I draw me near! Ah, what a gently-breathing calm is here, Dropping around Like dew upon the ground, Soothing the soul with hope, and scattering all her fear! O, where true joy and rest, Where an untroubled breast, Save here with Thee, O Jesu, shall I find? Here in Thy living Church of ancient days, Which, all amid the world's quick-shifting maze, Thou hast on Peter built, a refuge for mankind! Here are Thy servants found; Here do Thy praises sound, Mounting above the world's tumultuous roar; Here man with angel vies, And earth with skies, Thee, Father, Son, and Spirit, to adore!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">POEMS. I. THE EASTER SHIP, A LEGEND. Dies venit, dies tua, In qua reflorent omnia. Lætemur et nos in viam Tua reducti dextera. All ye who lament o'er England's fall From the Holy Catholic Faith! Hear what the Hermit of Finisterre From his rocky eyry saith: Last of that ancient brotherhood, Who forth from Tintern's Choir, Were forced across the roaring seas By wicked Henry's ire! He saith, that early one Easter morn, In false Elizabeth's reign, Musing sadly o'er England's fall, He was looking out on the main; From his narrow ledge of beetling rock, Athwart the basaltic steep, That foremost stands confronting the swell Of the broad Atlantic deep; When he saw a Ship in the misty dawn Becalm'd on the silent sea; Her sails all drooping—her helm unwatch'd— As though no crew had she! From stem to stern so quaintly shaped, A ship of Eld it seem'd; Anon some birthling of the dawn, So goldenly it gleam'd. Then as he gazed, there suddenly burst A storm right overhead, So deadly black, at once he knew From Satan's breath it sped. And, lo! before his very eyes That Ship went sinking down; Till nought at last of hull or mast Was left but a spar alone;— The topmost spar!—whence gallantly still, In the face of the storm unfurl'd, Old England's Catholic ensign waved, The Cross that rules the world! Ah, then I thought that all was o'er; And I breathed aloft a prayer, For all who, with the sinking Ship, Were cruelly sinking there. When, lo! a wonder most strange to tell! But stranger far to see! A wonder I scarce could have believed, Had it been told to me! For scarce had the Cross the waters kiss'd, When, ere they could o'er it close, Slowly—slowly—it mounted again, And again the spar uprose;— And after the spar the three tall masts With sails of glistering white; And after the masts the Ship herself, With all her armoury bright. While softly and softly over the sea I heard a music pass, Soothing the winds and soothing the waves, Till they lay as molten glass; And in the East a vista began To open, fold in fold, Streaking all the ocean flood With veins of purple and gold. For now had risen the blessed Sun Of the Resurrection Morn; And his broad beam in one full stream Upon the Ship was borne: Whose deck one living topaz seem'd; Each mast, a sapphire bright; Each cord, of rainbow tissue wrought, Each sail, of sheeted light; The whole so wondrously appearing Transfigured before mine eyes, That the sight it fill'd my heart with tears, My soul with Paradise. Thus as I gazed, there stole along A softly fanning breeze, Breathing a solemn incense fresh From Isles of the Southern seas. The sails, they fill'd—the Ship she began To walk the waters o'er;— Full straight she steer'd;—full well I mark'd She steer'd for England's shore: While on her deck in the sun's bright ray There knelt, in place of a crew, A goodly company all in prayer, Whom for England's Saints I knew: Save Her who stood at the helm apart, With a calm majestic mien; And Her I knew, by her robe of blue, To be Heaven's immortal Queen! That Virgin Mother, who loves the Isle Where she was beloved of yore; That Virgin Mother, who loves it still, Though it loves Her now no more. O Vision of bliss!—She turn'd her head; She smiled benignly on me; Pointing her hand to my native land, Far Northward over the sea. Then faster and faster the vessel sped, O'er the breadth of the bounding surge; Till into a speck I beheld it fade, On the dim horizon's verge. Such was the Vision, divinely fair, That on Easter Sunday morn, I, the Hermit of Finisterre, Beheld at break of dawn. And twice again, in the next two years, Believe it as ye may, The selfsame thing at the selfsame hour I saw on the selfsame day. Now, therefore, ye who for England weep, As lost for ever to God, Down in the black and dismal deep Of heresy's awful flood, Give ear, give ear to this prophecy, Which, with his parting breath, The last of Tintern's exiled sons For your consolation saith. Three centuries shall England lie Beneath the storm of Hell; Three centuries her Church shall fade, And all but seem to fail; Three centuries her Saints shall mourn To see the Faith expire; Ivy shall climb and birds shall sing In many a ruin'd choir. But in the fourth, on Peter's chair A Pope shall sit and reign, Who in the Virgin's glorious might Shall turn the tide again. He first to all the world shall give The long-desired Decree Proclaiming our sweet Lady's gift Of peerless Purity. Shall name Her the Immaculate, Without a stain conceived; And stamp the doctrine as of Faith Immutably believed. She, in return, to Peter's crown Shall gratefully restore Its long-lost gem, the Isle of Saints, Far brighter than before; Cleansed with the blood of martyr'd priests, And virgins' holy tears, That must for guilty England flow Through many doleful years. Then shall the children think again Of their dear Fathers' home; And fly, as doves upon the wing, To long-forgotten Rome. Then shall the Abbey rear its head, And open wide its door, And lift its sacrificial chant, As in the days of yore. Then shall the glorious Cross of Christ No more dishonour'd lie; Then shall the throne of Britain mourn Its long apostasy; Then shall the sons of Scotia hide The wreck their fathers made; Then Celt and Saxon shall unite Beneath St. Peter's shade. Then rank in rank, and file on file, The armies of the Lord Shall march, to spread through England's breadth The Faith so long abhorr'd; Which, once received, shall forth again As from a centre sweep, Borne on the wings of England's fleets Across the trackless deep, To earth's remotest empires Now sunk in night forlorn; To Isles, and shoreless Continents Of nations yet unborn: Till such a harvest shall be reap'd, Beyond the world's belief, As shall console the Church of God For centuries of grief. E'en now, O England, I behold, With solemn pace and slow, Through thy long desecrated shrines The glad Procession go. I see the mitred Pontiff tread Their festal aisles along; I see the Crucifix o'erhead; I hear their olden song. The fragrant incense high aloft Its waving circlet weaves; And Heaven again into its fold Its erring child receives. O day, O blissful day, for thee How many saints have sigh'd! And only to behold thy face Most gladly would have died. O prayer of longing Christendom! O balm for sorrows past! What joy 'twill be when thou shalt come! As come thou shalt at last. Such is the hope that evermore My lonely spirit cheers. O Jesu! speed the time;—O speed The intervening years! And grant of Thy dear mercy, Lord, That when these things shall be, I, safe from my long pilgrimage In living light with Thee, May from the crystal battlements That day of days behold; And in the sight, for present grief, Rejoice a thousandfold. II. ST. KENELM'S WELL. Come, all of you, and sit around, And listen while I tell A tale from ancient chronicles About St. Kenelm's well: But first, good Christians, one and all, Upon the Saint in glory call. ChorusO sweet St. Kenelm, O sweet St. Kenelm, Pray for us! Pray for us, O sweet St. Kenelm. St. Kenelm's well, St. Kenelm's well, How calm and clear it flows! As when a thousand years ago By miracle it rose: So flows the stream of Faith sublime, For ever clear in every time. This land was ancient Mercia, Which far and wide you see; And Kenelm he became its king When seven years old was he: A fairer little prince, I ween, A holier child, was never seen. But oh! what will not envy do? This good and gracious boy A cruel sister had, who sigh'd His kingdom to enjoy; And so, to gain her wicked will, She plotted this sweet lamb to kill. St. Kenelm rose at early dawn, And prayed his little prayer; But from his tender infant cheek Had fled the roses fair; Then signing with the Cross his breast, He thus his aged nurse address'd: ‘O Ella, dear, this morn I dreamt I stood upon a tree, All in a flush of blossoms bright, When down it fell with me; And like a bird I soar'd away:— Now read to me the dream, I pray.’ ‘Ah, sweetest child, the dream I read,’— Thus made the nurse reply; ‘Cut off in virtue's early bloom, I fear me thou must die; But like a bird thy soul shall mount, To sip and sing at glory's fount.’ St. Kenelm clapp'd his little hands, ‘God speed the time,’ quoth he; ‘I've often pray'd that I might go With holy Mary to be. One sight of Christ in glory clear Is better than a kingdom here.’ That eve they led him sporting forth Across the woodland wild, And there, beneath a hawthorn tree, They slew the royal child; And buried him, with witness none, Except the eye of God alone. O long and long was search around For Mercia's monarch made; But the cowslips they had mantled thick Above where he was laid; And nought remain'd to lend a trace Of little Kenelm's resting-place. But not in vain the blood of Saints Upon the earth is sown; And though their grave be hid from men, It is to Angels known; For holy Angels love the just, And keep a watch above their dust. Far off, a thousand miles away, Across the land and main, The Pope was chanting solemn mass In Peter's holy fane; When Heav'n to him the spot reveal'd, So long from British eye conceal'd. Lo! down beside the altar floats A dove on azure wings, Who in her beak a golden scroll Of mystic import brings: ‘Of his fair head St. Kenelm shorn Is sleeping low beneath a thorn.’ To England straight the tidings fly, The hawthorn soon is found; And crowds on crowds, to see their king, Flock in from all around; As incorrupt in death he lay, Like one who scarce was dead a day. See now the Peers and Bishops wend In long funereal line, With incense, cross, and silken pall, To Winchcomb's royal shrine, And there in consecrated shade The son is with his father laid. But on his sister justice came, Pursuing close behind; And all amidst her queenly state She pined, and pined, and pined; Till in their sockets, day by day, Her eyes had wasted both away. Meanwhile, to show to all below His glory in the skies, Up from the spot where he had lain Did this fair spring arise;— Memorial of the sacred sod Where rested once a Saint of God. Here miracles of might are wrought On deaf, and lame, and blind; Here all who only come in faith A benediction find.— St. Kenelm! for the pilgrims pray, Who in thy praise are met to-day. III. ON HEARING THE NIGHTINGALE SING IN THE DAY-TIME. Sweet bird, enchantress of the earth! Born in the world's young prime, The only bird of Eden birth Left to this latter time! Why on the sunny laughing day Thy golden voice expend? To lonely night belongs thy lay; Save thee she has no friend. The day, it has a thousand songs, Of leaflet, bird, and bee; The merry bell to the day belongs; The night—it has but thee! Then for sad solitary night Reserve thy liquid lay; And she to thee for this delight, Full many thanks will pay; Listening all still, o'er vale and hill, While from some copsewood tree, Thou with charm'd trill the air dost fill, Blending all things in thee! IV. EVENING. Now eve descends in meek array, More welcome than the gaudy day; The clouds forsake the upper sky To settle on some mountain high; Or round the Sunset's crimson close In variegated piles repose. Faint, more faint, and fainter still, Stealing on o'er vale and hill, The chimes from distant turret gray Into silence fade away. The hamlet swarms with rustic poor, At gossip by the cottage-door; Guided by little urchin strong, Homeward creeps the team along; The children, heedless to be seen, Bathe in the pond upon the green; Whence along their beaten track March the geese in order back. From the cot beside the oak Mounts a slender thread of smoke, Telling with what thrifty care Its two old dames their meal prepare; While from open lattice nigh Notes of village harmony Floating in a cadence clear Catch the idly listening ear. Now then the pensive task be mine, As into dusk the tints decline, In meditative mood to stray Along some brier-scented way: Where, perch'd beside her leafy nest, The linnet trills her young to rest. There let me muse, all else forgot, On the strange tide of human lot; How brief the measure of our day; On death's approach, on life's decay; On former times, on future things; On all our vain imaginings;— Till over fading lawn and mead Their beaded net the dews have spread; And the pale glow-worm shows her light, To guide me home at fall of night. V. SPRING. Come, Spring, O come; And loiter not so long In distant Southern isles, Or in the glens of Araby the Blest. Come, Spring, O come; For I am sick at heart Of the dull winter's length, And yearn to see thy winsome face again. On the fresh blade Glistens the rime of morn, Waiting for thee to come, And with thy breath exhale it to the skies. For thee the bud Its fragile form unfolds; And opening film by film Spreads to the tempting air its leaf of gauze. The lamb for thee, Thrilling with young delight, Skips through the fleecy fold On the warm slope of many a sunny vale; While near at hand, From hedge-rows faintly green, To frequent bleatings shrill The newly-mating birds in songs reply. Then from afar Once more appear, O Spring, Breathing most odorous sweets, With robe of violet and lily crown. Once more appear, Enchantress of the world! Who with sweet siren voice Lullest the harsh notes of the wintry gale! So to thy call All nature shall respond, And grateful, o'er thy head Strew the white blossoms of the early year. VI. AUTUMN. As late I stood a sluggish brook beside, Wherein from rustling alders dropping fast, Floated the leaves that were poor Summer's pride, But now to reckless winds aside were cast; A hoary-headed Hermit I espied, Sitting where o'er the stream an aspen hung: His robe with divers gaudy tints was dyed, And his glazed eye upon the brook was flung, As musing deep he seem'd the fading woods among. Anon he steps him forth with solemn tread, While round his feet strange mournful music rose; And from the groves a dirge, as of the dead, Came fitfully, lamenting Summer's close. Meanwhile the gossamers began o'erhead From branch to branch their airy woof to ply; And from the ground a sickly vapour spread, That slowly floating up shut out the sky, Drawing o'er nature's bier a funeral canopy! VII. ASSOCIATIONS WITH PLACES. 'Tis strange to think on this green earth How many spots there be, Mementos dear of grief or mirth, Unknown to you or me! The grot, the glen, the old grey tower Gaily we saunter by, Where ofttimes in a pensive hour Another stops to sigh. Each object speaks, if all were known, Heard by none else beside, To some one heart in solemn tone, Recalling what has died. Thus wide and far, o'er isle and main, A thousand memories dwell Of tears, of guilt, of love, of pain, Far more than we can tell. O, let us tread with thoughts profound Where'er our path may be; All earth is consecrated ground, To him who thinks with me! VIII. ON AN ANCIENT STONE-QUARRY. Know, visitor, that from this spot obscure, So shut from human gaze, Whither scarce once a year across the moor A lonely shepherd strays, In olden time, far off beyond the seas, A vast Cathedral rose, Whose fame extends to earth's extremities, And still with ages grows. The stones, that here in darkness would have lain, There piled in glorious state, Up to the skies the fretted roof sustain, Majestically great; Or carved in many a mystical device, And forms of Saints on high, In glory ever new bring Paradise Before th' entrancèd eye. Such power hath God for His eternal ends To human genius given; Genius sublime! upon whose wings ascends The mind from earth to heaven! So, at His will and bountiful decree, From low obscurest things, In everlasting truth and harmony, Celestial beauty springs. E'en as at first, from the rude formless mass Of earth's chaotic frame, This fair creation, at His word of grace, In perfect order came! IX. NATURE'S MYSTERIES. Nature! deign to drop thy veil, For a little moment's space; Well I know, its folds conceal Many a miracle of grace. Well I know that deep within Move in a mysterious scheme Things immortal, things divine, Fairer than the heart can dream. Oh, might I but look behind, What a blaze of glory bright, In thy hidden depth enshrined, Would confound my dazzled sight! Substances of beauty rare, Unconceived by human thought, Whence, as in a tissue fair, All that we behold is wrought! Living light in ebb and flow; Paradisal imagery! Angels glancing to and fro In the clear transparency! Ah, if thy exterior dress Is so beauteous, as we see; What must not the beauteousness Of thine inner splendours be! X. A DREAM OF CHILDHOOD. I had a dream when I was young,— It was a mystery to me, And ever to my heart has clung Its most enchanting memory. I stood a little lake beside, With roses fringed, as silver bright; Above me Angels seem'd to glide, All in a strangely liquid light. When suddenly there thrill'd me through A sound more sweet than I can name, Unheard before, but well I knew That from those angel forms it came. They caught me up, they bore me high, Softly their wings enwrapp'd me o'er; Strange things they show'd me in the sky,— Things I had never guess'd before. Then first I saw how little earth Can with eternal worlds compare; Then first I felt my higher birth Than beasts on land or birds in air. O joy of joys! I seem'd to fly; I seem'd at Heav'n's own gate to be; The Seraphs chanting through the sky Amidst their songs enseraph'd me. I woke;—the bells were chiming clear, Waking I strove to dream again; But then, and since from year to year, I've sought for that sweet dream in vain. O sunny hours of life's young light! O season blest of man's brief day! When in the dreams of morning bright Angels can steal the soul away! Would that again by grace divine My soul were fit such things to see! Gladly for this would I resign All that the world has brought to me. XI. ON PASSING BY A FORMER HOME ON A RAILWAY. All on a road of iron strong, Behind our iron steed, Old England's Westward length along We swept with fiery speed. Oh, drear to me was that long day, And weary was the din; No village scenes to cheer the way! My heart fell dead within. When suddenly there burst on me; A spot well known of yore; A spot I had not dreamt to see,— A moment seen and o'er! Within a little nook it lay,— Garden and house and lawn, Beeches and brook and steeple gray That saw my boyhood's dawn. O blest abode! to your sweet shade How did my spirit spring; Counting the gulf that time had made A momentary thing! And ringing back life's changes all, Till far away I heard The chimes of early childhood call, Like to a mocking-bird. O blest abode! like some deep thought A moment felt and o'er, As though Eternity it brought, Then left us as before! Farewell, farewell! the world sweeps by, And I with it must go; But I'll return before I die, If God shall grant it so. XII. SUMMER'S DEPARTURE. The glory of Summer Is faded and fled; The wreaths that adorn'd her Are dying or dead; The Autumn is coming, And strong in his blast Will open to Winter A passage at last. O, how to my spirit It seemeth to say,— ‘Thus, too, is thy Summer Fast fleeting away; And the things which thou lovest, Though pleasant they be, And the friends thou hast chosen Are fading with thee. Dost thou covet a Summer More certain of bliss?— Go seek thee a country Far brighter than this; Where the joys thou hast lost Thou shalt never deplore, And the friends thou hast chosen Shall quit thee no more.’ XIII. ON A SELFISH RETIREMENT. How many souls of strongest powers To selfish solitude consign'd Have whiled in idleness their hours, Nor nobly sought to serve mankind! Them, nor a widow'd nation's cries, Nor blood of freedom largely shed, Nor saintly martyr's dying sighs, From their false dream of quiet led. Listless beneath o'er-arching trees, They watch'd the birds attune their song, Or gather'd incense from the breeze, Or mark'd the streamlet glide along. But not to such the Muse may give Her sacred wreath, the Patriot's pride; Since for themselves content to live So for themselves alone they died. Happy the man who for his God Has left the world and all its ways, To tread the path that Saints have trod, And spend his life in prayer and praise: Unhappy, who himself to please Forsakes the path where duty lies, Either in love of selfish ease, Or in contempt of human ties. In vain have they the world resign'd Who only seek an earthly rest; Nor to the soul that spurns mankind Can even solitude be blest. XIV. TO ONE COMPLAINING OF LIFE'S MONOTONY. Dear Friend, you make no new complaint, But one, I think, we've heard before, Made by a certain royal scribe Dissatisfied in days of yore. He too of life's unchanging round Grew weary as the years went by; He wearied of the feast and song, And all his royalty could buy: He wearied of his gardens fair, And palaces of curious art! Of still unsated eye and ear, Of still unsated mind and heart. He wearied of the ways of men, So like in virtue as in sin; He wearied of the seas unfill'd By all the rivers flowing in; He wearied of the rivers all Returning back from whence they came; Of nothing new beneath the sun; Of all things ever still the same. Yet there's a thought, which might outweigh, Could we but duly feel its force, This sense of sameness which our life Brings with it in its daily course; So I at least have seem'd to find, Myself a fellow-victim too; And as an antidote I now Commend it, dearest Friend, to you;— The thought of that momentous change So quickly, quickly, drawing near, Surpassing all we can conceive Of all excess of changes here! O Change intense!—from life to death! O state to which it leads the way! A state of which no human words The proper image can convey! Because no images subsist Save what the senses first supply But all the senses fail to reach Beyond the limit where we die! Great God! no more in listless ease, Or dreariness of dull routine, Be mine to doze upon the verge Of everlasting worlds unseen. But mindful of my coming doom To endless weal or endless woe, So let me use thy solemn trust Of this diurnal life below; That at the last, O Love divine, I be not all unworthy found Of what Thy bounty may design In that eternal life beyond! XV. A VILLAGE INCIDENT. I know a man of many years, Full ninety years and more, On Summer-noons he oft appears Outside his cottage-door. And there with palsied hand will he Sit knitting in the shade; O, 'tis a curious sight to see That old man at his trade. In winter by his chimney-hole He spends the livelong day, And often gets a passing dole From those who go that way. For he is known the parish round, And all the neighbourhood o'er; And there has lived on that same ground For ninety years and more. No child has he, they are all gone, And rest them in a row; Last week he buried a younger son With hair as white as snow. In his old prayer-book at the end, Their ages you may see; That book it is his oldest friend, And twice as old as he. But yesterday I pass'd that way, And miss'd him from his chair; I saw that in distress he lay, And gave what I could spare. Then lifting up his clear blue eye, With trembling voice he cried, ‘May you be bless'd by God on high, And Christ the crucified!’ O words of comfort, how did they My heart with rapture fill! And ever since, do what I may, I seem to hear them still. And ever to myself I sing With a deep inward glee, ‘Old man, it was a pleasant thing To be thus bless'd by thee.’ XVI. THE UNSHED TEAR. Oh bitter is the tear that is not shed! Back to the heart they say it wends unseen; There nestles as a fountain in its bed, And ever and anon wells up, all fresh and keen; And tainting living joys with sorrows dead, Floods present sweet with bitter that hath been: Nor aught can heal this Mara of the soul, But the sweet Cross of Him who died to make us whole. XVII. WATER. O Water, element sublime, Alone unchanged since Eden time! For earth and air no more Are what they were before; And all Creation moans its hapless fate, Fallen with fallen man from its primeval state. But thou still pure dost rise, As when the guilty world thou didst baptise; As when first welling from th' untainted sod, Where Adam sinless trod, Fourfold thou flowedst through the Paradise of God! XVIII. TO ECHO. Genius most coy! Who in deep hermit-glen, Where through o'er-foliaged cleft the brooklet steals, A sylvan life dost lead! Or in high dome, To solemn-sounding choir, From thy calm realm wide-arching overhead, Returnest strain for strain! Thee in some grot, Far down primeval time, From noise of heaving chaos deep retired, Did Silence bring to birth; There nursed thee up Beneath a radiant roof, Where sparkled thick innumerable gems, The storehouse of a world! Whence still thy voice, Most heard in lonely scenes, Flies from the common haunt, from business rude, And the coarse hum of men. O, that with thee I, too, apart might dwell; Nor to the traffic of the world consign'd, Invert the ends of life! XIX. A SICK PERSON'S COMPLAINT. Like him who by Bethsaida's pool of old Long time in suffering expectation lay, So this tenth year I lie in pains untold; And seeing oft the funerals go this way, And hearing oft the knell float on the morning gray, I envy young and old who me before Into the grave go down from day to day. Jesu, forgive the sin, or me restore; Or help me thither soon, that I may sin no more! XX. A DREAM IN SPRING. One morn in Spring I did me fling Beneath our churchyard yew; Then sleep it stole Across my soul, Soft as the silver dew. The graves amid, Far down deep hid, Methought one dead I lay; Waiting all still, For good or ill, The Resurrection-day. It seem'd as though, Through weal, through woe, Thus I apart had lain, For years untold, In heat, in cold, In drought and drizzling rain. But now the sun had fill'd the air With summer warmth and glee; And like the soft breath of a prayer Was that warm sun to me. The buds had burst their winter shroud, The lark was in the skies; High up I heard him singing aloud, And long'd with him to rise. ‘Ah, why,’ thought I, ‘Must I thus lie, While in the Springtide gay, Waking from sleep, These earthlings keep Their Resurrection-day? ‘Oh, when at last Shall the trumpet-blast Be peal'd o'er earth and sea? By Prophets old Long since foretold, Sole hope of life to me!’ Then smote mine ear, From some grave near, Low whispering on the air, ‘That time is known In Heaven alone, Nor to the Angels there. ‘Suffice for thee That hour shall be, Then keep thee to thy rest, Thrice happy if the lot be thine, Waking at last, by grace divine To waken with the blest.’ XXI. THE SOUL. A COMPARISON. A narrow brooklet ill befits The ship in gallant trim, Destined across the ocean waves With precious freight to swim. So, too, the heart confined to earth A stranded object lies; Meant by its Maker to maintain Communion with the skies. O my poor bark, so long aground, Expand thy drooping sail; Forsake the limitary coast, And catch the open gale. It ill becomes thine origin, Thy destiny sublime, To lie immersed in vanities Upon the shoal of time. Let not a petty earthly pool That noble keel detain, Bound with immortal freight to cross Th' illimitable main! XXII. TO THE PLUMES ON A HEARSE. Ye sable plumes, That soft and tremulous, Like foliage of Norwegia's sombre pine, Wave in the listless breeze! Within your depth Of dim funereal shades, That to my brooding thought gigantic grow, What grisly spectres dwell! E'en as I gaze, I seem their forms to see, Through your recesses of umbrageous gloom In silence gliding by;— Sickness and Pain! And unrepented Guilt! Pale Disappointment, haggard Misery! Despair with wringing hands! Terror, Remorse! Bereavement dumb with woe! And agonising Grief that vainly wails And will not be consoled! Avaunt, avaunt! Ye phantoms of the grave! I sign me with the Cross! Your power is nought! In vain, in vain, ye try To fright the soul, To whom her Lord is nigh; Who, fix'd in Him, resolved for Him to live, In Him exults to die! XXIII. HOPE AND MEMORY. There are two Beings, rich in wondrous powers, Twin-sisters, kindly wont to dwell with man: One owns the treasures of all future hours; The other grasps the past within her span; Hope ever smiling, bright with thousand dyes From the gay hues distill'd of golden morn; And Memory breathing softly-soothing sighs, Sweet as the rose, yet not without its thorn. These two together, through life's weary way Trip hand in hand, and scatter fairy flowers; Together pour around inspiring day, And water desert earth with genial showers. Apart—so speaks a voice from yonder grave— The power of each to bless no more may last; Without a future, who the past would crave? And who a future, if denied the past? XXIV. ON VISITING THE ROOM WHERE I WAS BORN. Oh, for an hour of quiet thought, On this fair summer morn! When I behold what long I've sought, The room where I was born. And is it true, and can it be, That at no distant day, In this same room which now I see, A newborn babe I lay? And here, mysterious soul of mine, Did thy young life begin, Cast breathless by decree divine Into a world of sin? Mortality's immortal dawn! O truth sublimely strange! The more revolved, the more withdrawn Beyond my reason's range! Thou, Lord, alone, who didst create, Canst tell, and none but Thee, The marvels of my present state, Of what I yet shall be. I see the laurell'd garden gay, Whose flower-inwoven maze Greeted so oft at peep of day My youthful mother's gaze. I see the lattice, whence the light First smote my quivering eye, And flooding o'er me came the sight Of earth and azure sky; When frighted at the world so new, Wailing I hid my head; And to my mother's bosom drew, And there was comforted. O, mix'd vicissitudes of life! O, many mingled scene, Through which since then, in peace or strife, My being's course has been! Thoughts incommunicably strange Contract my aching brow, As musing on from change to change I trace my life till now. Jesu, all praise! Alas, in ways Of darkness I have trod! Yet still at least my early days Were sanctified to God; When at Thy Font of life divine Thine arms enfolded me, By nature born a child of sin, By grace new born to Thee. Since then I've sinn'd, since then I've stray'd, Till all but lost I seem; Yet still to Thee be glory paid, Who solely canst redeem! XXV. LESSON FROM A CLOUD. Dark and dismal as the tomb To the wretch condemn'd to die, So yon cloud with sickly gloom Overspreads the cheerful sky. While the shadows which it traces Thus obscure this lower scene; On the side that heavenward faces, All is sunny and serene. So in troubles small or great, Let us take the comfort given; Even to the darkest fate, There's a side that looks to Heaven! XXVI. THE SEASIDE. When in the sweet childhood that's gone I stood by the side of the main, At every new wave that roll'd on, I wonder'd again and again. As I gather'd the shells on its shore, As I gazed on the vessels at sea, The mystery grew more and more, And would not interpreted be. O dream which my childhood beguiled, How truthful an emblem wert thou!— As I thought of the sea when a child, So I think of eternity now. I stand by the side of its sea: I gather the shells on its shore; But its depths are mysterious to me As the depths of the ocean of yore. Every hour that rolls on its way Brings enigmas which reason transcend; And the best of all homage to pay, Is to wonder on still to the end. Then from the sea its depths shall go fleeing; All bare shall eternity be; And they who now wonder, not seeing, Shall wonder the more when they see! XXVII. ON SEEING SNOW UPON GOOD FRIDAY. Snow, what art thou doing here, At this season of the year, Just when earth begins to sing, Bringing Winter into Spring? Christmas is thy fitter day, Christmas long has pass'd away; Say, then, what has brought thee here, At this season of the year? Is it, upon this sad day, When upon the Cross He lay, To recall that happier morn When the Prince of Peace was born? Or, appearing to our sight, All in robes of virgin white, Wouldst thou rather us remind In a moral undesign'd, What great purity of heart Is required on our part, If we hope a life to spend Worthy of the Saviour's end? Thus in thee, if well inclined, We a useful lesson find; Thou wilt quickly melt away; May the lesson longer stay! XXVIII. TO THE HOURS. Ye solemn Hours, That swift and stealthily, Laden with stores untold, From past eternity to future glide! Methinks at night I see your phantom-forms, Down the dim vault of time Trailing in silent majesty along. Then to my mind, As amid leafless boughs The bleak wind whistles shrill, Throng buried hopes,—throngs the sad waste of years; Till half I wish I might my days recall; And tracing back my course, Find me some new and better path to Heaven XXIX. LINES WRITTEN ON LEAVING OXFORD. How well I remember the hour, When first from the brow of this hill, I gazed upon spire and tower, Becalm'd in the valley so still! The birds sweetly sang in mine ear, Still sweeter sang hope at my heart; How bright did the prospect appear, What thrilling emotions impart! Since then seven years have expired, Seven years which I sigh but to name; Yet I have more than all I desired Of knowledge, of friendship, of fame. How strange are the feelings of man! How changefully link'd with each other! One feeling is strong when we plan, We succeed,—it is turn'd to another. Oh teach me, great Teacher of all, Such wisdom to learn and to love, So to feel, that whatever befall, It may lead me to better above. There only are destined to bloom The hopes that we cherish below; There the past is divested of gloom; No pain can the future bestow. XXX. ON WEEPING WHILE ASLEEP. Waking one morn, in sickness, I was told By those who o'er my sleep their watch had kept, That they had mark'd a crowd of busy tears Trickling from my closed eyes the while I slept. But I, of any sorrow unaware, Had pass'd that night in freedom from all pain, Nor in my dreams the vision of a care Had visited the mansions of my brain. Ah, was it then that nature of herself Pour'd for her guilt th' involuntary tear? Smit inwardly like that hard rock of old By rod of secret Angel standing near? Or was it thou, my soul, in thine own depth Stirr'd with unfathom'd thoughts too sad to last, Anticipating death and judgment dread, Or pining o'er th' irrevocable past? Thou knowest, Lord, who dost my misery see; And Thou alone:—this only will I say, Thrice grateful I for tears to weep to Thee, Or choose Thou me the night, or choose the day. XXXI. LINES WRITTEN IN MOMENTARY DISGUST WITH METAPHYSICS. O, vain attempt! For us, poor offspring of primeval sin, To trace within our soul, Of its ideas the fontal origin! What! know ye not, O ye all-wise philosophers of earth, How radical a wound Of ignorance infests us from our birth? How shorn of grace This human nature lost in darkness lies! With scarce a memory left Of what it was in earlier Paradise! Whence to itself It must for ever an enigma be; A dim chaotic thing Degraded from its first integrity. O Lord, to thee I lift aloft my supplicating cry; Teach me my true estate, To feel how frail, how null, how nought am I! Teach me by grace Duly my nature's misery to scan; To look in all to Thee Who art my All, and know myself a man. XXXII. THE TEMPLE OF THE HOLY GOSPELS. Know, weary Pilgrim, that not far remote From this o'er-peopled tract of modern time So humming with the ever-restless wheels Of commerce and material industry, A sacred spot there is, from the rude throng Of vulgar recollections far retired, (O'er the green plain approach'd where Peter sits Tending his happy sheepfold evermore); A sacred spot—the cynosure of earth, And central in the labyrinth of years, Midway betwixt the solemn boundaries Of Past and Future. There upon a sward Of aromatic and most emerald grass, A temple stands, well worthy of thy gaze. Shaped circular, in pure chalcedony, And with a circling row of golden pillars Encoronall'd—four porticoes it hath, To earth's four quarters open; which at first Of poor appearance seem—but presently To Faith's clear vision'd and unfaltering eye Expanding, as she gazes, soar aloft From height to height, and in the clouds are lost. Archangels guard the gates with flaming swords, The same, 'tis said, who at an earlier day Did man unparadise; but now to man For His dear sake who died on Calvary, Propitious grown, his entrance they invite With most benignant smiles; excluding only Spirits of power malign, who formerly, Under old Paganism's doleful shade, Infested all the plain. Once enter'd in, You find yourself beneath a spacious dome, Within a Sanctuary most august, Abode of absolute tranquillity, Where not a footfall echoes. Round the sides A circuit fair of jewell'd chapelries, Each with its mystic altar, greets the eye, Each with its mystic window, upon which In blended tints of vivid imagery Glows the blest history of the Son of Man Ineffably portrayed. And evermore Myriads of worshippers, in spirit borne From earth's far ends, with mute enravishment Those courts perambulate, and wholly lost In musing ectasy, upon the scenes Of that dread Life of lives adoring gaze. Central beneath the dome, a palmlike fount Of purest living light, in thousand jets Incessant plays, and with its overflow A sapphire basin fills, in whose clear depth All Heaven reflected shines. Around it stand The four divine Historians; and from thence For all who come, in golden chalices The sparkling water draw, which whoso drink Drink endless life. Ah, then, without delay, Haste, Pilgrim, to that Temple, passing by Whatever else invites thee; there obtain Rest from thy weariness; and there enjoy Celestial consolations! Vain is all The world can show, with those delights compared. XXXIII. THE SOUL'S ABYSS. Far down within the castle of the soul Exists from ancient days a postern door, Opening upon th' abyss where ceaseless roll Time's silent surges on th' eternal shore,— A secret portal, which to-day self-closed Perchance to-morrow morn is open found; According as the thoughts have been disposed, Or momentary sight, or scent, or sound, Or breath divine may have its magic bars unbound. Thither one night by spiral stair descending, Within the central keep of my own mind, Flight below flight—so far, it seem'd unending— I went, absorb'd in thoughts of solemn kind; As through some ancient mine one all alone With his pale fitful light exploring goes; And starts to hear or weirdly whispering tone, Or rush of water as unseen it flows, Or other wandering sound for which no cause he knows. At length I came upon a lonely cell, That like a timeworn hermitage appear'd, Scoop'd midway in a cliff impregnable Of basalt rock.—A heap of leaflets, sear'd By Autumn's touch, the vagrant winds had piled Upon the floor; and in the wall was seen A niche, where meekly folding her dread Child Stood the blest Mother, of Archangels Queen, Carved in the living rock, with a most loving mien. Half open stood the door; I push'd it wide.— Ah, me, what sight was there! the dense profound Of sheer infinity's abysmal void Broke sudden from the threshold. Not a sound Stirr'd the strange blank; nor dark it seem'd, nor light; But a great nameless all-absorbing deep, Upon whose verge I shiver'd with affright, As the fledged eaglet, balancing to sweep Downward on his first plunge from the stern dizzy steep. Ah, then had I extinct in darkness been, Lost in the depths of that abyss unknown, But that a hand behind me came unseen, And pluck'd me back when I was all but gone. Breathless before the Mother and the Child A moment and I seem'd to kneel and pray; A moment and methought their faces smiled, As if they had some gracious thing to say: Then sudden from my dream I woke,—and it was day! I woke; but still the thought of that abyss Haunted my spirit with a fearful power; And long in vain I struggled to dismiss Its memory through many a waking hour. O bountiful compassion of the Lord! Thus warning us by day and night in turn; Forcing by fear, enticing by reward; That man may his mortality discern, And from his nothingness his true dependence learn O Nothingness, from whence my being sprang; O Nothingness, to which again I tend; If Thou, who didst the globe on nothing hang, Refuse Thine ever-present aid to lend! Essential Being, whence all beings flow, Teach me my native misery to see; Teach me my perfect nullity to know; Teach me to feel how I depend on Thee For all I was, or am, or may hereafter be. And thou, pure Virgin Daughter of the sky, Who, fashion'd like myself in mortal mould, Wast raised by thy deep lowliness so high As in thine arms Creation's Lord to hold, Entreat for me that I aside may cast All things that might my heavenward course impede; That I may humbly walk, and gain at last, From all temptation, sin, and suffering freed, The bosom of my God, whence endless joys proceed. XXXIV. BELIEF OF ANGLICANS IN THE REAL PRESENCE TESTED. My friends, ye use a solemn-seeming tone, And teach a truth sublime; Christ present in His Eucharist ye own, And count denial a crime. Be honest; if Him truly there ye hold, When next the Feast ye share, Bow down before the Mystery untold,— Bow down, and worship there! What, ye refuse! O men unreal, I see Ye have your words belied! Farewell, such teaching will not serve for me; I seek a surer guide. XXXV. A REMONSTRANCE. Dear friends, I know you mean your best, Thinking to serve your Lord and mine, When thus you pluck me from your breast For having join'd His Church divine. O if ye knew!—but words are vain; Ye cannot learn what ye despise: And it is idle to explain The truth to those who shut their eyes; Yet I will say, If but ye knew The things which blindly ye condemn; Could ye but feel as children do, And deign for once to learn of them; Before that Church which now you hate, That Church which you refuse to hear, Which in your hearts you execrate, And which, while you revile, you fear, O, with what love and joy and trust Would you not all with one accord Exult to bow yourselves in dust, As the pure image of her Lord! Bethink ye, friends, a day is near— How near to each, O who can say?— When falsities will disappear, And all be seen as clear as day. Unhappy those who now their eyes To close against the Truth agree, But then with sorrow and surprise Shall be compell'd that Truth to see! Pause and reflect; your time is short; Soon will this hurried life be o'er: Too late perchance ye may be taught What might have saved if learnt before! XXVI. THE ROCK OF PETER. Yes, there are times When through my being's depth, Shoots an ecstatic thrill Of bounding gratitude for mercies past;— To think that now, From sophistry's black web, From deadly subtle snare Of Heresy, I am escaped at last! O, happy I! Who, spent by baffling surge, Have now at length my foot Upon the Rock of Peter firmly set; Round which the waves Tumultuous rage in vain; Vainly have raged of old, And still in vain shall rage through ages yet. Now let the hills Be swept into the sea; Let the floods lift their voice; And mountains shake before the roaring deep;— I on the Rock Of ages safe from harm, Will lay me down in peace, And all amid the wrack securely sleep. Thou o'er my head Lulling the fretful sea, Star of the deep! shine down, Still evermore the same in storms or calms! And send sweet dreams Of Paradise to me, Taking my happy rest Safe in my everlasting Father's arms! XXXVII. ST. CLEMENT'S TOMB. Of all the mausoleums, old or new, High-famed in Italy or other lands, Thine, Clement, I admire, by Angel-hands Constructed underneath the billows blue, On the broad Euxine's amber-paven floor, Near where Chersona stood in days of yore. Long dwelt thy memory there among the race Of simple quarrymen, whose toil supplied Imperial Rome with porphyry to grace Her palaces; and long they certified, Father to child, the story of thy tomb, And well-remember'd glorious martyrdom. How exiled thither by the stern decree Of Trajan, thou through all the country round Didst spread the Christian faith; and being found Guilty of death wast carried out to sea, And toss'd into the dull oblivious deep, Yoked to an anchor for thy surer sleep. How then, as all the Faithful, on the shore Lamenting thy lost relics, knelt and pray'd, Lo, of itself the sea three miles and more Receding, a broad open pathway made; And they in search of thee, abreast the tide Exploring on, a wondrous structure spied! A lonely sepulchre, far out at sea, Of purest alabaster, by no tool Of mortal hand proportion'd,—beautiful With curious work of mystic imagery, O'er which on opal stalactites uprear'd A pearly-tinted canopy appear'd. And lo, within the tomb serenely lying, The Saint himself in tranquil death composed; Fragrant with Paradise; a bloom undying Upon his roseate cheek; his eyelids closed; His arms devoutly cross'd upon his breast; Picture sublime of everlasting rest! And not far off the anchor they espied, So late his instrument of martyrdom, But emblem now of better things to come; When at the Resurrection glorified, He, who for Jesus did his body give, In that same body shall with Jesus live. So runs Crimea's legendary lore, Clement, of thee; but our great Mother Rome, O Fourth of those whom Peter's lineage bore, In time thy relics claim'd, as thy true home; And she, who cast thee to a doom unjust, Now worships every remnant of thy dust! XXXVIII. THE TEMPLE OF NATURE. O thou, dread Nature, whose material frame In elemental strength compactly stands, In beauty ever varying, yet the same, Blending in unity all times and lands! What art Thou but a Temple to His name Who thee uprear'd upon th' abyss profound; The uncreated Word, who flesh became For us poor wormlings creeping on the ground, Unworthy that such grace should unto us abound? Who, lifting up thy mountain-pillar'd heights, Thy spacious floor with land and sea inlaid; Fill'd thy long aisles with mystic sounds and sights; Of starry sky thy roof cerulean made: That man in thee of ever-fresh delights, Through dying Autumn and reviving Spring, Through the long Summer-days and Winter-nights, Might find a store from whence His praise to sing Who is above all praise, of all creation King! Then, too, lest outward nature should enthrall Our souls oblivious of the things unseen, Deep in Creation's adamantine wall Windows He placed of rainbow-tints serene; Through which His holy Heaven on those might shine Who purely sought their God in all to see: O glorious work of mercy most divine, That nature thus might Thine Apostle be, Great Lord, and to our hearts preach not herself but Thee! Wherefore, all praise be Thine, who so hast wrought Each mind responsive to Creation's scheme, That outward sight should lead to inward thought, Through inward thought Thine inner glory beam! And teach us, gracious Lord, whene'er we go The wonders of this Temple to explore, Thyself, of all its life the life to know; Thyself in all its wonders to adore, Lord of all wisdom, might, and glory evermore! XXXIX. NATURE'S ORATORIES. Thou, too, O Nature, Temple most divine! Besides thy public transept wide display'd, Hast thine own private cells within thy shrine, For secret prayer and meditation made: Blest Oratories! on calm mountain-height, Or in the forest's dim recesses found; Or in the natural cave far hid from sight, Down by the shore where ceaseless billows sound, And the black beetling rocks reverberate around. To these thy cloistral haunts, in olden time, Often, 'tis said, the world's great sages came, To meditate apart on truths sublime, By glimpses caught through nature's outward frame; And here—while, listening to Creation's groan, They yearn'd for that Redemption yet to be— Thou, Lord, didst hear their heart's responsive moan, And pitying their dense mortality Liftedst in part the veil that hid their gaze from Thee. Hither came Orpheus, with his golden lyre, Anticipating Thine own David's strains; Here Homer sipp'd the fount of living fire, And pious Hesiod sang, not all in vain; Here Numa sat, from busy courts retired, And Socrates with Plato, side by side; Here Solon and Confucius were inspired; Here Virgil knelt; and many more beside, Whose names for ever live,—true souls unspoilt by pride! And evermore came wisdom all unsought On those who stole in silence here to muse: But evermore the proud return'd untaught; For Thou to them, O Lord, didst light refuse, And in its place Egyptian darkness came; Wherein, whoso Thy glorious works abuse, They for their pride shall perish in the same. O, teach us, then, a lowly path to choose, And in our hearts Thine own humility infuse. XL. THE CATHOLIC CHURCH THE BOND OF THE WORLD. Like Isles that on the lap of ocean sleep, Each a lone speck upon the watery maze, So to the English superficial eye Appear the Churches of our modern days, That multifold in central unity With Apostolic Rome communion keep: But peering downward into Time's still deep, Search thou the blue abyss with curious gaze, And lo, these separate seeming Isles are found To be the tops of mountains deluged o'er, By whose enduring bars the world is bound; Whose roots extend and meet from shore to shore, Keeping all earth in place till time shall be no more! XLI. FLOWERS IN THE SACRISTY. Sweet flowers! that here In bright disorder lie, Soon to be ranged Upon the Altar of the Lord most High; Gather'd for this By the fond hand of love: How blest your lot Above your other sisters of the grove! How blest to give To Heav'n your beauty's prime, While yet unmarr'd By sudden blight or slow-consuming time! Dear emblems ye Of such as early die, From life's fair mead Cull'd in their fresh baptismal purity! They from this earth By Angels quickly borne To God's own shrine, His ever-blooming altar to adorn; There in His sight Their graces fair display, And yield new tints In the pure light of beatific day; There set before The golden branches seven, Live evermore, And breathe a fragrance through the courts of Heaven. XLII. FLOWERS ON THE ALTAR OF THE BLESSED SACRAMENT. As on some ocean cliff Oft I have seen A patch of flowers along the perilous brink Basking serene In blooming heedlessness, For all as though No dread profundity of heaving main Upsurged below; So by yon altar-flowers Glistening so fair In their most delicate vases, each as in Its own parterre, Opens a dread abyss, A sea immense, Confounding in its dread reality All thought, all sense! For there in hidden might Of glory dwells, He who creation's whole infinitude So far excels, That countless worlds might blaze To nought before The fires of His magnificence, and all Would be no more, If with His Majesty We them compare, Than th' incense-wreath that round the altar rolls, Then melts in air! XLIII. ON THE USE OF ARTIFICIAL FLOWERS FOR THE ALTAR. Time was when I abhorr'd, Too much a partisan of nature's bowers, To see upon the Altar of the Lord Fictitious flowers. But now, more fully taught Thy hidden spirit, Church of ancient days I find in this another proof unsought Of wisdom's ways. O Mother thou of men! Who with all Heav'n unfolded in thy sight, Dost yet no work of human hand contemn, However slight! But sanctifying all That into thy full lap thy children bring, Offerest their gifts with grace majestical To Heaven's high King! Offerest for them whate'er Of beauty, Art, or Nature may afford, To Him who high o'er art or nature's sphere Of both alike is Lord! XLIV. LINES ON A CEREMONIAL SANDAL OF HIS HOLINESS. ‘How beauteous on the hills the feet of him, ('Tis thus Isaias sings) ‘Who preaches heavenly peace, and brings to man Glad tidings of good things!’ Christ first, his Vicar now, to us fulfils This gracious work of God; No land by seas or mountains so conceal'd, But Peter there hath trod. Hail, dearly-prized memorial, in late days By our loved Pius worn! Hail, emblem of the foot that walk'd the waves In our redemption's morn! Before this little cross embroider'd here Princes have bended low; And own'd the presence of a greater power Than their proud world can show. Here love hath left a kiss; here guilt hath been, Nor dropp'd a tear in vain At his dear feet who holds the potent Keys That pardon or retain! Here learning to the truthful Roman See Hath grateful homage paid; Here to religion's beauteous majesty Beauty hath bow'd her head. Oh by this sacred relic here I swear, As all my life shall prove, To him who sits in Peter's holy chair True loyalty and love! XLV. LINES ON A CEREMONIAL CAPELLA OF HIS HOLINESS. O high exalted instinct of the soul! That evermore doth find A grace and splendour not their own, in things Of customary kind! Casket, or signet-ring, or coat of mail, Or ornament of state, That once belong'd to History's Champions, The good, the wise, the great! This relic fair, which love most Catholic Devoutly treasures here, To me, beholding it, than rubied crown More glorious doth appear. For cinctured round with spiry wheaten ears And clustering grapes of gold, Types of the pure Oblation offer'd now For bloody rites of old, Here, (by no fancy-freak) beneath its rim Of emblematic red, It shaded from a Roman summer's sun The sacred snow-white head Of our dear Pius; as from Church to Church, Amidst the kneeling throng, Serene he pass'd;—a Vision of delight, The ancient ways along! Angels of Rome! O shield that head beloved From danger and all fears; Watch o'er the Pontiff brave, the Sovereign good, The Priest of fifty years! And when his hour arrives, so long postponed By Christendom's fond prayer, May he in Heaven's own Hierarchy throned Be still our glory there! XLVI. A SOUL'S LAMENT IN PURGATORY. Poor Letitia dead and gone, All her sprightly pleasures o'er, Thus to her Creator cries, Who His loving face denies Not enough desired before. ‘O Thou Trinity most true, In thy Unity confess'd, Whom in Purgatorial pain Now I seek, and seek in vain, Beatific Vision blest! ‘How for Thee, my God, I yearn Through a night that knows no day, Pining on without relief, In excess of purest grief, Till my debt be done away. ‘Nothing here to soothe my pangs! Nothing to distract my care! Gone away my joys to waste! Gone away my very taste For joy, if any joy there were! ‘Yet, oh yet, my comfort this, Through my penance-tide unknown, Never more at least can I Sin against thy sanctity, O adored, beloved, alone! ‘Whom despite of all the past, Through the Blood of Calvary With a hope that holdeth fast, Still I look to see at last In a glad eternity!’ Thus Letitia makes her moan:— Hades hears her, and replies, From th' impalpable profound Of the viewless regions round, With a thousand thousand sighs! XLVII. THE GRACIOUSNESS OF PURGATORY. So great the preciousness of merits earn'd With Christ's dear-purchased grace; Once ratified by death, no after change May aught of them efface. Therefore,—for those in grace deceased,—when still. Some penance must be paid, 'Tis not by compromise of merits past Against demerits weigh'd; Which would for ever leave behind in Heaven A certain trace occult Of evil, not itself, but as involved In th' ultimate result. But no!—Demerit on its own account Shall satisfaction pay, Till in a penal interim its stain Is wholly purged away; Then Merit, saved in full integrity, And from her thrall unbound, Shall enter Heav'n's dread holiness, and there Eternally be crown'd. O bounteous God! not only suffering us To count and call our own, By pure excess of gracious charity, What He in us hath done;— Not only through our life, when we repent Reviving merits past;— But after death securing us in full Their guerdon at the last! Then, welcome Purgatory with its pains, Whatever, Lord, they be; So only saving me from Hell, Thou save Thy works, as mine, for me! XLVIII. IN GOD'S SIGHT. Why should we vex our foolish minds So much from day to day, With what an idle world concerning us May think or say? Do we not know there sits a Judge, Before whose searching eyes Our inmost hidden being cleft in twain And open lies? O my omniscient Lord and God! Enough, enough for me, That Thou the evil in me and the good Dost wholly see. Let others in their fancies think of me Or say whate'er they will; Such as I am before thy judgement-seat So am I still. Praise they my good beyond desert, And all my bad ignore;— That am I which in Thy pure sight I am, No less, no more! Decry they all my good, and blame My evil in excess;— That am I which in Thy pure sight I am, No more—no less! XLIX. FAITH. Faith is no weakly flower, By sudden heat, or chill, or stormy shower, To perish in an hour. But rich in hidden worth, A plant of grace, though striking root in earth, It boasts a hardy birth; Still from its native skies Draws energy which common shocks defies, And lives where nature dies! L. THE TWO MOTHERS. ‘My husband's second wife am I,— The first had early died; Two little ones she left behind; And I her place supplied. ‘But they, when first they saw my face, By strange ideas misled, Me for their own dear mother took, And thus the elder said:— “O mother, mother, up in Heaven, How long you've been away! But now that you've come back at last, We hope you've come to stay.” ‘Then with a tear, I thus replied, Kissing the little brow, “My child, I am not her—you have Another mother now. “O happy things! to whom the Lord Has two fond mothers given; One to be theirs on earth, and one To pray for them in Heaven!”’ Such was the tale that once we heard Beneath Helvetia's sky;— A lady of Geneva's sect, Geneva's creed bely! O Nature, Nature! thou art strong; False creeds their work may do; But Truth and thou, I think, ere long Will break an entrance through. LI. LOVE. Love is like a little rose; First it buds and then it blows, Breathing over lane and bower Sweeter scent than any flower. If a canker eat the core All its bloom will soon be o'er. Dost thou wish it long to live? Nursing plenty thou must give, Feeding it on sighs and tears Trembling hopes and busy fears. So in time of winter bare Shall for thee be blossom fair; E'en the leaves, I've heard it said, Sweetly smell when they are dead! LII. CHASTISEMENT. I stood beside her early grave, Grave of my joy to me; To Him who punishes to save Lowly I bent my knee. ‘Father supreme! thy ways are best, Thy footsteps are not known; To her sweet head Thou gavest rest Beneath this quiet stone; ‘To me long grief of many years Still lengthening to the last, Remembrances that steep in tears The present and the past. ‘Her doubtless quick did Angels bear Into a home divine, For ever there thy love to share, Oh, better far than mine! ‘Me too thy chastening hand has brought Thy will in all to see, And from henceforth to welcome aught If only sent by Thee; ‘Learning, the longer that I live, In patience to be strong;— Oh, for thy dearest Son forgive If I have mourn'd too long.’ LIII. SUNDAY. Hence! avaunt! all follies vain! Idle pomp, and sordid gain! Frolic mirth, forget to play! Labour, throw thy spade away! Hark! from yonder spire-tipp'd trees, On the bosom of the breeze, Peals in pleasant fall and swell, Sunday's early matin-bell. Holy, holy, holy Day! Welcome thrice to thee, I say; Thee whom suits uplifted eye, Heart commercing with the sky; Bosom calm, and step sedate; Simple garb, and sober gait; But, though grave thy temper be, Yet, when thou dost come to me, I beseech thee, holy Day! Put not on a sad array; (As amongst our people here Thou too often dost appear, Like a widow all in weeds, Weeping o'er our wicked deeds); But, oh come, as suits thee best, Cheerful day of genial rest! Come, with happy winning smile Full of hope and free from guile! Come, attired in raiment bright, Roseate with celestial light! Come, encoronall'd with flowers Cull'd in Paradisal bowers! Come, with looks of radiant grace, Such as beam'd upon thy face, When on bright Italia's shore Thee I met in days of yore. So together, hand in hand, We within the aisle will stand, Listening to the solemn sound Now above, and now around;— Listening to the Sanctus clear Softly melting in the ear, As with incense to the skies Soars th' almighty Sacrifice; There shall rapt devotion kneel Breathing fire of holy zeal! There shall penitence sincere Plead the silent falling tear; There shall Charity attend Changing enemy to friend; Stedfast Hope that looks on high, And pure Faith that dares to die, Seeking out her sole reward In the bosom of her Lord. Or together down some glen, Far from busy scenes of men, Through the hawthorns we will go, Slowly wending to and fro; While the soul, all else forgot In her future final lot, Mounting high on vivid wings, Meditates immortal things, Till in excess of glory clear, Present worlds obscure appear, Heaven's own veil is lifted high, Death seems life, and life to die! Such the joys I ask of thee, Day of joy and Jubilee! Sweet delight of earth and Heaven! Sweetest day of all the seven! These if but thou wilt bestow, Here in turn to thee I vow, In the name of young and old, Faithful children of the fold, Never shall the joyous chime Fail to greet at rosy prime Thee, upon the hills of light Reappearing to our sight; Never through the livelong year, Summer gay or Winter sere, Early Spring or Autumn hale, Shall thy own High Altar fail Of the brighest flowers that bloom, Through the seasons as they come; Or of all that Art supplies Oft as fading Nature dies. LIV. THE ORDER OF PURE INTUITION. Hail sacred Order of eternal Truth! That deep within the soul, In axiomatic majesty sublime, One undivided whole, Up from the underdepth unsearchable Of primal Being springs, An inner world of thought, co-ordinate With that of outward things! Hail, Intuition pure! whose essences The central core supply Of conscience, language, science, certitude, Art, beauty, harmony! Great God! I thank Thy majesty supreme, Whose all-creative grace Not in the sentient faculties alone Has laid my reason's base; Not in abstractions thin by slow degrees From grosser forms refined; Not in tradition, nor the broad consent Of conscious humankind; But in th' essential Presence of Thyself, Within the soul's abyss; Thyself, alike of her intelligence The fount, as of her bliss: Thyself, by nurture, meditation, grace, Reflexively reveal'd; Yet ever acting on the springs of thought, E'en when from thought conceal'd! LV. THE CAPTIVE LINNET. This morn upon the may-tree tall That shelters our suburban wall A curious sight I spied, A linnet young, of plumage gay, Fast to the trembling topmost spray By strange misfortune tied. There helpless dangling, all in vain From his enthralling viewless chain To loose himself he strove; Till, spent at last, he hung as dead, No more by brook and flowery mead On happy wing to rove. Then, pitying a fate so sad, I call'd a little singing lad, And bade him climb the tree; With orders, at whatever cost, Though e'en a blooming branch were lost, To set the captive free; With steady eye aloft he goes; I trace him through the rustling boughs; A joyous shout is heard; Then, snowy white with tufts of may, Down to my feet descends a spray, And with the spray the bird. I loosed his bonds; away he flew; And grateful, from a neighbouring yew Repaid me with a song; But what, think you, I found to be The chain that in captivity Had held him fast so long? A single thread of silken hair, That borne by zephyrs here and there, Had settled on the spray; Then, as he sported there, had wound His soft and glossy neck around, And bound him fast a prey! MORAL. Ye children of the world, beware! Too oft a lock of silken hair Has made the soul a prize; And held it riveted to earth, When, by the instinct of its birth, It should have sought the skies. And ye who have for God resign'd The sympathies of womankind, With me give thanks and sing! Safe from the ties of earthly love, Let all your thoughts be fix'd above, On your eternal King! Thrice happy! who, for once and all Released from fond affection's thrall, No other wish retain, Except to serve your Lord aright, And his neglected love requite Who once for you was slain Erewhile enslaved to vanity, Rejoice that ye are wholly free To seek the joys to come! And bent on your immortal prize, On wings of contemplation rise To God's exalted Paradise, Your everlasting home! LVI. CATHOLIC RUINS. Where once our fathers offer'd praise and prayer, And sacrifice sublime; Where rose upon the incense-breathing air The chant of olden time; Now, amid arches mouldering to the earth, The boding night-owl raves; Or pleasure-parties dance in idle mirth O'er the forgotten graves; Or worse; the heretic of modern days Has made those walls his prize; And in the pile our Faith alone could raise, That very Faith denies! God of our fathers, look upon our woe! How long wilt Thou not hear? How long shall Thy true vine be trodden low, Nor help from Thee appear? Oh, by our glory in the days gone by; Oh, by Thine ancient love; Oh, by our thousand Saints, who ceaseless cry Before Thy throne above; Lord, for this Isle, compassionate though just, Cherish Thy wrath no more; But build again her Temple from the dust, And our lost joy restore! LVII. ENGLAND'S FUTURE CONVERSION. I thought upon the noble souls, That have from age to age, O England! shone upon the rolls Of thy historic page: I thought upon the nobleness That yet in thee appears, After the wasting heresies Of thrice a hundred years. And musing on thine earlier day, ‘Dear native land,’ I said, ‘It cannot be, for all they say, That thou art wholly dead.’ Ah no! I feel, and here declare With presage half divine, That in the days which coming are, If not at least in mine, Thy desecrated shrines once more Shall their true Lord receive; And kneeling Englishmen adore Where now they disbelieve. O joyous thought! how from these eyes The tears ecstatic start, Whene'er, as now, I feel thee rise Unbidden in my heart! O Day of days, so oft foretold! So surely drawing nigh! Which Saints have thirsted to behold, For which the Angels sigh! Methinks, although in Paradise My spirit then should be, 'Twould feel an increase of its joys In looking down on thee! Methinks these very bones of mine Will thrill beneath the grave, When thou shalt come, O Day divine! My native land to save! LVIII. TO THE HAND OF A LIVING CATHOLIC AUTHOR. Hail, sacred Force! Hail, energy sublime! Fountain of present deeds, And manifold effects in future time! Through thee have sped Forth on their blazing way Conceptions fiery-wing'd, That shall the destinies of ages sway! Through thee this Isle, Long bound in Satan's chain, To her original faith Inclines beyond all hope an ear again; And eyes askant, With a half wistful gaze, Passing in beauty by, The Vision of the Church of ancient days! Symbol august! Here on my bended knee, I venerate the truth And multitudinous grace that speaks in thee. Thou, drawing back The curtains of the night, First on this guilty soul, Shut up in heresy, didst open light. Through thee on her Eternal morning rose; O, how with all her powers Can she enough repay the debt she owes! LIX. ST. PHILIP NERI AND THE ROMAN NOBLE. ‘Unhappy youth! so strangely vice Has dull'd thy spirit's finer sense, That when I threaten endless Hell, My words appear a vain pretence. ‘We must to facts. Come hither then; And kneeling here beside my knee, Bend down thy face upon my lap, And for thyself behold and see!’ With easy grace, at Philip's feet The youthful noble knelt and gazed; But, oh, another man was he When up again his face he raised! ‘O Saint and Father, I repent, And here confess my guilt,’ he cries; ‘For what my heart refused to own Has been before my very eyes! ‘I saw the hidden depth of Hell Disclosed in all its raging might; I saw th' intolerable flames, And faint with horror at the sight!’ With tender strain St. Philip drew The frighted worldling to his breast, And on his terror-stricken soul The truths of life eternal press'd. Then all his saintly art he plied, Till fear in love had died away; And so absolving sent him back Converted to his dying day! LX. A PROPHECY. When this half-century its course has sped, And, like the vision of an earlier time, The Church of God again uplifts her head In this proud Isle; confronting social crime; Confronting Death and Hell—all stately, bright, sublime! Then, gazing back upon the years that now Beneath us glide, and tracing how uprose The fair-proportion'd citadel, and how Grew in its strength of terrible repose, Accessible to friends, impervious to foes:— History will tell, and men amazed will see, Amid what vast amount of tears and pain, Amid what martyrdoms of misery, Of torn affections, friendship's ruptured chain, Homes wasted, life upturn'd, and hopes indulged in vain, Were its foundations laid. Ah, Jesu, say, What mystery is this! that evermore Pure Faith should scatter thorns upon her way Instead of roses? now as heretofore!— No wonder that the world should her approach deplore. But we, of all things taught an estimate, Suspect in this some great necessity; Lest the soul faint hereafter with the weight Of that immeasurable felicity Predestinated theirs who witness here for thee!</field>
   </doc>
</add>