<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Warren, John Byrne Leicester, Baron de Tabley, 1835-1895</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Warren, John Byrne Leicester, Baron de Tabley, 1835-1895</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">warren john byrne leicester baron de tabley 1835 1895</field>
      <field name="author_text">Warren, John Byrne Leicester, Baron de Tabley, 1835-1895</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1860's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.2124.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1863</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:467246</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Praeterita (1863</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Praeterita (1863</field>
      <field name="title_facet">praeterita 1863</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">praeterita 1863</field>
      <field name="title_text">Praeterita (1863</field>
      <field name="year_display">1863</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1863</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1863</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467246&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:467246&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Warren, John Byrne Leicester, Baron de Tabley, 1835-1895&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;warren john byrne leicester baron de tabley 1835 1895&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Praeterita (1863&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;praeterita 1863&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1863&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1863&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Warren, John Byrne Leicester, Baron de Tabley&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1835&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1895&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Praeterita (1863)&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Macmillan and Co.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1863&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp4174&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;vii, 123 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Praeterita (1863)&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 20 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Majority of verse reproduced elsewhere in The English Poetry Full-text Database; only unique items included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE CHEERFUL AGE. More wrinkles score my brow than frowns, Uncheck'd my merry vein, For age, that gives us balder crowns, Makes ripe the under brain. Of something yet they rob us still These years that make us wise, For maids grow fair as then they were, But we look with other eyes. And what was music to our youth Is discord to our age: The songs we loved as vivid truth Are tinsell'd verbiage. We cannot mend the race of things That jostles towards solution: 'Twill see us out thro' falls and springs, One stride more near conclusion. There's sorrow if we earth it out, But ease if we prefer it. Then leave the thorn and pluck the rose, And next thy bosom wear it. O'er leagues of coast the rough foam flings: There still are quiet havens; If o'er our head one sky-lark sings We heed not twenty ravens. This world is in a slippery state, And men are fools to grumble, If, like a boy who learns to skate, They marvel at a tumble. But wisdom this and wisdom that, And every man her master, While only hearts of season'd proof Can weather life's disaster. Can find youth sped and bid him speed, Nor question out the reason; Then cheerly raise the latch to age, A quest, tho' sour, in season. AT LAST. We toss and twist upon a restless bed; Sleep comes at last. Our Love denies, and yet denies again, But yields at last. The apple grows and ripens many days, But falls at last. And we are riped with joy, and marr'd with tears, But end at last! HYPERBOLE. Ripe on the eyelids as a precious dream, Soft on the lip as lips of coral seam, Sweet on the ear as an imagined stream Threading between the full woods and the moon. Mellow as harvest song at steamy noon, Lovely as cuckoo's voice that cometh soon, Drowsy as music of the branch in June, And tremulous linnet-pipe by broom or thorn. Or shall I search the silver rose of morn, The royal fisher's wing, the fleecy lawn Of mountain lamb, all hues in nature born, To find my Love's compare or deck her grace? AN EVENING BY THE FIRE. When frogs pipe out in dripping dykes, And autumn wolds are sallow: When pigeons leave the stubble spikes, And homeward oxen bellow: And singing under greying blue, The ditcher and his fellow Come drenched knee-deep from pasture-dew, And foot-clogged from the fallow: The black frost in the white frost's wake May nip the marsh-buds yellow, And kindling under branch and brake The raying sunset mellow: Thro' branch and towards the trysting style Where skims each mustering swallow; As sits the lass to rest awhile, Strolls up some sheepish fellow. Our sun-track draws tonight as this That floods the level fallow: Yon maiden's cheek is ripe to kiss, But ours are lank and hollow. Our youth is gone, like this fair day, Our rusty bones shall follow, And rest they say, for heads of gray, Comes on a churchyard pillow. So runs it well, so runs it ill, What must be we must swallow. We'll keep a merry heart up still, Unsered, fresh, young, and callow. Draw closer to the blaze, old friend, Our ale is stiff and mellow. We have not much more light to spend, Two guttered ends of tallow. But I will grasp thee by the hand, What tho' thy cheek be yellow, I'll swear that thro' the whole broad land Ne'er walked a better fellow. A FUTURE. Thy lore may be the vocal memories Of idols overthrown, imperial hours: Thy lute may moan perpetual monodies Of desecrated bowers. Thy creed may be to move in solemn shade, With drooping head, a dream upon an earth Of careless creatures—proudly disarray'd Of any masking mirth. Thy rest may be a rest we cannot know— Beyond sleek envy's scorn and cant of sneers— Pervaded with the secret strength of woe, Yet consecrate to tears. A LAMENT. O gentle day and milky cloud, O faint and flowing sea, More fair than human estimate I read the story of your state— If you could comfort me! O gloom of clouds and rocking boughs, Thou fierce and furrow'd sea, Boom round yon isles of dreamy glow, And strow the rose with driven snow, That cannot comfort me. FRAGMENT OF AN ALLEGORY. My tale is but a shadow and a sign. Between the column'd summits broadly strown, The billowy light converged to blood-red zone. Lovely, and waning as a thing divine, Came eve, as even never came before, With red-gray rush to stagger to their core Eternal steeps, mysterious; by whose crest The floated vapour shattering over-bore The bleak-eyed raven in his glacier nest. Not less, when all the naked summits wore An echo-warmth against their iris west, Failed out the silken melancholy gleam Celestial, failing under spectral ways, All blindness, whence the sky-prevailing rays Are lost, as some great thought that threads a dream, And lost the crimson wreaths that ring'd the burning stream. There sat the glittering heights immoveable, Roof'd with the sun and stair'd in ridgey seams, Holding the folded azure's vapour streams; And from those heights a level dull and grey, Dull as its sand and pale as pale decay, Dispread perpetual towards a shining sea That was but mirage cloud, which blent away And to the skies glow'd vast and mightily. There an old man was seated on a bulk Of salt, that beasts had lick'd in pits and jags, With great knees huddled towards his chin, and shrunk His lean ring'd throat which fell in fleshless bags. Above him spread illimitable crags, And gray lights trembled from them: and his arm Trembled from wrist to elbow where his face Rested; the other moved not from its place Saving to screen his eyes, when over-warm A chance gleam wounding bit their weak white scums: And then he mumbled groans and stirr'd his mouth To show one wolf-tooth hung in rusty gums; Nodding with ague, if the whispering south Breathed but to puff a thistle seed along, And the woods bloom'd beneath it: yet his limbs Were palsied, and a wrinkling shiver strong Winning fierce way from foot to forehead climbs. For wizard he had been of knowledge ripe, But that a stronger weird had chain'd him there In this perpetual solitude. The gripe Of age was on him, and a lean despair Of impotence that held him from his share In those delights his stronger years had fed: They, blasted as the scalp of his foul head In seamy gaps or slimy mats of hair, Had perish'd inch-meal, but the ache lived on In that great mesh of ruin, made its lair By all corruption; as the fire-worm's glow Among the rotting leaves. There, woe-begone, He sate, and on the furthest peaky snow He lifted melancholy eye-balls rolling slow. Ay, on the limit of eternal rock, Or on the upper limitless expanse, Or where lake mirrors crossing clouds bemock, Painting as sharp below their plumed advance, As one that sees such prospect in a trance, He gazed, and gazing doubted all he saw For phantom mist or mirage: and he loathed The stately hills past loathing, glory-clothed, And found in fairest thing a falsehood and a flaw, Doubting himself besides and loathing nature's law. THE ARCADIAN SHEPHERD. Love of the rosy neck, the restless hair, The vales are breezeless, and the ring-dove's voice Sweetens or ebbs her patient aching pipe, Delicious throes of one old monody, Told and retold, immortal, to the hours. The footsteps of the sunlight, steam'd in blue, Melt from the veilèd portals of the flowers A cloudiness of dews, like trembling dust Behind the wayfarer: the onward lengths Fall bevill'd, seas of leaves and branching plains, Whereon the high noon striking, draws beneath In films of glimmering azure, zone by zone. And all the broad and creeping splendour-flakes Hover or wane their ripple woofs of floor. The swan, who by the sacred courses feeds, Beam-caught has made one star-point of his down. Thy shepherd in the shadows of the hills, I teach the forest lawns my trembling notes And brooding modulation of my loves, Where ripe noon sows the lazy woods with flowers, Moss-hyacinth and wind blooms and the rings Of purple vetches dazzling some sere pine With intertissued bravery as it dies— With love that comes too late in narrow time: We love a little here and fall asleep In earth: the fresh woods mix not with our dreams. The dead are past our grieving; not for these The tamarisk thickets waver, or the Hours Teach music to the branch, nor fountain-head Wakefully pulses out ambrosial sleep, With wave-drift, rainbows, and far-silvered heights Breaking along its changes towards the dawn. Deny not, love, for love is short in prime, So short, the fruit scarce ripe, the bloom-down fades; Reap in these fluttering moments ere they change, Loved or unloved the rough wind strips the tree. Nay, rather come and rest beside me here, The martens titter round the silver rock, The wood-bee hoarding in a wealth of combs; Nay come, I wait thee elbow-deep in flowers. The deep woods swoon with solitude divine; Grape clusters, ivy, poppies, tumbled pears, The gush of streams, and vistas of the Sun Leaning his sacred forehead towards the waves. Come, ere one sterile leaf of autumn sways, Come, ere one crisp bough sickens to the doom Of winter: ere the coronal I laid Breathless beneath the lintel of thy bower Has pined its crumpling petals with delay Sick for thy spicy tresses. Dearest, come, Where under umbrage of delicious coves The dusty cygnets watch their gleaming sires, And sedge-hair brushes the rosed filbert's cheek, And bunch and reed shake pictured in the wave. There, halcyons crown the under-gliding calm, There, the kid, blinking in the sweet-flag net, Butts thro' the osier-thick narcissus fringe; His eager nostrils dwell in leaning thirst, And sailing fishes watch him, golden-eyed. Cruel! I waste my piping and my heart; The rocks have answer'd, but thy voice is dumb. The nightingales change music with the doves; The thrush remurmurs, emulous of song. Thou speakest not, and, widowed of thy voice, The solitudes of pine are tranced with fear. Thy proud limbs move not in the tangled fern. Silent art thou, as some snow-freighted cloud, Robed in a frigid glory, cold and calm; With cruel lips and very noble eyes. And thou hast filled my heart, as some first dove Possesses with one song the early woods. Scornful and fair, in time relent—return! Where ripe days flout the gracious dues of love, Sere Age in sequel deals self-hating hours Of solitary wrinkles unbeloved. So thou relent, and reap the barren years. Arise, and Love shall guide thee thro' the meads, By rooted lilies, wonders of the spring, By vermeil-curtain'd poppies deep in grain, And all the fair ripe summer thro' the land; Until his finger on my threshold rest, My home is yonder and my home is thine. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>