<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Sharp, William,1855-1905</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Sharp, William,1855-1905</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">sharp william1855 1905</field>
      <field name="author_text">Sharp, William,1855-1905</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1880's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.0299.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1884</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466118</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Italian</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Earth's Voices ; Transcripts from Nature, Sospitra, and Other Poems. By William Sharp</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Earth's Voices ; Transcripts from Nature, Sospitra, and Other Poems. By William Sharp</field>
      <field name="title_facet">earths voices</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">earths voices</field>
      <field name="title_text">Earth's Voices ; Transcripts from Nature, Sospitra, and Other Poems. By William Sharp</field>
      <field name="year_display">1884</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1884</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1884</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466118&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466118&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Sharp, William,1855-1905&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;sharp william18551905&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Earth's Voices ; Transcripts from Nature, Sospitra, and Other Poems. By William Sharp&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;earths voices&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1884&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1884&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Sharp, William,1855-1905&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Earth's Voices&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Transcripts from Nature, Sospitra, and Other Poems. By William Sharp&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Elliot Stock&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1884&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp3501&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;ita&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;viii, 207 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Earth's Voices&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Transcripts from Nature, Sospitra, and Other Poems. By William Sharp&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 272 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted; verse reproduced elsewhere in The English Poetry Full-text Database omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">‘I hear the immense chorus over all the world of the return to joy.’ Towards Democracy xvii.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Dedicated IN High Esteem and in Personal Regard TO MY FRIEND, WALTER H. PATER, FELLOW OF BRASENOSE COLLEGE, OXFORD, Author of ‘Studies in the History of the Renaissance,’ Eto.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">‘It is enough to lie on the sward in the shadow of green boughs, to listen to the songs of summer, to drink in the sunlight, the air, the flowers, the sky, the beauty of all ? I want to be always in company with these, with earth, and sun, and sea, and stars by night.’ ‘The hours when the mind is absorbed by beauty are the only hours when we really live, so that the longer we can stay among these things, so much the more is snatched from inevitable time.’ Richard Jefferies.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">‘The tædium vitæ results from incapacity to see ? To write the poetry of Ennui is to mistake the first function of the poet, whose special work it is to lend a new seeing to our eyes, to enable us to see the glory and the wonder of Nature's largess.’ Theodore Watts.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EARTH'S VOICES. I. HYMN OF THE FORESTS. We are the harps which the winds play, A myriad tones in one vast sound That the earth hearkens night and day— A ceaseless music swaying round The whole wide world, each voiceful tree Echoing the wave-chants of the sea. For even as inland waves that moan But break not 'midst the unflowing green Our trees are: and when tempests groan And howl our frantic boughs between, Our tumult is as when the deep Struggles with winds that o'er it sweep. 'Neath bitter northern skies we stand, Silent amidst the unmelting snows, Gaunt warders of the desolate land: Silent, save when the keen wind blows The drifting wreaths about our feet, Then moan we mournful music sweet. Or in vast ancient woods of beech Far south we make Spring's dearest home The haunt of myriad songsters, each A living flow'r made free to roam From bough to bough, and thence we send A forest-music without end. 'Neath tropic suns and ceaseless glow With orient splendours we are filled: 'Midst Austral solitudes we grow, Where seldom human voice has thrilled: And ever and where'er we rise We chant our ancient harmonies. For aye the sea sings loud and long In strange and solemn mystery A wonderful transmitted song— The echo of all history— This song o'er all earth's lands we sing While round the circling seasons swing. II. THE HYMN OF RIVERS. Through all the wide lands of the earth We journey onward to the sea: Swift from the hills that give us birth In melting snows we race in mirth Down through green meadows joyously, Through wood and dale and desert lands, Where bridges span our floods with bands And cities foul our many strands. THE NILE. From Afric depths I come With ever mightier flow, Thro' deserts vast I go, Past crumbling cities dumb And dead, and Sphinxes fair That with a stony stare Brood on in old despair. Past Thebes and Memphis I Roll on my turbid flood: Tired now of ceaseless blood, Beneath this blazing sky I fain would bring long peace, From drought a long surcease. THE TIBER. Majestically, like some great song That moves unto a choral end, My yellow waters sweep along Through Rome, until at last they wend Through lonely Latin swamps till loud Sea-thunders greet them glad and proud. THE RHINE. Thro' pasture-lands and vine-clad heights I curve and sweep— With memories of a thousand fights Lying hidden deep, With echoes of uncounted wars Long laid asleep— Past ruins of ancient castles grim Upon each steep. A thousand meadows I make green With all delight Of flowers, till cornfields clothe the scene Where once the might And dread and tumult of fierce war Filled day and night With blood and death—tho' now I flow With waters bright. I am bless'd and bless: I crave no more Than that my waves may onward pour Forever thus, and be to all The best inheritance of yore. THE THAMES. Through wooded banks and lovely ways My silver waters flow: I linger long in some sweet place Where lilies blow: Past villages and towns I swim With ever-widening size, Until at last I chant my hymn Where London lies. The commerce of the world I bear, Till seaward I have pass'd And, blent with salt waves, onward fare Through ocean vast. THE MISSISSIPPI. With mighty rush and flow I sway For ever on my kingly way, And sing a new song night and day Wherever my brown waters stray: I sing a great land that shall be The glory of Humanity, I chant of nations all made free Under the flag of Liberty: Old beyond count, yet young am I— I read the stars that flash on high, And in their secret signs espy A great and glorious prophecy. THE AMAZON. Through tropic forests and old lands With ruin'd fanes, past sun-scorch'd sands, My mighty flood rolls vast and strong, Chanting a dirge-like ocean song! THE MURRAY. Through Austral plains my waters flow, Through gum-tree forests deep; And silently I grow and grow Until at last I sweep A thousand miles through plain and wood, Then turn my face to where I hear the thundering tidal flood Boom through the air. THE GULF STREAM. From out the Gulf of Mexico Impetuously my waters flow And through the fierce Atlantic glide, A wondrous tepid azure tide— Till all the lands in the North seas, Where else the Polar winds would freeze All life, are filled with warmth and stand Each like a long-drawn emerald band. And as from north to south I swing My song is what the sea-waves sing. Innumerable, our songs are blent In one great chorus that is sent, Now sad and strange, now full of mirth, In circling music round the earth: We are the children of the sea, And we too whisper as we flee The secret of life's mystery. III. THE SONG OF STREAMS. With ceaseless murmur of song We slip through meadow and wood, And we love to linger long Where old dead cities brood With stealthy sweep or with swirl Thro' highland and lowland we flow; In flood-time our waters we hurl, In drought we move shrunken and slow. We sing, like the birds who beside us Are fill'd with the joy of their days, And we follow the course that doth guide us Throughout the long length of our ways— And when in some mightier river Or depths of the sea we are tost, There also we live on forever, For nought that hath lived can be lost. IV. THE SONG OF WATERFALLS. Like veils of mist Adown the hills We bend and twist In a myriad rills, And sway and quiver in the air with a thousand rainbow-thrills. O'er crag and fell We bound in glee, Weaving our spray-spell Mistily About the sunlit mountain heights that flash like the flashing sea. Past mountain-vales And hill-tarns deep, And pine-wood dales Where the winds sleep, We bend, we sway, we quiver with laughter loud, we spring, we sweep. The winds at morn Us break in spray; But we laugh to scorn Their fierce swift play— What though they break us at day-dawn, we triumph throughout the long day! We fall and shiver, Through pools we splash; We flow like a river And downward flash, And loud is our tumult of laughter when over hill-ledges we crash Deep down thro' the heart Of a silent wood, Where the roedeer start And the wild doves brood, Filling the quiet greenness there with echoes of hill-strains rude. From the sun's birth Till the stars creep From the dark, our mirth Doth never sleep, But ever we bend, we sway, we quiver with joy, we spring, we sweep! V. SONG OF THE DESERTS. Wide, open, free, unbounded, vast, We leagueless stretch the wide world o'er: Above us sweeps the desert blast, Or booms the lion's reverberate roar Or the long howl of wolves that race Like shadows o'er the moonlit space In tireless, swift, relentless chase. We are the haunt of all the winds, O'er us as o'er the sea they sweep In boundless freedom: each blast finds A leagueless waste whereo'er to leap And race uncheck'd,—and day and night We hear the wild rush of their flight, A desert-music infinite. Ten thousand leagues of grassy plain We stretch, or trackless wastes of sand: O'er us no mortal king doth reign, But Bedouin or savage band And wild-eyed beasts of prey alone Wander about our tameless zone, That bondage never yet hath known. VI. SONG OF THE CORNFIELDS. For miles along the sunlit lands We sway in waves of gold,— A yellow sea that past the strands Has inland rolled. The sweet dews feed us thro' the night, The soft winds blow around; The dayshine gladdens us with light And stores the ground. We feed a thousand happy birds, The field-mice have their share— Surely to these the reaping swords Some grains can spare. The deep joy of the joyous earth, We feel it throb and thrill; The sweet return of natural mirth, Spring's miracle. All lands rejoice in us, we have A glory such as kings Might envy—but our gold we wave For humbler things. Our golden harvest is for those Who strive and toil through life, Who feel its agonies, its throes, Its want, its strife. O'er all the broad lands 'neath the sun, We spring, we ripen, glow; The seasons change, the swift days run,— Again we grow. VII. SONGS OF THE WINDS. 1. The North Wind. Across the Polar seas, From where the frozen snow Melts with no summer breeze But lieth for ever so, I come, with surging sound And frozen rains that sting, And lash the wintry ground With furious wing. But when 'tis summer weather I cool the sun-scorch'd earth, And chase the clouds together, And laugh with joyous mirth. 2. The East Wind. Keen and relentless My blasts sweep across Where the Baltic billows And North Seas toss; Like bolts from the bow In a tumult of war, They rush and they strike Wild coasts afar. And inland hurrying They sweep and they swirl, And the blossoms of spring From the orchards whirl. And I laugh to hear The moan of the trees, And the sound and tumult Of stormy seas. 3. The West Wind. I come from out the West, And I breathe a breath of rest, And the sweet birds greet me singing From every tiny nest. I am the wind of flow'rs— I haunt the wild-wood bow'rs— And when my song is ringing Spring knows her sweetest hours. But when the autumn days Grow short, I rise and race Thro' all the woodlands, flinging Strewn leaves o'er every place. When winter comes once more, With deep tumultuous roar I sweep o'er ocean, bringing Wild tempests to each shore. 4. The South Wind. From burning deserts bare, From tropic gardens where Sweet blooms and spices rare Make fragrant the warm air, I come, and o'er the deep, Where storm-winds no more sweep But soft-aired breezes creep, Summer I bear asleep. Sweet Summer! in her dreams Her face is fair with gleams Of thought of running streams, Of flowers, and moonshine beams. When I have reached the strand I lay her on the sand And blow away sleep's band— Till, waking, through the land She runs with eyes aglow With joy where rivers flow, Where myriad roses blow, And leaves wave to and fro. And after many days, When o'er the brown burnt ways That thirst 'neath the sun's rays She cares no more to gaze, I carry her again Back to her Southern plain— And till spring comes again I moan and rave in pain. VIII. THE SONG OF FLOWERS. What is a bird but a living flower? A flower but the soul of some dead bird? And what is a weed but the dying breath Of a perjured word? A flower is the soul of a singing-bird, Its scent is the breath of an old-time song: But a weed and a thorn spring forth each day For a new-done wrong. Dead souls of song-birds, thro' the green grass Or deep in the midst of the golden grain, In woodland valley, where hill-streams pass, We flourish again. We flowers are the joy of the whole wide earth, Sweet nature's laughter and secret tears— Whoso hearkens a bird in its spring-time mirth The song of a flow'r-soul hears! IX. THE WILD BEE. Where in the fields the new-mown hay Sweet fragrance makes, I wing my way: I swing within the pliant fold Of bindweed-bell, or o'er the gold Of dandelions and kingcups pass: At times entangled in the grass I sip the purple orchis sweet, Or climb the campion's stalk, then fleet With gauzy wings and happy hum Close to the seeding limes have come, Then off to where the hawthorn blows, And thence where meadow-sweet thick grows! All through the day I hum and fly, My honey-search ne'er cease to ply, And, when the sunlight passes swift, Upon the evening breeze I drift To where within my tiny nest I safely drowse in well-earned rest. X. THE FIELD MOUSE. When the moon shines o'er the corn, And the beetle drones his horn, And the flittermice swift fly, And the nightjars swooping cry, And the young hares run and leap, We waken from our sleep. And we climb with tiny feet And we munch the green corn sweet, With startled eyes for fear The white owl should fly near, Or long slim weasel spring Upon us where we swing. We do no hurt at all: Is there not room for all Within the happy world? All day we lie close curled In drowsy sleep, nor rise Till through the dusky skies The moon shines o'er the corn, And the beetle drones his horn. XI. THE SONG OF THE LARK. High up in azure heaven I sing a magic song, And thrill the wild notes sweetly In rapture loud and long. O joy of azure heaven, Of white clouds as they pass, O joy of sweet flow'rs blooming Down in the cool green grass. O joy of winds that bear me— O burst of song made free— A fount of songtide spraying In a purple sea! O rapture of sweet music— Too sweet, too glad, too dear— What mystery, what wonder, I see and hear! O joy of perfect singing! O joy of life made free! O world-joy, springing, ringing, Joy, joy, alone I see! XII. THE SONG OF THE THRUSH. When the beech-trees are green in the woodlands And the thorns are whitened with may, And the meadow-sweet blows and the yellow gorse blooms I sit on a wind-waved spray, And I sing through the livelong day From the golden dawn till the sunset comes and the shadows of gloaming grey. And I sing of the joy of the woodlands, And the fragrance of wild-wood flowers, And the song of the trees and the hum of the bees In the honeysuckle bowers, And the rustle of showers And the voice of the west-wind calling as through glades and green branches he scours. When the sunset glows over the woodlands More sweet rings my lyrical cry With the pain of my yearning to be 'mid the burning And beautiful colours that lie 'Midst the gold of the sun-down sky, Where over the purple and crimson and amber the rose-pink cloud-curls fly. Sweet, sweet swells my voice thro' the woodlands, Repetitive, marvellous, rare: And the song-birds cease singing as my music goes ringing And eddying echoing there, Now wild and now debonnair, Now fill'd with a tumult of passion that throbs like a pulse in the hush'd warm air! XIII. SONG OF THE NIGHTINGALE. Keen, through supremest music, My song is fill'd with pain: Hark! 'tis the same sad strain That with pathetic cadence thrilled The Thracian plain, When after Procne's flight I sang alone, And thro' my deathless music sent a dying moan. What moonlit glades, what seas Foam-edged have I not known! Through ages hath not flown Mine ancient song with gather'd music sweet— By fanes overthrown, By cities known of old and classic woods, And, strangely sad, in deep-leaved northern solitudes? Nightly my song swells forth, When the grey stock-dove broods And whirling bat eludes The forest boughs, and rings and pants and thrills In passionate interludes— Too sweet, too sad, O sorrow and old-time pain, The love, the glory I see, that will not come again. XIV. THE RAIN SONGS. 1. The Rains of the Equinox. From the gather'd clouds we sweep With lance-like shafts of rain, And we lash the sounding deep, And we scour the sodden plain; And we wheel like armies vast With a hissing sound of mirth, When the thundering trumpet-blast Of Tempest wakes the earth. Where the grey seas fume and rave We rush with stinging sleet, Till the foam on each white wave In scatter'd spray flies fleet; And over the lonely hills We pass in a driven cloud, And feed the mountain-rills Till they surge with clamour loud. Then past the forest trees Upon the wind we hurl, And o'er the low lying leas In gusts we sway and swirl, Past hamlet, village, and town, Till o'er great cities we sway, And break and stream straight down In a mist of smoky grey. 2. Summer Rain. When we're slowly falling, falling, Through the hush of summer eves, And the nightingales are calling Their sweet notes mid the green leaves, And the lilac boughs are sending Their keen fragrance thro' the air, And the slim laburnums bending With their weight of golden hair, Then we feel the thirsty flowers Uplift their blooms again; For the kiss of the sweet cool showers, And the ebb of sun-heat pain. And we breathe a breath of healing Over all things that we pass; Till with tired wings we go stealing To our sleep in the green grass. 3. The Torrid Rains. Above the sun-scorch'd sands we break In ceaseless fall for many days, And a sweet sound of waters make Within the dried-up river-ways. Far amid lonely deserts wide We thrill faint springs with life again, Where the wild things at dusk may glide, And quench at last their thirstful pain. And when at length the clouds arise, They bear us far away to where Pant similar lands beneath fierce skies And furnace-breath of fiery air. XV. THE SNOW WHISPER. Softly, silently, through the night We fall in starry flakes of white, Like wings that make no sound at all We downward float and drift and fall; A myriad downy feathers we, Shrouding the land mysteriously. We cover all the hill-peaks grey, And silently pursue our way Down mountain valleys where no sound Echoes along the frozen ground; We make a thick drift where the sheep Huddle together in their sleep, And o'er the weary stag's retreat We pass and shroud the tracks its feet Have made, and where the shivering hares Crouch low we clothe their barren lairs; Then o'er the hill-side pastures pass And cover up the meadow-grass, And on the branches of the trees Pile thickly till they bend and sway As though borne down by some strong breeze; And in the empty nests we lay Some votive feather-plumes like those Which once bore up the songs that rose From every woodland bough; then o'er The cart-wheeled roadways to the door Of each farm-house and tiny cot, With stiffly-ordered garden plot— Till all the land is clothed with light Soft shining robes of stainless white. And when the wintry moon gleams pale In the cold steel-blue dawn o'er dale And meadow and hill—and far In a faint shine the morning star Trembles from sight—and suddenly A sun-wave, like a wave o' the sea, Upwells from the east in a great flood O'er hill and valley and plain and wood— Behold, the sleeping earth lies there, No longer frozen, bitter, bare, But sacred, white, serenely fair. XVI. SIGH OF THE MISTS. We haunt the marge of streams, And where the bittern booms 'Mid twilight marish glooms, And where the curlew screams Above dim lowlying fields, We drift with motions slow: Or trailing swift we go Where the pine-forest yields Before the tempest's force, And hang in vapoury drifts Or trail in ghostly rifts Amongst the boughs all hoarse With windy tumult wild: Like ghosts, wan, dismal, grey, We haunt the dreary way Where barren rocks are piled: 'Mid valleys dark and dim We brood in sunless dells: We weave our dreamy spells Round ancient castles grim. Aye voiceless, with no sound At all where'er we be, We drift mysteriously Or brood along the ground. XVII. THE RED STAG. For leagues the purple heather lies Upon the hills; the brackens rise Yard high, and from the thorny gold Of gorse-shrubs swift the kestrel flies Unsated from the rabbits' hold: And everywhere the fresh wind sings A joyous song, a fragrance flings, And sweeps above the fern and makes The green fronds toss as when it flakes The calm sea-silence with white foam— And swoops from height to height, and clings To barren crags where nought doth roam Save we, swift-footed stags, in flight— With gusty cries it hurls its might Against those serried peaks that bare Rise up and know no life-joy fair, Save when the golden eagle's wings With rushing sound surge through the air. Ev'n as these mountain winds are we, Untamed and tameless, wild and free; For us the glory of the hills, Their lonely barren majesty— For us the surging mountain rills When melted snow their torrents fills, The windy heights, the sunlit glory Of mountain bastions scarred and hoary; And leagueless moors and mighty lakes, And each lone pine-clad promontory Round which the sea a fierce dirge makes— The children of the hills are we, Untamed and tameless, wild and free. XVIII. THE HYMN OF THE EAGLE. Upon a sheer-sloped mountain height My eyrie is; from thence my sight Looks down o'er the wide lands below: I watch the wild winds swoop and blow In savage violence—but here They howl in vain; I have no fear Who am the lord of this high sphere. At sunrise on this peak I stand, And watch the glory flood the land; And then on mighty wings I speed Far hence for lowland prey to feed My clamorous young—though when night falls Still echo loud their fledgling calls About these gloomy mountain walls. I watch the moon rise o'er the sea And inland sail mysteriously, A globe of silver fire on high; Then pulse the planets in the sky, And flash the stars, and meteors stream: And then I drowse, to wake with dream Of prey, and thro' the stillness scream. XIX. THE CRY OF THE TIGER. Deep in the jungle-grass I lie Until the burning sun on high Hath flamed to death—till shadows fall And far and wide the bulbuls call. Then swiftly, with slow waving tail, I follow some fresh-beaten trail, Or through the rice-stems wanly green I watch the peasant, gaunt and lean, Upon the further river-side: Or nigh some pool I softly glide And when the wild-deer seek the ground I spring with one tremendous bound And drink with thirsty tongue the hot Sweet blood, while far off round me trot The coward jackals with fierce eyes Watching for remnants of my prize. With savage mate I haunt the woods And roam these deadly solitudes, Howl answering howl, until the night Is filled with terror of our might. Twin deaths, we stalk through jungles deep, With swift fierce cries we bend and leap: In hollow thunders far away Our savage howls resound till day. XX. THE CHANT OF THE LION. Athwart the burning bronze-hued sands I send my deep hoarse roar, As boom the tidal seas that break upon a barren shore: Then back the dun hyenas howl, or fleet gazelles far hear And like a flying cloud drift swift across the waste in fear: The distant camels hearken in the long straight caravan, They know the King who feareth not their puny master man. Through cloudless days of blazing heat, through fiery afternoons I crouch and hear the desert winds moan out their mystic runes, But when the burning orb has set, and in the purple sky The star of evening leaps and flames and palpitates on high, Then down unto the desert-pool with stealthy steps I creep, And mid the tall green rushes bend and bide my deathly leap: At times alone come stealthily the fierce hyenas there, Or red-eyed wolves the water lap and howl thro' the still air, Or midst the reeds the leopard's yellow hide, black-spotted, gleams, Or o'er some festering carcase flap gaunt vultures with hoarse screams: At times alone the wild boar comes, or writhe upon the ground The mighty coils of cobras which long fasting hath unwound— Then loud and terrible and fierce my roar booms o'er the waste, And like a great gaunt shadow o'er the moonlit tracts I haste, But far the yellow zebras snort and spurn my stealthy flight And like meteors flash and vanish through the lonely night. But oftentimes the shy gazelles or great-horned fleet-foot deer With wary eyes in companies unto the pool draw near, And when assured they drink their fill and high their antlers fling, Like a sudden bolt from heaven within their midst I spring: Or if they come not nigh at all, mayhap the great giraffe Stoops o'er the wave his mighty neck the longed-for boon to quaff, Then with a sudden roar upon his yellow neck I hurl, And far across the desert sands rider and wild steed whirl, Until at last he sways and falls with red tongue lolling out, And then his quivering breast I tear with one long savage shout— And far and wide thereafter booms across the level plain My hoarse deep roar, like thunderous surge upon the distant main. XXI. THE HYMN OF MOUNTAINS. The mighty giants of the world are we; High o'er the level lands and seas we rise: Great winds sweep round our brows majestically Save when above the highest clouds, 'mid skies Of windless calm, we only hear their sighs, At times a mere faint hum, as to and fro They surge through mighty pinewoods far below. For us long silence and eternal peace: The holy garment of the pure white snow Abides upon our heights where all things cease To live, and where no Spring-breaths blow A sudden bloom of sweet flowers high and low: Alone o'er each wide slope and hollow vale The drifting clouds their purple shadows trail. Far down amongst the hills that cluster round, What solemn stillness reigns, tho' there each gale Howls like a famish'd wild-beast, and doth bound From height to height in vain attempt to scale These upper peaks, serene and cold and pale, Above all violence of night or day, Grandly supreme, inviolate for aye. We know the secret of the planets, where They leap in flame upon their heavenly way; We watch the constellations fill the air— The meteors flash, as though in Titan fray Great Powers launched these burning stars to slay Rebellious foes in some abyss of space: These, not earth's puny troubles, meet our gaze. XXII. THE OCEAN CHORUS. Sea meeting sea, we circle round all lands And chant aloud our old eternal song: With wild fierce music upon northern strands We break, or surge white tropic shores along, And thunder hoarsely our tempestuous boom Far inland till the hollow blast has rolled 'Midst distant vales with ominous sound of doom, The echo of sea-dirges manifold. THE BLACK SEA. Round desolate lands I sway, Round promontories bleak, With tumult fierce alway My sullen wrath I wreak. THE MEDITERRANEAN. Like a vast turquoise I Flow flowery lands between: But oft I moan and sigh For what hath been. THE ATLANTIC. Deep, turbulent, and wide, My waters seldom rest, But surge in tameless pride From east to west. THE INDIAN OCEAN. I bear a thousand freights— Of these I tribute take: No spoil my hunger sates, My long thirst doth not slake. THE AUSTRAL SEA. An ancient land I keep That lay unknown for long, Drowsed in a mighty sleep By my monotonous song. THE PACIFIC. Empress of seas, I roam Amidst a thousand isles Fringed round with snow-white foam— But treacherous my smiles! THE ANTARCTIC. Wan waves o'er grey wastes wander Where drifting icebergs go; With sullen surge I ponder Upon mine ancient woe. THE ARCTIC SEA. Around the Polar world My vast green billows sweep— Or hopelessly are hurled 'Gainst icewalls stern and steep. Sea meeting sea, one ocean ever flows With one tumultuous chorus-song for aye— The same although it chants the eternal snows That shroud the grim death of each Polar day, Or lifts a joyous voice, a tumult strong Where o'er blue waves the wind of summer flees: Ominous, terrible, glorious is our song, The blended chants and dirges of our seas. XXIII. THE HYMN OF SUMMER. Of late I wander'd far o'er southern lands; With lips long parch'd and dry I sang no strain; But wandering inland from hot barren strands O'er sun-scorch'd mountain and o'er burning plain, Upon drear treeless wastes I moved with pain Of fiery thirst, and sped athwart the sands With eager passionate gaze, But shivered as alone through the fierce bronze-hued haze The treacherous mirage afar did gleam, And nought I heard but the hyena's scream, The mournful howl of wolves, and o'er and o'er The lion's roar. But now that thence I come at call of Spring, How sweet the breath is of the fresh blue sea! My thirst and weariness aside I fling, And feel once more serenely glad and free: Old memories of past joys come to me, Each hour some reminiscence sweet doth bring: And now once more I pass Through green-leaved forests and o'er soft emerald grass, By honeysuckle hedges, cowslipp'd plains, Down lovely, winding, interlacing lanes; And ever as I go earth's joy fulfilled Is round me thrilled. Mine eyes are soft with dreams of happy things; Within my breath there is a drowsy spell; The woods grow warm and still, the stock-dove wings Through silent glades where late Spring's miracle Awoke the joyous life through grove and dell: No more with keen electric tremors sings The nightingale, though sweet The yellowhammer yet his glad song doth repeat Where far and wide upon the sun-hazed heights The prickly gorse still flaunts its golden lights,— Though still upon the moor the stonechat's cry Rings loud and high. Swift winds upraise my golden tresses fair; A fragrance of blown roses floats around; I sing a low song through the hot sweet air, A syren song, such as in old days wound 'Midst perilous rocks with magic dreamy sound That breathed of love and rest, of white arms bare And wildly dreamful eyes And snowy breasts, of ancient old-world strains, and sighs Of dear delights that almost were too sweet, Of falling fairy laughters, elfin feet, And murmur'd whispers low as furtive breeze On sundown seas. In dusky eves, when in a mazy dance The grey gnats hum and o'er each twilit field The nightjar swoops with sudden dissonance, And drowsy sheep-bells ring across the weald, And 'midst the ripening corn from sight concealed The corncrake cries, I breathe mine old romance O'er meadow, wood, and dale, And sigh a subtle magic through the moonbeams pale, Till lovers, speechless with their new won bliss, Together cling, as though each lingering kiss Were an embodied joy that might not be Recaught when free. XXIV. THE HYMN OF AUTUMN. I love the purple moors and northern hills Where the deer leap and whirling curlews cry; I love the breath of the west wind that thrills The mountain-pines until mellifluously They send a wild strain through the listening sky: I love to watch the azure shadows creep Across the windless surface of the deep. But more my joy is in the fields of grain, In orchards fill'd with fruit,—the ruddy pear, Peaches that through September suns have lain And breathed the sweetness of the mellow air, Vines heavy with the purple weight they bear, October woodlands where the brown nuts fall And where the redbreasts still their sweet cries call. But most I love th' autumnal peace that broods When ere the equinox come windless days: When spreads a golden glory o'er the woods, An amber-tinted crimson-deepening blaze: Ah! then I love to dream of Summer's ways, And have no fear of Winter stern and dumb, Because I know sweet Spring again will come. XXV. THE HYMN OF WINTER. Southward I come from where eternal snows Lie mass'd in frozen continents; before My wandering feet a bitter wild wind blows, And howls o'er ocean-waste and barren shore And lonely uplands, till o'er fertile plains In fierce tempestuous fury it doth cast Its sounding might, and round the homesteads flies With fierce auxiliaries of stinging rains And icy sleet whirled forth on new-born blast, Engender'd 'midst the dark dense vaporous skies. Far south my herald tempest speeds, and then With snow-bewildering steps I softly come And breathe my deadly breath o'er hill and glen, And leave the leafless forest bare and dumb, And turn to a moveless wave each amber stream, And freeze the lakes and pools to blocks of white, And dust with silver frost the meadow-grass— Wan, deathly, soundless, like a ghost I gleam; Intangible, yet nought resists my might, But stiffens when with chill blank eyes I pass. Nature sleeps fast while I relax no breath: Within the bleak grey air the very rooks Wing with infrequent flight: I breathe cold death Where frozen kingfishers haunt sedgy brooks And where amidst the snow-clad fields the hares Shiver, and skylarks with numbed pinions lie Songless for ever now on alien ground: All that was once so joyous wanly wears A shroud of white, and mournful melancholy In silence broods and hearkens to no sound. When on some day, after long-falling snow, My wild wind wanders from the south again, I break my frozen spell, and to and fro Wander an uncrown'd king, till I am fain To reach once more my changeless Polar waste— And as I northward go with sullen pace I hear faint joyous echoes far off ring, I hear behind fleet dancing footsteps haste, And looking back I see the shining face And flower-filled hands of bird-surrounded Spring. XXVI. THE HYMN OF SPRING. Across the green fields singing I lead my joyous way, A myriad bird-songs ringing Above my flower-strewn way: The white clouds drift above me Within an azure sky, Life stirs and thrills around me— I laugh and onward fly! Adown the lanes and hedges The blackthorns turn to snow, Along brown forest-edges The first primroses blow; A lark rings high and gladly, A blackbird whistles sweet, A speckled thrush sings madly Within some green retreat: With joy the whole land quivers, Woods, meadows, hills, and vales, Swift streams and rolling rivers, When nigh my sweet voice hails. A breath of balm, of healing, I follow Winter's strife— Like death he comes slow stealing, But I with songs of life: I am the transformation Of all that long since fled, The glorious resurrection Of Earth's innumerous dead. SOSPITRA. NOTE. The legend of Sospitra had long haunted my imagination: and when, one day in the late spring of last year, lying in a grassy hollow far out on the Roman Campagna, I came across a detailed reference to this legend in one of Ouida's eloquent books, the unexpected occurrence impressed me with such persistency that finally the story expanded into verse. The legend runs that Sospitra was visited by two spirits in the guise of Chaldeans, and that they endowed her with more than mortal power and knowledge, giving her supremacy over all creatures, and insight not only into the hearts of men, but also into the great laws of the universe. The ‘Chaldeans’ gave her lordship over herself, so that she could know neither grief nor mortal weakness, lordship over herself and over all things— save Love and Death. Proud, content, supremely wise, she dwelt far from the haunts of her kind, amongst ancient ruins in a lonely desert. As it is at this point the poem commences, and as the legend is fully evolved before the close, the ‘argument’ need not here be further extended. I Sospitra dwelt amidst the waste, Her home a ruined temple was; Thereby the fiery wild-ass raced, There the swift leaping wolf did pause, But never came there any one Of all the tribes under the sun. II At dawn she heard the winds arise, And knew where their swift wings would sweep Thro' that long day: athwart the skies She watched th' infrequent cloudlets creep, And saw where in remote lone lands The rains would break their vapour-bands. III She watched the long growth of the noon, The waning of the ample day; She watched the circling of the moon Through splendour of the Milky Way; Morn, noon, and night, she saw where each Successive passed, what far-off beach IV Of isle within Pacific seas Gleamed silver in the sunrise light, At the same time when Afric trees Stood parched amid the fierce noon's might, And dusk of evening slowly stole Where the grey windy north seas roll. V All things before her were laid bare, All knowledge and all power she had; She knew no sorrow, felt no care, Had perfect vision, and was glad: Even as in a glass she saw The evolution of one law. VI She watched the life of nations grow, She heard the sound of puny wars, Each mockery of triumph blow Beneath the same unchanging stars: She heard the sound of prayers rise, Felt the old stillness 'midst the skies. VII Within her brain each thought that passed Within the minds of men was held; Her gaze on each new dream was cast, To her the mists were all dispelled; She saw in flawless nakedness Each truth that man would curse or bless. VIII Far in an old deserted land Sospitra dwelt, 'mid columns vast That ruin'd stood amidst the sand, And had stood since that far off past When Baal fell, and far and wide The nations mocked his shattered pride. IX There sovereign and supreme she dwelt; To her the desert wild things came— The antelope before her knelt, The fierce hyena there grew tame, The lion wandered there by night And let her hand caress his might. X The nightingales that sang anear Flew to her call; lithe serpents twined Before her path; and knew no fear The grey-green lizards she would find On broken marble pedestals, Or clinging to the ruin'd walls. XI She had strange dreams, she felt the throb Of the great world-heart pulse and swing; She heard the low continuous sob Which universal death did wring, Amidst the loud and jubilant strife For ever echoing from life. XII Her days were calm and sweet and still; Her soul, knowing all things, was at peace: O'er her no breath of mortal ill Might blow, nor Time for her increase The burden of his years: alone, Death some far day might claim his own. XIII Death, and that other power—Love: But death would never come to her, From earth around or world above, If she ne'er turned idolater Before the face of him whose eyes Give man his dreams of paradise. XIV And ever when she thought of this Sospitra smiled: she saw too clear The mockery of his transient bliss To dread though Love should draw anear: She saw his myriad worshippers Tread o'er his countless sepulchres. XV To her all passions were as things Of little heed, like leaves that fall, And which the wind takes up and flings Aside: o'er her they had no thrall— She knew their heights and depths, but wise, She looked through each with cold calm eyes. XVI But most she loved the mystery Of night, when o'er the desert plain The twilight shadows stealthily Grew into darkness, and like rain The soft dews cooled the ground and made A new life thrill through each grass-blade. XVII Oft then she wandered from her home, And sought the lonely silent sands; Beneath the stars she loved to roam And call to her the wandering bands Of fleet gazelles, or by her side, Feel the fierce tawny lion glide. XVIII Or midst the ruins she would sit And watch the solemn moonrise fill The ancient halls, where the bats flit Hither and thither, whistling shrill: And dream that once again Baal's priests Held here their sacrificial feasts. XIX These when she wished alone for peace: But when the life-blood overbold Thrilled in her veins and would not cease To stir strange thoughts she scarce controll'd, She sat within her home—and then She looked into the souls of men: XX The inmost secret of each soul To her was bare; the hearts of all She read as she might read a scroll: She saw Death sweep above them all And ever and again stoop low And out some flickering life-flame blow. XXI Ev'n as a scroll that was outroll'd, So unto her the wide world lay: She saw men perish 'midst the cold Of northern lands, and far away The fierce sun beat o'er deserts wide And men athirst who gasped and died. XXII She watched the furious tempest sweep; The shattered vessel plunge and bound Till swallowed up within the deep; She saw the dead men swaying round And round in the green depths, with slow Long swing and eyes that nothing know. XXIII She saw the miner in the womb Of the dark earth: the diver slim Deep down in the strange world of gloom Above the cluster'd pearl-shells swim: And ever as she heard and saw, Her soul was fill'd with some strange awe. XXIV How little seemed each living thing, How puny life of man—brute—flower: And yet, how wonderful the Spring That with regenerative power Swept round the earth—how vast, how great, Humanity confederate! XXV Sospitra saw, and was content: What mattered each small life was vain When all in one great whole were blent, When all were links in one vast chain That rose from earth's remotest sod And passed the stars and reached to God! XXVI These things Sospitra felt and knew, Before her all of life being glass'd: But when the mortal spirit grew Weak with intense keen sight at last— How gladly then she turned to where The fresh wind fill'd the desert air, XXVII Felt its keen breath upon her face, And how it swept the whitening grass Like foam at sea, and swooped in chase Of the swift deer it could not pass: How gladly then she sought the flow'rs Upon the plains, and spent long hours XXVIII In tireless wandering to and fro, Ev'n as a white cloud in the sky Speeds where'er windy currents go: She watched the great-wing'd eagles fly, The wild-ass snort in desert pride Then stamp and race up to her side. XXIX She wished for nothing more; her heart Desired no things she knew of old— It felt no longing, knew no smart— And yet not passionless or cold Her nature—rather, like a hill With calm snows clad, whose heart fires fill. XXX But one day a strange restlessness Fell on her, and a keen desire To know the ill or happiness Of life herself—to feel the fire Ev'n though it should consume: but weak A moment only, with blanch'd cheek XXXI She changed her thought—for well she knew That if Love strove with her and won— Even as a leaf a wild wind blew, So would she be: for ever done The serene glory of her days, The sight and knowledge of God's ways. XXXII And so the seasons fled: the rains Swept from the skies: the winter passed: And one day o'er the shining plains Spring, singing, wandered back at last: Sospitra, glad, supreme, soul-strong, Sang back a sweet rejoicing song. XXXIII Beautiful beyond women she: Yet never had she felt again The wish amongst her race to be: Safe from all grief, or fear, or pain, She watched the unswerving laws of life Move on forever through the strife. XXXIV She looked, and felt her soul expand To see Humanity so great— In power, in will, in faith, so grand— Heedless of love or scorn or hate From Powers it dimly knew—but she Saw God's Will working ceaselessly. XXXV One eve o'ercast the sky became; Great purple-shadowed clouds rose high: There was a flash, a lurid flame— And all the vast vault of the sky Seemed one great mass of whirling fire, With crash on crash and tumult dire, XXXVI While a dull hollow roaring sound Swept through the heavens—as at sea A cyclone like a beast doth bound Upon the waves, and furiously, Finding its strength is vainly thrown, Howls with a long reverberate moan— XXXVII An hour of sound and fire and strange Convulsion and bewild'ring riot! But suddenly there came a change— The lightnings ceased, the sky grew quiet, The shattered clouds were swept away And faint stars fill'd the twilight grey. XXXVIII Sospitra felt the peace, and slept; She dreamed strange dreams: she saw a host Of spirits, and each spirit wept; She saw a bleak and lonely coast Where one soul evermore did pace— She looked, and knew her own pale face: XXXIX But last she dreamed that once again The Spirits who had come before, Who gave her power o'er things to reign, To be than mightiest king far more— That these two Spirits came and stood, With eyes that on her soul did brood: XL And that one spake to her and said, ‘Still is it well with thee? Hast thou No wish for mortal joys, fair maid— Would'st fain fulfil thy days as now? But, if thou would'st not change, be strong— For Love and Death have waited long.’ XLI Then down through sleep's phantasmal ways In dreams she wandered sad, alone, Until she came to a drear place And saw a monumental stone Whereon she read, Here lies the dust Of one who placed in Love her trust. XLII Then deeper still she slept, and dreamed No further dreams the whole night long: And when at dawn the sunlight streamed And woke her, she cried out, ‘Yea, strong I am, and fear nor Love nor Death, The chill cold touch, nor fiery breath!’ XLIII She rose, and with swift footsteps passed Between the columns, all aglow With roseate-hues, and faced the vast Reach of the plains, felt the winds blow About her the sweet desert scent— Was proud, and glad, serene, content. XLIV That eve upon the waste she spied What never she saw there before— A horseman swaying side to side, With reins fall'n down as if from sore Fatigue—or out of sheer despair In being on trackless deserts bare. XLV With steadfast eyes awhile she gazed And watched the horseman nearer come: She saw his eyes were dim and dazed, His dry parch'd lips were fixed and dumb, And that upon his clothes there lay Thick clots of blood from some fierce fray. XLVI Then with a slow strange smile she rose And 'midst the temple-columns stood— A marble goddess in her pose, And even as marble was her mood: And thus she watched the horseman ride With weary languor to her side. XLVII And he, who had no hope at all Save that in this deserted fane Death would not long abide his call Nor hesitate to end his pain, Stood wearily before the face He judged the goddess of the place. XLVIII Then suddenly he forth did reach His hands, and half in mockery And half unknowing what his speech Might be, he cried out bitterly— ‘Oh thou, pale goddess, whose old fame Is blown away like dust—whose name XLIX ‘Is rumoured in no lands, and here Is less than any flower that springs To life with each returning year, Who art less than these bright dying things That in the sunlight live an hour— Less than the least of these thy pow'r: L ‘Yet ev'n to thee I pray, who now Know all prayer to be vain indeed— To thee at last I bend my brow, Who of all other gods take heed But little—and since He they call The Lord Omnipotent o'er all LI ‘Has heard no weary cry of mine Upon these desert plains—lo I Before thee bend, and offer wine Of blood, and life's faint ebbing cry To thee who as a true god must Rejoice I turn again to dust. LII ‘The wine of blood and life's last sob I lay before thy shrine, who art So lonely now, I would not rob The long despair of thy chill heart Of such slight pitiful worship as My soul can give ere it doth pass. LIII ‘Take thou my life, poor goddess, take— Unless indeed some power remain Of thine old faculty to make The pulse of life beat swift again— Take thou or heal, who standest there Cold, passionless, serenely fair!’ LIV Scarce had he spoken, ere with moan Of fear and awe his heart grew still: He saw a tremor in the stone And watched the mantling life-blood fill The face, and heard a low voice say, ‘Whence comest thou who here dost pray?’ LV Then with the surge of hope he fell Upon his knees, and cried, ‘O save Me now, who by some miracle Dost speak, like one who from the grave Comes back with message to restore Sweet hope to one who hoped no more!’ LVI But with his cry his strength ebb'd fast, Prostrate he fell before her feet; Sospitra thought the life had passed, The weary throbbing heart to beat— But ere long breathed he a slow breath, And not as one that perisheth. LVII And then as in a dream he rose And stagger'd where Sospitra led His feeble frame to sweet repose, Cool water for the wounds that bled, And food and wine, and slumbers deep With one to guard and safe watch keep. LVIII But even as they entered where Her secret room was, an old wound Reopened, and he gasped for air And gave a cry and once more swooned: She caught him in her arms, afraid That Death his final thrust had made— LIX But where his faintly beating heart Lay close to hers she felt it throb:— A moment, and his eyes apart Wide opened, and a low glad sob Broke from his lips, and ere she knew His arms with sudden strange strength drew LX Her body close to his until They stood together breast to breast, And then she felt his life-blood thrill Her own, and knew his hot lips pressed To hers, and, all her heart aflame, Heard his mouth utter some sweet name. LXI Then from her arms he fell, and slid Upon the couch: some moments she With strange glad eyes her flushed face hid Within her hot hands tremulously, And then she swiftly bent o'er him, But as she looked her soul-sight dim LXII And dimmer grew, until no more She saw life like a scroll outrolled, Nor read the strange mysterious lore Her spirit brooded on of old: Her dreams seemed far away to her, Buried in some strange sepulchre. LXIII She laved his wounds, and brought him wine And food, that when he should awake He might have these things for a sign He lived indeed, and might partake And gain his past strength back, and be Once more his old self verily. LXIV And then Sospitra left, and through The silence of the dusk she went; She saw the same stars in the blue Dark vault, she felt the same sweet scent Blown from the wide free plains, saw race The swift deer fleeing from place to place— LXV The same, and yet to her how strange They were: they did not seem her own Familiar sphere, or else some change Had over them a dim veil thrown, As evening mists rise up and steal And make the landscape seem unreal. LXVI No thoughts were hers, but many sighs: One prayerful voice alone she heard 'Midst all the universe; her eyes Saw one who gazed, whose sudden word Had lit a fire within her veins And thrilled her with ecstatic pains. LXVII Long while she wandered to and fro In this dream-mood, then slowly turned And sought the room where he lay low Whom she had saved: a soft flame burned Therein, and by its crimson light She saw he slumbered still, death-white. LXVIII And as she watched, sleep came on her; She in a dreamless slumber lay As if entranced; no sounds there were In that still place, though far away The hoarse hyenas on the plain Howled in their savage hunger-pain. LXIX And while she slept, he woke: strange awe Filled him at first—he dimly thought This was a goddess whom he saw Beside him, whose pure face he sought With questioning eyes and heart that thrilled, But ever with a fear that chilled. LXX But as the strange magnetic gaze Of human sight can ev'n control The mind of one whom fevers daze And waken the sense-clouded soul, So in her sleep Sospitra stirred, And muttered dreamily one word— LXXI The one word Love, and through her eyes Two single tears came forth, and low From parted lips breath'd sudden sighs: But he who watched, with heart aglow With sudden exultation cried, ‘No goddess she who here beside LXXII ‘Me dreams, no prophetess austere! No goddess ever yet did keep A mind a mortal swayed, no tear A goddess ev'n in secret sleep E'er knew, no sad sighs ever moaned Nor even in dreams Love's lordship owned!’ LXXIII And with his low exulting cry Sospitra woke, his last words still Like dream-sounds echoing mockingly— Love's lordship—how the words did fill Her heart with a delirious bliss And all her old calm strength dismiss! LXXIV Then as a rain-cloud comes on swift Aërial wings across the vault Of heav'n, and the grey rain-mists drift Till the lost wayfarer, at fault, Succumbs and drops—so fever drew A mist across his mind and blew LXXV Phantasmal visions o'er his sight, Until his struggling soul sank far In darkness, as when clouds at night Hide the keen pulse of fieriest star: For days he lay thus, till at last One eve the fever ceased and passed. LXXVI The ebb of strength returned and flowed Till the new life felt sweet and strange: While day by day Sospitra glowed With lovelier beauty: some swift change Had turned the seer into a woman, Made the divine calm heart grow human. LXXVII One eve they sat together where Beyond the fane two palm-trees stood: There was a stillness in the air, Not ev'n the desert-wind did brood Afar; and neither spoke nor stirred, Each vaguely waiting some swift word. LXXVIII Slowly above the level waste The full moon rose and sailed on high: At times swift sudden meteors raced And flashed athwart the solemn sky: The planets pulsed in fire, and bright The starry hosts shone through the night. LXXIX Long silent they, till overhead A burning meteor swung through space, A crimson flame that flashed and sped: Then swiftly turned they face to face, And with one low sweet cry she knew His lips were press'd to hers and drew LXXX Her soul to his: she felt his breath Come quick and hard—and glad, elate, Her spirit cried—‘If this be death, Lo, than poor Life how much more great!’ Then passionate ardours swept her soul, As a wind sweeps o'er waves that roll: LXXXI She clung to him, she felt each kiss Like flame her very being fill, She quiver'd with the strange new bliss, She felt it throb, and pulse, and thrill— She knew the Passion of Love, and fell A slave 'neath its resistless spell. LXXXII O hours thereafter and strange night— How sweeter far than the old dream, To yield beneath Love's conquering might! Could any after-glory stream Upon the soul that would not be Compared with this a mockery!— LXXXIII So thought Sospitra: and for days In this long ecstasy of love She dwelt, content alone to gaze Upon her lover's face above, To hear the music of his words, to feel Sweet rapturous longings o'er her steal. LXXXIV The days and weeks went past; till he Felt weary for his life of old: The time grew long monotony, Passion wax'd faint and then lay cold And dead: and one day far he rode But never sought the ruin'd abode LXXXV Again, nor her who erewhile gave Him life, and thereby also laid Her greatness in a deep sure grave. Ev'n as a flower doth droop and fade Sospitra paler grew, faint, weak— She could not cry aloud nor speak LXXXVI A single prayer: she had no pow'r At all as she of old-time had: To her brought now the midnight hour No wondrous visions: she grew glad No more with fervour of high thought, God's mystic ways no more she sought. LXXXVII A woman now, she knew that Death Would follow Love, and for his rest She sighed with many a bitter breath: Till one night words came—‘It is best: I would not love's sweet dream undo, Though thus his mockery I rue. LXXXVIII ‘I also am of those who live A brief swift span, who pass away With all life's passions fugitive; But ah, in that miraculous day When all Life's complex mysteries Were clear unto my steadfast eyes, LXXXIX ‘I saw, as I might read a scroll, That death was but a change, a birth, A rest, and that th' enfranchised soul Reached to a higher life on earth— That ever upward, upward, went The soul in its divine ascent: XC ‘Therefore I fear no more at all; Therefore I do not cry again For the old glory I let fall From out my life: through joy, through pain I shall reach onward, till once more My life is as my dream of yore.’ XCI Slowly the long dull hours went by: No more Sospitra far and wide Roved o'er the plains, but listlessly She watched the days to evenings glide, The moon succeed the sun, the stars the moon, Each slow dawn lead to fiery noon. XCII Death came to her one lonely eve And looked upon her pale sad face: ‘Though Love doth pass, I shall not leave Thee ever in my silent place,’ He whispered gently through her sleep,— Then breathed o'er her his slumber deep. XCIII The wind blows there with hollow sound; The circling seasons bring no change: When sweet Spring's breath along the ground Wakens the flow'rs, no footsteps range The fragrant ways, no song is heard Save the shrill music of some bird. XCIV The ruined columns, stone by stone, Stand silent 'midst the desert vast: There the hyena howls alone, Or swells the fierce sirocco-blast Or the dull roar of lions, like sea Calling to sea monotonously. TRANSCRIPTS FROM NATURE. [First Series] NOTE. These ‘Transcripts’ (including the selection in the latter part of this volume), like those which appeared in The Human Inheritance: And Other Poems, are portions of a series forming a kind of private Liber Studiorum, and are here inserted in no natural sequence, but almost at random. This, while practically a necessity on the part of the selector, is calculated to afford more diversity of interest to the reader. As a rule, but not invariably, I have used the detached couplet which finishes each ‘Transcript’ as the means of some supplementary touch, heightening the effect by bearing in some way or other upon the broad outline produced in the preceding six lines. The ‘Transcripts’ are uniform throughout, save slight modifications of the final couplet in Nos. x. and xiv. I. TROUTLING. In the clear grey-brown stream the reeds Rise like tall branchless pines, and glades Are there, where in the twilight shades Like flowers seem the water-weeds: And to and fro amidst the slim Reflected leaves the troutling swim Like birds amongst the trees, but sing No song, and flit on noiseless wing. II. THE WASP. Where the ripe pears droop heavily The yellow wasp hums loud and long His hot and drowsy Autumn song: A yellow flame he seems to be, When darting suddenly from high He lights where fallen peaches lie: Yellow and black, this tiny thing's A tiger-soul on elfin wings. III. IN A GARDEN. (Midsummer.) Above the beds of mignonette, Or 'midst the wall-flowers' drowsy spells Or swaying in Canterbury bells The brown bee hums: o'er wild-thyme wet With streamlet sprays, the dragon-fly Hangs blue-black 'gainst the azure sky: And like blown wild-rose leaves alow White butterflies drift to and fro. IV. THE KINGFISHER. As Mr. W. Stokes has pointed out (Academy, 16th February, 1884), Tennyson, when referring to the kingfisher as ‘the sea-blue bird of March,’ in Stanza xci. of In Memoriam, has evidently taken the phrase from Alcman, who, in his twelfth fragment, uses an identical Greek phrase. Voss, in his hexametrical translation, speaks of it as the purpurner vogel des frühlings. See also subsequent suggestions in the Academy (15th March) in favour of the wheatear, the blue titmouse, and the swallow: but there is little doubt that both Alcman and the Laureate meant the kingfisher. 'Neath drooping grasses slips the stream, And on a bulrush bending low The ‘bird of March’ sways to and fro A-shimmer in his sunlit gleam; Some splendid orchid seems he there, Soft swaying in the bright Spring air, With yellow iris-flowers around And gold marsh-mallows o'er the ground. V. FIREFLIES. (In the Ardennes.) While the fireflies of Italy are invariably of flame colour, varying from red to pale crimson, and even to faint orange, those I have seen in more northern latitudes—as in the Ardennes and the Province of Luxembourg—have as invariably been green, as well as generally less resplendent. The farther south, the warmer the clime, the more brilliant are these ‘wandering fires.’ Softly sailing emerald lights Above the cornfields come and go, Listlessly wandering to and fro: The magic of these July nights Has surely even pierced down deep Where the earth's jewels unharmed sleep, And filled with fire the emeralds there And raised them thus to the outer air. VI. THE FIREFLY. While the fireflies of Italy are invariably of flame colour, varying from red to pale crimson, and even to faint orange, those I have seen in more northern latitudes—as in the Ardennes and the Province of Luxembourg—have as invariably been green, as well as generally less resplendent. The farther south, the warmer the clime, the more brilliant are these ‘wandering fires.’ The short sweet Tuscan twilight dreams Into the reverie of night— Darkness and stillness, save a light That comes and goes with sudden gleams;— A living flame, an unborn soul Slow wandering towards an unspied goal, Thus in its shining devious flight The firefly seems to me to-night. VII. TANGLED SUNRAYS. Aslant from yonder sunlit hill The lance-like sunrays stream across The meadows where the king-cups toss I' the wind, and where the beech-leaves thrill With flooding light they twist and turn And seem to interlace and burn, Until at last in tangles spun 'Mid the damp grass their race is run. VIII. A RAIN-MIST ON LAKE LUGANO. Dark as the night,—and still as though The mountain-shadows lying there Defied the wind's power to lay bare Their haunts of endless sleep,—below The rugged hills Lugano lies, No longer blue beneath blue skies: But o'er it broods a filmy mist, Stone-grey just touch'd with amethyst. IX. MOUNT PILATUS. (Thunder, without wind or rain.) A livid blue-black pall, with streaks Of lurid light, doth darkly frown Above Pilatus looking down With sovran scorn on lesser peaks; Wan shifting lights upon these lie— But no rains fall, no wind-wings fly Though now the steel-blue lightnings flash Where the scarr'd peak withstands the crash. X. MUSIC AND MOONLIGHT. (Lake of Lucerne.) The violet wavelets ripple in Upon the shelving shore; and through The scented limes a glimpse of blue, The purple-blue of night, I win: Yonder Lucerne lies mass'd, all white In the full moon's redundant light, And happy laughter comes on fleet Aerial wings, and echoing music sweet. XI. SIGNA. Thro' winter and thro' summer's days Hoar Signa dreams her old-time dream: The olives make a silvery gleam About her sun-white hillside ways And the old houses mellow-toned. Widowed, still sitteth she enthroned, Still watches Arno's swift stream flee With dead leaves to the Pisan sea. XII. A BOULDER. (On the Roman Campagna.) A sea of billowy green around— Above, the hollow azure dome: This rock, half buried in the loam, Has reached, man knows not how, this ground: Time-worn, and scored as with sea-shells, It doth not heed the blue harebells— The twin blue butterflies at rest— The lizard—on its old grey breast. XIII. SUNSET ON THE MAREMMA. Vast tracts of swamp and desert-land Stretch leagueless onward from the hills: No broad stream flows, but sluggish rills Crawl thro' the moss and marsh and sand: No sign of life, save one black crow That on a tireless wing doth go: The whole one crimson hue, from gleams Blood-red, the dead sun's dying beams. XIV. A SIROCCO NOON: FROM SAN NICOLETTO. As through a silver-woven veil Of gauze, I see Venezia gleam Thro' the June heat; a soft blue gleam Shifts o'er the shallow sea; a sail, Of saffron with a strange device, Hangs idly where a shallop lies Moveless:—o'erhead the acacia-blossoms turn I' the faint wind; around, the poppies burn. XV. THE LAGUNA MORTA. Above, the intense blue of the sky— Flawless, save that a white gull wings Seaward—soundless, save that there rings A rapturous lark-song from on high: But all around a dead drear waste Stretches for miles—rank swamps ungraced By life, save where the yellow newts Revel 'midst ooze-fed marish roots. XVI. A VENETIAN SUNSET: BEFORE A CHANGE. (Returning from Torcello.) In violet hues each dome and spire Stands outlined against flawless rose O'er this a carmine ocean flows Streak'd with pure gold and amber fire, And through the sea of sundown-mist Float isles of melted amethyst: Storm-portents, saffron streamers rise, Fan-like, from Venice to the skies. XVII. AN ‘IMPRESSION.’ (Midnight, on the Laguna di Mestre, under the long railway bridge spanning the distance between Venice and the mainland.) A hundred arches left and right Are mirror'd in the calm lagoon; The stars pulse there, and the gold moon Sails through a nether sphere of night: A distant roar—a flame—a crash— A whirling fiery bolt—a flash— The train is gone; the echo's o'er; The arch'd lagoon is still once more. XVIII. THE SOUTH FORELAND. (Stormy Sunset.) Across th' ensanguined sea the sun Sinks slowly through the blood-red west; The wind hath moaned itself to rest; A star leaps forth—the day is done; Far down below the tide doth lift Itself against the cliff, with swift Resurge adown the shingly shore And hollow, deep, resilient roar. XIX. SEA-SHALLOWS. The slow tide rises up the rocks Waving the seaweed to and fro, The amber tresses in their flow Seeming like those long mermaid-locks In which drown'd sailors lie adream: Between them little fishes gleam, And clouds of wavering shrimps o'er bars Of sand, and fork'd slow-moving stars. XX. THE NINTH WAVE. Lying here upon this rock whose base The grey sea keeps, I watch the waves, Wind-driven and rebellious slaves, Sweep hither in their reckless race: Now one dies, now another rears And breaks in countless briny tears, But one, the ninth, green, hollow, vast, Towers ere it falls, defying the blast. XXI. THE CAVES OF STAFFA. (Gale from the South-West.) The green Atlantic seas wash past The mighty pillars of basalt; A vast sea-echo through the vault Swells like a captive thunder-blast; The wind fierce show'rs of spray doth sweep Through the cave's gulf, and loud the deep Resistless billows in their course Thunder within in tumult hoarse. XXII. LOCH CORUISK. (Skye.) The bleak and barren mountains keep A never-ending gloom around The lonely loch; the winds resound, The rains beat down, the tempests sweep, The days are calm and dark and still,— No other changes Coruisk fill. Scarce living sound is heard, save high The eagle's scream or wild swan's cry. XXIII. THE AFTERGLOW. (Canary Islands.) The purple twilight dwelleth long Amid these western isles, and fills The ocean with a peace that stills The soul, as with their strange sea-song The old-time syrens soothed away The unrest of an earlier day: The crescent moon and one large star Hang o'er the Afric coast afar. XXIV. SUNSET AT THE AZORES. (Against the Orange Groves.) Across the Atlantic's moving gold The aerial floods of sunset flow, Till all the orange-orchards glow As if earth's ingots hither rolled Were mass'd, the giant task being done, To get a last touch from the sun: The sky-gold reddens—redder shine The groves, as steeped in ruby wine. XXV. ON THE THAMES EMBANKMENT. (Cleopatra's Needle.) Through centuries where the fiery sun Of Egypt scorched the desert sands, Greeted alone by Bedouin bands, The obelisk beheld Time spun Through generations as though hurled Down the long slope of a dead world: Now here it stands; but doth it see For England Egypt's destiny? XXVI. EMPIRE. (Persepolis.) The yellow waste of yellow sands, The bronze haze of a scorching sky! Lo, what are these that broken lie, Were these once temples made with hands? Once towers and palaces that knew No hint of that which one day threw Their greatness to the winds—made this The memory of Persepolis? GASPARA STAMPA. NOTE TO ‘GASPARA STAMPA.’ Gaspara Stampa—the Venetian Sappho as she has been called—was one of the most poetic and fascinating personages of the poetic and fascinating times in which she lived. The friend of Titian and Sansovino and others of that brilliant company who made Venice for a time the centre of the highest civilization, she had also every personal qualification—genius, beauty, culture—save that of patrician birth. Loving, and for a time loved by the Count of Collalto, one of the princeliest and most accomplished of the nobles of Venice, she was unfortunate in having her passionate love ill-rewarded. The Lord of Collalto, while on a mission to Paris, was there enthralled by the famous Diane de Poitiers, and this becoming known to Gaspara so preyed upon her life that, after writing many beautiful, dignified, and pathetic verses and sonnets, in which she embalmed her disastrous passion, she died, or, as is sometimes said, poisoned herself, in the full bloom of her lovely and accomplished youth. For my first acquaintance with the incidents of her life and the subjects of her verses (which I was fortunate in making before going to Venice) I am indebted to the eloquent little essay by Mr. Eugene Benson, the well-known American painter, residing in Rome. This essay prefaces a number of admirable translations of Gaspara Stampa's sonnets, by ‘George Fleming,’ the author of ‘A Nile Novel,’ etc., the whole forming a little book which was published in 1882, by Roberts Bros., of New York. In the following lines I have merely endeavoured to give four representative scenes from the life of Gaspara, founded partly on her own statements and partly on strong probability. (See also Notes.) If so slight a thing were worth dedicating, the writer would have asked his friend, Mr. Eugene Benson, to let him associate it with his name—not only as a mark of personal regard, or as an acknowledgment of indebtedness, but also from the high opinion he has of Mr. Benson as an artist. Saffo de' nostri tempi alta Gaspara. I. At San Salvatore. San Salvatore is where the Lords of Collalto had their seignorial residence. The name ‘Cadore’ in the ninth line is Anglicised from Cad?ré. Adown its stony sunwhite bed The hill-stream slipp'd—not as it sped In winter when it raged along In reckless ecstasy of song, Nor as in early Spring full fed By melting snows—but shrunken thin And with a dreamy murmuring sound Betwixt the rocks and stones it wound: It sang the cool joys of Cadore, It whisper'd lowly o'er and o'er The secrets which the flowers had lain— The flow'rs of the Trevisian plain— Upon its wavelets knowing they Would reach the great sea one sure day, That sea of which they vaguely knew As where their song-bird lovers flew When the sweet months had gone and all The land was no more musical. The blue Venetian Alps rose sheer And stretch'd far north, divinely clear, Height blending into height until It seemed as if the wave would fill And break and sweep in azure flood O'er mountain, meadow, and vale, and wood. Above the wild Piavè's stream An ancient cedar dreamed its dream In windless silence solemnly, Rememb'ring how the swift years fly, How brief the life of flower and bird And man, how futile every word Of love, whether of wooing wind Or mated songsters when they find Their nests wind-swept, or men who vow Time shall be unto them as now. And midway in its vast deep shade, Cool, fragrant, dark as greenest glade In some old forest, hand in hand Two lovers sat, with eyes that scanned Each other as with eager thirst The traveller in some lone land Beholds a visioned paradise Nor knows the vision then accurst. There was a wonder in her eyes, A wonder that such joy could be For her, and all the world not see The glory that upon it dwelt: Holding her lover's hand she felt The wide green earth a transient dream, And Time an evanescent gleam, And Fate an empty sound that blew About the windy wastes of space, And Death a shadow faint that flew Far off with an averted face. Ev'n as a flower she was, so fair, So sweet and delicate and rare: A face that one might see in dreams, With deep dark eyes whose sudden gleams Flashed straight from the pure soul within; And like a halo was the hair In golden glory gather'd where The lily-neck rose white and thin. A lily seemed she verily To him whom all men thought to be The perfect rose of manlihood: Within the eyes that oft did brood Upon Gaspara's loveliness Life ever burned in passionate mood; The very joy of joyousness, The lust of life was his, the glow, The fervour which in youth some know When all life's joyous fragrant flow'rs Hedge the glad way whereon we go, Heedless of Time's relentless hours. So sat the twain one autumn day In the cool cedarn shade whence they Looked down where the Piavè flowed Beneath, and past the sun-scorched road That led to white Collalto, high Against the azure of the sky, Amongst its olive-groves, upon The blue heights reaching on and on Till lost in that aerial haze Which is the breath of autumn days: Behind them the Trevisian plain Lay bathed in light, its fields of grain Like sheets of shimmering gold, and far, With the swift sparkle of a star, Where a broad band stretch'd wide away The azure Adriatic lay. Long had they silent sat; for love Broods on itself, ev'n as a dove Dreams scarcely crooning o'er its peace: Love scorns poor words, it hath release In silence. When at last he broke The silence with the words he spoke It seem'd to both as if the hour Were filled with some magnetic pow'r, Some vivid, keen, electric force That drew them each to each,—as though Twin leaves they were in one strong flow United 'midst a torrent's course. ‘Love, love,’ he cried, and bending low He kiss'd the tremulous lips again And yet again till the sweet pain Of yearning in her eloquent eyes And the soft magic of her sighs Set his hot heart aflame to hold Her lovely body in embrace, To feel her arms his frame enfold, With breast to breast and face to face. Sweet hours, too soon they passed away. The glory on the plain grew grey And Twilight stole with misty feet From purpling hill to hill to meet The swarthy darkness as it came With one bright starry signal flame: Then hand in hand the lovers went Up the steep hill-side path to where The castle's moonlit towers leant Against the purple-shadowed air. II. At Titian's House in Venice. lines 15 to 30. Irene here refers to the beautiful Irene of Spilemburg: Violante Palma was that lovely daughter of the famous painter of the same surname, whose portraiture the latter has transmitted to us in many paintings, but most memorably in the beautiful ‘Sta. Barbara’ in the Church of Sta. Maria della Formosa, in Venice: Cornelia was Titian's sister: Molino was a well-known poet in his time, and of course the names of Sansovino, Varchi, Cardinal Bembo, And Pietro Aretino require no comment. As the sun set o'er the low land Where Mestre lies, a goodly band With Titian held festivity: Slowly a glory changed the sea Till o'er each broad lagoon there rolled A tide of purple, crimson, gold, Or delicate amber: far away The blue aerial hills rose clear Beyond where the north islands lay Bathed in soft purplish light; more near Burano and Murano gleamed, And where by San Michele drear The buried dead of Venice dreamed A sudden saffron splendour streamed. All were the guests of Titian there: Gaspara Stampa, noble, fair; Irene, beautiful and young, For whom the fierce Tedeschi swung Their swords; and Palma's famous maid, Violante of the golden hair; Cornelia who so often played Sweet tunes to still the strange unrest Her brother knew: and for the rest, Varchi was there, and Bembo whom With Sansovino 'midst that room Titian most loved, the tall fair slim Molino, and anigh to him The lord Collalto debonair, And lastly with a mocking air Pietro Aretino, who Made most men his keen rancour rue. The foregoing lines are based on the fine painting by Mr. Eugene Benson, entitled An August Evening at Titian's Home, Venice, exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1882. Swift gondolas upon the tide Like swans went past, and far and wide The tinkling of the vesper bells Rang clear, or came in low soft swells Across the calm lagoons; at times A voice rose singing idle rhymes, Or a clear lute or mandolin Played one of those old tunes that win Our souls to memories of past years And fill the eyes with sudden tears. A brief while all sat hushed and still, Till Aretino rose to fill His neighbour's glass: then Titian spake— ‘When from such silence we awake Is it not even as we had seen Some strange new thing, as we had been Within the heavenly places where Pure spirits fill the holy air?’ ‘Yea,’ Sansovino said, ‘we see Then: at other times we dream. But Aretino laughed, ‘To me Such moments pleasant are, they seem Restful indeed, but more of earth Than heaven, a breathing-space for mirth To rest herself, for thought to sleep, A time the delicate wine to keep Within the mouth until we catch Its subtlest flavour, even to snatch Some moments' slumber. Come, we're fain For music—let's do life no wrong: Fair Violante, sing that strain Of mine I made for singing long Ago and called “The Syren-Song.”’ (Violante sings:) There where the lotos scents the drowsy day, And hushful fountains fall in ceaseless spray And strange bright birds their sweet songs sing alway— I dream, dream, dream of something sweet and dear, But when I dream I dream in secret fear. The great gold-hearted lilies lie alow Upon the gliding waters as they flow, Like white moons in a liquid sky they glow. Upon a bank of violets I lie Watching the purple shadows flitting by, And dream my dream's fulfilment is anigh: And the cool waters kiss my white limbs fair, And all about me falls my veil of hair, And some strange longing fills me unaware. But here at night, anigh the whisp'ring stream, I lie amid the lotos-lilies' gleam, And feel the sweetness of some coming dream. As when a nightingale doth sing At twilight and repeated sweetness fling Far thro' the dusky woods, so sang The singer with a voice that rang Far out across the twilit sea, Now clear and strong, now hushfully With magic in the low sweet notes: The fisher-folk within the boats That southward sailed swift crossed and prayed As though indeed some Syren maid Sang a too sweet prophetic tune. Then slowly rose th' autumnal moon, Golden and round, and made a track Of ever-changing silver where The tidal wash of the lagoon Swept past the islands, purple-black Already in the dusky air. And smilingly Collalto took His mandolin, with one swift look To where Gaspara sat with eyes That answered with a glad surmise: (Collalto sings:) While sways the restless sea Beyond the shore, And the waves sing listlessly Their secret lore, And the soft fragrant air From off the deep Scarce stirs thine outspread hair,— Sleep! Far up in purple skies Great lamps hang out, White flames that fall and rise In motley rout; While fall their silvern rays O'er crag and steep, Woodlands and meadow-ways,— Sleep! While the moon's amber gleams Gild rock and flow'r, Let no untimely dreams Possess the hour: Let no vague fears the heart 'Mid slumber keep, In dreams love hath no smart,— Sleep! When he had ceased, with a slow smile Scarce hiding its malicious guile Pietro Aretino said, ‘To whom, fair lord, to which sweet maid Were these words sung? For surely she Will answer with swift courtesy?’ But even as he spake and sneered, Gaspara turned with eyes that feared No mocking, but with far-off gaze Sang, with a strange light on her face: Song on page 97, beginning I gaze into thine eyes, is founded on the fifth and fourth of the Sonnets by Gaspara as translated by ‘George Fleming.’ I have kept as literally as practicable to the latter's more measured rendering. I gaze into thine eyes And gazing there behold The glory of Paradise: Only one fear can make my hope grow cold, Only one dread within my heart still lies— Would'st thou wert mine to my last hour to hold! O fair and fatal face, That steals my soul away, O sweet divinest grace: O miracle of love—that thou should'st pray My heart's desire, that knows no little space Wherein it never doth thy rule obey. But with a sudden evil look, Lent Aretino o'er, and took From off its place a small guitar, And said, ‘Love is a fallen star: We do not well to rant and rave Of what is soon quenched in the grave, Which doth not break death's silence, nor Arise, when once the tomb's closed o'er. I call it what it is: a thing To have awhile, laugh, jest at, fling To the winds again—but never I Pray for Love's lordship endlessly. Here is my song:—’ But Titian said, ‘Nay, is not Love that seed God laid Beyond the gates of Paradise— An Eden-flower to grow and rise, Which whoso gathereth shall know His soul is no mere empty breath, Nor closèd stand the Gates of Death?’ Then Bembo: ‘Love is God's first seal To sanctify the soul's advance: Death is the next.’ ‘And when we feel,’ Gaspara said, ‘Love's quenchless fire, We fall not but we reach up higher:’ ‘Love is a Spirit of Desire,’ Collalto cried, ‘it kills or saves: Lords are we of it or else slaves.’ To whom, Molino: ‘'Tis a dream Wherein we catch a transient gleam Of some life past or yet to come: It is the flower of things, the sum And head’—whereat laughed loud again Swart Aretino, ‘Be it pain, Or peace, or joy—here is my strain:—’ Love is a burning flame: It feeds on shame: Lust is its other name,— Love is a bitter flame. Love dwells in no one heart: It hath a poison'd dart, And leaves a bitter smart In the bruised heart. Love is a bitter thing, An empty jest to fling, A lewd song to sing, Love is a bitter thing— A bitter thing, a flame, It feeds on shame: Lust is its other name— Love is a burning flame. III. At Murano. From garden-ways that to the sea Sloped down 'neath many a cypress tree A sound of laughter came,—for there, Rejoicing in the sweet spring air, A joyous company was met: But two by a white parapet Together stood, Gaspara one, The other, he who late had won A happy meed of generous praise For the sweet beauty of his lays To subtle thought and music grown; Together there they stood alone, Tall slim Molino in the flower Of his full fame, she in the power Of her acknowledged loveliness. The cool wind touched with light caress The soft gold of her lovely hair, And lovelier than the flower most rare Transplanted from the east that grew Within these gardens was her face. A certain sadness left its trace Within the dreamful eyes, for he, He whom she loved so steadfastly, Far hence ‘made glad the land of France:’ The meaning of the opening lines of Gaspara's ninth Sonnet. To him life was a wide romance, To her 'twas one sole episode: He had fair paths—she one straight road. She knew not why her friend thus chose To turn awhile aside from those Who loved and honoured both: but glad She was to ask if aught of news Of the good lord Collalto had Of late been heard—with some excuse Of careless interest as though His very name sent not a glow Throughout her face: but with no smile Molino turned his face awhile And spake not—all his heart being thrill'd With sorrow and his dark eyes filled With tears that he who loved her so Should be her messenger of woe. Well knew Molino whom she loved, Well knew he that she looked unmoved On him, although with kindly eyes And sweet familiar courtesies She met him ever—well he knew The lord Collalto her heart drew Unto his life, as the moon draws The waves of ocean without pause— And bitterly he cursed this lord That idly tossed aside his word And for an untrue woman's sake Forsook one true, one fit to make A man's life fair and strong and sweet. None joined them there with wandering feet, But long a strange vague silence lay Betwixt them, as 'tween windy day And night a silence oft doth dwell. At last Gaspara cried—‘O tell Me quick this thing you have to say: He is not dead whom I so well Have loved and love!’ ‘He lives, but he, O dear, sweet friend, hath turn'd from thee: Be strong! I would to God that vain My words were, that this dreadful pain Might then not seize thy tender heart. Gaspara—friend—no words my tongue Would e'er have utter'd to thy hurt, Had I not feared some coarse jest flung Or that some heedless fool might blurt The truth out unawares: dear friend, Forgive me when I say an end Hath come upon thy high pure love— For he hath thrown it as a glove Aside—he is not worthy thee, Who long hath loved him faithfully!’ ‘Molino, I adjure thee by the trust I have in thee, all kindness thrust From out thy speech and let me have The bitter truth that nought can save!’ ‘A famous courtezan has made His weak heart captive: he has laid Honour aside, and knows no more The love he vowed thee o'er and o'er. In rumour you have heard her name— Diane de Poitiers—heed her shame And his no more, Gaspara! Dead He is to thee whose heart has bled In bitter ruth to hear.’ ‘Alas! I know it to be true: Love has For women ever a fierce thorn Behind each flow'r; a bitter scorn In Hope disguised: O true good friend I pray thee take me hence. The end Is come. The dream is dreamed. It is An old, old song. O life's poor bliss!’ (Aretino crosses the path, singing:) Love dwells in no one heart: It hath a poisoned dart, And leaves a bitter smart In the bruised heart. Love is a bitter thing, An empty jest to fling, A lewd song to sing, Love is a bitter thing. IV. The Last Journey. Nigh where the barren sandy shore Of Malamocco met the roar And surge of the tempestuous sea, Gaspara lay. Her misery Oft led her thither, where no eyes Would watch her grief, and where her sighs Unnoticed fell. For miles the strand Stretch'd bleak and bare—a waste of sand Where only the sea-popples grew, And where the wailing sea-birds flew Like ghosts of the unburied dead Lying fathoms deep: for leagues outspread The foam-swept Adriatic lay, Until it met the sky-line grey And sky and sea grew one dull waste Wherethro' the riotous tempest raced. All day she lay there like a flower Rent from its place by the wind's power And broken: nor as time waned fast And the fierce tempest wheeled and passed, Saw she the peaceful afternoon Bring transient rest ere once again The changing wind and driving rain Swept the sea-spray o'er each lagoon. At last even of this second pain Of silence she grew tired, and so She rose and wandered to and fro Where the cold grey insistent waves Swung heavily upon the shore: And murmuring to herself she said, ‘O happy they that in their graves Lie still and quiet, who feel no more Life's bitterness: O happy dead! Would God I in my narrow bed Slept the long sleep, and heard no sound At all, and no remembrance found, No tears, no sighs, no ghostly past, No kiss that turns to dust at last, No bitter mockery of love, Nor foiled Hope leaving all aghast The shivering soul: to hear above No sound, not even the sweet birds, For it might chance some stinging words, Some lover's vow, might reach me there And I should know the dreadful air Of life once more, and feel again Slain Love's intolerable pain.’ And then she knew that she would see No morrow: and the mystery Of coming death brought such release From grief, and such a sense of peace, It seemed to her as if even then She died, as if the world of men Were a past dream, and she were free: So then she made this song, Song on page 105 is almost literally the beautiful rendering by ‘George Fleming’ of Sonnet VI. Here the two closing lines have no prototypes in that sonnet, but such are to be found elsewhere amongst Gaspara's sonnets or madrigals. that he Might one day read and know how well She loved— ‘To suffer grief is to be strong, And to be strong is beautiful and rare:’ 'Twas in thy court, O Love, I learned it there, This sad, sweet song! No one man dwells thy ways among, Who shall not learn thy thousand ways of grief Or how wild fears succeed each poor relief In dark'ning throng: There too a man may learn to put away The crownèd summit of his heart's desire— But O, the bitter burning of love's fire— Its bitterer ashes grey! Swift in the waning afternoon Her gondoliers o'er the lagoon Urged the frail bark until they passed The Way of the Slaves and glided fast Before the wave-washed stairs that led Where ‘Santa Maria’ rose on high In domed majestic symmetry. Westward, beyond the broad canal, The blue-black sky was like a pall Drawn straight and smooth, with one broad span Of ominous orange-gold that ran Mid-way: and, nearer, fiery drifts Of crimson cloud with fringe-like rifts, Ev'n as serrated seaweed swings In the strong flow of a swift tide, Swayed to and fro, while overhead Dull bronze and lurid purple spread And intermingled. One white flash Fill'd the whole sky with fire, and crash Followed tempestuous crash, and blaze Streamed after blaze, till fire and sound And Venice all were interwound. And as the gondola flew fast Up narrow ways it darted past Swart Aretino's palace where He sat at meat with friends and quaffed His wine, and mocked, and loudly laughed To see the dread upon each face: Then hummed unto himself a space, And sang:— Love is an ended song; A cruel wrong; Love lasts not long: 'Tis an old-time song. Love is a bitter thing, An empty jest to fling, A lewd song to sing: Love is a bitter thing. MATER DOLOROSA. She, brooding ever, dwells amidst the hills; Her kingdom is call'd Solitude; her name— More terrible than desolating flame— Is Silence; and her soul is Pain. Day after day some weightier sorrow fills Her heart, and each new hour she knows The birth of further woes. And whoso, journeying, goes Unto the land wherein she dwells for aye Shall not come thence until have passed away For evermore the bright joy of his years. She giveth rest, but giveth it with tears, Tears that more bitter be Than drops of the Dead Sea: But never gives she peace to any soul, For how could she that rarest gift bestow Who well doth know That though in dreams she can attain the goal, In dreams alone her steps can thither go:— Solitude, Silence, Pain, for all who live Within the twilit realms that are her own, And even Rest to those who seek her throne, But these her gifts alone: Peace hath she not and therefore cannot give. SONNETS FOR TWO PICTURES BY ROSSETTI. I. MNEMOSYNE. She looks, in vision, upon some dead thing With steadfast eyes, subtly interpretive Of somewhat wonderful that once did live Beneath soft alien skies in some old Spring— She hears the laughter that shall no more ring, She hears the words no lips shall ever give Again in twilight moments fugitive, She knows the pain that long since lost its sting. Her right hand holds the lamp of memory Low burning, and behind her dies the day As dies for her the present. Hush! she hears Some antique time-forgotten mystery, Known only where the swart priests used to pray In shrines that were grown old in ancient years. II. LA PIA. La Pia (de' Tolommei) is she who is mentioned in the 5th Canto of ‘II Purgatorio’ as the bride of Nello della Pietra, and who was so cruelly imprisoned by the latter in a lonely fortress in the Maremma, where malaria erelong finished what grief had begun. ‘Ricorditi di me che son la Pia; Siena me fe' disfecemi Maremma; Scalsi colui che inanellata pria Disposando m'avea colla sua gemma.’ Dante. She sits behind the rampart, with sad eyes Watching the grey mists on the desolate plain Hover above the pools of stagnant rain— A dreary landscape underneath drear skies: Along the mouldy battlements there lies His crimson banner, and close by are lain Fierce Nello's lances—cursèd be his pain Who caused her all these tears and weary sighs. The stifling day is dead—dead as the fire That in her heart flamed once with glad desire For him who wedded her one fatal day— Death dwells in the Maremma, whose foul air Insidious moves about her everywhere, Misty and cold and damp and drear and grey. SONNETS ON THREE PAINTINGS BY BAZZI. (Sodona.) I have elsewhere (Art Journal, April, 1884) pointed out the advisability of either invariably calling this great artist by his right name, or else using what was probably the name he assumed when (like Titian) he was made a Count Palatine—viz., Sodona. Vasari's nickname should now be forgotten, if on no other account than on the principle of De mortuis, etc. I. THE ‘ST. SEBASTIAN’ OF THE UFFIZII. Still young, still wonderful, august, and fair— These long eventful ages that have fled With changeful years where Arno's flood has sped Through Tuscan dust until its sea-rest where The Pisan waves wash in, have brought no air Of dim decay about thy lovely head; Death has not come although thy wounds have bled So long; nor yet about thy body bare Has Time enwrapt his dull and dubious hue: With neck thrown back, and face, that fairer is Than ever man's was, lifted to the blue Of heaven for all the summer winds to kiss And soothe thy deathly pain—what is the clue Thine eyes have found, dreamful with mysteries? II. ‘CHRIST BEFORE THE SCOURGING.’(Siena.) No lurid sky is here, thunder and rain Come from no heaven in wrath, no fierce men shake Their spears before the sad strain'd eyes, or make Their laughter shrilly mock his bygone reign: Only the figure of a man in pain— Dire thirst of spirit that no hand will slake— A man who doth not fear, who doth not quake Although he knows how agony can gain The soul from its allegiance—for, far off, He sees beyond the cross, the grave, and death A multitude of ever nobler years— What then to him the cruel jeer and scoff, What then to him although a few hours' breath Be spent in agony too great for tears? III. ON THE NINETEENTH FRESCO OF THE ST. BENEDICT SERIES ON THE CLOISTER-WALLS OF THE MONASTERY OF MONTE OLIVETO MAGGIORE. (Umbria.) (Come Florenzo manda male femmine al Monastero.) Wouldst thou indeed, St. Benedict, have stood Thus undismayed while this fair wanton band Came from the outer world, that joyous land Long since condemned by thee; could thy calm mood Have thus outlasted; would not strange thoughts brood Within that eager brain until thy hand Withstayed awhile the banishing command And beckon'd rather for glad wine and food? But if, Florenzo, curses dwelt with thee Because of tempted saints, at least we feel, As Bazzi did, a joyous rapture steal Our sense away,—for like a dream is she Who, clothed in undulating azure folds, Still breathes the charm which over men she holds. DURING MUSIC. O tears that well up to my eyes, And vague thoughts wandering thro' my brain, Whence come ye? From what alien skies, From what dim sorrow, what strange pain? I hear old memories astir In dusky twilights of the past: O voices telling me of her, My soul, whom now I know at last: I know her not by any name, But she with hope or fear is pale; I see her ere this body came From mortal womb with mortal wail. Later and later through long years, Through generations of dead men, I see her in her mist of tears, I see her in her shroud of pain. I see her whom the æons have raised From one dim birth to endless life; I see her strive, regain, re-fail Forever in the endless strife. I see her, soul of man, and soul Of woman, and in many lands: Her eyes are fixt on some far goal But she hath neither thrall nor bands. On one day yet to come I see This body pale and cold and dead: The spirit once again made free Hovers triumphant overhead. Again, again, O endless day, I see her in new forms pace on, And ever with her on the way Fair kindred souls in unison. O wandering thoughts within my brain, O voices speaking low to me, O music sweet with stingless pain, Bring clear the vision that I see! O ecstasy of sound, O pain! Too sad my heart, too sad the tears It bringeth to my eyes again, Too strange the hopes, too strange the fears. OUTLINES. I. TWO MAJESTIES. (A picture by Gérôme.) Upon a vast grey barren block Of granite towering o'er the waste Of level sands a lion hath paced, And now lies crouching: from the rock He stares o'er leagues of deserts where No object gleams through the clear air— While far away the cloudless sun In golden blaze his rest hath won. II. MELANCHOLIA. (Albrecht Dürer.) She sits, with symbols of the pride That Reason hath, about her strewn: Her lips move with no secret rune, But on her forehead doth abide Weariness of all things that be, And from her eyes dreams Mystery. Life she hath drunken to the dregs, and lo She knows scarce more than children know. III. VERONICA VERONESE. (Dante Gabriel Rossetti.) She strikes the mystic chord, and on Her face the low soft echo seems To dwell: and in her eyes are dreams That Love not yet hath stirr'd but shone On only from afar, until The hour come of his conquering will. Fair spirit of woman and sweet sound— Each seems with other interwound. THE WATER-JOY. The Frog-bit, or Lesser Water-lily. The Water-Joy (from the generic name of the flower, which is from the Greek words ‘water’ and ‘to rejoice’) is the Lesser Water Lily, or, as it is commonly called, ‘Frog-Bit.’ The latter name is in reference to the haunts of this plant: in Germany also it is called Der Froschbiss. Its thick masses of white stars render pools and streams doubly beautiful, and none more so than the lovely Lesse, which flows into the Meuse at Anseremme, near Dinant. (On the Lesse—Southern Belgium.) Here at the river-bend, where stoop The trailing willows on one side, We drift by banks where, stretching wide, A low rich meadow bears a troop Of wilding flowers, moon-daisies white, Tall meadow-sweet with blossoms light, King-cups and purple scabious, The snow-white chickweed, slim hare-bell, The tiny scarlet pimpernel, And trailing white convolvulus. Fair as the fairest, on the stream The Lesser water-lilies gleam In starry masses far and near, The joy of running waters clear. THE CRESCENT MOON. As though the Power that made the nautilus A living glory o'er seas perilous Scatheless to roam, had from the utmost deep Called a vast flawless pearl from out its sleep And carv'd it crescent wise, exceeding fair,— So seems the crescent moon that thro' the air With motionless motion glides from out the west, And sailing onward ever seems at rest. MORNING. She, see, the sunlight breaking Over the mountain walls, In golden shafts and streamers Adown their slopes it falls; The curled white clouds are flushing, The dim grey tarns are blushing, And o'er the upland places The joyous cuckoo calls! It steals adown the valleys, It takes the pine tops there, And all the aery birches Wave now like golden hair; O'er torrents wildly splashing A myriad lights go flashing And make a dazzling shimmer Within the spray-swept air. With fiery crimson glowing Shine all the mountain walls; Hark, the sweet noise like laughter Of a myriad waterfalls! The curled white clouds are flushing, The dim grey tarns are blushing And o'er the upland places The joyous cuckoo calls! OUTLINES. I. SAPPHO. The high Leucadian steep aglow With sunlight on its tinted side; Dark blue, sky-bounded far and wide The Attic ocean dreams below; And on the highest craggy height A woman stands in waving white: 'Tis she whose heart's name was Desire, Who in the deep waves quenched its fire. II. LAIS. Within a marble balcony She sits whom all of Greece called fair, Lais of the won drous golden hair: Beyond her is the dimpled sea, Beside her the wild fig-leaves twine In shadow with the trailing vine:— So fair without; within lie deep The tigress-lusts that never sleep. III. HYPATIA. She stands within the lecture-room,— A glory on her perfect face: Perhaps some echo fills the place, Some echo of the coming doom When she, defiant still, will stand With brave eyes scorning the foul band: What care hath she of death—it means The ruptured veil that true life screens. AUSTRALIAN SKETCHES. NOTE. ‘Australia has rightly been named the Land of the Dawning. Wrapped in the mist of early morning, her history looms vague and gigantic. The lonely horseman riding between the moonlight and the day sees vast shadows creeping across the shelterless and silent plains, hears strange noises in the primeval forest, where flourishes a vegetation long dead in other lands. ? In Australia alone is to be found the Grotesque, the Weird, the strange scribblings of Nature learning how to write.’—Marcus Clarke. THE LAST ABORIGINAL. I see him sit, wild-eyed, alone, Amidst gaunt, spectral, moonlit gums— He waits for death: not once a moan From out his rigid fixt lips comes; His lank hair falls adown a face Haggard as any wave-worn stone, And in his eyes I dimly trace The memory of a vanished race. The lofty ancient gum-trees stand, Each grey and ghostly in the moon, The giants of an old strange land That was exultant in its noon When all our Europe was o'erturned With deluge and with shifting sand, With earthquakes that the hills inurned And central fires that fused and burned. The moon moves slowly through the vast And solemn skies; the night is still, Save when a warrigal springs past With dismal howl, or when the shrill Scream of a parrot rings which feels A twining serpent's fangs fixt fast, Or when a grey opossum squeals, Or long iguana, as it steals From bole to bole disturbs the leaves: But hush'd and still he sits—who knows That all is o'er for him who weaves With inner speech, malign, morose, A curse upon the whites who came And gather'd up his race like sheaves Of thin wheat, fit but for the flame— Who shot or spurned them without shame. He knows he shall not see again The creeks whereby the lyre-birds sing— He shall no more upon the plain, Sun-scorch'd, and void of water-spring, Watch the dark cassowaries sweep In startled flight, or, with spear lain In ready poise, glide, twist, and creep Where the brown kangaroo doth leap. No more in silent dawns he'll wait By still lagoons, and mark the flight Of black swans near: no more elate Whirl high the boomerang aright Upon some foe: he knows that now He too must share his race's night— He scarce can know the white man's plough Will one day pass above his brow. Last remnant of the Austral race He sits and stares, with failing breath: The shadow deepens on his face, For 'midst the spectral gums waits death: A dingo's sudden howl swells near— He stares once with a startled gaze, As half in wonder, half in fear, Then sinks back on his unknown bier. IN THE RANGES. Through a dark cleft between two hills A narrow passage leads the way Close by a lonely lake; two rills, Its children, sing the livelong day, And from the water's lapping edge The low tones of the long reeds come— No other sound, save in the sedge A black swan crooning; all the heights are dumb. This cleft leads to an open space Where arching tree-ferns grow around, A still and solitary place: Long waving grass grows from the ground, And great green lizards half-awake Lie silent hours, and in the light The fiery glances of a stealthy snake Keep glinting, glinting, like twin stars at night. Beyond, a wooded gully lies— A greenstone on the topaz plain; In its deep shade no glaring skies E'er shine, so thick are overlain The branches of the ancient trees; Within its depths the lyre-bird hides, And, save at mid-noon, never cease The bell-birds singing where the streamlet glides. Far off on higher uplands grow The spicy gum and hardy box, The delicate acacias throw Their feather-leafings o'er the rocks, And grey-green misletoe doth creep Till tree by tree is overlaid— While in the noonday stillness sleep The bright rosellas 'mid the wild-vine's shade. Gippsland, Jan., 1878. NOON-SILENCE. (Australian Forest.) A lyre-bird sings a low melodious song— Then all is still: a soft wind breathes along The lofty gums and faintly dies away: And Silence wakes and knows her dream is day. THE STOCK-DRIVER'S RIDE. O'er the range, and down the gully, across the river bed We are riding on the tracks of the cattle that have fled: The mopokes all are laughing and the cockatoos are screaming, And bright amidst the stringy-barks the parrakeets are gleaming: The wattle-blooms are fragrant, and the great magnolias fair Make a heavy sleepy sweetness in the hazy morning air, But the rattle and the crashing of our horses' hoofs ring out And the cheery sound we answer with our long repeated shout— Coo-ee-coo-ee-eee! Coo-ee-coo-eee—Coo-ee—Coo-ee! ‘Damnation Dick’ he hears us, and he shrills back Whoo-ee-ee! ‘Damnation Dick’ the prince of native trackers thus we call From the way he swigs his liquor and the oaths that he can squall! Thro' more ranges, thro' more gullies, down sunscorched granite ways We go crashing, slipping, thundering in our joyous morning race— And the drowsy 'possums shriek and o'er each dried-up creek The wallaroos run scuttling as if playing hide-and-seek: And like iron striking iron do our horses' hoofs loud ring As down the barren granite slopes we leap and slide and spring; Then one range further only and we each a moment rein Our steaming steeds as wide before us stretches out the grassy plain! And ‘Damnation Dick’ comes running like a human kangaroo And he cries the herd have bolted to the creek of Waharoo! So we swing across the desert and for miles and miles we go Till men and horses pant athirst i' the fierce sun's fiery glow. And at last across the plains where the kangaroos fly leaping And the startled emus in their flight go circularly sweeping, We see the trees that hide the spring of Waharoo and there The cattle all are standing still—the bulls with a fierce stare! Then off to right goes Harry on his sorrel ‘Pretty Jane,’ And to the left on ‘Thunderbolt’ Tom scours across the plain, And Jim and I well-mounted and on foot ‘Damnation Dick’ Go straight for Waharoo and our stockwhips fling and flick! Ho there goes old ‘Blackbeetle,’ the patriarch of the herd! His doughty courage vanish'd when Tom's long leash cracked and whirred, And after him the whole lot flee and homeward headlong dash— What bellowing flight and thunder of hoofs as thro' the scrub we crash! Back through the gum-tree gullies, and over the river-bed, And past the sassafras ranges whereover at dawn we sped, With thunderous noise and shouting the drivers and driven flee— And this was the race that was raced by Tom, Jim, Harry, and me! THE DEATH OF THE LUBRA. The native name for ‘wife.’ Stung by an adder unto death To this rough hut she comes to die: All day the fierce noon's fiery breath Hath filled the blazing sky— The long, strange, soundless Austral day Where through primeval forests come No cry or song, and far away The bell-birds ev'n are dumb— At sundown, tumult sweeps the skies From where a thousand parrots shrill; The laughing-birds' terrific cries The rapid twilight fill. And when the great moon rising gleams Athwart the rotting hut where low The lubra bends, one cry she screams As though some unseen blow Had stricken her with sudden might:— Without, flits past the wailing owl, And through the gloom of darkening night Swells high the wild-dog's howl. AUSTRALIAN TRANSCRIPTS. I. AN ORANGE GROVE. (Victoria.) The short sweet purple twilight dreams Of vanish'd day, of coming night; And like gold moons in the soft light Each scented drooping orange gleams From out the glossy leaves black-green That make through noon a cool dark screen. The dusk is silence, save the thrill That stirs it from cicalas shrill. II. BLACK SWANS ON THE MURRAY LAGOONS. The long lagoons lie white and still Beneath the great round Austral moon: The sudden dawn will waken soon With many a delicious thrill: Between this death and life the cries Of black swans ring through silent skies— And the long wash of the slow stream Moves as in sleep some bodeful dream. III. BREAKING BILLOWS AT SORRENTO. (Victoria.) A sky of whirling flakes of foam, A rushing world of dazzling blue: One moment, the sky looms in view— The next, a crash in its curv'd dome, A tumult indescribable, And eyes dazed with the miracle. Here breaks by circling day and night In thunder the sea's boundless might. IV. SHEA-OAK TREES ON A STORMY DAY. (S.E. Victoria.) The Shea-Oak (Casuarina) has long drooping filaments instead of leaves. The sound these give forth on a stormy day is extremely mournful, heightened by the dreariness of the surrounding tracts. O'er sandy tracts the shea-oak trees Droop their long wavy grey-green trails: And inland wandering moans and wails The long blast of the ocean-breeze: Like loose strings of a viol or harp These answering sound—now low, now sharp And keen, a melancholy strain: A death-song o'er the mournful plain. V. MID-NOON IN JANUARY. The giant lizard (here referred to), the ‘Monitor,’ or Hydrasaurus varius, varies from four to six feet in length. Although it can bite severely, it is not harmful to man. When there is not a sound from any living thing to be heard in the forest, when even the bell-birds are silenced, and the scorpions and centipedes are torpid in the furnace-heat, the monitor basks upon some spreading bough, motionless for hours, but ready in a moment for any restless beetle or other insect that may come his way. The first time I saw one (116° in the shade) it literally seemed to radiate heat, but it was probably impervious to the fiery breath of noon to which it lay fully exposed. Upon a fibry fern-tree bough A huge iguana lies alow, Bright yellow in the noonday glow With bars of black,—it watcheth now A gorgeous insect hover high Till suddenly its lance doth fly And catch the prey—but still no sound Breathes 'mid the green fern-spaces round. VI. IN THE FERN. (Gippsland.) The feathery fern-trees make a screen Wherethrough the sun-glare cannot pass— Fern, gum, and lofty sassafras: The fronds sweep over, palely green, And underneath are orchids curl'd Adream through this cool shadow-world; A fragrant greenness—like the noon Of lime-trees in an English June. VII. SUNSET AMID THE BUFFALO MOUNTAINS. (N.E. Victoria.) Only those who have witnessed the beautiful phenomenon referred to in the final couplet can have any true idea of its exquisite loveliness. This mysterious veil of translucent blue clothes the Austral hill-ranges only for a few wonderful moments during the brief twilight that is just long enough to form a recognisable interlude between day and night. Across the boulder'd majesty Of the great hills the passing day Drifts like a wind-borne cloud away Far off beyond the western sky: And while a purple glory spreads, With straits of gold and brilliant reds, An azure veil, translucent, strange, Dreamlike steals over each dim range. VIII. THE FLYING MOUSE. (New South Wales— Moonlight.) The ‘Flying Mouse’ here referred to is not a bat, but one of the Phalangistæ. The Phalangers of Australia are different from the opossums of America. The Flying Mouse is the smallest of the so-called flying opossums—and indeed is one of the smallest animals in creation — Wallace mentioning that ‘it could go to sleep in a good-sized pill-box.’ The eucalyptus-blooms are sweet With honey, and the birds all day Sip the clear juices forth: brown-grey, A bird-like thing with tiny feet Cleaves to the boughs, or with small wings Amidst the leafy spaces springs, And in the moonshine with shrill cries Flits batlike where the white gums rise. IX. THE WOOD-SWALLOWS. (Sunrise.) The wood-swallows of Australia have the singular habit of clustering like bees or bats on the boughs of a dead tree. The lightning-stricken giant gum Stands leafless, dead—a giant still But heedless of this sunrise-thrill: What stir is this where all was dumb?— What seem like old dead leaves break swift, And lo, a hundred wings uplift A cloud of birds that to and fro Dart joyous midst the sunrise-glow. X. THE BELL-BIRD. The stillness of the Austral noon Is broken by no single sound— No lizards even on the ground Rustle amongst dry leaves—no tune The lyre-bird sings—yet hush! I hear A soft bell tolling, silvery clear! Low soft aerial chimes, unknown Save 'mid these silences alone. XI. THE ROCK-LILY. (New South Wales.) The Rock-lily (Doryanthes excelsa) has a flower-stalk thirty feet high, crowned with lily-like blooms of a rich darkred hue, and several feet in circumference. The amber-tinted level sands Unbroken stretch for leagues away Beyond these granite slabs, dull grey And lifeless, herbless—save where stands The mighty rock-flow'r towering high, With carmine blooms crowned gloriously: A giant amongst flowers it reigns, The glory of these Austral plains. XII. THE FLAME-TREE. (New South Wales.) The Brachychiton acerifolium, or ‘flame-tree’ of the colonists, when covered with its large crimson blooms, is a most beautiful sight, especially when seen en masse. In the right season, the Illawarra mountain range (on the eastern side of New South Wales) is said to be conspicuous for miles at sea by reason of the glowing crimson of these flame-trees in full flower. For miles the Illawarra range Runs level with Pacific seas: What glory when the morning breeze Upon its slopes doth shift and change Deep pink and crimson hues, till all The leagues-long distance seems a wall Of swift uncurling flames of fire That wander not nor reach up higher. MORNING IN THE BUSH. (December). The magpie midst the wattle-blooms Is singing loud and long: What fragrance in the scatter'd scent, What magic in the song! On yonder gum a mopoke's throat Out-gurgles laughter grim, And far within the fern-tree scrub A lyre-bird sings his hymn. Amongst the stringy-barks a crowd Of dazzling parrakeets— But high o'er all the magpie loud His joyous song repeats. JUSTICE. (Uncivilized and Civilized.) Ling-Tso Ah Sin, on Murderer's Flat One morning caught an old grey rat: ‘Ah, white man, I have got you now! But no—dust be upon my brow If needless blood I cause to fall— So go, there's world-room for us all!’ That night Ah Sin was somehow shot— By accident! For he had got From earth a little gold—black sin For thee, though not for us, Ah Sin! Murderer's Flat, Feb., 1878. THE COROBBOREE. (Midnight.) Deep in the forest-depths the tribe A mighty blazing fire have made: Round this they spring with frantic yells In hideous pigments all arrayed— One barred with yellow ochre, one A skeleton in startling white, There one who dances furiously Blood-red against the great fire's light,— With death's insignia on his breast, In rude design, the swart chief springs; And loud and long each echoes back The savage war-cry that he sings. Within the forest dark and dim The startled cockatoos like ghosts Flit to and fro, the mopokes scream, And parrots rise in chattering hosts; The gins and lubras crouch and watch With eager shining brute-like eyes, And ever and again shrill back Wild echoes of the frantic cries:— Like some infernal scene it is— The forest dark, the blazing fire, The ghostly birds, the dancing fiends, Whose savage chant swells ever higher. Afar away gaunt wild-dogs howl, And strange cries vaguely call: but white The placid moon sails on, and flame The silent stars above the night. MOONRISE SKETCHES. I. MOONRISE AT SEA. The long slow swell of the still sea Rises and falls, and sluggishly The wind-bound ship rolls to and fro, Soundless, save when the huge sails go With a heavy boom from left to right: A few stars only trail their light In quivering snaky gleams below In the sea's depths, as though from caves Within whose twilight glooms no waves Move ever serpents writhe and rise: But westward far where sea and skies Blend in one darkness breaks a beam Of wan faint light—and now a gleam Curv'd like a golden scimetar And bright as though welded from a star Hangs for a moment, grows and grows More round and large, a golden rose Of one immaculate petal made: And now the moon is risen, has laid The music of her magic smile Upon the dim dark seas till mile On mile, league upon league, are bright With a broad track of silver light, And all the ship's sails seem to be Of moonbeam-gossamer woven free. II. MOONRISE IN AUSTRALIA. A trackless forest all around Of lofty gums that from the ground As saplings sprang in ages past:— The short sweet twilight fadeth fast And from the forest depths I hear The locust's whirling noise, the clear Soft magpie song, the sudden scream Where cockatoos like white ghosts gleam Among the melancholy boughs, The wild-dog's bark from where there browse Stray herds of kangaroos, the cry Of something death-struck—as I lie And listen to these sounds I see Long moonbeams pierce a lofty tree Like random lances thrust to kill Some fiend who baffles all their skill; And even as with sleepy eyes I watch, the full moon through the skies Sails with a seeming moveless motion, A globe of fire in a purple ocean. III. MOONRISE FROM IONA, N.B. Here, where in dim forgotten days A savage people chanted lays To long since perished gods, I stand: The sea breaks in, runs up the sand, Retreats as with a long-drawn sigh, Sweeps in again; again leaves dry The ancient beach, so old and yet So new that as the strong tides fret The island barriers in their flow The ebb-hours of each day can know A surface change. The day is dead, The sun is set, and overhead The white north stars shine keen and bright; The wind upon the sea is light And just enough to stir the deep With phosphorescent gleams and sweep The spray from salt waves as they rise: And yonder light—is't from the skies, Some meteor strange, a burning star— Or a lamp hung upon a spar Of vessel undescried? It gleams And rises slowly, till it seems A burning isle, an angel-throne Reset on earth, a mountain-cone Of gold new-risen from sea-caves— Until at last above the waves, Salt with Atlantic brine, it swims A silver crescent, Now no hymns In the wild Runic speech are heard, No chant, no sacrificial word: But only moans the weary sea, And only the cold wind sings free, And where the Runic temples stood The bat flies and the owl doth brood. IV. MOONRISE ON THE VENETIAN LAGOONS. A more than twilight darkness dwells Upon the long lagoons: the bells Of distant Venice come and go Like sounds in dreams; the tide's soft flow Sweeps onward, and a wandering gull Flits o'er the track of yon black hull Just fading in the gloom—no more I see or hear 'tween shore and shore: But as I lie and dreamily Watch the dark water from the sea Slip past the boat, in its blurred sky I see the crescent moon on high Casting curv'd golden flakes far down Amidst the calm lagoon—a crown Broken innumerably up, The gold bands of a broken cup. I take an oar and make a rift In the soft tide of the lagoons,— And lo, the blade itself doth lift A score of quivering crescent moons, And as they flash I seem to see Each droplet with a small moon flee. V. MOONRISE ON THE ANTARCTIC. The huge white icebergs silently Voyage with us through this lonely sea, Noiseless and lifeless, yet they seem Like haunted islands in a dream Holding strange secrets that no one May know and live. In the bright sun They shine immeasurably fair, Bluer than bluest summer air, Or clear to the very heart with green Pure light, or amethyst as seen 'Mid sunset-clouds—but now they shine With a cold gleam and have no sign Of loveliness. The ship swings on, Plunging mid surging seas whereon Few vessels ever sail, and as Slowly the long hours come and pass The late moon rises cold and white, And sends a flood of wintry light Along the sweeping waves and round Our black and sea-worn hull. A sound Far off dies while it grows—some seal Long-drifted, frozen, waking but to feel Death's grip. And now the spectral isles Grow whiter, icier still, and seem More hollow, with a strange weird gleam As though some pale unreal fires Consumed them to their utmost spires Yet without flame or heat. And still The moon doth rise, and seems to fill Each berg anew with life: we sail Upon a strange sad sea, where pale And moonshine isles float all around, Voyaging onward without sound. THE SHADOWED SOULS. If the soul withdraweth from the body, what profit thereafter hath a man of all the days of his life? She died indeed, but to him her breath Was more than a light blown out by death: He knew that they breathed the self-same air, That not midst the dead was her pale face fair But that she waited for him somewhere. To some dead city, or ancient town, Where the mould'ring towers were crumbling down, Or in some old mansion habited By dust and silence and things long dead, He knew the Shadows of Souls were led. For years he wandered a weary way, His eyes shone sadder, his hair grew grey: But still he knew that she lived for whom No grave lay waiting, no white carv'd tomb, No earthy silence, no voiceless gloom. But once in a bitter year he came To an old dying town with a long dead name: That eve, as he walked thro' the dusty ways And the echoes woke in the empty place, He came on a Shadow face to face. It looked, but uttered no word at all Then beckoned him into an old dim hall: And lo, as soon as he passed between The pillars with age and damp mould green His eyes were dazed by a strange wild scene. A thousand lamps fill'd the place with light, And fountains glimmered faerily bright; But never a single sound was heard, The dreadful silence was never stirred, Not even the breath of a single word Came from the shadowy multitude, More dense than the leaves in a summer wood, Than the sands where the swift tides ebb and flow; But ever the Shades moved to and fro As windless waves on the sea will go. Then he who had come to Shadow-land Swift strode past many a group and band; But never a glimpse he caught of her, In fleeting shadow or loiterer, For whom the earth held no sepulchre. He knew that she was not dead whom he So loved with bitterest memory, To whom through anguish'd years he had prayed; Yet came she never, no sign was made, No touch on his haggard frame was laid. At last to an empty room he came, And there he saw in letters of flame— ‘This is that palace no king controls, A place unwritten in human scrolls— This is the Haunt of Shadowed Souls: ‘If thy Shadow-soul be here no more Seek thine old life's deserted shore: And there, mayhap, thou wilt find again, Recovered now through sorrow and pain, The Soul thou didst thy most to have slain.’ SLEEPY HOLLOW. In Sleepy Hollow Cemetery are the graves of Thoreau and Hawthorne (to whom respectively reference is made in the first three verses) and near them, about two years ago, were laid the remains of Emerson. (In Memoriam: Ralph Waldo Emerson.) He sleeps here the untroubled sleep Who could not bear the noise and moil Of public life, but far from toil A happy reticence did keep With Nature only open, free: Close by there rests the magic mind Of him who took life's thread to wind And weave some poor soul's mystery Of spirit-life, and make it live A type and wonder for all days; No sweeter soul e'er trod earth's ways Than he who here at last did give His body back to earth again. And now at length beside them lies One great and true and nobly wise,— A King of Thought, whose spotless reign The overwhelming years that come And drown the trash and dross and slime Shall keep a record of till Time Shall cease, and voice of man be dumb. At last he rests, whose high clear hope Was wont on lofty wings to scan The future destinies of man— Who saw the Race through darkness grope, Through mists and error, till at last The looked-for light, the longed-for age Should dawn for peasant, prince, and sage, And centuries of night be past. Thy rest is won: O loyal, brave, Wise soul, thy spirit is not dead— Thy wing'd words far and wide have fled, Undying, they shall find no grave. BIRCHINGTON REVISITED. (D. G. R.) He sleeps a quiet sleep at last Who wearied for such blissful hours: The stress of high-strung life is past, The veil of death is o'er him cast, And for him hence no dark sky lowers. Sweet is the air here, clear and sweet; The larks with jubilant voices sing, And still their songs re-sing, repeat; The grass, starr'd white with marguerite, Is yet memorious of Spring. Yonder the blue sea, windless, still, Meets the blue sky-line far away— Soundless, save when the wavelets spill Their little crowns of foam, and fill The rock-pools full with swirling spray. How sweet to rest here, and to know The silence and the utter peace! To lie and rest and sleep below While far away tired millions go With eyes all yearning for such ease. 'Tis better thus: alone, yet safe From night and day, from day and night; Not here can jarring discords chafe Thy soul too sensitive, or waif Of stinging envy blown from spite. 'Tis quiet here, and more than all Things else is rest a boon to thee— Rest, peace, and sleep: above, the pall Of heaven; and past the white cliff-wall The ceaseless mystery of the sea. JUNE'S ADVENT. June, wandering hence, smiles through the summer heat In answer to the beckoning hand of May, Who, lily-crown'd, flits deck'd in green array Through field and wood, and with her presence sweet Fills all the birds with joy, and 'neath her feet Leaves fragrant flowers about each hedge-girt way: Laughing she chides sweet June for his delay— Her rose-crown'd lover, whom she longs to meet. Behold he comes, with splendour on his brow, All summer in his dark-blue dreamful eyes, And lips that move with murmurs of sweet song— And lo, each recognising forest-bough Waves joyous welcome, and with eager cries Him thrushes greet with music loud and long. PHANTASY. Biding o'er a lonely plain I came unto a wood— And there I met, in dreamful mood, A damsel singing a low strain, All ye who love me love in vain! Her song it seemëd far away, But oh her kiss was sweet: She led me to some green retreat, And there within her arms I lay The livelong day. All ye who love me love in vain— I kissed her wistful face But found a leaf-strewn space Alone, and far I heard her strain, All ye who love me love in vain. I seek the wood in twilit hours— At times I hear her sing: At times her white arms round me cling: She leads me into magic bow'rs And sings and wreathes me wilding flow'rs. Her eyes are tears, and pain Is in her kiss, but wildly gay She laughs, and fades away, And through the dim wood floats the strain, All ye who love me love in vain. QUINCE BLOSSOMS. (TO V. H. M. B.) How delicately sweet and rare These blossoms that the Roman air Hath nurtured exquisitely well: A mighty branch! how late it knew The fresh warm winds that round it blew Where high its parent tree did dwell. And now within your room they make A sweetness, as when lilies take The gloom from willow-darken'd streams: Here Spring lies captive, where no wind With furtive breath its blooms shall find Nor mock each transient blossom's dreams. Love, Poetry, and Art are flow'rs Sweet as the quince, and fill life's hours With joy and fragrance even as these: Thrice happy thou that these three hast, Sweet deathless flow'rs that aye will last Though quince-blooms wither on their trees. Rome, April, 1883. MAY-DAY. (Castello del' Quattro Torre—near Siena.) Above, the Four Towers feel the wind With half-closed pinions rest and play Around the bastions old and grey— But o'er the olive-slopes behind It sweeps like some aërial stream, Till every leaflet seems a gleam Of silver and the grasses sway In light and shade for miles away. Around, the flowering wild-beans make A fresh Spring fragrance in the air: The crimson clover everywhere Tempts the brown bees, and poppies shake Their dust amongst the corn and stand Like flames all over the green land— And in the sunlight's golden glare The snow-white lilies seem more fair. The swallows sweep in endless flight Above the orchard-slopes below, White with the scented blossom-snow: And hark! from yonder tree-clad height The sweet voice of the Spring rings clear— The herald Cuckoo, ever dear: And 'midst the warmth, the peace, the glow, The birthday of sweet May I know. IN THE VAL MUGNONE. (TO A. M. F. R. AND V. P.) Spring's laughter rings down thro' the valley; A thousand sweet blossoms are there; The world hath grown young and is happy And heedless of care. The river flows dashing and splashing Past banks where the primroses blow; The sunlight is streaming and flashing Where white olives grow. Joy beats through the heart of the valley: A thrush sings loudly and long: With the flow'rs and the birds we are happy, And life is a song. IN MAREMMA. The ardent azure sky above— Cloudless save little snowy isles That without motion seem to move So silently they sail through miles Of that calm blue of upper sea, White shoreless isles, unstable, free— Around, an ocean of green grass, Leagues upon leagues of rolling ground That stretch unbroken till they pass From sight in one long swelling mound That fades indefinitely away Into the sky-line's hazy grey. Far north a rugged mountain-chain Seems like a soft indefinite band Against the deeper blue; a plain Sweeps thence south-westward till the sand That drifts about the Latin shore Its sterile verdure covers o'er— A plain where marshy waters meet Drear pestilential tracts, where ring No human voices, though the sweet Song of the lark is trilled through Spring, And myriad scented flowers unfold And bloom above the treacherous mould. At times a lonely horseman rides Across the waste on shaggy steed; There too the hunted brigand hides; And often, with swift reckless speed, The fierce wild-cattle snort and fly, Tameless with savage liberty. A SUNSET. (From the Gates of Volterra.) Above the rugged Apennines In long thick wavy purple lines The storm-clouds rest: a space doth lie Betwixt them, and here glares an eye Socketless, blood-red, terrible. Slowly the fire-globe sinks,—but as Some miracle were come to pass, Some ominous enchantic spell,— Through the dark cloud-mass lying below A sword of lurid red doth crawl From whose serrated edges fall Great blood-like clots—as if some woe Impended where Volterra hung Where the last gleams of day were flung. ON THE CAMPAGNA. I Alark high in the heavens, A wilderness of grass— White cloudlets trailing slowly Blue shadows as they pass— Songs, flowers, and windy spaces Of skies divinely clear— If Heaven is anywhere 'Tis surely here! II The white moon leads the planets, Stars fill the skies— But where the flow'rs are sleeping Grey mists arise— The poison-mists are drifting, As o'er a shallow mere: If death lurks anywhere 'Tis surely here. FIREFLIES. (In the Cascine: Florence.) While the fireflies of Italy are invariably of flame colour, varying from red to pale crimson, and even to faint orange, those I have seen in more northern latitudes—as in the Ardennes and the Province of Luxembourg—have as invariably been green, as well as generally less resplendent. The farther south, the warmer the clime, the more brilliant are these ‘wandering fires.’ Under the olive-boughs and o'er The long lush grass the fireflies wheel In lonely flight, or rise and reel In a strange mazy dance before Yon ancient ilex that can keep A darkness where no moonbeams creep: Like souls they seem that have no rest, With death-lights seeking still life's quest. IN THE OLD PROTESTANT CEMETERY AT FLORENCE. (Easter, 1883.) The light wind scarcely breathes between The close-set cypress boughs, nor stirs To varying shades the ilex-green; A blackbird calls, a song-thrush whirrs Through leafy dusk till somewhere near Again its sweet wild song swells clear:— But otherwise no sound to break The hallowed peace that broods where lies The dust of her E. B. B., obiit 1861. for whose sweet sake Firenze and its ardent skies To all who love her sweet song-lore Are dear and sacred evermore. The river that she loved flows nigh, Slow washing to the Pisan sea— Behind, where solemn hills slope high The Vallombrosan torrents flee 'Mid crags and pines—and yonder way Morello and Fiesole. The Tuscan spring is warm and bright As when she loved to watch the sun Turn olive-leaves to slips of light, As fair the flowers where children run And laugh amidst their childish pranks Upon grey-green Mugnone's banks: But quiet the urgent heart, the brain That wrought with ceaseless love and care Sweet songs compact of joy and pain, Dreams from a soul that knew no air Of common earth—now where songs are The breath of souls she dwells afar. And as I think of her my heart Turns back to last year's Easter-tide, D. G. R., obiit Easter, 1882. Remembering with a sudden smart; I see again the cliffs beside The broad blue sea, in crescent bent Half round the windy breast of Kent— I see the little graveyard lie, The tombs encrusted with sea-salt; Above, I hear the larks sing high Within the cloud-flecked azure-vault— And surely that sound from the deep Must soothe those sleeping their long sleep. He too has rest, and knows no more Of joy or pain: and as the sea Is secret, so for evermore His voice is hushed. The mystery Of song! But no, afar he sings, Afar he knows diviner springs, Afar he feels the mystic change That veiled death wrought,—or here again His new-framed soul doth upward range Preparing for a nobler strain: The joy of Death! that leaves us here To live anew, or to some sphere Beyond the earth and mortal woes Wafts spirits to some stellar bliss! Ev'n as a flower from winter's throes Is born to feel Spring's breathless kiss, So is he filled with joy who here Wept oft to find life barren, drear. A RECORD. (A FRAGMENT.) I hear the dark tempestuous sea Boom through the night monotonously, The hoarse faint cries of breaking waves Lashed by the wind that moans and raves Upon the deep—I hear them fall Against cliff-bases smooth and tall, A music wild, funereal. I seem to listen to a sound That circles earth for ever round, The dirge of an eternal song, A dull deep music swept along The listening coasts of many lands, Sighed mournfully o'er level sands, Or thunder'd amidst rocky strands. I sit within my lonely room Where the lamp's flame just breaks the gloom, And thro' the darkness of the night I see far down a starry light Where nestled safely in the chine The village street in one long line Doth like a glittering serpent shine. The keen wind blows through the dark skies, The stars look down like countless eyes That see and know, and therefore stare Unmoved 'midst their serene high air: And life seems but a dream, a shade Which fleeing Time o'er space hath laid, But which with Time shall one day fade. Old memories are mine once more, I see strange lives I lived of yore; With dimm'd sight see I far off things, I feel the breath of bygone springs, And ringing strangely in mine ears I hear old laughter, alien tears Slow falling, voices of past years. Far back the soul can never see— But dreams restore mysteriously Dim visions of a possible past, A time ere the last bond was cast Aside that bound the struggling soul Unto the brute, and first some goal Loomed dimly over Life's vast shoal. And dreaming so I live my dream: I see a yellow turbid stream Heavily flowing thro' clustered weeds Of tropic growth, and 'midst the reeds Of tall green rice upon its bank A crouching tiger, long and lank, With slow tail swaying from flank to flank: Its eyes are yellow flames, and burn Upon a man who dips an urn Into the Ganges' sacred wave, Unknowing he has reached his grave— A short hoarse roar, a scream, a blow! And even as I shudder, lo My tiger-self I seem to know. And dreaming so I live my dream: I see a sunrise-glory gleam Against vast mountain-heights, and there Upon a peak, precipitous, bare, I see an eagle scan the plain Immeasurable of his domain, With fierce untameable disdain: When first the stars wax pale, his eyes Front the wide east where day doth rise, And with unflinching gaze look straight Against the sun, then proud, elate, On tireless wings he swoops on high O'er countless leagues, and thro' the sky Drifts like a dark cloud ominously: Then as day dies and swift night springs, I hear the sudden rush of wings And see the eagle from the plain Sweep to his eyrie once again With fierce keen dauntless eyes aglow— And even as I watch them, lo Mine eagle-self I seem to know. And dreaming so I live my dream: I hear a savage voice, a scream Scarcely articulate, and far I see a red light like a star Flash 'neath old trees, and the first fire Made by the brutish tribe burn higher Until unfed its flames expire: I see the savage whose hand drew The fire from wood, whose swift breath blew The flame until it gained new strength,— I see him stand supreme at length, And pointing to the burning flame Bend low his swart and trembling frame And cry aloud a guttural name: A god at last the tribe hath found, A god at whose strange crackling sound Each man must bend in dread until This strange new god hath worked his will: But lo, one day the fire spreads fast, And ere its fury is o'erpast The tribe within its furnace-blast Hath perish'd, save one man alone Who far in sudden fear hath flown: But with a gleam of new-born thought A second flame he soon hath wrought Only to tramp it down, aware At last that no dead god lies there, Or one for whom no man need care. He looks around to see some god, And far upon the fire-scorch'd sod He sees his brown burnt tribesmen lie, And thinks their voices fill the sky, And dreads some unseen sudden blow— And even as I watch him, lo My savage-self I seem to know. And dreaming so I live my dream: I see a flood of moonlight gleam Between vast ancient oaks, and round A rough-hewn altar on the ground Weird Druid priests are gatherëd While through their midst a man is led With face that seems already dead: A low chant swells throughout the wood, Then comes a solemn interlude Ere loudlier rings dim aisles along Some ancient sacrificial song; Before the fane the victim kneels, And without sound he forward reels When the priest's knife the death-blow deals: The moonlight falls upon his face, His blood is spatter'd o'er the place, But now he is ev'n as a flow'r Uprooted in some tempest hour, Dead, but whose seed shall elsewhere grow: And as I look upon him, lo Some old ancestral self I know. Thus far dreams bring mysteriously Visions of past lives back to me; Visions alone perhaps they are, Each one a wandering futile star Flash'd o'er the mental firmament,— Yet may be thus in past times went My soul in gradual ascent. None sees the slow sure upward sweep By which the soul from life-depths deep Ascends—unless, mayhap, when free With each new death we backward see The long perspective of our race, Our multitudinous past lives trace Since first as breath of God through space Each came, and filled the lowest thing With life's faint pulse scarce quivering; So ever onward upward grew, And ever with each death-birth knew An old sphere left, a mystic change— A sense of exultation strange Thus through a myriad lives to range. But even in our mortal lives At times the eager spirit strives To gain through subtle memories Some hint of life's past mysteries— Brief moments they, that flash before Bewilder'd eyes some scene of yore, Some vivid hour returned once more. Swift through the darken'd clouds of sense A sudden lightning-gleam intense Reveals some glimpse of the long past, Some memory comes back at last— And yet 'twas but a sudden strain Of song—a scent—a sound of rain— Some trifle—made all clear again. With a swift flash such glimpses come And go—but there are times for some When keen the vision is, so keen That thenceforth the indelible scene Remains within the mind for aye, Some reminiscence sad or gay, Some action of a bygone day. Thus came to me memorious gleams From the closed past, no sleep-brought dreams But revelations flashed out swift Upon the mind: a sudden lift Of the dense cloud of all past years,— A moment when the thrilling ears Heard, or the eyes slow filled with tears. Thus hath there flashed across my sight A desert in a blinding light Of scorching sun, a dreary waste Of burning sand where seldom paced The swift gaunt camels with their freight Of merchandise, but where the weight Of silence lay inviolate. There a few sterile rocks lay white In the sun's glare, a band by might Of old convulsion thither hurled In the far days of the young world: And in their midst a hollow cave Was cleft, where dwelt, as in a grave, One who came thence his soul to save. Young, and from out the joyous strife Of men he came to this drear life: No more for him the wine's swift spell, No more for him love's miracle— But bitter as the dead sea dust Seem'd all past joys,—dread things to thrust Aside, all equally accursed. In fervid prayer all day he sought God's grace: in dreams at night he fought The fierce temptations born of youth: Awake, he strove to reach God's truth— Asleep, he felt his passions rise And darken all the heav'nly skies With dread deceitful lovely lies. Thus year by year he fell and rose In endless conflict, till his woes Fill'd all his days with burning tears And dreadful never-ending fears: Haggard he grew from scanty food, With sun and blast and shelter rude And terrors of his lonelihood. With long hair streaming out behind He raced before the burning wind, With wild insane strained eyes alert For demons lurking to his hurt— And though the sun beat fiercely hot Upon the sands, he heeded not But like a wand'ring shadow shot Across the burning level waste, Oft shouting as he wildly raced ‘My body is in hell, but I, Its soul, thus hither speed and cry To God to blow me as a leaf From out this agony of grief, To slay, and give me death's relief!’ Oft as he fled, with from his mouth The white froth blown thro' maddening drouth, He pass'd the crouching lion's lair— But when his shrill laugh fill'd the air The desert monarch shrank, as though He feared this raving shadow's woe, This haggard wretch with eyes aglow. But when the sun sank past the west The hermit fled the desert, lest God's eyes should lose him in the night, And foes Satanic guide his flight Till soul and body once again Made one should with the pangs of twain In hell for ever writhe in pain. But when sleep came to him he lay In peace, and oft a smile would play Upon his face as though once more In dreams he lived his life of yore,— The life he did himself dismiss, The old sweet time of joy and bliss,— Heard laughter, or felt some loved kiss. Thus have I seen, and seeing known That he who lived afar alone, A hermit on a dreary waste, Was even that soul mine eyes have traced Through brute and savage steadily, That he even now is part of me Just as a wave is of the sea. Far out across the deep doth swell The hoarse boom of the Black-Rock bell, A heavy moan monotonous, An inner sea-sound ominous As though throughout the ocean there Relentless Conscience aye did bear A bitter message of despair. Still sweeps the old impetuous sea Around the green earth ceaselessly— Changeless, yet full of change, it seems The very mirror of those dreams We call men's lives—for are not they Like life-sea waves Fate's wind doth sway And break, yet which pass not away Through depths of silent air, but blend Once more with the great deep and lend Their never dying music sweet To the great choral song complete; Each death is but a birth, a change— Each soul through myriad byeways strange, Through birth and death, doth upward range. RAINBOW SKETCHES. I. THE RAINBOW. The rain-clouds slowly trail from the dun hills And the grey mists retreat from the grey seas, And a fresh wind comes forth and shakes the trees And blows the foam from the o'er-flooded rills, And softly then the sun the wet sky fills With chastened lights, and a long shimmer flees From cloud to cloud till over the drench'd leas A Rainbow curves its arc and glows and thrills. II. TOWARDS SUNSET. (Western Islands, N.B.) The whole sky to the west is wild With storm and tempest; clouds are piled Mass upon mass, like mountain-heights In skyey regions far; strange lights Gleam o'er their hollow flanks as though The furious wind that rears them so Breath'd fiery breaths—and overhead A maze of flying mists is spread, Cloud, mist, and rain, pure dazzling white A moment, lurid next and bright In slaty black, and now dull grey Descending in broad sheets away In furious rain above the sea. Far in the west shines yellowly A widening cloud-strait, and thereby The sun descending leaves the sky With ominous gleams—crimson flames, Purple, and bronze, hues without names; And ever underneath toils wide The windy sea, with wave and tide Lashing each other into flying Foam. Now, just as day is dying, The storm-clouds with a sudden thrill Seem windless and grow strangely still, And almost doth it seem as though Yon fugitive soft lights that glow Are the dying storm's dying smiles Dreamily waving to and fro, Like mists of the Enchanted Isles: Still wavering they blend and rise Till perfectly they arch the skies In one vast crescent bow, far seen O'er land and sea—an arch of green And soft and shadowy amethyst, Crimson as pure as sunrise-mist, Azure æthereally blue, And yellow gold with opal hue:— Some moments thus it flawless stands, A sign, a glory o'er the lands— The Soul of Hope it is we see Cloth'd in her immortality. III. DRIFTING RAIN-LIGHTS. Around this lonely sea-loch stand Huge mountain-shapes, a giant band Dwelling in solitude for aye, And silent save when through the grey Chill skies the eagle screams, or down Some sheer abyss where shadows frown In noontide loosen'd boulders fall Whirling and crashing, until all Is still once more, and once again The mountain-silence broods in pain. A curdling fume beyond the reach Of yonder headland, where the beach Scarce slopes a yard, betrays the tide's Fierce struggle where the current glides With swiftly outward flow, and as The conquering tide-waves inward pass The sleeping wind unfolds its wings And with sweet sudden laughter springs Upon the loch and sweeps the spray From startled wavelets fleeing away, Whence wheeling to the slopes it flies And where the heavy white mist lies Strikes with dividing pinions till The furtive sunlight on each hill Gleams, and the toiling vapours curl From crag to crag and wreathing whirl To higher mountain-hollows where Gaunt larches cling 'mid boulders bare. And as the grey clouds slowly lift, The sudden shimmering rain-lights drift Hither and thither, flash and fly As though bright spirits fill'd the sky— Wings here of azure, there of red, A golden glory overhead, A sudden rosy glow, a streak Of purple over some grey peak, A lovely waft of green (as though Some laughing sky-sprite from below Had filch'd a sea-wave's hue), a gleam Of amber like a strayed moon-beam, A sudden joyous skyey revel O'er mountain heights and lowland level, Now forming to an arch, again Flashing in drifting sprays of rain— Fair phantom hues that pass away Blown on the breath of dying day. IV. THE CIRCLE OF ULLOA. The scientific name given to this remarkable phenomenon. The white mists swathe the mountain-flanks And shroud the melancholy ranks Of gaunt green pines, until these seem Like ghostly figures in a dream Each standing silent by his grave. Far off swift mountain torrents rave Down rugged gorges, and below— Half muffled by the wastes of snow— A cataract in thunder booms. No sunlight fills these twilit glooms But only a wan greyness drear, And only where the peaks rise sheer Above the pine-clad heights the sun Faint yellow shines—a dismal gleam, No flashing golden coloured stream. But in the west a quiver stirs, As though a wind amidst the firs Were waving slow tired wings ere swift Awakening it rose to drift From hill to dale, from dale to hill, And the long waving pine-boughs fill With sudden music wild and sweet: Yet no wind comes with wings to beat The silence into sound—but slow A waving luminous mass doth glow And palpitate, and stretch, and rise, And hang suspended in the skies Until a mighty arch gleams there, A moonshine-coloured rainbow fair: Of palest amber is its hue And delicate as starlit dew, Till as a silver stream at dawn Slow stealing through a twilit lawn It seems to bend and circling flow Right through the mountain mists below, And curve again and upward sweep Till with a flash, a gleam, a leap The arch becomes a mighty ring And 'midst the windless mists doth swing. V. IN THE ANTARCTIC: AT DAYBREAK, BEFORE A STORM. Hither and thither the icebergs go With the urgent wind or the current's flow, And the stormy daydawn pales the fires That the stars had lit in the frozen spires, And the amber glow of the midnight moon Wanes swift in a dim wan silver swoon From the heart of each iceberg drifting slow With the wind and the current to and fro, While the darkling dawn of the colourless day Breaks o'er a thousand leagues of grey. And the sunrise coming brings no glad light, No golden glory, no radiance bright; But a strait of crimson that gleams blood-red And an ominous purple overhead Foretell of the wailing winds that will rise And sweep on their wild wings through the skies And howl and shout in their furious chase Of the waves and clouds in their twin swift race: And up from the south great masses come drifting, Night-black and snow-white, falling and lifting, With quivering rain-lights gleaming and shifting. But ere the wind and the rain and the hail Sweep down on the billows whereover we sail,— Like ghosts from the grave, like spirits that shine In the garb of their new-born life divine, From the womb of the clouds, round the brow of the gale Swift streamers of dazzling light combine, And flash and shimmer and swing on high Till five bright rainbows spanning the sky Of furious tempest prophesy. And the pinnacled icebergs rock and sway 'Midst rising billows and clouds of spray, And each holds deep in its frozen mass A prison'd rainbow—one green as grass, One blue as a sapphire fill'd with light, One shining all over with diamonds bright, One deeply flushing from base to spire With a glorious ruby's changeful fire, One all ablaze with an orange gleam— Till each iceberg there and each wave as well Are changed by a glorious miracle To a splendour greater than any dream. TRANSCRIPTS FROM NATURE. SECOND SERIES. I. THE ROOKERY AT SUNRISE. A remarkable occurrence which, circumstances being favourable, any one may see for himself who would think the sight worth rising for before day-dawn. Shelley had seen it at least once, as is evident by his graphic passage in the Lines written amongst the Euganean Hills. Mr. Stopford Brooke, also, in the notes to his delightful volume of Selections from Shelley, records having himself witnessed the spectacle. The loftly elm-trees darkly dream Against the steel-blue sky; till far I' the twilit east a golden star O'erbrims the dusk in one vast stream Of yellow light, and lo! a cry Breaks from a windy nest—the sky Is filled with wheeling rooks—they sway In one black phalanx towards the day. II. ON A THAMES BACKWATER. Its sweeping boughs the great ash trails Across the slow-flowing wave: around White waterlilies swim; no sound Disturbs the silence save when sails On the outer flood a passing boat— A water-hen quite close doth float, And, near, a kingfisher's bright gleam Is mirror'd deep within the stream. III. OCTOBER WOODLANDS. Here from this lichen'd crag I see The woodlands reach to yonder blues Which are the upland downs, in hues Of gold and red; pale greenery Yet unstain'd by the sun, and boughs Of dark-green firs where cushats drowse: Afar, poised motionless, a pair Of falcons hover in the air. IV. THE PINK ACACIA. Soft clusters mid the shadowy green— The pale sea-green acacias make When ruffling winds their leaflets shake— Lie thick and close, as blooms are seen Upon the pear-tree's boughs in May Or apple with its blossom-spray: A flash that melts to pink—such are Dawn's hues when pales the morning-star. V. MOUNTAIN-HAZE. The mountain-haze hides gulf and steep, A silver shifting gauzy veil: But as the hillside shadows fail And the glens waken from their sleep, Soft pink suffuses it—until It glows all saffron—seems to thrill In lucent gold—and then 'tis gone And lost where late the sunrise shone. VI. THE YELLOW POPPY. The beautiful Yellow Horned Poppy is familiar to those who know our southern shores. It is one of the very few flowers, like the Sea-side Convolvulus, the Sand-wort, etc., that grow close to the margin of the sea. Like flakes of beaten gold along The shingly beach the poppies blow: Their sunder'd blossoms to and fro Are drifted by the wind among The salt sea-grass, and o'er the wave That fain this upper beach would lave: Spring laughs not only o'er the land, But with her smiles transforms the strand. VII. MAGNOLIAS. (Australia.) The lofty blue-gums tower on high, A giant circle round us here— And tree-ferns fringe the little mere Around whose edge white masses lie, A thousand snowy blooms o'erbent With golden hearts and wondrous scent; And in the little dark-blue pond Another bloom-world gleams beyond. VIII. THE CORAL ISLE. A calm and waveless purple sea Scarce breathes with long slow heavy breath: A cloudless sky: 'twould be like death If rose not yonder faerily A magic isle with cool green palms, Adream 'mid coral-girdled calms, Around whose barriers night and day The sea-swell breaks in clouds of spray. IX. GREEN SEAS. (Terra del Fuego.) With thunder on this iron shore The fierce green South Pacific seas Break without ceasing: when no breeze Blows from the icy south they roar Like famish'd lions, shaking wild Their foamy manes where rocks are piled: When tempests ravage, then they grow Gaunt heralds of resistless woe. X. FROZEN RAINBOWS. (Antarctic Icebergs.) A north wind fills the straining sails, The blue-green sea is creased with white, An albatross screams in its flight And foam-jets rise from spouting whales: Beyond, around, great icebergs pass, Some amber, blue, some green as grass, Some filled with glorious lights—these seem Like rainbows in a frozen dream. XI. SUMMER ICEBERGS. (By Moonlight.) The black waves hurry on in hosts, Relentless squadrons 'neath the pale Cold moon; and thro' the moonshine sail Great grey wan shapes like island-ghosts: O'ertoppling, for the seas have laid Fierce hands upon their bases, made A hollow sound of waters where Of late was dead dumb polar air. XII. THE EVENING STAR. (At Sea.) Since this Transcript was written I find that in a poem called ‘Even Star,’ in his pleasant volume Io in Egypt: and other Poems, Mr. Richard Garnett has expressed the same motif much more successfully. The lines to which I refer are these: “The grey sky sparkles with my fairy light; I mix among the dancers of the sea, Yet stoop not from the throne I must retain High o'er the silver sources of the rain.’ Aflame with silver fires that glow With ruby-change and amethyst, Pants, pulses thro' this sundown mist The even-star, and to and fro O'er the sea-depths and weedy caves It dances in a myriad waves, Though still it thrills and throbs on high, The sole flame in the purpling sky. XIII. THE RUINED HILL-TOWER. A grey old tower of rough-hewn stone, Part ivy-clad, with sunlit base Where shadow'd branches interlace: Without, a blue pine stands alone Above where two stained columns lie, Memorial of days gone by. In the mere-waters dark and still The shadow sleeps of the tower'd hill. XIV. AN AUTUMNAL EVENING. Deep black against the dying glow The tall elms stand; the rooks are still; No windbreath makes the faintest thrill Amongst the leaves; the fields below Are vague and dim in twilight shades— Only the bats wheel in their raids On the grey flies, and silently Great dusky moths go flitting by. XV. TRAVELLERS' JOY. (Trailing Clematis.) The trees are leafless now, save where Some shelter'd oak prolongs its dream Of unfled Summer; by the stream The wither'd sedges show the lair Of some dead coot; but near the ways The scarlet hips shine thro' a maze Of clouded feathery blossoms light, Which in the sunshine gleam snow-white. XVI. A CRYSTAL FOREST. In Canada, Norway, Scotland, and other northern countries, this beautiful winter-transformation can frequently be seen. It is caused by intense frost setting in immediately upon a thaw, thus congealing the damp upon even the tiniest twigs and blades of grass and fernfronds into sheaths of thin transparent crystal. As the sun's heat intensifies, the crackling and dripping are incessant, and the change and beauty beyond description. The air is blue and keen and cold, With snow the roads and fields are white; But here the forest's clothed with light And in a shining sheath enrolled. Each branch, each twig, each blade of grass, Seems clad miraculously with glass: Above the ice-bound streamlet bends Each frozen fern with crystal ends. XVII. THE MOORS. (September.) A sky of rich deep blue: beneath, A mighty sterile mountain-range; Far west with shifting shades doth change The sea; all else is purple heath— A glorious purple world wherein A myriad lives each morn begin, Where the grouse call, and the grey hare Leaps, and whirling curlews fill the air. XVIII. THE DEAD STAG. Upon the purple moor quite dead The antlered monarch lonely lies, The proud fire vanisht from his eyes; The mountain-sunset burns blood-red, And makes the tarn beside the stag Flame like an outstretched crimson flag: Two hooded crows their wings flap near, Not long to be kept back by fear. XIX. THE HAUNT OF THE OSPREY. (Western Highlands.) A rugged scaur in the mid-lake Stands high and peak'd; on this doth rest The ragged semblance of a nest; Here the young birds their hunger slake With fish the parent ospreys bring, Here they shriek loud their hungering; Here the sea-eagles breed, and here As savage chiefs they rule through fear. XX. THE BLASTED PINE. The barren granite cliffs withstand The Atlantic surge that day and night Breaks in the thunder of its might: And on the furthest spur of land— A mighty fissured crag—rears high A blasted pine against the sky: Dead, lightning-riven, black, alone, Its bare boughs answer the wind's moan. XXI. SUMMER YELLOWS. The hill-side shimmers with live gold Of scented gorse; the celandine Lights up the lanes; o'er meadows green Kingcups and daffodils have rolled A sunshine wave; and by the stream Marsh-mallows and tall iris gleam: With sweet wild song the goldfinch flies, And oft the yellowhammer cries. XXII. AN AFTERGLOW AMID THE CUMBERLAND FELLS. (December, 1883.) Gloom shrouds the hills and hides the dales, The wintry sun an hour has set: But lo! a blood-red parapet Leans from the sky, and crimson veils Of stealthy vapour cling and crawl About the night's funereal pall— Till with a wind it seems to sway And drift in burning flakes away. XXIII. A WINTER HEDGEROW. The wintry wolds are white; the wind Seems frozen; in the shelter'd nooks The sparrows shiver; the black rooks Wheel homeward where the elms behind The manor stand; at the field's edge The redbreasts in the blackthorn hedge Sit close, and under snowy eaves The shrewmice sleep 'mid nested leaves. XXIV. WILD SWANS. (Western Isles.) An inland strait of the salt sea Lost in a purple wilderness Where seldom wandering feet transgress: Low rainy hills stand mournfully Amid the wide drear waste—and where The sea-loch laps their bases bare The wild-swans with the dying light Wheel, screaming, in their phalanx'd flight. XXV. THE SALMON POOL. The tassell'd birch o'erhangs the pool, Clear amber, where the pebbles shine Like opals amid golden wine; And where the margin dark and cool Reflects a tremulous world of green The thrush from its lithe spray has seen A band of living silver lie Deep down in moveless symmetry. XXVI. THE EAGLE. (Western Highlands.) Between two mighty hills a sheer Abyss—far down in the ravine A thread-like torrent and a screen Of oaks like shrubs—and one doth rear A dry scarp'd peak above all sound Save windy voices wailing round: At sunrise here, in proud disdain, The eagle scans his vast domain. MADONNA NATURA. I love and worship thee in that thy ways Are fair, and that the glory of past days Haloes thy brightness with a sacred hue: Within thine eyes are dreams of mystic things, Within thy voice a subtler music rings Than ever mortal from the keen reeds drew; Thou weav'st a web which men have callëd Death But Life is in the magic of thy breath. The secret things of Earth thou knowest well; Thou seest the wild-bee build his narrow cell, The lonely eagle wing through lonely skies. The lion on the desert roam afar, The glow-worm glitter like a fallen star, The hour-lived insect as it hums and flies; Thou seest men like shadows come and go, And all their endless dreams drift to and fro. In thee is strength, endurance, wisdom, truth: Thou art above all mortal joy and ruth, Thou hast the calm and silence of the night: Mayhap thou seest what we cannot see, Surely far off thou hear'st harmoniously Echoes of flawless music infinite, Mayhap thou feelest thrilling through each sod Beneath thy feet the very breath of God. Monna Natura, fair and grand and great, I worship thee, who art inviolate: Through thee I reach to things beyond the span Of mine own puny life, through thee I learn Courage and hope, and dimly can discern The ever nobler grades awaiting man: Madonna, unto thee I bend and pray— Saviour, Redeemer thou, whom none can slay! No human fanes are dedicate to thee, But thine the temples of each tameless sea, Each mountain-height and forest-glade and plain: No priests with daily hymns thy praises sing, But far and wide the wild winds chanting swing, And dirge the sea-waves on the changeless main, While songs of birds fill all the fields and woods, And cries of beasts the savage solitudes. Hearken, Madonna, hearken to my cry: Teach me through metaphors of liberty, Till strong and fearing nought in life or death I feel thy sacred freedom through me thrill, Wise, and defiant, with unquenchëd will Unyielding, though succumb the mortal breath— Then if I conquer take me by the hand And guide me onward to thy Promised Land!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">NOTE. ‘Australia has rightly been named the Land of the Dawning. Wrapped in the mist of early morning, her history looms vague and gigantic. The lonely horseman riding between the moonlight and the day sees vast shadows creeping across the shelterless and silent plains, hears strange noises in the primeval forest, where flourishes a vegetation long dead in other lands. ? In Australia alone is to be found the Grotesque, the Weird, the strange scribblings of Nature learning how to write.’—Marcus Clarke.</field>
   </doc>
</add>