<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Crosland, T. W. H., (Thomas William Hodgson), 1865-1924</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Crosland, T. W. H., (Thomas William Hodgson), 1865-1924</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">crosland t w h thomas william hodgson 1865 1924</field>
      <field name="author_text">Crosland, T. W. H., (Thomas William Hodgson), 1865-1924</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1910's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.0681.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1917</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466346</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Greek, Modern (1453- )</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Spanish</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Collected Poems of T. W. H. Crosland</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Collected Poems of T. W. H. Crosland</field>
      <field name="title_facet">collected poems of t w h crosland</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">collected poems of t w h crosland</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Collected Poems of T. W. H. Crosland</field>
      <field name="year_display">1917</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1917</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1917</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466346&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466346&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Crosland, T. W. H., (Thomas William Hodgson), 1865-1924&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;crosland t w h thomas william hodgson 1865 1924&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Collected Poems of T. W. H. Crosland&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;collected poems of t w h crosland&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1917&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1917&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Crosland, T. W. H., (Thomas William Hodgson)&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1865&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1924&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Collected Poems of T. W. H. Crosland&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Martin Secker&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1917&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0961&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;gre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;spa&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;x, 206 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Collected Poems of T. W. H. Crosland&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 175 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">‘Donde una puerta se cierra, otra se abre” Cervantes Note The pieces hereby assembled represent a period of production ranging over a quarter of a century. A number of those referring to the war are reprinted from ‘War Poems by X’ (Martin Secker, 1916). Others are now published for the first time. Lest the title ‘Collected Poems’ be taken in its post-mortem association, the author desires respectfully to say that he is still alive. POEMS Woman Four pomegranates grow for me, On my true love's silver tree. One I have tasted, and my mouth Is filled with fragrance of the South; One, which burns with holy red, He shall give me when we wed; The third from its branch shall be torn When our little son is born; The fourth, which is most delicate, Kinder than Love, sharper than Fate, Fairer than fruit of Samarkand, You shall put in my dead hand. Swan Song Who makes an Eden must set you in it, And who hath stars of crystal brimmed and bright, Planets of rose, Or moons of amber lit From lordly lending suns of chrysolite, And beautiful as those That ache to furious Saturn. For you are silver dawns And silver rain And silver snows: And the prodigious night Of balms and dews and darknesses and dreams And trancèd forests and enchanted streams, And unimaginable lawns, And unlatched lattices (Enlamped and tinkling) Suddenly shut-to, And snaring silences: Eternally for you The age-young seas are blue And the great peaks rose-white. The nightingale Which doth the world assail Athrob with old immitigable pain And music past her wit, And ambushed in the cedars, spilleth no note Or fret or flurry or strain Or magical sweet pattern That is not yours; Neither shall she, the minstrel, who doth sit Poisèd in extreme height And propped by April azures, So to fling The noise of her aspiring At angel feet And on immortal floors. You know the men and women who are dead Each by his name and each by her dim name, And you do count them as you count spent roses From the first down And till the last one closes: Time-which-hath-been, and cannot be, hath spread Beside the river of Time-which-is, a town Of echoless dwelling-places where inhabit Shadows that shine or bleed And creep and climb and falter and are sped, And are yet shadows, and shall never know More than they knew, And never more may say More than they said, And yours is their imperishable joy And yours their woe, And on your head Fall ruth and rapture: You are both quick and dead, While they, Whom luring life never again shall capture, Are only dead. There was a maid who had just heard of love, And an old man who had forgotten lust, A barren wife whose heart was motherhood, A wanton who could think on naught but good; A thief who still Had honour, and a liar To whom his lie Was whip and fire And an abhorr'd And grievous uttering: I heard a bride say in the night The world is builded on delight, I saw the murderer adore a sky Of summer and without fleck What time the hangman grabbled at his neck: They told me of a princess who had thrown From her sweet state, hot kisses to the dust, And of a peacock lord Who darkly understood He was a clown, And of a clown who surely was a king But minded apes. All loveliness, all ill, All innocence, all ruin and all dread, All glory and all disgrace Lifted themselves like ghosts, In infinite multitude, Innumerable hosts; And all these shapes Were yours, And they had looks like flowers And manifold soft graces, And ever in their faces I could trace, Somewhere, your face. O secret, consecrate Inviolable spirit, elate And amorous and proud With blanchèd plumes that shroud And glitteringly conceal The flame, and the vermeil And whiteness not for sight, Who to this garden of tears And the enthronèd spheres Art essence and breath and light; Who blessest for the blest And for the lowliest, And standest on heaven's rim Out-staturing seraphim, And sittest by poor men's fires And givest to the wicked their desires, And whom to gaze upon That which is done is done For ever, and shall be Unto eternity; In the translated clay Bathed out of Paphia, In love and laughter and might And the seven souls of right And seventy souls of wrong, In birth and sorrow and song And terror and despair, And all things fine and fair Whether of gold or green, The wonder have I seen, The immanence flashing by, And, slain with it, I die! The Weeping Through height on height Of the far Heaven, Which is a firmament And infinite air And bosom of light, Great seraphs swept On joyful errands bent; And in the seven Sweet spaces Where blessedness doth begin, The cherubin Holily strayed, And shined and slept, And shined again. And none that were Engardened of those bright places Sorrowed or wept Or knew the use of tears. It had been so a million, million years: And then,— The world was made. Payments I “I will come to you Across white dawns, In the night of stars, In the morning blue. “Like a shining dove Alone in heaven, In your sweet place I shall see you move.” . . . O Heart, it befell, When I came, when I came, You laughed ghost-white In the lamps of hell. II Fairer than the fair And than young moons, Thus to be lodged With sharp despair. O innocent, Unblemish'd and without spot And so without defence; For you the punishment. For you the rod And the impitying stroke, You loveliness, You city of God! III You had no tears Women may weep, Nor silver easing sigh Nor fortifying fears, No trepidance: Only the dumb amaze Of undeceivèdness Chanced upon all mischance; Nor agonies Nor sorrow unto death, That you should fall on your face In seven Gethsemanes. IV Your punctual candle lit, Your bowl kept bright, Your thoughts as still As the lily in it. A curtain of blue, A bed of cypress wood And ivory, And one great star for you. And cloths of fair White, and cups of gold— And in your heart the knife And winter in your hair. V How should you pray Or call to the saints, Who had small need of prayer Even as they? How should you guess That over you would fail The pinion shadowless Even for a minute's space? How could the air Forget its kindnesses, And the earth its love And your angel his care? VI There was a foul And livid, living thing That wept and died, Having no soul. The lips of it Scarlet with lies And impudent with leers, And on its forehead writ Evil and bale; And it hath fellowship Malefic as itself, But clad in cunninger mail. VII For ever, walls of fire And chasms of swords 'Twixt your green country And the world's mire. It were a sin That echo or breath Should reach to your tower From tents they riot in. Yet their desert Lifts them, and deviously From these and thence Cometh the hurt. VIII Into your book, Jewelled with flame And clamped with honour, Who shall look? Borders of woe, Letters of blood, Upon a page Of milk and snow. This justice for the just Thereby you read— Ashes to ashes Dust to dust. A Song of Death I Smile, O master of life, Safe in thy silver house, Be pleased with thy pleasant wife— Soon thou hast woe for spouse. Joy and joy are thy choice— (Shrewd art thou past a doubt!) Take they joy and rejoice— Sorrow shall find thee out. Laugh thou loud at the fool Munching his bitter bread;— Surely as thou dost rule One shall rule in thy stead. What though thy heart be flame, And perfume all thy breath?— Who hath written thy name Here in the book of Death? Yea, though thou shine rose-white Or though thou burn rose-red, Upon the lawful night Thou shalt lie spent and sped. Drink that is soft and sound! Meats for the delicate maw!— Already the beldame is found Who shall tape-up that jaw. Build through the golden day Cunning in every stroke— Adze from his bench must say, “Shall it be elm or oak?” And though thou hast all grace, All wisdom, and all wit, Mattock, in the right place, Will delve the appointed pit. With faith thou art rich; and firm In hopes like the young east— Let us promise the worm His certain year-long feast! II Fool that no man calls master, Irredeemable slave, Born for the stark disaster With nothing to hope or have. Inasmuch as thou moilest For sour and scanty bread, Rejoice, for wherever thou toilest One shall toil in thy stead. And inasmuch as they gall thee And bitterness is thy breath, On a day they shall call thee Forth to thy lawful death. Let it not be forgotten, This is the sure reward— Thou shalt lie dead and rotten, Even as dead as thy lord. So with the brand or the feather Each hath his tally and term— Let us sup nobly together, “Here's to the ultimate worm!” III Lo, there is anguish and wailing Out of the world and her wars, A cry goeth up unavailing Unto the steadfast stars. Set on sweet thrones they glister Over our pain and ruth, Each to her shining sister Telling the wordless truth. Though we be fools or sages, Who is it conquereth? Death shall pay this world's wages; All that he pays is death. By the prayers ye have faltered, By the blood and the tears, Which is the law ye have altered In all the faithful years? No new sign hath been given, No new tale is to tell— And still the earth is heaven, And still the souls are hell. Death for life is the guerdon, “Life for death” is the ban; None might carry the burden, Only the sons of man. Of whom there is no daunting Beneath the pitiless sky, For whom the final vaunting Is “men can only die.” Cursèd be he that setteth Snares for the bleeding feet; Cursèd be he that getteth, And giveth not, good wheat. Cursèd be he that showeth, Unto the simple, lies; Cursèd be he that throweth Dust in the star-set eyes. The Ballad of Poor Honesty “Now Good,” quoth he, “Be good for me, And Evil be thou evil”: O simple wight!— As well he might Have leagued him with the Devil— Who, when all's said, Is a gentleman bred, And civil to the civil. He trudgeth forth, Now south now north, To turn the needful penny, Upon his back He bears a pack Through suns and snows a-many And mile on mile— With an equal smile For Richard and for Jenny. “Yea these,” he sware, “Be God's own pair, They will not cog or cozen, In smocks they go To milk and mow, And threadbare are their hosen; But if your due Be twelve, for you They'll count out the full dozen.” Yet Dick, fell wretch, Did the hangman stretch, For cutting a babe's weasand, And by the Bench That brazen wench, Young Jenny, was imprisoned, That folk might cry, “In villainy The twain were properly seasoned.” “Still Good,” quoth he, “Be good for me, And Evil be thou evil; My grandam dear, Above her beer, Was wont to curse the Devil, ‘O little lad, Eschew the bad Which doth defile!’ she'd snivel.” Upon an ass He is fain to pass Into the virtuous city, And soon doth stop With my lord bishop, The learnèd and the witty: (“So honest a face!” Mused his lordship's grace— And hired him out of pity.) Here every saw Of the moral law With joy he heard repeated, Till on a night In the candle-light The bishop's guests were seated, And they played a game, Bezique by name, And my lord the bishop cheated. So, nothing loth, Our friend shogged off To service with a person Whom fools did rate For a prop of the State: There couldn't have been a worse 'un; For by wink or grin He approved the sin We are bidden to put a curse on. Then a judge he served Who quite unnerved This saint by actions foxy, Such as bringing home quills From the Office of Wills And going to church by proxy, And, once a week, Pinching the cheek Of a most offensive doxy. “Still Good for me Be good,” quoth he, “And Evil be thou evil; I will show my mind Unto mankind, And speak them fair and civil, And tell them how All men I know Are bondmen of the Devil.” He trudgeth forth Both south and north By markets and street corners, And saith aloud To the wondering crowd, “Ye are plagued with thieves and scorners And liars and cheats And hypocrites And losels and suborners!” He was the first That ever burst Upon them with such tiding; Eftsoons they cried, “This fellow's pride Is surely past abiding!” And with grievous stones, They bruised his bones, And hurried him into hiding. Upon the floor He lies full sore, Nor murmureth unduly, Although he must Give up the ghost His speech is not unruly; With his last breath He uttereth These words: “I ha' spoken truly!” So passeth he Most miserably, Without or sniff or snivel: Unhappy wight— As well he might Have leagued him with the Devil, Who on the whole Is a decent soul, And returneth good for evil! Faitan They have fetch'd for the king, To his city of might, The singers who sing In the dusks of delight And the noons of the night. Where the women are lain They have order'd his rest, With the blood of the slain On his sword and his crest, And his hands on his breast. SONNETS April 23 How shall we praise thee, who art England's praise And with the soul of her soul most accords, So that she vaunteth to the end of days England and Shakespeare high, fast-wedded words? O Royal thou, that spake us a new earth And new fair heavens, and a proud new sea, Greener is April, boasting of thy birth, More blossom'd May, because she swaddled thee! Before thy wisdom humbly stand the wise, Judged of thy goodness, Virtue hath no cause, Whoever mounts, a feeble feather tries By thy great pinion; and except thou pause, The sweetest singer falters in his scale— Eagle, and Lark, and Swan, and Nightingale! For Remembrance What wife had he, what sweetheart, what fair love? So will the gossips ask themselves when Fame Shall set her impudent lips upon my name And make an auction for your cast-off glove. They know you not. You are a brooding dove, Whose spirit, fearful of the world's sharp flame, Nestles unto the goodness whence it came, And hath nor wish to range nor will to rove. Yet, that through dusty Time you may not pass Unpictured, unenshrined, or unadored, I build this turret of eternal brass, Wherein, so long as word may chime with word, You are to sit before your jewelled glass Beautiful as the Garden of the Lord. For Algernon Charles Swinburne The cherry whitens in the April air, Young Spring has spilt her magic on the wold, The woodlands ring with rapture as of old, And England lies new-washen, green and fair; Yet is she heavy with a secret care, For Death the ever-sharp and over-bold Hath taken our Tongue of Honey, our Throat of Gold; And we have digged a pit, and left him there. So must he sleep, though it be high broad noon, Or Venus glister in the darkling firs: The roses and the music are forgot; Even the great round marigold of a moon, That is for lovers and for harvesters, And all the sighing seas, may move him not. For Stephen Phillips Now you are dead and past the bitter fret And the long doubt and the disputed throne, And the contempts which turn the heart to stone,— Who that hath wit shall breathe you a regret? Who that hath tears shall pay you pity's debt? Unto your place of easing you are gone, Having fetched for us Beauty from her own Lodges of gold by silver orchards set. O mortal man that looked in angels' eyes And still of baseness took both rood and reed, Griever who wed bright visions to great sounds, Teller of sorrowful proud histories; We put our silly fingers in your wounds And it is well that they no longer bleed. Ubi Bene Along the English lanes a budding green, Upon the English orchards pink and white, And over them the rapture and delight Of April sunshine! Fair and fresh and clean, Washen as if in wells of hyaline And very wondrous to the pilgrim sight; A glad, new land of all things soft and bright— Oh, surely, here an angel must have been And left his blessing! . . . Dead, young son of ours, Who didst so proudly taste the loving-cup, Whose blood but now shone like a living rose Dropped by the Lord upon the Flanders snows, What country shall they give you to be yours For this, the England you have given up? The Baby in the Ward We were all sore and broken and keen on sleep, Tumours and hearts and dropsies, there we lay, Weary of night and wearier of day, With no more health in us than rotten sheep. Then, tossed to us on some intangible deep, Alicia came, and each man learnt to pray That Providence would please find out a way To still or abate the voice with which she would weep. God's infinite mercy, how that child did cry, In spite of bottle, bauble, peppermint, nurse! The Tumour said he'd “tell the manager,” The Dropsy mumbled forth his bitterest curse; But still she wailed and wailed. And when we die We shall be sainted for forgiving her. Titanic Upon the tinkling splintery battlements Which swing and tumble south in ghostly white Behemoth rushes blindly from the night, Behemoth whom we have praised on instruments Dulcet and shrill and impudent with vents: Behemoth whose huge body was our delight And miracle, wallows where there is no light, Shattered and crumpled and torn with pitiful rents. O towers of steel and masts that gored the moon, On you we blazoned our pomp and lust and pelf, And we have died like excellent proud kings Who take death nobly if it come late or soon: For our high souls are mirrors of Himself, Though our great wonders are His littlest things. Valour Mounting his stairs of azure and of gold, The English lark sings in the August weather For joy which knoweth neither tie nor tether And is not troubled if the world grows old; While you, who were as blithesome and as bold, And held your life lightly as any feather, Sleep the high sleep that dead men sleep together, Careless of what is done and what is told. I know that all our England shone before you When you went down. It made a radiance Even of the front of Death. Oh, woman's son, You died for England . . . valiant as she that bore you, And sent you forth with a still countenance, And broke her heart for England—and lives on! Lovers He goeth and he returns not. He is dead; Their house of joy no further brightness shows, Their loveliness is come unto its close, Their last touch given, and their last kindness said; For him no more the vision of her bent head, For her no more the lily or the rose, Nor any gladness in this place of woes; The book is shut, the bitter lesson read. Yet who shall beat them down? Though the Abhorr'd Taketh the groom, and to the bride hath sent The dagger of anguish with the ice-cold hilt, Both of them triumph in a strange content— And out of souls like these will heavens be built And holy cities peopled for the Lord. On the Death of Edward VII All our proud banners mourn along the May, One who is plumed and powerful breaks us down: Marred are the orchards, shaken our strong town, And blackness covers up our bright array. The Sceptre and the Orb are put away; The scarlet changed for the funereal gown; And easy lies the head that wore a Crown, And this which was a King is simple clay. O mighty Death, the mightiest are thine, Thou set'st his Widow weeping in her place, And while thou pluck'st her heart with thy chill hand, And givest her to drink a common wine, The wondering sentry goeth at his pace, And England cries, and cannot understand. The Promise You know my pains, you see me in the hell Through which I toil, hurt and uncomforted, You see on what base errands I am sped, And what I reap where we sowed asphodel; And my songs are of sorrow, and I tell, Knowing no other, tales of grief and dread: Though I be warm I am as good as dead, And always we can hear my passing bell. And yet, dear Spirit, you who have kind eyes That meet disaster with a child's amaze, You who have got a wild rose for your lips And are all fashioned out of Paradise; You shall stand safe beside the sapphire bays, And I will show you all our golden ships. Ulster The savage leopardess, and she-wolves and bears Cherish their offsprings in the solitude, And red-eyed tigresses whose trade is blood, And female panthers, and jackals in their lairs. The lowliest, sullenest mother-creature wears In her hot heart a jewel of motherhood, And knoweth darkly that the only good Is to defend and succour her rude heirs. And thou whose Might is from the east unto the west, Whose Front is of chilled iron and fine gold, Who yet in glory and honour goest drest, O great-thewed mother of us all, behold How this thy sturdy child, who is foully sold, Fights that he be not banished from thy breast! Charing Cross At five o'clock they ring a tinkly bell; The April dawn glimmers along the beds, There is a lifting up of weary heads From weary pillows. Our old citadel Hath still held out, and while the miracle Of morning is unbared again, and spreads All the young East with greens and blues and reds Each of us wakes to his particular hell. But even on this bitter shore of Styx Where Life to dogged Death puts the last schism, We kindle for the ending of the dark: The Asthma feebly jokes the Aneurism, The little bandaged boy in Number Six Sings “Ye shall die” with a voice like a lark. For H. M. C. I wonder which hath triumphed, you or Death? For he has torn you ultimately from your place, And shattered all the woman in your face, And put his last injunction on your breath, And ferried you across to his dim staith Where there is none who hath either hope or grace, But only the unimaginable race Of broken souls his wing encompasseth. O pitiful and pitiful! And yet Not all he asks is yielded up to him, And we who fight have our shrewd joy therefor: Upon your brow sitteth a shining, grim Rapture of wars, and on your lips is set To-night the still smile of the conqueror. After And when I die, you should be grieved, and go Dumbly into the bitter fields alone, For you have long since made your widow's moan, And carried in your heart the widow's woe. Outrageous Death hath neither feint nor blow To hurt you further. Thus without a groan I shall go down, and be as cold as stone, And you will kiss me and I shall not know. But haply then some mercy may befall, And to your breast, this death in life being past, Quiet may come and peace without alloy: Seeing you lone and lovely and downcast They will possess you with a secret joy And keep you with an angel at your call. Dawn “This morning at dawn I attacked the enemy's second system of defence.” —Sir Douglas Haig These are the fights of Love and Joy and Men With Fate and Death and the illicit Beast, For guerdons, of which Glory is the least And Honour not the highest. The old reign Of Night shall topple, the old Wrongs be slain: Fitting it is that you go to the Feast While angel suns kindle the young-eyed east And bring the breath of Eden back again. Oh soldiers' hour! . . . For now the English rose Flames and is washed with the authentic dew And through the mist her ancient crimson shows: I see your shadows on the waking lawn Like shadows of kings, and all the souls of you Blazoned and bright and panoplied in the dawn. Cor Cordium He is gone hence. Weep no weak tears for him: You gave us freely what you valued most; It is not loss, for gifts are never lost Unto the giver. Lo, the star-kept, dim Limits where battle fades away, and grim Death halts and hath no power! On that coast His feet are set among the shining host Who range with cherubim and seraphim. A thousand suns are unregarded dust, A million dawns break and are counted not, And Beauty riseth up, and she departs Eternally—eternally forgot; But your fair stripling, dead beside his trust, Is safely folded in the Heart of Hearts. “Votes for Women” Mark how their shining effigies are set For ever on the firmament of Time, Like lovely words caught in a lovely rhyme, Or silver stars kept in a faery net. Ivory and marble hold them for us yet, And all our blossomy memories of them chime With all the honest graces of the prime— Helen, and Ruth, Elaine, and Juliet. And You, in this disconsolate London square Flaunting an ill-considered purple hat And mud-stained, rumpled, bargain-counter coat, You of the broken tooth and buttered hair, And idiot eye and cheeks that bulge with fat, Sprawl on the flagstones chalking for a vote! For a Rich Man who is said to “Believe in Poetry” Let us be filled with wild and fierce disdains, Let us contemn, disparage, and cry down These prancing stomachs who amass and own, Inherit and squander, and have nets and chains And panoplies of penalties and pains Wherewith to extort the uttermost half-crown; For whom indeed the world's hard fields are sown And its scant harvests gathered on gorged wains. Withal, we must believe good things of them, And show a kindly bosom while they stand Grinning out of their proud and cunning eyes; Nay, even the chiefest shall not stir our phlegm, For he hath still knowledge of Paradise, And hides an angel's feather in his hand. Leda Out of my silver turrets I look down Upon a garden wherein sleeps a rose Who hath a ruby heart; beside her glows Unblemished, in a drifted, vestal gown Yon lily, and beyond them lies a town Of tufted green and each sweet bloom that blows; Midmost from whence a little fountain throws His gentle sprays which seem but half his own. And on the lake that skirts our dreary wood There sails for ever a new-washen swan, Who is as white as milk or angels are: At dawn he glitters in the solitude, At dusk he goeth glimmering and wan To where one waits him, white like a young star. The “Student” A minx of seventeen, with rather fine Brown eyes and freckles and a cheerful grin, She saunters up the ward, and stricken sin Nods and looks pleasant (why should one repine?). She takes “her cases,” looks for every “sign,” Hammers and sounds the portly and the thin, Plies them with questions till their cheap heads spin And keeps them busy saying “ninety-nine.” It's my turn now! Oh, let me bare my chest And spread a level sheet across my crib, And be as wax for our meticulous Miss; While she, poor dear, doing her anxious best, Feels for the apex under the wrong rib And wonders fiercely where my liver is. Antarctic What tale is this which stirs a world of knaves Out of its grubbing to throw greasy pence Forth to the hat, and choke with eloquence In boastful prose and verse of doubtful staves? Four men have died, gentlemen, heroes, braves; Snows wrap them round eternally. From thence They may no more return to life or sense And a steel moon aches down on their chill graves. “They died for England.” It is excellent To die for England. Death is oft the prize Of him who bears the burden and the load. So with a glory let our lives be spent— We may be noble in the Minories And die for England in the Camden Road. Shepherd's Bush Preposterous stucco, naughty ropes of light, The drunken drone of twenty-two brass bands, A flip-flap, and some hokey-pokey stands; Smith on your left, and Lipton on your right, And Lyons, Lyons, Lyons; and that bright Particular marvel, which, be sure, commands Respect from fools of all and sundry brands— The Press Lord Harmsworth prints from every night. Here, noble London, dost thou prowl and yell, Or cause to disappear with horrid zest The meat and drink provided by the Jew; Here flickereth they paltry, shadowful hell— And like a silver feather in the West, And fair as fair, the moon that Dido knew! Death For thou wert Master of their windy keeps, In Tyre, in Ilium, and in Babylon, Which smote the welkin many a year agone With torches and with shouting. Whoso sleeps On the large hills, or drowns in the old deeps, His name shines in a book for thee to con; And thy chill pomps and aching triumphs are won Where the forlornest woman sits and weeps. So that for thee we make embroideries, And for thy foul pate twist a beamy crown, Who art the lord of laughter and of lust, Who readest all their lesson to the wise, And to the fools, as they go up and down; And it is this: A cry, a dream, and—dust. The End I know that our fair rose was slain last night: She is become a ruinous, delicate wraith, And now she gives her perfumes up to Death; No longer may she shine in the sweet light, Or drink the dewey darkness; for the might That breaks the hearts of kings and staggereth Bold men, hath borne her down. “Take me,” she saith, “Unto the old, dead roses, red and white.” So, dearest, when the ultimate foul dun And crawling knave into our hand shall thrust His figure of accompt and greedy fine For our poor gladness underneath the sun, I shall come laughing to your gentle dust, Or you will come like balm to comfort mine. For the Time Give me the robe an angel late hath worn, Give me the tongue of wonder and the pen Of magic which doth fetch the souls of men Out of deep hell; give me the stings of scorn, The rage of blood, agony of the thorn, Wisdom of hills and stars. Let me be ten Times tried in furnaces, and tried again, And searched in icy wells where proof is born. And I will say to you a word of breath More furious than the forty winds of night And fiercer and more terrible than death; And yet as holy as the words of light That love or mercy or sainthood uttereth, And sweeter than the prayers of women—Fight! Red Rose ???? ?? ??????? Red Rose importuneth the Lover, and he answereth herThe red rose called to me, “Be thou my Love; Lo, I am fire and flame For love of thee.” I said to the red rose, “It is in starry white, With brows and breasts of snow, That my Love goes.” She continueth to invite him and praiseth herself“Come to me, come to me, I shall be excellence, Softness and bloom and myrrh And heavy sleep,” saith she. “And I have doves, as of old, My lips are crimson joy, And my smiles are of light, And my tears are of gold.” She telleth him of her lovers, and biddeth him be the chief of them“Three Kings rage at my door, They would have love of me, Till I look forth on them, They are mean men and poor. “In purple they go drest, And bright gifts each King bears, Come thou and be with us, And I will love thee best.” She describeth her chamber and the pleasures thereof“There is a chamber lies In the heart of my house, Secret and sweet and dim, Lit only with mine eyes. “We will burn spices there, And we will say to Life, ‘Bring now for our delight All that is good and fair.’” The Lover telleth her of the chamber of his own LoveI said, “No Kings may wait Against my white Love's door, She hath no Love save one, She needeth not such state. “Her chamber is of blue, A gold lamp shines therein; A lily and a babe Are in her chamber too.” The Lover falleth captive to her beautyRed rose, red rose, Oh, thou red rose! I went into her house Upon the slow day's close, I lay down on her bed, She smiled her smile of light, She wept her tears of gold: “Oh, thou red rose!” I said. He parleyeth with her“Red rose, red rose, Red rose and rose of mine, Behold we are one soul, With love for its repose.” She laughed, like one who sings, Saying, “We are one soul.” She thought of my white Love, And I of those three Kings. They sleepShe thought of those three Kings, And I of my white Love: A cold moon look'd at us, Chill from a thousand springs. I said, “But we are one.” She said, “Yea, we are one.” We slept a lover's sleep Until that moon was gone. The awakeningAt dawn she stirred and woke. I said, “O red, red rose, What of my little white Love?” And never a word she spoke. Before her mirror long Stood she, and tired herself, Her hair flamed in the sun, Her laugh was like a song. They are to ride forth“The day is fair,” she said, “We will ride forth,” said she, “I on a milk-white horse, Thou on a roan of red. “The world is deck'd like a bride, And sharp and sweet the air, Those kings shall follow us, Thou ridest at my side.” They ride, and the Lover seeth his own LoveWe rode forth into the dawn, All a-glitter and shine, Along the sleepy streets, Past lodge and river and lawn, And fields that good men till; And out by the western gate I saw my little white Love Simpling upon a hill. He showeth her to Red RoseI said, “Red rose, red rose, Seest thou who is there? It is my own white Love, Mark with what grace she goes.” “Pardie, pardie, good Sir, Is it thy lady Love? Then, if thou lovest me true, Get down and speak with her.” He will not go to his own LoveShe smiled her smile of light, She pursed her crimson lips, She let her hand touch mine, Her eyes shone very bright. I said, “Red rose, I ween That thou and I are as one, I would not leave they side An she were Mary Queen.” Red Rose dealeth shrewdly with himSo that we rode and came Unto a fair green place; She put her head on my breast, And softly said my name. Those three Kings stood apart, Plotting my death they stood; She took a jewelled knife, And stabbed me in the heart. And leaveth him to perishAnd turned her milk-white steed, And kissed me on the lips, And laughed to those three Kings, And left me there to bleed. And, with those Kings, did ride Away in the sunshine: I could not wish her hurt, “O red, red rose,” I cried. He riseth upLike torches in the sky At night the stars awoke, The ghost of me stood up And ached exceedingly. The world seemed full of shows: I went to mine own door, And look'd on my white Love, And cried, “O red, red rose!” The endSpring sitteth at her loom, Weaving her green and gold, The sweet lark sitteth in heaven, And thou in thy red room! My white Love, still as a mouse, Still and quiet and pale, Sitteth beside her babe, And thou in thy red house! 1903 WAR POEMS War 1 She took of fire of the sun and steel of the icy moon And rage of furious seas and breath of the hurricane, And silver sound of April and blossom and dust of June, And tears of women and terror of babes and blood of the hearts of men; Through nights athrob with her rose-red star and aghast with the wild star's falling, And days of summer whereby she was throned and days of autumn that crowned her, She went to make dread feasts and great pomps; and she reigneth—for ever calling The fairest and kindest and bravest and youngest and dearest around her. 2 For them she hath lures which are swifter than joy and brighter than hope And subtler than aught that cunning deviseth or gildeth, Surer to snare and safer to catch than love-lamp or silken rope Hung from the moonlit window for token of love which yieldeth; She hath content for the high wild heart and content for the wooer, She is the lover of lovers, whom loving, none may love other, Softly she sayeth the names of her children that they may go to her, And she gathers them to her stark fierce bosom like a proud mother. 3 Of old hath she been contemned by mouths that were zealous and wise, Sister of Murder, procuress and bondwoman of Death; Yet is the blood on her hand made snow by the Faith in her eyes, And the tongue of triumphing Time for her righteousness witnesseth: Out of all darkness she comes with all sweet light on her tresses, Into the ear of the flesh she crieth quick speech of the spirit; And she bringeth the world from its travail and ache to its certain comfort, and blesses Them that endure and are broken and spent for them that inherit. A Song of Pride for England I Lo, the stark heavens are stirred: He cometh, plumed and spurred, To say the undaunted word, England! With high and haughty breath He hails the hordes beneath; This hath he for their teeth— “England again!” II King George in London Town, Sweareth our own's our own: Whose might shall pluck us down, England? Glories of slaughtered hosts, Splendours of English ghosts Beckon us from our coasts, England again! III Shrewd, on our world of seas, Waketh at dawn a breeze Singing bold melodies, England! Rose-red the long day falls, And the frore night wind calls To our proud Admirals, “England again!” IV Our Ensign flutters still On the unshaken hill; Our Bugle vaunteth shrill, England! What of the heathen draff? They are as burning chaff, Into their eyes we laugh, England again! V Death in his charnel-house, Rage and the Devil's spouse Hate—ruffle not your brows, England! Blood of your fathers' blood, Bred of great motherhood, Suckled on ancient good— “England again!” VI You shall be steel and ice, Stronger than love, and thrice Stricken for sacrifice, England! You shall bow to the flail, The hammer and the nail, And perish—and prevail, England again! VII While this our little land Hath a man-child to stand, He shall lift up his hand, England, To smite the accursèd bars: Out of the din of wars He shall shout to the stars, “England again!” VIII Troop you from field and fold, Market and shop of gold; Let the full tale be told, England! Time beats his pitiless drum, Fate's at her iron loom, For the New Earth, or Doom— England again! Sons I We have sent them forth To Christ's own rood; Their feet are white On the fields of blood, And they must slake Their young desire In wells of death And pits of fire. The red cock crows And the grey cock crows, And there is red On Flanders' snows; And sun-scorched sand And thirsty clay Drink a red spilth By Suvla Bay. And where Azizeah's Turrets gleam, And Tigris glitters, Like a dream, Through nights of scent And tinkling sounds, Sleep rose-white dead With rose-red wounds. II I saw the Shadow Count the fair Sum of his takings; Them that were Children in years When they were sped, And now are mighty Being dead. Like galaxies Of stars, they shone In the great places They have won; He sets them there, No sting hath he, And his is not The Victory. And whom he spared I saw return, Ambassadors From his brave bourne— Strong with the wisdom Of the Wars, Bright from the camps Of Conquerors. Unto the End Though the rivers of crystal run blood till the seas are blood, And the lands which were for proud harvests gape livid with death; And the goodness we had of the days is emptied for ever of good, And for ever the balm of the silver night faileth and perisheth; And though from the womb our sons know only to rage and kill, And our daughters forget that a bride is wed not for widow but wife; And War, which the wise of their wisdom accounted the chiefest ill, Boasteth itself for the glory and blessing and purport of life; Yea, though these things were established for ever—how should we quail, Or falter, or doubt that the sheer, stark soul of us shall prevail? We are done with the laughter and solace, the softness, the bloom, The clusters and sheaves of content, the honey and milk; We are gone from the beautiful places unto the brinks of doom, Where that is sharp which was sweet and that is steel which was silk, And that is woe which was flesh, and hurt which was delight, And the fairest and kindest love must sort with a lurking hate, And the heart of pity be stone within her, and wrong be but right, And our very prayers are for power to punish and desolate; Yea, stript to the spirit we stand, naked and very sure Of naught but the spirit, which, if it triumph not, yet shall endure. Post Prœlium [Jutland] I Lovely, and mightily-thewed Mother of this great brood, Lo, the beatitude Falls on thee like a flood, And folds thee where thou'rt stood Fronting the destinies With comfortable eyes. II Now knowest thou the rose Which to the sweet air blows In thy fair garden-close, And thine own lark that throws Down music as he goes Vaunting to heaven of thee, Are not for the enemy. III Now knowest thou the maid Of her young joy unstayed, And matrons who have said Most secret prayers, afraid To tell themselves they prayed— In thy green land shall dwell Safe and inviolable. IV Woodland and russet farm, And hamlet, and the warm And goodly towns where swarm Thy populations, Harm Taketh not in her palm; And never will they know The tread of any foe. V For round thee is the sheer Might of the mariner Whom thou didst suckle and rear And give for the ships. No peer Hath he to drive and steer And fight till the last bells The steely citadels. VI Now knowest thou the deeps Of a verity thine; nor sleeps Nor fails the ward. Who leaps For what thy Amireld keeps, Soweth a wind, and reaps The whirlwind from thy guns, The lightning from thy sons. VII Blessèd art thou that sent These to be strawne and spent; And blessèd they that went, Singing with heart's content, Unto the sacrament; And blessèd they that mourn Whoso shall not return. Marching On I I heard the young lads singing In the still morning air, Gaily the notes came ringing Across the lilac'd square; They sang like happy children Who know not doubt or care, “As we go marching on.” And each one sloped a rifle And each one bore a pack; They had no grief to stifle, No tears to weep, alack; They were too blithe to question Which of them should come back, As they went marching on. II Oh, thou whose eyes are sorrow, And whose soul is sorrowing, Who knowest that each to-morrow A deeper woe may bring, And knowest that all the comfort Is the very littlest thing While they go marching on; These sons of thine seek glory, As the bridegroom seeks the bride, And who shall tell the story Of their triumph and their pride? Like lovers, for the love of thee They have lain them down and died; And they go marching on. III They march by field and city, By every road and way, A march which angels pity And none may stop or stay Till the last head is rested On the last crimson clay; So they go marching on! They march in the broad sunlight And by the lovers' moon, Into the flame and gun-light From morns and eves of June, And Death for their entrancèd feet Pipes an obsequious tune, And keeps them marching on. IV And mid the battle thunder, And in the fields of blood, They see the untarnished wonder, The healing, and the good Which passeth understanding And can not be understood; And they go marching on. They see the rose's brightness Made perfect and complete, Lilies and snows of whiteness, And wings of gold that beat For ever and for ever Before the Paraclete; And they go marching on. Sergeant Death Oh, Sergeant Death, I've served with you, And chanced my breath A time or two! I've seen brave men Turn green as sin, When you have coughed, “Fall in, fall in!” I've heard brave men With cold fear shout, When you have piped, “Fall out, fall out!” Where'er a lad Would do his part, 'Tis you that probes His inmost heart. Though all be stirred By drums a-roll, 'Tis you that finds The soldier soul, And takes him through The conqueror's drill, And helps him home, Or leaves him still. 'Tis you that puts In one parade Them that were anxious And afraid, And them that were Fed-up and sick, And them that begged You to be quick, And them that gave You laugh for laugh, And bitterer chaff For bitter chaff. . . . Oh, you are old, And fierce and wise, But there is goodness In your eyes. And still your health Goes round the tents— “The Father of The Regiments!” Kitchener If Death had questioned thee, “Soldier, where wouldst thou take The immitigable blow?” Thou hadst answered, “Let it be Where the battalions shake And break the entrenchèd foe.” Yet wert thou nobly starred And destined. Thou dost die On the grim English sea; Thou goest to the old tarred Great Captains, and shalt lie Pillowed with them eternally. And they shall stir from their rest Each in his lordly shroud, And say, “'Fore God, we have room, So are the deeps made proud; Behold the glory on his breast, Kitchener of Khartoum!” For Righteousness' Sake Man that is born of a woman— The creature of doom, Who lives that the Shadow may summon Men forth to the tomb; Who knoweth not wages or earning, Who sows not to reap, Whose labour and passion and yearning Must finish with sleep; Who catches in vain at the glory; Whose brightness is rust; Whose days are a breath and a story; Whose house is the dust; Who lies, if he vaunt him of merit, Whose tree bears no fruit, Who quenches the spark of the spirit With lusts of the brute; Yet—standeth erect to the fighting And whirlwind and flame, And squanders himself for the smiting Of Terror and Shame; Who gathereth his weakness and brings it Where furies move; And loves the world so that he flings it Away out of love; Even though he were fashioned to perish By ordinance grim, The Sons of the Morning would cherish Memories of him: Who owing a debt went and paid it, And kept with his blood The Earth for the Wisdom who made it And saw it was good. John Travers Cornwell “Boy (first class) John Travers Cornwell, of Chester, was mortally wounded early in the action. He nevertheless remained standing alone at a most exposed post quietly awaiting orders till the end of the action, with the gun's crew dead and wounded all round him.” —Admiral Beatty Mortally hurt, alone he stood, England, in thy great fortitude. While his spent shipmates round him lay He held on in thine ancient way— A stripling with the veteran eye For the hard front of destiny. Effacing Time shall not destroy The memory of this, thy boy. On his young head the glory falls, As on the lordliest admirals; Fate sets his name in honour grim And even Death is proud of him. Steel-True and Blade-Straight I Steel-true and blade-straight— There's your man! And soon or late He is England—all of her; All the Blood that makes her fair, All the Soul that makes her great, Steel-true and blade-straight. II Steel-true and blade-straight— Neither puffed out, nor elate, Neither glad, nor sad, nor sorry, Seeking neither grace nor glory, Steadfast at the battered gate— Steel-true and blade-straight. III Steel-true and blade-straight— Let the pillars of the State Wrangle to their hearts' content— His to fend and thrust and feint, His to watch and ward and wait, Steel-true and blade-straight. IV Steel-true and blade-straight— While we bawl and perorate, Big with “ifs” about our war— He, the undoubting conqueror, Knocks the nonsense out of Fate— Steel-true and blade-straight. Sursum I saw his dread plume gleaming, As he rode down the line, And cried like one a-dreaming “That man, and that, is mine!” They did not fail or falter Because his front so shone; His horse's golden halter With star-dust thick was sown. They followed him like seigneurs, Proud both of mien and mind— Colonels and old campaigners And bits of lads new-joined. A glittering way he showed them Beyond the dim outpost, And in his tents bestowed them— White as the Holy Ghost. And, by the clear watch-fires, They talk with conquerors, And have their hearts' desires, And praise the honest wars. And each of them in raiment Of honour goeth drest, And hath his fee and payment, And glory on his breast. O woman, that sit'st weeping— Close, like the stricken dove,— He is in goodly keeping, The soldier thou didst love! The Full Share “I take my full share of responsibility for the initiation of that operation—my full share. . . . I do not propose to adopt the attitude of a white-sheeted penitent, with a couple of candles, one in each hand, doing penance and asking for absolution.” —Mr. Asquith. I Do not expect from me (Whom you have set In this authority) Defence, apology, Excuse or plea, Or even a regret: No sheeted penitent Am I, To stand Candle in hand And cry That I may be forgiven, Absolved or shriven, For what is spilt and spent. All that has happened so Is so. I lay it bare; Admission I make: The wisest of us err, The best plans go awry; Perhaps we blundered sore; But I would have you know No one is more Responsible than I, And of the accountability I take My share—and my full share! II In far Gallipoli Where Achi frowns to the sea, And wild war-fires are set; Stark to the Eastern moon, There lies, Huddled in the last agonies, Beside his shattered gun, A new-slain English boy: And his dead eyes Hint not apologies, Excuses or regret, Neither dismay nor joy; No candles at his head Nor sheet nor shroud has he, And by his blood-soaked bed No shriving words are said. It is a woman's son— The child she bare In England free and fair: Following the English drum Hitherward is he come, So to annul And break Himself for England's sake— He, too, hath taken his share, And taken it in full. III Lord of the Mysteries, Who on the shining air Launchest despair, And black, by rose and vine, Spillest the battle-line; This is the Bread, and this The perfumed Wine: No period dost Thou set Unto our dole and fret, Which, being of Thee, are Thine; Yet, if we yield our breath To death, Or keep in strife This fripperied fardel life, Help each of us to bear His share—and his full share! Killed Lieutenant Keen was “great,” and yet He would look over the parapet; And something smacked him in the head, And he lay down as dead as dead. He sluttered down, all proud and grim, And we set to and buried him; All night he lay and took his rest With lumps of Flanders on his breast. All day he lay in Flanders ground And rested, rested, good and sound; But when the dog-star glittered clear He calls, “By Jove, it's dark down here!” “Sergeant, ain't I for rounds?” sings he, “And where's the bally Company?” And he was answered, with respect, “Here, sir—all present and correct!” And—sure as I'm a man—at night He comes along the trench, as white And cheerful as the blessèd saints, To see if there was “no complaints.” They cannot quieten that boy's ghost, He'll have no truck with no “Last Post,” They mark him “Killed,” but you may swear He's with us, be it foul or fair. He goes before us like young fire, A soldier of his soul's desire; Through the hell-reek that smothers us, He fathers us and mothers us. When we have pushed the German swine Across the pretty river Rhine, Maybe he'll bide where he was spent And lie down happy and content. A Chant of Affection And so you hate us! You Hate England—hate, hate, hate! A bestial brewage, racked Out of the pits and holes Of foulness and deceit, Riots in your unclean veins; You burn, you rage, you choke You spit and splutter hate For England! . . . To the Russ, Battering your Eastern doors, You have a mind to turn The blubbered other cheek; The Gaul—your sweet old friend And crony of your love— For him, dear soul, white flags, Garlands and pretty lures, Doves, promises, desire To load him with the half Of that you filched away: For Belgia, “bleeding hearts,” Laments, regrets, “mild rule,” Cheap headstones for her sons, And for her daughters You— That they may suage your lusts And, by the fireless hearths You have made desolate, Be snugly brought to bed Of further Attilas And blonde Barabbases— Lieges and “gun fodder” For the top-heavy Dolt Whom ye call Kaiser and Lord. . . . Yea, holy are your eyes And filled with kindly beams For these and all the world: On Turk and Pole and Boer, Bulgar, American, You smile your panderous smile— But for the English—Hate! And you will rend our Throat, And you will bite our Heel, And you will stamp us down: You put an oath on bronze (Not paper this time—bronze! Which is not easily blown On winds of treachery!) You have made an oath of bronze, An oath no wind may shake, An oath for your sons and their sons One foe and one alone— ENGLAND! For England hate! And hate and hate and hate! How shall we hate you back We who are England; we Whose bugles round the world Blow to the punctual dawns And fail not; whose great ships Traverse the seventy seas And always are at home; Who are too big, for hate, Too careless and too fine, Too tempered and too proud— How shall we hate you back? For when you see us whole Our strength is an honest strength And based on what we love; And these be two things we love: Honour, and our fair land— Honour which is the crown And jewel and lamp and light Of them that are not clods; And our fair English land Peopled with forthright men Who make no talk of God, But fear Him in their hearts, And fear nor hate, nor death Nor the King's enemies;— A land of blunt, brave men, And blessed with memories Of old and high renown; Old Captains who beat forth In lofty ships of war, Tawny and tarred and proud, Old Admirals, who sleep Safe in the ancient deeps, And dream for England still: Oh, you shall stamp us down When all the seas are red With the good English blood, And all the beaches white With decent English bones, And when our pleasant fields Are hillocked with carrion flesh That cries and cries to heaven Of coward Englishmen, And the white Yorkshire rose Blushes for shame of us, And her red sister-rose Blanches for shame of us, Then shall you stamp us down, Then shall you suck the blood Out of the English throats, And tack this Isle of ours On to your German wastes! O haters, fools and blind Go home and make dolls' eyes, And silly little clocks, And plaisters for our gout, Wimples and crisping-pins! For now the outraged stars Have seen enough of you, The silver moons are sick That ye still blot the earth; From icy, hidden peaks And far-off fastnesses, From chambers of the South And in the unconquerable heart Of England, ware and wake, The tempest gathers up That shall be flails for you, And break you in your place And scatter you like straw; Instead of “Hate, hate, hate,” You shall cry “Doom, doom, doom,” And you shall wail and mourn, With none to comfort you But sprites of murdered babes, And ghosts of women raped, And wraiths of great slain men. The Riddle Through a glass darkly I can see Slaves, in whose blood ran liberty; Creatures of anguish, fear and wrong, Abject of eye, furtive of tongue; Whose joy hath taken wings and flown, Whose strength no longer is their own; Whose high tower toppled to the dust, Whose silk and steel are moth and rust; Whose name is water and shall be A byword and a mockery; Who eat the portion of the thrall, Whose drink is vinegar and gall; Whose flesh doth suffer whip and rope, Whose children's children may not hope; Upon whose fetters chuckling Fate Hath set her scornful mark “Too late.” And on whose brows that fronted God The leering Beast writes “Ichabod.” Read you the riddle: who are these So naked to their enemies— And so possessed of their old phlegm That one shall safely spit on them? I will not tell you who they are; It is enough—They lost the war. A Rhyme of Gaffer D? I know the old chap very well, He called on us when I was young— They sang a hymn and tolled a bell, “Friend after friend departs,” they sung. He took my father somewhat quick, He took my brother from his play, He took my dog (a dirty trick— Though he's the Gaffer, anyway). After—I didn't mind of 'im A-cuttin' up his grisly capers, For years and years, although I'd seem To read about 'im in the papers. When war broke out, I saw the bills, What says, “Your King and Country Need You,” My 'eart with Rule Britannia fills An' whispers, “Go where glory leads you.” But though I loved the 'Uns a treat, An' would have 'listed brisk an' 'earty, I always seemed to get cold feet A-thinkin' of that same Old Party. Till—well, at last, it had to be, My girl, she says, “You'll make me proud!” “Wot about 'im?” says I. Says she, “Sign up, my lad, an' 'im be blowed!” An' so I signed and so I joined, An' learnt my facin's an' my drillin', An' how to wash my ears behind, An' always be alert an' willin'. An' how to do things at the word, An' stamp when 'alted or “attention”-ed, An' all the time I never heard The Old Chap's name so much as mentioned. Our little lot, they say, is “it,” And not a bunch to stick at trifles, In fact for 'ficiency an' grit We're next door to the Artists' Rifles. An' yet, my friends, twixt you an' me, Despite the bluff they feed the boys on, The Reg'ment don't like Gaffer D? An', reely, 'ates 'im worse than poison. He is the Major's constant dread, The fly in the Lieutenant's ointment, Even the Colonel, so 'tis said, Will meet him only by appointment. Oh, he's a wash-out, that Old Gent! If 'tweren't for him, so 'elp me never, We'd all of us be well content, To fight for 'arth and 'ome for ever! You should ha' seen 'im t'other day, A-beckonin' us across the trenches— The very corporils knelt to pray, An' look at pictures of their wenches! We did our bit—oh yes, we did, An' he was in his element— He took a toll which can't be hid Until the big new draft is sent. But still I thank my stars, I does, ('Appy am I it should be so) That though he wasn't kind to us He weren't no kinder to the foe. . . . You won't get rid of that Old Card, Leastways till you've got rid of sin,— So here's his 'ealth, say I—the Hard Old Chap that spoils the soldierin'; The Chap that mocks at mothers' prayers, And loves to widow the young bride; Yet hurteth only whom he spares, And makes the rest most satisfied. The Ass The enemy without—and he within! You meet him on the stairs of your high tower All simpers. At his nose he hath a flower, Upon his tongue cheap honey; and his chin Waggeth for ever. If we lose or win— Please don't talk war! The witty luncheon hour, The joyous week-end! Good souls, who could sour So blithe a spirit, or prick so sleek a skin? Cheerfullest wight! It is his constant whim To beam on Fate. All that he asks is love, A salad, a glass of wine, music that charms, A book, a friend, and “the blue sky above”— And underneath, the everlasting arms Of them that toil and groan and bleed for him. The Diners “They died content,” he said, And bent a well-groomed head Sweetly above the soup: “Ah, splendid lads!” he sighed, “And . . . (Waiter!) . . . think!—they died Content! . . . (the cantaloup Wasn't quite ripe enough). Real top-hole lads and tough!— A lesson for those swine!— (Yes, yes—uncork the wine!) “Top-hole, I tell you!—(pish, I'm not so keen on fish!— Don't matter—eat it, dear)— Beat us? Good Lord! No fear!— With lads like that about! (Well, well—they call it trout!) Where can you match 'em? (Oh— Pâtés of riz de veau!) “All heroes!—(Gad—that's Jones— Wolfing his damned grilled bones— Pardon—but really—well— Grilled bones for dinner! . . . “Pell-Mell”? No, darling, let us go And see the other show)— Our chaps are simply ‘it’!— (Not just the weeniest bit? The waiting here's absurd: When will they bring the bird?) “They died content! . . . (Don't look— There's Mumble and the duke And Mrs. M.—Of course She does laugh like a horse!)— They died like gentlemen! (Chicken? No—ancient hen!— But still the salad's good)— My God—the British blood! “You very nearly kissed That fearful Casualty List?— Ah, precious, you've a heart!— (What excellent strawberry tart!)— Yes, Haig 's O.K., you bet He'll smother 'em—and yet There must be sacrifice!— (I shouldn't risk the ice!) “(Coffee for two—no cream!) It all seems like a dream: Still, we shall win right through, As we were bound to do. . . . They died content!—(Why, sure!— Did-ums want its liqueur? . . . And, waiter—that cigar! And, waiter—call the car!— And, waiter—bring the bill!— These ‘neutrals’ make me ill!)” July 1, 1916 We were unprepared, We were most unwise; We have been like that For centuries— But we've taught ourselves a thing or two, And we're muddling through. Twenty-three months! Twenty-three Men! Oh, the muddle And muddle again!— One can't deny it, because it's true— But we're muddling through. Shells and soldiers, Piles and files;— The roar goes up On seventy miles: We know now what we always knew— We shall muddle through! Oh, Banner of ours That shines in the wars, Oh, excellent bars Red, white, and blue, With glory in every fold of you— We shall muddle through! To the Kaiser [With a Child's Drum] He was three years old, a mirthful, tumbling wight, To see your cohorts pass, he stood at stare, Unwitting, but pleased; and out of his delight He laughed you forth a Vive l'Angleterre. Boiled the insulted blood in the high veins Of the most puissant and invincible (Whose fathers, spat upon, remarked “It rains!”): Your soldier fired—rebellious innocence fell. Wherefore we send you, Conqueror, a child's drum, And you shall beat upon it as you go Bloodily stalking to your crazy doom— The plaything of your murdered baby foe. 1912 [First published in 1910] O Fair and Fair and Fierce, Tigress mother of ours, Beautiful-browed, deep-thewed Passionate mother of ours, Hearken! The drums of doom Are beaten at the gate, And it is meet that THOU, Whose breasts are ice and steel, Whose heart is all a fire, Should show us frightened eyes, And lips becomingly blenched; So say the very wise. For when the thrones were made Thine, the throne of the thrones, Was set in the yeasty seas: Built and bastioned and braced, A tower of brass, a rock, An adamant pyramid, A strength unshakeable; And to thy hands were given Power and dominion Wherever water is salt, Wherever a shipboy sings, Wherever ships may ride; So that the seas of the world Though they be seventy times seven, Are English seas, and thine; Whether it be the harsh And bitter seas of the north, Flurried by little winds, And pushed by piping gales Against the winking stars; Or the still blue middle seas; Or where the daffodil moon Slips down an amethyst sky To walk with silver feet On the Southern, soft lagoons, It is the English sea. . . . Who is this that waits By the weary Baltic shore, By the kneeling Baltic shore, With shrouded arm and hand, And a hand whereon there gleams A glove of impudent mail? Behind him stretch afar The pleasant, placid spas, Fattened with English aches; And the four-three factories, And the reek of the dumper's fires, And the pretty river Rhine (Which owes so much to Cooks), And rows, and rows, and rows Of flat-head soldier men, And the works of Schichau and Krupp, And for a sign in the blue, The tender himmelblau, The good, grey Count's balloons! Do you know this singular Lord, This humorous, hearty Prince, Whose cry is “Peace, Peace, Peace,” Abroad, and at home “War, War”; Who preaches through the day With olive twigs in his hair, And rises in the night To fan the secret forge; Who says, “Why should we fight? Prithee, why should we fight? What cause have we to fight? Are we not friends, please God, And Customers? . . . My glass Is raised to you and Peace Hurra, Hurra, Hurra!” Who says again, “My arms Must flourish on the seas, My arms and mine alone If you wish a place in the sun; As for the one in our path The one whom we all so love, By nineteen hundred and twelve I shall be ready for HER!! I have promised you your Day— Hurra, Hurra, Hurra!” It is nineteen hundred and ten And the Seas are English seas, They will be English seas Till they shall give up Drake And the thousand English hearts Which have made rich the depths: Until they shall be rolled Together like a scroll They shall be English seas. We sleep sound in our beds; We fear no fist of mail; We fear no withered arm; We are not afraid of Krupp Nor yet of Blohm and Voss. We wish you the Devil's joy Of all you have hidden and built; It is nineteen hundred and ten. We have simple words for you: In the English history books There is Eighteen Hundred and Five; We say to you when you pray, Thank Heaven if we do not write In the English history books With beautiful German blood Nineteen Hundred and Twelve. Towards the Reckoning With tongue of oil and breath of myrrh They bid us turn the other cheek, And mark the blessing for the meek, The mourner and the peacemaker. They counsel, “Love your enemies; Do good to them who bear you hate; Agree thou quickly!” and they prate Of being, with the great wisdom, wise. “Of Eye for Eye and Tooth for Tooth None righteously exacts the debt; It is forbidden!” they say—and yet They publish only half the truth. And by their speech the grinning Host Which hath Blasphemed takes lease to live. . . . Harden our hearts, lest we forgive The Sin against the Holy Ghost! Verdun “One shall be taken and the other left”— 'Tis so with men, and even so with forts; One falls, another stands—the strong cohorts Beat vainly on it in rage of divers sorts— One shall be taken and the other left. One shall be taken and the other left— Behold the Bride that singeth through the gloom, And waiteth still with scorn the German groom, And fears not to be given away by Doom!— One shall be taken and the other left. One shall be taken and the other left— O eyes of Hell and fronts of bloody brass, France, by her Lilies, sweareth ye may not pass Unto her—though the bar were brittlest glass!— One shall be taken and the other left. The Dublin Rising I Our right—and your old wrongs. With men's and angels' tongues We did discourse. Alas— The tinkling cymbal and the sounding brass! We “ruled.” You mourned and planned. We had gifts to understand All knowledge, all dreams, all star-sad mystery; Mountains we moved, while you made prophecy. We doubted not. Your Eyes Were set on Paradise. Yet always, and most grievously, Both of us missed the “greatest” of “these three.” II Your fair dead—our fair dead. Now, by each fallen head And each rebuking wraith, Swear we another Faith. Your night of tears—our night. But, by the unquenchable Light Toward which, blindly, we grope, Behold, another Hope! Our agony—and yours. Yea, by the Passionate Hours And the Exceeding Bitter Cry, Do we still lack . . . the Charity! Wounded Back again! Back again! Out o' blood and mud and rain; Out o' gun-sound . . . God a'mighty! Out o' Blazes and home to “Blighty”!— Broke right up and full o' pain, But back again—back again! Back again! Back again! By an extry special train With the Red Cross on the panels— Snuggled in me nice new flannels— Like the blinkin' King o' Spain— Back again! Back again! Back again! Back again! Clapham Junction plain as plain!— Just as grimy, just as gloomy, Just as home-like, and as roomy— Dead on time—we can't complain— Back again! Back again! Back again! Back again! Waterloo and rows o' men Down the platform standing ready For to lift us quick and steady— Nurses smiling—“How's the pain?” Back again! Back again! Back again! Back again! London town and home again— Never knew how much they loved us,— In the ambulance they've shoved us— Nearly numbered with the slain But back again—back again! Come Young Lads First Sergeant went a-walking Wi' ribbons in his cap, “Ho-ho,” says he, “His Majesty Wants just another chap, An' as 'tis plain, for married men He no more cares a rap, Come young lads first!” Wherefore the bairn I suckled Goes now in khaki drest; So young is he, that he med be Still cosy from my breast; But he marches with his chin up An' his chest out, like the rest, Come young lads first! Old Squire says, “Oh yes, oh yes, 'Twill do him worlds of good”; An' parson says that losing bairns If rightly understood Is blessed, an' 'tis sweet, he says, For th' King to shed your blood— Come young lads first! “Abram,” he says, “gave Isaac, As writ in Holy Word, An' Mary broke the precious box At the feet of our dear Lord; So you must give your boy,” he says, “To carry England's sword, Come young lads first!” They speak you fair do gentlemen, But not more fair or free Than my young son, who's just the one His father used to be; And when I said he med get killed He angers up at me, “Come young lads first!” For he's no lad that hides his mind An' he's no lad that feigns; An' while he spoke my heart came back As easy of its pains As when his father courted me Along the scented lanes— Come young lads first! A woman has her love (it is Her glory and her crown) Which many waters cannot quench An' the great floods cannot drown; But men have that which passes love When they hear the bugles blown— Come young lads first! An' so the bairn I suckled Goes now in khaki drest, So young is he, that he med be Still cosy from my breast; An' he marches with his chin up An' his chest out, like the rest— Come young lads first! The Rhyme of the Beast Lo, the Beast that rioteth, Sick with hate and coveting— To the sons of men he saith, I will show you a new thing. This, the Earth, which was the Lord's, Prodigal of rose and vine, I will desolate with swords Till it own that it is mine. Every brow must bear my brand Every wrist must wear my steel, Every throat be for my hand, Every neck be for my heel. I will thrust into your souls Unnamed terrors and despairs— Populate the air with ghouls And the sea with murderers. While I prove that war is war, Saints shall mourn and angels weep, Star commiserate with star, Deep cry out to shuddering deep; Tigers marvel in their lust At the tale of blood and pain, Pity move the insensate dust, And the very stones complain. I will twist the tongue of Truth Till her speech be nought but lies, I will kill the faith of Youth, And the hope in Age's eyes. Not the altar, nor the tomb, Nor the Sufferer on the Tree, Nor the babe within the womb Shall be sacred unto me. I will rend and rage and cog, Rob and ravish till I die; I will be the Supreme Hog, And the world shall be my sty. Gaudeamus “Our whole High Seas Fleet, without any aid from coast batteries, has delivered a victorious blow against the most powerful navy in the world. . . . The great sea fight so eagerly expected on both sides in the North Sea for twenty-two months has been fought out.” —Tageblatt. This is your “victory”! We who brook no defeat, On any sea, Being of the old sea-mind, Smile the sea-smile, and find Our very losses sweet. Of your “victorious blow” We give you the full joy: Be glad! We know Our strengths majestical— Our every admiral, Our every sailor boy. Yet is it not “fought out”: Lick you your wounds, good friends, And shout and shout— You will not shake Nelson, or Hood, or Drake, Or the appointed ends. For Whom it may Concern Ye know that Freedom from her height Laughs on the world in Fate's despite: Here is her comfort set:— England is England yet. Ye know that all the fronts of War Shine with the effulgent English star; Ye know whose is the blood That baffled and withstood Old tyrants; and full well ye know There never can be shock or blow To hurt more than a reed The panoply of your breed. How shall you in such armour girt Palter behind a woman's skirt, Or that man's pledge, or this Man's broken promises? While the slipped flower of the race Comports him in the veteran's place— His shroud (oh, Fearlessness!) Worn like a wedding dress. You will not grieve those emulous dead Boy heritors of goodlihead, Who haply loved their lives Much as you love your wives. In the Train There's a soldier, By gad! Yes!— See her gi' me That there kiss?— All the people Crowdin' by: An' her a maid As shy as shy!— Kiss'd me fair An' plain an' free Before the blessed Company— Whisper'd when I bent my head— Mustn't tell you What she said! Little 'un, But very smart, Stands no higher Than my heart! An' that straight An' unafraid,— Like a corporal On parade! Smiles, an' loves you With her eyes: Steadies you, And keeps you wise: Learns you all There is to know: Makes you feel It's good to go! Women's funny— So they are! But who taught 'em About war? Where'd they learn Their bit of drill? Who is it took 'em Through the mill? And gave 'em grit Enough for ten, An' sense to share it With the men? An' made 'em so They'd rather die Than let a soldier See 'em cry? An' gives 'em strength And nerve and grace To look the postman In the face? Oh, don't forget it, Mother's son— They're soldiers, soldiers Every one! Soldiers loving Them that's gone, Soldiers, soldiers “Holding on”— Proudest Regiment Ever known,— Let us call 'em “The Lord's Own.” Then 1 The parson to the padre said, “Once, in a book, these words I read: ‘If any man take thy coat; why, go And offer him thy cloak also.’” 2 I heard the lump of shrapnel drone At midnight in the shatter'd bone: “Let us remember that sweet verse Which bids us bless who brings the curse.” 3 And from his grave one calleth clear: “When I come home again, my dear, And my head on your bosom lies, We will forgive our enemies.” Slain Dulce et decorum est pro patria mori You who are still and white And cold like stone; For whom the unfailing light Is spent and done; For whom no more the breath Of dawn, nor evenfall Nor Spring, nor love, nor death Matter at all; Who were so strong and young And brave and wise, And on the dark are flung With darkened eyes; Who roystered and caroused But yesterday, And now are dumbly housed In stranger clay; Who valiantly led, Who followed valiantly, Who knew no touch of dread Of that which was to be; Children that were as nought Ere ye were tried, How have ye dared and fought, Triumphed and died! Yea, it is very sweet And decorous The omnipotent Shade to meet And flatter thus. MISCELLANEOUS PIECES Mulier I saw a flake Of the burning lake Caught in an angel breath, And blown upon Until it shone Brighter than love and death Through the dark it sped Like a star that bled A-kindle; and I knew That heaven and hell, O, Miracle, Had made the soul of you. From the Chimney Corner When we are dead And newly burièd, The worm, 'tis said Out of a pity doth creep Unto the ear of our sleep, And with her little voice Singeth a note or so, As near 's she can like the lark, To help us in the dark: Saying, “Rejoice, rejoice, For all shall yet be well!” From Death who is terrible (Yet hath no sting), And from the grave Which bindeth us (Yet hath no victory), Physicians might not save Old parson. Thus, He lay Down in the churchyard clay; And I have heard folk say That on the second day The kind worm passeth that way And sidleth up to him, And doth her best to sing, Saying, “Be unafraid, 'Tis mortal lonesome here, Meanly thy bed is made, Thou lack'st both light and cheer And shalt, for many a year: Yet lift up th' heart—endure, For the reward is sure!”— ‘Um,” sniffs old parson, “two of a trade!” The Witling I An old poor rogue went down to the Ferry, Merry as merry. “Tho' some do die on the gallows tree, God send they dye a good colour!” quoth he. “For just as many years they'll be dead As who died snug i' the 'spital bed! “And Moll and Doll and the Pope of Rome La, la—each goeth the same way home! “And as for doleful dumps, why—drat 'em!— As Misery sang—‘Cheer up for Chatham!’” II “Boatman, thou tarriest,” he saith, “'Tes piercin' here by thy black staith; “And I ha' found nor crust nor apple Since yon loon got me by the thrapple. “Nor brandy-wine is brought to cheer me— A dead man hath small luck, I fear me. “Boatman, what meaneth thy ill look? Why burns the ripple thou hast strook? “Why is the hand thou touchest me with Unkinder than was that of Death?” The Little Old Knife With my little old Knife I killed the paramour; Her bosom was a soft flower, She had a girdle of vair And ruby combs in her hair: “Come hither,” calls she, “thou old wife,” Flirting her fan in the bower, “And pick up our kerchy,” calls she; “An 't please you, madam,” quod I— “And, madam . . . once only we die So here's good once for ye And everlasting rest— Both from my little old knife!” With my little old knife— Ahey! she looked and smiled Like a sleepy three-year child, And gaped, and drooped, and was dead; Only a trickle of red Slipt down her heavenly breast: “Thus endeth,” quod I, “a strife, An ache, a fragrance, a power, A shame, a wisdom, a mesh, A passion and rose of flesh, All finished at my hour And all with my little old knife!” Thames River of rivers, that dost lave the might And pomps and ships of England; if the white Dawns be upon thee, or thou goest dight In armour of the sun; or where at night With mirrored stars and lamps of chrysolite, Thou wooest this London to the ancient plight, Thou shalt be goodly for the English sight And proud till Time shall falter in his flight. Tiber, Euphrates, Tmolus from the height, Tigris and Nilus, streams of old delight, And Abbana and Pharphar which were bright For queens by swart Damascus—these invite Words from the dreamer and the Abderite; But thou art Thames—glorious in their despite. The Eagle They have him in a cage And little children run To offer him well-meant bits of bun, And very common people say, “My word! Ain't he a 'orrible bird!” And the smart, “How absurd! Poor, captive, draggled, downcast lord of the air!” Steadfast in his despair, He doth not rage; But with unconquerable eye And soul aflame to fly, Considereth the sun. Sigillum With thunder shod The hills be trod That the children of God Should quake at his nod; He had bolt and rod For angel and clod And he wrote on their foreheads, “Ichabod.” And in his eyes Was enterprise Still to devise Smooth subtleties And perjuries For the King of Flies; And goodness and truth were his enemies. We toil and spin, Held by the gin And web of sin He catcheth us in— This prance, this grin With the felon chin— This Heads-you-lose-and-tails-I-win! Cromwell “The damned Psalm-singing old humbug” He had the heart of love, The heart of love and steel, The unshaken English heart That can be merciless, That can be merciful. He looked upon the State And saw that it was foul. “It shall be cleansed,” he said, “Straightway it shall be cleansed: Yea, even with tears and blood!” The People loved him not, The Princes mocked at him; With Sword and Book he strode Among them like a tower; “I am your Lord,” he said. He woke the people's strength To know itself and fear No other strengths that were; For Princes of all time He read the lesson out. For England hath he set The way, the immutable plan, The rule of Empery: “If ye would rule abroad Be fitly ruled at home.” To the Little Muse Out of the light of the age, An age of superior things, I call unabashed unto thee O little Muse of the Valley. Scorn for the simple pipe, The trivial, trite tune That a man may make in his youth, Is the fashion with all the world; A fashion dear to the cheap Young supercilious scribe, Also to wits and wags And every honest fool. So that thy numerous sons, Sired by the windy Spring, Bristle, or blush, or blench At a hint of their parentage. But little Muse of ours, They err who have shame in thee And grievously do they err Who bandy thy name when they scoff. For comely art thou, and wise And affluent of heart; White are thy feet by the brooks And pleasant thy voice in the vines. Thy Sister, the beautiful-brow'd Calm friend of them that endure, Loveth thee from her heights, And wherefore not we, who are naught? Audrey Audrey knoweth naught of books, Naught to captivate the wise; But the soul of goodness looks Through the quiet of her eyes. She can bake and she can knit, Cunningly she wields the broom, All her pleasure is to sit In a neatly order'd room. . . . Touchstone, shaping a career, Shines at each exclusive house: “Such a clever man, my dear, Tied to—just ‘a country mouse’! “Married ere he dream'd of us, Ere he knew what gifts he had— Strange that Fate should yoke him thus, And very, very, very sad!” Touchstone (let them mark it well), When the social round is trod, Bored by dame and demoiselle, Goes home softly, thanking God. The Yeoman Across the counties came the sound Of war-drums that his fathers knew; He had no heart for horse or hound, He said, “Am I not English too?” All the old ardours in his blood Leapt like the flame from smitten steel, And, to himself revealed, he stood A buttress of the common weal. So that if cities give their pride To strengthen England's righteous arm, Men, too, are bred by countryside And quiet grange and folded farm. 1899 The Finer Spirit I I saw the painted worlds go by, And wonder'd what great good could lie Beneath that dreadful pageantry. What lamp of excellent brimming light Hath kept the immemorial night, And watches on, in Time's despite? What soul of saving sweetness lends The affable touch to things, and blends That which begins and that which ends? II And one, whose look shone kindness, ran And fetch'd his sheaf of charts—the plan “Mark'd out,” he said, “by God for Man. “Look thou! Thus far, and thus, the clear Seas sparkle; thou mayst pray, and steer Thy craft with knowledge here, and here; “But by the vasty marges loom God's well-set darknesses; the womb Bears not the man that skills this gloom.” III Another, wisely, “We are sure Of consciousness and some small store Of facts, as ‘two and two make four.’ “So nerved and lamp'd may Reason spell The systems out, and learn to tell The purport of the inmost cell; “But ever as she goes, she sees In new and old simplicities The old, invincible mysteries.” IV Also another, “Wine and wheat And oil have we, and liberal heat Of faithful suns; our pulses beat “With warmth and warm affections—Love The chief—and like a blessèd dove Joy winnows round us as we move; “And solace cometh for the stroke And strength to render dear the yoke— These are enough for honest folk.” V Yet who, that waits for happier skies, Or searches with assiduous eyes, Or dreams among the butterflies, Hath never felt the effulgence full From off the face of things, and all The sweetness sicken into gall? Hath never heard the implacable blast Crying afar through void and vast, And stood up shuddering and aghast? VI Yon planet, set out lustrously Upon the tinted dawn, may be Some dull immutable agony, Heavy with hideousness, and fell And terrible tribes that quake and yell For ever on the slags of hell; Creatures to whom death is a vain Vague legend of the prime, ere pain Bore down and smote them heart and brain. VII And this dear earth of green and grey And gold and blue—our broad highway And pleasant inn whereat we stay As travellers lighted luckily On goodly cheer and company And chambers lavendered—may be Out of the placid ages come With all its load of life and bloom Jump to the verge of some wild doom. VIII She called to me across the flood Of finish'd years, “Believe thy blood Which runs a living faith in good!” She called to me out of the still And molten noon, “Believe thy will Which, having force, would banish ill!” She called to me out of the day Next to be born, “Believe the clay Which sends up goodness from decay! IX “Here is the earnest to make whole The parted circlet of the soul, To crown thy mirth and star thy dole; “Here is the essence that hath kept The centuries sweet, and raced and leapt In veins that wither'd, eyes that wept; “Here is the jewel for the brow The beam to set the light aglow And to enrose the pinnacled snow. X “I am the crimson of the rose, The fair quick flame the crocus shows, The spice that with the blossom goes, “The witchery of the thrush's tune, The surge of March, the flash of June, The marvel of the reapers' moon, “And where the winter aches in white And mists, I haunt the doubtful light While dwindling suns loom red and bright; XI “I am the strength of all the dead, The wisdom and the goodlihead And pith of what they did and said; “I am the beauty that hath stood Bodied, like a beautitude In soft, calamitous womanhood “From the beginning; and the Rest Of Saints am I, and all the blest Rapture of bosoms babes have press'd; XII “And Man, the spirit and the dust The god that wears the chains, and must Be still the creature, and still trust “He is not wholly fool and slave, And live half angel and half knave To sup with Death and fat the grave; “Man that is nothing, yet divine Sifting the creeds for one sure sign Hath sureness in a look of mine!” Materiel Since wheels for the breaking of bone And hooks for the tearing of flesh, And pully and rack And screws to crack Sinew and joint are forgone; Shall Torture fail of her own And lose the admirèd moan Of thrice-slain agony, Or miss from her ancient mesh The victim fair and fresh? Nay, by the Rood, not she! Ablaze with glittering skill, On floors of anguish, still Plieth she pincer and bowl, And she hath profuse prey; And all night and all day, Though bodies go safe and whole, She thanks God for the soul. Strike Of trivial tide and chance, And dribs of circumstance, Flourish and feint and threat, Swords that are never wet, Daggers which only scratch, Springes not made to catch, Faleshood none uttereth, Mumblings of quick apology For prettily hinted infamy, And dirty hands in nice clean genteel gloves, Sick was he unto death. Dear knows, He hath seen his share Of fribbles and fret And seeming overthrows; Hence sayeth he this prayer To men and destiny: Let me be stricken fair With infallacious blows. Iris and the Water-Lilies All hidden like a jewel 'mid great hills There lies a clear-eyed lake, girt round with shade Of willow and green hazel, and behind, Forests of oak and fir stretch out and climb Unto the topmost sunshine of the heights. Here at the narrower end, a narrow arm Runs deep into the shadows of the wood, Losing itself in reedy lonesomeness; Dark wilding weeds, lovers of glamour, creep Along its shallow edges, and, in mid-stream Like faery shallops waiting for moonrise, A fleet of pallid water-lilies sleeps. At daybreak, when the lake was flushed and strewn With red, and gold, and purple; and the wood Shimmer'd with opal tintings, hither came The wind-footed Iris—Juno's messenger— Bound on her Autumn task to kill the bloom; Upon her brow duskily beat and throbbed Three lambent starlets, and her filmy hair Stream'd in a shining tangle after her. Like starshine from a star, ethereally, Or as some sweet soul drifting in bliss, she slid Down the hushed dawn to where those lilies were; And seeing them in their white loveliness, Cold, pallid, pure, she hovered over them, And smiled upon them, as a mother smiles Upon her sleeping children. Then the thought That she must slay them, even as the rest, Shot through her being like sharp agony, And lifting up her voice in golden speech, She cried upon the queen of gods and men: “O Juno, in thy heaven, Give ear and pity me; Lo, my young heart is riven With this I do for Thee, Wherefore I pray a respite from my task. “In valleys where the sun Had pitched his golden tent, As by their beauty won And bound to sloth, he meant To rest himself from travel evermore; “Vales where the white dove's wing Smote ever golden airs, And she that doth so sing Mounting her sunny stairs Met neither cloud nor shadow all the way; “Over the quiet top Of a thyme-laden hill, Where drowsy bees did drop Into cool cups, to fill Their pouches, or to loiter out the hours; “Where upward from the corn The reapers' voices rang, And on the airs were borne Light songs the maidens sang In the hill-vineyards as the hours slipt past— “Thither I went to tear The glory from men's sight And over all that's fair Have cast the seed of blight; And this my deed shall bring me naught but pain. “For the sweet days will pass, The sun will leave his camp, The dead leaves rot i' the grass, The airs wax chill and damp, The white dove shiver and the lark grow dumb; “And they that reaped the corn And laughed among the vines, Shall crouch themselves forlorn, Soon as the frostwork shines And wish the sun-time were come back again. “Therefore, I pray thee, give These lilies of the lake, Yet further days to live, So that the world may make Some solace of them when all else is dead. “And if thou wilt not—why I break my faith with thee! These are not meet to die Being so fair to see, And they shall live for any touch of mine!” Straightway the sun was darkly cast in clouds The gloom brought rain and lightning, and a wind Sprang up and wandered wailing round the woods; The fisher at the far end of the lake Heard troubled cries, toss'd on the fretful air, And putting forth, and coming to the arm, he saw One hovering like a glory round the lilies; And as he looked the rain was past and done, And seven slant sunbeams piercing thro' the shade, Beat on her form, which, like a richer light, Passed into them, and flushed them with soft hues, Rose-blush, rare azure, and all fairy tints; So that a shaft of painted mist arose From where she had been; and as he turned away, Behold! a rainbow stretched across the lake. Brandenburg Old duke, with the long white beard, Of what woe art thou afeared? What unplumbed and deathly wound Gapes unto thine eyes profound? What disastrous blaze of wing Smoulders in thy ruby ring? From thy cup gleams what disgrace From they napkin what dismays? Like a dreamer answereth he “It is one shall follow me, “Without virtue, without lust, A bowellessness, a painted dust “Perk'd up in our powerful seats For a race of liars and cheats, “Whom he knoweth not to contemn— Cozening, and not ruling them!” To John Bunyan John, it was sweet of thee to be a tinker, For poor men need a trade; And of all trades that picture well with art, John— Intuitive, innocent art, John— It is the tinker's. And it was sweet of thee to go to gaol, John, Even unto Bedford Gaol: Why may not all of us forthwith repair, John, To some such sunless fastness, And dream large dreams, John? And sweet it was of thee to make and write, John, A sweet and decent book Which hath an honest savour, like good bread, John, And keeps the general palate; though their fictions Do come, and go, John. Ah! who would not, to author such another, Take thy extremity, Thy petty craft; thy “gross, implacable” doctrine; Yea, even a threadbare “treatise-dowered” spouse, John, And thank his stars, John? Epitaph If I should ever be in England's thought After I die, Say, “There were many things he might have bought And did not buy. “Unhonoured by his fellows he grew old And trod the path to hell, But there were many things he might have sold And did not sell.” Christmas The Baby of Bethlehem Lay in a manger, And the Wise Men and the Kings came To give him gold and frankincense And myrrh; And Mary, his mother, bent over him, And he had a star for his own, Which shone white and fair in the East. And they have called his name The Prince of Peace; And in his name Men have cast out devils, And handled serpents, And ruled the people, And builded glories and greatness, And died very comfortably. And you of Babylon Shall consider Him now Stark, where He stands— The Man of Sorrows And Acquainted with Grief, The Light of the World— Shivering outside the halls Wherein you make feasts for Him. The Christmas Tree Far off in yon blue Palestine His star, His star, doth tremble and shine. O little Baby fair to see, Bless these branches for Thy tree, And these twinkling lights whose flame Is spent to glorify Thy Name, And these children, whose bright eyes Are a perpetual sacrifice! Graves in France Once there was a little moon That look'd down on Golgotha And three crosses rangèd there And the burdens which they bare: Naught might hurt or trouble her, Wise as wise and fair as fair. O thou silver little moon, Miles and miles of Golgotha Now are spread to thy still stare: And the myriad crosses there Glimmer on the evening air, Wise as wise and fair as fair. The Lonely Man For him There were no Springs, No tender green, no blue, nor living gold, No rose of holy white, No blessèd rose of red, No glory of love or death. The foolish and the faint Set many marks on him; The foolish and the faint Were easy, and they laughed. The Fool said, “Here is one Less than myself”; The Faint said, “Here is one Fainter than I; Wherefore lay on, And may the Lord be praised!” So that his bread was dust, And his drink bitterness. And his delight went past him, And he died Cheated, and bowed, and dumb. And when the Worlds, That are as sand and sand Upon the winds of Time, Dropp'd and were quiet, I looked athwart the broken battlement And saw his grey soul beating up the dawn The Admiring Admirer A daw that went in feathers not his own Sought out the opulent bird he had them from, And cried, “Behold, the plumage thou hast strown To glory come!” Whereon the other, “That thou shouldst aspire So stuck with wastage keeps thee in our love; They steal Jove's thunder and they steal his fire Yet hurt, not Jove.” Recipe Chidden still murmurs, Slapped and Rapped complain, Hurt, with a thousand tongues, Whines out his pain. This is the learning Unto which we come: Properly walloped Is for ever dumb. In Harness [After W. E. Henley] At the sultry hour of midnight, When we keep the door propped open For the little boys with “flimsy” I can hear our presses whirring. Whirling, whirring, in a rhythm, Steady, rational, persistent; Churning out the first edition, To illuminate the counties. Like the noise of many waters Broken on a weir of tea-trays, Is the sound—a choppy droning: And it rather soothes one's heart-strings. Yet, at times, I can't help thinking How much of my life goes whirring, Whirling, whirring, whir, whir, whirring With the whirring of those presses. The Good Conceit [After W. E. Henley] Out of the cloud that covers me And blots the stars and seldom lifts, I thank whatever gods may be For my indubitable gifts. Under the whip, upon the setts, Men drive me many a galling mile; My stock of editors' regrets Would fill a barrow, but—I smile. Fast by this trade of wind and wit I mean to hold till life be done, And every year I stay in it Finds, and shall find me, tugging on. It matters not how stiff and sheer The climb—how difficult the sum, I am the man they've got to hear! I am the man that's bound to come! July 1899 October 21 Dreams that shine for England still Like a city on a hill— Glory snatch'd from old dead woe, Names of battles long ago! Yea, with panoply of gold, Pomps and glitterings manifold, Shine they forth like happy stars On the midnight of the wars. Dreams that heal the banner's rents, Dreams that fire the regiments, Dreams that are for English eyes Smoke of the sweet sacrifice. Age-old tales of Chivalry Clearing still its place to die, Sturdy pikes, stout halberdiers Conquering through the misty years. Great grey galleons, saucy sloops, Proud-eyed men on haughty poops— One of them, with breast ablaze, Dies for England all her days! Thou 'Tis thine to give, And thine to scorn; So shalt thou live And reign and mourn. When all is done Fate worketh thee no ill, Leaving thee still Thy skill, Thy furious wise will, And they heart of stone. The End</field>
   </doc>
</add>