<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Mallock, W. H., (William Hurrell), 1849-1923</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Mallock, W. H., (William Hurrell), 1849-1923</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">mallock w h william hurrell 1849 1923</field>
      <field name="author_text">Mallock, W. H., (William Hurrell), 1849-1923</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1870's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.0569.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">1871</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466291</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Newdigate Prize Poem ; The Isthmus of Suez: Recited In the Theatre, Oxford, June 14, 1871, by William Hurrell Mallock</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Newdigate Prize Poem ; The Isthmus of Suez: Recited In the Theatre, Oxford, June 14, 1871, by William Hurrell Mallock</field>
      <field name="title_facet">newdigate prize poem</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">newdigate prize poem</field>
      <field name="title_text">Newdigate Prize Poem ; The Isthmus of Suez: Recited In the Theatre, Oxford, June 14, 1871, by William Hurrell Mallock</field>
      <field name="year_display">1871</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1871</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1871</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466291&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466291&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Mallock, W. H., (William Hurrell), 1849-1923&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;mallock w h william hurrell 1849 1923&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Newdigate Prize Poem ; The Isthmus of Suez: Recited In the Theatre, Oxford, June 14, 1871, by William Hurrell Mallock&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;newdigate prize poem&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1871&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1871&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Mallock, W. H., (William Hurrell)&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1849&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1923&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Newdigate Prize Poem&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;The Isthmus of Suez: Recited In the Theatre, Oxford, June 14, 1871, by William Hurrell Mallock&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Oxford&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Thos. Shrimpton &amp;amp; Son&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1871&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp2378&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;12 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Newdigate Prize Poem&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;The Isthmus of Suez: Recited In the Theatre, Oxford, June 14, 1871, by William Hurrell Mallock&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 14 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">“Consider the Sea's listless chime! Time's self it is, made audible.” “The Arabians do affirme that in this Isthmus are, certain places, where, when the night is quiet, may be heard the sound of both the seas, one upon either hand; the which (knowing not at that time the true distance betwixt them, which is, as I learn since, upward of three score miles) I certainly did believe myself to have heard, having strayed toward midnight a good distance alone from where our camels and their keepers had made halt. But whence cometh that noise which I took to be the voice of the sea, I cannot answer, nor have I yet met with one (though I have enquired of many) who with any shew of reason could.”—George Daymond, 1635. THE ISTHMUS OF SUEZ. It is but one low bar of dreary sand Reaching between them; and on either hand Through untold years hath moaned perpetually An unknown sea unto an unknown sea— The estranged waves of both the hemispheres; Breaking so near that each one well-nigh hears The other's sounding shingle, and hoarse stir Of pebbles in the grating surf-water. Yea, and when winds are low, and stars are bright, Betwixt the desert and the cloudless night, 'Tis told the eternal murmurings of the twain Have mixed at seasons on the lone mid plain, In one faint foamy whisper, east and west; And long ago, upon the loneliest Heart of the desert, murmured in the ear Of a lone eastward English wanderer. The hollow moonless midnight's naked height Towered there above the awe-struck eremite; And dark about him, fading far away, The strange plain's gloom and level stillness lay. The scene, the season smote into his blood— The night, the silence, and the solitude,— And all his pulses throbbed. His steadfast eyes Were turned towards the stars and foreign skies; Yet, still the same, he felt surrounding him The haunting presence of the desert dim; Whilst, o'er his soul's hushed lake, by slow degrees, Visions uncalled, and shifting images Rose like an evening mist. For all around Were ruinous kingdoms, and memorial ground, Places of gods and nations dead. He stood Neighboured by Pharoah's land, and Nilus' flood, And hallowèd Palestine and Araby, And by the matin and the evening sea— Stood with his feet upon the very plain O'er which had creaked the wheels of Israel's wain Of old towards Ægypt; and, on a later day— O'er which towards Ægypt three had made their way In flight, an agéd sire, an infant son, And a pure virgin. So the wanderer lone, Enisled amidst a waste of storied sand; Mused there,—a continent on either hand,— Whilst on those upturned English eyes of his, High o'er him in the unfathomable abyss, Unhomely Lybian stars shook quick and clear. And he, with fancy wandering far and near On random wing, through unconnected ways Went straying backward to the extreme days Whose monarchs and great deeds lie lost and hid In hieroglyph unknown, and pyramid; When the stupendous temples boomed with prayer And the clear darkness of the midnight air Grew gold with torch-light o'er Arsinöe; And singing choirs, and cymballed revelry Rang, where the spurted fountain-spray made shake The moon and stars asleep in Moeris' lake, And far through many a labyrinthine hall Echoed the wild Osirian festival. Thus while in these quaint visions rapt he dreamed, Within his ears, he knew not whence, it seemed He heard a dreamy distant murmur swell, Like that sea's voice which haunts a whispering shell, Invading his soul's vague imaginings Of remote days and those unknown old kings Royal in times which time remembereth not, From oft whose crumbling cheeks the cere-cloths rot In silence 'neath the runed sarcophagus. Then as the new sound blurred his fancies thus, Starting he woke, and knew that this must be The two strange waters calling, sea to sea. And “What!” he cried, “amidst these sterile ways Have I then found your voices' trysting-place, Ye two sad sundered oceans, just in reach Of either's weary inland-wandering speech, Where each spent voice arrives just audible? Of what hid things do ye meet here to tell? Mourn ye for that old kiss your waters gave Long, long ago, when mingling wave and wave Knew one another; and the desert air Turned cool with babble of sudden sea-water, As into that deep tideless blue of thine The Nile ran brackish with sweet Asian brine, O midland sea? Or do ye talk of when One like Sesostris shall arise again, Some lord of lords, some calm arch-conqueror, Some shackler of yoked monarchs to his car, To bid his ductile myriads of sad slaves Toil their hard lives away to join your waves, Gashing the desert through from shore to shore, As once of old, and make you one once more? Ah! do ye watch and wait for one like this— Some son of Ægypt's mummied dynasties, A splendid despot meet for Pharoah's throne? Alas! but these are all past over and gone— They and their glories all clean gone from us, Their cities and their shrines are ruinous, Their lichened gods forget the sound of prayer; And they in many a citied sepulchre— Forgotten, marvellous places underground, Where never sunlight comes, nor any sound, Sleep kingly slumbers, whilst the years roll on, Embalmèd in superb oblivion. Nay—these shall never more awake, arise, With pride or sunlight in their dusty eyes, To bid you mingle again, ye alien seas. And whence, then, shall help come, since not from these? Must ye be strangers, strangers evermore? And turning here, as I, toward either shore, Shall men for ever after turn their eyes On unblent waves, and different destinies? Shall half the world be dark, and half still light, Divided into changeless day and night? And ah! ye eöan oceans turned towards you That wash the shafted sunrise, and whose blue Billows are stained red with the fire of day, Even as I, must after ages say Ye—ye, along your golden fabulous lands Mourn over beds of pearls, or coral strands, Round slaves and slaveries? Whilst, O west waves, ye Have dashed your brine on headlands of the free, And leapt in foam about their plunging prows, From those first days of Greece adventurous, When lonely Argo took the untried gale, Or, with long oars, and each a single sail, The carven galleys rode round Salamis; Even to our times of later memories, And skyey masts, when Albion's thunders broke Roll upon roll, and our gray battle-smoke Blent with the vapours of the shifting main, And veiled from sight the ruinous waifs of Spain. But ah, ye waves of freedom, never more Shall those waves reach you from the further shore? And breaths of freedom in the western breeze Wander far off to purple Asian seas? When, once more, will ye meet and mix?” Since then The sundered twain have met and mixed again; Yea, they have kissed and met. But when will ye, Ye warring spirits of the bond and free? What power or knowledge is there, to unite The never-mingled seas of faith and sight? When shall such come? Or must we evermore, Standing midway, on either desolate shore Hear the deploring waters of each flood Mourn to themselves in alien neighbourhood, Nor ever mingle in silence till the day When all faiths fail, and knowledge fades away?</field>
   </doc>
</add>