<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Hubert, Francis, Sir</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Hubert, Francis, Sir</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">hubert francis sir</field>
      <field name="author_text">Hubert, Francis, Sir</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.0945.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1631</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:463636</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Egypts Favourite ; The Historie of Joseph, divided into four parts: Together with old Israels Progresse into the Land of Goshen. By Francis Hubert</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">Egypts Favourite ; The Historie of Joseph, divided into four parts: Together with old Israels Progresse into the Land of Goshen. By Francis Hubert</field>
      <field name="title_facet">egypts favourite</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">egypts favourite</field>
      <field name="title_text">Egypts Favourite ; The Historie of Joseph, divided into four parts: Together with old Israels Progresse into the Land of Goshen. By Francis Hubert</field>
      <field name="year_display">1631</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1631</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1631</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463636&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463636&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Hubert, Francis, Sir&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;hubert francis sir&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Egypts Favourite ; The Historie of Joseph, divided into four parts: Together with old Israels Progresse into the Land of Goshen. By Francis Hubert&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;egypts favourite&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1631&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1631&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Hubert, Francis, Sir&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Egypts Favourite&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;The Historie of Joseph, divided into four parts: Together with old Israels Progresse into the Land of Goshen. By Francis Hubert&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by A. M. for L. Chapman [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1631&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp1849&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;[126] p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Egypts Favourite&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;The Historie of Joseph, divided into four parts: Together with old Israels Progresse into the Land of Goshen. By Francis Hubert&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 182 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE AVTHORS Invocation. Nor high Olympus, nor Pernassus hill, Nor fam'd Pierian Sisters I implore, (The Poets Patrons) to assist my quill, A higher pitch my Eagle-Muse doth soare. Thou that taughtst Ishai's youngest sonne to sing The Songs of Sion, with thy heau'nly deawes Inspire my heart, as thou didst Sions King, And sacred drops into my quill infuse. Thou that didst loue the voyce of that sweet Singer, And Davids golden Harpe in tune didst keepe, Teach me that heau'nly Instrument to finger, Who Dauid-like now sing to Israels Sheepe. Thou Sonne of David, Davids Lord and King, Assist my Muse, for now shee takes her wing. Ioseph in Pvteo. OR, The Vnfortunate Brother. 1 Of all the worldly blessings which fr? heau'n (Like gracious dew) did fall on Iacobs head, I doe not thinke there was a greater giu'n, Then were the sons that from his loynes were bred. 2 It is a Cordiall to the Fathers heart, To see himselfe so often multiplide, The like was never made by Chimick Art, There's no extraction of such strength beside. 3 And in this blessing Iacob had a part, For Iacobs Zodiaque had twelue seu'rall Signes, (I meane his sonnes) whose influence did impart A powrfull strength to him, and his designes. 4 Of all the rest, I was his pretiest boy, And to my father from my cradle deare, Sonne of his age, therefore perhaps his ioy, As by my partie-livery may appeare. 5 Or else perhaps 'twas for my Mothers sake, To whom his soule with chaines of loue was tyde, Which caus'd him cherefully to vndertake Twice seu'n yeeres seruice, to make her his Bride. 6 O Loue, thou art the perfect Adamant, Which breakes all Hammers, wearies euery arme, Thou hast no sense of danger, or of want, No apprehension of ensuing harme. 7 But thou art carried in a full carreere, With highest speed to vvhat thou dost desire, Labours are sweet, and difficulties deere, To compasse that vvhereto thy hopes aspire. 8 Vnwearied loue or labours not at all, Or else at least doth make all labours light, Witnesse my father Iacob, Labans thrall, Or Rachels rather (for to speake more right) 9 Faint with heau'ns frost by night, heau'ns fire by day. Which (though distastfull) Iacob yet puts over, Thinking all Moneths alike for one sweet May, O such a thing it is to bee a Louer. 10 And well it may be that I was affected For my dead mothers sake, whom he held deare: But sure it is, that I was much respected, And Rachels loue in Joseph did appeare. 11 For he did loue mee more in truth and shew, Then all the children that he had beside, Who thereupon did discontented grow, His loue to me made me to be envy'de. 12 Alasse, that from a root so sweet should spring So noysome, and so venemous a flower: But thus (we see) it holds in euery thing, Great fortunes, great affections, place and power 13 Are subiect to great envie: men will hate That eminence, which they cannot attaine: It may be Natures fault, it may be Fate, It may be Custome, vvhich few can restraine. 14 What ere the cause be, that's th'effect (we see) Eu'n brothers of one backe will make it good, My fathers loue had fatall been to me, If gracious heau'n had not their wils withstood. 15 He loues, they hate: and to fill vp the streame, And swell the humour of their ranckling hate, (So God would haue it) I must haue a dreame, Which (foolish lad) to them I did relate. 16 Dreames are the Daughters of the silent Night, Begot on divers Mothers, most, most vaine; Some bred by dayes-discourse, or dayes-delight, Some from the stomacke fuming to the braine. 17 Some from Complexion; Sanguine Constitutions Will dreame of Maskes, Playes, Revels, Melody: Some of dead bones, and gastly apparitions, Which are the true effects of Melancholly. 18 And some are meerly forg'd to private ends, And (without doubt) some are Propheticke to, Which gracious God out of his goodnesse sends, To warne vs what to shun, or what to doe. 19 Or to discouer what in time will come, Either for priuate, or for publique weale: Such was my dreame, a true presaging one, Which to my brothers thus I did reueale: 20 Me thought we were together in the field Binding of sheaues, Mine riseth, stands vpright, Your sheaues encompasse mine, but stoope and yeeld, And honors mine: Dreamer, we know your spright 21 The brethren say: shalt thou rule ouer vs? Thou Lord it so? Proud boy, it shall not be. A second dreame I had, and told it thus: The Sunne, the Moone, the Starres I seem'd to see; 22 The Starres I saw eleu'n in number were, And all to me (as honouring) did bow, I told it so, that Iacob did it heare, Who frown'd vpon me with an angry brow. 23 Must I, your Mother, and your Brethren bee Your vassals? at your feet (proud boy) be cast? 'Tis more then time (I see) to humble thee, And lance that windie humour swels so fast. 24 And thus in outward shew old Israel chides, To coole his spleenfull sons, whose wrath did flame: But inwardly the double dreame he hides, And all his thoughts still worke vpon the same. 25 The sonnes of Iacob now in Sechem keepe Their flockes (the story sayes:) goe boy (quoth he) See how thy brethren fare, and how the sheepe, And bring a true relation vnto me. 26 From Hebron sent Ioseph now takes his vvay To Sechem-ward: vvandring, a man he met, Of vvhow he doth enquire, if he can say Ought of his brethren? Is to Dothan set: 27 For thither they would goe, I heard them say: He giues him thankes, and after them doth goe: Ioseph take heed, thou vvalk'st a dangerous vvay, In thine owne blood thou find'st a bosome foe. 28 They spi'd him soone, before he came much nigher, So Eagle-ey'd is Envie on her prey, And straight against his life they doe conspire, And to themselues vvith hatfull scorne they say: 29 Yon comes the Dreamer: now hee's in our power, Lets cut his throat, then cast him in some pit, And say some savage beast did him deuoure, Teach him to dreame: See vvhat vvill come of it. 30 Vile man, thou art a creature vvorse then beast, If powerfull heau'n doe not restraine thy will, A Wolfe, a Deu'll doth dwell within thy breast, Which alwayes stirs thee to extreamest ill. 31 And there's no tinder that's so apt to fire, As is thy wicked Nature to consent; Wee're easily drawn to what we doe desire, And our desires are most to mischiefe bent. 32 'Tis hatefull for one man to kill another, Though causefull fury doth distract the sence: But O, vvhat is it then to kill a brother? And in cold blood, and that vvithout offence? 33 Yea, and to offer at a fathers life, For out of his deare loue they well might gather, That eu'n that murdrous blow, that bloody knife That stab'd the son, might chance to kill the father. 34 But when that minds are bent to doe amisse, There's no respects that can the same controule, His other brethren were resolu'd of this, But Reuben onely had some touch of soule, 35 And therefore this conspiracie withstands, Vse we no force (quoth he) vse rather wit, He is our brother, lay no violent hands Vpon his life, yet cast him in the pit. 36 And thus he said, intending to restore To Israels armes the comfort of his age, Direct deniall had inflam'd them more, There's no opposing to a present rage: 37 What euer stops the current of a streame, Is swept away with furious violence, Force is effectlesse gainst a strong extreame: But yet a man with labour and expence 38 May turne the chanell to another course, Hee's oft a gayner that can purchase time: Therefore giue way whilst fury runnes in force, Which being spent, then on with thy designe. 39 And Reuben meanes to make aduantage so, Vnto whose motion all the rest consent; Ioseph meane while is come, but doth not know (Poore innocent) the drift of their intent. 40 And as men ioyfull of this happy meeting, They bid him welcome with a false embrace: As felons true men handle, such their greeting, And soone (perforce) they strip him of his case. 41 Joseph did more then wonder what they meant, He knew the parties were his fathers sonnes, By whom he was in visitation sent, And with a pleasing Ambassie he comes: 42 He lookes into himselfe, and finds all well, Good Lord (thought he) what do my brothers mean? I know no cause should make them thus to swell: But finding that their fury grew extreame, 43 He speakes them faire, with teares he doth intreat They would respect his blood, his loue, his youth, What was his fault (he ask'd) that was so great? For he knew none that he had done in truth: 44 He tells them, He was none of Esaus brood, Who with their father stroue eu'n in the vvombe, But he deriued was from Iacobs blood, Whose purer streames in all their veines did runne: 45 Yet wrathfull Esau with their Sire incens'd, Both for the birth-right, and the blessing too, Did not proceed to murder (though pretenc'd) And would they act what he forbare to doe? 46 Indeed good Abram (common great grand-sire Vnto them all) resolu'd to sacrifice Vnto his God (for he did so require) His deare-deare Lambe, more deare then his ovvne eyes: 47 But he had speciall Warrant for the deed, 'Twas not a worke of will, his owne deuice, God did command, vvhy should not Izhak bleed? Obedience is the truest sacrifice. 48 But they had no Commission for his death, Where was their Warrant so to spill his blood? Who sign'd the same? for he receiu'd his breath From God, to yeeld againe when he thought good. 49 If God requir'd it, hee vvas vvell content, But 'twas no vvorke of his, 'twas their owne vvill, Which executed, they would soone repent, For fearefull justice wayts on fearelesse ill. 50 With that they interrupted his discourse: Words were but lost (they said) he must not preach, His part was Patience: So with bruitish force, (First hauing stript him) without farther speach 51 They cast him straight into the deadly pit: And then (as well discerning of the state) In triumph round about the same they sit, And eat and drinke, and jest at Iosephs fate. 52 Indeed (braue spirits) 'tis a noble act, Deserving much, and memorable fame, Laurell at least: well, looke into the fact, 'Twill fill your soules with griefe, your browes with shame. 53 You haue betrayd a young and hopefull Lad, Alone without the helpe of any other: The chiefest comfort that his father had, Who is your father to, and he your brother. 54 Adde more to this, he was an innocent, Whom causelesse hate so fowly did betray, In loue and kindnesse by a father sent, And Messengers are sacred (as men say) 55 Besides, your root grew in the Holy Land, Neuer before tainted with such a sin, Izhak will surely grieue (if vnderstand) To thinke his Nephewes haue so bloody bin. 56 But all this while the Bird that's in the breast, Is fast asleepe, and no disturbance makes, 'Twas wont to be a Nightingale at least, But now 'twil proue a Scritch-owle when it wakes. 57 The Frontispice of sinne is fayre in shew, A pleasant Porter alwayes keepes the gate, But being in, it is the house of vvoe, Of feare, of shame, and of all deadly fate. 58 But I must leaue the brothers as they bee, Who now securely triumph in their wrong, Distressed Ioseph, I returne to thee, The subiect of my ill-made, well-meant Song. 59 Me thinkes I see how this poore youth doth lye, Vnmanly thus, vnnaturally vsed, Thinking the pit his graue, fixing his eye On heau'n, that sees, helps innocents abused. 60 Me thinkes I heare him say, and saying weepe, How vnexampled is my wretchednesse? My sea of sorrow is so very deepe, That there's no line to fathom my distresse. 61 O by what name shall I expresse my ill, It is not banishment that I endure, I am too truely in my Countrey still; But banishment were better, more secure. 62 Earth is my Countrey, and in earth I am, And yet I am not in my proper place: For I vvas borne to vvalke vpon the same, And with my feet to trample on her face. 63 Now am I in her armes, or bowels rather, Into my Mothers vvombe aliue I goe: O Iacob, my belou'd and louing Father, Didst thou beget mee, to be swallow'd so? 64 I know that shee embraces all at last, Shee is the Center vnto vvhich we tend; But yet with me she makes preposterous hast, Her right begins but when my life doth end, 65 And then she may with justice seize on mee, Now she intrudes before her lawfull time: O common Parent, I doe wrong to thee, Thou art not to be charged with this crime. 66 Yet Earth is the sole Agent of my ill, But 'tis indeed a more refined Clay, 'Tis breathing, vvalking Earth (against thy will) Makes me close prisner in thy wombe this day, 67 Where I am neither liuing, nor yet dead, And yet am both: I know not what I am: But this I know, that neuer was there bred Amongst all men a more disastrous man, 68 Which am depriued of that common good, That all Mankind, nay very beasts possesse, Ayre, light, heat, motion, and all hope of food, Who (though I liue) yet can I not expresse 69 The powers and actes of life: and (which is worse) Haue able actiue Organs for the same, And eu'n those blessings doe encrease my curse; For had I been decrepit, blind, or lame, 70 Benumb'd vvith Palsies, fine w-crackt vvith crampes, Without all vse of limbes and senses to, I should not haue been choak'd with Earth's cold dampes, Nor in my graue haue liu'd as now I do. 71 Nay, eu'n those nobler graces of the mind, Wit, Vnderstanding, Iudgement, Memory, Serue all as one sad Index, for to find, And read my wofull History thereby, 72 And the more actiue-able that they are, The more they set my suffrings on the racke, A feeling knowledge is more wretched farre, Then a dull stupid non-sense, that doth lacke 73 True apprehension of its proper ill, And therefore slightly entertaines distresse, Conceiuing sorrowes are most pregnant still, In ignorance is senselesse happinesse. 74 O how extreamely wretched is that man, Whose greatest blessings turne vnto his curse? All his endeauors (doe eu'n what hee can) Serue but as meanes to make his fortunes worse. 75 But Ioseph, whither doth thy stormy passion (Which doth indeed but swell thy misery) Transport thee from thy selfe in such a fashion, As thou art almost fallen to lunacie? 76 Why dost thou vent thy sorrowes to the earth? Shee heares thee not: 'Tis bootlesse to complaine, Besides thou hast no surplusage of breath, Why doest thou make such waste-thereof in vaine? 77 Rather improue the same vnto the best, Thinke not on earth, advance thy selfe to heau'n, If there be hope of helpe, there doth it rest, And onely by that hand it must be giu'n. 78 And thus resolu'd, this Phenix in his nest, Not built with Spices and Arabian Gummes, But of hard flints, with toads &amp; slow-worm's drest, An humble suppliant to his God becomes. 79 And being in the bowels of the Earth, The Antiperistists.cold thereof augments his inward heat, Which from his heart breaks forth into his breath, And thus (sweet incense) mounts to Gods high seat. 80 Father of Heau'n, let not my brothers hate (Their causelesse hate) prevaile against my blood; Thou canst their malice and their spleene abate, And turne their plots and proiects to my good. 81 They are but like to Pipes which doe convey, The streame of action, that doth flow from thee: The worke (as 'tis a worke) is thine: but they (As 'tis a sinne) they onely guiltie be. 82 They are thy instruments, though now they jarre, And thou canst sweetly tune them, as thou wilt, Extract my peace from forth this civill warre, And thine owne glory raise out of their guilt. 83 But if my sinnes (which be in number great) Haue shut thine eare, and barr'd vp mercies gate, Forgiue my brothers yet, I thee intreat, And lay not to their charge their murdrous hate. 84 But let this pit (that now must be my tombe) Bury my body, and withall, their shame, O neuer let it to the world be knowne, That Iacobs sonnes were guiltie of such blame. 85 Especially shew mercie to my Sire, Let his gray head in peace goe to his graue, And once againe I humbly thee desire, Forgiue my brothers, and thy seruant saue. 86 Ioseph, thy body in the pit I find, (That's earth in earth) out thy more noble part, Thy purer soule (from earthly drosse refin'd) Mounts vp to heau'n, to which thou send'st thy heart. 87 In faithfull prayer: an Agent of such trust, So gracefull, and so pow'rfull to prevaile, That though thy selfe seemes buried in the dust, Yet that makes way to heau'n, and will not faile 88 With such effect to prosecute thy cause, To treat and mediate for thee with thy Lord, That though thou seem'st eu'n in destructions jawes, His mighty arme will timely helpe afford. 89 As here a troope of Ishmaelites came by, Merchants (it seemes) they were, to Egypt bound, Laden with Balme, and Myrrhe, and spicery, Such precious things as were in Gilead found. 90 So and more ancient is the Entercourse, By which one Countrey traffiques with another, And (as we see) oft times an able Nourse Supples the wants of a defectiue Mother: 91 So doth one Climate with its natiue wealth Furnish another, and by such supplyes We haue most sovereigne Simples for our health, Pearle, Gold and diuers rich Commodities: 92 For this Worlds deepe vnsounded Architect, Hath not confin'd all blessings to one Land, Each Countrey labours vnder some defect, Which must be helped by anothers hand. 93 And 'tis the chiefest cause, and vse of Trade, To bring in others vvealth, and vent our owne, And to that end long Voyages are made, Eu'n to remotest Climates, erst vnknowne. 94 But what? me thinkes my Muse doth trauaile too, And bends her selfe vnto a forreine cost, Returne againe to what thou hast to doe, Else will thy fruitlesse labour all be lost. 95 When Iudah did these Merchant strangers see, Some sparke of Pitie, or Hypocrisie Did seeme to touch his heart: Let vs (quoth he) Sell yonder Lad, that in the pit doth lie: 96 For, say we kill him, and the murder keepe Secret as night; Alas, will that availe vs? His blood will crie when wee are fast asleepe, And our owne Conscience to the Barre will hale vs. 97 Beside, there is no profit in his blood, Where by his sale there may arise some gaine, Let vs respect both his and our owne good, Such pleasing motions are not made in vaine. 98 Judah prevailes: Out of the pit they draw him, They play the Merchants, and to Merchants sell The louely Boy: And when these strangers saw him, They offred ready Cash, they lik'd so well. 99 Of siluer twentie pieces was the price: They pay the Money, and they take their ware, And now the brethren studie a device To cloake their sinne, that is their chiefest care. 100 At length they doe this stratageme devise, They staine with blood of a slaine Kid or Goat, (To cast a mist before their fathers eyes) The Ensigne of his loue, the partie Coat. 101 That they resolue to bring vnto their Sire, And say they found it so with blood defil'd: A murderer will euer prooue a lyer, How easely is an honest heart beguil'd? 102 Thy I ambe into the field why hast thou sent? Why made such wolues the keepers of thy sheepe? Shall we condemne mens actions by th'euent, When all successe is buried very deepe? 103 Into a fathers heart how could it sinke, So many sheep-heards Butchers all should be? How could old Israel once conceiue or thinke, That such sowre Crabs should grow vpon his tree? 104 The stocke was good that hee had grifted in, And God had blest it with much goodly fruit, And as their birth, so had their breeding bin, His precepts and their practise did not sute. 105 But say he might mistrust some of his sonnes, Simeon and Leui had been soyl'd in blood; But this within no reach of reason comes, That such a generall guilt should taint his brood: 106 That all his sonnes should so conspire in one, To spill the blood of a poore Innocent: Where was his Iudah when it should be done? Without all doubt he neuer would consent. 107 Besides, no cause, nor colour did appeare, Why they should be so cruell to a brother: A vertuous soule that in its selfe is cleare, Is hardly drawne to thinke ill of another. 108 And yet (we see) brother did brother kill Long before this: Cayne innocent Abel slew: But sure there was this diffrence twixt their ill, That was a single Duell: they but two: 109 But this vvas tenne to one: yet I confesse, One of the tenne was touch'd vnto the heart, And shew'd at least some sparkes of tendernesse, And sau'd his life by taking of his part. 110 And yet it seemes he saw him in the pit, Yea in the pit (the Embleme of his graue) But blame not Reuben, 'twas a worke of wit, Or honest wit, vvhose purpose was to saue: 111 For he did meane the lad home to haue led, Witnesse the rending of his clothes and haire, When he return'd, found not, suppos'd him dead, (It seemes, that in the sale he had no share) 112 But when the deed vvas done, he was content (To hide his brothers shame) to tell a lye, In vice how easely multitudes assent? How quickly sinne with sinne doth multiply? 113 Most men haue itching fingers to shed blood, And to Reuenge as to a Feast they goe, But vnto actions, honest, fayre, and good, We creep like snayles, or men benumb'd with snow. 114 But whither strayes my Muse? By this the Boy Arriues at Egypt, Iacobs heart doth burne, To heare some tidings of his long-mist Ioy, And vvith strange tidings (loe) his sonnes returne. 115 He reades their message written in their face, But cannot reade the tablets of their hearts, Sad lookes at least, and sighs must seeme to grace That Tragedie, vvherein they play'd their parts. 116 But (O) wee know that lookes are often lyers, Who can iudge truely by the outward shew? We practice how to palliate our desires, No more of man, but the bare barke we know. 117 And yet it may be they vvere touch'd indeed With sad remembrance of their fact so soule: There are some wounds that inwardly doe bleed, And gastly lookes come from a troubled soule. 118 Vice well may paint her face, and maske her brow, And looke aloft with a bold strumpets eye: But Conscience, what a biting vvorme art thou? Wh? thine own thoughts do giue thy looks (the lie) 119 Where is my sonne (quoth Iacob) vvhere is hee? Why doe I not behold my Iosephs face? Loe, this is all of him that vve did see, The brethren sayd, and then they shew'd his case. 120 And vvhen old Israel saw this killing sight, A wicked beast (he cries) hath slaine my sonne: Good aged Father, thou art in the right, It was a beast indeed, a bloodie-one. 121 That monster Envie seyzd vpon thy child, And with his Harpies Tallons grip'd him so, That from thy sight thy Ioseph is exild, And thou art left to waste thine age in woe. 122 Meane while (me thinkes) I see these fratricides Hanging their heads, as if with sorrow smitten, False complement, foule actions often hides: For hearts are seldome in the fore-heads written. 123 Well, though you could deceiue a poore old man, (Who would not think, that from his Cristall spring Should flow such muddy streames) goe (if you can) And blind Heau'ns eye, that sees, marks euery thing, 124 Whose present Iustice (though it seeme to sleepe) Will surely wake, and call you to the Barre, The Court of Heau'n a Register doth keepe, Where all our daily deeds enrolled are: 125 Therefore (dissembling men) goe make your peace, Prepare (whilst you haue time) for your account, Let your true teares petition for release: Teares (against waters nature) vp will mount, 126 Eu'n to the highest Heau'ns, and there will crie For grace and mercie, gainst your crying sinne: There is great vertue in a weeping eye, And teares (dumbe Orators) when you beginne 127 To plead for pardon, seldome sue in vaine, You are successefull advocates of ours: Marble is pierc'd with often drops of raine, How th? is mercy mou'd with such sweet showers? 128 But all this while doth Iacob dwell in teares, Why should he longer liue now Ioseph's slaine? Loue (whilst the loued liues) is full of feares, And dead, then griefe begins his tragique raigne. 129 And the more strong and fervent that it was, So much the more it breakes forth into passion: A heart halfe hote breathes forth a cold (alas) And sutes it selfe in blacke, perhaps for fashion. 130 But the sad soule that's truely touch'd indeed, With losse of that, which it did hold so deare, A long time after of that wound doth bleed, And eu'n till Death the scarre will still appeare. 131 So Iacob will go mourning to his graue, Gen. 37. 35. Though all his sonnes and daughters doe their best To comfort him, but hee'l no comfort haue, His heart was kild before in Iosephs breast. 132 Good kind old Father, cheare thy selfe againe, Hope in the bottome of the basket lies, It may bee that thy Ioseph is not slaine, Loue is too often full of ielousies: 133 Thou shalt suruiue with these thy teare-drownd eyes To see thy Ioseph next the Kingly throne, To see him nurse thee and thy families, And in a forreine Land make Israel knowne. 134 O the great goodnesse of All-pow'rfull God, How vvondrously doth he his works dispose? That he can fetch our comforts from the rod, And raise our fortunes by the meanes of foes. 135 'Twas not the brothers malice, nor their wit, That could the Wisedome of high heauen preuent, They draw the Plot, but God doth build on it, They serue his ends against their owne intent. 136 They fear'd the Youth should liue to be their Lord, And therefore made him (as they thought) a slaue: But their owne tongues those Titles shall afford, Which they so fear'd, and yet so freely gaue. 137 But stay my Muse, me thinks thou flagg'st the wing, As if thy plumes were wet with Iacobs raine, Whose tearefull sorrowes will not let thee sing, Till he hath dry'd his aged eyes againe. Timens Deum, non habet quod timeat vlterius. THE CHASTE COVRTIER. Ioseph in Gremio. OR, The Faithfull Seruant. 1 Braue gallant Youthes, the hope and pride of Courts, Whose haughty spirits actiue fire inflames, Clayming by Birth (as Charter) your disports, Chiefely the sweet Prerogatiue of Dames, 2 Take my Survey vvith a true-iudging eye, I shall be found a Master-piece of Nature, For forme, and fortune of great raritie, Not paralleld by any common Creature. 3 I was borne free, but (loe) I now must serue, I was a youth borne faire and fit for action, My dutious seruice did so well deserue, As soone I wonne into my Lords affection. 4 O no, it was not any worth in me, That made such way into my Masters heart: This streame (great Sea of goodnes) flow'd fr? thee, Thou Sunne of grace and glory didst impart 5 One beame of brightnesse to my clouded state. It was indeed thy heau'nly influence, Whose vertue drew me from the pit of late, And now workes strongly on my Masters sense, 6 Whose apprehension made him quickly find, That God was with me, and did blesse my wayes, That was the Loadstone drew his steely mind, My luster did reflect from Heau'ns faire rayes. 7 All vnder-Planets were in opposition, I was a stranger borne, and eu'n from thence, He might deriue a very iust suspition, Strangers are entertain'd with diffidence. 8 I was but greene, and tasted of the tree, Vnripe for service, or for secrecie, And no true iudgement could he make of me, He could not take my height so suddenly. 9 But grant I were completely honest, yet By vnexperience I was vselesse made For any great imployment, and that Bit Might hold me hard, till I was better way'd. 10 But all these heauie morsels are digested, Heau'n had so vvhetted on his appetite, That he did seeme eu'n with my service feasted, And relisht all my actions with delight. 11 So (like a Mushrumpe) in a night I grew So great in grace, that I had in my hand All that was his, so much, he scarcely knew What he should eat, or drinke; his coyne, his land, 12 His whole Revenue, Jewels, Stocke and Plate, Indeed himselfe was manag'd by my hand, He seem'd the servant, vvhilst I swayd the state, For all his fortunes were at my command. 13 This was a gallant and vnlook'd-for Rise, Much for a youth and stranger to attaine: But thus it pleas'd (I say not Destinies) But Providence, who rides Fate with his raigne. 14 Still I increas'd in favour and in grace, And (which is strange) grew great yet not envi'd, And being of comely presence, faire of face, Of winning carriage, and well qualified, 15 My Lady-Mistresse cast an amourous eye Vpon my forme, which her affections drew, Shee was Loues Martyr, and in flames did frye, But (like a woman) did that loue pursue) 16 Wisely and cunningly: To my deare Lord A true and faithfull seruant shee commends me; And he that durst relye vpon her word, Alas, not ghessing once what shee intends me, 17 Addes fewell to the fire, that scorch'd her heart, My youth, my forme, my haviour he admired, He read a Lecture on each seu'rall part, And prayes her cherish what she most desired. 18 Which for his sake (she sayes) she will effect, And sith I was so high in his opinion, Who vvas her soule, I should haue her respect, And thenceforth be her Favourite, her Minion: 19 For well she knew, himselfe was so compleat In Iudgement, and in euery worthy part, That 'twas no common vertue that could get So neere, and deare a place within his heart. 20 And she had learn'd (by his example taught) To favour vertue, though it seeme deiected, And thus shee mask'd the foulnesse of her thought, And made her way to what shee most affected. 21 From that time forward shee would cast such lookes To all my actions, giue such commendation, As one but meanly read in Cupids bookes, Might know the stories end by th'insinuation. 22 Shee vs'd me like a sonne, not like a slaue; Or (if that Title, full of heau'nly fire, Fits not her hellish heat) then let it haue Some other name, to palliate her desire, 23 Which oft wrought in her passionate extreames, Shee drawes me to discourse, free, friendly, close, Shee questions me both of my wants and meanes, And largely offers full supply of those. 24 Ebrew (shee sayes) me thinkes you doe not looke With that aspect, that you were wont to doe, Your heart is not your owne: I doubt, y'are tooke With some Egyptian beautie: Is't not so? 25 Come tell me truely, and I here protest By Putipher himselfe, whom thou holdst deare, Who loues thee too, next to my selfe the best, In this thy loue, my loue too shall appeare. 26 He be thy spokes-woman, for thee Ile wooe. With that he blushes: which shee soone espies, And (heeding well the beautie of his hew) Shee blusht her blush, with him to sympathize. 27 But he that did not, would not, at least, know, Whither her speech and soft discourse did tend: Madame (replyes) now by the loue I owe To Putipher, and shall vntill my end, 28 And next my duetie to you (fairest Dame), No womans loue yet euer touch'd my heart, I thanke my God, I never knew that flame: But vvere it scortch'd (me thinks) I durst impart 29 It to your goodnesse. Pray thee (quoth shee) doe. And so I will (quoth he) when I am shot: I owe my selfe vnto my Lord and you. And may shee perish that affects thee not. 30 Thus softly to her selfe (of him vnheard) The Lady spake: And glad that he was free, Within her selfe she plotted and conferr'd How Iosephs loue by her might compast be. 31 Woman, thou art a fayre and winning Creature, Did I say comming too, I should not lye: And yet that word doth not expresse thy nature, For thou art seeking too, if men would flye. 32 But tis thy Tenure to be sought vnto, Men vvooe by Custome, that's thy Copie-hold, We sue for that which thou art sicke to doe, And art all fire, yet seemest ycie cold. 33 And why should'st thou not colour thy desire? Since thou hast learn'd to colour head and face, Which are indeed but Beakons set on fire, To giue vs warning (if we had the grace 34 To apprehendie) of thy foes arriving, Old age and time, which are thy greatest foes, Gainst whom, thou and thy Boxes will be striving, But striu'st in vaine; thou canst not conquer those. 35 For Age will seize thy colours in the field, Thy youths faire colours, being red and white, That great Commander, Time, wil make thee yeeld, And forreine aydes will fayle thee in the fight. 36 But whither dost thou stray, my wandring Muse? I doe not thinke, that in those ancient times, Though women could their husbands then abuse, They vvere not guiltie yet of these new crimes. 37 But then it was (I hope not now) the guise, To make all meanes answere vnto their ends, Our age breeds fooles: the women then were vvise, And had, and kept, and vs'd their private friends. 38 But (O) you vertuous and vnspotted Dames, That now are ty'd with Hymens golden chaine, Whose holy thoughts ne'r dream't of vnchaste flames. But truly louing, are so lou'd againe. 39 Who (as that worthy Romane Lady sayd) Doe know no other but your husbands breath: True Turtles, Virgine vviues, that never stray'd From wayes of life, into the paths of death. 40 Frowne not vpon my Muse, and her free Song, Nor cast into the Vrne a coale-blacke stone, Your Vertue is your owne: Nor is't a wrong, To blaze the errours of one faultie one: 41 Let her vnchastnesse serue but as a foyle To make your constant vertue shine the more: Some vveeds will grow eu'n in the richest soyle, Nor doe we prize the same the lesse therefore. 42 Then on, my Muse, and feare not to relate Those songs of death, vvhich this faire Siren sung: Poore Ioseph, once betrayd by too much hate, Now too much loue (I feare) will doe thee vvron. 43 For on a day, (the servants all being out, By accident, or purpose sent away, But sure it was her wit brought it about) The Lady on her Day-bed slumbring lay, 44 And (as she wish'd) this Ebrew had accesse, The house was voyd, and all things did conspire To make her set abroach her filthinesse. Joseph (quoth shee) approach, and quench my fire: 45 I must confesse I loue thee, and no longer Can this my passion hide from thee, my Loue; Deferre not (gentle youth) thou shouldst be stronger In thy desires, being Man: for Men must moue. 46 Come, lye thee downe, and hug me in thine armes: (With that the clothes that covered the bed Shee cast aside) and then displayd such charmes, As would haue rays'd a man, eu'n almost dead. 47 Feare not (soft youth) for here are none but we: Lust-blinded vvoman, thou art much awry, An eye (standing vpon a staffe) doth see, (The Emblem of his knowledge is the eye, 48 And of his power the staffe) He sees thee well, And he will strike thee too vvith his strong arme, The shapelesse vnseene Deu'll (the Prince of hell) Stands by thee too, and prompts thee to thy harme. 49 And thine owne Conscience is a witnesse now, And will, in time, be a tormentor too: But (all respects remou'd) shee labours how To compasse that vvhich shee resolu'd to doe. 50 And therefore thus continues her blacke spell, Ioseph (faire Ioseph) thou hast stolne my heart, Heartlesse I cannot liue: Sweet vse me well; 'Tis shee that begs, that might command in part. 51 This ycie youth (when thus he heard her speake) Lookes pale for sorrow, like a man halfe dead, And with a sigh (as if his heart would breake) Bashfully modest, thus to her he sayd: 52 Madam, you are a wise and vertuous woman, And know vvhat 'tis to breake a sacred trust; This vnment Parley (which you now doe summon) Must trie, if to my Lord I will proue iust. 53 Your selfe except (deare Lady) what is his, But I may freely vse it as mine owne? And shee is thine too, seale it with a kisse: 'Tis strange, a youth of flesh should be a stone. 54 Milk-sop, what dost thou feare? Here's none can see: Or say they should, there's none that dare relate: Great Lords haue sought what's freely offred thee, And with some hazard would be glad to haue't. 55 The pride of Egypts Court I haue withstood, And am esteem'd a chaste and modest Dame, To thee alone I prostitute my blood, And shall I be deny'd? Fie boy, for shame 56 Collect thy spirits, wrong not thy Countrey so: Doth Palestine faire Eunches onely breed? Are Canaans childrens bodies made of snow? Or vpon Agnus castus doe they feed? 57 Without all doubt thy father was not such, When he made loue vnto his louely Pheere: Thou wrongst both ours, &amp; thine own sex too much, But most of all thou wrongst thy selfe (my deere.) 58 By Heau'n I doe not speake to sift thy faith, There is more fire, more passion in my speech, Grant me thy loue, and presently (she saith) (Yet once againe I humbly thee beseech) 59 Or by th'Egyptian Gods, (and then she swore) As forcing her she would an out-cry make: Shee lou'd him much, but she should hate him more, If now her profer'd fauours he forsake. 60 Still mute he stands: nor doth one signe expresse, That might giue comfort to her foule desire: Still grew shee hotter from his backwardnesse, Deniall like a bellowes blowes the fire. 61 Yet finding Man and Youth speake in his blood Rebellious thoughts, to vvhich he was not vsed, And that her words grew not to be withstood, They were with so much loue, and sting effused. 62 First, he betakes himselfe vnto his God: Shall I (quoth he) offend that dreadfull Power, That whips all sinners with a steely rod? Whose wrath (like flaming fire) doth all devoure. 63 O could I act this ill without his sight, I might be drawne to hazard this sweet sinne: Or (say he saw it) vvere he not of might, To plague me for't, I might offend therein. 64 Or (both to grant his knowledge and his might) Were I not sure it vvere against his will, The pleasing taste of such a deare delight Might easely vvorke me to commit this ill. 65 But (O faire Dame) I know my God too vvell, Too well, so to prouoke him to my death, My death of soule and body both in hell, In hell, vvhere there's no ease, nor end of breath. 66 And with this point he breaks the dangerous thrust; And could we all be drawne vnto this vvard, Without all doubt vve should haue little lust, To rush so into sinne without regard. 67 But (O) the present pleasure of the sense Is such a Pulley, to draw on consent, That vve are hurryed head-long to th'offence, And neuer thinke on following punishment. 68 And that same soule vnto the left hand leanes, Or rather vvith full pace doth thither bend, That in the quest of good neglects the meanes, And in the acts of ill forgets the End. 69 Besides this first safe locke, Ioseph recourses Next to his Masters fauours and his trust, And those good thoughts his Mistres loue diuorces, And were strong repercussiues to her lust: 70 Can I (quoth he) abuse so deare a Loue, So great a trust, as is repos'd in me? By such an act I very well might prooue My selfe a slaue, and worthy so to be. 71 For all the gracious fauours hee hath done me, Shall I requite him vvith so great a wrong? Your selfe would hate me, if you so had wonne me: For Lust is hot at hand, but lasts not long. 72 Kind thankfulnesse doth dwell vvith noble minds, But neuer comes in kenning of a slaue, A present profit onely vvorkes on hynds, All former favours haue one birth, one graue. 73 And had not Heau'n directed Josephs heart, He might haue thought it, (in a reach of wit) This Ladies Glue, and mine may well impart A hopefull meanes of future benefit. 74 But Ioseph knew, that fortunes raisd by sinne, Are like to Summer fruit, that soone will rot; And therefore no such motiues worke on him, Greanesse is good, but not by lewdnesse got. 75 Who thinkes by meanes vnlawfull to prevaile, Doth build his fortunes vpon brittle sand, Whose weake foundations cannot chuse but faile, When glorious vertue doth securely stand. 76 Though Earthquakes come, yea though the Heau'ns doe fall, A spotlesse Conscience stands without controule, It needs no props to stay it selfe withall, But hath its strength from motions of the soule. 77 This is a stedfast Rocke, and euery waue Turnes but to froth that beats against the same, The care to keepe this calme, vvas that vvhich gaue Ioseph support against his lustfull Dame. 78 For from the Lady, manger smiles and teares, And all her bayts that vnto lewdnesse tend, He loose perforce doth breake, (the cloke he weares, Left in her hand) himselfe away doth wend: 79 Which seene, deluded Lust becomes a rage, Her flow of loue turnes to a flood of hate, Foule secrecies each other may engage, But neuer truly will incorporate. 80 Murder and Rape she cries: (his Mantle left) The Ravisher (as one afraid) is fled: Shee lookes like one of sense and wits bereft, Ravisht in truth, and not imagined. 81 Her out-crie's heard, and Putipher returnes, He knew the voyce, and wonders at the cause, Which wh? he heard, excuse him, though he burnes To be reveng'd of Ioseph by the Lawes. 82 My Lord (quoth shee) the slaue so deare to you, Whom you made Ruler of your house and State, Imboldned by your loue, so sawcie grew, As needs he vvould mine honour violate: 83 Nay, and by force too: But your Loue arm'd feare, And (though alone) inabled me to crie, Which heard (base slaue) he fled: See Putipher, The Ensigne of your Hebrews modestie. 84 With that she shewes his robe, and then she weeps, For ioy, to thinke vvhat danger she had past, Into her Lords armes flyes, and there she keeps Her hold, as drowning folkes (they say) doe fast. 85 Did the slaue thinke I could be false (quoth she) Or that I vvould vnsauorie pleasures proue? Can courser cates be welcome vnto me, That haue bin feasted with thy sweets of Loue? 86 Oft haue I drunke, (and yet I still am drie) Of purest Nectar, from thy lips distilling, Commanding Cupid dwelleth in thine eye, And binds me to be thine, vvere I vnwilling. 87 O Putifer, I haue no Heau'n but thee, I cannot moue but onely in thy spheare: Deare is my life, mine honour deare to me, Then Life and Honour too, thou art more deare. 88 And therewithall (as languishing in loue) With a soft sigh she straines him in her armes, Iosephs desire might stirring passions moue: Lust vp in armes soone stirres vvith small alarmes. 89 Let goe (deare Wife) he cries: 'tis now high time To punish goatish and vngratefull youth: Weepe not, his blood shall expiate his crime, Vnto the vvorld proclaime his fault, thy truth. 90 With much adoe to part shee is content; But by all Loue, all powrfull spells adjures, Her Lord should not remit the punishment, Which ielious angry Putipher assures. 91 O vvoman, thou art euer in extreames, Either an Ætna, or a Caucasus, Or burning, like the Dog-starr's fiery gleames, Or like the bleake North-wind benumbing vs. 92 Ioseph (who went not farre) was quickly found, And brought before his angry Lord, whose face Speaking his fury: hee in yrons bound, Was streight committed to th'offenders place. 93 'Twas then no time to plead: vpon thy Iurie Had I been summon'd, heard the Evidence The Lady gaue, poore Ioseph, I assure thee, I should haue found thee guilty of th'offence, 94 All things did so concurre, the time, the place, The circumstances, her report, her teares, Th'amazed lookes of her sad-seeming face, The servants absence, ioyn'd to Potiphers, 95 The beautie of his forme, his fire of age, His parts of Nature 'gainst himselfe reflect, His greatnesse in the house, the Ladies rage, His robe, her crie, his flight, all vrge suspect. 96 Man could haue iudg'd no lesse, and but a woman, No creature could her malice so expresse: This vvas a new vvay then, perhaps, since common, Sweet youth, I can but pray for thy release. 97 But he that is the God of Innocence, And vvill not not see the Iust (though scourged) fall: How he in prison kept, how freed from thence, If vvinds blow vvell, the Muse discouer shall. 98 For now shee's grieu'd so much with Iosephs wrong, That she but heauily and harshly sings; A troubled mind doth make an vntun'd Song, As muddy water flowes from trampled springs. Timens Deum, non habet quod timeat vlterius.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">IOSEPH IN CARCERE. OR, The Innocent Prisoner. 1 From hopes of Court, to horrors of a Iayle, From great respect, from friends, from wealth, from place, Vnto a loathsome dungeon without Bayle; A wofull fall: yet this was Iosephs case. 2 They which of late did crouch with cap and knee, And would haue done worse offices perhaps, In his reproach are open now and free, With bitter tongues discoursing his mishaps. 3 Now is he censur'd by the vulgar breath, For a most base, and most vnthankfull slaue, For a perfidious villaine, worthy death, And after death, vnworthy of a graue. 4 'Tis wretchednesse too much to be cast downe; What is it then to fall with infamie? But he that is to any greatnesse growne, Vpon a change must looke for obloquie. 5 Vnhappy Vertue cannot be secure, Scarce from the hands, not from the tongues assault, Faire actions foule constructions must indure, When our misfortunes shalbe thought our fault. 6 Nay Putipher himselfe is constru'd too, And pierc'd, perhaps, by the Plebeian wind, In that he would so vndiscreetly doe, As lay such trust vpon an vnknowne Hind. 7 Thou many-headed Monster that art bred Out of the vulgar mud, without all braine, How easely is thy erring judgement led? To passe a sudden sentence, idle, vaine, 8 Without all certaine ground, without all weight, Nay, without any scanning of the matter: But thou art sway'd with a receiu'd conceit, And thy light ayre soone turneth into water: 9 For rashly-heady, thou art easely borne Now vnto one, streight to another mind: So haue I seene a field of eared Corne Bending all South, blowne with a Southerne wind, 10 And let the same but shift into the North, Then stalkes and heads, and all doe bend that way: And can that man be vvise, of reall vvorth, That doth on such light puffes his fortunes lay? 11 But stay: Me thinkes my selfe forgets my course, And I begin to sayle without my Card, Though emptie Caskes without all true discourse, Are in their censures sudden, sowre and hard, 12 Yet hee that lookes with other eyes then men, And finds the heart vntainted with offence, Binds whom we free, &amp; frees whom vve condemne, 'Tis he alone that safe-gards innocence. 13 And oft he works beyond the reach of man, We cannot fathom him with our short lyne, We may as well graspe Heau'n within our span, As sound the depth of what he doth designe. 14 How could it be conceiu'd by mans discourse, That gives and fetters were the meanes to rise? Yet all-commanding God doth take that course, And Ioseph must be rays'd by enemies. 15 Me thinks I see him looking on his hands Fast bound vvith chaines, vvhich vnto heau'n hee reares, And are (sayes he) these heauy yron bands The golden bracelets that poore vertue weares? 16 Had my too cruell brothers bin so chain'd, I had not then bin thus in prison pent, Such manacles their furies had restrain'd, And I had bin as free, as innocent. 17 Or had I with my Lady chang'd imbraces When in her armes she would haue clasp'd me fast, I had not tasted then of these disgraces, Which will (I feare) proue fatall at the last. 18 Vertue, I thought, had bin a reall thing, But now I find, that 'tis an ayrie name: Hate did my brothers, lust my Lady sting, Yet neither they nor shee feele smart or blame. 19 But I that onely a meere Patient was, And not an agent with them in their sinne; 'Tis I alone that vndergoe the lash, And I must smart for what they faulted in. 20 Me thinks my crop should haue been like my seed, I planted Vertue, that sweet smelling Rose, And can that root such stinging Nettles breed? But there is vse of Nettles, so of foes. 21 Why was I called Ioseph? that's Increasing, And doe not I increase in misery? My name was rightly giu'n, for without ceasing My strange disasters daily multiply. 22 Yet Iob had been a fitter name for me: Iob, Sorrowfull, or hated, which you will: For that sad name doth both wayes vvell agree With those sad fortunes that pursue me still. 23 For am I not a man made vp of sorrow, Whose matter, and whose forme is vvretchednesse; Vnhappy now, but shall be more to morrow, My dayes are but additions to distresse. 24 That Sunne, that sees me breathing out my ill, Will shortly see me without any breath; Malice and meanes, a vvoman and her vvill, Lust and neglect; the very sounds of death. 25 And that will be the period of my paine, The short and sweet compendium of all vvoe: Weake-hearted Ioseph, raise thy spirits againe, Collect thy selfe, be not deiected so. 26 Oft hast thou heard thy father Jacob say, There was a Libra 'mongst the Signes of Heau'n, Who alwayes did in equall Ballance weigh The actes of men, and kept the Scales most eu'n. 27 And without doubt, when thou art truely weigh'd, Thou shalt goe current, though thou suffer now: Heau'n must not be contested; but obey'd, To whose iust ends all Mortals needs must bow. 28 And Ioseph, he that rays'd thee from the pit, Wheu thy enraged brothers play'd their part, Can find both time and meanes, when he thinkes fit, To free thee from this dungeon vvhere thou art. 29 But say hee doe not, why should wretched dust Be so much daring, as to question God? Whose Councels oft are secret, euer iust: If therefore still he please to vse the rod, 30 Bee it for me, I haue for my defence Armour of Proofe, to beare all blowes withall, A spotlesse and a peacefull Conscience, And that is safer then a brazen wall. 31 And, Ioseph, though thy sufferings be most great, Yet thinke vpon the letters of thy name, Which being inverted bring some comfort yet: For (Hope Is) is Ioseph his Anagramme: 32 And there is Hope; nay, there's assurance rather, Where God is pleas'd to interpose his hand, Who out of Poysons Antidotes doth gather, As by the Storie heere wee vnderstand: 33 For in close prison where poore Ioseph lyes, Mew'd vp in bolts and chaines to death and shame, Pursude by many dangerous enemies, Th' abused agents of a lustfull Dame: 34 There, (eu'n vnlook'd for there) vpon a day. (And sure 'twas God that put it in his mind) The Iaylor thought his Prison to survay, Where many soules, and foule ones he doth find. 35 Some theft, some bloody murther did commit: Ioseph, thy name is callenderd for lust, Which they tearm'd Rape; and (which did add to it) Thy Ladies Rape, against thy Lords deare trust. 36 Whom when the Iaylor viewes, through his faire face, A fayrer soule and heart hee sees within, (Inspir'd no doubt) hee finds the Iaylors grace, Who did not onely quit him of the sinne, 37 But of the paine: From chaines he sets him free, And (which was strange) he giues to him the charge Of all his fellow-prisners: so that hee Was both a prisner, and was yet at large. 38 Ioseph the prison kept, God Ioseph keepes, And he finds fauour eu'n amongst the bad: The Iaylor was secure, eates, drinkes, and sleepes, And trusted this faire youth with all he had. 39 And all that Ioseph did, (and hee did all) Did prosper farre beyond all expectation: Thus God can rayse, whom men would haue to fall, And this was strange and worthy admiration. 40 But see more wonders yet: some few dayes past, Pharoes chiefe Butler fell into disgrace, An! from the Court, was into Prison cast, And that (wee see) is oft a Courtiers case. 41 What was his fault, I list not to define, Great Kings are men, and subiect vnto Ire, Perhaps hee did not please his tast with wine, Small faults doe oft add fewell to their fire. 42 Perhaps some other itch'd to haue his place, Which could not bee, till hee was first remou'd: The fall of one is oft anothers grace: Such trickes are play'd at Cardes, and well approu'd. 43 And this (for ought I know) might be his case, But the true Cause I find not in the Text, But this I find: The Butler's in disgrace, And in the Prison too, and much perplext. 44 But yet this somewhat qualifyde his griefe, My Lord the Baker is committed too, And some good Natures hold it some releefe, To haue their friends partakers of their woe. 45 Some fatall starre in Egypt rul'd this yeare, So many starrs of Court from their Orbes fell, And yet no blazing Comet did appeare: Which to great states doe dire euents fore-tell. 46 But now these Lords to Josephs care committed, Are entertayn'd by him with much respect: Nothing that might content them was omitted, Yet miserie meetes often with neglect. 47 Sweet Natures doe behold calamitie, With Eyes of pittie, not of churlish scorne, 'Tis base to triumph ouer misery, To treade vpon a poore deiected worme. 48 Would'st thou behold the Picture of a slaue? This very Caracter shall speake him right, Bee sure to find him insolentlie braue, Against that man, whom fortune doth despight. 49 Hee is a fearefull Tyrant to affliction, A Phalaris vnto a sinking state: Nor doth he weigh the causes of deiection, 'Tis fault enough to be vnfortunate. 50 Ioseph is better moulded: He doth well And gently vse his charge (though in distresse) Affliction's wayward, apt to fret and swell, It need not to be gall'd with bitternesse. 51 I know not how these Lords did spend the day, But in one night they both fell on a Dreame: Dreames are the daughters of the wine (some say) But this was no such vapour, no such steame. 52 Ioseph (as was his vse) doth early wake, Sad Care, and quiet sleepe were euer foes, A thinking soule doth heauie Eye-lids make, For want of timely rest, and sweet repose. 53 His Charge, his Care was great, and soone he rises, And rising, finds his prisners much perplext; To tell the cause, he gently them advises, And fairely ask'd, what so their temper vext? 54 They answere freely: They had seene that night A Vision, or a Dreame, they knew not whether, And this the rather did them so affright, Because what it should meane, they cannot gather. 55 But Ioseph then replies, Dreames are from God, (That God whom Ioseph serues) please you vnfold The same, by me they may be vnderstood, Which cannot be expounded, if not told. 56 Gladly they tell the Youth what they had seene, And first the Butler doth his Vision shew: Me thought (quoth he) I saw a Vine all greene, Put forth three stocks, and fr? those stocks did grow 57 Leaues, branches, grapes, that were both ripe &amp; faire; Into my hand (me thought) I tooke the cup, And prest the grapes: The King was debonaire, Receiu'd the liquour fairely, drunke it vp. 58 Ioseph replies: The Dreame is very good, And (noble Lord) this is th'interpretation: By the three stockes three dayes are vnderstood, That will restore thee to thy former station. 59 And when my Lord before the King shall stand, And giue him wine, as hee was wont to doe, And hee shall take the Goblet from thy hand, Remember Ioseph, Partner of thy woe. 60 And by thy noble selfe, I thee adiure, Who now canst tell what is a Pris'ners case, Remember me to Pharaoh, and procure My liberty, from this delightlesse place. 61 VVho am a stranger, and by force was brought, Out of my natiue Countrey to this land, Sold by my brethren, and by Merchants bought, And why kept here, I scarsely vnderstand. 62 Thus Ioseph thought it fit, to vse his friends, To compasse his deliuerance, if hee can: Hee must vse meanes, that will attayne his Endes: Good fortune hath forlworne a carelesse man. 63 VVee must not thinke, that wish'd felicitie VVill drop downe from the cloudes, like showers of raine Our selues must watch all opportunitie, Vse all Endeuour, if wee vvill attayne 64 VVhat vvee desire: Some say, that Iupiter Doth sell his blessings: and the price wee pay, Is our ovvne labour: and they much doe erre, VVho thinke by standing still, to end their vvay. 65 But I goe on: vvhen Ioseph had fore-told, The Butler thus, It seemes the Diuination, Did likevvise Please the Baker: vvho grevv bold, To tell his Dreame, hoping like Explanation. 66 Mee thought (hee sayes) I boare vpon my head, Three Baskets, full of bak'd meates, and of bread, And round about the vppermost there fled, Birds of the Ayre, that from that basket fedde. 67 The Augure sayes: Three baskets three dayes bee, In fine vvhereof, prepare to loose thy head, And thou shalt hanged bee vpon the Tree, And vvith thy flesh, The Birds and Rauens bee fedd. 68 The houres spend quickly: and that very day, The third (I meane the Critick of the dreame) VVas Pharaoh's birth day: (As the Text doth say) VVherein hee feasts the Nobles of his Realme, 69 And to make good what was divin'd before, The King the Baker hangeth by command, But did the Butler to his place restore, Who gaue againe his Cup into his hand. 70 And this great Lord (so must I call him now) Regaining Honour, promises forgot, And (as some Courtiers doe) neglects his vow, Per Dures made: such vowes we know bind not. 71 Why should he take to heart anothers harme? He had no feeling how poore Ioseph far'd, Himselfe (hee thanks his starres) was well &amp; warme, What others suffred, he nor felt, nor car'd. 72 Indeed we doate vpon our selues too much, And that divides vs from all due respect: Nature (we see) doth often loose her touch; Then 'tis not strange, that strangers should neglect 73 The loving service, and kind entertaine Of honest Ioseph, are forgotten quite; Looke what he did, was but for hope of gaine, And all he did, no more then was his right. 74 Vnthankfulnesse is euer apt to find, At least some colours wherewithall to paint: Good turnes receiu'd vve giue vnto the wind, And in requitall we are dull and faint. 75 Because it is no pleasing Meditation For mounting men, that are to greatnesse growne, Alwayes to thinke vpon their Obligation, And what an answering kindnesse must be showne. 76 Two yeeres of dayes run on, and all this while The Butler (drunke with honour) soundly sleeps, No care of Ioseph, and of his exile, He dreames not, and his vow therefore not keepes. 77 And here my musing thoughts are at a stand, And I doe more then marvell, that so long Poore Ioseph scap'd the knife; the bloody hand Of his enraged Lord, vvhose thought of vvrong, 78 Of most vnworthy wrong (as he might deeme) Might whet him to the worst of punishment: But graunt, that Time did coole his boyling spleene, And that the malice of his madnesse spent 79 On it's owne matter, did extinguish so, As fierie meteors in the feeding Ayre, The vapors being consum'd whence they did grow, Cease of themselues: but that his Dames dispayre 80 Of euer now attayning her blacke ends, Arm'd with the furie of neglected loue, Impatient with reuenge, which neuer lends One thought of peace, but doth with madnes moue, 81 To bring his plotted Tragedie to act, And so to free her selfe from all her feares, How she (I say) should so long time protract, As not to worke his end within these yeeres, 82 Is more then my conceit can diue into. But (O) thou deepe vnfounded Providence, We must admire what thou art pleas'd to doe, And not survey thy workes by our vveake sense. 83 Thicke clouds and darknesse doe encompasse thee, And are about thy great Pauilion; Wonder wee may, and must adorers bee Of all thy workes: but we must let alone 84 All curious Queres, and all busie prying Into those secrets which thou dost conceale: We melt our wings, and fall, by too high flying; Prometheus, that the fire from Heau'n did steale, 85 Was sharply punisht for his enterprise: That outward barke containes this pith within, We must not labour to be ouer-wise; To prie into Gods Arke, it is a sinne. 86 We know 'twas he that calm'd these billowing seas, And brought wrackt Ioseph to his hau'n at last, Else had hee sunke vnder such stormes as these, But that Gods hand (his Anchor) held him fast. 87 And now th'eternall and still-waking Eye, (That is all Eye to see, to helpe all Hand) Lookes downe at last on Iosephs miserie, And finds him by affliction fully fann'd, 88 And streight he stirres: and now all other meanes, (All hopefull meanes) doe seeme to fayle him quite, Now hee (in mercy pitying his extreames) Doth rouse himselfe, to doe wrong'd Ioseph right. 89 O happie men that are in Gods protection, No earthly Monarch hath a guard so sure: Legions of Angels serue at his direction, To fortresse those, whom he will haue secure. 90 All the whole Creature is at his command, The Sunne stands still to wayt on Ioshua, The Starres of Heau'n (enrolled in his band) Doe in their courses fight 'gainst Sisera. 91 Nay, fire and vvater too are ioy'nd in one, Both starres and streames doe their best helpe afford, The riuer Kishon vnto armes doth runne, Iudg. 20. 21 To fight the glorious battels of the Lord. 92 The Elements are Marshals of his hoste, By night the fiery Pillar, and by day The Cloud conducts his people to their coast, To which the very Sea it selfe giues way. 93 The Vict'lere of his Campe he makes the Winds, Somtimes with bread from Heau'n, sometimes with Quailes; The stony rocke plenty of water finds, To giue his Souldiers drinke when water failes. 94 O euer to be fear'd, and lou'd withall, (Fear'd for thy might, and for thy mercy lou'd) I am all wonder, when to mind I call, With what strange weights thy motions still are mou'd. 95 Ioseph must be releast: that's the Decree, And from the Prison to the Court be brought, That's in the Order too: And now let's see How God doth worke, till all his will be wrought: 96 First vnto Pharaoh (Egypts King) he sends A double Dreame, with which hee's much perplext: He wakes, and longs to know what it portends; (What the Dreames were, I leaue you to the Text) 97 Then doth he send, and summon to the Court All Egypts Magi, to expound his Dreames: They heare them told, but cannot make report Vnto the King, what this his Vision meanes, 98 And that was strange: Th'Egyptians were renownd Aboue all Nations, for their skill that way, In hidden Learning they were held profound, And so the sacred Text doth seeme to say. 99 Witnesse beside the skill they labour'd so, In that abstruse and secret Mysterie Of Hieroglyphicke Art, which they did shew In an obscure deepe-shadow'd Charactrie. 100 But yet in this the Magi must be blind, Because the taske for Ioseph was reseru'd; And now the Butler wakes, and cals to mind Forgotten Ioseph, vvhom he thus preferr'd: 101 Great King, I must confesse my fault this day, And craue your pardon: I haue broke a vow Which once I made (when I in prison lay) Vnto an Hebrew, and remember now: 102 When as my Lord was vvith his servants vvroth, And put his Baker, and my selfe in chaines, A vision in one night appear'd to both, And there this Hebrew pris'ner it explaines. 103 And as he did divine, it did succeed, You hang'd your Baker, tooke me to your grace, Th'inspired Prophet can your Dreame aread. Make haste (quoth Pharaoh) let me see his face. 104 And now is Ioseph sent for to the Court, And (new adorn'd) doth looke as fresh as May, And well he might doe so, there's reason for't: Good fortunes breed good blood, good spirits (men say.) 105 Being come, the King doth take him by the hand, (Eu'n Kings know to be kind, to gaine their ends) Although no phrase did fit him but command, Yet he vnto a milder forme descends, 106 And (welcome) sayes: I had a Dreame this night, And what is meant thereby I faine would learne; And thou in Visions hast (I heare) insight, Thy piercing eye heau'ns secrets doth discerne. 107 And then hee tels him, what before he told To Egypts Magi. Ioseph streight replies: Your double dreame one meaning doth infold, And that God will not hide from Pharaohs eyes. 108 In me it is not; but the God of Heau'n Gen. 41. 16 Shall answere Pharaoh to his hearts desire. Poore puffe-past Man, here is example giu'n Vnto thy swelling thoughts, not to aspire. 109 Not to assume the glory and the praise Vnto thy selfe, of what is giu'n to thee: Thy parts are but reflections from those Rayes, By whose faire beames thy clouds dispersed be. 110 Cymerian darknesse doth possesse thy spirit; If gracious God be pleas'd to lend thee light, Wilt thou ascribe it to thy proper merit? And steale from him that which is his in right? 111 Wilt thou vnto thy Netts doe sacrifice? Hab. 1. 16 And hug thy selfe in th'armes of thine owne loue? If thou beest noble, learned rich, and wise, Know, 'tis the highest sphere that makes thee moue. 112 Thy graces are but Donatiues from Heau'n, The good is thine, returne the glory thither, For feare God take away what he hath giu'n, And he that made thee grow doth make thee wither 113 What, is not this great Babel I haue built Dan. 4. 30 To shew my power, perpetuate my name? Alas (poore Prince) thy outside is but guilt, A sudden storme will wash away the same. 114 For whilst the word was yet eu'n in thy mouth, A voyce from Heau'n did tell thee heauy newes, Promotion comes not from the North or South, Heau'ns influence onely doth all good infuse. 115 I could not choose when I had yoak'd my Teame, But make this furrow to enrich my field, And now I doe returne to Pharaohs Dreame, Whose Exposition Ioseph thus doth yeeld: 116 The seu'n fat Oxen that you saw ascend, That were so faire to sight in your first dreame, Seu'n yeeres of ioyfull plentie doe portend, Seu'n yeeres of famine the seu'n leane ones meane. 117 The Eares of Corne divine the selfe same thing: But God is good, and what he meanes to doe, He now is pleas'd to shew vnto the King, And giue him warning ere it shall ensue. 118 After seu'n yeeres of store, seu'n yeeres of want, Of bitter famine shall the land oppresse, Wherein both bread and food shall be so scant, As all the land shall mourne for barrennesse. 119 Twice did my God present it to your view, Because he would haue Pharaoh marke it well: When God speaks one thing twice, beleeue 'tis true; Make vse (great King) of what I doe foretell. 120 Cull out some man that's provident and wise, And let him be Surveyor of your Land, Let him collect the fruits that shall arise From forth the first seu'n yeeres of plentie, and 121 Let every Towne and Citie Garners build, Where they may safely lay vp corne and graine; And when those Garners are so stor'd and fild, Take care (O King) it be not spent in vaine. 122 The King was glad to heare the Divination, And his great servants were as glad as hee: What man so fit as thou in all the Nation, (The King replies) in whom heau'ns graces be? 123 Be it as thou hast sayd: Thy selfe alone Shall be the Regent of my Land and State. Onely my selfe will sit vpon the Throne, And next my selfe I thee subordinate. 124 With that he takes the Signet from his hand, And therewith Iosephs finger doth invest; A golden chaine (the Ensigne of command) Puts on his Necke: clads him in linnen vest. 125 And on his second Charret makes him ride, Whil'st through the Court the Trumpets sound his name, By officers, who were therein imployd, Who seem'd most forward to performe the same. 126 Because that Ioseph now is in his spring, But if a Winter should but chance to come, Those Nightingales that now so sweetly sing, I doubt, would chaunge their notes, or els be dumbe. 127 Nay (which is worse) they would like Adders bee, And hisse and bite: Greatnesse trust not too much, Vnto a smiling brow, a Cringing knee, A soothing tongue: they'l scarse abide the touch, 128 When they are truely brought vnto the Test: Momus did find an errour in Ioues Art, Because he made no windowes in mans breast, By which he might both see and know his heart. 129 Well Ioseph now is mounted very high, And God hath rays'd him to a loftie Pitch, Whose Agent Pharoah still doth multiply: His fauours to him: Hee growes great and rich. 130 The eyes of Kings are more then common eyes, They are the starres that doe predominate, Th'affayres of men, and in their influence lyes, The good or badd of euery ones estate. 131 They are the Primum Mobile of all, They whirle about our fortunes, as they list: Their motions make Inferiours rise or fall: And as they fauour, wee are curst or blest. 132 Though Poets fictions seeme to sauour much Of Idle Errours, yet they haue their sence: King Midas turn'd to gold all hee did touch, The morall is: the fauour of the Prince. 133 This gracious hand can worke the like effect, Not India's richest mines breede purer gold, Then those fayre Rayes of comfort that reflect, From th'eyes of Kings: there growes that precious mold. 134 Whose smooth and smiling brow is the true place, Of honour, wealth, respect, dependencie, And in his frowning Fore-head dwels disgrace, Common contempt, hate, wrong, and pouertie. 135 And it is fitting, that it should bee so, All Light must bee deriued from the Sunne, And as all Riuers from the Sea first flowe, So they againe into the Sea must runne. 136 Pharoah still studies to doe Ioseph good, And (to compleate the pleasures of his life) Fayre Asenath, of grace and Princely blood, A beautious Virgine, must bee Iosephs wife. 137 Asenath, Daughter of the Prince of On: Thus for his seruants gracious God prouides, Who after troubles and affliction, Fils vp their ioyes: as rivers the Spring-tides. 138 Now you haue seene a true particular Of Iosephs fortunes, weigh them at a Beame, His sowre, his sweet, his losse, his gaine conferre, 'Twill be a vsefull and delightfull Theame. 139 Ioseph remou'd from Canaans fruitfull Soyle, Planted in Egypt, with great growth is blest; In vulgar Phrase this may be cal'd Exile, But that's a mans best countrey where hee's best. 140 In Canaan Ioseph in a Pit I find, Here I doe see him next the Regall Throne, There hee hath many brothers, but vnkind: Here many fauours are by strangers showne. 141 But hee's diuided from a Fathers sight, To whom hee was as deare, as his owne Eyes: In liew whereof a monarch of great might, Eu'n Pharoahs loue old Iacobs losse supplyes. 142 And yet hee is not lost: Hee shall bee met, With a more tender touch of true delight: So broken bones proue stronger, being well set, And darkest grounds make white to seeme more white. 143 The Ishmalites did sell him for a slaue, But (loe) hee's rays'd to bee a power-full Lord: The Prison, (that at least was ment his graue) The meanes of his aduancement doth afford. 144 His first disaster did arise from dreames, And dreames must cure the woundes that dreames did make Friends oft do faile their friends in their extreames, But God his seruants neuer doth forsake. 145 Twas hee that made this Metamorphosis, And marke how all his workes are fitted right: The Prison to a Pallace changed is, The yron grates to Prospects of delight. 146 His Alchymy did turne the gyues hee wore, (The yron gyues) Into a golden chayne, With course and common cates hee fedde before, Now Sea and Land both giue him entertayne. 147 Without all doubt Ioseph did often beare, The bitter burden of offensiue scorne: Now ( A word of honour amongst them. Abrech, Abrech) sounds in euery eare, Whil'st in his Charet hee's in Triumph borne. 148 The loathsome Sauours change to sweet perfumes, The Prison garment to a Robe of Price, The groanes of wretched Soules to cheerefull tunes, All hell indeed is turn'd to Paradice. 149 And for th'imbraces of an vnchaste Dame, (Whose softest touch is but an Aspicks sting, Whose fayrest lookes doe breed a hellish flame, Whose sweetest breath a deadly dampe doth bring) 150 Ioseph enioyes the pure and heauenly heat Of both a lawfull and delightfull bed, Whose vertuous pleasures onely are compleat, From whence there is nor shame, nor sorrow bred. 151 Well, then I see the Prouerbe holdeth true, Bees make not hony onely for the bad, Triumphant Vertue shall attaine his due, Whose acts endswel, though the first sceanes be sad. 152 Where sinne seemes Suger to vs at first tast, Which oft we swallow down with deepe delight, But still it ends in bitternesse at last, And proues to bee a deadly Aconite. 153 Well, Ioseph is at rest with his faire Phere, And that (my weary Muse) is fit for thee. For this time (loe) I pitch my Pillers here, And (Ne plus vltra) shall my Posie bee. Timens Deum, non habet quod timeat vlterius. IOSEPH IN SVMMO. OR, The Noble Favourite. 1 Now after thunder and tempestuous stormes, The purged aire grows to be calme &amp; cleare, And all the stars put on their fairest formes, To smile on Ioseph each one from its Sphere. 2 Old froward Saturne (earst malevolent) Is now appeas'd by his more gentle Sonne, Whose sweet aspect hath made him eminent, And he is seated next the Kingly throne. 3 Sterne Mars, that but of late was bent to blood. Being now with Venus in coniunction. Hath chang'd his fury to a milder mood, And now from Armes he is to Amours wonne. 4 Sol shines vpon him with his cherefull rayes, Who giues him wealth; and Hermes eloquence, And Cynthia shee her brightest beames displayes, And he growes fruitfull by her influence. 5 But these are not the giuers of our good, 'Tis onely God that doth command them all, And his commands can neuer be withstood: He smiles, and men doe rise; He frownes, they fall. 6 The Planets are but agents of his will, They rule in vs sometimes, he rules them euer: The Alluding to the blessed Trinitie.Trine aspect is the most blessed still, Who's vnder that can be vnhappy neuer. 7 Ioseph was so, vvho but of late was seene, Eu'n in his depth of Winter almost dead; And (loe) a sudden Spring hath made him greene, Much growne in height, and very greatly spread. 8 Obserue the flowes and ebbes of Mans estate; See how that part of the still turning vvheele, Which was but low, and toucht the ground of late, Is now the highest, and will straight wayes reele 9 Downe to the Center: No man is so fix'd, But that he may be soone remoou'd againe, The vvorld hath nothing simple: all is mix'd, An houre of pleasure, and a day of paine. 10 Therefore what ere thou be, doe not despaire, Loose not thy fortunes, and thy hopes together: Thy Morning's foule, thine Euening may be faire, For Mans estate doth alter like the weather. 11 Oft haue I heard some aged men foretell Or following Raine, by th'aking of their bones: I doe not like that Almanacke so well, Ide rather fetch my skill from sweating stones: 12 For stones (some say) will sweat against a raine: That may be so: but this is certaine true, Our states haue somtimes cramps, then sound again, Then sicke againe, and then comes health anew. 13 Joseph you saw late in a deadly swoune, Now he recouers, and to strength doth grow, Who (notwithstanding all his great renowne) Doth not forget why he was raysed so. 14 Hee knowes although hee were a Magistrate, T'was not for his owne ends, or for his ease, But to prouide for, and preserue the state, Which seuen yeares bitter famine els would seyze. 15 Hee thinkes vpon his worke hee hath to doe: Hee mouldes his busines in his carefull minde: Great King, braue Court, deare wife to all adue, Ioseph must sayle now with another winde. 16 Hee's Country-bound: and now hee doth prouide, For following famine, In the yeares of store: 'Tis good (men say) to take both Wind and Tyde, And whil'st they both serue well, to ply the Oare. 17 Mee thinkes, I doe behold this labouring Bee, How hee flyes vp and downe to store his hiue, And (sweetest time) hee gathers most from thee, And so must all Bees doe that meane to thriue. 18 There are some happy houres which if wee take, Wee crowne our labours with desir'd successe, And if those fitting seasons wee forsake, Wee well may wish them more, but find them lesse. 19 Hee builds, hee gathers, and hee layes vp grayne, The best of his abilityes hee spends, In ceass-lesse labour, and vnwearied payne: That hee may bee succesfull in his ends. 20 It was no May-game that hee had in hand, His charge was weighty, and requir'd him all; Men that are great in Place, and in command, Are not their owne, must not bee seuerall. 21 They must be like the Sunne, whose common flame, Affordeth heate and light to euery-one, Ther's more in greatnes then the very name, It hath much matter for to worke vpon. 22 The prudent states-man often-times doth wake, Whil'st sweet Repose seales vp the vulgar Eye: His countrey care oft makes his head to ake, With forging thousand formes of policie. 23 And without doubt, they which sit neere the healme And haue the greatest steerage of the state, Are the most painefull seruants of the Realme, To whom the Prince his power doth delegate. 24 Both for his owne, and for his Countreys good, Which must be the chiefe end of their endeauors: So Ioseph is imployd to gather food, And in that seruice seuen yeeres he perseuers. 25 And the Almightie pleas'd to blesse him so, That he did store vp graine in such a measure, As that the number numberlesse did grow, And yet he was not barr'd from lawfull pleasure: 26 For in those yeeres God gaue him two fayre Boyes, To be the staffe of his declining Eld, And in those blessings Iosephs soule more joyes, Then in the greatest honours that he held: 27 Manasseh, Ephraim, (comforts of his life) You are his glory, and his strength beside, Himselfe divided was, his loving wife, His children vvere himselfe, but multiplide: 28 So many selues will make one selfe long liu'd, In whom he still shall liue, when he is dead: Egypt saw Josephs end, yet hee surviu'd In those faire boughs, that from his root were spred. 29 But I must to my taske, for Time goes on, And (as men say) flies with a Swallowes vving: The yeeres of plentie soone are past and gone, And famine now thrusts forth her deadly sting; 30 And then how Ioseph did himselfe deport, How well he gouern'd his long-gather'd graine, And how all Egypt did to him resort For needfull food, whose sale brought in great gaine 31 To his Lords coffers: how he bought their Land, Their goods, their cattell, and themselues vvithall, The sacred Writ will make you vnderstand. Egypt farewell: for Canaan now doth call. 32 Yet this before I goe, (obserue it well) And 'tis but touch'd, to shame our wretched Time: Although wise Ioseph, (as the Text doth tell) Did make a purchase of th'Egyptian Clime 33 To his Kings vse: yet did he hold his hand From buying of the Priests that which was theirs, He would not meddle vvith the Holy land, 'Twas consecrated: therefore he forbeares 34 Such irreligious purchase: yet the King, Supplyes them, with all necessary food: Though th? their fields no fruitful crops did bring; Yet they that serued for the common good, 35 T'was iust the common-good should serue for them, Eu'n Heathen people held it pietie, To furnish with fit meanes religious men: Although they worship'd a false Dietie. 36 How then should wee respect and honour too, The faithfull seruants of the liuing Lord? And so (wee see) our sacred Soueraigne doe: And (O) mee thinkes his Copie should afford 37 A fayre example, for to guide our hand; In other things Autoritie swayes much: And wee are willing Apes to great command: But yet in this wee haue too little touch. 38 And so (indeed) wee haue in all deuotion, Our heau'n is on the Earth: wee sweate for that: Our Ayme's at wealth, at honour, and promotion, And in pursuite of them, w'are very hot. 39 But stay, my Muse, why dost thou change thy course? For thou wert shipt and bound for Canaan, Where famine likewise raged with great force; Eu'n Iacob wants, that vvas a vvealthy man, 40 That had both Coyne, and Cattell at command, Strong in his issue, and belou'd of God: Yet now hee's vnder his afflicting hand, Whose dearest children cannot scape the rod. 41 And he doth often rule them with blacke Lead, That he may keepe them straighter in the line. And (left by rest there should a rust be bred) By filing them hee doth them oft refine. 42 Therefore thou happy soule, that seekes for Heau'n, Expect not here a Deluge of delight: If God doth make thy cares and comforts eu'n, It is a worke of Mercie, not of right. 43 When Iacob heard, that Egypts store did yeeld Sufficient graine, eu'n for a forren good, He cals to him his sonnes, and then he wild They should for Egypt make, to buy some food. 44 Hee needs not bid them spur (the Prouerbe sayes) Whom bitter famine on their way doth driue, They take their fathers blessing, goe their wayes: And speed for Egypt, where they soone arriue. 45 To Ioseph brought, their busines they declare, And to the ground their humble knees they bow, VVithout his warrant they can haue no ware: And by the name of Lord salute him now. 46 Ioseph his brethren sees, and wonders much, And now his former dreames hee cals to mind: Hee beares him selfe, as if hee had no touch, Of nature in him: striues to bee vnkind. 47 Hee knew them well: but would not know them now O, they were spies, and came to search the land, Corne was their Colour, but they practis'd how To bring all Egypt vnder their command. 48 How soone may greatnesse draw the innocent, At least within the seeming gripe of lawes? And if it bee to rigorous courses bent, How readily it finds, or makes a cause? 49 The brethren tell him, that they came to buy, Food for their father, and their familyes, That they his seruants ment no trachery, That they were neither borne, nor bred for spyes. 50 That they were one mans sons, who had two more, And that the youngest with their Syre was left, And that the other was (long time before) By fatall accident from him bereft. 51 I, thence it is, that I suspect you spyes, You goe not hence, except that youth come hither, By this you shall be try'd (Ioseph replyes) As by a third they parley'd thus together. 52 Ther's no contesting with great Ioseph now: They must to Prison, whither they were sent, Till farther time more leasure did allow, And better meanes, to sound their whole entent. 53 Imprisonment, thou art the liuing graue, Wherein to bury men, whil'st they are quicke, And yet the soule may freest motions haue: Although the body bee immur'd with bricke, 54 For nothing can confine the working soule, That may recourse vnto Heau'ns glorious frame, And compasse all the vvorld vvithout controule, And see, and sound the actions of the same. 55 An able actiue Sir Th. Palmer died with Iohn D. of Northumb in I. Q. Mary. Ioh. Stowe.Gentleman of worth, That lost his head vvhen Mary swayd the State, Vpon the Scaffold freely gaue it forth, That he had learn'd more in the Tower of late, 56 Then in the course of all his life beside, Being vvell-traveil'd, vvell-imployd at home; And yet (quoth he) whilst I did there abide, I got more knowledge in yon little roome, 57 (Poynting vnto a corner of the Tower) Then before that I euer could attaine: For there I learn'd to know Gods supreame power, My selfe a sinfull worme, the vvorld most vaine. 58 O happy man, that studiest well this art; And happy place that made him study so: And blessed Bookes (deare bolts) that did impart Such sacred, secret Science, vvhich few know, 59 And fewer care to learne: and that's the cause Why our desires so doat on vanitie, That we are carried hood-wink'd vvithout pause, Into vnseene, but certaine miserie. 60 I may eu'n of my selfe an instance make: When did I entertaine such thoughts as these? Oh vvhen did I this theame for subiect take? Whilst sin (begot with wealth, and nurst with ease, 61 Confirm'd with vse) did onely sway my will, Without all care of God, my selfe, or other. But this is not the story of my ill, The brothers call me, shut vp by a brother, 62 And so restrain'd, and all remoou'd from them: Me thinks, I seeme to see them, how they stare Each vpon other, like amazed men, Wondring both why, and how, and where they are. 63 A three dayes durance they indured there: Ioseph, thou keep'st not iust proportion, One day the Pit contain'd thee, and vvas cleare Of thee againe before the setting Sunne. 64 The punishment in this transcendes th'offence, Eu'n like for like, had bin equalitie: Yet Ioseph, this Ile say in thy defence, And truely, without partialitie. 65 Their act was diu'llish, and vnnaturall, Which cast vpon thee many-yeares-restraynt, In daily feare of death (the gall of gall) Whil'st their vnsuffring soules no care did taynt. 66 No thought of thee, no pittie of thy wrong, And therefore now they very iustly beare This short, and easie durance: thine was long, And vndeseru'd: thou free, they faultie were. 67 And yet it seemes, that Iosephs soule did grieue; For sending for them, thus to them hee sayd: I likewise feare your God: doe this, and liue: Let one of you a Pris'ner here be stayd, 68 The rest returne vnto your aged Sire, Both his, and your owne wants shalbe supplide, But bring your brother with you I require, For that's the Test whereby you shalbe tryde. 69 Ioseph had spoke the vvord, they must obey; And yet they tooke it to the very heart, And to themselues in their owne language say, That these their sufferings came by due desert. 70 Although that they were spotlesse of this crime, Wherewith vniustly they were charg'd vvithall, Yet when they cast th'account of their whole time, And summ'd vp all their actes in generall, 71 They found a Brother missing, whom they sold, (Stirr'd vp by spleenefull hatred) to his graue, And now ther are by sad Remembrance told, That they must Legem talionis haue. 72 Now Conscience giveth better Evidence, Who is both Witnesse and Tormentor too, And Reuben now vpbraids them with th'offence, Now see, what your blind malice made you doe. 73 I wish'd you not to sinne against the youth, But you were deafe as Adders, would not heare, Now is his blood requir'd: And now in truth, Your seed of sinne this crop of shame doth beare. 74 They doe confesse th'Indictment, 'twas too true, Their brothers blood did for iust vengeane crie, And now the hand of Heau'n payes them their due, And they are caught in their impietie. 75 O sinne, the fretting corr'siue of the heart, The biting worme that breeds within the breast, A sure, but sad remembrancer thou art, No rest till done, and then indeed no rest. 76 Well, now there's no resisting Iosephs will: Of all extreames 'twas best to chuse the least: Simeon as Pledge must stay in prison still, (For so was Josephs choyce) for all the rest, 77 Who were dismist in peace, and all their sackes By Iosephs Officers vvere fild with graine, Who likewise put their moneys in their packes, And vvhat they brought, restor'd to them againe. 78 Home they returne, and to their father tell How Egypt vs'd them, what the Ruler sayd, Of all things in the voyage them befell, A short, plaine, true narration to him made. 79 You may conceiue, that aged Israell, Heard the relation with a great distast: And inwardly his grieued heart did swell, Till thus it leap't into his tongue at last. 80 Ioseph is not: Simeon is not to mee, And shall I likewise Beniamin forgoe? Why haue you done these things: since these things be Against your father, and all worke his woe. 81 What, doe you find your owne affections such, As that you hold the losse of Children light? In my sad soule I feele another touch, And nature workes in mee with powerfull might. 82 The motions of a tender father's loue: An vntouch'd heart can hardly comprehend: But you are fathers too: and well may proue, Eu'n by your selues: that nature doth discend. 83 I cannot yeeld, that Beniamin should goe, His brother's dead, and hee is left alone: If hee should die, I should but liue in woe, And dying, goe into my graue with moane. 84 When hee was borne, his mother was bereft mee, My dearest Rachell (see, you make mee weepe) And nothing now of her, but him is left mee, And (as her dying Pledge) I him will keepe. 85 Thus hee resolu'd: but famine still growes hot, The food was almost spent, that late was brought: In Canaan there was little to bee got: A new supply from Egypt must bee sought. 86 The stately Steed that champes the steely bit, And proudly seemes to menace friend and foe, Doth fling and foame, and boundeth oft, and yet, (Poore beast) perforce hee is inforc'd to goe. 87 And good-old Israell, so it fares with thee, Thy Beniamin must goe: there is no boot, For all thy other sonnes in this agree: That without him, they will not stirre a foot. 88 Better at home to end their weary race, And with their dearest friends together dye: Then goe and seeke for death in a strang place, And that with publicke scorne, and infamie. 89 Besides his Iudah earnest suit did make, That to his care hee would commit his sone: His deare-lou'd Darling, hee would vndertake, For his returne: which should be safe, and soone. 90 Iacob replyes: it must bee so (I see) Well, take with you the best fruits of the land, Gifts silent speakers, but preuailers bee: For Haukes come not vnto an emptie hand. 91 Therefore take somewhat of each seu'rall thing, To shew your thankfull mindes in worst extreames: A better fortune greater gifts would bring: But your poore present answeares to your meanes. 92 And in your hand the money hither brought, Doubly returne: for feare some ouersight By you my sonnes should formerly be wrought: And take your brother too, my chiefe delight. 93 And when that you haue done all that you may, God make you gracious in the great-mans eyes, For onely hee must guy'd you in your way: And giue a blessing to your enterprize. 94 I, holy father, tha's the poynt indeed, Now thou hast hit the nayle vpon the head, The best of our endeuours cannot speede, If by the hand of heau'n not seconded. 95 Vaine are their thoughts, that think their watching can Preserue that Cittie, which God doth not keepe, And their's as vaine, who quit all vse of man, And thinke that God will guard them, though they sleepe 96 Where to our safetie our sedulitie, Is requisite: God seldome workes alone, Neglect of meanes is fond credulitie, First for the Lord, and then for Gideon. Iudg. 7. 18. 97 And that's the only course that men can take, Vnto Gods blessing ioyne thyne owne endeuour, Heau'n helpes not him, that doth him-selfe forsake, The end and meanes doe alwayes goe together. 98 But stay my muse, mee thinkes thy pace is slow, Thou mak'st no speed in thy intended way: Perhaps th'art tyr'de with trauell to and fro, Then take thyne Inne vntill some other day. 99 Or els perhaps the famine makes thee faynt, Which works too strongly in thy feeble braine: I, ther's the gall: These are thy yeares of want, Some better times will make thee sing againe. Timens Deum, non habet quod timeat vlterius. The Continuation. 1 After a blessing from their aged Syre, To Egypt land the Brethren bend their course, A speedy helpe such sad extreames require, They needs must haste, whom griping famin force. 2 Some time being spent, and weary travell past, Once more they gaine the wisht-for Land of food, And once againe before the face at last, Of their knowne Lord, but vnknown Brother stood; 3 Who had their errand, e'r they could it tell, He knew 'twas Hunger forc'd them to that place: 'Twas Egypts food that must that Monster quell, And that could not be had without his grace. 4 He could not likewise choose but call to mind Their cruell and vnnat'rall insolence, How once with envie more then famine pynd, To thraldome they betrayd his innocence. 5 Without regard of dutie to their Syre, Or pitie to the moanes of him their brother: Now time seru'd fit for to repay their hyre; Yet all these faults his tender loue doth smother, 6 And his mild Heart relents to see their want They were his Brothers though before vnkind, Perhapps (saith hee) their error they recant And if they doe, shall they not pardon find? 7 So fed, his Beniamin he doth behold, Then calls his Steward, wills him to prepare Plenty of Meat. Those Hebrew-strangers should Dyne at his hoame, and of his bounty fare. 8 To Iosephs house the Steward leads these Men, They went vnwilling being sore afraid, Their hearts misgaue them some state-plot ev'n then To worke their Bondage cunningly was layd. 9 And therefore to the Steward they confesse That food of him they once had bought before Feare was so powrefull, they could doe no lesse Their full confess' on pardon doth implore. 10 They told him that the price, last paid for Graine, Was vnexpected found in each Mans sacke, But they that silver, and as much againe For new supplies had honestly brought backe. 11 The Steward saies, all's peace, be not dismay'd Your God, your fathers God that silver gaue, I had your money; for the Corne ye payd: And you, your Symion left for pledge shall haue. 12 Them all, into his Lords faire house he guides Prepares them water for to wash their Feete, And for their Beasts he provender provides, With other things for their refreshment meet. 13 Meane while the great Lord they prepare to greet, With those rich presents they from Canaan brought He's now retur'd from Court, loe at his Feete They prostrate fall, and him of grace besought. 14 To buy some food his favour they desire, He kindly greets them, rayseth them from ground And quest'ond them how far'd their aged Syre The good old Man, they spake off; safe and sound? 15 They lowly bow'd againe, then make replye Our aged Syre thy servant yet doth liue Wherewith on Beniamin he cast his Eye, And loving lookes vnto the Lad doth giue, 16 Is this the youth of whom ye earst did tell, To thee my sonne (he said) God gracious be: With that kind Nature in his breast doth swell, His bowels yernd his Mothers sonne to see. 17 Moou'd by affection, be from them vvithdrawes, And in his priuate chamber weepes amaine: Then dries his eyes after a little pause, With cheerefull lookes he visits them againe. 18 Meane while good Ioseph rowes against the tide, Nature, kind Nature would it selfe display, But (willing) yet awhile himselfe to hide, He forc'd his Loue, Discretion to obey. 19 He cals for meat, which was seru'd vp in state, And at the table he doth sit alone: The Hebrewes vvere in order seru'd, vvhereat Within himselfe, they marveiled each one. 20 The Hebrewes and Egyptians severd set: For by the Law of the Egyptian Nation, They might not at one board together eat, Because by them 'twas held abomination. 21 To count the seuerall dishes of this Feast In these deare times, would make my Muse too sad, Messes they had, the Text saith, who had least, But Beniamin fiue times their portion had. 22 They are full-fed now vvith delicious cates, Whose hungry soules did whilome pine for food, Such is the change of our vncertaine states, After a dead low water, comes a flood. 23 The fickle vvorld is neuer at one stay, Humane affaires roule in vncertaintie, Vaine men, vve ring the Changes: euery day Brings forth, to light, some new varietie. 24 Then let this ceaselesse, restlesse agitation Inflame our soules; all our affections moue To seeke for rest, and a sure habitation In Heau'n the new Ierusalem aboue. 25 The Dinner ended, Ioseph doth provide To haue each Hebrewes sacke fild full with graine, And each mans Coyne in his sackes mouth was tide: Thus they haue food for nought yet once againe. 26 Into the Sack of his deare Beniamin, Hee caus'd his siluer Cup to bee conueyd, And by this meanes hee doth occasion winne, To haue the youth from his departure stayd. 27 As soone as morne displayd her blushing red, And cleare light shew'd to Trauellers their way, Each Hebrew with his chardg from Ioseph sped: Little suspecting of a new delay. 28 They had not from the Citie traueld farre, But Josephs Steward them in hast pursues: Hee ouer-takes them, they arrested are, And speechlesse stand amaz'd at this sad newes. 29 Hee question'd them, why ill for good they payd, His Lords diuining Siluer Cup was gone, They strangers were, and false perhaps hee sayd: For but themselues, himselfe suspected none. 30 This sayd, at length they thus to him replyde: Why should our Lord to vs these speeches say, In our sackes mouthes when wee the siluer spyde, Brought backe from Canaan wee did it repay. 31 It is vnlikely therefore wee should steale, And vse such falshood where such loue wee found: Yet search vs all, and hee that thus shall deale, Let him to death, the rest to Prison bound. 32 Bee't so, the Steward sayes; with that each one, Takes from his Loden beast his sacke of corne, From eldest Reuben now the search is gone, And by degrees come to the youngest borne. 33 The siluer Cup is found in the youths sacke, The brethren rend their cloathes to find it so, Now once againe each man assumes his packe, And with sad lookes backe to the Citie goe. 34 And hee that whilom seru'd these men in state, With dainty dishes at a Princelike board, Safe-guards them now as fellowes of stolne-plate, So great a change so small time doth afford. 35 To Iosephs house they now againe are brought: Where hee did stay expecting their surprize, For hee was witting of what would bee wrought, And theeues now made them that supposd them spyes 36 When they beheld his face, (with shame deiected) To bended knees they doe themselues betake: A as (quoth he) what's this ye haue effected; Did you not know that I could tryall make? 37 Then Iudah (thus) What shall we plead or say Vnto my Lord, our selues vve cannot free, Tis Israels God that doth our sinnes repay, And for our theft we must thy bond-men be. 38 Nay God forbid that I should vse you so, Ioseph to those afflicted men replyed, Who stole my Cup, himselfe to me doth owe, He is my seruant, no man else beside. 39 The rest depart in peace vnto your Sire. Then Iudah on his knees sayes, O my Lord, Whom as a second Pharaoh we admire, Vouchsafe to heare thy servant speake a word: 40 When first before my Lord we did appeare, It pleas'd him aske, if we had Syre or Brother: We truely told, we had a father deere, All we his sonnes, and that he had one other, 41 A little one, begot in his old age, Therefore the more belou'd, the more respected, His brother dead, and he the onely gage, Left by that Mother, whom our Syre affected. 42 Then you enioyn'd vs, neuer see your face, Or bring the youth, you might his face behold: When to our father we first told our case, The sad relation made his old heart cold. 43 One of my sonnes (quoth he) sent to the field, Was torne in pieces, neuer more seene since, Should I depart with this, and he should yeeld To death, by sicknesse, or by violence, 44 'Twould breake my aged heart, my old gray head With griefe and sorrow throw into the graue: (O my good Lord) detaine me in his stead, I am his Pledge, and to my father gaue 45 My saith for his returne, with execration, Let Iudah beare the blame for euermore, Vnlesse I bring to Israels habitation, Young Beniamin; euen thus thy servant swore. 46 Then since the old mans being doth depend On the Youths life, let me thy servant be And with my Brethren backe the stripling send And Iudah will be bound, to pray for thee. 47 When Ioseph heard his Brothers sad relation, He could no longer his affection hide Though great ones present, of th' Egyptian Nation Yet Ioseph wept, the text saith, loud he cryed. 48 Avoyd the Roome, quoth he, let no man stay Except these Hebrewes, all the rest depart, Then Ioseph to his brethren doth display The inward feelings of his tender heart. 49 See Ioseph, liues our father? make report, But they were stricken dumbe with that surprize Be not dismay'd, God sent me to the Court For to relieue your wants, by my supplyes. 50 And this was done to worke your preservations, Our fathers God made me his instrument, Two yeeres hath famine seiz'd vpon most nations, And fiue such yeere of want must yet be sent. 51 Therefore returne vnto our aged Syre And from my selfe, salute him in this sort; Egypts Protector Ioseph doth desire To see old Isr'el at King Pharaohs Court. 52 Himselfe, his Childrens Children, heards and sheep, In fruitfull Goshen land, shall haue a Rome Neere to my selfe, I them, and theirs will keepe From fiue yeeres Famine that is yet to come. 53 Remember what I giue in charge ye tell, And Iosephs Honours seene by you relate, With that on Beniamins faire necke he fell, And wept so fast, his teares, their teares begat. 54 This was a wondrous and strange salutation, And vnto Egypts King was quickely brought Who was affected so with the relation That till he Ioseph saw, full long he thought. 55 And seene, he sayes, vnto thy Brethren say Doe this, depart, load beasts, to Canaan goe And bring your father hither that he may Here with his houshould liue, aud let him know. 56 'Tis Pharaohs will, the best of Egypts land Ye shall possesse, and ye shall eat the fat, Eu'n Egypts fat. This more I doe command, You giue them Chariots, to conveigh them, that 57 Their father, children, wiues may come at ease, They shall bee welcome, vnto Egypts King, Care not for stuffe, nor vtensils, for these Pharoah shall giue them, and what other thing 58 Egypt is master of, my land is yours The best of all my land, tis Pharoahs gift; Wee well may call that ours which God assures, Ti's hee from ashes vnto Thrones can lift. 59 I am so ouerioy'd I cannot write, What were the Ioyes the brethren did conceiue? But sure I am each heart must needs bee light; For Royall Gifts ioyfull impressions leaue. 60 They came to Egypt Merchant-like at best: But home are caried like great Lords in state, Their iourney was for bread, now they may feast, Both Horse and Seruants, many on them vvaite. 61 These (once vnkind) their Brother stript, but he Doth giue them change of raiments of the best: To his lov'd Benjamin he was more free, And fiue times more did giue him, then the rest. 62 For Israels journey Ioseph doth provide, And by the way, what dainties he should eate, And ten shee-Asses sent to him beside, All heavy loaden with the purest wheat. 63 And thus set foorth, Ioseph each one salutes, And wills them in their travaile to agree: Vnfayned concord best with Brethren sutes, Small jarres, 'mongst you so link'd, great discords be. 64 Who best instructs, doth best example giue, This good doe I, is better, then this Doe, Most by the Eye, few by the Eare doe liue, Faire actions doe compell, good words but wooe. 65 He that had shew'd himselfe so kind a Brother, Beyond their hope, beyond all expectation, Had by his paterne taught them loue each other, They goe; and bring Iacob this gratulation. 66 Ioseph is yet aliue, and, which is more, 'Tis he that rules all Egypt: Israel heard, And his Heart fail'd, he was so moov'd therefore, But when he saw the gifts that were conferr'd, 67 And did behold the Chariots Ioseph sent, His Heart reviu'd (whom would not such a sight Recall from Death?) and then incontinent, Like one new moulded, full of actiue spright. 68 Ioseph, faith he, doth liue, my child is found And like a Man distract with joy doth try, I haue enough, nay, now my joyes abound, I will goe downe, and see him ere I die! 69 Tis time these happy travellers opprest With their long voyage make a little stay, Israel (good night) my weary Muse must rest, To Egypt will be worke for a new day. O gracious God, thou searcher of each heart, Thou three in Person, but in Essence one: Some Heavenly power to my weake Muse impart: To end the sacred taske she works vpon.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">IACOBS PROGRESSE. 1 Mee thinkes I see in what religious wise, Old Iacob vnto Beersheba went, I heare him pray, I see him sacrifice, And on his knee his heart to God present. 2 From Israels God I heare him craue protection, In this his long, and last peregrination, For though to Ioseph Egypt bore affection: She had strange Gods, was full of fornication. 3 Ibis, and Apis, Crocodiles, and Leekes, Such beastly stinking Gods shee did adore, Against these and the like old Israel seekes, And from the true God doth true grace implore. 4 And marke the issue of his good intention, God, Izaacs God doth meet him the mid-way, And of his mercies infinite propension, That night in vision thus to him did say. 5 Iacob, goe downe to Egypt, doe not feare, I am thy God along with thee will goe: And I will make thee a great nation there; Who could dispaire, that was encourag'd doe. 6 And I will surely bring thee vp againe, Ioseph shall put his hand vpon thine eyes, Me thinkes I see new blood in each old Vayne, Me thinkes I see him cheerefully arise. 7 How like a Gyant to his course he runnes, His Heart with joy, with heavenly joy enspir'd And how he ranckt, and marshalled his sonnes, And from his natiue soyle how he retyr'd. 8 Canaan adue, thy father Israel The top, the hope, the glory of thy Nation, Takes his last leaue, for ever bids farewell, Goshen hencefoorth must be his habitation. 9 Me thinkes I see him like an aged tree, Digg'd vp by th' Rootes, and in a new soyle planted, That growes no more, at least, no more to thee, Leaues now, for fruit beares, those but thin &amp; skanted. 10 Mee thinkes I see him now in triumph ride, I heere his Chariot-wheeles: his Horses neigh, I see his Sonnes, and Daughters by his side, And how they march in order on the way. 11 His Sonnes his Childrens children, Sheepe, and Oxe, Their goods, &amp; all that carriage worth they thought Horse, Cattell, Asse, and in one word their stockes, They driue from Canaan, and to Egypt brought. 12 I could, but that your memories twould cumber, Tell you the names of all their families; All his sonnes names, threescore and sixe in number, Which Scripture saith descended from his thighes, 13 Besides his Sonnes wiues; thus old Israel takes His progresse into Egypt, like a Prince, Iudah his sonne, his Harbinger he makes, Who went before to giue intelligence 14 Of Iacobs comming: which when Ioseph knew His father was at hand, and did draw neere, He mounts his Chariots, and with all his crew, Rides foorth to meet him, moov'd by loue and feare. 15 You sonnes of Belial, that advanc't to state Forget your Parents, nay your Parents scorne, See how well duty in a Magistrate Shewes to a Syre, though but a Sheepheard borne. 16 My Lord Protector from his Chariot lights, And craues his fathers blessing on his knee, Before great Lords; his Peeres: in all their sights To teach them Duty, and Humility. 17 Rise blessed sonne, heereafter ever be The worthy favorite, through the world styled Thine armes the Storke embleme of piety, Thine honourd name, on fames record be filed. 18 At Goshen was this interview (wee find) (If that an interview wee may it call) When Egypts Ruler on his knee enclind, And on his neck his reuerent Sire doth fall. 19 There weepes a good while too, the teares hee shed Were teares of kindnesse and of inward ioy: And when for weeping, hee could speake (he sed) Now let mee dye; since I thy sight enioy. 20 Doe but imagine, hee that was so tender, When to his brethren first made himselfe knowne, How hee his kindnesse to his Sire doth render? And to his fathers house what loue was showen. 21 Egypts great-Patron was not now to learne His complements and courtly entertainements, But by his deeds his kindred might discerne, His welcomes were not shewes, nor verball feynments. 22 They found a reall hearty bien venu: Egypts best soyle elected for their seat, No sooner come, but had to Pharoahs view, Who like a royall King doth them entreat. 23 Ioseph himselfe in person made their way, And doth to Pharoah reu'rent Israel bring: Hee tels his brethren too, what they should say, And how behaue themselues before the King. 24 Fiue of his brethren with the good old man Were to the Court and to the presence brought: Long stayd not there, but the Egyptian, Pharoah appeares. Old Iacob kneeles: besought 25 The God of Israel; the true God to blesse The life of royall Pharoah, keepe his Crowne, And giue him his desires and good successe, And fill his Cup with honour and renowne. 26 The King beheld old Iacob with delight: His graue aspect, his age hee doth admire, And being greatly pleased with his sight, His studies and his age hee doth enquire. 27 Iacob replyes, the number of my dayes, A hundred thirty yeares doe speake mee old, Euill and few, compar'd, short euery wayes, To those good dayes, my ancestors haue told. 28 Thy seruant and his sonnes in acts and bookes Haue little skill, our onely education, Haue beene to keepe our flockes: our sheepheards hooks Those are thy seruants wayes &amp; recreation. 29 Thus Ioseph had before hand them aduis'd, Happy t'auoyd th'Egyptians emulation: (For they were schollers) haply 'twas deuis'd, They might together follow their vocation. 30 And so not mingling with the vnknowne nation, Not suck their euils. Ioseph knew the trade Of keeping sheepe, was an abomination To Egypt, Josephs brethren Pharoah made 31 Rulers of all his Cattle, all his Flockes. They are in office now, who late like spyes, Were in disgrace: thus fortune playes and mockes, Changes; throwes downe, erects vnto the skies. 32 Fortune sayd I? mine error I recant: It is a Pagans voice, an Atheists phrase, 'Twas Abrahams God, that Israel new doth plant: The Author and the cause of all good dayes. 33 Youth to your trust, good father to thy rest, Repose thy weary limbes, thy progresse done: Goshen, fat Goshen entred and possest, Sleepe in the bosome of thy watchfull sonne. 34 The remnant of thy dayes in comfort spend, Grow, plant new nations, doe thou find a graue, My muse that brought thee to thy iourneyes end, Doth here shake hands, and leaue to part doth craue. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>