<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Bourdillon, Francis William, 1852-1921</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Bourdillon, Francis William, 1852-1921</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">bourdillon francis william 1852 1921</field>
      <field name="author_text">Bourdillon, Francis William, 1852-1921</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1910's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.0662.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">[1915]</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466332</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Easter Lilies for nineteen hundred and fifteen ; by F. W. Bourdillon</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Easter Lilies for nineteen hundred and fifteen ; by F. W. Bourdillon</field>
      <field name="title_facet">easter lilies for nineteen hundred and fifteen</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">easter lilies for nineteen hundred and fifteen</field>
      <field name="title_text">Easter Lilies for nineteen hundred and fifteen ; by F. W. Bourdillon</field>
      <field name="year_display">[1915]</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1915</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1915</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466332&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466332&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Bourdillon, Francis William, 1852-1921&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;bourdillon francis william 1852 1921&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Easter Lilies for nineteen hundred and fifteen ; by F. W. Bourdillon&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;easter lilies for nineteen hundred and fifteen&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;[1915]&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1915&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Bourdillon, Francis William&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1852&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1921&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Easter Lilies for nineteen hundred and fifteen&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;by F. W. Bourdillon&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Arthur L. Humphreys&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;[1915]&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0492&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;25 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Easter Lilies for nineteen hundred and fifteen&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;by F. W. Bourdillon&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 20 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Easter Lilies. The Lilies of Earth's Easter-tide Come year by year to say: Fair Life for ever shall abide, Though fair lives pass away. The Golden Record. The Angel of the Record writes In blood and tears their roll Who leave sweet life and its delights To save their nation's soul. In blood and tears the roll is writ, Much blotted. But, behold, God's finger lightly touches it, And turns each name to gold. Under the Starlight. Yon glorious stars, that night by night go down From the dark world come night by night again. Not so, alas! the spirits of renown Who vanish in Death's all-engulfing main. On what dim seas do they arise and shine? In what far countries soothe the eyes of sleep? In what vast orbit round the Light Divine Do souls, here setting, luminously sweep? Nunc est Vivendum. Oh, not to-day shall the end be Of tears, nor yet to-morrow! Life's to live, tho' each day we spend be A day of sorrow! Dear dead, beloved and sighed for, In many a green mound lying! How shall we make the lives ye died for Worthy your dying? ‘Hold on!’ Stout be your hearts, and fail not As the fitful battle sways! Strong be your souls, and quail not Though victory long delays! Hold on, my brother, This day and another! These be thy Judgment Days! Weary and heavy-hearted, With the joy of battle spent, And the light of the eyes departed As friend or comrade went; Hold on, my brother, This day and another! This is God's Tournament. Ye too, with eyes drained tearless, Who watch across the seas, And toil through long days cheerless, Or pray on weary knees! Hold on, my brother, This day and another! Thy proof-days too are these! Freedom Calls. Hark! who calls? What voices waken England from her long repose, Range her thus—old feuds forsaken— Side by side with ancient foes? Hark! who calls? What dreams rekindle Ancient chivalries of France, Bid the fires that seemed to dwindle In her eyes again to dance? Hark! who calls? What spirit quickens Russia through her mighty frame, Gathering, as the storm-cloud thickens Till the lightning leap in flame? Freedom calls! Arise! Confess you Champions all, ye glorious three! Strive, till Europe rise and bless you, Triple-fenced with Liberty! Russia. One voice, but million-throated! One heart, with myriad hands! One single soul, devoted! One pulse, that shakes the lands! Has Earth in all her story A greater thing to tell? Valour, that seeks no glory, Matched soul to soul with Hell! To Belgium. Lift thy heart to the Lord, O People, Though thy head in the dust be laid! No more are glorious fane and steeple, No more religion in pride arrayed. Broken images—ruined altars— Hardly a roof for the thorn-crowned head; Slain the singers and burnt the psalters— How shall the ordered rite be said? Lift thy heart to the Lord, O Nation! More than these is that faith of thine! Tho' the house of God be a desolation, The heart of Man is His dearer shrine. Under which King? Who is the King ye are dying for, Brothers and men of Germany? Kaiser—Emperor—Lord of War? Pluck the mask from the face, and see! Bid for an hour to stand aside Yon sceptred actor who holds the stage! What is the Shadow that, stride for stride, Prompts his motion and pricks his rage? Who is the Lord ye are toiling for, Brothers and men of Germany? Kaiser—Emperor—Lord of War? Look to the work of your hands, and see! Art and labour and busy brain, Aching limbs of the pit and forge, Breathless deeds in the sky or main— Nought to profit Man, all to scourge! Say for whom the Zeppelin flies, And living men to the deep go down, And Music, your own sweet daughter, dies, Wed to a Lord she will not own? Kaiser—Emperor—Lord of War! Only a puppet King is he! Death is the Lord ye are dying for, Brothers and men of Germany! Christmas Morning, 1914. I slumbered in a dream of dread, Thunder of cannon in my ears; Before my eyes were thousands dead, And in my heart a thousand fears. Is there in Heaven a Love Divine, Stronger than wickedness and woe? Or do the Powers of Hell combine The King of Love to overthrow? I wakened in a crystal world; A silver-point was every tree; The spider's network, frost-empearled, Was daintier than filigree. Around my spirit's nakedness A garment of warm thought was wove, As Nature whispered, Loveliness Is visibility of Love! A Dark Night. What, are the stars yet there, Sirius, Orion, shining? Arcturus and the Bear, Arising and declining? Yes; from these darkened skies, Battle and death and sadness, The eternal lamps shall rise— Faith, Hope, Love: even Gladness. In Winter. The woods, that undergo The fierceness of the wind And cruelty of the snow, Change not their mind, But in their day and hour Put forth sweet leaf and flower. Heart, be it with thee so! Though the full rage of Death Fall on thee blow on blow, Draw deep thy breath To endure, and after pain Put on sweet joy again! Doubt. Search now and see Where Wisdom hides, If Love there be, Or Truth abides! The snow lies deep On mount and moor, Our bravest sleep, And Love is o'er. Lord of the Spring, The doubt forgive! Thy birds yet sing, Thy flowers live. With hills and groves O heart awake! And from dead leaves Bid green hopes break! In Early Spring. Still the music of the thrush Wakes the morning; Though our hearts would bid her hush Her blithe warning, Hearing through her joyous throat Echoes of another note. Still the flowers in woodland ways Stand entreating, Though our eyes' averted gaze Give no greeting, Fearing 'neath that tender blue Memories of another hue. But the Giver of the Spring Never stayeth For our sullen looks one thing, Nor delayeth, Lest Despair take Sorrow's place, Saying, God too hides His face! The Seed. In a wild, wild night of tempest, From its nursing-husk new-freed, There whirled afar on the storm-wind A wingèd seed. In a wild, wild day of battle, When struggling nations fought, There sprang from the soul of a people A wingèd thought. Forests fell in the tempest, And waste were lawn and lea; But the seed in the torn earth nestled, And grew a tree. Nations sank in the battle, Cities in wreck were hurled; But the thought in silence quickened, And saved the world. Two Sonnets. I. [Art thou insatiable, O soul-less Death?] Art thou insatiable, O soul-less Death? Is thy dread hunger infinite, O Grave? Enough, enough! For now from hurst and heath Spring calls, and how shall our dead hearts behave? Too cruel is the laughter of the wave; The fluttering Zephyr seems a dying breath; In this blue Speedwell, Love remembereth Eyes ne'er again to open clear and brave. And when, on April evenings, the first star Brightens before it follow Day to rest, And in the darkening wood the last-awake Love-minstrel, from some Heav'n-gate left ajar, Bid Earth prepare a room for Joy her guest, Must not the heart—till then enduring—break? II. [Break? Nay! Is there nought mightier in thee] Break? Nay! Is there nought mightier in thee, O Man, than force which force can overthrow? Art thou but as the tempest-battling tree, That yet is broken by soft-falling snow? Shall Love be tested by the weight of woe Borne till the burden pass some scaled degree? Shall Hell but marshal hosts sufficiently, And man fall unresisting 'neath the blow? A seed of fire is in the human soul That tears can quench not. Not our peaceful hours And prosperous years have made us what we are; But griefs and labours, and the will-control Won by resistance to the o'erwhelming Powers— Hate, Fate, Ill-fortune, and our Evil Star. A Prayer. Eternal! to the tribes of Man Revealed as merciful and just, Since of Thy purpose he began The part to know, the whole to trust! We pray Thee in this hour of woe Thy mercy and Thy justice show! The wrath of Man shall praise Thee, Lord, If Thou the lingering feud restrain! In furrows cloven by the sword Thy hand can sow a righteous grain. From graves of rancour bid increase The vine Goodwill—the olive Peace!</field>
   </doc>
</add>