<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Heber, Reginald, 1783-1826</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Heber, Reginald, 1783-1826</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">heber reginald 1783 1826</field>
      <field name="author_text">Heber, Reginald, 1783-1826</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1840's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.1319.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1841</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466726</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">French</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Greek, Modern (1453- )</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Poetical Works of Reginald Heber</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Poetical Works of Reginald Heber</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poetical works of reginald heber</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poetical works of reginald heber</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Poetical Works of Reginald Heber</field>
      <field name="year_display">1841</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1841</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1841</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466726&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466726&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Heber, Reginald, 1783-1826&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;heber reginald 1783 1826&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Poetical Works of Reginald Heber&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poetical works of reginald heber&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1841&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1841&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Heber, Reginald&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1783&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1826&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Poetical Works of Reginald Heber&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;John Murray&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1841&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp1699&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;fre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;gre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;xii, 455 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Poetical Works of Reginald Heber&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 373 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted; hymns omitted; translations omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PALESTINE: A PRIZE POEM, RECITED IN THE THEATRE, OXFORD, IN THE YEAR MDCCCIII. Reft of thy sons, amid thy foes forlorn, Mourn, widow'd Queen, forgotten Sion, mourn! Is this thy place, sad city, this thy throne, Where the wild desert rears its craggy stone; While suns unbless'd their angry lustre fling, And way-worn pilgrims seek the scanty spring?— Where now thy pomp, which kings with envy view'd? Where now thy might, which all those kings subdued? No martial myriads muster in thy gate; No suppliant nations in thy Temple wait; No prophet bards, thy glittering courts among, Wake the full lyre, and swell the tide of song: But lawless force, and meagre want are there, And the quick-darting eye of restless fear, While cold oblivion, 'mid thy ruins laid, Folds his dank wing Alluding to the usual manner in which sleep is represented in ancient statues. See also Pindar, Pyth. I. v. 16, 17.“ ??????? ????? ????? ??????.” beneath the ivy shade. Ye guardian saints! ye warrior sons of Heaven, Authorities for these celestial warriors may be found, Josh. v. 13. 2 Kings vi. 2. 2 Macc. v. 3. Ibid. xi. Joseph. Ed. Huds. vi. p. 1282. ct alibi passim. To whose high care Judæa's state was given! O wont of old your nightly watch to keep, A host of gods, on Sion's towery steep! It is scarcely necessary to mention the lofty site of Jerusalem. “The hill of God is a high hill, even a high hill as the hill of Bashan.” If e'er your secret footsteps linger still By Siloa's fount, or Tabor's echoing hill; If e'er your song on Salem's glories dwell, And mourn the captive land you loved so well; (For oft, 'tis said, in Kedron's palmy vale Mysterious harpings See Sandys, and other travellers into Asia. swell the midnight gale, And, blest as balmy dews that Hermon cheer, Melt in soft cadence on the pilgrim's ear;) Forgive, blest spirits, if a theme so high Mock the weak notes of mortal minstrelsy! Yet, might your aid this anxious breast inspire With one faint spark of Milton's seraph fire, Then should my Muse Common practice, and the authority of Milton, seem sufficient to justify using this term as a personification of poetry. ascend with bolder flight, And wave her eagle-plumes exulting in the light. O happy once in Heaven's peculiar love, Delight of men below, and saints above! Though, Salem, now the spoiler's ruffian hand Has loosed his hell-hounds o'er thy wasted land; Though weak, and whelm'd beneath the storms of fate, Thy house is left unto thee desolate; Matt. xxiii. 38. Though thy proud stones in cumbrous ruin fall, And seas of sand o'ertop thy mouldering wall; Yet shall the Muse to fancy's ardent view Each shadowy trace of faded pomp renew: And as the seer Moses. on Pisgah's topmost brow With glistening eye beheld the plain below, With prescient ardour drank the scented gale, And bade the opening glades of Canaan hail; Her eagle eye shall scan the prospect wide, From Carmel's cliffs to Almotana's tide; Almotana is the Oriental name for the Dead Sea, as Ardeni is for Jordan. The flinty waste, the cedar-tufted hill, The liquid health of smooth Ardeni's rill; The grot, where, by the watch-fire's evening blaze, The robber riots, or the hermit prays; The mountains of Palestine are full of caverns, which are generally occupied in one or other of the methods here mentioned. Vide Sandys, Maundrell, and Calmet, passim. Or where the tempest rives the hoary stone, The wintry top of giant Lebanon. Fierce, hardy, proud, in conscious freedom bold, Those stormy seats the warrior Druses hold; The untameable spirit, feodal customs, and affection for Europeans, which distinguish this extraordinary race, who boast themselves to be a remnant of the Crusaders, are well described in Pagés. The account of their celebrated Emir, Facciardini, in Sandys, is also very interesting. Puget de S. Pierre compiled a small volume on their history; Paris, 1763. 12mo. From Norman blood their lofty line they trace, Their lion courage proves their generous race. They, only they, while all around them kneel In sullen homage to the Thracian steel, Teach their pale despot's waning moon to fear “The Turkish sultans, whose moon seems fast approaching to its wane.” Sir W. Jones's first Disc. to the Asiatic Society. The patriot terrors of the mountain spear. Yes, valorous chiefs, while yet your sabres shine The native guard of feeble Palestine, Oh, ever thus, by no vain boast dismay'd, Defend the birthright of the cedar shade! What though no more for you th' obedient gale, Swells the white bosom of the Tyrian sail; Though now no more your glittering marts unfold Sidonian dyes and Lusitanian gold; The gold of the Tyrians chiefly came from Portugal, which was probably their Tarshish. Though not for you the pale and sickly slave Forgets the light in Ophir's wealthy cave; Yet yours the lot, in proud contentment blest, Where cheerful labour leads to tranquil rest. No robber rage the ripening harvest knows; And unrestrain'd the generous vintage flows: In the southern parts of Palestine the inhabitants reap their corn green, as they are not sure that it will ever be allowed to come to maturity. The oppression to which the cultivators of vineyards are subject throughout the Ottoman empire is well known. Nor less your sons to manliest deeds aspire, And Asia's mountains glow with Spartan fire. So when, deep sinking in the rosy main, The western sun forsakes the Syrian plain, His watery rays refracted lustre shed, And pour their latest light on Carmel's head. Yet shines your praise, amid surrounding gloom, As the lone lamp that trembles in the tomb: For few the souls that spurn a tyrant's chain, And small the bounds of freedom's scanty reign. As the poor outcast on the cheerless wild, Arabia's parent, Hagar. clasp'd her fainting child, And wander'd near the roof, no more her home, Forbid to linger, yet afraid to roam; My sorrowing fancy quits the happier height, And southward throws her half-averted sight. For sad the scenes Judæa's plains disclose, A dreary waste of undistinguish'd woes: See war untired his crimson pinions spread, And foul revenge that tramples on the dead! Lo, where from far the guarded fountains shine, The watering-places are generally beset with Arabs, who exact toll from all comers. See Harmer and Pagés. Thy tents, Nebaioth, rise, and Kedar, thine! See Ammianus Marcellinus, lib. xiv. p. 43. Ed. Vales. 'Tis yours the boast to mark the stranger's way, And spur your headlong chargers on the prey, Or rouse your nightly numbers from afar, And on the hamlet pour the waste of war; Nor spare the hoary head, nor bid your eye Revere the sacred smile of infancy. “Thine eye shall not spare them.” Such now the clans, whose fiery coursers feed Where waves on Kishon's bank the whispering reed; And theirs the soil, where, curling to the skies, Smokes on Samaria's mount her scanty sacrifice; A miserable remnant of Samaritan worship still exists on Mount Gerizim. Maundrell relates his conversation with the high priest. While Israel's sons, by scorpion curses driven, Outcasts of earth, and reprobate of heaven, Through the wide world in friendless exile stray, Remorse and shame sole comrades of their way, With dumb despair their country's wrongs behold, And, dead to glory, only burn for gold. O Thou, their Guide, their Father, and their Lord, Loved for Thy mercies, for Thy power adored! If at Thy Name the waves forgot their force, And refluent Jordan sought his trembling source; Psalm cxiv. If at Thy Name like sheep the mountains fled, And haughty Sirion bow'd his marble head;— To Israel's woes a pitying ear incline, And raise from earth Thy long-neglected vine! See Psalm lxxx. 8—14. Her rifled fruits behold the heathen bear, And wild-wood boars her mangled clusters tear. Was it for this she stretch'd her peopled reign From far Euphrates to the western main? For this, o'er many a hill her boughs she threw, And her wide arms like goodly cedars grew? For this, proud Edom slept beneath her shade, And o'er th' Arabian deep her branches play'd? Oh, feeble boast of transitory power! Vain, fruitless trust of Judah's happier hour! Not such their hope, when through the parted main The cloudy wonder led the warrior train: Not such their hope, when through the fields of night The torch of heaven diffused its friendly light: Not, when fierce conquest urged the onward war, And hurl'd stern Canaan from his iron car: Nor, when five monarchs led to Gibeon's fight, In rude array, the harness'd Amorite: Joshua x. Yes—in that hour, by mortal accents stay'd, The lingering sun his fiery wheels delay'd; The moon, obedient, trembled at the sound, Curb'd her pale car, and check'd her mazy round! Let Sinai tell—for she beheld His might, And God's own darkness veil'd her mystic height: (He, cherub-borne, upon the whirlwind rode, And the red mountain like a furnace glow'd); Let Sinai tell-but who shall dare recite His praise, His power, eternal, infinite?— Awe-struck I cease; nor bid my strains aspire, Or serve His altar with unhallow'd fire. Alluding to the fate of Nadab and Abihu. Such were the cares that watch'd o'er Israel's fate, And such the glories of their infant state. —Triumphant race! and did your power decay? Fail'd the bright promise of your early day? No:—by that sword, which, red with heathen gore, A giant spoil, the stripling champion bore; By him, the chief to farthest India known, The mighty master of the ivory throne; Solomon. Ophir is by most geographers placed in the Aurea Chersonesus. See Tavernier and Raleigh. In Heaven's own strength, high towering o'er her foes, Victorious Salem's lion banner rose; Before her footstool prostrate nations lay, And vassal tyrants crouch'd beneath her sway. —And he, the kingly sage, whose restless mind Through nature's mazes wander'd unconfined; The Arabian mythology respecting Solomon is in itself so fascinating, is so illustrative of the present state of the country, and on the whole so agreeable to Scripture, that it was judged improper to omit all mention of it, though its wildness might have operated as an objection to making it a principal object in the poem. Who every bird, and beast, and insect knew, And spake of every plant that quaffs the dew; To him were known—so Hagar's offspring tell— The powerful sigil and the starry spell, The midnight call, hell's shadowy legions dread, And sounds that burst the slumbers of the dead. Hence all his might; for who could these oppose? And Tadmor thus, and Syrian Balbec rose. Palmyra (“Tadmor in the Desert”) was really built by Solomon, (1 Kings ix. 2 Chron. viii.) and universal tradition marks him out, with great probability, as the founder of Balbec. Estakhar is also attributed to him by the Arabs. See the romance of Vathek, and the various Travels into the East, more particularly Chardin's, in which, after a minute and interesting description of the majestic ruins of Estakhar, or Persepolis, the ancient capital of Persia, an account follows of the wild local traditions just alluded to. Vol. ii. p. 190. Ed. Amst. 1735, 4to. Vide also Sale's Koran; D'Herbelot, Bibl. Orient. (article Solimon Ben Daoud;) and the Arabian Nights' Entertainments, passim. Yet e'en the works of toiling Genii fall, And vain was Estakhar's enchanted wall. In frantic converse with the mournful wind, There oft the houseless Santon It is well known that the Santons are real or affected madmen, pretending to extraordinary sanctity, who wander about the country, sleeping in caves or ruins. rests reclined; Strangè shapes he views, and drinks with wondering ears The voices of the dead, and songs of other years. Such, the faint echo of departed praise, Still sound Arabia's legendary lays; And thus their fabling bards delight to tell How lovely were thy tents, O Israel! Numbers xxiv. 5. For thee his ivory load Behemoth bore, Behemoth is sometimes supposed to mean the elephant, in which sense it is here used. And far Sofala teem'd with golden ore; An African port to the south of Bab-el-mandeb, celebrated for gold mines. Thine all the arts that wait on wealth's increase, Or bask and wanton in the beam of peace. When Tyber slept beneath the cypress gloom, And silence held the lonely woods of Rome; Or ere to Greece the builder's skill was known, Or the light chisel brush'd the Parian stone; Yet here fair Science nursed her infant fire, Fann'd by the artist aid of friendly Tyre. Then tower'd the palace, then in awful state The Temple rear'd its everlasting gate. Psalm xxiv. 7. No workman steel, no ponderous axes rung! “There was neither hammer, nor axe, nor any tool of iron, heard in the house while it was in building.” 1 Kings vi. 7. Like some tall palm the noiseless fabric sprung. Majestic silence!—then the harp awoke, The cymbal clang'd, the deep-voiced trumpet spoke; And Salem spread her suppliant arms abroad, View'd the descending flame, and bless'd the present God. “And when all the children of Israel saw how the fire came down, and the glory of the Lord upon the house, they bowed themselves with their faces to the ground upon the pavement, and worshipped.” 2 Chron. vii. 3. Nor shrunk she then, when, raging deep and loud, Beat o'er her soul the billows of the proud. Psalm cxxiv. 4. E'en they who, dragg'd to Shinar's fiery sand, Till'd with reluctant strength the stranger's land; Who sadly told the slow-revolving years, And steep'd the captive's bitter bread with tears;— Yet oft their hearts with kindling hopes would burn, Their destined triumphs, and their glad return, And their sad lyres, which, silent and unstrung, In mournful ranks on Babel's willows hung, Would oft awake to chant their future fame, And from the skies their lingering Saviour claim. His promised aid could every fear controul; Thisnerved the warrior's arm, thissteel'd the martyr's soul! Nor vain their hope:—bright beaming through the sky, Burst in full blaze the Day-spring from on high; Earth's utmost isles exulted at the sight, And crowding nations drank the orient light. Lo, star-led chiefs Assyrian odours bring, And bending Magi seek their infant King! Mark'd ye, where, hovering o'er his radiant head, The dove's white wings celestial glory shed? Daughter of Sion! virgin queen! rejoice! Clap the glad hand and lift th' exulting voice! He comes,—but not in regal splendour drest, The haughty diadem, the Tyrian vest; Not arm'd in flame, all-glorious from afar, Of hosts the chieftain, and the lord of war: Messiah comes!—let furious discord cease; Be peace on earth before the Prince of Peace! Disease and anguish feel His blest controul, And howling fiends release the tortured soul; The beams of gladness hell's dark caves illume, And Mercy broods above the distant gloom. Thou palsied earth, with noonday night o'erspread! Thou sickening sun, so dark, so deep, so red! Ye hovering ghosts, that throng the starless air, Why shakes the earth? why fades the light? declare! Are those His limbs, with ruthless scourges torn? His brows, all bleeding with the twisted thorn? His the pale form, the meek forgiving eye Raised from the cross in patient agony? —Be dark, thou sun,—thou noonday night arise, And hide, oh hide, the dreadful sacrifice! Ye faithful few, by bold affection led, Who round the Saviour's cross your sorrows shed, Not for His sake your tearful vigils keep;— Weep for your country, for your children weep! Luke xxiii. 27, 28. —Vengeance! thy fiery wing their race pursued; Thy thirsty poniard blush'd with infant blood. Roused at thy call, and panting still for game, The bird of war, the Latian eagle came. Then Judah raged, by ruffian Discord led, Drunk with the steamy carnage of the dead: He saw his sons by dubious slaughter fall, And war without, and death within the wall. Wide-wasting plague, gaunt famine, mad despair, And dire debate, and clamorous strife was there: Love, strong as death, retain'd his might no more, And the pale parent drank her children's gore. Joseph vi. p. 1275. Ed. Huds. Yet they, who wont to roam the ensanguined plain, And spurn with fell delight their kindred slain; E'en they, when, high above the dusty fight, Their burning Temple rose in lurid light, To their loved altars paid a parting groan, And in their country's woes forgot their own. As 'mid the cedar courts, and gates of gold, The trampled ranks in miry carnage roll'd, To save their Temple every hand essay'd, And with cold fingers grasp'd the feeble blade: Through their torn veins reviving fury ran, And life's last anger warm'd the dying man! But heavier far the fetter'd captive's doom! To glut with sighs the iron ear of Rome: To swell, slow-pacing by the car's tall side, The stoic tyrant's philosophic pride; The Roman notions of humanity cannot have been very exalted when they ascribed so large a share to Titus. For the horrible details of his conduct during the siege of Jerusalem and after its capture, the reader is referred to Josephus. When we learn that so many captives were crucified, that ??? ?? ?????? ???? ?? ?????????? ???? ???????? ??? ??????? ???? ???????? and that after all was over, in cold blood and merriment, he celebrated his brother's birth-day with similar sacrifices; we can hardly doubt as to the nature of that untold crime, which disturbed the dying moments of “the darling of the human race.” After all, the cruelties of this man are probably softened in the high priest's narrative. The fall of Jerusalem nearly resembles that of Zaragoza, but it is a Morla who tells the tale. To flesh the lion's ravenous jaws, or feel The sportive fury of the fencer's steel; Or pant, deep plunged beneath the sultry mine, For the light gales of balmy Palestine. Ah! fruitful now no more,—an empty coast, She mourn'd her sons enslaved, her glories lost: In her wide streets the lonely raven bred, There bark'd the wolf, and dire hyænas fed. Yet midst her towery fanes, in ruin laid, The pilgrim saint his murmuring vespers paid; 'Twas his to climb the tufted rocks, and rove The chequer'd twilight of the olive grove; 'Twas his to bend beneath the sacred gloom, And wear with many a kiss Messiah's tomb: While forms celestial fill'd his trancèd eye, The daylight dreams of pensive piety, O'er his still breast a tearful fervour stole, And softer sorrows charm'd the mourner's soul. Oh, lives there one, who mocks his artless zeal? Too proud to worship, and too wise to feel? Be his the soul with wintry reason blest, The dull, lethargic sovereign of the breast! Be his the life that creeps in dead repose, No joy that sparkles, and no tear that flows! Far other they who rear'd yon pompous shrine, The Temple of the sepulchre. And bade the rock with Parian marble shine. See Cotovicus, p. 179; and from him Sandys. Then hallow'd peace renew'd her wealthy reign, Then altars smoked, and Sion smiled again. There sculptured gold and costly gems were seen, And all the bounties of the British queen; St. Helena, who was, according to Camden, born at Colchester, See also Howel's Hist. of the World. There barbarous kings their sandal'd nations led, And steel-clad champions bow'd the crested head. There, when her fiery race the desert pour'd, And pale Byzantium fear'd Medina's sword, The invasions of the civilised parts of Asia by the Arabian and Turkish Mahometans. When coward Asia shook in trembling woe, And bent appall'd before the Bactrian bow; From the moist regions of the western star The wandering hermit waked the storm of war. Peter the Hermit. The world has been so long accustomed to hear the Crusades considered as the height of frenzy and injustice, that to undertake their defence might be perhaps a hazardous task. We must, however, recollect, that had it not been for these extraordinary exertions of generous courage, the whole of Europe would perhaps have fallen, and Christianity been buried in the ruins. It was not, as Voltaire has falsely or weakly asscrted, a conspiracy of robbers; it was not an unprovoked attack on a distant and inoffensive nation; it was a blow aimed at the heart of a most powerful and active enemy. Had not the Christian kingdoms of Asia been established as a check to the Mabometans, Italy, and the scanty remnant of Christianity in Spain, must again have fallen into their power, and France herself have needed all the heroism and good fortune of a Charles Martel to deliver her from subjugation. Their limbs all iron, and their souls all flame, A countless host, the red-cross warriors came: E'en hoary priests the sacred combat wage, And clothe in steel the palsied arm of age; While beardless youths and tender maids assume See Vertot, Hist. Chev. de Malthe, liv. i. The weighty morion and the glancing plume. In sportive pride the warrior damsels wield The ponderous falchion, and the sun-like shield, And start to see their armour's iron gleam Dance with blue lustre in Tabaria's stream. Tabaria (a corruption of Tiberias) is the name used for the Sea of Galilee in the old romances. The blood-red banner floating o'er their van, All madly blithe the mingled myriads ran: Impatient Death beheld his destined food, And hovering vultures snuff'd the scent of blood. Not such the numbers, nor the host so dread, By northern Brenn or Scythian Timur led; Brennus, and Tamerlane. Nor such the heart-inspiring zeal that bore United Greece to Phrygia's reedy shore! There Gaul's proud knights with boastful mien advance, The insolence of the French nobles twice caused the ruin of the army; once by refusing to serve under Richard Cœur-de-Lion, and again by reproaching the English with cowardice in St. Louis's expedition to Egypt. See Knolles's History of the Turks. Form the long line, and shake the cornel lance; The line (combat à-la-haie), according to Sir Walter Raleigh, was characteristic of French tactics; as the column (herse) was of the English. The English at Créci were drawn up thirty deep. Here, link'd with Thrace, in close battalions stand Ausonia's sons, a soft inglorious band; There the stern Norman joins the Austrian train, And the dark tribes of late-reviving Spain; Here in black files, advancing firm and slow, Victorious Albion twangs the deadly bow:— Albion,—still prompt the captive's wrong to aid, And wield in Freedom's cause the freeman's generous blade! Ye sainted spirits of the warrior dead, Whose giant force Britannia's armies led! All the British nations served under the same banner. Sono gl' Inglesi sagittarii, ed hanno Gente con lor, ch' è più vicina al polo, Questi da l' alte selve irsuti manda La divisa dal mondo, ultima Irlanda. Tasso, Gerusal. lib. i. 44. Ireland and Scotland, it is scarcely necessary to observe, were synonymous. Whose bickering falchions, foremost in the fight, Still pour'd confusion on the Soldan's might; Lords of the biting axe and beamy spear, The axe of Richard was very famous. See Warton's Hist. of Ancient Poetry. Wide-conquering Edward, lion Richard, hear! At Albion's call your crested pride resume, And burst the marble slumbers of the tomb! Your sons behold, in arm, in heart the same, Still press the footsteps of parental fame, To Salem still their generous aid supply, And pluck the palm of Syrian chivalry! When he, from towery Malta's yielding isle, And the green waters of reluctant Nile, Th' apostate chief,—from Misraim's subject shore To Acre's walls his trophied banners bore; When the pale desert mark'd his proud array, And desolation hoped an ampler sway; What hero then triumphant Gaul dismay'd? What arm repell'd the victor Renegade? Britannia's champion!—bathed in hostile blood, High on the breach the dauntless Seaman stood: Admiring Asia saw th' unequal fight,— E'en the pale crescent bless'd the Christian's might. Oh day of death! Oh thirst, beyond controul, Of crimson conquest in th' Invader's soul! The slain, yet warm, by social footsteps trod, O'er the red moat supplied a panting road; O'er the red moat our conquering thunders flew, And loftier still the grisly rampire grew. While proudly glow'd above the rescued tower The wavy cross that mark'd Britannia's power. Yet still destruction sweeps the lonely plain, And heroes lift the generous sword in vain. Still o'er her sky the clouds of anger roll, And God's revenge hangs heavy on her soul. Yet shall she rise;—but not by war restored, Not built in murder,—planted by the sword: Yes, Salem, thou shalt rise: thy Father's aid Shall heal the wound His chastening hand has made; Shall judge the proud oppressor's ruthless sway, And burst his brazen bonds, and cast his cords away. Psalm ii. 3. cvii. 16. Then on your tops shall deathless verdure spring, “I will multiply the fruit of the tree, and the increase of the field, that ye shall receive no more the reproach of famine among the heathen.”—“And they shall say, This land that was desolate is become like the garden of Eden,” &amp;c. Ezek. xxxvi. Break forth, ye mountains, and ye valleys, sing! No more your thirsty rocks shall frown forlorn, The unbeliever's jest, the heathen's scorn; The sultry sands shall tenfold harvests yield, And a new Eden deck the thorny field. E'en now, perchance, wide-waving o'er the land, That mighty Angel lifts his golden wand, Courts the bright vision of descending power, “That great city, the holy Jerusalem, descending out of heaven from God, having the glory of God.” Rev. xxi. 10. Tells every gate, and measures every tower; Ezekiel xl. And chides the tardy seals that yet detain Thy Lion, Judah, from his destined reign. And who is He? the vast, the awful form, Revelation x. Girt with the whirlwind, sandal'd with the storm? A western cloud around His limbs is spread, His crown a rainbow, and a sun His head. To highest Heaven He lifts his kingly hand, And treads at once the ocean and the land; And, hark! His voice amid the thunder's roar, His dreadful voice, that time shall be no more! Lo! cherub hands the golden courts prepare, Lo! thrones arise, and every saint is there; Revelation, xx. Earth's utmost bounds confess their awful sway, The mountains worship, and the isles obey; Nor sun nor moon they need,—nor day, nor night;— God is their temple, and the Lamb their light: “And I saw no temple therein: for the Lord God Almighty and the Lamb are the temple of it. And the city had no need of the sun, neither of the moon, to shine in it: for the glory of God did lighten it, and the Lamb is the light thereof.” Rev. xxi. 22. And shall not Israel's sons exulting come, Hail the glad beam, and claim their ancient home? On David's throne shall David's offspring reign, And the dry bones be warm with life again. “Thus saith the Lord God unto these bones, Behold, I will cause breath to enter into you, and ye shall live.—Then he said unto me, Son of man, these bones are the whole house of Israel.” Ezek. xxxvii. Hark! white-robed crowds their deep hosannas raise, And the hoarse flood repeats the sound of praise; Ten thousand harps attune the mystic song, Ten thousand thousand saints the strain prolong;— “Worthy the Lamb! omnipotent to save, Who died, who lives, triumphant o'er the grave!” EUROPE: LINES ON THE PRESENT WAR. WRITTEN IN MDCCCIX. ID. QVANDO. ACCIDERIT. NON. SATIS. AVDEO EFFARI. SIQVIDEM. NON. CLARIVS. MIHI PER. SACROS. TRIPODES. CERTA. REFERT. DEVS NEC. SERVAT. PENITVS. FIDEM QVOD. SI. QVID. LICEAT. CREDERE. ADHVC. TAMEN NAM. LAEVVM. TONVIT. NON. FVERIT. PROCVL QVAERENDVS. CELERI. QVI. PROPERET. GRADV ET. GALLVM. REPRIMAT. FEROX PETRVS, CRINITVS. IN. CARMINE AD. BER. CARAPHAM. At that dread season when th' indignant North Pour'd to vain wars her tardy numbers forth, When Frederic bent his ear to Europe's cry, And fann'd too late the flame of liberty; By feverish hope oppress'd, and anxious thought, In Dresden's grove the dewy cool I sought. The opening lines of this poem were really composed in the situation (the Park of Dresden), and under the influence of the feelings which they attempt to describe. The disastrous issue of King Frederick's campaign took away from the author all inclination to continue them, and they remained neglected till the hopes of Europe were again revived by the illustrious efforts of the Spanish people. Through tangled boughs the broken moonshine play'd, And Elbe slept soft beneath his linden shade:— Yet slept not all;—I heard the ceaseless jar, The rattling waggons, and the wheels of war; The sounding lash, the march's mingled hum, And, lost and heard by fits, the languid drum; O'er the near bridge the thundering hoofs that trode, And the far-distant fife that thrill'd along the road. Yes, sweet it seems across some watery dell To catch the music of the pealing bell; And sweet to list, as on the beach we stray, The ship-boy's carol in the wealthy bay:— But sweet no less, when justice points the spear, Of martial wrath the glorious din to hear, To catch the war-note on the quivering gale, And bid the blood-red paths of conquest hail. Oh! song of hope, too long delusive strain! And hear we now thy flattering voice again? But late, alas! I left thee cold and still, Stunn'd by the wrath of Heaven, on Pratzen's hill. The hill of Pratzen was the point most obstinately contested in the great battle which has taken its name from the neighbouring town of Austerlitz; and here the most dreadful slaughter took place, both of French and Russians. The author had, a few weeks before he wrote the above, visited every part of this celebrated field. Oh! on that hill may no kind month renew The fertile rain, the sparkling summer dew! Accurs'd of God, may those bleak summits tell The field of anger where the mighty fell. There youthful faith and high-born courage rest, And, red with slaughter, freedom's humbled crest; It is necessary perhaps to mention, that, by freedom, in this and in other passages of the present poem, political liberty is understood, in opposition to the usurpation of any single European state. In the particular instance of Spain, however, it is a hope which the author has not yet seen reason to abandon, that a struggle so nobly maintained by popular energy, must terminate in the establishment not only of national independence, but of civil and religious liberty. There Europe, soil'd with blood her tresses grey, And ancient honour's shield,—all vilely thrown away. Thus mused my soul, as in succession drear Rose each grim shape of wrath and doubt and fear; Defeat and shame in grisly vision past, And vengeance, bought with blood, and glorious death the last. Then as my gaze their waving eagles met, And through the night each sparkling bayonet, Still memory told how Austria's evil hour Had felt on Praga's field a Frederic's power, And Gallia's vaunting train, The confidence and shameful luxury of the French nobles, during the Seven Years' War, are very sarcastically noticed by Templeman. and Mosco's horde, Had flesh'd the maiden steel of Brunswick's sword. Oh! yet, I deem'd, that fate, by justice led, Might wreathe once more the veteran's silver head; That Europe's ancient pride would yet disdain The cumbrous sceptre of a single reign; That conscious right would tenfold strength afford, And Heaven assist the patriot's holy sword, And look in mercy through th' auspicious sky, To bless the saviour host of Germany. And are they dreams, these bodings, such as shed Their lonely comfort o'er the hermit's bed? And are they dreams? or can the Eternal Mind Care for a sparrow, yet neglect mankind? Why, if the dubious battle own His power, And the red sabre, where He bids, devour, Why then can one the curse of worlds deride, And millions weep a tyrant's single pride? Thus sadly musing, far my footsteps stray'd, Rapt in the visions of the Aonian maid. It was not she, whose lonely voice I hear Fall in soft whispers on my love-lorn ear; My daily guest, who wont my steps to guide Through the green walks of scented even-tide, Or stretch'd with me in noonday ease along, To list the reaper's chaunt, or throstle's song:— But she of loftier port; whose grave controul Rules the fierce workings of the patriot's soul; She, whose high presence, o'er the midnight oil, With fame's bright promise cheers the student's toil; That same was she, whose ancient lore refin'd The sober hardihood of Sydney's mind. Borne on her wing, no more I seem'd to rove By Dresden's glittering spires, and linden grove; No more the giant Elbe, all silver bright, Spread his broad bosom to the fair moonlight, While the still margent of his ample flood Bore the dark image of the Saxon wood— (Woods happy once, that heard the carols free, Of rustic love, and cheerful industry; Now dull and joyless lie their alleys green, And silence marks the track where France has been.) Far other scenes than these my fancy view'd: Rocks robed in ice, a mountain solitude; Where on Helvetian hills, in godlike state, Alone and awful, Europe's Angel sate: Silent and stern he sate; then, bending low, Listen'd th' ascending plaints of human woe. And waving as in grief his towery head, “Not yet, not yet the day of rest,” he said; “It may not be. Destruction's gory wing Soars o'er the banners of the younger king, Too rashly brave, who secks with single sway To stem the lava on its destined way. Poor glittering warriors, only wont to know The bloodless pageant of a martial show; Nurselings of peace, for fiercer fights prepare, And dread the step-dame sway of unaccustom'd war! They fight, they bleed!—Oh! had that blood been shed When Charles and valour Austria's armies led; Had these stood forth the righteous cause to shield, When victory waver'd on Moravia's field; Then France had mourn'd her conquests made in vain, Her backward-beaten ranks, and countless slain;— Then had the strength of Europe's freedom stood, And still the Rhine had roll'd a German flood! “Oh! nursed in many a wile, and practised long To spoil the poor, and cringe before the strong; To swell the victor's state, and hovering near, Like some base vulture in the battle's rear, To watch the carnage of the field, and share Each loathsome alms the prouder eagles spare: A curse is on thee, Brandenburgh! thé sound Of Poland's wailing drags thee to the ground; And, drunk with guilt, thy harlot lips shall know The bitter dregs of Austria's cup of woe. “Enough of vengeance! O'er th' ensanguined plain I gaze, and seek their numerous host in vain; Gone like the locust band, when whirlwinds bear Their flimsy legions through the waste of air. Enough of vengeance!—By the glorious dead, Who bravely fell where youthful Lewis led; Prince Lewis Ferdinand of Prussia, who fell gloriously with almost the whole of his regiment. By Blücher's sword in fiercest danger tried, And the true heart that burst when Brunswick died; By her whose charms the coldest zeal might warm, The Queen of Prussia; beautiful, unfortunate, and unsubdued by the severest reverses. The manliest firmness in the fairest form— Save, Europe, save the remnant!—Yet remains One glorious path to free the world from chains. Why, when yon northern band in Eylau's wood Retreating struck, and track'd their course with blood, While one firm rock the floods of ruin stay'd, Why, generous Austria, were thy wheels delay'd? And Albion!”—Darker sorrow veil'd his brow— “Friend of the friendless—Albion, where art thou? Child of the Sea, whose wing-like sails are spread, The covering cherub of the ocean's bed! “Thou art the anointed cherub that coverest.”—Addressed to Tyre, by Ezekiel, xxviii. 14. The storm and tempest render peace to thee, And the wild-roaring waves a stern security. But hope not thou in Heaven's own strength to ride, Freedom's loved ark, o'er broad oppression's tide; If virtue leave thee, if thy careless eye Glance in contempt on Europe's agony. Alas! where now the bands who wont to pour Their strong deliverance on th' Egyptian shore? Wing, wing your course, a prostrate world to save, Triumphant squadrons of Trafalgar's wave. “And thou, blest star of Europe's darkest hour, Whose words were wisdom and whose counsels power, Whom Earth applauded through her peopled shores! (Alas! whom Earth too early lost deplores:—) Young without follies, without rashness bold, And greatly poor amidst a nation's gold! In every veering gale of faction true, Untarnish'd Chatham's genuine child, adieu! Unlike our common suns, whose gradual ray Expands from twilight to intenser day, Thy blaze broke forth at once in full meridian sway. O, proved in danger! not the fiercest flame Of discord's rage thy constant soul could tame; Not when, far striding, o'er thy palsied land, Gigantic treason took his bolder stand; Not when wild zeal, by murderous faction led, On Wicklow's hills her grass-green banner spread; Or those stern conquerors of the restless wave Defied the native soil they wont to save.— Undaunted patriot! in that dreadful hour, When pride and genius own a sterner power; When the dimm'd eyeball, and the struggling breath, And pain, and terror, mark advancing death;— Still in that breast thy country held her throne, Thy toil, thy fear, thy prayer, were hers alone, Thy last faint effort hers, and hers thy parting groan. “Yes, from those lips while fainting nations drew Hope ever strong, and courage ever new;— Yet, yet, I deem'd by that supporting hand Propp'd in her fall might Freedom's ruin stand; And purged by fire, and stronger from the storm, Degraded justice rear her reverend form. Now hope adieu!—adieu the generous care To shield the weak, and tame the proud in war! The golden chain of realms, when equal awe Poised the strong balance of impartial law; When rival states as federate sisters shone, Alike, yet various, and though many, one; And, bright and numerous as the spangled sky, Beam'd each fair star of Europe's galaxy— All, all are gone, and after-time shall trace One boundless rule, one undistinguish'd race; Twilight of worth, where nought remains to move The patriot's ardour, or the subject's love. “Behold, e'en now, while every manly lore And every muse forsakes my yielding shore; Faint, vapid fruits of slavery's sickly clime, Each tinsel art succeeds, and harlot rhyme! To gild the vase, to bid the purple spread In sightly foldings o'er the Grecian bed, Their mimic guard where sculptured gryphons keep, And Memphian idols watch o'er beauty's sleep; To rouse the slumbering sparks of faint desire With the base tinkling of the Teian lyre; While youth's enervate glance and gloating age Hang o'er the mazy waltz, or pageant stage; Each wayward wish of sickly taste to please, The nightly revel and the noontide ease— These, Europe, are thy toils, thy trophies these! “So, when wide-wasting hail, or whelming rain, Have strew'd the bearded hope of golden grain, From the wet furrow, struggling to the skies, The tall, rank weeds in barren splendour rise; And strong, and towering o'er the mildew'd ear, Uncomely flowers and baneful herbs appear; The swain's rich toils to useless poppies yield, And Famine stalks along the purple field. “And thou, the poet's theme, the patriot's prayer!— Where, France, thy hopes, thy gilded promise, where? When o'er Montpelier's vines, and Jura's snows, All goodly bright, young freedom's planet rose? What boots it now, (to our destruction brave,) How strong thine arm in war? a valiant slave! What boots it now that wide thine eagles sail, Fann'd by the flattering breath of conquest's gale? What, that, high-piled within yon ample dome, The blood-bought treasures rest of Greece and Rome? Scourge of the Highest, bolt in vengeance hurl'd By Heaven's dread justice on a shrinking world! Go, vanquish'd victor, bend thy proud helm down Before thy sullen tyrant's steely crown, For him in Afric's sands, and Poland's snows, Rear'd by thy toil the shadowy laurel grows; And rank in German fields the harvest springs Of pageant councils and obsequious kings. Such purple slaves, of glittering fetters vain, Link'd the wide circuit of the Latian chain; And slaves like these shall every tyrant find, To gild oppression, and debase mankind. “Oh! live there yet whose hardy souls and high, Peace bought with shame, and tranquil bonds defy? Who, driven from every shore, and lords in vain Of the wide prison of the lonely main, Cling to their country's rights with freeborn zeal, More strong from every stroke, and patient of the steel? Guiltless of chains, to them has Heaven consign'd Th' entrusted cause of Europe and mankind! Or hope we yet in Sweden's martial snows That freedom's weary foot may find repose? No;—from yon hermit shade, yon cypress dell, Where faintly peals the distant matin-bell; Where bigot kings and tyrant priests had shed Their sleepy venom o'er his dreadful head; He wakes, th' avenger—hark! the hills around, Untamed Asturia bids her clarion sound; And many an ancient rock, and fleecy plain, And many a valiant heart returns the strain: Heard by that shore, where Calpe's armed steep Flings its long shadow o'er th' Herculean deep, And Lusian glades, whose hoary poplars wave In soft, sad murmurs over Inez' grave. Inez de Castro, the beloved mistress of the Infant Don Pedro, son of Alphonso IV. King of Portugal, and stabbed by the orders, and, according to Camoëns, in the presence of that monarch. A fountain near Coimbra, the scene of their loves and misfortunes, is still pointed out by tradition, and called Amores.—De la Clede, Hist. de Portugalle, 4to. tom. i. page 282—7; and Camoëns' Lusiad, canto 3, stanza cxxxv. They bless the call who dared the first withstand The Asturians, who under Pelagius first opposed the career of Mahometan success. The Moslem wasters of their bleeding land, When firm in faith, and red with slaughter'd foes, Thy spear-encircled crown, Asturia, “La couronne de fer de Dom Pélage,—cette couronne si simple mais si glorieuse, dont chaque fleuron est formé du fer d'une lance arrachée aux Chevaliers Maures que ce héros avoit fait tomber sous ses coups.” Roman de Dom Ursino le Navarin, Tressan, tom. ix. 52. rose. Nor these alone; as loud the war-notes swell, La Mancha's shepherd quits his cork-built cell; Alhama's strength is there, and those who till (A hardy race!) Morena's scorched hill; And in rude arms through wide Gallicia's reign, The swarthy vintage pours her vigorous train. “Saw ye those tribes? not theirs the plumed boast, The sightly trappings of a marshall'd host; No weeping nations curse their deadly skill, Expert in danger, and enured to kill:— But theirs the kindling eye, the strenuous arm: Theirs the dark cheek, with patriot ardour warm, Unblanch'd by sluggard ease, or slavish fear, And proud and pure the blood that mantles there. Theirs from the birth is toil;—o'er granite steep, And heathy wild, to guard the wandering sheep; To urge the labouring mule, or bend the spear 'Gainst the night-prowling wolf, or felon bear; The bull's hoarse rage in dreadful sport to mock, And meet with single sword his bellowing shock. Each martial chant they know, each manly rhyme, Rude, ancient lays of Spain's heroic time; See the two elegant specimens given by Bishop Percy in his Reliques; and the more accurate translations of Mr. Rodd, in his Civil Wars of Granada. Of him in Xeres' carnage fearless found, The Gothic monarchy in Spain was overthrown by the Mussulmans at the battle of Xeres, the Christian army being defeated with dreadful slaughter, and the death of their king, the unhappy and licentious Roderigo. Pelagius assembled the small band of those fugitives who despised submission, amid the mountains of the Asturias, under the name of King of Oviedo. (His glittering brows with hostile spear-heads bound;) Of that chaste king whose hardy mountain train Alonso, surnamed the Chaste, with ample reason, if we believe his historians: who defeated, according to the Spanish romances, and the graver authority of Mariana, the whole force of Charlemagne and the twelve peers of France, at Roncesvalles. Bertrand del Carpio, the son of Alonso's sister, Ximena, was his general; and according to Don Quixote (no incompetent authority on such a subject), put the celebrated Orlando to the same death as Hercules inflicted on Antæus. His reason was, that the nephew of Charlemagne was enchanted, and, like Achilles, only vulnerable in the heel, to guard which he wore always iron shoes.—See Mariana, l. vii. c. xi.; Don Quixote, book i. c. i.; and the notes on Mr. Southey's Chronicle of the Cid; a work replete with powerful description, and knowledge of ancient history and manners, and which adds a new wreath to one, who “nullum fere scribendi genus intactum reliquit, nullum quod tetigit non ornavit.” O'erthrew the knightly race of Charlemagne; And chiefest him who rear'd his banner tall Rodrigo Diaz, of Biva, surnamed the Cid by the Moors.—See Mr. Southey's Chronicle. (Illustrious exile!) o'er Valencia's wall; Ungraced by kings, whose Moorish title rose The toil-earn'd homage of his wondering foes. “Yes; every mouldering tower and haunted flood, And the wild murmurs of the waving wood; Each sandy waste, and orange-scented dell, And red Buraba's field, and Lugo, Buraba and Lugo were renowned scenes of Spanish victories over the Moors, in the reigns of Bermudo, or, as his name is Latinized, Veremundus, and Alonso the Chaste. Of Lugo the British have since obtained a melancholy knowledge. tell, How their brave fathers fought, how thick the invaders fell. “Oh! virtue long forgot, or vainly tried, To glut a bigot's zeal, or tyrant's pride; Condemn'd in distant climes to bleed and die 'Mid the dank poisons of Tlascala's An extensive district of Mexico: its inhabitants were the first Indians who submitted to the Spaniards under Cortez. sky; Or when stern Austria stretch'd her lawless reign, And spent in northern fights the flower of Spain; Or war's hoarse furies yell'd on Ysell's shore, And Alva's ruffian sword was drunk with gore, Yet dared not then Tlaseala's chiefs withstand The lofty daring of Castilia's band; And weeping France her captive king Francis I. taken prisoner at the battle of Pavia. deplored, And cursed the deathful point of Ebro's sword. Now, nerved with hope, their night of slavery past, Each heart beats high in freedom's buxom blast; Lo! conquest calls, and beckoning from afar, Uplifts his laurel wreath, and waves them on to war. —Woe to th' usurper then, who dares defy The sturdy wrath of rustic loyalty! Woe to the hireling bands, foredoom'd to feel How strong in labour's horny hand the steel! Behold e'en now, beneath yon Bœtic skies Andalusia forms a part of the ancient Hispania Bœtica. Another Pavia bids her trophies rise;— E'en now in base disguise and friendly night, Their robber-monarch speeds his secret flight; And with new zeal the fiery Lusians rear, (Roused by their neighbour's worth) the long-neglected spear. “So when stern winter chills the April showers, And iron frost forbids the timely flowers; Oh, deem not thou the vigorous herb below Is crush'd and dead beneath th' incumbent snow: Such tardy suns shall wealthier harvests bring Than all the early smiles of flattering spring.” Sweet as the martial trumpet's silver swell, On my charm'd sense the unearthly accents fell: Me wonder held, and joy chastised by fear, As one who wish'd, yet hardly hoped to hear. “Spirit,” I cried, “dread teacher, yet declare, In that good fight, shall Albion's arm be there? Can Albion, brave and wise, and proud, refrain To hail a kindred soul, and link her fate with Spain? Too long her sons, estranged from war and toil, Have loathed the safety of the sea-girt isle; And chid the waves which pent their fire within, As the stall'd war-horse wooes the battle's din. Oh, by this throbbing heart, this patriot glow, Which, well I feel, each English breast shall know; Say, shall my country, roused from deadly sleep, Crowd with her hardy sons yon western steep? And shall once more the star of France grow pale, And dim its beams in Roncesvalles' vale? See the former note on Alonso the Chaste. Or shall foul sloth and timid doubt conspire To mar our zeal, and waste our manly fire?” Still as I gazed, his lowering features spread, High rose his form, and darkness veil'd his head; Fast from his eyes the ruddy lightning broke, To Heaven he rear'd his arm, and thus he spoke: “Woe, trebly woe to their slow zeal who bore Delusive comfort to Iberia's shore! Who in mid conquest, vaunting, yet dismay'd, Now gave, and now withdrew their laggard aid; Who, when each bosom glow'd, each heart beat high, Chill'd the pure stream of England's energy, And lost in courtly forms and blind delay The loiter'd hours of glory's short-lived day. “O peerless island, generous, bold, and free, Lost, ruin'd Albion, Europe mourns for thee! Hadst thou but known the hour in mercy given To stay thy doom, and ward the ire of Heaven; Bared in the cause of man thy warrior breast, And crush'd on yonder hills th' approaching pest, Then had not murder sack'd thy smiling plain, And wealth, and worth, and wisdom all been vain; “Yet, yet awake! while fear and wonder wait On the poised balance, trembling still with fate! This line is imitated from one in Mr. Roscoe's spirited verses on the commencement of the French revolution. If aught their worth can plead, in battle tried, Who tinged with slaughter Tajo's curdling tide; (What time base truce the wheels of war could stay, And the weak victor flung his wreath away;)— Or theirs, who, doled in scanty bands afar, Waged without hope the disproportion'd war, And cheerly still, and patient of distress, Led their forwasted files on numbers numberless! “He look'd and saw what numbers numberless.” Milton, Paradise Regained. “Yes, through the march of many a weary day, As yon dark column toils it seaward way; As bare, and shrinking from the inclement sky, The languid soldier bends him down to die; As o'er those helpless limbs, by murder gor'd, The base pursuer waves his weaker sword, And, trod to earth, by trampling thousands press'd The horse-hoof glances from that mangled breast;— E'en in that hour his hope to England flies, And fame and vengeance fire his closing eyes. “Oh! if such hope can plead, or his, whose bier Drew from his conquering host their latest tear; Whose skill, whose matchless valour, gilded flight: Entomb'd in foreign dust, a hasty soldier's rite;— Oh! rouse thee yet to conquer and to save, And wisdom guide the sword which justice gave! “And yet the end is not! from yonder towers While one Saguntum The ancient siege of Saguntum has been now rivalled by Zaragoza. The author is happy to refer his readers to the interesting narrative of his friend, Mr. Vaughan. mocks the victor's powers: While one brave heart defies a servile chain, And one true soldier wields a lance for Spain; Trust not, vain tyrant, though thy spoiler band In tenfold myriads darken half the land; (Vast as that power, against whose impious lord Bethulia's matron Judith. shook the nightly sword;) Though ruth and fear thy woundless soul defy, And fatal genius fire thy martial eye: Yet trust not here o'er yielding realms to roam, Or cheaply bear a bloodless laurel home. “No! by His viewless arm whose righteous care Defends the orphan's tear, the poor man's prayer; Who, Lord of Nature, o'er this changeful ball Decrees the rise of empires, and the fall; Wondrous in all His ways, unseen, unknown, Who treads the wine-press of the world alone; “I have trodden the wine-press alone, and of the people there was none with me, for I will tread them in mine anger, and trample them in my fury.”—Isaiah lxiii. 3. And rob'd in darkness, and surrounding fears, Speeds on their destin'd road the march of years! No!—shall yon eagle, from the snare set free, Stoop to thy wrist, or cower his wing for thee? And shall it tame despair, thy strong controul, Or quench a nation's still reviving soul?— Go, bid the force of countless bands conspire To urb the wandering wind, or grasp the fire! Cast thy vain fetters on the troublous sea!— But Spain, the brave, the virtuous, shall be free.” THE PASSAGE OF THE RED SEA. With heat o'erlabour'd and the length of way, On Ethan's beach the bands of Israel lay. 'Twas silence all, the sparkling sands along; Save where the locust trill'd her feeble song, Or blended soft in drowsy cadence fell The wave's low whisper or the camel's bell.— 'Twas silence all!—the flocks for shelter fly Where, waving light, the acacia shadows lie; Or where, from far, the flattering vapours make The noon-tide semblance of a misty lake: While the mute swain, in careless safety spread, With arms enfolded, and dejected head, Dreams o'er his wondrous call, his lineage high, And, late reveal'd, his children's destiny.— For, not in vain, in thraldom's darkest hour, Had sped from Amram's sons the word of power; Nor fail'd the dreadful wand, whose god-like sway Could lure the locust from her airy way; With reptile war assail their proud abodes, And mar the giant pomp of Egypt's Gods. Oh helpless Gods! who nought avail'd to shield From fiery rain your Zoan's favour'd field!— Oh helpless Gods! who saw the curdled blood Taint the pure lotus of your ancient flood, And fourfold-night the wondering earth enchain, While Memnon's orient harp was heard in vain!— Such musings held the tribes, till now the west With milder influence on their temples prest; And that portentous cloud which, all the day, Hung its dark curtain o'er their weary way, (A cloud by day, a friendly flame by night,) Roll'd back its misty veil, and kindled into light!— Soft fell the eve:—But, ere the day was done, Tall, waving banners streak'd the level sun; And wide and dark along the horizon red, In sandy surge the rising desert spread.— “Mark, Israel, mark!”—On that strange sight intent, In breathless terror, every eye was bent; And busy faction's fast-increasing hum And female voices shriek, “They come, they come!” They come, they come! in scintillating show O'er the dark mass the brazen lances glow; And sandy clouds in countless shapes combine, As deepens or extends the long tumultuous line;— And fancy's keener glance ev'n now may trace The threatening aspects of each mingled race: For many a coal-black tribe and cany spear, The hireling guards of Misraim's throne, were there. From distant Cush they troop'd, a warrior train, Siwah's Oasis.—Sennaar. Meroe. green isle and Sennaar's marly plain: On either wing their fiery coursers check The parch'd and sinewy sons of Amalek: While close behind, inured to feast on blood, Deck'd in Behemoth's spoils, the tall Shangalla The black tribes, whom Bruce considers as the aboriginal Nubians, are so called. For their gigantic stature, and their custom of ornamenting themselves and their houses with the spoils of the elephant, see the account he gives of the person and residence of one of their chiefs, whom he visited on his departure from Ras el Feel. strode. 'Mid blazing helms and bucklers rough with gold Saw ye how swift the scythed chariots roll'd? Lo, these are they whom, lords of Afric's fates, Old Thebes hath pour'd through all her hundred gates, Mother of armies!—How the emeralds The emerald, or whatever the ancients dignified by the name of smaragdus, is said to have been found in great quantities in the mountain now called Gebel Zumrud (the mount of emeralds). glow'd, Where, flush'd with power and vengeance, Pharaoh rode! And stoled in white, those brazen wheels before, Osiris' ark his swarthy wizards bore; And still responsive to the trumpet's cry The priestly sistrum murmur'd—Victory!— Why swell these shouts that rend the desert's gloom? Whom come ye forth to combat?—warriors, whom?— These flocks and herds—this faint and weary train— Red from the scourge and recent from the chain?— God of the poor, the poor and friendless save! Giver and Lord of freedom, help the slave!— North, south, and west, the sandy whirlwinds fly, The circling horns of Egypt's chivalry. On earth's last margin throng the weeping train: Their cloudy guide moves on:—“And must we swim the main?” 'Mid the light spray their snorting camels stood, Nor bathed a fetlock in the nauseous flood— He comes—their leader comes?—the man of God O'er the wide waters lifts his mighty rod, And onward treads—The circling waves retreat, In hoarse deep murmurs, from his holy feet; And the chased surges, inly roaring, show The hard wet sand and coral hills below. With limbs that falter, and with hearts that swell, Down, down they pass—a steep and slippery dell— Around them rise, in pristine chaos hurl'd, The ancient rocks, the secrets of the world; And flowers that blush beneath the ocean green, And caves, the sea-calves' low-roof'd haunt are seen. Down, safely down the narrow pass they tread; The beetling waters storm above their head: While far behind retires the sinking day, And fades on Edom's hills its latest ray. Yet not from Israel fled the friendly light, Or dark to them, or cheerless came the night. Still in their van, along that dreadful road, Blazed broad and fierce the brandish'd torch of God. Its meteor glare a tenfold lustre gave On the long mirror of the rosy wave: While its blest beams a sunlike heat supply, Warm every cheek, and dance in every eye— To them alone—for Misraim's wizard train Invoke for light their monster-gods in vain: Clouds heap'd on clouds their struggling sight confine, And tenfold darkness broods above their line. Yet on they fare by reckless vengeance led, And range unconscious through the ocean's bed: Till midway now—that strange and fiery form Show'd his dread visage lightening through the storm; With withering splendour blasted all their might, And brake their chariot-wheels, and marr'd their coursers' flight, “Fly, Misraim, fly!”—The ravenous floods they see, And, fiercer than the floods, the Deity. “Fly, Misraim, fly!”—From Edom's coral strand Again the prophet stretch'd his dreadful wand:— With one wild crash the thundering waters sweep, And all is waves—a dark and lonely deep— Yet o'er those lonely waves such murmurs past, As mortal wailing swell'd the nightly blast: And strange and sad the whispering breezes bore The groans of Egypt to Arabia's shore. Oh! welcome came the morn, where Israel stood In trustless wonder by th' avenging flood! Oh! welcome came the cheerful morn, to show The drifted wreck of Zoan's pride below; The mangled limbs of men—the broken car— A few sad relics of a nation's war: Alas, how few!—Then, soft as Elim's well, It is interesting to observe with what pleasure and minuteness Moses, amid the Arabian wilderness, enumerates the “twelve wells of water,” and the “threescore and ten palm-trees,” of Elim. The precious tears of new-born freedom fell. And he, whose harden'd heart alike had borne The house of bondage and th' oppressor's scorn, The stubborn slave, by hope's new beams subdued, In faltering accents sobb'd his gratitude— Till kindling into warmer zeal, around The virgin timbrel waked its silver sound: And in fierce joy, no more by doubt supprest, The struggling spirit throbb'd in Miriam's breast. She, with bare arms, and fixing on the sky The dark transparence of her lucid eye, Pour'd on the winds of heaven her wild sweet harmony. “Where now,” she sang, “the tall Egyptian spear? On's sunlike shield, and Zoan's chariot, where? Above their ranks the whelming waters spread. Shout Israel, for the Lord hath triumphed!”— And every pause between, as Miriam sang, From tribe to tribe the martial thunder rang, And loud and far their stormy chorus spread,— “Shout, Israel, for the Lord hath triumphed!”</field>
      <field name="fulltext">FRAGMENT OF A POEM ON THE WORLD BEFORE THE FLOOD. The sons of God saw the daughters of men that they were fair. Gen. vi.2. There came a spirit down at eventide To the city of Enoch, and the terrac'd height Of Jared's palace. On his turret top There Jared sate, the king, with lifted face And eyes intent on Heaven, whose sober light Slept on his ample forehead, and the locks Of crisped silver; beautiful in age, And, (but that pride had dimm'd, and lust of war, Those reverend features with a darker shade,) Of saintly seeming,—yet no saintly mood, No heavenward musing fix'd that steadfast eye, God's enemy, and tyrant of mankind. To whom that demon herald, from the wing Alighting, spake: “Thus saith the prince of air, Whose star flames brightest in the van of night, Whom gods and heroes worship, all who sweep On sounding wing the arch of nether heaven, Or walk in mail the earth,—‘Thy prayers are heard, And the rich fragrance of thy sacrifice Hath not been wafted on the winds in vain. Have I not seen thy child, that she is fair? Give me thine Ada, thy beloved one, And she shall be my queen; and from her womb Shall giants spring, to rule the seed of Cain, And sit on Jared's throne!’” Then Jared rose, And spread his hands before the Evil power, And lifted up his voice and laugh'd for joy. “Say to my Lord, thus saith the king of men,— Thou art my god,—thy servant I,—my child Is as thine handmaid!—Nay, abide awhile, To taste the banquet of an earthly hall, And leave behind thy blessing!” But, in mist, And like a vision from a waken'd man, The cloudy messenger dissolved away, There melting where the moonbeam brightest fell. Then Jared turn'd, and from the turret top Call'd on his daughter—“Haste, my beautiful! Mine Ada, my beloved! bind with flowers Thy coal-black hair, and heap the sacred pile With freshest odours, and provoke the dance With harp and gilded organ, for this night We have found favour in immortal eyes, And the great gods have bless'd us.” Thus he spake, Nor spake unheeded; in the ample hall His daughter heard, where, by the cedar fire, Amidst her maidens, o'er the ivory loom She pass'd the threads of gold. They hush'd the song Which, wafted on the fragrant breeze of night, Swept o'er the city like the ringdove's call; And forth with all her damsels Ada came, As mid the stars the silver-mantled moon, In stature thus and form pre-eminent, Fairest of mortal maids. Her father saw That perfect comeliness, and his proud heart In purer bliss expanded. Long he gaz'd, Nor wonder deem'd that such should win the love Of Genius or of Angel; such the cheek Glossy with purple youth, such the large eye, Whose broad black mirror, through its silken fringe, Glisten'd with softer brightness, as a star That nightly twinkles o'er a mountain well; Such the long locks, whose raven mantle fell Athwart her ivory shoulders, and o'erspread Down to the heel her raiment's filmy fold. She, bending first in meekness, rose to meet Her sire's embrace, than him alone less tall, Whom, since primeval Cain, the sons of men Beheld unrivall'd; then, with rosy smile, “What seeks,” she said, “my father? Why remain On thy lone tower, when from the odorous hearth The sparkles rise within, and Ada's hand Hath deck'd thy banquet?” But the king replied,— “O fairest, happiest, best of mortal maids, My prayer is heard, and from yon western star Its lord hath look'd upon thee; as I sate Watching the Heavens, a Heavenly spirit came From him whom chiefest of the host of Heaven Our fathers honour'd,—whom we nightly serve (Since first Jehovah scorn'd such sacrifice) With frankincense and flowers and oil and corn, Our bloodless offering; him whose secret strength Hath girded us to war, and given the world To bow beneath our sceptre. He hath seen My child, that she is fair, and from her womb Shall giants spring, to rule the seed of Cain, And sit on Jared's throne. What, silent! nay, Kneel not to me; in loud thanksgiving kneel To him whose choice—Now by the glorious stars She weeps, she turns away! Unhappy child! And lingers yet thy mother's boding lore So deeply in thy soul? Curse on the hour That ever Jared bore a bride away From western Eden! Have I train'd thy youth Untouch'd by mortal love, by mortal eyes Seen and adored far off, and in the shrine Of solemn majesty reserved, a flower Of guarded paradise, whom men should praise, But angels only gather? Have I toil'd To swell thy greatness, till our brazen chain From furthest Ararat to ocean's stream Hath bound the nations? And when all my vows At length are crown'd, and Heaven with earth conspires To yield thee worship, dost thou then rebel, And hate thy happiness? Bethink thee, maid, Ere yet thine answer, not to be recall'd, Hath pass'd those ivory gates—bethink thee well. Who shall recount the blessings which our gods Have richly lavish'd on the seed of Cain? And who, if stung by thine ingratitude, Can meet their vengeance?” Then the maiden rose, And folding on her breast her ivory arms, “Father,” she said, “thou deem'st thy warrior gods Are mighty,—One above is mightier: Name Him, they tremble. Kind, thou call'st them; Lavish of blessings. Is that blessedness To sin with them? to hold a hideous rule, Water'd with widows' tears and blood of men, O'er those who curse our name? Thy bands went forth, And brought back captives from the palmy side Of far Euphrates. One thou gavest me, A woman for mine handmaid; I have heard Her mournful songs as, in the strangers' land She wept and plied the loom. I question'd her: Oh, what a tale she told! And are they good,— The gods whose work these are! They are not good,— And, if not good, not gods. But there is One, I know, I feel, a good, a Holy One, The God who fills my heart, when, with glad tears, I think upon my mother; when I strive To be like her, like her to soothe thy cares With perfect tenderness. O father, king, Most honour'd, most belov'd, than Him alone Who gives us all less worshipp'd! at thy feet I lowly cast me down; I clasp thy knees, And, in her name who most of womankind Thy soul hath blessed, by whose bed of death In short-lived penitence thy sorrow vow'd To serve her God alone,—forgive me now If I resemble her!” But in fierce wrath The king replied,—“And know'st thou not, weak girl, Thy God hath cast us off? hath scorn'd of old Our father's offering, driven us from His face, And mark'd us for destruction? Can thy prayer Pierce through the curse of Cain—thy duty please That terrible One, whose angels are not free From sin before Him?” Then the maiden spake: “Alas! I know mine own unworthiness, Our hapless race I know. Yet God is good; Yet is He merciful: the sire of Cain Forgiveness found, and Cain himself, though steep'd In brother's blood, had found it, if his pride Had not disdain'd the needful sacrifice, And turn'd to other masters. One shall be, In after times, my mother wont to tell, Whose blood shall help the guilty. When my soul Is sick to death, this comfort lingers here, This hope survives within me; for His sake, Whose name I know not, God will hear my prayer, And, though He slay me, I will trust in Him.” Here Ada ceased, for from her father's eye The fire flash'd fast, and on his curling lip The white foam trembled. “Gone,” he cried, “all gone! My heart's desire, the labour of my youth, Mine age's solace gone! Degenerate child, Enemy of our gods, chief enemy To thine own glory! What forbids my foot To spurn thy life out, or this dreadful hand To cast thee from the tower a sacrifice To those whom thou hast scorn'd? Accurs'd be thou Of Him thou seek'st in vain! accursed He, Whose hated worship hath entic'd thy feet From the bright altars of the host of Heaven! I curse Him—mark me well—I curse Him, Ada! And, lo! He smiteth not!” But Ada bow'd Her head to earth, and hid her face, and wept In agony of prayer. “Yea,” cried the king, “Yea, let Him smite me now, for what hath life Left worth the keeping? Yet, I thank the stars, Vengeance may yet be mine! Look up and hear Thy monarch, not thy father! Till this hour I have spared thy mother's people; they have pray'd And hymn'd, and have blasphem'd the prince of air; And, as thou saidest, they have curs'd my reign; And I have spar'd them! But no longer—no! Thyself hast lit the fire, nor Lucifer Shall longer tax my sword for tardy zeal, And thou shalt live to see it!” From his path He spurn'd his prostrate child, and groaning, wrapt The mantle round his face, and pass'd away Unheard of her whom, stretch'd in seeming death, Her maidens tended. Oh, that, in this hour Her soul had fled indeed, nor wak'd again To keener suffering! Yet shall man refuse The bitter cup whose dregs are blessedness? Or shall we hate the friendly hand which guides To nobler triumph through severer woe? Thus Ada murmur'd, thus within her spake (In answer to such impious murmurings) A spirit not her own. Stretch'd on her couch She silent lay. The maidens had retir'd Observant of her rest. Her nurse alone, Shaking and muttering with a parent's fear, Knelt by her side, and watch'd her painful breath, And the wild horror of her fixed eye, And long'd to hear her voice. “Peninnah! thou! My mother, is it thou?” the princess cried; And that old woman kiss'd her feet and wept In rapturous fondness. “Oh my child! my child! The blessing of thy mother's mighty God Rest on thine innocent head, and 'quite thy love For those kind accents. All, my lovely one, All may be well. Thy father doats on thee; And, when his wrath is spent, his love, be sure, Will grant thee all thy will. Oh lamps of Heaven! Can ye behold her thus nor pity her! Is this your love, ye gods!”—“Name not the gods,” The princess cried, “the wretched gods of Cain; My mother's God be mine; they are no gods Whose fleshly fancy doats on mortal clay, Whose love is ruin! Thinkest thou this night I have first withstood their tempting? first have proved Their utter weakness?”—“Have the angels, then, Visited thee of old?” the nurse inquired, “Or hath thy father told thee of their love And thou hast kept it from me?” As she spake A bright and bitter glance of lofty scorn Shot from the virgin's eyes. A mantling blush Of hallow'd courage darken'd on her cheek; She waved her arm as one whose kingly state Repels intrusion from his privacy, And answer'd, with a calm but painful smile: “They are beside us now! Nay quake not thus, I fear them not; yet they are terrible— But they are past, resist them and they flee, And all is peace again; yet have I groan'd Beneath such visitation, till my faith In Him I serve hath almost pass'd away.” With that she rose, and wrapt in silent thought, Gaz'd through the portal long,—then pac'd awhile The marble pavement, now from side to side Tossing her restless arms, now clasping close Her hands in supplication, lifting now Her eloquent eyes to Heaven,—then sought again Her lowly couch, and, by the nurse's side, Resum'd the wondrous tale. “Oh friend,” she cried, “And only mother now, yon silver moon Has twenty times renew'd her course in Heaven, Since, as my bosom o'er its girlish zone With painful tightness rose, I bade thee change Th' imprisoning cincture. Canst thou yet recal Thy playful words of praise—thy prophecies Of one to loose ere long that golden clasp, A royal bridegroom? Strange to me, thy words Sunk in my soul, and busy fancy strove To picture forth that unknown visitant, His form and bearing. Musing thus, and lost In troubl'd contemplation, o'er my soul A heavy slumber fell; I sank not down; I saw, I heard, I mov'd; the spell was laid Within me, and from forth my secret heart A stranger's accents came: ‘Oh! blessed maid! Most beautiful, most honour'd! not for thee Be mortal marriage, nor the feeble love Of those whose beauty is a mortal dream, Whose age a shadow. What is man, whose day, In the poor circuit of a thousand years, Reverts again to dust? Thee, maiden! thee The Gods have seen: the never-dying stars Gaze on thy loveliness, and thou shalt reign A new Astarte. Bind thy flowing hair, Brace on thy sandals, seek the myrtle grove West of the city, and the cavern well, Whose clear black waters from their silent spring Ripple with ceaseless stir: thy lover there Waits thee in secret, and thy soul shall learn The raptures of a god! But cast away That peevish bauble which thy mother gave, Her hated talisman.’ That word recall'd My straggling senses and her dying prayer Pass'd through my soul like fire; the tempter fell Abash'd before it, and a living voice Of most true consolation o'er me came, ‘Nor love nor fear them, Ada; love not them Who hate thy mother's memory; fear not them Who fear thy mother's God; for this she gave, Prophetic of this hour, that graven gold, Which bears the title of the Eternal One, And binds thee to His service: guard it well, And guard the faith it teaches; safer so Than girt around by brazen walls, and gates Of seven-fold cedar.’ Since that hour, my heart Hath kept its covenant, nor shrunk beneath The spirits of evil; yet, not so repell'd, They watch me in my walks, spy out my ways, And still with nightly whispers vex my soul, To seek the myrtle thicket. Bolder now, They speak of duty—of a father's will, Now first unkind—a father's kingly power, Tremendous when oppos'd. My God, they say, Bids me revere my parent; will He guard A rebel daughter? Wiser to comply, Ere force compels me to my happiness, And to my lover yield that sacrifice Which else my foe may seize. Oh God! great God! Of whom I am, and whom I serve alone, Be thou my strength in weakness—Thou my guide, And save me from this hour!” Thus, as she spake, With naked feet and silent, in the cloud Of a long mantle wrapt, as one who shuns The busy eyes and babbling tongues of men, A warrior enter'd; o'er his helm The casque was drawn</field>
      <field name="fulltext">MORTE D'ARTHUR. A fragment. CANTO I. It was the blessed morn of Whitsuntide, And Carduel echoed to the festive call, As his shrill task the clear-voiced herald plied, And shriller trumpet shook the castle wall. I Ye whom the world has wrong'd, whom men despise, Who sadly wander through this vale of tears, And lift in silent dread your wistful eyes O'er the bleak wilderness of future years, Where from the storm no sheltering bourn appears; Whom genius, moody guide, has led astray, And pride has mock'd, and want with chilling fears, Quench'd of each youthful hope the timid ray; Yet envy not the great, yet envy not the gay! II Say, can the silken bed refreshment bring, When from the restless spirit sleep retires? Or, the sharp fever of the serpent's sting, Pains it less shrewdly for his burnish'd spires? Oh, worthless is the bliss the world admires, And helpless whom the vulgar mightiest deem; Tasteless fruition, impotent desires, Pomp, pleasure, pride, how valueless ye seem When the poor soul awakes, and finds its life a dream! III And those, if such may ponder o'er my song, Whose light heart bounds to pleasure's minstrelsy; To whom the faëry realms of love belong; And the gay motes of young prosperity, Dance in thy sunshine and obscure thine eye; Suspect of earthly good the gilded snare, When sorrow wreathes her brow with revelry, And friendship's hollow smiles thy wreck prepare! Alas! that demon forms should boast a mask so fair! IV See'st thou yon flutterer in the summer sky, Wild as thy glance, and graceful as thy form? Yet, lady, know, yon beauteous butterfly Is parent of the loathsome canker-worm, Whose restless tooth, worse than December's storm, Shall mar thy woodbine bower with greedy rage.— Fair was her face as thine, her heart as warm, Whose antique story marks my simple page; Yet luckless youth was hers, and sorrowful old age! V 'Twas merry in the streets of Carduel, When Pentecost renew'd her festive call, And the loud trumpet's clang and louder bell The moss-grown abbey shook and banner'd wall; And still, from bower to mass, from mass to hall, A sea of heads throughout the city flowed; And, robed in fur, in purple, and in pall, Of knights and dames the gaudy pageant yode, And conquering Arthur last, and young Ganora rode. VI Still as they pass'd, from many a scaffold high, And window-lattice scatter'd roses flew, And maidens, leaning from the balcony, Bent their white necks the stranger bride to view, Whom that same morn, or ere the sparkling dew Had from his city's herb-strewn pavement fled, A village maid, who rank nor splendour knew, To Mary's aisle the conqueror's hand had led, To deck her monarch's throne, to bless her monarch's bed. VII Who then was joyful but the Logrian king? Not that his hand a five-fold sceptre bore; King Arthur, according to his historian, Sir Thomas Malory, reigned in Britain about the beginning of the sixth century; he conquered Ireland, France, Denmark, and Norway, and was victorious in several expeditions against the Saracens, many of whom he forcibly converted to Christianity. He instituted the order of the Round Table made by Merlin “in token of the roundness of the world.” Hist. of Prince Arthur, Part II. chap. 50. Traditionary traces of king Arthur, of the loves of his queen Guenever (or Ganora) and Sir Lancelot, with the adventures of the Knights of the Round Table, are still to be found in Wales, and in parts of Shropshire. Not that the Scandian raven's robber wing Stoop'd to his dragon banner, and the shore Of peopled Gallia, and where ocean h o ar Girds with his silver ring the island green Of saints and heroes; not that paynim gore Clung to his blade, and, first in danger seen, In many a forward fight his golden shield had been. VIII Nor warrior fame it was, nor kingly state That swell'd his heart, though in that thoughtful eye And brow that might not, even in mirth, abate Its regal care and wonted majesty, Unlike to love, a something seem'd to lie; Yet love's ascendant planet rul'd the hour. And as he gaz'd with lover's ecstacy, And blended pride upon that beauteous flower, Could fame, could empire vie with such a paramour? IX For many a melting eye of deepest blue, And many a form of goodliest mould were there, And ivory necks and lips of coral hue, And many an auburn braid of glossy hair. But ill might all those gorgeous dames compare With her in flowers and bridal white array'd; Was none so stately form nor face so fair As hers, whose eyes, as mournful or afraid, Were big with heavy tears, the trembling village maid. X Yet whoso list her dark and lucid eye, And the pure witness of her cheek to read, Might written mark in nature's registry, That this fair rustic was not such indeed, But high-born offspring of some ancient seed. And, sooth, she was the heir of Carmelide, And old Ladugan's blood, whose daring deed With rebel gore Lancastrian meadows dyed, Or ere that Uther's son his mightier aid supplied. XI But, when the murderous Ryence' archer band With broad destruction swept the Ribble side, Ladugan forth from that devoted land His daughter sent, a smiling babe, to bide Where Derwent's lonely mirror dark and wide Reflects the dappled heaven and purple steep, Unhonour'd there, unown'd and undescried, Till fate compell'd her from her tended sheep, In Arthur's kingly bower to wear a crown and weep. XII There are who teach such crystal drops express (So near is each extreme of joy or woe) Alike, the burst of painful happiness, And the still smart of misery's inward throe. From man's perturbed soul alike they flow, Where bitter doubt and recollected sorrow Blend with the cup of bliss, and none can know From human grief how short a space to borrow, Or how the fairest eve may bring the darkest morrow. XIII Say, fared it thus with young Ganora's heart? Did hope, did Hymen call the rapturous tear? Or mourn'd perchance the village maid to part From all the humble joys her heart held dear? And, turning from that kingly front severe, Roam'd her sad memory o'er each milder grace Of him her earliest love, the forestere? Ah lost for ever now! yet sweet to trace The silver studded horn, green garb, and beardless face. XIV The chanted anthem's heaven-ascending sound Her spirit mov'd not with its sacred swell; And, all in vain, for twenty steeples round Crash'd with sonorous din the festive bell; Upon her tranced ear in vain it fell! As little mark'd she, that the monarch's tongue Would oft of love in courtly whisper tell; While from the castle bridge a minstrel throng, To many a gilded harp attun'd the nuptial song. XV “Ah see,” 'twas thus began the lovely lay, “The warrior-god hath laid his armour by, And doft his deadly sword, awhile to play In the dark radiance of Dione's eye; Snared in her raven locks behold him lie, And on her lap his dreadful head reclined; May every knight such silken fetters try, Such mutual bands may every lady bind! How blest the soldier's life if love were always kind! XVI “Oh Goddess of the soul-entrancing zone, Look down and mark a fairer Venus here, Call'd from her hamlet to an empire's throne, As meet of womankind the crown to wear, And of a nobler Mars the consort dear! Oh fairest, mildest, best, by heaven design'd With soothing smiles his kingly toil to cheer, Still may thy dulcet chain the conqueror bind. Sure earth itself were heaven if love were always kind!” XVII So sang they till the gaudy train had past The sullen entrance of that ancient tower, Which o'er the trembling wave its shadow cast, Grim monument of Rome's departed power. That same, in Albion's tributary hour, The Latian lords of earth had edified, Which all unharm'd in many a martial stour, Might endless as the steadfast hills abide, Or as the eternal stream that crept its base beside. XVIII And Arthur here had fix'd his kingly see, And hither had he borne his destin'd bride, Amid those civil storms secure to be That rock'd the troublous land on every side. For not the fell balista, bristling wide With barbed death, or whirling rocks afar, Nor aught by that Trinacrian artist tried, To save his leagured town such strength could mar. How easy then to mock the barbarous Saxon war. XIX Austere and stern, a warrior front it wore, The long dim entrance to that palace pile, And crisped moss, and lichen ever hoar, Trail'd their moist tresses in the portal aisle. But, past the gate, like some rude veteran's smile Kindly, through dark, a milder grace it show'd; And music shook the courts, and all the while Fair stripling youths along the steepy road, Fresh flowers before their feet and myrtle branches strew'd. XX By them they pass, and now the giant hall Bids to the train its oaken valves unfold, From whose high rafter'd roof and arched wall, Five hundred pennons, prize of war, unroll'd, In various silk display'd and waving gold, The armories of many a conquer'd knight; And some of Arthur's sword the fortune told, Of Gawain some, but most were redde aright, “These Lancelot du Lake achieved in open fight.” XXI Here might I sing (what many a bard has sung) Each gorgeous usage of that kingly hall; How harp, and voice, and clashing goblet rung, Of page and herald, bard and seneschall. But antique times were rude and homely all; And ill might Arthur's nuptial banquet vie, With theirs who nature's kindly fruits forestall, And brave the seas for frantic gluttony, And every various bane of every clime supply, XXII Nor car'd the king, a soldier tried and true, For such vain pampering of impure delight. His toys, his gauds, were all of manlier hue, [bright; Swift steeds, keen dogs, sharp swords, and armour Yet wanted nought that well became a knight Of seemly pomp; the floor with rushes green, And smooth bright board with plenteous viands dight, That scant the load might bear, though well be seen With ribs and rafters strong, and ponderous oak between. XXIII And shame it were to pass the warrior state Of those, the favour'd few, whose table round, Fast by their sovereign and his beauteous mate, Apart from all the subject train, was crowned, Whose manly locks with laurel wreaths were bound, And ermine wrapt their limbs; yet on the wall Their helms, and spears, and painted shields werefound, And mails, and gilded greaves, at danger's call, Aye prompt for needful use whatever chance might fall. XXIV And bounded high the monarch's heart of pride, Who gazed exulting on that noble crew; And leaning to his silent spouse, he cried, “Seest thou, Ganore, thy band of liegemen true? Lo, these are they whose fame the liquid blue Of upper air transcends; nor lives there one Of all who gaze on Phœbus' golden hue, From earth's cold circle to the burning zone, To whom of Arthur's knights the toil remains unknown. XXV “Yes, mark him well, the chief whose auburn hair So crisply curls above his hazel eye, And parted leaves the manly forehead bare. That same is Gawain, flower of courtesy; Yet few with him in listed field may vie. Gahriet the next, in blood the next and might; And Carados whose lady's loyalty Sir Carados was the only Knight of the Round Table who possessed a wife of fidelity sufficient to enable her to wear the enchanted mantle, and to wind the horn brought by a fairy to King Arthur's court.The mantle gain'd and horn of silver bright; And stout Sir Kay, stout heart, but not so strong in fight, XXVI “But he, the best of all and bravest peer That drinks this hour the crystal air of day; The most renowned and to me most dear, As ill befalls, is journey'd far away, A strange and stern adventure to essay, Whom Heaven defend, and to his friend's embrace Again resistless Lancelot convey!” So spake the king, and more his words to grace, An unsuspected tear stole down his manly face. XXVII To whom with faltering voice Ganora spake, “Oh happy knights of such a king,” she said, “And happy king for whose revered sake So valiant knights unsheathe the deadly blade! And worthless I, an untaught village maid, In Arthur's court to fill the envied throne, Who meeter far in russet weeds array'd, Had fed my flock on Skiddaw's summit lone, Unknowing of mankind and by mankind unknown.” XXVIII The monarch smiled, a proud protecting smile, That spoke her lovelier for her lowliness; And, bending from his loftier seat the while, Hung o'er her heaving form, yet ill could guess What terror strove within, what deep distress Rose in her painful throat, while struggling there, A stronger awe the sob would fain repress; Nor other cause he sought than maiden fear To chill the shrinking hand, to call the trickling tear. XXIX “Mine own Ganore!” he said, “my gentle maid! Oh deem not of thyself unworthily; By charms like thine a king were well repaid, Who yielded up for love his royalty. And heroes old, and they that rule the sky, Have sought in lowly cot, as fables tell, A purer love than gems or gold can buy, And beauty oftener found in mountain cell, Than with the lofty dames in regal court who dwell. XXX “Go, ask the noblest of my knightly power, Ask of Sir Lancelot, what secret pain So oft hath drawn him forth at twilight hour, To woods and wilds, his absent love to plain, Whom many a courtly fair hath sought in vain? Oh, he will tell thee that the greenwood tree Recalls the hour of happier youth again, When blithe he wont to range the forest free, With her, his earliest choice, the maid of low degree.” XXXI He ceased, to whom the maiden nought replied, But in the patience of her misery Possess'd her secret soul, and inly sigh'd. “Why ponder thus on what no more may be? Why think on him who never thinks on thee? For now seven autumns have with changing hue Embrown'd the verdure of our tr sting-tree, Since that shrill horn the wonted signal blew, Or that swift foot was heard brushing the twilight dew. XXXII “Then rouse thee yet thy silent griefs to bear, And rein the troublous thoughts so far that rove: Faithless or dead, he little needs thy care; And ill such thoughts a wedded wife behove; Then turn to him who claims thy plighted love; Nor weeping thus, thine inward shame confess, Whom knightly worth nor regal state may move; Nor he whom Albion's sister-islands bless, Can tame thy stubborn grief and minion frowardness!” XXXIII So sadly past the festal eve away, While at each courteous word her bosom bled, And every glance her heart could ill repay, Through the chill conscience like a dagger sped. Yet still with secret prayer her soul she fed, And burst with holier thoughts each inward snare, Which in that wither'd heart, where hope was dead, Yet hopeless passion wove, and darkest there, The dreadful whisper crept of comfortless despair. XXXIV And softer seem'd her silent grief to flow, And sweeter far her unrestrained tear, While soft and sweet, a tale of tender woe Iölo wove, the bard, whose harp to hear Even the rude warder, leaning on his spear, Prest to the further door; and squire, and knight, And lingering pages on those accents dear, Paus'd round the unserved board; and ladies bright, Breathless, with lips unclos'd, drank in the wild delight. XXXV A strange and melancholy tale it was, “Of one who, for a tyrant uncle's right, Lay bleeding, breathless, on the crimson grass, All vainly victor in th' unequal fight; And who is she whose hands of lily white, Too beauteous leech! his festering hurt would bind? Ah, fly thee, princess, from the Cornish knight, Who, now preserv'd, a sorer fate must find, By guilt, and late remorse, and hopeless passion pin'd. XXXVI “Yet pleasant was the dawn of early love, And sweet the faery bowl of magic power! Sir Tristan, being wounded in battle with Sir Marhans of Ireland, who had unjustly demanded truage from his uncle Sir Mark of Cornwall, was carried to Ireland, and there nursed by La beale Isonde (or Yseult), daughter to the king of that island. Some time after, Sir Mark, who was jealous of his nephew, sent him, on what was considered a dangerous embassage, to demand Isonde in marriage of her father. Sir Tristan successfully accomplished his mission, and set off with his uncle's destined bride to return to Cornwall. On their voyage they unfortunately drank of a love potion prepared by Isonde's mother to be given to Sir Mark on their wedding day. The consequence was, “that by that their drink they loved each other so well as that their love never departed from them for weal or woe.” Hist. of Prince Arthur, Part I. chap. 24. But following mists the early heat reprove, And April frosts abash the timid flower. Behold him now at midnight's harmful hour, His pale cheek pillow'd on his trembling knees, Whose frantic brain rejects the shelt'ring bower, Whose parched bosom woos the autumnal breeze, And whose poor broken heart sighs with the sighing trees. XXXVII “Ah, sweet it seem'd when, through the livelong day, 'Mid tall Iërne's forest dark and wide, In hunter garb he took his tireless way, Love in his breast and Yseult at his side! Gone are those days! Oh Yseult, oft he cried, Relentless Yseult, beauteous enemy! May happier fate thy gentle life betide, Nor ever may'st thou waste a tear on me, Nor guess the nameless tomb of him who pined for thee! XXXVIII “And Lancelot! (for, Lordings, well ye know How Tristan aye to Lancelot was dear) Sir Lancelot! he sung, of all below The best, the bravest, and the worthiest peer! To thee my helm I leave, and shield and spear, That not from harm their wretched lord might save. Yet, noblest friend, my last petition hear, By thine own secret love a boon I crave, Defend mine Yseult's fame when I am laid in grave.” XXXIX Here ceas'd the harp; but o'er its trembling chord In silent grief the minstrel's sorrow fell, And silence hush'd the throng where all deplor'd The recent woes of knight who lov'd so well, And most had known the heir of Lionelle; And sweet it seem'd for others' woe to weep To her whose secret anguish none could tell; Yet nigh such strain could lull her pangs to sleep; And now the star of eve beam'd o'er the twilight deep. XL When, in that sober light and sadness still, Arose a madd'ning hubbub hoarse and rude, Like hunters on the brow of dewy hill, And panting deer by nearer hounds pursued: And a cold shudder thrill'd the multitude, As, at the breath of that mysterious horn, Each with inquiring gaze his neighbour view'd, For never peal on woodland echoes borne, So ghastly and so shrill awoke the spangled morn. XLI At once the steely bars in twain were rent; At once the oaken valves asunder flew; And warrior breasts, in iron corslets pent, Their tighten'd breath with painful effort drew; For louder, louder far the tumult grew, That earth's firm planet quaked at the din, And the thick air assumed a browner hue, Such as on Nilus' bank hath whilom bin, When Amram's mighty son rebuked the tyrant's sin. XLII And through the portal arch that open'd wide (How came she or from whence no thought could tell) The wedding-guests with fearful wonder eyed, A hind of loveliest mould, whose snowy fell Was dyed, alas! with dolorous vermeill. For down her ruffled flank the current red, From many a wound issued in fatal well, As staggering faint with feeble haste she sped, And on Ganora's lap reclin'd her piteous head. XLIII With claws of molten brass, and eyes of flame, A grisly troop of hell-hounds thronging near, And on her foamy steed a damsel came, A damsel fair to see, whose maiden cheer But ill beseem'd the ruthless hunting spear; Whose golden locks in silken net were twin'd, And pure as heaving snow her bosom dear; Yet ceased she not that dreadful horn to wind, And strain'd a quivering dart for fatal use design'd. XLIV Reckless of loathed life, and free from stain Of deep transgression, could Ganora fear! Forlorn herself, she felt for others' pain, And cast her sheltering robe around the deer. To whom that magic maid with brow severe And glaring eye, “Oh, doom'd to lasting woe, Waste not, unhappy queen, thy pity here, Nor bid my righteous rage its prey forego, Who keener pangs thyself, Ganora, soon shalt know! XLV “Poor wither'd heart, that hid'st from human eye The bitter secret of thine inward wound, Go, doff the cumbrous garb of royalty, And seek betimes the cloister's sacred bound! Ah, warn'd in vain! I hear the clarion sound; Rings to the charger's tread the shadowy glen; For thee, for thee, the guarded list is crown'd; For thee dark treason quits her snaky den; The battle's roar resounds for thee, and groans of mangled men! XLVI “Heap high the wood, and bid the flames aspire! Bind her long tresses to th' accursed tree! A queen, a queen, must feed the funeral fire! Queen Guenever (or Ganora) was twice brought to the stake for treason, towards the latter end of Arthur's reign, and twice delivered by Sir Lancelot du Lac, who, on the second occasion, carried her off to his castle of Joyous Gard. Thither Arthur pursued her, and, though Lancelot tried to persuade him to “take his queen into his good grace, for that she was both fair and just and true,” he would not receive her again till, after the shedding of much knightly blood, the pope issued a bull, “commanding him upon pain of interdicting of all England, that he take his queen, dame Guenever, to him again, and accord with Sir Lancelot.” Hist. of Prince Arthur, Part II. chap. 154. On Arthur's death, Guenever retired into a nunnery at Almesbury, and Lancelot into a hermitage near Glastonbury. Ah, hope not thou, though love shall set thee free, With that restored love in peace to be. And shall my country bend her awful head To lick the bitter dust of slavery? Illustrious isle! is all thy glory fled? How soon thy knightly boast is number'd with the dead! XLVII “Yet art thou safe, and Arthur's throne may stand.” (Down from the lofty saddle, bending low, The dart she proffer'd to Ganora's hand;) “Nay, shrink not, maiden, from the needful blow, Nor spare, in yonder hind, thy fiercest foe, Whose secret hate from forth her dark recess, Besets thy guiltless life with snares of woe. Take, take the steel! thy wrongs and mine redress! Mercy were impious here!—be strong, be merciless!” XLVIII Giddy and faint, unknowing where she was, Or if, indeed, were sooth that ghastly view, Pale as some wintry lake, whose frozen glass Steals from the snow-clad heaven a paler hue, Ganora sate; but still, to pity true, Her milk-white arms around the quarry spread, Then rais'd to Heaven her eyes of mildest blue, And to her cheek return'd a dawning red, As, with collected soul, she bow'd herself and said:— XLIX “And I can suffer! let the storm descend; Let on this helpless head the thunder break; Yet, exercis'd in grief, yet, God to friend, I can endure the worst for mercy's sake! No, wretched suppliant!” (to the hind she spake That lick'd her hand, and with large tearful eye Dwelt on her gentle face:) “thy fears forsake! Be thou my friend, I doom thee not to die, And thy mute love shall cheer my joyless royalty.” L “Have then thy wish!” the spectre damsel cried, And call'd her dogs, and wheel'd her courser round, And with the javelin smote his quivering side; When, swifter than the rocket's fiery bound, Aloft they sprang, huntress, and horse, and hound, And, dimly mixing with the horizon grey, Fled like a winged dream, yet traces found Of gore and talons told their recent way; And still before the queen that wounded quarry lay. LI How fares the knightly court of Carduel? How fare the wedding guests and warrior throng, Where all conspired the nuptial mirth to swell, The dance, the feast, the laugh, the wine, the song? Oh they are silent all! the nimble tongue Of him, whose craft, by motley kirtle known, Had graver wits with seeming folly stung; The vaunting soldier and the simpering crone, And breath'd in beauty's ear the sighs of softest tone. LII As one who, stretch'd upon a battle-field, Looks to the foeman's hand who laid him low, And, with faint effort, rears his broken shield, And dreads, where needeth none, a second blow.— Or, likest him who, where the surges' flow Bares the bleak surface of some wave-beat steep, A shipwreck'd man, expects in breathless woe, Till the returning wave, with giant sweep, Unlock his desperate hold, and whelm him in the deep. LIII So blended fears, the future and the past, The past yet seen by terror's glazed eye, That, tearless still and wild, those phantoms traced, Peopling the twilight's dismal vacancy With fancied shapes, and shades of fiendish dye; The future wildest, darkest, unexprest, Danger untry'd, unfancy'd agony, In the mute language of dismay confest, Thrill'd in the bristling hair, throbb'din th'expanded breast. LIV Sternly the monarch rose, and o'er his brow A horrent pang of dark anxiety Shot like the stormy shadow, scudding low Along the surface of the purple sea. A smile succeeded. Not to mine, or me, Be that portentous smile of hate and scorn, Which each strong furrow, stronger made to be, By toil, and care, and ruthless passion worn, And recollected guilt of youth's tempestuous morn! LV “Sister!” he spake, (half-utter'd, half-represt, From his shut teeth the sullen accents stole;) “And deem'st thou, sister, that thine arts unblest Can tame the settled bent of Arthur's soul? No; let the stars their fiery circles roll; Let dreams of woe disturb the prophet's breast: Can these, or those, the warrior's will controul? 'Tis chance, 'tis errour all!—Oh, trusted best! Be thou mine omen, sword! I reck not of the rest!” LVI The wedded pair are to their chamber gone, While minstrel sounds of breath, and beat, and string Pour on the dewy breeze their blended tone; And wreathed maidens, link'd in jocund ring, “Hymen” around them, “Io Hymen” sing. So, trampling roses in their path, they sped, The veiled bride and the triumphant king, A festal glare while hundred torches shed, Tinging the cheek of night with all unwonted red. CANTO II. I Blest is the midnight of the cradl'd boy, Along whose dimply cheek in slumbers mild The warm smile basks of visionary joy! And blest is she, who by her sleeping child Has the long hours in watchful love beguil'd; And blest the weary man whose wistful eyes From his tall frigate scan the ocean wild, When the fair beacon paints the ruddy skies, And on his tearful heart the thoughts of home arise. II And dear to faithful love that lovely hour, And dear to him beyond the beam of day, Who tracks the footsteps of eternal power, Where the broad Heavens their starry map display. Guilt, only guilt detests the silent ray Of that soul-searching moon, whose lustre sad Restores neglected conscience to her sway, And bitter memory of all things bad, In crowds forgotten erst, or drown'd in revel mad. III The harp was silent, and the tapers' light Had faded from the walls of Carduel, Which late, through many a window's latticed height, On the dark wave in fitful lustre fell; And far and faintly peal'd the drowsy bell That wakes the convent to unwilling prayer; When she, that seeming hind of snowy fell, Erect upstarted from her secret lair, Erect, in awful grace, a woman goodly fair. IV Dark o'er her neck the glossy curls descending Half hid and half reveal'd her ivory breast; And dark those eyes, where pride with sorrow blending Of hate and ruth a mingled tale confest. Her wreath was nightshade, and her sable vest All spangled o'er with magic imagery, In tighter fold her stately form exprest, As when the empress of the silent sky Explores her sleeping love on Latmos' summit high. V Or likest her whose melancholy feet In Stygian valleys wander lonelily, Singing sad airs, and culling flowers sweet, (Yet sweeter flowers in Enna wont to be) Daughter of Ceres, sad Persephone! Oh, not of hell the adamantine throne Nor golden bough from Acherusian tree, Can for the balmy breeze of Heaven atone, Or match the common light of earth's supernal zone! VI So sad, so beautiful, so sternly bright, Skimming the silent air with magic tread, And fairer seen beneath the fair moonlight, That elfin lady stood by Arthur's bed. A tear, in spite of strong disdain, she shed; One little tear, as o'er the sleeping twain Her dark eye glanc'd; then, with averted head, “Ye whom I serve forgive this transient pain; I little thought,” she sigh'd, “that Morgue would weep again.” VII Again she gazed, again a softer dew Dimm'd of her lucid eye the fiery ray, As sad remembrance waken'd at the view Of those who wrapt in dewy slumber lay. Nor could the Chian's mimic art display A goodlier pair; yet did Ganora's cheek A hectic flush unlike to joy display; And from her half-clos'd lips, in accent weak, Would ever and anon a mournful murmur break. VIII “Oh brother once most dear,” the faery said, “A little while sleep on, a little while On that warm breast pillow thy careless head, And bless thy waking eyes with beauty's smile. But danger hovers near, and thorny guile And jealous love that borders close on hate, And angry doubt in impotent turmoil, Whose murderous purpose not for proof shall wait, With following sorrow join'd and penitence too late! IX “And thou, poor victim of another's crime, Hell knows I hate not thee,—thy simple breast Sought not to so sad eminence to climb! Yet can I bear to see Ganora blest, Who blesses him my foe? Oh dire unrest! Oh Morgue condemn'd with frustrate hope to groan! I sought to lure her from her cottage nest; I sought to plant her on an empire's throne; I sought and I obtain'd; would it were all undone! X “For this, alas, I watch'd those op'ning charms, In the cool covert of her native grove; And with a mother's hope, for Modred's arms Foredoom'd Ganora's crown compelling love! Now shall that spell bound life a bulwark prove To Arthur's reign! Ah me, whose feeble power In fate's perplexing maze with Merlin strove, And with my rival of the watery bower, Of that too potent Mage the elfin paramour! XI “What yet remains?—to blast with mutter'd spell The budding promise of their nuptial bed; Of jealous doubt to wake the inward hell, And evil hopes of wandering fancy bred!” She spake, and from her dewy chaplet shed Pernicious moisture o'er each dewy limb, And such strange words of imprecation said, That Heaven's own everburning lamp grew dim, And shuddering, ceased a while the saints' triumphal hymn. XII But all in vain o'er young Ganora's breast, Guarded by prayer, the demon whisper stole; Sorrow, not sin disturb'd that tranquil rest; Yet 'gan her teeth to grind and eyes to roll, As troublous visions shook her sleeping soul; And scalding drops of agony bedew'd Her feverish brow more hot than burning coal. Whom with malignant smile the faery view'd, And through the unopen'd door her nightly track pursued. XIII Like as that evil dame whose sullen spell, To love dire omen, and to love's delight, (If all be sooth that ancient rabbins tell,) With death and danger haunts the nuptial night, Since Adam first her airy charms could slight; Her Judah's daughters scare with thrilling cry, Lilith! fell Lilith! The Jews have a tradition that, before the creation of Eve, Adam was married to an aërial being named Lilith; to revenge his deserting her for an earthly rival, she is supposed to hover round the habitation of new-married persons, showering down imprecations on their heads. The attendants on the bride spend the night in going round the house and uttering loud screams to frighten her away. from her viewless flight, What time with flowers their jetty locks they tie, And swell the midnight dance with amorous harmony. XIV With slope flight winnowing the winds of Heaven, So sped king Uther's child, till her dark eye Glanc'd on a stately knight, whose steps uneven And folded arms might inward grief imply, Or love's wild sting, or canker'd jealousy. Above whose lucid mail and shoulders strong, The furred mantle flow'd of royalty, And, coil'd around his crest, a dragon long Upwreath'd its golden spires the wavy plumes among. XV Alone he paced, from all the band afar Who kept with equal watch their sovereign's bower. Alone with gloomy mien and visage bare, Courting the cool breeze of that early hour. Of sterner eye than Arthur's, and the flower Of youth as yet on his dark features glow'd; Yet seem'd like Arthur's brows his brows to lower; The same of giant height his stature show'd, His raven locks the same, but not with silver strow'd. XVI “Modred!” in accent low and bending near, “Modred, my son!” the beauteous faery said, “Ah, wherefore, at my voice that glance severe, And that dear cheek suffus'd with angry red? Yes, I deserve thy frown, thy mother's head, Child of my pangs, thy keenest curse shall bear, Who with warm hope thy young ambition fed, And weaved the secret spell with nightly care, Vain hopes, and empty spells to win thy promis'd fair! XVII “And com'st thou yet, mother unfortunate! To mock with dreams of transport and of power My gloomy path, whom, with a common hate, Since first thy shame disgrac'd my natal hour, Of Heaven the curses, and of hell devour! What spell-bound virgin may thy charms pursue? What hovering diadems in golden shower Shall mock mine oft-defeated hopes anew?” He ceas'd, and o'er his eyes his hollow beaver drew. XVIII To whom, deep sighing, Uther's daughter spake, “Ah, never more may mother hope to find, Who weeps and watches for her infant's sake, The boy obedient, or the warrior kind! Our toil, our hope is theirs, our heart, our mind; For them we meditate, for them we pray; The soul for them in sinful chain we bind; And for their weal we cast our own away; Yet when did filial love a parent's grief repay? XIX “O thou, for whom of mortal things alone, Unthankful as thou art, yet ever dear, My soul bends downwards from its cloudy zone, And on mine elfin cheek a mortal tear Warm ling'ring, tells me of the times that were! Accursed for whose sake, my restless wing And more than mother's pangs condemn'd to bear, (Till time and fate mine hour of torment bring,) Circles the arch of Heaven in melancholy ring! XX “My Son! by all I feel, by all I dread, If either parent's fate thy sorrow move, (A father slain, a mother worse than dead,) Grudge not the little payment of thy love! Nor scorn my power! though spell unfaithful prove, Though Merlin's mightier skill my hope have crost, Yet not the fiends below, nor saints above, Nor elfin tribes in airy tempests tost, Can tame my stedfast will. All, Modred, is not lost!” XXI “Then tell me,” cried the youth, “who was my sire, And wherefore thou, estrang'd from mortal clay, Bearest so dark a doom of penal fire, A wretched wanderer on the Heavens' high way, Once Albion's princess, now an elfin grey? Too long thou tir'st with boding saws my breast, Mocking thy son with phantoms of dismay, Whose ardent soul by feverish doubt opprest, Burns o'er the unfinish'd tale, and longs to hear the rest.” XXII The faery grasp'd his mailed hand, and led Where the deep waters rolling silently, Beneath the western gate their mirror spread, And on the giant walls and arches high, A lonely horrour sate continually. No warder there with beacon flaming bright, Needed with weary pace his watch to ply, But cold and calm the sinking stars of night, Play'd on the rippling wave with ineffectual light. XXIII There, where adown the solitary steep, With foxglove twin'd, and mosses silver grey, A trickling runnel seem'd the fate to weep Of one whose rustic tomb beside it lay, That lovely sorceress bent her mournful way; And gathering strength—“Behold the honours here Bestow'd by Arthur on thy parent's clay! Behold! forgive, my boy, this coward tear; Blood, blood alone should soothe the ghost who wanders near! XXIV “He, when of downy youth the vernal light Play'd on thy mother's cheek now wan with care, And many a peer of fame, and many a knight, To Britain's princess pour'd the tender prayer, He, only he, the valiant and the fair, To this weak heart an easy entrance found; An humble squire; but not an empire's heir Could vie with Paladore on listed ground; With every manly grace, and every virtue crown'd. XXV “Oh days of bliss, oh hope chastis'd by fear, When on my lap reclin'd the careless boy, Chid my faint sighs, and kiss'd my falling tear! He knew not, he, what bitter doubts annoy Of unpermitted love the trembling joy; He knew not till my brother's thirsty blade Flash'd o'er his head, impetuous to destroy. I clasp'd the tyrant's knees, I wept, I pray'd; Oh God, on Arthur's soul be all my griefs repay'd! XXVI “When from a trance of senseless agony I woke to keener pangs, by frenzy stung, Reckless of Arthur's late repentant cry, Fire in my brain and curses on my tongue, From yonder cliff my wretched frame I flung; Alas, th' enchanted wind my weight upbore, While in mine ears an elvish chorus rung, —‘Come, kindred spirit, to our cloudy shore! With fays, thyself a fay, come wander evermore!’ XXVII “Since, on the rolling clouds or ocean blue, Or 'mid the secrets of our nether sphere, The goblin leader of a goblin crew, I wander wide; but ill may mortal ear Of faery land the mystic revels hear! Short be my tale! one earthly thing alone, One helpless infant to my heart was dear, Bright in whose eyes his either parent shone, Rear'd by their pitying foe, my son, my blessed son!” XXVIII She ceas'd, and round his linked hauberk threw Her mother arms, and on his iron breast (The rough mail moistening with tender dew) A kiss, the seal of bitter love, imprest. He, stern and dark, no kindly glow confest, With face averted and with frozen eye, Where softer passion never dared to rest, But cunning seem'd with sullen pride to vie, Calm, calculating hate, and damned cruelty. XXIX “How I have train'd thee, with what potent charms My magic care thy tender frame imbu'd, How nurs'd thy youth for empire and for arms, And how in Derwent's mountain solitude I rear'd thy destin'd bride,” the fay pursu'd, “And what strange chance o'erthrew mine airy skill, Alas, thou know'st it all! yet to delude The force we cannot stem is triumph still, And from reluctant fate t' extort our good or ill. XXX “Oh earth! how many wonders wonderful, In thy large lap and parent bosom lie, Which whoso knows (few know them all) to cull, May drag the struggling planets from on high, And turn the land to sea, the sea to dry; Yea, not man's will, by God created free, Can match their strange mysterious potency, Nor love nor hate so firmly fixed be, But love must yield and hate to magic's dark decree. XXXI “A ring there is of perfect diamond stone, Such as no mining slave is train'd to seek, Nor Soldan numbers on his orient throne, Nor diving Ethiop from his sultry creek Has borne so rich a prize; for who shall speak What unseen virtue in its orbit dwell? Press it, the fiends attend in homage meek; Turn it, the bearer walks invisible; Ah who the hidden force of smallest things may tell? XXXII “That same to one of regal race I lent, Who now perforce must render back the prize, For of his stars the danger imminent, And guiltless blood loud crying to the skies Alarm all hell; do thou as I desire; This self-same morn depart for Scottish land, There Urgan seek, king Pellea's uncle wise, And bid him yield to thy deputed hand Thatring of diamond stone, for such is Morgue's command. XXXIII “Have we not heard how shepherd Gyges bare, By like deceit from old Candaule's bed, It is related of Gyges that he descended into the earth, where he discovered a large horse made of brass; and within it the body of a man of gigantic stature, on whose finger was a brass ring. This ring possessed the power of making its wearer invisible, and with its assistance he gained access into the palace, murdered the king, whose throne he afterwards usurped, and married the queen. In naked beauty seen, the Lydian fair, And kingly circle from his dotard head, Thenceforth himself a king?”—“No more!” he said— “Mother, no more! or ere the sun's bright round Have tinged yon eastern cloud with lively red, My fiery steed shall paw the spangled ground, And on the Cattraeth's side my clashing arms resound.” XXXIV Like as the hawk from hidden durance free Springs from the falc'ner's wrist, the eager knight, His dark cheek warm with savage ecstacy, Burst from his parent's hold. She with delight His warrior mien beheld and giant height, Awhile beheld, then, rapt in mist away, Back to the bridal turret bent her flight, There closely couch'd amid the rushes grey, O power of wicked spells!—a seeming hind she lay. XXXV By this the fiery wheeled charioteer Had raised above the fringed hills his head, And o'er the skies in molten amber clear A flood of life and liquid beauty shed, When sun-like, rising from his fragrant bed, All glorious in his bliss, the bridegroom king Pass'd to the common hall, and with him led, Blushing and beauteous as that morn of spring, The fair foredoomed cause of Albion's sorrowing. XXXVI The mass was ended, and the silver tone Of shawm and trumpet bade the courtier crew In martial pastime round their monarch's throne, That livelong day their mimic strife pursue, As each the thirst of various pleasure drew; Some launch'd the glossy bowl in alleys green, Some the stiff bar with sturdy sinews threw, Some in bright arms and wavy plumage seen, Wielded the quivering lance the guarded lists between. XXXVII So was there mirth in stately Carduel; Till in the midst a stranger dame was seen, Whose snowy veil in graceful wimple fell Above the sable garb of velvet sheen; Als in her hand, of metal deadly keen, A sheathed sword and studded belt she bare. Golden the hilt, the sheath of silver clean, Whose polish'd mirror back reflected fair Her cheeks of vermeil tinge, her auburn length of hair. XXXVIII Stately she rode along, and keen her eye That scann'd with eager glance that warrior crew; Yet was her blush so meek and maidenly, That never village lass in apron blue With purer roses caught the passing view. Stately she rode along, and in her train, With floating locks and beards of silver hue, Two goodly squires array'd in mourning grain, On either side controul'd her palfrey's silken rein. XXXIX Like as that lovely month to lovers dear, Unlocks the green bud on the scented spray, And laps in freshest flowers the tender year, And tunes the songs of nature,—blessed May; Such was the joy this damsel to survey. But that deceitful hind who by the bride, Licking her hand, in treacherous fondness lay, Arose, and skulking to the farther side In guilty darkness sought her harmful head to hide. XL Alighting from her steed, some little space Propt on that antique sword the maiden leant; While silence gave her blushing cheek more grace, And her warm tears touchingly eloquent, Through warrior hearts a pleasing anguish sent. Then, with collected voice she told her grief, Of bitter wrong, and treason imminent Done to her kindred by a Scottish chief, 'Gainst whom at Arthur's court she, suppliant, sought relief. XLI Her lands he wasted, and with tortuous wrong Herself had banish'd from her native right; A felon warrior, neither bold nor strong, But safe and reckless of all human might By charms impregnable and magic sleight. “For, as some evil thought, he walks unseen Scattering around in murderous despight From viewless bow his arrows deadly keen, That strength and courage fail t' oppose so fatal teen.” XLII “Alas,” said Arthur, “and can mortal wight With trenchant steel a viewless life invade, Or probe with dagger point his pall of night?” “Who,” she replied, “can draw this charmed blade Worn by my sire, on him my doom is laid. But now seven years through many a distant land, Patient of ill, my weary course has stray'd, Nor knight is found so brave whose stainless hand Can from its burnish'd sheath unlock my fatal brand.” XLIII She ceas'd, and through the crowded fort there spread A deep hoarse murmur, as th' autumnal sound In hazel bower, when Sherwood's rustling head Shakes in the blast, and o'er the dusty ground, And in mid sky the falling leaves abound. Beneath her bramble screen the crouching hare Erects her ears, and quaking as astound, Shrinks from the breath of that inclement air, And the fast driving sleet that strips the branches bare. XLIV Then sudden from a hundred tongues arose Harsh words and high, and hand to hilt was laid, And taunt and threat portended deadly blows, Each claiming for himself that charmed blade, And envied guidance of the noble maid. But Arthur, rising from his gilded throne, “Back, on your lives, presumptuous subjects!” said, “For this adventure I resign to none, Not Lancelot himself of knights the paragon!” XLV Awed, yet reluctant, back the crowd withdrew While Arthur from the maid her sword required, And poising in his hands with curious view, Its antique frame and massy weight admired. Then, bending low, with gripple might, desired Forth from its silver sheath the blade to strain, Which, following for a space, again retired, Mocking with magic sleight his fruitless pain; Seven times the king essay'd, seven times essay'd in vain. XLVI As some stout churl by sinewy toil embrown'd, Foil'd by a stranger in the wrestler's play Arises, mourning, from the plashy ground, His batter'd limbs and face deform'd with clay, And cursing oft that luckless holiday; So Arthur back the charmed steel restor'd, And turn'd with sullen scowl his eyes away, As many a knight of fame, and warlike lord In long succession strove to drag that fatal sword. XLVII But not Sir Carados thine iron arm, Nor Kay's stout heart and vaunted pedigree, Nor Gahriet's youthful grace could break the charm, Nor Gawain's force and faith and courage free; Though when he strove, the knight of courtesy, The conscious sword awhile his hand obey'd, That men a span's length of its edge might see, As sunbeam radiant and with gold inlaid; Yet would not all suffice to bear that stubborn blade. XLVIII Whereat the damsel made exceeding moan, Shedding salt tears; nor did her sorrow spare Her breast more lovely white than marble stone, Nor the long radiance of her sunny hair; That not the rudest groom such sight could bear: But a sudden murmur through the palace spread “Alas the while that Lancelot were there! Then had not Arthur's court been shamed”—they said, “Nor those love-darting eyes so bitter fountains shed.” XLIX A knight there was, whose erring hardihood And fiery soul, that insult ill could bear, Had bath'd his falchion in Cucullin's blood, Who yearly made to Britain's court repair; (Haughty Cucullin, Erin's haughty heir,) Condemn'd for this (such vengeance Arthur vow'd) To the chill dungeon's damp and stony lair; Through the close-grated loop he call'd aloud, And what that tumult meant, besought the passing crowd. L Which, when he heard, so strangely confident, With such warm hope he crav'd his chance to try, That through the court a louder murmur went, As pity kindled into mutiny; And Arthur, yielding to his people's cry, “Let him come forth!—his doom in sooth was hard; A soldier's fault!” he mutter'd carelessly; “And knight so long in listless prison barr'd, Has well such fault aton'd—Go bring him hitherward!” LI So was Sir Balin brought before the throne, A gaunt and meagre man, of hue forlorn; For forty months of lingering care were gone, Since on his flinty couch the smile of morn Had rested, or, on dewy pinions borne, The fragrant summer blest his solitude. His limbs were with the linked iron worn, And his long raven hair in tresses rude Hung o'er his hollow cheeks with prison damps embued. LII Around him wildly gazing, (for his sight Shrank from th' unwonted beam of perfect day, And those embattled guards whose armour bright Flash'd in the sunshine like the torch's ray,) He to the stranger damsel bent his way. And, “Lady, scorn me not! the time has been Or ere this bondage,” he began to say, “That gayer robes, and knights of statelier mien, Have felt mine arm as strong, my lance as deadly keen.” LIII “I pray thee give the sword!”—the sword she gave; “Long, very long it seems,” the captive cried, “Since these poor hands have felt a battle glaive!” Yet as the pommel's wieldy grasp he tried, Dawn'd on his hollow cheek a martial pride, And the dark smile of warrior ecstacy Across his care-worn visage seem'd to glide; And, flashing like a meteor to the sky, Forth sprang the charmed blade, the blade of victory! LIV Say, have ye mark'd what winged moments fall Between the distant cannon's flash and roar? Such was the pause ensued, and such the swell Of following rapture shook the ocean shore. Rung every vaulted gate and turret hoar; Rung the far abbey spires, and cloister'd bound; While, as they sail'd the moss-grown rampart o'er, The sea-bird reel'd on giddy pinions round, And the wood-fringed rocks return'd a hollow sound. LV When all was hush'd, the not unmindful king From Balin bade the guard unloose his chain, While robes of knightly blue the pages bring, And furred mantle of majestic train. He, with a settl'd smile of calm disdain, Receiv'd the gifts; but when his well-known mail, And shield, and rusted helm were brought again, Quak'd his dark lip, and voice began to fail, And the fast-falling tear bedew'd his features pale. LVI So when the feast was ended in the hall, Nor longer wonld remain th' impatient maid, Though Arthur much, and much his nobles all, But most her presence young Ganora pray'd; To each with courtly smile her thanks she paid, And graceful on that docile palfrey sprung; While close beside, in wonted steel array'd, Victorious Balin's clashing armour rung, Whom many a knight beheld, with serpent envy stung. LVII But while o'er many a wood-fringed hill And heath of purple tint their journey lay, That seeming hind, fair architect of ill, In Arthur's palace sojourn'd many a day, Expert in fraud, and watchful to betray. Expert with pliant limb, and bounding high Before the queen, her gambols to display; Or fond and flattering at her feet to lie, And mirror every thought in her large lucid eye. LVIII So past the day; but when the seven-fold team, That fear to tinge their feet in ocean deep, Shot from the topmost north their twinkling beam, And over mortal lids the dews of sleep (To weary man blest visitation) creep, Forth in the silence of the world she sped, A nymph of air her unblest watch to keep; Or, wrapt in mist, beside the bridal bed Of poor Ganora's heart the wandering wishes read. LIX The early trace of youthful love was there, And airy hope that flatter'd to betray; But disappointment, with salt smarting tear, Had blotted half the simple lines away; The other half too deeply graven lay, And, though contending with that earthly flame, Celestial ardours sent their purer ray, Though late—Ah, female heart, of feeble frame, Of pomp, and rank, and power, the novel rapture came. LX Yet in the midst, and sov'reign o'er her breast, Cadwal, young Cadwal, held his fatal throne, And, e'en to wakeful conscience unconfest, Her fear, her grief, her joy were his alone: Yes, every sigh that heav'd her silken zone, From hapless love a dearer sorrow drew, And, to Ganora's secret self unknown, Arose before the faery's eager view; Ah me! what airy spies our silent thoughts pursue! LXI And think'st thou, man, thy secret wish to shroud In the close bosom's sealed sepulchre? Or, wrapt in saintly mantle from the crowd, To hug thy darling sin that none may see? A thousand, thousand eyes are bent on thee; And where thy bolts the babbling world exclude, And in the darkness where thou lov'st to be, A thousand, thousand busy sprites intrude; Earth, air, and heaven are full, there is no solitude. CANTO III. I When I rehearse each gorgeous festival, And knightly pomp of Arthur's elder day, And muse upon these Celtic glories all, Which, save some remnant of the minstrel's lay, Are melted in oblivious stream away, (So deadly bit the Saxon blade and sore) Perforce I rue such perilous decay, And, reckless of my race, almost deplore That ever northern keel deflower'd the Logrian shore. II Oh thou the ancient genius of the land, Who wont on old Belusium's sunny steep, And nigh the holy mount, with armed hand, In vision dimly seen, thy watch to keep, Our angel guard, whose eagle pinions sweep In circling flight around his rock-built nest, Now soaring high, now dark'ning half the deep, The broad wave bursting with his shadowy breast, Oh did not his lament foreshow the nearer pest? III Say, did not he when Hengist plough'd the main, With gathering mist the conqueror's track dismay, And smite his radiant brows in parent pain And sadly rend his samphire wreath away? No, brighter beam'd his prescient eye that day, And as the proud bark swept the waters free, He bade the rustling waves around it play. While softly stole across the sunny sea, From many a twisted shell the mermaid's harmony. IV Now forty times the golden-haired dawn Had sprung from old Tithonus' dewy bed, And forty times across the fading lawn, Had summer eve her filmy mantle spread, Since young Ganore to Mary's aisle was led A pensive bride; and yet, I wot not why, But those who best could read her blushes said, Not now so much she droop'd the timid eye, Nor paid her Arthur's warmth with so cold courtesy. V She was his wife! for this she strove to bear Of that portentous eye the tawny glow; And those deep indents of ambitious care That mapp'd his dark and melancholy brow; She was belov'd; for well the fair might know How that stern heart was fix'd on her alone, When, melted all in love's delirious flow, The vanquish'd victor at her feet was thrown; And she was inly vain to feel such power her own. VI So was she pleas'd herself who sought to please; Till on a day when all the court would ride To drink in Cattraeth's woods the cooler breeze, And rouse the dun deer from Terwathlin's side, It chanced the queen within her bower to bide, As one in boisterous pastime rarely seen; Who little loved the hunter's cruel pride, Or maddening shout that rends the forest green, Or their poor quarry's groan the bugle notes between. VII Loth was her lord to miss that livelong day, Her soft sweet glances and her converse sweet; Yet cared he not to cross her purposed stay; And forth he fared, but still with ling'ring feet And backward look, and “Oh when lovers meet How blest,” he thought “the evening's tranquil hour, From care and cumbrous pomp a glad retreat.” Not since his youth first quaff'd the cup of power, Had Arthur praised before the calm sequester'd bower. VIII And forth he fared; while from her turret high That smiling form beheld his hunter crew; Pleased she beheld, whose unacquainted eye Found in each varying scene a pleasure new. Nor yet had pomp fatigued her sated view, Nor custom pall'd the gloss of royalty. Like some gay child a simple bliss she drew From every gaud of feudal pageantry, And every broider'd garb that swept in order by. IX And, sooth, it was a brave and antic sight, Where plume, and crest, and tassel wildly blending, And bended bow, and javelin flashing bright, Mark'd the gay squadron through the copse descending; The greyhound, with his silken leash contending, Wreath'd the lithe neck; and, on the falconer's hand With restless perch and pinions broad depending, Each hooded goshawk kept her eager stand, And to the courser's tramp loud rang the hollow land. X And over all, in accents sadly sweet, The mellow bugle pour'd its plaintive tone, That echo joy'd such numbers to repeat, Who, from dark glade or rock of pumice-stone, Sent to the woodland nymphs a softer moan; While listening far from forth some fallow brown, The swinked ploughman left his work undone; And the glad schoolboy from the neighbouring town, Sprang o'er each prisoning rail, nor reck'd his master's frown. XI Her warm cheek pillow'd on her ivory hand, Her long hair waving o'er the battlement, In silent thought Ganora kept her stand, Though feebly now the distant bugle sent Its fading sound; and, on the brown hill's bent, Nor horse, nor hound, nor hunter's pomp was seen. Yet still she gaz'd on empty space intent, As one, who spell-bound on some haunted green Beholds a faery show, the twilight elms between. XII That plaintive bugle's well remember'd tone Could search her inmost heart with magic sway; To her it spoke of pleasures past and gone, And village hopes, and friends far, far away, While busy memory's scintillating play Mock'd her weak heart with visions sadly dear, The shining lakelet, and the mountain grey, And who is he, the youth of merriest cheer, Who waves his eagle plume and grasps his hunting spear? XIII As from a feverish dream of pleasant sin, She, starting, trembled, and her mantle blue, With golden border bright, and silver pin, Round her wet cheek and heaving bosom drew; Yet still with heavy cheer and downcast view, From room to room she wander'd to and fro, Till chance or choice her careless glances threw Upon an iron door, whose archway low, And valves half open flung, a gorgeous sight might show. XIV It was a hall of costliest garniture, With arras hung in many a purple fold; Whose glistening roof was part of silver pure, And silken part, and part of twisted gold, With arms embroider'd and achievements old; Where that rich metal caught reflected day, As in the hours of harvest men behold Amid their sheaves a lurking adder play, Whose burnish'd back peeps forth amid the stubble grey. XV And, in the midst, an altar richly dight With ever-burning lamps of silver pale, And silver cross, and chalice heavenly bright, Before whose beam a sinful heart might quail, And sinful eye to bear its beauty fail. It was, to ween, that gracious implement Of heavenly love, the three-times hallow'd Grayle The Grayle or Sancgreal, according to the original romance, was a vessel of gold, said to contain some of the blood of our Saviour, carried about by a fair maiden; besides its healing virtues, it possessed the property, into whatever castle it was brought, of “fulfilling the hall with great odours, and every knight had such meat and drink as he best loved in the world.” It was invisible, as well as the damsel who bore it, to all but the “perfect man.” The Knights of the Round Table made a quest to find it out; but Sir Galabad, son of Sir Lancelot, was the only one of sufficient purity of life to be allowed to see it; after which “he kneeled down and made his prayers, and then suddenly his soul departed unto Jesus Christ, and a great multitude of angels bare his soul up to heaven, that his two fellows might behold it; also his two fellows saw come down from heaven a hand, but they saw not the body, and then it came right to the vessel and took it, and so bare it up to heaven. Sithence was there never no man so hardy for to say that he had seen the Sancgreal.” Hist. of Prince Arthur, Part II. c. 103. To Britain's realm awhile in mercy lent, Till sin defil'd the land, and lust incontinent. XVI Strange things of that time-honour'd urn were told, For youth it wont in aged limbs renew, And kindle life in corpses deadly cold; Yea palsy warmth, and fever coolness drew, While faith knelt gazing on its heavenly hue. For not with day's reflected beam it shone, Nor fiery radiance of the taper's blue; But from its hollow rim around was thrown A soft and sunny light, eternal and its own. XVII And many a riven helm around was hung, And many a shield revers'd, and shivered spear, And armour to the passing footsteps rung, And crowns that paynim kings were wont to wear; Rich crowns, strange arms, but shatter'd all and sere; Lo! this the chapel of that table round, And shrine of Arthur and his warriors dear; Where vent'rous knights by secret oaths were bound, And blest by potent prayers their foemen to confound. XVIII Nor less the scene such solemn use became, Whose every wall in freshest colours dight, Display'd in form, in feature, and in name, The lively deeds of many a faithful knight; And told of many a hardly foughten fight Against the heathen host in gory field; Of those who reap renown with falchion bright, Or list in war the ponderous axe to wield, Or press the courser's flank with spear and shield. XIX The stripling conqueror of a giant foe, Belov'd of Heaven, was David there to see, And wallowing wide the headless bulk below; And there the self-devoted Maccabee, Content in death to leave his Israel free, Sustain'd unmov'd the towered elephant, With javelin planted firm, and bended knee; And grimly smiling on the monster's vaunt, Slaying, was nobly slain, a martyr militant. XX There too, she mark'd, in blood-red colours writ, The Christian conqueror of British line, Who seem'd aloft in golden car to sit, Rais'd on the ruins of an idol shrine, Lord of the earth, resistless Constantine! And, blazing high above his chosen head, The meteor cross shed forth its light divine; That that great dragon shook with guilty dread, And all his countless host from forth the heaven fled. XXI Nor less her own paternal Carmelide, With arms begirt, and warrior faces round; Nor less the queen with greedy wonder eyed The giant form, whose uncouth mantle, bound With beards of captive monarchs, swept the ground. Vain-glorious Ryence! Ryence was sovereign of North Wales; he overcame eleven valiant kings in battle, and caused their beards to be sewn on the edges of his mantle, in token of their doing him homage; he then sent a messenger for king Arthur's beard. “For king Ryance had perfected a mantle with the kings' beards, and there lacked for one place of the mantle, wherefore he sent for his beard, or else he would enter into his lands, and burn and slay, and never leave till he have thy head and beard.” But Arthur was little accustomed to be taken by the beard, and returned an angry answer; on which Ryence prepared to enter Britain with a large army, when he was himself defeated by the brothers Balin and Balan. Hist. of Prince Arthur.—Ed. him the Christian host With plunging spears in Mersey's current drown'd; Who, wading through the river depths, almost Had stemm'd th' indignant wave, and reach'd the farther coast. XXII But oh, what rage of war! what ghastly blows! Where silver Avon ran with sanguine hue; And fierce in fight the youth of Denmark rose, And Arthur's strength his deadly falchion drew. Her own brave lord Ganora there might view, As 'mid the meaner trees a kingly oak; How fast the fire-sparks from his armour flew; How from his courser's panting side the smoke; How high he bare his targe, how rose at every stroke! XXIII Around the king, behind him and before, Red ran the tide of death, and dark the throng; And Merlin there his dragon standard bore, Scattering dismay the mailed rands among; A living standard, whose biforked tongue Hiss'd with strange magic, and its brazen eye Darted pernicious rays of poison strong; Als were its threatful spires uplifted high, And wings of molten brass outspread in air to fly. XXIV Strange was it to behold the enchanter's mien, Whose robe of various colours wildly roll'd, And naked limbs in battle seldom seen, And magic girdle all of graven gold, In uncouth wise his prophet frenzy told. Swart with his visage, and his raven hair Hung loose and long in many a tangled fold; And his large eyeballs, with unearthly stare, Flash'd on the withering host a wild portentous glare. XXV Fast by that fiend-born sire was Gawain placed, Gawain the gentlest of the knightly throng, With ladies' love, and minstrel honour graced, The good, the brave, the beautiful, the strong; And, breathing fury, Modred spurr'd along, Sir Modred, sternest of the table round, Injurious chief, who reck'd nor right nor wrong; Yet forward in his suzerain's service found, And next to Arthur's self for princely lineage crown'd. XXVI But who is he? the chief whose single might Girt by the Saxon host in desperate ring, With slender lance redeems the reeling fight, While death and conquest poised on dubious wing Hung o'er the strife his valour witnessing? Cleft is his helmet, and his sanguine cheer And beardless cheeks betoken manhood's spring, Ah well-known glance, ah form to memory dear, It is the nameless youth! it is the forestere! XXVII Was it a dream? her unassured eye Paused on the form awhile—awhile withdrew; She chafes her lids their perfect sense to try; It was no dream! alas, too well she knew The locks of auburn and the eyes of blue, And, her own work, the scarf and broider'd vest! And her ears tingled, and a death-like dew Through her cold marrow thrill'd and quivering breast, And suffocating sobs the abortive shriek supprest. XXVIII When overpast was that strong agony, And doubt and fear resumed their blended reign, She on that arras bent her frenzied eye, And line retraced, and well known line again. “His locks were auburn, these a darker grain, Fair is yon knight, yet sure than him less fair, Yon shield, yon crownet mark a princely strain, And sterner seems that brow.” Ah fruitless care! That lip! those eyes! that scarf! his pictur'd self is there! XXIX “And art thou he?” for o'er his conquering head In Gothic letters all of silver bright, That chieftain's woven name Ganora read, “And art thou he, thy sovereign's darling knight, The wise in court, the matchless in the fight, Strength of our Logrian land in danger's hour! Oh Lancelot! (if thus I read aright Thy lordly style,) 'mid pomp, and wealth, and power Full soon hast thou forgot thy humble village flower!” XXX “Yet Arthur cull'd that flower!” (a female ire Flush'd in her cheek, and sparkled in her eye) “Yet Albion's lord could this poor form desire; And thou shalt view thy rustic Emily In pomp of queenly state enthroned high! Then, Cadwal, shall thy soul new pangs endure, And in each slighted charm new grace descry, And, scorn'd in turn—Ah passion hard to cure! Break, break my tempted heart while yet my will is pure.” XXXI Thus raved she long, till from her throbbing breast Exhausted passion loos'd his iron sway; And holier thoughts her struggling soul possest, And that pure chalice with its saintly ray, And that still chapel turned her heart to pray. So prostrate at the marble altar's base, With floating locks and folded hands she lay; And moistening with her tears the sacred place, Clung to the silver cross with Magdalen embrace. XXXII So by that heavenly toil re-comforted, She, slowly rising from the sacred ground, Dried her moist eye, with streaming anguish red, And those loose locks in decent fillet bound, And cast, in matron guise, her mantle round, And forth she went; yet ere the morrow's light, She of her maidens fit occasion found To ask the lineage of “that absent knight, Who now in Albion's war fought for his suzerain's right. XXXIII “He of the Lake, whose empty seat was placed And in the hall his banner waving wide, A golden hound with chequer'd collar graced, And the broad field with seeming verdure dyed?” To whom the young Ygwerna swift replied With arched brows and finger pointing sly, “Oh who shall dare to praise that chief of pride, Who, when the jealous Gwendolen is nigh, Whose proffer'd love he meets with so cold courtesy?” XXXIV “Peevish Ygwerna!” Gwendolen rejoin'd, “By forged tales to shroud thy secret care! Who more than thou the myrtle branch has twined, And ring'd with flowery wreath his auburn hair? Ah wooing vainly spent! some absent fair Has o'er the warrior hung her silken chain; Witness the purple scarf he loves to wear, Witness his wanderings o'er the nightly plain, Witness Ygwerna's love and Lancelot's disdain!” XXXV Ganora sigh'd; but all unmark'd the sigh As Gwendolen pursued her eager word! “Oh lady mine, long were the history To reckon up the praise of that young lord, In Logris and in distant Gaul ador'd, And sprung from elder kings of Brutus' race; But changeful fate, and war with ruthless sword Could ancient Tribles' goodly towers deface, And poppies wave the head in the tall banner's place. XXXVI “When bloody Claudas sack'd the Armoric shore, The sire of Launcelot its sceptre held, For wealth renown'd, for virtuous wisdom more, And the fair peace of honourable eld. But the base rabble from his rule repell'd, And ancient Ban, no longer prompt to bear (As when at Carohaise, the foe he quell'd) The conquering falchion and the pennon'd spear, Fled from his dangerous throne to wood and desart drear. XXXVII “There, wretched sire, by daily wrath pursued, Himself, his infant heir, and beauteous dame, A shelter seeking in the solitude, To a wild cave with painful travel came, Where toil and grief opprest his hoary frame: A little space with arms to Heaven spread, A little space, on cities wrapt in flame; And ravaged fields, he gazed, but nothing said, Then in his Helen's arms sank down his dying head. XXXVIII “She, chafing his cold brows, and with her tears Moistening in vain the breast was ever true, Nor space, nor leisure found for other fears; But when her much-loved lord deceased she knew, All wildly frantic thro' the desart flew, Reckless of him who, 'mid the bushes laid, Her sleeping babe, a faery's pity drew; Who haply wandering through the twilight glade. Stoop'd from her phantom steed, and home the prize convey'd. XXXIX “Beneath the hollow waters is her home, Upbuilt with arched waves of crystal cold, Where never wight of mortal seed should come. Yet did she there the beauteous infant hold, And train'd in knightly lore and pastimes bold; But luckless Helen, dame disconsolate, When late her loss returning reason told, Sought the sad shelter of a convent grate, And wept with live-long grief her boy's untimely fate.” XL “Him, when his vigorous youth was ripe for war, And downy cheek was cloth'd in darker shade, On airy wheels and dragon-yoked car, To Arthur's court his elfin nurse convey'd, In polish'd arms of maiden white array'd, And silver shield as princely youth became; Who since untam'd, unrivall'd, undismay'd In tourney strife and war's illustrious game, Has borne from every knight the foremost meed of fame.” XLI “All otherwise I deem,” Ganora cried, “Nor him account the best and bravest knight Who, wrapt in sordid gain or warrior pride, Is dead to ladies' pain and love's delight.” “Ah who,” said Gwendolen, “shall read aright The close-kept secret of a hero's love! Yet some have said, in magic beauty bright, His elfin dame has power his mind to move, And urge his pensive steps along the twilight grove.” XLII A livid blush the queen's pale face o'erspread, “Yet, yet aread, where is that faery's wan?” “Ah who shall tell her haunt,” the maiden said, “Who in the desart water dwells alone, Or under hollow hill or cavern'd stone? Yet beauteous Derwent claims her chiefest grace.” Ganora heard, but answer made she none, And with her kerchief shrouding close her face, Broke from th' unfinish'd tale and sadly left the place.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">FRAGMENTS OF THE MASQUE OF GWENDOLEN. Enter two Goblins bearing a casket. GWENDOLEN. What forms are these? GOBLIN. Spirits of nether earth Are we, and servants to the mighty Merlin, From whom we bear these treasures to his bride. Or ere the raven twice hath flapt her wing He will himself be here. GWENDOLEN. Good angels guard me! Enter two Sylphs and two Sea Nymphs. SONG. Nymphs of air and ancient sea, Bridal gifts we bring to thee! Lo these plumes of rich device, Pluck'd from birds of paradise! Lo these drops of essence rare, Shook from a wand'ring meteor's hair! Nymphs of air and ancient sea, Such the gifts we bring to thee! Take these shells, approach them near, And they shall murmur in thine ear Tunes that lull the slumbering sea More than mermaid's harmony! Take these pearls, no diving-slave Drags their like from ocean cave,— Nymphs of air and ancient sea, Such can only bring to thee. Enter two Genii of Fire, with a case. FIRST GENIUS. Loveliest of mortal mould! distant we kneel, Lest our hot breath should mar thy snowy skin, Or scorch thy raven locks! We are of fire The swarthy ministers, whose active heat Is as the soul of earth and sea and air; Who sow the seeds of gold, who give the diamond Its eye of flame, and wake the carbuncle To rival day. Of such strange alchemy We bring thee tokens; and before thy feet Bow down our crisped heads, and in the dust Abase our terrors! MERLIN. Am I proud, who lay Mine empire at thy feet? All thou hast seen Are but the least of wonders. Toiling fiends Shall sweat to work thy bidding, and their claws Rend from the greedy earth its buried treasure, And drag the deep for thee. The sylphs of air Shall fan thy slumber, and their viewless harps Pour on thy waking ear strange melody. The elfin nations, with fresh herbs and flowers, Shall in thy chambers keep perennial spring; And the wild mermaid sleek, with coral comb Thy dark and perfumed tresses. Seek'st thou more? More is in Merlin's power! Be thou my bride, And I will place thee on a regal throne Of solid adamant, hill above hill, Ten furlongs high, to match whose altitude Plinlinmon fails, and Idris' stony chair Sinks like an infant's bauble; there, enshrin'd A queen and goddess, shall the elements Wait on thee, and the countless multitude Of Genii worship thee supreme in hell! I pause for thy reply. GWENDOLEN. This then it is: Thy power I know not, but thine art I know For most unholy, and thy person hateful! I own my folly, with remorse I own it, Which play'd with such a visitor; but mine ears Drank in thy wisdom,—and it soothed my pride To see the powers of magic tax'd for me, And the strong features of a face like thine Relaxing in my presence! This forgive me! My last request! Nay look not thus on me, Nor press my hand! I may not dally longer. MERLIN. Ah, do not raise the fiend within my soul, Nor arm, sweet petulance, against thyself My worser nature! In this rugged breast The heart which throbs is Etna's earthy fire, Which, unprovok'd and slumbering in its strength, Rejoiceth Ceres, and with fresher flowers To Enna's valley lures back Proserpine: But, if it burst its bounds, hath hellish mettle Which is most dangerous! I was not made To soothe a lady's scorn, or woo her lattice, What time the cold moon on her garden bower Flickers in silver whiteness, and the winds Blend with mine amorous harp's sad lullaby. My love or vengeance must be gratified.— Wherefore, proud dame, I say to thee, Be wise! In love unmatch'd, in hate unmatchable, I have done that ere now which mine own eyes Have wept to look upon. My Father's spirit Is blent with mine, and schools me to such horrors! Wherefore, I charge thee as thou lov'st thyself, Be timely wise! One little moment more, I feel the demon rush into my soul, And prayer will then be vain! Be wise! Be wise! GWENDOLEN. Oh horror, horror! Oh for leprosy To scathe this fatal form! oh that the veil Wherewith I shroud me from thy dreaded glance, Were some wild thicket, some brake-tangled wood Where this poor head might shelter,—where no foot Of man approacheth; that myself were made A thing of loathing and of natural horror, Such as is pain to look on!—better so Than thus to tempt thy wooing: take me, throw me To the wild boar, or where the lioness Seeks for her brindled young their human banquet; Yea, rather marry me to death, and make My bridal bed within the sepulchre, Than bid me mount with thee thy guilty throne! MERLIN. Thy wish be on thine head, and thine own curse Feed on thee till it waste thee! Exquisite maid; Ev'n in the bitterness of my revenge I love thy graceful passion! But my sire, Whose flames now burn within me, goads my purpose To wittier malice! Shroud thee in thy veil, Oh my fair enemy;—for that withdrawn Thy face shall never win a suitor more! Hear, spirits, hear!— (Thunder.) I fix on thee Curses, curses, one, two, three! Fouler than a grandame ape, Be thy features and thy shape; Be thy face, so fresh and fair, Worse than those of furies are; Be thy snowy forehead dark, And rougher than the maple bark; In the green wood range alone Thy disastrous lot to moan; Lion wild and bristly boar, Let them fly thy face before; And the wolves that round thee prowl, More from fear than hunger howl; As a thing most scorn'd and hated, And with demons only mated, Every kindly creature shun thee: And this burden be upon thee, Till a youth of form divine, Sprung from Brutus' ancient line, Of beauty careless, and delight, Shall woo thee to the nuptial rite; Shall his arms around thee twine, Shall his warm lips press to thine, And sign thee with the holy sign! (Thunder. Merlin sinks.) (Gwendolen asleep as transformed by Merlin. Three Fairies strewing flowers and leaves over her. SONG. Rest thee on this mossy pillow 'Till the morning light! Softly wave this whispering willow O'er thy bed to night! Every mortal grief forsake thee As our drowsy spells o'ertake thee, Nought from blessed sleep awake thee 'Till the morning light! Enter Titania. TITANIA. Spirits, well done! for not of ruthless mood Are we, the rangers of the nightly wood. Where found ye this sad maid? FIRST FAIRY. Down in yon dell We found her, where the moon-beams brightest fell; For Cynthia mark'd her with benignant eye, And mourn'd, methought, a virgin's misery. We mark'd her too, with what intense despair She scatter'd on the winds her raven hair, Invoking death: then with accurst intent Of wilder madness, to the lake she went; But, bending o'er its mirror, shriek'd to spy In that wild glass her own deformity, And fled apace. Anon, amid the brakes, Like some pursued fawn a lair she makes, And shrouding with her furry gown those eyes Which not the curse of Merlin could disguise, As at herself she trembled, 'till her grief Found in a flood of gracious tears relief. TITANIA. Poor wretch! ye sooth'd her then? FIRST FAIRY. Her tears we dried, And pluck'd the brambles from her bleeding side; O'er her hot brain a grateful vapour threw, And sprinkled every limb with drowsy dew; Then bore her slumb'ring to this green retreat, And with star-jelly cool'd her blister'd feet, And scatter'd every flower of purple dye, And fann'd her rest with owlet's plumery. TITANIA. Well have ye done! Sleep on, poor Gwendolen, The hour of retribution is arrived, And Merlin hath no longer power to harm.— FIRST FAIRY. Is Merlin dead? TITANIA. Ev'n now I heard the yell Of ghastly merriment; in upper air The fiends keep holiday. I knew their song, A song of triumph: “Merlin is no more! Merlin, the mighty one! Haste, haste to meet him Ye rulers of the damn'd, and open wide Your everlasting gates, to entertain The master of the spell! Such charms no more Shall tax our labours till the final doom!” FIRST FAIRY. How died he? Say— TITANIA. By female wiles he fell. She of the Lake, his elfin paramour, Jealous of his late wanderings,—in a tomb, (First having won by sugar'd blandishment From his dark soul the unutterable name Which all things fear in hell, in earth and heaven,) Inclos'd the struggling wizard. Nine long nights Within the rock the fairies heard him moan, The tenth was silence! FIRST FAIRY. May the merciless Such fate meet ever! But, our Gwendolen, Is she now free? TITANIA. The fates their course must have, And Merlin's spells have power beyond the grave. But Heaven, and those bright stars whose golden eyes Behold the link of mortal destinies, An equal lot of weal and woe prepare To Harlech's virgin and to Albion's heir. For this I came, to shed a soft controul Of Heavenly wisdom o'er her sleeping soul; And bring to mind whate'er of secret lore She from her wizard lover learnt before. But soft, she stirs,—our potent pharmacy Has roused her dream, and oped her sealed eye. Vanish kind fays—our forms she must not spy! (Gwendolen awakes.) GWENDOLEN. Oh sacred hour of retribution, Foredoom'd to dry the wretch's tear, And rectify this dark confusion, Of earthly sin and shame and fear; And art thou then a fond delusion Around our slumber hovering near, Of Heavenly bliss a blest infusion Too holy to be tasted here? Oh, in my dreams I feel them, see them! The days of bliss return again, As victor angels tread beneath them, The snare of fiends, the rage of men! And evermore a sweet delusion Above my slumber hovers near; And tells of holy retribution, And chides my doubt and soothes my fear; I wake—and all is dark and drear. The oak wood rustles over head; The aspen sheds its foliage sere Upon my wild and dewy bed; Before the melancholy blast Autumnal clouds are driving fast; For canopy of state I see The white moon glimmering through the tree; I tremble as with woman fear The wolf's approaching howl I hear; In sickening doubt I turn mine eyes From mine own self thus hideous grown; And, ranging, in this goblin guise, The thorny brake, unseen unknown, I curse my sleep, whose magic power Hath mock'd with bliss my hopeless heart, And trebly curse my waking hour, Which bade that fancied bliss depart; And doubt, so quick the changes seem, If this or that were all a dream. Alas! how know we which is true, The night or day, the sun or shade, The forms which glide in long review Before our eyes in slumber laid, Or those our waking scenes renew? Was it a dream that Harlech's hall Receiv'd my wandering steps again, As throbb'd my heart at rapture's call, More rapt'rous from remember'd pain! On my cold cheek in joyful thrill, My brother's tear, I feel it still; And, closer to my heart than he, The youth's warm kiss who set me free! Was this a dream? or, dream I now, Of mourning weeds and desert wild; Of whistling wind in hawthorn bough; Of form by magic curse defil'd? Come pitying death, dissolve the strife, —And wake me from the trance of life! A footstep in the wood! an armed man, And hither bound! Retire thee, Gwendolen. Yet, what hast thou to fear? Thine alter'd form Is safe from the worst danger, and thy life, Not worth the keeping, mocks his cruelty.— Yet must I hide me—lend me your shade kind boughs To shade this hideous face from earth and Heaven! Scene, the Court. Arthur on his throne, Llewellin in chains, Guards, &amp;c. &amp;c. ARTHUR. How wears the time? KAY. The sun hath well nigh scaled The pinnacle of Heaven. ARTHUR. Oh say not so :— Is it indeed so late?—Where art thou Gawain, Too slow to save thy friend? Ah, cursed oath! Which stops the mouth of mercy, and but leaves A barren grief to after penitence— That I might now recall thee! Yet again Be it proclaimed,—if that mortal tongue Can solve our oracle,—and solving save Yon gallant gentleman,—our kingdom's power Is tax'd for their reward. Still, still,—all still! Oh good Llewellin, when the headsman's blow Redeems mine oath, my hoary hairs shall follow (Believe it) to the grave. Oh, that thy wrath Had cool'd betimes, or mine. Pardon, oh pardon! As I forgive thee thine unruly brow Triumphant o'er mine age, thy words of fire And looks of mutiny, such as no king Can brook without resistance,—pardon thou The rashness of mine oath, which sends thy youth Untimely to the tomb. LLEWELLIN. My parting prayer Waits on your silver locks; be brief, good king; Dismiss a soul which on its tiptoe stands Knocking at Heaven's high gates. I have met death In uglier shapes before, nor find I now, Save in this tardiness, his teeth or sting. Have with you, headsman. ARTHUR. Stay I charge ye, stay!— A noise—I hear it well,—a horse's tread As one in speed—and hark that shout, O Heaven! Run some of ye and learn. (Cry without.) Long live Earl Gawain! ARTHUR. Welcome brave nephew, Now more than ever welcome; have ye sped? Is mine oath cancell'd?—is the prisoner free? Hath Merlin told his secret? GAWAIN. He hath borne That secret to the land of secrecy, Nor can Llewellin claim a further sentence Than Heaven hath past on Merlin. O! my liege, Strange things have chanced, which at fitting season I shall unfold. Now to my chiefest care. Unlock these rivets, jailor, for thy charge By Arthur's oath is free;—Arthur hath sought What women mostly crave;—my answer follows. Power is their passion. From the lordly dame To the brown maid that tends the harvest field, They prize it most. Wherefore is pleasure scorn'd But to increase their sway?—why riches lavished, But as an argument of queenly state? Wherefore is virtue scorn'd? why vice thought comely? But for the pride of taming him whose wiles Have ruin'd many,—why is beauty marr'd By ceruse or by corset?—wherefore love Led like a blithe and perfum'd sacrifice To Phœbus' altar, but in hope to reign?— Ye have mine answer.— ARTHUR. Loose Llewellin's chain! Gawain, thou hast thine earldom. Valiant friends, This day be peace to all. Let me embrace you With penitent fondness. Ah! what ghastly spectre Troubles our happiness?—Can this be human! She kneels, she holds a ring— GWENDOLEN. A boon, a boon From Arthur and from Gawain! What I am, What I have done, he knows.—What he hath sworn, This ring be witness. GAWAIN. I acknowledge all, And nobody will repay thee. Come to-morrow,— To-day,—this even,—only scare not now This royal presence. GWENDOLEN. I sav'd thy friend, I brought thine earldom back; my wisdom sounded The craft of Merlin; and the grateful Gawain (For he was grateful then) sware by his sword, This ring his sponsor,—to reward my pains With whatsoe'er I ask'd. I ask it now, Before the king-my hire, my righteous hire, Such as a knight must pay. GAWAIN. Ask and receive! I own my oath,—and though my colder blood Thrills to its fountain at thy gaze, and nature Forebodes of something monstrous in thy soul, Which I may shrink to answer—I have sworn; And bid me tame the brindled pard, or keep Mine unarm'd vigil in a dragon's den,— Be the king witness, and this table round, I will perform thy bidding; speak and obtain. GWENDOLEN. Give me thyself,—be thou mine husband, Gawain! What! scar'd already,—hast thou sworn in vain? Am I so monstrous?—Oh, I feel I am! Yet have I sav'd thy friend. GAWAIN. So we are married. Rule thou in my house, Govern my treasure,—prank thee in my jewels; All, all is thine!—for me, I mount my steed And ramble forth to-night, an errant warrior, To see thy face no more.— GWENDOLEN. Alas for me! Is this a marriage?—thus did Gawain swear, To mock me with himself,—to leave me thus, His lawful partner, to the scoffs of men, And the constructions of a peevish world, Weak and defenceless, childless, husbandless? Oh, my good lord,—shall it be said this face Has robb'd my country of its bravest knight? And shall the Saxon, and the ruthless Dane, Triumphant in your absence, thank the foulness Of Gawain's countess for their victory! Far be such curse from me! If I am loath'd, Beyond endurance loath'd,—command me hence, And I forsake your roof;—I know my duty; And your poor wife, from forth her wilderness, Shall bless and pray for Gawain. GAWAIN. Nay, not so; For I have sworn to shield thee; rest thee here, And ev'n in absence shall mine eye behold Thy comforts and thy safety; weep not, dame, I am thy guardian, and will well discharge A guardian's office. Friendship may be ours, Thy form forbids not that. What—weeping still! I will not leave thee;—with a brother's zeal For thy past service done I will watch over thee. Be of good courage,—come, one kiss of peace To seal our bargain.—Hateful! horrible! And dost thou cling around me, cursed fiend, To drag me to perdition! Out, aroint! For in God's name I charge thee set me free, And by this holy sign! GWENDOLEN. Oh, bless'd be thou!— Turn, Gawain, turn!— (Loud thunder.)</field>
      <field name="fulltext">BLUE-BEARD. A SERIO-COMIC ORIENTAL ROMANCE. Scene I. A Court-yard before Fadlallah's House. FADLALLAH. Good neighbour, be quiet!—my word is a law— I have said that my daughter shall wed the Bashaw! SELIM. But, neighbour, your promise! FADLALLAH. My promise! go to! With him must I break it to keep it with you? SELIM. You promis'd me first! FADLALLAH. But I promis'd him since! And what saith the Koran? “Speak truth to thy prince!” SELIM. You swore by the Prophet! FADLALLAH. I tell thee, forbear! In abundance of words is abundance of care! And again saith the Koran, in Surah the third, “Confine not thy neighbour too close to his word!” SELIM. Would you yield to this monster your Fatima's life? Why, he eats every night for his supper a wife! FADLALLAH. Mere libellous nonsense! I tell thee, Selim, I know nothing less like a monster than him! AYESHAH. Oh, father! but think on his whiskers of blue! FADLALLAH. I tell you, the man is as rich as a Jew! I wish I could find such a husband for you! SELIM. Allow me, at least, to take leave of the maid! FADLALLAH. You may do as you please—I shall not be afraid. No daughter of mine has a spirit so mean, To prefer her kab-kabs to a gilt palankeen; To trudge to the baths with no soul in her train, And wrapp'd in a shawl from the wind and the rain, When she might, if she pleas'd, on an elephant ride, With trumpets before her and troops by her side, And sweep through the streets like a lady of honour, Dwarfs, negroes, and eunuchs attendant upon her. Selim!—I once lov'd you. Be but a good boy, I'll speak to the Bashaw to give you employ. But my daughter's affianc'd! [Exeunt Fadlallah and Ayesha. SELIM. Says Fatima so? FATIMA. I am but the slave of my father, you know. I must do as he wills, or with you, my Selim, A cottage were more than a palace with him! But, alas, 'tis in vain! and, since love is denied, I must fold my pale form in the mantle of pride,— Must loll on my couch with an indolent mien, Of a heart-chilling haram the heart-broken queen, And trifle the time while my tyrant reposes, With diamonds and arrack and attar of roses! SELIM. I cannot endure it! The Bashaw I'll meet, I'll fling myself down in the dust at his feet. I'll tell him our story. FATIMA. His heart is of steel! SELIM. By Allah! my dagger shall force him to feel! I'll drag from his horse the oppressor, and then— FATIMA. A peasant! and fight with a leader of men! You can but fall a victim to numbers, and I!— I never will live to look on, when you die! Farewell!—be resign'd—take this ring for a token; So long as its stone is unblench'd and unbroken, You may know that I live—that I'm well—that I bear In peace and in patience the load of despair.— But if once its smooth surface begins to decay, And the tint of the ruby to vanish away, You may learn that my life is in danger, and—pray! SELIM. Yet, yet there is hope! I have told you before, My mother's an Arab, and born in Mount Hor: Her kindred disown'd her for wedding a clown; But my uncle the Shekh, as he pass'd by our town, Half-famish'd, half-naked, hard press'd by the foe, Was pleas'd for a moment his pride to forego, To be fed, cloth'd, and shelter'd, as best we were able: To be warm'd by our hearth, to be hid in our stable; And to say, on the morrow, as grimly he smil'd; He would “make me a man if I came to the wild!” In less than three days I can reach his retreat; I'll tell him my sorrows, fall down at his feet. He hates Abou Malek! FATIMA. But what can he do, Our tyrant so mighty, his people so few? He may rifle a pilgrim, set fire to a village, Or threaten the monks of Mount Sinai with pillage;— But to cope with a Bashaw! SELIM. No matter, I'll try! [Martial music at a distance. FATIMA. Good Heaven—they are here! if you value me, fly! Enter Fadlallah. FADLALLAH. In, into the house, silly girl!—By my beard, This moment the sound of a trumpet I heard: Would you stand in the court with no veil on your face, When his highness, your husband, rides into the place? In, in—get the clothes on he sent you this morning! And, neighbour, kind neighbour, I give you fair warning, If longer in sight of my door I survey you, I'll speak to my son-in-law's worship to flay you! [Exeunt severally Fatima and Selim. ABOU MALEK (speaking without). Sound, trumpets, a halt! My Albanians may wait, Drawn up in two lines, from the bridge to the gate! Let none dare to enter! (Entering). Well, father-in-law. FADLALLAH. I hope that your highness will pardon the awe— [Hesitating. Unprepar'd as I am, unaccustom'd to view The shadow of one so illustrious as you! Oh, Lud! I'm afraid of those whiskers of blue! [Aside. I could speak very well if I once made a start, But 'tis gone from me clean what I'd gotten by heart. Where was I?—Oh now— (Aloud.) Will your highness be pleas'd— ABOU MALEK. Slave, infidel, hound! am I thus to be teas'd With your bowing and cringing, and kneeling and talking, Detaining me here from night until dawning? Go, call out your daughter—'tis her that I seek,— But you, if I let you, would chatter this week! FADLALLAH (aside). His highness is hasty.—I dare not complain, But 'tis hard that my speech should be studied in vain. ABOU MALEK. What have I forgot?—I return to the gate To give out some orders.—Your daughter may wait. [Exit. FADLALLAH. He's a Bashaw indeed! How I envy his state! How noble his action!—“Your daughter may wait!” Enter Fatima and Ayesha. Come, Fatima, girl, and give thanks on your knee For a husband so kind, condescending, and free! “Good father-in-law,” said his highness to me, “You speak like an angel, good father-in-law;” He's the civilest gentleman ever I saw; And, by the same token, will make me a Cadi, So soon as my daughter comes out as his lady!— What,—weeping, you fool? By the Caaba, I'd tear, If it were not for rumpling that head-dress, your hair! I'd make you come out by the head and the shoulder! You are only too lucky! AYESHA. And that's what I told her! I'm sure she has plenty to make her content. Do look at the things which the Bashaw has sent! Such silks and such kincobs, such collars of pearl! She looks like a Peri far more than a girl. And I, her poor bride-maid, by all am confess'd, As sweetly, though not so expensively dress'd. Come, keep up your spirits! do, Fatima, do! I don't think his whiskers so frightfully blue! Re-enter Abou Malek. All kneel. All hail, Lord of Damascus! ABOU MALEK. Young woman, I come, According to promise, to carry you home. Your sister goes with you. Of course you are ready.— Black eunuchs without! form a guard for your lady!— Come kiss me! I like you! FATIMA. In mercy forbear! Despise me, and fix your affections elsewhere! FADLALLAH. Perhaps, if your highness my girls would compare, This other's as handsome. ABOU MALEK. But less to my taste.— Come Fatima, rise from the ground—I'm in haste! The affairs of the East on my leisure attend.— Fadlallah! farewell! kiss with reverence the end Of this worshipful finger, which, were the whim in it, Might beckon your head from your shoulders this minute. FATIMA. O Bashaw! if pity e'er enter'd your breast! ABOU MALEK. You have reason, I trow, to be sadly distress'd! The spouse of a Bashaw! mere maidenish stuff! I like you—have bought you—will keep you, enough! [Exeunt. Scene II. A large Hall or Staircase with many doors. Music and Dancing heard without. Enter Abou Malek, Fatima, Ayesha. ABOU MALEK. I hate all this nonsense!—these gardens of myrtle, These long wedding suppers, how vastly absurd! These verses comparing my spouse to a turtle! I'm wed to a woman, and not to a bird! I can gaze with delight on her person and graces, And hope that the sequel fresh charms will disclose; But it bores me to hear such bombastical praises,— No nightingale I to be gull'd with a rose! Go—order the minstrels to silence their tabours! Bid the dancing-girls pack up their rags and be gone! AYESHA. Lord sir! you'll offend all your kindred and neighbours; The nach-girls and singers have scarcely begun! I never can find an excuse that is clever— They'll needs see your highness before they retire. ABOU MALEK. Go tell 'em I'm sick—have the plague—have a fever, Say the sherbet is out!—say the Harem's on fire! [Exit Ayesha, lingeringly. I breathe at my ease now Ayesha is gone! O born in a cottage, but fit for a throne! You, perchance, think my mannersare rough and austere? But why do you tremble—my Houri, draw near! I have secrets of moment to pour in your ear! Twelve years have I languish'd a partner to meet, Kind, beautiful, humble, domestic, discreet; Twelve times have I hoped that my labour was sped; Twelve times I have fail'd—for the rest, ask the dead! Twelve damsels in turn—but alas! you have heard The crime which has call'd down this curse on my head! You have heard it? FATIMA. Your Highness I have—but I know That slander still follows the mighty. ABOU MALEK. 'Tis true! Now learn the sad cause!—in my cradle when laid My mother gave alms to a soothsaying maid, A poor crazy wanderer in ruins that slept, And her vigils with Gouls in the monument kept, Till her soul, from the haunts of humanity driven, Grew skill'd in the visions of Hell and of Heaven, And her words of wild raving had power to unfold Whatever the eyes of the Prophet behold:— She stopt at our cottage, sate down by our door (I care not who knows it—my parents were poor, I rose by the sabre's adventurous law, First robber, then rebel, and last a Bashaw); But she, when relieved by our water and bread, Took the babe in her arms, prest her lips to his head, And—You mark me? FATIMA. Intently! ABOU MALEK. She shudder'd and, “thou! Strange matters are written,” she cried, “on thy brow! High valour, high fortune, untimely o'erthrow! Yet, warrior, no bow-string shall bring thee thy doom; No writ of the Sultan conduct to the tomb; Live, live Abou Malek! fear'd, honour'd, carest, Of the chiefs of the Koran the boldest and best; Fear no sabres that glisten, no bullets that fly, Till—a bride's curiosity doom thee to die!” FATIMA. Strange doom! ABOU MALEK. Dost thou wonder that twelve I have tried, Dost thou wonder that they who deceived me have died! Let their fate be thy warning! Last hope of my life, Be firm! and I make thee my queen and my wife! Thou shalt rule o'er our heart, shalt rule o'er Damascus, Whatever thou seek'st, thou hast only to ask us! But first, to thy trial! take charge of my keys, Wherever thou wilt, they admit thee with ease. Range at will through my castle,—its wealth is thine own! But yon south turret chamber must yet be unknown! Do this, and be blest!—for three days we must part: Be firm,—or my dagger must smoke in thy heart! Farewell for three days! FATIMA. Oh, my Lord, I entreat, Show grace to my weakness! I sink at your feet; I will honour you, love you, obey you, adore! All, all but this trial! ABOU MALEK. It must be!—no more! [Exit. Enter Ayesha. Thank Heaven he is off! I have heard your dispute— He a Bashaw, indeed! A fantastic old brute. FATIMA. You heard it? AYESHA. I listen'd, my love, at the door— I never have met such a monster before. Kill a woman for peeping! why here's a to-do! I wonder what's in that same chamber—Don't you? FATIMA. Oh talk not of prying! AYESHA. The Prophet forbid! But—he never could know it, my dear, if we did. And—now that I look, what a beautiful key! Do, Fatima, trust it a moment with me. [Snatching the key. FATIMA. What, what are you doing? [Ayesha tries the key in the lock of the door. AYESHA. I want to be sure If this is the key which belongs to the door— It fits I declare like a finger and glove! FATIMA. In mercy, return it! AYESHA. Return it, my love! I have not yet turn'd it,—nor do I intend. No, child, on my prudence you well may depend! I would not for the world—Oh, my stars! it is done! [The door flies open with a tremendous sound, several Skeletons seen within. The chamber is open, as sure as a gun, And oh! what an object! See, Fatima, see! Oh shut-to the door! turn the key, turn the key! Run! Run for your life—Oh! FATIMA. [Fatima closes the door. Wretched girl! we're undone! The key is all bloody! AYESHA. Run, Fatima, run! [Exeunt. Scene III. A wild rocky Desert, without trees or vegetation. At a small distance a cluster of low black Tents. Enter Selim with a staff, scrip, and bottle for holding water. SELIM. To think that my uncle takes pleasure to dwell In a country whose heat the best spirit would quell; 'Tis true he's a thief, and of thieves the commander, But his quarters would puzzle the best salamander. A plague on these flints that have worn out my feet! A plague on these rocks half calcined by the heat! How dreadful these waterless vapours that make, To torture the pilgrim, the farce of a lake! Not a tree, not a spring has this wilderness in it. My pulse beats two hundred and ten in a minute. My tongue is on fire, and my brain in a muddle, I would give all the world for a good draught of puddle! Then, when one least thinks of it, comes the Simoom' And these sands will supply me a couch and a tomb! Or, who can be sure but some merciful Shekh, For the sake of my garments, may twist off my neck?— Oh dear! I'm afraid!—I've a mind to turn back, But—I doubt that I never shall hit on the track— And Fatima! Thou!—can I leave thee in thrall? Cheer up!—a high spirit may scramble through all!— And—hurrah—I have found them; dark perch'd on the sand Like a cluster of ravens, the tents are at hand. And, sure, that's my uncle— Enter Shekh. SHEKH. Stand, infidel stand! Stand, slave, and deliver! SELIM. 'Tis vastly distressing, That he won't recollect me! Kind uncle, your blessing! SHEKH. Ha, rascal! who art thou? SELIM. Oh—look not so grim! The son of your sister, your nephew, Selim! Destroy not the seed of your father with fear! SHEKH. Selim, by the Prophet!—and what brings thee here? Hast thou taken my counsel, and is it thy bent To sojourn with us in the shade of the tent? To cast in thy lot with thy friends, and to rear, Dimly seen through the twilight, the long Arab spear? To mark from some mountain where, patient and slow, The rich-laden caravan circles below? Then spring to thy courser, exulting and gay, And swift as an eagle dart down on the prey! Oh blithe are my pastimes on desert and down, Far, far from the smoke and the noise of the town; And calm my repose when the carpet is spread, 'Twixt the steed of my bosom, and the wife of my bed, When camel-bells tinkle, and embers burn bright, And the tent curtain flaps in the breezes of night! Though poor my apparel, though scanty my fare, A cake on the hearth, and a mantle of hair, How sweet is that morsel, how light is that vest, And how rich do I feel of this sabre possest! SELIM. This is charming, I own; in this tranquil retreat, You've the blessings of hunger, of thirst and of heat,— May you long time enjoy them; for me, when I'm bent To taste of these pleasures, I'll visit your tent. But now for protection, dear uncle, I sue— You know the Bashaw of Damascus? SHEKH. I do.— SELIM. The monster has borne off my beautiful bride. SHEKH. He's perfectly right for himself to provide. SELIM. Is my uncle in earnest? SHEKH. I am, my Selim: And, thou wilt do right to assassinate him! SELIM. By my beard! I intend it,—but how shall I do it? SHEKH. Oh just as thou wilt, so thou fairly goest through it.— Thou mayst shoot him, or stab him, or beat out his brain. SELIM. But how to get at him?—your meaning explain. SHEKH. I have spoken!—and he who hath purpose to slay, If he have but the courage, will find out the way! If thou diest, I'll avenge thee. SELIM. Far rather defend me! I hoped that the spears of Mount Hor would befriend me! You have eaten our salt, have been warm'd at our fire, And there flows in my veins of the blood of your sire. To a castle in Hauran, if truth is in fame, Abou Malek has borne my disconsolate dame. The walls are not strong, and the garrison few. What say you to singeing those whiskers of blue? Will you aid my revenge? SHEKH. I don't care if I do. First come to the tent, share my bread and my water, And the moon of to-morrow shall light us to slaughter. SELIM. Oh pause not a moment! SHEKH. And why, my Selim? SELIM. The ring on my finger! its ruby grows dim! She dies,—she is bleeding,—I see by the stone! Oh haste, or I fly to her rescue alone! SHEKH. By my head—a brave youth! I will lend thee a steed, And I and my people will help at thy need. And woe to these Turks when the whirlwind of war Is gather'd in clouds on the summit of Hor! When the locusts of Maon are dark on the blast, And the leopards of Arnon— SELIM. Oh haste! uncle, haste! [Exeunt. Scene IV. An Apartment in Blue-Beard's Castle. Fatima, Ayesha. FATIMA. In vain you console me,—too sure is my doom, And the dews of to-morrow must weep o'er my tomb. Enough! I forgive you! 'twas Azrael's decree, That bloody my death and untimely should be. Poor captives of fate! the entangled gazelle May break through the snare of the hunter as well, As we, with our wisdom, our cunning and wit, Escape from the meshes by destiny knit! Be at rest, I forgive you! AYESHA. Yet, yet we have space To contrive our escape from this horrible place. Two days have gleam'd sadly o'er dungeon and tower, Since the Lord of Damascus set forth with his power. One more must be wash'd from the tables of fate, Ere the shade of his presence will darken the gate. And Selim, by this time, must his uncle have met. And, my dear injured sister!—I'd lay you a bet That, or ever our tyrant returns to our door, His way will be block'd by the bands of Mount Hor. FATIMA. Can Arabs contend with a warrior like him? Oh better I die than endanger Selim! AYESHA. Yet, yet I have something to check your despair— I have search'd through the south turret chamber, and there— FATIMA. Oh name not the turret—that desolate room Where my wretched forerunners in folly and doom Lie mouldering and green! AYESHA. I beheld with affright, And horrid, most horrid indeed was the sight! But I still persevered, for there prest on my mind A suspicion of mystery lurking behind. And at length I have found it; an aperture small That leads to a stair in the bulk of the wall; Beneath it a postern conceal'd, and I hope That with me you will pack up your things and elope. FATIMA. No packing! no loitering! conduct me this minute! AYESHA. Law!—your train will be bloodied! allow me to pin it: We have plenty of time. [Looking through the door. Oh, confusion and sorrow! The Bashaw has mistaken to-day for to-morrow, He is now on the staircase.—Oh, would it might crumble— I'd break my own neck to ensure him a tumble! ABOU MALEK (speaking without). Within there! what, slaves! are ye sleeping or dead? If ye sleep till the morning your couch will be red! Am I forced like a dog of the desert to wait, No slaves at my stirrup, no guard at my gate, And unhonour'd by sign or salute from the wall— To sneak like a thief to my own castle hall? Up, up to the ramparts! unlimber the swivels, You will soon have a visit from Arabs or devils! They are hard on my track! AYESHA. Recollect what I told you! Cheer up! he must not in this anguish behold you; Put him off for a while if he talks of the keys, By the help of a kiss you may do it with ease. But gain a few hours and, I'll wager my neck, Some tidings will come of Selim and his Shekh. [To Abou Malek as he enters. Oh my lord! my dear brother! such sudden delight! We never expected you home by to-night! ABOU MALEK. So, so, where's your sister? AYESHA. And as I was saying, Your highness, we thought, in the city was staying; So we fasten'd the gate, sent the servants to sleep, Good hours we were always accustom'd to keep, And we were just talking— ABOU MALEK. My curse on your head. No doubt you were talking— AYESHA. Of going to bed. And— ABOU MALEK. Fatima! well may you boast of the charms That bring back your husband so soon to your arms. Three days I had promised—my heart could not wait, And the second has seen me return to your gate. Escaped from an ambush that threaten'd my life, I come with delight to my home and my wife. My wife and my queen! Yes—your trial is o'er, And the Fiend of suspicion shall haunt me no more! But what?—All in tears—in confusion! FATIMA. Great Sir, Your return so unlook'd for, so sudden,—I fear—— ABOU MALEK. Fear! what? AYESHA. That some sudden disaster or sickness Is the cause, mighty Lord, of your singular quickness. Then, you seem to be wearied, and I have a notion, You had better retire with a nightcap and potion. Then, the ambush you mention'd has thrill'd us with fear. Who could be your foes? ABOU MALEK. From Mount Hor, or Mount Seir, Some rascally Arabs— AYESHA. My love, do you hear? (Aside to Fatima.) (Aloud.) And pray does your Highness suppose they are near? ABOU MALEK. Oh Prophet! great Prophet!—if ever I come To bliss, I entreat let my Houri be dumb! Give that clapper a holiday once in thy life. But come thou to my bosom, my friend, and my wife! (To Fatima.) Thy silence, thy gentleness, ever must please. Alas—I forgot—you may give me the keys. FATIMA. The keys, my dread Lord?—give me time to prepare, I have lost them, mislaid them—can't tell where they are. ABOU MALEK. You have lost them! mislaid them! oh ominous word! The keys, in an instant! FATIMA (kneeling and covering her face.) Receive them, my Lord! ABOU MALEK. (After looking at the keys, he drops them.) And art thou detected, whom least I suspected! Oh prophetess! prophetess! great was thy skill! AYESHA (flinging herself at his feet). It all was my doing?—mine, mine, be the ruin! But do not, oh do not your Fatima kill? ABOU MALEK (turning away from Fatima). I dare not behold thee,—should my arms once enfold thee, My purpose, I feel, in a moment would cool. AYESHA (aside to Fatima.) Yet, yet I would try him—with compliments ply him A husband, well flatter'd, is always a fool.— FATIMA. Is pity so strange to a conqueror's bosom? So slight an offence must such vengeance pursue? AYESHA. Was your father a wolf?—was your nurse an opossum, That your heart does not melt her distresses to view? FATIMA. When first from the cot of my father you bore me, I hoped for protection from peril and scorn. ABOU MALEK. Oh horror to see thee thus kneeling before me, And kneeling in vain ! I have sworn! I have sworn! (A great noise without, fire of musketry, shouts, &amp;c.) By Heaven! are these Arabs so close on my traces? Have the rascals such courage, such conduct and skill? For a moment I leave thee, 'twere bliss to reprieve thee, But hope not, oh hope not to soften my will, [Exit. AYESHA. Thank our stars! he is gone, and the castle's surrounded! And—oh! blessed accident, here are the keys! I swear he shall keep us no longer impounded, Make off!—we can get through the postern with ease. Oh me! come again. Re-enter Abou Malek, who catches Fatima— Ayesha escapes. ABOU MALEK. What, ye fiends! are ye flying? Have ye sold me to fall by the hands of Mount Hor? AYESHA (without). Oh hasten to rescue a lady from dying! Oh hasten Selim, I'm unbolting the door! ABOU MALEK. Is it thus? Oh I thank thee for giving me rest; Thy treason has taken a load from my breast! I can murther thee now without fear of relenting, And fall, if my doom is to fall, unrepenting! But live, while I print a last kiss on thy brow, The last and the sweetest! SELIM (rushing in with a drawn sabre). Now, murderer, now! Turn infidel Giaour! ABOU MALEK. Is the lion at bay! Woe, woe to the hunter who stands in his way! [Fight. ABOU MALEK. Ha! Peasant! well fought! that last thrust was a raker, And my business—will soon be—with Monkir—and Hakir. (Falls.) Enter Ayesha and Arabs. ABOU MALEK. Oh prophetess! prophetess! well hast thou said! And Fatima, fear not! kneel down by my head! Believers—bear witness! my sins to atone I make her my heiress—the castle's her own! Forgive me! farewell !—I had more—but 'tis past, The first of my wives whom I loved is—the last! [Dies. SHEKH. The Bashaw had a right to devise his estate. But the Shekh of Mount Hor has a hold on his plate! (The Shekh, and his Attendants are all loaded with booty.) FATIMA. Alas, my Lord Shekh !—you can ne'er be repaid, For your generous assistance! SHEKH. Pooh! fighting's my trade! But Selim, in my mind, ere your union is hurried, Abou Malek had better be handsomely buried. Of weddings, poor man! he abundance has seen, But 'tis always unlucky to marry thirteen!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">MISCELLANEOUS POEMS. TO LIEUTENANT-GENERAL SIR ROWLAND HILL, K.B. Hill! whose high daring with renew'd success Hath cheer'd our tardy war, what time the cloud Of expectation, dark and comfortless, Hung on the mountains; and yon factious crowd Blasphem'd their country's valour, babbling loud! Then was thine arm reveal'd, to whose young might, By Toulon's leaguer'd wall, the fiercest bow'd; Whom Egypt honour'd, and the dubious fight Of sad Corunna's winter, and more bright Douro, and Talavera's gory bays; Wise, modest, brave, in danger foremost found.— So still, young warrior, may thy toil-earn'd praise, With England's love and England's honour crown'd, Gild with delight thy father's latter days! LINES SPOKEN IN THE THEATRE, OXFORD, ON LORD GRENVILLE'S INSTALLATION AS CHANCELLOR. Ye viewless guardians of these sacred shades, These lines were spoken (as is the custom of the University on the installation of a new chancellor) by a young nobleman, whose diffidence induced him to content himself with the composition of another. Of this diffidence his friends have reason to complain, as it suppressed some elegant lines of his own on the same occasion. Dear dreams of early song, Aonian maids!— And you, illustrious dead! whose spirits speak In each warm flush that tints the student's cheek, As, wearied with the world, he seeks again The page of better times and greater men; If with pure worship we your steps pursue, And youth, and health, and rest forget for you, (Whom most we serve, to whom our lamp burns bright Through the long toils of not ingrateful night,) Yet, yet be present!—Let the worldly train Mock our cheap joys, and hate our useless strain, Intent on freighted wealth, or proud to rear The fleece Iberian or the pamper'd steer ;— Let sterner science with unwearied eye Explore the circling spheres and map the sky; His long-drawn mole let lordly commerce scan, And of his iron arch the rainbow span: Yet, while, in burning characters imprest, The poet's lesson stamps the youthful breast; Bids the rapt boy o'er suffering virtue bleed, Adore a brave or bless a gentle deed, And in warm feeling from the storied page Arise the saint, the hero, or the sage; Such be our toil !—Nor doubt we to explore The thorny maze of dialectic lore, To climb the chariot of the gods, or scan The secret workings of the soul of man; Upborne aloft on Plato's eagle flight, Or the slow pinion of the Stagyrite.— And, those grey spoils of Herculanean pride, If aught of yet untasted sweets they hide ;— If Padua's sage be there, or art have power To wake Menander from his secret bower. Such be our toil !—Nor vain the labour proves, Which Oxford honours, and which Grenville loves! —On, eloquent and firm !—whose warning high Rebuked the rising surge of anarchy, When, like those brethren stars to seamen known, In kindred splendour Pitt and Grenville shone ;— On in thy glorious course! not yet the wave Has ceased to lash the shore, nor storm forgot to rave. Go on! and oh, while adverse factions raise To thy pure worth involuntary praise; While Gambia's swarthy tribes thy mercies bless, And from thy counsels date their happiness; Say, (for thine Isis yet recals with pride Thy youthful triumphs by her leafy side,) Say, hast thou scorn'd, mid pomp, and wealth, and power, The sober transports of a studious hour?— No, statesman, no !—thy patriot fire was fed From the warm embers of the mighty dead; And thy strong spirit's patient grasp combined The souls of ages in a single mind.— —By arts like these, amidst a world of foes, Eye of the earth, th' Athenian glory rose ;— Thus last and best of Romans, Brutus shone ;— Our Somers thus, and thus our Clarendon; Such Cobham was ;—such, Grenville, long be thou, Our boast before,—our chief and champion now !— EPITAPH ON A YOUNG NAVAL OFFICER, DESIGNED FOR A TOMB IN A SEAPORT TOWN IN NORTH WALES. Sailor! if vigour nerve thy frame, If to high deeds thy soul is strung, Revere this stone that gives to fame The brave, the virtuous, and the young!— Captain Conway Shipley, third son to the dean of St. Asaph, perished in an attempt to cut out an enemy's vessel from the Tagus with the boats of his Majesty's frigate La Nymphe, April 22,1808, in the twenty-sixth year of his age, and after nearly sixteen years of active service; distinguished by every quality both of heart and head which could adorn a man or an officer. Admiral Sir Charles Cotton, and the captains of his fleet, have since erected a monument to his memory in the neighbourhood of Fort St. Julian. For manly beauty deck'd his form, His bright eye beam'd with mental power; Resistless as the winter storm, Yet mild as summer's mildest shower.— In war's hoarse rage, in ocean's strife, For skill, for force, for mercy known; Still prompt to shield a comrade's life, And greatly careless of his own.— Yet, youthful seaman, mourn not thou The fate these artless lines recall: No, Cambrian! no, be thine the vow, Like him to live, like him to fall !— But hast thou known a father's care, Who sorrowing sent thee forth to sea; Pour'd for thy weal th' unceasing prayer, And thought the sleepless night on thee ?— Has e'er thy tender fancy flown, When winds were strong and waves were high, Where listening to the tempest's moan, Thy sisters heav'd the anxious sigh? Or in the darkest hour of dread, 'Mid war's wild din, and ocean's swell, Hast mourn'd a hero brother dead, And did that brother love thee well ?— Then pity those whose sorrows flow In vain o'er Shipley's empty grave !— —Sailor, thou weep'st :—indulge thy woe; Such tears will not disgrace the brave !— FRAGMENT ON ALCHEMY. So fares the sage, whose mystic labours try The thorny paths of fabled alchemy. Time, toil, and prayer, to aid the work conspire, And the keen jaws of dross-devouring fire. In one dim pile discordant embers blaze, And stars of adverse influence join their rays; Till every rite perform'd, and labour sped, When the clear furnace dawns with sacred red, From forth the genial warmth and teeming mould, The bright-wing'd radiance bursts of infant gold. IMITATION OF A SONG, SAID TO HAVE BEEN COMPOSED BY ROBERT DUKE OF NORMANDY, DURING HIS CONFINEMENT IN CARDIFF CASTLE, ADDRESSED TO AN OAK WHICH GREW IN AN ANCIENT ENCAMPMENT WITHIN SIGHT OF HIS WINDOWS. Oak, that stately and alone On the war-worn mound hast grown, The blood of man thy sapling fed, And dyed thy tender root in red; Woe to the feast where foes combine, Woe to the strife of words and wine! Oak, thou hast sprung for many a year, 'Mid whisp'ring rye-grass tall and sear, The coarse rank herb, which seems to show That bones unbless'd are laid below; Woe to the sword that hates its sheath, Woe to th' unholy trade of death! Oak, from the mountain's airy brow Thou view'st the subject woods below, And merchants hail the well-known tree, Returning o'er the Severn sea. Woe, woe to him whose birth is high, For peril waits on royalty! Now storms have bent thee to the ground, And envious ivy clips thee round; And shepherd hinds in wanton play Have stripp'd thy needful bark away; Woe to the man whose foes are strong, Thrice woe to him who lives too long! HONOUR ITS OWN REWARD. Swell, swell the shrill trumpet clear sounding afar, Our sabres flash splendour around, For freedom has summon'd her sons to the war, Nor Britain has shrunk from the sound. Let plunder's vile thirst the invaders inflame, Let slaves for their wages be bold, Shall valour the harvest of avarice claim? Shall Britons be barter'd for gold? No! free be our aid, independent our might, Proud honour our guerdon alone; Unhir'd be the hand that we raise in the fight, The sword that we brandish our own. Still all that we love to our thoughts shall succeed, Their image each labour shall cheer, For them we will conquer—for them we will bleed, And our pay be a smile or a tear! And oh! if returning triumphant we move, Or sink on the land that we save, Oh! blest by his country, his kindred, his love, How vast the reward of the brave! TRANSLATION OF A FRAGMENT OF A DANISH SONG. King Christian stood beside the mast, In smoky night; His falchion fell like hammer fast, And brains and helms asunder brast; Then sunk each hostile hull and mast In smoky night; Fly, fly! they shrieked—what mortal man Can strive with Denmark's Christian In fight? Niels Juel raised a warrior cry, “Now, now's the day!” He hoisted up the red flag high, And dashed amidst the enemy With blow on blow, and cry on cry, “Now, now's the day!” And still they shrieked—“Fly, Sweden, fly! When Juel comes, what strength shall try The fray?” TRANSLATION OF AN INSCRIPTION ON A MONUMENT, INTENDED TO PERPETUATE THE MEMORY OF THE FRIENDSHIP OF TWO PERSONS WHO WERE LIVING WHEN IT WAS WRITTEN. “May every light-winged moment bear A blessing to this noble pair. Long may they love the rural ease Of these fair scenes, and scenes like these; The pine's dark shade, the mountain tall, And the deep dashing water-fall. And when each hallowed spirit flies To seek a better paradise, Beneath this turf their ashes dear Shall drink their country's grateful tear; In death alike and life possessing, The rich man's love, the poor man's blessing.” VERSIFICATION OF THE SPEECH OF GEOORGIN TO BEYUN, (FROM THE SHAH NAMEH.) Seest thou yon shelter'd vale of various dye, Refreshing prospect to the warrior's eye? Yon dusky grove, yon garden blooming fair, The turf of velvet, and of musk the air? Surcharged with sweets the languid river glides, The lilies bending o'er its silver tides; While through the copse in bashful beauty glows The dark luxuriance of the lurking rose. Now seen, now lost, amid the flowery maze, With slender foot the nimble pheasant strays; The ringdove's murmur lulls the cypress dell, And richest notes of tranced Philomel. Still, still the same, through every circling year, Unwearied spring renews an Eden here. And mark, my friend, where many a sylph-like maid Weaves the lithe dance beneath the citron shade! Where chief, of Touran's king the matchless child, Beams like a sun-ray through this scented wild; Sitara next, her sister, beauteous queen, Than rose or fairest jasmine fairer seen; And last, their Turkish maids, whose sleepy eyes Laugh from beneath each envious veil's disguise; Whose length of locks the coal-black musk disclose, Their forms the cypress, and their cheeks the rose; While on their sugar'd lips the grape's rich water glows. How blest the traveller not forbid to stay In such sweet bowers the scorching summer's day! How fam'd the knight whose dauntless arm should bear To great Khi-Kusroo's court a Turkish fair! FROM THE MOALLAKAH OF HARETH. And Asma! lovely sojourner! wilt thou forsake our land, Forgetful of thy plighted vows on Shamma's glittering sand? No more in Shoreb's rugged dell I see thee by my side, No more in Katha's mead of green where vocal waters glide! In Ayla and in Shobathan all lonely must I go, And, therefore, sleep has fled my soul, and fast my sorrows flow! Yet am I loved, and yet my eyes behold the beacon light, Which Hinda kindles on her hill, to lure me through the night, Broad as the dawn, from Akik's brow its ruddy embers shine, But Hinda's heart may never meet an answering glow in mine! And I must seek a nobler aid against consuming care, Where all the brethren of my tribe the battle bow prepare. My camel with the mother-bird in swiftness well may vie, Tall as a tent, 'mid desert sands that rears her progeny, That lists the murmur of the breeze, the hunter's lightest sound With stealthy foot at twilight fall soft gliding o'er the ground; But not the ostrich speed of fire my camel can excel, Whose footstep leaves so light a mark we guess not where it fell; Now up, now down, like wither'd leaves that flit before the wind, On her I stem the burning noon that strikes the valiant blind. Yes, we have heard an angry sound of danger from afar, Our brother's bands of Tayleb's seed have braved us to the war; The good and evil they confound, their words are fierce and fell, “Their league,” say they, “is with the tribe that in the desert dwell.” Their men of might have met by night, and as the day began, A proud and a disdainful shout throughout their army ran, And horses neighed, and camels screamed, and man cried out on man! THE BOKE OF THE PURPLE FAUCON. Icy commence le Romaunt du Grand Roye Pantagruelle. Yt is a kynge both fyne and felle, That hyght Sir Claudyus Pantagruelle,— The fynest and fellest, more or lesse, Of alle the kynges in Heathenesse. That Syre was Soudan of Surrye, Of Œstrick and of Cappadocie, His Eme was Lorde I understonde Of all Cathaye and of Bœhman Londe. LXX Dukes, that were soe wighte, Served him by daie and by nighte. Le Royaume de Pantagruelle. Thereto he made him a lothely messe, Everie morninge more or lesse, A manne chylde of VII yere age, Thereof he seethed hys pottage. Comment Pantagruelle tenayt bonne table, et fesoyt belle chere; Everie knyghte who went that waye His nose and ears was fayne to paye; Sothely, as the Romaunts telle, For the Dyner of Pantagruelle. Yn all the londes of Ethiopeè et estoyt digne roy. Was ne so worthy a kynge as hee. Ande it befelle upon a daye Thys Pantagruelle he went to playe With his Ladye thatte was soe brighte, Yn her bowre yn alle mennes syghte. Comment il aimoyt la Royne Cycile. Thatte Ladye was hyghte Cycelee; And thereto sange shee Alle into Grekysh as she colde best,— “Lambeth, Sadeck, Apocatest;” Namely, “My love yf thou wouldest wynne Bringe wyth thee a purple falcon ynne.” Thatte laye made hym sadde and sowre, And careful came hee adowne the towre. He layde his hedde upon a stone; Comment Pantagruelle estoyt mescontent. For sorrow hys lyfe was well nigh gone; He sobbed amayne and sighed sore “Alacke Cycile, for evermore.” Hys page he broughte him hys helmette, Ses armures. Thatte was cleped Alphabet; He donned hys bootes made of the skyn Of Loup-garou and of Gobbelyn, And hys hauberke that was soe harde Y woven welle of spykenarde. Virgile hadde made that cote-armure Li graund magycien Virgile. With Maumetry fenced and guarded sure; And Hypocras and Arystote Had woven the rynges of thatte cote. He tooke hys spere that was so strong, Hys axe was sharpe, his sworde was long, And thys the devyse upon his sheilde— A red rose yn a greene fielde, And under, yn language of Syrie, “Belle rose que tu es jolye.” Ycy commence le II Chant du Bon Roy Pantagruelle. Lysten Lordynges to the tale Of Pantagruelle and hys travayle. He through many a lande has gone, Pantagruelle hymself alone; Many a hyll most hyghe has clome, Many a broade rivere has swome. Ses Voyages.He paste through Cathaye and Picardie, Babylon, Scotland, and Italie; And asked of alle as yt befelle, But of no adventure herde he telle, Tyl after manie a wearie daye, Lyghtly he came to a foreste graye: Manie an auncient oke dyd growe, Doddered and frynged with mysletoe; Manie an ashe of paly hue Whyspered yn every breeze that blewe. Li Serment de Pantagruelle.Pantagruelle hath sworne by Mahoune, Bye Termagaunt and by Abadoune, Bye Venus, thatte was soe sterne and stronge, And Apollin with hornes longe, And other fiendes of Maumetrye, That the ende of that foreste he would see. Lysten Lordinges the soothe I tell: Nothyng was true that here befelle, La Forest enchantée.But all the okes that flourished soe free, Flourished only in grammarie; In that same foreste nothing grewe But broad and darke the boughes of yew. Sothely I tell you and indede There was many a wicked weede; There was the wolf-bane greene and highe, Whoso smelleth the same shall die, And the long grasse wyth poyson mixed, Adders coyled and hyssed betwixt. Yn thatte same chace myghte noe man hear Hunter or horn or hounde or deer; Neyther dared yn thatte wood to goe Coney or martin, or hare or doe. Nor on the shawe the byrdes gay, Starling, Cuckoo, or Popynjay; But Gryphon fanged, and bristly boare, Gnarred and fomed hys way before, And the beeste who can falsely weepe, Crocodilus, was here goode chepe; Satyr, and Leopard, and Tygris, Bloody Camelopardalys, And every make of beastes bolde, Nestled and roared in that their holde. Dayes and nyghtes but only IV, And Pantagruelle could ryde no more. Hys shoulders were by hys helmet worne, He was a wearye wyghte forlorne, And hys cheeke thatte was soe redde, Colde and darke as the beaten ledde. Sa misère.Hys destriere might no further passe, It lothed to taste that evyl grasse. Heavy he clombe from offe hys steede, Of hys lyfe he stoode in drede: “Alacke, alacke, Cycelie, Here I dye for love of thee!” Forth through the thorny brake hee paste, Tylle he came to a poole at laste; And bye that poole of water clere Satte a manne chylde of seven yere; Clothed he was in scarlet and graine, Cloth of silver and cordovaine; As a field flower he was faire, Seemed he was some Erle's heir, And perchynge on hys wriste so free, A purple Faucon there was to see. Courteous hee turned hym to that Peere, But Pantagruelle made sory cheare. Highe and stately that boye hym bare, And bade hym abyde hys Father there. When the Father was there yn place, Never had knyght so foul a face; He was tusked as anie boare, Brystly behind and eke before; Lyons staring as they were wood, Salvage bull that liveth on blood, He was fylthy as any sowe, Blacke and hairy as a black cowe; All yn a holy priest's attyre, Never was seene so fowle a syre. A FRAGMENT. AFTER THE MANNER OF SPENSER. And by that mansion's western side there stoode An ancient bowre enwrapte in darkest shade Of sacred elde, and wide-encircling woode; Seemed it was for saintlye abbesse made. Strong were the doors with yron barrs arraide For fear of foe that them enharmen myghte, Ne any durst that fort for to invade, For by the wicket grate, bothe daye and nyghte, A snowy gaurdian sate; of old that Bunny highte. And all withinne were books of various lore, St. Leon's toils, and Bible nothinge newe, And needle-work, and artists' busie store Of crumbling chalke, and tyntes of everie hue; And on the ground, most terrible to view, Dame Venus' mangled limbs were strewed around; For soothe to tell, the goddess envyous grewe When here she saw myght fairer forms be found, And dash'd in pieces small her statue on the ground. Such is that bowre, but who shall dare pourtraye What sister fairies there their spells combine; She, whose younge charms the rugged harte cold swaye Of prelate olde, and never tamed divine. She, limneresse of Spenser, (master mine,) Angelic limneresse, in whose darke eye Dothe wit's wilde glance and playful beauty shine And she of shapeliest form and stature highe, And meeke unconscious state and winning majestie. TRANSLATION OF AN ODE OF KLOPSTOCK'S. HE. Ah Selma! if our love the fates should sever, And bear thy spirit from the world below, Then shall mine eyes be wet with tears for ever, Each gloomy morn, each night of darker woe; Each hour, that past so soon in thy embracing, Each minute keenly felt shall force a tear; The long, long months! the years so slowly pacing! Which all were swift alike, and all were dear. SHE. My Selmar! ah, if from thy Selma parted, Thy soul should first the paths of darkness tread, Sad were my course, and short, and broken-hearted, To weep those lonely days, that dismal bed! Each hour that erst in converse sweet returning, Shone with thy smile, or sparkled with thy tear; Each lingering day should lengthen out my mourning, The days that past so swiftly and so dear! HE. And did I promise, Selma, years of sorrow? And canst thou linger only days behind? Few minutes, few, be mine from fate to borrow, Near thy pale cheek and breathless form reclin'd, Press thy dead hand, and, wildly bending o'er thee, Print one last kiss upon thy glazed eye. SHE. Nay, Selmar, nay—I will not fall before thee; That pang be mine; thou shalt not see me die; Some few sad moments on thy death-bed lying, By thy pale corpse my trembling frame shall be; Gaze on thy altered form, then, inly sighing, Sink on that breast, and wax as pale as thee.” SONG TO A SCOTCH AIR. I love the harp with silver sound, That rings the festal hall around; But sweetest of all The strains which fall, When twilight mirth with song is crown'd. I love the bugle's warbling swell, When echo answers from her cell; But sweeter to me, When I list to thee, Who wak'st the northern lay so well. THE RISING OF THE SUN. TO A WELCH AIR. Wake! wake! wake to the hunting! Wake ye, wake! the morning is nigh! Chilly the breezes blow Up from the sea below, Chilly the twilight creeps over the sky! Mark how fast the stars are fading! Mark how wide the dawn is spreading! Many a fallow deer Feeds in the forest near; Now is no time on the heather to lie! Rise, rise! look on the ocean! Rise ye, rise, and look on the sky! Softly the vapours sweep Over the level deep, Softly the mists on the water-fall lie! In the cloud red tints are glowing, On the hill the black cock's crowing; And through the welkin red, See where he lifts his head, (Forth to the hunting!) The sun's riding high! SONG TO A WELCH AIR. The moon in silent brightness Rides o'er the mountain brow, The mist in fleecy whiteness Has clad the vale below; Above the woodbine bow'r Dark waves our trysting-tree; It is, it is the hour, Oh come, my love, to me! The dews of night have wet me, While wand'ring lonelily; Thy father's bands beset me— I only fear'd for thee. I crept beneath thy tower, I climb'd the ivy tree; And blessed be the hour That brings my love to me. I left my chosen numbers In yonder copse below; Each warrior lightly slumbers, His hand upon his bow: From forth a tyrant's power They wait to set thee free; It is, it is the hour,— Oh come, my love, to me! INSCRIPTION PROPOSED FOR THE VASE PRESENTED TO SIR WATKIN WILLIAMS WYNN, BY THE NOBILITY AND GENTRY OF DENBIGHSHIRE, AT THE CONCLUSION OF THE WAR IN 1815. “Ask ye why around me twine Tendrils of the Gascon vine? Ask ye why, in martial pride, Sculptured laurels deck my side, Blended with that noble tree, Badge of Albion's liberty? Cambria me, for glory won By the waves of broad Garonne, Sends to greet her bravest son; Prov'd beyond the western deep, By rebel clans on Ulster's steep; Prov'd, where first on Gallia's plain, The banish'd lily bloom'd again; And prov'd where ancient bounty calls The traveller to his father's halls! Nor marvel, then, that round me twine The oak, the laurel, and the vine; For thus was Cambria wont to see Her Hirlas-horn of victory: Nor Cambria e'er, in days of yore, To worthier chief the Hirlas bore!” TIMOUR'S COUNCILS. Emirs and Khâns in long array, To Timour's council bent their way; The lordly Tartar, vaunting high, The Persian with dejected eye, The vassal Russ, and, lured from far, Circassia's mercenary war. But one there came, uncall'd and last, The spirit of the wintry blast! He mark'd, while wrapt in mist he stood, The purpos'd track of spoil and blood; He marked, unmov'd by mortal woe, That old man's eye of swarthy glow; That restless soul, whose single pride Was cause enough that millions died; He, heard, he saw, till envy woke, And thus the voice of thunder spoke:— “And hop'st thou thus, in pride unfurl'd, To bear those banners through the world? Can time nor space thy toils defy? Oh king, thy fellow-demon I! Servants of Death, alike we sweep The wasted earth, or shrinking deep. And on the land, and o'er the wave, We reap the harvest of the grave. But thickest then that harvest lies, And wildest sorrows rend the skies, In darker cloud the vultures sail, And richer carnage taints the gale, And few the mourners that remain, When winter leagues with Tamerlane! But on, to work our lord's decree; Then, tyrant, turn, and cope with me! And learn, though far thy trophies shine, How deadlier are my blasts than thine! Nor cities burnt, nor blood of men, Nor thine own pride shall warm thee then! Forth to thy task! We meet again On wild Chabanga's frozen plain!” THE SPRING JOURNEY. Oh! green was the corn as I rode on my way, And bright were the dews on the blossoms of May, And dark was the sycamore's shade to behold, And the oak's tender leaf was of emerald and gold. The thrush from his holly, the lark from his cloud, Their chorus of rapture sung jovial and loud; From the soft vernal sky, to the soft grassy ground, There was beauty above me, beneath, and around. The mild southern breeze brought a shower from the hill, And yet though it left me all dropping and chill, I felt a new pleasure, as onward I sped, To gaze where the rainbow gleam'd broad over head. Oh, such be life's journey, and such be our skill, To lose in its blessings the sense of its ill; Through sunshine and shower may our progress be even, And our tears add a charm to the prospect of Heaven! HAPPINESS. One morning in the month of May I wander'd o'er the hill; Though nature all around was gay, My heart was heavy still. Can God, I thought, the good, the great, These meaner creatures bless, And yet deny our human state The boon of happiness? Tell me, ye woods, ye smiling plains, Ye blessed birds around, Where, in creation's wide domains, Can perfect bliss be found? The birds wild caroll'd over head, The breeze around me blew, And nature's awful chorus said, No bliss for man she knew! I question'd love, whose early ray So heavenly bright appears; And love, in answer, seem'd to say, His light was dimm'd by tears. I question'd friendship,—friendship mourn'd, And thus her answer gave: The friends whom fortune had not turn'd Were vanish'd in the grave! I ask'd of feeling,—if her skill Could heal the wounded breast? And found her sorrows streaming still, For others' griefs distrest. I ask'd if vice could bliss bestow? Vice boasted loud and well: But, fading from her pallid brow The venom'd roses fell. I question'd virtue,—virtue sigh'd, No boon could she dispense; Nor virtue was her name, she cried, But humble penitence! I question'd Death,—the grisly shade Relax'd his brow severe; And, “I am happiness,” he said, “If virtue guides thee here!” ON HEAVENLY AND EARTHLY HOPE. Reflected on the lake I love To see the stars of evening glow, So tranquil in the heavens above. So restless in the wave below. Thus heavenly hope is all serene, But earthly hope, how bright soe'er, Still fluctuates o'er this changing scene As false and fleeting as 'tis fair. MAN'S PILGRIMAGE. Oh for the morning gleam of youth, the half-unfolded flower, That sparkles in the diamond dew of that serener hour, What time the broad and level sun shone gaily o'er the sea, And in the woods the birds awoke to songs of ecstacy. The sun, that gilds the middle arch of man's maturer day, Smites heavy on the pilgrim's head, who plods his dusty way; The birds are fled to deeper shades—the dewy flowers are dried, And hope, that with the day was born, before the day has died; For who can promise to his soul a tranquil eventide? Yes—though the dew will gleam anew—though from its western sky, The sun will give as mild a ray as morning could supply— Though from her tufted thorn again will sing the nightingale, Yet little will the ear of age enjoy her tender tale; And night will find us toiling on with joyless travail worn, For day must pass, and night must come, before another morn. SONG TO A WELCH AIR. I mourn not the forest whose verdure is dying; I mourn not the summer whose beauty is o'er; I weep for the hopes that for ever are flying; I sigh for the worth that I slighted before; And sigh to bethink me how vain is my sighing, For love, once extinguish'd, is kindled no more. The spring may return with his garland of flowers, And wake to new rapture the bird on the tree; The summer smile soft through his crystalline bowers; The blessings of autumn wave brown o'er the lea; The rock may be shaken—the dead may awaken, But the friend of my bosom returns not to me. CAROL FOR MAY-DAY. Queen of fresh flowers, Whom vernal stars obey, Bring thy warm showers, Bring thy genial ray. In nature's greenest livery drest, Descend on earth's expectant breast, To earth and Heaven a welcome guest, Thou merry month of May! Mark how we meet thee At dawn of dewy day! Hark! how we greet thee With our roundelay! While all the goodly things that be In earth, and air, and ample sea, Are waking up to welcome thee, Thou merry month of May! Flocks on the mountains, And birds upon their spray, Tree, turf, and fountains, All hold holyday; And love, the life of living things, Love waves his torch, love claps his wings, And loud and wide thy praises sings, Thou merry month of May! TO ?. When I was sick, how patiently thou sat'st beside my bed, When I was faint, how lovingly thine arm upheld my head, When I was wearied out with pain, perverse in misery, How ready was thy watchful aid my wishes to supply! And thou art sick, and thou art weak, and thou art rack'd with pain, But cheerful still, untam'd of ill, does yet thy heart remain; And have I nurs'd and tended thee since first thy griefs began? Forgive, forgive, my ?, the selfishness of man! BOW-MEETING SONG. Merry archers, come with me! Come with me, come with me; Merry archers, come with me, To our tent beside the holly! Summer gilds the smiling day, Summer clothes the tufted spray, Earth is green and Heaven is gay, Wherefore should we not be jolly! Merry archers, come &amp;c. Here is friendship, mirth is here, Woodland music, woodland cheer, And, with hope and blended fear, Here is love's delightful folly. Our life, alas! is fraught with care, And mortals all must have their share, But yet to-day we well may spare From our load of melancholy. Merry archers, come with me! Come with me, come with me; Merry archers, come with me, To our tents beside the holly! FAREWELL. When eyes are beaming What never tongue might tell; When tears are streaming From their crystal cell, When hands are link'd that dread to part, And heart is met by throbbing heart, Oh bitter, bitter is the smart Of them that bid farewell! When hope is chidden That fain of bliss would tell, And love forbidden In the breast to dwell, When, fetter'd by a viewless chain We turn and gaze and turn again, Oh death were mercy to the pain Of those that bid farewell! PARODY OF LISTON'S “BEAUTIFUL MAID.” My fishmonger told me that soles were most dear: I trembled to hear what he said, For salmon and shrimps 'twas the wrong time of year, So I pitch'd on a Beautiful Maid. I brought home my beautiful maid, “Here cook, dress this beautiful maid! Come boil it, don't spoil it, but see it well done, And I'll dine on my beautiful maid!” But an ugly black cat—I speak it with grief, My delicate tit-bit waylaid, The cook turn'd her back, and the long-whisker'd thief Ran away with my beautiful maid! She claw'd up my beautiful maid! She elop'd with my beautiful maid! Oh pussy—you hussy, oh what have you done, You've eat up my beautiful maid! TRANSLATION OF AN INSCRIPTION RECENTLY DISCOVERED IN SAMOS. (CLARKE'S TRAVELS.) Turinna, fam'd for every grace Of learning and of ancient race, Whom all the virtues did consent With all their gifts to ornament, When thrice nine little years are flown Hath left her parents to bemoan With bitter tears, the early dead By whom their house is widowed. For nought remains, now she is gone, That love or hope may rest upon. And she hath left her palace home To sleep within the narrow tomb. Yet may her race, or good men feign, Revive from such distress again. THE OUTWARD-BOUND SHIP. As borne along with favouring gale And streamers waving bright, How gaily sweeps the glancing sail O'er yonder sea of light! With painted sides the vessel glides, In seeming revelry; And still we hear the sailor's cheer Around the capstan tree. Is sorrow there where all is fair, Where all is outward glee? Go, fool, to yonder mariner, And he shall lesson thee! Upon that deck walks tyrant sway Wild as his conquer'd wave, And murmuring hate that must obey; The captain and his slave. And pinching care is lurking there, And dark ambition's swell, And some that part with bursting heart From objects loved too well; And many a grief with gazing fed On yonder distant shore, And many a tear in secret shed For friends beheld no more; Yet sails the ship with streamers drest And shouts of seeming glee: Oh God! how loves the mortal breast To hide its misery! BOW-MEETING SONG. Ye spirits of our Fathers, The hardy, bold and free, Who chas'd o'er Cressy's-gory field A fourfold enemy! From us who love your sylvan game, To you the song shall flow, To the fame of your name Who so bravely bent the bow. 'Twas merry then in England, (Our ancient records tell,) With Robin Hood and Little John Who dwelt by down and dell; And yet we love the bold outlaw Who brav'd a tyrant foe, Whose cheer was the deer, And his only friend the bow! 'Twas merry then in England In autumn's dewy morn, When echo started from her hill To hear the bugle-horn. And beauty, mirth, and warrior worth In garb of green did go The shade to invade With the arrow and the bow. Ye spirits of our Fathers! Extend to us your care, Among your children yet are found The valiant and the fair! 'Tis merry yet in Old England Full well her archers know, And shame on their name Who despise the British bow! TO CHAUNCEY HARE TOWNSHEND, ON HIS LINES PRAISING THE TRANQUILLITY OF A RIVER, WHILE THE SEA WAS HEARD ON THE NEIGHBOURING SHORE. (See Townshend's Poems, p. 206.) Oh Townshend! could'st thou linger where scarce a ripple play'd Across the lily's glossystem, or beneath the willow's shade, And did that mighty chorus allure thy bark in vain, The laughter of the dancing waves and music of the main? The breeze may tell his story of soft and still delight, As whisp'ring through the woodbine bower he fans the cheek of night, But louder, blither, sings the wind, his carol wild and free, When the harvest moon sails forth in pride above her subject sea. I love to thread the little paths, the rushy banks between, Where Tern, in dewy silence, creeps through the meadow green; I love to mark the speckl'd trout beneath the sunbeam lie, And skimming past, on filmy wing, the danger-courting fly. I praise the darker shadows where, o'er the runnel lone, The regal oak or swarthy pine their giant arms have thrown, Or, from his couch of heather, where Skiddaw bends to view The furrows of his rifted brow in Derwent's mirror blue. But not that narrow stillness has equal charms for me, With thy ten-thousand voices thou broad exulting sea, Thy shining sands, thy rugged shores, thy breakers rolling bright, And all thy dim horizon speck'd with sails of moving light. Oft on thy wonders may I gaze, oft on thy waters ride, Oft with no timid arm essay thy dark transparent tide, Oft may thy sound be in my dreams, far inland though I be, For health and hope are in thy song, thou deep fullvoiced sea! BOW-MEETING SONG. By yon castle wall, 'mid the breezes of morning, The genius of Cambria stray'd pensive and slow; The oak-wreath was wither'd her tresses adorning, And the wind through its leaves sigh'd its murmur of woe. She gazed on her mountains with filial devotion, She gazed on her Dee as he roll'd to the ocean,— And, “Cambria! poor Cambria!” she cried with emotion, “Thou yet hast thy country, thy harp, and thy bow!” “Sweep on, thou proud stream, with thy billows all hoary; As proudly my warriors have rush'd on the foe; But feeble and faint is the sound of their glory, For time, like thy tide, has its ebb and its flow. Ev'n now, while I watch thee, thy beauties are fading; The sands and the shallows thy course are invading; Where the sail swept the surges the sea-bird is wading; And thus hath it fared with the land of the bow! “Smile, smile ye dear hills, 'mid your woods and your flowers, Whose heather lies dark in the morn's dewy glow! A time must await you of tempest and showers, An autumn of mist, and a winter of snow! For me, though the whirlwind has shiver'd and cleft me, Of wealth and of empire the stranger bereft me, Yet Saxon,—proud Saxon,—thy fury has left me Worth, valour, and beauty, the harp and the bow! “Ye towers, on whose rampire, all ruin'd and riven, The wall-flower and woodbine so lavishly blow; I have seen when your banner waved broad to the Heaven, And kings found your faith a defence from the foe; Oh loyal in grief, and in danger unshaken, For ages still true, though for ages forsaken, Yet, Cambria, thy heart may to gladness awaken, Since thy monarch has smiled on the harp and the bow!” ON CROSSING THE RANGE OF HIGH LAND BETWEEN STONE AND MARKET DRAYTON, JAN. 4, 1820. Dread inmate of the northern zone! And hast thou left thine ancient throne On Zembla's hills of snow, Thine arrowy sleet and icy shower On us, unbroken to thy power, With reckless hand to throw? Enough for us thy milder sway, The yellow mist, the shorten'd day, The sun of fainter glow; The frost which scarce our verdure felt, And rarely seen, and but to melt The wreath of transient snow. I met thee once by Volga's tide, Nor fear'd thy terrors to abide On Valdai's sullen brow; But little thought on English down Thy darkest wrath and fiercest frown So soon again to know. Oh for my schube's accustom'd fold, Which then, in ample bear-skin roll'd, Defied thy dread career! Oh for the cap of sable warm, Which guarded then from pinching harm My nose, and cheek, and ear! Mine old kibitka, where art thou? Gloves, boots, peketch,—I need ye now,— Sold to a Lemberg Jew! In single vest, on Ashley Heath, My shrinking heart is cold as death, And fingers ghastly blue! BALLAD. I “Oh, captain of the Moorish hold, Unbar thy gates to me, And I will give thee gems and gold, To set Fernando free. For I a sacred oath have plight A pilgrim to remain, Till I return with Lara's knight, The noblest knight of Spain.” II “Fond Christian youth,” the captain said, “Thy suit is soon denied, Fernando loves a Moorish maid, And will with us abide. Renounc'd is every Christian rite, The turban he hath ta'en, And Lara thus hath lost her knight, The boldest knight of Spain.” III Pale, marble pale, the pilgrim turn'd, A cold and deadly dye; Then in his cheeks the blushes burn'd, And anger in his eye. (From forth his cowl a ringlet bright Fell down of golden grain,) “Base Moor! to slander Lara's knight, The boldest knight of Spain! IV “Go, look on Lugo's gory field! Go look on Tayo's tide! Can ye forget the red-cross shield, That all your host defied? Alhama's warriors turn'd to flight, Granada's sultan slain, Attest the worth of Lara's knight, The boldest knight of Spain!” V “By Allah, yea!” with eyes of fire The lordly paynim said, “Granada's sultan was my sire, Who fell by Lara's blade; And tho' thy gold were forty fold, The ransom were but vain To purchase back thy Christian knight, The boldest knight of Spain.” VI “Ah, Moor! the life that once is shed No vengeance can repay; And who can number up the dead That fall in battle fray? Thyself in many a manly fight Hast many a father slain; Then rage not thus 'gainst Lara's knight, The boldest knight of Spain.” VII “And who art thou, whose pilgrim vest Thy beauties ill may shroud; The locks of gold, the heaving breast, A moon beneath a cloud?— Wilt thou our Moorish creed recite, And here with me remain? He may depart,—that captive knight, The conquer'd knight of Spain.” VIII “Ah, speak not so!” with voice of woe, The shuddering stranger cried; “Another creed I may not know, Nor live another's bride! Fernando's wife may yield her life, But not her honour stain, To loose the bonds of Lara's knight, The noblest knight of Spain!” IX “And know'st thou, then, how hard a doom Thy husband yet may bear? The fetter'd limbs, the living tomb, The damp and noisome air? In lonely cave, and void of light, To drag a helpless chain, Thy pride condemns the Christian knight, The prop and pride of Spain!” X “Oh that within that dungeon's gloom His sorrows I might share, And cheer him in that living tomb, With love, and hope, and prayer! But still the faith I once have plight Unbroken must remain, And God will help the captive knight, And plead the cause of Spain!” XI “And deem'st thou from the Moorish hold In safety to retire, Whose locks outshine Arabia's gold, Whose eyes the diamond's fire!” She drew a poniard small and bright, And spake in calm disdain, “He taught me how, my Christian knight, To guard the faith of Spain!” XII The drawbridge falls! with loud alarm The clashing portals fly! She bar'd her breast, she rais'd her arms, And knelt, in act to die! But ah, the thrill of wild delight That shot through every vein! He stood before her,—Lara's knight, The noblest knight of Spain! SYMPATHY. A knight and a lady once met in a grove, While each was in quest of a fugitive love; A river ran mournfully murmuring by, And they wept in its waters for sympathy. “Oh, never was knight such a sorrow that bore!” “Oh, never was maid so deserted before!” “From life and its woes let us instantly fly, And jump in together for company!” They search'd for an eddy that suited the deed, But here was a bramble, and there was a weed; “How tiresome it is!” said the fair with a sigh; So they sat down to rest them in company. They gaz'd on each other, the maid and the knight; How fair was her form, and how goodly his height! “One mournful embrace!” sobb'd the youth, “ere we die!” So kissing and crying kept company. “Oh, had I but lov'd such an angel as you!” “Oh, had but my swain been a quarter as true!” “To miss such perfection how blinded was I!” Sure now they were excellent company! At length spoke the lass, 'twixt a smile and a tear, “The weather is cold for a watery bier; When summer returns we may easily die, Till then let us sorrow in company.” LINES WRITTEN TO A MARCH COMPOSED IN IMITATION OF A MILITARY BAND. I see them on their winding way, Above their ranks the moon-beams play, And nearer yet, and yet more near, The martial chorus strikes the ear. They're lost and gone,—the moon is past, The wood's dark shade is o'er them cast, And fainter, fainter, fainter still, The dim march warbles up the hill. Again, again,—the pealing drum, The clashing horn—they come! they come! And lofty deeds and daring high, Blend with their notes of victory. Forth, forth, and meet them on their way, The trampling hoof brooks no delay; The thrilling fife, the pealing drum, How late—but oh! how lov'd they come! THE WELL OF OBLIVION. SUGGESTED BY A STANZA IN THE ORLANDO INNAMORATO OF BOIARDO. There is, they say, a secret well, In Ardennes' forest grey, Whose waters boast a numbing spell, That memory must obey. Who tastes the rill so cool and calm In passion's wild distress, Their breasts imbibe the sullen balm Of deep forgetfulness. And many a maid has sought the grove, And bow'd beside the wave; But few have borne to lose the love That wore them to the grave. No! by these tears, whose ceaseless smart My reason chides in vain; By all the secret of a heart That never told its pain; By all the walks that once were dear, Beneath the green-wood bough; By all the songs that sooth'd his ear Who will not listen now; By every dream of hope gone by That haunts my slumber yet,— A love-sick heart may long to die, But never to forget! THE ORACLE. IMITATED FROM THE GREEK. To Phœbus' shrine three youths of fame, A wrestler, boxer, racer came, And begg'd the Delphic god to say, Which from the next Olympic game Should bear the envied wreath away? And thus the Oracle decided:— “Be victors all, brave youths, this day, Each in your several arts!—provided That none outstrip the racers' feet, None at his trade the boxer beat, None in the dust the wrestler lay!” TO A WELCH AIR, “CODIAD YR HYDOD.” Why that neck of marble whiteness, Why that hair of sunny brightness, Form of perfect mold, Why those fringed eyelids screening Lights of love and liquid meaning, While the heart is cold? Shame on her whose pride or malice With a lover's anguish dallies, Scorn our scatter'd reason rallies, Thou shalt mourn thy tyrant sallies, Ere that thou art old—young Alice, Ere that thou art old! THE GROUND SWELL. How soft the shades of evening creep O'er yonder dewy lea, Where balmy winds have lull'd to sleep The tenants of the tree. No wandering breeze is here to sweep, In shadowy ripple o'er the deep, Yet swells the heaving sea! How calm the sky! rest, ocean, rest, From storm and ruffle free, Calm as the image on thy breast Of her that governs thee! And yet beneath the moon's mild reign Thy broad breast heaves as one in pain, Thou dark and silent sea. There are whom fortune vainly woes With all her pageantry, Whom every flattering bliss pursues, Yet still they fare like thee; The spell is laid within their mind, Least wretched then when most resigned, Their hearts throb silently! TRANSLATED FROM THE GERMAN. Take here the tender harp again, O Muse! which thou hast lent to me; I wake no more the joyous strain To youthful love or social glee. Forgive the weak and sickly shell That could so ill my soul express; What most I wished I durst not tell And chose my themes from idleness. Oft when I told of peace and pleasure, I marked the hostile sabre shine; And water, doled in scanty measure, I drank, who wont to sing of wine. Might peace, might love's auspicious fire But gild at last my closing day, Then Goddess, then return the lyre To wake perhaps a loftier lay. BOW-MEETING SONG. We find it well observ'd by an ancient learned Rabbin, The man was raving mad who first to sea would go, Who would change the tented field for the quarter-deck and cabin, And the songs of blooming beauty for a Yo! heave oh! Yet since your bard is bent to try The fervours of an eastern sky, And where, across the tepid main, Arabian breezes blow, While yet the northern gale Fans his cheek and swells his sail, Accept his latest tribute to the British bow! Dear scenes of unrepented joy, our nature's best physician, Can all Golconda's glittering mines so pure a bliss bestow? Oh deem not that for sordid gold he left you, or ambition, Or shall e'er forget your peaceful charms 'mid India's brightest glow! Oft, oft, will he be telling Of the glades of Nant-y-bellin, Of the lilies and the roses that in Gwersylt blow, Oft, oft recall the snow-white wall of yonder ancient dwelling, Whose lords, in Saxon Edwin's days, so nobly bent the bow! Oh when the dog-star rides on high, how oft shall memory wander Where yonder oaks their aged arms 'mid blended poplars throw; And hollies join their glossy shade, and the brook with cool meander Steals, like a silver snake, through the copse below! Where many a mild and matron grace Adorn the mother's gentle face, And ? in beauteous garland blow, And proved in many a martial fray Their sire holds sylvan holiday, And flings his well worn sword away To bend the British bow! The bard is gone, and other bards shall wake the call of pleasure That prompts to beauty's lip the smile, and lends her cheek its glow, And strike the sylvan lyre to a louder, livelier measure, And wear the oaken wreath, which he must now forego! But yet, though many a sweeter song Shall float th' applauding tent along, And many a friendly health to the Sons of Genius flow, Forget not them, who, doomed to part, Will keep engraven on their heart The sons and the daughters of the British bow! FROM THE GULISTAN. INSCRIPTION OVER THE ARCHED ALCOVE OF FERIDOON'S HALL. Brother! know the world deceiveth! Trust on Him who safely giveth! Fix not on the world thy trust, She feeds us—but she turns to dust, And the bare earth or kingly throne Alike may serve to die upon! FROM THE GULISTAN. The man who leaveth life behind, May well and boldly speak his mind: Where flight is none from battle field, We blithely snatch the sword and shield; Where hope is past, and hate is strong, The wretch's tongue is sharp and long; Myself have seen, in wild despair, The feeble cat the mastiff tear. FROM THE GULISTAN. Who the silent man can prize, If a fool he be or wise?k his mind: Yet, though lonely seem the wood, Therein may lurk the beast of blood. Often bashful looks conceal Tongue of fire and heart of steel. And deem not thou, in forest grey, Every dappled skin thy prey; Lest thou rouse, with luckless spear, The tiger for the fallow deer! IMITATION OF AN ODE BY KOODRUT. Ambition's voice was in my ear, she whisper'd yesterday, “How goodly is the land of Room, how wide the Russian sway! How blest to conquer either realm, and dwell through life to come, Lull'd by the harp's melodious string, cheer'd by the northern drum!” But Wisdom heard; “Oh youth,” she said, “in passion's fetter tied, O come and see a sight with me shall cure thee of thy pride!” She led me to a lonely dell, a sad and shady ground, Where many an ancient sepulchre gleam'd in the moonshine round. And “Here Secunder sleeps,” she cried; “this is his rival's stone; And here the mighty chief reclines who rear'd the Median throne. Enquire of these, doth ought of all their ancient pomp remain Save late regret and bitter tears for ever and in vain? Return, return, and in thy heart engraven keep my lore; The lesser wealth, the lighter load,—small blame betides the poor.” TRANSLATION OF A SONNET, BY THE LATE NAWAB OF OUDE, ASUF UD DOWLA. In those eyes that glisten as in pity for my pain, Are they gems, or only dew drops? Can they, will they long remain? Why the strength of tyrant beauty thus, with seeming ruth, restrain? Better breathe my last before thee, than in lingering grief remain. To yon planet, Fate has given every month to wax and wane; And—thy world of blushing brightness,—can it, will it long remain? Asuf! why in mournful numbers, of thine absence thus complain, Chance had joined us, chance has parted!—nought on earth can long remain. In the world may'st thou, beloved! live exempt from grief and pain. On my lips the breath is fleeting—can it, will it long remain? LINES ADDRESSED TO MRS. HEBER. If thou wert by my side, my love, How fast would evening fail In green Bengala's palmy grove Listening the nightingale! If thou, my love, wert by my side, My babies at my knee, How gaily would our pinnace glide O'er Gunga's mimic sea! I miss thee at the dawning gray, When, on our deck reclined, In careless ease my limbs I lay And woo the cooler wind. I miss thee when by Gunga's stream My twilight steps I guide, But most beneath the lamp's pale beam I miss thee from my side. I spread my books, my pencil try The lingering noon to cheer, But miss thy kind approving eye, Thy meek attentive ear. But when of morn and eve the star Beholds me on my knee, I feel, though thou art distant far, Thy prayers ascend for me. Then on! then on! where duty leads, My course be onward still, O'er broad Hindostan's sultry mead, O'er bleak Almorah's hill. That course, nor Delhi's kingly gates, Nor wild Malwah detain; For sweet the bliss us both awaits By yonder western main. Thy towers, Bombay, gleam bright they say, Across the dark blue sea, But ne'er were hearts so light and gay As then shall meet in thee! AN EVENING WALK IN BENGAL. Our task is done! on Gunga's breast The sun is sinking down to rest; And, moored beneath the tamarind bough, Our bark has found its harbour now. With furled sail and painted side Behold the tiny frigate ride. Upon her deck, 'mid charcoal gleams, The Moslem's savoury supper steams; While all apart, beneath the wood, The Hindoo cooks his simpler food. Come walk with me the jungle through. If yonder hunter told us true, Far off, in desert dank and rude, The tiger holds its solitude; Nor (taught by recent harm to shun The thunders of the English gun) A dreadful guest but rarely seen, Returns to scare the village green. Come boldly on! no venom'd snake Can shelter in so cool a brake. Child of the Sun! he loves to lie 'Midst Nature's embers, parch'd and dry, Where o'er some tower in ruin laid, The peepul spreads its haunted shade; Or round a tomb his scales to wreathe Fit warder in the gate of Death. Come on! yet pause! Behold us now Beneath the bamboo's arched bough, Where, gemming oft that sacred gloom Glows the geranium's scarlet bloom A shrub whose deep scarlet flowers very much resemble the geranium, and thence called the Indian geranium., And winds our path through many a bower Of fragrant tree and giant flower; The ceiba's crimson pomp displayed O'er the broad plantain's humbler shade, And dusk anana's prickly glade; While o'er the brake, so wild and fair The betel waves his crest in air. With pendant train and rushing wings Aloft the gorgeous peacock springs; And he, the bird of hundred dyes The Mucharunga., Whose plumes the dames of Ava prize. So rich a shade, so green a sod Our English fairies never trod! Yet who in Indian bowers has stood, But thought on England's “good green wood!” And bless'd, beneath the palmy shade, Her hazel and her hawthorn glade, And breath'd a prayer, (how oft in vain!) To gaze upon her oaks again? A truce to thought,—the jackall's cry Resounds like sylvan revelry; And through the trees yon failing ray Will scantly serve to guide our way. Yet mark, as fade the upper skies, Each thicket opes ten thousand eyes. Before, beside us, and above, The fire-fly lights his lamp of love, Retreating, chasing, sinking, soaring The darkness of the copse exploring, While to this cooler air confest, The broad Dhatura bares her breast, Of fragrant scent and virgin white, A pearl around the locks of night! Still as we pass, in softened hum Along the breezy alleys come The village song, the horn, the drum. Still as we pass, from bush and briar, The shrill Cigala strikes his lyre; And, what is she whose liquid strain Thrills through yon copse of sugar-cane? I know that soul-entrancing swell, It is—it must be—Philomel! Enough, enough, the rustling trees Announce a shower upon the breeze, The flashes of the summer sky Assume a deeper, ruddier dye; Yon lamp that trembles on the stream, From forth our cabin sheds its beam; And we must early sleep, to find Betimes the morning's healthy wind. But oh! with thankful hearts confess E'en here there may be happiness; And He, the bounteous Sire, has given His peace on earth,—his hope of Heaven!</field>
   </doc>
</add>