<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Jones, Henry, 1721-1770</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Jones, Henry, 1721-1770</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">jones henry 1721 1770</field>
      <field name="author_text">Jones, Henry, 1721-1770</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1750's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_2.1373.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">1751</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:465465</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">An epistle to the Right Honourable The Earl of Orrery ; Occasion'd by reading his Lordship's Translation of Pliny's Epistles. By Henry Jones</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">An epistle to the Right Honourable The Earl of Orrery ; Occasion'd by reading his Lordship's Translation of Pliny's Epistles. By Henry Jones</field>
      <field name="title_facet">epistle to the right honourable the earl of orrery</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">epistle to the right honourable the earl of orrery</field>
      <field name="title_text">An epistle to the Right Honourable The Earl of Orrery ; Occasion'd by reading his Lordship's Translation of Pliny's Epistles. By Henry Jones</field>
      <field name="year_display">1751</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1751</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1751</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465465&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465465&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Jones, Henry, 1721-1770&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;jones henry 1721 1770&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;An epistle to the Right Honourable The Earl of Orrery ; Occasion'd by reading his Lordship's Translation of Pliny's Epistles. By Henry Jones&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;epistle to the right honourable the earl of orrery&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1751&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1751&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Jones, Henry&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1721&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1770&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;An epistle to the Right Honourable The Earl of Orrery&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Occasion'd by reading his Lordship's Translation of Pliny's Epistles. By Henry Jones&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for William Owen, [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1751&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp1978&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;15 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;An epistle to the Right Honourable The Earl of Orrery&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Occasion'd by reading his Lordship's Translation of Pliny's Epistles. By Henry Jones&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 15 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">AN EPISTLE To the Right Honourable The Earl of ORRERY, Occasion'd by reading his Lordship's Translation of Pliny's Epistles. Whilst all to Reason make such strong Pretence, Impartial Reason, and superior Sense, How few, my Lord, to her Decrees submit, Who'd mend our Morals, or who'd form our Wit! Conceit and Judgment work such different Ways, What the weak Head should hide, the Heart betrays. Tho' Truth unchanging, like the Pole, is seen, Such Mists and Vapours often rise between, Such Rocks and Shelves, in fansy'd Forms appear, When Pride looks out, and Passion's Arm would steer: Affrighted Candour quits the Helm with Pain, And Judgment points, and Virtue toils in vain. Self-love, in Man, wise Nature's Purpose shews, Springs in the Soul, and with his Reason grows; Awakes each Movement of th'exerted Will; His Guide thro' Dangers, and his Guard from Ill: Yet taught by Custom's Hand too oft contends With Reason's Dictates, and defeats her Ends. While Passion pours on Truth her glowing Tints, And Fancy forms, and Prejudice imprints Each false Resemblance on the yielding Heart, Hence Habit sways, and Error acts her Part. Opinions hence their partial Progress take, By Pride impell'd, and Reason's Line forsake; Th'unerring Line from which they widely stray, As Fraud excites, or Fashion leads the Way: Till lost at length in frantic Rounds they run, And Wisdom's Walk, and Virtue's Footsteps shun. Indulgent Nature left her Sons of yore, The crystal Spring, and Earth's spontaneous Store, Which on her bounteous Lap abundant grows, And from her genial Breast forever flows: The blameless Banquet Wisdom spreads out still, To feast Reflection, and to temper Will. No bloated Rage from such Repasts could rise To waste th'afflicted Earth, and scale the Skies. No Lust of Lucre from such Fumes was wrought, No Vicc provok'd, no Conscience sold or bought. Ambition there could claim no noxious Place, Nor vile Hypocrisy with borrow'd Face; No false Opinion Reason's Robe put on; For Truth and Nature were from first but one. Still far remov'd from all outrageous Strife, The rapid Whirls and boisterous Gales of Life, Let peaceful Science to those Shades retreat, Where Wisdom's Wish, and Nature's Welcome meet, Above the gilded Baits Ambition strews The Smiles of Friendship, and the Frowns of Foes. Which tempt, or threat the virtuous Mind to fall, From Honour's sacred Height at Folly's Call; Where Genius, Reason, Virtue, all combine, To kindle Stanhope's raptur'd Thought, and thine; Where ev'ry Muse, and ev'ry Grace agree, To smile on him, rejoyc'd, rejoyc'd, on thee. Illustrious Pair from public Scenes retir'd, Yet still with Zeal, with public Zeal inspir'd, Your fervent Souls, like Guardian-Angels grieve, And mourn those Virtues which ye can't relieve. The Heav'n-touch'd Heart, the Thought refin'd and clear, To sacred Solitude, to Goodness dear, At Wisdom's Beck has ever sought the Shade, Where unreproach'd Delight with Science play'd, Where Truth extends her disintangled Clue, And all her richest Treasures spreads to View, Where Judgment holds with steady Hand the Scales In undisturb'd Repose from Passions Gales. And where, would Heav'n indulge my Wish, let me, On sacred Wisdom wait, O Boyle! and thee. Seclude me Fate from what true Joys detest, What Fools are fond of, and what Knaves infest, The Paths of Perfidy, the Scenes of Strife, The Walks of Villains, and the Snares of Life. Where plain Sincerity no Safety finds, Nor fair Integrity, nor Justice binds; Where Honesty too oft is held Disgrace, And blushing Innocence must hide her Face. Far, far embosom'd in some howling Waste, By raging Storms and hideous Wilds embrac'd. With Savage Inmates, whose ingenuous Roar Proclaim their honest Wants, and seek no more. Let my secreted Lot be fix'd by Fate, From Rapine shielded in this dread Retreat. Thou sacred Muse, to whom my Fancy flies, O grant my Wishes, what the World denies. In spight of Fortune, thou can'st Comfort bring, And waft me Cordials on thy kindly Wing. Celestial Maid, in whom my Soul delights, Who smooths my anxious Days, and chears my Nights, O lead me onward to some ancient Sage, And let me scan the Greek and Roman Page. But that, alas! penurious Fate denies, I ne'er on Latian Lays shall feast those Eyes; Never shall Plato's golden Mines explore, Nor turn immortal Tully's Treasures o'er: Depriv'd their splendid Beams, I mourn in Night, And from Reflection only feel their Light. Yet even thence some gladsome Radience springs, Since Homer's Muse, in British Homer sings. Since Pliny's Patriot-Soul my Breast expands, Shap'd and adorn'd by your illustrious Hands. O Boyle! the Roman Fire transmitted Shines, With added Vigour, in your easy Lines: Each manly Thought with native Fervour flows, And English Grace in ev'ry Period glows. The polish'd Text in you no Copy seems, But all your Soul thro' ev'ry Sentence beams. The moral Rectitude by Courts refin'd; The simple Dignity, the Power of Mind; The finish'd Taste, the unaffected Air, Th'extensive Knowledge, and the Judgment clear; The Aspect mild, the condescending Mein, At Distance sought, and lov'd as soon as seen. O dear to Fame, to virtuous Fame most dear; Who gives to Titles, more than Titles bear; Who build'st high Worth on Honour's blameless Plan, And o'er th'exalted Station lifts the Man. How few like thee, by pure Ambition fir'd, Can tread the toilsome Path to Truth untir'd; Can climb the Cliffs where Virtue's Harvests grow The rocky Cliffs which fright the Crowd below.— Up Learning's Steep your Father's Steps you trace, With equal Strength, and vindicate your Race. Whilst plac'd aloft in your paternal Hand, Your earliest Hope, your blooming Charles shall stand, On Worth's high Top, his bounding Heart shall rise, To Wisdom's Crown, and Virtue's glorious Prize. The Prize held up by Fame, in Merits View, To tempt the many, but reward the few. O Youth to Greatness and to Goodness born! At once to serve your Country, and adorn; Preserve inviolate the Gem divine, The sacred Pledge in your illustrious Line; The bright Inheritance your Fathers bless'd, From them descending, and by you possess'd: With still encreasing Splendor hand it down, To latest Years, the Test of true Renown. To latest Years untouch'd by Time's foul Soil, To grace Humanity, and mark a Boyle. He comes, he comes, my Lord! his Bosom burns, And ev'ry Virtue warms his Breast by Turns. He feels th'implanted Precept vig'rous Shoot, Spring in the Soul, and in the Heart take Root. The rip'ning Growth see grateful Time extend, To thank the Sage, the Father, and the Friend; T'enrich with spreading Odours all the Plain, And tell the World your Work was not in vain. Amidst the perfect Joy your Portion lends Of Knowledge, Virtue, Wealth, and faithful Friends. Let my intruding Verse, my Lord, draw nigh (Which hates to flatter, and which scorns to lie;) My grateful Verse has long your Notice sought, To honest Trifles turn awhile your Thought. I seek no higher Rank, no Critic's Claim, And only eccho what I hear from Fame, In circling Sounds, which wide extended swell What Fame asserts, and Stanhope bade me tell: Whose awful Tongue pronounc'd the just Decree, Whose Hand compos'd the Wreath he sent by me; The much applauding Wreath by Merit won, Which Diffidence declin'd, but Worth put on; O nobly earn'd, O well distinguish'd Praise! Your Pliny gain'd not more in Pliny's Days. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>