<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Bowden, Samuel</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Bowden, Samuel</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">bowden samuel</field>
      <field name="author_text">Bowden, Samuel</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1730's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_2.1519.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1733&amp;#8211;1735</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:465555</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Greek, Modern (1453- )</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Poetical essays on Several Occasions ; By Samuel Bowden</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Poetical essays on Several Occasions ; By Samuel Bowden</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poetical essays on several occasions</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poetical essays on several occasions</field>
      <field name="title_text">Poetical essays on Several Occasions ; By Samuel Bowden</field>
      <field name="year_display">1733–1735</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1733</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1733</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465555&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465555&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Bowden, Samuel&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;bowden samuel&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Poetical essays on Several Occasions ; By Samuel Bowden&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poetical essays on several occasions&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1733–1735&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1733&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Bowden, Samuel&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poetical essays on Several Occasions&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By Samuel Bowden&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for J. Pemberton ... and C. Davis [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1733–1735&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0505&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;gre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;2 v.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poetical essays on Several Occasions&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By Samuel Bowden&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 331 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">VOL. I. Fir'd at first Sight with what the Muse imparts, In fearless Youth we tempt the Heights of Arts; Good Nature and Good Sense must ever join, To err is human, to forgive divine. Pope's Essay on Criticism. To the Right Honourable THOMAS, Lord Viscount Weymouth, AND Baron of Warminster, THE RETREAT: OR Contemplative Solitude. Inscribed to the Right Honourable the Countess of HERTFORD. Non est quod contemnas hoc studendi genus. Mirum est ut animus à recessu agresti, motuque corporis excitetur. Jam undiq; silvæ &amp; solitudo, ipsumq; silentium magna cogitationis incitamenta sunt. Experieris non Dianam magis montibus, quam Minervam inerrare. Plin. Epist. Lib. 1. Come, all ye sable, solitary Train, Offspring of Nature, or the Poet's Brain; Come, follow me to yonder gloomy Grove, Or o'er the desert Mountain with me rove; Come, and be Witness to a Hermit's Plaints; Come, slow, and silent, as the Shades of Saints; While, tir'd with human Sounds, and vulgar Sport, The Buzz of Crouds, and Follies of a Court, I trace the deep Recesses of the Mind, And, charm'd with Nature, leave the World behind. Whilst I to you shall sing, the Wilds among, Hertford will listen, and approve the Song, Her Presence makes the rudest Wilds polite, Mute Groves grow tuneful, and dark Grotto's bright, Gives Bloom to Winter, Elegance to Cells, And from the Desert Solitude dispells. Farewel, ye Towns, the Theatres of Noise, Empty Amusements, and fantastic Joys; Adieu to all the Pageantry of State, The vain Parade, and Splendor of the Great. To rural Scenes, to rural Sweets I fly, And view the Country with a ravish'd Eye: And, ere the tall majestic Trees appear, The Chorus of the Woods, in Fancy, hear; The painted Natives are already seen, And visionary Fields, bedeck'd with Green. Thus pines the Mariner, by Tempests tost, Impatient, lingring on some barren Coast, While happier Climes, rich Ganges, or Peru, Or spicy Isles are imag'd to his View. Now, midst unfolding Lawns, entranc'd, I stand, Struck with unclouded Skies, and verdant Land, Within the Breast ecstatic Transport reigns, So thrills soft Musick thro' the tingling Veins. The colour'd Fields, which in gay Landskips rise, Reveal Ten Thousand Beauties to my Eyes, Where various Nature, in Profusion, pours Embroider'd Robes, pure Sweets, and painted Bowers: On ev'ry Side Mosaic Meads are seen, Inlaid with Flowers, enamell'd o'er with Green. Sometimes, more studious, with attentive Ears, I catch the tuneful Rhetoric of the Spheres, Which, o'er the still Expanse, incessant speaks, And from the vocal Hills Pindaric breaks. Here, cleans'd in wholsome Air, from Dust and Smoke, I hail the Mountains, and the Groves invoke. So freed from Dregs of pestilential Air, The tainted Turks for distant Skies prepare; So were polluted Jews of old made pure, Ere they approach'd the consecrated Door. Welcome, blest Grove! and no less sacred Shade, By Silence hallow'd, and for Sages made. Welcome, blest Freedom! here the Goddess dwells, With simple Majesty, in peaceful Cells. Oft banish'd from the Plains by barbarous Sports, And tir'd with tinsel Pomp, and guilty Courts, Affrighted, here she quietly resorts. No glitt'ring Gems, no Tyrian Robes she wears, But great, without an Equipage, appears: Pensive, some Tears she sheds, and looks behind, With sorrowing Eyes, sad Exile of Mankind! So the brave Roman, banish'd from his Home, Pitying, look'd back, and wept o'er Orphan Rome. These are the silent Seats of Love and Rest, By Men forsook, but once by Gods possess'd. Here, slighted Poets have their Lawrels found, And seen themselves with Nature's Trophies crown'd, In Poverty and Want, here met Repose, Sung to the Woods, and smil'd amidst their Woes. 'Twas here, the antient Godlike Heroes dwelt; Here, the first Bards their Inspiration felt: In Shades, Apollo's Muse, and Orpheus sung; And Grecian Groves with learned Echoes rung; Each Field was throng'd with Academic Youths; Each Hill resounded with Athenian Truths; To Harps and Odes the vocal Riv'lets flow'd, And on each Mountain dwelt some Genial God. To British Bards the Woods were sacred too, Where holy Druids liv'd, conceal'd from View; Solemn their Shades, and from the hallow'd Oak, With mystic Sound, tremendous Accents broke. In such Esteem were rural Scenes of old, Now chang'd for Greatness, and despis'd for Gold! Gold, thou false Idol of a sordid Age, For thee, what Vot'ry's fight, what Kingdoms rage? For thee, what Pray'rs ascend, what constant Vows? To thee the Merchant sighs, the Statesman bows: All Sects unite, and worship at thy Shrine, And own thy glitt'ring Altar all-divine. But thus revolving, whither do I rove? Lost in the grateful Horrors of the Grove; In Love with Error, thro' the Vistas stray, Pleas'd, in such lonely Wilds, to lose my Way, Now on some flow'ry Bank I rest my Head; On high, the Trees a gloomy Covering spread; Only some Rays of Light break in between, And Spots of Splendor beautify the Green. So, thro' the sable Canopy of Night, The Stars appear in Points of glowing Light. 'Tis here, the Soul a heav'nly Calm enjoys, No irksome Thought the still Composure cloys: In soft Tranquility declines the Day, And Time, on Wings of Quiet, glides away. Thus soars the Bird of Jove, serene on high, And, pois'd with even Pinions, sweeps the Sky. Now, weary of the dark, o'ercasted Scene, New Pleasure rises from the open Plain; Where gilded Mountains, and the azure Sky, With sunny Prospects, gleaming, glad the Eye. Here, nods the Brow of some romantic Hill, Enthron'd in Trees, while all around is still; All but the Murmurs of far falling Streams, Lulling soft Slumbers, and Poetic Dreams. The peaceful lowing Herds stand mute around, Their solid Necks reclining to the Ground; Or half digested Food, with steady View, And pensive Posture, ruminating chew. O happy Race, by Instinct only led, To Good unerring, by kind Nature bred: Nature whose constant Light points out their Way: But, bless'd with Reason, we politely stray! Fast by, a slow, deep Stream in Silence flows, On whose cool Banks the sable Willow grows, Spreading afar a melancholy Scene, And with dark Shadows black'ning all the Green. Now barren Wastes invite a wilder Lay, Where savage Beasts have mark'd the lonely Way, Where huge deformed Rocks salute the Eye, And pendant Herbs wave near the shaded Sky. And here some dreary Cave, with Aspect rude, Allures the Mind to pleasing Solitude, Hung with the Ivy's venerable Wreaths, Where the hoarse Raven nightly Accents breathes; Where humid Hart's-tongue flourishes alone; And silver Moss creeps o'er the dewy Stone; While falling Drops the silent Moments mark, And mock the Adder, hissing in the Dark. Oft in the Veil, and solemn Cope of Night, The Moon's pale Orb appears with trembling Light. Hail, Queen of half the Year! whose silver Chair, In clouded State, majestic gilds the Air. The lonely Bird to his own Echo hoots, And, thro' the Gloom, desponding Accents shoots. Sweet, afar off, the pensive Nightingale To vocal Woods tells her lamenting Tale. Oh, blissful Bird! to live secure alone, And to the Trees and Stars repeat thy Moan: Wisest and sweeest of the tuneful Throng, Nature is only Witness to thy Song: What others shun is thy contented Choice, Nor Noise, nor Envy, interrupt thy Voice; Pleas'd with thy warbling, I my Lays resign, Forsake the bright Assembly of the Nine, And leave their Musick, heav'nly Bird! for thine. THE First Pastoral of VIRGIL; OR, Tityrus and Melibœus. MEL. In Shades reclin'd, you, Tityrus, waste your Hours, And sylvan Songs compose in beechen Bow'rs: While we, far wandring, fly our rural Seats, Our native Haunts we fly, our dear Retreats: You, Tityrus, tune your oaten Pipes at Ease, And Amaryllis warble thro' the Trees. TIT. Some God, for sure he merits Godlike Praise; To me, my Friend, indulg'd these Halcyon Days. For him the Fairest of the fleecy Train, Fresh from the Fold, shall oft his Altars stain; He bad these Herds, you see, securely stray, And, as I fancy'd, frame my rustic Lay. MEL. I envy not, but wonder you remain Thus blest, when Desolation fills our Plain. See, these few Goats I drive with aking Mind, This, lagging, lead, her Young just left behind; Just yean'd, she left them on the thorny Rock, Ah me! her Twins, the Pride of all the Flock; Oft would my boding Breast these Ills foretell, When on our riven Trees red Lightning fell; And oft prophetic, from the hollow Oak, Disastrous Ravens hoarsely us'd to croke. But, Tityrus, who's this Pow'r you thus invoke? TIT. Once, Meliboeus, like a witless Clown, I fancy'd Rome but like our Mantua's Town, Where we, the Shepherds of the neighbouring Plain, To Market us'd to drive the fleecy Train. So Whelps and Kids their Sires and Dams confess, And greater Things are copy'd in the less; But she, sublimely fair, as far exceeds Our Villages, as Cypress humble Weeds. MEL. What urgent Business hurry'd you to Town? TIT. 'Twas Freedom, which at last look'd smiling down On my gray wintry Locks, her gladsome Reign Smil'd down at last, and rais'd a sluggish Swain. Long since my Galatea pleas'd no more, Now Amaryllis sways, as she before: I'll own, while held with Galatea's Charms, I valu'd not my Freedom, nor my Farms. Tho' still my Sheep on smoaking Altars hung, And every Day my creeking Presses wrung The purest Cheese for that ungrateful Town, Still I came empty Home, still Fate would frown. MEL. I often wonder'd that, with silent Sigh, Sad Amaryllis would invoke the Sky, And why ripe Apples linger'd on the Tree: But oh! I find 'twas, Tityrus, for thee, For thee the pitying Pine Trees droop'd their Head; The Streams and Floods complain'd when thou wast fled. TIT. What more could I, my Freedom to restore? What greater Names, what greater Pow'rs implore? There I beheld that Youth of Godlike Fame, To whom, each circling Month, our Altars flame: Soon as my Pray'r he heard, he kindly spoke, Still feed your Flocks, ye Swains, your Oxen yoke. MEL. Hail! bless'd old Man! then safe is your Retreat, Tho' small the Spot, Contentment makes it great; While ragged Rocks, rude Heaths of furzy Ground, And swampy Moors, look wasteful all around. With no strange Herbs your teeming Flocks shall faint, Nor your chaste Herds infectious Murrain taint. Hail! bless'd old Man! here stretch'd along the Shade, For you the bubbling Brooks shall gild the Glade; And, with sonorous Charm, Sicilian Bees, Fast by, extract the Sweets of Willow Trees, O'er flow'ry Walks, with soaring Murmurs sweep, And with their Musick lull delightful Sleep. High o'er the shaded Rock, the Pruner stand, And with glad Voice awake the silent Land; While Turtles from the Elm, with plaintive Tone, And Doves, your fond Amusement, muttering, moan. TIT. The nimble Hinds shall first in Æther feed, And Seas, retiring, leave their scaly Breed; First, Parthians, wandring from their Seats, shall drink, Exchanging Climes, at distant Arar's Brink; At Tygris' Streams the banish'd Germans rest, Ere his lov'd Image vanish from my Breast. MEL. But exil'd we must other Realms explore, Range Scythian Wilds, or bask on Afric's Shore; Be toss'd on Candia, where Oaxis rolls; Or Britain seated under other Poles. And must I never see these Mansions more, This lowly Cot, with Sedges cover'd o'er? Or, after rolling Years, with wondring Eyes, See other Greens, and other Harvests rise? Must savage Troops these fertile Fields enjoy, And our full Barns their barb'rous Hands employ? Ah me! what Ills from civil Discord flow! For whom, my Tityrus, did we plant and sow? Go, Colin, now go till, and prune again, Go, Colin, ah! thy Labour is in vain. To you, oh craggy Wilds! oh shady Cell! To thee, my tuneful Pipe! I bid farewel: Farewel, my Goats, farewel; no more you'll browze On flow'ry Hawthorn, or green Willow Boughs. TIT. But here, my Meliboeus! rest this Night, A verdant Couch your Slumbers shall invite. On Chesnuts, Curds, and Cream, here welcome live, And the best Apples which my Farm can give. For see yon Village Chimneys smoke around, And deeper Shadows lengthen o'er the Ground. To his Royal Highness the Prince, on his Arrival in December, 1728. Ascanium surgentem, &amp; spes hæredis Iüli, Respice. Virg. Æn. IV. Thy Monarch's Fate, Britannia, mourn no more, See! a bright Scene salutes thy sable Shore: The long-expected Youth at length appears To bless thy Land; Britannia, dry thy Tears. At his Approach let every Aspect smile, And universal Joy transport the Isle. From eastern Climes the dawning Glory spreads, With sudden Day, and brightens o'er our Heads. So northern Coruscations instant rise, Swell with a Flood of Light, and sweep the Skies. Silent his Progress, unobserv'd his Flight, Still, as the March of Angels in the Night; Still, as the fleecy Clouds which flew before His Steps, for Him new whitening Albion's Shore. No Guards, no pompous Trains adorn'd his Way, No Troops by Land, no Convoy on the Sea: Too mean such Guards; 'tis only Seraphs Care, With spreading Wings, to shield Britannia's Heir. Believe the Muse, she saw the circling Host Patrol around, and guide him to the Coast. Hail, happy Prince! with blooming Virtues fraught, Greatness of Mind, and Probity of Thought. Hail, happy Prince! without a Kingdom bless'd, Content has built her Palace in thy Breast; There seated on a Throne, looks greatly down, With calm Philosophy, and scorns a Crown. No sordid Flatt'ry swells thy generous Mind, With Learning polish'd, and in Courts refin'd; Courteous to all, strict to thy self alone, And blind to no one's Virtue but thy own. Thus shone Ascanius, sprung from Venus' Race, And Rome already triumph'd in his Face. O may'st thou late ascend the Royal Seat, Great in thy Actions, in thy Empire great, Belov'd by all, our native Rights maintain, And Liberty still smile throughout thy Reign. On her Majesty's erecting the Bustos at the Hermitage in Richmond Park. While you, O Caroline! your Grotto grace, And sacred Learning to its Fountain trace, To sleeping Worth erect a deathless Shrine, And civilize the Shades with Busts divine, Permit the Muse to consecrate the Grove, Pleas'd in the venerable Gloom to rove. Science, thus cherish'd, shall repine no more, While crowned Heads her fading Greens restore, But wak'd from Slumber, leave her antient Tomb, And o'er your Bow'rs with spreading Branches bloom; On purer Altars rais'd, luxuriant rise, And shoot her Olive Banners to the Skies: The joyful Muses on each Mountain sing, And in each pathless Wild, Politeness spring. See these four Sages point the shining Way, And in immortal Volumes Truth display; Unshaken Systems see Mathesis frame; Divinity assume a milder Flame; Ethics the virtuous Road to Bliss explore; And Logic slow on Reason's Pinions soar. As Truth of old lay dormant in a Well, In Shades retir'd it still delights to dwell, Lodg'd in th'Asylum of the Royal Cell. Chaste Learning best with Solitude agrees, And courts the Silence of the Caves and Trees. Thy Trees, O Richmond! are instructive made, And Youths grow wise beneath the learned Shade. Methinks Arcadian Odes inspire the Green, And in each Wood Lycean Walks are seen; The Grecian Sages in each Grove appear, And Academic Lectures charm the Ear. Now rapt in Transports of romantic Dreams, I hear the Murmur of Aonian Streams, Thro' classic Meads see Peneus loit'ring creep, And o'er yon Tow'rs the fam'd Stagyra peep; Here Theban Chiefs, there Spartan Temples rise, Here Chios, there immortal Samos lies; Clog'd with slain Heroes, Xanthus slumb'ring flows, Fam'd Argos there, and Ida tipt with Snows. Let others, studious of ignobler Praise, Triumphal Thrones, and shining Structures raise; Semiramis her wondrous Babel frame, With Turrets proud, and curb Euphrates' Stream; 'Tis yours, O Queen! the drooping Arts to save, And raise the Shades of Sages from the Grave, Thro' Mists of Dulness spread a Light divine, Make Swains inspir'd, and Savages refine. Thus Pallas form'd the listning Croud polite, Bœotians humane, and Barbarians bright; Till Athens rose, with Godlike Heroes blest, Guardian of Arts, and Mistress of the East. But while you raise each Sage's shining Bust, And build a Temple o'er their sacred Dust; On the same Pile your Praises loftier rise, Fix'd on a Monument that never dies. Thus Sulphur, long imprison'd in the Earth, Lifts bury'd Mines, and gives to Mountains Birth; But as the Piles ascend, the Flames rise higher, O'er their own Works ambitiously aspire, And shine aloft in Pyramids of Fire. On the New Method of treating Physic, inscribed to Dr. Morgan, on his Philosophical Principles of Medicine. In corpore humano divini conditoris mechanicen ad regulas mathematicas planè adaptatam satis admirari non possumus; siquidem nulla alia in re manifestiùs, ? ???? ?????????? videtur. Willis Pharm. Rat. Distinguis'd Worth demands the Poet's Lays, Accept this grateful Tribute to your Praise; Med'cine the Muses Patronage may claim, For both from one illustrious Offspring came: Each from Apollo boasts a Race divine, And Gods and Heroes in the Lineage shine. Great is the Task, superior to my Skill; For heav'nly Themes require an heav'nly Quill: Yet when you labor in the vast Pursuit, Shall Fame be silent, or the Muse be mute? In the primæval, happy Days of old, When golden Years their shining Circles roll'd, When with wild Fruits and Herbs, Men liv'd content, And thankful took, what Heav'n's rich Bounty sent, No noxious Humors stain'd the crimson Flood, And what is Physic now, was then their Food. They drank the crystal Stream, and sweetly slept On mossy Couches, with the Flocks they kept. Grief then was absent, Pain was hardly known; Peaceful they liv'd, and dy'd without a Groan. Disease at first sprung from her Parent Vice, And hence the healing Art deriv'd its Rise: Blest Art! whose Pow'r dispels our Pain, and saves From pining Sickness, and devouring Graves. Plain Remedies at first were valu'd most, The Drugs were few, and moderate the Cost: The Sick were cur'd without a gilded Pill, A sov'reign Bolus, or a pompous Bill. As Vice increas'd, so Physic by Degrees Increas'd its Empire, and increas'd its Fees. In after-times it more mysterious grew, As Pride prevail'd, and Int'rest came in View; Dress'd by designing Men in dark Disguise, And veil'd in awful Shapes from vulgar Eyes. With Galen's Sect a Cloud of Med'cines came, Of various Forms, and venerable Name: Physic was all Confusion, all profound, While Jargon reign'd, and Learning lay in Sound; Till the last Age appear'd, when Gleams of Light Dart thro' the Chaos, and dispel the Night. Then Bacon flourish'd, in whose spacious Soul Unnumber'd Truths in beauteous Order roll. Then shone the learned, the industrious Boyle, And sought out Truth with an unweary'd Toil; Boyle on Experiment alone rely'd, And Nature, which he lov'd, was still his Guide. Locke now like some propitious Star appears, And his fair Fabric of Ideas rears; Which all the Schoolmen's Sophistry display'd, And welcome Light to ev'ry Art convey'd. Syd'nam made Practice from Experience plain, Taught by no idle Fictions of the Brain: Syd'nam the old, the simple Way renew'd, Nor study'd what was great, but what was good. He rescu'd Physic from its useless Load, And pointed out a more successful Road. The Scene still brightens each revolving Year, And lo! fresh Wonders to our View appear: Lo! Med'cine shines with Mathematic Rays, The welcome Omen of propitious Days. Such was of late the pleasing vast Surprize, When Northern Streamers lighted all the Skies; When soon as Shades of Night the Earth o'erspread, Amaz'd we saw new Morning o'er our Head. Charm'd with the Tidings, many a learned Sage Does eager in the great Design engage; While new Discov'ries their Researches crown, Give Health to others, to themselves Renown. But tho' such Numbers have pursu'd the Theme, To You alone we owe a finish'd Scheme: All that Bellini, or that Pitcairn dar'd, At best is faint Essay with Yours compar'd: The Method clear, each part with Judgment wrought, Enrich'd with labor'd Skill, and Depth of Thought. The learn'd Boerhave will hail the grateful Sight, And read you o'er with Wonder and Delight; While the fam'd Tribe you treat with such Regard, Who best can judge of Worth, and best reward; The Man they love with just Applause extol, And in their shining Rank your Name enrol. Thus the vast Genius is at length reveal'd, Which long, too long in Darkness lay conceal'd; Thro' interposing Clouds it makes its Way, And breaks, refulgent with celestial Day. So Gems disclos'd in some Peruvian Mine, With innate Fire, and rugged Lustre shine. Great Souls blaze out with their own native Light, Tho' Fortune frown, and Envy wrecks her Spight. You leave the beaten Circle of the Schools, And the dull Round of antiquated Rules: On obvious Facts your Principles depend, And heal our Errors, as our Health they mend: While by just Consquence, from these you draw Some fundamental Truth, and useful Law, To guard Man's feeble Frame from fell Disease; Or, when we sink with Pain, to give us Ease; To ev'ry Ail ascribe its proper Cause: For Nature's govern'd by Mechanic Laws. With nicest Skill you paint her outward Dress, In vain we'd penetrate the deep Recess; No human Eye her secret Springs can trace, But lost in Mazes leaves the fruitless Chace. Mount Ætna thus conceals her unknown Fires, And rapid Nile to hidden Paths retires. Sages now trust to Fairy Scenes no more, Nor venture farther, than they see the Shore: They build on Sense, then reason from th'Effect, On well establish'd Truths their Schemes erect; By these some new Phænomena explain; And Light divine in ev'ry Process gain. Such was the Path immortal Newton trod, He form'd the wondrous Plan, and mark'd the Road; Led by this Clue he travel'd o'er the Sky, And marshal'd all the shining Worlds on high, Pursu'd the Comets, where they farthest run, And brought them back obsequious to the Sun. Men may on Fancy's airy Pinions rise, And in Imagination touch the Skies; Be pleas'd with Theories, because they're new, And then, for being pleas'd, believe them true: On Nature call, but call, alas! in vain, To softer all the Monsters of their Brain. Nature has no imaginary Schemes, No vain Chimeras, nor romantic Dreams; She offers Truth, not Fiction to the Mind, Nor makes us fancy, what we never find. Mature in Thought, you Newton's Laws reduce To nobler Ends, and more important Use. You shew, how heav'nly Orbs affect our Frame, And raise, or sink by Turns the vital Flame: How Moons alternate in their changing Sphere Impress their Force, and agitate the Air; How as without successive Tides advance, While Cynthia pale pursues her silent Dance, So does the refluent Blood her Influence know, And Tides within roll high, or creep on slow. When raging Fevers kindle Flames within, Which dreadful glow o'er all the scorch'd Machine, You shew, how Nature grows averse to Food, And pants for Liquors to dilute the Blood, Shuts up the Pores, and prudently detains The flowing Serum in the burning Veins. Your gentle Med'cines mitigate the Heat, And cool the Blood without Expenee of Sweat: The Monster Febris flies the mighty Spell, In Haste retires, and calmly seeks her Cell. So when the sultry Dog-star reigns on high, And all the Fountains of the Earth are dry, When parched Fields look with'ring all around, And frequent Chasms divide the thirsty Ground; Indulgent Heav'n bids num'rous Vapors rise, And, lo! th'obedient Vapors croud the Skies; While bursting Clouds descend in Show'rs of Rain, Revive the Plants, and cool the burning Plain. Med'cine from hence shall boast of sure Success, Nor Patients long remain without Redress. But raise from Scenes of Death their drooping Heads, And flush'd with sudden Life forsake their Beds. For this shall future Ages sound your Fame, And distant Climates echo loud your Name: Your Work itself will its Admirers raise, And Men that breathe by you, shall breathe your Praise My raptur'd Muse sees with prophetic Eyes New Ages roll along, new Nations rise; Sees Physic on Mechanic Reas'ning climb, And raise a Structure to the Skies sublime; Sees Sickness fled, Health bloom in ev'ry Face, And Age creep on with slow, reluctant Pace. Experience with her Torch shall guide our Youth, Scatter the Mists, and light the Way to Truth. While dark Hypothesis no more prevails, Nor Pupils listen to romantic Tales; Nor proud Authority with bugbear Rules Controuls the Church, nor dictates in the Schools. But Liberty sits Goddess of our Isle, And peaceful Blessings all around her smile; Darkness and Bigotry before her fly, And Truth and Virtue grow beneath her Eye. To Richard Champneys of Orchardly, Esq; when in Danger of the Small-Pox, which raged in the Neighbourhood. Quis non è timidis ægri contagia vitat, Vicinum metuens ne trahat inde malum? Perlege, nec mecum pariter mea verba relega; Villa licet vestra versibus esse meis. Ovid. While Blasts contagious taint the ambient Air, And o'er each Mind diffuse a gloomy Care, Amidst the public Loss I mourn my own, And banish'd from your Seat, in Silence moan. Cruel Disease! whose subtle Poison flows Unseen, and wafts Infection as it goes; Thy Darts not only Death, and Vengeance spread, But make the Living, Strangers like the Dead. To live, is not in Solitude to dwell, In Cloisters lock'd, or sleeping in a Cell: 'Tis not an idle Flux of useless Breath, Perpetual Absence is a Sort of Death. But tho' condemn'd an Exile from your Seat, Permit the Muse to visit the Retreat, Where once she lov'd in echoing Walks to play, Sing to the Streams, and o'er the Gardens stray. She no Infection in her Presence brings, No dire Effluvia lurk beneath her Wings; Or should you fear some Venom lies unseen, She'll round the Air perform a Quarantine, Above the cloudy Regions tow'ring rise, In purer Climes, and unpolluted Skies, Where no terrestrial Vapours ever soar, Nor Thunders thro' the peaceful Æther roar, No sickly Meteors there portentous play, But Titan shines with an unsully'd Ray. But ah! how dull, how lifeless are these Lays! Not like the Flame your Bounty us'd to raise, When all the Sweets of Orchardly inspir'd, And rich Champagne the languid Genius fir'd; What now avail these visionary Lines, That Seat which only in Description shines, In Fancy round the fairy Scene to soar, And dream of Pleasures which are now no more? In vain I bring the vanish'd Pile to View, And form a pictur'd Paradise anew: Only faint Landskips skim before my Sight, Departing Bow'rs, and Grottos wing'd for Flight: In vain I bid the floating Prospects stay; Alcoves, and Grots, and Forests fleet away; As transient Shadows hurry o'er the Lawn, And Vapors vanish at Aurora's Dawn: Yet pleasant 'tis past Pleasures to revive, And trace in Picture what was once alive. Thus I each Charm of your Retreat survey, Your Temper candid, generous, and gay: A Lady blest with each endearing Grace, Good Sense, and Softness smiling in her Face. Such mild Complacence fills her gentle Mien, One Look would Fury quell, and charm Chagrin; The Muses listen when she strikes the Strings, And Birds forget their Warbling while she sings. Would Time once more roll down the happy Day, And let these Eyes again the Scene survey, The Bow'rs more fair should bloom in ev'ry Line, And ev'ry Beauty with new Lustre shine. But all these Glories have their destin'd Doom, And all Creation hurries to the Tomb; Impending Fate hangs threat'ning o'er our Head, Fly where we will, we're Neighbours to the Dead; And tho' awhile we may elude the Foe, 'Twill soon, or late, strike home the fatal Blow. The Story of the Trojan Women Burning their Ships. Virgil. Æneid. Lib. V. The Trojans now their solemn Rites display'd, Sacred to great Anchises' awful Shade. But while their ritual Games his Manes grace, Here first inconstant Fortune chang'd her Face. On her old Grudge Relentless Juno bent, Sends Iris from the Skies her Rage to vent, Swift bids her hasten to the Trojan Fleet, And with celestial Breezes wings her Feet. Unseen she glides along the gilded Skies, From her fair Bow a thousand Colours rise: The painted Virgin sees the Trojan Band, The crouded Theatre, the silent Strand, Sees the forsaken Ships, the desart Port, Where, far retir'd, the Dardan Dames resort, There, for Anchises, lonely weeping stood, And weeping all beheld the crystal Flood, One Voice, one Passion, all the Troop possess'd: What, must we still explore a Place of Rest? Fatigu'd with Storms and Billows, leave our Home, Still fated o'er yon trackless Seas to roam? While skilful Iris mingles with the Croud, The Goddess, veil'd in a terrestrial Shroud, By Juno taught her radiant Form to hide In Beroe's Guise, Doryclus' aged Bride. Ismarian Doryclus, whose Race and Name, When Ilium stood, were not unknown to Fame. Thus unobserv'd, amidst the Throng she press'd, And in these Words the Female Clans address'd. Unhappy Matrons! whom the Grecian Bands Unkindly spar'd to rove o'er foreign Lands; Bless'd had ye been beneath Troy's Ruins slain, And not reserv'd for Scenes of future Pain. The Sun has sev'n times pass'd his vernal Bound, Since we poor Pilgrims strole the World around. What Seas, what Stars, what Climates have we cross'd, On barren Rocks, and barren Regions toss'd? And o'er tumultuous Waves in vain pursue Italian Shores, eluding still our View. Now on Sicilia's friendly Banks we stand, The kind Acestes' hospitable Land, Ah! let us here our toilsome Journey close, Erect new Walls, and seek at last Repose. O Country! now no more, O Trojan Names! O sacred Gods! in vain secur'd from Flames, Shall Troy, and Hector's Streams be nam'd no more, And no new Simois bound another Shore? But come, ye Matrons! and let Rage inspire, Come, set, with me, these cursed Ships on Fire. To me Cassandra's Form in Dreams appear'd, And with up-lifted Arm bright Torches rear'd: Here seek lost Troy, here fix your Home, she said, Conclude your Toils; and strait the Vision fled. Then haste, beloved Sex! the Call obey, Since Prodigies and Omens point the Way. Sacred to Neptune, see, four Altars lie, The God himself will Fire and Force supply. She spoke; and snatching swift a flaming Brand, With glitt'ring Vengeance waves her vig'rous Hand, Thro' the sing'd Air the winged Lightning flies, While the mad Matrons gaze with wondring Eyes. But one, nam'd Pyrgo, eldest of the Throng, The royal Nurse of Priam's royal Young, Believe, this is not Beroe's Aspect, cry'd, Nor can she be the fam'd Doryclus' Bride. Observe with what majestic Gate she walks, Her Mien how noble, how divine she talks, What Spirit in her Looks, what heav'nly Grace, And charming Splendor brightens in her Face. Beroe herself I feeble left behind, Detain'd by Sickness and Chagrin of Mind, Lamenting her unhappy Fate to stay, Nor share the Honors of Anchises' Day. She ceas'd; the doubtful Matrons, in Amaze, With Looks malignant, on the Gallies gaze; Whether to stay, involv'd in sad Suspense, Or listen to the Fates, which call'd them thence. When, lo! the winged Goddess quits the Croud, And forms a splendid Arch across the Cloud. Then, struck with Visions, frantic Rage inspires The shrieking Troops to pluck the hallow'd Fires, The Altars rob, while from their vengeful Hands Fly mingled, smoaking Boughs, and flaming Brands. Devouring Vulcan now begins his Wreck, Preys on the Seats, and fastens on the Deck; The painted Stern aloft, of Firr-tree-frame, With crackling Noise, falls mould'ring in the Flame. Eumelus hastens to Anchises' Tomb, The first sad Envoy of the Navy's Doom, And soon the crouded Circus sees from far, Volumes of Smoke obscure the dusky Air. And first Ascanius, with his mounted Band Of Trojan Youths, flies to the noisy Strand. In vain th'affrighted Guides his Course would stay, Nor Cries nor Tears, can interrupt his Way. And thus the Youth, O wretched Females! cries, What means this Rage, this Frenzy in your Eyes? No Grecian Tents, no hostile Seats you burn, But your own Hopes to Flames and Ashes turn, See your Ascanius thus before you stands, And throws his useless Helmet on the Sands, With which, at his old Grandsire's Games, array'd, The mimic Face of War the Youth display'd. Æneas next, with the concurring Train Of Dardan Bands, hastes o'er Sicilia's Plain. But the pale Sex, confus'd, and tim'rous rove Wild o'er the Beach, or seek the silent Grove; In winding Caverns hide, and fill'd with Shame, Grow sick of Life, and their mad Actions blame; Confess their Friends with milder Thoughts possest, And banish'd Juno peaceful leaves their Breast. Not so the spreading Flames their Force allay, But with unconquer'd Fury sweep their Way. The nourish'd Fire here hovering feeds on Tow, And smother'd Planks emit thick Fumes below. In vain the Art of Chiefs, and Men conspires, In vain full Currents ply the growing Fires, The raging Element resistless spreads Destruction round, and tow'rs above their Heads. Then rent the Chief his Garments from his Breast, Invok'd the Gods, and thus his Pray'rs address'd. “Almighty Jove! if yet thy Mercy reigns, “Nor everlasting Hate to Troy remains, “If antient Love will human Toils reward, “Oh! from surrounding Ills the Navy guard, “Snatch it from Ruin, and, if not too late, “Preserve our little Weal from threatning Fate: “Or if I merit Death, Great Jove! (he said) “Direct thy forked Thunder at my Head. Scarce had he spoke, when thro' the sounding Skies, With clatt'ring Noise, a sweeping Tempest flies; The lowring Clouds let loose th'imprison'd Show'rs In Floods of Rain, and Thunder shakes the Tow'rs; High on the Mountain Tops the Lightnings glare, And rattling Storms rush thro' the noisy Air. The Ships, replete with Rain, o'erflow the Brim, And half-burn'd Planks in Lakes of Water swim, Till in the Flood dies each dull Spark away, And only four to Vulcan fall a Prey. MARSTON-HOUSE. Inscribed to the Right Honourable the Earl of ORRERY. Te nostræ, Vare, miricæ, Te nemus omne canet Virg. Ecl. VI. Since you, my Lord, from public Cares refrain, Nor rural Seats, or rural Songs disdain, Proud of so great a Guide, the rustic Muse Thro' the lone Shade your silent Steps pursues, And like fond Birds, which follow your Retreat, Haunts your Repose, and hovers round your Seat, As you approve, advances, or withdraws, In Woods gives Musick, and in Courts Applause. Your Presence now our Marston Groves confess, From civil Noise, soft Region of Recess. At Your Approach the Country smiles around, And vocal Forests with the Tidings sound: Long absent Echoes pleas'd return again, Wind thro' the Woods, and wanton o'er the Plain: At Your Approach the Fields appear more gay, And thro' those Fields the Streams more chearful play: The grateful Brutes come fawning at your Feet, And conscious Doves in Flocks your Chariot greet. No Crouds, no busy Fops, this Clime annoy, No Cares this Region of Repose destroy: No public Knaves, no Parasites intrude, No Zealots vex these Seats of Solitude. Here o'er th'Horizon wide a Mountain reigns, That with gay Brow o'erlooks the subject Plains. In whose Mid-way a gentle Flat is seen, From Damps below, and Winds above a Screen. Here hangs the Villa in majestick Show, And high in Beauty fronts the Meads below, And seated thus, looks to the distant Eye, Like some inchanted Palace in the Sky. A spacious Court, which lofty Walls surround, And loftier Trees, the splendid Entrance bound: Deep, mossy Banks in artless Hills decline, And sloping Verdures beautifully shine. Behind, with slow Ascent, the Gardens rise, Whose airy Top looks downward to the Skies; And on each Side such distant Scenes surveys, The Sight is buried in the boundless Gaze. Like the old hanging Gardens of the East, 'Twixt Heav'n and Earth th'exalted Arbors rest: Thro' Sweets we climb, and climbing, seem to share Ambrosial Odors, and celestial Air. Below, an Area of enamel'd Green Displays its Robes, where Statues rise between, And shine with Features of a Roman Mien. Here polish'd Bowls o'er the smooth Surface glide Serene, like Bubbles floating on the Tide. Illustrious Game! which in contracted Space, Forms a low Copy of th'Olympic Race. See the pois'd Globes with Emulation roll, As stream'd swift Chariots to the destin'd Goal; Now round the Mark with oblique Shiness bend, And feign to shun that Point to which they tend; But drawn by Gravity of inward Steel, Near and more near in lessening Eddies wheel, Then drop at once, like Birds with downward Wing; And loud Applauses o'er the Verdure ring. Thus Vessels near some Vortex in the Deep, With various Path long round its Edges sweep, But once within the Gulphy Circles cast, Sink to the Centre with impetuous Haste. But see, th'Antagonists, 'twixt Joy and Fear, Alternate vary with the shifting Sphere; As this revolves, their Passions rise or fall, Just Picture of the great terrestrial Ball; When from the Mark the Bowl elopes in Flight, Persuading Muscles try to wind it right, And with mechanic Impulse, laboring guide Its Path erratic, and the Motion chide; When slowly waddling with dull, slumbring Pace, The flying Words precipitate the Race; But when too swift, the Language slacks its Sound, And Syllables sleep loitering o'er the Ground. Here you, my Lord, unsully'd Pleasures find, And from severer Scenes relax your Mind; Books and Diversions, happy Contrast! blend Gentle Amusements, and a gentle Friend; And with these Bowls more glorious Contest hold, Than the Pellæan Ravager of old, Or rapid Cæsar in his martial Robe, Crossing the Rhine, and toiling for the Globe. Blest in your Lady, whose attractive Air, And chaste Endearments, sweeten every Care. While in your blooming Offspring we presage Uncommon Blessings to the rising Age. Let Men of Pleasure of their Raptures boast, 'Tis but a momentary Joy at most, A treach'rous Sea which will no Storm abide, While virtuous Pleasure is a constant Tide. Let others restless rove the World around, In vain Pursuits no Happiness is found; Let needy Courtiers pine for wretched State, 'Tis private Virtue makes the good Man Great. Heroic Souls, of such a Prize possess'd, May scorn the tinsel Treasures of the East, And fraught with calm Tranquility can find A better Treasure in a guiltless Mind. 'Tis thus the Brave all Ills of Life despise, And know that to be Blest, is to be Wise. To Miss Raleigh, Great Grand-daughter of the famous Sir W. Raleigh. Igneus est illi vigor, &amp; cœlestis origo Seminibus. Virg. Æn. VI. As in a tender Plant impress'd we see The mimic Features of the parent Tree; Or as young Painters, in their first Essay, The Soul within in each light Sketch betray: So, rising Raleigh, 'midst your Bloom we trace The Rays of Greatness dawning in your Face; And wondring view, as in a Picture shine Sublime Ideas, and an Air divine: The vivid Strokes in Miniature proclaim Your genuine Title, and deserved Name. Like Prints in Sand, or Images in Sleep, Th'Impression's obvious, tho' the Stamp not deep. We need no lineal Pedigrees of Books, But read the fair Tradition in your Looks; Your true Descent each Lineament betrays, And the immortal Origin displays. So the fair Morning, spangled o'er with Gold, Does by Degrees its glorious Light unfold: Thus infant Letters grav'd upon the Bark, Grow with the Stock, and still improve the Mark. Fresh to our View Sir Walter's Actions rise, And all the Hero sparkles in your Eyes: Fresh o'er his Grave triumphant Lawrels bloom, And the new Foliage blossoms round his Tomb. See! the great Patriot rears his rev'rend Head With Tears of Joy, and smiling leaves the Dead. Now his pale Image beckons you along, His Wounds still bleeding for his Country's Wrong; He points you out a glorious Path to tread, The Path of Liberty, for which he bled. Bids you each Tyrant's servile Cause disdain, Great Ends pursue, and bravely suffer Pain. Fir'd with these godlike Views, he, undismay'd, Saw glitter o'er his Head the fatal Blade: That awful Head which Years had silver'd o'er, The Ruffians saw, relentless as before. Wit, Valour, Learning, Virtue plead in vain, The last low Sands of drooping Life to gain. Infernal Zeal! to antedate his Doom, Whom trembling Age stood ready to consume. Then gush'd the Tears from each Spectator's Eye, Deep groan'cth e Croud, and Nature seem'd to sigh; A pale Concern did in each Face appear, All but in his, whose solemn Fate drew near. But the Muse startles at the tragic Tale, And o'er the bloody Sequel draws a Veil, Your tender Grief unwilling to renew, And bring the sad Catastrophe to view. Curst be those Villains who his Fate conspir'd, By Jesuits prompted, and by Traytors hir'd. Thus did thy King thy brave Exploits requite; Thus let thee basely fall to Spanish Spite; Thus, guarded by a Mob, ignobly march; A Scaffold rais'd for thy triumphal Arch. Hear how sedate the dying Hero speaks, And in prophetic Stile his Passion breaks. “Mourn not my Fate, the Scene of Life is short, “Death throws the Die, and we are Nature's Sport; “Yet if we bravely live, and bravely die, “'Tis but a kind Transition to the Sky. “Still o'er the Grave this Spoil the Virtuous claim, “To mock their Fun'rals, and survive in Fame: “While like a Stream still fed by fresh Supplies, “We o'er our Ruins more illustrious rise; “And in succeeding Progenies behold “Our Age renew'd again as we grow old. “Pleas'd I foresee, as I my Breath resign, “A sparkling Female in my Lineage shine, “Whose gen'rous Breasts an Infant Heir shall nurse, “Whom Rome in vain shall threat, and Spaniards curse; “Their golden Mines his conq'ring Hand shall seize, “Free vassal'd Realms, and triumph o'er the Seas; “Shall barb'rous Climes to Softness civilize, “And spread the painted Flags in polar Skies. “Then shall Astrea reign, grim Discord cease, “And o'er Britannia pour a balmy Peace. Rise, destin'd Virgin! rise, convinc'd we find, The glorious Prophecy for you design'd. The public Care your blooming Graces win, See, sighing Youths their early Vows begin. To own your Name the Great themselves are proud, And in your Lap unsought their Presents croud. See, Patriots strive to give your Merit due, For Friends to Liberty are Friends to you. With gen'rous Love their Hearts already glow, Still may their Favours with your Virtues grow. So Dido, melted with his youthful Charms, Clasp'd the divine Ascanius in her Arms; The little Hero's Heart o'erflow'd with Joy, While with rich Gifts she crown'd the beauteous Boy; Fair in whose radiant Mien began to bloom, The future Greatness of immortal Rome. Shine on, bright Nymph! and may your Charms subdue As many Slaves as your great Grandsire slew. Still may his godlike Virtues fire your Breast, Still be his Image on your Mind imprest; Be that the Mirror which you most admire, Mortality itself can rise no higher. TO HIPPIA. So much good Sense, and airy Life, In Hippia's Looks are seen, In her the Graces are at Strife, And combat in her Mien. Vivacity now reigns alone, Then Gravity sedate; And like two Rivals to the Throne, Alternate take their Seat. Thus Mercury diffusive flies, And penetrates our Veins, Still volatile, delights to rise, Yet pond'rous still remains. Such humble Air, and modest Grace, 'Midst sparkling Jewels shine, Even Criticks would pronounce your Face Half human, half divine. Such charming Images arise, When she the Pencil dips, Nought, but the Lustre of her Eyes, Can her own Works eclipse. When o'er Romance fair Tears she sheds, Or sighs o'er Lovers Lays, There is no tragic Tale she reads, But what herself might raise. The strange Adventures of each Knight, For his Dulcinea fair, Would be no vain fictitious Flight, Was Hippia pictur'd there. Happy, too happy! is the Swain Whose Vows she deigns to hear, Who sighs, but has not sigh'd in vain, Nor shed a fruitless Tear. Possess'd of such a spotless Gem, So fair, so kind, so wise, He Indian Monarchs may condemn, And Indian Mines despise. TO MARCIA. Who can be silent, when such Charms invite, As teach the dumb to speak, the dull to write? 'Tis not mere Feature our Devotion fires, That is true Beauty which the Mind inspires. Ill Nature cannot please, nor Folly charm, Tho' it had Angels Looks, and Cupid's Arm. When Marcia dazzles, 'tis the Soul shines thro', Brightens each Feature, and transports our View. Survey the fairest Form, we still shall find Beauty's an Emanation of the Mind; 'Tis the Reflection of the Rays within, Which throws the noble Lustre o'er the Mien, Which every Lineament with Light supplies, And gives Divinity to Marcia's Eyes. This is that Spark no Sickness ever shades, This triumphs when external Beauty fades. 'Tis what, a Grace, an Air, the Vulgar name, But Plato's Sense of Beauty means the same: Tho' blooming Roses sparkle o'er the Face, 'Tis all inanimate without this Grace. To Reason's Eye the gaudy Outside yields No more Delight than Lilies in the Fields. As well the Swain might o'er stain'd Canvass sigh, Or Holbein's Colours with Southampton's vie. Like the fam'd Painter who enamour'd grew, And pin'd for that fair Venus which he drew, Marcia! did you to the same Artist sit, With his own Work he would again be smit. Thus must I languish, cruelly remote From the dear Nymph, and picture you in Thought. Fancy, that mimic Limner of the Mind, Has with its Pencil ev'ry Air design'd; And, wonder not, like the Enchanter's Ring, Can every Action to its Presence bring, And in Imagination hear you sing. Boast not your magic Pow'r, your conq'ring Skill, For Fancy can create, if you can kill. In vain you fly, I now behold your Eyes, See your Blush kindle, and your Bosom rise. So oft your Apparition fleets in View, I almost think the Tales of Spectres true. The fair Idea rises to my Sight, And glides in transient Slumbers every Night. Visions and airy Ghosts disturb our Rest. With yours, O airy Visiter! I'm bless'd. But this is all fine, visionary Love, Like Dreams of Pleasure in th'Elysian Grove. When in the Garden, Love remembers well, You gave me Fruit to taste, and Flow'rs to smell, Ah, fair Seducer, soon, too soon I found, 'Twas dang'rous Fruit, and Paradise the Ground. Be not in Treach'ry, tho' in Charms, like Eve, Lest as you still beguile, we still believe. An ODE composed by the ArchBishop of Cambray, when he lived a Youth on the Mountains of Auvergne. Translated from the French. I. Hail Mountains, who, with daring Brow, In the Skies aspiring reign, Whose Tops eternal Frosts surround, And the Gods Abode sustain. Underneath your oaken Towers, Above the Clouds, I gather Flowers, While at my Feet, against the Ground, Subterranean Thunders sound, And a thousand Cascades hiss, Rushing down the Precipice. II. Like the Thracian Hills of old, When the Rebel Giant strove, And Mountains upon Mountains pil'd, To scale the Throne of Jove. Your lofty Tops are Plains, which bear Loftier Hills upon their Backs, so high, They mock the Fury of the Air, And brave the Winds Artillery. III. Soon as the Vermilion Morn Is with sparkling Splendor dress'd, And on the verdant Hills appear Blushes, peeping from the East, The tender, bleating Lambs are seen, Wandring o'er the Flowery Green. Here a dark and solemn Grove, Shadowy, near a River's Side, Is ruffled by the Zephyr's Breath, While the Waters murmuring glide, And invite both Swains and Sheep, With gentle Sounds to gentle Sleep. IV. But in this romantic Scene Every Thing capricious looks, And a savage Beauty reigns O'er the Mountains and the Brooks; Brooks which always peaceful flow, And no Storms nor Torrents know; Where the Heaven, serenely clear, Always beautifies the Year, Where no malignant Winter's found, But after Autumn, Spring adorns the Ground. V. Blest Solitude A little Abby which he then enjoyed.! Hail, peaceful Stream! Which does no other Sound convey, But the soft Motion of the Waves, As they froth and fall away. Two happy Islands rise between, Crown'd with never-fading Green, The Prospect charms the wondring Eyes, With all that Fancy can desire, Oh! for some Anthem from the Skies, To tune the Music of my Lyre. VI. The Zephyr's sweet and balmy Breath, O'er the blooming Hedges spreads, And o'er the waving Harvests plays, While they nod with golden Heads. See! all our Barns kind Ceres fills, Blithe Bacchus purple Juice distils From a thousand pregnant Hills, And o'er the happy Plain below, Tides of Wine descending flow. VII. Where yon Landskips bound my View, Azure Prospects blended rise, Various Objects painted play, In chequer'd Lustre to my Eyes. Gay Nature in a Fit of Mirth, To these alternate Scenes gave Birth, The fair Canal far off displays In Æther these reflected Rays, As floating o'er the crystal Plain, Th'Horizon is renew'd again. VIII. With rich Autumn's fruitful Womb, The Spring too mingles its Perfume, And Vineyards bear both Grapes and Bloom. Amidst the Meads the River smiles, Gliding fair 'mongst fragrant Isles. Now the Waters, soft and clear, Muttering warble to the Ear, Anon with rapid Currents chide The verdant Carpet as they glide. IX. Dancing on a violet Couch, The gay Shepherd chearful sings, And with Flutes, and Hautboys Sound, Every vocal Valley rings. Sweet Birds in Concert chant their Strains, And chase all Trouble from these Plains; Only sad plaintive Doves, with tender Tone, Are in these happy Regions heard to moan. X. On some flowery, downy Bed, Stretch'd on Moss, I rest my Head, Calm and gentle Slumbers bind All Avenues of my Mind. In these Charms each Sense is sunk, With this Nectar I grow drunk: From all Cares and Dangers free, Gods themselves might envy me. The treacherous Images of Sleep, Are like the Dreams at Court, False Dreams, but mine are much more sweet, Which in my Fancy sport. XI. Free from the dark, impending Storms, Which hover o'er the Great, I safe beneath these shady Grotts, Enjoy a blest Retreat. A safe Asylum from all Harms, Here Truth to me unfolds her Charms: Here, without Books, I musing find Her native Traces in my Mind. Now History, and Fable rise, And place Antiquity before my Eyes. XII. I see the wisest Grecian Sage, The Sport of Fortune's giddy Rage; Yet calm upon the shipwreck'd Sea, Thro' Storms and Billows steer his Way. He Winds and Waves, and Pleasures too withstood, And vanquish'd for his Country's Good. But in my Hermitage reclin'd, More certain Joys are found, Within the Circle of this Shade, All my Desires are bound. Here, far from Toils of Civil State, I halcyon Days enjoy, No Guilt the Muses Calm chagrins, No Wars my Peace annoy. My Breast, contented with my Lyre, Can to no greater Height aspire, Than here to sing my happy State, And this Elysium celebrate. And thou, false Fortune, I despise, The World is nothing in my Eyes. In whatsoever Clime I rove, No other Region can I love; This happy Corner of the Earth, Is still replete with harmless Mirth. Here to crown my peaceful Days, Some kind Sister from the Sky, Here shall spin my fatal Hour, Here my Ashes silent lie: Till Thyrsis comes to mourn my Doom, With Tears of Friendship o'er my Tomb. TRANSLATION FROM HORACE, Lib. III. Ode III. The Man of firm and upright Soul, No Danger can affright, Not Thunders cracking round the Pole, Nor Tempests in the Night. Securely fix'd on Virtue's Seat, He scorns the Tyrant's Chains, Unshock'd, when Tumults rend the State, Or Earthquakes shake the Plains. Should Nature from her Base be hurl'd, And into Chaos reel, Serene he'd view a sinking World, Himself unshaken still. 'Twas in this Path brave Pollux trod, And gain'd the glorious Prize; Alcides press'd the shining Road, And travell'd to the Skies. There the divine Augustus sits, Amidst the Heroes crown'd, His rosy Lips the Nectar greets, And sparkles all around. 'Twas thus, oh, Bacchus! fam'd in Song, Thy Name immortal grew, By savage Tygers drawn along, Illustrious to the View. The warlike Founder of our State, Thus fled Hell's dark Abodes, And Juno, pleas'd, forgot her Hate, And thus address'd the Gods In Council met. Troy, haughty Troy Is now consum'd to Dust, By that false Judge, that wanton Boy, And Helen's fatal Lust. Laomedon's deceitful Mind, Who Heav'n's Decrees o'erthrew, With Mine, and Pallas' Anger join'd, Destroy'd the Rebel Crew. No more the Traytor with his Spouse, Now shine in Robes of State, No longer Priam's perjur'd House Resists approaching Fate. In vain was Hector's Valor prais'd, Too weak for Grecian Strength, The War by our Divisions rais'd, In Conquest ceas'd at length. But thou from Mars and Rhea born, Shalt unto Mars ascend, The blest Elysian Seats adorn, And Jove shall be thy Friend. There ravish'd in the peaceful Scene, Shalt taste the rich Perfume, While distant Oceans roll between Deserted Troy and Rome. Still shall the Trojans happy reign, In other Regions nurs'd, While lowing Herds insult the Plain, And tread on Priam's Dust. Devouring Beasts shall haunt the Land, And rav'nous Birds of Prey, While Rome's proud Capitol shall stand, And barb'rous Medes obey. Her Laws shall distant Nations guide, Shall make her Eagles soar, Where interposing Seas divide Europe from Afric's Shore. Her Empire spread o'er Scythian Snows, Where the wild Parthian reigns, And where the bounteous Nile o'erflows, And deluges the Plains. With noble Scorn she dares despise The Gold in foreign Lands, By Nature hid from human Eyes, And sacrilegious Hands. O'er torrid Zones, and wintry Seas, Shall Roman Power extend, Where Nature's utmost Confines cease, And distant Climates end. But let not the brave Nation dare, Induc'd by haughty Zeal, The ruin'd Walls of Troy repair, And my Decrees repeal. For know, Destruction is its Doom, And should the Town arise, It quickly should its Fate resume, With Vengeance from the Skies. Thrice should Apollo all the Town With brazen Bulwarks screen, Yet thrice it should be broken down, By me the Thund'rer's Queen. Thrice should the captive Wife bemoan Her absent Lord in vain, And thrice with Tears lament her Son, By conqu'ring Grecians slain. But why, my Muse! dost thou aspire, In too advent'rous Odes, And lessen, in thy wanton Lyre, The Actions of the Gods? On the Death of a beautiful young Lady. When Beauty drops untimely to the Tomb, What Bosom melts not at Dorinda's Doom? When Death, relentless, seiz'd her youthful Charms, And clasp'd her, blooming, in his icy Arms, Nor Pray'rs, nor Tears, his Rigor could repell, Nor screen the fair one from his gloomy Cell. Thus Vulcan snatch'd his Goddess from above, And to his Den convey'd the Queen of Love; In vain she strove, he bore the Prize away, And smil'd with awkward Pleasure o'er the Prey. Dorinda's fled, fair Idol of the Plains! Dull are her Graces, torpid all her Veins, Those Veins where once Life's Purple flow'd so clear, That Harvey might have seen it circle here, And at one View, without Dissecting Art, Trac'd the fair refluent Fountain to the Heart. But what avails it to be fair, or wise? Death sees no Features, and admires no Eyes. If Beauty could have sooth'd the Tyrant's Will, The charming Nymph had reign'd immortal still. But adverse Fate is seldom so severe, That with the Storm, we can no Sunshine share; As Good from Evil, Moralists retail, And Chymists, from bad Dross, fine Parts exhale, Thus by her Doom, her future Slaves shall gain, Peace in their Bosoms, and Release from Pain: Sav'd by her Death, reprieved Youths shall live, To whom those Eyes as sure a Death would give. Too young for Conquest yet, her dawning Charms But threatned now, with unexperienc'd Arms; As tender Fawns their budding Horns essay, Dare harmless war, and imitate the Fray. Thus Sulphur sleeps, in secret Caverns pent, Till Heat expands, and gives the Thunder vent. But where's that Soul, that heav'nly Genius fled, That sprightly Wit which once our Wonder fed? For in the Tomb no Wisdom latent lies, Nor Understanding with the Carcase dies. Her Shape, her Figure, in the Coffin rest, In shrouded State, like painted Babies dress'd. No radiant Spark informs the lifeless Clay, Which from the ruin'd Mansion fleets away. See! while the Thinking Mind deserts the Frame, Inactive Matter still remains the same, Still perfect, all its Properties retains, And knows no Pleasure, as it feels no Pains; But in some other System circling glides, Soars in a Fly, or in a Flow'r resides. Whether the Soul patrolling o'er the Skies, From Star to Star, in airy Stages flies; Or other Vehicles ethereal meets, As thro' the boundless Void it naked fleets; Or with her kindred Saints, serene above, Riots in Bliss, and Deluges of Love, Is yet unknown; Death is a trackless Main, All launch it o'er, none cross the Deep again; When once this still, this awful Gulf is cross'd, 'Tis all in Darkness, and in Lethe lost, Thick Mists, and hazy Vapors hang between, And Night eternal draws her sable Screen. But tho' we Mortals know not how, or where, We know kind Death is a Relief from Care; No anxious Dreams this peaceful Rest awake, No horrid Storms the downy Slumber shake. Seal'd in this Sleep, the bright Dorinda lies, Nor hears our Praises, nor regards our Sighs. Clos'd are those Eyes, which others wakeful made, And pale those Lips which bid the Roses fade; Silent that Tongue, which charm'd the listning Swains, So sweet, the Birds from thence learn'd finer Strains. Say, ye soft Winds! which on her Bosom flew, And from so chaste a Seat, more gentle blew, Say, did you e'er so pure a Spot explore, Tho' wafted from Arabia's spicy Shore? Now o'er her Tomb, in whirling Eddies play, Or in loud Sighs the tragic News convey. For her relenting, Virtue deigns to weep, And future Triumphs in her Ashes sleep. But thus each Fair is punish'd in her Kind, For, like their Cupid, Death is ever blind. Part of the first Book of Torquatus Tasso's Conquest of Jerusalem, or the Holy War. Done from the Italian. I sing the Pious Chief, whose valiant Band, From Pagan Armies rescu'd Judah's Land, Wondrous Designs inspir'd the Hero's Thought, And with his Hand he wondrous Actions wrought: In vain dread Dangers, and surrounding Foes, In vain did hellish Legions interpose, While Heav'n approv'd, couragious on he led, And o'er his Troops the holy Ensigns spread. Celestial Muse, who, seated in the Skies, Dost fading Bays, and vulgar Fame despise, Who with Contempt on Pindus' Top look'st down, Adorn'd with an immortal starry Crown; Do thou my Soul with lofty Thoughts inspire, O kindle in my Breast a sacred Fire; And pardon, if, misled, I Fable join, And gild my Verse with other Robes than thine. Thou know'st Parnassus' Sweets the World invite, And smoothest Strains give always most Delight, When Truths sublime in Verse harmonious roll, 'Twill into Rapture raise a Stoic Soul. Thus to allure the sickly Infant's Taste, Inviting Sweets are round the Vessel plac'd, Deceiv'd he smiling drinks the bitter Juice, Deceiv'd he lives, nor knows the kind Abuse. Oh, great Alphonse! who far from Fortune's Rage, Hast safely fix'd me in a quiet Stage, Still pleas'd to stand my Guardian and my Guide, 'Midst Rocks and Seas that frown on ev'ry Side, With Looks benign, accept the Muse's Flights, Who prophesies thy Glory as she writes; And while she dedicates these mimic Lays, Draws but the Outlines of thy future Praise. If e'er the Christian Powers expect to free The Grecian Land from Turkish Tyranny, And peaceful, rescu'd from unrighteous Sway, With Fleets, and Arms, regain the ill got Prey, To thee they must commit the vast Design, To thy just Sceptre Land and Sea resign; Great Godfry's Rival! now thy Arms display, And arming, read thy Deeds in every Lay. Six rolling Years were measur'd by the Sun, Since the brave Troops their pious March begun: Nice was by fierce Assault already gain'd, And pow'rful Antioch by Surprize obtain'd: While, 'midst the Persian Host, encamp'd around, Undaunted Knights maintain the conquer'd Ground. Tortosa won, they close the glorious Year, For wintry Scenes o'er all the Fields appear. ON SOLITUDE. Nunquam minus Solus, quam cum Solus. What Charms, O Solitude! reside in thee? Thou art no Solitude at all to me. Tho' the World gives thee but an empty Name, Thy sweet Society is still the same. Is he Alone, who can with Heav'n converse, And entertain his Mind with rural Verse? Can bid his Thoughts, in pleasing Raptures rise, And find out Company above the Skies? What tho' no human Sound the Hermit hears, Yet Nature's Musick strikes his wondring Ears, Her Voice to him in Silence speaks around, Speaks from the lofty Skies and lowly Ground. Sweet is the Sound, and charming is the Theme, 'Tis heard in ev'ry Breeze, in ev'ry purling Stream, In ev'ry flying Bird, or flying Cloud, That thunders thro' the liquid Air aloud. God is the Theme of Nature's glorious Song, The Stars repeat it as they roll along, The Vallies echo with the chearful Voice, And in the solemn Truth the Hills rejoice. Here o'er the Meadows I securely stray, Now write, or read, or with the Pencil play, While Nature dictates what I must indite, And all Creation rises to the Sight. Nature's a fair Original, and he Who draws her well, must all her Features see, Mark every Charm, and love her Company. Now thro' the Woods, and Plains, I wildly rove, And range from Hill to Hill, and Grove to Grove; Or sing responsive to the feather'd Race, Wind the swift Fugue, or airy Echos chace. Pursue the wandring Motion of the Stream, Or on its Banks in pensive Slumbers dream, Where Osiers weave a Covering for my Head, And pleasing Gloom, with artless Arbors spread. Now on some Mountain, tune the Muse's Lyre, While Nature, and its God, each Lay inspire. Thus variously consume the shining Day, While Time, on Wings of Peace, dissolves away. But who can treat of Solitude in Noise, Or sing her Praise, who has not felt her Joys; Hermits alone, her Pleasures can explore, And paint her best, who often view her o'er. TO AURELIA. How bless'd is that successful Swain, Who shall the bright Aurelia gain? In whom original we find Such happy Excellence of Mind, And copy from the gentle Fair, An easy Wit, an easy Air; Such melting Sounds flow from her Tongue, To hear her sing, old Age grows young, Each Fibre dances to her Strains, And Pleasure thrills along the Veins. But when those Lips sage Speech unfold, To hear her talk, the Youths grow old; That Tongue informs them to be wise, And guards the Mischief of her Eyes. Let deep Interpreters explain This bold Ænigma, I maintain, How the same Organ can inspire, Wisdom in Youth, in old Age Fire. TO CELIA. Again the Spring salutes the Year, Again the Sun returns, And, like his Beams, a Flame of Love, Once more my Bosom burns. Part of your Charms awhile lay hid, By Winter's envious Shade; But with the new returning Light, New Charms are still display'd. So fair your Features, and each Air So exquisitely fine, That the more Light surrounds your Face, The brighter still you shine. Your Eyes have Beauties, yet unseen, Which lie from us conceal'd, Beauties which need immortal Day, To be at full reveal'd. Ladies of meaner Charms oft fly The Sun's too splendid Ray, Most beauteous, when false Lights supply The Absence of the Day: When Tapers round dark Rooms dispense A tremulating Light, Sparkling they glow, divinely fair, Beneath the Veil of Night. But flush'd with more than human Grace, You borrow'd Rays despise, To Phoebus dare appeal, and face The Lightning of the Skies. And yet the clear resplendent Day Hides half your blooming Airs, And the most bright unshaded Sky, A Cloud o'er Celia wears. Ev'n thus my Passion lies conceal'd, Too great to be express'd, Nor can the purest Language tell The Torments of my Breast. No Images can Fancy raise, To give my Passion vent, I might as soon a Painter find, Your Face to represent. Then let my silent dull Complaint Your amorous Pity move; And as you have an Angel's Looks, Oh! have an Angel's Love. Antiquities and Curiosities IN Wiltshire and Somerset. Primus Idumæas referam tibi Mantua palmas. ? tibi res antiquæ laudis &amp; artis Ingredior. Virg. Georg. II. Shall foreign Scenes still captivate our Eyes, And distant Piles and Landskips still surprize; Still shall we read of fam'd Versailles's Bow'rs, Eternal Grotts, Cascades, and gilded Tow'rs; While unobserv'd our native Stores remain, And Caverns yawn, and Mountains rise in vain? Italian Streams and Groves so oft appear, Almost the Musick of the Place we hear, Oft have we heard of vast Vesuvio's Womb, Oft of the Catacombs stupendous Tomb, And god-like Lineaments of Antient Rome. Who is a Stranger to the pois'nous Grott, And can Puzzoli's Wonders be forgot? Grateful the Theme; but when so oft enjoy'd, The View grows languid, and Attention's cloy'd. Tir'd with a Series of repeated Strains, Muse turn thy Prospect to Britannia's Plains; Some Marks of Grandeur, some of Age we find, In her lone Isle, tho' rough and unrefin'd. See with what Pride stupendous Stonehenge stands, Of antient Date, and built by unknown Hands: Amidst the Plain, the tall gigantic Pile Looks like some desolate unshelter'd Isle Far in th'Atlantic Ocean left alone, When Seeds of Nature were promiscuous thrown. First to our View a Groupe of Rocks arise, Of various Shape, and of unweildy Size: Vast is their Number, vast their Bulk and Height, As if design'd to bear some Babel's Weight; They stand in sullen Majesty, and frown With Aspect stern, upon the gentle Down. Thus on a Plain, themselves had level made, The Giants stood, with Thunder undismay'd, With Brow sublime, defy'd th'ethereal Tow'r, And, arm'd with Rocks, dar'd Jove's avenging Pow'r. As o'er Creation's wondrous Works we find The Stamp of Wisdom, and a regent Mind, So Signatures of Art impress the whole, Bright thro' the Ruins, and point out a Soul. Columns of Stone cemented cross on high, And form a stately Portal to the Eye: Some o'er the Plain, like Tityus stretch'd, extend, Or lean, each Moment ready to descend. Others in massy Fragments hang sublime, Majestic Spoils, the Triumph of old Time! And seem the silent Guardians of the Plain, Like some tall Pharos, pendant o'er the Main. Such was the ruin'd Scene, Historians tell, When the Colossus in an Earthquake fell; Pillars and Arms lay spread on every Side, The falling Statue rais'd itself a Tide, And swell'd the Sea, o'er which it stood astride. In vain sagacious Antiquaries try To trace these Works thro' long Obscurity, And, sunk in Gothic Æras, to restore The sacred Relicks, and their Cause explore. For whether rais'd the Frontier Lands to bound, A hallow'd Terminus of conquer'd Ground; Or peaceful here, the slaughter'd Nobles sleep, That future Eyes might o'er these Altars weep; Or for a Temple to the Sun design'd, Like that which once on Cynthian Delos shin'd, Is still unknown; we but Conjectures raise, Lost in the Circle of devouring Days. The Sage who loves to pore in antient Time, May find Chimeras in his Fancy chime: In Busts, and ruin'd Urns, deluded, read Imaginary Memoirs of the Dead: See Runic Periods peep thro' regal Rust, And idolize false Shrines of sacred Dust, For Cornucopias and Medaillons pine, And to the Pow'r of Fiction Sense resign. But Truth, immortal Truth! still bright appears, Dispells the Darkness of a thousand Years, Spreads Light divine 'mongst Urns and Heroes Graves, As Tapers burn in subterranean Caves. As anxious Politicians pant for News, Or Critics long some Libel to peruse; As sighs the Beau for an Assembly Day, Or Ladies languish for a Modern Play, With Thirst immortal, thus the Muse proceeds, Where Novelty inspires, or Fancy leads. Now Selbury-hill, a Monument august, Salutes our View, the Tomb of royal Dust. Near Marlbro's splendid Town of antient Fame, Immortal made by Churchill's glorious Name, Where generous Hertford keeps his rural Seat, And lives, retir'd from Noise, in silent State, The lofty Pile its reverend Head erects, And o'er the Down a distant Shade projects. 'Twas here, traditionary Legends say, The Roman Eagles wav'd in dread Array; Here letter'd Coins, and lawrel'd Heads are found, Enrich'd with Rust, beneath the hallow'd Ground, And Urns and Tumuli of Heroes slain Memorial, grace the antiquated Plain. No Trees amidst the wide expanse are seen, No Vales nor Hedges break the charming Scene, Thro' one vast Carpet uniformly green. As some tall Pile o'erlooks th'inferior Town, So stands the Hill conspicuous on the Down. We see the verdant Fabric with Surprize On the smooth Area regularly rise. Thus was the Indian World at first amaz'd, When at bold Cortez' tow'ring Sails they gaz'd, And trembled on their silent Shores, to see The floating Castles sweep their pathless Sea. A Vale profound, from whose paternal Bed The mighty Pile first rose, is round it spread. The grateful Hill its Sire beneath sustains, With the rich Moisture of descending Rains. Old Story says, thro' Centuries of Shade, A slaughter'd Prince beneath these Piles was laid, Yet in Fame's Book his Memory shall bloom, Preserv'd from Wreck by such a glorious Tomb. Thy Tomb, O unknown Prince! shall flourish still, And an eternal Verdure dress thy Hill, When rich Mausoleums shall consume in Rust, And Ægypt's Wonders moulder into Dust; When mighty Names expire, and none can say Where the great Heroes liv'd, or where they lay. Others may in their gilded Urns repose, Or shine in Marble, where the Yew Tree grows; In Paint or Medals live, and blaze a while, In fine Inscriptions, or a tragic Stile; This Hill secure thy Fame unfaded keeps, For Thee in Dew it every Morning weeps, For Thee the Fields which once bright Sunshine bless'd, Are every Day in sable Mourning dress'd, Mourning which envious Time shall never fade, While o'er the Plain the Hill reflects its Shade. A neighb'ring Scene presents new Wonders next, Almost within the Shade the Hill projects, When in the blushing Sky the Sun ascends, And into distant Fields the Gloom extends. Where Kennet rises with a pregnant Rill, And glides thro' fatt'ning Meads serenely still, Old Avebury's Relicks feed the curious Eye, And great in Ruins Roman Structures lie. By Time consum'd, huge Fragments only say, Where nobler Piles in distant Ages lay. Witness gigantic Heaps which Fortune left, By sacred Ransack of the rest bereft, While Towns and Churches flourish by the Theft. A vast Intrenchment still surrounds the Place, And massy Stones adorn the hallow'd Space. Pile after Pile, once lay far stretch'd along, In silent Order, like the starry Throng. Yet scatter'd stand some Pyramids of Stone, Promiscuous left, and each a Rock alone. So when Jerusalem's proud Walls were raz'd, The Streets ran bloody, and the Temple blaz'd, Some Tow'rs the Conqu'ror left, his Spoils to grace, And mark the antient Splendor of the Place. From open Prospects, and a View serene, The trav'lling Muse surveys a diff'rent Scene, Where, Somerset! thy charming Landskips rise Alternate, and relieve our wearied Eyes; Where Hills, Woods, Vales, and Hedges sweetly blend, And Prospects in a gay Confusion end. Oh! had I Skill thy Beauties to explore, And trace the rural Paradise all o'er, Each Hill should rise with a poetic Name, And not a Riv'let flow unknown to Fame; Avonian Streams with Hippocrene's compare, And Quantoke Hills with Mount Aonia share; Nor should the Vale beneath unsung be lost, The richest Soil Britannia's Realm can boast. Bath's sov'reign Wells with Spaw or Pyrmont vie, And Health on Zephyrs Wings around her fly, Divinity reside in ev'ry Cell, And Demigods in thy thick Forests dwell. Fir'd with a social Sympathy, which flows From native Air, the Muse this Tribute owes, Blest Somerset! to thee, whose happy Groves, Her Sex's Glory, Philomela loves. Yet thy bright Parts but glimmer thro' these Lines, And mix'd with Spots thy chequer'd Beauty shines, Which, like dark Patches in Aurelia's Face, Improve by Contrast each surrounding Grace; Or as o'ershadowing Clouds of sable Die, Set off the Lustre of the azure Sky. Now Chedder Cliffs, far fam'd, our View invite, And o'er rough Mendip's Glebe we speed our Flight, And as the sadd'ning Green we bound along, Mendip itself demands the Muse's Song. Hail! ye bleak Mountains, lin'd with hidden Store, Fallacious Wilds disguising Mines of Oar. Rich Veins of Calamine thy Desart fills, And Lead the solid Basis of thy Hills. Thus thro' the Veil of Want we often find Bright Charms within, and a luxuriant Mind. The guiltless Swain here slumbers on a Rock, Or with his Crook directs the wandring Flock. Savage the Scene, and barbarous the Plain, And Desolation ruful spreads its Reign. The Fern in humble Forests waves around, And sable Furzes darken all the Ground. Haggard some solitary Trees appear, And o'er the Waste their starveling Branches rear; Their naked Fronts like the stern Cyclop stand, When he pursued Ulysses to the Strand. The wither'd Tops confess eternal Blight, And hungry Ravens on the Branches light. Around our Head familiar Lapwings play, With hov'ring Wings, and bask in open Day. While at a Distance rapid Falcons buoy'd With poised Pinions, skim the liquid Void; The tuneful Larks, still chanting, upwards climb, And, lost in Æther, Sea-gulls soar sublime. And now with awful Front tall Cliffs arise, And gaping Chasms, and ruin'd Heaps surprize. Two Chains of Rocks erect on either Hand, O'er many a Furlong stretch'd, contiguous stand: With solemn Brow gigantic Tops ascend, And o'er the Vale with threatning Aspect bend: The nodding Arches big with Ruin show, And, prominent, still frown with pond'rous Woe. Thus tottering hangs upon a single Thread, The Sword just dropping on the Tyrant's Head. Their adamantine Fronts ascend so high, Half way, they bid Defiance to the Sky; While solid Ribs, like Parapets, from far, Present an Image of embattled War. Amidst the craggy Piles some Spots of Green, And pendant Shrubs with leafless Tops are seen. Uncommon Herbs, peculiar to the Place, Peep thro' the Fissures, and the Prospect grace. The studious Simpler here delights to stray, Nature his Guide, and his Companion Ray; And when some long sought Plant its Features shows, The Sage with philosophic Rapture glows; Pleas'd with the green Anatomy, now roves Thro' untrod Paths, and vegetable Groves, The curious Texture of each Herb to find, Whither of bulbous or umbellous Kind. This Search, Great Cowley! thy last Hours employ'd, When with gay Life, and courtly Duty cloy'd; The Fields then saw their Fugitive again, And bloom'd afresh in his botanic Strain. Here garden Flowers on Precipices grow, And with wild Sweets, and untaught Beauty blow; Pale Pinks, and purple Stocks the Air perfume, And fragrant Woodbinds in the Desart bloom. Fantastic Mixture! like the uncouth Grace Of blushing Paint laid o'er an antient Face. Yon lonely Beasts browse on the savage Weed, And o'er the vast Abyss securely feed: In Ætna's Shade thus sleeps th'advent'rous Swain, Till Clouds of Sulphur intercept the Plain. Along the rocky Vale pale Trav'lers ride, Fenc'd with aspiring Walls on either Side; Before the View unfathom'd Vista's lie, And Theatres of Horror fill the Eye, Each winding Sound reactive Hills repeat, And echoing Flocks from distant Pastures bleat. Thus thro' the parting Sea great Moses fled, While the uplifted Waves forsook their Bed, And pil'd on high, in terrible Array, Silent withdrew, and made, and fenc'd the Way. Thus we forsake this solitary Gloom, Like Ghosts departing from a vaulted Tomb; And quitting Chedder's Rocks, again arise On Mendip Hills, and breathe serener Skies. Anon monastic Wells its Domes erects, And from its gilded Spires the Sun reflects. Wells, whose Cathedral, with majestic Air, Sublime, may with Italian Piles compare; Nor can Turin or Padua fair display, Pillars more splendid, or a Front more gay. But while the Works of Art attract our View, Here Nature shews uncommon Wonders too. Where Wookey-Hole dilates with hideous Look, Dark as the Passage to th'infernal Brook. Low in the Covert of a neighb'ring Vale, Where nightly Dews from weeping Rills exhale, Deep sunk beneath a Hill, the Cavern yawns, A dismal Gulph! and saddens all the Lawns, Vast and impervious; not one Beam of Light There sheds its Lustre, to dispel the Night; Only faint Tapers guide our doubtful Way, And scatter thro' the Gloom a sickly Ray. As when Æneas, led by fond Desire, To see the Shade of his departed Sire, Felt when he first approach'd the dreary Plains, A sudden Horror shudder thro' his Veins, Astonish'd, thus we walk with secret Dread, And seem to trace the Regions of the Dead. The weeping Rocks distil with constant Dews, And still a new form'd Drop the last pursues. Emblem of Time, which in successive Tides, Wave after Wave, in endless Motion glides. I see Time's hoary Monarch, seated here, Record the Drops, and guide the circling Year. Pleas'd with the Shade of these coeval Cells, In silent State, the Sire of Ages dwells, Reclining on a Rock, the Moments rolls, And counts the Revolutions of the Poles. Still groping thro' the dark Recess, we find New Scenes of Wonder to amuse our Mind; A gentle Lake, sedate as Lethe, stands So clear, its Bottom shews deep shining Sands; A hollow Rock the silver Flood contains, Which never sinks with Drought, nor swells with Rains. Thro' craggy Paths and Labyrinths we stray, Entomb'd alive, and wish for absent Day. Here a low Track, anon a spatious Room, Where the high Vault collects substantial Gloom, So vast the Arch, the Cavity so wide, Scarce can the Eye extend from Side to Side. High o'er the Roof alternate Echos wave, And every Step sounds sighing thro' the Cave; From Cell to Cell the wandring Accents flow, And, oft returning back are loath to go. But if you'd hear it thunder under Ground, Thro' the still Grotto let your Pistol sound, Unnumber'd Echoes ring from Rock to Rock, And all the Cavern trembles with the Shock. Slow, from some unknown Source, a River flows, And lonely wandring murmurs to repose, Thro' dark Meanders bends its silent Rout, And at the Cave's wide Conduit issues out. Swift o'er the Sands the purling Waters play, With smiling Waves, pleas'd with long absent Day. Fam'd Alpheus' Stream is story'd thus to rise, And see new Light beneath Sicilian Skies. So Boetic Anas permeates the Earth In secret Ducts, and knows a second Birth. Nor shall thy neighb'ring Piles, O Stanton Drew! Tho' unobserv'd, escape the Muse's View, Whose Theatres could once with Stone-henge boast, Now sunk in Ruins, and in Silence lost. Tho' small the Village and obscure its Name, These solemn Memoirs eternize its Fame; Like patriarchal Monuments they rise, Of various Figures and gigantic Size. Thy Birth-place here, immortal Lock! we trace, And Wrinton owns the consecrated Place: Still may thy Praises fill the neighb'ring Shore, Scarce Samos for her Sage could merit more, Whose tow'ring Mind forsook the servile Crowd, Itself a Star, and chas'd the Schoolmen's Cloud; Who taught the Youth on Reason's Wings to soar, And struck out Morning where 'twas Mist before. Yet thy grave Pen, like Cato's, too severe, Frown'd on the trembling Muse with Looks austere. For could the Splendor of thy Name be kept, If o'er thy Urn each Bard had silent slept? Who can the Dawn of thy great Genius trace, And not with Adoration view the Place? And tho' no pompous Monument appears, No Marble Statue to demand our Tears, Yet near thy Birth-place Providence has thrown These firm Memorials of immortal Stone. But see! near yonder Mountain edg'd with Blue, A smoaky Prospect breaks upon the View; Half hid in Mist, see rising Turrets fair, And gleaming Rays illume the dusky Air; Now ruddy Buildings strike the dazzled Eye, And with Aurora's Livery gild the Sky. A busy Theatre invites our Stay, And calls the Muse unwillingly away, Who leaves her rural Paradise with Pain, And views thy Pomp, O Bristol! with Disdain. Yet she must on; the Voice of Commerce calls, Loud as Fame's Trumpet, or her Cannon Balls. Who can so near this noisy Centre guide His wandring Steps, nor with the Torrent glide? As long the weary Pilot strives in vain, To shun some dire Charybdis in the Main, Such as alarms Sicilia's frighted Shores, Or at fam'd Maelstroom near th'Arctic roars, Till on the whirling Waves the Vessels sweep, And snatch'd at once, are plung'd into the Deep. Thus with thy Tide, O Severn! born along, I join the Croud, and mingle with the Throng, Lost in the Gulph of Business, quit the Shade, And view the glorious Energy of Trade. Trade! on whose Wings the Dircean Poet born, Might launch secure, and his Olympus scorn; He must like Phidias paint, like Pindar climb, Who draws the Grandeur of thy Theme sublime. On thy vast Wheels inferior Kingdoms move, As Planets circle in their Spheres above. I only touch, a Stranger, on thy Shore, But glympse thy Greatness, nor attempt to soar. Thou, pregnant Commerce! art the Source of Peace, Parent of Arts, and Parent of Increase; By thy diffusive Stores all Nations smile, Thou art to every Clime a second Nile. Pacific Bristol with thy Plenty flows, And all her Splendor to the Rudder owes. As Paphia's Queen, thou, sprung from Ocean's Womb, Dost charm all Nature with victorious Bloom. Blest with thy Bloom, eternal Spring resides, And distant Harvests float upon our Tides: When Winter blasts the Beauties of the Year, Thou bring'st the Spring of other Countries here: The Sun may there with warmer Influence shine, We share the Golden Fruit, the Purple Vine. Each Climate is thy own; thy Wings, the Sails; The Oars, thy Arms; thy Breath, soft Zephyr's Gales. Thou, Commerce! may'st the Stars thy Pilots boast, Each Haven is thy Inn, each Prince thy Host: Kings are but Tenants to thy Farms and Thee, O! Glorious Commerce! Landlord of the Sea: Their Sceptral Sway must to the Trident bow, They the Receivers, but the Donor Thou: For Thee Golconda's wealthy Caverns shine, And the rich Mountains of Peru are thine. O! Goddess! Bristol owns thy gentle Power, To her descending in a Golden Show'r. View her gay Palaces, her pompous Piles, See Cornucopia o'er her Severn smiles: How bright her Squares, how the fair Haven charms, And holds both Indies crowded in its Arms. The burden'd Tide heaves up the floating Store, And having lodg'd it, leaves again the Shore; But, like a thrifty Carrier, loads both Ways, And back to Sea departing Ships conveys. Thus, like thy River, pants a Mother's Breast, With Streams of Milk, where smiling Infants rest: Thy Ships, rich Severn! are thy Sons, which throng Thy nursing Bosom, as they sail along. Still may thy Waves expand, with softest Gale, And Bristol's milky Treasure never fail, While pregnant Vessels on thy Surface glide, Or painted Flags wave o'er the tumid Tide; While Tritons plough the Kingdoms of the Deep, While flames red Cancer, or pale Hyads weep. See the tall Masts, like living Forests, soar, And emulate those parent Woods which bore The flying Towers, and furnish'd out the Store: Hear the Guns thunder, Sailors shout below, Not Rome, in Triumph, such a Scene could show. Here circling Business moves on fervent Wheels, And ev'ry Breast a glowing Ardor feels. Thy zealous Merchants at the Tollsey range, And, on this little Spot, the World exchange. 'Twas thus great Tyre, the Mart of Nations grew, And naval Carthage on its Banners flew: Britannia thus, inferior Empires braves, High on the Helm enthron'd, amidst the Waves. The Seas alike, her and the World surround, She awes the World, and, like it, knows no Bound. But now these busy Scenes no longer please, The Muse forsakes the Tumult of the Seas: But as Neptunian Bristol draws her Wealth From Watry Stores, to these she owes her Health. Fast by the Banks where slumb'ring Avon flows, Where rocky Hills romantic Scenes disclose; Where Belles, in gilded Chariots, take the Air, And, at a Distance, splendid Villa's glare; Where Beaus, for Ev'ning Solitude, retire, To kindle some, and some to damp their Fire; A Fountain glides, salubrious, from a Rock, Like that which wond'rous gush'd, when Moses spoke. A Stream more sacred than Castalio's Fount, Or that which murmur'd near th'Aonian Mount, A genial Heat the tepid Fountains send, Warm like the Blood which they're design'd to mend. Here some for Pleasure, some for Health resort, These find a Hospital, and those a Court. Swoln Hydrops here a lesser Size assumes, And with new Vigour meagre Phthisis blooms. No more consuming Diabetes flows; And with new Blush the pallid Virgin glows; Deformed Lepra leaves its livid Stain, And purer Currents glide in ev'ry Vein, Pure as the Streams they drink, which silent flow Thro' chalky Ducts, and mineral Veins below. Yet other Scenes the restless Mind invite, Still pants the Breast impatient for the Flight, New Play-things thus the Infant's Taste employ, Old Sports still drown'd in some succeeding Toy. On Avon's gentle Tide serene we soar, While echoing Music answers to the Oar, Flies o'er the Waves, and dies along the Shore. The wealthy Stream, now navigable made, Bears on its back the Pyramids of Trade; The Trees and Villages dance swift away, And transient Shadows o'er the Waters play, Till Bath! thy Piles elate, in Pomp surprize, And emulate the Hills which round thee rise. Hail! great Asylum of the Sick and Weak, How shall my Verse thy healing Wonders speak! As Bards of old Pirene first drank, then writ, Thy Waters thus inspire poetic Wit, Diffuse new Vigour o'er the languid Frame, And kindle in the Blood a sprightly Flame. The feeble Nerves receive a firmer Tone, Convulsions fly, and Cholics cease to groan: Hush'd are the Sorrows of the Female Sex, Nor Hypo sighs, nor Rheumatisms vex; No more the trembling Paralytic reels, But animated Power all Nature feels. Hygeia here array'd in Light appears, With Beauty deck'd, and in the Bloom of Years. High on the Mountain's Top she peaceful reigns, Smiles on the Sick, and banishes their Pains, While Graces round her breathe the softest Strains. She guides the secret Conduits of the Springs, And bears immortal Hebe on her Wings. But say, ye Genii of the Shades below, Where, hid in Caverns, infant Zephyrs blow, How filtred Fountains thro' the Strata creep, Ooze thro' the Globe, ascending from the Deep, Now silent gleet thro' Veins of Iron Oar, And rob the smoaking Sulphur of its Store; Climb o'er the Cells where unborn Atoms rest, And future Insects slumber in their Nest; Thro' spangling Salts of cooling Nitre weep, Where infant Seeds of Vegetables sleep, Till with extracted mineral Virtues fill'd, The teeming Wells prolific Currents yield, By Nature drawn with chymic Labor flow, Distill'd in her alembic Pipes below, In Tubes convey'd, arise in reeking Dews, And round th'impregn'd Air rich Steams diffuse. Imperial Bath! behold thy Princes wait, And gilded Chariots throng at every Gate. See Crouds each Morning to thy Pump-house press, And Beaus inspir'd, the hallow'd Fountains bless. Ev'n S? drinks Courage. C?n learns to sigh, And consecrated Crutches hang on high; Prophane T?y at thy Temple bows, And to the streaming Altar pays his Vows. Thus throng'd the Sick to Epidaurus' Shrine, Ador'd the Tomb, and felt the Cure divine. Here Art and Nature with each other vie, And in alternate Contrast strike the Eye. Here glitt'ring Flambeaux in long Order blaze, And blending, form a Galaxy of Rays. The fair Cathedral shines with solemn Grace, To awe the gaudy Follies of the Place. The Terrass Walks smooth Elegance disclose, And beauteous Limes extend in shady Rows. Harmonious Views on every Side delight, Ev'n Stones and Trees theselves are here polite: While artless Nature, to compleat the Scene, O'er the gay City looks with rugged Mien. The hanging Hills romantic Forests crown, Here Caverns yawn, tall Precipices frown, And nod with awful Horror o'er the Town, Tir'd with the noisy Splendor of the Place, Now Froom concludes the long laborious Race. Welcome, blest Shore! hail, happy native Seat! From Pomp and Vanity a safe Retreat. Renown'd for Trade! for thee the fleecy Trains Feed on high Mountains and Iberian Plains: Thy Looms the Scythian Savages supply, And warm the Russians in their frozen Sky. For thee the vast Leviathan is slain, And Indian Insects shed a purple Stain, Thy crouded Streets are with fair Plenty crown'd, And Industry smiles joyful all around. THE POWER of LOVE. In me tota ruens Venus Cyprum deseruit. Hor. Ode XIX. L. 1. Farewel, my Muse, to rural Themes, To verdant Fields, and murm'ring Streams; Farewel to evey silent Shade, Every Grove, and every Glade; Farewel, ye Songsters of the Sky, To Love's superior Charms I fly. Come, Love! and in my Bosom rest, Come, fill each Region of my Breast. Tho' a new Liv'ry cloaths the Ground, And Hedges blossom all around; Tho' Odours breathe from every Plant, And Birds o'er all the Meadows chant, Yet, charming Celia! when with thee, No Birds I hear, no Beauties see; Thou art my only favorite Theme, My daily Song, and nightly Dream. E'er since the lovely Maid was seen To pass along the neighbouring Green, Love's Force I've felt; and oh! I find Strange Revolutions in my Mind. On her th'attentive Shepherds gaz'd, And, mute with Wonder, stood amaz'd, And dropt their Crooks; while at her Sight The Country grew almost polite. As musing underneath a Tree, She smil'd upon my Sheep and me, The gentle Passion seiz'd my Heart, And watchful Cupid threw his Dart: Then vanquish'd Nature droop'd her Head, All the gay Scenes about me fled; The solemn Shades delight no more, Nor Riv'lets murmur'd as before; The pining Flowers lost all their Smell, And as she pass'd, their with'ring Glories fell. To move my Passion I defy Ev'n all the Earth, and all the Sky. The Stars, those Eyes of Night, can't shine, My Celia! half so bright as thine, Not all their Influence can compare With thine, thou charming, lovely Fair! Thou shed'st a more indulgent Ray, And more celestial far than they. In vain the Trees with Breezes sport, And, whispering, my Attention court. In vain the God of Day around, With pregnant Blessings warms the Ground; While Herbs arise with all their Sweets, And Zephyrs fan in cool Retreats: The Trees will wither, Herbs will fade, But Celia's Beauty knows no Shade; The radiant Sun itself descend, And all its blooming Triumphs end. Spring smiles, but wintry Scenes appear, My Celia shines throughout the Year. Or should her with'ring Winter come, And blast the fair one in her Bloom, Shou'd Nature's Frame dissolve away, Celia has Charms that ne'er decay, Charms that will shine in Worlds above, Bright as the Day, eternal as my Love. Let Nature summon all her Pow'rs, Arabian Sweets, and Myrtle Bow'rs; In every Bush let Roses glow, And Beds of Violets round me blow, Perfumes distill from ev'ry Tree, And ev'ry Scene be Italy, And ev'ry Month as fine, as gay, As is the smiling Month of May. Let the first Age again arise, With Halcyon Days, and cloudless Skies, Fair Eden's Products bless the Ground, While shining Æras take their Round, Yet Nature, thus adorn'd, would yield, And Paradise to thee, must quit the Field. In vain the Shepherds pipe around, While Echos wanton with the Sound; In vain the Nymphs, the Deities, And all the rural Companies, The sylvan Goddesses, the Fawns, Who grace the Woods, or haunt the Lawns, Try all their Music, all their Skill, That I may love the Country still. In vain Diana, with her Horn, Awakes the purple, silent Morn, Another Goddess calls to me, Diana! no less fair than Thee. Blithe Pan a Holiday would keep, And dance before his sober Sheep; While Nymphs fantastic round him sing, And welcome in the charming Spring. Go, Pan! with all thy jovial Train, Go, gambol on the sunny Plain; Or take thy merry Evening Round, While Shades are lengthen'd o'er the Ground: O Pan! my Celia calls to me, With more Authority than thee; She call'd, and lo! I strait withdrew, Farewel, ye Country Scenes! ye Swains! Adieu. THE PAPER-KITE. Fertur in arva volans, plausumq; exterrita pennis, Dat cœlo ingentem; mox aere lapsa quieto, Radit iter liquidum, celeres neque commovet alas. Virg. Æn. L. V. While grov'ling Sports the humble Croud delight, My Muse shall trace aloft the Paper-Kite, Which on expanded Wings sublimely flies, And with Dædalian Skill ascends the Skies. Say then, how modell'd by mechanic Art, She boasts true Symmetry in ev'ry Part. And first two crossing Sticks you aptly join, Then gird each Corner with surrounding Twine. To make the arched Piece a Thorn you tie, For light Materials are the best to fly. Next let the Sides at equal Distance swing; The least Excess retards her airy Wing. So Cooks first poize the Spit, and oft essay, Lest, dire Mishap! this Side should that outweigh. In Form quadrangular the Fabric stands, Erected Idol of laborious Hands. Now round the wooden Frame the Youth rejoice, And hail the half-form'd Kite with grateful Voice. Not mathematic Sages triumph more, Who figur'd Schemes and Orbs above explore. The Grecians thus acclaim'd their Horse of Wood, When fraught with Vengeance on the Shore it stood. The Body next with Paper Sail they fill, With Paste cemented by superior Skill. To represent the Wings at either Side, Two fringed Tufts like Pulpit Bobs are ty'd. In equal Focus's then floats between, The central String, which guides the whole Machine, While, rudder-like, the Tail beneath is bound, And sweeps its lengthen'd Train in State along the Ground. You who new Pamphlets or old Folios prize, Now guard your learned Shelves with watchful Eyes, For oft unthinking Boys, on Plunder bent, To form their Kite, have labour'd Volumes rent. Oft the Concordance suffers for its Age, Its blotted Lines, and dark, tremendous Page. Here pond'rous Pool, with Scotus' empty Stuff, In Ruins fall, their Bulk is Crime enough. In the same Fate discordant Parties mix, And great Le Clerc here joins with Dr. Hicks. Here Hobbs with Hall, or Hammond, falls a Prey, And rakish Rochester is tack'd to Ray. Now Cowley's sacred Leaves with Ballads fly, And Whigs with Tories friendly mount the Sky. But oh, rash Youth! th'immortal Page forbear, Nor Lock's, nor Cudworth's gen'rous Essays tear, On Schoolmen waste your Rage, but not your Time, And let the dark Imposer mount sublime. The Kite, compleated thus, is born along, By some blest Leaders of the shining Throng, Who to the Fields elate with Joy repair, And wait the Blast that wafts her in the Air. So when some new-built Ship is launch'd for Sail, And only tarries for the prosp'rous Gale, Th'impatient Crew each rising Breeze explore, And long to see her sail, and quit the Shore. Now from the central String extends the Line, And for the Flight lie harness'd Rolls of Twine. This takes the String, remote his Partner stands, And holds the Kite, impatient, in his Hands. She tugs to go; he scarce without a Prayer, Commits the struggling Engine to the Air. But oh! what Passions fluctuate in his Mind, To whom th'important Office is consign'd, To whom 'tis giv'n to steer the rising Kite, Pilot her Motions, and assist her Flight! Soon as she mounts, he flying meets the Wind, Oft chides his Mate, and often looks behind. The trickling Twine glides thro' his glowing Hand, And Joy transporting flushes all the Band, Applauding Shouts pursue her as she flies, And raise the Wind that bears her to the Skies. So Larks on poised Pinions soar sublime, In Ether lost, still singing as they climb. The Paper Yatch high hovers with its Train, While Birds affrighted leave th'ethereal Plain All vacant to her Sweep, and wondring find Their Empire lessen'd, and their Flight confin'd. Oft when th'unballanc'd Kite requires more Sail, Their Hats and Handkerchiefs assist the Tail. Oh happy Boy! who now with Pleasure sees His flying Glove mount on the airy Breeze, How does he almost fly with rapt'rous Charms, To meet the Bird descending to his Arms! And how transported tell to listning Crouds, This is the Glove which lately reach'd the Clouds! Scarce are deluded Papists pleas'd so much, When their blest Robes retain some Idol's Touch. Not Seamen more, from Nile, or Ganges' Coast, Or Plata's Shores, their sar-fetch'd Treasure boast. But if the Line by some Misfortune breaks, Her lofty Seat the prone Machine forsakes, In many a giddy Vortex whirl'd around, Like Icarus swift rushes to the Ground All torn, the anxious Troop about her throng, And weeping bear the shatter'd Frame along. While all to view each gaping Breach are griev'd, As if themselves had every Wound receiv'd. And as their Hands the shipwreck'd Bird repair, Some blame the Architect, and some the Air. But if supported by a gentle Breeze, She glides serene, and rises by Degrees, Far as the Line permits, she still ascends, Till in the Clouds her lofty Voyage ends: Beyond our narrow Ken, will dare to soar, Where never ventrous Bird has reach'd before. Now swift on wavy Wings descending slow, She's kept from headlong Flight by Guides below; Then with a gentle Fall salutes the Earth, Caress'd by puny Bands with shouting Mirth, Their infant Accents ring from Field to Field, As when glad Victors tatter'd Ensigns wield; While fair their curled Locks in Breezes flow, And smiling Blushes in each Aspect glow. O happiest State of Life! bright Spring of Youth! Fair Period, fraught with Innocence and Truth. Of golden Æra's, and Saturnian Times, Let Poets story in romantic Rhimes, This Age, if any, is the Age of Gold, Ere thrice five Winters have their Circles roll'd. No Flames of Love, nor Wine their Breasts annoy. No Cares of Business interrupt their Joy: In soft Amusements, and the Sweets of Play, The thoughtless Chorus spend the shining Day; To grateful Sports, as grateful Books are join'd, And Study's made a Plaything to the Mind. Man's Life in its first Bud still fairest shews, As Orchards in their Bloom most Sweets disclose. Sometimes a Scene more wondrous feasts the Sight, When the mechanic Bird is rais'd by Night. For in a Paper Orb by Artists made, With dextrous Skill a Candle is convey'd; Tied to the Tail the pendant Lanthorn glows, And, mounting, lights its Passage as it goes. The Kite remote soars in a Path unseen, While the bright Tail far-stretching hangs between. Thus Jupiter we see in Light array'd, While his attending Moons are hid in Shade. Still Comet-like it sweeps, erratic Fire, And Crouds beneath the floating Blaze admire. The country Swains who at a Distance gaze, Survey the painted Meteor with Amaze, Quote from old Almanacs portentous Times, Spell future Ills, and ponder former Crimes. Partridge and mystic Moor are oft turn'd o'er, And Bunyan brought to Light, ne'er seen before; Some long ago these Wonders could foretel, When Salt prophetic at the Table fell, This Sight, blue Flame, and Hares which cross'd the Road, This, Dreams presag'd, and Ravens us'd to bode. But high the wavy Luminary shines, Till the spent Taper droops, and sick'ning pines; Thro' the dark Air the gilded Phantom flies, And rustles like a Whirlwind down the Skies. So with her Lamp the Muse ascends the Sphere, Pleas'd in her little Orb to flutter there, Till the dim Light expiring dies away, Like the last Ruins of declining Day, And thus descending with the Paper Kite, With her alike concludes th'adventrous Flight. ON THE Lady B???ton's Birth-Day. Hæc est illa Dies, magni quæ conscia Partûs. Once more the Day returns which bless'd the Earth, And crown'd the Year with fair Aurelia's Birth, At whose Nativity the infant Flowers Shot forth new Sweets, new Roses clad the Bow'rs; The gay Musicians of the Lyric Shade Wak'd her to Life, and hov'ring round her play'd, While the new Blushes of the orient Sun Half faded look'd, so much by her outdone. Some by their Crown, their Conquest, or their Crime, Cast a long Lustre thro' the Rolls of Time. A Saint's, a Poet's, or a Monarch's Rays, Fair in the Rubric, or the Medal blaze; Shall these in Epocha's distinguish'd live, And Immortality receive and give, In monumental Piles survive their Fate, And conq'ring Beauty fade without a Date? First may those Birds their Harmony forget, Those beauteous Flowers with all their Lustre set. The twinkling Stars not only gild the Night, But thro' the sable Day dispense their Light. In Beauty's Cause the flaming Lamp on high Begun his Giant-Journey in the Sky; Thro' the dim Cave of Space irradiate play'd, And Nature rose illustrious from its Shade, Its various Charms broke from the darksome Cell, And each harmonious String in Concert fell. View the wide Universe from Pole to Pole, Bedeck'd with Beauty, Beauty fills the whole: Each bearded Leaf sweet Symmetry betrays, And each rang'd Atom tunes its Parent's Praise. This Morn let all be joyous and serene, Calm as her Looks, and radiant as her Mien. 'Tis Vision all, or sure the conscious Skies Dart stronger Beams, and with new Glory rise: Corrected Time hence a new Cycle steers, And in his Rolls Aurelia's Stile appears. Others may celebrate their annual Feasts, And to exalt their Monarch, sink to Beasts, Devoutly curse in Raptures once a Year, Warm'd with a Flood of Bigottry, or Beer; With other Joy my Muse shall crown the Day, When the twelve Signs have march'd their golden Way, With other Fires her grateful Verse shall glow, And where Aurelia treads, her Garlands strow. Array'd in Sweets fair Flora shall be seen, And Youths exulting mark the flow'ry Green. Melodious Birds a Jubilee shall keep, And interluding Roes in Concert skip; The sportive Lambs in Salian Dances bound, While o'er the Plain glad Shepherds pipe around, And ecchoing Vallies propagate the Sound. FINIS.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">VOL. II. Agrestem tenui meditabor arundine musam. Virg. Æquum est Peccatis veniam, poscentem reddere rursus. Hor. TO The Right Honourable JOHN, Earl of Orrery, Baron Boyle of Marston in the County of Somerset, &amp;c. A POEM Sacred to the Memory of Sir ISAAC NEWTON. Per te, jam cœlum in terris, jam sidera nota, Quem primum infernis licuit cognoscere terris Munera cœlestum— Manil. I leave my wonted Themes, the Nymphs and Swains, The shady Woods, clear Streams, and sunny Plains, To sing the studious Sage, whose towering Mind To this low Spot disdain'd to be confin'd: Who to Creation's distant Regions soar'd, And Wonders hid from human Eyes explor'd; Did Nature's deep Recesses open lay, Dispel the Gloom, and spread immortal Day. O! could my Numbers like his System move, Nor from just Laws of Truth, excursive rove, Be smooth, yet nervous, regular, yet great, Harmonious, lofty, simple yet compleat, On Reason's well-pois'd Wings his Fame should rise, And Newton's Column reach beyond the Skies. Fair as the Spring, or Heav'n's ethereal Blue, See each Discovery opens to our View. See Light from him it's various Beauty draw, And every sleeping Atom own his Law: While Stars erratic regularly roll, Know their markt Orbits, and obey their Pole. He, doubtful Schemes to Demonstration brought, What Plato sung, and Samos' Prophet taught. A wondrous Power he saw diffus'd o'er all, Which unremitting governs every Ball: He saw perpetual Gravity obtain, And o'er the System hold coercive Reign; Without whose central Power, each lawless World Wou'd thro' the Void in swift Career be hurl'd, In boundless Skies still sweeping unwith-held, For Matter only moves, as 'tis impell'd, And when no foreign Energy's imprest, Is still alike inclin'd to roll, or rest. He shew'd before the wondrous Frame begun, E'er infant Rays shot radiant from the Sun, E'er darksome Planets knew their future Bound, Or ductile Air confest the flow of Sound, How in each separate Sphere, by Skill divine, Two different Powers compos'd the great Design; While the Projectile, and the Central share Balance of Empire, in celestial Air. And lo! each stagnate Mass begins its Race, Starts from its Sleep, and wheels in empty Space. Attending Moons perceive th'impulsive Force, And round their Center steer in silent Course: Still govern'd by the same mechanic Laws, Each Orb obeys the Universal Cause. With Force reciprocal in Concert shine, Associate Planets in a curved Line. Else by two Motions hung in Balance high, They'd form a glittering Desart in the Sky, A stagnate, wild, inhospitable Seat, Curst with eternal Cold, or scorch'd with Heat. But see from distant Heav'ns, a blazing Star The Comet in 1680., Visits our Coast, and flames in solar Air. Nature in Labor sickens at the sight, And fancy'd Judgments hover in its Light. The fiery Tail a Croud of Ills portends, Famine and Sword the baleful Meteor sends, The Air is poison'd with th'impending Blaze, And jarring Nations kindle at its Rays. But Newton views the Scene without Surprize, Salutes the Star, and hails it to our Skies; Its wondrous Path soon open'd to his View, And his swift Thought the lingring Light out flew; He mark'd its Motions each returning Night, Nor cou'd the Day conceal it from his sight. And now it quits our Hemisphere, and flies Beyond the narrow ken of human Eyes; Thus Newton quits it not; but sees it sweep, Far sunk behind the Curtains of the Deep: Fathoms the vast Ellipsis in his Mind, And leaves this planetary Spot behind, Still he was with it where it farthest shone, And steer'd the flying Flambeau round the Sun. Led by this Guide, he march'd from Clime to Clime, And trac'd the mazy Labyrinth of Time; Beheld it first in morning Robes appear, And dawning, usher in the infant Year. Reform'd the Æras of the Golden Fleece, And mark'd th'Olympic Kalendars of Greece. When Truth was wrapt in Shade, and Science young, Thro' the dim Space, he Lamps celestial hung, To guide the dark Historian's erring way, And o'er dull Records scatter welcome Day. The Nations taught by him, no more shall dread O'er half the Heav'ns, to see the Comet spread, But pleas'd survey the Horrors of his Tail, Worship his Beams, and his Approaches hail. The silver Moon that with resplendent Robe Majestic walks each Night around our Globe, Watchful supplies her absent Brother's room, And Queen of sleeping Nature, gilds the Gloom, By Newton watch'd in her nocturnal Rounds, Was oft observ'd to wander in her Bounds; And shewn as oft to wander with design, Recede by Rule, and quit th'Ecliptick Line. To him with various Elegance she moves, Retires in State, and regularly roves, And constantly, inconstant in her Pace, Error itself looks lovely in her Race. Thus when disorder'd Grace, and artless Shew Dwells in some Cynthia's careless Dress below, Tho' we perceive no Order in her Air, Yet Art lies hid behind each Lock of Hair, The scatter'd Charms are plac'd with so much ease, We know not how, but only that they please. The watry Orb by his attractive Laws, High in her azure Disk, the Deluge draws: Ten thousand Streams her Influence obey, And ebb, or flow by her celestial Sway. The conscious Seas the wondrous Impulse feel, And passive Billows with Reluctance reel. The long mysterious Tides, obscure no more, By Laws salute, by Laws forsake the Shore; Their various Flows on Gravity depend, Rise by its Force, and by its Force descend. To this th'uncertain Fluxes round the Earth, Ægean, or Atlantic, owe their birth, When Cynthia in her Sphere alone attracts, Or with the feebler Sun in concert acts. 'Tis thus she agitates th'elastic Air, Successive Tides confess her Influence there; In springy Filaments expanded rise, And float in wavy Circles to the Skies. Then to the Earth the Sage descending slow, Sees how th'eternal Law prevails below; Thro' all her Texture propagates its Force, And keeps inferior Nature in its Course: Else by the Globe's Rotation, Hills wou'd start, And Trees, and Towns, in tangent Lines depart. 'Tis thus the Air within its Confines flows, Moves in an Orb, and its own District knows: This Power the raging Seas, and Winds contains, Else might a Tempest reach th'ethereal Plains, The Waves ungovern'd sally from the Deep, And lawless Oceans thro' the Concave sweep. Still step by step, the Godlike Chief pursues The glorious Purpose, and the Toil renews. In vain coy Nature wou'd his Grasp elude, Conceal'd in mystic Shapes, and Solitude; He traces each Meander of her Flight, And keeps the shifting Fugitive in sight. Thro' the fine Texture of material Parts His subtle Thought with equal Swiftness darts; Attraction sees in various Form obtain, And Regent of atomic Kingdoms reign. To this ascending Fountains owe their Birth, And oozing Vapors percolate the Earth, Weep thro' the porous Stone, pervade the Hill, And filtred thro' the Glebe, in Streams distil. Thus climbs the vital Sap, and by degrees, With Heat expanded, penetrates the Trees; The vivid Blood, thus permeates the Veins, And thro' invisible Meanders strains. Thus the minutest Corpuscles attract, And little Powers in little Orbits act, Obedient at the Point of Contact draw, Embrace, and feel the universal Law. The shining Fountain of refracted Rays, In Robes of Lustre glitters to his Praise. Reform'd by him, the Day more beauteous shews, And the fair Morn with fairer Purple glows; Earth looks more charming to the curious Eye, And every Flower displays a richer Dye. While all the fair Phænomena of Light, Inform the Judgment, as they please the Sight. We see the Texture of the glittering Bow, And parent Colours from their Fountain flow; Whence variously combin'd, with blended Blaze, Starts all the wild Variety of Rays. He taught, that Bodies vibrated around, Produce the flow of Light, or flow of Sound: How ambient Air in dancing Pulses heaves, Unfolds its Web, and propagates its Waves, Thro' the thin Cantons, undulating plays, And to the trembling Organ Sound conveys. How vast, how infinite th'amazing Train Of simple Truths, which in his System reign! Beauteous Cement! in one connected Line, Like Rays from Heav'n, they in conjunction shine: Thus in Assemblage, shine the starry Rays, And form afar one undistinguish'd Blaze. Blest is the Man, whose ever-studious Mind, Can the fair Series of his Truths unwind, And step by step th'harmonious Chain pursue, Till Nature's Secrets open to his View. In Philosophic Flights he soars serene, And, rapt in Vision, sees the wondrous Scene: Th'eternal Beauty opens to his sight, Diviner Charms, and Deluges of Light. He sees the Chain from Heav'n to Earth descend, And on their latent Cause Effects depend, That unseen Cause which agitates each Sphere, Pervades the Mass, and rules the circling Year. He views th'expanded Theatre above, Where Planets in sublimer Orbits move. To still remoter Tracts, his Thoughts arise, And build exalted Stories in the Skies; Where yon fix'd Stars their own bright Vault behold, And other Spheres their spangled Lights unfold; Where other Dramas, other Suns take place, And flame throughout the Latitudes of Space. Still rising, he adores the Power which reigns, Supreme o'er all, and every part sustains. For Newton saw, fair Stamp of Hand divine, With conqu'ring Beauty o'er Creation shine; He saw a mild Omnipotence preside, And Deity diffus'd the System guide. Charm'd with this Truth, a calm Devotion fir'd, And Godlike Virtue all his Frame inspir'd. A Mind thus buoy'd above terrestrial Show, Smiles at the Comedy of Life below. The World inform'd by his unerring Rules, Quits the Enchantment of the slumbring Schools, Forsakes her vain, and visionary Schemes, The Din of Sounds, and Tyranny of Names; Authority itself can't guard the Youth, Nor, rob'd in all her Splendor, charm like Truth. She comes encircled with resistless Ray, And Sounds, and Signs, and Jargon fly away. On airy Wings, Conjecture loves to climb, And builds her Turret to the Skies sublime: There on a Globe the hov'ring Phantom dwells, Rais'd on a splendid Pyramid of Shells. There soars the Phenix, with her flaming Plumes, Fantastic Beings wander o'er the Rooms, Chimæras, Sylphs, and banisht Fairies rest, And Rosicrucian Sects the Clime infest; But Newton came, and scatter'd all the Spell, And to the ground the mimic Palace fell. He from unquestion'd Facts his Work began, And on a lasting Basis built his Plan. From plain Experiment deriv'd his Scheme, Still on Mechanic Reasoning, rais'd his Frame. And from a Pendule, or Prismatic Glass, Amazing Theorems of Truth could trace. Hail! blest Experiment, whose grateful Light, Dispels the Gloom of Sophistry and Night; Discov'ry sits, close waiting, at thy side, And Paths of Evidence thy Foot-steps guide; Error from thee, as from the Morning, flies, And Bigots half awake, see Light, and close their Eyes. But oh! what equal Honors can be paid, Illustrious Newton! to thy sacred Shade? Let every gentle Blast of wavy Air, To distant Climes, thy high Discov'ries bear, And Light in every tremulating Ray Diffuse thy Praise, who didst its Robes display: And while the watry World obeys thy Laws, Let grateful Billows swell with thy Applause. Let none for him with Tears inglorious mourn, Or shed unmanly Sorrows o'er his Urn; To grace his Exit let no human Show, Or tinsel Pomp attend his Hearse below: But Ghosts of ancient Heroes rise in State, And philosophic Shades, in Silence wait; While Meteors 'midst the dim Procession play, And Northern Streamers faintly gild the way, Or Peals of Thunder murmur o'er the Sky, Or Storms, like those, which rush, when Heroes die. See where he mounts the high, diurnal Sphere, And leaves a Trail of Light along the Air; The Stars accost him, as he soars along, And Souls of wandring Sages round him throng. Mark! where he halts on Saturn, tipt with Snow, And pleas'd surveys his Theory below; Sees the five Moons alternate round him shine, Rise by his Laws, and by his Laws decline, Then thro' the Void takes his immortal Race, Amidst the vast Infinity of Space. Modern Courtship: Inscrib'd to Miss W???t. You ask me, Delia, why Papillio reigns The Darling of the Fair, and mocks the Swains? You are a Stranger to his Charms; for know, He powders, prates, and bows profoundly low; He dresses, dances, dallies, daubs with Snuff, What think you, Delia? is not this enough? Pert, pretty, proud, and of a pliant Size, In Laces, Modes, and Treats extremely wise: No Sin so great, as Ignorance of Fashion, Clowns, in his Creed, will scarce obtain Salvation; Whate'er he says,—is with an Air so bright, Drury grows chaste, and Dullness sounds polite. He laughs, he prays, he sneezes with a Grace, Each Muscle knows its Post, each Curl its Place. As froths the Yeast fermenting from the Bung, So lambent Nonsense trickles from his Tongue. Thus Dross refin'd glides purer thro' the Still, And Rags are whiten'd in the Paper-Mill. I know you'll deem Papillio but a Fop, And all his Furniture a gew-gaw Shop, A Shop of Toys to please a dazzled Eye, Which some admire, and some pass wisely by. Women like Widgeons are decoy'd by Show, Where one the plain, ten like the painted Beau. Delia, let Phillis spend each gaudy Day, In Balls, Ridottos, Puppet-shows, and Play: As Kate with Rattles lulls the Babe to sleep, Thus one eternal Lullaby they keep. Like Squirrels pleas'd with their own tinkling Sound, And still in Motion ring one airy Round. The Wise in decent Bounds restrain their Gust, Season their Joys, nor drink but when they thirst. He tastes most Bliss who husbands well his store, We only pall our Appetite with more. Like Prodigals, the Frolick and the Gay Lavish their Stock in one short Holiday. Papillio thus, fantastically vain, Flies his own Company, and courts a Train Of low Amusements, to delude the Sense, And cheat poor Life with gay Impertinence. Thus he humms Tunes, and trifles with the Fair, Now Riddles tells, now capers in the Air. Now suddenly in love, he swears he dies, And who wou'd think,—so fine a Lover lyes? Now on his Dinner dwells, and now his Dreams Of Coffee-Grounds, Flow'rs, Weddings and whipt Creams. If such Perfections must obtain a Wife, Give me, ye Gods! a Cave, and private Life. How soft the Slumber, how secure the Shade, Safe, where no Coxcombs rush, no Fools invade? While some fair Nymph, with kind, but artless Air, Governs each rustic Song, and sooths each Care. And if some learned Friend his Stock will join, And mingle Cares with Cares, and Wit with Wine, W??lp??le, I wou'd not change my Lot for thine. Pray Ladies, listen to a country Tale, John treats his Lass with Nutmeg and with Ale; Clad in new Sunday Clothes, struts thro' the Wake, And gives her sometimes Kisses, sometimes Cake. I love thee, charming Joan! with all my heart, A Love which Death, and Death alone can part; For let me tell thee with a faithful Sigh, For thee, my Dear, I willingly wou'd die: Thy yielding Breasts, like new-press'd Cheeses shew, And thy blue Eyes are like the glossy Sloe. A-field I have ten Ewes, and ten milch Kine, Had I a hundred more, they all were thine. When home from Plough the weary Team I goad, And ease the lab'ring Oxen of their Load, While on our Elm the peaceful Poultry rest, I find a greater Burden in my Breast. Their Toil is ended with the setting Sun, But far from thee,—my Toil is just begun; Thro' all the live-long Night no rest I find, Still something lies so heavy on my Mind. Musing on thee my Sheep are wont to stray, And I with them have often lost my way; 'Twas strange at first! but I'm surpriz'd no more To lose my way, who lost my Heart before. John's Love is homely, but sincere his Heart, This Nature is, the other is but Art. For all the tinsel Courtship of the Town, Give me the honest Passion of the Clown. But oh! to dress, to dance, to sigh, to sing, To prate, to play—is so polite a thing— Thus Moderns love—Delia! you smile at this, But who thus loves, will seldom love amiss. Alas! for me there is no room for Hope, I cannot play Quadrille—nor dance the Rope. Delia, you say Baboons will do the same, Ev'n Elephants their Gambols learn when tame. How fine the Jay, how active is the Ape! Sure Fops are Monkeys in a human Shape: Birds have their Notes, and Lap-dogs know their Airs, There have been dying Polls, and dancing Bears. If Phillis smiles on such Gallants as these, I thank my Stars—I was not born to please. Others like me have felt a fruitless Pain, Granville for Myra sigh'd, but sigh'd in vain. Still sounds the Shade with Sacharissa's Name, And Thames still weeps her injur'd Cowley's Flame. Then foolish Muse! thy fond Complaints give o'er; If Delia says 'tis right, I ask no more. Now hail! ye dusky Groves, ye Fair farewel, I envy not your Bliss; nor envy you my Cell. TRANSLATIONS FROM The Italian of Signor Rolli's SONNETS. Song I. L. 1. Sweet Nymph! what means your amorous Grace, And all your beauteous Charms, If Love is absent from your Face, And Cupid flies your Arms? The radiant Splendor of your Eyes Has set my Soul on flame; But soon, alas! the Ardor dies, Unless you feel the same. When the fair Nymph enjoys those Fires Which her own Beauty gives, Blest is the Swain, who then admires, And on her Beauty lives. Then let another Phillis dare To captivate his Eye, In vain; she is not half so fair, Nor worthy of a Sigh. But if the gentle Maid returns, All ravishing, and bright, Love in his heaving Bosom burns, And trembles in his sight. Not Wealth, nor Pow'r, with all their State, Like Love can charm the Mind; Let Love and Beauty on me wait, I'll leave the rest behind. Song II. Oh! shady, solitary Grove, Receive my troubled Breast, While to thy silent Gloom I rove, And court in Shades my Rest. Those Objects which the World delight, To me no Pleasure give, The Charmer's banisht from my sight, And absent can I live? O! tell me where my Fair-one's gone, And in what Covert laid, Ye Groves, and Woods, while wild I run, And hunt from Shade to Shade. Say lovely Boughs! how oft have you From us fenc'd off the Day, While the blest Moments peaceful flew, And gently roll'd away? Say where she is, ye friendly Trees! And whisp'ring let me know: But Echo answers in the Breeze, And seems to tell me, No. I hear a Murmur in the Shade, Perhaps her sighing Strain, A Sigh from my adored Maid, That says, return again: But ah! the Brook deludes my Grief, O'er Pebbles gliding by, And only murmurs some Relief, Responsive to my Cry. What will her Pity then avail To her neglected Swain, When lying breathless, cold and pale, She weeps for me in vain? Song II. L. II. The airy Nymph prefers the Rose That with such various Beauty blows; But if it hangs too near a Thorn, To other Flowers she flies with Scorn. O! fair, but proud Irene hear What Doris said the other Day: The Rose, said she, is Queen of Flow'rs, The Pride of all the springing Year; But Jessamin that decks the Bow'rs, O'er her with blooming Lustre tow'rs. I own the Jess'min, like the Rose, Will not the Spring adorn, But drest in white it beauteous grows, And hangs without a Thorn. Others may chuse that glowing Flow'r, To entertain their Sense; But let me have fair Jess'min clad In virgin Innocence. Song IV. Beauteous Irene, say no more Of Love, now I am safe at Shore: Its Pleasures have so many Pains, And leave such Stings behind, That I'm resolv'd to quit the Chains, And free my captive Mind. Then cease, my fair Irene, cease To love; for Lovers have no Peace. No more I swear, will I consume Whole Nights without my Rest; Nor spend the cheerless Day in Gloom, With a tormented Breast: Each Moment fearing lest my Love Will treach'rous or ungrateful prove. How senseless 'tis to court those Joys, Which are so full of Smart? But the free Swain, no Care annoys, No Fevers plague his Heart: Let Curses light upon that Swain Who, when he's free, returns again. If there's no Pleasure more sincere Than Liberty, and Ease, Then wretched's he who courts the Snare, And trusts again the Seas. To the Reverend Mr. STOGDON, Author of Colin's Advice, or Damon to Nisa. I thought such a Ditty was writ By some Shepherd inspir'd by Pan; Simplicity, Softness, and Wit, Thro' each Stanza so prettily ran: 'Mongst the Grottos, the Lawns, and the Plains, Those Regions of Pleasure and Love, Where Nature condoles with the Swains, And Nymphs such soft Sentiments move. But when undeceived I knew 'Twas a Spiritual Pastor that wrote, Then without e'er a Pause I guess'd who, And trac'd you in ev'ry fine Thought. Sure divinely inspir'd you write, And Charity fir'd your Breast To compassionate Damon's sad Plight, And your Eloquence furnish'd the rest. Assemblies dissolve into Joy, And soar up in Rapture above, When your Thoughts Hallelujahs employ, And you picture a Heav'n of Love: But when you describe the last Day, And dwell on the Regions of Woe, We see all the dreadful Array, And start at the Terrors below. When disconsolate Damon alone In Silence breathes forth his sad Sighs, We too sympathize with his Moan, And view him with pitiful Eyes. Her Heart must be harder than Steel Not to soften with such a soft Muse; 'Twill soon make her Fortitude reel, Sure Nisa can never refuse. The Swain will soon have his Desire, The Courtship will happily end; The Nymph her poor Damon admire, And Damon remember his Friend. The Legacys. I leave my Carcass to the Dust, My Soul to Guardian Spirits trust; My Fortune let my Neighbours share, To my Good Name the World is Heir. VERSES To the Memory of a young Gentleman of Bristol. Huc omnis ista, quæ in foro litigat, in theatris desidet, in templis precatur, turba, dispari gradu, vadit. Et quæ veneraris, et quæ despicis, unus exequabit cinis. Senec. As springs a Flow'r beneath the orient Skies, Smiles all the Day, and in the Evening dies; Thus Phaon fled untimely to the Tomb, Effac'd his Beauties, and extinct his Bloom. His guardian Genius chid his lazy Stay, And beck'ning cry'd, Fly Phaon, fly away; Leave this fantastic Comedy below, This chequer'd Theatre of Bliss and Woe; Where Men of Pleasure have a transient Reign, And others live but to grow old in Pain. Where Good and Ill by turns the Mind amuse, And shift so fast, we know not how to chuse. Ye fond Companions, and ye happy Few, Who when he liv'd, his shining Virtues knew, Leave your vain Mirth, and mourn for ever lost, All that Good-nature, or a Friend cou'd boast. View your old Comrade in the Pangs of Death, With fainting Looks, and agonizing Breath: Then boast the tinsel Splendor of thy State, Is it a Pleasure to be bury'd great? Life smiles out fair, but Fate is ever blind, While in thy Train Death stalks unseen behind. An airy Phantom hovers round thy Dome, Or with thy last sad Tapers lights thee home: With famish'd Looks haunts thy luxurious Board, Or stands with fun'ral Napkins near my Lord. See one not idle in thy lazy Train, Pensive her Air, and in her Vesture plain; See by thy side pale Clotho rueful stands, And spins thy Fate, the Distaff in her hands. Lament the Youth, ye Groves with all your Shade, Ye Gardens which he lov'd your Glories fade; Droop, ye tall Limes, ye Poplars hang your Head, And every Leaf, ye wintry Tempests shed; Ye Flow'rs in setting Dews resign your Charms, Once wont to flourish in your Phaon's Arms. His Guardian Genius chid his dull Delay, And beck'ning cry'd, Fly Phaon, Fly away. RECOVERING FROM SICKNESS. Eternal God! thy sovereign Power Our sinking Frame can save, Scatter the dark impending Show'r, And snatch us from the Grave. The Structure of this frail Machine Was modell'd by thy Art, In every Breath thy Skill is seen, Thy Hand in every Part. By thee th'harmonious Fibres strung In decent Order move, And tunefully with silent Song Confess the Power above. Thou badst the refluent Muscle beat, And lo! each Pulse obey'd; Each conscious Atom knew its Seat, And in its Station play'd. The sprightly Flood obsequious flew Thro' every winding Vein, And vital Bellows wondrous blew To fan the purple Train. See curious Valves unlock their Springs To let the Current glide, And close again with folding Wings To stop the backward Tide. At every Tube amaz'd we stand By optic Glass descry'd, Strange Subtlety! when one small Sand A thousand Pores will hide. The Organs strung in various ways Harmoniously combine, And every Organ tunes thy Praise, O! Architect Divine. When shiv'ring Sickness, Pain, Despair, In frightful Form arose, On Thee my Soul devolv'd its Care, And sleepless found Repose. When toss'd with Heat, and vext with Pain, Long, gloomy Nights I lay, Thou thro' the dark and dismal Scene Didst spread reviving Day. May Gratitude inspire my Breast, And ev'ry Action grace; The Soul with steady Virtue blest Dissolving Worlds may face. While hov'ring round with dubious Fate Death's meagre Form stood near, The Prospect of a future State Dispell'd each gloomy Fear. In all its Pomp, eternal Day Unfolded to the View, Where other Skies new Lights display, Beyond this Cope of Blue: Where Beings, unconfin'd in Flight, With tow'ring Pinions soar Thro' boundless Latitudes of Light, And Seas without a Shore. There Songs of everlasting Praise Great God! I'll raise to thee, Till then accept these humble Lays, And still my Guardian be. THE Deserts of Devonshire. Mihi nunc Ligus ora Intepet. ? qua latus ingens Dant scopuli, &amp; multa, terra se valle receptat. Persius. Ye Sages, who wise Nature's Laws explore, And to celestial Regions studious soar, Who regulate the distant Suns on high Which nightly dart their Glories o'er the Sky; Describe each Orb revolving in its Sphere, And how the Planets round their Center steer. Look down to this neglected Globe below, And say from whence such dire Disorders flow; Uncultivated Deserts, burning Sands, Ætna's, and Earthquakes that unpeople Lands, Why fair Creation wears inglorious Stains, And some black Foil amidst each Beauty reigns. What Scenes of Horror blest Britannia yields! So rich in fertile Lands, and blooming Fields. See in each Shire deformed Prospects rise, See ruin'd Rocks, and frightful Forms surprize. Beyond where Exon rears her Steeples fair With lofty Vanes far glittering in the Air, Where Ting's impetuous Torrents swiftly glide, Resistless rolling as the raging Tide; In lawless Sway despotic Chaos reigns, And dreary Ruin desolates the Plains: While Nature takes a pleasure to be odd, And wears the ancient Spoils of Noah's Flood: Rocks, Hills, Vales, Caverns, on each side abound, And spread their solitary Scenes around. The awful Mountains labor up the Skies, And o'er your ken in cloudy Summits rise. When Heav'n's bright Chariot with triumphant Ray Has o'er Earth's Surface shed meridian Day, Half the stupendous Pile is darken'd still, And Light prevails but over half the Hill. Who can thy shapeless Wilds, O! Dartmore, trace, And see without Surprize thy haggard Face? Confusion here its mazy Line has spread, And drest the howling Mansions of the Dead. Day hurries hence, and Beauty takes its flight, While drowsy Dullness rules these Realms of Night. Hoarse Bats, and Owls, in plaintive Dirge bewail, And lazy Mists hang thick o'er ev'ry Dale. Wide, yawning Caves, Æolian Mouths present As if they ope'd to give some Monster vent. The Mountain Tops are cover'd o'er with Oaks Which long have stem'd rough Storms, and Thunder-strokes, And with bleak Limbs far stretching in the Air, And solid Trunk, autumnal Tempests dare. The Ting tumultuous rolls betwixt the Hills, And all the Country with its Murmurs fills: In haste the Torrent tumbles swiftly on, Waves press on Waves, impatient to be gone. So rough the Stream it cheats the curious Eye, Alternate Billows intercept the Sky, And half-form'd Objects just dance up and die. Nature alone manures the desert Land Which scorns all Tillage, but of Nature's Hand. Dark Furze, and darker Broom the Ground o'erspread, And dully wave a Wilderness of Shade; But blaze forth Streams, and Pyramids of Light, When thrifty Peasants on some Winter's Night, To clear th'encumber'd Ground whole Forests burn, And long extended Brakes to Embers turn. Here pond'rous Rocks vast Masses underprop, Or hideous stare stupendous from the top. Such Rocks gigantic Ægeon of yore Himself a Prodigy of Nature bore, When with audacious Hands the Rebel strove To hurl them upwards to the Realms of Jove. Here savage Stags in lonely Wilds reside, And branchy Heads in shady Coverts hide; Or browze on some green Hill, or mossy Rock, Or on the Plain stalk proud before their Flock. Till kill'd in Chase, the rural Squire's Sport, Their Horns hung high adorn his Hall or Court. Uncommon too the Natives in their Kind, Rough as the Soil, in Manners unrefin'd, Yet courteous, brave, and of an honest Mind. In humble Cottages, and homely Cells, Sweet Peace, Simplicity, and Freedom dwells: No meanless Modes, no sycophantic Arts, But Words still speak the Language of their Hearts. True Valor forms their Tempers, as of yore, When Gallic Pyrates storm'd the neighb'ring Shore; Fir'd with a native Love of Liberty They drove the tim'rous Slaves again to Sea. An hospitable Goodness fills their Breasts, And Plenty circles at their frequent Feasts: Tho' with no Epicurean Oglios stor'd, No silver Goblets glitter at their Board; Yet greater Curiosities you find, A candid Heart, and a contented Mind. 'Twas such a Life the ancient Heroes led, Blest with low Fortune, and to Virtue bred: What Nature's Calls requir'd they thankful took, Rul'd their own Minds, and drank the crystal Brook; They sought no Riches, for no Wants they knew, And Gold unminded in their Mountains grew. Health, and immortal Quiet crown'd their Days, Humble their State, but high as Heav'n their Praise. Then like exhausted Lamps, with peaceful Breath, Serenely slumber'd in the Shades of Death. THE Lilliputian Combat, OR PIGMYOMACHIA. Pygmæus parvus currit bellator in armis. Juven. One Summer's Eve, ye Muses say, At the Declension of the Day; When from their Coverts Fairies rally, And muster in some lonely Vally, O'er Fields, and Hedges nimbly trip, Or round enchanted Circles skip; Till sated with nocturnal Sport, As ancient Chronicles report, They at some Farmer's Hogshead tipple, Or pinch at night the churlish People. When Jack-a-lanthorns in the Air, Flutter with tremulating Glare, The wand'ring Light, deluded Swains Pursue o'er Desarts, Hills, and Plains, Till in some sedgy Quagmire lost They vanish with the Moon-light Ghost. Say how two Pigmies big with Rage Did terribly this Eve engage: They too like other Things take fire, And kindle into wrathful Ire. That which the Squabble first began Was who shou'd lord it o'er the Clan: Each had a Title fair, and clear, As to himself it did appear; So to avoid a World of Tattle They try the Cause in Field of Battle. Spadillo one my Muse shall name Long knighted in the Rolls of Fame: The other Mikro much renown'd In all the short Republick round For Prowess, and gigantic Size, He rose three Foot towards the Skies. A Kid, or Lambkin cou'd he wield, And chase the Ravens from the Field: Nor fled he from the angry Dam, Or fear'd the horned, warlike Ram. In a wet Day, or dewy Morn, He'd travel thro' the Fields of Corn, Trip thro' the tallest mowing Grass, And never wet his taller Face. Yet was Spadillo more heroic, And had the Courage of a Stoic. Often he vaunted that true Merit Lay all in a courageous Spirit; And tho' he nearer drew to Man, By the Dimensions of a Span, Yet real Manhood must consist, Quoth he, in dint of Sword and Fist. Thus spoke the puny Prince, not fearing, To vent such Words in Mikro's hearing: Who having view'd his Limbs awhile, Elate, returns a scornful Smile; Erects his Elbows on his side, And triumphs in a haughty Stride. Spadillo fearlesly reply'd, He shortly wou'd suppress his Pride. Thus they insult, and brave by turns, Till in each Breast fell Anger burns. Resentments rise by slow Degrees, And swell like an autumnal Breeze; Which gently first its Progress takes, And scarce the smallest Scions shakes, 'Till driv'n by some approaching Cloud It fills its Wings, and roars aloud; The Tops of stately Cedars bends, And stubborn Oaks asunder rends. Or as a little fatal Spark Creeps unperceived in the dark, By silent Steps collects new Force, And lights its own destructive Course; Till its Foe Water it defies, And flames, and crackles to the Skies. Thus in each Breast a Tempest reigns, And boils within their slender Veins. And now the fated Time drew nigh, The Sun had almost left the Sky; Just on th'Horizon's Verge it stood, And flusht the Western Skies with Blood. Some Records scruple not to say, Strange Omens usher'd in that Day: That Armies in the Air were seen, And Spectres stalking o'er the Green. A melancholy Dale they choose To grace their dreadful Interviews, Where Fairies blithe, and Fauns resort, And where the Pigmies keep their Court. Hither the puny Champions tripp'd, For desp'rate Deeds of War equipp'd. Their Bodies with tough Withy brac'd, Knit close, and strongly interlac'd. A Pumpkin's Coat secur'd the Head, By Art adorn'd, and dy'd with Red. Adown their Sides sharp Sabres hung, Shining with fatal Glare, as long As iron Skewers; but design'd To stick Flesh of another Kind. Guns too they bore, and lighted Matches, Powder, and Ball of fatal Vetches. Thus Cap-a-pee they both were arm'd, While all the petty Clan alarm'd In Troops came tripping o'er the Green To be Spectators of the Scene. When Heralds give th'expected Sound, And shake the Neighbourhood around, Their Guns the Heroes first explode, And at a Distance Wounds bestow'd. Spadillo made the best Discharge, And seldom miss'd a Mark so large. The flying Shot, like Storms of Hail, The brittle Tegument assail. But Mikro finding all his Strength, Did nought avail at such a Length, For closer Fight impatient grew, And on his Adversary flew; Who calmly stood, and undismay'd, Receiv'd him with his glitt'ring Blade. And now the doughty Fight grows fierce, The fatal Swords the Armor pierce. But Mikro guiding well his Stroke, Spadillo's crested Helmet broke, Pierc'd thro' the Pumpkin to his Head, And dy'd it of a diff'rent Red. But ah! unlucky was the Blow, And kind, tho' bloody to the Foe, In Pieces the Toledo flew, In dismal Spangles to the View. But Force, nor Fortune ought avail, When cruel Fate will turn the Scale; And trivial Accidents oft prove, The Bane of Heroes, and of Love. A Cow that Morning chanc'd to stray, Led by ill Destiny that way; And dropt behind as she past o'er, The Food she eat the Morn before; Who can the dire Mishap relate? Here fell Spadillo urg'd by Fate, Then round a Mole-hill stole away, And Mikro won th'important Day. Thus in some atmospheric Fleet, Two Clouds replete with Sulphur meet Rudely the vap'ry Bodies dash, The Thunders roar, the Lightnings flash, They sally, grapple, wheel, and fly, And chase each other round the Sky; Till one consum'd in th'other's Fires, And burst in Floods of Rain expires, Drops downwards bleeding thro' the Air, And leaves its Foe triumphing there, In Peals of Joy, and Streams of Glare. With daisy Crowns the Pigmies dress'd, In Swarms around the Victor press'd: And this Day each revolving Year, They for their Champion Daisies wear: Such Numbers rev'lling o'er the Land, With flow'ry Crowns exulting stand, The Cows have oft mistook their Meat, And bit a Pigmy on the Pate. The regal Pow'r thus Mikro gain'd, And o'er the petty Cantons reign'd, Gave to his Subjects Peace and Plenty, And dy'd, a good old Age, at twenty. TO A Young Lady. When, fair Cleora, flusht with Bloom, Your Beauty furnishes the Room, Surrounding Objects dull appear, And wear a Shade when you draw near. The fading Pictures sully'd shew, The dying Lamps no longer glow, The softest Sounds of Music die, Lost in superior Harmony. Yet such Perfections grace your Mind, Whether you are more fair, or kind, We scarce can tell; for such Debate Wou'd to a Sanderson create A knotty Task: yet Beauty fails, When Virtue over Time prevails. 'Tis not a Dress, a Shape, an Air, Or Feature, which compose the Fair; If Sweetness does not deck the Mien, Mere Beauty is but painted Skin. Good Sense, and Wit, and Virtue join To make your Features all divine. Three Pow'rs maintain with equal Grace Balance of Beauty in your Face: Nor can Britannia's Monarch say, He o'er three Kingdoms has more Sway, Since such bright Excellencies join'd Liege Subjects make of all Mankind. Think not, fair Nymph, in venal Lays, I flatter you with empty Praise. 'Tis a just Debt we Merit owe, The Muse wou'd else perfidious grow: While dunning Cupids Night and Day, Teize me till I the Debt defray. Such Charms wou'd dullest Souls excite, And teach ev'n Savages to write: Such Charms the blindest Swain can move, And teach the coldest Breast to love. ON A Young Gentleman, who died suddenly by a Fall from a Waggon. Infelix Puer! Fertur equis, curruque hæret resupinus inani; Lora tenens tamen, huic cervixque, comæque trahuntur Per terram. Virg. Æneid. To thee, dear Youth, I dedicate this Verse, And hang the Muses Mourning on thy Herse: For whom the Poplars sympathising pin'd, And drooping Flow'rs their painted Heads declin'd; For whom the Swans sweet sung in dying Strains, And languid Fountains loiter'd o'er the Plains: Whom Philomel with Mid-night Note condol'd, Whose tragic Tale responsive Echos told. How frail is Life, how sudden Heav'n's Decree? The Waggoner a Charon prov'd to thee; The Youth rejoic'd the Chariot to ascend, Pleas'd with that Motion, which his own must end. Strange Labyrinth of Life thro' which we stray, And Slaves to Fortune with Destruction play! See the slow Car with slumbring Motion slide, Like the rock'd Billows of a torpid Tide. 'Twas thus in solemn Equipage of old, Lamented Pallas to his Tomb was roll'd; When Trojan Eyes with pious Tears o'erflow'd, And deep Revenge in ev'ry Bosom glow'd. Cou'd the just Cadence of a tragic Strain, With plaintive Numbers represent the Wain, Like that sedate shou'd lagg the sable Woe, “The Lines too labor, and the Words move slow. Morpheus himself shou'd guide the lazy Herse, And drowsy Dullness pause in ev'ry Verse. Ambitious Boy! like Phaeton to try Too great a Height, like Phaeton to die. The Muse in Vision saw him mount afar, And rising glitter like a Morning Star: She saw the guilty Team ascend the Sky, And fix a radiant Monument on high; Fair in the Heav'ns a shining Relique reign, And sparkle o'er our Heads like Charles's-Wain. Why weep ye thus the Rigor of his Fate Whom Heav'n saw fit so kindly to translate? And to secure him, snatch'd him up in haste, E'er tainting Vice his tender Bloom cou'd blast: Pure and unspotted to those Climes he flew Where Youth still blooms, and Beauty's ever new. For if we die but to revive again, And rise with Pleasure, when we sink with Pain, Why at Death's Summons pants the Breast with Fear, Why swell our Eye-lids with the farewel Tear? 'Tis but a short Eclipse by Nature made That we may shine the fairer for the Shade. TO CELIA. In vain, false Charmer! every Grace Embellishes your Mien; In vain triumphing o'er your Face Aurora's Blush is seen. In vain, if with tyrannic Art, False Modesty denies, And cruel Lessons of your Heart Still contradict your Eyes. If your Beholders from afar Must idly view your Charms, 'Tis but like gazing at a Star Which tempts and mocks our Arms. Oft on a Tree too tall for you We see the blushing Rose, Pray what avails its Tyrian Hue? Uncropt it blooms and grows. Thus in some lonely, absent Shade, Pale Lillies beauteous bloom, In Silence bud, in Silence fade, And shed a vain Perfume. Then, lovely Celia! learn betimes To act a wiser part; For Age will but increase your Crimes, As 'twill increase my Smart. TO Miss S?????by. Lucinda wonder not to see Your Parroquets so well agree: In Love and Harmony ally'd, They never leave each other's side. Those beauteous Birds from India came To raise in you that tender Flame; And by Example let you know, Beauty and Love together grow. THE TEMPEST. Stay gentle Guardians of the lower Air Who on your Wings the panting Zephyrs bear, Who keep unweary'd Centry in the Skies, And watch the Tempests when they sink or rise, Permit the Muse with you sublime to soar, And on your Pinions buoy'd forsake the Shore; Amidst your pathless Regions guide me right, And thro' the Storm facilitate my Flight. Say then how unobserv'd the rising Breeze With infant Wings first murmurs thro' the Trees: How on the Tops of Hills it softly blows, And spreads its little Conquests as it goes: Now whispers thro' the Vales, and gently bends The flutt'ring Corn, and with the Flow'rs contends; Curls the fair Stream, skims o'er the quivering Sea, And scarce disturbs the Billows as they play. But soon in loftier Regions learns to soar, And bends those Trees with which it play'd before: Thus their old Guide aspiring Youths despise, And scorn those Rules by which they learnt to rise. Now the big Current in Meanders roves Thro' whistling Forests, and resounding Groves, High with aerial Tide resistless roars, And Waves indignant lash the sounding Shores. As rising Springs first bubble on the Hill, Then gleet down gently in a tinkling Rill; And as they float along the flow'ry Meads, The Stream rolls swifter, and the Channel spreads, Riv'lets croud in from ev'ry neighb'ring Plain, And now almost a Sea, it tumbles to the Main: So lesser Gales to louder Surges rise, Collect new Blasts, and muster new Supplies, Favonian Winds their lighter Cohorts bear, And charge with martial Clangor thro' the Air. While each Æolian Cave Artill'ry yields, And War, and Discord fill th'ethereal Fields. Old Boreas takes th'Alarm, and rushes forth With all his hoary Squadrons from the North: Th'affrighted Nations at his Progress shakes, And with his single Breath a Tempest makes. Thus from the gelid Hyperborean Climes, Pour'd forth the Goths to scourge the Roman Crimes. The lab'ring Ground unusual Burden bore, Earthquakes behind, and Whirlwinds march'd before. Columns of Dust obscur'd Day's faded Lamp, And Storms and Chaos travell'd with the Camp. Then first the Mistress of the World knew Fear, And Pallas trembled with her Guardian Spear. Raging as Fire, and as a Deluge strong, The agitated Fluid sweeps along: Wave after Wave successively transferr'd From Clime to Clime the dreadful Din is heard. Hung like the Sea, the Air observes its Shores, Knows its own Orb, and in its Circle soars; Calm, and unruffled, now serenely glides, Or buoys aloft, and propagates its Tides. Now marches o'er the desolated Land, Nor Tow'rs, nor Temples can the Wreck withstand; Here Sheets of massy Lead are whirl'd on high, And sacred Statues from their Niches fly. Beams cross with Beams, and wafted o'er the Plain To their forsaken Groves return again. All in the awful Silence of the Night What Theatres of Woe escape the Sight? What dire Confusion o'er the Welkin reigns, Levels the Woods, and palpitates the Plains? The Hills convuls'd against each other bow, And tremble from the Basis to the Brow. Majestic Oaks, the Glory of the Wood, Which undisturb'd whole Centuries have stood, Seen Groves decay beneath their spreading Shade, Are sudden Martyrs to its Fury made. Prostrate with horrid Crash they rend the Earth, Cæsarean like, that fed, and gave them birth. Such was the Scene when Michael's Host engag'd, And with Hell's Legions War cælestial wag'd; When Mountains with their Woods on Mountains flew, And Rocks uplifted charg'd the Rebel Crew. Nature in Labor her Diseases knows, Has Ague Horrors, and intestine Throws, Pants thro' her shockt Machine, her Frailty feels, With Ferments glows, or in Convulsions reels. The guiltless Swain in his low Cottage lies Secure, nor fears the Tumults of the Skies. In his calm Bosom downy Slumbers dwell, And Storms on high but murmur o'er his Cell. While dread Ideas haunt the Miser's Rest, And fiercer Tempests agitate his Breast. Still rolls the Element with lawless Reign, And spreads a watry Chaos o'er the Main. Neptune can scarce command his tott'ring Throne, Or call the Empire of the Seas his own; While civil Anarchy his Realm invades, And frighted Sea-Nymphs hide in coral Shades; While Sea on Sea, on Ocean Ocean rolls Successive Thunder on the sounding Shoals. Now a wide Deluge o'er the Country flows, Nor Banks nor Mounds the Torrent can oppose. The exil'd Fish lie panting on the Shore, And Seamen vainly struggle with the Oar. In vain her Notes the airy Songster tries, Oft claps her Wings, and oft essays to rise; Stopt in her Flight with many a giddy Round, Breathless and faint, she silent seeks the Ground. Thus leaves the weary Muse her native Skies, And with the Gales to her still Grotto flies. Her Songs declining with the Tempest cease, And drowsy Nature slumbers into Peace; With weaker Pulses each expiring Breeze But fans the Air, and pants along the Trees. In Order to their Cells the Winds repair, And universal Silence cloaths the Air. TO A Friend in Wales: Writ in the Spring. The spacious Theatre we here survey, Above so splendid, and below so gay; The Sky's fair Tap'stry hung with Lamps of Light Which twinkle thro' the Horrors of the Night; The painted Earth array'd in Mantle green, With lofty Woods, and limpid Streams between; All the fair Show and Order of the Frame, Immortal Skill and Art divine proclaim. What less cou'd steer the Orbs their pathless Way, And o'er each Planet spread a Flood of Day; Bid the Sun travel in an oblique Line, And with alternate Influence learn to shine; Cou'd tune th'harmonious Music of the Spheres Which only sounds to philosophic Ears; Bid the bleak Winter freeze, fierce Cancer burn, And all thy Bloom, O! charming Spring return? Inspir'd by Thee the slumbring Insects wake, And animated Birds their Silence break; In Notes of Harmony salute the Year, And all Creation with their Music cheer. No more tempestuous Winds the Forest rend, Nor clatt'ring Hail-storms tho' the Air descend. In every Gale sweet Smells, and sweeter Sounds With Blasts alternate keep delightful Rounds. See how the sleeping Plants forsake the Tomb, Smile on the Sight, and beautifully bloom. See the green Herbage on your Mountains grow, And Streams descending from your Hills of Snow. And can you pensive sit, be frozen still Like Scythian Seas, or like an Alpine Hill? Can you sit mute amidst the tuneful Throng, Nor join in Nature's universal Song? While Birds, Plants, Beasts in Symphony conspire, Awake your Consort, and compleat the Choir. TO A Retir'd Lady. Like Pearls in Fish, or Diamonds hid in Stone Fair Sylvia sparkles to the Croud unknown In vain; such Charms were made to be reveal'd; The more you hide, the less you are conceal'd. Thus glows the Insect in the Dead of Night, With vivid Beams disclos'd by his own Light: And Bards retiring thro' their Shades are seen Crown'd with those Laurels which were once their Screen. The curious Mind still labors to explore The arduous Road, and seeks the hidden Store; No Shade, no Distance cou'd efface the View Of Danae's Charms, for Love will still pursue. Shades are oft fatal to a Lover's Pain, Unhappy Procris in the Groves was slain; And still to sighing Swains each gloomy Dale Repeats the Tragedy of Thisbe's Tale. Tho' soft your Slumbers on the silent Green, Beware, fair Nymph! there Serpents lurk unseen: There Satyrs, Harpies, Birds obscene resort, And frightful Fairies keep their Mid-night Court. His wily Frauds insidious Satan laid When in lone Wilds our ductile Parent stray'd. Lamented Dido in the Shade first fell, Tho' Virgil blush'd the guilty Tale to tell; To shun the Storm without the Huntress fled, Nor dreamt of that which in her Bosom bred. EPITAPH On Mr. John Mason of Bristol. Weep not the good Man slumbring here, For him ev'n Virtue sheds a Tear. So much of her inspir'd his Heart, That when he dy'd She bore a Part. Single he liv'd, but his chaste Mind Was with this happy Consort join'd. So just, so kind, so brave, so wise, Th'Alliance ended in the Skies. O'er all diffusive Goodness reign'd; Free, catholic, and unrestrain'd. Of every Sect Love made him one, Yet fixt and steady to his own. To all complacent, yet sincere; True to his Friends, to Vice alone severe. THE EARTH: A Philosophical Poem. At manet incolumis mundus, sua nomina servat, Quæ, nec long a dies auget, minuit que senectus. Manil. L. 1. Salve, magna parens frugum, pulcherrima Tellus Magna virum. Virg. Geor. II. While some the gaudy Glare of Art admire, The Pomp of Princes, or the Beaux Attire, Cascades, Ridottos, animated Rooms, Mosaic Sculptures, and Corinthian Domes; My humbler Muse the fertile Earth detains, Where artless Beauties wander o'er the Plains: Where Nature blooms in everlasting Greens, And sheds around ten thousand charming Scenes. From thee, great Sire! the Vegetables rise, The reptile Race, and Commonwealths of Flies. The animated Tribes of every Sort Which croud the Air, or in the Water sport; And those new Worlds which Microscopic Aid Unfolds to View, imprison'd long in Shade. From thee the Flow'rs their infant Charms commence, And Sweets luxurious feed the ravish'd Sense; Rais'd from thy Bed a balmy Fragrance yield, And spread their morning Blushes o'er the Field. Hail! ever youthful, ever pregnant Queen! With lofty Turrets crown'd, array'd in Green. In Thee a mimic Paradise is found, Resemblance fair of Eden's happy Ground! Thy Sons with bushy Tops the Skies invade, And recompense thy Culture with their Shade. O'er the parch'd Surface filial Branches play, And from their Parent screen the Noon-tide Ray, While her capacious Lap each Year receives Th'enriching Burden of autumnal Leaves. When sunk with Age majestic Oaks decline, Or rent with Winds aspiring Forests pine, Each fading Tree new Nourishment supplies, And young Creations from the Ruins rise. So when in Flames the mystic Bird consumes, Another Phœnix from her Ashes blooms. Within Earth's Womb exhaustless Stores lie hid; Here Isles of Spice, there Woods in one small Seed; To build some future Palaces design'd, Or warm the World in Ages far hehind. Here Fields of Corn are in one Stamen roll'd, Which the last Conflagration shall unfold, Rais'd by that Heat their short-liv'd Greens display, Greens sprung to grace old Nature's fun'ral Day. Here wrapt in Acorns British Fleets reside, Which late discover'd Longitude shall guide To distant Climes, and Regions yet unknown, The Pole Antarctic, or the Northern Zone. E'er Time was measur'd out by Nights and Days, Or feather'd Choirs begun their morning Lays, E'er from the Deep attracted Vapors flew, Or o'er the Surface infant Breezes blew, Replete with plastic Energy the Earth Contain'd each future Offspring's latent Birth. From hence the snouted Beast unwieldy grew, And slender Silk-worms their fine Texture drew. Here slept the Adder's Spleen, the Lion's Rage, The Panther roaming, and the Serpent sage. The vast Leviathan, who spouts a Sea, In rudimental Seed contracted lay. Unnotic'd lay the shining Robes of State, And all the tinsel Splendor of the Great: The parent Colors blended lay unseen, The flaming Purple, and refreshing Green. Formless and void, then Darkness cloath'd the Deep, And mute Creation felt primæval Sleep. Till Breath divine the dark Abyss inspir'd, And hideous Chaos with its Train retir'd. Their proper Form appointed Atoms knew, And new-born Worlds from Solitude withdrew. As on the Banks of Nile the teeming Earth Replete with Being feels th'approaching Birth, When solar Heat unlocks the wondrous Store, And Animalcules throng the living Shore; Thus from their Coils th'untwisting Organs start, Expanded into Form by heav'nly Art. Ev'n Man deriv'd his Miniature from Clay, A Clod inform'd with a celestial Ray, Mixture of Elements, of Godlike Form, A figurated Mould, a reas'ning Worm. While the new World before its Maker stood, And God, as Moses wrote, pronounc'd it Good, Lo! at the known Command obsequious Dust Swarm'd into Action, and its Fetters burst: Each conscious Particle harmonious came, And rang'd in Consort, strung the human Frame. Some into Tubes in beauteous Order grow, Or thro' the Veins in gentle Currents flow; Others more dense acquire a firmer Tone, Glew into Chords, or harden into Bone: Of Texture fine some form th'unfathom'd Brain, Or mixt with Air assume a purple Stain. Soon sinks the human Frame; but blest with Bloom Immortal, Earth retains her pregnant Womb. Still the same vast Fecundity remains, And still she spreads new Dresses o'er the Plains. See the pale Fields are fertiliz'd anew, The drooping Hyacinth resumes its blue; The gorgeous Piony in Crimson drest 'Midst Violets glows, like Phœbus in the East. With parti-colour'd Robes, Carnations gay, And painted Tulips princely Pomp display. The gaudy Turnsole with majestic Blaze Still emulous, confronts the solar Rays; While pale Narcissus hangs with pining Look, As when he languish'd o'er the crystal Brook. What diff'rent Offsprings variegate the Fields! What wise Confusion ev'ry Species yields! Each checquer'd Herb has its peculiar Grace, As Features vary in each human Face. Thus every Clime assumes a different Dress, And various Products various Soils confess. Each Plant enjoys a Genius of its own, And feels the Sickness of a foreign Zone. The Groves which bloom beneath the burning Line, Here chill'd amidst our wintry Dog-days pine. Say what Divinity resides within The wondrous Globe, and rules the vast Machine. To brutal Herds Philosophers assign An innate Soul, and rational Design: The feather'd Architect contrives her Nest, And prudent Ants provide for Winter's Rest. The Indian Beast with armed Turrets crown'd, The wary Want, wise Collier of the Ground; And he that o'er Nile's Flood tyrannic reigns, Or the fierce Lord of Mauritanian Plains, All with Sagacity of Frame possest, Are born with Instinct, and with Conduct blest. Then own, ye Sages, Earth's congenial Soul Which reigns diffusing Life from Pole to Pole. As Earth Man's Structure emulates, we find Some latent Emblems of the Plastic Mind: See every Part analogous in Frame, The human Spirit, and terraqueous Flame: Thro' subterranean Tubes fair Fountains glide, As in arterial Pipes the purple Tide. The Sea distributes Juice to ev'ry Part, Ebbing and flowing like the panting Heart. Here Nerves and Bones, there Rocks and Hills we find In adamantine Chains the Fabrick bind Secreting Ætnas Exhalations vent, And Nature's Outlets aptly represent: While like excrescent Hair thick Forests stand, With shady Heads to grace the subject Land. Thro' all a constant Circulation reigns, And scarce an Atom unemploy'd remains, While the whole Mass with Speed incessant rolls, And whirls around the Sun its fervent Poles. In Rapture rais'd I view the trav'lling Sphere, Clime after Clime successively appear. See polisht China in the East advance, And savage Tartary lead on the Dance; Here Russia clad in Ignorance and Snows, Here o'er their Mummy-pots dull Germans dose; Gay Gallia next takes its aerial Round, And Pipes and Hautboys thro' the Ether sound. Now distant Thule rises to the Sight, Where Britons set contending Nations right; Sedate, yet bold, and blest 'twixt each Extreme Of Gallic Fury; and Batavian Phlegm. Beyond, diffus'd, floats the cerulean Main, With Sun-beams trembling o'er the lucid Plain; Like spotty Clouds, green Isles promiscuous stand, Th'Azores here, there fair Bermudas Land: The wild Canadans in gay Colours drest, Rove o'er the Woods, with native Freedom blest. Then Mexico turns up her injur'd Ground, While murder'd Ghosts indignant haunt around. Unhappy Clime! for Idol-worship sold To Christians, worse Idolaters of Gold. Now shines the Sea again with glossy Dye, And the same circling Scene salutes the Eye; Thus glide the Seasons with ambrosial Wing, And painted Robes, in an eternal Ring; Thus with revolving Waves a Vortex whirls, And the lasht Top still round its Centre twirls. In vain we view this Theatre around, And all the teeming Glories of the Ground, If at the View no pleasing Wonder fires Th'attentive Mind; while ev'ry Part conspires To form the Drama, and connect the Chain Where social Harmony and Beauty reign. Yet Man, unthinking Man! regardless sees Himself more dull, Herbs, Animals and Trees; Sees all the fair Creation round him rise, Sees Ants, and Flow'rs with unsurprized Eyes. The Scene indeed is grateful to the Sight, Cool Show'rs refresh us, and gay Fields delight; While the rich Furniture regales our Taste, Thoughtless we slumber o'er the full Repast: Thus Brutes their better Appetites employ, Their verdant Meads, and Summer Shades enjoy. We're pleas'd with Prodigies and foreign News, And Novelty the gaping Croud pursues. We gaze at Meteors, and the Northern Light, And visit vagrant Comets all the Night, That rove like Outlaws up and down the Sky, We know not whither, and we know not why, That once an Age within our Heav'ns appear, And are the Talk of Nations half the Year. Inconstant Man! Heav'n's Proteus, loves to roam, And slights the Prospects of his native Home. Astronomers can distant Worlds descry, And mark out Shores, and Systems in the Sky; Imaginary Seas and Kingdoms trace, And Vales and Mountains claim in Cynthia's Face, But scorn the base, inglorious Earth, nor know, How Herbs and Flow'rs in their own Gardens grow. Descend ye Sages! nor presumptuous rise With Giant Labor to invade the Skies; To this paternal Spot your Searches bend, Where nobler Wreaths the gen'rous Toil attend. In Thee a fair Preheminence we find, Parent of Fruits! and Parent of Mankind! A PRAYER of Cleanthes, a Stoic Philosopher, to the Supream GOD. Translated from the Greek. Great Father of the Skies, whose boundless Sway Both Gods above and Worlds below obey: Thy Laws sustain the universal Frame, Various thy Titles, but thy Pow'r the same. Hail! Sov'reign Jove! all Nations shall address Their Songs to thee who gave 'em Tongues to bless. Behold thy Image, grov'ling on the Earth, Faint Echos of thy Voice which gave us birth: Then back will I reflect thy Praises still, And sing the Wonders of Almighty Skill. The wide Expanse of yon ethereal Plain, And all below, is subject to thy Reign. The forked Lightnings which with doubtful Glare Sublimely wave, and linger in the Air, From thy dread Arm with pointed Fury fly, And ting'd with ruddy Vengeance sweep the Sky. Thy Ray divine o'er all the Frame presides, Glows in the Sun, and in the Ocean glides. From thee each Atom of Creation springs, Hail! great Support of all inferior things. The Orbs above, and floating Seas below, Move by thy Laws, and by thy Influence flow. All rang'd in Order know their destin'd Place, All but the mad, degen'rate human Race. But Thou canst Order from Confusion bring, Bid Peace from Discord, Good from Evil spring; And when all Nature frowns, and Nations jar, See Calm in Storms, and Harmony in War. Great Jove so justly fram'd the earthly Ball That universal Good results from all. While common Sense still shines with certain Ray, And thro' the seeming Maze points out the Way; Yet thoughtless Men to this blest Convoy blind Court the wild Dictates of a restless Mind; Perversely fly the universal Light, And the sweet Voice of heav'nly Reason slight. Unhappy Men! who toil, and hunt for Bliss, But the plain Road of sacred Wisdom miss. Led by this constant, this unerring Guide, Thro' flow'ry Paths Man's Life wou'd smoothly glide; But urg'd by Passion, heedless we pursue The first mad Pleasures that invite the View. Some Avarice, and sordid Taste inspire, Ambition some, and Fame's ungovern'd Fire; Soft Lux'ry some, and Cyprian Charms delight, While all rush forward to the Heav'n in Sight. But Thou who thundrest in the Vault above, Correct these vain Desires, O! bounteous Jove! Let Godlike Reason in our Bosoms dwell, And from weak Minds this Lunacy expel. A Ray of Wisdom on our Souls bestow, By which thou rul'st all Nature's Scenes below: Then with Devotion fir'd we'll hail Thee King, And in eternal Songs thy Wonders sing. No greater Good can Men, or Gods attend, Than at thy Throne with prostrate Hearts to bend. TO Miss S???y, dancing at a BALL. Once I condemn'd the dancing Art Which captivates each female Heart, Abhorring that fantastic Fashion With philosophic Indignation; And witless thought such motly Shapes Transform'd Mankind to mimic Apes; Like Harlequins on Doctor's Stage, Or Squirrels frisking round a Cage, Like Puppets drest at Country Wake, Or Scaramouch with antic Freak. 'Midst flutt'ring Hoops, and flying Aprons, Salutes, Cross-overs, Whirls, and Cap'rings, Like Fairies now to frisk it round, Then couple, figure, clap and bound. Was some old Stoic posted here To see the Whirligig appear, He'd deem it a prophetic Trance, And say Enchantment led the Dance; Or that some Engine set 'em going, Or Wind-mill circularly blowing; While Miller-like the Essenc'd Beau Does with Perfumes and Powder flow. But whither roves my Satyr Lay? Celia, I only meant to say; Soon as you grac'd the shining Train, All my Philosophy prov'd vain: Beauty so graceful, such a Mien, Wou'd overcome a Cynic's Spleen! With so much Majesty you mov'd, Ev'n Cato had the Art approv'd, And acquiesc'd in that bold Notion, That there is Music ev'n in Motion. With so much Life you swept the Ground That all the Tapers hung around Gave not that Lustre to the Place As your superior smiling Grace; In whom so many Charms we view, They recommend whate'er you do. Others to dancing owe their Praise, Celia the Arts themselves can raise; Dancing from you new Beauty draws, Nor does it give, but take Applause. Enchanting Nymph! your Virtue keep; For shou'd so great a Leader trip, Vice will almost look lovely too, In such an Advocate as You. HORACE. L. I. Ode VIII. Prithee, Lydia, tell me why, By all the Gods who rule the Sky, The Youth Sybaris bold and brave Is now become thy am'rous Slave? Once he was wont to range the Plain, Nor fear'd the Sun, the Dust or Rain; Why does he cease to take delight In manly Sports, and martial Fight? Why fear to ride the gen'rous Horse, And with the Spur correct his Course? Shun Wrestlers Oil, like Viper's Blood, And dread to plunge in Tiber's Flood? With vig'rous Arm no longer throw The pond'rous Disk, or bend the Bow? Whirl o'er his Head the Dart around, And fix it far beyond the bound? Why does the Youth his Cohorts shun, And lie conceal'd like Thetis' Son, Who in a Woman's Dress attir'd, Ignobly from the Croud retir'd? L. I. Ode IX. See, Thaliarch my dearest Friend, The wintry Skies in Snow descend, The Woods are whiten'd, and with Pain The still increasing Load sustain; Yon Mountain' tops are cover'd o'er, And Streams transfixed glide no more. Then let the gen'rous Sabine flow, And cheerful Fires around you glow. Fill up again the sparkling Bowl To chase the Frost, and cheer the Soul; No more for worthless Trifles pine, But to the Gods your Cares resign. At their Command the Tempests cease, The troubled Air is hush'd to peace; The Waves retire; the Winds are still, And Silence broods on every Hill; No more the aged Elms are shook, And not a Zephyr stirs the Brook. Strive not with anxious Thought to pry Into thy secret Destiny; Enjoy each Day which Fate shall give, And easy, and contented live. Let Beauty sometimes court thy Eyes, Nor too severely Love despise, Before thy sprightly Youth is fled, And Age comes on with hoary Head. Let Dancing, Exercise, and Play Succeed, and crown each shining Day, While gentle Slumbers bless the Night, And murm'ring Streams to Sleep invite. Now pleas'd to see some Fair-one's Smiles, Her ogling Looks and am'rous Wiles; To steal a Ring or trifling Toy, While hypocritically coy, She half unwilling feigns to fly, Still granting, when she wou'd deny. L. II. Ode XV. How fast the stately Piles ascend, And o'er departing Fields extend? The Fish-ponds too enlarge their Bound, And on the Continent get ground: Wider their Circuit than the Lakes Which Nature wise, and frugal makes. Now Jessamin, and Myrtle Bowers, Lime-trees, and odorif'rous Flow'rs Stand where fat Olives us'd to thrive, When our Fore-fathers were alive. The Sun can hardly force his way Thro' Groves of Ever-green, and Bay. Wise Romulus, nor Cato grave, With rigid Mind, such Lessons gave. Then was the public Treasure great, While they enjoy'd a small Estate. No ten-foot Porticos did then Refresh the Doors of private Men: Nor did the Laws lay hold of those Who us'd green Turf for their Repose. L. IV. Ode VII. Now the gay Spring her new Attire puts on, The Hedges bloom, and Frosts and Snows are gone. Once more the rolling Earth renews the Scene; Once more the Fields are cloath'd in charming Green: O'erflowing Streams within their Banks subside, And in their ancient Channels smoothly glide. The Graces, Nymphs, and all the rural Train In naked Dances tread the smiling Plain. Hope not, frail Man, for an immortal State, Perpetual Changes warn thee of thy Fate. The fleeting Moments, the revolving Years Fly swiftly round, and whirl about the Spheres. In silent Haste, Time softly steals away, And soon concludes the kind, the jovial Day. Behold the shifting Seasons take their Turns, First blooms the Spring, then sultry Summer burns; Autumn succeeds with loaded Plenty crown'd, Then torpid Winter lags her lazy Round. The silver Moon soon rises from her Night, And fills her Horns afresh with borrow'd Light; But when we launch, and reach the unknown Shore, Our Sun is set, and will return no more. There in still Groves Æneas' Shade is blest, There Tullus, and good Ancus peaceful rest. Thou know'st not what th'immortal Pow'rs design, Nor can'st thou call to-morrow's Moments thine: Haste then, be liberal, and freely give, This Day may be the last thou hast to live, E'er thy forsaken Wealth shall fall a Prey, And by rapacious Heirs be snatch'd away. When once we have receiv'd the fatal Doom, And Death has fix'd us in the silent Tomb, When awful Minos shall decree our Fate, Not Beauty, Wit, or Wealth shall change our State; Virtue with all its Charms will not avail, To move the rigid Judge, or turn the Scale. In vain wou'd Theseus break Pirithous' Chain, Or chaste Diana free Hippolitus again. L. I. Ode VII. Some Rhodes, some Mytilene prize, Some lift fam'd Athens to the Skies To Pallas sacred, and with Verse, And Olives crown'd, her Praise rehearse. Some Ephesus, and Corinth please, Whose Walls are wash'd with double Seas: Mycenas rich, and Argos known For Horses swift, and Juno's Throne. Some say that Tempe's Fields excel, And wou'd in Thebes or Delphos dwell; Thebes by the God of War renown'd, And Delphos by Apollo crown'd. For me, I scorn Larissa's Plains, And Sparta where such Rigor reigns, If with Albunca's Seats compar'd Where Anion's rushing Streams are heard; Tiburnus' Lake, where Orchards grow, Water'd by rolling Floods below. The weeping South not always brings Dark Clouds and Moisture on its Wings; Sun-shine, and Sky are sometimes seen To open 'midst the gloomy Scene. O! Plancus! thus from Toil forbear, And mix some Pleasure with your Care, Whether with shining Troops you rove, Or peaceful seek Tiburnus' Grove. When Teucer took his farewel Flight, And shun'd his angry Father's sight, Thus to his weeping Friends he said, While Poplar Garlands crown'd his Head: “My dear Companions, now we trust “To Fortune, more than Parents just: “Pursue her Star, in me confide, “Nor fear while Teucer is your Guide. “In Lands remote, Apollo cries, “Another Salamine shall rise. “Come ye, who long with me have dwelt, “With me have oft worse Evils felt, “Come, and in Wine your Sorrows steep, “To-morrow we'll explore the Deep. ON THE SPRING. From Anacreon. Ode XXXVII. With the new-returning Spring See the Graces Garlands bring: See the Sea's tumultuous Tide Calm, and peaceful, now subside. See the Swans glide o'er the Lake, And the Crane his Journey take. While bright Titan shines on high, And the transient Vapors fly Swiftly sweeping o'er the Sky. Now again Man's Labours shine In the Olive and the Vine; While the Willows all around Spring luxuriant from the Ground; And the Fruit-trees budding out In a thousand Blossoms sprout. ANACREON. Ode XVII. Great Vulcan, with thy Art divine, Make my silver Goblet shine: But prithee Vulcan grave not there Grim Mars, with Helmet, and with Spear. Let me no radiant Armor see, Pray what has War to do with me? But let it be as large, and wide, As you think fit from side to side. Carve me no Stars, no Charles's-Wain, Nor stern Orion with his Train; Let Bootes and Bears and Pleiads roll (I mind them not) around the Pole. For me engrave the charming Vine, And here and there let Branches twine; Here let am'rous Cupids play, And paint the Cyprian Goddess gay. Let youthful Bacchus too be there, And Ivy Garlands deck his Hair. TO A Lady who refus'd to answer a LETTER. Will you, my Sylvia, always mute remain, Nor with one distant Whisper ease my Pain? Blest with your Presence, you vouchsafe Reply; If not in Words, you answer with a Sigh. Epistles are but Words expos'd to Sight, Or but a trav'lling Language in its Flight. Say not you'd write, but can't your Lines convey; O! dictate first, and Love will find a way. Cupid, that trusty Post-Boy of the Air, On silver Wings the am'rous Mail will bear. How long will this dumb Quietism hold, And when Love's gentle Heat dissolve the Cold? Heat softens Steel; what will not Heat subdue? The lifeless Flow'rs, clos'd up in virgin Dew, By Heat expanded, all their Charms display, Diffuse their Fragrance, and adorn the Day. The feather'd Choirs seal'd up in wintry Sleep, Awak'd by Heat, their Matin Consort keep. And the mute Streams in frozen Silence bound, Dissolv'd from icy Fetters, bless the Ground. By Heat all Nature moves; by Cold imprest Creation stagnates to eternal Rest. This genial Power the Roman Bard implor'd, And Venus must descend before he soar'd. May Love with tepid Rays your Frost unbind, And chase this wintry Torpor from your Mind. Tempests and Storms may break another's Rest, Your Silence drives all Quiet from my Breast. Like a Sea-calm, this still, this dead Serene Portends more Danger than a Hurricane. The Caves and Rocks, more civil to my Cry, Will in fond Echos to my Plaints reply. The Groves in gentle Whispers sigh again, And babbling Fountains murmur to my Pain: But you more deaf than Caverns, Rocks, or Trees, With no kind Answer give a Lover Ease. In vain you plead you have no Skill to write, Let Love inspire, and Nature will indite, E'er th'Art of Writing to Perfection grew, Various rude Arts the untaught Ancients knew To fix Ideas e'er they fled away, And Images of Thought to Sight convey. Brass, Wax, or Wood the Characters retain'd, Some liv'd on Slates, and some the Canvas stain'd; Some trac'd in Iv'ry, or engrav'd on Stone, Or sunk in Clay, e're Biblo's Reed was known; E're sacred Pergamus acquir'd a Name, Or humble Charta gave to Egypt Fame. The magic Tongues, here clad in mystic Shapes, In Symbols lurkt of Fishes, Birds and Apes. When Philomela cou'd not speak her Fate, The silken Robes exprest her tragic State. O! Sylvia, thus your distant Damon bless, And in some Vehicle your Thoughts express. Couch'd in whatever Dress, your Sense I'd find, And thro' the darkest Cyphers trace your Mind: Veil'd in Ænigmas let me read my Doom, O! write, tho' 'tis a Distich for my Tomb. Writing can fill up Space, can Distance cheat, And spread Society in dull Retreat. Thus may our Minds Platonic Friendship boast, Returning mutual Visits ev'ry Post: And born in pictur'd Lineaments shall fleet Thro' the pure Ether, and its Consort greet. HORACE. L. II. Ode XVI. Tost on the wide Ægæan Seas The restless Merchant prays for Ease, When sable Clouds hide Phœbe's Ray, And doubtful Stars perplex the Way. The warlike Thracians who delight In fierce Exploits of savage Fight; The Medes adorn'd with glitt'ring Bows, All sue for Quiet and Repose. But Peace, my Grosphus! is not sold For Gems, for Purple, or for Gold. Nor Wealth, nor Lictors richly drest, Can quell the Tumults of the Breast. Anxiety, and pensive Gloom, Hang lingring round the fretted Room. Content with their paternal Store The Wise sit down, nor covet more; In the old trenchard Dish can dine, Nor at the rural Fare repine; No sordid Lusts their Minds infest, No Fears disturb their downy Rest. Why dost thou pitch thy Aim so high, Who shortly must descend to die? Why leave thy native Clime, and run Restless, beneath some other Sun? Deluded Men! in vain they try From their uneasy selves to fly. Care will pursue with winged Feet, And climb upon the flying Fleet: Care will o'ertake the Horseman's Train Swifter than Hinds, or stormy Rain. Contented with the Good they feel The Wise regard not future Ill, Weather the Bad with cheerful Air; Nothing below is free from Care. Quick Death Achilles snatch'd away, But linger'd out Tithonus' Day. Perhaps old Time may lend to me Those Hours which he may steal from thee. A hundred Flocks bleat o'er thy Ground, Sicilian Heifers low around, Thy sprightly Horses neigh afar, Worthy to draw a Consul's Car. Rich Garments sparkle in thy Train, Ting'd with a double Tyrian Stain. But happy in my small Estate, Peace and Contentment make it great. Nor did the Fates to me refuse Some little Portion of the Muse, With this, a Mind, (the greatest Prize,) That can the sland'rous Croud despise. TO ARABELLA. When you, fair Arabella, deign to write, The Muses round attentive stand, And catch your Thoughts at second hand, To aid their Pencil, and inspire their Flight. Then waft them high on painted Wings To strike with Harmony their Strings. The tuneful Sisters love their Play, And Gods themselves keep Holiday. Now lest Apollo shou'd the Truants know, They pillage some bright Genius here below. But oft, incens'd he finds the Cheat, And doubly tasks them for Deceit. He sees low Thoughts, and sublunary Light, And dull Mortality hang o'er each Flight. So bright your Fancy, and so soft each Line, That when the Vagrants steal from you Their Censor thinks each Stanza new, And says 'tis all divine. THE Wasp and the Lady. Hasta sub exertam donec perlata papillam Hæsit, virgineumque altè bibit acta cruorem. Virg. Æn. Why, cruel Wasp! didst thou delight On that fair Arm to wreck thy Spight; Fell Spight on that defenceless Arm, Which ne'er did Fly nor Insect harm? Inhuman Animal! to vex With armed Force that tender Sex; A Sex! so merciful, so sweet, Cou'dst thou no other Object meet? And oh! no other Female find, Than one so fair, and one so kind? More cruel than the Asp unseen, Which stung lamented Egypt's Queen. The harmless Beast securely laid, On the rich Basket only prey'd, Till in her Arm, with fatal Wring, Th'heroic Lady forc'd the Sting. Why unprovok'd, O barb'rous Wasp! More savage than the pois'nous Asp, Why didst thou wound the gentle Maid, With Love and Innocence array'd? Oh! why annoy that peaceful Breast, Where only Cupids us'd to rest? Their Darts to her shou'd only fly, Those Darts with which her Lovers die. Was it to seize ambrosial Lymph, Extracted Essence of the Nymph, As Bees cull out the richest Flow'r And aromatic Sweets devour? Fly, wicked Chymist! far away, In Deserts such Alembics lay, Or on the Garden's Essence prey. Ye Sylphs! that hover in the Air, As Poets say, to guard the Fair, With watchful Wings around their Bed, Where were ye now, ye Truants fled? But say what Punishment shall I Assign for this audacious Fly? May Dangers still attend his Flight, Till some dire Vengeance on him light. May artful Webs his Wings ensnare, Or Birds transport him thro' the Air; Or may he with tremendous Clap Be smother'd by fell Butcher's Flap; Like Pilgrims choak'd in desert Land, With Whirlwinds of tempestuous Sand; Or when sojourning in the Streets The Felon feeds on foreign Sweets, May the arch Prentice lay a Gin T'entice the Epicure within; Some empty Sugar-Cask prepare With brimstone Toil, and fiery Snare, While Wasps invited by the Smell Like Trojans haunt the wooden Cell, 'Till suffocated Crouds expire In Clouds of Smoak, and nitrous Fire. Thus where Vesuvio's Cavern reigns, And Sulphur fructifies the Plains, The vent'rous Natives oft repair For finer Soil, and purer Air; When lo! Eruptions hideous rise, And Exhalations fill the Skies, Rivers of burning Brimstone flow, And eat their Channels as they go, The smother'd Victims gasping die, Beneath the torrid, sulph'rous Sky. But if by Wonder kept alive The Ravisher regains his Hive, May pirate Boys explore the Nest And there th'absconded Thief infest, Plunder the Brood with barb'rous Joy, And all the Tenement destroy. Thus does the Muse Revenge pursue, And sacrifice the Wasp to you: The Monster at your Feet lies slain, And here I finish the Campain: The Muse in Perils oft your Guard, Now Victor, waits her just Reward. Heroes you know, and Champions bold, And those romantic Knights of old Who Giants vanquish'd, Dragons kill'd, And for Dulcinea kept the Field, Were always mickle Fav'rites thought By those fair Dames for whom they fought; Let me be only dubb'd your Squire, And I no other Boon require. THE Lady and the Wasp. Obliqua invidia, stimulisqua agit abit acutis. Virg. Æn. XI. Why, Cynthia, will you thus complain At such a momentary Pain? Why wonder that the Wasps pursue A Nymph so innocent as you? Why let that peaceful Bosom rise, And Anger kindle in those Eyes? Those Eyes where gentle Pity flows, That Breast the Region of Repose. Believe the Muses Divination, No Errors rise from Inspiration; Prophets and Bards were once the same Both in their Virtue, and their Name; Believe the Muse, 'tis Vengeance sent, For your own Crimes, just Punishment. Thus Sages hold, profound of Sense, That Judgments quadrate with th'Offence, And like alternate Echos chime In their Resemblance to the Crime: As fell brave Cassius in the Field With the same Sword which Cæsar kill'd; And Hercules the Robber hung On the same Tree he Trav'llers swung. Thus since with dull, tyrannic Joy, You Cupid's pointed Darts employ, And new Artillery invent Your patient Vassals to torment, At last some small Revenge we meet, (And oh! Revenge is very sweet!) The Wasp has took each Lover's Part, And stung your Hand, as you their Heart. Had she believ'd what Nurses fear She might have known some Danger near; But Infidelity will reign, Calpurnia dream'd, but dream'd in vain. The Chimny-Insect by her side Oft with presaging Ditty cry'd, Omens of Salt spilt near her Plate, And boding Ravens croak'd her Fate. Portentous Signs, orac'lous Screams, Unlucky Sights, and adverse Dreams, The Fire burn'd blue, the Wine grew sour, Ev'n Tray foretold the destin'd Hour, As slumbring with uneasy Nap He shiv'ring started in her Lap: While the Death-watch with solemn Knell Did ev'ry Night some Ill foretel. And Ghosts of living Men were seen, On well-known Eve, glide o'er the Green. Her Genii from their Coverts ran, Some conscious flutter'd round her Fan, With glowing Heat some flush'd her Ear, Or hung upon a pearly Tear: While Voices strange, with Aug'ry dire, Were heard at Midnight by the Squire, Yet still the unbelieving Maid Dar'd all these Omens, undismay'd: Till round her Room the Insect flew, Oft hover'd near, and oft withdrew; Thrice he display'd his sounding Wing, Thrice brandish'd the tremendous Sting. O! magic Number! by what Charm Dost thou portend approaching Harm? Thrice from the Ground dread Pallas rose, Her Statue left with Grecian Foes, Thrice shook her adamantine Spear, True Harbinger of Perils near. Jove's Thunder flies in triple Line, A Tripod form'd the Delphian Shrine. Thus, Harpy-like, return'd again, Return'd the Wasp, but not in vain: Deep in her Arm with pungent Smart, Vengeful, he fix'd th'envenom'd Dart; Strait from the Wound impetuous flew The vital Juice, of Tyrian Hue. Far sounds the Ether with her Cries, And from her Cheeks the Colour flies. Not with less Grief Camilla dy'd When Aruns' Dart had pierc'd her side. But grateful what Returns shall I Confer on this advent'rous Fly? For him may balmy Sweets distil On ev'ry Vale, on ev'ry Hill: Rich as that Morning Manna Dew Which nourish'd once the wandring Jew. Where'er he roves, where'er he flies, May Gardens bloom, and Odors rise. Long, unmolested, may he rob The Butcher's Stall, or Grocer's Tub; In hollow Tree, on hollow Bank, Reign dignify'd with princely Rank: Then metamorphos'd wondring find Existence in a nobler Kind, And leave his Species far behind. Thro' Scenes of Transmigration grace The finny, or the feather'd Race, And rob'd with all their Titles shine, Exalted to the Peacock Line; O'er his old Troop destructive soar, And live on what he was before. Thus oft we see some Upstart rise, And his own Parentage despise, With Hands rapacious plunder those Industrious Swains from whom he rose, And with encroaching Sway infest Those Fields which his Forefathers drest. CHARACTERS Out of the first Book of Tasso. Done from the Italian. Now Tancred came, a bold, intrepid Knight, Rinaldo only equall'd him in Might: None but Rinaldo in the Camp was seen Of nobler Soul, or more majestic Mien. If any Foil did his vast Glory fade, 'Twas Love; by wretched Love a Captive made. Fame tells on that great Day when France subdu'd The Persian Army, and the Foe pursu'd, Victorious Tancred spent with Toil and Heat, Far from his Troops explor'd a cool Retreat; His weary'd Limbs near a fair Stream reclin'd Which gently thro' the Grove did murm'ring wind, Forgetful of his Cares there peaceful lay, And pleas'd, survey'd the Triumphs of the Day. When lo! a pagan Damsel thro' the Glade Rush'd swift along, and brighten'd all the Shade: She too fatigu'd some cool Recess desir'd, All but her Head in shining Arms attir'd. He saw her martial Air, her lovely Grace, The Charms and Fire which darted from her Face; Unable to sustain so bright a View, The captive Prince, her love-sick Vot'ry grew. O! wondrous Force of Love! whose Pow'r is such It quite o'ercomes, when first we feel its Touch. Soon as the warlike Maid the Knight beheld, Her Face expos'd, the Helmet close conceal'd, And had she not approaching Soldiers spy'd, She Tancred strait to Combat had defy'd: So fled; but left the Prince transfixed there, Charm'd with the Image of the beauteous Fair; Still are her Features on his Mind imprest, And still her lov'd Idea haunts his Breast; With languid Look and melancholy Air Sighing he bears his Passion to the War. But see fair Edward with Gildippe rise In Song illustrious, and attract our Eyes. Inseparable Pair! by Love ally'd, Together liv'd they, and together dy'd, Love knit their Hearts, what will not Love inspire! It led her to the War with fond Desire: Still by his Side a constant Guard she dwelt, With him, no Trouble, no Fatigue she felt. A dear and virtuous Friendship warm'd their Veins, Mutual their Joys, and mutual were their Pains. The Youth Rinaldo next attracts our View, In whom ten thousand shining Virtues grew: Of each unrivall'd Excellence possest Godlike he shines exalted o'er the rest; With graceful Presence, and majestic Air, Gives a distinguish'd Lustre to the War. His Mind serene no sordid Blemish stains, And instant Courage glows thro' all his Veins. Commanding Beauty sparkles in his Face, Where Mars and Venus strive with mutual Grace. On Adige's flow'ry Banks, Sophia fair The great Bertoldo's Spouse, the Hero bare: Beauteous Sophia, worthy such a Son, But nurs'd by Maud, since Infancy begun. That tender Princess rais'd him in her Arms, Train'd him to Virtue, and improv'd his Charms; Till fir'd with Thirst of deathless Praise, he hears The Eastern Trumpet sounding in his Ears; Then fled alone, with native Courage bold Thro' Paths unknown, scarce fifteen Winters old: O'er distant Climes he rov'd to Grecian Shores, Where throng'd with Islands the Ægean roars. Glorious the March, advent'rous was the Flight, Worthy the Labours of the bravest Knight. Three Years he past already with Renown E'er his soft Chin was grac'd with manly Down. AN ELEGY On a late Reverend, Pious, and Ingenious Gentleman. Omnibus est eadem leti via, non tamen unus Est vitæ cunctis, exitiique modus: Hac pueri at que senes pariter, juvenesque feruntur; Hac par divitibus pauper egenus erit. Gall. Eleg. Some as they grow in Fortune, grow in Fame, And on their Pomp engraft their borrow'd Name; While o'er their sordid Dust proud Piles arise, And prouder Praises that affront the Skies: And shalt thou, Strephon, unlamented lie, And live in Silence, and in Silence die? Thou who might'st claim thy Monument and Bays, And Holbein's Pencil to transmit thy Praise. Fir'd with thy Worth, the Muses shall presume, To draw some shad'wy Out-lines o'er thy Tomb. Tho' o'er thy Grave no polisht Marble shines, Nor Indian Colours gild the glowing Lines, Yet if chaste Truth her better Charms shall show, And artless Virtue thro' the Periods flow, Thy Name without an Obelisk shall live, Nor greater Fame Egyptian Labors give. As Painters in light Sketch large Draughts contain, As living Forests lurk in one small Grain, Thus each Perfection of the human Race, In him, divine Epitome! we trace. And the wide Theatres of Truth and Wit In wondrous Miniature distinctly writ. With thee, the Sweets of social Life are lost, And all the Friendship which I valu'd most: Friendship by no low Views of Int'rest bred, Kindled by Reason, and by Reason led. No more in deep Attention shall I sit, Pleas'd with thy Smiles, and ravisht with thy Wit; Thy Wit which quick as Lightning flow'd so fast, That still new Sallies overtook the last. When spent with thee, soft fled the Hours away, Untold they fled, and Pleasure rul'd the Day: Thy Talk, free, hum'rous, solid and sublime Brighten'd dull Hours, and sped the Wheels of Time. How was I pleas'd to emulate thy Flight, And trace the pearly Palaces of Light? How pleas'd to view, when trav'lling by thy side, New Truths display'd, new Miracles descry'd? And rais'd by thee behold with vast Surprize A new Creation all around me rise. Like that brave Chief who first the Ocean crost, And found in unknown Skies, an unknown Coast. When first my Muse her infant Wings essay'd, And rural Scenes in artless Flights display'd, He check'd her Sallies, taught her how to fly, Nor meanly sink too low, nor soar too high: Still wou'd he labour something to commend, And often lose the Critic in the Friend. Long did he slumber in a lone Recess, And savage Regions with his Presence bless. A solitary Dale near Mendip lies, Almost conceal'd by Rocks from human Eyes, The Scene so wild, so desolate the Hills, A dreary Horror all the Prospect fills; So thick the Woods, the Mountains swell so high, They shade the Plain, and darken half the Sky: Obscure the Place, the Region unadmir'd, Till Strephon here religiously retir'd; Pleas'd thro' the venerable Gloom to rove, And with his Presence sanctify the Grove. But now the desart Wilds his Name shall bear, And each rude Rock his dear Remembrance wear; Each mystic Tree, and each memorial Stream Flow with his Image, or retain his Name. Each whisp'ring Breeze shall on his Accents dwell, And vocal Caves reply from Cell to Cell. Hail! blest Retirement! innocent Retreat! Religion's Mansion, and the Muses Seat. 'Twas here he read Young's celebrated Lines Where the Last Day in tragic Splendor shines; Fir'd with his Godlike Flights, and magic Lays He felt himself the Fury of the Blaze; The Conflagration kindled in his Veins, And the fresh Flame flew higher in his Strains. Beyond this Scene he rais'd his tow'ring Soul To Worlds dissolving, and a fiery Pole; With Strength of Thought surviv'd the final Doom, And lodg'd frail Nature in a decent Tomb. See the Rocks rend, the Hills asunder crack, The azure Curtains of the Skies fold back; See Earth to Ætna turn, the Ocean fry, And Peals of Thunder thro' the Chaos fly, See Storms of Sulphur, Deluges of Fire Sweep thro' the Skies, and bid the Waves retire: The vast Abyss display its unknown Store Where shapeless Monsters in dark Grottos roar, While the last Trumpet with tremendous Sound Shakes the firm Basis of the solid Ground. See the Tombs open, naked stand the Dead, The grand Tribunal blazing o'er their head; The Judge conspicuous with a starry Crown Striking more Terror with a single Frown Than all the dire Catastrophe below, Tho' Hell and Devils mingle in the Show: He frowns; the Skies are flusht with crimson Rays, And at each Glance reflected Lightnings blaze: He smiles; the Heav'ns their gentle Robes assume, And with pacific Aspect gild the Gloom: But see pale Nature all in Flux expire, Itself a Pile for its own fun'ral Fire. Convuls'd Creation agonizing lies, Pants with vext Billows, or in Tempests sighs, Diffus'd in Atoms one deep Groan she gave, And Space, at first her Womb, became her Grave. Thus sung his Muse the Ruins of the Frame, Clear as the Light, and rapid as the Flame. But while he drest the Fun'ral of the Sky In sable Robes, thought not his own so nigh. Already in his Breast the Train was laid, And o'er his Veins a Fire as fatal prey'd. So subtle Vapors thro' the Ether glide, And future Poisons in their Bosom hide. Thus as Creation's final Peal he rung, His own sad Dirges too the Poet sung: The tragic Lines his Elegy wou'd frame, Various the Subject, but the Plaint the same. Reason his Pole-star was, his friendly Light Which thro' Life's Labyrinth convoy'd him right. For while his tow'ring Genius soar'd so high, Buoy'd up in Rapture to its native Sky, Still at the Basis solid Judgment grew, And sunk as deep as that sublimely flew: Thus Egypt's Cones the wondring Prospect tire, But the broad Base supports the rising Spire. When thick around him gath'ring Tempests brew'd, He unappal'd the rising Billows view'd: Perplext in Mazes, or beset with Foes, Still wou'd the Guardian Mentor interpose. When Bigot's Darts with poison'd Fury flew, She o'er his Head her heav'nly Helmet threw. When Levi's Sons in Consultation sate To pass their Censures, and decree his Fate; He all their Terrors with a Smile beheld, Their keenest Rage his Innocence repell'd: Like the fix'd Stars in purer Light array'd Beneath his Feet their harmless Thunder play'd. As well the Pole with ev'ry Breeze might shake, As his fix'd Peace their zealous Curses break: Nor cou'd vain Sounds, or vainer Schemes controul, Or wrest a mean Confession from his Soul. With just Integrity of Thought possest, Contempt of Fame, and Suff'ring fir'd his Breast. The Cause of Virtue is a Godlike Cause, And scorns to stoop to popular Applause: Supported on her Wings, he rose sublime, Where no low persecuting Storms cou'd climb. And like blest Quintus for his Country's Good, The Baits of splendid Slavery withstood. Let Epicures in Paphian Pleasures glide, And venal Sycophants, and Slaves deride. Let Misers on the Seas their Bliss explore, And barter Quiet for Peruvian Ore. The wise Man's happy in himself alone, And fraught with Peace all India is his own. He needs not calm a Tempest to be blest, Nor ask the Ocean leave to sleep at rest. Wrapt with incircling Probity the Mind In her own Port a Sanctuary can find; Collected in herself a Harbor there Unfolds a Region of untroubled Air; Where blest Contentment soars with downy Wing, And smiling Flora breathes eternal Spring. No sullen Clouds annoy the Peaceful Scene, The Groves still tuneful, and the Skies serene: External Toys reach not her Orb within, We raise the Storm, and Fancy forms the Spleen. Let the World frown, and Tempests shake the Plain, The Mind's the same, Opinion gives the Pain. Objects without raise visionary Ill, Nor is it they that strike, but we that feel. Thus silver Fountains saliant ebb, or flow, Just as the Artist guides the Pipes below; The shifting Breeze without no impulse brings To raise the Conduit, or direct the Springs. Like Fountains in the Soul the Passions dwell, And as we please the Bubbles sink, or swell. Above the Clouds Contentment builds her Seat, Or in some Grotto seeks a chaste Retreat: There views the busy Croud in Flux around For Trifles pine, and labor for a Sound: There undisturb'd the present Hour enjoys, Free from mad Scenes of Folly, Rage and Noise. So in the silent Caverns of the Deep On oozy Beds quiescent Billows sleep. Such was our Hero, so sedate his Mind, Calm as the Light, undaunted, yet resign'd. So great his Piety that he had been In Romish Register unstain'd with Sin. His Body so deform'd, his Thoughts so high, He was not fram'd to live below the Sky. It was a Foil by Nature thus design'd In fairer Contraste to dispose the Mind; A Mind which soon disdainful took her flight, Fledg'd for immortal Liberty and Light. For oh! blest Bard! if any Heav'n there be There is a Paradise reserv'd for Thee. Thy dying Pray'rs must unretarded rise, And pave an easy Entrance to the Skies. Shall the brave Man here weather Fortune's Frown, Obscurely fall, and reap no future Crown? Forbid it Heav'n, and all that's good, and great, There is beyond this Cope a happier Seat; Full of divine Tranquillity and Peace, Where all these Hurricanes of Life will cease; Where no dark Clouds rise low'ring o'er the Day, No sable Mists obscure th'eternal Ray; Where free from all his Conflicts, all his Pains, In blissful Groves triumphant Strephon reigns. Love Idolatrous. As o'er the Skies bright Venus flew One shining Summer's Day, While gentle Doves her Chariot drew, And Cupids fann'd the Way: Beneath a Tree fair Phillis sat, In past'ral Dress array'd, Where Beauty sparkled without State, And grac'd the solemn Shade; The Moon amidst the Gloom of Night Thus beautifies the Sky, And flusht with Majesty of Light Gilds the dark Cope on high. Encircling Flow'rs beneath her Feet In Emulation grew, To her they offer'd up each Sweet, And for her Pleasure blew. Sweet Innocence sat on her Face As cloudless Skies serene, Divinity fill'd all the Place, And sanctify'd the Scene. At my Approach the Goddess blush'd Like Roses in their Bloom, Fresh Glory deck'd the Grove, and flusht Refulgent o'er the Gloom. Struck with such Charms the Gazer fell Transfix'd with Cupid's Steel; The Passion was too great to tell, The Wound too deep to feel. Bright Nymph inferior Charms than thine A vulgar Flame may raise, But I like Vot'rys at a Shrine Pay Homage as I gaze. Your strict Iconomist I grow, Thus dedicate my Vow, As at Loretto's gilded Show Deluded Papists bow. My Love does to Devotion turn, Devotion kindles Love; And thus alternately I burn, And in two Regions move. You, Phillis, you can turn the Scale, False Idol, I your Priest, Let Love o'er Reverence prevail, And idol Vows desist. Regard my Sighs, or you'll become Some Magdalene indeed, Fit Image to adorn a Room, And dumb Adorers feed. Phidias, or Guido, in their Sphere, May have Admirers still, But ah! fine Paintings cannot hear, Nor a Minerva feel. TEDEUM. From the Latin of Dr. Alsop. Great God! thy Praises we proclaim In Hymns of grateful Verse; Great God! all Climes revere thy Name, All Climes thy Pow'r confess. Bright Choirs of Angels round thy Throne Thro' Heav'n's high Regions sing, And all the shining Cohorts own Thee, their eternal King. The Cherubim for ever cry, And Seraphim around, O'er all the Palaces on high, Thy Praise for ever sound. Great God of Armies, God of Grace, Thy boundless Glory reigns Thro' all th'Immensity of Space, And fills th'ethereal Plains. Apostles shout thy Praises loud, While ecchoing Prophets throng, And Martyrs, an illustrious Croud, Wind up the glorious Song. Th'Assemblies of the Just combine, And joyfully acclaim, And with united Worship join Harmonious in thy Name; Thy boundless Attributes confess, And hail th'eternal Son, And the coæval Spirit bless, All equal in the Throne. All hail! O glorious Paraclete, Who gave the sacred Word, Hail Christ! who, in immortal Light Still lives immortal Lord. Who the eternal Offspring reigns Of Heav'n's eternal Sire, And to redeem our mortal Pains Did in the Womb retire. Soon as thy Godlike Spirit fled, Great Victor of the Grave, The Gates of Heav'n expanding spread Our sinking Souls to save. To all who thy Perfections love Thy bounteous Favour shew; And may they reign with Saints above, Who worship thee below. There in full Bliss triumphant shine, With fadeless Glory crown'd, While chaunting on thy Name divine Thro' ev'ry Age shall sound. This Day devoutly may we spend In Piety and Love, Great God! thy gentle Grace extend To guide us safe above. May Beams of everlasting Light Descend on all the Just, And to thy Kingdom lead us right Who on Thee fix our Trust. Ungenerous Love. With youthful Blood Flotillo fir'd A blooming Beauty long admir'd: And vow'd, and sigh'd, and sung, and swore How he did every Charm adore. Not Sleep by Night, nor Cares by Day His flaming Passion cou'd allay; 'Twas Heav'n did she but smile or sing, Her Breath was sweeter than the Spring; But when she frown'd what Storms wou'd rise, And sudden Gloom eclipse the Skies? Then oh! ye Gods! what Lips, what Breast? Twas too divine to be exprest. And—for her Eyes—they shone so bright They made it Sun-shine when 'twas Night: With all the Cant which Coxcombs use When they the injur'd Sex abuse. At length the Nymph reliev'd his Pain, And smil'd upon the dying Swain. Such Softness in her Bosom dwelt All that Flotillo feign'd, she felt. But ah! how soon the Scene is turn'd, The Beau grew cool, the Beauty burn'd. His Pray'rs, his Curses, and what not? Are all forsook, or all forgot. The Sailor thus for Help implores When frowning Tempests shake the Shores, But soon as a calm Heav'n succeeds Nor Pray'rs, nor Tears, nor Vows he heeds. But cease, Belinda, nor lament That Fate which Virtue can't prevent; The Wise from needless Grief abstain, Nor mourn when they must mourn in vain. ON The Prince of Orange's Arrival at Bath. Translated from the Latin of Robert Parran, S. T. P. and Chaplain to the Duke of Dorset. Great Offspring of that Hero's Blood Who royal Tyranny withstood, And with propitious Courage broke Ignoble Chains of Servile Yoke! Come gentle Prince! to bless our Isle, And bid Britannia's Genius smile, Let Gratitude inspire each Breast Thus with a second William blest. Hear Joy tumultuous shout aloud, And Echos murmur midst the Croud; While Nobles guard thee thro' the Street, And sulph'rous Streams thy Presence greet. Where Bath's divine Protectress, see, Presents her sacred Draughts to Thee, For Thee she guides the Urns below, And with new Heat the Waters glow. While thus the Goddess—Taste these Springs, Great Prince! which have befriended Kings. Nassau did hence new Health resume, And hence thy future Sister Bloom. Witness thy own too, Pallas cries, And smiles at such a glorious Prize. The Guardian now with juster Pride Her tutelary Rills shall guide. O! may these Streams prolong thy Years, And doubly thus repay th'Arrears Of those which a devouring Tide Did from thy luckless Sire divide. Unhappy Prince! by Fortune slain; But cease, my Muse, thy Verse to stain, Nor mingle in thy tragic Lays His gloomy Fate with brighter Days. Taste then, blest Prince! while Sickness flies, And Vigor sparkles in thy Eyes: O! may thy Youth immortal be, From each Disease, and Danger free. In this just Pray'r all Britons join, Whose Senate owes its Health to thine; All Europe to this Pray'r will bow, And Anna crown the gen'ral Vow. TO The Reverend Dr. Watts, Author of Horæ Lyricæ. When thy pure Soul, seraphic Watts, shall rise, And mingle with the Music of the Skies; Thy Bliss with greater Extacy will glow, For thou hast felt a Taste of Heav'n below: Already tun'd sublime, immortal Lays, And strung thy Harp in Jubilees of Praise; Already pitch'd for Saints thy lofty Song, And Hallelujahs consecrate thy Tongue, Anticipate the sacred Choirs on high, And ope' the Antichambers of the Sky. Inferior Saints will feel but little more Of their first Heav'n than Watts has felt before: Angels to hear his Lays in Crouds will throng, And Heav'n will learn new Lessons from his Song. TO The Right Honourable Lord Viscount Weymouth, on his late Marriage with Miss Carteret. While Crouds, my Lord, applaud your happy Choice The Muse attempts the Theme with grateful Voice. Tho' low her Notes, and unobserv'd her Song, Lost in the louder Murmurs of the Throng, Yet are her Raptures true, her Duty paid, Tho' sung to Rocks, and utter'd in the Shade. Yet shall the vocal Rocks resound thy Lays, And vocal Hills the nuptial Concert raise; The whisp'ring Winds repeat it as they rove, And waft the welcome News from Grove to Grove. While Birds harmonious catch the artless Strains, And Hymen, Hymen ecchoes o'er the Plains. How oft they hear me in the russet Vale, Or low-brow'd Downs, repeat the nuptial Tale? And when Aurora's Curtains gild the Sky Swift as her Beams the gentle Tidings fly. How blest th'Alliance where no Int'rest rules, The Bane of Bliss, and Perquisite of Fools! Where Love its full unmingled Joy displays, And Reason dictates while the Heart obeys: Where Wisdom, Innocence, and Beauty join To make the destin'd Object all Divine. Well might such Virtues rigid Romans win, And in soft Bondage captivate a Thynne. Beauty like her's cou'd Envy's Sting disarm, And with one Smile reluctant Stoics charm. Sprung from a Peer whom matchless Virtues grace, And stamp a lasting Lustre on his Race: Alike Mæcenas to the Muse, and State, Whom Foes must love, and Faction cannot hate. How gay the Country, and the Fields how drest, When first the Fair these rural Regions blest! While Sylvan Choirs conduct her o'er the Plain, And smiling Meads reflect her Smiles again, The jocund Swains dance rustic Carols round, And Pan loud piping propagates the Sound: The distant Dales the Harmony prolong, And bubbling Fountains murmur out a Song: Blithe Fauns and Naiads on the Banks are seen, And hail her guardian Goddess of the Green. Welcome, bright Nymph! to these poetic Rills, These savage Forests, and romantic Hills: Like Druid Priests you consecrate the Grove, And each soft Scene breathes Innocence and Love. The rugged Wilds a gentler Air assume, And sudden Verdures brighten thro' the Gloom. To these lone Walks you unknown Day diffuse, And warm these Accents of the rustic Muse: 'Twas thus Minerva civiliz'd the Swains, And spread Politeness o'er Arcadia's Plains. Still may your Joys increase, illustrious Pair! Not flusht by Fortune, nor deprest by Care, Till beauteous Offsprings in your Likeness smile, And add fresh Graces to Britannia's Isle. TO His Royal Highness the Prince of Orange. Design'd to have been presented to him, on his Arrival at Bath. Illustrious Prince! while Crouds their Vows address, Accept the Tribute of a rustic Verse. What Swain, what Savage can a Moment pause, When Princes, and when Heroes claim Applause? Amidst the wintry Horrors of the Year. The Muse her Halcyon feels when you draw near; Forth from her Cell, where she had slumber'd long, Now ventures out, and meditates a Song; Like Birds in Covert, from the Shade she springs, With short-liv'd Flights, and tries her infant Wings. New Meteors thus with welcome Light surprize The northern Natives in benighted Skies. Think not I labour at ignoble Praise, In artful Lines, and mercenary Lays. Fame is the Tax of Justice to the Few, To Virtue, Learning, Liberty, and You; A Friend to each triumphing Britain sees Dawn forth in You, and ripen by Degrees. No Monuments can screen a Tyrant's Name, Nor Titian hide, nor Maro guard his Fame. When Merit calls, the Labor is not lost, He who says least of Merit, praises most; Ev'n silent Eloquence can more display Than all the Pomp of Language can convey: Who writes—here Bacon rests—here Milton lies, May Raphael's Paint, and Tully's Tongue despise. Thus o'er your Tomb, whatever Poet weeps, And says with pious Tears—Here Orange sleeps; In one short Sentence has your Annals writ With Cæsar's Energy, and Plutarch's Wit. Your future Conquests grav'd on ev'ry Breast In fairer Characters will speak the rest. Pleas'd we behold you rise betwixt th'extreme Of Gallic Fury, and Batavian Phlegm: Contraste of both, the British Soul is seen In all your Actions, and in all your Mien. Calmness, and Courage, Constancy and Fire To form the Patriot, and the Prince, conspire: Like that brave Monarch, when he swore sedate In the last Dyke to meet his Country's Fate; And fir'd with Freedom in the Bloom of Age, Withstood the Torrent of a Tyrant's Rage. Heir to his Virtues, as his Lands, we view Great Nassau from his Tomb revive in you. Behold the Patriot from his Slumbers rise, And all his Triumphs sparkle in your Eyes! To you his Arms and Genius he bequeaths, Fires with his Deeds, and crowns you with his Wreaths. Then like Anchises in th'Elysian Plain Returns, and rushes to the Shades again. The scatter'd Virtues of that glorious Line Centring in you, with blended Lustre shine. A Line commission'd from the Gods to save Afflicted Lands, and Bourbon's Fury brave; Born to redress the injur'd Captives Pains, And break the Curse of arbitrary Chains. To bid Mankind that lawful Freedom use Which Nature gave, and Vassals would refuse. For this in ev'ry Age have Heroes rose, Whom Heav'n Avengers of its Wrath has chose. May you for this your native Health resume, And all the Graces in your Aspect bloom: Restore lost Peace and Liberty again, And bless the Nations with a golden Reign. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>