<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Whitney, Isabella</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Whitney, Isabella</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">whitney isabella</field>
      <field name="author_text">Whitney, Isabella</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">16th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.0998.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">[1573]</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:463683</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">[A sweet Nosgay, Or pleasant Posye ; contayning a hundred and ten Phylosophicall Flowers] [by Isabella Whitney</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">[A sweet Nosgay, Or pleasant Posye ; contayning a hundred and ten Phylosophicall Flowers] [by Isabella Whitney</field>
      <field name="title_facet">a sweet nosgay or pleasant posye</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">sweet nosgay or pleasant posye</field>
      <field name="title_text">[A sweet Nosgay, Or pleasant Posye ; contayning a hundred and ten Phylosophicall Flowers] [by Isabella Whitney</field>
      <field name="year_display">[1573]</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1573</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1573</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463683&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:463683&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Whitney, Isabella&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;whitney isabella&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;[A sweet Nosgay, Or pleasant Posye ; contayning a hundred and ten Phylosophicall Flowers] [by Isabella Whitney&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;a sweet nosgay, or pleasant posye&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;[1573]&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1573&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Whitney, Isabella&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;[A sweet Nosgay, Or pleasant Posye&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;contayning a hundred and ten Phylosophicall Flowers] [by Isabella Whitney]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;[London]&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;[R. Jones]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;[1573]&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp4293&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;[301] p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;[A sweet Nosgay, Or pleasant Posye&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;contayning a hundred and ten Phylosophicall Flowers] [by Isabella Whitney]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 145 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To the worshipfull and right vertuous yong Gentylman, GEORGE MAINVVARING Esquier: IS. VV. wisheth happye health with good succsesse in all his godly affayres. The Auctor to the Reader. This Haruest tyme, I Haruestlesse, and seruicelesse also: And subiect unto sicknesse, that abrode I could not go. Had leasure good, (though learning lackt) some study to apply: To reade such Bookes, wherby I thought my selfe to edyfye. Somtime the Scriptures I perusd, but wantyng a Deuine: For to resolue mee in such doubts, as past this head of mine To understand: I layd them by, and Histories gan read: Wherin I found that follyes earst, in people did exceede. The which I see doth not decrease, in this our present time More pittie it is we folow them, in euery wicked crime. I straight waxt wery of those Bookes, and many other more As VIRGILL, OVID, MANTVAN, which many wonders ?bore?. And to refresh my mased ?mu?se, and cheare my brused brayne: And for to trye if that my limmes. had got their strength agayne I walked out: but sodenly a friend of mine mee met: And sayd, yf you regard your health? out of this Lane you get. And shift you to some better aire, for feare to be iniect: With noysome smell, and sauours yll, I wysh on that respect. And haue regard unto your health, or els perhaps you may: So make a dye, and then adieu, your wofull friends may say. I thankt him for his carefulnes, and this for answer gaue: I'le neither shun, nor seeke for death, yet oft the same I craue. By reason of my lucklesse lyfe, beleeue mee this is true: In that (sayd he) you doo a misse, than bad he mee adieu. For he was hastyng out of Towne, and could no lenger byde: And I went home, all sole alone, good Fortune was my guyde. And though she neuer hath denyde, to hoyce me on her Wheele: Yet now she stood me in some steede. and made mee pleasures feele. For she to Plat his Plot mee brought, where fragrant Flowers abound: The smell whereof preuents ech harme, if yet your selfe be sound. Amongst those Beds so brauely deckt, with euery goodly Flower: And Bankes and Borders finely framde, I mee reposde one howre. And longer wolde, but leasure lackt, and businesse bad mee hye: And come agayne some other time, to fill my gasing eye. Though loth: yet at the last I went, but ere I parted thence: A slip I tooke to smell vnto, which might be my defence. In stynking streetes, or lothsome Lanes which els might mee infect: And sence that time, I ech day once haue viewd that braue prospect. And though the Master of the same, I yet dyd neuer see: It seemes he is a Gentylman, and full of courteleye: For none that with good zeale doth come, doe any one resist: And such as wyll with order get, may gather whilst they ?lis?t. Then pyttie were it to destroy, what be with payne did plant. The moderate heere may be suffizde, and he no whit shall want. And for my part, I may be bolde, to come when as I wyll: Yea, and to chuse of all his Flowers, which may my fancy fill. And now I haue a Nosegay got, that would be passing rare: If that to sort the same aright, weare lotted to my share. But in a bundle as they bee, (good Reader them accept: It is the geuer: not the guift, thou oughtest to respect, And for thy health, not for thy eye, did I this Posye frame: Because my selfe dyd safety finde, by smelling to the same. But as we are not all a lyke, nor of complexion one: So that which helpeth some we see, to others good doth none. I doo not say, it dyd mee help, I no infection felt: But sure I think they kept mee free, because to them I smelt. And for because I lyke them well, and good haue found therby: I for good wyll, doo geue them thee, fyrst tast and after trye. But yf thy mind infected be, then these wyll not preuayle: Sir Medicus with stronger Earbes, thy maliadye must quayle. For these be but to keepe thee sound, which if thou use them well: (Paynes of my lyfe) in healthy state thy mind shall euer dwell. Or if that thy complexion, with them doo not agree: Refer them to some friend of thine, tyll thou their vertue see. And this I pray thee, whether thou infected wast afore: Or whether with thy nature strong, they can agree no more. That thou my Nosegay not misuse, but leaue it to the rest: A number may such pleasure finde, to beare it in their brest. And if thy selfe wolde gather more, then I haue herein bound: My counsell is that thou repayre, to Master Plat his ground. And gather there what I dyd not, perhaps thy selfe may light: On those which for thee fitter are, then them which I resighte. Which if thou doo, then render thanks, to him which sowed the soyle: If not, thou nedes must him commend, when as thou viewst his toyle. In any wise, be chary that thou lettest in no Swine: No Dog to scrape, nor beast that doth to rauin styll inclyne. For though he make no spare of them, to such as haue good skyll: To slip, to shere, or get in time, and not his braunches kyll: Yet barres he out, such greedy guts, as come with spite to toote: And without skill, both Earb &amp; Flower pluck rashly by the roote. So wishing thee, to finde such Flowers, as may thee comfort bring: And eke that he which framd the Plot, with verturs styll may spring. I thee commend to mighty IOVE, and thus I thee assure: My Nosegay wyll increase no payne, though sicknes none it cure. Wherfore, if thou it hap to weare and feele thy selfe much worse: Promote mee for no Sorceresse, nor doo mee ban or curse. For this I say the Flowers are good, which I on thee bestow: As those which weare them to the stalkes, shall by the sequell know. One word, and then, adieu to thee, yf thou to Plat his Plot Repayre: take heede it is a Maze to warne thee I forgot. FINIS. quod IS. VV. T. B. in commendation of the Authour. Marching among the woods of fine delighte VVhere as the Laurell branch doth bring increase Seelde, of Ladies fresh, a solem sight: I viewd, whose walkes betokened all their ease: And bow in friendly wise, it did them please: VVhiles some did twist the Silke of liuely hewe Some others slipt the Braunch for prayses dew. Nor musing did not rest, nor scorne my sight, nor prest in haste to breake their silence I But as at first, they held their whole delight: and casting mirth, said Friend that passest by: did neuer wrethes of loue thee binde perdy As thus: who framde her Plot in Garland wise So orderly, as best she might deuise. Not yet (quoth I,) but you might force the same whose face doth staine the colour red as Rose: No VIRGILL this, nor OVID eke may blam, For Beautie pressing as the Cunduit floes, Was cause that PARIS greatest loue arose: who lou'd before, though neuer touched soe, As OVID showes, with many writers moe. But Ladies sure, my loue consistes in this my whole delight, and pleasure all I take To decke the wight, that worthie praises is: and sure my great good wyll must neuer slake From VVHITNEY: loe, herein some partie take For in her workeis plainly to be seène, why Ladies place in Garlands Laurell greene. She flattering Fate too much, nor skies doth trust: suche labor lîeth finisht with the lyfe: She neuer did accompt Dame Fortune iust, that tosseth vs with toyes and plunges rife: But her defieth, as Auctor of her stryfe: She doth not write the brute or force in Armes, Nor pleasure takes, to sing of others harmes, But mustred hath, and wrapped in a packe a heape of Flowers of Philosophie: No braunche of perfect wisdome here doth lacke, But that the brused mynde, refresht may bee, And that it is no fable, you shall see: For here at large the sequell will declare To Cuntrey warde, her loue and friendly care. The smelling Flowers of an Arbor sweete, An Orcharde pickt presented is to thee: And for her seconde worke, she thought it meete, sithe Maides with loftie stile may not agree: In hoape hereby, somthynge to pleasure thee, And when her busie care from head shall lurke, She practize will, and promise longer worke. Now happie Dames, if good deserueth well, her praise for Flowers philosophicall: And let your Branches twyned that excell her head adorne: wherin she floorish shall: And BERRIE so, resles alwaies at your call, The purple blew, the red, the white I haue, To wrappe amyd your Garlands fresh &amp; braue. FINIS. THO. BIR. A sweet Nosgay, Or pleasant Posye: contayning a hundred and ten Phylosophicall Flowers. &amp;c. I Such Freendes as haue ben absent long more ioyful be at meeting Then those which euer pres?t are and dayly haue their greetyng. II When peryls they are present, then doth absence keepe thee free: Whereas, if that thou present werte might dangers light on thee. III The presence of the mynd must be preferd, if we do well: Aboue the bodyes presence; for it farre doth it excell. IIII Yet abs?ce, s?times bringeth harme, when Freends but fickle are: For new acquaint?ce purchase place and old doo lose their share. V What profit things that we posses doo by their presence bring We can not know: til by their lacke, we feele what harmes do spring. VI For to abound in euery thing, and not their vse to know: It is a pinching penury: wherfore, thy goods, bestow. VII A saying olde, once out of sight, and also out of minde: These contraries, that absent frends much ioy at meeting finde. VIII Well yet, for the Antiquitie, it grew amongst the rest: And true it proues, by those whose minds Obliuion hath possest. IX Care not how mani things thou hast but haue a great regarde: That they be good, for quantytie, doth merite no rewarde. X Yet so thou must increase thy stock as cleare thine owne it be: And neither fleece thy friend, nor seke thy neighbours beggerye. XI We easely may abuse the great and chiefest thing of all: But hard it is to vse a right, such as are trifles small. 12 Our eares we must not euer ope, to each mans accusation: Nor without tryall, trust too much, to any ones perswation. 13 A fault right greater seemeth far, on the accusers part: Then it on the Defendants doth much more should be his smart. 14 Thy Friends admonysh secretly, of crimes to which they swarue: But prayse them openly, if so be, their deeds do prayse desarue. 15 In euery check, vse some faire speach for words do sooner pearce That playnly passe, then those which thou w? rughnesse might reherse. 16 Admonisht be with willingnesse, and paciently abyde A reprehension, for such faults, as friends in thee haue spide. 17 Those precepts which in youthfull yeares are printed in thy brest: Wyll deepest diue, and do more good then euer shall the rest. 18 You must not suffer youth to raing nor stray abrode at wyll: For libertye doth lewdnesse breed, wherfore preuent that yll. 19 The vigor of our youth, no whit doth differ from the Flower: Which for a time doth florish fayre, and quickly lose his power. 20 Whilst thou art yong, remember that thyne Age approcheth fast: And folow thou the steps of such, whose lyfe doth euer last. 21 In youth to thee such learning get as it may make thee wise: So people shall in elder yeares, come seeke thy sage aduise. 22 The inclinations of our youth, desyres that thence doth spring: Foreshew what fruict in future tyme our ripened age wyll bring. 23 No hope of goodnesse can be had of hym, who spends his prime, In liuing so lycentious, that he respects no crime. 24 That mind which sensual appetites in youth doth blyndly guyd: To Age do bodyes yeld deformde, because they wandred wyde. 25 How vaine it is for crooked Age his youth for to requyre: So ist for youth that childish yeares would willingly desire. 26 Olde people deeme them nearer death then those that youthfull seeme But youth is proaner to his end, and lesse doth lyfe esteeme. 27 Great cruelty it is for vs, to vse a churlysh check To any, when aduersitie, hath brought them to a wreck. 28 None in aduersitie hath help, except they prospered haue And by y? menes haue purchast frends of whom they ayde may craue. 29 If miserie thou wouldest not know, liue dangerlesse thou must Or els to taste of troubles great thou shalt, though thou wert iust. 30 Prosperitie wyll get thee friends, but pouertie wyll crie For then, except they faythfull are apace from thee they flye. 31 Tis better with the truth offend, then please with flatteryng words For truth at l?gth shal kepe thee safe when to ther cuttes lyke swords. 32 To all men be thou liberall, but vse to flatter none, Nor be familyer but with few which nomber make but one. 33 A fawning frende wyll at the length a frowning foe approue The hate of such is better sure, then their deceatefull loue. 34 She that is an Adulteresse of euylles is a sea: Her wickednesse consumes her selfe and husband doth decay. 35 Men doo by emulation, of others, proue the same In euery yll as custome is, so commonly we frame. 36 Those strokes which mates in mirth do geue do seeme to be but light: Although somtyme, they leue a signe seemes greuous to the sight. 37 All men thou shalt thine equal make if thou such playnesse vse As thou not fearest, nor yet art feard, nor art, nor doest abuse. 38 Whylst haires are hidden craftely Age doth himselfe bewray: For wyll we, nyl we, h'eele appeare, when youth is chaste away. 39 Children are lykened to the spring and Stripplings to the Sommer. And yongm?, thei ar Autumpne like and olde men wery winter. 40 Haue thou accesse alwayes to such let such resort to thee: As temper all their talk with truth, and are from enuie free. 41 When Bretheren be at varience, how should the enemyes gree? When frends fall out among themselues. who shal their dais men be? 42 A friendly mind, accoumpt it for the neerest of thy kyn: When al shal fayle, it sticks to thee, what euer chaunce hath byn. 43 Affection is of force so stronge, that other qualities: He deemeth to be lyke himselfe, and doth no worse surmise. 44 Let thine affections ruled be, least that they do thee rule: For then no strength wil thee availe nor back canst thou recule. 45 The sorowfull do think it death, to linger in this lyfe: And wish to be desolu'd therof, therby to stint their stryfe. 64 What s'ere it bee that doubtful is, grauntes health th' aflicted tyll: He vtterly denyes that he, to health restore him wyll. 47 The Plowman is accompted smal his reputation none: Yet of the members in a Realme of chiefest he is one: 48 At diceplaying, he that excelles and counningstly can play: In my conceat, for wickednes, may beare the price away. 49 Prease not too hie, but haue regarde yf thou should chaunce to fall: From hie might kyl, fr? mean might hurt alow stand sure thou shall. 50 The man that is ambicious, doth lose such honour oft: As he hath got, wh? Fortune pleasd, to set him vp aloft: 51 When Potentats ambicious are, the poore men, they are wrackt, When Realmes deuide within themselues no cities are vnsackt. 52 He that is voyd of any friend, him company to keepe: Walkes in a world of wyldernesse, full fraught with dangers deepe. 53 Iudge of a friend ere friendship be but when thou hast him tryde: Then maist thou trust, &amp; eke beleeue as thou his doyngs spyde. 54 The falt which in thy frend, y? seemst to suffer, or permit: Thou gilty art, therof thy selfe, not punishing of it. 55 So oft as faithfull friends depart so oft to dye they seeme: To seperate, the griefe is great, but absence is extreeme. 56 Accompt so euer of thy friend, as he thy foe may frame So beare thee, that in enmytie, he thee procure no shame. 57 To all men vse thou equytye, show faith vnto thy friende In euery thyng that thou pretendst, do styll respect the ende. 58 By benefits vnto thy friende, show thyne abilytie: And that thy foes may know y? same thine Iniuryes let flye. 59 Al things with frends in c?mon are at least it should be so That pleasures might imparted bee so like wise grief, or woe. 60 The poore, they haue no frends at al for to participate, The sorow and the griefe they finde in their most wretched state. 61 In louing, ech one hath free choyce, or euer they begin, But in their power it lyeth not, to end when they are in. 62 The angry louer flattereth himselfe with many lyes: And fondly feedeth on such toyes as fancy doth deuise. 63 Ech louer knoweth what he lykes and what he doth desire, But seld, or neuer doth he know, what thing he should require. 64 In time, may loue, by peecemeale weare and wither cleane away: But presently to pluck his rootes, in vayne you do assay. 65 The louers teres, wil soone appease his Ladyes angry moode: But men will not be pacified, if Wemen weepe a flood. 66 As Poets fayne, y? Gods th?selues in loue could vse no wyt: Then mortall men may be allowde, such follyes to commit. 67 The yongmen when they are in loue may profit gaine therby: But in the oulde, it is a fault for they should loue defye. 68 If loue haue geuen thee a blow, and that thou art vnsound, Make meanes that y? a plaster haue, of them which gaue the wound. 69 When secret loue once kindled is, twill burne with fiercest flame: The surest way to be beloued, is fyrst to doo the same. 70 The louer which doth looke aloft. and doth submission hate: Shal haue a slip, or answered be, that he is come to late. 71 Who s'ere they be, the lawes of loue hath guided for a season: It is a doubt, that neuer more. they will be ruld by reason. 72 The cough it is so cumbersome, that none the same can hide: So loue ful fraught w? foolish toies may easely be espyde. 73 The formost step to wisdome is, from loue to keepe thee free: The second for to loue so close, that none the same may see. 74 An olde man when he is in loue, of him this may we deeme: Of all hard haps and chaunces fel, he hath the most extreeme. 75 The loue of wicked persons must, be got by wicked-meanes: Make thine accompt, when y? hast done and geue the deuil y? gaines. 76 Affection fond deceaues the wise and loue maks men such noddyes That to their selues they seeme as dead yet liue in other boddies, 77 A vertuous man, y? hath the feare of God: before his eyes: Is sure in safetie for to walke, for all his enemyes. 78 No credit geue, or not to much, to that which thou doest heare, If that out of a troubled minde thou spyest it to appeare. 79 The bow that euer standeth bent too far wyll neuer cast The mind which euermore is slack, doth badly proue at last. 80 Such minds, as are disposed wel brings wanderers to the way: And redy are with helping hand, to such as go astray. 81 Of worldly things, the chiefest is a well contented mind: That doth dispise for to aspyre, nor gapeth gifts to fynde. 82 If thou doest yll, it forceth not what mind thou shewest therto, Because thy mind cannot be seene, but that which thou doest do. 83 A lothsome sight, God knowes it is a fickle mind to see: It shuld be pure for to reiect, that vile impuritie. 84 Our yeares &amp; dayes wax worse and worse more greuous is our sorow: He thats vnfyt to mend to day, wyll worser be to morow. 85 The present dai we cannot spend as we the same should do Except to count it as our last, we frame our selues vnto. 86 As ours do please some other men, so theirs doo vs delight: Which shews our yl c?tented mind that often works vs spight. 87 He that with his owne weapon is dispatched of his lyfe: Twice slayne he is, because himself was kyld with his owne knyfe. 88 Those promises which are forgot, be not for aye neglect They may perfourmed be at last, and haue their full effect: 89 A miserable griefe it is, by him to haue a harme On wh? we dare not once c?plaine nor can our selues him charme. 90 Their sight is weake y? waxeth dim to see another blinde And very little comfort shall, th' afflicted by them finde. 91 A pleasure yll, and profyt none it is, delight to make, In th' use of any neighbours goods for which they paynes did take. 92 He is not much deceiu'd, whose sute full quickly hath denyall Nor can he say, that he had cause, to linger for the tryall. 93 Full hard it is, and hazard great to keepe for any while: A thing that ech one lusteth for for some wyll thee beguile. 94 Do not accompt y? for thine owne, which may from thee be take: But much exteeme such tresure, as wyll neuer thee forsake. 95 The day doth dally so with vs, that we can neuer know: For what to wish, from what to flie what workes vs weale or woe. 96 He doth not soone to ruyne come that feares it ere it fall: But may prouide it to preuent, if Fortune graunt he shall. 97 Ask nothing of thy neighbour, that thou woldst not let him haue: Nor say him nay, of y? which thou woldst get, if thou didst craue. 98 If that thou minded are to geue aske not if they wyll haue it For so, they eyther must denye or seeme that they do craue it. 99 It gloryous is, to geue all things to him that naught doth craue: So lykewise let him nothing get that euery thing would haue. 100 Whilst that thou hast fre libertie to do what lykes thee best: Thou soone mayest se into thy selfe what disposytion rest. 1001 That Lawyer, which is chose to plead for rich &amp; mighty men: Must either let the trueth go by, or lose their friendship then. 1002 A little gould in law wyll make, thy matter better speede: Then yf thou broughtest of loue as much as might in kindreds breed. 1003 Gold sauours wel, though it be got with occupations vile: Yf thou hast gold, thou welc?e art, though vertue thou exyle. 1004 Such poore folke as to law do goe, are dryuen oft to curse: But in meane while, the Lawyer thrusts the mony in his purse. 1005 A hasty tonge, which runs at large not knowing any measure, It is a wicked thing that makes the minde repent at leasure. 1006 Two eyes, two ears, &amp; but one tong Dame nature hath vs framed That we might se, and heare much more th? shuld w? t?g be named. 1007 Kepe wel thy tong, &amp; kepe thi frind yll vsde, it causeth foes In vttryng things, commit to thee thou faithfull friends doest lose. 1008 Seke not ech man to plese, for that is more then God bids do: Please thou the best, &amp; neuer care, what wicked say therto. 1009 Of wicked men to be dispraysd, for prayse do it accompt: If they commend, then art y? mad so doth their credit mount. 10010 When as the wicked are in midst of all their iolitye: Misfortune standeth at the dore, and skornes the same to see. FINIS. A soueraigne receypt. The Iuce of all these Flowers take, and make thee a conserue: And vseit firste and laste: and it wyll safely thee preserue. By Is. VV. Gent. A farewell to the Reader. Good Reader now you tasted haue, and smelt of all my Flowers: The which to get some payne I tooke, and trauayled many houres. I must request you spoyle them not, nor doo in peeces teare them: But if thy selfe doo lothe the sent. gene others leaue to weare them. I shall no whit be discontent, for nothyng is so pure: But one, or other will mislyke therof we may be sure. Yf he for whom I gathered them, take pleasure in the same: And that for my presumption, my Friends doo not mee blame. And that the sauour take effecte, in such as I doo know: And bring no harme to any els, in place where it shal goe. And that when I am distant farre, it worne be for my sake: That some may say, God speede her well that dyd this Nosegay make. And eke that he who ought the Plot, wherein they same dyd grow: Fume not to see them borne aboute, and wysh he did mee know. And say in rage were she a man, that with my Flowers doth brag, She well should pay the price, I wolde not leaue her worth a rag. If as I say, no harmes doo hap, but that this well may speede: My mind is fully satisfyed, I craue none other meede. So wishing thee no worse then those, of whom I think none yll: I make an end and thee commend, the liueing Lorde vntyll. FINIS. IS. VV.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Certain familier Epistles and friendly Letters by the Auctor: with Replies. To her Brother. G. VV. Good Brother wh? a vac?t time doth cause you hence to ryde: And that the fertyl feelds do make, you from the Cittie byde. Then c?not I once from you heare nor know I how to send: Or where to harken of your health and al this would be kend. And most of me, for why I least. of Fortunes fauour fynd: No yeldyng yeare she me allowes, nor goodes hath me assind. But styll to friends I must appeale (and next our Parentes deare,) You are, and must be chiefest staffe that I shal stay on heare. Wherfore mine owne good brother graunt me when y? you ar here: To se you oft and also hence, I may haue knowledge wheare A messenger to harke vnto, that I to you may wryte: And eke of him your answers haue which would my hart delight. Receaue of me, and eke accept, a simple token heare: A smell of such a Nosegay as I do for present beare. Unto a vertuous Ladye, which tyll death I honour wyll: The losse I had of seruice hers, I languish for it styll. Your louyng (though lucklesse) Sister, IS. VV. To her Brother. B. VV. Good Brother Brooke, I often looke, to heare of your returne: But none can tell, if you be well, nor where you doo soiurne: Which makes me feare, that I shall heare your health appaired is: And oft I dread, that you are dead, or somthyng goeth amys. Yet when I thinke, you can not shrinke, but must with Maister bee: I haue good hope, when you haue scope, you wyll repaire to mee. And so the feare, and deepe dispaire, that I of you then had I dryue away: and wysh that day wherin we may be glad. Glad for to see, but els for mee: wyll be no ioy at all: For on my side, no lucke wyll byde, nor happye chaunce befall. As you shall know, for I wyll show, you more when we doo speake, Then wyll I wryt, or yet resyte, within this Paper weake. And so I end, and you commend, to him that guides the skyes: Who graunt you health, &amp; send you welth, no lesse then shall suffice. Your louing Sister, Is. VV. An order prescribed, by IS. VV. to two of her yonger Sisters seruinge in London. Good Sisters mine, when I shal further from you dwell: Peruse these lines, obserue the rules which in the same I tell. So shal you wealth posses, and quietnesse of mynde: And al your friends to se the same, a treble ioy shall fynde. 1. In mornings when you ryse, forget not to commende: Your selues to God, beseching him from dangers to defende. Your soules and boddies both, your Parents and your friends: Your teachers and your gouerners so pray you that your ends, May be in such a sort, as God may pleased bee: To liue to dye, to dye to liue, with him eternally. 2. Then iustly do such deedes, as are to you assynde: All wanton toyes, good sisters now exile out of your minde, I hope you geue no cause, wherby I should suspect: But this I know too many liue, that would you soone infect. Yf God do not preuent, or with his grace expell: I cannot speake, or wryte to much, because I loue you well. 3. Your busines soone dispatch, and listen to no lyes: Nor credit euery fayned tale, that many wyll deuise. For words they are but winde. yet words may hurt you so: As you shall neuer brook the same, yf that you haue a foe. God shyld you from all such, as would by word or Byll. Procure your shame, or neuer cease tyll they haue wrought you yll. 4. See that you secrets seale, tread trifles vnder ground: Yf to rehersall oft you come, it wyl your quiet wound. Of laughter be not much, nor ouer solemne seeme: For then be sure th' eyle coumpt you light or proud wil you exteeme. Be modest in a meane, be gentyll vnto all: Though cause thei geue of contrari yet be to wrath no thrall. Refer you all to hym, that sits aboue the skyes: Uengeance is his, he wil reveng, you need it not deuise. 5. And sith that vertue guides, where both of you do dwell: Geue thanks to God, &amp; painful bee to please your rulers well. For fleetyng is a foe, experience hath me taught: The rolling stone doth get no mosse your selues haue hard full oft. Your businesse being done, and this my scroule pervsd, The day wyll end, and that y? night by you be not abusde. I some thing nedes must write, take paynes to read the same: Hencefoorth my lyfe as wel as Pen shall your examples frame. 6. Your Masters gon to Bed, your Mistresses at rest. Their Daughters all w? hast about to get themselues vndrest. See that their Plate be safe, and that no Spoone do lacke, See Dores &amp; Windowes bolted fast for feare of any wrack. Then help yf neede ther bee, to doo some housholde thing: Yf not to bed, referring you, vnto the heauenly King. Forgettyng not to pray as I before you taught, And geueing thanks for al that he, hath euer for you wrought. Good Sisters when you pray, let me remembred be: So wyll I you, and thus I cease, tyll I your selues do see. (?) IS. VV. To her Sister Misteris A. B. Because I to my Brethern wrote, and to my Sisters two: Good Sister Anne, you this might wote, yf so I should not doo To you, or ere I parted hence, You vainely had bestowed expence. Yet is it not for that I write, for nature dyd you bynde: To doo mee good: and to requight, hath nature mee inclynde: Wherfore good Sister take in gree, These simple lynes that come from mee. Wherin I wish you Nestors dayes, in happye health to rest: With such successe in all assayes, as those which God hath blest: Your Husband with your prety Boyes, God keepe them free from all annoyes. And graunt if that my luck it bee, to linger heere so long: Til they be men: that I may see, for learning them so strong: That they may march amongst the best, Of them which learning haue possest. By that tyme wyl my aged yeares perhaps a staffe require: And quakyngly as styll in feares, my lims draw to the fire: Yetioy I shall them so to see, Yf any ioy in age there bee. Good Sister so I you commend, to him that made vs all: I know you huswyfery intend, though I to writing fall: Wherfore no lenger shal you stay, From businesse, that profit may. Had I a Husband, or a house, and all that longes therto My selfe could frame about to rouse, as other women doo: But til some houshold cares mee tye, My bookes and Pen I wyll apply. Your louing Sister. IS. VV. To her Cosen. F. VV. Good Cosin myne, I hope in helth and safety you abyde. And sore I long, to here if yet you are to wedlock tyde. Yf so you be, God graunt that well both you and she it spend: If not when s'ere it haps, I wish that God much ioy you send. And when you to the Cuntry come or thither chaunce to send: Let me you see, or haue some scroll, that shall of you be pend. And this accompt as nature binds and meryts yours deserue: I Cosin am, and faithfull Friend, not minding once to swerue. So wishing you as happy health, as euer man possest: I end, and you commyt to him that euermore is blest. Your poore Kinsewoman, IS. VV. A carefull complaynt by the vnfortunate Auctor. Good DIDO stint thy teares, and sorrowes all resigne To mee: that borne was to augment, misfortunes lucklesse line. Or vsing styll the same, good DIDO doo thy best: In helpyng to bewayle the hap, that furthereth mine vnrest. For though thy Troyan mate, that Lorde ÆNEAS hight: Requityng yll thy stedfast loue, from Carthage tooke his slight. And fowly brake his oth, and promise made before: Whose falshode finisht thy delight, before thy haires were hore. Yet greater cause of griefe compells mee to complayne: For Fortune fell conuerted hath, My health to heapes of payne. And that she sweares my death, to playne it is (alas) Whose end let malyce styll attempt, to bring the same to passe. O DIDO thou hadst liu'de, a happye Woman styll, If fickle fancie had not thrald thy wits: to retchlesse wyll. For as the man by whom, thy deadly dolors bred: Without regard of plighted troth, from CARTHAGE Citie fled. So might thy cares in tyme, be banisht out of thought: His absence might well salue the sore, that earst his presence wrought. For fyre no lenger burnes, then Faggots feede the flame: The want of things that breede annoy, may soone redresse the same. But I vnhappy moste, and gript with endles griefes: Dispayre (alas) amid my hope, and hope without reliefe. And as the sweltyng heate, consumes the Wax away: So doo the heapes of deadly harmes, styll threaten my decay. O Death delay not long, thy dewtye to declare: Ye Sisters three dispatch my dayes and finysh all my care. (?) IS. VV. An answer to comfort her, by shewyng his haps to be harder. Friend IS. be now content, &amp; let my sorowes quel: the extreame rage, &amp; care thou restest in: For wayling sprights, ne furies fearce in hell: nor grisley soules, that styll in woe haue bin: Haue euer felt lyke stormes that I sustayne, fro wust so I am, and duld in deepe dispaire, That sure (mee thinks), my extreme raging payne: might gaine thee helth: &amp; set thee free from fere. For DIDO, thou, and many thousands more, which liuing feele the panges of extreme care, Though tottered much; and torne in peeces smal: whom euer griping death doth neuer spare. Nor he, that falsey, Carthage Citie fled, so fraught with wiles, nor ye such sorowes tast: By thousand partes, as I who rightly sed: do pine as VVAX, before the fire wastes. I freece to YCE, I heate with perching SON, and torne with teene, thus languishing in paine, Doo feele my sorowes euer fresher run: to flowing cares, that endles sorowes gaine. For what, for whom, and why this euyll woorks frind IS. VV, time, nor silence, may it show But once ere many dayes, my care that lurks, shall blowne be, and thou the same shalt know. Till then, with silly DIDO be content, and rip no more, thy wronges in such excesse: Thy FORTVNE rather, wills thee to lament, with speedy wit, til hope may haue redressè. FINIS. T. B. I Replye to the same. The bitter force of Fortunes frowardnesse, is painted out by B. his changed hew: Report bewrayes, that tirants doublenesse. which I by triall, proue (alas) so true. constraynde I am, on thy mishaps to rue: As oft as I consider thine estate, Which differs far, from that y? wast of late. Where be thy wonted liuely lookes becom? or what misch?ce, hath dimd thy beauty so There is no God y? deales such doutful dom No Iubiter hath brought thee down so low: thy haples fate, hath wroght thy ouerthro For as Saturnus reaues the Berryes ioy, So Fortune striues, to further thine annoy. O Fortune falce, O thrice vnstedy ioyes why doth not man mistrust thy sutle shoes Whose profers proue in time to be but toies is this the fruit y? from your blossom groes then may you rightly be c?pard with those whose painted spech, professeth frindship stil but time bewrayes the meaning to be yll. For time y? shewes, what erst I could not see Hath brought aboat, that I suspected least: Complayning still on our simplicitye Who hedlong runs, as doth y? carles beast til h?ters snares, haue laid his lims to rest For wh? we lest mistrust &amp; drede deceit Then ar we snard, with vnsuspected bait. As lately vnto thee it did be fall, whose hap enforceth me to rue thy chance For thou that florisht earst at beautyes stal: Hath felt y? force of froward Fortunes lance Compeld to furnish out misfortunes dance See heere the suertie that belongeth aye, To mortal ioys wheron the world doth stay But liue in hope that better hap may light, For after stormes Sir Phebus force is seene So when Saturnus hath declarde his might: And VVinter stints to turne y? world to teene then ples?t Ver shal cloth y? groud in greene And lusty MAY shall labour to restore. the things y? VVinters spit had spoyld before Th? shal the Berrey cleaue her wonted hew, And eke my B. that long hath rasted payne When Fortun doth her former grace renew shal hoysed be to happye state agayne Delightyng oft among his friends &amp; Kin, To tell what danger earst his lyfe was in. Which happye sight of mortal creturs, who shal more reioyce, then &amp; thy friend to see And while dame fortune, yeelded not therto but doth proseed: to proue her spite on thee yet shalt thou not so yll beloued bee, But that thy Fame, for euer florish shall, If IS. her Pen, may promise ought at all. Farewell. IS. VV. to C. B. in bewaylynge her mishappes. Yf heauie hartes might serue to be a sacrifice for sinne: Orels, if sorowes might suffice, for what so ere hath byn: Then mine Oblacion, it weare made, Whiche longe haue liued in Mourners trade. The dryrie daye in dole (alas) continuallye I spende: The noysome nightes, in restlesse Bedde, I bring vnto his ende: And when the daye appeares agayne, Then freth beg yn my plaints amayne. But this I feare, wyll sooner cease: the nomber of my sinne: Then make amendes, for former misse, that I haue liued in: Because I take not pacientlye Correction in aduersytie. VVherfore (my God) geue me that gyfte, As be dyd I O B vntyll: That I may take with quietnesse, what soeuer is his wyll: Then shall my lucklesse lyfe soone ende, Or frowarde Fortune shall amende. And for because your sound aduice, may ease me in distresse: For that two wittes may compasse more then one, you must confesse: And that, that burthen dothe not deare, Whiche frende wyll somtyme helpe to beare. Therfore, in this perplexitie, To you deare frende I write: You know mine endlesse miserie, you know, how some me spite: With counsell cure, for feare of wracke, And helpe to beare, that breakes my backe. So wishing you in health to bide, and troubles not to taste And geuing tendance for your ayde, which I requier in haste I cease: and humbly me commend, To the conducting of my Friende, Your vnfortunate Friend. IS. VV. In answer by C. B. to IS. VV. Your lamentable letter red, and finding by the same: That you my skillesse counsel craue, to bring you to some frame: Suche as it is, I redy preste, Both am, and wyll, to doo my best. And where as thou in sorow soust doest pyne thy selfe away: I wysh thee for to conquer care, least she bring thy decay: Those fretting fyts, that thou art in, Offends the Lord, augmenteth sin. The heauy hart: and mind opprest, he neuer doth reiect: And at what hower we lament, he doth vs styll respect. Yet that for sin thou shuldst thee kyll, Wold both thy soule and body spyll. But tis not altogether sinne, that makes you sorow this: It is because that Fortune she, doth frowne on you iwis: Wherfor if you my counsell lyke, Turne of your teares, and cease to syke. Impart thy woes, and geue to mee, the greatest of the same: Pluck strength thee to: and cherish thee, to modest mirth now frame: Then friends and you may worke so well, That Fortune shal your foes expell. Yf euell words and other wants, haue brought thee to this woe: Remember how that Christ him selfe, on earth was euen so: Thy Friends y? haue thee knowne of long, Wil not regard thy enemies tong. The vertue that hath euer beene, within thy tender brest: Which I from yeare to yeare, haue seene, in all thy deedes exprest: Doth me perswade thy enemies lye, And in that quarell would I dye. That wisedome which y? doest posses, is rare for to be founde: Thy courtesse to euery one, so greatly doth abound. That those which throwly thee do know, Wil thee defend from any foe. Wherfore as earst I write to thee, pluck vp that hart of thine: And make accompt for friendship, or for seruice: els of mine. I wyl nat fayle for friend or foe, Thy vertues they doo bind me so. Thus wishing God to be your guide, and graunt you Nestors lyfe: With health and haps, so good as earst, had any mayde or wyfe. I end and rest in what he may, Your friend vnto my dyeing day. By mee C. B. To my Friend Master T. L. whose good nature: I see abusde. Dyd not Dame Seres tell to you? nor fame vnto you shew? What sturdi ?st?orms haue bin abrod and who hath playd the shrew. I thought y? Goddesse in your feelds had helped with your crop: Or els y? fame iil you had knowne, her trump would neuer stop. But sith I se their silentnesse, I cease the same to write: Least I therfore might be condemd to do it for a spite. But this I wish that you my frind go chuse some vertues wife: With wh? in feare of God do spend, the residue of your lyfe? For whylst you are in single state none hath that right regard: They think all wel y? they can win, and compt it their reward. With sorow I to oft haue seene. when some wold fleece you much And oft in writting wolde I say good friend beware of such. But all my wordes they weare as wind my labour yll was spent: And in the end for my good wil, most cruelly was shent. Yf I were boxt and buffeted, good wyll shall neuer cease: Nor h?d, nor t?g, shal so be charmd to make me holde my peace. Wherfore I warne you once againe be warie of your selfe: For some haue sworne to lyke you well so long as you haue pelfe, Yf warnings styll you do reiect, to late your selfe shal rew: Do as you lyst, I wish you well, and so I say ade we. Your welwiller. Is. VV. An other Letter sent to IS. VV by one: to whom shee had written her infortunate state. Your Letters (Cosin) scarsley seene, I catcht into my hand: In hope therby some happy newes, from you to vnderstand, But wh? I had suruaid the same, &amp; waid the tenor well A heuy beap of sorowes did, mi former ioyes expel. I do reioyce, as doth the Swanne, who redy for to dye, with buryall songe salutes, her hard and dolefull desteny. In deed, I se &amp; kno to wel, how fortune spites your welth: And as a tirant Goddesse, doth disdain your happie health. Whose poyson serpentine I trust, in tyme shal wasted bee, For tinie amends the greatest misse, &amp; sets the captiue free. Wherfore (good Cosyn) as before, so now my barren quill Disdayneth not in simple sorte, to vtter his good wyll. And to discharge the dutie that, bel?geth to a frend, whose welth, I wold to God wer such, as might your case dom?d But luck preu?ting euery meane, that might your harms redresse Denieth power to me that do, a fr?dly mind possesse Yet Cosyn, rest in perfect hope, to see the happy day, That shal vnlade your heped-grief, &amp; driue your cares awai And sith the co?sel of the Gods surpasse the humayne wit. Rem?ber what the ?uerb saith: hereafter coms not yet. And p?der wel y? Shipm?s case, whose deth, y? tossing tyde Doth threaten oft: assaulting sore his shak? Ship with pride Yet wh? NEPTVNVS staieth, &amp; calmes the Seas again, His ioyes more ample are by farre, then theirs y? did c?plain He tels at home with iocund mind am?g his friends &amp; kyn The danger great, &amp; deep dispair, that erst his life was in: Tri?phyng ouer Neptunes spite, whose force he felt before: And ioyes to vew the Seas, when he obtained hath y? shore So wh? the floods, of Fortunes spite y? swel w? foming rage Shal st?t their strugl?g strif, &amp; wh? their malice shal aswage Then may you gain, &amp; long enioy the Hauen of good hap: For Nurses chide ful oft, before they lull their child in lap. And take delight perhaps to tel, what trobles erst I knew, Whose bare rehersal might enforce, a stonie hart to rew. Why shuld we th?, w? such disdain: endure the chastism?t Wherbi, perhaps, the Gods in vs, som further harms ?uent And sith no creature may deserue, Dame Iunos graces well, Whi shuld we grudg, &amp; blame the gods, whose goodnes doth excel Wheras our dutie bindeth vs, their doyngs to allow: Whose actions all, are for the best, wh? we perceiue not how We rather should with quiet minde, abide the dated time, Wherin the Goddes shal vs accompt, as worthy for to clime. Whiche after trial shal betide, to those that suffre smarte: For: he doth yll deserue y? sweet, y? tasteth not y? tarte Which argueth those y? for a while, doth bide y? br?t of pain To be the owners of good hap, when Fortune turnes again Whose n?ber, I beseech the Gods your self may furnish out, And that his eies may see you plaste, amid that happirowt Whose great goodwil shal neuer dy: althogh the w?t of time Hath don me wrong, &amp; euer doth: in shortning of my rime. Your most louyng Cosyn. G. VV. IS. VV. beyng wery of writyng, sendeth this for Answere. No lesse then thankes, I render vnto you, What? though it be a Beggers bare rewarde Accept the same: (for Cosyn this is true, Tis all I haue: my haps they are so hard: None beareth lyfe, is so from Fortune bard, But this I know, and hope it once to finde God can, and wyl, exalt the humble minde. This simple verce: content you for to take for answer of your louing letter lardge, For now I wyll my writting cleane forsake till of my griefes, my stomack I discharge and tyll I row, in Ladie Fortunes barge. Good Cosin write not nor any more replye, But geue mee leaue, mo to quietnes to trye. Your Cosin IS. VV. The Aucthour (though loth to leaue the Citie) vpon her Friendes procurement, is constrained to departe: wherfore (she fayneth as she would die) and maketh her VVYLL and Testæment, as foloweth: VVith large Legacies of such Goods and riches which she moste aboundantly hath left behind her: and therof maketh LONDON sole executor to se her Legacies performed. A comunication which the Auctor had to London, before she made her VVyll. The time is come I must departe, from thee ah famous Citie: I neuer yet to rue my smart, did finde that thou hadst pitie, Wherefore small cause ther is, y? I should greeue from thee go: But many Women foolyshly, lyke me, and other moe. Doe such a fyxed fancy set, on those which least desarue, That long it is ere wit we get, away from them to swarue, But tyme with pittie oft wyl tel to those that wil her try: Whether it best be more to mell, or vtterly defye. And now hath time me put ? mind, of thy great cruelnes: That neuer once a help wold finde, to ease me in distres. Thou neuer yet, woldst credit geue to boord me for a yeare: Nor with Apparell me releue except thou payed weare. No, no, thou neuer didst me good, nor euer wilt I know: Yet am I in no angry moode, but wyll, or ere I goe In perfect loue and charytie. my Testament here write: And leaue to thee such Treasurye, as I in it recyte. Now stand a side and geue me leaue to write my latest Wyll: And see that none you do deceaue, of that I leaue them tyl. The maner of her Wyll, &amp; what she left to London: and to all those in it: at her departing. I whole in body, and in minde, but very weake in Purse: Doo make, and write my Testament for feare it wyll be wurse. And fyrst I wholy doo commend, my Soule and Body eke: To God the Father and the Son, so long as I can speake. And after speach: my Soule to hym, and Body to the Graue: Tyll time that all shall rise agayne, their Judgement for to haue. And then I hope they both shal meete. to dwell for aye in ioye: Whereas I trust to see my Friends releast, from all annoy. Thus haue you heard touching my soule, and body what I meane: I trust you all wyll witnes beare, I haue a stedfast brayne. And now let mee dispose such things, as I shal leaue behinde: That those which shall receaue the same, may know my wylling minde. I firste of all to London leaue because I there was bred: Braue buildyngs rare, of Churches store, and Pauls to the head. Betweene the same: fayre streats there bee, and people goodly store: Because their keeping craueth cost, I yet wil leaue him more. First for their foode, I Butchers leaue, that euery day shall kyll: By Thames you shal haue Brewers store, and Bakers at your wyll. And such as orders doo obserue, and eat fish thrice a weeke: I leaue two Streets, full fraught therwith, they neede not farre to seeke. Watlyng Streete, and Canwyck streete, I full of Wollen leaue: And Linnen store in Friday streete, if they mee not deceaue. And those which are of callyng such, that costlier they require: I Mercers leaue, with silke so rich, as any would desyre. In Cheape of them, they store shal finde and likewise in that streete: I Goldsmithes leaue, with Iuels such, as are for Ladies meete. And Plate to furnysh Cubbards with, full braue there shall you finde: With Purle of Siluer and of Golde, to satisfye your minde. With Hoods, Bungraces, Hats or Caps, such store are in that streete: As if on ton side you should misse the tother serues you feete. For Nets of euery kynd of sort, I leaue within the pawne: French Ruffes, high Purles, Gorgets and Sleeues of any kind of Lawne. For Purse or Kniues, for Combe or Glasse, or any needeful knacke I by the Stoks haue left a Boy, wil aske you what you lack. I Hose doo leaue in Birchin Lane, of any kynd of syse: For Women stitchte, for men both Trunks and those of Gascoyne gise. Bootes, Shoes or Pantables good store, Saint Martins hath for you: In Cornwall, there I leaue you Beds, and all that longs thereto. For Women shall you Taylors haue, by Bow, the chiefest dwel: In euery Lane you some shall finde, can doo indifferent well. And for the men, few Streetes or Lanes, but Bodymakers bee: And such as make the sweeping Cloakes, with Gardes beneth the Knee. Artyllery at Temple Bar, and Dagges at Tower hyll: Swords and Bucklers of the best, are nye the Fleete vntyll. Now when thy Folke are fed and clad with such as I haue namde: For daynty mouthes, and stomacks weake some Iunckets must be framde. Wherfore I Poticaries leaue, with Banquets in their Shop: Phisicians also for the sicke, Diseases for to stop. Some Roysters styll, must bide in thee, and such as cut it out: That with the guiltlesse quarel wyl, to let their blood about. For them I cunning Surgions leaue, some Playsters to apply. That Ruffians may not styll be hangde, nor quiet persons dye. For Salt, Otemeale, Candles, Sope, or what you els doo want: In many places, Shops are full, I left you nothing scant. Yf they that keepe what I you leaue, aske Mony: when they sell it: At Mint, there is such store, it is vnpossible to tell it. At Stiliarde store of Wines there bee, your dulled mindes to glad: And handsome men, that must not wed except they leaue their trade. They oft shal seeke for proper Gyrles, and some perhaps shall fynde: (That neede compels, or lucre lurss to satisfye their mind. And neare the same, I houses leaue, for people to repayre: To bathe themselues, so to preuent infection of the ayre. On Saturdayes I wish that those, which all the weeke doo drug: Shall thyther trudge, to trim them vp on Sondayes to looke smug. Yf any other thing be lackt in thee, I wysh them looke: For there it is: I little brought but no thyng from thee tooke. Now for the people in thee left, I haue done as I may: And that the poore, when I am gone, haue cause for me to pray. I wyll to prisons portions leaue, what though but very small: Yet that they may remember me, occasion be it shall: And fyrst the Counter they shal haue, least they should go to wrack: Some Coggers, and some honest men, that Sergantes draw a back. And such as Friends wyl not them bayle, whose coyne is very thin: For them I leaue a certayne hole, and little ease within. The Newgate once a Monthe shal haue a sessions for his share: Least being heapt, Infection might procure a further care. And at those sessions some shal skape, with burning nere the Thumb: And afterward to beg their fees, tyll they haue got the some. And such whose deedes deserueth death, and twelue haue found the same: They shall be drawne vp Hothorne hill, to come to further shame: Well, yet to such I leaue a Nag shal soone their sorowes cease: For he shal either breake their necks or gallop from the preace. The Fleete, not in their circuit is, yet if I geue him nought: It might procure his curse, ere I vnto the ground be brought. Wherfore I leaue some Papist olde to vnder prop his roofe: And to the poore within the same, a Boxe for their behoofe. What makes you standers by to smile. and laugh so in your sleeue: I thinke it is, because that I to Ludgate nothing geue. I am not now in case to lye, here is no place of iest: I dyd reserue, that for my selfe, yf I my health possest. And euer came in credit so a debtor for to bee. When dayes of paiment did approch, I thither ment to flee. To shroude my selfe amongst the rest, that chuse to dye in debt: Rather then any Creditor, should money from them get. Yet cause I feele my selfe so weake that none mee credit dare: I heere reuoke: and doo it leaue, some Banckrupts to his share. To all the Bookebinders by Paulles because I lyke their Arte: They ery weeke shal mony haue, when they from Bookes departe. Amongst them all, my Printer must, haue somwhat to his share: I wyll my Friends these Bookes to bye of him, with other ware. For Maydens poore, I Widdoers ritch, do leaue, that oft shall dote: And by that meanes shal mary them, to set the Girles aflote. And wealthy Widdowes wil I leaue, to help yong Gentylmen: Which when you haue, in any case be courteous to them then: And see their Plate and Iewells eake may not be mard with rust. Nor let their Bags too long be full, for feare that they doo burst. To ery Gate vnder the walles, that compas thee about: I Fruit wines leaue to entertayne such as come in and out. To Smithfeelde I must something leaue my Parents there did dwell: So carelesse for to be of it, none wolde accompt it well. Wherfore it thrice a weeke shall haue, of Horse and neat good store, And in his Spitle, blynd and lame, to dwell for euermore. And Bedlem must not be forgot, for that was oft my walke: I people there too manyleaue, that out of tune doo talke. At Bridewel there shal Bedelles be, and Matrones that shal styll See Chalke wel chopt, and spinning plyde, and turning of the Mill. For such as cannot quiet bee, but striue for House or Land: At Th' innes of Court, I Lawyers leaue to take their cause in hand. And also leaue I at ech Inne of Court, or Chauncerye: Of Gentylmen, a youthfull roote, full of Actiuytie: For whom I store of Bookes haue left, at each Bookebinders stall: And parte of all that London hath to furnish them withall. And when they are with study cloyd: to recreate theyr minde: Of Tennis Courts, of dauncing Scooles, and fence they fiore shal finde. And euery Sonday at the least, I leaue to make them sport. In diuers places Players, that of wonders shall reporte. Now London haue I (for thy sake) within thee, and without: As coms into my memory, dispearsed round about Such needfull thinges, as they should haue heere left now vnto thee: When I am gon, with consience, let them dispearced bee. And though I nothing named haue, to bury mee withall: Consider that aboue the ground, annoyance bee I shall. And let me haue a shrowding Sheete to couer mee from shame: And in obliuyon bury mee and neuer more mee name. Ringings nor other Ceremonies, vse you not for cost: Nor at my buriall, make no feast, your mony were but lost. Reioyce in God that I am gon, out of this vale so vile. And that of ech thing, left such store, as may your wants exile. I make thee sole executor, because I lou'de thee best. And thee I put in trust, to geue the goodes vnto the rest. Because thou shalt a helper neede, In this so great a chardge, I wysh good Fortune, be thy guide, least thou shouldst run at lardge. The happy dayes and quiet times, they both her Seruants bee. Which well wyll serue to fetch and bring, such things as neede to thee. Wherfore (good London) not refuse, for helper her to take: Thus being weake and wery both an end heere wyll I make. To all that aske what end I made, and how I went away: Thou answer maist like those which heere, no longer tary may. And vnto all that wysh mee well, or rue that I am gon: Doo me comend, and bid them cease my absence for to mone. And tell them further, if they wolde, my presence styll haue had: They should haue sought to mend my luck; which euer was too bad. So fare thou well a thousand times, God sheelde thee from thy foe: And styll make thee victorious, of those that seeke thy woe. And (though I am perswade) that I shall neuer more thee see: Yet to the last, I shal not cease to wish much good to thee. This, xx. of October I, in ANNO DOMINI: A Thousand: v. hundred seuenty three as Alminacks descry. Did write this Wyll with mine owne hand and it to London gaue: In witnes of the standers by, whose names yf you wyll haue. Paper, Pen and Standish were: at that same present by: With Time, who promised to reueale, so fast as she could hye The same: least of my nearer kyn, f?r any thing should vary: So finally I make an end no longer can I tary. FINIS. by IS. VV.</field>
   </doc>
</add>