<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Billingsley, Nicholas, 1633-1709</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Billingsley, Nicholas, 1633-1709</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">billingsley nicholas 1633 1709</field>
      <field name="author_text">Billingsley, Nicholas, 1633-1709</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_2.1396.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1657</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:465478</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Greek, Modern (1453- )</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Brachy-Martyrologia ; Or, A Brewery of all the greatest Persecutions Which have befallen the Saints and People of God From the Creation to our present Times: Paraphras'd, By Nicholas Billingsly</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">Brachy-Martyrologia ; Or, A Brewery of all the greatest Persecutions Which have befallen the Saints and People of God From the Creation to our present Times: Paraphras'd, By Nicholas Billingsly</field>
      <field name="title_facet">brachy martyrologia</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">brachy martyrologia</field>
      <field name="title_text">Brachy-Martyrologia ; Or, A Brewery of all the greatest Persecutions Which have befallen the Saints and People of God From the Creation to our present Times: Paraphras'd, By Nicholas Billingsly</field>
      <field name="year_display">1657</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1657</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1657</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465478&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:465478&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Billingsley, Nicholas, 1633-1709&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;billingsley nicholas 1633 1709&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Brachy-Martyrologia ; Or, A Brewery of all the greatest Persecutions Which have befallen the Saints and People of God From the Creation to our present Times: Paraphras'd, By Nicholas Billingsly&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;brachy martyrologia&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1657&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1657&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Billingsley, Nicholas&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1633&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1709&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Brachy-Martyrologia&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Or, A Brewery of all the greatest Persecutions Which have befallen the Saints and People of God From the Creation to our present Times: Paraphras'd, By Nicholas Billingsly&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by J. Cottrel [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1657&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0415&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;gre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;213 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Brachy-Martyrologia&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Or, A Brewery of all the greatest Persecutions Which have befallen the Saints and People of God From the Creation to our present Times: Paraphras'd, By Nicholas Billingsly&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 438 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted; some notes omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Psal. 44. 22. For thy sake are we killed all the day long; we are counted as sheep for the slaughters. Nil crus sentit in nervo, cum animus est in cœlo. Tertul. Naz. contra Ar. p. 113. ????, ? ????????? ???????? ??? [illeg.] ? ?????? ????? ?????? ???? ??? ????? ??????? ?? ????. To the Right Worshipful, JEREMY MARTIN Doctor of Physick in Bristol, All Internal/External/Eternal Happiness. In Amici sui charissimi Nicholai Billingsly Brachy-hagio-Martyrologiam Distichon Panegyricum. Hîc magnum in parvo; veter? Monumenta viror?, Et Mortem &amp; Mores (candide Lector) habes. It skills no less large Tomes t'Epitomize, Then at the first the same for to devise. 'Twas Homers praise his Iliads to indite, Anothers in a Nut-shell them to write. Like worth belongs to thee, &amp; to thy book; Wherein (as in an Optick) if we look, We may at once more briefly far behold, What Fox, and others, have at large us told, Touching such Martyrs as did live and die I'th' faith of Christ; whose sacred memory Thou do'st receive, that they on earth again May live with us, we'n heaven with them may raign. God grant us this; and so to make an end, Thou them, I thee, cannot too much commend. Aug. 11. 1656. T. C. de Ospringe Clevie Deo Opt. Max. Great God, who grasp'st in thine eternal fists The world, &amp; boundest with appointed lists The swag'ring billowes; thou who hast enroll'd Thy Marble Gallery with studs of Gold, Whose throne the face-veild Seraphims on high Advance above the Porph'ry-Arched skie; Who all things did'st, and do'st, and wilt fulfill, According to the counsel of thy will: O shew thy power in thy servant weak, Rouze my dull Muse, enable her to speak Divinely of thy Saints, that in this story The World (as in a glass) may see thy glory. Finish this work, this work in thee begun, And make it live, when I am dead and gon. Those looser Poets who begin betimes To please vain fancies with lascivious Rhimes, Thinking thereby to eternize their name, What do they leave but Monuments of shame? Their works shall rot; while such as have a sure Foundation, shall eternally endure. Let no man deck with Apollinean Bayes My browes; thine be the Glory, thine the Praise. Brachy-Martyrologia THE PERSECUTIONS Mentioned in the Old Testament. SECT. I. The Persecution of the Church in the first Ages of the World, and so forward till Christ's Incarnation. Adam being left unto his own free-will, Satan the Primo-genitor of ill, Maligning his so prosperous estate, Did exercise his Diabolick hate, Under the hood of friendship, to o'rethrow Both root, and branch at one pestiferous blow. VVith large-pretending promises, his suit He varnish'd thus; if the forbidden fruit But kiss their lips, they should more clearly see, And full as wise as their Creator be. Thus Satan's Engines play'd, till in conclusion He took the Fort, by his so smooth delusion. Poor man made shipwrack of his Innocence, Thwarting his God-requir'd Obedience: Thus Adam fell, and by his hapless fall, Hath lost his happiness, his God and all, For ever; Ah! he cannot any more Enjoy those blessings he enjoy'd before In his first state; and all that he can win, Is death, Death is the VVages due to sin. But what of that? yet hath it pleas'd the High'st To give eternal life through Jesus Christ Our blessed Lord: whoever do believe In him alone, are certain to receive A glorious Crown: O see what God hath done, To save poor sinners, he hath sent his Son, His onely Son, who willingly came down, To bear the cross, that we might wear the Crown. Strange condescention! the great God above Is pleas'd t'embrace us in the armes of love. O groundless depths! O love beyond degree! The guiltless dies, to set the guilty free! Nor ceas'd the malice of the black-brow'd Prince Of the Low-Countries, hell; for ever since Mans forfeiture of his heav'n-granted lease, He hath been active to molest the Peace Of Christ-confiding Saints, and like a Lyon Hath seiz'd on those who bear good will to Sion: Amongst the wheat, he sows seditious tares; And setteth men together by the ears. Nay more unnatural then that, one brother He instigates to persecute another: VVitness nefandous Cain, whose brothers bloud To heaven for vengeance cry'd, and cry'd aloud: Did not curs'd Ham his naked Father mock, (A graceless branch, sprung from a righteous stock.) Did not the Sodomites deride Just Lot? And spurious Ishm'el Isaac, did he not? Jacob rough Esau hates; young Joseph's sold To Ishma'itish Merchants; and behold Oppressed Isr'el, how their shoulder grones Beneath their massy loads, hard hearted ones! And must the new-born Males be stifled by The Mid-wives? O unheard-of cruelty! And if these fail, may they not live a while? No; drown'd they must be in septemfluous Nile. Breast-hardned Phar'oh, what did Moses do VVorthy thy wrath? and may not Isr'el go From thy enslaving hands, but bear the print Thy scourges leave? O heart wall'd round with flint! Years not a few the Isra'lites were drudges Unto th' Idolatrous and self-law'd Judges; Compel'd to leave their homes, and hide themselves In dens and caves, from persecuting Elves: And when Gods bounty fertiliz'd their land, All was destroyed by the Midian band: The Philistins thirty four thousand slay Of them, and carryed Gods Ark away; A Smith in Israel could not be found To fit their instruments to till the ground, The land was so enslav'd; they rather chose, Then starve, to be beholding to their foes. VVith his keen javelin, spirit-haunted Saul Assay'd to stick up David 'gainst the wall. Prophetick David, with a patient ear, Did Shimei's railing accusations bear. Egyptian Shishak prov'd Jerus'lems rod, And took the treasures from the house of God. And (which is strange) good Asa's spirit risen Against Gods Prophet, casts him into prison. Ahab hates Micah. In Jehosaphat His reign, the Church of God was stormed at. Elijah, was despis'd by Jezabel, By whom so many holy Prophets fell. Elisha suffers; in Jehorams reign Judah's oppress'd. Good Zechariah's slain By Joash, for's reproof. Israel's King Thousands of Judah slew, did thousands bring Into captivity. Poor Judah pines By th' Edomites, Assyrians, Philistines. The Prophet Esay by Manasses Law, Was sawn in sunder with a wooden saw. And Jeremiah after slandrous mocks, VVas beaten sore, and put into the stocks. Then was he (liberty deny'd him) flung Into the myry dungeon, where he clung; At last drag'd thence, into th' Egyptian land He needs must go, the Captains him command: And his Thren-odes those pious Elegies, Lament the falling Churches miseries. Nebuchadnezzar in a rage doth throw Shadrach, and Meshech, and Abednego Into the furnace hot: By wicked men Daniel is cast into the Lyons Den. Proud Haman persecutes poor Mordecay, And a decree procures, that in one day Gods people should be killed murth'rously. The Jews returning from captivity, Judah's disturb'd and opposition's found When they would raise Gods Temple from the ground: Build it they do: though men and devils conjoyne They'r Powers, they cannot frustrate Gods designe. SECT. II. The Persecution of the Church from Nehemiah to Antiochus his time; and also under Antiochus Epiphanes, before the nativity of Christ, about 168 years. Eliashib the High-Priest being dead, Judas his son succeeded in his stead; And John the next, who in the Temple slew Jesus which sought to wrong him of his due. No sooner had Bagoses heard the News, But with a potent force, he kept the Jews, (The Jews inclos'd within Jerus'lems walls) Till sev'n years ended, under slavish thralls; Compelling them to lay down fifty Drachmes For ev'ry Lamb that fed their dayly flames. Jaddus (John dead) succeeded, who b'ing told, Of Alexander's acts, and how he would Come shortly, he in's Priestly robes aray'd, For Gods direction and protection pray'd. The King fell down, the Jews did in a ring Encircle him, and said, God save the King. He check'd, reply'd, I do not (that were odd) Adore the High-Priest, but the High-Priests God. Then leave to live after their Ancient orders He grants the Hebrews, and deserts their borders. Antiochus Epiphanes did go Unto Jerusalem: nor friend nor foe Escap'd his fury; he the Temple spoil'd Of all her Ornaments, and it defil'd: Yea, he inhibited the godly Jews Those daily sacrifices they did use; And having made their goodly structures void, He led some captive, many he destroy'd, Forc'd others to forsake God, and adore Those Idols he himself fell down before: But they that minded not his menacings, VVere whip'd and maim'd, had cruel torturings; Some crucifi'd; they hang'd the female sex, And hung young Children at their parents necks. VVhat books of Sacred VVrit they found, the same VVere cast into the all-devouring flame. Upon a Sabbath day these merc'less slaves Did stifle thousands hid in unclos'd caves. And now Mathias pious and devout, Led forth the Christians 'gainst this impious rout, Destroy'd their Altars; Providence did bless All his endeavours with defir'd success. His sons, Mathias, Judas, and the rest Did scowre their country, and their foes supprest. SECT. III. The Martyrdom of the Maccabees, under the same Antiochus. Onias acts with a religious care His High-priests office, and may therefore fear Degrading; nay, Antiochus is bent To turn him out: the moving Argument Drawn from the Justness of Onias cause, Subjects Onias to th' Imperious Laws Of wilfull Tyranny, by whose compunction, This good man leaves his Sacerdotal function, For one that least deserved it; no other Might take it up, but his false-hearted brother: VVho now but Jason! Jason is the man Must drive on the design; Jason began To force the people to renounce the true And old Religion, to embrace a new; T'abjure their Temples, to extruct them baths: To quit their beaten and accustom'd pathes, For prosecution of more choice delights, And abrogate their ceremonial Rites; To drink in Greekish customes, and betimes Train up their striplings to unlawful crimes. But mark th' event, a sin-provoked God Doth flame in fury, making them a rod (Whose Laws were studiously observ'd,) to scourge Those Mimick emulators, who would urge So good a God; their friends become their foes, T'inflict on them innumerable woes. For an edict is forthwith by the King Set forth, and sealed with his Royal Ring; The sence is this, Whoever of the Jews, Or Hierosolymitanes, refuse To offer up a Sacrifice unto The gods, he without any more ado (Besides those beatings he was like to feel) Should have his members Racked on a wheel. Antiochus perceiving this Edict VVas little prevalent, although so strict, So rigorous, but that a many chose Rather to die, then their Religion lose; He took th' advantage of an em'nent place, And summoning the Jews, his graceless Grace Caus'd sacrific'd swines flesh be given about To ev'ry man. Amongst the mixed rout Stood Eleazar honor'd for his age, Reverend, Pious, Vertuous and sage, In whom the graces all in one combin'd; Indeed he had an heaven-enamel'd mind: To whom Antiochus doth break the chains Of silence thus: Old man, avoid those pains VVait on the obstinate, for once b'advis'd By me, and eat what here is sacrific'd: Cherish thy rev'rend age, and do not scorne The benefit of life: what though th' art born A Jew? yet eat: no wise man will refuse That meat which nature hath ordain'd for use: VVhy should this beast be more abominable Then other beasts? canst tell? sure th' art not able: VVhy was it made, if not to be injoy'd? And gifts unus'd, what are those gifts but voy'd? Admit your Laws are just, yet may coaction Excuse thee; 'tis no voluntary action. To whom this Nestor (whose undaunted brest VVas flam'd with zeal) an answer thus exprest: We, O Antiochus, love not vain shows But true Religion; nor Racks, nor blows, Nor brest all gor'd with darts, hands worn with chains, Nor ease exchanged for a thousand pains; Famine nor sword, nor all, should make us smother Our lov'd Religion, to embrace another: Know then Proud King, I nothing weigh thy threats, As to profane my lips with profane meats: I'le joy to suffer for a righteous cause, Rather then violate those Heav'n-made Laws: 'Tis but a death at most, if I fulfil not Thy will; and disobey my God I will not: Urge me no more, for do it I will never; This I resolve, and will herein persever. Expose me to the ravenous Lyons paw, Yet I'le not make a rupture in the Law; Rip up my Entrails, do; and when that's done, Fling, fling m'into an hate-light Dungeon: Pluck out these eyes with Pinsers; let the flame Burn me to cinders, I'll be still the same. Think not that I'll recant because I'm old And feeble no; torments shall make me bold: I am content to suffer for my God, And patiently sustain his chastning rod: The zeal I bear is not a zeal that founds It's happiness on such unstable grounds, As once to move me or to make me totter; No, Tyrant, were thy fury ten times hotter. I'le laugh death in the face, when I lay down This life, to take up an immortal Crown. Blest I shall be, although by thee accurst; Tyrant I challenge thee, do, do thy worst. With that the soldiers hale him to the place Of torment, strip him, whip him, and do lace His back with stripes, till bloody streams out-gush, And in the face of the tormentor blush: While he was under the afflicter's hand, One stood, and cry'd, Obey the Kings command: But patiently this worthy man endur'd A world of wounds, too dang'rous to be cur'd: And darting up his venerable eyes, He knew for whom he was a sacrifice; In whom he did believe: then casts a look On his afflicted self, and sees a brook, A bubbling brook, with uncontrouled tides, Crimson their passage from his mangled sides: And when his sufferance over-flow'd the banks Of torment, he admir'd, gave God the thanks. They loathsome liquor int' his nostrils pouring, Did then commit him to the flames devouring: Yet when his nat'ral life began to fail And his approaching death would take no bail; Having his wafting eyes on Heaven laid, His dying breath breath'd forth these words, &amp; said, Thou O my God art he who bringest down To th' grave, giv'st life, and with that life a Crown; Behold (dear Lord) I'm swallow'd by deaths jaws, For the strict keeping of thine own-made Laws. Sweet Father hear me; O be pleas'd to keep Thy bosome-Nation, suffer not thy Sheep, To be devour'd by Wolves, that are too bold To worry them, or scare them from their fold: O let my death conclude all miserie, And grant in dying I may live to thee. Now I am found in thee, can I be lost? He ceas'd, and ceasing yeilded up the Ghost. The Kings displeasure waxing now more strong, Sent for sev'n Hebrew children, who being young, He thought them weak, unable pains to bear, He therefore either by entreats, or fear, Presum'd he should induce them to abjure Their Law, and eat what by their Law's impure. The crafty Tyrant ambushing his guile, Beholdeth them with a dissembling smile, And thus reveal'd himself: Admir'd young men, I wish your good, O do not madly then Shun my Behests; prevent the torments due Unto the refractory, not to you; As for my part, I desire nothing more Then to advance you, and increase your store: Contemn your superstitious vanities, And come along our tracts, if you be wise: Tis no such crime if you your Law fulfil not. If you neglect ours (as I hope you will not) With ling'ring deaths I'll study to torment you; You may it may be then too late repent you. Am I a King? and shall contempt accrue To me a King, from such low worms as you? Bring forth those Wheels Rods, Cauldrons, Hooks &amp; Racks, Grid-irons, Cages; here's not all, here lacks; Let's see the Engines to torment the hands, Gauntlets, Auls, Bellowes, Brass-pots, Frying-pans. Obey, young men; if I enforce a fact Not good, 'tis not your voluntary act, You do not sin; be prudent then, I say, Not actively but passively obey. The zeal-inflam'd young men do vilify His threats, intreats, retorting this reply, Speak Tyrant, say, say, why art thou so bent To persecute us that are innocent? We will observe, for all afflictions rod, What Moses taught us from the mouth of God; Know, we detest your sense-deluding shows, Nor will we be seduc'd by words or blows: No Tyrant, no, do thou the best you can To do thy worst, we will fear God, not man: Our cause is God's, and death is our desire; Heaven is our portion, yours eternal fire. Th' enraged Tyrant after one another Lop'd off these hopeful sprouts: the eldest brother, Named Macehabous, first was stretched out Upon a Rack, and beaten round about His naked ribs, with a Bulls-pizle, till His wearyed tormentors had their fill Of long continued strokes, and did desire Rather to leave, then he did them require: Nor was this all; fresh tort'rers have extended Him on a wheel, weights at his heels appended: While yet his sinews and his entrails brake, He call'd on God, then to the Tyrant spake: Blood-guilty wretch, who labor'st to disthrone Gods Majesty it self; know, I am one Am for the cause of God a sufferer, And no witch, nor inhuman murtherer. When the afflicter with compassion sway'd, Bid him submit unto the King, he said, Accursed ministers of Tyranny, Your wheels as yet, are not so sharp, that I Should thereby be enforced to abjure Heaven, wherein is my foundation sure. See, tyrant, see how resolute I am; Winde off my flesh with pinsers, do, and cram Young Vultures with the bits before mine eyes: Put, put me to the worst of cruelties: Rost (if you please) by a soft fire my flesh, And if that will not serve, invent a fresh: Inflict, inflict, till there cannot be found A place, whereon t'inflict another wound. So said, thus rack'd, into a fire he's thrown, And now his wasting bowels stared on The Tyrants face; yet with an unmov'd brest He to his brethren thus himself exprest: Beloved brethren, learn by my example To scorn the worlds alluring baits, and trample All torments under foot; obey God rather Then this proud Tyrant: God's a gracious father; And when him pleases, with a smile or frown, Can raise the humble, strike the lofty down. This torment's not enough to end his pain, For he is snatch'd out of the fire and flame Alive; his tongue was plucked out and then His life he ended in a frying pan: And now his soul enjoy'd what he desir'd, His friends rejoyced, and his foes admir'd. Then was the second brother, Aber call'd, Who with the tort'ring Engines unappal'd, Refus'd to eat, chains did his hands restrain: His skin (the garment of his flesh) was flain From head to knees; the tort'rer did devest His intrails peeping from his unglaz'd brest, Too grievous to behold; and him at last Unto a famine-pined Leopard cast: The beast (though truculent) did onely smell, And went her way, forgetting to be fell, Nor was sh' injurious to him in the least. The Kings displeasure but the more increas'd, And Aber grown more constant by his pain, Thus, thus his dying voice did loudly strain: How sweet! How pleasant is this death to me! Yea 'tis most welcome, for I'm sure to be Rewarded by my God; the cross I bear On earth, in heav'n a glorious Crown to wear; I thank my God, that I am more content To suffer, Tyrant, then thou to torment. And yet is not this misery of mine In suff'ring, so exorbitant as thine Is by inflicting; keeping of the Laws Thus aggravates my pains, and thou the cause Shalt by the justice of the Holy One Be banished from thy usurped throne, And be reserved for those horrid chains Of utter darkness, and eternal pains. He said no more; his soul forsook his brest, To take possession of aye-lasting rest. Machir the third son's brought, who was not quell'd, But angrily their counsel thus repell'd: One Father us begat; one Mother bore us; One Master taught us, who is gone before us: Protract no time, for I am not so weak To yield; I come to suffer, not to speak: What care I though I drink the brim-fild boul Of thy displeasure? twill not hurt my soul. A Globe was brought, his woes must b'aggravated, And bound thereon; his bones were dislocated; They flaid his face; and while a crimson river Flow'd from him, thus he did himself deliver: O Tyrant, we, what we endure, endure For the pure love of God: thou shalt be sure To rove in Sulph'ry flames, and be tormented Eternally, unpity'd, unlamented. His tongue b'ing taken out, this good young man Departed in a red-hot Frying-pan. Judas is next, whom neither menacing Nor flattries, could induce t'obey the King: Your fire (said he) shall me attract more near Gods holy Law, and to my brethren dear: I tell thee Tyrant, thou shalt be acurs'd, And true believers blest: thou that art nurs'd By cruelty it self: I bid thee try me, And see if God will not also stand by me. Hereat the Tyrant in a hot displeasure Hastily left his chair t'afflict by leasure; He charg'd his tongue to be cut out, in brief; T'whom Judas thus; Our God is not so deaf As you imagine; his attentive ear Hears the dumb language of his servants pray'r: He hears the heart, not voice; our thoughts he sees A distance off; distongue me if you please: Divide me limb from limb, do Tyrant, do, But know, thou shalt not long scape Scot-free so. He's tongueless, and with ropes ends beaten sore, Which he with much admired patience bore: At last upon the Rack his life was spent, And to his brethren (gone before) he went. Then Achas the fifth brother unaffraid To hug grim death, disclos'd his lips, and said, Tyrant, behold, I come for to prevent Thy sending for; and know that I am bent To die couragiously, my mind is steady; Thou art to hellish flames condem'd already, By my dear bretherens effused gore, And I the fifth shall make thy grief the more. What is't that we have done? what other cause Canst thou alleage, but this, We keep Gods Laws? And therefore in the midst of torturing We joy O 'tis an honourable thing! Though each part suffer, heaven will right our wrongs, And fill your mouths with howlings, ours with songs. Then was he in a brazen morter pounded, Nay th'less he said, Those favours are unbounded With which thou crown'st us (though against thy wil) We please our God, rage thou, and rage thy fill: If thou shouldst pity me, I should be sorry; Death's but the prologue to immortal glory. So said, he made a stop, and stopping dy'd. Now the sixth brother Areth must be try'd, Honour and dolour's put unto his choice; But grieving at it, with a constant voice He shot forth this reply: I weigh not either; As we like brethren liv'd, wee'll die together In Gods fear; and the time which in exhorting Thou hast a mind to spend, spend in extorquing, His down-ward head unto a pillar ty'd, Antiochus rosts him by a soft fires side; And that the heat might enter to the quick, And multiply his paines, sharp Auls must prick His tender flesh; about his face and head Much blood like froth appear'd; yet thus he said, O Noble fight! O honourable warre! Glad grief! O pious! and O impious jarre! My bretheren are gone, and I ally'd To them in blood, would not that death divide Our love-united souls: invent, invent More horrid pains, indeavour to torment This flesh with greater torments; study, study New wayes t'afflict me, more severe, more bloody: I thank my God, these are o'recome already; Let thousands worser come, I will be steady. We young men have bin conqu'rours of thy power; Thy fire is cold, nor can thy rage devour Our faith-fenc'd souls; we have a greater joying In suffering, then thou hast in destroying: As God is just, so will he right our wrongs. These words scarce out, a pair of heated tongs Eradicate his tongue; then being cast Into the Frying-pan, he breath'd his last. And now the youngest brother's onely left, Jacob; who coming forth, compassion cleft The Tyrants heart, who took aside the child By th' hand and spake, and as he spake, he smil'd: Thy bretheren may teach thee to expect The worst of ills, if thou my will neglect: Thou shalt, if thou wilt of thy self be free, A Ruler, Gen'ral, and my Counc'ller be. This not prevail'd, he thus the mother dons; O worthy woman, where are now thy sons? Yet thou hast one, turn him, lest thou be reft Of him likewise, and so be childless left. The mother bowing to the king, bespake Her child in Hebrew; Pity, for Christ's sake, And chear thy woful mother: O despise These pains, and be a willing sacrifice, As were thy bretheren; that in the day Of grace, in heaven receive you all I may. Unbound, he forthwith to the torments ran, And with a serene countenance began; Blood-wasting wretch, what dost thou but adde fuel, To make hell hotter, by persisting cruel? Worm that thou art, who crown'd thee? who gave thee Those Purple robes thou wearest? was't not be Whom thou in us dost persecute? but die Thou must at last, for all thou perk'st so high: I crave no favour at thy hands, but will Follow my brethren, and be constant still. Torments ensue: through mouth and nose he bled; His mothers kinde hand held his fainting head: His arms cut off, Lord take my soul, he cry'd; Distongu'd, he ran into the fire, and dy'd. Now Salomona (all her children dead) Enflam'd with zeal, came to be Martyred; Herein excell'd them all, in that sh' endur'd Sev'n painful deaths, before her own's procur'd, She tearless could abide to see them spurn'd, And rack'd, and torn, and beat, and flaid, and burn'd: And kowing well, death cutteth off our dayes By Fluxes, Agues, and a thousand wayes; That pains were momentary, she exhorted Them thus in Hebrew, ere they were extorted: Most choyce fruits of my womb, let's hasten hence, And fear not, heaven will be our recompence: Shall's bear what Eleazar undergon? You know good Abram sacrific'd his son: Remember Daniel, in the Lyons den; And cast your eyes on the three childeren. The restless Tyrant caus'd her to be stripp'd, Then hang'd up by the hands, and soundly whipp'd, Her paps pull'd off: she while her body fryes, Lifts up her hands and eyes, and prayes, and dyes. SECT. IV. The Persecution of the Church from Christs time to our present age; and first of those mentioned in the New-Testament. Herod the Great having intellegence That there was born unto the Jews a Prince At Bethleem; a band of men he sent, To do full execution as they went, On smiling babes, throughout Judea's land: (Supposing Jesus might not scape his hand;) Snatch'd from the breast, the pretty little ones Were tost on Pikes, and dash'd against the stones. The Tyrant, after this, distracted grew, And's wife, his children, and familiars slew. With sickness struck, he knew not where to turn, What course to take; for a slow fire did burn His inward parts: his canine appetite Was unsuffic'd; his lungs corrupted quite; His bowels rot; his secrets putrify'd; Consum'd with wormes, he miserably dy'd. Herod the Less incestuously wedded; John Baptist for his plain reproof beheaded. Peter and John restor'd a man born lame, Preach'd Christ, and were imprison'd for the same. The High-priests and the Sadduces up-risen Against th' Apostles, cast them into prison: But in the night, an Angel of the Lord Op'ning the doors, their liberties restor'd: They on the morrow, for divulging Christ, Re-apprehended were, beaten, dismist. False witnesses suborned, holy Steven Did through a Stony-volley go to heaven. A gen'ral persecution breaking out At Solyma, the Saints disperse about The Judean and the Samarian borders: A persecuting Saul the Church disorders. The Jewish fury, new-converted Saul Scapes by a basket let down o'r the wall. James is beheaded: while Agrippa storms Against the Church, he was devour'd by worms. Peter enlarged by an Angel was: Sosthenes, Silas, Paul, and Barnabas Were beaten, whipp'd, and forced several times To leave their Country, and seek other climes. Paul's ston'd at Lystra, and for dead he lay; But God reviv'd him; he took Derbe-way: Much he endur'd abroad, and much at home, And in the end was Martyred at Rome. James, Jesus brother, from a Pin'cle cast, Recov'ring on his knees, thus spake his last: Father (thee on my bended knees I woo) Forgive them; for, they know not what they do. A Camels knees were said to be more soft Then his, by reason that he kneel'd so oft.) Vespasian did to him the Jews subject; Titus Jerus'lem and the Temple sack'd. Andrew and Philip's crucifi'd: rough blows Kill Barthol'mew; Thomas a dart o'rethrows. Mathew's thrust through: Simon Zelotes dead Upon the cross. Mathias lost his head: And Judas (brother unto James) not mist A murth'rous stroke: Mark the Evangelist Went up to heaven in a fi'ry Car: One of the Deacons named Nicanor, Did with two thousand Christians lay down This life, to take up an immortal crown. THE Persecution of the Church Under the Heathen Roman Emperours. SECT. V. The first Primitive Persecution, which began Anno Christi, 67. Domitius Nero, while in sheets of fire The Roman City caper'd, sang t'his Lire The incendiums of Troy, and from a Tow'r Feasted his eyes, to see the flames devour Those goodly structures, and high Tow'rs of state, Which startled the beholders eyes of late: The Circus fell, the pondrous beams and stones, Crushing to pieces many thousand ones; The fire burns others, and the flame and smoak Nine dayes continu'd, a great number choak. Thus Nero on himself an Odium brought; And to excuse himself, transfer'd the fault Upon the harmless Christians: it was they Had done it out of malice; no delay Detards his hasty feet from shedding bloud: VVhere e're he comes, he makes a crimson floud Flow down the streets: in wild-beasts skins he wraps Christians, and throws them to dogs worr'ing chaps. In paper stiffened with molten wax, He packs up some; and puts on others backs A searcloth-coat, and bolt upright them bound To axle-trees, first pitched in the ground, Then at the botom fir'd: these constant flames Afforded light to Nero's nightly games Kept in his garden: other some he takes, And goars in length upon erected stakes. This persecution through th' whole Empire spred; So that the Cities were replenished With slaught'red carkases; the old, the young, And naked women, altogether flung. Such was his rage, a Christians loathed name He strove t'extirpate wheresoe're he came. At four years end, this direful blast expires In Paul and Peter, two bright-shining fires. Peter (as he desir'd) was crucifi'd With his head downward; so a Martyr dy'd. And Paul, his faith's confession having spoke, Yielded his neck unto the fatal stroke. SECT. VI. The second Primitive Persecution, which began Anno 96. Domitian his brother Titus slaies, And doth the second persecution raise: (For whilst Vespasian and his son remain'd, The Church with golden links of Peace was chain'd) He slew the Roman Nobles; and decreed The extirpation of David's seed, John, the belov'd Disciple, boyl'd in oyl, Unhurt, was banish'd into Patmos Isle. Anno 97 One Simeon Bishop of Jerus'lem, dy'd Upon the cross: a number more beside Of Christians he impoverish'd, and sent Them out, to lead their lives in banishment. The Roman Senate passed this decree, That Christians should not have their libertie VVhen brought before the Judgment-seat, unless They deviate from their Religiousness. The Heathenish Idolaters devise Against the Saints abominabile lies, And envious slanders; That they were seditious, Incestuous, rebellious, and pernicious Unto the Empire; none could them importune, By any means, to swear by Cæsars fortune. If famine, plague, or war amongst them came, The Christians were the Authors of the same. And look what accusations they related, Domitian was the more exasperated; And us'd what e're mans wicked wit invents; Stripes, Rackings, Scourgings, and Imprisonments, Deep dungeons, Stoning, Strangling, the Gridiron, Gibbet, and Gallows, red-hot plates t'environ The tendrest parts; the teeth of salvage bears; The horns of Buls, and sticking up on spears, &amp;c. Thus kill'd, a lawful burial was deny'd them: Pil'd up and tear-throat dogs were left beside them. Though Christians sufferings were very sore, Yet still the Church encreased more and more, In the Apostles doctrine deeply grounded, And with the blood of Martyr'd Saints surrounded. Good Timothy, Religious from his youth, Was stoned, as a witness to the truth, By those that worshipped Diana bright: One Dionysius th' Areopagite VVas slain at Paris by a treach'rous villan. Protasius and Gervasius fell at Millain. SECT. VII. The third Primitive Persecution, which began Anno Christi 108. Domitian being by his servants slain, Nerva succeeded; in whose gracious reign (VVhich was but thirteen months) the Saints enjoy'd A peaceful season, and were not destroy'd. Trajan, next him, the Roman crown put on; He 'twas rais'd the third Persecution, VVorse then the former were; which did incite An heathenish Philosopher to write I'th' Christians behalf, to Trajan shewing, That whereas many thousands in his viewing VVere killed; yet contraite the Roman Laws None did, which might such Persecution cause; Saving that every morn by break of day, They to a God call'd Christ did sing and pray: In other things they were to be commended. Trajan returns this answer: he intended To search them out no more; but if they were Brought and convicted, them he would not spare. Sentence confus'd! he them as harmless tenders, And yet would have them punish'd as offenders. The rage was by this act a little curb'd: Yet ill-disposed men the Peace disturb'd; Especially, if new commotions flam'd Amongst them, then the Christians must be blam'd. Trajan commands the lineage of David. Which could be found, should by no means be saved He Phocas, Pontus Bishop-cast in's wrath, First int'a lime-kiln, next a scalding bath. Ignatius, and many thousands more Exposed to the wild beasts to devour: Nor did in Adrian's reign this fury slake, Ten thousand sufferd for the Lord Christ's sake. In Ararath thousands were crucifi'd, Crowned with thorns, and thrust into the side VVith needle-pointed darts, in imitation Of Christ, our blessed Lord and Saviours passion. Faustinus, Zenon, and Eustachius, Dy'd for the truth. VVhen Calocerius Saw how the Saints did bear afflictions rod, He cry'd out, Truly, great's the Christians God: For which he apprehended, did become Partaker likewise of their Martyrdom. Symphorissa, a fair and vertuous dame, Hang'd up by th' hair, was scourged for Christs name, And then made fast unto a pondrous stone, Into the bosom of a river thrown: Seven sons she had, all stak'd, rack'd, and at last Thrust thorough, were into a deep pit cast. Adrian b'ing come to Athens, sacrific'd After the Greekish manner; authoriz'd Any that would, to persecute, abuse VVhoever in contempt should it refuse. Quadratus, an Athenian Bishop, hence Did out of zeal i'th' Christians defence Write learned Tractates: Serenus did do The like; and famous Aristides too; Declaring that 'twas neither right nor reason That bare opinion should b'accounted treason In harmless persons; and no other fault Should bring their lives in danger, at th' assault Of th' hair-brain'd rabble; th' Emperour hereat Grew milde, and pity'd their afflicted state. After him Antonius Pius swaid And he this persecuting storm allaid. Gods word's fulfill'd, the wicked's rod shall not Alwayes remain upon the righteous lot. SECT. VIII. The fourth Primitive Persecution, which began Anno Christi 162. Now Antoninus Verus, Pius son, (Who dead) rais'd the third persecution. Germanicus, Pionius, Metrodore, Polycarp, Carpus, and a number more In Asia burn'd. Felicitas at Rome, With her seven children suffered Martyrdome. Scourg'd was her eldest Son; and after, prest To death with leaden weights, attain'd true rest. The two next had their brains knockt out with mauls: The 4th thrown headlong down a prec'pice, sprawls With his broke neck: The three that do remain, Must lose their heads. In fine, the Mother's slain. Concordus suffered; who in disgrace, Did spirt out spittle in the Idols face. In France the Christians underwent all wrongs; As Scourgings, stonings, and the spatt'ring tongues Of railing Rabshakeh's: at home, abroad, Their backs must tolerate afflictions load: Yet well they knew, that griefs were transitory, If but compared to eternal glory. Sanchis the Bishop of Vienna, stood Unmov'd, under such pains, as flesh and blood Could not endure to bear: no torments could Prevail to make him to let go his hold. When he was ask'd, where he was born and bred; He, I'm a Christian, onely answered: And when another did demand his name, Urging it much, his answer was the same: A third enquir'd, whether he were a man, Or bond, or free; I am a Christian, He still reply'd: no torments could divorce His constant lips from using that discourse. When there were plates of candent Brass apply'd T'his tendrest parts: O how did he abide That scorching heat! nor was he seen to shrink, As did his body: while his tort'rers think, With new supplies to force his recantation, He quite contrary to their expectation, VVas so restor'd, that what he did endure These latter times, did prove his Sov'raign cure. At last plac'd in a red-hot iron chair, His spir't (with others) vanish'd into Air. Thus were the holy Saints, from morn to night, A spectacle unto the people's sight. Biblides in the midst of pains spake thus, Ah! how should we (as you report of us) VVe Christians, think you, of our babes make food? VVhen we not taint our lips with bestial blood. Attalus frying, thus Your selves do eat Mans flesh: and as for us, we loath such meat. B'ing asked what he call'd their God by name; He answer'd, Man's and his was not the same. Then let your God, if that a God he be So powerfull (said they) come set you free. Pont'cus a youth of fourteen years of age, Perpass'd the utmost of the fo-mens rage. VVilde beasts are put to Blandina, but they; More merciful then men, would go their way. VVhipped she is, then broyl'd and thrown on ground For Buls to tear: from every gaping wound Blood gushes forth, and runneth out afresh From th' unstopp'd chinks of her bemangled flesh. She felt no paine, by reason she was fill'd VVith spir'tual joy: she at the last was kill'd. The bodies of the Saints were made a mock, A scorn, a by-word, and a laughing-stock I'th' open streets, till thrice two Suns were down, Then burn'd their ashes in the river thrown. Th' Apostatized Christians, which came Unto their tryals, did confess their shame By down-cast looks, and sorrow-boding faces; The Gentiles pulveriz'd them with disgraces, As persons too degenerous, addicted To vice, deserving what should be inflicted: But they which constant to the last remain'd, VVent with a cheerful brow, and entertain'd An obvious death; and, as it were combin'd Their glorious rayes, and like to Phœbus shin'd. So have I seen a fair and comly Bride, Richly attir'd, with what a decent pride She quits her conclave, or interior room, And steps to meet with her returning Groom, Who drawing neer, about her neck doth fall, And seals his favours on her lips withall. Faith as an ornament the soul endows; Christ is the Bridegroom, and the Church the Spouse Prepares to meet him, and direct her paces, That he may hug her with entwin'd embraces. They meet; Christ &amp; his following Spouse do clamber Up by steep staires; heaven is the Bridal Chamber: Where, with Unknown delights, they are possest Of sweet reposes, and eternal rest. Marcus Aurelius, and Antonius go To war against the Quades the Vandals too: Their Army by innum'rous foes beset, Were so put to't, the souldiers could not get The least of water, their thirst to allay: VVith that, a Christian Legion fell to pray, (VVithdrawing from the rest) the heav'n disburst Abundant show'rs; the Romans quench'd their thirst: Against their enemies, such lightnings flash'd, As made them fly discomfited and dash'd. The Emp'rour pleas'd hereat, commands that none Kill Christians more, whose God such things had done: And his (which was not long in force) decree Burn'd the accusers, set th' accused free. SECT. IX. The fifth Primitive Persecution, which began Anno Christi 205. When Peace-maintaining Pertinax was dead, Severe Severus reigned in his stead; By envious rumors, and through false suggestion, The Christians lives were dayly brought in question. The King commands; his willing Subjects strive To bring't about, that none be left alive. In Sun-burnt Affrick, Cappadocia, In Carthage and in Alexandria. So that the number slain was numberless; Amongst whom Plutrach, and Leonides, Origen's father, with whom Origen His son had dy'd, had not his mother bin An hinderance, in that she did convey, The night before, his shirt and cloaths away; Hereat, he not for fear of Martyrdome, But shaming to be seen, remain'd at home. Tertullian, Irenæus, Andoclus, Urbanus, Satyrus, Secundulus, Perpetua, Felicitas, and Rhais, Did by untimely deaths conclude their dayes. Caspodius, a Divine, drag'd up and down The streets; at last was into Tyber thrown. Cecilia Idolatry contemn'd, And therefore by the Judge must be condemn'd; The Sergeants minding how she did behave her, How fair she was; sollicite her, to favour Her self, and not to cast her self away; She was but young, and many a merry day Might live to see: but she discreetly sent Such gracious words, as caus'd them to relent, And unto that religion yield their hearts 'Gainst which they threw their persecuting darts. Which, when perceiv'd, leav gain'd, she runs her home And for Urbanus sends: Urbanus come, He grounds them in the faith so highly priz'd; Four hundred do believe and are baptiz'd. This holy Martyr afterwards was shut Twice twelve hours in a Bath; at last they cut Her head off from her shoulders: thus she ended Her dayes, and up into the clouds ascended. Agapetus, of fifteen years of age, VVas scourg'd, then hang'd up by the feet: in rage He scalded was; unto the wild beasts tost; But they not hurting him, his head he lost. Pamachius, a Roman Senator, VVith's wife, his children, and neer fourty more, All in one day beheaded were; their pates Fixed on high, over the City gates, As Bug-bears to affright and scare the rest From Christianity, which it profest. Potamiena, (boyling Pitch being pour'd Upon her naked flesh) the flames devour'd. And Zepherinus; after him Urbanus, Both Roman Bishops; good Valerianus, Tybartius too, two Noble men of Rome, For their Religion suffer'd Martyrdome. 'Gainst Narciss, three false witnesses suborn'd; Th' one lost his eyes, the fire a second burn'd; The third lay languishing: thus we may see Th' accusers suffer, the accus'd go free. Antiochus fell down, and having cry'd, His bowels burn'd within him, sadly dy'd. SECT. X. The sixth Primitive Persecution, which began Anno Christi 237. Maximinus (Severus dead and gon) Stirr'd up the twice-third Persecution: Disliv'd the Teachers, Leaders, and the best; By this means thinking to seduce the rest. Thousands were Martyred, whose names are lost With Or'gen's book, in which they were engrost. About this time Natalius, a Priest, (Who much had suffer'd for the cause of Christ,) Seduced was by Asclepiodot And Theodore, who promis'd to allot A hundered and fifty silver Crowns To him each month, if he would but renownce The Christian God, and give to theirs respect: He did, and was a bishop of their sect: But God (whose mercy would not have him lost, Who had so much endur'd, so oft been cross'd) Admonished him by a vision plain, T'adjoyn himself to the true Church again: Which the good man, b'ing for the present blinded With gain and honour (as he ought) not minded. He the night after b'ing by Angels scourg'd, Did put on sackcloth in the morn, and purg'd His soul with tears: with doleful lamentation, He runs in hast to th' Christian congregation: Of all loves, and for Jesus Christ his sake, Humbly entreating them, once more to take Him into their society, and quire, Accordingly they granted his desire. Horse-torn Hippol'tus dy'd: the Martyred By sixties in a pit were buried. SECT. XI. The seventh Primitive Persecution, which began Anno Christi 250. Decius, that cruel Emperour, begun The seventh bloody persecution: Of which Niceph'rus thus; Can any tell The sands? they may the Martyr'd saints as well. Fabian, that kept a Bishoprick at Rome, And the Kings treasures, suffred Martyrdom. Babilas dy'd in prison; and a train Of forty Virgins were in Antioch slain. The Alexandrian Christians are bereft Of all their goods; yea, they have nothing left: Yet they rejoyce, and are therewith content, Knowing their substance is more permanent. When Apollinea's teeth had dash'd out bin, A fire was made; they threat to throw her in: She paus'd a while, (refusing to be turn'd) And gave a leap into the fire and burn'd. Julian, Epimachus, and Alexander, The flame consum'd: many (poor souls) did wander In the deserted deserts; others lives Lay open, to the raging cut-throat's knives. A certain Minister with pains opprest, And fearing death, desir'd to be releas'd: A young man, then, too glorious to behold For mortal eyes, appearing, did unfold His angry lips: What would you have me do? You dare not bear, and out you will not go. Because chast Theodora did refuse To sacrifice, they sent her to the stews; Where lust-enflam'd young men for entrance press'd: But Didymus slip'd in before the rest, Having the habit of a souldier on, He chang'd for hers; and she in his is gon. Didymus stayes behind: b'ing found a man, He soon profess'd he was a Christian; Confessing th' whole state of the matter; so He was condemn'd, and must to torment go: Which Theodora having understood; To save the shedding of innocuous blood, Comes to the Judge, and said, I bear the guilt; And lo I'm here, condemn me if thon wilt: As for that man, I pray let him go free, Let not your fury light on him, but me. She was not heard; both for their lives were try'd, Condemned both, Beheaded both, both dy'd. No torments that the Prætor could devise, Could force Nicetas t'offer sacrifice: He therefore him into a garden brought, With all variety of pleasures fraught: There laid him down upon a bed of Down, (A silken net softly upon him strown,) Among the Lillies, and the fragrant Roses, Neer murm'ring streams inviting sweet reposes; To the sweet whistling of the leaves mov'd by A gentle gale, he left him: presently In comes a Strumpet garishly, attir'd, And in a wanton dialect, desir'd The non-denial of her earnest sute, To use her body lowly prostitute. Nicetas, (fearing he should be by folly Conqu'red, and led to do what was unholy,) Bites off his tongue, and with a certain grace, He spits it out into her whorish face; So by this smarting wound he did prevent Sins sting, and consequently punishment. Nichomacus most sensible of pain, I am no Christian, cry'd; so was not slain: He had no sooner put his hand to evil, But was possessed with an unclean devil, And thrown with violence upon the ground, Bit off his tongue, and died of the wound. Many Apostates were possess'd, and some Suddenly struck, (were ever after) dumb. Though some thus fell away, others stood fast, Remaining glorious Martyrs to the last. But Decius not long securely slept: For conquer'd by the Goths, with's horse he leapt Into a whirlpool, and therein was drown'd; Nor was his body ever after found. Yea, God throughout the Roman Empire spred A ten-years plague, t'avenge the blood was shed. Brotherly love the Christians shew'd t'each other, By visiting, relieving one another: But the Idolaters fled from, neglected, Cast out, not succour'd, those that were infected: Shift onely for themselves, go where they will, This spreading punishment pursu'd them still. Gallus succeeding (Decius being dead) This persecution continued: The weight of his displeasure fell most heavy Upon the shoulders of the Tribe of Levi. He banish'd Cyprian, and more Divines, Condemned others to the Metal-Mines: T'whom Cyprian wrote letters cons'latory Shewing, affliction is the Saints true glory; Deep wounds and scars are to a Christian brest As Ornaments to bring them in request With God himself; to multiply their fame, And not as markes of stigmatized shame. And though the naked Mines afford no beds, Can they want ease that lay in Christ their heads? What if their aking bones lie o'th' cold floor? Is't pain to lie with Christ? say they are poor, Yet are they rich in faith: suppose their hands Be manacled, put case coacted bands Hold their worn feet: Can he be said to be Fetter'd with chains, whom the Lord Christ doth free? He lies ty'd in the stocks, thereby whose feet To run a heav'nly race become more fleet. Nor can a Christian be bound so fast, But his life's crown, adds wings unto his hast. They have no clothes, cold weather to resist: Can he be naked who hath put on Christ? Do they want bread? Christ is the bread of life, That commeth down from heaven, in him is rife: Man by the word which doth from God proceed, Is said to live, and not alone by bread. What matter is't though you deformed seem? You shall be honour'd, and of great esteem: Your God will turn your miserable dayes To peace; your mournings into songs of praise: You sail through troublous Seas, to be possest Of heaven, the haven of eternal rest. And do not grieve, because you are forbid To serve the Lord, (as formerly you did) In your Parochial places, God's enclin'd T'accept th' endeavours of a willing minde: The dayly sacrifices you impart, God loves; a broken and a contrite heart His soul takes pleasure in: he doth regard, His servants tears, and will at last reward Fidelious brests, which do confess his name: Promis'd he hath, and will perform the same. SECT. XII. The eighth Primitive Persecution, which began Anno Christi 259. Valerian next adds fuel to the fire, And blows the flames of persecution higher; By an Egyptian Sorcerer beguil'd, He now is cruel, who before was milde. The Christians are banished his Court, Where lately he allow'd them to resort; Nor was this all; young men, maids, husbands, wives, All sorts, and ranks, must lose (dear hearts!) their lives. Three hundred souls, then by the President Of Carthage were into a lime-kiln sent. Three Virgins first had Vinegar and gall Forc'd down their throats; then scourg'd, then rack'd and all Besmeared were with lime: then broil'd, then cast To wild beasts, and beheaded at the last. When Cyprian long had born afflictions yoke, His neck submitted to the fatal stroke. Sixtus a Bishop of the City Rome, And his six Deacons, suffer'd Martyrdome. Laurence the seventh, as along he went With Sixtus going to his punishment, Complain'd he might not (seeing he had rather Suffer then live) die with his Rev'rend father. Sixtus reply'd, before three dayes were out He should come after: go and give about I'th' interim thy treasures to the poor: Th' observing Judge supposing he had store Of wealth crock'd up, commanded him to bring All that he had: For to effect which thing, Laurence crav'd three dayes respit; in which stock Of time, he gath'red a poor Christian flock Into a ring; the fourth day doth afford New light, and he must now make good his word. Being enforc'd by a severer charge, Couragious Laurence doth his arms enlarge Over the needy throng, and said, These be The precious Jewels of the Church: see, see, Here treasure is indeed; here Christ doth dwell. But Oh! what tongue sufficiently can tell The raving fury which the Tyrant acted; How he did stamp, did stare like one distracted? His eyes did sparkle, his gnash'd teeth struck fire, And's mouth all in a foam, thus wreak'd his ire: Kindle the fire; Faggots on Faggots fling: What, doth the villain thus delude the King? Away, away with him; whip beat him sore; Jesteth the Traitor with the Emperour? Pinch him with red-hot tongs; let candent plates Engird the Raskals loyns; heat, heat the grates; And when y'have bound the Rebell hand and foot; On with him, rost him, broil him: look you do't, On pain of our displeasure; toss him, turn him; I charge you, do not leave him till you burn him, And that to cindars too: each man fulfill His office quick, and execute my will. Revenge findes nimble hands; the tort'rers lay Him on a soft Down-bed; I will not say, A fi'ry iron one: God made it so, That it afforded Laurence ease, not woe. Valerians heart burns, Laurence flesh doth rost; 'Tis doubtful whether was tormented most. Then Laurence thus: Tyrant, this side's enough: turn up the rest; Or rost or raw, try which thou likest best. SECT. XIII. The ninth Primitive Persecution, which began Anno Christi 278. Claudius, and after him Quintilian, (Both which but one and thrice three years did reign) Maintain'd the Churches Peace: while they endur'd, The Saints were happy, and their lives secur'd. Aurelian, nat'rally severe and cruel, Succeeds; his rage fomented by the fuel Of mis-informing sinister suggestions, Prov'd Tyrannous; his Nephew's life he questions; And questioning, abrepts: then he begun To stir up the ninth persecution. But thus it happ'ned: while he went about To seal the Edict that was issuing out, There did a Thunder-bolt so neer him fall, That he was kill'd, 'twas the consent of all. The Emp'rour strake with such astonishment, Gave over his Tyrannical intent. He after six years reign was murthered: And the Church forty four years flourished Under a various Emp'rour. O what peace Doth crown the Christians brows! what large increase Of honour doth betide them! they resort Unto the Court, who lately were a sport T'insulting foes: and they that were a prey, Are prais'd and priz'd: who now more great then they? While thus the Christians bath'd themselves in quiet, Their natures drew them to excessive riot, T'indulge to idleness, to scold, and brawl For very trifles, or nothing at all; With railing words bespatt'ring one another, Moving sedition against each other: Bishops with Bishops; and the vulgar train Do with the vulgar altricate for gain: Thus, thus their sins encreased ev'ry day, Till Gods wrath came, where sin chalk'd out the way: And now the Christians enemies abound, Laying their Churches level with the ground; Burn sacred Writs. i'th' open market-places; Pursue their Priests, and load them with disgraces: Slanders and contumelious opprobries, Abhor'd their Doctrine, and their words despise. SECT. XIV. The tenth Primitive Persecution, which began Anno Christi 308. Tvvo Tyrants, Dioclesian in the VVest And Maximinian in the East, distress'd The Saints of God: the foe-men overcome, They instituted solemn games at Rome, As glad memorials of their b'ing victorious: Nay Dioclesian was so vain-glorious, He needs would be a god, and be ador'd By ev'ry bended-knee, as supream Lord: Nor did he stick to say, that he was brother Unto the Sun and Moon, as was no other. His shoes adorn'd with gold and Precious stones, The people kneeling on their marrow-bones He bid to kiss his feet, (O height of pride!) He persecution rais'd; at Easter tide Places of Divine worship he or'eturn'd; And in contempt the Sacred Scripture burn'd, Some Elders of the Church were torn in sunder; The rest variety of deaths went under. Sylvanus Bishop, with him thirty nine, Ended their sorrowes in a Mettle-Mine. The Tyrian Christians (none this fury spares) VVere cast to Lyons, Leopards, and Bears Kept hungry for that purpose: male-content, The beasts not touched them; their claws were bent At other preyes; they vehemently rage 'Gainst those which brought the Christians on the stage, And seiz'd on them; who though they thought they stood Out of harms way, became the wild beasts food. And afterwards, these holy Martyrs slain, VVere soon committed to the foaming main. The Syrian Pastors lay in prison chain'd; Zenebius a Physician, Brick-bats brain'd. Yea good Serena Dioclesians wife, Was for religions sake depriv'd of life. The Martyrs blood ran like a flowing tide, Such an innumerable number dy'd. Upon a Christmas-day Maximinus fir'd A Church whereto the Christians retir'd, To celebrate that joyful day, wherein Jesus was born to save them from their sin. He also did a Phrygian City burn, And all th' inhabitants which would not turn. Forty young Gentlemen of good repute, Confess'd their faith, and boldly did refute False wayes: their names up to the Marshal gave, Who seeing them so gallantly behave Themselves, admir'd, and stood in a quandary, What course to take, his anxious thoughts did vary: Resolved, he try'd what fair words would do; Proff'ring them money, and preferment too: They answer'd thus; We nothing do desire, But Christ alone; the wheel, the cross, the fire, Are easie pains. His eyes the Marshal casts Upon a pond expos'd to northern blasts; Bids them be stripp'd unto their naked skin; 'Twas winter-weather, yet they must go in, There stay all night. We put not off our cloaths, Say they, but our old man, which God so loaths. The pond receiv'd them, and the nipping frost Stiffened their members; breath not fully lost When day appear'd unto the wakened world, They were took out, and burn'd; their ashes hurl'd Into the gliding streams. ? In France, in Colen, Italy, and Spain, Were many millions of Christians slain, As witnessed unto the truth: in Trevers The brookes of blood discolour'd ample Rivers. This persecution run along, and came Into our Britain, where the Christians flame. Besides the kindes of deaths, the torments were So great, that they unutterable are; As whippings, scourgings, rackings, hackings, manglings, Hangings, bangings, prickings, kickings, stranglings, Smoakings, choakings, rostings, scorchings, spoylings, Cuttings, guttings, flayings, fryings, broylings: Some manded to the mines, others were quarter'd; In brief, there were seventeen thousand Martyr'd In one months space; yet still the Christians joy'd, And still encreas'd, the more they were destroy'd. Galerius invading Antioch, Romanus runs, and tells the Christian slock, That wolves, which would devour them up, were neer: But therewithal, exhorts them not to fear The greatest perils, but that young and old Would be couragious, resolute and bold, To hazard life and limb, for to maintain God's cause and theirs. With that, an armed train Pour'd in upon them; but the Christian throng Arm'd with the staffe of faith, were too too strong For them to grapple with then: speedy word Was sent their Captain, that no power of sword Could e're prevail; it was in vain to strive Against the stream Romanus yet alive. The ireful Captain, in a fume, commands Romanus be deliver'd to his hands. Romanus comes; thus did the Captain say, And art thou then the Author of this fray? Art thou the cause why thus so many fall? By Jove I swear that answer for them all Thou shalt; and that e're thee and I do part, I'll make thee undergo the self-same smart Thou do'st encourage others to abide. Galerius ceas'd: Romanus thus reply'd; Tyrant, I hug, and willingly embrace Thy sentence; know, I count it no disgrace To be for my dear breth'ren sacrific'd, By worst of torments, that can be devis'd. Galerius raging at this answer stout, Commands his men to truss him, and draw out His bowels. Th' executioners defer Such horrid deeds, and say, Not so good Sir, He is of noble Parents, and his breath May not be stop'd by an ignoble death. Scourge him then soundly, let your yerking lashes, Weighty with leaden knobs, cut wounds, and gashes. To whom Romanus used this expression; Not my descent, but Christian-like profession Nobilitateth me; be not therefore More favourable, but inflict the more: Your Idol-worship I detest, despise, And all your superstitious fooleries. With that his sides, his naked sides, were lanc'd T'his bones; yet still this blessed Saint advanc'd The living God, and Christ, whom he hath sent: Then were his teeth struck out, for this intent He might not speak so audibly: his face Was buffeted, his cheeks were slic'd; nor was This all; nails tear his eyelids: from his chin They pluck'd his beard, and with his beard the skin: Yet this meek Martyr said, I give to thee O Captain, thanks, for opening wide to me So many mouths, whereby to shew the power Of God, and Jesus Christ my Saviour: Look Tyrant look, upon my various wound; So many mouths have I, Gods praise to sound. The Captain wond'ring at his constancy, Ceased to exercise more cruelty: Yet menaced to burn him, and did say Thy cruc'fi'd Christ is but of yesterday, The Gentiles gods of longer standing are. Romanus takes occasion to declare Th' eternity of Christ: of seven year old Give me a childe (said he) what he'll unfold Listen unto: From out the gazing throng A pretty boy is pick'd: Romanus tongue Bespeaks him thus; My Lamb, ought we not rather To worship Christ, and in this Christ one Father, Then a plurality of Deities? Speak, 'tis a good boy, speak: the Child replies, There needs must be but one God we conceive; That there are more, we children can't believe. Th' amazed Captain said, Young villain, where, And of whom learn'dst thou this? my mother dear, He answer'd, taught it me; this from her breast I suck'd in with my milk, that I must rest My faith in Christ alone, and in no other. In comes rejoycingly the sent-for mother; The child's hors'd up and scourg'd, the standers by, With wat'ry eyes behold this cruelty; While the glad mother, a tear-less Spectator Chides her sweet babe, for asking for cold water: After that cup she chargeth him to thirst The babes drank of, which were in Bethlem nurs'd: Upon my blessing, Isaac record, Proff'ring his neck unto his father's sword. Then did the barbarous tormentor pull The hair, the skin, and all, from the childs scull. The mother cryes, This pain will soon be gon; Suffer, my child, my sweet-fac'd child, anon Thou'lt pass to him, who will adorn thy head With an eternal crown, a crown indeed! Thus doth the mother chear the child: the child Takes heart to grass, and in his pains he smil'd. The Tyrant seeing how the Child stood fast, Himself subdu'd, commands him to be cast Into a stinking Dungeon, whilst that pain Unto Romanus was renew'd again. Romanus is drag'd forth, to have a fresh Supply of stripes, on his bemangled flesh. Discovering the bare bones, a second smart Augmenteth each already-wounded part. Nor was this yet enough; cut, prick'd, and pounc'd He suddenly must be; then was denounc'd A final sentence 'gainst him, and the child; Both must be burn'd, their torments were too milde; The tort'rers did too favourably deal. Romanus boldly said, I do appeal From this ungodly sentence of thine own, To Christ his righteous Tribunal Throne, Who is an upright Judge; not that I fear Thy merc'less handling; no, I more can bear Then thou canst lay upon me; but that I May shew thy judgments to be cruelty, The childe's demanded of his mother; she, Embracing it, deliver'd it to be Bereav'd of life; and when the fatal stroke Was given, Farewel, sweet child, Farewel, she spoke: All praise O Lord, with heart and word, Unto thy name we render: The Saints that dye, are in thine eye Most precious, dear, and tender. The childs head's off, the mother tender-hearted Enwrap'd it in her lap, and so departed. Romanus then into the fire is flung: A storm extinguish'd it; and now his tongue Must take a farewel of his head; his neck Becomes the subject of a halters check. One Gordius having liv'd a certain time In deserts, counted it at last a crime Not to endure; he therefore when a game Was celebrated unto Mars, forth came, And up in a conspicuous place b'ing got, He said, I'm found of those that sought me not: Then apprehended, he his faith confesses; And in the midst of torment this expresses: God's my adjutor, Ah! why should I than Fear in the least the Tyranny of man? Nothing shall me dismay, that can fall out; Thou Lord art with me, fencing me about With Bullwarks of thy love; thy favour still Surrounds me: Ah! how can I then fear ill? These torments are but light, which I endure; Let heavier come. Tormentors, pray procure Substantialler then these; these are too small: Gibbits? and racks? as good have none at all. VVhen foul means could not shake his faith in Christ, He was by specious promises entic'd: But Gordius said, I do expect in heaven Greater preferments, then on earth are given. Now for this good man going to be burn'd, How many tender-hearted persons mourn'd! To whom he thus; Let not your brimfill'd-eyes Weep showres for me, but for God's enemies; VVho make a fire for us, But in conclusion, Purchase a greater to their own confusion: O weep for them, or none; good people curb Those gliding streams, and do not thus disturb My calmed minde: for truely I could bear A thousand deaths for Christ, and never fear. Some pity'd him, while others, standing by, Perswade him to deny Christ verbally, And to himself reserve his conscience. My tongue, said he, will under no pretence Deny its donor: unto righteousness Our hearts believe, but 'tis our tongues confess Unto salvation; O let me excite You all to suffer for a cause so right: Good folks, fulfill a dying mans desire. So said, he ceas'd, and leap'd into the fire. One Menas, an Egyptian born and bred, Leaving his temporal subsistence, led A solitary life, in desert places; Where he might wholly exercise his graces, In fasting, prayer, meditation, fit And dil'gent reading of the sacred Writ. At last return'd to Cotis, when the croud Were at their pastimes, he proclaim'd aloud Himself to be a Christian: then surpriz'd, His faith in God more boldly he agniz'd. Torments ensu'd; no torments could revoke His minde, but thus he confidently spoke: In my minde, nothing comparable is To the enjoyment of eternal bliss: Nay, all the world, if put into one scale, Is lighter then one soul: VVho can prevail, To disunite us from the love of Christ? Can tribulation? anguish? he's the high'st; To him will I look up; he bids me fear not Those that can kill me bodily, but are not Able to hurt the soul; but fear him who Hath pow'r to slay the soul and body too, And fling them into hell. Having receiv'd The final sentence, up to heaven he heav'd His eyes, hands, heart, and said: O Lord my maker, Thanks be to thee, in that I am partaker Of Christ his precious blood: thou hast not let My foes devour me, but hast beset My heav'n-fix'd soul with such true constancy, That in the faith I liv'd, for that I die. The lift up axe, upon his neck falls down, And so he lost his head, but found a Crown. In Portugal a Noble Virgin nam'd Eulalia, of twelve years old, enflam'd With holy zeal, most earnestly desir'd To suffer death, and heartily requir'd The blest assistance of Gods willing arm, And faith all her corruptions to charm: Her godly Parents, fearing she should come T'untimely death, did keep her close at home; But she (not brooking long delay) by night Stole out of doors, by that time it was light She came into the City, and appearing Before the Judge, spake boldly in his hearing: What, no Shame in you? will you still be bent To shoot your arrowes at the innocent? Never have done (because no power controuls) To break their bodies, and afflict their souls? Are you desirous what I am to know? I am a Christian, and an open foe Unto your diabolick sacrifices: As for your Idols, them my soul despises: I do aknowledge, with my voice and heart, Th' all-powerfull God: Hangman, in ev'ry part Come cut and mangle me, dishead me, burn me; What ever thou canst do, shall never turn me. Alas! alas! my flesh is too too weak, And may be conquer'd; thou maist eas'ly break This brittle Casket: but my inward minde A jewel is which thou shalt never finde. Then thus the angry Judge; Here Hangman, take her, Drag her out by the hair, to torments; make her Be sensible of what our Gods can do, And we: But yet before thou undergo A miserable end, O sturdy girle, I'de fain have thee recant; life is a pearl Too precious to lose: call but to minde Thy Noble Birth, and be not so unkinde To thine own self as to neglect thy fortune; Methinks the glist'ring Bride-bed should importune Thee to preserve thy life: bar not thine ears, But be entreated by thy Parents tears, Not to contemn th' Aurora of thy time; The flower of thy youth is in its prime, And wilt thou slight it now? well, if thou wilt, Know, that to make thee answer for thy guilt, Engines are ready; if thoul't not be turn'd, Thou shalt beheaded be, or rack'd, or burn'd: What a small matter is't, not worth this strife, To strew incense? yet that shall save thy life. Eulalia not reply'd, but spurn'd abroad The incense heaps, and did with spittle load The tyrants face: the Hangman having retch'd her; With wilde-beasts talons to the hard bones scratch'd her. But she ceas'd not to praise the Lord and prize Th' attainment of these sublime dignities. VVith th' iron grate her mangled body's gor'd; Her brests, with flaming torches are devour'd; Her long hair set on fire: she opened wide Her mouth, and sucked in the flame, and di'd. The Judge told Agnes, if she did refuse To sacrifice, there was a common stews, And in she should: the chast religious maid Unto the flock'd-lascivious youngsters said, Christ will not suffer this (I tell you true) This spotless soul to be defil'd by you By you base slaves to lust; then was she plac'd Naked i'th' street, and publickly disgrac'd: Amongst the rest, one scoffing at her shame, A flame like to a flash of lightning came And struck out both his eyes; he falling down, Did wallow in the dirt, while she did crown Her soul in praising God: the Judge sends word To th' executioner to sheath his sword In her warm bowels; Agnes maketh hast To meet with him; she cannot run so fast. O this (said she) this, this is he whom I Am taken with: I long, I long to die: My brest stands fair; thrust souldier, if thou wilt, Thy glitt'ring rapier up unto the hilt. Dear Father open wide the gates of heaven To entertain my soul: her life's bereaven. SECT. XV. The Persecution of the Christians in Persia, under Sapores, about the same time. And now the Persian Magicians bring In accusations, to Sapores King, Against the Christians, for their adhering To Constantine the Great, (a crime past cleering.) The King incens'd herewith, with taxes, fines, Oppress'd them sore, and killed their Divines: Simeon their Priest was into prison sent, For slighting Idol-gods; and as he went, Usthazares (a Christian of late, Since fall'n away) who at the Court-gate sate, Espying him led by, obeysance did him: But Simeon for Apostatizing chid him. The conscious Eunuch suddenly let fall A briny showre; his costly garments all Laid by, he mourn'd, and with dejected face, Deplored thus his lamentable case: Ah me! with what a brazen brow shall I Look upon God, see'ng Simeon doth deny His kinde salute? He to the King must go, Who gently ask'd him why he mourned so? If in my Palace thou want'st any thing Speak man, and by the honour of a King It shall be thine: that tolerable were; But Ah! who can a wounded spirit bear? 'Tis this (said he) that acerbates my woe; I live, who should have dyed long agoe; This Sun I see, to which I seem'd to bow Thereby denying Christ, to pleasure you; I'll take a solemn vow, for to adore The great Creator, not the Creature more. The King adjudged him to lose his head; And at his death at his request 'twas spread, Here's one that suffers not for any treason, But for religion, and no other reason. The Christians which disheartened had bin By his Apostacy, he sought to win By his profession and example too, To take new courage, and to undergo The like if need requir'd. Good Simeon Rejoyc'd, and prais'd the Lord for what was don. When the next Sun had rais'd them from their beds, He and a hundred more all lost their heads. The King decreed, no mercy should be us'd To them which to adore the Sun refus'd. The sword rang'd over all the Persian bounds; Devour'd whole Cities, and unpeopled towns. In brief, in all, during Sapore's reign Were more then sixteen thousand Christians slain. SECT. XVI. The Churches Persecution under Julian the Apostata, Anno Christi 365. No sooner was Constantius deceas'd, Julian his nephew, of the West and East Is made sole Emperour: he from his youth Was well instructed in religion's truth: His good behaviour and ingenious parts, Made him a Load-stone to attract all hearts. In brief, he had (what's difficult to finde) The rare endowments of a vertuous minde. But he Apostatiz'd: Satan his tutor, Learn'd him to be the Churches persecutor: He op'd the Idol-Fanes, lock'd up before; And when the Christian faith grew more and more By torments, he was pityful and mild, And by his gifts and flatteries beguil'd The weaker sort, who avarous of gain, VVere drawn aside: he also did ordain, That none professing Christianitie, Master of any Art should dare to be, Or any Officer: he did suborn Jesters, to load them with contempt and scorn: Himself put none to death; yet did the crew Of Heathenish Idolaters imbrew Their hands in Christian gore, brain'd them with stones, And tore the flesh from off their naked bones; Drench'd some in scalding water; some were stripp'd Stark naked; others had their bellies rip'd And stuff'd with barly, for the greedy swine To champ upon; while some with famine pine. Some smear'd with honey up against the Sun, In baskets hung, for VVasps to feed upon. The children neither spar'd father nor mother, Nor parents child'ren; no nor brother brother. The flesh-deprived bones of some were mix'd VVith asses bones: here hangs on crucifix'd, And there's one drag'd about the streets; a third Is taken captive like a twiglim'd bird. VVhen Julian sacrific'd to Fortune, one Maris, Bishop of blind-ey'd Chaleedon, Sharply rebuk'd him, call'd him impious man, Apostate, Atheist: to whom Julian Retorts, Blind fool, thy God of Galilee VVill not restore thy fight, and make thee see. Maris reply'd, I am not so unkinde, As not to thank my God which made me blinde. Lest that mine eyes, (turn'd from a better fight.) Upon thy so ungracious face should light. Cyrillus, Deacon in Hicrapolis, Demolished the Gentiles Images; He's took, his belly's rip'd, his liver drawn Out of his body, with their teeth is gnawn. A little tract of time b'ing wheel'd about, Their tongues were rotted, and their teeth fell out Of their loose sockets; their blind eyes no more Beheld the objects they beheld before. While of Apollo's Delphick Oracle Julian enquir'd, a flash of lightning fell From the collided clouds, which overturn'd The Temple, and Apollo's Image burn'd. The Christians made complaint to Julian, that The fines were more then they were sessed at: He scoff'd them thus; You ought to undergo All wrongs: does not your God command you so? Ath'nasius said, This persecution Is but a little cloud, 'twill soon be gon. SECT. XVII. The Churches Persecution under the Arrian Hereticks, which began An. Christi 339. Great Constantine, a while before he dy'd, Amongst his sons did equally divide His Empire; to the rule he did assigne Constantius, Constans, and Constantine: Constantius, that governed the East, Was soon seduced by an Arrian priest; Who him inform'd, that Athanasius Return from exile was pernicious Unto the publick good: incensed then, The Emp'rour sent five thousand armed men To cut him short: the Church was round beset, Yet he from them mirac'lously did get; Though many Arrians cast their eyes about For this intent, t'indigitate him out; Not much unlike a sheep ordain'd for slaughter: Nor could this good man live in quiet after, In banishment till he was forc'd to hide In a deep pit, where he no light espide For twice three years; and at last by a maid That us'd to bring him food, he was betraid: But God's directing spirit did befriend him; He scap'd, before they came to apprehend him. Thirty Egyptian Bishops slain; twice seven Were banished; some in their way took heaven. In Alexandria (the Arrians urg'd) Twice twenty Orthodox Divines were scourg'd. The Emperour, at his approaching death, Griev'd for his changing of the Nicene faith. Valens held on these damnable designs 'Gainst Christians; fourscore eminent Divines He ship'd, and fir'd; so they resign'd their breath, By patient suffering of a double death. Many he caused to be crush'd to shivers; Some to be drown'd i'th' Sea, others in rivers; Some in the desarts wandred up and down, Cloathed in sheeps-skins, pityed by none: While other-some, (so put unto their shifts,) Lurked in dens and hollow rocky clifts. At last this Tyrant from the Goths did fly, Who fir'd a village o're his head, whereby He miserably dy'd: unto his name Leaving behind a monument of shame. SECT. XVIII. The Persecution by the Donatists, Anno Christi 410. The Donatists, and Circumcellions, In Sun-burnt Affrick, rais'd rebellions: The Orthodox, innumerable wrongs Lay under; Bishops lost their hands and tongues: And others, that remain'd sincere and sound, This barbrous outrage either hang'd or drown'd; Their goods are plunder'd, and their houses turn'd To heaps of cindars, and their Fanes are burn'd. The sacred Scriptures are by flames devour'd; Wives are defil'd, and Virgins are deflour'd. Where ever these profane Schismaticks came, They holy things profan'd; nor was't a shame Counted amongst them, but a grace, to feed Their mungrell currs with Sacramental bread. But God's just judgements did not long forbear: The Dogs run mad, and their own Masters tear. These furious persons, cast into the stocks The godly Christians, and the Orthodox: All Affrick o're, they empty out their gall, Destroying many, and affrighting all. SECT. XIX. The Persecution of the Church in Affrick, by the Arrian Vandales, Anno Christi 427. The Vandales, under Genserick's command Remov'd their Quarters from th' Iberian land, And march'd to Affrick: as along they went, Cut down the shrubs, which yeilded aliment To the dispersed Saints; what e're they found Unruin'd, they laid level with the ground. The Min'sters sinking underneath their loads, Are pricked forward with sharp-pointed goads. Some had (until they crack'd again) their legs Wrested with bow-strings: grease and oily dregs, Salt-water, stinking mire, and Vinegar, Into the mouths of others forced are. The Reverend gray hairs, from them obtain'd No mercy: as for infants, they were brain'd, Or torn in pieces from the fundament. The Carthaginian Senators were sent To wander in exile; without respect To sex, or age, the Roman City's sack'd. Upon Ascention-day, a Christian train Meeting at Church, were by these her'ticks slain. There was a Noble man, nam'd Saturus, The Tyrant seeing him, bespake him thus: Y'had best to execute my just commands, Or you shall forfeit else, your house and lands; Your wife shall marry one that drives the plow; Your children shall be sold: nor did this bow The good mans faith; his wife hearing her doom Was to be marry'd to a scurvy groom, Runs to her husband doth her fine clothes tear, And rends from off her head her curious hair; Her brood of children hanging at her heels, A suckling in her arms then down she kneels, And said (my dearest) Oh some pity take On thy poor wife: O for the Lord Christ's sake Let not thy bantlings under slav'ry tire, Nor me be linked to a filthy Squire. Be rul'd, sweet heart, if by constraint th' art brought To act amiss, thine will not be the fault. He thus; Thou speakest like a foolish wife, Acting the Devils part; thy husbands life If thou didst dearly tender, as thou shouldst, Entice him so to sin, thou never wouldst; Which will procure a second death to me, Worse then the first; I am resolv'd to be Obedient therefore to my Gods commands, And quite forsake wife, children, house, and lands, To b'his Disciple. Scarce these words were out, He was despoil'd of all, and sent about The Country begging. Genserick being dead, Hunrick succeeded in his fathers stead. Well nigh five thousand that did Christ profess, He banished into the wilderness: He made his Courtiers dig the earth for corn, And brought the women into publick scorn. Mothers their little children followed, Right glad that Martyrs they had born and bred. One leading by the hand her little Son, Hasting t'oretake them, said, Run Sirrah, run; Seest how the Saints do trudge along? how fast They make unto their crown? hast, sirrah, hast. She's thus rebuk'd: How now? why do you go So speedy? woman, whither haste you so? She thus reply'd; Good folks pray pray for me, I go to exile with this child you see, For fear the enemies corrupt his youth, And so mislead him from the wayes of truth. As the Saints went along to banishment, Multitudes follow'd, and with one consent Flinging their children down, did this express; And must we then be wedded to distress? While you haste to your crown, what will become Of us (poor wretches as we are) at home? VVhat Ministers have we (you gon) to feed Our hungry souls with sacramental bread? VVho shall baptize our infants? tell us who Instruct us? w'have a greater minde to go Then stay behinde: but Ah! our feeble strength VVill not hold out so great a journeys length. Now they that went, and could not mend their paces, Were dragged by the Moors, through rugged places; Their flesh all rent and torn; they that were stronger Came to the wilderness, to kill their hunger, And barely are allow'd; the Scorpions crawll About them, but do them not hurt at all VVith their lethif'rous stings: thus God did please After affliction to send them ease. Hunrick sends Mandates throughout Affrica, That all the Bishops should by such a day At Carthage meet, on purpose by dispute To prop their faith; and if they could confute The Arrian Bishops: now the time drew near, And they according to command appear. Dispute began; The Orthodox thought best To cull out some, to answer for the rest. The Arrians plac'd themselves on sublime thrones; These stood o'th' ground, and said, Inequall ones Are too unfit to hold an argument, No, no, it is by general consent, That Disputants the controversie rear On equal termes, until the truth be clear. An hundred strokes, on ev'ry one were laid For this bold speech; whereat Eugenius said, The Lord in mercy look upon our woes, And mark our sufferings under raging foes. The Arrian Bishops moved to propound What they intended, at the first, gave ground, Declining the dispute: the Orth'dox then A Declaration of their faith, did pen, And did it with this protestation show: What our belief is, if you long to know, Here 'tis: the Arrians stormed at this thing, Gave them foul words, accus'd them to the King; He all of them out of the City turn'd; Who them reliev'd, must by his Law be burn'd. The Bishops which i'th' open fields did ly, Bespake the Tyrant as he passed by: What evil have we done? we fain would know The reason why we are afflicted so; If we be called to dispute, we crave Why are we thus despoil'd of all we have? Why must we live on dunghils, in distress, Afflicted, housless, cold, and comfortless? He bids, and over them his horsmen ride; Many are bruised sore, then they deny'd, B'ing urg'd, unto an oath to put their hands; And said, Our God contrarily commands: Nor are we mad-men, or such fools, as that We should subscribe, before we know to what. This was the tenour of the oath then read: You all shall swear, that when the King is dead Hildrick shall reign, and that no man shall send Letters beyond the seas. The King your friend, Upon your taking it, will you restore Unto the Churches you were at before. They that did not, and also they that did Were all enslaved, and to preach forbid. What doleful outcries! what heart-rending grones Were throughout Affrick caus'd by bloody ones! With cudgels, either sex and age was bang'd: Here, some they burned; there they others hang'd. Women, and naked gentlewomen were Openly tortur'd, all their bodies bare. Fair Dionysia bolder the rest, Thus the conceptions of her mind exprest: Afflict your fill, God's favour I have got; Onely my woman-hood disclose you not. These words scarce out, they more enraged strip'd her, Expos'd her to all eyes, and soundly whip'd her, Untill the blood flow'd down: that which you broach, Satanick slaves (said she) for my reproach, Is my best garland. Then she wisely chear'd Her young and onely son, who persever'd Patient in all his pains, till he disburst His spirit unto him that gave it first. Hunrick b'ing dead, succeeding Gundabund Twice six years tyranniz'd: mild Thrasamund And Ild'rick ruled well. But in conclusion, Bell'zarius brought the Vandals to confusion, After they ninety years had been a rod To scourge the Saints and Israel of God. THE Persecution of the Church Under the PAPACY. SECT. XX. The Persecution of the Waldenses, which began Anno Christi 1160. When the black cloak of Popery was hurl'd Upon the shoulders of the christian world, The saints still labour'd to dispel away Those shades Cimmerian, and reveal the day With truth's bright lustre; and withall devest The Roman glory. One among the rest, A learn'd and godly man at Lions, whose name Was Peter Valdo, much oppos'd the same; Declaring plainly Transubstantiation To be no better then an Innovation: He mov'd the cred'lous people to embrace The precious offers of the means of grace, They which unto his Doctrine gave respect, From him were called the Waldensian Sect: Which like a Snow-ball rowling down a hill, Decreased nothing, but increased still. Though ev'ry day and hour the Martyrs bleed, Yet is the Martyrs blood the Churches seed. This her'sy in a thousand Citys swarme, Maintaining seventy thousand men of arms: Nor could the popish Canons, Constitutions, Curses, Decrees, alter their resolutions: To suffer wrong, in body, goods, or name, For Christ his sake, was counted not a shame. Valdo yet still proceeds (nor can he hope Long life) to publish to the world, the Pope Is Antichrist; the Mass abominable; The Host an Idol; Purgator'a fable. Anno 1198 Pope Innocent the third, did authorize Monkish Inquisitors for to surprize These Her'oicks (as he call'd them) by process, That so the sec'lar power might them suppress, Is any rich, the inquis'tors had a trick To make him poor, Oh he's an Heretick, Let him have such a death; no power controul'd Or curb'd them in; but what they would, they would. If any, water, or a pad of straw, Gave to the Saints, he was condemn'd by law. If any advocate, assaid to plead His kinsmans cause an Action indeed! And if an Heir, his father that way leans, And that's enough to rob him of his means. Nay, for to keep the people in more aw, They prisoners do in their processions draw Triumphantly; injoyning them to vex And scourge themselves; with ropes about their necks, A torch in either hand, others along Must pass to terrify the gazing throng. Besides all these, they have a thousand Querks; They send cut some to fight against the Turks And Infidels; (no need to seek for heires) Their houses, goods, and chattels, all are theirs. At their return, if any ask'd their wives VVho lay with them? They 'ndangered their lives. The foes confess'd, they had not wherewithall To build up prisons for th' accused all: And yet for all this persecution, there Anno 1260.Above eight hundred thousand Christians were. The faith encreas'd, and with a prosp'rous gale Clim'd o're the Alps came to Pragela's vale; From thence the people bordered upon St. Martin, Piedmont, La Perouse Angrogne. Wander there did innumerable flocks Upon the craggy cliffs, and algid rocks. Above three thousand being hid in caves, VVere stifled by these marble-hearted slaves. The poor Waldenses by their pray'rs and tears Oft mov'd the Lord to free them from their fears. Two horsemen flying, cry'd, They come, they come; Another while, the beating of a drum Caused their foes retreat: whith stones, and slings, They thousands kill'd at several skirmishings. Thus God for his despised Saints did fight, A handful putting num'rous foes to flight. But when the godless party overcame, They did commit their captives to the flame, Or hang'd them up, or cut them out in quarters; All which discourag'd not the glorious Martyrs. Through the industrious Waldenses toil, Abundant store of Corn, and VVine, and Oil, Enrich'd Calabria; And God did bless Their pains in Provence, with the like success. At last when freely they the Gospels worth Began to publish, Pope Pius the fourth Disturbing them, they left behinde their goods, VVith wives and children flying into th' woods; But were pursu'd: some slain and others wounded, Some famine-pined souls in caves were found dead, And they that were of St. Xist and la Garde, VVere rack'd, strip'd, whip'd, nor old nor young was spar'd Panza slays eighty, and stakes up their joynts For thirty miles together; he appoints A quarter to each stake. Merindol Town VVas razed by Opede, and batter'd down. The Cabrierians brought into a field, VVere hack'd to pieces 'cause they would nor yield. And in a barn replenished with straw VVomen were fir'd. Opede himself did draw Young Infants from their mothers rip'd-up bellies; His men kill'd them of Aïx and Marseilles: Some two and two, together bound, they slew And boots of scalding oil (O cruel!) drew On others legs, But heav'n at last decreed A woful end, to that accurs'd Opede. The Waldenses, which into Albi came, Of Albigenses thence receiv'd the name, Pope Al'xander the third, his wrath did smoke When they shook off his Antichristian yoke; He them condemn'd as Her'ticks, yet they spred, And many potent Towns inhabited: Nay many Lords, and Earls, did with them side, Against the Pope, and constantly deny'd The Romish faith, and resolutely spake Their willingness to suffer for Christs sake. Beziers was stormed by the Pilgrim train, And in it sixty thousand persons slain. The Legat saies, Souldiers kill old and young, For why? God knoweth those to him belong. The Catholicks besieg'd and batter'd down On the inhab'tants heads Carcasson Town. When Baron Castle was surpriz'd, th' enclos'd Of th' Albigenses were disey'd, disnos'd, Then sent to Cab'ret with an one-ey'd guide. Yet still like gold that's in a furnace tri'd, The Saints, appear'd; their sparkling zeal like fire Blown by afflictions bellows, blaz'd the higher. Now Luther rose, the Antichristian terror, And those that were seduc'd, reduc'd from error. SECT. XXI. The Persecution of the Church of God in Bohemia, which began Anno Christi 894. Borivojus, Duke of Bohemia, Entring the confines of Moravia, By a strange providence was Christianiz'd, And with him thirty Pal'tines were baptiz'd. At his return, he raised from the ground Churches, and Schools; and all the Country round Flock'd thither: many of the Noble race, As well as Commons, did the Truth embrace. Malicious Satan env'ing the progress The Gospel made, gainst those that it profess Rais'd persecution up: Borivojus Is sent into exile. Sanguineous Drahomira' the Christian temples locks, Forbidding Ministers to tend their flocks; And in the silent night, three hundred lives Pay'd tribute to the bloody cut-throats knives. But Gods just Judgement, Drahomira follow'd, The opening earth, her and her Carr up swallow'd. The Popish party having got the day, Did all the obvious Bohemians slay. At Cuttenburge four Thousand souls were thrown Into the Metal-Mines; O hearts of stone! The Priests cry out, Blow out, good people, blow These sparks, before into a flame they grow: Water is us'd; the more they did endeavour To drown the Saints, they flamed more then ever: Many are scourg'd, some sent into exile. Two German Merchants brought unto the pile, Exceedingly encourag'd one another: One sayes, Since Christ hath suffered (dear brother) For wretched us, let's do the same likewise For him; and such a high-bred favour prize, That we are counted worthy so to die For his sweet sake: the other did reply, The joy that in my Marriage-day I found, Was small to this; O this doth more abound! Both cry'd aloud, (the Faggots set on fire) Blest Christ, thou in thy torments didst desire Thine ea'mies peace; the like we also crave: Forgive the King; let not the Clergy have Thy scalding vengeance; O forbear to plague The poor misled inhabitants of Prague: O be thou pleas'd to let them Scot-free go: For Ah! poor souls, they know not what they do; Their hands are full of blood: they pray'd and wept; And wept and pray'd, till in the Lord they slept. On Noble-men intolerable Fines Were laid; two hundred eminent Divines Are exil'd; some are burned; others brain'd; Some shot to death; with blood the earth's destain'd. The Martyrs one by one, that were in hold, Are called forth; who resolutely bold Hast to their sufferings, with as great content, As if they had unto a banquet went. When one was called for, he thus exprest Himself, in taking leave of all the rest: Farewel, dear friends, Farewel; the Lord support Your spirits, that you may maintain the fort Against the common foe; and make you stout, And resolute to keep all batt'ry out; That what you lately with your mouths profest, You may by your so glorious death attest. Behold, I lead the way, that I may see My Saviours glory; you will follow me To the fruition of my fathers sight. O how my soul is ravish'd with delight! This very hour all sorrow bids, adieu To my glad heart: O now my joyes renew: Transcendent joyes! heaven and eternity Is mine, is mine. Then did the rest reply, God go along with you: O heaven we pray Assist thy servant, in his thorn-pav'd way. O may the willing Angells come to meet Thy obvious body, and direct thy feet Into thine, and our Fathers Mansion: Go, go, dear brother go; and we anon Shall follow after, and be all receiv'd To bliss through Christ in whom we have believ'd. Farewel, farewel; let equal joyes betide To us that follow, and to you our guide. First the Lord Schlick, a man as wise as grave, Condemned to be quarter'd, did behave Himself most gallantly, and said, My doom Me pleaseth well, what care I for a Tombe? A Sepulchre is but an easie loss; Fear death? not I: welcom my crown, my cross: Let, let these limbs be scatter'd here and there; I have Gods favour, and I do not fear The worst that foes can do: see how the Sun Displaies his shining beams. Jesuites be gon, And build not Castles in the empty air, For I dare die for Christ; I that I dare. Be pleas'd, blest Jesus, thorough deaths dark night, To Manu-duct me to eternal light; Eternal light! O what a happy sound That word reports! my soul, at a rebound Catch heaven, catch heaven: no sooner had he spoke, But he submitted to the fatal stroke: His right hand, and his head (lop'd off his shoulders) Are hung on high, to terrify beholders. The Lord Wenceslaus, seventy years old, B'ing next, was asked, why he was so bold In Fred'ricks cause: he said, My conscience run Along with me; and what is done, is done. My God, lo here I am, dispose of me, Thine aged servant as best pleaseth thee: O send that grim-look'd messenger, that staies For none, to end these miserable dayes; May I not see the ruines that do wait Upon our sinking, our declining State. Behold this Book; my Paradise was never So cordial as now: Judges, persever In sucking Christian blood; but know, Gods ire Shall smoak you for't. Up starts a cowled Fryer, And said, Your Judgement errs. With this reply, He answer'd him, I on the truth rely, And not on bare opinion; Christ's the Way, The Truth, the Life; in him I cannot stray. Then stroaking his prolixed beard, he said, My gray hairs honour serves you: having pray'd, And giv'n his soul to Christ his Saviour, His cut-off head was fixed on the Tower. Lord Harant next was call'd, who bravely said, I've travell'd far, and many journeys made Through barb'rous countries and escaped dangers By sea and land: yet was my life by strangers Surrepted not: b'ing safe returned home, My friends and Country-men my foes become: For whom I, and my Grandsires have let fall And wasted our estates, our lives and all. Forgive them father; I O Lord have grounded My faith in thee; let me not be confounded. Then on the Scaffold, thus: O Lord, I give My spir't into thine hands; in hope to live By Christ his death, according to thy word: And so he yielded to the murth'rous sword. Sir Caspar Kaplitz, eighty six years old, Said to the Minister, Behold behold Me a decrepit wretch, whose frequent pray'rs Have beg'd deliverance from this vale of tears; But all in vaine: for to be gaz'd upon By the worlds eyes I'm kept; God's will be done, Not mine; my death to mortal eyes may seem Disgraceful, but 'tis rich in Gods esteem. Oh Lord my God my trembling feet support, For fear my sudden fall occasion sport To my observing foes. The Minister (Perceiving that the executioner Could not perform his office as he meant, His crookedness b'ing an impediment) Bespake him thus; My Noble Lord, as you Commended have your soul to Christ, so now Advance your hoary head to God: he try'd What he could do: his head struck off, he dy'd. Then the Lord Otto, a judicious man, Having receiv'd the sentence, thus began: And do you then, O Cæsar still think good For to stabilitate your throne with blood? Can God be pleas'd with this? say Tyrant say: How will you answer't at that dreadful day? Kill this my body; do, let my blood fill Your veins; disperse my members where you will; Yet this is my belief, My loving father Will be so pleas'd as them together gather, And cloath them with their skin; these very eyes Shall see my Lord, where e're my body lies: These ears shall hear him; and this very tongue Ring peals of joy; his praises shall be sung By this same heart of mine. I must confess, I was perplex'd at first; but now, I bless My God, I finde a change: I was not troubled So much, but now my joyes are more redoubled; I fear not death; now death hath lost her sting: To die with joy O 'tis a pious thing! Am not I sure, Christ and his Angels will Guide me to heaven, where I shall drink my fill Of those Celestial cups, those cups of pleasure, And measure drinking, though not drink by measure? Shall then this death have power to divide My soul from him? the heavens open wide: See where my finger points. The standers by Beheld eye-dazeling corruscancy. After a silent prayer made, he spake, Lord save thy servant; Oh some pity take: I am thy creature; O let me inherit Christ-purchas'd glory: Lord receive my spirit. Next, Dionysius Zervius (that storm'd Against the saints; but) when he was inform'd Of Gospel-truths, how Christ procured rest For those believ'd, he forthwith smote his brest, And fetch'd a sigh, while tears ran down; did cry, This is my faith, and in this faith I'll die: Through Christ alone, I can acceptance finde, Yet God will not despise my contrite minde; Upon these knees, these bended knees, I call For mercy; mercy, Lord: although I fall, Help me to rise in thee: My foes controul May hurt my body, but not hurt my soul. An aged man b'ing brought, both these commended Their souls unto the Lord; so their lives ended. Next was the Lord of Rugenice arraign'd; Who said, I have a greater priv'ledge gain'd, Then if the King had spar'd me, and augmented My restor'd substance; and am more contented. God is our witness, that we onely sought Religions Liberty; for that we fought: Who, though w'are worsted, and must end our days, The Lord is righteous in all his ways. His Truth we must defend, (as he sees good) Not by our naked Swords, but by our Blood. What is the cause, my God? O tell me why, So soon as others do, I may not die? For ah! thou knowst, thou knowst that I resign My self unto thee, and am wholly thine. Put not thy servant off with long delay, But take me hence: sweet Jesu come away. The Sheriff came for him; he rejoycing said, Blessed be God: then towards him he made. Upon the Scaffold, he himself did chear With that of Christ, Father, I will that where I am, thy servants may there also be, That they may my heaven-given glory see: I haste to lose this life, so transitory, That I may be with Christ and see his glory. Climbe up my soul, climbe up to be embrac'd In Christ his arms: and so he breath'd his last. Valentine Cockan spake to this effect, Upon the Scaffold: Gracious Lord, direct My feeble steps; O let deaths valley be A Pasport to the clearer view of thee; For why? thy word hath bin my hidden treasure; O what satiety of joy and pleasure Take residence with thee! there's nothing can Afford my soul more satisfaction than Thy self's fruition: Lord, my spirit flies Into thy Courts: so having said, he dies. Next, Toby Steffick's brought, a man whose heart Walk'd upright with his God; though like a cart Press'd with afflictions sheaves, to heaven he heav'd His wasted eyes, and said, I have receiv'd From the beginning of my life till now, Good things of God, and shall not I then bow My will to his, but his chastisements shun? I will not; no, God's holy will be done. Can I, poor dust and ashes, have the face To plead with God? I chearfully embrace Thy pleasure, Lord; I come to bear the cross; O be thou pleas'd to purge away my dross: Calcine my soul; obliterate my sins; And make me pure against that day begins. He pray'd; and having drunke the lethal cup, His spirit into heaven ascended up. Doctor Jessenius after him was Martyr'd, His tongue cut out, head off, his body quarter'd And fix'd on stakes. Christopher Chober, thus (Citing the saying of Ignatius) Chears his co-sufferers. We are Gods corn, Sown in the Churches field, and must be torn By beasts, to fit us for our Masters use: But here's our comfort, one a bloody sluce The Church is founded, and hath been augmented By blood, nor shall the opened vein be stented. The blow must now be fetch'd; his soul he gave To heav'n, his body to the gaping grave. Then being call'd to execution; I come, said he; a pious resolution Takes up my heart; I'm not asham'd, nor sory To suffer these (nay worse things) for his glory; I have, I have, by my heav'n-borrow'd force Fought faith's good fight, and finished my course. Then praying, Father, in thy hands I leave My spir't; he did a Martyrs crown receive. John Shultis, while he on the Scaffold stood, Said thus, Leave off this melancholy mood, Dejected soul: O be not so cast down: Hope thou in God; though for a time he frown, Yet will he smile again, and thou shalt yet Praise him, though Nature do receive her debt. The righteous are among the dead enrold By fools, whenas they rest: Behold! behold! I come sweet Jesus: O some pity take Upon thy creature, for thy promise sake. Cast me not off, my misery condole; My sins O pardon, and receive my soul: Make no long tarriance; come, Lord Jesus, come: And so he underwent his Martyrdome. Next Maximilian Hoslialeck, (Whom Learning, Worth, and Piety did deck:) After the sentence past, one asked him The reason why he look'd so dull, so grim, And sadder then the rest: To rell the truth, The sins (said he) I acted in my youth Come now afresh into my minde: for though I know that no remainder can o'rethrow Them which with Jesus Christ have made a close; Yet know I, that the Lord his Justice flowes As well as mercy, on those are his own. Summon'd to death, he said, Lord, from thy throne Look on me, O illuminate mine eyes, Lest death o'recome me, and mine enemies Insulting say, We have prevail'd. O Lord, (Be pleased to make good thy promis'd word) Let me whose eyes have thy salvation seen Depart in Peace: an Ax did pass between His head and neck. Then four more Christian brothers They hanged one by one, and begger'd others. Nor might they have the ben'fit of the Laws: When some did plead the Justness of their cause, The Judges scoff'd them, thus; Although you ha'nt Sins that are actual, yet you do not want Th' orig'nal sin of Heresie, and store; You can't exempted be from death therefore. The Saints deprived of their livelyhoods In towns and villages, retir'd to th' woods. The Parent his encloystred child bemoans, But cannot help it. Oh! the griefs and groanes Of marriagable maids! what sad farewels Take parting friends, when into Monkish cells Forc'd are their neer'st relations! Great mens sons, Fryers must tutour, and their daughters Nuns. Wives from their husbands, husbands from their wives Part with wet eyes: some thousands lost their lives; Others were stripp'd in frosty snowy weather; While some imprison'd lay, and starv'd together. The Mass-priests are the men that must be heard, And rude men, if Apostates, were prefer'd. Bol'slavia the principallest seat The brethren had (two hundred years compleat) Was seized on; her Ministers turn'd out, And crafty Friers to pervert the rout Plac'd in their rooms: but when this would not do, They must into a stinking dungeon go. The Cities Bidsove, Tusta, Zaticum, Litom'ric, Rokizan, Radecium, Don Martin, all were brought to desolation, Under a fair pretence of reformation. Some Citizens were into exile sent; Some into voluntary exile went. The Maj'r and sixteen hundred persons more, At Prachatice, lay weltring in their gore. They threw Religion down, where ere they come, And set up superstition in the room. As for the Bible, Christians were forc'd from it, Wiblia (the Bohemian word) is vomit; Nor was there (O most damnable designe!) A toleration giv'n to Books divine. The mouths of some are gagg'd, the Host they do Thrust down their throats, whether they will or no. Others t'auricular confession forc'd; And many were from all they had divorc'd. To tell how they the women-kinde did use, Is not so proper for a modest Muse. SECT. XXII. The Churches Persecution in Spain, which began Anno Christi 1540. A Spanish Factor Francis Roman nam'd, Hearing at Breme a Sermon, was s'enflam'd And wrought upon, that in a little space He grew in knowledge, and encreas'd in grace. Upon a time when he return'd agen, He labour'd to convince his country-men Of blind-fold ign'rance; for the wayes they trod Were dissonant unto the word of God. But they reproachfully despis'd, contemn'd His words, and him unto the fire condemn'd. Then with a paper-Mitre on his head, Painted with ugly Demons, was he led To execution: and by the way Being urg'd to bow unto a cross, said Nay, The Christians are not wont to worship wood: So having said, he was the fire's food. How many honest-hearted persons cast Into infectious dungeons, breath'd their last! The pris'ners cloath'd with red-cross'd Sambitoes, Were at Validolid plac'd all in rowes. Anno 1550. The inquisition was first invented By the Domin'can Friers; who attented The extirpation of the Christian race, By death, or ignominious disgrace. One while they strive with flatt'ries to ensnare The doubting Christian e're he be aware: And if they see that fair means will not do, They exercise compulsion. O who! Who is there able to demonstrate fully The kinde of torments that were us'd? the pully Hang'd on the Gibbit, holds the hands or thumbs Of the poor wretch; then the Strappado comes, And rends his weight-distended joynts asunder. Some in the Trough are tortur'd; some are under Cruel imprisonments, where is not any Light but what enters the Key-hole or crany. Some are injoyn'd to run unto the racks, With yellow Sambenitoes on their backs: Their tongues in a cleft-stick have not the scope To empty out their mindes; and while a rope Encompasseth their necks, coacting bands Press hard behinde them their united hands. Thus, thus poor Creatures, in a piteous plight, Are led to suffer in the peoples sight. Anno 1560. Burton and Burgate, Burgess, Hooker, Baker, English-men born, were each of them partaker Of Martyrdom at Cadiz; and ascended To happiness, which never shall be ended. SECT. XXIII. The Churches Persecution in Italy, which began Anno Christi 1546. Encenas, by his Parents sent to Rome For educations sake; at last become An able Scholar through the grace of God, In Christ his School, the wayes the Romans trod Renouncing quite: for which he's apprehended, And clapt up; yet he constantly defended The Christian faith: he with his life might go, If he would but put on the Sambito; Which he refus'd; nor any badge would wear Save that of Jesus Christ; which was, to spare No blood to seal up what he had profest: So being burn'd, be in the Lord did rest. The Maj'r and Bishop of St. Angelo Long arguing the case, which of the two Should, at his proper cost, procure some wood, For Galeacius burning; while they stood Demurring, he bade them no more debate, It should be fetch'd out of his own estate. John Mollius, a Roman, did Christ own: If he but named him, salt tears ran down On his wet cheeks: he preach'd where e're he came The word of truth, until he fed the flame. One Francis Gamba, born in Lombardy, Went to the slaughter with alacrity. Algerius, a fine young man, acquaints, By way of writing, the afflicted Saints, How much his joy in prison did abound, And how he Honey in a Lion found: Exhorting them to patience; in the end Writes From a delectable Orchard pen'd; He's burned. Pope Pius the fourth dislives At Naples, many Nobles, with their wives. The City Venice after twelve years peace, Was by the Pope disturb'd, to the encrease Of Martyr'd Saints; who unto stones were bound, And in the bottom of the Ocean drown'd. An Englishman Martyred in Portugal. One William Gardiner, whom Bristol bore, In Portugal the Martyrs Garland wore. SECT. XXIV. The Persecution of the Church in Germany, which began Anno Christi 1523. When Luther, with his fellow-labourers, Converted many Germans, unto wars The Pope his Highness stir'd up Charles the fift 'Gainst Protestants: to further this his drift, Two hundred thousand crowns, and at a boot Five hundred horse, and twice six thousand foot, He sent with speed; the Prot'stant Princes hence, Rais'd also Armies for their own defence: And now the Emp'rour for no other reason, Proclaim'd them guilty of no less then treason. Both parties are engag'd; but the success Is left to God, who doth not alwayes bless The better cause with Victory, nor shield His Saints from wrong; the Christians lost the field. Then persecution rose in sev'ral places; Author'ty arm'd with rig'rous Laws, outfaces Candid simplicity: 'tis sad to tell The barb'rous outrage to the Saints befel. Some rock'd; from place to place some toss'd and turn'd; Some driven into woods and caves; some burn'd. About this time, the Boors in arms did rise, And rob'd the Abbeys, and Monasteries; They after they had entertained bin By Mr. Spencer, strip'd him to the skin; Who weeping, said, This violence will i'th' end Bring mischiefe on your heads: you do pretend The Gospel; but alas! how quite contraire Unto the Gospel-rules, your walkings are! They jeer'd him for his pains; at last he's bound Both hands and feet, and in the river drown'd. His gaping wounds let out a Crimson flood, Which on the surface of the water stood. When Wolfgang Scuch was asked if his woe He would have be abridg'd, he answer'd, No; God, which hath hitherto upheld my head, Will not forsake me in my greatest need; No, no, he will not: 'tis a happy flame Which lights to heaven, thrice blessed be his name. George Carpenter b'ing cast into the fire, Fulfill'd his Christian bretherens desire, In giving them a signe of his true faith, Cry'd, Jesus, Jesus till he lost his breath. Our Leonard Korser also at the stake, Said, I'm thine, save me Lord for thy Truths sake: His willing spir't impatient of the flame Went up to heaven, whence at first it came. A cruel Bishop in Hungaria took A godly minister, (who could not brook Erroneous wayes) and Hares, Geese, Hens, he tide His naked body with on ev'ry side: Being by set-on dogs, and bloody hounds, All rent and torn, he died of his wounds. But God is Just: the Bishop that so acted His cruel part, did forthwith fall distracted: His hair by handfulls from his head did rend, And raving, made a miserable end. SECT. XXV. The Persecution of the Church in the Low-Countries. There was in Holland a religious Dame, Called Wendelmuta, she for Christ's name Was sent to prison, where she must be kept Till the next Sessions; her kinde kindred wept And said thus, Ah! why dost thou not conceal What thou believ'st but madly thus reveal Thy secret thoughts? be more reserv'd, thereby Thou'lt life prolong. To whom she did reply, You know not what you say; the heart alone Believes to righteousness; confession Unto salvation with the tongue is made: She burn'd, her spirit did the heav'ns invade. George Scherter, a Divine, passing along Tow'rd execution, to the gazing throng Delivered these words; That you may know I die a Christian, I a signe will show: His head cut off, he turned on his back, And cross'd his arms and legs; by which aspect Many believe the Gospel; whom alive They bury, drown, or into exile drive. In Colen, Holland Suevia, Lovain, The godly well-disposed part was slain. Some lost their heads in Flanders, some were sent Into perpetual imprisonment, Anno 1543. Two hundred Saints in Arteïs Brabant, Were made away with not a few at Gaunt. At Delden two young Virgins well-descended, For their frequenting Sermons apprehended, Examin'd and condemn'd must both partake Of Martyrdom and suffer at the stake. But after death the bodies of them both Remained white, the fire to hurt them loth. At Antwerp, one Christopher Fabri's brains Are beat cut with a hammer. Sev'ral pains Afflict the innocent; these bear great loads; Those are companions to Frogs and Toads. One Nicholas and Austine, with their wives, At Dornick apprehended lost their lives. When Nicholas did hear a Captain swear, He said, Hath Christ done ought that thus you tear His name in pices, reading life and limb? Pray vent your malice upon me not him: B'ing silenc'd at the stake. Thwarting their will, He cry'd, O Charles wilt thou be hardned still? With that, a souldier gave him a great blow: He thus! Ah miserable people know, God's word's too good for you: the Fryars cry'd, A Devil, a Devil: with David, he reply'd, Depart ye workers of iniquity; Depart, depart: my God hath heard the cry My weeping voice hath made; his holy name Be prais'd: so said, he vanish'd in the flame. Anno 1555At Dormick-Bert'rand trod the Cake about; For which distongu'd, he yet on God call'd out: A ball is thrust into the mouth of him; He's burnt, and's ashes in the river swim. At Lile, for three years space in woods and caves God's word was preached: Satan and his slaves Took the advantage of the silent night So finde their meetings: finding none, they light On Robert Oquir's house; his wife, his sons And he, rejoyce in tribulations. Bound at the stake, their spirits they commend To God, and make a comfortable end The Persecution of the Duke de Alva, in the Netherlands. The Gospel shining in the Netherlands; Philip, that wore the Spanish crown, commands The Duke de Alva, with a warlike train, To slay Professors, and with might and main, Promote the Romish Doctrine; to rebuke Nobles, and Commons too: the desep'rate Duke Scarce breath'd, but on them violently pour'd; Matrons he ravished, and Maids deflour'd Before their husbands and their parents eyes, Or put them unto worser cruelties. He on a time (at his own Table sate) Boasted his diligence t'eradicate Heret'cal weeds: for that besides the slain During the war in six years space, a train Of more then eighteen thousand persons were By him deliv'red to the hangmans care. Don Frederick his son kindely receiv'd By Zutphen Bourgers cruelly bereav'd The poor inhabitants of all their lives, Hang'd, drown'd, brain'd very infants, virgins, wives; Then marched he to Naerden; and the town (All the indwellers kill'd) he batt'red down. At Harlem, he three hundered Walloons Beheads; five hundred Bourgers and Dragoons He hangs, or drowns: all th' English, and the Scots, To lose their heads in gen'ral, he alots. The wounded, and diseas'd, are killed all Before the entrance to the Hospital John Herwin said unto the gazing throng, (As he to execution went along) See what rewards the wicked world do give Christ his poor servants: for whilst I did live A drunkard's life, and play'd at Cards and Dice, A foe to Vertue, and a friend to Vice; O then I liv'd at ease, and was a stranger To bonds, and fetters; nay, was out of danger Of suffering for the Truth; yonder they cry A Boon Companion goes; who then but I? No sooner did I seek my God, but lo This fawning friend, became a frowning foe: Yet this doth not, (and so I hope shall never,) Discourage me one jot; I must persever In what is good, and follow Christ the faster: The servant is not better then his master. His soul refreshed then with Gileads Balm, To sing he did begin the thirtieth Psalm With lift-up heart: but an impatient Frier Thus interrupted him, Avoid the fire, Oh John, and turn; yet you have time and space. The disregarding Martyr turn'd his face Another way: then some that were in sight, Retorted this; Turn thou, thou hypocrite. Herwin sung on, until his Psalm was ended: The Fryer then: Good people ben't offended To hear the clamour of this Her'ticks song. Her'tick? thou Bala'mite thou, hold thy tongue, The crow'd reply'd; no living soul here bears Offence: his Musick much delights our ears. Four hundred folks encourag'd him to run His race, and finish what he had begun: To whom he thus; Breth'ren, I undertake This spir'tual Combate, meerly for the sake Of my great Lord, and Captain Jesus Christ: I now am going to be sacrific'd; And when God shall of his abundant grace Call you to suffer, follow me apace. He's on the gallowes, and the ladder's turn'd, And then his body's into ashes burn'd. Some Cit'zens in a fi'ry Chariot sent From Antwerp, to the City Heaven went. One Scoblant, as he to his Tryal past, Said thus; Would God that I might be the last That thus might suffer death; O that my blood Might satisfy their thirst, if God see good; That so the Church of Christ, forlorn, distrest, Might ever after live, at ease, and rest. I now put off this Mantle transitory, In hope to wear a robe of lasting glory. A Popish Priest, by a religious Dame Converted to the faith, spake thus: I came To comfort you; but I my self indeed, Of you to comfort me have greater need. Christopher Gaud'rin said, Mans life on earth Consists but of two dayes; the first his birth; The next, his dying day: and therefore I Must needs die once: who would refuse to die To live for ever? death and I must kiss: 'Tis death conducteth to eternal bliss. The sentence past, he did apart repair, And poured out his soul to God in pray'r: Then from his hands and face he wash'd the dirt; And puting on his back a fine white shirt, He thus his fellow-prisoners bespake: Breth'ren, this is my wedding-day: I make To heav'n-ward: being come unto the place, He found three other ready to embrace The self-same death: these four themselves did chear With patient suff'ring, and rejoyc'd to bear. Then came a Fryar under a pretence To win them: Christopher said thus; Hence, hence, Thou soul-seducer; from our presence flee; We have not any thing to do whith thee. They must be gag'd: May not our tongues have power Said they, to praise God at our latest hour? Sermons they used to frequent: hard ropes Annex'd their necks, they finished their hopes. In Flanders multitudes of true believers Were sent to be eternal life's receivers. In Breda, there a Goldsmith dwelt, his name Was Peter Coulogue; whose renowned fame Had spred all o're the town, and ev'ry mouth Proclam'd him faithful, if they spake the truth. This Pious Deacon quickly was beset With popish catchpoles; neither would they let Him once enjoy the company of any Of his own Church; he over-pows'd by many Was hurry'd to the Castle, while he staid A pris'ner there: once every day his maid Brought him his sustenance, till they perceiv'd He had much comfort from her lips receiv'd. She also was imprison'd, where she found Such inward joys as made her heart rebound. Now when a little tract of time was spent, Peter was called forth; who underwent Great pains with admirable patience: These cruel villains for to recompence His maids true zeal, fetch'd Betkin to the rack, Cruelty undeserv'd! she nothing slack, Went chearfully along; ere she did part With life, her tongue thus empty'd out her heart: Since needs I must sustain afflictions rod, First suffer me to pray unto my God. This they consented to; she scap'd a scouring By this; for whilst she out her pray'rs was pouring, One of the then-Commissioners fell down Into an irrecoverable swown. This miracle was hush'd, as though in vain 'Twas sent: now to their cruelty again; Examples will not take; they'll not be turn'd, They are condemned, and they must be burn'd. The people wept; Peter and Betkin pray'd To God for strength: the courage of the maid Did work so kindly on the well-affected, That breaking through (the danger unrespected) The throng'd crowd, they the pris'ners did embrace, And praised God for his supporting grace; Then spake to this effect: Fight on, fight on, The crown prepared you shall wear anon. These words spake Betkin (with a brow as clear As day) My Bretheren and sisters dear, See you to Gods word, be obedient still, And fear not them who can the body kill, Not hurt the soul; but rather fear him, who Hath power to kill the soul and body too, And fling them into hell. I go to meet My glorious Spouse, wrap'd in a fi'ry sheet. Then falling on their knees, they sent their prayers As welcom ghests to Gods attentive ears. Bound to the stake, they prais'd the Lord; the flame Sent up their souls to heav'n, from whence they came. William of Nassaw Prince of Orange, by A bloody villain shot, did thus let fly His latest words: O God, my God, condoul My wounded state, take pity on my soul, On my departing soul; O spare, O spare The Spanish people, though they sinful are. These words no sooner cut, his soul forsook This earthly, and an heavenly Mansion took. SECT. XXVI. The Modern Persecution of the Church in Germany, since the year 1630. Th' Imperialists, when they by storm had gain'd Paswalick town, the Swedish souldiers brain'd: At the inhabitants their fury lavish'd, And in the open street, they females ravish'd, Nay, child-bed women too; they slew the men And fired o're their heads their houses then. They massacred Divines, and burned down The Christian Churches, and at last the town. An. Chr. 1631. Tilly and Pappenheim became a scourge Unto the famous City Magdenburge: Her goodly structures and aspiring Towers Were burn'd down in the space of twice six hours. Without the least respect to old and young, Were six and twenty thousand slain burnt, slung Into the river Elve: by sev'ral wayes The torturers abridg'd poor Chrstians dayes. Ladies and Gentlewomen yok'd together, Forc'd into woods, in frosty snowy weather, Were ravish'd there, strip'd, whip'd, and with a scoft Dismiss'd, while others had their cars crop'd off. An. Chr. 1634. Hexter is taken, and the Popish rage Hew'd all in pieces, either sex, and age, All serv'd alike: what the flesh-eating sword Had left unspoil'd, the greedy flame devour'd. At Griphenburge the Senators were starv'd; The Heidleburg-Divines and Bourgers serv'd With onely bread and water. Like dogs not men Were the Frankendales us'd. In Pomeren The poor inhabitants were forc'd to eat Up their own excrements: unpleasing meat! Many suspected to have hidden Gold, Or silver, suff'red torments manyfold: With cords the heads of some they wound about, And twisted them until the blood did sprout Out of their eyes, ears, noses; nay, unto Tongues, Cheeks, Breasts, Legs, and secret parts they do The burning matches, yea, the parts of shame Stuff'd with gun-powder, burst with horrid flame. With knives and bodkins they do pink the skin And flesh of some, draw stiff cords out and in. Some rosted were with gentle fires, some smok'd Like bacon-hogs; others hot Ovens chok'd; The hands and feet of some so hard were girted, That from their fingers ends and toes there spirted Sanguineous drops. They ty'd the arms and legs Of some together backwards and with rags Ram'd up their mouths, because they should not pray. Some hung up by the privy members; they Hearing their outcries, did with tear-throat tones, Contend to drown their lamentable mones. Had any ruptures? they enlarg'd their pain By firing gunpowder: they faces plain With chisels; and detesticle some men I'th' presence of their wives and childeren. Others, stark naked through the streets are drag'd, VVounded with axes, hammers; some are gag'd And stinking water, Urine, and the like, Pour'd down their throats, till sudden sickness strike Them well-nigh dead: their bellies beyond measure B'ing fill'd, did swell and so they dy'd by leasure. Down others throats they knotted clouts constrain, Then with a packthread, pull them up again, To the displacing of their bowels; some VVere by't made deaf, or blinde, or lame, or dum'b. Some have their legs sawn off; and others have Their members dislocated; those that crave Gods blest assistance, are enforc'd to call Unto the Dev'l for help, or none at all. And if the husband pleaded for his wife, Or the wife beg'd but for her husbands life, They take the intercessor, and likewise Excruciate him before the others eyes. Of many by their hard frications They bar'd the legs, unto the very bones. Others bound backward by the arms, were hung By those distorted parts; both old and young Rather desired to be shot, or slain, And so die in an instant, then remain Alive, and be partakers of such woes As they were like to feel; for Ah! their foes Took away all their corn; in stead of bread, On roots and water, they were glad to feed. And other some, stripp'd to the very skin, Had not one sory ragg, to wrap them in. Hence fruitful soils, were utterly destroy'd, Cities, and towns, and villages left voyd, Or sack'd; all the woods fell'd; the ground untill'd; And ev'ry Church with desolation fill'd. A Reverend Divine, bound to a table, Was tortur'd by a cat. VVhat pen is able To paint their beastliness? maids wives, chast dames, They forc'd to prostrate to their lech'rous flames, Friends looking on; yea, women great with child, In child-bed too: the Churches they defil'd; The Bedlam-houses, Hospitals also. In Hessen land they let the women go, After they ty'd about their ears their coats. Dead corpses violated were. The Croats Devour'd young infants, and the commons brain'd On light occasions; scarce a man remain'd Alive in many places, that might tell The outrage of those furies born in hell. God did this land his warning-pieces show, Before his murth'ring-pieces gave the blow. A blood-red Comet with a flaming beard Anno 1618.For thirty daies together there appear'd; God sent to those, which had so long abhor'd His faithfull Pastors, and despis'd his word, This ominous Torch, that while asleep they lie On the soft pillow of security, They might b'awoken and repent reform Their lives or otherwise expect a storme, Foretold by's Monsters, (so ill-befriended,) And which this formidable sigre portended. At Groningen a blazing Star hung forth, Anno 1619. One Army in the East and in the North Another were engag'd and did contest Till that was worsted, this obtain'd the best. An. Chr. 1619. At Wien water turn'd to blood; three Suns Appear'd at once; the thundring of great guns Was heard; two Armyes then by clear day-light An. Chr. 1621. Deeply engaging in a bloody fight. At Wittemburgh and Darmstad, blood it rain'd. An. Chr. 1622. So much, that houses and stone walls were stain'd Therewith; trees wept red drops besmear'd were then The hands and sickles of the Harvest-men. At Rat'sbone a strange tempest batt'red down An. Chr. 1624. Above four hundred houses in the town; Kill'd onely four; it trees by th' roots up tore, And all within a quarter of an hour. Near Troppaw a great number of Jack Daws An. Chr. 1625. Eagerly fought with their adva'cd claws, The battle lasted long and many Jacks Fall'n down the country-men replenish'd sacks. In lower Saxony a loaf of bread Bought by a woman in the cutting bled. During Magdenburge siege a captain's wife An. Chr. 1631. In child-bed dy'd, her body with a knife Was ripped open, and her womb did hold A boy as big as one of three years old; Having an Helmet, and a breastplate on, Great boots also after the French fashion, And by his side there hang'd a bullet-pouch. At Altenburge, it any did but touch Anno 1633. A blood-turn'd stinking fish-pond, he not well Could in three dayes wash off the stinking smell. An. Chr. 1635.Two Armyes of strange birds in Henssen fought; A randevouz of dogs could not be brought T'a peace; but seeing musqueteers, they joyn, For all their guns beat them away, kill'd nine. SECT. XXVII. The Persecution of the Church in France, which began Anno 1524. At Melden, Pari, Fonutains, Lions, Rhone, Many were put to death, some burn'd, some thrown Into the liquid floods; into the fire Others let down by pulleys, did expire; Others with Oyl and brimstone were anointed, Then burnt; many distong'd, disnos'd dis-joynted: Some slander'd; some imprison'd were; some rack'd; And they that would not bow, nor give respect Unto the Images of molten-lead, Passing along the streets, were massacred. John Clark, through zeal, brake all the Idols down That he could light on: in the Metzian town, Condemn'd he was to die, and first to lose His right hand, then his arms, and breasts, and nose; VVhich quietly he bore, pronouncing then Their gods are silver, and are made by men: At last they burnt him. At the Castle Vik Doctor John Castellane was burned quick. James Panane one that educated youth, At Paris dy'd for the professed truth. John de Cadurco, a renown'd Divine, Degraded was, and burnt at Limosine. One John de Beck a Minister at Troyes, Went through the fire unto eternal joyes. At Rutiers, Stephen Brune for Christ his sake, Adjudged was to suffer at the stake; The fire was kindled, but the wind so drave The flame from him, that he stood up and gave (A whole hours space) instructions to the rude And easily-seduced multitude: They brought Oyl-vessels, and more faggots too; The wind continu'd, and all would not do. With that, the hangman struck him on the head: To whom he thus: And must I then indeed Be beaten like a dog? as well as I, You know by fire I am condemn'd to die. He was thrust through, and in the fire thrown down, And his left ashes in the Air were strown. At Bourdeaux, Aymond de Lavoy accus'd, His friends advis'd his flight, but he refus'd. Not so, said he, I shall be thought absurd To feed men with vain dreams not Gods pure word, Whereas I fear not, as a truths defender, My soul and body too up to surrender. In pains he said, This body once must die, My spir't shall live, and that eternally. He swowned, but recov'ring, said he, Oh Lord, Lord, why hast thou forsaken me? Nay, said the president, thou art mistook Curs'd Lutherane, thou hast thy God forsook: Alas good masters, why, why do you so Torment me? Lord, they know not what they do: Forgive them I beseech thee. See, said thus The Pres'dent, how this Caitiff prayes for us. The Frier drew neer, and he (condemn'd) begins: To God, not you, will I confess my sins. O Lord, make hast to help; do not despise Thine-handy work. My brethren, I advise You that are Scholars, to improve your youth In learning of the everlasting truth: Labour to know what is Jehovahs will, And fear not them that can the body kill, Not hurt the soul: my flesh (too weak) withstands My spir't; which Lord I give into thine hands. With that he strangled was, his body burn'd, His soul until the day of Doom adjourn'd. One Bribard, to a Card'nal Secretary, And William Husson an Apothecary Had, for their scattering good books about, And cleaving to the truth, their tongues cut out; Then with a pully pulled up and down Anno 1544.Into the fire, they dy'd, but gain'd a crown. James Cobard, having prov'd the Mass a fable, Anno 1545.Unto the quick nor dead not profitable, Was at St. Michael burnt. Stephen Polliot Anno 1546.Suffred at Paris. 1547. Michael Michelot Was put unto his choice, either to turn And lose his head, or persevere, and burn. He answer'd, God who caus'd him not to tire, Would give him patience to abide the fire. Blondel a Merchant that profess'd Christs name, Anno 1548.Condemn'd at Paris, yeilded to the flame. Anno 1549.One Hubert, a young man, who did rely on Christ Jesus merits, suffered at Dyion. Anne Audeburt drag'd forth, said thus; This rope My wedding-girdle is, wherewith I hope To be conjoyn'd to Christ: I was first marri'd Upon a Saturday, and now have tarri'd Until another Saturday, wherein I shall (glad day!) be married agin. She in the dung-Cart sang and in the fire Her constancy Spectators did admire. One Florent Venote, that had four years lain In Paris prison, where all kinds of pain He felt and overcome; for seven weeks space Was close confin'd to such a narrow place, That he could neither stand (with ease) nor ly: At last distongu'd, he in the fire did die. Anno 1551. One Thomas, a young man, was rack'd so long, The hangman grew a weary: one among Th' Inquis'tors wept. They bare him to be burn'd, And asked him, if he would yet be turn'd. To whom he said, Friends, I am in my way To God, O do not hinder me I pray. One Mathew Dimonel, Simon Laloe, An. Chr. 1553. And Peter Serre, did torments undergo. Two men at Nivern, had their tongues pull'd out; An. Chr. 1554. Yet God was pleas'd to bring it so about, That they spake plain, We bid the world, flesh, sin, And devil farewel, never to meet agin; Of brimstone, and gunpowder bring a fresh Supply; salt on, salt on this stinking flesh: And so persisting constant till the last, Their souls to heaven, their earth to ashes past. Anno 1557. One Philbert Hamlin fed the cruel flame, One Nicholas of Jenvil did the same. An. Chr. 1558. At Paris did a Christian congregation Run through much sorrow: by the Mediation Of the Palat'nate Prince, and Switzers, some Of them (hardly) escaped Martyrdome. In Dauphin, Provence, multitudes were kill'd; In many other places blood was spill'd: And yet the Church, the more it was supprest Like to a Palm, still more and more encreast. SECT. XXVIII. The Persecution in the time of the Civil Warrs, which began Anno 1562. The Duke de Guise, as he upon a day Tow'rds Paris past, took Vassy in his way: His ears informing him there was a Bell That rang to service in a Barn, he fell Thereon with all his troops: his widened throat Bawl'd out, Kill, death of God, each Huguenote. Some then with bullets, some with swords, were slain; Some hang'd; the heads of others cleft in twain: Some lost their arms and hands; some shred for fowles To feed upon; above twelve hundred souls Of all degrees, and ranks, were kill'd: so don The Duke to Paris march'd, and seiz'd upon The King himself, and filled with abuses The places set apart for pious uses, Roan taken by him, was for three dayes sack'd, The Citizens thereof disliv'd, and rack'd. Then menacing to ruinate Orleance, A young man shot him, to deliver France From his great violence. Peace was procur'd; A happy Peace, but it not long endur'd: The Popish party banishing all pity, Kill'd all, spar'd none in the Lutetian City. At Amiens, the slain were thrown in brooks; All Bibles burned and Divin'ty books. At Meaux, Sens, Mans, they drag'd some on the stones, And dash'd against the walls the little ones: Some had their houses level'd with the ground, Hundreds were massacred, starv'd, hang'd, or drown'd. Many were hal'd to Mass; and some re-wedded, Babes re-baptized; others were beheaded. At Bar they rip'd up many brests, and draw'd Mens hearts thereout, &amp; with their teeth them gnaw'd. VVhen Malicorn, Montargis town had got, He slew the towns-men, and with Cannon-shot Threatned the Lady Rhene to batter down Her Castle, if she did the Christians own, Not give them up to him: the Princess stout, Bravely reply'd: Look what you go about, I charge you, for there's no man in this Realm (The King excepted) that can overwhelm My pinace, with the waves of a command: And if your battery go on, I'll stand I'th' breach, to try, whether or no you dare Thus kill the daughter of a King: I fear Your threats? not I: I want nor means, nor power T'avenge me on your boldness, and devour Your murtherous heart, and utterly deface The infants of your most rebellious race. When Malicorn thus heard the Lady say, He pulled in his horn, and sneak'd away. At Angers into rivers some were thrown, Some executed: a gilt Bible shown Upon an halbard was, and this they sang, Behold how well the Hug'nots truth doth hang; Hark what the everlasting God, will tell; Behold the truth of all the devils in hell: They throw't i'th' river, and renew'd their sound, Behold! the truth of all the devils drown'd. At Ablevilly,, Angers, Foix, Auxerre, At Troys, Crant, Nevers, Chastillon, and Bar In Bloys, Tholouse, as also Carcasson, Many outragious villainies were don. At Sens, and Tours, hundreds were put to slaughter; Some hang'd up by one foot, and in the water Their heads and breasts: the bowels are pluck'd out Their rip'd-up bellies, and are thrown about The mi'ry streets: they torture ev'ry joynt, And stick their hearts upon their daggers point. A Counsellor was hang'd, at the request Of his own father, (O unnat'ral brest!) Anno 1562.By the Parisian Senators decree, The bells are sounded, and the Christians be Destroy'd in ev'ry place, all their estates Seiz'd on by Catholicks and run agates. In Ligneul some they hang'd. The village Aze They set one fire, and joy'd to see it blaze. Augustine Marlorate was hang'd at Rhone, Where streets with slaughter'd carkasses were strown. In Gaïllac, from a steep precipice Many were flung down headlong, in a trice Caught break-neck falls. In Souraze some were cram'd VVith lime, and down their throats had Urine ram'd. One Peter Roch, they buried alive VVithin his self-made grave. They did deprive Many of all they had, others were crown'd VVith thorns; and others in a well were drown'd. One Captain Durre, a godly widdow told Unless she would produce her hid-up gold, He'd rost her quick, and after throw her down From the sublimest tower in the town. VVell (said she) though I fall, yet shall I stand Supported by the Lord Almightie's hand. He made her drink his piss; then in her face Flung the remainder, and withall the glass. He claps her up, more torments to abide: Her friends redeem'd her, but she shortly di'd. The Prot'stants of Valougne, their dear lives lost, And souldiers in their houses rul'd the rost. In Mascon, Bonnet Bor, a rare Divine, Scoff'd, beaten, drown'd, Lamp-like in heav'n doth shine. Monsieur Valongues a Minister, they kill'd, And spurn'd his naked corps: the Mass-Priests fill'd His mouth and wounds with Bible-leaves, and said, Preach thou Gods truth, now invocate his aid. Monluc at Reim brain'd sucking infants, then The mothers; hang'd above five hundred men. They sprinkled salt, upon the bleeding wounds Of one poor mangled man. Monluc confounds The Protestants in fight, the prisoners He hangs, especially the Ministers. Captain Lamoths, he stabs; that will not do, He thrusts him with a rapier, through, and thro: And his blasphemous mouth these words lets fly, Villain, thou in despite of God shalt die. He prov'd a lyar, though the man endur'd Such mortal wounds, yet was he strangely cur'd. In Limoux, Grenoble, Beann, Cisteron, Normay, and Aurange, many undergon Hard usage, Ah! what hearts? what tongues? what Quills? Can think, can speak, can write, those worst of ills? Females were ravish'd: others drown'd: some kill'd, Their houses with unruly souldiers fill'd. Hundreds of women, nay, and children too Like harmless sheep unto the slaughter go. Those to blaspheme that would not be constrain'd, Were with the butt-end of a musket brain'd, Or hewn as small as herbs unto the pot; Others rhrown out at windowes, others shot. A fair young woman, after much disgrace, Was ravished before her husbands face; Then forc'd to hold a rapier wherewith One made her, her own husband kill. A Smith Because he would not give the devil his soul, B'ing on his anvil laid, they beat his poul In pieces with great hammers; some were crush'd To death with weights, others were harquebush'd. They dash'd brest-sucking babes against the walls, And slew the crazy in the hospitals. No sex, nor age, nor quality they let So free: all, all was fish that came to net. The Massacre at Paris, Anno 1571. When the third Civil War in France was ended, A Massacre at Paris was intended, And put in execution: first of all They set upon and slew the Admiral; The watch-word was, the tolling of a bell, Which rang by break aday: the cut-throats fell On the attendants of the King of Navar, And Prince of Conde; not the least of favour Was shew'd to any: they knock'd down and brain'd Ten thousand persons: Sein's swift streams were stain'd With the effused blood; the streets were pav'd With mangled bodies, not a man was sav'd These blood-hounds met with; Pistols, Poiniards, Knives, Curtlaces, Pikes, did make away with lives. The Muskets bouncings! Oh the horrid tones Of howling murth'rers mix'd with dying grones! The Lords and Gentlemen were murthered Some on their houses roofs, and some in bed. In France (this persecution so encreas'd) Were thirty thousand Massacred at least. But let's to some particulars descend; One Monsieur de la Place was brought t'his end. And Peter Ramus with his life did part, (The Kings Professor in that subtile Art) Thrown from the chamber window, trail'd about The streets, and whip'd, his bowels falling out. A villain snatched up a little child, Who toy'd, and played with his beard, and smil'd, But he (hard hearted wretch! not mov'd at all, Drew out his sword, and stabbed it withall, And cast it all gore-blood into the river: This gnaws an infant's heart, and he the liver. Such protestants, as did through fear revolt, Must in the fore-front, give the first assault, Or else be kill'd themselves. Some had their grease Try'd out and sold. They us'd such blasphemies: Where's now your God? are Psalmes and Prayers come To this? sure he is either deaf, or dumb. Let him come save you, if he can: they cry'd, Kill, kill them all, and let's the spoil divide. What fearful shrikes, and outcries were there then Caus'd by these Devils in the shapes of men? What breaking up of doors? what noise of guns At Orleance was there heard? confusion runs In ev'ry street; what trampling of War-Horses? Rumbling of Carts, that bore away dead coarses! The Papists, in this massacre confess'd, That they slew eighteen thousand at the least. Some of them boasted in the streets aloud, Th' nad dy'd their doublets in the Hug'nots blood. At Tholouse, they the call'd-out pris'ners slay, Not suffring them to speake, much less to pray. VVhen the Parisian massacre was known, At Bourdeaux the like cruelty was shown. How sad was it to see poor Protestants VVander now here, now there, and none their wants Supply! Alas unparalelled woes! Rejected by their friends, destroy'd by foes! SECT. XXIX. The siege of Sancerre, Anno Christi, 1573. The Chastrian Lord besieging Sancerre town, His thundring cannons play'd, and batter'd down Her stony walls; the shiver'd timber flew Continually about, yet none it slew. Some had their hats, breeches, and coats through shot, Themselves not hurt nor prejudic'd one jot. The siege endured long; at last, through want, Horse-flesh was turn'd to food; which growing scant, The Twons-men fed on dogs, cats, rats, mice, moles, Hides, parchments, halters, Lantern-horns, roots, coals, Their bread was made of straw-meal; they did boyl Them pottage of old Oyntments, grease and Oyl. And when these fail'd, they pounded nutshels, slates, Eat mens dung fry'd: ho! these were precious cates! A lab'rer and his wife were put to th' slaughter, For feeding on their famin-starved daughter. Some little corn by stoldred brought to town, Each pound was valued at half a crown. The sword did but eighty four persons slay. The famine half a thousand swept away. Many chose rather to resign their breath At the swords point, then famish'd be to death. The parents look'd upon with grief of heart Their children, but could no relief impart. A boy of five years old, neer spent with hunger, Did run about the streets; but when no longer His feeble feet could bear him, down he fell Before his parents sight: 'tis sad to tell The horrour of their souls, and how their eyes Ran down, when they did feel his with'red thighs. Then said the child, Father and mother dear, What mean you so to weep? for Gods sake spare Those needless drops, and do'nt my cause bemone; I ask no bread, as knowing you have none: But since it is Gods will, that I should rest By such a death as this; his name be blest: Have not I (mother) in my Bible read, Of Laz'rus wants? and that was all he said. At last God stirr'd up the Polonians, To free the poor distress'd Sancerrians. They with their arms and goods might go away; And such as would, might without trouble stay. The siege of Rochel Anno 1573. Rochel besieg'd, the towns-men salli'd out, And often put the en'my to the rout. In one months space the foe lay'd on so hot, That more then thirteen thousand Cannon-shot Discharg'd against the Rochellers, which held Out siege so long, till famine them compell'd T'unlawful meats, all their provision spent: But O admired Providence! God sent Them fishes, and in such abundant store, The like was never seen nor heard before: As soon as the edict for Peace came out, (Which Legates sent from Poland brought about) They went away, and ne're return'd again. Divers great Lords and Gentlemen were slain During this siege: commanders full sixscore, And twenty thousand souldiers or more, That did from bloody Massacres retire, Receiv'd at Rochel their deserved hire. Anno 1574.King Charles himself fall'n sick, t'his mother cry'd, Madam, I pray revenge my foes, then dy'd. Anno 1628. Rochelexpecting help in time of need From England, England prov'd a staff of reed Which ran into their hands, whilst they depended Too much thereon; the City (ill befriended) B'ing close besieged by the King of France, And his adherents, the inhabitants Shrewdly put to't, for want of better meat, Did horses, dogs, cats, rats, and leather eat. The poorer sort of people wanting bread, Upon the buttocks of the dead did feed. Young maids did look with such a wrinkled brow, As though they had a hundred years ran through. And all the English, when the French had took The City, like Anatomies did look. How sad was it to see, their hollow eyes And meagre cheeks, lank bellies, withr'ed thighs? A strike of wheat at twenty pounds was rated; A pound of bread, worth one pound estimated; A quarter of a sheep did six pounds utter; And thirty shillings bought a pound of butter; For one poor egge, eight shillings was layd down; An ounce of sugar, yielded half a crown. A dry'd fish given for a piece in gold; A pint of French-Wine, for as much was sold; A pound of grapes, thrice twelve pence; milk but filling A pint-pot full, valu'd at thirty shilling, &amp;c. SECT. XXX The Persecution of the Church of Christ in the Valtoline, Anno Christi 1620. The bloody Papists, in the Valtoline Rising in arms, did furiously combine To th' extirpation of the Christian train; Drown'd some in Alba, others they did brain: Shot some, and strangled others; some they bet With knotty clubs; and many that they met They inhumanely murth'red; some they drew Out of their naked beds, and did imbrew Their hands in their effused gore; they slit The mouths of some up to their ears; and hit Others with the Strappado; some were hack'd To pieces; others slash'd; and others rack'd. One was compell'd to ride upon an Asse, His face turn'd to the tail, and he to pass The market-place, holding in's hand the tail As 'twere a bridle; some when food did fail Were famished; others were ston'd, or drown'd; Some had their very bones, to powder ground. Thus having made a quick dispatch at Tel, These profane wretches, marched thence, and fell Upon the Protestants at Church elsewhere, Kill'd old and young, and shew'd no mercy there, To Lords, nor Gentlemen: to death they shot The Ministers: Ladies and Children, got Into the Bell-free for security: The place is fired; and by fire, they die. The Popish party under a pretence Of standing for the Protestants defence At Sondres (yet for all they kept a pother) They one destroyed now, and then another; As if it had bin done by accident, Concealing their malevolous intent: Then did they fall to plunder, and imbrew, Their hands in blood, all those they met they slew. There was a Noble Lady which refus'd The Romish faith: to whom such words they us'd; Madam, out of the tender love you bear To your young infant, in your arms, give ear To us, or else you shall be kill'd together. But she undaunted, thus; I came not hither To abnegate my faith, nor left I all I had behind in Italy, to fall From my first principles; yea, I will rather Suffer a thousand deaths; my heavenly father Spar'd not his son, but up to death him gave, Me, and such sinners as I am to save; How shall I then regard this babe of mine? O foe, said she, into the hands of thine I give my little child: God which takes care For the wing'd Cit'zens of the liquid Air, Is much more able to save this poor child, Though you should leave it on these mountains wild. Unlacing then her gown, she bar'd her brest, And said, Here is the body; you may feast Your swords therewith: to kill it you have power, My soul is Gods, it can you not devour. They slay the mother, and the infant spare, Committing it t'a Popish nurses care. Many that did refuse to go to Mass, Were dragged to the mountaines tops (Alas!) And thrown thence headlong down: for want of food Others were famish'd; into Adda's flood Some flung from bridges; and with corpses dead The woods and mountains ev'rywhere were spread. A Noble Virgin, through the streets was led Disgracefully; they put upon her head A paper-mitre, buffeted her cheeks, And so besmear'd her face with dirt, (that leeks Might grow thereon) then was she bid to call Upon the Saints; she smiling said, All, all My hope, my trust, and my salvation Is in my Saviour Jesus Christ alone. As for the Virgin Mary, 'tis confest She is above all other women blest; Yet is she not omniscient, and therefore Knowes not what we request, what we implore: Yea she her self her own son's merits needed, And had bin damn'd, had he not interceeded. Christ hath despis'd the cross, endur'd the shame, And so will I, thrice blessed be his name, His holy name; with that, these villains drew her Into the fields, and barbarously slew her. Then came a letter from a Governour, That these blood-suckers should with all their power Destroy both in the country and in City All that were Lutherans, without all pity. Whereat destroying all at Tyrane, Tell, Bruse, Sondres, and Malenco, they more fell Then Hyrcan Tygres, fell on Birbenno, Caspano, Trahen, slaying high and low. They kill'd a man, and's wife. A cradled child Fair and well-favour'd, in their faces smil'd; They took her by the heels (not mov'd at all) And dashed out her brains against the wall. At Bruse, a very aged Matron was Sollicited by them, to go to Mass, And have respect unto her age, not die; To whom she answer'd; God forbid that I Who have one foot already in the grave, Should now forsake my Lord, my Christ, who gave Me to be constant in his truth profest, And upon sublunary creatures rest. Shall mens traditions, or Gods holy word Take place? so said, they slew her with the sword. The pagination of the source document has been followed. SECT. XXXI. The Persecutions of the Church in Scotland, which began, Anno Christi 1527. One Mr. Patrick Hamilton by name, Sprung from an honourable stock, became An able Minister; his holy zeal Did the despised Mysteries reveal To hood-wink'd souls, so long untill at last Th' enraged Bishops him in prison cast: And after condemnation, he was brought To execution; his cap, gown, and coat, He gave t'his servant and exhorted him To venture all for Christ; yea, life and lim. Bound to the stake, he cry'd, For Christ his merit, O Lord be pleased to receive my spirit: How long shall clouds of darkness overwhelm? Great God! how long shall foes oppress this realm? A Fryar then; Unto our Lady pray; Salve Regina, say, &amp;c. Away, away, Satanick Imps; God hears me in the flame. His soul went up to heav'n to praise Gods Name. Straton converted, said, O Lord I have Bin wicked, and deserv'd thy wrath, yet save; O let not me, for fear of corp'ral pain, Or death, deny thee, or thy truth again: They his and Mr. Norman's person bring, And burn them in the presence of the King. Such words the Bishop of Dunkelden us'd To one Dean Porret (whom the Fry'rs accus'd:) My joy, Dean Thomas, I do love thee well, And therefore take the liberty to tell Thee of thy faults; I am inform'd you do Preach the Epistle, nay the Gospel too, Each Sunday to your people; and refuse To take from them (as a reward) your dues: Which prejudicial to the Church-men is. My joy, Dean Thomas, I advise you this; Take tythes, or else it is too much to preach But once a week: for if thou gratis teach, May not the people think that we likewise Should do the same? Tom, be not so precise; It is enough for you when you have found A good Epistle and Gospel, to expound The liberty of holy Church express'd Therein, and 'tis no matter for the rest. Thomas reply'd: My Lord, if I abstain From tythes, will my parishioners complain? I know they will not: and whereas you say, It is too much to preach each Sabbath-day, I think it is too little, for my part; And from the very bottom of my heart Wish, that your Lordship would be pleas'd to take Such pains as that. Nay, nay, Dean Thomas, spake The Bishop then, no orders do us reach. Whereas, said Thomas, you do bid me preach When a good Chapter I do light upon; I've read them over all, and finde not one That's bad amongst them; shew me where they lie, And at your shewing I will pass them by. I bless God, said the Bishop, I ne're knew What was the Testament nor old nor new: And I will not know any thing at all, Saving my Portvise, and Pontifical. Go, go your wayes, and cease so much to prate, Lest you repent you, when it is too late. I trust, said Thomas, that my cause is clear In Gods eyes; therefore, what need I to fear? And so he went his way. But when time's glass Had run a little more, he burned was. Though bloody clouds were rais'd, Religion's raies Shone forth in Scotland, in those worst of daies: Partly by reading (comfort flowing thence) And partly by fraternal conference; Which so enrag'd the Papists, that they came And burnt four noted persons in one flame; One Jerom Russet, that profest the truth, And Alexander Kennedy, a youth, Were brought to Judgement: Kennedy's heart panted For fear at first, and would have fain recanted. But when no hopes was left, God's Spirit reviv'd His drooping soul; yea inward comforts striv'd To shew themselves, both in his face and tongue: Then falling on his knees, these words out sprung: Great God! What love hast thou to all express'd, And unto me vile wretch, above the rest! O who hath tasted of thy clemency In such a high degree (O Lord) as I! For just now when I would deny thy power, And Jesus Christ, thy Son, my Saviour, T'have plung'd my self all over head and ears In everlasting flames, (unquench'd with tears) Thy right hand hath not suffer'd me to dwell With the black subjects of the Prince of hell: And I, that was of late with fear opprest, Enjoy by thee a joy-enamel'd brest. I fear not death, do with me as you please; I praise God I am ready, death's an ease. Then railed they on him, and Jerom, who Said also unto them, Miscal us, do; This is your hour and power to command; Yee sit as Judges, we as guilty stand: But know, a day will come shall clear our blame, And yee (curs'd yee) to your eternal shame Shall see your blindness. Go on forward still, Till you the Ephah of your sins up fill. No sooner were they both condemn'd to die, But Jerom comforted young Kennedy: Brother (said he) fear not, he that indwels Our souls, him that is in the world excels; The pain we here indure is light and short, But we shall have unfading glory for't. O strive we then (though many rubs annoy) To enter in unto our Masters joy: And, with our Saviour, pass the narrow road Which few shall finde; the way to hell is broad. We die for Christ, and Christ hath death subdu'd, Death cannot hurt us: hence me may conclude We are the members; and if Christ our head Be risen, can the members long lie dead? Thus death, and Satan, under-foot they trod, And in the flame, breath'd up their souls to God. Anno 1543.At Edenburgh the cruel Card'nal Beton Hang'd some, upon suspicion they had eaten Goose on a Friday; and above the rest, A woman with her suckling at her brest, He drown'd for being scrupulous and wary Of making prayers to the Virgin Mary. He sent into exile some Christian brothers; And at St. Johnstons he imprison'd others. Mr. George Wischard, a Divine, whose worth Wan him much admiration in the North, Having drunk deeply of afflictions cup, Cheerfully in the flames surrendred up His soul unto its donour. God fulfill'd Anno 1546. His prophesy, the Cardinal was kill'd. One Henry Wallace, as an Heretick Anno 1550. Condemned to be burnt, was burned quick. One Henry Forr'st, betrayed by a Fryar, Anno 1553. Was burnt, and had the end of his desire. Said Ol'phant to one Walter Mill, who pray'd, Rise up Sir Walter. Prayers don, he said, My name is Walter if you call me right, I have bin too too long a Popish Knight, Ben't there sev'n Sacraments? Give me but two Said he, and all the rest I leave to you. Wilt thou recant? he answer'd, I am corn, Not chaff, and will not be i'th' truth out-born: Then go to th' stake. Said he, I may not kill My self, but put me in, and bear I will; This is my resolution. Having made His pray'r to God, he to the people said, Although it be confess'd, that I have bin A friend to Satan, and a slave to sin, Yet 'tis not that, that doth my suff'rings cause, I suffer for observing God's just Laws. And now God out of his abundant grace Doth honour me so farr, as (in this place) To make me seal (what others not withstood,) His truth's profession with my dearest blood. Dear friends as you'd escape eternal doom, And live still happy in the life to come, Let not Archbishops, Bishops, Abbots, Priors, Seduce you any more, for they are Lyars. Trust God alone, O alwayes make his power Your rock, your bulwark of defence, your tower. So slep'd he in the Lord: and was the last In Scotland that the fi'ry tryal past. SECT. XXXII. The Persecution of the Church in Ireland, Anno Christi 1642. The factious Archbishops, Abbots, Pryors, False Jesuites, Romish Priests, and knavish Friars, Stirr'd up rebellion by their instigation, Against the English in the Irish Nation. And when they thought their malice had invented Such thriving plots, as could not be prevented, They in their publick prayers recommended The good success of their designes, which tended, To the advancement of the Cath'lick cause, And told the people 'twas no time to pause. Their nation over-run with hereticks; Call'd Protestants sworn foes to Catholicks; Who were not to be suffered alive Amongst them; and for any to deprive Them of their breaths, the crime was not more great, Then to destroy a dog: to give them meat, Or yield to them relief at any time, 'Twas mortal, O unpardonable crime! Romes Doctrine they pretended to suppress, And root out those that did the same profess; They Laws would make, they thought, should under-trample All Pop'ry, after Englands good example. Observe we how their words and deeds did vary, Said one thing, but did act the quite contrary. And now they fall to murthr'ous blows; and glory, 'Twill save them from the pains of Purgatory: None that spake English the least mercy found; The English language was a loathed sound: All are resolv'd to scowre the Irish borders From these supposed Authors of disorders. Poor Protestants! some were to exile packt; Some kill'd; 'twas thought a meritorious act To slay those Devils in the shapes of men, (For so they called them;) not one of ten Escap'd their clutches: what a deal of good, Said they, it does us, thus to bath in blood! When these injurious wretches are destroy'd In Ireland, and their habitation voyd, We'll then for England; have at England then, We will not leave alive one English man. Put case we should be of our lives bereaven, Immediately our souls would fly to heaven. Why should such scoundrels breath? to work let's fall, And take away their lives, estates, and all. Strip, strip, man, woman, child, base rogues and whores, Leave not a rag on, turn them out of doors. So now they shelter them; but woods and caves Sha'n't be their dwellings, but shall be their graves, Whom wee'l—But many by the high-wayes side, For want of sustenance fell down, and dy'd: And many thousands that for succour fled To towns, by that time they came there, were dead, To tell their horrid Massacres, would make The ear to tingle, and the heart to ake. In Armagh, and Tyrone, this barb'rous rage Spar'd neither rich nor poor, nor sex, nor age: And elsewhere many thousands did expire By sword, by water, famine, or by fire. Some had their guts rip'd out, some drag'd thro bogs; Young children thrown to be devour'd by dogs. If any chanc'd to beg but leave to pray, And kneeled down, they lost their heads straight-way Some in dark dungeons lie; others half slain, Earnestly beg'd to be rid out of pain. They cover'd some alive with dirt, and stones, And laugh'd, to hear their lamentable grones. Some were from bridges, into rivers flung; Others, on tenter-hooks by the chin hung: They hang'd up some by th' arms, with their swords trying How long an English-man would be a dying. Young infants rip'd out of their mothers womb, Were given to the hogs, for to entomb. Children were forc'd to kill fathers, and mothers; Parents, their childeren; and brothers, brothers; Wives their own husbands; husbands their own wives: And they themselves in fine must lose their lives. No mercy's shown, man, woman, no nor child; The dead's dig'd up, th' alive in cauldrons boil'd. Some had their hands cut off, and eyes pluck'd out; Many were left alive, their guts about Their very heels: and of some's grease and fat Candles were made; while others rosted at Slack fires: Nay, boys and women were employ'd To perpetrate such deeds, and therein joy'd. The Rebels, in the country Portendown, Did many thousands in the river drown. At Lisgool, Tullah, Lissenskeah, and Cumber, (All Castles) a considerable number Were brought unto untimely ends. Man, woman, And child was kill'd at Killmore and Killoman. An ancient dame, which towards Dublin went, Was strip'd in one day seven times, and sent To seek her God, and to her God complain, And bid him if he could, cloath her again: All mercy was exil'd; these murth'rous Cains: Brain'd some; stab'd others with their swords, forks, skeins. Thousands of Protestants in snowy weather Turn'd out stark naked, perish'd all together, Through cold and hunger; many that were sick, Were drag'd out of their beds, and hang'd up quick. One Goodwife Lin, they hanged in the Air, And then the daughter by the mothers hair. Upon a day a Cittadel they fir'd Over the Christians heads therein retir'd; And thus express'd their joy: Behold, how high The flames mount, O how sweetly do they fry! A Divines mouth up to the ears they slit; So don, they put a Bibles leaf to it, And bid him preach, and teach some pretty stuff, For now he had a mouth was wide enough. A naked woman, her bare skin to hide, A wisp of straw about her middle tide; They fir'd it, boasting how it did enhance Their spirits to see the English jade so dance: They stab'd Jane Addis, and her young child stuck T'her brest, and said, Suck English bastard, suck. If any hid themselves in cellars, caves, They all were murther'd by these hell-sent slaves; Who made their boast, they pleas'd the devil well In sending him so many souls to hell. Against God, and his holy word, likewise, They belch'd out execrable blasphemies. Bibles they burnt, and said, They burnt hell-fire; Cut some, and soaked others in the mire, Then dash'd them on the owners faces; some They stamp'd on, saying, Hence all mischiefs come; A plague upon them all; in a short time, We hope to see none in our Irish clime. They told th' Apostates, that they thought it good To kill them while they were in a good mood. Anne Nicholson said boldly she'd not turne; And rather then she would her Bible burn, As they would have her, she the death would die; And did, as it fell out: for by and by She and her mate was stabb'd; but he that acted The vill'ny, grew immediately distracted. At Glascow fifty English men and Scots They made recant, and then cut all their throats. In Mayo, and in Tiperary too, Both Counties, not a few did undergo All sorts of cruel deaths; these bloody ones Did flash, hew, hack, and pellet them with stones. They forc'd some in the Sea (swoln big with waves) To take possession of those watry graves. In Sligo, forty Protestants were strip'd, And lock'd up in a cellar; then there slip'd A butcher in (appointed so to do) And with an axe cleav'd all their heads in two. Into the Jail belonging to this town, Poor Protestants were sent, and there knock'd down. About Dungannon, Tyrone, Charlemount, Hundreds were slain upon the same account. An Irish Quean kill'd forty five: Mac Crew No less then thirty in one morning slew. There were above twelve thousand knock'd at head In the high-wayes, as towards Down they fled. These rogues a Scotch-mans belly did divide, And having one end of his smal guts tide Unto a tree, they forc'd him round about The same so long, till they were all drawn out: Said they, We'll try which is the longest size, A dogs guts, or a Scotchmans; O glad eyes! In Antrum fell nine hundred fifty four In one morn, afterwards twelve hundred more. Sir Phileme O Neal boasted he had kill'd Above six hundred at Gravagh; and fill'd Whole houses with the slain; brain'd old and young Within the Baronry of Monterlong. In Ulster Province, by all sorts of deaths, One hundred fifty thousand lost their breaths. One man for saying he'd believe the Pope No sooner then the devil, stretch'd a rope. In Munster, many eminent Divines They hanged up. Alas! what woful signs Poor children made for bread; but they must fast Or feed on grass, and then be brain'd at last. Dear hearts! in what inextricable woes Are they involv'd? inexorable foes On ev'ry side to bring them to their ends; 'Tis sad to hear wives, children, servants, friends, Send to the ayr their stormy sighs, and grones, Their shrieks, their cries and lamentable mones! Alas! what tongue, is able to relate The fears, and cares, of their afflicted state? O was it, was it not enough almost To break a Christians heart, to hear them boast Of knocking down? (said one) my arm's so sore I cannot lift it up, to brain one more. Another bragg'd, that he abroad had bin, And of the English rogues had kill'd sixteen: Others so many kill'd, that they believ'd, That of the very grease and fat which cleav'd Upon their swords, a man might undertake An Irish candle (if he list) to make. The English are (said they) fit meat for dogs, Their children bastards, drown them in the bogs; The daye's our own, we'll wound their beasts therefore; Oh 'tis a gallant thing to hear them rore! Thus have we had a tast of what befel The Protestants: now they that did rebel Have ever since by the just hand of God Bin soundly scourg'd with his severer rod; He so emasculates their spirits in fight, That handfuls put innum'rous foes to flight; Anno 1650.Thousands of them have perish'd by the sword; As many, if not more, the plague devour'd: The Lord still fights for his; and will, no doubt, Utterly root up that rebellious rout. A MARTYROLOGIE Containing A COLLECTION Of all the PERSECUTIONS Which have befallen The Church of England, Since the first Plantation of the Gospel, To the end of Queen Maries Reigne. Victi sunt Gentiles/Papistæ &amp;c Idololatria corum non a repugnantibus, sed morientibus Christianis. August. Ep. 42. Quo malis presentibus durius deprimor, eo de futuris gaudiis certius presumo. Gregor. In nothing be terrified by your adversaries, which to them is an evident token of perdition, but to you of salvation, and that of God, Phil. 1. 28. To the Right Honourable, WROTH ROGERS ESQUIRE; High Sheriff, and Governour of the City and County of Hereford: AND TO THE REVEREND, Mr. William Voyle/William Low/Samuel Smith/George Primrose Ministers of Christs Gospel in Hereford. THE PERSECUTIONS Of the Church of England, From the first planting of the Gospel, to the end of Queen Maries Reign. SECT. I. The Persecution of the British Church, till the coming in of the Saxons. To tell exactly who the persons were That first preach'd to the Britains, in what year The Gospel first took root, is past my skill, Since Authors cite them with a diff'ring Quill. Some say Zelotes preach'd here first of all; Some Arimathean Joseph; others Paul: Fagan, and Damian, did the Gospel bring Into great Britain. Lucius the King, With many of his subjects, did embrace The proffer'd Gospel, as the means of grace: Converted, and baptiz'd, they overturn'd Th' Idol'trous Temples, and the Altars burn'd: All superstitious rites they laid aside, Advancing Christ: the Scripture was their guide, And onely rule; they judged nothing fit But what had warrant from the Sacred Writ. Two hundred sixteen years this faith did flame Amongst them till the Pagan Saxons came. Religious Lucius without issue dy'd, And now the Barons and the Nobles vy'd For King; and while they for the crown contended, In step'd the Romans, so the quarrel ended: For they usurp'd the crown, and did o'rewhelm With misery and ruine the whole Realm. Sometimes th' Idol'trous Romans bore the sway; Sometimes the Christian Britans won the day: By turns they got the best, by turns they got The worst, as Providence did them allot. In Dioclesian's time, and in the Reign Of Maximinian, the Christians slain In Britany and elsewhere, did amount To sev'nteen thousand. One of great account, Alban his name, the Proto-Martyr was Of Englands Isle; and many more did pass That way he went. Religion decaid, Bibles were burned, and the Churches laid, Laid level with the ground; disord'red orders Took place; and Piety forsook our borders. But the fore-named Tyrants over-tir'd With blondy butcheries, at last respir'd; Experience telling them, the more they shed The Christians blood, the more the faith still spread. They both went down from the Imperial seat; Constantius; next Constantine the Great Succeeding in the British government, The Church was quiet, and enjoy'd content: Which peace continu'd till the Arrian Sect The novelty-affectors did infect. Hereat God raised up the Picts and Scots (Two barb'rous nations) and to them alots The Victors wreath: poor England was opprest, And did for many years enjoy no rest. Which made them send Embassadors to Rome With sad complaints, entreating them to come To aid them; so a Roman Legion came, Slew some, making the rest retreat with shame, And quit these coasts; advising us withal To raise betwixt us and the Scots, a wall: A wall being builded by the English men, The Roman force returned home agen. This news was brought unto the Picts and Scots One this side of the wall; they landed boats, O're-ran the country, laid the corn-fields waste, And bare down all before them as they past. The Britans send their Legates unto Rome A second time; the sent-for souldiers come And vanquish'd them; the rest put to disorders, Enforcedly desert the British borders. Which done, they told the Britans flat and plain, They should expect no aid from them again; Besides, it stood not with their ease, to take So long and tedious journeys for their sake: Now therefore arm your selves, and exercise In Warlike feats (said they) if yee be wise: Go, go and build you firmer walls, that so You may be able to keep out your foe, The Romans having took their last farewel Of Britany, the Picts and Scots soon fell On the re-builded walls, and put to flight The trembling Britains, not train'd up to fight. They that stood out were barb'rously destroy'd; And all their goods the enemies enjoy'd. Lo an Aceldama of blood! what store Of slaughtred Carkasses, ev'n swim in gore! Rome b'ing again solicited to send Relief, refus'd; the Britains in the end Took heart to grass, when earthly comforts fail'd Sought God, and 'gainst their enemies prevail'd; Gave them the total rout; the Picts began To keep their bound, save onely now and than They inroads made into the Land; the Land At last became under her own command. The ground was now manur'd; the Lord did bless Th' industrious Britains with a large encrease Of full-ear'd corn, that such abundant store Scarce ever in the Land was seen before. But Oh! mans sinful heart! this Peace, this Quiet, This Plenty, led them to excess, and riot, To pride, contention, envy, and the like: God sent the plague among them, which did strike So many dead, that the alive were all Unable to afford them burial. Yet could the judgements that abroad were sent Not melt their hearts, nor move them to repent; The death of friends, the danger they were in Themselves, but hardened them more in sin; Not work'd their Reformation; oftentimes, Judgements prove Shooing-horns to greater crimes. They wax still worse and worse; the Laity chose, And Clergy too, to live like ranc'rous foes, Gods thundring vengeance which upon them fell, My breathing Muse shall in the sequel tell. SECT. II. The Persecution of the British Church under the Heathen Saxons and English, Anno 429, &amp;c. The Britains with ill-neighbours re-infested, Instead of turning to the Lord, requested The Pagan Saxons aid, for to oppose The raging fury of these Northern foes; They came, and coming, conquer'd them; at length, The Saxons knowing their sufficient strength To over-pow'r the weaker Britains, they Fell foul on them, exacting greater pay, And more provision, or else they would Side with the Picts, and do the best they could To spoil their country. This their resolution No sooner said, was put in execution: All goodly edifices they destroy'd: The Ministers, the while they were employ'd In Divine service, were of lives depriv'd, And rev'rend Bishops with their flocks disliv'd. Some left their country and beyond Seas fled; Some on the mountaines tops were murthered. Some pin'd with hunger, creeping from their caves, Were soon dispatch'd, or made perpetual slaves. The English Nobles summoned to treat Concerning peace, did on a fix'd time meet At Almsbury; but by the faithless train Of Saxons, were most treacherously slain At Stoneheng; and, that they were bury'd there, The yet-remaining monuments declare. Now when the Britans found no other way Lay open to redress, they fell to pray. A fast was call'd, and all, with one accord Humbled their souls, before th' Almighty Lord. Ambrosius Aurelian, being chose To be their King, did profligate their foes; And from that day Gods hand appearing glorious, They went out prosp'rous, and return'd Victorious. At last Aurelian with poyson dead, Uter Pendragon reigned in his stead: He bidding battail to the enemy, Two of their Chieftains took; who scaping fly To Belgia for more aid; and in the mean The Saxons flock'd in; conflicts past between Th' English and them: now these, and sometimes they, (As Providence saw good) did win the day, Octa, and Cosa, with a force renew'd Came o're again; the Britans are subdu'd; Their pastors slain, Churches demolished, No mercy's shown; King Uter sick in bed, Seeing his Subjects fall, would needs be brought Into his camp: so resolutely fought His souldiers then, they (under God) obtain The Victors wreath: Octa and Cosa slain. Soon ever this great Victory was won, Uter of poyson dy'd; Arthur his son Was crowned King, who twice six Victories Obtain'd against the Saxon enemies, His stranger acts, and unbeliev'd success, As fabulous, I leave; but questionless Much peace and safety to the British Isle Was in his happy reign enjoy'd; yet while They were at Peace with others, they agin Returning to their loathed wayes of sin, Fell to intestine broils, embracing evil Instead of good, and worshipped the Devil, Under the notion of an Angel bright. The Priests withheld the Gospels purer light From deviating souls; which soon procur'd The wrath of God (too great to be endur'd) Driv'n out of house and home, no ease, no rest They found; the Saxons had the Land possest, And turn'd out all the Christian Divines. So done, they did in the usurp'd confines, The Heptarchy erect: These Kings did smother All peace, fell out and warr'd with one another: Till disempowr'd, they could not well defend Themselves, much less with enemies contend. King Lucius was the first that did receive Anno 180. The Gospel, and in Jesus Christ believe: From which time (as't in Chronicles appears) It staid in Britain full four hundred years: One hundred fourty and three years Gods word Anno 598. Grew cold; but Austins comming it restor'd. Some English children being brought to Rome, There to be sold, Gregory chanc'd to come Into the market-place: when his fix'd sight Saw in their lovely cheeks pure red and white Contend for Mastership, he much admir'd At their so sweet complexions, and enquir'd What country they were of; then being told That they were English heathens, to be sold For slaves: here's choice enough, if any wants, Said he, 'tis pity such inhabitants, So fair, and so Angelical, should dwell As subjects to the sooty Prince of hell. Inform'd their Province Deira was; said he, I Could wish them Manu-miss'd De ira Dei. And further, being given to understand, That one nam'd Alle rul'd the British land; There, there, saith he, ought Praises to be given And Allelujah's to the King of heaven. He also had a great desire to go To England, and there preach: but Rome said, no. Pelagius dy'd: he in his room assign'd Romes Bishop, calling his intent to minde: Anno 590. Austin, and forty more Divines, he sent To undertake this work: they land in Kent, At Thanets fertile Isle: King Ethelbert, Anno 186.In Canterbury City, they convert, And did baptize: by whose example, many Dayly came in, the King enforc'd not any, But much respected, and affected those Who willingly with Christ would make a close. Austin sends Greg'ry word, how God did bless, And crown their labours with desir'd success. The joyful Bishop sendeth more Divines Over, for to effect those great designs Were now on foot: a letter of advise He writes to Austin, not to be too wise In his own eyes, nor be puft up at all By those great miracles, which did befall The English Church: For why? for this intent, God onely us'd him, as an instrument. Ascribe all, Austin, to God's pow'r Divine; His be the glory, and the praise, not thine: And when thy heart t'ebullulate begins, O think upon thy God-offending sins, And that will humble thee: all Gods elect Have of themselves no power to effect A miracle like this; and yet heav'ns book Contains their names. O do not, do not look So much on thine own works; be this thy strife, To have thy name writ in the book of life. What ever miracle the Lord hath brought To pass by thee, know this, it was not wrought For thy sake; no, 'twas wrought for the salvation Of the seduc'd, misguided English nation. If I might be so worthy to advise, The Temples built for heath'nish sacrifice I would not have demolish'd, but th' abuse Remov'd, converted to another use. God go along with you, and lest you stumble Through pride, and glory, keep you alwayes humble, &amp;c, He an Epistle also did direct Unto the King, which was to this effect: He first prais'd God, then did the King commend, Wishing he might prove constant to the end In his professed faith; and to his power, Convert his Subjects to a Saviour, Who holds forth life to those that will receive It freely, and in's promises believe. And lastly, he intreats his gifts may finde Acceptance, coming from a willing minde. Miletus, by his preaching did convert Th' east Angles and the then-King Sigebert; Who with his Unckle Ethelbert did found St. Paul his Church, and built it from the ground. Austin a Synod gath'red in this nation Of Bishops, to consult of Reformation; But nothing's done therein: King Ethelbert Having a mighty force, went to evert The Chestrian City, where the Monks of Bangor Assembling, pray'd God to divert his anger, From their friends heads, and turn it on their foes, To shield the English from approaching woes. When the king saw them so intent in pray'r, Demand he did, what sort of men they were: And being credibly inform'd, they pray'd For those that were his enemies; he said, Although unarm'd, they fight against us do, And with their prayers persecute us too; My hearts, fall bluntly on them; upon pain Of our displeasure, let them all be slain. Eleven hundred Monks had their blood spill'd; Which God reveng'd: the bloody Tyrant's kill'd In fight by Christian Edwin, who obtain'd The crown, and the Christ-builded faith maintain'd. The Idols, and the Altars he destroy'd, Making all ancient ceremonies voyd. He caused brazen dishes to be tide By ev'ry fountain in the High-wayes side, That so each passenger without controul, Might be refreshed with a liberal boul: He alwayes carried himself propitious Unto the good, but rig'rous to the vitious: So that a woman charg'd with gold might pass From Sea to Sea, unquestion'd who she was. At last, by Penda, and Cadwalla's might, Subdu'd, Josiah-like, he dy'd in fight: His Christian Subjects felt the worst of woes, Nay, cruelst deaths, by those insulting foes. The Queen, her daughter, and Paulinus went, To save their lives, by water into Kent: Oswald was crowned next; whose pray'rs did gain A glorious Victory, Cadwalla slain. His love to piety, his fervent zeal To spread the Gospel in his common-weal, Was known to all. From Scotland he procur'd Aidanus Bishop; and the King inur'd To Scoth, himself interpreted the words Aidanus preach'd, unto his noble Lords And Subjects in their mother tongue, more known To them then the exotique Scotish tone. He to the poor was so compassionate, That when on Easter-day at meat they sate And serv'd in silver, he was told the poor Stood flocking thick and threefold at the door He caused them for to be serv'd in state With his own food, taking a silver plate, And straight-way breaking it in pieces small, Distribute it he did amongst them all. Aidanus seeing this, admir'd, and got Him by the hand, O may this never rot That to the poor so beneficial was (Said he:) as Authors say, it came to pass. This Oswald also was a means to bring Kinigilsus of the West-Saxons King, And Quicelinus King of Dorsetshire, With many of their Subjects, to the clear Knowledge of Christ; under the Minist'ry Of Berinus famous for piety. Thus Oswald having reigned nine years space, Mercian Penda did his life uncase. Oswic succeeded him; Oswic as glorious A Prince, as pious, and no less Victorious: He rais'd an army, fought, and overthrew A greater force, and impious Penda slew. And now the Bishops and the Ministers, Sequester'd from the World, and its affairs, Preach'd freely to the people, until they About the celebrating Easter-day (Which bone amongst them Satan cast) contended, A Synod's call'd, nor was the diff'rence ended, Wolferus now a license having gain'd, Converted the south-Saxons; then there rain'd Abundant showrs which fertiliz'd the land Laine barren for three years: thus Gods good hand Appeared in a plenteous increase; He sent his Gospel, with his Gospel-peace. Thus the South-Saxons, with the Isle of Wight, Did last of all embrace the Gospels light. About this time the Roman Church disown'd Her pristine beauty; Antichrist enthron'd, The Pope did Lord it over all; he sent Italian Theodorus into Kent With many Monks, there Masses must be sung, And in the Latin, not the mother-tongue: Bishops, and Ministers he did displace At's pleasure, so that in a little space Truth turn'd to errour, Piety to vainness, Zeal to contempt, Religion to profaness. Because their iterated crimes did urge Gods wrath, the Pagan-Danes became their scourge. SECT. III. Of the Heptarchy united by Egbert; and of the invasion by the Danes, and of the Persecution of the English Church under them King Egbert after many battails fought, United first the Heptarchy, and brought In Monarchy, into the British land; The whole Realm his, he gave a strict command That Britain should be England nam'd, and all The Saxons answer to the English call. The Pagan-Danes invaded several times (To plague her for her execrable crimes) This British Isle, not striving to enjoy And conquer it, but t'utterly destroy. They whosoe're they met, man, woman, child, Kill'd or enslaved, and the Churches spoil'd. They sacked Canterbury, in which place Above nine thousand souls they did uncase. Throughout the Land their cruelty was such, Of blood they thought they could not shed too much. This Isle was subject to a forreign power, Till freed by William the Conquerour. Who list to know the intercourse of things. The Acts and the Successions of Kings, May if he please, (for brevity's my mark) Read them at large in famous Mr. Clarke. SECT. IV. The Persecution of the English Church under the Papacy. Although Religion from the time this Isle Embrac'd grace first, retain'd not all this while Its Prim'tive splendour, but grew more obscure, More superstitious, and no less impure; Yet in those Pristine dayes, the peoples crimes Were not equivalent to after-times. The Church now being in the desarts hid, Affraid to shew her face, th' Almighty did Raise Bernard up, and many more beside, T'unmask and check the Antichristian pride; And superstitious disordred orders Too too luxuriant in the British borders. At which the Pope and his adherents urg'd, They were imprison'd, hang'd, and burnt, and scourg'd About the streets, or branded in the forehead, With an Heret'cal character: O horrid! Yet many did most readily embrace Their Doctrine, as the onely meanes of grace: That man of sin, that offspring of perdition Renounc'd, and all the wayes of superstition. God still preserv'd a Church unto his name, From Christs time, till the time that Luther came. Anno 1518. John Patrick Engina, when Alfred reign'd, The first Reader in Oxford was ordein'd: Anno 884.He wrote a book about the Sacrament, For which a Martyrs death he underwent. They branded in the face, and banish'd some Anno 960. Divines at Oxford, who declam'd 'gainst Rome. One Arnold there they butcher'd, who decry'd Against the Priests lewd lives, and Prelates pride. Anno 1126. In Henry's reign the second of that name, Thirty Waldenses into England came, Anno 1160. Gerard their Pastor; and without all pity, Were whipped publickly through Oxford City; They singing all the while, Blessed are yee, When you shall hated, and misused be, &amp;c. With want and cold, they dy'd; none might afford Them any comfort, nor at bed nor board. Gualdo who 'gainst the priests invectives wrote, Anno 1170. And also Doctor Gilbert Foliot, Who oft blam'd Thomas Becket to his face, Were persecuted much: to them a grace. Sylvester Gyrald by his writings rears Such Hornets up, as fall about his ears. Anno 1200. One Alexander, for his bitter stile Banish'd by Langton, died in exile. Anno 1207. Ashton fellow of Merton colledge went Into perpetual imprisonment. One William Sawtre, Thorp, and Swinderby, With sundry more Divines condemn'd, did die Under the Christian Banner, and their spirits Anno 1382. Pass'd into glory through Christ Jesus merits. And now because my Muse finds nothing new But onely Martyrs names, she dids adieu At present, Reader, but intends to meet Thy serious eye within another sheet. SECT. V. The Persecution of the English Church after the rising of Martin Luther. The Christian world appear'd not very clear Until the fifteen hundred eighteenth year, Wherein God pleased to unbosome night, Anno 1518.The Art of Printing being brought to light; Which furnished the Church with useful books, And made them to discerne Religions looks From superstition, (as in a mirrour;) Substantial Truth, from counterfeited errour. God also rais'd up sundry men of parts; Who by their learning and ingenious Arts, Most strenuously opposed Barbarism, Truths Sunshine breaking from the clouds of Schism. Picus, and Franciscus Mirandula, Laurentius Valla, Francis Petrarcha, Erasmus, Doctor Collet, Wesalinus Rhenanus Grocinus, and Revelinus, &amp;c. Were in Gods vineyard faithful labourers; Then Martin Luther, and his followers, By Gods appointment came into this nation, To work his Church t'a fuller Reformation. Anno 1519.Six persons suff'red death at Coventry, Onely for teaching of their family The Lords pray'r, ten commandments, and the creed, I'th' English tongue. Severity indeed! Anno 1523.One Thomas Harding on an Easter day, When others worship'd Idols, went to pray Within a silent grove; where apprehended, Condemn'd, and burnt, his soul to heaven ascended. At London one John Raimond was abjur'd; Anno 1528. Who fifteen hundred Testaments procur'd Of Antwerp Print, and brought five hundred over Into this Isle, the darkness to discover. One Sigar Nicholson was hung up by Anno 1529. The privy members: and the reason why, Was this: in Cambridge he (a Stationer) Kep'd in his house some works, that Luther's were. One Thomas Hitten, a Divine in Kent, Anno 1530. After a tedious imprisonment, Was over to the sec'lar power turn'd, And by them in the Town of Maidstone burn'd. Cardinal Woolsy persecuted sore Anno 1531. Bilny, Lome, Garret, Barnes, and many more. One Richard Bayfield, was from Lollards tower Anno 1532. Deliver'd over to the sec'lar power, And after bound at stake; when with the flame His left arm burned was, he rubb'd the same With his right hand so hard, that down it fell: He pray'd until he went in heaven to dwell. Edward Freese, Johnstone, Wylie, Father Bates, All shut up with their wives in Fulham grates, During their hard imprisonment, were fed, O misery indeed! with saw-dust bread. After a tedious lying in the stocks, Thay let them go, but clog'd their legs with locks. James Bainham, when half burned at the stake, To this effect unto the Papists spake: Behold, ye look for miracles; and here A miracle indeed, doth now appear: For I am as insensible of pain, As if I on a bed of down were lain; All's one to me, both equally do please: O tis a Rosy bed, a bed of ease! A. 1530.An Idol nam'd The Rood of Dover Court, Was burnt, and some in chains were hanged for't. Now suffer'd Andrew Hewet, and John Frith. One Thomas Bennet, who was cursed with Bell, Book, and Candle, fastned to the stake, And fir'd a comfortable end did make. The Papists to their power the truth supprest, And Persecuted those that it profest: But God was pleas'd deliverance to bring To his afflicted Saints; for now the King Divorc'd the Lady Katharine of Spain, And took to wife Lady Anne Bullen. Vain Were all the Popes projects; none in this nation Might now enforced be to abjuration. Eliz'beth Barton, th' holy maid of Kent, A Nun both subdolous and fraudulent, By the strange alt'ring of her countenance Gull'd silly people, lying in a trance (As Quakers do) and then, as if sh' had been Inspir'd by God, would in reproof of sin Speak much, and raile against the Gospels light, Calling it Heresy; her ranc'ous spight She vented to the King and Queens dishonour. By Satan back'd, she also took upon her T'advance Rome's Doctrine, praising constitutions Idol'try, Pilgrimages, Absolutions, &amp;c. Anno 1533.But Doctor Cranmer, with the Lord Cromwel, And Mr. Latimer, did wisely smell Anno 1534.Out all the knavery; so that the Nun And her associates hang'd, their dayes were don. Anno 1536.Though England did the Popish pow'r disown, Yet Popery still hover'd up and down: And William Tindal was betraid, arrain'd, Condemn'd and burned for the Truth maintain'd. Anne Bullen also, that Religious Queen, (Who now about three yeers had married been) By false reports and sinister suggestions, Had lost the Kings affection; he questions Her dearest love; which he intends to smother, By marrying himself unto another. Queen Anne was to the Tower carried; And, e're three weeks were over, lost her head. The Vertuous Lady, standing up erect Upon the Scaffold, spake to this effect: Good Christian people, if you wonder why I am come hither, know, it is to die; Having already heard my sentence strict: Nor lies it in my pow'r to contradict. I come not hither for this end, to clear My self, nor tell who my accusers are: I pray God save the King his life maintain, And make you flourish in his happy reign, &amp;c. And if among you, there be any shall Presume to question my untimely fall; Anne Bullen begs, Anne Bullen does implore, That they would judge the right, and judge no more. Thus, thus vain world, I take my leave of you: Dear Christian friends, I bid you all adieu: I pray be fellow-feelers of my case, And put up prayers to the Throne of grace In my behalf. Oh Lord in mercy shine Upon me, take my soul, for it is thine: Sweet Jesu, it is thine. This oft she sed On her bent knees, until she lost her head. The King, (no longer time then three dayes tarried, But) to the Lady Jane Seymor was married. About this time, (which God to pass did bring) Lord Cromwel grew in favour with the King: By whose advise, and sage deliberation, The Church was brought unto a reformation. Anno 1538.The Kings injunctions all abroad made known, Idol'trous Images were overthrown: Our Ladies at Walsingham, Worcester, Ipswich, and Thomas Becket's image, were Cast down; with others, which had long deceiv'd The silly people, who indeed believ'd They liv'd; for they (by secret Engines found) Could open, shut their eyes, and roll them round. The same year (as Lord Cromwel, did advise) Abbeys were ruin'd and Monasteries. A little after, for opposing Rome, Mr. John Lambert suff'red Martyrdome. Packington Collins, Leiton, Puttedew, Peck, Doctor Barnes, Garret, and Heirom too, Two eminent Divines, the Lord Cromwel, Great Essex Earl, all for the truths sake fell. Yea all the prisons, within London walls Were fill'd, and many were enclos'd in Halls, By vertue of an Act for prohibition Of truth, and countenancing superstition. Anno 1541. John Porter, unto New-gate Dungeon sent For reading in the Bible; underwent Hard usage: bolts and Iron chains did check The freedom of his legs, his hands, and neck: At last, into the lowest dungeon cast, Not many dayes expir'd, he breath'd his last. At Lincoln Bishop Longland took away James Morton, Thomas Bernard, in one day. One Mr. Barber, who the truth deny'd, With sorrow wore away until he dy'd. One Testwood, Person, Filmore, tost and turn'd Anno 1544. Under afflictions hand, at last were burn'd Neer Windsore Castle: with a cheerful face, Anthony Person did the stake embrace, Kissing it, said, Welcom mine own sweet Bride, For this blest day shalt thou and I be ty'd As man and wife together, in the love And Matrimonial peace of God above, Of God above; I long for to be there, &amp;c. When all of them unto the stake bound were, Said Filmer then, My bretheren rejoyce In God, unto him make a joyful noise: For after this sharp breakfast, we a boon Dinner shall have with Christ in heaven at noon. Testwood with hands and eyes to heaven up heav'd, Desir'd God that his spir't might be receiv'd. Person (said thus) tricking with straw his head, This is Gods hat, now I am dress'd indeed, Like a true souldier of Christ, by whom This day into his joy I trust to come. And so they suffer'd with such constancy, That many with them could afford to die. The Lord Lisle, Thomas Brooks, James Cook, Ralph Hare, James Barber, Mr. Smith, John Butler, bare The cross of Christ. Said Rockwood, Bad's my state I can't repent, All too late, all too late. The under-Marshal fell upon the floor, I'th' Councel-room, and never spake word more. One Richard Mekins, that had scarce out-worn The fifteenth year, they did in Smithfield burn. Anno 1541. Two labouring men, there was at Callice Martyr'd; And Mr. Damslip was hang'd, drawn and quarter'd. Button, was persecuted; Mr. Dod Resign'd up in the flame his soul to God. One Mr. Saxie, to his end was brought, Anno 1546.By Gardiner's appointment, as 'twas thought. Kerby at Ipswich, Roger Clarke at Bury Fry'd Faggots, to appease their foemens fury. Anne Askew being tost from post to pillar, And cruelly misus'd, an evil-willer Led her into a dungeon; where he rack'd Her body till her very bowels crack'd: Nay, when her bones and joynts were pluck'd asunder, She praised God and pray'd; (to all a wonder) Then the Lord Chanc'ller sent her word that burn'd She should be, if she chang'd not: she return'd An answer back, that she would rather die, Then once recant, and her true faith deny. To New-gate being sent, she penned there Her faith's confession, ending with this prayer: O Lord, the hairs which on my head do grow, Are not so num'rous as my foes, I know: Yet Lord, take not thy grace and comfort from me; So shall they not with flatt'ring words o'recome me: Do thou fight for me; so my soul shall fear No danger, for on thee I cast my care. With all the mischief that they can invent They fall upon me, and have even spent Me thy poor creature. Sweet Lord let me slight My foes, for thou alone art my delight. And Lord, I pray thee, when thy wrath begins To burn them, quench it: O forgive their sins: Lord open thou their hearts, restore the blind, That they may please thee; give them grace to minde The things that do belong unto their peace In this their day, lest when they would, they cease. Let not the fancies vain of sinful men Destain thy truth: Amen, O Lord, Amen. She brought to Smithfield in a chair, was bound To th' stake, and with the flames besieged round. So slep'd she in the Lord, and in Gods eyes Anno 1546. Became an acceptable sacrifice. At that time Nicholas Belerrian, A Shropshire Min'ster; and a Gentleman, John Lacels, servant to the King; with one John Adams Tailour, burning undergon. The same year, Bishop Gardiner did bring Malicious accusations to the King Against Queen Kath'rin Parre (supposing all The boughs would wither, if the stock did fall) In that she gave her minde (which was unfit) To read and meditate on Sacred Writ. And Chaplains kept seditions to rear, None b'ing deny'd the priviledge to hear: As also, that her heart was fully bent To spurn against the present government: Her life was dangerous: nor could he rest, That nourish'd such a Viper in his brest. The Kings love turn'd to hate; and now the Queen Must die the death: but Prov'dence stept between; The plot's found out; she wisely did behave her: The King receiv'd her to his wonted favour. Now also Sir George Blake condemned was, For casting out some words against the Mass. A pardon's granted him; after which thing, He being in the presence of the King; The King said to him, Ah my Pig, (for so He us'd to call him:) yea, said he, I know, Had not your Majesty been more enclin'd To save my life, (such was your Royal minde) Then were your Bishops to reak out their teen; Your Pig, I'm sure, e're this had rosted been. Streight after, Winchester, and his complices (Sworn foes to Vertues, and fast friends to Vices) Set forth in the Kings name, a Proclamation That all the English Bibles in the Nation, And other Books which yielded any light Unto the truth, should be abolish'd quite. This done, said they, So, now the Gospels lain So low that it shall never rise again; And for the greater terrour, strict inquest They made for those that verity profest: Of many pricked down the names; of whom, They some expelled, and imprison'd some: So that these varlots did in no wise doubt The bringing of their wicked ends about. But God, who careth for his truth, and those That countenanc'd the same, dispers'd their foes: Amidst their vain projects the King was dead, And with him all their hopes were buried. SECT. VI. The Persecution of the Duke of Somerset in the Reign of King Edward the sixth. Now when King Henery the eighth was dead, His son Prince Edward reigned in his stead; During whose happy reign Religion flourish'd, Pop'ry decai'd, the Church of God was nourish'd With the full breasts of Peace, the Gospel spred And superstition was abolished: Onely the Godly Duke of Somerset With Persecutions, and great troubles met; Some of the Nobles lab'ring most of all To raise themselves upon his suddain fall. Edward, and Thomas Seymer were ally'd Unto King Edward, by his mothers side; Edward the eldest (fit to guide the Helm) Was made Protector of the King, and Realm: Thomas the second, of this British Isle Was chosen Lord high Admiral; the while These brethren joyned in fraternal love, Nothing fell out amiss; but when they strove, (Spur'd on by make-bates) unto one another They prov'd destructive; and the younger brother Attainted, was condemn'd, and lost his head On Tower-hill: hence insurrections bred. Anno 1549. The Lords, at London privily conjur'd Against the Lord Protector, and immur'd Him once, nay twice, yea thrice, in a short season, Then charged him with Felony, and Treason. He's to the Tow'r-hill brought, where he commended His soul to God; his prayers being ended, He rose from off his knees, and like a man Couragiously bold, he thus began: Dearly beloved friends, Lo, I am here To suffer death, though (God knows) I am clear From thinking, speaking, or from acting ought Against the King, in word, in deed, or thought; But alwayes to this Realm have born a brest As faithful, and as loyal as the best. Yet in obedience to the Laws command, I here as a condemned person stand; And praise my God, for his abundant grace In giving unto me both time and space, Who might have justly took away my breath, Had he so pleased, by a sudden death, Now as for the Religion which I During the time of my Authority Maintain'd to my power, nor do I now Repent of what I did, but both to you And me agnize it as a favour great; And do you all most heartily entreat To joyfully receiv't, and set it forth In your lives, as a thing of unknown worth; Which studiously to do, if you neglect, Great misery I fear you may expect. These words no sooner out, a sudden sound As terrible as thunder, did confound The people so, that some fell down through fear, Some this some that way run, but none knew where. Anthony Brown Knight came; that he did bring, The crowd suppos'd, a pardon from the King; With that a shout arose: but the good Duke Did gravely with his beck'ning hand rebuke The clam'rous throng. And silence being gain'd, He said, Dear friends, Pardon is not obtain'd As you conceive; God otherwise is bent; His will be done, and we must be content. Let's joyn in prayer, that safety may pursue The King, t'whom loyal I have bin. 'Tis true, The people cryed out. O heaven bless His Highness with all health and happiness: I wish his Counc'llours grace to rule, and then You all obedient hearts: all said, Amen I ask forgiveness if I wronged any; O Lord remit my sins, for they are many. As for my foes, I freely them forgive. For Christ I die, in whom I hope to live, &amp;c. Farewel, farewel, he lay him down, and spoke A. 1552.Christ save me, thrice: the hangman gave the stroke. SECT. VII. The Persecution of the English Church under the Reign of Queen Mary. Edward the sixth (Englands Josiah) dead, Lady Jane Grey was crowned in his stead; The Lady Mary, having heard the news, Sent to the Lordly Councel for to chuse Her to be Queen: and if they did withstand The execution of her just command, By force of arms she threatned to regain Her wronged right, and her defrauded reign. The Lords return'd this answer, There was none Had such just right and title to the Crown As Lady Jane: the ancient Laws allow It hers, and place it on her Princely brow; 'Twas hers by Letters patent from the King, And made Authentick with his Royal Ring Before his death; and since she was invested As an apparent heiress, all protested Adherence to her and no Queen beside. The Lady Mary to rest satisfiy'd, Request they did, entreating her to cease By new pretences to molest the peace The quiet Realm enjoy'd; promising her They would be nothing wanting to prefer Her next the Queen: if possibly they could Serve her in any other thing, they would, Provided that she did her self so carry, As fits a duteous Subject, Lady Mary Having receiv'd this answer, heavy hearted, From out the City's circuit streight departed. Here at the Councel did set out a band Of armed souldiers under the command Of the Northumbrian Duke: Mary withdrew her Self into Suffolk, many flocking to her: And while she in Fermingham Castle staid, All Suffolk freely proff'red her their aid And best assistance to procure her Reign, With this Provisoe, that she would maintain Religion established of late By her good brother, and not broach debate Amongst her Subjects, nor foment the seed Of war: to this she easily agreed, And did to God so solemnly protest, That no man could suspect her in the least: Now with this power, of those Godly men, She vanquished her foes; yet after when The self-same party spplication made Unto her Grace, to do, as she had said: She answer'd, Forasmuch as you that are But members arrogantly seek to bear Rule o're your head, I fear me to your cost You'l once know what it was to rule the rost; By sad experience you shall find one day, That Subjects may not rule, but must obey. Then in the Pill'ry famous Mr. Dobbe, Exposed was to many a bitter bobbe; Some others for presenting that request Were laid up fast to terrifie the rest. The Marches of the Duke not over-long, The Lady by his ling'ring grew more strong. So that the London Councel having heard How much the Commons for her aid appear'd, And that some of the Nobles too, did lean That way, they presently proclaim'd her Queen. The Gen'ral by his souldiers forsook, At Cambridge left almost alone, was took. And brought to London-Tower; in a short season On Tower-hill he lost his head for treason. After his condemnation he was Promis'd his life, if he would go to Mass, Which he assented to, his words regrest The truth he had so formerly profess'd, He to the Cath'lick cause the people led To th' papists great joy; yet did he lose his head. Queen Mary thus possessed of the crown, Began the pure Religion to disown; As soon appear'd, by her displacing all The godly Bishops; Ridly, Coverdale, Poinet, Hooper, and Scory, Gardiner Set free, was made Bishop of Winchester, Also Lord Chancellour of England, Bonner Too undeservedly attain'd the honour Of being London's Bishop. To the Fleet Was Mr. Hooper manded (O unmeet!) To see the Queen good Doctor Ridly went, But on a lame Jade to the Tow'r was sent. A Parliament was call'd, a Proclamation Forthwith the Queen set forth throughout the nation; Wherein she shew'd, She could by no means brook To smother that Religion which she took In with her Infant-milk, and to her power Meant to observe until her latest hour, Wishing that all her Subjects (which would sleep Secure in their whole skin) the same might keep: She also did declare, whereas there were Evil-disposed persons, who did dare To preach God's word misled by their own brain; She therefore did by strict command ordain Such should not henceforth preach (as held unfit) Read or interpret any Sacred Writ, Or other points Religion concern'd, Or Print Books by the which it might be learn'd, Without a special licence from the Queen On pain of stirring up her Highness spleen; Requiring all her Officers to see Her will and pleasure executed be: If herein any wilfully offend, She authoriz'd them, them to apprehend And send them forthwith to the neighb'ring gaol, Without admitting Mani-prize, or bail; Till for their punishment, and the example Of others, Orders be procur'd more ample. Also the London-Aldermen were will'd To send for all the Ministers which fill'd The streight'ned Wards, and silence them on pain Of death, commanding them that none explain, Or preach, or read the Scripture in their stead, Anno 1553.But such as by the Queen were licensed. One William Rutler, Humphry Palden, too, He must to prison, this to th' Counter go, For speaking but against what was express'd At Paul's-Cross by one Bourn, a Popish Priest. Good Mr. Rogers was t'his house confin'd; Bradford, Vernon, and Beason, were assign'd Close pris'ners in the Tower. Then did they send For Coverdale, and Hooper to attend The Councel; and for Newgate they allot John Melvine a Divine, by birth a Scot. Mr. Hugh Latimer was sent to th' Tower; And so was Dr. Cranmer by this power. Mr. Simonds, Sanders, Horn, Durhams Dean, Were summon'd to appear before the Queen. Soon after this, the Parliament began; Where Mr. Harly, a judicious man, Bishop of Hereford, degraded was, For marrying a wife, and shunning Mass. Sir James Hales Justice of the Common-Plea, In charge against the Popes supremacie Producing Statutes, &amp;c. into prison cast Was there so roughly dealt with, that at last Recant he did; but (O dire consequence!) He felt the terrours of his conscience, And his own executioner had been, Had not God's special goodness step'd between The knife and him. From prison he releas'd, (His self-made wounds recur'd) no inward rest Enjoy'd at home: so having made his will, He drown'd himself, and's end began his ill. At the same time, for their dis-approbation Of a presented Bill, the Convocation By Bonner was dissolv'd: From Coventry, (For their oppugning of Idolatry) Baldwin, Clark, Careless, Willcocks, all in hast Sent up to London by the Mayor, lay fast. Bishops imprison'd were, Archdeacons, Deans, All Beneficed men, put by their means, Who closely to the truth reveal'd adher'd; And Popish Parsons, in their roomes prefer'd, (Too bad supplies.) within a little season, Archbishop Cranmer, for no less then Treason At Guild-Hall was araing'd; clear'd of that charge, For's heresy he might not live at large. One Mr. Thomas Wotton an Esquire, Anno 1554. And Doctor Crome did in the Fleet retire. Now Hymen went to joyn with Nuptial bands, Iberian Philip's, and Queen Maries hands: Some of the Nobles, and the vulgar sort, Not very well resented this report; The Duke of Suffolk, labour'd to prevent The match: Sir Thomas Wyat rais'd in Kent Some forces to oppose it; for he fear'd The Realm would be enslav'd, and Popery rear'd. Wyat for London march'd: Queen Mary then At Guild-Hall stirred up the City-men. Wyat came into Southwark; having found Entrance block'd up, he went by Kingstone round, And faced Lud-gate, which to entertain Such guests refusing, he return'd again; And having got the worst at Temple-Bar, Became Sir Clement Parson's prisoner, Who sent him to the Tow'r: on Tower-Hill Anno 1554.He and the Lady Jane, their dayes fulfill. Bonner did in his Diocess disperse Injunctions to all the Ministers, Wherein they were required to give in The names of all whoever were agin Auricular confession, the next Lent Encroaching on. Queen Mary also sent To Bonner, Articles, commanding streight The Church-Laws made by Henery the eight Should be in force; that heresy abhor'd Should fall, the Popes supremacy restor'd: That Ministers which did lead marri'd lives Should be divorced from (themselves) their wives; And that processions should be said, or sung, From that time forward, in the Latin tongue, &amp;c. John a Lasco, Peter Martyr, and more Protestant forr'ners, were exil'd this shore: And many godly-minded English fly To Friez land, Cleaveland, Basil, Germany; Where through God's mercy they were kept from dangers, And all found favor, in the eyes of strangers. The number of these Peregrines encreas'd Unto eight hundred persons, at the least. Then to the Tower Lady Elizabeth Was sent, and bore afflictions worse then death. Latimer, Cranmer, Ridly, Bishops, spent Much time at Oxford in imprisonment. One Mr. Sanders crying down the Mass, Became close pris'ner. Doctor Tailour was To London sent for up. Henry Lord Gray Of Suffolk Duke, condemn'd, was brought to pay His sought-for life; where having open broke His sealed lips, he to the people spoke; I have displeas'd the Queen, contrair'd her Laws, Take notice Christians, that's the onely cause I suffer so: and seeing they are bent T'abridge my fleeting dayes, I am content, And do beseech you all, bear me record, I die in the true faith of Christ, my Lord; And for salvation on his merits rely, Not on inefficacious trumpery. For me, and all true penitents beside, Who in him steadfastly believe, Christ dy'd. Repent I do, and do desire you all To pray for me, that when my body shall Resigne its breath, God will be pleas'd to take My soul unto himself, for Christ his sake. Forgive me yee, whom I offended have. Saies Dr. Weston then, As he doth crave The Queen hath done: him thus the throng rebuke, God send thee such forgiveness. So the Duke Kneel'd down and prai'd, concluding, I resigne My soul (O Lord) into those hands of thine: Then made he preparation to embrace The bloody blow; and having veil'd his face With his own handkerchief, he kneeling said The Lords pray'r over, down his head he laid Venting these latest words, Christ look upon me, Have mercy, Jesus, O have mercy on me. And now the stroke was fetch'd, he being cast At the black bar of death, breath'd out his last. Divers of all degrees, who bought or sold Some good religious books, were kep'd in hold. As Bonner past his Visitation, He charg'd all Sacred sentences upon The Church-walls painted should be washed out. And Visitors he also sent about The Universities, to bring therein All Popish trash: to turn out they begin The ablest men: some of themselves forsook Their fellowships, while worth-less persons took Their places up, to the great hinderance Of learning, and religions advance. By this 'twas bruited over all the land, The Queen went quick with child: upon command, Thanks were returned to Almighty God In ev'ry Church, and after, all abroad Prayers were made, that she might have e're long A male child, fair, wise, valiant, and strong. The Godly Min'sters before Winchester In and about the City must appear; Who ask'd them, If they would recant, and so Have pardon from the Queen? All answer'd, No, Yea, all of them unan'mously agreed To stand to what they taught: the Bishop's speed Made them close prisoners, and did divorce Their friends from interchangable discourse. Mr James George, one of them, there did yield His spir't up, whom they bury'd in the field; Then Mr. Hooper, Rogers, Bradford, (hated) And Sanders too, were excommunicated: And Pious Dr. Tailour, Ferrar, Crome, Did all of them, with them receive their doom. Commissions and inquisitors were sent Throughout the Realm; great multitudes from Kent, From Essex, Suffolk, Norfolk, and elsewhere, VVere brought to London, and encloystred there. Part of them dead in prison, out were turn'd To dunghills, and the flames a many burn'd: Also Hanks, Hunter, Pigot, Laurence, brought Before the Bishops were, for no just fault. When Stephen Gard'ner saw that what h'assail'd By threats, hard usage, not at all prevail'd To make men shake off truth; he did begin (As utterly discouraged therein) The business in hand, for to renounce, Meddling no more with condemnations; But unto Bishop Bonner, them referr'd, Who in that trust imposed so bestirr'd Himself, that sending for all in great hast Th' above nam'd parties, he upon them past Death's final sentence: Dr. Ferrar, quick He sent down to St. Davids Bishoprick Within the Cambrian country, there to be Condemn'd and executed (crueltie!) To th' Queen in Mr. Coverdale's behalf Twice wrote the King of Denmark for his safe Release from prison; but with much ado To him, the Queen permitted him to go, One Thomas Tomkins, Weaver by his trade, An humble man, and one that conscience made Of what he did, who would begin his labour With fervent prayers; and to his needy neighbour So charitable was, that he'd disburse Unto them, all the mony in his purse If any came to borrow of him: when His creditors would bring it home agen, He u'sd to bid them keep in longer yet, Till they more able were to pay the debt. This man was kept in pris'n a half years space, By Bonner's means, who beat him on the face With livid blows, and plucked off a piece Of his fast beard; yet this did but increase His patience more: the Bishop then assail'd (When other tearms nothing at all prevail'd) With gentle words to win him; but the trial Succesless prov'd: Tomkins return'd denial. The Bishop, having by, a flaming Torch, Took Tomkins by the fingers and did scorch His hand therewith; afterwards Tomkins told A friend of his, that whilst Bonner did hold His hand to burn, he felt no pain at all, Such consolation from God's spirit did fall; Nor shrunk he in the least, until his veines The fire contracted (fire you know constreines) And sinewes crack'd again, and water spurt On Dr. Harpsfield's face (as from a squirt.) Who was so pityful compassionate, As to beseech the Bishop to abate His cruel minde: O be not so, so rough, (Said he) have you not tryed him enough? Into the Bishops consistory brought, Examined he was, whether he thought Christs real body in the Sacrament Was present yea, or no? to which he sent This answer, that he verily believ'd, The Sacrament by a true faith receiv'd, Was onely its remembrance; with the High'st The very body, and the blood of Christ, In heaven is, and nowhere else: being ask'd If he'd recant? God hath (said he) unmask'd His truth to me in such corruscancy, That in it I resolve to live and die. The Bishop then, death's sentence on him past, And to the Sheriffs deliv'red him, who cast Him into Newgate prison; in Smithfield The truth (in fine) with his dear blood he seal'd, And in the Lord slep'd sweetly. ? Anno 1555. Then William Hunter, that had scarce out-worn The nineteenth, year of Godly Parents born, VVho him instructed in Religion's truth, And plac'd him out in London; this good youth VVas charg'd by special command to go To Mass, break bread; which he refus'd to do. Hunter when threatened that this should come Unto the Bishop's ear, leave got, went home To Burnt-wood, and did with his Parents stay About six weeks. And going on a day Into the Chappel there, (which pleas'd him well) He found a Bible, and to reading fell: In came a Sommoner, who thus did say, VVhat dost thou meddling with the Bible? Ha? Know'st thou well, what thou read'st? canst thou unfold The Sacred VVrit? I dare not be so bold. Said Hunter then, Nor Scriptures to expound Take I upon me now; but having found The Bible here, that joy might me betide I read in it. The Sommoner reply'd, Twas never merry world, since in our tongue The Bible first came forth; would it were hung. Said Hunter, Oh! for Godsake say not so; 'Tis Gods Book, by it ev'ry soul may know, That hath one sparke of grace, the way which leads To lasting bliss: 'tis this true comfort breeds. God grant that we may still amongst us have The blessed Bible, as a means to save. Sommoner. O now I know your minde, y'are one of them That slight the Queen, and her decrees contemn; But you and others, must a new leaf turn, Or else I fear me, you'l go neer to burn. Hunter. Pray God I build my faith on his word still, And his great name confess, come what come will. Sommoner. Confess his name? No, no, you'l in a mess All to the Devil go, and him confess. Then step't the Somm'ner forth, and fetch'd a Priest, The Vicar of that place, a drunken beast, VVho finding William Hunter at his Book, Rebuk'd him for't, and ask'd if he could brook The Doctrine well of Transubstantiation: Hunter made answer it had no relation Unto the truth reveal'd: he understood Those words of Christ touching his flesh and blood Carnal Capernait-like, who thought to feed On Christ his flesh, and drink his blood indeed. VVherefore to them he said, The words I speak Are spirit, and life, and not as flesh so weak. Ah! quoth the Vicar, have I found you out? Thou art an Her'tick now, without all doubt, &amp;c. Hunter. VVhereas you of my faith do question make, I would we two were fastned to the stake, To prove whether of us should closest stick Unto our faith, and which was Heretick, &amp;c. The Vicar to complain of him did threat, Flung out of doors, departing in a heat. Hunter went home, and having farewel took Of his dear friends, his fathers house forsook. Brown, call'd old Hunter, ask'd if he could tell VVhere his son was; who said, He knew not well. Brown told him, Either you miss'd-son produce, Or go to prison; bring me no excuse. The old man strides his horse, and rides to look him, And after two dayes journey overtook him; Telling him all what happ'ned; yet said he, Go on, I'll say I cannot light on thee. No, no, said William, home with you I will, And save you harmless; me they can but kill. At his return, a Constable him caught, And brought before this Mr. Brown, who thought VVith arguments to win him; and enrag'd At his judicious answers, he engag'd No more to hold on the dispute, but streight Sent him to Bonner, Bonner to the Grate; VVhere he for two dayes lay, allowed just A dish of water and a brown-bread crust. At two dayes end, the Bishop coming found The slender fare, he bids he be unbound, And break his fast with them, but he's revil'd, Call'd Heretick, worthy to be exil'd Their company: said Hunter, I decline Their company, as much as they do mine: The Bishop sent for him, and thus did rant; And wilt thou not, thou Heretick, recant? Recant (said he) the faith I have profest So publikely? I will not, I protest: No, no, I will not; what? shall I be whirl'd By errours wheels? I would not for a world. Then take him Jailor, mand him to the stocks; Be sure you load him well with bolts and locks Till I shall burn him. VVhereupon he said, Great God! O let thy all-sufficient aid Corroborate my soul. He's born away; The Bishop to a half-penny a day Stinted his lively-hood; thus nine months space Imprison'd, he before the Bishop's face Was six times brought, to th' question still propounded Hunter a pertinacious No, rebounded. The Bishop read his charge, and him return'd To Newgate, so to Burnt-wood to be burn'd. His parents see him, and petitions send To God, to make him constant till the end: His mother added this, that she was blest In bearing such a child, as could devest His life for Christ's sweet sake. William reply'd, For the small pain, which I shall here abide But a short time, my Christ a joyful crown Hath promis'd me. His mother kneeling down Said thus, I pray God strengthen thee my son To run the race thou hast so well begun; I think thee now as well bestow'd (my dear) As any child that ever I did bear. VVhilst he remain'd at Burnt-wood, many friends Came to him, to whom he the truth commends: Three dayes expir'd all things were ready made; The Sheriffs son hugg'd him in his arms, and said William, don't fear these men with Bills Bowes, That bring you to the place; death as he showes Is not so grim. I've cast up mine accounts (Said he) and know t'how much the cost amounts. With that the young man, while he went about To speak, could not, his tears so fast burst out. So Hunter his way cheerfully went on, His father meeting with him, said, My son God be with thee. God be with you likewise Good father, answer'd William. Let your eyes Smile on your son; O be not so, so sad; For we shall meet, and have our hearts made glad. Come neer the stake, he kneeled down, and read The one and fiftieth Psalm. The Sheriff said, Here is a pardon: if thou wilt be turn'd, Thou shalt live, otherwise thou must be burn'd. No, I'll not turn (quoth William) and did go To th' stake, and so was fast'ned thereunto. Then spake he to the throng, Good people strive By pray'r for me while I remain alive, And I'll for you. Not I, I'll make my boon Said surly Brown, (there standing by,) assoon For a cur-dog as thee. Hunter. Sir you have got What you desir'd; I pray God it be not Laid to your charge, but I forgiv'n you have, Said Brown, Brown. That's more then at your hands I crave. Hunter. If God forgive you not, I tell you true, This blood of mine shall be requir'd of you. O Son of God shine on me; from a cloud The Sun brake out (till then thick shades did shroud The face of day) his eyes he turn'd aside, Too weak such radiant glory to abide. A Priest brought him a book to look upon. To whom he thus, False Prophet thou, be gon: Good folk beware of them, for Jesus sake; Who of their sins, shall of their plagues partake. Brown. Marke what I say, as thou burn'st in this fire, So shalt thou burn in hell. Hu. Thou art a lyar. False Prophet hence, from me away be gon: Fire made, he pray'd, and breath'd his last. Anon Higbid, and Causton, Gentlemen as good As great, in Essex, with their own hearts blood Sealed their faith unto Gods glory then, And the rejoycing of all Godly men. At Braintree, William Pigot, for Christs name Endur'd the fury of the ardent flame; At Maulden, Stephen Knight, before the stake Kneel'd down and pray'd; Sweet Jesu, for whose sake I freely leave this life and rather choose Thy cross, and irrecoverably loose All worldly goods, then to give audience To men in breaking thy commandements: Thou seest (O Lord) that whereas I but now VVas preffer'd great preferments, if I'd bow To a false helpless God; I was content My body should be burnt, and my life spent, Counting all things below, but dung and dross, For thee; happy such gain which comes by loss! Thousands of silver, and as much of gold, Then death I do of lesser value hold. Just as the wounded Deer desires the soil, So longs my soul for thee: pour down the Oil Of consolation on a crumbling clod So helpless of it self: Thou know'st O God, That I, who am but sinfull flesh, and blood, Can of my self act nothing that is good; And therefore, as of thine abundant love And goodness still deflowing from above On me, (me that am lesser then the least Of mercies,) thou hast bid me to this feast, And judg'd me worthy to drinke of this cup With thine elect: even so, O bear me up Great God! against this Element of fire So formidable, to the sence so dire; Sweeten it by thy spirit, so asswage The heat, that I may overcome its rage, And pass into thy bosome. Holy father Forgive thou me, as I do all men; gather My soul, sweet Son of God, my Saviour, Beneath thy shady wings, a Balmy Bower; O blessed Holy-Ghost, whose strength destroies Fleshly corruptions, hasten thou my joyes, Eternal joyes. Lord I commend, take then My parting spirit, Amen, Amen, Amen. John Laurence legs, with bolts and irons lame, His body with hard usage out of frame, Was to the stake transported in a chair, And suff'red for the faith at Colchester: Young children while he burn'd, cry'd out, O Lord Strengthen thy servant, and make good thy word, Stand up, stand up, for thy poor servant's aid, As thou art just, O do as thou hast said. Ferrar (set o're St. Davids Bishoprick) Was apprehended for an Heretick: Him Winchester misus'd, call'd him base slave, False-hearted fellow, and a cross-grain'd knave: Morgan (a fraudulent supplanter) turn'd him Out of his place, and at Carmarthen burn'd him: Not long before his death, one Richard Jones A Knights son comming, his sad pains bemones; T'whom Ferrar thus: Sir if you see me move My hand or foot during the flames, do prove What mettle I am of, believe not then My Doctrine oft inculcated to men. And as he said, he did: with the fire hot Besieged round, he stirred not a jot, Held his stumps bolt upright; then with a pole Knock'd down i'th' fire he breathed out his soul. One Rawlins White, a Fisher-man in Wales, Of Cardiffe town, when superstitions scales Drop'd from his eyes, the Truth he understood, And in his country did a deal of good; He dayly now expects to be surpriz'd By truths oppugners: his dear friends advis'd Him to retire elsewhere and be excus'd: For their good will he thank'd them, but refus'd. He's apprehended, and in prison laid In Cardiffe Castle, where a year he staid; His friends resorting to him, he would spend The time in pray'r, exhorting them to mend: At last the Bishop of Landaffe commands That he be brought: he threats him now, then stands On fairer terms; but all this would not stir His unmov'd brest, a day's appointed for His condemnation; which being come The Bishop call'd him forth, and told him some Heretical opinions he did hold, And had seduced others; Rawlins bold Reply'd; My Lord, a Christian man I am I praise God for't, my tenents are the same With Sacred Writ: if from God's word I stray I would be gladly brought in the right way. The Bishop said, Speak, if you will be won, Else I'll proceed to condemnation. Proceed, said Rawlins; but you never shall Condemn me for an Heretick. Let's fall To pray'r (said Landaffe) that the Lord some spark Of grace would send thee, to disclose the dark; Now (said he) you deal well; and if your pray'r Do with God's will agree, he'll doubtless hear. Pray to your God, and I to mine will pray; I know my God will hear, and not say nay. The Bishop and his Chaplains pray'd anon: Rawlins pray'd by himself alone: pray'r don, The Bishop said, How is it with thee now? Thine errours (what?) wilt thou revoke, and bow To our true God? no, surely no said he, Rawlins you left, and Rawlins you finde me; Rawlins I was, and am, and Rawlins will Through God continue to be Rawlins still. God would have heard you, had your sute bin just, But he hath heard me, and on him I trust. The Bishop being wroth him soundly shent, So went to Mass. Rawlins his minde then bent Shot forth these words: Good people if there be Amongst you any breth'ren, two, or three, Or if but one, bear witness at the day Of judgement, that I to no Idols pray. Anno 1554. Mass don, he was condemn'd, and after thrown Into a darke and loathsome dungeon. There Rawlins pass'd his time in drowning wrongs With spir'tual prayers and religious songs. The night before his death t'his wife he sent To send his wedding weed (a shirt he meant) Which he rejoycingly next morn put on; And being led to execution, Guarded he was with bills, and Pike-staves too, Alas! said he, what need all this ado? By God's grace, I will nothing start aside; VVho is't that gives me power to abide All this affliction for his own names sake But God? his be the glory. At the stake He his dear wife and children having found Pickled in briny tears, or rather drown'd; His eyes let fall a tear; but having made A recollection of himself, he said, Ah flesh! saiest thou me so? would'st thou obtain The Victor's Palm? I tell thee 'tis in vain To strive; thy pow'r is like the morning mist: Then falling on the ground, the ground he kist, And spake, Earth unto earth, and dust to dust, Thou art my mother, and return I must To thee. With an exhilarated brow, Then going to be bound to th' stake, I now (Said he t'a friend of his,) finde great contest Betwixt the flesh and spirit, for the best. I pray you therefore, when you see me shrink, Hold up your finger, that I may bethink My too oblivious self. B'ing bound he rais'd These words up to the height; The Lord be Prais'd. Unto the Smith then spake he, Pray good friend Anno 1554.Knock it in fast, the flesh may much contend; But God, support me, let thy grace refresh My fainting spirits, and my trembling flesh. About him pulled he the reeds and straw, VVith such a merry look, that all that saw Much wondred at it. Now a Priest appear'd And preached to the people: Rawlins heard Until he spake of Transubstantiation, Alledging Scripture for its confirmation; This is my Body; Come you here good folk (Said Rawlins) don't hear that false Prophet's talk. Ah! naughty Hypocrite dar'st thou produce A Scripture-proof for so profane a use? I have heard your already-quoted text; But look immediately what follows next; Do this for my Remembrance: then streight-way The Priest stood still, not knowing what to say. The fire was kindled, Rawlins in the flame Bathed his aged hands, till in the same The sinews shrunk, the fat drop'd out, and all That while he cried out; Lord, let my fall Mount me to thee; Receive this soul of mine, O Lord receiv't; his spirit he did resign. It was observ'd of him, that whereas through Infirmity of age he round did go, And with dejected countenance, he now Went bolt upright t'his death, his smoother brow As clear as day; his speeches and behaviour, Of courage, vigour very well did savour. And now the Queen restor'd the Abbey-lands She late possess'd. A Pope-sent Bull commands All do the like; but none therein was seen T'obey the Pope, or imitate the Queen. A Popish Priest at Crondale (impious fool!) Boasted that he had bin with Card'nal Pool, Who cleans'd him from his sins; the Bull sent o're He prais'd, fell down, and never spake word more. Some burn'd, because they on their necks did tie This Motto, Fear God, fly Idolatry. George Marsh, one William Flower, John Cardmaker John Simpson, and John Warne, were each partaker Of life, by suff'ring death, climb'd heavens story: Death is the ladder to immortal glory. Bonner for many things John Ardly accus'd, To whom John Ardly such expressions us'd; My Lord, not you, nor any of your breed Are of the true Catholick Church indeed; Your faith is false, and when you most depend Upon it, it will fail you in the end. You have shed much, too much innocuous blood, And are not weary yet: Can this be good? Were ev'ry hair upon my head a man, So many lives I'd part with, rather than Lose the opinion I am in; so said, In Essex burnt a joyful end he made. One Thomas Hauks, a Courtier comly tall, VVas greatly admired and belov'd of all For his rare qualities, in Edward's dayes; But in Queen Maries Reign Religion's rayes Waxing more dull, he left the Court, home went And practis'd Godliness, t'his great content. While thus he staid at home, a son he got, But in the Popish way baptiz'd it not. By using oil, cream, spittle, salt, (absurd!) Nowhere enjoyned in the holy Word: Told Bonner so: the Bishop left him than A while; and Mr. Darbisher began: You are too curious, and on none will look, Unless your little pretty God's good book. Hauks. Sir, is not that sufficient to save? Bishop. Yes, but not to instruct: that I may have H. Salvation to my God, I humbly sue, As for instruction, that I leave to you. B. Shall your child be baptiz'd, you not look o're? H. I had such councel given me before. B. Why we can have it done, if we be bent, H. True, but you never shall, with my consent. B. I'd Gladly do thee good, save thee from hell; I am thy pasture and would teach thee well. H. I'll stand to what I said, you shall not finde My resolutions waver like the winde. B. I am the bread of life, the Scripture saith, And this bread is my flesh; is this thy faith? H. 'Tis so, I will believe what Scriptures say. B. Well, let's to Evensong. H. There I'll not pray, I'm best when furthest off from such resort: And so he walked forth into the Court. B. What thinke you of the Altar's Sacrament? H. Excuse me, for I nere knew what it meant. B. But we will make you know't, when we begin, Faggots shall make you do't. H. Faggots? a pin For all your faggots, you no more can do Then God permits you, and no further go. Much more was said; in prison he at last Was for his bold judicious answers cast; Nor could that move him in the least to doubt: What's bred in the bone, will not eas'ly out. Being (his sentence read) to Coxshal sent, In Essex, he exhorted as he went His friends: and at the stake (as he had spoken That he would do) he gave to them a token By lifting up his hands all in a flame, Above his head, and clapping of the same, To let them understand, that he was able To 'bide the pain not too intolerable. Then gave the people an unusual shout, And so this blessed Lamp (all burnt) went out. An. Chr. 1555. One Thomas Watts in Essex, who defended The truth so much oppos'd, was apprehended, Condemn'd, and after sent to Chilm'ford, where The little time he had, he spent in pray'r. Come to his wife and his six child'ren small, He said; Wife, and my hopeful branches all, I now must leave you all; henceforth therefore Alas! I cannot know you any more: As unto me at first, the Lord did send you, So I unto the Lord, do recommend you; Him I command you to obey, and fear As long as life shall last I see you beware Of this loath'd papistry, which I withstood, And shall against it give my dearest blood By God's grace by and by. Let not the number Of bleeding Saints discourage or incumber Your active faith, and move you to relent, But thereby take occasion to be bent For greater service in Jehovah's fight: 'Tis happy dying for a cause that's right. I do not doubt, nor have you cause to fear But he which strikes, will give you strength to bear He'll be unto the widdow, in distress Husband, and father to the fatherless. Farewel, (said he) farewel, gave each a kiss, So past he through the fi'ry blaze to bliss. One Bainford, Osmund, Osborne, overturn'd Unto the Sec'lar power, in Essex burn'd. Mr. John Bradford and John Leafe did climbe Up fiery stairs to heaven about this time. The next day after at Maidstone in Kent One Mr. Minge dy'd in imsprisonment. Mr. John Bland, God's faithful Minister, Was for the truth a constant sufferer. John Frankish, Humphry Middleton, two men Of admirable worth, were martyr'd then. John Fettie's child, such cruel whippings feels, That the gore blood ran down about its heels; The father put in the tormenting stocks, Must see his Lamb misus'd (O hearts of rocks!) One Nicholas Sheterden being brought, Him Doctor Harpsfield asked what he thought That passage, This my Body is, should mean; Said Sheterden, This cannot well be seen By carnal eyes: thus much I gather thence, It must be taken in a spirituall sence; Else when, This Cup's my blood's so understood, The substance of the Cup must needs be blood. Nicholas Hall, Christopher Waide, Joan Beach, John Harpool, Marg'ry Boley, who did reach At the despised truth, and Popery spurn'd, Condemn'd at Rochester in Kent, were burn'd. Dirick Carver, a Surrey Gentleman Call'd to the stake, unto his God began His fervent pray'r, which having done he strip'd Himself, and so into the barrel skip'd; They threw his book in also but in vain; For to the throng he flung it out again: I charge you, said the Shrieffe, in the Queen's name To fling that Vip'rous book into the flame. Then spake he with a cheerful voice, and said, Dear friends, bear witness I am not affraid To seal Christ's Gospel with my dearest blood, Knowing 'tis true, and was of late your food, Though now surrepted from you; and because I'll not deny it to obey mans laws, Condemn'd I be to dy; see that you walk In answer to the truth, of which you talk. And as for those that do the Pope believe, Hell's theirs, without Gods merciful reprieve. Except (said then the Sheriffe) believe thou do The Pope, th' art damn'd both soul and body too: Pray to thy God that he may set thee free, Or strike me down. The Lord forgive, said he, Your temerarious words. Dear Lord, thou knowst How I left all, to come to thee; thou dost Draw with Magnetick-love; to thee I fly For shelter, Ah! but when my serious eye Darts on thy power, and on my self looks down, I fear the wrath of a condemning frown. What, shall I shrink? no; now the flames surround me, I'll trust my God, although my God confound me. Christ Jesus help, Christ Jesus look upon me; He cry'd, and dy'd, with Lord have mercy on me. Iveson said, All the treasure in the nation Should never draw him to a recantation: I to the mercy of my God appeal, And would be none of your Church for a deal: Yea though an heaven-sent Angel came t'expound Unto me other Doctrine, I'm not bound For to receive it: hereupon condemn'd And put into the fire, he death contemn'd. James Abbes, a Godly man did shift about From place to place for safeties sake: found out At last, they carri'd him to Norwich town, VVhere, by the Bishop's threats he did disown VVhat he profess'd; the Bishop seeing so, Gave him some money, and dismiss'd him too: But conscience bringing him upon the rack, The Bishops money he returned back, Repenting e're he took it: then again The Bishop strove to gain him, but in vain; Though Peter-like he fail'd now to persever Resolve he did, and stood more fast then ever, Even to his last-drawn breath; the Bishop's fury Condemn'd him to be burn'd, he burn'd at Bury. John Denly, Newman, Partrick, Packingham, Dy'd constant Martyrs for their Saviours name, Wright, Coker, Collier, Hooper, Stere, and more Besides in Canterbury, faggots bore. Robert Smith, Stephen Harwood, Thomas Fust, And William Hale, dy'd for the truth their trust. Eliz'beth Warne, condemned to be burn'd By Bonner, unto Bonner soon return'd These words, Do what you will with me; for why, If Christ was in an errour, so am I; Otherwise not: but Christ spake true I know Therefore then was she burn'd at Stratford-Bow. About this very time George Tankerfield Did at St. Albanes to their rancour yield. George King, John Wade, and Tho. Leyes, with sore Usage fell sick, and dy'd in Lollards tower. In Suffolk Mr. Robert Samuel Of Barfold Min'ster, who instructed well The flock committed to his charge, was tost To Norwich goal, there chained to a post, And so erect that's body did command For some small ease induc'd his tip-toes stand. Hunger and thirst (bad helpers) are procur'd; VVhat tongue can tell what he poor man endur'd! At last brought to be burn'd (an easie pain To what he felt before) he did detain Some friends in telling them, a most strange story Of what fell out, while he was us'd so sory: VVhen I much want (said he) had undergon, I slept, and then me thought appeared one Cloath'd all in white, who whisp'red in mine ear, Samuel, Samuel, be of good cheer; Take heart to grass man, thou hast past the worst, Henceforth thou shalt nor hunger feel, nor thirst: VVhich came to pass, such consolation did Sweeten his woes, that modesty forbid Him tell the same. So as he went along To execution, amidst the throng A maid there was, (who after scap'd) did fall About his neck, and kissed him withall. The while his body burn'd, it shin'd as bright As new-try'd Silver, or as Cynthia's light. Next day Anne Potten and Joan Trunchfield, come From Ipswich prison unto Martyrdome. Thomas Cob, William Allen, Roger Coo Death for the sake of Christ did undergo. In Coventry and Litchfield-Diocess, One Mr. Robert Glover, did profess The Gospel; he surprized, had his doom To be confined to a narrow room, And dark withall, next to the dungeon, Scarce having straw enough to lie upon. No chair nor stool to sit on; none might look To him though sick; pen, paper ink nor book, Was not allow'd him; yet a Testament And Prayer-book, by stealth he getting spent Most of his time in pray'r, and meditation On Gods great love in working mans salvation. Yea, said he, health began to come; my peace Of conscience did more and more encrease: God's spir't reviv'd me; I had sometimes some Glimm'ring reflections of the life to come. All for his own Son's sake: to him alwayes Be Glory, Honour, and Obedience, Praise. Two dayes before his death, he found his heart Less lightsome then it was, and fear'd the smart Would too much try his patience, for his pray'rs God heard not; he unbosomed his fears Unto a Godly Minister his friend, Who wish'd him to be constant to the end: O play the man, your cause is just and true, God will appear anon, I'll warrant you. The stake in sight, he said, I see him whom I call'd for, Austin, Oh he's come, he's come: And look'd so cheerful e'en as though new breath He should receive, and not a painful death. Cornelius Bongey, Capper also came With him, and burned in the self-same flame. Mr. John Glover now was troubled sore, Seeing his brother took for him; therefore He would have suff'red in his brother's stead, But by his friends importunings he fled Into the neighbouring Woods, did there abide Till he with cares and cold sickned and dy'd. His body privately was buri'd in The Church-yard: they his bones dig'd up agin A twelvemonth after, threw them out (O pains!) For to be trampled on by Horses, Wains. And thus though in his life, he scaped from Their rage, yet after's death, on him they come. William the third brother, in Shropshire dead, Might not (by their consent) be buried. Wolsey, and Pigot, suff'red in the Isle Of Ely. And within a little while Bishop Ridly, and also Latimer Burned at Oxford. Stephen Gardiner That day to dine till almost night deferr'd; (Th' old Norfolk Duke then with him) having heard Word of their deaths, he with a smiling brow Said to the Duke, let us to dinner now. The Table fill'd, as merry as a Buck The Bishop was, but on a sudden struck: (Two bits scarce eaten) carry'd from the table To bed he was, his pains intolerable; Nature he could not ease, for fifteen dayes, His tongue was swoln, and black, his mouth's assaies Could giv't no house-room; his pin'd body all Sadly enflam'd, he gasp'd and gave a sprawl. And now John Webbe, George Roper, Greg'ry Parke, At Canterbury burn'd, not miss'd their mark. An. Chr. 1556: One Thomas Whittle Minister, accus'd By Bonner, was most wickedly misus'd; Who fell upon him, beat him with his fists, And him enclos'd within a close rooms lists: There (said he) though I did on the bare ground lie Two nights I (prais'd be God) slep'd very soundly. He, Joan Warne, Is'bel Foster, Thomas Brown, John Went, Iohn Tudson, Bartlet Green, lay down Their lives together did at Smithfield stake, Of heaven-prepared joys for to partake: The last of which going to bear the yoke, Cheerfully this repeated Dystich spoke; Christe Deus, sine te spes est mihi nulla salutis; Te duce vera sequor, te duce falsa nego. In English thus: O Christ who art my God In thee for mine abode, With thee, I onely hope: Under thy conduct I Seek the truth and deny The falsi-loquious Pope. He was a man exceeding charitable Unto the poor, so far as he was able. Nor did he love (his modesty was such) Pop'lar applause, though he deserved much. His beatings he conceal'd, till neer his end, When he declar'd it to a bosome-friend. Anne Albright, Agnes Snoth, Joan Catmer, Sole, At Canterbury were burnt to a coal. Good Doctor Cranmer, then of Canterbury Archbishop, also past the fi'ry fury. At Salsbury, on William Coberly, John Spicer, and John Mandrel, so did die. Richard and Thomas Spurge, Tims, Cavel, Drake, Ambrose, all Essex-men, fell at the stake. Master Tims many Godly letters sent T'his friends, not long before his life was spent: In one he us'd these passages; I praise The Lord for helping you to minde his wayes. Consider I beseech you, what of late Fell from my lips, so shall we meet in state: I'm going to the Bishops coal-house now, And hope to go to heaven e're long; do you Hie after me: I have a great while tarri'd For you; but seeing y'are not yet prepared, I'll stay no longer, you shall finde me blest And singing, Holy, Holy Lord of Rest, At my race end; now therefore my dear hearts Make hast and loyter not, lest light departs, And yee (who with the foolish Virgins stay) Be with the foolish Virgins turn'd away: And now in witness that I have not taught Contrary to the truth revealed, ought, My blood-writ name I send you, for a Test That I will seal my Doctrine with the rest. So fare you well, and God defend you then From Antichrist, and his false Priests, Amen. Use constancy in pray'r, with faith require; And gain the fulness of your choice desire. John Hullier (formerly an Eaton Sholar) At Ely, by his patience, conqu'red dolour. Hugh Lavrock, John Ap-Rice, this blind, that lame, Told Bishop Bonner, that he laws did frame To take mens lives away, making the Queen His hangman: Bonner burn'd them out of spleen, At Stratford-Bow. In Litchfield, Colchester, Gloster, and Leister, many burned were. One Mr. Julines Palmer, and some more At Newb'ry dy'd. One Sharp at Bristol bore The flames with joy. In Darby town Joan Waste. (Born blind) did in the fire breath out her last. Sir John Cheek for the truths sake underwent In London-Tow'r a sore imprisonment. A new Commission from the King and Queen Anno 1557.(Like Dracoes laws) came forth, that they which lean T'his Holiness the Pope, should raise the fire Of Persecution yet a little higher: By means whereof, throughout the Kingdoms quarters Prisons were stuff'd with Saints, fires grac'd with Martyrs. First to begin with Colchester, where they Apprended three and twenty in one day, And burnt the major part. Margaret Hyde, With Agnes Standly, stak'd at Smithfield dy'd. They Stephen Gratwick William Moraunt, King, Into St. Georges field, in Southwark bring, And burn together. In the Diocess Of Canterbury, many did profess The truth and suffered. In Lewis town Ten faithful servants in one fire laid down Their lives for Christ; one of them Richard Woodman Betraid was b'his father and brother, (good man!) Eliz'beth Cooper, Simon Millar too, At Norwich fir'd; Eliz'beth cry'd Ho, ho, And shrunk a little: Simon Millar said, Reaching his hand out to her, What? affraid? Raise up your spirits, in the Lord be strong And cheerful; for these pains are of no long Continuance (Good sister) by and by We'll take our supper with alacrity: This so becalm'd her heart, she through-stitch run The work she had so happily begun, And so committing their blest souls to God, They clim'd to heaven, death being under trod Mrs. Joyce Lewis a gentlewoman born, Accused, and condemn'd, contemn'd with scorn Death's rigid brow: my Christ is fair, when him I see (said she) death looks not half so grim. Urg'd to confess before her end begins, She said, to God she had confess'd her sins, And he had pardon'd them: the Priest befool'd Told her e're long her courage would be cool'd. At stake the Mass she pray'd against, cry'd then The crowd, and Sheriffe himself a loud, Amen. Taking a cup of drink, Here here's to all That love the truth, and wish proud Babel's fall; Her friends do pledge her, and some others too; For which fact penance many undergo. Bound at the stake, her smiling ruddy face Made all spectators (pitying her case) Go with wet eyes, much grieving for her woes Inflicted on her by tyran'cal foes: She striv'd nor strugled when the fire rag'd most, But with her lift-up hands, gave up the ghost. Ralph Allerton, and Richard Roth, with James Astoo, and his wife, dyed in the flames At Islington; as did at Colchester Margaret Thurstone, and Agnes Bongier. John Noyes a godly Shoo-maker, who liv'd At Laxfield in Suffolk, sentence receiv'd There to burn'd: the people in the town Put out their fiers, and no house but one (And that discov'red by the Chimnies smoak) Had some: the Sheriffe and's Officers in broke, So got a coal. John Noys fell down and pray'd, And being bound unto the stake, he said, Fear not the bodies killer; but him, who Can kill thee, damne thee, soul and body too. Seeing his sister weep, he thus begins, Weep not for me, but weep you for your sins. He took a faggot up, gave it a kiss, And said, Did I e're think to come to this? Blessed be God that ever I was born; Then spake he to the people, Of bread-corn They tell you they can make God, but beleive Them not at all, nor their false truths' receive: Pray bear me witness I expect salvation Not by mine own good works but Christ his passion. The fire was kindled, and his last-spoke word Was Christ have mercy, O have mercy Lord. Within the Diocess of Chichester, Many accus'd, condemn'd and burned were. Hillingdal, Sparrow, and one Gibson dy'd In Smithfield flames. John Rough Minister try'd With Marg'ret Mearing, neer about this time, Were also burned for the self-same crime. One Cuthbert Sympson, Deacon, in one day Though rack'd no less then thrice, would not betray The Congregation, lying in the stocks, At midnight one (whom he well heard) unlocks The coal-house doors, and though no candles light Nor fire's he saw yet his amazed sight Splendour beheld; he that came in said Ha! And after that, soon vanished away: This much rejoyc'd his soul; upon the morrow He, Hugh Fox, and one Devnish, fire went thorough. One Thomas Hudson, Thomas Carman too, And William Seaman, Norfolk-men, did go Through tribulation to heavenly bliss, To have the crown their own, the cross they kiss. There was one mother Bennet of the town Wetherset, who was driven up and down For Jesus sake; returning home, she dy'd, Her corps b'ing buri'd by the high-wayes side. She was exceeding lib'ral to the poor; Her mate once told her merrily, their store If she had bin but sparing had bin much To what it was: said she, I cannot grutch The poor: Alas! good husband, be content, Let us be thankful, God enough hath sent; Wee still (sweet heart) have good competent fare: “Content's a feast, although the feast be bare: I cannot see the needie's wants, and hoard, Least in so doing I displease the Lord: But husband let's be rich in good works still, So pleasing God, we shall have all at will. One Cicely Orms b'ing ask'd, over his head What 'twas the Priest held up? she answ'red, Bread, Bread at the best; and if you do endeavour To make it better, 'twill be worse then ever. Brought to the stake, she kiss'd it, and respir'd Welcome Christs cross, his sweet cross so desir'd! My soul doth magnify the Lord, my spirit In God rejoyceth, and my Saviours merit. So casting up her head, on heaven she fix'd Her eyes, and in the flames her hands commix'd She yielded up the ghost. Thomas Spurdance Of Norwich suff'red for the truths advance. George Eagles, Tailour, travell'd up and down In sev'ral countries, went from town to town Confirming weaker Saints: in a short season At Chelmsford he condemned was for treason, And hang'd up with two theevs, the one whereof With tears sought Christ, the other with this scoffe Put off George Eagle's exhortation, Our Captain leads, we shall to heaven anon. The Pen'tent thiefe did call upon the Lord. The mockers flitt'ring tongue spake not one word Upon the ladder. Eagles was cut down Half dead, his heart pull'd out, his members strown. George Eagles sister, and a man call'd Fryer, At Rochester did in the fire expire. An. Chr. 1558.A Proclamation was sent about, That all good books within this Realm set out, Or from beyond seas brought, should all be turn'd To ashes; if not so, their owners burn'd. Soon after this dire Proclamation, Twice twenty persons met neer Islington Were caught, some scap'd, some burn'd with faggot-sticks In Smithfield thirteen, and in Brainford six. Amongst these Godly persons there was one Nam'd Roger Holland, (who had boldly done His duty in reproving bloody Bonner) Spake thus: at last, God will redeem his honour With your destruction, and will soon asswage (His spir't so tells me) your unbridled rage Against his Church: he heareth the complaints His servants make, for the afflicted Saints, Whom you so dayly persecuted have As us you do now: Christ will shortly save His spotless Spouse; in God I dare be bold To tell you that you are too fierce to hold. And my dear breth'ren, know that in this place After this day, not any shall embrace The fire and faggot by this means procur'd: Mark what I say, and be thereof assur'd. Which came to pass; for, for the Lord Christ's sake None after them suff'red at Smithfield stake. Said Bonner then, What? Roger I perceive here Thou art as bad an Heretick as ever; And in thine anger thou wouldst now become A railing Proph't, but th' hadst as good be dumbe: Though thou, and all like thee, would see me turn'd Over the ladder, yet to see thee burn'd I shall live; yea, and (before God I vow) I'll make you rue it, ev'ry one of you That comes within my clutches; so he went. Roger call'd on the people to repent, And to think well of all the Saints, that past The fiery tryal which not long should last, For God intended to abridge straightwayes For his elect's sake, those sanguineous dayes. Roger embrac'd the stake, and said, O Lord I praise thee for affording me thy word, And fellowship with Saints, which in heavens coasts Sing, Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord of Hosts: O God receive my soul, preserve thy flock, Save them from Idols, O be thou their Rock. So with his fellowes praising God above, They all reposed in the arms of love There was one William Pikes amongst the six (VVhich dy'd at Brainford) false-nam'd Hereticks: VVho (while that he his liberty enjoy'd) I'th' Summer, at noon-day, (of cares devoyd) His Bible with him in t'his garden took, Sate down to read upon it; on his book Four drops of blood fell suddenly, he knows Not whence it came; t'his call'd-wife it he showes, Saying, I well perceive God will have blood; It cannot, no, it must not be withstood: His will be done; God help me to abide The trial, for without him I shall slide. And so they went to pray'r, and in short space Burned he was, in the aforenam'd place. One Thomas Hinshaw, like a dog was us'd By Harpsfield first, by Bonner next abus'd, Who in an arbour pulled down his breeches, VVhip'd him with willow-rods, and with sharp speeches Returned him to prison: there was one John Willis the like usage undergone; T'whom Bonner thus, Me bloody Boxner call Ye do, a plague of God upon you all: I'd fain be rid of you, but you delight In burning sure I think; but if I might Have my desires, O then I'saith I'd stitch Your mouths up, sack you, throw you in a ditch Or down the stream, this would I do with speed; My fingers itch to do this pious deed. Upon a time Bonner came to the stocks VVhere this John Willis lay, and spake with mocks, How like you (John) your lodging and your fare? Willis said, VVell, had I a straw-pad here. VVhile thus they commun'd, in the good man's wife Came (great with child) to beg her husbands life; Told Bonner she within his house would stay, And there (her count neer out) her belly lay, Unless her (loving) husband might be freed, And pack along with her. Indeed, indeed, Said Bonner then, that were a handsom trick: How say'st thou John, thou damned Heretick; Suppose thy wife should with her brat mscarry, And perish man, art thou not accessary To both their deaths? what thinkst thou? To be short, The woman would not go ('twas pretty sport To hear these parly) Bonner left in's house She should cry out, did let her husband loose On easie tearms. A Godly Minister Nam'd Mr. Richard Yeomans, much did bear: At last (he finding how his foes were bent To take away his life) went down to Kent, Selling pins, needles, points, thred, white and black, And some odd triflles, to supply the lack Of himself, his poor wife and childeren: He was imprison'd but releas'd agen: He went to Hadly to his wife, and there Hiring a chamber, they abode a year; Carding of Wool he sets himself about, She spins; thus pick they a poor living out. At length the Parson having understood How this good old man liv'd, he took a brood Of Officers with him, at night, rebound He made the doors, search'd diligently, found Old father Yeomans and his family laid In bed together; whereupon he said, Ne're trust me if I did not think a knave I with a whore should finde, and so I have; And would have pull'd the bed-cloaths off withall: But father Yeomans held them fast: Call, call Us what you please, here's neither knave nor whore, But a conjugal pair in God (though poor) I bless God for it; you in darkness grope, And I defie (with all his trash) the Pope. Then in the cage they carri'd him away; There to the stocks with one John Dale he lay, (VVho shortly after dy'd) he told's faith, for which Degraded and condemn'd he burnt at Norwich. John Alcock a young man, by trade a Shear-man In Hadly-Parish said, I do not fear man, But God if for my God I suffer may, 'Twill be a happy and a joyful day: As for the Pope, I will not be forgiven By him, forgive me thou great God of heaven. He was a Newgate pris'ner hereupon, And thrust into the lower dungeon, Where he with cruel handling, and beside Ill keeping, suddenly fell sick and dy'd. One Mr. Thomas Benbridge though estate Enough he had, yet through the narrow gate Of persecution did he chuse to enter Into heaven's Kingdom; manfully adventure His life and limb for Christ, Truth he defended Against the Pope till he was apprehended, Condemn'd therefore; at the place unappal'd, His rich apparel he put off, and call'd Upon his God; then fastned to the stake, Said Dr. Seaton to him, Do but make A recantation, and thou shalt be freed; Said Mr. Benbridge, Shall I so, indeed? I thank you, but I will not, Christ's my Guerdon; I don't regard you man, no, nor your pardon. The Doctor said, In troth it is a sin Good folk, to pray for such a dog; begin Benbridge, begin a new leaf wilt thou? say? Away thou Babylonian, away, Benbridge reply'd; they kindled then the wood VVhich burnt his beard, yet he unmoved stood: Fire seiz'd on's legs; unable to abide So grievous pains, I do Recant he cry'd: The fire's removed, and his life is granted; But he his recantation recanted, (It pleasing God his conscience to awake) And six dayes after suff'red at the stake. John Cook, James Ashly, Alexander Lane, And Robert Miles, because they did abstain From going to the Church, did pass the Fury Of corm'rant Vulcan at St. Edmunds Bury. One Philip Humphry, John and Henry David, Two brothers, were destroy'd, and yet were saved. Green, Wilmot, Williams, Cotton, Collingborow, And Harris, whip'd, run through a deal of sorrow. One Alexander Gouge, and Alice Driver, By Mr. Noon a Suffolk-Justice were So hunted after, that a while they lay, For safety sake, hid in a mow of hay: The Justice with his men searching about, Thrust Pitch-forks in the mow, and found them out, Sent them to Melton goal, where being prov'd A certain time, they were to Bury mov'd; At the Assizes, they Christ crucifi'd Boldly confessed, and the Pope defi'd. Alce Driver did compare (exceeding well) Queen Mary, in her rage, to Jesabel; Her ears to be cut off the Judge procur'd, Hereat, which she rejoycingly endur'd. Both are to Ipswich sent, examin'd there By Dr. Spencer, Norwich Chanceller, And others; the main matter was intent About Christs presence in the Sacrament. Alce Driver did so baffle them herein, That they had nothing to reply agin: Thus she concluded then, the Lord be blest You are (though learn'd) not able in the least T'oppose God's spirit in me a silly woman Of low degree, and tutoured by no man; I am no Academick, nor was I E're brought up in the University, As ye have been; yet in the truths defence, And in the cause of Christ my Master, whence I power derive, I will set foot to foot To any of you, if you put me to't, For to maintain the same; and if I had A thousand lives to lose, I should be glad To let all go for it. The Chancellour Condemn'd, and sent her to the Sec'lar power. Gouge also was condemn'd for Christ his name, And so both sweetly dy'd in Ipswich flame. Alce Driver's neck being chain'd, O said she (heed) Here is a goodly handkerchief indeed! VVell, God be praised for it. As they stand At stake, some came to take them by the hand: The Sheriffe bids they be caught: the crowd forbid: The Sheriffe bids let alone, and so they did. There liv'd in Cornwall a religious Dame, Her husband a recusant, often came To hear Mass read, nor would he ever lin Till his forc'd-wife did joyn with him therein, VVhich was no little trouble to her soul; She thereupon did seek the Lord, and roul Her self upon him, and by earnest prayer Crav'd his direction; God was pleas'd to hear, And one night fill'd her with such spir'tual mirth, That she enjoy'd a little heaven on earth; From husband, children, and from all she run For conscience sake, and for her living spun: Yet to her husband she return'd at last, VVhere (but a very little time being past) Her neighbours apprehending, carry'd her To th' Bishop of the town of Exeter; She was condemned, and the reason why, VVas that she spake against Idolatry. The Bishop said to her, VVoman do y'hear? Minde your good husband, and your children dear. She answered, Remembred and forgot They're soon; I have them and I have them not: While I enjoy'd my ease, I them enjoy'd, But now (all such relations are voyd) Standing here, as I do, in Christ his cause, Where I must either frangifie the Laws Of Grace, or Nature; either Christ forsake, Or else my Husband; I'm content to take Christ as my heavenly Spouse, and to renounce The other with my children all at once. The Bishop after much Argumentation, Gave her a months time for consideration. Seeing a Dutch-man who new Noses made For images defac'd when Edward swaid; She said, Mad-man, what meanst thou to compose New Noses for such images as those, Which will so shortly loose their heads? For this She was close pris'ner kep'd, nor did she miss Threatnings, taunts scoffes, call'd Anabaptist, whore, Mad-woman, drunkard, vagabond, and more. Then many specious promises were us'd, Of liberty, of wealth; which she refus'd. With husband, goods, and children they assail To win her but yet nothing would prevail, Her heart was fixed trusting in the Lord; She had cast anchor, and renounc'd, abhor'd The sin-involved world, with all the wiles Which Satan uses when he souls beguiles. She was devoyd of learning, yet so vers'd I'th' Scriptures, that not onely she rehers'd Apposite proofs, Quotations, but could tell The Book and Chapter also very well. Condemn'd and given to the sec'lar power, The country Gentlemen came flocking to her Bidding her, yet to call on God for grace, And cease her fond opinions to embrace; So go t'her husband, and her children dear; Thou art a woman ignorant (we fear) And these things are too far above thy reach (Said they) the shrub is lower then the Beach. I am, said she, indeed, and yet my breath I'll give in witness of my Saviours death. O do not put me off with longer stay, For Ah! I am impatient of delay; My love hath wings, it hovers up and down, Nor can it rest, till glory is her own. My heart is fixed, I will never go From what I said, nor do as others do. Then said the Bishop, There's no hopes to win her, The devil leadeth her, the devil is in her. Not so my Lord (quoth she) Christ is my guide, His Spirit uphelds me, that I cannot slide. She, when she heard deaths sentence past upon her, Advanc'd her voice, and said, Unmated honour! The Proverb's true. Long look'd for, comes at last; My Lord, my God, I thank thee, that thou hast Granted to me this day, my hearts desire, In listing me with thy celestial Quire. Woman, said one, be thou a happy wife By thy recanting; O the sweets of life! No, said she, by no means; my life is hid With Christ in God, now the good Lord forbid That for this life, at best but transitory, I should lose heaven and eternal glory: I have two husbands, but will onely cleave Unto my heavenly, and my earthly leave; The fellowship of Saints in heaven I trow Exceeds the having children here below: And if my husband and my children prove Faithful, then am I theirs, they have my love; God my good father is, God is my mother, God is my sister, and God is my brother, God is my kinsman, God's my faithful friend Who will stick close unto me, till the end. To execution then led along, She was attended with a num'rous throng. Bound to the stake, she by the Popish Priests Was set upon again (unwelcom guests!) To whom she thus: for God's sake now give o're Your bibble babble, trouble me no more With empty sounds, fain would I, Oh! divorce My self from your impertinent discourse. O God be merciful to sinful me, For Ah! I onely do depend on thee. She stood with admirable patience Amidst the flames and so her soul slew hence. Sh' had such a cheerful look, that one would say It was her wedding, not her burning day. She had been alwayes sober in her diet, Neat in apparel, peaceable and quiet; Alwayes a doing, never fitting still, During her health and limbs, by her good will; Chain'd to her house; she ever would refuse To gad abroad, as most ill-houswives use. To all that came to her, her gracious heart Would streams of consolation impart. Gods word was her delight, she gave good heed T'her husband in the Lord, a wife indeed! According to her power, she at her door, And at their sev'ral homes, reliev'd the poor; And in the time of her calamity Would take no proff'red coyne; for, said she, I Am going now to (Heaven) a City, where No mony any Mastery doth bear; And whilst I here remain, the Lord will feed My craving stomack, and supply my need; It is his promise, and full sure I be, That he which feeds the Ravens, will feed me. One Richard Sharp, a Weaver by his trade In Bristol City apprehended, made A large confession of his faith before One Dr. Dalby the there-Chancellour, Who by perswasive Arguments so wrought Upon his weakness, that he soon was brought To make a promise, That he would appear And publickely recant, and when, and where. But after this Apostacy, Sharp felt His conscience gall'd, hell's horrour so indwelt His soul, that he his calling could not minde, His colour went away, his body pin'd: Next Sabbath day going to Church, he made. To the Quire-door, and with a loud voice said, That Altar, neighbours, pray bear me record, Is the Great Idol: I deny'd my Lord, But from the bottom of my heart am sorry For what I don, in hazarding my Glory. He caught, condemn'd, and burn'd, with Thomas Hale Climb'd up to heaven from this tearful vale. One Thomas Benson of the same town went To pris'n, for saying, That the Sacrament Was as they us'd it, nothing else but bread, And not the body of the Lord indeed; As for the Sacraments, which you call seven, Five were ordain'd by men, but two by heaven: Give me the two, which I acknowledge true, And all the other five I'll leave to you. Soon after this he did receive death's sentence; And executed, to his God he sent hence His blessed soul, which left its bodie's jail For Paradise, death having put in bail. Now to conclude, The last that did maintain The Gospel with their hearts-blood in the Raign Of Mary Queen, that hell-begotten fury, Were these five Citizens of Canterbury, John Hurst, John Cornford, (Captains in the fight) Christopher Brown, Alice Snoth, and Kath'rine Knight The things imputed to their charge were, that Christs real presence they denyed flat, Affirming onely those that do believe, Not wicked men, Christs body do receive. The Pope they said was Antichrist, the Mass Abominable; that a sin it was To pray to Saints; that cringing to a cross Was meer Idol'try and an errour gross, &amp;c. Sentence of condemnation being heard, Forthwith John Cornford, was in spirit stirr'd, And with an ardent zeal for God, express'd In the name of himself, and all the rest This doom: I'th' name of Christ our Saviour, The Son of God, the High'st, and by the power Of his most Holy-Ghost, as also by The Holy and Divine authority Of the Apostolick and Cath'lick Church (Never yet totally left in the lurch) We here turn over to the Prince of hell As slaves eternally to howle and yell In sulph'ry flames, the bodies of all those Blasphemers, Hereticks, who do oppose The living God, and bolster up their errours Against the Truth, hence to the King of Terrours; So that by this thy righteous judgement shown Against thy foes, great God, thou mayst make known Thy true religion to thy greater glory And our souls comfort when we read the story Of thy great power, and to th' edification Of all our well-nigh ruinated Nation. Good Lord, so be it, be it so, Amen. And this his excommunication then Took great effect against truth's enemies. Queen Mary within six dayes after dies, And Tyrannie with her; there is no hope Of any longer footing for the Pope; In England now great joy betides to all The faith-ey'd Saints, who wish'd proud Babels fall: Yet the Archdeacon, and's associates quick (Knowing the Queen was dangerously sick) Condemn'd those pious persons to the flame, And hurri'd them away. When there they came, In Christ his name they offer'd up their prayers, As holocausts to the Almighties ears. To God they pray'd, to God for ever blest, Preferring this request amongst the rest; That if it were his will, their blood might be The last that should be shed, so Lord pray we. No sooner had they pray'd, but heaven return'd A gracious answer, they the last that burn'd. Great God (said they) we cheerfully resign Our souls into those blessed hands of thine Amidst these flames; their spirits did ascend To glory, which shall never have AN END. Gloria Deo in Excelsis. SECT. Ult. God's Judgements upon the Persecutors of his Church and children. Since first the Gospel in the Ears did ring, Of England under Lucius the King; Never did King or Queen the Land so stain With Christian blood as in her four years reign Queen Mary did: she burned in her fury An Arch-Bishop, (and he of Canterbury) Four Bishops, twenty one Divines or more, Eight Gentlemen, Artif'cers eighty foure, Husbandmen, Servants, and poor Labouring men Five score; Wives twenty six, Widdowes twice ten; Nine Maids, two Boyes, and two young Babes (to heaven VVere sent) in all two hundred seventy seven. Sixty four more for Jesus Christ his sake VVere persecuted sore; which could not shake Their heaven-built faith; seven whereof were strip'd Stark naked, and most mercilesly whip'd. Sixteen in prison perishing, had dung (After the Nabathœan custom) flung Upon their outcast bodies: Some did lie In captivated chains, condemn'd to die, But were deliv'red from approaching death By th' happy entrance of Elizabeth, “Our glorious Queen, our Pallas and Astræa, “Of Grace and Virtue the divine Idea, Many did spend, by reason of exile, Their dayes in trouble, and their years in toile. But as Queen Mary lavished the blood Of her best subjects, and the truth withstood Unto the utmost of her power; so God Scourged her soundly with his flaming rod, Both in her life and death; for whilst she liv'd, What did she prosper in which she atchiev'd? To instance in a few particulars, And first, her fair'st and greatest man of War Unmatch'd i'th' Christian world, cal'd the great Harry Was burnt by heavenly flames. Then would she marry Spanish King Philip, so expose to dangers Poor England under barb'rous foes and strangers. She labour'd much, but never could attain To joyn the English to the Spanish Raign. Then did she set about the restauration Of Abbey-lands throughout the British nation: Her self began according to the Popes Directions, yet frustrate were all her hopes. God o're her land then such a famine spred, That her poor subjects upon Acorns fed, Then Calice where the English did remain During eleven Kings reigns from her was ta'in; Which loss so griev'd her, as she did impart, That Calice was engraven in her heart. Again in child-birth never woman had S'unfortunate success as she, so bad: For if she was with child, and had e're been In travel, why? why was it never seen? If not, why was the Kingdom so beguild? Some in the Pulpit for her new-born child Returning thanks: thus her desires b'ing crost, She then th' affections of her husband lost: She could not him enjoy, nor might she smother This her first love, by marrying another, Although she did so many Judgements feel, Yet would she not her bloody Laws repeal: She had no minde to stop the opened vain, Or close the bleeding Orifice again Of dying Saints. At last the Lord did please To strike her with a languishing disease, VVhereof she dy'd; and having held the crown Five years, and five months onely, laid it down. Horrible tempests, mortal sicknesses, Plagues, famines, burning fevers, did perpess The grieved land, (the fourth year she did sway) And swept a multitude of folks away: So that in six weeks space in London there Dy'd seven Aldermen. VVheat that same year Yielded four marks the Quarter: Mault a Peck Fourty four shillings; as much Pease did make Two pound six shillings eight pence: to a crown The following year a Peck of VVheat came down; Four shillings eight pence Mault; of Ry a Strike Take for a groat you may, if it you like. In her fifth year, a thundring tempest came And batt'red down two towns neer Notingham, Flung sheets of lead abroad, bells from the steeple, Tore trees up by the roots, slew divers people, &amp;c. Also a great mortality was known In Autumn then; Corn stood unreap'd, unmown, And rotted in the fields, hence did ensue Great scarcity, the lab'rours being few. So much of her; nor must my Muse pass by Her chiefest Instruments of cruelty, First to begin with Stephen Gard'ner then Bishop of Winchester, whose end my pen Disdains to mention twice: I will therefore Add onely this, That lying at the door Of merc'less death, and being put in minde Of Peter his denying Christ, he whin'd This answer out, VVith Peter I deny'd The Lord, but there is somewhat else beside VVanting in me: Alas! I never spent A tear, nor can (as Peter did) repent. Morgan St. Davids Bishop, who (high base) Condemned Ferrar, and usurp'd his place, Did vomit up his meat through mouth and nose (O horrible) until his life did close. Then Mr. Leyson high Sheriffe, fet away This Martyrs Cattel int'his own ground: they No meat would eat, nor touch a blade of grass, But bellowed and roar'd till death (Alas!) One Justice Morgan who condemned had Lady Jane Grey, within a while fell mad: Nothing but Lady Jane, his voice did sound; The Lady Jane, (Oh! how her name did wound!) The Lady Jane, the Lady Jane; O take The Lady Jane away; no more he spake. Dunnings the Norwich Chancellour for's hate To the truth, dy'd as in his chair he sate. Berry of Norfolk Commissary, one Burn'd harmless Saints, fell with an heavy groan Down to the ground, and never did recover. One Bishop Thornton Suffragan of Dover, A cruel man, while on a Sabbath-day He looked o're his men, to see them play At Bowles, on him did the dead palsey fall; Carry'd to bed, he was desir'd to call The Lord to minde: Yea, said he, so I do, Not onely so, but my Lord Card'nal too: So desperately dy'd. Another tool Of Hell at Greenwich went to Card'nal Pool To get his blessing; but returning fast, He fell down stairs, and brake his neck for hast. Grimwood a wretch, who had himself forsworn, Being in Harvest stacking of his corn, His bowels suddenly fell out. These two Capon and Jeff'ry Doctors, undergo At Salsbury sudden deaths. Mr. Woodroffe Sheriffe of London dyed soon enough. One Clerk who did the Godly Saints devour, Hanged himself, at last in London-Tower. Cox a Promoter, going well t'his bed, When the next morn arose, was found stone dead. Dale dy'd of lice. One Troling Smith, a great Foe to the truth, dy'd suddenly i'th' street. Paul, London Town-Clerk, an accursed wretch Did voluntarily an halter stretch. A lightning stroke did Robert Baldwin kill. Cardinal Pool of an Italian Pill Dy'd as 'twas thought. Dr. Foxford, Blomefield, And Leland too, to sudden deaths did yield. One Dr. Williams Chanc'llour of Glocester, Died the death before he was aware. One Lever said he had at Oxford been, And that ill-favour'd knave, Latimer seen, Tooth'd like an horse: but mark we what did follow, His son soon hang'd himself. One William Swallow Lost all his hair; off all his nails did pill; And's wife was taken with the falling ill. Brown, Lardin, Potto, en'mies of George Eagles, D'yd a dogs shameful death (three pretty Beagles!) A Sheriffes man, who cruelty had acted Against James Abbes, despair'd &amp; dy'd distracted. In Lincolnshire, Burton who Bayliffe was Of Crowland, labour'd to set up the Mass; But the Parishioners with wise delay Still put him off; upon a Sabbath-day This Burton went to Church, (when all men fail'd) And on the Service-reading Curate rail'd: Sirrah (said he,) a Mass, (what?) may'nt we have? Buckle your self to it, you whorson knave, Or by Gods-Blood I'll sheath, I that I will, My dagger in your shoulder; vex me still, Do? you had best. Th' affrighted Curate made No more ado, but Mass in Latin said. Soon after this, as Burton with one more, Rode on the road, a croaking Crow flew o're His head, and dung'd; which falling on his nose, Ran down his slab'ring beard; but in the close Burton was so perfum'd, that one would think No Jakes could yield so horrible a stink As he good man! Sweet Burton go thy way Contented, th' hast enough; such luck they say As thine is good: if the best luck betide To fools thou art not on the wiser side. Hast Burton, hast what need I bid thee hast Whom mischance drives? Oh, Oh, cries he, at last, My very bowels up such reachings make, My head even breaks, ough, ough, and heart-strings ake: A plague upon a vengance take the crow That poyson'd him, and made him vomit so: And so he dy'd. The black-ey'd night inters Bonners corps amongst thieves and murtherers. Is not destruction to the wicked, and strange Judgements to the Workers of iniquity? It's a Righteous thing with God, to recompence tribulation to them that trouble you; and to you that are troubled, rest with us. Roma diu titubans, varijs erroribus acta, Corruet, &amp; mundi desinet esse Caput. Rome tot'ring long laden with Errours store, At last shall fall, and Head the World no more. AMEN. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>