<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Cornwall, Barry, 1787-1874</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Cornwall, Barry, 1787-1874</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">cornwall barry 1787 1874</field>
      <field name="author_text">Cornwall, Barry, 1787-1874</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1820's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.1233.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1822</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466677</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The poetical works of Barry Cornwall ; [i.e. Bryan Waller Procter</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The poetical works of Barry Cornwall ; [i.e. Bryan Waller Procter</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poetical works of barry cornwall</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poetical works of barry cornwall</field>
      <field name="title_text">The poetical works of Barry Cornwall ; [i.e. Bryan Waller Procter</field>
      <field name="year_display">1822</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1822</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1822</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466677&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466677&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Cornwall, Barry, 1787-1874&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;cornwall barry 1787 1874&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The poetical works of Barry Cornwall ; [i.e. Bryan Waller Procter&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poetical works of barry cornwall&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1822&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1822&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Cornwall, Barry&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1787&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1874&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The poetical works of Barry Cornwall&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;[i.e. Bryan Waller Procter]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Henry Colburn and Co.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1822&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp3200&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;3 v.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The poetical works of Barry Cornwall&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;[i.e. Bryan Waller Procter]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 54 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted; verse reproduced elsewhere in The English Poetry Full-text Database omitted; verse drama omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">VOL. I. TO ROMANCE. (By a Friend of the Author.) Beautiful Spirit, who dost sit at eve Within thy tapestried hall of shield and spear, Upgazing where the dying sun-beams leave The heaven in crimson—on thy cheek a tear, Like dew upon the red rose, quivering, clear— From thy pale brow half raised thy nun-like hood— Thy ruby lip half opened, as to hear Some floating music of the sky or wood— Come, sweet Romance! from thine enchanted solitude. Not for myself I woo thee now to stand Beside the harp: Loved Spirit, spread thy wings Of veiling splendour over one whose hand Wakes its first music from the golden strings;— For he is thy true votary, and clings To thy fallen altar with a love sublime, And brings a gift of wild and witching things From glorious Greece, from the Italian prime, A coronal of gems from the rich depths of time. G. C MISCELLANEOUS POEMS. A VISION. This is little more than the recollection of an actual dream. The night was gloomy. Through the skies of June Rolled the eternal moon, 'Midst dark and heavy clouds, that bore A shadowy likeness to those fabled things That sprung of old from man's imaginings. Each seem'd a fierce reality: some wore The forms of sphinx and hippogriff, or seemed Nourished among the wonders of the deep, And wilder than the poet ever dreamed: And there were cars—steeds with their proud necks bent, Tower, and temple, and broken continent: And all, as upon a sea, In the blue ether floated silently. I lay upon my bed and sank to sleep: And then I fancied that I rode upon The waters, and had power to call Up people who had lived in ages gone, And scenes and stories half forgot, and all That on my young imagination Had come like fairy visions, and departed. And ever by me a broad current passed Slowly, from which at times up started Dim scenes and ill-defined shapes. At last I bade the billows render up their dead, And all their wild inhabitants; and I Summoned the spirits who perished, Or took their stations in the starry sky, When Jove himself bowed his Saturnian head Before the One Divinity. First, I saw the landscape fair Towering in the clear blue air, Like Ida's woody summits and sweet fields, Where all that Nature yields Flourishes. Three proud shapes were seen, Standing upon the green Like Olympian queens descended. One was adorned, and one Wore her golden tresses bound With simple flowers; the third was crowned, And from amidst her raven hair, Like stars, imperial jewels shone. —Not one of those figures divine But might have sate in Juno's chair, And smiled in great equality On Jove, though the blue skies were shaken: Or, with superior aspect, taken From Hebe's hand nectarean wine. And that Dardanian boy was there Whom pale Ænone loved: his hair Was black, and curl'd his temples 'round; His limbs were free and his forehead fair, And as he stood on a rising ground, And back his dark locks proudly tossed, A shepherd youth he looked, but trod On the green sward like a god; Most like Apollo when he played ('Fore Midas,) in the Phrygian shade, With Pan, and to the Sylvan lost. And now from out the watery floor A city rose, and well she wore Her beauty, and stupendous walls, And towers that touched the stars, and halls Pillar'd with whitest marble, whence Palace on lofty palace sprung; And over all rich gardens hung. Where, amongst silver waterfalls, Cedars and spice-trees and green bowers, And sweet winds playing with all the flowers Of Persia and Araby, Walked princely shapes: some with an air Like warriors, some like ladies fair Listening, and, amidst all, the king Nebuchadnezzar rioting In supreme magnificence. —This was famous Babylon. That glorious vision passed on, And then I heard the laurel-branches sigh That still grow where the bright-eyed muses walked: And Pelion shook his piny locks, and talked Mournfully to the fields of Thessaly. And there I saw, piercing the deep blue sky, And radiant with his diadem of snow, Crowned Olympus: and the hills below Looked like inferior spirits tending round His pure supremacy; and a sound Went rolling onwards through the sunny calm, As if immortal voices then had spoken, And, with rich noises, broken The silence which that holy place had bred. I knelt—and as I knelt, haply in token Of thanks, there fell a honeyed shower of balm, And the imperial mountain bowed his hoary head. And then came one who on the Nubian sands Perish'd for love; and with him the wanton queen Egyptian, in her state was seen; And how she smiled, and kissed his willing hands, And said she would not love, and swore to die, And laughed upon the Roman Antony. Oh, matchless Cleopatra! never since Has one, and never more Shall one like thee tread on the Egypt shore, Or lavish such royal magnificence: Never shall one laugh, love, or die like thee, Or own so sweet a witchery: And, brave Mark Antony, that thou could'st give Half the wide world to live With that enchantress, did become thee well; For Love is wiser than Ambition.— Queen and thou, lofty triumvir, fare ye well. And then I heard the sullen waters roar, And saw them cast their surf upon the strand, And then rebounding toward some far-seen land, They washed and washed its melancholy shore: And the terrific spirits, bred In the sea-caverns, moved by those fierce jars, Rose up like giants from their watery bed, And shook their silver hair against the stars. Then, bursts like thunder—joyous outcries wild— Sounds as from trumpets, and from drums, And music, like the lulling noise that comes From nurses when they hush their charge to sleep, Came in confusion from the deep. Methought one told me that a child Was that night unto the great Neptune born; And then old Triton blew his curled horn, And the Leviathan lashed the foaming seas, And the wanton Nereides Came up like phantoms from their coral halls, And laughed and sung like tipsy Bacchanals, Till all the fury of the ocean broke Upon my ear—I trembled and awoke. CROMWELL. Somewhat apart, but undistinguish'd all From those around, sate Cromwell. In his eye Collected, peered deceit: yet withal blazed A stern and steady fire: half hypocrite And zealot half was he, and had become Perchance, but that the dawning light then shone, A dark inquisitor, and fit to share Those works of fire, whereby the cowled monk Was wont convince the writhing heretic. At last he slowly rose.—Silent at first He stood as night: gloomy his brow, but touch'd And elevate by fanatic flame, that rose Far from the heart. Like some dark rock, whose rifts Hold nitrous grain, whereon the lightning fires Have glanced, and left a pale and livid light, So he, some corpor'al nerve being struck, stood there Glaring, but cold and pitiless.—Even hope (The brightest angel whom the heavens have given To lead and cheer us onwards) shrank aghast From that stern look despairing. A HAUNTED STREAM. ‘Of objects all inanimate I made ‘Idols.’ Byron. It is perhaps a fable: yet the hind Tells it with reverence, and at times I deem The tale allied to truth. They say yon brook That circles with its silver arms that grove Of forest trees, is—haunted: nay, you smile; But I was born beside it, and through life, Aye, 'midst the jarrings of this bitter world, In pain, in calumny, my mind hath dwelt Upon this stream as on some holy thought. See where it wanders from its mossy cave, And toward the dark wood, like a bashful thing Surprised, runs trembling as for succour. Look! Such streams as these did Dian love, and such Naiads of old frequented. Still its face Is clear as truth; and yet—it roams like error. In former times, rivers were celebrate: One told how Achelöus dived beneath Sicilian seas, to meet his nymph divine, The blue Arethusa; one (‘the loftiest’) sung The rough Scamander, oh, and how he rushed And mingled with Troy fight; and some did tell Of Aganippe's fount; of Hippocrene, And Simois, and ‘immortal Castaly.’ Come then, my stream, and I will sing of thee: Worthy from beauty, oh! but worthier far From sweet associate pleasures. Thou to me Art like the glass of memory, where the mind Sees, charmed and softened by thy murmuring, things It elsewhere dare not dream of; things that fled With early youth, and went—I know not whither: Shadows forgot, and hope that perished.— —Beautiful river! on thy banks remote Still does the half-sunned primrose waste its sweets, And that pale flower that loves the valley, (white Like purity) comes forth; blue violets, The wild-brier-rose, and spotted daisies, which The young year scatters on the sward, and all That June or April love, or Autumn spares Amidst her golden bounty, live unhurt. Here, on May mornings, I may hear the thrush Pour from his silver throat sweet music; and, 'Neath summer stars the nightingale—(for she Is queen of all earth's choristers, and holds Acquaintance with the evening winds, which waft her Sweet tidings from the rose.) The stockdove here Breathes her deep note complaining, 'till the air Seems touch'd, and all the woods and hollows, sighing, Prolong the sound to sadness. Hark! a noise. Song. Look upon these ‘yellow sands,’ Coloured by no mortal hands: Look upon this grassy bank, Crown'd with flowers and osiers dank, Whereon the milk-white heifers feed: (White as if of Io's breed.) Look upon these glassy waters, Where earth's loveliest daughters Bathe their limbs and foreheads fair And wring their dark and streaming hair. Here, if on summer nights you stray, When rolls the bright and orbed moon Thro' the sultry skies of June, You will see the Spirits play, And all the Fays keep holiday. Think not that 'tis but a dream: For I (the Naiad of the stream) Have often by the pale moonlight, Seen them dancing, joyous, light. Some, heedless of the midnight hours, Laugh, and 'wake the sleeping flowers: Some on water-lilies lie And down the wave float silently: Some, in circles flying, Beat with their tiny wings the air, And rouse the zephyr when he's dying: Some tumble in the fountain's spray, And in the lunar rainbows play: All seem as they were free from care. —Yet, One there was, who at times would stray, As on her breast some sorrow weigh'd, And rest her in the pine-tree shade: (The blue-eyed queen Titania;) She, from very grief of heart, Would from the revel oft depart, And like a shooting sun-beam, go To where the Tigris' waters shine, Or the Cashmere roses blow, Or where the fir-clad Appennine Frowns darkly on Italian skies, Or where, 'neath Summer's smile divine, Tydoré's spicy forests rise. —But hark! my master Ocean calls, And I must hie to his coral halls. What think you now?—Believe the spirit; and own The place is haunted. On yon slanting tree That dips its tresses in the wave, 'tis said Poets have leant, and when the moon hath flung Her bright smile on the quivering element, Have thought a strange communion liv'd between That planet and the stream. Perhaps a nymph Of Dian's train, here, for her voice or beauty, Was changed by some envious deity. Whate'er it be, it well doth manifest The lives of those who dwell around it: Calm, And undisturbed its current, never chafed By the rude breeze, it flows on till—'tis lost. But I have sailed upon a stormier wave, And, in my course of life, dark shoals were hid, And rocks arose, and thundering currents clashed; Like when the mighty rivers of the West Meet the tempestuous seas; but still I lived, And held my way undaunted. Now, I come To this sweet place for quiet. Every tree, And bush and fragrant flower and hilly path, And thymy mound that flings unto the winds Its morning incense, is my friend; for I Did make acquaintance with inanimate things In very boyhood, and did love to break With shouts the mountain silence, and to hang O'er flashing torrents, when the piny boughs Shook their dark locks, and plained in mournful tones Mysterious to the barren wilderness; And still in solitary spots my soul Resumes its youth.—Think not that this is all An idle folly; he who can draw a joy From rocks, or woods, or weeds, or things that seem All mute, and does it—is wise. STANZAS. And now with gleams of half extinguish'd thought, With many recognitions dim and faint, And somewhat of a sad perplexity, The picture of the mind revives again. Wordsworth. I I have liv'd many seasons: and I stand Nor low nor lofty on this world at last: Yet with some hope (which I cannot withstand) I shall not wholly bow me to the blast, Nor, all unknown, like a base weed be cast Away, and wither in my wintry grave, Shaming the soil that fed me: For the past— 'Tis gone: and 'twould be idle now to rave Of wasted hours, or mourn: I am not folly's slave. II Yet, like a pestilence, despondence hung Upon the spirit of my prime. In vain I sought for cure: like wasting fire it clung Against my heart: it struck upon my brain. Then, like a lion bursting from his chain, (For I was not the fool of phantasy) I rush'd away, and rid me of my pain; And, with that courage that becomes the free, Stood on the verge again: safe—for at liberty. III In deep embowering woods I built my home, For Nature nurses best the sickly mind; And when Apollo thro' my leafy dome Came visiting, I rose: at eve, reclined, I caught strange secrets from the whispering wind, That with its cooling freshness bath'd my head As with Olympian dews: 'twas then my mind Gather'd its powers, and sickly visions fled. I stood like a man new born—recover'd from the dead. IV It is upon the mountains—the vast sea, That we hear Nature's language: 'tis the tide Which rolls for ever, speaks ‘Eternity:’ The hills declare she is to Heaven allied, And in the thunder comes her voice of pride: Her mirror is the lake: her garb the field With all the colours of the Iris dyed: Somewhat of mighty moment does she yield From every part. To me, her soul she hath revealed. V For I did woo her in my early youth, And sought the marvels of her lonely ways; And often in those fountain depths, where truth Springs from its parent source, I loved to gaze, And watch'd its many wanderings, where it strays The world's rude rocks, and wildering woods among; And where the elemental lightnings blaze I've trod—aye, stood above 'em, while along The precipice they play'd, wild, glittering, and strong. VI I've roamed amongst the eternal Alps. I've stood And gazed upon the diminish'd world below; Marking, at frightful distance, field and flood, And spire and town, like things of pigmy show, Shrink into nothing: while those peaks of snow (Which yet the winds themselves but seldom climb) Arose like giants from the void below, But fashion'd all for everlasting time: Imperishable things—unstain'd, as 'twere, by crime. VII Oh, ye unbending mountains! If ye be Aught more than human view may contemplate— If on your crowned heads the Deity Rests his bright foot eternal, when in state He bends arrayed in lightnings; consecrate Then stand for ever. Perchance your heaven-ward look Infused such feeling, strong and elevate, That madness in the soul's bright temple shook. Silent ye pointed high. I read as from a book. VIII Sacred ye are. The very eye of God Darts roses on ye as it shuts at even. The earthquake on your breast hath never trod; Nor in vast fragments have your limbs been riven; Nor through your heart the red volcano driven, That foams in lava-cataracts from its bound; Or flings its blazing columns up to heaven, Sinking in darkening ashes on the ground. Thus Hecla, Etna feel; and all, save ye, around. IX And oh! thou viewless Spirit, who dost breathe Life on the world: whose home is on the seas, And plains, and mountain summits, and beneath This earth; whose couriers are the storm and breeze; Whose children, the gay birds—the beasts—the trees, And we (the monarchs of mortality) And whatsoe'er hath being. That thou didst please To draw from me the mind's calamity, I thank thee. Thou hast given the world again to me X For not alone with Alpine heights my soul Communed in silence: 'Twas from forests deep— The everlasting ocean that doth roll Bursting in thundering billows 'gainst the steep; The rainbow that, when summer vapours weep, Arches the sky; the free and sightless wind: The Moon, the Sun, and (last) those fires that keep Nightly their starry watch. From all my mind Caught light, and strength, and joy, to no one aid confined, XI Two poets saw I there: one had I seen In boyhood mix in many an idle game; Since when his hand had gathered laurels green For his own brows, and on the scroll of fame Had written his imperishable name, Amidst the golden characters that lie Distinguishable there—even as the flame Of moon or sun burns out conspicuously Amongst the stars that crowd the bosom of the sky. XII Upon his beautiful forehead scorn was sitting, And weariness and woe; and o'er his eye Shadows of dim tumultuous thought were flitting, And passions, which are buried ere they die, Exorcised by the enchantress Memory From their dark grave—the heart. But quickly these Like clouds of rain in summer, passed by; And then he wantoned with the mountain breeze, And with the soft mysterious music of the trees XIII Held frequent talk, like some familiar spirit. And his companion young would join him then, And tell how mortal creature might inherit Ethereal essence here, and haply again (Though like a world-abandoned denizen) Expand into that perfect element, Whate'er it be, that fills the frames of men With their incomparable light. Intent Upon that theory sublime his soul was bent. XIV And who may tell (though I believe it not) But that the soul by meditation may Plume its bright wings, and from its grosser lot Spring, like a thing immortal, far away; Or, as the white Alps mount and meet the day, Accumulate upon its airy head Thoughts that fine spirits have bequeathed, ere they Lay down in silence on their wormy bed, And conquer that chill voice which summons to the dead. XV I have seen the Alpine sun-set:—oh! how weak My verse to tell what flash'd across my sight. Green, blue and burning red, was every streak: Like rainbow-beams, but trebly, trebly bright; The earth, the air, the heavens, were living light: My vision was absorbed. I trembled—then Softening his glance, and sinking in his might, The Sun slow faded from the eyes of men, And died away. Ne'er have I seen the like again. XVI Yet have I lain in many a leafy nook Sequester'd, hiding from the summer beam, Idling, or haply with that charmed book Writ by the Avon side; and loved to dream Of pale Cordelia, gentle Imogen: Or, on some brook that slid, like guilt, away, Hurrying the pilfered mosses down its stream, Pondered, and often at the close of day Gazed on the coming Moon, and felt, perhaps, her sway. XVII It is in high, remoter scenes, that we Become sublim'd, yet humble: there we learn That still beyond us spreads—infinity, And we still clay: or, all admiring, turn To where those characters of beauty burn, Which God hath printed on the starry skies: And haply guess why we alone may learn The world's vast wonders: why alone our eyes See far: why we alone have such proud sympathies XVIII For with creation and its marvels none Save we, can hold communion. On the earth Are many stately footsteps, and the Sun Shines on eyes bright as ours: yet hath our birth (Holy) shed 'round us an immortal worth, Beyond the rest: though with the rest we fade, And are encircled by as frail a girth To life, as they: and in the deadly shade Wither as quick, and are as loathsome when decayed. XIX But while we live, the air, the fruit, the flower, Doth own to us a high, superior charm: And the soul's radiance in our wintry hour Flings a sweet summer halo round us, warm; And then, the multitudinous things that swarm From the brain's secret cells, and never die, (Though mortal born,)—Oh! for that boasted balm Of life, to raise the mighty when they lie Wrecks, both in frame and mind—common mortality. XX Seems it not hard, that they whose spirits have Engendered and matured such thoughts sublime, And lived but for the world, must in the grave At last sink like the things of folly—crime, Ere yet the soul hath blossom'd in its prime? For who may tell how high the labouring thought Might reach, if giv'n to live till after-time: And what a pyramid it might build, how fraught With treasures, but from time and meditation caught? THE MAGDALEN. ‘And Woman who had wept her loveliest dower, ‘There hid her broken heart.’ Paris, st. 15. I do remember it. 'Twas such a face As Guido would have loved to dwell upon; But oh! the touches of his pencil never Could paint her perfect beauty. In her home (Which once she did desert) I saw her last; Propped up by pillows, swelling round her like Soft heaps of snow, yielding, and fit to bear Her faded figure.—I observed her well: Her brow was fair, but very pale, and look'd Like stainless marble; a touch methought would soil Its whiteness. O'er her temple one blue vein Ran like a tendril; one through her shadowy hand Branched like the fibre of a leaf—away. Her mouth was tremulous, and her cheek wore then A flush of beautiful vermilion, But more like art than nature; and her eye Spoke as became the youthful Magdalen, Dying and broken-hearted. ? WISHES. Now, give me but a cot that's good, In some great town's neighbourhood: A garden, where the winds may play Fresh from the blue hills far away, And wanton with such trees as bear Their loads of green through all the year, Laurel, and dusky juniper: So may some friends, whose social talk I love, there take their evening walk And spend a frequent holiday. And may I own a quiet room, Where the morning sun may come, Stored with books of poesy, Tale, science, old morality, Fable, and divine history Ranged in separate cases round, Each with living marble crowned; Here should Apollo stand, and there Isis, with her sweeping hair; Here Phidian Jove, or the face of thought Of Pallas, or Laocoon, Or Adrian's boy Antinous, Or the winged Mercurius, Or some that conquest lately brought From the land Italian. And one I'd have, whose heaving breast Should rock me nightly to my rest, By holy chains bound fast to me, Faster by Love's sweet sorcery. I would not have my beauty as Juno or Paphian Venus was, Or Dian with her crested moon, (Else, haply, she might change as soon,) Or Portia, that high Roman dame, Or she who set the world on flame, Spartan Helen, who did leave Her husband-king to grieve, And fled with Priam's shepherd-boy, And caused the mighty tale of Troy. She should be a woman who (Graceful without much endeavour) Could praise or excuse all I do, And love me ever. I'd have her thoughts fair, and her skin White as the white soul within; And her fringed eyes of darkest blue, Which the great soul looketh through, Like heaven's own gates cerulean: And these I'd gaze and gaze upon, As did of old Pygmalion. FLOWERS. There the rose unveils Her breast of beauty, and each delicate bud O' the season comes in turn to bloom and perish. But first of all the violet, with an eye Blue as the midnight heavens, the frail snow-drop, Born of the breath of winter, and on his brow Fixed like a pale and solitary star: The languid hyacinth, and wild primrose. And daisy trodden down like modesty: The fox-glove, in whose drooping bells the bee Makes her sweet music; the narcissus (named From him who died for love,) the tangled woodbine, Lilacs, and flowering limes, and scented thorns, And some from whom the voluptuous winds of June Catch their perfumings. SERENADE.—(Twilight.) The western skies are no longer gay, For the sun of the summer has died away, Yet left no gloom: For ere the Spirit of heaven went, He strung night's shadowy instrument, And hung on every leaf perfume. To each sweet breeze that haunts the world, And sleeps by day in the rose-leaf curled, A warmth he gave: He has left a life in these marble halls, And beauty on yon white water-falls, And still at his bidding these dark pines wave. Rich is the sun with his golden hair, And his eye is too bright for man to bear; And when he shrouds His brow in vapour, and all the west Strews gold, as to welcome a kingly guest, He looks like a god on his throne of clouds. Yet—I know an eye as bright as his, And a smile more soft, and lips of bliss, Oh! lovelier far: And an arm as white as the milk-white dove, And a bosom all warm and rich with love, And a heart—as the hearts of angels are. She listens now to my wild guitar, And she hides her beyond yon lattice bar, (A girl's delight:) Yet she never will let me linger long, But comes and rewards my twilight song, And treats her love with—a kiss by night. TO ? Beauty! never more shalt thou Gently speak unto me, Nor thy smile undo me: (I may tell thy witchery now.) Like the lips of love Came thy sweet caressing, Grateful as a sudden blessing Falling from the skies above. And is thy beauty gone— And thy voice departed? And is thy bright eye bright no more? Oh! why were we for ever parted? Thou art lying now alone, Chained in thy lasting sleep, In those low chambers of the deep, Where sea-nymphs are dreaming, And the under-waters streaming Silently by the coral shore. And not a wind that wantons here With the upper billow, Can reach thee on thy sandy pillow: So thou wilt slumber quiet, dear. Thou wast buried nobly; all The elements in their pomp attended, And their various music blended To grace thy funeral. The thunder muttered along the sky, And the lightning lit his torch on high; The tempest blew his trumpet o'er thee, And the ocean rose and sunk before thee, And its mountains roared harmoniously. For me—I do believe that we Shall meet again in after days, And I shall, once more, see The smile I used to praise, And touch the roses of those lips, And in the splendour of thine eye (Now shrouded in a cold eclipse,) Bask as beneath the sunny sky. I would not lose the thought that flies By me, that I shall see thee, dear, In the bright bowers of Paradise, As sweet (no more) as thou wast here, For all the promised joys that man Hath gather'd from the Ottoman. A SONG. Lie silent now, my lyre, For all thy master's fire Is gone.—It vanish'd like the summer sun. Brightly the passion rose, And, 'till its turbulent close, It shone as bright; though all he wished was won. Deem me not false, ye fair, Who, with your golden hair And soft eyes chain man's heart to yours: the deer Thus bound by beauty's chain Wanders not again: Prisoner to love, like me—never to fear. She whom I loved has fled; And now with the lost dead I rank her: and the heart that loved her so, (But could not bear her pride,) In its own cell hath died, And turned to dust,—but this she shall not know. 'Twould please her did she think That my poor frame did shrink, And waste and wither; and that Love's own light Did blast its temple, where 'Twas worshipped many a year; Veiled (like some holy thing) from human sight. Oh! had you seen her when She languished, and the men From the dark glancing of her fringed eye Turned, but returned again To mark the winding vein Steal tow'rd her marble bosom, silently. What matters this?—thou lyre, Nothing shall e'er inspire Thy master to rehearse those songs again: She whom he loved is gone, And he, now left alone, Sings, when he sings of love, in vain, in vain. TO A CHILD. Fairest of Earth's creatures! All thy innocent features Moulded in beauty do become thee well. Oh! may thy future years Be free from pains, and fears, False love, and others envy, and the guile That lurks beneath a friendlike smile, And all the various ills that dwell In this so strange compounded world; and may Thy look be like the skies of May, Supremely soft and clear, With, now and then, a tear For joy, or others sorrows, not thy own. And may thy sweet voice Like a stream afar Flow in perpetual music, and its tone Be joyful and bid all who hear rejoice. And may thy bright eye, like a star, Shine sweet and cheer the hearts that love thee, And take in all the beauty of the flowers, Deep woods, and running brooks, and the rich sights Which thou may'st note above thee At noontide, or on interlunar nights, Or when blue Iris, after showers, Bends her cerulean bow, and seems to rest On some distant mountain's breast, Surpassing all the shapes that lie Haunting the sun-set of an autumn sky. WOMAN. Gone from her cheek is the summer bloom, And her lip has lost all its faint perfume: And the gloss has dropped from her golden hair, And her cheek is pale, but no longer fair. And the spirit that sate on her soft blue eye, Is struck with cold mortality; And the smile that played round her lip has fled, And every charm has now left the dead. Like slaves they obeyed her in height of power, But left her all in her wintry hour; And the crowds that swore for her love to die, Shrunk from the tone of her last faint sigh. —And this is man's fidelity! 'Tis Woman alone, with a purer heart, Can see all these idols of life depart, And love the more, and smile and bless Man in his uttermost wretchedness. ROSAMUND GRAY. (A Fragment. The latter part of this poem is lost.) Once—but she died—I knew a village girl (Poor Rosamund Gray,) who, in my fancy, did Surpass the deities you tell me of. Haply you may have passed her; and indeed Her beauty was not made for all observance, If beauty it might be called. It was a sick And melancholy loveliness, that pleased But few; and somewhat of its charm, perhaps, Owed to the lonely spot she dwelt in.—I Knew her from her infancy; a shy, sad girl; And gossips when they saw her, oftentimes Would tell her future fortunes. They would note Her deep blue eyes, which seemed as they already Had made fast friends with sorrow, and would say Hers was an early fate: that she would pine From grief—neglect—or cast her youth away On love without requital.—She grew a woman: Yet, when from some long absence I returned, I knew again the pretty child I left. Her hair of deepest chesnut, (that which once Fell in thick shining clusters,) 'round a brow Pale as Greek marble, wandered tastefully: But still there were the same blue eyes, and still Their melancholy splendour; bearing now Proof of the gossip's prophecy. ? SONNET. To Michael Angelo. Michael! thou wast the mightiest spirit of all Who taught or learned Italian art sublime: And long shall thy renown survive the time When Ruin to herself thy works shall call. One only, (and he perished in his prime,) Could mate with thee; and in one path alone. Thou didst regenerate art; and from the stone Started the breathing image, perfect great; And such as haply, in his after state, Man shall attain: and thou could'st trace the rhyme That lifts its parent to the skies, thus bending To thy resistless powers the sisters three, Painting, and Sculpture, and wing'd Poetry. —Whom can I place beside thee—not descending? SONNET. To ? (1817.) Upon what pleasant slope, or sunny field, Sweet, unforgotten girl, are your delaying? Or are you with those sportive children playing, Whose loveliness time has not quite revealed? Or with that serious sister, who has sealed Her nuptial bond in joy—are you arraying Her, or your own dark hair hind'ring from straying Down that white bosom vanity never steeled? Or are you, in unostentatious duty, Tending the kindest mother in the world, Whose looks are fix'd on those blue eyes of beauty, That shine as softly as a summer star? Yet wherefore wish I the dim veil unfurl'd? May joy go with you wheresoe'er you are. SONNET. Imagination. Oh, for that winged steed, Bellerophon! That Pallas gave thee in her infinite grace And love for innocence, when thou didst face The treble-shaped Chimæra. But he is gone That struck the sparkling stream from Helicon; And never hath one risen in his place, Stamped with the features of that mighty race. Yet wherefore grieve I—seeing how easily The plumed spirit may its journey take Through yon blue regions of the middle air; And note all things below that own a grace, Mountain, and cataract, and silent lake, And wander in the fields of poesy, Where avarice never comes, and seldom care. SONNET. Winter. I love to listen when the year grows old, And noisy: like some weak life-wrinkled thing, That vents his splenetic humours, murmuring At ills he shares in common with the bold. Then from my quiet room the Winter cold Is barred out like a thief: but should one bring A frozen hand, the which December's wing Hath struck so fiercely, that he scarce can hold The stiffened finger tow'rd the grate, I lend A double welcome to the victim, who Comes shivering, with pale looks, and lips of blue, And through the snow and splashing rain could walk, For some few hours of kind and social talk: And deem him, more than ever, now—my friend. SONNET. A Fresh Morning. It is a noisy morning: yet the sky Looks down as bright as on a summer's day. The ocean, curling as in wanton play, Doth bare her bosom to Apollo's eye, And every whispering wind that flutters by Seems like a spirit charged to greet the day, And duly hurries tow'rd the East—away: For there the sun, seen o'er the mountains high, Comes smiling on the world. The fruit, the flower, Earth, heaven, the sea, and oh! the heart of man, And all that came within his mighty plan Fling back the glance in joy: And from her bower The spirit of Meditation comes, to see All nature join in social jubilee. THE END.</field>
   </doc>
</add>