<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Elderton, William</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Elderton, William</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">elderton william</field>
      <field name="author_text">Elderton, William</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">16th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.2204.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">1584</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464559</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">A new Yorkshyre Song Intituled: Yorke, Yorke, for my monie: Of all the Cities that euer I see, For mery pastime and companie, Except the Cittie of London [by William Elderton</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">A new Yorkshyre Song Intituled: Yorke, Yorke, for my monie: Of all the Cities that euer I see, For mery pastime and companie, Except the Cittie of London [by William Elderton</field>
      <field name="title_facet">new yorkshyre song intituled yorke yorke for my monie of all the cities that euer i see for mery pastime and companie except the cittie of london by william elderton</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">new yorkshyre song intituled yorke yorke for my monie of all the cities that euer i see for mery pastime and companie except the cittie of london by william elderton</field>
      <field name="title_text">A new Yorkshyre Song Intituled: Yorke, Yorke, for my monie: Of all the Cities that euer I see, For mery pastime and companie, Except the Cittie of London [by William Elderton</field>
      <field name="year_display">1584</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1584</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1584</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464559&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464559&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Elderton, William&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;elderton william&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;A new Yorkshyre Song Intituled: Yorke, Yorke, for my monie: Of all the Cities that euer I see, For mery pastime and companie, Except the Cittie of London [by William Elderton&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;new yorkshyre song intituled yorke, yorke for my monie of all the cities that euer i see for mery pastime and companie except the cittie of london by william elderton&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1584&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1584&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Elderton, William&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;A new Yorkshyre Song Intituled: Yorke, Yorke, for my monie: Of all the Cities that euer I see, For mery pastime and companie, Except the Cittie of London [by William Elderton]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Imprinted ... by Richard Iones [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1584&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp1243&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;[1 sheet]&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;A new Yorkshyre Song Intituled: Yorke, Yorke, for my monie: Of all the Cities that euer I see, For mery pastime and companie, Except the Cittie of London [by William Elderton]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 22 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">A new Yorkshyre Song, Intituled: Yorke, Yorke, for my monie: Of all the Cities that euer I see, For mery pastime and companie, Except the Cittie of London. As I came thorow the Northcountrey, The fashions of the world to see, I sought for mery companie, to goe to the Cittie of London: And when to the Cittie of Yorke I came, I found good companie in the same, Aswell [illeg.]posed to euery game, as if it had been at London. Yorke, Yorke, for my monie, Of all the Citties that euer I see, For mery pastime and companie, Except the Cittie of London. And in that Cittie what sawe I then? Knightes, Squires, and Gentlemen, A shooting went for Matches ten, as if it had been at London. And they shot for twentie poundes a Bowe, Besides great cheere they did bestowe, I neuer saw a gallanter showe, except I had been at London. Yorke, yorke, for my monie, &amp;c. These Matches you shall vnderstande, The Earle of Essex tooke in hand, Against the good Earle of Cumberlande, as if it had been at London. And agreede these matches all shall be, For pastime and good companie, At the Cittie of Yorke full merily, as if it had been at London. Yorke, yorke, for my monie, &amp;c. In Yorke, there dwels an Alderman, which much, I neuer heard of any such, in all the Cittie of London. His name is Maltbie, mery and wise, At any pastime you can deuise, But in shooting all his pleasures lyes, the like was neuer in London. Yorke, yorke, for my monie, &amp;c. This Maltbie, for the Citties sake, To shoote (himself) did vndertake, At any good Match the Earles would make, as well as they doe at London. And he brought to the fielde with him, One Specke, an Archer proper and trim, And Smith, that shoote about the pin, as if it had been at London. Yorke, yorke, &amp;c. Then came from Cumberland Archers three, Best Bowmen in the North countree, I will tell you their names what they bee, well knowne to the Cittie of London. Wamsley, many a man doth knowe, And Bolton, how he draweth his Bowe, And Ratcliffes shooting long agoe, well knowne to the Cittie of London. Yorke, yorke, &amp;c. And the Noble Earle of Essex came, To the fielde himself to see the same Which shalbe had for euer in fame, as soone as I come at London. For he shewed himself so diligent there, To make a Marke and keepe it faire: It is worthie memorie to declare, through all the Cittie of London. Yorke, yorke, &amp;c. And then was shooting out of crye, The skantling at a handfull nie, And yet the winde was very hie, as it is sometimes at London. They clapt the Cloutes so on the ragges, There was such betting and such bragges: And galloping vp and downe with Nagges, as if it had been at London. Yorke, yorke, &amp;c. And neuer an Archer gaue regarde, To halfe a Bowe, nor halfe a parde, I neuer see Matches goe more harde: about the Cittie of London: For, fairer play was neuer plaide, Nor fairer layes was neuer laide, And a weeke together, they keept this trade, as if it had been at London. Yorke, yorke, &amp;c. The Maior of Yorke, with his companie, Were all in the fieldes, I warrant ye, To see good rule kept orderly, as if it had been at London. Which was a dutifull sight to see, The Maior and Aldermen there to bee, For the setting forth of Archerie, aswell as they doe at London. Yorke, yorke, &amp;c. And there was neither fault nor fray, Nor any disorder any way: But euery man did pitch and pay, as if it had been at London: As soone as euery Match was done, Euery man was [illeg.] that won, And merily vp and downe did ronne, as if it had been at London. Yorke, yorke, &amp;c. And neuer a man that went abroade, But thought his name well bestowde: And monie layd out for [illeg.]eape and loade, as if it had been at London, And Gentlemen there, so franke and free, As a Mint at Yorke, againe should bee, Like shooting did I neuer see, except I had been at London. Yorke, yorke, &amp;c. At Yorke, were Ambassadours three, Of Russia, Lordes of high degree, This shooting they desirde to see: as if it had been at London: And one desirde to drawe a Bowe, The force and strength thereof to knowe, And for his delight he drewe it so, as seldome seene in London. Yorke, yorke, &amp;c. And they did maruaile very much, There could be any Archer such, To shoote so farre the Cloute to tutch, which is no newes to London: And they might consider than, An English shaft will kill a man, As hath been proued where and whan, and Cronicled since in London. Yorke, &amp;c. The Earle of Cumberlands Archers won. Two Matches cleare, ere all was done: And I made hast apace to ronne, to carie these newes to London. And Wamsley did the vpshot win, With both his shafts so neere the pin, You could scant haue put three fingers in, as if it had beene at London. Yorke, &amp;c. I passe not for my monie it cost, Though some I spent, and some I lost, I wanted neither sod nor roast, as if it had been at London. For there was plentie of euerything, Redd and fallowe Deere for a King, I neuer sawe so mery shooting, since first I came from London. Yorke, yorke, &amp;c. God saue the Cittie of Yorke therefore, That hath such noble frendes in store, And such good Aldermen send them more, and the like good lucke at London: For, it is not little ioye to see, When Lordes and Aldermen so agree, With such according Communaltie, God sende vs the like at London. Yorke, yorke, &amp;c. God saue the good Earle of Cumberlande, His praise in golden lines shall stande, That maintaines Archerie through the land, aswell as they doe at London. Whose noble minde so courteously, Acquaints himself with the Communaltie, To the glorie of his Nobilitie, I will carie the praise to London. Yorke, yorke, &amp;c. And tell the good Earle of Essex thus, As he is now yong and prosperous, To vse such properties vertuous, deserues great praise in London: For, it is no little ioye to see, When noble Youthes so gracious bee, To giue their good willes to their Countree, as well as they doe at London. Yorke, yorke, &amp;c. Farewell good Cittie of Yorke to thee, Tell Alderman Maltbie this from mee, In print shall this good shooting bee, as soone as I come at London. And many a Song will I bestowe, On all the Musicions that I knowe, To sing the praises where they goe, of the Cittie of Yorke, in London. Yorke, yorke, &amp;c. God saue our Queene, and keepe our peace That our good shooting maie increase: And praying to God, let vs not cease, aswell at Yorke, as at London. That all our Countrey round about, May haue Archers good to hit the Clout, Which England cannot be without, no more then Yorke and London. Yorke, yorke, &amp;c. God graunt that (once) her Maiestie, Would come her Cittie of Yorke to see, For the comfort great of that Countree, as well as she doth to London. Nothing shalbe thought to deare, To see her Highnes Person there, With such obedient loue and feare, as euer she had in London. Yorke, yorke, for my monie, Of all the Citties that euer J see, For mery pastime and companie, Except the Cittie of London. From Yorke, by W. E.</field>
   </doc>
</add>