<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Wroth, Mary, Lady, 1586-1640</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Wroth, Mary, Lady, 1586-1640</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">wroth mary lady 1586 1640</field>
      <field name="author_text">Wroth, Mary, Lady, 1586-1640</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1980's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.2249.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240353</field>
      <field name="date_text">1983</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464595</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Poems (1983</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Poems (1983</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poems 1983</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poems 1983</field>
      <field name="title_text">Poems (1983</field>
      <field name="year_display">1983</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1983</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1983</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464595&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464595&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Wroth, Mary, Lady, ca. 1586-ca. 1640&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;wroth mary lady ca 1586 ca 1640&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Poems (1983&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poems 1983&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1983&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1983&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Wroth, Mary, Lady&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1586&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1640&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poems (1983)&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Baton Rouge&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Louisiana State University Press&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1983&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp4426&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;xiv, 251 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poems (1983)&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 37 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Majority of verse reproduced elsewhere in The English Poetry Full-text Database; only unique items included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">POEMS FROM THE NEWBERRY MANUSCRIPT The Secound Part of the Countesse of Montgomery's Urania [Why doe you thus torment my poorest hart?] Why doe you thus torment my poorest hart? Why doe you cleerest eyes obscure all day, From mee loves poorest vassall? Can my smart Ad triumph to your Crowne? Make noe delay Butt quickly O conclude, and doe nott stay, Rebellions must bee crusht by present art Yett I a subject ame without dismaye, For loyalty I justly claime great part, Butt if thos cruell eyes will nott impart A favourable sensure, Oh poore claye How can an new mould bee to ease my smart? Noe an new death must all thes ills repay, Then wellcom death since by thos eyes I dy, Love looke, are any cleerer in your skye? [Most deere, more hapy soverainsing harts] Most deere, more hapy soverainsing harts, Free from flattering; Murdering peeces prove your sweet eye darts Joys from desire scattering, Why alas were you framd if alone to kill? You knowe murdering A crime by all condemn'd, is this your skill, Nor caus'd nor furdering? Yett you alas may certainly controle Thos humours flowing, Butt if itt bee you love to fleet, and role Poor slaves for honors showing, Certainly you will end att last as wee, And pitty wanting cry alas wo's mee. [Honor now injoye the day] Honor now injoye the day Love is falen into desmay, Nay is conquer'd, yeeld all right To the power of his might Honor, honor, now is all: Captive Cupid sees his fall; Never lett a slight love come, In honors sight for a doombe Or thinke light affections thrall Dare apeere, noe now 't'is gall; Honor Monarck is of Love, Under him affections move, This is Honors purest throne, Heere hee brightly shines alone, Poore love like meane sphears appeere, In him's onely brightnes cleere, Had I knowne him thus beefore, Myne armes, I had layd att his dore, Now I yeeld them to his worthe This doth knowledg true bring forthe Arrowes, bowe, darts, and wings Which death brought to mortallings: All I offer up to you Deere Honor, as the Monarck true. [This is Honor's holly day] [1] This is Honor's holly day Now sheapheard swaines, neatheards play Cupid wills itt soe: Kings, and princes come alonge You shall safely pass from wronge Desire was your foe, 2 Fond desire is now layd waste Truth of love in his stead plaste Honor guides you now, 'T'is true Cupid was desire, Fondly using wanton fire Therfor thus doth bowe, 3 Love's nott Love, that vainely flings Like a harmfull waspe that stings Therin I did miss Desire should nott bee stil'd love Butt with honors wings to move Bright love tells us this, 4 Honor like the brightest morne Shines while clowded love is worne And consum'd to dust, Like faire flowrs long beeing pulld Dy, and wither if nott culld Slightest like the wurst, Butt lett harts, and voices singe Honor's Cupids just borne kinge. [Come lusty gamesters of the sea] Come lusty gamesters of the sea Billowes, waves, and winds, Like to most lovers make your plea Say love all combinds; Lett nott Dian rule your sprites, Her pale face shuns all delights, Venus was borne, of the sea foame Queene of love is she Like her sweet pleasant phantisies roame, This Varietie; Juno yett a firme wife is, Soe may I bee in my blis, Pallas is yett a fierce, sterne lass, Wisdome doth profess, Ceares a hous-wife I soone pass, Lovers I express; Venus, my deere sea borne Queene, Gives mee pleasures still unseene, And you faire starry sky, beeholde Venus mee commaunds, That by noe meanes love should grow colde Butt blowe the fire brands; Soll's best heat must fill our vaines, Thes are true loves highest straines. [This night the Moone eclipsed was] This night the Moone eclipsed was Alas, Butt quickly she did brightlier shine Devine, Prognosticating by sweet raine That all things showld bee cleere againe, Sweet raine foretells us good to growe, And flowe, Coole drops sweet moisture, flowers bring To spring, Which fruict brings forthe, and soe shall wee Live hopefully all good to see, Butt in this time the sun is loste And crost, Thought in Antipides nott quite beereft Nor left, Butt in just course shall come againe, And with pure light both shine, and raigne. [Stay holy fires] Stay holy fires Of my desires Flame nott soe fast; My loves butt young From bud new sprunge Scarce knowes loves taste, Flames showld nott rise Till sacrifies Were reddy made; A love scarce greene Was never seene In withring shade, Stray till 't'is blowne If then orethrowne With curst denyes; Poore hart swell'out Send flames about With murdering eyes, Summon all men To Court agen Wher loves inthround, If they persist And smiles resist, While chast love is scornd, Then spoile their harts With fierce lovs darts, And with that store Of harts which shakes Make martir stakes Still framing more, Then with thos eyes Wher all truth lies A blaze of fire frame, As Heccatombbe For victors doombe To true loves name, Soe holy fires Of my desirs May rise, and flame Pheanix for truth Consum'de in youth Burnt to loves fame. [Were ever eyes of such devinitie] [1] Were ever eyes of such devinitie Devine? Noe they are of the Gods And soe have ods, Of the Gods? Noe, more of Eternitie; They are blew, sure they are then heavens sky Firmly Kings they rule and commaund, Motives of government doe ly To their imply Readely And soe att mercy stand, 2 Bee they nott two suns, most shiningly Beaming? Noe they are meators rare Without compare, Meators noe? Thunderbolts killingly Were they of Gods, they would deale beningly Gently Two sunns were never seene Att once, devinitie Doth that deny Really Butt lightnings oft have binn, 3 Lightnings O noe, they are induring, And bright, are they nott Cupids eyes Falen from the skies While hee is doubly blinded in aluring? Shall I yett name them must, O then say You may They are of Gods, of eyes, Of the heavens, of ayre most bright, Of purest light, Fierce sight, Yett sweetest under skies. [Fierce love, alas yett lett mee rest] [1] Fierce love, alas yett lett mee rest, Beeholde my boyling brest: Lett mee butt slumber, if nott sleepe Continually to weepe Is too great a smart To a hart Transform'd like Niobé to watry powers Telling howers In drops of my misfortunes arte; 2 Cruell, alas, why doe thos eyes Rule of the heavenly skies Joye in my ruin? My poore streames Flumes can nott coole your beames For loves sacred fire Must aspire Transcendant to the highest powers Telling howers In flames of my consuming fire, 3 The Firmament may mee imbrace Ther wanderers may finde place Transform'd by love into a space Borowing of lovers trace Wher continuall faire Will tell ayre Wee destined by force, earth, water, ayre, fire Bred in ire May yett to evenings faire aspire, 4 Butt dull earth I see you contend Nott willing I assend, Give mee then fruicts of plenty heere True increase of beauties cheere, Why doe you create Such a bate To singe all harts, by such a fire And intire Consuming us to our last fate? [Beehold this sacred fire] [1] Beehold this sacred fire In waters curstest ire Remaines in mee Desdaining change to see As hee makes waters touch His prowd inclosing my desire And in his bosome keeps my fire While I lament too much, 2 This lampe inflamed with love Consumes nott yett doth move And spends the oyle Soe doe I waste in toile To clime to honors high Which with water, and the time Doth the flame make higher clime And soe I may rise nigh; 3 Butt while I heere admire Water, and flames conspire Nott yeeld to mee Yett cunningly agree Noe ease unto my burning smart Butt extinguish fyry rays The aulter for my loving bays To act his lastest part; 4 Time butt an attome is Limited by powers blis Of heavenly might Made by eternall right For heaven erelasting beeing Makes eternitie the name, And mee the attome of my flame, Consumed, and burnt by seeing. [Love lett mee live, ore lett mee dye] Love lett mee live, ore lett mee dye, Use mee nott wurse then poorest fly Who finds some comfort, while alone I live, and waste in moane; I have noe shrouding place from woe, The billowes beare my overthrowe, And sands they cover in disgrace Of my loves truest face. Wretch sayth the sea heer stay, and drowne: Can you nott feare her curstest frowne? Alas she chides us that you stay, After her just denay, She is the Goddesse sole of Love; How dare you mortall thus to move? Bow hart, and soule to her least frowne And sensur'd thus ly downe. [Love butt a phantesie light, and vaine] [1] Love butt a phantesie light, and vaine Fluttering butt in poorest braine, Birds in chimnies make a thunder Putting silly soules in wounder Soe doth this love, this all commaunder To a weake poore understander; 2 Slight him, and hee'le your servant bee, Adore him, you his slave must bee, Scorne him, O how hee will pray you, Please him, and hee'lle sure beetray you, Lett nott his faulshood bee esteemed Least your self bee disesteemed. 3 Crush nott your witts to place him high, A thought thing, never seene by eye, Implore nott heaven, nor deities They know too well his forgeries Nor saints by imprications move 'T'is butt the Idolatry of love. [Was I to blame to trust] [1] Was I to blame to trust Thy love like teares when t'is most just To judg of others by our owne? While mine From heads of love and faith did flow Yett fruictles ran, could I suspect that thine When in my hart each teare did write a line Showld have noe spring butt outward showe? 2 My love I never went In maske, which made mee confident That thine had binn love too, and noe disguise, Nott love put on, butt taken in, Nor like a scarfe to bee putt off which lies, Att choise to weare ore leave, butt when thine eyes Did weepe thy hart had bled within, 3 Butt as the guilfull raine The sky that weeps itt doth nott paine Butt weares the place wherein the drops doe fall Soe when thy clowdy lids impart Thos showers of subtill teares; which seeme to call Compassion when you doe nott grieve att all, You weepe them, butt they frett my hart, 4 Deere eyes I wrong'd nott you To thinke you were as faire, soe true; Why wowld you then yourselves in griefe attire With pitty to inlarge my smart When beauty had enough inflam'd desire And when you were even cumber'd with my fire? Why would you blowe the coales with art? 5 For was less fault to leave Then having left mee to deceave For well you might have my unworthe refused, Nor cowld I have of wronge complaind Butt since your scorne, you with deceipt confusd My undesert you have with teares excus'd And with the guilt your self have stained. [Lying upon the beach] [1] Lying upon the beach, Beelow mee on the sands, I saw within small reach A lady ly in bands, With armes across, and hands Infolded in thos twines, Wherby a true love shines And for loves triumph stands, 2 Alas, cride she, can love Beequeath mee noe small space Wher I may live, and love Butt run in ruins race? Nor yett to gaine deaths trace, You locks of his owne haire, Wittnes I still you beare In my harts deerest place, 3 Butt O faulse is his hart, Yett faithfull is his haire, Dead is his love, a pretty art If wee thes two compare. Haire once cutt off hath share With death, loves lyfe beeing fled, To shaddow haire is fled, Soe are my joys to care. 4 Unconstant man, yett deere Beehold thy haire outlive Thy faith, thy worthe, and cleere As thine eyes, which did drive Wrack to my hart, take back Thes reliques, lay the rack On shriveld harts, and cry Haire outlives Constancy. [Come deere, lett's waulke into this spring] [1] Come deere, lett's waulke into this spring Wher wee may heere the sweet birds sing And lett us leave this darcksum place Wher Cupid never yett had grace, For loves bright light Must us delight And Cupids fire Must still respire, And brightest showe in darckest night. 2 'T'is nott the shades can harbour love; Hee lives in highest spheares above, And from his beames gives worlds ther light, Hee raigning Crownd with sweets delight, In darknes spite Hee rules in light, For Cupids fire Must still respire And brightest show in dullest night, 3 Love doth nott dwell in colde fainte shade, Nor lurcks wher warme love growes to vade, Hee's perfect heat, and strives to move Wher equall flames with him showes love. In Coldes despite Hee rules in might For Cupids fire Must still aspire And pow'rfulst show in darckest night. [Most hapy memory bee ever blest] Most hapy memory bee ever blest Which thus brings into my most weary minde Joys past though others would them tortures finde, Butt I delighted was in them, though rest I never felt, soe was my soule distrest, Yett lov'd the fetters did mee slavelike binde, O love, what is thy force? Some say thou'rt blind, Noe thou canst see best, and can give ease best, Then grant my memery may with mee live, And darken nott my first, and deerest choise, From which though swervd, I in itt still rejoyse, Nor lett the fates from mee those phantsies drive, For though a secound love doth mee infolde, Non must the former from my soule unfolde. [Returne my thoughts, why fly you soe?] Returne my thoughts, why fly you soe? Sorrows may my good outgoe, Phantsie's butt phantasticks skill The soule alone hath onely will, Heathen people had their Gods Whom they implor'd to have the odds Of mortalls all, butt 't'would nott bee For Love was high'st inthron'd to see, Soe love of all things hath most sight, And noe thing more then love is light, Then Cupid take thy honor right: Thou'rt neither God, nor Earthly sprite.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SONGS FROM THE HUNTINGTON MANUSCRIPT OF Love's Victorie [You pleasant floury meade] You pleasant floury meade Which I did once well love Your pathes no more I'le tread Your pleasures noe more prove Your beauty more admire Your coulers more adore Nor gras with daintiest store Of sweets to breed desire; Walks once soe sought for now I shunn you for the darcke, Birds to whose song did bow My eares your notes nere mark; Brooke which soe pleasing was Upon whose banks I lay, And on my pipe did play Now, unreguarded pass; Meadowes, pathes, grass, flouers Walkes, birds, brooke, truly finde All prove butt as vaine shouers Wish'd wellcome els unkind: You once I loved best Butt love makes mee you leave By love I love deseave Joy's lost for lives unrest. [Joyfull pleasant spring] Joyfull pleasant spring Which comforts to us bring Flourish in your pride: Never lett decay Your delights alay Since joye is to you ti'de, Lett noe frost nor wind Your dainty coulers blind Butt rather cherish Your most pleasing sight Lett never winter bite Nor season perish. [O my eyes how do you lead] O my eyes how do you lead My poore hart thus forth to rang From the wounted course to strang Unknowne ways, and pathes to tread? Lett itt home returne againe Free untouch'd of gadding thought And your forces back bee brought To the ridding of my paine. Butt mine eyes if you deny This smale favor to my hart, And will force my thoughts to fly Know yett you governe butt your part. [When I doe see] When I doe see Thee, whitest thee Yea whiter then lambs wull, How doe I joy That thee injoy I shall with my hart full. Thy eyes do play Like goats with hay And skip lik kids flying From the sly fox Soe eye lids box Shutts up thy sights priing. Thy cheecks as red As okar spred On a fatted sheeps back, Thy paps are found As aples round, Noe prayses shall lack. [By a pleasant rivers side] By a pleasant rivers side Hart, and hopes on pleasures tide Might I see with in a bower Proudly drest with every floure Which the spring can to us lend Venus, and her loving freind. I upon her beauty gas'de, They mee seeing were amas'de, Till att last up stept a child In his face, nott actions mild; Fly away saide hee for sight Shall both breed, and kill delight. Come away, and follow me; I will lett thee beautys see. I obay'd him, then hee staid Hard besid a heav'nly maide When hee threw a flaming dart, And unkindly strooke my hart. [Love, and Reason once att warr] Love, and Reason once att warr Jove came downe to end the jarr; Cupid said love must have place Reason that itt was his grace. Jove then brought itt to this end: Reason should on love attend Love takes reason for his guid Reason can nott from love slide. This agreed, they pleasd did part Reason ruling Cupids dart Soe as sure love can nott miss Since that reason ruler is. [Cupid blessed bee thy might] Cupid blessed bee thy might, Lett thy triumph see noe night, Bee thou justly god of love Who thus can thy glory move, Harts obay to Cupids sway, Prinses non of you say nay; Eyes, lett him direct your way For without him you may stray; Hee your secrett thoughts can spy Beeing hid els from each eye; Lett your songs bee still of love, Write noe satirs which may prove Least offensive to his name; If you doe you will butt frame Words against your selves, and lines Wher his good, and your ill shines, Like him who doth sett a snare For a poore betrayed hare And that thing hee best doth love Lucklesly the snare doth prove; Love the king is of the mind, Please him, and hee will be kind; Cross him you see what doth com, Harmes which make your pleasures tomb; Then take heed, and make your blis In his favour, and soe miss Noe content, nor joy nor pease Butt in hapines increase. Love command your harts and eyes And injoy what pleasure tries; Cupid govern, and his care Guard your harts from all dispaire. [Silent woods with desarts shade] Silvesta: Silent woods with desarts shade Giving peace Wher all pleasures first ar made To increase, Give your favor to my mone Now my loving time is gone. Chastity my pleasure is Folly fled From hence now I seeke my blis Cross love dead, In your shadows I repose You then love I now have chose. Musella: Choise ill made were better left, Beeing cross Of such choise to bee bereft Were no loss, Chastity you thus commend Doth proceed butt from loves end. And if love the fountane was Of your fire Love must chastitie surpas In desire, Love lost bred your chastest thought Chastity by love is wrought. [Love thy powerfull hand withdraw] Love thy powerfull hand withdraw, All doe yeeld unto thy law; Rebells now thy subjects bee, Bound they are who late were free, Most confess thy power, and might, All harts yeeld unto thy right; Thoughts directed ar by thee, Souls doe strive thy joys to see; Pitty then, and mercy give Unto them wher you doe live; They your images doe prove, In them may you see great love; They your mirours, you theyr eye By which they true love doe spy. Cease awhile theyr cruell smarts And beehold theyr yeelding harts; Greater glory 'tis to save When that you a conquest have Then with tiranny to press Which still make the honor les; Gods doe prinses hands direct, Then to thes have some respect.</field>
   </doc>
</add>