<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Ravenscroft, Thomas, 1592-1635</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Ravenscroft, Thomas, 1592-1635</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">ravenscroft thomas 1592 1635</field>
      <field name="author_text">Ravenscroft, Thomas, 1592-1635</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_1.1813.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">1609</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:464293</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Pammelia ; Mvsicks Miscellanie. Or, Mixed Varietie of Pleasant Roundelayes, and delightfull Catches, of 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. Parts in one</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700</field>
      <field name="title_display">Pammelia ; Mvsicks Miscellanie. Or, Mixed Varietie of Pleasant Roundelayes, and delightfull Catches, of 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. Parts in one</field>
      <field name="title_facet">pammelia</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">pammelia</field>
      <field name="title_text">Pammelia ; Mvsicks Miscellanie. Or, Mixed Varietie of Pleasant Roundelayes, and delightfull Catches, of 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. Parts in one</field>
      <field name="year_display">1609</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1609</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1609</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464293&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:464293&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Ravenscroft, Thomas, 1592?-1635?&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;ravenscroft thomas 1592 1635 &lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Pammelia ; Mvsicks Miscellanie. Or, Mixed Varietie of Pleasant Roundelayes, and delightfull Catches, of 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. Parts in one&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;pammelia&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1609&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1609&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Ravenscroft, Thomas&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1592&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1635&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Pammelia&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Mvsicks Miscellanie. Or, Mixed Varietie of Pleasant Roundelayes, and delightfull Catches, of 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. Parts in one&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by William Barley, for R. B. and H. W. [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1609&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp3718&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;51 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern, 1500-1700&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Pammelia&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Mvsicks Miscellanie. Or, Mixed Varietie of Pleasant Roundelayes, and delightfull Catches, of 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. Parts in one&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 38 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted; Latin verse omitted; non-English verse omitted; music omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Songbooks.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">None so ordinarie as musicall, none so musical, as not to all, very pleasing and acceptable.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TO THE VVELL DISPOSED TO READE, AND to the merry disposed to Sing. The following poems are scored for music in the source text. Where poems are not stanzaic, no attempt has been made to reconstruct the metrical lines. Variations for different voices have been ignored. Repetition marks have been ignored.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Rounds or Catches of three Uoices. [1 Hey hoe, to the greene wood now let vs goe] Hey hoe, to the greene wood now let vs goe Hey hoe, to the greene wood now let vs goe, sing heaue and hoe, and there shall we find both bucke and Doe, sing heaue and hoe, the Hart the Hinde, and the little prety Roae sing heaue and hoe, Hey hoe. [2 O My fearefull dreames] O my fearefull dreames neuer forget shall I O my fearefull dreames neuer forget shall I, neuer forget shall I, me thought I heard a maiden child condemnd to die, whose name was Iesus. [3 Iolly shepheard] Iolly shepheard and vpon a hill as he sate Iolly shepheard and vpon a hill as he sate, so lowd he blew his little horne, and kept right well his gate: Earely in a morning, late in an Euening, and euer blew this little boy, so merily piping: Tere liter lo terli terlo, terli ter liter lo rer liter lo terli. Ioly shepheard. [4 Call in to service let vs ring] All in to seruice let vs ring, merily together All in to seruice let vs ring, merily together, ding dong ding dong Bell. [5 New Oysters] New Oysters, new Oysters New Oysters, new Oysters, new Oysters new, haue you any wood to cleaue haue you any wood to cleaue, what kitchin stuffe haue you maides what kitching stuffe haue you maides? New Oysters. [6 Oken leaves in the merry wood so wilde] Oken leaues in the merry wood so wilde Oken leaues in the merry wood so wilde, when will you grow green a, fayrest maid and thou be with child, lullaby maist. thou sing a, lulla lullaby lulla lulla lullaby lullaby maist thou sing a Oken leaues. [7 Now God bee with old Simeon] Now God bee with old Simeon Now God bee with old Simeon, for he made Cannes for many a one, and a good old man was he, And Iinkin was his Iorneyman, and hee could tipple of euery can, and thus he said to me, to whome drinke yon sir knaue, to you, then hey ho Iolly Iinkin, I spie a knaue in drinking, come trole the bole to me. [8 Well fare the Nightingale] Well fare the Nightingale Well fare the Nightingale, faire fall the Thrush cocke too, but foule faire the filthie bird that singeth Cuckow. [9 Follow me quickly] Follow me quickly, Iacke is a pretty boy Follow me quickly, Iacke is a pretty boy, round about, standing stout, singing ale in a bole, fala sol, la my dirry come dandy. [10 Now kisse the cup cosen with curtesie] Now kisse the cup cosen with curtesie Now kisse the cup cosen with curtesie, and drinke your part with a heart willingly, then so shall we all agree merily. [11 New oysters] New oysters, new walefleet oysters New oysters, new walefleet oysters, at a groat a pecke each oyster worth two pence, fetch vs bread and wine that we may eate, let vs loose no time with such good meat, a banquet for a prince. [12 All into seruice] All in to seruice, the belles toles All in to seruice, the belles toles, Al into seruice now ring they all in to seruice, Ding dong dong bell, ding dong bell. Cannon three parts in one, in the fift and ninth. [13 Hey downe a downe] Hey downe a downe, behold and see Hey downe a downe, behold and see, what song is this, or how many this bee, three parts in one: Sing all after mee with hey downe downe a downe downe a trole the berry drinke and be mery. Poems 14–18 are in Latin and have thus been omitted. [19 O Prayse the Lord ye that feare him] Prayse the Lord ye that feare him Prayse the Lord ye that feare him, magnifie him all yee seed of Iacob, and prayse him all yee seed of Israell. [20 The Nightingale] The Nightingale, the mery Nightingale, she sweetly sits and sings The Nightingale, the mery Nightingale, she sweetly sits and sings, and sings: The prety nimble Doe doth trip it to and fro, the stond horse kickes and flinges and flings, the Cuckow he doth flie from tree to tree: And merily through the woods cuckow, cuckow rings. [21 The old dogge] The old dogge, the iolly olde dogge as he lay in his denne The old dogge, the iolly olde dogge as he lay in his denne a Huffa, trohlo as he lay in his denne a. Buffa, trolito, as he lay in his denn a. [22 Ioan come kisse me now] Ioan come kisse me now Ioan come kisse me now, once againe for my loue, gentle Ione come kisse me now. [23 My Dame has in her hutch at home] My Dame has in her hutch at home My Dame has in her hutch at home, a little dog, hey dog hey. With a clog. [24 Goe no more to Brainford] Goe no more to Brainford, vnlesse you loue a Punke Goe no more to Brainford, vnlesse you loue a Punke, for that wicked sinnefull towne hath made me drunke, come follow me. [25 Dame lend me a loafe] Dame lend me a loafe from saturday to saturday Dame lend me a loafe from saturday to saturday And longer if you longer may, Dame lend me a loafe. [26 I am a thirst] I am a thirst, what should I say I am a thirst, what should I say, alasse I haue no money to pay, fill the pot Butler, fill, fill, for I will drinke with a good will. [27 There lies a pudding in the fire] There lies a pudding in the fire There lies a pudding in the fire, and my parte lies therein a: whome should I call in, O thy good fellowes and mine a. Call in, call in, O thy good fellows and mine a. [28 Hey downe a downe downe a behold and see] Hey downe a downe downe a behold and see Hey downe a downe downe a behold and see, good hostesse fill the pot for mee, and yet it is the first of three, this is the best ale belieue me, if ye will drinke more, then call me, Take and fill this pot yet once againe, we will for this time thus remaine, when this is spent fill pot againe, Hey downe. [29 What hap had I to marry a throw] 1 What hap had to marry a throw for she hath giuen me many blow, and how to please her alacke I doe not know. 2 From morne to euen her tongue neere lies, Sometime she braules, sometime she cries, Yet I can scarse keepe her tallants from my eyes. 3 If I goe abroad, and late come in, Sir knaue (saith she) where haue you beene, And doe I well or ill, she claps me on the skin,</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Rounds or Catches of foure Uoices. [30 Hey downe downe] Hey downe downe Hey downe downe hey d. d. d. a d. d. d. down heaue and ho, Rumbelo, follow me my sweet heart follow me where I goe Shall I goe walke the woods so wild, wandering here and there as I was once full sore beguild, what remedy though alas for loue I die with woe, Oft haue I ridden vpon my gray nag, and with his cut tayle he plaid the wag, and down he fell vpon his cragge, fa la re la, la ri dan dino. [31 Vt, re, me, fa, sol, la] Vt, re, me, fa, sol, la, Vt, re, me, fa, sol, la, la, sol, fa, me, re, vt. Hey downe downe hey down down a. My heart of gold as true as steele as I me leant vnto the bowres, but if my Lady loue me well, Lord so Robin lowres, heaue and hoe Rumbelo, hey trolo troly lo, hey troly trolly hey My Ladies gone to Canterbury, S. Thomas be her boote. Shee met with Kate of Malmsbury, why weepst thou maple roote: O sleepst thou or' wakst thon Ieffery, Cooke, the rost it burnes, turne round about about, O Frier how fares thy bandelow bandelow Frier, how fares thy Sandelow, Sandelow. Poems 32–44 are in Latin and have thus been omitted. [45 Lord of whome I doe depende] O Lord of whome I doe depende, beholde my carefull heart, And when thy will and pleasure is, Release mee of my smart. Thou seest my sorrowes what they are, my griefe is knowne to thee: And there is none that can remoue, or take the same from mee. But onely thou whose aide I craue, whose mercy still is prest: To ease all those that come to thee, for succour and for rest. [46 Attend my people and giue eare] Attend my people and giue eare, of ferly things I shall thee tell See that my words in mind thou beare, and to my precepts listen well. I am thy soueraigne Lord and God, which haue thee brought from carefull thrall: And eke reclaimde from Pharaohs rod, make thee no Gods on them to call. Nor fashioned forme of any thing, in heauen or earth to worshippe it: For I thy God by reuenging, with grieuous plagues this sinne will smite. [47 O Lord in thee is all my trust] [1] O Lord in thee is all my trust, Giue eare vnto my wofull crie, Refuse me not that am vniust, But bowing downe thy heauenly eye. 2 Behold how I doe still lament my sinnes wherein I doe offend, O Lord for them shall I be shent, sith thee to please I do entend. 3 No, no not so, thy will is bent, to deale with sinners in thine ire: But when in heart they shall repent, thou grantst with speed their iust desire. [48 O Lord turne not away thy face from him] [1] O Lord turne not away thy face from him That lieth prostrate, Lamenting sore his sinnefull life Before thy mercies gate, Which gate thou openest wide to those That doe lament their sinne, Shut not that gate against me Lord, But let me enter in. 2 And call me not to mine accounts how I haue liued here: For then I know right well O Lord, how vile I shall appeare. I need not to confesse my life I am sure thou canst tell, What I haue beene, and what I am, I know thou knowest it well. Poems 49–52 are in French and Latin, and have thus been omitted. [53 As I mee walked in a May Morning] [1] As I mee walked in a May Morning, I heard a birde sing Cuckow. As I mee walked in a May Morning, I heard a birde sing Cuckow. 2 From March till midst of June She sung this plesant tune She had more friends in towne Cuckow. 3 Shee nodded vp and downe, and swore all by her crowne, Shee had friends in the towne, Cuckow. 4 All you that married be, learne this song of me, So shall we not agree, Cuckow. 5 All young men in this throng, to marry that thinke it long, Come learne of me this song, Cuckow. [54 The white Henne shee cackles] The white Henne shee cackles and layes in the puddles The white Henne shee cackles and layes in the puddles, Sing hey cocke without a combe, cocke a dle luddle. [55 The winde blowes out of the west] The winde blowes out of the west The winde blowes out of the west, thou gentle Mariner a, looke to the loosse wel, beware the lee still, for deadly rockes doe now apeare a, looke to thy tacke, let bowling goe slacke, so shal wee scape them and goe cleare, Tarra tan tarra stir well thy course sirra, the wind waxeth large, the sheetes doe thou vear, goe fill the canne, giue vs some beare. Ile drinke thee Ile brinks thee my mates, what cheare? [56 Iacke boy] Iacke boy, ho boy newes, the cat is in the well Iacke boy, ho boy newes, the cat is in the well, let vs ring now for her knell, ding dong ding dong bell. [57 Blow thy horne thou iolly hunter] Blow thy horne thou iolly hunter Blow thy horne thou iolly hunter, thy hornes for to reuiue a, shew thy selfe a good huntsman whilst that thou art aliue a, that men may say and sing with thee, thou hast a merry life a, in pleasure all the day, and Venus mate to wise a. [58 Banbery Ale] Banbery Ale where where where Banbery Ale where where where, at the Blacke Smithes house, I would I were there. [59 A Miller would I be] A miller a miller, a miller would I be A miller a miller, a miller would I be, to learne his craft as well as he, by art to steale, by cunning to lie, to get a poling penny thereby. [60 Birch and greene holly] Birch and greene holly Birch and greene holly, birch and greene holly, if thou beast beaten boy, thanke thine owne folly. [61 The larke Linit and Nightingale] The Larke Linit and Nightingale to sing some say are best The Larke Linit and Nightingale to sing some say are best; yet merily sings little Robin, prety Robin with the red breast. [62 Trole trole the bole to me] Trole trole the bole to me Trole trole the bole to me, and I will trole the same again to thee, beginne now hold in now, for we must merry be as you see, be lusty so must we, Oh it is a braue thing for to passe away the spring with mirth and ioy to sing, Tan tan tan tara tant tant, all a flant braue boyvs, what ioy is this to see, when friends so well agree. [63 Now Robin lend to me thy bow] 1 Now Robin lend to me thy bow, Sweet Robin lend to me thy bow, For I must now a hunting with my Lady goe With my sweet Lady goe. 2 And whether will thy Lady goe, Sweet Wilkin tell it vnto me And thou shalt haue my hawke, my hound, and eke my bow to wait on thy Lady. 3 My Lady will to Vppingham, to Vppingham forsooth will shee, And I my selfe appointed for to be the man, to wait on my Lady. 4 Adiew good Wilkin all be shrewde, thy hunting nothing pleaseth mee, But yet beware thy babling hounds stray not abroad, for angring of thy Lady. 5 My hounds shall be led in the line, so well I can assure it thee: Vnlesse by view of straine some persue I may find, to please my sweete Lady. 6 With that the Lady shee came in, and wild them all for to agree: For honest hunting neuer was accounted sinne, nor neuer shall for me. [64 Farewell mine owne sweet heart] Farewell mine owne sweet heart Farewell mine owne sweet heart farewell whome I loue best since I must from my loue depart, adew my ioy and rest. [65 Fay mi, fa re la mi] Fay mi, fa re la mi Fay mi, fa re la mi, beginne my sonne and follow mee sing flat fa, me, so shall wee well agree, hey tro lo ly lo ly lo, hold fast good son with hey tro lily lo tro lo ly, O sing this once again lustily. [66 Mvsing musing mine owne selfe all alone] Mvsing musing mine owne selfe all alone Mvsing musing mine owne selfe all alone, I heard a maid I heard a maid making great mone with sobs and sighes, &amp; many a grieuous moan, for that for that for that her maiden head was gone. [67 To Portsmouth] To Portsmouth it is a gallant towne To Portsmouth it is a gallant towne, and there wee will haue a quart of wine with a nutmeg browne, diddle downe. The gallant shippe, the Mermaid, the Lion hanging stout, did make vs to spend there our sixeteen pence all out. [68 Come drinke to mee] Come drinke to mee Come drinke to mee, and I will drinke to thee to thee, and then shall we full well agree. I haue loued the iolly tankerd full seuen winters and more, I loude it so long till that I went vpon the score, he that loues not the tankerd is no honest man. and he is no right souldier that loues not the can: tappe the canikin, tosse the Canikin, trole the canikin turne the canikin, hold good sonne and fill vs a fresh can, that wee may quaffe it round about from man to man. [69 Lets haue a peale for Iohn Cookes soule] Lets haue a peale for Iohn Cookes soule Lets haue a peale for Iohn Cookes soule, for he was an honest man with belles all in an order, the cruse with the blacke bole. the tankard likewise with the can, and I my owne selfe will ring the treble bell, and drinke to you euery one stand fast now my mates, ring merily and well till all this good ale is gon. [70 Sing we this roundelay merily my mate] Sing we this roundelay merily my mate Sing we this roundelay merily my mate, ill may he thriue that doth vs hate, Sing we this roundelay merily each one, take care who will for ile take none. [71 Vt re mi fa mi re vt] Vt re mi fa mi re vt Vt re mi fa mi re vt, hey derry derry sing and be merry, quando veni quando cœli, whip little Dauids bome, bome.Bome. Bome, Bome. [72 Lady come down] Lady come down and see Lady come down and see the Cat sits in the Plumtree. [73 Loue, loue sweet loue for euermore] Loue, loue sweet loue for euermore Loue, loue sweet loue for euermore farewell to thee, for fortune hath deceiued me. Fortune my foe, most contrary hath wrought me this misery, but yet my loue, my sweet loue farewell to thee, farewell to thee. 74 A Round of three Country dances in one. Sing after fellows, as you heare me Basse or Ground. Sing after fellows, as you heare me, a toy that seldome is seene a: three country dances in one to be a prety conceit as I weene a. Tenor. Robin Hood Robin Hood said little Iohn, come dance before the Queene a. In a redde Petticote and a greene iacket, a white hose and a green a. Cantus. Now foote it as I do, Tomboy Tom, now foot it as I doe Swithen a, And Hicke thou must tricke it all alone, till Robin come leaping in betweene a. Medius. The crampe is in my purse full sore, no money will bide there in a, and if I had some salue therefore, O lightly then would I sing a, hey hoe the Crampe a, hey hoe the Crampe a, hey hoe the crampe a the crampe a.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Rounds or Catches of fiue Uoices. [75 Come follow me merily my mates] Come follow me merily my mates Come follow me merily my mates, lets all agree and make no faults. Take heed of time, tune and eare, time, tune and eare, And then without all doubt, wee need not feare to sing this catch throughout: Malkin was a country maid, a country maid tricke and trim, tricke and trim as she might be, she would needes to the Court shee said to sell milke and firmenty, hey hoe, haue with you now to Westminster, but before you come there, because the way is farre some prety talke lets heare. Adew you dainty dames, goe whether you will for me, you are the very same I tooke you for to be. [76 White wine and suger] White wine and suger is good drinke for mee White wine and suger is good drinke for mee, for so said Parson Brat, but Gough saide nay to that, for hee loued Malmesie. white wine. Poems 77–82 are in Latin, and have thus been omitted. [83 Sing you now after me] Sing you now after me Sing you now after me, and as I sing sing yee, we well agree, fiue parts in vnity, ding dong, ding dong, ding dong, ding dong bell. [84 Inkin the iester] Inkin the iester was wont to make glee Inkin the iester was wont to make glee with Iaruis the Iugler till angry was he, then Wilkin the Wiseman did wisely foresee, that Iugler and Iester should gently agree, hey down, d. d. did down derie d. d. d. d. down, d. [85 Hey ho no body at home] Hey ho no body at home Hey ho no body at home, me ate nor drinke nor money haue I none, fill the pot Eadie. [86 Vt, re, mi, fa, sol, la, la, fa, fa, mi, re vt] Vt, re, mi, fa, sol, la Vt, re, mi, fa, sol, la, la, fa, fa, mi, re vt. Hey down a d. a dising you three after me and follow me my lads my lads and we will merry be fa, la, la, la, la, fa, la, fa, la, la. la well song before hold fast hold fast betime, take heed you misse not nor breake the time, nor for if thou misse the Basle a note theres nere a man can sing a lot. [87 Let Lobcocke leaue his wife at home] Let Lobcocke leaue his wife at home Let Lobcocke leaue his wife at home with lustie Iinkin that clownish Groome, with tighee, with two alone, with ta ha farewell my kind moame, yet must we looke kindly when Lobcocke comes home. [88 Vt, re, mi, fa, sol, la, la, sol, fa, mi, re, vt] Vt, re, mi, fa, sol, la Vt, re, mi, fa, sol, la, la, sol, fa, mi, re, vt. Hey downe, down, down, down, sing you now after me, la, mi, sol, re, fa, so shall we well agree, take heede to your time, and rest as you find, the round and the square must be tunde in their kind: O well sung my Lads I say, we are as good by night as by day. la, mi, sol, re, fa, let vs be merry, heare so long time as you may, for time truely passeth away, hey ho, hey ho, hey ho, hey ho, hey ho. [89 Keepe well your ray my lads] Keepe well your ray my lads Keepe well your ray my lads, and shew your selues like men, this day our foes shall feele our forces once againe, now let the trumpet sound their deadly blast, tantarra, tantarra, tantarra tan, stand to it first and last, with tautara ra. see hey, they flie full fast. [90 How should I sing wel] How should I sing wel and not be weary How should I sing wel and not be weary, and Since we lacke money to make vs merry, to make vs merry, since we lacke money to make vs merry, since we lacke money to make vs merry.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Rounds or Catches of sixe Uoices. [91 Ioy in the gates of Ierusalem] Ioy in the gates of Ierusalem Ioy in the gates of Ierusalem, peace bee in Sion. Poems 92–94 are in Latin and have thus been omitted. [95 Now thanked bee the great God Pan] Now thanked bee the great God Pan Now thanked bee the great God Pan, which thus preserues my loued life, and thanked be I that keepe a man who ended hath this bloudy strife, for if my man must prayses haue, what then must I that keepe the knaue. Poem 96, the only Round for seven voices, is in Latin and has thus been omitted.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Rounds or Catches of Eight Voices. [97 Lets haue a peale for Iohn Cookes soule] Lets haue a peale for Iohn Cookes soule Lets haue a peale for Iohn Cookes soule for hee was a very very honest man, an honest man. Poem 98 is in Latin, and has thus been omitted.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">A Round or Catch for Nine voices. [99 Hey hoe what shall I say] Hey hoe what shall I say Hey hoe what shall I say, Sir Iohn hath carried my wife away, they were gone ere I wist, she will come when she list, hey trolly trolly lolly, come againe ho, hey.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">A Round or Catch for ten or eleuen voices. [100 Sing we now merily] Sing we now merily our purses be empty hey ho Sing we now merily our purses be empty hey ho, let them take care that list to spare for I will not doe so, who can sing so merry a note, as he that cannot change a groat, hey hoe trolly lolly loe, trolly lolly lo. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>