<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Montgomery, James, 1771-1854</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Montgomery, James, 1771-1854</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">montgomery james 1771 1854</field>
      <field name="author_text">Montgomery, James, 1771-1854</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1830's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.1282.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240352</field>
      <field name="date_text">1836</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466702</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The poet's portfolio</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The poet's portfolio</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poets portfolio</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poets portfolio</field>
      <field name="title_text">The poet's portfolio</field>
      <field name="year_display">1836</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1836</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1836</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466702&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466702&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Montgomery, James, 1771-1854&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;montgomery james 1771 1854&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The poet's portfolio&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poets portfolio&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1836&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1836&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Montgomery, James&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1771&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1854&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The poet's portfolio&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Longman, Rees, Orme, Brown, Green, &amp;amp; Longman&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1836&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp2723&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ix, 297 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The poet's portfolio&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 45 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Majority of verse reproduced elsewhere in The English Poetry Full-text Database; only unique items included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">“Fall'n feathers of a moulting wing, Which ne'er again may soar; Notes, sung in Autumn woods, where Spring Shall hear their sounds no more: Her voice and plume—the Bird renews; Man fails but once;—'tis in the tomb, His strength He mews.” A Page of Oblivion.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">AT HOME IN HEAVEN: I Thess. iv. 17. Part I. “For ever with the Lord!” —Amen; so let it be; Life from the dead is in that word, 'Tis immortality. Here in the body pent, Absent from Him I roam; Yet nightly pitch my moving tent A day's march nearer home. My Father's house on high, Home of my soul, how near, At times, to faith's foreseeing eye, Thy golden gates appear! Ah! then my spirit faints To reach the land I love, The bright inheritance of saints, Jerusalem above. Yet clouds will intervene, And all my prospect flies, Like Noah's dove, I flit between Rough seas and stormy skies. Anon the clouds dispart, The winds and waters cease, While sweetly o'er my gladden'd heart Expands the bow of peace. Beneath its glowing arch, Along the hallow'd ground, I see cherubic armies march, A camp of fire around. I hear at morn and even, At noon and midnight hour, The choral harmonies of heaven Earth's Babel-tongues o'erpower. Then, then I feel that He, (Remember'd or forgot,) The Lord is never far from me, Though I perceive Him not. Part II. In darkness as in light, Hidden alike from view, I sleep, I wake within his sight, Who looks existence through. From the dim hour of birth, Through every changing state Of mortal pilgrimage on earth, Till its appointed date; All that I am, have been, All that I yet may be, He sees at once, as He hath seen, And shall for ever see. How can I meet His eyes? Mine on the cross I cast, And own my life a Saviour's prize, Mercy from first to last. “For ever with the Lord!” —Father, if 'tis thy will, The promise of that faithful word, Even here to me fulfil. Be thou at my right hand, Then can I never fail; Uphold Thou me, and I shall stand, Fight, and I must prevail. So when my latest breath Shall rend the veil in twain, By death I shall escape from death, And life eternal gain. Knowing as I am known, How shall I love that word, And oft repeat before the throne, “For ever with the Lord!” Then though the soul enjoy Communion high and sweet, While worms this body must destroy, Both shall in glory meet. The trump of final doom Will speak the self-same word, And heaven's voice thunder through the tomb, “For ever with the Lord!” The tomb shall echo deep That death-awakening sound; The saints shall hear it in their sleep, And answer from the ground. Then upward as they fly, That resurrection-word Shall be their shout of victory, “For ever with the Lord!” That resurrection-word, That shout of victory, Once more,—“For ever with the Lord!” Amen; so let it be. HEAVEN IN PROSPECT. Palms of glory, raiment bright, Crowns that never fade away, Gird and deck the saints in light, Priests and kings and conquerors they. Yet the conquerors bring their palms To the Lamb amidst the throne, And proclaim in joyful psalms, Victory through his cross alone. Kings for harps their crowns resign, Crying, as they strike the chords, “Take the kingdom,—it is thine, King of kings and Lord of lords.” Round the altar, priests confess, If their robes are white as snow, 'Twas the Saviour's righteousness, And his blood that made them so. Who were these?—On earth they dwelt, Sinners once of Adam's race, Guilt, and fear, and suffering felt, But were saved by sovereign grace. They were mortal, too, like us; —Ah! when we, like them, shall die, May our souls, translated thus, Triumph, reign, and shine on high! GARDEN THOUGHTS, On occasion of a Christian assembly in the grounds of a gentleman at York, for the purpose of promoting Missions among the Heathen. In a garden—man was placed, Meet abode for innocence, With his Maker's image graced; —Sin crept in and drove him thence, Through the world, a wretch undone, Seeking rest, and finding none. In a garden—on that night, When our Saviour was betray'd, With what world-redeeming might, In his agony he pray'd! Till he drank the vengeance up, And with mercy fill'd the cup. In a garden—on the cross, When the spear his heart had riven, And for earth's primeval loss, Heaven's best ransom had been given, —Jesus rested from his woes, Jesus from the dead arose. Here, not Eden's bowers are found, Nor forlorn Gethsemane Nor that calm, sepulchral ground At the foot of Calvary; —Yet this scene may well recall Sweet remembrances of all. Emblem of the church below! Where the Spirit and the Word Fall like dews, like breezes blow, And the Lord God's voice is heard, Walking in the cool of day, While the world is far away:— Emblem of the church above! Where, as in their native clime, Midst the garden of his love, Rescued from the rage of time, Saints, as trees of life, shall stand, Planted by his own right hand! Round the fair enclosure here Flames no cherub's threatening sword; Ye who enter feel no fear: —Roof'd by heaven, with verdure floor'd, Breathing balm from blossoms gay, This be paradise to-day. Yet one moment meditate On our parents' banishment, When from Eden's closing gate, Hand in hand, they weeping went, Spikenard groves no more to dress, But a thorn-set wilderness. Then remember Him who laid Uncreated splendour by, Lower than the angels made, Fallen man to glorify, And from death beyond the grave Unto life immortal save. Think of Him,—your souls He sought, Wandering, never to return; Hath He found you?—At the thought Your glad hearts within you burn; Then your love like His extend, Be like him the sinner's friend. O'er Jerusalem He wept, Doom'd to perish;—can't you weep O'er a world, by Satan kept Dreaming in delirious sleep, Till the twinkle of an eye Wakes them in eternity? Ye, who smile in rosy youth, Glow with manhood, fade through years, Send the life, the light, the truth, To dead hearts, blind eyes, deaf ears, And your very pleasures make Charities for Jesus' sake. So shall gospel-glory run Round the globe, to every clime, Brighter than the circling sun, Hastening that millennial time, When the earth shall be restored As the garden of the Lord. TO MR. AND MRS. T. OF YORK, WITH THE FOREGOING STANZAS. Ye who own this quiet place, Here, like Enoch, walk with God; And, till summon'd hence, through grace, Tread the path your Saviour trod; Then to paradise on high, With the wings of angels fly. THE FIELD OF THE WORLD. Sow in the morn thy seed, At eve hold not thine hand; To doubt and fear give thou no heed, Broad-cast it o'er the land. Beside all waters sow, The highway furrows stock, Drop it where thorns and thistles grow, Scatter it on the rock. The good, the fruitful ground, Expect not here nor there; O'er hill and dale, by plots, 'tis found; Go forth, then, every where. Thou know'st not which may thrive, The late or early sown; Grace keeps the precious germs alive, When and wherever strown. And duly shall appear, In verdure, beauty, strength; The tender blade, the stalk, the ear, And the full corn at length. Thou canst not toil in vain; Cold, heat, and moist, and dry, Shall foster and mature the grain, For garners in the sky. Thence, when the glorious end, The day of God is come, The angel-reapers shall descend, And Heaven cry—“Harvest-home!” FAREWELL TO A MISSIONARY. Home, kindred, friends, and country,—these Are things with which we never part; From clime to clime, o'er land and seas, We bear them with us in our heart; And yet 'tis hard to feel resign'd, When they must all be left behind. But when the pilgrim's staff we take, And follow Christ from shore to shore, Gladly for Him we all forsake, Press on, and only look before; Though humbled nature mourns her loss, The spirit glories in the cross. It is no sin, like man, to weep, Even Jesus wept o'er Lazarus dead; Or yearn for home beyond the deep,— He had not where to lay his head; The patriot's tears will He condemn, Who grieved o'er lost Jerusalem? Take up your cross, and say—“Farewell:” Go forth without the camp to Him, Who left heaven's throne with men to dwell, Who died his murderers to redeem: Oh! tell his name in every ear, Doubt not,—the dead themselves will hear,— Hear, and come forth to life anew; —Then while the Gentile courts they fill, Shall not your Saviour's words stand true? Home, kindred, friends, and country still, In earth's last desert you shall find, Yet lose not those you left behind. AN AFTER-THOUGHT. I cannot call affliction sweet, And yet 't was good to bear; Affliction brought me to thy feet, And I found comfort there. My weaned soul was all resign'd To thy most gracious will; Oh! had I kept that better mind, Or been afflicted still! Where are the vows which then I vow'd, The joys which then I knew? Those vanish'd like the morning cloud, These like the early dew. Lord, grant me grace for every day, Whate'er my state may be; Through life, in death, with truth to say, “My God is all to me!” “LOVEST THOU ME?” John, xxi. 15–17. “Lovest thou me?” I hear my Saviour say: Would that my heart had power to answer—“Yea; Thou knowest all things, Lord, in heaven above, And earth beneath; Thou knowest that I love.” But 'tis not so; in word, in deed, in thought, I do not, cannot love thee as I ought; Thy love must give that power, thy love alone; There's nothing worthy of thee but thine own; Lord, with the love wherewith thou lovedst me, Reflected on thyself, I would love thee. “THE PRISONER OF THE LORD.” A SABBATH HYMN FOR A SICK CHAMBER. Thousands, O Lord of Hosts! this day, Around thine altar meet; And tens of thousands throng to pay Their homage at thy feet. They see thy power and glory there, As I have seen them too; They read, they hear, they join in prayer, As I was wont to do. They sing Thy deeds, as I have sung, In sweet and solemn lays; Were I among them, my glad tongue Might learn new themes of praise. For Thou art in their midst, to teach, When on Thy name they call; And Thou hast blessings, Lord, for each, Hast blessings, Lord, for all. I, of such fellowship bereft, In spirit turn to Thee; Oh! hast Thou not a blessing left, A blessing, Lord, for me? The dew lies thick on all the ground, Shall my poor fleece be dry? The manna rains from heaven around, Shall I of hunger die? Behold thy prisoner;—loose my bands, If 'tis thy gracious will; If not,—contented in thine hands, Behold thy prisoner still! I may not to thy courts repair, Yet here thou surely art; Lord, consecrate a house of prayer In my surrender'd heart. To faith reveal the things unseen, To hope, the joys untold; Let love, without a veil between, Thy glory now behold. Oh! make thy face on me to shine, That doubt and fear may cease; Lift up thy countenance benign On me,—and give me peace. THE LOT OF THE RIGHTEOUS. “We know that all things work together for good to them that love God.” —Rom. viii. 28. Yea—“all things work together for their good!” How can this glorious truth be understood? 'Tis like Jehovah's throne, where marvellous light Hides in thick darkness from created sight: The first-born seraph, trembling while he sings, Views its veil'd lustre through his shadowing wings; Or, if he meets, by unexpected grace, The beatific vision, face to face, Shrinks from perfection which no eye can see, Entranced in the abyss of Deity. Yea,—“all things work together for their good!” How shall the mystery be understood? From man's primeval curse are these set free, Sin slain, death swallow'd up in victory? The body from corruption so refined, 'Tis but the immortal vesture of the mind? The mind from folly so to wisdom won, 'Tis a pure sunbeam of the eternal sun? Ah! no, no;—all that troubles life is theirs, Hard toil, sharp suffering, slow-consuming cares; To mourn and weep; want raiment, food, and rest, Brood o'er the unutter'd anguish of the breast; To love, to hope, desire, possess, in vain; Wrestle with weakness, weariness, and pain, Struggle with fell disease from breath to breath, And every moment die a moment's death. This is their portion, this the common lot; But they have sorrows which the world knows not; —Their conflicts with that world, its fair, false joys, Ensnaring riches and delusive toys, Its love, its hatred; its neglect and scorn; With self-abhorrence harder to be borne; The pangs of conscience, when God's holy law, Through Sinai's thunders, strikes them dumb with awe; Passions disorder'd, when insane desires Blow the rank embers of unhallow'd fires; Evils that lurk in ambush at the heart, And shoot their arrows thence through every part; Harsh roots of bitterness, light seeds of sin, Oft springing up and stirring strife within; Pride, like the serpent, vaunting to deceive, As with his subtilty beguiling Eve; Ambition, like the great red dragon, hurl'd, Sheer from heaven's battlements to this low world, Boundless in rage, as limited in power, Ramping abroad, and roaring to devour: —These, which blithe worldlings laugh at and contemn, Are worse than famine, sword, and fire to them. Nor these alone, for neither few nor small The trials rising from their holy call: —The Spirit's searching, proving, cleansing flames; Duty's demands, the Gospel's sovereign claims; Stern self-denial counting all things loss For Christ, and daily taking up the cross; The broken heart, or heart that will not break, That aches not, or that cannot cease to ache; Doubts and misgivings, lest when storms are past, They make sad shipwreck of the faith at last: —These, and a thousand forms of fear and shame, Bosom-temptations, that have not a name, But have a nature, felt through flesh and bone, Through soul and spirit,—felt by them alone; —These, these the Christian pilgrims' sore distress, Like thorns and briars of the wilderness; These keep them humble, keep them in the path, As those that flee from everlasting wrath. Yet, while their hearts and hopes are fix'd above, As those who lean on everlasting love, On faithfulness, which, though heaven's pillars bend, And earth's base fail, uphold them to the end;— By them, by them alone 'tis understood, How all things work together for their good. Wouldst thou too understand?—behold I show The perfect way,—Love God, and thou shalt know. A BENEDICTION FOR A BABY. What blessing shall I ask for thee, In the sweet dawn of infancy? —That, which our Saviour, at his birth, Brought down with Him from heaven to earth. What next, in childhood's April years Of sunbeam-smiles and rainbow-tears? —That, which in Him all eyes might trace, To grow in wisdom and in grace. What in the wayward path of youth, Where falsehood walks abroad as truth? —By that good spirit to be led, Which John saw resting on his head. What, in temptation's wilderness, When wants assail, and fears oppress? —To wield like Him the Scripture-sword, And vanquish Satan by “the word.” What, in the labour, pain, and strife, Combats and cares of daily life? —In his cross-bearing steps to tread, Who had not where to lay his head. What, in the agony of heart, When foes rush in, and friends depart? —To pray like Him, the Holy One, “Father, thy will, not mine, be done.” What, in the bitterness of death, When the last sigh cuts the last breath? —Like Him your spirit to commend, And up to paradise ascend. What in the grave, and in that hour, When even the grave shall lose its power? —Like Him, your rest awhile to take; Then at the trumpet's sound awake, Him as He is in heaven to see, And as He is, yourself to be. “OCCUPY TILL I COME.” Luke, xix. 13. ON THE DEATH OF THE LATE JOSEPH BUTTERWORTH, ESQ. AN EXEMPLARY CHRISTIAN, PATRIOT, AND PHILANTHROPIST. “He was a burning and a shining light:” —And is he now eclipsed in hopeless night? No; faith beholds him near the sapphire throne, Shining more bright than e'er on earth he shone; While, where created splendour all looks dim, Heaven's host are glorifying God in him. If faith's enraptured vision now be true, And things invisible stand forth to view, Though eye to eye the' unbodied soul can see, Self-lost amidst unclouded Deity, He chooses, rather than a seraph's seat, The lowest place at his Redeemer's feet; And, with the' eternal weight of glory prest, Turns even in paradise to Christ for rest. Come we who once beheld his noontide blaze, And hid before him our diminish'd rays; Since his translation to a higher sphere, We may, we must by our own light appear; When sun and moon their greater beams resign, The stars come out; they cannot choose but shine; With force like his all eyes we cannot strike, We may not equal him, but may be like: Nor let the meanest think his lamp too dim, In a dark world the Lord hath need of him; By feeble instruments in providence, God is well pleased his bounties to dispense: In his economy of grace the same; —The weakest are almighty in his name. What though the great, the good, the glorious fall, He reigns whose kingdom ruleth over all. —Talk not of talents;—what hast thou to do? Thy duty, be thy portion five or two; Talk not of talents;—is thy duty done? Thou hadst sufficient, were they ten or one. Lord, what my talents are I cannot tell, Till thou shalt give me grace to use them well: That grace impart, the bliss will then be mine, But all the power and all the glory thine. EVENING SONG. FOR THE SABBATH DAY. Millions within thy courts have met, Millions this day before thee bow'd; Their faces Zion-ward were set, Vows with their lips to thee they vow'd: But Thou, soul-searching God! hast known The hearts of all that bent the knee, And hast accepted those alone, In spirit and truth that worshipp'd Thee. People of many a tribe and tongue, Men of strange colours, climates, lands, Have heard thy truth, thy glory sung, And offer'd prayer with holy hands. Still, as the light of morning broke O'er island, continent, or deep, Thy far-spread family awoke, Sabbath all round the world to keep. From east to west, the sun survey'd, From north to south, adoring throngs; And still, where evening stretch'd her shade, The stars came forth to hear their songs. Harmonious as the winds and seas, In halcyon hours, when storms are flown, Arose earth's Babel-languages, In pure accordance to thy throne. Not angel-trumpets sound more clear, Not elders' harps, nor seraphs' lays, Yield sweeter music to thine ear Than humble prayer and thankful praise. And not a prayer, a tear, a sigh, Hath fail'd this day some suit to gain: —To those in trouble Thou wert nigh; Not one hath sought thy face in vain. Thy poor were bountifully fed, Thy chasten'd sons have kiss'd the rod, Thy mourners have been comforted, The pure in heart have seen their God. Yet one prayer more;—and be it one, In which both heaven and earth accord; —Fulfil thy promise to thy Son, Let all that breathe call Jesus Lord! OUR SAVIOUR'S PRAYERS. In these stanzas the Scripture-quotations are from those passages to which direct reference is intended in the lines themselves rather than to the corresponding accounts of the same transactions by others of the sacred historians. Preamble. High Priest for sinners, Jesus, Lord! Whom as a man of griefs I see, Thy prayers on earth while I record, If still in heaven thou pray'st for me, My soul for thy soul's travail claim; I seek salvation in thy name. Part I. Baptized as for the dead he rose, With prayer, from Jordan's hallow'd flood; Ere long, by persecuting foes, To be baptized in his own blood: The Father's voice proclaim'd the Son, The Spirit witness'd;—these are one. Luke, iii. 21, 22. Early he rose ere dawn of day, Mark, i. 35. And to a desert place withdrew, There was he wont to watch and pray, Until his locks were wet with dew, And birds below, and beams above, Had warn'd him thence to works of love. At evening when his toils were o'er, He sent the multitudes away, And on the mountain or the shore, All night remain'd alone to pray, Luke, vi. 12. Till o'er his head the stars grew dim: —When was the hour of rest for him? In field or city when he taught, Mark, viii. 12.Oft went his spirit forth in sighs; And when his mightiest deeds were wrought, Mark, vii. 34.To heaven he lifted up his eyes; He pray'd at Lazarus' grave, and shed John, xi. 41–43.Tears, with the word that waked the dead. When mothers brought their babes, he took Matt. xix. 13.The lambs into his arms, and pray'd; On Tabor, his transfigured look, Luke, ix. 28, 29.While praying, turn'd the sun to shade, And forms, too pure for human sight, Grew visible amidst his light. “O Father! save me from this hour, Yet for this hour to earth I came:” He pray'd in weakness; then with power Cried, “Father! glorify thy name:” “I have,” a voice from heaven replied, “And still it shall be glorified.” John, xii. 28. Part II. For Peter, bold in speech and brave John, xviii. 10 In act, yet in temptation frail, (As once he proved him on the wave,) Matt. xiv. 31. He pray'd lest his weak faith should fail; Luke, xxii. 32. And when by Satan's snare enthrall'd, His eye the wanderer recall'd. Luke, xxii. 61. Amidst his mournful family, Who soon must see his face no more, With what divine discourse did he Strength to their fainting souls restore! Then pray'd for all his people:—where Have words recorded such a prayer? John, xvii. Heb. v. 7.Next, with strong cries and bitter tears, Thrice hallow'd he that doleful ground, Where, trembling with mysterious fears, His sweat like blood-drops fell around, And being in an agony, Luke, xxii. 44.He prayèd yet more earnestly. Here oft in spirit let me kneel, Share in the speechless griefs I see, And while he felt what I should feel, Feel all his power of love to me Break my hard heart, and grace supply, For him who died for me to die. Stretch'd on the ignominious tree For those, whose hands had nail'd him there, Who stood and mock'd his misery, Luke, xxiii. 34.He offer'd up his latest prayer; Then with the voice of victory cried, “'Tis finish'd,” bow'd his head and died. Then all his prayers were answer'd;—all The fruits of his soul's travail gain'd; The cup of wormwood and of gall Down to the dregs his lips had drain'd; Accomplish'd was the eternal plan, He tasted death for every man. Now by the throne of God he stands, Aloft the golden censer bears, And offers, with high priestly hands, Pure incense with his people's prayers: Heb. vii. 25. Well pleased the Father eyes the Son, And says to each request, “'Tis done.”</field>
   </doc>
</add>