<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Hayes, Alfred, 1857-1936</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Hayes, Alfred, 1857-1936</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">hayes alfred 1857 1936</field>
      <field name="author_text">Hayes, Alfred, 1857-1936</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1910's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.0227.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">1911</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466072</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Cup of Quietness ; By Alfred Hayes</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Cup of Quietness ; By Alfred Hayes</field>
      <field name="title_facet">cup of quietness</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">cup of quietness</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Cup of Quietness ; By Alfred Hayes</field>
      <field name="year_display">1911</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1911</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1911</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466072&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466072&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Hayes, Alfred, 1857-1936&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;hayes alfred 1857 1936&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Cup of Quietness ; By Alfred Hayes&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;cup of quietness&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1911&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1911&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Hayes, Alfred&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1857&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1936&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Cup of Quietness&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By Alfred Hayes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Methuen&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1911&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp1667&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;x, 61 p.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Cup of Quietness&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;By Alfred Hayes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 69 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TO ROBERT MICHAEL SIMON, Kt., M.D. IN GRATEFUL ACKNOWLEDGMENT OF A DEBT OF KINDNESS WHICH CAN NEVER BE REPAID PRELUDE ‘And, behold, the Lord passed by.’ When silent on the Mount of Song I wait until the Lord pass by, Not while the storm of thought is strong The Maker draweth nigh; Nor while, by pangs of earthquake torn, Faith's ancient rocks asunder roll, From inward agony is born The secret of the soul; When indignation's flash illumes Hell's darkness, and the heart is hot With fire that cleanses and consumes, The Master cometh not. But when through woods the whispered word Is passed, and in the breathing field The beat of Nature's heart is heard, Then is the Lord revealed. Let others seek a stormy sign; Not passion's trumpet is my choice; Content if rather it be mine To hear the still small voice. BROKEN MUSIC Again the strange delight, the strange distress, The wistful voice that calls from far away; Again the after-sense of loneliness, Of golden times turned grey. Solemn and lustreless the moon's full sphere Ascends; a star keeps virgin watch on high; The birch's lightest tress is pencilled clear Against the naked sky. A breath of God makes pure the heart, and fills Its secret places with a whispering; Through all the air a sudden sweetness thrills— The tremor of the Spring. The thrush's song throbs with it; all things take A swift significance, a pathos deep; The quickened spirit seems about to wake From life's oppressive sleep; Heights, that we long had struggled to achieve, Seem close at hand and simple to attain; The baffling mists of doubt dissolve, and leave The heavenly landmarks plain; The beating heart is heard of songs unsung, Faint echoes of some lost romance of youth, And fragments of an old forgotten tongue— The native speech of truth. The light that makes the sordid beautiful, The touch that turns our common clay to gold— Alas! 'tis gone, and leaves the world more dull, The darkened soul more cold. Ah! not with men abides the voice divine; All that our mortal ears avail to win Is broken music, wafted from the shrine Where none may enter in. ONE THING WANTING Not for the gift of strength that cannot tire, Not for a fuller, nobler, sphere of strife, Nor purer draughts of joy, do I desire An after life. Here 'tis no paltry warfare; if death ends The fight, then death is rest, and rest is gain; And life had moments that made large amends For all its pain. Nor do I greatly long to see unfurled The scroll of fate, the clouds dispelled from earth; The shadow and the mystery of the world Are half its worth. One boon alone I covet, here denied,— Commune of soul with soul, skill to remove The veils that keep our lives apart and hide The truth of love; To feel from heart to heart emotions pass, The deep content of spiritual embrace; To see no longer darkly through a glass, But face to face. Love is a hunger never here appeased, A question never answered; vainly speech Pursueth; long ere love's intent be seized, 'Tis out of reach. I fear no disenchantment; I would prove That here things seem less precious than they are; My faith is, that the hearts of those I love Are greater far Than thought can comprehend, or tongue express; If death reveal love's truth, then I rejoice To die; meanwhile a silent wistfulness Is love's best voice. THE AGE OF IRON Let faith and hope grown grey, Confusion and decay Mingle their tears, And let oblivion weave an ample shroud; The Age of Iron is faint to death and, bowed Beneath the burden of his hundred years, Sinketh on time's highway. Farewell!—of all the ages that have run, Most arrogant and swift, Most fraught with care; Behind thee cometh one Eager of aspect, who will dare Thy fallen load to lift Of dreams fulfilled, of hopes undone, Of triumph and despair. Gather the darkness round thee and depart, Worn brain and weary heart; Well hast thou striven, and unashamed may'st fare To that high senate where thy fathers brood O'er counsels of eternity, Travails and tribulations long gone by, And wonders unrevealed, Hate's frenzy healed, War vanquished, evil overcome with good, Christ risen, and man's accomplished brotherhood. Thy birth-cry was the crash Of thrones, the people's wrath; Dread and destruction o'er thy cradle hung; And reason's lightning flash Athwart thy doubtful path The shadow of a tottering system flung; Proudly thy manhood wore the bays Of bloodless conquests; yet thy riper days Saw not the prophet's promised life, The nations leagued in peaceful strife, But envious rivals, fearful of the clash Of arms that ache with pent-up power; And ever in thy dying ears hath rung The laugh of them that live but to devour, The cry of them that cower Beneath the yoke of greed and want's remorseless lash. Of what avail to tame the levin's speed, To hold the winds in leash and quell the waves, If health no more be labour's meed, If love be stifled, honour spurned, And beauty crushed in Mammon's blind stampede? What boots it to have turned The soil's dull serfs to nervous factory-slaves, If pain that stunts, if pleasure that depraves, Hurry the haggard millions to their graves? What gain to have been orphaned of our God, To know, when worms destroy Man's frame, his spirit lies beneath the sod, If soul thereby be sacrificed to flesh, If Christ be crucified each day afresh? What profits it to heap Hoard upon hoard in festering towns, and miss The pure sky and the live air's kiss, To weigh the stars and lack the wine of joy, Outstrip the storm and lose the balm of sleep? Gather the darkness round thee and depart, Hot brain and restless heart; We mourn thy death, but would not have thee stay; Yet go not all in tears, For through the incumbent gloom Of thy vast cares, thy tribulation sore, To watchful eyes at length appears The dim uprising of a clearer day; The shadows flee, and from the sealéd tomb Where Christ lies stark and cold The stone is slowly rolled; The living Christ will dwell with men once more, To fevered souls will tranquil strength restore, Will quicken as of yore The breathless clay, Appease the waves of strife, And pilot to the long-expected shore The labouring bark of human life, When we that grieve, with all that we deplore, Have passed away. Let them whose faith is fled, The dead, attend the dead; But ye whose hope is fresh, whose love is young, Go forth to greet the light That kindles yonder height, The dawn that seers have dreamed and poets sung; Nor falter if the splendours ye discern Wake but a weary smile in those Who muse how fair the sun arose Of their departing day, Who marched beneath its dazzling fire, And watched its setting glories burn To ashen grey; So, home returning from his toil, the sire Wearily smiles to see his children play. Poor emmets, to and fro we run, Rejoice and are afraid, While in the night of space sun beyond sun Doth flash awhile and fade; The ages come and go, But there abideth One Whom none hath made, From Whom all things proceed, To Whom they flow; Giver of breath, Taker of all that perisheth; Who, evermore persisting, hath no need For pause or speed; Who is the First and Last, To Whom there is no future and no past, Nor birth nor death. TO MY LITTLE DAUGHTER Sweet blossom, to my soul more dear Than snowdrop to the darkened heart Of winter; though with graver cheer And weightier load, Now that the rainbow dreams of youth depart, I take the road Which leads to that obscure defile Where all ways meet, thou, little maid, Dost all unconsciously beguile The tedious way With laughter, and my heavy toil dost aid With thy light play. My purest joy, my tenderest care And solace; ere God's deep designs Revealed thee, dreams of flowing hair And sunny eyes And wild-rose cheeks, a music of soft lines, Whose harmonies Should utter all the grace of life, Made hunger in my soul; but now Wonder and worship are at strife; The Maker's scheme Outshines my brightest vision; darling, thou Hast shamed my dream. I grudge the sorry years wherein I had thee not; my breathless love, In full pursuit, can scarcely win The fleeting charms Each day puts forth; so I would keep my dove Caged in my arms. O linger in the fairyland Of childhood; all too soon 'twill fade; Too soon illusion's magic wand Will break; too soon The dayspring's fresh enchantment, little maid, Will be high noon; Too readily thou wilt unlearn Thy lawless babble for the rule Of our harsh speech, wilt feel time's stern Old hand repress Thy overweening innocence, and school Each sweet excess. Yet would I not my bird's young wing Should stay its flight; thou canst but change From charm to charm, from childhood's Spring To girlhood's May; And I would learn thy beauty's utmost range; I only pray That I may live to see thee wear The rose of perfect womanhood; But lest wise Heaven deny my prayer, And I must go Before thy beauty's bud unfold, I would That thou shouldst know, In years to come, the watchful love I longed to give thee; so I twine This wreath, on some bright day to prove Haply a pride, In some dark hour a solace; sweet, 'tis thine, Whate'er betide. What though the long-deserted muse Be jealous that for thee my lyre Awakes, who art the dear excuse For many a dream Neglected?—Could the Muse herself desire A happier theme? And though thy wilful fancy preys On my scant leisure, thou art more Than poesy; thy sinless days Breathe more than song; To miss one lesson of the heavenly lore Were grievous wrong. Thou still hast taught me, since the dawn Of that May morning, when I stood Joy-stricken on the dew-drenched lawn, While all around The great bird-chorus gathered to a flood Of rapturous sound; And mingled my full heart with theirs, And, as the sun rose, sought again The cradled answer to my prayers, And met those eyes Untroubled yet by joy, undimmed by pain, So calm, so wise. Since that strange sunrise, summers three; Already 'mid thy smiles there hide Some pretty tricks of coquetry; Already gleams The coming glory of thy maiden pride; Soon will thy dreams Be moonlit with romance, the gold Of thy young head be stained with brown; Life's inmost petals will unfold, Till, made aware Of all thyself, thou 'lt find that beauty's crown Has many a care. Yes; in that perilous Spring-time Tremble to think what queenly power Thou hast in trust; so use thy prime That love's pursuit May prove a sacred quest; then shall life's flower Yield noble fruit. A traitress she to beauty's throne, Whose pride it is to see hearts torn With honest anguish, whilst her own Beats false and cold. The vulgar tinsel may'st thou ever scorn, And prize the gold. May Spring's first flush, the lark's first song Make wine of thy young blood; the moon Becalmed o'er autumn woods, the long Slow thunder-roll Of ocean, the heart-hush of summer noon Enchant thy soul; May sunrise be a festival, Sunset a prayer; the peaceful breast Of thy fair motherland enthrall Thy wakening sense; May it be thine to seek and hold the best With love intense. May flowers be thy familiar friends, The birds thy gossips, brook and breeze Thy playmates; Nature best defends From sordid cares, Puts guile and vanity to shame, and frees From worldly snares. This crowning grace may Heaven bestow— An eager hand, a ready tear, For others' need, for others' woe; So shalt thou move Encircled with a radiant atmosphere Of joy and love. A SOUTH-WESTER All night the bold wind, drenched With ocean's wine, Earth's boisterous libertine, Hath hustled the spent clouds and wrenched The mountain pine. The darkness gasps for breath, The great trees fall, Wildly the waters call From drowning dales; he rioteth More loud than all. The day dawns savagely; He doth not shun To meet the indignant sun, But laughs in heaven's white face to see The havoc done. He grasps the billow's mane; The mad sea-horse Bears him, without remorse, In arctic slumber to regain His squandered force. A SUNSET The day goes down In unfamiliar state; the distant town Dissolveth to a dream Of golden domes and silver spires; The sea becomes a lake of leaping fires, The shore one gleam Of liquid glory; veiled with crimson spray, The solid headlands seem Jewels alive with lights that pulse and play; Till purple gloom engulfs the sun's last beam; So dieth day. When love declines On death's horizon-bound, the world's harsh lines Relent; hope fading flings Her farewell splendour as a pall O'er life's storm-worn, forsaken strand; then all Familiar things Look strange; wild lights o'er memory's ocean move, And mystic glimmerings; The past assumes the colours of the dove, Till all grows dim, and darkness spreads her wings; So dieth love. MAY Fair maid, on whom all seasons wait With gifts of grace, the month is here That unto thee is consecrate— The girlhood of the year. Awake! for dewy-fingered May Hath gathered in her lap of green The cowslip's tribute gold, to pay To thee, her chosen queen. Since moonlight through thy casement stole, The beauty of thy sleep to see, The nightingale hath spent his soul In serenading thee. Now sunbeams to thy lattice troop, The solace of thy face to seek; Though soft the young beech-leaves, they droop With envy of thy cheek. By that red blossom of thy mouth The apple-bud was taught to bloom, And thence the flower-caressing South Hath stolen its perfume. To earth the bluebells bring the sky, Because with blue thine eyes are bright; In semblance of thy purity The lanes are clothed in white. Thou sufferest the maiden year To wear the mask of thee awhile; But, ah! thou canst not lend her, dear, The summer of thy smile. And yet one glory May doth boast Wherein all other glories meet— For this I honour her the most— She is thy namesake, sweet. SOLDIERS OF SPRING What makes young Spring so glad? He has put old Winter to flight With his soldiery brave and bright, Columns in purple clad, Companies dressed in white, Regiments eager and bold In armour of gold. By thousands from ambush teem The crocus-troops;—they have won The battle ere half begun; See how their breastplates gleam And their keen blades flash in the sun, Who wide his gates doth fling To the armies of Spring. TO URTICA Think not the sullen beauty of a brow Bedimmed, or music of light mockery, Or wild caprice of frolic maidenhood Can fret my soul, bright lady; Spring, I trow, Is not less winsome for her fitful eye, But doth command my knee in every mood. Not February's frank laugh and scornful frown, Nor flashing bravery of boisterous March, Nor cold-eyed April's petulance can chill My faith; I know that May, with white-thorn crown, Shall queen it 'neath the rainbow's triumph-arch, That June the rosy promise must fulfil; However masked, I know the year's young heart Beats true to that great impulse which gives birth To flower and song, bids the bare woods array Their limbs in splendour, bids the lark upstart To tell the sunbeams of the joy of earth, And all that makes the miracle of May. What though the needle quiver, and the wave Inconstant sway; yet well the seaman knows, Through sunless days and starless nights, his guide Is faithful; and though baffling gusts may rave, And thwarting currents vex his course, there flows Beneath his keel the strong and silent tide. Tumult may shake, and poignant discords rend The frame of Music; yet her inmost soul Keeps unperturbed its peace; rash chords may cry Against her law; yet all resolving blend In beauty, paying under one control Due homage to the rule of harmony. So unto thee, fair potentate, is paid Obeisance by thy rebel moods; they fling Charms at thy feet; and as bluff March puts forth The tender bud, so thou, impetuous maid, Art loving as the secret heart of Spring, And loyal as the needle to the North. HEPATICA Most welcome, while the meagre East Rebuffs the Spring, is thy brave face, Dear nursling of the Alps, and least Of all the windflower race. Ere crocus-blades defend their gold, Or woods are with thy kinsfolk white, Thou beckonest thy comrades bold, Snowdrop and aconite. Not Winter's tyranny can blanch Thy cheek, or bruise thy buds of silk;— Hast thou not heard the avalanche, And quaffed the glacier-milk? So to his face thou dost profess Thy faith in Spring, and dost outrun Thy very leaves in eagerness To hail the insurgent sun. A GUARDIAN ANGEL Ambassadress from heaven to earth, Priestess of all things pure and good, The meekness of whose maidenhood To Christ doth yet give birth; Could sickly sophistries confute Thine eyes' celestial eloquence, Weak man, the struggling slave of sense, Would lapse again to brute. When passion beckons, not remorse, Nor frown of stern philosophy, Nor thundered code of Sinai Avail to bar his course. But where the ways of men begin To slope toward hell, an angel stands, Whose silent lips and suppliant hands Persuade him more than sin. O thou that makest Springtime sweet, My love for thee is pure as prayer, My kneeling soul doth hardly dare To kiss thy gentle feet. Spirit of dawn, whose breath divine Doth bid the fiends of night depart, Accept the worship of a heart Whose holiest thought is thine; Nor deem my love idolatry, For surely if the Son of God Still walks the earth which once He trod, 'Tis hand in hand with thee. TO A COQUETTE Bright poison-flower, whereat who sips For love's pure honey vainly sighs; Hearing thee lie with those prim lips, Seeing thee stab with those keen eyes, Almost I would my fate were his Who blindly flings his burning heart At thy cold feet, so bitter 'tis To know thee for the thing thou art; To know what subtle snares infest Those trustful ways, what torments hide For captured victims in that breast, The marble home of heartless pride; To know an evil spirit works In looks that seem so sweetly shy, Beneath that cloak of kindness lurks The coward steel of cruelty. Those simple words, those modest wiles Are but the mask of proud desire; A harlot—thou dost sell thy smiles, With broken hearts of boys for hire; Thy soul's insatiate vanity Must evermore be freshly fed On bleeding youth; less guilty she Who barters loveliness for bread, Than thou, who, donning love's disguise To hide thy cruel lust, dost prey On honest hearts, and serpent-wise Dost only fascinate to slay. O gifted with a power above All powers, dost think God's bounteous will Gave it that thou might'st murder love, And, cat-like, torture ere thou kill? Down on thy knees, poor child, and pray Thy beauty may not long survive To swell the penance thou must pay If thou would'st save thy soul alive. POTPOURRI As roses, dreaming after death, Embalmed within some curious urn, Bewitch the air with subtle breath, Till garden-visions haunt the brain, The golden hours of love return, And bygone summers glow again; So when those rarer blossoms fade, That sun their glories on thy cheek, Their rich remembrance, beauteous maid, Enshrined within the fragrant heart Of some old-fashioned song, may speak To souls unborn how sweet thou wert. ON RECEIVING A PROSPECTUS OF THE SNOWDON SUMMIT RAILWAY AND HOTEL Unthrone him; let the crowd's horse-laughter flout Those solemn brows that commune with the sky; Let nothing great preserve its privacy; For, Snowdon once dishonoured, never doubt Ben Nevis soon shall hear the rabble shout Its last street-song, the vulgar hue and cry Shall desecrate Helvellyn's sanctuary, Scafell shall entertain a drunken rout. No more its calm their high seclusion lends, The fever of our restless life to heal; A people with the mountains would be friends, To whom their great reserve makes no appeal, Whom height provokes and solitude offends— A mob, that neither cares to climb or kneel. PASTEUR'S GRAVE No cypress-shadowed churchyard, nor the gloom Of haunted cloisters, doth immortalise The dust of him, whose patience proved more wise To save, than Death to slay. The busy loom Glancing with silk, the teeming herd, the bloom Of purpling vineyards, and the grateful eyes Of souls reprieved at Death's most dread assize, Shall make eternal gladness round his tomb. Not 'mid the dead should he be laid asleep Who wageth still with Death triumphant strife, Who sowed the good that centuries shall reap, And took its terror from the healer's knife; Defender of the living, he shall keep His slumber in the armoury of life. WASTWATER Recluse of lakes, whose dark tranquillity No season moves; not to that valley blest Where all that died of Wordsworth lies at rest, Nor where the grace of Derwent glideth by, Or Windermere receives the enamoured sky— Not unto these, but unto thy stern breast, And thine o'erclouded brows, the soul oppressed With sorrow's burden comes for sympathy. For thou dost hold thy solemn state apart From those familiar splendours; giants keep Their vigil o'er thy solitude; weird forms Of mist are gathered to thy troubled heart; Sadly the sunbeams on thy bosom sleep; Abode of gloom and congregated storms. GENTLE SHAKESPEARE As one who hears the tide of traffic roll Around the silent temple where he kneels, Hears it but heeds it not, and only feels The eternal harmonies enthral his soul; Even so thy master-music doth control The world's heart-wearying discordance, heals The rankling wounds which pride or passion deals, And makes the fever-stricken spirit whole. O gentle Shakespeare—for by that kind name Thy friends best knew thee—in these blatant days Of shriller voices, meaner minds, we bless The majesty of thine immortal fame, Thy power and wisdom win our fervent praise, But most of all we love thy gentleness. OUT OF THE DARKNESS How sorrowful o'er yonder shuddering meres The mountains bow their heads; no signs remain Of yesterday's brief gladness; winds complain And waters wail to Heaven, that hath no ears For Earth's repining; naught above appears But restless grey; the valley, blind with rain, Seemeth a sepulchre where joy lies slain, The hermitage of woe, the home of tears. So the storm-laden brows of Fate o'erhang Our troubled life; darkness and mystery Reward our pleading. Yet, we trust, above All doubt, all anguish—yea, the supreme pang Of death itself—abides the eternal sky, And sovereign influence of the sun of love. ENGLAND'S ANSWER (On a rumour of war with America)[Christmas, 1895] What frantic words are these from over sea? Shall we, whose fathers in one womb have lain, Disown our lineage, unearth again With sacrilegious hands the sword? Shall we, The nurselings of one mighty mother's knee, Invoke upon our heads the curse of Cain, Affront the sacred face of Peace, and stain With kindred blood the brows of Liberty? Brothers, not so! Our proudest sue to wear The favours of your pearls of maidenhood; Your cities boast our ancient names; we share One mother-tongue, profess one faith in God. Bone of our bone, flesh of our flesh, forbear! We love you, with a love as warm as blood. IN CANDORE DECUS Disarmed, but undefeated, low he lies Whose steadfast courage manfully upbore Honour's derided standard, 'mid the roar Of vulgar passions and vainglorious cries Of self-styled patriots. Not for him will rise The long-expected day which shall restore Her soul to England. That dear hope no more May cheer the sorrow in those wistful eyes. Yet is the sword unbroken that he drew; Though feebler arms must wield it, Heaven will bless The wilder brain, the weaker heart of youth, If only they who guard his cause indue The panoply he wore of righteousness, The stainless beauty of the soul of truth. JOHANN SEBASTIAN BACH (1685-1750) Not Alpine!—Himalayan is the range Of thy stupendous voice. Through every clime Of passion mounting, where the mists of time Girdle unconquered heights, above all change Of seasons, thou dost fling to Heaven thy strange Prodigious harmonies, that grandly chime In pauses of the storm of sound, sublime As thunder of descending avalange. Thine are the giant leaps, o'er monstrous chasms, From ledge to ledge; depths of abysmal gloom; Rending of stubborn rocks by lightning-spasms. Thine too the gently-sloping vales, where loom Soft forms, the rainbow weaves her frail phantasms, Butterflies toy, and fairy flowers bloom. Mid yonder pinnacles of ice, that hold Communion with the silent hosts of heaven, Where broods the eagle and where sleeps the levin, Where first alights the day's young dream of gold, There well the fountains, free and clear and cold, Of music's mightiest flood, its pathway riven By glacier-ploughs, till all its streams are driven To where the runes of ocean are unrolled. There is its power at large; the billows raise The pæan which the sons of morning sang; Deep in its bosom huge Behemoth plays, The tempest tears its breast with granite fang; Or, when the great tides slumber, placid bays Reflect the snow-clad mountains whence it sprang. Many the crownéd heads of music;—thou Of song's wide realms art emperor alone; No rival hath assailed that peerless throne, Such splendour shines upon no other brow; Poets before thy footstool pay their vow; Thou keep'st a state whereat proud kings fall prone, A majesty of music all thine own, A sway to which the laureled masters bow. To thee the lords of song ascribe their fame, For thee the chiming spheres attune their fires; To all the ends of earth thy glorious name Resounds, while high in heaven immortal lyres Salute thee, and the streets of gold acclaim Thy worth with plaudits of celestial choirs. KISSES As flame seeks flame to make one heart of fire, As music is most sweet When differing voices in one chord conspire, So lips of lovers meet; One burning mantle, woven of delight, Enfolds the girl and boy; Their secret fills the universe, their sight Reels with excess of joy; Their lips have learnt the spell that can extort Pure gold from clay; their kiss Lingers, till all eternity seems short To count their wealth of bliss; Life seems a store of pleasure never spent, Death but the price thereof, The world a picture of their own content, Limned by the Master, Love. Alas! that noon should drown morn's light and shade, Or beauty's bloom decay, That passion's altar-fire so soon should fade To ashes cold and grey. Care stablishes his dull dominion, kills Romance, and turns to stone Illusion's tender heart; and Duty fills Love's abdicated throne; Chiller the kiss that custom turns to give, Fainter and faltering The music grows, till Love, if yet he live, Has ceased, poor bird, to sing. Then bleak distrust, estrangement's formal kiss, The winter of neglect; Then barren years when lips no longer miss What lips no more expect; Till comes at last, to answer Love's despair, Death; and the faded eyes, No more to be averted, blankly stare; And love, too late, grows wise; Too late the pride that held their souls apart Is melted, and a flood Bursts from the frozen fountains of the heart, Bitter and hot as blood— O God! one moment grant ere all be o'er, Call back one struggling breath! O Pity! keep the warmth one moment more On the damp brow of death!— Ah! that the final unfelt kiss had power, With rain of ceaseless tears, To summon back one solitary hour Of all those wasted years! ELEGY Here sleeps the eager form I held so dear, Here lie the ruins of my iondest dreams; Often I seek the spot, for only here, When evening's eyes grow dim, The heart of sorrow slowlier beats, and seems Almost at rest with him. Here 'tis so simple; just one young life less, One sweet book closed; and all our weight of woe— What matters it to him?—our wakefulness Disturbeth not his sleep; Our pleadings touch him not; he doth not know Whether we smile or weep; Or, if he knows, no tidings hither come From that secluded land; if spirits grieve For mortal sorrows, they to us are dumb, As we to them are blind; Either they cannot reach us, or they leave All care of earth behind. Here only death is peace; around 'tis all One loud and senseless turmoil; nothing blends With death but death; no voice is musical, Earth's sweetest harmonies Are discord, and the skylark's song offends The silence where he lies. The city's distant roar, the wood-dove's note, Cursings and blessings, joy, and love, and strife Seem of some other world, unreal, remote; Death only seems to own A soul, and ceaseth not to mock at life Till here we meet alone; But here no rival energies dispute Death's lordship; therefore gracious grows his mien And merciful; love's rebel mouth is mute; Grief's passionate storm is spent, And sinketh to a sadness more serene Than joy's short-lived content; For death has done his worst, and nothing now Remains to fear; the wistful dreams which lay In those deep eyes, the candour of that brow, The hopes which had their birth In that warm heart, can never know decay, Or take the taint of earth. Rapt in a moment from a world of flowers And song and sunshine, May at her sweet best, He will not taste the misery that sours Love's cup at last, nor wake To find hope's promise false, nor shrink from rest Because dull day will break; Tears will not rise at sight of Spring's young green, Nor all that gave delight be over-grown With sad remembrances, nor each dear scene Be haunted by regret, Till old age turn the weary heart to stone, And life's pale planet set; The swiftness of his joy will never tire; Ah! well for him!—better to be uptorn In Springtime's golden leaf, with love's pure fire Glowing in every vein, Than, branch by branch, to rot and fall, outworn With labour, grief, and pain. For him 'tis well indeed; but we, who still Must drain the cup of sorrow to the lees, Pine for the impulse of his ardent will, Need his fresh strength to brace Our weakness; nor can faith or hope appease The hunger for his face. For us remain the fever and the fray. Whether he simply sleeps, or quits him well In some diviner conflict, who shall say? We trust love doth not die, But only know him gone, and cannot tell Whither he went, or why. To fight our best, and take no count of death— This high command is all our guidance here; And how and when each soldier perisheth Must rest with Him Who plans The battle; to what issue, in what sphere, Is God's concern, not man's. Yet in the pauses of life's bitter stress, For those whose autumn sky was overcast, 'Twas good to bask in love's young happiness; Alas! the joy he lent To poorer lives is like a summer past; That treasure too is spent. O all bright things that knew him not, be glad; O birds that tune your love-notes o'er his grave, Sing sweeter still; he would not wish you sad; Fling your full hearts across The silence of his death, that Earth may have No feeling of her loss; But we, who knew and loved his presence here, In toil for others' joy must seek relief, For others' sakes not let our pain appear, Knowing for him 'tis well, Though deep within our souls the pulse of grief Throbs like a funeral bell. PARVA DOMUS, MAGNA QUIES Dear treasure-house of rich content, Calm shelter from care's anxious wind; Here life is clean and innocent, And all the plagues that fill The noisome town are left ten leagues behind Yon guardian hill. Beneath thy lowly roof abide Untroubled sleep, unconscious health; Never the foot of worldly pride Profanes the threshold's moss; No vain pretence is here, no hope of wealth, No fear of loss. Here toil is dignified and blest, For Nature's gracious self employs My willing hands; she gives deep rest For guerdon, days secure From vulgar strife, and luminous with joys Serene and pure. Here all wild things exult; the dawn Still trembles with the nightingale When the lark wakes the drowsy lawn; The yaffel laughs along The spinney, and the cuckoo fills the vale With lusty song. The shy birds here are bold; nuthatch And wryneck find a safe retreat; The martin warm beneath the thatch Chuckles his cheerful love, While from the copse purrs in the noonday heat The hidden dove. Here roses can rejoice; no reek Of Man's dark prison-house degrades Their purity. The thrush sits meek In motherhood, her spouse Fluting his rapture where the lilac shades Their little house. ‘Small house, great quietness’; so runs The portal's legend, half concealed By leafage; there the jasmine suns Its earliest gold; below, The crocus-cluster first uplifts the shield Of melting snow. Nor even Winter lacks the grace Of flowers; the doughty aconite Welcomes the frost with cheerful face; The snowdrop blades disclose Their guarded pearls, and Christmas brings to light Its own pure rose; While many a tender alien, born In lonely mountain-dell, unfolds Her beauty to the bright-eyed morn, And sips the taintless rain By warm airs wafted from the gentle wolds O'er Severn's plain. Here two fair princes, May and June, Delight to meet; the royal field With cloth of cowslip-gold is strewn, Dappled with purple shades Of clouds becalmed, that kiss the dreaming weald And bless the glades. Hither escaping from the grime And din of hideous streets, I feast On Nature's song and silence, climb The hill at dawn, to see The gold belt of the crimson-skirted east Gleam through the tree; Or search the brow of eve, to catch In opal depths the first faint beat Of Vega's fiery heart; and watch The long decline of day From beechen aisles, whose polished columns greet The last low ray. Then, if the year be ripe, await O'er woods, with glorious blazon tinged, The solemn progress of the great Red moon, through gold and green To silver, till each slumbering thatch is fringed With mellow sheen; While all around the fragrant night Breathes of ripe fruit and garnered corn, And now and then from distant height There floats the voice of sheep, With echoes of the brown owl's plaintive horn Where orchards sleep; Or wake on winter morns to find The plain a phantom sea of mist, Isled with dim trees, whereon half-blind The tearful eye of heaven Broods, through a veil by little rainbows kissed And light airs riven. Amid these peaceful wolds man yet May dwell in beauty; church and farm, Cottage and ancient hall, have met In one grey brotherhood, Now bare to upland blast, now nestled warm In sheltering wood. Here bygone ages linger; high On yonder ridge the Age of Stone Upreared its giant ossuary; The grim centurion strode Home to those crumbling walls, along that lone Unbending road; Behind those daisied banks a lord Of desperate Britain stood at bay; From that soft coombe the Saxon sword Swayed all the Mercian realm; Beneath yon tower the Norman knelt to pray; That friendly elm O'erlooks a field which once was drenched With rain of the two Roses' blood; A captive monarch's light was quenched Where yonder ivied keep Hears Severn, swollen with many a tribute flood, Pant for the deep. Noble the spacious drama viewed From Cotswold, whose wide wing outspread Doth from the clamorous world seclude The beauty of my home; There oft companioned by the mighty dead I love to roam, And bearing to my simple hearth Rich store of memories, gaily sup With makers of immortal mirth, Or wrapt in dream possess My full-fed soul in peace, and quaff the cup Of quietness; While, from beyond those classic hills That cradled English song, sunset With chords of silent music fills The heavens; till all grows pale, And twilight spreads her purple coverlet Athwart the vale. Here with the comrades of my choice I share the liberal fellowship Of Nature, catch the still small voice, And weave the rustic rhyme, Content that lightly through love's fingers slip The sands of time; Content to plough no more, but reap The harvest of a thankful mind; To grow in wonder; till the sleep Which is God's last caress Close all, and in the grave's small house I find Great quietness. ENVOY Loyal and tried, whose gentleness, Made strong by grief, serene by pain, Still turns to love, as after rain The blossom lifts its head again To meet the sun's caress; White flower of that old tree, which stood In Arden's forest-ways ere set The star of great Plantagenet, And, branching wide, is parent yet Of many a gracious brood; Kinswoman of that courtly soul Who reared the grey secluded halls That nursed my Muse;—their shadow falls On cloistered green and bastioned walls Where waves of Isis roll;— Sprung from his race who, while his feet Were spattered by the storm which dyed Edgehill with kindred blood, descried The secret course of that red tide Which fills all hearts that beat; Child of a house whose men were hale But brushed by wings of old romance, And, stout in use of bow and lance, Yet chose to wear for cognizance The lily of the vale; Handmaid of Christ—thy Master's grace Enfolds thee; for thy tender heart Hath chosen Mary's better part; Not what thou dost, but what thou art, Illumes thy flower-like face. Thou seem'st a mild September rose, Lit with the low sun's placid flame; Thy mien, thy garb, thy very name, All that belongs to thee, proclaim The beauty of repose. How precious in these hustling days The mellow voice, the restful eye, The loftiness of soul too high For pride, the simple dignity Too natural for praise. Not ours the bridle-path of ease, But duty's high and toilsome way, Where yet birds sing and breezes play, The rainbow blossoms on the grey, And autumn gilds the trees. No more the glamour of the feast, But frugal fare of sober joys, A bitter-sweet that never cloys, Pulses that keep a steadier poise— Of bounties not the least. The wine runs thin, the lamp burns low, Gone are the minstrels and the dance; But fewer fly the bolts of chance; And faith, a kindlier tolerance, A deeper insight, grow. Then, ere we quit Earth's genial board, Let us pronounce a hearty grace, And take the road with gentle pace, Pleased that our children run the race And twine the silver cord. If youth's bright passion-flower must fade, Some fruits of life remain to win; And though the sunny hours begin To close, we still may kneel within The sanctuary of shade, And, gazing through the golden bars, Watch evening's benediction rest On the dear past, till night's behest Reveal beyond the wistful West The wonder of the stars; Thankful if, while the distance grows More sombre, and our feet draw near The darkness and the hush, no fear Assail us, and the rounded year Be calmest at the close.</field>
   </doc>
</add>