<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Allingham, William, 1824-1889</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Allingham, William, 1824-1889</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">allingham william 1824 1889</field>
      <field name="author_text">Allingham, William, 1824-1889</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1880's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ep/uvaGenText/tei/chep_3.1412.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240351</field>
      <field name="date_text">[1887]</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:466770</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Rhymes for the young folk by William Allingham ; With pictures by Helen Allingham, Kate Greenaway, Caroline Paterson, and Harry Furniss: Engraved and printed by Edmund Evans</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Rhymes for the young folk by William Allingham ; With pictures by Helen Allingham, Kate Greenaway, Caroline Paterson, and Harry Furniss: Engraved and printed by Edmund Evans</field>
      <field name="title_facet">rhymes for the young folk by william allingham</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">rhymes for the young folk by william allingham</field>
      <field name="title_text">Rhymes for the young folk by William Allingham ; With pictures by Helen Allingham, Kate Greenaway, Caroline Paterson, and Harry Furniss: Engraved and printed by Edmund Evans</field>
      <field name="year_display">[1887]</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1887</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1887</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466770&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:466770&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Allingham, William, 1824-1889&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;allingham william 1824 1889&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Rhymes for the young folk by William Allingham ; With pictures by Helen Allingham, Kate Greenaway, Caroline Paterson, and Harry Furniss: Engraved and printed by Edmund Evans&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;rhymes for the young folk by william allingham&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;[1887]&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1887&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Allingham, William&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1824&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1889&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Rhymes for the young folk by William Allingham&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;With pictures by Helen Allingham, Kate Greenaway, Caroline Paterson, and Harry Furniss: Engraved and printed by Edmund Evans&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Paris&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Cassell and Company&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;[1887]&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chp0038&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;75 p.; ill.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Rhymes for the young folk by William Allingham&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;With pictures by Helen Allingham, Kate Greenaway, Caroline Paterson, and Harry Furniss: Engraved and printed by Edmund Evans&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 36 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted; music omitted; verse reproduced elsewhere in The English Poetry Full-text Database omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To GERALD, EVA, and LITTLE HENRY, and Others like them, THIS BOOKLET IS LOVINGLY INSCRIBED. [Green Hills, Blue Mountains, Rocks and Streams] Green Hills, Blue Mountains, Rocks and Streams, Birds, Woodland, Starry-Night, Sea-Foam, Flowers, Fairies, Children, Music, Dreams, A Book, a Garden-Chair—Sweet Home! THE ELF SINGING. An Elf sat on a twig, He was not very big, He sang a little song, He did not think it wrong; But he was on a Wizard's ground, Who hated all sweet sound. Elf, Elf, Take care of yourself! He's coming behind you, To seize you and bind you, And stifle your song. The Wizard! the Wizard! He changes his shape In crawling along, An ugly old ape, A poisonous lizard, A spotted spider, A wormy glider, The Wizard! the Wizard! He's up on the bough, He'll bite through your gizzard He's close to you now! The Elf went on with his song, It grew more clear and strong, It lifted him into air, He floated singing away, With rainbows in his hair; While the Wizard-worm from his creep Made a sudden leap, Fell down into a hole, And, ere his magic word he could say, Was eaten up by a Mole. CHORUS OF FAIRIES. Golden, golden, Light unfolding, Busily, merrily, work and play, In flowery meadows, And forest shadows, All the length of a Summer day! All the length of a Summer day! Sprightly, lightly, Sing we rightly, Moments brightly hurry away; Fruit-tree blossoms, And roses' bosoms,— Clear blue sky of a Summer day! Dear blue sky of a Summer day! Springlets, brooklets, Greeny nooklets, Hill and Valley, and salt sea-spray, Comrade rovers, Fairy lovers,— All the length of a Summer day All the livelong Summer day! JINGLE, JANGLE! Jingle, jangle! Riot and wrangle! What shall we do With people like you? Here's Jingle! There's Jangle! Here's Riot! There's Wrangle! Never was seen such a turbulent crew! You, north must go To a hut of snow; You, south, in a trice, To an island of spice; You, off to Persia And sit on a hill, You, to that chair And be five minutes' still! DREAMING. A strange little Dream On a long star-beam Ran down from the midnight skies, To curly-hair'd Fred Asleep in his bed, With the lids on his merry blue eyes. Under each lid The thin Dream slid, And spread to a picture inside, A new World there, Most strange and rare, Tho' just by our garden-side. Rivers and Rocks, And a Treasure-Box, And Floating in Air without wings, And the Speaking Beast, And a Royal Feast, My chair beside the King's; A Land of Flowers, And of lofty Towers Carved over in marble white With living Shapes Of Panthers and Apes That gambol in ceaseless flight; And a Cellar small With its Cave in the Wall Stretching many a mile underground! And the Rope from the Moon!— Fred woke too soon. For its end could never be found. I LOVE YOU, DEAR. I love you, Dear, I love you, Dear, You can't think how I love you, Dear! Supposing I Were a Butterfly, I'd waver around and above you, Dear. A long way off I spied you, Dear, No bonnet or hat could hide you, Dear, If I were a Bird, Believe my word, I'd sing every day beside you, Dear. When you're away I miss you, Dear, And now you're here I'll kiss you, Dear, And beg you will take This flow'r for my sake, And my love along with this, you Dear! SEASONS. In Spring-time, the Forest, In Summer, the Sea, In Autumn, the Mountains, In Winter,—ah me! How gay, the old branches A-swarm with new buds, The primrose and bluebell Fresh-blown in the woods, All green things unfolding, Where merry birds sing! I love in the Woodlands To wander in Spring. What joy, when the Sea-waves, In mirth and in might, Spread purple in shadow, Flash white into light! The gale fills the sail, And the gull flies away; In crimson and gold Sets the long Summer Day. O pride! on the Mountains To leave earth below; The great slopes of heather, One broad purple glow; The loud-roaring torrent Leaps, bound after bound, To plains of gold Autumn, With mist creeping round Ah, Wind, is it Winter? Yes, Winter is here; With snow on the meadow, And ice on the mere. The daylight is short, But the firelight is long; Our skating's good sport; Then story and song. In Spring-time, the Forest, In Summer, the Sea, In Autumn, the Mountains,— And Winter has glee. THE CAT AND THE DOG. There once lived a Man, a Cat, and a Dog, And the Man built a house with stone and log. “If you'll help to take care of this house with me, One indoors, one out, your places must be.” Said both together, “Indoors I'll stay!” And they argued the matter for half-a-day. “Come, let us sing for it!” purrs the Cat; “No!” barks the Dog, “I won't do that.” “Come, let us fight for it!” growls Bow-wow; “Nay!” says Pussy, “mee-ow, mee-ow!” “Well, let us race for it!”—said and done. The course is mark'd out, and away they run. Puss bounded off; the Dog ran fast; Quickly was Puss overtaken and pass'd; But a Beggar who under the hedge did lie Struck the poor Dog as he gallop'd by A blow with his staff, and lessen'd his pace To a limp: so Pussy won the race. The Beggar went on his way to beg; Dog was cured of his limping leg; And Cat keeps the inside of the house, Watching it well from rat and mouse, Dog keeps the outside, ever since then, And always barks at beggar-men. HERE AND THERE. (A JUVENILE CHORUS.) Where's Lucy? where's Lucy? Far, far in the wood, With wild birds for play-mates, And beech-nuts for food? CHORUS. No, here she is! here she is! Happy and gay, With singing and ringing To join in our lay. Where's Gerald? where's Gerald? He's out in the snow; The stars shining keenly, The cold wind doth blow. No, here he is! here he is! Happy and gay: With singing and ringing, To join in our lay! Where's Evey? where's Evey? She's lost in the fog; Go seek her, go find her, With man and with dog. No, here she is! here she is! Happy and gay; With singing and ringing, To join in our lay! Where's Henry? where's Henry? Poor Henry's afloat; The sea-waves all round him. High tossing his boat. No, here he is! here he is! Happy and gay; With singing and ringing To join in our lay! Where's Charley? where's Charley? In China dwells he; He wears a long pig-tail, Perpetually drinks tea. No, here he is! here he is! Happy and gay; With singing and ringing, To join in our lay! Where's Johnny? where's Johnny? In Nubia, I know; He has climb'd a tall palm-tree,— A lion's below. No, here he is! here he is! Happy and gay; With singing and ringing, To join in our lay! Where's Mary? where's Mary? Young Mary's asleep; And round her white pillow The little dreams creep. No, here she is! here she is! Happy and gay; With singing and ringing, To join in our lay! Where's Bertha? where's Bertha? She has wings—she can fly! She has flown to the bright moon— Look up there and spy! No, here she is! here she is! Happy and gay; With singing and ringing, To join in our lay! [AD INFINITUM.] WISHING. Ring-ting! I wish I were a Primrose, A bright yellow Primrose blowing in the Spring! The stooping boughs above me, The wandering bee to love me, The fern and moss to creep across, And the Elm-tree for our king! Nay—stay! I wish I were an Elm-tree, A great lofty Elm-tree, with green leaves gay! The winds would set them dancing, The sun and moonshine glancing, The Birds would house among the boughs, And sweetly sing! O—no! I wish I were a Robin, A Robin or a little Wren, everywhere to go; Through forest, field, or garden, And ask no leave or pardon, Till Winter comes with icy thumbs To ruffle up our wing. Well—tell! Where should I fly to, Where go to sleep in the dark wood or dell? Before a day was over, Home comes the rover, For Mother's kiss,—sweeter this Than any other thing! YES OR NO? Yes or No? Stay or Go? He never can tell, he never will know! We must not wait, We'll all be late, While Barnaby puzzles his queer little pate! What do you say? Off and away! Make up your mind to go or to stay. Fix on your plan, Step out like a man, And follow your nose as fast as you can! SLEEPING. Do all your sleeping at night, For then niddy-noddy is right; But awake you must keep, And it won't do to sleep, In the middle of broad daylight. The sun at the end of the day Takes his mighty great candle away; A curtain on high Is drawn over the sky, And the stars peep thro' if they may. There's the curtain of night over all, There's our own window-curtain so small, And least in their size, Over Emily's eyes Her fringed little eyelids will fall. She kneels at the side of her bed, And softly her prayers are said; Now, a kiss, my Dear; Come, Angels, near, And keep watch round the little one's bed. A SWING SONG. Swing, swing, Sing, sing, Here's my throne, and I am a King! Swing, sing, Swing, sing, Farewell earth, for I'm on the wing! Low, high, Here I fly, Like a bird through sunny sky; Free, free, Over the lea, Over the mountain, over the sea! Up, down, Up and down, Which is the way to London Town? Where, where? Up in the air, Close your eyes, and now you are there! Soon, soon, Afternoon, Over the sunset, over the moon; Far, far, Over all bar, Sweeping on from star to star! No, no, Low, low, Sweeping daisies with my toe. Slow, slow, To and fro, Slow—slow—slow—slow. BIRDS' NAMES. Of Creatures with Feathers, come let us see Which have names like you and me. Hook-nosed Poll, that thinks herself pretty, Everyone knows, of all birds most witty. Friendly Daw, in suit of gray, Ask him his name, and ‘Jack!’ he'll say. Pert Philip Sparrow hopping you meet, “Philip! Philip!”—in garden and street. Bold Robin Redbreast perches near, And sings his best in the fall of the year. Grave Madge Owlet shuns the light, And shouts “hoo! hoo!” in the woods at night. Nightingale sweet, that May loves well, Old Poets have call'd her Philomel, But Philomelus, he sings best, While she sits listening in her nest. Darting Martin!—tell me why They call you Martin, I know not, I; Martin the black, under cottage eaves, Martin the small, in sandy caves. Merry Willy Wagtail, what runs he takes! Wherever he stops, his tail he shakes. Head and tail little Jenny Wren perks, As in and out of the hedge she jerks. Brisk Tom Tit, the lover of trees, Picks-off every fly and grub he sees. Mag, the cunning chattering Pie, Builds her home in a tree-top high,— Mag, you're a terrible thief, O fie! Tom and Philip and Jenny and Polly, Madge and Martin and Robin and Willy, Philomelus and friendly Jack,— Mag the rouge, half-white, half-black, Stole an egg from every Bird; Such an uproar was never heard; All of them flew upon Mag together, And pluck'd her naked of every feather. “You're not a Bird!” they told her then, “You may go away and live among men!” NICK SPENCE. Nick Spence, Nick Spence, Sold the Cow for sixpence! When his Master scolded him, Nicky didn't care. Put him in the farmyard, The stableyard, the stackyard, Send him to the pigsty, And Johnny to the fair! AMBITION. The Sea! as smooth as silk, And the froth of it like new milk, And the sky a wonderful blue, The cliff harebells have it too, And scatter'd all over the shore A thousand Children or more! Suppose we join, one-will'd, A City of Sand to build, With a rampart broad and strong From rock to rock along, Solid and firm enough To last till the sea grows rough And the days turn chilly and short, The end of our seaside sport, When all must bundle and pack And swift in the train go back, Big folk and little folk, To London lamps and smoke? Let's draw out our plan to-night, Begin it with morning light. We'll bring all the Children together And build in the sweet sunny weather. What use in a House of Sand? But a City—that would be grand! O yes, I am sure it will stand! And I, who first thought of the thing, Perhaps they will make me King? THE BALL. All men, black, brown, red, yellow, white Are brethren in their Father's sight. To do each other good is right, But not to wrangle, steal, or fight. A thousand millions, young and old, Some in the heat, some in the cold, Upon this Ball of Earth are roll'd Around the Sun's great flame of gold. And this great Sun is like indeed One daisy in a daisied mead; For God's power doth all thought exceed. And of us also He takes heed. RIDING. His Lordship's Steed Of a noble breed Is trotting it fleetly, fleetly, Her Ladyship's pony, Sleek and bonny, Cantering neatly, neatly. How shall they pass The Turf-Cadger's Ass, Creels and all, creels and all? Man on him bumping, Shouting and thumping, Heels and all, heels and all! Lane is not wide, A hedge on each side, The Ass is beginning to bray; “Now,” says my Lord, With an angry word, “Fellow, get out of the way!” “Ha!” says the Cadger, As bold as a badger, “This way is my way too!” Says the Lady mild, And sweetly smiled, “My Friend, that's perfectly true.” The Cadger look'd round, Then jump'd to the ground, And into the hedge pull'd Neddy. “O thank you!” says she, “Ax pardon!” says he, And touch'd his old hat to the Lady. His Lordship's Steed Of a noble breed Went trotting it fleetly, fleetly, Her Ladyship's pony, Sleek and bonny Cantering neatly, neatly. The Cadger he rode As well as he could, Heels and all, heels and all, Jolting and bumping, Shouting and thumping, Creels and all, creels and all. TOM CRICKET. Tom Cricket he sat in his hole in the wall, Close to the kitchen fire, Up and down ran the Cockroaches all, Red coats and black coats, great and small; “Ho, Tom! our hearts are set on a ball, And your music we desire!” Tom sat in his hole, his horns hung out, He play'd away on his fiddle; The Cockroaches danced in a rabble rout, Scrambling and scurrying all about, Tho' they had their own steps and figures no doubt, Hands across, and down the middle. Till, “Stay!” says a Fat One,—“We're no Elves, To dance all night without stopping! Now for supper!” They help'd themselves, For the servants were gone to bed; on shelves And tables they quested by tens and twelves, And quick to the floor kept dropping. As a Cockroach ran by, says Tom Cricket to him, “Fetch me up a piece of potato, Good Sir!—to mix in the crowd I'm too slim.’ Says Jack Cockroach, “I see you are proud and prim; To eat alone is merely your whim,— Which I never will give way to!” “Come down,” says he, “and look out for your share!” “I won't do that,” says Tom Cricket. And when for another dance they care, And call upon Tom for a lively air, They find he has drawn himself back in his lair. “How shameful,” they cry, “How wicked!” “Let's fill up the mouth of his cave with soot, Because he's behaved so badly!” They ran up and down the wall to do't; But ere half-done—a dreadful salute! In came the Cook, and the Scullion to boot, And off they all scampered madly. THE YEAR OF HARDSHIPS. January, Bitter, very! February damp, Sir; March blows On April's nose, May has caught the cramp, Sir; June, Without a sun or moon! July, August, Many a raw gust; September, October, November, December, Ten times worse than I ever remember. No apples, or hay, or honey, or corn; I'm sure it wasn't a fat year. Whenever you and I were born, Good-luck it wasn't in that year! A RIDDLE. What I say you'll scarce believe, Yet my words shall not deceive. I saw what seem'd a little Boy, With a face of life and joy; He danced, he ran, he nodded, he smiled, Just like any other Child; But could not speak, (how strange was this!) Or cry, or breathe, nor could I kiss, To save my life, the cherry red Of lips, not living and not dead! He was no picture, statue, doll; He was not a Child at all; He was Nothing, as near as could be, He was as real as you or me. —There he is: turn and see!</field>
   </doc>
</add>