<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Danforth, John, 1660-1730</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Danforth, John, 1660-1730</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">danforth john 1660 1730</field>
      <field name="author_text">Danforth, John, 1660-1730</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1960's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ap/uvaGenText/tei/chap_AM0960.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240350</field>
      <field name="date_text">1969</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:440389</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">[Poems by Danforth in] Proceedings of the American Antiquarian Society ; April 17, 1968 - October 16, 1968 : Volume 78</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">[Poems by Danforth in] Proceedings of the American Antiquarian Society ; April 17, 1968 - October 16, 1968 : Volume 78</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poems by danforth in proceedings of the american antiquarian society</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poems by danforth in proceedings of the american antiquarian society</field>
      <field name="title_text">[Poems by Danforth in] Proceedings of the American Antiquarian Society ; April 17, 1968 - October 16, 1968 : Volume 78</field>
      <field name="year_display">1969</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1969</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1969</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440389&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440389&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Danforth, John, 1660-1730&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;danforth john 1660 1730&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;[Poems by Danforth in] Proceedings of the American Antiquarian Society ; April 17, 1968 - October 16, 1968 : Volume 78&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poems by danforth in proceedings of the american antiquarian society&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1969&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1969&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Danforth, John&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1660&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1730&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;[Poems by Danforth in] Proceedings of the American Antiquarian Society&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;April 17, 1968 - October 16, 1968 : Volume 78&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Worcester&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Published by the Society&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1969&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3865978-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;cham0960&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;[Poems by Danforth in] Proceedings of the American Antiquarian Society&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;April 17, 1968 - October 16, 1968 : Volume 78&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1996&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1996 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 111 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only poems by Danforth included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-AmPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELEGIES Upon the Triumphant TRANSLATION of a Mother in Our ISRAEL, Viz. MRS. ANNE ELIOT From This Life to a Better. on March 24th. 1687. Aetatis Suae. 84. ALL Hallelujahs, Oh ye Heav'nly Quires, Ye Powers, ye Winged &amp; Immortal Fires! Redouble to the Highest ONE: Here's Joy, to your Eternal Jubile Advanc'd, by th' New come welcome Company Of a Bright Soul, but lately flown. Congratulate Eternally. With Sacred Symphony, Her happy State. Haile! Happy Soul! In Luster excellent Transcending far the Starry Firmament, Which is thy Footstool now become: With all the World, America shall Vye, For to Produce thy Peer: Now cast thine Eye All round about that Spacious Room, None shalt thou see Of Blest Women, Much more Triumphant than Thy self to be. Haile! Thou Sagacious &amp; Advent'rous Soul! Haile, Amazon! Created to Controll Weak Nature's Foes, &amp; t' take her part, The King of Terrours, Thou, ('till the Command Irrevocable came to Stay thy Hand,) Didst oft Repel, by thy Choice Art: By High Decree, Long didst thou stand An Atlas, in Heav'n's Hand To th' World to be. All Hallelujahs to His bounteous Care, That such a Peerless Consort did Prepare For HIM, whom Sacred Things with-held From Seculars; Who was to Gospellize, And Preach Redemption to GODS Enemys Beyound all Memory, Rebell'd: For his sake, sure, Thine Aged Life It did with Death in Strife So long endure. Heav'n's Richest Spices, Choicest Graces were (Queen Esther like,) allotted to Thy Share, For to Prepare Thee for thy KING: Thee, to Pay Able, for Full Recompence, With Interest, for all thy Vast Expense, Angels, on Wings of Grace, strait, bring: As Phaltiel, Thy CONSORT Dear Mourning, Thee follow'th near, To bid FAREWEL. J. D. To the Blessed MEMORY of the Venerable Mr. JOHN ELIOT, TEACHER to the Church of CHRIST in Roxbury, and a PROPAGATOR of the Gospel to the Indians in N-England. Who rested from his Labours, May, 20. Anno Dom. 1690. Aetatis Suae. 86. SHall ELIOT slip away? &amp; not his Sons Spy &amp; Regret it, with Athletick Groans? None Cry Alarm, when Horse &amp; Chariots taken? None Feel, when Israel's weal's Foundation's shaken? Lately, a stately Stone pluckt out; none 'spy it? Nor run to stop the woful Breach made by it? Where's sweet Tongue'd David, sad Song'd Jeremiah, Jon'than to 'wail, to Elegize Josiah? Where's matchless Moses's Muse? Had I his Staff, I'd find one Grave, and 'Grave one Epitaph. English and Indian Work, he did so well, Define we cannot, which did which excell. Pagans, This Paul converts; Peter doth use His Talents chiefly to confirm the Jews. Paul to Barbarians, own's Himself a Debtor; Our John, a brave Divine, T' Himself, no better Dares supererrogate, in the vast Cost And Pains, expended to Reduce the lost. A brave Divine, said I? I had not mist, Sure, had I Stil'd Him an Evangelist. To Trace their Pagan Genealogies Was not his Task, yet would his curious Eyes Maugre oblivions Dust, 'venture to scan At least by guess, These hideous Wrecks of Man: And thought, he trackt, to Palestina's Strand: How e're; He was resolv'd, to th' Holy Land Them to reduce; (might Heav'n a Moses make him) Nor did their barb'rous Heathenism shake him. Th' Eternal Mind in Mortal Airs, nev'r blew Unformed Blast; His Sov'reign Shalms yet flew On Syriac Wings; His Gentleness equips His Sacred Chariot with Chaldean Chips: Three Other, His own Mother-Tongue beside, Upon His Pascal Cross, He Sanctify'd. His Tharsian-bred Apostle don't refuse To sharp his Tools with Philistines, to use Greek Poets, cited to the Sacred Bar, T' wait on Effata's more Oracular. Like Hercules toils ELIOT, lest that He Should to Barbarians, a Barbarian be. Since Babel's Trait'rous Tower was Thundersmit, By Heav'ns Inraged Ire, &amp; fell, &amp; split One Tongue into a Thousand Shivers, none Can tell the Wounds, which this one Wo alone, Hath more than scarr'd the World with; next th' Expulsion At first from Paradise, &amp; th' next Convulsion In Grandsire Japheth's Time, no Storm before, The Universal World e're delug'd more: But now, thro' matchless Grace, to Eliot's given The Key t' expel what lockt men out of Heaven. His Tongue sails right, with Indian Tempest tost; Puts in for Peter's Plea, at Pentecost. The Ambassadour unto Them dares preferr Offers of CHRIST, without Interpreter. Th' Incarnate Furys, straitway from the Pit Of Darkness worse than Egypts, Rise, &amp; Spit On all their Daemons, whilst their Breast &amp; Brow They to the LORD, &amp; to His Baptist vow. One Testament Seventy Interpreters Translate to Greek, Antiquity avers; Both Testaments, yet ELIOT alone Converts into the Indian Tongue &amp; Tone; Abel, tho' dead, yet speaks, in one Tongue more; Isay's, Apollo's Eloquence, before, Ne're Rode in such a Chariot: Luke Physician, ('Tho' skill'd in Pulse,) would scarce tell the Condition Of His own Gospel: Paul, with his much Learning Would here be Posed:— For 'though to many Regions He did pass, Yet no West-Indian Antiquary was. Sir Thomas Eliot was Great Brittains Glory: Our Saint shall have a Chronicle in Ages Story: Great XAVIER brings the Crucifix &amp; Libel, To Indian Souls, of Masses; Ours, the Bible. Sanctius, for this, owns Him a Tutelary: Calls on him &amp; him joyns with GOD &amp; MARY: Eliot before such cursed Adoration, Would chuse much rather, an Annihilation. Yet made His Works before mens Eyes to shine, That they might Glorifie the Name Divine. The Indian-Work lay greatly on his Heart; Until the Last, when He and That must part. They parted not without most solemn Blessing, While Clouds thereon were to his Soul-Distressing. He dyes; His Work, when Time Dyes shall survive; 'Tho' Dead, yet speaks, that th' Indian Work may Live, And to 's Successors doth good Counsel give: ‘Address (I pray) our Senate for good Orders, ‘To Civilize the Heathen in our Borders. ‘Vertue must turn into Necessity; ‘Or this brave Work, will in its Urn still lye. ‘'Till Agriculture, and Cohabitation, ‘Come under full Constraint and Regulation, ‘Much you would do, you'l find Impracticable, ‘And much you do will prove Unprofitable. ‘In common Lands that lie unfenc'd you know ‘The Husbandman, in vain doth plow &amp; sow: ‘We hope in vain, the Plant of Grace shall thrive ‘In Forrests, where Civility can't Live. ‘In English Towns, when they their Months do spend, ‘Make Them, Gods Worship with us, to attend. ‘Whilst I us'd (as you must) sharp Discipline, ‘The saving Gains were Theirs, the Pains were mine. ‘Their Tender Sons to Sacred Learnings Throne ‘None can advance, but such Divines alone, ‘As are most Expert in their Dialect, ‘If Teaching in their own Tongue we respect: ‘Such Youths, (if GOD vouchsafe to Sanctify ‘Their studious minds) the sacred Oars may Ply, ‘Each Sabbath too, through Starry Arches bring, ‘Their Common Homage to our Mighty King. ‘Look well to the Uprising Nursery: ‘You know full well, none more for Schools than I. ‘To drown their Woes, some drown their Wits, and All ‘Their Common Grace: Correct that Fault you shall. ‘If you be Instant, only out of Season, ‘Your Hope soars out of sight of all my Reason, ‘If you expect, (while Lords Days hold their Station) ‘To Lecture them, on Week-Days, to Salvation. ‘Is it impossible to make a Purse, ‘T' Invite a Lecturer, in Turns, to Nurse ‘Your English Flocks, That those may have good Dressing ‘That have most need, upon the Day of Blessing? ‘Their Indian Teachers are but Weak; I Wiss; ‘Their Preaching, by their Hearers, slighted is: ‘Take then this Way, to readvance the Standard ‘Of Holiness, by late backslidings Slander'd. ‘Let fire-hot Zeal, boile in your thirsty Veins, ‘To save poor Caitiffs from Eternal Pains. ‘Our Antient Heroes, with their English Prayers ‘Did edify Their Souls; yet then, such Ayres ‘Were Unintelligible, more by far, ‘Than now adays, (since long Converse) they are. ‘Call many English Suppliants: Let them Kneel, ‘With Them &amp; for Them; for their saving Weale, ‘Joyn hand in hand: Help up the Weak, Heav'ns Stairs: ‘Salvation, serves in pay of Joyned Prayers. ‘The Friends of Christ, &amp; Souls, Let none be mute ‘In any Tongue, that can GODS Throne salute: ‘FAST with and for Them also twice a Year, ‘'Twill shew, and bring their Resurrection near. ‘May GOD in Heav'n, &amp; may poor Heathens see ‘That much affected, &amp; concern'd All be: ‘Christs Intercessions may they have redound, ‘Echo'd from hence, 'Twill to their Weal rebound ‘(Grand Usurer) I, nev'r gave Heav'n a Mite ‘But gain'd, &amp; gather'd, Thousand Millions by 't. ‘Never Regret (Brave Hearts!) your vast Expence ‘Of Time &amp; Pains: Mark well the Difference ‘'Twixt Indian Traders &amp; their Teachers made; ‘What Blessings These, what Blastings Those Invade ‘Those often are annoy'd with mischiefs, whiles ‘These doe enjoy most sweet Cœlestial smiles. His Counsels, we have done with; And return, To close the Ashes of his Sacred Urn. When Pious Grandson lately came to visit This Saint, then at Heav'n's Gate, And said, How is it? Such was his sense, he sagely made reply, I am Afraid: But not afraid to Dy: Sir! Thankfull Joy, My Motto is, (Quoth He) Unto Another; And I Joy to see What Lights Christ sets in's Churches, &amp; that still GOD hath His Folk, that doe His Temples fill. How solemnly He Blest 'em, some can tell; Like Paul; Begging, mean while; their Pray'rs as well: And may they Blessed be! May they inherit, A Double Portion of Elijah's Spirit. On Golden Letters of His Name I mused; JOHN, distill'd HONY; ELIOT, TOILE produced: Pains bring in gains; for sweets, he sweats: thus frau't With richest Lading, To His Port, He's brought. This Vessel yet of Honour, had not been So soon seen under Saile, Had not our Sin Deserved &amp; Provoked such a sign Of Woe descending from the Wrath Divine. This blurs the Trophys of our New Elections, With Interlinements of sad Interjections. Indians! Your Hearts are Marble, if Distress Seize you not, for Unprofitableness. Fear you not Wrath poor Souls! will you not grieve Th' Ambassador of Peace has tak'n his Leave. He Lov'd your Nation dearly; did He not? (Adding your Language to the Polyglott;) In ways unparellell'd, his strange Compassion Drew Soul &amp; Substance out, for your Salvation. Heav'ns Fiery Balls, Flames, Smoke &amp; Thundring Shot And Bloody Drops, (late Prodigies) are not More signal than this Death, at such a season, Such was Methuselah's: and we have Reason, May we have Grace, t' repent the Provocation With speed, that crys aloud for Desolation. Yet Muse! Don't overgroan: thy Fathers Glee In 's reimbraced Colleague should with Thee, Advance new Sonnets to His Jubilee Indulcify'd, sweet ELIOT by Thee. J. D. A FUNERAL ELEGY Humbly Dedicated to the Renowned Memory of the HONORABLE, THOMAS DANFORTH, Esq. Of Cambridge, Sometimes Deputy GOVERNOUR in the Colony of the Massachusetts-Bay, and President of the Province of Maine; and One of His Majesties Honourable COUNCIL, Judge of the Superior Court in the Province of the Massachusetts-Bay in New England; where (after He had long Served His Generation by the Will of GOD in several High Stations) Did to our Inconceivable Loss, but His Unparallel'd Gain, Rest from all His Labours, on the Sacred Day of Rest, the Memorable 5th. of November: Anno Domini. 1699. Aetatis Suae, 77. Honos, Onus: Mors, Pax. JUDGE of the Quick and Dead I am not, Yet HIM and my self should very much forget If that I should decline the Bench to take Nor give my sence and sentence of this Fate. Pardon me, Sir; 'Twere better first to Die Than prove Disloyal to your Memorie 'Tis Conscience gives Commission not t' be Mute Justice and Gratitude shall Execute. The Isle which (Alfred sings) no Help desires, Yet all the World supply from Her requires Able to Glut King Solomon with Pleasures And Surfeit Great Augustus with Her Treasures: Whence the First Christian Emperour did spring And since that, Many a Heroe, Many a King Rich in all Merchandize: More Rich in Men: (Scarce such an Island is the World agen) And whence New England sprang. It did produce Him, to this Land who was of Glorious Use. He, Nature drew from Him whom Grace Divine, Rather than Worldly Grandieur, made to Shine. Who urg'd to Knight Him, Him, He follow'd not Follow'd a Greater King, to Desart Lot; Like Marsaeus, when He saw Saints to Goe Would fain be Knight of their Wing'd Order too. Such was His Father: and poor Framingham Lost a Choice Lecture when He hither came By Prophets Preach'd; But He procur'd the fame. After His Father's Death This Son was bless'd, Rudeness and Lewdness much He did Detest; Fear'd God from's Youth, like good Prince Obadiah An Early Convert, like Renown'd Josiah. Glowing His Love; most Veh'ment His Desire Like Coals of Juniper and Flames of Fire, To Jacob's Portion: Angels, Powers, Life, Death Heights, Depths, could not put either out of breath Harnass'd and Rigg'd with th' Christian Panoplie; Well under girt with sound Sincerity: In every State, undelug'd, could Sail Right; His Anchor held, on something out of Sight. Left not his Sweets, when He Promotion wan His Wine still Cheer'd the Heart of God and Man His Speech well Season'd both for Time and Grace For in His Soul, most Sav'ry Salt had Place. He had an Art, He practis'd to the last, What e're was Talk'd, in Spiritual mould to Cast. God's Samuel He; 'Mongst those that on Him call 'Mongst Thundring Hosts, an Expert General: Nobly Seraphick, and most Rapturous, In Prayer; A Secon'd Theodosius. What's Parent came Three Thousand Miles, to Win That, to neglect, He dare'd not Count no Sin. God's Temple had Him, A Professor Press'd God's Table found Him Young, a Worthy Guest. 'Twas Time, a Vine Grew up on His House side: Withington's Halls afford this Saint a Bride. Precious as Gold Their Faith, yet as Behov'd 'Twas by both Fining Pot and Furnace Prov'd; Them Ten Rare Pledges, early fledg'd, forsook And the Directest way to Heaven Took: 'Mongst whom count Chief the Famous Samuel Whose Excellencies Englands both can Tell. During that Wondrous Term of Seven times Seven, Co-heirs They Lived, of the Grace of Heaven. Just in the Fiftieth year of Jubilee His Aged Virtuous Consort went out free, Yet not so Free, as He to Follow was, And to o're take Her, Mends His Heavenly Pace. 'Twas His High Care when first He saw that Comet Of Earthly Wealth arise, to cut off from it Its Dreadful Fiery Tail; th' Intailment even Of Difficulty in the way to Heaven; That Sin bred Fate, can't course of Law out-root A Gospel Course, He found might greatly doe 't. Saw on His Hand that Viper Venimous: To Alms it temper'd, Made a Treacle thus Honours to seek or shun H' was never buisy. His Head could bear Great Height &amp; not be Dizzy. Bless'd by Bless'd Wilson first on Bench when sat Regal'd with th' Anagram, Handsom for that. Edicts, Examples, and Sharp Punishment States, warping from their Standard ought prevent. Sagacious He betimes to Meet and Mate Ill Humours, threatning to subvert the State. Flat fell They who would 'laid New-England flat; Thank GOD &amp; th' MAN with Little Band, for That. Him, and His Country, who would Wast, in Hast He made Repent, Their Rents came in so fast. I've sometimes heard Him say that He had ever As lieve dy by the Ax as by the Feaver; In a Good cause, and with a Conscience Good; For Church &amp; State, so Truth's Great Champion stood. Like Samuel Rode the Circuit, Judg'd each Tribe, And like Brave Samuel, never took a Bribe. So Good, Great, Wise, Just, Steady, Trusty, Free; We'll ne're want Men, while we have Such as Thee. His Thoughts Pure Spirits were, He therefore us'd Physician like, to give them, well infus'd In some sweet proper Vehicle of Wit, Some Proverb, Story, Simile, most fit. When Men of Sense addres'd Him, 'twas His fashion Reasons to shew, and leave the Application: And when some nimble Case out ran His Vicit, Still Gave forth Sentence, in a Nihil Dicit. Dangers, as soon as meant, He oft Suspected Forgers, He oft Sagaciously Detected: At Helm in Tempests, yet His Courage Stout 'Though Dangers were Extream, would nev'r give out. Of Them, like Nicodemus He was One, And stood like Him, stout Protestant alone 'Gainst a Committee, whose blind Indignation Condemn'd the Best Men of that Generation. I know not where to stop; His Course was thus To make New Englands Journal Glorious: Hath stood our Churches Pillar ever since, Not without Envy, for His Recompence. Harvard! For Honourable, Thou must goe; Who was thy Steward, Treasurer, was soe. Charg'd and Discharg'd were the Quarter Bills, Drain'd not thy Stock, but with large Hundreds fills A Bounteous Patron unto many a Plant, In thy fair Nursery, whose Means were scant. Resolves so to continue, 'Spite of Death, By Lands and Rents, His last Will witnesseth. Bring Tribute to thy Benefactors Dust To be Ungrateful is to be Unjust. Church Messengers CHRISTS Glory are, so He (In that Relation,) oft was seen to be; Nor was 't a Shame for a Profess'd Divine, To be beholden to His Golden Mine. So well-read in all Points, Men of best fashion, Unto His Judgment pay'd a Veneration When Church Disturbances requir'd His Best He signally with great Success was Bless'd. In 's Family as exact Order's seen, As if that it a Soveraign State had been: Reading, Instruction, Prayer, and Repetition So constant were, You'd envy their Condition. From Families would Spring New Englands Bliss Might all be taught and Govern'd as was His. Great is the Loss of such a Man as This! Full of Good Works, not therefore void of Fears; No Works so Good but call for Fasts and Tears; Justification through His Saviours Blood, And Righteousness, (His Aged Souls last Food,) His Readings, Meditations, there, were spent So Views His Title, and Receives Content. Like Solomon, All Gainful Arts He trys To Dye in Christ, Best Gain He finds; so Dies. His Arms: On Gold, the single opened Eye, (Man's Noble Part) imports Sincerity, And Wisdom too: That Gemm, the Di'mond dwells Invulnerate' though it cutts all things else. He left with's Children Dear a Num'rous Race, Lord! Give 'em Portions of their Grandsire's Grace Thousands up springing so, in His rich Heap Shall Love Thy Name, &amp; Thy Commandments keep. Amen. JOHN DANFORTH. A Pindarick ELEGY Upon the Renowned, MR. SAMUEL WILLARD, Late Reverend Teacher of the South Church in Boston, and Vice-President of Harvard College in Cambridge; Who Deceased September the 12th. 1707. Aetatis Anno 68. ENdited by an Heart with Grief repleat, My Verse doth Homage at his Mourners Feet: Is a Just Mourner too: It's Grief is Loud: Louder the Cause: Invading ills so crowd. In trembling Airs, its feather'd Arrow flys; But not so High, nor half so Swift, as doe our Destinys. It spies, big with Portentousness and Dread, Amazing Signs advance their Lofty Head: Views, how fierce Lightnings doe our Steeples strike And Temples Batter, And their most Sacred Riches Scatter. Victims, and Priests in flames ascend alike, Most wondrously; such horrid Carnage make Heav'ns fiery Bombs, when they so fall &amp; break. It views our choicest Treasures made a Prey; Death Triumphs them away: But so much for to lose, altho' no more, Would Beggar Nations, make Rich Empires Poor, The High &amp; Mighty States a Begging send, Or Borrowing at least; But where are they can lend? It sees, (and Sighs,) Hereby we were Undone, Hereby Alone; So much choice Gold is Buried in this Grave; But that it sees our Mines no Bottom have; Mines that for Proselyted Rebels, lie Within the Treasury Of Grace Ador'd, Of our Dear Saviour and Ascended Lord. 'Twill yet, to Gain so much, take a long Day, For choicest Pioneers to dig, and Pray; And Get again what we have forfeited away. In Crimson Flood, wade Thousands to his Tomb, Swell'd Big with Heroe's Blood, like Trojane Womb: Troy were forgot, But for our Parallel Lott; Ah! Woful Day! One Conquering Horse of Fate Severe &amp; Just, Enter'd our Opened Gate; Nay 'Twas a Troop, Enough to Seize, and swallow up Long horded Stores that made Us Rich, &amp; Proud, That many Scores of Plenteous years had bounteously bestow'd. Such Losing Bankrupts We; 'Twould break Heaven too But that it's Wealth is Infinite, to Set us up Anew. Let all New-England, and let Boston know, How much they do to CHRIST for Willard owe; Christ's Precious Blood produc'd this Copious Good, (In all Its worth) not fully understood. Harvard! I'le call thy Head (for tis no Treason) Master of Reason; Master of all the Wisdom of the Sages, That's handed down to later Ages: Master of Tongues; Master of Policy's So much Admir'd; And in Theology's Doctrines &amp; Truths, which most Mysterious Are, His Learned Mind might safely take the Chair. He Liv'd and Wrought in the Oraculous Flame, 'Till he an Oracle became; Whereat when many did Enquire, They had the mind of Christ, to their Desire So strong in Christ his Pen, Thousands do know And stoutest foes have found it so, That when he pleas'd to Conquer, he was able, Chastiz'd the Rash, and settled the Unstable. One of the King of Israel's Mightys he, Of the First Three Full of the Holy Ghost: (Wou'd so were we.) His Virtue's Roll's so large, Th' Ocean's so Deep; My Verse could do no more, but only creep And Spy, and Speak a little on the Brink: And thus much he must say who will speak least: But of the Rest, Bright Angels may, and such as They with Just Amazement Think. JOHN DANFORTH PROFIT AND LOSS: AN ELEGY Upon the Decease of MRS. MARY GERRISH, Late Vertuous Wife of Mr. Samuel Gerrish, and Daughter of the Honourable Judge SEWALL. Who on Novemb. 17. 1710. the Night after Publick Thanksgiving, Entred on the Celebration of Triumphant Hallelujahs, to her Profit, and our Loss. Aged 19. Years &amp; 20. Days. MARY, the Blessed VIRGINS Name, EXALTED, Signifies: ARMY, was once the Anagram, a Poet did devise. Behold! How her Exaltedness an Army justly Boasts: Because within her, HE Incamp'd, who was the LORD OF HOSTS. To many a Precious MARY, since, great Exaltation's Given; Fill'd with the Spiritual Presence of the Eternal LORD of Heav'n. Our beauteous MARY too, She was (Of Honourable Race;) Besides all other Brightnesses, enobled most by Grace. By Grace she chose the better Part; ne're to be taken from her; Her Heart, Rabboni, cry'd to Christ whose Love did overcome her. WHO 'twas that pitch'd His Tabernacle within her sacred heart, Her Letters, Carriage, and Discourse, unto her Friends impart. Her PARENTS dear, will nev'r Repent her Pious Education: Or wish their Prayers unpray'd, that sped so well, in her Salvation. They'l Joy, Because Eternal Life, (the Crown of Righteousness,) She Carries, notwithstanding Death's Hereditariness: Armies of Merits, All her LORD's, (while she her own deny'd;) Prevailing for her, and all Such, as in whose stead He Dy'd. By Faith she dy'd, depending still upon the Grace Divine, That thro' the Mediator, would in her Salvation shine. She has Attaind now, with Advance, what she desir'd below; (Joyn'd to the Church in Heav'n,) She doth to Full Communion go. Her Place is Empty; bear 't you must, She's on a Visit gone, To better Friends, than any here; and will Return anon. The Raising-Day hastens apace; her Second Coming too; Twill dazzle all such Eyes as ours, her Beauty then to view. Now, for her Absence, and her Stay, She need no Pardon ask; Commanded hence; but not before She first had done her task. Onely she craves, by Friends here left for to be Visited; And would Rejoyce to see them all at th' Heav'nly Table fed: Yet is content they stay a while; while 'tis for th' Churches gain: For which; we, (with Submission,) Pray they here may long Remain. She's satisfy'd, her Relatives can never be Undone, By the departure of a star, while they enjoy the Sun. Good is the Country she has left; it is IMMANUEL'S. But HEAVEN the Better Country is; and there her SPIRIT dwells. The more of Excellence in her your ravish'd Eyes did fill; Your Resignation shines the more to Heav'ns Remanding Will. You grieve, the Time's so short; but yet had you Enjoy'd her longer, The Bands of Love had Faster grown, and Bands of Grief much stronger. You'd but short warning of her Death, its suddenness is Trying; Yet ben't surpriz'd to see that Dead, you always knew was Dying. Your sweetest Terrene Hopes are cross'd by disappointment sad: That your Eternal Hope's secure, your Souls may yet be glad. Who Gave her, He has Taken her; this is beyond Dispute: Indisputable Sov'raignty then binds you to be Mute. Partings are Grief: Happy the Hearts here, made Bereavement-Proof; In Times of need, you know WHERE there is Grace and Help enough. A Daughter, Sister, Spouse, is tak'n; whom dear Relations miss; Much of their Worldly Comfort's gone, now she is gone to Bliss. Stop your Pursuing Griefs for her, your Hue-en-crys forbear; You want her Much: SEEK HER IN CHRIST AND YOU WILL FIND HER THERE. Maestus Composuit J. D. HONOUR AND VERTUE ELEGIZED IN A POEM Upon an Honourable, Aged, and Gracious Mother in our Israel, MADAM ELIZABETH HUTCHINSON, Late Vertuous Consort of our Hon. JUDGE, Col. ELISHA HUTCHINSON, Esqr., in Boston. She Entred into the Joyes of Paradise, Feb. 3. 1712, 13. Aetatis Suae 71. Not Artful Verse, but Hearty Goodness gives, That Fame, in Earth &amp; Heav'n, that ever Lives; Verse only gives the Eccho, and Attest: And Saints, who need it Least, Deserve it best. Remembrance, GOD hath Promis'd to the Just: Long Years then, spent in Vertue have it must. Full long, this Abram's Daughter did appear Like Polisht Saphire, and like Rubies, rare; Full of all Goodness: Grace Abounded so; Light from Above, thus made Her Shine below. May Trees be known by Fruits; Not many be So Fit to Live, and Fit to Die, as She. Her Life was Speaking, and Her Death not Dumb; She gives Instruction from the very Tomb; She calls aloud; ‘LADIES, BE READY; Mind Me; ‘I'm Gone before; But Leave the WAY Behind Me. ‘LADIES! Be Lesson'd, by My Silver Hairs, ‘To Banish from your youth all Carnal Fears ‘Of Dying soon, if You are Early Pious; ‘With Aged Years, See Heav'n doth Gratify Us. ‘Did I (think you) One Day the sooner Die, ‘Because in CHRIST so SOON, in Grace so HIGH? ‘The ALTAR may Renounce your SACRIFICE, ‘If you to Age Prorogue your fervent Cries.’ Her SAMPLAR, needle-wrought, with threads of Gold And Stars, doth Useful PARABLES Unfold; Namely; THAT Heav'n's-Way's in the Temple; where She kept Her Heart; and Her Resort was there: THAT, They DO most and best, who feel and know That they themselves can nothing WILL or DO: THAT, th' Word, Pray'r, Faith are th' best Viaticum, For Travellers, that would to Heaven Come. Her FURNACE also with Instruction Shines: There She Refines, Weeps, Prays, Submits, Resigns: And when Exempted from Calamity She Pays the Vows of Her Adversity. And, long e're Age had founded a Retreat To Worldly Pleasure, Her Recess was Great: She kept an Undegenerated Soul, Which Times could not corrupt, nor Blasts controul. In Her, the Meekness, which the most do Want, It was both Radical and Radiant. Sweet Lowliness, in Greatness, most men Slight; Sure, They are Wrong if CHRIST was in the Right; She was, (so Richest Mines do Lowest lie,) Low in HUMILITY; in HONOUR High. Her Mind was Generously Elemented; And with Her Noble Heart, Her Hand Consented; Some lose no little by their Costiveness; Her Lib'ral Hand the Poor did often Bless: Heav'n would give Interest, She did not fear; There was Her Treasure, &amp; Her Heart was There. Yet One Thing more; She brought on Honour's Stage, (Almost Unpresidented in Our Age,) Most Pious Talk; for such Distill'd from HER; Sweeter than Hybla's Drops, and Richer far. New-England's VERTUOSO this Espied; And Chose and Made this Noble Vine His BRIDE. Bereav'd before; They saw, (and wip'd their Tears,) Their Breaches well made up, for Many Years. With Honour They sustain'd their Worthy Station, Maintain'd 'by Correspondent Inclination. Happy in one another; Happy too In Lovely Branches, that do Heav'n-woo. O Happy Family! Like Heav'n above For Order, Vertue, Piety, and Love. SHE the Bright Vertues of Good Wives &amp; Mothers Practis'd Her Self, and Cherished in others. The Greatest Ladies well might Emulate Her Gracious Life, and now Her Glorious State. SHE's Run Her Race, The Glorious Prize is won (Painful to Do; and Pleasing to be Done.) T' Her Joyful Soul, the MERCY comes at Last On High, Her Longing Soul Desir'd to Tast: No Darts can Fly so High; No Violence Of Foes can Reach Her there, or force Her thence. This Saint's Removal unto Consolation Yet causeth Anguish, and deep Lamentation. Be Comforted: Time's Short; And GOD Lives still, He Wills your Good; 'Tis fit He have His Will; He's not Inconstant, Feeble, or Unkind; Nor to His Saints shews a Forgetful Mind. Excessive Grief's an EVIL manifold; To Cure it, you must have CHRIST'S Touch and Gold; He gives it, ev'n for Alms; Keep it you must; Th' EVIL Returns if th' Royal Gold be Lost. The HEROE'S sorely wounded by this fate, Whose Shoulders long have help'd t' Uphold our State; His Children too; O! May th' Almighty LORD Strong Consolations to Their Souls afford; Dissolve Their Griefs: Prolong Their Useful Years; And turn into Eternal Joyes their Tears. Amen. Ita humillime Precatur, J. Danforth, V. D. M., Dorchest. GREATNESS &amp; GOODNESS ELEGIZED, In a POEM, Upon the much Lamented Decease of the Honourable &amp; Vertuous MADAM HANNAH SEWALL, Late Consort of the Honourable Judge SEWALL, in Boston, in NEW-ENGLAND. She Exchanged this Life for a Better, October, 19th. Anno Dom. 1717. Aetatis Suae. 60. A Mind Serene is only fit for Verse, Deserved by this Honourable Herse: Our Ruffled Mind can scarcely Think, for Tears; Trembling Our Pen, at This Great Death, appears. The PATRIOT, now in Sorrow almost Drown'd, Merits Condoleance from the Country round. Shall We adventure these Unpolish'd Lines? Lucina's Dust deserves far Richer Shrines. To Name Her Father first We'll not think much; We knew Him well, &amp; Wish there were More Such. Choice HULL the fifth Command observ'd so well, His Carriage to His Parent did Excell; Wilson Pronounc'd the Promis'd Blessing then; The LORD of Providence too said AMEN. The Hull, soon Built upon, became an Argo; Deep fraighted with Terrene &amp; Heav'nly Cargo: Immortal Vertue gave Immortal Name; Long Life, Power, Honour, Added to His Fame. Stretching his Course, Refresh'd with Prosperous Gales, Quitting New-England's Coasts, to Heav'n He Sails. This Precious Fragant Flower was, when he went, Heir of's Vertues, Left in's Heavenly Tent: A Paragon, upon New-England's Stage; Her Piety advancing with her Age. Her Radiant Graces, of so Rich a Worth, Pencils of Angels scarce can Paint 'em forth. She was too Sparkling for Plebeian Eyes, Heaven Bless'd SEWALL with this Noble Prize; Plac'd in the Chrystal Sphere of Chastest Love, She Flow'r'd a Race, Devote to Heav'n above. Full of Contentment and Devoid of Strife, In Golden Characters She wrote her Life. Her Mind, Bright &amp; Serene: A Charming Sight: No Saphire or Rich Ruby Shone so Bright. Such was her Course, &amp; Choice, &amp; Disposition; The Greatest Queens may Envy her Condition. Observing-Ladys must keep down their Vail, 'Till They're as Full of Grace, &amp; Free from Gall, As Void of Pride, as High in Vertue Rare, As much in Reading, and as much in Prayer. Wisdom, with an Inheritance, She had: Her Charities did make her Neighbours Glad. When Darkned with Afflictions, in her Day, Th' Bright Cloudy Pillar Guided still her Way: The Skie O'recast; Yet in her Cittadel The COMFORTER Vouchsaf'd to Shine, &amp; Dwell. Her Faith, Hope, Patience, Holiness, and Love (Thank Heav'ns Free Grace,) did All, most-stedfast prove. Up to the Blessed-Seats, Kind Angels bear Her 'Parted-Soul; With Hallelujahs there: To CHRIST, in Youth, drawn by His Saving charms, Is now Incircled with His Blessed Arms. The Cares of State &amp; Courts are Burdens Great; Grief for her Death is a more Pressing Weight. Behold! Our Samuel to the Utmost Try'd: CHRIST's Alsufficient Grace, Ne're yet Deny'd. Poor Borrowed Greatness dares not to Demur; Th' ALMIGHTY well Accepts your Offerings, SIR. Whole Hecatombs you offer now in ONE; JESUS Remains; You cannot be Undone; Excessive Grief, Saints well may Blush to own. Long may You Stay, to Bless the Church &amp; State! Kind Heav'n, We Hope, will large Years longer Wait. Strong Consolations from th' OMNIPOTENT, Let Fill your Heart, in your thus Emptied Tent! And may your Progeny, still Left you, Stand Sacred to GOD, and Blessings in the Land! Ita humillime Precatur JOHN DANFORTH, V. D. M. Dorcestriae. A FUNERAL POEM IN MEMORY OF MR. HOPESTILL CLAP, Who was for many Years a prudent and faithful Representative of the Town, and one of the Ruling Elders of the Church of Dorchester, who went to his Everlasting rest in the General Assembly of the first born in Heaven, Sept. 2, 1719, Etatis qui Anno 72. To our Great Loss, and his Great Gain. Inroll'd i' th' Number of Christs Witnesses, To Follow Him into a Wilderness; A Blessed Number of This Precious Name, Elect by Heaven, into this Patmos Came. This Saints choice Parents, Pliant to Heavens Call; Grace early Sanctify'd Their Children all. Such a Bright Family, How rarely seen! No Ishmael, Esau, Dinah, found therein. O! Happy Family! O! Glorious sight! Who Do &amp; Bear, for CHRIST, lose nothing by 't. This Family did God vouchsafe to Bless With Copious, and Extensive Usefulness. The Father Held Our Castle without Fear, And was Chief, Pious, Valiant, Bulwark there. Vertuous in Heart, and Useful in their lives Were also his Collateral Relatives. For his Descendants, View the Assembly's List: Long Years, Three Sons in General Court Assist; And in the Ruling Eldership, No less: In whom their Pastors Heart could acquiesce. Our Hopestill, with the food of Angels Fed, His Name, and Fathers Hope well Answered: Converting Mercy and Restraining Grace With their sweet Fruits within his Soul had Place. The Chasma's Closed; The Rec'ning is made even: The Gates of Hell held not his Heart from Heaven. The Hopes of Hypocrites he durst not Cherish; Nor Durst he Rest in Works, where many perish. He did (and so should we, when sin doth seize us) Lose-hold, on all, But GOD's free Grace in JESUS: GOD in Man's Nature; That most Blessed One: On Him he Liv'd, as his High Priest, alone. So while he Liv'd, and when he came to die, CHRISTS Glorious Riches gave him full supply. Such Lives as his, deserve all Observation, Lasting Remembrance, Constant Imitation; Adorned with Goodness, Sweetness, Self Denial, Meekness of Wisdom under every Trial, With Fear of GOD; and Hate of Sinful Strife 'Gainst Strangers, Neighbors, Brethren, Children, Wife. None could Repine; He was so Debonair, So True, so Just, so Kind, so Calm, so Fair; So Valuable (tho' no Son of Thunder), The Church Rejoyc'd when such an Elder Crowned her. While Prayers went up, the Life of CHRIST Descended. Winged with the Dove, his Ravish'd Soul Ascended. Light for th' Upright in Publick Meetings Sown And Private too, He wisely made his own. His House, Feasts of Devotion did afford; Resolv'd, his Family Should Serve the LORD. Thro' Pride his Talents, he would not decline To Use, altho' he could not see them shine: Trusting in GOD; was not reduced to be Unuseful thro' excess of Modestie. No Laws he Brake, altho' he voted many: Fewds he Compos'd, altho' he Raised not any: His Greatness Goodness was; His Victory His Faith; his Honour, his Humility, With Wisdom, Trustiness, Sincerity. His Vertues let us duely Imitate. Our Loss of such a Peace-full Man is Great. Mourn we aright. And may kind Heav'n Afford Widow, and Children, Comfort in the LORD. Amen. An ELEGY upon the much Lamented Decease of MRS. ELISABETH FOXCROFT of Cambridge in New England (late Excellent Consort to the Worshipful Col. Francis Foxcroft, Esq; and Daughter to the Honourable, our late Judge &amp; Deputy-Governour, THOMAS DANFORTH Esq; of blessed Memory,) Whose Funeral was Attended, with great Honour, on the 6th Day of July, 1721. Her Immortal Spirit having been Translated to the Paradise of GOD some Days before. EMINENT Honour, and Esteem, And Goodness too shall be my Theme. The Beauties of the Character No Panegyricks can Declare. Attempts are Vain: Yet Grief will speak; And Duty too must silence break. Most Shining was the Piety Of that Renowned Family, From which (To Heav'n be all the Praise;) This Heroine Extracted was. This Branch Rear'd up Her Graceful Head From th' Chast and Sacred Marriage-Bed: Exciting in Dear Parents Breast, A Thankful Joy, and happy Rest. The main Concern was to obtain Her Clearance from the Guilt and Stain, Of Adam's Sin which reaches All; With new Formation of Her Soul. The MEDIATOR They address; In Prayers of Faith Their Wish Express, A Miracle might Change Her State, Her tender Soul Regenerate, Furnish Her well with Every Grace, And Fix Her in the Heav'nly Race. At Heaven's High Throne of Grace, Their Pray'r And Pious Vows Accepted were; And Love and Power Immense so wrought, She's from a State of Nature brought; Her Parent's Darling's Sanctify'd; Kept Spotless; and now Glorify'd. No Care, no Pains, no Cost were spar'd She might be Polish'd and Prepar'd; Instructions, Counsels were not Waste; Her Orient Soul Implem'd so fast. Unto Dear FOXCROFT She is Given; To Help Him in the Way to Heaven; A Partner of His Joys, and Cares; Which, with His Griefs, She freely Shares: But O! the Blessing, in a Wife! While She Continu'd in this Life! Deceas'd, She leaves this Legacy, A dear and Fragrant Memory. Rare Virtues, in a Rare Degree, Thou Precious Soul! did Shine in Thee: Good Prudence, humble Industry, With undissembled Piety; Amidst Domestick Pains and Care, Thy Tradings still for Heav'n appear. Thy Ripe'ning Time, didst well Imploy For Blessed Immortality. Abundantly didst Thou Inherit That Ornament, the Quiet Spirit. Thy Willing Hand took up the Cross; And Every Furnace Purg'd the Dross. In Meekness, Patience, Charity, Thou didst excel most gloriously. From Thee, the Splendours, that did flow, To Heaven's Refulgent Grace we owe. Thy Children do Thee Blessed Call; Thy Husband Praises Thee; And All Lament the Loss our Land Sustains: Compensate' only by Thy Gains. But, Gracious Soul! What? Must Thou goe? And leave Us, in a World of Woe? Thou Radiant Gem! Thou Glorious Star! Than Rubies Richer, and more Rare! While in the Body, much Desir'd! Most Faithful, Useful, and Admir'd! What? Go so soon? Why? Is this Fair So soon to Leave Thy Children Dear, And let thine Honour'd Head sit down, Deprived of His Joy and Crown? A Crown more Bright than th' Galaxy! Fit to be Worn by Majesty! How could'st, with such a willing Mind, Thy Ransom'd DUST leave here behind! Earth's Magnet lost its Influence, E're Thy Translation did Commence: And many Items of Remove, Fix'd Thine Affections more above. Peace of Dependence held Thee fast: Peace of Rejoycing shone at Last. All Perilous Encounter's o'er; Thou'rt Landed on the Halcyon-shoar; Where Just Men's Spirits Perfect are, And bid Adieu to Pain and Fear. There Meet Thee now Ten Thousand Quires, To Greet Thee with Their Heav'nly Lyres: How sweetly all their Sonnets flow! Far sweeter Melody than here below! Thou Gain'st, But We the Losers are; Thy Work is Praise, still Ours is Prayer; ‘Thy Worthy CONSORT, now in Tears, ‘GOD lengthen out His Useful Years! ‘Conduct His Soul to th' Highest Shore, ‘To meet Thee there and Part no more! ‘As Thou Thy Parents Piety ‘Partook'st, so may Thy Progeny ‘Share Thine! CHRIST's Church Acknowledge will, ‘The Cov'nant-keeping GOD lives still.’ Thy Reverend Son thy Grace Partakes, Heav'ns Herauld, He in Duty makes Thy Virtues, from the Pulpit, Known: By Telling Thine, He shews His Own: May Heav'n His Pious Years &amp; Labours Crown! AMEN. Maestus Composuit, J. Danforth, V. D. M., Dorcestriae. AN ELEGY UPON THE MUCH LAMENTED DECEASE OF THE REVEREND AND EXCELLENT MR. JOSEPH BELCHER, Late Faithful Pastor of the Church of Christ in Dedham, N. E. Qui Obiit, April 27, Anno Dom. 1723. Aetat. Suae 53. THE Name of BELCHER long has Bless'd the State With Heroes in Succession Good and Great: And Bless'd the Church too, with a Radiant Star, A Man of GOD, an Angel-Tutelar. The Sin, we must Arraign, and not the Doom, That brings our Saints and Heroes to the Tomb; Adore the Sovereign Grace, (when they Remove,) That takes their Souls to the blest Seats above. Darker than Midnight, is this Day's Eclipse: We flow in tears upon the Dying Lips; The Lips, that did with heavenly Nectar flow, And every Sabbath Bless the Church below. Such as GOD Honours, we should Honour too; And view their Death as a Presage of woe: May Heav'n Avert it! Such may be Distressed, Whom th' shines for 30 Years have not Impressed. Yet bless we CHRIST, that we may not complain And say, His Faithful Labours were in vain: By this bless'd Instrument, this Heavenly Guide, Many Converted, many Edify'd. Bred in the Eagle's Nest and taught to fly, Travers'd the Circle of Philosophy; Thirsty of Arts, He many an Helicon Drank up, as thirsty Stars drink up the Sun. Made noblest Flights up to the upper Region, Feasted best at the Banquets of Religion. His Learning vast, like Moses and like Paul, To GOD in CHRIST He sacrific'd it all. His Rule and Conduct, Prudent, Steady, Mild, Honour'd the House of GOD and th' Chair he fill'd. His 'Scutcheon, Glorious Vertues; and His Crest Humility, the Crown of all the Rest. By Breath of Heav'n this saving Trumpet blown, The Walls of Jericho came tumbling down. A Friend unto New-England's first-best-ways; To th' Constitution that the Scripture lays. The Teacher Dextrous and Laborious; The Word he Taught, Divinely-Glorious; He liv'd it all: To walk the way He trod, (Prove it who will,) will bring a man to GOD. Stopt is the Conduit-Pipe that did Supply GOD's Holy Church, and many a Family, Abundantly, and that for many a Year: Then Run to the Fount', and take Refreshment there. This Loss so Public of such vast Extent, Christ's Ministers throughout the Land, Lament. Heav'ns Balm we need; for Bitter is the Cup; Great is the Breach: JEHOVAH make it up. Thine Alsufficient Blessing, Gracious LORD! To Consort, Children, and the Church afford! May they in their Distress Depend on THEE; And thy great Goodness now and ever see! The Heavenly Temple, and the Earthly Tomb Have each a part, till th' Resurrection come. Our Part were humbling to the last Degree But that his Dust united is with THEE, Blest JESUS! waiting till the Jubilee, And that there's left us, His Immortal Memorie. Sic Condoluit, J. DANFORTH The DIVINE NAME Humbly Celebrated, On Occasion of the Translation to Heaven of the Bright Soul of the Pious and Vertuous, MADAM SUSANNA THACHER Late Consort of the Reverend Mr. PETER THACHER, Pastor of the Church of CHRIST in Milton. September 4. Anno Domini 1724. Ætatis Suae 59. O SUN of Righteousness! Inspire our Tongue! Sacred to Heav'n shall be Our Funeral Song. Th' ALMIGHTY, Not our Broken-Selves, Our Theme, HIM will we Sing, and we will Sing TO HIM. We'll Sing to HIM, who MAKER is of All; But is Himself without Original: To HIM alone whose All-Creating Turn Drew Real Substance out of Nothing's Urn: To HIM alone whose Wondrous Word and Art Made Flames Leap out and Glorious Spirits start; Adorning those Sublime Vitalities With Rare Abilities and Qualities. We'll Sing to HIM, the Word who did but say, A Spacious, Numerous World did Him Obey, Come into Being, and their Homage Pay: Made Thinking SOULS, in DUST polite and terse, To View His Glories on the Universe, (Once very Good;) and in His Glorious SON, Who Saves th' Elect, who had Themselves Undone. We'll Sing His Grace, who made Two Stars Combine And in One Wedlock-Constellation Shine, In Bright Conjunction, to Irradiate The Darkned Times of the Domestick State: Vile Antichrist alone forbad the Band; Not HE, who holds the Stars in His Right Hand. We'll Sing HIS Praise, who made the Star we see Just now Ascending to her Apoge, A Practick Transcript of the Heav'nly Volume; Each Line and Letter Bright, in every Column; Loyal to Heaven; True to her Earthly Guide; In THACHER's Halls, Six Lustres do Abide A Blessing Rare; And near One Lustre more Unto Another MAN OF GOD before. We'll Sing HIS Thanks who Sanctify'd Her Youth; And Fill'd Her Soul with Grace, Her Mind with Truth; The Law of Kindness at her Lips, Sent forth, Than Worlds of Shining Gold and Pearls more worth; Made Her not Trust in Duties, but yet Love 'em; Be much in Duties, and yet much above 'em; Trusting the Merits of Her Glorious HEAD; With the Wise Virgins Oil Replenished, Most inexhaustibly to Her Supply'd, Death to Outlive, and Endlesly Abide: Makes Momus Swoon at mention of Her Name, Th' Infernal Fangs not Fastning on Her Fame. We'll Sing HIS Praise, who to an Orb much Higher Removes this Saint, this Gem of Our Desire; Can We or She Her Taking hence Repine? We see the Cause presents an Anodyne. We'll Sing HIS Care Paternal and Dear Love; He doth not Both Bright Stars at once Remove; Still Abram stays us to Irradiate, Tho' 'tis His Pleasure Sarah to Translate. We'll Sing the Power that makes Him bear the Smart Of Joynts divuls'd, with an Undaunted Heart: One Partner's gone, yet He's not left alone: His GOD is with Him; CHRIST and He make One. H' Works in Bright Flames of Mysteries Divine, To Enlighten Souls; CHRIST makes Him strongly shine. We'll Sing, by Heavens Good Leave, ‘Shine may He long! And Late, the Cherubims be Plac'd among.’ But, ah polluted Lips, and Songs, and Layes! We must Go Higher, to Sing JEHOVAH's Praise. May HE our Souls, and His own Sion Raise. Amen. Humilime Offert. J. D. Two vast Enjoyments commemorated, and two great Bereavements lamented, in two excellent Persons, viz. the Reverend Mr. PETER THACHER And the Reverend Mr. SAMUEL DANFORTH, Pastor of the Church of CHRIST in Milton, who was born into this World July 18. Anno Dom. 1651. and ascended to a better World, December 17. Anno Dom. 1727. Aetatis 77. and in the 47th of his Pastorate. Pastor of the Church of CHRIST in Taunton, whose Nativity was December 18. Anno Dom. 1666. and his Translation to the heavenly Paradise, November 14. Anno Dom. 1727. Fifteen Days after the first Shock of the great Earthquake in New-England. WHAT! Without Feeling? Don't we make Pretense, In some Degree, unto that vital Sense? Dumb too! and would be press'd to Death as Mutes? Angels use speaking Arts: but rarely Brutes. Lisp we no Ecchoes to the dismal Sound, From Caverns and Convulsions under Ground? To th' Peals from the charg'd Chambers of the Skies? To th' Voice from Temples of the LORD most High? To th' Shrieks from the bereav'd BRITANNICK THRONE, And Realms; Great GEORGE's Death that loudly groan? When Warning-Pieces great are fired and shot; When shook, and struck, and call'd, answer we not? Blind Eyes, deaf Ears, hard Hearts, bind fast the Tongue: What frightful Maladies upon us throng? O SON of David Mercy on us shew! Restore our Souls! Our spiritual Sense renew! From Blindness, Deafness, Hardness, instantly LORD! If thou wilt, Thou can'st our Souls set free. We'll then with Thanks review Enjoyments past, For poor Improvements we will be abas'd. Our late Bereavements we will lay to Heartt; But most of all, GOD's Wrath, and our Desert. We long enjoy'd a Sky, that did refrain; An Earth, that Terra Firma did remain; And not Infirma, but a quiet Seat; Groan'd not so loud, to make our Hearts to beat. Long were we bless'd with GEORGE's Influence, By whom GOD gave us great Deliverance. Th' ascended LORD long favour'd us with Lights To Shine vile Rebels into Favourites. The Council-Board, the Bench, the sacred Desk Long shone with Heroes, who are now at Rest. CHRIST's two last aged Shepherds tarried long, His dear, (but now bereaved) Flocks among. View their paternal and maternal Lines, Both of them sprang from many great Divines, Honour'd in England, and New-England too, For Service they for CHRIST, and's Church did do. Angels, per Saltum, took their high Degree, Commencing Spirits, from Non-Entity, These Angels of our Churches, Babes first were; How excellent the Mothers that them bare? Again they both were New-Born of the SPIRIT: And both great double-Portions did inherit, Of the rare Spirit of the bless'd ELIJAHS, Whose Mantles fell to these good young ABIJAHS. What Man (since Miracles are ceas'd) e're gains, Without the Teachers, and the Learners Pains, And th' Blessing upon both, from GOD most High, Sufficient Knowledge in the Mystery Of Arts, of Languages, and of Religion To qualify for the Prophetick-Vision? GOD bless'd the Pains, (bless'd be His glorious Name!) To both of these, that quickly they became (Like well-taught Pegasuss) thorow-pac'd; Before they were with College-Laurels grac'd. Their Temper far from Injucundity; Their Tongues and Pens from Infacundity. Solid and Grave, yet pleasant they were each; Lest any should of Starch'dness them impeach. In Med'cine, and in civil Laws, well read Were Luke and Zenas; for their Neighbours Need. Each, on Occasion, might few Minutes lend, To Advise a Sick or an exposed Friend: Both these our Pastors very Skilful were, Like Luke the one, th' other like Zenas rare. Their Usefulness thence flowing, by the by, How full of Piety and Charity! All to their Office-Work subordinated; A Work unrivall'd, not to be check-mated. A Work, upon the Wheels forever going; A Work (whatever else was done) still doing. A Work for which they left no Stone unturn'd; A Work for which the Indian-Tongue they learn'd, Th' Indians in their own Language had their Lectures, All full of CHRIST, and Grace, and Heav'nly Nectars. But th' English mainly had their Pains and Care, To th' English they were Angels Tutelar. High in Employments, but not high in Pride, Their HIGH-EMPLOYER was their Guard and Guide. To batter Sin they mighty were: For Zeal Chariots and Horsemen of our Israel. Their Churches were by them (as Bulwarks strong) From Vice (thank the MOST HIGH) defended long: While the Resistless Sword was in their Hand, Agags were hewn to Pieces in their Land. 'Gainst Sin did Lions in GOD's Cause appear, But in their own, they Lambs for Meekness were. They left a sacred Stamp, where e're they trod; Their Lives-Right-Steps shew'd Men the Way to GOD: They both were to their Flocks unblotted Paterns; And of all Godliness and Virtue Patrons. Shepherds they were, the Sheep who right did guide; And who seducing Wolves could not abide. Both wrought with GOD, and wrought by Faith and Prayer, Both wrought for GOD, and were His tender Care. Both many thousand sacred Sermons preach'd, That th' Ears and Hearts of many Hundreds reach'd. Most bounteously GOD answered their Desire, Hard Hearts would melt by their seraphick Fire. Their Prayers and Prophecyings (by Heav'ns Might) Rais'd up dead Souls, restor'd the Blind to sight. Right noble Wisdom thus each of 'em had; Wise to win Souls, to make their SAVIOUR glad. Careful they were CHRIST's Sheep should never feed On Arian, Popish or Arminian Weed. Careful lest worldly Lusts should hot pursue 'em, Bad Company and Pleasures should undo 'em. Careful to bring 'em from destructive Things, To the safe Shelter of bless'd JESUS's Wings. For Foresight and good Forecast, few their Match: Were ever on their Guard, and on their Watch. Both Men and Things they studied well, and knew; Their Bow they seldom at Adventure drew. In Councils frequent and in Travels oft; Success (like joyful Streamers) seen aloft. But I omit whole Volumes yet behind; So great Enjoyments tell us GOD is kind. Lustres of Years (though fit for Heaven) they stood, By CHRIST continued, for His Churches good. Their precious useful Memory remains, For wise Improvers everlasting Gains. Who gain'd no Gold by these Aurifick-Stones, Have Reason now to make their doleful Moans. Our Loss in their Remove is far from finall, Who were such copious Blessings unto all. May Heaven, that takes our Treasures, make Retrievements! Else Bankrupts are undone by such Bereavements. Levi'thans they who do not (for their Part) The wounding-Warnings duely lay to heart. Portended Ills prevent! most gracious GOD! Make all take Warning, by thy speaking Rod! Bereaved Families, and Flocks with Tears, Ask tender Sympathy, and fervent Prayers: May Heav'ns kind Ears receive their Lamentations! Give, LORD! Their weakned Hearts strong Consolations. Amen. Ita humillime precatur J. D.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TWO FRAGMENTS OF ELEGIES Upon the decease of the pious Mr. Thomas Bromfield, aged twelve years, the second son of the Honourable Edward Bromfield, Esq. Feb. 8, 1709/10. Bright and sweet soul! just long enough in sight To charm affection, and attract delight; How soon ascended to the Heavenly Sphere! So angels quickly vanish, that appear. His early death, doctrine and use afford, And reason too for turning to the Lord. Profit by this! we'll Heavenly Grace adore, Although he never preach a sermon more. Nature and Grace are mourners at this sight, But 'tis religion gives to mourn aright. Charming the musick in the Heavenly ears, While Christ is bottling of your trickling tears. Elegy on the Death of Captain Jonathan Danforth. d. Billerica, Sept. 7, 1712, a. 84. He rode the circuit, chain'd great towns and farms, To good behavior; and by well marked stations, He fixed their bounds for many generations. His art ne'er failed him, though the loadstone failed, When oft by mines and streams it was assailed. All this is charming, but there's something higher, Gave him the lustre which we most admire.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">MISCELLANEOUS POEMS ALMANAC VERSE (1679) March TH' Imperial Prince of Light shall now arise, And banish darkness from the Cloudy Skyes, And having won and worn the Golden Fleece Will promise unexhausted Springs of Peace: But yet in's HORNED forehead you may read That now the Queen of heav'n is Queen indeed, Who's Face shall screen the Earth fro's scorching Ray, And so this Equal moneth shall March away. April NOw such as all their food to Labour owe The rugged Earth and Surging Sea must plow: The Farmer joye's when he (his Labour ended) With Showrs of Blessing, see's his toile attended, Fair Winds on Seamen, work the same effect When to the Hav'n, their course clear Heav'ns direct. But first i' th' Cloded Earth the Seed must dy, Or 'twill not to the Ploughman multiply. May THe subtil Chymists now begin to act, Who Quintessential virtues will extract That so from bitter weeds Sweet may proceed To serve the Rich mans pleasure, Poor mans need. Now Freemen in their Liberty rejoyce Of Choisest men to make a Worthy choice; The which, who e're are wise or otherwise This moneth agree with joy to Solemnize. June OUr Lights one Phenix now doth lightly fall Into the bosome of his Cardinall: The Cattled Earth he doth compassionate: And to her speeds apace in Pompous state: But seing Saturns Chariot very neer He cryes adue! and Posts away for fear. Solsticial Heat's and Cold's each in their time, Do much distemper this our Temp'rate Clime. July THe noble Ships, which the vast Ocean try, And nothing neer them see, but Sea and Sky, Now homeward with their Wings advance apace, And having periodiz'd their restless race: The Merchants house will fill with plenteous Store, But Silver Angels onely ope' the dore: The Sun from th' Lyon now will make retreit In truth 'twould joy a blind man much to se it. August BY Planet's Vote this sound surrounds the Sky, The Garland giv'n must be to Mercury: When to the Peerless Sun (who scorners scorn's) The Dog shalt shew his heels, the Moon her horns: To all (but Doctours now) the seeds of Woe May quick be sown, by such sweet fruits as doe First give th' Inamour'd eye a pleasant taste And then between the watering teeth are plac't. September THe Starry Ballance now doth poized stay, The Golden Talent of our time to weigh; Whereof each moments value far surmounts All Finite numbers and conceiv'd accounts; He may expect no fruitfull harvest now, His Springing Seed who did neglect to sowe, Wheras the Prudent Farmers constant care Provides enough to spend and some to spare. October DIana's dwelling Saturn doth possess, And Jove to Citharea doth no less: Apollo joynes with Hermes to destroy And rob poor Venus of her house and joy: VVhilest that Lucina's Courses do decide VVhat Changes shall both Winds &amp; Tides betide, Her head and horns unto the Earth she'l show, That thirteen Moons unto the doz'n may go. November NOW Sol and Venus take their sweet repast And blust'ring Boreas storm's the world: At last Joynd with Appolo's foll'wer Mercury His Edicts Echoe round the spangled sky: Whose thundring voyse ('though all ye world withstand it) Will never Court attention, But Command it. Whose thunder-threats you need not fear or flee, If Winter-tite your Woollen brestplates bee. December NOW he that time's our Time &amp; rules the Light Doth make our Shortest Day &amp; longest Night, And in his Antique Mode, his Chariot turn's, And to our Artick world with Cold return's. The Fal is fal'n &amp; Winter holds his throne. Doom's idle hands to Cold: when Such alone Who Sowe the Seed of Diligence in Time, Shall Reap Heats harvest in the Coldest Clime. January WHite Winter now our loss of heat repairs With th' New years Guift of clear &amp; healthy Aires. A cleanly Dish Indeed! (and so 't had need) Whereon each minute every man must feed. And now the Potent Blasts of Mercury, Will chain the Northern Seas and Surges high, And each confine unto his proper seat While living Springs retaine their native heat. February SOL ended hath this YEAR: But not his Race, But thither whence he came, He speeds apace. Seed time and Harvest shall with Cold and Heat (While th' Earth endures) retain their proper seat; So neither Winter nor shall Summer miss Their wonted Courses: And a Time there is All Sublunary Labours to begin, Except (which every day we do) to Sin. O' th' large Extent of Time this Year hath shown, The Instant only can we call Our own. EPITAPH ON JOSIAH FLINT A man of God he was, so great, so good, His highest worth was hardly understood So much of God &amp; Christ in him did dwell. In grace &amp; holyness he did excell. An honor &amp; an ornament thereby Both to ye Church and ye Ministry. Most zealous in ye work of reformation To save this selfdestroying generation With courage strove gainst all this peoples sin He spent his strength his life his soul therein Consumd with holy zeal for God for Whome He livd &amp; dy.d a kind of martyrdome If men will not lament their hearts not breake No wonder this lamenting stone doth speake His tomb stone crys Repent &amp; souls to save Doth prach repentance from his very grave Gainst sinners doth as lasting record lye This monument to his blesd memory. Psal IIX Prov. 10. 7. POEMS FOR COTTON MATHER'S MAGNALIA Cottonus Matherus Anagr. Tu tantum Cohors es. Epigramma. Ipse, vales Tantum, Tu, mi memorande MATHERE, Fortis pro Christo Miles, es ipse cohors. A Pindaric. Art thou Heavens Trumpet? sure by the Archangel blown; Tombs Crack, Dead Start, Saints Rise, are seen and known, And Shine in Constellation; From ancient Flames here's a New Phoenix flown, To shew the World, when Christ Returns, he'll not Return alone. A FEW LINES TO FILL UP A VACANT PAGE WO worth the Days! The Days I spent I' th' Regions of Discontent; Where I nought rightly understood, But thought Good, Evil; Evil, Good; Friends I deem'd Foes; Wrong I conceiv'd was done me; I Swell'd &amp; Rage'd, whole Heaven could not Atone me: My Soul ('tis known) was not my Own, so far it had undone me. Health, Fame, and Wealth were full of Stings; Children, and Friends were no such Things; My wholesome food was Poison'd all, And Hony did but Swell my Gall; God was no God, Christ was no Christ to me, While thus I Drave in Discontentments Sea: Thank this first Vice, that Adam e're lost Paradice, and me. Thus being Lost, wrong Course I Steerd While neither Sun, nor Stars appear'd Instead of Heav'n's Land, I made Hell, I knew't by its Sulphureous Smell: Coming on Waters, strait my LORD spy'd I; Avaunt, Foul Fiend! Avoid, fell Foe! Cry'd I; So vilely I mistook, and therefore spake foul Blasphemy. 'Tis I, quoth He, Be not Afraid. Which Words He had no sooner said, But all my Discontents resil'd; The Ruffling Winds, and Waves were still'd; By what Time, Faith and Hope my Sailes could hoise, I got safe and firm Anch'rage in a trice, Within the very inmost Bays of Blissfull Paradice. EPITAPH ON MIRIAM WOOD A Woman well beloved of all her neighbours, from her care of small Folks education, their number being great, that when she dy'd she scarsely left her mate. So Wise, Discreet, was her behaviors that she was well esteemed by neighbours. She liv'd in love with all to dy So let her rest eternally. LOVE and UNITY ENCOURAGED AND CONTENTION and DIVISION DISSWADED, in a POEM. THe Costly Nard, on Jesus Feet, Was dutifully Plac'd: Light finger'd Judas vilely Cry'd, What meaneth all this Waste? His Discontent at mild Reproof, Shot forth in Wrath and Strife, And Consultations of Revenge Against the Lord of Life. By Giving of the Pascal Sop, The Traitor was detected, The Supper of the Lord came on; He being first Ejected. Christ's Sufferings hastened on apace, And He Prepar'd to Die, His Will and Testament Declar'd, And His last Legacie: And thus Began; The Son of Man Is Glorify'd Hereby; And in Him, God is Glorify'd, And shall Him Glorify. My Children Dear! Saith He, I go Where yet you cannot Come, (By Whom much Work is to be done, Before your Martyrdome.) Know all Men, Ye are Mine: Let All My NEW Commandment View, That Ye must One Another Love, As I have Loved you. This New Command is Mine; This Test If you Endure, when Try'd, And keep my Law, you in my Love, And Favour shall Abide. This Precept I'l Repeat, and say My Love, that's wondrous Great Unto you all, you labor shall By Love, to Imitate. Yea to my Friends, I'l say't again, (Lest you Forgetful prove;) I strictly do Command, That you Shall One Another Love. My Loves sweet Fruits, the Comforter Shall then to you Impart, A Life of Fruitfulness shall shew Your Heav'nly Joyful Heart. Abundantly when you shall Ask The Father in My Name, By all Our Truth, and Love, and Power, We will Perform the same. Much more He Spake, Ending at length, His Farewel Exhortation; Then to His Father turn'd, and made His Fervent Supplication. O FATHER! Glorify thy SON; WHO Glorifys Thee still, And Gives to Men Eternal Life According to Thy Will. My Taught-Apostles Sanctify; From Evil keep them Free: As Holy FATHER! We are ONE! ONE also Let Them be. Not for the World, But Them I Pray, And Such as shall Believe On Me, by vertue of the Word, They shall of Them receive, As Thou'rt in Me, &amp; I in Thee, In Glorious Unitie, One in the Father and the Son, That They may also be; In Truth &amp; Faith &amp; Amitie That every Christian Brother Be Joyned unto Me and Thee, And All to One Another. The World doth Hate 'em, &amp; will Strive To Rob their outward Rest; With God, with Conscience, &amp; with Saints My Peace shall make them Bless'd. My Peace to them I therefore give; My Peace I with them leave; May they Enjoy 't, till I shall them Unto My Self Receive. To Purchase Love and Unity, Dear Saviour! Thou hast bled, And to pursue 'em, all thy Saints Under strong bands hast laid. That these thy precious Legacies, They surely may Inherit, Inherent and Assisting Grace Are offer'd, by Thy Spirit. How is it then (since Thou has made Such plentiful Provision, For Love and Unity) we find Contention and Division! Those Blessings, if we don't enjoy, The Fault and Blame's our own: We've shut up Heav'n, if they descend Not from that Glorious Throne. The Means and End lie close Conjoyn'd In the Divine Decree: Thou wait'st but till we use the means, And well prepared be: Thy Laws neglected, lose their Force; Thy Promise is not Heeded; Judgment on Murmurers takes Place; So Grace is Superseded; Our Meribahs are Multiply'd, As if we were Possess'd; Our Loose Affections soon Divide; For Trifles, we Contest. Our Honour's trampled under foot; Our Crown is made Profane; To many Souls, while Strife is rife, The Means of Grace are vain. The Storms grow long, the hopeful seeds Under the Clods grow rotten; The Blasted Years of strife do make The plenteous years forgotten; By Hot Contention's Thunderbolts Are Temples rent in twain; Armies of Abels too, Advance, Arm'd with the Clubs of Cain. Batter'd and Shatter'd by such Storms, Are best mens Reputations; In vain they talk, while strife is loud, of working Reformations. And by strife's means, much Pray'r is stop'd And much is turn'd to Sin: It breaks all Dams; so Hells black Waves Amain come tumbling in. Setting aside the Fear of God, And violently mov'd By Instigation of the Devil, Thousands of times (it's prov'd) This wicked strife has broke the Peace In Christian Families, In Kingdoms, Provinces and Towns, Churches and Colonies; It has Eclips'd, to great Degree, Each Radiant Quality, That gave 'em greatest likeness to Th' Eternal Deity. Their Wisdom, Justice, Holiness, Long suffering, Clemency, Their Meekness and Indulgence too, Love and Benignity, God's Great and Glorious Name also Strife vilely doth Despise, And what God's Soul Abominates Doth to Him Sacrifice. The Halt and Sick and Mutilated (Which God doth not desire) It doth upon His Altar burn, All with Unhallowed Fire. An Enemy to the Vitals 'tis; Seizing both Heart and Head; Many that seem'd Alive before, It's Poysonous Breath strikes Dead. To flay this fiery Dragon strife, Where's the Effectual Dart? O Saints! God's Word's the pow'rful sword That Stabs it to the Heart: Let Faith God's Promises improve, And Fear His Threatnings Weild, And Conscience stand by His Command, And Strife will soon be Kill'd. And is't a Plague, then call for Pray'r; Our Churches often prove it; No Hand but what inflicted it Is able to Remove it. Then set His Hand on work by Pray'r, Add Faith and Fasting to it; If 't's possible to cast it out, This Heav'nly Course will do it. Cutting Rebukes for to forbear No such Forbearance is As Christ will own, when milder means Encourage the Disease. Yet when Constrain'd to Cut and Lance, Be sure you mourn and weep, And tremble, lest by any means, Your Lancet pierce too deep. For things, in Notion, Disputable, Not inconsistent with Faith, Love, and New Obedience, Do not Strifes Sword Unsheath. If you must needs come to Debate, You greatly ought to fear it: And for such Trial of Self-denial, Bring a submitting Spirit, Knowing your weakness, come (I say) With some degree of terrour, Lest truth and right you would assert, Should suffer by your Errour. Be not of Evil Overcome: Be good invincibly; That ill men by your goodness great, At length may vanquish't be. Do Churlish Neighbors not deserve, Your Pardons Peace and Kindness, Yet Christ deserves; if you can't see't 'Tis owing to your Blindness. Whoso desires that He himself, And others live at Rest, Must Hear and See, with Charity, And wisely Say the best. Be deaf to Tatling Tale-bearers; Credit not all Reports; Avoid the Charms of Whisperers; Forbear all sharp Retorts; Would you not have the Sun seem Red, Put by the Heliotrope; If you'd not hear the Clapper strike, Then do not pull the Rope; If you'd not have the Blood burst forth, The nose then do not wring; Do not disturb the wasps or bees, If you'd avoid their sting; Would you not have your Glass-house broke, Then throwing stones forbear; Would you prevent a Powder blast, Then let no Coals come near; Remove the Leaven you see laid Before it be fermented; Occasions of Disturbance, let Be Carefully Prevented; Forbear when Censures you receive, Like Censures to return; Of Fire-balls make no Foot balls, lest You Towns and Churches burn. Are Spirits roil'd and blood inflam'd With Feavour to Convulsion; Purge sharp and peccant humours well, And make a quick Revulsion. From the hot Caldron pluck the brands, If you'd not have it boil; VVould you not have the swelling burst, Then supple it with Oyl. Although for outward quietness, POWERS are and LOTS ordain'd, Yet Lotts, and Law-suits rarely use, Lest they and Peace be stain'd. Common Received Customs Good Resolve, not to oppose; Nor violently to impose Whate're you shall propose. In Doubtful Things and Difficult, Be not too Peremptory; Suspect, suspend your judgment then, And be not Refractory. Would you've good Peace and Unity And Friendship with a Brother, In Lawful Things let ev'ry one Both serve and please each other. Offences neither give nor take; Pray God to make you Wise; Let Patience have its perfect work; Meekness it's Exercise; All Envy and Vexatious Wrath, Well mortify you must; Contention comes by Pride, this Pride It must be ground to Dust; Lastly, break not your Peace with God; His Laws keep as your Life, If you'l secure your mutual Peace And not be plagu'd with Strife. Prov, 16. 7. EPITAPH ON HOPESTILL CLAP His Dust Waits Till The Jubile Shall Then Shine Brighter Than ye Skie Shall meet &amp; joine (to Part no more) His Soul That's Glorify'd Before Pastors &amp; Churches Happy Be With Ruling Elders Such As He Present Usefull Absent Wanted Liv'd Desired Died Lamented THE MERCIES of the YEAR COMMEMORATED: A SONG for Little CHILDREN in NEW-ENGLAND. December 13th 1720. (1) Heaven's MERCY shines, Wonders &amp; Glorys meet; Angels are left in sweet surprise to see 't. The Circle of the Year is well near Run Earth's-Conflagration is not yet begun. (2) Heavens spares the Bulwark of our Peace, King GEORGE; Our CHARTER holds; and Privileges large. Our GOVERNOUR and SENATORS can meet; And Greet, and Join in Consultations sweet. (3) Though Great our Loss in GREENWOOD's bless'd Translation Yet well fill'd Pulpits bless the Little Nation. New Churches Gather'd; Th' Eastern Peace not lost; And Satan's overthrown with all his Host. (4) Sickness from Distant Lands Arrives, and Fears; JEHOVAH in the Mount as oft Appears. Contagion stops with Precious Captain GORE; How Great our Loss? but Heav'n will draw no more. (5) Tho' ripening HEAT came late, yet Frost held off, We Reap the Harvest, and have Bread enough. Provision's dear, Goods high, Bills low, Cash none; And yet the Suffering Tribe is not Undone. (6) A Miracle! The Ocean-Seas of Sin, Have not prevail'd to let a Deluge in! That Earth's upheld to bear the heavy Load! Adore the Grace of a Long suffering GOD! (7) Some Vices in the Church not yet subdu'd; Old Barren Vines and Trees not yet down hew'd. Sinners, not sent to their Deserved Place; A YEAR is added to their DAY of Grace. (8) The Fugitive may be returned home; The Foe to GOD, a Favourite become. Who have no shelter from Thy Jealous Eye, JESUS! for shelter to thy Wounds may Fly. (9) The whole Years Space for Faith, Repentance, Prayer; The Most have not improved well, I Fear: Look then, with broken Hearts, upon your ways; And see, your Future Lives, JEHOVAH Praise. THE VANITY OF THE WORLD, A POEM. I WHAT if a Day, or a Month, or a Year, Crown thy Delights with a Thousand sweet contentings, May not the Chance of a Night or an Hour, Cross thy Delights with as many sad lamentings. Fortune, Honour, Beauty, Youth, are but Blossoms dying; Wanton Pleasures, doating Love, are but shadows flying: All our Joys are but Toys, idle Thoughts deceiving; None has Power of an Hour, to his Life retrieving. II The Earth's but a Point of the World; and a Man Is but a Point to the Earth's compared Center:— Shall then a Point of a Point be so vain, As to triumph in a silly Points adventure.— All is hazard that we have, there is nothing 'biding, Days of Pleasure are like Streams, thro' fair Meadows gliding; Weal or Woe, Time doth go; Time hath no returning;— Secret Fates guide our States, both in Mirth and mourning. III What hast thou then, silly Man, for to boast, But of a sad, and a sorrowful Life perplexed, When Heart and Hope, and the Fancy at best, Then Grief and Fear with despair are annexed. Blossoms, Ashes, Earth and Bell, doth thy State resemble; Fear of Sickness, Death and Hell, should make thee to tremble. Every Thing that doth spring, soon is ripe, soon rotten! Pomp and Pride, soon doth slide, soon they are forgotten. IV So soon as Death shall have ended thy Race, And cut the Thread of thy Life,—thy Soul is ascending, Into it's Rest, 'foredeemed the Place, Whither thy Thoughts, Words and Works, were ever 'tending. Death doth hasten, and the Grave, waiteth for thy coming; Neither Friends nor Foes can save, thou art thither running. Every Day taketh away part of thy Time flying; Therefore strive, whilst alive, to be fit for dying.</field>
   </doc>
</add>