<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Woolson, Constance Fenimore, 1840-1894</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Woolson, Constance Fenimore, 1840-1894</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">woolson constance fenimore 1840 1894</field>
      <field name="author_text">Woolson, Constance Fenimore, 1840-1894</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1930's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ap/uvaGenText/tei/chap_AM1002.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240350</field>
      <field name="date_text">[1931]</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:440428</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">[Poems by Woolson in] Five generations (1785-1923 ; being scattered chapters from the history of the Cooper, Pomeroy, Woolson and Benedict families, with extracts From their Letters and Journals, as well as articles and poems by Constance Fenimore Woolson</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">[Poems by Woolson in] Five generations (1785-1923 ; being scattered chapters from the history of the Cooper, Pomeroy, Woolson and Benedict families, with extracts From their Letters and Journals, as well as articles and poems by Constance Fenimore Woolson</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poems by woolson in five generations 1785 1923</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poems by woolson in five generations 1785 1923</field>
      <field name="title_text">[Poems by Woolson in] Five generations (1785-1923 ; being scattered chapters from the history of the Cooper, Pomeroy, Woolson and Benedict families, with extracts From their Letters and Journals, as well as articles and poems by Constance Fenimore Woolson</field>
      <field name="year_display">[1931]</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1931</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1931</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440428&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440428&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Woolson, Constance Fenimore, 1840-1894&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;woolson constance fenimore 1840 1894&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;[Poems by Woolson in] Five generations (1785-1923 ; being scattered chapters from the history of the Cooper, Pomeroy, Woolson and Benedict families, with extracts From their Letters and Journals, as well as articles and poems by Constance Fenimore Woolson&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poems by woolson in five generations 1785 1923&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;[1931]&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1931&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Woolson, Constance Fenimore&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1840&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1894&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;[Poems by Woolson in] Five generations (1785-1923)&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;being scattered chapters from the history of the Cooper, Pomeroy, Woolson and Benedict families, with extracts From their Letters and Journals, as well as articles and poems by Constance Fenimore Woolson&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Ellis&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;[1931]&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3866227-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;cham1002&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;[Poems by Woolson in] Five generations (1785-1923)&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;being scattered chapters from the history of the Cooper, Pomeroy, Woolson and Benedict families, with extracts From their Letters and Journals, as well as articles and poems by Constance Fenimore Woolson&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1996&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1996 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 65 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only poems by Woolson included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-AmPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Voices out of the past. LAKE ERIE IN SEPTEMBER. Oh, gray and sullen sky! Oh, gray and sullen beaches! Oh, gray and sullen billows, coming rolling, rolling in! Oh, are ye not aweary of chill September dreary, With days so gray the earth knows not when its gray nights begin? All through the summer noons, all through the summer twilights, Came the vessels, snowy winged, gayly sailing, sailing by; Your waters then were dancing, your beaches gold were glancing, While the south wind blew the sunbeams and moonbeams through the sky. At times the east wind came, the east wind off the ocean, And vessels from Ontario went sweeping, sweeping past— From prairies blew the west wind, of all the winds the best wind, And Huron's fleet went scudding down the lake upon its blast. But now your winds are still, your sluggish waves are sullen, The cheerless rain, nor fast nor slow, is dropping, dropping down; The beach below is soggy, the air above is foggy, And one dark ship, with ragged sail, is lying off the town. Oh, gray and sullen sky! Oh, gray and sullen beaches! Why lie ye here in lethargy, all glooming, glooming pale? If not the summer's soft rest, then why not have the tempest? If ye cannot have the zephyr, then why not have the gale? And since the summer's gone, gray sky to winter darken, And shadow all these sullen waves to inky, inky black— Let these dull forests bristle, as loud the fierce winds whistle, And sweep that one dark ship, a wreck, adown the foaming track. Wake up, wake up, O Lake! and lash your sluggish waters In fury, till your whole expanse is raging, raging mad— Well may it be wrong-doing if it but be strong-doing! Give us one thing or the other: strong! whether good or bad. For the very heart is sad with this monotone of Nature, The very soul is palsied with this half-drawn, half-drawn breath; A gray sky is most dreary, a gray life the most weary, If all our sunny life is gone, then forth! to fight with Death. OFF THUNDER BAY. A Legend of Lake Huron 1772. “We sail, we sail in our Mackinac boat; Over old Huron on we go; Above, above us the summer clouds float, Sailing aloft, as we sail below; Behind us the north wind sings in our wake, Wing-and-wing he bears us away; And off to the right o'er the sparkling lake Looms up the headland of Thunder Bay.” Her brown hands toy with the flowers in her lap— Spicy juniper, balsam sweet; Her black hair waves from her red-beaded cap Down to her little moccasined feet, “Alone with ourselves, alone with our love, Wing-and-wing through the summer day, We sail below, and the clouds sail above, O'er the deep waters off Thunder Bay.” Up on the Evergreen Isle in the north, The Indian mother silent waits; The old French father strides back and forth, And hails the ship coming through the straits: “Ho, brave voyageur, our child hast thou seen— Petite Marie, Flower of the Snow? We find but the fringe of her mantle green, The print of her foot off Tuskenoe.” “Ah, oui, Antoine,” cries the voyageur. “Down on Huron her boat we met; But a blue-eyed stranger was with La Fleur, And all the canvas was southward set, The wind was fair, the boat sailed at its best, Wing-and-wing went dancing away; They sailed south-east, we were tacking north-west, We passed each other off Thunder Bay.” O'er the island fort the English flag waves; English soldiers pace to and fro; Behind, the plateau with Indian graves, A little French town on the beach below. The old commander comes down from the height, Hails the vessel with pompous mien: “A young subaltern escaped last night— A boat sailing southward have you seen?” “Ah oui, Capitaine” cries the voyageur, Bowing before the gold-laced form; “We saw a young soldier with sweet La Fleur; We caught the gleam of his uniform; Two lovers behind, and two sails before; Wing-and-wing they vanished away— First a sail, then a speck, then nothing more, Save the blue offing of Thunder Bay.” The Indian mother soon passed away— Passed away with her fading race: But year after year, and day after day, French Antoine watched with eager face— Watched the long point of the green Bois-Blanc shore, Watched for his child with longing pain, Watched for the sail-boat that came back no more, Watched out his lingering life in vain. The cross of St. George came down from the height; Stars and Stripes wave in Huron's breeze; A hundred long years have rolled into night, A navy dots the fresh-water seas; But still the lake sailors see the white sails, Wing-and-wing on a summer day; As the boat glides past them the soldier hails, And they hear his song off Thunder Bay. “We sail, we sail in our Mackinac boat; Over old Huron on we go; Above, above us the summer clouds float, Sailing aloft as we sail below; Behind us the north-wind sings in our wake, Wing-and-wing he bears us away; And off to the right o'er the sparkling lake, Looms up the headland of Thunder Bay.” PINE-BARRENS. Abroad upon the Barrens, the Florida Pine-Barrens, Where all the winds of heaven come to gambol wild and free, With none to watch their races, save the flowers whose little faces Look up with wonder as they rush across from sea to sea. Abroad upon the Barrens, how wide the mighty heavens! A thousand times more sky above than hangs o'er any town, For nothing breaks its clearness in the farness or the nearness, From zenith to horizon far rounding bluely down. Abroad upon the Barrens the Southern pine-tree ripens Its spicy cones in plumy green that swayeth soft on high: Not closely set in vistas like its sober Northern sisters, But each alone in feathery grace against the tropic sky. Abroad upon the Barrens the saw-palmetto reddens The ground with arméd ranks that firm for centuries have stood; They kneel and pray to Heaven that their sins may be forgiven, Their long green knives in readiness, bold outlaws of the wood! Abroad upon the Barrens the care-worn soul awakens From brooding on the long hard paths its weary feet have trod; How little seem earth's sorrows, how far off the lost to-morrows, How broad and free the Barrens lie, how very near to God! THE FLORIDA BEACH. Our driftwood fire burns drowsily, The fog hangs low afar, A thousand sea-birds wild and free Hover above the bar; Our boat is drawn far up the strand Beyond the tide's long reach, Like fringeing to the dark green land Shines the silvery Florida beach. Behind, the broad pine-barrens lie Without a path or trail, Before, the ocean meets the sky Without a rock or sail; We call across to Africa— The waves from mile to mile Bear on the hail from Florida, And the answering cry of the Nile. Far to the South the beach shines on, Thick-gemmed with giant shells, Coral sprays from the white reef won, Radiate spiny cells, Glass-like creatures that ride the waves With azure sail and oar, Wide-mouthed things from the deep-sea caves And the purple-hued drift of the shore. Wild ducks gaze as we pass along, They have not learned to fear; The mocking-bird keeps on his song In the palmetto near; The slow stream from the everglade Shows the alligator's track. The sea is rift in light and shade By the heave of the dolphin's back. The Spanish light-house stands in haze, The keeper trims his lights, No sail he sees through long, long days, No sail through still, still nights; But ships that pass far out at sea Along the warm Gulf Stream From Yucatan and Carribee Keep a watch for his far-away gleam. Alone, alone, we wander through The southern winter day, The ocean spreads his mighty blue, The world is far away; The tide comes in,—the birds fly low, As if to catch our speech— Ah Fate! why must we ever go From the beautiful Florida beach? “GENTLEMAN WAIFE.” Only a poor little dog, Why should you grieve? He had not an atom of soul, So we believe. Instinct and animal life Only were there— Poor little Waife, he has gone Why should you care? Only a dog, let him go Under the sod. Not a small foot-mark remains Where he has trod. Even his few human friends Scarcely vouchsafe, More than a thought to his death, Poor little Waife! Joyous he followed your steps, Joyous he went After his master, and felt Perfect content Just to be near you. He kept Trying to say How much he loved you, poor dog. In his dumb way. Gay little Waife, how he ran Happily on, Down the long Florida roads, Ever anon, Looking to see you were there, Swift rushing back— Little brown spot of live joy On the white track. Bounding and circling for glee; Then far away Over the palmetto wastes On a foray, All by himself, coming in, Proudly, as though Wonderful things he had learned You did not know. Changed are the afternoon walks, Something seems wrong, Lifeless the pine-barren roads— Lifeless and long; Coming home over the bridge In the red light Thrown by the sunset that shines Far into night. While the first emerald stars Silvery show, You will miss Waifey, I think— More than you know, More than the careless of heart Could comprehend, Only a poor little dog— Yes; but a friend. His vague little life has run out; Why did he live? We know not; he knows least of all; Yet I would give Something if I could but think, Fancy, that he Had a small future somewhere, Even as we. Wrapped in his soft silken shroud, Calm may he sleep, Down in his dark little grave, Hollowed out deep. “Hic jacet Gentleman Waife,” Write on the scroll; He was, and he is not; poor dog, That was the whole! YELLOW JESSAMINE. In tangled wreaths, in clustered gleaming stars, In floating, curling sprays, The golden flower comes shining through the woods These February days; Forth go all hearts, all hands, from out the town, To bring her gayly in, This wild, sweet Princess of fair Florida— The yellow jessamine. The live-oaks smile to see her lovely face Peep from the thickets; shy, She hides behind the leaves her golden buds Till, bolder grown, on high She curls a tendril, throws a spray, then springs Herself aloft in glee, And, bursting into thousand blossoms, swings In wreaths from tree to tree. The dwarf-palmetto on his knees adores This Princess of the air; The lone pine-barren stands afar and sighs, “Ah! Come, lest I despair;” The myrtle-thickets and ill-tempered thorns Quiver and thrill within, As through their leaves they feel the dainty touch Of yellow jessamine. The garden roses wonder as they see The wreaths of golden bloom Brought in from the far woods with eager haste To deck the poorest room, The rich man's house, alike; the loaded hands Give sprays to all they meet, Till, gay with flowers, the people come and go, And all the air is sweet. The Southern land, well weary of its green Which may not fall nor fade, Bestirs itself to greet the lovely flower With leaves of fresher shade; The pine has tassels, and the orange-trees Their fragrant work begin— The spring has come—has come to Florida With yellow jessamine. DOLORES. Her old boat loaded with oranges, Her baby tied on her breast, Minorcan Dolores bends to her oars, Noting each reed on the slow-moving shores But the way is long and the inlet wide— Can two small hands overcome the tide Sweeping up into the west? Four little walls of coquina-stone, Rude thatch of palmetto-leaves; There have they nestled, like birds in a tree, From winter, and labour, and hunger free, Taking from earth their small need, but no more; No thought of the morrow, no laying in store, No gathering patient sheaves. Alone in their Southern island-home, Through the year of summer days, The two love on; and the bountiful beach Clusters its sea-food within his reach; The two love on, and the tropical land Drops its wild fruit in her indolent hand, And life is a sunshiny haze. Luiz, Dolores, and baby brown, With dreamy, passionate eyes— Far in the past, lured by Saxon wiles, A simple folk came from the Spanish sea-isles, Now, tinged with the blood of the creole quadroon, Their children live idly along the lagoon, Under the Florida skies. Luiz, Dolores, and baby brown, Ah! their blossoming life of love! ... But fever falls with its withering blight, Dolores keeps watch through the sultry night, In vain her poor herbs, in vain her poor prayers ... Her Luiz is mounting the spirit-winged stairs That lead to her heaven above. So, her old boat loaded with oranges, Her baby tied on her breast, Dolores rows off to the ancient town, Where the blue-eyed soldiers come marching down From the far cold north; they are men who know ... Thus Dolores thinks ... how to cure all woe; Nay, their very touch is blest. “Oranges! Oranges!” hear her cry, Through the shaded plaza-path; But the Northern soldiers come marching in, Through the old Spanish city, with stir and din, And the silent people stand sullen by, To see the old flag mount again to the sky, The flag they had trampled in wrath. Ah, brown Dolores! will no one hear, And buy thy poor little store? Now north, now south, on the old sea-walll ... But her pitiful tears unheeded fall; Now east, now west, through the angry town, Patient she journeys up and down, Nor misses one surly door. Then, desperate, up to the dreaded ranks, She carries her passionate suit; “I have no money; for none would buy; But come, for God's sake, or he will die! Save him, my Luiz—he is so young!” She pleads in her liquid Minorcan tongue And proffers her store of fruit. But the Northern soldiers move steadily on, They hear not nor understand; The last blue rank has passed down the street, She sees but the dust of their marching feet; They have crossed a whole country by night and by day, And marked with their blood every step of the way, To conquer this Southern land. They are gone—O despair! She turns to the church, Half-fainting, her fruit wet with tears; “Perhaps the old saint who is always there, May wake up and take them to pay for a prayer; They are very sweet, as the saint will see, If he would but wake up and listen to me. But he sleeps, so he never hears.” She enters; the church is filled with men, The pallid men of the North; Each dingy old pew is a sick man's bed, Each battered old bench holds a weary head, The altar candles are swept away, For vials and knives in shining array, And a new saint is stepping forth? He must be a saint, for he comes from the shrine, A saint of a Northern creed ... Clad in a uniform—army blue, But surely the saints may wear any hue, Dolores thinks, as he takes her hands And hears all her story, and understands The cry of her desperate need. An orange he gives to each weary man, To freshen the fevered mouth, Then forth they go down the old sea-wall, And they hear in the dusk the picket's call; The row-boat is manned on the shadowy shore, The Northern saint can manage an oar, And the boat glides fast to the south. A healing touch, and a holy drink, A bright little heavenly knife, And this strange Northern saint who prays no prayers, Brings back the soul from the spirit-winged stairs, And once more Minorcan Luiz's dark eyes, In whose depths the warmth of the tropics lies, Rest calm on the awe-stricken wife. “Oh, dear Northern saint, a shrine will I build, Wild roses I'll bring from afar, The jessamine, orange flower, wood tulip bright. And there will I worship each morning and night.” “Nay, nay, poor Dolores, I am but a man, A surgeon, who binds up with what skill he can The wounds of this heart-breaking war. “See, build me no shrines, but take this small book, And teach the brown baby to read.” He is gone; and Dolores is left on the shore, She watches the boat till she sees it no more; She hears the quick musketry all through the night, She holds fast the book in her pine-knot's red light, The book of the Northerner's creed. The sad war is over, the dear peace has come, The blue-coated soldiers depart; The brown baby reads the small book, and the three Live on in their isle in the Florida sea; The brown baby learns many things wise and strange, But all his new English words never can change The faith of Dolores' fond heart. A boat with a load of oranges In a flower-decked shrine doth stand Carved in coquina, and thither she goes To pray to the only real saint she knows, The Northern surgeon in army blue; And there she was found in this morning's dew, Dead, with the book in her hand. KENTUCKY BELLE. (Told in an Ohio farm-house; 1868). “Summer of sixty-three, sir, and Conrad was gone away— Gone to the county-town, sir, to sell our first load of hay; We lived in the log-house yonder, poor as ever you've seen; Röschen there was a baby, and I was only nineteen. Conrad he took the oxen, but he left Kentucky Belle; How much we thought of Kentuck, I couldn't begin to tell; Came from the Blue-Grass country, my father gave her to me, When I rode north with Conrad, away from the Tennessee. Conrad lived in Ohio,—a German he is you know: The house stood right in the cornfields, stretching on row after row— The old folks made me welcome; they were kind as kind could be, But I kept longing, longing, for the hills of the Tennessee! Oh! for a sight of water, the shady top of a hill, The smell of the mountain balsams, a wind that never is still! But the level land went stretching away to meet the sky, Never a rise from north to south to rest the homesick eye; From east to west no river to shine out under the moon, Nothing to make a shadow in the yellow afternoon, Only the steady sunshine as I looked out all forlorn, Only the “rustle, rustle,” as I walked among the corn. When I fell sick with pining, we didn't wait any more We moved away from the cornfields out to this river-shore; The Tuscarawas it's called, sir, off there's a hill you see— And now I've got to like it next best to the Tennessee. I was at work that morning. Someone came riding like mad Over the bridge and up the road—Farmer Rouf's little lad; Bareback he rode; he had no hat; he hardly stopped to say: ‘Morgan's men are coming, Frau, they're galloping straight this way! ‘I'm sent to warn the neighbours. He isn't a mile behind; He sweeps up all the horses, every horse that he can find; Morgan, Morgan the raider, and Morgan's terrible men, With bowie-knives and pistols are galloping up the glen!’ The lad rode down the valley; and I stood still at the door; The baby laughed and prattled, playing with spools on the floor; Kentuck was in the pasture; Conrad, my man, was gone; And nearer and nearer Morgan's men were galloping, galloping on! Sudden I picked up baby, and ran to the pasture-bar, ‘Kentuck,’ I called, ‘Kentucky’; she knew me ever so far. I led her down the gully that turns off there to the right, And tied her to the bushes; her head was just out of sight. As I ran back to the log-house, my ears they caught a sound, The ring of hoofs, galloping hoofs, thundering over the ground; Coming into the turnpike, out from the White-Woman glen, Morgan, Morgan the raider, and Morgan's terrible men! I scarce could breathe, and nearly my heart it stopped in alarm, As still I stood in the doorway, with baby on my arm; They came; they passed; with spur and whip in haste they swept along, Morgan, Morgan the raider, and his band, six hundred strong. Oh! fierce they looked and jaded, riding through night, and through day, Pushing straight on for the river, many long miles away, They must reach the edge of Virginia where it bends up toward the West. They must reach the ford and cross it, before they could stop for rest. On like the wind they hurried, and Morgan rode in advance, Bright were his eyes like live coals as he gave me a hasty glance, And I was just breathing freely, after my choking pain, When the last one of the troopers suddenly drew his rein. Frightened I was to death, sir; I scarce dared look in his face, As he asked for a drink of water, and glanced about the place, I gave him a drink, and he smiled; his eyes were soft and blue— 'Twas only a boy; and his tired voice was the dear home-voice I knew! Only sixteen he was, sir—a fond mother's only son, Off and away with Morgan before his life had begun; The big drops stood on his temples, drawn was the boyish mouth, And I thought me of that mother, waiting down in the South! Oh, pluck was he to the backbone, and clear grit through and through, Boasted and bragged like a trooper, but the big words wouldn't do! The boy was dying, sir, dying—as plain as plain could be, Worn out by his ride with Morgan, up from the Tennessee. But when I told the laddie that I, too, was from the South, Water came to his dim eyes and quivers about his mouth; ‘Do you know the Blue-Grass Country?’ he wistful began to say, Then swayed like a willow sapling, and fainted clean away. I had him into the log-house, and worked and brought him to:— I fed him, and I coaxed him, as I thought his mother'd do; And when the faintness left him, and the noise in his head was gone, Morgan's men were miles away, galloping, galloping on. He tried to go—the laddie! ‘You've kept me half the day! Morgan, Morgan is waiting for me! Oh, what will Morgan say?’ But I heard a sound in the distance, and kept him back from the door, The very same sound of horses' hoofs that I had heard before! And on, on, came the soldiers, the Michigan Cavalry, And hard they rode, and black they looked, galloping rapidly, They had followed hard on Morgan's track; they had followed day and night But of Morgan and Morgan's raiders, they had never caught a sight. And rich Ohio sat frightened through all those troubled days, For strange wild men were galloping over her broad highways, Now here, now there, now seen, now gone, now north, now east, now west, Through river valleys, and cornland farms, sweeping away her best. A bold ride and a long ride! But they were taken at last! They had almost reached the river by galloping hard and fast, But the boys in blue were upon them, or ever they crossed the ford, And Morgan, Morgan the raider, laid down his terrible sword. Well—I kept the lad till evening, kept him against his will, But he was too weak to follow, and sat there pale and still; Then when his head was better, you'll wonder to hear me tell— I stole down to that gully and brought up Kentucky Belle. I kissed the star on her forehead—my pretty, gentle lass— But I knew that she'd be happy, back in the old Blue-Grass; A suit of clothes of Conrad's, and all the money I had, And Kentuck, pretty Kentucky, I gave to the worn-out lad. I guided him to the southward as well as I knew how; The boy rode off with many thanks, and many a backward bow; Then when the glow had faded, my heart began to swell, As down the glen away she went, my lost Kentucky Belle! When Conrad came in the evening, the moon was shining high, Baby and I were both crying, I could'nt tell him why! But a battered suit of rebel grey was hanging against the wall, And a thin old horse with drooping head stood in Kentucky's stall. Well—he was kind and never once said a harsh word to me— For he knew I couldn't help it—'twas my love for Tennessee. But after the war was over, just think what came to pass— A letter, sir; and the two were safe, back in the old Blue-Grass! The lad got across the border, riding Kentucky Belle, And Kentuck, she was happy, and fat, and hearty, and well, He kept her, and he petted her, nor touched her with whip nor spur— Well—we've had many horses, but never a horse like her! LONGING. I. In the wide valley open to the sun, Where the slow river flows on toward the south Between the grain-fields, whose low fences run As far as eye can reach, ne'er ending, ne'er begun, The longing people pause amid the burning drouth, And, gazing over the hot fields with dreaming eyes, They seem to see a distant rocky island rise From out the furrows; and a cry bursts forth,— A cry of weary longing for the North. “Oh, for the cedars that grow on the northern island Oh, for the larches that toss in the northern breeze, Oh, for the path beneath the dark aisles of the spruces, The dancing foam-crested waves of the fresh-water seas! Oh, for a sight of the clambering mountain blue-bell, The wash of the sounding surf on the pebbly shore, The spicy smell of the blue-green juniper-berry, The storm-beaten peaks of the gray cliffs towering o'er Cool-shaded nooks, afar from this heat and glare— Would I were there, would I were there!” II. On the far island at the great lake's head Where the short summer scarcely warms the air, Or turns the early cherry to its red, Before quick-coming autumn nips the forest dead, The silent people in their stony furrows bare, Pause in their task, as though their weary, care-worn eyes, Saw, from the waves, a distant sunny valley rise, And, dreaming, gaze, until from hard-set mouth, Bursts forth a cry of longing for the south: “Oh, for the deep lush grass of the green mill-race meadow, Oh, for the broad fields golden with fast growing grain, Oh, for the pulse of the earth in ripening weather, The glowing heat of the sun on the dead level plain! Oh, for a sight of the full-bosomed water-lily Basking at ease as the slow river onward flows, The sound of the myriad-gilded summer insects, The scent of the heliotrope and the sweet tube rose! Oh, land of the South, fruitful, blossoming, fair— Would I were there, would I were there!” MACKINAC—REVISITED. A Fragment. The sunset gate in shadow lies Before the morning radiance, And shineth still down Michigan The far-off flash of Waugoschance; But nearer looms a cloudy shape Up from the waves, its outlines draw The tears;—thy every line I know O purple-hued, beautiful Mackinac! Isle of the north, thy shadowed tints Again I see,—the aisles of pines That sweep around like outer court, The spicy cedars' sharpened lines Of lighter hue, the blue-green spruce In Gothic spires; and, thick between The banners of the maple leaves That brighten the pines with their summer green. O when the time doth come for me To yield obedience to the law Of mortal life, I fain would rest Under thy sod, O Mackinac! I should lie quiet there, and know Thy pine-crowned cliffs were e'er the same, Thy foam-capped waves, St. Ignace point, The western pass in the sunset flame— And ships all gold-tinged sailing down To some fair land beyond the gates. The echo of the evening gun, The twilight falling o'er the Straits, The stars slow rising; my sealed eyes Lying calm in Death's long trance Would still dream on of Bois Blanc light And the far-away flash of Waugoschance. O purple isle, through long, long years A wide, wide world I've wandered o'er, From mountains of the western skies To silver sands of southern shore, And—ever sad!—no more I strive, I come again where love doth draw My lonely heart,—O take me back And comfort me, beautiful Mackinac!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">“The Benedicts Abroad.” FOUR-LEAVED CLOVER. She journeyed north, she journeyed south, The whole bright land she wandered over, And climbed the mountains white with snow, And sought the plains where palm trees grow— But—never found the four-leaved clover. Then to the seas she spread her sail, Fled round the world—a white-winged rover, Her small foot pressed the Grecian grass— She saw Egyptian temples pass— But—never found the four-leaved clover. The costliest gems shone on her brow, The ancient Belgian spinners wove her A rope of lace a queen might wear— Her eyes found all most rich, most rare But—never found the four-leaved clover. The throng did flock to see her pass, To hear her speak,—and all men strove her Smile to win; she had the whole Of each one's life and heart and soul— But—never found the four-leaved clover. A storm flew down and tore her sail, A biting tempest came and drove her Homeward, bereft, alone and poor, The fair friends fled, the journeyings o'er That never found the four-leaved clover. GETTYSBURG. 1876. Oh ye too old to feel, too young to know The memory of those years that stirred our hearts Deeper than human hand can ever stir, Or single sorrow, lost to you the glow, The thrill, the tears, as, now while day departs Beyond the soft blue mountains, on this spur I stand—among the graves, the soldiers' graves, The dead of Gettysburg. The slow years pass,— The youths who lie here underneath this grass Would have been men now, and the men have worn The graver look of age.—O lives forlorn, O girl-heart crushed, O heart of wife that craves One look, one touch—O mother reft of son, Though all the world beside forget these graves, Ye, ye do not forget! They may not know Around you, but the birthday of the one, The one, the lost one, silently is kept, Deep in your hearts, and swift hot tears still flow Upon your pillows, though they deemed you slept In calm forgetfulness. Come, hither, ye Who dwell in city streets, and view the scene Rich with the harvest, fresh from summer rain, Studded with orchards. Yet, the agony Was fierce there in the wheat-field, and the green Was drenched with red; a thousand men were slain In those fair orchards; from that low stone wall Along the brookside, started the fierce rush Up the hill's crest—What is it thus to fall And die in bitter pain while yet the flush Of youth is on the cheek? They could not know More than the space before them, dim with smoke From the hot guns,—but, when the captains spoke, Each man did aim straight at his nearest foe, To slay him or—be slain. 'Twas all he knew Of the wide battle—the few feet of earth That held him when he fell. And yet, the worth Of deeds like this it was that gained the day With its red hosts of death. But no dark pall Broods now upon this slope, or on our hearts, Despite these tears; the graves stretch green away, And flowers bloom everywhere, the evening dew Doth pearl the carved “unknown”—They gave their lives, Yea, through their faults, their sins, perhaps, there starts Ever this thought—they gave their lives! Fair day Of Consecration, thou didst hear the man, The plain grand speaker,—say those words that live Immortal on the page. “The world not long Will note what we say here,—but never can Forget what they did here,”—O, listening throng Of dead, ye heard it! None so fit to give This tribute as that one whose memory drives Mere gilded grace and courtier's art away, The people's son—their Leader. Let us say His words again. The land will not note long, Ye dead of Gettysburg, ye voiceless throng Of mounds, what we may write; but God forbid It e'er forget, or care not, what ye did! MORRIS ISLAND. Night is falling over Charleston harbour, Sea-fog to and fro its veil is shifting, Sumter looms up dark; the ocean-vessels Anchored in the stream seem slowly drifting— Drifting with the tide; the distant city Folded in its rivers, emblematic Of its close-wrapped pride, low on the water Lies like Venice on the Adriatic. Silently we wander o'er the island, Silently, we know our feet are treading Graves unnumbered that the ocean guardeth, Graves unnumbered where the sand is spreading Thick its veil along the line of trenches; Though no sign the dumb white desert giveth, They are there beneath its wind-swept beaches, Thought of them the only thing that liveth Now upon its shore; no land-bird flutters O'er its barren slope, no grasses growing, Few its very sea-shells, while the sunset Gilds the pallid levels with its glowing Like a mockery, and doubly arid Shine the sand-hills of the lighthouse station, Gold-tipped rise the broken lines of Wagner, Looking down upon the desolation. Yet we find upon these ruined ramparts, Old embrasures of the cannon looming Over them for shade, the legend-crowned Chrismal passion-flowers, richly blooming All alone, more wonderful in beauty On these sands of death, more gently tender For their very loneliness; they grow here Only for the dead, their purple splendour Given him who has no other blossoms, Marble-carven, or the living roses By a churchyard-mound, the common soldier Who beneath this sand somewhere reposes, Throes of dying o'er. O flower of passion, Flower of suffering, how fit to meet thee On these pale wan shores of solemn silence, Watching by the dead! We pause to greet thee, Thinking of the hour when each poor mortal Buried here, the life that his Creator Gave him for his own, did yield in anguish— Yea, 'mid sins, could give a gift no greater Were he saint or martyr! Shine on, flowerets, Far the ships sail o'er the dusky ocean, Far the world has gone away; ye only Steadfast wait with Nature's still devotion; And no flower had ever fairer mission, Rose, or lily, blue-bell of the highland, Than is thine, O lovely aureoled blossom, Blooming here alone on Morris Island! CHARLES DICKENS. CHRISTMAS 1870. Ring out, O Bells, for merry, merry Christmas, Down through the crowded street; Let all the city chimes in pealing chorus The Gloria repeat; And sounding onward over hill and valley, Buried beneath the snow, Let village spires take up the joyful story, Echoing to and fro. Bring in the evergreens, wreathe shining holly With odorous dark pine, Festoon the dim Cathedral's gothic arches, The glittering organ twine; Gather together round the glowing fireside, The old, the grave, the gay, And sing in carols how the holy Christ-child, Was born on Christmas-day. But 'midst the chimes from cross-crowned steeples ringing, The Christmas garlands green, The children's voices joyous carols singing, The merry household scene, Forget not one who told the Christmas story With matchless loving art, “Peace and good-will to men” with tender glory Filling his kindly heart. Forget not one who hailed the Christmas season In child-like faith and joy, Sharing the festal song and merry frolics, A laughing, grey-haired boy; Forget not one, who yearly gave us legends Through the long, happy past, Each one exhaling spicy Christmas perfumes More fragrant than the last. The kindly heart is still; the voice is silent; No more we wait to hear The magic accents of the Great Enchanter, The story-teller dear; But from the stormy shore of dark Atlantic To fair Pacific's wave Thousands of hearts will send a Christmas blessing To rest on Dickens' grave. To GEORGE ELIOT. O wondrous woman! shaping with thy pen As Michael Angelo did shape from stone, Colossal forms of clear-cut outline, when We dwell upon thy pages, not alone The beauty of thy rose, we see, as finely traced As roses drawn by other woman-hands Who spend their lives in shaping them but faced We find ourselves with giant's work that stands Above us as a mountain lifts its brow, Grand, unapproachable, yet clear in view To lowliest eyes that upward look, Oh, how Hast thou shed radiance as thy finger drew Its shapes! A myriad women light have seen And courage taken, because thou hast been. [Clara—bright, illustrious] Clara—bright, illustrious; Benedict—a benediction. May perpetual light shine on her ... Yes, hope returneth ever. It is the coward's part to loiter sad Among the April trees in leaf buds clad, Even my dead are living and are glad In some fair spring! ON A HOMELY WOMAN, DEAD. And hast thou served the purpose of thy life, Poor helpless clay, that many times did ask, “Why was I born?” Not thine the daily task Of direst Poverty that, with its strife For bread, doth crush all faces to one mould Of haggard care; nor thine the grace of age, Which covereth all our lack with reverence For silver hairs. No: in thy pilgrimage Thou knewest always that all eyes did hold Thee as a blot upon their loving sense Of beauty: there was discord in the air When thou passed by. Thou couldst not ope thy mind, Shed out a radiance, or compel the ear To listen while the eye forgot; no kind Relenting Fortune turned and gave thee wit Or eloquence as compensation. Spare And lean thy stores of pleasure through the years— Some thanks, some small remembrance; thou didst sit And gather thankfully a breath, a crumb Of happiness thrown to thee, as the dumb And patient dog doth wait. And if there came One who professed to love thee, in thy shame At thine own bitter sad deficiency, Thou hatedst him for his dull mockery Of love, when it was household need alone That wanted thee. And if a kinder tone Did sue, thou knewest, through thy hidden tears, It was but pity, and thy pale cheek turned Paler as thou saidst—no! Thy pulsing years, That radiant should have been, have dimly burned In their cramped darkened prison: couldst thou dream Of love, of motherhood? Thou wouldst not take The false for want of true, the gilt for gold, The tinsel for the gem; so thou didst hold Thy dreary life alone. And, for the sake Of womanhood, thou wouldst not condescend To things beneath thee; but didst ever seem To walk with fixed endurance on thy brow Through life, nor e'en look upward toward the end, Lest thou shouldst lose the path that thou didst trace In early years for all thy life. O Face! Poor homely Face, still, rigid, dead, and now Soon to pass out forever from our sight Beneath the sod, no more to vex the light, Wert thou a mask? Then, oh! how fair must be The face she weareth now, for wearing thee! IN MEMORIAM. G.S.B. Gone! But we could not understand, When broken voices said That he was gone—we could not feel That George, our George, was dead, Until they brought him home, his hands crossed on his breast, The kindly grey eyes closed, the noble heart at rest. Home! He was hastening home, but in One heart-beat, one quick breath, One prayer, there met him, face to face, The fiery form of Death And caught his soul away. What wonder if we cried, “Lord! If Thou hadst been there, our brother had not died!” So young, so beautiful, so strong, So dearly, deeply prized; So needed, trusted, leaned-upon, So loved, so idolized— Why was he called away, while we of little worth, The useless and the weak, live on to cumber earth? How can we spare thee, George? How live Through the long dreary hours Without thee? As the cold white snow Came down upon the flowers We buried in thy grave, so cold grief over all Our hearts and homes and lives came down—an icy pall. There is no comfort earth can give, No consolation. None Can hope for more than faith to say, Thy will, O Lord, be done. Help us to bear our part, as he did, in the strife— Help us to follow after his pure, unselfish life. Then, when our pilgrimage is o'er, When there are no more fears Of parting, when the Lord Himself Shall wipe away our tears, When the grave gives up its dead, when Death is overcome, George will be first to meet us, and bid us welcome home. PLUM'S PICTURE. Red-golden hair with flossy wave, Two blue eyes filled with wonder grave, Cheeks tinted with rose-bloom, Sweet coral mouth pursed up in awe, For many fairy things she saw Up in the artist's room; From out the simple little dress Bare in their baby loveliness, Two rounded shoulders come,— Two dimpled hands, so soft and fair, Holding the flowers with folded care, And there you have our Plum. O, darling Plum, your three short years, Have held a charm to dry the tears Of many mourning hearts,— When dark the life, and deep the grief, No words, no help, bring the relief That baby-love imparts; And, looking in your sunbeam face, Watching your ways, your winsome grace, Your little pleasures glad,— Hearing your questions, baby-wise, Your rippling talk, your gay surprise, Who, who, can long be sad? Dear little Plum, we love to trace Your likeness to another face, A something hov'ring o'er Your baby features, which recalls A portrait hanging on our walls, And brings him back once more; Back to our life, as, in your eyes We see the father's likeness rise, His bright expression come,— And of all loves our hearts confer, We love you best because you were His darling little Plum.</field>
   </doc>
</add>