<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Pierpont, John, 1785-1866</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Pierpont, John, 1785-1866</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">pierpont john 1785 1866</field>
      <field name="author_text">Pierpont, John, 1785-1866</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1840's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ap/uvaGenText/tei/chap_AM0475.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240349</field>
      <field name="date_text">1843</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:439925</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Cold water melodies, and Washingtonian songster ; Enlarged and improved</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- 1783-1850</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- 1783-1850</field>
      <field name="title_display">Cold water melodies, and Washingtonian songster ; Enlarged and improved</field>
      <field name="title_facet">cold water melodies and washingtonian songster</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">cold water melodies and washingtonian songster</field>
      <field name="title_text">Cold water melodies, and Washingtonian songster ; Enlarged and improved</field>
      <field name="year_display">1843</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1843</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1843</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:439925&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:439925&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Pierpont, John, 1785-1866&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;pierpont john 1785 1866&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Cold water melodies, and Washingtonian songster ; Enlarged and improved&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;cold water melodies, and washingtonian songster&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1843&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1843&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Pierpont, John&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1785&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1866&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Cold water melodies, and Washingtonian songster&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Enlarged and improved&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Boston&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Theodore Abbot&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1843&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3865483-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;cham0475&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- 1783-1850&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1783&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1850&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Cold water melodies, and Washingtonian songster&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Enlarged and improved&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1996&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1996 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 238 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-AmPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SONG FOR A COLD WATER ARMY. Tune—“Auld Lang Syne.’ Shall e'er cold water be forgot, When we sit down to dine? O no, my friends, for is it not Pour'd out by hands divine? Pour'd out by hands divine, my friends, Pour'd out by hands divine; From springs and wells it gushes forth, Pour'd out by hands divine. To Beauty's cheek, tho' strange it seems, 'Tis not more strange than true, Cold Water, though itself so pale Imparts the rosiest hue; Imparts the rosiest hue, my friends, Imparts the rosiest hue, Yes, Beauty, in a water-pail Doth find her rosiest hue. Cold water too, (tho' wonderful, 'Tis not less true, again)— The weakest of all earthly drinks, Doth make the strongest men:— Doth make the strongest men, my friends, Doth make the strongest men; Then let us take that weakest drink And grow the strongest men. I've seen the bells of tulips turn, To drink the drops that fell From summer clouds;—then why should not The two lips of a belle? The two lips of a belle, my friends, The two lips of a belle? What sweetens more than water pure The two lips of a belle? The sturdy oak full many a cup Doth hold up to the sky, To catch the rain; then drinks it up, And thus the oak gets high; 'Tis thus the oak gets high, my friends, 'Tis thus the oak gets high; By having water in its cups, Then why not you and I? Then let cold water armies give Their banners to the air; So shall the boys like oaks be strong, The girls like tulips fair; The girls like tulips fair, my friends, The girls like tulips fair; The boys shall grow like sturdy oaks, The girls like tulips fair. COME SIGN THE VOW! Air—“God save the King” Come, sign the Temperance pledge, Thou on life's tottering edge, Come sign the vow! What though thy hair be gray, Languid thy pulses play, Give us thy parting day, Quick sign the vow. Manhood, with sinewy form, Breasting the hard world's storm, Come sign the vow! Here, dry thy partner's tears, Here, hush thy children's fears, Here, bless thy coming years, Now sign the vow. Childhood, with earnest glance, Hither thy steps advance, Come, sign the vow! Haste, thy young promise bring, Pure, simple offering, Fresh, from th' Eternal Spring, Now sign the vow. Sinner of many cares, Wilder'd with doubts and snares, Come sign the vow! Give us thy trembling hand, Soon shall foul habit's band, Break like an osier wand. Come sign the vow. Maiden, untouched by care, Lovely, and fresh and fair, Come sign the vow! Turn here thy sparkling eye, Lend us thy check's soft dye, In all thy charms stand by, And sign the vow. Youth, with thy upward look, Which not a stain can brook, Come sign the vow! On, for thy country's weal, On, at dear home's appeal, Take, for thy soul this seal— Come sign the vow. EXHORTATION TO BE TEMPERATE. Oh! what are the pangs that result from excess, In quaffing the juice of the vine; Tho' the bosom may feel them the tongue can't express Half the pain that is lurking in wine. Go ask of the drunkard, he'll tell you the throes Of remorse that he feels in his breast; Of his anguish, his sorrows, his pains and his woes, Of the grief which his soul has possest. He'll tell you 'tis wine has depriv'd him of friends, Of comfort, of peace, and of health, Of every enjoyment that Temperance lends, Of character, credit and wealth. He 'll tell you his standard as Man is disgraced; He 'll portray the disease of his soul; He 'll tell you he's humbled, degraded, debased, By the demon that lurks in the bowl. Then shun the vile spirit which causes the ills, Too many have had to deplore; Let your thirst be assuaged at the pure water rills, And taste of the wine-cup no more. TEMPERANCE SONG. PARODY. Air—“Some love to roam.’ Some love to roam Where the glasses foam, And the poison circles free— But a chosen band, In a rescued land, And a Temperance Life for me. When morning beams O'er the mountain streams, Oh merrily forth we go, To hallow our life, With a glorious strife, And to crush our country's foe. Ho, ho, ho, Some love, &amp;c. The snake we mark, In the bar room dark, And untempted turn our back, And the best of cheer, At our homes so dear, Oh why should the temperate lack? For with steady aim At an honored name, And hearts that fear no foe, Our brother to save From the drunkard's grave, In the spirit of love we go— Ho, ho, ho, Some love, &amp;c. FILL A BUMPER OF WATER. Tune—“The King, God bless him.” Fill a bumper of water that's pure from the spring, Bright sparkling and clear as the glass, And with rapture the joyous emotions we'll sing, Which enliven our hours as they pass We'll spurn the rude mirth of the wine-bibber's bowl, While our Abstinence pleasures exceed it, And we give you the Pledge with our heart and our soul, Here's success to the cause and God speed it, God speed it—God speed it, Here's success to the Pledge, and God speed it. Surrounded by virtue, by beauty, and youth, Dear woman we drink to thy charms; If we pledge thee in water, we pledge thee in truth And we take thee with joy to our arms. Go look at our homes and observe the glad smile, What welcome on earth can exceed it, Where affection thus greets us our cares to beguile, Then success to the Pledge, and God speed it, God speed it—God speed it, Success to the Pledge and God speed it. Tho' we boast not of wealth yet we gladly impart To a brother a share of our store, And we hail him with feelings of joy from the heart, When the slave of Intemperance no more; Our motto is sympathy, friendship and love, And aid to a friend should he need it, Our Charter's recorded by Angels above, Then success to the Pledge and God speed it, God speed it—God speed it, Success to the Pledge and God speed it. THE FATHER'S REFORMATION. Air—“Woodman spare that tree.” Father spare that cup, Thy daughter's feelings spare It stirs thy passions up, And fills me with despair. Husband! spare that glass, It breaks my heart with pain; Sad are the hours that pass, If thou away remain. Stay with thy children dear, Drink no more at the place, Where thou wilt as I fear, Fall into deep disgrace. Oh! sign the Temperance pledge, Then shall we happy be; It shall thee safely hedge From every enemy. Daughter! no more the cup, Shall I in madness drain; Burning my vitals up, No! I'll from hence refrain. Wife! let thy tears be dry, I now at home shall stay; Vain shall the tempter try, Me to entice away. I've signed the Temperance pledge, True Washingtonian am; No more the wine I'll quaff, Ne'er take another dram. Now shall we happy be, United all in love; For thou forgivest me, And so does God above. AWAY WITH MELANCHOLY. Air—“Away with Melancholy.” Away with melancholy, Let all our voices ring,— We've given up our folly, So merrily, merrily sing. Too long on land and ocean, We've served a tyrant king, Farewell perpetual motion! We merrily, merrily sing. Our heads that once were reeling, Now shun the poisoned thing, And hearts once lost to feeling, Now merrily, merrily sing. We've raised the Temperance banner, Our bark is on the wing. May favoring breezes fan her, We merrily, merrily sing What though some foes assail us,— We do not fear their sting, Our strength shall never fail us, So merrily, merrily sing. Then come, ye sober hours, Life's happiest moments bring, Our path is strewn with flowers, So merrily, merrily sing. THE VOW OF THE RECLAIMED. Tune—Bonny Boat. Let others quaff the ruby wine, I'll drink from gushing springs, Nor bow again at folly's shrine, For misery it brings. I'll seek no more the festal board, I'll drink from gushing springs, Nor bow again at folly's shrine, For misery it brings. I'll seek no more the festalboard, Where the midnight taper gleams; Nor mingle with the drunken horde, But drink from mountain streams. The Temperance Pledge, I'll hold it strong, And bear the drunkard's jeers; Nor sing the bacchanalian song, But dry a young wife's tears. I'll spurn the blind, besotted crowd, I'll scorn the drunkard's sneers, And Temperance I'll proclaim aloud, And dry a mother's tears. The limpid nectar I will quaff From brooks, nor seek to roam Where rings the reveller's drunken laugh, But stay content at home. I'll dash the poisoned chalice down, And swell the Temperance train; No more shall wine my senses drown, I'll be a man again. SONS OF LIBERTY. Air—“Bruce's Address.” Sons of Liberty, arise! Who your country's glory prize, Spread your banner to the skies! Wake from apathy! Join the Washingtonian Band, Firmly to your pledges stand, Drive intemp'rance from the land, Crime and misery. Who would not a brother save, Who would be himself a slave, Who would fill a drunkard's grave, Let him spurn our laws— Who his country loves and owns, Who would free and bless her sons, Who would stay her tears and groans, Let him aid our cause. Now's the time our foe to press, See his foll'wers less and less! See they falter and confess! Haste the joyful time, When the tyrant shall be slain, Universal Temp'rance reign, And our flag without a stain, Wave from clime to clime. While we swell our grateful lays— While our voices high we raise, Loudest we will ever praise God who makes us free. A HEALTH TO DEAR WOMAN. Tune—“The Sun sets at night.” A health to dear woman! she bids us untwine From the cup it encircles the fast-clinging vine: But her cheek in its crystal with pleasure will glow, And mirror its bloom in the bright wave below. A health to dear woman! the days are no more When she watched for her lord till the revel was o'er, And smoothed the white pillow, and blushed when he came, As she pressed her cold lips on his forehead of flame. Alas for the loved one! too spotless and fair, The joys of his banquet to chasten and share; Her eye lost its light that his goblet might shine, And the rose of her cheek was dissolved in his wine. Joy smiles in the fountain, health flows in the rills, As their ribands of silver unwind from the hills; They breathe not the mist of the bacchanal's dream, But the lilies of innocence float on the stream. Then a health and a welcome to woman once more! She brings us a passport that laughs at our door; It is written on crimson—its letters are pearls— It is countersigned Nature—so, room for the Girls! SONG. Jubal. Woodstock, C. M. Bost. Acad. Coll. Oh! touch it not for deep within, That ruby tinted bowl, Lie hidden fiends of guilt and sin, To seize your precious soul. That sparkling glass if you partake, Will prove your deadly foe, And may, e'er yet its bubbles break, Have sealed your endless wo. Then pause e'er yet the cup you drain, The hand that lifts it, stay, Resolve for ever to abstain, And cast the bowl away. OH, NO; I'LL NEVER DRINK AGAIN. Air—Oh no; I never mention her. O, no, I'll never drink again, The cup I'll never take; My lips are now forbid to taste E'en for old friendship's sake. From shop to shop they beckon me, To banish my regret, And Brandy freely offer me— They think that I'll forget. With shame I blush to view the scene, That I so oft did see; As with the tipler I have been— They'll find a change in me. 'Tis time that I had drunk my last, My cheeks with tears are wet, To think of follies of the past, O, how can I forget. They tell me I'm unhappy now, They'd wish to make me gay; And hint that I'll forget my vow— I heed not what they say. Through life I now will press my course, Until my sun is set, And bless the hour I took the pledge, Oh! how can I forget. FEMALE AID SOLICITED. Tunes—Triumph. Marah. Bost. Acad. Coll. O, that the Lord would hear Our supplicating cry; In our behalf appear, A Saviour ever nigh; And shine in every woman's heart, That she may take an active part. Let Sarahs now arise, And Miriams all come forth; With Hannahs truly wise, To prove their genuine worth. No power like theirs—save that above, To teach sobriety and love. Marys and Marthas join, Ye vessels of his grace, Counsel with love combine, To save our sinking race; And bid them of strong drinks beware, That they may shun the tempter's snare. Come all ye lovely train, Those nobler powers display; Nor shall you plead in vain, But win the well fought day. Mothers and maidens then will sing, And earth with hallelujahs ring. Each house shall then become A paradise below; And all enjoy a home, Where sweetest pleasures flow: Pure temp'rance through our land will shine, And prove your labors are divine. PRAYER FOR DIVINE BLESSING. Tune—St. Martins. C. M. O, Thou from whom all gifts proceed, A blessing now dispense; And give us, Lord, with power to plead, The cause of temperance. With wisdom, charity, and zeal, May we its blessings trace; That all to whom we shall appeal Those blessings may embrace. That self-denial we may show, Which men of old enjoin'd, And every vain desire forego, To benefit mankind. Of what offends a brother's eye, Or gives another pain, May we in love ourselves deny, And from its use abstain. CHRISTIAN'S DUTY TO ATTEMPT THE SALVATION OF DRUNKARDS. Tunes—Turin. Rutland. While intemperance, as a cloud, Hovers o'er our native land, While its victims, in a crowd, Round the burning altar stand, Shall we not, as Christians, rise To prevent the sacrifice? While on every hand we see Drunkenness the cause of wo, While despair and misery From its fatal fountain flow, Shall we not attempt to save Thousands from a drunkard's grave? God of love, their aid impart, Fill us, now, with holy zeal, Soften every harden'd heart, Let us for each other feel, From each direful draught abstain, That we may our brother gain. TEMPERANCE EVENING HYMN. Air—“Carrier Dove.” Oh Thou, whose never-sleeping eye Regards us, night and day, Whose watchful care is ever nigh, To keep us in thy way; We praise thy name; we bless thy love That shields our souls from harm, That leads our thoughts to soar above, Where sins no more alarm. Be with us through the gloomy night, Till morn unbars her gates, And from the East, the dawning light The darkness dissipates. And while through life we heedless stray, Surrounded by thy care, Oh keep us in the temp'rance way, And save from every snare. THANKS FOR TEMPERANCE LIGHT. Tune—Hamburg. L. M. We thank Thee that, amid the throng Of ransom'd drunkards, we can stand, And praise Thee that the temp'rance star E'er rose on this benighted land. For lost in dire oblivion's maze, To ruin had we heedless run, And follow'd in the tempter's ways, Nor dreamt that we were then undone. The light of love broke o'er the gloom, And darkness, which beset our path; Revealing to our view the doom Of an Almighty's righteous wrath. Lord! may the star of temp'rance shine In each deluded drunkard's breast; And then thy blessed truths, divine, Shall fit them for “eternal rest.” DANGER OF SENSUAL PLEASURES. Tune—Winter. Dundee. C. M. When in the light of faith divine We look on things below, Honor, and gold, and sensual joy, How vain and dang'rous too. The pleasures that allure our sense, Are dang'rous snares to souls! There's but a drop of flattering sweet, And dash'd with bitter bowls. And shall the followers of the Lord, Still drink the drunkard's cup; Find in its frenzy their reward, And life and hope give up. God is my all sufficient good, My portion, and my choice; In him my vast desires are fill'd, And all my powers rejoice. In vain the world accosts my ear, And tempts my heart anew; I cannot buy your bliss so dear, Nor part with heaven for you. THE EFFECTS OF WINE. Prov. xxiii. 29–34 Tune—Nuremburg. 7s. Who hath sorrows, who hath foes? Who hath babblings, who hath strife? Causeless wounds, and fancied foes? Redden'd eyes? embitter'd life? They that tarry at the wine, They that love the feast and song, They that round the bowl combine, Early haste and tarry long. Look not on the wine when red, When it foams and sparkles bright, Lo! it hides an adder's head! Like a serpent will it bite. Wantons then will charm the eye, Things perverse thy heart disclose, On the billow shalt thou lie, At the mast-head seek repose. “I was stricken,” thou shalt say— “Yet when beaten felt no pain— When shall dawn another day? I will seek it yet again!” TO TEETOTALLERS. Tunes—Stephens. Coronation. C. M. Press on ye band who nobly brave A world's unpitying scorn; Ye stand erect in virtue's cause, By virtue's strength upborne. Can scorn unfix creation's base, Or shake the throne of God? Can taunts, however fierce, disarm Stern justice of her rod? No! nor shall they daunt your zeal, Nor bend your souls to yield; But ye shall wave, exultingly, Your banners o'er the field. No dying groans, no mother's shriek, Shall mar your triumph hymn, No blood shall stain your battle flag, No cloud your glories dim! But there shall follow in your train A holy, happy throng, The wise and good will soon abstain, And join the conq'rer's song. COME ALL YE YOUNG TEETOTALLERS! Air“Yankee Doodle.” Come all ye young teetotallers— Come with us while we go To fight with old king Alcohol, A brave and mortal foe. Then rouse, my lads, then rouse ye up; Come forward every one; We'll banish far the poison cup, Nor stop till vict'ry's won. A hard old enemy is he, And brave and bold in fight; But labor hard—we'll soon be free, For God defends the right. Then rouse, my lads, &amp;c. But though he may be brave and bold, We'll show what we can do; We're not the temp'rance men of old— We go for something new. Then rouse, my lads, &amp;c. “We touch not, taste not, handle not,” What can intoxicate; We'll live and die without a blot, And shun the drunkard's fate. Then rouse, my lads, &amp;c. Grog men may laugh, and joke, and sneer, They laugh and tremble too; For when the boys take hold, they fear There's something then to do. Then rouse, my lads, &amp;c. And now, my boys, since we've begun, The cause must never fall; Let each man bring some other one, And soon we'll have them all. Then rouse, my lads, &amp;c. THE PLEDGE. Tune.—Auld Lang Syne. I've signed the pledge! It is the bond Between my God and me— 'Tis done!—I've broke th' enchanted wand; I breathe—I live—I'm free! Darkness, which was my world, is past, And sounds of discord cease; And what was once a chaos vast, Is harmony and peace! And as I turn me to that home, Once cheerless to my sight, Seraphic voices seem to come, With welcome of delight. The very faces round my hearth Are sweetly new to see, And woman's love, and childhood's mirth, Are paradise to me. O! glorious change! a beauteous world Appeareth now around, The evening clouds seem flags unfurled, With gold and crimson bound; The wood, the harvest field and hill, With living splendor glow, While ocean, river, stream and rill, Give music as they flow! O! that the veil were rent before, That I might see these things, And glad with gratitude adore The power whence wisdom springs. But mercy o'er life's pathway yet Her lustre will display, As suns in cloudless light will set, Which led a stormy day. MY COUNTRY 'TIS OF THEE. Tune—America. My country! 'tis of thee, Sweet land of liberty— Of thee I sing, Land where my fathers died; Land of the pilgrim's pride; From every mountain side Let temp'rance ring. My native country! thee— Land of the noble free— Thy name I love: I love thy rocks and rills, Thy woods and templed hills; My heart with rapture thrills Like that above. Let music swell the breeze, And ring from all the trees, Sweet freedom's song; Let infant tongues awake, Let all that breathe partake, Let rocks their silence break, The sound prolong. Our fathers' God! to thee— Author of liberty! To thee we sing: Long may our land be bright, With temp'rance's holy light; Protect us by thy might, Great God, our King. REASONS FOR DRINKING. One drinks because he's very hot, As we are often told; Another can't refuse a pot, Because he's very cold. A third will drink because he's wet, Its benefits to try; A fourth must sure a tankard get, Because he's very dry. Another must a bargain make, And have a glass to strike it; While one and all the liquor take, Because, in fact, they like it. THE DRUNKARD'S HOME MADE SWEET. Tune—Knight Errant. The drunkard's home shall soon be sweet If he will but abstain; With needful comforts, all replete, To soothe each minor pain. The cheering wife and smiling child, With cheeks of rosy hue, And blue eyes beaming, fair and mild, Shall youthful joys renew. Oh, drunkard, poor deluded man, Beguiled from virtue's way; Thy callous heart, thy visage wan, Thy hapless state betray. Oh, come e're it shall be too late To spring from sorrow's hold; For thee the dearest blessings wait, In water clear and cold, Come, come, poor drunkard, come away From gnawing wo and sin; There is no time for thee to stay, Haste, come poor drunkard, in. The drunkard's home shall soon be sweet, When he himself is freed; With zeal and love his heart shall beat— He'll say, “I'm blest indeed.” THE LIGHT OF TEMPERANCE. Air—“Twilight Dews.” When first I saw the gleaming crest Of temp'rance's silver star, I watch'd it, till its radiance blest Illum'd the world afar: It rose in glory, and its rays Shone bright at morn and even, And promise gave of happier days On Earth;—and hopes of Heaven. I marked its glory-beaming light, As up the heavens it sprung, While o'er the Earth the clouds of night No longer darkly hung; And those bright rays of heavenly birth, To erring man were given, To wean his spirit from the Earth, And point his way to Heaven. Oh! may that bright and shining light Still beam the wide world o'er, To guide man's wand'ring footsteps right, Till time shall be no more. And then, when death the light of life From this dull clay has riven, The soul may soar in glad relief, To yon bright home in Heaven. WILL YOU COME TO THE SPRING. Tune—Will you come to the bower. Will you come to the spring that is sparkling and light, Where the birds carol sweetly, the sun-set is bright? Will you, will you, will you, will you come to the spring?—[rep. 3 t.] Then the cup runneth o'er with the purest of drink, And as sweet as the roses that bend from the brink. Will you, &amp;c. Let it flow lovely stream it, will surely impart, Both a new glow to beauty and peace to the heart; Will you, &amp;c. When the gay flowrets droop in the noon summer's heat, Or the bright dew descending restores every sweet; Will you, &amp;c. With new blessings of life, it forever o'erflows, It refreshes all nature wherever it goes; Will you, &amp;c. FAREWELL THE BOWL. Farewell to the cup, we have tarried too long, Where the juice of the grape adds its witch'ry to song. And the thoughts that flow'd freely are sombre and dull, Our brains become heavy, farewell to the bowl, Farewell, farewell, farewell, farewell to the bowl.—[rep. 2 t.] Oh, tarry no longer where joy flies away, The heart and the soul lose their richest array, Where eye mocketh eye, as unmeaning they roll, The tongue whispers folly—farewell to the bowl. Oh, think, if the maiden, who smiles in thine eyes, Once saw thy proud mind in this shameful disguise; Her heart would reject thee, how sadly her soul Would pity and leave thee—oh, flee from the bowl. Oh think, e'er the moment of thinking is past, And chains of the mighty upon thee are cast! Return—ere the iron shall enter thy soul, And the dregs of thy life—a curse on the bowl. ADDRESS TO WASHINGTONIANS. Tune—Bruce's Address. Ye who have from Brandy fled! Ye whom Gin has often led! Welcome are ye, from the dead! Glorious victory! Now's the day, and now's the hour; Lo! the tyrant's waning power, Darkly o'er us still doth lower; Chains and slavery! Who will be a traitor knave? Who will fill a drunkard's grave? Who so base as be a slave? Do not turn and flee! Who to virtue's king and law, Would not every drunkard draw? And from sin's devouring maw Set them nobly free! By the drunkard's woes and pains: By our brethren still in chains; While the life-blood fills their veins, Say they shall be free! Lay the proud usurper low; See, he reels at every blow! End his reign of sin and wo! Shout for victory! SONG OF JOHN HAWKINS AND COMRADES. Tune—Washing Day. Hurrah! hurrah! we've burst the chain; O God! how long it bound us! We run! we leap! O God, again Thy light, thy air surround us, From midnight's dungeon depths brought We hail hope's rising star; Ho, comrades! give the stirring shout, Hurrah! hurrah! hurrah! The world has kissed the tyrant's throne The Beast! the Man of Sin! “Legion!” “Apollyon!” The title Apollyon, Abaddon, the destroyer; the name ascribed to the angel of the abyss; king and head of the apocalyptic locusts, may well be applied to Prince Alcohol, emphatically, “The Destroyer.” better known As Brandy, Beer, or Gin! Roused up at Reason's clarion cry, We go to holy war, To slay the dragon, or to die! Hurrah! hurrah! hurrah! Hurrah! hurrah! there's joy within, Where all before was wo; And sunk is passion's dreadful din, And crush'd for aye 's the foe. Yet one charge more, in glorious strife, Stout hearts! to end the war; 'Tis done—our spoils! the babe! the w Hurrah! hurrah! hurrah! Debased by drink, we'd lost the sign Of manhood, God imprest, The open face, the look divine To show what He had blest. Behold! erect! with honest brow, Restored to Nature's law— We're men! we're men! heaven knows us now, Hurrah! hurrah! hurrah! Of ten men cleansed, did one return To bless the healing hour? All of our rescued thousands burn To praise redeeming power. Come! bless God now! and what for us He's done—so reads the law— We'll do for others! and the curse Root out; hurrah! hurrah! Hurrah! hurrah! we've burst the chain; O God! how long it bound us! We run! we leap! O God, again Thy light, thy air surround us. From midnight's dungeon-depths brought out, We hail hope's rising star; Ho, comrades! give the stirring shout, Hurrah! hurrah! hurrah! DRINK OF THIS CUP. Tune—Peterboro.' (C. M.) Drink of this cup! 'tis that which erst Our pilgrim fathers quaffed, When here they raised their dwellings first: There 's safety in the draught. Drink of this cup! the stream that laved Old Lethe's fabled shore, From want and misery never saved, Like that which now we pour. Drink of this cup! it bears a charm Of more than magic worth: A spell to keep the soul from harm, A gift from heaven to earth. Drink of this cup! its virtue strong Shall keep the soul so bright, That angel visiters may throng, Rejoicing in its light. Drink of this cup which temperance brings, And reap the immortal gain! See peace beneath her spreading wings, And freedom in her train. Drink only of this crystal cup! Now be the deep vow spoken! Now in the strength of God rise up! And keep your vow unbroken. ODE. Tune:—“Brighton.” (L. M.) The temperance pledge—the Temperance song, In tuneful chorus let us sing; Here our proud banners wave along,— Our heart's best tribute we will bring; Here let the patriot's song ascend, Here all our holiest feelings blend. 'Tis Freedom's day—the favored day To chant the hymn of Liberty And all our choicest offerings lay Upon the altar of the free; To God our raptured voices raise The grateful homage of our praise. Sing of the fount—the crystal stream Whose sparkling waters ever flow; Revere the sacred, holy theme, Which cheers the heart in joy or wo: The Temperance pledge,—the Temperance theme, The healing fount—the cooling stream. Here, midst our ranks, with joy we view The captive from his chains set free; His altered mien,—his feelings new, We all with grateful pleasure see; No more he drains the deadly bowl; The healing fount hath made him whole. Far o'er the land—far o'er the wave, Our banners peacefully shall float; The young, the beautiful, and the brave To this great cause their lives devote; Then raise the Temperance shout on high, And sing the fount that's never dry! THE OLD OAKEN BUCKET. How dear to my heart are the days of my childhood, When fond recollection presents to my view The orchard, the meadow, the deep-tangled wild wood, And ev'ry lov'd spot which my infancy knew; The wide spreading pond, and the mill which stood by it; The bridge and the rock where the cataract fell, The cot of my father, the dairy-house nigh it, And e'en the rude bucket that hung in the well— The old oaken bucket, The iron bound the bucket, The moss covered bucket that hung in the well. That moss covered bucket I hail as a treasure; For often at noon, when return'd from the field, I found it the source of an exquisite pleasure, The purest and sweetest that nature could yield. How ardent I seized it, with hands that were glowing, And quick to the white pebbled bottom it fell; Then soon, with the emblem of truth overflowing, And dripping with coolness, it rose from the well. The old oaken bucket, The iron bound bucket, The moss covered bucket arose from the well. How sweet from the green mossy rim to receive it, As pois'd on the curb it inclined to my lips; Not a full flowing goblet could tempt me to leave it, Tho' filled with the nectar that Jupiter sips. And now, far removed from that situation, The tear of regret will intrusively swell, As fancy reverts to my father's plantation, And sighs for the bucket which hung in the well. The old oaken bucket, The iron bound bucket, The moss covered bucket that hung in the well. THE WIFE'S REJOICING. Tune:—“There's nae luck about the house.” And are ye sure the news is true, And are ye sure he's signed? I can't believe the joyful tale, And leave my fears behind. If John has signed and drinks no more, The happiest wife am I That ever swept a cottage hearth, Or sung a lullaby! For there's nae luck about the house, O there 's nae' luck at a', And gane 's the comfort o' the house, Since he to drink did fa'! Whose eye so kind, whose hand so strong, Whose love so true will shine, If he has bent his heart and hand The total pledge to sign. But what puts doubting in my head? I trust he 'll taste no more; Be still, be still, my beating heart! Hark! hark! he 's at the door! For there 's nae luck about the house, &amp;c. And blessings on the helping hands, That send him back to me, Haste, haste, ye little ones, and run Your father's face to see. And are you sure, my John, you 've signed? And are you sure 't is past? Then mine 's the happiest, brightest home On tem'prance' shores at last! There 's been nae luck about the house, But now 'tis comfort a'! And Heaven preserve my ain gude man, That he may never fa'. HYMN OF THE EMANCIPATED. Tunes:—Duke street—Old Hundred. L. M. Before thy throne we boast the name Of Freemen:—God, thy frown is just. Immortals, break your bonds of shame! Arise, inebriates, from the dust! Slavery and death the cup contains; Dash to the earth the poisoned bowl! Softer than silk are iron chains, Compared with those that chafe the soul. Hosannas, Lord, to thee we sing, Whose power the giant fiend obeys. What countless thousands tribute bring, For happier homes and brighter days! Thou wilt not break the bruised reed, Nor leave the broken heart unbound: The wife regains a husband freed! The orphan clasps a father found! Spare, Lord, the thoughtless, guide the blind; Till man no more shall deem it just To live, by forging chains to bind His weaker brother in the dust. With nature's draught your goblets fill, And pledge the world that ye are free! God of eternal truth, WE WILL! Our cause is thine, our trust in thee! THE SEAMAN'S LAY. Air—Oh! no, we never mention her. List, shipmates, to a seamen's lay: Jack Temperance and Jack Grog Are gallant sailors in their way, As ever hove a log: But Grog's a lad of fits and starts; You'll find him sharp and slow; Now hot, now cold: his spirits up, He's all for dash and blow. But if at times he's sharp and quick, 'T is soon he'll flag and tire; And then so hot, he'd eat Old Nick, Or set the sea on fire! And though you hear him brag full oft He bangs the other hollow, I never knew him go aloft, When Temperance would not follow. But when he's had the drop he likes— He loves his glass we know— The squall comes on, the boatswain pipes All hands to reef and stow: 'T is then aloft, and lying out, To reef, or stow, or bend, Jack Temperance has the ready hand To stay his falling friend. Oh! Temperance is a seaman bold As ever trod the deck; And oft, when seas like mountains roll'd, Has saved the ship from wreck; And when there rolls that mountain-sea, All theatening to o'erwhelm, White breakers thundering on the lee, Let Temperance take the helm. THE TEMPERANCE CREW. Air—The Bold Buccaneer. Luff up, boys! clew up, and furl every sail; Clear the cables—let all fly, and clew; Though rocks are a-lee, she will laugh at the gale, For our ship has a Temperance crew. Chorus. Tho' rocks are a-lee, she will laugh at the gale, For our ship has a Temperance Crew. We ask not “grog courage,” so vaunted of yore; Let it blow as it never yet blow! To ride amidst breakers upon a lee shore Is the vaunt of a Temperance Crew. Chorus To ride amidst breakers upon a lee shore Is the vaunt of a Temperance crew. Down anchors—pay out—let her swing free and wide: As our hearts, so our cables are true; Like a sea bird she sits!—now she breasts the rough tide! Hold on then, brave Temperance crew. Chorus. Like a sea bird she sits, as she breasts the rough tide! Hold on then, brave Temperance crew. Come, a bright, bright look-out. Hail each lull, or a pause In the gale!—we have death in our view! But may weather the squall—for in God and our cause Is the trust of a Temperance crew. Chorus. But may weather the squall—for in God and our cause Is the trust of a Temperance crew Bear a hand—the storm lulls—and the tide sets off fast, Ere again the wild hurricane brew, Set her topsails, and slip—and the danger is past; Then huzza for a Temperance crew. Chorus. Set her topsails, and slip,—and the danger is past; Then huzza for a Temperance crew. THE VOICE OF MY COUNTRY. Tune—“Aylesbury.” S. M. I heard a bitter sigh Break from a mother's breast, And knew it was my country's voice That thus her sons addrest,— “Ye are my crown of hope,— Dim not its peerless ray,— Ye are the sinews of my strength,— Cast not that strength away. There is a fiery cup,— Whose ministry of wo Can melt the spirit's purest pearl, And lay the mightiest low. Turn from its treacherous tide, Repel its siren claim, Nor make me 'mid the nations blush, And mourn my children's shame. And will ye, in the fire That 's in the wine cup brought, The record of my fame consume, By blood and suffering bought?— And will ye cast a stain Upon my banner's ray, Which all the rivers of your realm Can never wash away?” O! SHUN THE BOWL. Tune—Burns' Farewell. Hebron. (L. M.) O! shun the bowl!—the draught beware, Whose smile but mocks the lips of men: When foaming high with waters rare— O! never touch the goblet then. With friends we love, though sweet to sip The nectar'd juice at close of day, Yet trust ye not the siren lip That wins to cheat, and lures to slay. O! shun the bowl, and thou shalt know A deeper spell than swims in wine; Though bright its hours of sunset glow, Their crimson clouds as briefly shine. A few short days in madness past, And thou wilt sink unknown to years; Without a hope beyond the blast, Which mourns above thy grave of tears. WELCOME BROTHERS! FOR A COLD WATER ARMY. Tune:—“Watchman, tell us of the night.” Welcome, brothers, welcome here! Cheerful are our hearts to-day, Tell us, we would gladly hear, How our cause speeds on its way. Brothers, then the foe shall fall, When we take our father's seats, Here we pledge us, one and all, We will drive him from our streets. 'Tis on us the work depends, On the young and rising race; And we'll try to make amends For our country's deep disgrace. Here we pledge ourselves anew, Not to touch the drunkard's drink; Proving faithful, proving true, We will make the demon shrink. SONG OF THE REDEEMED. Auld Lang Syne. Brattle street. Jordan. C. M. We come! we come, that have been held In burning chains so long, We 're up! and on we come, a host Full fifty thousand strong. The chains we 've snapped that held us round The wine-vat and the still;— Snapped by a blow—nay, by a word, That mighty word I WILL! We come from Belial's palaces, The tippling shop and bar; And, as we march, those gates of hell Feel their foundations jar. The very ground, that oft has held All night our throbbing head, Knows that we're up—no more to fall, And trembles at our tread. From dirty den, from gutter foul, From watch-house and from prison, Where they, who gave the poisonous glass, Had thrown us, have we risen; From garret high have hurried down, From cellar stived and damp Come up;—till alley, lane and street Echo our earthquake tramp. And on—and on—a swelling host Of temperance men we come, Contemning and defying all The powers and priests of rum: A host redeemed, who 've drawn the sword, And sharpened up its edge, And hewn our way, through hostile ranks, To the tee-total pledge. To God be thanks, who pours us out Cold water from his hills, In crystal springs and babbling brooks, In lakes and sparkling rills! From these to quench our thirst we come, With freeman's shout and song, A host already numbering more Than fifty thousand strong. WASHINGTONIAN SONG. Tunes—“Indian Philosopher.” “Of all the lands.” Of all the causes East or West I love the Temperance Cause the best— I love its cheerful greetings: No joys on earth can e'er be found, Like those pure pleasures which abound At Washingtonian meetings. Of all the people, East or West, I love the Temperance men the best, I love their noble spirit! In generous deeds, not words, they deal; They have at heart the poor man's weal— All praise their efforts merit. To all the world I give my hand— My heart is with that noble band, The Washingtonian Brothers. God speed and prosper every plan Whose basis is the good of man, But this before all others. NEW YEAR'S HYMN. Burns' Farewell—Old Hundred—Mendon. (L M.) We praise thee—if one rescued soul, While the past year prolonged its flight, Turned shuddering, from the poisonous bowl, To health, and liberty, and light. We praise thee—if one clouded home, Where broken hearts, despairing, pined, Behold the sire and husband come, Erect, and in his perfect mind. No more a weeping wife to mock, Who on his arm in faith had leaned, No more the trembling mind to shock, And sink the father in the fiend. Still give us grace, Almighty King! Unwavering at our posts to stand, 'Till, grateful at thy shrine we bring The tribute of a ransomed land. TEMPERANCE RALLY. Air—“All on Hobbies.” We have entered the field, and are ready to fight, Against the rum demon from morning till night, The groggeries, too, we're determined to crush, And we'll drink good cold water to nerve for the brush. Who will go with us—will you go with us, Will you go with us for temperance too? We're determined to conquer or die in the fight, For we can't bear a rum hole at all in our sight, For they look bad—they smell bad—they are bad we know, So come along with us, for on we will go. Who will go with us, &amp;c. Now ye dealers in rum, our advice is to you, Just drop your foul traffic, it never will do. It is injuring us—it is ruining you, So get yourselves out and go teetotal too. Who will go with us, &amp;c. And ladies, good ladies, we ask you to night, Just go along with us and aid in the fight— With you on our side, this is what we will do, We'll make all the topers to go teetotal too. Who will go with us, &amp;c. FOURTH OF JULY ODE. America. Italian Hymn. (6 &amp; 4) With patriotic glee, Columbia's jubilee Once more we hail: Let nothing damp our joys— The Temp'rance pledge destroys The last foe that annoys.— Quail, monster, quail! To aid us in the fray, A new and bold array Push to the field:— Men who for years have quaff'd The devil's firy draught, Have grappled with the Craft, Thundering “Yield!” Through this most blessed breach The drunkard we can reach!— Oh! joyful sound! The wife's crushed hopes revive— The drunkard's children thrive— The dead return alive— The lost are found! The captive to unbind— To save from wreck the mind Torn, tempest-tossed— May Heaven this labor speed Till from the foe we're freed, And not one heart shall bleed For loved ones lost. Our fathers, when they broke Proud Britain's galling yoke, Fought one good fight!— A better one fight they Who “cast the bowl away,” And toast this glorious day In water bright. Reformers, go ahead! No more let it be said By freedom's foe, That this, our fair domain, Wears worse than British chain, Under the tyrant reign Of ‘Death &amp; Co.’ HYMN. Tune—“Windham.” “Hamburg,” L. M. O! shun the bowl—as thou wouldst leave The poison'd spot where reptiles crawl; Lest widow'd hearts for thee should grieve— For thee untimely tears should fall. Yea! thine may be the fearful lot To prove, ere Time bath dimm'd thy brow, A sire—and yet the witness not Of them who weep his broken vow. Hast thou a bride whose every sigh Deep trembles with the joy it gives? Hast thou a child whose meek mild eye Lives in the light its father lives? Then shun the bowl—the draught beware, Whose smile but mocks the lips of men; When foaming high with waters rare— O never touch the goblet then! AWAKE, AWAKE, AND TAKE THE PLEDGE There is nae luck about the house. Archdale. C. M. Awake! awake! and take the pledge, Without a fear or doubt! 'T will weave around your heart a hedge, To keep the demon out; 'T will wake a thrill of heavenly joy In her who weeps at home; And laughing girl and prattling boy Will smile to see you come. O, take the pledge and break the cup That poisons all the land! 'T will sweetly come and raise you up, Where Honor waves her hand; 'T will wipe contempt and scorn away, Which all that knew ye bore, Till ye become beloved as they, And ye are brutes no more. O, take the pledge, poor, trembling sot! Dash down the poisonous wave! Ye see the dreadful path you've got To travel to the grave. Come joyful up: there's hope, there's bliss, And blessings yet in store, Even in a checkered world like this, If you will drink no more. O, take the pledge, all ye that think Of moderate cups to-day! For ye may win the sot from drink If ye but lead the way. 'T will be a sweet and thrilling thought, As on through life you go, That one poor wretch was timely caught, And snatched from shame and wo. O, take the pledge, all ye that sell This poison of the soul! What good ye'll do, no tongue can tell, By dashing down the bowl. The drunkard's wife, with tears of joy, Will bless you morn and even; And lovely girl and happy boy Will lisp your name to Heaven. O, take the pledge, both old and young— The resolution seal! It would require an angel's tongue To tell the joy ye 'll feel. Your heart will then the deed approve, Though grovelling sense should frown; And God himself will bend in love, And send a blessing down. TEMPERANCE HYMN. Tune—Mondon. Ward. L. M. God of our fathers! Thee we praise; To-day, our grateful thanks ascend: Accept these thanks—our cheerful lays With organ's solemn chantings blend. Thy grace the wretched drunkard found Cast out, and weltering in his blood; Now from his tongue doth praise resound— He owes that praise to thee, O God! Restored to virtue by thy hand, The father, brother, son, arise; From sin and wo reclaimed, they stand, And swell thy praise with tearful eyes. The mother, sister, daughter, too, With tears of gratitude and praise, Behold the change, and now, anew, Receive their friends to their embrace. No longer poverty and shame— A sad inheritance—are theirs; Their altered looks aloud proclaim A happy change in their affairs. Thanks, thanks, to thee, O God, we give! What better tribute can we pay? 'T is on thy bounties that we live;— We praise thee for this festal day! THANKSGIVING HYMN. Air:—“America.” Italian Hymn. (6 &amp; 4.) God of the spreading earth, From many a happy hearth, This day shall rise Thanks from glad hearts to thee, For heaven-born liberty, That wakes from hosts made free,— Reaching the skies. Thanksgiving will we bring, That wives this hour may sing, In holy strains, Triumphant songs, for sires Plucked from their funeral pyres, Erst bound in angry fires, And damning chains. From crowding children break Anthems that raptures wake, For parents found; With dawning light they bend Where holy thoughts ascend, And prayer and praises blend In joy profound. God of the Right! still speed Our holy cause, till freed Is every soul; Let echoing pæans swell, Telling that Truth can quell The raging fires of hell, From pole to pole. TEMPERANCE HYMN. Tune:—“Zion,”—from the Boston Academy's Collection of Church Music. From the mountain top and valley, See! the banner streaming high! While the sons of freedom rally, To the widow's lonely cry. Sisters weeping, Bid us to the rescue fly. Could we hear the mother pleading, Heaven relief would quickly send; Can we see our country bleeding, And refuse our aid to lend? No! dread monster, Here thy triumph soon shall end. Hear the trump of Temperance sounding, Rouse! ye freemen, why delay? Let your voices all resounding, Welcome in the happy day When that tyrant Must resign his cruel sway. Nor again shall he molest us, Though he has oppress'd us sore, Nor his poisonous breath infest us— Soon we'll drive him from our shore: All uniting, Shout, “the monster's reign is o'er.” THE PLAGUE. Tunes.—“Ballermo.” St Martin. C. M. “The Plague! the Plague! bring out your dead.” Through all the land the cry Rang shrilly forth. “We bring our dead!” Was murmured in reply. And still no art could stay the sore, By night, by day it ran; Till written on our nation's door, Was “Lazaret of Man!” Beyond the pestilence that sweeps The Oriental power, Where Death, the busy toiler, reaps A province in an hour; To touch and taste, and taste and die, And fill the maniac's grave, Millions essayed, till from the sky, Came Abstinence to save. Now we are healed! yet at the pool Lie many in their sin; The “moderate” mad, the ruined fool— No angel puts them in. Ay, angel Temperance never tires, But healing wing doth plume Where soaring Faith, itself, expires, And Hope is in the tomb. Shout, Drunkard! shout! your chain of steel Is sundered, link by link; Shout, Maker! Vender! ye can feel, Shout, Children! ye may think. And Woman, in whose halcyon breast The star of hope doth shine, Would shout—but tears reveal the rest— Lord God! the work is thine. TE-TOTALLER'S AULD LANG SYNE. Be days of drinking wine forgot, Let water goblets shine— And from your memory ever blot The days of drinking wine. Those days of drinking wine my friend, Those days of drinking wine; A temperance hour is worth a power Of days of drinking wine! We twa have quaff'd in days long past Bright juices of the vine, But let us from our memories cast Those customs of “lang syne.” Bad customs of “lang syne,” my friend, Bad customs of “lang syne;” Our temperance age must blot the page Of customs of “lang syne.” We twa can meet as friends should meet, We twa together dine, Our beverage quaff from fountains sweet, And never think of wine. At temperance's shrine, we're pledg'd, my friend, We're pledged at her fair shrine; And hold her cause above the laws And customs of “lang syne.” ODE. Tune:—“Scots wha hae.” Friends of freedom! swell the song; Young and old, the strain prolong, Make the temp'rance army strong And on to victory. Lift your banners, let them wave, Onward march the world to save; Who would fill a drunkard's grave, And bear his infamy? Shrink not when the foe appears; Spurn the coward's guilty fears; Hear the shrieks, behold the tears Of ruined families! Raise the cry in every spot— “Touch not—Taste not—Handle not,” Who would be a drunken sot, The worst of miseries? Give the aching bosom rest; Carry joy to every breast; Make the wretched drunkard blest, By living soberly. Raise the glorious watchward high— “Touch not, taste not, till you die!” Let the echo reach the sky, And earth keep jubilee. God of mercy! hear us plead, For thy help we intercede! See how many bosoms bleed! And heal them speedily. Hasten, Lord, the happy day, When beneath thy gentle ray, Temp'rance all the world shall sway, And reign triumphantly. THE CUP FOR ME. Tune:—“The rose that all are praising.” The drink that's in the drunkard's bowl Is not the drink for me, It kills his body and his soul, How sad a sight is he! But there's a drink that God has given, Distilling in the showers of heaven, In measures large and free; Oh, that's the drink for me. (Repeat 3 ts.) The stream that many prize so high, Is not the stream for me; For he who drinks it still is dry, Forever dry he'll be. But there's a stream so cool and clear, The thirsty traveller lingers near, Refreshed and glad is he; Oh, that's the stream for me. The winecup that so many prize Is not the cup for me; The aching head, the bloated face, In its sad train I see, But there's a cup of water pure, And he who drinks it may be sure Of strength, when old is he;— Oh, that's the cup for me. THE COLD WATER ARMY. Tune.—“Auld Lang Syne.” With banner and with badge we come, An Army true and strong, To fight against the hosts of rum, And this shall be our song:— We love the clear cold water springs, Supplied by gentle showers: We feel the strength cold water brings— “The victory is ours.” “Cold Water Army,” is our name,— O may we faithful be, And so in truth and justice claim The blessings of the free. We love the clear, &amp;c. Though others love their rum and wine, And drink till they are mad, To water we will still incline, To make us strong and glad, We love the clear, &amp;c. I pledge to thee this hand of mine, In faith and friendship strong; And, fellow-soldiers, we will join The chorus of our song: We love the clear, &amp;c. THE TEMPERANCE SHIP. Tune—Weymouth. H. M. Speed, speed the temperance ship! Ye winds fill every sail, Behold her on the deep, Outriding every gale, The tempest's fury she out-braves, And hosts of deathless drunkards saves. Speed, speed the Temperance ship! Who joins us in the cry? Mothers and children, cease to weep, Our ship is passing by: We wish to take you all on board— A freight of mercy to the Lord. Speed, speed the Temperance ship! For her we 'll ever pray, 'T is Israel's God alone can keep In safety, night and day; On him we'll evermore depend, Who is the contrite drunkard's friend. Speed, speed the Temperance ship! Ye young and aged shout, Behold her sailing o'er the deep, With all her streamers out, Bound for the true tee-total shore— Where streams of death are drunk no more. WATER!—OH! WATER FOR ME. “Osborne.” “Lyons.” (10s.) Repeat the 3d and 4th strains. Oh! water for me—bright water for me! And wine for the tremulous debauchee! It cooleth the brow, it cooleth the brain, It maketh the faint one strong again; It comes o'er the sense like a breeze from the sea: All freshness, like infant purity. Oh water for me, bright water, for me! Give wine, give wine to the debauchee! Fill to the brim! fill, fill to the brim! Let the flowing crystal kiss the rim: For my hand is steady, my eye is true, For I, like the flowers, drink nothing but dew. Oh! water, bright water's a mine of wealth, And the ores it yieldeth are vigour and health. So water, pure water for me, for me! And wine for the tremulous debauchee! When over the hills, like a gladsome bride, Morning walks forth in her beauty's pride, And leading a band of laughing hours, Brushes the dew from the nodding flowers, Oh! cheerily then my voice is heard, Mingling with that of the soaring bird, Who flingeth abroad his matins loud, As he freshens his wing in the cold grey cloud. But when evening has quitted her sheltering yew, Drowsily flying, and weaving anew, Her dusky meshes o'er land and sea, How gently, oh Sleep, fall thy poppies on me! For water I drink, pure, cold and bright, And my dreams are of heaven the live long night. So, hurrah for thee, water, hurrah, hurrah! Thou art silver and gold, thou art ribbon and star, Hurrah for bright water! hurrah! hurrah! AWAY THE BOWL. Tune:—“Away, away to School. Our grateful hearts with temperance burn, Away, away the bowl, From dram shops all, our steps we turn, Away, away the bowl; Farewell to rum and all its harms, Farewell the wine-cup's boasted charms, Away the bowl, away the bowl, away, away the bowl. See how that staggering drunkard reels! Away, away the bowl; Alas, the misery he reveals, Away, away the bowl; His children grieve, his wife's in tears! How sad his once bright home appears! Away the bowl, away the bowl, away, away the bowl. We drink no more, nor buy nor sell, Away, away the bowl! The grog-shop's offers we repel, Away, away the bowl. United in a temperance band, We 're joined in heart, we 're joined in hand, Away the bowl, away the bowl, away, away the bowl. 'T IS BUT A DROP. Tune:—“Auld Lang Syne.” “Jordan.” C. M. “'Tis but a drop” the father said, And gave it to his son; But little did he think a work Of death was then begun. The “drop” that lured him when the babe Scarce lisped his father's name, Planted a fatal appetite Deep in his infant frame. “'T is but a drop,” the comrades cried, In truant school-boy tone; “It did not hurt us in our robes, It will not now we're grown.” And so they drank the mixture up— That reeling, youthful band; For each had learned to love the taste From his own father's hand. “'T is but a drop,” the husband said, While his poor wife stood by, In famine, grief, and loneliness, And raised th' imploring cry. “'T is but a drop—I'll drink it still— 'T will never injure me: I always drink—so, madam, hush! We never can agree.' She wept, she pleaded, but in vain, The hunger of her child, And her own tatter'd dress—the wretch Her mournful words revil'd. He took the cup with fiend-like air, And deep and long he drank; Then dash'd it down, and on the earth Insensible he sank. “'T is but a drop—I need it now,” The staggering drunkard said; “It was my food in infancy— My meat, and drink, and bread. A drop—a drop—oh, let me have, 'T will so refresh my soul!” He took it—trembled—drank and died, Grasping the fatal bowl. THE DYING DRUNKARD. Tune—Oh no, we never mention her. Stretch'd on a heap of straw—his bed!— The dying drunkard lies; His joyless wife supports his head, And to console him tries: His weeping children's love would ease His spirit, but in vain:— Their ill paid love destroys his peace;— He'll never smile again. His boon companions—where are they— Who shared his heart and bowl? They come not nigh, to charm away The horrors from his soul. What have gay friends to do with those Who press the couch of pain? And HE is rack'd with mortal throes;— He'll never speak again. GOD'S HELP IMPLORED. Halelujah metre. How long, O God, how long Must thy pure eyes behold This fair world blasted by the wrong, Man does to man for gold? How long shall Reason be cast down, And a fierce demon wear her crown? The mother of our race, Whose sin brought death and wo, Yet in her weakness found thy grace;— The Tempter's curse we know: Doth he who drinks, wrong most the soul? Or he who tempts him to the bowl? Help us, O God, to weigh Our deeds as in thy scales; Nor let gold dust the balance sway:— For good o'er gold prevails, At that dread bar where all must look Upon the record in thy Book MEMORY OF THE PAST. Air—Auld Lang Syne. Can we forget the gloomy time, When Bacchus ruled the day,— When dissipation, sloth and crime, Bore undisputed sway? The time—the time—the gloomy time The time has passed away, When dissipation, sloth, and crime, Bore undisputed sway. Can we forget the tender wives, Who found an early tomb? For, ah! the partners of their lives Had met the drunkard's doom. The wives—the wives—the tender wives May bid adieu to gloom; For now the partners of their lives Abhor the drunkard's doom. We'll ne'er forget that noble band, Who feared no creature's frown, And boldly pledged both heart and hand To put intemperance down. The band—the band—the noble band— The band of blest renown— Who boldly pledged both heart and hand To put intemperance down. Nor shall the Pledge be e'er forgot, That so much bliss creates— We'll touch not—taste not—handle not, Whate'er intoxicates. The Pledge—the Pledge is not forgot— The pledge that Satan hates; We'll touch not—taste not—handle not, Whate'er intoxicates. THE WASHINGTONIAN CALL. Tune—“When I can read my title clear.” Come join the Washingtonians, Ye young men bold and strong, And with a proud and cheerful zeal, Come, help the cause along. O that will be joyful, joyful, joyful, O that will be joyful, when young men drink no more, When young men drink no more, on all our happy shore; 'T is then we'll sing and offerings bring, When young men drink no more. Come join the Washingtonians, Ye men of riper years, And save your wives and children dear From want, and bitter tears. O that will be joyful, joyful, joyful, O that will be joyful, when strong men drink no more, When strong men drink no more on all our happy shore; 'T is then we'll sing and offerings bring, When strong men drink no more. Come join the Washingtonians, Ye men of hoary heads, And end your days where temperance Its peaceful influence sheds. O that will be joyful, joyful, joyful, O that will be joyful, when old men drink no more, When old men drink no more, as they have done before; 'T is then we'll sing and offerings bring, When old men drink no more. Come join the Washingtonians, Ye dames and maidens fair, And breathe around us in our path, Affection's hallowed air. O that will be joyful, joyful, joyful, O that will be joyful, when woman cheers us on, When woman cheers us on, to conquests not yet won; 'T is then we'll sing and offerings bring, When woman cheers us on. Come join the Washingtonians, Ye who distill, and sell The poison, that destroys the health, And brings the fatal spell. O that will be joyful, joyful, joyful, O that will be joyful when the STILL is worked no more, When the STILL is worked no more, on all our happy shore 'T is then we'll sing and offerings bring, When the STILL is worked no more. Come join the Washingtonians, Ye sons and daughters all, Of this our own America, Come at the friendly call. O that will be joyful, joyful, joyful, O that will be joyful, when all shall proudly say,— When all shall proudly say, “Away the bowl, away.” 'T is then we'll sing and offerings bring, When all shall own our sway. DRINKING SONG. Tunes—“Tolland.” “Archdale,” C. M. Drink, friends, drink deep—the moon is high; Drink, and forget your care— The sultry summer suns are nigh— Drink, and your strength repair; The deer, that from the hunter flies, The warrior, red with slaughter, The camel, under burning skies, Quaff deep the crystal water! Our father, Sun, the example gives, Our mother, Earth, also; He, jocund, drinks above the clouds, She, blushing, drinks below— Pledge high, pledge long, the friends you love, To absent wife and daughter, Or blooming maid who rules your heart, Drink deep—but in cold water! THE RANSOMED DRUNKARD'S SONG Tune—“Canaan.” Our days of noise and strife are past, We drink, we drink no more; We're happy now, as kings at last, We drink, &amp;c. Once guilt and shame enwrapp'd our frame, And scorn and laughter met our name; 'T is pleasant now, 't is pleasant now, We drink, &amp;c. No longer now we loathe our food, We drink, &amp;c. Kind Nature's bounty does us good, We drink, &amp;c. We now give up the drunkard's cup, And sweetly breakfast, dine and sup, We're hearty now, we're hearty now, We drink, &amp;c. Our friends no longer do us harm, We drink, &amp;c. Sweet Friendship's smile regains its charm, We drink, &amp;c. Each friend and foe that used to throw, Dark frowns where'er we used to go, Are pleasant now, are pleasant now, We drink, &amp;c. The wags no longer laugh and scoff, We drink, &amp;c. Our filthy rags have fallen off, We drink, &amp;c. The spindle plies,—the shuttle flies, And forms a cloth that kings might prize, For us to wear, for us to wear, We drink, &amp;c. Our shattered huts have tumbled down, We drink, &amp;c. They 've disappeared all over town, We drink, &amp;c. The neat white cot, that we have got, Of all this world the sweetest spot, Is where we live—is where we live— We drink, &amp;c. FOURTH OF JULY WASHINGTONIAN SONG. Tune—“The morning light is breaking.” A glorious day is breaking, Upon our sinful earth, Our land to life is waking, With shouts of joy and mirth; Our army is preparing To meet the rising sun, On all its banners bearing The name of Washington. We meet to day in gladness:— As moves our host along, No note of painful sadness Is mingled with our song; This day, renowned in story, The day of freedom's birth, We hail in all its glory, We highly prize its worth. The temp'rance flag is waving, O'er valley, hill, and plain, Where ocean's sons are braving, The dangers of the main; The pledge, the pledge, is given To float on every breeze, Waft it, propitious heaven, O'er all the earth and seas. Our cause, our cause, is gaining New laurels every day; The youthful mind we're training, To walk in virtue's way; Old age, and sturdy manhood, Are with us heart and hand, Then let us all united In one firm phalanx stand. HYMN. Tune:—“From Greenland's Icy Mountains.’ From the bright crystal fountain That flows in beauty free, From shady hill and mountain Fill high the cup for me! Sing of the sparkling waters, Sing of the cooling spring— Let Freedom's sons and daughters Their joyous tribute bring. From many a happy dwelling, Late misery's dark abode, Now the glad peal is swelling— The hymn of praise to God. Hear the glad song ascending, From many thankful hearts; Hope, Joy, and Peace are blending, And each its aid imparts. We'll join the tuneful chorus, And raise our song on high; The cheering view before us Delights the raptured eye;— The glorious cause is gaining New strength from day to day,— The drunkard host is waning, Before cold water's sway. BEGONE VILE RUM. Air—“Begone, dull Care.” Begone, vile rum, I prithee begone from me, Begone, vile rum, thou and I shall never agree, Long time hast thou destroyed my home And fain thou would'st me kill, But I tell thee, murderous demon, Rum, Thou never shalt have thy will. Too much wine will make a young man run mad, And too much gin, an old man ugly and sad. The pledge is signed, my wife shall sing And happily pass the day, Cold water, we find, is the very thing To banish grief away. TEMPERANCE JUBILEE. Tune—“All are here.” Cheerily, cheerily sound the joyful strain; Happily, happily now we meet again, Here we' stand, On this cheerful temperance day, Gracious God to thee we pray, Let our cause, so righteous, sway Every heart in the land. Cheerily, cheerily sound the joyful strain; Happily, happily, now we meet again; We are here, We who love the temperance cause, We who wish for righteous laws, We cold water girls and boys, We are here—we are here. Cheerily, cheerily sound the joyful strain; Happily, happily, now we meet again; Here we raise Songs of praise to God, who sends Blessings on our temperance friends. On Him all our hope depends, For the triumph of this cause. THE SAVING PLEDGE. Air—Paradise. C. M. No more the sparkling glass invites, It hath no charm for me; The spell that bound me with delights Is broken; and I'm free! It lur'd me from my happy home, It fill'd my heart with woe; It made me wretched and forlorn, A wanderer to and fro. A beam of light broke on my mind, Why was I thus distress'd? What power on earth the will can bind? By whom was I oppress'd? Ay, now I see my deadly foe— His hideous form appears: He lurks within the pois'nous bowl, 'Mid sighs, and groans, and tears. The poison'd chalice to my lips Shall ne'er again be press'd The Pledge I'll ever, ever keep, For by the Pledge I'm bless'd! THE PRODIGAL'S RETURN. HARMONIZED FOR FOUR VOICES. Air—“Home, sweet home.” Too long have I stray'd, yet no more will I roam; I'll return, for my Father is calling me home. The richest of banquets his love will prepare, And the best of his robes is awaiting me there. Home, home, sweet heavenly home; There's no place on earth like my sweet heavenly home. By the smile of the harlot, her song and her wine, I've been made to lie down, and eat husks with the swine. But now she may smile, and her goblet may foam In vain, for I'm bound to my sweet heavenly home. Home, home, &amp;c. O, Father, though long hath thy prodigal child, Gone astray where the cup of the tempter hath smiled; Yet, now he hath broken the charm and the snare, To thy mansion receive him to sing to thee there, “Home, home, &amp;c. SONG. THE BUBBLING SPRING. If one bright spot there is on earth, More lovely than the rest, One, which fond nature at her birth, With purest beauty blest; It is the place where some cool fount Its crystal waters fling; Where, in the mead, or on the mount, 'Mid rocks and flowers, that hide the fount, Gushes the bubbling spring. Tell me not of the sparkling bowl, That glows with red'ning fire; Oh tell me not of the joy of soul, The wine-cup can inspire! A brighter glass—a purer joy— A healthier draught I sing; Nature's own cup without alloy— Pleasure that reason can enjoy— Health from the bubbling spring. Then fill the glass with water bright— The nectar nature gave; Let faithful hearts round this unite, A bleeding world to save: For naught can soothe the woful wound, And heal the viper's sting— Nay naught these fires of death hath drown'd, But pure and healthful water, found Fresh in the bubbling spring. HYMN. I heard a voice from heav'n Address the thoughtless throng, Who hasten downward to the tomb, With revelry and song. It warned them not to quench The holy flame within, And madly dare the fearful doom Of unrepented sin. It warned them of the shame That haunts the drunkard's grave, And of that leprosy of soul From which no skill can save. I looked, and thousands fled The tempter's fatal snare; But some were number'd with the dead, Who shall their doom declare? NATIONAL ODE. Tune—“Daughter of Zion.” Land of Columbia! the morning is gleaming, The day-star of temp'rance is seen in the skies; Awake to the glorious light that is beaming! No more let the darkness o'ershadow thine eyes. Land of Columbia! the morning is gleaming, Now, hail its clear shining with soul-cheering cries. Land of Columbia! awake to thy glory! And let thy blest influence be felt the world o'er! Awake, till intemp'rance be known but in story, Awake, till its woes shall oppress thee no more! Land of Columbia! awake to thy glory! Awake!! and the foe SHALL OPPRESS THEE NO MORE ODE FOR THE FOURTH OF JULY. WHO ARE THE BRAVE? “Eglon.” “Laban.” L. M.—Bost. Acad. Col. Who are the brave, if they were not, The mighty men of Bunker-hill— Our sires!—who'd shrink, if they did not, Their country's glory to fulfil? Who are the free, if we are not, Their sons!—O God! of all thy earth Seest thou this day one blessed spot As free as that which gave us birth? Who are the brave, if they were not, The men who woke the strife again, And wiped away tho drunkard's blot, And dashed to earth his cruel chain? Who are the free, if we are not, Who will no longer garlands twine Around the cup, nor cast our lot With those that tarry at the wine? Rejoice! rejoice! and who will not, In all that heaven has done for man! If slaves of drink refuse, yet what Prevents the free, who truly can? For what to us is habit's power, And what the sparkling tempter's bite? Who's here, that triumphs not this hour, In temperance and in freedom's might. “ONLY THIS ONCE.” Tune—“Ward.”. L. M. “Only this once;” the wine-cup glowed, All sparkling with its ruby ray; The bacchanalian welcome flowed, And folly made the revel gay. Then he, so long, so deeply warned, The sway of conscience rashly spurned; His promise of repentance scorned, And, coward-like, to vice returned. “Only this once;”—the tale is told; He wildly quaffed the poisonous tide; With more than Esau's madness, sold The birthright of his soul, and died. I do not say that breath forsook The clay, and left its pulses dead; But reason in her empire shook, And all the life of life was fled. Again his eyes the landscape viewed; His limbs again their burden bore; And years their wonted course renewed; But hope and peace returned no more. [Onward! onward! band victorious,] Tunes—“Days of Absence,” or, “Bounding Billows.” Onward! onward! band victorious, Rear the temp'rance banner high! Thus far hath your course been glorious; Now your day of triumph's nigh. Vice and error flee before you, As the darkness flies the sun; Onward, victory hovers o'er you, Soon the battle will be won! Onward! onward! song and shouting Ring to heaven's sublimest arch, Whensoe'er your flag is floating, And your conquering legions march. Gird the temp'rance armor on you, Look for guidance from above; God and angels smile upon you, Hasten then your work of love! Lo, what multitudes despairing! Widows, orphans, heirs of wo, And the slaves their fetters wearing, Reeling madly to and fro; Mercy, justice, both entreat you To destroy their bitter foe; Christians, patriots, good men greet you: To the conflict bravely go! To the vender and distiller, Thunder truth with startling tone! Swell the accents louder, shriller, Make their guilt enormous known. Onward! onward! never falter, Cease not till the earth is free; Swear on temp'rance' holy altar, Death is yours, or Victory. ROGER WILLIAMS' SPRING. Tune—“The harp that once,” or, “Pilot on the deep.” Some sing the praise of rosy wine, Its sparkling color bright; But in such songs with them to join We cannot take delight. We have a rich and noble theme, Fit for a prince and king— 'T is water, pure, and fresh, and good, From Roger Williams' spring. This will give health, and joy, and peace, Refreshing every power; We want no better drink than this In trial's darkest hour. To cheer the heart and quench the thirst It is the very thing; Then give us water pure and good, From Roger Williams' spring. Our sires drank from this living spring Two hundred years ago; And from this fountain water clear Continues still to flow. Then we, on this our festal day, Will of its virtues sing, And drink this water, pure and good, From Roger Williams' spring. TEMPERANCE TRIUMPH. Tune—“Westboro'.” (8s&amp;7s.) Onward! Onward! all victorious, Bright thou Sun of temp'rance shine! Soon our triumph will be glorious, For our leader is divine. Sing victorious! Sing victorious! For our Leader is divine. God does work!—See, none can hinder; Weak the agents he'll employ— With his trumpet loudly thunder, Compass round, and then destroy! Walls of Satan! Walls of Satan! Compass round, He will destroy. Rouse thee! rouse thee! Christian sleeping! Hark! thy Master draweth near, Search the camp,—in wrath He's speaking, “That an Achan's shelter'd there!” Sons of Zion! Sons of Zion! See, an Achan's shelter'd there. E'en poor Erin now is bursting From the chains which long she wore! See her, for cold water thirsting! Alcohol she 'll drink no more! Happy Erin! Happy Erin! Alcohol she 'll drink no more! THE WORD OF HOPE. “Nuremburg.” Pleyel's Hymn.” 7s. There's a blessing on the wing; Some of want and misery, sing; This the simple solemn strain, This the word of hope, “Abstain:” Touch nor taste; for dark despair Fills the cup of poison there: With a heaven-uplifted eye, From the fell destroyer fly! Tens of thousands he has slain, Tens of thousands court his chain; Never more his portion take, For your souls' and mercy's sake. Hear your wives, your children plead, Hear the gospel intercede! Helpless drunkards, hither fly! “Touch not, taste not,” or you die! Die! alas! there is a doom, Darker than the darkest tomb, Blacker than the blackest night, Rayless sorrow, endless blight; There the dying drunkard goes, Draining draughts of bitterest woes, List, then, to the simple strain, Hear the word of hope—Abstain! THEY SAY THE GOBLET'S CROWNED WITH FLOWERS. Scotch air—“Bonny Doon.” They say the goblet's crown'd with flowers, And round its brim do brightly shine, Like gems, remember'd joys and hours, The treasures of immortal wine. We know the cup is wreathed with plants, More deadly than the Upas-tree; Its richest recollection haunts, The soul with all that misery. They say the draught has potent spell, To wean the thoughts from ills away; And raise the drooping one to dwell Where dreary night is chang'd to day. We deem the wretch may never know, The meaning of unmix'd despair, Till tempted by his bitt'rest foe, He seeks the cup and finds it there. HYMN. Tune—“Pleyel's Hymn.” Gracious God, to thee belong, Songs of praises ever more; Wilt thou hear our grateful song, While thy goodness we adore. Thou hast kindly deigned to bless, Every effort we have made; Crowned our labors with success, And the course of evil stay'd. Fervent praise we give to thee, Thou, our counsellor and friend, Wilt thou still our guardian be, Still thine aid and blessing lend. Ordered by thy sovereign will, Guided by thy mighty hand, May the cause of Temp'rance, still Spread triumphant through our land. THROUGHOUT COLUMBIA'S BORDERS. Throughout Columbia's borders, There rings a song of gladness; Without control, its numbers roll, Dispelling gloom and sadness. 'T is the sweet song of temp'rance, O'er hill and vale it boundeth; Throughout the land, on every hand, The joyful news resoundeth. As on the wings of morning, The cheering anthem flyeth, Its notes are sung by many a tongue, The concert never dieth; But temp'rance, temp'rance, temp'rance, O'er every hill-top boundeth; On land and main, the glorious strain Unceasingly resoundeth. Far o'er Atlantic billows, The rapt'rorus theme is ringing; In cheerful songs, ten thousand tongues, Its glorious strains are singing: While Erin's verdant island, With swelling acclamation; In concert loud, ascribes to God Her great regeneration! Soon shall the cruel tyrant, From his high throne be driven; Each galling chain be rent in twain, And every link be riven: Then temp'rance, peace, and virtue, Shall reign o'er earth victorious; Our flag unfurled, throughout the world, Shall wave in triumph glorious! HYMN. Tune—“Uxbridge.” We come, our Father, to thy throne, With grateful hearts and joyful lays, For thou hast made our cause thine own, To thee, to thee alone, be praise. We loose the sandals from our feet, We feel that this is holy ground; Then let us seek thy mercy-seat, For there alone may strength be found. Strength to press on and upward still, To rein each passion's wild career, To conquer ev'ry form of ill, Uncheck'd by pride, unaw'd by fear. We come with voice of praise and prayer, Then Father, hear us from above! O! make the Temperance cause thy care, And o'er it spread thy wing of love! NEW YEAR'S HYMN. Tune—“Hebron.” L. M. Another year has run its round, In Freedom's Hall again we're found; All our dear friends that here we see, We greet with song and jubilee. We here are met—a youthful band; We 're pledg'd in heart, we're joined in hand, With hopes elate, and spirits free, From ev'ry path of vice we flee. We seek for morals just and pure That will our future good ensure; For virtue, temperance, and truth, To guard us from the sins of youth. We look to God to keep and aid The resolutions we have made, To strengthen ev'ry youthful heart, And unto all his grace impart. LET HIM WHO MAY THINK. Tune—“Bethlehem.” Let him who may think It is well to drink A health of wine to his friend, Reflect on the way He's taking that day, And look to his coming end. The path from right Is not all bright, But a downward thorny road; And the flashing wine, Though it seems divine, Will lead to the drunkard's abode. The joys of health, And home, and wealth, Will pass like the flying thought; In the groggery's cell, That earthly hell, Will he at last be caught. HYMN. Tune—“Scots wha hae.” Children who have rallied now Where Immanuel's soldiers bow, Who will take the Temperance vow, As a volunteer? Children! hear the battle-cry, Sounding loud and sounding nigh From the throne of God on high, Who will volunteer? See! the foe is gathering fast, Hark! his clanging trumpet blast; Who will fight him to the last, As a volunteer? Lo! o'er all the tented field God will be our sun and shield, Alcohol, the foe, shall yield, To the volunteer. NATIONAL ODE. COME SONS OF COLUMBIA. Tune—“Star Spangled Banner.” Come, sons of Columbia, while proudly and high, Every heart with the love of our freedom is swelling, While our star-blazoned bird has his home in the sky, And tyranny's death-song is heard in each dwelling, Come, the bright chalice drain—and again and again, Let our pledge, and our toast, in a far sounding strain, Be water—pure water, bright sparkling with glee, That flows, like our life's blood, unfettered and free. Oh! the wine-cup may sparkle in ruby drops bright, And o'er its glad brim, in gay phalanx advancing, Fair gossamer spirits, in rain-bow-like light, May to Bacchanal music be gracefully dancing: While they dazzle our eyes with the hues of the skies, Soft and silvery tones on the breeze seem to rise, 'Tis the gush of pure water, bright sparkling with glee, That flows, like our life's blood, unfettered and free. Oh! then hail to thee, water—the Bacchanal's toast May be drunk in red wine, that in ruddy light flashes But Columbia's freemen still proudly shall boast, Of the free gift of God, that o'er hill and vale dashes: The di'mond's bright ray seems for ever at play On the full glancing cup—and the soul-breathing lay, Shall be praise of pure water, bright sparkling with glee, The gift of our God—and the drink of the free. A YOUNG TE-TOTALLER'S MORNING HYMN. Tune—“Warwick.” “Claredon.” C. M. Be with me Lord throughout this day, Thy bounty let me share; And give me grace, that now I may, Pour out my soul in prayer. Do thou support my temperance vow, Preserve my soul from sin; And grant me grace to serve thee now, And endless life to win. Do thou assist me when I try The drunkard to reclaim, That so he may, O thou Most High! For ever bless thy name. TAKE THE RUBY WINE AWAY. Tune—“Hotham.” 7s. Bring me forth the cup of gold, Chased by Druid's hands of old, Filled from yonder fountain's breast, Where the waters never rest. This for me! in joyous hour— This for me! in beauty's bower— This for me! in manhood's prime— This for me! in life's decline. Bring me forth the humbler horn, Filled by hunter's hand at morn, From the crystal spring that flows Underneath the blooming rose, Where the violet loves to sip, Where the lily cools her lip: Bring me this, and I will say— Take the ruby wine away! Take away the pois'nous draught, By the Bacchanalian quaffed! Take away the liquid death— Serpents nestle in its breath, Terror rides upon its flood, Vice surrounds its brim of blood, Sorrow in its bosom stings— Sorrow buoyed on pleasure's wings! Dip the bucket in the well, Where the trout delights to dwell— Where the sparkling water sings, As it bubbles from the springs— Where the breezes whisper sweet— Where the happy children meet— Draw! and let the draught be mine— Take away the rosy wine! ENCOURAGE THE REFORMING. Tune—“Alps.”—Bost. Acad. Col. Cheer up—there yet is hope, The care-worn mother cried; I have not watched in vain So often by thy side. Cheer up—let not the past Upon thy spirits prey; The light of better days Is breaking on our way. Cheer up—and let the pledge— Upon its records bear Thy name, among the host Who fly for refuge there. The pledge—the pledge will keep The tempter from thy way, And happiness will dwell Again with us for aye. By all the happy hours That made our early bliss— By all the wretched thoughts That centre into this— Arise, and in thy might, Forswear the wine-cup now; And let these pages bright And Heaven record thy vow. I know thy strength of mind; I know the thoughts that swell Thy heaving bosom now— And feel, that “all is well.” Thank God—the deed is done; The hand of death is stayed; Kindness thy heart hath won; Reason hath lent her aid. SIGN, FOR FREEDOM. Air—“Scots wha hae.” Child, who wouldst not be a sot, Youth, who yet hast tasted not Of the death that 's in the pot, Sign, and you 'll be free. Youths and maidens blithe and gay, Sign the pledge and keep away From the tyrant's awful sway, Sign, and you 'll be free. Drunkards now throughout the land, Join to form a noble band, Join in heart and join in hand, Sign, and you are free. Touch not, taste not, handle not, Is the cure for every sot, May it never be forgot, Till they all are free. Many sots are in the grave, Many lie beneath the wave, Many live to drink and rave, Sign, and you'll be free. Think upon the bloated face, Think of ruin and disgrace, Stand not in the drunkard's place, Sign, and you'll be free. CALL TO PRAISE. Tunes—“Marion.” “Truro.” L. M. Bost. Acad. Coll. Let tempr'ance and her sons rejoice, And be their praises loud and long, Let every heart and every voice Conspire to raise a joyful song. And let the anthem rise to God, Whose fav'ring mercies so abound, And let his praises fly abroad, The spacious universe around. His children's prayer he deigns to grant, He stays the progress of the foe; And Temp'rance, like a cherish'd plant, Beneath his fost'ring care shall grow. THE RELAPSED INEBRIATE'S PRAYER. Tune—“Brattle Street.” C. M. I've struggled hard, yet all in vain, To quench this burning thirst, To calm this wild and madd'ning brain, Lest throbbing, it should burst Its frail confinement, and pour forth Its lava fire of thought, And give the fearful phantoms birth, With which it has been fraught. I've striven o'er and o'er again To keep this demon down, But even yet it holds the rein, The sceptre and the crown. Oh, many hours, while others slept, I've poured the earnest prayer, And burning tears of shame have wept In silence and despair. Yet once again, O God, I swear, Thy holy throne before, I'll try to break the chains I wear, And be myself once more. O Father, then, thy strength impart; Grant me to triumph o'er The wayward passions of this heart, And I will ask no more. HYMN. Air—America. Let the still air rejoice,— Be every youthful voice Blended in one; While we renew our strain, To Him with joy again, Who sends the evening rain, And morning sun. His hand in beauty gives Each flower and plant that lives, Each sunny rill. Springs, which our footsteps meet, Fountains, our lips to greet, Waters, whose taste is sweet, On rock and hill. So let each thoughtful child Drink of this fountain mild, From early youth; Then shall the song we raise, Be heard in future days, Along the pleasant ways Of peace and truth. Now let each heart and hand Of all this youthful band, United, move! Till on the mountain's brow, And in the vale below, Our land shall overflow With peace and love. WINE EXCHANGED FOR GRACE. Tune—“Oh no we never mention her.” Oh take the madd'ning bowl away, Remove the pois'nous cup; My soul is sick—its burning ray Has drunk my spirits up. Take, take it from my loathing lip, Ere madness fire my brain! Take, take it hence, nor let me sip Its liquid death again. Oh dash it on the thirsty earth, For I will drink no more; It cannot cheer the heart with mirth Yhat grief hath wounded sore; For serpents wreathe its sparkling brim, And adders lurk below; It hath no soothing charm for him Who sinks oppress'd with wo. Say not, “Behold its ruddy hue— Oh, press it to thy lips!” For 'tis more deadly than the dew That from the Upas drips; It is more pois'nous than the stream Which deadly nightshade laves; Its joys are transient as the beam That lights its ruddy waves. Say not, “It hath a powerful spell To soothe the soul of Care” Say not, “It calms the bosom's swell And drives away despair!” Art thou its vot'ry? Ask thy soul Thy soul in misery deep— Yes, ask thy conscience, if the bowl Can give refreshing sleep? Then hence! away, thou deadly foe, I scorn thy fell control! Away, away! I fear thy blow, Thou palsy of the soul! Henceforth I drink no more of thee, Thou bane of Adam's race; But to a heavenly fountain flee, And drink the dews of grace. CALL TO INEBRIATES AND THEIR FAMILIES. Tune—“Auld Lang Syne.” Oh! would'st thou find a safe retreat, On earth a peaceful home, Where friends with smiles thy presence greet, And turmoils never come? Then join our Washingtonian band, Help fight our common foe, We'll march together, heart and hand, And Alcohol lay low. Long, long, we worship'd at his shrine, Long felt his cruel reign, Our peace and comfort did resign, For infamy and pain; But now Jehovah is our King, His banner we 've unfurl'd, 'Gainst Alcohol our force we 'll bring, And arrows shall be hurl'd. Wives, mothers, sisters, with us meet; Their grief has pass'd away, Their presence to our hearts is sweet, They cheer us on our way; Then join our Washingtonian band, Help fight our common foe; We 'll march together, heart and hand, And Alcohol lay low. TO THE MODERATE DRINKER. Air—“Green Fields.’ Oh! turn from the wine-glass away, Nor look on the wine when it 's red; For who have such trouble as they, That oft to the bottle are led? Who else have such sorrow and wo, As they who to drinking incline? What evils unceasingly flow From tarrying long at the wine! Oh! turn from the wine-glass away, Nor look at the wine when it 's red; At last, like a serpent at play, It stings, and the poison will spread; The eyes it inflames with desire, The heart with all manner of sin, It setteth the bosom on fire, Consuming the spirit within. Oh! turn from the wine-glass away, Nor look on the wine when it 's red: Though urg'd by the wealthy and gay, Remember the blood it hath shed! Touch not, with the poison, thy lips, If thou would'st be free from its pains; For he is in danger who sips— He only is safe who abstains. REFORMED INEBRIATE'S PRAYER. Tune—“Turin.” 7s. Oft our steps have been astray, Reeling on the drunkard's way, Spreading round us wo and death, Muttering curses with each breath, Robbing wives of daily bread, Making children hate and dread. Wives no more shall spend the night Weeping, trembling, till the light; Starving children vainly plead Never more, for bread they need; Ne'er again shall tempting wine Quench in us the light divine. By the truth that shines around, By the chains that us have bound, By the wine-cup's madd'ning flow, By the wails of heart-wrung wo, Pledge we here, as sober men, Never will we drink again. God of mercy! be thou near, While these vows are spoken here; Shield the victor! guard and guide, Where the lurking tempters hide; Man can strive, but Thou alone Must the final conquest crown. CALL TO PARENTS, CHILDREN, PATRIOTS, &amp;c. Tune—“Days of Absence.” Parent! who with speechless feeling, O'er thy cradled treasure bent, Every year new charms revealing, Yet thy wealth of love unspent— Hast thou seen that blossom blighted By a drear, untimely frost? All thy labor unrequited— Every glorious promise lost? Wife!—with agony unspoken, Shrinking from affliction's rod; Is thy prop, thine idol broken, Fondly trusted—next to God? Husband! o'er thy hope a mourner, Of thy chosen friend ashamed, Hast thou to her burial borne her, Unrepentant—unreclaimed? Child! in tender weakness turning To thy Heaven-appointed guide, Doth a lava-poison burning Turn to gall affection's tide? Still that orphan-burden bearing, Darker than the grave can show, Dost thou bow thee down despairing, To a heritage of wo? Country!—on thy sons depending, Strong in manhood, bright in bloom; Hast thou seen thy pride descending, Shrouded, to th' unhonored tomb? Rise!—on eagle pinions soaring, Rise!—like one of godlike birth; Rise!—with eloquence out-pouring; Sweep the spoiler from the earth! STRIVE TO RECLAIM ALL. Hast thou a brother unreclaimed— A sister yet in sin, Who, though they listen to the truth, Feel not its power within! O pray for them!—pray day and night, That they may yet discern aright. Thou answerest:—“All my father's house Are servants of the Lord, They bless the Father for His Son, And reverence the word.” Are ALL thy Father's house, O youth! Humble adorers of the truth? Nay, nay, I tell thee they are not. “O yes, they are.” What, all? Whom dost thou, then, thy brethren term, And whom thy Father call? God is the sire of ALL MEN named;— Say, are thy brethren ALL reclaimed? WOMAN'S PART IN THE TEMPERANCE REFORMATION. Tune—“Pelham.” S. M. Say not, that woman's voice Must stay its silver note, While the far hills and vales rejoice, And on each breeze, doth float Glad-tidings, from the field, Where Temperance armies stand, Against king Alcohol, to wield The sword, with fearless hand! Let woman too, rejoice, To see the foe recede; And let her in the “still small voice,” The cause of Temperance plead: And while the thunder-tone Of eloquence is stirred; Her whispered warning God may own— His voice through her's be heard. Say not, that woman's heart Its fulness must contain; Nor from Compassion's fount, impart To other hearts again: For since her sex hath shared The evils of the foe; Let not her sympathy be spared, Where yet is felt his blow. Say not, that woman's hand For Temperance hath no power— That she, must a spectator stand, In Reformation's hour; Behold, in garments made, What woman now hath wrought! How is th' inebriate's home arrayed In comforts she hath brought! See how the gentle band Of sisters, onward move— How in one cause, have heart and hand, United works with love! Let woman lend her powers To aid us as she can; And be, as erst in Eden's bowers, A helper meet for man. COLD WATER. How sparkles the dew on the grass and flowers In rays of the early dawn! And how refreshing are summer showers To fields and meadows and drooping bowers! And how reviving their secret powers To garden and parching lawn! The earth drinks enough of the cooling rains, And quenches her burning thirst; The sea a portion by rills obtains, A part by vapor the cloud regains; And some sinks downward thro' earth's small veins In springs from her heart to burst. To spring, or to pump, or to well we 'll hie, Obedient to nature's laws; And this to others shall be our cry, O drink cold water whene'er you 're dry, And health and pleasure you 'll gain thereby, And honor a holy cause! THE TEMPERANCE PROCESSION. Air—“I see them on their Winding Way.” 8s. M. I see them on their Temp'rance way— About their ranks bright glories play; Their joyful looks and bearing high, Blend with the notes of victory. Their waving flags and banners bright, Are glancing in the heavenly light; The darkness of intemp'rance past, That brighter light is on them cast; While louder, louder, louder still, Their song peals forth a Freeman's will. Again, again, with cheerful hum, And waving flag, they come! they come! Their wives and children standing by, Send forth the shout of victory; And nearer, nearer, yet more near, Their Temp'rance chorus greets the ear. Brave Washingtonians are they— Go, meet them on their joyous way; With pledge and banner, there they come, Oh give them here a welcome home! DEPLORING THE REIGN OF INTEMPERANCE. Tune—“Litchfield.” “Lanesboro'.” C. M. Intemp'rance, like a raging flood, Is sweeping o'er the land; Its dire effects, in tears and blood, Are traced on every hand. It still flows on, and bears away Ten thousands to their doom: Who shall the mighty torrent stay, And disappoint the tomb? Almighty God! no hand but thine Can check this flowing tide; Stretch out thine arm of power divine, And bid the flood subside. Dry up the source from whence it flows, Destroy its fountain head; That dire Intemp'rance and its woes No more the earth o'erspread. THE DISENTHRALLED. He had bowed down to drunkenness, An abject worshiper; The pride of manhood's pulse had grown Too faint and cold to stir; And he had given his spirits up, Of appetite the thrall, And bowing to the poison cup, He gloried in the fall! There came a change—the cloud rolled off, And light fell on his brain— And like the passing of a dream That cometh not again, The shadow of the spirit fled, He saw the gulf before, He shuddered at the waste behind— And was a man once more. He shook the serpent folds away That gathered round his heart, As shakes the swaying forest oak Its poison vine apart; He stood erect—returning pride Grew terrible within, And conscience sat in judgment on His most familiar sin. The light of Intellect again Along his pathway shone— And Reason, like a monarch sat Upon his golden throne. The honored and the wise once more Within his presence came And lingered oft on lovely lips, His once forbidden name. There may be glory in the might That treadeth nations down Wreaths for the crimson Conqueror Pride for Kingly crown, But nobler is that triumph hour The disenthralled shall find, While evil passion boweth down Unto the Godlike mind. THE TEMPERANCE BALL. A New Song to an Old Tune. Come, all ye true friends of the nation, Attend to Humanity's call; Come, aid in your country's salvation, And roll on the Temperance Ball— And roll on the Temperance Ball And roll on the Temperance Ball Come, aid in your country's salvation, And roll on the Temperance Ball! And, when we have formed the blest union, We'll firmly march on, one and all; We'll shout, when we meet in communion, And roll on the Temperance Ball— And roll on the Temperance Ball, &amp;c. The Cold Water Army 's advancing, The cohorts of Rum to destroy; The glad eye of Beauty is dancing; Her heart 's overflowing with joy— Her heart 's overflowing with joy, &amp;c. The wife on her infant is gazing, But not now in sorrow alone; A husband her virtue is praising— The dark cloud of sorrow is gone— The dark cloud of sorrow is gone, &amp;c. The maiden, now truly delighted, Her heart beating wildly with joy, Confides in the vow that is plighted Her youth is a “Washington Boy” Her youth is a Washington boy, &amp;c. The drunkard our Pledge is now keeping, No more reeling boldly about; The old broken bottle is weeping The last drop of misery out— The last drop of misery out, &amp;c. How can you stand halting, while Beauty Is sweetly appealing to all, To come to the standard of duty, And roll on the Temperance Ball? And roll on the Temperance Ball, And roll on the Temperance Ball; To come to the standard of duty, And roll on the Temperance Ball. THANKSGIVING FOR PROGRESS. Tune—“Westboro'.” (8s. &amp; 7s.) Hark! o'er hill and dale is swelling, One rejoicing general song, Triumph of fair Temp'rance telling, On the breeze 't is borne along; Happy wives and joyous children, Still the cheerful strain prolong. We would lend our feeble voices, On Columbia's favor'd shore; For our ev'ry heart rejoices, And our tongues shall not give o'er; What, though few and weak our number, If it make our efforts more! Over ev'ry land and nation, Has her banner wide been flung! Men of ev'ry clime and station, Have the praise of Temp'rance sung: All have felt her happy influence, Poor and wealthy—old and young. Friends of Temp'rance! be not sleeping, Swiftly tread your glorious way! Famished children—mothers weeping, Call on you to haste the day, When o'er all the wide creation, Temp'rance shall her sceptre sway. Lord, to Thee the praise we render, For the good that has been done; Thou hast made the conscience tender; Thou hast softened hearts of stone! Still assist us in our labor, For we trust in Thee alone. THE COLD WATER ARMY. Air—“Hark, the soft Bugle.” Hark, hark, the sweet music that sounds o'er the land, And thrills in the ears of us all; As loud, and more loud does each cold water band Respond to the Temperance call; While thousands spring up from each valley and hill, And seizing the spirited strain, Send back the glad challenge with hearty good will, From hill-top to valley again. And thus may the sounds of the cold water song Be round us, while lasts the glad day; And night in its stillness, the echo prolong, As time with us all wears away! While hope with her warm light, each beaming eye fills, Evermore may that soul-stirring strain Ring out as an earnest of joy, till it thrills, And echoes to heaven again. WARNING AND CALL TO TAKE THE PLEDGE. Tune—“Jordan.” C. M. Stay, stay thy hand, lift not the cup Of rosy, glittering wine; Though clear its depths, there lurks beneath A curse for thee and thine. Thou say'st it gives a merry heart, And drives away dull care; It brings, what else thou wouldst not know, Unmixed with dark despair. Thou say'st it has a power to drown Thoughts of life's sternest ill, To bring forgetfulness of woes, And conscience' voice to still; Believe it not—oh! never seek Oblivion in the bowl— A draught will only deeper fix The agony of soul. Thou say'st it stirs the sluggish blood, And bids it quicker flow! Thou say'st 't is pleasant on the lip, And bright its ruby glow. Hast thou not seen the flashing light That from the wine-cup came, Lead on the tempted, trusting one, To misery and shame? Then taste not, touch not—dare ye thus Your glorious birthright stain? Would ye—descendants of the free, Clank the inebriate's chain? No! by the memory of the brave Who sleep beneath the sod— Shake off the curse—and give your pledge To virtue and to God. THE TEMPERANCE FIREMAN. When in the night The skies grow bright, With the flames of the poor man's dwelling, The Fireman springs, As the Hall Bell rings, The burning district telling, Hark! the cry, Fire! Fire! As the flames rise higher, The gallant Firemen fly, At the sleep-dispelling cry, Fire! Fire! Fire! Fire! And we 'll dash the water on till the flames expire. See,—the last gleam Of the burning beam Dies, and the danger is over; The Fireman goes To his sweet repose, From his toil and fatigue to recover, Till the cry, Fire! Fire! Shall again require The Fireman to fly At the sleep-dispelling cry! Fire! Fire! Fire! Fire! And we'll dash the water on till the flames expire. Thus in the height Of his drunken plight, If the tippler falls in the gutter, The Fireman kind, Who the Pledge has sign'd, Plies him with good Cold Water; He puts out Rum's fire, Drags him out of the mire, Nor leaves him there to die 'Neath the cold and stormy sky— On Rum's dread fire, He pours Cold Water down till the flames expire. REMEMBRANCE. Air—“Oft in the stilly night.” When I remember now The chains that I have broken, I would renew my vow, And take afresh my token; I feel like one, Whose pledge begun, Shall never be forsaken; With heart and hand At God's command, The Temperance vow I've taken. When I remember all My old companions jolly; I feel no more a thrall, In bonds of guilt and folly; No more, at night, To swear and fight, Am I the slave of drinking; But free once more, From chains so sore, I shall keep free, I'm thinking. “ONE GLASS MORE.” Tune:—“Brattle Street.” Stay, mortal, stay! nor heedless thus Thy sure destruction seal; Within that cup there lurks a curse, Which all who drink shall feel, Disease and death forever nigh, Stand ready at the door, And eager wait to hear the cry, Oh! give me “one glass more.” Go, view that prison's gloomy cells— Its pallid tenants scan; Go, gaze upon these earthly hells, And ask whence they began: Had these a tongue—O, man! thy cheek Would burn with crimson o'er, Had these a tongue to thee they'd speak, Oh, take not “one glass more.” Stay, mortal, stay! repent, return! Reflect upon thy fate; The poisonous draught indignant spurn, Oh, spurn it ere too late; Oh, fly the bar-room's horrid din, Nor linger at the door, Lest thou perchance shouldst enter in, And die of “one glass more.” THE WINE CUP'S BRIM. Tune—“Bonny Boat. We've heard that round the wine-cup's brim A thousand pleasures stray, And that strong drinks have wondrous power To drive dull care away; But we have seen the flashing light, Which from the goblet came, Lead, like the meteor, on to tears, And wretchedness and shame. We've heard that though 't is well enough For men the pledge to sign, Yet youth need never be in haste Their freedom to resign; But we are sure, ill habits formed In youth, destroy the man; And we will now avoid the snare, Thus woven, if we can. The children in Chaldea's court, Who would not drink the wine, Not only fair in flesh were seen, But wisdom had, divine. Like them, we choose the generous draught, God's cool, sweet springs supply; And at the last, those streams, of which Who drink, shall never die. SPARKLING AND BRIGHT. Sparkling and bright, in liquid light, Pure streams at our feet are beaming, With crystals fair as the evening star, That shines o'er our heads while dreaming. Chorus.—Then quaff from the brook, in the craggy nook, Where joy and health are meeting; Nor drown the soul in Bacchus' bowl, There 's death in the hue so cheating! We find on test, it can't arrest, Nor of old Time be master; Tho' it craze awhile with its madd'ning guile, It makes but the sands run faster. Chorus.—Then quaff from the brook, &amp;c. Though nature's drink can't sorrow sink, Nor hold our joys departing, It clears from pain the weary brain, Nor leaves behind a smarting. Chorus.—Then quaff from the brook, &amp;c. TEMPERANCE CALL. Air—“America.” Come ye who love our cause, Whose hearts for freedom's laws, With rapture glow. Come join our noble band, Be with us heart and hand, To save our happy land From sin and wo. Come ye who quaff the bowl, Death's billows near you roll, Come ere you're lost. Burst from the tyrant's reign Break now the tempter's chain, Be freemen once again. Join with our host. Come ye, who drink but wine, Round you it soon will twine Its fetters strong: Leave now the tempting cup, Touch not a single drop, Leave while there yet is hope, Join in our song. Come young and old,—come all, Come fight at freedom's call, For liberty. Loud let our songs arise, Till heaven, with glad surprise, Join in our joyous cries, Till all are free. THE CLARION. Air—“The Chariot.” The clarion—the clarion of freedom now sounds; Prom the east to the west Independence resounds; From the hills and the streams, and the far distant skies, Let the shout, “Independence from Alcohol,” rise. The army—the army have taken the field; The hosts of Cold Water, no never, will yield; From fountains refreshed, animation now glows, With ardor immortal they rush on their foes. The armor—the armor that girds ev'ry breast, Is the hope of deliv'rance for thousands oppress'd; With words of persuasion, we call on the throng, Desert the black banner, and join in our song. The banners—the banners of freedom now wave, Lo! the eagle now covers the ranks of the brave; With the shout, Independence, creation shall ring, From the cruel taxation of Alcohol King. The conflict—the conflict will shortly be o'er, And the demon Intemperance triumph no more Over tears, over sighs, over premature graves, See, the flag of our freedom eternally waves. The empire—the empire of freedom divine, Like the blue vault above us forever shall shine; Then as wide as creation her blessings shall roll, And a star of new glory illumine each pole. The laurel—the laurel unfading shall wave On the brows that have rescued their friends from the grave; And the thanks of a nation forever be given To the heroes immortal; co-workers with heaven. THE TEMPERANCE LIFE BOAT. Tune—“The Soldier's Tear.” The storm is on the deep, The lightning hovers o'er. The seaman on the stricken mast, And and the leeward breaker's roar; A cry of hope is heard The life-boat is at hand. And again upon the steadfast shore The rescued sailors stand. We see the raging tide Of double death—and send Our life boat, in the simple pledge, Which is the drunkard's friend To heaven we lift a prayer, And ply our watchful oar, To convey him where his Saviour's praise May greet him on the shore. AWAKE! AWAKE! Awake! awake! awake! Let none be laggards here; Life—liberty 's at stake! And all we hold most dear. 'Tis not a party feud, The cause that we embrace; The foe to be subdued Is the foe of all our race. Chorus—Then raise the standard high! Around it gather all, And be our battle cry, Freedom from Alcohol! More fraught with wo and death, Than war's unsparing brand, Or the pestilence whose breath Sweeps the fairest from the land; It strikes its victims low, In their glory and their prime, Or leads through courses slow, Of misery and crime. Then raise, &amp;c. My father's heart hath been By its influence turned to stone, And the husband we have seen, To a brutal monster grown. We have seen the good and great By its blighting touch defiled, And the home made desolate, Where erst, contentment smiled. Then raise, &amp;c. We have heard the widow's sigh, And the orphan's piteous moan, For the victims doomed to die, By this demon overthrown. We have seen the aged sire Sink in sorrow to the grave, As the last hope would expire For the son he could not save. Then raise, &amp;c. Thousands have rent the chain Who were once the tyrant's slaves, But thousands still remain, Who may sink to drunkards' graves Relax not then your powers, While a brother wears the yoke, Nor think the day is ours 'Till ev'ry chain is broke. But raise the standard high! Around it gather all! Loud shout the battle cry, Freedom from Alcohol! THE TEMPERANCE REVOLUTION. Air:—“Missionary Hymn.” From Plymouth's rock of story, From Yorktown's field of blood, Through many a woodland hoary, O'er many a rolling flood; On old plains scarred with battle, By old shrines rich with prayer, The sounds of conflict rattle— And yet no sword is there. But, like a clarion, loudly O'er storied hill and glen, This CALL is bursting proudly From the deep hearts of men— “Up, up, from prostitution To sin and misery!” The Temperance revolution Is setting thousands free. And on their crests they've taken The name of Washington, And forward, to awaken, Their call of Love hath gone; Its glad, fraternal meaning The poor inebriate hears, And woman follows, gleaning New hopes, with glistening tears. So, host with host assembling, The victory shall win: Lo! on his throne sits trembling, That old and giant Sin. Like foam by strong winds scattered His banded strength hath gone, His charmed cup lies shattered— And still the cry is “On!” Our Father's God! Our Keeper Be Thou—our Strength Divine! Thou sendest forth the reaper, The harvest is all Thine. Roll on, roll on this gladness, Till, driv'n from every shore, The drunkard's sin and madness Shall smite the earth no more. OUR VILLAGE FEAST OF SHELLS. Tune:—“Auld Lang Syne.” Let others sing the rosy god Beneath the purple vine, And bow them to the tyrant's nod, And pour the sparkling wine: Another theme the Muse for me Has chosen from her wells— 'T is this—beneath the green-wood tree To sing the “Feast of Shells.” When Ossian struck his lyre among The Caledonian hills, And charm'd the echoes as they sung Beside the mountain rills, He tuned his harp they say of old— His fame the story tells— And sung in strains both soft and bold The ancient “Feast of Shells.” Here Ossian's “ghosts” and “streams of fire” No soul with fear regards, And though we have not Ossian's “lyre,” We have “the song of bards.” No “spirit” comes to frighten us, Nor Folly with her bells, Of Reason's crown shall lighten us— She rules our “Feast of Shells.” And as we sing the groves shall ring So merrily this day, For none but happy hearts we bring Beneath the green-wood gay; The old and young together join, For here a spirit dwells That brightens with its smiles divine Our Village “Feast of Shells.” FROM ALL THAT CAN INTOXICATE. “From all that can Intoxicate!” The princely pledge that saves From million crimes that, ready, wait, From grief and early graves;— From ruin, and the certain grasp, That 's pitiless, of law; And from the sorer doom that 's ripe, When Heaven its sword doth draw. “From all that can Intoxicate!” This panacea will Such out the poison from thy heart, Its fevered throbbings still, And dry the hot and bitter tear, And melt away the frost, That hung about thy soul, when thou Didst deem thyself the lost! “From all that can Intoxicate! Give pledge, and thou art kept From woes that on the drunkard wait, From seas that he has wept; From that which binds continually His mind, as with a spell; And bars out hope, and locks on him The triple door of hell! “From all that can Intoxicate!” Omnipotent its strength To overcome the tyrant foe, And bid us live at length! Oh, set its characters on high; And to the world be given, Blazed on the everlasting sky— The Pledge that leads to Heaven! NEW YEAR'S HYMN. Tune—“Ellenthorpe.” L. M. Hail New-born Year—yes—new indeed To thousands lately sunk in wo; With joy we greet thee—while we plead With God to help us onward too. 'Tis by His grace we rescued, stand, Saved froma drunkard's awful grave; He spake the word—by His command We rise—whose arm is strong to save. Back on the finished year we look, With tears of joy and gratitude; When with a trembling hand we took The Pledge—the pledge of future good. O sacred pledge! how safe! how sure! To let the drunkard's cup alone: God give us courage to endure, And grace for former sins t' atone. Come—ye who sell the deadly bane; Come—see the peace, the joy we find; Come—see our families again, With social happiness entwined. Then go—give up your dangerous trade, And never, never sell again That which on Earth a Hell hath made, And brought all evils in its train. CHRISTIANS URGED TO PROMOTE THE TEMPERANCE CAUSE. Tunes—“Cesarea,” “Sicilian Hymn.” 8s. &amp; 7s. Christian, rise and pray for Zion; Lo! the tempter seeks his prey; Active as the roaring lion, Slumbering neither night nor day. Christian, rise—thy hours are flying; O, arouse thyself and save These thy brothers, round thee dying, From the drunkard's hopeless grave. MAN OF TOIL. Man of Toil, wouldst thou be free, Lend thine ear to Reason's call; There's folly in the Drunkard's glee— There's madness in the midnight brawl: The ribald jest, the vulgar song, May give a keener sting to care; The riot of a reckless throng May lead to ruin and despair: Let truth unloose thy fettered soul— There is no freedom in the bowl. Man of Toil, wouldst thou be wise, The paths of moral light explore; Pierce the human heart's disguise, And trace its motives to the core; Creation's boundless beauties scan, Observe its wonders—search its laws; Look on the vast harmonious plan, And learn to love the Eternal Cause: Let Truth illume thy darkened soul— There is no wisdom in the bowl. Man of Toil, wouldst thou be blest, Give thy purest feelings play; Bring all that 's noble to thy breast, Let all that 's worthless pass away. Let generous deeds bid sorrow cease, Let gentlest words thy lips employ: Scatter the seeds of love and peace, And reap a harvest, full of joy: Let Truth make glad thy harrassed soul— There are no blessings in the bowl. INVITATION TO FEMALES. Tune—Thou Shepherd of Israel. Ye mothers, ye sisters, arise! Your country now calls for your aid, And points to a glorious prize, With laurels that never can fade. The standard's uplifted on high, The banner of temp'rance unfurl'd, Come forward—come forward! they cry, To rescue a perishing world. Your armour is kindness to all; Your weapons are pointed with love; Before you intemp'rance must fall; Such weapons successful will prove. Your brethren have open'd the way; The siege has already begun; Come, fair ones, your valour display, The victory then will be won. Hell's palaces then must all close, And vanish the darkness and gloom, Our country enjoy sweet repose, And Eden around us will bloom: Intemp'rance with all its foul train, Shall sink to the lowest abyss: Joy, peace, and sweet harmony reign, Content and perpetual bliss. “AM I MY BROTHER'S KEEPER.” Tune—Litchfield. Warwick. C. M. “Am I my brother's keeper?” Yes! Bound by the social ties, Which link us to our fellow-man, Can we his soul despise? His sympathies 't is ours to share, His weal our heart's desire, Our aim a brother's happiness, Should all our thoughts inspire. Yes, on each brother's influences A brother's welfare hangs, God at our hands his blood will ask! Shall we not save his pangs? Then turn, O, turn a brother's feet, From death's destructive snare; O, lead him to his heavenly rest, God's smile will greet you there. ALL 'S WELL. Tune—“All 's Well.” Deserted by my dearest friends, Strong drink despair and sorrow sends; O'er children, wife, and lowly cot, There hangs a sad and threatening lot. Hark, hark, some footsteps hither stray, But joys can't soothe the drunkard's day. “Is there hope?—stranger, quickly tell! “Abstain—repent—believe—all 's well.” Now listed in the temp'rance band, With drunken sots on every hand, Our watchful guard explores the lanes, To snatch the slave from Satan's chains, And oft he hears the cheering voice, From homes reform'd where all rejoice. “What cheer?—neighbors, quickly tell, “All pledged, reformed, redeemed, all 's well.” AYE, DRINK A LITTLE LONGER! UNE—Missionary Hymn. Ay! drink a little longer! A little longer still; Let appetite grow stronger; Ay, gratify thy will; Indulge in every pleasure, That fancy can devise, Spend all thy earthly treasure, Lose all thy heart can prize. Drink now—to-night—to-morrow! Thy tender wife fersake!— Yes, fill her heart with sorrow, And thy smiling children'n break! Ne'er think of grief or sadness, Nor think of God or heaven; Till seized with perfect madness, Thou to despair art driven! Then, drunkard, die!—but glory Can never be thy home: And what will be thy story, When laid within the tomb? O tell it not—O let him Sleep now his last long sleep; Wife—sire—and child—forget him— 'T is folly now to weep. LICENSE LAWS. Tunes—Rithmah. Newcourt. Bost. Acad. Coll. “For so much gold, we license thee,” So say our laws—“a draught to sell, That bows the strong, enslaves the free, And opens wide the gate of hell: For public good requires that some Should live, since many die by rum.” Ye civil fathers! while the foes Of this destroyer seize their swords, And heaven's own hail is in the blows They're dealing—will YE cut the cords That round the falling fiend they draw, And o'er him hold your shield of law? And will ye give to man a bill, Divorcing him from heaven's high sway? And while God says, “thou shalt not kill”— Say ye, “for gold, ye may—ye may?” Compare the body with the soul! Compare the bullet with the bowl! In which is felt the fiercer blast Of the destroying angel's breath? Which binds its victim the more fast? Which kills him with the deadlier death? Will ye the felon fox restrain, And yet take off the tiger's chain? Are ye not fathers? When your sons Look to you for their daily bread, Dare ye, in mockery, load with stones The table that for them ye spread? How can ye hope your sons will live, If ye, for fish, a serpent give? O! Holy God! let light divine Break forth more broadly from above, Till we conform our laws to thine— The perfect law of truth and love: For truth and love alone can save Thy children from a hopeless grave. PRAYER FOR THE INTEMPERATE. Tunes—Newburg. Bethesda. H. M. Father of Mercies hear, And to our call attend, In our behalf appear And thine assistance lend. The drunkard's end hold up to view, Convince and make his heart anew. O! that thou wouldst ride on, Till sin's strong hold gives way, Till drunkards one by one, Shall hail the happy day; And all, with one harmonious voice, In true sobriety rejoice. That, sav'd from miseries Which from intemperance flow, Each family may rise, And many a comfort know; And all, the King of Kings revere, And daily bow their knees in prayer. Husbands and wives in love Their rising offspring train, In ways of truth—and prove, That abstinence is gain. Blest here on earth—redeem'd, forgiven, And crown'd at last with Christ in heaven. THE DECEITFULNESS OF STRONG DRINK. Tune—Woodstock. C. M. Drink has a thousand treach'rous arts To practice on the mind; With flattering looks it tempts our hearts, But leaves a sting behind. With boasted virtues it deceives The aged and the young; And while the heedless wretch believes, It makes his fetters strong. It pleads for all the joys it brings, And gives a fair pretence; But cheats the soul of heavenly things, And chains it down to sense. Thanks be to God! we now perceive The tempter's fatal snare; We will not drink, we will not give, But bid mankind beware. TEMPERANCE HOTEL. Tunes—Nuremburg. Wilson. 7s. Bost. Acad. Coll. Friends of temperance, who require Rest, refreshment, food, or fire, Or an hour may wish to spend O'er the news, or with a friend— Hither come, and draw a chair, While you read our bill of fare: Breakfast, dinner, tea and supper, In the lower rooms or upper. Cocoa, coffee, bread and toast, Good as any house can boast; Eggs and ham, if you can stop, Beef and mutton, steak or chop. Bun and biscuit if you please, Sandwich, omelet, milk and cheese; Added to this wholesome cheer, Lemonade and water clear. Food and fluids, these, we think, Sober men may eat and drink, And as such of course we rank you, Try us, pay us, and we 'll thank you. THE GOOD GIFTS OF GOD PERVERTED. Tune—Bethesda. H. M. God gave the gift to man; But man with fatal skill, Insensate form'd the plan To change the good for ill: The poison, tortur'd from the cane, Like Sampson hath its thousands slain. God gave the golden grain To hungry man for food; But querulous and vain, He spurn'd the proffer'd good: And Egypt's slothful sons, athirst, Drew forth the maddening beverage first. God gave the clustering vine: Ingenious man perverse, Exchang'd the boon for wine, And wrought Canaan's curse. The patriarch, who had safely past The deluge, was o'erwhelmed at last. To earth the cup be hurled, That holds an adder's sting; And let us pledge the world With nectar from the spring; That hence, like Rechab's ancient line, Though prophets urge, we drink no wine. TEMPERANCE WATCHWORD. Tunes—Broomfield. Bellville. Bost. [illeg.]ad. Coll. Hark, now we answer, see we come, We come at freedom's holy call: We come, we come, we come, we come, To do the glorious work of all: And hark! we raise from sea to sea, The temp'rance watch-word, Liberty. God is our guide, from field and wave, From plough, from anvil and from loom, We come, our countrymen to save, And speak a heartless tyrant's doom; And hark! &amp;c. We see the curse invade our land; We hear the sufferers call for aid; We come to lend a helping hand, And break the bonds strong drink has made. And hark, &amp;c. We draw not the devouring sword, Nor war's destructive fires we light, By reason and the living word Of God, we put our foes to flight. And hark, &amp;c. We bring rich blessings in our train, And spread them with a liberal hand; We wipe away the guilty stain Of drunkenness from off our land. And hark, &amp;c. We come the cottage to repair, And give back comforts banish'd long, To spread the board with ample fare, And tune afresh the cheerful song. And hark, &amp;c. We bid the dying drunkard live, To his parched lips the cup we bring, We burst his fetters, and we give Him rest beside our crystal spring. And hark, &amp;c. We come with tidings from above, Good will and peace to men on earth; We come to tell a Saviour's love, And fill the soul with heavenly mirth; We raise the watchword liberty, And call on all men to be free. THE TEMPERANCE STANDARD ERECTED. Tunes—Zion. Oliphant. 8s. 7s. &amp; 4s. Long misguided have we wandered In a dark and dreary maze; Now we rally round thy standard, Now we feel thy quick'ning rays. O, thou temperance, Guide our steps in virtue's ways. Drunkard, long forlorn and blighted, Keenly hast thou felt the sting; Join our cause; if once united, Blessings in thy path will spring. Join our standard. From thy soul the bondage fling. Freemen, have ye manly feeling? Will ye bear so foul a stain; At the tyrant's footstool kneeling, Will you hug his galling chain? Break it! break it! Break the shameful bond in twain. Now your downward course, forsaking, Shun the path that leads to wo; From your death-like slumber waking, If with zeal your bosoms glow— Rise, and virtue Round your names a light shall throw. Though the tyrant holds a station, Though he smile with aspect fair, Touch ye not his foul temptation, Shun the first, the fatal snare; Nobly fighting, Drive the demon from his lair. THE TEMPERANCE STAR. TUNE—Watchman tell us of the night. Long and gloomy was the night Hanging on our mental sight, While intemp'rance, dark and drear, Filled the lowering atmosphere. But behold a star arise, Brilliant in these western skies, Coming like redeeming power, In the last despairing hour. Onward speed thy radiant way, Harbinger of dawning day! Let the nations from afar— Hail New England's morning star. Sun of righteousness appear, Fill the moral hemisphere— On the scattering shades of night Pour a flood of heavenly light. THE CONTRAST. Says James to John, “come, now come on, And take a cheerful glass; If I were you, I'd bid adieu To all the temperate class. Their narrow mind with chains would bind, If they could rule the land, And men born free, must bow the knee, And yield to their command. They have no heart, to take a part, In all that makes life dear; The social glass, they never pass, And what's true joy, they fear.” “Oh, James,” says John, “too oft I've gone Your merry, merry round; The sparkling bowl, that lured my soul, I've dashed upon the ground. Your cheerful glass I now can pass, And shun its fatal power— For well I know there's nought below That can such evils shower. Could you but feel, the peace and weal, Which temperance imparts, You would desire the liquid fire To cease from burning hearts. Come, James, give up that firy cup, The source of all your pain, Then shall you see true liberty, And be a man again. THE REFORMED DRUNKARDS' PRAYER. Tune—Aithlone. C. P. M. O Lord of heaven, and earth, and sky, To the we look, to thee we cry, O hear our artless prayer; In thee we live, in thee we move: Make us the “children of thy love,” The objects of thy care. Once did we love the drunkard's drink, And quite beneath the brute did sink, Debased by sin and shame; Now changed our state, now temp'rate grown, Thy love we feel, thy care we own, And praise thy holy name. Oh, may we all, when life is o'er, Meet on that blissful stormless shore, To want, to pain unknown— Each robed in white, a noble throng, Together sing salvation's song, And wear a golden crown! DIFFUSION OF TEMPERANCE LIGHT. Calcutta. On the sons of dissipation, Who their mental powers debase; On the scenes of degradation, That our native land disgrace, Star of temperance, Now diffuse thy cheering rays. O'er the customs of our nation, That have thousands led astray; O'er the mist of moderation, More delusive still than they, Star of temperance, Shine with lustre bright as day. Where the bottle is presented, Where the social glass allures, Where the guest is complimented, Who the deepest draught endures, Star of temperance, Beam with all thy radiant powers. Though the wicked are reviling, Though the worldly scoff and sneer; While the Lord of Hosts is smiling, Still pursue thy bright career, Star of temperance, And throughout our land appear. THE BETTER WAY. Tune—Oh no we never mention her. In ancient days the young were wont, With rosy garlands crown'd, To sing their bacchanalian songs, The festive board around; While wine inflamed their fathers' hearts, And roused their senseless mirth, And left them viler than the brutes, That crawl upon the earth. But we have found a better way To give our parents joy; We spurn the wine-cup from our lips— It charms but to destroy. What though it seem so clear and bright, So fair and sweet a thing; It hath at last the serpent's bite, The deadly adder's sting. It turns the ruddy bloom of youth To blight and foul decay; And, what is worse, it takes the glow Of innocence away. O, give us but the crystal springs, The air and sunlight free, With love and truth—and who will then Be happier than we?</field>
   </doc>
</add>