<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Longfellow, Samuel, 1819-1892</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Longfellow, Samuel, 1819-1892</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">longfellow samuel 1819 1892</field>
      <field name="author_text">Longfellow, Samuel, 1819-1892</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1880's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ap/uvaGenText/tei/chap_AM0695.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240350</field>
      <field name="date_text">1887</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:440139</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Greek, Modern (1453- )</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">A few verses of many years</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">A few verses of many years</field>
      <field name="title_facet">few verses of many years</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">few verses of many years</field>
      <field name="title_text">A few verses of many years</field>
      <field name="year_display">1887</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1887</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1887</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440139&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440139&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Longfellow, Samuel, 1819-1892&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;longfellow samuel 1819 1892&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;A few verses of many years&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;few verses of many years&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1887&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1887&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Longfellow, Samuel&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1819&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1892&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;A few verses of many years&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Privately printed&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1887&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3865729-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;cham0695&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;gre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;A few verses of many years&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1996&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1996 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 21 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted ; verse reproduced elsewhere in American</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Poetry omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-AmPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TO THE FRIENDS FOR WHOM IT HAS BEEN PRINTED I OFFER THIS LITTLE BOOK, NOT FOR ITS OWN WORTH BUT FOR FRIENDSHIP'S SAKE. Cambridge, Christmas, 1887. TO A FRIEND WITH SOME VERSES. By cliff and stream and mountain pass Together we have wandered And looked on Nature's beauteous face And her high mysteries pondered; And still some bud or leaf or spray Or red wild-rose we'd gather In memory of the charming scene, Or day of lovely weather. So, on life's path from time to time Some fair experience staying, I 've thrown the feeling into rhyme To keep it undecaying. And now for you within these leaves I these wild-roses pressing Hope that some fragrance you may find, Some sweet perennial blessing. THE HOMESTEAD. Home of my fathers! once again I stand beneath the shade Of those ancestral trees where once A dreamy child I played. Those ancient elms still o'er thy roof Their sheltering branches spread; But they who loved their pleasant shade In heavenly places tread. No longer at the window now Their friendly glance I catch, No longer hear, as I approach, The sound of lifted latch; The ready hand which once threw wide The hospitable door— I know its warm and hearty grasp Shall answer mine no more. The red rose by the window still Blooms brightly as of old; The woodbines still around the door Their shining leaves unfold; The pale syringa scents the air Through the long summer hours; But ah! the old beloved hands No longer pluck their flowers. I wander where the little brook Still keeps its tranquil flow. Where blooms the crimson cardinal, And golden lilies glow; Or, crossing o'er the wooden bridge, I loiter on my way To watch where in the sunny depths The darting minnows play. That little bridge, the vine-clad elms That guarded either end,— Oh, with that spot how many dreams, How many memories, blend! When summer suns at morning kissed The dew from grass and flower, I 've wandered there; and lingered long At evening's holy hour. Still as each spring returns those trees Put on their garments green; And still in summer hues arrayed Those blooming flowers are seen; And when the autumn winds come down To wrestle with the wood, The gold and crimson leaves are shed To float along the flood. Thus seasons pass, and year on year Follows with ceaseless pace; Though all things human change or die, Unchanged is Nature's face. Yet, when these well-remembered scenes Before my vision glide, I feel that they who made them fair No more are by my side. And one there was—now distant far— Who shared my childish plays, With whom I roamed in deeper joy In boyhood's thoughtful days. Dear cousin, round thine early home When truant memory Lingers in dreams of fond regret, Dost thou e'er think of me? Gorham, 1839. EVENING LAMPS. The trees stand dim along the bank, In the sky float purple clouds; Inverted in the stream below, Dim trees and purple clouds! Out from the gray and dusky shore A single lamp now gleams, And, trembling far upon the tide, Its red reflection streams. No other light is kindled yet On the earth, or near or far, And but one lamp in heaven is set,— The holy evening star. Soon shall be lighted other lamps, From every window burn; And the laborers, guided by their rays, Shall homeward gladly turn. Soon, too, shall countless lamps, God-lighted, In the high heavens gleam, And the traveller, on his way benighted, Shall bless their holy beam. Cambridge, 1839. MY BOOKS. I am a monarch, though my realm is small; Four narrow walls contain my kingdom all. Yet, low as is my state, No royal potentate Hath wider power than I: Like the Olympian god I do but give the nod, And far and wide my messengers do fly, To bring me goodly company Lest I should be alone. Earth's wisest, noblest, saintliest, and most great Do, at their bidding, wait Around my throne, And lay their treasures at my feet. If I but stretch my hand At once I see Obedient to my command Sages before me stand, Teachers from every land; The orators unseal their golden tongues, The poets greet me with their sweetest songs, Earth's choicest inspirations are for me. Such is my throne, Such my dominion, While I sit here, alone! Cambridge, 1842. SONG FOR THE ?. ?. ?. DINNER. Drink, weary traveller, drink and pray For the poor soul of Sybil Grey, Who built this cross and well. Marmion. The pilgrim oft in days of old Paused on his weary road Where, guarded by its rude-hewn cross, The fountain's current flowed: And as upon the sparkling stream His eye delighted fell, He blessed in prayer the name of him Who built the cross and well. We in our weary pilgrimage Have turned aside to-day, For thick upon our sandals lies The dust of life's hot way. We drink of Friendship's living wave In Learning's sacred dell, And bless in prayer the names of them Who built this cross and well. MY ROOM. I wish I could bring you here, If only for a minute, That you might see my room And everything that is in it. But as there are no carpets In these degenerate days, Like those in Arabian story Which could take you from place to place, I must try what my pen can do As a sort of magic wand. I'll describe to you the room, And I hope you'll understand. First and foremost, then, you must know That it's up on the third floor In old Massachusetts Hall That's a hundred years old and more; As I dare say you would think If you saw those heavy beams That go across the ceiling Like so many broad seams. But they are not beams of oak With carvings rich and rare And all grown black with age;— I'm sure I wish they were. Two windows are in the room, Both on the northern side,— Very pleasant to sit at in summer When they are open wide; And from them you look out On the elms and the College Green; To the left the barren Common And the wide street are seen, And that modest little church, So pleasant to the eye, That was built by our English fathers In the years so long gone by. And among the many elms You see that noblest one,— That grand old tree with its broad boughs Once sheltered Washington. All this and more you may see In the pleasant summer-tide; But now it 's better within By the cheerful fireside. On the left, between the doors, Opposite the fireplace, You will see my greatest treasures In that old-fashioned case. Yet my books are few enough, And none of them are rare; But you'll find some good old friends, And perhaps some new ones there. Upon the centre shelf Are Shakspere's noble plays; And some of the many poets Who sing in our own days. And there is glorious Milton Whom suffering could not bow, And melancholy Dante With wrinkled cheek and brow. On the upper shelf is Schiller,— Youth living in the man,— And next the Greek tragedians; Greek and Barbarian! And “visionary Coleridge,” That German-English mind,— Three volumes of his poems And some prose works you'll find. For philosophy, there 's Jouffroy, A fair, clear-minded man, And Benjamin Constant, And much-abused Cousin. And now look at this ancient table With its nicely inlaid top And its prettily carved acorns; Each drawer has its brass drop. And near it the antique chair So very prim and tall, With its straight cane-woven back, And the carved rose crowning all. How many a gray-haired man Has rested in that chair; How many a bright-eyed child With softly curling hair! Or some young loving mother, With half-arrested breath, Has sat and watched her darling Slumbering into death. But now I wish you were in it, Dear heart, so true and fond! You should be there, this minute, If my pen were a magic wand. 1842. ON LAKE SUNAPEE. The summer night is wooing; “Come, come,” the lake is suing; With tender gleam, With witching beam, “Here am I,” Cries the beckoning half-moon in the sky. The boat impatient waiting, Our hearts within dilating, Away, away, In the mimic day,— You and I, And the silver half-moon in the sky. From oar-blades, slowly dipping, Fall drops in music slipping; We are afloat In charmèd boat,— You and I, And the magic half-moon in the sky! For us the night wind's sighing, The night-bird's soft replying; The world 's our own, We are alone,— You and I, And the silent half-moon in the sky. And now, dissolved in dreaming, The world is naught but seeming; The shadowy woods Reflect our moods,— You and I, And the dreamy half-moon in the sky. Of time we take no noting, Between the two worlds floating Of soft ideal And misty real,— You and I, And the mystic half-moon in the sky. Our thoughts and feelings mingle, We are not two, nor single; Our spirits blend, No word we send,— You and I; And the sinking half-moon leaves the sky! 1886.</field>
   </doc>
</add>