<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Bryant, William Cullen, 1794-1878</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Bryant, William Cullen, 1794-1878</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">bryant william cullen 1794 1878</field>
      <field name="author_text">Bryant, William Cullen, 1794-1878</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1800's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ap/uvaGenText/tei/chap_AM0076.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240349</field>
      <field name="date_text">1809</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:439555</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The embargo ; or, sketches of the times ; A satire</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- 1783-1850</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- 1783-1850</field>
      <field name="title_display">The embargo ; or, sketches of the times ; A satire</field>
      <field name="title_facet">embargo or sketches of the times</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">embargo or sketches of the times</field>
      <field name="title_text">The embargo ; or, sketches of the times ; A satire</field>
      <field name="year_display">1809</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1809</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1809</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:439555&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:439555&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Bryant, William Cullen, 1794-1878&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;bryant william cullen 1794 1878&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The embargo ; or, sketches of the times ; A satire&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;embargo or, sketches of the times&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1809&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1809&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Bryant, William Cullen&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1794&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1878&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The embargo ; or, sketches of the times&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A satire&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Boston&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for the author, by E. G. House [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1809&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3865159-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;cham0076&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- 1783-1850&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1783&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1850&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The embargo ; or, sketches of the times&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A satire&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1996&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1996 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 51 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-AmPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE EMBARGO. “When private faith and public trust are sold, “And traitors barter liberty for gold; “When fell corruption, dark, and deep, like fate, “Saps the foundation of a sinking state; “Then warmer numbers glow through satire's page, “And all her smiles are darken'd into rage; “Then keener indignation fires her eye, “Then flash her lightnings, and her thunders fly!” ESSAY ON SATIRE. Look where we will, and in whatever land, Europe's rich soil, or Afric's barren sand, Where the wild savage hunts his wilder prey, Or art and science pour their brightest day, The monster Vice appears before our eyes, In naked impudence, or gay disguise. But quit the meaner game indignant muse, And to thy country turn thy nobler views; Ill-fated clime! condemn'd to feel th' extremes, Of a weak ruler's philosophic dreams; Driven headlong on, to ruin's fateful brink, When will thy country feel, when will she think! Satiric muse, shall injured Commerce weep Her ravish'd rights, and will thy thunders sleep; Dart thy keen glances, knit thy threat'ning brows, Call fire from heaven to blast thy country's foes. Oh let a youth thine inspiration learn— Oh give him “words that breathe and thoughts that burn!” Curse of our nation, source of countless woes, From whose dark womb unreckon'd misery flows; Th' Embargo rages, like a sweeping wind, Fear lowers before, and famine stalks behind. What words, oh Muse! can paint the mournful scene, The saddening street, the desolated green; How hungry labourers leave their toil and sigh, And sorrow droops in each desponding eye! See the bold Sailor from the Ocean torn, His element, sink friendless and forlorn! His suffering spouse the tear of anguish shed, His starving children cry in vain for bread! On the rough billows of misfortune tost, Resources fail, and all his hopes are lost; To foreign climes, for that relief he flies, His native land ungratefully denies. In vain Mechanics ply their curious art, And bootless mourn the interdicted mart; While our sage Ruler's diplomatic skill, Subjects our councils to his sovereign will; His grand ‘restrictive energies’ employs, And wisely regulating trade—destroys. The Farmer, since supporting trade is fled, Leaves the rude joke, and cheerless hangs his head; Misfortunes fall, an unremitting shower, Debts follow debts, on taxes, taxes pour,— See in his stores his hoarded produce rot, Or Sheriff sales his profits bring to naught; Disheartening cares in thronging myriads flow, Till down he sinks to poverty and woe! Ye, who rely on Jeffersonian skill; And say that fancy paints ideal ill; Go, on the wings of observation fly, Cast o'er the land a scrutinizing eye; States, counties, towns, remark with keen review, Let facts convince and own the picture true! Oh, ye bright pair! the blessing of mankind, Whom time has sanction'd, and whom fate has join'd, Commerce, that bears the trident of the main, And Agriculture, empress of the plain; Who hand in hand, and heav'n-directed, go Diffusing gladness through the world below; Whoe'er the wretch, would hurl the flaming brand Of dire disunion, palsied be his hand! Like ‘Cromwell damn'd to everlasting fame,’ Let unborn ages execrate his name! How foul a blot Columbia's glory stains! How dark the scene! infatuation reigns! For French intrigue which wheedles to devour, Threatens to fix us in Napoleon's power; Anon within th' insatiate vortex whirl'd, Whose wide periphery involves the world. Oh, heaven defend, as future seasons roll, These western climes from Bonaparte's control; Preserve our freedom, and our rights secure, While truth subsists, and virtue shall endure! Lo Austria crouches to the tyrant's stroke, And bends proud Rome beneath his galling yoke; Infuriate, reeking with the spoils of war, O'er prostrate kingdoms rolls his blood-stain'd car; Embattled hosts in vain his fury meet, Sceptres and crowns he treads beneath his feet. Aspiring Belgia, once the patriot's pride, When barbarous Alva, her brave sons defied; The nurse of arts, th' advent'rous merchant's boast, Whose wide-spread commerce whiten'd every coast. Humbled, degraded, by the vilest arts, Beneath his iron scourge, succumbing smarts; The crowded city, the canal's green shore, Fair haunts of free-born opulence, no more! Ah, hapless land! where freedom lov'd to dwell, Helvetia's fall, what weeping bard shall tell! Warn'd too by Lusitania's fate, beware!— Columbians wake! evade the deep laid snare! Insensate! shall we ruin court, and fall, Slaves to the proud autocrator of Gaul? Our laws laid prostrate by his ruthless hand, And independence banish'd from our land! We who seven years erst brav'd Britannia's power, By Heaven supported in the gloomiest hour; For whom our Sages plann'd, our Heroes bled, Whom Washington, our pride, and glory led; Till heaven propitious did our efforts crown With freedom, commerce, plenty, and renown. When shall this land, some courteous angel say, Throw off a weak, and erring ruler's sway? Rise, injured people, vindicate your cause! And prove your love of liberty and laws; Oh wrest, sole refuge of a sinking land, The sceptre from the slave's imbecile hand! Oh ne'er consent, obsequious, to advance, The willing vassal of imperious France! Correct that suffrage you misus'd before, And lift your voice above a congress roar. And thou, the scorn of every patriot name, Thy country's ruin, and her council's shame! Poor servile thing! derision of the brave! Who erst from Tarleton fled to Carter's cave; Thou, who, when menac'd by perfidious Gaul, Didst prostrate to her whisker'd minion fall; And when our cash her empty bags supply'd, Didst meanly strive the foul disgrace to hide; Go, wretch, resign the presidential chair, Disclose thy secret measures, foul or fair. Go, search with curious eye, for horned frogs, Mid the wild wastes of Louisianian bogs; Or, where Ohio rolls his turbid stream, Dig for huge bones, thy glory and thy theme. Go, scan, Philosophist, thy ? charms And sink supinely in her sable arms; But quit to abler hands the helm of state, Nor image ruin on thy country's fate! Ah hapless State! with wayward councils curst, Blind to thy weal, and to thy laws unjust;— For, where their blasting ‘energies’ extend, Foes undermine and dire divisions rend;— Who shall sustain thy gradual sinking form, And guide thee safely through the gathering storm? What guardian Angel shall conduct thee o'er Misfortune's ocean to a peaceful shore?— Remove the source whence all thy troubles rose, And shield from foreign and domestic foes! Oh for a Washington, whose boundless mind, Infolds his friends, his country, and mankind; He might restore our happy state again, And roll our Navy o'er the billowy main; From all our shores bid lawless pirates fly, And lift our wond'ring Eagle to the sky! But vain are reason, eloquence, and art, And vain the warm effusions of the heart. E'en while I sing, see Faction urge her claim, Mislead with falsehood, and with zeal inflame; Lift her black banner, spread her empire wide, And stalk triumphant with a fury's stride. She blows her brazen trump, and at the sound, A motley throng, obedient, flock around; A mist of changing hue, o'er all she flings, And darkness perches on her dragon wings! As Johnson deep, as Addison refin'd, And skill'd to pour conviction o'er the mind, Oh, might some patriot rise! the gloom dispel, Chase error's mist, and break her magic spell! But vain the wish, for hark! the murmuring meed Of hoarse applause from yonder shed proceed; Enter, and view the thronging concourse there, Intent, with gaping mouth, and stupid stare; While in the midst their supple leader stands, Harangues aloud, and flourishes his hands; To adulation tunes his servile throat, And sues successful for each blockhead's vote. “The advocate of liberty I stand,— “Oh were I made a ruler in the land! “Your interests none more cherishes than I, “In your sweet service, may I live and die! “For the dear people, how my bowels yearn!— “That such may govern be your chief concern; “Then federalism, and all its lordling train, “Shall fall disgrac'd before our equal reign; “Dismay'd, diminish'd, our fair presence shun, “As shadows shorten to the rising sun; “Spontaneous banquets shall succeed to want, “No tax shall vex you, and no sheriff haunt.” The powerful influence of the knave's address, In capers droll, the foolish dupes express; With horrid shouts th' affrighted sky is rent, And high in air their tatter'd hats are sent. But should truth shine distinguishingly bright, And lay his meanness naked to the sight; He tries new arts to blind their willing eyes, Feeds with new flatt'ries, hammers out new lies, Exerts his influence, urges all his weight, To blast the laurels of the good and great; Till reconfirm'd, the fools uphold him still, Their creed his dictum, and their law his will. Now morning rises borne on golden wings, And fresh to toil the waking post-boy springs; Lo, trudging on his raw bon'd steed he hies, Dispersing Suns, and Chronicles, and Spys. Men uninform'd, in rage for something new, Howe'er unprincipled, howe'er untrue, Suck in with greedy throat the gilded pill, Whose fatal sweetness pleases but to kill. Wide, and more wide the dire contagion flies, Till half the town is overwhelm'd with lies. Hence that delusion, hence that furious zeal, Which wrong-heads cherish, and which hot-heads feel. Oh, snatch me heaven! to some sequester'd spot, Where Jefferson, and faction, are forgot; Where never ‘Suns’ nor ‘Chronicles’ molest, Duane and Colvin unregarded rest. Sick of the tumult, where the noisy throng, In wild disorder, roar of right and wrong; Where lying pamphlets round the town are sped, And knowing politicians talk you dead! In vain Italia boasts her genial clime, Her Rome's proud towers, and palaces sublime; In vain the hardy Swiss, inur'd to toil, Draw scant subsistence from a stubborn soil; Both doom'd alike, to feel, in evil hour, The giant grasp of huge despotic power! Touch not their shores, fair freedom dwells not there, But far remote, she breathes Columbian air; Yet here, her temple totters to its fall, Shook from its centre by gigantic Gaul! Oh, let not prating History proclaim, The foul disgrace, the scandal of our name! Write not the deed my hand! Oh may it lie, Plung'd deep, and mantled in obscurity! Forbid it heaven! that while true honour reigns, And ancient valour glows within our veins, (Our standard justice, and our shield our God,) We e'er should tremble at a despot's nod! Oh, may the laurels of unrival'd fame, For ever flourish round your honour'd name! Ye, who unthrall'd by prejudice, or power, Determin'd stood in that eventful hour; Tore the dire secret from the womb of night, And brought your country's infamy to light! Go boldly on the deep-laid plot unfold, Though much is known, yet much remains untold. But chief to thee our gratitude belongs, Oh Pickering! who hast scan'd thy country's wrongs, Whose ardent mind, and keen discerning eye, Trac'd out the true Embargo policy; Shew'd that our Chief, unable to control, The alien yearnings of his dastard soul; And curst with feelings hostile to our trade, At beck of France, the dire restriction laid! Hail first of Statesmen! Massachusetts' pride! Fam'd in her wars, and in her councils try'd; Long to thy friends by private worth endear'd, “In pure majestic poverty rever'd;” At thy rebuke, (though late so monstrous grown,) Corruption trembles on her venal throne! Oh, may the people, with attentive eyes, Peruse thy well-tim'd warnings and be wise! Mournful reverse! the muse with grief would trace, The painful scene of thy colleague's disgrace. Unhappy he, by glare of office lur'd, Renounc'd the truth, and federal faith abjur'd! With fine spun sophisms, and inflated style, Strove to mislead, bewilder, and beguile; O'er presidential error gently spread The flimsy veil, perverted reason made. Virtue abash'd beheld th' apostate's zeal, And freedom trembled for the public weal; Till Coleman rose, by honest anger led, And at his touch the gay delusion fled; The veil disparts, the painted bubbles burst, The splendid fabric crumbles into dust! Go on, ye pimps of France! intriguers fell! Wind your dark ways, and aid the work of hell! Go, rouse dire faction from her gloomy den, Wake the worst passions in the breasts of men; O'er a once free, once heaven-protected land, Impel the tempest with infuriate hand; Go, lure the simple, with unfaithful views, To paths where error her wild way pursues; But soon from heaven, shall justice wing her way, Arrest your course, and immolate her prey! So prays the muse;—while bursting on the sight, Hope's torch diffuses an enlivening light; And scenes, prophetic of Columbia's rise To former glory, greet the gladden'd eyes. Rous'd by the murmurs of the coming storm, Lo, freedom's genius lifts her radiant form! Rolls her keen eye, and hovering o'er the land, Calls in loud thunders to her slumbering band. Far o'er the realm, electric, unconfin'd, Flies the quick flame, and runs from mind to mind. Wak'd from her stupid lethargy, at length Old Massachusetts, feels returning strength; Her sons, reflecting, break the baneful league, With factious zeal, and popular intrigue; No more they hug delusion's magic chain, Nor grasp at objects, fleeting, and inane; But break the charm, false, flatt'ring error binds, The pleasing mania, that enchain'd their minds. And now as Truth with growing lustre shines, Before her beams Democracy declines; Vain are all arts her baffled leaders try, And vain alike, to flatter or to lie. From their long sleep alarm'd the people rise, And spite of sophisms, learn to trust their eyes. Rise then, Columbians! heed not France's wiles, Her bullying mandates, her seductive smiles; Send home Napoleon's slave, and bid him say No arts can lure us, and no threats dismay; Determin'd yet to war with whom we will, Choose our allies, or dare be ‘neutral’ still. Ye merchants arm! the tyrant Gaul repel, Your prowess shall the naval triumph swell; Send the marauders shatter'd whence they came, And Gallia's cheek suffuse with crimson shame. But first select, our councils to direct, One whose true worth entitles to respect: In whom concentrates all that men admire, The Sage's prudence, and the Soldier's fire; Who scorns ambition, and the venal tribe, And neither offers, nor receives a bribe; Who firmly guards his country's every right, And shines alike, in council, or in fight. Then on safe seas, the merchant's barque shall fly, Our waving flag, shall kiss the polar sky; On canvass wings our thunders shall be borne, Far to the west, or tow'rd the rising morn; Then may we dare a haughty tyrant's rage, And gain the blessings of an unborn age. 'Tis done, behold, the cheerful prospects rise! And splendid scenes the startled eye surprize; Lo! busy Commerce courts the prosperous main, And peace and plenty glad our shores again! Th' industrious swain sees nature smile around, His fields with fruit, with flocks, his pastures crown'd. Thus, in a fallen tree, from sprouting roots, With sudden growth, a tender sapling shoots, Improves from day to day, delights the eyes, With strength, and beauty, stateliness, and size, Puts forth robuster arms, and broader leaves, And high in air its branching head upheaves. Turn now our views to Europe's ravag'd plains, Where murderous war, with grim oppression reigns; There long, and loud, the storm of battle roars, With direful portent to our distant shores; The regal robber, rages uncontrol'd, No law restrains him, and no faith can hold; Before his steps, lo! cowering terror flies, And pil'd behind him, heaps of carnage rise! With fraud, or force, he spreads his iron sway, And blood, and rapine, mark his frightful way! Thus some huge rock of ice, on Greenland's shore, When bound in frost, the surges cease to roar, Breaks loosen'd from its base, with mighty sweep, And thunders horrid o'er the frozen deep. While thus, all Europe rings with his alarms, Say, shall we rush, unthinking, to his arms? No; let us dauntless all his fury brave, Our fluttering flag, in freedom's gale shall wave, Our guardian Sachem's errless shafts shall fly, And terrors lighten from our eagle's eye! Hear then I cease, rewarded, if my song, Shall prompt one honest mind, though guided wrong, To pause from party, view his country's state, And lend his aid to stem approaching fate. Written, April, 1808. THE SPANISH REVOLUTION. A BARD, in science young, unskill'd in song, Essays to tell, how, rous'd by gathering wrong, Iberia, rising from disgrace and chains, Repuls'd th' Usurper from her native plains;— O'er independence hung her faithful shield, Though fiend-like carnage hover'd round the field, And nobly brav'd the caitiff hordes of Gaul, At heaven-born freedom's life-inspiring call! When Bonaparte, (his death-dispensing hand Extending rudely o'er th' Iberian land,) Tore, to exalt a favourite of his own, The lineal monarch from his rightful throne; At first, a soft, a low complaint began, In spacious rounds, dissatisfaction ran! Wide spreads dislike, more loud complaints they rais'd, Till all the fury of their vengeance blaz'd. Thus the small spark, when kindled by the breeze, Swells to a flame, and tops the forest trees. And now the peasantry, awak'd to rage, With Gallic armies mid the streets engage; How dire the din! what horrible alarms, Of shrieks, and shouts, and ever-clanging arms Keen sabres glare, deep-throated cannons roar, And whizzing balls, in leaden vollies pour; While clouds of dust amid the blue immense, Hang o'er the scene, in ominous suspense; Confusion o'er the deathful fray presides, Insatiate Death, the storm of ruin guides, And wild-eye'd Horror screaming o'er the fight, Invokes the curtains of chaotic night! At length, by force o'erwhelm'd, the peasants fail'd, And Gallia's gathering myrmidons prevail'd. What scenes of blood, and massacre ensu'd! Who can describe them, though their eyes have view'd Curst, Cruelty, now owns the Gallic band Her progeny, and guides the murd'rous hand; Grins approbation, while the victim bleeds, And stamps her hell-born image on their deeds! The bursting flame by such rough means supprest, Still burns untam'd, still goads each patriot-breast; Through all restraints, its ardour forcing way, Impels them furious to the raging fray; Swift on the foe each hardy Spaniard flies, Fierce as a tempest of the arctic skies. Fell Discord thunders, unrelenting rage, And dire revenge, and patriot pride, engage. The battle glows, more dreadful than the first, The clouds of war, with deadlier vengeance burst; In louder din the mingled noises rise, And darker glooms conceal the noon-day skies! And now commission'd by the great Supreme, Poizes stern Justice, her unerring beam; Restrains th' Oppressor, with success elate, And seals the awful ‘Tekel’ of his fate! Spain's ravish'd rights, in the descending scale, O'er Gallic fraud, and violence prevail. Iberia triumphs,—deathless deeds were done, Wonders achiev'd, unfading laurels won; Her troops in war's destructive arts unskill'd, Yet like a whirlwind sweep the ensanguin'd field; While haughty France, a sad reverse endures, And veteran warriors yield to untrain'd boors! Iberia conquers,—Hope, electric, flies Throughout the realm, and bids despair arise; Gives energy to age, emboldens fear, Sooths the bereav'd, and dries the orphan's tear; In every visage smiles of pleasure glow, And joy sits dimpling in the face of wo! So, when the Demon of the tempest flies, In thund'ring chariot, o'er the clouded skies; Wide fly his fiery arrows, and his breath Sweeps o'er the scene in hurricanes of death; But soon his glooms disperse, his terrors fly, And Phœbus, beaming from the clear blue sky, Smiles o'er the freshen'd lawn, and vivid bow, The prospect gilding with his native glow! Now warm with hope, the glowing victors strive, The fell invaders from the realm to drive; While retrograde, they seek their native land, Or, yield by thousands to the patriot band; Or, in huge heaps, beneath a foreign sky, Pil'd undistinguish'd, where they fought, they lie. The fruitful vallies, the majestic hills, Adorn'd with groves, and interspers'd with rills, When Sol from cloudless ether looks serene, And fragrant Zephyrs hover o'er the green, With life, and pleasure, animate the soul, And bid the thoughts in placid calmness roll. So, where terrific rocks invade the sky, And thundering torrents tumble from on high; Where ancient towers rise o'er the lofty steep, And shaggy forests overhang the deep; Wak'd by the scene, sublime ideas soar, And lift the soul to heights unknown before! But when, intent on universal sway, Some furious despot drives his wasting way; Whose countless hosts in warlike toils long try'd, Roll in a deep and devastating tide; Should some brave people, rising void of fear, With firm resistance check his fell career; Oppose invasion, with the strength of war, And dash proud triumph from her splendid car; While valour, glowing with resistless ire, Directs the ardour of the patriot fire;— Then nobler feelings, feelings more refin'd, Exalt, inspirit, and sublime the mind! Though seas divide, or deserts intervene, Or ice-top'd mountains lift their heads between; Who, but iudulges in the generous tide Of patriot feelings, with a noble pride? Ye, in a land of freedom, and of peace, Midst plains of plenty, and in bowers of ease; Where truth flames forth, uncheck'd, before whose eye, The gloomy hosts of superstition fly; Where numerous schools their kindly influence spread, And daring science lifts her laurel'd head; Where law, and liberty combine their powers, And war with gloomy aspect never low'rs; Think of your fathers, how in tragic hour, They burst the fetters of Britannia's power; Then, if you can, the virtuous flame despise, Which bids an injur'd land indignant rise! Oh, thou Supreme! to whom revenge belongs, Save the opprest,—repay th' oppressor's wrongs! Ride forth, O God of armies! in thy might, With vigour nerve Spain's gallant sons to fight; Till treacherous France, repuls'd, thy justice own, And yield the captive King his ravish'd throne! My country! think, what injur'd Spain endures, Her righteous cause is liberty's,—'tis yours! Her generous sons, who, French finesse despise, Would gladly meet thy nourishing supplies. Why then, does Commerce still delay to steer To their green shores her breeze-compell'd career! Rise! bid her spread her enterprizing sail, And raise her streamers to the wavy gale; Explore the bounties of the torrid zone, And let its ripe productions be our own! Written, August, 1808. ODE TO CONNECTICUT RIVER. WHY should I blush to sing the rural lay, Where fair Connecta winds its gentle way? While smiling Spring, on southern breezes borne, With snowy pinions scents the breath of morn; And throws her dewy wreaths, with laughing glee, O'er the green mead and germinating tree! Could I thy charms, celebrious stream, rehearse, In glowing numbers and exalted verse; Me, did the Muse of poesy inspire, With Maro's strains, or Pope's celestial fire; Like the rough Tiber, or the gentler Thame, Should classic honours flourish round thy name. On thy green banks, let flowers perennial bloom, And forests shade thee with a grateful gloom; Bright towns ascending, flourish on thy shore, And cultur'd gardens spread their balmy store! When all is hush'd, and buoyant breezes sleep, I view the mirror of thy level deep; The sun reflected from thy bosom shine, With piercing beams, and splendours all divine; There glittering clouds, and glowing skies are seen, The towering forest, and the humble green. Oft, when soft breezes agitate thy tide, I mark thy waves in quick succession ride; While the small fry, disporting rise to sight, Their nimble fins with crimson edges bright; And from her perch the frighted heron springs, Soaring aloft with azure tinted wings! Here, foaming o'er the rugged rocks, he roars, Through dreary chasms, along unfertile shores; There, where yon gay parterre adorns his side, He rolls a gentle and majestic tide! Spread widely round, what beauties crowd the scene, High waving woods, and meadows broad and green; Tall spire-crown'd churches glitter to the day, And clust'ring domes their humbler heads display; In blue perspective, distant mountains rise, And Tempe's charms renew'd, attract th'admiring eyes! Long may thy sons in useful arts renown'd, With waving cornfields hide the furrow'd ground; Hung thick with fruitage bid the orchard bend, And from the vine the clustering grape depend; Plant the young wood, the flowery garden spread, And give the dome to lift its ample head. Long may thy Merchants borne on canvass wing, From various climates, wealth, and wisdom bring; Exotic wealth, that earth or ocean yields, The icy north, or India's purple fields! Oh, ne'er may war, with gloomy front appear, Nor hostile armies prowl for plunder here! May heaven-born peace, amid the sylvan dell, Erect her throne, and long delight to dwell; Led by her hand, may smiling plenty pour, The copious bounties of her flower-crown'd store! Written, May, 1808. THE REWARD OF LITERARY MERIT. “Slow rises worth, by poverty deprest.” LATE, as I took my customary round, What time dun twilight earth and skies embrown'd; I saw, near where yon garden walks are spread, An human form; his hand sustain'd his head; Now grief, now terror, seem'd t' oppress the man, At length his plaintive strain he thus began: “Ah me! neglected on the list of fame! My works unnotic'd, and unknown my name! Expos'd to rough reproach, and squint-eye'd scorn, And all the ills misfortune e'er has borne; By friends avoided, by the proud oppress'd, Pale pen'ry frowns, and care corrodes my breast. “Once I could dive in metaphysic lore,— Scan the wide heavens, the spacious deep explore, Relate where mountains rise, where rivers join, And boldly draw the geometric line. “On wings of poesy, I too could rise, And skim the flow'ry ground, or gain the skies; Could gather sweets in fancy's pathless maze, Or clothe fair truth in more attractive rays. “Again, with ornament I sought to please, With classic purity, unstudied ease, To sense instructive, pleasing to the ear, Correct, yet flowing, elegant and clear. “In politics no mean adept, I knew And trac'd the path my country should pursue Describ'd a happy method to ensure, Her dear-bought freedom, lasting and secure! “Thus fit, I ventur'd to assert my claim, 'Mong crowds of authors, with high hopes of fame. Fame, fickle Goddess, mock'd my humble pray'r, And gave my fruitless incense to the air. Nor pelf accru'd, nor friendship, nor respect, And I was left to undeserv'd neglect! “Is this the taste, the temper of mankind! Of worth neglectful, and to merit blind! And can fair science hope for no reward, But cold reserve, and silent disregard? “But I will chase the glittering toy no more, Fallacious fancy's golden dreams are o'er. I go, base world! where rural scenes are spread, Amidst retirement's shades, to hide my head; Where health and peace diffuse a lenient balm, And soothe the weary to a pleasing calm!” Written, 1807. ENIGMAS. Having observed in the Boston Repertory, several Enigmas, translated from the Latin, by Mr. L. M. Sargent; the following humble attempt was made in imitation of his manner. I. A giant form, erect I lift my brow, Square is my head, and square my shape below; My smoky nostrils breathe an ill perfume, And fierce combustion rages in my womb. II. Known to all men, in every country found, My taper form is rooted in the ground; Green ample tresses hide my lofty head, And high in air my lifted arms are spread. III. An imp of night, a blazing torch I bear, Small is my size, my texture light as air; O'er bogs and fens, I urge my trackless way, And lead the silly traveller astray. IV. With frowning aspect, and with streaming hair, I roam bewilder'd through the fields of air; My strange demeanour, ominous appears, And vulgar souls are fill'd with groundless fears. V. With force resistless, through the plains I glide, Leap from the cliff, or down the mountain slide; The earth beneath my footsteps melts away, And rugged rocks consume by slow decay. VI. Green is my aspect, wrinkled oft my face, My twining arms the ponderous globe embrace, Go, boasting mortal, of thy knowledge vain, And count the subjects that my realms contain! VII. Firm on my base, 'midst circumambient air, I rise, in native grandeur, strong and fair; My open breast receives the driving storm, And a green mantle clings around my form! VIII. No mortal power my fury can withstand, With swelling floods I inundate the land; On heavy wing, with sweeping force I ride, Tall forests crush, and whelm the builder's pride! IX. The son of war, in brazen armour bound, Black is my throat as midnight, and profound; From my dark entrails forc'd, with startling roar, Wide-rolling clouds and swift-wing'd death I pour X. Sulphureous mixtures in our bosoms ride, And chrystal waters, stolen from the tide; We give new beauty to the blasted heath, Or deal the stroke of instantaneous death. XI. Fair Flora's pride the daughters of the Sun, Our colour various, but our nature one; Woo'd by the breeze, at morn we ope our eyes, Frequent the lawn, or in the garden rise. December, 1807. THE CONTENTED PLOUGHMAN. A SONG. “LUXURIOUS plenty's festive board, And beauty's fascinating smiles; The careful miser's golden hoard, And glory's charms, have all their wiles. “Expos'd in tempting view, they please The lighter passions of mankind; We madly rush, and blindly seize, The honied poison of the mind. “But through each soul-seducing snare, Thrice happy he who keeps his way! Free from the manacles of care, Free from delusive pleasure's sway! “Young health shall shed her roses round. And vigour nerve th' elastic limb, The muse shall roam Parnassus' ground, And pluck unfading flowers for him. “More blest, though poor, the ploughman's lot Than the rich placeman's wrap'd in care: Contented with his homely cot, His coarse attire and frugal fare.— “His pleasure is his daily toil, On no fantastic visions built; His treasure is the teeming soil, His boon a conscience void of guilt.’ Thus sang the ploughman to his lyre, While oft his lingering team he cheers, Th' enchanting strains delight, inspire, Soft as the music of the spheres. “And, oh!” I cried, as I withdrew, Pleas'd with the skill the Hind display'd “Oh, would my country-youth pursue. The path so luringly pourtray'd!” “Then Vice, foul parent of disease, Should never root, and flourish here; Hygeia breathe in every breeze, And freshen round the flying year!” June, 1808. DROUGHT. PLUNG'D amid the limpid waters, Or the cooling shade beneath; Let me fly the scorching sun-beams, And the south wind's sickly breath! Sirius burns the parching meadows, Flames upon th' embrowning hill; Dries the foliage of the forest, And evaporates the rill. Scarce is seen a lonely floweret, Save amid th' embowering wood; O'er the prospect dim and dreary, Drought presides in sullen mood! Murky vapours, hung in æther, Wrap in gloom, the sky serene; Nature pants distressful,—silence Reigns o'er all the sultry scene. Then amid the limpid waters, Or beneath the cooling shade; Let me shun the scorching sunbeams, And the sickly breeze evade! July, 1807. TRANSLATION FROM HORACE. LIB. I. CAR. XXII. THE man whose life, devoid of guile, Is pure from crimes and passions vile; Needs not the aid of Moorish art, The bow, the shaft, and venom'd dart. Whether he tempt the scorching blast, Through Lybian sands, a trackless waste; Rude frosty Caucasus explores, Or treads Hydaspes' golden shores. For late through Sabine woods I rov'd, Remote, and sung the girl I lov'd, Careless, unarm'd:—with nimble tread, A hideous wolf before me fled. In warlike Daunia's spacious wood, Ne'er monster prowl'd of fiercer brood; Such Mauritania never bore, Where hungry lions bask and roar. Place me where never genial breeze, Awakes the flowers, revives the trees; Where low'ring clouds the skies deform, And angry Jove impels the storm; Place me where Sol with scorching rays Reflects intolerable blaze,— There shall the fair reward my toils, Who sweetly speaks, and sweetly smiles.</field>
   </doc>
</add>