<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Cawein, Madison Julius, 1865-1914</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Cawein, Madison Julius, 1865-1914</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">cawein madison julius 1865 1914</field>
      <field name="author_text">Cawein, Madison Julius, 1865-1914</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1900's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ap/uvaGenText/tei/chap_AM0035.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240350</field>
      <field name="date_text">1906</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:439515</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Nature-notes and impressions in prose and verse</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Nature-notes and impressions in prose and verse</field>
      <field name="title_facet">nature notes and impressions in prose and verse</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">nature notes and impressions in prose and verse</field>
      <field name="title_text">Nature-notes and impressions in prose and verse</field>
      <field name="year_display">1906</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1906</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1906</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:439515&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:439515&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Cawein, Madison Julius, 1865-1914&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;cawein madison julius 1865 1914&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Nature-notes and impressions in prose and verse&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;nature notes and impressions in prose and verse&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1906&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1906&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Cawein, Madison Julius&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1865&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1914&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Nature-notes and impressions in prose and verse&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;New York&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;E. P. Dutton and Company&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1906&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3865119-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;cham0035&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Nature-notes and impressions in prose and verse&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1996&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1996 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 121 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Verse extracted from the prose text.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-AmPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To the Memory OF GEORGE H. ELLWANGER TRUE FRIEND AND LOVER AND INTERPRETER OF NATURE, AS A SLIGHT TOKEN OF ESTEEM AND ADMIRATION [Would I could talk as the flowers talk] Would I could talk as the flowers talk To my soul! and the stars, in their ceaseless walk Through Heaven!—and tell to the high and low The things that they say, so all might know The dreams they dream, and have told to me! As Nature sees would I could see! Then might I speak with authority!— I stand below and look above, And see her busy with life and love, And can tell the world so little thereof. Oh, for a soul that could feel much less! Or, feeling more, could so express The things it feels and their tenderness: The very essence, the soul of art, And all the heavens and hells of heart! Then might I rise to the very peak, The summit of song, which poets seek, And speak with a voice as the masters speak. NATURE-NOTES and IMPRESSIONS Nature never did betray the heart that loved her.— Wordsworth. 1883–1886 [Lead me, thou Bard of Beauty, through those caves] Lead me, thou Bard of Beauty, through those caves Of pale Diana! let me hear the moan Of Ocean, sorrowing with all his waves As once he sorrowed on that Island lone In siren moonlight. Here, where twilight paves The woodland paths, I seem to hear her trail Dim raiment; her, that damsel who enslaves My soul; that Beauty, sad, divinely pale, That haunts thy song, mastering the gamut whole Of dreams and music; on whose easeful breast,— As once Endymion's head, soft-dreaming, pressed That Indian maiden's bosom,—rests my soul. [O let me sing as thou didst, Keats, and die] O let me sing as thou didst, Keats, and die! With soul poured on the circling starry night; When Dian's lune hangs dewy in the sky, And the wild nightingale with anguished might Bewails in some dense bramble's spicy dusk Its old heart-sorrow to the wild rose wan; Or let me, like thyself, drink in the musk Of some dull draught from Lethe's waters drawn, And sink, as thou didst, into dreamless sleep, Where disappointment, heartache, grief and scorn, And human misery can no longer heap The soul that treads life's path set round with thorn; Ay! fall asleep, as thou didst fall asleep Under the alien skies, of hope forlorn! [In the forest of music often and often] In the forest of music often and often, To the murmuring song of the winds and waters, Have our spirits mingled and mixed In the wildflower dance of the Hours On the mossy carpet under the whispering leaves: Or wandered, hand in shadowy hand, Beneath the song-suggestive stillness of the moon: Or leaned, listening, Over deep glens of echoing green, Carved in the ancient bosoms of the hills By sonorous and impetuous waters, Bearing upon their foamy crests Crescents and points, starry and still, Of reflected emerald flame, When the heavens bloomed and blazed with a million quivering fires. Dost thou know her name? Fairest of the Daughters of Music is she, Loveliest of all the Children of Art. [When winter nights are cold and shrill] When winter nights are cold and shrill, And winds sit rocking wild their arms, Far off, beyond the treeless hill, Sound ghostly faint the owl's alarms. Wail, wail, thou bird of ill omén, Within thy freezing glen! Screech, screech through all the frosty night Where gleams the cold moonlight! Well with man's mood thy song accords, Thy song that knows but wailing words. Lo, where the oats in barn are housed, The screech-owl sits and croons and cries, Until the cocks are all aroused And know to-night some pullet dies. Hush, hush, thou staring owl! And leave the roosting fowl! Go, seek the shivering wood, And there, where wild winds brood, Sing to the soul that hope has lost, The soul that still is tempest-tost. When snows drift deep the forest path, And sleet bows down the strongest trees, Like Edgar's fear and Lear's crazed wrath, The screech-owl's voice makes wild the breeze. Mourn, mourn, thou feathered witch Above the frozen ditch! Weep, weep, unto the icy gale, Where icicles hang pale, As weeps the heart, ingratitude Makes winter of, the grief pursued. [The roar of winter through the palsied oaks] The roar of winter through the palsied oaks, Wind-tortured on the withered fields, Is as the sound of giant chariot spokes, And clashing of innumerable shields. [I've wooed soft sleep all night] I've wooed soft sleep all night, Clothed in her mantle white And dim as rain; I've lain all night and wept For death, who past me crept, To still this pain, Heart's pain, but all in vain. Why cam'st thou not, O death? Why cam'st thou not, O sleep? Death's brother, calm of breath, For whom I keep Vigil the long night through: At last the day breaks blue And dim the dawn. Would that you yet might hear, And hearing me, draw near Ere night be gone. The night is wild; the bitter blasts sweep by; The shrouded snows with ghostly fingers beat The shuddering casements, and the candle flame Seems fluttered of phantom lips whose kiss is death. [With its helm of silver and spur of gold] With its helm of silver and spur of gold A fairy knight is the toad-flax bold, Who takes this form to mortal eyes, The form of a flower of golden dyes. [By the willow copse near the river shore] By the willow copse near the river shore, Where the white waves hush their splash and roar, With an idle sail and an idle oar I seemed to drift into other streams, Borne on by the sleepy current of dreams. [O wilding of the young, young June] O wilding of the young, young June, That this old rock holds fast, Thy day is done too soon, too soon, Too beautiful to last. [When all the orchards faded lie] When all the orchards faded lie, When roses drop and lilies die, When fall's full moon makes deep the sky, Lay me asleep, Where breezes bend the sighing trees, Lay me asleep. When all the dusty autumn day Is heard the locust's roundelay, And, dropping leaves, the tree-tops sway And wildflowers there, Beneath the wildflowers let me rest, The wildflowers there. Let not thy hand disturb the grass To plant an alien flower there; Let those wild infants, free as fair, Above me, sleeping, bloom and pass, Forgotten die, Forgotten as myself, alas! Who 'neath them lie. [The moon is a lemon petal] The moon is a lemon petal, And the west a wild-rose red, And the twilight twines her dusky locks With lily-like stars o'erhead. [Deep down, deep down, deep, deep, deep] Deep down, deep down, deep, deep, deep! Follow us! come with us!—See how we leap! Daughters of Æger, veiled white with the spray, Beckoning, calling you. Oh, come away! Children of Earth, come hither, where we Dwell in Ran's realms of cerulean hue; Where through her caverns of green and of blue Echo our songs, our songs of the sea, Dirging the dead, the sailors who sleep Deep down, deep down, deep, deep, deep! Come, where the dulse and the nautilus cling! Come away, come away, here where we sing! Where of your eyes we will fashion pale homes, Hollow, for pearls and the glimmering foams. [Come, kiss me, beautiful Death] Come, kiss me, beautiful Death, And lull me with thy wings; Breathe on me with thy breath, And touch my soul with things Unknown of life. Imbue My body with thy dew And bear me far away Into a deeper dawn Than lights life's shadowy lawn, Some fairer break-of-day. Life's sickness, long and old, Cure in me; everything: Life's greed for fame and gold And love and suffering. Yea, I am young and fair! Come, take me by the hair And kiss me on the eyes; Then bear me through the deep, As thy brother, dream-tossed Sleep, Hath borne me loving-wise. [Cheerily rang the bugle horn] Cheerily rang the bugle horn, Cheerily through the wood, For the ten-tined buck by the hunt outworn At bay 'neath the old oak stood. [And now yon crystal mount of clouds] And now yon crystal mount of clouds Silvers with light as 't were of wings, Whose base the thunder's blackness shrouds, While to its summit brightness clings. Along the west, flashed through the dun, Leaping, the angled lightnings fly, Cleaving the deeps, where thunders run Like mountain torrents down the sky. Out of it rises, partly hid, A cloud, rose-spar, all fair of form, Like some sky-pointed pyramid, Or pillar of light, above the storm. May 23, 1885; 6 P. M. [The broad Ohio's darkening stream] The broad Ohio's darkening stream Seems now as still as liquid glass, In which the bridge's pillars dream Unwavering where the still waves pass. The shattered thunder fragments fly; One cloud alone makes dark the west, Low stooping to the evening sky, A champion with a burning crest: Through whose mailed breast of darkness dim And ragged rents of vapors deep, The sun sweeps lances, long and slim, Of flame that fall on vale and steep. Through stratas torn of windy rack Full flashes now its crimson star, Blazing blood-red through stormy black And bronze of tempest scattered far. May 23, 1885; 6:30 P.M. [O wind of eve, what spices, steeped] O wind of eve, what spices, steeped In some more aromatic clime, Thou breathest,—as from islands reaped Of Summer, over seas of thyme. Thou bearest odor on thy breath Fresh as the scent of ocean's waves; Cool as if thou hadst lain beneath, All day, in dark and crystal caves. Night comes, with sparkling fireflies Like jewels tangled in her hair, And all around her perfumes rise Of rain, as 't were dim spirits there. [When eve casts on the day's dark bier] When eve casts on the day's dark bier The rhododendrons of her light, And trims her stars, like tapers clear, At feet and head, how fair is night. [O my Kentucky, forest old!] O my Kentucky, forest old! Where Beauty dwells, the stalwart child Of Love and Life, where I behold The dreams still glow that long beguiled The marble and the bronze of men, Whose Art made fair the world of old, Yet never held, of classic ken, A form like thine which I would mould. Around me now I turn and gaze: The earth is green; the heaven is clear: Where smile the stars, or bloom the days More absolutely fair than here! Young still is she, and fresh as morn, Standing her sister States among; Ah! would I were a poet born, To sing her as she should be sung! Bidding her keep beneath her heel The lust for wealth, wrong's iron crown; Her pioneer pride, a shield of steel, A buckler that no foe may down. Sister to Hospitality! Mother of Lincoln and of Clay! Make thyself worthy still to be Mother of men as great as they. Mother of loves and hopes that dare; Of dreams and deeds that sing and toil, Whose hands are open as the air, Whose honor none on earth may soil! Let mightier dreams be thine! arise! Let all the world behold thee set A constellation in the skies Where all thy sister Stars are met! 1885. [A distant river glimpsed through deep-leaved trees] A distant river glimpsed through deep-leaved trees. A field of fragment flint, blue, gray, and red. Rocks overgrown with twigs of trailing vines Thick-hung with clusters of the green wild-grape. Old chestnut groves the haunt of drowsy cows, Full-uddered kine chewing a sleepy cud; Or, at the gate, around the dripping trough, Docile and lowing, waiting the milking-time. Lanes where the wild-rose blooms, murmurous with bees, The bumble-bee tumbling their frowsy heads, Rumbling and raging in the bell-flower's bells, Drunken with honey, singing himself asleep. Old in romance a shadowy belt of woods. A house, wide-porched, before which sweeps a lawn Gray-boled with beeches and where elder blooms. And on the lawn, whiter of hand than milk, And sweeter of breath than is the elder bloom, A woman with a wild-rose in her hair. [No more for me shall gray-robed Dawn look through] “No more for me shall gray-robed Dawn look through Heaven's windows of the fog, or rain, or dew, The maiden Dawn with eyes of beautiful blue.” [I saw sweet Summer go] I saw sweet Summer go Into a woodland green, Unto a sliding stream, A drowsy water; With cheeks of sunset glow Dreaming she seemed to lean, Dreaming a wild-wood dream, The wood's wild daughter. She seemed to smile, then weep, Then lift, then bow her head, Deep with its golden hair, Sad as some maiden Who loveless falls asleep, Her eyes to sorrow wed, Her cheeks as wild flowers fair With dewdrops laden. I heard the streamlet moan; I heard the wood-wind wail; I heard the forest sob: “Summer is dying!” Whiter she lay than stone, And down each dell and dale I heard the wild heart-throb Of Nature sighing:— “Come back!—Oh, art thou dead, Thou, thou my sweetest child? Come back with all thy flowers!”— But naught she heeded, Lying with wild-flowered head In beauty undefiled, While 'round her sad the Hours Bowed down and pleaded. Then through the woodland there, With ribbons flying gay, Mocking at Summer's death With laughter hollow, Tossing her gipsy hair, In Romany array, Autumn, all wild of breath, Cried, “Follow! follow!” [When the jeweled lights of the fireflies gleam] When the jeweled lights of the fireflies gleam In fairy revelry; When the waning moon on the forest stream Looks down, I love to sit and dream, To dream her again with me. We speak of the past; of the things once said; Of the happiness long gone by; While one blue star burns bright overhead:— For sweet it is to talk with the dead, The dead that do not die. With the dead that are never far away, That are even as yonder star, Whose light the darkness, ray on ray, Makes visible, viewless all the day Though shining still afar. Like a lonely beautiful flower wild In the limitless lands of space, That star is, blossoming undefiled; More beautiful for that loneness, mild It shines on my upturned face. 'Mid the fairy lights of the fireflies, In the light of the waning moon, Born of the grief that never dies, Into my eyes gaze her dark eyes, The eyes death closed last June. And I hear her speak, and I hear her sigh:— For, the dead—they never forget: Around my heart her white hands lie, And she kisses my face and asks me why My cheeks with tears are wet. And as in life I clasp her and hold, And meseems it is no dream— That here we meet, as oft of old, When the lights of the fireflies' lamps gleam gold, In the trysting place by the stream. [Thus in the dusk as ghosts they met] Thus in the dusk as ghosts they met, Culling the pansy-violet, The violet of sweet regret And memory, dim and dewy wet. [In dimly lighted cloisters of the heart] In dimly lighted cloisters of the heart I met with one whose face was like to thine, The ghost-face of the love that once I wronged. [Amid the summer fields and flowers] Amid the summer fields and flowers, Let us be children for a day, Where laughter speeds the joyful hours And drives dull care away. [Keep thou my face engraven in thine heart] Keep thou my face engraven in thine heart, Now that we part; Forget me not; or if thou dost forget Hold me to blame, Who leave thee now, without one heart's regret, Forgotten even thy name. [One milk-white hand she stretched to me] One milk-white hand she stretched to me, My heart sobbed, “O beware!” But both my arms reached out to her Despite my soul's despair. 1887–1890 [Now that the dawn is up, is up] Now that the dawn is up, is up, And your vine drips dewy with cup on cup, Lean out, lean out, rare Marguerite, Lean out of your window over the street, Where Love stands waiting, sweet, for you, Like a rose 'mid roses wet with dew. [Dark woodland ways of drowsy rustlings] Dark woodland ways of drowsy rustlings Where, in the road, the clay-red nodules lie; And where the wild grape, green with clusters, swings, Dimmer than rain, the cool noon hours steal by. [The thunder boomed from cloudy ridge to ridge] The thunder boomed from cloudy ridge to ridge, Trailing the terror of sonorous arms; Making the lightning for his wrath a bridge, Planting his banners on the heights of storms. [Who now hath understood] Who now hath understood, Whose art may ever reach The velvet blush of the bud, The velvet bloom of the peach? [High up she glides, high up, the quartz-white moon] High up she glides, high up, the quartz-white moon, Tipping the mountains with exultant fire, And in her light each pine becomes a lyre, And every wind an Oread-whispered tune. [The hope, the hate, the bitterness of love] The hope, the hate, the bitterness of love Were in her eyes that levelly looked at me, While th' rebel blood went storming up her cheek. Devil and angel was she in a breath, Cursing and kissing me whom she wished dead. [Barbaric burgonets, heavy with gems] Barbaric burgonets, heavy with gems, And armor wrought of wondrous alchemy, The Spirits of the sunset don, and sweep, Vast, cloudy-charioted, along the skies. [Thou hast no thought for one who walks 'mid flowers] Thou hast no thought for one who walks 'mid flowers, Whiling away the humming-bird-like hours, Nay, nay, not thou! Nor think I now of thee who sittest where The vine leaves wreathe thy beautiful brow and hair, Forgotten now. [Thou art to me the whole of heaven] Thou art to me the whole of heaven, Its sun, its stars, its golden moon; Thou art to me as music given, As song that holds the world in tune. [Two unshed tears made beautiful her eyes] Two unshed tears made beautiful her eyes Lighting their liquid turquoise sorrowful; Yet was she false, in spite of all her tears, And with sin pregnant as the seeds of hell. [Oh, for the gods of the Greeks] Oh, for the gods of the Greeks, The oaks of Dodona! For the white-bosomed gods of the Greeks! The gods whom my fancy seeks 'Mid these woods whence is blown a Murmur of Naiad creeks;— Here where this old oak speaks, To my soul, like a god of the Greeks, An oak of Dodona! [A languid land of lazy moons and stars] A languid land of lazy moons and stars I wander in, watching the ripple bars Rocking the hyacinths and nenuphars. [The haymakers' sickles] The haymakers' sickles Flash wet on the leas; The wild honey trickles From tops of the trees, The noon is a poppy, the winds are its bees. [She whom I loved too well] She whom I loved too well, Crowned with the pomegranate bell Sits empress now in Hell; And there My soul sits by her, kissing her eyes and hair. [Tell me, do you love to lie] Tell me, do you love to lie With the dipping boughs above you, Where blue glimpses of the sky Greet you like the eyes that love you? [What gladness of the young, young Earth] What gladness of the young, young Earth Conceived the lily and rose? What sweetness of her soul's deep thought Into their fragrance flows? [Maid Marian rose in the morn betime] Maid Marian rose in the morn betime, Looked in her glass and hummed a rhyme. I saw her walk by the blossoming bean Busked in a gown of bombazine. [Look at me over your shoulder, lass] Look at me over your shoulder, lass, As you often look in your looking-glass, And trill to me that merry rhyme, That rhyme of love and the glad spring-time, With a fol-de-rol-de-rey oh! [Oh, could I only grieve you] Oh, could I only grieve you, And grieve you more and more! I who no more believe you, You, falser than before! Ah, could I but deceive you, You, whom I still adore! Oh! would I were a bee, my love, And you a wild-rose tree, my love, I'd sip the sweets I see, my love, And be no longer poor. When apple buds are breaking, And winds with musk o'erflow; When wren and thrush are making Sweet song where'er we go, The kiss I'll then be taking Is the kiss that still you owe. [You who would not have me] You who would not have me Now may not save me; Now you pursue me, I will not woo thee: Love is grown cold; Love is grown old. [Dim gleam and gloom] Dim gleam and gloom And breezy boom Of wild bees in the mustard bloom Swoon through the windows of my room, As if the young Spring trailed her raiment of perfume Through the old house, rustling from room to room. [Along the west a cloud-wrought crimson cloth] Along the west a cloud-wrought crimson cloth The curtained sunset draws, to which one star Clings, fluttering silver, like a glimmering moth, Pale and crepuscular. What voice is that which wanders in the wood? Is it the Twilight murmuring to the hills? Or, wrapped in mystery of the solitude, The far-off whippoorwills? [What of the sea when the storm clouds thicken] What of the sea when the storm clouds thicken? What of the soul when its loved hopes sicken? Look in my eyes and tell me this,— What of our lives when our hearts are stricken, Given and taken our love's last kiss? [Between the meads of millet] Between the meads of millet The soft wind breathes and blows; Between the meads of millet I kissed her mouth's warm rose, And on her hand I placed the band, Where all my future glows. [Her eyes were dark with the darkness of hell] Her eyes were dark with the darkness of hell And sweet with the sweetness of sin, And I was a dream of love, they tell, To her eyes that entered in. [Night came, treading the darkness into burning stars] Night came, treading the darkness into burning stars, And in my heart waking again old wars. The shadow of the past lay on my mind's sick gloom As on a waste the shadow of a tomb. [On the sunset's cloudy tide] On the sunset's cloudy tide Triremes of the storm did sit, All their hundred ports flung wide With wild battle lanterns lit. [Alas! how hearts go groping] Alas! how hearts go groping For that which may not be! Braving the gates where hoping, 'T is written, none shall see! In ways of blind endeavor And darkness of the never The gates are closed once open; The end is misery. [Why is it thus with me as days go by] Why is it thus with me as days go by? Oh, why, oh, why? Less frequent is the smile, more often now the sigh. [Swift as the poplar, with its lordly height] Swift as the poplar, with its lordly height, To clothe itself in green when Springtime calls, When forests still are bare, is hope to come Into our lives when love has said “prepare.” [While lone I stood] While lone I stood Within the wood I heard the feet of Silence edge And stumble on a rocky ledge— A sound of waters foaming down Between mossed banks of green and brown: And through the trees, that leaned to listen, I caught a momentary glisten Of her white limbs all interwound With white confusion of her gown, That made a dim and glimmering sound. 1891–1900 [A vagabond foot and a vagabond road] A vagabond foot and a vagabond road, And the love in our hearts our only load. An easy foot in an easy shoe, And who is it cares where the road leads to? An old plank gate at a lane's green end, And who is it cares where the lane may wend? A bowl of milk and a bit of bread, Who richer fares or is better fed? A crust, a spring and a blackberry, And who is it sups as well as we? A hut by the road and a girl to kiss, What man hath greater joy than this? The night, the stars, and a pillow of hay, Whose bed is sweeter than this, I say? Whose dreams are deeper? whose sleep as pure?— The heart that's heavy finds here its cure. Finley Woods, July 15th. [As, all distraught, with dark, neglected hair] As, all distraught, with dark, neglected hair She lifted up her face to mine I saw The moon-white glory of her soul, and love Smiled sadly at me from her shadowy eyes. [The milkweeds nod their Rip-Van-Winkle heads] The milkweeds nod their Rip-Van-Winkle heads When Autumn blows; and in the snoring flue The chill wind sleeps. All night it seems to me A goblin gnome, a Lob Lie-by-the-Fire, Sits humped upon the hob whining of cold, Or whistling to the flame to keep him warm. [In the Garden of Skulls and Serpents] In the Garden of Skulls and Serpents, By a tower of gold, Stood a woman, fair as fire, Wonderful to behold. Webs of starry flame she wove there, Webs of moony fire, Snares to seize the souls of mortals, Slay them with desire. [The pure precision of a star, a flower] The pure precision of a star, a flower, The punctuality of their return And order of their coming fill my soul With the astonishment which mortals feel For Bible beauties that no man explains. [I have listened long unto the promises] I have listened long unto the promises, The confidences of the trees; and now, Continuous with the trees, a stream expands, Expounding all the woods' dim mysteries In ripple rhymes sung softly to itself. [I saw the Spring go by, her mouth a thread] I saw the Spring go by, her mouth a thread Of wild-rose red, Blowing a golden oat; And now, a crown of barley on her head, The Summer comes, a poppy at her throat. [An Eldorado of vales and peaks] An Eldorado of vales and peaks, That the cloudy ore of the sunset streaks, Is the Eldorado my fancy seeks: Where the gold lies thick that they feign to find,— That never in earthly mine was mined,— In the airy caves of the dæmonkind. [A rune of glimmer and a scrawl of light] A rune of glimmer and a scrawl of light, Printing with gold the black-bound page of night, The glow-worm is, making its blackness bright. [The deep blue spike of the great lobelia glows] The deep blue spike of the great lobelia glows Beside the cardinal-flower along the ways Where Summer goes stripping the wayside rose Of all its blooms, and plumping red its hips; Her grasshopper gown of rustling golds and grays Bristling with burrs caught from the trefoil's sprays, And from the thorny marigold's tick-like tips. [I gazed upon the wasted lips of Want] I gazed upon the wasted lips of Want Within a city haunt Of vice and sin, And thought of the green, the abundant fields beyond The sordid streets, whither Want could not win, The sick and fond; And, where the white-top like dim streaks of steam Wavers its whiteness, lay him down and dream, Lapped in the murmur of a meadowed stream. [Green in the circle of contingent trees] Green in the circle of contingent trees The water lies wherein the new leaf sees Its twinkling shadow. Through the boscage leers The beast-like visage with the satyr smile Of what has followed me this many a mile, Earth's lust, hot-eyed, with horrible mouth and ears. [On every side the roses rise] On every side the roses rise In crimson insolence and pride; And near them, steeped in lordly dyes, That to the roses' are allied, Of transitory purple and pearl, The poppies' delicate flowers uncurl. [The shadows where no light looked through] The shadows where no light looked through, Ephemeral sapphire, lay in pools of blue; And there the spendthrift flowers flung Their petaled gold; and many a tongue Of many a wild bird of their beauty sung. [With all my heart I deem it no great folly] With all my heart I deem it no great folly To be in love with gentle Melancholy; [What bird is that that sings so long] What bird is that that sings so long? To hear whose song Each bashful bud opens its rosy ear, Leaning it near. While here, Under the blossoming button-tree, I seem to see A shape, a presence look out at me; And, clothed in raiment of white and gray, Pass on like the Spirit of Easter Day. [The sunset lets its heavy curtains down] The sunset lets its heavy curtains down Of thunder-purple orphreyed deep with gold Around the cloudy-builded couch of Day, Canopied with the star-wrought blue of heaven. [These are the cups of Comus] These are the cups of Comus, These tulips pranked with flame, The tulip-burning twilight fills With wine of wondrous name. [Yea; death behind her, gazing through her hair] Yea; death behind her, gazing through her hair; Death in her lips and in her body fair; Ten hundred deaths to him whose heart is hers, Who kisses her—death, darkness, and despair. [The blue wild hyssop, with its dewy mouth] The blue wild hyssop, with its dewy mouth,— Cool, moist, and heavenly 'mid the pink-bloomed mint Along the shallow creek, shrunk with the drouth,— Seen suddenly thus, seems, swift, an instant's hint Of some dim being—one, whom, still in vain, I follow where their many delicate ears The purple beard's-tongue and lobelia lean Sidewise to silence, listening for the rain Tiptoeing the trees through which she flees again— The presence that my soul adores yet fears, The Loveliness my eyes have never seen. [Drab-colored seed pods of the autumn hung] Drab-colored seed pods of the autumn hung, Like beggar's tatters, on the red-bud boughs: Around the old, old house there was no sound, No song or sound, save on the rotting shed, The dim old shed, a dove made plaintive moan. In rapt clairvoyance gray the shadows lay Around it seeing many things unseen Of mortal eyes, strange things now dead and gone, Ghosts of the sometime gladness dwelling there, Spectres of age and youth, and sorrows old, Older than all the oldness sleeping there 'Mid clemencies of days forever gone. [A poet's soul 's unconscious of its dreams] A poet's soul's unconscious of its dreams As is the night unconscious of its stars, As is the heaven of all its clouds and winds, And Earth, retentive Earth, of all its flowers. [The bright half moon, a boat pearl-white] The bright half moon, a boat pearl-white, Floats down the cloud-canals of night. [When earth forgets one flower that comes with spring] When earth forgets one flower that comes with spring, And heaven one star that beautifies the night, Shall I forget that song I heard her sing. [All night it rained. Now in the dawn] All night it rained. Now in the dawn The purple-berried cedars stand Weighed down with wet the sun strikes through. [I love to linger o'er the roseless rose] I love to linger o'er the roseless rose When hips are ripe and candle-flames they seem, Orange and red, lit in the Autumn's honor, Who softly goes, Her ruby crown upon her, Adown the ways where vines like banners stream. [The auroral scent of morning lilies blows] The auroral scent of morning lilies blows Mixed with nocturnal perfumes of the rose Around the Dawn whose state invades the sky Trailing wild raiment of sidereal dye, Holding her torch of spheric fire high. [As I went riding toward the sea] As I went riding toward the sea, By field and hill and flower and tree, The thickets parted and suddenly A satyr's face laughed out at me. [Clung o'er with cockle-burrs and thorny seeds] Clung o'er with cockle-burrs and thorny seeds, Sad Autumn dreamed among her feathering weeds. 1901–1905 [There was an old frog] There was an old frog Sat on a log In the light of the crescent moon, aboon, In the light of the pale new moon: And he said to the crescent, “My dear, look pleasant! I'm going to sing you a tune, real soon; I am going to sing you a tune.” [So let Noon lead me till at last she reaches] So let Noon lead me till at last she reaches That spot where Evening tarries brown Beneath the trees, through which the sunset bleaches; Deep in a wood of ancient oaks and beeches, Where I may lay me down, With all the loveliness that Nature teaches, And watch Night crown her with her starry crown. [Above the hills the sunset's rolled] Above the hills the sunset's rolled One long deep streak of lurid gold, [The bloodroot leaves of middle March] The bloodroot leaves of middle March Lift up their blooms, each one a torch Of creamy crystal in whose white The calyx is a golden light. [Croppings out of unmined gold] Croppings out of unmined gold, Of secret wealth no man hath told. [Moist, rocky places of the spring] Moist, rocky places of the spring, Rich with dark woodland loam, Where hosts of golden poppies cling And breaks the bloodroot's and the twinleaf's foam. The mossy hillside's bulging rocks O'er which the fragile white-heart flocks, Whose penciled leaves and shell-shaped blooms Seem fancies from the fairies' looms. [The hairy stems of the hepatica] The hairy stems of the hepatica, Beneath the wahoo-bush and leafing haw, Nod delicate as the heads of elfin maids Of fairy tales who haunt the forest glades; And bluets, like a Naiad's eyes adream, Assert their azure by the woodland stream; And, where the wind-flower braved the winds of March, The poppy lights its golden torch. Come dance, come flaunt yourselves, ye wild little wind-flowers of March! And, poppies, come light their way with the hollow gold of your torch! [Deep in the leaves' concealing green] Deep in the leaves' concealing green A wood-thrush flutes, The first thrush seen Or heard this spring, and straight, meseems, Its notes take on the attributes Of mythic fancies and of dreams— A faun goes piping o'er the roots And mosses, gliding through dim gleams And glooms, and while he glides he flutes, Though still unseen, 'Mid thorny berry and wild-bean. [The dewberries are blooming now] The dewberries are blooming now: The days are long; the nights are short; The dogwood blossom from its bough Drops snowy petals, heart by heart, Here where she laid 'gainst mine her brow When we did part. Soon where the dewberries' blossoms gleam The berries red will, ripening, glow; And if the dogwood by the stream Did ever bloom, no one will know, And she, too, seem a vanished dream Of long ago. The yellow star-flower shows its gold Among the trees, half hid in grass; Already do the leaves grow old; Already doth the springtime pass; And last year's leaf hath turned to mould, As love, alas! The crowfoot blossom lifts its eyes Of amber hue from 'round my feet; The bluet apes the Mayday skies With glances blue as they are sweet, Here where last spring we met with sighs, No more to meet. [Purple the hills stretch under purple mists] Purple the hills stretch under purple mists, A damson-frosted purple that persists Even in the valley, darkling there that lies— No bluer black hath night, no darker dyes. The low gray clouds, whose edges are thinned, And spun By the sun And the wind, How they swirl and curl And furl and unfurl Into lawny lengths of snow and pearl! Now feathering white as the moon-mists do, For the wind and the sun to tempest through, Now closing over, Cloud-cover on cover, Deep azure chasms of fringing blue. [Hark how the honey-throated thrush] Hark how the honey-throated thrush With notes of limpid harmony Scatters the noonday's liquid hush, Taking the woods with witchery. Hid in the foliage deeps of green He flutes his wildwood notes serene, Like some tree-spirit, lost, unseen. [The ground is strewn with the dead oak-bloom] The ground is strewn with the dead oak-bloom, Brown and withered as autumn broom: And there, in a hollow of the hills, Like a giant pearl in a giant hand, Is a white-washed hut where an old man tills A barren acre of barren land. An arid acre, that soon shall blow With wild-rose crimson and elder snow. [That little worm shall become a fly] That little worm shall become a fly, And sing and sting 'neath the summer sky; Or a gnat, like that which grows in the gall High on the oak leaf there—a ball That the elves shall loose and toss over all Merrily under the next new moon;— When it'll grow itself wings and a sting and a tune, Stinging and singing its way into June. [Invite my soul to rest awhile] Invite my soul to rest awhile And dream beneath their azure smile. [The smell of tannin in the ozoned air] The smell of tannin in the ozoned air Under the oaks when the woods are green, And the scent of the soil and moisture where The young leaves dangle and make a screen, Where the hiding wood-nymph combs her hair, Have breathed me full of the Faun again, And made me kin to the wind and rain. [The stealthy squirrel skips along] The stealthy squirrel skips along; The bush-bird lifts its twilight song; The great frog sounds his resonant gong At nightfall. The small wood-gnat, that stings and flies, And drowns itself for rage in your eyes, Sings and whines and thinly cries At nightfall. The hairy spiders, that crouch outside Their earth-bored lairs, now stealthily glide, Or spin great webs for the moths that hide Till nightfall. [Yesterday among the beeches, to-day among the oaks] Yesterday among the beeches, to-day among the oaks: Those with their emerald and gold, Their amber golds and grays, These with their blood-dark bronze, Translucent, frosty reds: The gold the Autumn dons, The blood her sad heart sheds, As slow she goes her ways; Sheds at each step, that cloaks Each pool that glimmers cold, Sunk in the woodland mould, 'Mid the oaks, of whose russets and reds Winds make their beds, Bowing their withered heads, That are old, so old, Where the Autumn cons, In her golds and grays, Her Book of Days. [The wind is rising and the leaves are blown] The wind is rising and the leaves are blown, Wild, swallow-high, reluctant still to fall, Swarming from hill to hill; and over all The sere, wild-sounding oaks a voice calls lone, As if the wood some ancient word were sighing, Some unintelligible word of beauty dying. [The dawn comes in clad all in hodden gray] The dawn comes in clad all in hodden gray, And, like a tattered cloak its wildness wears, The ragged rain sweeps stormily this way: The acorn, like a bullet, strikes the soil; And blown from its wild pod the milkweed's plume, Wan in the ghostly and the gusty gloom, Flares like a lamp hand-hollowed of trembling toil. November 12th, 1904. [Hylas, that pipe the little buds awake] Hylas, that pipe the little buds awake; The shrill hylodes, how they sing Before the wind-flower and the bloodroot shake Their twinkling stars frail in the locks of Spring. The rose-bruised blue of the bluebell's buds Will soon make gay the hem of her gown; Green as the green of the young oak woods With changing tints of mauve and brown. And soon will golden poppies cling In woodland places deep with loam, And we shall glimpse the feet of Spring— White in the twinleaf's flowers of foam. And all the hillside's rugged rocks She'll shower with shell-shaped white-heart blooms, Shaken from out her radiant locks, As down she comes through greenwood glooms. [Still are the forests barren of all buds] Still are the forests barren of all buds, And all the woods of wildflowers; but, behold! Within a week or less the invading hosts, Myriad and many as the stars of heaven, Shall utterly invade these woodland ways, When every foot of soil shall show and boast Its bud or blossom or balsam-beakéd leaf, Bragging of beauty to the passer-by, Beggared and bankrupt of all words to praise. [Come, let us forth and homage her] Come, let us forth and homage her, Clothed on with warmth and musk and myrrh, The indescribable odor wild that clings Around her like a garment: let us sing Songs to her, glad as grass and all the things Exulting in her presence—greening things And airy that have gotten them new wings: Come, let us forth and give our praise to Spring. [My mind's washed clean by the wind that brings] My mind's washed clean by the wind that brings The wild warm scent of the woods on its wings, The racy sweets of the bourgeonings Of flower and tree and brier that clings. My head I bare to the winds that blare, That blow from the purple heart of the cloud, Now low, now loud, From the heart of the cloud, like a giant's hair, Blown everywhere, Blue-black and low, Heavy with rain and the pearly glow Of sunlight gulfing its deeps with snow.— Blow, winds of spring! O blow, blow, blow! Caress my brow like fingers fair, Cool fingers touching my eyes and hair! Blow, spring winds, blow! O blow, blow, blow! Blow out of my soul all cark and care! And out of my heart, aye! out of my heart, despair! [The wind goes groping among the trees] The wind goes groping among the trees, Telling the bees Where the little buds open that no one sees. At intervals, as softly cool it blows, The wild-plum shows Its bee-swarm'd clusters 'twixt the wood's dark rows. [The sluggish snake now basks his uncoiled length] The sluggish snake now basks his uncoiled length Beside the windings of the water-course; With torpid beady eyes he lies and dreams Where warm the sunlight sleeps. Near by him claws Of some strange beast have marked the furrowed sand As with deep talonings of mighty rage Here on the wild road where it fords the stream. [Rocked by the winds of March the trees become] Rocked by the winds of March the trees become, Each one a maddened pendulum Swayed every way as if in time To some wild music, roaring rhyme Shouted from storm-tossed hill to hill, Amid the forests that are never still. [The gold-green blooms of the spicebush burn] The gold-green blooms of the spicebush burn Lighting the wood at every turn; Like the starry tufts of the sassafras, Whose fragrance thrills us as we pass, From out their patents of gold they spill A faint aroma that haunts the hill. [Placid and pure and clean the wild-phlox blooms] Placid and pure and clean the wild-phlox blooms Make glad the hillsides and deep-wooded banks Of wandering creeks. Beneath the old, gray beech The Mayapples, in myriad colonies, Advance-guards of the wildflowers' following hosts, Lift up their green-and-umber tents of leaves, Each unrolled tent tipped with its furled-up flag, Its pea-like bud, a knob of delicate green, Wherein the milk-white,—blazoned deep with gold,— Of its broad bloom, its banner's packed away. While at the wood's edge, at the turn o' the lane, A clear, a chilly crimson in its keys, Its million blooms, the maple fairly glows, Making a crystal blur of rosy gloom; Wherein the bluebird, like a sapphire closed In an enormous ruby, sits and sings; Upon his back and on his wayward wings The lapis-lazuli o' the April sky. April 5th, 1905. [Who is it knows] Who is it knows How the huckleberry grows, Blooms and blows?— Only the bird that sings and sings, Waving its wings, Saying, “Come see it where it swings! Ruddy green and amber rose, See, oh, see, In honor of Spring, Under this tree, See how they ring Their tiny bells, that cluster out, Silvery red, in a rosy rout.” [The liquid note of the thrush—what words can describe it] The liquid note of the thrush—what words can describe it? Above me now I hear it, dropping its globéd harmony, Golden-bubbled, crystalline clear, indescribably deep. Questioningly, answeringly its music falls, Notes of antiphonal gold, Full of youth and joy; A tree-spirit, seemingly, Voicing the innocence, the exuberance, the beauty of invisible, Inviolable things; wild myths that populate The world of the woods and streams. Pensively, hopefully now it pleads, Pleads for the dreams that haunt the hearts of the trees, The soul of the woodland— Dreams that it sees from its leafy height, Its breezy eyrie of green, Dreams that it sees and knows. And now for me its music, too, takes form, Visible, material form: And I seem to see— A presence, young with the youth that never ages, A Faun, a Spirit, slender and naked as Spring, Deep in the forest, approaching and now retreating, Blowing his flute of flowers, Gleaming, vanishing far in the verdurous glooms: A Spirit, happy with all that is happy, Communicated joy of all that is beauty, The wild, wild beauty it drew from the breasts of its mother, Its beautiful mother, Nature: A phantom supernal in loveliness, responsive and tender, Diaphanous, hyaline, translucently green and golden, Golden and green like the sound of a thrush's fluting: A form of light like that which shimmers and shades Under the day-deep boughs of the myriad beeches; Flitting, wavering now like a joy that dances, Silent, alone in the heart of the forest, Shimmering, glimmering here like the ray that stars the ripples, Sun-speared, flashing and fading on woodland waters, Falling, calling, foamy-lipped, like a Naiad, Lost in the leaves, the remotest deeps of the forest. Like the rain that tips the point of a poplar leaf, Trembling, a liquid star, to its twinkling fall, There it glances and glints, tinkling with silver the silence; There it hazes like heat that haunts the summer meadows, To whose kisses the wildflowers open their wondering and fragrant eyes: A glimmering form it leads me, musical ever of motion, From wildwood place to place, Retreating, advancing, luring from vista to vista, Far and far in the forest, the haunted deeps of the forest, To slay me there, perhaps, at last, At last with some last, long and lovelier note, Ringing as gold And deeper in magic than the myths of old. [The woodpecker! hear him, the redcapped] The woodpecker! hear him, the redcapped, Driving home his bill! Driving deliberately home his bill In the top limb of yonder tree. Swiftly, instantly, repeatedly it sounds, Resonant, distinct in the hollow wood.— What a prospect from such an outlook, What a world of limb and leaf, Ever moving, restless in its rest, Must that be from where he raps! That tallest giant of them all, That poplar there Where so unconcernedly he clings. What exultation of height! What intoxication of cloud and sky! Of wind and rapture in the blowing hair of the tree! Its rocking and nodding head!— Oh, that I too had wings! [The crawfish in his tower of ooze and clay] The crawfish in his tower of ooze and clay— What knows he of the day! Like some crabb'd misanthrope, Sans joy, sans hope, He sits within his pit Seeing no part of heaven, that azures over it. [Hag-tapers bow their heads i' the wind] Hag-tapers bow their heads i' the wind Like candles the witches bear; and, thinned As the moonlight is where a soul has sinned, Their blossoms look; and a flower red Blooms near them, shaped like a viper's head, A blood-blotched flower, like a symbol pinned To the breast of a gipsy dagger-dead, A damsel frail as a flower, oh! [Here where the twilight-colored trunks of trees] Here where the twilight-colored trunks of trees, Mottled with lichen, arch the twilight way, Where every crooked bough, swayed by the breeze, Now seems a knotted serpent, viperous gray, Because of one whose flat and horrible head, Reared in my woodland way, I crushed to-day, Fanging with poison its own side instead Of me advancing where unseen it lay. [Silvered with sun and rain the hills and vales] Silvered with sun and rain the hills and vales, O'er which a ragged rim of thunder trails, Show like some lunar landscape, pearl and frost, Crystaled with moon-dust and with star-drift crossed, Misted of silver and in silver lost. [The old tree, on which the man was hanged, sighed to itself] The old tree, on which the man was hanged, sighed to itself:— “Alas! why am I made an instrument of violent death? What have I done that I should be so punished? Made a participant in such a crime? I, whose life has evermore been one of peace and love: Whose mind has ever been employed with thoughts of mercy: Whose arms have always been stretched forth In kindness and protection, Sheltering the baby blossoms, The shy, the tender, the timid, The wild things of the woods, That love to nestle and lie at my mossy foot: I, whose limbs have unselfishly made, Year after year, A quiet cirque of coolth and comfort for the weary traveler, Hot and dusty from the road, Refreshing and restoring him with the soothing whisper, The lullabying lilt of my leaves: My verdurous bosom the home and haunt of unstudied song,— Birds and breezes rejoicing in its sheltering and maternal amplitude. Ah me! henceforward will Beauty and Love avoid me, Frequent visitors before! And Fear and Hate tenant in my boughs. The Dryad, who dwelt in my heart, Its beautiful and innocent inhabitant, is fled away. No more will the loveliness of things within me and about me Be as it was before. Accursed am I among trees! Accursed with the curse of murder! The contact and contamination of crime! Accursed with the stigma of slaughter! And accursed shall I ever remain through the crime of man, The most cruel, the most destructive, the most ferocious of all animals. Would now that some devastating bolt, Blindingly launched from yonder approaching cloud, Might fell me, thunderingly, to earth! Making me really that which I feel that I am become— A horrible thing, twisted and gnarled and black, Hideously crippled and scarred, Blasted and branded, as the brow of Cain, With withering, with elemental fire: Laying me prone; or leaving a towering and tortured trunk, A blackened shape, In the shuddering and rejecting forest— A trysting place for Murder, A roost for obscene things, Buzzards, carrion-crows, and owls.” [Where like an angry tyrant roars the sea] Where like an angry tyrant roars the sea, Pulling his yeasty beard, upon his throne Of iron crags; and where, like storm-lights strewn, The baleful stars redden tempestuously, I see him stand, blind Winter, all alone, Wild hair and beard, like snow, about him blown. [What boots it to keep saying] What boots it to keep saying That “life 's a hollow farce”? That “men are fools”? that “praying Helps not, nor doth remorse”? What boots it to keep dwelling On grief and sin and shame? The old, old story telling, “The end for all 's the same”? Who says that He, the Power That made us, as a rule Made fools with farce for dower, He only is the fool. [Until we meet again] Until we meet again Heaven keep thee gay! 'Neath skies of sun or rain, Or gold or gray, Heaven keep thee gay. Even as the sun-dial does, So let thy days Record no hour that was Not full of rays, Even as the sun-dial does. [Where bloomed the rose but yesterday] Where bloomed the rose but yesterday, Lamp upon lamp the hips burn red; And one by one leaves float away, Red leaves dropped in the wood-stream's bed. And now the spectres of the flowers Stream white across the stubble plains; Ghosts, shaken from their wind-swept bowers, Of weeds that tangle all the lanes. The partridge pipes; the blue-jays call; And caws the crow, that ribald bird: The woods turn gold; the acorns fall; And all day long the hunt is heard. [The climbing cricket clings] The climbing cricket clings, Moving its vibrant wings, To some green brier amid the fields turned sere: And to me, dreaming here, Its plaintive music seems An utterance of dreams And it itself lute of the dying Year. [My soul is sick of many things] My soul is sick of many things, But mainly of the word, The word of hope day never brings; That like some beautiful bird Above me and beyond me wings, Yet nevermore is heard. [Ah, not in vain] Ah, not in vain I see again The roses ruined of the rain: And in the mist The amethyst Of morning-glories wet and whist: The moonflower bent And torn and rent That yestereve was redolent. Back to my heart They bring the smart Of thoughts from which I can not part. Analogies Of memories That fall like rain on autumn leas. Sad memories all, Like rain, that fall On joy, a rose wrecked by the wall. [A thin fall rain] A thin fall rain, Whose spite again Whips wild the drizzled window-pane: Through which I see The blinded bee Beat down and ended utterly: The marigold And zinnia old Bent, wet, and wretched in the cold: And all the bowers Forlorn of flowers As are the hopes which once were ours. [Ephemeral gold] Ephemeral gold, Deciduous emerald, And crumbling ruby all the forests old Fling to the shining wind, deep-rolled Like some loud music through them: Majestic music, sad and manifold, The music of that ancient skald, October called, Who sits wild chanting to them. [The scarlet and the gold and bronze] The scarlet and the gold and bronze, The lemon, rose and gray, The splendors that October dons, Seen from this hilltop far away, Like some wild bugle blast, far blown,— The visible sound of something wild, unknown,— Crimsonly calling, shake my blood that thrills; Commanding me to follow Beyond the farthest hills; Exultantly to follow, Through flaming holt and hollow, Whereso their music wills; The trumpet-pealing fires Of trees and vines and briers, Whose leaves like notes are falling, The clarion color calling My heart beyond the hills. [Ochre-colored broom-sedge] Ochre-colored broom-sedge Yellowing desolate ways, Fields, the black thorns hedge, Bleached with sodden strays, Strays of leaves and flowers of dead, forgotten days. [In the forest by the rain-wild creeks] In the forest by the rain-wild creeks, Where the wet wind fumbles in the boughs, Rake the leaves away and, lo! the beaks Of a myriad germs, beneath, that house: Fingertips of gold and green and gray, Tongues and fingertips of countless flowers, Pointing us and telling us the way, Path up which the Springtime leads her Hours: At whose step awake the thousand pipes Of the hylas, ere our eye perceives In her cheeks the rose that morning stripes, In her hair the gold of all the eves. CATKINS I Misty are the far-off hills And misty are the near; Purple hazes dimly lie Veiling hill and field and sky, Marshes where the hylas cry, Like a myriad bills Piping, “Spring is here!” II A redbird flits, Then sings and sits And calls to his mate, “She is late! she is late! How long, how long must the woodland wait For its emerald plumes And its jewelled blooms?— She is late! she is late!” III Along the stream, A cloudy gleam, The pussy-willows, tufted white, Make of each tree a mighty light; Pearl and silver and glimmering gray They tassel the boughs of the willow way; And as they swing they seem to say, With mouths of bloom And warm perfume:— IV “Awake! awake! For young Spring's sake, O little brown bees in hive and brake! Awake! awake! For sweet Spring's sake, O butterflies whose wild wings ache With colors rare As flowers wear! And hither, hither, Before we wither! Oh, come to us, All amorous With honey for your mouths to buss. V “Hearken! hearken!— Last night we heard A wondrous word: When dusk did darken The rain and the wind sat in these boughs, As in a great and shadowy house. At first we deemed We only dreamed, And then it seemed We heard them whisper of things to be, The wind and the rain in the willow tree, A sweet, delicious conspiracy, To take the world with witchery: They talked of the fairy brotherhoods Of blooms and blossoms and leaves and buds, That ambushed under the winter mold And under the bark of the forest old: And they took our breath With the shibboleth, The secret word that casts off death, That word of life no man may guess; That wondrous word Which we then heard, That bids life rise Beneath the skies; Rise up and fill Far wood and hill With myriad hosts of loveliness, Invading beauty that love shall bless. VI “Then in our ears, Our woolly ears, Our little ears of willow bloom, Like wild perfume We seemed to hear dim woodland cheers Of hosts of flowers That soon would run Through fields and bowers, And to the sun Lift high their banners of blue and gold, And storm the ways of the woodland old. VII “Awake! awake! For young Spring's sake, O hylas sleeping in marsh and lake! Tune up your pipes and play, play, play! Tune, tune your reeds in ooze and clay, And pipe and sing Till everything Knows, gladly knows, Sowing the rose, The lily and rose, With her breast blown bare And the wind in her hair, And the birds around her everywhere, The Spring, the Spring, The young witch Spring, With lilt and laughter, and rain and ray, Comes swiftly, wildly up this way.” ANNOUNCEMENT. The night is loud with reeds of rain Rejoicing at my window-pane, And murmuring, “Spring comes again!” I hear the wind take up their song And on the sky's vibrating gong Beat out and roar it all night long. Then waters, where they pour their might In foam, halloo it down the night, From vale to vale and height to height. And I thank God that down the deep She comes, her ancient tryst to keep With Earth again who wakes from sleep: From death and sleep, that held her fast So long, pale cerements round her cast, Her penetential raiment vast. Now, Lazarus-like, within her grave She stirs, who hears the words that save, The Christ-like words of wind and wave. And, hearing, bids her soul prepare The germs of blossoms in her there To make her body sweet and fair; To meet in manifest audience The eyes of Spring, and reverence, With beauty, God in soul and sense. “WHEN SPRING COMES DOWN THE WILDWOOD WAY” When Spring comes down the wildwood way, A crocus in her ear, Sweet in her train, returned with May, The Love of Yester-year Will follow, carolling his lay, His lyric lay, Whose music she will hear. The crowfoot in the grass shall glow, And lamp his way with gold; The snowdrop toss its bells of snow, The bluebell's blue unfold, To glad the path that Love shall go, High-hearted go, As often in the days of old. The way he went when hope was keen, Was high in girl and boy: Before the sad world came between Their young hearts and their joy: Their hearts, that Love has still kept clean, Kept whole and clean, Through all the years' annoy. How long it seems until the spring! Until his heart shall speak To hers again, and make it sing, And with its great joy weak! When on her hand he'll place the ring, The wedding-ring, And kiss her mouth and cheek! HILDA OF THE HILLSIDE I Who is she, like the spring, who comes down From the hills to the smoke-huddled town? With her peach-petal face And her wildflower grace, Bringing sunshine and gladness to each sorry place?— Her cheeks are twin buds o' the brier, Mixed fervors of snow and of fire; Her lips are the red Of a rose that is wed To dew and aroma when dawn is o'erhead: Her eyes are twin bits o' the skies, Blue glimpses of Paradise; The strands of her hair Are sunlight and air— Herself is the argument that she is fair, This girl with the dawn in her eyes. II If Herrick had looked on her face His lyrics had learned a new grace: Her face is a book Where each laugh and each look, Each smile is a lyric, more sweet than a brook: Her words—they are birds that are heard Singing low where the roses are stirred,— The buds of her lips,— Whence each of them slips With music as soft as the fragrance that drips From a dew-dreaming bloom;— With their sound and perfume Making all my glad heart a love-haunted room. III But she—she knows nothing of love! She—she with the soul of a dove, Who dwells on the hills, Knowing naught of the ills Of the vales, of the hearts that with passion she fills: For whom all my soul Is a harp from which roll The songs that she hears not, the voice of my love, This girl who goes singing above. DAWN IN THE ALLEGHANIES The waters leap, The waters roar; And on the shore One sycamore Stands, towering hoar. The mountains heap Gaunt pines and crags That hoar-frost shags; And, pierced with snags, Like horns of stags, The water lags, The water drags, Where trees, like hags, Lean from the steep. The mist begins To swirl; then spins 'Mid outs and thins Of heights; and thins Where the torrent dins; And lost in sweep Of its whiteness deep The valleys sleep. Now morning strikes On wild rampikes Of forest spikes, And, down dim dykes Of dawn, like sheep, Scatters the mists, And amethysts With light, that twists, And rifts that run Azure with sun,— Wild-whirled and spun,— The foggy dun O' the heavens deep. Look! how they keep Majestic ward, Gigantic guard! And gaze, rock-browed, Through mist and cloud! Eternal, vast, As ages past! And seem to speak, With peak on peak, Of God! and see Eternity! MUSIC Oh, let me die in Music's arms, Clasped by some milder melody Than that which thrills with soft alarms The souls of Love and Ecstasy! Until the tired heart in me Is stilled of storms. So let me die, a slave of slaves, Within her train of lyric gold: Borne onward through her vasty caves Of harmony, that echo old With all our sad hearts hope and hold, And all life craves. Come with the pleasures dear to men In one long Triumph!—what are they Beside the one that sweeps us when Her harp she smites? and far away She bears us from the cares of day Unto her glen? Her hollow glen, where, like a star, That, in deep heaven, thrills and throbs, She sits, her wild harp heard afar, Strung with the gold of grief that sobs, And love that sighs, and, whispering, robs All life of jar. Beneath her all-compelling eye Our souls lie naked: nothing seems That is: but that which is not, by Her magic, lives: and all our dreams Are real, and, clothed in heavenly gleams, Smile, leaning nigh. The soul of love that can not die Breathes on our eyelids starry fire; And sorrow, with sweet lips that sigh, Kisses our lips; and faith, the choir Of all our hopes, its heart a lyre, Goes singing by. AUTUMN ETCHINGS I MORNING Her rain-kissed face is fresh as rain, Is cool and fresh as a rain-wet leaf; She glimmers at my window-pane, And all my grief Becomes a feeble rushlight, seen no more When the gold of her gown sweeps in my door. II FORENOON Great blurs of woodland waved with wind; Gray paths, down which October came, That now November's blasts have thinned And flecked with fiercer flame, Are her delight. She loves to lie Regarding with a gray-blue eye The far-off hills that hold the sky: And I—I lie and gaze with her Beyond the autumn woods and ways Into the hope of coming days, The spring that nothing shall deter, That puts my soul in unison With what's to do and what is done. III NOON Wild grapes that purple through Leaves that are golden; Brush-fires that pillar blue Woods, that, enfolden Deep in the haze of dreams, In resignation Give themselves up, it seems, To divination: Woods, that, ablaze with oak, That the crow flew in, Gaze through the brushwood smoke On their own ruin, And on the countenance of Death who stalks Amid their miles, While to himself he talks And smiles: Where, in their midst, Noon sits and holds Communion with their grays and golds, Transforming with her rays their golds and grays, And in my heart the memories of dead days. IV AFTERNOON Wrought-iron hues of blood and bronze, Like some wild dawn's, Make fierce each leafy spire Of blackberry brier, Where, through their thorny fire, She goes, the Afternoon, from wood to wood, From crest to oak-crowned crest Of the high hill-lands, where the Morning stood With rosy-ribboned breast. Along the hills she takes the tangled path Unto the quiet close of day, Musing on what a lovely death she hath— The unearthly golden beryl far away Banding the gradual west, Seen through cathedral columns of the pines And minster naves of woodlands arched with vines; The golden couch, spread of the setting sun, For her to lie, and me to gaze, upon. V EVENING The winds awake, And, whispering, shake The aster-flower whose doom is sealed; The sumach-bloom Bows down its plume; And,—blossom-Bayard of the field,— The chicory stout To the winds' wild rout Lifts up its ragged shield. Low in the west the Evening shows A ridge of rose; And, stepping Earthward from the hills, Where'er she goes The cricket wakes, and all the silence spills With reed-like music shaken from the weeds: She takes my hand And leads Softly my soul into the Fairyland, The wonder-world of gold and chrysolite, She builds there at the haunted edge of night. VI NIGHT Autumn woods the winds tramp down Sowing acorns left and right, Where, in rainy raiment, Night Tiptoes, rustling wild her gown Dripping in the moon's pale light, In the moonlight wan that hurries Trailing now a robe of cloud Now of glimmer, ghostly browed, Through the leaves whose wildness skurries, And whose tatters swirl and swarm Round her in her stormy starkness; She who takes my heart that leaps, That exults, and onward sweeps, Like a red leaf in the darkness And the tumult of the storm. WOOD-WAYS I O roads, O paths, O ways that lead Through woods where all the oak-trees bleed With autumn! and the frosty reds Of fallen leaves make whispering beds For winds to toss and turn upon,— Like restless Care that can not sleep,— Beneath whose rustling tatters wan The last wildflow'r is buried deep: One way of all I love to wend, That towards the golden sunset goes, A way, o'er which the red leaf blows, With an old gateway at its end, Where Summer, that my soul o'erflows, My summer of love, blooms like a wildwood rose. II O winter ways, when spears of ice Arm every bough! and in a vice Of iron frost the streams are held; When, where the deadened oak was felled For firewood, deep the snow and sleet,— Where lone the muffled woodsmen toiled,— Are trampled down by heavy feet, And network of the frost is spoiled, O road I love to take again!— While gray the heaven sleets or snows,— At whose far end, at twilight's close, Glimmers an oldtime window-pane, Where spring, that is my heart's repose, My spring of love, like a great fire glows. THE CHARCOAL-BURNER'S HUT Deep in a valley, green with ancient beech, And wandered through of one small, silent stream,— Whose bear-grassed banks bristled with brush and burr, Tick-trefoil and the thorny marigold, Bush-clover and the wahoo, hung with pods, And mass on mass of bugled jewelweed, Horsemint and doddered ragweed, dense, unkempt,— I came upon a charcoal-burner's hut, Abandoned and forgotten long ago; His hut and weedy pit, where once the wood Smouldered both day and night like some wild forge, A wildwood forge, glaring as wild-cat eyes. A mossy roof, black, fallen in decay, And rotting logs, exuding sickly mold And livid fungi, and the tottering wreck, Rude remnants, of a chimney, clay and sticks, Were all that now remained to say that once, In time not so remote, one labored here, Labored and lived, his world bound by these woods: A solitary soul whose life was toil, Toil, grimy and unlovely: sad, recluse, A life, perhaps, that here went out alone, Alone and unlamented. Lost forever, Haply, somewhere, in some far wilder spot, Far in the forest, lone as was his life, A grave, an isolated grave, may mark,— Tangled with cat-brier and the strawberry-bush,— The place he lies in; undistinguishable From the surrounding forest where the lynx Whines in the moonlight and the she-fox whelps. A life as some wood-fungus now forgotten: The Indian-pipe, or ghost-flower, here that rises And slowly rots away in autumn rains. Or, it may be, a comrade carved a line Of date and death on some old trunk of tree, Whose letters long ago th' erasing rust Of moss and gradual growth of drowsy years Slowly obliterated: or, may be, The rock, all rudely lettered, like his life, Set up above him by some kindly hand, A tree's great, grasping roots have overthrown, Where lichens long ago effaced his name. IN CLAY Here went a horse with heavy laboring stride Along the woodland side; Deep in the clay his iron hoof-marks show, Patient and slow, Where with his human burden yesterday He passed this way. Would that this wind that tramples 'round me here, Among the sad and sere Of winter-weary forests, were a steed,— Mighty indeed, And tameless as the tempest of its pace,— Upon whom man might place The boundless burden of his mortal cares, Life's griefs, despairs, And ruined dreams that bow the spirit so! And let him go Bearing them far from the sad world, ah me! Leaving it free As in that Age of Gold, of which men tell, When Earth was glad and gods came here to dwell. GRAY SKIES It is not well For me to dwell On what upon that day befell, On that dark day of fall befell; When through the landscape, bowed and bent, With Love and Death I slowly went, And wild rain swept the firmament. Ah, Love that sighed! Ah, Joy that died! And Heart that humbled all its pride; In vain that humbled all its pride! The roses ruin and rot away Upon your grave where grasses sway, And all is dim, and all is gray. SUNSET DREAMS The moth and beetle wing about The garden ways of other days; Above the hills, a fiery shout Of gold, the day dies slowly out, Like some wild blast a huntsman blows: And o'er the hills my Fancy goes, Following the sunset's golden call Unto a vine-hung garden wall, Where she awaits me in the gloom, Between the lily and the rose, With arms and lips of warm perfume, The Dream of Love my Fancy knows. The glow-worm and the firefly glow Among the ways of bygone days; A golden shaft shot from a bow Of silver, star and moon swing low Above the hills where twilight lies: And o'er the hills my Longing flies, Following the star's far, arrowed gold, Unto a gate where, as of old, She waits amid the rose and rue, With star-bright hair and night-dark eyes, The Dream, to whom my heart is true, My Dream of Love that never dies. MENDICANTS Bleak, in dark rags of clouds, the day begins, That passed so splendidly but yesterday Wrapped in magnificence of gold and gray. And poppy and rose. Now, burdened as with sins, Their wildness clad in fogs, like coats of skins, Tattered and streaked with rain, gaunt, clogged with clay, The mendicant Hours take their sombre way Westward o'er Earth, to which no sunray wins. Their splashing sandals ooze; their footsteps drip, Puddle and brim with moisture; their sad hair Is tagged with haggard drops, that with their eyes' Slow streams are blent; each sullen fingertip Rivers; while 'round them, in the drenchéd air, Wearies the wind of their perpetual sighs. WINTER RAIN Wild clouds roll up, slag-dark and slaty gray, And in the oaks the sere wind sobs and sighs, Weird as a word a man before he dies Mutters beneath his breath yet fears to say: The rain drives down; and by each forest way Each dead leaf drips, and murmurings arise As of fantastic footsteps,—one who flies, Whispering,—the dim eidolon of the day. Now is the wood a place where phantoms house: Around each tree wan ghosts of flowers crowd, And spectres of sweet weeds that once were fair, Rustling; and through the bleakness of bare boughs A voice is heard, now low, now stormy loud, As if the ghosts of all the leaves were there. MARINERS (Class Poem, Read June, 1886) A beardless crew we launched our little boat; Laughed at its lightness; joyed to see it float, Veer in the wind, and, with the freshening gale, Bend o'er the foaming prow the swollen sail. No fears were ours within that stanch-built barque; No fears were ours 'though all the west was dark, And overhead were unknown stars; the ring Of ocean sailless and no bird a-wing: Yet there was light; radiance that dimmed the stars Dancing like bubbles in Night's sapphire jars. We knew not what: only adown the skies A shape that led us, with sidereal eyes, Brow-bound and shod with elemental fire, Beckoning us onward like the god Desire. Brisk blew the breeze; and through the starry gloam, Flung from our prow, flew white the furrowed foam.— Long, long we sailed; and now have reached our goal. Come, let us rest us here and call the roll. How few we are! Alas, alas, how few! How many perished! Every storm that blew Swept from our deck or from our staggering mast Some well-loved comrade in the boiling vast. Wildly we saw them sink beneath our prow, Helpless to aid; pallid of face and brow, Lost in the foam we saw them sink or fade Beneath the tempest's rolling cannonade. They sank; but where they sank, above the wave A corposant danced, a flame that marked their grave; And o'er the flame, whereon were fixed our eyes, An albatross, huge in volcanic skies. They died; but not in vain their stubborn strife, The zeal that held them onward, great of life: They too are with us; they, in spite of death, Have reached here first. Upon our brows their breath Breathes softly, vaguely, sweetly as the breeze From isles of spice in summer-haunted seas. From palaces and pinnacles of mist The sunset builds in heaven's amethyst, Beyond yon headland where the billows break, Perhaps they beckon now; the winds that shake These tamarisks, that never bowed to storm, Haply are but their voices filled with charm Bidding us rest from labor; toil no more; Draw up our vessel on the happy shore; And of the lotus of content and peace, Growing far inland, eat, and never cease To dream the dreams that keep the heart still young, Hearing forever how the foam is flung Beneath the cliff; forgetting all life's care; Easing the soul of all its long despair. Let us forget how once within that barque, Like some swift eagle sweeping through the dark, We weighed the sun; we weighed the farthest stars; Traced the dim continents of fiery Mars; Measured the vapory planets whose long run Takes centuries to gird their glimmering sun: Let us forget how oft the crystal mountains Of the white moon we searched; and plumbed her fountains, That hale the waters of the æonian deep In ebb and flow, and in her power keep; Let us remember her but as a gem, A mighty pearl, placed in Night's anadem: Let us forget how once we pierced the flood, Fathomed its groves of coral, red as blood, Branching and blooming underneath our keel, Through which like birds the nautilus and eel, The rainbowed conch and irised fishes swept, And where the sea-snake like a long weed slept. Here let us dream our dreams: let Helen bare Her white breast for us; and let Dido share Her rich feast with us; or let Lalage Laugh in our eyes as once, all lovingly, She laughed for Flaccus. We are done with all The lusts of life! its loves are ours. Let fall The Catilines! the Cæsars! and in Gaul Their legions perish! And let Phillip's son In Ammon's desert die; and never a one Lead back to Greece of all his conquering line From gemmed Hydaspes. Here we set our shrine! Here on this headland templed of God's peaks, Where Beauty only to our worship speaks Her mighty truths, gazing beyond the shore Into the heart of God: her eyes a door Wherethrough we see the dreams, the mysteries, That grew to form in the Art that once was Greece: Making them live once more for us, the shapes That filled the woods, the mountains, and the capes Of Hellas: Dryad, Oread, and Faun; Naiad and Nereid, and all the hosts of Dawn.</field>
   </doc>
</add>