<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Stoddard, Richard Henry, 1825-1903</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Stoddard, Richard Henry, 1825-1903</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">stoddard richard henry 1825 1903</field>
      <field name="author_text">Stoddard, Richard Henry, 1825-1903</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1860's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ap/uvaGenText/tei/chap_AM1210.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240350</field>
      <field name="date_text">[1864]</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:440623</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The story of Little Red Riding Hood</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The story of Little Red Riding Hood</field>
      <field name="title_facet">story of little red riding hood</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">story of little red riding hood</field>
      <field name="title_text">The story of Little Red Riding Hood</field>
      <field name="year_display">[1864]</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1864</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1864</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440623&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440623&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Stoddard, Richard Henry, 1825-1903&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;stoddard richard henry 1825 1903&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The story of Little Red Riding Hood&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;story of little red riding hood&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;[1864]&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1864&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Stoddard, Richard Henry&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1825&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1903&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The story of Little Red Riding Hood&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;New York&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;James C. Gregory&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;[1864]&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3866181-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;cham1210&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The story of Little Red Riding Hood&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1996&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1996 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 34 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-AmPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE STORY OF LITTLE RED RIDING-HOOD. “Red Riding-Hood, the darling, The flower of fairy lore.”— L. E. L. I. Somewhere in merry England (The time was long ago), There lived a little maiden, Whose story you shall know. She came of simple people, Whose homely cottage stood, With a slip of garden near it, Against an ancient wood. Her father,—he made fagots, The firewood of the poor, While her mother sat a-spinning Beside the cottage door. There she lived, and there she grew, As the country children do; Eight years old, and fair as good, The little maid, Red Riding-Hood. II. They rose while she was sleeping, And her father trudged away, With his axe upon his shoulder, Before the break of day; Her mother scoured the platters, And set beside her bed A cup of sweetest honey, And the freshest crust of bread; Then went about her spinning As softly as she could, But the old wheel's endless humming Woke little Riding-Hood, Who rubbed her rosy eyelids, And started up in glee: “What, is it you, dear mother? I thought it was a bee!” “They should be bees, and busy, too, Who have a many drones like you.” She shook her head: “It isn't good To say such things of Riding-Hood.” III. She had an aged grandmother This pretty little may, Dwelling within the forest, A league or more away; Who, on her eighth sweet birthday, When leaves began to fall, Gave her a riding-habit, With a ruffled hood and all. And O, but it was bonny To see it on her head; Why, when she walked i' th' garden, The rose was not so red! And when the neighbors spied it, Like morning through the wood, They said to one another, “Here comes Red Riding-Hood.” Such the name the darling bore, From the scarlet hood she wore; For her christened name it stood— She was known as Riding-Hood. IV. “Rise up, rise up, my daughter,” One morn her mother said, “For you must go to Granny's, I hear she's sick abed; A pat of nice fresh butter Will do the poor soul good.” “And let me send my honey,” Said little Riding-Hood. The churn goes fast, and faster, The pat of butter's made, And with a pot of honey Is in a basket laid. The loving child is ready, Behold her where she stands, In her pretty riding-habit, The basket in her hands; Beneath the morning-glories That drape the cottage door, She lingers for a moment, To con her message o'er. “We heard that she was ailing, And I have brought her this; And father's very sorry, And mother sends a kiss.” Here she hears her mother say, “Daughter must n't stop to play.” And she answers, “I'll be good Or my name's not Riding-Hood.” V. Along the winding pathway The merry maiden went, So light her tripping footsteps The grass was hardly bent! 'Twas strung with silver dew-drops, With spider webs o'erspread, Like sheets of linen, bleaching For Mab, the fairy's, bed. At length she reached the forest, A still and dreamy place, Whose brooding shadows darkened The beauty of her face; Save where the morning struggled In long and golden lines. The narrow path was slippery With needles of the pines; Ferns grew along its borders, And vines were stretched across, And here were spotted toadstools, And there were beds of moss By bush, and brier, and bramble, She glided like a shade, Nor made the dry leaves rustle, Nor any thing afraid. The robins fed their young ones, The rabbits never knew The tripping of her footsteps From the dripping of the dew! But where the wood grew darker, So dense the roof o'erhead, Besides her pattering footfall There was a heavy tread, That made the dead leaves rattle, That crushed the tender flowers, That brushed the low-hung branches, And shook the dew in showers! Who was it stole behind her? What tracked her through the wood? It was a wolf that followed The helpless Riding-Hood! She turned her head and saw him, And stood stock still with fear, So fierce his eyes and cruel, And his sharp teeth so near! “I wonder will he kill me?” Thought little Riding-Hood; “He knows I never harmed him, And would not if I could.” “She'll make a dainty morsel,” He muttered in reply; “Shall I eat her where she's standing? Or wait till by and by?” While thus he was debating, But certain of his prey, She snatched her fallen basket, And hurried on her way. Where the tangled pathway wound; Past the trees that shut around; Through the thick and gloomy wood Went the wolf and Riding-Hood. VI. At last the sound of voices Was indistinctly heard; Or was it but the halloo Of some half-human bird? It was the fagot-makers, At work within the wood, About the path where wandered The wolf and Riding-Hood. The creature heard them talking, And slacked at once his pace; It would not do to chase her In such an open place: You would have thought to see him— “How could she be afraid! It is a good old house-dog That loves the little maid.” They met a fagot-maker, Who chopped a fallen bough: “Red Riding-Hood, good morning, Where are you going now?” She stopped, and swung her basket With pretty shame, and said: “I'm going, sir, to Granny's, For she is sick abed,” Meantime the wolf comes closer, To see how matters stand: He rubs his head against her, He tries to lick her hand! “Why, here's a wolf,” they shouted, And hastened at the sight: “I think it is the villain That stole my sheep last night.” “Upon my honor, gentlemen, I never in my life”— One raised his axe, with “Kill him!” Another drew his knife: “Pray don't! he mayn't be guilty,” Cried tender Riding-Hood; “I'm sure he didn't harm me, When I was in the wood.” “For your sake then we spare him, He owes his life to you; But if more sheep are missing, We'll all know what to do.” Back to their work they plodded, With many a look behind. “A thousand thanks, my lady,” The cunning creature whined: “I'll not forget your kindness, Indeed, you are too good; But now I must be going, Adieu, sweet Riding-Hood.” He trotted towards the forest, But soon came back and said: “The Grandmamma you spoke of, I think, is sick abed. Poor soul!”—he sighed for pity, “Where lives the good old dame?” “You see that littlè cottage, Whose windows are a-flame? With jessamines and woodbines The porch is covered o'er”— “And, pray, how do you enter?” “By tapping at the door, And Granny then will tell you (But you must hark to hear), That you must pull the latch-string; She'll say, ‘Come in, my dear.’” “Pull the string, and then you're in; Worldly wits are sure to win.” He took a short cut through the wood, Laughing at Red Riding-Hood. VII. Red Riding-Hood was troubled, Not knowing what he meant; And, glad that he had vanished, She wondered where he went. But brief the stay of sorrow In such a childish mind; A cloud the wind is chasing, That leaves no trace behind! The path led through a meadow, Where flowers so thickly grew You knew not which were thickest, The flowers, or the dew! They flaunted in the sunshine, They hid in shady nooks, They clambered through the grasses, They dipped along the brooks. “I'll gather some for Granny,” Said Riding-Hood anon, Stooping to save a blossom She nearly trod upon: She picked a lady-slipper, Was larger than her own; She stripped a royal rose-tree Of all the buds were blown: Handfuls of yellow cowslips, Whose cups are full of spots; And knots of frail sweet-purples, And dear forget-me-nots: The daisy, and the primrose, The rustic marigold— She heaped her little apron As full as it would hold! Then, tired with her sweet labor, She sat beneath a tree, To sort her dewy treasures, As busy as a bee. She made a pretty nosegay, Of posies white and red, To fill the earthen pitcher That stood by Granny's bed: She bound a bunch of violets, And lilies of the vale. With a rose that was the sweetheart Of the noble nightingale: She wove a wreath of purples In many a curious twine, With glossy leaves of ivy, And tendrils of the vine: And while her twinkling fingers Were braiding bud and flower, The lark, the morning's watchman, Was singing in his tower; High up above the meadow Where lay his grassy nest, Where slept the glassy river, No ripple on its breast: Where slid the snake, where burrowed The rabbit and the mole, And where the tiny field-mouse Was peeping from his hole! As she was idly watching Their labor and their play, A wasp, abroad for honey, Came buzzing on his way. He struck the trail of odor That floated in the air, And followed it as surely As does the hound the hare; Across the dewy meadow, And through a belt of wood, Until he reached the apron Of dear Red Riding-Hood, In which he darted sharply, So many and so fine The flowers whose cups he plundered, So sweet their honey-wine. Right well she knew the difference Between a wasp and bee; The humming-bee how thrifty— And what an idler, he! Yet, seeing God had made him, She killed him not, but said: “The thoughtless drone is hungry, And God would have him fed.” The wasp buzzed loud, and louder, As if he understood Her pity, and was thankful To good Red Riding-Hood! She rose that morn so early, Before the east was red, She quite forgot her breakfast Of honey and of bread: But just as she was starting, She heard her mother say: “Here's something for my darling To eat along the way.” She drew it from her pocket, And found it was a cake, Such as on merry Saints' Days Her mother used to bake. There came a hungry robin As she began to eat, The sugaréd crumbs to gather That fell about her feet. At first he pecked the furthest, And often stopped in fear, With many a trembling twitter; But soon he ventured near; For wherefore fear a Creature So gentle to the rest, Whose dress was like the morning That burned upon his breast? And Riding-Hood, who eyed him, As nigh her hand he stood,— She loved him that he buried The Children in the Wood! And as he pecked and twittered, “Eat, pretty bird,” said she; “There still will be a plenty For Granny and for me.” “Thanks,” the grateful robin cried; “Many thanks,” the wasp replied; Both together: “She is good, And we love Red Riding-Hood.” VIII. By this the child was rested, And her sweet task was done; So she arose light-hearted, And faced once more the sun, Which now had scaled the forest, Above the topmost trees: The birds were singing round her, And merrily hummed the bees. It was an ancient woman, Who stooped beside a brook, As if she searched for something: She had a weary look; Her hair with white was sprinkled, And her palsied hands she wrung: She seemed as old as Nature, That is so old—and young! “What do you look for, Goody?” Asked little Riding-Hood, Who stopped to watch the woman, And help her, if she could. “I gather water-cresses,” The feeble creature said; “A sorry trade to live by, It does not give me bread.” “'Tis hard the wasp and robin Should have their fill of food, And she be pinched with hunger,” Thought tender Riding-Hood, Who drew from out her pocket The fragment of her cake, Rejoicing she had saved it, For that poor woman's sake! “Here's something for you, Goody,” And she led her to a seat; “I'll pick your water-cresses, While you sit down and eat.” Along the glassy water She went a little space, Until she found a cluster That hid her happy face; The greenest, crispest, coolest, That drank the sun and rain: From this she heaped her apron, And hurried back again. The old dame smoothed her ringlets, “I thank you, Riding-Hood.” Stronger she looked, and younger, And more erect she stood. Then, “Meeting the green huntsman, Bear this,” she charged, “in mind: Give him my love, and tell him That game is in the wind.” “I'll take your message, Madam,” Red Riding-Hood replied, Whose little heart with wonder Was thumping at her side: Nor was her wonder lessened, When turning back she found No sign of that old woman In all the meadow round! The woman was a fairy, Forever young and fair; Her rags were robes of crystal, And like the light her hair! She waved her wand a moment, And crooned some magic words, The charm by which she governed The insects and the birds: The wasp and robin knew it, And flew obedient there; She whispered each his errand, And vanished in the air! Red Riding-Hood saw nothing, For all her looking back, Except the wasp and robin That followed on her track; Until, within a hollow, She found a stagnant lake, So stiff with scum no ripple Could o'er its surface break; And there was seen the huntsman, In green from top to toe; About his waist a bugle, And in his hand a bow! He stood so tall and stately, And not a word he said, But watched the birds in circles That wheeled above his head! “Good morning, Master Huntsman,” Said little Riding-Hood; “I met a strange old woman When I was through the wood, Who promised I should meet you, And said that I must mind And give her love, and tell you, ‘The game is in the wind.’” As when the wind is blowing, And trees are bowing round,— He nodded so, and stooping He listened at the ground: (What heard he?—distant voices, Or but the waters' flow?) He rose, and took an arrow, And bent his mighty bow! What did his strange silence mean? Who the huntsman clad in green? Lord of water, or of wood? It sorely puzzled Riding-Hood. IX. Her thoughts outran her footsteps, And wandered far and near, Till what at first was wonder, Was fast becoming fear. At last she saw the cottage, Whose windows shone afar, And flying to its garden, She found the gate ajar: She did not stop to close it, Her heart so gladly beat, Nor note along the gravel The marks of stealthy feet! (By shoon of man or woman Such prints were never made: Red Riding-Hood, my darling, I fear you are betrayed!) She crossed the patch of garden, She reached the rustic porch, Where many a scarlet creeper Did lift its fiery torch; Beneath the wedded woodbines And jessamines she stood, And spots of sun and shadow Were falling on her hood. “Rap! rap!”—her little knuckles Are tapping at the door; She hearkens, but for answer She hears her heart, no more! “Rap! tap! rap! tap!” still louder, She bends again her ear: “Who's there?” And she, “Red Riding—” A gruff “Come in, my dear.” She twitched the clicking latch-string, And pushing back the door, A streak of moted sunshine Was shivered on the floor; Then, heavily and harshly, The door swung to again, And the creaking of its hinges Was like a shriek of pain! Across the darkened chamber She stole in growing dread, Until she gained the bedside, Where, breathlessly, she said: “We heard that you were ailing, And I have brought you this: And father says he's sorry, And mother sends a kiss.” A voice beneath the bed-clothes, As gruff as gruff could be, Growled out, “Put down the basket, And come to bed to me.” She pulled aside the curtain, And buried in the bed There was a rumpled night-cap— But was it Granny's head? “How large your ears are, Granny.” “The more, my love, I hear.” “How large your eyes are, Granny.” “The more I see, my dear.” “How large your teeth are, Granny.” “So much the more I eat; And you, you silly chitling, Will make a morsel sweet! Prepare!” It was not Granny That sprang at Riding-Hood; It was the wolf that chased her When she was in the wood! Nor had he missed the darling, Who knelt to him in vain, But for the wasp that stung him, Until he howled with pain! And the robin at the window, Another watchman near,— He flew to the green huntsman, And twittered in his ear, “Red Riding-Hood's in danger,” And by his magic art He shot a mighty arrow, That cleft the monster's heart! Red Riding-Hood, the darling, So strangely snatched from death, She laughed and cried together— Was all things in a breath! But who came now? 'Twas Granny, Whose turn of illness past, Had been to see a neighbor, And had returned at last! “No need to tell the story, I know it all by this.” Twas “Granny” then, and “Sweetest,” And many a hug and kiss! They kissed and smiled, but tears would rise In sudden drops to Granny's eyes: “Such peril, and to one so good!” “The wolf is dead!” said Riding-Hood.</field>
   </doc>
</add>