<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Thompson, Maurice, 1844-1901</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Thompson, Maurice, 1844-1901</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">thompson maurice 1844 1901</field>
      <field name="author_text">Thompson, Maurice, 1844-1901</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1890's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ap/uvaGenText/tei/chap_AM0755.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240350</field>
      <field name="date_text">1892</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:440194</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Poems by Maurice Thompson</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Poems by Maurice Thompson</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poems by maurice thompson</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poems by maurice thompson</field>
      <field name="title_text">Poems by Maurice Thompson</field>
      <field name="year_display">1892</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1892</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1892</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440194&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440194&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Thompson, Maurice, 1844-1901&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;thompson maurice 1844 1901&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Poems by Maurice Thompson&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poems by maurice thompson&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1892&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1892&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Thompson, Maurice&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1844&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1901&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poems by Maurice Thompson&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Boston, New York&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Houghton, Mifflin and Company&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;The Riverside Press&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1892&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3865791-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;cham0755&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poems by Maurice Thompson&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1996&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1996 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 217 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Introductory matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-AmPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TO MY WIFE Songs of a mocking-bird Translated carefully, Golden note by golden word; Th' original melody Imitated phrase by phrase, As heard in dewy dawn-lit ways Of Freedom's solitudes Down by the sea in the springtime woods. Read them and heed them, As if you heard Prophecy out of the throat of a bird. IN CAPTIVITY. You ask me why I long to fly Out from your palace to the dreamy woods And the summer solitudes, Why I pine In this cage of mine, Why I fret, Why I set All manner of querulous echoes fluttering forth From the cold North And wandering Southward with beseeching pain In every strain. Ask me not, Task me not With such vain questions, but fling wide the door, And hinder me no more; Give back my wings to me, And the wild currents of my liberty! I pant, I faint; I die For the trees so high And the broad fields of luscious cane And the grassy plain And the red tiled villages so old and dull, Where (through the unkempt gardens rung) The timbre of the Creole tongue Makes every close so beautiful. Oh, if you please, Give me release! Open the gate Of this cage of Fate And let me mount the south wind and go down To Bay Saint Louis town, Where the brown bees hum In amber mists of pollen and perfume; And the roses gush abloom! There in the oleander groves, With drooping wings my dear mate moves And wonders why I stay So long, so long away, While the spring in fervid prime Has waxed to nesting time, And the air once more, in pungent ecstasy, Whirls the wasp and butterfly, Flings the orange petals high, And wrings a racy thrill from every tree! My memory turns To a place of vines and ferns And a cabin daubed with clay, Where many a day And many a sweet night long, In the old fig-tree and the scuppernong, I made the whole world wonder at my song. There the restless air Flung bubbling waves of freshness to and fro, Where The great japonica blossoms gleamed like snow, While from the cabin's eaves And from the waxen leaves The long gray moss fell down, Trailing like a gown. The cabin was a home Where naught but peace and happiness could come: The floor was earth, Well drained and cool, with loamy odor fine, And on its hearth Burned cedar boughs and knots of resinous pine That filled the place with tender, balmy heat, When the stout housewife broiled the juicy meat And brewed the coffee bright and clear as wine. There was a path down to a broad bayou, Whose waters blue The master of the cabin loved to sail, In breeze or gale, And overhead The huge arms of an ancient live-oak spread On high Between the roof-rib and the violet sky. A rout Of noisy, wild, black children, in and out, Ran and tumbled, leaped and sang, Till the brakes and thickets rang With the joy Of girl and boy, Who feel (and yet know not) what perfect bliss The careless way of utter freedom is. In the dusk of eve I heard (Sweeter than voice of any singing bird, Or strain of flute, or breathing of hautbois) The ditties in patois Warbled by two voices rich and deep, When the brood of children had been lulled to sleep, And man and wife sat by the cabin door, With the rose-vine drooping o'er, And the leaf-sounds creeping in With a rippling soft and thin. Ho! A banjo! Never was other music quite so good For the night and the solitude, And the fragrant, fruity silence of a Southern wood, And the black man's humble lot, With its curves of simple thought, Rounded to such rich fragments of conceit As only nature's genius may complete. Meantime, steadily, In the night-light vague and high, Angles of water-fowl winnowed the purple sky, Clanging their trumpet-notes As if from brazen throats, And seeming to fan the star-dust with their wings, And the breeze was like a flute, (A Pan-flute in the reeds) blown by the lips hirsute Of the jovial god who loves to be where the humblest minstrel sings. Love-music and love-song, Half-heathen and half-Christian, racy, strong, Vibrant with joy, flooded with humor droll, And rich with yearnings of the human soul, Washed round and over me And my sweet mate, brooding silently, On her nest in the old fig tree— Oh! Open the gate and let me go! Elusive hints And wavering tints Of citron blooms, And orange foliage and the soft perfumes Of violet and acacia come to me On some stray current, and I hear the sea Foaming and warm, After a storm And a rain, Softening down to sleep and dreams again, With the pelicans a-wing, And the white gulls hovering, And the great globe caught in the balmy palms of Spring! I long to be once more, On the warm Gulf-shore, In the dark magnolia foliage hidden quite, With the foam-capped waves in sight, And the vessels, wing by wing, Gleaming and wavering On the far horizon line, And the sun, right overhead, Flaring red, And flooding with flame divine The deep blue hollow of the sky, And gilding the vagrant gulf-caps gloriously. Oh, the shimmer and the sheen On the bay and the myrtle green! Oh, the keen bouquet From the wax-berry fruit! Oh, wafts that stray O'er vines all wine from top to root! Oh, the dull red gold in the lemon-tree! Oh, open the cage and let me go! Free me or I die, Give me sweet liberty, Whose every pulse was mine so long ago, Down by the sea. I feel—I feel so faint, my heart beats low, My throat is dry and harsh— Oh, give me back my thicket by the marsh! Let me see the herons wade In the watery glade, And let me see the water-fowl go by Glimmering against the sky. Fainter, fainter—so, My life-stream sinks—runs low. Oh! Oh! Open the cage and let me go, Floating, dreaming, reveling, dying, down To my mate, my queen, my love In the fragrant, drowsy grove Beyond the flowery closes of Bay Saint Louis town. TO AN ENGLISH NIGHTINGALE. Hear! Hear! Oh, will you hear? Reed-notes clear, (Fluted in flowery, May-drowsed solitudes, Filtered through sun-steeped woods) A challenge hurled To all the singing world! I, the mocking bird, Am stirred With song's wild rapture; and the prophet's mood Grows stronger in me with each freer breath Of balm-buds sweet as meth; I am no singer rude; Here, drink my melody, spiced with things as good As made the bragget that old Chaucer brewed. Or if Villon You dote upon, I have his note and more, And Ronsard's best in store, Caught from a gay garçon Who sang them clear and strong, On Bayou Teche, With a Creole dash In his voice and the brim of the hat he wore! What cheer! What cheer! That is the cardinal grosbeak's way, With his sooty face and his coat so red; Too shrill, too red, too loud and gay (Top-knotted like a jay), Too crude for the critical eye and ear! In a wild plum-thicket of Tennessee He flung a challenge out to me, And, as Marsyas, easily Beaten and flayed alive was he. Cheer! Cheer! What cheer! Oh, all the world shall be glad to hear! And the nightingale Shall fail When I burst forth with my freedom-song So rich and strong! Oh! Ho! That 's a brown thrush In the underbrush. Conceited, self-conscious, inclined to gush, His is a voice that will not wear; Faulty timbre and volume weak, He wrings from his beak A spiral squeak That bores like a gimlet through the air! And the catbird, too, With its feline mew, Is only fit for the springe and the snare! I like The shrike, Because, with a thorn for a guillotine, He does his work so well and clean, A critic keen— A practical bird, Whose common sense Must be immense, For, tell me, who has ever heard Of such a thing As a loggerhead shrike that tried to sing? Hear! See! Oh, see! What do you think of me? Do I sing by rote, Or by note? Have I a parrot's echo-throat? Oh no! I caught my strains From Nature's freshest veins. Where blows The Cherokee rose Amidst Floridian hills, a slave I heard Halloo across a green tobacco field, And sing as gleeful as a brook or bird, The whiles a heavy hoe his hand did wield; I mixed his tune With the heat of June, And sang it And rang it By the slow Aucilla And the deep Sattilla In groves of palm and pine by tropic breezes stirred, And all the world has heard. Mine is the voice of Spring, My home is the land of the new, And every note I sing Is fresh as the morning dew; For I am Freedom's bird Whom the Pilgrim Fathers heard, In their dreams of liberty, Calling them to the dark wild woods across the Western sea! Not a mere mimic I, That is a courtly lie To give precedence to the nightingale Bred in a classic vale, Shadowed by ruins old and dim. Give me a tilt at him! Prestige of fame? Romance of ages in his name? What care I! That bird shall die And lie My countless list of slain among, On the flowery field of song! He A match for me! No more than a wren or a chickadee! Mine is the voice of the young and strong, Mine the soul of the brave and the free! But I can pipe the oldest runes And trill the rarest tunes Of every tongue in which song's perfume is. Each swell I know, Each quaver low, The precious rhymes and rhythmic ecstasies Dreamed of by master-bards long dead And buried; And in my treasure The lightest measure, Rondeau, ballade, or virelay, To music set, Can match the vagabond troubadour's mandore fret for fret, And in a key more gay My triolet! And when night's vast and shadowy urn Overbrims with dreams I stir the vales of sleep with my nocturne; Slowly, tenderly Outflow its rippling streams To blend with Night's still sea of mystery; The pungent savor of the dewy buds, The coolness and the languor of old woods, And the slow murmur of the darkling rills My art distills Into a subtle philter, wild, intense, Of tenuous melody And slumbrous harmony, Blown round the dusky hills, Through fragrant fruity tropic thickets dense, Lingering and lapsing on, And lost before the dawn! Higher! Higher! I aspire To Freedom's fullest note; The vigor of waxing birdhood thrills my throat; Morn's wide horizon, rimmed with fervid fire, Broadens my hope And sets far limitations to the scope Of my desire! Cage me not! Enrage me not! Confine me to no purfled garden-plot: My song must grow, as grows the plant or tree, Out of the sun, and earth, and winds of Liberty! Upon no vast Dead past I turn my eyes; But every budding moment's blossom I forecast, And take each day's new melodies by surprise. I leap to meet fresh weather, And feel through every feather The first delicious foretaste of a change; I test the range Of Nature's every franchise, every tether! Dream on, O nightingale! Old things shall fade and fail, And the glory of the past shall not avail Against the Future, all-encompassing, Whose prophet and whose poet I would be, Whose promise and whose meaning I shall see, Whose fires shall flame in every note I sing! TO AN ENGLISH SKYLARK. Oh, How I long to go, On a seaward-blowing breeze, To the garden of the seas— To brave King Arthur's land, To that fair island Alfred made so free, To the haunt of chivalry, Where master-birds sang (in the days of song) So long And strong! Oh let me dwell a space by Avon's tide, Or hide In some old grove, where still a note may linger Of Herrick's flute, Of Sidney's lute, Or of some precious rondel voiced by a forgotten singer. Hark! Even now I hear a lark, The lark of England's ripe and mellow story, The lark of England's fallow fields of glory, Springing, Singing, Far and high in heaven's remotest blue, His wings still cool with dew, His voice (of which one song-god fair and young A lyric of immortal fervor sung) Still firm and true, Still rich with exultation, rising higher, And brimming with desire, To fill ethereal vastness with its fire; Forgetting love and sympathy and that law Of human harmony And rhythmic destiny, Which darkly through a glass the seers and prophets saw! O bird, Whom gods and heroes heard Sing in the far dim twilight hours of Time, Whose rapture stirred Through many a new sweet rhyme Whilst thou didst rise Into the skies To purify thy song in empyrean fire! Say where In upper air Dost hope to find fulfillment of thy dream? On what far peak seest thou a morning-gleam? Why shall the stars still blind thee unaware? Why needst thou mount to sing? Why seek the sun's fierce-tempered glow and glare? Why shall a soulless impulse prompt thy wing? Why are thy meadows and thy groves bereft Of Freedom's inspiration, and so left To silence in mid-spring? O lark! I mark, Since Shelley died, thy wings have somewhat failed. A precious note has faded from thy hymn, Thy lyric fire has smouldered low and dim! Nor ever have thy cloud-wrapt strains availed Against the will of tyrants and the dark, Strong doors of prisons grim, And shackles manifold, And dungeons cold, Wherein sweet Freedom lies With hopeless longing in her starry eyes And lifeless languor on her splendid wings! I hold This truth as gold: The grandest life is lowliest; he who sings To fill the highest purpose need not soar Above the lintel of the peasant's door, And must not hunger for the praise of kings, Or quench his thirst at too ethereal springs. As for me My life is liberty, And close to earth's bloom-scented, fragrant floor I gather more and more The larger elements, The fine suggestions of Time's last events; I strive to know Whither all currents flow; I sing On branches that the newest breezes swing; I overreach The limit of the present, day by day; I teach By shrewd anticipation, and foresay What wider life is coming, What joys are humming, Like Hybla's bees, around the Future's comb; My home Is where all wind-tides and all perfumes meet; Cool and clean and sweet The young leaves rustle round my sensitive feet, Whilst my enraptured tongue Rolls under it Morsels of all the songs the world's best bards have sung! Lo! Homer's strength is mine, And Sappho's fire divine. And old Anacreon's flask of purple wine Stains every note Blown from the silvery labyrinth of my charmëd throat! And yet the past Has nothing in it glorious as the vast Hope that the future holds, Of life whose flame enfolds The final focal thought— The meed for which the grandest souls from Time's first dawn have wrought. Erewhile I lived Where Liberty pined and grieved, Under the sunniest of all sunny skies, In a rich-fruited, dreamy, slumbrous paradise; Low And slow The tide of human sympathy did ebb and flow. At length, one day, I heard a bloodhound bay; The swamps were Freedom's sanctuary then; Year after year I sang the slave to cheer, And sang to fire the hearts of earnest, freeborn men, Until the new day broke, With the lifting of the yoke, And in broad floods of sudden light divine, I saw the slave to manhood's summit rise, His vision set on farthest destinies, And the slave cabin like a palace shine. Oh, what a bliss This love of Freedom is! And what delight To feel, by day and night, Its ecstasy run deeper in my blood While life's strong tide swells toward its highest flood! Not in the sky Where wastes of grandeur lie, May genius find wherewith to slake its thirst; The rainbow is not first On Beauty's list, Nor is the enchantment of heaven's highest mist The master maker's aim! The lowliest hearth-stone flame Is worthier of worship than the sun! The patter of bare brown feet that dance and run With childish grace on the roughest cabin floor, And the poor mother's happy smile, are more Than starry hosts And lofty ghosts And awful phantoms born of overwrought And soulless travail on the heights of thought! Come down, O Lark, to earth, And give a new song birth— The song of life that grants its sweets to all, In hut and lofty hall; Forsake the sky, And sky-born melody; Fill thy meadow and thy grove With a strain of human love— With a wide strong pulse of music for the waiting ears of men, Who, to be born again, And live the life of freedom that I live, More than their lives would give; Yea, Would slay, And heap vast hecatombs, and flood The world with blood, And jar Heaven with the thunder, And the wonder And the awful weltering whirlwind of the storm of war! Oh, ere it is too late, Take heed, and contemplate What tempests sleep, That yet will wake and leap Across thy starry fields and blot them out, And drown thy voice in their uproarious shout! Thou art too high; No longing ear or eye May follow thee, nor is thy sweetest note Echoed by mortal throat; But ever it goes forth with none to hear And none to catch its cheer! Come sit beside me now, Here on my orange-bough; Forsake the legendary lights, Forget the old hereditary heights, And we will pipe one lusty score together Wing by wing, In this land of spring, While all the world comes out to feel the weather Throb with the fire of Freedom as we sing! BEFORE SUNRISE. Mid foliage green and gold, And bloom-sprays manifold, I feel The fragrance of eternal freshness steal Forth from the rising day, And far away, Like the murmuring of a stream, Or a lute-chord in a dream, On the horizon stirs The rich and rapturous anthem of the Future's choristers. How it flows And grows! On its notes What triumph floats! Before it earth is gladdened and the sea is like a rose. The dawn Is coming on— Sweeter, Fleeter, In rhythms and rhymes and ripples flow the rays. The high, Blue, boundless, splendid sky Flares like a rimpled blaze Of sympathy divine. A rare Bouquet upon the air, As if of mellow wine Out of old flagons bursting, Sets the whole world wildly thirsting. The ships leap On the fragrant breezy deep, And the broad fields are billowy with grains. The great mills roar; Earth's veins of wealth outpour, And tireless engines pierce the hills and crash across the plains. Hurled Around the world, The lightning-bolts of man's best words to man Burn chains in two, Turn old things new; And, flung back from the trumpets in the van To the dull, listless ear Of the straggler in the rear, Come precious notes blown on the dewy rim Of the morning cool and dim. Hist! Ere the strain is whist, A voice, out of the dawn's vague, rosy mist: Pure as God's highest fire The worker's golden hire; And the home he makes with it, And the peace he takes with it To wife and children, are reward as fair As soul can compass or as love can bear. O brothers all! come near And hear A bird's Melodious dreaming set to words, And flung The spring's new leaves and tender buds among, For very joy of life, and hope, and love, In a world made broad enough For all God's creatures to be merry in, With joyous clash and din, And yet too small For any greed at all! Lo! deep and sure Is cut this truth in heaven's book of gold: Out of one mother in the garden old Were born the rich and poor. O ditcher in the mire! O stoker by the fire, And driver on the engine flying far, And brakeman on the car! O moulder, strong and grim! O longshoreman, and open-hearted tar, And pilot, tough and true! O miner in the coal-shaft damp and dim! O factory girl with eyes serenely blue, And cheerful matron washing clothes for hire! O all who work and suffer and aspire! Give ear! Look up, and hear And make thine own This song, out of the future blown So keen and clear:— O pure of heart and faithful, hand in hand, The strong, the weak, the great and small shall stand Upright and free in Freedom's favored land, And know That howso blow The winds of chance and change, Onward and upward every step shall go, And farther and freer every soul shall range! How good This universal bond of brotherhood, And all this wide, Strong, equal-flowing tide Of human love and human charity Foaming and heat-flushed as the rosy flood of some deep tropic sea! No? Not so?— As I swing And sing, I hear a myriad voices answer mine, From the oak woods and the pine, From the seas and from the lakes, From the brakes, From the cities and the shops, From the mines and the mountain-tops, From field and fold, Out of hot Southern marsh and Northern prairie cold, All murmuring: “We are poor; How long shall we endure This burden that we bear And the iron chains we wear? What is freedom but a name? What lot have we but poverty,—but shame? Are we not slaves and worse? Life is to us a bitter, burning curse!” O brothers, though you grope For the lowest rung of hope; O sisters, though you weep In darkness doubly deep, And cry From out foul pits of deepest misery, Or lie Dying in poverty, Yet see on lofty places Broad splendors and grand dreams Flashing from fervent eyes and godlike faces, Whereon the favor of Heaven divinely beams, Envy not, Nor curse your lot; For lo! the best of all God's gifts on you shall fall, And your hearts shall overbrim With ecstatic praise to Him! Yea, Deny it as you may, The dawn Is coming on, And the heights must feel the glow Before the valleys low; But the great midday Will strike The peaks and vales alike And they Who in life's hollows stay Shall feel the heat divine, When the strong noon sun shall shine At the zenith clear and high Of a just and liberal sky! In some manger cold, In some hovel mean and lone That the beasts would scorn to hold, Laughs the babe that shall be king, Whilst on a blazing throne Sits an abject, hopeless thing Silent and shivering! O poor! God's promises are sure; High As the starry sky Is your children's destiny; And broad And giant-waved and tempest-bearing, like the sea, Is the flood That shall come roaring, leaping, Over earth and sweeping The horses, chariots, hosts and homes, banners and citadel Of earth's tyrants into hell! O king! O lord! O usurer! O rich man's heart that no heart's cry can stir! What gold may bar the path Of the storm-flood and the whirlwind of God's wrath? What ships with iron mail, What steel-girt fortress, what hired army strong, Intrenched in wrong, With bristling guns and bayonets shall avail Against the crushing missiles of God's vengeance sent Out of the raging, rent, and foaming firmament? It is sweet, sweet, sweet, (I hear a million voices in unison repeat) This vengeance that is coming on the world, When the lofty shall lie low And the blood of kings shall flow In rivers round the thrones in fragments hurled; When the rich shall writhe and groan, Starving in deserts lone, When the palaces shall fall On the lords and ladies all, And pestilence shall stalk Where the money-lenders walk, And all the heavenly blue shall be a bloody pall. Peace! Cease! Such thoughts as these Send all their harshness hissing through my song And do my voice irreparable wrong. Blown clear, As glass through fire, Let breath of love grow sweeter year by year; Blown farther, higher, The bugle-call of Hope still guide us on, Until at last The night is past, And, rushing to the zenith from the dawn, We see the sun pour light of life on all, And hear a voice out of near heaven fall, Saying to those who in the caves and lonely hollows dwell: “Come forth, I am thy God, and all is well!” Ah, well! All well! In greening grove and dell Hear how my song of love goes ringing on! I am the prophet true, My words are fresh as dew, And lo! I say that it is morning time! No more the darkness and the hideous rime Of tyranny Shall compass land and sea; But, flaming o'er the world, God's glorious flag of peace shall be unfurled, And God's sweet law of liberty shall make all nations free! TO PROVENCE. Provence, where love and rhyme Sweetened one throb of time; Provence, whose voice is dead, Whose rose-tree vanishëd; Provence, old broken broc, Whose melodious Langue d'oc, Like sweet wine spilled and gone, Has left a fragrance ever lingering on; Whose nightingale finds no new song to sing,— I, a wild bird upon the outer rim Of a young choir, this sunrise carol fling Across thine ashes and thy ruins dim! Provence, This new song in my mouth Is of the younger South, Bright with the dawn of Freedom's renaissance, The South that has no care For the sad, grim cavalier, Dreaming of flaunting flag and crashing lance, And all unmindful of the day and year Whereon the world took leave of old romance. The South whose gaze is cast No more upon the past, But whose bright eyes the skies of promise sweep, Whose feet in paths of progress swiftly leap; And whose fresh thoughts, like cheerful rivers run, Through odorous ways to meet the morning sun! Gone is thy troubadour, Gone the soft clamor of thy cour d'amour, Rondeau, ballade, chanson; And the plaudits that they won Echo no more along the sheeny Rhone. All desolate! And why is this? Where is that splendid thing That leaped from thee on many-colored wing? Thou lifeless chrysalis! Remembered as a dream, Thy soft song glories seem To hover on Time's outmost purple bound; Thy hautbois and guitar— They touch us with the merest film of sound! Provence, Wafts of thy gaie science Still lightly pass, whereto we do not know, Like some frail, fine perfume, From a paradise of bloom Fallen to golden dust five hundred years ago! Thou art the old, dead South, Given over unto drouth; Given over unto memory, unto dust, Unto mildew, unto must, With a false smack of chivalry in thy mouth, Mumbling, in false pride, thy miserable crust! My South, too, was dead, And on her corse the ghoul of slavery fed; But the resurrection came, And a new life leaped, like flame, In every breast! Oh, it was joy to see The slave ride down the lists of Liberty, With shining shield and leveled lance in rest, His swart face lifted high, His eyes on destiny, While Lincoln's hand erased the inscription old Of the nation's palimpsest, And wrote thereon, in words of fire and gold, Freedom, from North to South, from East to West! Ah! what was dust Is dew! And what was rust Is new! The breath of death is gone, And life goes pouring on In a bright flood. No more The cannon's roar, And the blue sky is tinged no more with blood, Whilst from the mountains to the shining sea, The peace of morning evermore shall be! Provence, turn, turn away, From thy long yesterday, And see how fair to-morrow's promise shines! What is the past but death? How fresh the Future's breath! Awake. 'T is morn. Thy orchards and thy vines Are rich with bloom, The mistral throbs ecstatic with perfume, And fans to flame thine ashes with its wings! Lo, the Republic makes Life out of death, and takes Even ruin captive with the song it sings! TO SAPPHO. Note.—The italicized parts of this poem are translations of the Fragments of Sappho, and I have thought to weave them in as echoes, in the true mocking bird manner. Up from the Caribbean The wind comes like a pæan, As on my fragrant orange-bough I swing, Dreaming, and wondering, And piping Sapphic fragments o'er and o'er. Along the shore The surf foams madly and the breakers roar. Strange odors from afar, Spice, amber, nard, and tar, And Lesbian roses grown in Mitylene, And violet breath, and waft of myrtle green, Steep me in visions passionate and wild, Of love, all undefiled, Whereby was Sappho's bright Rose garden of delight, Flooded with starry splendors of old night! A bower of June, With morning freshness lingering after noon Upon the petals of the passion-rose; All round through apple boughs the cool air blows, Shaking soft slumber down the dusky leaves, Where still the subtle violet-weaver weaves! Eden of Love's own choice, Haunted of Love's own voice, Thy ways I could not take— Nay, not for Sappho's sake, And leave my orange grove And the fresh promise of the land I love! Liberty, Wild liberty, Not license, give to me! Give me the glory of what is to come— Fill me with prophecy—the mighty hum Of swarming years and wonders yet to be! And still, O Sappho! still I turn and sigh That all but these stray notes of all thy songs should die; That these chance fragments old, Of things more golden than the virgin gold, To music set beyond all melody, Have come to me, Of all thy treasure, blown across the sea! Mad maid of Mitylene, Song-slave, song-mistress, and song-queen! Blessëd the nightingale Whom thou didst sing And hail As tender messenger of Spring! Sappho, oh thou— Sweet-apple on the bough, Yea, blushing on the top spray of the tree, Whom all the apple gatherers failed to see, Nay, saw, but could not reach, and cannot now, Thy song perforce will fill my throat And burn it with each golden, molten note! Who knows thee best Knows never peace or rest, And yet his every thought Is a joy from Heaven caught; And his heart-flower open blows Like a dark red Lesbian rose! God-like he thrones himself, who sits by thee, And feels the dear delirium of thy words, And of thy laughter hears the tender chords! The vision thrills my heart; for if I see, In merest glimpse, thy form, my voice fails me, My tongue is numb, with fire my blood is shot, My ears hum, and my straining eyes see not, My frame, bedewed with madness, quivereth And, paler than pale grass, I look like death! Oh, not in wanton whirls Thy singing bevy sweet Danced round thee on charmed feet, Oh, blessëd girls! Who felt thy song-breath on their shining curls And thy fierce flame of longing in their veins! What delicate, deep, delicious bitterness, What stress Of overmastering, sad ecstasy within Each quivering heart! What glorious din Of girlish voices and love-smitten lyres! What incense from what all-consuming fires! O Sappho, didst thou sing This haunting, saddening thing?— Ever shalt thou lie dead, No more rememberëd, Since no Pierian roses blew for thee, Unnoticed mid the shadows dim and dread, Alone in the hereafter shalt thou be! Didst thou mean me? But what care I? I shall not die, For Liberty lends to me her deathless wing; My land is the eternal home of spring, Beyond all clouds my purple dome of sky, The nations hunger for the songs I sing Making the New World's groves with Freedom's transports ring! Naught have I for the tomb, Blooming, as centuries bloom, Fairer with each new day, No petal of my song-flower shall decay! Not so with thine. Veined like the lily's, as the rose's fine; Plucked by the vulgar hand of comedy, They scent the desert dust and sweeten all the sea! Pressed thin between the pages Of the torn book of ages, Suggestive of what fragrant thoughts it is To find a bloom like this: Last night I spoke with Venus in my dream! Ah, in what bower of bliss, By what Pan-haunted stream, Didst thou the lips of Aphrodite kiss? What bitter-sweet Wild love shook thee from head to feet, And tore thy breast, Like a wind that rends the oak-tree on the mountain's crest? What garland didst thou wear? And who was Althis fair, Loved once, loved madly, loved so long ago? And oh! For whom didst thou lie lonesome when the moon had set, And the Pleiades were down? What purple gown Didst thou quit wearing when thy love came not? And (O delicate thought!) For thy lost girlhood crying all in vain, What strange, wild joys were caught And tangled in thy pain? Far in the night, When the moon sails high and white, In the rich, dark firmament, And the sea-wind is spent, And the magnolia's heavy flowers are hung, Like ghastly death-bells waiting to be rung, I yearn In a low, many-toned, deep, sweet nocturne, To guess, And so express, The lost notes that, once stricken from thy lyre, Touched all the world with fiery tenderness, And filled the air with veins of tender fire; But of my longing cometh unto me Never the bubbling honey, nor the honey-bee! Nay, Never tongue may say What founts of inspiration and delight Forsook the day, what stars shrank from the night, When all thy songs, Torn into shreds and smirched with foulest wrongs, Were scattered, Battered, Bruised, and so left to lie In places lone and high, Dark petals of a hyacinth, odorous still, Crushed by rude feet on many a windy hill! PROEM. Though I am poor, and cannot buy The rare, time-mellowed things of Art, God keeps an open gallery Of glories for the poor in heart, Whose walls are hung with grander show Of color than old Titian knew, With outlines Michael Angelo Wronged in the best cartoons he drew! All this is mine to have and hold: Nor fire may burn, nor years may soil, With ruthless trace of gathering mould, These wonders of the Master's toil; Nor can some restless child of Fate, Some darkly gifted Corsican, By red successes decorate His Louvre from my Vatican! AN EARLY BLUEBIRD. Leap to the highest height of spring, And trill thy sweetest note, Bird of the heavenly plumes and twinkling wing And silver-tonëd throat! Sing, while the maple's deepest root Thrills with a pulse of fire That lights its buds. Blow, blow thy tender flute, Thy reed of rich desire! Breathe in thy syrinx Freedom's breath, Quaver the fresh and true, Dispel this lingering wintry mist of death And charm the world anew! Thou first sky-dipped spring-bud of song, Whose heavenly ecstasy Foretells the May while yet March winds are strong, Fresh faith appears with thee! How sweet, how magically rich, Through filmy splendor blown, Thy hopeful voice set to the promise-pitch Of melody yet unknown! O land of mine (where hope can grow And send a deeper root With every spring), hear, heed the free bird blow Hope's charmëd flute! Ah! who will hear, and who will care, And who will heed thy song, As prophecy, as hope, as promise rare, Budding to bloom ere long? From swelling bulbs and sprouting seed, Sweet sap and fragrant dew, And human hearts, grown doubly warm at need, Leaps answer strong and true: We see, we hear (thou liberty-loving thing, That down spring winds doth float), The promise of thine empyrean wing, The hope that floods thy throat! A PRELUDE. Spirit that moves the sap in spring, When lusty male birds fight and sing, Inform my words, and make my lines As sweet as flowers, as strong as vines. Let mine be the freshening power Of rain on grass, of dew on flower; The fertilizing song be mine, Nut-flavored, racy, keen as wine. Let some procreant truth exhale From me, before my forces fail; Or ere the ecstatic impulse go, Let all my buds to blossoms blow. If quick, sound seed be wanting where The virgin soil feels sun and air, And longs to fill a higher state, There let my meanings germinate. Let not my strength be spilled for naught, But, in some fresher vessel caught, Be blended into sweeter forms, And fraught with purer aims and charms. Let bloom-dust of my life be blown To quicken hearts that flower alone; Around my knees let scions rise With heavenward-pointed destinies. And when I fall, like some old tree, And subtile change makes mould of me, There let earth show a fertile line Whence perfect wild-flowers leap and shine. THE ARCHER. The joy is great of him who strays In shady woods on summer days, With eyes alert and muscles steady, His longbow strung, his arrows ready. At morn he hears the woodthrush sing, He sees the wild rose blossoming, And on his senses, soft and low, He feels the brook-song ebb and flow. Life is a charm, and all is good To him who lives like Robin Hood, Hearing ever, far and thin, Hints of the tunes of Gamelyn. His greatest grief, his sharpest pain, Is (when the days are dark with rain) That for a season he must lie Inert, while deer go bounding by; Lounge in his lodge, and long and long For Allen a Dale's delightful song, Or smack his lips at thought of one Drink from the Friar's demijohn. But when the sky is clear again, He sloughs his grief, forgets his pain, Hearing on gusts of charming weather The low laugh of his arrow feather! THE DEATH OF THE WHITE HERON. (CYPRESS LAKE, FLORIDA.) I pulled my boat with even sweep Across light shoals and eddies deep, Tracking the currents of the lake From lettuce raft to weedy brake. Across a pool death-still and dim I saw a monster reptile swim, And caught, far off and quickly gone, The delicate outlines of a fawn. Above the marshy islands flew The green teal and the swift curlew; The rail and dunlin drew the hem Of lily-bonnets over them; I saw the tufted wood-duck pass Between the wisps of water-grass. All round the gunwales and across I draped my boat with Spanish moss, And, lightly drawn from head to knee, I hung gay air-plants over me; Then, lurking like a savage thing Crouching for a treacherous spring, I stood in motionless suspense Among the rushes green and dense. I kept my bow half-drawn, a shaft Set straight across the velvet haft. Alert and vigilant, I stood Scanning the lake, the sky, the wood. I heard a murmur soft and sad From water-weed to lily-pad, And from the frondous pine did ring The hammer of the golden-wing. On old drift-logs the bittern stood Dreaming above the silent flood; The water-turkey eyed my boat, The hideous snake-bird coiled its throat, And birds whose plumage shone like flame,— Wild things grown suddenly, strangely tame,— Lit near me; but I heeded not: They could not tempt me to a shot. Grown tired at length, I bent the oars By grassy brinks and shady shores, Through labyrinths and mysteries Mid dusky cypress stems and knees, Until I reached a spot I knew, Over which each day the herons flew. I heard a whisper sweet and keen Flow through the fringe of rushes green, The water saying some light thing, The rushes gayly answering. The wind drew faintly from the south, Like breath blown from a sleeper's mouth, And down its current sailing low Came a lone heron white as snow. He cleft with grandly spreading wing The hazy sunshine of the spring; Through graceful curves he swept above The gloomy moss-hung cypress grove; Then gliding down a long incline, He flashed his golden eyes on mine. Half-turned he poised himself in air, The prize was great, the mark was fair! I raised my bow, and steadily drew The silken string until I knew My trusty arrow's barbëd point Lay on my left forefinger joint,— Until I felt the feather seek My ear, swift-drawn across my cheek: Then from my fingers leapt the string With sharp recoil and deadly ring, Closed by a sibilant sound so shrill, It made the very water thrill,— Like twenty serpents bound together, Hissed the flying arrow's feather! A thud, a puff, a feathery ring, A quick collapse, a quivering, A whirl, a headlong downward dash, A heavy fall, a sullen plash,— And like white foam, or giant flake Of snow, he lay upon the lake. And of his death the rail was glad, Strutting upon a lily-pad; The jaunty wood-duck smiled and bowed; The belted kingfisher laughed aloud, Making the solemn bittern stir Like a half-wakened slumberer; And rasping notes of joy were heard From gallinule and crying-bird, The while with trebled noise did ring The hammer of the golden-wing! A FLIGHT SHOT. We were twin brothers, tall and hale, Glad wanderers over hill and dale. We stood within the twilight shade Of pines that rimmed a Southern glade. He said: “Let's settle, if we can, Which of us is the stronger man. “We'll try a flight shot, high and good, Across the green glade toward the wood.” And so we bent in sheer delight Our old yew bows with all our might. Our long keen shafts, drawn to the head, Were poised a moment ere they sped. As we leaned back a breath of air Mingled the brown locks of our hair. We loosed. As one our bow-cords rang, As one away our arrows sprang. Away they sprang; the wind of June Thrilled to their softly whistled tune. We watched their flight, and saw them strike Deep in the ground slantwise alike, So far away that they might pass For two thin straws of broom-sedge grass! Then arm in arm we doubting went To find whose shaft was farthest sent, Each fearing in his loving heart That brother's shaft had fallen short. But who could tell by such a plan Which of us was the stronger man? There at the margin of the wood, Side by side our arrows stood, Their red cock-feathers wing and wing, Their amber nocks still quivering, Their points deep-planted where they fell An inch apart and parallel! We clasped each other's hands; said he, “Twin champions of the world are we!” THE FAWN. I lay close down beside the river, My bow well strung, well filled my quiver, The god that dwells among the reeds Sang sweetly from their tangled bredes; The soft-tongued water murmured low, Swinging the flag-leaves to and fro. Beyond the river, fold on fold, The hills gleamed through a film of gold; The feathery osiers waved and shone Like silver threads in tangles blown. A bird, fire-winged, with ruby throat, Down the slow, drowsy wind did float, And drift and flit and stay along, A very focal flame of song. A white sand-isle amid the stream Lay sleeping by its shoals of bream; In lilied pools, alert and calm, Great bass through lucent circles swam; And farther, by a rushy brink, A shadowy fawn stole down to drink, Where tall, thin birds unbalanced stood In sandy shallows of the flood. And what did I beside the river, With bow well-strung and well-filled quiver? I lay quite still with half-closed eyes, Lapped in a dream of Paradise, Until I heard a bow-cord ring, And from the reeds an arrow sing. I knew not of my brother's luck, If well or ill his shaft had struck; But something in his merry shout Put my sweet summer dream to rout, And up I sprang, with bow half-drawn, And keen desire to slay the fawn. But where was it? Gone like my dream. I only heard the fish-hawk scream, And the strong stripëd bass leap up Beside the lily's floating cup; I only felt the cool wind go Across my face with steady flow; I only saw those thin birds stand Unbalanced on the river sand, Low peering at some dappled thing In the green rushes quivering. THE BLUE HERON. Where water-grass grows overgreen On damp cool flats by gentle streams, Still as a ghost and sad of mien, With half-closed eyes the heron dreams. Above him in the sycamore The flicker beats a dull tattoo; Through pawpaw groves the soft airs pour Gold dust of blooms and fragrance new. And from the thorn it loves so well, The oriole flings out its strong, Sharp lay, wrought in the crucible Of its flame-circled soul of song. The heron nods. The charming runes Of Nature's music thrill his dreams; The joys of many Mays and Junes Wash past him like cool summer streams. What tranquil life, what joyful rest, To feel the touch of fragrant grass, And doze like him, while tenderest Dream-waves across my sleep would pass! THE BLUEBIRD. When ice is thawed and snow is gone, And racy sweetness floods the trees; When snow-birds from the hedge have flown, And on the hive-porch swarm the bees,— Drifting down the first warm wind That thrills the earliest days of spring, The bluebird seeks our maple groves, And charms them into tasseling. He sits among the delicate sprays, With mists of splendor round him drawn, And through the spring's prophetic veil Sees summer's rich fulfillment dawn: He sings, and his is nature's voice,— A gush of melody sincere From that great fount of harmony Which thaws and runs when spring is here. Short is his song, but strangely sweet To ears aweary of the low, Dull tramp of Winter's sullen feet, Sandaled in ice and muffed in snow: Short is his song, but through it runs A hint dithyrambs yet to be,— A sweet suggestiveness that has The influence of prophecy. From childhood I have nursed a faith In bluebird's songs and winds of spring: They tell me after frost and death There comes a time of blossoming; And after snow and cutting sleet, The cold, stern mood of Nature yields To tender warmth, when bare pink feet Of children press her greening fields. Sing strong and clear, O bluebird dear! While all the land with splendor fills, While maples gladden in the vales And plum-trees blossom on the hills: Float down the wind on shining wings, And do thy will by grove and stream, While through my life spring's freshness runs Like music through a poet's dream. THE WABASH. There is a river singing in between Bright fringes of pawpaw and sycamore, That stir to fragrant winds on either shore, Where tall blue herons stretch lithe necks, and lean Over clear currents flowing cool and thin Through the clean furrows of the pebbly floor. My own glad river. Though unclassic, still Haunted of merry gods whose pipings fill With music all thy golden willow-brakes! Above thee halcyon lifts his regal crest; The tulip-tree flings thee its flower-flakes, The tall flag over thee its lances shakes: With every charm of beauty thou art blest, O happiest river of the happy West! OKECHOBEE. Thy shadowy margin, O still, tropic lake, Is like a thought that hovers in the brain Beyond the reach of phrase to make it plain, Divinely sweet for its dim mystery's sake. The real and the ideal, matched so well In yonder palm-trees and their ghosts below, Have but a doubtful line between to tell That from a common root they do not grow! The delicate shifting shades that cloud the sheen Of water too harmonious to flow, Flit over tufts of flags and willows green, Which feel not even the faintest summer swell. O Lake, thy beauty inexpressible is Except by some song-wrought antholysis! DROPPING CORN. Pretty Phœbe Lane and I, In the soft May weather, Barefoot down the furrows went Dropping corn together. Side by side across the field Back and forth we hurried; All the golden grains we dropped Soon the ploughshare buried. Bluebirds on the hedges sat, Chirping low and billing; “Why,” thought I, “not follow suit, If the maid is willing?” So I whispered, “Phœbe, dear, Kiss me”—“Keep on dropping!” Called her father from the plough; “There 's no time for stopping!” The cord was loosed,—the moment sped; The golden charm was broken! Nevermore between us two Word of love was spoken. What a little slip, sometimes, All our hope releases! How the merest breath of chance Breaks our joy in pieces! Sorrow's cup, though often drained, Never lacks for filling; And we can't get Fortune's kiss When the maid is willing! THE MORNING HILLS. I. He sits among the morning hills, His face is bright and strong; He scans far heights, but scarcely notes The herdsman's idle song. He cannot brook this peaceful life While battle's trumpet calls; He sees a crown for him who wins, A tear for him who falls. The flowery glens and shady slopes Are hateful to his eyes; Beyond the heights, beyond the storms, The land of promise lies. II. He is so old and sits so still, With face so weak and mild, We know that he remembers naught Save when he was a child. His fight is fought, his fame is won, Life's highest peak is past; The laurel crown, the triumph-arch, Are worthless at the last. The frost of age destroys the bay,— The loud applause of men Falls feebly on the palsied ears Of threescore years and ten. He does not hear the voice that bears His name around the world; He has no thought of great deeds done Where battle-tempests whirled; But evermore he is looking back, Whilst memory fills and thrills With echoes of the herdsman's song Among the morning hills. AT THE WINDOW. I heard the woodpecker pecking, The bluebird tenderly sing; I turned and looked out of my window, And lo, it was spring! A breath from tropical borders, Just a ripple, flowed into my room, And washed my face clean of its sadness, Blew my heart into bloom. The loves I have kept for a lifetime, Sweet buds I have shielded from snow, Break forth into full leaf and tassel When spring winds do blow. For the sap of my life goes upward, Obeying the same sweet law That waters the heart of the maple After a thaw. I forget my old age and grow youthful, Bathing in wind-tides of spring, When I hear the woodpecker pecking, The first bluebird sing. NOVEMBER. A hint of slumber in the wind, A dreamful stir of blades and stalks, As tenderly the twilight flows Down all my garden walks. My robes of work are thrown aside, The odor of the grass is sweet; The pleasure of a day well spent Bathes me from head to feet. Calmly I wait the dreary change,— The season cutting sharp and sheer Through the wan bowers of death that fringe The border of the year. And while I muse, the fated earth Into a colder current dips,— Feels winter's scourge, with summer's kiss Still warm upon her lips. BETWEEN THE POPPY AND THE ROSE. How tired! Eight hours of racking work, With sharp vexations shot between! Scant wages and few kindly words,— How gloomy the whole day has been! But here is home. The garden shines, And over it the soft air flows; A mist of chastened glory hangs Between the poppy and the rose. The poppy red as ruby is, The rose pale pink, fullblown, and set Amid the dark rich leaves that form The strong vine's royal coronet; And half-way o'er from this to that, In a charmed focus of repose, Two rare young faces, lit with love, Between the poppy and the rose. Sweet little Jessie, two years old, Dear little Mamma, twenty-four, Together in the garden walk While evening sun-streams round them pour. List! Mamma murmurs baby-talk! Hush! Jessie's talk to laughter glows! They both look heavenly sweet to me, Between the poppy and the rose. Two flakes of sunshine in deep shade, Two diamonds set in rougher stone, Two songs with harp accompaniment Across a houseless desert blown,— No, nothing like this vision is; How deep its innocent influence goes, Sweeter than song or power or fame, Between the poppy and the rose! Between the poppy and the rose, A bud and blossom shining fair, A childlike mother and a child, Whose own my very heart-throbs are! Oh, life is sweet, they make it so; Its work is lighter than repose: Come anything, so they bloom on Between the poppy and the rose. SOLACE. Thou art the last rose of the year, By gusty breezes rudely fanned: The dying Summer holds thee fast In the hot hollow of her hand. Thy face pales, as if looking back Into the splendor of thy past Had thrilled thee strangely, knowing that This one long look must be the last. Thine essence, that was heavenly sweet, Has flown upon the tricksy air: Fate's hand is on thee; drop thy leaves, And go among the things that were. Be must and mould, be trampled dust, Be nothing that is fair to see: One day, at least, of glorious life Was thine of all eternity. Be this a comfort: crown and lyre And regal purple last not long; Kings fall like leaves, but thy perfume Strays through the years like royal song. HO, FOR THE KANKAKEE! Ho, for the marshes, green with Spring, Where the bitterns croak and the plovers pipe, Where the gaunt old heron spreads his wing, Above the haunt of rail and snipe; For my gun is clean and my rod 's in trim, And the old, wild longing is roused in me; Ho, for the bass-pools cool and dim! Ho, for the swales of the Kankakee! Is there other joy like the joy of a man Free for a season with rod and gun, With the sun to tan and the winds to fan, And the waters to lull, and never a one Of the cares of life to follow him, Or to shadow his mind while he wanders free? Ho, for the currents slow and dim! Ho, for the fens of the Kankakee! A hut by the river, a light canoe, My rod and my gun, and a sennight fair— A wind from the South, and the wildfowl due Be mine. All 's well. Comes never a care. A strain of the savage fires my blood, And the zest of freedom is keen in me; Ho, for the marsh and the lilied flood! Ho, for the sloughs of the Kankakee! Give me to stand where the swift currents rush, With my rod all astrain and a bass coming in, Or give me the marsh, with the brown snipe aflush, And my gun's sudden flashes and resonant din; For I am tired of the desk, and tired of the town, And I long to be out, and I long to be free: Ho, for the marsh, with the birds whirling down! Ho, for the pools of the Kankakee! ATALANTA. When Spring grows old, and sleepy winds Set from the south with odors sweet, I see my love, in green, cool groves, Speed down dusk aisles on shining feet. She throws a kiss and bids me run, In whispers sweet as roses' breath; I know I cannot win the race, And at the end I know is death. But joyfully I bare my limbs, Anoint me with the tropic breeze, And feel through every sinew thrill The vigor of Hippomenes. O race of love! we all have run Thy happy course through groves of spring, And cared not, when at last we lost, For life or death, or anything! THE SENTINEL. What of this Hour that passes With a shimmer of gold and blue? O Love, through your crystal glasses What seems this hour to you? I see the gold and blue Of the beautiful thing that passes On the wind through the summer grasses, But it is nothing new! Halt! sweet Hour, I stand on guard; You cannot pass this way! My heart (my master) bids me ward His outer court to-day; Stop where you are, and stay. Your face would witch full many a guard, But I am old and stern and hard; Beware, I say! What of this bright Hour, standing Just out before the gate, A passage of right demanding Because it groweth late? O Love, must I ope the gate? See, see the bright thing standing, Sharp, scintillant, commanding! Is it a fate? AT NIGHT. The moon hangs in a silver mist, The stars are dull and thin; Sleep, bending low, spreads loving arms To fold the whole world in. The air is like a spell; the hills Waver, now seen, now lost; The pallid river wanders by, A vast unquiet ghost. A hornëd owl on silent wings, From out a cavernous place, Speeds, like a bolt of darkness hurled Athwart the shining space Above the vale from wood to wood, And leaves no trace behind,— Like some dark fancy flung across A pure and peaceful mind! IN EXILE. I. The singing streams, and the deep, dark wood Beloved of old by Robin Hood, Lift me a voice, kiss me a hand, To call me from this younger land. What time by dull Floridian lakes, What time by rivers fringed with brakes, I blow the reed, and draw the bow, And see my arrows hurtling go Well sent to deer or wary hare, Or, wildfowl whistling down the air; What time I lie in shady spots On beds of wild forget-me-nots, That fringe the fen lands insincere And boggy marges of the mere, Whereon I see the heron stand, Knee-deep in sable slush of sand,— I think how sweet if friends should come And tell me England calls me home. II. I keep good heart, and bide my time, And blow the bubbles of my rhyme; I wait and watch, for soon I know In Sherwood merry horns shall blow, And blow and blow, and folk shall come To tell me England calls me home. Mother of archers, then I go Wind-blown to you with bended bow, To stand close up by you and ask That it be my appointed task To sing in leal and loyal lays Your matchless bowmen's meed of praise; And that unchallenged I may go Through your green woods with bended bow,— Your woods where bowered and hidden stood Of old the home of Robin Hood. Ah, this were sweet, and it will come When merry England calls me home! III. Perchance, long hence, it may befall, Or soon, mayhap, or not at all, That all my songs nowhither sent, And all my shafts at random spent, Will find their way to those who love The simple force and truth thereof; Wherefore my name shall then be rung Across the land from tongue to tongue, Till some who hear shall haste to come With news that England calls me home. I walk where spiced winds raff the blades Of sedge-grass on the summer glades; Through purfled blades that fringe the mere I watch the timid tawny deer Set its quick feet and quake and spring, As if it heard some deadly thing, When but a brown snipe flutters by With rustling wing and piping cry; I stand in some dim place at dawn, And see across a forest lawn The tall wild turkeys swiftly pass Light-footed through the dewy grass; I shout, and wind my horn, and go The whole morn through with bended bow, Then on my rest I feel at noon Sown pulvil of the blooms of June; I live and keep no count of time, I blow the bubbles of my rhyme: These are my joys till friends shall come And tell me England calls me home. IV. The self-yew bow was England's boast; She leaned upon her archer host,— It was her very life-support At Crecy and at Agincourt, At Flodden and at Halidon Hill, And fields of glory redder still! O bows that rang at Solway Moss! O yeomanry of Neville's cross! These were your victories, for by you Breastplate and shield were cloven through; And mailëd knights at every joint Sore wounded by an arrow point, Drew rein, turned pale, reeled in the sell, And, bristled with arrows, gasped and fell! O barbëd points that scratched the name Of England on the walls of fame! O music of the ringing cords Set to grand song of deeds, not words! O yeomen! for your memory's sake, These bubbles of my rhyme I make,— Not rhymes of conquest stern and sad, Or hoarse-voiced like the Iliad, But soft and dreamful as the sigh Of this sweet wind that washes by,— The while I wait for friends to come And tell me England calls me home. V. I wait and wait; it would be sweet To feel the sea beneath my feet, And hear the breeze sing in the shrouds Betwixt me and the white-winged clouds,— To feel and know my heart should soon Have its desire, its one sweet boon, To look out on the foam-sprent waste Through which my vessel's keel would haste, Till on the far horizon dim A low white line would shine and swim; The low white line, the gleaming strand, The pale cliffs of the Mother-land! O God! the very thought is bliss, The burden of my song it is, Till over sea song-blown shall come The news that England calls me home! VI. Ah, call me, England, some sweet day When these brown locks are silver gray, And these brown arms are shrunken small, Unfit for deeds of strength at all; When the swift deer shall pass me by, Whilst all unstrung my bow shall lie, And birds shall taunt me with the time I wasted making foolish rhyme, And wasted blowing in a reed The runes of praise, the yeoman's meed, And wasted dreaming foolish dreams Of English woods and English streams, Of grassy glade and queachy fen Beloved of old by archer men, And of the friends who would not come To tell me England called me home. VII. Such words are sad: blow them away And lose them in the leaves of May, O wind! and leave them there to rot, Like random arrows lost when shot; And here, these better thoughts, take these And blow them far across the seas, To that old land and that old wood Which hold the dust of Robin Hood! Say this, low-speaking in my place: “The last of all the archer race “Sends this his sheaf of rhymes to those Whose fathers bent the self-yew bows, “And made the cloth-yard arrows ring For merry England and her king, “Wherever Lion Richard set His fortune's stormy banneret!” Say this, and then, oh, haste to come And tell me England calls me home! BEFORE DAWN. A keen, insistent hint of dawn Fell from the mountain height; A wan, uncertain gleam betrayed The faltering of the night. The emphasis of silence made The fog above the brook Intensely pale; the trees took on A haunted, haggard look. Such quiet came, expectancy Filled all the earth and sky: Time seemed to pause a little space; I heard a dream go by! SPRING'S TORCH-BEARER. Oriole—athlete of the air— Of fire and song a glowing core, From tropic wildernesses fair, Spring's favorite lampadephore, A hot flambeau on either wing Rimples as you pass me by; 'T is seeing flame to hear you sing, 'T is hearing song to see you fly. Below the leaves in fragrant gloom, Cool currents lead you to your goal, Where bursting jugs of rich perfume Down honeyed slopes of verdure roll. In eddies, round some hummock cold, Where violets weave their azure bredes, You flash a torch o'er rimy mould And rouse the dormant balsam seeds. Upon the sassafras a flare, And through the elm a wavering sheen, A flicker in the orchard fair, A flame across the hedgerow green. Your voice and light are in my dream Of vanished youth, they warm my heart; With every chirrup, every gleam, Sweet currents from old fountains start. I take me wings and fly with you, Once more the boy of long ago. Oh, days of bloom! Oh, honey-dew! Hark! how the flutes of fairy blow! You whisk wild splendors through the trees, And send keen fervors down the wind, You singe the jackets of the bees, And trail an opal mist behind. When flowery hints foresay the berry, On spray of haw and tuft of brier, Then, wandering incendiary, You set the maple swamps afire! THE ASSAULT. (Amazilia cerviniventris.) A wingëd rocket, curving through An amethyst trajectory, Blew up the magazines of dew Within the fortress of the bee. Some say the tulip mortar sent The missile forth; I do not know; I scarcely saw which way it went, Its whisk of flame surprised me so. I heard the sudden hum and boom, And saw the arc of purple light Across the garden's rosy gloom; Then something glorious blurred my sight! The bees forgot to sound alarm, And did not pause their gates to lock; A topaz terror took by storm The tower of the hollyhock. Above the rose a halo hung, As if a bomb had been a gem, And round the dahlia's head was swung A blade that looked a diadem. What more befell I cannot say; By ruby glint and emerald gleam My sense was dazed; the garden lay Around me like an opal dream! ODE—SPRING. PARAPHRASED FROM ANACREON. When Zephyr on his drooping wings Soft sighs and spicy fragrance brings, How sweet to wander on the lawns Wrapped in the soft green grass of spring And dewy splendors of the dawns. How sweet with some dear, blushing maid To sit in cooling waves of shade And talk, while o'er her shoulders fair Falls the full glory of her hair! LAZING. Give me a day, let business right itself, Give me one day to drift in idleness Along the shores of dreamland. Let me build My castles in the air and dwell in them A space, while yet the happy May-winds blow. The oriole is come, and in the thorn Among the greening buds the catbird sings; The fields are sweet, and in the sky is set A tranquil glory. Let me go and lie Upon the grass while happy May-winds blow. I 'd rather rest to-day than be a king, For what are kings but slaves with golden chains? Talk not of work, this is too sweet a day To bow one's neck and tamely take the yoke, And I will not, while happy May-winds blow. This is the month of wooing; let me sit Close hand in hand with Nature, as a man, Being deep in love, would sit beside a maid, And ask for rest as lovers ask for love, In tender whispers, while the May-winds blow. And if I fall asleep in Nature's arms, Like any lover in the arms of love, Let no one passing by awaken me, For only once, in all the rolling year, Comes holiday while happy May-winds blow. TO A WILD FLOWER. In the green solitudes Of the deep, shady woods Thy lot is kindly cast, and life to thee Is like a gust of rarest minstrelsy. The winds of May and June Hum many a tender tune, Blowing above thy leafy hiding-place, Kissing, all thrilled with joy, thy modest face. About thee float and glow Rare insects, hovering low, And round thee glance thin streams of delicate grass, Plashing their odors on thee as they pass. The sheen of brilliant wings, Songs of shy, flitting things, The low, mysterious melodies that thrill Through every summer wood, thy sweet life fill. O bloom! all joy is thine, All loves around thee shine; The thousand hearts of Nature throb for thee, Her thousand voices praise thee tenderly. O bloom of purest glory, Flower of love's gentlest story, Forever keep thy petals fresh and fair, Forever send thy sweetness down the air! I'll put thee in my song, With all thy joys along, At which some sunny hearts may sunnier grow, And frozen ones may gently slip their snow. CERES. The wheat was flowing ankle-deep Across the field from side to side; And, dipping in the emerald waves, The swallows flew in circles wide. The sun, a moment flaring red, Shot level rays athwart the world, The quenched his fire behind the hills, With rosy vapors o'er him curled. A sweet, insinuating calm,— A calm just one remove from sleep, Such as a tranquil watcher feels, Seeing mild stars at midnight sweep Through splendid purple deeps, and swing Their old, ripe clusters down the west To where, on undiscovered hills, The gods have gathered them to rest,— A calm like that hung over all The dusky groves, and, filtered through The thorny hedges, touched the wheat Till every blade was bright with dew. Was it a dream? We call things dreams When we must needs do so, or own Belief in old, exploded myths, Whose very smoke is long since flown. Was it a dream? Mine own eyes saw, And Ceres came across the wheat That, like bright water, dimpled round The golden sandals of her feet. AOEDE. Her mouth is like a dewy rose That blows, but will not open quite; Like flame turned down, her long hair glows In thin, curled currents softly bright; Her breasts and throat are marble-white. Her lips will not have any kiss; They draw away, they flash a smile,— Half bashfulness, half scorn it is, A silent ripple.... All the while She meditates some charming wile. Her feet below her drapery shine Like roses under clinging sprays, When, late in summer, lolls the vine;— Like flag-leaves in long August days, To moods perverse her body sways. Her breath is keen and sweet as nard; Her limbs move like a stream flowing Among smooth stones. A lithe young pard Is not more quick than she to spring To guard or capture anything. She is a snare, a subtle lure,— A lily on a whirlpool's rim. She is as dangerously pure As fire.... She revels in a dream Wherein the daintiest fancies swim. She feasts upon my pain, and turns Her pink ear up to catch my sighs, And every word I speak. She yearns To see me die.... Her great gray eyes Are deep as seas and over-wise. Ah, over-wise those strange deep eyes! They master me, they take my breath; In them a nameless mystery lies.... They burn with life that joy bringeth, They gleam through shining mists of death. DIANA. She had a bow of yellow horn, Like the old moon at early morn. She had three arrows strong and good, Steel set in feathered cornel wood. Like purest pearl her left breast shone Above her kirtle's emerald zone; Her right was bound in silk well-knit, Lest her bowstring should sever it. Ripe lips she had, and clear gray eyes, And hair pure gold blown hoiden-wise Across her face, like shining mist That with dawn's flush is faintly kissed. Her limbs how matched and round and fine! How free like song! how strong like wine! And, timed to music wild and sweet, How swift her silver-sandaled feet! Single of heart and strong of hand, Wind-like she wandered through the land, No man (or king or lord or churl) Dared whisper love to that fair girl. And woe to him who came upon Her nude, at bath, like Acteon! So dire his fate that one who heard The flutter of a bathing bird, What time he crossed a breezy wood, Felt sudden quickening of his blood; Cast one swift look, then ran away Far through the green, thick groves of May; Afeard, lest down the wind of spring He 'd hear an arrow whispering! GARDEN STATUES. I. EROS. O naked baby Love among the roses, Watching with laughing gray-green eyes for me, Who says that thou art blind? Who hides from thee? Who is it in his foolishness supposes That ever a bandage round thy sweet face closes Thicker than gauze? I know that thou canst see! Thy glances are more swift and far more sure To reach their goal than any missile is, Except that one which never yet did miss, Whose slightest puncture not even death can cure, Whose stroke divides the heart with such a bliss As even the strongest trembles to endure,— Thine arrow that makes glad the saddest weather With the keen rustle of its purple feather! II. APHRODITE. And thou whose tresses like straw-colored gold Above the scarlet gladiole float and shine,— Whose comely breasts, whose shoulders fair and fine, Whose fathomless eyes and limbs of heavenly mould, Thrill me with pain and pleasures manifold, Racy of earth, yet full of fire divine,— Art thou unclean as that old Paphian dream? I know thou art not; for thou camest to me Out of the white foam-lilies of the sea, Out of the salt-clear fountain's clearest stream, The embodiment of purest purity, As healthful as the sun's directest beam, So life-giving that up beneath thy feet, Wherever thou goest, the grass-flowers bubble sweet! III. PSYCHE. And thou among the violets lying down, With gracile limbs curled like a sleeping child's, And dewy lips, and cheeks drawn back with smiles, And bright hair wrapped about thee for a gown, Does some implacable fate with scowl and frown Weave for thy feet its dark insidious wiles? Not so, for I have known thee from thy youth A singer of sweet tunes and sweeter words, To merry tinkling of soft cithern chords. Thine is the way of happiness and truth, And all thy movements are as swift and smooth As through the air the strongest flying bird's. Infinite joy about thy presence clings, Unspeakable hope falls from thy going wings. IV. PERSEPHONE. And thou that by the poppy bloom dost stand Robed in the dusky garments of the South, With slumber in thine eyes and on thy mouth, Sandaled with silence, having in thy hand A philter for death and a sleep-bearing wand, Bringest thou the immitigable fire and drouth? No; for thy shadowy hair is full of balm, Thy philter is delight, thy wand gives rest. See, now I fold my hands upon my breast! Come, touch me with thy cool and soothing palm, Lull me to measureless sleep, ineffable calm, And bear me to thy garden in the west, Beyond whose ever-clouded confine lies A sweet illimitable paradise! THE TULIP. (Caveat regina.) Seeing, above dark spikes of green, Your great bold flowers of gold and red, I think of some young heathen queen With blazing crown upon her head,— Some beautiful barbaric thing, Clothed in rich garments, emerald zoned, Whom simple folk, half worshiping And half in fear, have crowned and throned. You will not deign to give the breeze The slightest nod as it goes by; You will not move a leaf to please The drowsy gorgeous butterfly. With measureless nonchalance and pride, You take the humming bird's caress; The brown melodious bee must bide Your haughty, arrogant willfulness! You will not even stoop to hear The whisper of the adoring grass; The violets droop their heads in fear, The beetles grumble as they pass. Beware, O queen, some day ere long All these may drop their fealty, And for redress of causeless wrong Uprise in passionate mutiny. Ah, then what rapturous sound of wings, Applauding when your throne goes down! What cheering when the rude breeze springs, And whisks away your withered crown! WRITTEN ON A FLY-LEAF OF THEOCRITUS. Those were good times, in olden days, Of which the poet has his dreams, When gods beset the woodland ways, And lay in wait by all the streams. One could be sure of something then Severely simple, simply grand, Or keenly, subtly sweet, as when Venus and Love went hand in hand. Now I would give (such is my need) All the world's store of rhythm and rhyme To see Pan fluting on a reed And with his goat-hoof keeping time! EOS. She stood between two gold pillars; Behind her lay a misty field, And sunlight smote with great splendor Athwart her silver shield. From her high place she shot an arrow That broke the slumber of the sea; And one she shot upon a mountain, And one flew full at me. Then the sea began singing, and uplifted Its face made glorious for a kiss; And the mountain on its green summit Built fires of sacrifice. Then her little feet, gold-sandaled, Stepped down the current of a breeze, And stood upon a river flowing Broad like the Euphrates. And the hills cried, “It is Eos!” And the skylark soared away; And the little fire in the east enkindled, Flamed into perfect day! A BREATH OF MORN. Flow in upon my soul, O wind of morn! Touch me with ancient tenderness and faith, Thou perfumed waft from fields of blooming corn! Woo me, lure me from this poisoned shore of Death. I hear far voices, sweet as flutes, somewhere, Calling me into the darkness, and I know Their soft insidious languor on the air Comes from the land of burial, damp and low. Blow on me, O thou current of sweet youth! Come back dear days of boyhood and bright dreams: Arise again, thou white, clear bloom of truth; Babble once more, O careless morning streams! Kiss me, warm lips of purity and love; Sing to me, lasses from the meadow lands; Bind me with blossoms from the sacred grove Wherein the temple of my childhood stands. Lo! I am sick to death of Manhood's ways, And long to be a fighting man no more; No more for me the clanging iron days; So let me live my happy maytime o'er. Blow on me, wind, out of the early morn, And bear away from me the wear and fret; Bring me the perfume of the blooming corn, And I will sing through many a springtime yet! TWILIGHT. So short the time, and yet it seems so long, Since last I saw thee, O my beautiful! The very thought is resonant with song, And wraps my spirit in a tender lull. I count the hours till I shall come again: Each moment seems a little rose of time; Each gust of wind thrills gently with a strain Of soft, bewildering melody and rhyme. There comes a perfume from the sunset land, And from the sunset vapor comes a voice; Some one in evening's gateway seems to stand, And o'er a flood of glory shout, “Rejoice!” I seem to look through all the lapsing years, And see my path wind through a holy land, While wondrous as the music of the spheres Is the soft murmur of Time's golden sand. I see my springs go by, a golden train; I see my summers with their corn and wines; I see my autumns come and come again, And roar my winters through the windy pines! SEVEN GOLD REEDS. Seven gold reeds grew tall and slim, Close by the river's beaded brim. Syrinx, the naiad, flitted past; Pan, the goat-hoofed, followed fast. Oh, such a race was joy to see, Swift as the flight of bird or bee. As lightly beat the girl's white feet They made strange music low and sweet; So heavily trod the lusty Pan His hoofs clashed loudly as he ran. He spread his arms to clasp her there (Just as she vanished into air), And to his bosom, warm and rough, Drew the gold reeds close enough. Then the wind's low voice began To hum in the furry ears of Pan. Out of green bark he made a tether, And bound seven joints of the reeds together, And blew a tune so sweet and clear That all the wild things came to hear. So, to this day, the poet's fire Springs out of his unslaked desire, When Love on wingëd feet has fled, And seven gold reeds are clasped instead! THE ORPHIC LEGACY. When steadily blew the wind from shores of Thrace, And stirred the vines of Lesbos, loaded down With racy fruit all round Methymna town, Lo, floating on the water, came a dead man's face. And from the pallid, parted lips thereof Issued strange singing of idyllic song, As it lay tossing white-capped waves among, Upturned to the sweet sky that smiling bent above. What wondrous flotsam! And a golden shell Drifted beside it, stringed with silver chords, Playing fit accompaniment to the words That through the sounds of winds and swashing sea did swell. “Sweetest of all the Ægean Isles,” it said, “Oh, bury me beneath thy fruitful vines, And pour libations of thy choicest wines; For, lo, I am the far-famed Thracian singer's head! “And I am torn of jealous women's hands, Because to my dead love I held me true; Me the Bacchantes, over-drunken, slew; Now, bodiless, I drift upon thine island sands. “This my gold shell I bring as gift to thee; And thou shalt see full soon its precious use, When Sappho's voice awakes the lyric muse, And with his seven-stringed lute Terpander charms the sea.” Then through the splendid weather maids there came, With loving men, and walked upon the beach, Arm twined in arm, and murmuring each to each, Slow burning up their hearts in love's sweet, pitiless flame. But when the tender gusts of Orphic song Smote on their ears with lyre-accompaniment, Far down the beach's sandy slope they went, And found the singing head and tunëd shell among Sea-drifts that on the foamy surf-line lay. What jetsam! but they hailed it with delight; They buried the singing head from sight, And to Methymna took the sweet-stringed shell away. They hung it in the temple tenderly (Where all untouched, its chords kept quivering And with rare music never ceased to ring, That filled the temple as with moanings of the sea). Thence flaws of song, with charming chords between, Swept through the olive groves and dusky vines, And through the mastic and Aleppo pines To the rose-bannered garden walls of Mitylene. PAN IN THE ORCHARD. He carved a flute of elder green, And notched it well and true, Then pursed his lips and puffed his cheeks And merrily he blew. For it was spring-time holiday, A sun-tanned boy was he, With russet freckles on his face And a patch upon his knee. The apple boughs above him flung Their tangled sprays on high, With one dark, bristly blue-jay nest Rough sketched against the sky. He knew the secrets of the grass, The burden of the hour, He saw the fierce, bluff bumblebee Touse many a clover flower. Orphaned and poor as poor could be, The years before him lay Dark billows of an unknown sea, No light-house on the way. And yet, and yet his elder flute Could bring him comfort true; He pursed his lips and puffed his cheeks And blew, and blew, and blew! OUT OF THE SOUTH. A migrant song-bird I, Out of the blue, between the sea and the sky, Landward blown on bright, untiring wings; Out of the South I fly, Urged by some vague, strange force of destiny, To where the young wheat springs, And the maize begins to grow, And the clover fields to blow. I have sought, In far wild groves below the tropic line, To lose old memories of this land of mine; I have fought This vague, mysterious power that flings me forth Into the North; But all in vain. When flutes of April blow The immemorial longing lures me, and I go. I go, I go, The sky above, the sea below, And I know not by what sense I keep my way, Slow winnowing the ether night and day; Yet ever to the same green, fragrant maple grove, Where I shall swing and sing beside my love, Some irresistible impulse bears me on, Through starry dusks and rosy mists of dawn, And flames of noon and purple films of rain; And the strain Of mighty winds hurled roaring back and forth, Between the caverns of the reeling earth, Cannot bewilder me. I know that I shall see, Just at the appointed time, the dogwood blow, And hear the willows rustle and the mill-stream flow. The very bough that best Shall hold a perfect nest Now bursts its buds and spills its keen perfume; And the violets are in bloom, Beside the boulder, lichen-grown and gray, Where I shall perch and pipe, Till the dewberries are ripe, And our brood has flown away, And the empty nest swings high Between the flowing tides of grass and the dreamy violet sky. I come, I come! Bloom, O cherry, peach, and plum! Bubble brook, and rustle corn and rye! Falter not, O Nature, nor will I. Give me thy flower and fruit, And I'll blow for thee my flute; I'll blow for thee my flute so sweet and clear, This year, Next year, And many and many a blooming coming year, Till this strange force No more aloft shall guide me in my course, High over weltering billows and dark woods, Over Mississippi's looped and tangled floods, Over the hills of Tennessee, And old Kentucky's greenery, In sun, in night, in clouds, and forth Out of the South into the North, To the spot where first the ancestral nest was swung, Where first the ancestral song was sung, Whose shadowy strains still ravish me With immemorial melody. A CREOLE SLAVE-SONG. (Ah, lo zo-zo chan' dan' branche.) What bird is that, with voice so sweet, Sings to the sun from yonder tree? What girl is that so slim and fleet, Comes through the cane her love to meet? Foli zo-zo, sing merrily. The pretty girl she comes to me! What wind is that upon the cane? What perfume from a far-off rose Fills me with dreams? What strange, vague pain Stirs in my heart? What longing vain Is this that through my bosom goes? Oh, south wind, perfume and desire, You kiss, you soothe, you burn like fire! Ah, no! Ah, no! It is a cheat. There is no bird; my love comes not; The wind chills me from head to feet, And oh, it brings no perfume sweet. My slender girl the white man bought, And took her far across the bay— I cannot cut the cane to-day! I cannot cut the cane to-day— O zo-zo, moqueur, come and sing! O warm wind, through the cane-field stray, Wave the long moss so soft and gray! I have no heart for anything; But life was Heaven and work was play When my love loved me every day! White man, how I worked for you, When I was young and blithe and strong! The earth was green, the sky was blue, My love's eyes were as bright as dew; And life was like the zo-zo's song! But you—you sold my love away— I cannot cut the cane to-day! I did not dream a slave could be A man, and right a grievous wrong. I writhed and bore your cruelty; I felt the soul go out of me; And yet, I was so lion-strong I could have torn your heart away— I cannot cut the cane to-day! Freedom! I feel it when too late, Like Spring wind on a blasted tree, A waft of mockery and hate! Bring back my chains, O cruel Fate! Bring youth and slavery back to me; Bring back the lash, the hound, the pain, So that my own love come again! But hark! A gentle voice afar Calls me to go, I know not where— Yes, past the sun and past the star, Into God's land. A golden car And milk-white horses—she is there! So sweet—I dream—I float away— I cannot cut the cane to-day! A MORNING PRAYER. O breeze! Thou dewy, cool, sweet current of delight, Appease This longing for the ripe fruit of the right; Winnow my soul And flood my heart's cold caves with charity, And roll This burden of the love of sin from me! O sky! Pour thy vast cup of purity on me, That I May sound the flawless note of liberty, As I stand Waiting to see the flower of sunrise blow, Waiting to feel the fresher currents flow Into this morning land. O sea! Thou weltering giant, lend thy stormy voice To me, That I this day may make the earth rejoice With a sky-filling, world-o'erwhelming song, The tempest song of Freedom blowing down the walls of Wrong! Lord God! Thou master of the winds, the skies, the seas, Who trod The valley of man's lowest miseries, Lend me thy love, that I may love all men, That I may show all men the way of love, From palace high to deepest prison-den; That I may prove How Brotherhood is Freedom's other name, How Freedom's other name is but the Word, And that Word is the Lord Come down again. Amen. FULL-FLEDGED. (Une barbe de jeune dieu.) Is all discovery made? Is the hand of Conquest stayed? Are all the heroes dead, all epics told? Is Fame's grand tower no more On any height or shore? Is the bard's Excalibur worn thin and dull and old? O for a sweet, strange waft— A thrilling, hopeful draught From a land where no man's feet were ever set; Where nameless wild birds sing, And the woods and everything With fragrant, honey-flavored dews are wet! We build our ships in vain, If no new shores we gain. Though back and forth we track that Genoese Who found fresh, wholesome room For Freedom's root and bloom, Yet shall we long to sail the unknown seas! Where shall I lay my head? What grass shall be my bed? What holy, unsullied grove shall shadow me? Somewhere, somewhere I know, Untasted fountains flow And winds blow off an undiscovered sea! The clarion is whist; No knight rides down the list; High courage is but dust on rusted shields; Where grandest deeds were done, Most glorious battles won, Dull peasants plow in poor and arid fields. Old Homer and old wine, And Shakespeare the divine, And women for whose sake the world was changed,— All these are of the past; Romance has breathed her last; Genius, with lamp and lyre, through every grove has ranged. The jaded worshipers, The priests and followers Of the high God, no fresh gift-offerings bring From full-fed flocks and herds, But, mumbling unmeaning words, Burn fleshless bones and impotent censers swing. Love walks not anywhere; Venus, no longer fair, Into some lonely place has crept away; The dryad and the fawn And the river-gods are gone, And in the woods no more the lusty satyrs stray. But my young limbs are strong, My throat thirsts for a song! The meanings and the potencies of youth Are gathering in my reins And throbbing in my veins; I pant and pine for deep clean springs of Truth! I will not have the lute, Nor that old, worm-bitten flute Bequeathed by gods to the dull line of bards. Charmed reeds of song there are By happy streams afar, And I shall cut mine own, despite what demon guards! Ready, clear-eyed, alert, Mine own I shall assert, Repeating no man's manner, no man's note; But gathering from primal sources The pure and subtle forces That shall with rarest resonance flood my throat. I cannot stand and wait I have no faith in Fate. The sinews of my body, lithe and clean, Promise a better turn Than all the stars that burn, As o'er Morn's outmost rosy rim I lean. I will not look behind; But down some brisk, sharp wind, Exulting, into the future I shall spring, Brown-limbed, anointed, free, To breast swift floods and see What wider view Time's highest tide shall bring! I shall not tire or fail; Strange essence shall exhale (Suggesting life immortal) from my song, And all the world shall smile, Half-owning for a while The influence of the healthful and the strong! I shall break every chain, To farthest heights attain, And drink from wells no face has bent above. Oh! from what heavenly place Shall leap to my embrace The warm embodiment of innocent love? THE FINAL THOUGHT. What is the grandest thought Toward which the soul has wrought? Has it the epic form, And the power of a storm? Comes it of prophecy (That borrows light of uncreated fires), Or of transmitted strains of memory Sent down through countless sires? I tiptoe on the verge Of the Future, and I urge Into vast space the cry of my despair (Which, like a sea-gull lost in upper air, Glides weakly on and on); But whither is it gone, This straying cry with human anguish fraught? What is the final thought? Which way are my feet set? Through infinite changes yet Shall I go on, Nearer and nearer drawn To Thee, God of eternity? How shall the human grow, By changes fine and slow, To Thy perfection from the life-dawn sought? What is the highest thought? Ah, these dim memories Of when Thy voice spake lovingly to me, Under the Eden trees, Saying: “Lord of all creation thou shalt be,” How they haunt me and elude— How they hover, how they brood, On the horizon, fading yet dying not! What is the final thought? What if I once did dwell In the lowest dust germ-cell, A faint fore-hint of life called forth of God, Waxing and struggling on, Through the long, flickering dawn, The awful while His feet earth's bosom trod? What if He shaped me so, And caused my life to blow Into the full soul-flower in Eden-air? Lo! now I am not good, And I stand in solitude, Calling to Him (and yet He answers not): What is the final thought? What myriads of years up from the germ! What countless ages back from man to worm! And yet from man to God, oh help me now! A cold despair is beading on my brow! I may see Him, and seeing know Him not! What is the highest thought? Oh, higher than the skies My ecstatic prayers arise! The stars hear them go by Into the regions of Eternity— The angels meet them wandering after Him, Begging for just one ray Of perfect light across the spaces dim To guide me on my long and lonely way. Oh, lead me, I am blind! Back, back, until I find The rapture-haunted spot, Where still the all-creative Essence fills Forms (out of dead clay wrought) With godlike souls and heaven-aspiring wills— Back to the highest thought! A fragrant breath goes by; A subtile waft, from some far paradise, Blows on me fitfully, And colors, half unseen, allure my eyes, All sightless though they be; And so my heart is filled with wild desire, And all my soul is like a flaring fire! What is this flame in which my life is caught? Is it the highest thought? “Blasphemer, hush! The universe would rush To be a part of thee, if thou couldst know The garden where God's flowers of wisdom blow! Cry not to Him Across the spaces dim; Dare not to touch His ether with thy breath, Thou bearer of the ancient curse of death! Prayer shall avail thee not: Shrink from the final thought!” So comes, at last, The answer from the Vast.... Not so, there is a rush of wings— Earth feels the presence of invisible things, Closer and closer drawn In fragrant mists of dawn! One dies to conquer Death And to burst the awful tomb,— Lo, with His dying breath He blows love into bloom! Love! faith is born of it! Death is the scorn of it! It fills the earth and thrills the heaven above, And God is love, And life is love, and, though we heed it not, Love is the final thought. NECTAR AND AMBROSIA. If I were a poet, my sweetest song Should have the bouquet of scuppernong, With a racy smack in every line From the savage juice of the muscadine. The russet persimmon, the brown papaw, The red wild plum and the summer haw, Serviceberries and mandrake fruit, Sassafras bark and ginseng root, Should make my verse pungent and sweet by turns; And the odor of grass and the freshness of ferns, The kernels of nuts and the resins of trees, The nectar distilled by the wild honey-bees, Should be thrown in together, to flavor my words With the zest of the woods and the joy of the birds! Who sings by note, from the page of a book, So sweet a tune as the brawl of a brook? Shall Homer, or shall Anacreon Suggest as much as the wind or the sun? Give me a shell from the sea so green, Cut me a flute from the Aulocrene, Give me Nature's sweets and sours, Her barks and nuts, her fruits and flowers; And all the music I make shall be Good as the sap of the maple-tree, Whilst a rare bouquet shall fill my song From the muscadine and the scuppernong. A DREAM OF ROMANCE. The day is but a breezy dream, The sky is like a bloom; Life flows, a fragrant, bubbling stream, Along a lilied flume. The wandering butterfly is lost In films of mystery, From supple flower to flower is tossed The worried bumblebee. On high some idle spirit sings, Half sleeping, as it flies, Dropping from its charmëd wings The dews of Paradise. The pines are dozing, and the sea Is murmuring in its sleep; All round the sky rim drowsily Some shadowy wonders creep. The mosses drop their curtains low, The far ships settle down, And tenderly the Gulf winds blow, O'er Bay Saint Louis town. And lo! am I a mote to dance And shimmer here and there, Where faded beams of old romance Strike slantwise through the air. A weltering sound, remote and vast, Comes to my drowsy ear; The Gulf waves rolling from the past Suggest the buccaneer. A corsair sloop, hull down, retires With mysteries in her hold; Her sails, against the wizard fires Of morn, are torn and old. The buccaneer! The buccaneer! My boyhood dreams come true; What wild uproar is this I hear Across the waters blue? “Welcome! my brawny, bearded one, Salute!” the caverns boom, And the merchantmen, far scattered, run To give his ship sea room. He answers with a growling throat; Out leaps his rusty blade, And one dull, echoing thunder-note Bounds from the carronade. Lo! all the world stands by to gaze And lean and look askance, What time the sturdy tars upraise The banner of romance. Merrily, merrily, sing the crew; Dusky and grim are they, Against the islands soft and blue And the grizzly ocean spray. What is her name? What is her name? This ship so dark and strong. Oh, she was christened Lady Fame, And built by King o' Song. And she was manned by frowzy men, Bohemians eke, who love To fight at odds, like one to ten, And reck not where they rove. And who is captain, tell us true, Of this good Lady Fame? Shouts every tar of all the crew: “Will Shakespeare is his name!” Oh, welcome, goodly ship, in haste To bring us prize and cheer From all the hoards that tempt the taste Of lawless buccaneer! Ay, we will build us crafts galore, Like Shakespeare's they shall be, And we will plunder every shore And every ship at sea. All round the deep, wave-tossed and blown, Led by the Lady Fame, Our fleet shall make the world its own, Reckless of shame or blame. The South, the North, the East, the West, Our shout and rout shall hear; Oh, who shall foil, or who arrest The ruthless buccaneer? 'T was thus I dreamed, one balmy day, When dim ships went, hull down, Against the sky line far away, Off Bay Saint Louis town. There sapphire islands, held aloof In films of dream and chance, Between sea floor and blue sky roof, Are steeped in wild romance. So in this town I linger long, And watch and wait—alack! Never a breath of golden song Can blow the old time back! Oh, leave me thus, a mote to dance And shimmer here and there, Where faded beams of old romance Strike slantwise through the air! IN THE HAUNTS OF BASS AND BREAM. I. Dreams come true, and everything Is fresh and lusty in the spring. In groves that smell like ambergris, Wind-songs, bird-songs, never cease. Go with me down by the stream, Haunt of bass and purple bream; Feel the pleasure, keen and sweet, When the cool waves lap your feet; Catch the breath of moss and mould, Hear the grosbeak's whistle bold; See the heron all alone Midstream on a slippery stone, Or, on some decaying log, Spearing snail or water-frog. See the shoals of sun-perch shine Among the pebbles smooth and fine, Whilst the sprawling turtles swim In the eddies cool and dim! II. The busy nuthatch climbs his tree, Around the great bole spirally, Peeping into wrinkles gray, Under ruffled lichens gay, Lazily piping one sharp note From his silver mailëd throat; And down the wind the catbird's song A slender medley trails along. Here a grackle chirping low, There a crested vireo; Deep in tangled underbrush Flits the shadowy hermit-thrush; Coos the dove, the robin trills, The crows caw from the airy hills; Purple finch and pewee gray, Bluebird, swallow, oriole gay,— Every tongue of Nature sings; The air is palpitant with wings. Halcyon prophecies come to pass In the haunts of bream and bass. III. Bubble, bubble, flows the stream, Like an old tune through a dream. Now I cast my silken line; See the gay lure spin and shine, While with delicate touch I feel The gentle pulses of the reel. Halcyon laughs and cuckoo cries; Through its leaves the plane-tree sighs. Bubble, bubble, flows the stream, Here a glow and there a gleam; Coolness all about me creeping, Fragrance all my senses steeping,— Spicewood, sweet-gum, sassafras, Calamus and water-grass, Giving up their pungent smells, Drawn from Nature's secret wells; On the cool breath of the morn, Perfume of the cock-spur thorn, Green spathes of the dragon-root, Indian turnip's tender shoot, Dogwood, red-bud, elder, ash, Snowy gleam and purple flash, Hillside thickets, densely green, That the partridge revels in! IV. I see the morning-glory's curl, The curious star-flower's pointed whorl; Hear the woodpecker, rap-a-tap! See him with his cardinal's cap! And the querulous, leering jay, How he clamors for a fray! Patiently I draw and cast, Keenly expectant till, at last, Comes a flash, down in the stream, Never made by perch or bream; Then a mighty weight I feel,— Sings the line and whirs the reel! V. Out of a giant tulip-tree A great gay blossom falls on me; Old gold and fire its petals are, It flashes like a falling star. A big blue heron flying by Looks at me with a greedy eye. I see a striped squirrel shoot Into a hollow maple root; A bumblebee with mail all rust, And thighs puffed out with anther-dust, Clasps a shrinking bloom about, And draws her amber sweetness out. VI. Bubble, bubble, flows the stream, Like a song heard in a dream. A white-faced hornet hurtles by, Lags a turquoise butterfly,— One intent on prey and treasure, One afloat on tides of pleasure! Sunshine arrows, swift and keen, Pierce the burr-oak's helmet green. VII. I follow where my victim leads Through tangles of rank water-weeds, O'er stone and root and knotty log, O'er faithless bits of reedy bog. I wonder, will he ever stop? The reel hums like a humming top! Through graceful curves he sweeps the line, He sulks, he starts, his colors shine, Whilst I, all flushed and breathless, tear Through lady-fern and maidenhair, And in my straining fingers feel The throbbing of the rod and reel! A thin sandpiper, wild with fright, Goes into ecstasies of flight; A gaunt green bittern quits the rushes, The yellow-throat its warbling hushes; Bubble, bubble, flows the stream, Like an old tune through a dream! VIII. At last he tires, I reel him in; I see the glint of scale and fin. The crinkled halos round him break, He leaves gay bubbles in his wake. I raise the rod, I shorten line, And safely land him,—he is mine! IX. The belted halcyon laughs, the wren Comes twittering from his bushy den; The turtle sprawls upon its log, I hear the booming of a frog. Liquidambar's keen perfume, Sweet-punk, calamus, tulip-bloom; Dancing wasp and dragon-fly, Wood-thrush whistling tenderly; Damp cool breath of moss and mould, Noontide's influence manifold; Glimpses of a cloudless sky,— Soothe me as I resting lie. Bubble, bubble, flows the stream, Like low music through a dream. TO A REALIST. A crossbow old, with lathe and gaffle grim, And carven stock, hung in a castle hall— Mere bricabrac, but on the distance dim It sketched De Jourdan's quarrel, Richard's fall. A curious ballad written by Villon (The sweet old thief)—the page was wan and sere; But genius had set a glow thereon Like memory's flush on snows that fell last year. A broken plow beside a hedgerow flung Amid the flowering weeds of early June, Told of poor Burns, who from the furrow sung The “Banks of Ayr” and “Braes o' Bonnie Doon.” A fossil skeleton, delicate and rare, A bird (held fast in rock for ages long) Freed by the quarrymen. I heard the air Eons ago thrill to its morning song! A southern zittern found at Avignon; Broken its keys with pearls and opals set; Its strings were rust, its wreathëd sound-board gone, But chords of passion wrung it fret by fret. A leathern bottle, wrinkled, black and old, And dry as dust of Eden's apple bloom— Ah, but the philter that it used to hold Haunted it with the ghost of strange perfume. A phrase by Sappho, or a violin Made at Cremona—all the bits of clay That Palissy burned deathless color in— The crudest charcoal sketches of Millet,— How rich in charm, how redolent and ripe And fertile is the purple mood they bring! The heroes fight again, Pan blows his pipe, And from the sacred groves the Muses sing. Time spares the germs that subtle genius needs; Forth from the blue of distance they are sent; And poor indeed is he who never heeds What precious hints fall from the firmament. Aloft, arear, in caverns dark, profound, Where no dull commonplace has ever been, The golden web of genius is wound, Which all the thronging world is tangled in. Genius, that wind-worn reed, unsightly, rude, Notched by some strong, untutored artisan; That golden lyre, that lute of jeweled wood, That syrinx blown by furry lips of Pan! Ah, friend, as you read Keats one starry night, While on the world lay dreams and mystery, You felt a thrill, trembled, and cried outright: “Young god! Strange boy! Let go the heart of me!” AMERICA. Low-hung in darkness, steeped in tyranny, The earth was but a prison-pen for man, When a swift impulse leaped from sea to sea, And round the sodden zones a flash of fervor ran. A throb of God's great heart with sympathy Shook all the world. The torn sky and the stars Draped the majestic form of Liberty, The while around the West she built her golden bars. There was a sound of thunder rolling far, When Freedom's forest-altar was begun, A song of star that answered unto star, When Freedom's heaven-high temple in the West was done! Done? Oh, never done! the builder buildeth fair, Stone upon stone, that all the world may know; Higher and higher, in purer veins of air, The parapets of love, the towers of beauty grow. The slave whose ear feels yet the post and nail, The serf in some Siberian hell, the oppressed Of rack-rent, and the debtor in the jail, All pray with hopeful faces yearning to the West. Reality of life's divine romance Befalls what time the broken chains crash down; And lo! full manhood, leaping from a trance Shakes off the chrysalis shell of trodden clod and clown. Oh, brothers, come! The breath of heaven is here! One draught can make the slave and master one! The grace of liberty softens year by year, And in a richer flood the stream of life flows on. But come not here to batter and debase, Nor hoping to reach license unconfined; No alien hand our inscriptions may efface, Justice may be, but vigilant Freedom is not, blind! Come rather as the bridegroom to the bride, Or as a man made free to freeborn man, Love-blown across the ocean wild and wide, Upon our shores, to be a true American! And join our song, oh, every alien tongue, Make thunder-music on our highest wall, While hearts of kings are faint and terror-wrung, And all the olden thrones are toppling to their fall! America, new gospel bearer, hail! Thou second coming of the loving Lord! Thy thousand years of glory cannot fail, Thou dewy, bloom-sweet resurrection of God's word! Thy destiny the Father's fingers wove, The spell of power is on thee. Sweet and strong Flames in thine eyes the fire of heavenly love, And from thy brimming heart leaps love's immortal song! AN ADDRESS BY AN EX-CONFEDERATE SOLDIER, TO THE GRAND ARMY OF THE REPUBLIC. I. I was a rebel, if you please, A reckless fighter to the last, Nor do I fall upon my knees And ask forgiveness for the past. A traitor? I a traitor? No! I was a patriot to the core; The South was mine, I loved her so, I gave her all,—I could no more. You scowl at me. And was it wrong To wear the gray my father wore? Could I slink back, though young and strong, From foes before my mother's door? My mother's kiss was hot with fight, My father's frenzy filled his son, Through reeking day and sodden night My sister's courage urged me on. And I, a missile steeped in hate, Hurled forward like a cannon-ball By the resistless hand of fate, Rushed wildly, madly through it all. I stemmed the level flames of hell, O'er bayonet bars of death I broke, I was so near when Cleburne fell, I heard the muffled bullet stroke! But all in vain. In dull despair I saw the storm of conflict die; Low lay the Southern banner fair, And yonder flag was waving high. God, what a triumph had the foe! Laurels, arches, trumpet-blare; All around the earth their songs did go, Thundering through heaven their shouts did tear. My mother, gray and bent with years, Hoarding love's withered aftermath, Her sweet eyes burnt too dry for tears, Sat in the dust of Sherman's path. My father, broken, helpless, poor, A gloomy, nerveless giant stood, Too strong to cower and endure, Too weak to fight for masterhood. My boyhood's home, a blackened heap Where lizards crawled and briers grew, Had felt the fire of vengeance creep, The crashing round-shot hurtle through. I had no country, all was lost, I closed my eyes and longed to die, While past me stalked the awful ghost Of mangled, murdered Liberty. The scars upon my body burned, I felt a heel upon my throat, A heel that ground and grinding turned With each triumphal trumpet note. “Grind on!” I cried, “nor doubt that I, (If all your necks were one and low As mine is now) delightedly Would cut it by a single blow!” II. That was dark night; but day is here, The crowning victory is won; Hark, how the sixty millions cheer, With Freedom's flag across the sun! I a traitor! Who are you That dare to breathe that word to me? You never wore the Union blue, No wounds attest your loyalty! I do detest the sutler's clerk, Who skulked and dodged till peace had come, Then found it most congenial work To beat the politician's drum. I clasp the hand that made my scars, I cheer the flag my foemen bore, I shout for joy to see the stars All on our common shield once more. I do not cringe before you now, Or lay my face upon the ground; I am a man, of men a peer, And not a cowering, cudgeled hound! I stand and say that you were right, I greet you with uncovered head, Remembering many a thundering fight, Where whistling death between us sped. Remembering the boys in gray, With thoughts too deep and fine for words, I lift this cup of love to-day To drink what only love affords. Soldiers in blue, a health to you! Long life and vigor oft renewed, While on your hearts, like honey-dew, Falls our great country's gratitude. AN INCIDENT OF WAR. Our new flagbearer, pale and slim, A beardless youth of quiet mien, Much chaffed at by old soldiers grim (Before in battle he had been), Hid the heroic fire in him. He sang old hymns and prayed at night; “A bad sign,” quoth the sergeant bold, “Camp-meeting tunes before a fight Loosen a soldier's moral hold, And pluck beats prayer a mighty sight.” The boy blushed red, but tenderly He to the sergeant turned and said: “That God should mind me what am I? And yet by Him my soul is fed— Send this to mother if I die.” The sergeant, with a knowing look, And winking at the rest, replied: “Yes, son, I'll give your ma the book”— Just then a volley rattled wide And one great gun the valley shook. The pale flagbearer disappeared. “Gone to the rear,” the sergeant said; “Praying would make a Turk afeared; Those lonesome tunes have turned his head”— And then the tide of battle neared. We formed in haste and dashed away, Across the field, our place to fill; At first a skirmish, then a spray Of cannon smoke upon a hill Flanked by long lines in close array. Down charged the foe; we rushed to meet, We filled the valley like a sea, The cannons flashed a level sheet Of blinding flame, the musketry Cut men as sickles cut the wheat! Oh, then we shouted! More and more The fervor of our courage rose, As through our solid columns tore The death hail's crashing, gusty blows, And louder leaped the cannon roar! But how could human courage meet That icy flood? All, all in vain Our counter charge; in slow retreat We crossed the tumbled heaps of slain, With grave-pits yawning at our feet! “Rally! For shame!” rang out a cry Forth from the thundering vortex cast; A voice so steady, clear, and high, It sounded like a bugle-blast Blown from the lips of victory. We paused, took hope, yelled loud, and so Renewed the charge, all as one man, Leaped where Death's waves had thickest flow, And felt the breath of horror fan Our naked souls as cold as snow! The volleys quickened, coalesced, Rolled deep, rocked earth and jarred the sky, When lo! our banner bearer pressed His standard forward, held it high And rode upon the battle's crest. We saw him, wave it over all; Caught in the battle trough and dashed From side to side, it would not fall; But like a meteor danced and flashed And reveled in the sulphurous pall! We swept the field and won the hill; Our flag flared out upon the crest, Where wavering, gasping, pale and chill, A dozen bullets through his breast, The slender hero held it still! We leaped to lift his drooping head, The sergeant clasped him to his breast; “I bore the flag,” the low voice said, “And God bore me, now let me rest,” And so we laid him with the dead. TO THE SOUTH. O subtle, musky, slumbrous clime! O swart, hot land of pine and palm, Of fig, peach, guava, orange, lime, And terebinth and tropic balm! Land where our Washington was born, When truth in hearts of gold was worn; Mother of Marion, Moultrie, Lee, Widow of fallen chivalry! No longer sadly look behind, But turn and face the morning wind, And feel sweet comfort in the thought: “With each fierce battle's sacrifice I sold the wrong at awful price, And bought the good; but knew it not.” Cheer up! Reach out! Breathe in new life! Brood not on unsuccessful strife Against the current of the age; The Highest is thy heritage! Leave off this death's-head scowl at Fate, And into thy true heart sink this: “God loves to walk where Freedom is!” There is no sweet in dregs and lees; There is no fruit on girdled trees. Plant new vineyards, sow new fields, For bread and wine the Future yields; Out of free soil fresh spathes shall start; Now is the budding-time of Art! But hark! O hear! My senses reel! Some grand presentiment I feel! A voice of love, bouquet of truth, The quick sound of the feet of youth! Lo! from the war-cloud, dull and dense, Loyal and chaste and brave and strong, Comes forth the South with frankincense, And vital freshness in her song. The weight is fallen from her wings; To find a purer air she springs Out of the Night into the Morn, Fair as cotton, sound as corn. Hold! Shall a Northman, fierce and grim, With hoary beard and boreal vim, Thus fling, from some bleak waste of ice, Frost-crystals of unsought advice To those who dwell by Coosa's stream, Or on dark hummocks plant the cane Beside the lovely Pontchartrain, Or in gay sail-boats drift and dream Where Caribbean breezes stray On Pensacola's drowsy bay? Not so! I am a Southerner; I love the South; I dared for her To fight from Lookout to the sea, With her proud banner over me: But from my lips thanksgiving broke, As God in battle thunder spoke, And that Black Idol, breeding drouth And dearth of human sympathy Throughout the sweet and sensuous South, Was, with its chains and human yoke, Blown hellward from the cannon's mouth, While Freedom cheered behind the smoke! OUR LEGEND. The legend set upon our shield Brims with grand meaning: All in one, Hearts welded, souls together run At white heat on the battlefield! One shining way for all to take, One oath, one hope, one purpose grand, One flag for all in all the land, Upheld by all for Freedom's sake. One sign set in the central sky, Read of all men alike, a name Written in empyrean flame By the bold hand of Destiny! That legend naught could dim or mar; Though bathed in tears and hid in smoke, Forth from the focal storm it broke, A bow above the cloud of war. We read it pensively and knew Some element of precious gain Had come to it from wounds and pain, And mightily its meaning grew. And so we keep upon our shield The deathless legend: All in one, Hearts welded, souls together run At white heat on the battlefield. A myriad songs, together thrown Across old gulfs of hate, are blent Like starlight in the firmament, And round the world in triumph blown. Our starry unity of stars Gives man a manly masterhood, Our law of love engrossed in blood Is sealed with burning bullet scars! A TAUNT. In the oldest wood I know a brooklet, That bubbles over stones and roots, And ripples out of hollow places, Like music out of flutes. There creeps the pungent breath of cedars, Rich coolness wraps the air about, Whilst through clear pools electric flashes Betray the watchful trout. I know where wild things lurk and linger, In groves as gray and grand as Time; I know where God has written poems Too strong for words or rhyme. Come, let us go, each pulse is precious, Come, ere the day has lost its dawn; And you shall quaff life's finest essence From primal flagons drawn! Just for a day slip off the tether Of hothouse wants, and dare to be A child of Nature, strong and simple, Out in the woods with me. Out in the woods, on freedom's bosom, We shall be worthy sons of men, Bred of remotest sires who bearded The satyr in his den. Come, just a sip of the wild man's nectar Shall show you life from a point of view As old as the oldest stones of the mountains, And yet as fresh as dew! Supple joints and bulging muscles, Sinews taut as the chords of a harp, Veins full-flushed, eyes clear as water, And all the senses sharp. Who was Shakespeare? Where is Homer? Can Milton leap, or dance, or run? Should you care to cast a fly with Walton? Do you envy Napoleon? What of this lore of buried thinkers? What of these classic depths and heights? Better one strong, bright, living creature Than a myriad trilobites! Ah, I see you scoff at my meaning, You flaccid, indolent bookworm, you! What would you give for my good digestion And my nerve-cords sound and true? MORNING DEW. When germs were quickening in the mould, And sap was rich and leaves were young, Deep in the fragrant wood a lute, As old as Time, was newly strung. Some swift, divine, invisible hand, From fret to fret, tried all the chords, Until a tune, supremely sweet, Was set to immemorial words. And then the wild bird sought its mate; The lusty bee a-booming came; The maples, filled with racy pangs, Let go their buds' imprisoned flame; A dreamy mystery veiled the sun; Keen perfumes stole through glade and grove, And all the founts of Nature burst With sudden bubbling streams of love! Ah! passion, pure as morning dew, And fresh as breath of mint and thyme! Impulse of Spring, so new and true! Essence of innocence and prime! I bowed my head and stilled my breath (For it was May and I was young), While to a tune supremely sweet Those immemorial words were sung. OLD ROCHON. I. It was off the coast of the Terre aux Bœufs (And the breeze was brisk and the sea was rough) That Gaspard Rochon, the buccaneer, Sailed his schooner, and right good cheer Had he on his table, with pipes and wine, As he feasted the mate of the Caroline. II. The Caroline was a cruiser craft; Rochon had raked her fore and aft, With cannon and with carronade, And had boarded her with pike and blade, Had pillaged and sunk her; only the mate Was left to tell of his vessel's fate. III. “You fought like a tiger,” said old Rochon, “And I'll bet my schooner, the Gonfalon, That you have heard the broadsides roar And the cutlasses clang ofttimes before.” “Yes,” growled the mate, “for many a year I 've battled with pirate and buccaneer.” IV. “Drink and be merry,” the outlaw said; Drink to the living and drink to the dead. Drink pale sherry and drink old port! Eat and be merry, for life is short! Ay, drink like a fish and eat like a swine, For death may follow when pirates dine!” V. “By the way,” said the mate, “did you ever hear Of old Rochon, the buccaneer, Who used to sail the southern seas, With his rendezvous in the Florida keys?” “Perchance I have,” was the curt reply, With a savage gleam from the old man's eye. VI. “He was a terror,” the mate went on, (All unaware that he faced Rochon) “A cut-throat villain, a coward, too, With a stolen ship and a dastard crew;— But his race is ended, he 's feared no more By women and children on sea or shore.” VII. Over the mate, from head to heel, The pirate outflung a glance of steel. “Gaspard Rochon was a buccaneer Who never felt a touch of fear,” He said, “and I 'd like to drink a cup With the tar who broke his cruising up!” VIII. “Well,” said the mate, “I ran him down, Burnt his vessels and razed his town; Women and men, every devil's one, I killed of the gang, save old Rochon, Who made escape with loss of an ear.” “And who cut that?” roared the buccaneer. IX. “Who but I?” sang out the mate. “My cutlass glanced from his flinty pate And shaved his ear off, close and clean, Which I have in my pouch as dry as a bean.” “Show me,” the old man stormed, “that ear Of old Rochon the buccaneer!” X. “Here it is,” said the mate with pride, As out of the pouch that hung by his side He drew the relic and held it high, Like a bit of parchment brown and dry. “Ha! ha! ha!” laughed the buccaneer, “Eat and drink and have good cheer! XI. “Drink pale sherry and drink red port! Eat and be merry, for life is short!” And then he hurried the mate on deck And tied a halliard around his neck, While the crew stood by to haul away, And a hunchback fifer began to play. XII. For years the schooner Gonfalon Was sailed by the savage old Rochon, And wherever she went, at her topmast high Dangled a corpse against the sky— A corpse that like a mummy grew And lightly about in the breezes blew! XIII. Oh, red were the deeds of old Rochon And wild were the crew of the Gonfalon! In every nook of the Spanish main The cruisers cruised for them in vain, While they robbed and feasted and drank good wine To the health of the mate of the Caroline! A STUDY FOR THE CRITICS. A great king once, so I have heard, Went out to hunt a singing-bird Whose voice should be so sweet and strong, So fraught with all the tricks of song, That they who heard it would confess The king's fine taste and perfectness Of judgment. And it came to pass That where the wind poured through the grass, Fringing a brooklet's sinuous way, He saw a bird demure and gray, Of awkward mien and sleepy eyed, Bathing in the crystal tide. “O bird!” the king said, looking down, “A monarch I of high renown, Out searching for a singing-bird Whose voice, the sweetest ever heard, Shall cheer me in my hours of gloom, And coax my dead loves back to bloom.” “Take me, O king,” the gray bird said. “A sad and lonely life I 've led, Singing with not a soul to hear, Pining for but one word of cheer.” “Thou!” cried the king, half in surprise, A sudden anger in his eyes— “Thou insignificant, nameless bird! Thou ninny, hast thou never heard Of my grand palace and my throne Of pearl and gold and precious stone? Thou gray, sad eyed, presumptuous thing! Thou entertain a court and king! Begone! Say not another word: My cage must hold a royal bird.” There came a silken sound of wings Above the brooklet's murmurings; The wind fell still upon the grass To watch the gray bird upward pass; The sunlight milder, softer grew; The leaves took on a tenderer hue— As if all Nature, gently stirred, Bade farewell to the going bird. The monarch stood with lips compressed, Regret and choler in his breast, While from the sky, well-sent and strong, Came back a Parthian shaft of song. THE GOLD-BIRD. The gold-bird came in the May morn Down fragrant billows of southwest weather: He fell, like a flame, in the sweet thorn,— He and his brown mate close together. This was the promise of May-time; Wind-song and bird-song sweetly flowing Over the thorn, like a love-rhyme, Where buds were breaking and flowers were blowing. The gold-bird sang to his brown mate A song no words of mine may render, While she built a nest in the sweet thorn, In the dusky deeps of the thorn leaves tender. This was the joy of the May-time: A bird like a flame and a love like fire, The weather set to a soft tune Thrilled and filled with pure desire. The gold-bird sat by his brown mate, Brooding their young through the drowsy weather, And when June came with its red heat The birds and their brood flew off together. O sweet fulfillment of May-time! A gold-bird, a brown mate, a nest and fruition Of all the joys of a love-song! This was the whole of the gold-bird's mission. THE KINGFISHER. He laughs by the summer stream Where the lilies nod and dream, As through the sheen of water cool and clear He sees the chub and sunfish cutting sheer. His are resplendent eyes; His mien is kingliwise; And down the May wind rides he like a king, With more than royal purple on his wing. His palace is the brake Where the rushes shine and shake; His music is the murmur of the stream, And that leaf-rustle where the lilies dream. Such life as his would be A more than heaven to me: All sun, all bloom, all happy weather, All joys bound in a sheaf together. No wonder he laughs so loud! No wonder he looks so proud! There are great kings would give their royalty To have one day of his felicity! UNAWARE. There is a song some one must sing, In tender tones and low, With pink lips curled and quivering, And eyes with dreams aglow. There is some one must hear the tune, And feel the thrilling words, As flowers feel, in early June, The wings of humming-birds. And she who sings must never learn What good her song has done, Albeit the hearer slowly turn Him drowsily, as one Who feels through all his being thrown The influence sweet and slight Of strange, elusive perfume, blown Off dewy groves by night! FAREWELL. Farewell! It is no sorrowful word. It has never had a pang for me. Sweet as the last song of a bird, Soft as a wind-swell from the sea, The word Farewell. I part with you as oft before I 've parted with dear friends and sweet, And now I shake (forevermore) Your memory's gold-dust from my feet. Farewell! farewell! Soon I shall find a new sweet face, And other eyes as pure and strong As yours are now, and then a space Of life that ripples into song, And then farewell! Farewell! farewell! Throw me a kiss! How fast the distance grows between! Now memory fades—a film of bliss, A far-off mist of silvery sheen: Good-by! farewell!</field>
   </doc>
</add>