<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Tucker, St. George, 1752-1827</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Tucker, St. George, 1752-1827</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">tucker st george 1752 1827</field>
      <field name="author_text">Tucker, St. George, 1752-1827</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1970's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ap/uvaGenText/tei/chap_AM0656.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240350</field>
      <field name="date_text">[1977]</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:440101</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Poems of St. George Tucker of Williamsburg, Virginia 1752-1827</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Poems of St. George Tucker of Williamsburg, Virginia 1752-1827</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poems of st george tucker of williamsburg virginia 1752 1827</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poems of st george tucker of williamsburg virginia 1752 1827</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Poems of St. George Tucker of Williamsburg, Virginia 1752-1827</field>
      <field name="year_display">[1977]</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1977</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1977</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440101&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440101&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Tucker, St. George, 1752-1827&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;tucker st george 1752 1827&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Poems of St. George Tucker of Williamsburg, Virginia 1752-1827&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poems of st george tucker of williamsburg, virginia 1752 1827&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;[1977]&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1977&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Tucker, St. George&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1752&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1827&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Poems of St. George Tucker of Williamsburg, Virginia 1752-1827&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;New York, Washington&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Vantage Press&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;[1977]&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3866250-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;cham0656&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Poems of St. George Tucker of Williamsburg, Virginia 1752-1827&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1996&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1996 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 175 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries, introductory and editorial matter</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-AmPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">POEMS AMONG FRIENDS Written on Miss Cocke's Wedding Day. Of all the sprightly girls in town, In sack, or negligee, or gown, Or plain Virginia frock, There's none that can a charm impart To captivate a faithful heart Like lovely Patsy Cocke. So graceful is her mien and air, And then her face is wondrous fair The man must be a block, Who's unsubdued by charms like these, And makes it not his joy to please The lovely Patsy Cocke. But hark. She speaks: the youthful train Attentive listening to the strain, In crowds around her flock. So very pungent is your wit You knock down all you plan to hit My charming Patsy Cocke. Would fate to me this fair one grant, (If I was out of reach of want) I'd take her in her smock: Content with what my fortune gave No other riches would I crave But thee, my Patsy Cocke. The mariner, who, tempest tost, Beholds his laboring vessel lost And dashed against a rock, Never felt such anguish and despair As I in losing thee, my fair, My charming Patsy Cocke. Jan. 14, 1775 The Belles of Williamsburg Wilt thou, adventurous pen, describe, The gay, delightful, silken tribe, That maddens all our city; Nor dread, lest while you foolish claim, A near approach to beauty's flame, Icarus' fate may hit ye! With singed pinions tumbling down, The scorn and laughter of the town, Thou'lt rue thy daring flight, While every miss, with cool contempt, Affronted by the bold attempt, Will tittering, view thy plight. Yet girls, to you devoted ever, The object still of our endeavor, Is somehow to amuse ye; And if, instead of higher praise, You only laugh at these rude lays, We'll willing excuse ye. Advance then, each illustrious maid, In order bright, to our parade, With beauty's ensigns gay! And first two nymphs who rural plains Forsook, disdaining rustic swains, And here exert their sway. Myrtilla's beauties, who can paint! The well-turned form, the glowing taint, May deck a common creature; But who can make the expressive soul, With lively sense inform the whole, And light up every feature? At church Myrtilla lowly kneels, No passion but devotion feels, No smiles her looks environ; But let her thoughts to pleasure fly. The basilisk is in her eye, And on her tongue the siren. Fond youth! no longer gaze—beware, Lest once enclosed, the dangerous fair, May leave you in the lurch: The god who poets makes his case, I supplicate, that I may ne'er Behold her—but at church. More vivid beauty, fresher bloom, With taints from nature's richest loom, In Sylvia's features glow: Would she Myrtilla's arts apply, And catch the magic of her eye. She'd rule the world below. See Laura, sprightly nymph, advance, Thro' all the mazes of the dance, With light, fantastic toe! See laughter sparkling in her eyes! “These two lines were written by a gentleman at that time very much enamored of the lady characterized under the name of Laura, and afterwards married her. Col. Banister”— Tucker. At her approach new joys arise, New fires within us glow. Such sweetness in her look is seen, Such brilliant elegance of mien, So jaunty and so airy; Her image in our fancy reigns, All night she gallops thru' our brains, Like little Mab, the fairy. Aspasia next, with kindred soul, Disdains the passions that control Each gently pleasing art: Her sportive wit, her frolic lays, And graceful form attract our praise, And steal away the heart. We see in gentle Delia's face, Expressed by every melting grace, The sweet complacent mind While hovering round her, soft desires And hope, gay smiling fan their fires, Each shepherd thinks her kind. The god of love mistook the maid For his own Psyche, and 'tis said He still remains her slave: And when the boy directs her eyes, To pierce where every passion lies, Not age itself can save! With pensive look, and head reclined, Sweet emblems of the purest mind, Lo! where Cordelia sits; On Dion's image dwells the fair, Dion, the thunderbolt of war, The prince of modern wits! Not far removed from her side Statira sits in beauty's pride, And rolls about her eyes: Thrice happy for the unwary heart, That affection blunts the dart, Which from her quiver flies. Whence does that beam of beauty dawn? What luster overspreads the lawn? What suns those rays dispense? From Artemisia's brow they came; From Artemisia's eyes the flame; That dazzles every sense. But who is she, whose massy chain A motley tribe of youths sustain And frisk and dance around her? Like Cerberus they guard the fair, With triple clamors fill the air, And with the din confound her. 'Tis Melissandra, matchless fair! The widowed prey to black despair By Damon's loss oppressed, Whom neither fond attempts to gain, Nor antic gambols in her chain Can banish from her breast. Thrice happy Damon, that you died, Where sepulture is ne'er denied, To any pious swain! For if, on this side of the Styx, You wandered still, such curious tricks Might bring you back again. At length fatigued with beauty's blaze The feeble muse no more essays Her picture to complete, The promised charms of younger girls, When nature the gay scene unfurls, Some happier bard shall treat. 1777. A Dream on Bridecake “The following [two] dreams were written at the wedding of Mr. Nelson and Miss Cary, and were produced for the entertainment of the company each morning when they assembled at breakfast: the ceremony of putting bridecake under the head at night having been previously observed by the whole company.” Dear girls, since you the task impose Of scribbling rhyme, or humbler prose, Whene'er the bridecake fills the brain With emblematic dreams of pain, Or pleasure to be had hereafter, Or, whatso'er can move your laughter, The swain to you devoted ever Will every try his best endeavor, To tell you in his doggerel strain, What fancies visited his brain. Brimful of claret wine and perry, You know I went to bed quite merry, But, as I soon grew wonderous sick, I wished my carcass at Old Nick. At length, I sunk into a nap, With head reclined in fancy's lap; She rubbed my temples, chaffed my brain, And then displayed this scene of pain. Methought, the claret I'd been drinking So far from giving aid to thinking, Had muddled my idea-box, And clapped my body in the stocks. Beneath a beach's spreading shade At lubber's length my limbs were laid; My tongue alone had power to move, To rest in vain might wish to rove: Just then, my Flora passing by This pretty object chanced to spy; The wanton saw my hapless case, And clapped me in a warm embrace; Her balmy lips to mine she pressed, And leaned her bosom on my breast, Her fingers everywhere were gadding, And set my soul a madding; Whilst I, in vain, resistance made, Still on my back supinely laid. She whispered something in my ear Which I could not distinctly hear: Then cried, “Pray when will you be sober?” “My dear,” said I, “not till October. “My nerves I find are all unstrung “Except the one that rules my tongue; “Their wonted tones so wholly lost “I shan't recover till a frost.” Away the wanton baggage flew Laughing like any one of you And left me in that sordid plight, To mourn the follies of the night. Sept. 19, 1777 A Second Dream on Bridecake Well—sure no mortal e'er was cursed With dreams like mine—for they're the worst That ever visited a sinner, E'en after fat turtle dinner, And six good bottles to defend him From evils that might else attend him. Methought, I turned a mighty rover Resolved new countries to discover, And having travelled all around The globe, a desert isle I found, Where witches with their train resort To amuse themselves with magic sport. As soon as I set foot on land, And, in an instant—think how shocking! Turned me into a white silk stocking, Then wrapped me up among a dozen Which she was carrying to a cousin. Thru' various stores and shops I past, But got to Williamsburg at last, Where Flora, to the country gadding Resolved to buy me for a wedding: My fate I thought was much improved, For Flora was the maid I loved; But, little dreamed of pains in store, Such as ne'er mortal felt before. The wedding day at length was come, The girls retired to a room, Where first they dizzen out the bride, That done—they for themselves provide. My Flora laid me on the bed Whilst she was dressing out her head; And little thinking who was near, She laid her snowy bosom bare, Then wiped her ivory neck and breast, And then proceeded with the rest. But now, began the dreadful part, Which plunged a dagger in my heart; She thrust her hand into my throat, And quickly turned me, inside out; Then raised her pretty little foot, And finding that my mouth would suit, She drew me quickly on her heel, Which made my very vitals feel. But, here methinks I shall disclose The beauty of her foot and toes; Her foot and toes were alabaster And whiter, far, than Paris plaster; Of mother-pearl I thought her nails Or else, the silverfish's scales. She tried to draw me on her leg, I stuck, and would compassion beg, But, as, alas, I could not speak, She forced me on without a squeak. Her polished knee I next embraced, And there I stuck until the last; For tho' she wished to draw me higher, Yet, troth, I would not venture nigher. Then to my grief, and great surprise She with her garter bound my eyes. Good heaven, was ever such a case? Was ever man in such a place? My Flora tripped about, but where She went, her stocking still was there; I still embraced her leg and knee, But yet no object could I see, Until she went to bed at night, When she restored me to my sight; But then, with wonder and surprise, Poor I, like Milton, lost my eyes; And thus to utter darkness hurled, I wished myself in the other world. Sept. 20, 1777 Christmas Verses for the Printer's Devil, 1784 Now the season for mirth and good eating advances, Plays, oysters and sheldrakes, balls, mince pies and dances; Fat pullets, fat turkeys, and fat geese to feed on, Fat mutton and beef; more by half than you've need on; Fat pigs and fat hogs, fat cooks and fat venison, Fat aldermen ready the haunch to lay hands on; Fat wives and fat daughters, fat husbands and sons, Fat doctors and parsons, fat lawyers and duns: What a dancing and fiddling, and gobbling and grunting, As if Nimrod himself had just come in from hunting! These all are your comforts—while mine are so small, I may truly be said to have nothing at all. I'm a Devil you know, and can't live without fire, From your doors I can see it, but I dare not come nigher; Now if you refuse me some wood, or some coal, I must e'en go and warm, in old Beelzebub's hole; Next, tho' I'm a devil, I drink and I eat, Therefore stand in need of some rum, wine and meat; Some clothes too I want—for I'm blacker than soot, And a hat, and some shoes, for my horns and my foot; To supply all these wants, pray good people be civil And give a few pence to a poor printer's devil. Dec. 25, 1784 To Sleep 1 Come gentle Sleep and weigh my eyelids down And o'er my senses shed oblivion's balm, 'Tis thine alone corroding care to drown, 'Tis thine alone the troubled soul to calm. 2 'Tis thine t'assuage the cruel stings of grief, And scatter roses o'er a bed of thorns. From thee alone affliction seeks relief Even whilst from others that relief she scorns. 3 Thou o'er misfortune throwest thy murky veil And from our eyes dost kindly hide the past, Touched by thy poppies memory too shall fail, And reason bend, like willows with the blast. 4 Thy dreams past happiness can bring again, And to a dungeon give an Eden's charms; Pluck from my heart its agonizing pain, Restore my love—my Fanny to my arms— 5 This bed the scene of all my joys and woes Awakes Remembrance with her busy train, Where Bliss unrivalled used to court repose, Unrivalled Sorrow wakes to endless pain. 6 Dear partner of my blissful hour and care Friend of my soul, and mistress of my heart With thee, e'en wretchedness could bliss appear, Without thee, even blessings yield a smart. 7 Come then O Sleep, on downy pinions come By dreams attended, hover 'round my head, Convey my sorrows to the silent tomb And raise a sleeping angel from the dead. Jan. 24, 1788 To Mr. Page on His Marriage Farewell rhyming; farewell writing Dodesley, too, a long farewell Love and Hymen now inviting P—must break your magic spell. Rhyme like Circe's draught bewitching I was scribbling day and night Scratching, thus produced by itching Still increases the delight. Dodesley next my thought engrosses. Merchants, thus, by fortune blessed To secure their wealth from losses Lock it, in an iron chest. Love and Hymen now inviting P—must break the magic spell Farewell rhyming, farewell writing Dodesley, too, a long farewell. Mar. 1790 To Mr. Page On His Marriage to Miss Lowther Friend of my heart! may this auspicious day Renew those blessings which you once enjoyed. Oh! may they ne'er again be snatched away, Nor e'er thy peace of mind again destroyed. May all thy sorrows past be like a dream, From which the troubled sleeper wakes to bliss; So shall thy past and future blessings seem But one protracted scene of happiness. Whate'er of earthly, or of heavenly charms Adorned thy Fanny's form, or face or mind When bounteous heaven gave her to thy arms; On! mays't thou in thy Margarita find. Thus with each charm and grace and virtue stored, Which heaven propitious to thy Fanny gave, In her, thy Fanny's self shall be restored And e'en on earth shall triumph o'er the grave. Mar. 27, 1790 Hymn to the Creator O God! whose word spake into birth, Whate'er existence boasts; The moon, the stars, the sun, the earth, The heavens, and all their hosts. From world to world from sun to sun, I turn my wondering eyes; Their swiftest glance thy works outrun: New suns and worlds arise! Thy wonders still my soul pursues Through each remoter world, Till sight and thought their aid refuse, To utter darkness hurled: There lost—through endless time and space I seek thy light divine: O grant me Lord! to see Thy face, But—let Thy mercy shine. Jan. 13, 1790 Riddles [1 A pearl in Latin speech shall be my first] A pearl in Latin speech shall be my first, In grammar rules, my next, a bishop versed. Judah's first born my third will just supply, Grant me, kind heaven, the whole, or let me die! Nov. 7, 1789 [2 My first a mighty kingdom shall portray] My first a mighty kingdom shall portray, Where freedom, now triumphant, bears the sway. The line of beauty as by Hogarth found, Will lengthen and at once complete the sound. My next in books—nay more in courts you'll find. The youthful virgin's form, in all combined; Whence beams the dawning of an angel's mind. 3 Charade My first in sultry climates wafts in air My next from many you may nicely pair, Two-fifths of night, with just three-fourths of cold And that which Sarah gained when she was old, A beauteous virgin's name will straight unfold. 4 Charade My first devoutly humble met reproof, In Zion's temple while she stood aloof. My next to Britain's king a terror grown, Made many a simple knight of many a drone. My whole's the picture of my last reversed, And bears a strong resemblance to my first. 5 To Mrs. Pope I saw today upon our green, A thing I have not lately seen, Although it happens night and day At balls, at concert, and at play. But that you may the more applaud, I'll tell it to you in a charade. My first at Versailles, or St. James is seen, When the idol of worship's a king or a queen. My next in all parts of the ocean is found, Except where ice-regions prescribe it a bound. My third is of lasses, and lads the delight, As witness the Capitol, this very night. Mar. 6, 1817 Epigrams [1 The charge to battle should Bellona sound] On July 30, 1791, John Page wrote Tucker, “But now for the epigram I promised in the beginning of the scrawl. It is an impromptu occasioned by Mrs. Page's telling me that Webster in one of his lectures said that the word wound was improperly pronounced woond, unless applied as in the epigram—for after writing one I ran out the thought as you say I always do in a second, a Peter Pindaric. Take them both here they are: When hostile arms assail, and you cry zounds! The deep infected strokes you may call wounds. But when by gentle glows a lover swoons, The critic Webster sounds it woonds. When Mars attacks With broadsword hacks, Each frightful gash that's found Is called a ghastly wound. When Cupid's darts Pierce soft hearts The holes they make In maid or rake, Because these die in swoons Webster says we may call “woonds.” Tucker replied with these three epigrams: The charge to battle should Bellona sound Each well-aimed stroke inflicts a ghastly wound, But pierced by Cupid's dart when Streppon swooned, Cries critic Webster softly—“What a woond!” A battle fought—cries critic Webster “Zounds! What blood and slaughter—what disastrous wounds!” But pierced by Cupid's dart when Streppon swooned He whispers softly—“bless me! what a woond!” Noah Webster's Rule of Pronouncing Simplified When Daphne, jilted at her toilet swooned, No tender heart was sunk with such a wound; But when she pricked her finger, friends around Exclaimed with horror; bless us! what a wound! [2 God's! To Elysium what a passport's here] In another undated letter, Page wrote, “Mousr. De la Borde was going on a visit to Ferney; Madam du Barry begged of him to give Voltaire two kisses from her. He sent her in return these four lines: Quoi! deux baisers sur la fin de ma vie! Quel passeport daigner vous in envoyer! Ah! c' en est trop, adorable Egerte. Je serais mort de plaisir au premier. Only think of these Verses, when he was almost eighty!” Page then offered two verse translations of his own: Ah, dear Egeria you have given One passport sure too much, One kiss would send me quick to heaven Of what use then two such? What! two kisses when near my end! What passport have you deigned to give me! Ah! too much of it my dear you send The first with joy would kill, believe me Tucker replied with this one: God's! To Elysium what a passport's here! Two kisses by Egeria given! The second I shall lose, I fear: Transported by the first to heaven. [3 A subject to write a farce on] A subject to write a farce on; All drest so fine! ... to see the parson. [4 Columbia's flag displays an emblem bright] Columbia's flag displays an emblem bright, New stripes her lashes mark—new stars her night. 5 On Reading of Tho Heath's Motion in Congress to Prohibit the Printing of the Speeches of the Members Yes, Johnny, thou art surely right The Press's freedom to subdue, For should they print what you indite T'would damn the press, as well as you. 6 On Reading a Ridiculous Encomium on General Washington The fool that should a diamond varnish, Its genuine luster would but tarnish; So 'tis when fools by flattery aim, To gild a truly glorious name. [7 Quoth Jed to Tim, where did our John] Quoth Jed to Tim, where did our John Such heaps of knowledge gather. As if in Paradise he'd been, With Eve—or Satan, rather? Quoth Tim, I guess that famous tree That once in Eden grew, Hath been transplanted to our town, And got a name quite new. For sure as Latin's learned at college At Braintree John picked up his knowledge. 8 Impromptu, on Seeing the Name of Wilson Curle Carved in a Corner of the House of Delegates in Williamsburg, Dated 1776 Whilst on this floor some rise to deathless fame, Curle in the corner sits and carves his name. (Perhaps better thus:) Here Henry spoke, and rose to deathless fame: Curle in the corner sat, and carved his name. 9 Written in a County Courthouse Here Justice sits and holds her scales: But ah! her balance often fails. 10 On a Young Lady Vain of the Number of Her Admirers See beauteous Chloe, followed by a train Of powdered coxcombs, of their number vain: If numerous sweethearts constitutes a toast, Her namesake in the kennel more can boast. 11 Epigram When Celia dances, 'tis with as much force, As any racer, straining o'er the course! Her face, at once, all water and all fire; If this enflames, that quenches all desire. 12 On the Same Diana's nymphs returning from the chase In crystal streams their fervid limbs solace; But through the dance when lovely Celia flies, Each friendly pore, a cooling stream supplies. [13 When lovely Sappho on the guitar plays] When lovely Sappho on the guitar plays A gentle rill comes trickling thru' her stays, Till overwhelmed with exercise and heat She seems a water nymph; dissolved in sweat. To William Nelson Esq., of Charles-City How great your misfortune, dear Will, I can't well say, In losing our sweet entertainment at Chelsa, Where Madam Dunbarton had asked us to meet her And partake of a frolic, I think called sham Peter. But there was no sham—for we had in reality The cream of good cheer, with true hospitality. But first, like old Homer, methinks I should tell The names of the party that pleased me so well. Sweet Madam Dunbarton, our hostess, you know, Whose roses will ever continue to blow; Who like a ripe peach in the summer, is sweeter, Than the blossoms of spring, so much praised in meter. Next Laura the sprightly, so cheerful and gay, You would swear she was just in the middle of May: Like Hebe, by time, she no older appears, For it adds to her charms, as well as her years. Aunt Betty comes next, who careless, through life Has past all her days, without being a wife; And if all her days she could pass o'er again, I'm persuaded, through choice, she would careless remain. Our good friends the Doctor and Madam Barraud, Were both somewhat late in getting abroad. Our hearts were rejoiced when we saw her appear. Though rather too late to partake our good cheer. But as to the Doctor he ate very hearty, And to tell you the truth was the life of the party. Fanny Currie, Miss Dawson, Miss Farley and Fan, With my Godson I? C? that pretty young man, Messieurs W? and B?, Adonises Twain, In the eyes of the lasses who dance on the plain, With Madame, and myself, though last not the least, In my love and affection attended the feast. Three chariots, together, in order proceed, To these on gay horses our gallants succeed; Whilst the hearts of the lasses did terribly flutter, 'Twixt thinking of them, and Madame's bread and butter. Arrived, in the orchard a carpet we found, That was spread to prevent any damps from the ground, While the fruit on the trees hung in clusters around. A table with teacups and saucers was spread, When presently entered the butter and bread. The last like a sponge—the butter so nice, Like a marigold yellow, was covered with ice. Apoquimini cakes, with a delicate shad, Cold ham and broiled chicken, the best to be had, All seasoned with mirth and good humor unfeigned So keen were our stomachs as well as our wits That we dwelt a long while on the savory bits; Then with sherbert and negus the banquet was crowned Whilst the toast and the sentiment gaily went 'round. Till perceiving the approach of the heat of the day, We reluctantly parted, and all drove away, And made such a rout, as we entered the town You would almost have thought that the college fell down. July 9, 1795 To Miss Fanny Currie No language, dear Fanny, can tell you the rout That in sweet little Williamsburg lately fell out, Occasioned, good luck! by the wonderful news, Of a cargo of ribbons, and gauzes, and shoes. Miss C? who the first the glad tidings received Out of breath ran to tell, but was scarcely believed By Mrs. B? and sweet Nancy Taylor, Who skipped topmast high, as alert as a sailor; Away then they posted to get the first sight Which put Mrs. Charlton in such a sad fright She slammed to the door of her shop in their faces. Madam T? and Dunbar who were taking a ride The throng at the door no sooner espied, Than they called out to Robin to stop, and jumped out, Like rats from their holes, when they're out to the rout. The bellman at length was sent all through the town, To proclaim that tomorrow the sight would be shown, So the ladies all homeward reluctantly sent, To wait till the night intervening was spent. Some resolved to rise early, and some to sit up, And to keep them awake took a cheerupping cup. Madam T? went to bed, but her brain was so warm, She tumbled and tossed like a ship in a storm. At midnight at length she got up and was dressed, Ere her drowsy dull husband had turned in his nest. The morning star rose, but the horns of day, Were supposed to have strayed: for you could not well see, When Robin for once more alert than Apollo, Cried gee-up to his horses, and bade Ned to follow. The chariot had scarcely arrived at the gate When Madame cried out she no longer could wait; Fan, Betsy, and Polly came clattering downstairs, Rushed out and jumped into the chariot by pairs. Away then they drove to the eastward to chide The dull god of day who was still with his bride Though some have supposed that he had an intrigue With good Mrs. Ch?n, and both were in league To wear out the patience of those at the door. Till at length Mrs. Charlton and Phoebus once more Op'ed the gates of the morning and eke of the store. In rushed all the crowd, but to paint you this scene Would require the pencil of Hogarth I ween, One snatched up a shoe, and another its fellow. “What a sweet pretty ribbon! These colors, how mellow!” “This muslin's so lovely—This feather's quite killing.” “Pray look at this fan—Two sweet doves a billing.” “I shall die if I don't get this hat and this feather.” “Ma'am, I chose them first.”—“No, Ma'am, not so neither; I fixed my eyes on them the moment I entered.” “Ma'am, I got in first or I should not have ventured.” “See this beautiful doll—such eyes and such hair! She seems to want only one thing, I declare.” The sun now was up, and Myrtilla was called, But the jade seemed the deafer the louder I bawled, “Pray where is your Mistress, and where are my keys? Go bring me some water to shave if you please; And bid them make haste with the breakfast d'ye hear, I'm half dead with waking all night I declare.” “Sir, Mistress is gone with the keys in her pocket, In the drawer lie your razors, I cannot unlock it. The breakfast is ready, and all on the spot But the coffee and tea, which Mistress forgot.” So away to Dunbarton I posted in haste, Resolved of their breakfast to get a small taste. When instantly up drove man Robin with Ned: “Ma'am, Mistress has sent—” “Robin what's that you said? Get my cloak, and my shawl and my clogs; I protest I can't eat a morsel.” “Indeed, Ma'am, you'd best.” “No, no my dear Becky—Come, Molly, let's go.” Aunt Becky and I were thus left all alone With the coffee, and tea, and a sweet bacon bone; And you well may believe that we both took a slice, Of the butter and bread that were equally nice. Now Phoebus had finished one-half of his career, When slowly we saw the old chariot appear Not the famed Trojan Horse with the Greeks in his belly, Proceeded more heavily on let me tell ye. Band-boxes and bundles were stuffed in the front, You'd have thought that the seat had nobody upon't; But wedged in one corner, at length I descried Sweet Madam Dunbar, and Madam t'other side. The door then bounced open and poor little Poll, From under the seat crept with Bet and her doll. The whole were half-smothered and puffing and blowing. “My dear husband, I'm starved, I'm dead, I'm agoing. Some breakfast in pity I pray you bestow, Indeed, I shall faint if you answer me no. See this hat, and these shoes, and this feather so nice, And this beautiful fan—What a charming device! This sweet little doll with her lovely blue eyes, Is Madam Dunbar's—I declare 'twould surprise You to hear all the various remarks that were made By the ladies upon't—from her toes to her head. Come Aleck, the coffee—ladies, pray take a seat How charming this coffee! this butter, how sweet! O that beautiful doll! That hat and that feather! See there now come Fanny and Molly together. O there is Mrs. Banister just going home; She promised to dine here; I hope she won't come. Let me die if I know what to have for our dinner Phill, pray look about you and get us some fish, I protest I don't know what to do for a dish. Five guineas, my husband, see here is the bill, Is all I have spent. You must, and you will I am sure find the money to pay off this score; 'Tis the devil you know to be, and seem poor.” So you see, my dear Fanny, how things here have passed, The husband poor soul, pays the piper at last. Mar. 27, 1796 To Cynthia When Cynthia's crescent I behold A luster shedding 'round her brow, I'm half convinced when I am told, That Art can vie with Nature, now. But when her beauteous eyes I view, That sparkle with a ray divine, I feel the ancient maxim's true, That Art cannot, like Nature, shine. O! Were I suffered to descry Those other orbs that swell below, Where fancy sets before my eye, Two rosebuds, peeping through the snow; Transported at the sight, I'd swear, Art ne'er can rival Nature, there. Then Cynthia, deign to smile upon And make me, thy Endymion. Mar. 10, 1799 Resignation Days of my youth! Ye have glided away; Locks of my youth! Ye are frosted and gray; Eyes of my youth! Your keen sight is no more; Cheeks of my youth! Ye are furrowed all o'er; Strength of my youth! All your vigor is gone; Thoughts of my youth! Your gay visions are flown! Days of my youth, I wish not your recall; Locks of my youth, I'm content ye shall fall; Eyes of my youth, ye much evil have seen; Cheeks of my youth, bathed in tears have ye been; Thoughts of my youth, ye have led me astray; Strength of my youth; why lament your decay! Days of my age! Ye will shortly be past; Pains of my age, but a while can ye last; Joys of my age, in true wisdom delight; Eyes of my age, be religion your light; Thoughts of my age, dread ye not the cold sod; Hopes of my age, be ye fixed on your God! Mar. 21, 1807 Burletta “Composed partly between sleeping and waking in the morning; June 10th, 1807.” With lungs loud as Stentor's, I'll sing my tormentors, More frightful than centaurs; And him that adventures, To slay my tormentors; And him that adventures To slay my tormentors, And him that adventures, To slay my tormentors, To slay my tormentors To slay my tormentors. See they rush to to my bed: How they fill me with dread! Hovering over my head, Like the ghosts of the dead, Which a charnel o'erspread! Like the ghosts of the dead, Which a charnel o'erspread! Which a charnel o'erspread Which a charnel o'erspread. Chorus With lungs loud as Stentor's I'll sing my tormentors, More frightful than centaurs; And him that adventures, To slay my tormentors; And him that adventures To slay my tormentors, And him that adventures, To slay my tormentors To slay my tormentors. See their hosts how they rise! How they darken the skies! Oh! they put out my eyes! Ah! pity my cries! A plague on these flies! Ah! pity my cries! A plague on these flies! Ah pity my cries! A curse on these flies! A curse on these flies! A curse on these flies! Chorus With lungs loud as Stentor's I'll sing my tormentor's More frightful than centaurs; And him that adventures, To slay my tormentors, And him that adventures To slay my tormentors And him that adventures, To slay my tormentors To slay my tormentors To slay my tormentors. Song Tune—A cobbler there was, etc. I envy no man for his purse, or his wife, Or his horses, or coach, or his station in life; With a little content, independence I prize, And he that seeks more, is more greedy than wise, Derry down, etc. I care not a farthing for term, or vacation; Or the meeting of Congress to settle the nation; Or assemblies that talk of divorces and banks, Pass censures on some, and to others give thanks, Derry down, etc. What care I, whether Jackson's a general or judge? Whether Peter or Dabney the circuit shall trudge? Whether substitutes offered by Mercer or Leigh, The majority gain is no matter to me. Derry down, etc. Still less do I care, whether Caesar, or Kate, Who their freedom have bought, shall remain in the state. If a street be too wide, or a lane be too close, Or three pence be given for killing of crows, Derry down, etc. Speculators, and smugglers, and gamesters and racers, Now mounted in garrets, now mounted on pacers! Let who will win the race! whether Blacky or Roan, Break his rider's neck first, and then break his own. Derry down, etc. As for demagogues, Federalists, aristocrats, Now roaring like lions, now purring like cats, Catterwalling, and scratching, or watching a mouse, I regard them no more than a flea, or a louse. Derry down, etc. For the maniac George, and the tyrant of France, I would they were thrown in a thousand-year's trance; When waking, well purged of their infamous crimes, They may turn harmless poets, like me, and make rhymes. Derry down, etc. Feb. 1812 To Mrs. Page When a tyrant complains Of a forger of chains What mortal believes him sincere! Since we know 'tis his trade To make others afraid, And chains to impose—not to wear. When a master of arts To his pupil imparts A science he thoroughly knows; How grateful the youth To the teacher of truth, For what he so kindly bestows? In you Madam Page, The tyrant and sage, As in Pericles, seem to unite. 'Gainst chains while you preach Your fair pupil to teach, That art, in which all must delight. Dec. 10, 1812 The Sick Man's Return for a Kiss The grateful heart that can't repay The favors it has prized, Shall find acceptance in that day When hearts are undisguised— The widow's mite acceptance found Where talents were disdained, The will, and not the offering, crowned The preference it gained— While some good folks about us live, I'm beggared by your kiss, Accept then all I now can give, A lovely peach—and This— [Mrs. Page: Poor feverish soul! You are vastly demure God grant you a speedy and radical cure Your return for my kiss I greatly admire And take the will for the deed as the case doth require.] A Fable “In imitation of one in Bougier's French grammar, by La Fontaine, as well as I recollect: Je songais cette nuit, que d'envie consumé / Cote a cotes d'un pauvre on m'avait enhumé”— Tucker. I dreamed last night, the debt of nature paid, I, cheek by jowl, was by a Negro laid; Provoked at such a neighborhood, I cried, “Rascal! begone. Rot farther from my side.” “Rascal!” said he, with arrogance extreme, “Thou are the only rascal here, I deem; Know fallen tyrant, I'm no more thy slave! Quaco's a monarch's equal, in the grave.” Dec. 25, 1812 The Reflections of a Man in His Grand Climacteric 'Tis a folly for Age to repine at the loss Of the things which it ne'er can again come across; Agility, strength, youth, and health, are all gone, And with them the spirits that moved them are flown. Sad Remembrance must now the enjoyment supply Of the pleasures that sparkled in Passion's bright eye, When Youth held the torch, and Hope pointed to bliss, To be found in a bumper, the dance, or a kiss. The delusion is past, and diseases and pain Of vain promised pleasures usurp the domain; Dull Patience alone can a plaster apply, Their pangs to assuage till the time comes to die. That time now approaches,—and Death wields her dart, And the victim beholds it, well aimed at his heart; What now shall support him? A life that's well past! For a conscience that's sound, is a shield to the last. Then, shall Hope not desert him: that friend of his youth Shall in age be his nurse, and the teacher of truth: As she bends o'er his pillow bright visions shall rise, Whilst to life everlasting she points in the skies. Aug. 19, 1813. Aet. 62 Lines, Supposed to Have Been Found Upon the Palace Green at Williamsburg On May Day, 1816 O! what a pleasure's in the town, To the world, how little known! Pleasures, which there is no telling: Pleasures, which there is no knowing! When the belles are off, a-beau-ing, And the beaus are off a-belle-ing. O! the sweet, bewitching scene, Palace grounds, or college green, When the beaus, and belles, assembling; Beaus, their secret thoughts confiding; Belles, their smiles, and blushes hiding, Frowns, and careless looks dissembling. O! the dear enchanting sight, When at parties, just at night, Beaus, and belles, in pairs advancing; Beaus their willing partners handing, Beaus and belles on tiptoe standing, Music striking, all a-dancing! O! how charming in the church! Beaus and belles in gallery perch; As to hear a reverend preacher: Beaus and belles their eyes a-keeping Beaus through veils, and fans, a-peeping; Little love the only teacher! May, 1816 Occasioned by Some Remarks on the Word “Prancing,” in the Preceding by Three Scrupulous Ladies Three prudes, a poet's work perusing, Begun, at once, his rhymes abusing: “Sure, 'tis enough, for girls to dance! But here, this poet makes them prance; Like actresses, arrived from France!” “Deliver us from such wretched stuff; Sir, write no more:—we've read enough.” The poet hangs his head awhile, Looks up, then answers with a smile: “Ladies! your criticism's just: I'll change the phrase: I will: I must! For who, that ever had a glance At your bright eyes, ere saw them prance! Though even now, I see them dance.” A smile, at once, lights up their faces, And now, the prudes are changed to graces. May, 1816 Bacchanalian I have heard from my youth, That in wine there is truth: And let him who the maxim disputes Just put by his glass, And go feed upon grass, And drink puddle water with brutes. Wine renders the sage Blithe as youth, just of age, And as wise as the sage makes the youth, Whilst together they reel, And in unison feel, That wine is the essence of truth. 'Twas by nectar the gods Held o'er mortals their rods, Much more than the thunder of Jove; 'Twas Falernian wine Did fair Venus enshrine, And proclaim her the goddess of love. With imperial tokay, An empire I'd sway, Far better than Caesar, or Bony; And with sweet jack, and sherry, Like Falstaff make merry, And Pegasus mount like a pony. Wine shows in the glass, All the charms of the lass That the love-smitten shepherd adores; And each drop that he sips, Like the dew on her lips, In his heart a new ecstasy pours. In the sparkling champagne He encounters again The sparkles that beam from her eyes; Like her breath the old hock, From the true convent stock, An ambrosial odor supplies. In Madeira he'll find The attractions that bind His heart, to the heart of the fair; And in Burgundy trace The sweet blush of her face, When his passion she heard him declare. A bumper then fill, But a drop do not spill, To the lass that each heart can beguile; Who, like wine, inspires, Gay hope, love, and fires, And banishes care with a smile. Apr. 1, 1817 Be Merry and Wise Of all the enjoyments on earth that we prize Be mine the choice gift, to be merry, and wise; Mirth enlivens the heart, and the blood in each vein, 'Tis the province of wisdom excess can restrain. Mirth delights in the bottle, and smiles on the glass, And invites to the arms of the love-breathing lass: While wisdom, with caution a bumper declines, And love with the chaplet of Hymen entwines. Mirth and wisdom united will drive away care, And an antidote prove to remorse and despair; Then, of all the enjoyments on earth that we prize, Be mine the choice gift to be merry and wise. June 8, 1817 Anacreontic Come fill your glass! to Chloe's eyes, This bumper is addressed; Another to her lips we'll fill And two more, to her breast. Two more we'll fill up to her heart: They're not enough! two more!! And if she has a sweeter part, To that, we'll fill a score! On Mrs. Lucy Nelson (the General's Widow) Attending the Communion Table at Church on a very Cold Day Though cold the day, yon aged breast Is warm with pious zeal: Though blind those eyes, religion's light The Christian still can feel. A life in virtuous actions spent, Its sacred influence shows; And pious hopes with age increase, Like wheat beneath the snows. Nor doubt it will, in God's good time, A heavenly harvest yield, Abundant, as the fruits of Nile, To Pharoah's dreams revealed. Jan. 4, 1818 Woman Woman parent of mankind Tender nurse of infant years, Comfort of the sick and blind, Soother of all human cares. Object dear of infant love Magnet of the youthful heart, Every passion born to move, Every blessing to impart. Consort sweet of riper years, Idol of the manly breast, Age's guide through vales of tears, To the mansions of the blessed. Be thou still, as from the first, Joy and comfort of my heart, And when death thy bands shall burst May we meet, no more to part. Sept. 11, 1819 Written on Christmas Day, 1820 All hail, auspicious day! When gracious Christ was born; To point to heaven the way, And comfort the forlorn: To teach frail man to serve, And love his God, above; Nor from that path to swerve: His neighbors, next, to love: The wretched to relieve, The humble to exalt, To comfort those that grieve, And to forgive each fault: The orphan child to breed, To clothe the naked poor, The hungry wretch to feed, Nor, drive him from the door: In all his dealings just; His labors for the best: In God to put his trust; And leave to Him the rest. Dec. 25, 1820</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SATIRES The Alarm A Real Story Which Happened in Bermuda, in the Year 1776 When first the laurels 'gan to grow On Admiral Hopkins' dreadful brow, His fame was o'er the Atlantic spread, And stoutest bosoms filled with dread. For governors and folks of state Were surest objects of his hate; Thus when to Providence he went, With cannon he was not content, But added to his vast renown, By carrying off the governor Bruere. On mischief bent, and fraught with guile Fame hied her to Bermuda's isle. And in the shape of Afric's son, Her flight directed to the town. The hero's feats, his matchless fame She trumpets forth with loud acclaim, And adds, that with a mighty train Of ships he ploughed the watery main, Whose rapid course was hither bent, To glut the warrior's fell intent. “E'en now, borne by the western gales, I saw,” she cried, “his swelling sails, With other numerous ships beside, Which o'er the billows proudly ride; So swift their course, that e'en the sun Shall set, each wight will be undone.” A general panic now prevails And every Tory breast assails With hideous fears—each doughty Whig Now struts with self-importance big. Some to the caverned mansions hie; Some mount the hills, the fleet to spy; Another train with busy care For flight with their effects prepare. It chanced that day was marked by fete For Dromis to give a treat, Of turtle to a chosen few Whose hearts were loyal, warm and true. Each dainty that the isles afford. And richest viands crowned the board. The guests were all conducted in; Each with his napkin at his chin, Views with anticipating glee, The savory stew, and calipee: With brandished knives they now prepare To feast upon the dainty cheer; But as each hand its treasure reared, The dreadful trump of Fame was heard. Aghast, they listen to the sound: Not e'en the Gorgon's hissing head Could fill their souls with greater dread. With hairs erect, in wild dismay, They know not where to bend their way; Winged by their fears, at length they fly With sails and oars the bark to ply; And thus (as mice desert their cheese If they but hear the sound of keys) The loyal friends, with panic stored, The turtle left upon the board. Written in Bermuda, June, 1776 Parody By Charles, by title, Lord Cornwallis The scourge of all rebellious follies, Lieutenant-general commanding The British forces of long standing With those et ceteras at the end Which mean more than you understand A Proclamation Whereas by Providence divine Which on our arms has deigned to shine On Thursday last we fought a battle With lousy, vile, rebellious cattle, And, to our everlasting glory (Unaided by a single Tory) The rebel forces did defeat And gain a victory complete, Whereby His Majesty's command Is reestablished in the land, And Loyalty uprears its head While cursed Rebellion goes to bed; I, therefore, willing to uphold The weak and to reward the bold, Do issue this my Proclamation Without regard to sect or nation. Requiring every loyal Tory To come to me and share the glory And toil of bringing back to reason The wretches guilty of high treason. Whereby the government benign Of Britain's Majesty divine With luster primitive may shine. Moreover, since I understand That divers persons in the land, By vile seducers led astray Have left the true and perfect way Which loyal subjects should pursue And joined with the rebellious crew, Grown sorry for their former fault, Are anxious now to make a halt, And, cured of their rebellious pride Would wish to turn to our side, To such, I hereby notify (As God will judge me when I die) That (murderers alone excepted For whom no grace can be expected), If they will to my quarters run With their accoutrements and gun, In thirty days, next from this date They shall eschew a rebel's fate, And be permitted to go back With a parole, like pill of quack, To cure the numerous disorders That rage upon our army's borders; Or, like a talisman to charm Our soldiery from doing harm, Tho' truth obliges us to own They will not cure a broken bone, Nor 'gainst the rebels yield assistance Or keep their army at a distance; If such effects they could produce We'd keep them for our army's use. But this is only by the bye; On their effects you may rely. Let no ill-natured imputation Be cast on this Proclamation, Because from hence with God's permission I mean to march with expedition, Tho' I confess we do not mean To go in quest of Mr. Greene, Who two miles distant, it is said Weeps o'er his wounds and broken head. Humanity, the soldier's glory Which dignifies each loyal Tory, Which fills each generous Briton's heart In all my actions stands confessed. Her voice forbade me to pursue The frightened, naked, rebel crew Who filed an half a mile or more Before their panic they got o'er, Humanity alike commands Of bloody deeds to wash our hands, And should we follow Mr. Greene Much blood might then be split I ween: Humanity commands to yield The wounded whom we won in field, Nay more she bids us leave behind The maimed, the halt, the sick, the blind Among our soldiers who might prove A hindrance as we backward move. Her high behests we then obey; Now strike our tents and march away. March the eighteenth, eighty-one At Guilford Courthouse this is done. Mar. 20, 1781 THE PROBATIONARY ODES A Dedicatory Ode To a Would-be Great Man Jonathan sheweth his profound skill in heraldry—maketh an essay upon the subject of titles, and proposeth a most apt one for a certain distinguished personage. Ætavis Edite! Hor. O Thou! whatever be thy title loved, King of the Romans, Caesar, Czarowitz, Dauphin, or Prince of Wales, if more approved, Infant, or Daddy-Vice, as best befits, Deign from my hands t'accept this savory sprig To greet thy nostrils, or adorn thy wig. Say, who can rival thine illustrious line, Great son of unborn Adam's first-born son, By right of primogeniture divine Heir to those titles thy great grandshire won: Heir to this whole terraqueous globe, no doubt, As any herald's office can make out. But since thine humble nature condescends To wave thy title to the world at large, Were mine the envied task, the grateful charge, Thou should'st be greater in my verse sublime Than e'er was Gog, or Magog yet in rhyme. Caesars of old, were by adoption named, As kings of Romas are by fiction, now; Hence each securely the succession claimed; From portents sure, I ween, so wilt not thou; As gibbet-climbing worthies to the top Do never rise, but just beneath it drop. If Dauphin I should hail thee, some would say I meant to threaten with the guillotine; If Prince of Wales;—it might a thought betray Thy dad a madman was, thy dam a queen; If Czarowitz I style thee;—they would swear, I meant thy father was a Russian bear. Infants, in Spain, or Lisbon, may be born With bears, and bellies round, for ought I know; With wigs their nappers too they may adorn, Big as a bushel, and as white as snow: There, Doctor Slop might for an Infant pass, So may'st thou there; but not here, by the mass. Though Congress once, their ignorance to hide, Forebore on splendid titles to descant, A partisan who combats on thy side, A title fitting would not let thee want. Old George, he swore, might without title shine, But, most superfluous highness, should be thine. Ode I To All the Great Folks in a Lump The humble petition of Jonathan; containing after the manner of other candidates for honors and offices, many fair promises, which peradventure may never be fulfilled. Confedere duces, et vulgi stante corona Surgit ad hos Jonathan. Ovid. So please your Worships, Honors, Lordships, Graces! I Jonathan, to Peter Pindar cousin, Hearing that you possess a mint of places Have come to ask for less than half a dozen. I ask not that to serve me you should quit Your lofty stations or turn out your friends: No—I've more conscience! and at once admit Your duty's to consult on means and ends. Those ends once answered—and the means obtained, To Jonathan's petition lend an ear: Nor think his young ambition overstrained, Head of Department, should his claim appear. Heads of Departments, we have seen, can jump At once into the mysteries of their art: Not Richmond's Duke excels great K-x the plump, Not Law to H?n could teach his part. I ask not dollars; though in truth a few Would jingle sweetly in a poet's purse: And since t'encourage arts belongs to you, A pension would not make the thing the worse. I ask not such a patronage as brings To brother heads an influence far and wide; Commissions, loans, douceurs, jobs, pretty things, Bank votes, directorships, and offices beside. Let others, patrons—Me, your client be: I have abundant zeal, and long to show it; To celebrate your praises make me free And dub me here, at once, your laureate Poet. I'll puff you to the clouds! and, by the pigs, Whilst there is brightest arch the rainbow spreads, Comets shall lend their tails to make you wigs. And powdered sunbeams glitter on your heads. I'll swear to all the world—you never dipped In speculators' kennel your pure hands; That not a soul of you e'er dealt in script: To prove my words your broker ready stands. I'll say—that bank directors though you are, No private interest ever sways your vote: That you are chose, just to see all fair, And, who shall win or lose, care not a groat. I'll swear—that nation's debt's a blessing vast Which far and wide its genial influence sheds, From whence Pactolian showers descends so fast On theirs—id est—the speculators' heads. That to increase this blessing and entail To future times its influence benign, New loans from foreign nations cannot fail, Whilst standing armies clinch the grand design. That taxes are not burthens to the rich; That—they alone to labor drive the Poor; The lazy rogues would neither plough, nor ditch Unless to keep the sheriff from the door. I'll swear—your honors are not like the boy, Who killed his goose which golden eggs did lay; Your goose you've no intention to destroy; Content to squeeze out half a dozen a day. I'll swear—in treaties you never had a thought To give up gratis all right of preemption: Or that you had an agent on the spot, To purchase for yourselves, I will not mention. I'll say—that you're well read, and well expound, Much better than Vattel! the Law of Nations: That no newfangled doctrines have you found To fritter states away to corporations. I'll swear—they owe their charters to your grant, And if beyond their proper bounds you catch 'em, The means to bring them back you will not want, But instant, with a quo warranto match 'em. These things and many more—you'll not disown, Prove I can flatter in a proper way; Suppose me now a speculator grown, Hear what to little Atlas I could say. June 1, 1793 Ode II To Atlas Jonathan, turned Speculator, in behalf of the whole corps addresseth their great benefactor and patron. Ingreditor folo, et caput inter nubila condit, Virg. ?Nunquam dimoveas! Hor. Whilst you, great Atlas! prop the State, Nor totter underneath a weight, That would a giant crush; Let pigmy wights, in Congress Hall, Set sparrow traps to work your fall, Regard them not a rush! A lion should a spaniel bay, The king of beasts would keep his way Nor heed the babbler's throat; Then deign not, Atlas, to look down Or punish with a single frown The angry snarler's note. Whilst on your paper throne you sit With solid gold beneath your feet Fear not a regicide! Your faithful Janizaries all Shall muster thick in Congress Hall To guard their leader's side. Go on, great chief, to make us all, Not from your shoulders cast the ball, Lest we, like worms, should drop, Who on a golden pippin prey, Till haply on some stormy day 'Tis shaken from the top. June 5, 1793 Ode III To a Select Body of Great Men Jonathan approacheth the holy of holies:—is frightened out of his senses, and knocked down;—endeavors to deprecate the wrath of offended dignity. ?“Horrisono stridentes cardono facrae Panduntur portaie.” My Lords! your Poet Laureate, humbly knocks; And begs permission to approach your door; Nay! good my Lords! don't set me in the stocks! I vow to God, that I'll do so no more. Good Mister Sargeant! spare me this one time! Lord, Sir! you need not thus have knocked me down! Wretch that I am!—I'll freely own my crime Deserves I should be whipped through all the town. I never said, in secret you debate, Like Turkish divan, or Venetian peers; Hatching infernal plots against the State— Nay! good my Lords! I pay you spare my ears! I never said, whilst here in state you sit, Like Satan's Council, you're ten times as big, Swoln by the magic of your self-conceit, As folks that walk about without a wig. I never said that you were bound to do Aught else, but what your Lordships freely chose; That states have any right to question you, Or thrust in your concerns a busy nose. I never questioned your undoubted right To give what titles, and to whom you please; You shall be dukes and princes! by this light, I'll lie as quiet as a mouse in cheese. I ne'er asserted that you ruled the bank; Or said it had an influence over you: You all shall be Directors; first in rank; And if you please, kings, lords, and commons, too. Gad so! my gracious lords, I've found at last That I've been guilty of an indecorum: In thus addressing you, I've been too fast, I should have first addressed his worship Quorum. Great Sir! but troth, this measure will not hit The solemn style which I to him must use; So, if you please, I'll stop a tiny bit, And hold a conference with Madam Muse. June 12, 1793 Ode IV To a Would-be Great Man Jonathan defendeth the great Defender;—magnifieth and exalteth his works, and confesseth his own littleness of understanding. “Certat tergeminis tollere honoribus.” Hor. Daddy Vice, Daddy Vice, The drift of your fine publication: As sure as a gun, The thing was just done To secure you—a pretty high station. Defenses you call To knock down our wall, And batter the states to the ground, sir, So thick were your shot, And so hell-fire hot, They've scarce a whole bone to be found, sir. When you tell us of kings And such pretty things, Good mercy! how brilliant your page is! So bright in each line, I vow now you'll shine Like a glowworm, to all future ages. When you handle your balance, So vast are your talents Like Atlas your wonderful strength is, You know ev'ry state To a barleycorn's weight, For your steelyeard the continent's length is. On Davila's page Your discourses so sage, Democratical numbskulls bepuzzle With arguments tough, As white leather or buff, The Republican bulldogs to muzzle 'Tis labor in vain Your senses to strain Our brains any longer to muddle; Like Colossus, you stride O'er our noddles so wide, We look up like frogs in a puddle. June 19, 1793 Ode V To a Truly Great Man “Justum et tenacem propositi virum.” Hor. George—on thy virtues often have I dwelt, And still the theme is grateful to mine ear: Thy gold let chemists ten times over melt, From dross and base alloy they'll find it clear. Yet thou'rt a man—although perhaps the first; But man, at best, is but a being frail; And since with error human nature's curst, I marvel not that thou should'st sometimes fail. That thou hast long, and nobly served the State, The nation owns, and freely gives thee thanks: But, sir! whatever speculators prate, She gave thee not the power t'establish banks. No doubt, thou thought'st it was a phoenix nest, Which Congress were so busy to build up, But there a crocodile had fixed his rest, And snapped the nation's bowels at a sup. The greedy monster is not yet half cloyed, Nor will he, whilst a leg or arm remains; These parts the last of all should be destroyed; The delicious morsel is her brains. I trust thou'st seen the monster by this time, And hast prepared thy knife to cut his throat; His scales are so damned hard, that in thy prime, 'Twould take thee twenty years to make it out. God grant thee life to do it! Fare thee well! Another time examine well the nest, Though of Arabia's spices it should smell, It may produce some foul, infernal pest. June 22, 1793 Ode VI To Midas Jonathan entreateth Midas not to starve the nation—proposeth a project for paying off the National Debt through the instrumentality of the S?y of the T?y. Suae fortunae faber. O greedy Midas! I've long since been told, Whate'er you touched is instant turned to gold; Thine alchemistic fingers, prithee, stop, Or thou'lt not leave us all a single sop. Those fingers from thy birth have been employed With such well-timed precipitation, That had the sacred college tried, Thoud'st beat them all at transubstantiation. Briareus had a hundred hands, but thou hast more, Grasping at once this spacious globe around; One hand embraces the Chinesian shore, Beyond Ohio's banks another's found. Mountains and rivers, rocks and sugar trees, Nankeens and China, green and bohea teas, Are instant turned to gold whene'er you please, O spare untouched our codfish, rice and bacon, Or else the continent must for forsaken. Midas, much service might'st thou do the state, Thy talents wert thou willing to exert; Relieve the people from a grievous weight, And give reward where there has been desert. My project may appear a little bold; But sure I am, 'twill pay off honest claims: Touch H?n, and K?x, and F?r A?s, And turn the speculators all to gold; Let Congress send them straightway to the mint, They'll pay our debts—or else the devil's in't. June 29, 1793 Ode VII To the Well-born Under the type of the heathen gods Jonathan rehearseth the virtues of aristocracy. Paree, precor, stimulis. Ovid. Sons of Olympus, all! I kiss your hands, A stately company, as I'm a sinner! My little godlings! what are your commands? I hope you do not mean to stay to dinner. We've no ambrosia here—plain beef and mutton Your Godships' stomachs will most surely turn; Not for our whiskey would you give a button; Such home-brewed nectar you will spurn. We have no Ganymedes—no wanton Venus, Nor ugly cuckold Vulcan, for a buff; No pimping Mercury to go between us, Or pick our pockets, or our purses cut. We have no Jupiter, with lust unbounded, Our fair Alcmenes to seduce, No drunken Bacchus with his tuns surrounded; No Mars, God wot! can we produce. We have no Proteus changing every hour, As with his whim or interest stands, No greedy Saturn to devour His children in the midwife's hands. We for your playmates have no little Cupid To shoot at people when they're off their guard: We mortals, truly, are so stupid To think such treatment were a little hard. Such fit companions you'll not find I swear; Then why the devil should you tarry here? Each embryo Romulus and Alexander, So eager now to fill Fame's hundred trumpets, Would deem it neither crime nor slander To prove their virtuous mothers strumpets; If bastards they will be reputed Of gods that had their dads cornuted. Ye would-be Phaetons, now so intent To mount, and set us in a blaze, Or drive us to the devil and all; Trust me, you'd better be content, For, ere you've tried it many days, By G? you'll get a fall. July 3, 1793 Ode VIII To Minos ?Jura Silentibus Reddit.?. Ovid. Stern judge of shades! revisit'st thou this earth To try us all, ere we have crossed the Styx? Not only punishing our childish tricks, But damning us, by wholesale, from birth! As mortal bodies, states, no doubt, have souls, Which brings them all within thy jurisdiction; And since no earthly judge thy voice controls, They must be damned, without a legal fiction. Thine eminent domain, what state opposes, Or dares remember it was sovereign once! Since to the grindstone thou hast brought their noses, Thoul't leave among them not a single sconce. Their little corporations all shall melt In the hot crucible that holds thy brains, Till not a single particle remains Of all the fancied sovereignty they've felt: A voice shall then be heard in Congress Hall States are no more—and we are all in all!!! July 20, 1793 Ode IX To Liberty Jonathan addresseth his castoff mistress—pretendeth to have forgotten her name—revileth her groveling taste, furious temper and contempt for her betters—commandeth her not to disturb the peace, and driveth her beyond the Atlantic: but at parting seemeth half willing to be reconciled to her again. In vitium Libertas excidit? Hor. Et Tuba terribilem Sonnitu Tarrantantara dixit?. Virg. O Thou! whatever be thy doubtful name, Once dear to us, and still to Gallia dear, Whose boisterous accents, fill the trump of Fame, Accents which we have grown too deaf to hear: Who didst, erewhile, in Congress Hall preside, Each vote dictating to prevent mistakes, Though now thine image there be thrown aside, Doomed to oblivion in a filthy jakes: Who didst in many a well-fought battle wave Thy bloodstained banners o'er our fainting heads, And from the jaws of death and ruin save Full many a wight, that now thy presence dreads: Who, when the din of war no more was heard, Didst to the humble cottage straight retire, And to imperial palaces preferred Bar independence round a rural fire: Who, when thou'rt wooed, art as a virgin mild, Thine angel-visage all bedecked with smiles; But when opposed, like a hyena wild Thy savage fangs!—whose rage no art beguiles; Who dost like death on all conditions look, Nor spar'st a Stuart's or a Capet's head; Nor fear'st this earth must some convulsion brook For them; as if Tom Thumb the Great were dead; Who at one stroke, hast thousands beggars made, Of those whose Fortune's minions were before, And left them, without wealth, or worth, or trade, To starve—as they had millions starved before: Who carest no more for coronets, or crowns, Or any modern would-be lordling cit, Alike condemning both their smiles and frowns, Than if our Daddy-Vice had never writ— Avaunt!—Nor let thy clarion grate our ears With sounds, terrific as the final trump! Sounds which once turned our pruning hooks to spears, And from their scabbards caused our swords to jump: Sounds! that should Congress listen, might appall The stoutest champion there for right divine; Recall thine image back to Federal Hall, And to thy temple turn corruption's shrine: Sounds! that might even tempt them to reward The care-worn soldier's fears and wounds and woes, Though S?h and A?s should think the measure hard, And speculators turn from friends to foes: Sounds! that perchance might e'en the Senate wake From dreams of rank and titles, power and wealth; Or bank director's gilded slumbers break, And bring the Constitution back to health: Sounds! that perchance might to the states recall Some faint remembrance of lose sovereign rights, Those rights, which mighty Atlas doomed to fall, And which stern Minos banished from their sights: Sounds! that might peradventure drive away The faithful Britons from our western posts; Those sentinels, who guard us night and day, Our scalps defending from the Indian hosts: Sounds! that perchance might prompt a silent wish To aid their struggles, who once aided ours; Nor, whilst thy cause is fighting, mute as fish Behold the ambition of combining powers: To France return!!! There shall thy brazen lungs Yield music, sweeter than the Syren's voice, Though louder far than Fame's twice fifty tongues, And unborn millions at the sound rejoice. There, wave thy banners!—there thy falchion wield! There, lead to victory each gallant son! There, let thy slaughtered foes bestrew the field! Nor let e'en tyrants, there, thy vengeance shun! Nay—though imperial crowns, and heads should fall, Nor age, nor sex protect thy fiend-like foes, Rather than thou should'st quit this earthly ball, E'en Jonathan shall cry—God speed thy blows!!! Aug. 14, 1793 Ode X To the Democratical Society of Philadelphia Jonathan reproveth the impertinent views of that institution—prophesieth concerning a would-be great man.—By comparison with the heavenly bodies, showeth the respective merits of the great heads. Per insidias iter est, formasque ferarum. Ovid. Sons of sedition! say, what do you here, Where peace and loyalty unrivaled reign? Where wealth rewards the speculator's care, And rank and place your groveling arts disdain. Go watch the sun!—see his unfading light Since time begun still unobscured remain! Go watch his beauteous sister-orb of night! Go watch the planets which compose his train! Go plant your telescopes against each star Whose radiant sphere illumes the vast profound! Some blemish amongst them, shall easier far, Than in our bright galaxy here, be found. Not less in luster, as not less in size, Than a dim planet to the orb of day, Lo! next that height, to which he ne'er shall rise, Our Vice like Mercury pursues his way. Scowling malignant on the Indian plains, Intent to set their wigwams all on fire, See K?x like ruddy Mars his course maintains Through lions, scorpions, and chimeras dire. Hugest of planets that adorns our sphere, Refulgent in his triple, golden zone, See H?n like Jupiter appear, With satellites around his paper throne. Whilst on those minor orbs his light he sheds, That borrowed light on him shall they reflect: Nor whilst he pours down blessings on their heads, With incense to repay shall they neglect. Removed beyond the reach of vulgar eyes, As far as human brains or thoughts aspire, The self-illumined Minos sweeps the skies, Like Saturn, freezing, midst his ring of fire. Yon concave vast behold! where wolves and bears And geese and foxes all together meet; Say, if less bright, our Congress Hall appears, Prepared for George to take his annual seat? Cease then, ye elves of darkness, cease to pry Into those secrets you're forbid to know; Content yourselves to scrutinize the sky; Presume not to enquire what's done below! Aug. 9, 1793 Ode XI To Atlas Being the Second Part of Ode II Jonathan recanteth his former errors:—discloseth the secrets of a great assembly:—again doubteth, and concludeth with an apt simile. Atlas! 'Tis true that once I said You prop the states up, with your head; But I was wrong to do't: My recantation, then believe, And trust me, what I now perceive, You've trod them underfoot. 'Twas you that in Convention first Pronounced the government accurst, Whilst sovereign they remained: Then boldly moved to knock them down, And crush them all beneath a throne, Or, to it have them chained. Sure, 'twas enough to strike them dumb, To put them under sheriff's thumb, Like culprits vile and base: What tho' they are not hang'd as yet; Still, two to one, perhaps, you'd bet, That it will be the case. But after all—no doubt, I rate Too high your influence in the state, Nay, I'll be sworn, 'tis so: The town clock tells us when we dine; The weights that move its hands and thine Play out of sight, below! Aug. 11, 1793 Ode XII Jonathan taketh his leave of his correspondents: apostrophiseth a great man without stain, and giveth to real merit, merit's due. Majora canamus. Virg. Enough of Atlas! and the venal train That 'round his paper shrine attendant meet: Enough of Daddy Vice's fertile brain, Titles and rank Prolific to create, Prolific as Egyptian oven vast, Where chickens, ducks and geese are hatched so fast! Enough of the well-born! those lordling cits, Who now presume so high to hold their heads: Wretches, whose pride by far outweighs their wits, Who, if they know, try to forget their dads; Just as rank weeds that on a dung-hill grow, Shoot up at once to hide the filth below, As the philosopher in search of truth With high contempt each base deception spurns; As from the midnight punk the generous youth To the chaste object of his passion turns; As from a loathed disease returning health; Or, as from beggary the joys of wealth; As to the blind the newfound bliss of sight; As to the galley-slave fair freedom's hand; As from a dungeon the return of light; As from a shipwreck the long wished for strand;— My soul turns from them all with high disdain To find in George true greatness without stain. O Washington! for whom my willing lyre Unbidden vibrates loudest notes of praise When shall thy yet unrivaled worth inspire Some emulations of thy glorious days! Still, as a father to thy country dear, Regard not those who seek to wound thy peace, Nor to their impious falsehoods lend an ear, Who would persuade thee her regards can cease. Still at the helm go on our bark to steer, Nor quit it, till thou leave thine equal there. Aug. 12, 1793 A Supplementary Ode Heu, quam difficile est crimen non prodere. Ovid. Tussis pro crepitu, no doubt an art is, Not easy to translate in decent phrase; But understood and practiced by the parties That would be uppermost in modern days. Thus moderate men, who twenty years ago At independence frowned and made wry faces, Of mother Britain's rights made much ado, Meant nothing more, than just to keep their places. So when our soldiers perished on the decks Of prison ships,—or died by exaltation, Vile Tories, trembling for their forfeit necks, Loudly exclaimed against retaliation. So when our Daddy Vice bewrought his brain To tell us all of lords, and dukes, and kings, No doubt His Worship counted all the gain Which from preeminence and title springs. So when our our triple-headed Publius barked, Like Cerberus, at unbelieving Anty, Each proselyte-monger for himself had marked Of federal loaf and fish no portion scanty. Thus A?s and S?h so eager to repair The tattered remnant of our public credit, To patch the garment better, thought it fair On their own meager carcasses to spread it. Thus Atlas to support his paper throne, And give its faithful guards another sop, To pay off France, proposed a further loan, Gaps of instrumentality to stop. Thus Antigallicans and British mongrels Who at republican successes sweat, Buzzing like swarms of flies from fifty dunghills, Have neutrals turned to vilify Genet. As Witches, hating people, to torment 'em Stick pins in images that represent 'em. And now, good folks, a dozen odes I've writ (More by one-half than e'er I thought to write) And if I have not always shown my wit, No doubt you'll say that I have shown my spite: Foe to all party but the public weal, All secondary motives I disdain; For ne'er shall worth my smarting satire feel, Nor vice a plaudit from my hand obtain. Farewell! perhaps when next our Congress meets, Amongst them I may take a little peep; Not to disturb their worships in their seats, But just to see who wakes, and who's asleep. Sept. 7, 1793 A Trip to St. James's, 1794 Lend me thy trumpet Fame! thy brazen lungs, Thine hundred mouths, and eke thine hundred tongues! My liver swells with vehement desire, To tell such things as scarce will be believed; Namely, the wonders that have been achieved, Without the aid of sword or fire, But in a modest, decent, civil way, By our Extraordinary Envoy, Mr. Jay. Say, muse, 'midst what acclaims he did set out, Attended down to Whitehall stairs, By thousands in their Sunday airs; Who when he got on shipboard gave a shout: The mighty blast filled the Ohio's sails, Then homeward all the shouters turned their tails, And left the ship in charge of Mr. Jay, To sea-girt Britain's coast to make her way. Swift as an arrow from an Indian's bow, The ship across the Atlantic shot, Swifter than ever ship was known to go, And of her destination hit the very spot; As proud of such immortal honor As our great Envoy laid upon her; Then to New York came straightway back to tell, That in her charge she had succeeded well. Now muse, let us return to Mr. Jay, Who safe to London city found his way; With ceremonial due then went to greet Grenville's new lord, and Billy Pitt likewise, Who viewed the Envoy Ex with wondering eyes, Wondering what brought his Ex to Downing street; Then promised soon to show him to the king, To whom he might unfold the tidings he did bring. Meantime Lord Grenville asks his Ex to dine, An honor which his Ex could not decline: There cheek by jowl with lords he sits in state, With due decorum emptying every plate; Then dinner done, the loyal glasses ring, With loyal bumpers crowned, to George the king. Now mount, O muse, on eagle's wings, Attend with Mr. Jay the King of Kings. The day was come, the weather wonderous fair, When with Lord Grenville to St. James' Court His Ex the Extra-Envoy did repair, Of's errand and himself to make report. The monarch saw—and turning to the queen, “Look, look, there's Jay, there's Jay, there's Jay, I ween From Congress come to make a bow; I wonder if the dog knows how?” His Ex advanced and made a bow by rule, Which showed he had been at a dancing school; The monarch then returned a monarch's nod, Awful, no doubt, as the Olympian God; When thus, in humble tone of supplication, Did Mr. Jay begin his smooth oration. “O Sire! permit a wight thy subject born, His fellow subjects' sufferings to impart, Nor from their wailings turn thine ear in scorn, Like Egypt's king of old, of hardened heart. “I did not like Moses come, with threats to fright, Or daunt with spells and charms thy royal breast; Our unfledged eagle, all too young for fight, Sits, like the peaceful Halcyon, in its nest. “She, like the peaceful Halcyon, went to glide (If true the tale that's told of other times) Borne on the azure bosom of the tide, From shore to shore, from clime to distant climes. “But mews and seagulls now disturb her rest, And boobies strike her with their jobbernowls; Voracious sharks assault her peaceful nest, And warlike swordfish pierce it full of holes. “Thou, who like Neptune, dost the trident sway, Alone can'st quell those monsters of the main: O! let thy clemency shine forth we pray, And halcyon days prolong thy glorious reign!” Meanwhile, a gracious ear the monarch lent To Mr. Jay, and eke his compliment, To which he condescended such reply, As Billy Pitt dictated, by the bye. Next to the queen his Ex did make his leg, And with the king her intercession beg; To which the queen returned two royal dips, Though not a word escaped her royal lips; Then to each prince and princess low he bowed, As demagogue, when he salutes the crowd. This done, the monarch gave a gracious grin, And thus familiar question did begin. “Well! since your independence you have got, Are you much happier than before, or not? Good salaries, and sinecures! hae, Mr. Jay! Or are republicans too stingy, pray? Does Mr. Washington, hae, wear a crown? No, no, not yet, not yet, you'd knock him down.” “Great sir,” cries Mr. Jay, “We han't, as yet, A head among us that a crown would fit.” “No, no, I guess not,” instant cried the king, “His head, I'm sure's not fit for such a thing; You're all republicans, hae, Mr. Jay, All sans-culottes, no doubt, aye, aye, aye!” To which his Extra-Ex did make reply, In tone so sweet the king could but believe: “Permit me, sire, your ears to undeceive; That all are sans-culottes I dare deny, Nor need I further prove what I advance, Since I am here, O king, and not in France.” The monarch, half-convinced, exclaimed “Egad! If you were there, you'd chance to lose your head: Han't you among you got the guillotine? Yes, yes, I'm sure you have—myself and queen Would soon among you all be lopt off short As wheat in harvest—and as much in sport, “I'm sure,” cries Mr. Jay, in accents sweet, Confounded by what majesty had said; “Your sacred heads, more precious far than wheat, From scythes, or guillotines have naught to dread.” “Godso! I doubt it much, upon my life!” The sputtering monarch quick replied, “A lowly tailor (can it be denied!) Among you kicked my son that kissed his wife.” “That fact,” cries Mr. Jay, “I can't deny.” “No, no, no, that you can't, I, I, I, I!” The monarch said, “for Neddy swore 'twas true. And that the tailor beat him black and blue.” The blushing queen here turned her head aside, Blushing in part with shame, in part with pride; Each bashful princess hung her lovely head, And seemed to sympathize with brother Ned. Now Billy Pitt and Grenville's lord began To fear the monarch might betray the man; For monarchs can sometimes like parrots talk. As monkeys, on two legs, like monarchs walk. So Grenville plucked the envoy by the sleeve, And whispered it was time to take his leave. Oct. 1794. For the Washington Federalist A New Federal Song The Jacobins have got the day The Feds are homeward moving; But when they come again this way, There will be desperate shoving. Yankee doodle, keep it up, Yankee doodle dandy, The Feds will never start a peg Till cider turns to brandy. Duke Braintree is to Quincy gone, To study new defenses, For spite of all the old he finds, The folks have lost their senses. Yankee doodle, etc. There's Sedgewick quits his lofty seat For better speculation, Than can be found while surly Smith Will print the Fed's orations. Yankee doodle, etc. There's Dayton gone to see his lands And have them all surveyed, sirs, But shortly he'll be here again, With sword and black cockade, sirs. Yankee doodle, etc. There's Wolcott, he gives up the cash, To sit upon the bench, sirs: Like Felix, 'round the Jacobins He'll work till he is weary. Yankee Doodle, etc. There's Otis leaves seditious laws, To be the Fed attorney; When in your tails he sticks his claws, You'll wish the de'il to burn ye. Yankee doodle, etc. There's Griswold, he won't condescend, To be war secretary; But if you trust him with the cash He'll work till he is weary. Yankee doodle, etc. There's Dexter fit for any thing; Can preach on any text, sir; Let John or Jefferson, be king, You'll find him Ambidexter. Yankee doodle, etc. There's Read, and Green, and Hill, and More Are all turned into judges, For not a Fed, without a place, From Congress homeward trudges; Yankee doodle, etc. But Bayard, he won't go to France To see his gallant cousins, Lest Heaper's wonderous tales and plots, Should multiply by dozens, Yankee doodle, etc. There's Hamilton, he lies perdue, With old sly Pickering, sirs, In spite of all the fools can do, They soon will have a kind, sirs. Yankee doodle, etc. Then, we shall sing, “God Save the King”; Th' aristocrats and Tories, And placemen all from south to north, Will join, in joyful chorus. Yankee doodle, keep it up, Yankee doodle dandy, The Feds will never start a peg Till cider turns to brandy. Mar. 3, 1801 A New Song Merino sheep! Merino sheep! Come, who will buy Merino sheep! Merino sheep! now going cheap! Oh! what a chance to make a sweep! And have a flock of Merino sheep! Merino sheep! Merino sheep! A thousand dollars for a sheep! Merino sheep! I needs must weep, To see them going all so cheap! Oh! why did I bring Merino sheep! Merino sheep! Merino sheep! Why sure, good folks, you're all asleep! You will not buy Merino sheep! Though now they're going all dog cheap! Merino sheep! Merino sheep! A thousand dollars for a sheep! An hundred dollars for a sheep! Come make a sweep, they're quite dog cheap, Come, fifty dollars for a sheep! It makes me weep, they are so cheap, Come, twenty dollars for a sheep! Come, take the whole and make a sweep At fifteen dollars for a sheep! And you shall have Merino sheep. Merino sheep! Merino sheep! Come, who will buy Merino sheep! What glorious profits shall he reap, That now will buy Merino sheep! Merino sheep! Merino sheep! Merino sheep! Who wants a flock of Merino sheep! Oh! What a chance to make a sweep; And get a flock of Merino sheep! Merino sheep! Merino sheep! Merino sheep! A thousand dollars for a sheep! Why sure, good folks, you're all asleep, That you won't bid for Merino sheep! Merino sheep! Merino sheep! Merino sheep! Though here we offer them so cheap, A thousand leagues across the deep, We've brought these fine Merino sheep! Merino sheep! Merino sheep! Merino sheep! An hundred dollars for a sheep! It makes me weep, they are so cheap! Why won't you bid for Merino sheep! Merino sheep! Merino sheep! Merino sheep! Come, fifty dollars for a sheep! Come make a sweep! They're quite dog cheap And you shall have Merino sheep! Merino sheep! Merino sheep! Merino sheep! Come, thirty dollars for a sheep! Come, take the whole and make a sweep, At twenty dollars for a sheep, Merino Sheep! Come take the whole and make a sweep At twenty dollars for a sheep! Merino sheep! [1810] On Reading a Letter From a Very Sprightly Lady, Disclaiming All Ideas of Love, and Matrimony, to a Particular Friend More tranquil than the western breeze, Which fans in spring the blooming trees, My breast (the lovely Delia cried), Will ever be, on the left side, Where Cupid's arrows enter. Agreed! the sprightly Laura said, But, tell me, thou dear charming maid, How is it,—at the center? Apr., 1810 The Virginia Patriot's Invitation to His Customers Come all who love a savory dish, Here's codfish, cheese, and liver! There's no such liver, cheese, or fish, South of Potomac river. 'Tis wholesome food for every day, And for a feast on Sunday, It is superior every way, To New York salmagundi. Whoever tastes this wholesome dish, Shall strait grow wondrous wise; For, like the gall of Tobit's fish, It opens blindmen's eyes. Some Yankee cheese, as story tells, Killed all the Havana rats; Our dish, that famous cheese excells, Destroying Democrats. All ye who now refuse to store Yourselves with such a hoard, Nor codfish, cheese, nor Livermore, Shall ever grace your board. Apr., 1810</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PATRIOTIC POEMS On General Washington When Alcides, the son of Olympian Jove, Was called from the earth, to the regions above, The fetters grim Tyranny burst from his hand, And with rapine, and murder, usurped the command: While Peace, lovely maiden, was scared from the plains, And Liberty, captive! sat wailing in chains; Her once gallant offspring lay bleeding around, Nor, on earth, could a champion to save her to be found. The thunderer, moved with compassion, looked down, On a world so accurst, from his crystalline throne; Then opened the book, in whose mystical page, Were enrolled the heroes of each future age: Read of Brutus, and Sidney, who dared to be free; Of their virtues approved, and confirmed the decree; Then turned to the annals of that happy age, When Washington's glories illumined the page. “When Britannia shall strive with tyrannical hand, To establish her empire in each distant land, A chief shall arise, in Columbia's defense, To whom the just gods shall their favors dispense: Triumphant as Mars, in the glorious field, While Minerva shall lend him her wisdom, and shield: And Liberty, freed from the shackles, shall own, Great Washington's claim, as her favorite son.” Aug. 26, 1780 On General Arnold At Freedom's call, see Arnold take the field, With Honor, blazoned on his patriot shield! His gallant deeds a dazzling luster spread, And circling glories beamed around his head. But, when estranged from Freedom's glorious cause, Renouncing Honor, and its sacred laws, Impelled by motives of the basest kind, Which mark the vicious, mean, degenerate mind: To virtue lost, and callous to disgrace, The traitor hiding, with the hero's face; His cankered heart, to sordid views a slave, To Mammon yielding all that freedom gave, Enleagued with fiends of that detested tribe, Whose god is gold, whose savior is a bribe, Could basely join, his country to betray, And thus restore a ruthless tyrant's sway; On freedom's sons impose the galling yoke, And crush each foe to vice, beneath the stroke; Not all his laurels in the field obtained! Not all that Philip's son, by conquest gained! Not all that once adorned great Caesar's brow! Nor, all that Washington may challenge now! Could save a wretch, whom crimes, like these, debase, So far beneath the rank of human race! But, stung with keen remorse, his guilty soul, In vain, shall seek repose, from pole to pole; Perpetual anguish shall torment his breast, And hellish demons haunt his troubled rest; Not even death shall shield his hated name, For, still, the caitiff shall survive to fame; By fate's decree! who thus pronounced his lot: “Too bad, to live! too base, to be forgot! Thy crimes succeeding ages shall proclaim, And Judas be forgot, in Arnold's name!” Oct. 25, 1780 The Progress of Cornwallis An Irregular Ode I Bellona's thunder rends the western skies, The din of battle shakes the troubled air; Sounds of frantic horror rise, Shrieks of woe, and wild despair; Through Carolina's laurel groves, Secure, the prowling Briton roves, And mocks the foe, and fate defies; Since, prostrate on the ground, O'erwhelmed with many a wound, In agonizing pangs Rebellion gasping lies. “At the period alluded to, the British never spoke of the Americans but as rebels and the Revolution as a rebellion” (Tucker). II See Terror stalking through th' affrighted land! Grim Rage, and fell Revenge his steps pursue, Rapine, and harpy Famine join the band, The wretched victim's dying groans The widowed matron's tender moans, The virgin's plaints, the orphan's cries, Ascend, in concert, to the skies: There hollow Want in secret anguish pines, No more relieved from Plenty's cheering hoard; Here pale disease the parting breath resigns, And Desolation waves around her flaming sword! III See the gorgon foe advance! See him couch his quivering lance! Thine, Virginia: next to feel The fatal vengeance of his steel: Thine, with terror to survey, His splendid host in dread array: Thine, beneath is power to languish, Torn with rage, despair, and anguish! IV In her car triumphant riding, 'Midst ten thousand glittering spears, Through the liquid azure gliding, Bright-eyed Liberty appears. Far renowned in martial story See a chief her faulchion wield! Beaming with celestial glory, Lo! a monarch bears her shield! Britain! thy short triumphal course is run! Thy flitting glories vanish from the sight; Lost in the radiance of a brighter sun, Like falling stars they're seen, 'midst darkness, only, bright. June, 1782 Ode to Peace Come, sweet Peace, and with thee bring All the odors of the spring; Summer's golden harvests, too, Autumn's fruits of various hue, Winter's health, and cheerful fires, Joys, which competence inspires. Leave to war the vernal blights, Scorching summer's sultry nights, Autumn's fogs, and sickly dew, Rugged winter's blustering crew, Slavery, famine, and despair, Leave behind to cruel war. All the good that freedom brings, Mirth from innocence that springs, Temperance, the foe to strife, Friendship, sweetest balm of life, Love, that rivals bliss divine, Gentle Peace; be ever thine. 1787–1788 On Hearing of the Attack Made by the British Captain Douglas, of the Navy, on the Chesapeake, Commanded by Commodore Barron, in June, 1807, Near Cape Henry Tyrant! again, we hear thy hostile voice! Again, upon our coast thy cannons roar! For peace, again, thou leavest us no choice! Again, we hurl defiance from our shore. Hast thou forgot the day that Warren bled, While hecatombs around were sacrificed? Hast thou forgot thy legions captive led? Thy navies blasted, by a foe despised? Or, think'st thou we've forgot our brothers slain! Our aged fathers weltering in their gore! Our widowed mothers, on their knee, in vain, Their violated daughters' fate deplore! Our towns in ashes laid! Our fields on fire! Our wives and children flying from the foe! Ourselves in battle ready to expire: Yet struggling still to strike one other blow! Know then this day recalls the whole! Now, hear our solemn, and determined voice: In vain proud tyrant! shall thy thunders roll; Since, once more, victory or death's our choice. July 2, 1807 Ode For the new year—1809 Still, Bellona's thunders roll, Rend the earth, and shake the pole! Europe smokes from east to west; Gaul and Britain feed the fires; Tyranny erects its crest; Freedom from her shores retires. Hail Columbia! happy land! Peace, with liberty be thine! But, would Freedom's voice command, Instant, at the call divine, Rush to glory, at her shrine! Freedom! endless by thy sway! Boundless, as the solar ray! Peace the consort of thy reign; Virtue foremost in thy train; Wisdom thine unerring guide; War and tyranny defied. Hail Columbia! happy land! Peace with liberty be thine! But if Freedom's voice commands, To arms! To arms! To arms! Instant, at the call divine, To arms! To arms! To arms! Rush to glory at her shrine! Rush to glory! Rush to glory, Rush to Glory, at her shrine! (If such the will divine), Fall, with glory! Fall, with glory! Fall, with glory, at her shrine! Jan 1, 1809 Union March Rise, Columbia rise! For peace hath lost its charms! Hark from afar, The clang of war! Insulting foes Your rights oppose: Rise, Columbia rise! 'Tis freedom calls to arms! Rise, Columbia rise! Let union arm your bands. From east to west, Her high behest, Let all obey: In dread array Rise, Columbia rise! 'Tis freedom's voice commands. Rise Columbia, rise! At freedom's sacred shrine, Your vows renew: Swear to be true To Liberty! And still be free! Rise, Columbia rise! Be death or freedom thine. Feb. 26, 1809 Lines Written Soon After the Declaration of War Against Great Britain, in June, 1812, When Congress Passed an Act for Raising Troops. To the Friends and Supporters of Liberty, and Their Country. Remember the days, when fair Liberty's call Roused the sons of Columbia to arms; When we swore, one and all, at her altars to fall, Ere a tyrant should rifle her charms: When Montgomery, Warren, and Mercer the brave, Sealed the thrice-solemn oath, with their blood; And Washington, destined his country to save, Swept off all her foes, like a flood, Remember, when Freedom her banners unfurled, And exalted her standard on high; We swore to defend her against the whole world, And for her, to conquer, or die: Bunker's Hill, Saratoga, Kings Mountain, and York, Attested the truth that we swore; Independence, and union, and peace, crowned our work; And Liberty triumphed once more. Now, when insolent tyrants assail her again, And traitors are plotting her fall, Shall the bliss-giving Goddess invoke us, in vain, Like lions to rouse at her call? Remember our oath! And remember the blood, That sealed the dread oath, that we swore! And remember the days, when victorious we stood! And conquer for Freedom, once more. Aug. 7, 1810 Invocation Addressed to Every Friend of His Country; September 1814 Sons of freedom! who have bled, Where Washington or Warren led, Over heaps of mighty dead, 'Gainst a tyrant enemy; See again: The battle lower! Britain rallies all her power— Now descends a fiery shower! Cannons roar, and rockets fly. Shades of patriots in the grave! Shades of parted heroes brave! Born, your country's rights to save, From a ruthless tyrant's sway! Rouse your gallant sons to arms! Bid them wake to freedom's charms! Bid them rush to war's alarms! Rouse! And drive their foes away. Bid them hasten to the strand! Sword to Sword, and hand to hand! Suffer not a foe to land On the shores of Liberty! Back to ocean drive the slaves! There to perish in its waves! Sink them to their watery graves! Worthy not on earth to die! Chorus Sons of patriots in the grave! Sons of parted heroes brave! Born, your country's rights to save From a ruthless tyrant's sway; Be not blind to freedom's charms! Be not deaf to war's alarms! Rouse ye! rouse ye! quick to arms! Rouse ye! and drive your foes away! Haste ye! haste ye! to the strand! Sword to Sword, and hand to hand! Suffer not a foe to land On the shores of liberty! Back to ocean drive the slaves! There to perish in its waves! Sink them to their watery graves! Worthy not on earth to die! Aug. 15, 1810</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TALES Humps and Robin A True Story Oh muse, who didst ere while inspire The merry strains of Matthew Prior, Descend and to my pen indite A tale, which Matt, alone, should write Travelers and poets long ago Have claimed the privilege, you know, Of changing persons, time and place, To give their tales a better grace, Or to conceal from observation The real truth of their narration: Resolved this method to pursue, We mean to deal in fiction too, As far as names and places go, The rest our tale shall truly show. Near to a place whence royal George, Of this rebellious land the scourge, One of his oldest titles gains, There lived a youth the pride of swains, Whose swelling calf and back of brawn, Might cause a dowager to pawn, Her richest jewels for a sample Of strength and nerve beyond example: Yet sooth to say, our simple Humps, Although he held a hand of trumps, Knew not the value of his cards, Nor thought them worth his least regards, Until a lass of comeliest mold, Who twice nine years had scarcely told, His dormant faculties excited, Whence, she in turn was well requited. Humps like another Timon felt, His heart for Iphigenia melt, To Robin, first of wags, he goes His strange condition to disclose, The symptoms felt by youthful lovers: Rob tells him, wedlock is the pool In which his raging flames must cool; Humps grinned assent. The lass, tho' coy, At length consents to wed the boy. Suppose the wedding day arrived And honest Humphrey fairly wived, The dinner ate, the dancing ended, The bride by all her maids attended, Slip out unseen, and half undressed; Robin who dearly loved a jest, Once more takes honest Humps aside T'instruct him how to greet the bride. Quoth he—“What's to be done tonight, “Friend Humphrey, is a solemn rite, “At Hymen's altar 'tis expected “That not one state should be neglected, “Then let an offering go round “For each, with due libations crowned.” A message broke the conversation And Humps retired to his station: Like Milton, we too highly deem Of nuptial beds to follow him. Then here we choose to draw the curtain, Nor dare to speak of things uncertain. With folded arms and settled gloom Next morning Humps came in the room, While Robin smoked his second pipe: The wag, for mischief ever ripe, Asks how the posset-bowl held out? Humps sheepish looked—then turned about, And said, “Though not a drop was wasted, “Nine times, alone, the cup I tasted: “Four states, alas! unblessed remained, “The posset-bowl was fairly drained.” Quoth Robin—“Your libations's short, “Indeed I fear, by half a quart; “Tonight the matter may be mended, “Take t'other bowl when one is ended.” Humps thanked him for his good advice And swore he'd drain the goblet twice, Next morn, again with clouded brow, Humps meets with Robin at the plough. “Alas,” he cries, “my worthy friend “Where will my disappointments end? “Though twice the posset-bowl was crowned, “Nine times, alone, the toast went round; “The vain attempt I must give o'er, “I fear I ne'er can reach the score.” Quoth Robin—“Though there's much to fear, 'Tis best to hope and persevere.” Thus Humps each morn did Robin shrive, Until the score got down to five; Then Humps, with looks more sad than ever, “My friend, I've done my best endeavor “My feeble force again to rally “I can not rise beyond a tally, “My dear, my lovely Iphigene “Must surely sink into the spleen, “Thus of expected bliss beguiled, “She'll think she's wedded to a child: “Nor here concludes my sad disaster “I need a poultice, or a plaster, “What was no larger than my wrist “Is scarcely smaller than my fist.” “Adzooks,” quoth Robin—“never mind, “A hair of the same dog you'll find, “A better poultice to apply, “Than any plaster you can buy.” Humps groaned assent—but doubted much Whether the poultice he could touch. Two days had passed since Robin heared, How now with honest Humps it fared, At noon he finds him still in bed, With rueful face, and drooping head, To every kind enquiry dumb, He neither finger raised nor thumb. When Robin thus—“Why what a pother “You make of things which any other “Would think but very moderate duty. “Would Iphigene, too, such a beauty! “You should at least the score have doubled, “Nor at a trifle thus be troubled. “There's a neighbor Charles—ten years age gone “Since duty was to him but fun; “Eight bumpers are his common dose, “Less will not lull him to repose, “And if perchance he lacks his score, “Next night he takes a bumper more.” Humps groaning raised his eyes and said, “Ah! Robin—would that I were dead!” Just then a tittering laugh betrayed His Iphigene behind the bed. Nov. 8, 1788 The Tobacco Pipe The wag to mischief who's inclined To that, alone, gives up his mind, And sacrifices foes or friends, Without regret, to gain his ends. Where Roanoke rolls its limpid tide Through fertile fields on either side, Not long ago there was a wedding, Where guests were plentier far than bedding. A stranger, I forget his name, Who from a distant county came, At all events must have a bed; For Robin, Harry, George, and Ned, A pallet on the floor was spread, The clock struck twelve—to rest they went, And till the morning slept content; But Robin with the lark arose In haste, and to the garden goes: Then uprose Harry, George, and Ned, The stranger, fast asleep, in bed, Lay all uncovered on his face, Not dreaming of his foul disgrace; His hapless case when Harry found He casts his wicked eyes around. Takes Robin's pipe from off the shelf (The stem a reed, the bowl was delft), And to the stranger's nether eye The taper point he doth apply, And shoves it in, up to the bowl, So well he understood the hole: Dan Prior's ladle not more quick In old Corisca's bum did stick; Then out again the reed he takes, Before the abused stranger wakes: But had not time the stem to wipe When Robin came to seek his pipe, And presently begun to smoke, Quoth Harry—“Don't you smell a joke?” Robin threw down the pipe in haste, And spitting cried, “Some smell, some taste: “They're both so strong—so may I thrive, “They'll last as long as I'm alive.” Nov. 27, 1788 The Faithful Mastiff A True Story At lukewarm, or at faithless friends I've no design to rail: An honest, but mistaken zeal, The subject of my tale. Yet think not, with a cynic's eye That I regard mankind Because in men and brutes, alike, Some qualities I find. To err is human—and that dogs Can be mistaken too, Most clearly follows from a tale Which I can vouch is true. Ah! could I but as clearly prove That men, like dogs, were true, Full many a heart would now be blithe, Which now their falsehood rue. In Williamsburg, 'ere party rage The capital removed, Together lived three waggish sparks Who mirth, and frolic loved. Their names are still remembered there; For, still, some there remain, To curse that policy that razed Their city to the plain. Their house by night from thieves to guard A mastiff they had bred; Yet, oft, did honest Towser go The way their footsteps led. For well he knew their waggish tricks Might sometimes kindle rage, And well he knew the argument That passion to assuage. For he had found a single look From him could peace command, As readily as did the touch Of Hermes' magic wand: Or, as the intercessions strong Of well-armed faithful friends, Or, as the sheriff's puissant arm, When posse com. attends. One evening in the month of June, When sultry was the day To Waller's Grove our youngest wag Directs his lonely way: That Grove, where old Dodona's pride Spread far and wide its shade Till war and avarice allied A cruel havoc made. His steps the faithful Towser marked As on he saw him pass, And followed lest perchance there lurked Some snake beneath the grass. When night her sable mantle spread The youth a cottage spied, Where to solace from earth-born care, With nimble pace he hied. There, lived a nymph whose tender breast Was ne'er assailed in vain; Delighting pleasure to impart To all who felt a pain. Our weary pilgrim in the bed Now sought a soft repose; When Towser straight crept underneath, And fell into a doze. The creaking bedstead roused him soon; A rustling noise he hears Of conflict fierce above his head, And for his master fears. He bounces up—and seized the foe, Beyond the bended knee, Nor, heeds, that in the conflict, low, And panting, laid was she. “Why how now, Towser!” cried the wag. “Pray let us both alone: “Your aid, just now, I do not want, “My adversary's down.” Dec. 24, 1789 The Author's Muse to the Reader A Monitory Tale In fair Barbados once there dwelt a dame Of special note, though I forget her name; With flatulencies she was oft oppressed, They soured her temper and disturbed her rest. At length a grand specific she had found, 'Twas lemonade, with aqua-vitae crowned. A nutmeg o'er the potion should you grate 'Twould make it punch; and punch the dame did hate. One morning when the clock had just struck nine She calls to Betty with a sickly whine. “This dreadful colic—something I must take.” “A little spirit, madam, shall I add?” “Yes to be sure! Why sure the girl is mad! “Can pungent acids with my colic suit “Unless there's spirit to correct the fruit?” “A little nutmeg, madam—will you try?” “Punch in the morning! Gracious God, I die! “Think you with nasty punch I would get drunk! “Begone you vile, abominable punk!” Now listen reader! punch if thou dost hate Shut up the book before it be too late 'Twas wholesome lemonade I meant to brew, But troth I fear there's nutmeg in it too. So, gentle reader, if thou dost get tipsy Pray call me not a saucy wanton gipsy. Jan. 1, 1790 The Cynic Whoever to finding fault inclines Still misconceives the best designs: Praxiteles in vain might try To form a statue for his eye; Appelles too would pain in vain, And Titian's colors give him pain, Palladio's best designs displease him, And Handel's water piece would freeze him, Not Tully's eloquence can charm, Nor e'en old Homer's fire warm: On all occasions still a beast He frowns upon the genial feast, Swears that Falernian wine was sour, And rails at champagne for an hour, Not Heliogabalus's cook Could drop a dish at which he'd look. Anticipating time and fate He views all things when past their date, Destruction in his noodle brewing Turns palaces to instant ruin: Speak but of Paris or of London He tells how Babylon was undone: Ask him, with Thais if he'll sup He cries—“The worms will eat her up.” Once at a merry wedding feast A cynic chanced to be a guest; Rich was the father of the bride And hospitality his pride. The guests were numerous and the board With dainties plentifully stored. There mutton, beef, and vermicelli Here venison stewed with currant jelly, Here turkeys robbed of bones and lungs Are crammed with oysters and with tongues. There pickled lobsters, prawn, and salmon And there a stuffed Virginia gammon. Here custards, tarts, and apple pies There syllabubs and jellies rise, Ice creams, and ripe and candied fruits With comfits and eryngo roots. Now entered every hungry guest And all prepared to taste the feast. Our cynic cries—“How damned absurd To take such pains to make a ?!” Jan. 1, 1790 The Ass Turned Witness A Tale—from La Fontaine A painter jealous above measure, The better to secure his treasure, Above the keyhole of the place That held it, paints a little ass. The sequel how shall I reveal? A brother painter came to steal; The door unlocks—but in his haste The ass was totally effaced, Except the head; which would betray That somebody had been that way: In haste his pencil then he got, And drew another on the spot. Now see our jealous painter come To view his exhibition room. “Ye Gods, what here! Upon my life I'm robbed!” he bawls out to his wife. “No mortal has been near the place,” Quoth she.—“My witness is the ass.” “The ass! you jade! My brains you'll addle: Zounds! gypsy, who put on the saddle?” Feb. 14, 1790 The Impossibility, or, Old Nick Outwitted A Tale—from La Fontaine A devil once, as stories tell, The most malicious fiend in hell In solemn form of compact made A bargain with an amorous blade: The spark was by his aid to gain A nymph for whom he sighed in vain; Old Nick no recompense would have But to remain his humble slave, The youth was only to command Whenever Satan was at hand, Nor must his orders be delayed When smutty face his visit paid, His sole condition was dispatch For Satan's ever on the watch; Herein, whene'er the lover faltered The case should instantly be altered: Old Nick might drag him to his hole And roast his body with his soul. Our lover laughed at the condition; “Command is easier than submission: “Obedience were another thing: “What evil from command can spring!” Old Nick was faithful to his word The lover shortly was preferred, And 'midst his amorous caresses His sooty benefactor blesses. Think of him and his horns appear: Old Nick was straightway at his ear; The lover sends him on an errand, 'Twas presently performed I warrant; Whether to Italy or Spain Satan was quickly back again. Returned—our lover bids him go And bring some gold from Mexico; Then sends him off across the line For jewels from Golconda's mine: Behold, at once, a monstrous hoard Of gold and jewels on the board! Next sends to Canada for furs, Satan was not in need of spurs: A centaur's hide—a dragon's claw, A mermaid's skin—a griffin's paw, A craken's tooth—a phoenix' nest, In turn, were instantly possessed. “What! here again! Nay, this is Malice; Go—build a temple or a palace.” Not Pandemonium more quick Was raised without the aid of brick. Our frighted lover now bethought him That Satan in his trap had caught him; For not a moment did he lose, Nor leave the lover time to choose. What service next to send him on Before the last command was done. The promised feast he scarce had tasted And half the night in vain was wasted, Nor could he hope by night or day To keep the smutty fiend away, And while he thought upon his talons He lost all appetite for dalliance, Thus with perpetual care oppressed He to the nymph the whole confessed. “And is this all!” she smiling said, “That has our mutual Bliss delayed! Here—bid him straighten this”—she cried, “And lay your silly fears aside.” Then put into his hand a hair Which she had plucked the Lord knows where; Whether from cushion, or from wig, Or from stuffed hoop so round and big, Or from her eyebrow, or from her temple, 'Tis certain it was but a sample; As by the sequel will appear. Old Nick was in a moment there; For now he thought, that half an hour, Would give his prey into his power. “Here straighten this”—the lover cried, Old Nick t'his mouth the hair applied: The hair curled not a whit the less. Ha! this won't do! We'll try a press. A press, a vice, a weight in turn He tries in vain—he's yet to learn; He souses it into the ocean, He might as well have drunk a potion. In his own element he tries it, Then on an anvil stoutly plies it; Nor fire, nor water, press nor weight Could make the curling tendril straight: 'Tis vain to tamper with it longer It only makes the buckle stronger. No wonder if our spark was pleased To find himself at length released, For Satan came no more that night But stayed until the morning light. “Here, take your hair!” The tempter cries, “It both my toil and skill defies; Our bargain now is at an end.” The lover laughed and said—“Old friend You're in a hurry to give o'er I've just now found ten thousand more.” Feb. 18, 1790 The Discontented Student A True Story Returned from college R? gets a wife To be the joy and comfort of his life: But ere the honeymoon was in the wane He sighs for college and his books, again To his thought on all occasions flock: Like Madam Shandy, thinking of the clock. But, sad mishap! when Phoebus gilds the skies, If to his favorite authors he applies, Bright Venus throws her cestus o'er the book; In vain he tries upon the page to look; As Cupid blind, the classic page no more Delights his raptured sight as heretofore. Like that sagacious beast, who placed between Two cocks of hay—one dry, the other green, Can neither taste; our scholar every night Thinks of his books; and of his bride by light. Untasted joys breed always discontents; Thus to his sire, his rage the scholar vents. “Would that in Italy I had been born, And, early, of each vile encumbrance shorn, Which now seduces all my thoughts away From Classic studies or by night, or day. Uninterrupted then I might have read Or in my elbow chair, or in my bed; Till drowsy grown, and nodding o'er the book Upon the enchanting page I craved to look And then in rapturous dreams renewed the joy Till taking, I resumed the blest employ. But now in vain I quit the genial bed, My wife—a plague!—keeps running in my head In ev'ry page I read my raging fires Portray her yielding to my fierce desires.” “G? d? your books!” the testy father said “I'd not give ? for all you've read.” The Judge With the Sore Rump “Serva tibi minas!” To a judge who was seated on high; As (for some fatal crime) He devoted some time To prepare the poor culprit to die. “What's that about mine a?e?” (Says the judge to Aquinas, And turned up his rump as he spoke) “I've a boil on my bum, Thrice as large as my thumb: And see here!—the boil has just broke!” Says Aquinas—“I find That your tortures behind, Are more than you threaten, by far: So here end your farce, And take care of your a?e; And let me get out of the bar.” Jan. 27, 1819</field>
   </doc>
</add>