<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Fairfield, Sumner Lincoln, 1803-1844</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Fairfield, Sumner Lincoln, 1803-1844</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">fairfield sumner lincoln 1803 1844</field>
      <field name="author_text">Fairfield, Sumner Lincoln, 1803-1844</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1830's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ap/uvaGenText/tei/chap_AM0733.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240350</field>
      <field name="date_text">1832</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:440174</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The last night of Pompeii ; a poem : and lays and legends</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- 1783-1850</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- 1783-1850</field>
      <field name="title_display">The last night of Pompeii ; a poem : and lays and legends</field>
      <field name="title_facet">last night of pompeii a poem and lays and legends</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">last night of pompeii a poem and lays and legends</field>
      <field name="title_text">The last night of Pompeii ; a poem : and lays and legends</field>
      <field name="year_display">1832</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1832</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1832</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440174&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440174&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Fairfield, Sumner Lincoln, 1803-1844&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;fairfield sumner lincoln 1803 1844&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The last night of Pompeii ; a poem : and lays and legends&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;last night of pompeii a poem and lays and legends&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1832&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1832&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Fairfield, Sumner Lincoln&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1803&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1844&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The last night of Pompeii ; a poem : and lays and legends&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;New York&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Elliott and Palmer&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1832&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3865763-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;cham0733&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- 1783-1850&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1783&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1850&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The last night of Pompeii ; a poem : and lays and legends&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1996&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1996 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 37 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted ; verse reproduced elsewhere in American</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Poetry omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-AmPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">LAYS AND LEGENDS. HIPPIAS, THE TRAITOR OF MARATHON. Hipparchus and Hippias, called the Pisistratidæ, the sons of Pisistratus, who during the latter years of Solon, through artifice and treachery, acquired the sovereignty of Athens, by many acts of arbitrary exaction and cruelty, had awaked the vengeance of the Athenians. Harmodius and Aristogiton led the revolt, (indeed the inhabitants of Athens had never acknowledged the authority of Pisistratus or his sons,) and slew Hipparchus, while Hippias escaped into the castle of the Acropolis, and exercised, for three years after, the most atrocious severities upon all, whom by fraud or violence, he could seize and torture. I have supposed Harmodius dead, and Aristogiton living, till the battle of Marathon, though the anachronism is obvious enough. Clisthenes, who contributed so much to expel Hippias, afterwards invented the ostracism, and was himself the first sufferer. The Panathenea, which the Athenians are supposed to be celebrating, in the first part of the Poem, was the most splendid festival of Attica: and the month Hecatombæon, in which it was solemnized, being the period of the accession of the Archons and Thesmothetæ to office, would naturally awaken the people to the assertion of their rights. Autumnal twilight on the Zephyr's wing Hovered o'er Athens, and its iris hues Blended with ether's vestal blue, breathed o'er By the favonian airs, and with the clouds Pavilioned in the heavens, or diamond stars Now in their lustrous beauty coming forth. They myrtle and rose-flowered acacia flung Their vesper fragrance on the mellow breeze; The illumined sea, dimpling with smiles, sent up The gentlest music to the parting light And dawning Pleiades, and, man might dream, The tritons with Poseidon, in a heaven Beneath the emerald billows, mid strange flowers, O'erclustering coral temples, dwelt and sung. The vales of Arcady, from meads of thyme And hallowed fountains, for dim oracles Renowned, uplifted evening orisons, With forest hymns of the hoar hills, whose brows Gleamed in the earliest and latest light, Rejoicing in the loveliness of eve. And many a woodland pipe and cithern hailed Familiar constellations, as the blaze Of the divine Hyperion left the skies To the dominion of Love's blessed stars. Yet 'mid the pomp of luxuries, within Athena's citadel, in broidered robes, And tossing on his purple banquet couch In torture, lay the racked but noble form Of one who cursed the sunlight, and shut out The holy influences of the heaven, Loathing the beauty passion in his soul Had darkened with its midnight, and in wrath Shunning the spirit of magnificence He felt not in his bosom's depth of gloom. Among the splendors of a power, erewhile By treachery grasped, yet ministered with thoughts Of grandeur, lay the last, least-gifted heart Whose pulses bounded with the glowing blood Of Pisistratus: o'er his lofty brow, And lips of beauty—which disdained the soul That mocked them with its weak and evil powers— The chill dews of an agony, that shook Aside the veil that masked it to the world, Gushed, and in dark lines o'er his countenance The tempest of a foiled ambition fell. From burnished shield, statue and gleaming lance, Gem-hilted sabre and the pictured tomes Of Scio's deathless bard, and all the pomp Of pillared porticoes, he turned and breathed Quick, panting execrations, as the breeze Rustled the olives of the Parthenon, Or with the orange leaves, like oreads, played. Listening with the intensest hope and fear, He rose upon the couch and forward leaned; His pale lips writhed as if their scorpion curves Could fill his curse with venom—and his brow, Convulsed by pangs of guilt, e'en now in youth Burned with the ghastly light of blasted fame. “The Egyptian could not err—the Acropolis Hath never fail'd its master! yet the yells Of the wild faction—the dust-eaters—daunt My spirit—and I feel the spear-point glide Along my heart, whene'er Hipparchus' doom Darkens the mirror of fierce memories!” Thus in his solitude the tyrant spake. “A footfall echoes on the corridor! Was't not a voice beneath? he comes to bring The soldiers of the isles unto my aid. Ay, shout, and shriek, and with your torchlight glare Affright the heavens, ye faithless herd of serfs! I know ye merciless—can I be less? Howl in your wild Panathenea, howl! Your festival may close with unhoped feasts, Your saturnalia with the clank of chains! My trusted Medon comes with tidings fit To soothe my ear shocked by your Teian oaths. A nearer step—and a white banner borne Proudly—he comes with succor in his smile!” A lofty shadow crossed the vestibule, And in the purple twilight silent stood Before the tyrant, who but ill discerned Through the vast hall of revelries the face That with a marble sternness searched his soul. “Speak, Medon! will the isles avenge our cause, And crush the rebel slaves that seek our death?” “Gaze with a better judgment, Hippias! once Clothed with a power thou dost no longer hold. Thou seest no Medon! but the herald-king Of the Amphyctions—who thus, from them Bids thee resign the citadel, and part For ever from the shores thy crimes have cursed— Or struggle with the vengeance thou hast raised!” “Ha! 't is a gracious message, and I thank The artizans of Athens for their love; But what my father builded and the blood Of bold Hipparchus sanctified, I keep; Daring the Thesmothetæ and their host Of burden-bearers in their worst assault.” “The oppressor skills not in the lore of life, His grandeur is the sea-foam—and his power The gossamer a zephyr bears away. Beware thy answer, 't is the very last The desperation of the land allows. Hast thou forgot Lenæa on the rack? She spat her gory tongue at thee, and died Defying tyrants to make traitors, son Of the destroyer of the chainless Right! Aristogiton and brave Clisthenes May teach thee wisdom ere thy Medon comes!” “And I may teach it thee, unmannered slave Of men, who, while they envy me, aspire To gain the masterdom by fawns and smiles Flung on the vile democracies of Greece! The trusted may betray—the ruthless foe Assail—and famine be my only guest— Danger my only guard—despair, the pulse That throbs me on to death—but I to none Will render back my heritage! away!” “One word, proud Hippias! thou may'st depart With thine own Rhodope and all thy wealth, To any realm thou wilt—but hear me, lord! Aristogiton with Platæan troops Leads on the squadrons of brave Clisthenes! The Spartan and the Alcmæonidæ Are banded with Arcadia to o'erwhelm—” “And let them come! it shall be joy, whate'er The gods resolve, to dip my hand in hearts That clove my brother's! Did I rightly hear— Aristogiton? that thy place were his! I would abscind a whole Olympiad From being but to quench that thirst! he slew Hipparchus! and he will be deified! If ghosts are gods, my hand should make him one! Away! begone! the citadel is mine!” Slowly the herald, spurning the dust, retired Unto the assembling host that through the gates Poured o'er the city, while thronged galleys lay In the Piræus, and the cries of wrath From the Munychian fortress hastened on The assaulters of the tyrant's citadel. That night, festivities and liberal mirth, Accustomed at the nation's gayest feast, When all in Athens banqueted and sang, Wanted their worshippers; for human hearts, Goaded and gashed by wanton tyranny, Hurled their oppressions and oppressors forth, And robed their wounds with justice! every clime Hath had its crowned and sceptred torturers, Its diadems and dungeons—every clime May have its armed avengers, if the mind Feels its immortal majesty, and bathes The brand of bondage with the monarch's tears. The battle-cries—the rush—the trumpet's voice— The glare of torchlight combat—the dismay And triumph—dinted shields and shattered helms— And broken palisades, and trampled halls Of desolated splendor—all are o'er! Deserted in his peril by the shades Of his past glory, Hippias, through the gloom Of tangled wilds and shaggy caverns, groped His lonely path to banishment—amidst The forests, crags and torrents and defiles Of his wronged country—on the toppling peak, And in the voiceless grotto—danger—fear, And hopelessness and hunger, breathing one, One deep, remorseless passion, born of Hate And Agony—Revenge! Revenge for all! With ravening thirst of vengeance, borne for years, Through mountain gorges and o'er deserts fled The banished Hippias to the eastern king. Amidst the beauty and magnificence, The pomp and perfumes of the Sophi's court The outcast tyrant bow'd, while satraps laid Their foreheads in the dust and magi waved, From golden censers, odors o'er the throne Of Persia's King, in conquered Babylon. The diamond diadem, the Tyrrhene robes Girded by broidered zones of gems and gold, The violet colored turbans thronging round The sceptre that awed Asia, and the dread Of the adoring crowd—o'er Hippias threw No fear and veneration fitting herds Who grovel through the gloom of vassalage To breathe a glory they can never share. Might, majesty, the usages of kings, Palace and temple, and the matchless mind Of Greece had left the unsceptred wanderer now No admiration of barbaric pomp. “What wouldst thou, son of Pisistratus?” said Royal Hystaspes.—“Refuge and Revenge!” Replied the unfaltering prince.—“The first is thine, In Susa, by Choaspes, or the bowers Of fair Persopolis—or any dome Of all our empire that hath held a king, Till such time as the greatness of our cares Permits us further to discourse of thine. Thou shalt not lack our solace for the woes Revolt hath stirred within thy bosom, Prince! Nor our fit aid to wrest from rebel hordes A ransom such as Babylon has paid For treason and Zopyrus—when time serves. Thou comest not alone?” “My Rhodope, For we are childless, is the only charm That lingers round my desolated path, Great sovereign of the Orient! and she, Worn by our perilled flight, awaits, in grief. The edict of the monarch's gracious will.” “O Mythra! doth it come to this, at last? That a frail woman—like a summer cloud Upon the desert, is the only shade For the brave man in agony—the flower That with its fragrant leaves shadows the brow Which burns in Passion's fever—that our pride And pleasure and renown and majesty Are vanities beneath her starlight smile! Well, thou art happy, Hippias! in thy love. Choose from our regal mansions as thou wilt— And Peace, like the cool fountain's music, shed Her gladness round thee till we meet again!” When Freedom, phrenzied by the scorn and wrong Of purple power, tears from the place of guilt The Atlas of the crushed heart's agonies The sceptre trembles in each monarch hand O'er the glad earth—the brightest crown-gems fade, And battled legions—mercenary hosts— Are cast like avalanches, o'er the realm That doubts the archangel sanctitude of kings. So goodly sympathies expand, and crime Becomes impolicy, and shedded blood Lamented chance, and princely palaces In other kingdoms shield the despot, cells Of darkness in his own should carcerate. Time is but thought; and o'er the ill or good, It flies or lingers as their spirits will, Soothing misfortune, or to nurtured hate, Adding dark torrents of feigned injuries. Years drearily meandered o'er the heart Of Hippias amidst the loveliest bloom And verdure of the lote and myrtle groves, The Aurora and the vesper hymn of streams, The chequered shadows of the Zagros hills, The magic, love, romance and revelries Of his own beautiful and glittering home. Humiliation panted for revenge— Shame summoned demon pride—lost powers called up The faded apparitions of his hour Of homage and dominion; and he sued By starbeam and by sunlight, through the years Of banishment, to satraps at his feasts, And princes in their palaces to lead The vast hosts of the east against the land Where, tyraat once and traitor now, his soul Exulted to inflict its hoarded wrath. His head was hoary and his countenance Trench'd o'er, and charr'd by evil thoughts, ere forth The heralds of the Medes and Persians passed, To bid Arcadia to the Persian bow. And Hippias buried time, till one returned. “Brings't thou the earth and water? fear they not?” Astarte save me! I alone am left; The Grecians hurled my fellows from the rocks Into the abysses—saying ‘Take your fill!’” Mocked thus, Darius paused not, but arrayed His armies for the conquest, and the waves Of the Euphrates heard the shouts and songs Of thousands following thousands to the war. The barbs of Araby and towered elephants Bore dusky chieftains panoplied; the waste And mountain pass and plain with silken tents And costliest pavilions, pillowed round, Seemed an enchanted land; and instruments Of softest music breathed their harmonies On the spread camp and scattered wanton march. Emblazoned shields no blood had ever dimmed, And mirrored helmets ne'er a sword had left A hero's witness on—and garments soiled By no wild combat or untented sleep, Glittered and waved around the royal pomp. Beside the monarch in the centre rode The mover of this pageantry, and oft The doubting mind of Hippias, as he cast His troubled glances o'er the motley host, Betrayed the fear that, like a thraldom brand, Seared his proud heart; yet dared he not arraign The satrap's vaunted skill in high command. So on they passed, and o'er the Ægean swept The galleys of the Persian, and his bands, Like sundered glaciers, poured upon the plain Of deathless Marathon, leaving behind Dark solitudes of smouldering flame and gore. There stood Miltiades, mid the armed hearts Of Arcady, and in the bristling van Of the Platæans towered an aged form. Unbroken by the harvest years of joy And virtue; and the same heroic eye Watched the o'ercrowding foe, that erst, along The hallowed blade flashed on the cloven heart Of dead Hipparchus; and the traitor's brow Felt the pale shadows of the sepulchre, As he beheld Aristogiton there! Let me not feign a picture of that fight! The sanctities of ages shroud its deeds. It's name is glory, and the hero's fame, Shrined in the pantheon of deathless thought! It thrills the soul of childhood and inspires The sage, the warrior, and the statesman, when All other fields of triumph pass away! The earth became a reservior of blood, And carnage loathed its banquet, ere the waves Of war bore Hippias, crimsoned with the gore Of his betrayed and groaning country, near Its terrible avenger. “Art thou come, Hoar tyrant traitor! to invoke thy doom From him who gashed thy brother's perjured heart? And heard Harmodius, in his torture, name Thy parasites, his fellows in the death? Come! let the trophy of my best days be Thy head, upon the shield, that shall not save Thy bosom—when thy country bids thee die!” He grasped—he hurled him from his plunging steed— And, linked like maddened scorpions they strove, And on the earth struggled in the wild might Of merciless and all-redeeming hate. Aristogiton is above him now! Strike for thy country! strike for human kind! The sabre searched the tyrant's vitals then! Ha! the blood bubbles from the ruthless heart! Again—one other blow for Liberty! Why roll thine eye-balls, patriot? oh, the blade Of Hippias, by his dying anguish driven With all his living hate, is in thy heart! The red streams mingle—the deep rattling voice Of Death exults in this last wild Revenge, And the low prayer of gratitude, and sigh Of love flow from the stiffening lips that breathed Their latest blessing on Arcadia's realm. And there, at eve, the searchers of the dead, Locked breast to breast, and palled in darkened blood, The tyrant and the avenging patriot found. URN BURIAL. Give not the human temple of the mind To the dead loathsome dust of ages gone, In the cold, silent, glimmering vault consign'd To the dark sceptre of Death's ebon throne; Give not the quench'd and shattered shrine, whereon Thought burned its incense, feeling breathed its prayer, O'er which Hope, Faith, and Intellect have flown, To the bleak, haunted darkness of despair— Oblivion's utter gloom, where Love cannot repair. Time rends the ties which frail Earth briefly gives, And the soul's visions vanish like the wind, But love immortal in its glory lives, And in elysium links blest mind with mind; E'en now, wing'd angels, watching o'er their kind, In parted beings old affection burns, As hovering o'er the haunts of thought enshrined, To the heart's home, that, once lost, ne'er returns, They wander gladly back and breathe upon their urns. The seraph visitants, who dwelt in forms, Redeemed by tears and hallowed by the grave, Float o'er our thoughts in starlight and in storms, And vainly languish for the love they gave; While each loved bosom, to cold dust a slave, Decays in darkness, and no eye looks down Upon Earth's buried mysteries to save The spirit's ark from sacrilege unknown, Or bring affection back with the altar and the crown. But there, pale tremblers o'er the prison tomb, Where Death from each heart-thrilling feature springs. The plumes of spirits quiver in the gloom, And vain sighs murmur in their restless wings, Uttering their deathless, doomed imaginings; While life is stirring in the ardent veins Of cheered survivors, and each daybreak brings Fair gleams of hope and fresh Arcadian strains, To gild the weeds of woe,—to hush Death's clanking chains. Nourished in loneliness by beam and dew, The azure waters and the emerald shore, Light from the mind, like Gods from Ida, flew, And breathed the immortal seraph's holiest lore; And, from the world's corruptings, thought would soar, When twilight taught religion, not of creeds, Beyond the power of evil, and deplore Frailties, o'er which the burning bosom bleeds, And guilt, that casts deep night where'er it wildly leads. Can this be Love's last refuge? this, the home Of the heart's ardors and elysian charms? To Death's cold mansion none of Time will come, Where thou sit'st, Earth! thy dead ones in thine arms! But shrinking fears and doubts and quick alarms Pervade and agonize the soul, that shoots Through the still dwelling, where no object warms The frozen sea of memory, and the roots Of Love decay, and leave sear trunk and blasted fruits. But, oh, how beautiful the olden rite! The twilight burial and the spicewood pyre! The asbestos robe, the witnesses of light From the blue heavens beholding son or sire Bearing the dead with torch, and urn, and lyre! Hope, memory, feeling, adoration dwelt Within the mind, that purified by fire The form, which, late, earth's sin and sorrow felt, Yet kept the dust beloved and with it gently dealt. Imagination, pathless and alone, Went with a soundless tread through being's sky, Bounding the infinite, naming the unknown, And blending mortal with what could not die: No voice, no vision, no revealing eye Restored man's error in his maze of dreams, But, solitary in creations high, He gave immortal thoughts to woods and streams, Bathed death's cheek in young dew and filled death's eye with beams. Thus, mounting to the fount of life divine, The spirit revelled in its visionries, Creating in each star a sacred shrine— Having its home in the blue evening skies! Man's hallowed love of beauty never dies, But, born with being, gleams along the track Of life, and, shadowing human destinies, Revokes the evelights of glad childhood back, And throws the rainbow's hues along the dark cloud's rack. These lofty thoughts around the dead became Soarings of tenderness, of Love that brought Electric union of the deeds and name, The flesh and the far being of the thought; High Intellect hath even shrunk from NOUGHT, With loathing chill, and fashioned, at desire, Worlds, where the fever, famine, ice, and drought, Can slay no more—where friendship and the lyre May hail, from ashes urned, the souls their songs inspire. But who will weep when I shall be no more? Who to my manes offer life's regret! The barque departs from being's desert shore— The storm-veiled sun of saddened mind hath set! Few are the hearts my wayward fate hath met Which mine could fold as heaven unto my soul, And these Earth shrouds or treachery's poison net; And thus, alone, to Death's world-darkened goal, Friendless, I haste and leave the orphans to their dole. Dread not thy doom as mindless vassals fear The tyrant's lash and torture, but, through all The hours allotted to thy action here, Thy deeds, as incense, rise above man's fall! So wisdom redes: but man is feeling's thrall. Shudders to part from gifts and blessings shrined In his unfathomed soul, and, most, to call In vain, along the boundless realms of mind, For them who were his bliss mid thankless humankind. In the grey dawn of Time, when high decrees Were uttered by each bosom's pulse of pride, When waters and dim woods had deities, Oreads in the air and tritons on the tide, And Nature's spirits o'er the heart did glide Like most familiar friends—each thought and deed Lifted exulting man, and purified The stain and taint of crime, till all his creed Was love to being's God and charity in need. With what a passion, through all human things, Frail hearts have panted in their pain to know The mysteries that fold their midnight wings Around the daring spirit! but earth's woe, Like the lone upas fountain's poison flow, Utters alone the oracles that thrill The soul, and, like the moaning ocean's glow, Quiver along the waves of good and ill, That rush towards the gulph where all is cold and still. Inspired by grief, and guided by lone love, The seers and sages of a better time Gave beauty to the dead in every grove, And household sanctity in every clime, And fellowship and faith and hope sublime. The deeds of years were, as Love's offering given, To the dread manes of their sires, and crime Fled from the Dead's Tribunal, wildly driven,— Daring not souls on earth whose home and throne were heaven. Thus intellect and feeling gave to form Undying action; to the eye and brow The shadows of divinity; thus warm From the deep fount came thoughts that lift us now From earth, and wreathe our hopes with heaven's own bow! Thus could our living meditations dwell On doom, left fearless by the light and flow Of life and hearthlight commune, Death's farewell Might on the closing ear like songs of seraphs swell!</field>
   </doc>
</add>