<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Paulding, James Kirke, 1778-1860</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Paulding, James Kirke, 1778-1860</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">paulding james kirke 1778 1860</field>
      <field name="author_text">Paulding, James Kirke, 1778-1860</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1810's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ap/uvaGenText/tei/chap_AM0786.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240350</field>
      <field name="date_text">1819</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:440223</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The lay of the Scottish fiddle : a tale of Havre de Grace</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- 1783-1850</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- 1783-1850</field>
      <field name="title_display">The lay of the Scottish fiddle : a tale of Havre de Grace</field>
      <field name="title_facet">lay of the scottish fiddle a tale of havre de grace</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">lay of the scottish fiddle a tale of havre de grace</field>
      <field name="title_text">The lay of the Scottish fiddle : a tale of Havre de Grace</field>
      <field name="year_display">1819</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1819</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1819</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440223&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440223&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Paulding, James Kirke, 1778-1860&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;paulding james kirke 1778 1860&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The lay of the Scottish fiddle : a tale of Havre de Grace&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;lay of the scottish fiddle a tale of havre de grace&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1819&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1819&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Paulding, James Kirke&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1778&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1860&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The lay of the Scottish fiddle : a tale of Havre de Grace&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;New York, Philadelphia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Published by Inskeep &amp;amp; Bradford, and Bradford &amp;amp; Inskeep&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1819&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3865752-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;cham0786&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- 1783-1850&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1783&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1850&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The lay of the Scottish fiddle : a tale of Havre de Grace&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1996&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1996 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 236 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-AmPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE LAY OF THE SCOTTISH FIDDLE: TALE OF HAVRE DE GRACE. PREFACE OF THE EDITOR. The poem here presented to the American public, was transmitted to the editor by a friend now in Edinburgh. It is there universally attributed to Mr. Scott, and the following is its private history as delivered to our friend, who is intimate in the literary circles of that town, by Mrs. Grant, (the ladies can't keep a secret) author of Letters from the Mountains, and other popular productions. No sooner were the brilliant achievements of Admiral Cockburn, received in Edinburgh, then a distinguished Bookseller waited on Mr. Scott, and offered him a large sum to celebrate them in a poem. Mr. Scott began his task on Monday-morning, on Saturday it was finished, and the first impression disposed of before the middle of the ensuing week. Such is shortly the history of this poem, which the editor now offers to the public without vouching for its authenticity. It may however be permitted him to make a few observations on the internal evidence of the production itself, from which he trusts it will appears pretty evident that the work is genuine. The critical reader will perceive many characteristics of Mr. Scott's manner and taste, throughout the whole, and will trace in the notes, that persevering industry in the investigation of antiquity, as well as that extraordinary acquaintance with local scenery and tradition, for which our author is unrivalled. He will also perceive the same fondness for quoting old ballads, and tracing the genealogies of illustrious families to their source. Another resemblance which cannot fail to strike the attention, is the studious abstinence of the author from all allusion, to the mythology and traditions of the ancients; the whole poem containing but one instance of the kind, as far as the editor remembers. At all events, the work is undoubtedly of British origin, as may be demonstrated by the total ignorance it displays of the Geography of this country, an ignorance which is exhibited in most of their writings, and particularly in the speeches of members of Parliament, whose knowledge of America is really wonderful, considering how far off it is. The poet in the very outset betrays his want of information in this respect, by making a poor blind fiddler and his little dog, walk from New-York to Princeton in one day; a thing altogether beyond the bounds of that probability to which all civilized poets are restricted by the rules of criticism. The reader will doubtless smile when he comes to that part of the poem in which our old friends Archy Gifford, and John Joline, are mentioned with such distinction and honoured with the title of lords, to which however they may for aught we know, be as fully entitled, as some of the distinguished heroes of modern chivalry. Every body in the world, at least in the new world, knows that Archy Gifford was, and John Joline is, as arrant a Tavern keeper as any in Christendom; yet has Mr. Scott, with a singular sort of perverseness, dubbed them both lords, and traced their lineage into the very bowels of the crusades. The honest truth of the matter is, that Mr. Scott seems to labour under a species of madness similar to that of Don Quixote, and arising from the same cause, the perusal of those mischievous books of chivalry, upon which the curate and the barber pronounced such heavy judgments. The sage Hidalgo, never came to an inn without mistaking it for a stately castle, or encountered an inn-keeper, without metamorphosing him into a noble Castellan, Governor, or high born nobleman. In like manner, our author with a singular felicity of imagination has contrived to make lords out of every body he meets; to convert honest Archy Gifford's good stone house into a castle, and to discover an inscription on his stables at Newark, which we firmly believe never existed. Mr. Scott, it will be perceived takes occasion in his notes, to introduce several political opinions, which we think might as well have been let alone. We considered it our duty however to give the poem and its illustrations exactly as we received them. It has long been the custom with foreigners to meddle in the affairs of our country, and their opinions with regard to the measures of our government, are considered so conclusive, that they are often quoted with triumphant exultations by the news-papers here. Our author has certainly as fair a right to the privilege of intermeddling as the best of them, and doubtless his opinions may be entitled to almost as much consideration as those of a British news-paper, even though they were sactioned by the weighty support of its brother editor here. We were a little surprised to find Mr. Scott making many sty, end to say the truth, rather severe remarks upon the character and conduct of the people of New-England, and ridiculing their claims to superior virtue and intelligence. In truth, the people of that enlightened quarter of the United States, are no favourites in Scotland from their too great dexterity in making bargains, a dexterity which is so notorious, that many bonny Scots, are rather shy of having any thing to do with them in this way. We are ourselves rather inclined however to attribute this apparent dislike of Mr. Scott, to a more honourable motive, and place it to the account of that disgust which, without any reference to party, every high spirited man in every country, must feel in contemplating the spectacle exhibited by the majority of the people of New England. Like honest Peter in Romeo and Juliet, the eastern patriot exclaims, “I dare draw my sword as soon as another man, when I see occasion, in a good cause, and with the law on my side.” Of all which circumstances he is to be the sole judge. With regard to the merits of this poem, we are inclined to place it above all Mr. Scott's other productions, particularly in point of novelty, and invention. The scene being entirely in a new world, the names introduced such as have never before figured in epic poetry, and the adventures mostly of the nautical kind, give it a degree of interest, and an air of freshness, and newness, extremely agreeable to those who have been some what surfeited with the sameness of his former productions. As far as we recollect there are not more than two or three nautical epic poems extant. The argonauts of Apollonius Rhodius, the Lusiad of Camoens, and perhaps the battle of the frogs and mice of Homer, are of this class. The writer therefore who essays this species of poetry possesses many advantages over all others, because the subject is not altogether worn thread-bare. Another conspicuous excellence of the Lay of the Scottish Fiddle is its originality. We will venture to say that Mr. Scott has borrowed from no poet ancient or modern, except himself; and that is a species of plagiarism, which deserves to be pardoned on account of its novelty. Few writers are ever detected in purloining their own thoughts, because in general they are not worth the trouble; and besides there is in all probability a sort of unaccountable satisfaction in riding a Foray into the territories of a rival author, and carrying off some of his best thoughts, which induces a man sometimes to venture his neck for it. It comes under the class of stolen pleasures, which are most peculiarly gratifying. The most glaring plagiarism of this kind, we think which Mr. Scott has been guilty of in the present instance, is the manifest similarity exhibited in the characters of the Buccaneer in Rokeby, and the hero of this poem, Sir Cockburn, a similarity which must strike the most superficial observer. He has also introduced some of the same lines that have heretofore been given to the public in his former productions. But we know of no law, which forbids a man to purloin his own goods, unless with a view of defrauding, the underwriters, who in general we believe have little to do with any writings, except policies of insurance, INTRODUCTION. The last relique of the ancient and most honourable order of minstrels, or troubadours in America, is observable in the itinerant fiddler, who travels about for the purpose of administering to the harmless gaiety of the rustics, by playing, and sometimes singing for them at their merry makings. In ancient times the fiddle was usually accompanied by the music of a cat, as appears from the following fragment of a very rare ballad, communicated to me by my valued friend Mr. James Hogg, the Ettrick shepherd. The accompaniment of the cat must have been a delightful addition to the harmony; and it is no wonder that the cow was so hugely delighted that she jumped over the moon. Indeed, there is nothing in all antiquity which exhibits the wonderful effects of music more strikingly, than this precious little fragment. Heye dyddle dyddle, Ye catte and ye fythele, Ye keouw yumped over ye moone; Ye leetle dogge laugffed Vor to zee syche craffte, And ye dysche felle a-lyckynge ye spoone. It appears by an ancient manuscript, that the “leetle dogge,” who laughed as well he might, at this eccentric caper of the cow, belonged to the laird Buccleuch, and was ancestor to the very identical dog mentioned in the preceding poem. But it has been asserted by learned antiquarians, that the fiddle, vulgarly called violin, by certain people of affected refinement, though very ancient, was probably not known to the Greeks and Romans, as there is no notice of the bow in the writings of these people. The earliest mention of the instrument in English literature, occurs in one of the last places that one would look for it, to wit, in the Life of St. Christopher, a metrical composition of the twelfth century. “Christofre, him served longe, “The kynge loued the melodye of fithele and songe. It is not a little singular that the saint should make himself agreeable to the king in this manner. Be this as it may, it has been ascertained by those who have by their labours administered so much to the laudable curiosity of mankind, that the fiddle was not in common use, or admitted in a concert, until the time of Charles the second. He being a right jolly king, was highly tickled with the inspiring strains of this merry making instrument, and forthwith established for himself, a band of four and twenty fiddlers, which gave rise to the famous and well known song of “Four and twenty Fiddlers, all in a row.” Such are the gross errors of careless inquirers into the history of this ancient and venerable instrument, which if it did not precede, was certainly contemporary with the bag pipe, the harp, the lute, and other instruments of acknowledged antiquity. So much has been said of the Welsh harp, the Irish harp, and the Scots harp, that this fortunate instrument has borne away the palm from all others, and stripped the fiddle in particular of those honours which are lawfully its due. The divine Raphael, as he is called, not because he was a doctor of divinity, but because he painted divinely, has sufficiently proved the antiquity of the fiddle, by representing Apollo fiddling most vehemently to the muses; and still further to exalt his favourite instrument has on another occasion introduced it in a concert of angels. The silence of the ancient writers being merely negative is certainly not to be placed against the positive authority of the divine Raphael, who by putting the fiddle into Apollo's hand, has plainly indicated his conviction of its being at least as old as the sun itself. The way was long, though 'twas not cold But the poor bard was weak and old, And carried scor'd upon his front Of many a year the long account. His Fiddle sole remaining pride Hung dangling down his ragged side, In faded bag of flannel green, It has been the custom from time immemorial in America, for a fiddler to carry his fiddle in a bag of green flannel or baize, probably in a sort of punning allusion to the green Bays, with which the poets have crowned Apollo, the great patron of minstrelsy. Among the many modern innovations, introduced by the Normans, Danes, Saxons, and Britons, who are gradually overrunning that easy country, is that of carrying the fiddle about in a box, which singularly resembles a child's coffin, and presents an antidote to all gestic hilarity. Through which the well carv'd head was seen Of gaping lion, yawning wide, In regal pomp of beastly pride. Almost all the ancient fiddles I have seen, have the head of a lion rudely carved, and gaping in a most outrageous manner. The reason of this is obvious, for as the Lion is the king of beasts, and the fiddle the most perfect, of course, the king of musical instruments, the carved head is doubtless intended to have a sort of hieroglyphical allusion to this analogy. Whether some connexion might not be traced by means of this hieroglyphic between the fiddle and the lyre of Osiris; alias Hermes Trismegistus, alias Mercury, the great Egyptian player, is a question deserving the serious consideration of Mr. Bryant, were he alive. That learned Atlas having so successfully transplanted Troy, with all its walls and battlements, like the house of our lady of Loretto, from one country into another, might be expected to prove Homer a Scotch piper, and Trismegistus a blind fiddler. The last of all the race was he, Who charm'd the ear with tweedle dee For lack-a-day! full well I ween The happy times he once had seen. When in the merry capering days Of olden time he tun'd his lays, 'Mong gallant lads, or jolly sailors, And play'd “the de'el among the tailors.” Had given place to other glee, And different strains of harmony. “The bigots of this iron time “Had call'd his harmless art a crime;” And now, instead of dance and song Pricking the night's dull pace along, And sprightly gambols deftly play'd By rustic lad and gleeful maid, And all that decks the cheek of toil, With nature's warm and heartfelt smile; No sound is heard borne on the gale, In village lone or rural dale, But canting, whining, nasal notes Twanging through hoarse and foggy throats, Ascending up the startled sky, Mocking the ear of deity, With nonsense blasphemous and wild; While wretches of their peace beguil'd, Scare the dull ear of drowsy night, With screams that boding screach owls fright, And hollow moans, that seem to flow From damned souls in shades below. Love-feasts are held at midnight's hour, These orgies, which are undoubtedly borrowed from the aboriginal Americans, have a striking resemblance to the war-dances of the savages, being accompanied by similar howlings, groanings, gnashing of teeth, strange contortions, and extravagant gesticulations. When fancy wields her potent power, And to the trembling wretch's eyes Sepulchres ope, and spectres rise, Gaunt forms, and grisly shapes appear, And sweet religion turns to fear. A fiddler now (no wight so poor,) May beg his bread from door to door, Nor tune to please a peasant's ear, Those notes that blithe King Cole might hear. This jolly king, was a contemporary of Fergus, Brian Borhoime, king Twaddle, and many other illustrious monarchs, about whom we know nothing; at least, nothing worth knowing. It is probable that he was neither more nor less than one of the ancient lairds of Col, who was remarkable for being fond of fiddling. In these days there were a prodigious number of petty sovereigns, like those whom the bitter little Emperor of the Gauls has sent packing These high chieftains, if they only had a forest of five hundred trees, with a reasonable proportion of bushes; two or three half starved deer; a game keep er—I beg pardon—a forester—dressed in green and silver, with enormous whiskers, and a toasting-iron two yards long, to frighten the poor peasants—together with a corporal's guard of long-queued soldiers, would forthwith set themselves up for mighty kings, and under that sacred title pick pockets, and rob on the highways with the best of them. Be this as it may, we learn that king Cole, or Col, was a great admirer of the fiddle, as appears from the following fragment of an ancient ballad sung on the Borders, preserved in the Bodleian Library. Owlde kynge Cole was a iollye owlde soule, And a iollye owlde soule was hee— Owlde kynge Cole was a iollye owlde soule, And hee caulled forre fytheles three. Another reading of this valuable relique is communicated to me by my learned friend Mr R. Surtees of Mainforth, who had it from his nurse, a very old woman, deaf and blind, and therefore the more likely to have a good memory. It runs thus. “Merrye kynge Cole, was a thyrstye olde soule, “And a thyrstye ohle soule was hee. “Merrye kynge Cole was sette round a boule, “And hee caull'd for fythlers three.” I shall endeavour to decide which of these is the true reading, in the next edition of this work. A little dog with gentle speed, Though not of black St. Hubert's breed, I have taken infinite pains to ascertain the true breed of this faithful little animal, but cannot flatter myself with having arrived at that degree of certainty, which a matter of such interest demands. He was not a bull dog; nor a ban dog; nor a badger; nor a greyhound; nor a pointer; nor a turnspit; nor a pug; nor a wolf dog; nor a Danish; nor a Siberian; nor a Chinese; nor a Newfoundland dog. The most general tradition is, that he was mongrel, having the proboscis of a pug, the body of a greyhound, and the bandy legs of a turnspit. Led by a string this man of woe, Whose faltering steps all sad and slow, Seem'd hastening toward that long, long home, Where rich and poor at last must come. Why did'nt that puppy walk behind? Alas! the fiddler was stone blind, And might not find his way alone Ev'n though meridian sun had shone. Betide him weal, betide him woe, In summer heat or winter snow, Or when the cutting midnight blast Around the leafy forest cast, And withering frost launch'd on the air Laid the sweet face of nature bare; When man and nature seem'd combin'd With biting frost, and whistling wind, To waste his poor remains of life In anxious toil and fruitless strife; Still that same dog, ne'er shrunk the while From nature's frown or woo'd her smile; But faithful to his wonted trust, More true than man, than man more just, He led the wight, from day to day, Unharm'd through all his darksome way. In lonely shed, at brightning blaze, In dewy fields, or hard highways, Or under branch of spreading tree, Where'er his lodgings chanc'd to be, Still that same little faithful guide, Stretch'd at his feet or by his side, While the poor houseless wanderer slept, His guardian watch for ever kept. Now cross'd they noble Hudson's tide, In steam boat, our young country's pride, And meet it is the poet say They paid no ferriage by the way. Through Jersey City straight they wend And Bergen hilltops slow ascend, This village is of great antiquity, in somuch that the oldest man now living at that place, who is so old that he cannot tell when he was born, does not remember its first settlement. The people here are noted for their “steady habits,” a source of great self-gratulation in many parts of America, whether these “steady habits” be good or bad, it would seem. The men wear the same shaped hats, the same redundant galligaskins, the same veritable linsey-woolsey coats, and the women appear in the same long-eared caps, striped petticoats, high-heel shoes, little silver buckles, and long waists, they figured in, during the happy days of the Dutch dynasty, rendered so illustrious by the renowned history of my friend Knickerbocker. In these “steady habits” they exceed even their neighbours in Connecticut, where fashions have undergone great changes since the golden age of the Blue Laws, when their simple ancestors were wont to cover their heads with half a pumpkin shell, and cut the hair by its regular outline, that no upstart hair might pride itself upon being longer than its neighbour. With respect to the fashion of their garments, there is a sad falling off, for I am enabled to state on the authority of an historian, who has told so many disagreeable truths of them, that in pure revenge they have called him a liar, that there is still extant in the family of Governor Jones of New-Haven, a pair of breeches, anciently worn on state occasions, by that redoubtable governor, so enormously puffed and plaited, as to contain by actual measurement twenty-four yards! Whence he who is possessed of eyes A gallant prospect often spies. Far off the noiseless ocean roll'd, A pure expanse of burnish'd gold. And nearer spread, a various view Of objects beautiful and new; Fair Hackinsack, Passaick smooth, A pleasant river and village in Jersey, of which I can find nothing remarkable, except the following fragment of a ballad, preserved in the library of the honourable society of advocates in Edinburgh. Dounte yoeue heare ye yeneralle saye, Stricke youre tenttes and marche away, Wythe youere knapsacks oune youere backe, Alle ye waye toe Hacbynesacke. CHORUS. Alle ye waye toe Hackynsacke, Wythe yoeure knapsacke on yoeure backe. This fragment is of great value as demonstrating the antiquity of knapsacks, which have heretofore been considered of comparative modern invention. That the fragment itself is extremely ancient, is clearly ascertained from the peculiarity of the chorus, which it will be observed consists merely in a transposition of the two last lines of the preceding stanza. This is precisely the characteristic of the most ancient specimens of ballad extant, and may be observed in the productions of the old minstrels, as well as the romaunts of the troubadours, whose poetry is full of repetitions and transpositions. This peculiarity may be even detected in the writings of Homer, the great father of poetry, who frequently makes his heroes repeat in their speeches, what he has just before said in his own proper person, merely with some trifling transposition. Those conversant in ballad poetry, which is certainly the most ancient of all, will readily, by resorting to this criterion, be enabled to decide on the claims of any production to superior antiquity. Whose gentle murmurs sweetly sooth, And Newark bay, and Arthur's sound, And many an island spread around; Like fat green turtles fast asleep, On the still surface of the deep. And Gotham might you see, whose spires, The ancient name of New-York, the most enlightened, elegant, and refined city of the New World. It was from this place, which possesses a harbour almost as beautiful as the bay of Naples, that those famous argonauts the wise men of Gotham, embarked in a bowl, or as some say an egg shell, for the purpose of searching out the Island of Atalantis, which Plato (ancestor of Plato, general of the Don Cossacks,) had just then discovered, but not laying down the latitude correctly, could never afterwards light on. What became of these great navigators is not certainly known. The most received opinion is that they landed somewhere in Europe, and became the ancestors of that numerous race of metaphysicians, economics, encyclopedist, and Illuminati, who in their zeal to enlighten that unlucky quarter of the globe, have set it together by the ears, and put its fortunes to sea in an eggshell, to take the chance of their favourite mode of navigation. Shone in the sun like meteor fires. The vessels lay all side by side And spread a leafless forest wide; And now and then the yo heave O Borne on the breeze, all sad and slow, Seem'd like the requiem of trade Low in its grave for ever laid. Here roll'd along in matchless pride, Old Hudson's stream is seen to glide, Majestic to its noble course It springs a river at its source! A thousand vessels plough its tide, A thousand beauties deck its side, A thousand products gem its fields, Ten thousand various goods it yields; And white along its glorious way The villages so new and gay, All scatter'd here and there are seen, On rising hill or level green. Winding their way in silent toll, O'er bridge, through turnpike-gate, and stile, Our weary travellers pass'd along, Cheer'd by the wild wood's merry song, Till faint with hunger, tir'd and lame, With blistered feet they faltering came, To where old Princeton's classic fane, With cupola, and copper vane, And learning's holy honours crown'd Looks from her high hill all around, O'er such a wondrous fairy scene, Of waving woods and meadows green, That sooth to say, a man might swear, Was never scene so wondrous fair. Here many a sign-post caught the view Among the many learned dissertations on the origin of coats of arms, I am not a little surprised that no writer has yet attempted to deduce them from sign-posts. It is allowed on all sides that coats of arms came into use about the time of the Crusades. Now we are fully aware that in the innumerable mixed rabble of nobles, who could not read, and priests who could not write, of pious knights who took the cross to wipe off old scores, or run up new; and miserable retainers who went without any motive at all—amongst this promiscuous multitude there would be a prodigious number of tipplers, and consequently, a great many suttlers, would follow the camp to supply the wants, and minister to the vices of the soldiery. In order to create a sort of individuality, in other words, to distinguish the person who sold liquor, from him who dealt in other articles, it is extremely natural to suppose that each would put up a sign at his door, beaing some rude representation of his calling. Thus the chequer board would indicate to the shrewd instinct of the thirsty crusader, that he might step in and arouse himself with a glass and a game. The mason's square and compass, that here resided a free and accepted mason; and the bottle spouting beer, that here was to be sold that inspiring liquor. The numerous race of Gaultherus', Aimerie's, and Geoffrey's, who having no sir names, were jumbled together in such confusion that one could hardly tell himself from another, insomuch that when Duke Godfrey, called for one Geoffrey, there came an hundred,—these shrewd fellows, I say, did probably observe the great use of the aforesaid signs, in establishing an individuality of character, and took the hint of adopting something of the kind by way of distinction. Instead however of hanging their signs on a tree, or a pole, as did the suttlers, they procured them to be painted on their shields in a superior manner and with a variety of decorations, to distinguish them from the vulgar. As too, they followed no other business than that of cutting of throats, they would most probably adopt the figure of some beast of prey; a lion, a tiger, a unicorn, a griffen; or some strange, bitter, blood-thirsty looking animal with a horrible grim face, and a mouth wide enough to swallow a Saracen, or one of the giants so common in those days. When in process of time, the descendants of the tavern keepers and nobles, got to be able to spell without much trouble, the former would in all likelihood add their names to these signs, together with some appropriate legend, such as “spiritous liquors sold here;” or “good entertainment for man and horse.” This of course would be followed up by the nobility who had imitated them in the first instance, and hence arose the fair and high sounding mottoes which are supposed to indicate the character, profession, and exploits of either themselves, or their illustrious ancestors. Of our poor dog, whose instinct knew Those fanes, by wandering minstrels sought, Where liquor may be begg'd or bought. In quick succession rose to view, The mason's square and compass true, The chequer board, the crossing keys, And, waving in the poplar trees, The uncork'd bottle spouting beer, Into the tumbler standing near, With curve so graceful, yet so just, That not a single drop is lost. But here stern bigotry abides Which lovely charity derides, Save, that which vulgar bosoms wins, That which at home with self begins. Fiddling and dancing they abhorr'd, And drove the minstrel from their board. Sadly he felt that trying hour, For now approach'd the summer shower. The murmuring thunder rolling far Made windows rattle with rude jar, Blue lightnings o'er the dark cloud sprung, Like serpents with their forked tongue; The patient beast, the hurrying man, With headlong haste for shelter ran, And nought that might a shelter find, Brav'd the rude storm, and rushing wind. The old man rais'd his sightless eye, To Him who rules the earth and sky; And seem'd from out that sightless bell, A tear of hard reproach to fall, That he, who gave the snake a home, Should leave blind men thus sad to roam— Perchance that drop fell from the sky, For now the pattering shower was nigh, And those dark eyes had long been dry. Even now he reach'd the welcome door That ne'er was shut against the poor, Where lord Joline his merry cheer, Deals out to all from far and near. With hesitating step at last The ample gate he slowly past; The lady saw his weary pace, His matted beard, his furrow'd face, Mark'd how his glassy eye balls glar'd, Yet no intelligence appeared; And bade her page the menials tell, That they should tend the old man well, And careful be of that same dog Who with the minstrel on did jog. When kindness had his wants supplied, And the old man was satisfied, Began to rise the Fiddler's pride. His elbow itch'd to quaver now; The little dog, cried bow, wow, wow, And wagg'd his tail to hear again, The music of some well known strain That the reader may not doubt the singular instinct of the little dog in thus, as it were, knocking down his master for a song, I will relate a few instances of the sagacity of animals which are authenticated by undoubted history. I mean that sagacity which is displayed in a particular animal attaching itself to a particular man, and following him with such affectionate solicitude, as to indicate something more than instinctive devotion. Nathaniel Wanley relates the following singular anecdote of a lynx, which came from Assyria with a person whose name I have forgot, “who was so affected towards one of his servants that it would attempt to detain him with its claws, when he was going away, and on his return received him with a wonderful alacrity and congratulation. At last the man crossed the sea with me to go into the Turkish camp, when the lynx refusing all nourishment languished and died.” “At Patras in Achaia, a boy called Thoas, had formed a great friendship with a young dragon, who when he grew up was carried to the wilderness and left there, for fear he would do mischief. Bye and bye, Thoas returning with some of his companions from certain sights, he and his companions were set upon by robbers. Thoas cried out lustily: his voice was straight known to the dragon, who immediately came forth to his rescue, frighted some, and slew others, and so preserved the life of his friend.” This attachment is the more remarkable, as dragons have at all times been considered as deadly enemies to all mankind except Giants and Enchanters, and have therefore been killed without mercy by the errant Knights. King Porus had his life saved by an elephant, who when he was down, lifted him on his back with his trunk, and carried him off at the expense of his own life. A dolphin in the Lucrine lake, as related by Mæcenas Fabianus, and others, loved a certain boy so much, that he came regularly every day and carried him on his back from Baiae to Puteoli to school, and back again. This he continued for many years until the boy fell sick and died. The dolphin came several days to the place, seeming to be very heavy and mournful, and spouting water as if he were crying, until at length, as was supposed, he died of grief and sorrow, and was found dead on the shore. “Busbequius affirms, that a Spaniard of Minorca was so beloved by a crane, that the poor bird would walk any way with him, and in his absence seek about for him, make a noise, and knock at his door. When he took his last farewell, not able to endure her loss, she abstained from all food and died.” But the most extraordinary instance is that related by Pliny, who says “at Aegium, a town in Achaia, a goose fell in love with a young man of Obenus, named Amphilochus.” The goose prayed stoutly to Venus that her form might be changed, and the goddess at length taking pity on her, metamorphosed her into an exceeding pretty and foolish young lady, who could never however entirely divest herself of the love of feathers, and as Pliny says, “in many essentials remained a goose all her life.” These instances of an ardent attachment, are quite sufficient to render probable, all that has been related in this poem of the sagacity of the little dog, and his love for his master, though an old man and blind withal. The minstrel 'gan to prate anon, Of Archy Gifford—dead and gone, The family of Gifford of Newark Tower, or as it is spelled in ancient ballads, Gyfforde, is of singular antiquity, and its origin, like that of most other illustrious houses enveloped in great uncertainty. Walter de Gyfforde was a famous knight in his day, and very intimate with all the celebrated Border chiefs, such as Buccleuch, Douglas, Kerr, and Craustoun. His most intimate friend however was Roger Bigod, the great swearer. They were all “ryghte lustye roysteringe blades,” as appears from the following lines of an old ballad, furnished me by Jacobus Porcus, to whom I cannot sufficiently express my obligations for the invaluable reliques he has favoured me with from time to time. “Gyfforde whatte tak a mannes cattelle; “Cranstoun sponsebreker to tryue lyue; “Buccleuch whatte thieuery dydde lyue welle; “Roger wych swere by sainctes abyue, “All them ayenst ye lawes dydde stonde, “Ynne Scotlande, soe ynne merrye Englonde. It is but justice, however, to the late Lord Archy to say, that he never committed any of these chivalric outrages upon his neighbours, except honest Joe Miller, against whom he used now and then to ride a Foray, despoiling him of some of his best jokes, and converting them to his own use. In general, he demeaned himself like a right hospitable gentleman, keeping open house, and entertaining all comers most royally. Lord Archy built the magnificent stables in the rear of his stately tower of Newark, where he always kept “four and twenty steeds,” ready dight, for his visitors to ride a hunting. He also had painted the great picture representing a hunting match, which being too large for his hall is suspended by two stout poles at the south-west corner of the castle. The following curious inscription is cut on the corner stone of the stables. INSCRIPTION. “Ich, Archy Gifforde, dedde and ygonne, “Mysel trewliche putten thilke stonne. “Ye lorde delieueren hym yane mercye, “Fromme bodyliche penaunce synne and heresye. “Zo hertiliche toe eueryche yonne, “Whysheth hym holpe ynne godde hys sonne. This inscription is remarkable on many accounts, but principally as appearing to be written by Lord Archy, after he was “dedde and ygonne.” Of good John Gifford—rest him God— The present lord of Newark tower, who succeeded his brother Lord Archy in default of male issue, or indeed issue of any other kind. Lord John formerly resided at the stately castle occupied by Lord Joline at Princeton, but removed, to the ancient family mansion on the death of his brother. His lordship keeps up the ancient hospitality of the late lord, and is in every respect a worthy successor, and right worshipful supporter of the honours of his ancient and illustrious house. A stouter ne'er at training trod. And would the beauteous lady deign, To listen to his lowly strain, Though tir'd with walking many a mile, And worn with hunger, thirst, and toil, He did'nt know, he could'nt tell, Perchance the strain might please her well. The gracious ladye with a smile, Glad thus the evening to beguile, Granted the minstrel's lowly suit, And gave the wight a dram to boot. And now he said he would full fain, He could recall an ancient strain He never thought to sing again. It was not farm'd for common swine But such high lords as John Joline. He once had play'd for John Gifford. Till he fell asleep, and loudly snor'd, And much he long'd yet fear'd to try The sleep compelling melody. Amid the strings his fingers stray'd As if an harp he oft had play'd, But sooth to say he shook his head. Yet soon he caught the measure true, Of yankey doodle—doodle doo. And pleas'd to find he'd found the strain, Warm transport seem'd to fire his brain, The fiddle with his chin he press'd, The fiddle press'd against his breast, His fingers o'er the cat-gut stray'd, His elbow work'd, and work'd his head, And as he dol'd the jingling rhyme, With thundering rout his foot kept time They thought the d?l was in the man, When the Last Fiddler thus began. CANTO I. THE THREE KNIGHTS. I. The feast was over in the cabin below, And the knight was pacing to and fro, Sir Bolus, or Sir Boriase Warren, whose exploits in the Chesapeake are, as they say of quack medicines, “too well known to need any praise from us.” Sir Bolus, like the American Eagle, carries in one hand a bundle of arrows, and in the other an olive branch, to indicate that he brings the choice of peace or war. As the sage Gargantua, according to Monsieur Rabelais, was once in a situation in which he did not know whether to laugh, or cry, and compromised matters by laughing with one side of his face, and crying with the other; so in like manner Sir Bolus, being divided as it were between peace and war, one day burns a town, and the next, professes a violent inclination to be friends with America. On the quarter deck that was guarded well: Who thinks to pass that centinel, Jesu Maria! shield him well! No living wight, but that knight did dare, To print his vent'rous footstep there. II. The tables were clear'd, it was idlesse all, The gun room lads were fast asleep; Silent the rabble rout was all, And silent breeze and weltering deep. The sailors, bottle loving race, Stretch'd half asleep recumbent lay, And urg'd in dreams the galiant chase, Of oyster-boats far up the bay. III. Full seven hundred valiant tars, Doff'd their hats when the knight came by, All fam'd afar in aéval wars, And feats of modern chivalry. Six lieutenants, stout and bold, Twelve midshipmen, not quite so old, Jolly lads of mettle true, Officer'd this gallant crew. IV. All of these were clad in blue, With belted loins and broad-sword true, They quitted not their steel so bright. Neither by day, nor yet by night: They lay down to rest, With doublet all brac'd, Pillow'd on plank, so rough and hard; They carv'd at the meal With sword of true steel, And they drank their small beer out of buckets all tard V. Why do these lads stand ready dight? Why watch these warriors, armed by night They watch to hear the night watch hail, Some enemy's or neutral sail; To see the beacon glimmering far, Like will-o'-wisp or shooting star; They watch 'gainst suthron force and guile, Lest Hull, or Decatur, or Jones's powers, Should threaten their Lordly floating towers, From New-York, or Boston, or Norfolk the while VI. Sir Knight with anxious cares oppress'd, As little shar'd of peace or rest, But pac'd with doubtful step and slow, Now back and forth, now to and fro. Care sat upon his wrinkled brow, As deep revolving, when and how He might chastise the sinful fry, Who dar'd His majesty defy, And brac'd in arms, defend their right, Gainst such a true and valorous knight VII. And then he call'd his captains straight, By signal from far and near, Quick in his presence to appear, And on his Knightship wait. And then was heard the mournful strain. Of yo, heave O, and launch'd amain. The jolly boats began to ply, Their feathery oars right rapidly, While as they dip the briny tide, And o'er its swelling bosom glide, Who on the waters cast his eye, Might see them sparkle like the sky, When myriad stars all gaily bright, Gem the pale robe of dusky night. VIII. What gallant chiefs well known to fame, To answer thus the signal came? Sir Beresford, a sturdy limb, This gallant chieftain was formerly we understand on a visit to the city of Gotham, where he partook of the hospitality for which that ancient city is so celebrated, particularly with reference to any of his Britannic Majesty's officers. He was at all the entertainments given by the rich merchants, and to use his own phrase, “punished” some of their claret pretty handsomely. In fact you could go no where without seeing him. When he left that place he amused himself with cruising just without the harbour, bringing to every vessel going in or out, particularly if they happened to belong to the gentlemen whose claret he had “punished,” and practising all that train of petty tyrannical imposition, which America has been in the habit of receiving from the two “great Belligerents” for several years past. Sir Beresford has lately distinguished himself by capturing the Wasp, an American “seventy-four in disguise,” for which we believe he received the honor of knighthood. To drink or fight all one to him, Though sooth to say, 'twas always thought, In liquor he most bravely fought; Nor ever so resistless felt As when beneath his buck-skin belt, He carried store of claret rare, Sooth! then he'd fight, as well as swear. Far fam'd was he for noted feats 'Mongst oyster boats and neutral fleets, And never turn'd his back they say, To any ship that ran away: From “Emerald Isle,” he swaggering came To fill his purse, I ween full fain. IX. Sir Cockburn next, a border chief, Sir Cockburn, or Childe Cockburn, as he is indifferently called, is a distinguished freehooter of the new order of knights of the post. I have entered so fully into his character in the poem, that it is quite unnecessary to resort to my usual method of illustrating by notes. One anecdote however will show how nearly he approaches the models of the purest order of chivalry, in uniting the most unheard of bravery with the most gallant devotion to the ladies. After the burning of Havre de Grace, a party headed by Sir Cockburn, with his usual solicitude to be foremost in every gallant achievement, made an excursion to the house of a neighbouring gentleman, in which several ladies of the first respectability had taken refuge. After plundering the house, they were proceeding in the true spirit of border chivalry, to set it on fire, when a lady in an agony of terror, fell on her knees to the gallant knight, and begged him to spare the house, and “she would love him as long as she lived.” He did spare the house, but nothing else, and the next day in answer to the application of the lady for the restitution of her clothes, jocosely reminded her “that he hoped she would remember her promise.” This was in the true spirit of a William of Deloraine, and plainly showed that Sir Cockburn was well versed in the ordinances of chivalry, where the most lofty daring is coupled with the most “generous loyalty to age and sex.” I am told that America is a rare place for British officers, and that the ladies there, many of them, resemble a certain fish, which is easily taken with a bit of red rag. This circumstance probably induced sir Cockburn to play off his gallantry, not supposing that a lady of the least taste or refinement could hate one of his majesty's officers, even though he were a perfect Barrabbas. Descended from full many a thief, Who in the days of olden time, Was wont to think it little crime, In gallant raid at night to ride, And scour the country far and wide, Rifle the murder'd shepherd's fold, Do deeds that make the blood run cold, And cottage fire with burning hand, In Durham, or in Cumberland. Full well their great examples stole Into Sir Cockburn's daring soul, When in his father's mouldering hall, Where day light oft peep'd through the wall, And bats and rooks, and night's lone bird, O'er pilfer'd prey to scream were heard. His sybil nurse the story told, Of many a stout moss trooper bold, Who 'gainst his king, and country stood, Knee deep in pious christian blood. Blood of Armstrong and Deloraine, Skulk'd through the urchin's itching vein, And well he prov'd the great descent For both in him seem'd sweetly blent. When puling in his nurse's arms, He stole her amulets and charms, Pilfer'd her snuff, at sabbath day Purloin'd her lov'd prayer book away, And early shew'd how great he'd be, In feats of modern chivalry. X. Oft from his bed he forth did hie, At ghastly midnight hour, When witches on their broomsticks ply, And fairies leave their bowoe. And roam at large o'er hill and dale, And prowl in silence round, Skulking, like sheeted spectre pale, O'er holy churchyard mound. And if perchance he hap'd to find, A hen roost he might rob, Or shirt, aye swelling in the wind. Or any other job; Merrily, merrily he would hie, To the castle and hide his spoil, And when was rais'd a hue and cry, Like holy innocent would smile XI. Such were his childish feats I ween, And ere he sixteen years had seen, Five times in the stocks he'd been. At length to be more bravely free, To rob at large, he went to sea. For he had heard the valiant feats, Of British tars and British fleets, That bullies of the subject seas, Not only rob their enemies, But claim the right, as Yankies know, To plunder friend as well as foe. XII. Here full three years our hero pass'd, In phrase marine, before the mast, Where he was driven from pole to pole, Blasted his eyes, and d?d his soul, Chew'd, smok'd, crack'd jokes, and drank his flip, And learn'd all arts of seamanship. Until at last he rose to be, A boisterous captain of the sea. XIII. He once had sail'd the world all round, And could with many a tale astound, Of the far-fam'd Antipodes, Where people walk'd on hands and knees, And thus like flies against the wall, With back turn'd downwards us'd to crawl, And sometimes through sheer want of care, Would tumble off—the Lord knows where. He too had been on Lapland shore, Where witches keep such mighty store, Of winds compress'd in knot so tight, The Lapland witches, or rather wizards, are one of the last ragged remnants of the ancient pagan mythology, and derive their origin from high antiquity. They are probably the descendants of the priests of Æolus, who, according to Homer, made Ulysses a present, which destroyed his whole fleet, and threw him high and dry on the island of Ciree, who was no other than an arrant Lapland witch. It is difficult to account for people in this remote situation, retaining among them almost the only remnant of ancient classical superstition, now remaining in Europe. But when we consider, that many of the ingenious writers on the subject of the diffusion of mankind, and the consequent diffusion of science and learning, have pointed out the hyperborean regions, See Gibbon. Ed. as the most probable source of both, it will not appear altogether preposterous, to suppose that Lapland, being the very centre of that genial quarter, is the identical spot. This is rendered more probable, by the universal opinion of the natives who, one and all, agree in calling this seducing territory the terrestrial paradise. If so, it is a circumstance that may humble the pride of the arrogant natives of the east, to be told that they are not only descended, but derive all their pretensions to civilization and refinement, from a little diminutive set of Semi-Trogiodytes, who live half the time by the light of fish oil instead of the sun; who sell nothing but wind; who know no other physic, but moss, mushroons, and turpentine; live on dried fish, and bread made of pine trees; and are at present in such a confirmed state of ignorance, as to serve the father-in-law a whole year, only to get his daughter for a wife! Not one of them can take a flight, Or blow a breath without their leave, As all good seamen well believe. Sir Captain bought of these a store, And out to sea in triumph bore; Where like Ulysses he would brag He had them all tied in a bag. When e'er becalm'd on wat'ry waste, He made one of his knots unfast, And swore the wind did always blow, The very way he wish'd to go. XIV. Castor and Pollux, those dread lights, At mast head seen in stormy nights, Castor and Pollux. In meteorology, are fiery balls which appear at the mast head, or sticking to the shrouds of vessels during a storm at sea. When only one of these balls is seen, it is called Helen, and indicates that the worst part of the storm is yet to come. These lights were sometimes called Tyndarides by the ancients; by the Spaniards, they are called San Elmo, by the French, St. Nicholas; by the Italians, Hermo; and by the Dutch, Vree vuuren. Experienced mariners have informed me, that they have often sent their sailors up the shrouds to catch one of these balls of fire, but without success; and if sir Cockburn really caught one, he did what no other navigator ever performed. It is said that a large jack-o-lantern of this kind, inhabits a high mountain in the island of Samos, which is situated at the mouth of the Gulf of Glaucus, a very dangerous place on account of fogs and sudden gusts, and that many vessels have been preserved by it's light. Castor and Pollux, from whom these meteors derive their name, were two strange birds, hatched from two strange eggs of Leda. The story is extant in the ancient Grecian mythology, which is very properly put into the hands of children, to initiate them into the whole mystery of intrigue, terrestrial and celestial. The two brothers agreed very well together; so much so, that Castor dying, the surviving brother, who was gifted with immortality, for reasons set forth in the ancient scandalous chronicle, obtained permission to share his immortality with him. Accordingly, while one was on earth, the other sojourned in the regions below, resembling in this respect two well-buckets, one of which always descends, as the other rises. Castor being a great hunter of beavers, was the first to introduce into Greece that particular part of the animal, which has ever since been called by his name, which has likewise descended, or rather ascended, to the peculiar hat, which he formerly wore, and which to this day is called a Castor hat. The two brothers, as the story says, were at length translated to the skies, as was not unusual in those days, when no other translations ever took place, and formed the constellation of Gemini, which may be seen in front of the almanac. The exclamation of “O Gemini!” which is very ancient, is derived from this constellation. The Castorian dance, still in use among the American Indians, and which consists in jumping up as high as possible, and crying Boh! was instituted in honour of Castor, who in hunting the beaver, got exceedingly intimate with the savages of the north-west. Whether he was the original founder of the north-west company, is an inquiry, which though deserving attention, would lead me into too extensive a discussion. Castor and Pollux were very popular among the Romans, because they once appeared in a battle, and turned the scale of victory in their favour. There can be no doubt of the fact, because it is written in the famous Linen Books, that the constellation of Gemini was not visible for two nights; and where could it be gone, except to the battle? They were mounted on white horses; whence originated the custom among modern generals of riding on one of that colour. He had entrapt as we trap rats, Or boys catch fire-flies in their bats, Had tam'd them too with wondrous skill, And us'd to light his binnacle. The flying Dutchman, direful sprite! He chas'd one live long winter's night, And drove him ere the break of day, Full high and dry in Table bay. [Mr. Scott having unaccountably neglected hanging a note to this passage, the Editor has attempted to supply the omission.] Of the origin and history of this famous marine spectre, I have been able to learn but little. The general opinion among seamen is, that a certain Dutch skipper, as obstinate as a mule, beating up into Table Bay, at the Cape of Good Hope, with the wind in his teeth, and being frequently driven back, at length swore by “dunder and blixum,” his usual oath, that he would get into the bay in spite of God or man. No one knows what became of him; but the vessel is often seen by experienced mariners, ploughing the waves towards Table Bay, where as yet her has not arrived according to the latest information; neither have I seen any authentic account of her destiny, either in Lloyd's list, or the gazette of Solomon Lang, printed at Gotham. According to the Lusiad of Camoens, Vasco de Gama in weathering the Cape of Good Hope, encountered a stormy and gigantic spirit, which disputed his passage several days, and raised a variety of tempests in order to drive him back, but without effect. Whether the flying Dutchman has any connection with this memorable sprite, or whether he belongs to the family of the Water-kings, of which King George, as sovereign of the seas is the undoubted head; or whether a branch of the water-wraithe, or mermaid, so plenty about the Orkneys, it is difficult, perhaps impossible for us to decide at this distance. I am rather inclined to suppose, that all these nautical superstitions may be traced to the common centre of the Gothic mythology, with the exception of Neptune, who has of late been so completely kept under by the British navy, that he only now and then pops up his head like a frog, to take breath. Like all other deposed monarchs, he is held in great contempt, except indeed by poets and sailors. The former find him useful in giving dignity to their naval songs; and the latter, in crossing the line, celebrate an exhibition in his honour, which baffles all the mummeries of antiquity. Even gods have their day, and often in former times used to follow the fate of their worshippers. Thus, when the Goths and Vandals, the ancient Cossacks of the north, who delivered Europe into the bonds of ignorance and barbarity, overturned the western Empire of the Cæsars, the whole fraternity of Olympus lost their seats, and with them went the Dryades, the Hyades, the Nereides, the Naiads, the Potamides, the Oreades, and all the gentle beings, that rendered the woods, the fountains, the rivers, and the ocean of ancient times so delightful to the imagination. In their room came the upstart and ignoble herd of Gothic superstition, a set of mischievous, and diebolical goblins, the very engines of terror and dismay, as is thus set forth by honest Reginald Scott, great-grandfather to Michael Scott, the famous enchanter, whose shadow could not be seen in the dark. “Then came “says he,” the witches the urchins, elues, hags, imps, calcars, conieuers, changelings, incubus, Robin-Hood-fellow, the spoorne, the mare, the man in the oke, the Hell-waine, the fire drake, the puckle, hob-goblin. Kit with the canstick. Tom Thumbe, Tom tumble, boncles, and such other Bugs, that we are afeard of our own shadowes.” Oft o'er his cuts he made his boast, He'd seen on Norway's ire-bound coast. A Kraaken of such wondrous size, He scarcely could believe his eyes. The geographers make mention of a fish of this kind, that went on shore on the coast of Norway some years ago, which though not quite so large as the one seen by Sir Cockburn, was yet of a magnitude superior to any described in antiquity, and may almost compare with the famous turtle, who according to the highly curious and interesting mythology of the Brachmans, carries the earth on his back, and thus in reality prevents its sinking into the bottom of the sea. This knocks Sir Isaac Newton's theory of gravitation on the head, and I am surprised that Sir William Jones, and the Asiatic society, should inundate us thus with these puzzling notions, which militate against our established opinions, and set us again adrift on the ocean of conjecture. For my part, I had made up my mind in this respect, until the story of the great turtle drove me from my anchors, upon the shoals of doubt and uncertainty: to be shipwrecked, for aught I know to the contrary. Had Sir William Jones applied his great learning and unequalled talent for research, in the investigation of matters of more importance to mankind, such as the recovery and exposition of the memorials of border chivalry, or the discovery and collating of old ballads instead of poring over the remains of Sanscrit black-letter, he would have done much more towards enlightening and civilizing the human race than by all his multifarious eastern researches. Full easily the earth 'twould span, As eel a common frying pan; So heavily it press'd the ground, The world could hardly turn around; This side of earth quite low did seem, While t'other fairly kick'd the beam: Whence he deriv'd the long long nights, That vex'd those luckless northern wights. In short, from Sinbad fam'd of old, Down to the days of Crusoe bold, [Here Mr. Scott had inserted copious extracts from the romances of these renowned persons, noting all the editions of the Arabian Nights that ever have been published, and adding a copious biography of Daniel De Foe, the author of Robinson Crusoe, together with a full description of the island of Juan Fernandez. The editor supposing that though these matters may be novelties among the ignorant people of Great Britain, they are fully known in this country, has taken the liberty of omitting the whole note, which comprised nearly twenty-seven pages. The bookseller indeed stood out manfully for its insertion, as it would make the book larger, but it was at length agreed to omit it altogether, advertising the reader of the cicumstance. Ed.] There ne'er had liv'd a vent'rous elf, Who told such stories of himself; One who had rode so many gales, Or thrown so many tubs to whales. XV. Bold captain now of ship of war, He shew'd in triumph many a scar; But whether they at home were got, In midnight feats of yore, Or naval fight, yet well I wot, Some curious marks he bore. That look'd Gramercy! like the print, Of lashes given with heavy dint, Of cat-o-nine tail, or rope's end; From whose dread smart me heav'n forefend. XVI. Sir John and Sir Cockburn in plundering renown'd, Sat in the cabin, in thought profound, Waiting to hear sage Sir Bolus propound. His hand was press'd by his sun burnt cheek, As he por'd o'er the chart of our bay Chesapeake, While his finger along the surface did pass, Till it made a full stop at Havre de Grace. Then might you see his red eye flash; Then might you hear his white teeth gnash, As starting up with a ghastly grin, The Stalwart knight did thus begin. The minstrel paus'd, his faltering hand, No more could age and toil withstand. The hardships of his lonely way, And time, and grief had stol'n away, The vigour of his early prime, The spirit of his early time; And now he thought in bitter sooth, That rob'd of sight and lusty youth, He might not now, as wont, essay To please high lords and and ladies gay Yet still he trembling seem'd to ask, If they approv'd his minstrel task; And said, perchance his skill was fled, For well-a-day! his sightless head, Where winter snow and summer heat, Were wont in ruthless wrath to beat, Perhaps, lack'd fancy to impart, Sweet pleasure to the hearer's heart. It was not that 'twas dark midnight, That the pale moon withheld her light, Alike to him was time and tide, No day or night his hours divide; To him alike or gloom or light, For him 'twas one long pitchy night. Whether the wandering sun-beam play'd, Or moon-light o'er the waters stray'd, Or darkness veil'd the earth and skies, The same to his dark sightless eyes. T'was night when pleasure was away, And sunshine when his heart was gay. The lady now to praise began, And reassur'd the lowly man; Who pleas'd to think they lov'd his lays, And like all minstrel's fond of praise, Amid the strings his fingers laid, And thus the second canto play'd. CANTO II. THE COUNCIL. And said I, that my limbs were old, And that my head with age was cold; That time had quench'd my wonted fire, And stol'n the witchery of my lyre, And curb'd my fancy's youthful pride? If I said so, why, then I lied! I cannot view fair nature's face, Nor catch her well remember'd grace; Nor taste the balm of beauty's smile, That cheer'd my lonely heart ere while; Nor see the wood-land warbler stray, In careless freedom on the spray; Yet when I hear the summer breeze, Play o'er the bosoms of the trees, Whose answering whispers seem to tell, They love the gentle visit well; Or the wild music of the grove, Vocal with notes of lusty love; Or what is sweeter to my ear, The voice of gentle damsel near; Remembrance waken'd starts away, To blithesome scenes of distant day, When these dead eyes could freely scan, The face of nature and of man; Catch, mantling in young beauty's cheeks, The blush that untold secret speaks, Translate the glances of her eye— The only real witchery. I. The opening eye-lids of the dawn, A smiling glance threw o'er the lawn, Where dew-drops glitter'd in the ray. And Gossamers all sparkling lay, Like veil bespangled all with gold, And thrown in many a careless fold, O'er the fair head of damsel gay, To hide her beauties from the day II. Sir Bolus and the doughty knights, Who long ago had dous'd their lights, An expression of sailors to signify that a man has gone to sleep. In hopes to dream of some rare plan, To break the head of stout foeman, Awaken'd by the swift wing'd ray, Bright herald of the coming day, That o'er the world of waters play'd, And in the cabin window stray'd, Start up, as did their great compeer, When struck by bright Ithuriel's spear Sir Bolus then—prodigious man, Unfolded thus his glorious plan. III. “Did not Josiah Quincy say, “In congress only t'other day, Mr. Quincy is I understand a famous prophet, the Richard Brothers of the Eastern States of America, and their oracle in the Congress of the United States. The speech to which Sir Bolus alludes is full of prophetic denunciations, uttered, as I am told, with all the fury of a sybil, but without her inspiration it would seem. Like the unhappy Cassandra, he appears to be for ever prophesying, without ever having the good fortune to be believed. Cassandra, however, was always revenged on the incredulity of mankind by the fulfillment of her predictions; whereas, it is I understand observed of this honourable gentleman, that he has neither the pleasure of being believed when he tells of futurity, nor the melancholy consolation of being justified by the event. I remember he predicted the ruin of that country, if the bank of the United States was refused a renewal of its charter, and many of my friends on that event taking place, in great consternation wrote to America, to dispose of their public stock, supposing that an immediate dissolution of the confederacy would ensue. Indeed from a observation of his speeches for sometime past, it will appear that there was hardly any measure of a national nature, that did not loom before his prophetic vision, as the sad precursor of the ruin of the country. Yet it would seem that country, like an obstinante patient, whom some prophetic quack had foredoomed to death, still wickedly and indecorously survives, in spite of the Doctor's own potent endeavours to the contrary; a monument of his incapacity either to foretell, or to bring about his own predictions. For most assuredly it appears, from the view which we on this side the water are enabled to take of American affairs, that if the Union of the States is not speedily dissolved, it will not be owing to any want of exertion on the part of Mr. Quincy or his friends. “That Britain's power was unconfin'd, “As raging flood, or freeborn wind? “That in three months no Yankey sail, “Would spread its bosom to the gale? “With such encouragement we came, “In hope to share the glorious game, “And line our coffers with that gold; “The love of which makes bord'rers bold. “And yet by our bright ruling star, “The star of plunder and of war, “Save neutral, or d?d oyster boat, “Not fit on ocean's wave to float, “A skiff, a veritable log, “As none, but vent'rous Yankey dog, “Would trust his carcase in a mile, “Though ocean wore her sweetest smile; “Save such vile prey, our cruise has been, “The vilest cruise that o'er was seen.” IV. He ceas'd, then cast his hopeless eye, On a huge map just lying by, And straight that eye, with living fire, Was lighted up in bitter ire; In tones that quell'd the ocean wave, Thus our good knight began to rave. “The recreant wight, who dares to say, “In the bright face of this good day, “That in this land French influence “Exists not—sure has lost his sense. The proof here adduced by Sir Bolus of the existence of French influence is certainly one of the strongest that I have seen, and I really do not perceive how the American government can get over it. There can be no stronger proof of our regard for a friend, than that of naming our offspring after him, and certainly the naming of a town, is, if possible, a more striking proof of devotion. Being ignorant of the existence of these two places, Havre de Grace, and French town, I had hitherto supposed this charge of French influence against the American President, had no foundation. But I now without hesitation, coincide with Mr. Quincy, Lord Castlereagh, the Prince Regent, and other distinguished persons. So far should the President be from complaining, that I think he ought to be highly obliged to Sir Cockburn, for destroying such glaring proofs of his apostacy from the true interests of his country. “A living proof, behold we here, “In black and white distinct appear, “Behold sir knights, a vile French place, “Call'd Havre—with a d?d de Grace! “Another too! yclept French town, “Which we by Heav'n must tumble down, “Ev'n though their walls were twelve feet thick, “Of good grey stone, or blood-red brick; “Like those of far fam'd Lewistown, “We tried in vain to batter down; Sir Bolus is here jocular upon the letter of Sir Beresford, giving a pompous account of the walls of Lewistown, which at some future period will most likely be equally celebrated with these of ancient Troy, for having some Bully Hector, like the redoubted Knight, dragged by the heels round them. As the valour of the English seems altogether predicated of roast-beef, I think the Americans are in the right to keep them from procuring it, as much as possible; in which care they will in all probability be able to prevent their making any impression upon that country. The only satisfactory reason why an English sailor beats a Frenchman, is that the former eats roast-beef, when he can get it and the latter, soup, which is much more likely to make a man run away than fight. There can be no greater proof of the truth of this theory, than the events which have taken place on the Ocean, since the commencement of the present contest with America. It is a singular fact, which has hitherto escaped the sages who have attempted to account for the unexpected results of our late Naval engagements, that they all took place on what is called Banyan Days; that is, those particular days of the week set apart for the special eating of soup. That this, and not any small superiority of force, or any physical superiority in the men, or any superior excitement on the part of the enemy, “nor any over anxiety on our part to come to close quarters,” was the true cause of our repeated disasters, on our “own element,” I think cannot be doubted. In order to avoid such repeated disgrace in future, it would be advisable, either to strike the Banyan days out of the nautical calendar, or else always to make a point of coming to action some other day in the week. “Which like Amphion fam'd of old, “Sir Beresford, in safety bold, “Rais'd up by magic of his lyre, “To keep the town from catching fire. V. Childe Cockburn to Sir Bolus goes, With spectacles on Bardolph nose, I cannot positively say that Childe Cockburn had a red nose, but there are several reasons to suppose so. Dugdale in his account of the illustrious families of the British peerage, affirms, that the Cockburns were anciently called Cock, from their being such fighting fellows; and that the burn was afterwards added on account of one of them having distinguished himself, by burning several cottages and haystacks in a border-foray. Others say, that this addition was expressly given in honour of the red nose, which was hereditary in this family, and that Bardolph himself was one of the Cockburns, who were, as Shakespeare says, celebrated for “carrying a lantern in the poop.” That Sir Cockburn, who inherits the hereditary taste for burning, should also have succeeded to the red nose, is extremely probable, and I have accordingly directed that he should hoist his lantern, without further ceremony. In the dearth of Sirnames, which characterised those remote times, the colour of the nose often became of common use, to distinguish different individuals of the same name, different families, and different factious from each other. The most celebrated instance of this sort is the feud between the houses of York and Lancaster; and the most singular instance of historical blundering, I have ever known, is connected with this circumstance. All the historians I have met with, agree in saying that the badges of distinction between the two rival houses, were the red and the white rose; whereas, the late Lord Orford has, or at least could have demonstrated, that the true reading ought to be the red and the white nose. Under these two noses, all the people of England marshalled themselves; and the Cockburns, who were of course distinguished red-noseans, signalized themselves in various burning expeditions. Hence originated the different titles of Admiral of the red, and Admiral of the white, which were first need to distinguish the fleets of Lancaster and York from each other. The custom is still kept up, but the reasons, as usual, have been lost. Childe Cockburn, as may be inferred from his nose, is a distinguished admiral of the red. Those who are in the least intimate with ancient history, must occasionally have been not a little amused with the origin of most of the sirnames of the distinguished personages of Grecian and Roman, as well as of the early European history. Passing over Pericles, the Ptolomies, and the host of Pharaohs, I will merely mention the kings of France and England. There was Philip the fair, Lewis the gross, and Charles the fat, of France; Edward the confessor, Edmund Ironside, and Edward Longshanks, of England, besides a thousand others. It would be no unamusing speculation, to inquire what sirnames would suit some of the present notable race of monarchs, provided they were bestowed with a due regard to their distinguishing qualities of mind and body, or their peculiar habits and tastes—or lastly, their peculiar situations. Alexander might be called the Accoucheurer, or Deliverer—Napoleon, in addition to his sirname of Great, might have that of Sinner appended—Frederick might probably be called Lackland; Jerome, the Bigamist—Don Carlos, the Fiddler—Gustavus, the Double, because, as Joe Miller says, be is a man beside himself —and honest King George is fully entitled to the sirname of Well meaning. The rest, though they are such an obscure set of rogues, that I really dont recollect their names, yet doubtless have sufficient character to entitle them to a nickname at least. Having mentioned nicknames, it may not be amiss to observe that they probably had their origin in the waggery of mischievous boys; and because they were not sanctioned by any of the usual ceremonies of the church, were called Nick-names, in honour of Old-Nick, who was supposed to stand godfather on these occasions. Which burnt the glass at such a rate, It almost sing'd his whisker'd pate; Pores o'er the map with curious eyes, And soon the staring proof espies. Sir Beresford, though half asleep As usual, come and took a peep; And all agreed, was nought so clear, As that French influence triumph'd here. VI. Then thus Sir Bolus—“Who will dare “The dangerous glory, and repair, “To these vile towns, and wrap in flame, “Their being, nay, their very name? “Who dares, upon our knightly word, “His majesty shall make a lord.” Sir Beresford was capering round, With lightsome step and airy bound, Whistling an Irish jig the while, With many a self approving smile, His much admired leg to greet, In silken hose, “neat and complete,” He heard not, or seem'd not to hear, But whistled still, “Brave Brian's Bier.” VII. But keen Childe Cockburn, good at need, A stouter, never stole a steed, Or bullock with a single blow, Sent bellowing to the shades below; With noble spirit, valour stirr'd, Started up, and took the word. “O merrily I to the battle will hie, “And merrily, merrily burn; “And many a day, shall not pass away, “Till Sir Cockburn in triumph return. “Ere long will I gaze on the bright burning blaze, “Of this rascally town of the French; “And feast on the fright, of the scampering wight, “And the terror of half naked wench. “O swiftly can speed, my vessel at need, “And sweet blows the south wind so mild— “Gramercy! Sir Knight, I ne'er felt such delight, “Since I robb'd a hen-roost when a child. “And safer by none, can thy errand be done, “Than Noble Knight by me; “I love to hear, the shrill cry of fear, “And the bright burning cottage to see VIII. Childe Cockburn's hand Sir Bolus took. And like a knight of mettle shook; Well pleas'd to think what vast renown, Would spring from burning this French town And that his glory soon unfurl'd, Should light the shores of this New World And blaze like bale fire, near and far, The Phœnix of the Border war. I have made an allusion to the phœnix, in order to introduce a little bit of secret history, which puts an end to all the race, past, present, and to come. I beg pardon of the poets, who like this bird better than any other, except perhaps a roasted turkey, for thus depriving them of one great source of their similies; but as my object is, if possible, to knock on the head all the thread-bare classical supersititions, I cannot let the phœnix live another hour, on any account. According to the Abbe Mariti, who travelled into the Holy Land, the palm-tree is by way of eminence called, over all the east, the phœnix, because of its numerous uses, insomuch, that Palestine could hardly be inhabited without it. When the palm-tree grows old, it is cut down, and the stump burnt to ashes; from which ashes springs a young palm-tree; in other words, a young phœnix. Thus ends the history of that rare bird the phœnix, which though not admitted in the catalogue of ornithology, has made a great noise in the world, and given its name to a variety of institutions, such as the Phœnix Fire Office, the Phœnix Insurance Company, and others, who ought immediately to change the phœnix for the palm-tree. O then he call'd for generous wine To treat the gallant Knight, For well Sir Bolus did opine, He'd drink as well as fight The music too in merry peal, Struck up at his command, The Irish jig, the Scottish reel, Was danc'd on light fantastic heel, The three knights hand in hand At last Sir Bolus gave the order, To play “Blue Jackets o'er the Border;” A merry lilt, which at the time, When chivalry was in its prime, Stern Border chiefs would oft inspire, To dance round cottage, wrapt in fire, With howlings, as when Indian yell Is heard at midnight hour to swell, Sad herald of those damned rites, Which Indian chiefs, and modern knights, Pay to the god of their desire, The god of plunder, rape, and fire. IX. And now around the ample board, With Yankey plunder often stor'd, In silence for their dinner wait The stalwart knights in sober state; And soon the tarry scullions came, With many a dish well known to fame, Roast beef, (though not of merry England) At top of table took its stand; Beef, which Sir Beresford had won, In battle brave at Lewistown. The knight called out lustily for roast beef, at Lewistown; but to use a homely phrase, “got his belly full” of something else, and was fain to go eastward, where the pious puritans, who go beyond the scriptures in “loving their enemies” better than their friends, probably supplied him plentifully. Potatoes next were seen to smoke, Which Irish appetites provoke; To please Childe Cockburn's Scottish taste, The board with caten cakes was grac'd; Haggis, salt herring, and whate'er, Scotch palate tickles, too was there. X. But when their stomach's ran aground, The sparkling goblet pass'd around, For stout Sir Bolus, good at need, Was fam'd for making bottles bleed. He like Sir Quixote oft mistook; And pipes of wine for wind-pipes took, The which with keen pot-valour true, At backstroke he would slice in two; And while the blood-red liquor ran, Would swear 'twas blood of stout foemen. XI. Me lists not at this tide declare, What drinking feats these knights did dare, And how in fight of mantling bowl, Sir Bolus, as the representative of the English in this poem, is of course a great lover of good eating, and a huge wine-bibber. It would seem, by a reference to their popular songs, and even to their grave writers, that the only criterion by which to estimate the relative claims of nations to superiority, is the quality of their beef. A Frenchman who eats frogs and soup—a German who eats sour-krout—a Spaniard who eats onions and garlic—a Scotsman who eats oatmeal—and an Irishman who lives upon buttermilk and potatoes, are consequently not to be put on a level, in any respect, with the Englishman, whose beef is so excellent, as to have obtained the honour of knighthood. The Egyptians worshipped an ox; and such is the veneration of Englishmen for his flesh, that the famous song of “O the roast Beef of Old England,” has been known to quiet a mob at the theatre, when even “God save the King,” and “Rule Britannia, have entirely failed. An honest Mussulman, who kept a journal of a few weeks residence in England, noted down in his book, “that the English were certainly the descendants of the Egyptians, for they worshipped a piece of an ox, and sung hymns to a pot of porter.” It is by no means my intention to ridicule our sister country, for this truly aldermanly propensity, to boast of her good eating, and look down with contempt upon her poor neighbours, who are contentedly enjoying their humble fare. Neither will I express any surprise at the zeal with which Englishmen contest the point of superiority in such truly important articles, as mutton chops, small beer, and cheese. I am aware that the wisest people, are in general, the most impatient of rivalship in trifles; and that even the Goddess of Wisdom herself, changed Arachne into a spider, for disputing with her the superior management of the needle. This anxiety about such insignificant matters, proceeds therefore, probably, from the superiority of Englishmen in real wisdom and refinement, and the zeal with which they maintain the honour of their favourite, Sir Loin, (who is even more popular than Sir Francis Burdett) is a convincing proof of their being the most enlightened people in the world. This consideration may put a stop to those stupid expressions of wonder, which foolish people sometimes utter, that a nation, which can boast of an Alfred, a Shakesspeare, a Newton, a Wolfe, and a Nelson, should thus stoop to the paltry ambition of pluming itself on its beef, its beer, its cutlets, mutton chops, and cheese. Thus condescending, as it were, like the monarch in Goldsmith, who after reciting his titles of “lord of the sun, moon and stars,” “sole governor of the universe,” added that of “mighty monarch of the brass handled sword.” They sent full many a Yankey soul, Yankey is a term of contempt applied to the people of the United States, by the English naval officers, who usually call the captain of an American merchantman, “a Yankey son of a b?h.” It is now a term adopted by the American sailors, who will soon make it respectable if they go on as they have begun. A Yankey trick is applied exclusively to that finesse and keenness, which it is said distinguish the people of New-England, in bargaining and other matters. The first Yankey trick on record, is one related in the history of New-England, written by two reverend gentleman, the Rev. Jedediah Morse, and the Rev. Elijah Parish. Soon after the arrival of the first settlers, some Indians were employed by them, to drag a cannon by a long rope. While engaged in this business, some person, whose modesty would not permit him to claim the honour of the achievement, put a match to the touch-hole, and destroyed nearly every soul of them. The Indians called this a Yankey trick, and it was a long time before they forgave the joke. To wander in the shades of death, And scare their ghostships out of breath, With tales of mighty Border feats, Perform'd by gallant British fleets. Suffice that evening clos'd around, And our wet knights still quaffing found; Nor till night's dim and shadowy hand, The veil had drawn o'er sea and land, And shut the windows of the skies, Did this our great triumvirate rise, And when they rose in sooth be't said, They rose to reel to birth or bed. Ceas'd the high strain.—The lady smil'd Her grateful thanks, for time beguil'd, In sooth, by such a witching strain, She well might list it o'er again. Yet much she ponder'd in her mind, How one so weak, so old, and blind, Could touch the strings with such true art, As won the listening hearer's heart. She wot not of the sacred spark, That cheer'd him on his way so dark, That in his aged bosom burn'd, And all his hours to sunshine turn'd. Much too she marvell'd he should roam, In the wide world without a home, Whose art could minister so sweet, And mem'ry of her poisons cheat, And win the heart to peace and rest, When hope expires on sorrow's breast. “Was none to cheer his sightless hours, “To foster his sweet minstrel powers? “No son, no daughter, no dear friend, “To sooth, to succour, to defend; “To bury him when he should die, “And o'er his green grave sadly sigh? “Was none to guide his lonely way, “Through endless night, but little Tray!” The old man's spirit seem'd to roam, A moment to some long lost home, And on his dark cheek, once it seem'd, A tear of glistening sorrow gleam'd. Sadly he hung his snowy head, And sadly sigh'd, yet nothing said. Then, as to cheat, the hour of grief, Thus the sad minstrel sought relief, And try'd by magic of his art, To sooth the aching of his heart CANTO III. THE PROGRESS. [I.] 'Twas one bright morn in merry May, When all the fields were green and gay; When in the covert of the grove, Blithe songsters sit, and sing of love; When roses bloom, or ought to bloom, And all the air is one perfume; When on the damsel's ruddy cheek A thousand speaking blushes break; Whern tadpoles wriggle in the mud, Whence learned Colles of the blood. The rapid circulation shows, As all the world already knows— 'Twas then, as ancient legends say, Childe Cockburn stout, got under way II. The south wind blew a gentle gale, That swell'd the bosom of the sail; And swift the sister vessels glide, Impatient o'er the weltering tide, Till now the entrance of the bay, Before their eyes wide open lay. They saw the noble brothers twain, Twin giants, guardians of the main, Henry and Charles, renown'd I wot, For something which I have forgot; York-Town that made the Childe turn pale, [Mr. Scott had under the head of York Town, given a long account of the siege of that place, the surrender of Cornwallis, and the subsequent acknowledgement of our independence. He then entered into an enquiry whether this separation was not more advantageous to Great Britain than to the colonies, and whether the latter would not have been much more prosperous and happy, if they had remained as they were. Conceiving this enquiry rather uninteresting to American readers, the editor has thought proper to omit it entirely. Editor.] And brought to mind the glorious tale, Of stout Cornwallis, forc'd to yield, Before our country's sword and shield. III. The Rappahanock soon they saw, And then Potomack's yawning maw; So wide it seem'd, in sooth to say, 'Twould swallow up the mighty bay. With merry shout and thundering rout, They pass'd the bluff of Point Look-out, Saw the pale shrine of St. Jerome, The circumstance of a place on the shores of the Chesapeake, being called after St. Jerome, is not a little singular, and suggest a variety of interesting reflections. We learn from the legend of that eloquent saint, who was called the honey comb of doctors, “that he was a great traveller, and went about in divers distant countries preaching the gospel.” That he visited the shores of the Chesapeake, and abode there sometime is natural to suppose, from his giving name to that place; and his having preached the gospel there, is further corroborated by the extraordinary piety and strict habits of Religion, which I am told are observed among the people of that quarter. Where time long past, he found a home. Cox's rude cliff now near was seen, And Cedar point all smiling green; And Herring bay and Parker's isle, Where nature wears her sweetest smile, And fairies, as I was once told, Their nightly revels love to hold; Fairies are extremely scarce in America, though there is no inconsiderable number of witches, particularly in that part of the United States, aptly called New England, from its having, like Old England, a mighty propensity to boast of its superior “moral and religious habits.” The only authentic account of the appearance or agency of a fairy which I have been able to procure from that country, was communicated to me by a very learned physician of one of the middle states. That gentleman writes me, on this interesting subject, as follows. “Last summer as I was searching for flints, near the shores of the Musconaconck river, which runs at the foot of Schooley's mountain, a range stretching in a southwesterly direction through the state of New Jersey, and composed of alternate stratum of lime stone and granite, I was somewhat startled by the appearance of a little old woman, of very outré and singular appearance. She was crossing the river, mounted on the back of a tortoise. Her head was covered with a large bubble of azure colour; her spectacles were of the purest water, which by her art she had made to answer the purposes of glass; she had a coat of mail, made of the skin of a gold fish: her shield was a beautiful muscle shell; and her buskins were of sturgeon's nose, which bring incomparably elastic, must have exceedingly assisted her in walking, when inclined to that healthful, and too much neglected exercise. “The appearance of her face was not a little outlandish, exhibiting a variety of incongruities, of the first order. Her hair was almost white, apparently with age, though her face was that of a beautiful girl of sixteen, except that her eyes were of a flint colour, and her teeth of the finest red coral. She guided the tortoise across the rippling wave, with graceful management; the little animal all the while singing most melodiously in praise of fairy land. “As she reached the shore where I was standing, she dismounted from the tortoise, who making an elegant bow, slid back into the wave and disappeared, warbling the most delicious strains. “Approaching this extraordinary lady, with all the deference due to her apparent rank, I enquired if she could direct me where I might find some flints. “Flints!” exclaimed she—in a great rage—“I'll flint you with a vengeance!” and thereupon, her eyes which I then discovered were of real flint-stone, struck out actual sparks of fire, exceedingly bright and luminous. Know, ignorant and presumptuous mortal,” continued she “that my name is Agathe Pyromaque, and that I am the guardian of this haunted stream, and yonder woody mountain, inhabited by millions of flinty hearted beings, who never forgive any rash mortal, who violates their sacred recesses. Prepare then to suffer the penalty of thy intrusion, which is to be turned into a flint, and inhabit a tinder-box for one hundred and eleven millions of moons, having for thy companion nothing but an old piece of steel, which whilom, figured as a learned professor, and with whom you may dispute and strike fire as much as you please.” “So saying, she approached me, waving her wand, that looked like a little ivory ram rod, and already I felt the approaches of this terrible transformation. My teeth began to knock against each other, and at every blow, the sparks of fire came out of my mouth and nose, as if they had been actual chimneys, while my nails gradually assumed the appearance and consistency of gun-flints. At this awful moment I recollected that I had in my pocket a preparation for accomplishing an analysis of flint, by a most expeditious dissolution of its parts, and immediately sprinkled some of it over this diabolical damsel, who in less than five minutes, separated into her constituent parts, chalk and limestone, and disappeared. “Immediately the whole space of ether was animated with millions of flints, meeting in the air with horrible rattling, as if a hundred thousand triggers had been drawn at the same instant, and nothing could be seen but innumerable sparks of fire, flashing and hissing about in a most extraordinary manner. This tremendous uproar was heightened by the general discharge of all the guns in the neighbourhood, that were furnished with flints from this mountain, which went off simultaneously of themselves, doing infinite damage, but killing no one, as no enchantment whatever has power over the life of man. When this uproar ceased, the air became calm and still, and again I beheld the serene sky, bending down upon the mountain top, upon which the last rays of the setting sun were playfully sporting, and saw the pure stream silently winding its way, like a serpent through the green grass, and reflecting in its transparent bosom, one of the loveliest scenes of nature.” And oft by wandering wight are seen. Tripping along the dewy green. IV. Steady the vessels held their way, Coasting along the spacious bay, By Hooper's strait, Micomico, Nantikoke, Chickacomico, Dam-quarter, Chum, and Hiwassee. Cobequid, Shubamaccadie, Piankatank, and Pamunkey. Ompomponoosock, Memphragog. Conegocheague, and Ombashog, Youghiogany, and Choctaw, Aquakanonck, Abacooche; Amoonoosuck, Apoquemy, Amuskeag, and Cahokie, Cattabunk, Calibogie, Chabaquiddick, and Chebucto, Chihohokie, and Chickago, Currituck, Cummashawo, Chickamoggaw, Cussewago, Canonwalohole, Karatunck, Lastly great Kathtippakamunck. The reader acquainted with the geography of this country, will perceive that Mr. Scott, in his zealous pursuit of high sounding and poetical names, has brought together on the shores of the Chesapeake, places many of them, at least three thousand miles distant. The editor however being determined to give the poem just as he found it, has scrupulously retained these names, which are certainly highly sonorous, and only to be parallelled by a catalogue of Russian generals, or Indias chiefs. V. At length they came where gazing eye, A scene of beauty well mote spy. Far distant up a winding bay, Annapolis before them lay. Its ancient towers so stately rose, And wore an air of calm repose; And though the hand of slow decay, Had stol'n its ancient pomp away; And sometimes in the dead of night, The listening ear of wakeful wight, Might hear old time, relentless crone! Heave from its base some mould'ring stone, That trembled on the ruin'd wall, Ready at every touch to fall, Yet, still a noble sir it wore; As if in distant days of yore, Far better times it well had known, Though now decay'd and aged grown. VI. Here deep in dozing counsel sate, The master spirits of the state, Talking in solemn grave debate, How turnpike roads are cheapest made; Or what discreet and trusty blade, Is fit to Congress to be sent, Their wisdom great to represent. Gramercy! how their honours star'd When stout Childe Cockburn's fleet appear'd! The learned clerk began to stammer; Down fell the speaker's wooden hammer; And every wight, by terror aw'd, In boxing phrase gan look abroad, To see where best his legs might speed, To some safe place, in case of need; “Adjourn! adjourn!” cried every one, And so in sooth they did, hem-con.— VII. The sons of Tammany so stout, I am told there is a curious society in the United States, instituted in honour of the Aborigines of that country, the patron of which is St. Tammany, who though I have found no traces of him in the early history of that country, may for aught I know to the contrary, be as redoubtable a champion, as any one of the seven of Christendom; always excepting honest little St. Andrew. Be this as it may, this society has, by a sort of retrograde movement in the path of civilization, adopted not only an Indian tutelary saint, but many of the emblems, customs, names, and manners of their Indian neighbours, who are at present signalizing their gratitude on the borders of Canada. The sons of Tammany, as they affectionately denominate themselves, have probably of late become not a little sick of their patron Saint, and his whole race, and it is to be hoped will never again insult their wounded country, by the exhibition of such barbarous mummery, or degrade themselves by affecting either the dress, decorations, or manners, of such detestable monsters, who though, to the shame of every honest Briton, associated with the sole remaining “bulwark of our faith,” are only distinguishable from the tyger, by their form. With bows and arrows straight turn'd out, And valorously twang'd away, At neighbouring Church, where sooth to say, In sacerdotal pomp repos'd, A mitre, which those wights suppos'd, Was diadem, or Kingly crown, Therefore resolv'd to have it down. VIII. The sons of Erin's Isle so green, With stout Shillelahs too were seen. Waiting to taste the coming fight, And cry'd “By Jasus,” with delight But finding that the hostile fleet, Did not intend the town to greet And loth to have their pains for nought, Set too, and with each other fought; Till broken head, and bloody nose, And pelting shower of stalwart blows, Had cool'd their valour's furnace heat; A parley then the heroes beat, And pleas'd with this right pleasant fray, Contented homeward took their way. IX. Childe Cockburn wonder'd in his mind, Where he this vile French town might find; And well I ween, did well believe, Affrighted it had ta'en French leave, And in a panic run away, Like true militia in a fray. Yet on the stately vessels plow'd, Through curling wave, that ruddy glow'd, With sunset's sweet and mellow beam, That shed a mild, and gentle gleam, Of golden lustre o'er the tide, That softly murmur'd far and wide. X. And now they came in gallant pride, Where Susquehannah's noble tide, The Susquehanna on whose south bank, and near whose mouth, the little town of Havre de Grace was situated, is a noble river. It rises in the State of New-York, where indeed, it will appear by an inspection of the map, many of the principal rivers of the United States find their source. This is the case of the Delaware; and if at any time the people of New-York should become jealous of the prosperity of Philadelphia, they have only to go to the head of that river, which is there a mere brook, and by giving it another direction, deprive that city of its water, and convert it at once into an inland place. I know not whether the citizens of Philadelphia are aware of the practicability of this plan, but at all events I advise them to treat the people of New-York with great attention and respect when they come there, and conciliate them as much as possible. In silent pomp is seen to pay, Its tribute to the lordly bay. And on its beauteous margin spied, The little town in rural pride, Reposing in the folded arms Of peace, nor dreaming of those harms, Which fortune in her fitful spite, Decreed should come that fatal night. XI. The sun low in the west did wane, And cross the level of the plain; The shadow of each tree the while, Seem'd lengthen'd into many a mile; The purple hue of evening fell, Upon the low sequester'd dell; And scarce a lingering sunbeam play'd, Around the distant mountains head. The sweet south wind sunk to a calm, The dews of evening fell like balm; The night-hawk soaring in the sky, Told that the twilight shades were nigh; This bird was generally supposed to be the whip-per-will, until the ingenious Mr. Wilson, the excellent and indefatigable ornithologist of America, demonstrated the contrary. It is an evening bird, and is seen about sun-set and twilight in the country; sometimes solitary, but very frequently in great numbers. When alone, you may see it gradually rising in the air until almost out of sight, and then descending with prodigious velocity until very near the surface of the earth. When at the end of this rapid descent, it expands its wings to shoot again into the sky, it makes a rushing noise, which may be heard in the stillness of a summer evening at a great distance. The bat began his dusky flight, The whip-per-will, our bird of night, Ever unseen, yet ever near, His shrill note warbled in the ear; The whip-per will, like the owl, in America is connected with many tales of superstition; it is a rare poetical bird, and with the exception of the phœnix and the nightingale, neither of which are known in that quarter of the world, will stand the poets of that country more in stead than any other bird whatever. Independently of the ominous forebodings of speedy mortality, which his appearance under, or near a window, is sure to create, there is a lone and desolate obscurity in its character, that recommends it wonderfully to the imagination. In the summer twilight he is heard at intervals, and almost always singly, whistling his solitary notes, changing his position now and then, and often startling the peasant, as he is going home alone through the woods. It is very difficult to get sight of him, as he is rarely visible until the dusk of the evening; and his flight is so sudden and so swift, as to elude the attention, thus suddenly excited by the rustling of his wings. It is said that the appearance of his flight has something peculiar, resembling what is called “flitting;” a motion, which from time immemorial, has been appropriated to ghostly shadows. It is related among the transformations of the heathen mythology, that Pandion, king of Athens, was changed into a whoop-o-e, at the same time that one of his daughters was metamorphosed into a nightingale. The whip-per-will, whose name is derived from the sound of his cry, is probably the same as the hoop-o-e; the latter of which names approaches in reality, much nearer the sounds uttered by this bird, than the former. This suggestion receives additional force, from the circumstance of the nightingale, and the whip-per-will, being both night birds, and both fond of solitude; which traits of coincidence, would seem to indicate their former intimate relationship. The buzzing beetle forth did hie, With busy hum and heedless eye; The little watchman of the night, The fire-fly, trimm'd his lamp so bright, This little insect is another treasure to the American poet, who living as it were in a new world, has a better opportunity of introducing new imagery, than those of the worn-out and exhausted countries of the other three quarters of the globe, which are drained to the very dregs. If instead of glow-worms and nightingales, who are as common as farthing candles and fiddlers, he will now and then give us a little of real American scenery and imagery, the advantage of novelty will at least be obtained. In all countries there are objects, or at least combinations of objects, peculiar to itself; and it should be the business of the poet to catch these peculiarities of feature, which constitute the individuality of a country, without slavishly treading in the steps of others of different nations. I myself have seen the glow-worm foisted into an American night-piece, and heard the nightingale piping at the same time, though well aware that the glow-worm is so rare as never to constitute any accustomed feature of an evening landscape, and the nightingale not known at all in that country, except in the barren fancy of some servile imitator, who believes that because the English poets sing of that interesting bird, he must set her piping in the American forest. And took his merry airy round, Along the meadows fragrant bound, Where blossom'd clover bath'd in dew. In sweet luxuriance blushing grew XII. O nature! goddess ever dear, What a fair scene of peace was here! What pleasant sports, what calm delights, What happy days, what blameless nights, Might in such gentle haunts be spent, In the soft lap of bland content! But vain it is, that bounteous heav'n, To wretched man this earth has given; Vain, that its smiling face displays, Such beauties to his reckless gaze, While this same rash malignant worm, Raises the whirlwind and the storm, Pollutes her bosom with hot blood, Tarns to rank poison all her good, And plays before his maker's eyes, The serpent of this paradise. The fiddle stop'd; and sudden rose The music of the minstrel's nose. Though hush'd the song, the son'rous sound, Amaz'd the nodding audience round: Now it seems far, and now a-near, Now meets, and now eludes the ear; Now seems like couch-shell echoing wide, Along some misty mountain's side; Now like the low and solemn knell, Of village church, in distant dell; Now the sad requiem loads the gale, And seems like tithe-pig's smother'd wall, As pent in bag, to pay the tolls, Of parish priest—for saving souls. Seems now a groan, and now a squeak, Now through bass, and now shrill shriek As when some methodistic crew, Meet in their midnight gospel stew, Babble blasphemous nonsense there, And with loud rant, some dotard scare: Till tumbling breathless to the ground, The pious mountebanks flock round; Breathe bitter moans—muffle, and then, Through vocal nose, cry out “Amen!” After his nap—they mov'd him tell, How he who fiddle play'd so well, Could fall asleep mid such sweet tones, And vex their ears, with these strange moans? But ere the minstrel could reply, A shout in distant room rose high, And made the noble lady start, While beat Lord Joline's stalwart heart; Though ne'er in midnight raid of yore, That stalwart heart had beat before. Rous'd all the train, and pour'd amain, To see what caus'd this ranting strain; And soon they came, where sooth to say, Was ne'er such sight of gallants gay. Around the table's verge was spread, Full many a wine bewildered head Of student, learn'd from Nassau-Hall, Who broken from scholastic thrall, Had set him down to drink outright, Through all the livelong merry night, And sing as loud as he could bawl; Such is the custom of Nassau-Hall. Students in all ages, have been noted for their love of frolicking and mischief. In Spain it has passed into a proverb; and to say that a man is “as mischievous as a collegian or a monkey,” conveys an idea of a superlative pickle. It has been supposed that this propensity might be traced to the strict rules of scholastic discipline that exist in colleges, under the restraints of which, the student being rather uneasy, will make himself ample amends, by plunging into all the excesses of liberty, whenever he is indulged with a temporary relaxation. For my part, I cannot but attribute it to his becoming early familiar with the classic writers, particularly the poets, whose drinking odes, and animated descriptions of convivial parties, are enough to fire the imagination of youth with an irresistible desire of carousing it lustily. One of Horace's wet odes, or more especially one of Anacreon's, is a greater provocative to drinking than a salt herring, and it is little to be wondered at, if by the frequent perusal of these inflammatory productions, the unfortunate youths become notable frequenters of taverns. As mischief is generally a concomitant of drinking, that too is to be traced to the same “Pierian Spring.” That such is the true source of these remarkable habits of collegians, is pretty clearly demonstrated by this, that as soon as they leave College, and forget their Greek and Latin, which they do for the most part in a year or two, they become sober personages, and are no longer distinguishable from the rest of their fellow creatures by their frolicsome and mischievous propensities. The true way to remedy this crying evil would be to make a good fire in the College yards, and then institute an enquiry, similar to that held by the Curate and Barber over Don Quixote's library. Or perhaps it would be still more effectual to have all these combustible books, together with the whole scandalous chronicle of ancient classical mythology, burnt by the hands of the common hangman. The odes of Horace and Anacreon, would be well replaced by the minstrelsy of the Border; the haunts of the nymphs, the fauns, and the dryades, might be very respectably occupied by the goblins, the witches, and water-wraithes; and if a mythology is absolutely necessary, Mr. Southey has introduced us to one much more novel, stupendous, and incomprehensible, than even that of Scandinavia. No Latin now, or Heathen Greek, The senior's double tongue can speak; Juniors, from fam'd Pierian fount, Had drank so deep, they scarce could count The candles on the reeling table; While emulous Freshmen hardly able, To drink—their stomachs were so full, Hiccup'd—and took another pull. Right glad to see their merry host, Who never wine or wassal crost, They will'd him join the merry throng, And grace their revels with a song. That stalwart lord, a royster wight, That never flinch'd by day or by night, Obedient to the guests high law, Clear'd his hoarse throat, with a hem and a haw, And with a most alarming twang, His merry descant loudly sang. Lord Joline's Song. Professors are always a preaching and bawling, And drinking good liquor, sheer beastliness calling. They say that the head-ache and tavern bills float, In each glass of good stingo, that flows down the throat— Yet whoop boys! a fig for your musty professors, They all are no better than father confessors. Professors, they call it the D?l to taste, The ripe swelling lip of a bar-maid so chaste; They say that such wenches are cunning and sly, And lure you young lads with a glance of the eye Yet whoop boys! kiss all of them over and over, Till they redden like fields of our fresh ruddy clover. Professors they preach and palaver, my boys, And prate of stiff larning, and cramp all your joys; They're paid for it too, then why should they not, It helps them to tipple and toss off the pot. Then whoop Suthron lads! sweet Margery—caress her! Drink deep—laugh and sing, and d?n the professor. A knocking heard the door without, Stay'd in mid roar the merry rout; A Freshman stagger'd to the door, And shouted, loud as he could roar, “Joy! joy! the travelling fiddler's come, “His merry eat-gut strings to strum; “And many lads and lasses too, “A buxom, witching, merry crew; “As love's true gramary ever knew, “From country round are come, they say, “To dance the livelong night away.” Flew ope the door—and in there came, Full many a dancing loving dame, With chintz short gown, and apron check'd. And bead with long-ear'd lawn cap deck'd And high heel'd shoe, and buckles shene, And bosom prank'd with box-wood green With these well pair'd, came many a lad, With health and youthful spirits glad: To caper nimbly in Scotch reel, With toes turn'd in, and outward heel. CANTO IV. THE DIGRESSION I. 'Twas midnight now, and all around, Nature lay stretch'd in sleep profound; No sound was heard the door without, But all within was thundering rout. The minstrel chose a merry lay, And straight the lads and lasses gay Footed right deftly, round and round, With eager glee, and lightsome bound. One Shuffled “double-trouble” o'er, As if he'd grind quite through the floor; This is a favourite step, and considered the test of good dancing among the farmers' sons and daughters. It was undoubtedly introduced into America by the natives of Africa, in their first involuntary emigrations; and as one of the few customs borrowed from that unlucky quarter of the world, is entitled to particular notice. Dancing appears to be an amusement equally common to the savage and civilized state, and the wild Indian of the north-west coast of America, the ignorant negro of Whidah, the barbarous native of Madagascar, as well as the refined Parisian, are equally fond of this universal amusement. Even the Cozack, and the bear, are capable of imbibing a strong predilection for it. The dancing step, called “double trouble,” from its being twice as much trouble to dance it, as to dance any other, bears not the least resemblance to any of the ancient dances that have been described by learned men, nor to any of those of Europe; being altogether unique in itself, and possessing a character entirely distinct from all others. It consists in moving both feet without lifting them from the floor, in such a manner as to keep time to the music, and requires not only great dexterity of foot, but a very correct ear. It may be classed under the general head of shuffling, and is in fact the perfection of that difficult style of dancing, which is undoubtedly of African origin. The great distinction between the African and European modes of dancing, seems to be this, that the one strives to keep himself on the ground, and the other off of it. Thus the Mandingo, or Congo beau prides himself on his shuffling, and the French dancing-master, and his pupils, upon maintaining a sort of medium between heaven and earth, like some of those wandering ghosts, whose peculiar fate it was neither to belong to the world above, or the world below; and which were assuredly the shades of dancing-masters, if any such existed in those simple days. ‘Hoe-corn and dig potatoes’ too Was danc'd so to the music true. It seem'd an echo to the strain, Or the same tune play'd o'er again. II. Stout lord Joline with all his heart, In these gay gambols took a part; The family of Joline, anciently Josselin, or Joccelin, is of great antiquity, as we learn from the edifying chronicles of the crusades, where one Josselin of Montmorenci, distinguished himself on a variety of occasions, but particularly by killing a “beestely gigaunt” as we learn from the following curious fragment. Josselyne ynne Holye Londe belyke, Smote downe one Heathen heretike, Who thynken hur ryghte wel to daunte, Hur beynge a synnefulle, beestely gigaunt. From this confounding of the genders, it is difficult to decide whether, Josselyne and the gigaunt were male or female, unless we solve the difficulty by supposing the poet to have been a Welshman, which is probably the fact, as many of the Welch bards accompanied king Richard to the Holy Land. There is a curious distich quoted in the notes of Dr. Clarke's travels in Palestine, which is probably about the same date with that just recited, and which shews that the poets of those days had some other criterion of distinction betwixt man and woman, than the mere gender. “At port Jaff begnne wee “And so froth from gre to gre, “At port Jaff there is a place, “Where Peter rais'd through goddes grace, “From dedde to lif to Tabitane; “He was a woman, that was her name. If this poet was not a true Milesian, I am mistaken. For well I wot a merrier heart, Ne'er in such gambols bore a part. Though rather short, and round, and thick, None better play'd his cudgel stick; And none in merry gibe and jeer, Could ever make such pleasant cheer— The trav'ller never pass'd his gate, Forsooth, without a broken pate, Not from his stick, but sturdy joke, That many a stranger's head had broke. III. Brawny and low, with bushy head, And shoulders erst for Atlas made, One double-jointed arm was slung In kerchief, and all lifeless hung; And round about his either eye, A circling halo you might spy; Such as the moon's pale face deform, Prophetic of the coming storm. These he had got from crusty folks, Who did'nt like his lordship's jokes IV. Lord Joline, for his partner chose, A lass that bloom'd like blushing rose Fam'd in the dance for tiring swains, And call'd the rose of Scottish plains The Scottish, or as they are generally denominated, the Scotch Plains, are situated in the State of New-Jersey, in the neighbourhood of Pompton Plains, of which more will be said. From the name, it was probably settled by a colony of Scots, at a very early period, perhaps anterior to the discovery of America by Columbus; who probably gained some obscure hints of this matter, from the pedlars, who travelled through Europe, and was thus led to his great undertaking. If this hypothesis should be genuine, as there are strong reasons to believe, the honour of the first discovery and colonization of America, belongs neither to Americus Vespuccius, Christopher Columbus, Sebastian Cabot, nor Prince Madoc, but to some other obscure adventurer, who by an unaccountable negligence in history, has been thus cruelly defrauded of immortality. It may not be amiss to observe, that the custom here alluded to of “tiring swains,” is well known among the Lassies of Scotland; and this coincidence furnishes another proof of a common origin. The flower of Jersey was the maid, As babbling tell-tale rumour said What though the heavy hand of toll, And summer sun's tremendous broll, Her shoulders somewhat broad had made, And giv'n her cheek a copper shade; Though no Verbecq had taught her grace, To measur'd mood had train'd her pace— (Verbecq now gone to death's dark shades, He was a celebrated dancing master from Paris, who taught little babies to dance and look like women, but died of chagrin, because he could not jump up and cross his legs six times, before he touched the floor. To caper with light ghostly blades,) A foot more broad, a step more true, Mov'd not among the merry crew. V. Though bred afar from town and court, And train'd to toil, and rural sport, Yet instinct taught her all the arts Of city belles, to win the hearts Of village swains, who clean face shew, At Sabbath church, or gay review. Notwithstanding all that has been written about gentlemen peasants and shepherds, from the time of Theocritus to Allan Ramsay, I do most verily believe, that they have been, are, and always will be, from the very nature of their situation and employments, a set of indifferent fellows, who are ignorant without being simple, and whose ideas of love are limited pretty much to the ordinary conceptions of their near neighbours, the sheep and cattle. I can safely say, I never saw one with a clean face, except at a church or a review; and how a man without that indispensable requisite, can be an object of affection to any woman, except one who has a smutted face herself, I can form no conception. Pastoral poetry will probably never be very popular, except among the class of people thus caricatured, who of course, will be mightily tickled with it, and strut about in their borrowed plumage, like the daw in the peacock's feathers, or more appropriately, the ass in the lion's skin. If I were to look for homely honesty, or for sober matter-of-fact virtues, among any class of people, I would go to the labourers of the field, and the tenders of sheep and cattle; but he who expects to find among these classes the refinements of sensibility, or the purity of love, may look for soft hands and clean faces too. Plato maintains that there were two Cupids, one of whom was a god, and the other a dæmon; by which he clearly meant to distinguish between that polished and refined affection, which is the boast of cultivated minds, and that animal passion, which is, in general, the only bond of union among the low, the ignorant, and the corrupted. She had a smile for merry grigs, A sigh for sentimental sprigs, Song psalms to those that pious were, And songs to blithe and debonair: Is short she knew each wishing art, To wind about the simple heart— A farmer's daughter scorn'd the maid; And so she was, as fame betray'd. VI. At last the merry reel was done, And ceas'd the dancers every one; But ere their parting seats they took, The wight his quavering elbow shook, And in a freak of wanton glee, His fiddle squeak'd right merrily. The custom of occasionally “squeaking the fiddle” as it is called, is common at country wakes and dances, all over America; and the lass, who on this occasion, refuses the salute of her partner, is held to be sophisticated, by an intercourse with proud conceited people. The law in this case, is as strict as in cases of forfeit, where it is well known the damsel is obliged to fulfil certain conditions, before she can recover her pledge. It is pleasing to see the customs of our forefathers thus growing up in a far distant country, and pervading a new world. Perhaps the time will come, when America will be the sole depository of these endearing modes of early youth, when the aged countries of Europe will again relapse into second childhood, as in the dark ages, which succeeded the destruction of the western empire. Nations, like individuals, have their progress from infancy to maturity, from maturity to age, and, as inevitably, feel the effects of time, as the individuals themselves. The eastern world receives the first rays of the rising sun, but his last light beams in the west; and thus probably will it be with the sun of science. The time may come, when America, though the youngest sister, will, like Joseph, receive the obeisance of her elders, and behold them paying homage to her sheaf of wheat. Each dancer, as the custom is, Gave his fair mate's smacking kiss, Then led her to her wonted place, With genuine country bumpkin grace— All save Joline, who sad to say, Upon the floor all doleful lay. VII. Close in a darksome corner sat, A scowling wight with old wool hat, That dangled o'er his sun-burnt brow, And many a gaping rent did show; His beard in grim luxuriance grew; His great toe peep'd from either shoe; His brawny elbow shown all bare; All matted was his carrot hair, And in his sad face you might see, The withering look of poverty. He seem'd all desolate of heart, And in the revels took no part. Yet those who watch'd his blood-shot eye, As the light dancers flitted by, Might jealousy and dark despair, And love detect, all mingled there. VIII. He never turn'd his eye away, From one fair damsel passing gay; But ever in her airy round, Watch'd her quick step, and lightsome bound; Whereever in the dance she turn'd, He turn'd his eye, and that eye burn'd With such fierce spleen, that sooth to say, It made the gaser turn away, Who was the damsel passing fair, That caus'd his eye-balls thus to glare? It was the blooming Jersey maid, That our poor wight's tough heart betray'd. IX. By Pompton stream, that silent flows, Where many a wild flower heedless blows, Unmark'd by any human eye, Unpluck'd by any passer by, Pompton is a beautiful little pastoral stream, which after winding lazily through the plain of that name, joins the Passaic, at a place called the Three Bridges. The character of this river and its adjacent scenery is such as I have described; soft, silent, and gentle. The water hardly moves; on its banks are vast numbers of stately elms, whose extensive shade, allures the herds and flocks, and whose spreading branches shelter an infinite number of birds, whose song is the delight of the solitary rambler. The red-winged blackbird, the thrush, and the clover loving boblincon, whose notes may vie with the boasted songsters of Europe—and above all the mock-bird, the variety of whose minstrelsy imitates the melody of the whole forest. All these, sport undisturbed through the livelong summer day, in the rich meadows that skirt the stream; whose edges, at short intervals, are fringed with a rich border of dwarf willows, the little tendrils whereof touch the surface of the water. Enamoured of this still landscape, so favourable for meditation and sleep, the ancient Hollanders at a very early period settled on these plains; where their descendants still flourish in easy competency, and grow in wealth as well as numbers. Whenever a son marries, an additional door is knocked into the house, which is commonly of one story, but makes up in length what it wants in height; and thus an additional house is made off hand. Some of these long buildings are thus divided into several tenements, and not unfrequently, three or four generations will be found flourishing under the same roof. As they all dress invariably alike, it is often difficult to tell the relation in which they stand to each other, for they appear nearly of the same age, and very often the old grand-father will be found vying with his grand-son, in the labours of the field. There is a sort of homely, yet comfortable simplicity in the lives of these people, which when soberly contemplated is somewhat touching to the imagination, as well as gratifying to the feelings. It is so peaceful, so smooth, so unagitated so like their own little river. In short, it exhibits so many of the features of that little nestling place which every man in his prospective fancy creates to himself, as the refuge of his declining years. Perhaps after all, one of the most genuine pictures of sober happiness which it falls to the lot of man to contemplate, is that of one of these old patriarchs, sitting at the door of a comfortable house, and smoking his long pipe on a summer's evening. It has been objected to me, that I have, in my former productions, dwelt too long and too minutely on names and places, that have no title to the attention of any body but a provincial antiquarian; and that I have in this manner frivolously wasted the time of my readers who might have been better employed. In short, that my works resemble a road-book, where every little paltry town, blacksmith's shop, and tavern is laid down, and minutely particularized for the gratification of the curious traveller. In consequence of these cavils, and as a poor author must sometimes pull off his hat to the critic, the reader will perceive that I have turned my back upon several towns that occur in the part of the minstrel, many of which are ennobled. by tradition. This is most particularly the case with the ancient city of Brunswick in New Jersey, where several centuries ago Michael Scot studied necromancy under Mother Shoulders. Tradition says, that long before he “clove Eildon Hill” with a few sharp words, he had signalized his power by sneezing down the steeple of the old Episcopal church at Brunswick, out of pure spite; he being an obstinate sectarian, and a great enemy of orthodoxy. There stands a church, whose whiten'd side Is by the traveller often spied Glittering among the branches fair. Of locust trees, that flourish there Along the margin of the tide, That to the eye just seems to glide. And to the list'ning ear ne'er throws A murmur to disturb repose, The stately elm, majestic towers, The lord of Pompton's fairy bowers The willow, that its branches waves. O'er neighbourhood of rustic graves, Oft when the summer south wind blows Its thirsty tendrils, playful throws Into the river rambling there, The cooling influence to share, Of the pure stream, that bears impress Sweet nature's image in its breast. X. Sometimes on sunny sabbath day, Our ragged wight would wend his way. To this fair church, and lounge about. With many an idle sunburnt lout, And stumble o'er the silent graves; Or where the weeping willow waves, His listless length would lay him down, And spell the legend on the stone 'Twas here as ancient matrons say, His eye first caught the damsel gay, Tradition, if it did not originate with, at least, owes its chief support to, the class of females here alluded to. If they did not give birth to it, they are its chief nurses. As all history must originate in oral tradition, it follows that the ancient matrons are the grand-mothers at least of historical narration, and that though Herodotus may be called the father of history, they have an equal title to the honour of its birth. In every town or village you will find a little knot of these industrious and curious antiquarians, pilfering from that same wallet, in which, as Shakespeare affirms, old time “putteth things for oblivion” a thousand precious little scraps of secret history, and a thousand invaluable memorials, which like a silver spoon in dish-water would be thrown away unless preserved by their pious care. Anon comes the antiquary, who gleans all these detached particles of gold-dust, by sifting old nurses, ancient matrons, and curious grey headed maids, and maketh a book highly interesting, and valuable. In it, is set forth with admirable particularity, all that has happened in the town or village for several generations: who erected the church steeple, who put up the weather cock, who built the old stone-house opposite, who was mayor in such a year, and whose tomb it is, the inscription of which is entirely obliterated. Thus are the ancient matrons, the true chronicles of the times, and sorry as well as surprised am I, when I consider the base ingratitude of antiquarians and historians, who have thus maliciously, as well as wickedly, suppressed all mention of the sources from whence they, in all ages, have derived their most precious information. Who in the interval between The services, oft tript the green, In America, where the congregations are often dispersed over a large space of country, it is customary to preach two sermons, with a very short intermission, in order that the people may return home in time to their dinner. The interval between these “services,” as they are called, is devoted to rambling about the church-yard, reading epitaphs; or parading about the door, where are displayed all the new bonnets, and finery of the parish. Human nature is the same every where in respect to vanity, except that those who often get new bonnets, are not half so vain of them, as those who get them but seldom. The finest lady, dressed in all the gorgeous drapery of wealth, and fashion, and sparkling in jewels, displays not half the self-complacency exhibited by a rural damsel, appearing for the first time at church, in a new gown, or bonnet. And threw her witching eyes about, To great dismay of bumpkin stout, Who felt his heart rebellious beat, Whene'er those eyes he chanc'd to meet XI. As our poor wight all listless lay, Dozing the vacant hours away, Or watching with his half shut eye, The buzzing flight of bee or fly, The beauteous damsel pass'd along, Humming a stave of sacred song. She threw her soft blue eyes askance, And gave the booby such a glance, That quick his eyes wide open flew, And his wide mouth flew open too He gaz'd with wonder and surprise, At the mild lustre of her eyes, Her cherry lips, her dimpled cheek, Where Cupids play'd at hide and seek, Whence, many an arrow well, I wot, Against the wight's tough heart was shot. XII. He follow'd her where'er she stray'd, While every look his love betray'd; And when her milking she would ply, Sooth'd her pleas'd ear with Rhino Die; It has been hitherto supposed, that the people of America, like the birds of that country, are not naturally musical, because travellers have, I am told, drawn their conclusions, from what they observed in cities or along the public roads, without penetrating beyond the mere outside shell of the country. The real habits of any country, are not to be gathered in the streets or by the road side; but in lonely and remote situations, where the traveller never comes, and where with the exception of a wandering pedlar, a stranger is seldom seen. It is at the fire side of the farmer, where the ancient manners and customs, the natural tastes of a people make their last stand; and it is there and in his fields that I am assured, morning, noon, and evening, you may hear old ballads often sung by the workmen and maids, with whom it is altogether common and customary. With regard to the ballad of Rhino Die, I have been able to procure but two lines of it, which are the concluding ones of every verse, occupying the place of a sort of chorus. There is a simplicity in them which seems to indicate considerable antiquity. “My name is Rhino Die, “All on the mountains high” This ballad is probably of American origin, as neither Mr. Ritson, Mr. Ellis, nor my friend Jacobus Porcus, have given any account of it. All I can gather from my correspondent, who like most other Americans, is barbarously indifferent to genuine minstrelsy, is, that it is twelve cows in length. That is, according to the ancient system of measuring ballads; which was by the number of cows milked by the maid, while she was singing them. Formerly the Hollanders measured time by the pipe, as the learned Diedrich Knickerbocker affirms in his history; and at present the natives of the East, have a custom, somewhat analogous, of measuring distances by time. Or made the mountain echoes ring, With the great feats of John Paulding; A famous border chief, principal of the three who captured major Andre, the particular friend of my late friend Miss Seward. There is extant a fragment of a ballad, which only wants age, to make it exceedingly curious and interesting. It relates to that celebrated event. “Then up steps John Paulding, “And unto him did cry, “And if we draw our glittering swords, “One of us two must die.” CHORUS. Now here's a health to Jóhn Paulding, And let his health go round, And here's a health to Washington, And let his health go round. Nothing can afford a stronger proof of the high estimation in which this celebrated borderer is held in America, than his being thus put first in the chorus, than which circumstance, scarce any thing could more strongly indicate, that he was considered a greater man than even General Washington. How he, stout moss-trooper bold, Refus'd the proffer'd glittering gold, And to the gallant youth did cry, “One of us two must quickly die!” XIII. On the rough meadow of his cheek, The scythe he luid full twice a week, Foster'd the honours of his head, That wide as scrub-oak branches spread, With grape-vine juice, and bear's grease too, And dangled it in eel-skin queue. In short, he tried each gentle art To anchor fast her floating heart; But still she scorn'd his tender tale, And saw unmov'd his cheek grow pale, Flouted his suit with scorn so cold, And gave him oft the bag to hold. It is the custom in the country, thirty or forty miles from the cities, when the young men go sparkling as it is called, to judge of their reception by certain ceremonies which are well understood. If soon after his arrival, the damsel rises and takes a candle unto another room, it is understood as an acceptance of his devoirs, for that evening at least. If on the contrary, she remains in the room with her parents, he is said, I know not for what special reason, “to get the bag to hold.” XIV. Still would he linger where she stray'd, Still gaze upon the cruel maid, And watch her every look and smile, And pine with jealous pangs the while, Whene'er a losel wight essay'd, To tamper with his darling maid. But where's the keen poetic tongue, Can tell what pangs his bosom wrung, When Lord Joline first took her out, To dance with him the merry bout? With close shut teeth and speechless ire, And heart consum'd in smother'd fire, He saw delight dance in her eyes, He saw her mounting colour rise. But when he heard the fiddle squeak, And saw Lord Joline kiss her cheek, His peace he could no longer hold, Love and despair had made him bold. XV. Doubles his fist—his eye-balls flame, As near the fated spot he came, Where our gay lord, with dalliance sweet, The gentle damsel soft did greet. Not England's champion, matchless Crib, Who broke black Molyneux's rib; Not Milo, when the bull he slew, As story goes, and ate him too; Not stout lord Douglas, when at court, He spoil'd the great Fitz-James's sport, And for his Lufra gave a thump, That laid Sir Groom a lifeless lump— Not one of these e'er lent a blow, Like that which laid his lordship low. Flat on the floor his curl-pate lies, His light foot to the ceiling flies. XVI. As on the bank of some lone stream, Lit by the moonlight's quivering beam, The fairies in their gambols light, Are scar'd by some bewilder'd wight, The little caitiffs flit away, And leave undone their roundelay; Their faithful watchman of the night, The Fire-fly, shrouds his lamp so bright, The merry rout no more is seen, And silent is the dewy green: So all affrighted at his fall, The tripping dancers one and all, Pour'd through the portal of the door, And ne'er were seen at Princeton more. Save our poor wight, who all this while, The ladye held in durance vile. XVII. The ladye retir'd when his lordship fell, Within her bower to weave a spell; Nor over her husband's bloodless bier, Strew'd one fair flower, or dropp'd one tear. Vengeance deep brooding o'er the blow, Had lock'd the source of softer woe. And burning pride and high disdain, Forbade the rising tear to flow; Until smid the kitchen train, Her son lisp'd from his nurse's knee, “And if I live to be a man, “That caitiff blow reveng'd shall be. O! then the ladye heav'd a sigh, And flow'd her tears no one knew why. XVIII. Of noble race the ladye came, Her mother was a witch of fame, Of Shoulders' line in New-Jersey: This Mother Shoulders was celebrated in ancient times as a fortune-teller or witch, which indeed are synonymous terms. Ancient matrons, who remember to have heard their grand-mothers speak of her, say that she could certainly tell what had past, which is all that is necessary to get credit for what is to come. By her art she discovered where many silver spoons where hidden, which she had probably stolen herself; and divers young ladies to whom she had promised husbands, actually got married not many years afterwards. By the fulfilment of these wonderful predictions, she at last gained such a reputation for witchcraft, that not an orthodox inhabitant of Gotham, but nailed a horse-shoe at his door, and took other precautions to evade her influence. She lived as was affirmed by many to the age of two hundred and seventy odd years, and would probably have lived much longer, had she not incautiously ventured into Connecticut, where the witch-finders immediately detected her, because she made no shadow, and had rings round her eyes; both indubitable signs of witchcraft. She was burnt; and a bystander affirmed he saw the devil fly out of her mouth in the shape of a Quaker: the Quakers being at that time considered as little better than monsters. Men said she chang'd her maiden name, By feats of wondrous witchery. When lord Joline to woo her came, In lordly trappings fine; She chang'd for him her virgin name, From Shoulders to Joline. Dame Shoulders' skill, as bards have sung, Was taught the lady fair, And she could ride, when very young, On broomstick through the air. And well I wot, sage Michael Scott, Whose voice clove Eildon Hill, Though dead and gone, alive had not, A voice so loud and shrill. For when in angry mood she spoke, Gramercy! it appears, Like screech owl on the night it broke, And split his lordship's ears! XIX. And now she sits in secret bower, Weaving a spell of wondrous power. It has been objected to me, that in my attention to the lady and her spell, I have forgotten to inform the reader, whether Lord Joline was killed by the blow or not. The truth is, I left the matter in this kind of doubt, being aware, that uncertainty is one species of the sublime; and moreover, that the poet, by sometimes leaving the imagination of the reader to operate, often gives rise to a much better picture than his own fancy would have produced. Behind the dingy wooden door Was character'd full many a score, Of wicked potions, dealt about, To many an unsuspecting lout, Who straight the dire debauch would feel, And like a man possessed reel. A book of witching gramary, Before her open you might see, Where written down was many a spell, Of power to do—what none can tell. Whatever name is written there, Of dreadful evils should beware; For on the cunning ladye wait, In haughty pride of legal state, Magicians grim, with wand in hand, To do the ladye's stern command; And if the caitiff cannot pay The score of fate, him while away, And lodge in doleful donjon keep There all life long, to wail and weep. XX. The caitiff's name the lady view'd, And under it recorded stood, Mysterious words of dire import, And shapes of cabalistic sort. Here his sad destiny was shown, That he should weep and pine alone; Till he the dread account should pay, And clear his ancient score away. Well pleas'd she saw him in her power, And darting from her secret bower, Bad her familiar seize the wight, And lodge him safe that very night, Where he his deed might long bewail,— The safe-keep of the county jail. XXI. The dread enchanter's hand was laid, Upon the caitiff's shoulder blade; And as if struck by palsying age, Or wand of necromantic sage, That arm which late his lordship fell'd, And many a stalwart wight had quell'd, In mortal fight of fisticuff, And often made them cry, enough! Sunk down before the wizard spell; Wither'd his strength, his courage fell, And powerless he was borne away, Where though I wot, I dare not say; For none the dreadful word may speak, Even though in Hebrew, Erse or Greek. All this good time the minstrel slept, Nor watch nor wakeful vigil kept; And not until the roystering day, Had scar'd old squeamish night away, And birds their matins sweet began, Awoke the much enduring man. Gleeful he snuff'd the morning air, That drives away, the sprites of care, And makes the jocund spirits dance, Like capering wight of merry France. But soon he rais'd his sightless eye, And thought with many a bitter sigh. He could not see the buxom sun, His daily race of glory run; Nor, though he felt its kindling ray, Through his fast ebbing life-blood play, Ever enjoy its glorious light, Amid his never changing night. Seem'd the sad thought to break his heart. And seem'd his spirits to depart, As slowly drawing forth his how, In plaintive numbers, sad and low, The aged, worn, and houseless man. His doleful descant thus began. CANTO V. THE BURNING. I. The morn returns—but well-a-way! Comes not for me the welcome day. No blush of spring's fair vernal bloom, No summer rose in rich perfume, No flocks that in the meadows play, Nor lowing herds that devious stray, Nor sparkling centinel of night, Shall ever greet my waken'd sight. But dark my ever during way, Shut from the golden light of day; I know nor sun, nor star, nor moon, Nor midnight from the blaze of noon. The captive in his dungeon dark, Preserves of hope a brilliant spark, Which like some mild benignant star, Beckons the trembler from afar, To happy scenes of dear delight, To sunshine, liberty, and light. But I, no such fair vision see, The torch of hope burns not for me; In a dark world, aye doom'd to roam, Without a friend, a hope, a home. But why complain? in yonder skies, A sure and certain refuge lies. There, when my dark, dark course is run, I shall behold a glorious sun; A world ethereal, fair and bright, And forms of uncreated light; Spirits that glide through earth and sky, Unseen by any mortal eye; And never more in darkness roam, Without a friend, a hope, a home. II. Gather'd the shades of gloomy night, And hid the world from human sight, The chilly dews of midnight fell, When goblins weave the witching spell, When plundering caitiffs prowl around, And print with noiseless step the ground, And nothing wakes but guilt or woe, Or studious wight with thoughtful brow. Or drunkard nodding o'er the bowl, Or rascal wolf on midnight prowl. III. Childe Cockburn saw with grim delight, The gloom of that dark pitchy night. It minded him of olden time, When in his early manhood's prime, In border raid, he sallied out, And put the sleeping fold to rout, Or rous'd some unsuspecting wight, With slogan yell, or blazing light, Which, as its circling volumes play, Gives him good heed to run away. IV. Now swift around his order flew, To muster all the valiant crew, Who, save the centinels, that slow, Pac'd o'er the deckward to and fro, Were fast asleep in birth below. Rous'd every soul and rubb'd his eyes, In hope to see a gallant prize; Some noble coaster of the bay, Laden with oysters or new hay. Childe Cockburn with an out-strech'd hand, Deliver'd thus his high command. V. “Ye British tars! who man to man, “Beat the stout Yankies when you can, “Who o'er the ocean, far and wide, “In power imperial fearless ride, “And uncontroll'd, from neutrals steal “Their sailors for the general weal! Were it not that the false pretences of monarchs produce such melancholy effects, their hypocrisy would be altogether ridiculous. The king of England, according to his minister's account, is most disinterestedly fighting to preserve Europe from the yoke of Bonaparte by land; and the little French emperor, no less disinterested than his brother king, is fighting to preserve the world from the domination of England by sea. Between them both, a good portion of the whole world, by land and by sea, is kept in a state, to which, plague, pestilence and famine are modes of comparative happiness. There is somewhere, or at any rate, there ought to be, a fable to the following effect. The porcupine was once seized with an unaccountable fit of universal benevolence, so that he never could see any of the weaker sort of animals, but he must either carry them on his back, or cover them with his body, to keep them from harm. The consequence was, the poor little devils got so pricked and worried by the quills of their troublesome protector, that many of them, in a short time, had not a drop of blood left, and others were reduced to skin and bone. Upon this, the wretched survivors came to him in a body, and with great humility requested, that in future, when his majesty saw them in any difficulty, he would graciously suffer them to get out of it as well as they could, without his interference. VI. “O listen, listen, bullies say, “Of hardy feats of arms I tell, “And when you've listen'd, speed away, “Yon little Gallick town to quell. “Moor, moor the barge! ye gallant crew, “Moor, moor the barge! again I say, “Methinks I scent the morning dew, “And not a moment must we stay. “The stars begin to twinkle now, “The tints of morning streak the sky, “The vapour on yon mountain's brow, “Forebodes that tell-tale morn is nigh. “Up, and away! my lads with speed, “Swing battle blade, toss burning brand, “For lo! the fire-king has decreed, “Yon town must blaze beneath our hand VII. In silence now they go on board, The gallant barge with rockets stor'd, The muffled oars are still as death, And every sailor holds his breath. Childe Cockburn carried in his hand, A rocket, and a burning brand, And waving o'er his august head, The red-cross standard proudly spread, Whence hung by silken tassel air, A bloody scalp of human hair, Emblem of that pure Christian band, Which binds the savage, hand in hand With the “great bulwark of our faith”— As Caleb Strong devoutly saith. It was officially communicated to the American government, by Commodore Chauncey, commandant of the lakes, (who, by-the-bye, has called one of his vessels “The Lady of the Lake,”) that the mace of the Speaker of the parliament of Upper Canada, was surmounted by a scalp; which was taken down at the capture of York, and forwarded to the commander in chief. I rejoice, and so will his pious excellency Governor Strong, to find by this, that such an intimate and brotherly union subsists between our country and the savage, on whom the example of Englishmen cannot fail of having a most beneficial effect. The humane General Procter, will, doubtless, take every pains to have them properly instructed in the principles of the Christian religion, so that by the time the war is over, they will probably, under the guidance of the great prophet Tecumseh, be marvellously improved in humanity and politeness. VIII. The blinking morn began to peep From eastern skies, down on the deep, And cast a grey uncertain light, On the dark bosom of the night, Just as the gallant barges bore Childe Cockburn's powers bump on the shore. The Stalwart knight with furious heat, Jump'd on the strand, stiff on two feet, And eager as the royal beast, Who on hot carnage loves to least, Dauntless directed his swift way, To where some twelve militia lay, Safe as a thief behind a wall, Attending to their country's call The militia of America have, by the public accounts, distinguished themselves on various occacasions during the present war, but most especially by running away. Heretofore it was a popular theory with those who wrote against standing armies, that a militia was the best bulwark in case of an invasion. It was erroneously supposed that men would defend their property, their wives and children, and their “sacred homes,” with spirit, firmness, and vigour, whenever they were attacked. But experience has destroyed this, among many other popular and plausible theories; and it is now demonstrated, that the experiment is dangerous and destructive. It is found, even in America, where the mass of the people have more to defend than in any other country, that the militia, with the exception of those perhaps of Virginia, labour under a most extraordinary disinclination to defend even their own property; and, like the honest carter who, instead of helping himself, called upon Hercules, do nothing but clamour for the assistance of the general government, and grumble because it does not send a body of troops to every exposed point, on a frontier of more than fifteen hundred miles. Nay, such is the singular species of patriotism prevailing in America, that a distinguished member of Congress, did seriously utter the most extravagant praises of the people of Connecticut, because some of the militia turned out when they were ordered, to defend their own fire-sides! IX. The centinel, who half asleep From veiled lids, would take a peep, Saw eager Cockburn thundering on. And 'gan I wot to quake anon. In tribulation bawl'd he out For help, to his companions stout, Who bravely to his rescue came, And taking most delib'rate aim, At four miles distance, with shut eye, At Cockburn and his crew let fly. I've heard a true eye-witness say, Twelve canvas backs at morning play, By that discharge all found their grave, And with their broad bills bit the wave. It has been shrewdly suggested, that the real object of Sir Cockburn's expedition was to procure some of these ducks for Sir Bolus, who is remarkably fond of them. I think however the account of the minstrel is much more natural, for it is hardly to be supposed that Sir Bolus, however fond he might be of these celebrated ducks, would fit out a fleet on purpose to capture them. X. But true it is, that some stray shot, Sent one of Cockburn's men to pot; And our brave lads who wisely thought, A victory so dearly bought, Would give more cause of woe than weal. To those who only came to steal, Agreed to quit the bloody fray; So donn'd their arms and ran away, To tell with self-approving glee, Their wondrous feats of chivalry. XI. By this time all the town was rous'd, And not a living soul was hous'd; The foeman rais'd the yelling shout, The Congreve rockets whizz'd about, The fiery missives dreadful gleam'd, The half awaken'd women scream'd, Feebly the frighten'd infant cried, And uproar lorded far and wide. Was none to quell the foeman's heat, And stop the tide of wild defeat? None to arrest the caitiff band, Or quench the wrathful burning brand? XII. O'Neale from sea-girt Erin's isle, Where bulls are made that make us smile, Leland says, that before the invasion of Earl Strongbow, the rank of King of Ireland was disputed by the O'Conners, and the family of the Northern Hi-Niall, as it undoubtedly ought to be spelled. Of this family was the famous Brian Boirhoime, or Boromy, King of Munster, and King Twaddle, of whom I can discover nothing, except that he was a great friend of Tom Thumb. From Brian descended the well known John O'Neal, and Hugh, Earl of Tirowlow, or Teyrone, as it was afterwards written, who disputed so manfully the usurpation of Queen Elizabeth, but at length fell victims to her policy, and were executed, at least the latter; the former having died before. The descendants of these princes as is usual with the children of great families that fall into misfortune, having no respectable calling dwindled into great insignificance, and became in a generation or two common peasantry. Such are the vicissitudes of life! And those who live an hundred years hence, may in all probability, see many of the descendents of the present race of upstart potentates, following some respectable handicraft trade, and getting an honest livelihood, without picking people's pockets, or robbing on the highway. With high imperial lineage grac'd, Back his illustrious fathers trac'd To great O'Neale, who like king Log, Erst reign'd o'er many a fen and bog, In Munster or in Leinster fair, Or somewhere else, I know not where. Such was his birth, as saith dame fame, And from Milesian blood he came; That blood which in hot current flows, Unmix'd through all the race of O's— O'Rourke, O'Connor and O'Dwyer, And the round O's of Counaughtshire— That blood which flow'd in freedom's cause, For equal rights and equal laws, And boils whene'er its country's wrong Is sung in melancholy song. XIII. O'Neale from hard oppression's hand, A refuge sought in this fair land; This nestling corner of the earth, Where every plant of foreign birth, Blossoms in rich luxuriance rare, But seldom roots its fibres there. The philosopher in speculating on the curious figure exhibited by America, for the last ten or fifteen years, will be struck with the prodigious foreign influence of one kind or another which exists in that country; more especially in the places that border on the Atlantic Ocean. I have been told that a vast proportion of the people of the cities, whence public opinion generally emanates, are natives of other countries, who flock there, not from any disgust to their native land, but because they afford an easier opportunity to acquire a fortune. These people, as is natural and proper they should, ever retain a rooted affection for the scene of their youthful attachments, and the theatre of their earliest pleasures. Far be it from me to blame one of the most exalted affections of the heart, the affection for the land of our birth; I am merely stating circumstances which will in some measure explain the reason, why America, which possesses so many claims to the attachment of its citizens, contains more disaffected persons than any other country in existence, with the same number of inhabitants. I mean, not merely disaffected to any particular administration, but to the soil, to the nation itself, when ever its interests, come in competition with those of their native country. It is this which paralizes the proceedings of the government; for no sooner is there a disposition displayed, to resent any injury or insult of a foreign nation, than it is checked and repressed, or at least embarrassed, by the clamorous interference of a herd of interested foreigners, who swarm in their cities, and who being the principal supporters of newspapers, have always influence sufficient to direct the effusions of a patriotic editor into what channel they please. Men certainly ought never to forget the country that gave them birth; but they should recollect the fable of the lamb and its foster mother, and that the soil in which they thrive, and whence they draw their daily being and existence, is at least entitled to their gratitude, if not to their devotion. But it has been represented to me by intelligent Americans, that many of these people abuse the protection which is given them, by an impertinent interference in those political concerns, which are peculiarly the business of the citizen; by clamours against the government, and by degrading comparisons betwixt the country which they left, because it did not hold out a prospect of competency, and the one, upon which they have bestowed the honour of their adoption. Another charge brought against foreigners is, that they too often become citizens from mere motives of personal interest; thus sacrilegiously violating the most sacred of human obligations; and resembling the paltry and self-interested fortune-hunter, who proffers his hand to one mistress, while his heart is devoted to another. While this state of society exists, there will never be seen in that country, the noble spectacle sometimes exhibited by other nations—that of one strong sentiment actuating and impelling and uniting the people, in one great irresistible impulse—a vital feeling running through, pervading, animating the whole mass, and quivering at the touch. The national energy will be wasted in the energy of civil dimensions; its spirit dissipated in domestic broils; and its resentment neutralized by the collision of conflicting interests and passions. Here flock the growth of every clime. The victims of this iron time, As to a land of calm delight, Where every honest living wight, Can taste the bliss of plenteous glee, And go his ways in liberty. XIV. Here comes in search of glittering pelf, Full many an avaricious elf, Condemn'd through tolling world to roam, Without a country or a home, Save that in which his stinted mind, The loadstone of his heart can find. No early recollection charms, No sacred love of country warms, But ossified to its core, The bloodless, nerveless heart no more, Beats with one languid throb to see, The land of its nativity. In search of this accursed meed, He's now a Pole, a Dane, a Swede, A Portugueze, a renegade, A traitor—any thing for trade. XV. Of all the stranger wights who share, Our freedom and our native air; Who here a welcome haven find, From the rude storm they left behind; The storm which sweeps old Europe's coast, Like that which quelled Pharaoh's host; Who glitter in our western sphere, In the bright good they gather here— How few one grateful impulse feel, One wish for our kind country's weal! How many, like the fabled snake, The bond of benefits dare break, And vivified in the gleam Of fortune's bright and warming beam, Turn to the breast, where long they fed, That pillow'd long their outcast head, To blast it with their poisonous breath, And sting the quivering heart to death! XVI. Not so O'Neale, who in his heart, Warm took his foster-country's part, And try'd to rouse a losel wight, Who in his cabin lay that night. A tall, stout, rosy, lusty youth, Who canted much of gospel truth, And boasted of his “moral sense,” His “learning” and “intelligence;” One, as was learn'd from divers hints, Of Quincy's wise constituents, The following is the substance of a note of Mr. S. on this passage. Ed. The people of New England have so often been assured by their orators and select men, of the superiority of their religious and moral habits, their patriotism, and their intelligence, that it appears from many of the newspapers of that quarter, that they are perfectly satisfied of its truth. Like the lawyer in the play, they have so often repeated, “I am an honest man,” that they have not only convinced themselves, but persuaded a great many other people to believe it. The latter, with good natured credulity mistook every repetition of the same tale, for a proof of its authenticity, without considering that it was but the authority of men praising themselves. No one in America has hitherto it seems, thought it worth while to repress, the hitherto harmless vanity of these poor people; and the claim has been tacitly allowed, not because it was believed to be true, but because it was looked upon as the innocent delusion of credulous men, who having been cured of their belief in witches and other imaginary beings, had made themselves amends by indulging a new set of preposterous fancies. The silence hitherto preserved with respect to this diverting claim, is however no proof that any such superiority exists. Many things have been denied that were true; and many things that are false, remain uncontradicted. To escape being questioned is no demonstration of truth, and what remains for a long time undisputed, is not therefore indisputable. Nevertheless, such is the influence of assertions often repeated, that the weakness of human nature is seldom able to resist it. Experience every day demonstrates that if men hear continually the same thing, they confound the repetition with evidence, and mistake every reiteration for an additional proof of its truth. But after all the most general and universal delusion, is, that which men practise upon themselves. They weave their sophistries, till their own reason is entangled; and repeat their falsehoods till they are credited by themselves; by often contending, they grow sincere, and by long searching for proofs, come at last to believe they have found them. When arrived at this desperate stage of perverted reason, there remains scarce a hope of reasoning them from their delusion; but like the spider caught in the net woven by himself, they are destined to remain the monuments of their own self destruction. Without entering any farther into these deep speculations, I will conclude the subject with remarking, that I cannot help looking upon this locating, and taking as it were, such quiet possession of an unauthorised and unacknowledged pre-eminence, over their honest unassuming neighbours, as altogether analogous to other parts of the conduct of the people of New England to the sister States. Finding nobody in possession, they seem to have squatted down upon the public reputation, as they did upon the land, without enquiring particularly whether it belonged to them or not. Remaining a long time unmolested in their occupation, they grew at last to consider themselves the lawful possessors of the soil, and to talk of their farms, and their estates, as if they had actually held them by legal possession. [It cannot be sufficiently regretted that so many local prejudices, springing out of mere geographical distinctions, should have arisen in this country, to lay the foundation of national antipathies and national disunion. The pernicious distinctions of Eastern, Middle, and Southern States, seem to have laid the seeds of a precious harvest of ill blood, between the people of these sections, more especially since the claim made by the great representative of New England in the late Congress, to such a preeminence in “religion,” “moral sense” and “intelligence” over his neighbours. Such a claim, where it escapes ridicule and contempt, will excite emotions of jealousy and ill will, and lead perhaps to a lasting dislike. There is in human nature a principle which prompts us to repel any airs of superiority, that are considered ill founded, and men feel the same ill natured satisfaction in stripping away these borrowed feathers, that they do in unmasking the sly hypocrisy of a knave, or the blustering cowardice of a bully. Ed. Who think it wrong to raise their voice, Or any other way rejoice, When victory sits on our arms, And every patriot bosom warms. XVII. Of great Miles Standish's blood he came, And bore that mighty hero's name. This prodigious hero is called the Washington of the Plymouth Colony, in the history of New-England, written by two celebrated literary characters of America, the Rev. Jedediah Morse, and the Rev. Elijah Parish. “In 1636, at a very advanced age, died Capt. Standish, the military commander, the Washington of the Plymouth Colony. A man so conspicuous and celebrated in his life, ought not to be forgotten when dead.” His. New-Eng. p. 241. The following are the principal exploits of this “Washington of the Plymouth Colony.” “When Corbitant, one of the petty sachems of Massasoit, meditated a revolt, Capt. Standish, with fourteen men, surrounded his house in Swansea; but he being absent, they informed his people they should destroy them, if he persisted in his rebellion. This so alarmed the chief, that he entreated the mediation of Massassoit, and accordingly, was admitted, with eight others, to subscribe his submission to the English!” Id. p. 241. “Being on a trading voyage to Mutachiest, between Barnstable and Yarmouth, in February, 1623, a severe storm compelled him to leave his vessel, and sleep in a hut of the Indians. Being impressed with an idea of their design to kill him, he made his people keep guard all night, by which he escaped the snare they had laid for him.” Id. p. 241. “Often was the providence of God conspicuous in his preservation. The next month at Manomet, a creek in Sandwich, where he went for corn, he was not received with his usual cordiality. Two Indians from Massachusetts, were there; one had an iron dagger, and derided the Europeans, because he had seen them when dying, “cry and make sour faces like children.” An Indian of the place, who had formerly been his friend, appearing now very friendly, invited the captain to sleep with him, because the weather was cold. Standish accepted his hospitality, and passed the night by his fire; but sleep had departed from his eyes; he was restless and in motion all night, though his host seemed solicitous for his comfort, and “earnestly pressed him to take rest.” It was afterwards discovered that this Indian intended to kill him, if he had fallen asleep.” Id. Another time he was sent to a place, called Nessaquassel, on suspicion that the Indians were plotting against the white people. The following exploit is recorded of him, by the Rev. gentlemen, who so aptly call him the Washington of the colony. “Pecksuot being a man of great stature, said to Standish, “Though you are a great captain, yet you are but a little man; and though I be no sachem, yet I am a man of great strength and courage.” The captain had formed his plan, and was therefore silent. The next day seeing he could get no more of them together, Pecksuot, and Wittuwamat his brother, a young man of eighteen, and one Indian more being together, and having about as many of his own men in the room, he gave the word; the door was fast; he seized Pecksuot, snatched his knife from him, and killed him with it; the rest killed Wittuwamat, and the other Indians. The youth they took and hanged. Dreadful was the scene; incredible the number of wounds they bore, without any noise; catching at the weapons, and struggling till death.” p. 245. “In 1624, the people of Plymouth had erected fishing-stakes at Cape Ann. A company from the west of England, the next year took possession of them. Captain Standish was sent to obtain justice. His threats were serious; and the people of Cape Ann, assured the company they were dead, unless they satisfied the captain, for he was always punctual to his word. The company built another stage or stake in a more advantageous situation, which the Plymouth people accepted. Thus harmony was restored.” Id. p. 246. After all these exploits, which certainly justify the captain's claim to a comparison with the father of American liberty, we learn from this stupendous history, which reminds us not a little of the interesting and truly important “Memoirs of P. P. Clerk of the Parish,” that the captain's great sword was burned, and those who fancy they have it in their possession, are mistaken. “His name,” adds the writer, a great grandson of the captain's grandson Deacon Joseph Standish, “will long be venerated in New-England. He was one who chose to suffer affliction with the people of God; who subdued kingdoms, and put to flight the armies of the aliens.” Id. p. 249. With this, in pious union glow'd, Rare blood, that long time past had flow'd In wizard vein, as story tells, Of Georgy Burroughs hang'd at Wells, For conjuring up a wicked light, That mock'd a maid's keen searching sight. The following curious particulars, may be found in the History of New England; frequently alluded to in this work. Pages 309, 310, 311. “The public mind was shocked and alarmed, and the most decisive proceedings followed. For a time, all, or most of the people was of one mind. March 2d there was a public examination at the village, and several were committed to prison. March 21st the magistrates met in Salem, and Mr. Noyes opened with prayer. On the 24th they met at the village, and Mr. Hale prayed. On the 26th they met again in Salem, and kept the day in fasting and prayer.” Having thus duly prepared themselves they went to work. “There was another examination at Salem April 22d, and a number imprisoned. June 2d an old woman was tried and condemned at Salem, and executed on the 10th; making no confession. Five more were tried June 30, and executed July 19; six more were tried August 6th, and all executed the 19th, except one woman. One of these was Mr. George Burroughs, sometime minister at Wells; he also preached at the village, but met with great opposition. A great number of witnesses appeared at his trial: a specimen of their testimonies may be seen by the following deposition. “Elizur Keysar, aged about forty-five years, saith, that on Thursday last past, being the 5th of this instant month of May, I was at the house of Thomas Beadle in Salem, and Captain Daniel King being there also at the same time, and in the same room; said Captain Daniel King asked me, whether I would not go up and see Mr. Burroughs, and discourse with him; he being in one of the chambers of of the said house.” The witness did not go up at that time, but goes on to say; “The same afternoon I having occasion to be at said Beadle's house, in the chamber where Mr. Burroughs kept, I observed that the said Burroughs kept his eyes steadfastly fixed upon me. The same evening being at my own house, in a room without any light, I did see very strange things appear in the chimney, I suppose a dozen of them, which seemed to me to be something like jelly, that used to be in the water, and quivered with a strange motion, and then disappeared. Soon after which I did see a light up in the chimney about the bigness of my head, something above the bar, which quivered and shaked, and seemed to have motion upward; upon which I called the maid, and she looking up the chimney, saw the same; and my wife looking up could not see any thing. So I did and do conclude it was some diabolical operation!” On grounds like these, not only Mr. Burroughs, but hundreds of others were executed in different parts of New England. But the real ground on which Mr. Burroughs suffered, was probably, his intermeddling too much in political matters, for it seems that about this period, commenced that custom which has since so deeply stained the churches of New-England, and corrupted the Ministers of the Gospel there. I cannot sufficiently reprobate that canting spirit, which connects politics and religion inseparably with each other; nor refrain from bearing my testimony against those late attempts which have been made, not only in America, but Great Britain, to debase the pure spirit of christianity, by making it subservient to the views of interested ambition, or rancorous party spirit. Enough will be said on this subject if we merely revert to the days of the Barebones, and the canting Puritans of the Rump Parliament; to the example of those remorseless non-descripts, who half hypocrite and half devotee, united the practice of the most unrelenting persecution, with the theory of the mildest toleration; and who acting under the combined influence of fanaticism in religion, and enthusiasm in politics, equally outraged the divinity of the one, and the principles of the other. The perilous examples of the effects of this incestuous union, in stimulating party spirit into the most intolerant frenzy, are thick set in the pages of history, and float as buoys in an ocean of blood, to warn the interested politician against connecting any particular system of belief, with any particular party, or any particular modes of government, and above all, with any particular ruler. There is no being more dangerous to the repose of society, than a fanatical politician. He becomes the most choleric and revengeful animal; considers the deity as bound to assist him; that religion itself is wounded in his person; and that the bitterness of his intolerance originates in piety, and is sanctioned by Heaven. XVIII. With ardent zeal O'Neale essay'd, To stimulate this moral blade, And strike a spark of patriot ire, To light his paltry kitchen fire; But the asbestos of his soul, Nor brimstone match, nor burning coal, Lightning, nor Archimedes' rays, Could kindle into one poor blaze. “In sooth his country well he lov'd, “And if good Caleb Strong approv'd, “Or 'Siah Quiney thought it right— “Gramercy! then you'd see him fight.” No man if you would take his word, More readily would draw his sword, Or fight with more determin'd glee, In a just cause forsooth than he; But he must see occasion good, Before he shed one drop of blood “Nay more,” the whiffling caitiff cried, “Must have the law, fast on my side.” Sad recreant wight! contempt and scorn, Shall wring thy bosom all forlorn, If such a leaden heart can feel, What's sharper than the temper'd steel. XIX. Who would not fight with heart and hand, In any cause, for such a land, Ne'er may the dastard traitor know, The joys from sacred home that flow; Nor even for one moment prove, Man's dear respect, or woman's love; Ne'er may be taste the sober bliss, To live in such a spot as this; The poor man's long sought paradise, Where nature's choicest blessings rise, And plenty, with a lavish hand, Winnows her gifts o'er all the land; Where yellow harvests bounteous wave, Old Europe's starving sons to save; And where, in the wide world alone, “Sweet Harry's” gen'rous wish is known. One of the few kingly wishes on record, which deserve to be for ever honoured in our recollection, is that of Henry the fourth of France, whose favourite hope it was, that “He might live to see the day, when every peasant in his kingdom would have a fowl to put in his pot on Sunday.” This homely wish deserves to have, and indeed has, endeared the memory of that gallant and noble prince to the hearts of all, even those of the stoutest republicans. The only country in which this blessing is enjoyed in its fullest extent, is America, where the most common labourer can if he please, and without extravagance, have his fowl for dinner on Sabbath day. All impartial relaters agree in representing that country as holding out to the poor, and those with small means, a prospect, which could they but behold it, would quickly allure them from their native homes, which present, for the most part, a prospect of endless labour, and endless privation. The commonest day-labourer, without a trade, can earn six or seven dollars a-week; a sum that will afford him a dinner of fresh or salt meat, or both, every day, and enable him even to indulge in roast-beef; which though perhaps not so fine as that of “Old England,” has this special advantage, that it is much more accessible to the generality of the people. The Americans know and feel their superior national happiness; and if they took as much pains to circulate true accounts of their country, as disingenuous travellers have taken to disseminate false ones, nothing but the vast ocean would prevent the poor peasants of Europe from pouring themselves into the bosom of America. But the truth is, the writers of that country are divided into three classes, one of which claims the exclusive honours of patriotism, and is industriously employed in depreciating it; another in exalting it preposterously over the heads of other nations, without being able to give any reason for it; and a third, which knowing that the country has already quite enough of foreign leaven, to assist its rising, refrains from indirectly inviting foreigners, by setting forth its advantages; and is content merely occasionally, to refute unfounded aspersions and libellous sneers. Ne'er may the coward caitiff know, A country where such blessings flow; But pine in Afric's scorching sand, Or freeze on Lapland's ice-bound strand, Or crouch beneath a tyrant's throne, Nor dare to call his soul his own. Or live at home—to know far worse, The generous soul's most bitter curse— Live in his native clime abhorr'd, And dead, go down in black record, A slave, who would not lift his hand, To succour his own native land. XX. Valiant O'Neale amid the crowd, Cry'd out “by Jesus,” oft and loud; Mr. Scott here seems to insinuate that O'Neale distinguished himself only by making a great noise, and swearing lustily. Whether this injustice of the poet proceeds from some remains of the old grudge arising from the dispute about Ossian, or about the honour of peopling the two countries, the Editor cannot tell. This much is pretty certain, that he has not given due credit to O'Neale for his superior prowess. It has been clearly ascertained, that he killed two of the twelve canvas back duets, mentioned in the preceding poem; and it is, moreover, the general opinion in the neighbourhood of Havre de Grace, that he would have killed several of the British, had he not, by a very excusable blunder, shut both eyes instead of one, whenever he pulled the trigger. But finding that it would not do, To fright the plunder-loving crew, Retir'd behind a neighbouring wall, And swore as loud as he could bawl, Till Cockburn's men as legends say, Kidnap'd and carry'd him away. Thrice valiant wight! of mighty fame, And far as swearing goes—true game, I've heard, and I believe it true, A thousand heroes, just like you, Had put childe Cockburn's prowess down, And very likely, sav'd the town. XXI. But vain was all! the Rockets fly, Like stars athwart the summer sky, And soon a curling tide of smoke, From many a cottage blackening broke. Then might you see the bursting fire, Red'ning and spreading, higher, higher, Until its volume seem'd to rise, To the blue dome of yonder skies. Then might you hear the matron's shriek, The cry of infant, faint and weak, The crackling timber as it fell, And the brave Briton's Slogan yell, As prowling mid the tire he glides, Like spirit, that in flame resides, All mingling in one chorus drear, And smiting on the startled ear. XXII. The distant peasant hears the sound, And starting with elastick bound, Hies to the mountain's bright'ning head, And sees the fiery ruin spread; And marks the red and angry glare, Of water, sky, and earth, and air. Seem'd Susquehanna's wave on fire, And red with conflagration dire, The spreading bay's ensanguined flood, Seem'd stain'd with tint of human blood. O'er Cecil County, far and wide, Each tree, and rock, and stream was spied; And distant windows brightly gleam'd, As if the setting sun had beam'd. XXIII. The Elkton burgher rais'd his head. To see what made the sky so red: From Ararat the falcon sail'd, One great cause of the contemptuous opinion expressed by various of the learned of Europe, towards America, is her youth. An antiquary, or a theorist, despises a young country, as heartily as the Prince Regent does a young woman. They become enamoured of it, as the bucks of Vienna do of a lady, on account of her wrinkles: or as a collector does of a coin, for the precious rust it exhibits. There is in fact nothing in the world which a genuine scholar, so much detests, as a country exhibiting all the redundant freshness, and buxom hilarity of youth, health, and vigour, and having neither moss grown castle, ruined town, or desolate village in it. The antiquarian looks in vain, in such a place for objects worthy of his attention; and is induced to wish that some earthquake, or other convulsion of nature, would produce a premature ruin; or like the tragic lover, to pray that the gods would annihilate both space and time, and make him happy in the contemplation of the dear object of his affections. To him, the ruins of Palmyra or of Rome, the one swarming with banditti, the other with beggars, are a thousand times more gratifying than the spectacle of a country, rising out of the forest, breaking from the embraces of rude nature, and advancing with steps more rapid than the world has ever yet seen; or of cities, exhibiting all the careless gaiety of youth, all the varieties of business and pleasure, and all the splendour of wealth, acquired by the successful exertion of enlightened industry, and expended with tasteful liberality. In almost any other country now, but America, the name of Mount Ararat would be ominous of a dissertation. It's summit would be infested with an infinite number of learned men, who like ants about their sand-hill, would be running backwards and forwards, in search of a little crumb of conjecture, about the place where the ark rested, when the waters subsided after the deluge. In some parts of Asia, such a name would be invaluable; but here, alas! it is a mere worthless, every-day-mountain of vulgar strata, of no value, except to the plodding mineralogist; and its only claim to distinction is founded on the following tradition. A long time ago, when that part of the country was a desart, Lord Talbot, one of the ancient proprietors of Virginia, took refuge from the consequences of some crime, in this mountain. He inhabited a cave; and his only companions were two trained falcons, who contributed essentially to his amusement as well as his subsistence. After residing in this place several years, he quitted it, it is believed in consequence of a pardon, but his falcons remained; and it is said they are still sometimes seen soaring around the summit of the mountains. The owl at lonely distance wail'd, The gainst wolf far adown the dale. Loaded with loud lament the gale, As plaining that the morning's prime. Had come that day before its time. The wild deer started in the wood, And all on tiptoe listening stood, To hear the yell, so stern and drear, That smote upon his startled ear But when he saw the raging fire, Spring up the sky, and then retire, Now spread o'er ether, quick advance, And now o'er heav'n's blue concave dance With furious bound he hied away, And hid him from the light of day, Far in the distant forest green, Where fire, or man, was never seen. XXIV. The waning flame is waxing low, 'Tis all one smoking ruin now. The blacken'd walls, the charred pine, No more in blazing splendour shine; And the once animated scene, Is now, as if it ne'er had been. Where late the passing trav'ller view'd, A little nest of houses strew'd, Was nothing now, but mouldering wall, Already nodding to its fall; As it old time in wrathful spite, Had silent come that fatal night, And did, to shew his wondrous power, The work of years, in one sad hour. XXV. No more beheld the busy show, Of people passing to and fro, On business, or on pleasure bent, With smiling look of calm content; But here and there, there might be seen, The black, and ruin'd walls between, A ragged urchin prowling pass, To scratch among the smoking mass, And search with keen enquiring eye, Some precious relique to espy. XXVI. And many a houseless wretch was seen, Wending their way across the green, With slow and lingering step to view, The havoc made by lawless crew. Alas! where shall the wanderers roam, To find a refuge and a home? Will those who celebrate the feats. Of Russian boors, and British fleets, And universal patriots grown, Feast for all victories—but our own— [Mr. Scott is supposed here to allude to the following resolution, which was put by Mr. Quincy in the Senate of Massachusetts, and agreed to. “Resolved, as the sense of the Senate of Massachusetts, that in a war like the present, waged without justifiable cause, and prosecuted in a manner that indicates, that conquest and ambition are its real motives, it is not becoming a moral and religious people, to express their approbation of military or naval exploits, which are not immediately connected with the defence of our sea-coast and soil.” It is somewhat remarkable, that the very same individuals, who thus thought it unbecoming “a moral and religious people” to rejoice in the victories of their country, feasted most lustily for the Russian victories. Will these be just, and make amends, For the rude havoc of their friends? No, rather would they task their mind, Excuses for such acts to find, And justify the dastard feats, Of British tars and British fleets. XXVII. As tottering near the smoking heap, The houseless matron bends to weep, Methinks I hear her sighing say, As turning in despair away, “Are these the gallant tars so long, “The burthen of their country's song; “These, they, whose far resounding name, “Fills the obstreperous trump of fame; “Who lord it o'er the subject wave, “And France, and all her prowess brave? “These, who such deeds of glory wrought, “When Blake, and Howe, and Duncan fought? “These, who with Nelson, Honour's son, “The victory so often won? “These the same Britons, fam'd of yore, “At Cressy, and at Agincour? “These, the great “bulwark” to oppose, “Peace and religion's deadly foes? “These, who are destin'd to restore, “Repose to Europe's harass'd shore? “God help the while! if such they be, “What glorious times we soon shall see? XXVIII. “If such they be—God help the while! “Where shall the peaceful sons of toil, “Who take no part in that fell strife, “Which is ambition's land is rife; “But harmless trade industrious piy “Nor trouble aught beneath the sky— “To what lone scene must they retire, “To scape the Briton's wrathful fire? “Where shall the matron refuge seek, “The infant that can hardly speak? “Where the bed-ridden and the old, “Retire from reach of Briton bold? “Who comes in pious christian ire, “To purify the earth by fire; “Who labours for the world's repose, “By heaping up a world of woes; “Who points our hopes to realms of bliss, “By making us heart sick of this, “And thus as Farmer Caleb saith, “ACTS AS THE “BULWARK OF OUR FAITH.” Hush'd in the strain, the minstrel gone; But did he wander forth alone? No—close by Princeton college gate, Even to this day he holds his state, Where well his bearing you may know, By sightless eye, and head of snow. His little garden flourishes, With sallad rare and radishes; Cabbage and cucumbers, are seen, And turnips with their tops so green; And of the common garden stuff, The minstrel has more than enough. His faithful dog is often seen, Waddling across the college green, And not a little Freshman there, But pats his head with pious care. At summer eve there gather round The student lads, who stand astound, And listen with attentive glee, To tales of modern chivalry, And gallant feats of younger times, And various wild, and witching rhymes Once in the year he deigns to play, First fiddle on Commencement Day, When in Jolines high stately hall, Is held the Student's ANNUAL BALL. Scotch fiddle, fare thee well! the night dogs bark, Their wild notes with thy drowsy tones, aye blending, Rouse from his reverie some boozy spark, From porter house or tavern, homeward wending, Resume thy case again, thou wantest mending, And thy worn strings make droning minstrelsy, The squeaking tones with city vespers blending, Mix'd with the distant hum of nightly glee, In drowsy concert, sleepy maketh me. Yet once again, farewel Scotch fiddle dear, (For dear thou art, to those that buy thy lay,) Ah! little reck'd I of thy tones so clear, That scare love making Catlings far away. How often have I scrap'd whole nights away, And murder'd tunes the world hath never known What time to dancing wights and damsels gay, I tun'd thy strings and fiddled all alone: That I survive these nights, sweet fiddle, is thine own. Hark! as my lingering footsteps slow retire, Some airy minstrel wakes thy worn out string! 'Tis Church's ghost, come from Tartarean fire! Mr. Scott, I suppose, here alludes to the late Dr. Church, who invented a certain nostrum, which he had the insolence to call Scotch Ointment, and for which the poet has very properly consigned him to the regions of Tartarus. Editor. “Scotch ointment,” stead of rosin pure he brings. And hark! how sweet th' anointed fiddle rings! Fainter, and fainter in receding swell, As the pure spirit spread his singed wings, My fingers itch to play the wizard spell, But 'twill not be—SCOTCH FIDDLE, fare thee well!</field>
   </doc>
</add>