<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Davies, Samuel, 1723-1761</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Davies, Samuel, 1723-1761</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">davies samuel 1723 1761</field>
      <field name="author_text">Davies, Samuel, 1723-1761</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1960's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ap/uvaGenText/tei/chap_AM0874.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240349</field>
      <field name="date_text">1968</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:440309</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Greek, Modern (1453- )</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Collected poems of Samuel Davies : 1723-1761</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Collected poems of Samuel Davies : 1723-1761</field>
      <field name="title_facet">collected poems of samuel davies 1723 1761</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">collected poems of samuel davies 1723 1761</field>
      <field name="title_text">Collected poems of Samuel Davies : 1723-1761</field>
      <field name="year_display">1968</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1968</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1968</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440309&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440309&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Davies, Samuel, 1723-1761&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;davies samuel 1723 1761&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Collected poems of Samuel Davies : 1723-1761&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;collected poems of samuel davies 1723 1761&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1968&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1968&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Davies, Samuel&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1723&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1761&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Collected poems of Samuel Davies : 1723-1761&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Gainesville&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Scholars' Facsimiles &amp;amp; Reprints&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1968&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3865903-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;cham0874&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;gre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Collected poems of Samuel Davies : 1723-1761&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1996&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1996 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 399 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries, introductory, and editorial matter</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-AmPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">MISCELLANEOUS POEMS, CHIEFLY ON Divine Subjects. IN TWO BOOKS. Published for the Religious Entertainment of CHRISTIANS in general. Æthere dúm vesci datur, et vitalibus Auris, Hic Scil. Deus. mihi Materies Carminis unus srit. Jonst. ?????? ????????? ???? ? ?? ?????????, ?????, ?? ???????? ???????? ?????, ??????????. Hesiod imitat. Thus translated by Dr. Watts, Pierian Muses, fram'd for heav'nly Lays, Descend, and sing the God your Father's Praise. WILLIAMSBURG: Printed and Sold by William Hunter, M,dcc, ii. BOOK I. I. LORD Thou knowest all Things, Thou knowest that I love Thee. Joh. xxi. 17. My God! the Wretch that does not love Thy Name To Life and Being forfeits all his Claim, And may he sink to nothing whence he came. Or let the Yawn of the dire Mouth of Hell, Receive him with his Fellow-Fiends to dwell. 1 Cor. xvi. 22. Oh! if my Heart does not to Thee aspire, If ought with equal Fervour I desire, I'm self-condemn'd, and doom myself to Fire. Let not my guilty Breath profane Thy Air, Nor groaning Earth the monstrous Burden bear. Let Clouds with Vengeance big, burst o'er my Head, And Vollies of red Thunder strike me dead. The Sun convert his gentle Rays to Flames, And blast the Miscreant with his vengeful Beams. The whole Creation rise in Arms for Thee, To vindicate the Rights of Thy Divinity. Vile Wretch! that dare refuse to love a God, Who form'd me Man out of my native Clod; Whose Breath the Faculty of Love inspir'd, And with the heav'nly Spark my Bosom fir'd: Whose uncreated Beauties charm the Sight Of gazing Angels, in the Realms of Light. Whose Glories, faintly copy'd, round me shine, And mildly beam thro' all these Works of Thine, Proclaiming Thee their Origin Divine: Whose Grace, diffus'd around in thousand Rills, Arrays a thousand Worlds in chearful Smiles: Thou too, when Man to dreadful Ruin fell, Helpless, unpity'd on the Brink of Hell; When Justice frowning did the Prey demand, And None could rescue from his vengeful Hand; Thou, touch'd with Pity, did'st avert his Doom, And gav'st Thy Son a Victim in his Room. Nail'd to the Cross the bleeding Saviour hangs, And courts my Love with Groans and dying Pangs. Oh! I must love!—Or can the Groans and Blood Of an incarnate Godhead be withstood! Yet ah! in some dark Hours I hardly know Whether I love my gracious God or no. Gloomy Suspicions, twinging Jealousies, And anxious Doubts in all their Horrors rise. I hear the Whisperings of misgiving Fear, “Thy Love is feign'd, thy Ardour insincere' Too true! too true! my trembling Soul replies, Else whence so often could this Languor rise? Ah! these unruly Passions would not rove Thus wildly, were they fix'd with sacred Love. Nor would the Flame of pure Devotion die Thus frequent, and my Pow'rs so stupid lie. And yet methinks in some bright Moments too, I feel the heav'nly Flame divinely glow. To Thee so ardent all my Passions move, That if I love Thee not, I know not what I love. If I'm deceiv'd in this with empty Shew, Then my Existence is uncertain too: An universal Sceptic I commence, Beneath the Glare of brightest Evidence, In spite of Reason, and in spite of Sense. Oh! if I love Thee not, as Fears suggest, Why am I, in Thine Absence, thus distrest? Whence this strange Tumult, this uneasy Pain, 'Til Thy sweet Smiles compose my Soul again? Whence these wild Pantings of immense Desire? Why should poor breathing Dust so high aspire? I see my busy Fellow-Worms pursue Created Bliss, and nothing nobler view; Content they waste their Life, estrang'd from Thee In undisturb'd, serene Stupidity. And why, like them, can't I contented play, And eat, and drink, and sleep my Life away? Whence this immense Ambition in my Mind, That scorns all Joys but those of heavenly Kind? Why should a Worm, an animated Clod; Disdain all Bliss beneath a boundless God? Oh! what but the attractive Force of Love, Could raise my groveling Spirit thus above? Say, Great Omniscient! (for Thou know'st my Heart) Can Nature ease my Soul, if Thou depart? Can Riches, Pleasures, Honours, Empires, Crowns, Or Friends, content me, when I feel Thy Frowns? No! all Creation dwindles to a Toy, And Heav'n itself could not excite my Joy. The chearful Sun glares hateful to my Eyes, And every blooming Beauty round me dies. Thou great Invisible! Thou dear Unknown Why thus to Thee should my soft Passions run? Thus thro' the Objects of my Senses break, And Charms unknown and hidden Glories seek? Deep in Recesses of approachless Light Thou dwellest, far beyond my feeble Sight; Yet drawn by some strange mystic Influence, I love Thee more than all that strikes my Sense; Than all my Ears have heard, or Eyes have seen, Or lively Fancy's gayest Pow'rs can feign. O! if Thy Love does not my Heart inflame, Why do I thus delight in Jesus' Name? His Name is Music to my ravish'd Ears, Sweeter than that which charms the heav'nly Spheres A cheering Cordial to my fainting Breast; My Hope, my Joy, my Peace, my Heav'n, my Rest. I spring from Earth, and Heav'n is my Abode, When I can say those charming Words, my God; My God!—Infinite Joys lie in the Sound. Be Thou but mine; and all the Sun goes round Without reluctant Murm'ring I resign; I have enough, if I can call Thee MINE. O! if I love Thee not, why do I thus Love the dear Mansion of Thy earthly House? The sacred Morning shines with heav'nly Rays. More bright, more charming than ten thousand Days, That bids me visit that delightful Place. There would I dwell, and pass my Life away, 'Til Death convey me up to brighter Day In all the Institutions of Thy Grace, For Thee I look; and if Thou hide Thy Face, The sacred Rites would dull and tiresome seem, Did I not hope to find my God in them. When at Thy Throne I bow my suppliant Knee, Is Pray'r a stupid cold Formality? Oh! can my Pray'rs content me without Thee? No! these are but the Channels of thy Grace, Transparent Glasses where I see Thy Face: I thirst for living Water all in vain, If Thou Thy gracious Influence restrain: The radiant Glasses shew me nothing fair, Unless I see Thy Charms reflected there. Then Peace, my restless and suspicious Heart; And ye dire-boding Jealousies, depart. I love my God, or else I nothing love; And the pure Flame e'er long shall burn above, And from its native El'ment ne'er remove. II. Early Piety recommended. (Sent originally in a Letter to two young Ladies.) Ye lovely Flow'rs, that just begin to bloom, And raise our Hope of glorious Fruit to come; That just begin to open all your Charms, While vig'rous Youth your tender Bosoms warms: Indulge a Muse, that's anxious for your Good, Lest some rude Storm should blast the op'ning Bud; Indulge the Muse, that would the Blossoms shield, 'Till they mature, and Fruit immortal yield, And bloom forever gay in Heaven's fair azure Field. Now you begin to tread Youth's slippery Path, Where Thousands stumble, and sink down to Death. Where'er you walk, 'tis all enchanted Ground, And Snares in dang'rous Ambush lurk around. The flattering World presents her fairest Charms, And Vice would tempt you to her horrid Arms. The Crowd of fashionable Sinners aim To form you to the Mode, to walk with them; Spread false enchanting Scenes before your Eyes, And promise Bliss from empty Vanities: While sanguine, forward Youth is still intent To make the terrible Experiment; And will not, 'til by dear Experience taught. Indulge the true, tho' melancholy Tho't, That all beneath the Sun is Vanity and Nought. The dang'rous Path of Youth my Feet have trod, And lately left the smooth enchanting Road: Now safe advanc'd to a more solid Age, Let me conduct you o'er the slippery Stage. Trembling I wait th' Event of every Step, And shudder lest you make a fatal Slip. O! cautious tread: Let Virtue be your Guard: Virtue alone can keep you un-ensnar'd. O! chuse your Maker for your early Friend, And on His gracious Patronage depend. He can obscure Temptation's brightest Charms, And shelter feeble Youth from threatning Harms; Steel the weak Breast with Grace invincible, And baffle all the Stratagems of Hell. O! heave the Sigh, waft up the weeping Pray'r To HIM who loves that Harmony to hear: He looks and smiles and sheds His richest Grace On Virgin-Souls that early seek His Face. O! let not Earth you tender Hearts ensnare; Give your first Love to the eternal Fair. 'Twas He, 'twas He that form'd your mortal Frame, Inspir'd the living Soul, that heav'nly Flame: Taught senseless Dust to see and hear and move, And kindled in the Breast the gentle Pow'r of Love: But lately, from His all-creating Hand You came, and sprung to Life at His Command; 'Til then, you lay in native Nothing's Shade; And but for Him, had still remain'd unmade; A Father's tender Name He bears to you; And is not your first Love a Father's Due? O! can your grateful Souls so soon forget The gracious Pow'r from whence they came so late? Should not your Bosoms with His Love be fir'd, Whose Breath the tender Passions all inspir'd? He too, when Man to deepest Ruin fell, Helpless, forlorn on the dire Brink of Hell; He, touch'd with Pity, and impell'd by Grace, Sent his own Son to save a guilty Race, And yield His sacred Soul a Ransom in their Place. The Infant-God did soon begin for you To bear the Vengeance to your Follies duc. For you the heav'nly Mansions He forsook, And a vile Stable for His Chamber took. His Robes of Light Divine aside he threw, And wrap'd Himself in swaddling Cloaths for you. Just as He enter'd on the Stage of Life, He felt the painful circumcising Knife. In His weak Mother's Arms the young Exile, From Herod's Rage fled to the Land of Nile. Egypt. His Load of Sorrow grew still as He grew; At length, see! on the Cross He bleeds for you! There rack'd and tortur'd your Redeemer hangs, And courts your Love with Groans and dying Pangs. See how He agonizes! see His Blood! And say, Can such Allurements be withstood? Oh no! you melt! you yield! I hear you say, “See, Jesus! here we give our Hearts away! “Our earliest Love, Dear Lord! unrival'd take; “'Tis all the poor Requital we can make.” See how in youthful Prime, the smiling Year Now blooms, and all her flow'ry Charms appear: This Letter was written in Spring. The tuneful Birds, that hail the welcome Spring, Grateful at Nature's Restoration sing, And all the Groves with charming Music ring: A living Green arrays the Woods and Fields, And the sweet Vale a thousand Pleasures yields: The lovely Family of Flow'rs appear, And breathe Perfumes thro' all the balmy Air: The Sun shines bright and mild; the gentle Breeze Regales our Sense, and whispers thro' the Trees: The wide Creation smiles; Earth, Sky and Air In vernal Robes and blooming Youth appear. But ah! e'er long will surly Winter come, Strip the gay Year of all her youthful Bloom, And spread o'er all a cheerless sullen Gloom; Snow, Rain and Frost commixt, and savage Storms Ravage and bluster in a thousand Forms; The smiling World with baleful Influence blast, And turn these charming Scenes t' a rueful Waste. Here see your mournful Fate, ye blooming Fairs; Stern Death nor Youth nor Strength nor Beauty spares. The Young, the Old, the Wise, the Fair, the Gay, All fall a common undistinguish'd Prey. The Tyrant, senseless of the Pow'r of Charms, Hurries the Beauty to reside with Worms; Covers with mortal Pale the rosy Cheeks, And dooms the Dust with Fellow-Dust to mix: Hurries the Soul at once to Worlds unknown, Doom'd by the Sentence of th' Eternal Throne To shine with Angels, or with Fiends to groan. Then catch the fleeting Hour before 'tis past; The present Now perhaps may be your last. For barren Winter early lay up Store, That joyful you may meet the fatal Hour. Survey the Garden, where the fragrant Rose, In all the Pride of youthful Beauty glows; Go, pluck the tempting Flow'r, and pensive say, “So cruel Death may cut me off to-day.” And when the Sun withdraws his quick'ning Ray, And Ev'ning Shades shut up the cheerful Day; See! how the flow'ry Tribes their Beauties hide, And fade and languish in their gayest Pride; Shrivel their Leaves, and bend the drooping Head; “So (let your Heart suggest) so I may fade, “And sudden sink among the mould'ring Dead.” O! may the Lustre of your Minds surpass The with'ring Beauties of the fairest Face: May every shining Virtue deck your Youth, And ev'ry heav'nly Grace grow with your Growth; Life's fleeting Moments glide delightful by, With every Grace adorn'd, and every Joy; Till Death, far distant, finding you mature For Heav'n, convey you up to Joys more pure. III. Philosophic Devotion. (Occasioned by reading The Religious Philosopher.) 1. With Rapture wing'd, my eager Soul Thro' Thy unbounded Empire roves, Great Author of this Glorious All! And lost in Wonder, still approves. 2. Thy Works with Pleasure and Surprize O'erwhelm this weak enquiring Mind; Wonders in long Succession rise, Yet more and greater lie behind. 3. Fixt in Astonishment, my Eyes, Intense, attempt the vast Survey; But Glories too transparent rise, And dim them with excessive Day. 4. The Rays of Wisdom, Goodness, Pow'r, So sweetly blend and brightly shine, My Soul, o'ercome, can but adore, And own the Workmanship Divine. 5. Struck with the Sight, I shrink away, Conscious how weak and blind I am: Despair to finish the Survey, And silent dread Thy awful Name. 6. Mean tho' I am, (not wholly so, Since wisely fram'd by Skill Divine) Permit me at Thy Throne to bow, While round me all Thy Glories shine. IV. SOLOMON. A Paraphrastical Poem on sundry Passages in the Book of Ecclesiastes. Why shou'd I, anxious after Happiness, Pursue wrong Ways, or right without Success? Why fret and toil in Searches long and vain, Since a Director I with Ease may gain? A skillful Guide, made by Experience wise, That costly Med'cine for mis-judging Eyes. The Traveller bewilder'd asks the Way, And cautious shuns the Path where others stray: Come then, My Soul, exempt from every Care, Come, to the Royal Preacher lend an Ear; Attend the Monarch, whose unbounded Mind Made one Experiment for all Mankind, Past thro' the Lab'rinths that ensnare the Wise, Try'd all that's charming in the Miser's Eyes, Undaunted climb'd bright Honour's steep Ascent, And thro' the Round of sensual Pleasures went; Listen, while grey Experience tells the Truth; Nor fear Deception from her faithful Mouth. In happy Canaan, the World's Paradise, Where constant Harvests of rich Plenty rise; Where candid Milk and pleasant Honey flows In luscious Streams, and ev'ry Pleasure grows: In sacred Salem, the belov'd and great, Where Canaan's Blessings all collected meet; Where He who Empires crushes and sustains, Tremendous in His awful Temple reigns, And Clouds of sacred Incense early rise, Breathing Perfumes to the propitious Skies; Where foreign Merchants vend their richest Store, And Ophir-Ships import their golden Oar; The Fear and Wonder of the Nations round, Profuse in Wealth with endless Honours crown'd; Where, yearly, tributary Princes meet, To pay their Homage at their Sov'reign's Feet; There first my Lungs the vital Ether drew, And there the Light of Life first blest my View. Sprung from a Royal Sire, a Glorious Crown By heav'nly Designation was my own; Millions of loyal Heroes thro' the Land Confirm'd my Throne, and stoopt to my Command; The Sons of Jacob, Favourites of the Skies! At whose dread Name each Tyrant shrinks and dies, Mov'd at my Nod, their Sov'reign Law, my Will, The Dictates of my Tongue, their Oracle: While neighb'ring Sceptres yielded to my Sway, Ambitious of the Honour to obey; And gentle Peace her downy Pinions spread, Shadowing the Throne, and hovering round my Head. Nature and Art with Emulation strove, T' advance my Bliss, and every Grief remove. Ch. 1. v. 12. My Mind enlighten'd with a heav'nly Ray, Was calm as midnight Hours, and bright as Day, Deep as the vast Abyss, and vigorous as May; Freed from the Freaks of young Impertinence, And ripen'd by Experience into Sense. Thrice happy State! below but seldom found! A Heav'nly Paradise on earthly Ground! v. 16. Come then, My Soul, this Season sure was lent To qualifie me for Experiment; That Men from my Experience may discern. Where lies their Bliss, and what to follow learn: Come, in this happy Juncture, let us try Wherein the Happiness of Man does lie; Pursue that unknown Something, whether hid She in the Bosom of the Wise abide, Or lie conceal'd in the enchanting Stream Of sensual Joys, where the Luxurious swim: Extend thy Searches wheresoe'er the Ray Of yon' bright Sun extends, and kindles Day: The dear, coy Nymph, which Mortals never saw, Where'er she lurks, from her Retirements draw. Ch. 1. v. 13. 16. Ch. 2. v. 3. I said—And as an Eagle, Hunger-smit, Pours all his nimble Vigour into Flight, And thro' aërial Fields pursues his Prey, Swift as a Sun-Beam in the Blaze of Day: So flew my curious Mind thro' all the Plains, Where, in alluring Glory, Science reigns; With contemplative Eyes the Works explor'd, With which this spacious Universe is stor'd; The hidden Causes and the Ends of Things, And Order which from their Contexture springs; The Powers of immaterial Essences, And puzzling intellectual Mysteries; The Properties of Matter and its Laws, And each Phænomenon from unseen Cause: The Wonders of the Planetary World, The Rules by which their ample Orbs are hurl'd; The boundless Regions of the fixed Stars, And Comets scatt'ring Pestilence and Wars. Descending thence, I took a wide Survey Of this vast Earth, and the unbounded Sea; From the tall Cedars that luxuriant spread Their stately Branches on Libanus' Head, To the small Hyssop blooming on the Wall Mould'ring to Dust, and nodding to its Fall, My Search extended: 1 Kings 4. v. 33.—While each studious Sage As my Assistant gladly did engage; To their learn'd Lectures eager I attend, Embrace what's right; what's corrigible, mend; Hypotheses upon Hypotheses They raise, and the well-fram'd Illusions please. 1 Kings 4 v. 13, 17. My Enquiries thus finish'd I begun To view th' extensive Circuit I had run; If haply in the Maze of studious Thought True Happiness may with Success be sought: When struck, amaz'd, I call'd my Mind aside, And pausing deep—thus cry'd; In tiresome Labours of the busy Brain I seek for Bliss; but ah! I seek in vain. Insinuating Sorrows still pervade The knowing Heart, and contemplative Head. v. 18. This curious Itch is never satisfy'd With what is known, if aught continues hid, But eager pants and reaches after more, Pronouncing all in vain it knew before. Alass! what Glooms still hover o'er my Soul! And blended Clouds in close Succession roll! The clea est of my vast Discoveries lie Involv'd in Doubts and dark Uncertainty; And most of Things are wrapt in solid Glooms, Where a bright Beam of Knowledge never comes, Conceal'd forever from th' enquiring Sight In Caverns of imperviable Night. v. 15. The anxious Mind intense in the Pursuit, Faints with the Toil, but never tastes the Fruit; Perplexing Thoughts still ravage thro' the Brain, And twinge the Spirit with acutest Pain; And Melancholy, nurs'd with studious Care, Often erects her sooty Banner there; Hollow and sunk the poring Eye appears, And the dull Image of her Sorrows wears. Ch. 12. v. 12. In Parts superior, then, what Profit lies? Alas! how small the Pleasure to be wise? 'Tis but to know how little can be known, These three Lines are borrow'd, with small Alteration, from Mr. Pope's ingenious Essay on Man. To see our Ignorance and Weakness shown; To chase a Phantom, which our Chase outflies, And leaves us lagging, distant from the Prize. This fail'd; I try'd one more Experiment, Still in Pursuit of Happiness intent. Delicate Mirth array'd in tempting Smiles, Pleasures surrounding in delicious Rills, Facetious Jests, and Laughter op'ning wide Her sprightly Jaws, with Hands on every Side, Present themselves, and promise perfect Bliss: Ch. 2. v. 1. I try'd,—but found them lying Vanities. This empty Mirth tends but to make me sad, And thou, unthinking Laughter! too, art mad. v. 2. Her Vigour next the generous Grape bestow'd, And sprightly Wine in liberal Glasses glow'd: My Palate I indulg'd; yet, lest Excess Shou'd cloy my Taste, and make the Pleasure less, Or Wisdom with intemperate Vapours blind, And in luxurious Puddles drown the Mind, My Reason still her Government maintain'd, And the bold Licence of the Taste restrain'd. v. 3. But Happiness in Luxury and Wine I seek in vain, and Bliss is too Divine To lurk in Grapes: the Pleasures of the Taste Degrade the Man, and only suit the Beast. To Architecture next I turn'd my Mind, And Palaces magnificent design'd. Columns were rais'd, which spacious Roofs o'erspread; Sculpture and Paint their various Charms display'd: Marble was taught to live, and Shade and Light With fair Illusions pleas'd the ravish'd Sight. And shining Gold its yellow Radiance spread Thro' all the Buildings: Burnish'd Brass display'd Its rougher Glories: All the Charms of Art Blaz'd on my Eye, and sought to win my Heart. Ch. 2. v. 4. But all the Pomp of glitt'ring Roofs and Walls, Of stately Chambers and embellish'd Halls Is nought but Vanity and empty Shew, And never free from rude, intrusive Woe. Shy Happiness abhors this useless State, And shuns the gaudy Buildings of the Great. Wood, Brass and Gold, by all the Powers of Art However form'd, can never ease the Heart. Then in the sylvan Scene I sought for Bliss; I made me Vineyards, and I planted Trees. Unwithering Verdure, and eternal Blooms Form'd lovely Prospects, and diffus'd Perfumes. Perpetual Spring her numerous Beauties strew'd Thro' all my Groves, and blest the waving Wood. Refreshing Rills, thro' various Pipes convey'd, Their chearing Moisture thro' the Forest spread, And, murmuring, sooth'd the Ear; while Zephyrs mild Panted and breath'd thro' all the pleasant Wild. v. 4, 5, 6. Here oft' I walk'd in sacred Solitude, And, unmolested, Happiness pursu'd;— In vain; for Happiness cou'd not be found Among the Groves in this delightful Ground. I try'd the Pomp and Equipage of State. Obsequious Crowds did in long Order wait Around my sumptuous Table, and abroad When Pleasure call'd me, dazzled all the Road: Domestics home-born, and from every Clime. Of either Sex the Beauty and the Prime, Form'd my illustrious Retinue, and stood Waiting my Will, observant of my Nod. Ch. 2. v. 7. But ah! this proud Magnificence of State Can never make my Happiness compleat. But Music, sure, that calms the boist'rous Breast, And sooths tumultuous Passions into Rest, That charms deep-fixt Anxieties away, Makes even moping Melancholy gay; The Hero's Breast with martial Ardour fires, And dire Despair herself with Ease inspires: Music will breathe refin'd, exalted Bliss Into my Soul, and lull me into Peace: I said. The Masters of the tuneful Art v. 8. The utmost Pow'rs of Harmony exert. In sweetly-varying Strains the Music floats, While various Instruments try various Notes. But all these Strains are useless; I despair To find true Bliss in modulated Air. Hitherto disappointed, I'll behold My vast Possessions, and unnumber'd Gold. The Riches of the World are in my Hand; Surrounding Monarchs, aw'd at my Command, With Wealth immense my spacious Treasures fill, And yield their choicest Blessings to my Will. My Cattle graze upon a thousand Hills, And seed unnumber'd in the fertile Vales. So various, so unbounded is my Store, The greediest Wish can comprehend no more. But still unsatisfy'd, from the Survey Scornful I turn'd my weary Eyes away, And cry'd, Bliss is not made of Dust and glitt'ring Clay. Thus freely I indulg'd my Eyes to roll, And gave unbridl'd Licence to my Soul. Whate'er insatiate Appetite could crave, With lib'ral Hand, without Restraint, I gave. Ch. 2. v. 10. Not to indulge a Lust, was my Design, But act the Philosophic Libertine: I paus'd, I reason'd, and with Eye intense Observ'd the Issue of th' Experiments. But when the tedious Circuit I review'd, And all the anxious Labours I pursu'd, v. 11. In which my restless Spirit toil'd with Pain, Seeking for Bliss with eager Wish in vain; I saw that all beneath the lower Skies Is abstract Vanity of Vanities. Oppressive Sorrows and Vexations grow In ev'ry State, in ev'ry Clime below. Nor for themselves need future Ages try v. 12. Th' Experiment; for all is Vanity. Anxieties in all Things earthly dwell, Which All alas! can feel, but none can tell. Ch. 1. v. 8. No Novelties present themselves to View, To tempt succeeding Ages to renew Th' Experiment, or Bliss below pursue. v. 9, 10. In dull Succession early Pleasures run v. 9. In the same tedious Circle ever. The Ear with antiquated Harmonies v. 8. Is cloy'd, and with accustom'd Sights the Eyes. The ever-moving Wheels of Nature run In the same Tract; in the same Tract the Sun. v. [illeg.], 5. Rolls on his tiresome, everlasting Round; And still we tread the same old-fashion'd Ground. Besides; the Intervals of Bliss we find Are short, uncertain, varying as the Wind. Death unsuspected in close Ambush lurks, And undermining still, our Ruin works. Ch. ix. 12. Whether we laugh or weep, or wake or sleep, He haunts us, ready on his Prey to leap. So the unthinking Rovers of the Air, Caught unexpected, flutter in the Snare. So finny Shoals rush heedless into Death, Dragg'd to the Land, and gasp in vain for Breath. But see! above the Earth, beyond the Skies, What charming Scenes, what brighter Prospects rise! There the Paternal Mind, the Source of Good, Feeds His own Offspring with immortal Food. There Happiness in full Perfection grows; And restless Souls enjoy a calm Repose; A Bliss proportion'd to the widest Wish; Ever enjoy'd, yet ever new and fresh. Hail happy Realms! the Bliss we seek below In vain, is only to be found in you. Soon (welcome Prospect!) the bright Hour will come That wafts us to our blest celestial Home. Soon into Dust this brittle Frame will fall; The Soul return to her Original; xii. 7 Return exulting from her long Exile In this dark Dungeon, and laborious Toil: There dwell forever with her Father-God, And find the Bliss before not understood. Then since the Happiness of Mortals lies Beyond the Bounds of these inferior Skies, The only Happiness they here can share, Is for those blissful Regions to prepare. Thro' various Mazes then at length we come Ch. xii. v. 13. To this Conclusion as the total Sum. Fear thy Creator God with filial Awe, And all thy Life observe His holy Law. v. 13. Chuse as thy constant Path this heav'nly Plan; 'Tis the whole Duty, the whole Bliss of Man; They that are acquainted with the Hebrew need not be informed, that in this Sentence,—This is the whole Duty of Man,—The Word Duty is not in the Original; and I humbly conceive it is causelessly inserted by our Translators. It seems more correspondent to the Design of this Book to take it in the Latitude I have given it,—To fear God, and keep His Commandments, is the Whole of Man, his most important, his only Concern in Point of Duty, and in Point of Happiness. The only Point where Happiness is fixt, Pleasures in this World, greater in the next. Tir'd of my fruitless Searches, here I rest, With this Discovery pleas'd, content and blest, IV. I said, I will be wise: but it was far from me. (Compos'd when a Student, Nov. 12. 1744.) How rough, how steep, and intricate the Way To Knowledge, and the Worlds of mental Day! How thick the Gloom, how dark the dismal Night That stops the Dawn of Intellectual Light! Thro' what vast Labyrinths my Feet must rove, Ere I obtain the shining Pearl I love! At first it seems at Hand, just in Embrace; And thus allures me to the endless Chace: But as I run, new Wonders strike my Eyes; “Hills peep o'er Hills, and Alps on Alps arise.” Pope. As Knowledge, so new Objects still increase; The more I know, I seem to know the less. One Thing presents another quite unknown; A third starts up in View, ere that be gone; 'Till endless Crowds in long Succession rise, And spread Amazement o'er my gazing Eyes. So the etherial Bow, of various Dye, Immensely distant, shews its Colours nigh: The witless Trav'ler, fond of nearer Views, With fruitless Steps th' illusive Shade pursues. 'Till tir'd, bewilder'd, hopeless of his Aim, He rests, and blushes with ignoble Shame. While one Idea dances in my Brain, Another rising drives it out again. I loose the Treasures of Conceptions past: The Gain is lost, but studious Labours last. So while on Sand a Man his Foot-steps guides, One Foot makes Way, the other backward slides. Wasted in fruitless Toils, thus pass my Hours; And sacred Truth o'ercomes these feeble Pow'rs. Long last the Glooms of native Ignorance, And by slow Steps to Knowledge we advance. But this dark State will not forever last, This Infancy of Being soon is past: The Soul matur'd, and freed from cumbrous Clay, Shall then rejoice in everlasting Day: Serene employ her elevated Pow'rs On Truths too dazzling for this World of ours. If Darkness, then, must still surround my Head 'Till heav'nly Light succeed to Death's dark Shade; Be it my Study and my constant Care For that important Moment to prepare, Lest then, secluded from the Realms of Light, I sink forever in more dismal Night. O may the Sun of Righteousness arise, On a bewilder'd Wretch! Then shall my Eyes Discern the happy Path that leads to Bliss, Where perfect Knowledge, and where Jesus is. VI. Of Him, and thro' Him, and to Him are all Things. Rom. 11. ult. Thou only Good! Eternal All! What am I when compar'd with Thee? A Piece of animated Clay; An Atom sporting in thy Ray— The Loss would be but small, Should I again to Non-Existence fall: Nay, if thy Glory might but rise, Cheerful my Being I'd resign, And fall a willing Sacrifice To gain a Purpose so divine, So much more worthy than this little Life of Mine! VII. ANOTHER. I. What is great God! and what IS NOT, Should BE, and NOT BE, to thy Praise: Then, if my Non-Existence should but raise, Thy Glory, I'm content thy Hand should blot Me from the Rank of Being, and conclude my Days. 'Tis owing to thy Glory that I am, And fit I should NOT BE, if that might raise thy Name. Should I relapse to Nothing, scarce Would it appear a Blank in thy vast Universe. II. Thou art th' eternal Source and Spring Of Being and of Possibility. Thy wise omnific Hand can bring Non-Entity TO BE: Then with a Sov'reign Nod Thou can'st remand The vast Productions of thy Hand, To dreary Nothing whence they came,— And be it so, if that might glorify thy Name! III. Ah! what are Worlds compar'd with Thee, Great everlasting All! But Atoms hov'ring in the Air, Bubbles and Vanity, That at thy great Command appear, And at thy Word to nothing fall, Whose Pleasure gives them Leave TO BE. Thou viewest, independent, from on high, A Sparrow or a Hero die, Atoms or Systems moulder into Dust, And now a World, and now a Bubble burst. Mr. Pope, in his Essay on Man, expresses this Thought with inimitable Sublimity. —“Who sees with equal Eye, as God of all, A Hero perish, or a Sparrow fall; Atoms or Systems into Ruin hurl'd, And now a Bubble burst, and now a World.” IV. Yet since Thy Hand did build my Frame With Pow'r and Skill Divine, And in my Life Thy glorious Name Does more illustrious shine; O! let me still exist,—But to Thy Praise, That out of Nothing did me raise. VIII. Sinful Immortality worse than Non-Existence. 1. Thou only Holy! To Thy Name 'Tis fit eternal Praise be given, By all the Things Thy Hands did frame, Thro' the wide Earth, and wider Heav'n. 2. Being itself becomes a Curse, When not employ'd, Great God! for Thee: And Life estrang'd from Thee is worse Ten thousand Times than not to Be. 3. Better to Non-Existence sink, Or turn to elemental Clay, Than sleep and laugh, and eat and drink My precious Hours in vain away. 4. Were there no Ground to hope and plead Thy Grace may form my Soul a new, How should I wish to be unmade, And drop to Nothing from Thy View! 5. For Oh! the dire Disease of Sin Has canker'd all my active Pow'rs; Corrodes my languid Soul within, And all her vital Strength devours. 6. The Vigour of my Soul is spent On low Pursuits and empty Joys: But ah! how feeble, cold and faint, When to my God I try to rise! 7. Sin chills Devotion's sacred Fire, Makes Wisdom's Path a tiresome Road; Cumbers the Pinions of Desire, That flutter to ascend to God. 8. If, contemplative, I retire With Things eternal to converse; My Heart, that restless Wanderer, Rambles thro' the wide Universe. 9. Or if before Thy Gracious Throne, I humbly bend the suppliant Knee, Languors oppress my Spirit down, I cannot, cannot rise to Thee! 10. And when in some celestial Song, I pay my Homage to Thy Name; The Anthem dies upon my Tongue; Nor feels my Breast the heav'nly Flame. 11. So when I view the sacred Page, Where Love and Light united shine, Cold Criticisms my Thoughts engage, Quite blind to Beauties more Divine. 12. Almighty God! With pitying Eye, Behold these useless Faculties! Restore Thy fallen Progeny, That deep immers'd in Ruin lies. 13. Say, shall my Being still be vain! Oh! shall I never serve my God! Then Life itself's a tedious Pain; And gladly I'd lay down the Load. 14. Oh! shall my Immortality Be spent t' offend Thy dearest Name! No! Rather let me cease to Be, And sink to Nothing whence I came. 15. But if Thy Grace renew my Soul, 'Twill be my Privilege to Be; And while eternal Ages roll, Joyful I'll live and act for Thee. 16. When Nature dies, and Day and Night Measure the Flux of Time no more, In brighter Worlds, with long Delight, The Hands that made me I'll adore. IX. A Clergyman's Reflections on hearing of the Death of one of his pious Parishoners. Dec. 5. 1750. I. One more of my Dear Flock is gone T' appear before th' Eternal Throne, And pass the grand decisive Test: “Ashes to Ashes, Dust to Dust.” Surviving Friends with Tears entrust, There 'til the General Doom to rest. II. The Soul, dismiss'd from cumb'rous Clay, Expatiates in eternal Day, And with the Great Immortals dwells: The Dawn of Immortality With Scenes unknown surprize the Eye, And Wonders vast and new reveals. III. Thus while I'm dreaming Life away, Or Books and Study fill the Day, My Flock is dying one by one; Convey'd beyond my warning Voice, To endless Pains, or endless Joys, For ever happy, or undone! IV. I too 'ere long must yield my Breath; My Mouth for ever shut in Death; Nor sound the Gospel Trumpet more: Then may I, while they're in my Reach, With Fervuor pray, with Fervour preach, And eager catch the flying Hour! V Almighty Grace! my Zeal enflame; Oh! free me from this sluggish Frame; And fire my Breast with vig'rous Love. Oh! teach me that divinest Art, To reach the Conscience, warm the Heart, And all the tender Passions move. VI. Then when I must resign my Trust, And at Thy Word relapse to Dust, Undaunted I shall meet Thy Throne; Joyful present, without a Spot, The Children by Thy Word begot, And hear Thy Voice pronounce, “Well done.” X. The Soul releas'd by Death. The Plan of the first Part of this Poem, and one or two of the Lines, were borrowed from Mr. Pope's little charming Ode, entitled The dying Christian to his Soul. I. Active Spark of heav'nly Fire, In a Clod of Earth confin'd, Ever fluttering to aspire To the Great Paternal Mind; Strugling still with upward Aim To mingle with thy native Flame! Death soon will break this Pris'n of Clay, And give thee Leave to spring away; Then to thy native Regions go, There with th' Etherial Flames to glow. II. Come, thou shining Hour, appear! Happy Moment, Oh draw near!— 'Tis come!—I feel the purple Stream Stagnate; in misty Darkness swim My dizzy Eyes confus'd and dim; Bedew'd with cold and clammy Sweat; The dancing Pulses cease to beat; In vain I gasp for Breath— Strange! Can this be Death? III. Hark! Th' Angelic Envoy say, “Sister Spirit, come away, “Drop the Cumber of the Clay, “And with thy Kindred join”— Angels, I come; conduct me on: Instruct me in a World unknown, In Mysteries Divine: Instruct me unexperienc'd Stranger how To act as the Immortals do; To think, and speak, and move like you: Teach me the Senses to supply, To see without the Optics of an Eye; The Music of your Songs to hear Without the Organ of an Ear. IV. Yes! now Blest Angels, now I find The Pow'rs of an unfetter'd Mind! How active and how Strange! O happy Place! O blissful State! Welcome Felicity compleat! Welcome amazing, happy Change! V. And is this then Eternity! And am I safely landed here! No more to Sin, no more to die, No more to sigh, or shed a Tear!— My Soul! can this be I? I, who just now imprison'd dwelt In yonder World of Woe and Guilt! Just now shudd'ring, trembling, sighing, Startled at the Thought of dying! Am I indeed the same? Or is it all a pleasing Dream?— The very same!—Ye heav'nly Choirs! Cherubic and Seraphic Fires! Come, assist my labouring Tongue; Sound aloud the grateful Song; Assist a Stranger to express His Thanks to rich unbounded Grace— Jesus! th' unbounded Grace was thine, Who bled and languished on the Tree, And bore infinite Pains for me, To raise me thus to Joys Divine. And do I see Thy Face at last, O my Dear, incarnate God! And has Thy Love Thy Servant plac'd In this Thy shining, blest Abode! Enough!—Thy Bounty gives me more Than I could think or wish before. XI. Gratitude and Impotence Not all the shining Saints on high Owe so much Gratitude as I; Not all the mourning Saints below A Debt so vast and boundless owe. From me the highest Praise should rise, Oblig'd by such unequall'd Ties. My Breast with warmer Zeal should burn, With deeper tend'rer Sorrows mourn, Than Gabriel that surrounds the Throne, Than any Wretch beneath the Sun. For I of all the Race that fell, Deserve the lowest Place in Hell; And I of all the ransom'd Race, Am most in Debt to Sovereign Grace. Ye Saints, no more yourselves abase, But yield to me the lowest Place: No more my rightful Claim contest To offer Praise above the Rest. Yet, Oh my God! there's not a Saint, That sobs in secret his Complaint, That calls himself the very First Of Sinners, and his Case the worst; There's not a Saint, but (to my Shame) Presents more Glory to Thy Name, But serves Thee with a warmer Zeal, And with more Fervour does Thy Will. Kind Angels! Will You raise on high His Praise, and my Defects supply! Oh! will You pay, in nobler Song, The Debt of my unskilful Tongue! And you, Dear Saints! Will you below, Help me to pay the Debt I owe! No doubt the Blessings You receive, Exceed the highest Thanks you give; Yet sure, You can't refuse to join To pay a Debt so vast as mine. All-gracious God! the Thanks receive, From others, which these Lips should give. And Oh! forgive a Worm that mourns, Because he can make no Returns. XII. The universal Lamentation. I. When Heav'n with a vindictive Frown Throws an aspiring Monarch down, The trembling Nation takes th' Alarm. And when we view the wide Champaign Soak'd with the Blood of Heroes slain, The softest Passions wake, and every Bosom warm. Though I freely own, it requires a more exalted Muse than mine to manage this tender Subject with suitable Pathos and Energy; yet I hope None will censure the Matter and Scope of the Poem, as favouring of fanatical Affectation.—That the human Soul, tho' the immediate Progeny of the uncreated Paternal Mind, (as even a Heathen could stile Him) is now surprizingly alienated from its Divine Parent, indisposed for the exalted Purposes of its Existence; and under the Tyranny of ignoble Appetites, and criminal Passions; is a lamentable Truth we must assent to, unless we deny our own quickest and most deep-felt mental Sensations.—And that Many indulge themselves in this Depravity, without any eager Aspiration for the Reparation of their noble Nature, now in Ruins; and make it the main Business of this mortal Life, to obey the groveling Dictates, and gratify the impetuous Lusts, of a degenerate Soul; we are ungratefully constrained to believe, by the odious Scenes of Impiety and Prophaneness, that open round us, and importunately intrude upon our Observation, however willingly we would shun them.—And can there be any Thing so moving, any Thing so just an Object for manly Sorrow, as this? It cannot be justly looked upon as an Instance of effeminate Softness, for the most exalted and dispassionate Mind, to dissolve into the tenderest Sorrows, when it is our common Humanity that demands the sympathising Fear, and prompts the lamenting Groan. The Dignity of the human Soul,—the expensive and endearing Measures a gracious God has been pleased to take for its Recovery,—the ineffable Glories forfeited, and the intolerable Miseries incurr'd, by an obstinate Continuance in Sin,—and a thousand other Considerations, render this Degeneracy peculiarly lamentable.—And may it not therefore be pertinently improven, as the Occasion for an Universal Lamentation? 'Tis natural for a Mind full of tender and vigorous Passions to fall into Prosopopæia's, and to call the inanimate Creation to share its Sensations. Nothing is more common in Passions of Joy and Gratitude; both in sacred and prophane Writers. Of this the 148 Psalm, the Mattin-Song of our first Parents, according to Milton, Thomson's Hymn annext to the Seasons, and that surprizing Apostrophe in Isai. lxix. 13 are very noble Instances. Thus also the mournful Passions frequently vent themselves, upon various Occasions; and why may they not on this, the most Mournful of all?—St. Paul (Rom viii. 19, 22.) forms a moving Prosopopæia on the Subject of this Poem, with Energy of Language which no Translation can reach.—The whole Creation bursts into an united Groan, and labours with travailing Pangs, ever since Sin reduced it into Slavery, and subjected it to Vanity; and will continue to do so, 'til it partake of the glorious Liberty of the Sons of God.—And this Instance, not to mention a Variety of others, is a sufficient Precedent to vindicate the Scope of this Poem.—'Tis certain, if Sin were more lamented, it would be less indulged and practised in the World. And if Cicero, considering the physical Evils of Life could say, (Hæc quidem Vita Mors est, quam lamentari possem. (Tusc. Disput. L. I.) “This Life is truly Death, which I could lament”; sure, when we survey the moral Evils that ruin the immortal Mind, we may breathe out Jeremiah's passionate Wish, Oh that mine Head were Waters! and mine Eyes Fountains of Tears! (Jer. ix. 1.) II. The softest Passions wake and mourn, When Sons of Honour, nobly born, Are sold for Slaves in barb'rous Climes. The Wretch that on the Gibbet hangs Moves in us sympathethic Pangs, Tho' self-destroy'd he dies for his own scarlet Crimes. III. Th' importunate and helpless Poor, Naked and famish'd at our Door; The Widow and the Fatherless; The melancholy House where Pain, Sickness and Death and Sorrows reign, Dissolve the gen'rous Heart to softest Tenderness. IV. But from our Hearts if Death should rend Some darling Relative or Friend, How we bewail the mould'ring Dust! Our Life is Grief, our Breath is Sighs, Our Days are Glooms, and from our Eyes Torrents of ever-flowing Sorrows burst. V. But what are Thrones or Monarchs sunk, Or Fields with Blood of Heroes drunk, Or Lords in barb'rous Climes confin'd! Ah! what are Lumps of breathing Clay, That into Ruin pine away, What, when compar'd with one immortal Mind VI. Th' immortal Mind! a heav'nly Spark, Lost and extinguish'd in the Dark! By Sin seduc'd, by Sin undone!— Let all superfluous Sorrows cease; And Deluges of Tears, for this, For this alone! gush forth and unremitted run! VII. Souls form'd for Immortality, Th' Eternal Father's Progeny, Forgetful of their noble Birth, Despise the Great Paternal Mind, So bright, so fair, so good, so kind, And loose their heav'nly Essence in ignoble Earth! VIII. Souls ransom'd by the vital Blood And Death of an incarnate God, Insult his dying Groans and Cries; And still, remorseless, dare commit The Sins that pierc'd His Hands and Feet, And rack'd his tortur'd Soul with twinging Agonies! IX. The mild, propitious, heav'nly Dove Desends from his own Realms of Love, To strive with unrelenting Souls: In vain;—the Rebels love their Chains, And Sin, the Tyrant, Sov'reign reigns, And ev'ry heav'nly Tendency controuls. X. The Voice of Mercy sounds aloud, And offers a Redeemer's Blood, Eternal Joys, and heav'nly Crowns: But still, with stiff unyielding Neck, The gracious Offer they reject, And rather perish of their mortal Wounds. XI. Eager with full Career they run In Chase of Pleasures, 'til undone, Nor pause at Mercy's loudest Call: Dancing with inadvertent Feet Round the dire Borders of the Pit, 'Til helpless, unexpected, down they fall. XII. There are (delightful Thought!) a Few Who the unbeaten Path pursue, That leads to purer Joys on high: Transporting Sight! but Oh! how rare! While mournful Prospects every where Glare on our Eyes, and Thousands round us die! XIII. And shall they unlamented die!— Come every tender Heart and Eye, Join in the Lamentation, join! From both my Eyes let Rivers flow, And Floods of sympathetic Woe Gush from this adamantine Heart of mine. XIV. Ye Sons of Levi! Sacred Train! That spend your Breath and Strength in vain, That toil and sow, but seldom reap; See thoughtless Mortals, in your Eye, Deaf to your loudest Warnings, die! Behold the mournful Scene, ye sacred Tribe! and weep! XV. See your dear Fellow-Men undone, While shock'd, astonish'd, you look on, But can, alas, yield no Relief! Yet sure you may indulge your Tears, And ev'n o'er those that stop their Ears, Vent your full Hearts in Streams of useless Grief. XVI. Come ev'ry tender-hearted Saint, Give all the mournful Passions vent, Or are your Bowels form'd of Stone? See how ungrateful Worms despise Jesus the Darling of your Eyes! See the dear Souls you love by their own Hands undone! XVII Ye gen'rous Souls! whose Bosoms bleed O'er some dear Creature cold and dead, Some dearer Self torn from your Heart; Forbear your useless Tears, and turn The Stream from them, and only mourn The cruel Hands that kill their own immortal Part. XVIII. Come all ye Sons of Adam, join; Mingle your flowing Griefs with mine; Let Groans tumultuous heave your Lungs. But you alas! refuse your Tears; And waste them on inferior Cares; Or lull yourselves to Ease with Luxury and Song. XIX. Angels! that charm the list'ning Skies With everlasting Harmonies, Say, Have Ye ne'er a mourning String? O! while your Songs transport the Poles, Raise one sad Note for Kindred-Souls, Your Kindred lost to you, revolted from your King! XX. Fountain of Day and cheerful Light Why should the Gloomy Sons of Night, The Radiance of thy Beams abuse? The Mourner's sable Dress assume, And wrap the Globe in Midnight Gloom, Why should they see the Light who Works of Darkness chuse? XXI. Ye Lamps of Heav'n that nightly burn, O'er brighter Flames extinguish'd mourn, As wakeful you survey the World. Regent of Night! Resplendent Moon! Bewail the Scenes of Lewdness done, While thro' the silver Shades thy ample Orb is whirl'd. XXII. Ye Winds that gently fan the Air, Or ravage in fierce Tempests there, Expend your Breath in Groans and Sighs: Disgusting Joys of heav'nly Kind, Immortal Spirits feed on Wind, And eager pant for airy Vanities. XXIII. Ye Thunders groan from Cloud to Cloud, Roar your majestic Sorrows loud, O'er Worms that scorn Jehovah's Voice. Tempests, and Hurricanes and Storms, Bewail in all your dreadful Forms, The more pernicious Storm that Human Kind destroys. XXIV. Ye Clouds that lightly float in Air, Or roll in heavy Oceans there, Weep on a wretched World below. Soft Dews and fruitful Show'rs, bewail Th' ungrateful Plants, that constant feel The Show'rs of Grace distil, but never fruitful grow. XXV. Ye Rivers rapid, rough and strong, And Streams that gently glide along, And in Meandrine Circuits flow; Exhaust in Tears your liquid Store, And murmur Grief; or swell and pour Your useless Chanels dry in Deluges of Woe. XXVI. And thou immense, majestic Main, Let not thy Billows roll in vain; But swell each Billow to a Tear: Mortals the Pleasures disesteem That roll their plenteous Chrystal Stream In Paradise; and thirst for sordid Pleasures here. XXVII. Sweet Mourner! melancholy Dove, And all ye Songsters of the Grove, Let tuneful Sorrows swell your Throats; You warble grateful Songs of Praise, And join with heav'nly Choirs to raise Your Maker's Name; but Mortals will not join the Notes. XXVIII. Ye fierce, rapacious Beasts of Prey, That in the horrid Desert stray, Thro' the rough Wild your Sorrows roar: Men put your Savage Natures on, Renounce the Mildness of their own, And Tyger-like, their Fellow-Men devour. XXIX. Ye Cattle that on Mountains feed, Or graze in the luxuriant Mead, Low forth your Sorrows as you roam: Lament the wretched Animal, Fashion'd by Nature rational, Degraded by himself, and one of you become. XXX. Let all Things mourn: Let Rocks and Stones Learn Sympathy, and burst to Groans, And senseless Marble learn to melt: Marble will weep, and Rocks relent Sooner than stubborn Hearts repent, And contrite wail their own oppressive Guilt. XXXI. O Thou All-Good, Paternal Mind! Pity the Crowds of Human Kind, Whose Hearts are hearden'd from Thy Fear. The Madness of the Wretch controul, Who ruins his immortal Soul, Without acute Remorse, without a pitying Tear. XXXII. Jesus! Thy tender Griefs did stream O'er Obstinate Jerusalem, Thy dying Breath implor'd “Forgive.” O! may Thy soft Compassions move, And Thy unconquerable Love Constrain a dying World to turn and live! XXXIII. Then shall the glad Creation smile, New Pleasures every Bosom fill, And Sin and Death and Sorrow die: Angels with sevenfold Ardours flame, And sound new Praises to Thy Name, While Mortals join below, and to their Song reply. XIII. The Aspiration. I. Eager, craving, hungry Soul, All thy loose Desires controul: Anxious, restless Spirit, cease To search inferior Skies for Bliss: Flutt'ring, panting, wild Desires, Recall, abate your sprightly Fires: Upward guide the quivering Flame, There unremitted let it glow: There purer Joys than Wealth or Fame, Lasting, satisfying, grow. II. Sparks with nat'ral upward Aim, Wheeling, quivering, still aspire, To mix with elemental Fire: Come then, active heav'n-born Flame, Hov'ring, trembling, restless Spark, Still twinkling, sparkling in the Dark, Heav'nward, Homeward active tend, And to thy Kindred Flames ascend. Conscious of thy superior Birth Generous spurn ignoble Earth; Exert thy Vigour, spring away To Regions of eternal Day: No more obscur'd in Glooms below, Soar with thy kindred Flames to glow. III. Where the blest Immortals shine, Brighten'd with Lustre all divine, Fir'd with heav'nly Life within, Active, vig'rous, never tir'd: Once they were struggling here below, Fainting, opprest, as thou art now; Yet to their native Element aspir'd. O! the Bliss, the Joy they feel! Raptures succeed to Raptures still, And in their Bosoms ever burn: Then my Soul with soaring Wing, To thy great Companions spring; Nor linger here to weep and mourn. XIV. The Soul early estranged from its Divine Parent. Father of Spirits! why, ah! why Should thy own Offspring be so shy? This Soul inspir'd by thee so late, Her bright Original forget? So soon forget her heav'nly Birth, And basely grovel in the Earth? But a few Years their Rounds have run, Since first my Infant-Life begun: 'Till then, in native Nothing's Shade I lay infinite Years unmade; And but for thy creating Will, Had slept in dreary Nothing still. “Let Nothing spring to Life,” Thy Tongue Pronounc'd, and straight to Life it sprung. Thou only art my Father, Thou My Author and Preserver too. Yet, Father! Thy own Progeny Was soon, alas! estrang'd from Thee: Cast forth to Earth's remote Abode, Forgot her Father, lost her God: Enslav'd to Flesh, and Lust and Sense, Reluctant to aspire from thence: With gilded Toys familiar grown, Her Father lost, unsought, unknown. Not so my Child: His Infant Tongue, Owns me the Parent whence he sprung: His little fondling Actions show What grateful Passions inward glow: Joying he rests in my Embrace, Or fondling round me smiles and plays: From real or imagin'd Harms, Flies for Protection to my Arms; And thus, with undesigning Tongue, Upbraids me of ungrateful Wrong. Ah! shall this Child return to me, A warmer Love than I to Thee! To Thee the universal Cause, Whence Nature her Existence draws. Thou gracious Author of my Frame, A wand'ring Prodigal reclaim. From glitt'ring Toys my Soul recall, To Thee her bright Original. Allure me to my Father's Arms By Thy own uncreated Charms. XV. A Survey of human Nature. The Introduction. While inconsiderate here I play The uncertain Trifle, Life, away, Let me indulge a solemn Hour, And view the Race of Adam o'er; On Contemplation's Pinions rove To Worlds below and Worlds above. What different Scenes around me rise! What different Prospects strike mine Eyes! What strange, what various Characters The self-same human Nature wears! I. Part. HEAVEN. See in the fair celestial Plains, Releas'd from Sin, and Death, and Pains, How, clad in Robes of Light Divine, Human Immortals glorious shine! The mean, inglorious Sons of Earth, With Angels of celestial Birth, On Ever-Green, in blissful Bow'rs, Pass their eternal social Hours. No more expos'd to lurking Snares, No more perplext with trifling Cares, No more the eager starving Mind Would feed on Vanity and Wind; But Chrystal Springs of Pleasure burst, And gently flow, and quench the Thirst. The Tree of Life luxuriant spreads Its fragrant Shade above their Heads; And shook with gentle Breezes, pours Its Fruits around in golden Show'rs. Still eager, still uncloy'd, the Blest Th' immortalizing Apples taste. Grim Death with all his ghastly Train Attempts to enter there in vain, Heart-bursting Groans and heaving Sighs No more attempt to swell and rise. But Oh! the higher Joys they feel! Immortal, pure, ineffable! While the bright Deity displays The unveil'd Glories of his Face: While, lost in Wonder still, they see The God that bled upon the Tree? Fir'd with immortal Transports rove O'er all the Wonders of his Love: Unweary'd the dear Theme pursue; Still view'd, yet still beyond their View: From Wonders still to Wonders rise, 'Til lost in vast Infinities: Dazzled with sweet Excess of Light, For strong Seraphic Eyes too bright. Their Knowledge brightens more and more; And what they know not, they adore. The high celestial Arches ring With Hallelujahs while they sing; The Hills, the Dales, the Fountains round With sweetest Harmony resound. Say, my bright kindred Spirits, say, Dare an Inhabitant of Clay, Direct his Hope and wishful Eye, To share with you in Joys on high? Hope in some humble Place to sit Amongst your Thrones, or at your Feet? Or does his flagrant Guilt deny Th' Ambition of a Wish so high? Once You, in dull Mortality, Were struggling and opprest, like me; Allur'd with tempting Vanities, And the false World's ensnaring Lies: Unruly Passions in your Hearts; Wounded with Satan's fiery Darts: Thro' thousand Dangers fought your Way; Trembling to fall a helpless Prey. Trembling to lose the glorious Prize, You now enjoy above the Skies. Say, Human Angels! by what Art Did you subdue th' unruly Heart? O'er the ensnaring World prevail, And all the Stratagems of Hell? O! tell me whence your Vict'ry came?— And was it from the bleeding Lamb!— Blest Jesus! be my Guide, my Strength; And I shall triumph too at length. O! did the Sons of Men below, The perfect Bliss above but know; O could they dart a piercing Eye Thro' the blue Curtains of the Sky; And view in what Perfection there Some of their Family All Mankind are represented in this Poem as one great Family; and Heaven, Earth, and the infernal Regions as so many Colonies, peopled by its wide Dispersions. appear; To what Degrees an human Mind, May be exalted and refin'd; How would they nobly soar, and spurn This Earth, and all its Trifles scorn; With brave Ambition Heav'nward aim, And all inferior Joys disclaim; Gen'rous break thro' the narrow Rounds Of Time and all created Bounds; Break thro', and wing'd with strong Desire, To pure celestial Joys aspire! But they, alas! with sordid Aim, All Kindred with the Skies disclaim: Ignobly sink the heav'n-born Mind To Pleasures of the brutal Kind. Rev. xii. 11. Eternal God! erect our Souls; Nor let them grovel here like Moles. O! teach a downward World to rise; And seek to gain their native Skies. II. Part. HELL. But Oh!—what dismal Scenes of Woe Open in yonder Gulph below! See! how the fiery Surges swell, And dash against the Cope of Hell. The sulph'rous undulating Flames Thro' the thick Gloom shed awful Gleams; Pale Gleams that but expose to Sight The Horrors of eternal Night. A Dungeon horrible, on all Sides round, As one great Furnace flam'd; yet from those Flames No Light, but rather Darkness visible Serv'd only to discover Sights of Woe.— Par. Lost. B. 1. l. 60. Ah! there, forever, ever lost, On these dire Billows ever tost, Some of my wretched Kindred roar, Feeling the Flames they scorn'd before. When Mercy call'd, they would not turn; Now Mercy frowns, and they must burn. Now Justice makes the Rebels feel The Tortures of the restless Wheel. Now nail'd to Racks of endless Pain, They cry for some Relief in vain. Deep Groans and Screams torment the Air, The horrid Language of Despair. The Vulture, Conscience, preys within; Once charming, now tormenting Sin In all her hellish Colours glares, And pays her Slaves the long Arrears For all the painful Drudgery done— Sad Wages! worse by far than none. Ah! how they writhe, and agonize! How wildly stare their flaming Eyes! No Heart can think, no Language tell, No Fancy paint the Pains they feel. Yet in their greatest Pains they own The Justice of th' Eternal Throne. “Justice! all Justice! still they cry; “By our own Folly here we lie. “Where should we lie but in this Pit, “Who made ourselves for Heav'n unfit? “Alas! should Heav'n her Gates display, “And take us to the Realms of Day; “We Sons of Darkness, back to Night “Would shrink, confounded with the Sight. “And in these Glooms make our Abode, “Rather than see a holy God. “While sinful Passions rule our Breast, “Not Heav'n itself can make us blest. “Impossible we should be sav'd, “While thus corrupted and deprav'd. “Nor do these raging Flames refine “Our Spirits from the Dross of Sin; “But still we harden in the Fire, “And still our Lusts new Strength acquire, “The Bliss we would not have, we lose; “And have the Portion that we chose.” O! did surviving Mortals know The Pains their Kindred feel below; O! did they know the dire Reward For all the Slaves of Sin prepar'd; How would they shrink from Vice's Charms, And thrust the Monster from their Arms! The smooth broad Road with Trembling shun, Where Thousands walk'd, and were undone! At the loud Call of Mercy stop, And eager catch the offer'd Hope! But all these real Terrors seem But frightful Tales and Dreams to them. Their Fellow-Sinners die around; They lay their Reliques in the Ground: The ghastly Corpse they only view, But Oh! could they the Soul pursue; Pursue her t'other Side of Death, To her eternal Home beneath; What Terrors would alarm the Heart! How would the thoughtless Sinner start! What Fear the Hypocrite surprize, And tear away his base Disguise! Or might abandon'd Ghosts again Visit the Earth, and talk with Men: Might they in human Ears proclaim The Torture of infernal Flame: In Characters majestic draw The Honours of th' insulted Law: Sin and its heavy Punishment In their infernal Colours paint: With flaming Tongues aloud expose, The crying scarlet Guilt of those Who dare neglect a dying God, And trifle with redeeming Blood: How would a sleeping World awake, And conscious Guilt confounded quake! Security should take th' Alarm, And shudder at th' impending Harm. Hardy Prophaneness learn to shrink; And thoughtless Luxury to think. Misers no more with Gold bewitch'd, Should damn themselves to be enrich'd. No more the Proud for empty Fame, Should sink in everlasting Shame. No more th' insulted Heavens should hear The dull Formality of Prayer; But flaming high, Devotion's Fire In Zeal importunate aspire. Spiritless Breath and languid Zeal No more eternal Truths reveal; Nor cold Harangues, or Trifles vain, The solemn Pulpit more prophane. The Thunders of the Law should sound, And hardy Sinners tremble round: Jesus allure with winning Charms Despairing Sinners to his Arms. So Fancy dreams.—But if the Law Fails to inspire a pious Awe, And even the Gospel cannot draw; In vain Apostles from the Dead Might Thunder Wrath, and urge and plead: In vain infernal Messengers Would try t' alarm presumptuous Ears. The trembling Fright would soon be o'er, And all ascrib'd to Fancy's Pow'r. Or frequent Apparitions grow Familiar, and be treated so. III. Part. EARTH. Now to the Earth I turn my Eyes: And strange! what diff'rent Prospects rise! Here Honour glitters, Riches shine, And Pleasure's various Forms combine: There meagre Poverty, Disgrace, And sullen Griefs usurp the Place. Here Health her blooming Visage shews Clad in the Lilly and the Rose: There Sickness groans and pines in Bed, And scarcely lifts his fainting Head. Here the unthinking jovial Crowd Dissolve in Mirth, and laugh aloud; While Music all her Charms employs To lull their Cares, and wake their Joys: But hark! how Melancholy moans, And solitary Sorrow groans, Here Luxury her Table spreads, And, squeamish, on her Dainties feeds: There Hunger gnaws, and starving Want Unpity'd vents his vain Complaint. Prophaneness lifts her impious Eyes, And mocks the Thunder of the Skies; Presumes with daring Tongue invoke The Vengeance of the ling'ring Stroke: While here and there a pious Sigh, And humble Pray'r ascend the Sky; Jehovah hears, and with a Smile Lays the dread Thunder by awhile. The Ways of Vice are still pursu'd By the triumphant Multitude; Sin high-applauded walks the Street, And tramples Virtue with his Feet Yet an unfashionable Few Virtue's untrodden Path pursue. These are the Pillars of the Land, And by their Pray'rs whole Nations stand, When they are gone, Wrath shall be hurl'd To blast and burn a guilty World. Some now receive the vital Breath Some gasping in the Pangs of Death, Some landing on th' eternal Shore, The Dangers of Life's Ocean o'er; While others ent'ring on the Stage Of Life, begin their youthful Age. The Conclusion. But who can tell the various Views, The various Projects Man pursues? The States, Conditions, Characters, In which Humanity appears? O! were our narrow Views more wide, Did human Race our Cares divide; The tender social Tear would rise; The social Bosom sympathize. The Heart of Charity would bleed, And round her gentle Influence shed. Benevolence would open wide The generous Wish, to none depy'd. Nay, Vice appal'd in her Career, Should feel Remorse and drop a Tear. Oppression break her Rod of Steel, And senseless Tyrants Pity feel. XVI. Whom have I in Heaven but Thee? And there is none upon Earth I desire besides Thee. My Flesh and my Heart faileth; but Thou art the Strength of my Heart, and my Portion forever. Ps. lxxiii. 25, 26. Fountain of Good! from Thee incessant flow The Streams of Bliss that cheer the World below. The Charms of Nature in her fairest Dress Are but faint Copies of Thy fairer Face. As some sweet Flow'r, when vernal Suns infuse The vegetative Soul, and fertile Dews, Impearl the Grass, its painted Foliage spreads, Blooms fair and gay, and fragrant Odours sheds; But when the Sun withdraws his genial Ray, Contracts its Beauties, droops and pines away: So at Thy Smiles, the wide Creation blooms; But should'st Thou frown, Horrors and dismal Glooms Would cover All; Deformity would reign; All Nature die, and Chaos come again. Unnumber'd Worlds, thro' boundless Æther lost, Are clad by Thee in all their Charms they boast. Impell'd by Thee, the mighty Spheres roll on, And Nature's ample Wheels harmonious run. Thy Glory twinkles thro' the Midnight Sky, From thousand Golden Lamps suspended high In azure Vaults. Yon' boundless Source of Day, That flames from Age to Age without Decay, That cheers surrounding Worlds with vital Rays, Is but a Gleam from Thee; whose brighter Face, Dazzles the Eyes of Angels as they gaze Who sit'st enthron'd, insufferably bright, In the Recesses of eternal Light. Thy Goodness in the vernal Seasons blooms; From Thee the Rose derives its rich Perfumes. By Thee the Groves are in their Verdure clad, And Plains and Vales with flow'ry Carpets spread. Eternal All! what is this lovely Frame But a faint Transcript of Thy glorious Name? The soft enchanting Smile, the sparkling Eye, The charming Voice, the Strains of Harmony, The graceful Conduct, the unbounded Aim Of noble Minds, the Patriot's gen'rous Flame, Th' exalted Genius, the celestial Fire Of Piety, Thy Spirit did inspire. 'Twas thou Fidelio form'd in Friendship's Mould, And stampt the social Virtues on his Soul; The candid Temper, and the Heart sincere, Thee their divine Original declare. When Chara, the Companion of my Life, The chastest, mildest, tenderest, kindest Wife; The Honour and the Beauty of her Sex; Whom every Grace and every Virtue decks: When she blooms on my Sight in all her Charms, And every correspondent Passion warms; I farther look; and thro' this radiant Glass Gaze on the brighter Beauties of thy Face. Thus Mortals read some Letter of thy Name, On every Pin in this amazing Frame: View some reflected Beams of Charms Divine Break thro' Thy Works, and with bright Radiance shine. But O! how far the loveliest Creatures fall Beneath th' immensely bright Original! Thou Excellence unknown, divinely fair! Shew us what uncreated Beauties are. Reveal THYSELF! Let trembling Mortals see Th' unrival'd Glories that beam forth in Thee. The borrow'd Beauties of Thy Works but raise The restless Pant to view Thy brighter Face; But warms the eager Wish, that breaks thro' all The Ranks of Creatures to th' Original: But O! 'tis Thou, 'tis Thou alone canst fill The boundless Wish, and bid the Pant be still. Without Thee, every Charm insipid grows, And the aspiring Soul finds no Repose. In Quest of Thee she flies; in Quest of Thee Roves thro' the Mazes of Immensity, Restless, bewilder'd. O my only Joy! Reveal Thyself; these Cravings satisfy: Fill this unbounded Void; nor let me more For solid Bliss created Bounds explore. Oh! if Thy Goodness will not satisfy These boundless Aims, why were they rais'd so high? Why was I curs'd with this immortal Mind, This Dignity of Thought, these Pow'rs refined; O! why, if Thou wilt ever, ever hide Thyself, and leave them still unsatisfy'd? Far better had I flourish'd for a Day A fading Flow'r beneath the quick'ning Ray Of vernal Suns; or with my Fellow-Brutes Roam'd o'er the trackless Waste in low Pursuits, Graz'd the green Mead, or unmolested lain, And stretch'd my careless Bulk in some wild Den, Sleeping dull Life away; nor fear'd my Doom From Evil past, or present or to come. O envy'd Lot to mine! if I must pass My Immortality far from Thy Face; Whether on Earth, in Air, or Heaven I dwell, If Thou art absent, every Place is Hell. Advance me to the Grandeur of a Throne, And let me call the Universe my own; Let Planetary Worlds my Nod obey, And Earth and Ocean reverence my Sway: Yet, if depriv'd of Thy auspicious Smile, I shall be curst, abandon'd, wretched still. Let Heaven her sparkling Portals wide display. And take me to the Realms of endless Day; Angelic Harps their sweetest Notes employ. And round me Rivers flow of heav'nly Joy; My Soul would sicken at the hateful Sight, If hid from Thee, sole Spring of my Delight! The Light offensive to my Eyes would glare, And heavenly Notes grate harsh upon my Ear. But if refresh'd with Thy propitious Face, My Soul would find a Heav'n in ev'ry Place. Thy Presence would eternal Pains beguile, And cause the Realms of Desolation smile. A Beam from Thee would kindle into Light The solid Glooms of everlasting Night; Not even infernal Horrors could affright. O! then, where e'er Thou fix my last Abode, Be it in Reach of Thy sweet Smiles, my God! Be Thou my Portion, Thou my Bliss, my All; I care not to whose Share the Creatures fall; I have enough in Thee, th' immense Original. XVII. Conjugal Love and Happiness. February 27, 1750–1. Conjugal Love my joyful Heart inspires, And warms a languid Muse with active Fires. The pleasing Impulse the glad Muse obeys; And as a pious Monument of Praise, Grateful she consecrates these humble Lays. Nor can she stray in trackless Wilds unknown; Since to describe the Bliss, I need but tell my own. But hence! far hence! ye wild lascivious Fires; To purer Themes the modest Muse aspires, Hence banish'd, to your native Hell return! There with your loose degen'rate Bards to mourn; There with your kindred Flames to rage and burn. Hail, gentle Love! thou sacred Heaven-born Flame! Pure Spark, that from th' eternal Godhead came! Who clad in Glories infinitely bright, Does in this mild Perfection most delight; In Love rejoices as this darling Name, 1 John, iv. 8. Psalm clxv. 9. And breathes thro' Nature the celestial Flame. 'Tis Love adjusts this fair harmonious World; On Wheels of Love the heavenly Spheres are whirl'd, Ten Thousand Systems round Ten Thousand Suns, Impell'd by Love, each in its Orbit runs. What's the Attractive or Projectile Force, But Love well-ballanc'd, to direct their Course? Love, the great Cement of the Universe, That hinders Worlds to conflict and disperse. 'Tis Love that tunes th' harmonious Harps above; And the blest Voices sing immortal Love. There in its native Element it glows; There from the uncreated Fountain flows, Diffusing Heav'n where e'er its Current goes. Of firm Societies Love form'd the Plan, “And Creature linkt to Creature, Man to Man.” Blest the rude World with Friendship, downy Peace, And humaniz'd a wild, barbarian Race. The kindest Gift indulgent Heaven bestow'd, To sweeten Life, and ease the crushing Load; To sooth Anxieties, to lull to Rest The Hurricanes that ravage thro' the Breast; To double scanty Bliss, and multiply The rare celestial Plants of Peace and Joy, So apt in this unnat'ral Soil to die. Could Hell extinguish this celestial Spark, The Universe would fall, the Sun grow dark; Infernal Horrors thro' the World prevail: And Heaven itself would sadden into Hell: Men chang'd to Savages, forsake their Home, And with fell Tygers, the wild Desart roam: The screaming Infant die as soon as born, By his own Father's Rage to Pieces torn. But Thou, All-gracious Maker! hast imprest This heav'nly Stamp upon the human Breast; Mixt in the tender Embryo of our Frame, Some gentle Sparks of Thy essential Flame. O! early may the sacred Fire return To Thee its Source, and there divinely burn! Ev'ry soft Passion to Thy Name aspire, And Love to Thee the whole Creation fire! But chiefly, may thy Praises be exprest, By those whom gentle Love has rendered blest! Ye Parents, whose kind Bowels melt and move With all th' Endearments of paternal Love; Who feel the silken Bands of Nature tye Your yearning Souls to your fond Progeny; O! praise Him, who a feeble Spark imparts Of his paternal Kindness to your Hearts. Ye grateful Infants, whose young Souls begin To feel the soft Emotions work within; In thousand little fondling Actions shew The filial Duty that begins to glow; O! while you toy in your fond Mother's Arms, Lisp to his Honour who your Bosom warms: O! consecrate th' imperfect rude Essays Of your first Language, to your Maker's Praise. Ye Youths and Nymphs, who feel the pleasing Flame Pant in your Breast, and throb thro' all your Frame; Who lost in anxious, pleasing Transports prove The charming wild Extravagance of Love; Let human Beauties claim their proper Share, But Oh! supremely love the Everlasting Fair! Friendship, thou sacred Name! may every Mind Whom thy soft Fetters in sweet Bondage bind; Who melted into Union coalesce, And but one Joy, one Grief, one Life possess; O may their warmest Gratitude ascend In Extasies to their celestial Friend! Praise Him, ye happy Pairs, who no more sigh For absent Bliss, but all your Wish enjoy: Your Hands conjoin'd, cogenial Souls commixt; And not a jealous Thought intrudes betwixt; While mutual Confidence, and Peace serene Smile in your Looks, and still the Storms within: Your mutual Virtues mutual Wants supply; Your Burden shar'd, and multiply'd your Joy; Adore His Name who join'd two kindred Souls, And fashion'd you in correspondent Moulds. Connubial Love! thrice happy was the Hour I fell a willing Captive to thy Pow'r. Opprest I panted underneath my Load, While I a single Individual stood: But, Chara, since with thee I coalesc'd, And join'd thee to my maim'd imperfect Breast, I grew into a finish'd Man, compleat, And hardly feel the huge unwieldy Weight— So when a marble Pillar singly tries To bear the Weight of some vast Edifice, The Pillar trembles, and the tott'ring Wall Horrendous nods, and threats a thund'ring Fall. But if the prudent Architect bestows A Set of Columns in proportion'd Rows, The Building stands indissolubly firm, And mocks the blust'ring Hurricane and Storm. Nor will my other Self refuse to own She finds her Soul to perfect Stature grown, And two conjoin'd but make a finish'd One The rougher Virtues of a manly Mind With her more tender female Virtues join'd, Form a well-temper'd Compound.—So unite The Glooms of Black, and the mild Streaks of White, And form a well-mix'd Picture, pleasing to the Sight. The Mildness of her Temper seem'd to court Masculine Boldness for its kind Support; Unfit, alone, t' avert impending Harms, And face Life's Terrors and outragious Storms.— So creeps the noble Vine along the Ground, When no supporting Elm is near her found. No gen'rous Clusters her rich Boughs adorn, Smother'd with noxious Weeds and overborn. But place some kind Support within her Reach, Her marriageable Arms you'll see her stretch; Round the rough Trunk with loving Tendrils twine, And bloom on high, a fair prolific Vine. Chara, beneath thy Influence I felt The charming Flame; my Soul was taught to melt In Extasies unknown, and soon began To put the Stoic off, and soften into Man. The Veil of Modesty, in vain confin'd Th' alluring Beauties of thy lovely Mind: The shining Charms beam'd thro' the fair Disguise; Blush'd in thy Aspect, dazzled in thy Eyes; In every Word, in all thy Conduct known. And in thy artless Face, well-copy'd, shone— So thro' refulgent Clouds breaks the bright Morning Sun. I saw, I lov'd, I sought to gain, The blooming Fair; nor sought in vain. Thy yielding Bosom soon began to glow With the same Flame thy Charms taught me to know. Thy Soul, unskill'd in those inhumane Arts, Thy Sex affect to torture captive Hearts, A constant Lover did disdain to vex, Or with unkind Delays and treach'rous Wiles perplex. Thy Soul, that knew not what dissembling meant, With modest soft Reluctance, blush'd Consent. In Transport lost the joyful News I heard; And vow'd my Life the Favour to reward. A solemn Rite the willing Contract seal'd, To stand, 'til Death divide us, unrepeal'd. 'Twas gracious Heav'n presided o'er our Choice— Come, Chara, then, assist my grateful Voice. To Thee, Great God! to Thee alone we owe This mutual Bliss, this Paradise below. And dost Thou, Sovereign Ruler of the Spheres! Stoop down to Worms, and manage our Affairs! Thou, in Whose Sight Arch-Angels are but Nought, And highest Heav'n beneath Thy meanest Thought! Compar'd with Whom, ten thousand Worlds appear But Vanity, unworthy of Thy Care! Oh! what are we, or what our Father's House, That Thou should'st condescend so low to us, And with peculiar Favours crown us thus! 2 Sam. vli. 18. O! never, never be Thy Grace forgot That destin'd for us a distinguish'd Lot. While wretched Thousands, form'd of diff'rent Clay. In nuptial Fetters fret their Days away; Jangle and murmur in eternal Strife, And gnaw'd with Jealousies consume their Life; In mutual Love, in mutual Confidence, Unconscious of Suspicion or Offence, In Fondness, Peace and melting Tenderness, The calm unclouded Day of Life was pass: Pitying survey the angry jarring World, Contentious, loud, in boist'rous Passions whirl'd: Then into sweet Society retire, And find the peaceful Calm our Souls desire. Love charms the Heart, and in the Aspect smiles, Our anxious Griefs and fretting Cares beguiles; Doubles our Pleasures, while th' impartial Scale Of Sympathy divides the Woes we feel. Thus over Life's tempestous Sea we sail, When Storms blow fierce, and the rough Surges swell; With equal Hands ply the tough yielding Oar, And fly triumphant to the wish'd-for Shore. O! may our Days, Eternal God! be Thine; And every Passion yield to Love Divine. Oh! in our Hearts still do Thou reign supreme; Nor let us steal the Love thy Glories claim. But here, ah! here a guilty Scene appears!— Oh! break my senseless Heart, and flow my Tears! How manifold and strange my Frailties be! Chara, I find Temptations ev'n in thee! When fondly in thy loving Arms I rest, And thy resistless Charms enflame my Breast, The pleasing Tempter seizes all my Heart, Or leaves my God but the inferior Part. Almighty Grace! th' Extravagance controul Of this unruly Pow'r that captivates my Soul. From all created charms my Heart recall, To the all-perfect Fair, th' Eternal all! My lovely Chara! help me to restrain The wild Excesses of the Love you gain. With Horror, shun the sacrilegious Theft, And tho' I give, yet Oh! refuse the Gift. Far from my Breast expell each human Fair; But Oh! let Jesus reign unrivall'd there: Jesus! Thou sacred and unrivall'd Name! My warmest Love thy matchless Glories claim. Ah! shall this Spark Thy Spirit did inspire, From Thee, its Origin, my Heart ensnare! No! Claim my tend'rest Passions for Thy own; Or tear them from my Heart, and change me into Stone. Another pleasing Scene, my Muse, disclose— Love multiply'd in blooming Branches grows. These smiling Infants with a thousand Arts To fond parental Love dissolve our Hearts. In our fond Arms the pretty Triflers toy, And overwhelm us with oppressive Joy. Young Reason blooms, and shews its tender Flow'rs, And importunes Instruction's gentle Show'rs. Delightful Task! to rear the tender Thought; To teach the young Idea how to shoot; To form the pliant Mind in Virtue's Mould, Before it hardens, and stiff Vice grows old. Eternal God! to whom ourselves we owe, To Thee we dedicate our Offspring too. O! may Thy Conduct guide them o'er the Stage Of slipp'ry Youth to Manhood's sob'rer Age; And if Thou crown their Heads with hoary Hairs, May they devote to Thee their aged Years; Proclaim Thy Praise, when we resign our Breath, And lie forgotten in the Dust of Death. Then in Thy kind Embraces let them die, And people the celestial Colony. Chara, thou dear Partaker of my Heart, The Hour approaches, when ev'n we must part: We tho' in strongest Bonds of Union join'd, Must feel the painful Rupture of the Mind. When on the Bridal Day I took thy Hand, And clasp'd thee to me in the nuptial Band, This Thought did mod'rate my Excess of Joy, “Resistless Death this Union will destroy: “This spendid Jewel must not still be mine; “But cruel Fate will force me to resign.” I shudder at the Prospect!—Ah! my Dear, How could I leave you solitary here! Leave you, like the poor widow'd Dove, to mourn, Opprest with Cares, in the wide World forlorn! With all the Mother yearning in your Breast, To see your helpless Orphan-Babes distrest! Methinks I see you weeping o'er my Clay, And drown'd in Sorrow, my pale Corpse survey; “There all my Comfort, all my Joy lies dead, (You cry) “Each smiling Prospect now is fled. “My Love, alas! was impotent to save “The Man I lov'd from the all-conquering Grave. “To Thee, Great God! the Widow's Friend, I flee: “I've no Support, no Refuge now, but Thee.” Methinks I see you sad and solemn tread The Place where I lie mould'ring 'mong the Dead “Here the dear Reliques lie, the Dust lies here,” You say, and sob, and drop a tender Tear, “The Dust of that dear Man, who once possest “My Soul, whom these fond Arms have oft embrac'd. “Here silent, senseless, now he lies; nor hears “His Chara's Sighs, nor minds her flowing Tears.” O Chara! could the iron Bands of Death Be bursted, and its Slaves resume their Breath; Thy Sorrows would revive my mould'ring Clay, And Death's eternal Stupor drive away. My senseless Dust with thee would sympathize, And spring to Life to wipe thy streaming Eyes. But ah! the Tyrant Death will not dismiss His Captives, nor grant one poor Hour's Release. Yet now at least my pitying Tears can flow, In Prospect of th' approaching Scenes of Woe, And now anticipate the Sympathy I owe. Your Griefs at my own Funeral I share, And since I cannot then, now drop a Tear. But Oh! the Prospect overwhelms my Minds— I cannot, cannot leave my Fair behind. No!—Hear, Indulgent Heav'n! this humble Pray'r; “Let her net mourn for me, but me for her! “Doom me to live to close her dying Eyes, “And see her struggling in Death's Agonies. “The pale cold Clay with last Embraces clasp, “And from her Lips receive th' expiring Gasp. “Attend her Reliques to her clay-cold Bed, “And o'er her Grave my dewy Sorrows shed. “In pensive Solitude oft thither rove, “To view the Mansion of the Dust I love. “In melancholy Crape myself array, “And darken with the Pomp of Grief the Day. “Thus mourn away the sad Remains of Life, “'Til friendly Death restore me to my Wife.”— Ah no! ah no! Kind Heav'n! refuse to hear; Nor curse me with the Answer of my Pray'r. My Heart would break, my Spirit faint away, To see my Chara pallid lifeless Clay. To hear the Clods with hollow murm'ring Sound Fall on thy Coffin, would my Soul confound. And when th' important, solemn Hour draws nigh, When I must bow my fainting Head and die, How could I face the Terrors, if thou wert not by? May I expire in thy kind Arms embrac'd, And Guardian Angels take me from thy Breast, And guide my Soul to everlasting Rest! May thy dear Voice some cheering Thought suggest, And teach me on my Saviour's Arm to rest, Whisper some Promise from the sacred Writ, That thro' Death's Glooms may dart a cheerful Light. Above for thee I'll wait, 'til gentle Fate Waft up thy Soul, and make our Bliss compleat. But here again the dismal Views return,— I see my Chara pine and weep and mourn. The moving Sight my Spirit cannot bear; And here again I must retract my Pray'r. Straiten'd, perplext, I know not what to crave, A longer Life than she, or earlier Grave. Propitious Heav'n! direct my doubtful Vow, And what is best, ask'd or unask'd, bestow. Thus the best Blessing does perplexing prove; These are the wild Anxieties of Love. The senseless Stoic seeks the Bliss in vain, 'Tis true—but then, he pines not with the Pain. His little Self is all his narrow Care, And all his Fears and Wishes center there. But this fond Soul with various Passions tost, Is in a Maze of Contradictions lost. Now could I almost wish from Love to flee, And harden into quiet Apathy. But Oh! is there no Cure, no heav'nly Art To ease this twinging Anguish of my Heart? To arm this coward Soul, and make her smile At all the Terrors of approaching Ill? To teach these Spectres no more to affright, That stalk in future Time's impenetrable Night? O yes there is!—My anxious Soul be still; Calmly submit to Heav'n's all-ruling Will. His Will be done! Refuse to chuse thy Lot; And leave that Trust to His unerring Thought. He rules unnumber'd Worlds with Skill Divine; And can't He rule these mean Affairs of thine? What's best for us, His Wisdom only knows; And what is best, His boundless Grace bestows. Here will I rest: And here, my Chara too, Appears a Rock in every Storm for you. But Nature, perverse Nature, will rebel, And o'er my calm and settled Thoughts prevail. The rising Waves will dash me from my Rock; And all my firmest Resolutions shock. Father! forgive these Ravings of my Love; These lawless Passions that rebellious rove. O! to this Fondness proper Limits set, And its Extravagancies regulate. If my wild Pen one guilty Word has writ, Pity my Weakness, and that Word remit. Be Thou my Bliss, be Thou my All, in Life; My Strength, my Comfort, in the dying Strife. If 'tis Thy Will that I should pine alone, Bereft of Chara, may Thy Will be done! Or if I first relapse to native Dust, And leave her here to mourn, Thy Will is just. Thy Right it is, the Knot Thy Hands have ty'd When, where, and as Thou pleasest, to divide. Yet O! forgive Thy Servant if he speaks, And Dust and Ashes this one Prayer makes: If Thou consent, thankful before Thy Feet I fall! if not, I'm silent and submit. “O! may we both at once resign our Breath, “And sink together in the Arms of Death. “One humble Tomb preserve our mingling Dust, “'Til the all-rousing Trump demand the Trust. “Conducted by one heav'nly Convoy rise. “And soar together to the upper Skies. “There in eternal Union praise Thy Name, “And Love Divine our mingled Souls enflame.” Chara, this humble Monument I raise Of our fond Passion, in my youthful Days; That if you're doom'd the mournful Day to view, When I shall cease to speak or write to you; When my dull Muse shall silent lie in Death, Or in celestial Strains employ her tuneful Breath; To still, or rather vent your Griefs, you may With gushing Eyes these tender Lines survey, And as you pore upon them, sigh and say, “Well; once I had a Friend, whose loving Soul “Did antedate these Sorrows to condole; “That early wail'd my then uncertain Doom, “And mourn'd in Prospect what I mourn as come. Or if grim Death first tear you from my Breast; And waft you earlier to eternal Rest; I may at least enjoy that poor Relief, To find a Help to vent my bursting Grief, To raise the Sluices of o'erwhelming Woe, That Deluges of easing Tears may flow. But Oh! why does the cruel Muse repose So early, Treasures for our future Woes? Nor you nor I can then endure to view These sad Predictions then so sadly true. Again perplext, I wish my Work undone; But the resistless Passion push'd me on. I doom these dire Predictions to the Fire; Yet would the sad Accomplishment appear; Therefore I check my Ravings, and forbear. XVIII. The Messiah's Kingdom. Extracted out of the Prophet Isaiah This Poem is intended as a Supplement to Mr. Pope's Divine Eclogue, entituled Messiah: and therefore I have frequently borrowed his Lines with the usual Marks of Quotation, on such Verses as he has touched upon, tho' sometimes with small Variation or Addition. Descend, Celestial Dove! my Voice inspire O thou that tipt Isaiah's Tongue with Fire! Isai. vi. 6, 7. Teach me like him to feel th' extatic Flame, And raise my Numbers equal to my Theme. “Rapt into future Times, the Bard begun,— “A Virgin shall conceive, a Virgin bear a Son.” Ch. vii. 4. His Names Divine His Dignity declare! Immanuel, the wondrous Counseller, Th' eternal Father, the pacific Prince, The God arm'd with His own Omnipotence. Ch. ix. 6. Th' eternal Spirit shall profusely shed His richest Unction on his sacred Head: Wisdom and Knowledge, Piety and Might Descend, and on His sacred Temples light. Ch. xi. 2. The radiant Beam of His all-piercing Eyes Shall dart thro' lurking Frauds obstruse Disguise. Sly Hypocrites with all their artful Shews On His Omniscience try in vain t'impose. Coll. xi. 3. His Shoulders shall the Government sustain, And He triumphant o'er the Nations reign. His growing Empire o'er the World extend, And know no Bounds but Nature's utmost End. C. ix. 7. To this illustrious Ensign, high in Air, The numerous Tribes of Adam shall repair: Thither the Gentiles with unwearied Feet Shall tend, and there in endless Armies meet; With the Messiah's peaceful Conduct blest, Shall, undisturb'd enjoy eternal Rest. C. xi. 10. The scatt'red Remnant of the sacred Stock, Shall to their own Messiah's Standard flock; With eager Haste in endless Orders crowd From foreign Climes and barb'rous Servitude. v. 11. Impartial Justice shall erect her Scale, And weak, insulted Innocence prevail: The Meek, the Poor defy impending Harm, And smile secure beneath His Guardian Arm. v. 4. Eternal Righteousness shall rule the Globe, The glorious Girdle of His royal Robe. v 5. and Ch. ix. 7. Confusion, Anarchy, with wild Dismay, Shall fly afar from his well ordered Sway: Serene and steady his Affairs shall run In calm, harmonious Order ever on. ibid. Nor shall His Reign those Revolutions know That toss the petty Monarchies below; But while eternal Years their Circuits run, Triumphant He shall sit on David's Throne. ibid. Soft Peace shall bloom in His auspicious Reign; The Olive flourish in eternal Green. Ch. ix. 7. He into Peace the jarring World shall look, And still their Contests with his dread Rebuke: The jarring World, obedient to His Eye, Shall lay their useless martial Weapons by. The bloody Sword new form'd shall learn to plow, And mortal Spears to Pruning-Hooks shall bow; No more shall Fields drink in heroic Gore, Nor brazen Trumpets kindle Fury more, Nor deadly War with usual Thunder roar. Ch. iii 4. The Tribes that savage and rapacious rove In Quest of Prey, shall soften into Love; And weary of their former sullen Joy, Shall in the sacred Mount no more destroy, “The Lambs with Wolves shall graze the verdant Mead. “And Boys in flow'ry Bands the Tyger lead. “The Steer and Lion at one Crib shall meet, “And harmless Serpents lick the Pilgrim's Feet. “The smiling Infant in his Hand shall take, “The erected Basilisk, and speckled Snake; “Pleas'd the green Lustre of the Scales survey, “And with their forky Tongue and pointless Sting shall play.” The proud Rebuke, the big insulting Frown Shall on the smiling Earth no more be known. “No Sigh, no Murmur the wide World shall hear; “From every Face He wipes off every Tear.” C. xxv. 8. Then shall the Earth, the Air, the Sea, the Sky Eccho with Praise and grateful Harmony. To thee Jehovah! every Tongue shall sing; And with loud Praise the wide Creation ring. Tho' late Thy Wrath did with dread Fury glow, The Flame is quench'd, and now Thy Mercies flow. The Hand that wounded, now affords Relief, And endless Joy succeeds to transient Grief. C. xii. 1. Behold a God vouchsafes to be my Aid! Why should I, thus protected, be afraid? Th' Omnipotent becomes my Strength and Guard, And His Salvation my immense Reward. Therefore my Tongue, the Glory of my Frame, Exulting shall His grateful Praise proclaim. My Soul with lib'ral Draughts be satisfy'd, Where living Streams of pure Salvation glide: In parched Desarts copious Streams shall burst, And flow, and quench the Pilgrim's raging Thirst. v. 3. Then various Tongues shall say with one Accord, Come jointly let us praise th' Almighty Lord; With reverent Lips invoke His awful Name, And round th' astonish'd World His wond'rous Works proclaim. Let thousand Tongues with glad Submission own, Jehovah reigns exalted on his Throne; v. 4. Let thousand Voices in loud Accents sing The vast Exploits of the eternal King; Exploits to Earth's remotest Limits known, Vast as his Power, and boundless as his Throne. v. 5. As some besieged City, when they spy Their kind Deliverer's welcome Flag draw nigh, With Shouts triumphant stun the ecchoing Skies, And shock the Courage of their Enemies: So sacred Zion! with exulting Voice, Shout loud thro' Heav'n and Earth thy boist'rous Joys; For great in Majesty, and great in Arms, Clad in fair Holiness with all its Charms, Great in the Midst of thee Jehovah reigns, And the fierce Rage of hostile Pow'r restrains. v. 6. Thy Arm, Great God! has levell'd to the Ground Proud Cities that proclaim'd Defiance round; Ch. xii. 2. Laid in rude Heaps the strong aspiring Tow'r, And Palaces to be repair'd no more. C. xxv. 2. These mighty Works convey'd on Wings of Fame, Shall teach the World to reverence Thy Name. Conqu'rors shall lay their Laurels at Thy Feet, And savage Nations tremble and submit. v. 3. Tyrants shall feel the Terror of his Rod, And own, reluctant, a superior God. Oppression, blasted with his vengeful Breath, Wither and sink in everlasting Death; Thro' Rebel Crowds the Terror of his Word Shall pierce resistless like a griding Sword. C. xi. v. 4. Aspiring Mortals! hide you in the Rock From the majestick Terror of His Look: Into the Dust, abas'd, confounded sink, And struck with Awe from his dread Presence shrink. C. ii. 10. The supercilious Look, the lofty Brow, The stubborn Haughtiness of Man shall bow; And in that Day th' unnutterable Name, Shall reign unrivall'd on His Throne supreme. v. 11. The proud, aspiring Monarchs of the World Shall from their fancy'd Dignity be hurl'd. v. 12. His vengeful Thunder with destructive Strokes Shall rend and blast proud Bashan's sturdy Oaks, The stately Cedars of Libanus scathe, And blend their Fragments with the Shrubs beneath. v. 13. The tow'ring Mountains and aspiring Hills Adoring fall and sink to humble Vales. v. 14. The Tow'r impregnable, the fenced Wall Crumble to Dust, and with loud Ruin fall v. 15. The Ships of Tarnish, fraught with golden Store, Founder in the rough Deep and float no more. v. 16. Struck with the Terror of Jehovah's Look, Aspiring Worms shall creep into the Rock; To gloomy Clefts and Caves, with wild Dismay, From His majestic Presence shrink away, When He with Terror shall Himself enrobe, And rises to affright the trembling Globe. Ch. ii. 17. With pious Boasts then shall th' insulted Just Proclaim the Issue of their patient Trust. Ye impious Scoffers of our Patience, see! Our God appears! th' Incarnate Deity! Our God appears! for Him, for Him we sought; And lo! our patient Tears are not forgot. This is our God! and lo! the God appears! Exult our Hearts! and flow no more our Tears! Salvation on this glad Approach attends, And grants the largest Wishes of his Friends. Ch. 25. 9. Here shall Omnipotence itself exert, And His right Hand shall never hence depart: With wrathful Majesty His Feet shall tread On Zion's Foes, and Heaps of hostile Dead; Insult the Rebels prostrate struck with Awe; So heavy Oxen tread the rotting Straw. v. 10. Then shall He scatter the dark Glooms of Hell, And from benighted Nations tear the Veil, The universal Veil that now excludes The cheerful Light from groping Multitudes. v. 7. So bright a Glory shall He dart around, The dazzling Deluge shall the Sun confound, Absorpt and lost in the superior Light, The Sun shall hide his Face, in everlasting Night: The Moon confounded, thro' the midnight Shade Shall gleam no more, nor feeble Radiance spread. v. 23. For as th' accumulated Waters crowd Th' unbounded Deep, old Ocean's vast Abode; Th' unbottom'd Cavity compactly fill With Waves on Waves, Billows on Billows still: So shall the Dawn of bright celestial Light O'erflow the World, and banish ancient Night; Thro' thickest Glooms of Ignorance shall pierce, And dart its Lustre round the Universe. Ch. xi. 9. The wretched Tribes that walk in Death's dark Shade, With Clouds of Ignorance and Guilt o'erspread, Observe the heavenly Ray, with glad Surprize, Dart thro' the hideous Gloom and bless their Eyes. Ch. ix. 2. (Not so the Tribes beneath the Artic Bear, Immur'd in Ice and Darkness half the Year, Rejoice to see the Stranger-Sun appear.) With brighter Splendors fir'd, the languid Moon Shall shine the Rival of the Noon-day Sun; The Noon-day Sun with sevenfold Lustre glow, And seven Days Eight at once the World o'erflow. Ch. xxx. 26. The heav'nly Branch from Jesse's sacred Root, To bless the World shall germinate and shoot; See clad in vernal Beauty, how it blooms! And breathes among the Nations rich Perfumes: Blest with its Fruit th' expiring World revives, And Death avoids the Fragrance of its Leaves. Ch. xi. 1. O'ercome with sultry Heat, the fainting Head, Reclin'd beneath its fragrant cooling Shade, Shall fresh returning Life and Vigour feel, And in the Blaze of Noon himself regale. When ruptur'd Clouds in rapid Torrents burst, And rush o'erwhelming with outragious Gust, The verdant Shelter guards the Tempest off, That raves in vain around the arb'rous Roof. Ch. iv. 6. As with a Cloud Thou dost the Earth regale, When Noon-day Beams and scorching Suns prevail; Ch. vxv. 5. As cooling Streams in barren parched Lands Refresh the Trav'ler on the burning Sands; As some great Rock with its propitious Shade Protects from piercing Beams the drooping Head; Ch. xxxii. 2. So shall Thy Grace relieve the helpless Poor, When round them Crowds of hostile Strangers roar; Ch. xxv. 5. Their fiercest Rage shall ineffectual fall Like Blasts that ravage round a brazen Wall. The Lord of Armies shall his Table spread On Zion Mount, and famish'd Nations feed; With heav'nly Dainties form the sumptuous Feast, Where luscious Marrow shall delight the Taste; The gen'rous Grape her vig'rous Juice bestow And vet'ran Wine in copious Rivers flow; Wine well refin'd, extracted from the Lees. Season'd by Time, and ripen'd fit to please. Th' expiring World shall take what He prepares, Appease their Hunger and renew their Years. v. 6. On barren Wastes th' eternal Spirit pours His sacred Influence in prolific Show'rs; The Desart flourishes a fruitful Field, And verdant Groves adorn the horrid Wild. Ch. xxxii. 15. The Desert blossoms like the fragrant Rose, And there sweet Leb'non's flow'ry Beauty glows. Ch. xxxv. 1. There a new Sharon breathes its sweet Perfumes, Fresh Lilies spring, and sudden Verdure blooms. v. 2. “The Trav'ler starts amidst the Wilds to hear “New Falls of Water murm'ring in his Ear.” v. 6, 7. Thro' the wide Wastes eternal Justice reigns, And Judgment blooms thro' all the dismal Plains; Ch. xxxii. 16. Celestial Splendors from the Source Divine Thro' the sad Realms of Desolation shine. Ch. xxxv. 2. The barren Rocks, the bleak unwater'd Hills Shall with irriguous Streams refresh the Vales; From parched Mountains copious Rivers flow, And on their barren Peaks eternal Verdure grow! Ch. xxx. 24, 25. Surprizing Event! yet we rest assur'd; A God, a God has spoke the solemn Word; Even jealous Unbelief shall own it true, For what his Lips declare His Pow'r can do. Ch. xxv. 8. XIX. ???? Or, The invisible World. Proud Mortal! to what narrow Bounds confin'd Are the most ample Prospects of his Mind! Impenetrable Mists and Clouds surround His Reason, and its boasted Pow'rs confound. He roves, tho' fixt to this contracted Spot, In all th' Extravagance of boundless Thought. Behind, Before, from the precarious Now, (His only Time) he turns his eager View. Behind, Eternity's unbounded Main Extends infinite Lengths beyond his Ken, Before, the same vast Ocean swells again. Our Time is but a little floating Isle; For wide Discoveries we look round and toil, In vain; the Isle lies wrapt in thickest Glooms, Where scarce a Gleam of shining Knowledge comes. If back we turn our Eyes, we only see 'Twas some Almighty Pow'r gave us To Be; Some bright Invisible, some great Unknown Spoke us to Life But a few Years agone. Whate'er Thou art, Thou Dear Unknown! receive The humble Praise and Love Thy Offspring aims to give; For O! Thy innate Glories must outshine Their fairest Copies in these Works of Thine. Duration, ere that Hour, a Blank appears; We're lost in Mazes of unbounded Years. A thousand Contradictions press us round, And our unequal Faculties confound. Yet thro' the vast Obscure, we see and own The Maker reign'd on His eternal Throne, Self-happy, self-sufficient, Ages unbegun: Rich in unmov'd Benev'lence, planning Schemes To vent His Goodness in o'erflowing Stream To Worlds unborn; or then perhaps employ'd In new Creations thro' the boundless Void In long Succession; Worlds beyond our Ken, Or to their native Nothing turn'd again. Before me, What unbounded Prospects lie Wrapt in the Darkness of Futurity! I feel the Pulse of Immortality Beat, and assure me I must ever Be; But where! or how!—Here feeble Reason fails, The Gospel too but glimm'ring Rights reveals, Assures the good of Joys in Paradise, And thunders Vengeance to the Slaves of Vice; Enough to give fair Virtue winning Charms, And shock the Libertine with dire Alarms: Yet hides those Scenes, in which with humble Eye A Philosophic Mind aspires to pry. Eternity! We daily walk upon Its slippery Brink, and yet it lies unknown; Seems an unbounded Void, a dismal Waste, With Shadows, Clouds, and Darkness overcast. Fain would we plunge into the vast Abyss, And trace ourselves these boundless Mysteries; But dark Suspicion gives a sudden Check, And strait the Soul recoils and startles back. Some daily make th' Experiment around, But none return t' inform us what they've found: They leap impetuous from this mortal Shore, And dive; and we behold them rise no more; As tho' absorpt in the unbounded Deep, Or sunk and lost in everlasting Sleep. Some, whose dear Mem'ries now dissolve my Mind, Once to my Heart in closest Friendship join'd, Have gone before, and left me here behind. Now in th' immortal Colonies they dwell, And people Worlds to us invisible; Hold Converse with the Tennants of the Sky, The various Nations of Eternity; The various Tribes with which Omnipotence Has peopled Regions thro' the vast Immense. Robinson! The Reverend Mr. William Robinson, a pious Christian; a zealous, laborious and successful Minister of the Gospel; an accomplished Scholar, and a noble Orator: Who rested from his Labours, Aug. 3. 1746, in the Bloom of Life; and has left behind him so many Seals of his Mistry in various Parts, that this humble Monument is needless to perpetuate his Memory. Once my Father, Patron, Friend, Thy painful Labours now the Prize have gain'd. Now in a happy Somewhere dwells thy Soul, Where Rivers of immortal Pleasures roll. Tho' Heav'n no doubt is thy blest Residence Yet, where, O! where, thro' the unknown Immense, Dost thou reside? how live, and act, and move? And thro' what blissful Regions dost thou rove, Transported still?—O could I soar to thee, My Robinson! how happy should I be! Is Jesus still the Matter of thy Song? The Theme below of thy harmonious Tongue. O yes! His Name diffuses Heav'n to thee Thro' all th' Apartments of Immensity. Thy Voice on Earth to Mortals taught His Name; Now Angels listen to the glorious Theme. Or does thy Soul delight, as when below, T' attend as Guardian to conduct us thro' This dang'rous Wild? With Fellow-Angels wait To guide departing Saints to th' heav'nly Gate? Then in thy Turn the gen'rous Care resign, And hymn th' eternal Throne with Songs Divine? Converse with Seraphs, and in equal Lays And equal Zeal, proclaim thy Maker's Praise? There Carnwath Mr. Thomas Carnwath, a pious Student intended for the Ministry, who died much lamented June—1747. shines, who won the rich Reward Ere for the sacred Service quite prepar'd; Obtain'd the Prize before he felt the Toil, And reap'd his Harvest ere he till'd the Soil. He left the Theologic Subtilties Of Schoolmen, He died while engaged in the Study of Divinity, having finished his Course of introductory Learning. to be taught above the Skies; Blest Change! where one bright Hour instructs him more Than all his painful Studies could before. O! could'st, thou now thy Thoughts to me relate, As oft thou did'st, while in this mortal State; What wondrous Lessons would my Ears surprize, What unexpected Scenes before me rise, And in one shining Moment make me wise! Or were the Curtains of the Flesh withdrawn. That Immortality might round me dawn; What Prospects wonderful, immense and new Would instantaneous crowd into my View! Beings, and Worlds, and Regions hid before, And the Great Author, whom those Worlds adore! Well; I ere long th' Experiment must try, And launch into unknown Eternity. The mould'ring Bank that now supports my Weight, Ere long must fall, and sink beneath my Feet: Then tho' I catch and hold and strive to stay, My Doom is fixt, my Soul! thou must away; Thou must away, some distant Worlds t' explore, And see the Vanities of Earth no more; Must howl with Fiends, or with blest Angels shine, In endless Torments, or in Joys Divine. The Interval, at most, is short between The present fleeting NOW, and Worlds unseen. Forty or fifty Years, perhaps a Day, Or Hour, will break this tottering House of Clay. Alarming Thought! Almighty Grace prepare My shudd'ring Soul to fly she knows not where. All-gracious God! be Thou my Resting-Place; Heav'n flows exuberant from Thy smiling Face Thro' the Immensity of unknown Space. O! be Thou mine; and wheresoe'er I dwell All will be Heav'n, tho' in the Glooms of Hell. XX. The Triumphs of CHRIST's dying Love. This Poem is a Translation, at least an Imitation of a Latin. Ode of Dr. Watts's, inscribed Ad Dominum nostrum &amp; Servatorem JESUM CHRISTUM. Lyric Poems B. 1. P. 94. In which that divine Poet has excelled himself; but like most other Originals, its Beauty shines but faintly thro' the Medium of Translation. I. Thee, Great Incarnate Godhead, Thee Th' Almighty Father's equal Progeny, Thee, Jesus! dear and venerable Name, Partaker of our frail Humanity, Thee shall my Voice, my Harp, my Muse and Quill proclaim. II. Wake my Harp! melodious sing On each sweetly-sounding String Th' illustrious Conquests of the Saviour-King; In loud majestic Accents sound His Triumphs o'er the Pow'rs below, When He gave Death his everlasting-Wound, 'Led the infernal Monsters bound, And crush'd the direst Terrors of His Foe. III. While Ages unbegun Their vast, their boundless Circuits run, On His eternal Father's loving Breast, Self-happy, infinitely blest, Lay the coeval Son; In the immense Jehovah satisfy'd, And the entire Divinity enjoy'd. IV. There lay the filial Godhead, till He saw From the superior Sky, Adam transgress his Maker's Law, Hell yawn with greedy Jaws to draw Into one Ruin all his wretched Progeny. He saw the Flashes of vindictive Fire Break out impatient from the Throne, And the Angelic Messenger Wave his dread Weapons, that high-brandish'd shone, Thirsting for human Blood; while Hell grew proud With Hopes of Prey, and laugh'd prophanely loud. V. He saw, and (O amazing Grace!) He lov'd, With Pity all his inmost Bowels mov'd, And Love omnipotent began to glow: “Shall all the human Race, He cries, “Fall an eternal Sacrifice, “And grace the Triumphs of the insulting Foe? “What! shall Hell's Tyranny destroy “My Father's Image, Work and Boast, “And riot in malicious Joy “To see His fav'rite Creature lost? “No! rather confounded, “With Chaos surrounded, “Be Heav'n, Earth, Ocean and all! “The Wheels of Nature break, “The Universe to horrid Wreck, “Blended, disjointed, fall! “I will o'ercome, or be o'ercome, “Wrench from the Tyrant's Hand his royal Rod, “Or yield him mine, and own him God: “My chosen Race shall live, or I will share their Doom. “By the dread Life of the Divinity, “Possest by the eternal Three, “I swear and ratify the firm Decree. VI. He said; He rose, and bow'd The chrystal Heav'ns, and down he came: Aside He threw the Grandeur of a God, In mortal Regions fixt his low Abode, And cloath'd Himself in feeble human Frame. VII. He gave His Heart to the vindictive Sword Without a murm'ring Word, Patient, His sacred Breath At the Arrest of Death Resign'd—O! the dire Terrors of the Thund'rer's Wrath! O! the immense Severity Of the dread Law! the dire Reward Of Sin! the Vengeance of the flaming Sword Of Justice! O! dire Fruits of the forbidden Tree! VIII. Come, Sinners, see your Saviour dead, And weep around His Tomb: Your Hope, your Joy, your All is fled; For Oh! your Champion's overcome. For you in Conflict with the Pow'rs of Hell He nobly fought, but ah! He fell. IX. But whither, raving Muse? refrain; Nor with ignoble Tears profane The Triumphs of the God. The Dying Champion overthrows Th' united Force of all His Foes;— In louder Strains proclaim His Victories abroad: X. Sing how thro' the Shades of Death He enter'd the dark Realms beneath, Where Hell and Horror rage; Th' infernal Pow'rs perceiv'd the God, And the grim Monsters roar'd aloud, Nor durst the well-known Arm engage. XI. Old Chaos trembled, Satan fled, And in Hell's deepest Pit sought to conceal his Head. “In vain thou fleest, the Conqu'ror cries, “Fly to the Bottom of th' Abyss, “This vengeful Thunder-Bolt shall dart thee thro', “And to the lowest Deep pursue.” He said, and strait the glowing Bolt He threw: New Horror seiz'd the trembling Host, Blasted with vengeful Flame; For well they mind the Day when Heav'n they lost. And Thunder drove them to th' infernal Coast, To Darkness, Pain and Shame. XII. He broke the Instruments of Pain, Engines to torture, guilty Ghosts; And strew'd them o'er the gloomy Coasts; The Rack, the Wheel, the adamantine Chain He tore and scatter'd o'er th' infernal Plain, Unstrung the Monster Death, and bid him hiss in vain In allusion to Serpents, which can only hiss when depriv'd of their Stings. XIII. But see! the Conqu'ror leaves the Glooms Of Hell, and climbs His native Sky: Around His Head victorious Lawrel blooms, And Triumph sparkles in His Eye: He drags the Tyrant of the Gulf profound At His triumphant Chariot bound. XIV. Heav'n celebrates a Jubilee, And shouts aloud His glad Return; The heav'nly Choirs proclaim His Victory, And with unusual Rapture burn. His Triumphs all the Harps on high, His Triumphs Mortals grateful sing; The Universe joins in the Harmony, And Stars, and Earth, and Seas, with His loud Triumphs ring. BOOK II. (It has been my usual Method for some Time, after studying a Sermon, to cast a few Thoughts into a poetical Form, either containing the Substance of the Sermon, or expressive of my Disposition in composing it. The following Poems were written on such Occasions.) I. The obstinate Security of Sinners lamented. (annext to a Sermon on Matt. iii. 10. April 15, 1750.) I. Unhappy Man, allur'd by Sin, Still drinks the deadly Poison in; And tho' expos'd to endless Woes Still lolls secure in dull Repose. Tho' Thousands daily from his Side Are snatch'd by Death's resistless Hand, And hurry'd to the infernal Land; Yet still he lets his fleeting Moments glide Unheeded by: still busily employ'd In Chace of Toys; and while bright Prospects rise Thro' false Futurity, and charm his Eyes, Death unexpected comes; the Prospects fly Like vane'd Smoke that once allur'd his Eye, And all his flatt'ring Expectations die.— Not so the deathless Soul; but torn Reluctant, from her ancient Seat, She sinks tormented and forlorn Into the Flames she once could scorn, But now bewails, alas, too late! II. What Eye can view the mournful Scene, And not dissolve in Tears! Ah! who shall warn unthinking Man, And fill his Breast with useful Tears? Warn him!—'Tis all in vain; He scorns the Fears that human Pity sheds; Nay, laughs at all the melting Arguments Which Love Divine itself invents; Nor loves the Saviour tho' for him he bleeds, And dies in Tortures, Agonies and Pain! III. Ah! what can Thy poor Servant do? See, here he sits in fruitless Grief! While thoughtless Mortals all around Perish with Mercy's charming Sound Loud in their Ears; perish just in his View, And he looks on, but can give no Relief! A feeble Mortal's Breath Cannot speak Life to them that sleep in Death. IV. Then since I can't prevail To snatch my Fellow-Man from Hell! Since heedless of Disuasives, down The dread Descent with full Career they run, Nor pause at Mercy's loudest Call; Let me retire, and o'er them weep As down they sink into the fiery Deep, And my poor Tears pursue them as they fall! V. Maker of Souls! to Thee, once more to Thee I turn my interceeding Cry! See how Thy wretched Progeny Madly destroy themselves and die By Thousands in Thy Sight! O! let Thy Sovereign Grace appear, And stop them in their mad Career; Turn them from the frequented Path That leads unerring down to Death And everlasting Night. II. Penitential Sorrows. (annext to a Sermon on Luke xiii. 3.) I. 1. With bleeding Hearts, and gushing Eyes, With deep Repentance and Surprize, We take a tedious, sad Survey Of Sins of Heart and Lip and Way. 2. Early we left the sacred Road That leads to Bliss, prescrib'd by God, And rashly run a long Career Toward the dark Regions of Despair. 3. Our very Nature's all unclean, All ruin'd and defil'd by Sin: And filthy Currents from that Source Have flow'd with an incessant Course. 4. The God that taught our Lungs to heave, And still gives Rebels Leave to live; Whose Bounties have perpetual flow'd; Ah! we have griev'd that Gracious God. 5. The Terrors of the fiery Law Could not alarm our Hearts with Awe: Nor would these stubborn Hearts be won Ev'n by the Gospel of the Son. 6. Our guilty Ears heard all around His melting Invitations sound; And Jesus too, with Groans and Blood, Such unrelenting Rebels woo'd. 7. And yet we live! amazing Grace! Nor yet quite desperate in our Case; The Saviour still, with heav'nly Charms, Stands calling Sinners to his Arms. 8. Jesus! we yield! no more, no more Will we offend Thee, as before, Here, Lord! submissive at Thy Feet, We for Thy sovereign Pleasure wait. 9. O Thou Almighty, injur'd Name! O'erwhelm'd with Grief, and flush'd with Shame, Prostrate before Thee, see we lie! Frown us not from Thee, lest we die. 10. O may that Blood we once could slight Wash our polluted Spirits white! Then shall Thy Praise sound loud in Heav'n For guilty Worms on Earth forgiven. III. SELF-DEDICATION. (annext to a Sermon on Rom. vi. 13. June 15, 1750.) 1. To Him that form'd this mortal Frame. And still inspires my Lungs to heave, From whom my nobler Spirit came, My Flesh, my Soul, my All I give. 2. When Heav'n, and Life, and All were lost, Jesus redeem'd them, with his Blood; Great was the Ransom, vast the Cost, The Blood of an incarnate God! 3. And can my stubborn Heart withstand The Invitations of His Love! No; I resign me to His Hand, And to His loft Embraces move. 4. Yes, my dear Jesus, here I give All that I am and have to Thee; To Thee I'll die, to Thee I'll live; No other Lord shall govern me. 5. Let not a Motion of my Heart, From Thee once venture to depart; But bound with lasting Bands of Love, O! let me, let me ne'er remove. IV. Sight thro' a Glass, and Face to Face. (annext to a Sermon on Matt. v. 6. March 18, 1750. before the Lord's Supper.) The Channel of Thy Word conveys The sweet Instructions of thy Grace; And sacred Emblems, thro' the Sense, Strengthen our Faith with Evidence. My infant Days were wholly Thine, Devoted by an early Sign Baptism.; And at Thy holy Table still I bind myself to do Thy Will. Once more I purpose to renew The Tie, and promise to be true. Once more beneath Thy Cross I'll sit Weeping, and gladly dedicate My Soul, my Days, my All to Thee. Who groan'd away Thy Life for me. Thro' various Types and Shadows dart Thy Glories on my ravish'd Heart; While far above created Sight, Thou fit'st enthron'd on Hills of Light. But say, shall Types and Figures still The Glories of Thy Face conceal? While these thick Shades Thy Beauty shroud, It breaks but faintly thro' the Cloud. I love Thine Image in a Glass; But Oh! to see Thy naked Face! Thyself I long, I pant to see; I turn mine Eyes in Quest of Thee. Where is that dear, incarnate God, That once on Earth made His Abode? That Jesus, who upon the Tree Languish'd, and bled, and died for me? Ah! will my Saviour now be shy, Whose Love excited Him to die? He found me when I sought him not; And will he not be found, when sought? The Glories of Thy Face display, Tho' Life should for the Vision pay. O! let me die, opprest with Light, Rather than live without the Sight. V. The Law and Gospel. (annext to a Sermon on Gal. iii. 9, 10. Aug. 19, 1750.) 1. With conscious Fear and humble Awe, I view the Terrors of the Law; Condemn'd at that tremendous Bar, I shrink, I tremble, and Despair. 2. But hark! Salvation in my Ears Sounds sweetly, and dispells my Fears: Jesus appears, and by His Cross Fulfils His Father's broken Laws. 3. Jesus! a Saviour! dearest Name! By Him alone Salvation came; Terror, Destruction and Despair, Where e'er I look besides, appear. 4. Adam, my Head and Father fell, And sunk his Offspring down to Hell: And the dread Sword of Justice waits, To guard me from the heav'nly Gates. 5. Unnumber'd Crimes of dreadful Names Call loud for everlasting Flames; And all the Duties I have done Can neither merit, nor attone. 6. Yet weak and guilty as I am, I fix my trust on Jesus' Name. Jesus, whose Righteousness alone Can for the deepest Crimes attone. 7. On Him, my Soul, on Him rely; The Terms are fixt—Believe, or Die. Thee let the Glorious Gospel draw, Or perish by the fiery Law. VI. CHRIST the Beloved and Friend of His Church. (annext to a Sermon on Cant. v. 16. Oct.—1748.) 1. Let Others let their Passions rove Round all the Earth, from Shore to Since Jesus is my Friend and Love, My utmost Wish can grasp no more. 2. His Glories have allur'd my Eye, And into Love transform'd my Heart; To Him my tender'st Passions fly; Jesus! nor shall they e'er depart. 3 Upon His Friendship I rely, Still of His tender Care secure; My Wants are all before His Eye! Nor can they overcome His Power. 4 His Presence fills unbounded Space; My heav'nly Friend is always nigh: Full of Compassion, rich in Grace; Touch'd with the tenderest Sympathy. 5 Faithful and constant is His Love, And my ungrateful Conduct hides: Safe to the happy World above The meanest of His Friends He guides. 6 Amid the Agonies of Death, And Terrors of the Final Doom, He saves them from Almighty Wrath, And leads the helpless Pilgrims home. 7. O may an everlasting Flame Of Love possess my gratful Mind! And my last Breath adore His Name Who condescends to be my Friend! VII. The Spiritual Warfare. (annext to a Sermon on Rev. xxi. 7.) 1. Arm thee in Panoply Divine, My Soul, and fir'd with Courage rise; A Thousand Enemies combine T' obstruct thy Progress to the Skies. 2. Infernal Darts perpetual Fly, And scatter various Deaths around; Around thee Thousands daily die, And none escape without a Wound. 3. The World presents her tempting Charms, And wears the Aspect of a Friend, Yet ah! She carries deadly Arms, And all her Smiles in Ruin end. 4. But Oh! the Flesh! that latent Foe! That treach'rous En'my in my Breast! 'Tis hence proceeds my Overthrow, And hence I'm conquer'd by the rest. 5. Thro' Troops of potent Enemies, Thro' hostile Snares, and Fields of Blood, If I expect the Glorious Prize, I must pursue my dangerous Road. 6. But ah! how can a feeble Worm Obtain so hard a Victory? Alas! I perish in the Storm, And helpless fall, and bleed, and die. 7. The glorious Prize stands full in View, But Deaths and Dangers stop my Way: Thou glorious Prize! Adieu, adieu! Here, Cruel Foes! Come, seize your Prey. 8. But hark! an animating Voice Majestic breaks from th' upper Sky: “Courage, frail Worm! Live and rejoice, “I have procur'd the Victory. 9. “Suspended on th' accursed Tree, “I crush'd the Might of all thy Foes: “Dying, I spoil'd their Tyranny, “And triumph'd o'er them when I rose. 10. “This Arm that props the Universe, “And holds up Nature's tott'ring Frame, “Can all surrounding Harms disperse, “And safe protect the feeblest Name. 11. “The Captain of Salvation deigns “To lead the Van, and guard thy Way: “And since thy conquering Leader reigns, “Th' infernal Pow'rs shall miss their Prey. 12. “In Me confide; from Me derive “Courage and Strength to keep the Field: “In Crowds of Death then Thou shalt live, “And all thy stubborn Foes shall yield. 13. “The Spirit's Sword victorious wield, “And steel thy Breast with Righteousness; “Let Faith be thy Triumphant Shield; Eph. vi. 15, 16. “Thy Helmet, Hope of heav'nly Bliss. 14. “See in my Hands the glorious Prize; “This Crown the Conquerer shall wear: “Rise then with dauntless Courage rise, “And bid adeiu to every Fear. 15. Tho' sharp the Combat, 'tis but short; Vict'ry with active Wing draws nigh: “And my brave Soldiers, all unhurt, “Ere long shall triumph in the Sky.” 16. Blest Jesus! fir'd with martial Zeal I arm, and rush into the Fight; And thro' my Weakness still I feel, I am Almighty in Thy Might. 17. Thy gracious Words my Heart inspire With gen'rous Zeal for noble Deeds; Let Hell and all her Hosts appear, My Soul, undaunted, now proceeds. 18. Satan, affrighted at thy Frown, Retreats, despairing of his Prey; And all the Flatt'ries Earth has shewn, In vain their treach'rous Charms display. 19. The Flesh, subdu'd by Grace Divine, No more shall triumph o'er the Man. Now, Glorious Prize! I call thee mine, Tho' Earth and Hell do all they can. VIII. A guilty Conscience. (annext to a Sermon on 1 John iii. 20. Nov. 25. 1750.) 1. Ah! who can bear this twinging Smart, That tortures and corrodes my Heart! These guilty Horrors, that molest This self-condemn'd, self-tort'ring Breast! 2. Tremendous Prospects strike mine Eye, Through vast, unknown Futurity: Grim Death a thousand Terrors wears, And ready to arrest appears. 3. I view with a distracted Stare, The dread eternal Regions near; Tortures, and Racks, and quenchless Fire, And Shrieks, and Groans, and Torments dire! 4. The wrathful Heav'ns vindictive frown, And Thunders murmur to be down, To blast a Worm that durst provoke Omnipotence to give the Stroke. 5. Surmises, Fears and Jealousies In this self-conscious Bosom rise; And prest with Guilt my Spirits sink, When I allow myself to think. 6. But ah! this giddy rambling Soul, Ere a few fleeting Moments roll, Some vain enchanting Toy admits, And her unhappy Case forgets. 7. Amusements or th' intrusive Care Of this vain World, my Thoughts ensnare: My solemn Resolutions fly, All lost in thoughtless Levity. 8. But ah! the Agony returns; Again my Spirit pines and mourns; Again dire-boding Fears surround My shudd'ring Soul, and deeply wound. 9. A frightful Thought will sudden dart, And, unexpected, pierce the Heart. Pain would I shun these shocking Views, But Conscience restless still pursues. 10. A cheerful Aspect I assume, But all within is dismal Gloom: Or if I lose the inward Pain A Moment, ah! it gnaws again. 11. I leave this gloomy Solitude, And mingle with th' unthinking Crowd; There trifle, talk, and laugh awhile; But ah! the Anguish will recoil. 12. In Crowds and Noise the guilty Mind Some anxious Intervals will find: Guilt whispers Terror in the Breast, And interrupts the transient Rest. 13. Oh! Misery 'til now unknown! I am a Self-Tormenter grown: Nor can I my Accuser shun, Unless I from myself could run. 14. Oh Sin! is this the dire Reward For all thy wretched Slaves prepar'd! Are these, alass! are these the Fruits Of all my pleasing vain Pursuits! 15. Ah! had I kept the narrow Road, Where the blest Few enjoy their God, Then all serene, unmov'd with Guilt, These Horrors I had never felt. 16. Oh! can a guilty Wretch obtain A Balm to ease this twinging Pain? Or must he always feel the Road Of Conscience, and an angry God? 17. Jesus! if any Help remains, It flows from Thy dear bleeding Veins: Nothing can please an angry God, Or angry Conscience, but Thy Blood. I do not mean that presumptuous Libertines ought to ease their Consciences by an imaginary Dependance on Christ: But that humble conscious Penitents should place their only Trust in His Righteousness, both to relieve them from the Horrors of Guilt, and deliver them from their former Slavery to Sin. 18. Oh! dare I yet with wishful Eyes, Look for Salvation from the Skies? Oh! will that Blood my Sins have spilt, Relieve my Mind, and wash my Guilt? 19. All gracious Saviour! Oh! remit A Rebel prostrate at Thy Feet: He has no other Place to fly; If die he must, here let him die! 20. Say, shall that Hand that patient bore To be by Nails and Torments tore,— Oh! wilt Thou now, vindictive stretch That Hand to crush an humble Wretch! 21. No! Blessed Jesus! rather slay These Sins that led my Soul astray: O make my Heart and Conscience clean, And give me Heav'n and Peace within! IX. Love to God for His Holiness. (annext to a Sermon on 1 John iv. 16. Dec. 2, 1750.) 1. Come, Holy Spirit! Come, enflame Our lukewarm Hearts with sacred Fire: May all our Passions, to Thy Name, In Transports most refin'd, aspire. 2. May Love sublime our Hearts possess, From every selfish Mixture free, Fir'd with the Charms of Holiness, The Beauty of Divinity. 3. We see the Beauty of Thy Grace, That saves rebellious Worms from Hell: But ah! the Charms of Holiness We dimly see, and faintly feel. 4. Selfish and mercenary Views Are with our purest Passions mixt: A nobler Passion, Oh! infuse, On Holiness supremely fixt. 5. Thus in the glorious Worlds on high, Where Holiness is most ador'd, Th' Angelic Choirs incessant cry, “Thrice HOLY, HOLY, HOLY LORD!” 6. Refine our Hearts, inspire our Tongue, And We in humble Notes below Will imitate the heav'nly Song, And eccho “HOLY, HOLY,” too. X. Brotherly Love. (annext to a Sermon on 1 John iii. 14. Dec. 9, 1750.) 1. Descend, Thou mild, pacific Dove! Thine Image on our Hearts impress; Transform our Passions all to Love, And sooth our Discords into Peace. 2. In Arms of warm Benevolence, Teach us t' embrace all Human Kind; And like the Sun, around dispense The Wishes of a gen'rous Mind. 3. We are but Parts of one great Whole, And may our Hearts, enlarg'd, exult To scatter Bliss from Pole to Pole, And still the Gen'ral Good consult! 4. But may the beauteous Sons of Grace, Attract a more peculiar Love; And the fair Charms of Holiness A more exalted Passion move. 5. Where e'er our Father's Image shines, And his dear Lineaments appear, May we approve the heav'nly Lines, And our Affections center there. 6. May sympathetic Sorrows fill Our Hearts, to view another's Grief; And may our Hands be open still To bless the Needy with Relief. 7. May we our Brother's Fault conceal, And mild and inoffensive live; And may our Bosoms ever feel That God-like Pleasure, to forgive. 8. O gentle Love! Celestial Guest! Visit a jarring World again; Come dwell forever in our Breast, And there triumphant ever reign. 9. Then while the noisy Sons of Strife Are with tumultous Passions whirl'd, We shall enjoy a peaceful Life, Amid a murm'ring, jangling World. XI. The doubting Christian. (annext to a Sermon adapted for Self-Examination, on 1 John iii. 7, 8. December 16, 1750.) An Excellent poem—1752. May. 1. Happy the Man whose peaceful Breast A smiling Conscience charms to rest; Whose pious Heart and Life express The living Characters of Grace! 2. He humbly claims the Promises, And calls their richest Blessings his: In Peace he lives, and dies in Peace, And peaceful soars to heav'nly Bliss. 3. Thrice happy he! But ah! I feel The Twinges of Suspicions still; Dark boding Fears and wild Surmise, And Jealousies perpetual rise. 4. Perplext with various Characters, My Mind is tost 'twixt Hopes and Fears: Here some kind Tokens rise, but there The dismal Counter-Tokens glare. 5. I humbly hope, in some bright Hour, My State is safe, my Heav'n secure: But soon the shining Moment flies, And soon tremendous Glooms arise. 6. Thus in a dubious Twilight lost, With various Waves, alternate, tost, O'er Life's tempestuous Sea I roam, Uncertain where shall be my Home: 7. Uncertain where my Soul must go, To Fields of Joy, or Lakes of Woe: Before me the vast Prospect lies, But cover'd with Uncertainties. 8. I view the Ocean vast and wide, Where Time unites its ebbing Tide; Now, hoping, would th' Adventure make, Now trembling, shudd'ring startle back. 9. Confounded, now back shrinks my Soul, To see the fiery Billows roll: Now Rivers of immense Delight Glide copious by, and tempt her Flight. 10. O! if these Doubts were chas'd away, How calmly then, without Dismay, I'd launch into the boundless Deep, And fearless take the final Leap! 11. But what if in some dark Abode, Banish'd forever from my God, My Soul should pine in endless Pain!— Ah me! This Fear returns again. 12. Say, my dear God, and ease my Heart, O wilt Thou frown, and say Depart! Depart!—ah! where, Lord! shall I flee? I have no other Bliss but Thee. 13. Thou seest my Passions to Thy Name Kindle, tho' with a feeble Flame And shall a Spark of heav'nly Love From its own native Regions move? 14. O! shall the meanest of Thy Friends, Forever dwell with hateful Fiends? No! let me claim the humblest Place In the bright Mansions of Thy Grace. XII. CHRIST's Agony in the Garden. Luke xxii. 41, 44. See there, o'erwhelm'd with Agonies, Prostrate, forlorn, my Jesus lies! Panting, moaning, groaning there, On the cold Ground, in midnight Air: No Friend, no kind Assistant near; No sympathizing Comforter; But all alone, unheard, unknown, To the dark Night He makes His Moan. Malignant Spirits glare around, And with their fiery Arrows wound: Trying to add, with spiteful Pow'r, New Horrors to the dismal Hour; And in his tortur'd Soul to rear The gloomy Standard of Despair. The frowning Heav'ns tremendous low'r, And murm'ring Thunders dreadful roar; Then shot by sudden Vengeance dart, And tear and ravage thro' His Heart. To his own Heav'ns He lifts his Eyes. Father, remove this Cup, he cries, This deadly Cup of bitter Dregs, Mingled with Wrath and Pains and Plagues; Dear Father, O! remove this Cup; Or some kind Cordial in it drop: Yet if thy Will decree it just, That drink it I, or Sinners must, Rather than they should taste the Gall, See, Father; here I drink it all: Thy Will it is I should atone, And, Father! let Thy Will be done! The Father hides his wonted Smiles, And all his Soul with Horror fills, Transferring on his darling Son The heavy Crimes by Mortals done. See! prest beneath the dismal Load, He sinks, he falls, altho' a God! A mortal Sweat bedews His Limbs, And down his sacred Body streams; See! how it bursts thro' every Pore, Mingled with Lumps of clotted Gore! His hollow Groans with mournful Sound, Eccho thro' all the Garden round. While thus I view, with gushing Eyes, My dear Redeemer agonize, With crushing Sorrows overborn, Methinks I see him wishful turn His Face, where Love and Anguish mix, And full on me His Aspect fix; And from His Tongue methinks I hear, These moving Accents strike my Ear. “See, Sinner! see the cruel Load “With which thy Sins oppress thy God! “Thy Sins extort these hollow Groans; “For thee, for thee thy Jesus moans! “Thee so ungrateful, so unkind! “So prone to cast Me from thy Mind! “And can thy stubborn Heart endure “To grieve, forget and slight Me more! “Oh! canst thou hear these Groans and Cries, “And thy kind Saviour still despise! “Come, Sinner, view these Clots of Gore, “And say, Wilt thou forget me more! “Say, Canst thou view this mournful Scene, And strait return to Sin again! “What! Leave thy Saviour bleeding here, “And go”— —Forbear! my Lord, forbear! Thy Words o'ercome me! Jesus, stay! O here I faint and die away. It kills me, Lord! but to suppose That ever I should treat Thee thus! No! rather stop my guilty Breath! To treat Thee thus is worse than Death. If I such Love as this forget, Then let my Heart forget to beat: If e'er I slight Thine Agony, In that curs'd Moment let me die; Or if I cease to love Thy Name, Relapse to nothing whence I came: If Sin be any more my Joy, Me, with my own Consent, destroy. Sin!—When I hear the hated Name, With keen Revenge my Passions flame. Ah me! that e'er my foolish Breast Indulg'd the Monster as a Guest! Caress'd him in my dearest Part! Ah, this Reflection tears my Heart! What, blessed Lord! what shall I do? I own I have indulg'd Thy Foe; With my own Life the Monster fed, That made Thee groan, and sweat, and bleed, O could my Actions be undone! O were the Race of Life to run! Ye misimproven Hours! return, Which now with flowing Tears I mourn. Vain, fruitless Wish! the restless Wheel Of Time moves onward, onward still; Nor can Intreaties bring it back To roll again its former Track. Blest Jesus! take each future Hour; 'Tis all the Amends within my Pow'r: O may Thy Praise in grateful Song, Forever echo from my Tongue! O may Thy Love enflame my Soul, While everlasting Ages roll! XIII. Spiritual Inactivity lamented. 1. Jesus! What eager Zeal inspir'd Thy Heart to die for me! O that my languid Breast were fir'd With equal Flame to Thee! 2. But how has Sin benumb'd my Soul! My Heart how hard and dead! My softest Passions, ah how dull! Heavy and cold as Lead. 3. Mean Time inferior Toys can charm, And all my Passions move: A Friend or Relative can warm, And melt my Heart to Love. 4. My Thoughts refuse to soar to Thee, But full of Vigour spring To chase some gilded Vanity, Some useless trifling Thing. 5. Blest Jesus! I would rather lose My thinking Faculty, Than waste my Thoughts on Trifles thus, And never think of Thee. 6. If my soft Passions be not Thine, My Passions are a Pain; Let me the Power of Love resign, Rather than love in vain. 7. Lord, 'tis a Curse to live and breathe, Unless I live to Thee; If I must lie thus stupid, Death Is better than to Be. 8. Thy quick'ning Energy exert, Blest Jesus! and bestow A living Soul, a tender Heart To serve my God below. XIV On a sudden Death. (annext to a funeral Sermont on Eccles. ix. 12. Jan. 5. 1750–1.) 1. How thin the separating Wall 'Twixt Time and vast Eternity! How sudden thoughtless Mortals fall Into that dark unbounded Sea! 2. The Soul, this Moment vain and gay, Eager pursues the Trifles here, The next, reluctant torn away, In a dark Somewhere to appear. 3. Death still pursues us every-where, And unsuspected haunts our Steps; And while we think no Danger near, Sudden upon his Prey he leaps. 4. The Monster in close Ambush lurks, And steals upon us unawares: Still undermining ceaseless works; Still near, yet distant still appears. 5. My sudden Fate perhaps may seal The melancholy Truth I write; And e'er I farther move my Quill, The vital Pulse may cease to beat. 6. How strange, how solemn the Surprize! Hurried at once to Worlds unknown! Snatch'd from this Scene of Vanities, And plac'd before th' Eternal Throne! 7. The lower Skies, the Earth and Men All in a Moment out of Sight! While Wonders of the World unseen In endless Prospects rush to Light! 8. Great God! and do I heedless step On this tremendous Precipice, Perhaps to take the final Leap, Unwarn'd, ere this short Moment flies! 9. And does Eternity depend, And all its infinite Affairs, On every fleeting Hour I spend, And waste upon inferior Cares! 10. Alarming Thought! My Soul, awake! Prepare, prepare to meet thy God! These mortal Regions soon forsake, And often view thy last Abode. 11. Almighty Grace! in youthful Prime Teach me t'improve my fleeting Time; That whensoe'er the Summons come, I may receive a joyful Doom. 12. Then if perhaps a sudden Death Should unexpected stop my Breath, My Soul at once, with glad Surprize, Shall find herself in upper Skies. 13. Thrice happy Death! to drop the Chain Of Life, without a ling'ring Pain! To spring at once to endless Life! Without a tedious dying Strife! XV. The Conflagration. (annext to a Sermon on 2 Pet. iii. 11. Jan. 27, 1750–1.) 1. Now Harmony adjusts the World, And charming Order round me smiles: Ere long Confusion shall be hurl'd, And break and shatter Nature's Wheels. 2. The Day approaches, (dreadful Day!) When Chaos shall resume his Place? This mighty Frame of Things decay, And vanish in the general Blaze. 3. Ye azure Arches, lost in Smoke, Shall shrink, affrighted, to a Scroll: The Pillars of high Heaven be broke, While Lightnings glare from Pole to Pole. 4. Thou too, accurst terrestial Ball, That saw the Son of God expire; Thou and thy Works shall perish all, And sink in universal Fire. 5. Horrendous Sight! A World in Flames! Thunders loud rumbling thro' the Air! Dire Lightnings flushing fiery Streams, And glaring red and vengeful there! 6. Mountains wide-bursting! liquid Fire In glowing Torrents rushing down! Rocks, Stones, fierce Min'rals, Sulphur dire Melting, the Plains and Vallies drown! 7. Old Ocean of its Moisture dry'd, Receives the fierce descending Tide: Thither dissolving Worlds retire, And form a boundless Lake of Fire. 8. With loud Ætnean Thunders roars The Globe, with Earthquakes tost and torn: Palaces, Cities, Castles, Tow'rs, Towns, Wood and Plains united burn. 9. And where! O where shall Sinners then Flee from the universal Wreck! Aghast they view the burning Main, And plunge into the sulph'rous Lake. 10. There overwhelm'd, the rebel Worms Lie ever, ever, ever lost! Beaten with everlasting Storms, On fiery Eddies whirl'd and tost. 11. But ye dear Saints, ye pious Few, Jesus shall screen your feeble Souls: Safe from on high your Eyes shall view The burning Earth and melting Poles. 12. Jesus shall live when Nature dies; And while he lives, you must be blest: Behold he forms new Earth and Skies, Where you eternal Years shall rest. 13. Let Earth and Skies, convuls'd and torn, To common Desolation fall; Mountains dissolve, and Oceans burn, God is your Bliss, your Heav'n, your All. There is no Theme, perhaps, in the Compass of Nature, that so far exceeds human Language and Imagination, as the Conflagration. The Terrors of Ætna and Vesuvius, in their most outragious Eruptions, are but low and trifling Emblems of a burning World. But perhaps nothing can give us a more lively and striking Prospect of that tremendous Scene, 'til we ourselves are Spectators of it, than the elegant Dr. Burnet's Description, in his sacred Theory of the Earth. Book III. Ch. 12. from whence I have borrowed most of these Thoughts. XVI. Separation from GOD the most intolerable Punishment. (annext to a Sermon on Gen. iv. 13, 14. Jan. 13, 1750–1.) Fountain of Good! 'twas thy creating Breath Inspired the boundless Wish, th' immense Desire, That gasps for perfect Bliss. The panting Soul, That still unsatisfy'd, still restless, breaks Through Nature's Bonds, with dark implicit Aim Unconscious points to Thee, the unbounded Source Of all Perfection. So young Ravens cry, And gape to catch the Bounty from Thy Hand, By Instinct taught, unconscious what they ask, And whence the Blessing comes. So the parch'd Earth, When brazen Skies deny the timely Rain, With silent Importunity implores, Unknowing, the soft Show'r: her gaping Chinks Her with'ring Verdure, and dejected Flow'rs Mourning present the silent Pray'r to Thee. These innate Wishes, that impatient break Through all the Limits of created Joys, Direct their Flight to Thee: th' Extravagance Of these immense Desires, proclaim aloud My Soul can ne'er be happy but in Thee. In Thee alone her Faculties find Room, In Thee alone expatiate unconfin'd. Through all the Affluence that Earth can yield, Through all the Canopy of Heav'n contains, Through all the Ranks of heav'nly Forms, she breaks In Quest of Thee. In Quest of Thee she roves In all th' Anxieties of Discontent, In all the distant Prospects Hope can shew, And all the wild Excursions of Desire. For Thee she heaves the Sigh; for Thee dilates The boundless Wish; Thee under some Disguise, Tho' oft deluded with fallacious Views, Restless pursues; and short of Thee despairs To find true Bliss, proportion'd to her Wish. Let all the richest Blessings Nature yields Diffuse themselves around me, with Disdain My Soul would all th' insip'd Trifles spurn: Through all the gay Temptations still look out For some superior Bliss; look out to Thee, My only Happiness, with wishful Eyes, And find my Heav'n in Thy propitious Smiles. O! may I hope, when the long Drudgery Of Life is past, to rise and soar to Thee? There all my boundless Cravings satisfy, And fill my vast Capacities of Bliss? But gloomy Guilt obscures the glimm'ring Hope; Whispers a thousand Horrors, and forebodes Eternal Separation from Thy Face, In the waste Realms where Desolation frowns, Unconscious of Thy Smiles. Tremendous Thought! Oh! Horrors! Horrors!—An immortal Soul, With ever-gnawing and immense Desires, Torn off from all the Pleasures Sense can yield, Without a God! Without a Drop of Bliss To quench her raging Thirst! Curs'd from the Earth, A restless Fugitive thro' the dark Voids Of boundless Space, and the thick Glooms of Hell! Haunted with horrid Furies! Rack'd and torn With guilty, dire Reflections! Not an Eye To pity! Pining, panting, gasping still For Bliss in vain, with hungry wild Desires!— I sink beneath the Prospect! Horrors chill The vital Stream, and palpipate around My agonizing Heart!—My Maker God! My Father! Saviour! every dearest Name! Oh! wilt Thou doom me to a long Exile From thy propitious Face, my only Bliss! See! Lord, a Supplicant before Thy Throne Importunate I bow; for Grace I cry! For Grace to fit my Spirit to enjoy Thee as my final Portion and my All. THE APPENDIX Devout EJACULATIONS and SOLILOQUIES. [N?. I. No! never, never can this Heart] No! never, never can this Heart From Thee her God, her All, depart. Indulge my Boldness; I protest In Thee alone I must be blest; I'm fixt, resolv'dly fixt, in this Thyself, or nought shall be my Bliss: I swear by the eternal Three, I will accept no Bliss but Thee. Put me not off with golden Toys, With empty Honours, sensual Joys. O! do not thy poor Servant doom To Crowns and Empires in Thy Room. I loath the Happiness that springs From these and all created Things, Sooner may Gold or Dust asswage The parched Pilgrim's thirsty Rage, When under torrid Lybian Skies, On burning Sands, he faints and dies: Sooner, than these inferior Toys Can fill me with substantial Joys. Since of Thy Love I tasted first, All other Pleasures I disgust: Since first Thy Beauties charm'd my Sight, Created Charms yield no Delight. O! if I'm doom'd Thy Frowns to feel, Why didst Thou e'er Thy Smiles reveal? Why with Thy Glories charm my Eye, If I must see and ne'er enjoy? O! why torment me with the Views Of Bliss I must for ever lose? O! if I must for ever dwell Absent from Thee, why did not Hell Devour me, e'er I felt this Flame? This ardent Passion to Thy Name? Then had my Soul ne'er understood The Loss of an infinite Good; Nor languish'd in eternal Pain, Pleasures once tasted to regain; Nor in tormenting Anguish pin'd To call Thy once felt Smiles to Mind. But hence each dire Surmise! away! My gracious God would not display His Glories to enflame my Heart, If I were destin'd to depart. He would not cruelly deride My Soul with Bliss to be deny'd; Nor kindle Love to pant in vain, And rack me with augmented Pain. No! His own Self will satisfy The Wishes He has rais'd so high. [N? II. And must I call these Passions mine] And must I call these Passions mine That feel so faintly Charms divine? And must I own this useless Soul, To Thee so languid, cold and dull? I would, my God, call nothing mine But what is wholly, solely Thine. [N?. III. Life's but a Load, a tedious Pain] Life's but a Load, a tedious Pain, A Curse, if I must live in vain. Shall I my Hours inactive spend? Or thus be active to no End? O Thou who didst these Pow'rs infuse, Exalt them to a noble Use. Direct my Thinking Faculty No more to rove, but fix on Thee: Allure my Will Thyself to chuse, And all inferior Good refuse! O! teach my Passions to aspire To Thee, and burn with heav'nly Fire? My Conscience to perform its Part On Thy Tribunal in my Heart! My Tongue to celebrate Thy Grace, And every Breath to utter Praise; My Eyes to see Thy Glories shine Thro' this fair Universe of Thine; My Ears to hear with rapt'rous Joys, The charming Music of Thy Voice: This Spark of weak poetic Fire Refine, and teach it to aspire: Let all I have, and all I am Be sacred to Thy glorious Name, Thus train me to th' Employ above, Ere to these Regions I remove. [N?. IV. My God! I'm pleas'd that Thou art All in All] My God! I'm pleas'd that Thou art All in All, Should Nature totter, and to Nothing fall. My Being sprung from thy creative Breath, And on Thy Will depend my Life and Death. Let Heav'n, Earth, Men and Angels cease to Be, I've Bliss enough, I've all I wish in Thee; Thy single Self's compleat Felicity. I'm happy, since my God must always live, Tho' Vanity is my Prerogative. This Spark of Being Homage pays to Thee, Thou boundless Fountain of all Entity; Rejoices in the unbounded Plenitude Of Thy Perfections, Thou infinite Good! [N?. V. Oh! be Thy glorious Name exalted high] Oh! be Thy glorious Name exalted high, Thro' all the Spaces of Immensity. Let the wide World, let Heav'n and Earth and Hell, In various Ways, Thy wond'rous Glory tell, And thy unbounded Excellence reveal. O! raise me to the blissful Realms on high, Not to be glorify'd, but glorify; Not to be honour'd, but to honour Thee, Not there to reign, but bow th' adoring Knee. Give me a Crown, to cast before Thy Feet, Raise me, to bow the lower at Thy Seat. Exalt and dignify a groveling Worm, An humbler Adoration to perform; For while my Situation is so low, I cannot with profound Prostration bow. [N?. VI. That I'm the vilest Sinner, Lord! I own] That I'm the vilest Sinner, Lord! I own In penitent Prostration at Thy Throne; Worthy an endless Monument to be To thousand Worlds not to revolt from Thee: But did not Jesus die? This is my Plea; And has that charming Name no Force with Thee? Insult my Groans, reject my loudest Cries; But Oh! canst Thou the Saviour's Blood despise? Say, are my Crimes to such a Vastness grown, That ev'n the Blood of Jesus can't atone? O no! then let Thy boundless Mercy shine With Splendors equal to these Crimes of mine. But if Thou doom me from Thy blissful Sight, And frowning say, “I've in him no Delight; “Lo, here I am!” Sam. xv. 26.—But oh! the most undone And wretched Thing Omniscience e'er has known. The Thought is Death! 'tis Hell! my Spirits break! I'm overwhelm'd!—I'm lost!—I cannot speak! [N?. VII. Repulse me not; for whither shall I flee?] Repulse me not; for whither shall I flee? The Words of Life are found alone with Thee. Here slay me at Thy Feet, if die I must; Dying, in Thee I'll fix my humble Trust: Job xiii. 15. Dying, erect my Eyes to Thee in Pray'r, And in a suppliant Agony expire. Repulse me not; 'tis in my Saviour's Name, Not in my own, Thy Grace I humbly claim: And when in that prevailing Name I pray, Thou art oblig'd, Thou canst not say me nay. Hast Thou not bound Thyself with Thy own Mouth, In the Engagements of eternal Truth? And shall Hell's Pow'rs have Umbrage to blaspheme Thy sacred Truth, and charge Thy spotless Name With Breach of Faith? No! Thy Veracity Shall shine from all infernal Censure free, Exemplify'd, in Thy good Time, in me. Thou wilt not let me seek Thy Face in vain, Sigh to the Rocks, and to the Winds complain. The Blessings Grace does wisely now deny, Thou wilt in the most proper Hour supply. [N?. VIII. Ah! what avail these warm poetic Strains] Ah! what avail these warm poetic Strains, These feigned Raptures of the fawning Muse If cold and languid still my Heart remains, And my soft Passions to concur refuse? O! if I love Thee not, I'm self-condemned, This Hand the Sentence has transcrib'd and seal'd; Thee Greatest, Loveliest, Best, I've oft proclaim'd, And Thy unrivall'd Glories oft reveal'd. And am I still a Stranger to Thy Face? Are these extatic Flights affected Zeal? Forbid it Heav'n! or mine's the direst Case Of any perjur'd Wretch on this Side Hell. O! let the Flame of pure Devotion rise Above the Muse's most exalted Flight; And mingle with the Ardors of the Skies; While my poor Lays in vain attempt the Height. [N?. IX. Why should I, in the Rage of wild Despair] Why should I, in the Rage of wild Despair Job xiii. 14. And Agony, my Flesh thus gnaw and tear? Why sink desponding under hopeless Grief, And in my trembling Hand repose my doubtful Life? O say, my God, may not a Sinner dare Job xiii, 15. Confide in Thee, and sooth his wild Despair? O yes! Tho' Thou shouldst crush me in the Dust Like some vile Poison, still in Thee I'll trust, v. 25. In Thee I'll trust, hope in Thy gracious Word, Tho' Thou should'st slay me with Thy vengeful Sword. But oh! so mean a Worm's beneath Thy Wrath; v. 25. Unworthy by Thy Hands to suffer Death; Beneath a Look of Thy avenging Eye, Of Thy immense, exalted Majesty. Ah! will Thy God-like Vengeance condescend A fleeting Leaf, the Sport of Winds, to rend? Or will the Majesty of Justice claim A wretched Victim of so mean a Name; And of dry Stubble form a feeble Flame? [N?. X. Though luscious Figs no more shall bloom and grow] Though luscious Figs no more shall bloom and grow, Hab. iii. 17. Nor bending Vines with juicy Clusters glow; Though the fat Olive should our Hopes beguile, And burst no more with usual Floods of Oil; Though Barrenness should blast the fertile Field, And Earth no more her vital Fatness yield; Though Death should plunder every crouded Stall, And Flocks and Herds in common Ruin fall; Though meager Famine stalk across the Land, And tear our Blessing from our grasping Hand. In Thee, my God, I'm blest, I'm happy still; v. 18. Nor should the Loss of these vain Trifles feel, But at the gen'ral Devastation smile. Abstract from these, Thou art sufficient Bliss, But without Thee, how poor a Portion these! [N?. XI. Yes! soon the iron Hand of Death] 1. Yes! soon the iron Hand of Death Must seize my Frame, and stop my Breath, And snatch my Soul away. Methinks I feel its Agonies— Anhelant, panting, struggling lies The agonizing Clay. 2. Suffus'd with mortal clammy Sweat, Irregular the Pulses beat; The Lips hang quiv'ring down; The Eyes, depress'd and hollow, swim In dizzy Mists; the vital Stream Laggs in its mazy Round. 3. A deadly Cold from every Part Benumbs my Limbs, invades my Heart; I feel it creeping on! A ghastly Pale deforms my Cheeks; And now my falling Jaws relax; And now I'm gone! I'm gone! 4. In a deep Groan the Spirit flies, Unfetter'd by the former Ties Of cumb'rous Flesh and Blood— But, oh! my Soul, what unknown Place Through the Immensity of Space Shall be thy last Abode? 5. 'Till this important Doubt is solv'd, My Soul in anxious Fears involv'd, No solid Rest can know; Ah! what's the World and all its Toys Compar'd to everlasting Joys, Or everlasting Woe? 6. Oh, when I bid the World adieu, Should Guilt, the Fury, still pursue— Shocking, o'erwhelming Thought! Or should th' infernal Tyrant, Sin, Forever reign and rage within— Intolerable Lot! 7. Great God, though one continu'd Cloud My fleeting Day of Life should shroud, Yet be my Evening clear! Horror my shudd'ring Soul invades To enter Death's tremendous Shades, If Thou be absent there 8. Be Witness Heaven; I here protest My Mind shall never, never rest 'Till I Thy Presence gain. I'll pray away my vital Breath, Begging Thy gracious Smiles in Death; Nor cease 'till I obtain. [N?. XII. Oh! while eternal Ages roll] Oh! while eternal Ages roll, Be Thou supreme, above Controul! Be absolute! Thy sovereign Will Be done! for oh! 'tis righteous still. Thy Favours where thou wilt, dispense; With calm, implicit Confidence, I own Thy Reasons just and good, Ev'n where they are not understood By cavilling Wit. Oh! be Thy Will The Rule of Thy Procedure still. Though perverse Mortals, blind and vain, Thy Dispensations dare arraign; Yet self-approv'd, self-guided, rule Th' Affairs of this dependent Whole: No do Thou stoop to satisfy The haughty Worms that ask Thee why. For me, behold I helpless stand At the Disposal of Thy Hand: A Piece of mean polluted Clay, Thou may'st chuse or cast away: Thou may'st absolve my flagrant Guilt, Or bind it on me, as Thou wilt. Though Thou should'st blast me with Thy Frown, Thy sovereign Justice I must own, Thy Justice I must still acquit, Against myself Thine Advocate. But (Oh! how shall I praise Thy Name!) Submission here Thou dost not claim: The Wheels of Duty and Self-Love In the same Tract harmonious move, Thy dread Authority requires Me to escape eternal Fires: Thy Law commands me to be blest; My Duty is my Interest. My Mis'ry is my wilful Sin, Forbid by that kind Will of Thine. Accomplish then Thy sovereign Will, For oh! 'tis good and righteous still. Thou'rt just, whate'er become of me, And all Thy Ways from Censure free. XIII. A Description of a Storm, May 9, 1751. I. Now when the War of Elements is o'er, And Heav'n's Artill'ry cease to flash and roar; Calm'd by His sovereign Nod, who bids Th' etherial Forces rage or fall; Who in dread Majesty serenely rides On wild unruly Hurricanes and Storms; While all their most outragious Forms Tamely obey His mighty Call, To purge the Air, or shake this guilty Ball, To scathe the sturdy Oak, or blast audacious Worms. Now recollect my Muse, the solemn Scene, And rouse the sleeping Tempest up again. II. The solemn Scene appears! My Eyes Behold the glomerating Deluge rise, And heavy Oceans floating up the Skies: First, distant Murm'rings from the West With rumbling Sound break through the Air, And bid the World, Prepare; Strait anxious Expectation heaves the Breast, Presaging Horror stares intense, And, shuddering, thro' the Window looks from whence The vapoury Magazines advance: When lo! th' aërial Oceans roll, Lour deeper still, and gain upon the Sky; And on the West-Wind's Wings, above Controul, Draw nearer still, and nearer as they fly. Now Fear begins to palpipate, And looks, and looks with doubtful Eye, If haply the collecting Tempest yet May dissipate, or pass obliquely by. III. But faster still the thick'ning Clouds advance, And cast a darker Frown; With fiercer Glare the livid Lightnings glance, And blust'ring Winds rush on with hollow, solemn Sound; Now through the bending Forests sweep, And rock the trembling Dome; Blend Rows of stately Trees in one long shatter'd Heap, Whirl Clouds of Dust on high, and wrap All Æther in a wide deep-louring Gloom. A dismal Twilight frowns; the Sun Through the thick Dust in vain emits his Ray; Absorpt in all-surrounding Clouds, the Day Sickens and faints at Noon. IV. And now above and all around Majestic Thunders roll with murm'ring Sound, Convulse the Air, and rock the Ground. Now rumbling in the dark aërial Hall, Till scattering far away The horrid Murmurings decay, And die away and fall. Now quick as Thought, to the keen Flash Sudden succeeds the horrid Crash Crush'd terrible, shocking the Heart; Amaz'd, aghast, and stunn'd we start, Entranc'd, and doubtful if we live, And the oppressive Shock survive. V. Still the dire Lightning with malignant Glare In flaming Curves wheels through the Air; Here a fierce Streak of angry Fire Sudden in various Windings cuts the Cloud; Another here, another there Darts on the winking Eye, till all the Hemisphere One wide-expanded Sheet of flashing Flame appear; While Peals on Peals still undistinguish'd crowd, And Heav'n's eternal Cannons roar aloud. VI. Now conscious Guilt the sudden Bolt awaits, And hardly hopes to 'scape; Struck with dire-boding Horror, palpitates, And startles at each bursting Clap. The Sword of Justice brandish'd high Draws fiery Circles through the Air; And as the curving Lightnings fly, And threatning Thunder murmurs through the Sky. The hardy Bosom pants, and thinks Destruction nigh. Ye hardy Sinners, yield and bow; Nor dare Omnipotence to strike the Blow; Heavy, but O! divinely slow! Say, are you able to withstand Th' almighty Vengeance of that Hand Which whirls the Bolt, and guides it where The flaming Embassy to bear, To rive the stately Pine, or burn and tear Th' aspiring Fabric, or with sulph'rous Breath Blast the audacious Wretch with sudden Death. VII. Happy the guiltless Conscience now! Serene he hears his Father's thundring Voice; Amid the Terrors calm, he dare rejoice, When loudest Thunders roar, and fiercest Tempests blow: His smiling Eyes with solemn Joy survey The harmless Lightnings flash along and play, And his Almighty Guardian's Pow'r display. Should angry Fire and Thunder rend Heav'n's Convex, and in one Confusion blend Heav'n, Earth, and Sea and Air: Should all the Wheels of Nature break, He undisturb'd would view the gen'ral Wreck, Still safe and happy in the Thund'rer's Care. VIII. Now tow'rd the South the pregnant Clouds Retire and leave the middle Sky, Discharging still prolific Floods On Hills and Valleys, Fields and Woods, And drop down Fatness as they fly. The winding Curves worm through the distant Cloud, And Sheets of Flame expand abroad; Now shut and open, open still and shut, And an immense Effulgence flash about. IX. Now safe from Harm, Presumption hears The distant Vengeance roar; Pale Guilt renounces all her Fears, And palpitates no more. Mistaken Guilt! t' erect thy Crest, And proudly boast the Danger past; Behold a blacker Tempest gathering last, The Skies with deeper Horrors overcast, And louder Thunder roar in the last Trumpet's Blast; Behold the Judge! He comes! He comes In vengeful Flames and stormy Glooms! The Clouds His Chariot, and the Winds His Wheels; See! how before him Lightnings flash, and play! Hark! Thunders loud proclaim, Prepare the Way! As down He rides from the eternal Hills. X. Supreme, almighty, venerable Name! Proprietor of Earth and Sea and Sky, Commander of the Magazines of Flame, That in the aërial Regions lie; With Awe profound Thy Greatness I adore, Who wings the Storm, and bids the Thunder roar, And keeps th' unruly El'ments subject to Thy Pow'r. XXVII. On bearing of the Rev. Mr. Samuel Blair's desperate Illness by common Fame, and Letters from Correspondents in Pennsylvania, June 9. 1751. What melancholy News does distant Fame To anxious Crowds and my shock'd Ears proclaim! With what strange Panic is each Bosom struck, As though some Pillar of the Heav'n's were broke! Alas! is Blair, the great, unrival'd Blair, Most dear to All, but oh! to me more dear; My Father! Tutor! Friend! each tender Name That can the softest, warmest Passions claim! My faithful Guide to Science and to Truth, In the raw Years of unexperienced Youth: Ah! is the heav'nly Man just on the Wing, And to his native Skies about to spring? About to leave us mourning here below, And 'mong us share the Remnant of his Woe. Ah! does he pine away in hectic Fire, Anhelant, panting, ready to expire? Oh! cruel Fame! why didst thou haste thy Flight, To bring the inauspicious News to Light? Ah! cruel Correspondents! to reveal The dismal Tidings Love would fain conceal. Why did not Tears blot out th' Intelligence? Or your sad Hands tremble to guide your Pens? Oh! had you not the dismal! News divulg'd, My Mind had still the pleasing Dream indulg'd; Still feign'd my Blair with Health and Vigour blest, With some grand Purpose labouring in his Breast; In studious Thought pursuing Truth divine, 'Til the full Demonstration round him shine; Or from the sacred Desk, proclaiming loud His Master's Message to th' attentive Crowd; While dubious Truth with bright Conviction glares, And coward Error shrinks and disappears; While Quick Remorse the hardy Sinner feels, And Calvary's Balm the bleeding Conscience heals. But now alas! the sweet Delusion's fled; My Blair is dying, or perhaps is dead; Or hast'ning to the calm celestial Shore, Or safe arriv'd, and all the Dangers o'er. Even now perhaps, releas'd from cumb'rous Clay, His Soul expatiates in immortal Day; Serenely basking in the Smiles of God, With Fellow-Angels in their blest Abode. Pardon, Blest Shade! the Ravings of my Love, That would recall thee from the Bliss above; Would wish thee down in these sad Realms again, From Choirs of Angels to converse with Men; Ungrateful Men, who broke thy Heart, and long Withstood the strong Persuasion of thy Tongue; Baffled thy Love, and Vanity pursu'd, Deaf to thy Calls, deaf to a Saviour's Blood! Oh! might'st thou from the Dead return again. And that strange unknown World disclose to Men! Apostles from the Dead sure could not preach in vain. Superfluous Wish! What could'st thou teach us more, Than thy divine Discourses did before? But if in mortal Climes be still thy Stay, O! can our Pray'rs the fatal Hour delay? Prevail with Heav'n to spare thy sacred Breath, And snatch thee from th' impending Hand of Death? Come, Saints, your Importunities renew; Try what th' united Force of fervent Pray'r can do. Believing Pray'r, eternal Truth has sworn, Sha'n't pant in vain, but bring a rich Return: 'Twill gain this Blessing from propitious Heav'n; Or greater, if a greater can be giv'n. “Thou sovereign Arbiter of Life and Death, “At whose almighty Nod we catch and yield out Breath; “Whose fiat organiz'd our mortal Clay, “And can repair it in its last Decay, “And from the greedy Grave snatch the expected Prey: “Oh! hear the bursting, deep, united Groan, “That from ten thousand Hearts arises to Thy Throne; “Restore our Prophet!—Best for him, 'tis true, “To die; but oh! what shall poor Zion do? “Zion whose Foes are many, Friends are few! “See! how she languishes in plaintive Grief; “By Blair's Recovery only hopes Relief. “Where shall the wounded, tortur'd Conscience find “A healing Hand so skilful and so kind? “Where heav'nly Truth so firm an Advocate? “Or dubious Minds so certain Conduct get? “Restore our Prophet, and his Health renew; “For oh! we need him more than Heav'n can do. “There Myriads of Thy Ministers of Flame “Perform Thy Orders and adore Thy Name. “But here, alas! how few prepar'd like Blair “Thy sacred Message to the World to bear? “With equal Skill eternal Things to shew? “And guide Thy Churches militant below! “Restore our Prophet, Lord! and in his Stead “Let worthless me be to the Skies convey'd. “Thy earthly House such useless Lumber may “Resign; but oh! snatch not our Blair away.” But even his Worth now bids us to despair, And threatens the Denial of our Pray'r; His Worth that makes his sacred Life so dear. So great, so heav'nly, so divine a Mind Demands Employment of a nobler Kind. What Earth could teach, he learn'd, and now must rise To a superior Class above the Skies. Too much refin'd, in this dark World to bear The humble Place of Zion's Minister; Heav'n calls him to sustain some nobler Function there: With Gabriel to perform the Orders given, And bear Jehovah's Errands thro' the Vast of Heav'n; Prompt as th' angelic Armies to obey, Fervent and bright and vigorous as they. Heav'n kind to him, will not consent to hear, Nor curse him with the Answer of our Pray'r. Oh! did my cruel Distance but allow, I'd pay the last sad Offices I owe: With tender Hand support thy fainting Head, Wipe off thy mortal Sweat, and weep around thy Bed; I'd view thee struggling in the Grasp of Death, And share the Anguish of thy parting Breath; Thy languishing Francisca's Grief allay, As drown'd in Tears, she hovers o'er thy Clay; Thy sacred Reliques to the Grave attend, And cry, “There softly rest, my Father, Brother, Friend!” But ah! these Eyes shall see my Blair no more, 'Till my poor Pilgrimage, like his, is o'er, And we both meet on the eternal Shore. Yet though this cruel Distance lies between, Officious Fancy paints the dismal Scene; Even now the mournful Images arise, And various Shapes of Sorrow stalk before mine Eyes, There lies my Blair, suffus'd with clammy Sweat, Ghastly and pale; the Pulses cease to beat; The Springs of Life relax; the purple Stream Stagnates; his Eyes in misty Darkness swim; A deadly Cold creeps on from every Part, Benumbs his Limbs, and steals upon his Heart; And see at length in a long deep-fetch'd Groan The Soul's dismist, and flies to Worlds unknown. Delug'd in Sorrow, there Francisca stands, And twing'd with parting Anguish, wrings her Hands; Like the poor widow'd Turtle, vents her Grief, Her Tears indulges, and despairs Relief; Surveys the World, but sees no Refuge there, Her only Confidence in Heav'n and Pray'r. Thy infant Train, whose little Tongues had scarce Learn'd to pronounce thee Father, at thy Hearse, Or round thy Bed, burst their full Hearts in Sighs, While the big Tear sincere swells in their Eyes, And their loud filial Griefs break out in piteous Cries. Through thy once favour'd Flock the Sorrow spreads, And desp'rate Grief a thousand Hearts invades: Each fears lest 'twas his Guilt that did provoke Incensed Heav'n to give the dreadful Stroke. Now 'mong the Remnant of the sacred Train They search for one to fill his Place in vain. Compar'd with him, the most exalted Tongue, But mangles Truth, and does the Subject Wrong. From others heav'nly Truths insipid seem To them whose Relish was refin'd by him. Still farther spreads th' extensive Grief around Each Bosom feels the Anguish of the Wound, And bursting Groans from Breast to Breast rebound. Zion her Loss through all her Temples wails, And spreads the dismal Eccho round her Hills. To this far Clime the mournful Sound shall roll, And with fresh Anguish twinge my bleeding Soul. His dear sad Mem'ry on my Heart shall rest, While vital Breath inspires my heaving Breast; Mix with my tender'st Thoughts, and often move The doleful Anguish of bereaved Love, 'Till our Reunion heals the Wound Above. Since the Writing of this, I have received the melancholy News of the Reverend Mr. Blair's triumphant and joyful Transition through the Valley of the Shadow of Death—My Father! my Father! the Chariots of Israel, and the Horse-Men thereof!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">?????? ????????? ???? ? ?? ?????????, ?????, ?? ???????? ???????? ?????, ??????????. Hesiod imitat. Thus translated by Dr. Watts, Pierian Muses, fram'd for heav'nly Lays, Descend, and sing the God your Father's Praise.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">UNCOLLECTED POEMS [THIS UNCULTIVATED LAND] Say, shall a Brother, Sir, nay more, a Friend To you these rude Effects of Friendship send? A Muse untutor'd vent the ardent Fires, Tho' unpoetic, which fond Love inspires? Or shall I check her with impos'd Constraint? And cease to give the Tender Passion vent? On you perhaps, whose Eyes &amp; Ears &amp; Heart Are charm'd with Works of Nature &amp; of Art, With which the Wise Creator's Mighty Hand, Or Human Skill has grac'd the British Land, Unseas'nably these Verses may intrude, And Love itself appears impertinent &amp; rude; Therefore I promise, to appease your Mind, I'll take it well to be repaid in Kind. How gladly, did my Circumstance allow, Wou'd I pass o'er the boisterous Ocean too! And dare the Dangers of each distant Shore, The Works of Nature &amp; of Arts t'explore! glad wou'd I visit every knowing Sage In Countries ripen'd into Sense by Age. Knowledge transported from the farthest Clime Wou'd compensate the Trouble and the Time. Knowledge! That shining Pearl! The Value more Than all the Gold on the rich Indian Shore. But ah! in this uncultivated Land, Where Ignorance usurps supreme Command, Where raw, unripen'd Wit, &amp; infant Sense Produces nothing but Impertinence, And the fair Muses in a Place so rude, But seldom light, &amp; never take Abode, Here, unimprov'd, I must my Moments spend, And the bright Pearl forever unobtain'd. But you, Dear Sir, whom a more pleasing Fate Directs unerring to the Muses' Seat, (For Love persuades me, you are safe arriv'd, And the Persuasion's pleasing, when believ'd) Lay up the greatest Cargo in your Mind, Safe from the Ocean's Rage, &amp; stormy Wind; Th'immortal Mind demands, your highest Care; Liberal repose, your greatest Riches there; There treasure Knowledge; that, with generous Hand, When safe return'd to this unpolish'd Land, The sacred Treasure, you may wide disperse, And your instructive Passages rehearse. I entertain myself with Hopes of this, And such a Partnership will always please; For Knowledge bought by Wholesale or Retail T'enrich the Purchaser will never fail. But I forbear—The mean, self-conscious Muse, When Eyes on English Ground her Lays peruse, Retires &amp; blushes. Higher she cou'd rise, And these low, creeping strains with Scorn despise, Had some Britannic Hand her Pinions prunn'd, And her young Voice to loftier Numbers tun'd. [A PRAYER IN TIME OF STORMS] May he whose Nod the Hurricanes &amp; Storms And blustering Waves in all their dreadful Forms With calm adoring Reverence obey; May He with friendly Vigilance preside O'er the outragious Winds &amp; boisterous Tide, And safe thro' Crowds of Deaths conduct your dang'rous Way! ELEGIAC VERSES on the lamented Death of the Rev. Mr. Samuel Blair, Who made his triumphant Excite from this mortal Stage July 5. 1751, with the deserve! Character of a good Scholar, a masterly genius, a sincere Christian, and successful Minister of the Gospel. Hark! a long doleful Eccho round me groans, Heard by deaf Rocks, and felt by senseless Stones. The sympathizing Hills of Zion toss, The mournful Eccho, and lament the loss. Ten Thousand Bosoms feel a sudden Wound, And Crowds grow pale, and shudder at the Sound. From Heart to Heart with quick Contagion spreads Th' insectious Grief, and half the Land inwades. To this far Clime the dismal Tidings flies, And Deluges of Sorrow drown mine Eyes. Now hardy Souls, that never wept before, Disolve;—nor is it strange, since BLAIR IS NOW NO MORE, BLAIR IS NO MORE!—Then this poor World has lost. As rich a Jewel as her Stores could boast. Heav'n in just Vengeance has recall'd again, Its faithful Envoy from the Sons of Men: Advanc'd him from his pious Toils below, In Raptures there with kindred-Flames to glow. While hov'ring on the verge of Life he lay, Eager for Flight, and yet resign'd to stay; How oft' did we, in Agonies of Pray'r, Wrestle with Heav'n his sacred Breath to spare! Upon our rising Prophet fix our Sight, And anxious cry, “good Lord! delay his Flight”! But ah! his Worth but cherish'd our despair, And threaten'd the Denial of our Pray'r. So great, so heav'nly, so mature a Mind, Requir'd Employment of a nobler Kind. What Earth could teach, he learned; and now must rise, To a supperior Class above the Skies. Too much refin'd in this dark World to bear, The humble Place of Zion's Minister, Heav'n call'd him to sustain some nobler Function there: With Gabriel to perform the Orders giv'n, And bear Jehovah's Errands thro' the vast of Heav'n. Prompt as his Fellow-Angels to obey, Zealous and bright and vigorous as they. Heav'n kind to him, would not consent to hear, Nor curse him with the Answer of our Pray'r. Oh! could the Muse's languid colour's paint, The Man, the Scholar, Student, Preacher, Saint; I'd Place his Image full in public view; His Friends should know more than before they knew. His Foes astonish'd at his Virtues gaze, Or shrink confounded from th' oppressive Blaze. To trace his bright Example all should turn, And with the bravest Emulation burn. His Name should my poor Lays immortalize, 'Till he t'attest his Character arise, And the Great Judge th' Encomium ratifies. Propitious Heav'n endow'd the Man it lov'd, With Gifts t'adorn each Sphere in which he mov'd. An Intellect clear as the Blaze of Day; Sedate as Midnight, boundless as the Sea; Free as the Wind, yet steady as the Pole; Passive to Truth, impatient of controul From vulgar Error; regular and smooth As genuine Reason and harmonious Truth, Truth link'd to Truth, and Tho't to Tho't conjoin'd Spontaneous rose in his harmonious Mind. His rude unstudy'd Tho'ts in Order sprung, Exprest in equal Order by his Tongue; Clusters of ripen'd Sense on each young Period hung. His Passions vigo'rous, yet by Reason rul'd; By calmest Reason kindled, temper'd, cool'd. His Heart reserv'd as Prudence and confin'd; And yet as Truth sincere, as weeping Friendship kind. My Muse, now paint him in his studious Hours, In search of Truth exerting all his Pow'rs. To him familiar, Truths beyond the Reach Of vulgar Minds strain'd to the highest Stretch; His daring genius with exalted scorn, Forsakes the Path by hoary Custom worne: Eager to find a Treasure of his own, He tries new Paths and Regions yet unknown: Into th' Abyss of Science darts his Eye, Where the rude Elements of Knowledge lie: Where Truths with Errors wage eternal War, And Doubts with Embryo-Demonstrations jarr: A wasteful Chaos with wild Tempest tost, Whence cowards shrink, and where bold Wits are lost. Serene his plastic Mind digests the Mass, Assigns the blended El'ments each its Place; Ripens the Embryo-Notions into Truth, And gives to infant-Demonstration Growth. At length, behold! new Worlds of Knowledge rise, And sudden Light flash round the new-form'd Skies: Harmonious all the finish'd Systems roll, And Noon-Day Evidence illuminates the whole. Doubts disappear, and Error flies away, As Midnight Glooms before the rising Day. His Hands the new-found Stores around dispense, T' enlarge the petty Stock of common Sense. So yonder Sun, th' exhaustless Source of Day, To Earth's dark Caverns darts his vital Ray; Tranforms to Gold what was but Dross before, And ripens useless Stones to precious Oar; Transmits his radiant Influence thro' the Seas, To make the Ruby glow, the Di'mond blaze: These Secret Stores, collected and refin'd, Enrich the World, and polish Human Kind. Now with great Newton's Eyes he dares to look, On the wide Pages of deep Nature's Book. Reads the great Maker's Name in every Line; Above, below, around, his glories shine; Imprest on all in Characters divine. 'Till cold Philosophy, at length refin'd, Kindles to warm Devotion in his Mind. Adoring Transport, Pleasure, Love, Surprize, In sweet Confusion in his Bosom rise. So Boyle his Maker's Works explor'd; The more he knew, the humbler he ador'd. Now in the sacred Desk I see him rise, And well he acts the Herald of the Skies. Graceful Solemnity and striking Awe, Sit in his Looks, and deep Attention draw. His speaking Aspect (in the Bloom of Youth Rev'rend) declares unutterable Truth. Unthinking Crowds grow solemn as they gaze, And read his awful Message in his Face. Solemn, and conscious of the present God, As tho' before th' eternal Throne he stood: Solemn, as when some Angel lifts on high, His awful Hand with God-like Majesty, And swears by the Unutterable Name; While trembling Rev'rence spreads thro' Nature's Frame. Thro' various mazes now his lips pursue Intricate Truths, and bring them full to view. Celestial Mystries, hid from human sense, Shine forth in their Almighty Evidence. Bright Demonstration every doubt controuls, And forces the Assent of sceptic Souls. Glaring Conviction with resistless Light, Flashes on Minds wrapt in eternal Night. Dull Ignorance starts at th' unwellcome glare, And coward Error dreads th' unequal War. Triumphant Truth assumes her native State, And trusts her Rights to such an Advocate. So when the Splendour of the Morn appears, Deformity its native Horrors wear: Beauty puts on her charms; Confusion flies, And well-distinguish'd, Objects round us rise. Conscious of Guilt the Ravagers of Night Abscond from the ungrateful glare of Light Thick Glooms, obscure as Error, disappear; And Day succeeds, as Demonstration clear. Now to secure Impenitents he turns; And from his Tongue Almighty Vengeance burns. The vengeful Flames and Thunders of the Law, Equal the Terrors trembling Muses saw. He sets incens'd Omnipotence in Arms, And sounds the final Trumpet's dread Alarms. The Charmer Sin with hideous Aspect glares, And see! in naked Horrors Hell appears! The wasteful Deeps lie open to our Eyes, And Flames and Groans and Curses blended rise. Jehovah frowns; the Sword of Justice drawn Above; below the Gulphs of Tophet yawn! See! The great Judge his burning Throne ascend, Death and Destruction on his Nod attend. Hark! A dread Clangor! Death's old Prisons burst, And sudden Life inspires the rising Dust. In shudd'ring Expectation Millions stand, To hear their Sentence at the King's left Hand: Confounded with the Sound “Depart,” they shrink, Screaming away, and down to Hell they sink. The Elements dissolve; Earth, Skies and Seas, Vanish in one fierce universal Blaze. The hardy Sinner, happily deceiv'd, Now feels the Pains he ne'er before believ'd: With Bright Description dazzled, knows not where He is, but seems the Vengeance now to bear. Infernal Twinges thro' his Bosom dart, And Hell's dire Pangs already rend his Heart; He thinks the Miseries describ'd, his own; Sinks in Despair, and Cries, Undone! Undone! “Lift up (says Blair) lift up thy dying Eyes: “Say, who hangs yonder rack'd in Agonies? “Pity and Torture, Love commixt with Pain, “Throbs in his Heart, and pants in every Vein. “See! from his Hands and Feet his Head and Side, “Rivers of Blood and Mercy mingled glide! “Jesus! The Saviour!—Yes! 'Tis He!—Forbear, “Thou dying Sinner, to indulge Despair. “Believe and Live, there wash thy foulest Stains, “In this dear deluge from his bleeding Veins. “Now Justice smiles; thy Guilt appears no more; “And Sinai's Thunders cease to flash and roar. “Of Calv'ry's Balm receive a cordial Drop, “And black despair will brighten into Hope: “The tortur'd Conscience no more agoni'ze; “But hellish Fears to heav'nly Transports rise.” Oh! here the raptur'd Muse could ever dwell; And still with unremitting Wonder tell, How oft' has Blair allur'd our Minds to rove, Thro' all the Myst'ries of redeeming Love; Jesus display'd in his Almighty Charms, To draw reluctant Sinners to his Arms; With Jesus' charming Name cold Morality. fir'd And every Theme with Gospel-Sweets inspir'd. His darling Subject this: A heav'nly Flame Sublim'd his Language when he touch'd the Theme, This Cord of Love around our Hearts he threw, And backward Souls with pleasing Vi'lence drew. Reluctant and with pitying Fears, he shew'd, The vengeful Terrors of an angry God; But Oh! With Joy proclaim'd a Saviour's peaceful Blood. Conscious of all the Sorrows others feel, He kill'd to cure, and wounded but to heal. But in what nobler Language shall I paint, The pure, Seraphic Ardors of the Saint! His Life a fixt unerring walk with God; A constant Progress in the heav'nly Road. His Heart the Seat of constant Peace and Love; There glow'd the Passions Seraphs feel above; There pleas'd and unmolested dwelt the heav'nly Dove. His Breath like grateful Incense, to the Skies, Did daily in refin'd Devotion rise. His Soul exerted with his praying Breath, Th' Almighty Importunity of Faith. Hence guilty Heads escape the falling Blow, And Blessings to unworthy Millions flow, Nations partook the bounty of his Pray'r; And future Times the Benefit shall share. This gen'rous Legacy he left Mankind, Which, while he sleeps in Death, Heav'n will remind. So while great Moses rais'd his praying Hands, Exod. 11. 12. Vict'ry and Triumph wait on Isra'l's Bands. Each warm Petition slays a haughty Foe; And Am'lek Falls, but Moses strikes the Blow. But ah! The melancholy Hour appears, When Blair must rise, and leave the World in Tears. With zeal consum'd, with pious Labour spent, Too much refin'd for this gross Element, Mature for Heav'n, he breaks the Pris'n of Clay; Soars, and expatiates in eternal Day: Enjoys the Glories he describ'd unseen, And ev'n his Views immense Improvements gain. Heav'n smil'd upon his Life; but then most kind When friendly Death releas'd th' imprison'd Mind: But oh! The Loss to those condemn'd to stay behind! Extensive as the Loss, Oh! be the Grief; And in a hopeless Case, despair Relief. Sinners, lament! that animating Breath By which Heav'n Life inspir'd, is stopt in Death. Saints join your Tears! no more shall ye rejoice, Beneath the chearing Influence of his Voice. Ye doubting Souls, lament! now you may rove, Perplext and doubtful since our Blair's remove. Surviving Remant of the sacred Tribe, Who knew the Worth these plaintive Lays describe; Tennent's, three Worthies of immortal Fame, Brethren by Office, Birth, in Heart and Name: Finley, who full enjoy'd th' unbosom'd Friend; Rodgers, whose Soul he like his own refin'd, When all Attention, eager to admit The flowing Knowledge, at his rev'rend Feet Raptur'd we sat; and thou above the Rest, Brother and Image of the dear deceas'd, Surviving Blair! Oh! let spontaneous flow The Floods of tributary Grief you owe. And (in your Number if so mean a Name, May the sad Honour of chief Mourner claim) Oh! may my filial Tears more copious flow, And swell the Tide of universal Woe. O Blair! whom all the tend'rest Names commend, My Father, Tutor, Pastor, Brother, Friend! While Distance the sad Priviledge denies, O'er thy dear Tomb to vent my bursting Eyes, The Muse erects (the sole return allow'd) This humble Monument of Gratitude. Faint are her Lays; the mournful Theme she sings, Extinguishes her Fire, and cloggs her Wings. Affected Sorrow in a loftier strain, May flourish, and with nicer Art complain. These elegiac Numbers would appear, More warm and noble, were they less sincere. “Grief unaffected suits but ill with Art, “Or flowing Numbers with a bleeding Heart.” Mr. Tickel on Mr. Addison's Death. But tho' eternal Silence seize my Tongue, And the Dumb Muse no more attempt a Song; Yet to Life's close, my grateful Soul shall feel, The secret Sorrow Language fails to tell: In all my gay or studious Moments prove The pining Anguish of bereaved Love, 'Till our Reunion heal th' invit'rate Wound above. Lamented Shade! tho' rais'd beyond the Reach Of mortal Sense, my Tho'ts their Pinions Stretch In quest of thee; thro' unknown Regions rove, To find thee 'mong the shining Hosts above. But ah! insufferable Light surrounds, Thy Mansion, and my feeble Sight confounds. How dark the Views benighted Mortals have, Of that strange neighb'ring World beyond the Grave! O! Where in the unbounded Realms of Space, Has Heav'n allotted thee thy blissful Place? What glorious Novelties rush full to View, Which not before ev'n they vast Genius knew? Dost thou with Seraphs Hymn th' eternal Throne, In Strains which Seraphs would not blush to own? O lost in studious Tho't, as usual, rove, Thro' all the Mazes of redeeming Love? Or still the gen'rous Labour undergo, As Guardian-Angel to the Church below— But this wild License, raving Muse! Restrain; Nor pry to Things hid from the Sons of Men: Ere long Eternity's amazing Light, Will shew these Myst'ries naked to my Sight. Blest Shade! Adieu!—When a few Days have run, Their tedious Rounds, my painful Labour done, Ripen'd for Heav'n, may I resign my Breath, And smile like thee at the grim Face of Death! Foll'wing the Path thy Feet unerring trod, May I like thee ascend the heav'nly Road. And ever dwell with thee beneath the Smiles of God! There in divinest Intimacy spend, Eternal Years in Bliss and Friendship ne'er to End! Hanover in Virginia, November 10th 1751. She cecinit mærens. S. Davies. [Come, heav'nly pensive Contemplation, come] The following VERSES were composed by a Pious Clergyman in Virginia, who preaches to Seven Congregations, the nearest of which meets at the Distance of five Miles from his House, as he was returning Home in a very gloomy and rainy Night. Come, heav'nly pensive Contemplation, come, Possess my Soul, and solemn Thoughts inspire. The sacred Hours, that with too swift a Wing Incessant hurry by, nor quite claps'd, Demand a serious Close. Then be my Soul Sedate and solemn, as this Gloom of Night, That thickens round me. Free from Care, compos'd Be all my Soul, as this dread Solitude, Thro' which with gloomy Joy I make my Way. Above these Clouds, above the spacious Sky, In whose vast Arch these cloudy Oceans roll, Dispensing Fatness to the World below; There dwells The Majesty, whose single Hand Props universal Nature, and who deals His lib'ral Blessings to this little Globe, The Residence of Worms; where Adam's Sons, Thoughtless of him who taught their Souls to think, Ramble in vain Pursuits. The Hosts of Heav'n, Cherubs and Seraphs, Potentates and Thrones, Array'd in glorious Light, hover on Wing Before his Throne, and wait his sov'reign Nod: With active Zeal, with sacred Rapture fir'd, To his extensive Empire's utmost Bound They bear his Orders, and his Charge perform, Yet he, ev'n he (ye Ministers of Flame, Admire the Condescension and the Grace!) Employs a Mortal, form'd of meanest Clay, Debas'd by Sin, whose best Desert is Hell; Employs him to proclaim a Saviour's Name, And offer Pardon to a rebel World. This Day my Tongue, the Glory of my Frame, Enjoy'd the Honour of his Advocate: Immortal Souls, of more transcendent Worth Than Ophir, or Peru's exhaustless Mines, Are trusted to my Care. Important Trust! What if some wretched Soul (tremendous Thought!) Once favour'd with the Gospel's joyful Sound, Now lost, for ever lost thro' my Neglect, In dire infernal Glooms, with flaming Tongue, Be heaping Execrations on my Head, Whilst here secure I dream my Life away! What if some Ghost, cut off from Life and Hope, With fierce despairing Eyes up-turn'd to Heav'n, That wildly stare, and witness Horrors huge, Be roaring horrid, “Lord, avenge my Blood On that unpitying Wretch, who saw me run With full Career the dire enchanting Road To these devouring Flames, yet warn'd me not; Or faintly warn'd me, and with languid Tone, And cool Harangue, denounced eternal Fire, And Wrath divine?” At the dread shocking Thought My Spirit shudders, and all my inmost Soul Trembles and shrinks. Sure, if the plaintive Cries Of Spirits reprobate can reach the Ear Of their Great Judge, they must be Cries like these. But if the meanest of the happy Choir, That with eternal Symphonies surround The heav'nly Throne, can stand, and thus declare, “I owe it to his Care that I am here, Next to Almighty Grace: His faithful Hand, Regardless of the Frowns he might incur, Snatch'd me, reluctant, from approaching Flames, Ready to catch, and burn unquenchable. May richest Grace reward his pious Zeal With some bright Mansion in this World of Bliss.” Transporting Thought! Then blessed be the Hand That form'd my elemental Clay to Man, And still supports me. 'Tis worth while to live, If I may live to Purposes so great, Awake my dormant Zeal! For ever flame With gen'rous Ardors for immortal Souls; And may my Head, and Tongue, and Heart and all, Spend and be spent in Service so divine. The Rev?. M?. Samuel Davies, Minister of the Gospel To the Congregation of Hanover County In the Colony of Virginia. A Token for the Sacrament. Do this says Christ 'till Time shall end. In Mem'ry of your dying Friends Meet at my Table and record The Love of your departed Lord. [SIN THE DESPOILER] Sin haunts my steps, where e'er I fly, In every place is ever nigh As Streams from Mountain-Springs attend, The Trav'llers still as they des[c]end; So sin, the source of all my Woe, Still bubbles up where e'er I go. Sin spread a dark, tremendous Cloud Of Horrors o'er my Solitude: Presents a thousand Forms of Death To shock my Soul from Duty's Path: Wraps present Time in dreadful Gloom, And damps my Hope of Time to come Intimidates my Soul ashore, And makes old Ocean louder roar; Gives darker Horrors to the Storm, And Danger a more shocking Form. Companion dire by Land or Sea! No Bliss, no calm, 'till freed from thee, And Change of Place is Change of Misery. [TRUST NOT BEAUTY] Does Beauty spread her Charms? does Wealth o'erflow? Does Health bloom fresh, or youthful Vigour glow? Are all Earth's Blessings in Profusion pour'd? And all these Sweets with no Affliction sour'd? Ah! trust not these, to guard from early Death All these adorn'd the precious Dust beneath. Or Ye that in Beauty, or in Youth confide, Come view this Monument, Youth in flowery Bloom, Wither'd at Morn, lie mould'ring in this Tomb, And you may meet the same surprizing Doom. Or Thus Monument proclaims this solemn Truth, Beauty is fading, frail the Bloom of Youth; Life short, a Span, a Dream, an empty Shew, And all is fleeting Vanity below. Careless Spectator! learn from hence to die; Prepare, prepare for Immortality. [THE PIOUS MIND IN A TIME OF STORM] When the Storm thickens, and the Ocean rolls, When Nature trembles to the frightful Poles, The pious mind nor Doubts nor fears assail, Tempests are Zephyrs, or a gentler Gale. [TO CHARA] While objects various, strange and new, In numerous Prospects rush to view, The Tho'ts of Friends, the Tho'ts of Home Engross my Heart and still find Room. Chara with what strange, magic Art, Dost thou, so distant, charm my Heart? Not seas can quench, nor Distance cool The flame of Love that fires my Soul. Not works of Nature or of Art Can raze thine Image from my Heart. I shrink to view those Days to come, While cruel Absence is my Doom. Indulgent Heav'n! contract those Days, And give my anxious Bosom Ease. [“THE WAR OF THE ELEMENTS”] Inconstant, boistrous Element! the Type Of human Life. Now gentle Calms compose The wide-extended surface; to the Eye Opens a level Plain, a Sea of Glass, Smooth as the standing Pool, or purling stream, Or only rising gradual and slow In vast majestic swells, not wild, abrupt, A watry Precipice; such as these Eyes Now see collecting all their Terrors round, Ore every Tide. Above, the Clouds replete With Winds and angry Fire tremendous lower. The Lightening flashes a malignant Glare Thro' the thick Gloom, and helps but to descry The Horrors of the Dark, and Danger's Frown Now the fierce Flash spreads out in sheets of Flame Round Heav'n's wide Canopy—Mean Time the Winds Collect their Forces, and discharge their Rage On the fermenting Deep; ['till watery Hills,] And mountains rise, and roll along, beyond The Ken of light; or by quick-shifting Winds Driven adverse, dash in furious Conflict; then The mountains break, in a tumultous Roar; The angry foam flies up to Heaven in showers, And burns and sparkles in the briny Waves. Sure 'tis the War of Elements; the shock of Nature in Convulsions; 'tis the Wreck Of Worlds! What horrid Images can shew The dreadful Scene! What loud tremendous Sounds, What wild, tumultuous Verse can represent The blended Roar of Thunder, Winds and Waves In Tumult—Now how naturally Distress Casts up to Heaven the wild imploring Eye, And eager cries for Help—Now, now we sink! Strange! we survive the shock! Now fiercer still The Waves assault our Barque, convulse each Joint, And spread a Tremor thro' each Rib of Oak. Now we shall rise no more. Strange! we emerge Toss'd like a Cork, we float from Wave to Wave, From the huge, watry Precipice we plunge The yawning Gulph below; While howling Winds And roaring Waves, and midnight's sullen Glooms Surround us—O thou Ruler of the Seas, Send forth thy mighty Mandate, “Peace, be still,” And calm their Rage—But can even Mercy hear Such daring Rebels, who in one vile Breath Blend Prayers and Curses? But alas! my Heart Look home; thou art not innocent; my Guilt May hurl these furious Hurricanes in Air, And Arm each Billow of the Sea against me. But have not I, a suppliant at thy Throne, Indulgent Father, have not I bewailed my Guilt in deep Repentance? has not Faith Applied the Saviour's Blood?— [A STORM AT SEA] What Horrors crowd around! Destruction frowns In all its frightful shapes. The lowering Clouds Spread out their solid Glooms, and not a Star Emits a Ray of cheering Light. The Winds Discharge their whole Artillery; rear vast Piles Of Waves on Waves,—and watry Pyramids, Capt with white Foam, that lash'd to fiery Rage, Sparkles and burns: betwixt conflicting Seas, Toss'd like a Cork, alas! our feeble Barque, Our sole Defence, denies us Hope; the Waves In Deluges break o'er her. Hark! the Roar Of breaking Precipices, and the Howl Of Furious Winds, that from the Bottom turn The Wild, fermenting Ocean; while the Night Spreads her thick Glooms o'er all the dreadful Scene. The different States of Sinners and Saints in the Wreck of Nature. Isaiah xxiv. 18–20. Long Metre. I How great, how terrible that God, Who shakes Creation with his Nod! He frowns, and Earth's Foundations shake, And all the Wheels of Nature break. II Crush'd under Guilt's oppressive Weight The Globe now totters to its Fate, Trembles beneath its guilty Sons, And for Deliv'rance loudly groans: III And see the glorious dreadful Day That takes th' enormous Load away! See Ocean, Earth, all Nature's Frame Sink in one universal Flame. IV Where now, O where shall Sinners seek For Shelter in the gen'ral Wreck? Shall falling Rocks be o'er them thrown? See Rocks, like Snow, dissolving down. V In vain for Mercy now they cry; In Lakes of liquid Fire they lie; There on the flaming Billows tost, For ever, O for ever lost! VI But, Saints, undaunted and serene Your Eyes shall view the dreadful Scene; Your Saviour lives, tho' Worlds expire, And Earth and Skies dissolve in Fire. VII Jesus, the helpless Creature's Friend, To Thee my All I dare commend: Thou can'st preserve my feeble Soul, When Lightnings blaze from Pole to Pole. LVI. National Judgments deprecated, and National Mercies pleaded. Amos iii. 1–6. Long Metre. By the Reverend Samuel Davies, A. M This and the following Hymn were printed by the Author with two Discourses on Amos iii. 1–6. intitled, Virginia's Danger and Remedy, and occasioned by the severe Drought in sundry Parts of that Country, and the Defeat of General Braddock, 1756.. I. While o'er our guilty Land, O Lord, We view the Terrors of thy Sword; While Heav'n its fruitful Show'rs denies, And Nature round us fades and dies; II. While Clouds collecting o'er our Head Seem charg'd with Wrath to smite us dead, Oh! whither shall the Helpless fly? To whom but Thee direct their Cry? III. The helpless Sinner's Cries and Tears Are grown familiar to thine Ears; Oft has thy Mercy sent Relief, When all was Fear and hopeless Grief: IV. On Thee our Guardian God we call, Before thy Throne of Grace we sall; And in there no Deliv'rance there? And must we perish in Despair? V. See, we repent, we weep, we mourn, To our forsaken God we turn; O spare our guilty Country, spare The Church which Thou hast planted here! VI. Revive our with'ring Fields with Rain, Let Peace compose our Land again, Silence the horrid Noise of War! O spare a guilty People, spare! VII. We plead thy Grace, indulgent God; We plead thy Son's atoning Blood, We plead thy gracious Promises, And are they unavailing Pleas? VIII. These Pleas, by Faith urg'd at thy Throne, Have brought ten thousand Blessings down On guilty Lands in helpless Woe; Let them prevail to save us too! On the same. Long Metre. I While various Rumours spread abroad, And hold our Souls in dread Suspence, We look, we fly to Thee our God; Our Refuge is thy Providence. II This Wilderness, so long untill'd, An hideous Waste of barren Ground, Thy Care has made a fruitful Field, With Peace and Plenty richly crown'd. III Thy Gospel spreads an heav'nly Day Throughout this once benighted Land, A Land once wild with Beasts of Prey, By impious Heathen Rites profan'd; IV Thy Gospel, like a gen'rous Vine, Its Branches wide began to spread, Refresh'd our Souls with heav'nly Wine, And bless'd us with its cooling Shade; V And shall these Mercies now remove? Shall Peace and Plenty fly away? The Land, that Heav'n did thus improve, Will Heav'n give up an helpless Prey? VI O must we bid our God adieu! And must the Gospel take its Flight! O shall our Children never view The Beamings of that heav'nly Light! VII Forbid it, Lord! with Arms of Faith We'll hold Thee fast, and Thou shalt stay; We'll cry, while we have Life or Breath, Our God, do not depart away! VIII If broken Hearts and weeping Eyes Can find Acceptance at thy Throne, Lo, here they are: this Sacrifice Thou wilt accept thro' Christ thy Son. [FRONTIER WARFARE] Extract from a poem on the barbarities of the French, and their savage allies and proselytes, on the frontiers of Virginia. By Sam. Davies, A.M. Long had a mungrel French and Indian brood Our peaceful frontiers drench'd with British blood. There Horror rang'd, and her dire ensigns bore, Raw scalps her trophies, stiff with clotted gore; The heart and bowels smoaking on the ground, Still warm with life, and mangled corpses round. There buzzards riot, and each ravenous fowl, And all the monsters of the desart howl, And gnaw the naked bones; there mix in fight, Like Gallic tyrants, for their neighbour's right. See yonder cottage, once the peaceful seat Of all the pleasures of the nuptial state. The sturdy son, the prattling infant, there, And spotless virgin, bless'd the happy pair. In gentle sleep, undreaming ill, they lay; But oh! no more to see the chearful day. Mad with the passions of an Indian foul, The tawny furies in the thickets prowl, Thro' the dark night, and watch the dawn of day, To spring upon their unsuspecting prey. The musket's deadly sound, or murder's screams, Alarm the slumb'rers, and break off their dreams. They start, and struggle, but in vain the strife, To save their own, a child's, or parent's life, Or dearer, still, a tender bleeding wife. Now mingling blood with blood, confus'd they die, And blended in promiscuous carnage lie. Brains, hearts and bowels, swim in streams of gore, Besmear the walls, and mingle on the floor. Men, children, houses, cattle, harvests, all, In undistinguishing destruction fall. The infernal savages lift up the yell, And rouse the terrors of the lowest hell: Suck the fresh wound, in bloody puddles swill, And thence imbibe a fiercer rage to kill. From the raw skull the hairy scalp they tare, And the dire pledge in savage triumph wear. But see! on Mononghala's fatal banks, Blood flow in larger streams, and thicker ranks Of heroes fall. Unfortunately brave, Braddock alone was honour'd with a grave; A hasty grave, in consternation made, And there, uncoffin'd and unshrouded, laid. There Halket, Shirley, there a num'rous band Of brave Virginians, (oh! my native land! How great thy loss! yet greater thy renown, To call these brave heroic souls thy own.) Ah! there they fell, to wolves and bears a prey, Or human savages, more fierce than they. There men and steeds in common ruin lie; Some lifeless; wounded some; some seek to fly, In vain; the skulking savages forsake Their Thickets; and their thirst of blood to slake, Like furious lions, rush into the field, To butcher those not mercifully kill'd. Now direr terrors o'er the wounded spread, They envy now their fellow-soldiers dead. For simple death, or death by hands of men, Was now a privilege they wished in vain. Now horrid shrieks, and dying groans and cries, Mixt with wild shouts of Indian triumphs rise: Tygers and bears felt pity at the sound, And wilds, and vales, and mountains trembled round. The dying now just ope' the closing eye, And tawny murd'rers hov'ring o'er them spy. The ear just stopt in death perceives their yell, And trembles lest it be the cry of hell. The wounded feel the blow that ends the strife, Extinguishing the faint remains of life, And kindly leaves them senseless to the scalping knife. Infernal weapon!—Death o'erspreads the plain With heaps of carnage: pray'rs and tears are vain. Loud cries for mercy vengeance but provoke, And supplicating hands but tempt the stroke. The bended knee but stoops to take the blow, As hell itself, implacable's the foe. There toss'd in heaps, or scattered o'er the plain, Naked, unburied, lie the mighty slain. The soil is with their blood luxuriant grown, And still their bones lie whitening in the sun. There birds of prey long fed, and wheel'd their flight; And savage beasts carous'd and howl'd by night. Oh fatal spot! with theee be nam'd no more, Cannae, Pharsalia, wash'd with Roman gore: There men with men, here hellish furies fight, Riot in slaughter, and in blood delight.— The Blessing of Hope in Death; or Comfort in a dying Hour earnestly implored. Proverbs xiv. 32. Long Metre. I Yes; I must bow my Head and die! What then can bear my Spirit up? In Nature's last Extremity Who can afford one Ray of Hope? II Then all created Comforts fail, And Earth speaks nothing but Despair; And you, my Friends, must bid Farewel, And leave your Fellow-Traveller. III Yet, Saviour, thine Almighty Pow'r Ev'n then can sure Support afford, Ev'n then that Hope shall smile secure, That's now supported by thy Word. IV Searcher of Hearts! O try me now, Nor let me build upon the Sand; O teach me now myself to know, That I may then the Trial stand! The universal Call of God to Repentance. Acts xvii. 30. Common Metre. I Hark! from the Skies the great Command Sounds thro' the Earth abroad; “Repent, ye Sons of Men, repent; “Return unto your God.” II The Times of Ignorance are past, The Gospel-Day now shines: The sov'reign Judge no more o'erlooks, But marks down all your Crimes. III Sinners on Thrones, in Cottages, All on this guilty Ball, Whate'er you are, whate'er you be, This Charge includes you all. IV Come Thousands then, come all Mankind Fall at your Sov'reign's Feet: With broken Hearts, and weeping Eyes, Approach the Mercy-Seat. V There sits the Sin-forgiving God, And spreads his Arms to All; There his free Pardons deals abroad To each who hears his Call. AN HYMN BY THE AUTHOR OF THE SERMON FOREGOING, (Varied from Dr. Doddridge) With grateful hearts come let us sing, The gifts of our ascended King; Though long since gone from earth below, Through every age his bounties flow. The Saviour when to heav'n he rose In splendid triumph o'er his foes, His gifts on rebel men bestow'd, And wide his royal bounties flow'd. Hence sprung th' apostles' honour'd name, More glorious than the hero's fame; Evangelists and prophets hence Derive the blessings they dispense. In humbler forms, to bless our eyes, Pastors from hence and teachers rise; Who, though with feebler rays they shine, Still gild a long-extended line. From Christ their various gifts derive, And fed by Christ their graces live: While, guarded by his mighty hand, 'Midst all the rage of hell they stand. Thus teachers, teachers shall succeed When we lie silent with the dead! And unborn churches, by their care, Shall rise and flourish large and fair. Pastors and people, join and sing, This constant, inexhausted spring, Whence through all ages richly flow The streams that cheer the church below. Self-Examination. Gal. iv. 19, 20. Long Metre. I What strange Perplexities arise? What anxious Fears, and Jealousies? What Crowds in doubtful Light appear? How few, alas! approv'd and clear! II And what am I?—My Soul, awake, And an impartial Prospect take: Does no dark Sign, no Ground of Fear In Practice, or in Heart appear? III What Image does my Spirit bear? Is Jesus form'd, and living there? Say, do his Lineaments Divine In Thought, and Word, and Action shine? IV Searcher of hearts, O search me still; The Secrets of my Soul reveal, My Fears remove: let me appear To God, and my own Conscience clear: V Scatter the Clouds, that o'er my Head Thick Glooms of dubious Terrors spread; Lead me into celestial Day, And to my Self my Self display: VI May I at that blest World arrive, Where Christ thro' all my Soul shall live, And give full proof that he is there, Without one gloomy Doubt or Fear. An HYMN From Dr. Doddridge, varied. “Ye feeble Lambs, fly to His Arms, That open wide for you; He'll save you from the Lion's Rage, And all th' infernal Crew.” [CHRISTIAN, PREACHER, FRIEND] The Colours of Expression are too faint, Let Thought describe what Thought alone can paint: Think what the Christian, Preacher, Friend should be, You've then his Character: for such was He. The Glories of God in pardoning Sinners. As the Old 112?? Psalm. Micah vii, 18. I Great God of Wonders! all thy Ways Are matchless, godlike, and divine, But the fair Glories of thy Grace More godlike and unrivall'd shine: Who is a pard'ning God like Thee? Or who has Grace so rich and free? II Crimes of such Horror to forgive, Such guilty daring Worms to spare, This is thy grand Prerogative, And none shall in the Honour share. Who is a pard'ning God like Thee? Or who has Grace so rich and free? III Angels and Men, resign your Claim To Pity, Mercy, Love, and Grace, These Glories crown Jehovah's Name With an incomparable Blaze. Who is a pard'ning God like Thee? Or who has Grace so rich and free? IV In Wonder lost, with trembling Joy, We take the Pardon of our God, Pardon for Crimes of deepest Die, A Pardon bought with Jesus' Blood. Who is a pard'ning God like Thee? Or who has Grace so rich and free? V O may this strange, this matchless Grace, This godlike Miracle of Love, Fill the wide Earth with grateful Praise, And all th' Angelic Hosts above! Who is a pard'ning God like Thee? Or who has Grace so rich and free? Christ's Tenderness to the bruised Reed and smoking Flax. Matthew xii. 20. Long Metre. I Weak in myself, and burden'd too, Lo here I am, a bruised Reed; And see th' Almighty Conqu'ror comes, And I might feel his angry Tread. II But, O the condescending Grace, The humble Pity of his Soul, He sees the Straw, he sees its State, Stoops down, supports, and makes it whole. III The weak low Music of this Reed, To his kind Ear is Melody; Nor will he break the useless Thing, But tune it for the Choirs on high. IV If e'er his Love inflam'd my Breast, Alas! 'tis just expiring now: A dying Snuff is all remains, And furious Storms against it blow. V Deep in the Socket of my Heart The Flame breaks, catches, quivers, dies, But Jesus breathes upon the Spark, And the fresh Oil of Joy supplies. VI Angels, thro' all your shining Ranks Such Tenderness was never known; The brightest Wonders of his Grace To our rebellious Race are shown. VII But, Angels, ye with Rapture view That Pity which we Mortals share; Come then, assist a bruised Reed Emanuel's Praises to declare: VIII Low are its Notes, but you can raise Strains of sublimest Praise above, Yet your sublimest Strains must fall Far, far below his matchless Love. The one Thing needful generally neglected. Luke x. 42. Long Metre. I O, Was my Heart but form'd for Woe, What Streams of pitying Tears should flow, To see the thoughtless Sons of Men Labour, and toil, and live in vain! II One Thing is needful, one alone; If this be ours, all is our own: 'Tis needful now, 'twill needful be In Death, and thro' Eternity. III Without it we are all undone, Tho' we could call the World our own: Not all the Joys of Time and Sense Can countervail the Loss immense. IV Yet, (O the Horrors of the Thought!) The one Thing needful is forgot; Forgot, while Trifles of an Hour Our Love, and Hope, and Zeal devour. V Hurry, and Toil, and anxious Care, The busy Life of Mortals share, Till Death compels them to bemoan Their Folly, when their Sands are run. VI The Bliss of Heav'n they disregard, Hell's flaming Terrors rage unfear'd; Eternity a Trifle seems; Immense Realities are Dreams. VII O Sinners! will you now return? Or must I still your Madness mourn? O will you now at length be wise, And strive to gain the only Prize? VIII Great God! that powerful Grace of thine, Which rous'd a Soul so dead as mine, Can rouse these thoughtless Sinners too The one Thing needful to pursue. Spiritual Want and Misery confessed, and the Communication of spiritual Blessings implored. Rev. iii. 17, 18. Long Metre. I No, I'll indulge vain Hopes no more; I see I'm wretched, blind, and poor; By mad Delusions led astray, Till now Conviction shot its Ray. II Blest Jesus! 'tis thine heav'nly Light That opens this surprizing Sight, Shows me myself so long unknown, And by my Ignorance undone. III Welcome this Heart-affecting View, Tho' dreadful, just; tho' painful, true! Ye visionary Hopes, farewel, Ye dreams of Bliss that end in Hell! IV Lord, since my Danger now I see, O let me view my Remedy! And let the Day, that shows my Wound, Show me where Healing may be found! V The wretched, helpless, poor, and blind Relief in Thee alone can find. See one more Sinner from the Dust Look up, and make thy Name his Trust. VI O may that Sun which saw me poor, Tho' proud of my imagin'd Store, Dart down his setting Beams on me, Enrich'd, and safe, and blest in Thee! Applying for Relief to the All-Sufficiency of Christ. Rev. iii. 17, 18. Long Metre. I I hear the Counsel of a Friend; To the kind Voice, my Soul, attend. “Come, Sinners, wretched, blind, and poor, “Come, draw from my unbounded Store. II “I only ask you to receive, “For freely I my Blessings give.” Jesus, and are thy Treasures free, Then I may dare to come to Thee? III I come for Grace, that Gold refin'd, T' enrich and beautify my Mind, Grace that will Trials well endure, By Trials more divinely pure; IV Naked I come for that bright Dress, Thy perfect spotless Righteousness, That glorious Robe, so richly dy'd In thine own Blood, my Shame to hide. V Like Bartimeus, Lord, to Thee I come: O give the Blind to see! Ev'n Clay is Eye-salve in thine Hand, If Thou the Blessing but command. VI Poor, naked, blind I hither came, O let me not depart the same! Let me return, All-gracious Lord, Enrich'd, adorn'd, to Sight restor'd. The holy Spirit invoked, and his purifying and quickening Influences implored. As the Old 112th Psalm. I Eternal Spirit, Source of Light, Enliv'ning, consecrating Fire, Descend, and with celestial Heat Our dull, our frozen Hearts inspire, Our Souls refine, our Dross consume! Come, condescending Spirit, come! II In our cold Breasts O strike a Spark Of the pure Flame which Seraphs feel, Nor let us wander in the Dark, Or lie benumb'd and stupid still. Come, vivifying Spirit, come, And make our Hearts thy constant Home! III Whatever Guilt and Madness dare, We would not quench the heav'nly Fire: Our Hearts as Fuel we prepare, Tho' in the Flame we should expire: Our Breasts expand to make Thee Room: Come, purifying Spirit, come! IV Let pure Devotion's Fervors rise! Let ev'ry pious Passion glow! O let the Raptures of the Skies Kindle in our cold Hearts below! Come, condescending Spirit, come, And make our Souls thy constant Home! The Transcendent Excellency of Christ in his Person and Offices, and the Soul desirous to love Him. As the Old 112?? Psalm. I Jesus, how precious is thy Name! The great Jehovah's Darling, Thou! O let me catch th' immortal Flame, With which Angelic Bosoms glow! Since Angels love Thee, I would love, And imitate the Blest above. II My Prophet Thou, my heav'nly Guide, Thy sweet Instructions I will hear, The Words, that from thy Lips proceed, O how divinely sweet they are! Thee, my great Prophet, I would love, And imitate the Blest above. III My great High-Priest, whose precious Blood Did once atone upon the Cross, Who now dost intercede with God, And plead the friendless Sinner's Cause; In Thee I trust; Thee I would love, And imitate the Blest above. IV My King supreme, to Thee I bow, A willing Subject at thy Feet; All other Lords I disavow, And to thy Government submit: My Saviour-King this Heart would love, And imitate the Blest above. V Transcendant Prince! for ever dear, Dearer than thousand Worlds to me, Shall bold presumptuous Rivals dare Pretend to share my Love with Thee? Thee above all this heart would love, And imitate the Blest above. Christ most worthy of Esteem, but ungratefully neglected in our World. Long Metre. I Welcome to Earth, Great Son of God! His best-belov'd, his only Son! Hail, Thou blest Messenger of Peace To Sinners helpless and undone! II Hail, great Deliv'rer!—Bow the Knee, Ye Rebel-Nations, and adore! Jesus, who would not love thy Name? What Rebel dare offend Thee more? III See ev'n this stubborn Heart of mine Conquer'd by sov'reign Love, submit, And shall not all the Nations fall In humble Homage at thy Feet? IV [Shall not thy Praise from Tongue to Tongue Be spread? Thy Love from Breast to Breast? Thy Name the universal Song From North to South, from East to West?] V But, O my Heart, with Sorrow break, Mine Eyes pour out incessant Tears! The Son of God, the Sinner's Friend, Neglected in our World appears. VI The Wonders of his dying Love The Riches of his Grace forgot!— Strange! Justice should behold the Sight, And yet its Vengeance kindle not. VII [O Thou, whose Mercy deign'd to pray For those who nail'd Thee to the Tree, The Wonders of thy Pow'r display, And turn the Hearts of Men to Thee!] VIII Make Thyself Room in ev'ry Heart; Great Saviour! welcome into mine; Welcome, great Conqu'ror, to our World, To make all Tribes and Nations thine! Pious Breathings amidst general Wickedness and Desolation. Isaiah xxxii, 13–19. Common Metre. I While in a thousand open'd Veins Contending Nations bleed, While Bri'rs and Thorns on blooming Plains And fruitful Fields succeed; II While Desolation rages round, Like an o'erwhelming Flood, Where can a Remedy be found To stop these Streams of Blood? III Eternal Spirit! Source of Good! The Author of our Peace, Pour down thine Influence, like a Flood, On this wide Wilderness. IV O grant us one reviving Show'r, And let it spread afar: Thine Influence alone can cure The bleeding Wounds of War. V Come, Thou—and then the Wilderness Shall bloom a Paradise, And heav'nly Plants t' adorn and bless O'er this wild Waste shall rise: VI Then Peace shall in large Rivers flow, Where Streams of Blood have run; Then universal Love shall glow, And all the World be one; VII Then num'rous Colonies shall rise, A People all Divine, To fill the Mansions of the Skies, And bright as Angels shine. Self-Dedication at the Table of the Lord. Long Metre. A Sacramental Hymn. I Lord, I am thine, entirely thine, Purchas'd and sav'd by Blood Divine, With full Consent thine I would be, And own thy sov'reign Right in me. II Here, Lord, my Flesh, my Soul, my All I yield to Thee beyond Recal; Accept thine own so long withheld, Accept what I so freely yield! III Grant one poor Sinner more a Place Among the Children of thy Grace; A wretched Sinner lost to God, But ransom'd by Emanuel's Blood. IV Thine would I live, thine would I die, Be thine thro' all Eternity: The Vow is past beyond Repeal, Now will I set the solemn Seal. V Be Thou the Witness of my Vow, Angels and Men attest it too, That to thy Board I now repair, And seal the sacred Contract there. VI Here at that Cross, where flows the Blood That bought my guilty Soul for God, Thee my new Master now I call, And consecrate to Thee my All; VII Do Thou assist a feeble Worm The great Engagement to perform: Thy Grace can full Assistance lend, And on that Grace I dare depend.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The following small collection of poems was sent us from an ingenious clergyman in Virginia. Their merit sufficiently entitles them to a place in our Magazine, and engages us warmly to sollicit the continuance of the author's correspondence. One or two inaccuracies in the rhymes he has industriously disregarded, not thinking it worth his while, perhaps, to mangle the sublime sense of the passages for the sake of such critical nicety. Yet this might possibly have been avoided, and it may be thought carelessness, tho' we hope it is not unpardonable carelessness. To the Proprietors of the American Magazine. Gentlemen Tho' it is my misfortune to live at a distance from your metropolis, and in a colony where your magazines, tho' an object of general curiosity, are not likely to circulate, till the post become a more cheap and sure medium of conveyance; yet I feel myself interested in your design. A design that so directly tends to promote not only the literary honour, but the real utility, of these infant colonies; and that bears so favourable an aspect upon the progress of religion, learning and good policy. I would willingly contribute my quota to carry it to perfection: But neither my leisure nor abilities can give you sanguine expectations from me. And I am glad to find, by the perusal of the numbers already published, that you have so little need of my assistance. However, I allow your claim to whatever is in my power. Now and then I may perhaps send you some scraps of poetry, or criticisms upon the sacred classics (my favourite study) or some fortuitous thoughts, upon subjects that are not now in my view; the careless productions of some future hour of leisure; or extracts from my old manuscripts, which would have lain by me in perpetual secresy, had you not thrown this agreeable temptation in my way to make them public. These you may lend to my devout friend the Hermit, or insert in separate articles, as you may think proper. And I beg leave to inform you once for all, that I have no such ?????? or paternal fondness for my own productions, as to take it ill, if you should delay their publication, or entirely suppress them. On the other hand, I appoint you licensers of the press for me, and charge you to publish nothing of mine, to which you cannot safely prefix your Imprimatur. It would be stupid arrogance to insist, that you should humour me, at the expence of the public approbation. Whether I hear from myself thro' the medium of your magazine, or not. I am, June 16. 1758. gentlemen, your obliged humble servant. Virginianus Hanoverenses. ON THE BIRTH OF JOHN ROGERS DAVIES, THE AUTHOR'S THIRD SON. Thou little wond'rous miniature of man, Form'd by unerring Wisdom's perfect plan; Thou little stranger, from eternal night Emerging into life's immortal light; Thou heir of worlds unknown, thou candidate For an important everlasting state, Where this young embryo shall its pow'rs expand, Enlarging, rip'ning still, and never stand. This glimm'ring spark of being, just now struck From nothing by the all-creating Rock, To immortality shall flame and burn, When suns and stars to native darkness turn; Thou shalt the ruins of the worlds survive, And through the rounds of endless ages live. Now thou art born into an anxious state Of dubious trial for thy future fate: Now thou art lifted in the war of life, The prize immense, and O! severe the strife. Another birth awaits thee, when the hour Arrives that lands thee on th' eternal shore; (And O! 'tis near, with winged haste 'twill come, Thy cradle rocks toward the neighb'ring tomb;) Then shall immortals say, “A son is born,” While thee as dead mistaken mortals mourn; From glory then to glory thou shalt rise, Or sink from deep to deeper miseries; Ascend perfection's everlasting scale, Or still descend from gulph to gulph in hell. Thou embryo-angel, or thou infant fiend, A being now begun, but ne'er to end, What boding fears a Father's heart torment, Trembling and anxious for the grand event, Lest thy young soul so late by Heav'n bestow'd, Forget her Father, and forget her God! Lest, while imprison'd in this house of clay, To tyrant lusts she fall an helpless prey! And lest, descending still from bad to worse, Her immortality should prove her curse! Maker of souls! avert so dire a doom, Or snatch her back to native nothing's gloom! A PARAPHRASE on Jer. XXXI. 18, 19, 20. Homer's interview of Hector and Andromache, Virgil's elegiac lines upon Marcellus, and Eve's intercessions with Adam for reconciliation in Milton, have justly been the admiration of critics for their passionate tenderness and restless energy. But they all appear to be much less moving and pathetic, than these admirable strains of Jeremiah; an author, whom natural genius and divine inspiration formed to teach all the springs of the passions, and charm us into pleasing melancholy with the harmony of melodious sorrows. The supreme of Beings represents himself earnestly listening to catch the harmony of penitential groans, so grateful to his ears, from whatever spot of our guilty globe they come. And lo! He hears Ephriam bemoaning himself thus. “Thou hast chastised me, and I was chastised, as a bullock unaccustomed to the yoke: turn thou me, and I shall be turned; for thou art the lord my God.” Thus he prays, and mercy hears. The converting influence he sought, is granted: And by this, his heart, once so reluctant and unmanageable, is so effectually turned, that he cannot but reflect upon the sudden and surprizing change with delightful wonder—“Surely, says he, after I was turned, I repented; and after that I was instructed. I smote upon my thigh: I was ashamed, yea, even confounded, because I did bear the reproach of my youth.” The father can no longer hear these mournful strains of the broken hearted penitent: He can no longr keep silence, but agreeably surprizes and interrupts him with the soothing voice of mercy— Who is this that affects my ears with his penitential groans? “Is this my dear son Ephraim? So I would chuse to render it, rather that as our translators do: and the [Hebrew word] prefixt, may bear this emphasis, “Is this my Son?” Is this my pleasant child?” So I call him notwithstanding the aspect of wrath a farther but constrained to put on; “for since I spake against him, I do earnestly remember him still: therefore my bowels are troubled for him: I will surely have mercy upon him, saith the Lord.” —Can there be a heart so hard, as not to be dissolved with these melting strains of penitential sorrow? Or can there be despondency so deep and sullen, as not to be animated with these tender strains of paternal goodness? [EPHRAIM'S PENITENCE] 1. Hark! saith the Lord, what moving sound Affects my listening ear? 'Til Ephraim all in sorrow drown'd, That Moans himself in tears. 2. “Kindly severe, thy chastening stroke Thy stubborn child reclaim'd: So the wild bullock to the yoke Must be subdu'd and tam'd. 3. Made wise by thy instructive rod, My wandrings now I mourn: Fain would I turn to thee, my God; Turn me, and I shall turn.” 4. Thus groan'd the mourner: mercy heard And gave the help implor'd: Ephraim with joy and wonder fir'd, Was quicken'd, and adored. 5. “When grace, he cries, my spirit drew, (Before averse to move) My God, I turn'd, I ran, I flew, Nor could resist thy love. 6. With trembling consternation struck, My guilty thigh I smote: My stony heart dissolv'd and broke, For follies long forgot. 7. The impious vanities that stain'd My young unthinking days, My heart with keen reproaches pain'd And blushes flush'd my face. 8. Guilty, confounded, sunk in shame, Here at thy feet I fall. Should all thy wrath this moment flame, Lord, I deserve it all.” 9. “Is this my son, my darling son? Is this my pleasant child? My bowels move to hear him moan,” The father said, and smil'd. 10. “I'm reconcil'd, my threats repeal'd, That wounded but to heal: When all their terrors stood reveal'd, Thee I remember'd still, 11. All thy complaints shall be redrest. And all remov'd thy fears.” He said, and sooth'd his child to rest, And wip'd the mourner's tears. [THE FOUNTAIN] The Invitations of the Gospel. (Annext to a Sermon on Rev. XXII. 17. April 9, 1753. 1. To-day the living streams of grace Flow to refresh the thirsty soul: Pardon and life and boundless bliss In plenteous rivers round us roll. 2. Ho! ye that pine away and die, Come, and your raging thirst allay: Come all that will, here's rich supply; A fountain that shall ne'er decay. 3. “Come ALL,” the blessed Jesus cries, “Freely my blessings I will give.” The spirit echoes back the voice, And bids us freely drink and live. 4. The saints below, that do but taste, And saints above, who drink at will, Cry jointly, “Thirsty sinners! haste, “And drink, the spring's exhaustless still.” 5. Let all that hear the joyful sound, To spread it thro' the world unite; From house to house proclaim it round, Each man his fellow-man invite. 6. Like thirsty flocks, come let us go; Come every colour, Whites and Negroes. every age: And while the living waters flow, Let all their parching thirst assuage. [PSALM CXXXVII] There is a soft pleasing melancholy that runs thro' the first part of the CXXXIX [i.e., CXXXVII] Psalm, composed by some pious patriot-captive on the banks of the Euphrates. And at the request of a friend, the following version of it, fitted to a proper tune, has been attempted: But like all other translations of sacred poetry, it falls infinitely short of the divine original. SITTING by the streams, that glide Down by Babel's towering wall, With our tears we swell'd the tide, While our mournful thoughts recall Thee, o Zion! and thy fall. On the willows there we hung Our neglected harps on high, Silent, useles and unstrung, Strangers now to harmony, Once our business and our joy. There our proud triumphant foes, Haughty, insolent and gay, Call'd for music in our woes, “Sing us some sweet Hebrew lay, “Sacred to some holy day.” Cruel foes, t'insult us so! Sunk so deep in helpless grief: Sighs and groans to vent our woe, Now our only poor relief, To the charms of music deaf. Ah! shall Zion's sacred songs Warble sweet in ears profane? Shall we prostitute our tongues, With a consecrated strain, To delight the gay and vain? No! Jerus'lem, no! thy fate Wounds my bleeding heart so deep, Let my skillful hand forget How the tuneful strings to sweep, When for the thee I cease to weep. In that guilty moment, let Endless silence seize my tongue, When this heart shall once forget They dear image (there so long,) Or indulge a chearful song. Zion! thy deliverance first Shall awake the silent string, When thy walls shall from the dust In their ancient grandeur spring. Then my harp and tongue shall sing. [THE ETERNAL MIND] The following extract from a hymn sung at the initiation into the Eleusinian mysteries, is a curious orthodox relique of heathen antiquity, strongly asserting the unity and perfection of the Diety. With eager eyes and heart refined, Look up, and view th'eternal mind. Boldly ascend the arduous road Thro' nature up to nature's God: King of the world, he reigns alone; The cause of all, himself but one; The cause uncaus'd: His nature spreads, Immense, and all his works pervades. Himself unseen, with one wide view He looks the vast creation thro'. PERTH-AMBOY Nassau Hall, September 27, 1759. Yesterday the annual Commencent was held here. The Revd. Mr. Samuel Davies, lately elected President of the College of New-Jersey, delivered a Latin Oration, to the universal Applause of all his learned and numerous Auditors. The young Gentlemen (about 25 in Number) who were admitted to the usual Degrees in the Arts, performed the accustomed Exercises with uncommon Facility and Correctness. The whole Ceremony concluded with the followed ODE, set to Music by Mr. James Lyon, and of the Students. Chearful, fearless, and at ease, On the downy Lap of Peace, In the gentle Muses Seat, Unmov'd at War's tremendous Roar, That Consternation spreads from Shore to Shore, O'er solid Continents, and tossing Waves, From haughty Monarchs down to Slaves, Low cringing at their Feet; Far from Terror's loud Alarms, Peaceful Nassau! in thee we sing— We sing great George upon the throne, And Amherst brave in Arms; Amherst brave in Arms; While Bernard, in their milder charms, Makes the royal Virtues known. Chor. We sing great George, &amp;c. &amp;c. The Sword of the Lord and of Amherst from far, Gleaming tremendous, determines the War: At th' approaching Vengeance struck Gallic Slaves, tho' long enur'd To face the wide destroying Sword At a proud Tyrant's Word, Now disorder'd and broke, Despairing, confounded With Terrors surrounded by Amherst's Name subdu'd, By dread of Vengeance close pursu'd, Vengeance due to sacred British Blood, The useless Sword they drop. Nor dare for safety hope, But in swift flight, Beneath the Shade of Guilt-concealing Night. We sing great George upon the Throne, And Amherst brave in Arms, Amherst brave in Arms; While Bernard, in their milder Charms, Make the royal Virtues known. Happy, happy, happy, still, Safe from all the Alarms of ill; While George, the Friend of Man, adorns the Throne, And Amherst shines in Arms; While Bernard makes the royal Virtues known, In all their milder Charms. Happy, &amp;c. &amp;c. AN ODE ON PEACE While Nations die By mutual Wounds, And Terror and Destruction walk their Rounds; While wide-extended Countries lie Swimming in Seas of human Gore; And Death's horrendous Engines roar, And Horror glares in every Eye; Descend sweet PEACE! thy Balm prepare, And heal the bleeding Wounds of War. Gentle PEACE! with mildest Rays, Shine on the happy, happy Days, When GEORGE, the WELL-BELOV'D and GREAT, With Honor fills the Royal Seat, And over half the Globe from thence, Sheds his propitious Influence. Happy, happy Days, when BOONE Reflects the Splendors of the Throne, On distant Lands, beneath the setting Sun. Happy, happy, happy Days, When WOLFE victorious for his Country bleeds— (Eternal FAME! proclaim his Praise, And sound his mighty Deeds! Eternal FAME! proclaim his Praise, And sound his mighty Deeds!) When led by AMHERST, circumspect and brave, BRITAIN's intrepid Sons advance, O'er rugged Mountains, Desarts wide, And Wastes by human Foot untry'd, To chace the trembling Fugitives of France, Or crow'd them in a hasty Grave. Gentle PEACE! with mildest Rays, Shine on these happy, happy Days, Happy, happy, happy Days, Which with BRITAIN's Glory blaze. Descend sweet PEACE! thy Balm prepare; And heal the bleeding Wounds of War. [THE DIVINE LOVE AND SUFFERINGS OF OUR SAVIOR] The following Translation of a Latin Poem of Doctor Watts, in his Horae Lyricae. On the divine Love and Sufferings of our Saviour Jesus Christ for Mankind, By the Rev. Mr. Davies, late President of the College of New-Jersey, was intended for our Paper in Easter Week, but omitted by Accident. 'Twas He, who once descending from the Height Of heavenly Bliss, assum'd our mortal Clay; That, cloth'd in human Flesh, and in our Stead, He, our kind Surety, might discharge the Debt, The dreadful Debt we ow'd, and on Himself Transfer the Vengeance of the threatning Law, The Guilt of Man, and Sin's dire Punishment. See, prostrate on the Ground, forlorn He lies, On the cold Grass diffus'd; His guiltless Hands Towards His own Heaven, uplifted; and his Face Placid and mild, turn'd to His Father's Seat, Not to receive the Kisses of His Love, Or feel His usual, kind Embrace; but stript Of his bright starry Robe, His sacred Breast Expos'd spontaneous, to the piercing Wrath Of GOD in Arms. His willing Voice invites The lagging Vengeance. “Here, My Father! here, “In this pure Bosom sheathe thy angry Sword; “Let Blood Divine attone for mortal Crimes.” He said. And straight thro' the Celestial Arch Horrendous Thunder roar'd; JEHOVAH now Awoke his Wrath (whom, to have laid aside Paternal Love, the Muse almost complains, But struck with such amazing Splendours dumb, She dares not speak!) now rends the solid Sky, And open fly the doors, where Vengeance reigns, In her dire Magazine, with endless Stores Of Pains and Torments under her Command, Forth rush dread Hurricanes and boisterous Storms Pregnant with furious Sulphur; fiery Bolts Form'd of contorted Flames, upon his Head, His guiltless Head, with Force impetuous falls; Beneath the dreadful Burden while he stands, And spreads his Breast to take the impending Blow, A Luke xxii. 44. Flood of purple Gore bursts from his Pores, And thro' his Garments trickles to the Ground. Yet Vengeance, cruel Queen, will not remit The Torture; but She chides the lagging Fires, And rouses the[i]r dread Justice []ng Sword; “Awake! Zach. xiii. 7. Awake! [] Breast Divine; “With sacred Blood die thy vindictive Point. “Scatter dire Torments thro' the Soul and Flesh “Of the Anointed; He can bear a Load “Immense: th' indwelling Deity supports “His mortal Frame beneath the crushing Weight “Of Torments huge. Thou, violated Law! “Drink full Revenge; and Satisfaction take “From Slaughter vast. The Deity's Disgrace “Thy Honour shall secure, and Blood Divine, “Expiate human Guilt.”— This said, She whirl'd a thousand mighty Wounds And fixt them in His Breast; the inmost Doors Of His dear Soul are open'd; cruel Pain Flies in with eager Wing, and greedy, preys Upon his Vitals, and devours His Heart. Mean Time the Saviour, cheerful, o'er the Pain Sublimely triumphs; Col. ii. 15. and bedew'd with Blood, Exults in Misery; for a generous Zeal For His own Father's Honour, and His Joy To ransom guilty Wretches, urg'd Him more, And fir'd His Heart. O noble, generous Zeal To suffer Pains! O Love! how strong they Power In human Breasts! How mighty in Divine! What wonders hast thou done! SCIENCE. An ODE. Science! bright Beam of Light Divine! Dawn of immortal Day! On this thy new-built Temple shine, And all thy Charms display. Where wild untutor'd Ignorance Her savage Revels kept; And led the rude ferocious Dance, While gentle Reason slept; Where howling through her native Wood, With kindred Beasts of Prey, She rous'd her furious Sons to Blood, More wild and fierce than they: Thy Temple, there, expands in Gates To thee, celestial Guest! And each of thy young Vot'ries waits To hail thee to thy Rest. Hail, Science! Heaven born Stranger! hail! Adorn thy humble Shrine: Deign in this Western World to dwell, And its wide Wastes refine.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">POEMS ASCRIBED TO DAVIES VERSES ON Gen. Braddock's defeat. The attribution of this poem is uncertain. —Mares animos in martia bella Versibus exacuit. [The dying general speaks.] Then 'tis decreed—the vain exulting Gaul, In these ill-fated fields beholds my fall. But let not Britain, when she hears the tale, In timid indolence my fate bewail. O! rather let her sons, unus'd to fear, To women leave the tribute of the tear: A brave revenge alone becomes the brave, A brave revenge these dying heroes crave. See where their mangled limbs bestrew the field: Firm, undismay'd, unknowing how to yield. Behold them with their latest gasp of breath, Implore their country to revenge their death. May Britain then let loose her vengeful ire, Redouble force repeated wrongs require; Each active hand with martial error arm, Each martial bosom with her spirit warm: So haughty Gaul, when her exploits she hears, Shall with her ill-starr'd triumph mix her fears; As midnight-thieves, that wrapt in vile disguise Have made some luckless traveller their prize, Afraid of justice, drop the booty won, And tremble for the mischief they have done. In vain the fetter'd Gaul prepares his chains, For British freedom, ev'n in India's plains. Great George, born to command the free and brave, Shall break his weapons, and chastise the slave. My blood I freely spill; rejoic'd to make The first libation for fair Freedom's sake. For, as in Greece of old, the warrior's meed For liberty, is nobly thus to bleed. Here then I chearful quit life's poor remains, For glory well exchang'd in martial plains: In future times, (nor do I boast in vain), When Britain numbers o'er her warrior train; When time my errors shall obliterate, And veil my faults in pity to my fate; In the fair list perhaps shall stand his name, Who thro' these regions shew'd the road to fame; Who 'midst these pathless wilds, and streams that roll From sources unexplor'd, first taught the Gaul That Britain's freeborn sons, inspir'd by fame, Nor danger daunts, nor toilsome marches tame. What though by me these ill-starr'd heroes led, With me, oppress'd by numbers, fought and bled? What tho' our blood these barb'rous currents dye, To savage rage expos'd our bodies lie? Yet still our name a terror shall remain, For length of ages to the servile train. Oft shall these warrior shades, who sullen rove Along th' o'er shaded stream or twilight grove, Or o'er savannahs drear, in dread array, By moonlight gleam their marshal'd ranks display, Affright the Gaul, whose dazzled fancy sees The horrid armour glitt'ring through the trees. His shrivell'd soul within him dies with fear, Whilst bursts of imag'd cannon wound his ear. Nor will our pensive ghosts one comfort know, Till destin'd vengeance overtake the foe; Till (servile Gaul expell'd) fix'd in these plains By British valour, British freedom reigns. THE MILITARY GLORY OF GREAT-BRITAIN, AN ENTERTAINMENT, GIVEN BY THE LATE CANDIDATES FOR BACHELOR'S DEGREE, AT THE CLOSE OF THE ANNIVERSARY COMMENCEMENT, HELD IN NASSAU-HALL NEW-JERSEY The attribution of this poem is uncertain. September 29th, 1762. Introductory Chorus. Triumphant Fame ascend the Skies, Ever glorying in our Isle, Loud proclaim o'er distant Realms How British Power, and British Glory rise. Enter first Speaker; proclaiming Britannia Conqueror, by Way of Introduction to the next Speech. As down the plain with easy Tide, The placid Streams, when unmolested, glide; But, when descends a sudden Shower, They pour amain a foaming Flood; The Mountains hear the Torrents roar, And Echoes shake the neighbouring Wood: So mild and peaceful, fair Britannia mov'd Her harmless Sceptre; 'till, her Wrath enflam'd, Gallia all her Vengeance prov'd; Haughty Lewis's Rage was tam'd; Envy and Terror seiz'd the hostile Nations round, Chorus II. Gallia's Sons shall vaunt no more, Her Armies broake, her Fleets destroy'd; Gallic Power, And Gallic Pride In vain our injur'd Arms defy'd. Enter second Speaker; who enumerates several of the most important Conquests of Great-Britain, with Encomiums on some of the principal Generals. It is not mine to raise with forming Hand, A mute Encomium on its marble Base; But yet in humble Phrase I'll dare rehearse The mighty Deeds of Britain's conquering Arms: What could avail Monongahela's Rage, Tho' glutted to the full with Blood indignant, If in the Breast of Warlike Johnston lay Unerring Thunders of a just Revenge? To Him no Mean Reward of Honour's due; Since that glad Day, the first auspicious, shed A Tide of Glory o'er the Western World. Hence what new Triumphs in Succession croud Our smiling Annals! Gracious Powers indeed, To spin out such a Length of prosp'rous Fate! Immured in brazen Walls, Canadia's Hope, Stood Louisburg; whose tow'ring Bulwarks brav'd, In bold Defiance, Victory itself; But, not great Wolfe, and Amherst; Sons of War, Whose very Names struck Terror on the Foe. But, ah! let not the Ardour of thy Youth, Unc?scious Wolfe, with such Precipitance, E'er yet thy full Carreer of Glory's run, Urge thee on Dangers,—but 'twas thus ordain'd. Such Blood Canadia's Plains ne'er stain'd before; Nor happier Genius ever rose to Fame; His Death, itself, the Expiation slew; Wolfe, dying, conquer'd; conquering, was immortal. Nor ceases Victory; Amherst still appears, Illustrious from a Train of glorious Deeds: Him prudent Foresight, and sagacious Cares Led tho' the Perils of a savage War: 'Twas but to shew the Glittering of his Arms, And Montreal with all Canadia yeilds. Hence a long Tract of Continent subdued: The ruthless Natives champ the reigning Curb, And break their Arrows with indignant Rage. What shall I say of Afric's torrid Coast Where the parch'd Adder gasps for Life? or what, Of Laurels gather'd in those golden Climes, Where the first Sun beskirts the Eastern Clouds, And where the Roman Eagle never flew? What shall I say of all the wond'rous Deeds, Of which Germania's Witness? As, when falls Resistless Eurus on the Baltic Main, The heaving Billows, of enormous Weight, Dash, like projected Mountains, full against Th' unyielding Shore; thus, with impetuous Tide, Poured the whole Force of Gaul on Hanoveria; And had o'erwhelm'd it: But the mighty Soul Of Ferdinand, as Atlas firm, withstood; And broke the Vehemence of the pressing War. So, the spent Ocean weaken'd with the Rage Which long had urged the stable Continent, Falls back at length, and in itself subsides. Shall I again repeat the brave Exploits Of Monckton in the Western Isles? those late, Within these peaceful Walls we sung, enflam'd, With all the Ardours of a Patriot Heart: But Moncton's Deeds demand repeated Songs. Nor should I pass in Silence Guadaloupe, Belle-Isle, or what the British Flag atchiev'd, Whether it thunder'd on the Gallic Coast; Or rode in Triumph o'er the boundless Main? Surprising Series of renown'd Exploits! A God, a God directs th'Affairs of Men. What then avails Iberia's Insolence, So oft' suppress'd by our superior Arms, Fraught with almighty Aid? While British Sons, Inur'd to Toils heroic, burn with Love Of honourable Fame, nor Power, nor Threats, Shall damp their ardour in their bold Career. Chorus III Propitious Powers who guard our State, Let our earnest Prayer be heard; Our Prayer this solemn Day prefer'd. Check the Force and Pride of Spain; Render all her Efforts vain; But Power and Glory be Britannia's Fate. Enter Eugenio; who, by Way of Dialogue with Cleander, gives an Account of the Reduction of the Havanna. Eugenio. Hast thou not heard Cleander, of the Deeds So late performed by Albemarle? These, sure Methinks demand their equal Tribute Of Commendation; such as thou canst give. Cleander. I have Eugenio; nor has Gratitude To HIM who rules omnipotent the World For such amazing Fortune of our Arms, Been wanting to my Breast; But yet the Theme Seem'd worthy of a more exalted Muse; A Muse like thine, enobled by the Love Of British Freedom, and of British Fame. Wherefore without Reluctance bear thy Part In such illustrious Praise. Eugenio In Britain's Praises who can be reluctant? Whilst I have Lungs to heave, a Tongue to speak, I'll not be wanting to my Country's Cause. Here, Silence would be base Ingratitude; Nay, more, Rebellion. Cleander. But say, Eugenio, how that warlike Youth, Such glorious Conquest gained. Eugenio Greater the Toil, the greater Weight of Glory. No easy Effort gains the Alpine Summits, Secured by rugged Dangers; high enclosed In cliffy Bulwarks; each its' Towring Head In Clouds invelop'd, inaccessible, Full forty Days beneath the stormy Brow. Of Moro-Castle mov'd the British Troops, With various Art, and regular Approach Working Destruction and sure Victory. From Batteries on every Side erect, The mounted Engines poured incessantly Against her strong built Walls their iron Force; Thick Showers of Bombs implete with nitrous Death, Rain'd on their Heads defenceless, which forthwith, Bursting, disploded Ruin; every Art, Which military Prudence pointed out, Or Valour might perfect, was tried: But still the Foe with stubborn Pride resist; Still, reinforced, guard their batter'd Walls From close Assault; and, often sallying forth, Would check the approaching Siege; as oft repuls'd. At length ensues a Breach; their Arms appear; And all their mighty Secrets are reveal'd. Again, the cavern'd Ground beneath their Feet, With Grain sulphurious stor'd, by sudden Blaze, Bursts ruinous; up fly the Hopes of War, In smoky Whirls involv'd; th' uprooted Wall, A larger Chasm displays; the Fosse, fill'd up With shiver'd Rubbish, gives a fairer Entrance, And seems t'invite the meditated Storm. Then had you seen, Cleander, all the Fire Of British War, enflam'd by fierce Revenge. As furious Lions press'd with hungry Rage Leap roaring on the hopeless Prey; so rush'd The ardent Victors; bloody Shouts ascend; And Slaughter, Slaughter rends the vaulted Sky; They kill; they conquer; Death in every Shape, Confounds th' affrighted Foe; some in Dispair His Fury tempt, while others shrink away, And, trembling, merit an inglorious End. Cleander. A just Reward of Spanish Cruelty, So late exerted, when their merc'less Hands, At the first landing of our Arms, they drench'd In captive British Blood. Eugenio. A just Reward Cleander. Nor here ceas'd The vig'rous Effort; animated now With recent Conquest, our Commanders brave Press on to total Vict'ry. (Glorious Toils! Well worthy of immortal Fame!) straightway, With Force collected, and a martial Rage E'en passing British, on th' unyielding Town They turn the Charge decisive; and, at once, Lend all the Thunders of their various War. In vain the Foe resist; all Hope is fled; Their Cannon faintly roar; the lab'ring Walls, Fall piece-meal crumbling to the Ground: within Reign grizly Horror, loud Laments, and Death. Cleander. Such then Eugenio was their desp'rate Fate! What can withstand our all pervading Arms When Heaven ensures the Conquest? Such Glory to Britannia's Sons is due. Chorus IV. Glory, Triumph, Victory, Fame, For ever crown Britannia's Name. Sound her Praise; Her Honours raise; Her Triumphs in Iberia's Seas. Enter fourth Speaker; suddenly transported. What mean these Strains? these glad, triumphant Sounds? My Heart, with what unusual Joy it bounds! 'Tis Transport all; Britannia's Praise, Britannia's Praise my Soul inspires; Oh, how my Bosom 'glows with unknown Fires, Collecting Fuel as they blaze! Down the long Tract of future Time I view Effulgent British Glory shine, Unceasing as the Stars!— I see portray'd in every various Hue The Gallic and Iberian Wars; Here, Gallia trembling on her Throne; Her Shame, there, proud Iberia own, While in the midst, with radiant Crown Britannia's Splendors almost dazzle the Design. Ye Sons of War, pursue the Foe; Your Albemarle has struck th' auspicious Blow. See, Victory waits with laurel-Wreath to crown Your Temples; fondly hovering round Your glittering Arms. 'Tis Courage fights; 'Tis Courage conquers. Pour your Wrath abroad; with martial Sound The Foe confound; Assert your British Rights; And bid them feel the Weight of your avenging Rod. Part of the Fourth Chorus. Glory, Triumph, Vict'ry, Fame, Forever crown Britannia's Name. Enter fifth Speaker; who closes the whole with a solemn Wish, for the continued Prosperity of the British Nation. While on their Base th'eternal Mountains stand, And poise the balanc'd Globe; while Nature's Laws command, The fix'd Alternative of Night and Day; While Sun and Moon and Stars endure, And on our World their Radiance pour; May British Lands exulting see The full Rewards of Victory; Great in the Annals of Eternity. Long may a GEORGE the regal Sceptre sway, And scatter Blessings with a lib'ral Hand Around the peaceful Globe; but dire Dismay On all who dare his injur'd Arms withstand. Chorus V. While Mountains poise the balanc'd Globe, Shade and Light the World enrobe; While Sun, and Moon, and Stars endure, And a blended Radiance pour, British Fame shall bear the Prize; And in a Blaze of peerless Glory rise. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>