<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Church, Benjamin, 1734-1778</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Church, Benjamin, 1734-1778</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">church benjamin 1734 1778</field>
      <field name="author_text">Church, Benjamin, 1734-1778</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1750's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ap/uvaGenText/tei/chap_AM0263.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240350</field>
      <field name="date_text">1751</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:439722</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">A poem Occasioned by the Death Of the Honourable Jonathan Law Esq ; Late Governor of Connecticut</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775</field>
      <field name="title_display">A poem Occasioned by the Death Of the Honourable Jonathan Law Esq ; Late Governor of Connecticut</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poem occasioned by the death of the honourable jonathan law esq</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poem occasioned by the death of the honourable jonathan law esq</field>
      <field name="title_text">A poem Occasioned by the Death Of the Honourable Jonathan Law Esq ; Late Governor of Connecticut</field>
      <field name="year_display">1751</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1751</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1751</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:439722&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:439722&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Church, Benjamin, 1734-1778&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;church benjamin 1734 1778&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;A poem Occasioned by the Death Of the Honourable Jonathan Law Esq ; Late Governor of Connecticut&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poem occasioned by the death of the honourable jonathan law esq&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1751&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1751&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Church, Benjamin&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1734&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1778&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;A poem Occasioned by the Death Of the Honourable Jonathan Law Esq.&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Late Governor of Connecticut&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;New London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by Timothy Green&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1751&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3865361-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;cham0263&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;A poem Occasioned by the Death Of the Honourable Jonathan Law Esq.&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Late Governor of Connecticut&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1996&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1996 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 18 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-AmPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">A POEM Occasioned by the Death Of the Honourable Jonathan Law Esq; Late GOVERNOR OF CONNECTICUT. With mean complacence ne'er betray your trust, Nor be so civil as to prove unjust: Fear not the anger of the wise to raise; They best can bear reproof, who merit praise. Pope's Essay on Criticism. Hail great illustrious ghost! if heav'n can spare Thy kind attention, and important care: Or if dismiss'd to bless some happy sphere, Where plenty smiles around each circling year, To influence wisely its politic state, And govern ev'ry popular debate: Rebellious faction to restrain by law, And furious zeal compose with gentle awe, Or hasty schemes of sanguine heroes curb, Which common-weal and public peace disturb, Your practis'd talents strenuous you employ, Till ev'ry honest heart exults with joy; Yet once attend this solemn fun'ral song, And let the muse purge the plebeian wrong. To Law, great man, Connecticut, must owe More than to all the pow'rs, save George, below. Thy hand, when on the raging ocean tost, Her tott'ring back, sad fate, was almost lost, Guided thro' whirlwinds, hurricanes and storms, In all their terrible and ghastly forms. Euroclydon, or Eurus vex'd the main, Tumbled the mountains o'er the wat'ry plain: Pelion o'er Ossa, over Ossa Pelian rolls, And the hoarse thunder shakes th' astonish'd poles. Alternate fire and night the heav'ns confuse, Profundest hell her horrid entrails spues: A thousand Hydras drive the storm along, And ev'ry watry Demon swells the throng. Aghast the sailors stand! they dread the shores, Here's fatal sand, there howling Silla roars. Th' unchanging compass like, by which he steers, Calm as Ulysses thoughtful Law appears; This way, and that, as art directs his hand, Through the rough storm, the quiv'ring bark commands At length the tempest sinks, the hills arise, And a new heav'n salutes their ravish'd eyes. A brighter sun lights up th' auspicious year, And sapphires with new lustre grace the sphere: The sweetest constellations bless the sky, Whilst peace and plenty with each other vie. Impartial Justice holds Astrea's scales, And the poor peasant's righteous cause prevails. Fraud and injustice seek their dark retreat; But truth and plainness in the forum meet. The wrangling sophist's cant and loud chicane, And metaphysic jargon's all in vain. Discerning Law the labyrinth explains, Investigates the truth, and right maintains. His solemn brow and venerable face, Both awe and charm, and all the forum grace. He now th' important common-weal directs; Her liberty asserts, her rights protects. But Envy, that fell imp, the devils The female Bastards of the Romish Clergy are called their Nieces. niece, Grew pale and swore destruction to our peace. Behold in yonder livid gloomy sphere, A comet dire and baleful stars appear, Presaging vengeance, discord, war, and strife, With all the plagues that vex the human life. Gallia and hell with all their strength combine, The subtil priest, and pious devil joyn, New-England to subject to popish pow'r: They bless the scheme, and hail the happy hour; When Gallic ensigns spread, to all proclaim Lewis his might, and zealous W?f?d's fame. Long had the various arts of war been tri'd; Our blood the secret murth'ring hatchet dy'd. But stratagem and force can ne'er prevail, Unless a people's faith and virtue fail. The fatal project then must be essay'd, Baalam and Moloch lend their cursed aid. Fierce zeal and bitter rage, and hatred dire Kindle an inextinguishable fire. Passion must be enthron'd, and reason die; A furious storm preceeds the happiest sky. Wild superstition let the mind enrage, Or enthusiastic heat the soul engage Corrupt the moral tast, the trick is done: Truth nought avails, tho' brighter than the sun. If orthodox your faith and strong, fear not: No crime, not sodomy, can make a blot. Your brethren hate: to Moloch sacrifice The kindest gifts indulgent heav'n supplies. Be sure religion must be all in all, See that before some god you lowly fall, Approach his sacred fan: with pious rage, And loudly curse and damn the present age: Rake up the virtuous dead, and blast their fame, With all the odium of a hateful name. Moses and Aaron, if they serve the Lord, Ay, ev'ry virtuous man must be abhor'd. But if the softer rites of Venus move, Address the tempting dame with holy love: Sigh Jesus to her in the fond embrace, And prattle gospel sonnets on free grace. Take care she's Abraham's daughter, then she's free For ev'ry Israelite, besure for thee. Such was the motly creed, the wand'ring priest, Who once was half a devil, half a beast, Reviv'd: for sorcery had long before Been practised by the Babylonish whore; And well the fly inchantress knew to suit Religion to the devil or the brute. God's temples with seditious doctrines rung, And peace was curs'd by noisy T?n?t's tongue. Th' unstable croud the fatal poison gorge, And whisper James a fonder king than George. “'Twas Jeroboam humour'd Israel's tast, “Egyptian gods in Dan and Bethel plac'd: “Altars of Syrian mode he caus'd to rise, “Made ev'ry grove a place of sacrifice: “The vulgar herd (as best his gods became) “The fragrant incense mix and tend the flame.” In dusky wreaths the curling smoke ascends; A hideous cry the troubl'd æther rends Such was the humour of those zealous times, When solid virtue was the worst of crimes. The people too a warlike temper boast: In martial prowess they excel the most; Unus'd to fear, no enemy they know So dire as tyranny, a lawless foe. Impatient of restraint, they scorn the reins, And bound impetuous thro' the happy plains, Where liberty erects her lovely shrine, And suns without eclipse perpetual shine. This noble genius, thus with ardor fir'd, Which false religion's phrentic zeal inspir'd, The nicest management of art requir'd. But interposing heav'n controll'd the storm, Permitted thence a swift ætherial form To visit Shirley's warm projecting head, T' inspire the man, the scheme before him spread. “Rouze, said the visionary form, arise: “Heav'n will succeed the daring enterprize. “To thee I bear the uncontroll'd command, “Proud Louisburg to level with the sand. “Connecticut her valiant troops will send, “And prudent Law the great affair intend. “Gabriel the cautious hero's mind inspires, “Tells his behest, then back to heav'n retires. “Tis mine to warm the generous warrior's soul, “Infuse the god, and animate the whole.” Quick as the æther, charg'd with vapours, pours On half the continent th' incumbent show'rs, So quick so sudden rang'd the virtue round, And breath'd in ev'ry ear the martial sound. Th' impetuous troops compose the wide campain, Receive the stores, and rush into the main. The breath of heav'n th' extended canvass swells, And each opposing demon's force repels. Now with more malice, but less danger wrought The phrentic zeal the vagrant prophet taught. Enough remain'd to try the wisest soul; To keep the peace and anarchy controul: Religion's riot to restrain by art: Discern the factious from the honest heart: Suspend the balance with a steady hand, When fire and wind intestine shake the land. This was the province the all-ordering mind, For ever wise, to's fav'rite Law assign'd, The wondrous man the god in all display'd, His ev'ry act confess'd the heav'nly aid. His steady prudence grac'd each public scene, And honest skill controll'd the wild machine. Form'd for the glorious toil, a people free To govern and preserve their liberty. He like great Moses was in meekness great. For public good assum'd a public state: Free of access to all, to none deny'd The wisest counsel gracious heav'n suppli'd. Mistaken Zealot's rage and party beat, The hiss of dragons in their dark retreat, The bitter curses of envenom'd tongues, The horrid belches of infernal lungs Unruffl'd he could bear, and meekly pray Father forgive, they know not what they say. But when their crimes the civil vengeance dar'd, Mercy forbid the guilty to be spar'd, The mildest schemes of punishment were laid, But more effectual never have been made. Calm as an upper region was his mind; Clear of all passion truth resplendent shin'd; There spread her chast and unpolluted ray, And gradual rising made celestial day. On to the summit of eternal fame, By steady steps and diligence he came: There sat secure, and view'd the prospect wide, Without one giddy turn, or thought of pride. Strong was his genius like the hebrew sage, Nor suffer'd by th' arrest of time or age. Like him thus on the mount sublime, 'twas nigh To heav'n's eternal hills, he's bid to die. A swift translation to a nobler state, Where a superior crown proclaims him great Fix'd steady in an high important sphere, Where an eternity compleats his year.</field>
   </doc>
</add>