<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Sigourney, L. H., (Lydia Howard), 1791-1865</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Sigourney, L. H., (Lydia Howard), 1791-1865</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">sigourney l h lydia howard 1791 1865</field>
      <field name="author_text">Sigourney, L. H., (Lydia Howard), 1791-1865</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1830's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ap/uvaGenText/tei/chap_AM1099.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240349</field>
      <field name="date_text">1834</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:440520</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Poetry for children</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- 1783-1850</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- 1783-1850</field>
      <field name="title_display">Poetry for children</field>
      <field name="title_facet">poetry for children</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poetry for children</field>
      <field name="title_text">Poetry for children</field>
      <field name="year_display">1834</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1834</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1834</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440520&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440520&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Sigourney, L. H., (Lydia Howard), 1791-1865&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;sigourney l h lydia howard 1791 1865&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Poetry for children&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;poetry for children&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1834&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1834&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Sigourney, L. H., (Lydia Howard)&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1791&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1865&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poetry for children&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Hartford&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Robinson &amp;amp; Pratt&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1834&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3866278-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;cham1099&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- 1783-1850&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1783&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1850&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Poetry for children&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1996&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1996 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 109 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-AmPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">“Poetry holds children from their play, And old men from the chimney-corner.” Sir Philip Sidney JUVENILE POETRY. “Who made me?” He, who spread out the sky, That broad, blue canopy; Who made the glorious sun, The moon to shine by night, The stars with eye so bright, He made thee, little one. He, who with care doth keep The young birds while they sleep; And when their rest is done, Doth guide them through the sky, And feed them when they cry, He made thee, little one. I must not teaze my Mother. I must not teaze my Mother; For she is very kind, And every thing she says to me, I must directly mind; For when I was a baby, And could not speak or walk, She let me in her bosom sleep, And taught me how to talk. I must not teaze my Mother; And when she likes to read, Or has the head-ache, I will step Most silently indeed. I will not choose a noisy play, Nor trifling troubles tell, But sit down quiet by her side, And try to make her well. I must not teaze my Mother; I've heard dear father say, When I was in my cradle sick, She nurs'd me night and day. She lays me in my little bed, She gives me clothes and food, And I have nothing else to pay, But trying to be good. I must not teaze my Mother; She loves me all the day, And she has patience with my faults, And teaches me to pray; How much I'll strive to please her, She every hour shall see, For should she go away, or die, What would become of me? Morning Thoughts. Dark night away hath roll'd, Glad birds are soaring high, And see,—a ray like dazzling gold Comes darting from the sky. How shall I thank the Power Whose hand sustains me so, And o'er each waking plant and flower Bids dews of mercy flow? Teach me to look above; Receive my morning prayer, And Father in thy boundless love, Make me, this day, thy care. Thoughts at Sun-set. The sun hath gone to rest, The bee forsakes the flower, The bird doth hasten to its nest Within the leafy bower. Where have I been this day? Into what follies run? Forgive me, Father, when I pray Through Jesus Christ thy Son. When all my days are o'er, And in the tomb I rest, Oh, may my happy spirit soar Up to a Saviour's breast. The Dove. There was a lonely ark That sail'd o'er waters dark; And wide around, Not one tall tree was seen, No flower, nor leaf of green, All,—all were drown'd. Then a soft wing was spread, And o'er the billows dread, A meek dove flew; But on that shoreless tide No living thing she spied, To cheer her view. There was no chirping sound O'er that wide watery bound, To sooth her wo; But the cold surges spread Their covering o'er the dead, That slept below. So to the ark she fled, With weary, drooping head, To seek for rest: Christ is thy ark, my love, Thou art the timid dove,— Fly to his breast. Love to Brothers and Sisters. I had a little friend, And every day he crept In sadness to his brother's tomb, And laid him down and wept. And when I ask'd him why He mourn'd so long and sore; He answer'd through his tears, “because I did not love him more. “Sometimes!I was not kind, And cross or coldly spake;” And then he turn'd away, and sobb'd As though his heart would break. Brothers and sisters are a gift Of mercy from the skies, And may I always think of this Whene'er they meet my eyes. Be tender, good, and kind, And love them in my heart, Lest I should sink with bitter grief When we are call'd to part. Prayer at entering School. Lord!—lead my heart to learn, Prepare my ears to hear, And let me useful knowledge seek In thy most holy fear. Oh, make me kindly treat My dear companions, all, Nor let me causeless anger feel, Nor in temptation fall. If unforgiven sin Within my bosom lies. Or evil motives linger there To offend thy perfect eyes— Remove them far away, Inspire me with thy love, That I may please thee here below And dwell with thee above. Respect to Age. When leaning on the staff Amid the crowded street, With feeble step and wrinkled face Some aged form I meet. However poor and weak, Or ignorant and low, I must respect their hoary hairs, For God has told me so. I love to see the hair All venerably grey, A crown of glory 'tis to those Who walk in Wisdom's way. I love the reverend head, With years and honors white, 'Tis like the ripened fruit of heav'n, And angels bless the sight. Early Rising. Are my flowers awake That so sweet were sleeping? See,—they lift their heads, Dewy tear-drops weeping. Has the bee come forth? At her work she's singing, To her busy hive Honied treasures bringing. Is the linnet up? Hark! his song he raises, Let me join him too, With my morning praises. The Garden. Come, dear little friend, To the garden we'll go, I've water'd my rose-plants, Come see how they grow. The first one that blossoms, My mother's must be, For as I watch these rose-buds, She watch'd over me. Here, here are some pinks For your bosom and hair, 'Tis the pencil of Heaven, That hath dy'd them so fair. How thick the young violets Spring up at our feet, Let us love the kind hand That hath made them so sweet. Is it time for our school? Then we will thither repair, And the smile of our teachers Will welcome us there. The Sabbath. The best of the days has come, The day our Creator blest, And set an example to mark its hours By a sweet and holy rest. 'Tis a day to blessed thought And happy feelings given. A day to study that Blessed Book Which shews the way to Heaven. 'Tis a day to hear of God, Of angels and saints above, A day to learn how to fit our souls For their company of love. The grave of a Child. Come, see the grassy bed Where our companion lies, And mid your tears, remember well His buried dust shall rise. The seed that sown in earth Is hidden from the eye, At length puts forth the leaf, the bud, The flower of radiant dye. When wintry storms are past, Spring decks the verdant tree, And at the resurrection-morn Such shall his rising be. Hymn for the children of an Orphan Asylum. Not for our infant homes we pine, Nor mourn a parent's care, Adopted thus by christian love, And nurtur'd as we are; Instructed from the ways of sin To turn with cautious feet, And taught how truth and goodness make A lot of labor sweet. Hail, bounteous friends! who kindly guide Our steps in paths of peace, Ye ne'er shall be by us forgot Till life and memory cease; But daily, when we kneel in prayer We'll ask of Him above, To shed his blessing on your souls For all your deeds of love. Baby's note to a Baby with a pair of coral bracelets. Dear little Ann, I hope you can These bracelets wear, And that you will Remember still Whose gift they are. They're very plain, For to be vain I don't approve, Proud babies sure Few could endure, And fewer love. You're handsome, dear, They tell me here, But when you call To visit me, You'll quickly see I'm not at all. Tho' I've thick hair, No caps I wear, (Nurse says 'tis lawful)— My face is brown, And when I frown, 'Tis truly awful. You'll think I'm bold, Not six weeks old, To send this letter, Your're twice my age, And I'll engage Can write much better. So, when you've leisure 'Twill give me pleasure, Your notes to see; Some grave advice, Or precept wise, Pray send to me. Baby to a Baby with a New-Year's Present. 'Tis New-Year's day, The people say, Kind notes they frame, And presents send, So I, my friend, Will do the same. I think I must Write you the first, Because you see My age is four Whole months and more, And yours but three. You've talents great For church or state, I often hear, But don't be vain, Wise men are plain, And meek, my dear. When thought asleep I sometimes peep My cradle o'er, And slily turn My ear and learn Some curious lore. A doctor grave Who lives can save I thus espied; And when Nurse blam'd And loudly sham'd All babes who cried, He said 'twas better To lay no fetter Upon the lungs. Yet almost fear To have you hear My poor inditing, Your critic smile Must scorn my style Of baby-writing. Six months have shed Upon my head But little knowledge, While you are fit In sense and wit To enter college. My mother said The map you'd spread And shew with ease, All the globe boasts, Realms, isles and coasts, And lakes and seas. That you'd describe The four-legged tribe Both great and small, Both wild and tam'd That Adam nam'd In Eden, all. Years, at this rate Will make you great Or I'm mistaken. Perhaps with Locke, The crowd you'll mock Or shine like Bacon. With Franklin's zeal The lightning steal, And chain its rage, Or nobly write Your name like Dwight, On Heaven's own page. Our sex I'm told Are formed to hold A lower place, Our powers of mind Being far behind Your lordly race. I've understood That “household-good” Was our employment, To cook and mend, And babies tend, Our chief enjoyment. 'Tis very well, I sha'nt rebel, And when I grow, Shall like to make Nice pies and cake, And share also. But now good bye, 'Tis time that I Your patience spare, May you each day In love repay A parent's care. Mother and Boy. A DIALOGUE IN THE FIELDS. Come forth,—come forth, 'tis the time of joy, Bright summer is out, in the vales, my boy, Through its lillied bed, see the clear brook glide, And the white lamb sport by its mother's side, And the butterfly spread out a golden wing, And the bees to the honey blossoms sing, And the grasshopper leap 'mid the new-mown hay, So, we, my child, will be happy as they. Sweet words Speak the birds From the tree; Mother! teach Their speech Unto me. Of love they sing when they build their nest, Of love when they soar o'er the mountain's breast, Or nurture their young in their green retreat, This makes their music to us so sweet. And who can say but their warblings rise To our Father's ears in yon beautiful skies? Yet nobler, boy, than their highest lays, Is the language of man and the voice of praise. Mother's eye Like the sky Shines bright, Such beams To my dreams Give light. There's a smile on the earth and the waters mild, For the heart of a good and a happy child, And the sighing leaves on the wind-rock'd limb Will lull him to sleep like a cradle-hymn; While Nature, with pencil of rain-bow dye, Writes the name of God for his waking eye. Remember him, babe, in thy day of care, At morn, and at night, in thy simple prayer, Breathe the incense of childhood, fresh and free, And he in thine age will remember thee. Child of sixteen months old to a Cousin in Boston. My Cousin, dear, I almost fear To write to you; So rare your wit 'Tis surely fit, My words be few. Your native coast Has much to boast Of glorious name; Both antique lore And modern store Uphold its fame. You're proud, I fear, In Boston, dear; I wish you would Just come and share Our country fare, 'Twill do you good. Our rustic ways And boisterous plays Perhaps might fright you; But the sweet birds And lambs, and herds Must sure delight you. Pray give with this A Christmas kiss To aunties, three; And love to all, Both great and small, Who think of me. 'Tis time that I My cradle try, Nurse takes the light, And strains her ken, To snatch my pen, So, love, good night. A little Girl to a little Boy on his removal to New-York. You go, I'm told, This winter cold, A journey, sir, Pray shun the blast, And travel fast, Wrap'd close in fur. I'm sorry too, To part with you, Your courteous care At infant school, Next summer cool, I hop'd to share. My wish to go, I do not know But they'll refuse, Is it not shame My age should claim No right to choose. Twice has the sphere Roll'd round the year, Since I saw light; Yet all my skill To have my will, Has fail'd outright. I marvel why You wish to try A city life; Pleas'd as you were With rural care, And free from strife. Manners and men You'd better ken Among the throng; But the young breast Is nurtur'd best Mid Nature's song. I've heard that those Who pass for beaux, In lofty stations, Oft treat with scorn Their country-born, And poor relations. Now don't forget How oft we've met In Nurse's arms, When gay and free, You crow'd at me, And prais'd my charms. Little Girl to a little Girl, with a basket of wild flowers. You have green-house plants, I hear, Of rare and splendid tints, my dear, And I have no such gifts to send, Yet anxious still, to be your friend, These wild flowers from my father's grave, I charge with messages of love, —Microscopic tube will spy Charms in their simplicity, Hidden cells, where pure and free Springs the nectar for the bee, Graceful forms and radiant die From the pencil of the sky. Now my simple errand's told, For as I am but three years old, Letter brief, and scanty line, Best become a hand like mine. A little Girl to her friend, with a present of the Rev. Mr. Gallaudet's “Book of the Soul.” Unless my mother guides my hand, I cannot write, you know, But such a tide of tender thought Does round your image flow, I fain must send one simple scroll With this sweet book about the Soul. 'Tis written by a learned man, And though the size is small, Its subject is a boundless one, And much concerns us all, Because the soul can ne'er decay, When this frail body fades away. I've never seen this volume's power At all surpast, my dear, For making hidden mysteries plain, And abstract matters clear, Pray, let it have the highest place, Your chosen library to grace. I often of your sister, think, That early smitten flower, Who gave her soul so cheerfully To God, in life's last hour: Oh, may we meet her when we die, In yonder, bright, unclouded sky. Little Girl to her Pet Lamb. My Lamb, where hast thou been Roaming abroad all day? Cropping thy food in pastures green, Where the bright waters play? But of the sunny vale Thou'rt weary now, I see, So, thou may'st come and tell thy tale, And rest thy head on me. I have been sporting too, Where spring my favorite flowers, Among the lillies fresh with dew, Among the vine clad bowers, And by yon chrystal stream Where droops the willow tree, I sweetly slept, and had a dream, A pleasant dream of thee. And music all around Was breathing when I woke, From nest, and branch, and rose-deck'd bound, And from my lips it broke. Why does thy bosom beat? Hath aught disturb'd thy peace? Dear Lamb! have brambles torn thy feet, Or rent thy snowy fleece? Come! I can sooth thy pain, If thou wilt tell me free, And lull thee with that cooing strain, The young Dove taught to me. Thou by my side shalt run, Friend and companion dear, For since thou hast no evil done, What evil need'st thou fear? The Bee and Butterfly. “Come neighbour Bee,” said Butterfly, And spend a merry hour, For cloudless is the summer sky, And fragrant every flower; The Humming-bird a party gives. Closed by a ball in state, A fashionable life she lives, I'll shew you to the féte. Here is her card, she sent it down, She meant to call no doubt, But knew your Queen was apt to frown, And you are always out. But to the Butterfly, the Bee Replied, with serious brow, “Suppose you work an hour with me, I'm not at leisure now. By daily industry I live, Say, will you aid my task? And bear this pollen to the hive, If I do what you ask? Perhaps you'd better toil a while For your own winter store, For Summer wears a fleeting smile, And Autumn's at the door.” “Good bye,” the Butterfly rejoin'd, You've grown a mope I see, There's nothing hurts a brilliant mind, Like stupid industry,” And so, the Bee with cheerful care Pursued on pinions light, Thro' the vast regions of the air Her hackless path aright. The tallest trees she ventured up, And scal'd the vine-clad wall, Singing and tasting every cup, But temperate in all. One morn, as from her honied cell 'Mid Autumn's frost she sped, Beneath a flowret's withered bell The Butterfly lay dead. Aunt Nancy and her Parrot. Aunt Nancy was a maiden fair Who chose the lonely part; Birds, cats, and lap-dogs claim'd her care And rul'd her tender heart. Their every want she well supplied, But 'mid her hopeful race, A Parrot, gay as eastern bride, Maintain'd the highest place. He, to her elbow-chair would hie, Where she, erect and prim, Her fan and box of snuff laid by To play and talk with him. His wit and wisdom cheer'd her days, His accents charm'd her ear, As loud he conn'd his boasted phrase “Good bye, Aunt Nancy dear.” When in her garden's flowery spot The lady took the air, This proud prime-minister would trot, And scold, and chatter there. Her ancient favorites scarce could brook The eclipsing rival's state, His motions mark'd with jealous look, And ill-dissembled hate. The cross old lap-dog oft would snap. Regardless of the law, Or sly miss tabby give a tap With long protruded claw. Once as he chose alone to walk Like Eve, without a guide, A crooked-fang'd, marauding Hawk The morsel choice, espied. “My unfledg'd infants, sure,” he said, “Shall have a feast to-day,” So, with a fearful swoop, he made The struggling bird his prey. Aunt Nancy, by a shriek amaz'd Quick to the window flew, Put on her spectacles and gaz'd, And the lost darling knew. And as the Hawk, his talons sharp, With ruthless rage would ply It seem'd as if some breaking harp Shriek'd forth,—“good bye,—good bye.” Slow mingling with the summer cloud Those gorgeous plumes appear, Yet thence the Parrot scream'd aloud, “Good bye,—Aunt Nancy dear.” Then fast the pitying lady's tears Distain'd her wither'd cheek, At hearing thus from higher spheres, Her kidnapp'd idol speak. Full oft the tragic tale she told, And sympathy would claim, That even 'mid death's relentless hold, The bird pronounced her name. Oft too, her purring, growling train In dining-room, or grove, She lectur'd long in accents vain, Of Poll's superior love. And still, her tears each other chas'd, While some reproachful friend Would hint, that love on parrots placed Was apt in wo to end. The Rat. When others for their faults are blam'd, 'Tis a good rule to show Some causes for defence or praise, If any such we know. Now Rats are usually condemn'd As quite devoid of grace, And yet I can a story tell In honor of their race. A gallant ship to Lisbon went, And as it cross'd the sea, It found increasing 'mid its freight The rat fraternity. And most uncomfortable friends Those busy people were, For nothing could be so conceal'd But what they'd have a share. Candles, and eggs, and cheese, and bread, Off to their cells they bore, And rifled every apple-cask, And every sweet-meat store. And though to punish thefts like these The sailors oft would toil, Yet still these cunning culprits hid And fattened on the spoil. But when the vessel reach'd the port, Dark vengeance they secured, And fill'd their hold with sulphur smoke Too strong to be endured. The rats not fancying such perfume, Fled from their holes amain, And hurrying headlong o'er the wharf, Were without mercy slain. But one was seen with care to tread The path all red with gore, And on his back, a rat quite grey And blind with age he bore. Then some who mark'd this filial deed Did that good rat compare To Eneas, who from flames of Troy, His sire, Anchises, bare. The astonish'd executioners, No longer bitter foes, Did let the faithful creature pass In safety, where he chose. This simple tale is true, my dears, And so here ends the strain; For even if rats our candor crave, They should not ask in vain. Dialogue between the Canary and Humming Bird. HUMMING BIRD. You gaze from your narrow grate in vain, Poor prisoner-bird of the boasted strain; Fresh flowers spring up in each nook and dell, Every bird hath a tale of love to tell, And the fairest bowers 'neath the summer sky Are the haunt of the gadding butterfly; While you, in your pitiless durance pine, Say, what can you know of a joy like mine? CANARY BIRD. You hover about on the sunny spray, You revel among the flowers all day, You wound the rose if it wake your ire, But breathe no lay to the Bountiful Sire. While I, by a captive's ills opprest, Far, far from my native bowers of rest, Pour forth from the morn to the setting sun, The heart's deep music. “Thy will be done.” Cat and Kittens. Aunt Mary's cat, three snowy kittens had, Playful, and fat, and gay. And she would sport, And let them climb upon her back, and spread Her paws to fondle them,—and when she saw Her mistress come that way, would proudly show Her darlings, purring with intense delight. —But one was missing, and grimalkin ran Distracted, searching with a mother's haste Parlor and garret, sofa, box and bed, Calling her baby with a mournful cry, And questioning each creature that she met, In her cat-language, eloquently shrill. And then she left the house. Two hours past by,— When bringing her lost treasure in her mouth, She came exulting. While her mewing train Join'd in loud welcome, she with raptured zeal Wash'd and re-wash'd their velvet face and paws. —It had been given to a kind lady's care, By my Aunt Mary, out of pure good will To pussy, fearing she might be fatigued By too much care and nursing. But she sought From house to house, among the neighbors all Until she found, and numbered it again With her heart's jewels. One full month she fed And nurtur'd it. Then by the neck she took The same young kitten, and conveyed it back To the same house,—and laid it in the lap Of the same good old lady, as she sat Knitting upon the sofa. Much surpris'd She rais'd her spectacles to view the cat, Who with a most insinuating tone, Fawning and rubbing round her slipper'd foot Bespoke her favoring notice. This is true, Aunt Mary told me so. Did pussy think Her child too young for service?—and when grown To greater vigor, did she mean to shew Full approbation of her mistress' choice, By passing many a nearer house, to find The lady that its first indentures held? —This looks like reason,—and they say that brutes Are only led by instinct. Yet 'tis hard Sometimes to draw the line, where one begins, And where the other ceases. But I know That kindness to domestic animals Improves their nature,—and 'tis very wrong To take away their comforts, and be cross And cruel to them. The kind-hearted child Who makes them humble friends, will surely find A pleasure in such goodness, and obey The Book of Wisdom in its law of love. The Dog. “He will not come,” said the gentle child, And she patted the poor dog's head, And pleasantly call'd him, and fondly smil'd, But he heeded her not, in his anguish wild, Nor arose from his lowly bed. 'Twas his master's grave, where he chose to rest, He guarded it night and day, The love that glow'd in his grateful breast For the friend that had fed, controll'd, caress'd, Might never fade away. And when the long grass rustled near Beneath some traveller's tread, He started up with a quivering ear, For he thought 'twas the step of that master dear Returning from the dead. And sometimes, when a storm drew nigh And the clouds were dark and fleet, He tore the turf with a mournful cry, As if he would force his way or die, To his much lov'd master's feet. So, there through the summer's heat he lay, Till autumn nights were bleak; Till his eye grew dim with his hope's decay, And he pin'd, and pin'd, and wasted away, A skeleton gaunt and weak. And pitying children often brought Their offerings of meat and bread, And to coax him away to their homes they sought, But his buried friend he ne'er forgot, Nor stray'd from his lonely bed. Cold winter came with an angry sway, And the snow lay deep and sore; And his moaning grew fainter day by day, Till there, on the spot where his master lay He fell, to rise no more. And when he struggled with mortal pain, And death was by his side, With one loud cry that shook the plain, He call'd for his master, but all in vain, Then stretch'd himself and died. The Stork. See the stork, with labor tending Onward through the boundless sky; 'Neath those aged pinions bending, That had taught his own to fly. Still his parents' burden bearing Patient, o'er the trackless way, Ever for their comfort caring, Never wearied, night or day. Father! when thy head is hoary, When thine eye is dim with shade, Will it be my pride and glory Thy declining steps to aid? Mother! when thy spirits languish, When thy strength and youth are spent, Shall I love to soothe thine anguish, As thou o'er my cradle bent? Gentle, tireless, kind, and tender, Shall I watch lest thou art grieved? And the same affections render That I once from thee received? Filial lesson,—sweetly given! May it not be lost on me; Lest this simple bird of heaven Should my just reprover be. The Gold Fish. In globe of glass, and crystal tide, A graceful, golden form did glide, Still, in its shelter'd waveless sea, As happy as a fish could be. —But discontent it seems has place Even with the quiet, finny race, For raising oft a sadden'd eye, It heav'd a solitary sigh; Desiring some companion gay With whom to gambol and to play. —Its gentle master, ever prone To make another's wo his own, And able well to comprehend The priceless value of a friend, Did to its weakness condescend, And for his beauteous favorite bought A kindred spirit, as he thought. —But how the sequel shall I trace! That very night, the stranger, base, Destroyed the gentle, trusting fish, Whose only sin had been the wish, Not quite alone, without a mate, Life's little sea to navigate. —Then those who saw its death-clos'd eye So dim, beneath the waters lie, Might think they heard a pitying sigh Soft to their heart this warning send, “Be careful how you choose a friend.” War. War, is a wicked thing, It strikes the strong man dead, And leaves the trampled battle-field With blood and carnage red, While thousand mangled forms In hopeless suffering bleed, And vultures and hyenas throng Upon their flesh to feed. See with what bitter grief Those widowed ones deplore; And children for their father mourn, Who must return no more. And aged parents sink In penury and despair, And sorrow dwells in many a home,— War makes the weeping there. It comes with sins and woes, A dark and endless train, It fills the breast with murderous hate Where Christian love should reign, It desolates the land With famine, death, and flame, And those are in a sad mistake Who seek the warrior's fame. Oh, may I guard my heart From every evil thing, From thoughts of anger and revenge Whence wars and fightings spring. And may the plants of peace Grow up serene and fair, And mark me for a child of heaven That I may enter there. Difference of Color. God gave to Afric's sons A brow of sable dye, And spread the country of their birth Beneath a burning sky, And with a cheek of olive, made The little Hindoo child, And darkly stain'd the forest-tribes That roam our western wild. To me he gave a form Of fairer, whiter clay; But am I, therefore, in his sight Respected more than they? No,—'tis the hue of deeds and thoughts He traces in his Book, 'Tis the complexion of the heart On which he deigns to look. Not by the tinted cheek That fades away so fast, But by the color of the soul, We shall be judg'd at last. And God, the Judge, will look at me With anger in his eyes, If I, my brother's darker brow Should ever dare despise. Thoughts among Flowers. I've seen a full blown rose bow down, As though it fondly smil'd, Upon its little fragrant bud, As a mother loves her child. So have I seen twin lilies press Like tender sisters near, Affectionate in loveliness, And innocent as dear, And if a rain-drop's chilling tear Long on their bosoms lay, Those gentle friends divided it, Till the chillness fled away. I've seen the violet's dewy eye When summer showers did fall, Look grateful up to the clear blue sky, And the loving Sire of all. And clustering 'mid her neighbors fair, I've mark'd the daisy grow, As if she sought those sympathies That friendship can bestow. Perchance, around the flowers that glow So pure, in their green retreat, The same affections kindly flow, That make our lives so sweet. Letter from a little Western Emigrant Girl. Here are huge forests, cousin. The great elm With that low bench around it, where we sat At Summer's eve and ate our bread and milk, Thinking its green head reach'd into the sky, Was nothing to these tall, thick-woven trees That shut the sun out, here. I often think Of the sweet cherry-tree I us'd to call My own,—from which we gathered crimson fruit, So rich and ripe, and of the little bed Of tulips, which we two so oft would tend. Who helps you make your garden now? I hope Sometimes when you walk there, your heart will turn To your poor cousin, who remembers you, And has no garden. Tell my butterflies, Those red and black wing'd ones, that us'd all day To hover round our flowers, I wish they'd come On to this western country. They would find With their slight forms, and pinions swift as light, The journey but a trifle, which to us Was a sore labor, sure. We toil'd along, And toil'd, up hill and down, through dangerous roads, Plunging in rivers 'till the horses swam, And camping 'neath our waggon in the night, The baby always crying, as if he Who least could know the value of our home, Griev'd most to leave it. Yet 'tis pleasant here, And there are many birds, and father says 'Tis a good land. My elder sister mourns Because there is no school;—but as for me, I like to play all day among the hills, And frisk with the young lambs. When Sunday comes, And there is no sweet echoing bell, no church, No children with their lessons hasting on, Clean drest and happy,—in my breast there swells A sorrow unto tears, and by myself Where the thick bushes bend, I go and weep, Because I think my mother looks more sad To see her children grieving, and we ought To cheer her heart, who bears so much for us. —O cousin, love your teachers, love their voice Who bring you wisdom from the Book of God. And when you hear the tuneful bell that calls You to his house, lift up your heart in praise, And breathe a prayer, that we, poor emigrants, May share the blessings that you thus enjoy. Cheerfulness. ADAPTED TO THE TUNE OF “AWAY WITH MELANCHOLY.” Shall we oppress'd with sadness Strike Melancholy's string? No! take the harp of gladness, And merrily, merrily sing. Bright valleys crown'd with flowers, Gay birds on soaring wing, Incite our tuneful powers To cheerily,—cheerily sing. In sweet harmonious measures, Praise to Creation's king, The Author of our pleasures, We'll gratefully,—gratefully sing. Motto for a painted Work-Box. Might this light toy presume to teach, With radiant brow and pictur'd speech, The lesson of its choice would be, “Redeem the day from sloth,—through me:” So, while it aids with ready art The busy needle's dexterous part, Soft let it whisper to the heart, The absent giver's name,—and prove, The sweet remembrancer of love. Birth-Day Verses. TO A LITTLE GIRL WHO HAD LOST HER MOTHER. We love the flower that decks the spray, And brightens thro' the summer-day, We praise the fruit, whose ripening hue Of gold or crimson meets our view; But with delight far more refin'd, Behold the fair, expanding mind, Whose radiant blossoms charm the eye, Whose hallow'd fruits can never die. An eye there was whose tender beam Hung o'er thy being's earliest dream, That once upon this rising morn Wept tears of joy that thou wert born; And now, perchance, with watchful zeal, With such pure love as angels feel, Regards thee from that realm of day, Where every tear is wip'd away. Oh choose the path, that Mother trod, Belov'd on earth, and blest of God; At Pity's call, at Sorrow's sigh, Pour forth her heaven-taught sympathy, Her image in its grace restore, Print on thy brow the smile she wore, Bare as she bore, a Saviour's name, —What higher wish can Friendship frame? Dialogue between Orphan Sisters. YOUNGEST SISTER. Sister,—when I go to rest, The last image in my breast, Is of a hand that gently spread The covering o'er my cradle-bed, And of a bosom soft and kind On which my infant head reclin'd. And ever, when I wake,—my theme, As of some dear and blissful dream, Is of a tone prolong'd and clear, Sweet and birdlike to my ear, Of a fond kiss,—it was not thine, And murmer of the Name Divine: Sister,—you remember well, Tell me of our parents,—tell. ELDEST SISTER. Alas of him,—our father-guide, Few tints hath memory's scroll supplied; A tender smile,—a glance, whose pain Could well my wayward moods restrain, Fair gifts that still unsullied shine, In childhood's books some pencil'd line,— And then, a burst of bitter wo, Knell, coffin, and procession slow, And this is all of him who sleeps Where yonder drooping willow weeps, But of that blessed one who gave Our father to the lonely grave, So strong with every thought is wove, The tireless teachings of her love, With every fibre of the mind, So close her prayer her smile entwin'd, That my whole being's hidden store Seems by her pencil written o'er; And if within my heart there springs Some chasten'd love of holy things, She sow'd the seed with mild control That patient florist of the soul. Sweetest, let me dry thy tear, Thou art like that mother dear, And I fain would be to thee What that mother was to me. Winter Thoughts. Winter hath hid my flowers. I cannot find A single violet where so many grew, And all my garden-beds, so nicely fring'd With verdant box, are cover'd thick with snow. He has not left one lingering pink, to please My little sister. Sure,—tis very hard For Winter so to come,—and take away What was my own, and I had toil'd to keep Healthful, and free from weeds. They say he rocks The wearied flowers to sleep, as some good nurse Compels the infant to resign its sports, And go to needful slumber. Well,—I thought My roses all look'd sleepy,—and I know When one is tir'd, how very sweet it is, To shut the eyelids close, and know no more, Until the wakening of a mother's kiss. Winter looks stern and hath an angry voice. I hope he will not harm my tender buds, That had just put their velvet leaflets forth, And seem'd so frighten'd. But I know who rules Harsh Winter, and spreads out the spotless snow, Like a soft curtain over every herb, And shrinking plant that it may rest secure, And undisturb'd. He shields the lowliest shrub That strikes its lone root at the mountain's base, With the same gentle and protecting love As the moss-rose. Yea. He doth care for all, The ivy, and the aspen, and the moss Clothing the ancient wall,—who have no friend To watch them,—and no fragrance to repay. Father in Heaven! I thank Thee for the rest Thou giv'st my weary flowers. Grant them to wake At Spring's first call and rear their beauteous heads Rejoicing,—as my baby-brother springs From his sweet cradle-sleep,—with tiny arms Outstretch'd,—and eyes like my own violets bright. Intemperance. I saw a little girl With half uncovered form, And wondered why she wandered thus, Amid the winter storm; They said her mother drank What took her sense away, And so she let her children go Hungry and cold all day. I saw them lead a man To prison for his crime, Where solitude, and punishment, And toil divide the time; And as they forc'd him through its gate Unwillingly along, They told me 'twas Intemperance That made him do the wrong. I saw a woman weep As if her heart would break; They said her husband drank too much Of what he should not take. I saw an unfrequented mound Where weeds and brambles wave; They said no tear had fallen there, It was a drunkard's grave. They said these were not all The risks the intemperate run, For there was danger lest the soul Be evermore undone. Water is very pure and sweet, And beautiful to see, And since it cannot do us harm, It is the drink for me. Life. Life is like a fleeting dream, Like the rapid summer stream, Like the flashing meteor's ray, Like the shortest winter's day, Like the fitful breeze that sighs, Like the wavering flame that dies, Darting, dazzling on the eye, Fading in Eternity. Entrance to a Sunday School. Father in Heaven! my spirit ought Thy blessing to implore, Admitted where thy truths are taught, And pious hearts adore. Instruct my ignorance, I pray, My wayward passions tame, From every folly guard my way, From every sin reclaim. Each task with pleasure may I learn, Each Scripture-lesson prize, And grant thy wisdom to discern Whate'er in darkness lies. Short is the time we here may pass, And life is transient too, Like the brief flowret of the grass, Or like the morning dew. With trembling awe, thy power I see, Thy boundless mercy sing, Few words become a child like me Before so great a King. Teach me thy precepts to fulfil, To trust a Savior's love, To yield to thy most righteous will And seek a home above. “He is about my path,—and about my bed.” Psalm 139th. When first my infant feet essay'd, The movements of my will to aid, Parents and friends with watchful eye To guard my tottering steps would fly. But now, 'mid verdant paths I stray, Or on the clear brook's margin play, Till the Sun's parting lustres burn— Go fearless forth and safe return, For watchful ever by my side, A Father doth my footstep guide. When weary on my pillow laid Mild evening draws her curtaining shade, And busy dreams, with changeful sway Bring back the pleasures of the day, When the last form that linger'd near, My tender mother, ever dear, Hath left her kiss, hath breath'd her prayer, And in sweet rest resign'd her care: Still One, whose eye can never sleep, Around my bed his watch doth keep. Moses. There was a king of Egypt, and he made A cruel law, that every infant son Born to the Hebrew race, throughout his realm, Should be destroyed. Think! what a cruel law, That those sweet, sinless infants should be slain. —But one fond mother hid her babe away, So that they might not find him, and she went Silent, and gave him food; and when he cried She softly hush'd him, lest his voice should lead The murderers to their prey. So he became Exceeding fair, and health upon his cheek Gleam'd like an opening rose. Three months past by, And his glad eye grew brighter, when he heard His mother's footstep, though he did not know Why she would press her finger on his lip To check his joyous mirth. With bitter pang She gaz'd upon the beauty of his smile, And shuddering heard his laughter, for she felt She could no longer hide him. So, one morn, She wrapt him safely in a cradle-ark, And with a hurried foot-step laid him down Among the rushes by the river's brink. —Strangely the wild eye of the wondering babe, Gaz'd on her from the water,—and his arms Stretch'd from their reedy prison, sought in vain To twine about her neck. She turn'd away, Breathing that prayer, which none but mothers breathe, For their endanger'd babes. It was the Nile, On which she laid her son in his slight ark Of woven rushes. She remember'd well The gaunt and wily crocodile, that loves To haunt those slimy waters. But she knew That He who made the crocodile could stay His ravenous jaws. So, in his mighty arm She put her trust. Close by the river's brink, Her little mournful daughter staid to see What would befal her brother, and her voice Did sweetly struggle with her grief, to sing The hymn that sooth'd the child. But then there came Proud Egypt's princess, with her flowing robes, Walking that way. And when she saw the ark Among the flags, she bade her maidens haste, And bring it to her. Lo! there lay a babe, A weeping babe:—and when she saw its brow, Polish'd and beautiful, all wet with tears, And deadly pale, pity and love sprang up In her kind bosom, and she took the boy To her own palace-home. Yet still he wept, Like an affrighted stranger. Then she bade To call a nurse; and lo! the mother came! She, who had sown in tears, did reap in joy. —And when she drew her nursling to her breast, And fondly lull'd him to a gentle sleep, Know ye how warm the thrill of praise went up Unto the God of Israel? —So, this babe Of the poor Hebrew, 'neath the royal dome Of Egypt's monarch grew,—in all the lore Of that wise realm instructed. He became A prophet, mighty both in word and deed. And when you read, my children, how he broke The yoke of bondage from his people's neck, And smote with awful rod the parting sea, And brought pure water from the rock, and stood On Sinai, with Jehovah face to face, You will bethink you of this simple tale,— The Ark of rushes, and the Mother's prayer. Samuel. There came to Zion's courts, a guest, With meek and reverent air, Whose tender, watchful eye express'd A mother's anxious care. And by his hand, a boy she brought, And thus the priest bespake,— “Lo! of my God, this son was sought, The gift to him I make.” She hid the tear-drop in her heart, And musing, homeward sped, While the fond child, compell'd to part, Wept on his lonely bed. When night hung heavy in her sphere, And all was dark with shade, Jehovah's voice address'd his ear, And answering, he obey'd. The priest observed with wondering care The grace to Samuel given, Beholding how a mother's prayer Might win the grace of Heav'n; For pure devotion's holy flame Was with his stature rear'd, Till Hannah's son, a Seer became, By listening Israel fear'd. The Almighty. Who bade thy parents love thy infant form, And shield thy weakness from the wintry storm, Who gave the ear to hear, the mind to know, The eye to sparkle, and the blood to flow? Who grants the day of health, the night of rest, Strength to thy limbs, and comfort in thy breast? Who marks with kindest care thy daily lot? Whose arm sustains thee though thou seest it not? Whose watchful eye observes thy secret ways? Who writes the record of thy fleeting days? Go, ask the stream that rolls in torrents by, Ask of the stars that light the darken'd sky, Or of the fields, array'd in garments fair, Or of the birds that warble in the air, Or of the mountain-lilies wet with dew, Or of the trees, and they will tell thee who,— Then lift thine eyes adoring to his throne, And bow thy heart to Him, the Everlasting One. “He feedeth the young ravens that cry.” The new-fledg'd ravens leave the nest, And with a clamorous cry, Uncertain wing, and ruffled breast, In broken circles fly. Abandon'd by a parent's care, They famish'd press the sod, And in the wildness of despair Demand their meat of God. By him who feeds the ravenous bird And guards the sparrow's lot, Shall our petitions be unheard? Our sorrowing sighs forgot? Consider how the lilies grow, The young birds safely rove, Nor fear in every time of wo To trust your Maker's love. An Emblem. I've seen a drop of morning dew Like radiant gem serene, Bright sparkling on a verdant bough All clad in summer-green. The risen sun exhal'd the tear, And drank it, as it shone; The sudden lightning smote the branch, It shiver'd, and was gone. Was not that dew-drop like the bloom And morning of our span? And yonder broken, blasted bough, Like the frail hope of man? Sunday School Hymn. I hear the voice of Nature's praise 'Mid summer's joyous bowers, And where the streams with crystal maze Refresh the thirsty flowers. And where yon high o'er-arching trees In verdant robes are drest, It comes on every gentle breeze From bough, and spray, and nest. Then, if the things by Nature taught Breathe music o'er the sod, How high should rise our raptur'd thought, We, who are taught of God! To us he speaks,—from morning's cell, From evening's dewy sphere, And when the Sabbath's holy bell Melodious warns the ear. To us he speaks,—He guides our choice By heaven's own Book divine, And aids our teacher's much-lov'd voice To impress each treasur'd line. To us He speaks,—and we in praise Would still our answer bring; Here, where Creation prompts our lays, And there, where angels sing. A Scripture Story. Children, I'll tell a story of the sea, And Him, who walk'd upon it. It was night, Dark night, and the loud winds howl'd fearfully Along the madden'd billows. O'er these waves In all their pride and anger, Jesus came. —A ship lay tossing there, and the strain'd eyes Of the storm-driven mariners, were bent On Him with terror, for they did not know Their Master in that hour. But at the sound, Of his blest voice that cheer'd their fainting hearts, Peter, with eager footstep hasted down To meet his Lord. The wild and boisterous blast Made him afraid, and the cold surge came up Against his shuddering breast. “Save me!”—he cried, “Save, or I perish.” Then the Savior's hand Was stretch'd to succor him; even as it plucks The soul that trusts him from the flood of death, And gives it victory. Safe on the deck Among the glad disciples, Peter stood, Full of adoring gratitude, while all Gave praise and glory to the Son of God. —Then Peter learn'd he might not place his foot Upon the ocean's stormy face and live. Children, you know the reason. 'Tis not given To man to tread the sea. It riseth up, And sweeps him like a feeble weed away. —But God doth do, what man attempts in vain. And he who made the sea, can bid its waves In all the madness of their stormy strength, Spread a smooth pavement for his feet divine. Christ blessing the Children. “And he took them in his arms, put his hands upon them, and blessed them.” Mark 10:16. When the Redeemer dwelt in clay, The proud, the powerful shunn'd his sway, The scribe and pharisee, with frown On him of Nazareth look'd down, And Judah, long with dream elate Of her Messiah's regal state, Beheld the homeless one with hate, And Rome, with haughty mockery ey'd The Man of grief, the crucified.— —But they, the innocent, the blest, In childhood's meekness, sought his breast, Their little feet without a guide Came thronging to his peaceful side, And tho' the cold and stern command Bade them at greater distance stand, Yet strengthen'd by his cheering smile, They gather'd to his arms the while, And 'mid his bosom's holy shade Their beauteous heads, confiding laid. —Children! even now that heavenly Friend Doth to your weakness condescend; Yes, still he marks with favoring smile, Your trusting spirits, free from guile,— Still, by his gracious Word would guide Your steps in safety to his side; Still waits, in tender love to shed His blessing on your duteous head. —Lambs of the flock! with all your charms, Haste to your glorious Shepherd's arms. Death of the youngest Child. “Why is our infant sister's eye No more with gladness bright? Her brow of dimpled beauty, why So like the marble white?” My little ones, ye need no more To hush the sportive tread, Or whispering, pass the muffled door,— Your sweetest one is dead. In vain you'll seek her joyous tone Of tuneful mirth to hear, Nor will her suffering, dove-like moan Again distress your ear. Lost to a mother's pillowing breast, The snow-wreath marks her bed, Her polish'd cheek in earth must rest,— Your sweetest one is dead. Returning spring, the birds will call Their happy task to take; Vales, verdant trees, and streamlets, all From winter's sleep shall wake, Again your cherished flowers shall bloom, Anew their fragrance shed; But she, the darling, will not come,— Your sweetest one is dead. Ye know that blest Redeemer's name Who gaz'd on childhood's charms, Indulgent heard its gentle claim, And clasp'd it in his arms; To him, your sister-babe hath gone, Her pains, her tears are o'er, Safe, near her Heavenly Father's throne, She bows to death no more. Praise for religious Instruction. Awake the grateful hymn of praise To our Almighty Friend, Who bids instruction's holy light On infant minds descend;— Who bids the heaven-taught spirit toil To spread its knowledge wide, And urge the listening child to seek The love of Christ who died;— Who makes the moral desert hear Salvation's glorious voice, The wild and solitary place With sudden bloom rejoice. To us, oh Lord, who learn thy word, A docile mind impart, And deign to touch with tireless zeal Each faithful teacher's heart, Till as the rushing waters fill The boundless ocean's bed, The saving knowledge of thy will O'er all the earth shall spread. Funeral Hymn for a Sunday School Scholar. As crushed by sudden storms, the rose Sinks on the garden's breast, Down to the grave our brother goes In earth's cold arms to rest. No more with us, his tuneful voice The hymn of praise shall swell, No more his cheerful heart rejoice To hear the Sabbath-bell. Yet if in yon unclouded sphere, Amid a blessed throng, He warbles to his Savior's ear The everlasting song,— No more we'll mourn our buried friend, But lift the ardent prayer, And every wish and effort bend To rise and join him there. The First Martyr. There was a holy man, in ancient times Who taught the Jewish people, Full of power, And strong in faith, he told them of the Christ, The hope of Israel. But their hearts were hard, And their ears deaf to preaching. More than this,— They were offended at him. So, by force They brought him to the Council, and accused Falsely, of evil deeds, and impious words, Against their Law and Prophet. The High Priest, Majestic, from his seat of state inquired, “Are these things so?” Then, lo! the face of him Who stood arraign'd before them, brightly glow'd With such celestial light of innocence, That they who gaz'd upon it, deem'd they saw An angel's countenance. And then he spake The truth with boldness,—how the voice of God Bade faithful Abraham leave his native home For a far land of strangers,—and with power Speaking through Moses, led their fathers forth From Egypt's bondage, through the parted sea, And through the desert, to a fruitful land, Giving them rest, beneath the peaceful sway Of their own kings. But at his keen rebuke Of their ingratitude and unbelief, And sinful shedding of a Savior's blood, They gnash'd their teeth, and from the city's bound Hurried him forth, hurling with furious rage Stones at his guiltless head. Kneeling, he met The murderous shower. Before his stedfast sight There was a vision of the Son of God, And heaven's unuttered glory. His pale lip Trembling with painful death, still strove in prayer, For his blood-thirsty foes. “Lord! to their charge Lay not this sin.” And so, he fell asleep: The first meek martyr to the faith of Christ, Mangled and crush'd beneath the unpitying storm Of sinful anger. Children, who have read Of Stephen in your bibles, you will know That this was he. You do not live in days Of persecution,—but I'll tell you how You may resemble Stephen;—yea, even more, How to be like the Master whom he served. —When at your homes, or in your sports, you take Offence at your companions, and the blood Rushes up warmly to your brow, and prompts The deed of anger, ask of Stephen's God To teach you how to pardon, and to melt With gentle dews of love, the thought unkind. On a Child of two and a half years old, who wiped the tears of his Father with his dying hand. Pale was the little polish'd brow That lately bloomed so fair, And speechless lay the baby-boy, His parents' pride and care. The struggle and the fever-pang That shook his frame were past, And there, with fix'd and wishful glance He lay—to breathe his last. Upon his sorrowing father's face He gazed with dying eye, Then raised a cold and feeble hand His starting tears to dry. And so he wip'd those weeping eyes Even with his parting breath; Oh! tender deed of infant love, How beautiful in death! Yes,—ere that gentle soul forsook The fainting, trembling clay, It caught the spirit of that world Where tears are wiped away. And still its cherish'd image gleams Upon the parent's eye, A guiding-cherub to that home Where every tear is dry. The Infant's Prayer. A very young and lovely child in New-York, was found in prayer by her bed-side, for her little sick cousin. She was not able to say plainly, Elizabeth, which was the name of her dear playmate. So her prayer was, “please God, let Lilly live.” Those two sweet children died within a short time of each other, of the same disease. It was the will of their Father in heaven, that they should live together with him. The West had shut its gate of gold Upon the parted sun, And through each window's curtaining fold Lamps glimmer'd one by one; And many a babe had gone to rest, And many a tender mother's breast Still lull'd its darling care, When in a nursery's quiet bound, With fond affections circled round, I heard an infant's prayer. Yes, there it knelt,—its cherub face Uprais'd with earnest air; And well devotion's heaven born grace Became a brow so fair; But seldom at our Father's throne Such blest and happy child is known So painfully to strive; For long with tearful ardor fraught, That supplicating lip besought,— “Please God, let Lilly live.” And still the imploring voice did flow That little couch beside, As if for “poor sick Lilly's” wo, It could not be denied: Even when the balm of slumber stole With soothing influence o'er the soul, Like moon-light o'er the stream, The murmuring tone, the sobbing strife, The broken plea for Lilly's life, Mix'd with the infant dream. So Lilly liv'd.—But not where time Is measur'd out by woes; Not where cold Winter chills the clime, Or canker eats the rose; And she, who for that darling friend— In agonizing love did bend To pour the simple prayer,— Safe from the pang, the groan, the dart, That wound the mourning parent's heart, Lives with her Lilly there. The Last Day in the Year. Oh Thou, who dwellest in the heavens, Whom angels love and fear, Who giv'st us in thy tender love To close another year,— Did'st for our many daily wants Untiringly provide, And grant us friends and parents dear Our thoughtless steps to guide,— When sickness smote our feeble frames, Did'st take away our pain, And even when others sought the grave, Restor'd our health again,— And bade the lamp of knowledge shine With radiance full and free, And sent thy holy Book to shew The path that leads to Thee,— Oh! give us good and grateful hearts Thy mercy to adore, And take our spirits, when we die, Where they can praise thee more. New Year's Address to the Children of the United States. My children, 'tis the New Year's morn, And many a wish for you is born, And many a prayer, of spirit true, Breaks from paternal lips for you. —No more the vales with daisies glow, The violet sleeps beneath the snow, The rose her radiant robes doth fold And hide her buds from winter's cold. But Spring, with gentle smile, shall call Up from their beds, those slumberers all; Fresh verdure o'er your path shall swell, The brook its tuneful story tell, And graceful flowers with varied bloom Again your garden's bound perfume. —Ye are our buds; and in your breast The promise of our hope doth rest. When knowledge like the breath of Spring Shall wake your minds to blossoming, May their unfolding germs disclose More than the fragrance of the rose, More than the brightness of the stream, That through green shades, with sparkling gleam In purity and peace doth glide On to the ocean's mighty tide. —The country, too, which gave you birth, That freest, happiest clime of earth, To all, to each, with fervor cries, “Child! for my sake,—be good, be wise. Seek knowledge, and with studious pain, Resolve her priceless gold to gain. Shun the strong cup, whose poisonous tide To ruin's dark abyss doth guide, And with the sons of virtue stand, The bulwark of your native land. —Me, would you serve? This day begin The fear of God, the dread of sin; Love, for instruction's watchful care, The patient task, the nightly prayer, So shall you glitter as a gem, Bound in my brightest diadem.” Minerva's Prize. Minerva, a visit to Flora once made, When the flowers, in a body, their compliments paid, And charm'd with their manners and elegant dyes, She promis'd to give to the fairest a prize; And appointed a day when herself would preside, And on their pretensions to beauty, decide. —Then the rose bridled up with a confident air, As if she would say, “who with me can compare?” While the lily, but newly come out as a bride, Whisper'd long to her sisters, and laugh'd at such pride. —The hyacinth studied her wardrobe with care, Still puzzled to settle what colors to wear. The poppy ashamed of her dull, sleepy eyes, Wore a bright scarlet dress, with a view to the prize; While the tulip came flaunting and waving her fan, And turn'd up her nose at the daffodil clan. Then flock'd the anemonies, fair to behold, With the rich polyanthus in velvet and gold, And the jonquil with corsets lac'd terribly tight, The hump on her back to conceal from the sight, Tho' her gasping for breath, and stiff movements betray'd The pain she endur'd and the effort she made, While wiser globe-amaranth whisper'd apart How such folly would injure the lungs and the heart There were some so mistaken and vain, as to say That by fine dress alone, they could carry the day. So with them, there was toiling and prinking enough, And trying new fashions of head-dress and ruff. The stately carnations stood frizzing their hair, And the tall London-pride choosing feathers to wear; The pink at her mirror was ready to drop, And the snow-ball bought rouge at a milliner's shop, While in the same square, at a shoe-store so neat, The trim ladies'-slippers sat pinching their feet. —Thrifty lilac observed that her robe was not new, But with turning and furbishing thought it might do, While the queer ragged-lady, who pass'd for a poet, Wish'd to darn up her hose, and let nobody know it, And the monk's-hood who simper'd in scorn at a sonnet, Was tying new bows on her sombre old bonnet. —The green-house exotics in chariots went by, For their delicate nerves fear'd each frown of the sky, While from her low cottage of moss on the plain, The violet look'd up and admir'd the bright train, Not dreaming to join in a circle so gay, Or supposing that she had a charm to display, Then o'er a sick sister she tenderly bow'd, And kiss'd her pale brow, as she turn'd from the crowd. —With delight, Flora gaz'd on the glittering train, And bade them pass by her, again and again. But judge how that well dress'd conventicle star'd, When Minerva the prize to the violet declar'd! And added,—“tho' beauty and splendor were there, That modesty ever to her was most fair; Bright brows and gay costumes might dazzle the eyes, But merit, tho' meek, was preferred by the wise: And fashion might garnish the form with her art, But the pearl of true beauty lay deep in the heart.” A Mother's Grave. My mother's grave. 'Tis there beneath the trees. I love to go alone, and sit, and think Upon that grassy mound. My cradle hours Come back again so sweetly, and the smile That ever beamed upon me, when I woke And lifted up my head, to kiss the cheek That bow'd to meet me. And I seem to feel Once more the hand that smooth'd my clustering curls, And led me to the garden, pointing out Each fragrant flower and bud, or drawing back My foot, lest I should careless crush the worm That crawl'd beside us. And that gentle tone, Teaching to pat the house-dog, and be kind To the poor cat, and spare the little flies Upon the window, and divide my bread With those that hunger'd, and bow meekly down To the grey-headed man, and a look with love On all whom God hath made. And then her hymn At early evening, when I went to rest, And folded closely to her bosom, sat Joining my cheek to her's and pouring out My broken music, with her tuneful strain:— Comes it not back again, that holy hymn, Even now, upon my ear? But when I go To my lone bed, and find no mother there, And weeping, kneel to say the prayer she taught, Or when I read the Bible that she lov'd, Or to her vacant seat at church draw near, And think of her, a voice is in my heart, Bidding me early seek my God, and love My blessed Savior. Sure, that voice is her's. I know it is, because these were the words She us'd to speak so tenderly, with tears, At the still twilight-hour, or when we walk'd Forth in the Spring amid rejoicing birds, Or whispering, talk'd beside the winter fire. —Mother! I'll keep these precepts in my heart, And do thy bidding. Then, when God shall say, My days are finish'd, will he give me leave To come to thee? And can I find thy home And see thee with thy glorious garments on, And kneel at the Redeemer's feet, and beg That where the Mother is, the Child may dwell? A Prayer. Giver of our every blessing, Thou, for whose unceasing care, Earth is still her praise addressing, Hear thy little children's prayer. Wisdom, with our stature grant us, Goodness with each growing year, Nor let folly's wiles enchant us From our duty's sacred sphere. Grant us hope when life is ending; When the pulse forsakes the breast, May our spirit, upward tending, Father! in thy bosom rest.</field>
   </doc>
</add>