<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Wilcox, Ella Wheeler, 1850-1919</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Wilcox, Ella Wheeler, 1850-1919</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">wilcox ella wheeler 1850 1919</field>
      <field name="author_text">Wilcox, Ella Wheeler, 1850-1919</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1910's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ap/uvaGenText/tei/chap_AM0327.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240350</field>
      <field name="date_text">1912</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:439776</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Picked Poems</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Picked Poems</field>
      <field name="title_facet">picked poems</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">picked poems</field>
      <field name="title_text">Picked Poems</field>
      <field name="year_display">1912</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1912</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1912</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:439776&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:439776&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Wilcox, Ella Wheeler, 1850-1919&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;wilcox ella wheeler 1850 1919&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Picked Poems&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;picked poems&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1912&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1912&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Wilcox, Ella Wheeler&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1850&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1919&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Picked Poems&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Chicago&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;W. B. Conkey Company&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1912&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3866348-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;cham0327&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Picked Poems&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1996&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1996 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 29 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted ; verse reproduced elsewhere in American</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Poetry omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-AmPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I STEP ACROSS THE MYSTIC BORDER-LAND I step across the mystic border-land, And look upon the wonder-world of Art. How beautiful, how beautiful its hills! And all its valleys, how surpassing fair! The winding paths that lead up to the heights Are polished by the footsteps of the great. The mountain-peaks stand very near to God: The chosen few whose feet have trod thereon Have talked with Him. and with the angels walked. Here are no sounds of discord—no profane Or senseless gossip of unworthy things— Only the songs of chisels and of pens, Of busy brushes, and ecstatic strains Of souls surcharged with music most divine. Here is no idle sorrow, no poor grief For any day or object left behind— For time is counted precious, and herein Is such complete abandonment of Self That tears turn into rainbows, and enhance The beauty of the land where all is fair, Awed and afraid, I cross the border-land. Oh, who am I, that I dare enter here Where the great artists of the world have trod— The genius-crowned aristocrats of Earth? Only the singer of a little song; Yet loving Art with such a mighty love I hold it greater to have won a place Just on the fair land's edge, to make my grave, Than in the outer world of greed and gain To sit upon a royal throne and reign. BROTHERHOOD God, what a world, if men in street and mart, Felt that same kinship of the human heart, Which makes them, in the face of fire and flood, Rise to the meaning of True Brotherhood. IF— If I were a raindrop, and you were a leaf, I would burst from the cloud above you And lie on your breast in a rapture of rest, And love you, love you, love you. If I were a brown bee, and you were a rose, I would fly to you, love, nor miss you; I would sip and sip from your nectared lip, And kiss you, kiss you, kiss you. If I were a doe, dear, and you were a brook, Ah, what would I do then, think you? I would kneel by the bank, in the grasses dank, And drink you, drink you, drink you. LIFE'S LESSON BOOK Life is a ponderous lesson-book, and Fate The teacher. When I came to love's fair leaf My teacher turned the page and bade me wait. “Learn first,” she said, “love's grief”; And o'er and o'er through many a long tomorrow She kept me conning that sad page of sorrow. Cruel the task; and yet it was not vain. Now the great book of life I know by heart. In that one lesson of love's loss and pain Fate doth the whole impart. For, by the depths of woe, the mind can measure The beauteous unscaled summits of love's pleasure. Now, with the book of life upon her knee, Fate sits! the unread page of love's delight By her firm hand is half concealed from me, And half revealed to sight. Ah Fate! be kind! so well I learned love's sorrow, Give me its full delight to learn tomorrow. FREEDOM I care not who were vicious back of me, No shadow of their sins on me is shed. My will is greater than heredity. I am no worm to feed upon the dead. My face, my form, my gestures and my voice, May be reflections from a race that was. But this I know, and knowing it, rejoice, I am Myself, a part of the Great Cause. I am a spirit! Spirit would suffice, If rightly used, to set a chained world free. Am I not stronger than a mortal vice That crawls the length of some ancestral tree? AN EPISODE Along a narrow Moorish street A blue-eyed soldier strode. (Ah, well-a-day) Veiled from her lashes to her feet She stepped from her abode, (Ah, lack-a-day). Now love may guard a favoured wife Who leaves the harem door; (Ah, well-a-day) But hungry hearted is her life When she is one of four. (Ah, lack-a-day). If black eyes glow with sudden fire And meet warm eyes of blue— (Ah, well-a-day). The old, old story of desire Repeats itself anew. (Ah, lack-a-day.) When bugles blow the soldier flies— Though bitter tears may fall (Ah, lack-a-day). A Moorish child with blue, blue eyes Plays in the harem hall. (Ah, well-a-day.) THE EMPTY BOWL I held the golden vessel of my soul And prayed that God would fill it from on high. Day after day the importuning cry Grew stronger—grew, a heaven-accusing dole Because no sacred waters laved my bowl. “So full the fountain, Lord, wouldst Thou deny The little needed for a soul's supply? I ask but this small portion of Thy whole.” Then from the vast invisible Somewhere, A voice, as one love-authorized by Him, Spake, and the tumult of my heart was stilled. “Who wants the waters must the bowl prepare; Pour out the self, that chokes it to the brim, But emptied vessels, from the Source are filled.” TIME'S DEFEAT Time has made conquest of so many things That once were mine. Swift-footed, eager youth That ran to meet the years; bold brigand health, That broke all laws of reason unafraid, And laughed at talk of punishment. Close ties Of blood and friendship, and that joy of life, Which reads its music in the major key And will not listen to a minor strain— These things and many more are spoils of time. Yet as a conqueror who only storms The outposts of a town, and finds the fort Too strong to be assailed, so time retreats And knows his impotence. He cannot take My three great jewels from the crown of life; Love, sympathy, and faith; and year on year He sees them grow in lustre and in worth, And glowers by me, plucking at his beard, And dragging as he goes, a useless scythe. Once in the dark he plotted with his friend Grim death, to steal my treasures. Death replied: “They are immortal, and beyond thy reach: I could but set them in another sphere, To shine with greater lustre.” Time and Death Passed on together, knowing their defeat; And I am singing by the road of life. IN ENGLAND In England, there are wrongs no doubt, Which should be righted; so men say, Who seek to weed earth's garden out, And give the roses right of way; Yes, right of way, to fruit and rose, Where now but poison ivy grows. In England, there is wide unrest, They tell me who should know; and yet I saw but hedges, gayly dressed, And eyes where love and kindness met; Yes, love and kindness, met and made Soft sunshine even in the shade. In England, there are haunting things Which follow one to other lands; Like some pervading scent that clings To laces touched by vanished hands; Yes, touched by vanished hands, which made A fragrance that defies the grave. In England, centuries of art Give common things a mellow tone; And wake old memories in the heart Of other lives the soul has known; Yes, other lives in some past age Start forth from canvas, and from page. In England, there are simple joys, The modern world has left all sweet; In London's heart, are nooks where noise Has entered but with slippered feet; Yes, entered softly. Friend, believe, To part from England is to grieve. IN INDIA'S DREAMY LAND In India's land one listens aghast To the people who scream and bawl; For each caste yells at a lower caste, And the Britisher yells at them all. RANGOON Just a changing sea of colour Surging up and flowing down; And pagodas shining golden, night and noon; And a sun-burst-tinted throng Of young priests that move along Under sun-burst-hued umbrellas through the town. That's Rangoon. SONGS OF A COUNTRY HOME. I Who has not felt his heart leap up, and glow What time the tulips first begin to blow, Has one sweet joy, still left for him to know. It is like early loves' imagining; That fragile pleasure, which the Tulips bring, When suddenly we see them, in the Spring. Not all the gardens later royal train, Not great triumphant Roses, when they reign, Can bring that delicate delight again. II One of the sweetest hours is this; (Of all I think we like it best;) A little restful oasis, Between the breakfast, and the post. Just south of coffee, and of toast, Just north of daily task and duty; Just west of dreams, this Island gleams, A fertile spot of peace and beauty. We wander out across the lawn; We idle by a bush in bloom; The Household pets come following on; Or if the day is one of gloom, We loiter in a pleasant room Or from a casement, lean and chatter. Then comes the mail, like sudden hail, And off we scatter. III When roses die, in languid August days, We leave the Garden, to its fallen ways; And seek the shelter of wide porticos, Where Honeysuckle, in defiance blows Undaunted by the Sun's too ardent rays. The matron Summer, turns a wistful gaze Across green valleys, back to tender Mays; And something of her large contentment goes, When roses die. Yet all her subtle fascination stays To lure us into idle sweet delays. The lowered awning, by the hammock shows Inviting nooks for dreaming and repose; Oh, restful are the pleasures of those days When roses die. IV The summer folk, fled back to town; The green woods changed to red and brown; A sound upon the frosty air Of windows closing everywhere. And then the log, lapped by a blaze. Oh, what is better than these days; With books and friends and love a-near; Go on, gay world, but leave me here. CLARA MORRIS (Written for a Benefit Given Mrs. Morris) The Radiant Ruler of Mystic Regions Where souls of artists are fitted for birth, Gathered together their lovely legions And fashioned a woman to shine on earth. They bathed her in splendor They made her tender: They gave her a nature both sweet and wild. They gave her emotions Like storm stirred oceans, And they gave her the heart of a little child. These Radiant Rulers (who are not human Nor yet divine like the gods above) Poured all their gifts in the soul of a woman That fragile vessel meant only for love. Still more they taught her, Still more they brought her— Till they gave her the world for a harp one day, And they bade her string it— They bade her ring it, While the stars all wondered to hear her play. She touched the strings in a master fashion, She uttered the cry of a world's despair. Its long-hid secret, its pent-up passion, She gave to the winds in a vibrant air. For ah! the heart of her, That was the art of her, Great with the feeling that makes men kin. Art unapproachable, Art all uncoachable, Fragrance and flame from the spirit within. The earth turns ever an ear unheeding To the sorrows of art, as it cries for more: And she played on the harp till her hands were bleeding And her brow was bruised by the laurels she wore. She knew the trend of it, She knew the end of it. Men heard the music and men felt the thrill. Bound to the altar Of art, could she falter? Then came a silence—the music was still. And yet in the echoes we seem to hear it In waves unbroken it circles the earth: And we catch in the light of her dauntless spirit A gleam from the center that gave her birth. Still is the fame of her Felt in the name of her. But low lies the harp that once thrilled to her strain. No hand has taken it, No hand can waken it— For the soul of her art was her secret of pain. THE ENGLISHMAN Born in the flesh, and bred in the bone, Some of us harbour still A New World pride: and we flaunt or hide The Spirit of Bunker Hill. We claim our place, as a separate race, Or a self-created clan: Till there comes a day when we like to say, “We are kin of the Englishman.” For under the front that seems so cold, And the voice that is wont to storm, We are certain to find a big, broad mind And a heart that is soft and warm. And he carries his woes in a lordly way, As only the great souls can: And it makes us glad when in truth we say, “We are kin of the Englishman.” He slams his door in the face of the world, If he thinks the world too bold. He will even curse; but he opens his purse To the poor, and the sick, and the old. He is slow in giving to woman the vote, And slow to pick up her fan; But he gives her room in an hour of doom, And dies—like an Englishman. ON SEEING THE DIABUTSU—AT KAMAKURA, JAPAN Long have I searched, Cathedral shrine, and hall, To find a symbol, from the hand of art, That gave the full expression (not a part) Of that ecstatic peace which follows all Life's pain and passion. Strange it should befall This outer emblem of the inner heart Was waiting far beyond the great world's mart— Immortal answer, to the mortal call. Unknown the artist, vaguely known his creed: But the bronze wonder of his work sufficed To lift me to the heights his faith had trod. For one rich moment, opulent indeed, I walked with Krishna, Buddha, and the Christ, And felt the full serenity of God. SONG OF THE RAIL Oh, an ugly thing is an iron rail, Black, with its face to the dust. But it carries a message where winged things fail; It crosses the mountains, and catches the trail, While the winds and the sea make sport of a sail; Oh, a rail is a friend to trust. The iron rail, with its face to the sod, Is only a bar of ore; Yet it speeds where never a foot has trod; And the narrow path where it leads, grows broad; And it speaks to the world in the voice of God; That echoes from shore to shore. Though the iron rail, on the earth down flung, Seems kin to the loam and the soil, Wherever its high shrill note is sung, Out of the jungle fair homes have sprung, And the voices of babel find one tongue, In the common language of toil. Of priest, and warrior, and conquering king, Of Knights of the Holy Grail, Of wonders of winter, and glories of spring, Always and ever the poets sing; But the great God-Force, in a lowly thing, I sing, in my song of the rail. MEMORY'S MANSION In Memory's Mansion are wonderful rooms, And I wander about them at will; And I pause at the casements, where boxes of blooms Are sending sweet scents o'er the sill. I lean from a window that looks on a lawn; From a turret that looks on the wave. But I draw down the shade when I see on some glade A stone standing guard by a grave. To Memory's attic I clambered one day When the roof was resounding with rain, And there, among relics long hidden away, I rummaged with heart ache and pain. A hope long surrendered and covered with dust, A pastime, out-grown and forgot, And a fragment of love all corroded with rust, Were lying heaped up in one spot. And there on the floor of that garret was tossed A friendship too fragile to last, With pieces of dearly bought pleasures that cost Vast fortunes of pain in the past, A fabric of passion, once vivid and bright, As the breast of a robin in Spring, Was spread out before me—a terrible sight— A moth-eaten rag of a thing. Then down the deep stairway I hurriedly went, And into fair chambers below; But the mansion seemed filled with the old attic scent Wherever my footsteps would go. Though in Memory's House I still wander full oft, No more to the garret I climb; And I leave all the rubbish heaped there in the loft To the hands of the Housekeeper, Time.</field>
   </doc>
</add>