<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Odell, Jonathan, 1737-1818</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Odell, Jonathan, 1737-1818</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">odell jonathan 1737 1818</field>
      <field name="author_text">Odell, Jonathan, 1737-1818</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1980's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ap/uvaGenText/tei/chap_AM0788.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240350</field>
      <field name="date_text">1982</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:440225</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The New Brunswick Poems of Jonathan Odell</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">The New Brunswick Poems of Jonathan Odell</field>
      <field name="title_facet">new brunswick poems of jonathan odell</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">new brunswick poems of jonathan odell</field>
      <field name="title_text">The New Brunswick Poems of Jonathan Odell</field>
      <field name="year_display">1982</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1982</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1982</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440225&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440225&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Odell, Jonathan, 1737-1818&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;odell jonathan 1737 1818&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The New Brunswick Poems of Jonathan Odell&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;new brunswick poems of jonathan odell&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1982&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1982&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Odell, Jonathan&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1737&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1818&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The New Brunswick Poems of Jonathan Odell&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Kingston&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Loyal Colonies Press&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1982&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3865736-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;cham0788&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The New Brunswick Poems of Jonathan Odell&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1996&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1996 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 42 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries, introductory and editorial matter omitted ; verse</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">reproduced elsewhere in American Poetry omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-AmPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Poems of Public Life ON SEEING THE ADDRESS TO THE SHIP AMERICA IN WHICH GOVERNOR CARLETON AND HIS FAMILY EMBARK FOR ENGLAND With HAZEN'S prayer, so well express'd, And, though to fabled Names address'd, Yet meant to One Great Power Divine, Accept, fair Ship, and mingle mine. O may that Power, whose awful sway Contending Elements obey, With Western Breezes sweep the Sea, To clear a smiling path for thee! Yet, while he chacks the raging main, Let not a placid sameness reign, But let Parental Joy perceive The changing Scene, from Morn to Eve, From Eve to Morn of every day, New wonders of the Deep display, To fill the young enquiring Sight With fresh Surprise and fresh Delight. “Look EMMA, for your Infant Eye, Had learn'd no objects to descry, Beyond the Space that Shelter gave To cradle you across the wave, When, destin'd first abroad to roam, You reach'd yon temporary Home; Look Anne, who in this Western world First saw the light;—See how, unfurl'd, The swelling sail its bosom fills With Breezes from the lessening Hills; And while her wings the Vessel speed, See how those lessening Hills recede! The craggy mount, whose frowning Brow Is honor'd with the name of Howe, No longer shows the Banner spread Which lately mark'd his lofty head. Now can the straining Eye no more Discern the windings of the Shore; The Landscape seems to sink away, And leave the Sun's declining Ray, Without eclipse, to gild the Wave, Until, his burning Orb to lave, Beyond the bending Western Steep, He slowly glides into the Deep.” And here—when Evening, which now lights on high The starry Vault, and Morning, which comes round, Shall of this Voiage measure the first day,— O! had I Milton's Voice, to summon forth, In apt Succession, daily to appear, And daily to diversify the Scene, Such Natives of the main, as, whether oft Or seldom, have to man's intrepid eye, In various tracts of Ocean's wide Domain, Their various forms and characters displayed;— These all, by turns, or in well-mingled throngs, As best the occasion might befit, should come, (If happly at my bidding they would come) Round thee to play, and do thy Passengers Mute homage and fantastic gratulation. But hold—nor let my lips profane Attempt this lofty hallowed strain; Hallowed in Eden's blissful Seat And on the Tempter's last defeat. Disclaiming then the Poet's Art, Let me the wishes of my heart Briefly express:? ?Let CARLETON come, Attended as he goes, from home, With happy Omens, back to share, For us a gracious Monarch's care, Leaving that Monarch's Realm in Peace, With wealth and Glory's rich increase, Triumphant o'er his foes!—and then, I hope, with tuneful voice, again To lure sweet Echo from her Cave, And welcome Carleton, while a brave And Loyal People loudly Sing “Welcome CARLETON! and GOD Save the KING!” 1803 THE VACANT HOUSE Whence this emotion? Why, on entering here, Do I recoil, as with a sudden fear? In silence as I pass, from room to room, Why am I conscious of this pensive gloom? Say, gentle Spirit of the ethereal race, Thou tutelary Genius of the place, Sole inmate now, though present yet unseen, Am I infested with prophetic Spleen? Or can it be thy warning Voice I hear, Whispering alarm to Fancy's jealous ear? It seems, by turns, to rise and die away, And this burden of the mystic Lay— “Shall they Governor Carleton, and his family. return, whose absence we bewail? “Fond hope!—or must our vows and wishes fail? Thus restless Mortals covet to descry Tomorrow's destiny, for every eye Wisely conceal'd. Ah, rather thank High Heaven For blindness to the future kindly given! In youth, enamour'd of the Muse, I paid My ardent vows in her sequester'd Shade; Nor did She with disdain repay my Suit, Or to my Search refuse her treasur'd fruit. The charms of Science and the liberal Arts For softer charms prepare ingenuous hearts. Now smiling Love “his golden Shafts employed,” And all was joy, unbounded, unalloy'd. Suspecting no reverse, I thus had seen Five Summers pass, unclouded and serene; When o'er the blackening Sky a Storm arose, Which soon destroyed my Mansion of repose, And fierce Rebellion drove me from the Shore, Which I was destin'd to behold no more. From Anna far, and from her Infant train, Nine years exil'd, my heart endur'd the pain Of hope deferr'd; a hope in vain renew'd; By zeal supported, but by this Fate subdued! Then, in a Carleton's kind protecting care, I found, at last, a refuge from despair. O England! why recall him from the field, Just when Rebellion was prepared to yield? But History, to a more impartial Age, Must yet refer this dark discolour'd page. He took me from the Wreck, dispell'd my fear, And plac'd me in a safe Asylum here. Here, with the remnant of a loyal Band, Under a Second Carleton's mild command, My alienated native Land forgot, I have till now enjoyed a happy lot. And if my Bark, by some unlook'ed-for blast, Must yet again upon the Rocks be cast, Let me at least avoid one shallow Reef, The unhallowed bitterness of hopeless grief. But as the destin'd hour must now be near, When I shall enter on a new career, To you, my only Patrons upon earth, Brothers no less in virtue than by birth, To you I turn, and, with a heart impress'd With memory of the past, I yet request Your generous aid; complete what you've begun; Extend your kind protection to my Son! 1804 THE DROOPING ROSE June 1806 Sweet Rose, look up, thy Season comes at last; Fierce Aquile hath spent his chilling blast, And every Monument of Winter's power Melts in the Western Breeze and Vernal Shower. Sweet Rose, thy Season comes, and comes to bring The welcome period of no common Spring. Thrice has yon River burst his icy chain, And spread his annual tribute o'er the plain, Diffusing, from his rich and swelling tide, The Seeds of future plenty far and wide; While here, forsaken it has been thy lot “To blush unseen,” and in this charming spot, To mourn the want of Emma's fostering care, And “waste thy sweetness on the desert air.” But now, sweet Rose, look up. This joyless doom No more awaits thy renovated bloom. His task again, see, faithful Nichols plies; Again this spot attracts admiring eyes, And they, whose absence we so long bewail, Bespeak fair Winds to swell the lofty Sail, And speed their passage home. But is it home? Can it, alas, be so to them who come From England hither? Or, as hence they went, Can they return, with joy and gay content? Yes—When a sense of duty intervenes, Virtue will gladly quit the splendid Scenes Of pomp and pleasure, still secure to find In every place, that “Sunshine of the Mind,” That self-approv'd Serenity of Soul, Which tempers every clime from pole to pole, And turns the World in all its ample round, For England's progeny, to English ground. Then droop no more, sweet Rose; they come, they come! Here to enjoy again the sweets of home; Pure joys, which hallow the domestic spot; Pleasures which, tasted once, are ne'er forgot. Sweet Rose, they come, for whose return, the sighs And prayers of anxious thousands daily rise. O may propitious breezes waft them o'er With speed and safety to this Western Shore, Where loyal thousands with impatience burn To hail the Jubilee of their Return. POSTSCRIPT 1808 Thus did the Sylvan Muse, to Hill and Dale, Gaily proclaim her visionary tale. The pleasing Prospect, which had been so long The prompter and the burden of her Song, Now vanish'd, like the forms of dusky light Which fill the peering eye of Second-Sight. In vain the song. In vain did thousands burn, Impatient for the prophesied Return. But—though denied that wish of every heart, Another Boon was destined to impart A joy as universal as the grief, Which all had suffered for an absent Chief. Permitting him, for years of Service past In honor'd leisure to repose at last, The Royal Will a new Career ordains, And to a chosen Hand commits the Reins. With ardour the Patrician Board unites In due performance of the solemn rites To them assigned; and all, with hearts elate, See Hunter seated in the Chair of State. A tribute of unfeign'd esteem they pay And joyfully record the auspicious day. 24th of May 1808. Responsive acclamation spreads around, And, mingling with the Trumpet's silver sound, To Heaven ascends, and Hills and Vallies ring With the loud anthem of God save the King! Again released from Winter's breath so keen, Awake, sweet Rose, no more to blush unseen, But—sure to please, imbibe the genial dew, And spread thy bounties to Miranda's view. Devote thy bloom to her,—whose meekness awes The tongue that fain would blazon her applause. To her display thy charms, who is alone Regardless or unconscious of her own. The desert mansion, which so long had been All solitude without, all gloom within, Of whispering sprights no longer the Retreat, But of domestic joy once more the Seat, Resumes its wonted aspect, and displays The gay festivity of former days. Fresh Verdure decks the Lawn and tufted trees; The blooming terrace courts the western breeze; Calmly the River glides majestic by; And yonder Landscape charms the unwearied eye. From distant pilgrimage the Martins come To nestle in their temporary home. What joy the chirping Travellers express Their hospitable cells to repossess! And soon, returning from their southern flight, Shall come the Birds of Lincoln, with delight To join the feather'd tribes who winter here, And all, in sprightly chorus, sweet and clear, Warble their amorous Notes and hail the Scene, Where all is cheerful, tranquil and serene. 1806; 1808 TO THE MEMORY OF LORD NELSON Tho' envied and hated by Tyrants and Slaves, Britannia fair Queen of the Ocean remains. Repell'd by her Ramparts, that float on the Waves, War flies from her Borders and Want from her plains. For Ages renown'd, By Victory crown'd, Her Tars have display'd an invincible train. Surpass'd by no other, Each rivals his brother, And all prove their title as Lords of the Main. Lords of the Main! Aye, Lords of the Main, The Tars of Old England are Lords of the Main. This Charter, descending from Heroes of old, Expands in Succession as Ages roll on, A Climax of Glory! But oh, can it hold? Who shall rival the past, now that Nelson is gone! Yet hark, from on High, The angelic reply: “Your Nelson shall conquer and triumph again. Each Tar shall inherit A Share of his Spirit, And all prove incincible Lords of the Main. Lords of the Main! Aye, Lords of the Main, The Tars of Old England are Lords of the Main. Wherever your far-dreaded Sails are unfurl'd, The Genius of Nelson shall fight by your Side, And teach you again to astonish the World, By deeds unexampled, achievements untried. Then Britons strike home! For Ages to come Your Nelson shall conquer and triumph again, Each Tar shall inherit A Share of his Spirit, And all prove invincible Lords of the Main.” Lords of the Main! Aye, Lords of the Main, The Tars of Old England are Lords of the Main. Nor are we alone in the noble career; The Soldier partakes of the generous flame. To Glory he marches, to Glory we steer; Between us we share the rich harvest of fame. Recorded on High, Their names never die, Whose deeds the renown of their Country sustain. The King! then, God bless him! The World shall confess him, The Lord of those Men who are Lords of the Main. Lords of the Main, Aye Lords of the Main; The Tars of Old England are Lords of the Main. 1806 SONG FOR THE 4TH OF JUNE 1808 Though Storm and Tempest shake the World, And spread despair from Realm to Realm, Still are our dreaded Sails unfurl'd, And British Valour holds the Helm. Rule, Britannia, rule the waves, And defy the rage of Slaves. While Gallia's fierce Usurper drives His flaming Car o'er falling States, Though leagued with Hell, in vain he strives To come within thy peaceful Gates. Rule, Britannia, rule the waves, Secure against invading Slaves. For crimes and follies unatton'd, See thrones and altars round thee blaze; But still, in loyal hearts enthron'd, A Patriot King thy Sceptre sways. Rule, Britannia, rule the waves, The dread of Tyrants leagued with Slaves. Secure in Heaven's approving Smile, The loyal truth its aim attains, For thee and for thy Sister Isle Her throne fair Freedom still maintains. Rule, Britannia, rule the waves, The Ency of despairing Slaves. Then, oft as this auspicious day Fresh joy to Sons of Freedom brings, Let Love and Duty join to pay Their tribute to the best of Kings! Rule, Britannia, rule the waves; From tyrant Arts to rescue Slaves. 1808 SONG FOR THE 104TH For the Hundred and Fourth, let the Muses entwine, An unfading wreath from New-Brunswick Pine: On Ocean transplanted, aloft it displays, That Flag which the proudest of nations dismays; Hence a wreath from this cloud piercing Pine shall proclaim, A Brave Competition The Soldier's Ambition, To rival the Lords of the Ocean in fame. Belov'd by Apollo, the Laurel has long Deck'd the brows of the Hero, and bloom'd in his song: But Daphne shall now in a Chaplet combine, Her bright polished leaf with a tuft from the Pine: Far and near, like a Trumpet, my song shall proclaim, The Brave Competition, A Soldier's Ambition, To rival the Lords of the Ocean in fame. Mature for the Field, and enroll'd in the Line, You burn with impatience in action to shine; Well tried are your leaders, and well you may vie, With all who resolve or to conquer or die; Far and near, let your own Silver Trumpet proclaim, The Brave Competition, Your Ardent Ambition To rival the Lords of the Ocean in fame. 1811 HULL'S INCURSION INTO CANADA Air—“Cesar and Pompey were both of them honored.” Sung at a Ball given by General Smyth, at Fredericton, 9th September 1812 Come, tune up and summon, with pipe and with tabor, Sweet Echo—to sound a Salute to Our Neighbour, Whom Nap, the Destroyer of peace and good Order, Persuaded to make an attack on our Border, Impell'd by the foe to all peace and good Order, Neighbour Madison made an attack on our Border. At his bidding came Hull, and he made Proclamation— “Choose wisely, Submission or Extermination.” Full surely he thought, by this insolent Bluster, To put all his foes in a terrible fluster. With a medley of insolent coaxing and bluster, He thought he could surely put all in a fluster. Thus confident, once and again he assail'd us, But courage and conduct, as usual, avail'd us. When teaz'd with his bouncing and hasty retreating, We flew to his Rear, and there gave him a beating. With crossing, recrossing, advancing, retreating, Our patience he tried, till his Rear got a beating. His Prog intercepted, no whisky to cheer him, Though still two to one, yet he thought us too near him. In short—With Bellona no longer he flirted, But wisely surrender'd and—not a man hurted! With bloody Bellona no longer he flirted, But wisely surrender'd and not a man hurted. On the Shores of Potomack, in Washington City, Nap's Minions may sing thorough-bass to my ditty; But all who disdain to fight under his Order, Will curse Neighbour Madison's War on Our Border— All true Sons of Freedom will spurn at his Order, And curse Neighbour Madison's War on our Border. 1812 THE BATTLE OF QUEENSTON Again, with confidence elate, The invading Foe has found A captive's unexpected fate, On our Canadian ground. Triumphant, as before, though still Out number'd by the Foe, Our Chiefs again have shown how skill Can deal the unerring blow. Again we boast—but with a sigh— A brilliant day's career; For BROCK demands from every eye The tribute of a tear! Devoted to his Country's Cause, The Soldier's debt he paid, From age to age, with just applause, His name shall be convey'd. 1812</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Poems of Private Life SONG (Tune, Cold and peevish is the weather.) When first I beheld my Nancy Odell's wife, Anne, was affectionately called Nancy by her husband. Lightly tripping o'er the plain She excelled what poets fancy Of the bright etherial train. Her auburn tresses wild in air Courted each passing wanton breeze The Graces hovered round my fair And taught her every art to please. Swift then, Swift as the bolt of Jove Cupid drove in his arrow here It pained—it throbb'd my heart was burnt up with Love Ardent Love of my Nancy dear. Like the stricken Deer, sequestered Straight I sought the shady grove There my wounded bosom festered Sighs and tears expressed my love, My arms embraced the vacant air Fancy the fond illusion drew I knelt and I courted the scornful fair When soon the airy vision flew. Wild then, storming at all the Race Echo repeated each heart felt groan The Brook, compassionate, moved in a softer Pace Murmuring to my pensive moan. Now by Fortune doomed to languish Weary of the sight of day Death I called to ease my anguish— When my Nancy blithe and Gay From behind a hawthorne Bower Where, she'd seen me all the while The helpless Victim of her power Received me with a Generous Smile. Come then, come to my arms she cry'd Stephen deserves his Nancy's heart Our hearts, our hands together shall now be tyed Nought but death the bond shall part. Now the pain is turned to pleasure Every object doubly charms Nancy is My darling treasure Joy resides but in her arms All the bliss that man can know Short of that beyond the skies My Nancy doth on me bestow And grateful I possess the Prize Now, now long as I have to Live Clasping my lovely Nancy dear I know, I feel the Utmost that Jove can give Friendship Warm and Love Sincere. [date unknown] TO A YOUNG LADY, ON THE DEATH OF HER FATHER Almighty Ruler, whose unceasing Sway Millions of Suns and rolling Worlds obey, That, through all Space, thy power may be display'd, And light and life the boundless all pervade; O what is man! who, from this vale of tears, Of mingled joys and Sorrows, hopes and fears, Can dark his eye to Heaven, and catch a gleam Of light far brighter than the Solar beam, And, in the volume of created things, Discern the Source whence all creation springs. Man, thus by Nature's bounty richly fraught With active power and energy of thought, May claim alliance with angelic thrones, Yet oft, alas, his present lot bemoans. On passion's tide, by winds confliction toss'd, Wide of his course, his helm of reason lost, Oft over rocks and shallows is he driven, Until again for aid he looks to Heaven. On earth, a Pilgrim, for probation sent, In vain his high-born Spirit seeks content. Let Pleasure, Wealth and Power their gifts impart, In rich profusion, still the craving heart Even in the want of an untried desire, Would find fresh fuel for that hectic fire, Which, kindled at our birth, unquench'd remains During our passage o'er life's feverish plains. For—though unconscious of the cause—we roam In exile here, and sigh to be at home. Then, O fair Mourner, let my verse recall Your weeping eyes from yonder sable pall. Look up to Him, who can dispell the gloom Through which Imagination views the tomb. Hear his consoling Voice—“The dead are bless'd Who sleep in Christ, who now from labour rest,” Ere long to rise and, from their bed of dust, Pass to the peaceful Mansions of the Just. 1811 TO A MOTHER, ON THE DEATH OF AN INFANT Sad Mourner, let my friendly verse The balm of sympathy impart, Till calm reflection may disperse The grief now pressing on your heart. Your son, baptised, and born anew, The adopted Heir of peace and joy, Has realis'd the prize in view, Secure from forfeit or alloy. And now, escaped the toils of life, And all the Scenes of human woe, Safe from the perils and the Strife Of Virtue struggling here below; He sleeps an Infant, but shall rise Mature in high angelic lore, A Star in those eternal Skies Which dawn when Time shall be no more. Maternal Sorrows, then, adieu! Regard no phantoms of the tomb! The glorious prospect now in view Dispels their visionary gloom. But let Imagination soar On wings of faith, and, in your Boy, Behold a cherub, gone before, His Mother's future crown of joy! c. 1815 WHAT WE SHALL BE DOTH NOT YET APPEAR What we shall be doth not yet appear, Nor can we conceive—till the day When Time shall have clos'd his career, And Death shall surrender his prey. Then—to all who in Christ have repos'd Shall the Scene preordain'd be disclos'd. Those of every Age, from the first To the last date of time, shall arise; Shall spring, at his call, from the dust, And pass to the new-spreading Skies, There, like himself, shall they shine, Bright Heirs of all his Glory divine! Ineffable Anticipation! Here the Believer may find A Spirit of high animation, Yet humble and meek and resign'd. With such a prospect of joy, What present pains can annoy? Blest with a hope so sublime, Though life be a pilgrimage here, Let us seek, in our journey through time, That “Love which casteth out fear.” So shall our patience endure, And so shall our triumph be sure. 1814 REFLECTIONS IN SICKNESS, AND ON RECOVERY Awake, my Soul, and, ere it be too late, Let conscience rouse thee from this torpid State. O listen to that Monitor within, Who cries—“beware of unrepented Sin.” What fatal apathy can lull the fears Of one so near the brink of four-score years, To whom dark days and restless nights recall That Image, which may stouter hearts appal, The approaching hour, when all we value here Shall, like a baseless Vision, disappear, And dust to dust concludes life's perilous career. While on this fearful precipice I stand, The day far spent, the Night so near at hand, Can I the past with tranquil mind survey? Or to the future look without dismay? Ah, what is this but, in my utmost need, To dream that all is well, and on a Reed To lean securely, till the broken dart Transfix the hand or pierce the unguarded heart! My Soul, awake and, with suspended breath, Tremble, lest this may prove a Sleep of death; Eternal death! O what pernicious charm This image of its terrors can disarm! And at a time like this! alas, beware; Awake, and watch, and make thy fervant prayer To Him, who can this essential gift impart, A broken Spirit and a contrite heart. To Him, whose gracious promise cannot fail, That they who ask and faint not shall prevail. From mortal life, then, welcome a release! Thy Servant, Lord, shall then depart in peace, Obey thy summons with unclouded mind, By faith sustain'd and to thy will resign'd. Meantime thy will for me decrees again A gracious respite from a bed of pain, In one short Season twice have I been spared When Death approach'd me—ah how unprepared! And since, by Nature, with unquench'd desire, While life remains, to live we still aspire, O may it be in mercy that my days Unnumber'd yet, are still a theme of praise, Ascending from a family of love, In grateful homage to thy throne above. Thus, from a gloomy chamber of disease, Restor'd to light and Zephyr's cheering breeze, To Hill and Dale, mild Sun or shady Bower, The morning Walk, the social evening hour; O how shall I express the glowing thought Which melts my heart, and thank thee as I ought! Thank thee, O God, with mingled hope and fear; Dreading lest on that day, which must be near, Thy merciful forbearance may be found With fresh remorse my Conscience to confound; Yet humbly hoping, through thy gracious Aid, To meet the awful moment undismay'd. Protect me, then, Great Giver of All Good, And, through temptation watchfully withstood, Conduct me Safely in the doubtful Strife Of Virtue, struggling through the Snares of life, Till I may come victorious to the Shore, Where doubt and frailty shall be known no more. 1815 THE GAMUT—TO SARAH ANNE ODELL Odell's daughter. As Heaven bestowed the precious art Our thoughts by letters to impart; To “waft from Indus to the Pole The secret whispers of the Soul; So, by a like celestial aid Of graphic art, the Silent Maid May to the distant swain convey The sprightly Song or melting lay. And so, when Handel sweeps the Strings, When Harmony, from all her Springs, Fills up the measure of delight; The Sounds, arrested in their flight, Are treasured by this magic Scale, Secure till time and Nature fail. Come then, sweet Bird, whose early Note Has cheer'd me oft, while yet, by rote, The Voice could but repeat the Strain, Which Memory taught thee to retain; Now shall thy well-instructed eye Recorded harmonies descry, And prompt thy Voice at sight to sing, Thy hand at Sight to wake the String, And through my captive ear impart Sweet rapture to a Father's heart. 1818</field>
   </doc>
</add>