<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Kilmer, Joyce, 1886-1918</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Kilmer, Joyce, 1886-1918</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">kilmer joyce 1886 1918</field>
      <field name="author_text">Kilmer, Joyce, 1886-1918</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1910's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ap/uvaGenText/tei/chap_AM0024.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240350</field>
      <field name="date_text">1911</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:439504</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Summer of Love</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Summer of Love</field>
      <field name="title_facet">summer of love</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">summer of love</field>
      <field name="title_text">Summer of Love</field>
      <field name="year_display">1911</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1911</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1911</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:439504&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:439504&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Kilmer, Joyce, 1886-1918&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;kilmer joyce 1886 1918&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Summer of Love&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;summer of love&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1911&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1911&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Kilmer, Joyce&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1886&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1918&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Summer of Love&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;New York&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;The Baker &amp;amp; Taylor Company&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1911&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3865108-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;cham0024&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Summer of Love&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1996&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1996 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 48 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted ; verse reproduced</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">elsewhere in American Poetry omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-AmPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">In dedication: TO ALINE A vagrant minstrel of the street, No poet of the laurel crown, I kneel, dear Princess, at your feet, And lay my book of verses down. See all the love that lingers there, And so, for love's sake, find it fair. SUMMER OF LOVE June lavishes sweet-scented loveliness And sprinkles sunfilled wine on everything; The very leaves grow drunk with bliss and sing And every breeze becomes a soft caress. All earthly things felicity confess And fairies dance in many a moonlit ring; The fleetfoot hours fresh wealth of joyaunce bring; Life wears her gayest rose-embroidered dress. Kind June, why bear these golden gifts to me? All winter long I hear the throstle's tune, All winter long red roses I can see, Reading the while Love's ancient magic rune. In Love's fair garden-close I wander free, So take your guerdon elsewhere, lovely June. VILLANELLE OF LOVELAND Loveland is fair to see, Of all kind havens best, Dwell here, my Sweet, with me. Here flowers bloom for thee, Thy feet are rose-caressed, Loveland is fair to see. The violets shall be Thy soft and fragrant nest, Dwell here, my Sweet, with me. Thou shalt not lack for glee, Here life is but a jest; Loveland is fair to see. None shall be glad as we; Ah, grant me my behest, Dwell here, my Sweet, with me. Now would I ask my fee, Thy red heart I request; Loveland is fair to see, Dwell here, my Sweet, with me. THURIFER In a carven censer of burnished words, Swung on a golden chain of rhythm, For you I burn my heart. EADEM Sometimes within the garden of your sweetness I rest and dream and think of all the years Before my soul had bloomed to fair completeness, Those times of shadow-laughter, mixed with tears. And in my dreams I see a gentle maiden Whom I once loved and whom I still love, Sweet, For she is like a rose with sunlight laden, And my lips ache to kiss her little feet. She is so pure the very sky above her Is not so fair with all its white and blue, And so, my love, I cannot help but love her Although my life and love belong to you. IN FAIRYLAND The fairy poet takes a sheet Of moonbeam, silver white, His ink is dew from daisies sweet, His pen a point of light. My love, I know is fairer far Than his, (though she is fair,) And we should dwell where fairies are For I could praise her there. THE SORROWS OF KING MIDAS King Midas took delight In golden vessels bright, And yellow bars of ore he found most fair; But he had never seen The dancing, glancing sheen Of sunlight on your dark and fragrant hair. His wealth could buy him wine Made from the purple vine And sweet as all the blossom-breathing South; But he could never slake His thirst, nor ease the ache Of his hot lips at your love-pliant mouth. LOVE'S THOROUGHFARE As down the primrose path to Love I trod The golden flowers kissed my eager feet, The wayside trees with singing birds were sweet, The summer air was like the smile of God. “Turn back!” said one, “escape the avenging rod. Soon thou the deathless flames of Hell shall meet.” But I pressed on and thought of no retreat, Till soon with fire I was clothed and shod. But through the burning vales of Hell where flow The molten streams of bitterest despair, Made blind by pain I stumbled on, and lo! I stood at last in Love's own perfumed air. So, having reached my journey's end I know That God made Hell to be Love's thoroughfare. MY LADY The joy of pleasant places Where Saturn still doth reign Is in her gentle face's Calm ignorance of pain. The bliss of ages golden In her slim hand is holden, By old gods she was molden Before the world knew stain. Her body is an altar Wherein is Love enshrined. Before her worldlings falter And cruel eyes grow kind. Her breath is breath of roses From mystic garden-closes, The troubled it composes Like nectar-laden wine. GIFTS OF SHEE O Shee who weave the moonlight into shimmering white strands, O powerful and tender-hearted Shee! While I live at home in plenty or am poor in far-off lands, I will thank you for the gifts you gave to me. For the silver collar that you wrought me by your magic art, For the scarlet Seal that on my mouth you set, For the glorious White Flower that you placed upon my heart, When the sun and moon shall die I'll thank you yet. For around my throat the Silver Collar of soft arms I wear, On my mouth sweet lips have fixed the Scarlet Seal, On my heart the perfect Flower white of deathless love I bear, And these charms, your gifts, ensure my lasting weal. O Shee who weave the moonlight into shimmering white strands, O powerful and tender-hearted Shee! Though I live at home in plenty or am poor in far-off lands, I will thank you for the gifts you gave to me. WHEREVER, WHENEVER If I had lived down underneath the earth, And you had dwelt among the pleasant stars, I should have flown the caverns of my birth, And you have riven Heaven's silver bars. We owe no gratitude to wanton chance, For not through him does heart cleave fast to heart. Not time nor place nor any circumstance, Could keep our lips, our breasts, our souls, apart. LOVE'S ROSARY Love's rosary is ours this holiday, So let us worship Eros, Lord of bliss. Let me be priest and teach you as we pray Love's rosary. The first fair golden globe denotes a kiss, Curve your sweet lips the proper churchly way, And you must lie within my arms at this. Keep all the rites! It will not do to miss A single bead in all the long array. Ah, Sweet, we'll tell on every day, I wis, Love's rosary. “The Princess cried; her tears fell on the ground Like pearls of moonlight, precious, fair and round.” But when the Princess whom I worship cries Then from the clouded heaven of her eyes Rain of such sweet wild loveliness I sip My heart says “Stop!” but not my eager lip. TRIBUTE Because my Love has lips that taste of glory, That breathe of love, that are as red as wine, My days and nights are as a pleasant story Told in a valley sweet with rose and vine. Because my Love has hair that smells of flowers, That is as soft and cool as forest shade, Therefore the tale of all my blissful hours Be writ in gold and at her footstool laid. MATIN Soft purple shadows cloud love-weary eyes, Dawn's saffron glow is on the tossed white bed; Now passion's day, warm fragrant night is fled, A cold grey shroud on Love's bright altar lies. From dusky corners ghostly dreams arise, The pallid wraiths of kisses newly dead, They float and blend above her sleeping head, Her languid red lips quiver as she sighs. And so, like Adam when in fear and shame He saw God's soldiery in fierce array And sorrowing from Eden's threshold came To bear what pains life on his soul might lay, I see Dawn standing with a sword of flame, And from my Eden turn in grief away. A VALENTINE My songs should be as lilies fair, And roses made of crimson light, To lie amid the fragrant hair And on the breast of my delight. Such glory is for them too high; I'll scatter them adown the street, And when my love is passing by They will rise up and kiss her feet. STAR O' LOVE The Sun pours gold upon the waking earth And makes the hills and valleys ring with glee, Brings fruits and flowers to their joyous birth, And paints strange colors on the foaming sea. The Moon, with quivering wand of silver-white, Calls forth the fairies to their circling dance, Bids lovers seek their never old delight, And fills the air with perfume of romance. Yet, Sun, thy glory passes with the day, And Moon, the dawn destroys thy loveliness; But thou, sweet Star o' Love, wilt shine alway, Nor night nor day can make thy splendor less. Fade, lordly Sun, and Moon, forget to shine, Since thy white wonder, Star o' Love, is mine! THE USE OF NIGHT I said: “What is the use of sombre night?” The Moon replied: “To frame my love-wan face.” A fairy dame said: “That my fresh-wove lace May on the grasses catch the Sun's first light.” “That we may keep with song our ancient rite,” Croaked glistening frogs from their dank dwelling place. “That I may halt,” a man said, “in my race, And rest my eyes that are grown tired of sight.” Your ebon frame, pale Moon, makes you more fair; Weave, gentle neighbor; frogs, pipe loud your song; Sad traveller, be dreamless sleep your share. And I would have night twenty times as long, And clasp my love in some dark bower where The Day could never come to do us wrong. ALCHEMY I sang two little songs one day, I sang them for a lady's pleasure, I took her praise for wreath of bay, Her smile for largess beyond measure. I sang out in the market square And most folk could not understand; One who by chance was passing there Dropped down some silver in my hand. Now since the songs I gave you, Sweet, Have turned to silver fair and gleaming, For your pleasaunce as is most meet The silver turns to song and dreaming. WITH A MIRROR Carved by a swarthy knave Close by the Adrian wave Came I to being. To me a soul he gave, In gold he did me lave, To suit your seeing. Mine is a pleasant life, Jove bless his flashing knife, Who wrought my living. For me nor care nor strife, Joys in my days are rife, Joys of your giving. GEORGE MEREDITH He listened to the mighty lyre of earth, And learned the lore of soul-compelling song. He pondered on the rune of right and wrong, And saw the hearts of men, their woe, their mirth. In him our vision had a second birth, For by his words we saw as in some strong Enchanted lens the conscience of the throng, The font of ill, the hidden source of worth. Shall Death claim him, on deathless knowledge reared? Shall dreams o'ertake the Master of the dream? Nay, his perfect love that never feared, His words send through our grief a radiant gleam: “With Life and Death I walked and Love appeared And made them on each side a shadow seem.” “AND FORBID THEM NOT” (“No Trespassing” signs in a churchyard.) Tall, bleak, austere, the mighty buildings loom; Hard, bare and dull the grimy city street. Here by the church is found a little room Roofed with blue sky and with green turf made sweet. Surely the Master of this house would smile Seeing the children on His grass at play, Seeing the mothers rest a little while Out of the turmoil of the busy day. Soon will he ask, “Where are the children gone: They who should share this pleasant, sacred place? No little feet are treading this soft lawn, Here shines no glory from a little face.” Ye in whose trust this Christian church is left, Think ye that thus ye serve your Master mild? None by His will are of this home bereft; They love Him not who wrong a little child. THE MORNING MEDITATIONS OF FRERE HYACINTHUS So he is dead and damned and all is well. So fare all traitors to the church and God! Cursed and cast out with candle, book and bell, And thrust to rot beneath unhallowed sod. The mouth that sounded once Saint Mary's name He smirched and stained with scarlet wine of lust; Therefore is he become a thing of shame, Anathema and alien to the just. We prayed within the cloister side by side, He chose the world, wise in his own conceit; I kept our Blessed Lady for my bride, To paths of sin he set his wayward feet. And she is dead, too. Lies with him, they say? Aye, lies with him—they are together still— That golden girl I saw one summer day Tending her kine upon the pasture hill. God, God, is not my blood like his blood red? God, God, could I not see that she was fair? Did I not close my eyes and bow my head, And purge my soul with fasting and with prayer? God, see my flesh with scourgings cut and scarred! God, see my frame with fasting weak and thin! God, see my face with tears and sorrow marred! God, see my soul burnt white and clean of sin! Tempted I was like him, but did not yield. Outcast is he and damned and spit upon. Elect am I and with thine own sign sealed, Washed white and pure in blood of Christ thy Son. And yet, and yet—Ah, God, that dream last night! When I had prayed before Thy blessed shrine, And sought to rest a while before the light Should call me to new services of Thine. Then as I slept it seemed I was with Thee In Heaven, and I looked down into Hell, That I the cursed souls in pain might see And be more glad that I had served Thee well. I saw the place with blood-red flames alight, I saw the damned and heard their shrieks and groans, And then there burst upon my eyes a sight That turned to lead the marrow in my bones. There in his arms her soft white body lay; Shielded by him she kissed his mouth and smiled. Round them the flames kept their unheeded sway. Even to Hell Love made them reconciled. It's time for Mass. God bless the newborn day! How very fair it is, and sweet and still— Down yonder lane she used to make her way To tend her kine upon the pasture hill. VILLANELLE OF THE PLAYERS Violets fade with the May, Purple and fragrant they die, Players live for a day. What is their legacy, pray? Where does their loveliness lie? Violets fade with the May. Actors in motley array Grace of your memory cry, Players live for a day. Where the sad pine trees sway Lonely the reft winds sigh, Violets fade with the May. Withered the wreaths of bay, Wine-cups are cracked and dry, Players live for a day. Clouds of the sunset sky, None shall their eulogy say, Violets fade with the May, Players live for a day. WHITE MARBLE AND GREEN GRASS Starlight, sunlight, silver light and gold, All are dark for Love's great flame is cold. Rose wind, garden wind and morning's breath, Are ye stronger than the scent of death? ABSINTHE I have prayed to the Christ of the merciful eyes, I have prayed to the Lord of Hosts, I have prayed, but in vain, for God to rise And scatter these murderous ghosts, These horrible, beckoning ghosts that sign And beckon me where? ah, where? O little green god in your crystal shrine, You only will heed my prayer! The breath of your mouth is a powerful wind That whirls sorrow-shadows away; The light of your eyes burns the bonds that bind. I escape from the earth's fell sway. The pallid figures in threatening line, They falter and tremble and flee. O little green god in your crystal shrine, Shed some of your glory on me! I have given you service, sincere and prolonged, I have given you love—ah, you know! Though I pray in a fane by your worshippers thronged, There is no one who worships you so. My hand and my heart and my brain, ah, divine Lord, master of living, I give, O little green god in your crystal shrine, Take these—and then bid me to live! By a green marble house in a garden of green, Green roses bloom 'neath a green sun, Where the maidens have eyes of an emerald sheen, And the strife and the labor are done, O there let me dwell, where the ravenous whine Of the earth ghosts is soundless and dead. O little green god in your crystal shrine, Your heavenly dream-shower shed! THEOLOGY The blade is sharp, the reaper stout, And every daisy dies. Their souls are fluttering about— We call them butterflies. TO J. B. Y. Bitter and selfish sorrow, poverty, strife and ruth, Fear of the dreadful morrow,—these took away our youth. Ængus is bending o'er us—we are too old to see, Too old to hear before us moon-drenchèd songs of Shee. Dreamer of dreams and lover, young as are love and dreams, Show us the Shee that hover over the silver streams, Give us the song and story, make us to live anew, Bathed in your youthful glory let us be young like you. THE KING'S BALLAD Good my king, in your garden close, (Hark to the thrush's trilling,) Why so sad when the maiden rose Love at your feet is spilling? Golden the air and honey-sweet, Sapphire the sky, it is not meet Sorrowful faces should flowers greet, (Hark to the thrush's trilling.) All alone walks the king to-day, (Hark to the thrush's trilling,) Far from the throne he steals away Loneness and quiet willing. Roses and tulips and lilies fair Smile for his pleasure everywhere, Yet of their joyaunce he takes no share, (Hark to the thrush's trilling.) Ladies wait in the palace, Sire, (Hark to the thrush's trilling,) Red and white for the king's desire Lovewarm and sweet and thrilling, Breasts of moonshine and hair of night, Glances amorous soft and bright, Nothing is lacking for thy delight, (Hark to the thrush's trilling.) Kneels the king in a grassy place, (Hark to the thrush's trilling,) Little flowers under his face With his warm tears are filling: Says the king, “Here my heart lies dead Where my fair love is buried, Would I were lying here instead!” (Hark to the thrush's trilling.) JESUS AND THE SUMMER RAIN Over the hills and across the plain, Treading their gypsy way, Ragged and penniless, vagrants twain Went with a child one day. Sunburnt and barefooted was the man, Poor was the woman's dress, Over the baby the sunbeams ran, Winds gave him soft caress. “Brother o' mine,” said the summer rain, “Brother o' mine,” said he, “Take you the vagabond's joy and pain, Vagabond shall you be. “Banned by the rich and the folk of power, Outcasts shall love you well; Harlots and thieves in your dying hour Closest to you shall dwell. “Never a home nor abiding place Where you may rest your load; Ever the starlight on your face, Ever the open road. “Brother o' mine,” said the summer rain, “Brother o' mine,” said he, “Take you the vagabond's joy and pain, Vagabond shall you be.” THE BALLADE OF BUTTERFLIES Because we never build a nest And no one of us ever sings, We are the butt of every jest That strutting loud-mouthed robin flings. Unless the field with laughter rings And we are meek in our replies His claws and beak to bear he brings; Have pity on all butterflies! Since we are of no home possest, And have no joy in courts and kings, And love on working-days to rest, The name of “Idlers” to us clings. On all our gypsy travellings They follow us with jeering cries. From every rose a spider springs; Have pity on all butterflies! A little thing is our request— Some peace from nets of sticks and strings, An hour to feel the sunlight's zest, To 'scape the deadly bee that stings. From hostile fortune's bolts and slings Give us release ere Summer dies— We dread the Winter's threatenings; Have pity on all butterflies! L'ENVOI Great Pan, kind lord of living things, Look on us now with friendly eyes. We pray to you on trembling wings, Have pity on all butterflies! IN MEMORIAM: FLORENCE NIGHTINGALE She whom we love, our lady of Compassion, Can never die, for Love forbids her death. Love has bent down in his old kindly fashion, And breathed upon her his immortal breath. On wounded soldiers, in their anguish lying, Her gentle spirit shall descend like rain. Where the white flag with the red cross is flying, There shall she dwell, the vanquisher of pain. BALLAD OF THREE Upon the river's brink she stands And tastes the dawn's white breath. She wrings her slender, silver hands, “God's curse on love,” she saith. “Love binds me with his cruel bands That break not save with death.” “Now Geoffrey is a huntsman bold And slays the mountain deer, And Hugh plows up the fragrant mold And plucks the ripened ear. In friendship would these twain grow old Did I not dwell anear. “Hugh brings me grapes with sunlight sweet, Like globes of amethyst, While Geoffrey's fawn with snowflake feet Is corded to my wrist. They mutter curses when they meet, Their sight dims with red mist. “And it is love hath done this thing; Yea, Geoffrey loves my hair, And Hugh lifts up his voice to sing That my sad face is fair, And love strews poison in the spring And fouls the pleasant air. “But not for my poor loveliness Shall blood of brothers flow. What is one woman, more or less? And what is love but woe! I want no murderer's caress, So for love's sake—I go.” Lads, sheathe your knives, no use to fight. The lady you would wed Shall sleep alone in state tonight With candles at her head. Lift, friends, this figure still and white And bear her to her bed. COURT MUSICIANS As when in summer-scented days gone by The court-musicians, dressed in velvets gay And golden silks, would on their gitterns play And blend their voices with the strings' love-cry, So that the princess from her tower on high Might through the rose-framed window hear their lay, And make more splendid the resplendent day By leaning out, her choristers to spy; So now, with weary voice and violin, Two court-musicians rend the dusty air. Their shrill notes pierce the elevated's din, And thrill a girl's heart with a pleasure rare. For her has sweeter music never been; They never saw a princess half so fair. THE DEAD LOVER I tire of lovely faces free from pain And free from sin; Here none with lips wet with the crimson stain May enter in. One thing I lack, and lacking it, am dead— A woman's heart. “She cannot enter here,” an angel said; I will depart. I have one prayer that I will make to God, That I may stay Where lies my body underneath the sod. Then night and day I shall be where my dear false love may pass; It will be sweet To hear above my head, upon the grass, Her little feet. THE SUBWAY Tired clerks, pale girls, street cleaners, business men, Boys, priests and harlots, drunkards, students, thieves, Each one the pleasant outer sunshine leaves; They mingle in this stifling, loud-wheeled pen. The gate clangs to—we stir—we sway—and then We thunder through the dark. The long train weaves Its gloomy way. At last above the eaves We see awhile God's day, then night again. Hurled through the dark—day at Manhattan Street, The rest all night. That is my life, it seems. Through sunless ways go my reluctant feet. The sunlight comes in transitory gleams. And yet the darkness makes the light more sweet, The perfect light about me—in my dreams. AGE COMES A-WOOING With shameless and incessant lust Thy tremulous hot hands are thrust Upon my body's loveliness. O loathsome Age, thy foul caress Puts on my heart a deadly blight, Withers my hair to leprous white, Binds fetters on my eager feet That once on Springtime's road were fleet To bear me to Love's shining goal. Now bitter tides of sorrow roll To drown me in a sea of woe And God looks on, and wills it so! Give over thy pursuing, Age! Fearest thou not my lover's rage? For he is young and strong of limb, Thou canst not stand a bout with him. Ah, surely he will laugh to see So wan a suitor wooing me. Then with wild scorn his heart will swell And he will fling thee back to hell. O Love, that stronger art than Death, Enfold me from the burning breath Of Age that has grown amorous, That sears and blasts me. Even thus, Men say, his passionate embrace Spoils maids and flowers of their grace, And every woman's fate is cast To be his paramour at last. And so all lovely things are made Shameful, and in the ashes laid, To die alone, uncared for. Such Is the pollution of his touch. Stars that have shone since Time began, Rivers that saw the birth of man, And mountains that are fair and green, And were, when Helen was a queen, White dreams that never can grow old, Stories of love and glory told By Homer once, and ballads sung Eons ago—ye still are young. Tell me the secret of your youth. Can any weeping fill with ruth Age, that is harsh and pitiless? Nay, they are blind to my distress. They have not feared the grasping hand Of Age, and cannot understand. Love saw my whitened hair and laughed And bid me drain my bitter draught. While in my lover's startled eyes A lurking terror strangely lies. There is no place in which to hide When Age comes seeking for his bride. PRAYER TO BRAGI The world-rocking roar of the thunder, the red lightning's death-dealing flash, The wind that rends mountains asunder, the tempest's sharp, blood-bringing lash, Beneficent silvery rivers that stream from the dream-laden moon, And crimsoning fire that delivers bound life at the sun's freeing noon; These swell like a marvellous ocean, all throbbing and leaping and strong, O Bragi, in thy magic potion of pain and of sweetness and song! The life-blood of Kvasir was taken, sharp heart-seeking knives made him bleed, But still shall his spirit awaken in singers who drink of thy mead. The honey from forests of flowers, poured out as the milk from the kine, It flows through the undying hours from lips that are wet with thy wine. O Bragi, dear master of singing, song-thirsty I beg for thy dole! To thy knees, a suppliant clinging, I pray for a draught from thy bowl. IMITATION OF RICHEPIN'S BALLADE OF THE BEGGARS' KING Hey, come to me, you slipshod race, Picklocks and squealing bagpipe crew, Come, strumpet, knave and monkey-face, Come loafers, I'm the lad for you! Come ragged cloak and tattered shoe, Your wild, hot liberty I sing, For I am of your nation, too, The poet is the beggars' king. You playthings of the copper's mace, You toys of wind and rain and dew, You whom the yelping watchdogs chase, Whom blows and noisome ills pursue, Whose paltry rags the wind strikes through As through some rotten paper thing, To whom nor want nor woe is new, The poet is the beggars' king. You hoboes, whom the sun's embrace Has burned to darkly golden hue, You trollops, full of love and grace, Whom half a hundred lovers woo, You little crawling babies who Just wear your hides for costuming, Old toothless men with noses blue, The poet is the beggar's king. L'ENVOI My subjects all and vassals true, Come, give me royal welcoming, May booze be plenty, bulls be few, The poet is the beggars' king. LOVE AND THE FOWLER'S BOY (Bion IV, 14.) Lo, the fowler's little lad, Through the woodland straying, Sight of winged Love hath had In the branches playing. “Ah,” he cries, “a bonnie prey!” Sets his bow to wing him. Cupid blows the dart away That to earth would bring him. Now the boy in angry woe Casts away his quiver To his master straight doth go And the tale deliver. Saith the sage, “Nay, not for thee Such a bird to harry. From the haunted forest flee Where such creatures tarry. “Though it now escape thy dart Let not tears be flowing, It will light upon thy heart Ere thy beard be growing.”</field>
   </doc>
</add>