<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Calvert, George Henry, 1803-1889</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Calvert, George Henry, 1803-1889</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">calvert george henry 1803 1889</field>
      <field name="author_text">Calvert, George Henry, 1803-1889</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1860's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ap/uvaGenText/tei/chap_AM1033.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240350</field>
      <field name="date_text">1864</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:440458</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Cabiro ; a poem</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Cabiro ; a poem</field>
      <field name="title_facet">cabiro</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">cabiro</field>
      <field name="title_text">Cabiro ; a poem</field>
      <field name="year_display">1864</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1864</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1864</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440458&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440458&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Calvert, George Henry, 1803-1889&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;calvert george henry 1803 1889&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Cabiro ; a poem&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;cabiro&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1864&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1864&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Calvert, George Henry&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1803&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1889&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Cabiro&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;a poem&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Boston&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Little, Brown and Company&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1864&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3865613-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;cham1033&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Cabiro&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;a poem&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1996&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1996 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 82 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-AmPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CABIRO. ADVERTISEMENT A small edition of the first and second cantos of ”Cabiro“ was published in Baltimore in 1840. The third and fourth (with exception of the first four stanzas of the third) have been written recently. Should it happen that the public take interest enough in those now offered as to manifest a wish to see the other two, they will be republished. Newport, R.I., April 30, 1864. CANTO III. I. “Allow me, sir, to ask you just one question Ere you begin another canto.” No;— Excuse my bluntness;—but if the digestion Of readers' mental stomachs is so slow That stanzas stick, or miss the right direction, But two things are there for him,—to forego Such feasts, or beg a helpful critic urge The peccant matter through with wordy purge. II. For he is the physician; I'm the cook. My function then is done, when, smoking-hot, I serve the dishes up; and I'll not brook That guests come peering into pan and pot After they 've dined, and beg to have a look Into my spice-box. “But refuse you'll not, To tell what means Cabiro.” Oh! Cabiro! Why, bless you, 'tis the name, sir, of my hero. III. We left him eating his first dinner, which Being eaten, forth into the street he went. To be remembered aye,—however rich One's life may be in act, or incident, Or recollections that the mind bewitch,— Is that first walk on a new continent. It is a marriage, or more properly A fight 'twixt fancy and reality. IV. Or it is like a dream come more than true. At least such the sensation I once had, When old imaginations, struggling through The memory, strove to confront the glad O'erwhelming present. But as night's weak dew Evanishing before the sun, they bade Reluctant farewell at the strong array The bristling senses mustered.—Up Broadway V. He walked,—another droplet in the flood Of that long, lengthening artery's motley life, Bubbling all day with every climate's blood, With heats and pulsions of all passions rife; And—like a giant who, with lustful food Regendering sap for each to-morrow's strife, Sleeps heavily, his brain bescarred with seams— At night breathes coarse with gross, gigantic dreams. VI. Cabiro sauntered slowly; for the sights That drew him most so rapidly were flung Upon his vision, they confused his lights. These were all human faces, whether hung With gloom or glee, which, as the sun-ray smites The eye, smote on his senses; for, though young, He strove to measure on the features' plane The hollows and the hills beneath them lain. VII. A lively walk it was, albeit slow; And soon was wakened that intreasured thrill That blesses genial men when a fresh flow Of larger knowledge inward streams, and fill Themselves with joy, the higher wants that grow On truth; for, gazing with uncumbered will, He saw a broader day, more of the graces Of freedom born, on this new flood of faces. VIII. Men looked as though they went upon their feet More lightly poised, less biased by the weights Of other men. Thus did new facts repeat Imaginings, matching themselves the mates Of hopes half-trusted, with their sparkling heat Moulding to shape vague fancies,—like old dates Rechiseled,—making the Republic shine With lustres from its own fresh-opened mine. IX. Nor did the secondary shows escape A grasping eye,—the magazines, in piles Whose towering carvèd grandeurs more than ape The palaces of Genoa, and for miles Wall with magnificence the way, and scrape The clouds with marble cornices and styles Divergent; nor the whirling coil of wheels, Or coarse or fine, that told of myriad keels; X. Nor the stored wealth, in fleecy or golden heaps. But still the living current drew his eye: The more so that 't was one of those that reaps Perennial harvest from the fields that lie Flower-hedged by beauty, from whose closures leaps— When earthy wants can sway so high— A radiance, that with earthless splendor feeds Chastest imagination's choicest needs. XI. For never in a city's thoroughfare Had flashed on him so much of beauty's sheen In man and woman: not the shallow glare Of fleshly comeliness, nor the serene Of spiritual calm; but mostly in the air A fineness, and in woman's port and mien Ease tempering strength, and in her gait and face Freedom and purity combined for grace. XII. At times, from sudden blaze of features shot Such rays, they carried light into the brain That fused him in ethereal fire. 'T was not All rapture, for a momentary pain Followed the glow,—a rushing darkness' blot, Quick quenching an illuminated plane,— As he had lost a sanatory gift, In a great moment given, then snatched as swift. XIII. It was not and it never can be lost; For once enjoyed, it is for aye possest, A thing of beauty; and, if not embossed Upon the memory, it nestles pressed Within the inner folds, thence to be tossed, A secret fragrance, wherewith shall be blest The happy spirit in its higher moods, And comforted in its vicissitudes. XIV. Nature's broad prodigies, her uses, shows; Mountain and meadow, tree and tiniest flowers, The gaudiest life, the humblest thing that grows, Pour upon thirsty hearts transmuting showers: The seedful furrows each with quickness sows; For God the lowest with his beauty dowers, Feeding whereon, as seraphim on light, The gathering soul steels its immortal might. XV. Right on Cabiro walked, beneath the spell Of sparkling newness,—even his senses' fire Out-bidden by the blaze, as by the yell Of headlong hounds the woodland's matin choir. Now he bethought him of a “Guide.” 'T was well; For looking where he could become a buyer, Beside him rose a mart where one may buy Guides to all labyrinths in earth or sky,— XVI. One of those vast receptacles of brains,— Not brains in the coarse body, but distilled Through the fine chemistry wherewith in pains Of intellectual travail have been filled Page upon page with thought, tied up in skeins Called volumes, some in power and life so skilled, For ages they have flowed, exhaustless brooks, Into the vast of mind—undying books. XVII. Good books are th' essence of humanity, An attar pressed from nations' lives. Who seeks To know what peoples have been or will be, Must snuff their balm. To us there were no Greeks Had there not been Greek books. And what were we To-day without the Book? The holy peaks Of Sinai, wanting written leaves, were not, And Calvary a voiceless, bloodless spot. XVIII. The perfume must be there within the rind: Squeezed cabbages will not run hock. The Greeks Were teachers of the world, because of mind They bore such freight, and in their souls what speaks— And must from inward need—to human kind. The strenuous Hebrews! how they plied their cheeks With wail sublime and warning, to resound Through the ages, finding in deep hearts rebound. XIX. Books score the tides of history; and those Who are unflushed by their embalming breath Become the shadows of a name, the blows Of rude Oblivion sinking them beneath Its frothless sea. Of Carthage, Tyre, who knows The noted men, save where their being and death Are interlinked with Roman, Jew, or Greek? They bred no book, to time their fame to speak. XX. What we had lost but for old Homer's pen! Gigantic shadows shivered o'er the abysses Of Legend, there to be soon swallowed, when He seized them, and, as the fresh sunlight kisses To glowing life great peaks snatched from night's den, His love made bright immortals of Ulysses And fellows, who have ever since been part Of foremost men and women's head and heart. XXI. Without dear Plutarch, half a wilderness Were the thick tract sown with his lusty lives. The earth swings lighter in its orbit, less Of baseness is there in the world's close hives Of sting-armed men, for those great books. Egress And passport give they to the spirit that strives. Wanting one little book, millions were minus A good, great friend, Imperial Antoninus. XXII. The best books are a subtle distillation From the mixt nature of the richest men, When they, in moods of happy elevation Above themselves, are gifted with a ken And insights that are like a revelation,— Nay, are so, soulful minds using the pen To seize great thoughts that come without the will, To grave for others what their bosoms thrill. XXIII. Deep laid in secret, subterranean nests By the prolific sun,—obedient to Benignant, supervisive, far behests,— Mysterious eggs wait to be hatched by slow, All-ripening Time, when that his earthly guests Shall need this underlying overflow Of close-compacted heat, that lies, now cold, In black expectant blocks, millenniums old. XXIV. True books are a like brood, born of the light That fires the sun and kindles inward vision, Whereby men are undying, and 'twixt white And dark in spiritual things can make division, And know the good and true, and on this height Cull from their minds with luminous decision. Best books will ever be compacted soul,— Diamonds compressed from mounds of mental coal. XXV. Once they were scarce, a treasure of the few; But now that, where one read, ten thousand read, And creeds are older grown and thoughts more new, And thought has bred a longing to be freed, And freedom lifts the will to manhood's due, And lifted will and manhood are agreed To work unbaffled for emancipation,— Of books there is unspeakable multiplication. XXVI. Now that the world is quick with the life of thought, And the great globe is clasped with man's inventions,— On the stars even a deeper brightness wrought,— Books mentométers are of all pretensions, Deepen and freshen the fine currents fraught With the mind's messages, their high dimensions Swollen and ripened by warm books' keen ray, That makes perpetual motion, ceaseless day. XXVII. We have them daily, weekly, monthly, and Yearly or quarterly,—the pioneers Who clear and light the forward track with brand That, flashing on all souls alike, makes peers The lowest of the highest,—feat more grand Than Earth can show, and which through the sure years Shall work wide social weal, high spiritual health, Banding the Nations one sole Commonwealth. XXVIII. Cabiro having bought a “guide,” his feet Onward bore him again. But soon he passed From the great thoroughfare into a street Quiet and stately, where was thick amassed, Within stout walls for their high purpose meet, A public Library, rich, choice, and vast, Built, furnished, and endowed by the two Astors, Making themselves through time of thought the pastors. XXIX. And with these fames another should be mated,— Cogswell, the friend of books, the great Librarian, Whose brimming brain, with knowledge aye unsated, Carries the world's best brains with grasp Briarian. His bust beside the Donors' should be rated, Of native marble, or, what 's better, Parian, That all his intellectual face may see, And thank him down through far posterity. XXX. This courteous scholar led Cabiro through The linked recesses of a treasury, With ingots packed from Taurus to the Blue. Cabiro took not their full measure: he The honey hived in books had drawn and drew Not as a cultured idler, leisurely, But one who the fresh fragrant pages rifles Of juice, and never with a volume trifles. XXXI. But fruitfullest pages being themselves a fruit Of fullest life, life must be deeply borne, Ere books, that are its love-bred children mute, Can be deciphered fully, from them torn The finer meanings. Young life is a lute Smooth piping lone, which muffled drum and horn And trumpet and hard fife shall later quench,— Sometimes ere hairs grow gray or eyelids blench. XXXII. Not quench but silence; for through every life The lute will inly sound, and in the better, Mingling with disonants, will soothe the fife; And he is versed deepest in the spirit and letter Of life and books who through long years the strife Hath keenly felt and heeded, and, forgetter Of naught, can range from Perdita to Lear, To shriek or laughter giving learnèd ear. XXXIII. Cabiro was a gentleman as old— As Hamlet not, nor young as Juan.—Now I beg the reader will not be so cold, Despiteful as to point against my brow The brand of gross presumption, that so bold I could be as to hint for my lame crow The flight or stature of those eagles, soaring Where fame an everlasting noon is pouring. XXXIV. I almost wish that I had said, than Keats, When that great poet died, he 's somewhat older; And not so old as he whose master-feats Poetical mortals will ne'er let moulder,— Shelley, whose pure imaginative heats, Attempering when he sank without growing colder, In Adonais touched their perihelion, While vaulting Keats glowed greatest in Hyperion. XXXV. I said Cabiro had the subtle art— Or rather th' impulse that doth thither tend— To spell upon the features what the heart Most fondles. Partially to gain this end, (And the first adepts gain it but in part,) Imagination's royal seizures blend With subject-gifts. The man but blindly limps Who through this higher insight gets no glimpse. XXXVI. Imagination is no single power, But an ecstatic multitudinous clash Of many choice ones, all deckt with the dower Of fineness, so that from their conflux flash Lights sunny, pure, and wise, the very flower Of genius' tillage.—You would like more ash In the fast colors of a definition? Then the next stanzas answer your petition. XXXVII. When the Intellect's magnetic threads are held So tight and warm by Beauty, that she fires Through them the Feeling's finer chords, then—quelled All outward motions—tenderest desires, Selectest images that have upwelled From deepest fountains, pictures and tuned choirs, Master the soul's delivered citadel, Swaying the sceptres of creative spell. XXXVIII. This is Imagination in the phase Of might, as through her supersensuous lens The potencies of raptured poets blaze, Soulful with fresh self-kindled heats that cleanse The higher paths,—leaving the world agaze With upward look,—or throw upon the dens Within the lusting heart a ghastly glare, That startles wickedness from his hot lair. XXXIX. Again Cabiro found himself afloat On the strong current of the billowy street, Quick with immortal souls launched in a boat Each of the mortal body,—one vast fleet Sailing in sun or shade into the throat Of Death,—Death the renewer, who the feet Arrests of men, to give them in exchange Wings for fulfilment of their wider range. XL. In a close angle's nook Cabiro stopt, That from men's features harvest he might reap More than can be in twofold motion cropt,— Harvest not the less juicy that with sweep Of Fancy's blade the richer fruit was lopt From boughs, invisible but to eyes that leap All sensuous bars with swift ethereal glances: The half of what we label facts are fancies. XLI. Athwart the coming stream a figure shone Like a Diana, so outglittering all About her did she step, a one alone Under high sovereignty (as mid the hall Of marbles in the Louvre she of stone) Of virgin thoughts; but nearer seen, a fall She underwent from this cold height. Upon The magic disk of Steriopticon XLII. You 've seen two pictures each in other melt, An instant interfused both form and hue:— Thus this Diana, girt with the warm belt Of Venus, showed—and what at first than dew Unsunned seemed colder—vestal beauties,—dealt Soft wounds as on great fiery eyes (not blue) She passing took Cabiro's orbs of jet. But for a modest moment their eyes met; XLIII. And yet—so universally outspread And fine and keen attempered are the wires Wherewith by Love are circumnetted head And heart of all humanity, deep fires Quenchless for aye being kindled and besped By one sole flash falling on apt desires— That look had for Cabiro been enough, Had he been of inflammatory stuff. XLIV. His time was not yet come. And so he laid Within his brain upon the pulseful pile Where images of beauty are arrayed, One picture more; and then into the mile On mile of trampled stone his eye estrayed To light upon some other face, of style To draw the thoughts into its mysteries, And tie them to itself with sympathies. XLV. Like twins of thought and feeling intertwined, Of Beauty born by Meditation wooed, A pair came blended arm in arm, and mind Commingled through a common aim pursued,— The subtle service of the heart, refined By spiritual ministerings, and thence indued With delicate power,—a painter and a poet;— And what that means, how few are they who know it! XLVI. They paused ere parting at the angle where Cabiro stood; and as the poet raised His hat to let the breeze unbind his hair, Cabiro noted (thus is ever blazed The inward life on outward form and air) The swelling contours that the vision dazed With tender grace and the lit atmosphere Breathed from the soul upon the external sphere. XLVII. The painter courteously uncovering To agèd passer, the outline clean was shown Of head select, upon whose upper ring A somewhat less of thoughtfulness was thrown By th' inward sun, with finer chiselling Along the brow's arched pathway bold, thick sown With plastic agencies, a granary nigh For the rich harvests of a large gray eye. XLVIII. These vanished, twilight fell upon the throng,— A half eclipse wrought on Cabiro's eyes Through loss of their exceeding light. Not long He looked in shade, when far he saw arise, Faintly at first, then livelier,—like the song Of birds swelling to greet with tuneful cries The day a-dawning,—other twofold splendor, Not flaming, like the first, but orient tender: XLIX. Two sisters, hand in hand,—the one not quite A-tiptoe on the flowery marge where ends Flush childhood, and beyond, far out of sight Stretching, grave womanhood's domain that blends In the dim distance sky and earth, all bright Between with what imagination lends To maiden's wakeful, pure, transfiguring dreams, That steep the Future's web in golden gleams. L. A bud in fragrance still more closely folded, A reflex of the rainbow's sudden tints, A lesser growth as delicately moulded, Its beauties still more deeply hid in hints, The younger walked; and one would sore have scolded The tyrant Fortune who with niggard stints Had made him choose the one and leave the other,— A choice almost as hard as to their mother. LI. They both had amber curls, with eyes as blue As depths of most illuminated air, And skin pellucid with the perfumed dew Of life-abounding pulse,—creatures so fair They looked a vision stray, momently due Back to their heaven, but that the lithesome pair Trod with so firm a foot the elastic earth, And through their graces showed a work-day worth. LII. All the great loves that rule the manly breast Of brother, father, lover, all awoke From sweetest life-long sleep, in virgin nest Low chirping,—young Cabiro's heart, whence broke This chorus, thrilling him, all new possest With mighty loves; and as, like incense-smoke, The pair swept on, for the deep, saintly blessings They poured on him, his heart sent warm caressings. LIII. A face so sadly beautiful it bids The passer peer to learn its mystery, A palor vivified, as though the lids Were closed on life's red fountain, and to be Were but obedience in the soul that thrids The body's wearied currents passively,— This drew Cabiro's inmost look, who gazed As on a spirit that the vision mazed; LIV. So wrapt she seemed in calm, habitual grief, A grief so holy that it could not speak, And had within itself its sole relief, Enfolded in a heart that was too weak To bear it or cast out the secret thief Of all its joys, and yet too strong to wreak Itself on life; and so her daily breath Was but the feeder of a living death. LV. As moon by restless clouds the horizon near, She quick was swallowed by the shifting crowd, And in Cabiro's eyes a single tear Bedimmed their light with tender film, too proud To let upon his cheek their pearls appear, On woman glistening ornaments allowed. But still the street ran souls, with bodies more Or less fit for a window or a door LVI. Through which the soul could come or go, be seen Or see, and thus accommodated to Its earthly sojourn. That a link between The two is knit, and wherefore?—that to know Would hoist humanity a sovereign queen Over its being or conditions, low Or high, loosed from the despot, Chance, And the contractions gross of ignorance. LVII. Such knowledge absolute would sure imply Ascendencies that disinfect the will, And swing its aspirations up so high, All growling mutinies must then be still, The man self-ruled so nobly as to cry Avaunt! to malice, and despondence kill. But most men live as this were gospel text,— Bodies for this world are, souls for the next. LVIII. And some would think they have no deathless soul: Their thinking throws no sparks that seek a Heaven. Through burning breeding brains they 'd have to roll A blood mechanical that holds no leaven, Their senses thence so sodden that the scroll Of life's best story is for them unriven. With petty thoughts they 'd cramp our being in Their petty earthy world of sport and sin. LIX. Slowly a figure moved along the flag, As though he bore too much to be in haste. The weightiness that caused him thus to lag Was not all fleshly, but he was encased So tight in self-importance that to wag His limbs with rapidness would have unbraced His dignity, which like new crockery-ware Needed the label's heed—“Handle with care.” LX. Blood could no more be shut from what it bloats, Than he divided from his dividends: Silver was always oozing through his coats, And gold a-toying with his finger-ends: All o'er his shaven face you read bank-notes, While mortgage with his deepest thinkings blends. Of course he was a pillar of the church,— A golden, which poor rags must not besmirch. LXI. So subtly poisoned he by pride of purse, He had begun to think himself complete; Had judgments for all subjects, prose or verse; At dinners deemed he 'd not more right to eat All dishes than discuss all topics, terse Or loose, and would (in tongue at least) compete With scholars, poets, and not dream him rash,— Doing all this by virtue of his cash. LXII. Of many-threaded life it is a knot But partly loosed,—wherefore should budding shoots, Misblooming, be so cankered with the rot Of chronic greeds, that gnaw the tender roots Of joy, making men's earthly years a blot On the fair face of time? and what it boots To pile up credits here that change to debts Beyond the grave, to live there as regrets? LXIII. Life is so deep it deepens out of sight: Life is so vast its ends we cannot tie. Saint Paul we see, in mid-career, his might Turn on himself and brand as a long lie His past of faith and action; and the blight Of others' opening manhood, ere they die, Is purged from thought and feeling. This purgation (A passage in the spirit's education LXIV. Which men oft languish for, in some a change Gradual and still, for others a quick glow Of penitential warmth beyond the range Of will) not always issues here below; Is oft postponed to that blest realm, so strange To earthlings, who, although they say they know Their immortality, still fear to roam Towards Heaven, but hug the earth as all their home. LXV. Like icicle swift gliding down June leaves, Or on a banquet's glee stroke of tolled bell, Slid through that onward busy crowd (while heaves Cabiro's breast with long-suspended swell) A form, not wearing look that sharply grieves, But—like a dawn upon a dayless hell— One of pale startled joy,—a lurid stare Lighting a desolation with its glare. LXVI. Her cloak was worn and fine, and under it Something—hugged close against her bosom—sent Wild cheer into her eye, and seemed to unknit 'Twixt head and heart a tight entanglement, As she at last upon a friend had lit. She still was young, but youth had been so rent By wrong, its once warm sheen showed embers scattered And dying, trampled by Time's shod hoof, and shattered. LXVII. Wants, wishes, hopes that spring at youth's sweet beck, The flowery firstlings of a virgin soil, Snapt, blasted,—lay the fragments of a wreck About her heart, too poor to be the spoil Even of the poorest, she too seared to reck What else on earth might still bechance, her coil Of woe so tight it could no more be tightened. Love's throbbing hand, by which might yet be lightened LXVIII. The weight of haggard sorrows, was not there: The cold world turns its back upon the poor: Even love perhaps were now too late. Despair So long had clanked about her brain, the core Of thought was touched. Thence only could she dare With her own finger ope the dreadful door: And thence the smile wherein she glisteneth: Beneath her cloak she hugs a draught of death. LXIX. Cabiro, as she passed him, stood agape, Speechless and motionless with a new awe; Then, lest her waning figure should escape, Rushing to where she disappeared—“Who saw That woman?”—to a knot 'mong whom her shape He last had seen. One answered with a “pshaw”; The others stared as at a man astray: A deep breath drawing, he went on his way. LXX. “I'm glad he 's out of that numb nook, and hope He'll now keep moving. Don't you see he 's tired With standing, like myself. The place to mope Is not street-corners. I would be all fired With incidents and passions; and you grope Along the common flag, getting bemired In spongy moods and thinkings, my good sir.” I must have speech with this philosopher. LXXI. To you, my friend, I 'd like to say a word. A peaceful sinner, least of all with readers Would I have quarrel; for they are the herd We shear (my publishers and I), good breeders Of greenbacks. Feed they gross, like carrion-bird, They 're coarse in fleeces: I like daintier feeders, Who prosper on such high and delicate diet, Their blood will run æsthetically riot. LXXII. Some books are writ that all who run may read: I want no running readers. I like those With pith to think while reading, who thus breed Thought from my page. Now, sir, for fresh thought's blows You are too weak, strong as you think your need In books; and I suspect, spite of your clothes, A girlish fellow, one would throw a fan to. By Jove! you shant read me: I end the canto. CANTO IV. I. So bound our being is to higher joys, That life without them were a wilderness, Where vainly unto bestial man deploys Nature her wealth and beauties, aimed to bless Angelic man. The lower self destroys— If 't is not inly felt to be the less, Subordinated thus to loftier needs— All bounteous broadening manhood's sapful seeds. II. Men must forget themselves in man, to reach The plane of high humanity. Unchained From pettiness, they mount where visions teach Lessons deeper and truer than are deigned To those whose thought and look and daily speech Droop with th' entombment wherein, dimmed and stained, Impacted lie the crude and the unfreed, Th' unknowing or the wilful thralls of greed. III. The sweep of planets in their solar path, The work of corals in their crystal home, (Both swaying in a ceaseless silent swath,) Or an immeasurable vast of foam Whipt by an ocean-tempest, white with wrath, While winds, those viewless lions, roar and roam, Speak not more loudly law's majestic ease Than when large sympathies the reason seize, IV. And bid it lay the deep foundation-stones, (Furnished by them,) slowly whereon uprise Structures so broad and complex that the tones And wants of cultured life, or gross or wise, Find place for their unfolding, as all zones On equatorial mountain, of such size And height, all climates choose their own degrees, And feed fruits tropical and frosted trees. V. No marriage 'twixt high sentiment and thought, And there can be no growth. Nor man nor tribe Can grasp and hold the subtle rounds, self-wrought, Of culture's ladder, nor the breath imbibe That swells aspiring breasts with pantings fraught With spiritual purifications sweet, that bribe Towards Heaven, but through this union 's offspring, growing From age to age, and aye with freshness glowing. VI. Withdraw th' electric currents from our air, And earth's full life would dwindle and dissolve. Cabiro's tear for that wan lone despair Was but one flash of lightnings that involve Man in a circumambient glow, and glare Oft visibly in fervors that resolve Hard selfish chills, which, suffered to outspread, Would make of life's great heart death's icy bed. VII. That tear was the warm child of fellow-feeling, A drop from love's long string of perfect pearls That clasps humanity,—a sweet unsealing Of th' instant Heaven, which here on earth enfurls Each mortal with immortal breaths, appealing To purity that in the vilest curls At times up from the sore protesting soul, Smothered in fumes of lust that round it roll. VIII. Cabiro went his way, no more intent To con with thoughtful zest the features' page. On hopeless haggard ones his look was bent So vividly, his brain became a cage Wherein was singly hung that visage, rent With woe. He sought for something to assuage The tremor of his mind; nor long the search, For soon he came upon a showy church; IX. And shuffling through his “Guide,” from it he learned, 'T was one of those where congregate th' élite. Hereon the fancy nimbly working, churned, For his internal vision, pictures meet For Christian fane in Christian land, where burned Fires that with democratic radiance heat The brother-millions of the kingless nation, And purest warm a Sunday congregation. X. On a broad burnished area he beheld (Through his mind's eye) an intermingled throng Of rich and poor; nor could you there have spelled Which of them unto either class belong, So in the rich all pride of air was quelled, And from the carriage of the poor all wrong (If 't be a wrong) of fortune so was wiped: Mere women, men, with worldly streaks unstriped. XI. No feathered bonnets pranked in pews preferred, Paining so many eyes in other pews; No toilets stitched in France, in Russia furred, Of cost to shadow brows of richest Jews; By none hate courted, and as sure incurred, For claimed importance that for homage sues; No vulgar sacrilege by vulgar wealth, But everywhere a clean religious health. XII. A cordial congregation 't was of souls, Where bodies were even less than secondary: And woe! when body's needs are life's chief goals; For though when Jordan or the Styx we ferry We leave them far behind low laid in holes, They may have stained us, being not momentary Thin garments loose, with naught that 's lasting 'bout them, But such that best souls cannot do without them. XIII. They are the buds through which our being blooms Into eternity, so deeply freighted With savors, these outlive the coldest dooms Of passionate perversion, and created To die no more,—slow sickening in the glooms Of errant paths,—with essence unabated Requickening, in freshened perfumes lave Man's deathless life, far, far beyond the grave. XIV. The starred immensities are revelation Of th' incommensurable untold forces Issuing from God,—translucent incarnation Of the great soul that through all matter courses, Embodied for upward invigoration And stout organic play of fine resources, HE joying in corporeal pulse's beatings And subtile beauty's moulded self-repeatings. XV. Thus beauty gleams in its infinitude Of forms through thronged illuminated space, Each mote and sun almightily endued With life's ecstatic fire, creation's face Glassing omnipotence, her features dewed With love's sweet sap, and in the glowing race Of life each creature's core exhaling breath That the joint bonds of being strengtheneth; XVI. While through all kinds, degrees of life uptowers The paragon of corporated being,— In him co-mated qualities and powers, The highest here are known of God's decreeing,— Studded with manifold and deeper dowers Than earthly gauge can mete, and so far-seeing His thought grasps th' universe, himself still wondering More at himself than at the shook heavens thundering; XVII. The sunny climax he of all he scans, Nature's choice juice building with finest food The miracle of power and beauty, man's Erected body, fluent with the flood That floats the fleets of human life, and bans Stagnation,—the full rivers of hot blood That ply the pulses in the mighty brain, To forge thought's thunderbolts that war with pain; XVIII. Which nurture too the spiritual mightiness That weaves of light thought's argent upward wings,— A might supreme, a present heavenliness Within the mind, supernal ministerings Unseen, a benediction's unfelt stress, A blessing breath transvolant angel flings Upon the brain, that loosens it from earth And foretaste gives of future heavenly birth. XIX. It seemed thus loosed from self's short coarser ties That congregation, as with radiance mild It shone like an unangered sea that lies Rejoicing calm, and images the piled White clouds, and glistens with a thousand eyes, All looking at the sun.—But not inisled They seemed, as severed from their outside hours, A corpse deckt for a day with living flowers; XX. But rather was their mood a heightened tone, By contact heightened and the cheer imparted By souls to soul,—a prospering heat upblown To lively blaze, a fuller flame outdarted From fervid fuel stirred. Their love had grown Not in the shifting sand of creeds, but hearted In fellow-feeling: each in other saw God's image,—lifted thus their love by awe. XXI. A leader fit they had, one apt to lead, Through graces, through cherubic benison, Whereby the man angelic needs not plead For rule against the bestial rebel one Within, but sways with buoyant empire, freed From the pinched wolves of lust, that set upon The soul,—freed even from their yelp's long dart By the far light borne in a cleanly heart. XXII. In him there was no rebel. Every fire Warming the lower earthly only burned A happy servant to the human higher, That work beyond their clay, and having earned Great lessons, here to th' angel-height aspire, Their functions thriftly played, they having turned Passions to blessings, lusts to modest loves, Through the same virtue's might that planets moves. XXIII. His being was of those to whom 't is given, Through duteous range of reaching sympathies, Already on the earth to live in Heaven, So washed in the sweet flow of purities, Out of themselves by loves so daily driven, Swelling o'erblossomed with humanities,— Like the deep self-forgetting Nazarene, Who lived a million lives in one serene. XXIV. This heart-instructed teacher was so versed In lore of love and sapient charity, He could detect good meanings in the worst, And through the blackest blood a glimmer see To kindle hope. Nor was there one that durst Not near him as a father, sure to be Enfolded in soft words, medicinal 'Gainst guilty pangs and crime's envenomed gall. XXV. Too strong he was to love mere power, too fair And deep a self to be an egotist, Or court of listening crowds the shallow stare; His appetites too sane for worldly grist. Like that one on the mount, his sermons were Clear welling words, warm with such cordial gist The understanding through the heart they teach. Dear reader, did you ever hear him preach? XXVI. Almost by death-stroke was Cabiro sundered From visionary meditative mood. In one same instant the air blackened, flashed, thundered Above the very flag-stone where he stood. The next, the church-spire blazed: whereat he wondered: He did not know the steeple was of wood. Wind, rain, shrill screaming fast, quick thunderclaps, Bursting immixed in a few moments' lapse XXVII. Upon his dream-wrapped senses, hurried him, It seemed, into unblest transearthly homes, Where life raged fierce, with lawless fury grim. Deepening the din a band of giant gnomes Came bellowing, at their lips huge trumpets, brim With hoarseness, on their heads strange shiny domes. But now Cabiro's senses being full roused, He took an omnibus, to get him housed. XXVIII. The blossomed snow of the June-frosted thorn,— Smothered in clustering flowers its tender green,— Or the pure warmth of maid, through love new-born Ere yet her stature glows with woman's mien, Are emblems of a glistening late-spring morn, When May-days on the neighboring summer lean, Whose warmer, deep, maternal breathings bring A ruddier throb into the heart of spring. XXIX. On such a morning was Cabiro out Beyond the Park, well mounted. The blue air, So full of prime and daylight, breathed about His head with a mild vigor, as it were The playmate of far summits, and the shout Had helped of billows, from their ocean-lair Upon the shore with sunny laughter breaking, And shook the grass where violets are a-making. XXX. Cabiro, having ridden towards the Sound, Poured his joyed vision through its distant isles; Then westward saw great Hudson from a mound Towards where his palisades afar he piles; Then from the Park—the city's playing-ground So vast and beautiful—rode back through miles Of democratic palaces,—all new, Plutocracy's stronghold, Fifth Avenue. XXXI. The richer, fuller, finer natures seek Proportion, harmony,—a subtle want Which, outwardly unsatisfied, will wreak Itself in inward imagings that pant Up the green steeps of being, and then outspeak Their findings fresh in words so little scant Of power and truth, the generations drink Deep draughts of wisdom from their bolder brink. XXXII. As through the Avenue Cabiro rode, His pasturing eyes shifted from side to side To scan this that magnificent abode. A mettlesome imagination vied With senses vigilant, and purple-glowed With figures, seen behind such walls to glide, Graceful, accomplished, with the well-bred ease Given by Culture in its first degrees. XXXIII. 'T is easy for the young to dream, awake; For hope to fringe the dreams, as dawn the night: 'T is easy for the poet's pen to shake Legions of heroes down from realms brain-bright: Wishes were not so easy could they break Life's burdens, and dismount the Wrong with Right. Edens, Arcadias blest, have only been Brain-pictures by crude pastoral tenants seen,— XXXIV. By man unlearned alike in joy and grief, The visions of whose raw simplicity Stand to hale manhood's in as low relief As children's toys to Art's great enginery, As tents to temples, as the whistling brief Piping of reeds to Mozart's symphony. Heavens above and Edens here below With deepening culture in the bosom grow. XXXV. On the day's wane Cabiro stood within One of those mansions square, a dinner-guest; Welcomed with mien that was more than a thin O'ershiny varnish. The so cordial zest Of host and hostess made him feel akin To the whole company, at once possest Of social soil; not looking and looked at Askance, like dogs and an intruding cat. XXXVI. Dinner is the chief bolt that pins together Body and soul,—the pivot whereon wind In mystic coil the threads that knit the nether To th' upper being. With subtleties of mind Is freighted every swallowed morsel, whether Of flesh begored, or pulpy from the rind Of muskiest mellon; for, what very odd is, Bodies need souls not more than souls need bodies. XXXVII. Dinner being thus a daily consecration Of the high marriage 'twixt this mighty two, No time so choice for social celebration As when leaps nimble their lithe offspring true,— Speech, rhythmic with a mental elevation. Then is wit's harvest, then the hour to woo, When life is throbbing with a double birth, Rich with fresh fragrancies of heaven and earth. XXXVIII. There have been famous diners, who have come Flashed on our distant times,—like Socrates, The chief of Plato's high symposium,— By fleetness of electric tongues. Of these, Whose fame time has not yet been chill to numb, Shines rich Lucullus,—not by making seas Flood fish-ponds, but by giving dinners to The great, the wise, to Pompey, Cicero. XXXIX. One likes a logic life; and so Apicius Wins a respect, spite of the glutton's blot On his escutcheon's field. So avaricious His stomach was, it swallowed every jot Of his estate. His wonted meats delicious Thus to his palate lost, he slew him, not, After high Roman fashion, with a sword, But in the meaner modern mode, with cord. XL. Cæsar went once (it may be oft) to dine With Cicero. How rich, we think, the talk Between such two, each with a deepening mine Of thought, experience; fluent as the walk Avernian; both pickt pupils of the Nine. Though politicians both, that need not balk Our hope: for they were broad, and friends long tried, And so could cast their scurviness aside. XLI. Of all the diners that ere sat at board, The one who haunts my inner vision most Is exiled Dante at Can's table, gored By ribald flatteries, dulcet to his host,— Mute, tortured, like huge storm-torn warsman moored 'Mid corsair craft; save when himself is lost In the far solitudes of his great thought, His heaving brain by deathless fancies wrought: XLII. A man, sublime from the vicissitudes Which the deep grandeurs of his nature raised To rend him, as with subterranean feuds Mountains are rent, and men for ages mazed With spouted fire, and giant interludes Of sulphurous smoke and moanings: thus has blazed The heavenward-striving Dante o'er his land, Majestic lonely, beautifully grand. XLIII. At company-dinners, great or small, the dishes Are but the flies a hook is baited with. Unless they grapple intellectual fishes, They are fat worms to feed mere body's pith, And balk all save the grosser gourmand's wishes. Biographers relate of Sidney Smith, That when the wit was wrapped in the soft lull Of death, London's great dinners all grew dull. XLIV. Irving would tell of Moore, who was unable To take unwounded such an obligation From Lansdowne as a cottage small. “A fable Honor moulds,” Irving said; “your conversation Will pay the cottage and what at his table You eat.”—Moore had in talk no hesitation, And was so sprightly glib he let none droop, Adding a flavor to the daintiest soup. XLV. Since dinners first were given, the foremost host Is Rogers, called “the Poet,” who was none; But was in this poetic, that his roast For sixty years, as choice amphytrion, He gave to men of lustre, and could boast Wits, poets, marshals, nobles he had won As guests, aye choosing people blest with nous, Keeping for such a dinner-open house. XLVI. Allston lies garnered in my memory As, long ago at hospitable Boston board, Opposite he sat in silent dignity. The table's talker was a Frenchman, stored With worldly phrase, and volubility Of clever laud of Pope, whom he adored With other Gallic Britons, men forsworn By Allston with a deep Coleridgian scorn. XLVII. The lively Frenchman had a certain grace Of mind and manner. As he talked and smiled, You saw his goals were earthly in life's race, And that much time he had in pleasure whiled: The self lay naked all about his face. With pale poetic features undefiled Allston showed like a statue classic-clean, Amid a market's babble, still, serene. XLVIII. The drawing-room wherein Cabiro and His fellow-guests were greeted was not spacious, But almost seemed so from the right demand Of Art fulfilled, which, truthfully fallacious, Wields—through proportion's magic—fairy wand, Coming disguised to men, like goddess gracious, And, to uplift them with her subtle work, Bares with wise comely seeming truths that lurk. XLIX. Some would have said the furniture was scant; And so it was according to the measure Of one who has not known life's deeper want, Who with plump purse and famished noddle plays your Critic on things artistic, though he can't Tell joys æsthetic from mere senses' pleasure, And thinks refinement's needs can always be Tied to the tassels of upholstery. L. Pictures hung on the walls, not in close ranks, Darkening the room with surfaces opaque With shallow mimicries, frame-blazoned blanks, Mere mural furniture; but such as slake The thirst for beauty, as with daily thanks We front them gazing, while they freshly wake Emotion, teaching us what is true Art,— A union fine of intellect and heart. LI. They were not many, so that each enjoyed Apart the focus of your eye, each one Selected as a friend to fill a void In feeling, which its character and tone Could tenderly achieve; then, unalloyed With egotism or ostentation, shone Mildly on th' owner's better moments, clear As whispering star through heavenly atmosphere. LII. And buoyant bronzes, bearing lights so lightly They seemed almost uplifted too; and busts, Making a soul to shine through, calmly, whitely; And antique bits defying age's rusts, By genius' touch kept ointed infinitely; All spoke to mind and mind's refining trusts. There were no mirrors, sleek reverberants Of vanity, obsequious sycophants. LIII. From this you passed through one (alike in style But less in size, as through flush fragrant bower) Scented by near conservatory's smile. The dinner-table bloomed with fruit and flower. The meats,—served from the sideboards by a file Of featly servitors, at punctual hour, On silver,—like the wines, selectest, best, Were chosen for a pure abiding zest. LIV. A dinner, not to be frustraneous, Should be a concert conversational. Now, several duos simultaneous Are to both mind and ear probational, Being not with concord consentaneous. The conversation, to be rational In a high sense, at table should be one,— A harmony, a vocal unison. LV. With host and hostess there were ten at table, Enough for intellectual lingual feast; Enough, too, if uncultured, for a babel Of dislocated speech. The nimble yeast Of mind in a proved mixture will enable The whole with life. A bore is a witless beast Broke loose and braying, to strayed donkey apt kin: He should be strangled with a damask napkin. LVI. The guests were well assorted as to age: More than the half were past what 's called their prime; So called because we fit an animal gauge To life, ungratefully perverse towards Time, Who would be lifting us from stage to stage Through high eternity; while we but climb His jewelled rounds to reach some sensual prey, Scorning him when he will not coax our clay. LVII. The host and hostess were grand-parents glad. The host had known how to make riches yield Unrotting fruit. Inheritor, he had Not sunk his best mind in the miry field Where wealth is planted and manured,—a sad Chief business for an earthly mortal, sealed With an unearthly immortality: His spirit was spared such sharp adversity. LVIII. Upon the hostess' spacious brow there lay The sunshine of a happy mother's years, Tempered by thought's serenely active play. Hour linked to hour by duty's harness cheers Each morning, letting in an upper day Upon life's lowliest labors, and endears Work to the worker. She had soul to warm These with the joys that from high culture swarm. LIX. Upon her right was one, a man, well steeped, Not in bare years, but in the juices rich That from ascending phases may be reaped By him who can uplift him to the pitch Of beckoning possibilities, upheaped By Time about an open soul, from which Life is distilled by mind and love of beauty, Through joy and nature, sorrow, pleasure, duty. LX. Far had he travelled in adjacent space; Had drunk entrancing draughts from simple spring; Without or whip or spur had won life's race; And heard sweet melodies where none did sing. Dyed in his brain, light shone on word and face, Such light as wasting earth-lamps never fling, Which all were glad to have upon them flung: Children the most, who felt he too was young. LXI. Mere worldly witnesses deemed his career A failure; for he had not gathered store Of visible things, and held a million dear If bought with smallest coin of wisdom's lore. Of knowledge even he cared not to uprear Huge piles, but sucked the essence from its core, So that his spirit went on growing, brightening; And now at three-score-ten he still was ripening. LXII. Upon her left the hostess had a wit; Not one who watched and strained for dinner-show Of laughter-moving phrases, but could fit Fresh comic contrasts with due words; or throw Ironic shadows on their opposite,— Pretentious glare; or give a subtle blow To pert vulgarity: with genial ease All this, without an aim to wound or please. LXIII. He was a prosperous merchant, who had made His busy days yield time for marrowy books; Had travelled gainful choicely, having paid With golden ducats that his ears and looks Might hive good thoughts for later use, uplaid Fine treasures in the mind's remotest nooks. They were fast friends, he and the sunny sage, With ten years' difference in their lambent age. LXIV. One who a full maternity of mind Had earned, through the rich stages, plane or steep, Of womanhood, sat by the host. Behind, The years flowed from her as upon the deep, In storm or calm, the fleeing waves embrined From a great ship, in her majestic sweep Self-urged by burning heart, to star and sun Looking for guidance that her ports be won. LXV. She long had gained clear summits, where she dwelt In broad serenity, but not at rest. Through summers she had climbed, winters that pelt, Cropping with inward power each season's best, Like steadfast granite through each mountain-belt Of varying forest, till far shines his crest In ceaseless snow,—not in cold torpor furled, But feeding the great rivers of the world. LXVI. So from her height on others now she poured, From heaven-replenished fountains in the soul, Refreshment gathered through her loves, and stored In thought-ennobled heart. An onward whole Her life, the present paramount, so scored With debits to the future, its fresh scroll Had no spare room for lament, her to-morrows Too alive for retrospective joys or sorrows. LXVII. Upon the sunny sage her company Was like an intellectual genesis; His light enkindled to its warmest by Her light, of finer quality than his. He found his ripest judgments deeper lie Upon her intuition clear, which is Woman's high strength through wholeness, her full being By love flashed to a focus, keen, far-seeing. LXVIII. The gift of admiration, that doth draw The latent best there 's in us from its deeps, And educates the soul through love and awe, She had; and now joyful her spirit leaps; For one, whom not for the first time she saw,— One of those creatures whom coy nature steeps In such rare loveliness, men's raptured eyes Wonder to what high levels she can rise,— LXIX. Sat opposite, upon the other side Of the proud host. A child she might have been Of th' elder, while almost to be a bride Was her first daughter grown. A very queen She was of grace, which is a power allied To the divine even more than beauty's sheen,— From beauty's self a subtle distillation, Of life most delicate fragrant emanation. LXX. In her, great beauty, as he riper grew, Embalmed himself the more and more with grace, A spiritual light, a supersubtle dew, In which her words and motions—as through lace The finest, fairest skin—did glisten through. The music of her speech enwreathed her face In softness, as hymned breath a harp fine strung, Or the hushed stars a nightingale's rapt tongue. LXXI. Beside her sat an artist, one of those Selected men whose franchise 't is to read The beauty of the world, and then disclose With pencil, pen, or chisel what doth breed A higher sensibility, and sows Thought, courage, hope in hearts that joy or bleed. This one was mounting fervent towards his prime, With vision for what 's tender, pure, sublime. LXXII. Upon his other hand his bride was seated, Whose trustful eyes with him had just been learning Old Europe's Art, their unsoiled love more heated By joint allayment of congenial yearning. Scarce more by beauty's visual bliss was greeted Paris before the three, with envy burning, Than the Artist there between such two, a third In front lovelier than can be told by word. LXXIII. To several of the company, by host Or hostess, had Cabiro been presented; Which courtesy unpaid, constricting frost Numbs the new stranger, for whom should be scented The house's air. As on a hostile coast, Half-wrecked, one feels as he would have resented For an affront, not for a kindness bowed, To be thrown coldly on a foreign crowd. LXXIV. By one he stood, within whose atmosphere He seemed drawn from himself. There was a deep Heart-look upon her features, and so clear Her eyes, as though an angel's soul might leap Through them and shiver who should come too near With thought disloyal. Beauties yet to reap Lay thick about her heart, known but to God, Like violets veiled in March beneath their sod. LXXV. He led her in to dinner, and his seat Beside her grew each instant more and more A throne's befringèd step, he at the feet Of his high sovereign queen. Cabiro bore Him aye towards women as in them he 'd greet A holier being. What carriage then he wore Towards one whose presence was a blessèd might, Holding him with a sudden, sacred right. LXXVI. On her wrought so the new almightiness As on a bed of rose-buds the warm shower Awaited to unbind their loveliness, Or sleeping lilies touched by morning's power, That wake to feel how deeply he can bless. Nor did th' unconscious heaven-commanded flower Open with less distrust or fear's alloy Than she to the new soul-exalting joy. LXXVII. They sit there growing into one; nor miss The words around, decked heralds of the birth Of fancies, thoughts,—fit atmosphere, I wis, To fan great love within his new-made hearth. There then I leave them in a taintless bliss: A greater they will never know on earth. You, reader kindly, you I kiss my hand to: Adieu, farewell, good-bye, till the next canto.</field>
   </doc>
</add>