<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Calvert, George Henry, 1803-1889</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Calvert, George Henry, 1803-1889</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">calvert george henry 1803 1889</field>
      <field name="author_text">Calvert, George Henry, 1803-1889</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1880's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ap/uvaGenText/tei/chap_AM1034.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240350</field>
      <field name="date_text">[1883]</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:440459</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Sibyl ; A Poem</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="title_display">Sibyl ; A Poem</field>
      <field name="title_facet">sibyl</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">sibyl</field>
      <field name="title_text">Sibyl ; A Poem</field>
      <field name="year_display">[1883]</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1883</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1883</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440459&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440459&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Calvert, George Henry, 1803-1889&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;calvert george henry 1803 1889&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Sibyl ; A Poem&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;sibyl&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;[1883]&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1883&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Calvert, George Henry&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1803&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1889&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Sibyl&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Poem&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Boston&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Lee and Shepard&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;[1883]&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3865625-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;cham1034&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Sibyl&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Poem&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1996&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1996 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 37 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-AmPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SIBYL. Nestled within a grassy nook, where heaved Deep rocks their bald heads in the air, Around whose shoulders mosses weaved Soft web, to shield them from the wear Of cold and rain,—like woman's arms Twined tenderly round husband, whose bold will, Uplifting him with envied skill, Bares him to the world's pelting harms,— A cottage sent its solitary smoke Into th' all-clasping blue; And in the sea-tossed sailor woke Dear thoughts of his far home. The dew That shone before The sheltered cottage door, Its bright aërial twinkle, Tempered with salt-sea sprinkle From the near sprayful ocean, Whose never-ceasing motion, Through tuneful tidal stress, or tempest's whip, Was multitudinous companionship To th' inmates of the cottage. These were three. In every human group will be,— Be it man or child or woman,—one, Through whom, round whom, are spun Life's finest, strongest threads, woven by Love, The founder, mover, of all beings that move, The great heart of this throbbing universe. Here 'twas an infant girl, Soft-rounded as a sea-born pearl, In whom the mystery of growth lay coiled,— Like deity in the air unspoiled,— And on whom smiled a watchful nurse. This exquisite piece of heavenly work Smiled, too, and chirped, and then began to speak, The wonders that in such a creature lurk Outleaping in short syllables, too weak For their new burden. Him Who helped to tend her, and whose looks And thoughts clung to her, as to limb Of blossomed tree the ripening sun, She called “pa-pa,” and often drew, With her fresh joys, from his loved books. In her bright laughter was a ring Seraphic, and her earnest chatter Glad as to thirsty garden-beds in spring The warm shower's tuneful patter. Gleeful to make them visible in the twirls, Wherein upon her head they danced, Sea-breezes pressed and tossed her curls Upon her brow and eyes, whence glanced Beams, as though Joy and Hope Had found new Heaven in this earthly blue, Where they revelled in fullest scope, Looking enraptured through The darknesses of life, Seeing nor pain, nor grief, nor strife. Of these dull darknesses some fell On Sibyl as she played and laughed, Unconscious of the malign spell Which stung the joy that Oswald quaffed From her sweet ways and cheery lips, Holding his soul in half eclipse. As if accordant with his mood, He chose dark days for longest walks Upon the shore whereof no rood But is a rocky dyke that balks The wind-armed ocean's vast attack. And if the sea rose angrily, to lash The lifted land and dash Against it billows' rage, and they Were hurled growling and hissing back, Oswald, amid the flying spray, Would welcome the resounding fight, Th' ever-repeated onset and the flight. And when in darkest night Tempest took the sea's side, Flinging it 'gainst the steadfast rocks, As it would whelm them with new shocks, The electric air deepening the wide, Fierce tumult, thunder's crash Instant upon the blinding flash, Awed, he stood, on a headland high, The bellowing, fiery sky Uplifting him towards the sublime Great presence, as though, for the time, The soul were freed, and he stood there, a man Unfleshed, clean of all mortal earthly ban. Uprose the Sun above a laughing shore, Where waves came sweeping in to embrace The rocks they struck the night before, Storm's deafening clangor giving place To melody their meeting made. Deep Nature's lifeful voice Is ever tuneful, ceaseless pæan, paid To the creative Spirit,—a call On many-tongued creation to rejoice In being, with cadence musical. When cataract or lion roars, Each is in tune with robin's early pipe, Or the low-nested lark that singing soars. The storm left Oswald in a sunnier mood. He walked forth in the glittering day With thought more apprehensive apt, Emotions less unripe, More in deep Nature's wonders lapt; For he was given to brood On abstract thinkings, and to play With barren mongrels, born Of a subjective inwardness,— Which no outflamings bless,— And peering frigid intellect; A brood that feedeth less on love than scorn,— A brood so blind that when 't is near being wreckt, Deems it hath reached victorious goal. Oswald lived too much in his books; And they were not the highest, best, Those that wake aspiration in the breast, Those that reflect great Nature's soul, As do what 's over them clear running brooks. Shakespeare less often would he read Than Edwards and his juiceless kin, Keen, intellectual delvers in Mines of th' unsweetened self, where seed Can sprout of no benignant blessings, Or glowing, self-forgetting hopes, But where, wheedled by self-caressings, Unconscious drunk with incense from the me, Which dims the higher vision, the mind gropes While thinking that it mounts triumphantly. Close arguments of such books, narrow, bold, Unlighted by emotion's heat, Lead only to negations cold: Within them is no warm heart-beat. The servant of a loving heart That intellect must be that aims to teach Mankind its highest part, And help it a stout moral stature reach. Faith, Hope, and Love are holy fire, Kindled in man by superhuman power. If even one of these expire, A lurid cloud would o'er rent manhood lower; And if all three should fade to lifeless embers, Men would then screech and howl Like forest vagrants, and, no more ruled members Of wide, continuous wholes, would prowl Voracious, sullen, thriftless, sad; No memories out of joyance wrought, Nor visionary pictures glad, But only low-brow'd thought Within the shrunken brain, That gnaws itself in rabid pain, Having no outward longings to fulfil. Earth, ocean, sky, their beauty and their might, Now emptied of man's will, Would bring to him no wisdom-fraught delight. Oswald was startled into faith By the sublimities Of that resounding sea-coast storm; That in the lightning's flash there rayeth A light supernal, wherein lies The source of every living form, He felt within a deeper deep Than yet his soul had bared. That fiery, thunder-breeding leap Into his inmost being had glared, And bred there new religious thought, Linking him to supremest will,— Something more than his books had taught, Joying him with unearthly thrill. And when, after a calm sleep's rest, He went forth to re-meet The lifeful Sun, and tideful Ocean Coming in majesty to greet, With peaceful swell and shining crest, Th' expectant shore, 't was with the glad emotion Of one about to clasp dear slighted friends In penitent arms. From th' all-enfolding blue, Hope, as a moon that bends In a clear sky her bow anew, Beckoned him towards her silent beams, Like bright eyes in a lover's dreams. With spring of one in re-earned health, He walked back on th' erst barren shore, Now ripe with spiritual wealth. Within a stone's throw of his cottage door Welcomed he was by Love. As she had just been born Of fresh embraces of the sun and sea, Shone, in a little curvèd cove, Like dewdrop in an April morn, Sibyl, leaping with liveliest glee As th' ocean softly kissed her rosy feet. Then she would chase his swift retreat, Laughing with tuneful screech, As with a shoreward dash, Catching her on the beach, He would her little ankles splash. To Oswald's first surprisèd glance It seemed as he were gazing On sudden vision of a trance, The sun warm blazing On Sibyl in the curvèd cove, Outsparkling she The illuminated sea, So beautiful, she seemed to move With an immortal motion, Beauties of sunlit shore and ocean Frigid and pale to hers, Outflamed from fire enkindled By breath that stirs Divinely mingled, To outfill man's resplendent being. When she saw Oswald near her, Leaving her giant playmate on the sand, She ran to meet him who was dearer Than aught the sea or land Could show to her young seeing. Oswald stooped low the joyous child to fold Close to his heart, as he would press Her being into his, and hold It there in endless, warm caress. Just then a dense cloud passed between The sun and cove: discoloring shade, Like bad thoughts sudden seen Fair visage to degrade, Fell on the stainless bloom Of Sibyl, sending arrowy chill To blast his soul's warm thrill, As he had heard a deadly doom. He let the child slip to the earth, And giving to her little hand his finger, Unmindful of her prattling mirth, And her desire to linger, Silent, he walked in darkness, wrought By memories that o'ercast his thought. Near to the cottage they were met by Maude, The nurse, their sole attendant. She Looked daily on the broad, The boundless, changeful, sounding sea. As from the cottage door she saw it 'Twas a far-stretching gleam, A rock-framed picture; but she could not draw it In fancy, or in sunshine see, Did not its foreground beam With Sibyl's light and glee. A daily rainbow in her sky, A promise and a beauty, To Maude was Sibyl, a divine Illumination, high Celestial gift, a sign Of blessing, a sweet call to duty. Sibyl was six months old When Oswald trusted her to Maude, Whose first look was not mercenary, cold. In her strong nature lurked no fraud, And she was warm with woman's feeling. As th' infant oped its eyes into her own, In its dear helplessness appealing To the “eternal womanly,” a lone Immortal creature, she in her Deep soul felt th' angel stir. The dimpled babe she laid In her warm heart to warm it, And turn to brightness shade That clouded that good heart to alarm it,— A heart that was not only good But sound, not only sound but wise: She was again a mother, and her blood Blushed with the joy that dyes Only maternal hearts. Oswald turned him to th' ocean shore again. Oh, if its boundless solitude Could swallow up this pain! But his were inward smarts. Only the soul can purge What soul hath fouled. Imbued With too much me, to a dirge Life's music sinks, in spite Of seeming cheerfulness,— Often a flickering light To mask a deep distress. His harp of many strings, Whereon pure music flings Th' eternal God, Oswald had jangled: By rash misuse of freedom's boon, Had put it rudely out of tune; And so, his joy was daily mangled By one bad, selfish deed. His suffering was proof Of innate good, and of the power and need To cleanse his deathless being's woof Of mortal stains that darkened His life within, without; This suffering took from each joy its bloom, From every act its finer grace, From every pleasure its perfume,— Laming him for life's hardy race. To-day he felt upsprout Purest desires, and he hearkened To those profoundest, wisest whispers That in the sane will not be hushed; Breathings fresh from the Eternal source, That mould the speech of earliest lispers, Choice images of innocent force,— Breathings that never can be crushed. Tender, close, strong as sheaves Of light, Love weaves Imperishable filaments that bind The human creature to creative Mind: Thence wields he of the power native To the Supreme, and only Love is quick creative. For four years Oswald had been learning From Sibyl. Through her mystical unfolding He had daily sought with burning, Bold curiosity to spell Life's riddle, in the ceaseless swell Of body and of mind beholding That beautiful great miracle, A callow human creature climbing (From inward motion) th' infinite scale of being. Here nothing was vouchsafed his seeing, No inward to this outward rhyming. But when glad Sibyl left her play, And up to his loved bosom climbed, His heart's pulse therewith bounding rhymed; And in his brain upshot a ray Outshining sage Philosophy, And throwing on life's mystery, On th' aim of all creation, Beaming illumination. Like worm that 's sudden felt to crawl On maiden's shining neck, A shudder would appall His soul, and joy's fresh cargo wreck, As when on Sibyl in his arms That threatening shadow fell,— Whether from memory's whispering swarms, Or passing cloud, he could not tell. Along the shore he roamed, So sleepy tranquil now the sea Its greeting to the land not foamed By billows sparkling sunnily. He sought a sea-scooped nook, And sat down on a rock wave-washed By boldest tides, near which a brook Warbled among the stones at times tide-lashed. The little brooklet, hurrying to th' ocean, To Oswald's saddened musings brought Sibyl, with onward tuneful motion Speeding towards womanhood, so fraught With stormful wreck, through those affections sweet That gave to Sibyl's heart its happiest beat. The brooklet's lively monotone, Like children's sprightly prattle, soothed Sad Oswald's spirit, and the moan Of quiet Ocean, as the shore he kissed, Like mother's lullaby through tearful mist, His soul's rough tumult smoothed. In their soft married music he could feel More than an earthly voice, and ere He rose adown his cheek did steal A sweet, repentant tear. As he walked homeward, the familiar view Was unfamiliar: it had grown new. The spiritual is the only sight that sees: It only can the language read, And its deep meaning seize, Written with matter, and can heed Its deeper lessons, those That ceaselessly disclose Wisdom and beauty infinite. A ray brighter than sunbeam's flight Shone from within him, laying bare A hidden life in ocean, earth, and air. About his inmost being was a glow Of love and of good will, that made him know Himself, and feel him strong With a new strength; so, as he moved along, He looked upon the wondrous shore As he had never looked before. As he were hearing music from the spheres, When he approached the cottage door Rang in his changèd ears Sibyl's loved laughter, As she upon the floor, Through love that seemed to waft her Into far womanhood, Played mother to a playful kitten. At sight of the dear child, Conscience was still more deeply smitten. With pressure that was almost wild, Sibyl to his heart he pressed. “Papa, papa, you are crying!” As warm tears filled his eyes, tears blessed Flowing from deeps now first unsealed. About his head, in rapture flying, To an illumined eye would be revealed A jubilant, shining brood Of that bright, infinite, heavenly swarm,— Children of earth-life, now enskyed, Who help us keep our forces nobly warm, That we, too, may one day be glorified. Oswald, so deeply was he moved, Sank weeping on a seat, and, half in fears, Sibyl ran pale to the other whom she loved. To Maude they were a mystery, those tears. Oswald, with a sweet smile, unseen till now, Folded pale Sibyl on his heaving breast, Soothing good Maude with tender words and low, While Sibyl gently sobbed herself to rest. The next day, balmy summer day, Oswald, who had never known an hour's illness, Rose not, but as he lay Listened to the great ocean's stillness: He, whom the sun had never failed to waken And draw forth, lay contented not to rise, Filling Maude, Sibyl, with a new surprise. His earthly life was shaken. Who carries in his brain such true ideal, That when he puts it forth to view, Whether with chisel, pencil, or with pen, It shines for aye a beaming real, Like daily sunrise, ever new, Inspirer, lifter, of true men,— He is a revelator, One trusted with the sacred fire, Seer, prophet, poet, a creator, One who through beauty points us higher. This upward pointing, nowhere is it done With more illuminated finger Than in that lofty poem of Raphaél, ('Mong Dresden's treasures, high alone,) That with angelic spell Ever recalls and makes the vision linger. Before this glowing, painted masterpiece A mourning lady sat, not the first time; In thirty years her movement, figure, face Had ripened into faultless beauty's grace. Some of her pain would cease, When she beheld those heads sublime, The holy Infant and his holy mother: Her grief they could assuage, they could not smother. One day, as will be with a rooted sorrow, Her pangs shot sharper than was wont: Great Grief from cheerfullest things will borrow, To make his pallid cheeks more gaunt. But from the splendent figures came A finer effluence; as she gazed, A feeling that she could not name Sweetened her tears, her soul amazed. Upon their floating throne The child and mother shone As though from inward light Kindled by awful omnipresent might. A gentle touch, and her companion friend Laid in her lap a letter. She knew the hand: to rend, As 't were a spider's fetter, The enclosing folds, and rifle The sheet of all its meaning, Was instant: scarcely could she stifle A shriek of joy, as, leaning On her close friend, she cried, “No more delay! She lives! she lives! Away, away!” The letter ran in broken lines, Drawn from the soul's most secret mines. “Forgive! Forgive! Forgive! How could I live After such act! I robbed thee of thy child! Oh, I was rackt With devils, wild With love and hate! Upon my heart did skeleton fingers grate. Thou gav'st thy hand and heart (Oh no! Thy heart,—that could not be: Thy heart thou hadst given to me!) Unto my foe! What a revenge! I stole Thy babe, believing I had given my soul Some peace! 'T was fiercer war, a darker hell! But for thy child this theft Had been my knell. (Much more than thou was I bereft!) I soon began to love her: threw me Into her angelhood: Out of my damnèd self she drew me. The sun and stars and earth and sea Came back to me and pitied me. Less darkly coursed my blood: Me her light guided, saved: Deep on my heart was her heart graved. I'm teaching her to love thee,—easy part To her so quick, so loving heart. I ceased to hate and fear Myself. Again I shed a tear. Forgive! Forgive! Forgive! Then come: I have not long to live.” The sun was showering his great boon Of light upon the rock-based shore: Such calm was in the summer afternoon, That peaceful sea, how could it ever roar? Oswald lay restless in his bed; Like torches in a cavern glowed His large dark eyes beneath his black-haired head; Life round his features flowed With her inseparable dear comrade, Death, Gently as summer breeze's tenderest breath, That seems each moment just about to cease. He feebly turned his head to listen: The whirl of rapid wheels Made his dark eyes to glisten: Into his ear it peals, Like bells announcing peace. The carriage stops: a gush Of joy and his last tears; Then quick he hears The impatient rush: Then Sibyl cries, half frightened As she is snatched up from the floor, To be smothered in mother's kisses (To him, as her, sweetest of blisses): Then through the open door His long-loved Mary lightened Into his eyes before they died. Mary staggered to the bedside, Sank on her knees, while Sibyl, trembling pale, Fell into Oswald's arms with piteous wail. Oswald, laying his fleshless palm On sobbing Mary's head, “Thou hast forgiven me, Mary,” calm And confident, he said. She raised her vivid eyes to his, and sobbed, “Forgive, Henry, forgive! 't was thou was robbed.” Oswald pressed Sibyl to his breast: “Go to thy mother, Sibyl dear!” The quivering child obeyed without a tear. His head fell back: he was at rest. Maude knelt by the bedside, weeping: Sibyl still in her mother's lap, as she were sleeping: Ocean rolled slow long billows in, and sighed: Mary, who should have been his bride, In raptured awe gazed at his face, Beholding there unearthly gleam,— The beauty of angelic grace, The glow of an ecstatic dream. Through that blest look there breathed a breath Of Love divinely pure instilled: There was no mortal taint of death, But Hope immortally fulfilled.</field>
   </doc>
</add>