<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Fairfield, Sumner Lincoln, 1803-1844</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Fairfield, Sumner Lincoln, 1803-1844</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">fairfield sumner lincoln 1803 1844</field>
      <field name="author_text">Fairfield, Sumner Lincoln, 1803-1844</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1820's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_ap/uvaGenText/tei/chap_AM0734.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240349</field>
      <field name="date_text">1825</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey American Poetry</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:440175</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Mina, a dramatic sketch : with Other Poems</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">American poetry -- 1783-1850</field>
      <field name="subject_text">American poetry -- 1783-1850</field>
      <field name="title_display">Mina, a dramatic sketch : with Other Poems</field>
      <field name="title_facet">mina a dramatic sketch with other poems</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">mina a dramatic sketch with other poems</field>
      <field name="title_text">Mina, a dramatic sketch : with Other Poems</field>
      <field name="year_display">1825</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1825</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1825</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440175&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:440175&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Fairfield, Sumner Lincoln, 1803-1844&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;fairfield sumner lincoln 1803 1844&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Mina, a dramatic sketch : with Other Poems&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;mina, a dramatic sketch with other poems&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1825&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1825&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Fairfield, Sumner Lincoln&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1803&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1844&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Mina, a dramatic sketch : with Other Poems&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Baltimore&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Published by Joseph Robinson&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1825&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3865765-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;cham0734&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;American poetry -- 1783-1850&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1783&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1850&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Mina, a dramatic sketch : with Other Poems&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1996&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1996 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 100 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted ; verse reproduced</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">elsewhere in American Poetry omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-AmPoetry"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To STACY G. POTTS, Esq. MINA, A DRAMATIC SKETCH. PART I. Scene—The Rancho del Venadito, on the hacienda of Tlachiquera, near the city of Guanaxuato, in New Spain. Time—evening and the night succeeding. Mina seated by an open lattice, and Rosario, his page, dimly seen at the extremity of the room. MINA. In this lone mansion of my youthful friend, Don Mariano, will I rest awhile From war's tumultuous turmoil and the rage Of sanguinary horrors, and forget For some brief space, 'mid nature's still repose, The miseries of nations. O thou blest Spirit, Immutable, eternal Liberty! Thy home is on the mountains and thy sons Must toil and bleed to gain thy holy shrine, And break the tyrant's sceptre and bestrew Their gory pathway with the murderous tools Of fiendlike dominance;—their midnight couch Must be the cold damp earth—their bosom friends The full-charged carabine and sheathless brand, And the wild cries of forest animals Or lone responses of tired sentinels, Their broken slumbers' lullaby. The roar Of enfiladed musquetry—the clash Of gleaming sabres, and the shrieks and shouts Of onset, triumph, agony and death, Must be the softest accents that awake The patriot soldier from his tented bed, And break his feverish dreams of distant loves. But, oh! where breathes the base degenerate wretch Who dares not vindicate the holy laws Of all presiding nature, trampled on? Who crouches at the tyrant's beck and does The tyrant's bidding on his suffering peers, Hath lost the privilege of man and sunk Nature below her just prerogative. Where'er one man by conquest or descent Doth lord it o'er his fellows, and usurp Power from the nation, who alone may rule, There let the patriot rise in wrath and hurl The despot to the dust from which he sprung. For thee, O heaven descended goddess! thron'd In man's expanding soul e'en at his birth, The pride, the glory of his being—long And deeply hath my heart in silence bled. Torn from life's best affections—from the love Of mother, kindred, friend—and, more than all, Of her who was the birth-star of my fate— I have devoted my best years to thee: But now awhile I may count back the links Of fortune's cankered chain—and trace the clue Of being through the sufferings and the woes Of ever-varying destiny, till again I may behold in memory's light the scenes Of other days. Alas! ROSA. My lord, did'st call? MINA. No, good Rosario; dastard nature seeks To play the tyrant, and perchance I shrunk A moment from my spirit's dignity. Prisoned in gross material substance oft The heav'n-born soul will droop beneath the weight Of its vast energies, and leave the heart Sole lord of all its powers; but now 't is past, The encroaching weakness.—But thy fragile frame, My little page, unused to war's rude life, And wasting toils and dangers imminent, Claims due repose; for me, since early youth The starred heaven hath been my canopy, The rock or heath my bed; and I have slept Among blood-dripping banners, shattered arms, And corses not yet cold in death, so long That 't is a luxury, unknown for years, To slumber 'neath a roof;—guerilla chiefs Not often find a rancho for the night. Go to thy slumbers, lovely boy! ROSA. My lord, Can I do nought to serve thee—nought to give Relief to thy fatigued and war-worn frame, That may assist thy tranquilizing sleep? Could I but soothe thy spirit into soft Repose or by most fearful venture find An opiate for thy heart, I should indeed Be blest—oh, more than blest, my dearest lord! MINA. Thou art a faithful and sweet boy; but what Canst thou, with all thy tenderness and kind Observance, do to heal a broken heart Or still the torrent of a warlike soul? Canst thou allay the anguish of the past Or kindle hope into fruition?—On Thy youthful brow there hangs the solemn shade Of something ill by-gone; and canst thou pour Balm o'er a bosom robbed of all its joys? Thou well mayst turn away when such a task, Beyond all skill of mortal surgery, Is set before thee. ROSA. Good my lord, didst say Thy heart was robbed of all its former joys? MINA. Ay, thus I said in bitterness; I was So happy once, it poisons all my speech To tell my present sorrows. Wouldst thou know, Rosario, all the pleasures of my youth And all my past enjoyments—go and ask The Alpine solitudes of bold Monreal, The groves that skirt the vallies of Navarre, The cliff-arched grottoes of the Pyrenees, And many a bower of bliss that blossoms yet, And all will tell the tale. But what avails Weak reminiscence? I have wedded war— War for the rights of man, and holy bands Have hallowed my espousals—o'er crossed swords The irrevocable vow hath soared to heaven, And deeds have stamped it with the seal of fate, Unchangeable as Deity! Let the past Sleep in the unfathomed ocean of the soul Amid the wreck of glorious things, till time And chance and change no more have influence O'er man's fresh budding hopes—to blast and wither! But why so sad and pale, Rosario? ROSA. A thought passed o'er my mind, as thou didst speak, And I unwittingly upon my brow Did picture it—but now 't is gone. MINA. It was A thought of gloom: I may reciprocate Thy generous offering now and seek the cause Of sorrow in thy soul; perchance, my fate May teach thee moral warfare with the foes That make the heart their battlefield, while thou Art day by day familiar with the strife That nature's children wage for liberty. Thou well dost know that this my warring life Suits not the feelings of my heart; had Spain Been other than a dungeon of despair, Contending hosts had never known my name. ROSA. I thought, my noble lord, of thy bold deeds Of high emprise, and as I followed on From great to greater—from Marina's walls To San Gregorio, I could but think, Had'st thou in either of thy battles fall'n, How many eyes the story of thy fate Had filled with bitter tears; how many hearts Writhed in deep anguish at thine early doom! MINA. Thanks for thy friendly thought; but why forestall What fortune's chances may too soon achieve? Or why imagine, were I gone, no chief More worthy would be left to wage the war? ROSA. But, Signor, thou ere while didst speak of loves; Their hearts would surely bleed if thou wert gone. MINA. There thou art certain and thou well may'st be. Yes, many would bewail me—many weep And mourn awhile and then resume their smiles; There is but one who never would forget Or cease to sorrow for the daring chief Who fell on foreign strand; but she's afar And dead, perchance—away! thy boding speech Would make a dastard of immortal Mars. Go, bear my best affection to our host, The gallant Mariano, and desire The chief for converse of avail and high Import to meet me here ev'n now; and then, Rosario, seek thy couch and court repose, Drowning thy fancies and thy fears alike. ROSA. Be heaven the guardian of my noble chief! MINA. Amen, my little page! good-night, Rosario! (Exit Rosario.) So he hath gone, poor boy! his gentle heart Owns not the warrior's ardour in the rage And havoc of conflicting elements; But, oh, how often hath he soothed the last Dread moments of the soldier's agonies— Stanched the deep wound, allayed the burning thirst, Composed the bloody pillow, raised the head Delirious with anguish, and with soft Assuasives lulled the fevered pulse! How oft, Bent o'er the gory bed, hath he upheld The blessed crucifix before the eyes Of dying patriots and warmly breathed Their parting orison when o'er them came The shadows of untravelled worlds—the deep Darkness that wraps the spirit in the vale Of cold obliviating death, where yet Chaos maintains its old dominion dire. I fondly love that sad mysterious youth. Until this eve he hath been silent—watched My wants and answered to my wishes ere Articulated; ever by my side, In thoughtful silence he hath glided on, Searching for foes and warning their approach Long ere they came. So much devotion flows From some o'ermantled cause, beyond the grasp Of calculating thought—but I will search— Enter Don Mariano. Friend of my youth, I greet thee well! 't is long Since the wild waves of desolating war Sundered our fortunes, but again we meet The same as in the antique halls and towers Of venerable Saragossa. MARIANO. Ay, the same, Or more, O lion-hearted chief! thy praise Fills every heart that feels for human weal, And every tongue breathes eloquence when thou And thy achievements are the inspiring theme. Eternal glory and undying fame— MINA. Beshrew thy present speech, my noble friend, And cull thy words more carefully. It ne'er Doth appertain to principles of true And genuine liberty thus to o'erween The simplest acts of duty; freedom's sons Should never mimic royal pageantries, Nor deal in adulation, nor indulge In undue forms of reverence to those Whose names are heralded by bugle-horns, The eternal order of revolving worlds Is simple as sublime; let man's applause, When due, be the still look of gratitude! MARIANO. Disclaim, with such high terms and looks sincere, The extorted homage of the world, and thou Might'st reign in every human heart, the lord Of mind—an empire tyrants ne'er enslaved. MINA. Thy pardon, Signor! but I wished to speak Of things essential to the present weal Of myriads. Thou know'st the nature close, Subtle and envious of Torres' soul; How by most guileful artifice he worked My misadventures in the vicinage Of Sombrero; and how, when Linan drew His lines of siege round San Gregorio, And threatened ruin to the coward priest, He violently retained my choicest troops To guard his Reverence; and sent me forth With clowns undisciplined and unobeying, To urge the siege of Guanaxuato. There, First deed of shame that e'er befel me—there Disgrace frowned on my once victorious banner! But I'll not think of that discomfiture, For I would yet preserve my reason clear. Now for thy counsel—thou art wise in war; Abide we here or seek the open plains Of ever-blooming Silao? MARIANO. No foes Can thread yon deep barrancas unbeheld, And none dare force the pass that intervenes Us and Orrantia; therefore danger seems Afar from thee and thy guerilla band For a brief time; thou canst augment thy strength In silence here, and burst upon the foe Again in all thy terrors when he sleeps In lethargy of fancied safe repose. MINA. So be it then; Orrantia I despise Ev'n as the Pyrenean huntsman doth The spectre-haunted hind; 't would better fit The pampered parasites of ruthless power To play the matador, than thus to lead Things human to the war of sacrilege. The dastard cravens dare not wield the brand In manly fight, but steal behind and stab I' the darkness—and if by the sheerest chance They seize a prisoner, straight they bear him on To the camp's centre and display their valour In cruel slaughter of a pinioned man: Mother of God! it is beyond the calm Endurance of my nature to behold Such demons triumph in a nation's wrongs. MARIANO. Heaven speed the day when they shall meet the doom Their cruelties have earned. But, noble chief! Or if thou wilt, good friend! 't is time that thou Should'st woo thy needful rest. MINA. Thou dost not err, For well thou know'st the soldier's wakeful nights. But first I'll post videttes upon yon cliffs To guard contingencies. 'T is ever thus; Our safety must be bought with others' danger, And their's with ours; peace cannot reign below With holy liberty, but men will sigh For dignities beyond the common lot, And spurn the holiest laws, and trample down The highest principles of things to gain The privilege of being cursed by broken hearts With all the bitterness of hopeless woe. MARIANO. When I think o'er thy sufferings and thy deeds, My noble friend, since last we met, I scarce Can reason wonder to belief of fact. MINA. The warrior's course is like the boiling torrent, Roaring and flashing through tumultuous scenes, Till the uncertain fountain disappears. Come, Signor, we will tread the camp of death Again together; 't is perhaps the last Meeting of two oppressed and injured men Whose boyhood passed in words and acts of love. PART II. Scene—A grove in the rear of the Patriot camp, before the Rancho del Venadito. MINA —solus. Since waking thought doth mar my quiet sleep With dreams of horror and strange visionry Of coming ill, 't is fitting that I watch And meditate in silence on the ways Of changeful destiny. There is a gloom Unwonted on my heart; my nature's spirit, Erst active, vigilant and unsubdued By danger in most dread extremity, Doth listen now to fancy's whisperings And the half-uttered oracles of dreams. Dim visionary shapes around me flit Like shadows of futurity, and seem To hold dominion o'er my cowering soul, As 't were their right to tyrannize. Unused Am I to all fantastic visitings Of wild imagination, working on The temporary ills of human life And turning petty woes to agonies. I will disrobe my spirit of the spell Of fancy's wizardry by converse high With things aërial, and so forget These dark presentiments and auguries Of gathering sorrows.—On this lovely grove How softly gleams the waning moon! the leaves Dance in the autumnal night-breeze pure and fresh, And gleam in dewy radiance as they turn Their silken texture to the glimmering light, And breathe such music as the spirits of air And water love to drink; and stillness sleeps Upon the verdured earth and azure heaven, Like holy thoughts of heavenly love within The cloistered vestal's bosom.—But, alas! Man's warring passions blot the fairest scenes Of heaven's creation; and his curst ambition Corrupts and desecrates all human rights And natural prerogatives, till the slave Robes him in panoply of dire revenge, And rushes forth to deeds of wo and death. And thus doth grief turn every lovely sight And sound in heaven and earth to its own mood, Desponding, dark and desolate. The world Wears just the hue the spirit's robed withal, And is not gay or gloomy in itself. His heart is man's world, and as that is full Of joy or sorrow, so doth nature seem Or dark or beautiful. Ah, me! how sad, Whene'er the warrior sinks into the man, Appears this penal planet, where hopes, fears, And loves and agonies forever war! How little know the multitude that hail The conquering chieftain in the pride and pomp And power of victory, and send his name In shouts triumphant o'er the echoing skies— What sorrows in his bosom's inmost core Dwell—silently corroding life away! The most exalted deeds that ever blazed Amid the trophies of immortal fame, Have sprung from woes that sought relief and found Alleviation in the loud uproar And rage and slaughter of embattled armies. Oft from the dun obscurity of life Driven by hopeless passions, men have gone Forth to the spirit-stirring field of blood, And raised proud monuments, on which their names Live 'mid the eternal blazonry of fame, From individual sorrow, when the world Weened all their greatness sprung from purest thoughts, Or patriotic or aspiring. Deep Within the human breast unseen, the seeds Of actions lie; the first growth of our thoughts And feelings none can trace—beneath the veil Of motives undefinable they spring And flourish into being unbeheld; 'Tis only when they shoot up full and strong That their existence is perceptible; And then as they bear fruitage, good or bad, Beholders cultivate or check their growth. Discharging duty, I have blessed myself, And, while absorbed in general misery, Forgot my own. Rosalia's love hath been The exciting cause of my most famous feats In this exterminating war, though power Tyrannic forced me to the battle's shock. But now, amid this moonlight grove, my love! I'll think of thee in silence! Enter Rosario, suddenly. ROSA. O, my lord! MINA. How now, my little page! why thus abroad, Searching me out amid this lonely wood, Not rather using the dear privilege Of undisturbed repose, so seldom granted To any of our troop? ROSA. I could not sleep! My soul was harrowed up by fearful dreams And visions of such dread import, I rose And fled to shield me from their influence To thy forsaken room; but thou wert gone, My lord, and so I wandered forth to seek thee. MINA. Well, my sweet boy! sit down upon this knoll, And tremble not so fearfully—thou wilt Ne'er fail to find in me a guardian friend, Ready to shield thee from worse foes than dreams. ROSA. O, my dear lord—oh, wilt thou never leave me? How thy words gladden my affrighted heart! MINA. Why this emotion?—dost thou doubt my faith? Or think thou hast just cause for gratitude For that protection which each soldier claims From me by right of service 'neath command? ROSA. No—yes—my lord! I thought that thou—indeed I know not what I thought—but I hoped— MINA. What? Thou seem'st in strange bewilderment; but tell The dream that shook thy soul with such affright, And I will be the prophet of thy visions, And from thy fancy's revellings will draw Such sage revealments of approaching joy As shall dilate thy thrilling heart with rapture. ROSA. My dream was vision, and I saw two forms, A youth and maid, reposing in a grove Of flower-wreathed citrons, bordering a bright And beautiful lagoon, and they did seem Each other's heaven, so vividly their eyes Gleamed in their hearts' light, so rapturous fond Was every look, so passionate, and yet Pure was their long communion of delight. How blissful was their being! paradise Could never bless faith's fondest votaries With more ecstatic rapture. They appeared, As thus they sat within that bowering grove, Holding the eloquent converse of the heart, Like two young seraphs who were twins in soul, Whose every thought was melody. I watched The lovers long; and, oh, how happy thus Locked in each other's fond embrace, must be, I said and sighed, those two congenial spirits! That vision fled—the grove, the lake—were gone— The lovers parted. In a distant land Of sky crowned mountains and of ocean streams, I saw the youth, in martial garb arrayed, I' the van of a few high souled soldiers move Undaunted through the phalanxed ranks of foes Unsparing in their power, and like a god, Bear victory upon his morion's plume. I had not long beheld him glorying so When by his side I saw the well-loved maid, In stranger guise and aspect masked, with fond Devotion following the uncertain track Of him—the idol of her love— MINA. Strange dream, Rosario—thy vision is most marvellous. Go on—I hold my heart in deep observance. ROSA. The youthful hero through entangling snares And guileful ambuscades and perils dire Kept on his path of glory, and by love, Stronger than death, upheld 'mid scenes of blood, That agonized her soul, the gentle maid Went on, the unknown companion of the chief; Her sole delight to see him—hear him speak Counsel to rashness—ardour to the weak— Hope to despondency—to traitors death— And watch the serpent wiles of coward foes And blast them yet unformed. O, to be near Her warrior-love and see his generous heart, Unhardened by his wrongs, expand with true Philanthropy e'en to his enemies— 'Twas holier bliss than all his private love! MINA. Thou seem'st, enthusiast, in thy wondrous dream, To have beheld the secret springs of thought And loneliest founts of feeling, well as deeds That silently in wild meanders flow. ROSA. Ay, my good lord—thou dost surmise aright, Such was my vision—but I'll tell thee all. The youth and maid again each other knew, And loved as in the springtime of their hearts, Though changing years had passed; but as I watched Fondly once more their mutual loves, I saw A serpent wreathe his intertwisted folds Around them as they sat, and strain his coil Envenomed to its utmost dreadful power; I heard their shrieks—their dying sobs—I heard The sundering of their crushed and broken frames! —My spirit fainted in its agony, And, struggling in my terror, I awoke And flew to thee, my own dear lord, for help. MINA. A story of romance clothed in a dream! Methinks, howe'er, thy maid was passing bold Thus to adventure in the ranks of war. ROSA. How could I stay in peace—enjoying all The sweet delights of life save love, when thou Wert borne upon the hurricane of war, With none but mercenary hands to serve Thy wants or soothe thy sufferings! How— MINA. Hark! Rosario, heard'st thou that appalling shout? ROSA. I heard a hollow sound, my lord, as 't were Voices commingled with the tramp of steeds; Perchance, 't was but the gaunt wolf's midnight cry Or wandering tread of trooping chargers— MINA. Hark! Again! 't is some nocturnal fray—'t is base Orrantia ambuscading round our camp— The royal robber—the vindictive fiend Who riots in the brave man's agonies. We are betrayed by Torres—he did swear Revenge when I denied his right to sack And burn an unoffending pueblo—ah! He hath not yet forgotten our duello In earlier days, regarding Garza's child, The beautiful Rosalia. Let him come Within the compass of my Toledo, And he and treachery will part for ever. Away, Rosario! loose thy hold—I'll go And smite the midnight bandit to the dust. Dost hear me, boy? begone!—there—hark, again! By heaven! thou well maintain'st thy hold—but thus I free me! Now— ROSA. O Xavier, Xavier, stay! Rosalia bids thee stay! MINA. Rosalia! ROSA. Yes! Have this wan brow—these pale and hollow cheeks No traces left of her thou once did'st love, And oft hast named this melancholy night? Hath my voice lost by use of foreign tones Its well-known notes? O Xavier, look not thus Wildly in doubt upon thine own—own love! Say—dost thou know me now? MINA. O my sweet love! Let my heart speak in throbs of eloquence The holiest affection of my soul, Since words are vain to give my feelings meaning! ROSA. Thou wilt not leave me, Xavier?—no, 't is not In thy kind nature to forsake me now. Come, sit upon this velvet-tufted lawn, And I will tell thee all my wanderings And chance escapes and wondrous masquerades, In such a garb of speech as shall light up Thy face with smiles even if hot briny tears Were gushing from thy eyes. Come, dear love, come! MINA. Not now, Rosalia! Thou art more to me Than aught, save honour, 'neath yon holy dome! But slaughter rages—midnight massacre Shrieks for the avenger. Hark! the deadly clash Of sabres reeking with hearts' blood; the cries Of leaguer'd patriots echoing through the sky, And summoning their chief! I must be gone. O dearest love—thou fondest, truest, best! Let me from thy last looks endearing draw Valour invincible to stem the shock Of merciless Orrantia—courage such As only they can feel who war for right Eternal and unchangeable, linked with love Whose light irradiates eternity. Rosalia, be this kiss—and this—and this— Pledge of my love, my honour and my faith. Farewell! detain me not—I must be gone— Farewell! till victory weaves thy bridal wreath. Exit. ROSA. —sola. Alas!—and why alas? Hath he not gone To prove his fond devotion to my love By strict fulfilment of his duty, faith, And spotless honour? O, I love him more The less he heeds my womanhood of soul When glory tears him from my arms! From heaven Angels look down on nothing that so much Assimilates material things to pure Intelligences, as when man surmounts His selfish nature and in duty's cause Scorns low indulgence of his own desire. I would again encounter all the toils And sufferings and perils I have past Since last I saw the mountains of Navarre, To witness such a hero in the best And holiest cause that ever sanctioned war, As that dear youth, who spurns the encroaching power Of private feeling at the warning voice Of liberty—the life of life—the soul Of soul to man below. And yet, ah, yet A dread hangs o'er my heart—an omen dire Shadows my spirit that I ne'er shall see The conquering chieftain in his pride again. —Jesu Maria! what a yell of death! On the still air of night come screams and shouts And shrieks of agony and trumpet blasts, And short, quick orisons and curses fell, And notes of loud command and rallying cries, And thunder of dread musquetry, and groans Dreadful—commingled in one horrid mass Of rending sound! Amid yon glaring fires Of death, dark forms are grappling in the mad Struggle of desperation; there they tug And strain and stab and wield the clotted brand, Horseman to horseman in the latest strife That either foe will wage: and there—oh, there Upon his coal-black steed, through fire and smoke, O'er dead and dying, Mina hurtles on Mid bristling lances, bayonets and brands, Like the death-angel, while the Vive el Rey, Where'er he moves, becomes the loud, the wild, The joyful Viva la Republica! Ah, he hath vanished from my wondering eye On his career of victory, but still His voice in louder tones above the noise And din of battle like a clarion rings. I'll look no more—my hero-love will come Soon from the field of glory and receive His own loved maid. I see an armed band Approaching now like victors and their plumes Wave in the morning twilight as they come Careering on, like harbingers of good Tidings to me—O Xavier! they are here. Enter Don Pedro Negrette and soldiers. PEDRO. A delicate warrior, by the mass! no doubt The sage of sages in the council-hall Of conquering Mina! Art thou well prepared To hail the victor from his glorious field Of slaughter, and to chant triumphal songs In honour of his name, O prophet-boy? Guards! seize the rebel youth and onward wend To Don Francisco's central camp, where soon The wisdom of the beardless wizard will be shown And proved—if in his art abides the power To avert his master's or his own sure fate. ROSA. O Virgin Mother! have my fears come true? Is Mina vanquished? May the eternal ban Of heaven rest on the traitor Torres! PEDRO. Ha! Thou art a very prophet, but thy curse Falls harmless on the corse of Padre Torres. ROSA. O jubilate! Mina is avenged! His own tried sabre clove the traitor's brain! PEDRO. Prophet again! thou soon wilt know the art Of ruling traitors—onward to the camp! PART III. Scene—The camp of Don Francisco de Orrantia, the royal commander. Don Xavier Mina and Officers, prisoners, pinioned and manacled. FRANCISCO. So, Traitor! justice claims its own at last! Audacious rebel to the best of kings! In what close-woven mail of hardihood Could'st thou infold thy conscious soul to dare The vengeance due to most abandoned guilt, Thou renegado robber? When we laid With righteous arm thy base assassin horde I' th' dust beneath our conquering chargers' hoofs, And thou alone fled'st from our dreadful might, Did never vain repentance of thy crimes Torture and madden thee? Did'st never feel How impotent was all thy wrath and rage Against the anointed monarch of the Lord? Answer, bold rebel! ere the stroke of fate Fall like a thunderbolt upon thy head! MINA. That I do answer suits my own desire To tell thee what thou art—not thy command. First to thy charge—I glory in a name Which countless heroes by their blood have hallowed; The wreathing incense of the eucharist Is not more holy than the deeds of him Who toils and bleeds and welcomes perils dire That he may disenthral the sons of God From murderous tyranny. Next thy quest— My panoply through all this war hath been An unstained spirit, resolute and free— An uncorrupted heart that throbbed with love To God and man, and longed to see mankind, Unfettered by the tyrant's shackles, soar To that proud station guaranteed by heaven When first the sun burst on their infant eyes. And next, thou tool of power! thy boastful vaunt— Shall such as thou of war and victory prate? Or boast of battles? 'Twere enough to call The Cid from his long slumbers in the tomb To hear thee talk of prowess! I have seen Thee and thy thousands scattering like a flock Of vultures when I sent El Giro forth With one poor score of Creole peasantry, Armed scarcely with a lance! Reserve thy vaunts Orrantia, till thy mercenary troops, Confiding in the might of multitudes, Do that thou would'st not dare to do ev'n now, Chained as I am!—Ay, writhe and foam and stamp, Thou guilty coward! Wear thy haughtiest looks And prate of bloodiest battles as thou wilt, But, by the rood! the veriest boor that e'er Battled beneath my banner's crimson shade, Would with the flashing of a carbine fright Thy soul into annihilation. Now I've done with thee for ever, and with those Who sent thee forth to massacre and burn. I dare thee to the compass of thy power! Death hath too long been my companion—now To dread the shadows of another world. For one score years and five I have desired To do what laws or human or divine Enjoined in justice; if I've erred and sinned In passion's heat, the account remains with Him Who made me—not with thee nor thy dread king. Now take my dying words—and note them well— Thy sovereign is a tyrant—Spain a den Of slaves, to madness driven by fiends like thee, Who batten on a dying nation's blood. FRAN. There is my answer to thy rebel speech. (Strikes him.) MINA. Inglorious wretch! is this Castilian honour? Enter Don Alva Argensola, mariscal de campo. ALVA. It ill befits a son of Spain, my lord, Idly to look upon a deed so far Beneath Hispania's martial character As stroke of sabre on a pinioned man, And he a prisoner. FRAN. Keep thy counsel, sage! And leave my presence! ALVA. When it suits my will. I quail not at thy frown, proud chief! I hold Authority from higher powers than thee. FRAN. Leave me or ere I speak again, proud rebel! Else— ALVA. Rebel—ha!—Don Pedro! (Enter Pedro.) PEDRO. Well, my lord! ALVA , (aside.) The youthful prisoner thou just hast seized Bear thou in most observant courtesy To yonder holy convent dimly seen Of San Lorenzo; place thy tender charge Safe in its holy walls—then point thy march With all my powers toward Victoria's camp, Boquilla's citadel. I'll meet thee there. See it be done anon. PEDRO. I shall, my lord! (Exit. FRAN. What meant thy silent converse? ALVA. Honour. FRAN. Ha! Brief as the Spartan—bold as guilt; beware! ALVA. I shall beware of those who dare o'erstep Humanity's prerogatives and laws Of nations; threats from him, howe'er, who knows No better using of his sword than on A fettered captive, weigh not much with me. I wait thy orders, be they such as man Can execute. FRAN. Retire and call the guard! (Exit Alva. Now, Xavier Mina, for thy treason death Instant awaits thee! Padre Buenventura Will shrive thee of thy crimes as priests are wont, Then righteous justice will exact its own; Save that thou wilt accept Fernando's good Indulto and thy troops array beneath The royal standard.—Hear'st thou mercy's voice? MINA. I hear the voice of cowardice and shame; I hear a voice that trembles at its own Commands; the voice of him who dreads the sound Of death; of him whose bones will lie i' th' sun Bleaching or ere my corse is cold, if yet A patriot breathes in this ensanguined land. Re-enter Don Alva and guard. FRAN. Take yon base traitor outward of the camp Fronting the convent and despatch him there. ALVA. Hath he been sentenced by the laws to die? FRAN. Dar'st thou discourse on my commands? My will Is law not subject to appeal. ALVA. With slaves It may be—not with me. All men have rights Sworn to them by society when first They enter on the world, and all may claim Their native privilege; none can deny Their just demand except by forfeiture Of their own safety. Be the peril thine, If the Count Mina fall unheard, unjudged, Before his country's stern tribunal! FRAN. And mine it shall be!—and the peril thine To answer bold infraction of the laws Of war, ere yonder sun's last crimson beams Fade from the western horizon. Away! Bear on the traitor to the field of fate— The pleasure's mine to certify his death. (Exeunt [To the arena before the convent; a stake in the midst to which Mina is bound—soldiers preparing for execution. Francisco approaches with a blinding cap; and at the same time a shriek is heard from the convent, and Rosalia is seen at a grated window, gazing wildly on the scene below.] MINA. Away! I've looked on death too long to fear What man can do; no mortal power shall cloud My eye till expiration's shadows dim Its fire; it shall not close upon the earth Until it flashes on eternity. What shriek was that? ha!—soldiers—'t is the last And only wish I e'er shall speak—be sure Your aim err not—and let your signal be My last word—Now! (They fire—he falls.) ROSA. O God! O God! he's dead! FRAN. So perish traitors! Take ye careful note That life be utterly extinct, and word All your averments with perspicuous art— Then leave the unhallowed corse for vultures' food. And make ye close inquest whence came that shriek Of horror, and from whomsoe'er it came, Straight bring the rebel to my camp.—And now For potent Alva. (Exit. FIRST SOL. Comrade, is he dead? SEC. SOL. Ay, the great chief hath gone! My trembling heart Knocked 'gainst my ribs as 't would have rung a knell For the great hero; how he stood and looked And spake the death-word! Dost thou think our chief Would dare a score of carbines so? FIRST SOL. Canst tell Where is Don Alva? SEC. SOL. In the patriot camp Of Count Victoria ere this hour of doom. FIRST SOL. Will follow, comrades? ALL. Alva is our chief! SEC. SOL. Lift then the hero's corse within the walls Of holy San Lorenzo, where due rites Will hallow the great warrior's burial; Then follow on Don Alva's way and make Report through all the land that Mina lives, Devoted still to liberty and vengeance! (Exeunt. ROSA. (Embracing the body of Mina, surrounded by the sisterhood and monks.) Ah, he hath gone!—the great, the lovely one, Even in his pride of fame! The voice that spake Victory to nations in their glorious strife For freedom—and to me in softest tones Most holy love—is hushed for ever more! His early hopes of quiet happiness— Life's sweet affections and domestic joys, In youth he quitted to subserve the cause Of those who bled for freedom; long he warred For liberty not his own—long he bore Unmurmuring all the perils and the wants Of march, encampment, siege and battle—what Hath been the hero's recompense? His good Deeds and pure thoughts all turned against himself! O world! base world! thou changest at a breath Virtue to vice, heroes to fiends, and heaven to hell. The Holy One was scoffed and buffetted And mocked and beat and crucified! To Him Who was a Man of Sorrows while he dwelt Incarnate, and, O Holy Virgin! unto thee, In penance for the past, do I devote My melancholy days; and here in lone Seclusion o'er thy grave, my warrior-love! I will revere thy memory, howe'er Traduced and vilified by wicked men; Thy name shall be the theme of all my thoughts, The spell-word of my orisons; for long As high heroic deeds and virtues, pure As snow in upper air, shall claim regard, The wise, the great, the good of humankind Will chant the praises of the gallant Mina! Ye holy men! now bear the glorious chief To his last resting-place beneath yon lines Of cypresses and near his tomb I'll rest From all the feverish passions of the world, Its cares, its sorrows and its calumnies, With you, O holy virgins! From your shrine My penitential prayers shall rise what time The midnight tapers burn, and holy spirits Delighted hover o'er the perfumed altar! And, when the soul disrobes itself of clay, With sacred rites and high observances, Ye will my body lay not far from his Who loved and fought and bled and died in vain! INVOCATION. O thou bright Spirit! thou whose power is o'er The poet's all-creating thought, whate'er Thy unknown nature be, or like the air Impalpable, the essence of a soul, Star-winged and eagle-eyed, or human shape Lone dwelling amid silent solitudes, Nymph, muse or oread, Olympic-born, Unseen and shrined in mystery;—where'er The glory of thy beauty beams, among The ancient woods of thy proud dwelling-place, Parnassus, or the fair Ægean isles, Or o'er the haunted stream of Helicon, Gushing mid flowers that skirt its holy banks, To great Apollo sacred and the nine; Or mid the blue arcades of yonder sky Where Dian walks in brightness and the stars Stud ministering spirits' pathway thick and fair As bright-eyed daisies gem the mead;—whate'er Thou art and wheresoe'er thy presence dwells— O come, fair Spirit! come in all thy charms And bring elysium to a suffering heart! In childhood's hours—lone, visionary, wild, Silent and solitary, while yet the sum Of my heart's pulses could be reckoned—thou Wert my devotion and I loved to drink The incense of thine altar, and imbibe Thy spiritual breathings, and I felt my soul Dilate with rapture when upon me came A mighty awe and reverend majesty, A passion purified, a godlike power, Which brought the universe within my grasp, And made high seraphim my ministers. And now I would become thy worshipper, True and devoted, though too full of sin And mortal stains for thy immortal smiles, Undimmed by gross materiality. But, Holy Spirit! I have been the child Of sorrow, and my sole delight for years Of melancholy memories hath been Thy lofty service; oh, thou oft hast taught My heart forgetfulness of grief and pain And obloquy and scorn and poverty, And all the nameless ills and wrongs that wear With endless iteration life away. And I have gloried in thee when the world, The brutal world mocked thee with taunt and sneer, And one quick passing, visionary hour, Past in thy high communion, when the stars Were my companions and the moon my bride, Hath been more precious to my soul than all The pageantries of pride and show of art. When cares have come upon me, and the woes Of life grew darker on my tearful eye, And hate and envy blackened my good name, And the stern voice of strife assailed my ear Blended with demon shouts, and I beheld No friend among my unrelenting foes;— When in the invisible night, alone— Silence and solitude around—my heart Hath bled and my soul sunk into despair, I've turned to thee and found in thy sweet smile A paradise, beyond the reach of worms, Whose venom hath all qualities of hell Save power to give it action; there I've dwelt In loneliness and bliss, far from the noise And din of the world's warring, wholly blest In thy etherealizing look of love! Oh, then descend, great Spirit! on me now And light my bosom with empyreal fires! Spring with her flowers and verdure and gay birds, Soft-voiced and musical, and bright-blue skies, And calm, transparent waters, smiles around, And as I speak to thee, the silvering moon Lights the green-foliaged hills that gently slope Down to yon lovely bay, and on my brow Shines like a mother's eye upon her child, First-born, most loved; and from the lilac flowers, Purple and fragrant, and the aspen trees Fresh leaving, and the dark green dewy grass, The susurrating airs, sweet-scented, come Upon me, like the memory of youth. Sure thou wilt come on such a night as this, Spirit of Poesy! and from thy wings Scatter the perfume of the skies on earth; Thou wilt descend from thine aërial home, And teach thy son, (unworthy all, but true,) Knowledge of unseen worlds, and guide aright The searchings of his too adventurous thought, Free from the wiles and snares of disbelief, Or sceptic question;—thou wilt mark his path And note its errings manifold; thy smile Will light his way, and thus he may advance Onward to heaven in peace, unenvying all The gaudy state and circumstance of man. So thou wilt prove his minister of joy And change the poisoned waters of fierce strife And hate and envy into springs of love; And when the portal of the skies expands Before me, and death rends these bands of clay, Thou, Holy Spirit! wilt await my steps, And welcome home the wandering child of God! SONNET. Born in convulsions, nursed in grief and pain, And doomed in childhood to endure the spite Of hate long hoarded—earth had no delight For me in all her ways of mirth—no strain To soothe my heart; no charm to chain my sight; No spell of pleasure and no hope of gain; But all was bleak and dreary as the reign Of scowling winter, robed in endless night; Yet I have seen the world and known it well— Its hopes, fears, follies, crimes—and I have been The brother of affliction, and each scene Of fate, though varied, still was miserable; But I have learned to know myself and bow Humbly to Him, who doth my sorrows know. SONNET. The man who feels the majesty of Mind, And the omnipotence of Intellect, But little recks of vulgar disrespect And all the railings of a world unkind; They pass him by e'en as the winter wind Passes the towering ever-verdant pine, Howling but harmless;—from the affluent mine Of his proud spirit, by still care refined, Issue ethereal riches—worthier far Than if his earlier thoughts had wrought him fame, And all had wreathed with fragrant flowers his name; Triumphing thus o'er folly's fools, his star Gathers new glory and his soul new powers, Until he revels in Fame's heavenly bowers. THE EVENING STAR. Ere lingering sunlight leaves the western sky And mellow tintings mingle with the gloom, The crescent gilds the soft blue arch on high, With beams that seem in upper air to bloom, And down the cope of heaven afar, A world of beauty, bliss and love, Gleams brightly forth the Evening Star, The loveliest light of all the host above. Cold searching science may the spheres explore, And yon vast systems learnedly unfold, But, wrapt in beauty's charms, I scorn the lore, And lightly all such withering knowledge hold; When fancy revels in the skies, And rose-wreathed bowers are breathing balm, O who would know the mysteries Of heaven—and all the glorious scene uncharm? Let man, lone habitant of this dark sphere, Deem you bright orbs the starry halls of love, Where souls congenial meet that sorrowed here, And through elysian groves in rapture rove! Rend not away the magic veil That brightens beauties seen afar; Belie not fancy's fairy tale, That sees a paradise in every star! Thou Evening Star! o'er yon blue mountain sinking, Thy radiant beams along the white clouds burn, And, as I gaze, my wandering soul is thinking Of past delights that never can return; Thou art a friend beloved, and long I've told my sorrows all to thee, For I, a feeling son of song, Have been the sport of wayward destiny. Oft on the hill-top 'mid embowering woods I sit when night relieves my heart from care, And nothing sensual on my soul intrudes, As in the world's rude strife and day-light's glare, And watch thy light, sweet Evening Star! And think how dear a home thou art, Shrined in the ethereal sky afar, To the sad spirit and the suffering heart. Well have the wild-souled bards of Yemen deemed Thine orb the dwelling of the great and good, Where Indra's glory hath for ever beamed Since from the skies rolled Ganges' holy flood, And 'mid the Swerga's hallowed bowers Dwelt suras pure and glendoveers, Happy as heaven's own living flowers, Unchanging as the lapse of endless years. There pure ones dwell, for ever blest—and there Chant songs, whose music sometimes steals away, And faintly floats along the moonlight air, Like the low warblings of a seraph's lay; Around the holy shrine they throng In sacred groups, while soft perfume Waves in the breath of glowing song, And soars to God, like spirits from the tomb. Now in the budding springtime of the year Young hearts will blossom in the smiles of love, And soul-lit eyes, gem of the starry sphere! Delight in thee;—lone wandering through the grove Where fanning airs 'mid green leaves play, Lovers entranced gaze on thy beams, And paint a paradise far away Of groves and flowers and birds and murmuring streams. And, oh, how lovely are their visions! Light Descends from heaven on love's first blissful dream, And on the heart falls all that meets the sight In rainbow hues with ever-varying gleam. If e'er on earth we can define The joys that prophets tell of heaven, 'Tis when young hearts in love divine Blend like the blue and purple hues of even. But love is madness in a world like this— It smiles to agonize—it charms to slay! Demons watch o'er earth's holiest scenes of bliss, And laugh at sorrow nothing can allay. Fame, knowledge, wealth and pride and power, And love and joy are all in vain; They live and bloom one little hour, Then fade like Evening's Star and sink to pain. THE SON OF GENIUS. 'T was summer evening and the fair blue sky In rosy beauty hung o'er land and sea, And to the poet's visionary eye Burned with light gushing from eternity; The soft, sweet airs of heaven breathed o'er his brow As he gazed on the lovely scene below His solitary chamber—rich and bright, And watched the mellowing shadows as they fell O'er flowery vales and green isles robed in light, Till darkness dimmed the scenes he loved so well. But vainly beauty smiles when the heart bleeds In silent, untold agony of wo; Nought of fair forms the withering spirit heeds— All sight and sound is mockery; grief doth grow Deeper and wilder amid joy and mirth, And sorrow veils this bright and lovely earth In darkness and in dreariness—and all Seems cold and hollow in the ways of men; And the dark spirit wears a living pall Of deathless death—it cannot smile again. Oh! who can tell how hard it is to wear A mirthful look that hides a broken heart? How deep and desolate is that despair, Which sickly smiles of forced delight impart? 'Tis awful misery to seem in joy; Smiles on the lip—tears in the wandering eye; Hope on the brow—despair within the soul! Oh, why to man are all earth's sorrows given— The thousand woes that mock at man's control, But from earth's griefs to turn his thoughts to heaven? The bright creations of his soaring thought Had from the young bard passed away, and now He wept o'er all his mighty mind had wrought; And his heart's darkness gloom'd along his brow, And fearful forms appeared and bade him look Upon their ghastly horrors—and he took The terrors of their wild and withering eyes E'en to his bosom's core, and o'er him came That hollowness of sufferance which tries The spirit more than rack or bickering flame. He saw not—heard not—thought not of the crowd That passed him joyously on either hand; His spirit writhed within a shuddering shroud, And o'er him Genius waved his magic wand. (Genius! bright child of heaven—a god of earth! Despair and Death for ever give thee birth; Thou angel heir whose heritage is pain! Whose rapture, anguish and all countless woes; Whose only joy is sorrow's mournful strain— Whose only hope this being's early close!) Earth's charms availed not; sadness in him grew Darker and deeper till it sunk in gloom; Time o'er his bosom poured its deadly dew, And Death called on him from the yawning tomb— Stretched forth his skeleton arm and beckoned on The suffering soul whose meteor course was done— Rising in glory and the pride of fame, Soaring in beauty on its starry way, Then bursting o'er the ruin of a name— The glorious vision of a stormy day! There was no beauty in this world to him— No charm, no hope, no comfort, and he felt Power from his spirit, vigour from each limb, Life from his heart, departing; and he knelt In lone devotion to his God and prayed That Fate's dread arrow might not be delayed, And yet not pierce his bosom unprepared! “Father! thou knowest all my thoughts and deeds, The woes I've borne alone—the woes I've shared— And thou wilt purify the heart that bleeds.” But nothing can from human hearts expel The fear of death—it is not weal nor wo, That withers up the spirit, heaven nor hell; It is that awful void—that gulf below All reach of thought—that boundless depth of gloom Which hangs for ever o'er the oblivious tomb; No eye can span it and no thought unfold— Hopes, fears and passions and all human powers Perish before the mystery untold, Searching in vain for Eden's holy bowers. And death to him had terrors—oh, it had Terrors for thee, almighty Son of God! Oft callous, fears are felt not by the bad At the dread voice that summons to the sod; The doubtfulness of good that virtue feels Oft o'er the heart in withering anguish steals, And clouds the closing hour of sinless life With fears that hardened guilt denies; for, oh, Goodness doth question its own worth, though rife With all that hallows earth's intensest wo. The mournful bard—life's best affections gone, Its kindly charities and hopes of fame, Mused darkly on the ways of fate alone— Continual sorrows and a blasted name, Till in the pale light of his bosom's shrine Appeared a form majestic and divine; Mysterious greatness gleamed along his brow— His air breathed awe—his voice was like the sea's; His eye illumed all nature in its glow— And thus he spake the spirit's mysteries:— “Son of the Skies! thou, who dost oft commune With the ethereal stars when sleep locks up Life's founts of bitterness in night's still noon; Thou wilt not always drink this poison cup Of wretchedness allotted thee below; Thou wilt not always wear upon thy brow The visible torture of thy bleeding heart; Thy sunken cheek and hollow eye will yet Smile ere thy spirit from the world depart, And coming hours shall teach thee to forget. “Thy toil hath been for greatness and for fame, And thou hast panted in the poisoned air Of hate and envy to achieve a name For the fool's mockery; and thought and care, And vigilant observance and much pain, And watchings long thou could'st not bear again, Have been rewarded by a damning curse— The spleen of bastard wit and envy's gall; And low, base foes, whom fiends could make no worse, Have shouted o'er the ruins of thy fall. “One look of thine could blast them into death, But, mid the locust plague, thine eye would tire Of slaying, and the poison of their breath Taint and obscure thy spirit's holy fire. Pass o'er them—stoop not to their scope—'t is vain To battle with the fitchew; canst thou reign And banquet on thy proud and just applause Without the envenomed chalice, that will bear Death to thy vitals? In a lofty cause The world will crown thee with thy heart's despair. “But should'st thou bask in glory's fairest light, Canst thou make league with death to sound thy praise? Or hope to hear amid sepulchral night The voice of fame that charmed thy mortal days? Can mouldering dust resume its form again, Or thy soul hover o'er this realm of pain To drink the incense of a crowd, whose breath, Ere an hour wings its unreturning flight, May fan the cold, unearthly brow of death, And all their memories sink to endless night? “No! glory unbeheld is grief and shame— The spirit's power is wasted upon dust; Virtue and goodness never lead to fame, Nor breathing pictures of the wise and just. Fiends love not what they cannot falsify, And there are fiends who never dwelt on high. Let Genius dip his pencil in the gloom, That o'er man's heart comes from the depths of hell— Ages will weep above his laurelled tomb, And immortality his triumphs swell. “Yet thou must soar; immortal spirits wear Robes coloured in the skies—they cannot rest Mid earth's cold multitudes; the holy air Near heaven they breathe, and are supremely blest When, the false world and all its woes forgot, They feel their own divinity; thy lot, Lowly with men, is holy and sublime With angels and winged glories at the hour Of inspiration, when thy soul can climb Heaven's gate and hail each spirit in his bower. “Less for the world's applause, more for thy own, Howe'er, in humble consciousness of all The gifts of God, toil thou till crowns are won Of virtue and of glory; see thou fall Not from the principles of goodness given To all earth's sons by kind, indulgent heaven! Despair not of thy meed! though dark the hour Of disappointment, put the armour on Of faith and perseverance, and thy power Will strengthen still when centuries have gone.” Ceased the deep voice—the ideal phantom fled; But left that comfort which reflection gives To virtue in affliction;—well 't were said, He lives to glory who to goodness lives. O'er the young bard new freshened feelings rise, And thoughts of beauty beaming from the skies, And gay hope, like a sunbow, round his heart Glitters and colours every feeling there, And as his dark and dreary thoughts depart, He feels,—while heaven awaits, let none despair! THE PROPHET'S MALISON. And Elijah, the Tishbite, who was of the inhabitants of Gilead, said unto Ahab—As the Lord God of Israel liveth, before whom I stand, there shall not be dew nor rain these years but according to my word.— I. Kings, xvii. 1. The apostate king of Israel's holy land Was revelling in Samaria's idol bowers, And round him danced and sung a harlot band To soothe remorseful sin's long lingering hours;— The fair Zidonian wandered through the grove, The heathen queen of lawless faith and love. There Ahab lay, with pomp pavilioned round, Couches of gold and gorgeous canopies, And wanton harps of most melodious sound, And robes that wore the rainbow's mingled dies;— There nothing lacked of his luxurious show Save God's approval as he looked below. There wreathing flowers hung breathing rich perfume, And fragrant fruit of every form and name, And radiant beauty in voluptuous bloom To Ahab's bower, a willing victim, came; Not unobserved by Zidon's daughter, who Plunged him in crime and gloried in the view. Yet oft amid the music and the mirth His dark brow quivered and his eye grew wild; Forms passed before him not of mortal birth, And gleamed along his brain, and darkly smiled With that prophetic look which probes and sears The heart, and in a moment does the work of years. Beneath the glory of his gorgeous show A viper preyed upon his heart, and none, Save his false queen, could soothe the awful wo Of him who groaned—a slave upon a throne! She o'er him held the power of crime and he Bowed shuddering to her bloody sovereignty. Israel's grey fathers by the wayside stood Communing mournfully on other days, And oft they saw the awful sign of blood Shoot o'er the wrathful sky its fiery rays; And then they looked toward the groves of Baal And shrieked to see the warning portent fail. But save to eyes of faith no sign appeared, And Ahab revelled on in deadlier guilt, Nor Syrian king nor slaughtering angel feared; And by his side she lay whose hand had spilt The blood of God's high prophets and profaned The temple where His visible presence reigned. And each had sinned till heaven could bear no more, And mid their wildest riot, most profane, A tall, majestic shadow stood before Their blasted eyes—now downcast all in vain; The sable garb—the hoary beard—the tread, Solemn as death, shook Ahab's soul with dread. For well he knew the prophet of the Lord, And awfully he feared to meet him there, Amid those idol groves and bowers abhorred; And his heart quailed in horror and despair When with uplifted eyes and hands outspread, The Seer of God his awful message said:— “Hear, rebel king! and thou, false heathen, hear! Thus saith the Lord and thus it shall be done; Oft o'er this land shall pass the death-winged year Beneath the scorchings of the cloudless sun; Nor rain, nor dew, nor vapour shall assuage The burning heat in its wide-wasting rage. “All streams shall vanish and all fountains dry, And still the mighty sun shall burn and burn, Till stiffening lips can frame no dying cry— Till withered hearts to cracking masses turn— And chords and sinews cleave unto the bone, And the flesh shrink and harden into stone. “Groves, gardens, vineyards—all green things shall fail, And desolation reign o'er all the land; Proud men—fair women, choaking, ghastly pale, In vain shall struggle with impotent hand To end their agonies;—all earth shall lie Blackening in barrenness 'neath a burning sky. “The lips shall feel no moisture in the breath— E'en on the corse the famished worm shall die, And death go slaughtering o'er the wreck of death, Amid the still, unutterable agony; The babe shall die—to the hot bosom pressed— Pressing its withered lips unto its mother's breast. “The prince and beggar, and the lord and slave, Shall writhe and agonize and gasp for breath And perish side by side—and one wide grave, The lake's exhausted gurge, shall hold them; Death Shall ride victorious, mid low girgling moans, To slaughter o'er a nation's skeletons. “Amid the thick, intolerable glare A dull, dead sound shall murmur evermore, And flocks and herds pant in the sweltering air And lie down in the channel that before Held many waters, and devour the sand That yet is moist. And Israel's sons shall stand “Gazing until their eyes weep blood upon Creation's fiery furnace to behold The beauty of a cloud—there shall be none! No more the shepherd need to watch his fold, No more the vintager his vines—no more The merchant hail his vessel from the shore. “Yon holy mountains from their cloudy height Shall waft no breezes to the burning vale, But savage beasts shall yell in wild affright From rock and cave till sense and motion fail, And the black leafless forests mourn and sigh Between the dying earth and all-destroying sky. “Then thou, proud king! e'en in this idol grove Amid thy host of deities shalt feel The wrath of an offended God, and prove His penal might; here thou wilt pray and kneel E'en in the house of Baal—his house of crime— And weary heaven for mercy in that time. “But vainly shalt thou ask it—all as vain As God did long beseech thee to return And live—thou would'st not hearken then—again Thou shalt not hear his voice! o'er thee shall burn, And thy idolaters, his fiercest ire Till Israel's sins are purified by fire. “All earth shall blacken in a sea of flame Till years have rolled their desolating way— Till God restores the glory of the name That Israel bore beneath his holy sway; Thus saith the Lord! Prepare to meet thy doom! For vengeance o'er the idolatrous land will come!” The prophet vanished from the monarch's eye, Who stood there, chained by agonizing fear; His dark form towering on the crimson sky— His voice still ringing in the false king's ear. In waves of purple flame sunk the hot sun— The years of wrath and terror have begun. TO LUZELLE. If your soul were in my soul's stead, I would not blame but weep with thee, And every hope and pleasure fled Should be revived by sympathy; I could not smile amid thy tears, Nor feel a joy when wo was thine— But thou canst mock my darkest fears, And laugh at sorrow when 't is mine. Illusion may uphold belief That this false world is kind and true, And thou may'st smile at withering grief Who never felt its deadly dew; And I can bear thy wildest mirth, Though my cold heart entombs the dead— But dark would seem this joyous earth, If your soul were in my soul's stead. Time was when life looked gay and bright, And this world full of bowers of love; When sunny day and starry night Below smiled as they smile above; Then grief was but a strange, sad name, And mournful looks the theme of jest— Then hope was bliss, and love was fame, And but to breathe was to be blest. But now—my eye hath lost its fire, My soul its mirth, my heart its bloom, And all that's left me is my lyre, And a stern pride, dark as the tomb; Yet I can bear thy laugh and mirth, And blame thee not, though hope hath fled— For darker yet would seem this earth, If your soul were in my soul's stead! RHIGAS. [The first of modern Grecian worthies, who invoked and concentrated those thunders of vengeance which have since burst over the empire of Turkey in Greece. He fell by treachery, in May, 1798.] From Thessaly's woods a voice goes forth, A voice of wrath o'er the groaning earth, And the ancient hills, as it sounds along, Wail back the cry of a nation's wrong, And the Ægean Isles with a shout reply To the far-heard trump of victory. Olympus stoops to hear The voice of patriot power, And the gods of Greece appear In this dark and fearful hour. Men stand erect in their pride again, And grasp the sabre, that long hath lain, Like the soul of Greece, in the sloth and rust Of dead despair—and they shake the dust Of slavery from their banners proud, And swear they shall be their shield or shroud; The deep wild voice of wrath wails on, And Œta bows as it hurries by, And as it sweeps o'er Marathon, The dead send up an awful cry. That voice thrills through the hearts of men, Like lightning through a tomb—the glen, The vale, the hill, and the holy wood Return it back like an ocean flood, And the Priestess lights her Delphic shrine, And o'er it bends with a look divine; And helm and brand and spear In the altar's blazing glare, And the warrior dead come near, In the solemn guise of prayer. The beacon-lights of the brave around Blaze to the sky o'er the holy ground, And warrior-forms in their armour gleam, Like the giant shapes of a troubled dream; With lances in rest, and swords in hand, As the Grecians stood, the Grecians stand. The Turk is slumbering by In his garb of blood and death— A nation's victor cry Is hanging on a breath! 'Mid the pillared ruin's hollow gloom, Bursting in wrath from the sleepless tomb, In his hauberk each and his belted brand, The dead arise in their stern command; They long have groan'd in a restless trance, But they hear the voice, and seize the lance, And put their terrors on— And they throng around the brave, And chant high glories gone In the deep voice of the grave. A glorious shape is passing by, With a brow of gloom and a lowering eye— His casque is severed—his banner torn— His sabre broken, and his look forlorn! Like a warrior's ghost in the lightning's light, He stands before that altar bright. The voice of wrath is still, And the beacon-fires are dim, And o'er each midnight hill Is heard a funeral hymn. “Dark the Danube, but darker far The blood on the Turkish scymetar! Dark the Danube, and deep its wave! But darker and deeper Rhigas' grave! The mighty waters flow lonely on, But they bear the corse of Grecia's son! Not Passwan Oglou's power, Nor the shield of night could save— Death is the patriot's dower— His freedom is the grave!” Then thrice the warriors uttered “wo!” And thrice waved their sabres to and fro, And vanished then with a hollow groan, And the Priestess stood by her shrine alone. The fire burned dim, but it burned on still, When again there came from Ida's hill The wild low hymn of death; But in wrath and grief it came, And the listener held his breath, And called on Jesu's name. “Slaves to the Moslem! victory's lords! To the dust again bequeath your swords? No—they shall gleam in carnage yet 'Mid the deep death-thirst of the bayonet! The corse of Rhigas floats on the wave, But his spirit sleeps not in the grave. Let a nation's battle-cry Ring on the free-born air! Let groans ascend the sky— The hero dwells not there!” The voice of wrath is high and loud, And the Great of Greece are stern and proud, And the beacon-fires are lighted now On the sea's wild wave and the mountain's brow, And the sword gleams red on Marathon, And a strong arm shakes the Ott'man throne! In the Grecian army's van, 'Mid havoc, death and flame, Careers a god-like man— His war-word, Rhigas' name! SONNET. Syren, Farewell! perchance, a last Farewell! Thy victim votary loves alike and fears Thy potent spell, thy bay-wreath gemmed with tears; Thine eye and voice, that bid the bosom swell; Thy charms, thy woes, no mortal tongue may tell; Beauty that maddens, and despair that sears, The spirit glowing in its youth of years, Throned in its heaven of thought o'er yawning hell! Lonely and dark have been my youthful days; Burdened with poverty, and woes, and lies, And all to me beneath the watchful skies, Have been untrue, save Him I ever praise; Then fare thee well, O Syren of the heart! My hope in Heaven will never more depart.</field>
   </doc>
</add>