<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Chase, Henry</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Chase, Henry</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">chase henry</field>
      <field name="author_text">Chase, Henry</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1850's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2003_Q4/uvaBook/tei/z000000001.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240341</field>
      <field name="date_text">1856</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:32310</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The North and the South ; a statistical view of the condition of the free and slave states</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">United States</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">United States -- Statistics</field>
      <field name="subject_text">United States</field>
      <field name="subject_text">United States -- Statistics</field>
      <field name="title_display">The North and the South ; a statistical view of the condition of the free and slave states</field>
      <field name="title_facet">north and the south</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">north and the south</field>
      <field name="title_text">The North and the South ; a statistical view of the condition of the free and slave states</field>
      <field name="year_display">1856</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1856</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1856</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:32310&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:32310&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Chase, Henry&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;chase henry&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The North and the South ; a statistical view of the condition of the free and slave states&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;north and the south&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1856&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1856&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chase, Henry&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="contributor" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Sanborn, C.H., (Charles Henry)&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1822&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1899&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The North and the South :&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;a statistical view of the condition of the free and slave states&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Boston&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;New York&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;J.P. Jewett and Company&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Sheldon, Blakeman, and Company&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1856&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="LC call number"&gt;E431 .C48&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa call number"&gt;E431 .C48 1856&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;980570-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;l04005025&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;vi, [7]-134 p. ; 19 cm.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;United States&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;United States -- Statistics&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covplace&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;United States&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covplace&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covplace&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;United States.&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covplace&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The North and the South&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Statistical View of the Condition of the Free and Slave States&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2003&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2003 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 413 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PREFACE. It is the object of this work to compare the condition of the slaveholding and non-slaveholding States—the North and the South—as to territory, population, industry and wealth, education and intelligence, religion and moral advancement, and general progress. The authorities used are the official documents of the General Government and of the individual States. The calculations are, for the most part, for the year 1850, and based on the census returns for that year, as compiled by J. D. B. De Bow, and published in his Compendium of the Seventh Census. This work, prepared with much labor, is the only one of the kind within our knowledge. We think there is public necessity for it, and submit it without further remark. Concord, Mass., September, 1856</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INTRODUCTORY. The slaveholding States, fifteen in number, including the semislave States of Delaware and Maryland, have an area of eight hundred and fifty-one thousand, four hundred and forty-eight square miles. In latitude, they extend from 25° to 40° north, and, in longitude, from 75° to 107° west. This vast empire of nearly a thousand miles square has a sea and gulf coast of seven thousand miles in extent, and is drained by more than fifty navigable rivers. Through its centre flows the longest river of the globe, with its thousands of miles of navigable waters. The free States, sixteen in number, have an area of six hundred and twelve thousand five hundred and ninety-seven square miles. Exclusive of California, they extend, in latitude, from 37° to 47° north, and, in longitude, from 67° to 97° west. With California, they constitute a territory of nearly eight hundred miles square, with two thousand miles of Atlantic seacoast. A dozen navigable rivers flow from this territory to the Atlantic, two of them finding a passage to the sea through the far-extending bays of the slave States. By the great lakes and their outlets, its northern products find their natural channel to the ocean—ice-bound for several months in the year —through the territory of a foreign power; while, borne on the Mississippi for more than a thousand miles through the domain of slavery, its western products seek a passage to the ocean by the Gulf of Mexico. While the rivers of the slave States are never closed to navigation by the rigors of climate, those of the free States are closed by ice during the winter months of each year. In climate, the slave States excel, and in soil equal, the free. Certain productions, moreover, of great importance are mostly confined, by the laws of temperature, to the slave States. Among these are cotton, cane-sugar, rice, and tobacco. Thus, for agriculture, the slave States have a fertile soil, a climate adapted to the productions of tropical and temperate latitudes; for manufactures, are exhaustless motive power distributed throughout its whole extent, with the raw materials of cotton, wool, iron, lumber, etc., abundant and readily accessible, while coal, salt, and other precious metals are found in several of these States; for internal commerce, numerous rivers drain the whole territory; for external commerce, thousands of miles of sea and gulf coast with excellent harbors. The rigorous climate of all, and the sterile soil of some of the free States, render them less fitted for agriculture than the slave States, while the transportation of the raw material affects the success of manufacturers. For the purposes of commerce, the North has a moderate extent of seacoast and several good harbors, whose remoteness, however, from the producing and consuming regions affect disadvantageously the interests of trade. The great lakes, when not closed by ice, furnish good facilities for internal commerce. In the origin of their population and the date of their settlement, the North and the South are pretty nearly alike. Geographically, it will be seen that the old and new free States are nearly separated by the projection of Canada and northern Virginia, while the Pacific State of California is separated from the other free States by two thousand miles of unsettled country. The slave States, old and new, on the other hand, lie in a compact body. Resulting from these different geographical positions were the facts that the emigration from the older free States must seek, by extended and circuitous routes, a passage to the new; while the emigration from the slave States had only to cross a border line, of a thousand miles in extent, to find itself at once on its new territory.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE NORTH AND THE SOUTH. CHAPTER I. TERRITORY. As the basis for future comparisons, in this work, the following table is introduced, showing the area of the several States, together with that of the two great sections, the North and the South: TABLE I. Showing the Area of the Slave and the Free States. SLAVE STATES. Area in Sq. Miles. FREE STATES. Area in Sq. Miles. Alabama 50,722 California 155,980 Arkansas 52,198 Connecticut 4,674 Delaware 2,120 Illinois 55,405 Florida 59,268 Indiana 33,809 Georgia 58,000 Iowa 50,914 Kentucky 37,680 Maine 31,766 Louisiana 41,255 Massachusetts 7,800 Maryland 11,124 Michigan 56,243 Mississippi 47,156 New Hampshire 9,280 Missouri 67,380 New York 47,000 North Carolina 50,704 New Jersey 8,320 South Carolina 29,385 Ohio 39,964 Tennessee 45,600 Pennsylvania 46,000 Texas 237,504 Rhode Island 1,306 Virginia 61,352 Vermont 10,212 Wisconsin 53,924 Total 851,448 Total 612,597 It will be seen by the above table that the area of the fifteen slaveholding States is 851,448 square miles; and that of the sixteen non-slaveholding States 612,597 square miles; a difference of more than 238,000 square miles in favor of the Slave States.* * The estimates here made are according to the Compendium of the United States Census. In the Quarto Edition the area of Texas is given as 325,520 square miles; which would make the area of the Slave States nearly 100,000 square miles more than here given. Let it be remembered, therefore, that the area of the Free States is considerably less than three-fourths that of the Slave States. By the purchase of Louisiana, in 1803, and of Florida, in 1819, were added to the national domain 966,479 square miles; an area greater than the entire area of the United States at the time of gaining their independence.† † See Compendium United States Census, p. 32. By the annexation of Texas, in 1846, were added 318,000 miles more, and by a treaty with Mexico at the close of the war, 522,955 square miles; making an aggregate of 1,807,434 square miles. This, of course, is exclusive of the 308,052 square miles to which our title was "confirmed" by treaty with Great Britain in 1846. The expense of these purchases and conquests cannot be exactly determined. The territory of Louisiana, purchased of France, cost $15,000,000; that of Florida, purchased of Spain, $5,000,000; amount paid Texas, about $27,000,000; expenses of Mexican war, $217,175,575; paid for New Mexico, by treaty, $15,000,000. Making an aggregate of more than $270,000,000, which, together with interest on the same, the expense of the Florida war, about $100,000,000, and nearly the same amount paid for the extinguishment of Indian titles, etc., etc., make a sum, little if any short of $1,000,000,000. The manner in which this territory has been apportioned to the two sections is given by Mr. Clay, in his speech in the Senate in 1850. (See Appendix to Congress. Globe, vol. 22, part 1, page 126.) He says: "What have been the territorial acquisitions made by this country, and to what interests have they conduced? Florida, where slavery exists, has been introduced. All the most valuable parts of Louisiana have also added to the extent and consideration of the slaveholding portion of the Union." ...."All Louisiana, with the exception of what lies north of 36° 30′;"...."All Texas, all the territories which have been acquired by the Government of the United States during sixty years of the operation of that Government, have been slave territories —theatres of slavery—with the exception I have mentioned lying north of the line of 36° 30′." California has since been admitted a Free State. The other States, formed from territory thus obtained, and admitted into the Union, are Louisiana, Missouri, Arkansas, Florida, and Texas—five Slave States. The area of California is 155,980 square miles; that of the five Slave States named, 457,605; being 302,625 square miles more, and very nearly in the ratio of three to one. Indeed, the area of these five purchased Slave States is greater than that of all the Free States, if we except California. It will be seen by tables VII and VIII, that the number of Representatives in Congress from California is two, which, together with two Senators, entitle that State to four electoral votes. The number of Representatives from the five Slave States is sixteen, which, together with ten Senators, make twenty-six electoral votes, being in the ratio of six and one-third to one, and a majority of twenty-two. There is (of territory inhabited and uninhabited) north of the old Missouri Compromise line an area of 1,970,077 square miles, and 966,089 south of it. It will be noticed, in passing, that the area of Virginia is not quite four thousand miles less than that of all New England, and is larger than that entire section if we except Connecticut. It is also larger than the four States of New York, Massachusetts, Connecticut, and Rhode Island. Maryland contains over three thousand square miles more than Massachusetts, and is considerably larger than either New Hampshire or Vermont; Pennsylvania and New York are each smaller than either North Carolina, Mississippi, Georgia, Arkansas, or Alabama; while Ohio and Indiana are still smaller. Ohio has but two thousand two hundred and eighty-four square miles more than Kentucky, to which it is very similar in surface, soil, and productions. South Carolina is almost four times as large as Massachusetts, and three-fourths as large as Ohio.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER II. POPULATION. The following tables give the aggregate population of the several states in 1790, 1820, and 1850. (For a table showing the population at each decennial census, see Appendix.) In connection with this are also here given, the area, the number of inhabitants to a square mile in 1850, and the population at the present time, the last being taken from a late communication to Congress by the Secretary of the Treasury: TABLE II. Statement of the Area, and Aggregate Population in 1790, 1820, 1850, and 1856, with the Number of Inhabitants to a Square mile, in 1850, of the several Slave States. SLAVE STATES. Area in Sq. Miles. Population in 1790. Population in 1820. Population in 1850. Density in 1850. Population in 1856 Alabama 50,722 127,901 771,623 15.21 835,192 Arkansas 52,198 14,273 209,897 4.02 253,117 Delaware 2,120 59,096 72,749 91,532 43.18 97,295 Florida 59,268 87,445 1.48 110,725 Georgia 58,000 82,548 340,987 906,185 15.62 935,090 Kentucky 37,680 73,077 564,317 982,405 26.07 1,086,587 Louisiana 41,255 319,728 153,407 517,762 12.55 600,387 Maryland 11,124 407,350 583,034 52.41 639,580 Mississippi 47,156 75,448 606,326 12.86 671,649 Missouri 67,380 66,586 682,044 10.12 831,215 North Carolina 50,704 393,751 638,829 869,039 17.14 921,852 South Carolina 29,385 249,073 502,741 668,507 22.75 705,661 Tennessee 45,600 35,791 422,813 1,002,717 21.99 1,092,470 Texas 237,504 212,592 0.89 500,000 Virginia 61,352 748,308 1,065,379 1,421,661 23.17 1,512,593 Total 851,448 1,961,372 4,452,780 9,612,769 11.28 10,793,413 TABLE III. Statement of the Area, and Aggregate Population in 1790, 1820, 1850, and 1856, with the Number of Inhabitants to a Square Mile, in 1850, of the several Free States. FREE STATES. Area in Sq. Miles. Population in 1790. Population in 1820. Population in 1850. Density in 1850. Population in 1856. California 155,980 92,597 .59 335,000 Connecticut 4,674 238,141 275,202 370,792 79.33 401,292 Illinois 55,405 55,211 851,470 15.37 1,242,917 Indiana 33,809 147,178 988,416 29.24 1,149,606 Iowa 50,914 192,214 3.78 325,014 Maine 31,766 96,540 298,335 583,169 18.36 623,862 Massachusetts 7,800 378,717 523,287 994,514 127.50 1,133,123 Michigan 56,243 8,896 397,654 7.07 509,374 New Hamps'ire 9,280 141,899 244,161 317,976 34.26 324,701 New York 47,000 340,120 1,372,812 3,097,394 65.90 3,470,059 New Jersey 8,320 184,139 277,575 489,555 58.84 569,499 Ohio 39,964 581,434 1,980,329 49.55 2,215,750 Pennsylvania 46,000 434,373 1,049,458 2,311,786 50.26 2,542,960 Rhode Island 1,306 69,110 83,059 147,545 112.97 166,927 Vermont 10,212 85,416 235,764 314,120 30.76 325,206 Wisconsin 53,924 305,391 5.66 552,109 Total 612,597 1,968,455 5,152,372 13,434,922 21.93 15,887,399 From these tables it will be seen that, in 1790, the population in the present non-slaveholding States was 1,968,455; and in the present slaveholding States, 1,961,372; showing a difference of 7,083 in favor of the non-slaveholding States. This difference, at first so slight, only 7,000, we find constantly increasing, until in 1820 (thirty years from that time) it becomes 699,592; the population of the slaveholding States being at that time 4,452,780, and that of the non-slaveholding States 5,152,372. In thirty years more (1850), the population of the fifteen Slave States is 9,612,769, and of the sixteen Free States 13,434,922; a difference of 3,822,153 in favor of the Free States. Thus, from having a majority of less than four-tenths of one per cent in 1790, the Free States had in 1850 a majority of more than thirty-nine per cent. And this, notwithstanding 87,000 inhabitants were added to the Slave States by the annexation of Louisiana and Florida, and a large population by the annexation of Texas. The average number of inhabitants to a square mile, in the Slave States, is 11.28, and in the Free States 21.93; almost exactly two to one. On examining this table a little in detail, we notice the following, among many other interesting facts: The area of Virginia is 61,352 miles; that of New York is 47,000, or over 14,000 square miles less than that of Virginia. The population of Virginia, in 1790, was 748,308, and in 1850 it was 1,421,661. It had not doubled in sixty years. The population of New York in 1790 was 340,120, in 1850 it was 3,097,394; thus, New York had multiplied her population more than nine times in the same period. Kentucky has an area of 37,680 square miles, and Ohio 39,964, a little over two thousand miles greater. Kentucky had in 1850 a population of 982,405, and Ohio 1,980,329, or nearly a million more than Kentucky. Kentucky was admitted into the Union in 1792, and Ohio in 1802. The area of Mississippi is 47,156 square miles, that of Pennsylvania, 46,000. The population of Mississippi was, in 1850 (in round numbers), 606,000, that of Pennsylvania, 2,300,000. The number of inhabitants to a square mile in North Carolina was, in 1850, a little over seventeen, and in New Hampshire thirty-four; in Tennessee twenty-one, and in Ohio forty-nine; in South Carolina twenty-two, and in Massachusetts one hundred and twenty-seven. These comparisons are based upon the population as it was in 1850. The tables likewise show the present population, as given in a recent communication to Congress, by the Secretary of the Treasury. By this it will be seen that the ratio of increase still continues; there being now a majority of 5,093,986 or over forty-seven per cent, in favor of the Free States According to the same ratio, in less than three years more than two-thirds of the entire population of the Union will be found in the Free States. The entire white population of the two sections, at each decennial census, from 1790 to 1850, is as follows (for a statement of white population at each census, see Appendix): Slaveholding States. Non-slaveholding States. In 1790 1,271,488 In 1790 1,900,976 1800 1,692,914 1800 2,601,509 1810 2,192,706 1810 3,653,219 1820 2,808,946 1820 5,030,377 1830 3,633,195 1830 6,871,302 1840 4,601,873 1840 9,557,065 1850 6,184,477 1850 13,238,670 The difference of increase here may perhaps seem more remarkable than in the aggregate population. The white population of the present Slave States was, in 1790, 1,271,448, and of the present non-slaveholding States, at the same time, 1,900,976, a difference of 629,488; not quite fifty per cent. in favor of the non-slaveholding states. In 1850 that difference had become 7,054,193, or over one hundred and fourteen per cent. In other words, the white population in the Free States had become 869,716 more than double that in the Slave States. The population of the latter being 6,184,477, and that of the former 13,238,670. How far this difference, both of population and its increase, in the two sections, is due to foreign immigration, may be seen from the following statement (Census Compendium, p. 45): "There are now 726,450 persons living in slaveholding States, who are natives of non-slaveholding States, and 232,112 persons living in non-slaveholding States, who are natives of slaveholding States. There are 1,866,397 persons of foreign birth in the non-slaveholding States, and 378,205 in the slaveholding." There are then 494,338 more natives of non-slaveholding States in slaveholding States, than there are of slaveholding in the non-slaveholding States; while there are 1,488,192 more persons of foreign birth in the non-slaveholding than in the slaveholding States; which gives less than a million more persons residing in non-slaveholding States, who were not born there, than in the slaveholding States, nearly all of whom are white inhabitants. The difference is nearly 4,000,000 in the aggregate, and more than 7,000,000 in the white population, and is not therefore due to this cause. The following tables show the white population of the several States in 1790, 1820, and 1850: TABLE IV. White Population of the Slave States in 1790, 1820, and 1850. SLAVE STATES. 1790. 1820. 1850. Alabama 85,451 426,514 Arkansas 12,579 162,189 Delaware 46,310 55,282 71,169 Florida 47,203 Georgia 52,886 189,566 521,572 Kentucky 61,133 434,644 761,413 Louisana 73,383 255,491 Maryland 208,649 260,223 417,943 Mississippi 42,176 295,718 Missouri 55,988 592,004 North Carolina 288,204 419,200 553,028 South Carolina 140,178 237,440 274,563 Tennessee 32,013 339,927 756,836 Texas 154,034 Virginia 442,115 603,087 894,800 Total 1,271,488 2,808,946 6,184,477 TABLE V White Population of the Free States in 1790, 1820, and 1850. FREE STATES. 1790 1820 1850 California 91,635 Connecticut 232,581 267,161 363,099 Illinois 53,788 846,034 Indiana 145,758 977,154 Iowa 191,881 Maine 96,002 297,340 581,813 Massachusetts 373,254 516,419 985,450 Michigan 8,591 395,071 New Hampshire 141,111 243,236 317,456 New Jersey 169,954 257,409 465,509 New York 314,142 1,332,744 3,048,325 Ohio 576,572 1,955,050 Pennsylvania 424,099 1,017,094 2,258,160 Rhode Island 64,689 79,413 143,875 Vermont 85,144 234,846 313,402 Wisconsin 304,756 Total 1,900,976 5,030,377 13,238,670 The whole number of slaveholders in the Slave States, in 1850, was 346,048; and of this number 173,204 hold less than five slaves each, leaving 172,844 who are holders of more than four slaves; and, if we deduct the numbers holding less than ten slaves each, there will remain 92,215. The whole number of slaveholders, then, is less than 350,000, including females and minors. The number of voters in this class is therefore much smaller. But, counting them all as voters, they are less than the number of freemen who voted at the last Presidential election in New England, even without including Vermont. They are less than the number who voted in either Pennsylvania or Ohio, and less than two-thirds the number who voted in New York. The annexed table shows the free colored population of the United States. It will be seen that the number of free colored inhabitants in the Free States is 196,016, and in the Slave States 228,128, mingled with a white population of less than half that of the Free States. This, of course, does not include the District of Columbia, in which there are over 10,000 free colored persons; while the number in the Free States includes those in New Jersey, in which there are over 23,000, of whom 20,000 were born in the State. Indeed, if we examine the table giving the nativities of the free colored persons, we shall see that the number who still reside in the States where they were born is 354,470, out of the whole number, 454,495, which is over eighty-one per cent. On page 81 of the Census Compendium, in connection with a table showing the occupation of the free colored males over fifteen years of age, it is stated that in New York city there is one in fifty-five engaged in pursuits requiring education; while in New Orleans one in eleven is engaged in similar pursuits. In Connecticut, one in a hundred is thus employed, and in Louisiana one in twelve. These are the only cities and States compared in this way in the Census. It may be a fact a little surprising to some, that, while the ratio of the free colored inhabitants engaged in pursuits requiring education in Louisiana is one-twelfth of the whole, the ratio of the entire white male population engaged in the pursuits in the same State is less than one-eighteenth of the whole. The increase in the present slaveholding States, from 1840 to 1850, is 10.49 per cent., and in the non-slaveholding States 14.98 per cent.; being four and a half per cent. greater in the Free than in the Slave States. The proportion of free colored persons to the total population, in some of the States, is quite considerable; being greatest in Maryland and Delaware,— in the former twelve, and in the latter nineteen per cent. Had we not the example of De Bow's Compendium, we might be uncertain how to regard the slaves, whether as men, TABLE VI. Free Colored Population of the United States in the years 1790, 1820, 1850 SLAVE STATES. 1790 1820 1850 FREE STATES. 1790 1820 1850 Alabama 571 2,265 California 962 Arkansas 59 608 Connecticut 2,801 7,844 7,693 Delaware 3,899 12,958 18,073 Illinois 457 5,436 Florida 932 Indiana 1,230 11,262 Georgia 398 2,931 Iowa 333 Kentucky 114 2,759 10,011 Maine 538 929 1,356 Louisiana 10,476 17,462 Massachusetts 5,463 6,740 9,064 Maryland 8,043 39,730 74,723 Michigan 174 2,583 Mississippi 458 930 New Hampshire 630 786 520 Missouri 347 2,618 New Jersey 2,762 12,460 23,810 North Carolina 4,975 14,612 27,463 New York 4,654 29,279 49,069 South Carolina 1,801 6,826 8,960 Ohio 4,723 25,279 Tennessee 361 2,727 6,422 Pennsylvania 6,537 30,202 53,626 Texas 397 Rhode Island 3,469 3,554 3,670 Virginia 12,766 36,889 54,333 Vermont 255 903 718 Wisconsin 635 Total 32,357 128,412 228,128 Total 27,109 99,281 196,016 to be enumerated as so many inhabitants, or as so much property, estimated at so much per head; or, taking a middle course, to consider them three-fifths intelligent man, and two-fifths unintelligent property; thus realizing what was anciently but a fabulous monster, the Centaur, having the head of a man and the body of a horse. These three plans are all adopted in the Census Compendium. The number of slaves in the present slaveholding States was as follows: In 1790 657,527 " 1800 853,851 " 1810 1,158,459 " 1820 1,512,553 " 1830 2,001,610 " 1840 2,481,632 " 1850 3,200,304 From this it will be seen that there has been a constant increase, until there were, in 1850, over three millions; being almost one-third of the entire population of the Slave States,— more than double the population of either Norway or Denmark, —greater than that of Netherlands, Switzerland, Scotland, or Sweden,—and not quite three hundred thousand less than that of Portugal. Some very interesting facts may be gathered from the census tables with regard to this class. If we examine, for instance, the table with regard to the "Increase and Decrease per cent. of the Slave Population of the several States at each census" (see Appendix), we shall see, what is indeed remarked in the Census Compendium, that "the increase of slaves in the southern Atlantic States has only averaged about two per cent per annum in fifty years, though averaging eighteen per cent per annum in the Gulf States, etc., for the last twenty years." Thus, in South Carolina this increase diminished from thirty-six per cent in 1790 to seventeen per cent in 1850; and, indeed, in 1840 it was but three per cent. In North Carolina it is about the same. In Maryland, from an increase it has become a decrease, and that, too, at a rapid rate. In Virginia the ratio of increase has diminished from seventeen to five per cent, and generally the ratio of increase has been of late less than that of the white population. In the Gulf States, on the other hand, the increase has in many instances been immense, and much more rapid than that of the white population. The cause of this is given by those who have the best opportunity to know the facts, as follows: Hon. Henry Clay of Kentucky, in a speech, in 1829, before the Colonization Society, says: "It is believed that nowhere in the farming portion of the United States would slave labor be generally employed, if the proprietors were not tempted to raise slaves by the high price of the southern markets, which keeps it up in his own." Professor Dew, once President of William and Mary College in Virginia, in his review of the debates in the Virginia Legis lature in 1831–2, says: "From all the information we can obtain, we have no hesitation in saying that upwards of six thousand [slaves] are yearly exported [from Virginia] to other States." Again: "A full equivalent being thus left in the place of the slave, this emigration becomes an advantage to the State, and does not check the black population as much as, at first view, we might imagine; because it furnishes every inducement to the master to attend to the negroes, to encourage breeding, and to cause the greatest number possible to be raised. *  * Virginia is, in fact, a negro-raising State for other States." The extent of this domestic slave trade is not given in De Bow's census tables, but we may, by an easy computation from the tables, arrive at something near the truth, so far as they are reliable in such matters. On page 87 of the Compendium, we find the decennial increase of Slaves in the United States to be as follows: between 1790 and 1800, 27.9; between 1800 and 1810, 33.4; between 1810 and 1820, 29.1; between 1820 and 1830, 30.6; between 1830 and 1840, 23.8. The average of these ratios is 28.96. In 1840, the slave-exporting States, Delaware, Maryland, Virginia, North and South Carolina, Kentucky, and Tennessee, contained 1,479,601 slaves. Had they increased in the ratio of 28.96 per cent., the number in 1850 would have been 1,908,093. The actual number given is 1,689,158, being a difference of 218,935, or 21,893 for each year, to be accounted for. Applying the same rule to the slave-importing states, we have the following result: Georgia, Florida, Alabama, Louisiana, Mississippi, Arkansas, and Missouri contained in 1840 1,002,031 slaves. Increasing in the ratio of 28.96 per cent, their number in 1850 would have been 1,292,219. The number given in the census is 1,453,035; a difference the other way of 160,816, or 16,081 per year, which they had received by importation. The difference of nearly 6,000 between the import and export may be accounted for by the following: A writer in the New Orleans Argus, in 1830, says: "The loss by death in bringing slaves from a northern climate, which our planters are under the necessity of doing, is not less than twenty-five per cent." And the planters in those States, when advertising for sale a plantation and a lot of negroes, always mention distinctly the fact that they are "acclimated" (if that be the case), as enhancing their value. The number which the figures would seem to indicate as sold from the North to the South is no doubt very low; it certainly is so, if we take the estimate of Southern men. The Virginia Times, in 1836, estimates the number of slaves exported for sale during a single year at forty thousand. In 1837, a committee was appointed, by the citizens of Mobile, to investigate the causes of the existing pecuniary pressure. In their report they say: "So large has been the return of slave labor, that purchases by Alabama of that species of property from other States, since 1833, have amounted to ten millions of dollars annually." Rev. Dr. Graham, of Fayetteville, North Carolina, said in 1837: "There were nearly seven thousand slaves offered in New Orleans market last winter. From Virginia alone, six thousand were annually sent to the South; and from Virginia and North Carolina there had gone to the South, in the last twenty years, three hundred thousand slaves." Mr. Gholson, of Virginia, in a speech in the Legislature of that State, January 18, 1831, says: "It has always (perhaps erroneously) been considered, by steady and old-fashioned people, that the owner of land had a reasonable right to its annual profits; the owner of orchards to their annual fruits; the owners of brood mares to their product; and the owners of female slaves to their increase. We have not the fine-spun intelligence nor legal acumen to discover the technical distinctions drawn by some gentlemen. The legal maxim of partus sequitur ventrem is coeval with the existence of the right of property itself, and is founded in wisdom and justice. It is on the justice and inviolability of this maxim that the master forgoes the service of the female slave, has her nursed and attended during the period of her gestation, and raises the helpless infant offspring. The value of the property justifies the expense, and I do not hesitate to say that in its increase consists much of our wealth." The following, copied from a recent number of the Richmond Dispatch, will show the present condition of the trade: "High Price For Slaves.—There has been a greater demand for slaves in this city, during the months of May, June and July, than ever known before, and they have commanded better prices during that time. The latter is an unusual thing, as the summer months are generally the dullest in the year for that description of property. Prime field hands (women) will now bring from $1,000 to $1,100, and men from $1,250 to $1,500. Not long since, a likely negro girl sold in this city, at private sale, for $1,700. A large number of negroes are bought on speculation, and probably there is not less than $1,000,000 in town, now, seeking investure in such property." From the above, and similar sources of information, we may safely estimate the number of slaves annually sold from the Northern Slave States to the Southern at 25,000. An interesting feature of this traffic will appear on examination of the Census Table, showing the "ratio of ages of the slaves in 1850."* * See Census Compend., pp. 89–90. In the States of Maryland, Virginia, North Carolina, and South Carolina, the average number of slaves between twenty and thirty years of age is 16.72 per cent. In the States of Georgia, Alabama, Mississippi, and Florida, Arkansas, Louisiana, and Texas, the number between the same ages is 19.29 per cent. In like manner, in the four first-mentioned States the average number between thirty and forty years of age is 10.27 per cent, and in the seven last mentioned it is 11.94 per cent. On the other hand, the number between sixty and seventy years of age is, in the four exporting States, 2.76 per cent, and in the seven importing States, 1.94 per cent; also, between seventy and eighty years old, the number is, in the first four 1.16, and in the others but .55 per cent. Showing that in the slave-importing States the number of slaves between twenty and forty years of age is at least fifteen per cent greater than in the exporting; while, on the other hand, in the slave-exporting States, the number of slaves between sixty and eighty years of age is more than fifty per cent greater than in the importing. This is the more remarkable, since exactly the reverse is true of the free colored population in those same States, as will be seen by a similar analysis of the table on page 75 of the Compendium. Another fact with regard to the slave population of the South, and one which must soon become of great interest, is the increasing ratio of the slave to the free population. By a table on the 85th page of the Compendium* * See Appendix. it will be seen that, in the words of the Census Report, "while the proportion has been increasing for the slaves in the Southern States generally, it has decreased in Virginia, Maryland, the District of Columbia, and Missouri." Indeed, it has increased in most, until it has become in Arkansas (omitting fractions), 22 per cent; in Alabama and Florida 44 per cent; in Louisiana 47 per cent; in Mississippi 51 per cent; and in South Carolina 57 per cent of the whole population; whereas it was, in 1800 in Mississippi but 39 per cent, and in South Carolina but 42 per cent; and a similar increase of the ratio of the slave to the entire population will be found in all the Southern Slave States.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER III. POPULAR REPRESENTATION. The following tables present the subject of Popular Representation in a very plain and simple manner, showing the white population, free colored, and total free population, and the popular vote cast in 1852. They also show the number of representatives in Congress, and the electoral votes, both as they now are and as they would be were freemen only represented. TABLE VII. Political View of the Slave States. Slave States. White Population. Free Colored Population. Total Free Population. Popular Vote cast in 1852. Representation in Congress. Representation were not Slaves represented. Electoral Vote as it now is. Electoral Vote were not Slaves represented. Alabama 426,514 2,265 428,779 41,919 7 5 9 7 Arkansas 162,189 608 162,797 19,577 2 2 4 4 Delaware 71,169 18,073 89,242 12,673 1 1 3 3 Florida 47,203 932 48,135 7,193 1 1 3 3 Georgia 521,572 2,931 524,503 51,365 8 6 10 8 Kentucky 761,413 10,011 771,424 111,139 10 9 12 11 Louisiana 255,491 17,462 272,953 35,902 4 3 6 5 Maryland 417,943 74,723 492,666 75,153 6 6 8 8 Mississippi 295,718 930 296,648 44,424 5 3 7 5 Missouri 592,004 2,618 594,622 65,586 7 7 9 9 North Carolina 553,028 27,463 580,491 78,861 8 7 10 9 South Carolina 274,563 8,960 283,523 6 3 8 5 Tennessee 756,836 6,422 763,258 115,916 10 9 12 11 Texas 154,034 397 154,431 18,547 2 2 4 4 Virginia 894,800 54,333 949,133 129,545 13 11 15 13 Total 6,184,477 228,128 6,412,605 807,800 90 75 120 105 TABLE VIII. Political View of the Free States. Free States. White Population. Free Colored Population. Total Free Population. Popular Vote cast in 1852. Representation in Congress. Representation were not Slaves represented. Electoral Vote as it now is. Electoral Vote were not Slaves represented. California 91,635 962 92,597 74,736 2 2 4 4 Connecticut 363,099 7,693 370,792 66,768 4 4 6 6 Illinois 846,034 5,436 851,470 155,497 9 10 11 12 Indiana 977,154 11,262 988,416 183,134 11 12 13 14 Iowa 191,881 333 192,214 16,845 2 2 4 4 Maine 581,813 1,356 583,169 82,182 6 7 8 9 Massachusetts 985,450 9,064 994,514 132,936 11 12 13 14 Michigan 395,071 2,583 397,654 82,939 4 5 6 7 N. Hampshire 317,456 520 317,976 52,839 3 4 5 6 New Jersey 465,509 23,810 489,319 83,211 5 6 7 8 New York 3,048,325 49,069 3,097,394 522,294 33 36 35 38 Ohio 1,955,050 25,279 1,980,329 353,428 21 23 23 25 Pennsylvania 2,258,160 53,626 2,311,786 386,214 25 27 27 29 Rhode Island 143,875 3,670 147,545 17,005 2 2 4 4 Vermont 313,402 718 314,120 43,838 3 4 5 6 Wisconsin 304,756 635 305,391 64,712 3 3 5 5 Total 13,238,670 196,016 13,434,686 2,318,578 144 159 176 191 It will be recollected that the area of the Slave States is 851,448 square miles, and that of the Free States 612,597. The white population of the Slave States is 6,184,477, and of the Free States 13,238,670. The number of free inhabitants in the Slave States is 6,412,605, and in the Free States 13,434,686. The number of freemen in the Free States is, therefore, over 600,000 more than double the number in the Slave States. The representation in Congress is, from the Slave States ninety members, representing the 6,000,000; and from the Free States one hundred and forty-four, representing the 13,000,000. This discrepancy between population and representation arises from the fact that, in determining the number of representatives to which each State is entitled, five slaves are reckoned equal to three freemen. The 3,200,304 slaves, therefore, in the Slave States are reckoned equal to 1,920,182 ? freemen, and are represented accordingly. The slaves of the South have, therefore, a representation equal to that of the Free States of New Hampshire, Vermont, Connecticut, Iowa, and Wisconsin. Without the representation allowed to slave property, the number of representatives from the Slave States would be seventy-five, insteated of ninety; and from the Free States one hundred and fifty-nine, instead of one hundred and forty-four; a gain of thirty in favor of the Free States, making their representation double that of the Slave States, even without the representation of Rhode Island, Wisconsin, California, and Iowa.* * It will be seen that in the late severe contests in the House of Representatives, had freemen only been represented, the question would invariably have been decided in favor of the North. By such a change, Kentucky, Louisiana, North Carolina, and Tennessee, would lose one representative each; Alabama, Georgia, Virginia, and Mississippi, two each; and South Carolina three. Illinois, Indiana, Maine, Michigan, New Hampshire, New Jersey and Vermont would each gain one; Ohio and Pennsylvania two, and New York three. The free population of the whole fifteen Slave States is not 9,000 more than that of the three States of New York, Pennsylvania and Massachusetts. These three States have now sixty-nine representatives. The popular vote cast at the last Presidential election, (1852) in the Slave States was 807,800; in the Free States 2,318,578—a majority in favor of the latter of 1,510,778, and a ratio of almost three to one. The aggregate vote of the following eleven States, viz: Maryland, Virginia, North Carolina, Georgia, Alabama, Mississippi, Louisiana, Florida, Arkansas, Delaware, and Texas, was less than that of the single State of New York; the total vote of all these States being 515,159, while that of New York was 522,294; and yet, according to the present system of representation, these States are entitled to seventy-nine electoral votes, and New York to only thirty-five. The three States, Massachusetts, Pennsylvania, and Ohio, or even the two States of Pennsylvania and New York, cast a popular vote larger, by more than 60,000, than all the Slave States. The three first named States have sixty-three electoral votes; the last two have sixty-two; and the fifteen Slave States one hundred and twenty! In the North, 93,296 freemen and 16,101 voters are required to elect a representative to Congress. In the South, only 71,251 freemen and 8,976 voters. A President elected by the Northern votes over a candidate receiving the Southern votes would have a popular majority of 1,510,778 votes, or about twice the number of votes ever cast by the South. A President elected by the South, with the votes of States enough in the North to elect him, would not be chosen by the majority. Then, suppose a candidate to receive every vote in the South (one hundred and twenty electoral votes), and the votes of Maine, New Hampshire, Massachusetts, and Rhode Island (thirty electoral votes), this would give him one hundred and fifty electoral votes to one hundred and forty-six against him; but the popular majority against him would be almost a million of votes, or more than the whole Southern vote, as will be seen by the table, the South having 807,800 voters, and the Free States mentioned, 284,962; being a total of 1,092,762 votes; while the remaining Free States, casting but one hundred and forty-six electoral votes, would have a popular vote of 2,033,616, which is a majority of 940,854. If a President were so elected, would the North and the Northwest be justified in dissolving the Union therefor? Or, again: suppose a President elected by the vote of the South and the vote of Pennsylvania and New Jersey, the electoral vote would be one hundred and fifty-four for him and one hundred and forty-two against him; the popular vote would be 1,277,225 for him, and 1,849,153 against him—or a majority of 571,928 votes, which is about three-quarters of the whole vote of the South. Would the Northeast and Northwest probably dissolve the Union on such a result?</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER IV. AGRICULTURE. The tables found in this chapter show the condition of agriculture in the United States for the year ending June, 1850, when no other date is given. These tables show the number of farms and plantations, acres of cultivated land, value of the same, value per acre, value of farm implements and machinery, and whole area, in acres, of the several Free and Slave States. California is necessarily omitted from the list of the Free States, because of the defective returns of the marshals for that State. This omission can only be supplied by taking the State valuation for 1852, the first made by the State authority. In that year there were assessed for taxation in California, 6,719,442 acres of land, valued at $35,879,929, or $5.34 per acre. In Table X., there is an evident and remarkable error— either of the marshals, or of the compiler of the census returns —in regard to the value of farms in South Carolina. This table, carefully copied from the Compendium of the Census, gives for South Carolina: Acres improved and unimproved land, 16,217,600 Valued at, $82,431,684 " per acre, $5.08 Now the true value of lands in South Carolina is shown by its State valuation to differ essentially from this. Thus, in 1851, there were assessed for taxation in South Carolina (American Almanac for 1853, p. 278): Acres of land, 17,073,412 Valued at, $23,952,679 " per acre, $1.40 TABLE IX. Statement showing the Number of Farms and Plantations, Acres of Improved and Unimproved Land, Cash Value of Farms, Average Value per Acre, and Value of Farming Implements and Machinery, in the several Free States, with the whole Area of each, according to the Census Returns for 1850. FREE STATES. Number of Farms and Plantations. Acres of Improved Land. Acres of Unimproved Land. Cash Value of Farms. Average Value per Acre. Value of Farming Implements and Machinery. Whole Area of States in Acres. Connecticut 22,445 1,768,178 615,701 $72,726,422 $30.50 $1,892,541 2,991,360 Illinois 76,208 5,039,545 6,997,867 96,133,290 7.99 6,405,561 35,459,200 Indiana 93,896 5,046,543 7,746,879 136,385,173 10.66 6,704,444 21,637,760 Iowa 14,805 824,682 1,911,382 16,657,567 6.09 1,172,869 32,584,960 Maine 46,760 2,039,596 2,515,797 54,861,748 12.04 2,284,557 20,330,240 Massachusetts 34,069 2,133,436 1,222,576 109,076,347 32.50 3,209,584 4,992,000 Michigan 34,089 1,929,110 2,454,780 51,872,446 11.83 2,891,371 35,995,520 New Hampshire 29,229 2,251,488 1,140,926 55,245,997 16.28 2,314,125 5,939,200 New Jersey 23,905 1,767,991 984,955 120,237,511 43.67 4,425,503 5,324,800 New York 170,621 12,408,964 6,710,120 554,546,642 29.00 22,084,926 30,080,000 Ohio 143,807 9,851,493 8,146,000 358,758,603 19.99 12,750,585 25,576,960 Pennsylvania 127,577 8,623,619 6,294,728 407,876,099 27.27 14,722,541 29,440,000 Rhode Island 5,385 356,487 197,451 17,070,802 30.82 497,201 835,840 Vermont 29,763 2,601,409 1,524,413 63,367,227 15.36 2,739,282 6,535,680 Wisconsin 20,177 1,045,499 1,931,159 28,528,563 9.54 1,641,568 34,511,360 Total 877,736 57,688,040 50,394,734 $2,143,344,437 $19.83 $85,736,658 292,234,880 TABLE X. Statement showing the Number of Farms and Plantations, Acres of Improved and Unimproved Land, Cash Value of Farms, Average Value per Acre, and Value of Farming Implements and Machinery, in the several Slave States, with the whole Area of each, according to the Census Returns for 1850. SLAVE STATES. Number of Farms and Plantations. Acres of Improved Land. Acres of Unimproved Land. Cash Value of Farms. Average Value per Acre. Value of Farming Implements and Machinery. Whole Area of States in Acres. Alabama 41,964 4,435,614 7,702,067 $64,323,224 $5.30 $5,125,663 32,462,080 Arkansas 17,758 781,530 1,816,684 15,265,245 5.87 1,601,296 33,406,720 Delaware 6,063 580,862 375,282 18,880,031 19.75 510,279 1,356,800 Florida 4,304 349,049 1,246,240 6,323,109 3.97 658,795 37,931,520 Georgia 51,759 6,378,479 16,442,900 95,753,445 4.19 5,894,150 37,120,000 Kentucky 74,777 5,968,270 10,981,478 155,021,262 9.03 11,576,938 24,115,200 Louisiana 13,422 1,590,025 3,399,018 75,814,398 13.71 2,284,557 26,403,200 Maryland 21,860 2,797,905 1,836,445 87,178,545 18.81 2,463,443 7,119,360 Mississippi 33,960 3,444,358 7,046,061 54,738,634 5.22 5,762,927 30,179,840 Missouri 54,458 2,938,425 6,794,245 63,225,543 6.49 3,981,525 43,123,200 North Carolina 56,963 5,453,975 15,543,008 67,891,766 3.24 3,931,532 32,450,560 South Carolina 29,967 4,072,551 12,145,049 82,431,684 5.08 4,136,354 18,806,400 Tennessee 72,735 5,175,173 13,808,849 97,851,212 5.16 5,360,210 29,184,000 Texas 12,198 643,976 10,852,363 16,550,008 1.44 2,151,704 152,002,560 Virginia 77,013 10,360,135 15,792,176 216,401,543 8.27 7,021,772 39,265,280 Total 564,203 54,970,427 125,781,865 $1,117,649,649 $6.18 $65,345,625 544,926,720 In 1854 (American Almanac for 1856, p. 293), there were assessed for taxation: Acres of land, 17,289,359 Valued at, $22,836,374 " per acre, $1.32 By Table IX. it will be seen that the whole area in acres of the Free States, not including California, is 292,231,880 Number of acres under cultivation, 108,082,774 "of acres not under cultivation, 184,149,106 Value of the lands under cultivation, $2,143,344,437 " per acre, $19.83 Whole area of the Slave States (including South Carolina, according to the incorrect census figures) 544,742,926 Number of acres under cultivation, 180,572,292 " of acres not under cultivation, 364,170,634 Value of the land under cultivation, $1,117,649,649 " per acre, $6.18 As to general results, the error in the South Carolina return and the omission of California will about balance each other. Including only the lands under cultivation in the two sections, the value per acre in the North is more than three times that of the South. Including the whole area, the proportion is still larger. The value per acre of land in the States, on the dividing line between freedom and slavery, is suggestive—thus, in the Free States, the value of farms per acre is as follows, viz: New Jersey, $43 67 Pennsylvania, 27 27 Ohio, 19 99 Indiana, 10 66 Illinois, 7 99 Average, $22 17 In the border Slave States the value is as follows, viz: Delaware, $19 75 Maryland, 18 81 Virginia, 8 27 Kentucky, 9 03 Missouri, 6 49 Average, $9 25 Take those Slave States which, by position, population, or intercourse, feel least the influence of the Free States. Thus, the value of farms per acre is, in North Carolina, $3 24 South Carolina, 1 32 Tennessee, 5 16 Florida, 3 97 Georgia, 4 19 Alabama, 5 30 Arkansas, 5 87 Texas, 1 44 Mississippi, 5 22 Average, $3 74 Table XI. shows the value of the agricultural productions of the several Free States and Slave States for the year 1840. It is taken from the Annual Report of the Secretary of the Treasury on the Finances for 1854–5. It is understood that the articles of wheat (54,770,311 bushels in the Free States and 30,052,961 bushels in the Slave States), sugar (31,010,234 pounds in the Free States and 124,090,566 pounds in the Slave States), and molasses, are not included. Table XII. has been prepared with great labor. In the first two columns are given the amount and value of live stock, and the amount of agricultural products, in the Free and Slave TABLE XI. Statement of the Value of the Agricultural Productions of the Free and of the Slave States for the year 1840. FREE STATES. SLAVE STATES. Connecticut $11,201,618 Alabama $23,833,470 Illinois 11,577,281 Arkansas 4,973,655 Indiana 14,484,610 Delaware 2,877,350 Maine 14,725,615 Georgia 29,612,436 Massachusetts 14,371,732 Kentucky 26,233,968 Michigan 3,207,048 Louisiana 17,976,017 New Hampshire 10,762,019 Maryland 14,015,665 New Jersey 15,314,006 Mississippi 26,297,666 New York 91,244,178 Missouri 9,755,615 Ohio 27,212,004 North Carolina 24,727,297 Pennsylvania 51,232,204 South Carolina 20,555,919 Rhode Island 1,951,141 Tennessee 27,917,692 Vermont 16,977,664 Virginia 48,644,905 Iowa 688,308 Florida 1,817,718 Wisconsin 445,559 Total $285,394,987 Total $279,239,373 States, for the years 1840 and 1850. In the third and fourth columns are given the values according to the calculations of De Bow, in which the products of the North and the South are calculated at the same prices, which calculation is unfavorable to the North. As to those products whose value is given by De Bow (Census Compendium, p. 176), in the aggregate, their value has been distributed as follows, viz: Eggs and feathers, according to the relative amount of poultry in the North and South in 1840. Milk, according to amount of butter and cheese in each section in 1850. Annual increase of stock and cattle, sheep and pigs, under one year old, according to value of live stock in 1850. Residuum of crops, manure, etc., according to population. Small crops, as carrots, etc., one-fourth to the South and three-fourths to the North. In the fifth and sixth columns are given the values according to the prices in Andrews' voluminous Report on Trade and Commerce, made August 19, 1852. The prices are the same for the two sections. The aggregate products have been distributed according to the best authorities and information which could be obtained. In the seventh and eighth columns are given the average crops per acre in the two sections as returned by the marshals in 1850. "The quantity of wheat in 1850," says De Bow, "is believed to be under-stated, and the crop was also short." "Investigations undertaken by the State legislatures and agricultural societies," says Andrews (Report, p. 696), "prove that the aggregate production of wheat reported in the census tables was below the average crop by at least 30,000,000 bushels." It seems fair to add to our table for "understatement" the amount of 15,000,000 bushels, * * The following are the census returns of wheat, in five large wheat-growing counties in Ohio, for 1850, and the returns made by the State authorities for the same year: Counties. Census Returns. State Returns. Stark,   bushels, 590,594 1,071,177 Wayne,   " 571,377 1,020,000 Muskingum,   " 415,847 1,003,000 Licking,   " 336,317 849,116 Coshocton,   " 416,918 852,809 2,331,053 4,806,193 which distributed according to production would give Free States, 10,823,899 bushels; value $10,823,899; Slave States, 4,176,101 bushels; value, $4,176,101. Of hemp and flax, De Bow says: "It is impossible to reconcile the hemp and flax returns of 1840 and 1850. No doubt in both cases, tons and pounds have often been confounded. In a few of the States, such as Indiana and Illinois, the returns of 1850 were rejected altogether for insufficiency." TABLE XII. Amount of Live Stock (and its Value in 1850) and Agricultural Productions of the Free and Slave States, with the Value of the same (for 1850), according to De Bow and Andrews, for the years 1840 and 1850; and also the Average Crops, per Acre, of certain Products, according to De Bow. Amount of Live Stock and Agricultural Productions in the United States, for the years 1840 and 1850. Free States. Slave States. Value according to De Bow's prices. Free States. 1850. Value according to De Bow's prices. Slave States. 1850. Value according to the prices in Andrews' Report. Free States. 1850. Value according to the prices in Andrews' Report. Slave States. 1850. Average Crops per Acre. Free States. Average Crops per Acre. Slave States. Horses1850 2,310,984 201,551 Asses and Mules1850 45,840 518,933 Horses, Asses, and Mules1840 2,097,305 2,236,219 Working Oxen1850 881,607 821,976 Milch Cows1850 3,626,285 2,832,525 Other Neat Cattle1850 4,237,928 6,079,309 Total Neat Cattle1840 7,567,220 7,401,092 Sheep1850 14,691,999 6,635,076 "1840 14,144,478 5,166,190 Swine1850 9,605,978 20,807,403 "1840 10,085,150 16,211,470 Value of Live Stock1850 $286,374,541 $253,723,687 Value of Animals Slaughtered1850 $56,990,247 $54,386,377 $56,990,247 $54,386,877 Wheat, bushels1850 72,319,491 27,903,426 $72,319,491 27,903,426 $72,319,491 $27,903,426 12.35 9.35 "1840 54,770,311 30,052,961 Rye, "1850 12,580,732 1,608,240 6,919,403 884,532 11,196,851 1,431,334 15.55 10.50 " "1840 14,321,158 4,324,409 Oats, "1850 96,699,002 49,882,973 29,009,701 14,964,892 42,547,561 21,948,508 26.20 16.63 " "1840 80,056,173 43,015,168 Barley, "1850 7,966,110 161,907 5,576,277 113,335 4,779,666 97,144 23.70 " "1840 4,002,463 159,041 Indian Corn, bushels1850 242,735,176 348,992,271 121,367,588 174,496,135 145,641,106 209,395,363 31.14 18.93 " "1840 125,157,562 252,374,317 Irish Potatoes, "1850 59,320,970 7,705,362 23,728,388 3,082,145 39,490,727 5,779,021 118.53 112.50 Sweet " "1850 1,122,330 37,145,558 561,165 18,572,779 897,864 29,716,446 164. Irish and Sweet Potatoes, bushels1840 89,043,092 19,254,968 Buckwheat, bushels1850 8,550,618 405,347 6,669,482 316,171 4,275,309 202,673 19.62 8.50 " "1840 6,806,600 385,143 Hay, tons1850 12,693,661 1,137,784 88,855,627 7,964,448 158,660,762 14,222,290 1.21 1.19 " "1840 9,403,328 844,780 Hops, pounds1850 3,463,191 33,780 1,212,117 11,823 588,742 5,743 " "1840 1,219,418 19,084 Clover Seed, bushels1850 411,152 57,820 2,055,760 289,100 2,055,760 289,100 Other Grass Seed, bushels1850 351,221 65,588 702,442 131,176 1,756,105 327,940 Butter, pounds1850 245,799,578 67,249,744 $39,327,933 $10,759,959 $49,159,916 $13,449,949 Cheese, "1850 104,077,577 1,384,490 5,203,879 69,225 6,244,655 82,269 Value of Dairy Products1840 $27,494,806 $6,292,202 Peas and Beans, bushels1850 1,550,325 7,637,031 968,953 4,773,144 1,240,260 6,109,624 20. 11.75 Produce of Market Gardens1850 $3,780,832 $1,377,260 3,780,332 1,377,260 36,000,000 12,000,000 " " " "1840 $1,774,123 $827,073 Value of Orchard Products1850 $6,347,757 $1,365,927 6,347,757 1,365,927 6,347,757 1,365,927 " " " "1840 $4,836,685 $2,420,219 Beeswax and Honey, pounds1850 6,889,010 7,964,780 1,002,242 1,274,365 1,377,802 1,592,956 Value of Poultry, (estimated)1850 5,969,411 7,030,589 9,000,000 6,000,000 " " "1840 $4,287,883 $5,053,435 Cords of Wood1850 12,767,597 7,232,403 13,500,000 6,500,000 " " "1840 3,247,814 1,839,790 Flaxseed, bushels1850 358,923 203,384 538,384 305,076 466,600 264,399 Flax, pounds1850 2,948,278 4,760,208 294,828 476,021 176,897 285,612 Hemp, tons1850 198 34,673 29,793 5,217,246 26,938 4,715,528 Hemp and Flax, tons1840 26,816 68,435 Maple Sugar, pounds1850 32,164,799 2,085,687 1,608,240 104,284 1,608,240 104,284 Cane Sugar, pounds1850 none 237,133,000 12,378,850 none 9,485,320 8.75 Cane and Maple Sugar, pounds1840 31,010,234 124,090,566 Molasses, gallons1850 550,928 12,145,745 110,187 2,429,149 137,732 3,036,436 * * In this Table the product Cotton is found in quantity nearly two and a half millions of bales, worth almost a hundred millions of dollars. Let the word Cotton never be mentioned as an article of value, without saying, that it is owing to the invention of a Northern man, stolen by law and without it, by Southern planters, that it is found in any large quantities among the agricultural products of the United States. For the treatment of Whitney, see a subsequent page. Cotton, bales of 400 pounds1850 14 2,445,779 565 98,603,155 560 97,831, 160 1.02 " " "1840 none. 1,976,198 Rice, pounds1850 " 215,313,497 4,000,000 7,320,659 16.67 " "1840 " 80,841,422 Tobacco, pounds1850 14,752,387 184,991,406 1,032,667 12,949,398 885,143 11,099,484 7.30 6.82 " "1840 9,202,043 209,966,267 Wool, pounds1850 39,651,846 12,793,219 11,895,554 3,837,966 19,825,923 6,396,609 " "1840 27,559,135 8,242,980 Silk Cocoons, pounds1850 5,468 5,375 2,734 2,687 2,734 2,687 Wine, gallons1850 174,629 44,252 349,358 88,504 87,314 22,126 Eggs 2,453,422 2,704,073 Included with milk. Feathers 918,371 1,081,629 1,200,000 800,000 Milk 5,630,745 1,369,255 11,500,000 3,500,000 Annual Increase of Live Stock 92,750,598 82,249,402 71,593,635 63,430,922 Cattle, Sheep and Pigs under 1 year old 26,500,171 23,499,829 Residuum of Crops not consumed by Stock, Corn-Fodder, Straw, Seed, Cotton, Manure, &amp;c 58,725,718 41,274,282 75,000,000 25,000,000 Value of Small Crops, as Carrots, Onions, &amp;c., Orchard and Garden Products, of Cities—Milk, Butter, Cows, Horses, &amp;c., in Cities and Towns 15,000,000 5,000,000 Included in market gardens. Total $709,177,527 $634,570,057 $846,585,297 $627,101,316 Add, then, for "insufficiency" of returns, to the amount of hemp and flax for these two States enough to make their production in 1850 equal it in 1840, and its value will be, at six cents per pound, $1,225,138. With these corrections, the grand aggregate of the agricultural products of the United States, for the year ending June, 1850, will be, using Andrews' prices,— Free States, $858,634,334 Slave States, 631,277,417 Total, $1,489,911,751 The following is a list of the prices of leading products in the foregoing table, by De Bow, and Andrews: Indian corn, bushel, $50 $60 Wheat, " 1 00 1 00 Oats, " 30 44 Irish potatoes, " 40 75 Sweet " 50 80 Rye, " 55 89 Peas and beans, " 62 ? 80 Cotton, bale of 400 pounds, 40 32 40 00 Cane sugar, hhds. of 1000 lbs. 52 20 40 00 Maple sugar, pound, 5 5 Butter, " 16 20 Rice, " 2 3 4–10 Hay, ton, 7 00 12 50 Hemp, " 150 47 136 00 Wool, pound, 30 50 Tobacco, " 7 6 Flax, " 10 6 A glance at the prices of De Bow will satisfy any one that, if they be fair for Virginia, Tennessee, and the South generally, and for Illinois, Missouri, and the West, they cannot be for New England, New York, New Jersey, and Pennsylvania. Thus of Indian corn, which De Bow calls 50 cents per bushel. If Southern and Western corn be worth that price where it is raised, Northern and Eastern corn must be worth at least 75 cents. So of wheat, which De Bow puts at a dollar. If that be fair for Tennessee, Missouri, and Illinois, a dollar and twenty-five cents is a moderate price for the Northern and Eastern States mentioned. So of oats, rye, potatoes, hay, wool, peas and beans, and some other products. There should be added then to De Bow's aggregates, for the products of New England, New York, New Jersey, and Pennsylvania, as follows, viz: Indian corn, 56,639,174 bush. at 25 cts. $14,159,793 Wheat, 31,183,273 " 25 7,795,818 Oats, 59,570,301 " 15 8,935,545 Rye, 11,779,509 " 20 2,355,902 Potatoes, 44,204,441 " 35 15,471,554 Hay, 9,471,369 tons, $7 00 66,299,573 Wool, 22,283,776 lbs. 10 2,228,377 Peas and beans, 1,261,732 bush. 50 630,866 Total, $117,877,428 This list might be extended still further. Adding this amount to the aggregates, according to De Bow's figures, and the total amount will be,— Free States, $827,054,955 Slave States, 634,570,057 Total, $1,461,625,012 This is not essentially different from the result arrived at by taking Andrews' prices. By neither mode of calculation is full justice done to the North. VALUE OF AGRICULTURAL PRODUCTIONS, PER ACRE, IN 1850. The value of agricultural productions per acre for 1850 is obtained by dividing the total product by the number of acres of land under cultivation. Thus,— FREE STATES. Number of acres in farms, 108,193,522 Agricultural product, $858,634,334 Product per acre, $7,94 SLAVE STATES. Number of acres in farms and plantations, 180,572,392 Agricultural product, $631,277,417 Product per acre, $3.49 VALUE OF AGRICULTURAL PRODUCTS, PER HEAD, IN 1850. No enumeration was made in 1850 of the whole number of persons engaged in agriculture, as was done in 1840, and the returns for the latter year must therefore be the basis of our calculation for 1850, as to the number, and the consequent value, of the products per head in the two sections of our country. Assuming, then, that in the North the proportion of the whole population of those engaged in agriculture was the same in 1850 as in 1840, and that in the South the proportion of the free population thus engaged was no larger than in the North, we have the following result, viz: FREE STATES. Whole number engaged in agriculture in 1850, 2,509,126 Value of agricultural products, $858,634,334 Value per head, $342 SLAVE STATES. Number of free population engaged in agriculture in 1850, 1,197,649 Number of slaves engaged in agriculture in 1850, 2,500,000 Total, 3,697,649 Value of agricultural products, $631,277,417 Value per head, $171 De Bow says of the slave population of 1850 (Census Compendium, p. 94), there are "about 2,500,000 slaves directly employed in agriculture." This is a small estimate, and the number given above (1,197,649) of the 6,412,605 free population of the South engaged in agriculture is very small. With the little manufactures and commerce of the South, what are the people of that region engaged in? But, under protest, we adopt the above conclusions. This, then, is the grand result in the department of agriculture, the peculiar province of the South: The North, with half as much land under cultivation, and two-thirds as many persons engaged in farming, produces two hundred and twenty-seven millions of dollars worth of agricultural products in a year more than the South; twice as much on an acre, and more than double the value per head for every person engaged in farming. And this, while the South, paying nothing for its labor, has better land, a monopoly of cotton, rice, cane sugar, and nearly so of tobacco and hemp, and a climate granting two and sometimes three crops in a year. Nor does a comparison of the products of 1850 with those of 1840 afford any ground for hope for the South. A recurrence to Table XI. will show that, excluding wheat, sugar, and molasses from the aggregate, the production of the South for 1840 was nearly equal that of the North. Perhaps in 1830 it was greater. Table XIII. gives the population, white and slave, number of acres of land, value of farms, value of land per acre, number of students and scholars in public and private schools, and the number of whites over twenty unable to read and write, in the counties in the several States on the dividing line between the Free and Slave States, from the Atlantic to the Mississippi. The statistics are from De Bow's Compendium of the Census of 1850. The table is an important one, and deserves a more extended consideration than can be given it in this work. TABLE XIII. A Statement of Population, White and Slave, Number of acres of Land, Value of Farms, Value of Farms per acre, Number of Students and Scholars in Public and Private Schools, and the Number of Whites over 20 years of age unable to read and write, in the Counties on the dividing line between the Free and the Slave States, from the Atlantic to the Mississippi, with the like Statistics of the Remaining Counties of the respective States. Border Counties and Remaining Counties of their several States. White Population in 1850. Slaves in 1850. Acres of Improved and Unimproved Land in 1850. Value of Improved and Unimproved Land in 1850. Value of Farms per Acre. Pupils in Colleges, Academies, and Private Schools. White Scholars in Public Schools during the year. No. of Whites over 5 and under 20 years old. No. of Whites over 20 unable to read &amp; write. Counties of Delaware adjacent to New Jersey 50,849 741 501,667 $15,848,760 $31.59 2,075 10,596 18,707 6,292 The remaining County of Delaware 20,320 1,549 454,667 3,541,550 7.79 80 3,620 7,902 3,485 Counties of New Jersey adjacent to Delaware 47,486 386,720 14,553,731 37.63 185 10,642 17,628 1,120 Remaining Counties of New Jersey 418,023 2,366,226 105,683,781 44.66 10,129 78,633 148,253 11,667 County of Pennsylvania adjoining Delaware 23,122 105,569 9,067,082 85.89 303 5,142 8,320 422 Counties of Maryland adjoining Pennsylvania 315,282 17,430 1,615,227 47,851,615 29.63 10,386 42,885 105,229 19,268 Remaining Counties of Maryland 102,661 72,938 3,019,123 41,790,373 13.84 1,528 17,562 42,488 19,158 Counties of Pennsylvania adjoining Maryland 330,688 2,799,532 105,136,277 37.56 3,245 77,376 123,613 11,473 Counties of Virginia adjoining Pennsylvania 64,540 527 732,913 9,512,647 12.98 867 10,505 24,368 4,001 Remaining Counties of Virginia 830,260 472,001 25,419,398 213,910,668 8.42 9,544 99,206 320,897 83,382 Counties of Pennsylvania adjoining Virginia 128,927 1,373,119 32,985,617 24.74 1,330 31,283 49,350 3,708 Remaining Counties of Pennsylvania 2,129,233 13,545,228 374,890,482 27.68 25,941 466,828 775,320 47,575 Counties of Virginia adjacent to Ohio 38,251 1,689 980,219 5,543,346 5.65 150 5,677 15,614 3,845 Counties of Ohio adjacent to Virginia 97,963 843,545 9,354,429 11.09 762 22,374 38,463 4,998 Remaining Counties of Ohio 1,858,087 17,153,948 349,404,174 20.37 17,911 489,904 719,170 51,960 Counties of Kentucky adjacent to Ohio 81,749 9,672 926,151 66,923,351 18.27 942 12,327 30,944 4,422 Counties of Ohio adjacent to Kentucky 261,724 1,069,308 34,577,488 32.34 5,994 48,102 91,906 8,334 Counties of Kentucky adjacent to Indiana 106,473 28,731 1,653,014 17,250,889 10.44 2,764 16,267 39,303 5,252 Remaining Counties of Kentucky 654,940 182,251 15,296,746 142,839,410 9.34 11,721 114,650 263,596 62,107 Counties of Indiana adjacent to Kentucky 134,509 1,276,989 14,480,233 11.34 1,114 26,665 45,657 7,075 Remaining Counties of Indiana 842,645 11,516,433 121,904,940 10.59 6,140 193,369 353,635 62,370 Counties of Kentucky adjacent to Illinois 27,443 5,908 627,218 2,918,419 4.65 338 5,235 11,085 2,700 Counties of Illinois adjacent to Kentucky 18,101 235,716 1,093,685 4.54 none. 2,307 7,384 1,861 Remaining Counties of Illinois 828,933 11,801,696 95,039,604 8.05 4,686 179,662 328,079 33,575 In proportion to the white population, these border counties of the Slave States contain the following per cent of slaves, viz: Delaware, 1 per cent. Maryland, 5 " Virginia, 2 " Kentucky, 21 " The remaining counties of the same States give the following, viz: Delaware, 8 per cent. Maryland, 71 " Virginia, 59 " Kentucky, 31 " The value of lands per acre will be seen by an examination of the table; and it will be noticed, that, with the exception of the broken region of Virginia, which lies adjacent to Ohio, and that of Kentucky, which lies adjacent to Illinois, the value of lands per acre in the counties of the Slave States adjoining the Free is greater than that of the remaining counties of their respective States. The opposite is true, generally, of the border counties of the Free States. Thus, the effects of freedom and slavery on the value of the adjacent lands is reciprocal. The neighborhood of slavery lessens their value in the Free States; the neighborhood of freedom increases it in the Slave States. To such an extent is this true, that, in Virginia, for example, the lands in counties naturally poor, are, by the proximity of freedom, rendered more valuable than those unequalled lands in the better portions of the State. Indeed, this table shows the fact that the lands in the border counties of the Slave States are worth more per acre than the remaining lands in the same States, with the addition of the value of the whole number of their slaves at $400 per head. And this, be it remembered, while the value of lands in the balance of the counties of the border Slave States is double that of the lands in the Slave States not adjacent to the Free. It is for the interest of the Slave States to be hedged in by a circle of Free States. If Tennessee had been a Free State, her lands would have been worth as much as those of Ohio,— $19.99 per acre, instead of $5.16 as now,—and who cannot see that, in that event, the lands of North Carolina, South Carolina, and Georgia would have been worth more per acre than the sums of $3.24, $1.40, $4.19, respectively. Not only could Tennessee afford to sacrifice the whole value of her slaves for the sake of freedom, but even North Carolina, South Carolina, and Georgia could afford to sacrifice the whole value of their own slaves, and pay for all of the slaves in Tennessee for the sake of having a free neighbor. The increased value of lands would more than compensate for the sacrifice. The figures prove this. Tennessee has 18,984,022 acres of land under cultivation, worth $5.16 per acre. Multiply this number of acres by $14.83 (the difference between the value of lands in Tennessee and Ohio), and the amount is, $281,533,046 Tennessee has 239,459 slaves; value, at $400 each, 95,783,600 This leaves the respectable margin of 185,749,446 North Carolina, South Carolina, and Georgia have 60,891,774 acres of land, worth $3.08 per acre. Multiply this number of acres by $15.73 (the difference in value between the lands in these States and the border Slave State of Maryland), and the amount is $957,827,605 Number of slaves in these States, 1,055,214 Value at $400 each, $422,085,600 Value of slaves in Tennessee, as above, 95,783,600 Total, $517,869,200 Deducting this from the increased value of lands, and the balance in favor of free neighbors is the sum of $439,958,405 Thus, the figures show that Tennessee could afford, for the sake of freedom, to sacrifice the whole value of her quarter of a million of slaves, and pay in addition the sum of $185,749,446. For the sake of a free neighbor, and to bring up their lands to the value of those of Maryland, the States of North and South Carolina, and Georgia, could afford to sacrifice the whole of their own slaves, pay for those of Tennessee, and make $439,958,405 by the bargain, which sum is considerably more than twice the present value of all their lands. Nay, these States could afford to send off, singly, every slave within their limits, in a coach with two horses, and provisions for a year, if they could but bring up the value of their lands to that of the land in northern Maryland. Indignation, and patriotism, and dissolution of the Union, indeed, if a fugitive now and then be not reclaimed! South Carolina could afford to pay every year more money than she spent in the whole Revolutionary war, to make her whole number of slaves fugitives; and then make money enough by the transaction to fence in the whole State with a picket fence, to prevent their return. NEW ENGLAND, SOUTH CAROLINA, AND VIRGINIA. Comparisons between portions of the North and the South can be made to any extent. A few are added, with such suggestions as seem proper. Table XIV. is a comparison between the States of Rhode Island and Connecticut, and an equal extent of cultivated lands in certain counties of South Carolina. The table includes the city of Charleston. The comparison extends to the value of lands, population, value of agricultural and manufactured products, commerce, and education. The value of lands in the South Carolina counties is the fictitious one of De Bow's Compendium, and not the real one of the State valuation. The portions compared in Table XIV. are of equal age as well as extent. The free portion has eleven times the white population; nearly four times the total population of white and slave. Its lands are worth six times as much, and twice as much after TABLE XIV. A Statement of the Acres of Land in Farms, Cash Value thereof, Value per acre, White and Slave Population, with the Value of the Slaves and their Value per acre, Value of Agricultural and Manufacturing Products, Amount of Tonnage owned, and built in 1855, and the number of Students in Colleges, &amp;c., and Scholars in Public Schools, in the States of Rhode Island and Connecticut, and an equal area in South Carolina. States. Acres of Improved Land in 1850. Acres of Unimproved Land in 1850. Cash Value of Farms in 1850. Cash Value of Farms per acre, 1850. White Population in 1850. Slaves in 1850. Value of Slaves per acre, at $400 each. Value of Slaves at $400 each. Value of Agricultural Products in 1850, according to De Bow. Value of Manufactures in 1850. Tonnage owned June 30, 1855. Tonnage built during the year ending June 30, 1855. Students in Colleges, Academies, and Private Schools, 1850. Scholars in Public Schools, 1850. Connecticut 1,768,178 615,701 $74,618,963 $31.34 363,099 $8,636,789 $45,302,354 137,170 14,067 7,734 71,269 Rhode Island 356,487 197,451 17,568,003 31.55 143,875 1,633,974 22,119,753 51,038 7,862 1,884 23,130 Total 2,124,665 813,151 $92,186,966 $31.37 506,974 $10,270,763 $67,422,107 188,808 21,929 9,618 94,399 Counties in South Carolina of area equal to Rhode Island &amp; Connecticut. Charleston 183,236 636,495 $5,903,220 $7.20 25,208 54,775 $26.85 $21,910,000 $896,904 $2,767,760 56,419 61 3.082 1,196 Georgetown 49,609 318,514 5,704,920 15.49 2,193 18,253 19.83 7,301,200 1,104,685 68,519 4,516 281 170 Williamsburg 70,360 432,440 861,538 1.71 3,902 8,508 6.11 3,403,200 223,740 12,825 none. 378 Horry 33,664 472,971 385,840 .76 5,522 2,075 1.63 830,000 160,640 154,684 none. 488 Marion 124,306 652,342 2,680,544 3.45 9,781 7,520 3.87 3,008,000 377,826 40,624 50 350 Total 461,175 2,512,762 $15,536,062 $5.19 46,606 91,131 $12.17 $36,452,400 $2,763,795 $3,044,412 60,935 61 3,413 2,582 adding to the value of the lands the whole value of the slaves in this most intensely slave portion of the Union, at the rate of $400 for each slave. The value of the agricultural products of Connecticut and Rhode Island is four times as great as that of those of this portion of Carolina, although the latter has the monopoly almost of the rice-producing region. Of the value of the Carolina products, one-third is cotton; and here is the place to say, that it is owing to the invention of a Massachusetts man that the South is able to raise its cotton at all at this time. If the South had been obliged to clean cotton by hand, at the rate of a pound a day for each slave, as before the invention of Whitney, the whole cotton-producing region would have been bankrupt. The treatment which the Northern inventor received at the hands of those Southrons, whose fortunes he had made, is a sad portion of history. Before his patent was obtained, a mob of the chivalry (who despise so heartily and magnificently a money-making, peddling Yankee) broke open the building in which his machine was placed, carried off the machine, and made others from it; and, before he could go through the formalities of getting his patent, several machines were in successful operation on the plantations of different gentlemen. In the Georgia courts, Whitney's rights were decided against, on the ground mainly that, as "the introduction of the gin would open up boundless resources of wealth to the planters, it was too great a power to allow any one man a monopoly of the right to furnish the machines." South Carolina agreed to pay $50,000 for the invention, paid $20,000 down, then repudiated the contract, sued Whitney and his partner for the money paid, and cast the latter into prison. Afterwards, this action was reversed and the contract fulfilled. The action of Tennessee was similar to that of South Carolina, without the repentance. North Carolina did better, and was faithful to its contract. After years of litigation, Whitney got a decision in his favor in the United States Court; but meantime his patent was nearly out, and his application for a renewal was denied by the votes of those whose fortunes he had made. In Georgia, in the courts, witnesses, judges, and juries gave way, in spite of law and evidence, before the rapacity of the planters. "In one instance," says Whitney, "I had great difficulty in proving that the machine had been used in Georgia, although at the same moment there were three separate sets of this machinery in motion within fifty yards of the building in which the court sat, and all so near that the rattling of the wheels was distinctly heard on the steps of the court-house." To return to table XIV. In manufactures, the North has more than twenty times; in tonnage owned in 1855, three times; and in tonnage built in the same year, three hundred and fifty times as much as the South. The "tonnage built" in 1855, in South Carolina, consisted of one schooner of sixty-one tons burden. This is since the sitting of several Southern conventions, in which they resolved to have an extensive commerce of their own, not only with Europe, but with Brazil and Central America. As to education, the New England figures are twenty times as large as those of Carolina. Table XV. is a comparison between Massachusetts and an equal extent of territory in Virginia. The portion of Virginia taken is the southeastern, from the Atlantic to the mountains. It includes Norfolk, the commercial capital of Virginia, and the land taken is naturally as good as that of other parts of the State, and much better than the lands in Massachusetts. The age of the two sections is about the same. As compared with Virginia, the white population in Massachusetts is ten times as great, and five times as great as its total white and slave. Her lands are worth nearly six times as much per acre, and almost twice as much as the lands and slaves of the Virginia counties added together, although they constitute the most dense slave section of the State (the slaves being worth twice as much as the lands and buildings). The agricultural products of Massachusetts, at De Bow's prices, are nearly double those of the Virginia counties, while her manufacturing products are more than forty times as great, and eight times as much in a single year as the whole value of this great portion of Virginia, including TABLE XV. A Statement of the Number of Acres in Farms, Value of Farms, Value of the same per acre, White and Slave Population, Value of Slaves, Value of Agricultural and Manufacturing Products, Tonnage owned, and built in 1855, Pupils in Colleges, &amp;c., and Number of Scholars in the Public Schools, in the State of Massachusetts, and an equal area in Virginia. Counties in Virginia of area equal to the State of Massachusetts Acres of Improved Land in 1850. Acres of Unimproved Land in 1850. Cash value of Farms in 1850. Cash Value of Farms per acre in 1850. White Population in 1850. Slaves in 1850. Value of Slaves per Acre at $400 per Slave. Value of Slaves at $400 per Slave. Value of Agricultural Products in 1850, according to De Bow. Value of Manufactures, 1850. Tonnage Owned June 30, 1855. Amount of Tonnage Built in 1855. Pupils in Colleges, Academies, and Private Schools, 1850. Scholars in the Public Schools in 1850. Patrick 38,192 184,034 $734,771 $3.31 7,187 2,324 $4.18 $929,600 $246,326 $140,172 none. 826 Henry 61,539 96,409 820,070 5.19 5,324 3,340 8.45 1,336,000 258,525 99,956 none. 1,391 Pittsylvania 210,580 300,295 2,850,908 5.58 15,263 12,798 10.02 5,119,200 925,141 878,660 142 667 Halifax 242,758 202,291 3,420,990 7.68 10,976 14,452 12.98 5,780,800 1,128,810 287,666 none. 288 Mecklenburg 215,646 179,183 2,535,628 5.12 7,256 12,462 10.07 4,984,800 831,248 226,654 239 574 Brunswick 177,196 117,702 1,097,948 3.68 4,885 8,456 11.46 3,382,400 524,157 44,941 86 186 Greenville 74,906 82,066 427,173 2.72 1,731 3,785 9.64 1,514,000 198,836 17,641 30 95 Sussex 91,408 98,677 600,096 3.15 3,086 5,992 12.60 2,396,800 328,892 80,133 14 235 Southampton 159,668 176,023 1,068,103 3.28 5,940 5,755 7.06 2,302,000 456,902 36,600 68 288 Nansemond 62,308 117,968 1,717,090 9.52 5,424 4,715 10.46 1,886,000 355,055 168,751 174 298 Norfolk 89,014 75,866 1,252,031 10.89 20,329 10,400 36.21 4,160,000 297,209 1,412,594 35,051 2,171 363 1,926 Princess Anne 50,064 63,175 1,110,673 8.67 4,280 3,130 11.05 1,252,000 257,835 33,337 none. 819 Isle of Wight 65,925 92,901 982,939 6.18 4,710 3,395 8.55 1,358,000 257,046 58,432 56 149 Surry 44,298 65,466 562,052 5.12 2,215 2,479 8.95 991,600 158,347 19,348 30 150 Total 1,533,502 1,852,056 $19,080,472 $5.64 98,606 93,483 $11.04 $37,393,200 $6,224,329 $3,504,885 35,051 2,171 1,202 7,892 Massachusetts 2,133,436 1,222,576 $109,076,347 $32.50 985,450 $11,003,887 $151,342,478 970,727 79,620 14,479 176,475 its commercial capital. Tonnage owned, Massachusetts twenty-eight parts, Virginia one part; tonnage built in 1855, Massachusetts thirty-seven parts, Virginia one part. Education, scholars, Massachusetts twenty-one parts, Virginia one part. TABLE XVI. Population, Crops, and other Statistics of Plymouth and Norfolk Counties, in Massachusetts, and James City and Westmoreland Counties, in Virginia, for the year 1850. Population, Crops, &amp;c. Plymouth County, Mass. James City County, Va. Norfolk County, Mass. Westmoreland County, Va. Whites 55,241 1,489 78,643 3,376 Free Colored 456 663 249 1,147 Slaves 1,868 3,557 Total 55,697 4,020 78,892 8,080 Dwellings 9,506 396 12,545 869 Whites between the ages of 5 and 20 17,342 540 23,460 1,330 Pupils in public &amp; private schools 11,249 315 18,252 367 Natives unable to read and write, over 20 years of age 50 52 64 398 Number of Farms 2,447 129 2,637 443 Acres of Improved Land 101,135 21,251 107,884 68,627 Acres of Unimproved Land 114,254 44,132 67,444 6,450 Value of Farms $6,048,442 $561,931 $13,748,505 $1,132,197 Value of Farms per acre $28.08 $8.59 $78.41 $8.70 Number of Horses and Mules 2,458 534 3,311 1,101 " " Neat Cattle 11,855 2,365 12,656 6,225 " " Sheep 5,384 1,217 580 3,676 " " Swine 4,574 4,009 8,209 8,237 Wheat, bushels 251 25,476 356 82,774 Rye, " 17,143 17,423 502 Oats, " 26,809 22,040 14,939 7,897 Indian Corn, bushels 105,243 102,430 112.132 269,115 Irish Potatoes, " 208,402 2,789 253,158 4,970 Sweet Potatoes, " 5,730 6,176 Peas and Beans, " 871 300 3,952 1,350 Barley, " 3,267 5,462 Buckwheat, " 239 454 Butter, pounds 374,816 17,785 347,089 28,437 Cheese, " 130,478 90,160 Hay, tons 28,532 8 41,588 32 Hops, pounds 12 81 129 Clover Seed, bushels 152 Other Grass Seed, bushels Tobacco, pounds 1,346 Cotton, bales 7 Wool, pounds 16,643 2,197 879 8,603 Beeswax and Honey, pounds 3,352 1,047 3,700 Value of Animals slaughtered $176,102 $14,339 $289,809 $41,740 Value of Produce of Market Gard's $13,502 $365 $136,796 $26 " " Orchard Products $19,205 $55,458 $512 Wine, gallons 21 91 2 Manufacturing Capital $2,397,305 none. $5,433,300 $3,330 Number of Hands 8,024 none. 15,628 19 Annual Product $6,713,906 none. $13,323,595 $16,300 Value of Domestic Manufactures. $953 $544 $25,702 $7,843 Table XVI. is a comparison between the counties of Norfolk and Plymouth in Massachusetts, and the counties of Westmoreland and James City in Virginia, as to population, education, agriculture, etc. James City Co. is the county in which are situated Jamestown, the Plymouth of Virginia, and William and Mary's College, the rival in age of Harvard University. Jamestown now contains two houses, and of William and Mary's College it is said that it seldom has more than forty students (the Census Compendium gives it thirty-five in 1850). Westmoreland Co. is the native county of Washington. Of the Massachusetts counties, Norfolk is the county of the Adamses, and Plymouth that of the Pilgrim settlement. VALUE OF LAND IN NORTHERN AND SOUTHERN COUNTIES. The value of land per acre in some of the counties in the South, where there is the largest proportion of slaves, is as follows, viz: Charles Co., Maryland (whites 5,665; slaves 9,584), $10.50. Amelia Co., Virginia (whites, 2,785; slaves, 6,819), $7.60. Beaufort, Colleton, and Georgetown Co.'s, South Carolina (whites, 14,915; slaves, 71,904), $7.30. The value of land per acre in some Northern counties is as follows, viz: Hudson Co., New Jersey, $178; Delaware Co., Pennsylvania, $86. No more tables will be given in the department of agriculture. Some further comparisons and illustrations are given. Virginia, free, and as thickly settled as Massachusetts, would have had, in 1850, 7,751,324 whites instead of 894,800. Massachusetts, a slave State, and as thinly populated as Virginia, would have had in 1850, 102,351 white inhabitants instead of 985,450. Virginia, free, would have had an annual product of manufactures amounting to $1,190,072,592. instead of $29,705,387. Massachusetts, a slave State, would have had manufactures amounting to $3,776,601, instead of $151,137,145. Virginia, free, would have been worth in real and personal property (on the basis of the census estimate), $4,333,525,367, instead of (value of slaves deducted) $203,635,238. Massachusetts, a slave State, would have been worth $48,604,335 instead of $551,106,824. Boston, with slavery, according to the increase of population in Virginia, would have contained 3,489 people instead of 136,881. In the whole South there are less than fifty cities with a population of 3,500. Richmond, Virginia, free, according to the increase of population in Massachusetts, would have contained 1,076,669 free people instead of 17,643. If Virginia had not a settler within her territory, and should be opened at once to free settlement, in ten years she would have nearly as many white inhabitants as she now has, two hundred and fifty years after her settlement, and in twenty years she would have nearly as many whites as the whole number of slaveholding States now have, provided 60,000 settlers should go in the first year, and that the rate of increase should be as great as that of Wisconsin, Iowa, or Minnesota. Even with this population of twenty years, she would not be so densely peopled as Massachusetts was in 1850. The figures prove our statements: thus, Wisconsin had, in 1840, 30,749 whites; in 1850, 304,756. Ratio of increase 89.11 per cent. Assume 60,000 whites in Virginia at the close of the first year, and the rate of increase as above, then in ten years she would have 594,660 white inhabitants, and in twenty years 5,793,475. Number of whites in Virginia in 1850, 894,800; in the slaveholding States, 6,184,477. Thus, as to population, slavery in two hundred and fifty years has done the work of twenty. As to the value of lands, it has done still worse. Thus, in little more than ten years, Wisconsin had brought up the value of her farms per acre to $9.54; Virginia in two hundred and fifty years had barely raised the price of her lands to $8.27. We give below, from different authorities, the past and present condition of the lands of the Free and Slave States. "New England" (says "A perfect description of Virginia," published in London in 1649) "is in a good condition of livelihood; but for matter of any great hope but fishing there is not much." Compared to Virginia, "it's as Scotland is to England, so much difference, and lies upon the same land northward as Scotland does to England; there is much cold, frost, and snow; their land is barren, except a herring be put into the hole you set the corn in, it will not come up; and it was a great pity all those planters, now about 20,000, did not seat themselves at first at the south of Virginia, in a warm and rich country, where their industry could have produced sugar, indigo, ginger, cotton, and the like commodities." Said Sir Thomas Dale, in 1612, speaking of Virginia, "Take four of the best kingdoms in Christendom, and put them all together, they may no way compare with this country either for commodities or goodness of soil." Says Beverley at a later period: "In extreme fruitfulness, it (Virginia) is exceeded by no other. No seed is sown there but it thrives, and most of the northern plants are improved by being transplanted thither." Says Lane, the Governor of Raleigh colony, in 1585, speaking of Virginia and Carolina: "It is the goodliest soil under the cope of heaven, the most pleasing territory of the world. The climate is so wholesome that we have not one sick since we touched the land. If Virginia had but horses and kine, and were inhabited with English, no realm in Christendom were comparable to it." Such was the country which slavery took two hundred years ago: and any quantity of testimony to its fertility could be quoted. Mark the change which slavery has made. Says Washington (letter to Arthur Young, Nov. 1, 1787). "Our lands, as I mentioned to you, were originally very good, but use and abuse have made them quite otherwise." Says Olmsted (Seaboard Slave States, pages 63 and 65), speaking of the lands, stock, and vehicles of a certain locality in eastern Virginia in 1855: "Oldfields'—a coarse, yellow, sandy soil, bearing scarce anything but pine trees and broom-sedge. In some places, for acres, the pines would not be above five feet high—that was land that had been in cultivation, used up, and 'turned out' not more than six or eight years before; then there were patches of every age; sometimes the trees were a hundred feet high. At long intervals there were fields in which the pine was just beginning to spring in beautiful green plumes from the ground, and was yet hardly noticeable among the dead brown grass and sassafras bushes and blackberry vines, which nature first sends to hide the nakedness of the impoverished earth. "Of living creatures, for miles, not one was to be seen (not even a crow or a snow-bird), except hogs. These—long, lank, snake-headed, hairy, wild beasts—would come dashing across our path, in packs of from three to a dozen, with short hasty grunts, almost always at a gallop, and looking neither to the right nor left, as if they were in pursuit of a fox, and were quite certain to catch him in the next hundred yards." (Number of swine in Virginia in 1850, 1,829,843.) "We turned the corner, following some slight traces of a road, and shortly afterwards met a curious vehicular establishment, probably belonging to the master of the hounds. It consisted of an axle-tree and wheels, and a pair of shafts, made of unbarked saplings, in which was harnessed, by attachments of raw-hide and rope, a single small ox. There was a bit made of telegraph wire in his mouth, by which he was guided, through the mediation of a pair of much knotted rope-reins, by a white man—a dignified sovereign wearing a brimless crown —who sat upon a two-bushel sack (of meal, I hope, for the hounds' sake), balanced upon the axle-tree; and who saluted me with a frank 'How are you?' as we came opposite each other." Said Henry A. Wise, in 1855, during his canvass for Govenor, speaking to the Virginians: "You all own plenty of land, but it is poverty added to poverty. Poor land added to poor land, and nothing added to nothing makes nothing; while the owner is talking politics at Richmond, or in Congress, or spending the summer at the White Springs, the lands grow poorer and poorer, and this soon brings land, negroes, and all, under the hammer. You have the owners skinning the negroes, and the negroes skinning the land, until all grow poor together. "You have relied alone on the single power of agriculture, and such agriculture! Your sedge-patches outshine the sun; your inattention to your only source of wealth has scared the bosom of mother Earth. Instead of having to feed cattle on a thousand hills, you have to chase the stump-tailed steer through the sedge-patches to procure a tough beef-steak." (Number of neat cattle in Virginia, in 1850, 1,076,269.) "I have heard a story—I will not locate it here or there— about the condition of the prosperity of our agriculture. I was told by a gentleman in Washington, not long ago, that he was travelling in a county not a hundred miles from this place, and overtook one of our citizens on horseback, with perhaps, a bag of hay for a saddle, without stirrups, and the leading line for a bridle, and he said, 'Stranger, whose house is that?' 'It is mine,' was the reply. They came to another. 'Whose house is that?' 'Mine, too, stranger.' To a third, 'And whose house is that?' 'That's mine, too, stranger; but don't suppose I'm so darned poor as to own all the land about here.' " Wise was speaking at Alexandria, in Fairfax Co., the county of Mount Vernon, and the farm of Washington. In certain parts, this county has been wonderfully improved by Northern emigrants, who have purchased lands and applied free labor and skill to them. So much have they improved their portion, that the Patent Office Report says, "A traveller who passed over it ten years ago would not now recognize it." Says the Hon. Willoughby Newton, of Virginia, in his agricultural address, in 1850: "I look upon the introduction of guano, and the success attending its application to our barren lands, in the light of a special interposition of Divine Providence, to save the northern neck of Virginia from reverting into its former state of wilderness and utter desolation. Until the discovery of guano—more valuable to us than the mines of California—I looked upon the possibility of renovating our soil, of ever bringing it to a point capable of producing remunerating crops, as utterly hopeless." Is Virginia to be saved by guano? Mr. Newton recommends the application of two hundred pounds per acre. Number of acres of land under cultivation in Virginia in 1850, 26,152,311. Amount of guano requisite to cover this land, at the rate of two hundred pounds per acre, 2,615,231 tons. This, at $50 per ton, would cost $130,761,550. Guano must be applied every other year. This would give the annual amount 1,307,615 tons, and the annual cost $65,380,775. Where is the money to pay this annual tax to come from? How long would it take the permanent registered tonnage of Virginia (9,246 tons in 1855) to import enough for one year's use? And then the spectacle of this magnificent fleet (of eighteen vessels of five hundred tons, or thirty of three hundred), officered by the chivalry, and manned by slaves, toting bird-manure around Cape Horn, in quantities enough to cover the worn-out surface of the Old Dominion! Of North Carolina, the Patent Office Report for 1851 says (communication of G. S. Sullivan, of Lincoln Co.), "We raise no stock of any kind except for home consumption, and not half enough of that; for we have now worn out our lands so much, that we do not grow food enough to maintain them." Of Alabama (communication of N. B. Powell): "We are the most dependent people in the Union, rely mainly, as we do, upon our neighbors of the West for nearly all our supplies." Says Olmsted (page 475) of the threshing of rice in South Carolina: "Threshing commences immediately after harvest, and on many plantations proceeds very tediously, in the old way of threshing wheat with flails by hand, occupying the best of the plantation force for the most of the winter. It is done on an earthen floor in the open air, and the rice is cleaned by carrying it on the heads of the negroes, by a ladder, up on to a platform, twenty feet from the ground, and pouring it slowly down, so that the wind will drive off the chaff, and leave the grain in a heap under the platform." Threshing machines have, however, been introduced on some large plantations. Of Alabama, says Hon. C. C. Clay, Jr., a politician and leading man, in an address in 1855: "I can show you, with sorrow, in the older portions, of Alabama, and in my native county of Madison, the sad memorials of the artless and exhausting culture of cotton. Our small planters, after taking the cream off their lands, unable to restore them by rest, manures, or otherwise, are going farther west and south, in search of other virgin lands, which they may and will despoil and impoverish in like manner." "In 1825, Madison county cast about 3,000 votes; now she cannot cast exceeding 2,300. In traversing that county, one will discover numerous farm-houses, once the abode of industrious and intelligent freemen, now occupied by slaves, or tenantless, deserted, and dilapidated; he will observe fields, once fertile, now unfenced, abandoned, and covered with those evil harbingers—fox-tail and broom-sedge; he will see the moss growing on the mouldering walls of once thrifty villages; and will find 'one only master grasps the whole domain' that once furnished happy homes for a dozen white families. Indeed, a county in its infancy, where fifty years ago scarce a forest tree had been felled by the axe of the pioneer, is already exhibiting the painful signs of senility and decay, apparent in Virginia and the Carolinas; the freshness of its agricultural glory is gone; the vigor of its youth is extinct, and the spirit of desolation seems brooding over it." Enough of these extracts to show the blight of slavery in the department of agriculture; no extracts are needed to show that the farms in the Free States increase in value with every succeeding year. It is not now necessary "that a herring be put into the hole" with corn, "or it will not come up."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER V. MANUFACTURES. The tables in this chapter, compiled—when no other authority is given—from the Compendium of the Census of 1850, show the state of manufactures in the United States for the year ending June, 1850. The tables for 1850 are preceded by tables (from the annual Report of the Secretary of the Treasury on the Finances, for 1855) giving the population, and value of the manufactures, of the several Free and Slave States for the years 1820 and 1840. The returns for 1820 were defective in some particulars, and the article of sugar is included among the manufactures for 1840. TABLE XVII. Population and Value of Manufactures in the Free States, for the years 1820 and 1840. FREE STATES. Population in 1820. Population in 1840. Value of Manufactures for 1820. Value of Manufactures for 1840. Connecticut 275,202 309,978 $2,413,029 $21,057,523 Illinois 55,211 476,183 100,983 8,021,582 Indiana 147,178 685,866 397,814 9,379,586 Iowa 43,112 483,700 Maine 298,335 501,793 486,473 14,525,217 Massachusetts 523,287 737,699 2,523,614 73,777,837 Michigan 8,896 212,267 100,460 3,898,676 New Hampshire 244,161 284,574 747,959 10,523,313 New Jersey 277,575 373,306 1,175,139 19,571,496 New York 1,372,812 2,428,921 9,792,072 95,840,194 Ohio 581,434 1,519,467 5,290,427 31,458,401 Pennsylvania 1,049,458 1,724,033 6,895,219 64,494,960 Rhode Island 83,059 108,830 1,617,221 13,807,297 Vermont 235,764 291,948 890,353 6,923,982 Wisconsin 30,945 1,680,808 Total 5,152,372 9,698,922 $32,430,763 $375,444,572 TABLE XVIII. Population and Value of Manufactures in the Slave States, for the years 1820 and 1840. SLAVE STATES. Population in 1820. Population in 1840. Value of Manufactures for 1820. Value of Manufactures for 1840. Alabama 127,901 590,756 $101,207 $4,975,871 Arkansas 14,273 97,574 56,408 2,614,889 Delaware 72,749 78,085 1,318,891 2,709,068 Florida 54,477 915,080 Georgia 340,987 691,392 607,751 5,324,307 Kentucky 564,317 779,828 2,296,726 13,221,958 Louisiana 153,407 352,411 272,500 11,378,383 Maryland 407,350 470,019 5,027,336 13,509,636 Mississippi 75,448 375,651 none. 3,562,370 Missouri 66,586 383,702 297,443 5,946,759 North Carolina 638,829 753,419 445,398 7,234,567 South Carolina 502,741 359,000 168,666 5,638,823 Tennessee 422,813 829,210 2,352,127 8,517,394 Virginia 1,065,379 1,239,797 6,686,699 20,684,608 Total 4,452,780 7,055,321 $19,631,152 $106,233,713 Taking tables XX. and XIX. without the modifications suggested hereafter, and the relation of the North and South to manufactures in 1850, was as follows, viz: In the North. In the South. Capital invested in manufactures $430,240,051 $95,029,879 Value of raw material used 465,844,092 86,190,639 Number of hands employed, males 576,954 140,377 " " " females 203,622 21,360 Annual wages 195,976,453 33,257,560 " products 842,586,058 165,413,027 " profit 376,741,966 79,222,388 " profit per cent 42 44 " wages per hand, males and females 251 206 " product " " " 1,079 1,029 " profit " " " 484 489 From this aggregate of Southern manufactures should be deducted the manufactures of certain counties where there is a large or predominating free population born out of the limits of TABLE XIX. A Statement of the Number of Individuals and Establishments engaged in Manufactures, the Amount of Capital invested in such Establishments, the Value of the Raw Material used, the Number of Hands employed, the Annual Wages paid, the Annual Product and the Annual Profit of such Manufactures, in the several Free States, according to the Census Returns of 1850. FREE STATES. Number of Individuals and Establishments. Capital. Value of Raw Material used. Hands Employed. Annual wages. Annual Product. Annual Profit, according to De Bow. Male. Female. California 1,003 $1,006,197 $1,201,154 3,964 $3,485,820 $12,862,522 $11,661,368 Connecticut 3,482 23,890,348 23,589,397 31,287 16,483 11,695,236 45,110,102 21,520,705 Illinois 3,164 6,385,387 8,915,173 11,632 433 3,826,249 17,236,073 8,320,900 Indiana 4,288 7,941,602 10,214,337 13,677 665 2,809,116 18,922,651 8,708,314 Iowa 522 1,292,875 2,356,881 1,687 20 473,016 3,551,783 1,194,902 Maine 3,977 14,700,452 13,555,806 21,856 6,222 7,502,916 24,664,135 11,108,329 Massachusetts 8,259 83,357,642 85,856,771 96,261 69,677 39,784,116 151,137,145 65,280,374 Michigan 1,963 6,534,250 6,105,561 8,930 360 2,387,928 10,976,894 4,871,333 New Hampshire 3,211 18,242,114 12,745,466 14,103 12,989 6,123,876 23,164,503 10,419,037 New Jersey 4,108 22,184,730 21,992,186 28,549 8,762 9,202,788 39,713,586 17,721,400 New York 23,553 99,904,405 134,655,674 147,737 51,612 49,131,000 237,597,249 102,941,575 Ohio 10,622 29,019,538 34,677,937 47,054 4,435 13,467,660 62,647,259 27,969,322 Pennsylvania 21,605 94,473,810 87,206,377 124,688 22,078 37,163,232 155,044,910 67,838,533 Rhode Island 853 12,923,176 13,183,889 12,837 8,044 5,008,656 22,093,258 8,909,369 Vermont 1,849 5,001,377 4,172,552 6,894 1,551 2,202,348 8,570,920 4,398,368 Wisconsin 1,262 3,382,148 5,414,931 5,798 291 1,712,496 9,293,068 3,878,137 Total 93,721 $430,240,051 $465,844,092 576,954 203,622 $195,976,453 $842,586,058 $376,741,966 TABLE XX. A Statement of the Number of Individuals and Establishments engaged in Manufactures, the Amount of Capital invested in such Establishments, the Value of the Raw material used, the Number of Hands employed, the Annual Wages paid, the Annual Product and the Annual Profit of such Manufactures, in the several Slave States, according to the Returns of 1850. SLAVE STATES. Number of Individuals and Establishments. Capital. Value of Raw Material used. Hands Employed. Annual wages. Annual Product. Annual Profit, according to De Bow. Male. Female. Alabama 1,026 $3,450,606 $2,224,960 4,399 539 $1,106,112 $4,538,878 $2,313,918 Arkansas 272 324,065 268,564 873 30 169,356 607,436 338,872 Delaware 531 2,978,945 2,864,607 3,227 651 936,924 4,649,296 1,784,689 Florida 103 547,060 220,611 876 115 199,452 668,335 447,724 Georgia 1,527 5,460,483 3,404,917 6,660 1,718 1,712,304 7,086,525 3,681,608 Kentucky 3,609 12,350,734 12,170,225 22,445 1,940 4,764,096 24,588,483 12,418,258 Louisiana 1,017 5,318,074 2,958,988 5,581 856 2,086,212 7,320,948 4,361,960 Maryland 3,708 14,753,143 17,326,734 22,641 7,483 7,374,672 32,477,702 15,140,968 Mississippi 877 1,833,420 1,290,271 3,065 108 775,128 2,972,038 1,682,767 Missouri 3,029 9,079,695 12,446,738 15,997 873 3,184,764 23,749,265 11,302,527 North Carolina 2,604 7,252,225 4,805,463 10,693 1,751 1,796,748 9,111,245 4,305,782 South Carolina 1,431 6,056,865 2,809,534 5,935 1,074 1,128,432 7,063,513 4,253,979 Tennessee 2,861 6,975,279 4,900,952 11,154 878 2,277,228 9,728,438 4,827,486 Texas 309 539,290 394,642 1,042 24 322,368 1,165,538 770,896 Virginia 4,741 18,109,993 18,103,433 25,789 3,320 5,413,764 29,705,387 11,601,954 Total 27,645 $95,029,879 $86,190,639 140,377 21,360 $33,257,560 $165,413,027 $79,222,388 the several States in which the counties are situated. The amount of the manufactures, and the character of the population, as regards birth, of the most important of these counties, is shown in the following table. Even this deduction leaves too large a balance for Southern manufactures, proper, for everywhere throughtout the South the most thriving manufactures were founded, or are sustained, by Northern capital, skill, or labor. TABLE XXI. A Statement of the Number of Free Inhabitants born within and without certain Counties of the Slave States, in which there is a large or predominating exotic Population, with the Amount of Capital invested in Manufacture, Number of Hands Employed, and the Annual Product thereof in 1850. COUNTIES. Free Population born, out of the State in which each Co. is situated. Do. born in the State. Capital. Hands Employed. Annual Product. Newcastle, Del 13,801 28,555 $2,593,830 3,235 $3,945,399 Baltimore, Md 61,472 142,456 9,929,332 23,863 24,540,014 Ohio, Va 9,020 8,822 1,184,111 2,493 2,401,434 Charleston, S. C 7,844 21,225 1,487,800 1,413 2,749,961 Muscogee, Geo 2,589 7,833 713,217 719 738,580 Richmond, Geo 3,252 5,183 775,600 995 1,020,651 Mobile, Ala 10,379 7,865 522,800 540 1,261,450 Orleans, La 68,525 32,867 2,969,660 3,134 4,470,454 Galveston, Texas 2,907 908 46,450 131 207,100 Davidson, Tenn 7,716 16,991 855,015 1,219 1,075,287 Shelby, Tenn 9,077 7,720 424,130 789 840,789 Jefferson, Ky 30,174 18,746 4,115,582 8,865 11,002,103 St. Louis, Mo 71,617 27,394 5,215,716 10,239 16,046,521 Total 298,373 326,565 $30,833,143 57,636 $70,296,743 This table includes the counties in which are situated the cities of Baltimore, Wheeling, Louisville, St. Louis, New Orleans, Mobile, Charleston, and some others. It will be seen that, in these counties, the free population born within and without the limits of each State, respectively, is nearly equal. The manufacturing establishments in these counties are generally confined to their cities, and a table showing the origin of the free population of the cities only, would give a large preponderance of persons born without the limits of their respective States. The means of constructing such a table are not accessible. There are, besides, other counties of smaller size which should be included with those in the foregoing table. These are necessarily omitted. Deducting the aggregates of this table from the total manufactures reported for the South, and there are left for the manufactures of the Slave States, Capital, $64,196,736 Hands employed, males and females, 104,101 Annual product, $95,116,284 Annual product per head, 914 Adding the aggregates of table XXI. to those reported above for the manufactures of the North, and the total manufactures of the free population of the United States, will be: Capital, $461,073,194 Hands employed, males and females, 838,212 Annual product, $912,882,801 Annual product per head, 1,089 Further amendment of these aggregates should be made by adding for California—in which State the marshal's returns for 1850 were generally defective, and for the most important localities lost or destroyed by fire—the following estimates, based on the returns of the State census for that State, taken in 1852, and ordered by Congress to be made a part of the National census, viz: Capital, $5,942,526 Annual product, 30,000,000 The true total, then, of the manufactures of the free population of the United States for 1850 will be: Capital invested, $467,015,720 Hands employed, males and females, 838,212 Annual product, $942,882,801 Thus, then, in seven times the capital invested, in eight times the number of hands employed, in ten times the annual product, is the triumph of freedom over slavery seen in the department of manufactures. And this, after allowing to slavery millions of the capital of the North, thousands of its intelligent mechanics and operatives, and hundreds of its inventions and improvements, scattered throughout the South, wherever machinery is in motion, or labor skillfully applied to it. And this stagnation and sleep of slavery beneath the thundering of its thousands of waterfalls, and beside its millions of cotton bales. Well did Governor Wise say to the Virginians: "You have the line of the Alleghanies, that beautiful ridge which stands placed there by the Almighty, not to obstruct the way of people to market, but placed there in the very bounty of Providence, to milk the clouds, to make the sweet springs which are the sources of your rivers. And at the head of every stream is the waterfall, murmuring the very music of your power. And yet commerce has long ago spread her sails and sailed away from you; you have not as yet dug more than coal enough to warm yourselves at your own hearths; you have no tilt-hammer of Vulcan, to strike blows worthy of gods in the iron foundries. You have not yet spun more than coarse cotton enough to clothe your own slaves. You have had no commerce, no mining, no manufactures." (Speech at Alexandria, 1855.) Table XXII. contains a list of those counties in the Free and Slave States which had, in 1850, the greatest relative amount of manufactures. The areas given are from Baldwin and Thomas' Gazetteer of 1854; the value of the land is ascertained by dividing the value given in the Census Compendium by the whole area. The Southern counties taken are such as have no large admixture of exotic population. In these counties are included the important cities of Wilmington, N. C., Lynchburg, Va., and Clarksville, Tenn. TABLE XXII. Counties in the Free and Slave States which had, in 1850, the greatest relative Amount of Manufactures. Countries in Free States. Area in Square Miles. Population. Value of Farms. Annual Product of Manufactories. Value of Land per Acre. Average Product of Manufactures per head of whole population. Bristol, Mass 517 76,192 $7,101,582 $12,595,695 $21.46 $165 Essex, Mass 500 131,300 9,582,992 22,906,805 29.95 174 Middlesex, Mass 830 161,383 19,417,796 26,548,932 36.55 164 Norfolk, Mass 520 78,892 13,748,505 13,323,595 41.31 169 Kent, R. I. 180 15,068 1,951,111 2,620,788 17.80 174 Hartford, Conn 807 69,967 14,004,683 10,888,780 27.12 156 N. Haven, Conn 620 65,588 10,413,662 11,283,816 26.24 172 Essex, N. J. 450 73,950 7,219,566 16,293,198 25,07 220 Passaic, N. J. 270 22,569 3,302,051 4,213,669 19.11 187 Total 4,684 694,909 $86,741,948 $120,675,308 $28.94 $174 Counties in Slaves States. Campbell, Va 576 23,245 $2,452,604 $1,839,307 $6.65 $79 N. Hanover, N.C. 1,000 17,668 1,035,874 1,409,568 1.62 80 M'tgomery, Ten. 550 21,045 1,359,836 1,376,300 3.86 65 Total 2.126 61,958 $4,848,314 $4,625,175 $3.56 $74 Tables XXIII. and XXIV. show the value of the manufactures of cotton, wool, iron, the fisheries, and salt, in 1850. It is to be regretted that the returns of the details of the other branches of manufactures have not yet been published by Congress. These tables will repay a careful examination. Table XXV. gives the value of the domestic manufactures in the several Free and Slave States, for the year ending June, 1850; and gives also the annual increase of slaves in the several Slave States, with their value at $400 per head. It is to be understood that a larger proportion of slaves is born in the slave-raising States, and a smaller in the slave-consuming States, than is shown by the tables. As to this product of Southern labor, or skill, or necessity—the annual slave product—it may be classed indifferently under the head of agriculture, manufactures, or commerce. As live TABLE XXIII. A Statement of the Value of the Manufactures of Cotton, Wool, Pig Iron, Iron Castings, Wrought Iron, and of the Products of the Fisheries and Salt Manufactures, in the several Free States, for the year ending June, 1850, with the average Wages per month of the Hands employed. FREE STATES. Value of Cotton Manufactures. Value of Woollen Manufactures. Value of Manufactures of Pig Iron. Value of Manufactures of Iron Casting. Value of Manufactures of Wrought Iron. Value of Products of the Fisheries. Value of Salt Manufactures. Wages per month in Cotton Manufactures. Wages per month in Woollen Manufactures. Wages per month in Manufactures of Pig Iron.—Males. Wages per month in Manufactures of Iron Casting.—Males. Males. Females. Males. Females. California $20,740 $23.38 Connecticut $4,257,522 $6,465,216 $415,600 981,400 $847,196 $1,734,483 $5,600 19.08 $11.80 $24.12 $12.86 $26.80 27.02 Illinois 206,572 70,200 441,185 6,000 22.00 12.52 22.06 28.50 Indiana 44,200 205,802 58,000 149,430 11,760 13.02 6.77 21.81 11.05 26.00 25.74 Iowa 13,000 8,500 11.14 32.35 Maine 2,596,356 753,300 36,616 265,000 569,876 9,700 29.35 12.15 22.57 11.77 22.00 29.00 Massachusetts 19,712,461 12,770,565 295,123 2,235,635 3,908,952 6,606,849 93,850 22.90 13.60 22.95 14.22 27.52 30.90 Michigan 90,242 21,000 279,697 72,775 21.65 11.47 35.00 28.68 New Hampshire 8,830,619 2,127,745 6,000 371,710 20,400 59,281 26.00 13.47 22.86 14.53 18.00 33.05 New Jersey 1,109,524 1,164,446 560,544 686,430 1,079,576 17.98 9.56 25.22 8.60 21.20 24.00 New York 3,591,989 7,030,604 597,920 5,921,980 3,758,547 484,345 998,315 18.32 9.68 19.97 11.76 25.00 27.49 Ohio 394,700 1,111,027 1,255,850 3,069,350 127,849 27,565 132,293 16.59 9.42 20.14 10.90 24.48 27.32 Pennsylvania 5,322,262 5,321,866 6,071,513 5,354,881 9,224,256 206,796 17.85 9.91 19.43 10.41 21.65 27.55 Rhode Island 6,447,120 2,381,825 728,705 223,650 64,430 18.60 12.95 20.70 15.18 29.63 Vermont 196,100 1,579,161 68,000 460,831 127,886 15.53 12.65 24.46 11.81 22.08 28.27 Wisconsin 87,992 27,000 216,195 16,875 22.48 30.00 26.73 Total $52,502,853 $41,309,363 $9,483,366 $21,191,669 $19,330,072 $9,636,479 $1,452,554 TABLE XXIV. A Statement of the Value of the Manufactures of Cotton, Wool, Pig Iron, Iron Castings, Wrought Iron, and of the Products of the Fisheries and Salt Manufactories, of the several Slave States, for the year ending June, 1850, with the average Wages per month of the Hands employed. SLAVE STATES. Value of Cotton Manufactures. Value of Woollen Manufactures. Value of Manufac tures of Pig Iron. Value of Manufactures of Iron Casting. Value of Manufactures of Wrought Iron. Value of products of the Fisheries. Value of Salt Manufactures. Wages per month in Cotton Manufactures. Wages per month in Woollen Manufactures. Wages per month in Manufactures of Iron Casting.—Males. Wages per month in Manufactures of Pig Iron.—Males. Males. Females. Males. Females. Alabama $382,260 $22,500 $271,126 $7,500 $11.71 $7.98 $17.60 $30.05 Arkansas 16,637 14.61 5.88 Delaware 538,439 $251,000 267,462 38,200 15.31 11.58 $18.79 $17,33 23.36 Maryland 2,120,504 295,140 1,056,400 685,000 771,431 15.42 9.42 18.60 11.89 20.14 27.50 Florida 49,920 $18,676 $6,000 32.14 5.00 Georgia 2,135,044 88,750 57,300 46,200 12,384 14.57 7.39 27.47 14.10 17.44 27.43 Kentucky 273,439 318,819 604,037 744,316 299,700 57,825 14.95 9.36 15.30 11.11 20.23 24.89 Louisiana 312,500 35.60 Mississippi 30,500 117,400 14.21 5.94 37.91 Missouri 142,900 56,000 314,600 336,495 68,700 10.93 10.00 32.00 6.50 24.28 19.63 North Carolina 831,342 23,750 12,500 12,867 331,914 250,025 11.65 6.13 18.00 7.00 8.00 23.46 South Carolina 748,338 87,683 13.94 8.30 13.59 Tennessee 510,624 6,310 576,100 264,325 670,618 10.94 6.42 17.66 6.00 12.81 17.96 Texas 15,000 55,000 5,900 20.00 20.00 43.43 Virginia 1,486,384 841,013 521,924 674,416 1,098,252 95,002 700,466 10.18 6.98 18.17 9.91 12.76 19.91 Total $9,266,331 $1,895,782 $3,264,961 $3,874,790 $3,298,699 $363,703 $770,191 TABLE XXV. A Statement of the Value of the domestic Manufactures of the several Free and Slave States for the years 1850; with the average Annual Increase, and Value at $400 per head, of Slaves, for the ten years ending June, 1850. FREE STATES. Value of Domestic Manufactures for 1850. SLAVE STATES. Value of Domestic Manufactures for 1850. Annual Increase of Slaves from 1840 to 1850. Value at $400 per head. California $7,000 Alabama $1,934,120 8,931 $3,572,400 Connecticut 192,252 Arkansas 938,217 2,717 1,086,800 Illinois 1,155,902 Delaware 38,121 31 12,400 Indiana 1,631,039 Florida 75,582 1,359 543,600 Iowa 221,292 Georgia 1,838,968 10,074 4,029,600 Maine 513,599 Kentucky 2,459,128 2,872 1,148,800 Massachusetts 205,333 Louisiana 139,232 7,638 8,054,400 Michigan 340,947 Maryland 111,828 63 25,200 N. Hampshire 393,455 Mississippi 1,164,020 11,467 4,586,800 New Jersey 112,781 Missouri 1,674,705 2,918 1,167,200 New York 1,280,333 North Carolina 2,086,522 4,273 1,709,200 Ohio 1,712,196 South Carolina 909,525 5,795 2,318,000 Pennsylvania 749,132 Tennessee 3,137,790 5,640 2,256,000 Rhode Island 26.495 Texas 266,984 5,816 2,326,400 Vermont 267,710 Virginia 2,156,312 2,344 937,600 Wisconsin 43,624 Total $8,853,090 Total $18,631,054 71,936 $28,774,400 stock raised and fattened for market, it would seem to belong legitimately to the department of agriculture; as an article of trade, to commerce; but a better arrangement is to class it with domestic manufactures, that class of manufactures in which it will be seen that the South is ahead. In this work, then, the slave product is classed with domestic manufactures, and its value—no estimate having been made by De Bow— computed from the best authorities, will be included in the aggregates for that branch of manufactures. The number of slaves annually manufactured by the Northern Slave States for the Southern markets is given elsewhere as 25,000; their value at $400 per head is $10,000,000. This is a small estimate both as to number and value. As to the capital invested, the value of the raw material used, the number of hands employed, and the annual wages paid in this species of manufacture, the census tables give no information.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER VI. COMMERCE. It is difficult to apportion the results of commerce to the several States. The statistics of the great branch of domestic or internal commerce are very incomplete; the returns of the minor branch of foreign or external commerce are more full. De Bow suggests that "half the agricultural products and all of the manufacturing are subjects of commerce, and that the whole commercial movement may be estimated at between $1,500,000,000 and $2,000,000,000" annually. Adopting this suggestion, the value of the products which enter into the commerce of the two sections, for 1850, would be as follows, viz: Free States, $1,377,199,968 Slave States, 410,754,992 Total, $1,787,954,960 No enumeration, by States, of the persons engaged in commerce, trade, and navigation, is given in the Compendium of the Census of 1850. In 1840, however, such enumeration was made, and is found in the published census returns for that year. The number of persons engaged in commerce, navigating the ocean, and in internal navigation, was in 1840 as follows, viz: Free States, 136,856 Slave States, 52,622 Total, 189,478 This would give, in 1850, as the number of persons engaged in commerce and navigation,— Free States, 188,271 Slave States, 70,165 Total, 258,436 Domestic commerce is carried on by the enrolled and licensed tonnage (with the participation, in a small proportion, of the registered), by railroads, canals, and public roads. Of enrolled and licensed tonnage, there were in 1850, in the Free States, 1,459,232 tons. Slave States, 475,405 " Total, 1,934,637 " Of railroads in operation in 1854, there were, miles, in the Free States, 13,105 Slave States, 4,212 Total, 17,317 Of canals, there were in 1854, miles, in the Free States, 3,682 Slave States, 1,116 Total, 4,798 There are no statistics of the miles of public roads in the two sections, or of the merchandise and produce transported over them. We may be aided in forming an estimate of the amount of our domestic commerce, by the following tabular statements, from Andrews' report: TABLE XXVI. Lake and River Commerce. 1851. NET. GROSS. Tons. Value. Tons. Value. Lake Commerce 1,985,563 $157,236,729 3,971,126 $314,473,458 River Commerce 2,033,400 169,751,372 4,066,800 339,502,744 Aggregate 4,018,963 $326,988,101 8,037,926 $653,976,202 Coasting Trade, Canal and Railway Commerce. Estimate of 1852. NET. GROSS. Tons. Value. Tons. Value. Coasting trade 20,397,490 $1,659,519,686 40,794,980 $3,319,039,372 Canal Commerce 9,000,000 594,000,000 18,000,000 1,188,000,000 Railway Commerce 5,407,500 540,750,000 10,815,000 1,081,500,000 Aggregate 34,804,990 $2,794,269,686 69,609,980 $1,588,539,372 It is estimated by Andrews that the number of tons of shipping engaged in the coasting trade is 2,039,749. This is the amount of the "enrolled and licensed tonnage." In addition, considerable "registered tonnage" frequently enters the coasting trade between the Atlantic ports and those on the Gulf and the Pacific. The "licensed tonnage" engaged in the lake commerce is 215,975 tons. The tonnage engaged in the river commerce is 169,450 tons. The foregoing figures are for the years 1851 and 1852. In a late report of the Committee on Commerce, it is stated that, "The lake tonnage for 1855 was 345,000 tons, which, valued at $45 per ton, is $14,838,000. The present value of lake commerce (exclusive of the ports of Presque Isle and Mackinac, not reported) is $608,310,320." Our foreign commerce is carried on by the registered tonnage of the United States, and by the tonnage of other nations. The foreign tonnage which entered the ports of the United States, in 1851, was 1,939,091 tons; the American tonnage, 3,054,349 tons. De Bow says, of 1851, that the value of merchandise imported in "foreign vessels was $52,563,083; in American Vessels $168,216,272." By this, it will be seen that something more than three-fourths of the value of our foreign commerce is carried on in American vessels. The registered tonnage of the two sections, in 1850 was, in the Free States, 1,330,963 tons. Slave States, 250,880 " Total, 1,581,843" We may now approximate the truth in regard to the commerce of the two sections of our country in three ways. First.Taking the value of the products which enter into commerce, we find the North has $1,377,199,968; the South $410,754,992, giving the North more than three to one. Second.Taking the number of persons engaged in trade, and the North has 136,856 persons, the South 52,622 persons, giving the North nearly three to one, and this on the supposition that the average amount of business done by merchants in the South is as great as in the North. Third.Taking the tonnage, miles of railroads, and canals: the North had, in 1850, 2,790,195 tons of registered, enrolled and licensed tonnage, the South 726,285 tons. (The amount of tonnage in 1855 was, in the North 4,252,615 tons, in the South 855,517 tons.) The North had in 1854, 13,105 miles of railroad in operation, the South 4,212 miles. The North had in the same year 3,682 miles of canals, the South 1,116 miles. This gives a ratio of something more than three to one in favor of the North. It may, we think, be fairly assumed that the amount of commerce and its profits in the two sections are quite four times as much in the North as in the South. We have thus shown, from such data as could be obtained, the relative proportion of the domestic and foreign commerce of the Free and Slave States. Adopting the suggestion of De Bow (as to the value of the "commercial movement"), the domestic commerce of the United States, in 1850, was six times that of the foreign. The figures are as follows: Value of manufactures and half of agricultual products, $1,787,954,960 Value of imports, 178,078,499 Total, 1,966,033,459 Total value of imports and exports, 329,896,631 Adopting the estimates of Andrews (Report on Lake Commerce), the domestic commerce of the United States, in 1851–2, was nearly eight times the foreign. The figures are as follows, viz: Value of lake and river commerce, $326,988,101 Value of coasting trade, railway and canal commerce, 2,794,269,686 Value of imports, 1851, 216,224,932 Total, 3,337,482,719 Total value of imports and exports, 1851, 434,612,943 It is, perhaps, not far from right to call the domestic commerce of this country seven times the foreign. Tables XXVII. and XXVIII. give the value of the exports and imports of the several Free and Slave States for 1850 and 1855; and the amount and value of tonnage owned and built in the same years. The tables are compiled from the annual report on commerce and navigation. The statistics of exports and imports show the foreign commerce of the several States. The aggregates for the two years given are— Free States, $631,396,034 Slave States, 234,936,306 Total, $866,332,340 being nearly three times as much in the North as in the South. TABLE XXVII. A Statement of the Value of the Exports and Imports of the Several Free States, for the years ending June 30, 1850, and June 30, 1855, with the Tonnage owned in said States at those dates, and the Tonnage built therein during said years, with its Value. FREE STATES. Value of Exports for the year ending June 30, 1850. Value of Imports for the year ending June 30, 1850. Value of Exports for the year ending June 30, 1855. Value of Imports for the year ending June 30, 1855. Tonnage owned June 30, 1850. Value at $50 per ton. Tonnage built for the year ending June 30, 1850. Value at $50 per ton. Tonnage owned June 30, 1855 Value at $50 per ton. Tonnage built for the year ending June 30, 1855. Value at $50 per ton. Maine $1,556,912 $856,411 $4,851,207 $2,927,443 501,422 $25,071,100 91,212 $4,560,600 806,587 $40,329,350 215,905 $10,795,250 N. Hampshire 8,927 49,079 1,523 17,786 23,096 1,154,800 6,914 345,700 30,330 1,516,500 8,928 496,400 Vermont 430,906 463,092 2,895,468 591,593 4,530 226,500 77 3,850 6,915 345,750 none. Massachusetts 10,681,763 30,374,684 28,190,925 45,113,774 685,442 34,272,100 35,836 1,791,800 970,727 48,536,350 79,670 3,983,500 Rhode Island 216,265 258,303 336,023 536,387 40,489 2,024,450 3,587 179,350 51,038 2,551,900 7,862 393,100 Connecticut 241,930 372,390 878,874 636,826 113,087 5,654,350 4,820 241,000 137,170 6,858,500 14,067 703,350 New York 52,712,789 111,123,524 113,731,238 164,776,511 944,349 47,217,450 58,342 2,917,100 1,404,221 70,211,050 115,231 5,761,550 New Jersey 1,655 1,494 687 1,473 80,300 4,015,000 6,202 310,100 121,020 6,051,000 10,960 548,000 Pennsylvania 4,501,606 12,066,154 6,274,333 15,309,935 258,039 12,901,950 21,410 1,070,500 397,768 19,888,400 44,415 2,220,750 Ohio 217,632 582,504 847,143 600,656 62,462 3,123,100 5,215 260,750 91,607 4,580,350 17,751 887,550 Michigan 132,045 144,102 568,091 281,379 33,145 1,907,250 2,062 103,100 69,490 3,474,500 7,844 392,200 Wisconsin 174,057 48,159 15,624 781,200 1,452 72,600 Illinois 17,669 15,705 547,053 54,509 21,242 1,062,100 1,691 84,550 53,797 2,689,850 1,903 95,150 California 8,224,066 5,951,379 17,592 879,600 92,623 4,631,150 2,118 105,900 Indiana 3,698 184,900 738 36,900 Total $70,720,099 $156,307,442 $167,520,693 $236,847,810 2,790,195 $139,509,750 237,368 $11,868,400 4,252,615 $212,630,750 528,844 $26,442,200 TABLE XXVIII. A Statement of the Value of the Exports and Imports of the several Slave States for the years 1850 and 1855, and of the Tonnage owned in said States on the 30th of June, 1850 and 1855, and of the Tonnage built therein for the years ending June 30, 1850, and June 30, 1855, with the Value of said Tonnage. SLAVE STATES. Value of Exports for the year ending June 30, 1850. Value of Imports for the year ending June 30, 1850. Value of Exports for the year ending June 30, 1855. Value of Imports for the year ending June 30, 1855. Tonnage owned June 30, 1850. Value at $50 per ton. Tonnage built for the year ending June 30, 1850. Value at per ton. Tonnage owned June 30, 1855 Value at $50 per ton. Tonnage built for the year ending June 30, 1855 Value at $50 per ton. Delaware $68,087 $5,821 16,720 $886,000 1,849 $92,450 19.186 $959,300 5,488 $274,400 Maryland $6,967,353 $6,124,201 10,395,984 7,788,949 193,087 9,654,350 15,965 798,250 234,805 11,740,250 22,534 1,126,700 Virginia 3,415,646 426,599 4,379,928 855,405 74,071 3,703,550 3,584 179,200 92,788 4,639,400 4,603 230,150 North Carolina 416,501 323,692 433,818 243,088 45,219 2,261,950 2,652 132,600 60,077 3,003,850 2,595, 129,750 South Carolina 11,447,800 1,933,785 12,700,250 1,588,542 36, 072 1,803,600 60,935 3,046,750 61 3,050 Georgia 7,551,943 636,964 7,543,519 273,716 21,690 1,084,500 684 34,200 29,505 1,475,250 195 9,750 Florida 2,623,624 95,709 1,403,594 45,998 11,273 563,650 80 4,000 14,835 741,750 275 13,750 Alabama 10,544,858 865,362 14,270,585 619,964 24,158 1,207,900 114 5,700 36,274 1,813,700 729 36,450 Louisiana 38,105,350 10,760,499 55,367,962 12,900,821 250,090 12,504,500 1,592 79,600 204,149 10,207,450 872 43,600 Mississippi 1,661 1,828 91,400 2,475 123,750 370 18,500 Tennessee 27,966 3,776 188,800 8,404 420,200 428 21,400 Missouri 359,643 20,908 1,445,400 1,354 67,700 60,592 3,029,600 5,084 254,200 Kentucky 190,987 14,820 741,000 6,461 323,050 22,680 1,134,000 9,401 470,050 Texas 24,958 25,650 916,961 262,568 4,573 228,650 106 5,300 8,812 440,600 324 16,200 Total $81,098,033 $21,771,057 $107,480,688 $24,586,528 726,285 $36,314,250 34,441 $1,722,050 855,517 $42,775,850 52,959 $2,647,950 The tonnage of the two sections in 1855 was as follows, viz. Free States, 4,252,615 tons. Slave States, 855,517 " Total, 5,108,132 " being five times as much in the North as in the South. The foreign commerce of New York alone, for 1855, was as follows, viz: Exports, $113,731,238 Imports, 164,776,511 Total, $278,507,749 The foreign commerce of the Slave States for 1855 was as follows, viz: Exports, $107,480,688 Imports, 24,586,528 Total, $132,067,216 This statement shows that the foreign commerce of New York, in 1855, was more than twice that of all the Slave States. The tonnage of New York in 1855 was 1,404,221 tons. The tonnage of the Slave States for the same year, 855,517 " Or a little more than half that of the State of New York. The foreign commerce of Massachusetts and South Carolina, for 1855, was as follows, viz: MASSACHUSETTS. Exports, $28,190,925 Imports, 45,113,774 Total, $73,304,699 SOUTH CAROLINA. Exports, $12,700,250 Imports, 1,588,542 Total, $14,288,792 The tonnage of Massachusetts, in 1855, was 970,727 tons. The tonnage of South Carolina for the same year was 60,935 " The tonnage built in Massachusetts, in 1855, was 79,670 tons, valued at $3,983,500; the tonnage built in South Carol lina in the same year, was 61 tons, valued at $3,050. It will be observed by Tables XXVII. and XXVIII. that the large States of Indiana, Tennessee, Kentucky, and Missouri have no foreign commerce, and that the States of New Hampshire, New Jersey, Mississippi, and Delaware have very little. The tonnage built in 1855 was as follows, viz: Free States, 528,844 tons. Slave States, 52,959 " Total, 581,803 " The North, therefore, builds of tonnage ten times as much as the South. In 1855, the tonnage built in the State of Maine was more than four times that built in the South; Maine having built 215,905 tons, the Slave States 52,959 tons. Of the tonnage built in the South, more than four-fifths of it is built in ports where there is a large or predominating free population, born out of the limits of the States in which such ports are respectively situated, as in Baltimore, St. Louis, Louisville, Wheeling, etc. Making a proper deduction for this, and the amount of shipping annually built by the Slave States will not exceed 10,000 tons. Even this small amount is not the work of slaveholders, or slaves, or of the poor whites of the South, but of northern and foreign-born mechanics and ship carpenters. In case of a dissolution of the Union, and hostilities between the North and South, the highest naval science would need to be called into requisition by the South, so to station this naval armament of sloops, schooners, and steamboats as to command her seven thousand miles of exposed sea and gulf-coast. We close what we have to say on commerce, with the following extract from a letter of Mr. London, of Richmond, Va., to the Richmond Enquirer, and published in that paper early in 1854, just before the sitting of a Southern commercial convention at Charleston, S. C. He had been alluding to the sittings of other Southern commercial conventions at Memphis and elsewhere: "We have, since that time, appropriated millions of dollars to works of internal improvement; some of us have embarked more largely in foreign trade; but there are not half a dozen vessels engaged in our own trade that are owned in Virginia, and I have been unable to find a vessel at Liverpool loading for Virginia, within three years, during the height of our busy season. Every foot of railroad and every yard of canal constructed in the Southern States is only so much added to the area of the influence of New York, and but binds you that much more securely to her bonds. Instead of these immense improvements resulting in an enlargement of your foreign commerce, it is but a contribution to your coasting trade, and results in establishing the calculation as to how long it will take your shopkeepers to get the productions and importations of New York into your villages; all else but this is not considered. As to any one of your improvements contributing to forward your own importations, that is not thought of at all by your interior shopkeepers; for, throughout the South, all merchants have disappeared, entirely and completely."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER VII. VALUE OF REAL AND PERSONAL ESTATE. Tables XXIX. and XXX. give the value of the real and personal estate of the several States in 1850, according to the published census returns; the true value of the same as estimated by the superintendent of the census; the value of the slaves in the Slave States at $400 per head; and the value of the real and personal estate in 1856, as given by the Secretary of the Treasury in a communication to Congress at its late session. The estimate of $400 per head for slaves is, perhaps, too low. With a single apparent exception, the value of slaves is included by the compiler of the census returns in the value of personal estate. The exception is the State of Louisiana, in which State the value of the slaves is included in the value of real estate. With reference to the estimates of Mr. Secretary Guthrie, for Texas, it is hardly probable that its taxable property has gone up, in five years, from $55,362,340 to $240,000,000, an increase of about $200,000,000; while Iowa, which has increased in population since 1850 faster than any other State, is allowed an increase in taxable property of only $86,285,362, and Wisconsin of only $45,443,405. The valuation of Georgia is given by the secretary, not from the State valuation, but from an estimate of the governor of that State. The estimate for California is evidently too low, and is not according to any State valuation. In the case of Indiana, whose auditor, as quoted by Mr. Guthrie, says that a valuation at that time (November 24, 1855) would make the total taxables $380,000,000, the secretary, in 1856, gives the sum of $301,858,474, instead of the auditor's estimate, TABLE XXIX. A Statement of the Value of the Real and Personal Estate of the several Free States, and the True Value of the same in 1850; with the Value of the Real and Personal Estate of said States in 1856. FREE STATES. Value of Real Estate. 1850. Value of Personal Estate. 1850. Total Value of Real and Personal Estate. 1850. True Value of Real and Personal Estate, as given in Census Compendium. 1850. Value of Real and Personal Estate, as given by Secretary of Treasury. 1856. California $16,347,442 $5,575,731 $21,923,173 $22,161,872 $165,000,000 Connecticut 96,412,947 22,675,725 119,088,672 155,707,980 203,756,831 Illinois 81,524,835 33,257,810 114,782,645 156,265,006 333,237,474 Indiana 112,947,740 39,922,659 152,870,399 202,650,264 301,858,474 Iowa 15,672,332 6,018,310 21,690,642 23,714,638 110,000,000 Maine 64,336,119 32,463,434 96,799,553 122,777,571 131,128,186 Massachusetts 349,129,932 201,976,892 551,108,824 573,342,286 597,936,995 Michigan 25,580,371 5,296,852 30,877,223 59,787,255 116,593,580 New Hampshire 67,839,108 27,412,488 95,251,596 103,652,835 103,804,327 New Jersey 153,151,619 not returned. 153,151,619 153,151,619 179,750,000 New York 564,649,649 150,719,379 715,369,028 1,080,309,216 1,364,154,625 Ohio 337,521,075 96,351,557 433,872,632 504,726,120 860,877,354 Pennsylvania 427,865,660 72,410,191 500,275,851 729,144,998 1,031,731,304 Rhode Island 54,358,231 23,400,743 77,758,974 80,508,794 91,699,850 Vermont 57,320,369 15,660,114 72,980,483 92,205,049 91,165,680 Wisconsin 22,458,442 4,257,083 26,715,525 42,056,595 87,500,000 Total $2,447,115,871 $737,398,768 $3,184,514,639 $4,102,162,198 $5,770,194,680 TABLE XXX. A Statement of the Value of the Real and Personal Estate in 1850, of the True Value of the same, of the Value of the Slaves, of the True Value of the Real and Personal Estate, deducting the Value of the Slaves, with the Value of the Real and Personal Estate (including Slaves) for 1856, of the several Slave States. SLAVE STATES. Value of Real Estate. 1850. Value of Personal Estate, including Slaves. 1850. Total Value of Real and Personal Estate. 1850. True Value of Real and Personal Estate, as given in Census Compendium. 1850. Value of Slaves at $400 per head. 1850. True Value of Real and Personal Estate, deducting the Value of Slaves, at $400 per head. 1850. Value of Real and Personal Estate, as given by Secretary of Treasury. 1856. Alabama $78,870,718 $162,463,705 $241,334,423 $228,204,332 $137,137,600 $81,066,732 $279,233,027 Arkansas 17,372,524 19,056,151 36,428,675 39,841,025 18,840,000 21,001,025 64,240,726 Delaware 14,486,595 1,410,275 15,896,870 18,855,863 916,000 17,939,863 30,466,924 Florida 7,924,588 15,274,146 23,198,734 23,198,734 15,724,000 7,474,734 49,461,461 Georgia 121,619,739 213,490,486 335,110,225 335,425,714 152,672,800 182,752,914 500,000,000 Kentucky 177,013,407 114,374,147 291,387,554 301,628,456 84,392,400 217,236,056 411,000,098 Louisiana 176,623,654 49,832,464 226,456,118 233,998,764 97,923,600 136,075,164 270,425,000 Maryland 139,026,610 69,536,956 208,563,566 219,217,364 36,147,200 183,070,164 261,243,660 Mississippi 65,171,438 143,250,729 208,422,167 228,951,130 123,951,200 105,000,000 251,525,000 Missouri 66,802,223 31,793,240 98,595,463 137,247,707 34,968,800 102,278,907 223,948,731 North Carolina 71,702,740 140,368,673 212,071,413 226,800,472 115,419,200 111,381,272 239,603,372 South Carolina 105,737,492 178,130,217 283,867,709 288,257,694 153,993,600 134,264,094 303,434,240 Tennessee 107,981,793 87,299,565 195,281,358 207,454,704 95,783,600 111,671,104 321,776,810 Texas 28,149,671 25,414,000 53,563,671 55,362,340 23,264,400 32,097,940 240,000,000 Virginia 252,105,824 130,198,429 382,304,253 391,646,438 189,011,200 202,634,638 530,994,897 Total $1,430,589,016 $1,381,894,183 $2,812,473,199 $2,936,090,737 $1,280,145,600 $1,655,945,137 $3,977,353,946 and this after having added to the valuation of Georgia $165,000,000, on the bare conjecture of her governor. The following recent State valuations will further illustrate the estimates of the Secretary of the Treasury: Valuation of New Hampshire, 1856, $121,417,428 " " New York, 1855, as follows, viz: New York city and county real estate, 337,038,526 " " " personal estate, 150,022,312 " " " aggregate, 487,060,838 Remainder of State real estate, 770,234,189 " " personal estate, 143,990,252 Total valuation of the State of New York, 1,401,285,279 Valuation of New York city, 1856, 517,889,201 " " Connecticut, 1854, 202,739,431 " " Michigan, 1853, 120,362,474 " " Indiana, 1854, 290,408,148 " " Maryland, including slaves, 1851, 191,888,088 " " South Carolina, including slaves, 1854, 82,613,530 " " Tennessee, including slaves, 1855, 219,011,048 " " Kentucky, including slaves, 1854, 405,830,168 It will be seen by tables XXX. and XXXI. that the value of real and personal estate in 1850, was as follows, viz: Free States, $4,107,162,198 Slave States, 2,936,090,737 Deduct value of slaves, 1,280,145,600 True value in Slave States, 1,655,945,137 The total value of real and personal estate in 1856 is as follows, viz: Free States, $5,770,194,680 Slave States, 3,977,353,946 Deduct value of slaves in 1856, 1,472,167,600 True value in Slave States in 1856, 2,505,186,346 The whole area of the Free States (Table IX.) is 392,062,080 acres; the valuation of real and personal property in 1850, $4,107,162,198, or $10.47 per acre. The whole area (Table X.) of the Slave States is five hundred and forty-four million, nine hundred and twenty-six thousand, seven hundred and twenty (544,926,720) acres; the valuation of real and personal estate in 1850 one billion, six hundred and fifty-five million, nine hundred and forty-five thousand, one hundred and thirty-seven ($1,655,945,137), or three dollars and four cents ($3.04) per acre. The valuation of the Free States in 1856 was five billion, seven hundred and seventy million, one hundred and ninety-four thousand, six hundred and eighty ($5,770,194,680), or fourteen dollars and seventy-two cents ($14.72) per acre; the valuation of the Slave States in 1856 was two billion, five hundred and five million, one hundred and eighty-six thousand, three hundred and forty-six ($2,505,186,346), or four dollars and fifty-nine cents ($4.59) per acre. Thus, in five years the value of property in the Free States advanced from ten dollars and forty-seven cents ($10.47) per acre to fourteen dollars and seventy-two cents ($14.72), or four dollars and twenty-five cents ($4.25), being more than the whole valuation of the Slave States in 1850. The value of property in the South advanced in the same time from three dollars and four cents ($3.04) to four dollars and fifty-nine cents ($4.59) per acre. The value of the slaves in the Slave States, in 1850, at four hundred dollars ($400) each, was one billion two hundred and eighty million, one hundred and forty-five thousand, six hundred dollars ($1,280,145,600). The value of the farms in the Slave States in the same year (Table X.) was one billion, one hundred and seventeen million, six hundred and forty-nine thousand, six hundred and forty-nine dollars ($1,117,649,649). Excess of value of slaves, one hundred and sixty-two million, four hundred and ninety-five thousand, nine hundred and fifty-one dollars ($162,495,951). Thus, the value of the slaves in 1850 was one hundred and sixty-two million, four hundred and ninetyfive thousand, nine hundred and fifty-one dollars ($162,495,951) more than the value of all the improved and unimproved lands in the South. The number of slaveholders in the Slave States is three hundred and forty-six thousand and forty-eight (346,048). If we estimate their value at four hundred dollars ($400) per head, and add it to the value of the farms, it will make the value of the slaveholders and farms nearly equal to that of the slaves. The figures are: Value of farms, one billion, one hundred and seventeen million, six hundred and forty-nine thousand, six hundred and forty-nine ($1,117,649,649); value of three hundred and forty-six thousand and forty-eight (346,048) slaveholders, at four hundred dollars ($400) each, one hundred and thirty-eight million, one hundred and ninety-two thousand, two hundred dollars ($138,192,200), being a total of one billion, two hundred and fifty-six million, sixty-eight thousand, eight hundred and forty-nine dollars ($1,256,068,849); value of slaves as above, one billion, two hundred and eighty million, one hundred and forty-five thousand, six hundred dollars ($1,280,145,600). Thus has the industry and political and domestic economy of the slaveholders, in two hundred and thirty years, been able to bring the value of their lands and themselves nearly up to the market value of their slaves; and all three together, lands, slaves, and slaveholders, to nearly half the value of the property of the Free States. The valuation of the State of New York in 1855 was one billion, four hundred and one million, two hundred and eighty-five thousand, two hundred and seventy-nine dollars ($1,401,285,279), being more than the whole value of the real estate of the Slave States in 1850, which, after deducting from the aggregate the value of the slaves in Louisiana, was one billion, three hundred and thirty-two million, six hundred and sixty-five thousand, four hundred and sixteen dollars ($1,332,665,416). The value of the real and personal estate of Massachusetts in 1850 was more (slaves excepted) than that of the States of Virginia, North and South Carolina, Georgia, Florida, and Texas; the valuation of Massachusetts being five hundred and seventy-three million, three hundred and forty-two thousand, two hundred and eighty-six dollars ($573,342,286); that of the six States mentioned being five hundred and seventy-three million, three hundred and thirty-two thousand, eight hundred and sixty dollars ($573,332,860.) In this calculation, South Carolina is reckoned at its State valuation of 1854. The whole area of Massachusetts is (Table IX.) four million, nine hundred and ninety-two thousand (4,992,000) acres; value of its whole property per acre, one hundred and fourteen dollars and eighty-five cents ($114.85.) The whole area of the six States above mentioned is (Table X.) three hundred and seventeen million, five hundred and seventy-six thousand, three hundred and twenty (317,576,320) acres; value of their whole property, except slaves, five hundred and seventy-three million, three hundred and thirty-two thousand, eight hundred and sixty dollars ($573,332,860), or one dollar and eighty-one cents ($1.81) per acre. Thus, Massachusetts is able to buy and pay for considerably more than half the great empire of slavery, and have more money left than the Pilgrims landed with at Plymouth; while Pennsylvania could easily buy out the other half. Table XXXI. shows the number of miles of canals and railroads in operation in 1854, (with the cost of construction of such railroads), the number of miles of railroads in operation in January, 1855, and the amount of bank capital near January, 1855, in the several Free and Slave States. The first three columns of the tables are from the Census Compendium, the last two from the American Almanac for 1856. Table XXXII. gives the total debt, amount of productive property, and the annual expenditure of the several Free and Slave States. The figures are from the American Almanac for 1856. TABLE XXXI. A Statement of the Number of Miles of Canals and Railroads in operation in 1854 (with the cost of construction), and the Miles of completed Railroads, and the Amount of Bank Capital, near January, 1855, in the several Free and Slave States. FREE STATES. Canals, miles. 1854. Railroads, miles in operation. 1854. Cost of Railroads. 1854. Railroads, miles in operation. Jan'y, 1855. Bank Capital 1854–5. SLAVE STATES. Canals, miles. 1854. Railroads, miles in operation. 1854. Cost of Railroads. 1854. Railroads, Miles in operation. Jan'y, 1855. Bank Capital. 1854–5. Connecticut 61 669 $20,857,357 625 $15,597,891 Alabama 51 221 $3,636,208 363 $2,296,400 Illinois 100 1,262 25,420,000 1,964 2,513,790 Delaware 14 16 600,000 22 1,393,175 Indiana 367 1,127 22,400,000 1,632 7,281,934 Florida 54 250,000 26 Iowa 54 Georgia 28 884 16,084,872 1,146 13,413,100 Maine 50 417 12,662,645 470 7,301,252 Kentucky 486 233 4,909,990 187 10,369,717 Massachusetts 100 1,283 55,602,687 1,437 54,492,660 Louisiana 101 117 1,131,000 251 20,179,107 Michigan 601 13,842,279 699 980,416 Maryland 184 597 26,024,620 545 10,411,874 New Hampshire 11 512 16,185,254 502 3,626,000 Mississippi 155 3,070,000 67 240,165 New Jersey 147 408 11,536,505 444 5,314,885 Missouri 50 1,000,000 140 1,215,398 New York 989 2,345 94,523,785 2,287 83,773,288 North Carolina 13 249 4,106,000 568 5,205,073 Ohio 921 2,367 44,927,058 2,423 7,166,581 South Carolina 50 575 11,287,093 608 16,603,258 Pennsylvania 936 1,464 58,494,675 1,690 19,864,825 Tennessee 388 7,800,000 274 6,717,848 Rhode Island 50 2,614,484 66 17,511,162 Texas 30 Vermont 422 14,116,195 556 3,275,656 Virginia 189 673 12,720,421 1,023 14,033,838 Wisconsin 178 3,800,000 231 1,400,000 Total 3,682 13,105 $396,982,924 15,080 $230,100,340 Total 1,116 4,212 $92,520,204 5,250 $102,078,948 TABLE XXXII. Debt, Productive Property, and Annual Expenditure of the several Free and Slave States, compiled from State Returns, near January 1,1855. FREE STATES. Total Debt of State. 1855. Productive Property, exclusive of School Fund. 1855. Ordinary Annual Expenditure, exclusive of Debts and Schools. SLAVE STATES. Total Debt of State. 1855. Productive Property, exclusive of School Fund. 1855. Ordinary Annual Expenditure, exclusive of Debts and Schools. Maine $685,500 $648,289 $150,000 Delaware none. $350,638 $11,000 New Hampshire none none 80,000 Maryland $15,132,909 12,555,842 170,000 Vermont " " 100,000 Virginia 28,603,979 5,395,582 600,000 Massachusetts 6,739,555 8,967,509 600,000 North Carolina 3,409,633 600,000 75,000 Rhode Island 382,335 55,000 South Carolina 2,917,696 5,460,291 115,000 Connecticut none. 406,000 120,000 Georgia 2,644,222 5,000,000 131,000 New York 26,047,898 38,800,000 750,000 Florida none. 45,000 New Jersey 65,000 252,174 90,000 Alabama 6,168,887 700,000 100,000 Pennsylvania 40,613,160 35,060,667 425,000 Mississippi 7,271,707 130,000 Ohio 16,662,959 18,000,000 200,000 Louisiana 12,459,350 515,000 Michigan 3,213,245 125,000 Texas 12,436,991 100,000 Indiana 7,338,473 80,000 Arkansas 3,319,596 35,000 Illinois 13,994,615 125,000 Tennessee 8,744,857 2,244,827 165,000 Iowa 79,796 58,571 25,000 Kentucky 6,147,284 250,000 Wisconsin 100,000 40,000 Missouri 9,802,000 378,538 110,000 California 1,812,502 700,000 Total $117,735,038 $102,193,210 $3,665,000 Total $119,059,111 $32,685,718 $2,552,000</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER VIII. EDUCATION. I. COLLEGES. The first college established in the Free States was Harvard University, founded in 1636; which was sixteen years after the landing of the Pilgrims at Plymouth. The first college in the Slave States was that of William and Mary, in Virginia, founded in 1692, or eighty-four years after the settlement of Jamestown. The number of students in the former is now 365; in the latter, 82. The number of alumni of the former, 6,700; of the latter, 3,000. The number of volumes in the library of the former is 101,250; of the latter 5,000. It will be seen by Tables XXXIII and XXXIV, taken from the American Almanac for 1856, and showing the present condition of the colleges in the two great sections, that the number of colleges is nearly the same in each. The comparative character and efficiency of these institutions, may be in some measure learned from the following facts. The number of volumes in the libraries of the Southern colleges is 308,011; in those of the northern, 667,297; over two to one. The number graduated at the South is 19,648; at the North 47,752; about two and one-half to one. The number of Ministers educated in the Southern colleges is 747, and in the Northern, 10,702; a ratio of fourteen to one. It would indeed be interesting, were it possible, to compare these institutions in respect to value of buildings, apparatus, cabinets, &amp;c.; but the statistics of these cannot be readily obtained. Still more difficult would it be to compare statistically the ability of professors and the standard of scholarship. TABLE XXXIII. Colleges in the Slave States. SLAVE STATES. No. of Colleges. No. of Instructors. No. of Alumni. No. of Ministers. Students. Volumes in Libraries. Delaware 2 18 83 42 137 11,500 Maryland 5 69 607 13 399 33,292 Virginia 10 72 9,528 146 1,174 65,875 North Carolina 3 24 1,406 123 469 23,700 South Carolina 2 14 3,124 3 190 23,800 Georgia 5 34 1,359 133 643 25,700 Alabama 4 40 676 28 333 23,200 Mississippi 4 16 252 16 315 10,700 Louisiana 4 26 94 10 157 9,000 Tennessee 8 39 838 74 570 29,744 Kentucky 7 54 1,342 130 700 27,900 Missouri 5 44 339 29 568 23,600 Total 59 450 19,648 747 5,655 308,011 TABLE XXXIV. Colleges in the Free States. FREE STATES. No. of Colleges. No. of Instructors. No. of Alumni. No. of Ministers. Students. Volumes in Libraries. Maine 2 15 1,418 303 274 43,150 New Hampshire 1 12 4,187 883 258 31,900 Vermont 3 16 1,536 527 228 21,650 Massachusetts 4 47 9,404 2,612 807 122,750 Rhode Island 1 10 1,860 500 225 34,000 Connecticut 3 43 7,407 1,956 669 91,000 New York 8 84 6,888 1,461 1,080 80,516 New Jersey 3 54 3,855 837 449 28,000 Pennsylvania 9 66 8,298 741 959 71,180 Ohio 12 88 1,958 644 1,191 92,191 Indiana 4 27 546 158 300 19,600 Illinois 4 30 257 79 245 15,860 Michigan 2 14 130 180 13,000 Wisconsin 5 11 8 1 30 2,500 Total 61 517 47,752 10,702 6,895 667,297 II.—PROFESSIONAL SCHOOLS. The condition of the Professional Schools is shown by the following Table, taken from the same authority as the above. From this it appears that at the South a larger proportion of professional students are in the Law Schools than at the North. Next in order in this respect in Medicine, and last, Theology. Indeed, the Census Tables do not show where the great body of the Southern clergy are educated, since but 747 are returned from the colleges, and only 808 from the Theological Schools. It will be noticed that the number of Professional Schools in the Slave States is 32, and in the Free States 65, or two to one. The ratio of Professors is a little larger. The number of Students in the former is 1,807, and in the latter 4,426. The number of volumes in the libraries of the former is 30,796, and in those of the latter, 175,951; more than five to one. The number graduated at the former, 3,812, and at the latter, 23,513; over six to one. TABLE XXXV. Showing the Condition of the Professional Schools in the North and the South, from the American Almanac for 1856. SLAVE STATES Professional Schools. Number of Schools. Number of Professors. Number of Students, 1854–5. Number Educated. Number of Vols. in Libraries. Law 9 19 231 Medicine 13 75 1,307 3,004 Theology 10 28 269 808 30,796 Total 32 122 1,807 3,812 30,796 FREE STATES. Professional Schools. Number of Schools. Number of Professors. Number of Students, 1854–5. Number Educated. Number of Vols. in Libraries. Law 9 19 240 Medicine 22 152 3,095 15,950 Theology 34 98 1,091 7,563 175,951 Total 65 269 4,426 23,513 175,951 III.—ACADEMIES, PRIVATE AND PUBLIC SCHOOLS. In all the New England colonies, a law was passed in 1647, "That every township, after the Lord hath increased them to the number of fifty householders, shall appoint one to teach all children to write and read; and when any town shall increase to the number of one hundred families, they shall set up a grammar school; the masters thereof being able to instruct youth so far as they may be fitted for the university." See Colonial Laws. Again, in Connecticut we find the following: "Forasmuch as the good Education of Children is of singular behoofe and benefit to any Commonwealth, and whereas, many parents and masters are too indulgent and negligent of theire duty in that kinde:— "It is therefore ordered by this Courte and Authority thereof that the Selectmen of every Town, in the Several precincts and quarters where they dwell, shall have a vigilant eye over theire brethren and neighbours to see first that none of them shall suffer so much Barbarism in any of theire families as not to endeavour to teach by themselves or others theire Children and apprentices so much Learning as may enable them perfectly to read the Inglish tounge, and knowledge of the Capitall Laws, upon penalty of twenty shillings for each neglect therein." See "Code of Laws established by the General Court of Conn., May, 1650," as recorded in Vol. II. of the Colonial Records of Conn. In the year 1671, or twenty-four years after the establishment of public schools by law in the Plymouth Colonies, and over thirty years after Harvard college was founded, and a printing press set up in Cambridge, Gov. Berkley, at that time Governor of Virginia, said of that State: "I thank God there are no free schools nor printing, and I hope we shall not have these hundred years, for learning has brought disobedience and heresy and sects into the world, and printing has divulged them, and libels against the best government; God keep us from both." The following Tables Nos. XXXVI., XXXVII., XXXVIII., and XXXIX., show the condition of the Academies, Private and Public Schools in 1850, as given in the Census Compendium: TABLE XXXVI. Academies and Private Schools in the Slave States. SLAVE STATES. Number. Teachers. Pupils. Annual Income. Scholars in Colleges, Academies and Public Schools. Alabama 166 380 8,290 $164,165 37,237 Arkansas 90 126 2,407 27,937 11,050 Delaware 65 94 2,011 47,832 11,125 Florida 34 49 1,251 13,089 3,129 Georgia 219 318 9,059 108,983 43,299 Kentucky 330 600 12,712 252,617 85,914 Louisiana 143 354 5,328 193,077 31,003 Maryland 223 503 10,787 232,341 45,025 Mississippi 171 297 6,628 73,717 26,236 Missouri 204 368 8,829 143,171 61,592 North Carolina 272 403 7,822 187,648 112,430 South Carolina 202 333 7,467 205,489 26,035 Tennessee 264 404 9,928 155,902 115,750 Texas 97 137 3,389 39,384 11,500 Virginia 317 547 9,068 234,372 77,774 Total 2,797 4,913 104,976 $2,079,724 699,079 TABLE XXXVII. Academies and Private Schools in the Free States. FREE STATES. Number. Teachers. Pupils. Annual Increase. Scholars in Colleges, Academies and Public Schools. California 6 5 170 $14,270 219 Connecticut 202 329 6,996 145,967 79,003 Illinois 83 160 4,244 40,488 130,411 Indiana 131 233 6,185 63,520 168,754 Iowa 33 46 1,111 7,980 30,767 Maine 131 232 6,648 51,187 199,745 Massachusetts 403 521 13,436 310,177 190,924 Michigan 37 71 1,619 24,947 112,382 New Hampshire 107 183 5,321 43,202 81,237 New Jersey 225 453 9,844 227,588 88,244 New York 887 3,136 49,328 810,332 727,222 Ohio 206 474 15,052 149,392 502,826 Pennsylvania 524 914 23,751 467,843 440,977 Rhode Island 46 75 1,601 32,748 25,014 Vermont 118 257 6,864 48,935 100,785 Wisconsin 58 86 2,723 18,796 61,615 Total 3,197 7,175 154,893 $2,457,372 2,940,125 TABLE XXXVIII. Public Schools of the Slave States. SLAVE STATES. Number. Teachers. Pupils. Annual Income of Public Schools. Alabama 1,152 1,195 28,380 $315,602 Arkansas 353 355 8,493 43,763 Delaware 194 214 8,970 43,861 Florida 69 73 1,878 22,386 Georgia 1,251 1,265 32,705 182,231 Kentucky 2,234 2,306 71,429 211,852 Louisiana 664 822 25,046 349,679 Maryland 898 986 33,111 218,836 Mississippi 782 826 18,746 254,159 Missouri 1,570 1,620 51,754 160,770 North Carolina 2,657 2,730 104,095 158,564 South Carolina 724 739 17,838 200,600 Tennessee 2,680 2,819 104,117 198,518 Texas 349 360 7,946 44,088 Virginia 2,930 2,997 67,353 314,625 Total 18,507 19,307 581,861 $2,719,534 TABLE XXXIX. Public Schools of the Free States. FREE STATES. Number. Teachers. Pupils. Annual Income of Public Schools. California 2 2 49 $3,600 Connecticut 1,656 1,787 71,269 231,220 Illinois 4,052 4,248 125,725 349,712 Indiana 4,822 4,860 161,500 316,955 Iowa 740 828 29,556 51,492 Maine 4,042 5,540 192,815 315,436 Massachusetts 3,679 4,443 176,475 1,006,795 Michigan 2,714 3,231 110,455 167,806 New Hampshire 2,381 3,013 75,643 166,944 New Jersey 1,473 1,574 77,930 216,672 New York 11,580 13,965 675,221 1,472,657 Ohio 11,661 12,886 484,153 743,074 Pennsylvania 9,061 10,024 413,706 1,348,249 Rhode Island 416 518 23,130 100,481 Vermont 2,731 4,173 93,457 176,111 Wisconsin 1,423 1,529 58,817 113,133 Total 62,433 72,621 2,769,901 $6,780,337 It will be seen that in the South a larger proportion of the children who attend School, attend at private Schools, than at the North. Still the number of scholars in these Schools is but a slight fraction over two-thirds as great at the South as at the North, and the amount of money paid for the support of these Schools nearly $400,000 less in the slave than in the free States. It is to be regretted that we are unable to compare these Schools in other respects, but figures can carry us no further at this time. Perhaps by comparing the different sections of this chapter we may be able to form a just opinion. It will be observed that the Public School statistics would not be materially affected for purposes of comparison, were those of the private Schools added to them. The number of public Schools at the South is 18,507; at the North, 62,433; a ratio of about three and one-half to one. Teachers at the South, 19,307; at the North, 72,621; almost four to one. The number of Scholars at the South is 581,861, and at the North, 2,769,901; nearly five to one, and over 2,000,000 more at the North than at the South. Indeed, if we compare the entire number attending all Schools (Colleges Academies, private and public Schools,) we find in the North a majority over the South of 2,241,046, which is now more than three times the entire number attending School in the Southern States. In other words, more than four-fifths of the children attending School in the Union are in the free States. The amount of money expended annually for these Schools is, in the Slave States, $4,799,258; and in the free States, $9,237,709. The State of Ohio is not quite two-thirds as large as Virginia. Virginia has 77,764 scholars at School and Ohio has 502,826. The area of Kentucky is very nearly equal to that of Ohio, the population almost exactly one-half as great, and the number of scholars at School a little more than one-sixth. Massachusetts is one-fourth as large as South Carolina, and contains nearly four times as many white inhabitants. The number of scholars attending School in South Carolina, is 26,025; in Massachusetts, 190,924. The amount expended for Schools, both public and private, in South Carolina, is $406,089; in Massachusetts, it is $1,316,972; a difference of almost a million of dollars. The whole number of scholars at School in the fifteen slaveholding States, is 699,079; in the single State of New York, it is 727,222. Such are the figures of the Census for 1850. Great effort has been made to obtain such statistics as to show the condition of all grades of Schools at the present time, much more fully than it can be learned from the census for the time when that was taken. Not enough, however, could be obtained for purposes of just comparison, the annual reports from the Slave States being so exceedingly meagre. So far, however, as such reports could be obtained, they show that the difference between the free and slave States, in regard to education, is constantly increasing. This arises from the want of any regular system for education of the poorer classes, who are increasing so rapidly in the Southern States. Proofs of this might be given, were it not a well known fact. On page 146 of the Census Compendium, it is said of "Georgia—no public Schools strictly, but Schools receive a certain amount of aid from State funds. This is true for many Southern States." The State of South Carolina appropriates annually the sum of $75,000 to free Schools. Gov. Manning, in his message of Nov. 28, 1853, says that "under the present mode of applying it, that liberality is really the profusion of the prodigal, rather than the judicious generosity which confers real benefit." In the State of Arkansas, only forty Schools were reported to the Commissioner for 1854. It is of course utterly impossible to obtain any reliable information with regard to the Schools there, though we may form a very just opinion concerning their character in such a community. The Commissioner says "The great obstacle to the organization of common Schools is not so much a deficiency in the means to sustain them, as it is the indifference that pervades the public mind on the subject of education." The amount expended by the State of Virginia, in 1854, for the education of poor children, was $69,404. For the maintenance of the public guard, $73,189. New England, whose area is less than one-twelfth greater appropriated $2,000,000 for Public Schools, and felt secure without a public guard. The State of South Carolina has established one Free State Scholarship; the State of Massachusetts has established forty eight. In Kentucky, the average number of scholars at school in 1854, was 76,429. In Ohio it was 279,635. The total amount of money distributed (for public schools) during the year 1854, in Kentucky, was $146,047. The amount appropriated by the State of Ohio for the same purpose, was $2,266,609; a difference of over $2,000,000. There are very many items of expenditure for educational purposes at the North, for which the corresponding sums at the South cannot be ascertained. Among these are Teachers' Institutes, holden annually in every county in many of the Northern States; Teachers' Associations, Normal Schools, School-houses, &amp;c. The value of school buildings in the State of Ohio in 1854, was $2,197,384, and in Massachusetts it was, in 1848, $2,750,000; even in the little State of Rhode Island it is $319,293. The amount raised by taxation for educational purposes is now, in each of the three states, New York, Pennsylvania, and Massachusetts, over one million dollars annually. The Report of the Commissioner of Public Schools to the Mayor and City Council of Baltimore, for the year 1851, gives the following facts: The value of school buildings in the city of Baltimore, is $105,729; New York, $552,457; Philadelphia, $858,224; and in Boston $729,502.* * Besides this there were paid for new buildings in Boston, $56,000; in Philadelphia, $24,473; and in Cincinnati, $10,000. The following table is copied from the same report: TABLE XL. Showing the Condition of Public Schools in certain Cities. CITIES. Population. Schools Teachers. Pupils. Cost of Tuition. Boston 138,788 203 353 21,678 $237,000 New York 517,000 207 332 40,055 274,794 Philadelphia 409,000 270 781 48,056 341,888 Baltimore 169,012 36 138 8,011 32,423 Cincinnati 116,000 17 124 6,006 81,623 St. Louis 81,000 73 168 6,642 The population of Baltimore is 30,000 greater than that of Boston. Baltimore has 8,000 scholars at school, for whose instruction she pays $30,000. Boston has 20,000, and pays for instruction, $230,000. It would indeed be interesting, were it a matter capable of statistical comparisons, to trace the results of the superior educational advantages enjoyed by the children of the North; to compare the philosophers, orators, and statesmen, men of skill, science, or literature, authors, poets, and sculptors, of the two sections. To see how many of those who are most distinguished at the South were born, bred, and educated at the North. DeBow, in a labored article in the Census Compendium, in behalf of the southern schools, says: "An examination of Massachusetts shows, out of 2,357 'students,' mentioned, 711, or one-third nearly, born out of the State, and 152, or one-fifteenth, born in the South. On the other hand a southern town, taken at random, furnished one out of three editors, four out of twelve teachers, two out of seven clergymen, born in the non-slaveholding States." The presumption is that not so large a proportion of the students in Southern institutions are sent there from the North to be educated, and that, on the other hand, not so large a proportion of the editors, teachers and clergymen of the North are of Southern birth and education. IV.—LIBRARIES. The following tables, Nos. XLI. and XLII., are of great importance in connection with the subject of education, as showing the literary tastes, habits of thought, and sources of enjoyment, of the people. These tables also show the character of the various institutions in the two sections, more correctly than it could be ascertained from almost any other source, embracing as they do the Public School, Sunday School, College and Church libraries: TABLE XLI. Libraries other than Private in the Slave States. SLAVE STATES. Public. School. Sunday School. College. Church. Total. Number. Volumes. Number. Volumes. Number. Volumes. Number. Volumes. Number. Volumes. Number. Volumes. Alabama 4 3,848 32 3,500 15 5,775 5 7,500 56 20,623 Arkansas 1 250 2 170 3 420 Delaware 4 10,250 12 2,700 1 5,000 17 17,950 Florida 1 1,000 2 800 4 860 7 2,660 Georgia 3 6,500 11 1,800 15 1,988 9 21,500 38 31,788 Kentucky 47 40,424 18 4,617 11 33,225 4 1,200 80 79,466 Louisiana 5 9,800 2 12,000 3 5,000 10 26,800 Maryland 17 54,750 8 6,335 84 28,315 10 33,792 5 1,850 124 125,042 Mississippi 4 7,264 103 3,650 6 730 4 10,093 117 21,737 Missouri 13 23,106 13 17,150 66 14,500 4 19,700 1 600 97 75,056 North Carolina 4 2,500 1 1,500 19 2,352 5 21,593 9 1,647 38 29,592 South Carolina 16 73,758 3 2,750 7 30,964 26 107,472 Tennessee 9 5,373 2 5,100 18 2,498 5 9,925 34 22,896 Texas 3 2,100 3 430 5 1,600 1 100 12 4,230 Virginia 21 32,595 6 2,706 11 1,975 14 50,856 2 330 54 88,462 Total 152 273,518 186 57,721 275 63,463 79 249,248 21 5,627 695 649,577 TABLE XLII. Libraries other than Private in the Free States. FREE STATES. Public. School. Sunday School. College. Church. Total. Number. Volumes. Number. Volumes. Number. Volumes. Number. Volumes. Number. Volumes. Number. Volumes. California Connecticut 42 38,609 4 5,039 107 38,445 8 82,600 3 265 164 165,318 Illinois 33 35,982 29 5,875 86 12,829 4 7,800 152 62,486 Indiana 58 46,238 3 1,800 85 11,265 4 8,700 1 400 151 68,403 Iowa 4 2,650 4 160 24 2,980 32 5,790 Maine 77 51,439 11 2,225 131 26,988 8 39,625 9 1,692 236 121,969 Massachusetts 177 257,737 792 104,645 433 165,476 18 141,400 42 14,757 1,462 684,015 Michigan 280 65,116 119 31,427 15 3,500 3 7,900 417 107,943 New Hampshire 47 42,017 3 1,200 70 20,117 3 19,975 6 2,450 129 85,759 New Jersey 77 43,903 10 4,080 35 8,564 4 24,000 2 338 128 80,885 New York 43 197,229 10,802 1,388,729 137 33,294 25 138,870 6 2,698 11,013 1,760,820 Ohio 65 65,703 13 9,665 248 53,910 22 56,573 4 975 352 186,826 Pennsylvania 90 184,666 30 17,161 226 58,071 21 77,050 26 26,452 393 363,400 Rhode Island 26 42,007 12 5,814 50 23,765 1 31,000 7 1,756 96 104,342 Vermont 30 21,061 16 9,700 38 10,020 9 23,280 3 580 96 64,641 Wisconsin 9 12,040 33 2,163 28 5,017 2 1,800 72 21,020 Total 1,058 1,106,397 11,881 1,589,683 1,713 478,858 132 660,573 109 52,723 14,911 3,888,234 From these it will be seen that the total number of volumes in the libraries of the South, is 649,577; in those of the North, 3,888,234; a difference more than 3,000,000 in favor of the free States. Six volumes in the libraries of the North to one at the South. But we need not compare aggregates when the difference is so overwhelming. The Sunday School libraries of the North are nearly twice as great as the College libraries of the South; and the College libraries of the North greater than all the libraries of the South. Maine has more volumes in her libraries than South Carolina, Rhode Island than Virginia, or even more than all the five states, Georgia, Alabama, Mississippi, Louisiana, and Florida; and Massachusetts more than all the fifteen slave States. Michigan and Arkansas are very nearly equal, both in age and territory, Michigan having been admitted into the Union in 1837, and Arkansas in 1836; while the area of Michigan is 56,243 square miles, and that of Arkansas 52,198. Michigan has 107,943 volumes in her libraries, Arkansas has 420; a ratio of 257 to 1. The public school libraries alone of the single state of New York, contain more than twice as many volumes as all the libraries together of the whole South. Nor are we to suppose that because Common School Libraries, they are necessarily inferior either in cost or character. We learn from the American Almanac for the present year, that in the State of Illinois "690 school libraries, of 321 volumes each, were distributed throughout the state. The aggregate cost of these 221,490 volumes was $147,222, or an average of $213 for each library." If the New York common school libraries were purchased at a similar cost, (over sixty-six cents per volume,) their value is doubtless greater than that of all the libraries in the fifteen slave States. V.—ILLITERATE. Thus far the large figures have been all in one direction, but here the case is different. The South is in advance and still advancing. The following tables, Nos XLIII. and XLIV., show the number unable to read and write. It will be seen that the number of native white citizens of this class in the free States is 248,725, and in the slave States 493,026, a number about twice as great in a population of far less than half. The number of native white adults who cannot read and write, in the State of Tennessee, is 77,017, in a white population of 756,836. The number in New York, 23,241, in a white population of 3,048,325. TABLE XLIII. Persons in the Slave States over Twenty Years of Age who cannot Read and Write. SLAVE STATES. Whites. Free Colored. Natives. Foreign. Native Whites. Alabama 33,757 235 33,853 139 33,618 Arkansas 16,819 116 16,908 27 16,792 Delaware 4,536 5,645 9,777 404 4,132 Florida 3,859 270 3,834 295 3,564 Georgia 41,200 467 41,261 406 40,794 Kentucky 66,687 3,019 67,359 2,347 64,340 Louisiana 21,221 3,389 18,339 6,271 14,950 Maryland 20,815 21,062 38,426 3,451 17,364 Mississippi 13,405 123 13,447 81 13,324 Missouri 36,281 497 34,917 1,861 34,420 North Carolina 73,566 6,857 80,083 340 73,226 South Carolina 15,684 880 16,460 104 15,580 Tennessee 77,522 1,097 78,114 505 77,017 Texas 10,525 58 8,095 2,488 8,037 Virginia 77,005 11,515 87,383 1,137 75,868 Total 512,882 55,230 548,256 19,856 493,026 The number in Georgia is 40,794, in a white population of 521,572, and of Pennsylvania it is 41,944, in a white population of 2,258,160. Again. The number of white inhabitants over twenty years of age, in the state of New Hampshire, is 174,232. The number of native white adults who cannot read and write, is 893, or 1 in 201. In Connecticut it is 1 in 277; in Vermont 1 in 284; and in Massachusetts 1 in 517. In South Carolina, on the other hand, it is 1 in 7; in Virginia 1 in 5, and in North Carolina 1 in 3. Such facts as these show the condition and character of the schools in the North and the South more clearly than all other statistics combined. TABLE XLIV. Persons in the Free States over Twenty Years of Age who cannot Read and Write. FREE STATES. Whites. Native Whites. Natives. Foreign. Free Colored. California 5,118 117 2,318 2,917 2,201 Connecticut 4,739 567 1,293 4,013 826 Illinois 40,054 1,229 35,336 5,947 34,107 Indiana 70,540 2,170 69,445 3,265 67,275 Iowa 8,120 33 7,076 1,077 7,043 Maine 6,147 135 2,134 4,148 1,999 Massachusetts 27,539 806 1,861 26,484 1,055 Michigan 7,912 369 5,272 3,009 4,903 New Hampshire 2,957 52 945 2,064 893 New Jersey 14,248 4,417 12,787 5,878 8,370 New York 91,293 7,429 30,670 68,052 23,241 Ohio 61,030 4,990 56,958 9,062 51,968 Pennsylvania 66,928 9,344 51,288 24,989 41,944 Rhode Island 3,340 267 1,248 2,359 981 Vermont 6,189 51 616 5,624 565 Wisconsin 6,361 92 1,551 4,902 1,459 Total 422,515 32,068 280,793 173,790 248,725</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER IX. THE PRESS. In the language of DeBow: "In every country the press must be regarded a great educational agency. Freedom of speech and of the press are the inalienable birthright of every American citizen, and constitute the ægis of his liberties." The earliest newspaper in North America was the Boston News-Letter, issued April 24, 1704. There were in 1775 but 37 Newspapers in the American Colonies.* * It will be perceived by looking on the 54th page of the Census Compendium, that there is a descrepancy between the several numbers and the amount given. I presume the separate numbers to be correct. Of these there were three in South Carolina, two in each of the States Maryland, Virginia, and North Carolina, and one in Georgia; making in all 10 in the present slaveholding States. In New Hampshire there was one, two in Rhode Island, four in Connecticut, the same number in New York, seven in Massachusetts, and nine in Pennsylvania; making 27 in the present non-slaveholding States. At that time the white population in the two sections was very nearly equal. The following tables show the number of papers and their circulation, in the several States, in 1810; also the number of papers in 1828, and of papers and periodicals in 1840. They also show the character of the newspaper and periodical press, the number of copies printed annually, the number of papers, and the circulation of each class, in 1850. TABLE XLV. Newspapers and Periodicals in the Slave States in 1810, 1828 and 1840. SLAVE STATES. 1810. 1828, 1840 Papers. Circulation. Papers. Papers and Periodicals. Alabama 10 28 Arkansas 2 9 Delaware 2 166,400 4 8 Florida 2 10 Georgia 13 707,200 18 40 Kentucky 17 618,800 23 46 Louisiana 11 763,900 9 37 Maryland 21 1,903,200 37 49 Mississippi 4 83,200 6 31 Missouri 5 35 North Carolina 10 416,000 20 29 South Carolina 10 842,400 16 21 Tennessee 6 171,600 8 56 Texas Virginia 23 1,289,600 34 56 Total 117 6,962,300 194 455 TABLE XLVI. Newspapers and Periodicals in the Free States in 1810, 1828, and 1840. FREE STATES 1810. 1828. 1840. Papers. Circulation. Papers. Papers and Periodicals. California Connecticut 11 657,800 33 44 Illinois 4 52 Indiana 1 15,600 17 76 Iowa 4 Maine 29 41 Massachusetts 32 2,873,000 78 105 Michigan 2 33 New Hampshire 12 624,000 17 33 New Jersey 8 332,800 22 40 New York 66 4,139,200 161 302 Ohio 14 473,200 66 143 Pennsylvania 71 4,542,200 185 229 Rhode Island 7 332,800 14 18 Vermont 14 682,400 21 33 Wisconsin 6 Total 236 14,673,000 649 1,159 TABLE XLVII. Newspapers and Periodicals Published in the Slave States, 1850. SLAVE STATES. Daily. Tri-Weekly. Semi-Weekly. Weekly. Number. Number of copies printed annually. Number. Number of copies printed annually. Number. Number of copies printed annually. Number. Number of copies printed annually. Alabama 6 869,201 5 266,500 48 1,509,040 Arkansas 3 9 377,000 Delaware 62,400 7 358,800 Florida 1 31,200 9 288,600 Georgia 5 1,086,110 3 146,380 37 2,609,776 Kentucky 9 2,243,584 7 1,125,280 38 3,053,024 Louisiana 11 9,947,140 6 676,000 37 1,646,684 Maryland 6 15,806,500 4 499,700 54 3,166,124 Mississippi 4 245,440 46 1,507,064 Missouri 5 3,380,400 4 273,000 45 2,406,560 North Carolina 5 414,310 40 1,530,204 South Carolina 7 5,070,600 5 549,250 27 1,413,880 Tennessee 8 4,407,666 2 266,240 36 2,139,644 Texas 5 525,400 29 771,524 Virginia 15 4,992,350 12 1,416,550 55 2,518,568 Total 72 47,803,551 63 6,435,250 3 62,400 517 25,296,492 TABLE XLVIII. Newspapers and Periodicals Published in the Free States, 1850. FREE STATES. Daily. Tri-Weekly. Semi-Weekly. Weekly. Number. Number of copies printed annually. Number. Number of copies printed annually. Number Number of copies printed annually. Number. Number of copies printed annually. California 4 626,000 3 135,200 Connecticut 7 1,752,800 4 374,400 30 2,117,232 Illinois 8 1,120,540 4 214,500 84 3,575,936 Indiana 9 1,153,092 2 195,000 95 2,920,736 Iowa 2 577,200 25 923,000 Maine 4 964,040 5 302,900 39 2,906,124 Massachusetts 22 40,498,444 4 351,000 11 2,070,016 126 20,371,104 Michigan 3 1,252,000 2 52,000 3,116,360 47 1,685,736 N. Hampshire 35 3,538,152 New Jersey 6 2,175,350 43 1,900,288 New York 51 63,928,685 8 776,100 13 308 39,205,920 Ohio 26 14,285,633 10 1,047,930 62,400 201 13,334,204 Pennsylvania 24 50,416,788 2 78,000 1 25,200 261 27,359,384 Rhode Island 5 1,768,450 2 228,800 12 963,300 Vermont 2 172,150 1 30 2,142,712 Wisconsin 6 1,053,245 4 198,250 35 1,395,992 Total 177 181,167,217 47 4,167,280 28 5,502,776 1,374 124,475,020 TABLE XLIX. Newspapers and Periodicals published in the Slave States in 1850. SLAVE STATES. Semi-Monthly. Monthly. Quarterly. Aggregate.* * This aggregate is the aggregate of this table together with the last. Number. Number of copies printed annually. Number. Number of copies printed annually. Number. Number of copies printed annually. Number. Number of copies printed annually. Alabama 1 18,000 60 2,662,741 Arkansas 9 377,000 Delaware 10 421,200 Florida 10 319,800 Georgia 6 228,600 51 4,070,866 Kentucky 8 160,950 62 6,582,838 Louisiana 1 146,400 55 12,416,224 Maryland 1 48,000 3 92,400 68 19,612,724 Mississippi 50 1,752,504 Missouri 7 135,600 61 6,195,560 North Carolina 6 76,050 51 2,020,564 South Carolina 5 102,600 2 9,600 46 7,145,930 Tennessee 4 127,200 50 6,940,750 Texas 34 1,296,924 Virginia 3 267,600 1 24,000 1 4,000 87 9,223,068 Total 30 901,800 16 525,600 3 13,600 704 81,038,693 TABLE L. Newspapers and Periodicals published in the Free States in 1850. FREE STATES. Semi-Monthly. Monthly. Quarterly. Aggregate.* * This aggregate is the aggregate of this table together with the last. Number. Number of copies printed annually. Number. Number of copies printed annually. Number. Number of copies printed annually. Number. Number of copies printed annually. California 7 761,200 Connecticut 1 6,000 2 8,800 46 4,267,932 Illinois 3 43,200 7 147,200 1 900 107 5,102,276 Indiana 1 48,000 107 4,316,828 Iowa 2 12,600 29 1,512,800 Maine 1 30,000 49 4,203,064 Massachusetts 3 61,800 29 1,357,200 7 24,000 202 64,820,564 Michigan 3 134,400 3 123,600 58 3,247,736 New Hampshire 1 15,600 2 13,800 38 3,067,552 New Jersey 2 23,040 51 4,098,678 New York 9 1,704,000 36 6,629,808 3 24,600 428 115,385,473 Ohio 23 1,781,640 1 24,000 261 30,473,407 Pennsylvania 19 6,972,000 2 7,600 309 84,898,672 Rhode Island 19 2,756,950 Vermont 2 24,000 35 2,567,662 Wisconsin 1 18,000 46 2,665,487 Total 64 10,783,680 84 8,362,208 16 89,900 1,790 334,146,281 TABLE LI. Character of the Newspaper and Periodical Press.—Number of copies printed annually in the Slave States, as given in 1850. SLAVE STATES. Literary and Miscellaneous. Neutral and Independent. Political. Religious. Scientific. Alabama 265,200 313,000 1,889,169 158,400 36,972 Arkansas 171,600 205,400 Delaware 46,800 374,400 Florida 202,800 117,000 Georgia 1,411,976 747,340 1,491,350 239,200 181,000 Kentucky 650,800 250,400 5,245,888 429,450 6,300 Louisiana 657,300 3,335,100 8,356,224 52,000 15,600 Maryland 14,654,000 8,400 4,196,924 669,400 84,000 Mississippi 233,480 1,519,024 Missouri 608,800 5,496,280 90,480 North Carolina 266,200 113,750 1,457,664 182,950 South Carolina 474,800 2,140,400 4,310,930 1,092,040 24,800 Tennessee 206,200 503,930 5,138,580 195,500 Texas 350,324 148,400 660,400 137,800 Virginia 247,880 1,251,900 6,698,176 1,001,112 24,000 Total 20,245,360 8,812,620 47,243,209 4,364,832 372,672 TABLE LII. Character of the Newspaper and Periodical Press.---Number of copies printed annually in the Free States, as given in 1850. FREE STATES. Literary and Miscellaneous. Neutral and Independent. Political. Religious. Scientific. California 135,200 626,000 Connecticut 489,900 3,422,432 223,200 7,200 Illinois 721,700 403,770 3,384,162 499,044 93,600 Indiana 647,504 3,569,324 100,000 Iowa 36,000 187,200 1,281,800 7,800 Maine 987,216 2,501,680 438,568 275,600 Massachusetts 11,794,304 13,591,000 32,996,800 4,405,200 2,033,260 Michigan 456,500 26,000 2,556,836 134,400 74,000 New Hampshire 579,480 1,673,672 778,000 36,400 New Jersey 181,640 93,900 3,823,138 New York 18,449,016 37,317,010 45,463,015 12,438,432 1,718,000 Ohio 3,865,880 4,220,805 18,865,282 3,334,240 187,200 Pennsylvania 18,515,028 21,908,548 37,808,960 6,588,136 78,000 Rhode Island 280,800 782,500 1,693,650 Vermont 208,600 2,025,430 333,632 Wisconsin 130,000 2,517,487 18,000 Total 57,478,768 79,156,733 163,583,668 29,280,652 4,521,260 TABLE LIII. Number of Papers, and the Circulation of each Class, in the Slave States, in 1850. SLAVE STATES. Literary and Miscellaneous. Neutral and Independent. Political. Religious. Scientific. Aggregate. Number. Circulation. Number. Circulation. Number. Circulation. Number. Circulation. Number. Circulation. Number. Circulation. Alabama 11 5,100 1 1,000 45 24,336 2 3,450 1 711 60 34,597 Arkansas 3 3,300 6 3,950 9 7,250 Delaware 2 900 8 6,600 10 7,500 Florida 7 3,500 3 2,250 10 5,750 Georgia 18 29,638 6 3,046 20 20,900 3 4,600 4 9,300 51 67,484 Kentucky 12 14,900 2 800 42 55,936 5 12,525 1 525 62 84,686 Louisiana 13 22,025 6 12,000 34 45,522 1 1,000 1 300 55 80,847 Maryland 20 71,000 1 700 39 31,637 6 13,950 2 7,000 68 124,287 Mississippi 10 4,490 40 26,380 50 30,870 Missouri 17 19,400 42 48,340 2 2,740 61 70,480 North Carolina 8 5,675 2 875 35 24,564 6 5,725 51 36,839 South Carolina 10 12,700 5 8,300 24 28,115 5 4,600 2 2,000 46 55,715 Tennessee 5 10,350 2 1,610 36 33,147 7 22,770 50 67,877 Texas 17 6,737 1 1,400 14 8,350 2 2,650 34 19,137 Virginia 10 5,690 5 4,200 62 51,988 9 25,256 1 2,000 87 89,134 Total 156 211,905 31 33,931 454 413,265 51 101,516 12 21,836 704 782,453 TABLE LIV. Number of Papers, and the Circulation of each Class, in the Free States, in 1850. FREE STATES. Literary and Miscellaneous. Neutral and Independent. Political. Religious. Scientific. Aggregate. Number. Circulation. Number. Circulation. Number. Circulation. Number. Circulation. Number. Circulation. Number. Circulation. California 3 2,600 4 2,000 7 4,600 Connecticut 12 11,200 28 34,916 4 5,400 1 1,200 45 52,716 Illinois 22 17,725 1 1,290 73 51,111 8 12,097 3 6,400 107 88,623 Indiana 21 12,452 84 47,900 2 3,000 107 63,352 Iowa 2 1,000 1 1,200 25 20,150 1 650 29 23,000 Maine 15 20,458 29 29,695 4 8,434 1 5,300 49 63,887 Massachusetts 80 283,027 9 50,700 82 171,387 24 117,650 14 94,205 209 716,969 Michigan 13 13,625 1 200 39 28,793 3 5,600 2 4,500 58 52,718 New Hampshire 10 11,790 22 32,186 5 15,500 1 700 38 60,176 New Jersey 6 4,010 1 300 44 40,144 51 44,454 New York 101 528,908 15 127,370 263 399,755 37 507,246 12 59,500 428 1,622,779 Ohio 37 111,790 6 13,485 192 189,304 21 90,130 5 10,400 261 415,109 Pennsylvania 71 445,364 12 70,396 198 267,940 28 198,018 1 1,500 310 983,218 Rhode Island 6 5,400 1 2,500 12 18,075 19 25,975 Vermont 5 5,550 27 33,990 3 6,416 35 45,956 Wisconsin 3 2,500 42 29,236 1 1,500 46 33,236 Total 407 1,477,399 51 269,441 1,160 1,394,582 140 970,141 41 185,205 1,799 4,296,768 It will be seen on examination of these Tables, that in 1810 the number of papers in the Slave States was 117, and in the free States, 236; almost exactly two to one. The ratio of circulation was a little larger. In 1828, the number of papers at the North was to that at the South as 3 to 1; and in 1840 as 2 1–2 to 1. The circulation for those years is not given. In 1850, the number of papers at the South was 704; at the North 1,799; while the circulation at the South was 782,453, and at the North, 4,296,768; or over five at the North to one at the South. The circulation in Michigan, is 52,000; in Arkansas, 7,000; in Kentucky, 84,000; in Ohio, 415,000; in South Carolina, 55,000; in New Hampshire, 60,000; in Mississippi, 30,000; and in New Jersey, 44,000; in Maryland, 124,000, (which is far the largest circulation of any Southern State); and in Massachusetts, 716,969. The circulation in Massachusetts, is but little less than that in all the slave States; that in Pennsylvania is greater by one-fourth than of that entire section; while the circulation of New York is considerably more than double that of the whole dominion of slavery. The circulation of the single paper, the New York Weekly Tribune, is at the present time greater than was, in 1850, the circulation of all the newspapers in the States Virginia, North Carolina, and Mississippi; indeed, we might add a couple more slave States, and it would still be greater. On examining the character of the Newspapers and Periodicals in the two sections, we see that a large proportion (more than one-half,) of the Southern Papers, are political; and a much larger proportion than of the Northern, the proportion in the North being less than one-third. In this class they have a circulation nearly equal to one-third of the Northern, while of the literary and miscellaneous, neutral and independent, it is one-seventh; in the scientific, one-eighth; and in the religious, one-ninth. These ratios are in some instances greater, if we compare the number of copies printed annually. The number of copies, of neutral and independent papers, printed in a year, in the slave States, is 8,000,000; and in the free States, 79,000,000. Of the religious, in the slave States, 4,000,000; and in the free States, 29,000,000. Of the scientific, the number is, at the South, 372,000; and at the North, 4,000,000; while of the political, the number at the South, is 47,000,000; and at the North, 163,000,000. The number of copies of scientific papers printed in the fifteen Southern States, is 372,000. The number printed in Massachusetts alone, is 2,000,000; more than five times as many as in all the slave States. The number of copies of religious papers printed in the fifteen slave States, is 4,000,000; in the State of New York, 12,000,000. Of neutral and independent papers there are, in the slave States, 8,000,000; and in Pennsylvania, 21,000,000. The political press of either Massachusetts or Pennsylvania, issues annually more copies than half the political presses of the slave States; while that of New York issues but a slight fraction less than the whole. Finally. The daily press of the South issues 47,000,000 annually; that of Massachusetts and Pennsylvania the same; and of the free States, 181,000,000. The weekly press of the South issues 25,000,000 copies; that of Pennsylvania 27,000,000; of New York, 39,000,000; and of the free States, 124,000,000. The New York Daily Herald had a circulation nearly, if not quite, half as great as all the daily papers of the slave States, in 1850. The aggregate number of copies printed annually in Arkansas, is 377,000; in Wisconsin, 2,665,000. In Kentucky, 6,000,000; in Ohio, 30,000,000. In Maryland, Virginia, North Carolina, South Carolina, Georgia, Alabama, Mississippi, Florida, Louisiana, and Texas, together less than Massachusetts. In the fifteen slave states, 81,000,000; in Pennsylvania, 84,000,000; in New York, 115,000,000; and in the sixteen free states, 334,000,000.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER X. POST OFFICE DEPARTMENT. The following tables, Nos. LV., LVI., and LVII., will show the amounts actually credited for the transportation of the mails in the several States, and the amount of postages collected in the same, for the fiscal years ending June 30, 1850, and June 30, 1855. Few tables can be more suggestive, or more amply repay a careful investigation, than these. At the present day, the energy and business character of a people, their roads, railroads, steamboats, and other means of transportation, are all given, in a word, in their Post-Office reports. TABLE LV. Showing the Amounts actually credited for the Transportation of Mails, and the Amounts of Postage collected in the Slave and Free States in 1850. SLAVE STATES. Total Postage Collected. Transportation. FREE STATES Total Postage Collected. Transportation. Alabama $75,937 75 $143,798 70 California $227,152 82 $111,515 87 Arkansas 17,215 53 61,244 90 Connecticut 119,971 81 62,176 13 Delaware 12,521 38 6,489 87 Illinois 115,184 53 156,685 71 Florida 13,793 24 31,701 55 Indiana 83,638 03 76,225 82 Georgia 101,749 42 146,772 94 Iowa 26,568 86 24,850 05 Kentucky 86,472 49 87,121 70 Maine 89,761 92 46,690 25 Louisiana 116,936 06 68,464 61 Massachusetts 358,120 72 132,164 84 Maryland 121,864 61 143,150 97 Michigan 62,387 69 39,634 58 Mississippi 55,536 01 84,256 58 N. Hampshire. 59,902 20 27,662 00 Missouri 83,787 95 101,313 23 New Jersey 66,156 20 42,813 37 N. Carolina 46,647 07 154,977 40 New York 933,977 13 324,970 14 S. Carolina 76,108 62 108,488 80 Ohio 286,311 24 138,836 32 Tennessee 64,185 86 74,142 59 Pennsylvania. 396,699 91 146,105 64 Texas 28,474 12 114,744 83 Rhode Island. 39,328 34 12,088,20 Virginia 141,579 13 169,687 83 Vermont 58,965 44 50,643 93 Wisconsin 60,725 35 34,759 77 Total $1,042,809 24 $1,496,356 50 Total $2,975,852 19 $1,427,822 63 TABLE LVI. Showing the Amounts actually credited for the Transportation of the Mails, and the Amount of Postage collected in the Slave States in 1855. SLAVE STATES. Letter Postage. Newspaper Postage. Stamps Sold. Total Postage Collected. Transportation. Alabama $46,416 $13,583 $44,514 $104,514 $226,816 Arkansas 16,894 4,828 8,941 30,664 117,659 Delaware 9,967 2,377 7,298 19,644 9,243 Florida 8,167 2,343 8,764 19,275 77,553 Georgia 59,117 16,066 73,880 149,063 216,003 Kentucky 59,307 15,065 55,694 130,067 144,161 Louisiana 69,140 13,833 50,778 133,753 133,810 Maryland 82,029 31,712 77,743 191,485 192,743 Mississippi 36,092 11,464 31,182 78,739 170,785 Missouri 71,372 14,537 53,742 139,652 185,096 North Carolina 26,831 11,692 34,235 72,759 148,249 South Carolina 36,156 8,075 47,368 91,600 192,216 Tennessee 42,070 13,238 48,377 103,686 116,091 Texas 37,373 8,532 24,530 70,436 209,936 Virginia 92,562 28,499 96,799 217,861 245,592 Total $693,493 $195,844 $66,845 $1,553,198 $2,385,953 TABLE LVII. Showing the Amounts actually credited for the Transportation of the Mails, and the Amount of Postage collected in the Free States in 1855. FREE STATES. Letter Postage. Newspaper Postage Stamps Sold. Total Postage Collected. Transportation. California $141,833 $11,319 $81,437 $234,591 $135,386 Connecticut 75,691 24,254 79,284 179,230 81,462 Illinois 142,177 32,457 105,252 279,887 280,038 Indiana 95,248 24,578 60,578 180,405 190,480 Iowa 44,540 9,680 28,198 82,420 84,428 Maine 75,779 15,413 60,165 151,358 82,218 Massachusetts 239,894 33,226 259,062 532,184 153,091 Michigan 77,223 15,201 49,763 142,188 148,204 New Hampshire 46,225 10,995 38,387 95,609 46,631 New Jersey 66,645 11,556 31,495 109,697 80,084 New York 734,453 106,206 542,498 1,383,157 481,410 Ohio 237,457 47,227 167,958 452,643 421,870 Pennsylvania 301,646 64,073 217,293 583,013 251,833 Rhode Island 23,812 4,520 30,291 58,624 13,891 Vermont 44,465 12,036 36,314 92,816 64,437 Wisconsin 65,406 13,959 33,538 112,903 92,842 Total $2,412,494 $436,700 $1,719,513 $4,670,725 $2,608,295 A few of the facts which stand forth prominent in these Tables, are the following: In 1850, only two slave States, Delaware and Louisiana, paid for the transportation of their mails by the amount of postages collected. Of the free states, Illinois alone did not. In the slave States, the postages for that year less than paid for the transportation, by nearly half a million of dollars. In the free States, the postages more than paid for the transportation, by over a million and a half of dollars. In 1855, this difference is very greatly increased. The postages of the slave States less than paid the cost of transportation by over $800,000, while the free State postages more than paid the transportation, by over $2,000,000. In the slave territory, the only State which paid for transportation of its mails, by its postages, was Delaware. In the free States, the only States which did not, were Illinois, Indiana, Iowa, and Michigan. Neither North Carolina, South Carolina, Mississippi, Alabama, or Texas, paid half the expense of transporting their mails, by postages received; while Florida paid less than a fourth, and Arkansas less than a fifth. Massachusetts paid for her own transportation, and had a surplus remaining of more than four times the amount of postage collected in South Carolina. New Hampshire, Connecticut, and Pennsylvania, each paid for their transportation, by their postages, more than twice over, and Rhode Island more than four fold. The postages of New York are not an eighth less than those of all the slave States, while the expense of transportation is but little more than one-fifth the expense in those States. The fifteen slave States did not pay, by postages, two-thirds the expense of transporting their mails. The free States paid for theirs, and had a surplus of over $2,000,000; half a million more than all the postages collected in the slave States. In other words, the free States, in this matter, support themselves, pay the deficit in the slave States and have over $1,200,000 besides.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER XI. VALUE OF CHURCHES, AND AMOUNT OF CONTRIBUTIONS FOR CERTAIN BENEVOLENT OBJECTS. The following tables, Nos. LVIII. and LIX. show the amount contributed in the several States, for the Missionary, Tract, and Bible cause, by all the principal Christian denominations, except the Methodist. This denomination is not included in the tables, from the fact that all receipts are returned by conferences, which are frequently made up of several parts of States, thus precluding the possibility of separating so TABLE LVIII. Showing the Amount contributed in the Slave States for purposes of Christian Benevolence in 1855, together with the Value of Churches in 1850. SLAVE STATES. Amount contributed for the Bible cause. Amount contributed for Missionary purposes. Amount contributed for the Tract cause. Value of Churches, 1850. Alabama $3,351 $5,963 $477 $1,244,741 Arkansas 2,950 455 110 149,686 Delaware 1,037 1,003 163 340,345 Florida 1,957 340 5 192,600 Georgia 4,532 9,846 1,468 1,327,112 Kentucky 5,956 6,953 1,366 2,295,353 Louisiana 1,810 334 1,099 1,940,495 Maryland 8,909 20,677 5,365 3,974,116 Mississippi 1,067 4,957 267 832,622 Missouri 4,711 2,712 936 1,730,135 North Carolina 6,197 6,010 1,419 907,785 South Carolina 3,984 15,248 3,222 2,181,476 Tennessee 8,383 4,971 1,807 1,246,951 Texas 3,985 349 127 408,944 Virginia 9,296 22,106 6,894 2,902,220 Total $68,125 $101,934 $24,725 $21,674,581 TABLE LIX. Showing the Amount contributed in the Free States for purposes of Christian Benevolence in 1855, together with the Value of Churches in 1850. FREE STATES. Amount contributed for the Bible cause. Amount contributed for Missionary purposes. Amount contributed for the Tract cause. Value of Churches. 1850. California $1,900 $192 $5 $288,400 Connecticut 24,528 48,044 15,872 3,599,330 Illinois 28,403 10,040 3,786 1,532,305 Indiana 6,755 4,705 1,491 1,568,906 Iowa 4,216 1,750 2,005 235,412 Maine* * $18,628 as given in the Report for the four together. 5,449 13,929 1,794,209 Massachusetts* 43,444 128,505 10,504,888 Michigan 5,554 4,935 1,114 793,180 New Hampshire* 6,271 11,963 1,433,266 New Jersey 15,475 19,946 3,546 3,712,863 New York 123,386 172,115 61,233 21,539,561 Ohio 25,758 19,890 9,576 5,860,059 Pennsylvania 25,360 43,412 12,121 11,853,291 Rhode Island 2,669 9,440 2,121 1,293,600 Vermont* 5,709 11,094 1,251,655 Wisconsin 4,790 2,216 474 512,552 Total $319,667 $502,174 $131,972 $67,773,477 as to give the amount from each State. Indeed, there is some difficulty in dividing the amount justly between the slave and free States; but this is not as great as in dividing it between all the several States, since the sum collected in all the conferences, made up partly of slave and partly of free Territory, is but $35,000, which could make but little difference in the result, however it might be divided. The amount collected for the Tract cause and the support of missions, was, for the past year, in the Northern conferences, $225,000, of which $35,000 was from conferences embracing both slave and free territory. According to the Annals of Southern Methodism, for the year 1855, the amount raised in the Methodist Church South, in the year 1854, was $168,931, "and for the year just closing, the amount will fall somewhat below that," says the author. Taking these facts and dividing the $35,000 according to the best of our information, the amount contributed for these purposes, in the Methodist Church, is a few thousand dollars greater in the free than in the slave States. This of course is exclusive of the operations of the "Book Concern," &amp;c., &amp;c. The amount contributed by all other denominations is given by States in the tables, which are compiled from the last annual report of the several societies. The amount contributed in the slave States, for the Bible cause, was, during the past year, $68,125; in the free States, $319,667; a ratio of over 4 1–2 to 1. The amount contributed for the support of missions was, in the slave States, $101,934, and in the free States, $502,174; almost exactly five dollars to one. The amount contributed in the slave States for the publication and distribution of Tracts, was $24,725; and in the free States, $131,972; a ratio still greater, and over five dollars at the North to one at the South. The amount contributed in the State of Massachusetts, for the support of missions, is greater than in all the slave States, while the amount contributed in the State of New York, both for the missionary and Bible cause, was nearly twice as great as in all the territory of slavery. It will be seen that the value of Churches in the slave States is $21,674,581, and in the free States, $67,773,477; a ratio of more than 3 to 1—the Churches of New York being equal in value to those of the fifteen slave States. The amount contributed in the several States for the various benevolent objects which from time to time present themselves, it is impossible to ascertain. But the report of the Portsmouth Relief Association, just published, shows the amount received from the different States "For the relief of Portsmouth, Va., during the prevalence of the yellow fever in that town in 1855." It is certainly gratifying to see that the call for help was no promptly answered from the most distant States. The amount of money contributed by the slave States, exclusive of Virginia, in which State the sickness prevailed, was $12,182. In the free States it was $42,547, or 3 and 1–2 times as much in the free as in the slave States. Including the State of Virginia, the amount given by the slave States was $33,398, or $9,141 more given by the sixteen free States than by the fifteen slave States. This is exclusive of provisions and other valuable supplies, amounting to thousands of dollars, sent from all parts of the Union.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER XII. THE LAWS OF KANSAS. That our readers may understand exactly what the laws are which the free State men in Kansas are now threatened with death for disobeying, we present such portions of the statute book of that Territory as relate especially to the institution of slavery. The public must judge whether or not the laws deserve the epithets, "outrageous," "unconstitutional," "disgraceful," lately bestowed on them by Mr. Cass, Mr. Geyer, and Mr. Weller. The title of the volume from which we quote, is: "The Statutes of the Territory of Kansas, passed at the first Session of the Legislative Assembly, one thousand eight hundred and fifty-five. To which are affixed, the Declaration of Independence, and the Constitution of the United States, and the Act of Congress organizing said Territory, and other Acts of Congress having immediate relation thereto. Printed in pursuance of the statute in such cases made and provided. Shawnee M. L. School: John T. Brady, Public Printer. 1855."* * This volume is extremely rare. There is thought to be but one copy in New England—the one we have used—which belongs to Dr. T. H. Webb, of the Emigrant Aid Company. At the treaty, recently made by Gov. Shannon with the free State men at Lawrence, it was one of the stipulations that two copies of this work should be furnished the people of Lawrence. We have not learned whether the governor keeps his promises as well as usual. Pp. 1058. Elections.—(Chapter 66, section 11, page 332.) Every free white male citizen of the United States, and every free male Indian, who is made a citizen, by treaty or otherwise, and over the age of twenty-one years, who shall be an inhabitant of this Territory, and of the county or district in which he offers to vote, and shall have paid a Territorial tax, shall be a qualified elector for all elective officers; and all Indians who are inhabitants of this Territory, and who may have adopted the customs of the white man, and who are liable to pay taxes, shall be deemed citizens; Provided, that no soldier, seaman, or marine, in the regular army or navy of the United States, shall be entitled to vote by being on service therein; And provided further, that no person who shall have been convicted of any violation of any of the provisions of an act of Congress, entitled, "An act respecting fugitives from justice, and persons escaping from the service of their masters," approved February 12th, 1793; or of an act to amend and supplementary to said act, approved 18th September, 1850; whether such conviction were by criminal proceeding, or by civil action for the recovery of any penalty prescribed by either of said acts, in any court of the United States, or any State or Territory, of any offence deemed infamous, shall be entitled to vote at any election, or to hold any office in this Territory; And provided further, that if any person offering to vote shall be challenged and required to take an oath or affirmation, to be administered by one of the judges of the election, that he will sustain the provisions of the above recited acts of Congress, and of the act entitled, "An act to organize the Territories of Nebraska and Kansas," approved May 30, 1854, and shall refuse to take such oath or affirmation, the vote of such person shall be rejected. Sec. 12. Every person possessing the qualification of a voter, as herein above prescribed, and who shall have resided in this Territory thirty days prior to the election at which he may offer himself as a candidate, shall be eligible as a delegate to the house of representatives of the United States, to either branch of the legislative assembly, and to all other offices in this territory, not otherwise especially provided for; Provided however, that each member of the legislative assembly, and every officer elected or appointed to office under the laws of this territory, shall, in addition to the oath or affirmation specially provided to be taken by such officer, take an oath or affirmation to support the constitution of the United States, the provisions of an act, entitled, "An act respecting fugitives from justice and persons escaping from the service of their masters," approved February 12, 1793; and of an act to amend and supplementary to said last mentioned act, approved September 18th, 1850; and of an act, entitled, "An act to organize the Territories of Nebraska and Kansas," approved May 30, 1854. Officers.—(Chapter 117, section 1, page 516.) All officers elected or appointed under any existing or subsequently enacted laws of this Territory, shall take and subscribe the following oath of office: "I——do solemnly swear, upon the holy Evangelists of Almighty God, that I will support the Constitution of the United States, and that I will support and sustain the provisions of an act, entitled, 'An act to organize the Territories of Nebraska and Kansas,' and the provisions of the law of the United States, commonly known as the 'Fugitive Slave Law,' and faithfully and impartially, and to the best of my ability, demean myself in the discharge of my duties in the office of——; so help me God." Jurors.—(Chapter 92, section 13, page 444.) No person who is conscientiously opposed to the holding of slaves, or who does not admit the right to hold slaves in this Territory, shall be a juror in any cause in which the right to hold any person in slavery is involved, nor in any cause in which any injury done to or committed by any slave is in issue, nor in any criminal proceeding for the violation of any law enacted for the protection of slave property and for the punishment of crimes committed against the right to such property. Attorneys at Law.—(Chapter 11, section 3, page 132.) Every person obtaining a license (to practice law) shall take an oath, or affirmation, to support the Constitution of the United States, and to support and sustain the provisions of an act, entitled, "An act to organize the Territories of Nebraska and Kansas," and the provisions of an act, commonly known as the "Fugitive Slave Law," and faithfully to demean himself in his practice, to the best of his knowledge and ability. A certificate of such oath shall be endorsed on the license. Slaves.—(Chapter 151; page 715.) An Act to punish offences against slave property. Section 1.Be it enacted, by the Governor and Legislative Assembly of the Territory of Kansas, That every person, bond or free, who shall be convicted of actually raising a rebellion, or insurrection of slaves, free negroes or mulattoes, in this Territory, shall suffer death. Sec. 2.Every free person, who shall aid and assist in any rebellion or insurrection of slaves, free negroes, or mulattoes, or shall furnish arms, or do any overt act in furtherance of such rebellion or insurrection, shall suffer death. Sec. 3.If any free person shall, by speaking, writing, or printing, advise, persuade, or induce any slaves to rebel, conspire against, or murder any citizen of this Territory, or shall bring into, print, write, publish, or circulate, or cause to be brought into, printed, written, published, or circulated, or shall knowingly aid or assist in the bringing into, printing, writing, publishing, or circulating in this Territory, any book, paper, magazine, pamphlet or circular, for the purpose of exciting insurrection on the part of the slaves, free negroes, or mulattoes, against the Territory, or any part of them, such person shall be guilty of felony and suffer death. Sec. 4.If any person shall entice, decoy, or carry away out of this Territory, any slaves belonging to another, with the intent to deprive the owner thereof of the services of such slaves, or with intent to effect or procure the freedom of such slave, he shall be adjudged guilty of grand larceny, and, on conviction thereof, shall suffer death, or be imprisoned at hard labor for not less than ten years. Sec. 5.If any person aids or assists in enticing, decoying, or persuading, or carrying away, or sending out of this Territory, any slave belonging to another, with intent to procure or effect the freedom of such slave, or with intent to deprive the owner thereof of the services of such slave, he shall be adjudged guilty of grand larceny, and, on conviction thereof, shall suffer death, or be imprisoned at hard labor for not less than ten years. Sec. 6.If any person shall entice, decoy, or carry away out of any State or other Territory of the United States, any slave belonging to another, with intent to procure or effect the freedom of such slave, or to deprive the owner thereof of the services of such slave, and shall bring such slave into this Territory, he shall be adjudged guilty of grand larceny, in the same manner as if such slave had been enticed, decoyed, or carried away out of the Territory, and in such case the larceny may be charged to have been committed in any county of this Territory, into or through which such slave shall have been brought by such person, and, on conviction thereof, the person offending shall suffer death, or be imprisoned at hard labor for not less than ten years. Sec. 7.If any person shall entice, persuade, or induce any slave to escape from the service of his master or owner in this Territory, or shall aid or assist any slave escaping from the service of his master or owner, or shall assist, harbor, or conceal any slave who may have escaped from the service of his master or owner, he shall be deemed guilty of felony, and punished by imprisonment at hard labor for not less than five years. Sec. 8.If any person in this Territory shall aid or assist, harbor, or conceal any slave who has escaped from the service of his master or owner in another State or Territory, such person shall be punished in like manner as if such slave had escaped from the service of his master or owner in this Territory. Sec. 9.If any person shall resist any officer while attempting to arrest any slave that may have escaped from the service of his master or owner, or shall rescue such slaves when in custody of any officer or other person, or shall entice, persuade, aid, or assist such slave to escape from the custody of any officer, or other person who may have such slave in custody, whether such slave has escaped from the service of his master or owner in this Territory or in any other State or Territory, the person so offending shall be guilty of felony, and punished by imprisonment at hard labor for a term not less than two years. Sec. 10.If any Marshal, Sheriff, or Constable, or the Deputy of any such officer, shall, when required by any person, refuse to aid or assist in the arrest and capture of any slave that may have escaped from the service of his master or owner, whether such slave shall have escaped from his master or owner in this Territory or any other State or Territory, such officer shall be fined in a sum of not less than one hundred nor more than five hundred dollars. Sec. 11.If any person print, write, introduce into, publish, or circulate, or cause to be brought into, printed, written, published, or circulated, or shall knowingly aid or assist in bringing into, printing, publishing, or circulating within this Territory, any book, paper, pamphlet, magazine, handbill, or circular, containing any statements, arguments, opinions, sentiment, doctrine, advice, or inuendo, calculated to produce a disorderly, dangerous or rebellious disaffection among the slaves in this Territory, or to induce such slaves to escape from the service of their masters, or resist their authority, he shall be guilty of felony, and be punished by imprisonment at hard labor for a term not less than five years. Sec. 12.If any free person, by speaking or writing, assert or maintain that persons have not the right to hold slaves in this Territory, or shall introduce into this Territory, print, publish, write, circulate, or cause to be written, printed, published, or circulated in this Territory, any book, paper, magazine, pamphlet, or circular containing any denial of the right of such persons to hold slaves in this Territory, such person shall be deemed guilty of felony, and punished by imprisonment at hard labor for a term not less than two years. Sec. 13.No person who is conscientiously opposed to holding slaves, or who does not admit the right to hold slaves in this Territory, shall sit as a juror on the trial of any prosecution for the violation of any of the sections of this act. This act to take effect and be in force from and after the 15th day of September, A. D. 1855. Chapter 152, page 718. An Act giving meaning to the word "State." Sec. 1.Wherever the word "State" occurs in any act of the present Legislative Assembly, or any law of the Territory, in such construction as to indicate the locality of the Operation of such act or laws, the same shall in every instance be taken and understood to mean "Territory," and shall apply to the Territory of Kansas.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER XIII. EXTRACT FROM AN ARTICLE BY CHARLES C. HAZEWELL, IN THE BOSTON DAILY CHRONICLE, OF AUGUST 12, 1856. The first Southern authority that we shall quote, is that of an actor in the business spoken of—William Moultrie. There is no purer name connected with the history of our Revolution than that of Moultrie. He commanded the American forces that successfully defended the fort on Sullivan's Island, June 28th, 1776, against a strong British squadron—perhaps, all things considered, the most gallant action of the war, and the last that was fought, so far as we know, while our country was still in a formal condition of colonial dependence. The fort was subsequently named after him. He served with brilliancy and usefulness subsequently to the date mentioned, and rose to the rank of major-general in the national service. He was elevated to the place of Governor of South Carolina, in days when men thought worthy of that post would sooner have died than have approved of an attempt to commit murder. In 1802, Governor Moultrie published, in two volumes, Memoirs of the American Revolution, so far as it related to the States of North and South Carolina, and Georgia, ete. This is an interesting work, boldly written and faithfully compiled, and bearing on every page evidences of the author's ability, integrity, and enlightened patriotism. He was, in short, worthy to stand side by side with Marion, Sumpter, Laurens, and the rest of those Carolina soldiers who served their country so well, and whose eminent worth has ever been admitted by all Northern men. When the British Gen. Prevost (Moultrie calls him Provost) appeared before Charleston, May 11th, 1779, Gen. Moultrie was appointed to command the troops in that town, by Governor Rutledge and the council, who were then and there present. He represents the governor to have been much frightened, overrating the enemy's force, and underrating that of the Americans. Governor Rutledge, says Gen. Moultrie, "represented to me the horrors of a storm; he told me that the State's engineer (Col. Senf) had represented to him the lines to be in a very weak state: after some conversation, he proposed to me the sending out a flag, to know what terms we could obtain; I told him, I thought we could stand against the enemy; that I did not think they could force the lines; and that I did not choose to send a flag in my name, but if he chose it, and would call the council together, I would send any message: they requested me to send the following, which was delivered by Mr. Kinloch: "General Moultrie perceiving from the motions of your army, that your intention is to besiege the town, would be glad to know on what terms you would be disposed to grant a capitulation, should he be inclined to capitulate." (Moultrie's Memoirs, vol. I., p. 427.) To this message, Gen. Prevost made a reply, full of those promises which the British commanders were so ready to give, and equally ready to break after their enemies had been deluded into placing faith in them. This letter was given to the governor, who called a meeting of the council, at which Moultrie, Pulaski, and Laurens were present. The question of giving up the town was argued, the military men all advising the civilians not to think of surrendering, and showing that the enemy could be beaten off; but Gov. Rutledge would have it that the American force was much exaggerated, and was ready to believe in any statement that exaggerated the British strength. Finally, Gen. Moultrie was authorized to send an answer to Gen. Prevost, refusing to surrender on the latter's terms, but offering, if he would appoint an officer to confer on terms, to send one to meet him, at such time and place as Gen. Prevost might fix on. Gen. Moultrie says: "When the question was carried for giving up the town upon a neutrality, I will not say who was for the question but this I well remember, that Mr. John Edwards, one of the privy council, a worthy citizen, and a very respectable merchant of Charleston, was so affected as to weep, and said, 'What, are we to give up the town at last?' "The governor and council adjourned to Colonel Beekman's tent on the lines, at the gate. I sent for Colonel John Laurens from his house, to request the favor he would carry a message from the governor and council to General Prevost; but when he knew the purpose, he begged to be excused from carrying such a message that it was much against his inclination; that he would do anything to serve his country; but he could not think of carrying such a message as that! I then sent for Colonel M'Intosh, and requested he would go with Colonel Roger Smith, who was called on by the governor, with the message; they both begged I would excuse them; hoped, and requested I would get some other person. I, however, pressed them into a compliance; which message was as follows: "'I propose a neutrality during the war between Great Britain and America, and the question, whether the State shall belong to Great Britain, or remain one of the United States? be determined by the treaty of peace between those two powers.'" (Memoirs, Vol. I., pp. 432–33. John Marshall, so long Chief Justice of the United States Supreme Court, a Virginian by birth, and a man of the highest reputation, has given a brief account of what happened at Charleston after Prevost's arrival befor it, "The town was summoned to surrender," he says, "and the day was spent in sending and receiving flags. The neutrality of South Carolina, during the war, leaving the question whether that State should finally belong to Great Britain or the United States to be settled in the treaty of peace, was proposed by the garrison and rejected by Prevost." (Marshall's Life of Washington, vol. I. pp. 298–9, Phil, ed., 1832.) Among the historians of the American Revolution is Dr. Ramsay, of South Carolina, whose history was published in 1789. In his account of what happened at Charleston, after Gen Prevost's arrival before that place, occurs the following passage: "Commissioners from the garrison were instructed to propose a neutrality during the war between Great Britain and America, and that the question whether the State shall belong to Great Britain, or remain one of the United States, be decided by the treaty of peace between these powers." The British commanders refused this advantageous offer, alleging that they had not come in a legislative capacity, and insisted that, as the inhabitants and others were in arms, they should surrender prisoners of war. (Ramsay, p. 425.) The last authority we shall quote is Professor Bowen.* * Of Harvard University. After mentioning the proposal made to the British commander, he comments on it as follows: "This proposal did not come merely from the commander of a military garrison, in which case, of course, it would have been only nugatory; the governor of the State, clothed with discretionary powers, was in the place, and probably most of his council along with him. Whether such a proposition would have been justifiable under any circumstances is a question that needs not be discussed; at any rate, it would not have evinced much honorable or patriotic feeling. But to make such an offer in the present case was conduct little short of treason. Till within a fortnight, not an enemy's foot had pressed their ground; and even now, the British held no strong position, had captured none of their forts, and occupied only the little space actually covered by the army in front of the town. The garrison equalled this army in strength, and might safely bid it defiance. No succors were at hand for the British, while the certain arrival of Lincoln within a week would place them between two fires, and make their position eminently hazardous. Yet, with these prospects before them, the authorities of the place made a proposition, which was equivalent to an offer from the State to return to its allegiance to the British crown. The transaction deserves particular notice here, because the surrender of Charleston, in the following year, a surrender brought about by the prevalence of the same unpatriotic feelings, was made the ground of some very unjust reflections on the conduct of Lincoln, their military commander." (Life of Benjamin Lincoln, in Spark's American Biography, Sec. Ser., vol. XIII, pp, 285–6 " "The Committee appointed to take into consideration the circumstances of the Southern States, and the ways and means for their safety and defence, report, that the State of South Carolina (as represented by the delegates of said State, and by Mr. Huger, who has come here at the request of the governor of said State, to explain the circumstances thereof,) is UNABLE to make any effectual efforts with militia, by reason of the great proportion of citizens necessary to remain at home to prevent insurrection among the negroes, and to prevent the desertion of them to the enemy. That the state of the country and the great number of these people among them, expose the inhabitants to great danger from the endeavor of the enemy to excite them to revolt or desert." (From the Secret Journal of the Continental Congress, vol. I, page 105, under date of March 29,1779.)</field>
   </doc>
</add>