<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university of virginia</field>
      <field name="author_text">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1910's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2005_Q2_2/uvaBook/tei/z000000249.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240342</field>
      <field name="date_text">January 1, 1918</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:114302</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The University of Virginia record. New Series Vol. IV, No. 1, January 1, 1918</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">University of Virginia -- Periodicals</field>
      <field name="subject_text">University of Virginia -- Periodicals</field>
      <field name="title_display">The University of Virginia record.  New Series Vol. IV, No. 1, January 1, 1918</field>
      <field name="title_facet">university of virginia record</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">university of virginia record</field>
      <field name="title_text">The University of Virginia record.  New Series Vol. IV, No. 1, January 1, 1918</field>
      <field name="year_display">January 1, 1918</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1918-01-01</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1918</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:114302&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:114302&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;serial volume&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;university of virginia&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The University of Virginia record. New Series Vol. IV, No. 1, January 1, 1918&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;university of virginia record&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;January 1, 1918&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1918-01-01&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The University of Virginia record&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="volume"&gt;New Series Vol. IV&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="issue"&gt;No. 1&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;January 1, 1918&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Va.&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="LC call number"&gt;LD5667 .A43&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa call number"&gt;LD5667.2&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;X004575062&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;o07560180&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;21 p. ; 23 cm.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;University of Virginia -- Periodicals&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The University of Virginia Record&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="volume"&gt;New Series, 4&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="issue"&gt;1&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1918-01-01&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2005&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2005 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 88 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PUBLICATIONS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. The University of Virginia Record: No. 1, January 1: Catalogue of the Department of Law. No. 2, January 15: Preliminary Summer School Announcement. No. 3, February 1: General Catalogue. No. 4, February 15: Catalogue of the Department of Medicine. No. 5, March 1: Catalogue of the Department of Engineering. No. 6, March 15: Catalogue of the Summer School. No. 7, April 1: Circular of Information. No. 8, April 15: Catalogue of the Department of Graduate Studies. The University of Virginia Record, Extension Series, published ten times a year. The Alumni Bulletin of The University of Virginia, published five times a year: October 1, January 1, April 1, July 1, August 1. The Alumni News, published by the Alumni Association twenty times a year, appearing bi-weekly throughout the session. The Virginia High School Bulletin, published quarterly, in November, February, May and August. Bulletin of The University of Virginia Library, published at intervals during the session. The Virginia Law Review, published by the Virginia Law Review Association monthly from October to May.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA RECORD New Series, Vol. IV, No. 1 January 1, 1918 DEPARTMENT OF LAW CATALOGUE 1917-1918 Entered as Second-Class Matter September 28, 1914, at the Post-office at Charlottesville, Virginia, under the Act of August 24, 1912.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DEPARTMENT OF LAW. Edwin Anderson Alderman, Ph.B., D.C.L., LL.D. President. William Minor Lile, LL.D. Dean. William Minor Lile, LL.D. East Lawn James Madison Professor of Law. Charles Alfred Graves, M.A., LL.D. East Lawn Professor of Law. Raleigh Colston Minor, M.A., LL.B. West Lawn James Monroe Professor of Law. * * Absent on leave, for military service. Armistead Mason Dobie, M.A., LL.B. Monroe Hill Professor of Law. George Boardman Eager, Jr., B.A., LL.B. Minor's Cottage Professor of Law. Charles Wakefield Paul McCormick Road Adjunct Professor of Public Speaking. Forrest Jesse Hyde, Jr., LL.B. Colonnade Club Acting Adjunct Professor of Law. Catherine Rebecca Lipop Law Librarian Inquiries with reference to Entrance Requirements should be addressed to the Dean of the University. For information as to lodgings, board, expenses, etc., and for catalogues and other printed matter, address the Registrar. For other information, address the Dean of the Department of Law. Historical.—Among the original Schools contemplated in Mr. Jefferson's plan for the organization of the University of Virginia was "Law: Municipal and Foreign; Embracing the General Principles, Theory and Practice of Jurisprudence, together with the Theory and Principles of Constitutional Government." Accordingly the School of Law was established in 1826, and has been in continuous operation since. From the establishment of the Law School until 1894, the course comprised the work of a single year. With the session of 1894-95, a two years' course was inaugurated, which continued up to the session of 1899-10, when the course was extended to three years. The aim of the Department of Law has always been to maintain a high standard as a requirement for graduation—the degree being conferred only upon such students as are thorough masters of the prescribed course of study. This policy has been rigorously enforced, and its wisdom has been vindicated by the high position which the graduates of the Law School are accustomed to attain at the bar or in public life. The course of instruction has been extended from time to time to conform to changing conditions and to meet the increasing needs of the profession. Minor Hall.—By action of the Visitors, the new home of the Law School has been named Minor Hall, in honor of the late John B. Minor, whose distinguished service of fifty years as a professor in the Law School, the University thus commemorates. The building is located between Dawson's Row and the southern end of West Range. The architecture is on classic lines, in keeping with the general design of the other university buildings. It contains on the first floor four large lecture halls, with convenient offices, lavatories, etc., and on the second floor a stack room with ample space for books, two commodious reading rooms, and a number of offices for the use of the librarian and the teaching staff. Liberal provision has been made for heat, light, and ventilation. Special care has been taken to provide comfortable seats and desks in the lecture halls. Law Library.—The Library contains about fourteen thousand volumes. Its financial resources, from appropriations by the Visitors, and from an endowment of ten thousand dollars by Mr. W. W. Fuller ('78), of New York City, make possible the addition of several hundred volumes annually. The Library contains the English Reports, from and including the Year Books to date; the United States Supreme Court Reports; reports of all the American States; the National Reporter System, complete; modern selected and annotated reports, such as the American Decisions, Reports and State Reports, Lawyers' Reports Annotated, American and English Annotated Cases, English Ruling Cases, etc., together with modern search-books in the form of general Digests (including the Century and Decennial editions), and the leading Encyclopedias, besides a large collection of text-books, bound volumes of law magazines, etc. Law students have all the privileges of the general University Library, containing more than ninety thousand volumes, without extra charge. The Virginia Law Review.—Under the title of The Virginia Law Review, the undergraduate students of the Law School conduct a law journal devoted to the discussion of general questions of American jurisprudence. Eight numbers are issued annually, from October to May inclusive. The Review is now in its fifth volume. From its inception it has maintained a high standard of excellence, and a worthy rank among the leading law journals of the country. Suggestions as to Preliminary Education.—Students, and their parents or guardians, are warned that the law is peculiarly an intellectual profession, and demands for its successful prosecution, whether in a law school or in the broader fields of professional life, a well-trained mind. If it be true that untrained recruits, in rare instances, under diligent and persistent effort, develop into successful practitioners after entrance upon the practice, such exceptional cases but serve to illustrate the rule that out of a given number of young men entering upon the study of law, those with sound preliminary training will have incomparable advantages, while those without such training are likely never to rise above mediocrity in their profession. The experience of the Law Faculty—indeed, of all law teachers—is, that the standing and progress of law students may, in general, be measured by their academic preparation. Young gentlemen are therefore advised not to begin their legal studies until they have completed an academic course approximating that required for the degree of Bachelor of Arts. So high a standard, however, is not exacted as a condition of entrance into the Law School. These conditions are shown in the following sections. ENTRANCE REQUIREMENTS. Regular Students.—Candidates for the degree of Bachelor of Laws must have attained the age of eighteen years before entering the department, must produce a certificate of good character from the school or college last attended, or from other satisfactory source, and must conform to the general requirements following: For Admission to the Department of Law the candidate must offer fifteen units, of which three must be in English and one in History. Notice is given that an additional requirement of one year of work in a standard college will become effective with the beginning of the session of 1919-20. The Subjects accepted for Admission and their values in units are given in tabulated form on page 5. The applicant for admission may enter (1) by certificate or (2) by examination. (1) For Admission by Certificate the candidate must file with the Dean of the University not later than September 1 a Certificate of Preparation, made out on the blank form furnished by the University. This certificate must come from some recognized institution of collegiate rank or from an accredited high school; but admission by certificate from accredited public high schools in Virginia is extended only to graduates of four-year high schools. The certificate must bear in all cases the signature of the head of the school; must specify the character and content of each course offered for entrance credit; must give the length of time devoted to the course, and the dates of the examinations; and must give the candidate's grades in percentages. Each unit in the entrance requirements is the equivalent of one full year of high school work, including five periods a week at least forty minutes each during not less than thirty-six weeks. For schools in which the number of periods given to any study, or the length of the period, is below the standard here specified, the credit for such study will be reduced pro rata. In the scientific subjects two hours of laboratory instruction will be counted as the equivalent of one hour of recitation. High school courses in physics and chemistry, otherwise adequate, will be allowed half credit, when individual laboratory work is not done by the student or is not attested by proper note-books filed with the certificate. Certificates of preparation from private tutors will in no case be accepted; students thus prepared must, in all cases, take the entrance examinations. (2) For Admission by Examination the candidate must present himself for test at the University in June or September, according to the dates given in the Programme of Entrance Examinations, which may be had by applying to the Registrar. The examinations are held under the honor system, no paper being accepted unless accompanied by the usual pledge. All candidates who take their examinations at the times appointed are tested free of charge. In case of delayed entrance, where the grounds of postponement are good, the President of the University may admit the candidate to a special examination, for which an additional fee of five dollars is charged. The fee is payable in advance, and is in no case returned. Satisfactory certificates as to character and age are in all cases required. SUBJECTS ACCEPTED FOR ADMISSION Subject Topics Units English A Grammar and Grammatical Analysis 1 English B Composition and Rhetoric 1 English C Critical Study of Specimens of English Literature 1 English D Critical Study of Specimens of English Literature 1 Mathematics A1 Algebra to Quadratic Equations 1 Mathematics A2 Quadratics, Progressions and the Binomial Formula ½ or 1 Mathematics B Plane Geometry 1 Mathematics C Solid Geometry ½ Mathematics D Plane Trigonometry ½ History A Greek and Roman History 1 History B Mediaeval and Modern European History 1 History C English History 1 History D American History and Civil Government 1 Latin A Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 Latin B Caesar's Gallic War, I-IV; Grammar; Composition 1 Latin C Cicero's Orations (6); Grammar; Composition 1 Latin D Virgil's Æneid, I-VI; Grammar; Composition 1 Greek A Elementary Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 Greek B Xenophon's Anabasis, I-IV; Grammar; Composition 1 Greek C Homer's Iliad, I-III; Grammar; Composition 1 German A Elementary Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 German B Intermediate Grammar, Composition and Translation 1 German C Third-Year Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 German D Fourth-Year Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 French A Elementary Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 French B Intermediate Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 French C Third-Year Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 French D Fourth-Year Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 Spanish A Elementary Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 Spanish B Intermediate Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 Spanish C Third-Year Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 Spanish D Fourth-Year Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 Science A Physical Geography 1 Science B Inorganic Chemistry 1 Science C Experimental Physics 1 Science D Botany ½ Science E Zoölogy ½ Science F Agriculture (special schools) 2 Drawing Mechanical and Projection Drawing 1 Shop-Work Wood-Work, Forging, and Machine-Work 1 Special Students.—An applicant who is at least 23 years old, and who presents proper evidence of good character, and of needful maturity and training, though unable to fulfill the foregoing entrance requirements, may, by special action of the Law Faculty, in exceptional cases, be admitted as a special student, and not as a candidate for the degree. Every applicant for admission as a special student shall make written application to the Dean of the University, on a blank furnished for the purpose, with detailed information as to his age, general habits, his educational and business experience, and his general fitness to undertake the study of law. Such application, together with such testimonials as may be required, must be filed with the Dean of the University not later than September 1 of the year in which the applicant desires to enter the Law School. For good cause shown, the requirement as to the time of filing such application may be waived. Every such applicant for admission as a special student must pass a satisfactory examination, to be held at the University during the registration days of the session. The examination, which will be conducted by a committee of the Law Faculty, may include the subjects of English, American and English History, and Civil Government. This regulation is subject to the general university regulation as to delayed entrance examinations. Special students who fail to complete 60 per cent of the work taken during any session may be declared ineligible for readmission the following session. Admission to Advanced Standing.—No credit is given for attendance at another law school, nor for time spent in private reading. The candidate for graduation must spend three years in residence. The Session begins on the Thursday preceding the nineteenth of September, and continues for thirty-nine weeks. The first three days of the session are given to registration, and all students, both old and new, are required during that time to place their names upon the books of the University and the rolls of their respective classes. Lecture courses begin on the following Monday, and absences will be recorded against any student not present from the opening lecture of each course. Students entering after the first three days, without satisfactory excuse, will be charged a fee for registration. Late Entrance.—Students are advised that late entrance is a serious hindrance to progress. The student who enters late must begin his work at the point to which the several courses have advanced at the time of his entrance; and credit for three years' attendance cannot be secured unless the student is in actual residence at least thirty weeks per session. No registration in absentia is permissible. Expenses.—The necessary expenses of a student in the Department of Law may be estimated at $425 per session of nine months. This minimum estimate includes all university and tuition fees, board, lodging, washing and books. An average estimate would be $500 per session, reckoning board, lodging, washing and books at a somewhat higher figure. The university fee applicable to all law students (including those from Virginia) is $40; and the tuition fee is $100 for the regular work of each session. For special students who desire to take selected courses, the tuition fee is estimated according to the ratio which the work chosen bears to the whole. Three Years' Course.—The course of study embraces three years of thirty-six weeks each, exclusive of holidays. Residence for three years, with attendance of at least thirty weeks a year, exclusive of holidays, is essential to graduation. Plan of Instruction.—The instruction is as thorough as possible, and is given partly through textbooks and lectures, and partly through the study of cases. While convinced of the value of the combined text-book and lecture system, which has prevailed for more than half a century in the Law School, the Law Faculty have long appreciated the value that the study of cases possesses, in illustrating the practical application of legal principles, and in forcing the student to extract for himself the doctrine which the cases establish. The recent enlargement of the course gives opportunity for more emphasis on this form of instruction, and the case-book will, therefore, be used more extensively than heretofore—not as supplanting, but as supplementing, the textbooks and lecture. The daily oral quiz has long been a marked and, as experience has proved, a most valuable feature of the system of instruction. As cross-examination exposes error and develops truth, so the daily quiz enables the instructor to discover and rectify misconception of legal principles on the part of the student. This oral quiz is supplemented by frequent written tests, the results of which are carefully recorded, and, in the professor's discretion, are considered in estimating the final grade of the student. Practical Work.—In the course on Equity Procedure, Virginia Pleading, Practice at Law, Code Pleading, Criminal Procedure, and Legal Bibliography and Brief Making, special stress is laid upon practical work. In the Pleading and Procedure courses, every student is required to draw, and submit for correction and criticism, all of the principal pleadings, orders, decrees, and other forms encountered in actual litigation. In the course on Legal Bibliography and Brief Making, an intimate acquaintance with law books and skill in their use are secured by oral and written quizzes, and finally by practical tests; and briefs on assigned topics are required to be prepared according to rigorous standards. Much practical work is done in the headnoting of cases on scientific principles. Required for Graduation.—The degree of Bachelor of Laws (LL.B.) is conferred upon such students as have attained the age of twenty-one years; have satisfied the entrance requirements; have attended three full sessions of the Law School; and have successfully passed the required examinations, with satisfactory performance of assigned practical work. More specifically, the candidate for graduation must have completed all of the obligatory courses (see Outline of Courses, below), and at least two elective courses, one of which must be either the course in Virginia Pleading or that in Code Pleading. It follows that of the courses termed "elective," a required minimum is in fact obligatory—the candidate being permitted to exercise an election among them. OUTLINE OF COURSES. The course, as outlined below, contemplates an average of ten lecture periods (or fifteen hours) per week. Each session is divided into three terms. See table, page 11. Written examinations are held during the final week of each term, on the subjects completed during the term, with the exception of the examination in Forensic Debating, which is held at the end of the session. See Schedule of Examinations, page 13. The following outline indicates the extent of the courses offered: TABULAR OUTLINE OF COURSES. [Asterisks indicate elective courses.—Lecture periods are one and a half hours each.] FIRST YEAR. Course No. FIRST TERM. Periods per week Total periods 1. Study of Cases—Legal Bibliography—Brief Making— Statutes. Cooley's Brief Making; Wambaugh's Study of Cases; the Professor's Printed Notes. Professor Lile 2 26 2. Contracts. Clark on Contracts; Huffcut and Woodruff's Cases on Contracts; the Professor's Printed Notes. Professor Graves 4 52 3. Criminal Law. Mikell's Cases on Criminal Law. Adjunct Professor Hyde 2 26 12. Domestic Relations. Long on Domestic Relations. Professor Eager 2 26 4. Forensic Debating. Adjunct Professor Paul 2 26 SECOND TERM. 6. Torts, including Master and Servant. Chapin on Torts; Chase's Cases on Torts; the Professor's Printed Notes; Burks' Printed Notes. Professor Graves 4 40 7. Bailments and Carriers. Dobie on Bailments and Carriers; Dobie's Cases on Bailments and Carriers. Adjunct Professor Hyde 3 30 8. Agency. Mechem's Principles of Agency. Professor Eager 2 20 4a. Forensic Debating. Adjunct Professor Paul 3 30 THIRD TERM. 9. Negotiable Paper. Bigelow on Bills, Notes and Cheques; the Negotiable Instruments Law; the Professor's Printed Notes. Professor Lile 2 20 10. International Law. Davis' Elements of International Law. Professor Minor 2 20 11. Sales. Benjamin's (R. M.) Principles of Sales. Adjunct Professor Hyde 2 20 13. Insurance. Vance on Insurance. Professor Eager 3 30 4b. Forensic Debating. Adjunct Professor Paul 3 30 SECOND YEAR. FIRST TERM. 14. Equity Jurisprudence. Merwin's Principles of Equity; the Professor's Printed Notes. Professor Lile 4 52 15. Common Law Pleading. Burks on Pleading and Practice; Sunderland's Cases; the Professor's Printed Notes and Questions. Professor Graves 2 26 17. Real Property (begun). Minor on Real Property. Professor Minor 4 52 SECOND TERM. 18. Private Corporations. Clark on Corporations; the Virginia Corporation Act; Wormser's Cases on Private Corporations. Professor Lile 4 40 19. * * Omitted 1918-1919. Pleading in Virginia. Burks on Pleading and Practice; the Professor's Printed Notes. Professor Graves 2 20 17a. Real Property (concluded). Minor on Real Property. Professor Minor 3 26 16. Constitutional Law (begun). Minor's Notes on Government; Black's Constitutional Law. Professor Minor 3 4 22. * * Omitted 1918-1919. Code Pleading.1 Bryant on Code Pleading. Professor Dobie 2 20 20. * * Omitted 1918-1919. Admiralty. Hughes on Admiralty. Professor Eager 2 20 THIRD TERM. 21. Practice at Law, including Extraordinary Remedies. Burks on Pleading and Practice; Graves' Printed Notes. Professor Eager 3 30 16a. Constitutional Law (concluded). Minor's Notes on Government; Black's Constitutional Law. Professor Minor 4 40 27. Taxation. Goodnow's Cases on Taxation. Adjunct Professor Hyde 2 20 THIRD YEAR. FIRST TERM. 25. Criminal Procedure. Beale on Criminal Pleading and Practice; the Professor's Printed Notes. Professor Minor 2 26 26. Wills and Administration. Costigan's Cases on Wills. Adjunct Professor Hyde 2 26 38. * * Omitted 1918-1919. Roman Law. Morey's Outlines of Roman Law. Professor Dobie 2 26 28. Bankruptcy. Remington on Bankruptcy (Students' Edition). Professor Eager. 2 26 29. Partnership. Mechem's Elements of Partnership. Professor Eager 2 26 SECOND TERM. 31. Equity Procedure. Lile's Equity Pleading and Practice. Professor Lile 2 20 32. Conflict of Laws and Jurisdictions. Minor on the Conflict of Laws. Professor Minor 3 30 33. Federal Jurisdiction and Procedure. Hughes on Federal Procedure. Adjunct Professor Hyde 3 30 34. * * Omitted 1918-1919. Damages. Hale on Damages. Professor Eager 2 20 THIRD TERM. 35. Public Corporations. Macy's Cases on Municipal Corporations; the Professor's Printed Notes. Professor Lile 2 20 36. Legal Ethics, Preparation of Cases, and Practice of the Law. Costigan's Cases on Legal Ethics; Cohen's The Law—Business or Profession; the Code of Ethics of the American Bar Association; Answers to Questions by the Committee of the New York County Bar Association on Professional Ethics. Professor Lile 2 20 37. Evidence. Greenleaf on Evidence (16th edition by Wigmore); Throckmorton's Cases; the Professor's Printed Notes. Professor Graves 6 60 CONDENSED TABLE OF COURSES FOR THE SESSION OF 1918-1919. (Subject to alteration.) FIRST YEAR SECOND YEAR THIRD YEAR First Term—September 15 to December 16—13 Weeks.† † Exclusive of one week devoted to examinations. Professor Lile Periods per week Total periods Professor Lile Periods per week Total periods Professor Minor Periods per week Total periods 1. Study of Cases 2 26 Legal Bibliography Brief Making Interp. Statutes 25. Criminal Procedure 2 26 Professor Graves 14. Equity Jurisprudence 4 52 Professor Hyde 2. Contracts 4 52 Professor Graves 26. Wills and Administration 2 26 Professor Hyde 15. Common Law Pleading 2 26 38. * * Electives. Roman Law‡ ‡ Omitted 1918-1919. 2 26 3. Criminal Law 2 26 Professor Minor Professor Eager Professor Paul 17. Real Property (begun) 4 52 28. Bankruptcy 2 26 4. Forensic Debating 2 26x x Sections 1, 2 and 3 only. Other sections in subsequent terms, as per schedule next page. 29. Partnership 2 26 Professor Eager 12. Domestic Relations 2 26 Second Term—January 2 to March 14—10 Weeks.† † Exclusive of one week devoted to examinations. Professor Lile 18. Private Corporations 4 40 Professor Graves Professor Lile Professor Graves 19. * * Electives. Pleading in Virginia 2 20 31. Equity Procedure 2 20 6. Torts, Including Master and Servant 4 40 Professor Minor Professor Minor 17a. Real Property (concluded) 3 26 32. Conflict of Laws 3 30 Professor Hyde Professor Hyde 7. Bailments and Carriers 3 30 16. Constitutional Law (begun) 3 4 33. Federal Jurisdiction and Procedure 3 30 Professor Eager 8. Agency 2 20 Professor Eager Professor Eager 20. * * Electives. Admiralty 2 20 34. * * Electives. Damages 2 20 Professor Dobie 22. * * Electives. Code Pleading‡ ‡ Omitted 1918-1919. 2 20 Third Term—March 22 to May 31—10 Weeks.† † Exclusive of one week devoted to examinations. Professor Lile Professor Eager Professor Lile 9 Negotiable Paper 2 20 21. Practice at Law 3 30 35. Public Corporations 2 20 Professor Minor Professor Minor 36. Legal Ethics, Preparation of Cases and Practice of the Law 2 20 10 International Law 2 20 16a. Constitutional Law (concluded) 4 40 Professor Hyde 11. Sales 2 20 Professor Hyde Professor Graves Professor Eager 27. Taxation 2 20 37. Evidence 6 60 13. Insurance 3 30 SCHEDULE OF LECTURES FOR THE SESSION OF 1918-1919. (Subject to such alteration as the faculty may deem necessary.) FIRST TERM Hours Monday Tuesday Wednesday Thursday Friday Saturday 9:30 to 11:00 Forens. Debating (i) Real Property Criminal Law Real Property Forens. Debat. (ii) Real Property Roman Law Criminal Law Criminal Procedure Forens. Debat. (i) Real Property Roman Law Criminal Procedure 11:00 to 12:30 Contracts Forens. Debat. (iii) Com. Law Plead. Contracts Forens. Debat. (iii) Com. Law Plead. Contracts Contracts 12:30 to 2:00 Forens. Debating (ii) Equity Jurisp. Bankruptcy Brief Making Partnership Domestic Rel. Equity Jurisp. Wills and Admin. Brief Making Bankruptcy Domestic Rel. Equity Jurisp. Wills and Admin. Equity Jurisp. Partnership. SECOND TERM 9:30 to 11:00 Forens. Debating (iv) Real Property Constitutional Law Bailments and Carriers Admiralty Conflict of Laws Forens. Debat. (iv) Real Property Constitutional Law Damages Bailments and Carriers Admiralty Conflict of Laws Forens. Debat. (iv) Real Property Constitutional Law Bailments and Carriers Damages 11:00 to 12:30 Torts Virginia Pleading Torts Virginia Pleading Torts Torts 12:30 to 2:00 Forens. Debating (v) Private Corporations Fed. Jurisd. &amp; Proced. Agency Equity Procedure Code Pleading Forens. Debat. (v) Private Corporations Fed. Jurisd. &amp; Proced. Agency Equity Procedure Code Pleading Forens. Debat. (v) Private Corporations Fed. Jurisd. &amp; Proced. Private Corporations Conflict of Laws THIRD TERM 9:30 to 11:00 Evidence International Law Evidence Sales Evidence International Law Evidence Sales Evidence Evidence 11:00 to 12:30 Forens. Debating (vi) Constitutional Law Practice at Law Forens. Debat. (vi) Constitutional Law Practice at Law Forens Debat. (vi) Constitutional Law Constitutional Law 12:30 to 2:00 Legal Eth. &amp; Pr. of L. Insurance Negotiable Paper Taxation Insurance Public Corporations Negotiable Paper Taxation Insurance Public Corporations Legal Eth. &amp; Pr. of L. Practice at Law SCHEDULE OF EXAMINATIONS. For Session 1918-1919. Examinations will be held on successive days during the last week of each term, on all subjects completed during the term, and in order indicated below. Examinations in courses marked (a) are held in the afternoon; those marked (o) are omitted in 1918-1919. First Term Second Term Third Term 1. Contracts Federal Procedure Constitutional Law Bankruptcy (a) Bailments and Car. (a) Negotiable Paper (a) 2. Real Property (i) Real Property (ii) Evidence 3. Roman Law (o) Conflict of Laws Legal Ethics, etc. (a) Criminal Law (a) Admiralty (a) 4. Wills and Adm. Torts Sales Equity Procedure (a) 5. Brief Making, etc. (a) Private Corporations Insurance Equity Jurisprudence Damages (a) Public Corporations (a) 6. Criminal Procedure Virginia Pleading Practice at Law Domestic Relations (a) Agency (a) International Law (a) 7. Common Law Plead. Code Pleading (o) Taxation (a) Partnership (a) The Charles Minor Blackford Prize in the Department of Law was established through the liberality of Mrs. Susan Colston Blackford, of Lynchburg, Va., in memory of her husband, the late Charles Minor Blackford, a distinguished alumnus of the Law School. The prize consists of fifty dollars in cash, and is awarded each year to a student in the Department of Law for the best essay on some legal or sociological subject. Each competitor must file with the Dean of the Department of Law not later than April 15 his name and the title of his essay, and must file his completed essay not later than May 1st. All essays must be typewritten, must contain not more than 15,000 words, and must not be folded. The award is made by a committee of three competent persons, not locally connected with the University, to be selected annually by the Law Faculty. In making the award, literary form as well as subject matter is taken into consideration. GENERAL REGULATIONS. 1. Registration of New Students.—Before registration in the Law School, students who have not before been registered in any department of the University must produce to the Dean of the Law School (office in Minor Hall) a certificate from the Dean of the University that entrance requirements have been fulfilled. 2. Registration Generally.—Students must register in advance at the office of the Dean of the Law School and with the Registrar for every course taken, and no credit will be given for work done in any course without proper registration therefor. 3. Delayed Registration.—Students are not permitted to delay their registration through carelessness or for inadequate reasons. Any student, new or old, who fails to present himself for registration during the first three days of the session, and between the hours of nine a. m. and two p. m. on the first week-day after the Christmas Recess, will be admitted to registration only upon the consent of the Dean, and will be charged a special registration fee of three dollars. 4. Exchange or Omission of Courses.—After registration no course may be exchanged or omitted except on the written approval of the professor in charge and of the Dean. 5. Carrying Over Uncompleted Work.—Students who are deficient in the work of one year will be permitted to take but a limited amount of the work of the succeeding year. 6. Minimum for Which Student Must Register.—No student, without special permission, and for good cause, may register for less than nine periods per week. 7. Advanced Work.—Students of one year are not permitted to anticipate the courses of a subsequent year, without urgent reasons satisfactory to the Dean. 8. Late Entrance Into Classes.—No credit is given for the completion of any course upon which the student has entered after fifty per centum of the lectures thereon have been delivered. 9. Optional Attendance.—A student who has attended the required lectures upon any subject may, on written application, with the endorsed approval of the professor in charge, and of the Dean, secure optional attendance on a limited number of such subjects the following session, but subject to Regulation 5. 10. General Requirements.—Every student of the Law School is required to attend all regular exercises of the classes of which he is a member, and to perform all the work assigned, including quizzes and examinations, unless excused for good cause by the faculty. 11. Invalids.—Students whose condition of health is too precarious to permit regular attendance upon lectures, but not serious enough to admit them as patients of the hospital, will be required to withdraw from the University until able to resume their regular work. 12. Conditions of Readmission.—Any student who, without satisfactory cause, has not attained for the session, on his examinations, credit for courses comprising in the aggregate at least 150 periods, or, in lieu thereof, a grade of 75 per centum on courses aggregating 200 periods, will be excluded from the Law School the following session. The result of one or more special examinations, granted for cause under existing regulations, may be considered in determining whether this requirement has been met. The foregoing provisions do not affect students who have been permitted, for cause, to take less than two-thirds of a full year's work. Such students will be subject to exclusion or other conditions as may be prescribed. In this connection, attention is called to Regulation 5 foregoing. 13. Students Admitted on Terms of Diligence, by reason of previous unsatisfactory record in the Law School or other department of the University, will be held to an average class grade (or examination grade, in classes in which class grades are not recorded) of 75 per centum, in the work of the first term. Failure to attain this grade without satisfactory cause, unless the result of his other examinations shall raise his average grade to the required standard, will operate to exclude such delinquent from the Law School for the remainder of the session. An average class grade of less than 75 per centum, at the end of any term, will be regarded as evidence of a lack of the diligence required by the terms of this condition. 14. First-Year Students.—Failure on the part of any first-year student, without just cause, to attain, for the first term, an average grade of 75 per centum on the daily written quizzes, will place such student on probation for the remainder of the session, and the student and his parent or guardian will be so notified. Unless, in the opinion of the Law Faculty, a decided improvement in the character of such student's work is indicated at the end of the second term, he will be required to withdraw from the Law School. 15. Absence from the University is permitted upon the written leave of the Dean of the Law School. But leaves of absence for the purpose of accompanying the athletic teams or musical clubs on excursions will not be granted, except to the officers and members of the organizations. 16. Absence from Lectures may be excused by the professors for sickness or like providential cause. Such excuses must be rendered on the day of the first lecture attended after the absence. Unexcused absences from lectures render the student liable to be disciplined. 17. Special Examinations.—No special examinations are granted, save in cases of sickness on the day of examination (attested by physician's certificate), or for other imperative cause approved by the Law Faculty. In no case will such examination be granted, unless prompt application be made therefor. 18. Reöxaminations—Third-Year Students.—Candidates for the degree, who have failed on one or more subjects during their third year, may return the following session, and stand the regular examinations on such subjects, without further attendance upon lectures. But this privilege may be exercised but once—that is to say, after a second failure the candidate must take the lectures over again, on the subject or subjects on which he has for a second time proved deficient. 19. Examination Fees.—The fee for standing such examinations as are mentioned in the preceding regulation is $5 for each examination taken. Students who, under such circumstances, return for further lectures, and who have paid full matriculation and tuition fees for three years, pay a matriculation fee in proportion to the amount of work taken plus $5 for each course. There is no charge for special examinations granted for imperative cause. 20. Honor System.—All examinations are conducted under the Honor System. 21. Application for Degree.—Candidates for graduation are required to file a written application with the Dean, not later than November 15th of their third year, indicating the courses completed, together with a schedule of the courses to be pursued during their final year. Blanks for his purpose will be supplied on application to the Dean. 22. Required Withdrawal.—The right is reserved to require the withdrawal of any student who, in the opinion of the faculty, is not profiting nor likely to profit by the instruction offered; or whose neglect or irregular performance of required duties, after admonition, indicates indifference or contumacy; or whose habits are a menace to the good order of the Law School. REGISTER OF STUDENTS. FIRST-YEAR CLASS. Adkins, John Chandler Williamsburg, Ky. Bowman, Norman Wilson Vanceburg, Ky. Bryan, Albert Vickers Alexandria, Va. Carpenter, Winfred Wayland, Jr. New Franklin, Mo. Chapman, John Sherman, Jr. Stanardsville, Va. Cheatham, Walter Hill Richmond, Va. Cumming, Thomas William Augusta, Ga. Devier, Sheffey Lewis Harrisonburg, Va. Dudley, Oliver Witcher, Jr. Danville, Va. B.A., University of Virginia. Duke, Thomas Walter Daniel Hopewell, Va. Edmunds, Thomas Murrell Lynchburg, Va. Etheridge, James Edward Norfolk, Va. Fitzpatrick, Walter Cabell University, Va. Ford, Fitzhugh Lee Newport News, Va. Frost, Edward Marshall Lynchburg, Va. Godwin, Charles Bernard, Jr. Chuckatuck, Va. Groseclose, Hubert French Pulaski, Va. Hart, Henry Beverly, Jr. Memphis, Tenn. Harvey, Irvin Abraham Pizarro, Va. M.A., Princeton University, N. J. Hill, Napoleon Memphis, Tenn. James, Rorer Anderson, Jr. Danville, Va. Knight, Howard Vernon Fredericksburg, Va. Kootz, Samuel Melvin Portsmouth, Va. Lavenstein, Meyer Harry Petersburg, Va. McGregor, George Pate Laurinburg, N. C. Mackall, John Chichester Langley, Va. Mahood, Charles Decatur Princeton, W. Va. Mears, Leonard Cecil, Jr. Keller, Va. Palmer, Allison Everhart Orlando, Fla. Pearce, Clarence Benjamin Kirkwood, Ga. Phillips, John Barton Alexandria, Va. Preston, Leonard Washington Glasgow, Ky. Quesenbery, William Doyle Waynesboro, Va. Ruffin, Richard Willing Norfolk, Va. Rumble, Gerould McLean Norfolk, Va. B.A., University of Virginia. Sheppard, Lawrence Baker Hanover, Pa. Silver, Maurice Aaron Philadelphia, Pa. Smith, Richard March Norfolk, Va. Thornton, William Tobin Floresville, Texas Vest, George Burnley Charlottesville, Va. Wolfe, Samuel Dante Elkton, Va. Wood, David Joseph Birdwood, Va. SECOND-YEAR CLASS. Bishop, Marvin Lord, Jr. Casper, Wyo. Blackwell, Charles Claiborne Broad Run, Va. Block, Maurice Leon Gordonsville, Va. Cabell, William Wymond Richmond, Va. Carlisle, James Douglas Savannah, Ga. B.A., Mercer University, Ga. Cassidy, John Thomas Lexington, Ky. Cole, John Norfolk, Va. Collins, Cecil Cornelius Covington, Va. B.A., Rock Hill College, Md. Fatherly, Dunton Jacob Weirwood, Va. B.A., Richmond College, Va. Franklin, William Donovan Charlottesville, Va. Gaither, Roscoe Bradley University, Va. B.S., University of Virginia. Harris, A. Hardin Richmond, Va. Herd, Marc Allaire Casanova, Va. Hudson, John McConico Newport News, Va. Jackson, Thomas Brown Charleston, W. Va. B.Litt., Princeton University, N. J. Jones, Sydney Bruce Galax, Va. Lankford, Charles Magruder, Jr. Franktown, Va. Meade, Edwin Baylies Danville, Va. Mears, Benjamin William Eastville, Va. Monroe, Joseph Simpson Wise, Va. Norris, Hannon Edwards Fredericksburg, Va. Oppenhimer, Henry A. Wise Richmond, Va. Orr, John Burrow Morristown, Tenn. B.A., Emory and Henry College, Va. Pidgeon, James Memphis, Tenn. Powell, William Smith Springdale, Ark. Revercomb, William Chapman Covington, Va. Showalter, English Roanoke, Va. B.A., Virginia Christian College, Va. Stanton, Hugh Wright Memphis, Tenn. B.S., A. and M. College, Miss. Terrell, Claudius Keyser, W. Va. Wallace, Philip Hugh Paducah, Ky. Whitehead, Robert Lovingston, Va. Woodward, Thomas Lassiter Suffolk, Va. Wright, John Wesley Roanoke, Va. THIRD-YEAR CLASS. Bishop, John Henderson Monterey, Va. Booker, Bernard Douglas Newport News, Va. Boyd, Edwin Thurman Wilmette, Ill. Dolan, Harry Thomas Montrose, Pa. DuVal, Thaddeus Ernest, Jr. Gloucester, Va. Flood, Joel West Appomattox, Va. Garden, George Alan Wheeling, W. Va. Holland, Walton Gregory Virginia Beach, Va. McCormack, Michael Joseph Ansonia, Conn. Maxey, Melville Anderson Richmond, Va. Moncure, Powhatan Bealeton, Va. O'Connor, Leo Charles Richmond, Va. Ruffin, Edmund Sumter, Jr. Norfolk, Va. B.A., University of Virginia. Spandorfer, Reuben Esor Norfolk, Va. Vansant, William Galen Chestertown, Md. B.A., Washington College, Md. Wilson, John Goodrum, Jr. Smithfield, Va. SPECIAL STUDENTS. Lenahan, James Rafter Richmond, Va. Martin, Reuben Joseph Washington, D. C. Snyder, Ben Paul Norfolk, Va. Thompson, Howard Clark Hampton, Va. SUMMARY BY STATES. Arkansas 1 Connecticut 1 District of Columbia 1 Florida 1 Georgia 3 Illinois 1 Kentucky 5 Maryland 1 Missouri 1 North Carolina 1 Pennsylvania 3 Tennessee 5 Texas 1 Virginia 65 West Virginia 4 Wyoming 1 Total 95</field>
   </doc>
</add>