<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university of virginia</field>
      <field name="author_text">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1920's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2005_Q2_2/uvaBook/tei/z000000306.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240342</field>
      <field name="date_text">April 1, 1924</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:117795</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The University of Virginia record. New Series Vol. X, No. 9, April 1, 1924</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">University of Virginia -- Periodicals</field>
      <field name="subject_text">University of Virginia -- Periodicals</field>
      <field name="title_display">The University of Virginia record.  New Series Vol. X, No. 9, April 1, 1924</field>
      <field name="title_facet">university of virginia record</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">university of virginia record</field>
      <field name="title_text">The University of Virginia record.  New Series Vol. X, No. 9, April 1, 1924</field>
      <field name="year_display">April 1, 1924</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1924-04-01</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1924</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:117795&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:117795&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;serial volume&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;university of virginia&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The University of Virginia record. New Series Vol. X, No. 9, April 1, 1924&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;university of virginia record&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;April 1, 1924&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1924-04-01&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The University of Virginia record&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="volume"&gt;New Series Vol. X&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="issue"&gt;No. 9&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;April 1, 1924&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Va.&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="LC call number"&gt;LD5667 .A43&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa call number"&gt;LD5667.2&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;X004169703&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;o07560180&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;38 p. ; 23 cm.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;University of Virginia -- Periodicals&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The University of Virginia Record&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="volume"&gt;New Series, 10&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="issue"&gt;9&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1924-04-01&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2005&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2005 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 137 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PUBLICATIONS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. The University of Virginia Record: No. 1, December 15: Department of Medicine: Announcements. No. 2, January 1: Department of Law: Announcements. No. 3, January 15: Department of Engineering: Announcements. No. 4, January 15: Summer Quarter: Preliminary Announcement. No. 5, February 15: General Catalogue. No. 6, March 1: Catalogue of the Summer Quarter. No. 7, March 15: Department of the College: Announcements. No. 8, March 15: Department of Graduate Studies: Announcements. No. 9, April 1: Department of Education: Announcements. The University of Virginia Record, Extension Series, published ten times a year. The Alumni Bulletin of The University of Virginia, published five times a year: October 1, January 1, April 1, July 1, August 1. The Alumni News, published by the Alumni Association twenty times a year, appearing bi-weekly throughout the session. The Virginia High School Bulletin, published quarterly, in November, February, May and August. Bulletin of The University of Virginia Library, published at intervals during the session. The Virginia Law Review, published by the Virginia Law Review Association monthly from October to May.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA RECORD New Series, Vol. X, No. 9 April 1, 1924 The Curry Memorial Department of Education ANNOUNCEMENTS 1924-1925 Entered as Second-Class Matter September 28, 1914, at the Post-office at Charlottesville, Virginia, under the Act of August 24, 1912.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CALENDAR. 1924 Thursday, January 3 Beginning of Second Term. Wednesday, March 5—Saturday, March 15 Second Term Academic Examinations. Monday, March 17 Beginning of Third Term. Monday, April 14 Jefferson Day Holiday. Monday, May 26—Thursday, June 5 Final Academic Examinations. Monday, June 2—Saturday, June 7 Entrance Examinations. Sunday, June 8 Baccalaureate Sermon. Monday, June 9 Alumni Day. Meeting of the Rector and Visitors. Tuesday, June 10 Final Day. Monday, June 16 Opening of the Summer Quarter, First Term. Saturday, July 26 Closing of the Summer Quarter, First Term. Monday, July 28 Opening of the Summer Quarter, Second Term. Saturday, August 30 Closing of the Summer Quarter, Second Term. Monday, September 15—Saturday, September 20 Entrance Examinations. Thursday, September 18 Beginning of One hundred-first Session. Thursday, September 18—Saturday, September 20 Registration Days. Monday, September 22 Beginning of Lecture Courses. Thursday, October 2 University Convocation. Thursday, November 27 Thanksgiving Day (Holiday). Wednesday, December 10—Saturday, December 20 First Term Academic Examinations. Monday, December 22—Friday, January 2 Christmas Recess. 1925 Saturday, January 3 Beginning of Second Term. Wednesday, March 11—Saturday, March 21 Second Term Academic Examinations. Monday, March 23 Beginning of Third Term. Monday, April 13 Jefferson Day (Holiday). Monday, June 1—Thursday, June 11 Final Academic Examinations. Monday, June 8—Saturday, June 13 Entrance Examinations. Sunday, June 14 Baccalaureate Sermon. Monday, June 15 Alumni Day. Meeting of the Rector and Visitors. Tuesday, June 16 Final Day.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE CURRY MEMORIAL DEPARTMENT OF EDUCATION. Edwin Anderson Alderman, Ph.B., D.C.L., LL.D. President. John Levi Manahan, M.A., Ph.D. Dean. THOMAS FITZHUGH, M.A. Professor of Latin HARRY TAYLOR MARSHALL, B.A., M.D. Walter Reed Professor of Pathology CHARLES GILMORE MAPHIS, Ped.D., LL.D. Professor of Education IVEY FOREMAN LEWIS, B.A., M.S., Ph.D. Miller Professor of Biology and Agriculture JOHN LEVI MANAHAN, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Educational Administration WILLIAM ALLISON KEPNER, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Biology WILLIAM ROYALL SMITHEY, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Secondary Education GEORGE OSCAR FERGUSON, JR., M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Psychology and Education JOSEPH HUDNUT, M. Arch. Professor of Art and Architecture W. PATTON GRAHAM, M.A. Associate Professor of Romanic Languages CARL CASKEY SPEIDEL, Ph.B., Ph.D. Associate Professor of Anatomy WILLIAM EDWARD KNIGHT, M.E. Assistant Professor of Romanic Languages WILLIAM SUMNER APPLETON POTT, M.A., Ph.D. Assistant Professor of Philosophy WILLIAM SHIREY KEISTER, A.B., A.M., M.D. Assistant Professor of Public Health HISTORY. The Curry Memorial School of Education was founded in 1905 as one of the academic schools of the University. It was endowed by gifts of $100,000 from John D. Rockefeller and $50,000 from the General Education Board, and was named in honor of Dr. J. L. M. Curry, the Southern educator. There were originally two professorships in the School, the Curry Memorial Professorship of Education and the Professorship of Secondary Education. In 1914 a chair of Educational Psychology and Principles of Teaching was added to the School, and two years later a Professorship of School Administration was established. In 1919 the School was organized into a Department of the University, with four professorships, and was placed upon a professional basis similar to that of the Departments of Law, Medicine and Engineering. The relation of the Department of Education to the various academic schools of the University remains close, however, since the academic training of students of Education is obtained in the academic schools, and courses in Education are credited toward the academic degrees. PURPOSE. The rapid development of educational science and practice has made it necessary that ample provision be made for the professional training of those who expect to teach or to administer school affairs. It is the main purpose of the Department of Education to provide opportunity for such professional training. Since education is of great importance as an agency of Democracy and as an aspect of civilization, the Department also aims to provide courses of cultural value for citizens generally. In addition to affording opportunities for study and training, the Department, as a part of the State University, offers its services to school authorities throughout Virginia, with a desire to coöperate in the solution of practical educational problems and in the furtherance of public education. PEABODY HALL. Peabody Hall, the Education Building, was named in honor of George Peabody, who in 1867 made his great gift to the cause of education in the South. The building was made possible through a gift of $40,000 from the trustees of the Peabody Education Fund. This amount was supplemented by an appropriation of $12,000 from the Rector and Visitors of the University. The building was completed in 1912, and is the home of the Curry Memorial Department of Education. The plans were drawn by a modern school architect, and approved by the leading authorities on school architecture in this country who were consulted before its erection. It is, therefore, a model of excellence in this regard. It is one of the best equipped buildings in the University, and has ample classroom and laboratory facilities, and an excellent auditorium equipped with a modern motion picture machine. Modern requirements in heating, lighting and ventilation are exemplified in its construction without sacrificing conformity to the general style of classic architecture prevailing in the University. THE HECK MEMORIAL LIBRARY. The Department of Education maintains its own library in Peabody Hall, named in honor of the first professor of Education in the University, the late Professor William Harry Heck. The library was made possible through the gift by Mrs. Anna Tuttle Heck of Professor Heck's private library containing approximately 2000 well-selected books on Education, and the transfer of all books on Education from the General Library of the University. Splendid equipment was procured through a gift of money from students in Education, the Education Club and friends of Professor Heck. A recent gift of $2000 from Mr. Alfred W. Erickson of New York City will enable the Department so to strengthen its professional library as to offer very superior facilities to its rapidly growing student body, by making possible the enrichment of every course now offered. At present the library consists of several thousand select books covering most fields of Education, a complete file of publications of the United States Bureau of Education, various national, state and foreign documents, state school laws, annual reports of state superintendents of public instruction, city superintendents' reports, etc. Files of the leading educational magazines are available for free use of the students. Exhibits of elementary and high school texts for comparative studies are made available through the generosity of various publishers. OBSERVATION, DIRECTED TEACHING AND RESEARCH STUDIES. Laboratory facilities are made available through the coöperation of the school systems of the County of Albemarle and the City of Winchester, the local school boards in each case having approved such coöperation. This arrangement gives to students in the Department of Education a splendid opportunity to study the problems of both city and county school organization and administration. The school system of Albemarle County is now organized on the county unit basis. It consists of the following schools for white pupils: seven accredited four-year high schools, four junior high schools, five four-room schools, four three-room schools, fourteen two-room schools and twenty-one one-room schools. A number of the small schools are recognized by the State Department of Education as standard in their respective grades. During the session of 1922-23 there were 4500 white pupils enrolled. These were taught by 130 elementary school teachers and 36 high school teachers. The supervision of the county schools is under the direction of the county superintendent and four full time supervisors. The total value of sites, buildings and equipment is $435,000. This includes several new buildings of modern construction. The school system of the city of Winchester is open for observation, research and experiment by students of the Department of Education. This school system is divided into four departments: Primary, consisting of kindergarten and Grades 1, 2 and 3; Elementary, consisting of Grades 4, 5 and 6; Junior High School, consisting of Grades 7, 8 and 9; and Senior High School consisting of Grades 10, 11 and 12. Each department is in charge of a supervisor who gives all of his or her time to supervision except in the case of the supervisor of the junior high school, who does part time teaching temporarily. There are twelve teachers in the primary department, ten in the elementary department, and seventeen in the junior and senior high school departments. The new plant opened in 1923 provides many features in addition to the regular classrooms. For the elementary school division there will be a covered play court with fresh air ventilation for year-round use; a nature study court; outdoor classrooms for convalescent and anemic children; and facilities for hot lunch provided in the high school cafeteria. In the junior and senior high school division, besides the regular classrooms equipped with movable desks, there will be a business department with special equipment; science laboratories and science lecture rooms; sewing and cooking laboratories with special equipment; art studios; music studios; industrial shops for woodworking, metal working, electrical working and agriculture; library study and reference room; gymnasium and swimming pool; teachers' work room and library. For recreation and community service there will be provided an art gallery exhibit and history museum, auditorium seating twelve hundred, an athletic stadium, tennis courts, golf course, arboretum, and public park. ENTRANCE REQUIREMENTS. Requirements for the Admission of Men.—To be admitted to regular standing in the Department of Education, men must have satisfied the entrance requirements of the College. Students who have decided to enter the teaching profession at the time of entering college should register with the Dean of the Department of Education in order to be advised in planning their curricula. Holders of State Teachers' Scholarships are required to register in the Department of Education. Requirements for the Admission of Women.—To be admitted to regular standing in the Department of Education, women must be twenty years of age, must meet the entrance requirements of the University and must have completed two years of college work aggregating thirty session-hours in academic subjects. Candidates not able to meet these requirements may make up their deficiencies during the summer quarter. Special Students.—(a) Graduates of colleges and universities other than the University of Virginia, desiring to secure the necessary professional training to qualify for the Collegiate Professional Certificate, may register in the Department of Education and upon completion of the required courses receive a certificate which will entitle them to the Collegiate Professional Certificate issued by the State Board of Education. (b) Men may be admitted as special students without fulfilling the entrance requirements above specified, provided that, if they are Virginians, they are more than twenty years old or, if they are not Virginians, they are more than twenty-three years old, on the day of registration, and give adequate evidence of serious purpose and of the training needed to pursue with profit the courses for which they are registered. No special student may be a candidate for a degree; but such students are permitted and encouraged to make up deficiences by private study or by taking courses in the Summer Quarter. They will then be admitted as regular students, and may be accepted as applicants for degrees, provided all entrance requirements are met at least one academic year before the date of graduation. (c) Women, twenty-five years of age, giving satisfactory evidence that they are qualified to pursue courses in Education successfully, may be admitted as special students, even though they fail to show credit for the 30 session-hours of academic work required of women for admission to regular standing. In addition to the above, each candidate must pass at the University a qualifying examination in English before his registration can be completed. This examination will be held on the Tuesday of the first week of the session. Advanced Standing is given to any candidate who, in addition to meeting the minimum requirements for entrance above stated, can show by passing an examination given sometime during the first month of his first session that he has done work equivalent to that covered by any of the following courses offered in the college: Latin A1, Greek A1, Greek A2, English A1 or A2 or A3, German A1, Mathematics A1, French A, Spanish A. Candidates who apply for examination for advanced standing must present a special certificate showing that the full content of the course, on which advanced standing is sought, has been covered in a systematic manner in the preparatory school, and in addition must present the specific recommendation of the principal of the school that the candidate be admitted to the advanced standing examination in question. This examination will be held on the Tuesday of the week during which entrance examinations are held. College Credit.—Candidates who desire credit for work done at other colleges, must satisfy the entrance requirements for regular students, and must, in addition, file with the Dean of the Department a certificate covering the courses for which college credit is desired. The certificate must bear the official signature of the head of the candidate's college, must specify the character and content of the courses passed by the candidate, and must give his grades. The final validation of such certificates is effected by the successful completion of not less than 12 session-hours of work during his first session. In no case will credit be given on more than forty-five session-hours of work done elsewhere, and any candidate who receives this maximum amount of credit can count among the remaining fifteen session-hours required for his degree only the credit value of the courses he has passed as a resident student in the College, exclusive of any credit for work done in the Summer Quarter or in any of the professional departments. In every case the candidate must spend the last session of his candidacy, which must be a regular session of nine months, exclusively in college work in this university; and the courses offered as major electives must all have been completed in residence in this university. A maximum of 15 session-hours may be granted for one year of college work, and 33 hours for two years. Conditioned Students.—A candidate for entrance must offer fifteen units as defined by the Southern Commision on Accredited Schools. At least thirteen of the units offered must be included in the list of units accepted for admission on page 9. A student who, while able to offer fifteen units, cannot offer, fifteen units as defined in this list may be conditioned on any two units not including English A, B, or C, or Mathematics A1. All conditions must be absolved before the beginning of the session following initial registration. This may be done by passing entrance examinations or by passing equivalent courses in the Summer Quarter. But no course taken to remove a condition may be counted as part of the work credited toward a degree. No conditioned student may be later registered as a special student. GRADUATE WORK IN EDUCATION. Graduate work in Education leading to the degrees of Master of Arts, Master of Science or Doctor of Philosophy may be pursued in the Department of Graduate Studies. Graduate students who choose Education as their major for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy must meet the entrance requirements of the Department of Graduate Studies, and, in addition, must pass, at least two terms prior to receiving the degree, preliminary written examinations in each of the following fields: History of Education, Educational Psychology, Educational Administration, Secondary Education, and Educational Sociology. The candidate must also pass a final oral examination upon his dissertation and the general fields of his major and minor subjects. The Department of Education offers the following graduate courses: Education C1, Advanced Educational Psychology; Education C2, Educational Surveys, State, City and County; Education C3, Standard Tests in School Subjects; Education C4, Problems in Secondary Education; Education C5, Social Education; Education C6, Mental Tests and their Applications; Education C7, Sociology and Education; Education D1, Seminar in Educational Psychology; Education D2, Seminar in School Administration; and Education D3, Seminar in Secondary Education. SUBJECTS ACCEPTED FOR ADMISSION. The subjects accepted for admission and their values in units are given below in tabulated form. Fuller definitions of the units may be had upon application to the Dean. Subject Topics Units English A Grammar and Grammatical Analysis 1 English B Composition and Rhetoric 1 English C Critical Study of Specimens of English Literature 1 English D Critical Study of Specimens of English Literature 1 Mathematics A1 Algebra to Quadratic Equations 1 Mathematics A2 Quadratics, Progressions, and the Binomial Formula ½ or 1 Mathematics B Plane Geometry 1 Mathematics C Solid Geometry ½ Mathematics D Plane Trigonometry ½ History A Greek and Roman History 1 History B Medieval and Modern European History 1 History C English History 1 History D American History and Civil Government 1 Latin A Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 Latin B Caesar's Gallic War, I-IV; Grammar; Composition 1 Latin C Cicero's Orations (6); Grammar; Composition 1 Latin D Virgil's Æneid, I-VI; Grammar; Composition 1 Greek A Elementary Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 Greek B Xenophon's Anabasis, 1-VI; Grammar; Composition 1 Greek C Homer's Iliad, I-III; Grammar; Composition 1 German A Elementary Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 German B Intermediate Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 German C Third-year Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 German D Fourth-year Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 French A Elementary Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 French B Intermediate Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 French C Third-year Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 French D Fourth-year Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 Spanish A Elementary Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 Spanish B Intermediate Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 Spanish C Third-year Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 Spanish D Fourth-year Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 Science A Physical Geography 1 Science B Inorganic Chemistry 1 Science C Experimental Physics 1 Science D Botany ½ Science E Zoology ½ Vocational Subjects (Not more than four Units) Manual Training Mechanical and Projection Drawing ½ to 1 Free-Hand Drawing ½ to 1 Shop-Work ½ to 4 Agriculture (Accredited Agricultural Schools) 1 to 4 Commercial Subjects Commercial Geography ½ Shorthand ½ to 1 Typewriting ½ Bookkeeping 1 Commercial Arithmetic ½ to 1 ADMISSION BY CERTIFICATE. For admission by certificate, the applicant should file with the Dean of the University not later than September 1 a Certificate of Preparation, made out on the blank form furnished by the University. This certificate must come from a recognized institution of collegiate rank, from an accredited public high school, or from an accredited private secondary school. The candidate for admission from a public high school must be a graduate of an accredited four-year high school. The candidate for admission from a private secondary school must be a graduate of the school, or must present a certificate showing that he has completed at least the equivalent of four years of satisfactory high-school work of standard grade, covering at least fifteen entrance units. In every case the candidate for admission must have the recommendation of the principal of the certifying school. Private secondary schools in Virginia are accredited by the faculty of this university after inspection and report by a committee of the faculty. The university also accredits all four year public high schools which are fully accredited by the State Board of Education of Virginia. The Dean of the University is further authorized to accept certificates from schools outside Virginia, accredited by their own state universities or institutions of equal rank, or by their own state departments of education, provided the courses of study offered in such schools meet the requirements demanded of accredited schools in this state. If in any accredited school the number of periods given to a study, or the length of the period, is below the specified standard, the credit for such subject is reduced pro rata. In the science subjects only half-credit is allowed unless individual laboratory notebooks, properly attested by the teacher in charge, are filed with the certificate. Certificates of preparation from private tutors will in no case be accepted; students thus prepared must in all cases take the entrance examinations. ADMISSION BY EXAMINATION. For admission by examination, the candidate must present himself at the University in June or in September, according to the dates given in the Program of Entrance Examinations. The examinations are held under the honor system, no paper being accepted unless accompanied by the usual pledge. All candidates who take their examinations at the times appointed are tested free of charge. In case of delayed entrance, where the grounds of postponement are good, the President of the University may admit the candidate to a special examination, for which a fee of five dollars is charged. This fee is payable in advance, and is in no case returned. PROGRAM OF ENTRANCE EXAMINATIONS. June, 1924 9-11 A. M. 11 A. M.-1 P. M. 3-5 P.M. Sept. 1924 Mon. 2 Science D Greek C Science F Mon. 15 Science E Science A Science C French A French B History D Tues. 3 English A English B English C Tues. 16 Greek A Greek B French C Wed. 4 History A History B History C Wed. 17 Spanish A Spanish B Science B Thurs. 5 Math. A1 Math A2 Math. B Thurs. 18 French D Fri. 6 German A German B German D Fri. 19 Spanish C Spanish D Math. C and D Sat. 7 Latin A Latin C Latin D Sat. 20 Latin B German C English D REGULATIONS. (1) The Session-Hour.—All courses are measured in terms of the session-hour as a unit. A session-hour is one hour a week throughout the session of lecture or recitation, or two hours a week throughout the session of laboratory work. (2) Maximum and Minimum Number of Session-Hours.—Each College student is required to undertake each session courses aggregating at least fifteen session-hours (with the exception noted under Probation below). This number may be increased in the following cases: (I) Any first-year student may take eighteen session-hours, provided he is credited with six session-hours of advanced standing. (II) A student not in his first year in the College may take eighteen session-hours, provided he (a) has passed in the preceding session or in the third term thereof courses aggregating fifteen session-hours, or (b) is in his graduating year and needs eighteen session-hours for his degree. (III) A student not in his first year may take twenty-one session-hours provided he passed in the preceding session or in the third term thereof courses aggregating eighteen session-hours. (IV) Any student whose term grade (or class grade, if the term grade is not available) for the first or second term is at least 75 per cent. in each of his courses, may take three additional session-hours for the ensuing term. Exceptions to the above regulations will be allowed only by special permission of the Committee on Rules and Courses. Physical Training is not counted in the maximum and minimum requirements detailed above. (3) Grade.—The grade of a college student in any course either for a term or for the session, is determined by his class standing and his examination grade, combined in such proportion as the professor in charge of the course in question may decide. Class standing in any course is determined by the regularity of the student's attendance upon the lectures (and laboratory or other similar exercises) of the course, and by the quality of his work, as indicated by his recitation grades, written tests, laboratory work, etc. For passing in any course in the college a grade of seventy-five per cent. is required. (4) Exclusion from Courses, Probation and Suspension. (I) Exclusion from Courses: A student who, after due admonition, is evidently making no real progress in a course, may, at any time during the session, be excluded from the course by the Dean upon the recommendation of the instructor concerned. A student whose term grade in a course is less than 50 per cent., or who discontinues the course without the permission of the Dean, or who is absent without excuse from the term examination, will be automatically excluded from the course. Any student receiving a grade of less than 65 per cent. in English A1, A2, or A3 in the first or second term, must drop the course and take up English A4 at the beginning of the ensuing term. (II) Probation: (1) A student placed on 15-hour probation must pass on at least 6 session-hours of his work and average at least 60 per cent. on all his courses, or else be suspended from the College. A student placed on 15-hour probation who attains an average grade of at least 70 per cent. on all his courses, is absolved from probation. (2) A student placed on 12-hour probation must pass on at least 6 session-hours of his work and average at least 65 per cent. on all his courses, or else be suspended from the College. A student on 12-hour probation whose average grade on all his courses is at least 75 per cent., may take up 3 additional session-hours and be absolved from probation. (3) A student placed on 9-hour probation must pass on 6 session-hours of his work and average at least 70 per cent. on all his courses, or else be suspended from College. A student on 9-hour probation whose average grade on all his courses is at least 75 per cent., may take up 3 additional session-hours and be placed on 12-hour probation for the term next ensuing. A student on 9-hour probation who passes on all his courses may take up 6 additional session-hours and be absolved from probation. (III) Suspension: Suspension means enforced withdrawal from the College. If imposed during the session, it applies to the remainder of the regular session; if imposed at the end of the session; it applies to the whole of the subsequent session. In no case does it apply to the Summer Quarter. See also (6) below. No student suspended for a second time may re-enter the College. (IV) Probation and Suspension are administered as follows: (1) A student who by exclusion from a course or courses is left at the end of the first or second term with only 12 session-hours, is put on 12-hour probation* * Or 15-hour probation for a student excluded from English A1, A2, or A3, and thereby forced to take up English A4. for the term next ensuing, unless his average grade on the remaining 12 session-hours is at least 75 per cent. In this case he may take up 3 additional session-hours and escape probation. (2) A student who by exclusion from a course or courses is left at the end of the first or second term with only 9 session-hours, (a) will be put on 9-hour probation,† † Or 12-hour probation for a student excluded from English A1, A2, or A3, and thereby forced to take up English A4. unless his average grade on his remaining 9 session-hours is at least 75 per cent., in which case he may take up 3 additional session-hours and be put on 12-hour probation, or, (b) if he be other than a first-year student he will be suspended unless he has passed on at least 3 session-hours. (3) Any student not in his first year, who by exclusion from a course or courses is left at any time during the session with only 6 session-hours, will be suspended at the end of the term. Any first-year student left with only 6 session-hours will be suspended at the end of the term unless he has passed on at least 3 session-hours. In this case he will be required to take up 3 additional session-hours and be put on 9-hour probation for the ensuing term. (4) Any student not on probation who fails to attain a third-term grade or a session grade of at least 75 per cent. on at least 9 session-hours of his work, will be put on 15-hour probation for the first term of the subsequent session. A student who is permitted to withdraw from the University during the session will be readmitted on 15-hour probation if, at the time of his withdrawal, he was (a) on probation, or (b) passing on less than 9 session-hours of his work. A student previously suspended will, if re-admitted to the College, be placed on 15-hour probation. (5) No student may remain on probation for more than three terms, whether consecutive or not, in his entire college course. If his record is such as to call for the imposition of probation for a fourth time, he will be suspended instead of being placed on probation. (6) Probation or suspension imposed at the end of the regular session may be absolved by the successful completion of prescribed work in the Summer Quarter. (7) No student on probation may receive a leave of absence, except for imperative cause, nor may such a student be a member of any student organization which publicly represents the University, such as athletic teams, musical clubs, student publications, etc. (5) Absence from Examinations will not be excused, except for sickness on the day of examination, attested by a physician's certificate, or for other cause which the Faculty by special order may approve. An unexcused absence is counted as a total failure. A student excused from more than one-half of his term examinations on account of illness may not be a member of any student organization which publicly represents the University, such as the athletic teams, musical clubs, student publications, etc., until he has passed his examinations. No student may remain in the College if he misses all the examinations of two consecutive terms on account of illness. (6) Special Examinations.—A student whose absence from an examination is excused, in accordance with (5) above, is entitled to a special examination on a date during the regular session to be arranged between himself and the professor in charge of the examination. (7) Re-Examinations.—(I) A College student whose session grade in any course falls below seventy-five per cent., but not below sixty-five per cent., may, upon the written recommendation of the professor in charge, be admitted to re-examination upon that course, or upon such portion of it as the professor shall determine, during the registration week of the following September. The fee for each re-examination is five dollars, and it should be paid to the Bursar on or before July fifteenth. (II) The candidate for an academic degree who fails on only one term of one of his courses during his final session of candidacy, is entitled to a special re-examination on the work of that term before the Final Day. The candidate who passes the re-examination, as an independent unit and not averaged in with the grades of the other terms, will receive credit for the work of the whole course in question. No fee is charged for such re-examination. (8) Reports.—Reports are sent at the end of each term to the parent or guardian of each College student. These reports indicate the number of times the student has been absent from lectures, and give his term grade on each course. The dean will be glad at any time to furnish to the proper person a special report on any student's standing. In addition to the above, a report on the standing of each first year student in the College is sent to the student's parent or guardian early in November. (9) Conduct.—The laws of the University require from every student decorous, sober, and upright conduct as long as he remains a member of the University, whether he be within the precincts or not. Drunkenness, gambling, and dissoluteness are strictly forbidden, and the President may dismiss from the University for the residue of the current session every student found guilty of them, or may administer such other discipline as seems best under the circumstances. In all cases of discipline, the law requires that the student must first be informed of the objections to his conduct and afforded an opportunity of explanation and defense. The keeping of dogs by students within the University grounds is forbidden. (10) Voluntary Withdrawal.—Voluntary withdrawal from the University requires the written consent of the Dean of the University as well as the consent of the student's parent or guardian, if he is a minor. Any student who withdraws without permission will be recorded as having been suspended for the residue of the current session. No student on probation may withdraw except for imperative reasons; and any student on probation who withdraws without permission will be suspended, not only for the residue of the current session, but also for the whole of the subsequent session. (11) Enforced Withdrawal is inflicted for habitual delinquency in class, habitual idleness, or any other fault which prevents the student from fulfilling the purposes for which he should have come to the University. See also Suspension, above. (12) Change of Studies.—No change can be made in a student's program of studies except with the written consent of the Dean, together with official notification by the Registrar. No permit for change of courses will be issued after the end of the first week of each term, except that first-year students may make such changes within the first two weeks after the beginning of lectures in September. Any student who drops a course without permission will receive a grade of zero in that course; and no credit may be received for any portion of a course attended before formal permission has been granted as outlined above. (13) (a) Absence from Lectures may be excused by the professors, but only for sickness or like providential cause. Any explanation of an absence which a student has to offer must be made on the day of the first lecture attended after the absence. Unexcused absence from lectures renders the student liable to discipline by the Faculty It should be carefully noted that no student is "entitled" to be absent at all. His presence is required at each class or laboratory exercise at which he is due, unless his absence is excused for reasons outlined above or in the next paragraph below. Even if the student is absent with excuse, he must make up the work lost by such absence. No student who was, for any reason, absent from more than fifty per cent. of the lectures of any one term, can receive a grade on the work of that term. (b) Absence from the University is permitted upon the written leave of the dean, and should in every case be obtained in advance. But leaves of absence for the purpose of accompanying the athletic teams or musical clubs on excursions will not be granted, except to the officers and members of these organizations. The laws relating to absence from the University of members of the athletic teams are found on page 306 of the General Catalogue. The same regulations apply, mutatis mutandis, to members of other student organizations. No student on Probation may receive a leave of absence except for imperative cause. It should also be carefully noted that no leave of absence can be granted just before or just after a vacation, or just after term examinations, except for very grave reasons, or unless the applicant is passing in all his courses. REQUIREMENTS FOR DEGREES IN THE DEPARTMENT OF EDUCATION. Three baccalaureate degrees are offered in the Department of Education: Bachelor of Science in Education, Bachlor of Science in Health Education, and Bachelor of Science in Physical Education. The specific requirements, together with suggested curricula for the various degrees, are herewith presented. I. BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN EDUCATION. Candidates for the Degree of Bachelor of Science in Education must complete 63 session-hours, divided among Required Subjects, Education, and Electives-at-large. A. Required Subjects.—33 session-hours distributed as follows: 1. Foreign Languages. 6 session-hours, in two subjects. 2. Mathematics. 3 session-hours in Mathematics A1 or Mathematics A2. 3. Natural Science. 6 session-hours. 4. Social Science. 6 session-hours. 5. English. 9 session-hours, of which 3 must be English A1 or English A2. 6. Philosophical Science. 3 session-hours in Psychology B1 or Education B1. B. Education: 15 session-hours in Education, which must include Education B2, B5, B7, B10 and B11. Candidates having had successful experience in teaching may be permitted to substitute other work for Education B11. It should be noted that Education B10 and B11 give one session-hour and two session-hours credit, respectively, thus leaving one course in Education to be elected. Students taking Education B1 to fill the requirement in Philosophical Science will elect some course other than Education. C. Electives-at-Large: Exclusive of Education: 15 session-hours, of which 3 should be in Physical Training B1. (Not less than 9 session-hours, including one C course, of required subjects and electives must be in some one subject to be known as the candidate's Academic Major.) SUGGESTED CURRICULA LEADING TO BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN EDUCATION. Mathematics and Science. First Year Second Year Third Year Fourth Year English A1—(3)* * Credit in session-hours. Eng. Lit. B2, or Eng. B2—(3) Science (6), or Math. (3) and Hist. (3)—(6) Social Science (3) and Math. (3), or Science (6)—(6) Mathematics A1— (3) Chemistry B1, or Physics B1—(6) Educ. B11—(2) Biology B1—(6) Math. B1, or Foreign Lang.—(3) Eng. B2, or Eng. Lit. B2—(3) Educ. B5—(3) Educ. B2—(3) one elective.—(3) Foreign Lang.— (3) Psych. B1, or Educ. B1—(3) Educ. B7—(3) (14 hrs.) Physical Tr. B1— (1½) Phys. Tr. B1—(1½) Educ. B10—(1) Total 16½ hrs. (16½ hrs.) (16 hrs.) English and History. First Year Second Year Third Year Fourth Year Foreign Lang.—(3)* Eng. Lit. B2—(3) English B2—(3) Hist. C1, or Eng. C1—(3) Math. A1—(3) Hist. B1—(3) Hist. B2, or Gov. B1—(3) Educ. B11—(2) Biology B1—(6) Foreign Lang.—(6) Educ. B2—(3) Educ. B5—(3) Eng. A1—(3) Psych. B1, or Educ. B1—(3) Educ. B7—(3) 3 to 6 hrs. electives. Phys. Tr. B1—(1½) Phys. Tr. B1—(1½) Educ. B10—(1) (11 to 14 hrs.) Total 16½ hrs. (16½ hrs.) 3 to 6 hrs. electives. (16 to 19 hrs.) Foreign Languages. First Year Second Year Third Year Fourth Year Foreign Language —(3)* Foreign Lang.—(6) (continue language begun in first yr. and begin another.) Foreign Lang.—(3) Foreign Lang.—(3) Math. A1—(3) Science (6), or Math. B2 (3) and English B2 (3)—(6) Science (6), or Math. B2 (3) and Eng. B2 (3)—(6) Eng. A1—(3) Biology B1—(6) Eng. Lit. B2, or Eng. B2—(3) Educ. B2—(3) Educ. B11—(2) Phys. Tr. B1—(1½) Psych. B1, or Educ. B1—(3) Educ. B7—(3) Educ. B5—(3) Total 16½ hrs. Educ. B10—(1) (14 hrs.) Hist. B2, or Gov. B1—(3) (16 hrs.) Phys. Tr. B1—(1½) (16½ hrs.) II. BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN HEALTH EDUCATION. Purpose. The curriculum leading to the degree of Bachelor of Science in Health Education is organized to furnish the training deemed necessary for the preparation of teachers of health education in teacher-training institutions in Virginia attempting to meet the requirements of the West Law. Curriculum. The curriculum leading to this degree covers four years of training and includes a total of 63 session-hours of credit distributed by years and subjects as follows: First Year Session Hours English 3 Mathematics 2 Biology 6 Chemistry 4 Physical Education 1 ½ Total 16 ½ Second Year Session Hours English 3 Foreign Language 3 Medical Bacteriology 2 Anatomy and Psychology 3 Educational Psychology 3 Physical Education 1 ½ Total 15 ½ Third Year Session Hours English 3 Foreign Language 3 Educational Administration 3 Public Health and Health Education 4 Methods of Teaching Health Education 1 Physical Education 1 ½ Total 15 ½ Fourth Year Session Hours History and Principles of Health and Physical Education 3 Advanced Biology 3 Practice Teaching and field study 2 Educational Sociology 3 Nutrition and Foods 1 Home Nursing 1 First Aid 1 Physical Education 1 ½ Total 15 ½ III. BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN PHYSICAL EDUCATION. Purpose. The curriculum leading to the degree of Bachelor of Science in Physical Education is organized specifically for the training of supervisors of physical education. Curriculum. The curriculum leading to this degree covers four years of training and includes a total of 63 session-hours distributed by years and subjects as follows: First Year Session Hours English 3 Foreign Language 3 Mathematics 2 Biology 4 Psychology 3 Educational Gymnastics 1 ½ Total 16 ½ Second Year Session Hours English 3 Foreign Language 3 Chemistry 4 Advanced Biology 3 Medical Bacteriology 2 Educational Gymnastics 1 ½ Total 16 ½ Third Year Session Hours English (Including Public Speaking) 3 Public Health and Health Education 4 Anatomy and Physiology 3 Methods of Teaching Physical Education 1 School of Hygiene and Sanitation 3 Physical Training 1 ½ Total 15 ½ Fourth Year Session Hours History and Prin. of Health and Physical Education 3 Anthropometry, Med. Gymnastics 2 Applied Physical Education 2 ½ Practice Teaching 2 Educational Administration 3 Kinesiology 2 Total 14 ½ DESCRIPTION OF COURSES. For Undergraduates. Education B1: History and Philosophy of Education.—A study of the chief educational ideals of mankind in relation to their social and historical conditions, and as the expression of corresponding philosophies of life.—(B.A. or B.S. credit, 3 session-hours.) M. W. F., 10:30-11:30, P. H. 2. Assistant Professor Pott. (Not open to first-year students.) Education B2: Educational Psychology.—Psychology B1, prerequisite.— Original tendencies; the nature and laws of learning; principles of teaching.— (B.A. or B.S. credit, 3 session-hours.) M. W. F., 12:30-1:30, P. H. 8. Professor Ferguson. Education B3: Educational Sociology.—First and Second terms: Principles of sociology. Third Term: Educational Sociology.—(B.A. or B.S. credit, 3 session-hours.) T. Th. S., 9:30-10:30, P. H. 2. Professor Smithey. Education B5: Educational Administration and Supervision.—First term: State and county school organization. Second term: City school systems. Third term: State and local school organization in Virginia. A study of State laws.—(B.A. or B.S. credit, 3 session-hours.) T. Th. S., 11:30-12:30, P. H., 4. Professor Manahan. Education B6: Planning and Equipment of School Buildings: Education B5 or B7 prerequisite.—Lectures on school design, supplemented by drawing room practice and field work. Assigned readings and reports. Third Term. (Credit, 1 session-hour.) Professor Hudnut. Hours to be arranged. (Omitted during 1924-25.) Education B7: Principles of Secondary Education.—(A course intended primarily for students who expect to teach or to occupy some administrative position in the high school or general educational work.) First term: Historical development of the secondary school; its social principles and its present tendencies. Second term: Aims and functions of the secondary school in organized society, and its relation to elementary and higher education. Its program of studies. Third term: Junior high schools: Their organization, standardization and supervision.—(B.A. or B.S. credit, 3 session-hours.) T. Th. S., 10:30-11:30, P. H. 2. Professor Smithey. Education B8: Hygiene and Education.—First term: Personal and community hygiene. Second term: Characteristics, defects, and hygiene of physical development. Third term: Hygiene of school buildings; equipment and management.—(B.A. or B.S. credit, 3 session-hours.) (Omitted in 1924-1925.) Education B9: Elementary School Administration and Supervision.— First term: Organization of the elementary school and its relation to the high school. Second term: Duties and qualifications of elementary school principals and teachers; the training of teachers in service. Third term: The curriculum of the elementary school and its reorganization.—(B.A. or B.S. credit, 3 session-hours.) T. Th. S., 10:30-11:30, P. H. 7. Professor Manahan. Education B10: Methods of Teaching High-School Subjects.—Unit courses of six weeks each in methods of teaching school subjects will be given by representatives of the various academic schools concerned. These courses will be required of third-year students who are candidates for degrees in Education. Each student must take the methods courses in at least two subjects, his major and minor, which he expects to teach in high school.—(Credit toward the B.S. in Education.) Hours to be arranged. In meeting the requirements of Education B10 the student may select any two of the following courses in the teaching of high school subjects: (a): The Teaching of Biology in Secondary Schools: Biology B1, prerequisite.—Field and laboratory study of local fauna and flora with the object of familiarizing the prospective teacher with the materials he will be called upon to use, by means of an ecological and systematic study of native animals and plants. Weekly field trips with laboratory study of the specimens collected. Course given from September 15 to November 1, and from April 1 to May 15. Written and graphic reports and assigned reading are required. Credit: 2 session-hours. Professors Kepner and Lewis. (b): A brief course on the Teaching of English in Secondary Schools will be offered if conditions permit. (c): The Teaching of French in Secondary Schools: French A and B, prerequisite.—Lectures, assigned reading, class reports. Hours to be arranged. Associate Professor Graham. (d): The Teaching of Latin in Secondary Schools: Latin A1, prerequisite.—Hours to be arranged. Professor FitzHugh. (e): The Teaching of Spanish in Secondary Schools: Spanish A and B, prerequisite.—Lectures, assigned reading, class reports. Hours to be arranged. Assistant Professor Knight. (f): The Teaching of Health Education: Education B13, B14 and B15, prerequisite.—Hours to be arranged. Assistant Professor Keister. (g): The Teaching of Physical Education: The best methods of teaching and supervising physical education in elementary and high schools and in colleges are brought to the attention of the student. Education B11: Directed Teaching: Education B10, prerequisite.— (For candidates for the degrees in Education and must be taken during the candidate's fourth year.) Students will be grouped in pairs and will teach one class each day in their major or minor subjects for 18 weeks, one student teaching the first half of the school year and the other student teaching the second half. The student not teaching will serve as an assistant and critic of his associate who will in turn become an assistant and critic when his period of teaching is completed.—(Credit, 2 session-hours toward degrees in Education.) Hours to be arranged. Education B12: School Hygiene and Sanitation: Course prescribed by the State Board of Education and State Board of Health for all students desiring certificates to teach in public schools. The following topics are considered: 1. General Public Health and Medical Inspection of Schools. 2. Physical Defects and their Control. 3. Personal Hygiene. 4. Communicable Diseases and their Control. 5. First Aid. 6. The Sanitary School. 7. Community Health. Credit will be apportioned on the basis of the time and work prescribed. Hours to be arranged.—Assistant Professor Keister. Education B13: Public Health and Health Education: Biology B1, Medical Bacteriology, Education B14, and Anatomy and Physiology, Education B15, prerequisite.—First Term: The control of communicable diseases and immunity. Second Term: The water supply and sewage disposal, refuse disposal, milk, foods and diet. Third Term: Child and maternity hygiene, mental hygiene, industrial hygiene, vital statistics, public health education, etc. Journal Club. One class period each month will be devoted to meetings of the Journal Club, at which time various public health topics, assigned by the instructor, will be discussed by the class. (Credit, 4 session-hours.) Assistant Professor Keister. Education B14: Medical Bacteriology for Teachers of Health Education: Biology B1, prerequisite. Bacteria in nature; life habits of bacteria. Elements of public health bacteriology. Cultural study of selected disease-producing bacteria. Modes of transmission and portals of entry. Changes produced during infection. Immunity. Modes of exit of bacteria from infected body. Carriers. Given only during first term. (Credit, 2 session-hours.) Professor Marshall. Education B15: Anatomy and Physiology.—(Lectures, demonstrations, recitations and reports.) A study of the anatomy and physiology of the human body, especially adapted for the student of physical education and health. First and Second Terms: A brief general study of the structure and function of the various parts of the body. There will be frequent demonstrations of anatomical dissections, models, microscopic preparations and physiological experiments. Third term: A more detailed consideration of the physiology of movement and exercise, including discussion of such topics as the following: the general physiological effects of muscular exercise; the effects of muscular overwork including fatigue, breathlessness, exhaustion, stiffness, chronic overwork, habituation to work or training; the special physiology of the various forms of exercise—gymnastics, games, dancing and athletics. (Credit, 3 session-hours.) Hours to be arranged. Associate Professor Speidel. Education B16: History and Principles of Health and Physical Education.—The history of health and physical education with particular reference to progress in Europe and America within recent times. The purpose of the course is to acquaint the student with the various programs of health education and systems of physical education, with leaders in these fields and with present-day conceptions of these subjects. It would also consider the place of health and physical education in the general scheme of present-day educational endeavor and the principles governing the organization and administration of health and physical education study in order to realize their aims, values and ideals. (Credit, 3 session-hours.) Education B17: Kinesiology.—Deals exclusively with the mechanical problems of bodily movement of bones, joints and muscles. The principal types of muscular exercise in gymnastics, athletics, etc. are studied as to their reaction on the body, their relation in bodily development, efficiency of movement, and the prevention and correction of certain physical defects and deformities. (Credit, 2 session-hours.) Education B18: Anthropometry, Corrective and Medical Gymnastics.— The influence of family and personal history upon the present condition of the individual; laws of growth; bodily measurements and examinations of special senses; practical work in measuring, testing, and recording, and coordination with the physical inspection program of school children in Virginia; examination of heart, lungs, and for hernia; prescription of exercise for common structural and postural defects of trunk and feet; functional defects and their treatment by exercise and message; the use of massage in health, athletics, and disease. (Credit, 2 session-hours.) For Undergraduates and Graduates. Education C1: Advanced Educational Psychology: Psychology B1 and one B course in Education, prerequisite.—An intensive study of fundamental processes and problems, involving a survey of important modern contributions to psychological literature, with emphasis upon a systematic formulation of results. M. W. F., 10:30-11:30, P. H. 8. To be given in alternate years with Education C6. Professor Ferguson. Education C2: Educational Surveys: State, City and County: Education B5 and one other B course in Education, prerequisite.—First term: Organization, aims, scope and methods of school surveys. Second term: A detailed study of selected school surveys. Third term: The limitations and possibilities of educational surveys in the fields of elementary and secondary education. M. W. F., 3-4:30, P. H., 4. To be given in alternate years with Education C3. Professor Manahan. Education C3: Standard Tests in School Subjects: Education B5 and one other B course in Education, prerequisite.—First term: Problems in the application of the principles of scientific management to education. Second term: Standard tests in school subjects; their derivation and standardization. Third term: Application of educational tests, and the interpretation of the results. M. W. F., 3-4:30, P. H., 4. To be given in alternate years with Education C2. Professor Manahan. Education C4: Problems in Secondary Education: Education B7 and one other B course in Education, prerequisite.—An advanced course in secondary education. Students will be required to make original investigations of special problems relating to secondary education. T. Th. S., 11:30-12:30, P. H., 2. Professor Smithey. Education C5: Social Education: Education B3 and one other B course in Education, prerequisite.—First Term: The family as a social and educational institution. Second Term: Population problems. Third Term: Social education program. Hours to be arranged. To be given in alternate years with Education C7. Professor Smithey. Education C6: Mental Tests and their Applications: Psychology B1 and one B course in Education, prerequisite.—A study of the more important mental tests and intelligence scales, with practice in their administration and interpretation. M. W. F., 10:30-11:30, P. H. 8. To be given in alternate years with Education C1. Professor Ferguson. Education C7: Sociology and Education: Education B3 and one other B course in Education, prerequisite.—First Term: Poverty and Dependency. Second Term: Crime—its cause and treatment. Third Term: Social theory. Hours to be arranged. To be given in alternate years with Education C5. Professor Smithey. For Graduates. Education D1: Seminar in Educational Psychology: Research studies. Hours by appointment. Professor Ferguson. Education D2: Seminar in School Administration: Research studies in state, city and county school organization and administration will be made and reported for class discussion by each student. Hours by appointment. Professor Manahan. Education D3: Seminar in Secondary Education: Research studies in secondary education. Each student will be given a special problem which will be reported to the class for discussion. Hours by appointment. Professor Smithey. COLLEGIATE PROFESSIONAL CERTIFICATE. Recipients of the Bachelor of Science in Education will receive the Collegiate Professional Certificate, the highest form of certificate for high-school teachers issued by the State Board of Education. This certificate is valid for ten years, renewable for a similar period, and entitles the holder to teach in both high and elementary schools in Virginia. Holders of Collegiate Certificates, the certificates of second rank issued by the State Board of Education, may obtain the Collegiate Professional Certificate by attending the University one session and taking four three-session-hour courses in Education. Curricula organized to meet the requirements for the degree of Bachelor of Science in Education fulfill both academic and professional requirements for the highest grade of professional high school certificates issued without examination by the various state departments of Education to holders of baccalaureate degrees. The graduate courses in Education are recognized in states requiring graduate study for professional certificates. SPECIAL CERTIFICATES IN HIGH SCHOOL SUBJECTS. Students who find it necessary to leave college to teach before completing their full course may be issued special certificates by the State Board of Education to teach any high-school subjects in which they have completed six session-hours of study of college grade. These students should plan to take two courses in Education during their second year in order to become familiar with school problems. COURSES FOR TEACHERS IN SERVICE. Saturday courses in any subject offered in the Department of Education will be arranged at the University for teachers in service, if requested by at least five teachers. Degree credit will be allowed on the same basis as in the regular courses, provided that not more than one and one-half session-hours' credit shall be given for the work in any course for one year. Superintendents and Teachers of Public Schools Exempt from Fees.— White male teachers and superintendents of the public schools of Virginia will be admitted, during the last three months of the session, to the Academic Schools of the University without payment of fees (except those charged in laboratory courses), upon presentation of certificates that they have been teachers in the public schools of the State during the year. Applicants for admission as teachers are required to send their names to the President of the University not later than March 5. UNIVERSITY EXTENSION TEACHING COURSES. Extension teaching courses are courses of instruction corresponding closely with those regularly given in the University by regular members of the faculty, and are under the administration, supervision and control of the University, for the benefit of persons unable to attend the regular courses of instruction and to take work in residence. Each course represents a definite amount of study corresponding to an equivalent amount of work done in residence at the University, and when completed satisfactorily by persons meeting the entrance requirements of the University, receives the same credit as if taken in residence. Extension teaching classes in Education, conducted by members of the faculty of the Department of Education, were organized in the session of 1923-24 under the Division of Extension of the University, in Alexandria, Lynchburg, Manassas, Richmond and Waynesboro-Basic. Additional Extension Teaching classes were conducted by members of the regular faculty of the University and instructors in the Extension Division of the University in Amherst, Richmond, Bristol, Charlottesville, Lynchburg, Roanoke, and Schoolfield. Extension Teaching Courses will be organized upon application for them in as many centers as possible, if a sufficient number (usually not fewer than fifteen) apply for them. Application for such courses should be made to the Director of University Extension, Box 149, University, Virginia. THE SUMMER QUARTER. The Summer Quarter is an integral part of the University year. Courses in the College of Arts and Sciences, as well as the Department of Education, are the same in character and in credit value as in any other Quarter of the University. Degrees are conferred upon men and women upon exactly the same terms for work done in the Summer Quarter when the degree requirements are fully met. Sixty-three session-hours of undergraduate courses, taken in conformity with the requirements published herewith, are required for the Bachelor's degree. Those who contemplate completing their degree requirements in the Summer Quarter should keep clearly in mind, in estimating the time that will be required, that the normal amount of credit which may be taken in one Summer Quarter is six session-hours. Candidates for a degree who desire credit for work done at other colleges must satisfy the entrance requirements for regular students and must, in addition, file with the Dean of the Summer Quarter a certificate covering the courses for which college credit is desired. This certificate must be acceptable both to the Dean of the Summer Quarter and to the Dean of the Department in which the degrees will be obtained. The certificate must bear the official signature of the head of the candidate's college and must specify the character and content of the courses passed by the candidate and must give his grade. In every case the candidate must spend at least three full Summer Quarters at the University in order to meet the residence requirements. The Master's degree may be obtained by properly qualified persons in three Summer Quarters. In no case is this degree to be conferred upon any person who has not attended and done graduate work three full Summer Quarters or the equivalent time in the regular session of the University and the Summer Quarter. On account of the increasing demand for graduate work in the Summer Quarter, the number of graduate courses will be enlarged in 1924. All persons who are looking forward ultimately to taking a degree through summer work are urgently requested to file with the Dean of the Summer Quarter an official statement of their entrance requirements and work for which college credit is desired. Blanks for this purpose will be mailed upon application. BUREAU OF TESTS AND MEASUREMENTS. Educational Tests.—The Department of Education maintains a Bureau of Tests and Measurements as a feature of its extra-University service. Select standard tests in school subjects will be supplied to cities, counties and individual schools at cost. Members of the Faculty of Education will visit the schools to be tested, train teachers in the use of the tests and personally direct the giving and scoring of them, provided the necessary traveling expenses are borne by the schools served. Mental Tests.—In connection with its work in educational psychology, the Department undertakes to assist school authorities in the diagnosis and training of backward and gifted children. Assistance will be rendered in the making of mental surveys and the establishment of special classes. A clinic will be maintained for the study of cases accessible to the University and the services of the professor in charge will be available to any community in Virginia at the cost of the necessary test materials and traveling expenses. Any school official desiring the services of the Bureau of Tests and Measurements should address the Dean of the Department of Education. BUREAU OF APPOINTMENTS. The University of Virginia maintains a Bureau of Appointments in charge of a committee consisting of Professors J. L. Manahan, W. R. Smithey, J. C. Metcalf and I. F. Lewis. The services of the bureau are free to all teachers and prospective teachers seeking positions in secondary schools (both public and private), normal schools, and colleges. Correspondence with regard to appointment should be addressed to the Bureau of Appointments (J. L. Manahan, Director), University, Virginia. PHI DELTA KAPPA FRATERNITY. A chapter of the national honorary educational fraternity of Phi Delta Kappa has been organized in connection with the Department of Education. Under the constitution of the fraternity, only those students are eligible to membership who expect to make teaching or administration of schools a permanent vocation, and who give evidence of superior qualities of character, scholarship and initiative. The standards of scholarship governing election to membership in the fraternity are similar to those prescribed for election to Phi Beta Kappa. The purpose of the fraternity as stated in its constitution is "to develop among the students of Education at the University of Virginia the spirit of `Research, Service and Leadership,' " and to endeavor by every worthy means at its command to create and foster fellowship and true fraternalism among the members of the society. EDUCATION CLUB. An Education Club is conducted for the purpose of fostering a scientific study of educational problems. Membership is open to all students taking courses in Education, teachers, principals and superintendents now in service, and members of the faculty of the University who are willing to lend their influence and efforts toward placing the teaching profession in Virginia and the South on a professional basis. SCHOLARSHIPS. In order to encourage the training of teachers, the General Assembly of Virginia, in 1918, founded one hundred and nineteen Virginia State Teachers' Scholarships, one for each School Division in the State. The emolument is free lodging, heat, light and janitor service in the university dormitories. The holder of one of these scholarships must be a Virginian needing financial assistance in order to attend the University, and he must pledge himself to engage in some form of school work in the State for at least two years, or, failing this, to repay to the University the value of the scholarship. Appointments are made prior to September 1, upon the recommendation of Division Superintendents of Schools. If any Superintendent fails to make a recommendation, the vacancy thus created may be filled from the State at large by the President of the University. Blank forms of application will be sent upon request. In addition to the Virginia State Teachers' Scholarships, there are a number of other scholarships in the University available for students of Education. A detailed description of them is given in the General Catalogue of the University. LOAN FUNDS AND STUDENT SELF-HELP. The University is in possession of funds from which loans are made to deserving students in need of such assistance. An account of these loans is given in the General Catalogue, page 106. Inquiries concerning them should be addressed to the Bursar. Opportunities for obtaining remunerative employment are afforded to students who are desirous by this means of partially paying their way through the University. It is difficult to give definite assurance of employment to a student before he reaches the University, but it may be stated that any student with sufficient resources to carry him through the first half of the session can be reasonably sure of obtaining work which will help defray his expenses for the rest of the academic year. Information as to employment may be obtained from the secretary of the Committee on Student Self-Help, Madison Hall, University, Virginia. EXPENSES. The necessary expenses of a Virginia student in the Department of Education may be estimated at from $320 a year upward, according to the mode of living; for students from other States, $510 upward. A fuller statement of expenses will be found in the General Catalogue of the University. SCHEDULE OF LECTURES, 1924-25. THE ACADEMIC DEPARTMENTS. (1) Some courses not listed below meet at hours not arranged until the beginning of the session. (2) In courses having more than one section, sections meeting on M-W-F are designated by odd numbers; those meeting on Tu-Th-S are designated by even numbers. Sections meeting irregularly are designated by letters. (3) Lecture courses are printed in Roman type, and their sections are designated by Arabic numerals. Laboratory courses are printed in Italic type, and their sections are designated by Roman numerals. (4) Courses continuing for more than one hour have printed in parenthesis the total number of hours, and they are listed in each block of the schedule corresponding to the hours in which they are in progress. (5) Courses not meeting on days corresponding to the usual M-W-F and Tu-Th-S division have printed after their names the exact days on which they meet. Monday, Wednesday, Friday Hours Tuesday, Thursday, Saturday Biology B1, Lab. Sec. I (8:30-10:30) 8:30 to 9:30 Biblical Lit. C1 English A1, Sec. 1 Chemistry B2 English A2, Sec. 1 Commercial Geography B1 English B3, Sec. 1, 3 Commercial Law B1 French A1, Sec. 1 (Tu-W-Th) Economics B4, Sec. 2 Geology B1, Sec. 1 English A1, Sec. 2 History B1 English A4 (2nd and 3rd terms only) * * Open only to students not having high school credit for Solid Geometry. Mathematics A1, Sec. 1, 3, 5 French A1, Sec. 1 (Tu-W-Th) Physical Exercise, Sec. I Geology B1, Lab. Sec. II (8:30-10:30) Spanish A1, Sec. a (Fri. only) Music A1 (Also Tu-Th 2:30-3:30) Zoology B1 Physical Exercise, Sec. II Public Speaking B1, Sec. 2 Spanish A1, Sec. d (Sat. only), C2 Biology B1, Lab. Sec. I (8:30-10:30) 9:30 to 10:30 Art B2, B3, C1 (9:30-12:30) Economics B1 (M-W) Biblical Lit. B2 Economics B1, Sec. a, b, c, d (Fri. only) Biology B1, Lab. Sec. II (9:30-11:30) Economics B5 Chemistry C4 English A1, Sec. 3 Economics B4, Sec. 4, C5 English C2 Education B3 French A1 (M-F) French A1, Sec. 2, 3, 4 (Tu-W-Th) French A1, Sec. 2, 3, 4 (Tu-W-Th) French C1 or C2 or C3 (Tues. only) French C4 (Mon. only) French C5 (Thurs. only), C8 (Sat. only) Geology B1, Lab. Sec. I (9:30-11:30) Geology B1, Lab. Sec. II (8:30-10:30) German A1, Sec. a (Also Tu-Th) German A1, Sec. a (Tu-Th; also M-W-F) Latin C1 Government B1 Philosophy C1 History B2 Physics B2 Latin C2 Spanish A1 (Tu-W) Music B1 Spanish A1, Sec. a (M-Th) Philosophy C2 Spanish A1, Sec. b, c (M-Th-F) Public Speaking B1, Sec. 4 Spanish C3 Spanish A1 (Tu-W) Zoology B1, Lab. (9:30-11:30) Spanish A1, Sec. a (M-Th) Spanish A1, Sec. b, c (M-Th-F) Spanish A1, Sec. e, f (Sat. only) Art B1 10:30 to 11:30 Applied Mathematics C1 Biology B1, Lab. Sec. III (10:30-12:30) Art B2 (9:30-12:30) Chemistry B1, Sec. 1 Art B3 (9:30-12:30) Chemistry C3, Lab. (10:30-12:30) Art. C1 (9:30-12:30) Economics B1, Sec. e, f (Fri. only) Biblical History B1 Economics B3 Biology B1, Lab. Sec. II (9:30-11:30) Economics B9 Botany C1 Education B1 (Phil. B6) Chemistry B1, Sec. 2 Education C1 or C6 (Psychology C1 or C2) Commercial Geography B2 English A1, Sec. 5 Economics B2 English A2, Sec. 3 Economics B6 English B1 Education B7 French C9 (Wed. only) English A1, Sec. 4, 6 Geology B1, Lab. Sec. I (9:30-11:30) English Lit. B1 German B1 French C6 (Thur. only) Greek B1 French C7 (Thur. only) History B3 Geology B1, Sec. 2 Latin A1 Latin A2 Mathematics B1 † † Open only to students having high school credit for Solid Geometry. Mathematics A1, Sec. 2, 4, 6 Philosophy B2 Mathematics C1 Philosophy B6 (Education B1) Music B2 Psychology C1 or C2 (Education C1 or C6) Philosophy B5 Spanish A1, Sec. d, e, f (M-Th) Physics C2 Zoology B1, Lab. (9:30-11:30) Spanish A1, Sec. d, e, f (M-Th) Art C2 11:30 to 12:30 Art B2 (9:30-12:30) Astronomy B1 Art B3 (9:30-12:30) Biology B1, Lab. Sec. III (10:30-12:30) Art C1 (9:30-12:30) Chemistry C2 Biology B1 Chemistry B1, Lab. Sec. I (11:30-1:30) Chemistry B3 Chemistry C3, Lab. (10:30-12:30) Chemistry B1, Lab. Sec. II (11:30-1:30) Economics B4, Sec. 1; B7, C1 Economics B8 English A1, Sec. 7 Economics C4 English A2, Sec. 5 Education B5 English Lit. B2 Education C4 French B1 (Wed. only) English A1, Sec. 8, 10 French B1, Sec. 1, 2, 3 (M-F) English B2 Geology B2 (M-Tu-W) French C10 (Thur. only) Geology, B1, Lab. Sec. III (11:30-1:30) French C11 (Sat. only) German B2 Geology B2 (M-Tu-W) Greek A1 (Also Tu-Th) Greek A1 (Tu-Th. Also M-W-F) History C1 History C2 or C3 Latin B1 Latin B2 Mathematics B2, Sec. 1 * * Open only to students not having high school credit for Solid Geometry. Mathematics 1, Sec. 8, 10 Music C1 Mathematics B2, Sec. 2 Philosophy C3 Music B3 Physics 1, Lab. (11:30-1:30) Philosophy B1, Sec. 2 Psychology B1 Philosophy B3 Spanish B1, Sec. 1 Spanish B1, Sec. 2, 4 Spanish B2 Astronomy B3 12:30 to 1:30 Applied Mathematics B1 Biology C1 Chemistry B1, Lab. Sec. II (11:30-1:30) Chemistry C3 Economics B11 Chemistry B1, Lab. Sec. I (11:30-1:30) Economics C7 Education B2 Education B9 English C1 Education C5 French B2 English A1, Sec. 12 Geology B1, Lab. Sec. III (11:30-1:30) English Lit. C1 German A1, Sec. b (Also Tu-Th) German A1, Sec. b (Tu-Th. Also M-W-F) Government C1 Government B2 Greek A2 Greek B2 † † Open only to students having high school credit for Solid Geometry. Mathematics A1, Sec. 7, 9, 11 Philosophy B4 Philosophy B1, Sec. 1 Physics 1 Physics 1, Lab. (11:30-1:30) Physics B1 Spanish C1 Physics C1 Architecture B1 (2:30-5:30) 2:30 to 3:30 Arch. Const. B1, B2, B3 (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Architecture B2 (2:30-5:30) Biology B1, Lab. Sec. IV (2:30-4:30) Architecture B3 (2:30-5:30) Botany C1, Lab. (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Biology B1, Lab. Sec. V (2:30-4:30) Chemistry B2, Lab. (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Chemistry B1, Lab. Sec. III (2:30-4:30) Chemistry B3, Lab. (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Chemistry B4, Lab. (2:30-5:30) Forestry B1 (M-Tu-W) Education C2 or C3 (3-4:30) Music A1 (Tu-Th. Also Tu-Th-S 8:30-9:30) Forestry B1 (M-Tu-W) Physical Training Sec. 2 (Tues. only) Geology B1, Lab. Sec. V (2:30-4:30) Physics B1, Lab. Sec. II (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Physical Training Sec. 1 (Mon. only) Physics B1, Lab. Sec. I (2:30-4:30) Physics C3, Lab. (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Zoology C1 Physics C4, Lab. (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Architecture B1 (2:30-5:30) 3:30 to 4:30 Arch. Construction B1 (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Architecture B2 (2:30-5:30) Arch. Construction B2 (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Architecture B3 (2:30-5:30) Arch. Construction B3 (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Biology B1, Lab. Sec. V (2:30-4:30) Biology B1, Lab. Sec. IV (2:30-4:30) Chemistry, BI, Lab. Sec. III, (2:30-4:30) Botany C1, Lab. (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Chemistry B4, Lab. (2:30-5:30) Chemistry B2, Lab. (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Education C2 or C3 (3-4:30) Chemistry B3, Lab. (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Geology, B1, Lab. Sec. V (2:30-4:30) Physical Training, Sec. 4 (Tues. only) Physical Training, Sec. 3 (Mon. only) Physics B1, Lab. Sec. II (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Physics B1, Lab. Sec. 1 (2:30-4:30) Zoology C1, Lab. (3:30-:530) Physics C3, Lab. (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Physics C4, Lab. (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Architecture B1 (2:30-5:30) 4:30 to 5:30 Arch. Const. B1, B2, B3 (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Architecture B2 (2:30-5:30) Botany C1, Lab. (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Architecture B3 (2:30-5:30) Chemistry B2, Lab. (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Chemistry B4, Lab. (2:30-5:30) Chemistry B3, Lab. (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Physical Exercise, Sec. III Physical Exercise, Sec. IV Zoology C1, Lab. (3:30-5:30) Physics B1, Lab. Sec. II (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Physics C3, C4, Lab. (Tu-Th) (2:30-5:30) Physical Exercise, Sec. V (5:30-6:30) Physical Exercise, Sec. VI (5:30-6:30) Choral Drill (Mon. only) (5-6) Band Drill (M-Th) (7:30-9) Glee Club (Fri. 5-6. Also Tues. 7:30-8:30) Glee Club (Tu. 7:30-8:30. Also Fri. 5-6) Band Drill (M-Th) (7:30-9) Orchestral Drill (Fri. only) (7:30-9) REGISTER OF STUDENTS. Undergraduates.* * This list includes only those students who are registered in the Department of Education, and does not include those taking courses in Education while registered in the Department of the College. Allman, Thomas Lee Glade Hill, Va. Atkins, Elizabeth Richmond, Va. Aylor, Melvin Winfrey Aylor, Va. Baines, Lillian Hope Newport News, Va. Bancroft, Robert Huntley Hot Springs, Ark. Bass, Charles Edward Evington, Va. Bolen, Mary George Culpeper, Va. B.S., Farmville State Normal School. Bolen, Virginia Franklin Culpeper, Va. Bowles, Walter Truman Sandidges, Va. Bradley, Carson M. Luray, Va. Brooks, Irene Onemo, Va. Burke, Lena Fullington Keyser, W. Va. Carter, Aubrey Richardson Fry Fork, Va. Carter, Willie Henry Free Union, Va. Chapman, Charlie Thomas Luray, Va. Cocke, Elton Cromwell Rockville, Va. Dabbs, Sophie Mayesville, S. C. B.A., Winthrop College. Davis, Maurice Cyril Rose Hill, Va. Deal, Willis Rutler Deep Creek, Va. Dowell, Margaret Swift Gordonsville, Va. Dunn, George Franks Halifax, Va. Faison, Zachariah Andrew, Jr. Sebrell, Va. Farmer, Paul Altavista, Va. Fifer, Kate Lee (s) Staunton, Va. Fitzhugh, Oscar Garth Lignum, Va. Griffin, Harry Rio, Va. Halterman, Geneva Florence Westgap, Va. Hastings, Mamie Salisbury, Md. Haydon, Richard Challice (s) Alexandria, Va. Heishman, Raymond E. Mt. Jackson, Va. Heyl, Helen Hay University, Va. Hill, Elizabeth Tucker Charlottesville, Va. Hirsh, Harry Strause, Jr. Baltimore, Md. Honaker, Ethel Wytheville, Va. Jones, Alice Walton Charlottesville, Va. Jones, Lucy T. Salem, Va. Jones, Robert Jefferson Lawrenceville, Va. Kilby, Walter LeRoy Hughes River, Va. Kyle, Ethel Lewis Woodlawn, Va. Lindsey, Marion McGuire Richmond, Va. Lonsdale, Gertrude E. University, Va. McMahan, Evalyn Chattanooga, Tenn. Meade, Janet Hamilton University, Va. Morrison, Hazel Constance University, Va. Motley, Pearl Cousins Danville, Va. Mundie, Joseph Ryland Newtown, Va. Nishimoto, Mitoji Osaka, Japan. Payne, Boyd Hawthorne Amherst, Va. Peery, Helen Burkes Garden, Va. Penn, Sydney Stella, Va. Philips, Lula Osgood Richmond, Va. Phipps, Beulah Clintwood, Va. Pinchbeck, Abner Carlton Chula, Va. Read, Joseph C. Catlett, Va. Revere, James Hall Wake, Va. Reynolds, Leon Wilson Danville, Va. Simmons, Milton University, Va. Smith, Henry Hancock Lee Bealeton, Va. Somerville, Lila Cabell Norwood, Va. Stewart, John Thomas, Jr. Portsmouth, Va. Strader, Clarence Haven Bane, Va. Swertfeger, Floyd Frank Carson, Va. Thornton, Florence G. Earlysville, Va. Totusek, William Joseph Highland Springs, Va. Turman, Christopher Madison, Jr. Arcola, Va. Vaughan, Carroll H. Altavista, Va. Walker, George Franklin, Jr. Syringa, Va. West, E. Alice Greenwood, Va. West, Julius Ewell Alexandria, Va. Wilkinson, Charles William Mt. Jackson, Va. Witcher, Elma C. Danville, Va. Summary by States. Arkansas 1 Maryland 2 South Carolina 1 Tennessee 1 Virginia 64 West Virginia 1 Foreign (Japan) 1 Total 71 Graduate Students Majoring in Education. Acker, Henry Grady Bridgewater, Va. B.S., The Citadel. Barnhart, Walter W. (s) Oxford, N. C. B.A., Randolph-Macon College. Bennett, Albert Luther Charlottesville, Va. B.A., Washington and Lee, M.A., University of Virginia. Bennett, Elisha Keen University, Va. B.A., Lynchburg College. Bingham, James Boyce (s) Chester, S. C. B.A., Erskine College. Bowling, Robert (s) Chase City, Va. B.A., University of Richmond. Eutsler, George W. (s) Ivy Depot, Va. B.A., University of North Carolina. Daniels, Freeman J. Beverly, W. Va. B.A., Davis-Elkins College. Gilbert, Luther C. Meridian, Miss. B.A., Mississippi College. Glick, Joseph Paul (s) Bridgewater, Va. B.A., Bridgewater College. Gittinger, Georgianna Simmons Frederick, Md. B.A., Hood College. Godbey, Stanley Taylor Radford, Va. B.A., Roanoke College. Goode, B. Clifford (s) Henry, Va. B.A., University of Richmond. Greene, John Howard (s) Clintwood, Va. B.A., Randolph-Macon College. Hatcher, Lucy Louise (s) Johnson City, Tenn. B.A., Milligan College. Haynes, W. Dwight (s) Dayton, Va. B.A., Carson and Newman College. Hayes, Wayland Jackson University, Va. B.S., M.S., University of Virginia. Hinson, Jesse James (s) Abbeville, Ala. University of Alabama. Horne, J. Roy (s) Cedar Springs, Va. B.S., College of William and Mary. Hulvey, Charles Newton University, Va. B.S., Sweetwater College. Lehman, Daniel Webster Harrisonburg, Va. B.A., Franklin and Marshall College. MacDonald, Kenneth A. (s) Hope Mills, N. C. B.S., Davidson College. Martin, Lecora Geneva Henrietta (s) Danville, Va. B.A., Randolph-Macon Woman's College. Mort, James Richard Bristol, Va. B.A., Emory and Henry College. Nash, Mary Hall Amherst, Va. M.A., George Peabody College. Patterson, Joseph Isham De Leon, Texas B.A., B.D., Southern Methodist University. M.A., Columbia University. Quisenberry, J. Rice (s) St. Just, Va. B.A., Furman University. Th. D., Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. Rorer, John Alexander (s) Forest Depot, Va. B.A., Randolph-Macon College. Rowell, Robert Milton (s) Winchester, Va. B.S., University of Tennessee. Scott, Thurman Carlisle Fincastle, Va. B.A., University of Virginia. Seese, Norman A. Bridgewater, Va. B.A., Bridgewater College. Shelburne, Kingman C. (s) Danville, Va. B.A., Howard College. Sherrill, Mildred Irene(s) Newton, N. C. B.A., University of North Carolina. Sloan, Isabel Raleigh, N. C. B.A., University of North Carolina. Stanley, Border Levi (s) Weyer's Cave, Va. B.A., Franklin and Marshall College. Thomas, Walter Henry (s) Indian Head, Md. B.S., University of Maryland. Thorpe, H. Wilson (s) Hampton, Va. B.A., College of William and Mary. Tignor, Henry G. (s) Ashland, Va. B.A., Washington and Lee University. Vanderslice, Samuel Pettit (s) Suffolk, Va. B.S., University of Virginia. Vaught, Ira B. (s) Goodwin's Ferry, Va. B.A., Roanoke College. Wilkie, Mary Cecilia Beaverdam, Va. B.S., University of Virginia. *The symbol (s) signifies registration in Summer Quarter. Summary by States. Alabama 1 Maryland 2 Mississippi 1 North Carolina 4 South Carolina 1 Virginia 29 Tennessee 1 Texas 1 West Virginia 1 Total 41</field>
   </doc>
</add>