<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university of virginia</field>
      <field name="author_text">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1930's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2005_Q3_2/uvaBook/tei/z000000396.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240342</field>
      <field name="date_text">February 1, 1935</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:132483</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The University of Virginia record. New Series Vol. XXI, No. 2, February 1, 1935</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">University of Virginia -- Periodicals</field>
      <field name="subject_text">University of Virginia -- Periodicals</field>
      <field name="title_display">The University of Virginia record.  New Series Vol. XXI, No. 2, February 1, 1935</field>
      <field name="title_facet">university of virginia record</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">university of virginia record</field>
      <field name="title_text">The University of Virginia record.  New Series Vol. XXI, No. 2, February 1, 1935</field>
      <field name="year_display">February 1, 1935</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1935-02-01</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1935</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:132483&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:132483&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;serial volume&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;university of virginia&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The University of Virginia record. New Series Vol. XXI, No. 2, February 1, 1935&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;university of virginia record&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;February 1, 1935&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1935-02-01&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The University of Virginia record&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="volume"&gt;New Series Vol. XXI&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="issue"&gt;No. 2&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;February 1, 1935&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Va.&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="LC call number"&gt;LD5667 .A43&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa call number"&gt;LD5667.2&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;X004321690&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;o07560180&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;70 p. ; 23 cm.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;University of Virginia -- Periodicals&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The University of Virginia Record&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="volume"&gt;New Series, 21&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="issue"&gt;2&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1935-02-01&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2005&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2005 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 267 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PUBLICATIONS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA The University of Virginia Record: No. 1, January 15: The College of Arts and Sciences: Announcements. No. 2, February 1: Department of Engineering: Announcements. No. 3, February 1: Department of Law: Announcements. No. 4, February 15: Department of Graduate Studies: Announcements. No. 5, March 15: Catalogue Number of the Summer Quarter. No. 6, March 1: Department of Medicine: Announcements. No. 7, March 1: Department of Education: Announcements. No. 7-a, March 1: School of Nursing Education: Announcements. No. 8, April 1: General Catalogue Number. The University of Virginia Record, Extension Series, published ten times a year. The Virginia Quarterly Review, published four times a year. A national journal of discussion. The Alumni News, published by the Alumni Association twelve times a year. The Virginia High School Quarterly, published in November, February, May and August by the Department of Education. Bulletin of the University of Virginia Library, published at intervals, during the session. The Virginia Law Review, published by the Virginia Law Review Association, monthly from October to May. University of Virginia News Letter, published semi-monthly from October 1 through June by the School of Rural Social Economics.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Thornton Hall—Now in the Process of Erection—Will be Occupied in the Fall of 1935</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA RECORD New Series Vol. XXI, No. 2 February 1, 1935 Department of Engineering ANNOUNCEMENTS 1935-1936 Entered as Second-Class Matter September 28, 1914, at the Post Office at Charlottesville, Virginia, under the Act of August 24, 1912.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">UNIVERSITY CALENDAR 1935 Thursday, January 3 Beginning of Second Term. Wednesday, March 13—Saturday, March 23 Second Term Academic Examinations. Monday, March 25 Beginning of Third Term. Saturday, April 13 Jefferson Day (Holiday). Wednesday, May 1 Doctors' Dissertations Due. Wednesday, May 15 Masters' Theses Due. Monday, May 27—Thursday, June 6 Final Academic Examinations. Monday, June 3—Saturday, June 8 Entrance Examinations. Sunday, June 9 Baccalaureate Sermon. Monday, June 10 Alumni Day. Meeting of the Rector and Visitors. Tuesday, June 11 Final Day. Monday, June 17 Opening of the Summer Quarter, First Term. Saturday, July 27 Closing of the Summer Quarter, First Term. Monday, July 29 Opening of the Summer Quarter, Second Term. Saturday, August 31 Closing of the Summer Quarter, Second Term. Monday, September 9—Saturday, September 14 Entrance Examinations. Thursday, September 12 Beginning of One Hundred Twelfth Session. Thursday, September 12—Saturday, September 14 Registration Days. Monday, September 16 Beginning of Lecture Courses. Tuesday, October 1 Applications for Collegiate Degrees Due. Wednesday, October 2 University Convocation. Thursday, November 28 Thanksgiving Day (Holiday). Tuesday, December 10—Friday, December 20 First Term Academic Examinations. Saturday, December 21—Thursday, January 2 Christmas Recess. 1936 Friday, January 3 Beginning of Second Term. Wednesday, March 11—Saturday, March 21 Second Term Academic Examinations. Monday, March 23 Beginning of Third Term. Monday, April 13 Jefferson Day (Holiday). Friday, May 1 Doctors' Dissertations Due. Friday, May 15 Masters' Theses Due. Monday, May 25—Thursday, June 4 Final Academic Examinations. Monday, June 1—Saturday June 6 Entrance Examinations. Sunday, June 7 Baccalaureate Sermon. Monday, June 8 Alumni Day. Meeting of the Rector and Visitors. Tuesday, June 9 Final Day.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DEPARTMENT OF ENGINEERING JOHN LLOYD NEWCOMB, B.A., C.E., Sc.D., LL.D. President of the University WALTER SHELDON RODMAN, M.S., S.M. Dean of the Department of Engineering * * On the Carnegie Foundation. WILLIAM MYNN THORNTON, B.A., LL.D. Emeritus Professor of Applied Mathematics * FRANCIS PERRY DUNNINGTON, C.E., E.M. Professor of Analytical and Industrial Chemistry (retired) ROBERT MONTGOMERY BIRD, B.A., B.S., Ph.D. Professor of Chemistry WILLIAM HARRISON FAULKNER, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Germanic Languages LLEWELLYN GRIFFITH HOXTON, B.S., B.A., M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Physics WALTER SHELDON RODMAN, M.S., S.M. Professor of Electrical Engineering TIPTON RAY SNAVELY, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Economics WILBUR ARMISTEAD NELSON, B.S., M.A. Corcoran Professor of Geology GARDNER LLOYD CARTER, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Chemistry ALBERT JULIUS BARLOW, B.A., C.P.A. Professor of Commerce and Business Administration W. PATTON GRAHAM, M.A. Professor of Romanic Languages JOSEPH KENT ROBERTS, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Geology JOHN HOWE YOE, M.S., M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Chemistry ARTHUR FERGUSON BENTON, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Chemistry EDWARDS WATTS SAUNDERS, Jr., C.E. Professor of Civil Engineering ARTHUR FRANCIS MACCONOCHIE, B.Sc. (Engrg.) London Professor of Mechanical Engineering EARNEST JACKSON OGLESBY, M.A. Professor of Engineering Mathematics CHARLES WAKEFIELD PAUL Associate Professor of Public Speaking FREDERICK LYONS BROWN, M.A., Ph.D. Associate Professor of Physics JAMES SHANNON MILLER, Jr., B.S., B.A., E.E. Associate Professor of Electrical Engineering CHARLES HENDERSON, E.E. Associate Professor of Experimental Engineering CHARLES NEWTON HULVEY, M.S., LL.B. Associate Professor of Commercial Law LAUREN BLAKELY HITCHCOCK, S.M., Sc.D. Associate Professor of Chemical Engineering GEORGE WASHINGTON SPICER, B.A., Ph.D. Associate Professor of Political Science DUNCAN CLARK HYDE, M.A., Ph.D. Associate Professor of Economics FREDERIC TURNBULL WOOD, B.A., Ph.D. Associate Professor of Germanic Philology ORESTE RINETTI, Ph.D. Associate Professor of Italian HERMAN CARL HESSE, B.S., M.E. Associate Professor of Engineering Drawing ARTHUR AUGUST PEGAU, M.A., Ph.D. Assistant Professor of Geology FRANZ KARL MOHR, M.A., Dr.Jur. Assistant Professor of Germanic Languages HUGH MILLER SPENCER, B.A., M.S., Ph.D. Assistant Professor of Chemistry THADDEUS BRAXTON WOODY, M.A. Assistant Professor of Spanish FREDERICK TRACY MORSE, M.E., E.E. Assistant Professor of Mechanical Engineering Service Fellows and Instructors James Charles Alexander, B.S. Chemistry Richmond Thomas McGregor Bell, B.S., Ph.D. (Instructor) Chemistry Joshua Robert Calloway Brown, Jr., B.S. Chemistry George Landon Browning, B.S. Chemistry James Webb Cole, Jr., B.S. Chem. Chemistry Thomas Bigelow Crumpler, M.S. Chemistry George Walter Francis Dandelake, B.S. (Instructor) Cost Accounting Hugh Nelson Dyer, Jr., M.S. Chemistry Richard Royston Fell, B.S., Ch.E. Chemistry Howard Montgomery Fitch, B.S. Chemistry Henry Louis Forbes, Jr., B.S., Ch.E. Chemistry Harry Brice Graves, B.S.Com., M.S. Economics Allan Talbott Gwathmey, B.S., S.B. Chemistry William Taylor Ham, B.S.E., M.S. Physics Edmund Frank MacDonald, B.S.Com. Economics Lawrence Reginald Quarles, B.S.E. Physics and Electrical Engineering William Monroe Spicer, B.S. Chemistry Albert Herbert Stuart, B.S. Chemistry Herbert Trotter, Jr., M.S. Physics Graeme Stockton Turnbull, B.S.Chem. Chemistry Joseph Lee Vaughan, M.A. (Instructor) English Matthew Volm, Ph.D. (Instructor) German Walker Champe Williams, B.S., LL.B. Commercial Law John Lewis Wood, B.S.Chem. Chemistry ASSISTANTS Gordon Keith Carter, B.S.E. Freshman Applied Mathematics, Sophomore Mathematics, Mechanics, Electrical Laboratory and Experimental Engineering Robert Gamble Copper Field Work, Mechanical Engineering and Mechanics Monroe Couper Chemistry Joseph Moreland Cowgill Field-work Henry Blount Daniel Freshman Mathematics William Lee Davis, Jr. Junior Applied Mathematics and Experimental Engineering Hugh Edward Donnally Railroad Field-work and Civil Engineering Howard Jackson Dutcher, Jr. English Howard Berryman Edwards English and Freshman Mathematics Earl Thayer Ellis, B.S.E. Senior Applied Mathematics David Milton French Chemistry Barth John Gilcrist Field-work Charles Archie Hahn, Jr. Junior Applied Mathematics and Experimental Engineering Martin Seymour Herz Field-work William Milligan Irvine, Jr. Freshman Applied Mathematics John William Lucas Mechanical Engineering Colin Tassie Montgomery Experimental Engineering Ruth Carolyn Newman, B.S. Cost Accounting William Walker Payne Field-work, Sophomore Mathematics and Senior Applied Mathematics Charles Pleasants Roberts, B.S. Chemistry John Penn Rutherfoord Freshman Mathematics George Chester Seward, B.A. Business Speaking William Wallace Starke, Jr. Field-work Benjamin Franklin Watkins Experimental Engineering GENERAL ENTRANCE REQUIREMENTS For admission to any department of the University, the general conditions are the following: 1. Sufficient Age.—The minimum legal age is sixteen years. 2. Good Character.—This must be attested by a certificate of honorable dismissal from the school last attended, or by other valid proof. 3. Adequate Preparation.—This must be such as will enable the candidate to meet the requirements for admission to the several departments of the University, as detailed below. ADMISSION BY CERTIFICATE For admission by certificate from a secondary school the applicant should file with the Dean, a certificate of preparation, made out on a blank form furnished by the University. This certificate must come from an accredited public high school or from an accredited private secondary school. For admission from an institution of collegiate rank, an official transcript of the applicant's record, made out on the form used by the institution in question, must be submitted. In addition, each applicant, whether from a secondary school or a college, must submit a formal application for admission, on a blank form supplied by the University. The candidate for admission from a public high school must be a full graduate of an accredited four-year high school. The candidate for admission from a private secondary school must be a full graduate of the school, or must present a certificate showing that he has completed at least the equivalent of four years of satisfactory secondary school work of standard grade, covering at least 15 entrance units. Certificate credit for any unit is invalidated by failure in a college entrance examination on the unit in question in the year admission is desired, unless the applicant ranked in the highest quarter of his class. An applicant for admission who ranked in the lowest quarter of his class, or who failed on more than two subjects in secondary school, will not be admitted unless he presents positive evidence that he is likely to succeed in college in spite of his secondary school record. An applicant for admission from outside of Virginia may be required to supplement his application by an interview with a representative of the University. In every case the applicant must have a general character recommendation from the principal of his school, and personality and promise, as well as scholarly attainment, will be considered in determining admission. The University accredits all four-year public high schools and all private secondary schools which are fully accredited by the State Board of Education of Virginia. Schools outside of Virginia which are fully accredited by their own state universities or institutions of equal rank, by their own state departments of education or by recognized regional associations of secondary schools, are also accredited by the University. Certificates of preparation from private tutors will in no case be accepted; students thus prepared must in all cases pass the entrance examinations. ADMISSION BY EXAMINATION For admission by examination, the candidate must present himself at the University in June or in September, according to the dates given in the Program of Entrance Examinations. The examinations are held under the Honor System, no paper being accepted unless accompanied by the usual pledge, and they are held only on the dates given in the Program of Entrance Examinations. A fee of one dollar is charged for each examination taken. This fee is payable in advance and is in no case returned. The entrance examinations of the University are similar, in many respects, to those of the College Entrance Examination Board. The University does not furnish sample copies of its entrance examinations. Official records of the examinations of the College Entrance Examination Board or of the University of the State of New York may be submitted in lieu of taking entrance examinations here. PROGRAM OF ENTRANCE EXAMINATIONS June, 1935 9-11 A. M. 11 A. M.-1 P. M. 2:30-5 P. M. Sept., 1935 Mon. 3 Science D Greek C Science F Mon. 9 Science E Science A Science C French Cp. 2 History D Tues. 4 English Cp 2 Greek Cp. 2 English C-D Tues. 10 French C Wed. 5 History A History B History C Wed. 11 Spanish Cp. 2 Science B Thurs. 6 Math. A1 Math. A2 Math. B. Thurs. 12 Math. Cp. 2 Math. C Fri. 7 German Cp. 2 Spanish D German C Fri. 13 Spanish C French D Math. D Sat. 8 Latin Cp. 2 Latin C Latin D Sat. 14 German D SUBJECTS ACCEPTED FOR ADMISSION The subjects usually accepted for admission and their values in units are given below in tabulated form. Other subjects are also acceptable. SUBJECT TOPICS UNITS English A Grammar and Grammatical Analysis 1 English B Composition and Rhetoric 1 English C Critical Study of Specimens of English Literature 1 English D English or American Literature 1 Mathematics A1 Algebra to Quadratic Equations 1 Mathematics A2 Quadratics, Progressions, and the Binomial Formula ½ or 1 Mathematics B Plane Geometry 1 Mathematics C Solid Geometry ½ Mathematics D Plane Trigonometry ½ History A Greek and Roman History 1 History B Medieval and Modern European History 1 History C English History 1 History D American History and Civil Government 1 Latin A Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 Latin B Cæsar's Gallic War, I-IV; Grammar; Composition 1 Latin C Cicero's Orations (6); Grammar; Composition 1 Latin D Virgil's Æneid, I-VI; Grammar; Composition 1 Greek A Elementary Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 Greek B Xenophon's Anabasis, I-VI; Grammar; Composition 1 Greek C Homer's Iliad, I-III; Grammar; Composition 1 German A Elementary Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 German B Intermediate Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 German C Third-year Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 German D Fourth-year Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 French A Elementary Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 French B Intermediate Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 French C Third-year Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 French D Fourth-year Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 Spanish A Elementary Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 Spanish B Intermediate Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 Spanish C Third-year Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 Spanish D Fourth-year Grammar, Composition, and Translation 1 Science A Physical Geography 1 Science B Inorganic Chemistry 1 Science C Experimental Physics 1 Science D Botany ½ or 1 Science E Zoölogy ½ or 1 Science F Biology 1 VOCATIONAL SUBJECTS (Not more than 4 Units) Manual Training Mechanical and Projection Drawing ½ to 1 Free-Hand Drawing ½ to 1 Shop-work ½ to 1 Agriculture (Accredited Agricultural Schools) 1 to 4 Commercial Subjects Commercial Geography ½ to 1 Shorthand ½ to 1 Typewriting ½ Bookkeeping ½ to 1 Commercial Arithmetic ½ to 1 ENGINEERING ENTRANCE REQUIREMENTS For admission to the Freshman Class in the Department of Engineering the candidate must be at least sixteen years old. He must present a certificate of honorable withdrawal from the school last attended, or other valid proof of general good character. He must further satisfy the Dean of the Department of Engineering as to his adequate preparation for the work by passing the Entrance Examinations specified below or by the presentation of equivalent certificates of preparation signed by an official of a recognized institution of collegiate rank, or by the principal of an accredited public high school or of an accredited private secondary school. An applicant for admission from outside of Virginia may be required to supplement his application by an interview with a representative of the University. The topics required for entrance and their values in units are as follows, the unit being one year's work on the subject in an accredited high school: English A—Grammar and Grammatical Analysis 1 English B.—Composition and Rhetoric 1 English C.—Critical study of Specimens of Literature 1 Mathematics A1.—Algebra to Quadratics 1 Mathematics A2.—Quadratics, Progressions, Binomial Formula 1 Mathematics B.—Plane Geometry 1 Mathematics C.—Solid Geometry ½ Mathematics D.—Plane Trigonometry ½ History.—Ancient; Medieval; English; American (any one) 1 Electives 7 Total 15 High school students who expect to study Engineering are advised to include among their electives at least one Foreign Language (Latin or French or German), one Science (Chemistry or Physics with adequate laboratory work) and an additional unit of History. Other electives which may be profitably offered are History of English and American Literature, Greek, Botany, Zoölogy, Physical Geography. Conditioned Students.—A candidate may be admitted as a Conditioned Student in spite of some deficiencies in required entrance subjects, provided these are not such as will impair the integrity of his work, but he must submit not less than 15 units. No such candidate will be conditioned except upon subjects actually taught in this University, nor will any candidate be conditioned on more than 2 units; and all conditions must be absolved before the beginning of the next session after initial registration. Courses taken for the removal of entrance conditions may in no case be counted as part of the work credited for any degree. No conditions will be allowed in English A or B or in Mathematics A1, A2, or B. As the table of Entrance Requirements shows, the full High School course in Mathematics is required for entrance to the Department of Engineering, but unfortunately the graduates of the High Schools are often deficient in Solid Geometry and Plane Trigonometry and can be admitted only upon conditions in those subjects. High School principals are advised to urge their graduates, with this status, to attend a Summer Session at the University before entering the Department of Engineering so that these deficiencies may be overcome. If the prospective student finds it impossible to attend a Summer School previous to his regular matriculation, a course has been planned which will allow him to make up his deficiencies by taking work in the Summer School following his first year in Engineering. This course provides for Trigonometry, Solid Geometry and College Algebra in the three terms of the regular session, with the other work as outlined for the regular student, and in addition, in the two terms of the Summer School, Analytical and Coördinate Geometry are taken. Such a program will prepare the student for Sophomore standing and will save him from the failure usually encountered by students who attempt to make up the deficient work in regular session in addition to the full course of required subjects. Special Students.—A candidate may be admitted as a Special Student, without formal examination, provided he is more than twenty years old if a Virginian and not less than twenty-three years old if a non-Virginian, and gives evidence of serious purpose and of fitness to pursue with profit the course for which he is registered. No special student may be a candidate for any degree. No conditioned student may register later as a special student. ADMISSION OF WOMEN Women are admitted as candidates for the Engineering Degrees but not as Special Students. A candidate must be at least twenty years old on the birthday preceding matriculation; must present certificates showing graduation from an accredited public high-school, or not less than four years' attendance in an accredited private school, with credit for not less than 15 college entrance units obtained at least two years before admission to the University; and must in addition show by proper certificate the completion in a standard college, subsequent to the credit obtained for 15 entrance-units, of at least 30 session-hours (60 semester-hours), of courses of college grade, in not less than eighteen calendar months. ADVANCED STANDING Under the elective system of the University of Virginia, a student who has completed courses of college or university grade in other institutions of learning on mathematical or scientific subjects may be excused from attendance upon these courses by the Dean, with the advice and consent of the professor in charge, and will then be registered for the more advanced work, provided the full entrance requirements have been satisfied. In order to secure College Credit upon such courses toward a degree in Engineering from the University, the applicant must show— 1. That the courses offered are coextensive with the corresponding courses as given in the University of Virginia. 2. That his grades on them were not below the 75 per cent pass-mark of this University. Such credits may be granted by the faculty upon the recommendation of the Dean and the professors in charge; but are automatically revoked by the failure of the student to pass in the more advanced courses in the related topics. Advanced standing in the technical engineering subjects of higher grade than those of the Sophomore year will not be given except to graduates of other institutions offering technical engineering instruction and then only upon special consideration of each application for such advanced standing. No degree in Engineering will be awarded for less than one full year's work in a regular session of this University and the work of a candidate's last year must be performed in residence here. The same rules apply to Credit on Summer School Courses; except that for courses in the Summer School of this University the examination questions must be prepared by the professor in charge of the regular course, and the answers must be read and graded by him. Students, suspended from other universities, are not granted college credits on courses previously passed, except upon explicit recommendation of the suspending university, and after such additional tests as this Engineering Faculty may impose. Credits on Practice-Courses, in Drawing, or Field-work may be granted to applicants who have gained in professional practice the training which these courses represent. Such applicants must file with the Dean proper certificates from the official under whom the work was done and must in every case pass an additional practical test on the subjects for which credit is desired. College credit is not granted for high-school work. PROGRAMS OF STUDY The candidate who has satisfied the requirements for entrance as above defined is matriculated as a student of Engineering and admitted to the Freshman Class. The studies of this class comprise lecture courses in English, Mathematics, Applied Mathematics, and Chemistry with associated laboratory courses in Chemistry, Drawing, and Field-work. All Freshmen have the same courses. For advancement to the Sophomore Class the student must have completed at least two-thirds of his Freshman work. Upon entering this class the students majoring in Chemical and Mechanical Engineering begin their specialized work, while all others pursue identical courses of study through the year. On entering the Junior year each student elects his specialty. At this time the students of Mechanical Engineering must choose either the power or the aeronautical option. The courses thereafter diverge according to the major subject chosen by the student. Programs of study for each degree are given below. The courses are so ordered that the specified entrance requirements are adequate for the work of the Freshman Year. Each succeeding year presupposes the completion of the work for all the foregoing years. Students are advised to adhere strictly to the regular programs. The arrangements specified in them have been carefully planned and are the best. Departures from the curriculum will in almost every case produce conflicts in lecture hours or laboratory periods and may cost the student a year's time. Haphazard election is discouraged and in extreme cases will be prohibited. No student will be registered for a course unless, in the opinion both of the Dean and of the professor, his preliminary training has fitted him for the profitable pursuit of that course. Students are especially advised against the attempt to crowd too many studies into their scheme of work, and are warned that admission to advanced courses will be granted only to those who have adequate mathematical and scientific training to profit by them. Men overloaded with work, too great in volume or in difficulty for their powers, suffer inevitable discouragement and incur almost certain failure. Changes of classes with transfer of fees may be made, subject to the approval of the Dean, within two weeks after the beginning of any term. Thereafter such changes may be made only by special order of the faculty, and then without transfer of fees. Upon the completion of the four years' course as defined in any one of the Programs of Study, the faculty will award to any student in regular and honorable standing the degree of Bachelor of Science in Engineering. Upon the completion of the additional Graduate Course in a satisfactory manner the faculty will award the appropriate degree of Chemical Engineer, Civil Engineer, Electrical Engineer, or Mechanical Engineer. The five-year curriculum has been adopted at the University of Virginia in view of the impressive and growing demand from practicing engineers and industrial leaders that Schools of Engineering should enlarge the field of study to embrace more of the humanities and better opportunities for student research, to the end that the graduates may be better fitted to undertake their duties as engineers and citizens. GENERAL REGULATIONS REGISTRATION Registration.—Applicants seeking admission to the University must present themselves to the Deans of their respective Departments at some time during the first three days of the session. Delayed Registration.—Any student who fails to present himself for registration during the first three days of the session will not be admitted unless he can explain his delay in a manner satisfactory to the Dean and will be charged a delayed registration fee. Registration after the Christmas Recess.—On the first week-day after the Christmas Recess, every student is required to register by attending all the classes or laboratory exercises at which he is due that day. No further formality is necessary. Any student failing to register thus will be required to pay the delayed registration fee, and will be liable to penalties imposed for unexcused absences. But if the delay is due to illness or other providential cause the Dean is authorized to remit the fee. RESIDENCE AND ATTENDANCE The Academic Year begins on the Thursday preceding the nineteenth of September and continues for thirty-nine weeks. Thanksgiving Day and Jefferson Day are holidays, and there is a Christmas recess beginning on the last week-day before the twenty-third of December and closing on the evening of the second of January. Attendance is required of each student throughout the entire session, with the exception of holidays, unless he receives permission to be temporarily absent, or to withdraw before the close of the session. While in residence each student is required to attend regularly all lectures and other prescribed exercises in the courses which he pursues, or else suffer such penalties as may be imposed for unexcused absences. Voluntary Withdrawal from the University requires the written consent of the Dean of the Department in which the student is registered. For the conditions governing the return of fees upon withdrawal, see page 15. Enforced Withdrawal is inflicted by the several department faculties for habitual delinquency in class, habitual idleness or any other fault which prevents the student from fulfilling the purposes for which he should have come to the University. See also the regulations as to delinquent students in the various departments. Absence from Examinations.—Written examinations are an essential part of the work of every course in the University, and attendance upon them is required of every student. Absence may be excused only on the ground of sickness on the day of examination (attested by a physician's certificate), or for other imperative cause which may be approved by the several faculties of the University. Special Examinations are granted only upon prompt application therefor, and in case the applicant's absence from the regular examination has been excused. See the preceding paragraph. Honor System.—All examinations are held under the Honor System, and an unpledged paper is counted a total failure. In matters of class standing as well, students are expected to regard themselves as governed by the law of honor. Prohibition of Credit.—An act of the Legislature prohibits merchants and others, under severe penalties, from crediting minor students. The license to contract debts, which the President is authorized to grant, is limited (except when the parent or guardian requests otherwise in writing) to cases of urgent necessity. CONDUCT Conduct.—The laws of the University require from every student decorous, sober, and upright conduct as long as he remains a member of the University, whether he be within the precincts or anywhere else. Drunkenness, gambling, and dissoluteness are strictly forbidden, and the President may dismiss from the University for the residue of the current session every student found guilty of them, or may administer such other discipline as seems best under the circumstances. The President will dismiss from the University every student convicted of public drunkenness, or of other conduct reflecting serious discredit upon the University. In all cases of discipline, the law requires that the student must first be informed of the objection to his conduct and afforded an opportunity of explanation and defense. The publication or sale of anonymous publications is forbidden. Motor driven vehicles either owned or operated by students are prohibited from parking in the roadways or elsewhere on the University grounds between the hours of 9:00 a. m. and 3:30 p. m. At no time may they park in the alleys, near fire hydrants, or on curves. However, students suffering from serious physical disability may be granted permits to park. MEDICAL ATTENDANCE Medical Attendance.—Any student who is temporarily ill from causes not due to his own misconduct, is entitled, without charge, to all necessary medical advice from the University Physician; and, if necessary, to nursing in the University Hospital at a reasonable charge for his maintenance while there. This exemption from charge does not apply to cases requiring surgical operation, treatment of the eye, ear, nose and throat, or to constitutional disorders from which the student in question was suffering at the time of his coming to the University. Nor is the University responsible for the expense incurred through the employment of private nurses, necessitated by severe illness of students, or through the maintenance of quarentine precautions in contagious cases. Students who take the responsibility of boarding at houses not approved by the Board of Health forfeit the right of medical attendance. Any student sent to the University Hospital by the advice and under the care of a physician other than the University Physician will be required to pay the regular hospital charges for private patients. EXPENSES OF REGULAR STUDENTS The average annual expense of a student who pursues the regular course in Engineering will be: NonVirginians Freshmen Virginians Other Virginians University Fee $ 60.00 $ 50.00 $ 50.00 Tuition Fee 200.00 65.00 130.00 Athletic Fee 15.00 15.00 15.00 Topics Fee 1.50 1.50 1.50 Laboratory Fees (average) 35.00 45.00 35.00 Living Expenses (for 9 months) 375.00 375.00 375.00 Books and Drawing Materials 30.00 30.00 30.00 Incidental Expenses (for 9 months) 60.00 60.00 60.00 Total annual for average conditions $776.50 $641.50 $696.50 The charges for Tuition are uniform to all students, except that Virginians are relieved of tuition on courses offered in the College, this exception saving regular Freshmen from Virginia $135 and all other Virginia students $70 each year in comparison with non-Virginians. The laboratory charges are $15 per class for the year's course in Physics, and $20 per class for a year's course in Chemistry. A deposit for breakage of $5 is required for each laboratory course in Chemistry. A fee of $5 for the year's course in Engineering Geology is charged. The fee for each practice course in the Engineering Department, Drawing, and Engineering Laboratories is $5 per term for each course. The fees for Field-work and Bridge Drafting are each $10 per term per course. These fees include all charges for laboratory materials; but the student is held further responsible for breakage. The Living Expenses include board, lodging, fuel and lights, servant and laundry; the average is $10.00 per week, the minimum $7.50, and a reasonable maximum $12.50. Books and Drawing Materials will cost about $120 for the four-year course. Incidental Expenses ought to be kept within modest bounds; the above estimate is sufficient; large allowances of pocket money promote idleness and attract companions of the baser sort. No allowances are included for clothing and travel, the expenses for which vary too much to be introduced into any general estimate. The charges payable on entrance are the University Fee, the Athletic Fee, the Topics Fee, and the Tuition and Laboratory Fees. Payment of Fees.—When the aggregate charge for University fee, tuition fee, laboratory fees, and room rent does not exceed $50 for the session, the total amount shall be paid upon registration. If said fees aggregate more than $50, but do not exceed $100, one-half thereof shall be paid upon registration and the remainder at the beginning of the second term. When the fees aggregate more than $100, payment shall be made one-third upon registration; one-third at the opening of the second term and the remainder at the opening of the third term. If any payment remain unpaid for fifteen days after the date on which it is due, the Bursar shall immediately notify the Dean of the Department in which such student is entered of the delinquency, and such student shall by him be required at once to cease attending lectures, using laboratories, library, gymnasium, athletic grounds or buildings, boarding at the dining hall, and making use of any other privileges as a student until his financial relations with the University have been arranged satisfactorily with the Bursar. Return of Fees.—A student withdrawing within five days after registering shall have his fees refunded in full, except the sum of $5 to cover cost of registration, and his name shall be stricken from the rolls. If he withdraw or is dropped from the rolls for any cause after the fifth day of the term and before the middle thereof, his fees shall be returned pro rata. If he withdraw or be dropped from the rolls for any cause after the middle of any term no refund shall be made for that term, except in case of sickness when the refund shall be pro-rated upon certificate of the University Physician or other reputable medical practitioner. In any case a minimum charge of $5 shall be made to cover cost of registration. Laboratory fees shall be refunded upon statement of professor in charge except where the withdrawal is within five days after registering. Regulation Concerning Registration as Virginia Student.—In order to be considered a Virginia student, it is necessary that the applicant's parents be domiciled in the State if he be under twenty-one years of age; or if he has attained his majority, that he himself be domiciled in said State; and that either his parents or the applicant for admission shall have been bona fide taxpayers in the State of Virginia for at least two years prior to said application. Sons of Regular Officers of the United States Army, Navy, Marine Corps, Coast Guard, or Public Health Service, whether on the active or retired list, irrespective of the location of their posts of duty, are accorded the privilege of registering under the rules applicable to the registration of Virginia students. SCHOLARSHIPS The Accredited School Scholarships from accredited public or private secondary schools may be assigned to the Department of Engineering. Tenure, one year. Emolument, for Virginians, the remission of $60 in fees; for nonVirginians, the remission of $150 in fees. The holder must be a graduate of his school, he must rank in the highest quarter of his class, and he must enter the University the session immediately following his graduation. The Alumni Scholarships may be assigned to the Department of Engineering. Tenure, one year, but an incumbent may be eligible for reappointment upon recommendation of the Dean. Emolument, for Virginians, the remission of $60 in fees; for non-Virginians, the remission of $150 in fees. The holder must need financial aid in order to attend the University, and must file a written statement to this effect, together with a similar statement from his parent or guardian. He must have ranked in the highest quarter of the graduating class of his school, and must enter the University the session immediately following his graduation. The Philip Francis duPont Scholarships: Founded in 1928 upon the generous bequest of Philip Francis duPont, '00: In the Department of Engineering a number of these scholarships are awarded annually to both new and old students of the department. The emolument will vary from $100 to $150, depending upon the income available, with apportionment at the discretion of the Faculty of Engineering. The tenure of each scholarship is one year, but any incumbent may be reappointed upon recommendation of the Dean. Applicants for these scholarships who have not previously attended the University must have complied with the entrance requirements before their applications can be considered; they must give evidence of financial need; and they must have ranked in the highest quarter of their class. Preference is given to applicants who ranked in the highest tenth of their class. Applications must be made on a blank form supplied by the Dean. Students who have not attended the University must submit their application not later than July 1; students attending the University must apply not later than May 1. The Isabella Merrick Sampson Scholarship in the Department of Engineering, with an income of $100: Founded in 1910 upon the gift of Mr. W. Gordon Merrick, of Glendower, Albemarle County, Virginia. Appointments are made upon the recommendation of the trustees of the Isabella Merrick Sampson Endowment. Preference is given to an applicant from Albemarle County. A limited number of additional scholarships may be granted in the Department of Engineering from those general scholarships open to any department of the University. A complete statement regarding all scholarships will be found in the General Catalogue. LOAN FUND AND STUDENT SELF-HELP The University is in possession of funds from which loans are made to deserving students in need of such assistance. An account of these loans is given in the General Catalogue. Inquiries concerning them should be addressed to the Bursar. Opportunities for obtaining remunerative employment are afforded to students who are desirous by this means of partially paying their way through the University. It is difficult to give definite assurance of employment to a student before he reaches the University, but it may be stated that any student with sufficient resources to carry him through the first half of the session can be reasonably sure of obtaining work which will help defray his expenses for the rest of the academic year. Information as to employment may be obtained from the Director, Bureau of Student Self-Help, Box 1487, University, Virginia. BOARD AND LODGING Dormitories.—Students may reside in the University dormitories, in their homes, or in private houses approved by the President. The President will withdraw from the approved list any house in which the regulations as to the conduct of students are not observed. Any change of residence during the session should be reported at the office of the Registrar. For rules governing the rental and occupancy of University dormitories, and the rates charged for the same, see below. For list of private lodging houses, with rates, apply to Bursar. The University Dormitories The dormitories of the University of Virginia consist of The Halls, East Lawn and West Lawn, East Range and West Range, Dawson's Row, and Randall Building. Hot water heat and electric light are furnished throughout the dormitories. Each occupant of a dormitory room must provide a pillow, pillow cases, single sheets, blankets, towels, etc., and whatever rugs, curtains, etc., he may desire. Description and Rates The Halls.—The most comfortable, best-equipped, and most modern rooming accommodations in the University or in the city are to be found in the new University dormitories, erected in 1929. This group of eight buildings stands on the crest of the slope west of Monroe Hill, with an outlook on the Ragged Mountains and the range of the Blue Ridge, and is within less than three minutes walking distance from the gymnasium, the academic, engineering and law class-rooms, and the University Commons. These eight buildings are divided into twelve separate units, known as Halls, each with its individual entrance, and each bearing the name of some professor, distinguished in the history of the University. The buildings are of three stories and of full fire-proof brick and cement construction throughout. They provide one hundred and fifty-three two-room apartments, of living-room and bedroom, each apartment intended to accommodate two students. All of the rooms are approximately fifteen feet square. Each living-room has an open fire-place and is furnished with a desk with drawers, a table with drawer, a steel waste-basket, two rocking-chairs, two straight chairs and floor-plugs for reading lamps. Each bedroom has two large built-in clothes closets, and is furnished with two single beds, two chiffoniers, and two straight chairs. All furniture is new, of excellent quality and attractive design, the bed-springs and mattresses of especially high grade. There is an average of one bathroom to every five students. The bathrooms, each equipped with showers and an individual built-in steel locker and a medicine chest with mirror for each student using it, are so placed that every bed-room, with one sole exception, opens directly into a bath. Telephone service is provided in each Hall. Trunks and packing cases will not be permitted in the apartments of The Halls dormitories. They must be delivered to the trunk room in each Hall from which the student will remove the contents to his room. Trunks and packing cases will be stored in dry racks located in the basement. Each apartment will ordinarily be occupied by two students. The rental for the nine months of the regular session is $150 per student (or $300 for each apartment). East Lawn and West Lawn are of one-story brick construction. They contain thirty-eight rooms, each approximately twelve feet square, located between the pavilions and opening into colonnades running the entire length of "The Lawn." The rental of twenty-seven of the rooms, for the session, is $125 for one occupant or $170 for two occupants. The remaining nine rooms, called Bachelors' Row, rent for $115 to one occupant, or $160 for two occupants. These rooms are reserved for applicants for senior degrees. East Range and West Range consist of forty-six one-story brick rooms, approximately twelve feet square, built in sections running the entire length of "The Ranges," and opening into arcades. In addition, there are two two-story brick houses called the Old Gymnasium and the Club House, containing fourteen rooms, approximately fifteen feet square. The rental of the rooms on the Ranges, for the session, is $125 for one occupant or $170 for two. The rooms in the Old Gymnasium and the Club House rent for $80 for one occupant or $110 for two. Dawson's Row consists of a series of four eight-room two-story brick houses and a six-room one-story brick house, located on the southwest side of the grounds. The rooms are approximately fifteen feet square. The rental of fifty-one of the rooms, for the session, is $95 for one occupant or $130 for two. Four of the rooms rent for $60 for one occupant or $80 for two. All of the rooms on the Lawns and Ranges and in Dawson's Row are provided with running cold water. For each of the Lawns and Ranges one bath-house is provided and there is a bath-house in Dawson's Row Randall Building.—A two-story brick building, located at the south end of East Range, containing thirty-one single rooms ten by fourteen, ten by fifteen and ten by sixteen; eight double rooms fourteen by fifteen, fifteen by fifteen and fifteen by seventeen; one double room with study-room attached. Single rooms rent at $80 to $90; double rooms $125 for one occupant or $150 for two occupants. Double room with study-room attached, for one occupant $135, or $180 for two occupants. The furnishings of the rooms on the Lawns and Ranges, in Dawson's Row and Randall Building is as follows: For one occupant—an enamelled iron bed with comfortable springs and mattress, a chiffonier, a table, a straight chair and a rocking-chair. For two occupants—two single beds or one double-deck bed with springs and mattresses, one chiffonier, one desk or two tables, one rocking-chair and two straight chairs. BOARD Board.—Students may board at the University Commons, at their homes, or in private boarding houses or restaurants approved by the President. For cost of board at the University Commons, see below. For list of private boarding houses, with rates, apply to the Bursar. University Commons Meals may be had at the University Commons, a handsome building overlooking the McIntire Theatre and within two minutes walk of the dormitories. The interior of the beautiful panelled main room makes a charming atmosphere for dining and the furnishings are attractive. The meals are prepared by an experienced chef under the supervision of a trained dietitian and careful attention is given to quality and service. Board is supplied at cost and it is expected that the rate will in no event exceed $25 per month. Since the capacity of the Commons limits the number accommodated to about 350, it is essential that students make early application for reservations to Dr. E. A. Kincaid, Manager, 15 Monroe Hall. STUDENT ACTIVITIES JEFFERSON SOCIETY Connected with the University is the Jefferson Society founded in 1825 to provide for common improvement in debate, to promote general culture among its members and the student body, and to drill its members in all those exercises which strengthen for the free duties of citizenship. All students in regular attendance upon one or more of the schools of the University of Virginia who are not members of any similar organization in this institution shall be eligible to regular membership. Such candidates shall make written application on forms provided by the Membership Committee. These forms may be obtained at any of the literary meetings of the Society all of which are open to the public. They are announced in College Topics. PUBLICATIONS College Topics is a bi-weekly newspaper published by the students and devoted to the interests of the University at large. Corks and Curls is the University Annual, its aim being to present some record of the scholastic, religious, athletic and social activities of the college year. Its publication is in the hands of a chartered corporation formed by the fraternities and literary societies of the University. The Virginia Law Review is a journal devoted to the discussion of general questions of American jurisprudence published monthly from October to May, inclusive, by the students of the Law Department. The University of Virginia Magazine is a literary journal published seven times a year by students and is sponsored by the Jefferson Society. Engineering News is a monthly publication devoted to general news of the Department of Engineering and edited and managed by the students. STUDENT UNION The Student Union was organized in 1932. The University has taken over Madison Hall for use as a center of student activities under the supervision of the Union of which all students are considered members. The affairs of the Union are conducted by the Student Senate. Facilities are offered for meetings of student organizations and groups and a social program is carried forward throughout the session. In the reading room are newspapers from many of the cities in the South and East. Recreation rooms are also provided. Offices of College Topics, the Magazine, Corks and Curls, the Dulaney Memorial Library and the Student Self Help Bureau are located in the building. ATHLETICS Intercollegiate and intramural athletics are under the supervision of the Director of Athletics and his staff. The University is represented in intercollegiate competition by both varsity and first-year football, baseball, basketball, track, cross-country, boxing, tennis, swimming and lacrosse teams. The athletic plant is one of the finest in the South. Memorial Gymnasium contains three basketball courts, a swimming pool, a track, boxing and wrestling rooms, and adequate locker facilities. Scott Stadium, which seats 22,000 people, is regarded as one of the most beautiful in the country. Lambeth Field has excellent facilities for track and baseball. Twenty-two tennis courts and four practice fields for mass games have been built near the Gymnasium. STUDENT BRANCHES OF NATIONAL PROFESSIONAL SOCIETIES There have been established at the University of Virginia Student Branches of the American Institute of Electrical Engineers (1912), the American Society of Civil Engineers (1921), the American Society of Mechanical Engineers (1922), and the American Institute of Chemical Engineers (1934). These societies hold regular meetings for the discussion of periodical literature and the exposition by resident and visiting engineers of the present-day problems in Engineering. A valuable feature of the meetings is the opportunity presented for practice in public speaking and debate. At stated meetings the Branches hold joint sessions for the discussion of mutually interesting questions. ENGINEERING COUNCIL In 1934 was established the students' Engineering Council with representatives of the Student Branches and a Faculty advisor chosen by the Council. This Council coördinates the activities of the student societies and plans in general to advance the welfare of students in Engineering by every means within the reasonable reach of the Department. TAU BETA PI In May, 1921, a chapter of the National Honorary Engineering Fraternity Tau Beta Pi was granted and the Alpha of Virginia Chapter of Tau Beta Pi will henceforth serve to further inspire high scholarship and integrity. This fraternity is recognized as the leading honorary engineering fraternity of this country and its chapters are found in a limited number of engineering schools of the highest standing. The members are elected with care and the standards maintained are rigid both in respect to scholarship and character. THETA TAU In June, 1923, a chapter of the National Engineering Fraternity of Theta Tau was granted at the University of Virginia. This fraternity has chapters in a score or more of the leading engineering schools of the country and membership is eagerly sought and greatly appreciated by the members of the student body. Elections are made each year based on scholarship and general record of ability and promise of future service to the profession of engineering. TRIGON SOCIETY The Trigon Engineering Society was founded at the University of Virginia early in the spring of 1923. It is a local organization which has for its object the broadening of the education of the engineering student by fraternal and social contact and by encouraging lectures and study on subjects aside from those dealing primarily with engineering. The society is active in the student affairs of the department and is always ready to help in any undertaking for the betterment of the Engineering School. Members are selected for their personality, sociability, and promise of high engineering attainment. ALPHA CHI SIGMA On May 27, 1922, a charter was granted at the University of Virginia, creating the Alpha Kappa chapter of the National Chemical Fraternity of Alpha Chi Sigma. This fraternity recognizes high scholarship, character, and seriousness of purpose in students specializing in chemistry and chemical engineering. As the leading national fraternity in this field, it has 47 active college chapters, 10 professional chapters, and six professional groups, serving to advance chemistry and chemical engineering both scientifically and professionally. Among the regular activities of the local chapter are the sponsoring of the annual Alpha Chi Sigma lecture, the award of a membership in the American Chemical Society to the outstanding student in chemistry and chemical engineering, and general assistance to the faculty in the conduct of official functions. JONES AND BARKSDALE MEMORIAL FUNDS A gift to the Department of Engineering from Messrs. Arthur P. Jones, William Barham Jones (B.A. 1907) and Major Kenneth S. Jones (B.A., LL.B., C. E. 1915, Major U. S. A., Engineer Corps) in memory of their father, the late Walter H. Jones, of Norfolk, Va., and of his deep interest in the University of Virginia, in the form of an endowment fund has made it possible to provide a considerable number of professional periodicals representing the various engineering activities. A gift to the Department of Engineering from Mrs. Hamilton Barksdale in memory of her husband, an alumnus of the Engineering Department, specifically donated for the purpose of building up the department library, has made possible much needed changes and additions to the library. EXAMINATIONS AND REPORTS Oral Examinations are held at the beginning of each lecture hour on the topics of the preceding lecture. Written test papers are set monthly, or at such interval as the professor may appoint. Absences from lecture except by reason of sickness are not excused without a written leave from the Dean. Class standing is determined on the basis of the oral examinations and the written tests. Absence from the latter or failure to answer incurs a 0 grade. Absences from laboratory periods, however caused, must be made up by special private arrangement with the instructor. Written Examinations are held at the end of each term on the entire work of that term. The result of examination combined with the student's class-standing gives his term-grade. The pass-mark is 75 per cent. Absence from the written term examination incurs a 0 term-grade, which may not be removed except by the passage of a special written examination on the work of that term. Such special examinations are granted only upon presentation of a written certificate from a reputable physician that the student by reason of sickness on the day of the regular examination was unable to attend. Regular Reports are sent out at the end of every term to the student's parent or guardian. These state for each course followed the term-grade. Further comment may be added by the Dean or the professor, if it appears probable that such comment would be helpful to the student. Parents are urged to examine these reports carefully and to exert such parental influence as may seem needed to establish and confirm the student in habits of industry and order. Special Reports are sent to parents at the end of each month for students delinquent in attendance or studiousness and for delinquents only. When a student is making steady progress and showing due diligence in his work, only the regular reports are sent. The receipt of a special report is evidence that, in the judgment of the faculty, prompt and pointed parental admonition is urgently needed. If in any class the Department of Engineering a student fails to make satisfactory progress, he is first admonished by the professor in charge. In default of prompt and permanent improvement, he is next formally warned by the Dean. If due amendment is then not immediately effected, the student's name is dropped from the rolls of the Department, on the ground that he is not accomplishing the purposes for which he should have entered upon a University course of study. DEPARTMENT REGULATIONS The following regulations, adopted to define the policy of the faculty, are published for the information and guidance of the students: 1. Practice-courses as well as lecture-courses must be conducted under the Honor System. The student who submits any work to be graded is considered to submit it under pledge. 2. When the lecture-course and the associated practice-course are given in the same term of the same year, no student will be admitted to examination on the lecture-course until he has completed at least three-fourths of the practice-course. 3. No student will be admitted to any practice-course unless he is at the same time pursuing the associated lecture-course, or has already received credit for the same. 4. No student will be admitted to the graduating examination on a lecture-course unless he has been present at more than half the lectures in that course. 5. In the technical courses in Engineering (i. e., courses not given in the College) term-grades shall not be averaged; except that the term-grades for Freshmen Applied Mathematics may be averaged for the first-year men only, provided no mark is below 65, and term-grades in Freshman English, Freshman Mathematics, Sophomore Mathematics, and Sophomore Physics may be averaged, provided a grade of 75 or higher be made in the third term of the course with no grade below 65 in the first and second terms of the course. 6. The pass-mark in every course is 75. Class standing and written examination are combined for the term-grade in such proportions as the several professors may determine. 7. No student who fails to make 75 on term-grade shall be granted another examination on the course until he has again attended lectures on that course. 8. A student who fails a second time on any course will be allowed to attempt the course for a third time only by special permission of the faculty; a third failure in a course will prevent such student from acceptance as a degree candidate here in engineering. 9. Special examinations are not given except by reason of sickness on the day of examination, attested by the written certificate of a reputable physician, or for other like providential causes. In every case they must be validated by special vote of the faculty. 10. Any engineering student who fails to attain a passing grade of 75 on at least 9 term-hours will be placed on probation for the following term, probation to continue until at least 9 term-hours are passed in one term. No engineering student shall remain on probation for more than three terms, whether consecutive or not, in his entire engineering course. If probation is imposed a fourth time the student shall be suspended. 11. Any engineering student on probation who fails to attain a passing grade of 75 on at least 6 term-hours and whose average grade on all courses taken is less than 65 will be suspended. Any engineering student who passes less than 6 term-hours and whose average grade on all courses taken is less than 65 will be suspended. Suspension during a session continues for the remainder of the regular session. Suspension imposed at the end of a session holds for the whole of a subsequent session, except that such suspension may be absolved by the successful completion of prescribed work in the Summer Quarter. No engineering student suspended for a second time shall re-enter the department. 12. The Dean's List.—A student, who in any successive three terms, passes on all courses taken, aggregating not less than 18 session-hours, with an average grade on all courses of not less than 82 per cent, will be placed on the Dean's list. A student, who, in any successive three terms, passes on all courses taken aggregating not less than 18 session-hours, but who does not average 82 per cent, and who, in any subsequent term, passes on all courses taken, aggregating not less than 18 term-hours, with an average grade on all 18 term-hours of not less than 82 per cent will be placed on the Dean's List. A student will be automatically dropped from the Dean's List, if, in any term, he does not pass on all courses taken, aggregating not less than 18 term-hours, with an average grade on all courses of not less than 82 per cent. A student dropped from the Dean's List will be again placed on it if he meets the above mentioned standard for a term. A student on the Dean's List is not subject to the regulations limiting the issuance of leaves of absence from the University, nor does absence from any class entail on such student any penalty, affecting class standing, imposed for absence alone. Students on the Dean's List must attend all laboratory classes and must perform all written problem work and take all written quizzes under the same conditions as all other students. DRAFTING ROOMS The Drafting Rooms are abundantly lighted and are provided with solidly constructed tables with locked drawers for instruments and materials. Each student is assigned to a table and has a drawer for his exclusive use. The regular Drawing Classes execute each one plate a week under the supervision of the Instructors in Drawing. The more advanced students have such additional drawings assigned by their respective professors as are needed for the full development of the courses of study. Careful attention is given to the training of the students in free-hand lettering, in the conventional signs of mechanical drawing, in the proper layout of drawings, and in neat and accurate execution. Exercises are required also in tracing and in blue-printing, the rooms for which are conveniently arranged and in close contiguity to the drafting rooms. A vertical blue-printing machine with arc lamp, complete with trays, has recently been procured and installed. While, however, technical dexterity is demanded, the graphical method is taught and used primarily as an indispensable instrument of research, the thoughtful mastery of which is essential for the instructed Engineer. The construction and theory of the Polar Planimeter, the Slide Rule, and the Pantograph are carefully taught, and the student is trained in the practical use of these appliances for the rapid and accurate production of estimates and copies from finished drawings. EXPERIMENTAL ENGINEERING LABORATORIES Roads Materials Laboratory.—The apparatus for tests of non-bituminous road materials includes a two-cylinder Deval abrasion machine, a ball mill, a moulding press for briquettes of rock dust, a Page impact cementation tester, a Page impact toughness tester, a rock crusher and a Purdue brick rattler. This outfit the University owes to the generous aid of the late Dr. Logan Waller Page. In addition, the Department has acquired a 40,000-pound compression tester, a diamond core drill, a diamond rock saw, a grinding lap, a Westphal balance, specific gravity apparatus, and a complete set of sieves. Useful researches in the road-building rocks and gravels of Virginia, as well as the standard tests, are conducted each year by the class in Civil Engineering. The apparatus for tests of bituminous road materials includes the New York Testing Laboratory penetrometer, the Kirschbaum ductility machine, the Engler viscosimeter, the asphalt viscosimeter, the New York Testing Laboratory extractor, the New York State Board of Health oil tester, Hubbard pyknometers, asphalt flow plates, gas and electric hot plates, and the accessory apparatus needed for research on bituminous road-binders. Structural Materials Laboratory.—The Sinclair Laboratory for work in testing structural materials was founded on the original donation of Mrs. John Sinclair, of New York City, as a memorial to her late husband. The collection has since been considerably enlarged. It contains a Riehle 100,000-pound machine, arranged for tensile, compressive, and transverse tests, with an attachment for taking autographic diagrams; an Olsen 100,000-pound machine and fitted with a suspended ball compression block; a 200,000-pound Olsen machine suitable for compressive tests and also supplied with extension arms for making transverse tests of beams; an Olsen torsion machine of 50,000 inch-pound capacity; an Olsen impact-testing machine of 100 foot-pounds capacity; three machines of rotating beam type for fatigue tests of metals; Shore scleroscope; a Ewing machine for finding the modulus of elasticity; hand machines for testing rods and wires under pull, and small specimens of timber and cast iron under transverse loads. It is also equipped with accessory measuring instruments; these include a Riehle extensometer, an Olsen compressometer for metals and timber, an Olsen special strain gauge extensometer, an Olsen special extensometer, Olsen wire extensometers, a Ewing extensometer of great delicacy, and tools for shearing tests of metals and timber. Cement Laboratory.—The laboratory is completely equipped for making tests of cement, cement aggregates, and concrete. It contains a Fairbank's tensile tester of 1,000 pounds capacity; a compressometer for concrete specimens; Riehle dial compressometer for concrete specimens; Riehle dial compressometer-extensometer for specimens up to 3-inch diameter; tools for shearing tests of concrete; an Olsen steaming oven for accelerated tests; a Freas electric drying oven with automatic temperature regulation; moist air closets; sieves for mechanical analysis; moulds for tension and compression tests; and the required small apparatus. Fuel and Oil Laboratory.—For the determination of the heating value of coal, petroleum, etc., the laboratory has an Emerson bomb calorimeter. For gas and liquid fuel calorimetry, a Junker calorimeter made by the American Meter Co. is used. The equipment also includes two electric muffle furnaces, a Freas electric drying oven with automatic temperature regulation, sample crusher and grinder, a Brown high resistance pyrometer, balances, platinum crucibles, etc. For investigating lubricants, the laboratory is equipped with such apparatus as flash and chill point testers, hydrometers, viscosimeters, etc., used in the determination of the physical properties of oil. Hydraulics Laboratory.—The laboratory equipment for work in hydraulics comprises a steel tank for weir experiments with interchangable bronze notches; a hook gauge for measurement of surface levels; a stand-pipe provided with a set of standard bronze orifices for experiments on efflux; commercial pipe and elbows arranged for determining friction losses; Gurley current meter; and the necessary scales, tanks, manometers, etc. It also includes a pump which is piped to circulate water from a cement cistern to a tank in the attic of the building. Additional equipment of this laboratory is a motor driven centrifugal pump with a capacity of 350 gallons per minute at 100 feet head, equipped with a Venturi meter and the necessary piping, valves and gauges to provide for complete performance tests on the pump. This unit also supplies water at constant pressure for the other hydraulic tests. Recently added were a motor driven centrifugal pump with a capacity of 300 gallons per minute at 500 feet head, and a Pelton wheel manufactured by the Pelton Wheel Company expressly for laboratory use. Power Laboratory.—The laboratory is equipped to illustrate the theory involved in Mechanical Engineering; to give practical instruction in the handling of machinery; and to teach the fundamental methods of experimental work. It contains a Ball high-speed engine; a De Laval turbine with condensing and noncondensing nozzles, which is direct-connected to a 20-kva. alternating-current generator; an Otto gasoline engine with a special piston for alcohol; a White and Middleton 12 HP. Engine (gasoline or illuminating gas); two Liberty aeroplane motors; a Wheeler surface condenser to which the exhaust from any of the steam units may be connected; a Sturtevant engine and blower; an air compressor; an A. B. C. Pitot tube; a steam pump; steam traps, etc. For boiler tests, the boilers of the University Heating and Lighting Plant are used. The work of this laboratory has been facilitated by the recent installation of a Wickes 50 horsepower three drum bent tube boiler designed for a working pressure of 150 pounds. This boiler supplies steam to the laboratory and also affords excellent opportunities for boiler tests. The instrument room contains all necessary apparatus for carrying out complete tests. Among this may be mentioned indicators, thermometers, gauges, planimeters, with standards for their correction and calibration; two types of Orsat apparatus; separating and throttling calorimeters, etc. FIELD WORK IN CIVIL ENGINEERING The outfit of field instruments contains compasses, transits, and levels of various approved makes; a solar transit, furnished also with stadia wires and gradienter for tachymetric work; a Gurley mining transit, one of the finest products of the instrument maker's art; a complete Gurley transit, graduated to 30 seconds, with solar attachment; hand-levels and clinometers for field topography; plane tables; a sextant; together with an adequate supply of leveling rods, telemeter rods, signal poles, chains, tapes, pins, and so on. For hydraulic surveys a hook gauge and a current meter are provided. All students are instructed in the theory and adjustments of the field instruments and in their practical use in the field. They are also required to make up their field-books in standard forms; to reduce their surveys and execute all the necessary profiles, plans and maps; and to determine lengths, areas, and volumes both from the maps and from the original notes. Polar planimeters are provided for facilitating such estimates, and a pantograph for making reduced copies of finished drawings. A set of Beggs' Deformeter apparatus is available for use in the work of Bridge Design. ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING LABORATORY The Scott Laboratory of Electrical Engineering.—This laboratory was initially equipped and endowed by Mrs. Frances Branch Scott, of Richmond, Va., as a memorial to her late son, an alumnus of this University. During the year 1910 the equipment was substantially increased through the generosity of the Hon. Charles R. Crane, of Chicago, Ill., a friend of the University. In recent years a large number of new machines, measuring instruments and pieces of auxiliary apparatus have been purchased. Improvements are constantly being made and items of equipment added. As a result the laboratory is now well supplied with the best modern equipment. Power is supplied to the laboratory from the University distribution system through a transformer vault located in the building. There is also installed a motor generator set consisting of a synchronous motor driving an alternator and a three-wire direct-current generator. A complete three-panel switchboard for the control of this set is equipped with the necessary instruments and includes an automatic voltage regulator for the alternator. Power is carried from the switchboard to distribution panels located at convenient points. Universal plug-and receptacle-connections facilitate the setting up of all experimental combinations. For the machine testing there are available several direct-current motor generator sets with automatic control; numerous series, shunt and compound motors and generators; synchronous and induction motor driven generator sets; high voltage direct-current generator; steam turbine driven three-phase alternator with exciter and control switchboard; two experimental test sets for alternating current single or polyphase generator operation; single-phase induction motor; single-phase repulsion-induction motor; two-phase induction motor; three-phase squirrel cage induction motors of the general purpose, high reactance and double cage types; wound rotor induction motors; induction generator; wound rotor induction motor set for concatenation; Fynn-Weichsel synchronous induction motor; frequency changer set; synchronous motors; rotary converter; arc welding generator set; constant potential transformers; constant current transformer; polyphase transformer; induction regulator; mercury arc and thermionic rectifiers; a number of different types of A. C. and D. C. fractional horsepower motors; prony brakes for all motors; adjustable resistances, inductances and capacitances. The instrument room is unusually well equipped with all of the types of high grade portable meters required for the laboratory tests, including frequency and power factor meters, watthour meters, synchroscopes, tachometers, instrument transformers, recording voltmeters, ammeters and wattmeters. For testing and calibrating the portable instruments and for more precise work in electrical measurments there are available a set of laboratory standard instruments with standard shunts and resistances; standard cells; standard condensers, inductances and resistances; galvanometers of the best modern type and numerous other pieces of apparatus of the highest precision such as the Wolff potentiometer, Siemens and Halske-Thomson double bridge, Carey-Foster bridge, Koepsel permeameter, Fahy simplex permeameter and others. For experiments in illumination and photometry there are a Station photometer with Lummer-Brodhun screen, a Macbeth illuminometer, General Electric and Weston portable foot-candle meters. Equipment for the study of communication and power transmission includes a complete artificial transmission line; an adjustable frequency test oscillator; bridge; vacuum tube voltmeter-ammeter; representative pieces of modern telephone equipment including two central office ringer sets; equipment for the study of vacuum tube performance; model network distribution system; all with the necessary auxiliary apparatus. The laboratory is equipped with three oscillographs which are available for the study of wave forms and transient phenomena. Two of the oscillographs are of the latest portable type—one a six element and the other a one element. All are complete with the necessary accessories for both visual observation and photographic recording. CHEMICAL ENGINEERING LABORATORY For convenience in the supply of chemicals and accessories, facilities for chemical engineering laboratory work are provided principally in the Chemical Building. In addition to individual research rooms, approximately 2,000 square feet of floor area exists in the chemical engineering laboratory located in the recently completed addition to the Chemical Building. This room is provided with water, air, and electrical outlets of suitable capacity, floor drainage, and a pit giving extra headroom for special apparatus. Plans are in preparation for equipping this laboratory. Additional facilities exist at the University Power House, where semi-plant scale absorption equipment has been installed for the experimental treatment of flue gas. BUILDINGS The buildings at present devoted wholly or in part to the work of the Department of Engineering are the following: The Mechanical Laboratory is the main seat of the instruction in technical studies. It is 180 by 70 feet and contains on the main floor the Dean's office and the offices of three other professors; and three lecture-rooms. Above are two offices, a reading room for students, and blue-print and photographic rooms. Below on the ground floor are an office and classroom, the electrical laboratories, the testing laboratories, apparatus and storerooms, and the student's lavatory. In order to more adequately care for increased numbers this building has undergone a considerable rearrangement during recent years. Wood and machine shop equipment has been entirely removed from the building. This change made available much needed classroom space and allowed the electrical laboratories to be expanded. Incident to the changes new cement floors were constructed for the Road Materials Testing Laboratory, the main testing Laboratory and the main hall. A new high-pressure steam line from the Power House was also installed. The New Power House is a single story building 130 by 60 feet, in which is housed the University heating plant. The equipment includes two 310 horsepower Heine water tube boilers, equipped with single retort stokers of the underfeed type, supplied by the Combustion Engineering Corporation, two Babcock and Wilcox boilers (Stirling type) fitted with underfeed twin-retort Detroit stokers, two steam and two electrically driven circulating pumps, low pressure heaters, etc. Provision has been made for the future installation of two steam turbine generator sets for the supply of electric current to the University buildings. The entire plant is available for instructional purposes. Plants available for inspection both locally and elsewhere throughout the State include the Bremo Bluff and other generating stations of the Virginia Public Service Company, numerous chemical plants, the Langley Memorial Aeronautical Laboratory, Hampton, the Newport News Shipyard, the Norfolk Navy Yard, the Rothwell Cold Storage and Ice Company's plants in Charlottesville and Waynesboro, the Norfolk and Western Railway shops and the works of the Virginia Bridge and Iron Company at Roanoke, the Charlottesville Woolen Mills, etc. Visits of several days' duration are organized to distant points and are made to coincide, if possible, with some event of more than usual interest, such as the launching of a cruiser at the Newport News Shipyard, the visit of an airplane carrier to Hampton Roads or the sea trials of a passenger liner. The Geological Museum is 120 by 50 feet. It is a three-story building. The main floor is devoted to the very extensive geological collection of specimens, charts, relief maps, and so on. The gallery above contains an equally good collection of minerals and numerous models of typical crystallographic forms. The upper floor contains the lecture-rooms and the laboratories of Economic Geology. In the basement are stored subsidiary collections and new material accumulated in more recent geological surveys. The Physical Laboratory faces the Mechanical Laboratory on the opposite side of the quadrangle, and has almost the same proportions. The main floor contains the lecture-room, the professors' offices, the laboratory of experimental physics, and the storeroom for the very large collection of apparatus used in the lectures. On the ground floor is the laboratory of theoretical electricity, the storage battery room, a well-equipped shop for the repair and manufacture of apparatus, and smaller rooms for the work of graduate students. The new Chemical Laboratory was opened for use in September, 1917. In this fire-proof structure all the work in Chemistry is assembled. The floor area provided is about 45,000 square feet. The lecture-rooms seat classes of 300, 75 and 25 students. The laboratories assigned to General Chemistry, Organic Chemistry, Qualitative Analysis, Quantitative Analysis, and Physical Chemistry contain 110, 60, 40, 30, and 20 desks. Altogether by dividing classes into sections, 600 students may be accommodated. Smaller private laboratories are provided for research workers. Large stock rooms communicating by elevators with the several floors contain ample stores of chemical supplies. The 5,000 volumes of books and bound sets of journals constituting the Departmental Library of Chemistry are so housed as to be accessible to both teachers and students. NEW FACILITIES FOR ENGINEERING INSTRUCTION Construction is now under way for a new center of engineering instruction at the University of Virginia. Upon completion of the building program, at the opening of the session of 1935-1936, the present center for engineering instruction will leave the Mechanical Laboratory and be wholly cared for in the new engineering group. In general this new group will consist of three interconnected buildings forming a U-structure approximately 300 feet on each side, and enclosing a grass court about 150 feet square. The buildings are designated as Buildings A, B and C, and they are to conform in architectural characteristics with the University group as a whole with the emphasis in this group placed upon the arcade rather than the colonnade motive. The site selected affords ample ground and provides a most attractive setting and outlook. The buildings are being erected on Observatory Road to the west of Clark Hall, the Law Building, and not far from the Scott Stadium, giving a fine outlook in all directions. Building A, the main unit, will be of three stories. The basement will house the laboratories of Hydraulics, Cement, and Fuel and Oil Testing, each in a separate laboratory; general locker space for 300 and lavatories with several storage rooms complete the basement. The first floor will provide the office suite for teaching staff, with eleven offices, small lavatories, faculty conference room, two class-rooms seating 75, four seating 40, and three seating 25. The second, or top, floor is to be occupied by two large drawing rooms with two smaller ones for advanced work; a fine library and reading room with librarian's office, two other offices for instructors and a blue-printing room. Building B will be a one-story structure devoted to the Strength of Materials, Steam and Gas Power, and Road Materials Testing, each in its separate quarters; an instrument room for surveying equipment with office for the instructors is included as well as office and storage rooms for the testing laboratories; a student lounge room will be provided on a mezzanine gallery level. Building C will be of two stories. The ground floor houses the electrical laboratory equipment, in a large main machinery laboratory with separate laboratories for communication, illumination, and standardization work; transformer room, battery room, and dark room completing the set-up with an instrument room and office for the instructing staff. The upper floor will provide a metallurgical laboratory, a demonstration machine shop, and wood shop, tool room, repair shop, and a large laboratory for aeronautical apparatus, with office and lavatory. The repair shop will be connected by elevator with the lower floor to facilitate handling machinery needing repairs. The opening of this group for service in September, 1935, will supply facilities of a modern character long needed here to make possible the best training in engineering, so far as physical plant is concerned, that the University has ever been able to offer. The well-known rigid disciplines of the formal instruction will hereafter be adequately supplemented by physical equipment conveniently and substantially installed without crowding. It is expected that the experimental equipment and fixtures will be very considerably increased over the existing ones by the time the group is ready for opening. Great care has been taken to supply the best lighting facilities for all rooms and intercommunicating telephones will offer rapid communication between all offices in the group. More complete details with regard to the buildings and the new equipment will appear in the catalogue for next year. A fair idea of the finished appearance of the new group is given by the architects' drawing depicted near the front of this catalogue. COURSES OF INSTRUCTION The subjects of Instruction in Engineering are grouped into classes, each designated by a distinctive number for each term, the lecture and laboratory courses being likewise differentiated. This grouping follows the arrangement shown below: Humanities 1 to 99 Mathematics 100 to 199 Physics 200 to 299 Chemistry and Chemical Engineering 300 to 399 Geology 400 to 499 Applied Mathematics 500 to 599 Experimental Engineering 600 to 699 Civil Engineering including Field-work 700 to 799 Mechanical Engineering including Aeronautics 800 to 899 Electrical Engineering 900 to 999 Lecture courses are listed in the first fifty numbers of all classes; laboratory or practice courses are listed in the second fifty numbers of all classes. The same numbers are used in schedules of lecture hours, laboratory periods and examination days. HUMANITIES 1-2-3: English: 12:30-1:30, M. W. F. 2:30-5:30, M. First term: Composition, with frequent themes and parallel reading in scientific literature. Second term: The short report and letter writing. Third term; The composition of technical papers with especial reference to the long report. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Mr. Vaughan, Mr. Edwards, and Mr. Dutcher. 7-8-9: Business Speaking: 9:30-10:30, T. Th. S. This course is intended to fit engineers for effective speaking in the modern business world. It includes the principles of persuasive speaking, various types of business talks, radio and telephone speaking, and a detailed treatment of the personal conference. This training is required of all Juniors. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Associate Professor Paul and Mr. Seward. 10-11-12: Economics: 10:30-11:30, M. W. F. First and second terms: Survey of the principles of economics. Third term: The bearing of these principles upon present American conditions. Instruction will be given by lectures, assigned readings, reports, and discussions. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Optional course, for all except Chemical Engineering students, in place of which a 3-session-hour course in Modern Language (40-41-42), French, German, Italian or Spanish may be taken. Professor Snavely, Associate Professor Hyde, Mr. Graves and Mr. McDonald. 13-14-15: Commercial Law: 11:30-12:30, T. Th. S. A detailed study of the fundamental and important, rather than the technical, principles of those subjects of which knowledge is necessary in ordinary commercial transactions. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Optional for Government (16-17-18) or History (31-32-33). Associate Professor Hulvey and Mr. Williams. 16-17-18: Government: 9:30-10:30, T. Th. S. A description and comparison of the principles and essential features of the governments of the United States, England, France, Germany, and Switzerland, with especial emphasis on the characteristics of the American Constitutional system and the operation of Congressional government. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Optional for Commercial Law (13-14-15) or History (31-32-33). Associate Professor Spicer. 21-22-23: Cost Accounting: 9:30-10:30, M. W. F. First term: Theory and practice in General Accounting. Second and third terms: Application of accounting principles to various types of manufacturing and engineering enterprises. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Professor Barlow, Mr. Dandelake and Miss Newman. 26: Engineering Economics and Specifications: 9:30-10:30, T. Th. S. Lectures, parallel reading and written work dealing with the economic considerations involved in engineering problems and specifications for engineering structures. Special emphasis is placed upon the general problem of economic selection of methods, machinery and apparatus in the several engineering fields. Qustions of first cost, depreciation, rates for service, etc., will be treated. Complete specifications are required from each student, subjects being chosen particularly from the special field of study of each individual student. (Spring.) Assistant Professor Morse. 31-32-33: History: A college course in history to be chosen by the student and approved by the Faculty of Engineering. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Optional for Commercial Law (13-14-15) or Government (16-17-18). 34-35-36: Elective: A graduate-year humanistic course chosen from Philosophy, Architecture, Fine Arts, or other subject approved by the Faculty of Engineering. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) 40-41-42: Modern Languages: 8:30-9:30 or 9:30-10:30 or 12:30-1:30, M. T. W. Th. F. A college credit course in modern language chosen between French, German, Italian and Spanish and upon approval of the student's major-subject professor. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) An optional course, for all except Chemical Engineering students, which may be taken in place of Economics (10-11-12). Chemical Engineering students are required to take German for two years. Professor Graham, Associate Professor Rinetti and Assistant Professors Mohr and Woody. 43-44-45; German: 10:30-11:30, T. Th. S. A course in second-year German required of students in Chemical Engineering in their Junior year. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Professor Faulkner, Associate Professor Wood and Assistant Professor Mohr. MATHEMATICS 100: Trigonometry: 8:30-10:30, T. Th. S. A complete course in plane trigonometry is pursued with constant drill in the solution of problems, equations, identities, and exercises in the use of logarithms. (Fall.) Professor Oglesby, Mr. Edwards, Mr. H. B. Daniel and Mr. Rutherfoord. 106: Analytical Geometry and College Algebra: 8:30-10:30, T. Th. S. In this course Cartesian and polar coördinates are presented and applied to the study of the straight line, the circle, the parabola and the ellipse. About one-third of the time is spent on related topics in college algebra. (Winter.) Professor Oglesby, Mr. Edwards, Mr. H. B. Daniel and Mr. Rutherfoord. 107: Analytical Geometry and College Algebra: 8:30-10:30, T. Th. S. This course is a continuation of course 106. The topics studied are the hyperbola, transformation of coördinates, the general equation of the second degree, systems of conics, tangents and polars, and problems on loci. The study of college algebra is continued. (Spring.) Professor Oglesby, Mr. Edwards, Mr. H. B. Daniel and Mr. Rutherfoord. 108: Calculus: 11:30-12:30, M. W. F. A first course in the differential calculus. The topics studied are limits, differentiation of algebraic and transcendental functions, applications to geometry, elementary kinematics and mechanical problems, parametric equations, polar equations, differentials and curvature. (Fall.) Professor Oglesby, Mr. G. K. Carter and Mr. Payne. 109: Calculus: 11:30-12:30, M. W. F. A first course in the integral calculus. A study of the process of integration with applications. (Winter.) Professor Oglesby, Mr. G. K. Carter and Mr. Payne. 110: Calculus: 11:30-12:30, M. W. F. The topics studied are the theorem of mean value and its applications, series, expansions of functions, partial differentiation and multiple integrals. (Spring.) Professor Oglesby, Mr. G. K. Carter and Mr. Payne. 111: Differential Equations: 11:30-12:30, T. Th. S. An elementary course in differential equations with particular reference to the differential equations of electrical engineering. (Fall.) Professor Oglesby. 158-159-160: Mathematics Laboratory: 2:30-5:30, W. F. This course is conducted in conjunction with 108-109-110. It consists of an intensive, supervised study of calculus problems. (Fall, Winter, and Spring.) Professor Oglesby, Mr. G. K. Carter and Mr. Payne. PHYSICS 200-201-202: Sophomore Physics: 9:30-10:30, M. W. F. 250-251-252: Physics Laboratory: 9:30-11:30, T. Th. S. An elementary course in general physics consisting of lectures, lecture demonstrations, recitations and laboratory exercises. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Associate Professor Brown and Assistants. CHEMISTRY AND CHEMICAL ENGINEERING 300-301-302: General Chemistry: 10:30-11:30, T. Th. S. 350-351-352: Chemistry Laboratory: 11:30- 1:30, T. Th. S. The fundamental principles and phenomena of inorganic, organic, and physical chemistry, and the foundations of analytical chemistry. Most of the time is devoted to inorganic phenomena. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Textbooks: Richardson: General Chemistry; Carter: Laboratory Course in General Chemistry; Long and Anderson: Chemical Calculations. Professor Carter, Dr. Bell and Assistants. 303-304-305: Chemical Principles: 8:30-9:30, T. Th. S. 353-354-355: Quantitative Analysis Laboratory: 2:30-5:30, M. W. F. Chemistry 300-301-302 and 350-351-352 prerequisite. Two hours of lecture per week are devoted to chemical principles, as an intermediate course designed to bridge the gap between general chemistry and physical chemistry, the principles touched upon during the first-year course are restated and treated from a more advanced viewpoint. The accompanying laboratory course is designed to introduce the theory and practice of volumetric and gravimetric methods of analysis, including an introduction to electroanalysis. Nine hours per week, including one demonstration or recitation on the technique and theory of quantitative analysis. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) (Not given after session 1934-35.) Professor Yoe and Assistant. 309-310-311: Organic Chemistry: 10:30-11:30, M. W. F. 359-360-361: Organic Chemistry Laboratory: 2:30-5:30, W. F. Chemistry 300-301-302 and 350-351-352 prerequisite. An introduction to the study of the compounds of carbon, including the application of modern chemical theory to such compounds and their reactions. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) (Not required after session 1935-36.) Professor Bird and Assistants. 312-313-314: Organic Chemistry: 11:30-12:30, T. Th. S. 362-363-364: Organic Chemistry Laboratory: 2:30-5:30, M. Chemistry 300-301-302 and 350-351-352 prerequisite. An introductory study of Organic Chemistry. Typical reactions are discussed largely around questions and problems which illustrate chemical principles and reaction tendencies. Intrinsic influencing factors, conditions and the mechanisms of reactions are stressed. The laboratory work: An experimental study of unit processes and the control of reactions by imposed conditions. A thorough study of the textbook is called for in connection with every experiment. Parallel reading. 3 hours of lecture and 3 hours of laboratory per week. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) (Required beginning session 1935-36.) Textbooks: Bird: Typical Reactions of Organic Compounds; Laboratory Notes and Groggin's Unit Processes for parallel study. Professor Bird and Assistants. 315-316-317: Qualitative Analysis: 8:30-9:30, T. Th. 365-366-367: Qualitative Analysis Laboratory: 2:30-5:30, T. or Th. Chemistry 300-301-302 and 350-351-352 prerequisite. A course devoted to the study of systematic qualitative analysis. In the lecture work special emphasis is given to the theoretical foundations of analytical chemistry. 2 hours of lecture and 3 hours of laboratory per week. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) (Required beginning session 1935-36.) Textbooks: Noyes: Qualitative Chemical Analysis; Engelder: Calculations of Qualitative Analysis. Professor Yoe and Assistants. 318-319-320: Quantitative Analysis: Lecture by appointment. 368-369-370: Quantitative Analysis Laboratory: 2:30-5:30, M. W. F. Chemistry 315-316-317 and 365-366-367 prerequisite. An introductory course in volumetric and gravimetric methods of analysis. 9 hours per week, including 1 lecture or recitation on the technique and theory of quantitative analysis. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) (Required beginning session 1936-37.) Textbook: Fales: Inorganic Quantitative Analysis. Professor Yoe and Assistant. 321-322-323: Physical Chemistry: 12:30-1:30, M. W. F. 371-372-373: Physical Chemistry Laboratory: 2:30-5:30, T. Th. Chemistry 303-304-305 or 315-316-317 prerequisite, as well as some knowledge of the Calculus and previous training in Physics. An introductory study of atomic structure theory, kinetic theory and the principle of the conservation of energy form the foundations of the study of gases, liquids, solids, solutions and rates of reaction. A brief study of the direction of chemical change is then followed by the consideration of homogeneous and heterogeneous equilibria. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Textbooks: Taylor: Elementary Physical Chemistry; Daniels, Mathews and Williams: Experimental Physical Chemistry. Professor Benton, Assistant Professor Spencer and Assistant. 324-325-326: Principles of Chemical Engineering: 9:30-10:30, M. W. F. Chemistry 321-322-323 prerequisite. A course designed to give the prospective chemical engineer a thorough foundation in the unit operations. Regularly taken in the fourth year. Practice in the application of the principles involved is given by the solution of numerous type problems in which quantitative treatment is emphasized. Attention is first devoted to a detailed study of flow of fluids and flow of heat, since these topics are fundamental in the subsequent development of unit operations in Chemical Engineering. These subjects are followed by evaporation, humidification, drying and distillation. Facility is developed in the stoichiometry of chemical industry. Plant inspection trips are made from time to time. Lectures and recitations, 3 hours a week. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Textbooks: Walker, Lewis and McAdams: Principles of Chemical Engineering; Badger and McCabe: Elements of Chemical Engineering; Perry: Chemical Engineers' Handbook. Associate Professor Hitchcock. 327-328-329: Advanced Chemical Engineering: 10:30-11:30, M. W. F. Chemical Engineering 324-325-326 prerequisite. Regularly taken in the graduate year by candidates for the Ch. E. degree. The subjects of distillation and drying are treated in more detail than in the preliminary course, while the additional subjects of filtration, absorption, and extraction are taken up. Further practice is had in applications of calculus to the solutions of problems in these fields. Principles in the flow of fluids and flow of heat are used in solving problems of more advanced character. Recent developments in Chemical Engineering are studied. Lectures and recitations, 3 hours a week. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Textbooks: Walker, Lewis and McAdams: Principles of Chemical Engineering; McAdams: Heat Transmission. Associate Professor Hitchcock. 340-341-342: Applied Chemistry: 8:30-9:30, M. W. F. Chemistry 309-310-311 or 312-313-314 and 321-322-323 prerequisite. The lectures and recitations in this course are devoted to the study of fundamental principles underlying the more important phases of industrial chemistry, including both theoretical and economic problems. A considerable amount of collateral reading in descriptive industrial chemistry is assigned, and written reports involving use of the literature are required. Better appreciation of the quantitative relationships existing in the applications of chemistry is gained through problem work paralleling the lecture material. A number of plant inspection trips are arranged during the year. Lectures and recitations, 3 hours a week. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Textbooks: Badger and Baker: Inorganic Chemical Technology; Lewis and Radasch: Industrial Stoichiometry; Riegel: Industrial Chemistry. Associate Professor Hitchcock. 374-375-376: Chemical Engineering Laboratory: The student demonstrates to himself essential features of the unit operations of chemical engineering, by constructing and testing with his own hands suitable apparatus for the illustration of principles in the parallel classroom work. Under minimum supervision, he plans, builds, and tests such equipment as orifices and other measuring apparatus, fluid flow devices verifying Fanning's equation, apparatus for determination of heat transfer coefficients in the more common cases, model vacuum pan sufficient to demonstrate the ordinary relationships of evaporation, and packed columns for the absorption of gases in liquids. The primary object of this course is to teach the students how to obtain the data necessary for the interpretation of the unit operations in chemical engineering. It is inevitable that at the same time, he gains a clearer understanding of these operations, as well as facility in shop work and the use of his hands, the preparation of working drawings, and the reduction of his results to writing in the form of an acceptable report. Whether the apparatus is particularly efficient, or even practicable from a production standpoint, is not regarded as important at this stage. The students work in small groups in order to make better use of the time, and the results obtained by each group are made available to all through dependent problem work in the classroom. 6 hours per week. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) (This course will be required beginning 1936.) Associate Professor Hitchcock. 383-384-385: Undergraduate Chemical Engineering Research: Opportunity is afforded undergraduate students to obtain an introduction to research methods in problems pertaining to chemical engineering. As a rule the course is open to those who are taking the major portion of their work in senior subjects, and who have had or are taking Chemical Engineering 324-325-326. A minimum of nine hours per week for one term is required in the laboratory, and it is expected that normally the students will continue the work through the entire session. (An elective course for those having the time to apply to it.) Associate Professor Hitchcock. 386-387-388: Chemical Engineering Research: This course is designed for candidates for the Ch. E. degree and affords an introduction to research methods. Fundamental problems are selected, whenever possible, from the field of greatest interest to the student. The method of attack is in general to reduce the selected problem to laboratory scale leading to the collection of basic data susceptible of definite interpretation, rather than to attempt investigations on commercial equipment which usually yield empirical results. The use of the chemical literature as an aid in conducting investigations prefaces and accompanies the laboratory work, as well as practice in the mathematical and graphical treatment of the data obtained. The preparation and submission of a satisfactory thesis marks the completion of this course, and is a partial fulfilment of the requirements for the Ch. E. degree. Two copies of the thesis, typewritten on paper of prescribed quality and size, and substantially bound, must be deposited in the office of the Dean of the Department of Engineering not later than May 15 of the year in which it is expected that the degree will be conferred. The back of the cover must bear the title of the thesis and the writer's name, and the title page must bear the words: A thesis presented to the Engineering Faculty of the University of Virginia in candidacy for the degree of Chemical Engineer. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Associate Professor Hitchcock. Advanced Courses: A number of advanced courses in Chemistry, not listed above, are described in the catalogue of the College. When time permits, students in Chemical Engineering, who are properly prepared, may take such of these courses as are approved by the Faculty of Engineering. The Chemical Journal Club will meet once a week (hour to be arranged) for the critical review and discussion of various topics of interest in current chemical literature and of such chemical researches as are in progress in the University. All members of the teaching staff and advanced students in chemistry are expected to participate in these meetings and to take part in the discussions. GEOLOGY 400-401-402: Engineering Geology: 8:30-9:30, M. W. F. 450-451-452: Field and Laboratory: 6 hours a week. Fundamental principles of dynamical and structural geology for first term with Professor Roberts; minerals and rocks for second term with Assistant Professor Pegau; and building stones and ores for third term with Professor Nelson. The laboratory work is devoted to the interpretation of topographic and structural maps, the principal building stones and their mineral content and properties, field trips, the use of the plane table in topographic mapping, and geologic mapping. Professors Nelson, Roberts, Assistant Professor Pegau and Assistant. APPLIED MATHEMATICS 521: Plane Surveying: 10:30-11:30, M. W. F. Lecture course: Theory, uses, and adjustments of compass, level, transit, and stadia. Special methods of land, city, topographic and mining surveys. Survey computation and maps. (Fall or Spring.) 571: Field course: Practical use of chain and tape, level, compass, transit and stadia. Field notes, records and reports. 6 hours a week. Professor Saunders and Assistants. 522: Mechanical Drawing: 10:30-11:30, M. W. F. Lecture course: Principles of lettering; use of instruments and drawing equipment; geometric constructions; orthographic projection; sectional views and commercial conventions; free-hand sketching; pictorial representation; principles of dimensioning; detail and assembly drawings; commercial practice. (Fall or Winter.) 572: Practice course: The students execute a series of drawings, applying the principles acquired in the lecture course, in pencil and ink, on paper and tracing cloth. 6 hours a week. Associate Professor Hesse and Assistants. 523: Descriptive Geometry: 11:30-12:30, M. W. F. Winter 10:30-11:30, M. W. F. Spring Lecture course: Orthographic projection; point, line and plane fundamentals; intersections; developments and applications. (Winter or Spring.) 573: Practice course: The students execute a series of drawings, applying the principles acquired in the lecture course to problems selected from various branches of engineering. 6 hours a week. Associate Professor Hesse and Assistants. 524: Graphical Statistics: 10:30-11:30, T. Th. S. Lecture course: Graphic composition and resolution of forces; centers of gravity and moments of inertia; strain sheets for simple types of roof and bridge trusses; beams under fixed and rolling loads; reservoir dams and retaining walls; internal stresses and beam deflections. (Winter.) 574: Practice course: Each student executes a weekly plate 15″×20″ of problems based on the lectures. 6 hours a week. Professor Saunders, Associate Professor Hesse and Mr. W. L. Davis, Jr. 525: Structural Drawing: 10:30-11:30, T. Th. S. Lecture course: Graphic analysis of steel and timber trusses for roofs and bridges; of solid beams and plate girder bridges; and of reinforced concrete slabs, girders, columns, and retaining walls. (Spring.) 575: Practice course: Design and detailed drawings of simple examples of roofs and bridges, with complete computations for each structure. 6 hours a week. Professor Saunders, Associate Professor Hesse and Mr. W. L. Davis, Jr. 526: Elementary Mechanics: 12:30-1:30, T. Th. S. Lecture course: Composition and resolution of forces; friction; problems in equilibrium; rectilinear motion, circular motion, projectile motion. (Spring.) 576: Practice course: Solution of weekly problems in mechanics by graphical and analytical methods. 6 hours a week. Associate Professor Miller and Mr. Copper. 527: Applied Mechanics: 10:30-11:30, T. Th. S. Review of elementary mechanics; dynamics of a particle; moments of inertia; revolving bodies; rolling bodies; theory of work and energy; collision of elastic solids; dynamics of the Steam Engine. Weekly problems are assigned for solution by graphical and analytical methods. (Fall.) Associate Professor Miller and Mr. Hahn. 528: Strength of Materials: 11:30-12:30, T. Th. S. Fundamental laws of stress and strain; straining actions and stresses in ties and struts, beams and shafts, reinforced concrete slabs and girders; deflections in simple, restrained and continuous girders; columns under axial and eccentric loads. Laboratory courses 661-2-3. (Winter.) Associate Professor Miller and Mr. G. K. Carter. 529: Hydraulics: 11:30-12:30, T. Th. S. Equilibrium of fluids, applied to the analysis and design of thin and thick shells and pipes, dams and weirs. Motion of fluids and discharges from orifices, weir notches, pipes, canals, and rivers. Principles of linear and angular momentum with applications to the analysis and design of hydraulic motors and pumps. Laboratory course 680. (Spring.) Associate Professor Henderson and Mr. Payne. Laboratory studies in Strength of Materials and Hydraulics are given in the Classes in Experimental Engineering. 530: Machine Design: (For Electrical Course.) 10:30-11:30, T. Th. S. Lecture course: Materials and methods of Machine Design; friction, lubrication, plain, roller and ball bearings; positive and friction clutches; belt, rope and chain transmission; gearing and commercial speed reducers; riveted and screw fastenings; fits, shafts; flywheels; machine frames. (Spring.) 580: Practice course: Application of principles studied in the lecture course to problems of particular interest to the Electrical Engineer. Design, re-design, selection and layout of equipment. 6 hours a week. Associate Professor Hesse. 581: Engineering Design: (For Chemical Course.) 7 hours a week. Machine and structural elements; elementary graphic statics; applications of mechanics to problems of power transmission, conveying and materials handling. The course is planned to teach students to attack problems of design in an orderly manner. The major portion of the work is individual, and is done in the laboratory, with one lecture each week on design and application. (Fall.) Associate Professor Hesse. EXPERIMENTAL ENGINEERING Lectures are given to explain the origin and manufacture of materials, the design and operation of equipment, methods of conducting the tests and the calculation of the desired results from the data taken in the laboratory. The work is done principally in the laboratories where special emphasis is laid upon (1) a thorough understanding of the problem to be undertaken, (2) accuracy in carrying out the investigation, (3) the presentation of the results in a report which must meet the standards of professional practice. 650: Road Materials Testing: 6 hours a week. Standard tests of Portland cement. Samples of stone are tested for specific gravity, absorption, cementing value, toughness, resistance to abrasion, and compressive strength. Asphalts and tars are tested for specific gravity, penetration, melting point, volatilization, viscosity, flash point, fixed carbon. (Winter.) Associate Professor Henderson. 661: Structural Materials Testing: 5 hours a week. Tests of cement, timber and metals. A course for Electrical and Mechanical Engineers, similar to 662 and 663 but arranged so as to cover all of the work in one term. (Winter.) Associate Professor Henderson and Mr. Watkins. 662: Structural Materials Testing: 5 hours a week. Tests of sand; tests of fine and course aggregates; proportioning of concrete; compression tests of concrete and mortar, with measurements of deformation; tests of reinforced concrete beams; construction of forms for concrete. For Civil Engineers. (Fall.) Associate Professor Henderson. 663: Structural Materials Testing: 5 hours a week. Continuation of Course 662. Tests of wires; tension, compression and torsion tests of metals; tranverse tests of metals and timber; determination of the Modulus of Elasticity of metals; autographic testing; impact tests of metals; fatigue tests; hardness tests. For Civil Engineers. (Winter.) Associate Professor Henderson and Mr. Watkins. 670: Fuel and Oil Testing: 5 hours a week. Standard methods of sampling coal; proximate analysis of coal; determination of the heating value of coal by the bomb calorimeter, with a study of the cooling correction; the heating value of gas by the Junker calorimeter; determination of heating value of liquid fuels; determination of specific gravity, flash and boiling points, chill point, viscosity, carbon residue, and emulsification value of oils. (Fall.) Associate Professor Henderson, Mr. G. K. Carter and Mr. Hahn. 680: Hydraulic Testing: 5 hours a week. The measurement of the flow of water by means of orifices and weir notches; determination of the coefficient of friction for pipe and pipe elbows; study of a piston water meter; tests of large and small Venturi meters; performance tests of piston and centrifugal pumps; measurement of stream velocity and discharge by means of current meter. (Spring.) Associate Professor Henderson and Mr. W. L. Davis, Jr. 690: Power Laboratory: 5 hours a week. The calibration and adjustment of gauges; calibration of themometers, planimeters, pyrometers, and indicators, flue gas analysis; steam quality tests; valve setting; determination of clearances; tests of steam boilers; tests of a steam engine. For Mechanical and Chemical Engineers. (Winter.) Associate Professor Henderson and Mr. Montgomery. 691: Power Laboratory: 5 hours a week. Continuation of Course 692. Complete tests of a gasoline engine; complete tests of a steam engine; tests of a steam turbine with a study of methods of correcting to standard conditions. The Power Test Code of the American Society of Mechanical Engineers used. For Mechanical Engineers. (Fall.) Associate Professor Henderson. 692: Power Laboratory: 5 hours a week. Continuation of Course 690. Tests of an air compressor; tests of a blower; complete tests of a centrifugal pump, and other assigned tests. For Mechanical Engineers. (Spring.) Associate Professor Henderson and Mr. Montgomery. CIVIL ENGINEERING 701: Curves and Earthwork: 11:30-12:30, M. W. F. Lectures on simple circular, compound, reverse, transition and vertical curves. The form of excavations and embankments, earthwork surveys, computation of volumes, formation of enbankments, computation of haul, cost of earthwork, blasting. Practical problems covering work of lecture course. (Fall.) Professor Saunders and Mr. Donnally. 703: Highway Engineering: 11:30-12:30, M. W. F. A study of highway economics, administration, legislation and organization. The principles of highway location, surveying, mapping and design. The construction, maintenance and characteristics of earth, sand-clay, gravel, and broken stone roads. A study of bituminous materials. The construction, maintenance and characteristics of bituminous macadam, bituminous concrete, asphalt, cement-concrete, wood-block, brick and stone block pavements. Sidewalks, curbs and gutters. (Winter.) Professor Saunders. 705: Bridge Engineering: 10:30-11:30, M. W. F. A study of bridge stresses, the design and construction of selected types of steel bridges. (Winter.) Professor Saunders. 708: Water Supply: 10:30-11:30, M. W. F. A study of the elements of public water supply systems covering such topics as quality, quantity, methods of collection, conveyance, purification, and distribution of water. Text study is supplemented by the assignment of numerous problems of a practical nature. (Fall.) Professor Saunders. 709: Sewerage and Sewage Treatment: 10:30-11:30, M. W. F. A preliminary study of sewerage systems and methods of sewage treatment. This course covers estimates of sewage quantity and the design of sewage collector systems; a study of sewage disposal by dilution; and studies of sewage treatment by tank, filtration, and other standard methods. The lecture course is paralleled by the assignment of appropriate practical problems. (Spring.) Professor Saunders. 715: Materials of Construction: 11:30-12:30, T. Th. S. A descriptive study of the properties, characteristics and manufacture of the materials used in engineering structures. Problems in estimating quantities and costs. (Fall.) Associate Professor Henderson and Mr. Ellis. 718: Masonry Structures: 11:30-12:30, T. Th. S. A study of the theory of reinforced concrete design. The design and construction of selected types of masonry structures. Practical exercises in design together with structural drawing. (Spring.) Professor Saunders. 720: Structural Engineering: 9:30-10:30, M. W. F. An advanced course in the design and construction of engineering structures of steel and masonry. The student will be required to design, detail and prepare completed drawings of selected structures. (Fall.) Professor Saunders. 721: Design of Water Supply and Sewerage Systems: 9:30-10:30, M. W. F. The design, construction and operation of water supply and sewage systems. The student will be required to make complete designs and prepare all necessary plans and specifications. (Fall.) Professor Saunders. 722: Sanitary Engineering: 9:30-10:30, M. W. F. A study of water purification and sewage disposal. The design, construction and operation of water purification works, and sewage disposal plants. The student will be required to make complete designs and prepare all necessary plans and specifications. (Winter.) Professor Saunders. 723: Structural Engineering: 9:30-10:30, M. W. F. Continuation of course 720. (Winter.) Professor Saunders. 725: Civil Engineering Research: This course will be devoted to intensive study and research planned to accord with the student's individual choice of major topic of study in the graduate year. (Spring.) Professor Saunders. PRACTICE COURSES 751: Railroad Surveying: 9 hours a week. This course supplements 701, Curves and Earthwork. The class is divided into squads, each squad making complete surveys, maps, profiles, and estimates for a mile of located line. (Fall.) Professor Saunders and Mr. Donnally. 755: Bridge Drafting: 12 hours a week. This course accompanies 705, Bridges. Each student is required to make complete design and detail drawings of one plate girder and one selected type of bridge truss. (Winter.) Professor Saunders and Associate Professor Hesse. MECHANICAL ENGINEERING 800: Elementary Thermodynamics: 12:30-1:30, T. Th. S. Physical units and their measurement. Properties of the permanent gases, of steam, ammonia, and carbon dioxide. Laws of thermodynamics. Fuels and combustion. The transformation of heat into mechanical work and the production of cold. The generation of steam. (Fall.) Assistant Professor Morse and Mr. Copper. 801: Elementary Applied Thermodynamics: 12:30-1:30, T. Th. S. An introduction to the design and performance of stokers, boilers, and boiler auxiliaries, steam engines and turbines, internal combustion engines, and refrigerating plants. (Winter.) Assistant Professor Morse and Mr. Copper. 802: General Thermodynamics: 11:30-12:30, M. W. F. Energy transformations. Laws of thermodynamics. Changes of state. Entropy and availability. Thermodynamic properties of gases and vapors. Power cycles for gases and vapors. Refrigeration cycles for gases and vapors. Fluids in motion. Thermodynamics of the steam engine, steam turbine, and Diesel engine. Theory of the combustion of fuels. (Fall.) Assistant Professor Morse. 803: Power Plants: 11:30-12:30, M. W. F. Factors affecting location and design of power plants. Economics of power production. Costs and rate making. The Diesel plant. Hydro stations. Cycles and heat balances of the Rankine, regenerative, reheating, and binary vapor types of power plants. (Winter.) Assistant Professor Morse. 804: Heating, Ventilation, and Refrigeration: 10:30-11:30, M. W. F. Principles of the heating and ventilation of factories, offices, and other public buildings. Air conditioning and humidifying. The manufacture of ice and solid carbon dioxide. The storage and transportation of perishables. The production of very low temperatures. (Spring.) Professor Macconochie. 805: Steam Generators: 12:30-1:30, M. W. F. Modern boiler design and fuel burning equipment. Economic considerations governing plant location and capacity. The use of high-pressure steam. Boiler corrosion and boiler plant embrittlement. Control of smoke and dust, and ordinances pertaining thereto. By courtesy of the Virginia Public Service Company students have access to the Bremo Bluff generating station on the James River. (Fall.) Professor Macconochie. 806: Steam Turbines: 12:30-1:30, M. W. F. Types of modern steam turbines and their application to land and marine practice. The economy of the isolated station versus purchased power. Nozzle flow and results of research on the properties of steam. Opportunities will be offered for the study of industrial power plants and for keeping in touch with current development in the power field. (Winter.) Professor Macconochie. 807: Diesel Engines: 12:30-1:30, M. W. F. Design and performance of modern Diesel engines. Their application to industrial, marine, and locomotive service. Fuel injection and combustion. The gas turbine. (Spring.) Professor Macconochie. 808: Steam Power Plants: 11:30-12:30, M. W. F. Study of the steam boiler-turbine-condenser unit. Functional relationship of steam plant equipment. Heat transfer computations. Combustion and combustion equipment. Feedwater heating and treatment. Pumping problems. Selection of piping. Piping systems. Electrical equipment and layout. Instruments and meters. (Spring.) Assistant Professor Morse. 811: Machine Design: 12:30-1:30, T. Th. S. The application of basic principles to the design of simple machine elements. Toothed wheels. Screw and worm gearing. Cams. Transmission systems. (Fall.) Associate Professor Hesse. 812: Theory of Machines: 10:30-11:30, M. W. F. Kinematic chains and linkages. Simple machines. Mechanisms possessing some particular geometrical property. Higher and lower pairs. Velocities and accelerations in mechanisms. (Fall.) Professor Macconochie. 813: Metallurgy: 10:30-11:30, M. W. F. The extraction of metals from their ores, with special reference to the manufacture of iron and steel. The theory of alloys. Heat treatment of metallic bodies. Corrosion and its prevention. Measurement of temperature in industrial operations. Testing and inspection of metallurgical products. (Winter.) Professor Macconochie. 815: Elementary Mechanical Technology: Fall and Spring, 11:30-12:30, W. Winter 2:30-3:30, W. An introduction to preparatory and manipulative process. The production of castings. Machining, forging, rolling, stamping, and wire drawing. The elements of welding. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Professor Macconochie and Mr. Lucas. 820: Mechanism: 9:30-10:30, M. W. F. A study of the action and design of selected machines. (Fall.) Professor Macconochie. 821: Mechanics of Machinery: 9:30-10:30, M. W. F. Dynamics of rotating bodies. Critical speeds and vibrations. Balancing. (Winter.) Professor Macconochie. 822: Engineering and Industrial Processes: 9:30-10:30, M. W. F. A study of the technique of industrial operations as afforded by local industries, e. g., textiles, silk, furniture, velvet, electric ranges, etc. Considerations governing plant location. Community surveys. (Spring.) Professor Macconochie. 826: Industrial Management: 8:30-9:30, M. W. F. Organization and location. Layout, design and construction. Transportation. Heating and ventilation. Standardization. Fatigue. Human relations. Operation studies. Wage plans and incentives. Budgeting and purchasing. Inspection and production control. Costs. (Fall.) Professor Macconochie. 827: Industrial Management: 8:30-9:30, M. W. F. This is a continuation of 826, developing a broader emphasis in the field of industrial planning, problems of unemployment and the influence of industrial economics on the growth of social well-being. (Winter.) Professor Macconochie. 830: General Aeronautics: 10:30-1130, M. W. F. An introductory course including a brief history of the subject; a complete nomenclature and explanation of the various parts of both heavier-than-air and lighter-than-air craft; theory of flight; use of the controls; construction; stability; engine development and present design; future possibilities; civil and military aviation; Department of Commerce Rules and Regulations. (Winter.) Assistant Professor Morse. 833: Aerodynamics: 9:30-10:30, M. W. F. Aerodynamic theory involving consideration of circulatory and vortex flow. Induction and its effects. Theory of wing sections; of complete wings. Application of wing theory to multiplanes, propellers, ground effect, etc. Mechanics of airplane stability and control. (Fall.) Assistant Professor Morse. 834: Airplane Structures: 9:30-10:30, M. W. F. Typical airplane structures. Layout to satisfy assumed performance requirements. Determination of center of gravity. Preliminary performance calculations. Study of airworthiness requirements of the U. S. Department of Commerce, establishing critical loading conditions. Analysis of forces in truss structures, Design of spars, torque tubes, struts, and ties. (Winter.) Assistant Professor Morse. 835: Airplane Structures (Concluded): 9:30-10:30, M. W. F. Materials employed in construction of airplanes; their characteristics and uses. Combined stresses. Statically indeterminate structures. Fused, brazed, glued, riveted, and bolted connections. Design of fittings and joints. (Spring.) Assistant Professor Morse. 836: Airplane Design: 10:30-11:30, M. W. F. Continuation of design begun in course 834. Three-view layouts with details. Power plant selection and installation. Technique of experimental methods of checking designs. The student completes design drawing of a plane designed to give specified performance in the degree of completeness as required by the airworthiness requirements for aircraft of the U. S. Department of Commerce. (Spring.) Assistant Professor Morse. 860: Engineering Drawing: 6 hours a week. Design of simple elements of machines such as screws, bolts, nuts, keys and cottered joints, riveted joints and connections, pipes and pipe joints, shafts and shaft couplings, clutches, bearings and supports, thrust blocks, engine details. (Fall.) Associate Professor Hesse. 863: Metallography of Iron and Steel: 3 hours a week. This is a practice course involving the study of the structure of pure metals, of cast iron, wrought iron and steel. Thermal critical points, their cause and effects. Hardening and tempering. Annealing and case hardening processes. Special and alloy steels. (Winter.) Professor Macconochie. 867-868: Engineering Design: 7 hours a week. In this course the student will be offered an opportunity of preparing an original design of a machine tool, pump, or other device to required specifications. 1 hour of lecture per week will be given. (Fall and Spring.) Associate Professor Hesse. PLANT INSPECTION Senior students in Mechanical Engineering are required to make a three-day inspection trip to the Tidewater area of Virginia (or other selected region) for the purpose of visiting the Langley Memorial Aeronautical Laboratory, the Newport News Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Co., the Norfolk Navy Yard, the James River Bridge, and the Reeves Avenue Power Station. This is usually organized during the Spring Term. Professor Macconochie. ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING 900: Elements of Electrical Engineering: 11:30-12:30, M. W. F. Lectures treating fundamental principles of Electrical Engineering; basic ideas and fundamental units discussed; magnetic circuits and continuous electric currents treated in detail; electromagnetism carefully studied. Special attention is given to the physical conceptions involved, and numerous assigned problems exemplify and broaden the theoretical discussions. 3 hours per week of supervised problem work. (Fall.) Professor Rodman and Mr. L. R. Quarles. 901: Direct Current Machines: 11:30-12:30, M. W. F. Lectures on the theory, construction, characteristics, and operation of direct current generators and motors and the necessary apparatus required for the proper management and control of these machines. The principles of testing such machines are carefully discussed. Problems illustrating the methods of calculation involved in continuous current circuits and practical examples from standard engineering practice form an important part of the work. 3 hours per week of supervised problem work. (Winter.) Professor Rodman and Mr. L. R. Quarles. 902: Periodic Currents: 11:30-12:30, M. W. F. Lectures on electrostatic phenomena, variable currents, alternating currents, and alternating current circuits, both single and polyphase. A careful study is made of circuits with periodic currents and their characteristics when resistance, inductive reactance and capacity reactance are present in their various combinations. Extensive problem work is required to facilitate the treatment of simple and complex circuits. 3 hours of supervised problem work per week. (Spring.) Professor Rodman and Mr. L. R. Quarles. 903: Alternating Current Machinery: 10:30-11:30, M. W. F. Lectures on balanced and unbalanced polyphase circuits and power measurements followed by the treatment of theory, construction, characteristics, and operation of synchronous alternating current generators. The principles of testing such apparatus under various conditions of loading are discussed, and assigned problem work illustrates the theory and practice. 3 hours per week of supervised problem work. (Fall.) Professor Rodman and Mr. L. R. Quarles. 904: Alternating Current Machinery: 10:30-11:30, M. W. F. This course is a continuation of 903. The lectures treat more particularly transformers, synchronous motors and parallel operation of alternating current generators. Methods of testing are outlined and graphical methods of calculation and predetermination of operating characteristics are discussed. Problems taken from engineering practice serve to broaden and fix the theoretical deductions. 3 hours per week of supervised problem work. (Winter.) Professor Rodman and Mr. L. R. Quarles. 905: Alternating Current Machinery: 10:30-11:30, M. W. F. This course is a continuation of 903-4. Lectures deal with the theory, construction and operation of rotary converters, induction, series, and repulsion motors. Problems are solved to clarify the theory. 3 hours of supervised problem work per week. (Spring.) Professor Rodman and Mr. L. R. Quarles. 906: Illumination and Photometry: 9:30-10:30, T. Th. S. Lectures on light, its physical properties; illuminants and their characteristics; shades and reflectors; photometry, standards and apparatus; illumination calculations for point and surface sources; principles of interior, exterior, decorative, and scenic illumination. Problems illustrating computations necessary for the consideration of the Illuminating Engineer are assigned. (Winter.) Optional for Electronics (920), or Electric Traction (907), only one given in any year. Professor Rodman. 907: Electric Traction: 9:30-10:30, T. Th. S. Lectures on the various types of electric motors for traction purposes, controllers and systems of control, brakes, rolling stock, track, train performance, and electric railway economics. A discussion with problems of the complete electrification system for electric railways, including generating apparatus, transmission, sub-stations and equipment, distribution, and utilization of electrical energy for car propulsion. (Winter.) Optional for Electronics (920), or Illumination and Photometry (906-956), only one given in any year. Professor Rodman. 910: Direct Current Systems: 10:30-11:30, T. Th. S. Lectures dealing with the fundamentals of electrical circuits and direct current machinery. Problem work accompanies the lectures. The course is essentially for the non-electrical engineering students. (Fall.) Professor Rodman and Mr. L. R. Quarles. 911: Alternating Current Systems: 10:30-11:30, T. Th. S. Lectures covering the fundamentals of alternating current circuits and machinery. Brief expositions of the subjects of electric lighting and power fundamentals. For non-electrical engineering students. (Winter.) Professor Rodman and Mr. L. R. Quarles. 916-917-918: Advanced Alternating Current Machinery: 11:30-12:30, T. Th. S. A more detailed study of advanced character dealing with alternating current machinery under abnormal conditions of service with attention to the more refined problems involved. Optional for Electric Communication (940-941-942), only one given in any year. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Professor Rodman. 920: Electronics: 9:30-10:30, T. Th. S. A course of lectures dealing with the general subject of electronics, its developments and applications. (Winter.) Optional for Illumination and Photometry (906-956), or Electric Traction (907), only one given in any year. Professor Rodman. 925: Electric Transients: 9:30-10:30, T. Th. S. A course dealing with transients as they are encountered in varied electric circuits with both lumped and distributed constants; an introduction to the operational method as applied to electrical circuit theory. (Fall.) Associate Professor Miller. 930-931-932: Electric Power Transmission: 10:30-11:30, T. Th. S. A study of the problems involved in modern electric power transmission. Treating the inductance and capacity of lines, aerial and underground; corona; steady state solutions for short and long lines; consideration of stability power limits and factors entering into the operation of complete power systems. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Associate Professor Miller. 940-941-942: Electrical Communication: 11:30-12:30, T. Th. S. A course dealing with the general subject of electrical communication of intelligence by wire and wireless telegraph and telephone with emphasis on the theoretical details of the subject. Treatment of the various mechanisms and circuits utilized with particular reference to the vacuum tube engineering. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Optional with Advanced A. C. Machinery (916-917-918), only one given in any year. Professor Rodman. LABORATORY COURSES 950-951: Direct Current Laboratory: 5 hours a week. This course supplements 900-1. The laboratory work is devoted to a study of electrical instruments, their use and manipulation; simple electrical circuits and study of direct current apparatus and its operation; characteristics of generators and motors. (Winter, Spring.) Associate Professor Miller and Mr. G. K. Carter. 953-954-955: Alternating Current Laboratory: 5 hours a week. This course supplements 902-3-4-5, dealing with measuring instruments for alternating current circuits; series and parallel circuits and their characteristics; polyphase circuits, balanced and unbalanced; and alternating current generator, motor and transformer characteristics. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Associate Professor Miller and Mr. G. K. Carter. 956: Photometric Laboratory: 2 hours a week. This course accompanies 906. Photometric tests are made upon different types of incandescent lamps. The operating characteristics of incandescent and arc lamps are studied. Tests of illmuination, interior and exterior, are carried out. Study of photometric standards and devices. (Winter.) Associate Professor Miller. 960-961: Electrical Laboratory: 5 hours a week. This course supplements 910-11. The work of the first term is devoted to direct current tests; the second term exercises are on alternating current circuits and machines. (Winter, Spring.) Associate Professor Miller and Mr. G. K. Carter. 966-967-968: Advanced Electrical Machinery Laboratory: 4 hours a week. This course supplements 916-17-18. Special tests are carried out with emphasis upon original work by the student. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Professor Rodman and Associate Professor Miller. 975: Transient Laboratory: 4 hours a week. A course supplementing 925. It deals largely with oscillographic study of illustrative transient circuit phenomena of varied types. (Fall.) Associate Professor Miller. 980-981: Electrical Power Transmission Laboratory: 4 hours a week. A course supplementing 930-1-2 and dealing with certain phenomena encountered in transmission circuits as they may be subjected to test on artificial lines. (Winter, Spring.) Associate Professor Miller. 990-991-992: Electrical Communication Laboratory: 4 hours a week. A course supplementing 940-1-2 and devoted to various special tests of communication circuits and apparatus. (Fall, Winter, Spring.) Professor Rodman and Associate Professor Miller. SUMMER SCHOOL In the Summer School at the University of Virginia it has been possible for some time to procure many of the non-technical courses required in the engineering curricula, such as Chemistry, Physics, Commercial Law, Economics and the Modern Languages. In the Summer School of 1935 there will be given the following courses as they are given in the regular session: Mathematics 100-106-107 and 108-109-110 with 158-159-160. In addition at least two courses in Mechanics will again be offered from the three 526, 527 and 528. If there be a sufficient demand Mechanical Drawing, 522-572, and Descriptive Geometry, 523573, will be given. ENGINEERING CURRICULA, 1935-1936 Freshman All courses Sophomore All except Chemical Sophomore Chemical * * Starred courses involve laboratory work or quiz or supervised problem work. L. F.—Laboratory Fees. English 1-2-3 * Calculus 108-9-10 * Calculus 108-9-10 * Math. 100-106-107 * Physics 200-1-2 * Physics 200-1-2 * Chem. 300-1-2 Engrg. 800-801-526 or * Org. Chem. 312-13-14 * Ap. Math. 521-2-3 Engrg. 811 with 860-830-526 (for M. E. only) * Qual. Anal. 315-16-17 * Field-work 571 El. Mech. Tech. 815 Com. Law. 13-14-15 or Govt. 16-17-18 or Hist. 31-32-33 L. F. $45 L. F. $15 for M. E. $20 L. F. $40 Junior Senior Graduate Chemical * Org. Chem. 309-10-11 Chem. Engrg. 324-5-6 Cost. Acct. 21-2-3 * Phys. Chem. 321-22-23 * Org. Chem. 309-10-11 Ad. Chem. Engrg. 327-8-9 German 43-4-5 * Elec. Sys. 910-11 Ap. Chem. 340-1-2 Engrg. 800-801-526 Ap. Math. 715-x-529 Engrg. Econs. and Spec. 26 * Exp. Engrg. 690-680 Elective 34-5-6 * Design 581 * Chem. Engrg. Research 386-7-8 L. F. $50 L. F. $50 L. F. $25 Civil Business Speaking 7-8-9 Cost. Acct. 21-2-3 * Eng. Geol. 400-1-2 Ap. Math. 527-* 4-* 5 Ap. Math. 715-528-x * Elec. Sys. 910-11 C. E. 701-3-529 * Exp. Engrg. 662-3-80 Engrg. Econs. and Spec. 26 * Exp. Engrg. 650 C. E. 708-9-5-18 Elective 34-5-6 Econs. 10-11-12 or * Bridge Drafting 755 Option: C. E. 720-23 or Mod. Lang. 40-1-2 C. E. 721-22 Ry. Field-work 751 C. E. Research 725 L. F. $25 L. F. $25 L. F. $15 Electrical Business Speaking7-8-9 Cost. Acct. 21-2-3 E. E. * 930-1-2 Ap. Math. 527-* 4-* 30 Ap. Math. 715-528-529 Option: E. E. * 906 E. E. 900-1-2 * Exp. Engrg. 670-61-80 or 920 or 907 Math. 111 * E. E. 903-4-5 Engrg. Econs. and Spec. 26 * E. E. Lab. 950-1 * E. E. Lab. 953-4-5 * E. E. 925 Econs. 10-11-12 or Options: * E. E. 916-17-18 Mod. Lang. 40-1-2 or * E. E. 940-1-2 Elective 34-5-6 L. F. $20 L. F. $30 L. F. $30 Mechanical Business Speaking 7-8-9 Aeronautics 833-4-5 or M. E. 805-6-7 * Ap. Math. 527-* 4-* 5 Cost Acct. 21-2-3 M. E. 820-21-22 M. E. 802-3-8 Ap. Math. 715-528-529 M. E. 826-27 * Exp. Engrg. 670-690-92 Exp. Engrg. 691-61-80 Engrg. Econs. and Spec. 26 Econs. 10-11-12 or M. E. 812-* 13-4 or 836 Elective 34-5-6 Mod. Lang. 40-1-2 or * Elec. Sys. 910-11 Cost Acct. 21-2-3 * M. E. Design 867-8 L. F. $25 L. F. $40 L. F. $00 SCHEDULE OF FOUR-YEAR COURSES, 1935-1936 LABORATORY C—lectures per wk. S-H—session hours. L—hrs. of practice per wk. C L S-H M. W. F. T. Th. S. Freshman English (1-2-3) 3 3 4½ 12:30-1:30 2:30-5:30, M. Math. (100-106-107) 3 3 4½ 9:30-10:30 8:30-9:30, T. Th. S. Gen. Chem. (300-301-302) 3 6 6 10:30-11:30 11:30-1:30, T. Th. S. Ap. Math. (521-522-523) 3 6 6 10:30-11.30 8:30-10:30, M. W. F. El. Mech. Technology (815) F. W. S. 1 1 11:30-12:30, W. (Fall-Spring) Field-work (571) 6 h. a w. Fall or Spring Sophomore Com. Law (13-14-15) or Govt. (16-17-18) 3 3 11:30 or 9:30 or History (31-32-33) 3 3 11:30-12:30 Math. (108-109-110) 3 6 6 11:30-12:30 2:30-5:30, W. F. Phys. (200-201-202) 3 6 6 9:30-10:30 9:30-11:30, T. Th. S. Organic Chem. (312-313-314) 3 3 4½ 11:30-12:30 2:30-5:30, M. Qual. Anal. (315-316-317) 2 3 3 8:30-9:30, T. Th. 2:30-5:30, T. or Th. Engrg. (800-801-526) 3 4 12:30-1:30 Engrg. (811-830-x) 3 2 10:30-11:30, Winter 12:30-1:30, Fall Engrg. (860-x-x) 6 1 6 h. a w. Fall. Junior Business Speaking (7-8-9) 3 3 9:30-10:30 Econs. (10-11-12) or 3 3 10:30-11:30 Mod. Lang. (40-41-42) M. T. W. Th. F. 5 3 8:30-9:30 or 8:30-9:30 or 9:30-10:30 9:30-10:30 German (43-44-45) 3 3 10:30-11:30 Math. (111) Fall 3 1 11:30-12:30 Org. Chem. (309-310-311) 3 6 6 10:30-11:30 2:30-5:30, W. F. Phys. Chem. (321-322-323) 3 6 6 12:30-1:30 2:30-5:30, T. Th. Ap. Math. (527-524-525 or 530) 3 6 6 10:30-11:30 11:30-1:30, T. Th. S. Winter and Spring Ap. Math. (x-x-529) 3 2 11:30-12:30 Civil Engineering (701-703-x) 3 2 11:30-12:30 Mech. Engrg. (802-803-808) 3 3 11:30-12:30 Elec. Engrg. (900-901-902) 3 3 4½ 11:30-12:30 2:30-5:30, T. Exp. Engrg. (650) 6 1 6 h. a w. Winter Exp. Engrg. (691-690-692) 1 4 3 9:30, Th. or 12:30 Th. 2:30-6:30, M. or W. Elec. Lab. (950-951) 1 4 2 9:30-10:30 2:30-6:30, M. or W. or Th. Winter &amp; Spring Ry. Field-work (751) 9 1½ 9 h. a w. Fall. Senior Cost Accounting (21-22-23) 3 3 9:30-10:30 Org. Chem. (309-310-311) 3 6 6 10:30-11:30 2:30-5:30, W. F. Chem. Engrg. (324-325-326) 3 3 9:30-10:30 Ap. Math. (715-528-529) 3 6 11:30-12:30 Civil Engrg. (708-705-709) 3 6 5 10:30-11:30 6 h. a w. Fall and Spring Civil Engrg. (x-x-718) 3 6 2 11:30-12:30 6 h. a w. Spring Mech. Engrg. (812-813-804) 3 3 10:30-11:30 Mech. Engrg. (833-834-835) 3 3 9:30-10:30 Mech. Engrg. (x-x-836) 3 1 10:30-11:30 Elec. Engrg. (903-904-905) 3 3 4½ 10:30-11:30 2:30-5:30, Th. Elec. Engrg. (910-911) 3 2 10:30-11:30 Engrg. Design (581-x-x) 1 6 1 6 h. a w. Fall Exp. Engrg. (662-663) 1 4 2 9:30-11:30, T. 2:30-6:30, T. or Th. or F. Exp. Engrg. (670-661-680) 1 4 3 12:30, Th. or 9:30, S.-Th. 2:30-6:30, T. or Th. or F. 12 h. a w. Winter Bridge Draw. (755) 12 2 3 h. a w. Winter Met. Lab. (x-863-x) 3 ½ 6 h. a w. Fall and Spring Engrg. Design (867-x-868) 1 6 2 2:30-6:30, M. or W. or F. Elec. Lab. (953-954-955) 1 4 3 11:30-12:30, W. 2:30-6-30, M. or W. or F. 1 4 2 9:30-10:30, T. Winter and Spring 1935-1936 CURRICULUM IN CHEMICAL ENGINEERING Humanities Mathematics and Science Technical Engineering Freshman English: Mathematics: Plane Surveying Rhetoric and Composition Trigonometry Mechanical Drawing Reports and Letter Writing Analytical Geometry and Descriptive Geometry College Algebra El. Mech. Technology Technical Papers Chemistry Drawing Laboratory Field-work Sophomore Mathematics: Differential and Integral Calculus Physics Organic Chemistry Qualitative Analysis Mathematics Laboratory Junior Organic Chemistry Elementary Thermo. German Physical Chemistry Elem. Ap. Thermo. Elementary Mechanics Senior Organic Chemistry Materials of Construction Engrg. Design Electric Systems Hydraulics Chemical Engineering Principles Hydraulics Laboratory Power Testing Degree of B. S. in Engineering on completion of Four-Year Course. Graduate Cost Accounting Applied Chemistry Engineering Economics and Specifications Elective: Philosophy Chemical Engineering Research or Architecture or Fine Arts Ad. Chemical Engineering or other subject approved by the Faculty of Engineering Degree of Ch. E. on completion of the additional Graduate Course. Practice courses are printed in Italics; courses with combined lectures and laboratory work in Black Face Type. 1935-1936 CURRICULUM IN CIVIL ENGINEERING Humanities Mathematics and Science Technical Engineering Freshman English: Mathematics: Plane Surveying Rhetoric and Composition Trigonometry Mechanical Drawing Reports and Letter Writing Analytical Geometry and Descriptive Geometry College Algebra El. Mech. Technology Technical Papers Chemistry Drawing Laboratory Field-work Sophomore Options: Mathematics Elementary Thermo. History Differential and Elem. Ap. Thermo. or Government Integral Calculus Elementary Mechanics or Commercial Law Physics Mathematics Laboratory Junior Business Speaking Applied Mechanics Curves and Earthwork Options: Graphical Statics Highways Economics Structural Drawing Road Materials Tests or Modern Language Hydraulics Railway Surveying Drawing Laboratory Senior Cost Accounting Strength of Materials Materials of Construction Mechanics Laboratory Masonry Bridges Water Supply and Sewerage Bridge Drafting Degree of B. S. in Engineering on completion of Four-Year Course. Graduate Elective: Engineering Geology Engineering Economics and Specifications Philosophy or Architecture Option: or Fine Arts Advanced Structural Engineering or other subject approved by the or Advanced Water Supply and Sewerage Faculty of Engineering Electric Systems C. E. Research Degree of C. E. on completion of additional Graduate Course. Practice courses are printed in Italics; courses with combined lecture and laboratory work in Black Face Type. 1935-1936 CURRICULUM IN ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING Humanities Mathematics and Science Technical Engineering Freshman English: Mathematics: Plane Surveying Rhetoric and Composition Trigonometry Mechanical Drawing Reports and Letter Writing Analytical Geometry and Descriptive Geometry College Algebra El. Mech. Technology Technical Papers Chemistry Drawing Laboratory Field-work Sophomore Options: Mathematics: Elementary Thermo. History Differential and Elem. Ap. Thermo. or Government Integral Calculus Elementary Mechanics or Commercial Law Physics Mathematics Laboratory Junior Business Speaking Mathematics: Elements of Electricity Option: Differential Equations Direct Cur. Machinery Economics Applied Mechanics Periodic Currents or Modern Language Graphical Statics Machine Design Drawing Laboratory Electrical Laboratory Supervised Problem Work Senior Cost Accounting Hydraulics Materials of Construction Strength of Materials Alternating Current Machinery Mechanics Laboratory Electrical Laboratory Supervised Problem Work Degree of B. S. in Engineering on completion of Four-Year Course. Graduate Elective: Electric Power Philosophy Engineering Economics and Specifications or Architecture or Fine Arts Electric Transients or other subject Option: approved by the Illumination and Photometry Faculty of Engineering or Electronics or Electric Traction Option: Adv. Alternating Current Machinery or Electrical Communication Degree of E. E. on completion of the additional Graduate Course. Practice courses are printed in Italics; courses with combined lecture and lavoratory work in Black Face Type. 1935-1936 CURRICULUM IN MECHANICAL ENGINEERING Option A—Power; Option B—Aeronautics Humanities Mathematics and Science Technical Engineering Freshman English: Mathematics: Plane Surveying Rhetoric and Composition Trigonometry Mechanical Drawing Reports and Letter Writing Analytical Geometry and Descriptive Geometry College Algebra El. Mech. Technology Technical Papers Chemistry Drawing Laboratory Field-work Sophomore Options: Mathematics: Machine Design History Differential and General Aeronautics or Government Integral Calculus Elementary Mechanics or Commercial Law Physics Engineering Drawing Mathematical Laboratory Junior Business Speaking Applied Mechanics General Thermodynamics Option: Graphical Statics Power Plants Economics Structural Drawing Steam Power Plants or Modern Language Mechanics Laboratory Power Testing Drawing Laboratory Senior Cost Accounting* * Taken in Junior year instead of Economics by those choosing B-option. Hydraulics Materials of Construction Strength of Materials Theory of Machines Mechanics Laboratory Metallography of Iron and Steel Aerodynamics ((B-option) Airplane Design (B-option) Heating, Ventilation and Refrigeration (A-option) Airplane Structures (B-option) Power Testing Electric Systems Engineering Design Degree of B. S. in Engineering on completion of Four-Year Course. Graduate Elective Steam Generators, Turbines and Diesel Engines Philosophy or Architecture Mechanism, Mechanics of Machinery and Engrg. and Industrial Processes or Fine Arts or other subject approved by the Industrial Management Faculty of Engineering Economics Engineering Degree of M. E. on completion of the additional Graduate Course. Practice courses are printed in Italics; courses with combined and laboratory work in Black Face Type. LECTURE HOURS AND EXAMINATION DAYS, 1935-36 MONDAY, WEDNESDAY, FRIDAY TUESDAY, THURSDAY, SATURDAY Exam. Day Lecture Hour Exam. Day Fall Winter Spring Fall Winter Spring II IX II 8:30 to 9:30 Anal. Chemistry (315-316-317) VII II IV V VI VIII Cost Accounting (21-22-23) 9:30 to 10:30 Business Speaking (7-8-9) VIII III V Physics (200-201-202) Mathematics (100-106-107) Chem. Engineering (324-325-326) Mech. Engineering (833-834-835) I X I Economics (10-11-12) 10:30 to 11:30 X V VII Organic Chemistry (309-310-311) General Chemistry (300-301-302) Applied Mathematics (521-522-523) Applied Mathematics (527-524-525-530) Civil Engineering (708-705-709) Mech. Engineering ( 812-813-804) Elec. Engineering (910-911-x) Mech. Engineering (x-830-836) Elec. Engineering (903-904-905) III VIII X 11:30 to 12:30 Commercial Law (13-14-15) VI I III Mathematics (108-109-110) Mathematics (111-x-x) Civil Engineering (701-703-x) Organic Chemistry (312-313-314) Mech. Engineering (802-803-808) Civil Engineering (715-528-529) Elec. Engineering (900-901-902) Civil Engineering (x-x-718) IV VII IX English (1-2-3) 12:30 to 1:30 Engineering (800-801-526) IX IV VI Physical Chemistry (321-322-323) Mech. Engineering (811-x-x) The examination days for the various classes are fixed by the hour of regular lecture period. The examination day for a particular course is indicated in the table above by the Roman numeral in the first or last columns, for the corresponding lecture hours in the middle column. The examination period covers ten days at the end of each term. Examination days change each term. A change in lecture for any course will change the examination day correspondingly. Classes for which lecture periods are not indicated will have examination days fixed by the arranged lecture hour in accordance with above schedule. Laboratory examinations are arranged to suit classes. RECIPIENTS OF DEGREES, DEPARTMENT OF ENGINEERING JUNE 12, 1934 Bachelors of Science in Engineering Allen, Francis Leonard Fairfield, Va. Cadot, Henry Meade Richmond, Va. Carson, James Samuel Perryville, Md. Carter, Gordon Keith University, Va. Conn, Ellis Newport News, Va. Doswell, Stonewall Jackson, Jr. Staunton, Va. Ellis, Earl Thayer University, Va. Follin, Ernest Randolph, Jr. Clarendon, Va. Garrett, Benjamin Hipple Jetersville, Va. Glunt, John Spencer Pedlar Mills, Va. Goldberg, Milton Chauncey Portsmouth, Va. Grady, James Arthur, Jr. Pueblo, Colo. Halstead, Woodrow Jennings Buell, Va. Hammond, Harry Martin Winchester, Va. Hancock, John Beverly, Jr. Richmond, Va. Harper, Holmes Douglas Winchester, Va. Kinney, Theodore Simonson Hasbrouck Heights, N. J. Mizroch, Jacob Norfolk, Va. Nelson, William Seddon Cabell Winchester, Va. O'Brien, Edwin Morrow Ridley Park, Penna. Page, John Ruffner Fort Monroe, Va. Palmer, Aubrey Edwin Crystal Hill, Va. Pike, Frederick Philips Washington, D. C. Price, William Keyser, Jr. New Market, Va. Robinson, John Hunter Cismont, Va. Rosenberger, Richard Coe Winchester, Va. Ross, William Tyler Roanoke, Va. Savage, Seth Alonzo, Jr. Portsmouth, Va. Semones, Charles Howard Indian Valley, Va. Smiley, Samuel Dixon Charleston, W. Va. Watkins, Joel Hill, Jr. Charlotte C. H., Va. Werkman, Kenneth Shaner Yeadon, Penna. Chemical Engineers Lewis, Hunter Fielding, Jr. B.S.E., University of Virginia Richmond, Va. Williams, John Randolph, B.S.E., University of Virginia Richmond, Va. Civil Engineer Palmer, Aubrey Edwin, B.S.E. (1934), University of Virginia Crystal Hill, Va. Electrical Engineers Conn, Ellis, B.S.E. (1934), University of Virginia Newport News, Va. Stahl, Chester Earl, B.S.E., University of Virginia Charlottesville, Va. Mechanical Engineers Edwards, Tazewell Wayne, Jr., B.S.E., University of Virginia Charlottesville, Va. Miller, Luther Samuel, B.S.E., University of Virginia Charlottesville, Va. Robinson, John Hunter, B.S.E. (1934), University of Virginia Cismont, Va. SUMMARY OF DEGREES IN ENGINEERING, JUNE, 1934 Bachelors of Science in Engineering 32 Chemical Engineers 2 Civil Engineer 1 Electrical Engineers 2 Mechanical Engineers 3 Total 40 DEAN'S LIST OF DISTINGUISHED STUDENTS, DEPARTMENT OF ENGINEERING, ENTIRE SESSION 1933-34 Babb, Andrew Bird Winchester, Va. Ballard, Leonard William, Jr. Charlottesville, Va. Carter, Gordon Keith University, Va. Conn, Ellis Newport News, Va. Daniel, Henry Blount Charlottesville, Va. Edwards, Howard Berryman Sweet Briar, Va. Edwards, Tazewell Wayne, Jr. Charlottesville, Va. Follin, Ernest Randolph, Jr. Clarendon, Va. Grady, James Arthur, Jr. Pueblo, Colo. Irvine, William Milligan, Jr. Culpeper, Va. Miller, Luther Samuel Charlottesville, Va. Palmer, Aubrey Edwin Crystal Hill, Va. Payne, William Walker Boyds, Md. Robinson, John Hunter Cismont, Va. Rutherfoord, John Penn Roanoke, Va. Watkins, Joel Hill, Jr. Charlotte C. H., Va. Williams, John Randolph Richmond, Va. Total, 17. REGISTER OF STUDENTS, DEPARTMENT OF ENGINEERING Freshman Class Arundale, Alfred Garner Charlottesville, Va. Benham, Arthur William, Jr. Pottstown, Penna. Bennett, John Rutherfoord, Jr. Charleston, S. C. Bolongaro, Denis James Charlottesville, Va. Brown, George Kenneth Cherrydale, Va. Burhans, George Albert, Jr. Locust Valley, N. Y. Calhoun, John Thompson Charlottesville, Va. Condon, David Edward Goshen, Va. Cowgill, Harry Bramell, Jr. Paulsboro, N. J. Davison, John Franklin Miller Pittsburgh, Penna. Dorrier, William Addison Waynesboro, Va. Faulkner, William Harrison, Jr. University, Va. Garnand, Ambrose Lane Rogers, Va. Gray, Walter Winfred St. Paul, Va. Hansbrough, Samuel Scott Winchester, Va. Hart, John Greenlee Woodridge, Va. Hawkins, Eugene Gaines Washington, D. C. Jones, Louis DuBriel New Canton, Va. Jordan, Ralph Curtis, Jr. Columbus, Ga. Keith, Joseph Cline Roanoke, Va. Laidlaw, Henry Bell Plainfield, N. J. Langhorne, Harry Forsyth Warren, Va. Lapsley, James Woods, Jr. Miller School, Va. Lewis, Ivey Foreman, Jr. University, Va. Lyon, Matthew Charlottesville, Va. Martin, Earl Moseley Richmond, Va. Mason, Edward Valentine Charlottesville, Va. Massey, Alfred Hubard McLean, Va. Molten, Robert Potter, Jr. Newport, R. I. Munson, Harlan Peirce Westfield, N. Y. Nea, George Andrew Brighton, Mass. Novey, George Francis, Jr. Panama, R. P. Oliver, William Roland North Garden, Va. Oliverio, John Clarksburg, W. Va. Olsen, Lloyd Thomas West Hempstead, N. Y. Pack, Emmett Erastus, Jr. Hinton, W. Va. Quarles, Vernon Charlottesville, Va. Railey, Merritt Maupin, Jr., B.S., University of Virginia University, Va. Sargeant, James Franklin, Jr. University, Va. Shell, Charles Clemon, Jr., B.A., University of Alabama Brookside, Ala. Sherwood, Albert Maurice Fairfax, Va. Simpson, John Parke, Jr. Washington, D. C. Smith, James Warfield Richmond, Va. Smith, Sandy Charlottesville, Va. Snead, Ellis Pollard, Jr. Scottsville, Va. Spalding, Basil Dennis, Jr. Richmond, Va. Talbot, Richmond dePeyster New York, N. Y. Townes, William Armistead, Jr. Wilmington, N. C. Tucker, James Warnock Richmond, Va. Via, Charles William, Jr. Waynesboro, Va. Wade, Clement Manly, Jr. Charlottesville, Va. Waxelbaum, Sidney Brooklyn, N. Y. Weaver, James Albert, Jr. Remington, Va. Wheeler, Henry Garth Charlottesville, Va. Wiebel, James Lee University, Va. Wright, Ernest Brinton, Jr. Newark, Del. Zepp, Allen Lewis Lansdowne, Penna. Sophomore Class Adams, John Quincy Greenport, N. Y. Armentrout, Edwin Lee Goshen, Va. Batten, Earl Wilson Carters Bridge, Va. Bayless, Charles Nield Shelbyville, Ky. Black, Junie Almy Churchland, Va. Britton, William Ralph Charlottesville, Va. Brown, Jury Yates, Jr. Charlottesville, Va. Caldwell, William Everett, Jr. Washington, D. C. Carrick, Robert Craig Richmond, Va. Carruthers, William Benjamin North Fork, Va. Cowgill, Joseph Moreland Paulsboro, N. J. duPont, Francis George Montchanin, Del. Ehrich, Louis Siegman, Jr. New Rochelle, N. Y. Ferrer, Peter, Jr. New York, N. Y. Fitzhugh, Donald Lewis Charlottesville, Va. Fitzpatrick, Paul William Washington, D. C. Forsyth, George William Esmont, Va. Franke, Walter Royden Brookings, S. D. Gilbert, Chauncey McLean, Jr. Charlottesville, Va. Gilcrist, Barth John Newburgh, N. Y. Glenn, John Forsyth Cobb Ivy Depot, Va. Gordon, Nicholas Thouron Merion, Penna. Herz, Martin Seymour Chicago, Ill. Hurt, Percy Fuqua Marion, Va. Jones, Archer LeBaron Hampton, Va. Kasakoff, Harry University, Va. Landis, Herbert Joseph, Jr. Belleville, N. J. McGaughy, John Bell Virginia Beach, Va. Mizroch, Aaron Norfolk, Va. Roberts, John Merritt Charlottesville, Va. Rucker, John Tinsley, Jr. Lynchburg, Va. Somerville, Henry Brooke Richmond, Va. Stocker, Jesse Jones Hampton, Va. Swing, David Jackson Charlottesville, Va. von Tacky, Richard Lewis Titusville, Penna. Whitcomb, John Gray Orange, N. J. Williams, James Simons San Diego, Calif. Junior Class Adams, James Richard Lynchburg, Va. Armistead, John Grant, Jr. Richmond, Va. Armstrong, Charles Glasgow Charlottesville, Va. Beachley, Elmer Taylor Williamsport, Md. Carter, Walter Scott Charlottesville, Va. Clark, Morris Skinner, Jr. Charlottesville, Va. Copper, Robert Gamble Lyndhurst, Va. Daniel, Henry Blount Charlottesville, Va. Daniel, Richard Micou Alexandria, Va. Dill, Joseph Ellis, B. S., Davidson College Buchanan, Va. Donnally, Hugh Edward Charlottesville, Va. Edwards, Howard Berryman Sweet Briar, Va. Fall, James Huey, Jr. Greenville, Va. Irvine, Williams Milligan, Jr. Culpeper, Va. Janos, Angelus Alexander Hinton, W. Va. McIlhenny, John Stauffer, B.S.Chem., University of Virginia Charlottesville, Va. Maupin, Herman Rea Charlottesville, Va. Poindexter, William Green, Jr. Morgan City, Miss. Porter, George Jones Norfolk, Va. Priestman, George Dawson Elizabeth, N. J. Reese, Eben Bent Wilmington, Del. Rutherfoord, John Penn Roanoke, Va. Starke, Vincent William Crozet, Va. Starke, William Wallace, Jr. Norfolk, Va. Stipe, James Leslie Stephenson, Va. Wattles, Henry Starr, III Alexandria, Va. White, George Frederic, Jr. Richmond, Va. Winston, Lucien Dade, III Winston, Va. Senior Class Babb, Andrew Bird Winchester, Va. Ballard, Leonard William, Jr. Charlottesville, Va. Belmore, Edward Arthur Schuyler, Va. Bress, Lewis Alfred Norfolk, Va. Browder, Francis Elton Lawrenceville, Va. Davis, Howard Roper Norfolk, Va. Davis, William Lee, Jr. Portsmouth, Va. Dudley, Aldrich, Jr. Alexandria, Va. George, Joseph Myron Catlett, Va. Hahn, Charles Archie, Jr. University, Va. Kennedy, William Paca Charles Town, W. Va. Liady, Fred Gardner, Jr. Charlottesville, Va. Lucas, John Wilson Petersburg, Va. McGhee, John Curran Alexandria, Va. McNaught, John Moses Portsmouth, Va. Montgomery, Colin Tassie Warrenton, Va. Paterson, Roy Mackenzie Newport News, Va. Payne, William Walker Boyds, Md. Watkins, Benjamin Franklin Richmond, Va. POST GRADUATES Cadot, Henry Meade, B.S.E., University of Virginia Richmond, Va. Carter, Gordon Keith, B.S.E., University of Virginia University, Va. Ellis, Earl Thayer, B.S.E., University of Virginia University, Va. SUMMARY BY CLASSES Freshmen 57 Sophomores 37 Juniors 28 Seniors 19 Post-Graduates 3 Total 144 SUMMARY BY STATES Alabama 1 California 1 Delaware 3 District of Columbia 4 Georgia 1 Illinois 1 Kentucky 1 Maryland 2 Massachusetts 1 Mississippi 1 New Jersey 6 New York 9 North Carolina 1 Pennsylvania 5 Rhode Island 1 South Carolina 1 South Dakota 1 Virginia 99 West Virginia 4 Foreign: Panama 1 Total 144</field>
   </doc>
</add>