<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university of virginia</field>
      <field name="author_text">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1910's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2005_Q2_1/uvaBook/tei/z000000238.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240342</field>
      <field name="date_text">April 15, 1916</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:113657</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The University of Virginia record. New Series Vol. II, No. 8, April 15, 1916</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">University of Virginia -- Periodicals</field>
      <field name="subject_text">University of Virginia -- Periodicals</field>
      <field name="title_display">The University of Virginia record.  New Series Vol. II, No. 8, April 15, 1916</field>
      <field name="title_facet">university of virginia record</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">university of virginia record</field>
      <field name="title_text">The University of Virginia record.  New Series Vol. II, No. 8, April 15, 1916</field>
      <field name="year_display">April 15, 1916</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1916-04-15</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1916</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:113657&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:113657&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;serial volume&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;university of virginia&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The University of Virginia record. New Series Vol. II, No. 8, April 15, 1916&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;university of virginia record&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;April 15, 1916&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1916-04-15&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The University of Virginia record&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="volume"&gt;New Series Vol. II&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="issue"&gt;No. 8&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;April 15, 1916&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Va.&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="LC call number"&gt;LD5667 .A43&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa call number"&gt;LD5667.2&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;X001597562&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;o07560180&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;37 p. ; 23 cm.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;University of Virginia -- Periodicals&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The University of Virginia Record&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="volume"&gt;New Series, 2&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="issue"&gt;8&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1916-04-15&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2005&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2005 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 131 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PUBLICATIONS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. The University of Virginia Record: No. 1, January 1: Catalogue of the Department of Medicine. No. 2, January 15: Preliminary Summer School Announcement. No. 3, February 1: General Catalogue. No. 4, February 15: Catalogue of the Department of Law. No. 5, March 1: Catalogue of the Department of Engineering. No. 6, March 15: Catalogue of the Summer School. No. 7, April 1: Circular of Information. No. 8, April 15: Catalogue of the Department of Graduate Studies. No. 9, July 1: Courses Passed and Degrees Conferred. The University of Virginia Record, Extension Series, published ten times a year. The Alumni Bulletin of The University of Virginia, published five times a year: October 1, January 1, April 1, July 1, August 1. The Alumni News, published by the Alumni Association twenty times a year, appearing bi-weekly throughout the session. The Virginia High School Bulletin, published quarterly, in November, February, May and August. Proceedings of the Philosophical Society, published annually. Transactions of the Philosophical Society, published at intervals during the session. Bulletin of The University of Virginia Library, published at intervals during the session.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA RECORD New Series, Vol. II, No. 8 April 15, 1916 DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES CATALOGUE 1915-1916 Entered as Second-Class Matter September 28, 1914, at the Post-office at Charlottesville, Virginia under the Act of August 24, 1912</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE ACADEMIC FACULTY. THE ACADEMIC FACULTY. Edwin Anderson Alderman, Ph.B., D.C.L., LL.D. President James Morris Page, M.A., Ph.D., LL. D. Dean Francis Henry Smith, M.A., D.C.L., LL.D. West Lawn Emeritus Professor of Natural Philosophy. William Wynn Thornton, B.A., LL.D. Monroe Hill Professor of Applied Mathematics. Francis Perry Dunnington, B.S., C.E., M.E. University Heights Professor of Analytical and Industrial Chemistry. Charles William Kent, M.A., Ph.D., LL.D., Litt.D. West Lawn Linden Kent Memorial Professor of English Literature. William Holding Echols, B.S., C.E. East Lawn Professor of Mathematics. Richard Heath Dabney, M.A., Ph.D. Rugby Road Corcoran Professor of History. Richard Henry Wilson, M.A., Ph.D. Park Street Professor of Romanic Languages. James Morris Page, M.A., Ph.D., LL.D. McCormick Road Professor of Mathematics. Thomas Fitz-Hugh, M.A. West Lawn Professor of Latin. Albert Lefevre, A.B., Ph.D., LL.D. West Range Corcoran Professor of Philosophy. William Harry Heck, M.A., Ph.D. Preston Heights Curry Memorial Professor of Education. Thomas Walker Page, Ph.D., LL.D. Fry's Spring James Wilson Professor of Economics. Thomas Leonard Watson, M.S., Ph.D. University Place Corcoran Professor of Geology. Robert Montgomery Bird, B.A., B.S., Ph.D. University Place Collegiate Professor of Chemistry. THE ACADEMIC FACULTY. Charles Alphonso Smith, A.M., Ph.D., LL.D. East Lawn Edgar Allan Poe Professor of English. William Mentzel Forrest, B.A. Preston Heights John B. Cary Memorial Professor of Biblical History and Literature. William Harrison Faulkner, M.A., Ph.D. Rugby Road Professor of Germanic Languages. Charles Gilmore Maphis Park Street Professor of Secondary Education. Robert Henning Webb, M.A., Ph.D. University Place Professor of Greek. Samuel Alfred Mitchell, M.A., Ph.D. Observatory Mountain Professor of Astronomy. Ivey Forman Lewis, A.B., M.S., Ph.D. Preston Heights Professor of Biology and Agriculture. Llewelyn Griffith Hoxton, B.S., M.A. Fry's Spring Associate Professor of Physics. Graham Edgar, B.S., Ph.D. Monroe Hill Associate Professor of Chemistry. William Allison Kepner, M.A., Ph.D. University Place Associate Professor of Biology. John Sharshall Grasty, A.B., Ph.D., Sc.D. University Place William Barton Rogers Associate Professor of Economic Geology. Alfred Lawrence Hall-Quest, M.A., B.D. University Place Associate Professor of Education. Ralph Chapin Jones, B.A. Neve Apartments Associate Professor of Forestry. Charles Wakefield Paul University Heights Adjunct Professor of Public Speaking. Carroll Mason Sparrow, B.A., Ph.D. Monroe Hill Adjunct Professor of Physics. James Sugars McLemore, M.A., Ph.D. West Main Street Adjunct Professor of Latin and Instructor in Greek. Albert George Adam Balz, M.A. Colonnade Club Adjunct Professor of Philosophy. James Cook Bardin, M.D. Dawson's Row Adjunct Professor of Romanic Languages. Charles Pollard Olivier, M.A., Ph.D. Observatory Adjunct Professor of Astronomy. THE ACADEMIC FACULTY. Herman Patrick Johnson, M.A. University Place Adjunct Professor of English Literature. Leon Rutledge Whipple, M.A. University Place Adjunct Professor of Journalism. Justus Henry Cline, M.A. Altamont Circle Adjunct Professor of Geology. Lindsay Rogers, M.A., LL.B., Ph.D. West Lawn Adjunct Professor of Political Science. INSTRUCTORS. Ernest Jackson Oglesby, M.A. Mathematics Gardner Lloyd Carter, M.A. General Chemistry George Lloyd Barton, Jr., B.A. Latin Harold Hopkins Neff, B.S., M.A. Romanic Languages Eugene Price Brown, B.S. Analytical Chemistry Harold Lee Alden, B.A., M.S. Astronomy Frank Lee Bruce, Ph. B. English Literature John Letcher Harrison, M.A. English Forrest Jesse Hyde, Jr., LL.B. Economics Ernest Linwood Lehman, B.A. Latin Lyde Stuart Pratt, A.B., Ph.D. Organic Chemistry Gilbert Paul Voigt, B.A. German ASSISTANTS. Samuel Overton McCue, M.A. Philosophy Richard Lee Morton, M.A. History Thomas Stuart Luck, M.A. History John Spottswood Graves, M.A. Economics and Political Science Edward Tankard Browne, B.A. Mathematics Robert Macdonald, Jr. Physics Francis Milton Massie, B.A. Chemistry Thomas Fitz-Hugh, Jr., B.A. Philosophy Frank Stringfellow Barr English John Graham Edwards, M.A. Botany Palmer Hampton Graham, M.A. Astronomy Nicholas Ewing Oglesby, B.A. Economics and Political Science John Ridout, Jr. Mathematics STUDENT ASSISTANTS. Ellis Nimmo Tucker Mathematics Thomas Jeffries Betts English Literature Nathan Cockrell Zoölogy William Ellyson Currie Chemistry Ernest Bouldin Harper Philosophy Reginald Clair Lamb Physics John Seward Lawrence Physics Hugh Leach Botany Judson Hall Robertson Chemistry Monroe Warren Zoölogy George Arthur Wilson Biology DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. ENTRANCE REQUIREMENTS. Required for Admission to the Department.—A candidate for admission to the Department of Graduate Studies must have a baccalaureate degree from a recognized institution of collegiate rank; or, in case the institution he attended does not confer such a degree, he must present a certificate of graduation in a course of study accepted by the Academic Faculty as fully equivalent to that ordinarily required for the degree in question. Required for Admission as Applicant for a Degree.—In order to be recognized as an applicant for a Master's or Doctor's degree, any candidate who has not received a baccalaureate degree from this university must secure from the Registrar of the University a blank form, which, when properly filled out, he must file with the Dean of this department, together with a catalogue of the institution from which he graduated. If that institution has (1) a faculty of at least six professors giving their full time to college or university work; (2) entrance requirements equal to those of this university, and (3) a course of four full years in the liberal arts and sciences, the candidate will not be required to take any undergraduate courses except such as the Committee on Rules and Courses or the professors in charge of the graduate courses he elects may consider necessary for the successful prosecution of those courses. If, however, the institution in question does not meet the three conditions mentioned above, the candidate's preparation will be carefully considered by the Committee on Rules and Courses, which will prescribe such undergraduate courses as are deemed necessary to supply his deficiencies. REGULATIONS. Grade.—The grade of a student in any course, either for a term or for the session, is determined by his class standing and his examination grade, combined in such proportion as the professor in charge of the course in question may decide. Grade Required for Passing.—For passing in any course a grade of seventy-five per cent is required. Absence from Examinations will not be excused except for sickness on the day of examination, attested by a physician's certificate, or for other cause which the Faculty by special order may approve. An unexcused absence is counted as a total failure. Special Examinations.—A student whose absence from an examination is excused, is entitled to a special examination on a date to be arranged between himself and the professor in charge. Change of Schools can be made only with the consent of the Dean and of the professors concerned. DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. REQUIREMENTS FOR DEGREES. Graduate in a School. Any student who successfully completes all the courses offered in any academic School is entitled to a diploma of graduation in that School. The Master's Degrees. A candidate who has received a baccalaureate degree from this university, or who has fulfilled the conditions above specified under Entrance Requirements, is entitled to a Master's degree upon his successful completion of four graduate courses, chosen in accordance with the restrictions detailed below: No C course may be counted for a Master's degree unless preceded by a B course or courses in the same subject aggregating at least six session-hours; or, in case only one three-session-hour course is offered in that subject, by one B course in that subject and a second B course in the same Group, chosen with the approval of the professor in charge of the C course in question. No C course which a candidate has offered as part of the work credited for baccalaureate degree may be counted for a Master's degree. A candidate must take at least two graduate courses during the last year of his work for a Master's degree, and no candidate may receive this degree until at least one year after he has received his baccalaureate degree, except by special consent of the Academic Faculty. The degree of Master of Arts is conferred upon a Bachelor of Arts who has successfully completed four graduate courses, chosen with the approval of the Academic Faculty. These four courses must be in at least three distinct subjects, and in three different academic Schools, except by special order of the Academic Faculty. Three of the subjects must be cognate, which means that they must be selected from kindred groups of subjects, such as, for example, languages and literature, or mathematics and natural science, or history, economics, and philosophy, or philosophy, education, and biology. The degree of Master of Science is conferred upon a holder of the cultural degree of Bachelor of Science, who has successfully completed four graduate courses chosen in accordance with the regulations prescribed for the Master of Arts above. The degree of Master of Science in a Special Subject, the name of which is inscribed on the diploma, is conferred upon a holder of the vocational degree of Bachelor of Science in a Special Subject, who has successfully completed four graduate courses selected from among those offered in his special subject, or from among other courses which meet with the approval of the professor or professors in charge of his special subject. DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. Doctor of Philosophy. A candidate for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy must hold the degree of Bachelor of Arts or the cultural degree of Bachelor of Science of this university, or, if he be a graduate of some other institution, he must have fulfilled the conditions above specified under Entrance Requirements. The requirements for the degree are as follows: (1) A reading knowledge of French and German, attested by the successful completion of the B courses in these languages, or else by examinations held at the beginning of the first year of the candidate's work for the doctorate, by committees consisting of the professor in charge of the candidate's major subject and the professors of French and German, respectively. If the candidate fails on one or both of these examinations, he will be required to enter the appropriate course in one or both of these languages. No student will be regarded as a regular candidate for the doctorate until he has fulfilled this requirement. (2) The successful completion of at least three years of graduate work in three subjects, to be known, respectively, as the candidate's major, primary minor and secondary minor. These subjects must be cognate, and must be chosen, with the approval of the Committee on Rules and Courses, from at least three academic Schools. The major must be pursued for at least three years, the primary minor for at least two years, and the secondary minor for at least one year. No C course may be counted for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy unless preceded by a B course or courses in the same subject aggregating at least six session-hours; or, in case only one three-session-hour course is offered in that subject, by one B course in that subject and a second B course in the same Group, chosen with the approval of the professor in charge of the C course in question. Any student taking a D course in any subject may be required by the professor, with the approval of the Academic Faculty, to attend such lectures or courses in any of the academic Schools as the professor may deem necessary. Graduate work done in other universities may be accepted in lieu of resident work, provided sufficient evidence is furnished by examination, written or oral, or both, that such work has been of a grade similar to that required here, and has been satisfactorily performed, and provided also that the candidate takes in this university at least one graduate course in his primary minor, and does at least one year's resident work in his major subject. A candidate who is a professor in a chartered college or university, of the subject selected by him as major, may be allowed by the Academic Faculty to spend only two years in resident work. In all cases the work of the last year of candidacy shall be done in residence, unless the Academic Faculty shall for special reasons direct otherwise. DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. (3) A dissertation exhibiting independent research in some branch of the candidate's major subject. The dissertation must be submitted to the Academic Faculty not later than April fifteenth of the year in which the candidate applies for the degree. Moreover, the copy presented for the Faculty's approval shall be written (typewritten, if feasible) on paper of prescribed quality and size, shall be bound, and shall have certain prescribed phrases on the cover and title page. If the dissertation is accepted by the Faculty as satisfactory, the copy submitted shall immediately become the property of the University. Before the degree is conferred the dissertation must be printed at the candidate's expense, and one hundred copies deposited in the library of the University; or, if this be impracticable on account of lack of time, the candidate must deposit with the Bursar a sum of money sufficient to have a hundred copies of the dissertation printed. EXPENSES. The necessary expenses of a Virginia student in the Department of Graduate Studies may be estimated at from $220 a year upward, according to the mode of living; for students from other States this minimum should be increased by a sum ranging from $90 to $130 for tuition fees. A fuller statement of expenses, including the conditions under which Virginians and other students are entitled to free tuition, will be found on pp. 104-113 of the general catalogue. Applicants for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy who are granted the privilege of non-residence during a period of their candidacy, under the conditions above stated, are required to register each year during such period of non-residence, and to pay the annual university fee ($10 for Virginians, $40 for students from other States). ESTIMATE OF NECESSARY EXPENSES IN THE GRADUATE DEPARTMENT. VIRGINIANS NON-VIRGINIANS Low Average Liberal Low Average Liberal University Fee $ 10 $ 10 $ 10 $ 40 $ 40 $ 40 Tuition Fee 75 75 75 Laboratory Fees (Average 3 Years) 5 5 5 5 5 5 Room, Heat, Light, Furniture, and Service 50 90 105 50 90 105 Board 125 150 180 125 150 180 Books 15 25 30 15 25 30 Laundry 15 20 25 15 20 25 Total for Session of 9 Months. $220 $300 $355 $325 $405 $460 DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. SCHEDULE OF LECTURES AND EXAMINATIONS IN THE DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES.* * Many C courses and most D courses have hours set by appointment at the beginning of the session. The examination date of any course corresponds to the hour set, as shown in the above schedule. 1916-1917. Any change in the lecture-hours of a course involves a corresponding change in the examination dates. Hours Monday, Wednesday, Friday Tuesday, Thursday, Saturday Hours 9 to 10 English C1; Philosophy C2; 9 to 10 Wednesday, Dec. 13. Wednesday, Dec. 20. Thursday, Mar. 15. Thursday, Mar. 22. Tuesday, May 29. Tuesday, June 5. 10 to 11 Analytical Chemistry C1; German C1; 10 to 11 Applied Mathematics C1; Saturday, Dec. 16. Philosophy C1; Monday, Mar. 19. Tuesday, Dec. 12. Friday, June 1. Wednesday, Mar. 14. Thursday, June 7. 11 to 12 Economics C2; Mathematics C1; 11 to 12 Mathematics D3; French C1; Friday, Dec. 22. Monday, Dec. 18. Saturday, Mar. 24. Tuesday, Mar. 20. Monday, May 28. Saturday, June 2. 12 to 1 Biblical Literature C1; 12 to 1 Government C1; Latin C2; History C1; Latin D1 (Sat.); Latin C1; Industrial Chem. C1 (Tues.); Latin D1 (Fri.); Thursday, Dec. 21. Tuesday, Dec. 19. Friday, Mar. 23. Wednesday, Mar. 21. Wednesday, June 6. Monday, June 4. 1 to 2 Government C2; English Literature C1; 1 to 2 Government C3; Latin D1 (Sat.); Latin D1 (Fri.); Friday, Dec. 15. Political Science C1; Saturday, Mar. 17. Thursday, Dec. 14. Thursday, May 31. Friday, Mar. 16. Wednesday, May 30. 3 to 4:30 Industrial Chemistry C1; Thursday, Dec. 21. 3 to 4:30 Tuesday, Dec. 19. Friday, Mar. 23. Wednesday, Mar. 21. Wednesday, June 6. Monday, June 4. DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. ANNOUNCEMENT OF COURSES. SCHOOL OF PRACTICAL ASTRONOMY. Professor Mitchell. Adjunct Professor Olivier. Mr. Alden. Mr. Graham. For Undergraduates and Graduates. Astronomy C1: Spherical and Practical Astronomy: Astronomy B1 and Mathematics B2 (or its equivalent) prerequisite.—Spherical Astronomy and theory of astronomical instruments, with practical exercises in making and reducing astronomical observations. Hours by appointment. Rouss Physical Laboratory and McCormick Observatory. Adjunct Professor Olivier. Astronomy C2: Celestial Mechanics: Astronomy B1 and Mathematics B2 (or its equivalent) prerequisite.—Rectilinear motion, central forces, potential; problems of two, three and n bodies, perturbations, determination of a preliminary orbit. Hours by appointment. Rouss Physical Laboratory. Adjunct Professor Olivier. For Graduates. Astronomy D1: Advanced Practical Astronomy: Astronomy C1 prerequisite.—Determination of the positions of the fixed stars, use of transit instrument, equatorials and measuring machines. Hours by appointment. Professor Mitchell. Astronomy D2: Theoria Motus: Astronomy B1 and Mathematics B2 (or its equivalent) prerequisite.—Determination of the position of an undisturbed body from known elements, determination of the elements of an undisturbed orbit, theory of special perturbations. Hours by appointment. Professor Mitchell. Astronomy D3: Advanced Celestial Mechanics: Astronomy C2 prerequisite.—Problem of three bodies, and theory of general perturbations. Hours by appointment. Professor Mitchell. Astronomy D4: Photographic Astronomy: Astronomy C1 prerequisite. —Theory and reduction of astronomical photographs, including spectrograms. Hours by appointment. Professor Mitchell. For information in regard to the Vanderbilt Fellowships in Astronomy, see page 116. For summer-school courses in Astronomy on which college credit will be allowed, see p. 256. The Astronomical Observatory is situated upon Mount Jefferson, which furnishes an unobstructed horizon. The principal building is a rotunda DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. forty-five feet in diameter, which contains the great Clark refractor of twenty-six inches aperture. The instrument and building are the gift of the late Leander J. McCormick, Esq., of Chicago. The telescope is fitted with micrometer, photometer, and a plate-holder for stellar photography. The computing rooms adjoining contain clocks, chronograph, machines for measuring astronomical photographs and spectrograms, and an excellent working library. In a smaller building are a three-inch transit and a six-inch equatorial. A temporary Students' Observatory, erected in the rear of Dawson's Row, is intended primarily for the use of students in Astronomy B1. JOHN B. CARY MEMORIAL SCHOOL OF BIBLICAL HISTORY. Professor Forrest. For Undergraduates and Graduates. Biblical Literature C1: Any two B courses from the English Group prerequisite.—The Origin and History of the English Bible: The Canon; The Text; The English Versions. Monday, Wednesday, Friday, 12-1. Peabody Hall, Basement Room 1. For Graduates. Biblical Literature D1. The Religious Ideas of the Bible, or the Theology of the Old and New Testaments. Hours by appointment. Peabody Hall, Basement Room 1. MILLER SCHOOL OF BIOLOGY. Professor Lewis. Associate Professor Kepner. Mr. Cockrell. Mr. Edwards. Mr. Leach. Mr. Warren. Mr. Wilson. The work of the School is planned to illustrate the fundamental laws underlying the phenomena of life. The undergraduate work is designed to meet the needs of three classes of students: first, of those who desire a knowledge of biological phenomena and principles as a proper part of a liberal education; second, of those who are looking forward to positions as teachers; and third, of those seeking a broad foundation for subsequent work in Agriculture or in Medicine. A laboratory fee of $5 is charged for each course. Any course may be withdrawn unless elected by at least four students. DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. I. BIOLOGY AND AGRICULTURE. Professor Lewis. Associate Professor Kepner. For Undergraduates. Biology B1: General Biology.—An elementary study of living organisms and the relations between animals and plants. Plants will be studied from the standpoint of metabolism and growth and animals with special reference to their responses. Types will be chosen which illustrate the fundamental biological laws and throw light on the place of man among living things. (B.A. or B.S. credit, 6 session-hours.) Lectures, Tuesday, Thursday, Saturday, 12-1. Laboratory: Section I, Monday, Wednesday, Friday, 9-11; section II, Tuesday, Thursday, Saturday, 9-11; section III, Monday, Wednesday, Friday, 3-5. Cabell Hall. Professor Lewis, Associate Professor Kepner and assistants. Biology B2: Agricultural Botany: Biology B1 prerequisite.—The physiology of the higher plants, especially as related to nutrition and growth; the principles of crop-raising as based on the laws of plant life. Hours by appointment. Cabell Hall. Professor Lewis. Biology B3: Agricultural Zoölogy: Biology B1 prerequisite.—The parasitic protozoa, worms, and arthropods; the insects will be considered in their economic relations, and the anatomy of the domestic animals examined. The relation of animals to the soil and to plant life will be discussed. Hours by appointment. Cabel Hall. Associate Professor Kepner. Candidates for a diploma of graduation in Biology and Agriculture are required to complete Biology B2, Biology B3, Botany C1 and Zoölogy C1. II. BOTANY. Professor Lewis. For Undergraduates and Graduates. Botany C1: Plant Physiology: Biology B1 prerequisite.—A detailed study of the various activities of plants, such as nutrition, growth, reproduction and reactions to stimuli. The part plants play in the economy of ature and their relation to human welfare will be considered. Two lectures and two three-hour laboratory periods weekly. Hours by appointment. Cabell Hall. Professor Lewis. For Graduates. Botany D1: Opportunity is offered for advanced work along some of the lines indicated above. The work will be varied to suit the needs of the students applying for the course. Hours by appointment. Cabell Hall. Professor Lewis. DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. III. ZOÖLOGY. Associate Professor Kepner. For Undergraduates and Graduates. Zoölogy C1: Biology B1 prerequisite.—Experimental Zoölogy. A comparative study of the morphology and behavior of typical invertebrates. Two lectures and two three-hour laboratory periods weekly. Hours by appointment. Cabell Hall. Associate Professor Kepner. For Graduates. Zoölogy D1: Principles of Animal Histology. Protoplasm, cell organization, and tissue formation. The student is required to become familiar with the principles of histological technique and to make his own preparations. Two lectures and two three-hour laboratory periods a week. Also a weekly meeting of one hour for a discussion with the instructor of current literature and of the problems arising out of the students' work. Hours by appointment. Cabell Hall. Associate Professor Kepner. Further advanced work may be arranged to meet the needs of students. SCHOOL OF CHEMISTRY. Professor Bird. Associate Professor Edgar. Dr. Pratt. Mr. Carter. Mr. Massie. Mr. Curry. Mr. Robertson. Students taking courses in Chemistry are required to pay for each course a laboratory fee of $10, and to make a special deposit of $5 to cover breakage of apparatus. For Undergraduates and Graduates. Chemistry C1: Physical Chemistry: Chemistry B1 and Analytical Chemistry B1, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Some knowledge of the Calculus is required, and previous work in Physics is desirable. This course will include work upon such topics as the gas laws, kinetic theory of gases, the properties of dilute solutions, osmotic pressure, the determination of molecular weights, mass action, reaction velocity and equilibrium, electrolysis and electrolytic dissociation, the phase rule, etc. The laboratory work will consist of a thorough course in physico-chemical methods, including the measurement of electrolytic conductivity, electromotive force, etc. Towar the end of the course the student may be required to do a limited amount of research on some chemical problem suggested by the instructor. Hours by appointment. Organic Laboratory. Associate Professor Edgar. Chemistry C2: Advanced Organic Chemistry: Chemistry B1 and B2, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—During the first term some time will be devoted to a review of the historical development of the subject, with special attention DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. to fundamental theories. Parallel reading will be assigned. The remainder of the year will be devoted to an intimate study of one or more of the special phases of Organic Chemistry, such as Dyes and Indicators, Carbohydrates, Terpenes, Polymethylenes, Coal Tar Products, etc. Reading from the scientific journals and reference books will be assigned. The laboratory work will consist of the more difficult organic preparations, partially adapted to the topics under discussion in the lectures, special attention being given to a quantitative study of the reactions. Hours by appointment. Organic Laboratory. Dr. Pratt. For Graduates. Chemistry D1: Advanced Inorganic Chemistry: Chemistry B1, C1 and Analytical Chemistry C1, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—The lectures deal with the fundamental theories and laws of chemical action. Parallel reading in the history of Chemistry is required. In the laboratory the study of chemical reactions is taken up in an advanced way, and when the student has shown proper fitness he undertakes work upon some special problem in Inorganic Chemistry. Hours by appointment. Professor Bird. Chemistry D2: Advanced Physical Chemistry: Chemistry B1, C1 and Analytical Chemistry C1, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—This course will be given only as occasion demands, and the nature of the work will be arranged for the individual student. It is intended for those seeking the degree of Doctor of Philosophy who elect to do work in Physical Chemistry. Hours by appointment. Associate Professor Edgar. The Chemical Journal Club meets every Thursday, 11-12, in Professor Bird's lecture-room, for the critical review and discussion of various topics of interest in current chemical literature, and of such chemical researches as may be in progress in the University. All instructors and advanced students in Chemistry are expected to participate in these meetings and to take part in the discussions. The privileges of the club are extended to all persons in the University or in the vicinity of Charlottesville who are interested in the progress of Chemistry. SCHOOL OF ANALYTICAL AND INDUSTRIAL CHEMISTRY. Professor Dunnington. Mr. Brown. Students taking courses in Analytical Chemistry are required to pay a special tuition fee of $40 for each course. Each student is required also to pay a laboratory fee of $10, and to make a deposit of $10 for one course, or $15 for two courses, to cover the cost of apparatus. The regular work of this School, constituting a complete course in Practical Chemistry, is divided into three courses, as follows: DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. For Undergraduates and Graduates. Analytical Chemistry C1: Quantitative Analysis: Analytical Chemistry B1 or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Training in manipulation and gravimetric estimations, followed by volumetric estimations and a full course in Quantitative Analysis of minerals, ores, coal, soil, iron and steel, technical products, and so on. Weekly written exercises are required, and twelve hours or more of laboratory work per week. As the student advances in the course he is encouraged to undertake original research and assist in its prosecution; and in determining his fitness for graduation, work of this kind is considered as having much weight. The laboratory is open to students six days in the week, during all the working hours of the day. Text-books: G. S. Newth's Manual of Chemical Analysis; Fresenius's Qualitative and Quantitative Analysis. Monday, Wednesday, Friday, 10-11. Laboratory hours by appointment. Analytical Laboratory. Professor Dunnington, Mr. Brown. Industrial Chemistry C1: Chemistry B1 or Analytical Chemistry B1 prerequisite.—A detailed study is made of the chemical principles and processes of the more important manufacturing industries, upon which, in large measure, depend the development of the natural resources of the country. Among the more important subjects discussed are: the metallurgy and uses of the principal metals and alloys, and thermit, the manufacture of acids, alkalies, salts, explosives, glass, pottery and fertilizers; the preparation and preservation of food, including bread, meat, sugar, etc.; the chemical arts relating to clothing, such as bleaching, dyeing and tanning; the chemistry of arts concerning building, including the manufacture of brick, lime and cement; the production of artificial lights and heating; disinfectants, soap, paper, etc. The subjects specially related to Agriculture are treated of in different portions of this course. There is a weekly quiz and weekly written exercises are required. Text-book: F. H. Thorp's Outlines of Industrial Chemistry. Recommended for reference: T. E. Thorpe's Dictionary of Applied Chemistry; W. E. Roberts-Austen's Introduction to the Study of Metallurgy; Roger and Aubert's Industrial Chemistry; Sadtler's Hand-Book of Industrial Organic Chemistry, etc. H. K. Benson's Industrial Chemistry for Engineering Students. A clear comprehension of all lines of industrial manufacture is the aim proposed in this course, a preparation needed by students who expect to enter upon any branch of such work. Since these lectures are designed to give some accurate information about materials with which everyone is concerned in daily life, it is judged that they will afford a valuable addition to a general education. Monday, Wednesday, Friday, 3-4.30; Tuesday, 12-1. Analytical Laboratory. Professor Dunnington. The collections of the University in illustration of the processes and products of Industrial Chemistry have been procured at much expense and pains in this country, England, France, and Germany, and are unsually extensive and good, being among the best on this side of the Atlanic. Students who accomplish the work of Analytical Chemistry B1 and DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. C1, and Industrial Chemistry C1, together with Chemistry B1, B2, C1, are prepared for entering upon work in these several lines of industry. For Graduates. Analytical Chemistry D1: Analytical Chemistry C1, Industrial Chemistry C1, and Chemistry B1, B2, and C1, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—The work is adapted to the special aims or tastes of each student, but will, in all cases, comprise some practice in the more elaborate processes of analysis, ultimate and proximate organic analysis, some study in analytical methods, and some original problems; also the reading and the summarizing of extracts from current journals. Laboratory work will be conducted daily, and suggestions and due assistance will be given in its prosecution. Professor Dunnington. The Analytical Laboratory is completely fitted with approved appliances, and stocked with apparatus, models, materials, and specimens. The main working-room is furnished with work-tables, gas, water, and all proper fixtures; smaller rooms are devoted to weighing, evaporations, assaying, etc. JAMES WILSON SCHOOL OF ECONOMICS. Professor Thomas Walker Page. Adjunct Professor Bardin. Adjunct Professor Rogers. Mr. Hyde. Mr. Graves. Mr. N. E. Oglesby. For Undergraduates and Graduates. Economics C1: The Growth of American Industry and Commerce: Economics B1 or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Economic principles as illustrated by American experience, with a study of the influence of economic conditions upon American social and political development. The work is mainly topical and the topics receiving chief emphasis vary from year to year. Professor Page. Offered in alternate years with Economics C2. Omitted in 1916-1917. Economics C2: Public Finance, Money and Banking: Economics B1 or the equivalent, prerequisite.—First and second terms: The general principles of public finance, with a detailed investigation of state and local taxation. Third term: The financial institutions and methods of the Federal Government. Monday, Wednesday, Friday, 11-12. Professor Page. Government C1: Municipal Government: Government B1 or the equivalent, prerequisite.—The causes and characteristics of urban growth and the various forms of municipal government that have been tried in the United States and in Europe, with special attention to the question of home rule, the newer forms of city government, and problems of municipal administration. Monday, Wednesday, Friday, 12-1. Cabell Hall. Adjunct Professor Rogers. DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. Only one of the following courses will be given in 1916-1917. Government C2: Recent State Constitutions: Government B1 or the equivalent, prerequisite.—The problems of reconstructing state government, and the trend of constitutional development, with a study of the political theories involved, such as the short ballot, the bi-cameral legislature, legislative responsibility, budgetary control, suffrage qualifications, limitations on legislative action, direct government, and judicial review. Monday, Wednesday, Friday, 1-2. Cabell Hall. Adjunct Professor Rogers. Government C3: Politics and Jurisprudence: Government B1 or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Various concepts of the state, of sovereignty, and of political obligation, the reconciliation of government and liberty, and principles of state interference; the nature, sources, and forms of law, its philosophical and sociological aspects, and problems of social legislation. This course is of especial value for those intending to take up the study of law. Monday, Wednesday, Friday, 1-2. Cabell Hall. Adjunct Professor Rogers. For Graduates. The following are courses of research. Competent students are guided in the intensive and methodical investigation of selected topics, and the results are presented for discussion. The members of the teaching staff of the School will combine to give guidance and instruction. Economics D1.—Hours by appointment. Professor Page. Government D1.—Hours by appointment. Adjunct Professor Rogers. Commercial Geography D1.—Hours by appointment. Adjunct Professor Bardin. CURRY MEMORIAL SCHOOL OF EDUCATION. Professor Heck. Professor Maphis. Associate Professor Hall-Quest. For Undergraduates and Graduates. Education C1: Educational Hygiene: Two B courses in Education prerequisite. First Term: Measurement, Defects, and Hygiene of Development. Second Term: Hygiene of School Buildings, Equipment, and Management. Third Term: Personal and Community Hygiene. Monday and Wednesday, 4:45-6:15. Peabody Hall, Room 2. Professor Heck. DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. Education C2: The Psychology of Biography.—Philosophy B3 and any B course in Education, prerequisite. First Term: Analysis of the qualities of greatness, including a study of the psychology of leadership and personality. Second Term: Detailed study of the biographies of inventors and scientists. Third Term: Detailed study of the biographies of writers and statesmen. Text-books: Jastrow's Character and Temperament; Larned's A Study of Greatness in Men; Anna Burr's The Autobiography. Monday and Tuesday, 7:30-9 P. M. Peabody Hall, or at the Professor's home. Associate Professor Hall-Quest. Recommendation of Teachers.—The recommendation of teachers from the School of Education is in charge of the Bureau of Appointments, through which positions are secured, not only for students of the School of Education, but for other students who are known to be fitted to fill vacancies reported. In response to requests from the proper authorities, teachers are recommended for positions as instructors in colleges and normal schools, as superintendents, as supervisors in special subjects, as principals or department teachers in high schools, and as principals of elementary schools. The demand for teachers has been greater than the supply. Correspondence with regard to this matter may be addressed to the Bureau of Appointments, University, Virginia. EDGAR ALLAN POE SCHOOL OF ENGLISH. Professor Smith. Mr. Harrison. Mr. Barr. For Undergraduates and Graduates. English C1: American Literature: A Study by Types: Any two B courses in the Schools of English and of English Literature, prerequisite. 1. A Survey of the Eleven Types. The Epic, the Drama, the Ballad, the Lyric. 2. The Lyric concluded. History, Biography, the Essay, the Oration, the Letter. 3. The Novel, the Short Story. Monday, Wednesday, Friday, 9-10. Cabell Hall. Professor Smith. For Graduates. English D1: Old English Poetry. A rapid reading of the extant body of old English Poetry. Hours by appointment. Professor Smith. DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. English D2: 1. The Ballad. Professor Smith. 2. Robert Browning. Professor Smith. 3. Comparative Literature. Professor Smith. LINDEN KENT MEMORIAL SCHOOL OF ENGLISH LITERATURE. Professor Kent. Adjunct Professor Johnson. Mr. Bruce. Mr. Betts. Mr. Gordon. For Undergraduates and Graduates. English Literature C1: Any two B courses in the Schools of English and of English Literature, prerequisite. 1. Shakespeare as a Dramatic Artist. 2. English Romanticism. 3. Contemporary Drama. Tuesday, Thursday, Saturday, 1-2. Cabell Hall. Professor Kent. For Graduates. English Literature D1: 1. The History of English Prosody. 2. The History of English Prosody. 3. The History of English Prose Rythm. Wednesday and Friday, 12:30-2. Professor Kent. CORCORAN AND ROGERS SCHOOLS OF GENERAL AND ECONOMIC GEOLOGY. Professor Watson. Associate Professor Grasty. Adjunct Professor Cline. For Undergraduates and Graduates. Geology C1: Petrology: Geology B3, or its equivalent, prerequisite.— This course aims to give a thorough knowledge of the determination of minerals and rocks in thin sections under the microscope. It includes: (a) Physical Crystallography.—A full discussion of optical and microscopical mineralogy, with especial reference to the behavior of minerals as constituents of rock masses. (b) Petrography.—A discussion of the microscopic structure, mineralogical composition, genetic relations, and distribution of igneous, sedimentary, and metamorphic rocks. The laboratory work enables the student to become familiar with the various groups of rocks by means of the polarizing microscope. DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. Lectures and laboratory work to the amount of 19 hours a week throughout the year. Hours by appointment. Brooks Museum. Professor Watson, Adjunct Professor Cline. Geology C2: Geology of Ore Deposits: Geology B1, or its equivalent, prerequisite, and Geology C1 in addition recommended.—A general but comprehensive account of the origin, nature, distribution, and uses of the metallic products, with especial reference to those of the United States. Lectures, collateral reading, laboratory and field work, to the amount of twelve hours per week throughout the year. Hours by appointment. Brooks Museum. Professor Watson. Omitted in 1916-1917. Geology C3: Geology of the Nonmetallic Minerals: Geology B1, or its equivalent, prerequisite, and Geology C1 in addition recommended.—A comprehensive account of the origin, nature, distribution, and uses of the nonmetallic products, with especial reference to those of the United States. Lectures, collateral reading, laboratory and field work, to the amount of twelve hours per week throughout the year. Hours by appointment. Professor Watson. As outlined, Geology C2 and C3 make up the subject of General Economic Geology. The two courses are planned to be given in alternate years. Geology C4: Geological Field Methods: Geology B1, or its equivalent, prerequisite, and Geology C1 in addition recommended.—Special course for students in geology and engineering, designed to familiarize the student with the methods employed and the instruments used in making topographic and geologic maps. The structural relationships of rocks and the proper cartographic representation of these occurrences in nature are especially emphasized. Lectures and field work. Hours by appointment. Brooks Museum. Associate Professor Grasty, Adjunct Professor Cline. Geology C5: Structural Geology: Geology B1, or B2, and Geology B3, or their equivalent, prerequisite, and Geology C2, and C4, in addition recommended.—A discussion of the causes, manifestations, and recognition of the evidence of various types of earth movements, and of the relation of topography to structure. The more important mountainous regions of this and other countries are treated with reference to age, lithologic succession, and characteristics of their rocks and structures. The economic effects of folding in general are also considered. Special emphasis is given to the regional and structural geology of the Atlantic States. Lectures, collateral reading, preparation of papers, laboratory and field work to the amount of twelve lecture hours per week throughout the year. Hours by appointment. Brooks Museum. Associate Professor Grasty. For Graduates. Geology D1: Advanced Geology: Geology B1 and B3 prerequisite.— A thorough treatment of the broader problems of the science, involving the knowledge of stratigraphical principles, as a preparation for independent research. Especial attention will be given to imparting a practical knowledge DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. of the various rocks, and of the animal and plant fossils of the different eras, with a view to using them in determining unknown formations. Stress will be laid upon field work, and the methods of determining and describing the geology of new regions. To impart such knowledge the student will be required to work up some particular region or formation, and report his results. Topics involving a knowledge of the literature and growth of opinion in relation to particular questions may be assigned to form the subject of theses. Hours by appointment. Brooks Museum. Professor Watson, Associate Professor Grasty. Geology D2: Advanced Mineralogy and Petrography: Geology C2 and C3 or their equivalent, prerequisite.—Adapted to the needs of the individual student. Properly qualified students may pursue work directed along the line of crystallography (crystal measurements and drawings, and crystal optics), chemical mineralogy (mineral or rock analysis), or petrographic research. Hours by appointment. Brooks Museum. Professor Watson, Associate Professor Grasty. Geology D3: Advanced Economic Geology: Geology C2 and C3, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Special topics in mining geology for advanced students, selected according to the needs of the individual student. Lectures, laboratory and field work, reading, reports and theses. Hours by appointment. Brooks Museum. Professor Watson, Associate Professor Grasty. Geology D4: Economic Geology of the Southern Appalachians: Geology C2 and C3, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Detailed study of the mining geology of the region, especially that of Virginia. Excursions to various parts of the region will be taken and individual reports required. Original investigation of an assigned area, based upon field work, is required of each student. Hours by appointment. Brooks Museum. Professor Watson. Geological Seminary.—Review and discussion of the more important current geological literature, and the preparation of papers on special subjects based on field and library investigations. All instructors and advanced students in geology are expected to take part in the discussions at these meetings. Time to be arranged. The Lewis Brooks Museum contains collections illustrating the main subdivisions of Natural History. Each of the collections is arranged so as to exemplify the principles of the science, and at the same time offers a large variety of subjects for advanced study. In Geology the specimens show all the different kinds of rocks, classified according to mineral character and the formation in which they occur; the collection of fossils, plaster casts, maps, etc., is exceptionally fine, and fully illustrates Historical Geology. In Mineralogy the principles of the science are made plain by well-chosen suits of specimens, models of crystals, etc. The general collection of minerals contains all the important species, and many of the rarer ones, in good specimens. In addition to the above, a beginning has been made of a collection to illustrate the geology and mineralogy of the State of Virginia, and this is being increased as rapidly as possible. DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. SCHOOL OF GERMANIC LANGUAGES. Professor Faulkner. Mr. Voigt. For Undergraduates and Graduates. The following courses are offered in alternate years. Unless otherwise stated, all lectures and class work are in German. Hence students desiring to enter either of these courses will be required to give satisfactory evidence of ability to understand spoken German. German C1: German B1 and B2, or the equivalent, prerequisite.— First Term: Die Tragödie der Klassiker; Seminar: Schillers Wallenstein. Second Term: Der deutsche Roman, 1795-1870. Third Term: Seminar: Goethes Wilhelm Meisters Lehrjahre; Kellers Der Grüne Heinrich. Tuesday, Thursday, Saturday, 10-11. Peabody Hall. Professor Faulkner. Offered in 1916-1917. German C2: German B1 and B2, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—First Term: Historical Grammar, with selected readings in specimens of early New High German prose and poetry. (Given in English.) Second and Third Term: Goethes Jugend: Gedichte bis 1775; die Leiden des jungen Werthers; Götz von Berlichingen; Dichtung und Wahrheit. Seminar: Goethes Faust, I. und II. Teil. Tuesday, Thursday, Saturday, 10-11. Peabody Hall. Professor Faulkner. Omitted in 1916-1917. For Graduates. The following courses are open only to candidates for a doctor's degree in one of the Schools of English, English Literature, Latin, Greek, Romanic or Germanic Languages, who have already completed not less than one year of graduate work as candidates for that degree. Only one course will be given in any one session. The selection will depend on the wishes and needs of the applicants. Graduate students, therefore, who wish to enter any one of these courses are requested to notify the head of the School not later than June fifteenth, preceding the session in which they desire to enter the course. For all of these courses German C1 or C2 is a prerequisite. German D1: Gothic and Old High German. Three hours a week, by appointment. Professor Faulkner. German D2: Middle High German, with readings in the Nibelungen lied. Three hours a week, by appointment. Professor Faulkner. German D3: Middle High German, with readings in Walther von de Vogelweide. Three hours a week, by appointment. Professor Faulkner DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. SCHOOL OF GREEK. Professor Webb. Adjunct Professor McLemore. For Undergraduates and Graduates. Greek C1: Greek B2, prerequisite. Thucydides, Book II; Aristophanes, Acharnians and Frogs; Euripides, Bacchae; Sophocles, Œdipus Tyrannus; Æschylus, Prometheus; Theocritus, selections. Hours by appointment. Cabell Hall. Professor Webb. For Graduates. Only one of the following courses will be offered in any one session. Hours by appointment. Greek C1, prerequisite. Greek D1. Sophocles. Professor Webb. Greek D2: Aristophanes. Professor Webb. Greek D3: Greek Epigraphy, Palaeography, and Text-Criticism. Professor Webb. CORCORAN SCHOOL OF HISTORY. Professor Dabney. Mr. Morton. Mr. Luck. For Undergraduates and Graduates. History C1: History of the United States: History B1 and B2 prerequisite.—In addition to a considerable amount of reading, essays or reports, based upon the sources as well as upon secondary authorities, will be required. Monday, Wednesday, Friday, 12-1. Rotunda, N. W. Professor Dabney. For Graduates. Only one of the two following courses will be given in any one year. The first is broad and extensive, the second, minute and intensive. History D1: History B1 and B2 prerequisite.—Intellectual, Moral, Religious and Social Development of Europe.—In addition to critical discussions of, and written examinations upon a large number of historical works, a critical essay upon each of them will be required. Hours by appointment. Professor Dabney. History D2: History C1 prerequisite.—History of the Reconstruction of the Southern States. A close study of the sources as well as of the secondary authorities on this period. Hours by appointment. Professor Dabney. DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. SCHOOL OF LATIN. Professor Fitz-Hugh. Adjunct Professor McLemore. Mr. Barton. Mr. Lehman. For Undergraduates and Graduates. Latin C1: Latin B1 and B2, or the equivalent of both, prerequisite. I. In Language: History of the Latin Language (Whitney's Language and the Study of Language, Bennett's Latin Language), with oral and written exercises (Moore, Bennett, Nettleship). II. In Literature: Historical and epistolary, Tacitus' Annals and Cicero's Letters—dramatic and satirical, Plautus' Captivi, Terence's Phormio, and Horace's Satires and Epistles, with study of the meters of the drama— critical, Cicero's De Oratore and Orator, and Tacitus' Dialogus de Oratoribus. III. In Life: The literary life of the Romans (Duff's Literary History of Rome and Laing's Masterpieces of Latin Literature). Monday, Wednesday, Friday, 12-1. Cabell Hall. Professor Fitz-Hugh, Adjunct Professor McLemore. Latin C2: Latin B1 and B2, or the equivalent of both, prerequisite. I. In Language: History of the Latin Language (Whitney's Life and Growth of Language, Grandgent's Vulgar Latin), with oral and written exercises (Moore, Bennett, Nettleship). II. In Literature: Historical and epistolary, Tacitus' Histories and Pliny's Letters—dramatic and satirical, Plautus' Mostellaria, Terence's Andria, and Juvenal's Satires, with study of the meters of the drama—philosophic, Lucretius, De Rerum Natura and Cicero's De Natura Deorum. III. In Life: The philosophic life of the Romans (Mackail's Latin Literature, Mayor's History of Ancient Philosophy from Thales to Cicero, and Pater's Marius the Epicurean). Tuesday, Thursday, Saturday, 12-1. Cabell Hall. Professor Fitz-Hugh, Adjunct Professor McLemore. For Graduates. Latin D1: Latin C1 or C2, or the equivalent of either, prerequisite.—This course extends through three years and is intended for those who desire to specialize for one, two or three years in classical philology. It contemplates especially the needs of those who choose Latin as their major for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy. If the candidate's major be Latin, a respectable familiarity with Greek is required, since the language, literature, and life of the Romans are saturated with Greek influence. If the candidate's major be Romanic, the technical Greek requirement is waived as far as practically possible, and he is guided into the history of the Roman popular vernacular, the common source of the Romanic tongues, and into an acquaintance with the authors illustrating the Vulgar Latin in literature. DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. Plan of Work.—It is the aim of this course to prepare the candidate to investigate independently the sources of our knowledge of the language, monuments (literary and objective), and life of the Romans. The following is, therefore, an outline of the course: I. In Language: Elements of comparative grammar (Giles, supplemented by Hirt and Sommer on Sounds and Inflections and by Brugmann and Schmalz on Syntax)—introduction to Latin historical grammar (Lindsay, supplemented by Landgraf)—systematic grammar (Kühner) with stylistic exercises, oral and written, in conjunction with Cicero's De Oratore —reading of epigraphic and literary monuments illustrating the history of the Latin Language. II. In the Literary and Objective Monuments of the Romans: Reading of authors in groups systematically planned to illustrate the literary life of the Romans—history and interpretation of texts—elements of palæography (Johnston, supplemented by Thompson), epigraphy (Lindsay, supplemented by Egbert and Cagnat), numismatics (Gnecchi, supplemented by Hill), topography and remains (Platner, Petersen, Huelsen, Mau, Strack, Furtwængler). III. In Roman Life: Constructive study of Roman culture-history— reading of authors illustrating the development of Roman civilization— study of modern authorities in Roman culture-history (Philippson, Nissen, Mommsen, Marquardt-Mommsen, Wissowa, Preller-Jordan, Springer-Michaelis and Winter, Schanz, Windelband, Sandys). Friday, Saturday, 12-2. Cabell Hall. Professor Fitz-Hugh, Adjunct Professor McLemore. Aids.—For the sake of first-hand access to important modern authorities in Latin philology, the candidate is required to have a good reading knowledge of German and French. SCHOOL OF MATHEMATICS. Professor Echols. Professor J. M. Page. Mr. Oglesby. Mr. Browne. Mr. Tucker. Mr. Ridout. For Undergraduates and Graduates. Mathematics C1: Mathematics B1 and B2 prerequisite.—Analytical Geometry of Three Dimensions; Advanced Differential and Integral Calculus, continued from the point reached in Mathematics B2; Ordinary Differential Equations. Parallel reading on the History of Mathematics. Text-books: Charles Smith, Solid Geometry; Murray, Differential and Integral Calculus; Williamson, Differential Calculus; Williamson, Integral Calculus; Murray,Differential Equations; Cajori, History of Mathematics. Tuesday, Thursday, Saturday, 11-12. Cabell Hall. Professor Echols. DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. For Graduates. The work of these courses is carried on by means of lectures, notes, and the systematic reading of the standard authors in texts and in journals. Only one of the courses D1 and D2 will be offered in 1916-1917. Mathematics D1: Differential Geometry: Mathematics C1, prerequisite.— The applications of the Differential and Integral Calculus to Geometry, with special reference to the theory of the General Space Curve, the Surface, and the Surface Curve. Hours by appointment. Professor Page. Mathematics D2: Differential Equations: Mathematics C1, prerequisite.— Ordinary and Partial Differential Equations. In the discussion of the Ordinary Differential Equation particular attention is paid to the theory of integration of such equations as admit of a known Transformation Group, and the classic methods of integration are compared with those which flow from the Theory of Continuous Groups. A similar method is adopted in the study of the Linear Partial Differential Equation of the First Order. As far as the time admits, the theories of integration of the Complete System, as well as those of the General Partial Differential Equation of the First and Second Orders, will be discussed. Hours by appointment. Professor Page Mathematics D3: Theory of Functions: Mathematics C1 prerequisite.— Mathematical Analysis for advanced students. The treatment of the subject is arranged under three heads, as follows: (1) The design of the numbers of analysis and the laws of the operations to which they are subject are studied after the methods of Dedekind and Tannery, Cantor and Weierstrass, as introductory to the study of functions. (2) The study of the Theory of Functions of a Real Variable, including series, products, and continued fractions. (3) The General Theory of Functions of a Complex Variable is studied after the methods of Cauchy, Riemann, and Weierstrass. Monday, Wednesday, Friday, 11-12. Professor Echols. SCHOOL OF APPLIED MATHEMATICS. Professor Thornton. For Undergraduates and Graduates. Applied Mathematics C1: Theoretical Mechanics: Mathematics B2 or B3, or the equivalent, prerequisite. First Term: The fundamental laws of motion, force, and energy, and their applications to the Statics of material particles and solid bodies. Elementary dynamics of the particle and the rigid body. DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. Second Term: The dynamics of the particle. Third Term: The dynamics of the rigid body; attractions and potential. Monday, Wednesday, Friday, 10-11. Mechanical Laboratory. Professor Thornton. For Graduates. Applied Mathematics D1: Analytical Mechanics: Lectures are given in alternate sessions on the following topics. Hours by appointment. Professor Thornton. A. Theoretical Dynamics; Theory of Attractions (1916-1917). B. Theory of Elasticity; Hydrodynamics (1915-1916). CORCORAN SCHOOL OF PHILOSOPHY. Professor Lefevre. Adjunct Professor Balz. Mr. McCue. Mr. Fitz-Hugh. Mr. Harper. For Undergraduates and Graduates. Philosophy C1: The History of Philosophy: Philosophy B1, or B2, or B3, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—The history of thought and the influence which philosophical ideas have exerted in the development of civilization. The lectures will give a general account of philosophical speculation from its beginnings among the Greeks to the present time. The endeavor will be made to present the various philosophical systems in their relation to the science and general civilization of the ages to which they belong, and to estimate their social and political significance. A large part of the year will be devoted to the theories and problems of modern times. Reading of texts and commentaries, lectures, discussions, and essays. Monday, Wednesday, Friday, 10-11. Peabody Hall, Room 3. Professor Lefevre. Philosophy C2: Social Psychology: Philosophy B1, or B2, or B3, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—A consideration of certain major topics of general psychology, followed by the psychology of group living, with especial reference to instinct and emotion, the sentiments, the psychology of the crowd, etc., including a brief survey of the genesis and growth of social institutions. Reading of texts, lectures, discussions, and reports. Tuesday, Thursday, Saturday, 9-10. Peabody Hall, Basement Room 1. Adjunct Professor Balz. For Graduates. Only one of the following courses will be given in any one session. Philosophy D1.—(Open to students who have taken or are taking Philosophy C1.) Empiricism and Rationalism. The empirical movement DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. as represented by Locke, Hume, and Mill, and the rationalistic movement as represented especially by Descartes, Spinoza, and Leibnitz, will be studied with reference to their distinctive methods. Reading of texts and commentaries, lectures, discussions, and essays. Professor Lefevre, Adjunct Professor Balz. Philosophy D2.—(Open to students who have taken or are taking Philosophy C1.) The Critical Philosophy of Kant. The greater part of the year will be devoted to the careful study of the Critique of Pure Reason and the Critique of Practical Reason. Collateral reading of standard commentaries and of selected recent literature on the subject will be required. Special attention will be given to Kant's relation to previous philosophical systems, to the development of his own philosophy, and to the interrelation of his three Critiques. Reading of texts, lectures, discussions, and reports. Professor Lefevre, Adjunct Professor Balz. Further advanced work in Philosophy, including the critical study of recent tendencies, will be arranged in accordance with the needs of individual students. SCHOOL OF NATURAL PHILOSOPHY. Associate Professor Hoxton. Adjunct Professor Sparrow. Mr. Macdonald. Mr. Lamb. Mr. Lawrence. A laboratory fee of five dollars is charged for Physics C1 and C2. For Undergraduates and Graduates. Physics C1: General Physics, Selected Topics: Physics B1, and Mathematics A1, or A2, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—The work in the class-room emphasizes the general principles of dynamics and their application to physical problems, special attention being given to the properties of matter and thermodynamics. The laboratory work develops the basic principles of accurate measurement. Laboratory work six hours per week. Hours by appointment. Rouss Physical Laboratory. Adjunct Professor Sparrow. Physics C2: Electricity and Optics: Physics B1, with the addition of either Physics C1, Mathematics B2, or B3, or the equivalent, prerequisite.— Electricity is given during the first half-year, Optics during the second. The elements of the classical mathematical theory and outlines of important modern conceptions are given in the lectures. In the laboratory, especial attention is paid to methods of measurement and studies of important phenomena and principles. Laboratory work, four to six hours per week. Hours by appointment. Rouss Physical Laboratory. Associate Professor Hoxton. DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. For Graduates. The courses of this grade vary from year to year, ranging over the more important fields of Physics in a cycle of about three years. The list given below includes courses which have recently been given and those which are offered for the coming session. The formal preparation necessary for these courses varies somewhat with the nature of the subjects treated. What is necessary is a certain maturity of mind with reference to the subject. The student who has not had training in Mathematics equivalent to Mathematics C1 will probably be unable to follow with profit any D course dealing with the mathematical side of Physics, while the student who has not had the equivalent of the corresponding C course in Physics will be unable to pursue a D course dealing with the experimental side. Physics D1: Electromagnetic Theory: The mathematical theory of substantially the same content as Maxwell's Treatise. Adjunct Professor Sparrow. Given in 1914-1915. Physics D2: Advanced Thermodynamics, Kinetic Theory of Gases: The mathematical theory and an account of the state of experimental knowledge of the subject. Associate Professor Hoxton. Offered for 1916-1917. Physics D3: Dynamics: A general course in Dynamics, including Hydrodynamics and the Theory of Elasticity. Adjunct Professor Sparrow. Given in 1913-1914. Offered for 1916-1917. Physics D4: Conduction of Electricity Through Gases, Radioactivity: Chiefly the experimental side of the subject. Associate Professor Hoxton, Adjunct Professor Sparrow. Given in 1914-1915. Physics D5: Theory of Electrons, Electromagnetic Theory of Light: The mathematical theory and an account of the state of experimental knowledge of the subject. Adjunct Professor Sparrow. Given in 1915-1916. Journal Meeting: The Faculty and advanced students in Physics and Astronomy meet once a week for the presentation and discussion of current research. The students, as well as the professors, take an active part in the presentation of these reports. The Rouss Physical Laboratory is a commodious building, specially designed for and devoted to the work in Physics. The building throughout is characterized by structural stability. The rooms are abundantly lighted, while some may be darkened at will. There is a general distribution of water over the building, while all the rooms are supplied with steam heat, gas and electricity. The equipment includes an exceptionally rich set of demonstration apparatus, and a good stock of apparatus for elementary laboratory instruction. In addition to this there is a special line of electrical and optical instruments, a 21½-foot concave grating with Rowland mounting, photographic dark room, liquid air plant and storage battery, and an instrument DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES. shop for the repair and construction of physical instruments. For advanced work in some lines the facilities offered are excellent. SCHOOL OF ROMANIC LANGUAGES. Professor Wilson. Adjunct Professor Bardin. Mr. Neff. For Undergraduates and Graduates. Undergraduates of exceptional ability, who desire to continue their studies in the Romanic languages, will be allowed to follow these courses after having completed the collegiate courses described above. French C1: French B1, and one other B course in the School of Romanic Languages, prerequisite.—The course is conducted in French. The tendencies of modern French fiction are studied. French life is analyzed, and a general survey is made of the nineteenth century. Tuesday, Thursday, Saturday, 11-12. Rotunda, S. E. Professor Wilson. Spanish C1: Spanish B1, and one other B course in the School of Romanic Languages, prerequisite.—The literature of one or more of the Latin-American republics will be studied. A general survey will be made of Spanish-American life and literature. Hours by appointment. Adjunct Professor Bardin. REGISTER OF STUDENTS. REGISTER OF STUDENTS Courses in Roman type are undergraduate courses. Alden, Harold Lee (2) Topeka, Kans. M.S., University of Chicago, Ill. Physics, Astronomy. Balthis, Thomas Alphonse (4) University, Va. B.A., University of Virginia. Industrial Chemistry, Analytical Chemistry, Physical Chemistry, Geology. Barton, George Lloyd, Jr. (7) Charlottesville, Va. B.A., University of Virginia. Greek, English, German, French. Brown, Eugene Price (7) Mountfair, Va. B.S., University of Virginia. Physical Chemistry, Petrology, Economic Geology. Brown, William Henry (1) Narrows, Va. B.A., Emory and Henry College, Va. History, Industrial Chemistry, Economics, English Literature. Browne, Edward Tankard (5) University, Va. B.A., University of Virginia. Physics, German, Mechanics. Bruce, Frank Lee (1) Hollins, Va. Ph.B., Cornell University, N. Y. English, Philosophy, Biblical History and Literature, Education. Carter, Gardner Lloyd (8) Charlottesville, Va. B.A., M.A., University of Virginia. Inorganic Chemistry, Physical Chemistry. Christian, Frank Gordon (1) Richmond, Va. B.A., Hampden-Sidney College, Va. English Literature, English, Philosophy. Cline, Justus Henry (4) University, Va. B.A., Bridgewater College, Va.; M.A., Northwestern University, Ill. Petrology, Industrial Chemistry. Dimmock, Marion Stuart (4) Richmond, Va. B.A., University of Virginia. Philosophy, English Literature, Latin, Industrial Chemistry. Edwards, John Graham (5) Rushmere, Va. B.A., M.A., University of Virginia. Botany, Zoölogy, Education. REGISTER OF STUDENTS. Ehrman, Clarence Davis (3) Charlottesville, Va. B.A., Roanoke College, Va. Mechanics, Physics, Industrial Chemistry, Political Science. Eutsler, George Willard (1) University, Va. B.A., University of North Carolina. English Literature, English, History, German. Garrett, Stuart Grayson (5) Seattle, Wash. B.S., University of Virginia. Geology, Petrology. Graham, Palmer Hampton (5) Jonesville, Va. B.A., Emory and Henry College, Va.; M.A., University of Virginia. Astronomy. Grant, Benjamin Ernest (2) Lodi, Va. B.A., King College, Tenn. English Literature, Economics, Education. Green, Jesse Henry (4) Clifton Forge, Va. B.A., Virginia Christian College; M.A., University of Virginia. Gwathmey, Edward Moseley (1) Richmond, Va. B.A., Richmond College, Va. English, English Literature, History. Hall, Eugene Hedgman (2) Lynhams, Va. B.A., William and Mary College, Va. Education, English. Harrison, John Letcher (7) University, Va. B.A., M.A., University of Virginia. English Literature, German, Italian. Howard, Kalford Wall (6) Portsmouth, Va. B.S., University of Virginia. Zoölogy. Huffman, Charles Herbert (1) Mt. Crawford, Va. B.A., Bridgewater College, Va.; M.A., Clark University, Mass. Philosophy, English Literature, English. Ingram, Joseph Robinson (1) Glade Spring, Va. B.A., Richmond College, Va. Organic Chemistry, Philosophy, English, Analytical Chemistry, Industrial Chemistry. Jacob, Cary Franklin (4) Richmond, Va. B.S., University of Virginia. English Literature, German, English. REGISTER OF STUDENTS. Johnson, Thomas Cary, Jr. (1) Richmond, Va. B.A., Hampden-Sidney College, Va. English, English Literature, Philosophy. Keith, William Steptoe (1) Anniston, Ala. B.A., Alabama Presbyterian College. History, Economics, Philosophy, English Literature. Kerr, James (5) Norfolk, Va. B.A., University of Virginia. Latin, Greek, French, German. Lehman, Ernest Linwood (4) Suffolk, Va. B.A., University of Virginia. Greek, Philosophy, Latin. Luck, Thomas Stuart (2) Ashland, Va. B.A., Randolph Macon College, Va.; M.A., University of Virginia. History, Economics, German. Lunger, Henry Jacob (4) Charlottesville, Va. M.A., Transylvania University, Ky. English. McCormick, Dougald Stuart (1) Manchester, N. C. B.A., Davidson College, N. C. History, Philosophy, English. McIlwaine, William Baird, III (4) Petersburg, Va. B.A., Hampden-Sidney College, Va. Education. Massie, Robert Kinloch, Jr. (4) University, Va. B.A., University of Virginia. English, Political Science, Philosophy, Education. Morton, Richard Lee (3) Meherrin, Va. B.A., Hampden-Sidney College, Va.; M.A., University of Virginia. History, Economics, German. Nelson, Alexander Hamilton (6) University, Va. B.A., M.A., University of Virginia. Portuguese, Journalism, English Literature. Oglesby, Earnest Jackson (4) Glade Spring, Va. B.A., Emory and Henry College, Va.; M.A., University of Virginia. Mathematics. Oglesby, Nicholas Ewing (4) Draper, Va. B.A., University of Virginia. Political Science, Analytical Chemistry, Physics, Economics. REGISTER OF STUDENTS. Paine, Frederic Howard (2) Charlottesville, Va. B.A., Colby College, Maine. German, French, Botany, Spanish, Italian. Pate, William Robertson (5) Albany, Ga. B.A., University of Virginia. Analytical Chemistry, Chemistry, English. Powers, David Pinckney (4) Richmond, Va. B.A., University of Virginia. English Literature, Economics, Philosophy, Biblical History and Literature. Rogers, William Hudson (1) Amelia C. H., Va. B.A., Davidson College, N. C. Latin, English, English Literature. Scott, Robert Dinken (3) Blue Ridge Springs, Va. A.B., B.D., Virginia Christian College. Biblical History and Literature, Philosophy, French, German. Scott, William John (1) Cape Charles, Va. B.A., Hampden-Sidney College, Va. Zoölogy, Geology, Chemistry, Spanish, Latin. Smither, Richard Ellis (5) Saluda, Va. B.A., University of Virginia. Economics, History, English. Snavely, Tipton Ray (2) Pennington Gap, Va. B.A., Emory and Henry College, Va.; M.A., University of Virginia. Economics, Political Science. Voigt, Gilbert Paul (2) Columbia, S. C. B.A., Newberry College, S. C. German, English. SUMMARY BY STATES. Alabama 1 Georgia 1 Kansas 1 North Carolina 1 South Carolina 1 Virginia 41 Washington 1 Total 47</field>
   </doc>
</add>