<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University of Virginia., Library</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University of Virginia., Library</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university of virginia library</field>
      <field name="author_text">University of Virginia., Library</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2006_01/uvaBook/tei/z000000557.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240342</field>
      <field name="date_text"/>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:182385</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Annual report on historical collections University of Virginia Library. [Vol.] twentieth, 1949-1950</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Archives -- Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Manuscripts -- United States</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Virginia -- History -- Sources</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Archives -- Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Manuscripts -- United States</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Virginia -- History -- Sources</field>
      <field name="title_display">Annual report on historical collections University of Virginia Library.  [Vol.] twentieth, 1949-1950</field>
      <field name="title_facet">annual report on historical collections university of virginia library</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">annual report on historical collections university of virginia library</field>
      <field name="title_text">Annual report on historical collections University of Virginia Library.  [Vol.] twentieth, 1949-1950</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1949</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:182385&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:182385&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;serial volume&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;University of Virginia., Library&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;university of virginia, library&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Annual report on historical collections University of Virginia Library. [Vol.] twentieth, 1949-1950&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;annual report on historical collections university of virginia library&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia., Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Annual report on historical collections University of Virginia Library&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="volume"&gt;[Vol.] twentieth&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1949-1950&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="LC call number"&gt;CD3560 .V5 v.16-20 1945-1950&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;X000467433&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;o04107376&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;[250]-[341] p. ; 23 cm.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Archives -- Virginia&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Manuscripts -- United States&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Virginia -- History -- Sources&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covplace&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;United States&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covplace&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covplace&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covplace&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Annual report on historical collections University of Virginia Library&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="volume"&gt;[Vol.] 20&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1949-1950&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2006&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2006 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 225 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA LIBRARY Harry Clemons Librarian</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DIVISION OF RARE BOOKS AND MANUSCRIPTS Including the Byrd Library, the Coles Collection, and the McGregor Library John Cook Wyllie Curator of Rare Books Ruth Evelyn Byrd Assistant, Rare Books Lucy T. Clark Cataloguer George O. Davis, Jr. Assistant, Maps Virginia R. Corey Photographer Jean C. McCauley Secretary Francis L. Berkeley, Jr. Curator of Manuscripts Frank L. Evans, Jr. Assistant, Manuscripts Constance E. Thurlow Assistant, Manuscripts Helen M. Godwin Assistant, Newspapers Elizabeth Hoskins Photographer Carol Tanner Secretary Louise Savage Acquisitions Librarian</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ADVISORY COMMITTEES TRACY W. McGREGOR LIBRARY: Thomas Perkins Abernethy; David K. E. Bruce; Harry Clemons; Colgate W. Darden, Jr., Chairman; Henry S. Hulbert, Vice-Chairman; Kenneth L. Moore; Robert B. Tunstall; John Cook Wyllie, Curator and Secretary. ALFRED HENRY BYRD LIBRARY and the ELIZABETH COCKE COLES COLLECTION: Thomas Perkins Abernethy, Francis L. Berkeley, Jr., Harry Clemons, Bernard Mayo, Louise Savage John Cook Wyllie, Edward Younger.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">HARRY CLEMONS AND THE TWENTIETH ANNUAL REPORT TWENTY YEARS AGO when the first of these annual reports was issued, Harry Clemons, then in his fourth year as Librarian of the University, had recently set aside the southeast wing of Mr. Jefferson's Rotunda as a "Virginia Room," dedicated to the housing of and to research in Virginia manuscripts and related materials. Aided and abetted by the late John Calvin Metcalf, Dean of the Department of Graduate Studies, he was beginning his planning and campaigning for the Alderman Library building, which was to open its doors in 1938. This twentieth report goes to press late enough for us to enclose in it an issue of the University of Virginia News Letter (Vol. XXVII, No. 15) which discusses some aspects of the collecting and preservation of "Manuscripts in Virginia, 1930-1950," a subject which in these reports must usually be confined to the manuscripts work of our own library, Mr. Clemons' library. Readers of these reports will recall that a cumulative index for the first fifteen reports was issued several years ago. A similar index to the reports for 1945 to 1950 will be issued shortly, and will be sent to libraries, and also to individuals who request it. The two decades which have passed since our first report have witnessed extraordinary development, not only of the historical collections and the other departments of the University Library, but in libraries and librarianship throughout Virginia. It is more than coincidence that this growth has taken place during the administration of the University Library by Harry Clemons. His name is linked directly or indirectly with so many library developments in Virginia that it is particularly fitting that this introduction to the twentieth report should carry at least a thumbnail sketch of his career up to now. A happy feature of his retirement at the close of the 1949-50 academic year is that he is to remain at the University to do research in his library, where his wise counsel will be, as always, available to us all. HARRY CLEMONS, LIBRARIAN Harry Clemons, who retired as librarian of the University of Virginia on June 30, 1950, has served in that post since 1927. During his incumbency, he has seen the University's enrollment expand from 2,000 to 5,000, with especially heavy growth in the graduate and professional departments. The collections of catalogued printed books have grown during his administration from 150,000 to more than 575,000 volumes, the manuscripts from a few thousand to over 3,500,000 pieces, while picture and print collections of 50,000 and map collections of 68,000 items have been assembled. Several developments during these years, including the acquisition of some notable special libraries, have made the University a center for American studies, with unusual strength in regional materials of the southeastern states. Mr. Clemons was graduated from Wesleyan University in 1902 with the B.A. degree, receiving the M.A. at the same university in 1905, and the Litt. D. in 1942. Pursuing post-graduate studies as a Scribner fellow at Princeton University, 1903-4 (M.A., 1905) and as a Jacobus fellow of Princeton at Oxford University, 1906-7, he later studied in the School of Library Service at Columbia University in 1927. Beginning as a library assistant at Wesleyan in 1902, he served as instructor of English at Princeton, 1904-6 and 1907-8, and reference librarian of Princeton from 1908 until 1913. A year after his appointment as professor of English (1913-1920) in the University of Nanking, China, he became librarian of the same university, a position which he held (with a brief "furlough" interlude in 1922 with the Chinese collection at the Library of Congress) until the Communist uprising (the "Nanking Incident") of 1927, when he returned to the United States and began his librarianship at Virginia. During World War I Mr. Clemons served as official representative of the A. L. A. in charge of library war service with the American Expeditionary Force in Siberia. During World War II he made room at the University of Virginia for the Library of Congress Union Catalog and its staff as well as for manuscripts deposited by the Library of Congress, and furnished special reference services for various military organizations. He is the author or editor of several books, and his memberships in library and other organizations are not few. But these are enumerated in Who's Who in America, and it is of more significance at this moment to suggest some of the milestones in his library administration. These included, at Princeton, the expansion of library service coincident with the establishment of the Preceptorial System by President Woodrow Wilson; at Nanking, the organization of a college library, the development of its services in ways appropriate to Chinese needs, and the training of a Chinese staff; and at Charlottesville only a few items will be mentioned from a list that might be greatly expanded. Such are the recataloguing of the printed books in the Library of Congress classification; the appointment in 1930 of the University's first archivist as a library official, and the creation of a regional collection of historical source materials; the campaign and planning for the Alderman Library building and the removal to it in 1938 of the general library from Jefferson's Rotunda; the creation of a department of rare books; the compilation, 1933-1943, of the checklist of the surviving papers of Thomas Jefferson; the development of a cooperative project for the preservation of all newspapers published in Virginia; the acquisition by the University of such special collections as the McGregor Library of southeastern Americana and English literature, the Coles collection of Virginia books and manuscripts, the Lomb optical collection, the Mackay-Smith music collection, the Stone library on the history of printing, the Streeter collection of material on southeastern railways, the Sadleir-Black collection of Gothic novels, the Taylor collection of American novels, and the Victorius collection on evolution; the establishment of nearly a score of special endowment funds for the purchase of books; and the activities of the University of Virginia library as publisher of the Annual Report on Historical Collections (twenty reports to date), of the University of Virginia Bibliographical Series (nine volumes to date), and of the publications of the McGregor Library (of which eight have already been issued). Mr. Clemons would himself earnestly disclaim any part in many of these and other projects except approval. To quote his own words, he insists that he has merely "helped to create and maintain an atmosphere in which new ideas would have free motion" and that he had had "an amazingly alert and original group of associates." During the second world war Mr. Clemons assumed a heavy load of library detail. Postwar developments expanded more rapidly than did the staff, and it seemed necessary for him to continue to carry much of that detail. His work schedule (8:00 A.M. to 2:00 P.M. and 8:00 P.M. to 2:00 A.M., the morning portion being omitted on Sundays) has attracted considerable local interest. Many of the night hours have been devoted to the conduct of an extensive correspondence, by means of which he has cultivated friends for the library. The charm of Mr. Clemons' letters is something of a legend. Over all the twenty-three years of his librarianship at Virginia, Mr. Clemons has striven untiringly for the development of the library as a research institution and as an institution for willing service; for the raising of the professional standards of his own staff and of librarians throughout Virginia; and above all for the fostering of the cooperative spirit among American libraries. Referring recently to Mr. Clemons' assistance to Princeton's Jefferson publication project, Julian Boyd wrote that "as an American and quite aside from its effect on my personal plans, I felt proud of the country that could produce such magnanimity of spirit at the head of an important institution." Note: This sketch, prepared for College and Research Libraries, Vol. XI, No. 4 (October, 1950), pp. 382-383, is reprinted here by permission of the Editor. To do honor to Mr. Clemons' continuing work for the library, and to guarantee the future of the library's publications, a group of Mr. Clemons' friends have established the Harry Clemons Publication Fund. Future gifts to the Fund from Alumni and other friends of the library can do much to extend the library's usefulness beyond the walls. One hundred copies of the first publication issued on the Fund, The Fry and Jefferson Map of Virginia and Maryland, a facsimile edition, with an introduction by Dumas Malone, were presented to Mr. Clemons on 11 May 1950, twelfth anniversary of the McGregor Library and of the Alderman Library building. —Francis L. Berkeley, Jr. Curator of Manuscripts October 1950</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EXPLANATORY NOTES MOST ENTRIES describe the manuscripts of a single acquisition, all the items in such a group being usually the papers of the single individual or family whose name is given. Dates in parentheses following names are birth and death dates. Dates not in parentheses indicate inclusive years of the manuscripts, with an occasional added date in parentheses to show the period covered by the bulk of the material. Thus 1725 (1900)-1928 means that while the earliest manuscript is dated 1725, the majority of papers fall in the period after 1900; 1805-(1850)1910 means that the body of the material ends in 1850, with a few scattered items up to 1910; and 1791 (1840-1860) 1902 means that the bulk of the papers fall between 1840 and 1860. Abbreviations, MS for manuscript, ALS for autograph letter, signed, etc., are those in common use. Numbers which appear at the end of each heading are accession numbers, included for their convenience to the library staff. As used in this report, "manuscripts" is the all-embracing term used to describe all handwritten items on parchment or paper, and our policy is to employ this expression not only in the general sense for all handwritten material, but also specifically for what some institutions describe as "personal papers," namely the unofficial writings of persons and families. "Papers," as used herein, indicate a special kind of manuscripts, the writings of a public officer, and are official or semi-official in character. It is misleading, we feel, to use "papers" as a general substitute for "manuscripts." "Archives" are the official manuscripts, or "records," of a government or other institution. The word "collection" may be used broadly to describe a single group of manuscripts, such as the manuscripts of a single acquisition, but more specifically for an artificially assembled group, such as an autograph collection. Non-manuscript material, other than books, acquired for the historical collections will be found under the following headings: Broadsides, Maps, Microfilm, Newspapers, and Prints and Pictures. Under University of Virginia a statement regarding the University's archives is given. The names of depositors of manuscripts on loan to the University are not included; it should be understood that while the majority of such manuscripts are accessible for research, all are subject to such restrictions as the depositor has made, and none may be reproduced without consent of the owner.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">MATERIALS ACQUIRED 1 July 1949 to 30 June 1950 AITKEN, ROBERT INGERSOLL. 1919 Nov. 4. 1 LS. Gift of William Bainter O'Neal. No. 3359. To Dr. Edwin A. Alderman, President of the University of Virginia, concerning the George Rogers Clark Monument, Charlottesville, Virginia, for which Aitken was commissioned as sculptor. ALBEMARLE, ANNE, COUNTESS OF. 1744 Aug. 24. 1 ALS. Deposit. No. 3419. To Mr. Stover concerning a debt. ALBEMARLE COUNTY, VIRGINIA. ante 1775. 1 DS. Gift. No. 3433. Pre-Revolutionary warrant issued by Justice Nicholas Meriwether to Aron Mackinse to appear before any one of "his Majesty's Justices for the County" to answer the complaint of James Meriwether on the payment of a 14—shilling bill. ALBEMARLE COUNTY, VIRGINIA. 1782-1783. 1 vol. Coles Collection. No. 3455. Sheriff's ledger of [Nicholas] Hamner, for collection of parish and county levies and taxes on land and livestock. In the back is a list of county records "saved from destruction of the enemy." Entries include: John Blair, Joseph Cabell, Charles Clay, James Cocke, John Coles, Bennett Henderson, John Henderson, Charles Irving, Thomas Jefferson, Charles Lewis, Isham Lewis, Philip Mazzei, Robert C. Nicholas, Wilson Cary Nicholas, James Quarles, John Randolph, and Thomas Staples, and the estate of John Fry, and members of the Bailey, Carter, Dollins, Goolsby, Hamner, Jones Langford, Martin, Melton, Morris, Smith, Stockton, Wood, Woods, Woolfolk, and other families. ALBEMARLE COUNTY, VIRGINIA. 1872 Oct. 30. 1 item. Gift of Mrs. Cammann C. Duke. No. 3305. An advertisement for sale of 2800 acres of land by George C. Gilmer. ALBEMARLE COUNTY FAMILIES. 8 items. Deposit. No. 3426. Genealogical notes on the Beck, Carr, Fitch, and Thurman families, of Albemarle County. ALBEMARLE COUNTY HISTORICAL SOCIETY COLLECTIONS. The manuscripts owned by the Society, and deposited in the Alderman Library for safekeeping, are kept in a special set of locked files in the Manuscript Reading Room. They are available for research. Some of the more outstanding acquisitions are reported in these pages. For a complete description of accessions see the annual report of the archivist in the Papers of the Albemarle County Historical Society, published annually since March 1941. ALEXANDRIA, VIRGINIA. 1840 July 1. 1 DS. Deposit. No. 3249. Bond of Daniel Bryan as postmaster of Alexandria, Va., witnessed by Peter Laphen, B. F. Gallahen, and F. C. Collins, and signed by R. U. Brooking, Justice of the Peace of Orange, Va. ALLYN, JOSEPH TYLER. 1861-1903. 16 items. Deposit. No. 3344. Two letters to his father from the University of Virginia, 1861; official copy of the recommendation for his promotion to captain in the Confederate Army, 1864; diary of his European tour, 1866; copy of address on his Civil War experiences, and a description of the Virginia—Monitor battle. ARITHMETIC BOOK. ca. 1800. 1 vol. Deposit. No. 3407. Manuscript arithmetic book, containing problems and solutions by John Fray, Albemarle County, Virginia. ASHBY, TURNER (1828-1862). 1861-1862. 2 items. Deposit. No. 3199. Picture of the Confederate General and photograph of his gravestone. ASHBY FAMILY. 120 items. Deposit. No. 3199. Genealogical notes on Thomas Ashby (1690?-1752) and his descendants and the related Buck, Moncure, and Turner families of Clarke, Fauquier, and Warren counties, Virginia, from 18th to 20th centuries, compiled by Mrs. Mary Ashby Graham. ASTOR, VISCOUNTESS. 1922 May 10. 1 ALS. Gift of Mrs. Richard Gwathmey. No. 3358. To Mrs. Charles Talbott from Rose Hill, Greenwood, Virginia; original and typed copy. ATKINSON, ROGER (1725-1784). 1762-1803. 1 vol. Gift of Thomas W. Atkinson. No. 3238. Account book containing invoices for shipments received from London and Glasgow, 1762, with copies of 14 letters to Benson Fearon, Samuel Pleasants, and John Ponsonby, in which Continental Loan Office Certificates and the Battle of Yorktown are discussed, 1775-1789, and accounts of Thomas Atkinson, 1792-1803. AUDEN, WYSTAN HUGH. ca. 1949. 1 item. Deposit. No. 3350. Typescript of "The Enchafèd Flood", a study of the romantic iconography of the sea, with some autograph corrections by Auden. BACHE, FRANKLIN (1792-1864). 1864-1866. 3 vols. Gift of Howard S. Mott. No. 3389. Account books settling the estate of Benjamin Franklin's great-grandson, a professor of chemistry at Jefferson Medical College, Philadelphia. BATH COUNTY, VIRGINIA. 1801-1842. 3 items. Coles Collection. No. 3329. Land grants to John Lewis, signed by Governor James Monroe, 1801, and to Samuel Lewis, signed by Lieutenant Governor John Gregory, 1842. An indenture between John Brown, Sr., and his wife, Polly, and John Brown, Jr., 1809. BEALE, JANE B. 1850-1862. 1 vol. Deposit. No. 3288. Diary of Mrs. Beale of Fredericksburg, Va. including a detailed description of the capture of Fredericksburg and the campaign in 1862 in northern Virginia. BERGLUND, ABRAHAM. 1920-1940. 70 items. Gift from his estate. No. 1984. Additional material relating to his teaching and research in commerce and business administration, University of Virginia. See earlier reports. BIBLIOGRAPHY. 1950. 9 items. Gift of Fredson T. Bowers. No. 3491. Manuscript of W. W. Greg's "The Rationale of Copy-Text", sent by Greg to Professor Bowers, University of Virginia, for publication, with several letters from Greg to Bowers on bibliographical matters; and three letters to Bowers on his Principles of Bibliographical Description. BLEDSOE, ALBERT TAYLOR (1809-1877). 1838-1894. 120 items. Deposit. No. 3311. Collection of copies of original contemporary items, and some secondary material, relating to Bledsoe as professor at the University of Mississippi and the University of Virginia, and as editor of The Southern Review, collected by Mr. David Rankin Barbee. Photostats of thirty-six letters to Bledsoe, 1858-1875; of two series of newspaper articles by Bledsoe on the Civil War, 1861 and 18631864; typed copy of a memorandum book; list of his artcles that appeared in The Southern Review. Also notes on Maximilian Schele de Vere, professor at the University of Virginia, and F.A.P. Barnard, who became president of Columbia College, New York, in 1864, after leaving the south. BLEDSOE, ALBERT TAYLOR (1809-1877). 1858-1875. 25 items. Deposit. No. 3461. Letters from Jefferson Davis, Edwin De Leon, Stephen Elliott, Edward Everett (photostat), L.C. Gailand, S.S. Haldeman, Wade Hampton, Joseph Henry, John H. Hopkins, J.E. Johnston, L.Q.C. Lamar, R. E. Lee, William McClosky, Leonidas Polk, Margaret J. Preston, James Spence, F.H. Tremlett, and R.H. Wilmer. Related letters as follows: William Gladstone to Mr. Froude, Cornelia Grinnan to the Duke of Argyll introducing Bledsoe and M. O. W. Oliphant. Pass made out by Abraham Lincoln for Mrs. Harriet C. Bledsoe and autograph of Jefferson Davis for Miss Anna Bledsoe (photostats). Bledsoe was professor at the University of Virginia, Assistant Secretary of War in the Confederate Government when sent by Jefferson Davis to London to write on the issues of the Civil War, and founder and editor of the Southern Review. See also Herrick. BOLLING, LENEAUS (1773-1836). 1814. 1 vol. Deposit. No. 3006. Diary describing operations at his farm, Chellowe, Buckingham County, Va., expenses, social life, militia activities around Norfolk, and personal and family matters. From January to March 1814. BOUTWELL, MINSON and SAMUEL. 1855-1898. 60 items. Gift of David Rothman. No. 3325. Papers relating to service as sailmakers for the U. S. Navy (predominately Samuel's) 1855-1861 and 1873-1891, signed by ten different Secretaries and Acting Secretaries of Navy; deeds, indentures, U. S. tax receipts for 1864, Norfolk County, Virginia, and a Norfolk County court report containing genealogical information on the Hodges family, to which the Boutwells were related, 1861. BRADY, JAMES D. 1859-1900. 550 items. Gift of Mrs. James T. Rahily. No. 3436. Papers covering his career as officer in the Second Army Corps of the Army of the Potomac; as official of the Navy Yard, Portsmouth, Virginia; as Collector of Internal Revenue at Petersburg; and as leader in the Republican Party in Virginia. Material on his service in Congress, 1884-86, and his break with William Mahone. Collected in two scrapbooks. Documents include signatures of Presidents Rutherford B. Hayes, Benjamin Harrison, and other officials of the period. BRAMHAM, RACHEL. 1852-1890. 27 items. Gift of Mrs. George J. Collins. No. 3437. Personal letters from friends, relatives, and soldiers during Civil War to Rachal Bramham, Scottsville, Albemarle County, Va. BRANDUM, MARGARET. 1824 Dec. 11. 1 ALS. Coles Collection. No. 3307. A negro woman writes to Col. John and Charles Tucker about her claims as heir of a Revolutionary soldier. BRAXTON, ALLEN CAPERTON (1862-1914). 1883-1947. 52,000 items. Coles Collection. No. 3329. Papers concerning extensive law practice in Staunton and Richmond, consisting of letters, ledgers, and journals. Partners were Carter Braxton, Edward Echols, Richard Ker, Taylor McCoy, and Lewis C. Williams. Material on competitive practices of Virginia railroads, 1901-1902, the Virginia Constitutional Convention of 1902, of which Braxton was a prominent member, and attempts to place Braxton for Vice-President on the Democratic ticket in 1904. Letters of H. D. Flood, William A. Anderson, papers of Judge Henry Holt, (the administration of Braxton's estate, ca. 1920-1947), and ledgers of Hugh Braxton. BROADSIDES. Byrd, Coles, and McGregor libraries, deposits, and gifts of Rowland A. Egger, B. F. D. Runk, and others. Our rarer and more important broadsides have in recent years been made accessible through full cataloguing in our public catalogue. A somewhat larger number of the less rare but representative broadsides, especially of the nineteenth century and earlier, are, though uncatalogued, available in a chronological file in the manuscript reading room. Newspaper broadside-extras are filed and catalogued with the newspapers. But the majority of the late nineteenth and twentieth century broadsides, too bulky for individual handling, are stored in several major subject groupings. This year's accessions include, as usual, numerous Virginia and University broadsides, family "trees", war posters, Confederate bonds, and the like. Currency received ranges from Maryland Revolutionary paper of 1775 to the Japanese, English, and Dutch money of World War II presented by Mr. Runk. An out of the way item is the Gestapo seal placed on Mr. Egger's books at the International Institute of Administrative Sciences in Brussels from 1942 to 1946. BROADUS, JOHN ALBERT (1827-1895). 1850-1894. 405 items. Deposit. No. 3458. Letters to Dr. Broadus, professor and chaplain of the University of Virginia and president of the Southern Baptist Theological Seminary, Louisville, Kentucky from 1889-1895 from frequent writers: Maria C. Broadus (his wife), Noah K. Davis, E. L. C. Harrison, Samuel Chiles Mitchell, Mr. and Mrs. John D. Rockefeller, Francis H. Smith, Jacob Henry Smith, George Boardman Taylor, George Braxton Taylor, William M. Thornton, and Crawford H. Toy. Other correspondents include James Alexander, Albert Taylor Bledsoe, Mrs. H. C. Bledsoe, Sophie M. Bledsoe, Frederick W. Boatwright, Joseph C. Cabell, John Carr, John H. Cocke, Robert Lewis Dabney, John Staige Davis, Basil L. Gildersleeve, Gessner Harrison, Charles R. Hemphill, Frederick W. Holliday, Hollins Institute, Moses D. Hoge, Peyton Carr Hoge, Thomas Cary Johnson, W. Gordon McCabe, William H. McGuffey, Richard McIlwaine, Addison Maupin, Socrates Maupin, J. C. Metcalf, Lucian Minor, John B. Minor, Dwight L. Moody, William E. Peters, F. Petrie, Lizzie M. Railey, Bronson Ray, William Barton Rogers, Maximilian Schele de Vere, George Tucker, Zebulon B. Vance, Rosalie C. Vandergrift, and Charles S. Venable. Also available on microfilm is the card index to the entire Broadus Collection at the Southern Baptist Theological Seminary at Louisville, where the collection is located, and through whose courtesy the index and these selected letters were lent for microfilming. BROCKENBROUGH, JAMES CABELL. 1898-1899. 2 vols. Deposit. No. 3330. Notebooks of the Richmond, Va. civil engineer and teacher's trip through Italy and Switzerland. BROOKE, FRANCIS TALIAFERRO (1763-1851). 1825 April 27. 1 item. Gift of Herbert B. Chermside. No. 3331. Photostat of letter written at "St. Julien" to Robert S. Brooke. Supplements Brooke manuscripts previously acquired. BRUCE FAMILY OF BERRY HILL. 1817-1898. 1 item and 16 vols. Deposit. No. 2692. Additional manuscripts of James Coles Bruce (1806-1865) of Berry Hill, Halifax County, Va., including twelve account books of his Meadsville Mills, 1841-1854; journal of tobacco shipments and prices, 1817-1825; cash accounts, 1843-1849; list of debts owed him, 1 May 1846; and two ledgers of Bruce family accounts in settling his estate by Alexander Bruce, 1865-1898, with references to Berry Hill, 1865-1879, and mentioning Eliza W., Rosa, Thomas, Walter C., and William B. Bruce; Lancaster &amp; Co., R. H. Maury &amp; Co.; and State Bank of Virginia. Previous acquisitions of manuscripts of the Bruces of Berry Hill and of the related family, the Bruces of Staunton Hill, Charlotte County, are described in sixteenth-seventeenth and eighteenth-nineteenth annual reports. BRUNSWICK COUNTY. 1813-1836. 7 items. Coles Collection. No. 3307. Three militia lists for Brunswick County as follows: return of Captain Richard Trotter's company, 2nd Batallion, 66th Regiment, 15th Brigade, 1st Division of Virginia militia, 6 November 1813; return of Green Hill's troop of cavalry attached to 66th Regiment for April 1817; and return of James B. Mallory's company of light infantry, 2nd Batallion, 66th Regiment, April 1817. Two Brunswick County Court Claims, 24 June 1822, and June 1833. Two documents of sheriff summoning David Jones to prove will of Micajah Harristed. 18 April 1832 and Thomas I. Bishop and James L. Wright in case of Pegram &amp; Boisseau, 9 April 1836. BRYAN FAMILY. 1770-1887. 719 items. Deposit. No. 3400. Manuscripts of the Bryan, Coalter, Randolph, and Tucker families, consisting chiefly of letters to and from the following: Elizabeth T. Coalter Bryan, 1812-1887, John Randolph Bryan, 1818-1835, Joseph C. Cabell, 1804-1827, Frances B. Tucker Coalter, 1791-1831, John Coalter, 1788-1832, St. George Coalter, 1822-1826, Francis Walker Gilmer, 1818-1821, John Randolph, Sr., 1770-1774, John Randolph of Roanoke, 1781-1833, Judith Randolph, 1796-1814, Nathaniel Beverley Tucker, 1804-1851, and St. George Tucker, 17811826. 150 letters (some of them copies) of John Randolph of Roanoke and 200 of St. George Tucker's letters. Other correspondents include: Theoderick Bland, Theoderick Bland, Jr., Delia F. Bryan, Thomas M. F. Bryan, Richard Randolph, St. George Randolph, Theoderick Randolph, John Taylor, Henry St. George Tucker, Lelia Tucker, Thomas Tudor Tucker, and William Wirt. There are also copies of the Augusta, Georgia, Weekly Republic, 9 July 1850, the Union Seminary Magazine for September-October 1893, and the Petersburg, Virginia, Index-Appeal, 24 February 1901. BUCKINGHAM COUNTY, VIRGINIA. 1819-1877. 12 vols. Deposit. No. 3378. Account books of the general store at New Store kept by Louis D. Jones and others, 1819-1821, 1835-1844, and 1856-1877. CANADAY, JOHN EDWIN. 1943-1949. 9 items. Gift of Professor Canaday. No. 3495. First and final typescript versions of four mystery stories by the Professor of Art at the University, written under the pseudonym of Matthew Head, and published by Simon and Schuster in their Inner Sanctum series: The Smell of Money, 1943; The Devil in the Bush, 1945; The Accomplice, 1947; and The Cabinda Affair, 1949. See also eighteenth-nineteenth annual report. CHARLOTTESVILLE, VIRGINIA. 1843-1847. 3 vols. Gift of Mrs. Cammann C. Duke. No. 3305. Two account books of a store-inn, one inscribed Hugh Minor and headed "Monticello House", and a ledger. CHARLOTTESVILLE, VIRGINIA. 1896-1938. 4 vols. Gift of Mrs. J. Callan Brooks. No. 3312. Guest registers for Lee Hall, Mrs. L. B. LeTellier's tourist home, 1929 and 1935-1938. In one of them is a register of white voters of the Fourth Ward recording original registrations, 1896-1904, and ward transferrals, 1916-1933. CHARLOTTESVILLE, JANIE PORTER BARRETT DAY NURSERY. 1943-1948. 75 items. Deposit. No. 3283. Records and correspondence including copies of constitution and certificate of incorporation, financial statements, and executive committee and board meetings of this nursery for pre-school Negro children. CHIANG KAI-SHEK, MME. 1932 Apr. 15. 1 ALS. Deposit. No. 3324. Madame Chiang, in Nanking, China, writes about her two children's school work to Miss Helena Koiner, their teacher. CLAY, HENRY (1777-1852). 1798-1799. 2 items. Deposit. No. 3261. DS and ADS, 21 September 1798, as a court and county official in Kentucky, Fayette, and Woodford counties. CLAY, HENRY. 1824 Jan. 14. 1 ALS. Coles Collection. No. 3472. To Robert R. Henry, of Albany, New York, on alleged malpractices of government officials called to his attention by Mr. Henry. CLAY, HENRY. 1838 Aug. 28. 2 items. Gift of Bernard Mayo. No. 3417. Letter to C. C. Baldwin on slavery, internal improvements, and the Bank of the U. S.; photostat with typed copy. CLAY, HENRY. 1844-1851. 7 items. Deposit. No. 3402. Copies of letters published in newspapers: on secession, 1844 and 1851; on the Philadelphia Convention, 1848; on the recognition of Liberia by the U. S., 1851; and on his defeats; to Benjamin Coates, Stephen H. Miller, and D. Ulman. CLEVELAND, GROVER (1837-1908). 1888 Feb. 7. 1 DS. Deposit. No. 3261. Grant of land in Kansas, subject to law encouraging the growth of timber, 1888. COALTER, JOHN. 1808-1835. 46 items. Deposit. No. 3321. Correspondence of the Staunton, Va. judge (son of the explorer and trapper) who married Frances Bland Tucker, half-sister of John Randolph of Roanoke, and some letters of the following: Elizabeth Tucker, John Randolph, and Joseph Bryan; Joseph Carrington Cabell; Dr. Carr; Frances Bland Tucker, and Francilea Coalter; Mrs. Frances Davenport, including a copy of her will; Judith Randolph; Beverley, Henry St. George, Lelia, and St. George Tucker; and William Wirt. COCKE, JOHN HARTWELL (1780-1866). 1858 Oct. 30. 1 item. Coles Collection. No. 3444. Covenant of John Hartwell Cocke to convey a large house (erected for a hotel) on a four-acre lot near the University of Virginia, and of Philip St. George Cocke to give $20,000 of University bonds to William Cabell Rives and William H. Macfarland, as trustees for the establishment of an Agricultural College of Virginia near the University of Virginia. COCKE FAMILY. 1852-1865. 285 items. Deposit. No. 3272. Additional letters and accounts of General John H. Cocke (17801866) and General Philip St. George Cocke (1809-1861) which supplement the files of each previously deposited. This group deals largely with the Civil War career of Philip St. George Cocke; and material on White Sulphur Springs, the James River and Kanawha Canal Company, and Kentucky lands. Correspondents include P. G. T. Beauregard, Jubal Early, J. B. Cocke, and Jeremiah Morton. COCKRELL, MONROE F. 1926-1949. 63 items. Gift of Mr. Cockrell. Nos. 3357 and 3393. "Where was Pickett at Gettysburg?"—a detailed study of the activities of Confederate General George Edward Pickett (18251875) at the battle, compiled from primary and secondary sources, typescript; collection of 62 clippings on Thomas Jefferson. CONNOR, WILLIAM MELLARD (1878-1949). 1920-1949. 400 items. Gift of Colonel Connor's estate. No. 3287. Papers of the former member of the Judge Advocate General's Staff, teacher on various phases of military law and authority on local government in the Philippine Islands. Included is a copy of his dissertation submitted to Harvard Law School, 1929, for degree of Doctor of Juridical Science—"The Government of the Moro Province a Legal Experiment in the Delegation of General Legislative Power to a Local Legislative Body." Among the correspondents in the collection were: James F. Brynes, Garwood Glenn, and William Lile. CRENSHAW, MAY V. 1913-1921. 250 items. Gift of Miss Crenshaw. No. 3289. Papers and correspondence relating to her effective campaign for the establishment of a public library in Charlottesville to serve Charlottesville and Albemarle County, and to her library work at the New York Public Library, New York, Carnegie Public Library, Paducah, Ky., Virginia State Library, Richmond, Va., and special work for the United War Fund Drive among libraries in Virginia. Also included are many of her class notes and a copy of her thesis, "Public Libraries in the South," presented to the Library School of the New York Public Library, where she graduated in 1915. DABNEY, CHARLES WILLIAM (1855-1945). ca. 1945. 1 volume. Deposit. No. 3308. Typescript of his memoirs, including accounts of his activities on behalf of education in the South, as President of the University of Tennessee, 1887-1904, and as President of the University of Cincinnati, 1904-1920. DABNEY, CHISWELL. 1805-1865. 310 items. Gift of Mrs. Edward W. Saunders. No. 3315. Correspondence relating to his law practice in Lynchburg, Va., and the affairs of the Dabney family, including their lands in Hanover County and Lynchburg; George Dabney's will, 1821; letters of William Cabell Rives, 1837, introducing Chiswell Dabney to Mallon Dickerson, Secretary of the Navy, Joel R. Poinsett, Secretary of War, and to Maj. W. R. Lewis, Second Auditor; diary of George William Dabney, Clerk of Campbell County, Va., 1862-1865. Correspondents include Mary Allen; Ann D. Brown; Triplett Burnley; Bowling Clark; Robert Criald; Catherine M., Cornelia, Elizabeth, George E., Jane, John B., John F., Mary Jane, Sarah E., and William B. Dabney; G. Fontaine; Catherine M. Grantland; S. Grantland; David Herndon; Sarah Hoffman; Sarah E. Langhorne; J. S. Langhorne; John and Mary Lynch; James Mallory William Mapie; John and Richard Morris; Lucy B. and Van R. Otey; E. B. Pearson; Elizabeth and William Pollard; William Pope, Nancy Richeson; Thomas Robinson; A. Stuart; John and Philip Tabb; George Tucker; Moses Watkins; and Lucy W. Wharton. DARWIN-EVOLUTION COLLECTION. 1784-1921. 120 items. Anonymous gift. No. 3314. Letters, manuscripts, prints, photographs, and drawings dealing with people who contributed to the theory of evolution. Correspondents include Samuel Butler, John Chapman, Charles Darwin, Erasmus Darwin, Francis Galton, James Hall, J. W. Herschel, James D. Hooker, Thomas Huxley, Charles Lyell, Herbert Spencer, Alfred R. Wallace, and J. P. Mansel Weale. These manuscripts constitute only a small portion of the Darwin-Evolution collection, which consists principally of printed works, largely first editions and association copies. DAVIS, JACKSON. 1937-1947. 3,000 items. Deposit. No. 3072. Papers, professional and personal, of Jackson Davis, Associate director of the General Education Board. Correspondence with Alexander Armour, College of William and Mary, J. Curtis Dixon, J. H. Dillard, Leo M. Ravrot, Paul Foreman, Hampton Institute, W. T. Hodges, Griffin Lamkin, Phi Beta Kappa, Dr. W. T. Sanger, and the Virginia Education Commission. Also 500 photographs and slides taken during his field trips through the South and in Liberia. DAVIS, JOHN STAIGE (1824-1885). 1839-1885. 500 items. Deposit. No. 3247. Papers of the University of Virginia physician and teacher, consisting of about 450 letters, three University of Virginia diplomas, 1839, and eighteen manuscript notebooks, including epistolary records, 1860-1885, copies of letters sent, 1858-1869, and extensive list of Southern doctors by states, ca. 1870. DAVIS, JOHN STAIGE (1824-1885). 1863 June 2. 1 ALS. Coles Collection. No. 3361. To Lantz M. Blackford at General James Longstreet's Headquarters, Hamilton's Crossing, Virginia, quoting prices on a ledger that Blackford wished Dr. Davis to purchase for him. DAVIS, JOHN STAIGE (1866-1933). 1879-1927. 5,700 items. Deposit. No. 3247. Papers, consisting of over 5,500 letters, fifty-six manuscript notebooks, including school notes as well as medical records, and medical slides. Included is a letter box containing correspondence and medical records of Dr. T. Duckett Jones, University of Virginia Hospital, 1926-1927. DAVIS, W. W. 1849 June 23. 1 ALS. Coles Collection. No. 3333. To Benjamin E. Payne describing serious monetary difficulties resulting from the irresponsibilities of Mr. Forest, his partner in publishing the "Temperance Advocate." DENNY, BISHOP COLLINS (1854-1943). 1876-1930. 25 items. Gift of Collins Denny, Jr. No. 2672. Additional material from the estate of Bishop Denny, the late Methodist Bishop including: reports of the American Presbyterian Mission in Syria, 1876-1886; of the Methodist Episcopal Church (South) General Conferences in 1914 and 1918; some World War I broadsides and clippings; and two letters to Rev. L. E. Alford, Vicksburg, Miss. DEWEY, JOHN. 1942-1949. 5 items. Gift of Albert G. A. Balz. Nos. 3219 and 3394. Address by Dewey at Hollins College Centennial on "Religion and Morality in a Free Society," 1942, with introductory remarks by Dr. Balz. Program and seating arrangement for the special dinner at the Hotel Commodore, New York, 20 October, 1949, and issues of The New Leader, 22 October, in honor of Dewey's ninetieth birthday. DINWIDDIE, EMILY. 1902-1937. 530 items and 8 vols. Gift of the estate of Miss Dinwiddie. No. 3194. Correspondence, reports, and other data when a social worker in Wichita, Kansas; notes on courses at George Washington University, 1926; and other material, including: lectures, sermons, garden notebook, 1902-1934, notes on Lebanon Presbyterian Church 1824-1933, with list of baptisms, poetry notebook, and scrapbooks. DINWIDDIE, ROBERT (1693-1770). 1757 Dec. 15. 1 DS. Deposit. No. 3371. Land grant from George II to Henry Shelton for 29 acres in Louisa County, signed by Robert Dinwiddie, Governor. DINWIDDIE FAMILY. 1856-1940. 350 items and 30 vols. Gift of estate of Emily W. Dinwiddie. No. 3194. Additional material (including accounts, real estate transfers, insurance, bonds) relating to Greenwood, Albemarle County estate of Rev. William Dinwiddie (1830-1894) and Elizabeth Morton Dinwiddie; business correspondence and account books of Greenwood Fruit Farm operated by William A. Dinwiddie and Dinwiddie Brothers (Courtenay and Malcolm), 1896-1938; account books for the Greenwood School, 1889-1900; notes concerning Lebanon Church, Greenwood, Va.; tax receipts for Albemarle County, 1856-1907, Halifax County, 1851, and Charlottesville and Samuel Miller Districts, 1856-1888. The other members of the family included in the correspondence were: Mrs. Mary Agnes Bruce, Edgar, and William A. Dinwiddie, Jr. See eighteenth-nineteenth annual report. DIXIECRATS. 1948 Oct. 7. 1 item. Gift of Jack Dalton. No. 3037-b. Typescript of political address by Governor J. Strom Thurmond of South Carolina, the Party's presidential candidate, delivered at the University of Virginia and broadcast over radio station WCHV. DUKE, RICHARD THOMAS WALKER (1822-1898). 1870-1922. 6 ALS and 1 print. Gift of Mrs. Cammann C. Duke. No. 3305. Correspondence of Congressman Duke with J. H. Baker and W. Bath, Commissioners of Pensions, Mr. Fishburne; W. B. Robertson, Secretary of the Virginia Immigration Society, regarding the plans to accommodate some French immigrants from Alsace and Lorraine on 30,000 acres of land on both sides of James River Canal; print of autograph photograph of Duke as Grand Master; letter of W. R. Duke to Harris Hart, Superintendent of Public Instruction, 23 February 1922, inquiring per capita cost of instruction of school children. DUMMERSTON, VERMONT. 1808-1840. 1 vol. Deposit. No. 3298. Record book of the Dummerston Social Library, containing constitution and by-laws, list of books owned, and circulation records for each proprietor. DUNGLISON, ROBLEY (1798-1869). 1840 Apr. 11. 1 item. Gift of John M. Jennings. No. 3405. Photostat of letter to unspecified "Gentlemen," endorsed by Hugh Blair Grigsby, on a minor error in his Physiology. ECONOMISTS. 1949. 4 ALS. Gift (restricted). No. 2807. Letters of the following English and American economists on pertinent issues facing capitalism, government and labor unions: Raphael Demos, Alvin H. Hansen, Paul A. Samuelson, and John H. Williams. ECONOMISTS' NATIONAL COMMITTEE ON MONETARY POLICY. 1933-1949. 120 items. Gift of Elbert A. Kincaid. No. 3146-f. File of circular letters, pamphlets, and some correspondence on activities of the Committee, collected by Prof. Kincaid. ELIOT, THOMAS STEARNS. 1947 Mar. 21. 1 item. Gift of William J. Rushton. No. 3442. Printed program of the McGregor Room Seminar, "The Poetry of T. S. Eliot," by Willard Thorp, annotated by T. S. Eliot. FAIRFAX FAMILY. 1717-1944. 30 items. Deposit. No. 3463. Guest Book, signed by visitors at Belvoir, home of Lord Fairfax, Fairfax County, Virginia, 1737-1757, and by guests of the late Fairfax Harrison at the same house, 1909-1938, with genealogical data on the Cary, Fairfax, Harrison, and Washington families. Guests' autographs were written in the blank leaves of Ralph Thoresby's Ducatus Leodiensis, or the Topography of the Ancient and Populous Town and Parish of Leeds . . . , London, 1715. Passing through the hands of Miles and Christopher Gale between 1717 and 1728, the book reposed at Salem, Massachusetts, in the hands of William Fairfax, between 1728 and 1734. In its subsequent crossings of the Atlantic, the book was owned at various times by Joseph Hunter and by Henry Stevens, who added historical notes. Enclosures include family data in the hand of Wilson Miles Cary, the printed record of Albert Kirby Fairfax's successful claim to the Fairfax peerage in 1908, photostats of entries in the Herbert family Bible and the parish register of Pohick Church, and modern blueprints of Belvoir's house and lands. FAUQUIER, FRANCIS (1703-1768). 1759-1764. 2 DS. Deposit. Nos. 3302 and 3415. Land patent from George II, 16 March 1759, to Lawrence Young for 529 acres in Louisa County of part of 2400 acre grant to John Aylett, but forfeited by Joseph and Lydia Herron for failure to pay quit rents, and from George III, 15 August 1764, to Henry M. Daniel for 142 acres of land in Fauquier and Amherst counties, both signed by Francis Fauquier, Lieutenant Governor. FEILDEN, COL. SIR HENRY WEMYSS (1838-1921). 1860-1920. 150 items. Deposit and microfilm. Nos. 3372 and 3401. Papers and correspondence of the British soldier, naturalist, and scientist particularly concerning his service as Assistant Adjutant General under Gen. P. G. T. Beauregard, 1862-1865, and with his wife, the former Julia McCord, and her family of Charleston, S. C. Portions of the microfilm are from originals at the Library of Congress and the South Carolina Historical Society. Diary and correspondence of Colonel Feilden with Charlotte and R. S. Cheves, Julia McCord Feilden, John Johnson, Adele King, and Mary Magnoth, 1863-1890, including a description of the attack on Charleston and of Southern business and finance in this period; and with Gerald Smythe and Maj. Gen. R. S. Ripley, 1913-1921, mentioning Gordon McCabe. Scrapbook of Julia McCord Feilden, 1862-1890, containing poems of George Herbert Sass and Henry Timrod; three drawings relative to attack on Charleston, 7 April 1863; letter of General Beauregard, 16 July 1864; clipping of letter of General Early to New York News, 18 December 1865; and various Confederate autographs. Five photographs of Charleston and seventeen of the following Confederate officers: Capt. Robert Chisholm, Gen. Ewell, Lt. Col. Alf Freneau, Gen. Johnson Hagood, Charles Haskell, Gen. A. P. Hill, Weaver V. Hix, Gen. Jamieson, Laurence M. Keith, Gen. James W. Pace, Capt. J. W. V. Penill, Capt. Robert Pringle, R. B. Rhett, Jr., Lt. Col. T. B. Roy, Gen. Earl Van Dorn, and Lt. Col. J. R. Waddy. Sermon by Bishop Stephen Elliott, 18 September 1863; program of Washington Light Infantry Charitable Association, Charleston, 22 February 1869, with a poem of George Herbert Sass; fragment of Fort Moultrie flag, 1861; and note of Gen. Beauregard to Jefferson Davis, 26 September 1864. General Orders from Adjutant and Inspector-General's Office, Confederate States Army, Dept. of S. Carolina, Georgia, and Florida, 1862-1863 and 1864 (Columbia 1864 and —). Typescript of 55 letters, 19021921, to members of the McCord family in Charleston, S. C., concerning his activities and general conditions in England before and during World War I. FIELD, DR. JOHN A. 1867-1869. 1 vol. Coles Collection. No. 3307. Account book of this Brunswick County physician in the Reconstruction period. FOOTE, WILLIAM HENRY (1794-1869). 1848 Jan. 10. 1 ALS. Coles Collection. No. 3260. To Rev. Francis McFarland of Augusta County, Va., requesting information from the records of the Virginia Synod on a Rev. Mr. Graham, active in Presbyterian affairs in 1791-1792; mentions Hampden-Sydney College. FORT BROWN, GLOUCESTER POINT, VIRGINIA. 1862 Jan. 13. 1 item. Coles Collection. No. 3322. Colored manuscript map drawn during the Peninsular Campaign by James A. Overstreet. FOX FAMILY. 1647-1935. 38 items. Deposit. No. 3262. Fox Family Bible (1680, 6th Oxford edition) with typescript and photostat copies of the family records of David Fox, born 1647, who married Hannah Ball (daughter of William Ball and Hannah Atherod and great-aunt of George Washington) and of Richard Kenner and John Crawley. Known to genealogists as the "Fox Bible," it was used in Hayden's Virginia Genealogies. Fifteen letters concerning the families in the Bible from William M. Forrest, James Fox, Miss E. F. McCue, C. Purcell McCue, and others. Also included are genealogical notes on Opie, Ware, and Washington families and a printed genealogy of Savage and Kenner families by Laura Davis Worley. Other items include: articles from Southern Churchman, 1906-1907; Virginia Churchman, 1927; accounts of colonial churches in Lancaster County, Virginia. FRAY'S MILL RECORDS. 1806-1884. 64 vols. Deposit. No. 3407. Ledgers and other account books of John Fray and his grist mills in Albemarle, Green, Madison, and Orange counties, Va., 18111835, and of his business associates and later members of his family (Fray's Mill, near Earlysville, has continued in operation by the Fray family to the present day). Accounts of Speedwell, Madison, Bennett's Ford, Old Speedwell (later Creek Mills), and Robinson River mills. Three volumes, 1808-1818, are Thomas Bohannon's journals. A journal of 1846-1849 also includes Thomas N. Harrison's execution records, 1842-1844, as deputy sheriff of Madison County. Six volumes record Lewis A. Smith's management of Olive Mills, 1878-1884. One volume, 1835-1845, is Jacob Hite's ledger. FREEMAN, MARGARET. 1870 August 1. 1 ALS. Gift. No. 3453. To W. Torrey, thanking him for a copy of Whittier's "Snow Bound," and discussing her father, Philip Freeman (1818-1875), church architecture, Rheims Cathedral, Lord Bryce, and other matters. GARLAND, HUGH A. 1824-1947. 14 items. Gift of Miss Mary L. Garland. No. 3410. Two essays written at Hampden-Sydney; extracts from his diary, 1829-1830; several political speeches, 1832-1833; contemporary account of his life; shorter notes; and three pieces of correspondence about him, 1946-1947. GILMER, FRANCIS WALKER (1790-1826). 1815-1816. 1 item. Gift of Mr. Gilmer Craddock. No. 3278. Manuscript of Gilmer's Sketches of American Orators, 1815, published in 1816. GOOCH, ROBERT KENT. 1947-1949. 9 items. Gift of Professor Gooch. No. 3218. Broadsides and letters on federal union with Britain; Edward R. Stettinius's plan for the development of Liberia; and the University of Virginia radio station, WUVA. GOOCH, SIR WILLIAM (1681-1751). 1728 Sept. 28. 1 DS. Deposit. No. 3290. Grant of land in Brunswick County, Virginia, to William Brown, by George II, signed by Gooch as Lieutenant Governor of Virginia. GOODRICH, BENJAMIN B. 1836 March 15. 1 ALS. Deposit. No. 3327. Letter to Edmund Goodrich in Tennessee about General Santa Ana's assault on the Alamo, in which Benjamin's brother, John, was killed. Written from Washington-on-the-Brazos, Texas. GOSS FAMILY. 1799-1882. 50 items. Gift of Miss Ellen Goss. No. 3285. Deeds, bank books, tax receipts, and store accounts of Rev. John, James W., and John W. Goss, Jr., of Bellevue, Albemarle County, Va., and eleven broadsides, 1817-1827, on two projects of the Baptist Church—Columbian College (Washington, D. C.) and a periodical, the Latter-Day Luminary—for both of which Rev. John Goss collected subscriptions in Albemarle County. See also eighteenth and nineteenth annual report. GRAHAM, CHARLES. 1872. 1 vol. Deposit. No. 3427. Sketches in pencil and water color, chiefly of scenes in Montana, made by Graham while serving as an engineer on Gen. Thomas L. Rosser's survey of the route of the Northern Pacific Railroad. GRAVEL HILL MANUSCRIPTS. 1799-1873. 77 items. Deposit. No. 2320. Additions to the papers of the Gravel Hill plantation in Charlotte County, Va., including 14 items relating to the building of Gravel Hill for George C. Hannah, 1850-1854; eight wills made by Hannah, 1834-1855; receipts; indentures—some relating to his land in Arkansas; and letters. Among the persons mentioned in the collection are: Ann Dabbs, Ann Johnston, William Johnston, Col. William Morton, George W. Read, and Samuel Thomas. Two letters of Moses Hoge, to Col. William Morton, 1803-1835, and a reprint of a sermon preached in 1861 by H. C. Alexander. See also previous annual reports. GREEK LABOR MOVEMENTS. 1930-1948. 27 items. Deposit. No. 2897. Documentary material, especially for the years 1945-1948; historical articles, including British, American, and Greek items. The material which is typed, printed, and mimeographed, was collected by Mr. Robert Smith Simpson, U. S. foreign service officer in Athens. GRIFFITH, DAVID (1742-1789). 1749-1789. 1 vol. Deposit. No. 3416. Account book of the first Episcopal bishop-elect of Virginia, who during the American Revolution was a surgeon in Washington's army, providing medical care for British soldiers and who because of his services was exempted from molestation by General Cornwallis. Previous acquisitions of Griffith manuscripts are described in the sixteenth-seventeenth annual report. GRIFFITH, DAVID. 1786 July 3. 1 item. Deposit. No. 3309. University of Pennsylvania diploma conferring degree of Doctor of Sacred Theology on Griffith, then rector of the Episcopal church of Alexandria, Virginia. Signed by the Prefect, John Ewing, and six professors, including Benjamin Rush, M.D. HALE, CLARENCE. 1940. 1 item. Gift of University News Service. No. 3514. Manuscript of his address, "Physical Education Programs in Virginia Colleges," presented May 3, 1940, at meeting of Virginia Academy of Sciences. HALL, AUGUSTA RUSSELL. 1 item. Gift of Thomas W. Atkinson. No. 3238. Manuscript poem, "He Leadeth Me." HART, JAMES. 1947-1949. 1,000 items. Gift of Professor Hart. No. 3282. Typescript of his book, The American Presidency in Action, 1789; a study in Constitutional History with correspondence relative to its publication. Proof sheets corrected and revised of the 2nd edition of his book, An Introduction to Administrative Law With Related Cases, published in 1950, and some correspondence for 1948-1949. Mimeographs of 3 speeches by Harold Stassen, 1947, and draft of a talk on communism. HARVIE FAMILY. 1700-1949. 1 item. Gift of John Harvie Creecy. No. 3297. Genealogy of the descendants of Col. John Harvie, of Albemarle County, member of the Continental Congress, Register of the Virginia Land Office, and Mayor of Richmond. For description of John Harvie manuscripts see eleventh and fourteenth annual reports. HAVANA, CUBA. 1801 Nov. 8. 1 item. Deposit. No. 3247. Document in Spanish of a legal process undertaken by Don Gabriel Maria Cardenas y Santa Cruz and other officials to be sent to Don Antonio Argote Villalobos, Spanish consul in Norfolk, attested to by John Morton, American consul in Havana. HENRY, PATRICK (1736-1799). 1786 Aug. 1. 1 DS. Coles Collection. No. 3351. Land grant to Henry Banks for 336 acres of land in Botetourt County signed by Patrick Henry, Governor of Virginia. HERRICK, SOPHIA BLEDSOE. 1872-1908. 32 items. Deposit. No. 3461. Letters of American and British writers, chiefly to Mrs. Herrick, who was associated with her father (q.v.) in the editing of The Southern Review, and later with the staff of Scribners and The Century. Among the letters is an autograph poem, Celia Thaxter's "Midsummer." The correspondents include: Frances Hodgson Burnett, William M. Canby, Frances Power Cobbe, Charles L. Darwin, Francis Darwin, Norman Duncan, C. Watts Dunton, John Fiske, Richard Watson Gilder, Ellen Glasgow, Asa Gray, Samuel S. Haldeman, Lady Herschel, M. B. Herschel, Josiah Gilbert Holland, L. Q. C. Lamar, Fanny D. Lowell, James Russell Lowell, William Lytton, George MacDonald, Caroline E. Norton, Margaret Junkin Preston, Jacob A. Riis, Margaret E. Sangster, Eugene Schuyler, Frank D. Sherman, John Tyndall, Anna Bartlett Warner. HIGGINBOTHAM, DAVID. 1801-1856. 24 items and 11 vols. Deposit. No. 3330. Letters and copy of the deed of Thomas Jefferson to David Higginbotham on sale of land in Richmond as follows: 12 September 1811; 24 May 1812 (fragmentary); 5 November 1812; and 8 August 1813. Group of letters, deeds and plans concerning David Higginbotham's purchase of the "Indian Camp" tract, near Monticello, originally patented by a son of King Carter and later called Morven, of 1,340 acres for $13,340 from Col. William Short, friend and former Secretary of Jefferson when Minister to France, and later the U. S. Minister to the Netherlands and diplomatic representative to Spain. Included are four letters and documents from Jefferson about the property and the buildings of the house, 1813-1817, and a photostat of his drawing of a house for Mary E. Higginbotham; letters to Stephen Doll, 25 December 1820, about purchase of lime for plastering; to D. Hickey, 15 August 1820, concerning the plastering of rooms; to Robert Carter Nicholas, 25 December 1819, on safe arrival of two marble mantels; James Ross and John Carter's appraisal of Morven at $8,000, 5 June 1821, and to Mr. Taylor, 15 August 1820, President of Ferrix Insurance Company about insurance rates. Supplementing this material are the following documents: copy of 1730 grant to John Carter of a tract of land in Goochland County; two plats of David &amp; E. G. Higginbotham property, 1813-1846; deeds for sale of some property of Higginbotham to D. G. Smith, by his widow, Mary E. Higginbotham and Elmslie G. Higginbotham, 1853-1856. Among the manuscript volumes are: David Higginbotham's account book, 1801-1848, of Albemarle County merchants' records of milling, shipping of flour and tobacco and of invoices for large shipments from London; two letterbooks of correspondence, 1819-1853, with Anderson, Blair &amp; Anderson, Francis T. Barbour, Philip P. Barbour, William Barrett, John G. Blair, Francis T. Brooke, George D. Fisher, Dr. Robert Haxall, Daniel and Edward G. Higginbotham, Francis Hoskins, Thomas Jefferson, John T. London, James Lynch, Samuel Marx, Boyd Miller, James Monroe, Cornelius Powell, Jacquelin P. Taylor, and Nathaniel Wattles; journal and ledger of J[ohn] H[igginbotham] &amp; Co., Warminster, Va., 1820-1824. HILDRETH FAMILY. 1949. 3 items. Archival transfer. No. 3253. List of descendants of Eugenius A. and Jane B. Hildreth who have attended the University of Virginia; letter from Mrs. Hildreth to Dr. John L. Newcomb, and from Blanche L. Shepherd to Marvin Perry explaining the list, 15 June and 6 July, 1949. HINSDALE, GUY S. (1858-1948). 1941-1948. 54 items. Gift of Dr. Hinsdale's estate. No. 3504. Manuscript, typescript with illustrations, of two articles of the former medical director of "Greenbrier," White Sulphur Springs, W. Va., fellow and curator of the Mütter Museum of College of Physicians of Philadelphia, and student of Doctors S. Weir Mitchell and William Osler; "S. Weir Mitchell, Poet, Novelist, Friend, Physician," The General Magazine and Historical Chronicler, 303-313; and Our Medical Debt to France, New York, P. B. Hoeber, 1942, and reprinted in Annals of Medical History (3rd ser., vol. IV, no. 2, 154-166) with 52 letters from the following: Dr. William Seaman Bainbridge, C. F. Brooks, Dr. Myrtelle M. Canavan, Harry Clemons, Simon Flexner, Dr. Walter Freeman, Dr. J. F. Fulton, Dr. C. F. Gardiner, Dr. Thomas A. Gates (President of the University of Pennsylvania), Dr. John E. Gibbon, Jr., Dr. Ellyrne G. Gill, Joel E. Goldwait, Dr. Alfred Gordon, Dr. Russell L. Haden, C. W. Home, Dr. W. B. Hinsdale, Dr. Gilbert Horrax, Cordell Hull, Franklin Jones, Thomas E. Keys, Dr. E. B. Krumbhaar, Dr. Frank H. Krusen, Dr. Sanford V. Larkey, Dr. Walter S. McClellan, William B. McDaniel, II, James G. McManaway, Dr. George R. Minot, Dr. J. H. Musser, Reginald H. Patterson, Dr. William Pepper, Elizabeth H. Pitney, Dr. Joseph H. Pratt, Dr. Francis M. Rackemann, Dr. Maximilian A. Ramirez, Dr. William H. Robey, Dr. George Cheever Shattuck, Dr. James H. Smith, Dr. John M. Swan, Dr. J. Gurney Taylor, Beverley R. Tucker, and F. Park Weber. HOGE, REV. MOSES DRURY (1819-1899). 1839-1896. 126 items. Deposit. No. 3071. Correspondence with his family, including two clippings and a picture, and a copy of the will of James D. Wood, his wife's father, 13 December 1841, 123 pieces; diary of his voyage to England, January 1863; and broadside reprint of a sermon preached in commemoration of Jefferson Davis' death, 11 December 1889. Photostat of Robert Adam's certificate for a tract of land in Texas, 29 April 1833, from New Arkansas and Texas Land Company for 3,165 acres. HOLLADAY, LEWIS (1868-1946). 1903-1922. 2 items. Gift of the estate of Dr. Holladay. No. 3286. Account book, 1903-1909, and check-stub book, 1921-1922, of the Orange County, Va., physician. HOLST, GUSTAV. [1949]. 1 item. Gift of Stephen O. Tuttle, No. 3468. Mr. Holst's card to introduce Professor Tuttle to Dr. Harris of Christchurch, Oxford, England. HULL FAMILY. 1609-1948. 4 vols. Deposit. No. 2597. Typescript copy of John W. Herndon's "The Hull Family of Northumberland and Spotsylvania Counties, Virginia, and Notes on Some Allied Families," unpublished, Charlottesville, 1948. HUME, FANNY PAGE (1838-1865). 12 items and 3 vols. Deposit. No. 1713. Additional diaries of Miss Hume of Selma, Orange County, Va., for 1858, 1860, and 1861, concerning family affairs, and particularly interesting for the description of Confederate and Union armies in that area. Included are two personal letters to Mr. Rhind; two to Miss Lizzie Rhind, his sister, November 1863-January 1864; with typescripts and a picture. See also thirteenth annual report. HUNTER, JOHN. 1795 Aug. 2. 1 ALS (facsimile). Gift of Lord Alfred Webb-Johnson. No. 3340. Facsimile of letter to Edward Jenner. JACKSON, ANDREW. 1829 Apr. 2. 1 DS. Deposit. No. 3261. Deed for purchase of public land in Missouri, 1829. JACKSON, THOMAS JONATHAN (1824-1863). 1863 May 2. 1 item. Gift of Leigh D. Williams. No. 3339. Facsimile of a letter to General R. E. Lee. JAMES RIVER AND KANAWHA COMPANY. 1842 May 9. 1 item. Coles Collection. No. 3362. Mortgage of this Virginia canal company's property with the President and Directors of the Board of Public Works of Virginia in return for a loan of $250,000 authorized by the General Assembly by an act of 25 March 1842 and signed by Joseph C. Cabell, President, and W. B. Chittenden, Secretary of the Company. JAMES RIVER CANAL. 1813. 3 items. Coles Collection. No. 3307. Three letters concerning a survey for the proposed canal route to connect the James River to the Roanoke River in 1813. George A. Newton in letter, 16 October 1813, to Dr. Alexander S. Field, one of Virginia's Commissioners, stated that Major Perrault, former professor of mathematics at the College of South Carolina and Topographical Surveyor in the U. S. Army, had been appointed engineer to make the survey. Dr. Fields wrote, 17 November 1813, to Commissioner William Edward Broadnax declining commission because of ill health. Mr. Broadnax in letter, 29 December 1813, to Capt. James Harrison, member of the Virginia Assembly, reported that North Carolina's commissioners had no available funds for the survey, that subscription had failed and suggested that the Virginia Assembly finance the survey. JAMESTOWN, VIRGINIA. 1900-1907. 19 items. Transferred to Manuscript Collection. No. 38-591. Surveys, maps, and plans of the town and vicinity, showing locations of many properties, and buildings, in the 17th and 18th centuries. Several maps were made by Samuel Yonge. Some are copies of contemporary surveys, and two are copies of maps made by the French in July 1781. JEFFERSON, PETER AND THOMAS, PRAYER BOOK. 1752. Annotations, 1753-1826. 1 vol. Gift of C. Waller Barrett and the estate of Alexander W. Weddell. Bought by Peter Jefferson, who wrote on the flyleaf his name and the date, 30 April 1753, and noted the cost, six shillings, this Book of Common Prayer (5 by 8 inches, bound in tooled morocco) was printed at Oxford in 1752 by Thomas Baskett. Thomas Jefferson, who inherited the volume after his father's death in 1757, utilized eight of its blank pages for a detailed record (with entries made throughout his life) of births, marriages, and deaths in the Jefferson, Randolph, Eppes, and Skelton families. JEFFERSON, THOMAS (1743-1826) PAMPHLETS. ca. 1807-1818. 16 items. McGregor Library. Several pamphlets in this group, which was presented to a friend in 1829 by Senator Robert Y. Hayne of South Carolina, are authors' presentation copies. JEFFERSON, THOMAS (1743-1826) PAPERS. The most notable event in this Jefferson year has been the appearance of Volume One of the Papers of Thomas Jefferson, last May 17th, marked by a ceremonial at the Library of Congress in honor of the Editors and of the staff members of the Princeton University Press, at which President Truman and General George C. Marshall were among the speakers. Our own library published in February The Jefferson Papers of the University of Virginia, a calendar of chronologically arranged abstracts of our 2,500 original Jefferson manuscripts, with a fifty-page index. We continue to collect Jefferson's manuscripts, and particularly to collect information about those which we cannot acquire. Such information we record in our card-file union list of Jefferson's writings (and letters addressed to him) as a means of assisting the Editors at Princeton and others. Listed below are the manuscripts acquired this year, some of them since our calendar went to press. By means of this listing from year to year the information provided in the published calendar will be kept up to date. Friends of the University of Virginia are again urged to bring to our attention information about any Jefferson manuscript, however fragmentary, which might aid the Princeton Editors in their superbly begun task of making available to the public the writings of our Founder. JEFFERSON, THOMAS (1743-1826). 1784-1826. 3 items. Gift of C. Waller Barrett and the estate of Alexander W. Weddell. No. 2958. ALS of 21 April 1803 to Dr. Benjamin Rush, with a two-page enclosure, also in Jefferson's autograph, headed "Syllabus of an Estimate of the merit of the doctrines of Jesus compared with those of others." Twelve-page list in Jefferson's hand, giving the room-byroom and wall-by-wall arrangement of the paintings, art objects, and other items in the various rooms at Monticello. Autograph list in French of his furniture, presumably made during his residence in Paris. JEFFERSON, THOMAS (1743-1826). 1795 Aug. 12. 1 ALS. Gift of Mrs. Arthur K. Peck. No. 3456. Letter to [Josiah Donath] on window glass for Monticello. JEFFERSON, THOMAS (1743-1826). 1799 Jan. 25. 1 ALS. McGregor Library. No. 3528. To Henry Remsen disclaiming any responsibility for the amateur diplomacy of George Logan (of "Logan Act" notoriety). JEFFERSON, THOMAS (1743-1826). 1801 Mar. 4. 1 item. Gift of Mrs. Francis Eppes Shine. No. 38-592. Medal struck for his inauguration as President and in commemoration of the 25th anniversary of the Declaration of Independence, and presented to him by Congress. JEFFERSON, THOMAS. (1743-1826). 1805-1806. 8 items. McGregor Library. No. 3352. Drawing of a carriage designed by Jefferson, with detailed specifications in his hand, and related correspondence and notes. JEFFERSON, THOMAS. (1743-1826). 1817 Mar. 10. 1 ALS. Gift of C. Waller Barnett. No. 3360. To James Madison, at Montpelier, asking him to attend a meeting of the visitors of "our proposed college." JEFFERSON, THOMAS. (1743-1826). 1817 June 25. 1 ALS. Gift of Miss Nelly C. Preston. No. 3353. From Monticello, to James Dinsmore, Petersburg, Virginia, on the site for Central College. JEFFERSON, THOMAS. (1743-1826). 1821 Sept. 25. 1 ALS. Gift of Joseph Hartfield. No. 3354. From Monticello, to Samuel Taylor, Jefferson County, Virginia, explaining the effect the Legislature's action in regard to the grant from the Literary Fund will have on the opening of the University. JEFFERSON, THOMAS (1743-1826). 1823 Nov. 12. 1 ALS. Coles Collection. No. 3351. Letter from Jefferson as Rector, University of Virginia, to accompany a report to the State Literary Fund. JEFFERSON, THOMAS (1743-1826). 1824 Jan. 19, 22, and 23. 3 ALS. Transferred from Virginia State Library. No. 3296. To Joseph Carrington Cabell, member of State Senate, about an unsatisfactory bill for the financing of the University then pending in the Legislature. JEFFERSON, THOMAS (1743-1826). ca. 1825. 1 item. Coles Collection. No. 3337. Portrait embossed in plaster, from the St. Memin profile. JEFFERSON, THOMAS (1743-1826) MISCELLANY. 1 folder, 62 items. Gift of Mrs. Monroe Cockrell. Nos. 3357 and 3501. Collection of clippings on Jefferson and an anonymous essay of 1901, "The Centennial of Jefferson's Inaugural as President," a critical commentary on research in Jefferson's period. JEFFERSON, THOMAS (1743-1826) TRANSCRIPTS. 1775-1845. Nos. 3252, 3367, 3384, 3423, 3439-40, and 3449. Our own Jefferson papers are supplemented by a very extensive collection of transcripts (more than 50,000) available in our Manuscripts Reading Room, including microfilm copies of the great Jefferson collection at the Library of Congress, of the Coolidge Collection at the Massachusetts Historical Society, and of the holdings of many of the lesser Jefferson depositories, as well as photostats and other copies donated by hundreds of private owners of individual manuscripts. Also available to researchers in the reading room is a chronological list (77,000 cards covering some 45,000 to 50,000 items of Jefferson's writings and letters to him) which shows the present location of Jefferson manuscripts and any known printing or partial printing of the texts. Messrs. Julian P. Boyd and Lyman H. Butterfield and Mrs. Mina R. Bryan, of the Princeton staff; the Library of Congress, the College of William and Mary, and other institutions, and numerous individuals, especially Mr. Charles W. Porter, Mr. John P. McGuire, Jr., and Mr. John C. Emmerson, Jr., have generously aided us this year in obtaining valuable additions to our files of transcripts. Among these additions are the Jefferson items in the Papers of the Continental Congress; photostats of 170 papers relating to the planning of the National Capitol; extracts from the diary of Mrs. William Thornton, attacking President Jefferson for his preoccupation with such trivialities as the design of a carriage; photostats of another draft of the memoirs of Jefferson's servant, Isaac; and letters on a variety of subjects to C. W. F. Dumas, James Gray, Gen. John Lamb, Nicholas Lewis, Nathaniel Macon, Robert Patterson, Thomas Pinkney, Thomas Read, Caesar A. Rodney, James Tucker, St. George Tucker, William Wirt, and many others. JEFFERSON FAMILY. MONTICELLO MUSIC COLLECTION. ca. 1775-1827. 34 items. Deposit. No. 3177. Music once owned by Thomas Jefferson, his wife, Martha Wayles Jefferson, his daughters, Martha Jefferson Randolph and Maria Jefferson Eppes, including manuscript and printed items in sheet and book form with several annotations by Jefferson, his wife, and daughters, and one Jefferson holograph. The list is as follows: 1. . . . Minuets with their Basses . . . for German Flute, Violin, or Harpsichord. London, n. d. Inscribed "T. Jefferson to his grand daughter, V. J. Randolph, `Monticello' ". The handwriting of one inscription is that of Fanny M. Burke. Contains notes on tuning [in T. J.'s hand?]. 2. Manuscript book of songs, minuets, and hymns, inscribed by F. M. Burke: "This book supposed to belong to Martha Wayles Jefferson, wife of Thomas Jefferson, who was Martha Wayles." The writing in the early part of one volume is in the hand of Martha Jefferson; some later additions in another hand (authority of Marie Kimball). 3. Stabat Mater, Composed by Sigr. [Giovanni Battista] Pergolesi, London, n. d. An Ode—the Dying Christian to his Soul, by Mr. [Alexander] Pope . . . Adapted to the Principal Airs of the Hymn, Stabat Mater. Compo'd by Signor Pergolesi. The Anthem which was Performed in Westminster Abby at the Funeral of Her most Sacred Majesty, Queen Caroline. Compos'd by Mr. [Georg Friedrich] Handel. Vol. II London. Handel's Celebrated Coronation Anthems [three] in Score, for Voices and Instruments. Vol. I. London. Inscribed by F. M. Burke "Mademoiselle Jefferson, Panthemont, Paris." 4. The Psalms set full for the Organ . . . by Mr. Danl. Purcell . . . London, n. d. 5. Songs and Duets composed by Mrs. Cosway. Inscribed "Monsieur Jefferson." F. M. Burke has inscribed "Thomas Jefferson from Mrs. Cosway." Seven songs of Francis Hopkinson. Written about 1784 and dedicated to George Washington. Sent to Thomas Jefferson in Paris, December 1788, for his daughters. 6. The Harpsichord or Spinnet Miscellany . . . by Robert Brenner. London, n. d. Eight Lessons for the Harpsichord. Compos'd by . . . Gio[vanni] Batt[ist]a Pergolesi. London. Variations for the Harpsichord To a Minuet of Corelli's, The Gavot in Otho and the old Highland Laddie by J. Snow. London [1769]. Six Favorite Overtures Adapted for the Harpsichord or Organ. Compos'd by C[hristian] F[erdinand] Abel. London [1769]. Six Sonatas for the Piano-Forte or Harpsichord Compos'd by Sigr C. E. [Carl Philip Emanuel] Bach. Inscribed M. E. [Maria Eppes]. 7. Six Concerto, pour le Clavecin, ou le Forte-Piano . . . composés par J. S. Schroetter. Oeuvre III. Paris. Ouverture et Airs de Ballets D'Alexandre aux Indes Arrangés pour le Clavecin ou Forte-Piano par lauteur . . . Charles de Peysac. Inscribed by Miss F. M. Burke "Mademoiselle Jefferson, Panthemont, Paris, 1785." "Mademoiselle Jefferson" on inside front cover in Martha Jefferson's hand. 8. [Manuscript] Sonates pour le Clavecin, par differens auteurs, 1788. Probably in the hand of Martha Jefferson. A group of manuscript songs including a printed song in Alexander's Feast by [Georg Friederich] Handel, 1790. Inscribed on cover "M. J." Inscribed inside cover "Mademoiselle Jefferson, Panthemont, Paris" in hand of F. M. Burke. 9. Quatre Sonates pour la Harpe, par M. Nicolaï. Oeuvre Ier. Paris. Trois Sonates Pour le Clavecin ou le Piano- Forte avec Accompagnement de Violon par Valantino Nicolaï. Op: VII, Paris. Trois Duos Concertants Pour le Clavecin Ou Forte Piano et Violon Obligé Composés par M. Nicolaï. Oeuvre X, Paris. Inscribed on cover and title page: "Mademoiselle Jefferson. L'Abbaye Royale de Panthemont, Paris 1785," by F. M. Burke. 10. Sei Sonate de Cembalo e Violino Obligato da Luigi Boccherini, Opera V. Paris. Six Sonates pour le Clavecin avec accompagnement d'un Violon ad Libitum par Mr. [Johann Friedrich] Edelmann. Oeuvre I. Paris. Trois Sonates en Trio pour le Clavecin . . . avec accompagnement d'un Violon et Violoncelle . . . par Ernesto Eichner. Paris. Inscribed on title page and cover by F. M. Burke, in the latter case writing over an old script, "Mademoiselle de Jefferson, 1785." 11. XII Solos for a Violin with a Thorough Bass for the Harpsichord or Violincello, composed by Arcangelo Corelli, London, n. d. XII Solos for a Violin with a Thorough Bass for the Harpsichord or Bass Violin Composed by Antonio Vivaldi. Opera 2der. London. XII Solos for a German Flute, a Hoboy or Violin with a Thorough Bass for the Harpsichord or Bass Violin Compos'd by Carlo Tessarini. Opera Seconda. London. Six Solos for a Violin and Bass, Compos'd by Wenceslaus Wodizka. London. Six Favourite Solos for a Violin with a Bass for the Violincello and Harpsichord, Compo'd by Sigr [Carlo Antonio] Campioni &amp; Sigr Chalran. London. Inscribed by Miss F. M. Burke "Thomas Jefferson, Monticello." 12. Overture to Artaxerxe. London, n. d. Two Grand Sonatas, for the Piano Forte or Harpsichord, with an Accompanyment for the Violin, ad Libitum. Composed by Ignace Pleyel, London. Three Sonatas, for the Piano Forte or Harpsichord . . . Composed by E[rnesto] Eichner, London. Bland's Collection of Sonatas, Lessons, Overtures, Capricios, Divertimientos &amp;c., &amp;c. for the Harpsichord or Piano Forte, without Accompts. by the most Esteem'd Composers. No. 20, vol. 2. [Johann Friedrich] Edelman's Sonata 1st Op. 1st. pg. 192-198, and Sonata del Sigr Vento. pg. 199-291. . . . No. 22, v. 2. Edelman's Sonata 1st Opa 16. pg. 212-215, Overture to the Bastille. London. pg. 216-218, Edelman's Sonata 2d. Opa 16. pg. 219-221. . . . No. 28, v. 3. [Ignace] Pleyel's Cottage Maid, pg. 272- 277, and Edelman's 3d Sonata Op. 8, pg. 278-281. . . . No. 29, v. 3. Edelman's [Sonata] 3d Op: 16, pg. 282-284, and Martini's Grand Overture, to Henry the 4th, pg. 285-291. . . . No. 38, v. 4. [Christoph Wilibal von] Gluck's Overture Paradie et Elena, pg. 373-378, and Edelman's Sonata 4th Opa 16. pg. 379-382. . . . No. 42, v. 4. Overture Oedipe a Colonne, Arranged by Mr. [Ludwig Wenzel] Lachnitt[h], pg. 412-416, and [Ernesto] Eichner's 4th Sonata, pg. 417-421. [Joseph] Haydn's Grand Orchestra Sinfonie, Adapted for Piano Forte or Harpischord. With an Accompanyment for a Violin by S[tephen] F[rancis] Rimbaut. London. Haydn's Grand Orchestra Sinfonie . . . at the Nobility's Concerts; Adapted for the Organ, Harpsichord or Piano Forte. London. Symphonie La Chasse [by Haydn]. Adapted by Mr. Percy (No. 6) London. Sinfonia IV [by Haydn]. A part of another symphony [by Haydn]. Concerto, pour le Clavecin, Hautbois, ou Flute, avec l'Accompagnement de Deux Violons, Taille, &amp; Basse, deux Cors de Chasse ad Libitum. Composèes par J[ohann] C[aspar] Fischer. Berlin [and] Amsterdam. Inscribed by F. M. Burke "Martha Jefferson, Paris, 1786." 13. Five miscellaneous sheets of music, including, Overture to the Deserter. Part of a book of minuets, inscribed, "This sheet belonged to Thomas Jefferson." The following pieces were in booklet. I'd be a Butterfly—I. Bayley Let us Haste to Kelvin grove—C. E. Horn The plain Gold Ring—Weber Buy a Broom—German 14. Pièces de Clavecin par Mr Balbastre, Paris, n. d. Trois Quatuors de Mr. Ignace Pleyel . . . Arrangée pour Clavecin par Mr. [Ludwig Wenzel] Lachnitt[h], 2nd Suitte, Paris. Trois Sonates pour le Clavecin ou le Forte-Piano avec Violon, ad Libitum, par L[eopold] Kozeluch. Oeuvre 20, Paris. Trois Sonates pour Clavecin ou Forte Piano avec Violon et Violoncelle Composés Par Mr. J. S. Schroetter, Oeuvre VIII, Paris. A Duett for two Performers on One Forte Piano by Sigr [Muzio] Clementi. Op. VI. London. Inscribed on cover "Mademoiselle Jefferson L'Abbaye Royale de Panthemont, Paris [believed to be in the hand of Maria Jefferson Eppes]. 15. Six Sonates pour le Clavecin . . . par Jean Cretien Bach [Oeuvre V] Paris, n. d. La Chasse pour le Clavecin . . .par Muzio Clementi. Oeuvre XVI. London. Trio pour le Clavecin . . . avec Accompagnement de Violon ou Clarinette et Alto, par W[olfgang] A[medus] Mozart. Oeuvre 16. Paris. Inscribed on cover, "Mrs. Randolph, Monticello, Virginia." 16. Manuscript book of songs, waltzes, and miscellaneous pieces. 17. Six sonatas. 18. Trois Quatuors de M. Ignace Pleyel. With Violin accompanyment by [Ludwig Wenzel] Lachn [ith]. [page torn]. Paris, n. d. 19. Ouverture de la bonne fille . . . arrangée Pour le Clavecin . . . Paris, par L. F. Despreaux, n. d. Title page bears signature of Eliza M. Barclay, 12 December 1787. 20. Le Carillon des Trois Fermiers; Trio d'Azor; Air des Trois Fermiers; Rose Cherie de Zemire et Azor; Air de Trois Fermiers. "Eliza M. B[arclay] St. Thomas de Volumo" appears on title page. On cover: Catalogue des Oeuvres de Musique appartenants à M. Cousineau. Notes and lyrics in hand of Martha Jefferson. 21. II Sonates pour le Clavecin . . . par M. [Johann Friedrich] Edelmann, Paris, n. d. Inscribed "Martha Jefferson, Paris, 1786" by F. M. Burke. Title page bears inscription "à Mademoiselle Jefferson Fevrier 7 1786 Panthemont." Marie Kimball believes this is Martha Jefferson's hand. [Second Sonata is incomplete]. 22. Harpsichord Sonatas dedicated to "Miss Louise Chauvet by C[harles] Dibdin." Sonatines or Easy Lessons for the Harpsichord . . . by Sigr. [Georg Christoph] Wagenseil. To which are added several favorite Airs and Lessons by Messrs. Graff Toeschi, Pescetti, Rutini, T. Giordani. London. A Favorite Lesson for the Harpischord composed by Mr. Geo. Green. A Favorite Lesson for the Harpsichord compos'd by Sigr. [Pietro?] Castrucci. Inscribed by F. M. Burke, "Mlle. Jefferson, L'Abbaye Royale de Panthemont, 178-". 23. Recueil de Petits Airs, et Pastorales Tirées du Roman D'Estelle avec Accompagnement de Piano-Forte ou Harpe par Mr. Darondeau. Oeuvre VI. Paris, n. d. Recueil de Romances et Dariettes avec Accompagnement de Clavecin ou de Piano Forte par Mr. Darondeau. Oeuvre IV. IIme Recueil de Petits Airs de Chant Avec Accompagnement to Piano Forte ou de Harpe . . . par M. Martini. Inscribed on cover "Mlle. Jefferson Abbaye Royale de Panthemont, Paris." 24. Le Tout—Ensemble, de Musique, pour le Forte Piano, ou Clavecin avec Accompagnemens par les plus grands Maîtres de L'Europe . . . (par l'editeur) Niccolai's Opera 3d, Sonata III, IV, V, VI. Six Sonatas for the Piano Forte or Harpsichord, with an Accompanyment for a Violin composed by T. Sterckel. Opera III. London. Sei Sonate per Cembalo ò Piano Forte con Violino ad Libitom composte da Matia Vento. Opera IIa. Lyon. Quatre Sonates pour la Harpe avec Accompagnement de Violon et Basse, ad libitum par M. Gros [Sonate III omitted]. Oeuvre III, Paris. Six Sonates pour le Clavecin ou Piano-Forte avec Accompagnement de Violon ad Libitum par Valentin Nicolay. Oeuvre XIe Paris. Inscribed: "Miss Jefferson, Paris, 1785." Concertos Nos. 1-4, Op. XI-XV, of Mons.r [Johann] Schobert's Works for the Harpsichord or Piano Forte. London. Sigr. [Joseph] Haydn's Grand Orchestra Sinfonie [No. 1] as Performed at the Nobility's Concerts, adapted for the Organ, Harpsichord or Piano Forte. London. The Celebrated Overture La Chasse. Composed by Sigr Giuseppe Haydn. Adapted for the Harpsichord or Piano-Forte. London. A Concerto [No. 3] for the Harpsichord or Piano-Forte with Accompaniments for Two Violins, Two Horns, Two German Flutes or Oboes, a Tenor &amp; Violoncello, by J. F. Kloffler. London. A Favourite Concerto for the Harpsichord or Piano-Forte, with Accompaniments for two Violins, Hautboys, or Flutes, two Horns ad libitum Tenor and Violoncello, composed by Vincent Manfredini. London. The Celebrated Overture, [to Sinfonie II] Composed by Sigr [Joseph] Haydn . . . Adapted for the Piano Forte or Harpsichord. London. Three Sonatas for the Harpsichord or Piano Forte Composed by W[olfgang] A[medus] Mozart of Vienna. London. On cover is red leather inset with "Miss Jefferson" in gold. Endorsed inside cover by F. M. Burke, "Mlle. Martha Jefferson, Abbaye Royale de Panthemont, Paris, 1786." Bound in are nine pages of manuscript music bearing signature of Maria Jefferson. 25. Sonates en Quatuor pour le Clavecin . . . par Mr. Balbastre . . . Oeuvre III, Paris, n. d. Six Sonates Pour le Piano-Forte ou le Clavecin Avec Accompagnement d'une Flute ou Violon Composed Par Mr. [Muzio] Clementi. Oeuvre II. Paris. Six Sonatas for the Piano Forte, or the Clavecin . . . par Mr. [Muzio] Clementi. Opus IV, London. La Chasse pour Le Clavecin ou Forte Piano par Leopold Kozeluch. Oeuvre V. Vienne. Endorsed on cover and title page by F. M. Burke, "Mlle. Jefferson, L'Abbaye Royale de Panthemont, Paris, 1783." 26. Sonates pour le Clavecin . . . Opera V. par M. [Johann] Schobert, Paris, n. d. Sonates en Quatuor pour le Clavecin . . . par Mr. Schobert. Oeuvre III. Paris. Sinfonies pour Le Clavecin . . . par Mr Schobert . . . Opera IX. Paris. Sinfonies pour le Violon et Cors de Chasse . . . par Mr Schobert. Opera X, Paris. Six Sonates pour Clavecin Ou Forte Piano . . . Composés par Jean Cretien Bach. Oeuvre XV. Paris. Endorsed by Miss Burke: "Thomas Jefferson, Monticello, Albemarle County, Virginia" on cover and "Thomas Jefferson, Monticello" on title page. 27. Manuscript music book, including: Overture to Lodoiska by Krielzer; Cony Owen; Allemande D. Sleibelt; Dutch Minuet; Murphy Delany by Labour; Jack Labin; Additional variations to Duncan Gray; Song by Lord Lyttleton; [on end paper] New Crazy Jane—a light dance with words. Endorsed Virginia J. Randolph. 28. Manuscript music book which included a Sonata by [Johann Friedrich] Edelman, La Canonade by Balbastre, a German Waltz, was endorsed "Ellen Wayles Randolph," "Eliza Waller," and "Jane Blair Cary." 29. Miscellaneous sheet and manuscript music, including: New York Serenading Waltz; Aurora by Labitzksy (inside a duet-Valse Hongroise); vocal exercises; Rondo de Paganini, duet; fragment of duet-Air de Ballet; There's Nothing True but Heaven; Charming Village Maid (with words); Air de Danse de Roland; Sonata del Sigr. Haydn; Diro de Ballise de Babet; fragments of pieces 6-15 of ————; Don Giovanni (selection) by Mozart; Song—The Lingering Winds; Acuerda le Biennial-song with words; Air—Vedrai Garino, and—Batti Batti by Mozart. 30. Manuscript music book, early 19th century. Not in Jefferson's hand. Among those pieces are: Variations on a Sicilian Hymn; Knight Errant; The Portrait (with words); Hungarian Waltz; Come Rest in this Bosom; The Ill Wife; A Favourite Scot's Air (arr. by Charles Gilbert); Air in the Battle of Maringo; the Waltz Cotillon; Fin'ch Dal Vino from Mozart's "Il Don Giovanni"; Merrily danced the Quaker's Wife; Air du Barbier de Seville; Overture of Panange by Gretry; Overture de Arinene (arr. by Foder); Air Lison Dormoit; There's nae luck; Bonaparte's Grand March; God Save the King, by Haydn; Grandmarchiee with Variations. 31. New and complete preceptor for Spanish Guitar, Philadelphia, 1827. 32. Der FreiSchutz Romantische Oper in 3 Aufzügen [by] Carl Maria von Weber. Endorsed on title page, Margaretta Deverell. 33. Manuscript music book of songs, including: A Poor little gypsy; The silver moon; Onven-a Welsh Song; Ellen Aroon; Flitt'ring spread thy purple pinions; Air du barbier de Seville de Poiselle; Life let us cherish; Song in the Stranger; When Pensive Thought my love from Blue-Beard; The tear; Poor Richard; Ah! Gentle Hope; The Sailor Boy; Thou art gone on a Mary; Flora; Psalm 148, by Dr. Miller; Old 100th Psalm—ascribed to Mr. Luther; Hanover—Psalm 57, v. 8 by Handel; Brunswick—Psalm 42, v. 9 by Handel; Sanctus by Luther O.; Lewis Gordon; Evening Hymn; Duke of York March; The Blue Boy; The Mermaid's Song by Haydn. Inscribed Mr. Randolph inside cover. 34. Opening phrases of the compositions of Carlo Antonio Campioni owned by Thomas Jefferson. Two pages of manuscript music and notes in the hand of Thomas Jefferson. Inscribed as follows: "On this paper is noted the beginning of the several compositions of Campioni which are in possession of T. Jefferson. he would be glad to have every thing else he has composed of Solos, Duets, or Trios. printed copies would be preferred; but it not to be had, he would have them in manuscript." JOHNSTON, R. WICKLIFFE P., JR. 1941-1942. Deposit No. 3412. Diary kept by Johnston while in the American Field Service, on duty in the Western Desert with the British Eighth Army, November 1941-November 1942. KEAN, JEFFERSON RANDOLPH (1860-1950). 1898-1950. 1600 items. Gift of General Kean. No. 3379. Papers of the late Brigadier General and army surgeon, active in the Spanish-American War, in the fight against yellow fever, and as Director-General and organizer of military relief of American Red Cross, and Chief Surgeon of AEF in World War I. Material in the papers on the Western frontier and Sioux campaigns, the efforts to help Cuba organize an effective sanitary and health program, Walter Reed, American Red Cross, World War II, the National Expansion Memorial Commission, and the Thomas Jefferson Bicentennial Commission. Among the correspondents are: J. Randolph Anderson, Newton D. Baker, Harry Clemons, W. C. Gorgas, Cary T. Grayson, Maj. Gen. M. W. Ireland, Gen. Fitzhugh Lee, William Howard Taft, and Maj. Gen. Leonard Wood. KENT AND LANGHORNE FAMILIES. 1749-1846. 22 items. Deposit. No. 3343. Sixteen land patents, one indenture, four court documents, and one manuscript map relating to the property of the Kent and Langhorne families in Augusta, Botetourt, Montgomery and Roanoke counties, Va., and involving Thomas Barnett; Peter and Elizabeth Madison Keefavain; Jacob and Maury Kent; Joseph King; Andrew Lewis; Thomas, Gordon, and David Lloyd; John Madison; William Muncy; Jacob Murry; John Penitent; John Pendleton; George Robertson; and Ephraim Vause. Signed by the following royal governors of the colony: Thomas Lee; Francis Fauquier; Norborne Berkeley, Baron de Botetourt; John Murray, Earl of Dunmore; and by early governors of the Commonwealth, as follows: Beverley Randolph; Robert Brooke; James Monroe; William H. Cabell; and William Smith. KINCAID, ELBERT ALVIS. 1933-1949. 675 items. Gift of Professor Kincaid. No. 3146. Additions to collection of articles, pamphlets and speeches on economic matters by Dr. Kincaid, professor of business administration at the University of Virginia, and Vice-President of Richmond Federal Reserve Bank, including additional material on the Economists' National Committee on Monetary Policy; the Virginia Bankers Association; reports of the Richmond Federal Reserve Bank; correspondence with Elmer C. Crowell; and miscellaneous material on the World Calendar, Navy League, and the 1949 Virginia gubernatorial campaign. See earlier annual reports. LANSBURY, GEORGE. 1936 May 6. 1 item. Gift of Eliot Bartlett. No. 3280. Program, autographed by the British M. P., when he addressed the National Emergency Peace Campaign, Hartford, Connecticut. LEE, ROBERT EDWARD (1807-1870). 1862-1865. 3 items. Deposit. No. 3327. Telegram from General Lee at Richmond to Major Harman for General Edward Johnson, near Staunton, 18 April 1862, telling him to keep in communication with General Jackson and to send back surplus ammunition to Charlottesville. Note to General Lee from General Thomas Jonathan Jackson, Brown's Gap, 11 June 1862, requesting four pieces of artillery with every thousand men. Manuscript copy of his General Orders No. 9, of 10 June 1865. LITTLETON, FRANK C. 1913-1915. 400 items and 1 vol. Gift of Mr. Littleton. No. 3248. Business correspondence of Frank C. Littleton, officer of Industrial Finance Corporation of New York, 1913-1914. Address book, 1915. See also eighteenth-nineteenth annual report and Oak Hill Collection. LOUTHAN, HENRY T. 1895-1949. 50 items. Gift of Dr. Louthan. No. 3366. Personal papers, including material on his student days at the Baptist Theological Seminary in Louisville, Kentucky, 1895-1897; and correspondence on national politics, 1937-1947. Also scrapbook of clippings on John W. Davis, Democratic presidential candidate in 1924. MacARTHUR, GENERAL DOUGLAS. 1945. 2 items. Gift of Mrs. J. P. Carroll. No. 3382. General Order No. 1, issued on the liberation of the Philippines, in press-release form, 6 February 1945; and a letter, signed, to the mother of James P. Carroll, killed in service, 3 August 1945. McCUTCHAN FAMILY. 1758-1890. 12 items. Deposit. No. 3334. Bible records of this Augusta County, Va., family, including information on related families, especially Browns, Irvins, and Meeks. MADISON, JAMES. 1826 Nov. 24. 1 ALS. Coles Collection. No. 3351. Letter from Madison as Rector, University of Virginia, accompanying report of the Rector and Visitors to the State Literary Fund. MAPS. Gifts, deposits, Coles Collection; Byrd, McGregor, and general libraries. The University acquired 4,990 maps in the year covered by this report. The collection now totals 73,098 maps. A few samples of the acquisitions are given in the following skeleton groupings: Notable maps of Virginia include photographs of all states of the Farrar map (see Studies in Bibliography, Vol. 3, 1950, p. 281-284) assembled by Coolie Verner; a copy of the 1818 edition of Bishop Madison's A Map of Virginia (the library already owns the earlier edition); and a manuscript map of Orange, Fauquier, and Rappahannock counties, showing (among other things) the route of the Orange and Alexandria Railroad from Warrenton to south of Culpeper. This latter was the gift of Mr. Frank C. Littleton of Aldie, Virginia. Of modern maps, two series showing something of the trend of our acquisitions are the Russians maps of the Glavnoe Upravlenie Geodezii i Kartografi; namely their Historical Atlas, Moscow, 194950, 2 vols.; and their Geographical Atlas, Moscow, 1950. Map acquisitions of a non-geographical nature may be characterized by reference to a gift from Mr. Charles Venable of a huge 19th-century outline of world history. Important books in the history of cartography acquired during the period included Richard Blome's L'Amerique Angloise, Amsterdam, 1688; and Edward Well's A New Set of Maps, London, 1701. MARSHALL, JOHN (1755-1835). 1828 Mar. 6. 1 item. Gift of Robert B. Tunstall. No. 3408. Letter to John Randolph of Roanoke, thanking him for his latest speech on retrenchment and reform. Typed copy. MICROFILM. 1400-1935. 325,000 exposures. To strengthen our source materials, especially historical manuscripts relating to Virginia and the southeastern states, the library has continued during 1949-50 to acquire microfilm and photostats of manuscripts in private hands and in other libraries in the United States and abroad. In most instances the microfilm is acquired to assist specific research projects of students in this University or to augment collections of original manuscripts in the library. Some of the currently acquired microfilm appears elsewhere in this report under subject; the remainder is listed below. For generations it has been necessary for any student interested in first hand research in the western expansion of America to consult the great assembly of manuscript collections at the State Historical Society of Wisconsin known as the "Draper Manuscripts." The enterprise of the Society in undertaking the microfilming has made it possible for us to acquire this year a film copy of the whole of this vast collection on 133 reels of film—an event of the first importance in the development of our own historical resources. Geoffrey Chaucer (1340?-1400). "Envoy to Allison" as it appears in MS Tanner 346 and MS Fairfax 16, and "The Book of the Duchess" from Tanner MS. Seventeen photostats from originals in The Bodleian Library, Oxford University. No. 3492. Geoffrey Chaucer. 1410-1500. All known manuscripts of the Canterbury Tales, collected by John Manly and Edith Rickert for their exhaustive study of The Text of the Canterbury Tales (Chicago, 1940). Microfilm from originals at University of Chicago. No. 3454. Clay Family Papers. 1828-1866. An extensive correspondence and other papers of Henry Clay, Henry Clay, Jr., Anne Clay McDowell, James B. Clay, Thomas H. Clay, and James H. Clay, Jr., rich in Kentucky and United States history for the years covered. From originals at the University of Kentucky. No. 3484. Draper Manuscripts. 1735-1815. Collections assembled over many years by Lyman Copeland Draper, as basic source material for the history of the settlement of the West and the biographies of the western heroes. Collected from families through the middle Atlantic and Southern states, the original papers were bequeathed to the State Historical Society of Wisconsin in 1891, and are bound into 486 volumes as follows: George M. Bedinger Papers, 1 vol.; Draper's Life of Boone, 5 vols.; Boone Papers, 32 vols.; Border Forays, 5 vols.; Samuel Brady and Lewis Wetzel Papers, 16 vols.; Joseph Brant Papers, 22 vols.; Brant Miscellanies, 3 vols.; Daniel Brodhead Papers, 3 vols.; George Rogers Clark Papers, 64 vols.; George Rogers Clark Miscellanies, 5 vols.; Jonathan Clark Papers, 2 vols.; William Clark Papers, 6 vols.; William Croghan Papers, 3 vols.; Daniel Drake Papers, 2 vols.; Draper's Biographical Sketches, 3 vols.; Draper's Historical Miscellanies, 8 vols.; Draper's Memoranda Books, 3 vols.; Draper's Notes, 33 vols.; Thomas Forsyth Papers, 9 vols.; Frontier Wars Papers, 24 vols.; Georgia, Alabama, and South Carolina Papers, 1 vol.; Josiah Harmar Papers, 2 vols.; William Henry Harrison Papers, 5 vols.; Thomas S. Hinde Papers, 41 vols.; Illinois Papers, 1 vol.; William Irvine Papers, 2 vols.; Simon Kenton Papers, 13 vols.; Kentucky Papers, 36 vols.; King's Mountain Papers, 18 vols.; London Documents at Albany, 1 vol.; Mecklenburg Declaration, by Draper, 3 vols.; Mecklenburg Declaration Papers, 3 vols.; Mecklenburg Declaration Miscellanies, 2 vols.; Newspaper Extracts, 4 vols.; North Carolina Papers, 1 vol.; Paris Documents at Albany, 1 vol.; Robert Patterson Papers, 3 vols.; Pittsburgh and Northwest Virginia Papers, 10 vols.; Pension Statements, 1 vol.; John and James Potter Papers, 1 vol.; William Preston Papers, 6 vols.; Rudolph-Ney Papers, 10 vols.; David Shepherd Papers, 5 vols.; South Carolina Papers, 1 vol.; South Carolina in the Revolution Miscellanies, 2 vols.; Thomas Sumter Papers, 24 vols.; John Cleves Symmes Papers, 4 vols.; Tennessee Papers, 7 vols.; Tecumseh Papers, 13 vols.; Virginia Papers, 16 vols. The Society has issued a Descriptive List of the collections, 1906, and nine volumes of calendars of specific groups. 133 reels of microfilm. No. 3301. Alexander Hamilton (1757-1804). 1714 (1760-1804) 1849. 46 reels of microfilm from the 113 volumes of the Papers in the Library of Congress. No. 3365. James Iredell (1751-1799). 1767-1856. Papers of Iredell, his wife Hannah, and their son James (1788-1853), dealing chiefly with events in North Carolina from 1770 to 1830. Gift of Mr. Ollen L. Burnette from originals in the Duke University Library. No. 3452. Medicine. Student notebooks of George P. King on medical lectures of Dr. Benjamin Rush, at the University of Pennsylvania, 1802, interleaved with notes of Carter Harrison Irving, of Cumberland County, Va., on chemistry, medicine, and anatomy and surgery lectures of Professors John P. Emmet and James L. Cabell at the University of Virginia, 1840-1841. From originals of Dr. C. R. Irving. No. 3409. Mexico. United States Consulate at Mazatlán, reports of, 18261906; 7 reels of microfilm from originals in the National Archives. No. 3364. Edgar Allan Poe (1809-1849). Manuscript of William Friedman's "Edgar Allan Poe, Cryptographer" (published in the Virginia Quarterly Review, 1935) and photostats of Poe's "Marginalia" as published in La Republique des Letters. No. 3276. English Printing. 1600-1700. "A Survey of the History of Printing, Typefounding and Bookselling in Seventeenth Century England with some examples of the Books published which are representative of the books printed during the period; and a Chronology of events important in the annals of English printing 1600-1700," by Horace Richard Archer, submitted as thesis for Master of Arts degree in Librarianship from the University of California, 1943. No 3273. Thomas Mann Randolph (1740-1793). Correspondence of David Campbell with John and Maria H. Campbell and Thomas Mann Randolph, 1813-1822, concerning the War of 1812 and family affairs. Microfilm of 18 letters in David Campbell Papers in Duke University Library. No. 3471. Thomas Mann Randolph (1740-1793). Family correspondence of Maria Jefferson Eppes; Thomas Jefferson; Ann Cary, Judith, Martha Jefferson, Mary, and Thomas Mann Randolph; and Elizabeth, Nicholas P., and Virginia Randolph Trist (especially letters of Martha Jefferson Randolph to her son-in-law Nicholas P. Trist). Microfilm of 38 items in the Nicholas P. Trist Papers in the University of North Carolina Library. No. 3470. William Cabell Rives (1793-1868). 1757-1826. Papers of Thomas Jefferson, including correspondence with Rives, James Madison, and others of the Rives and Walker families of Castle Hill, Albemarle County, Va. 1 reel of microfilm from the Rives Papers at the Library of Congress. Gift of The Papers of Thomas Jefferson, Princeton. No. 3375. Cynthia White Smith. 1839-1850. Letters from Missouri, and from Williamsburg and Loudoun County, Va. Miss Smith, daughter of Gen. Thomas Adams Smith, granddaughter of Col. James White (founder of Knoxville) and a niece of Senator Hugh Lawson White of Tennessee, married in 1845 Maj. William N. Berkeley of Aldie, Loudoun County, Va. These letters are to her brother Crawford Smith, her sister Lucy Ann S. Tucker (wife of Judge Nathaniel Beverley Tucker), and to her niece, Cynthia Beverley Tucker, wife of Henry A. Washington. From originals in the Tucker-Coleman papers on deposit with Colonial Williamsburg. No. 3435. Charles Thomas. 1778-1782. Journal of his western travels in Kentucky and Missouri. From the five volumes of original manuscript at the Missouri Historical Society. No. 3356. War of Jenkins Ear. 1739-1741. Musterlists showing participation by Americans who went on the naval expedition to Cartagena led by Admiral Vernon including original records and extracts of the admiralty office. Photostats of originals and extracts at the Public Record Office, London, England, presented by Leander McCormick—Goodhart. No. 3496. Thomas Willis White (1788-1843). Fifty-two letters of the founder of the Southern Literary Messenger, which Edgar Allan Poe edited from 1835-1837, to Nathaniel Beverley Tucker, author and William &amp; Mary law professor, 1834-1840. From originals in Tucker-Coleman Papers, deposited at Colonial Williamsburg, microfilmed by the Virginia State Library. No. 3435. MILLER, FRANCIS PICKENS. 1948-1949. 3 items. Gift of Mrs. John Flynn. No. 2999. Speeches made during his campaign for Governor of Virginia. MILLER, JOHN N. 1862-1949. 8 items. Gift of John Nicolson. No. 3348. Letter to "Friend Nathan" 5 October 1862, describing his work as a surgeon in charge of 150 wounded soldiers at Capitol General Hospital, Washington, D. C., located in part of the Capitol building. Two typed copies and two photostats of the letter; letter to War Department verifies his commission at Washington as surgeon from 20 September to 23 October, 1862. MISCELLANEOUS TRANSCRIPTS. 1798-1868. 11 items. Deposit. No. 3402. Copies of the following letters of representative American statesmen, educators, and ex-presidents as published in various newspapers: George Washington to Mrs. Francis Washington, 24 February 1798, expressing condolence on death of a friend (Boston Advertiser, June 11, 1862); Thomas Jefferson to Horatio Turpin, 10 June 1802, on nepotism and position of Postmaster at Richmond, Va. (Cincinnati Enquirer, June 30, 1870); James Madison to Robert R. Livingston, 28 October 1803, discussing Jerome Bonaparte's coming marriage to Elizabeth (Betsy) Patterson, of Baltimore, Md. (Baltimore American February 21, 1861); Timothy Dwight to John Taylor, of Caroline, 3 September 1805 about inquiries of curriculum at Yale University and Taylor's reply to Dwight's letter on behavior of Virginia students and their attitudes on morals, industry, and slavery with severe warning of the evil of wrong impressions of Northerners about the South (Richmond Examiner June 20, 1863); John Tyler, Governor of Virginia, to Whig members of New York Legislature, 20 March 1840, on favorable personal comments and New York politics (National Intelligencer July 8, 1840); Andrew Jackson to A. J. Cotton, Manchester, Indiana, 29 September 1841, thanking him for praise of his actions while President and of his cordial relations with his Cabinet (Portland (Me.) Argus, March 2, 1877); Resolution of Southern Commercial Convention, Knoxville, Tennessee, 1857, proposed by E. B. Bryan of South Carolina against Articles 8 and 11 of Treaty of Washington (ratified 1842) and a letter of John Tyler, 31 August 1857 in regard to this resolution, and keeping of a squadron on the Coast of Africa to suppress the slave trade (Richmond Enquirer August 4 and September 4, 1857); Jefferson Davis to Mrs. J. K. Kyle, Fayettesville, North Carolina, 22 April 1866, thanking her for check to Mrs. Davis, written from Fortress Monroe (New York Herald May 6, 1866); Robert E. Lee reply to Army friends, 25 January 1867, on gift of game cocks (Chicago Tribune March 18, 1867); Franklin Pierce to J. D. Hoover of Louisville, Kentucky, 22 April 1868, on political affairs (Louisville Democrat May 21, 1868). MITCHELL'S MAP OF NORTH AMERICA, 1755. 1949. 1 item. Gift of Howard Garth Hamilton. No. 3385. Mr. Hamilton's typescript essay on the 1755 map of Dr. John Mitchell. MONROE, JAMES (1758-1831). 1781-1830. 58 items. Deposit. No. 3342. Correspondence among the Committee of Public Safety, Maria Monroe Gouverneur, Samuel Gouverneur, George Hay, Thomas Jefferson, Chapman Johnson, and the Marquis de Lafayette, and four letters of congratulations on retiring from Presidency from Carson Colins, Speaker of the Assembly, for New York Resolutions, Governor H. Johnson for Louisiana Resolutions, and Albion K. Parris, Governor, for Maine Resolutions. Land grant, 18 May 1786, to James Monroe for 5,625 acres of land in Fayette County [now W. Va.] signed by Patrick Henry, Governor; article on France by Monroe signed Aratus, [1795]; memorandum book, 1795-1810; bank book, 1811; thirty-eight orders signed by him, 1813-1822. MONROE, JAMES (1758-1831). 1783-1834. 60 items. Deposit. No. 3419. Correspondence with James Brown, Mr. Campbell, P. DeRieux, George E. Erving, William Eustis, Charles Everett, John Graham, Christopher Hughes, Jr., the Marquis de Lafayette, Mr. Lewis, John Mason, C. F. Mercer, Humphrey Peake, Caesar Rodney, Jonathan Russell, Thomas Swann, and John Taliaferro; manuscripts on financial matters with: Bank of Columbia, William Faley, Charles J. Ingersoll, B. L. Lear, Andrew Monroe, Tench Ringgold, and Littleton W. Tazewell; documents addressed to Monroe concern Lydia Barker, whose son had been impressed by the British, Benjamin Lovett, and Israel Thorndike; those issued by Monroe were a land grant to Joshua Farnsby for a tract in Harrison County, Indiana, and a sea letter for the ship Leonidas, signed by Monroe and John Quincy Adams. Other letters include: George Graham to T. Worthington, 3 April 1815; William Lee to Colonel Symmes, 5 December 1817; J. B. Cooper to John Page, 13 March 1822; and Thomas Monroe to John Randolph Clay, 24 November 1834. Seven printed pamphlets on Monroe including an act authorizing the Fourth Census, 1820, one presidential message, 1823, and a memorial and two reports on his behalf by citizens of Albemarle to reconsider his claims and secure him some money; and the Christian Intelligencer and Eastern Chronicle, Gardiner, Maine, for February 4, 1831. MONROE, JAMES (1758-1831). 1805-1821. 5 items. Deposit. No. 3355. Letters to [Joseph Prentis] from London 29 October 1805; Cheltenham, 6 January 1806; and Richmond, 22 January and 13 November 1808; and document appointing Joseph Prentis surveyor and inspector of revenue for Suffolk, Virginia, 9 March 1821. MONROE, JAMES (1758-1821). 1829 Nov. 30. 1 LS. Coles Collection. No. 3351. To the President of the Board of Directors of the State Literary Fund, accompanying the report of the use of funds at the University of Virginia, passed by the Board of Visitors and signed by Madison, Rector pro tempore. MORRIS, ANNA MARIA JACKSON DE CAMP. 1850-1858. 1 vol. Deposit. No. 3448. Diary of the wife of Major Gouverneur Morris containing particularly a record of her trip West with her husband over the Santa Fé Trail in 1850 to Santa Fé, where he was stationed, and of life in New Mexico in the early 1850's. MORTON, JEREMIAH. 1841 Dec. 27. 1 item. Gift of Miss Texie P. Watts. No. 3383. Agreement for sale of a slave to William Hume, Orange County, Va. MORTON FAMILY. 1778-1824. 18 items. Gift of Miss Texie P. Watts. No. 3319. Copies of Virginia and South Carolina deeds, wills, and other papers relating to the Mortons, and connected families of Clarkson and Ragland, including photostats of indenture and bounty warrants for the River Hill estate at Stony Point, Albemarle County, Va. NASH, OGDEN. 1950. 2 items. Gift of Miss Roy Land. No. 3466. Introduction by Professor Dan S. Norton, University of Virginia, to Nash's talk before the Friends of the University, April 1950. Typescript with carbon copy. NEWSPAPERS. Byrd, Coles, McGregor, and General libraries; gifts and deposits. Virginia's state-wide cooperative program for the preservation of currently published Virginia newspapers, maintained by a majority of the editors and publishers in cooperation with the libraries of Virginia, has been supported by the University Library during the past two years through the cataloguing for permanent preservation of sixty-eight Virginia dailies and weeklies. The purpose of the program is to ensure the preservation of at least one complete file of each Virginia newspaper in at least one library. The publishers are asked to furnish one free subscription to one library. The libraries bear the cost of cataloguing, storage, and maintenance or microfilming. Fifty-five subscriptions have been received by this library during the period of this report as the publishers' contribution to this project in our library. A list of these is appended at the end of this report. As this report goes to press a sub-committee of the Virginia Committee for Library Development, under the chairmanship of Miss Catherine Slaughter of Radford College, is at work on a plan to bring this cooperative program up to date. Beginning with a new inventory of existing files, the committee hopes to distribute the preservation of Virginia newspapers among a greater number of libraries (a disproportionate number are now kept by the University Library and the Virginia State Library), to assure better continuity of the work by the newspaper publishers as well as the libraries, and to promote large scale microfilming projects. Leading regional newspapers of the United States and foreign countries come to the library by subscription, the most constantly used of these being the rag-paper edition of the New York Times, with its index. Provision of adequate storage space is an ever-increasing problem, and consideration is being given to a greater use of the space-saving (but costly and time-consuming) expedient of microfilm. Some subscriptions are already received in the form of microfilm. Participation in cooperative microfilming projects has added to our files for research; and files of original newspapers have been received by exchange and on deposit. Editors' files, deposited for safekeeping, are catalogued and made available for research in all cases where that is authorized by the owners. Among the unique issues added to our collections during the year, and listed below, the Fredericksburg Virginia Herald of 31 December 1799, presented by Dr. William B. Sims, is of extraordinary interest. This issue, which happens to be in a fine state of preservation, carries an account, published five days before New York's famous issue of the Ulster County Gazette, of the death of George Washington. For other rare issues, and for special services to the newspaper collection, we are indebted to many of the friends of the library listed at the end of this report. New acquisitions listed below include only those issues which, so far as is known (from Brigham's and Cappon's bibliographies) have never previously existed in any library. Amherst, Virginia Amherst New-Era, 1901 Jan. 31; Feb. 14; Apr. 18; May 9, 16, 23; June 6, 27; July 4, 11; Aug. 22; Oct. 3, 10. Berryville, Virginia Clarke Courier, 1869 Nov. 3, 10. Bridgewater, Virginia Bridgewater Herald, 1895 Nov. 29; 1901 June 7; (Only issues known of this title.) Clifton Forge, Virginia Clifton Forge Review, 1921 Dec. 16. Culpeper, Virginia Culpeper Times, 1874 Apr. 3. Fredericksburg, Virginia Virginia Herald, 1799 Dec. 31. Gloucester, Virginia Gloucester Gazette, 1925 July 23. Gordonsville, Virginia Sun-Herald, 1891 June 4. Hot Springs, Virginia The Telegraph, 1914 Aug. 24, 29; Sept. 2, 15, 19, 23. (Only issues known of this title.) Leesburg, Virginia Democratic Mirror, 1859 Jan. 12; Feb. 2, 16. Genius of Liberty, 1832 Apr. 14. Loudoun Chronicle, 1852 Sept. 10. The Mirror, 1866 Feb. 28. The Washingtonian, 1844 Jan. 13. Lynchburg, Virginia Evening Star, 1876 Jan. 18. Madison, Virginia Free-Press, 1893 Dec. 21. (Only issue known of this title.) Marion, Virgina Patriot and Herald, 1874 July 9; Sept. 24; Dec. 17. New Market, Virginia Spirit of Democracy, 1856 Sept. 12; Oct. 24, 31. Newport News, Virginia The Wedge, 1883 June 3. (Title unknown to Cappon.) Orange, Virginia Orange Observer, 1899 Oct. 13. Pocahontas, Virginia Industrial Messenger, 1892 Aug. 6; (Only issue known of this title.) Portsmouth, Virginia Tidewater Times, 1879 Oct. 6. Richmond, Virginia Weekly Dispatch, 1901 Oct. 10. Scottsville, Virginia Scottsville Register, 1872 Feb. 17. Staunton, Virginia Republican Farmer, 1814 Mar. 10. Suffolk, Virginia Weekly Observer, 1892, Aug. 17. Charlestown, [West] Virginia Spirit of Jefferson, 1853 May 3. NICHOLAS, WILSON CARY. 1789 Jan. 8. 1 ADS (photostat). Exchange. No. 3254. Recommendation to Albemarle County Court that Wilson Cary Nicholas be made county lieutenant; attested by John Nicholas, clerk. Photostat of original at Virginia State Library. Has Albemarle County seal. NOURSE FAMILY OF WESTON. 1685(1786-1870)1904. 1400 items and 31 vols. Deposit. Gift of the Misses Constance and Charlotte Nourse. No. 3490. Personal, business, and official correspondence, account books, and common-place books of the Nourse family of Weston, Herefordshire, England; Berkeley County, Va. (now W.Va.); Washington, D. C., and of Weston, Fauquier County, Va., and of their relatives, the Bull family of Berkeley County, Va., and the Morris family of Philadelphia. James Nourse (1731-1784) the immigrant, married Sarah Fouace in 1753, was a woolen draper for fifteen years in London before sailing to Virginia in 1769 with a family of nine children, lived in Hampton a year, moved to Piedmont plantation near Charleston, Berkeley County (W.Va.), was a farmer, one of thirteen trustees of Berkeley Springs, financier for Berkeley and Frederick counties, in Virginia militia, member of House of Delegates in 1778, and was appointed Commissioner to settle claims against the U. S. in 1781 where he lived at the home of Mr. Hammond, near Annapolis, until his death in 1784. James Nourse (1754-1841), educated in England and in his father's business in London and on his plantation in Virginia, was military secretary to General Charles Lee, Commander of Southern Department of the American Army, first register of U. S. Treasury, 1789-1829, married Maria Louise Bull, was vice-president of the American Bible Society, elder of a Presbyterian Church in Philadelphia and "F Street" Presbyterian Church in Washington. Charles Josephus Nourse (1786-1851) was Jefferson's special courier to England in 1808, rose to Adjutant General in the War of 1812, married Rebecca Morris, became chief clerk of the War Department, 1827-1829, owned flour mill in Georgetown and was Justice of Peace, 1839-1851. This correspondence, principally of Joseph and Charles Josephus Nourse, contains material on American finance during the Revolutionary and Confederation periods, the operation of the U. S. Treasury, campaigns in the War of 1812, American diplomacy in Spain in 1814, the administration of the U. S. Army, 1819-1829, the effect of Jackson's spoils system; and social life in Washington, D. C. in the ante bellum period. Other members of the family mentioned are: James Burn Nourse; J. Pemberton Nourse; Anthony Morris, merchant, politician, director of Bank of North America, and unofficial representative of United States in Spain; Mary Pemberton Morris, and Phoebe Morris. Other correspondents included: Nicholas Biddle, Sir Augustus John Foster, Sam Houston, James and Dolly Madison, Richard Rush, Gen. Winfield Scott, Robert John Walker, and George and Martha Washington. Typescript memoirs of the Nourse family, compiled by Miss Constance Nourse in 1940 consisting chiefly of copies of family letters, 1769-1825 on microfilm. PAGE, FREDERICK WINSLOW (1826-1913). 1849 Sept. 3. 1 ADS. Gift of Miss Anne Page Brydon. No. 3386. Authorization to practice law in Virginia, signed by the three examining judges—John J. Allen, Briscoe G. Baldwin, and William Daniel, Jr.—Lewisburg, Virginia. Page was associated with the University of Virginia faculty for many years, being librarian in the years 1881-83 and 1891-1903. PAGE, JAMES MORRIS (1864-1936). 1885-1932. 40 items. Archival Transfer. No. 3284. Among the papers of the late Dean of the University and of the College of Arts and Sciences, and professor of mathematics, are accounts of his trip to Germany and his student days there, 1885-1887; his trip to Italy in 1931; his investigations of the office of Dean at Harvard and Yale, 1917; and some correspondence, 1924-1932, regarding a seventeenth century Italian painting. See also heading, University of Virginia, College of Arts and Sciences in this and previous annual reports for the official records of the Dean. PANAMA CANAL. 1912-1915. 13 items. Gift of Miss M. M. Withrow. No. 3281. Clippings and articles on the building of the Canal and the issues involved there; copy of a Congressional speech on the matter by H. D. Flood of Virginia. PARLIER, FRANK H. 1950. 1 item. Gift. No. 3493. Typescript of essay, "American Foreign Policy Toward Palestine from the Balfour Declaration of 1917 to the end of the British Mandate on May 15, 1948". PATTON, JOHN SHELTON (1857-1932). 1906-1907. 8 items. Gift of Mrs. J. Callan Brooks. No. 3312. Eight letters relating to Nathaniel Francis Cabell's Jefferson, Cabell, and the University, by the former librarian of the University of Virginia, with forty clippings of reviews of the book. PEYTON, BERNARD. 1885. 1 item. Gift of Bernard Chamberlain. No. 3381. Memorandum by Peyton regarding the "Knights of the Horseshoe," listing the members of Governor Alexander Spotswood's expedition across the Blue Ridge Mountains. PHILIPPI, WEST VIRGINIA, BANK OF. 1857-1865. 2 vols. Deposit. No. 3247. Ledgers, covering the period when Barbour County with other western counties were formed into the State of West Virginia. POE, EDGAR ALLAN (1809-1849). 1949-1950. 40 items. Gift of Irby B. Cauthen. No. 3497. Correspondence with Harry Ammon, E. A. Balderston, Robert W. Hill, Dard Hunter, William M. Ivins, Jr., Thomas O. Mabbott, David A. Randall, Rollo G. Silver, J. Armistead Welbourn, and Mr. and Mrs. Hampleton Welbourn, on the authenticity of Poe's "Alone," dated and given title by Eugene Didier but originally written by Poe in the autograph album of Lucy Holmes (Mrs. Isiah Balderston) of Baltimore, Md., including photostats of "Alone" and another poem in the album now owned by Mr. and Mrs. Welbourn, with galley proof of Cauthen's article which was published in the Bibliographical Society of Virginia, Studies in Bibliography, III, 284-291 (Charlottesville, 1950). POE, EDGAR ALLAN (1809-1849). 1 item. Gift of Miss Margaret M. Withrow. No. 3281. Engraving of Poe. POLK, JAMES KNOX (1795-1849). 1841 Mar. 17. 1 DS. Deposit. No. 3261. Commission for justice of peace, 1841, when governor of Tennessee. PRATT, AGNES ROTHERY. 1900(1949)-1950. 2,000 items and 7 vols. Gift of Mrs. Pratt. Nos. 3335, 3369, and 3469. Additions to the collection of literary manuscripts of Agnes Rothery (Mrs. Harry Rogers Pratt), including drafts of Rome Today and The Joyful Gardener, with notes, galley and page proofs, clippings, correspondence, illustrations, and other items relating to these books. Three scrapbooks of clippings of James L. Rothery, four photograph albums of the Rothery family, and some material on the Pratt family. See also previous annual reports. PRESTON, ALFRED D. 1885-1910. 8 items. Gift of Mr. Preston. No. 3274. Letters, copies of poems, 25 clippings and 2 articles on a muster roll of Thurmond Rangers discovered by Mr. Preston. PREVITALI, GIOVANNI. 1950. 1 item. Gift. No. 3493. Typescript of paper, "The Living Language System of Teaching Foreign Languages." PRINTS AND PICTURES. Mackay-Smith Collection, addition to the Byrd, Coles, McGregor, and General libraries. Among the 2,413 prints and pictures acquired during the year, the following will serve as examples: Wood blocks for the views of Petersburg and of White Sulphur Springs that were used in Henry Howe's Historical Collections of Virginia, Charleston, S. C., 1845 (gift of Mr. Paul Victorius); a blueprint of a Revolutionary Cemetery at Williamsburg, Virginia, made as part of an archaelogical survey in 1930 (gift of Francis Duke); a cartoon portrait of John Randolph of Roanoke, engraved before 1833. Seventeen additions have been made to the Jefferson iconographic collection, all early 19th century engravings except one portrait, ca. 1825?, embossed in plaster, from the St. Mémin profile. Two groups totaling 36 items presented by Mr. Alexander Mackay-Smith are worthy of special notice. These are contemporary engravings of European musicians of the 17th to the 19th centuries. They include portraits of: Mr. Abel, Thomas Arne, William Boyce, J. B. Breval, Thomas Britton, Wilhelm Cramer, J. B. Davaux, William Davenant, Nicolaus Daleyrac, Hanns Fiedelbogen, Frederick II of Prussia, Christoph W. Gluck, Niclas Gomelli, Carl Heinrich Graun, A. E. M. Grétry, Hans Leo Hasler, Joseph Haydn, Michel Haydn, William Herschel, Michel Richard De Lalande, Orlando de Lassus, Joannes Mattheson, J. G. Naumann, Antonio Pisani, Ignaz Pleyel, Henry Purcell, Johann Joachim Quanz, J. P. Rameau, A. M. G. Sacchini, Joseph Schuster, Heinrich Schütz, Johannes Staden, and S. T. Staden. There are also engravings of "Les Musicians" by I. S. Ostade and of the engraver Steffano de la Bella. RANDOLPH, EDMUND. 1803. 2 DS. Coles Collection. No. 3347. Documents giving his opinion in the cases of Davis Smith vs. John Wilder and Susanna Simmons' execution of the will of her husband, Henry. RANDOLPH, JOHN (1773-1833) PAPERS AND TRANSCRIPTS. In addition to the notable group of Randolph manuscripts deposited this year with the Bryan family manuscripts (and so entered earlier in this report), we have received important original manuscripts from Mr. Leigh D. Williams and others as listed below. A score of institutions have generously cooperated in supplying us with microfilm copies, for which the reader is referred to The Papers of Randolph of Roanoke, a checklist separately published by the library this year, and to the supplement to that checklist printed below. Through the courtesy of a private owner, Mrs. George P. Coleman, and the generous help of Colonial Williamsburg and the Virginia State Library, we have obtained microfilm of Randolph's commonplace book and the extensive correspondence with St. George Tucker and others in the Tucker-Coleman papers. We regretted the omission from the Checklist of the microfilm from the Tazewell papers courteously supplied by the University of North Carolina, and it is a satisfaction to include it in this first supplement. RANDOLPH, JOHN OF ROANOKE (1773-1833). 1800-(1833) 1851. 29 items. Gift of Leigh D. Williams. No. 3339. Correspondence with John Brockenbrough, Joseph Bryan, John Randolph Clay, George Hay, Benjamin W. Leigh, William Leigh, Prince Lieven, John Marshall, James Monroe, Richard Stanford, Martin Van Buren, and Daniel Webster; and three letters between Benjamin, William, and Rebecca Leigh, 1845-1851. RANDOLPH, JOHN OF ROANOKE (1773-1833). 1811-1904. 11 items. Deposit. No. 3400. Letters to J. H. Nicholson; Thomas Forman on Joseph Bryan; John Rodgers and Mrs. Joseph Bryan on John Randolph Bryan's service in the Navy; and from Elizabeth Tucker Coalter. Order of Randolph's for payment of $100 to Cheston Ringgold, and note by the undertaker on Randolph's measurements. Letter of Daniel Grinnan to Joseph Bryan enclosing his copy of Francis West's reminiscences of Randolph's death, 1887; and letter of Lambert Tree to Joseph Bryan on a Randolph document, 1904. Also, John Randolph's prayer book, originally inscribed 1811 and presented to John St. George Randolph in 1818. RANDOLPH, JOHN OF ROANOKE (1773-1833). 1814 July 28. 1 ALS. (photostat). Gift of Miss Mary L. Garland. No. 3410. Letter to David Parish mentioning Randolph's proposed trip to Europe. RANDOLPH, JOHN OF ROANOKE (1773-1833). 1832 Sept. 22. 1 ALS. Coles Collection. No. 3432. Letter to the Department of State (with seal) concerning a letter he had failed to receive from John Randolph Clay, Secretary of the Legation at the Court of Russia, St. Petersburg, where John Randolph was Minister until ill health forced him to return to the United States. RANDOLPH, JOHN OF ROANOKE. SUPPLEMENT TO CHECKLIST OF HIS WRITINGS. 1790-1830. 124 items. Microfilm. The items listed below in this as in future annual reports will serve to supplement the checklist of John Randolph's surviving manuscripts published recently by the library as number 9 in its bibliographical series. Some of the items in this list appeared in the published volume, but are repeated for the sake of additional information. Others were inadvertently omitted by the compilers or have come to light since. 1790 Apr. 26. J R, New York, to HENRY M. RUTLEDGE. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. 1790 May 15. J R, New York, to HENRY M. RUTLEDGE. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. 1791 July 16. J R, Philadelphia, to HENRY M. RUTLEDGE. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. Partial text: Bruce II 323. 1791 July 29. J R, Philadelphia, to HENRY M. RUTLEDGE. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. 1795 Dec. 28. J R, Bizarre, to HENRY M. RUTLEDGE. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. Partial text: Bruce I 93, 135. 1796 May 7. J R, Columbia, to HENRY M. RUTLEDGE. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. 1797 Apr. 29. J R, Bizarre, to HENRY M. RUTLEDGE. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. 1798 Mar. 19. J R, Bizarre, to JAMES BROWN. ALS in NN. Film in ViU. 1801 Dec. 26. J R, Washington, to ST. GEORGE TUCKER. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. Partial text: Bruce II 234. 1802 Jan. 19. J R, Washington, six-line note. NN. Film in ViU. 1802 Apr. 8. J R, signed note to MR. LINCOLN. MHi. Film in ViU. 1802 Apr. 30. J R, note to MR. LINCOLN. MHi. Film in ViU. 1803 Nov. 13. L. W. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J. R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1803 Dec. 29. L. W. TAZEWELL, Hampton, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1804 Jan. 8. J R, Washington, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1804 Feb. 26. J R, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1804 Mar. 4. L. W. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1804 Apr. 21. J R, Bizarre, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. Partial text: Bruce I 297. 1804 May 8. L. W. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1804 June 8. J R, Bizarre, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1804 Dec. 7. J R, Washington, to MR. LINCOLN. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. 1807 Aug. 23. J R, Bizarre, to THOMAS NEWTON, JR. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. 1807 Sept. 18. J R, Bizarre, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1807 Dec. 24. J R, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1808 Mar. 20. J R, Georgetown, to EDWARD LEIGH. ALS in NN. Film in ViU. 1810 Apr. 10. J R, Georgetown, to —————————————. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. 1810 Nov. 12. C. W. CUSTIS, Arlington House, to GEORGE LOGAN. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. 1810 Nov. 13. J R, Roanoke, to JOHN TAYLOR. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. 1810 Dec. 4. J R, Bizarre, to GEORGE LOGAN. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. 1811 Feb. 4. L. W. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1811 Feb. 6. J R, Georgetown, to GEORGE LOGAN. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. 1811 Mar. 13. J R, Todd's, to JOHN TAYLOR. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. 1811 Nov. 18. L. W. TAZEWELL, Richmond, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1811 Dec. 13. J R, Georgetown, to JOHN TAYLOR. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. 1812 Feb. 4. J R, Georgetown, to CHARLES SCOTT. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. 1812 May 12. J R, Georgetown, to —————————. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. 1812 June 16. J R, Georgetown, to JOHN TAYLOR. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. 1812 June 25. J R, Washington, to [DAVID PARISH]. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. 1812 Dec. 15. J R, Georgetown, to JOHN TAYLOR. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. 1813 Jan. 4. J R, Port Royal, to JOHN TAYLOR. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. 1813 Feb. 13. J R, Georgetown, to GEORGE LOGAN. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. 1814 Jan. 7. L. W. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1814 Mar. 7. J R, Richmond, to OUTERBRIDGE HORSEY. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. 1814 Nov. 8. J R, New York, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1814 Dec. 22. J R, Philadelphia, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1814 Dec. 30. L. W. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1815 Jan. 3. J R, Port Royal, to JOHN TAYLOR. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. 1815 Mar. 14. L. W. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1815 Apr. 7. J R, Roanoke, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. Partial text: Bruce I 599. 1816 Jan. 24. J R, Georgetown, to ——————————. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. 1816 Jan. 24. J R, Georgetown, to GEORGE LOGAN. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. 1816 Feb. 15. J R, Oaklands, to DENNIS A. SMITH. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. 1816 Feb. 20. J R, Georgetown, to GEORGE LOGAN. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. 1816 Feb. 21. J R, Georgetown, to GEORGE LOGAN. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. 1816 Mar. 4. J R, to ————————————. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. 1816 Apr. 27. J R, Georgetown, to GEORGE LOGAN. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. Partial text: Bruce II 597. 1817 Mar. 2. J R, Georgetown, to GEORGE LOGAN. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. 1817 Mar. 2. J R, Georgetown, to TIMOTHY PICKERING. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. 1817 Mar. 15. J R, Richmond, to TIMOTHY PICKERING. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. 1817 Apr. 20. J R, Roanoke, to TIMOTHY PICKERING. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. 1817 May 5, J R, Richmond, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1820 Jan. 1. J R, Washington, to TIMOTHY PICKERING. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. 1821 Jan. 25. L. W. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1822 Feb. 10. J R, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 182[3] Mar. L. W. TAZEWELL, to JR. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1824 Mar. 20. L. W. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1824 May 11. L. W. TAZEWELL, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1824 Dec. 14. J R, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1825 Feb. 19. J R, to JACOB HARVEY. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. 1825 Mar. 8. J R, Kerwards, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. [9]. L. W. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. 12. J R, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. 12. L. W. TAZEWELL, Alexandria, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. 13. J R, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. 14. J R, Washington, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. Partial text: Bruce II 641. 1826 Feb. 15. J R, Washington, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. 15. J R, Washington, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. 16. L. W. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. 17. J R, Washington, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. Mentioned: Bruce I 54, 60. 1826 Feb. 17. L. W. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. 17-18. J R, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. 19. J R, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. 20. J R, Washington, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. Partial text: Bruce II 594, 698. 1826 Feb. 20. L. W. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. 21. J R, Washington, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. Partial text: Bruce I 352, II 641. 1826 Feb. 22. J R, Washington, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. Partial text: Bruce I 87. 1826 Feb. 22. L. W. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. 23. J R, Washington, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. 23. L. W. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. 24. J R, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. 25. J R, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. 25. L. W. TAZEWELL, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. 26. J R, to L. W. TAZEWELL. (1st part missing) ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. 27. J R, Washington, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. 27. L. W. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. 28. J R, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Feb. 28. JOHN H. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Mar. 1. J R, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Mar. 2. JOHN H. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Mar. 4. L. W. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Mar. 5. J R, Kerwards, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Mar. 6. L. W. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Mar. 7. J R, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Mar. 8. J R, to L. W. TAZEWELL [cover only] NcU. Film in ViU. Partial text: Bruce I 592, II 317. 1826 Mar. 9. L. W. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Mar. 13. J R, Kerwards, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. Partial text: Bruce I 560. 1826 Mar. 13. L. W. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Mar. 14. J R, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Mar. 21. J R, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 Mar. 26. ELIZABETH TUCKER COALTER, Richmond, to JR. ALS owned by St. George T. Grinnan. Photo in ViU. 1826 Apr. 22. J R, to L. W. TAZEWELL. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1826 May 6. J R, Washington, to —————————————. ALS in PHi. Film in ViU. Partial text: Bruce II 684-685. 1827 Feb. 6. J R, Chatham, to HENRY TUCKER. ALS owned by St. George T. Grinnan. Photo in ViU. 1828 Jan. 16. J R, Washington, to WILLIAM R. JOHNSON. ALS in CSmH. Film in ViU. Text: Bouldin 225-6. 1828 Mar. 19. J R, Washington, to TIMOTHY PICKERING. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. 1829 Jan. 26. J R, Washington, to HENRY TUCKER. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. 1829 Apr. 4. J R, to TIMOTHY PICKERING. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. 1828[9] Apr. 24. J R, Washington, to TIMOTHY PICKERING. ALS in MHi. Film in ViU. 1830 May 26. L. W. TAZEWELL, Norfolk, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1830 May 30. J R, Bizarre, to JOHN A. SKINNER, Editor of the Turf Register, of Baltimore. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. 1830 June 30. L. W. TAZEWELL, to J R. ALS in NcU. Film in ViU. n. d. J R, to L. W. TAZEWELL. NcU. Film in ViU. n. d. L. W. TAZEWELL, to J R. NcU. Film in ViU. n. d. L. W. TAZEWELL, to J R. NcU. Film in ViU. RICHMOND JOCKEY CLUB. 1824-1838. 1 vol. Deposit. No. 3447. Photostats of minutes, and records of the racing, which was held at Tree Hill. Officers of the club included Charles T. Bott, A. L. Botts, H. Davis, Theo. Field, Benjamin Harrison, J. B. Harvie, John Heth, Edmond Irby, William R. Johnson, John Minge, Wade Mosby, Jr., Bernard Peyton, Thomas M. Randolph, Jr., of Tuckahoe, Thomas Sawson, R. G. Scott, James M. Selden, and Andrew Stevenson. Also a photostat of a broadside advertising Planet, a racehorse owned by Thomas Doswell and Thomas W. Doswell. ROLFE, JOHN (1585-1622). 1617 June 8. 1 ALS (photostat). Coles Collection. No. 3446. To Sir Edwin Sandys, describing conditions at Jamestown. SCHUYLKILL COUNTY, PENNSYLVANIA. 1845 Mar. 27. 1 item. Gift of Lambert Molyneaux. No. 3269. Improvement lease, for a tract of land with buildings, in Union Township, between the mayor, aldermen, and citizens of Philadelphia, through their agent, Jacob Sheafe, and Immanuel Loro. SEAY FAMILY PAPERS. 1842-1890. 300 items. Gift of Henry T. Louthan. No. 3366. Additional papers of the Seay family of Richmond and Caroline counties, Va., consisting chiefly of the official and private papers of Joseph Seay, Sheriff of Carolina County, 1842-1855, and receipts and bills of E. Y. Seay and Joseph M. Seay, 1887-1890. Names appearing most frequently in records are: Joseph D. Broaddus, Hugh Chandler, Robert E. Coleman, John L. Henley, Joseph W. Holt, A. S. Hundley, Thomas Hurt, John R. Jones, W. Moncure, McKenzie R. Robertson, F. S. Scott, Thomas L. Scott, B. F. Smoot, John L. Tod, and Wesley Wright. Previous acquisitions of Seay manuscripts are described in the eighth and fifteenth annual reports. SEIBEL, FREDERICK OTTO. 1940-1944. 3 items. Gift of M. F. Partridge. No. 3271. Three original drawings of political cartoons by the noted cartoonist of the Richmond Times Dispatch, all inscribed to Mr. Partridge: "Smoke gets in his eyes," "Call to colors," and "Thomas Jefferson in Virginia." For description of the Seibel Archive see previous annual reports. SNEAD, ISRAEL. 1799. 1 vol. Gift of Miss Sara K. Gilliam and Mrs. J. T. Gilliam. No. 3270. Manuscript arithmetic lessons of Israel Snead of Halifax County, Virginia. SOUTHERN WRITERS CONVENTION. 1931. 91 items. Gift of James Southall Wilson. No. 3422. Letters (carbon copies) of James Southall Wilson to thirty-six of the writers invited to the convention, held at the University of Virginia in October 1931. This group complements the correspondence of the invited writers with Wilson, which was given to the Library some years ago. Those to whom Dean Wilson wrote were: Conrad Aiken, Sherwood Anderson, Katherine Anthony, Emily Clark Balch, John Peale Bishop, James Boyd, Roark Bradford, Struthers Burt, James Branch Cabell, Willa Cather, Maristan Chapman, Donald Davidson, William E. Dodd, William Faulkner, Ellen Glasgow, Isa Glenn, Paul Green, Archibald Henderson, DuBose Heyward, Mrs. DuBose Heyward, Gerald Johnson, Mary Johnston, Mrs. H. L. Mencken, Julia Peterkin, Ulrich B. Phillips, Josephine Pinckney, Burton Rascoe, Lizette Woodworth Reese, Mrs. Cale Young Rice, Elizabeth Maddox Roberts, Herbert Ravenel Sass, Mrs. Lawrence Stallings, Allen Tate, Irita Van Doren, Thomas Wolfe, and Stark Young. TAX RECORDS, VIRGINIA. 1819-1820. 1 item. Gift. No. 3403. Memorandum of town and county taxes collected in Fairfax, Halifax, Jefferson, Loudoun, and Washington counties. TENNESSEE COAL, IRON AND RAILROAD COMPANY. 1932. 1 vol. Gift of Edward R. Stettinius. No. 2723. Historical study, based on company records, from its founding in 1852 to 1932, by W. B. Allen. The United States Steel Corporation acquired control of the company in 1907. TEXAS, LAND SPECULATION. 1833. 1 item. Deposit. No. 3071. Certificate for a 4,000 acre tract issued to Robert Adams by the "New Arkansas and Texas Land Company," signed by the trustees. THAYER, WILLIAM SYDNEY (1830-1864). 1835-1895. 450 items. Deposit. No. 3445. Papers of the American Consul-General to Egypt, including correspondence and pictures of Abijah W., New England editor, and Susan B. Thayer, his parents, and James B. and Sarah S. Thayer, his brother and sister, 1835-1860; 40 themes written while at Harvard College and an 1850 commencement program; 45 items of the expedition to Nicaragua of J. W. Fabens and Col. H. L. Kinney, including stocks of the Nicaragua Land and Mining Company, and clippings, including a complete first issue of the San Juan del Norte Central American 1855-1856; 200 clippings of Thayer's dispatches for the London Times and the New York Evening Post, 1860-1861; correspondence with John Bigelow, 1861-1864; typescript of journal begun in 1852 but most complete for 1861-1864 period; incomplete set of his dispatches as Consul-General in Egypt, 18611863; letters relating to death of Abijah and William Sydney Thayer, 1864-1895. THOMPSON, JOHN REUBEN (1823-1873). 1864. 1 vol. Deposit. No. 3400. Journal of this critic, poet, editor of Southern Literary Messenger, and correspondent for the London Index and the Memphis Appeal, for 1864, describing life and conditions in Richmond and in England, where he met such personages as Albert Taylor Bledsoe, Thomas Carlyle, Alexander Collie, Lord and Lady Donoughmore, Walker Fearn, James E. MacFarland, Norman Walker, and David Watson. THOMPSON, JOHN REUBEN (1823-1873). 1872 July 6. 1 ALS. Coles Collection. No. 3391. To Benjamin Johnson Barbour, about the election of a new rector at the University of Virginia, mentioning John B. Minor and E. A. Pollard. TRIST, NICHOLAS PHILIP (1800-1874). 1869 Apr. 2. 1 ALS. Coles Collection. No. 1670. Personal note to Henry C. Carey. TUCKER, JOHN. 1811-1847. 20 items. Coles Collection. No. 3307. Papers of John Tucker of Smokey Ordinary, Justice of the Peace and Sheriff of Brunswick County, Va., including letters, documents, deeds, and bank notes, on his administration of plantations and slaves of Elizabeth Rainey and Mary Ann Tucker of Putnam and Troup Counties, Georgia, and of mill and lands of Pugh and Mary Price, and Thomas and Patsy (Clay) Ingram of Boone County, Ky.; interesting letter by "a citizen of Brunswick," [by John Tucker, sheriff], 24 May 1811, titled "If the cap fits you wear it" or "Qui facit ille capiat," on the corruption of office holders with special reference to the magistrates of Brunswick County; fragment of letter of Thomas Gholson to Major John Tucker, 4 July 1812, in reply to a broadside which is in our collection here on the methods of the British to create distrust and to try to divide the United States on such issues as the embargo and impressment of sailors; Valentine verse with an itemized record of sale of grain, livestock, and slaves of the Tuckers of Hanover. Among correspondents are: Benjamin I. Harper, James M. Hill, Edward C. Smith, Edward B. Tucker, William Vawter, and William Wells. TUCKER, JOHN E. 1844-1850. 1 vol. Coles Collection. No. 3307. Account book of his blacksmith and machine shop in Brunswick County. TUCKER FAMILY OF BRUNSWICK COUNTY. 1797-1843. 6 vols. Coles Collection. No. 3483. Ledger of a store-inn, 1797-1801; day book for cash, and ledger of Sheriff Hartwell Tucker, who entrusted the expenditure of the sheriff's monies to John, Leroy, and Sterling Tucker, 1801-1807; day book for store of Sterling Tucker, 1810; ledger of farm accounts of Hartwell Tucker, 1814-1826, including records of Gideon Perkins, Charles Clay, and Bennett Thomas, overseers, 1821-1826, and accounts for the settlement of the estate of John Tucker, 1843; and farm account book of John Tucker, 1833-1835. TYLER, JOHN (1790-1862). 1842 Feb. 19. 1 item. Gift of David Rankin Barbee. No. 3402. Letter to political friends in Philadelphia on his general intentions as the new President. Typed copy. UNITED STATES, ELECTIONS. 1824. 1 item. Gift. No. 3403. Tally of electoral votes in the 1824 presidential campaign between John Quincy Adams and William Harris Crawford. UNITED STATES NAVY. 1886-1887. 1 volume. Gift of Mrs. Richard Fell. No. 3486. Captain's order book for a cruise of the U.S.S. Juniata to the South Atlantic and the Pacific, the orders signed principally by W. T. Burwell; but also by N. H. Barnes and G. T. Davis. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. 1819-1950. Archives and unofficial records. Official records of the University, transferred at intervals to the Archives from the non-current files of schools, departments, committees, administrative offices, and other agencies of the University, are entered in this, as in previous reports, under the name of the agency of origin. Users of these records should consult Philip Alexander Bruce's five-volume centennial history of the University, Thomas Perkins Abernethy's Historical Sketch of the University, the annual general catalogues, and W. Edwin Hemphill's Bibliography of the Unprinted Official Records of the University of Virginia, published as an appendix to the sixth annual report. A card index to the Alumni Bulletin and Alumni News is maintained in the office of the Division. It should be noted that in the nineteenth century the Chairman of the Faculty and the Proctor performed duties now borne by the President, the Bursar, the Registrar, the chairmen of schools, and the deans of departments. Thus the older matriculation records appear under Faculty. Some of the oldest official records appear in the papers of individuals. The Jefferson, Cabell, and Cocke papers are cases in point. Material relating to the University is also to be found in the papers of Madison, Monroe, and others. Most of the first volume of the minutes of the Board of Visitors is recorded in the hand of the first Rector, Thomas Jefferson, with the minutes of individual meetings carrying the signatures of other members present, including President Monroe and ex-President Madison. Modern official and semiofficial papers relating to the University will be found listed in this and other recent reports not only under the name of the University activity concerned, but in a number of cases under the name of a teacher or administrative official whose papers have been placed in the library. Under a recent directive of the Governor of Virginia, machinery has been set up for a state-wide program of records administration under the supervision of the State Records Administrator at the State Capitol. The program aims to achieve greater efficiency and economy in records keeping and records equipment in the State departments and agencies; to provide for regularly scheduled review of current records; and for proper selection of non-current records for preservation in archives, and prompt destruction of useless records. Following a preliminary survey, the program has been inaugurated at the University, with helpful assistance from Mr. Lloyd Myer, State Records Administrator, who reviews our records-retirement procedures, and clears specific retirement proposals with the State Archivist and the State Auditor. Copies of individual and annual reports made to the State Records Administrator are on file in the office of the Division. Most unofficial and semi-official records are separately entered in these reports under the names of the individual societies, fraternities, clubs, religious groups, publications, and other organizations of students and faculties. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA, ALUMNI. 1947-1948. 40 items. Archival transfer. No. 3500. Literature sent to the Dean of the Graduate School, describing the aims and workings of the Development Fund, headed by Fleet Admiral William F. Halsey. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA, BOARD OF VISITORS. 18171949. 103 items and 1 vol. Archival transfers and gifts of Barron Foster Black, Charles Henderson, and Mrs. Ivey F. Lewis. Nos. 171, 3263, 3336, and 3430. Resolution of the "Board of Visitors and Governors" of Central College, 1817, signed by Jefferson, Madison, Monroe, and Gen. John Hartwell Cocke, with an early University class schedule in Jefferson's hand (photostats); volume kept from 1846 to 1872 in which are entered (for use by the Chairman of the Faculty) Resolutions of the Rector and Visitors of the University; additional minutes of sixteen meetings of the Board in 1938-1939 and 1945-1947, with special reports and correspondence; manuscript of Convocation address by Barron F. Black, Rector, 22 September 1949. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA, BUILDINGS. 1822 and 1896. 4 items and 1 vol. Gift of Charles Henderson and exchange. Nos. 3263 and 3313. Ground plan of the University of Virginia as designed by Thomas Jefferson, probably the model for Peter Maverick's engraving of 1822 (photostats from Virginia State Library); volume recording subscriptions to the fund for restoring the Rotunda (library) following its destruction in the fire of 27 October 1895, with typescript specifications of the architect, Stanford White, for the restoration work, 20 April 1896. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA, BURSAR. 1939-1945. 2,500 items. Archival transfer. No. 3275. Bursar's general correspondence, 1939-1945, A-K. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA, CLUBS, SOCIETIES, AND OTHER ORGANIZATIONS. 1848-1950. 2,080 items and 11 vols. Gifts and deposits as listed below. Bibliographical Society. 1946-1949. 430 items of correspondence and other records of the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia and its various activities, including its annually published volume, Studies in Bibliography, during the first three years of its existence. Deposit. No. 3388. Class of 1950. "History of the Class of 1950," by Benjamin L. Carleton, class historian. Typescript copy presented by Mr. Carleton. No. 3488. Magazine. 1924-1925. Five issues of the University of Virginia Magazine, October 1924-February 1925, containing articles and stories by Erskine Caldwell, Henry Taylor, and G. P. Wertenbaker, prepared originally as exercises in writing for Professor Atcheson L. Hench's courses in "English Literature C-2" and "English B-3." Gift of Mr. Hench, with explanatory notes. No. 3256. Phi Beta Kappa, Beta Chapter of Virginia. 1907-1947. A volume of minutes and 1,600 items of correspondence, by-laws, and other records of the chapter. Deposit. No. 514. Phi Delta Phi "Libel." 1949-1950. Scripts and other material of the legal comedy, written and staged annually during "Easters Week" by the law fraternity to dramatize the foibles and follies of the Department of Law, its faculty, students, and professions. Deposit and gift of Atcheson L. Hench. Nos. 3457 and 3464. Philomathean Society. 1848-1850. Minute book of the Society. Gift of Mrs. Cammann C. Duke. No. 3305. Players Club. 1916-1926. 200 items of correspondence, programs, business accounts, and other records of the University's dramatic society, forerunner of the mid-century's Virginia Players and Rotunda Stagers. Gift of Mrs. Samuel A. Mitchell. No. 3349. Sigma Alpha Epsilon. 1945. Correspondence of the faculty advisor, Professor Atcheson L. Hench, regarding problems of the postwar reactivation of the chapter. Gift of Mr. Hench. No. 3304. Sigma Xi. 1924-1947. Card-file list of the 700 members of the University's chapter of this honorary scientific fraternity. Deposit. No. 2856. Straight Democratic Ticket Club. 1948. Correspondence, membership list, a final report on the club's activities, and clippings of this, the first group in Virginia to organize in support of Harry S. Truman's presidential candidacy, affiliated with the national TrumanBarkley Clubs. Gift of Thomas Daniel Shumate. No. 3306. Student Police. 1938-1943. 9 volumes of records of this organization. Archival transfer from the office of the Dean of the College. No. 3299. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA, FACULTY. 1843-1949. 6,350 items. Archival transfers and gifts of James C. Bardin, Mrs. Cammann C. Duke, Charles Henderson, C. Venable Minor, William H. Parker, the late U. J. Peters Rushton, William S. Weedon, and Mrs. George F. White. Administrative Council. 1923-1940. 225 items of correspondence and other papers relating to undergraduate affairs, records of the Administrative Council under Dean James Morris Page, 1923-1932, and Dean Ivey Foreman Lewis, 1933-1934 and 1940. No. 3284. College of Arts and Sciences. 1929-1944. 6,000 items of correspondence of Ivey F. Lewis as Dean of the University, 1929-1942, and records covering student withdrawals from all departments of the University, 1929-1934, and from the College, 1934-1944. No. 3299. College, Certificates and Attendance Reports. 1843-1905. Certificates awarded to Carthon Archer, 1843, and to James Cook Bardin, 1904-1905, for the completion of various courses; report to the parents of George William Keesee of his sundry absences from class during May 1852. Nos. 3363, 3425, and 3450. College Curriculum. 1943-1944. Records of the Committee on the Post-War College, organized to study the curriculum and organization of the College, and to recommend changes; minutes of meetings, reports of sub-committees (e.g., Committee on Orientation and Education of the Post-War Veteran), and statements submitted by members of the teaching and administrative staffs. No. 3500. Experimental Farm. 1874. "Third Annual Report of the University of Virginia Experimental Farm," lithographed chart signed by J. Wearmouth, Farm Manager, and by John Randolph Page, Director, and Professor of Natural History and Agriculture. No. 3305. Honors Courses. Program for the Bachelor of Arts degree with honors in philosophy, prepared by the faculty of the University's Corcoran School of Philosophy. No. 3500. Matriculation Records. 1897-1901. Index to the University's Matriculation Books for the four sessions of 1897-1901, compiled by William Mynn Thornton. No. 3263. Public Occasions Committee. 1948-1949. Letters from W. H. Auden, James B. Conant, Sir Oliver Franks, Francis P. Gaines, Peter L. Ireton, Philip C. Jessup, Fiske Kimball, Ernest O. Lawrence, George M. Modlin, Igor Stravinsky, Charles P. Taft, Carl Van Doren, and others invited to speak at various public celebrations at the University. No. 3338. Research Committee. 1938. A survey prepared by the secretary of the committee, Professor A. G. A. Balz of the School of Philosophy, of the publication needs of the University, particularly the publication of research undertaken by students and faculty, and of student theses and dissertations, with a digest of information received from other universities in response to questionnaires submitted. No. 3500. University Cemetery Committee. 1906-1913. Reports on the care of the cemetery by Professor Francis P. Dunnington, 1907-1913; printed reports, 1906-1908, by Mrs. Raleigh C. Minor, treasurer of the Society for the Continual Care of the Cemetery; constitution of the Society signed by President Edwin A. Alderman, 18 June 1907. No. 3451. University Senate. 1925-1927. Typescript copy of the report of the committee on the formation of a University Senate to perform the functions formerly exercised by the General Faculty, 7 December 1925; copy of an amendment to the constitution of the Senate, increasing membership from 19 (9 ex officio and 10 elective) to 21, by adding the Assistant Dean of the College and an additional representative from the College and Graduate departments. No. 2544. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA, GRADUATE DEPARTMENT. 1937-1948. 1,500 items. Archival transfer. No. 2613. General correspondence of the Dean of the Department of Graduate Studies, and other papers of Dean James Southall Wilson, Chairman of the Schools of English. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA, INSTITUTE FOR RESEARCH IN THE SOCIAL SCIENCES. 1931-1932. 2 items. Gift of Richmond Area University Center. No. 3467. Typescript of reports on the Institute's work by Wilson Gee, Director the first sent to Dr. Edmund Day of the Rockefeller Foundation and the second to J. L. Newcomb, acting president of the University. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA, NEWS SERVICE. 1925-1944. 2,130 items. Gift of William H. Wranek. No. 3380. Correspondence, press releases, radio scripts, pictures and clippings relating to articles for the Alumni News and concerning the Alderman Alumni Fund, athletics, University events and buildings, faculty activities and speeches, and the student body (collected by the staff of the University News Service). UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA, PERSONNEL AND PLACEMENT OFFICE. 1933-1948. 12,000 items. Archival transfer. No. 3398. Records and correspondence for student part-time jobs and loans, particularly for NYA, FERA and CCC work; the applications files contain much biographical data on former students. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA, PRESIDENT'S OFFICE. 19301947. 40,000 items. Archival transfer. No. 3345. Correspondence and other papers of John Lloyd Newcomb, former Professor and Dean of Engineering, as Assistant to the President, 1930-1931; as Acting President, 1931-1933, and as second President of the University of Virginia, 1933-1947. Supplements files reported in the previous annual report. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA, SUMMER SESSION. 1949. 1 item. No. 3295. Manuscript of Summer Session Finals address to graduates, 20 August 1944, by Gilbert Norman Ward, Professor of Applied Mathematics at the University of Manchester, England, and visiting professor in the University's Department of Engineering. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA, STUDENT ALBUMS AND NOTEBOOKS. 1828-1872. 14 vols. Coles Collection, deposits, and gifts of C. R. Irving, Morgan B. Raiford, Mrs. Woodford Spears, W. B. Stephens, George C. Walker, and John Bell Williams. Nos. 3255, 3265, 3330, 3341, 3368, 3409, 3431, 3481, and 3487. John A. Greeter's certificate for completion of mathematics course, 18 July 1828; William D. Christian's notebook on Robley Dunglison's medical lectures, 1830-1831; Edward G. Higginbotham's notebook on Gessner Harrison's lectures on Roman history, 1841-1842; Thomas J. Rice's autograph album, 1851-1853; Robert Waterman Hunter's notebooks on courses in chemistry, French, Italian, history, and Latin, 1854-1856; James Fenton Bryant's autograph album, 1860 and 1866; notebook of Benjamin Taylor Perkins and David Greenbaum on John B. Minor's law lectures, 1866-1867, and Samuel Walker Williams' notebook on Minor's lectures, 1868-1869; notebooks on courses in natural philosophy and mathematics taught by Francis H. Smith and Charles S. Venable, 1870-1872, kept by James Cabell Brockenbrough. VIRGINIA. 1791-1884. 7 items. Coles Collection. No. 3421. A miscellaneous group of papers and legal documents of Virginia interest, including: letter of John Page, Lieutenant Governor of Virginia, 1776-1779, colonel in the American Revolution, member of U. S. Congress, 1789-1797, and Governor of Virginia, 1802-1805, 25 August 1791, concerning poetry, with a poem of his own attached; indenture of Robert Ould (1820-1881), Assistant Secretary of War, C. S. A., and lawyer, and Sarah A. (Turpin) Ould, Hugh Caperton, Richard and Martha B. L. Jeffries, 8 October 1850 and witnessed by Gen. William Worth Belknap (1829-1890), Brigadier General, and Secretary of War, 1869-1876, under Grant; letter of James Lyon to Gen. Francis Henney Smith, 31 March 1874, concerning debts; deposition by Samuel M. Bowman in the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia in suit of Mary A. Neilson, witnessed by William B. Hill, Commissioner for Virginia in Maryland, at Baltimore, 21 April 1877; two letters of Edward Callohill Burks (1821-1897), member of House of Delegates, 1861-1863, and of Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals, to Judge E. H. Fitzhugh, 8 January and 14 March 1884, discussing the Married Woman's Act of 1877; and autograph of John Herbert Claiborne, of Petersburg, Confederate Surgeon-in-Chief. VIRGINIA, BOARD OF IMMIGRATION. 1866. 3 items. Coles Collection. No. 3362. Proclamation inviting people of Scotland, England and Wales to emigrate to Virginia, describing in detail conditions of life in Virginia, prepared by John Tyler, Jr. Letter of John Tyler, Jr. to James Black, 18 May 1866 and of John Howard, agent for Tyler, to James Black 21 May 1866. VIRGINIA FAMILIES. 1 item. Deposit. No. 3426. Genealogical notes on the Beck, Carr, Fitch, and Thurman families. VIRGINIA, HIGHER EDUCATION. 1923. 5 items. Gift of Richmond Area University Center. No. 3467. Report on Virginia's expenditures for higher education in comparison to financial support given in other Southern states, prepared for the Alumni Association of the University of Virginia by McLane Tilton and Lloyd Morey, and sent to Douglas Southall Freeman, editor of the Richmond News-Leader. VIRGINIA, LOCAL GOVERNMENT. 1934. 1 item. Gift of Bureau of Public Administration. No. 3141. Additional manuscript material concerning local government in the city of Norfolk. Typescript, "The Replanning of Certain Areas of Norfolk, Virginia" by David F. Stoddard. VIRGINIA NEGROES, HISTORICAL RECORDS SURVEY. 1937. 6 items. Gift of Archibald Anderson Hill. No. 3462. Interviews with Mrs. Nancy Williams of Norfolk by Wilson &amp; Anderson and Mrs. Fannie Berry, Rev. and Mrs. John Brown, Dr. Carter and Rev. Massey, of Petersburg, by Miss Susie Byrd—six exslaves. Letter from Roscoe E. Lewis, Hampton Institute, 6 December 1937, to Professor Hill explaining these interviews and their part in the history of the Negro in Virginia. VIRGINIA SECESSION ORDINANCE. 1861 Apr. 17. 1 DS. (facsimile). Gift of Mrs. Charles Thurman and Miss Rosalie Thornton. No. 3292. Facsimile of this famous document. WALKER, THOMAS LINDSAY (1818-1892). 1892. 8 items. Gift of Edwin Watts Saunders. No. 3414. Obituary notices from the Lynchburg News and the Daily Virginian on the death of Dr. Walker. WARREN COUNTY, VIRGINIA. 1857-1865. 2 volumes. Deposit. No. 3407. Journals of W. E. Eumers, carpenter, of Front Royal, 1857-1861, and of [Lewis A. Smith], 1857-1865. WASHINGTON COLLEGE. 1845-1866. 1 vol. Deposit. No. 3448. Registrar's account book for sessions of 1845-1846 to 1865-1866. WATTS, EBENEZER. 1825. 1 vol. Deposit. No. 3330. Scrapbook of newspaper clippings of this, the first Charlottesville bookbinder. WAYLAND, JOHN WALTER. 1931-1950. 750 items. Gift of Mr. Wayland. No. 2386. Correspondence on genealogy and local history of Rockingham County, and the Shenandoah Valley, with references to his book, Historic Harrisonburg, and earlier publications. WIRT, WILLIAM (1772-1834). 1807 Jan. 1. Deposit. No. 3390. "Memoirs of Patrick Henry. In a series of Letters to a Young Gentleman at William &amp; Mary College; Williamsburg. Letter I." St. George Tucker persuaded Wirt to abandon his epistolary form for his biography of Henry. WORLD WAR II. 1939-1945. 1943-1945. 2 items. Gift of William Edwin Hemphill. No. 3300. Flight log book of William Richard Marvin, Aviation Radioman Third Class, Bombing Squadron 8, July 1943-August 1945 (on microfilm), including flights made on combat duty in the Pacific from U. S. S. Bunker Hill March-October 1944; an eight page manuscript diary of his missions against the Japanese, March 1944October 1944, of which the library also has a typescript copy. WORLD WAR II, ORDNANCE COLLECTION. 1943-1945. 1 vol. Deposit (restricted). No. 2931. Loose leaf volume of "Miscellaneous Information" concerning bomb disposal, an addition to the collection described in the eighteenth-nineteenth annual report. YALDEN-THOMSON, DAVID. 1949-1950. 1 vol. and microfilm. Deposit (restricted). No. 3479. Manuscript of Mr. Yalden-Thomson's "Calendar of Eighteenth Century Papers in the Possession of Sir Mark Dalrymple, Bart., at Newhailes, Musselburgh, Midlothian, Scotland," with a microfilm copy (8 reels) of the manuscripts listed in this preliminary calendar. The manuscripts described are a portion of the Newhailes manuscripts, chiefly the papers of Sir David Dalrymple, Lord Hailes (1726-1792), noted jurist, author of the Annals of Scotland, of an eulogy of Hume, a rebuke to Gibbon, and other works, and a defender of Christianity in a period of skepticism. Correspondents include James Boswell, Edmund Burke, James Cook, William Cooke, John Erskine, John Gillies, David Hume, Richard Hurd, John Ogilvie, John Pringle, William Robertson, Adam Smith, Horace Walpole, and many other men of letters, theologians, and scientists. YOUNG, JOHN BROOKE. 1935. 3 items. Gift of A. Churchill Young. No. 3465. Notes on Young as a student at the University of Virginia, where he received a law degree in 1834, based primarily on two contemporary articles in the Richmond Enquirer.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">FRIENDS OF THE LIBRARY 1950-1951 Anonymous donors and depositors, as well as institutions and organizations, are not included in this list of those who have given generous assistance to the Historical Collections during the year covered by this report; nor does the list include the names of donors to the printed collections of the library. Thomas Perkins Abernethy Mrs. Edwin A. Alderman G. M. Alexander M. Carl Andrews Thomas W. Atkinson Mrs. Anne Atkinson-Chamberlayne Mrs. Charles Baird Albert G. A. Balz David Rankin Barbee Mr. and Mrs James C. Bardin W. C. Barnes C. Waller Barrett Eliot Bartlett Mrs. Jesse Beams Samuel M. Bemiss Estate of Abraham Berglund F. S. Beverly Barron F. Black James Baylor Blackford Sam C. Blackwell Mrs. Thomas E. Blackwell Howard B. Bloomer, Jr. Fredson T. Bowers Mrs. J. Callan Brooks Walter Coles Bruce D. Tennant Bryan Miss Anne Page Brydon George N. Buck J. D. Buky, Sr. Alfred Burger Miss Isabella N. Burnet Ollen Lawrence Burnette J. C. Bushong Lyman H. Butterfield Hartwell Cabell John Canaday Lester J. Cappon B. L. Carleton, Jr. W. L. Carne C. J. Carrier Mrs. J. P. Carroll Mr. and Mrs. Randolph Catlin Irby C. Cauthen Bernard P. Chamberlain Herbert B. Chermside Frank Christian W. G. Christian G. C. Clanton James E. Cleveland Miss Betty Cocke Cary H. Cocke Monroe F. Cockrell W. C. Coleburn Mrs. George J. Collins William M. Connor, Jr. R. T. Corbell Mrs. Celeste Costas Mrs. M. J. Cox Gilmer Craddock John Harvie Creecy Miss Mary V. Crenshaw J. E. Currell Mrs. Thomas H. Daniel Charles K. Davenport Alexander Davidson D. N. Davidson J. L. Davidson C. Carroll Davis John Staige Davis, Jr. R. S. Davis Collins Denny, Jr. W. A. Dryden Mr. and Mrs. Cammann C. Duke Francis Duke R. J. Dunnington R. J. Edwards Rowland A. Egger Joseph D. Eggleston John and Antoinette Eisenhard John C. Emmerson, Jr. Mrs. Richard Fell John C. Fix Mr. and Mrs. Richard Fletcher Mrs. John Flynn J. N. Fray William Friedman Miss Mary L. Garland Harry George Mrs. J. T. Gilliam Miss Sara K. Gilliam B. F. Ginther Carter Glass, Jr. Robert Glass Robert Kent Gooch Miss Ellen Goss Mrs. W. L. Grant James W. Green Mrs. Lucille D. Green Carmon C. Greer George W. Grider Mrs. Richard Gwathmey H. Garth Hamilton Lewis M. Hammond Mrs. Harris Hancock The late Lathrop Harper W. P. Harris Francis Burton Harrison W. M. Harrison James Hart Joseph M. Hartfield Miss Olivia Hazelton W. Edwin Hemphill Atcheson L. Hench Charles Henderson John W. Herndon Archibald A. Hill Mrs. Charlton Hinman Lawrence Gouverneur Hoes Mrs. Lewis Littlepage Holladay Mrs. John M. Hopkins Llewellyn G. Hoxton Thomas P. Hughes Harold Hugo Cecil A. Hutchinson Christian S. Hutter, Jr. C. R. Irving E. B. Jackson Stuart W. Jackson Werner L. Janney John M. Jennings Jay W. Johns Miss Mildred Johnson Maben Jones Charles H. Kauffmann The late Jefferson Randolph Kean John Kelly William A. Kepner Mrs. D. H. Keys Mrs. Fiske Kimball Elbert A. Kincaid Lewis P. Kinsey E. L. Knowles Miss Helena C. Koiner Miss Roy Land Mr. and Mrs. Charles R. Langhorne J. H. Latchum E. W. Lauck Edwin P. Lehman Ivey F. Lewis Frank C. Littleton Henry T. Louthan Robert W. Lull Vernon S. McCasland Leander McCormick-Goodhart Mr. and Mrs. C. Purcell McCue John P. McGuire, Jr. Alexander Mackay-Smith Mrs. G. T. Mackenzie Mrs. John W. MacLeod Mrs. E. H. McPherson John E. Manahan, Jr. Linton Massey Bernard Mayo Miss Ada Meek Paul Mellon Mrs. Joseph Mills C. Venable Minor Mrs. Samuel A. Mitchell John Lambert Molyneaux Mr. and Mrs. Maurice Moore W. Y. Morgan Howard S. Mott Benjamin Muse Barrows Mussey Wilbur A. Nelson Mr. and Mrs. H. D. Newcomb John L. Newcomb Willoughby Newton John Nicolson William Lindsay Norford Dan S. Norton Misses Constance and Charlotte Nourse William B. O'Neal L. T. Page William H. Parker Harcourt Parrish Douglas Parsonage Mr. and Mrs. M. F. Partridge M. W. Paxton Arthur K. Peck Mrs. L. L. Phillips H. B. Phipps John F. Pinner Mr. and Mrs. Harry Rogers Pratt Alfred D. Preston Miss Nelly C. Preston A. S. Rachal William M. E. Rachal Mrs. James T. Rahily Morgan B. Raiford M. L. Richardson C. H. Rieley A. Robbins, Jr. E. Graham Roberts Joseph K. Roberts Miss Barbara Rosser Mrs. Thomas L. Rosser David Rothman B. F. D. Runk The late U. J. Peters Rushton William J. Rushton Mr. and Mrs. Edward W. Saunders Mr. and Mrs. Vincent Shea Willis Shell Mrs. Francis Eppes Shine T. Daniel Shumate, Jr. Josephus Simpson R. Smith Simpson Forrest B. Smith Glenn Curtis Smith Mrs Woodford Spears Louis Spilman Mrs. John Sproul William Force Stead James S. Steck W. B. Stephens The late Edward R. Stettinius, Jr. Thomas W. Streeter Anne G. Strother Mrs. Mabel Talley Mr. and Mrs. Henry M. Taylor Miss Jamie Terrill Gerard Tetley J. H. Thornton Miss Rosalie Thornton Mrs. Charles Thurman Franklin H. Titlow, Jr. Carl R. Tomlinson Roland Tree Ronald Tree Annie W. Trott D. D. Tucker, Jr. Robert S. Tunstall Stephen D. Tuttle Coolie Verner Paul B. Victorius George C. Walker Mrs. Edward Waller, Jr. Mrs. T. R. Waring Mrs. E. Alban Watson Miss Texie P. Watts John W. Wayland Robert H. Webb Lord Webb-Johnson William S. Weedon Mrs. E. Hambleton Welbourn Mrs. George F. White Orland E. White John Bell Williams Leigh D. Williams Philip Williams Mrs. Ernest R. Wilson James Southall Wilson R. A. Wilson Miss M. M. Withrow Edwin Wolf Charles K. Woltz H. B. Wood William H. Wranek, Jr. David McCord Wright Richard M. Wright E. A. Wyatt Mrs. John Cook Wyllie David C. Yalden-Thomson A. Churchill Young George B. Zehmer</field>
      <field name="fulltext">VIRGINIA NEWSPAPERS As a part of the cooperative program for the preservation of Virginia newspapers, the publishers and editors of these fifty-five newspapers have furnished subscriptions free of charge to the University Library for cataloguing and preservation, 1949-1950. See also the section on Newspapers in this report. Alexandria. Northern Virginia Shopper's Journal Altavista. Altavista Journal Arlington. The Sun Ashland. Herald-Progress Bedford. Bedford Bulletin Bedford. Bedford Democrat Blacksburg. Virginia Tech Blackstone-Crewe. Courier-Record Bowling Green. Caroline Progress Brookneal. Union Star Buchanan. Buchanan News Buena Vista. Buena Vista News Christiansburg. Montgomery News-Messenger Clintwood. Dickenson County Herald Crewe. Crewe Chronicle Culpeper. Culpeper Exponent Danville. Danville Bee Drakes Branch. Charlotte Gazette Fairfax. Fairfax Herald Fincastle. Fincastle Herald Franklin. The Tidewater News Front Royal. Warren Sentinel Gloucester. Gloucester Gazette-Journal Harrisonburg. Daily News-Record Hopewell. The Blender Hopewell. Hopewell News Kilmarnock. Rappahannock Record Leesburg. Loudoun Times-Mirror Lexington. Rockbridge County News Luray. Page News and Courier Lynchburg. Daily Advance Manassas. Manassas Messenger Martinsville. Martinsville Daily Bulletin Monterey. Highland Recorder New Market. Shenandoah Valley Newport News. Times-Herald Orange. Orange Review Pennington Gap. Powell Valley News Petersburg. Progress Index Petersburg. Rural Virginia Purcellville. Blue Ridge Herald Richmond. Richmond Afro-American Richmond. Virginia Farm Bureau News Roanoke. Roanoke World News Salem. Times-Register South Boston. South Boston News Stanardsville, Greene County Record Staunton. Evening Leader Tappahannock. Rappahannock Times Urbanna. Southside Sentinel Warrenton. Fauquier Democrat Warsaw. Northern Neck News Washington. Rappahannock News Waverly. Sussex Surry Dispatch Waynesboro. Waynesboro News-Virginian</field>
   </doc>
</add>