<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university of virginia</field>
      <field name="author_text">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1900's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2005_Q2_1/uvaBook/tei/z000000193.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240341</field>
      <field name="date_text">April, 1908</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:107007</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The University of Virginia record. Volume I, No. 8, April, 1908</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">University of Virginia -- Periodicals</field>
      <field name="subject_text">University of Virginia -- Periodicals</field>
      <field name="title_display">The University of Virginia record.  Volume I, No. 8, April, 1908</field>
      <field name="title_facet">university of virginia record</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">university of virginia record</field>
      <field name="title_text">The University of Virginia record.  Volume I, No. 8, April, 1908</field>
      <field name="year_display">April, 1908</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1908-04</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1908</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:107007&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:107007&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;serial volume&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;university of virginia&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The University of Virginia record. Volume I, No. 8, April, 1908&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;university of virginia record&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;April, 1908&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1908-04&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The University of Virginia record&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="volume"&gt;Volume I&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="issue"&gt;No. 8&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;April, 1908&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Va.&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="LC call number"&gt;LD5667 .A43&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa call number"&gt;LD5667.2&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;X000896178&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;o07560180&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;42 p. ; 23 cm.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;University of Virginia -- Periodicals&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The University of Virginia Record&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="volume"&gt;1&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="issue"&gt;8&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1908-04&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2005&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2005 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 168 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SUMMER SCHOOL OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA OFFICERS OF THE SUMMER SCHOOL Administrative Board. EDWIN ANDERSON ALDERMAN, D. C. L., LL. D., President of the University. BRUCE RYBURN PAYNE, M. A., Ph. D., Professor of Psychology and Secondary Education. Director of the Summer School. CHARLES WILLIAM KENT, M. A., Ph. D., LL. D., Professor of English Literature. WILLIAM HOLDING ECHOLS, B. S., C. E., Professor of Mathematics. THOMAS FITZHUGH, M. A., Professor of Latin. THOMAS WALKER PAGE, M. A., Ph. D., LL. D., Professor of Economics. CHARLES G. MAPHIS, Registrar. FACULTY LULA ANDREWS, Elementary English. (Instructor in English State Normal School, Farmville). D. R. AUGSBURG, Drawing. (Director Drawing Public Schools, Oakland, California). JOHN BLAIR, Drawing. (Superintendent Schools, Wilmington, N. C.) J. A. ANDERSON, Ph. D., Physics. (Instructor in Physics, Johns Hopkins University). ROBERT MONTGOMERY BIRD, B. A., B. S., Ph. D., Chemistry. (Professor of Chemistry, University of Virginia). EDITH G. CHARLTON, Domestic Science. (In charge of Domestic Science Extension Department, Iowa State Agricultural College). HARRY CLO, M. S., Physics. (Instructor in Physics, University of Virginia). E. COLEMAN, Reading. (Teacher in Roanoke City Schools). RICHARD CRAWFORD, M. A., Manual Training. (Professor of Manual Training and Mechanical arts, William and Mary College). K. C. DAVIS, Ph. D., Agriculture and Nature Study. (Dean of New York State School of Agriculture). WILLIAM M. DEY, M. A., Ph. D., French. (Assistant Professor of Romanic Languages, University of Missouri). WILLIAM HOLDING ECHOLS, B. S., C. E., Mathematics. (Professor of Mathematics, University of Virginia). CLARA EMENS, Writing. (Formerly Principal of Commercial Department, Lockport High School). WILLIAM HARRISON FAULKNER, Ph. D., German. (Adjunct Professor of German, University of Virginia). THOMAS FITZHUGH, M. A., Latin. (Professor of Latin, University of Virginia). E. C. GLASS, (Superintendent Lynchburg Public Schools and Conductor of School of Methods). Education. VIRGINIA GREEN, Drawing. MARGARET WINIFRED HALIBURTON, Primary School Work. (Instructor in Primary Methods and Supervisor of Primary Grades, State Female Normal School, Farmville, Virginia). CORNELIUS J. HEATWOLE, B. A., Education. (Formerly Superintendent School, Morristown, Tenn. Graduate Teachers College, Columbia University). JOHN B. HENNEMAN, M. A., Ph. D., English. (Professor of English, and Dean of the University of the South). MARI RUEF HOFER, School Music. (Instructor in School Music and Games at Teachers' College; Columbia University Extension Lecturer). WILLIS A. JENKINS, A. B., Mathematics. (State School Examiner, Second Circuit, Virginia). WILLIAM A. KEPNER, M. A., Biology. (Instructor in Biology, University of Virginia). CHARLES WILLIAM KENT, M. A., Ph. D., LL. D., English. (Professor of English Literature, University of Virginia). MARGARET KING, Nature Study and School Gardens. (Supervisor School Garden at Jamestown Exposition). WILLIAM ALEXANDER LAMBETH, Ph. D., M. D., Botany. (Professor of Hygiene, Materia Medica, University of Virginia). ALBERT LEFEVRE, Ph. D., LL. D., Logic and Philosophy. (Professor of Philosophy, University of Virginia). CHARLES G. MAPHIS, Physiology and Hygiene. (State School Examiner of Fifth Circuit, Virginia). EDWIN MIMS, A. M., Ph. D., English. (Professor of English Literature, Trinity College, N. C., and Editor of South Atlantic Quarterly). F. A. MILLEDGE, M. A., Ph. D., Geography. (Professor of Science, State Normal, Farmville, Virginia). S. C. MITCHELL, Ph. D., LL. D., History. (Professor of History, Richmond College). WALTER ALEXANDER MONTGOMERY, Ph. D., Latin and Greek. (Professor of Latin, William and Mary College, Virginia). MRS. M. S. MOFFETT, Teachers' Training Class. (Supervising Principal of Schools, Manassas, Virginia). THOMAS WALKER PAGE, Ph. D., LL. D., History and Civil Government. (Professor of Economics, University of Virginia). JAMES MORRIS PAGE, M. A., Ph. D., Mathematics. (Professor of Mathematics and Dean of the University of Virginia). BRUCE RYBURN PAYNE, M. A., Ph. D., Education. (Professor of Psychology and Secondary Education, University of Virginia). HERBERT M. PECK, Ph. B., Physical Training. (Instructor in Physical Culture, University of Virginia). WILLIAM CARL RUEDIGER, Ph. D., Psychology and Education. (Assistant Professor of Educational Psychology, George Washington University). C. ALPHONSO SMITH, Ph. D. LL. D., English. (Professor of the English Language and Dean of Graduate School, University of North Carolina). T. DWIGHT SLOAN, Chemistry. (Assistant in Chemistry, University of Virginia). MARGARET STARKE, School Music. (Graduate Teacher College). ALBERT HENRY TUTTLE, M. S., Biology. (Professor of Biology, University of Virginia). RICHARD THOMAS WYCHE, Story Telling. (Lecturer on Story Telling, and President of Story Tellers' League). GENERAL STATEMENT. The University of Virginia Summer School is conducted primarily for teachers and students in high schools, academies and colleges. It takes as its peculiar province, not the ordinary summer institute, nor the more popular and inspirational summer school, but the solid and substantial training of high school teachers, college teachers, college students, and teachers who either have professional and life certificates or wish to procure them. Because the courses of instruction in high schools are not clearly defined but merge into the grammar grades below and into the lower college classes above, the high school offers itself as a strategic center around which to build up instruction, the emphasis of which is upon subject matter. The justification of such a summer school for high school teachers is the unusual activity in the South just now in behalf of secondary education. The large number of high school and college teachers attending the Summer School last year is an additional proof of the need of such a school. LOCATION.—Charlottesville, the seat of the University of Virginia, is in a picturesque and healthful situation among the foot-hills of the Blue Ridge Mountains. It is at the junction of two great lines of railway, the Chesapeake &amp; Ohio and the Southern, and is thus of easy access from every part of the country. The sanitary arrangements of the University are excellent. The climate is invigorating, healthful, and free from malarial conditions, the average elevation of the surrounding country being about six hundred and fifty feet above sea level; the water supply is pure, being drawn by gravity from a mountain reservoir six miles away; the system of drains and sewers is complete. One mile from the University is an excellent iron spring connected with the Jefferson Park Hotel, a much frequented resort. LABORATORIES AND MUSEUMS.—The equipment possessed by the University for the work of instruction, alike in Academic and in the Professional departments, has been much augmented in recent years, and is now excellent in quality, as well as extensive. In scientific studies large facilities are offered by the Rouss Physical Laboratory, the Chemical Laboratory and the Museum of Industrial Chemistry, the Lewis Brooks Museum, the Biological Laboratory. LIBRARY.—In addition to the departmental libraries the general university library is common to all departments. Originally selected and arranged by Mr. Jefferson, it has since been much enlarged by purchases and donations, and contains at present upwards of fifty thousand volumes. Students are allowed the use of the books under the usual restrictions, and the Librarian is present in the Library for eight hours daily to attend to their wants. REST AND STUDY ROOMS.—Madison Hall, the beautiful new building of the Young Men's Christian Association, which was recently erected at the cost of seventy-five thousand dollars, will be open to students of the Summer School from nine o'clock in the morning until ten at night. Students will have access to the current periodicals in the reading room during the day and until ten at night. The other rooms will be used for rest, for study, for recreation, and for social gatherings. North of the building there are fifteen tennis courts which will be equipped for the use of the students. DAILY GENERAL ASSEMBLY.—Daily from 11:45 to 12:15 there will be a period, in which the students may have the privilege of attending a gathering of the entire body. At this time there will be short addresses on some interesting topic, and a brief prayer and song service, under the leadership of some clergyman or member of the Faculty. Generally the singing will be choral, under the direction of the instructor of music, but occasionally, as opportunity offers, prominent soloists will be procured. SUNDAY VESPER SERVICES.—Experience has shown that no Sunday Chapel service held here during the summer has been more attractive or more appreciated than what has sometimes been called the Sunset Service. Further advantage of holding this service at this hour is, that it enables all the Faculty and the students of the summer school to unite in one common service without at all interfering with their attending the churches of their choice in the city. This service, which will always be kept within one hour, will begin at six-thirty. It will consist of congregational singing and a brief address by some prominent minister or layman. The pipe organ used in this service is the work of one of the best organ makers in the country, and is admirably adapted, both in size and tone, for church purposes. RECREATION.—Provision has been made to keep the Fayerweather Gymnasium open during the summer, under the control of a competent gymnasium director, who will give daily systematic instruction in physical culture. No fee will be charged for these courses nor for the use of the gymnasium, and it is hoped that every student will come prepared to take advantage of the physical training courses. A portion of each day set apart to systematic physical development will be profitably spent. The swimming pool and baths will be at the service of the students. The tennis courts belonging to Madison Hall will also be kept in readiness, duly marked and with nets in place. The splendid athletic field, one of the finest in the South, with base-ball grounds and quarter mile running track, will be at the disposal of those who wish to engage in the manly sports. Within three minutes walk from the Academic Building, the woods may be reached. These woods and the neighboring mountains furnish ample opportunity for pleasant strolls or for longer tramps on the part of those more vigorous. One of these walks leads to Frye's Spring, a most efficacious chalybeate spring, which may also be reached by street car. EXCURSIONS.—Under the directorship of Professor Maphis, there will be excursions to neighboring points of interest such as Monticello, the home of Thomas Jefferson; the Natural Bridge; Luray Cavern; the battlefields in Virginia; and any other points to which a sufficiently large number may care to go. The proximity to Washington and Richmond (three hours ride to each) should make a visit to either exceptionally interesting. Saturdays will be reserved for these excursions. ORGAN RECITALS AND ENTERTAINMENTS.—Elsewhere in this announcement mention has been made of the pipe organ in Cabell Hall. It is not out of place here to say that this organ, which has recently been installed, is one of the best products of one of the largest organ manufacturers in America. It is an antiphonal organ with fifteen hundred pipes, and exhibits all of the possibilities of organ manufacture. To bring out all these possibilities requires a master organist, and it is the purpose of the management of the summer school to procure distinguished organists for recitals. Seven such recitals have been arranged for the coming summer. Other evening entertainments will be announced during the session of the summer school. LECTURES.—Besides the addresses mentioned elsewhere there will be at least six others, one each week, by such speakers as President E. A. Alderman, Dr. Chas. W. Kent, of the University, Dr. S. C. Mitchell, of Richmond College, Dr. Edwin Mims of Trinity College, Dr. Alphonso Smith, of University of North Carolina, and others whose names will be announced after the opening of the Summer School. RURAL LIFE WEEK.—The week beginning July 13th and ending July 18th will be devoted especially to the problems of rural life in general, and rural school problems in particular. There will be addresses, stereopticon views, and demonstrations by various national experts, upon these subjects. Deputy State Superintendent E. C. Bishop of Nebraska, who has been favored with such phenomenal success in this work will be present the entire week. Other speakers will be Professor K. C. Davis, Dean of the College of Agriculture of the State of New York, who will teach agriculture for six weeks in the Summer School; Supt. O. J. Kern, County Superintendent of Winnebago County, Illinois, and author of "Among Country Schools;" Miss Edith Charlton, of the Iowa College of Agriculture, Dr. A. S. Knapp, of the U. S. Department of Agriculture, Mr. T. O. Sandy of Virginia, and several other workers, among them certain prominent teachers of Home Economics who will consider the life and work of women in our rural communities. This work should be especially interesting to county superintendents, progressive farmers, members of county school boards, rural school teachers, and officers of the citizens' improvement leagues of the State. It will be entirely free to the public. The following are some of the topics to be considered: Agricultural Education as related to community life; consolidation of rural schools; visitation of schools; how schools may help farmers; schools of agriculture and rural life (illustrated); farmers reading courses; reading circle work; patronizing social events—granges, fairs, shows, school as social center in winter; spelling schools; school gardens; arbor-day—what to plant, where, how, how to get it; beautifying homes, beautifying school grounds; how to keep boys and girls interested in farming; boys and girls clubs; the farm help problem; parcels post, rural mail, telephone; sanitation in our homes; sewage disposal on the farm; water supply on the farm; the farm shop for our boys; care of buildings, machinery, etc.; domestic science and manual training without funds or equipment; earth roads and the King drag; dedication of rural homes; permanence of rural estates—in Old World, value here, relation to fertility; co-operation among farmers; suggestions to Southern farmers; emergencies—what to do until the doctor comes. THE HIGH SCHOOL CONFERENCE.—On Friday and Saturday, June 26th and 27th, the Association of Colleges and Preparatory Schools of Virginia will hold its Summer Conference in the University buildings. At this meeting the chief topic will be the discussion of the typical state high school course. A Committee has been considering this topic for a year, and has met the Association and discussed it once already. This Committee will submit its final report at this meeting. All high school and college teachers are invited to this Conference. CREDIT.—Certificates will be granted in each course in the University Department to those students who attain a grade of 75%. This grade will be the average of the recitation and examination marks. No student will be allowed to take more than three courses without the permission of the Director. This regulation does not apply to the School of Methods. As a rule, students wishing University credit should not attempt more than two courses in one summer: they must receive in all cases permission to take more than three. In registering, students should state what credits they desire, as arrangements for credit must be made before taking the course. After each course in this catalogue is stated its credit value in case University credit is allowed for it. Any course outlined from page to page may be counted toward the Virginia Teachers Professional Certificate. No credit is allowed either toward this certificate or toward University courses, for work done in the School of Methods, except in certain special courses where permission has been granted by the Director and the Registrar; in all such cases additional work is assigned and an additional fee is charged. 1. Professional Certificate.—The following regulations with reference to credits towards the Professional Teaching Certificate in Virginia have been passed by the Board of Examiners: "Resolved, That those teachers holding first grade certificates, who attend the Summer School of the University of Virginia for two sessions of six weeks each, and who make an average of 75% on class work and examinations, in six courses, other than elementary school subjects, shall be entitled to the Professional Certificate which shall continue in vogue for seven years, subject to renewals from time to time." These six courses would necessitate the work of at least two sessions and must include at least four different subjects. 2. Credit Allowed by Other States than Virginia.—Application has been made to other Southern States for credit equal to that accorded by the Virginia Board of Examiners. Credits are now allowed toward the extension of the certificates by certain other States. In others the University Summer School instructors are appointed to hold State examinations. In some other States arrangements may be made upon application of the teachers from those States. All persons wishing to arrange for credits with their respective school authorities should correspond with the Director of the Summer School. 3. University of Virginia Credit.—Below are stated the conditions upon which credit in the University of Virginia may be granted for work done in the Summer School. (a) The student must satisfy the entrance examination requirements of the University of Virginia and matriculate before he can receive credit in the College for any work done in the University of Virginia Summer School. (b) The Dean of the College will accept the completion of the courses in the Summer School in lieu of the entrance examinations in the same subject, provided that in his judgment the courses are equivalent to those required for entrance to the University of Virginia, and provided, that the certificates of courses completed be approved by the University of Virginia professor concerned. (c) The Dean of the College and the professor in charge of the school in which credit is desired will accept certificates of completion of summer courses in lieu of "A" courses in the University of Virginia, provided that such summer courses be approved by the University of Virginia professor concerned as the full equivalent in character and scope of the corresponding "A" courses in the University. (d) Certificates of completion of certain summer courses approved by the Academic Faculty will be accepted in lieu of portions of "B" courses, provided that in each case the Dean of the College, the Faculty Committee on Degrees, and the professor in charge of the courses for which credit is desired certify in writing that the summer courses completed are equivalent in character and scope to that portion of the regular sessional work for which credit is desired. (e) The character of the examinations and the numerical standard (75%) required for their successful completion shall be the same as those of the sessional examinations. TEACHERS POSITIONS.—The University Appointment Committee receives more demands for teachers than it is ever able to fill. This Committee would be glad to have well qualified teachers who are in attendance upon the Summer School leave their applications with the Director, who is a member of the Committee. BOARD AND ROOMS.—Board and rooms may be had at prices ranging from $3.00 per week, where several stay in the same room, upwards, according to accommodations, the average being $4.00 per week. For a list of boarding houses see page 38. Many of these boarding-houses are situated on, or immediately adjoining the University grounds. A limited number of students may, upon application, procure rooms in the University buildings at a nominal rental to cover actual expenses of furniture and attendance. The handsome new dining hall on the University grounds is now nearing completion. If it can be finished before the opening of the Summer School and if a sufficiently large number apply by correspondence before June 1st, it will be opened for the benefit of the Summer School students. The cost of board in the dining hall will not exceed $4.00 per week. Applications should be made as early as possible. REDUCED RAILWAY RATES.—All students coming to the Summer School from points south and west of Virginia should apply several weeks in advance to their local agents for reduced rates. In case the agent has received no instructions for selling reduced rate tickets to Charlottesville, Virginia, the Director of the Summer School should be written promptly for information. The Southern Railway and the Chesapeake and information promptly. The Southern Railway and the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway have agreed to sell round-trip tickets to the University of Virginia Summer School at greatly reduced rates from all points on their lines south and west of the Virginia State line. These reduced rate tickets can be bought only on one of the following dates—June 16th, 18th, 22nd, 29th, July 6th and July 13th. In order that the tickets may be good for return on any date before Sept. 30th they must be deposited with Anderson Bros., Agents of the Southern Railway, at the University of Virginia, within two days after the arrival of the holder of the tickets and a fee of fifty cents paid for having them extended to the desired date for returning. It is expected that all other railways south of the Potomac and east of the Mississippi rivers will co-operate in these reduced rates. All persons intending to start from points along other railways than the Southern or Chesapeake and Ohio should write to the Director for information several weeks in advance. No return trip tickets at reduced rates will be sold within Virginia, as the straight ticket at the unusually low rate of two cents per mile now provided for by law over all Virginia Railways is as low as the usual reduced rates. It may be that other rates still lower will be available at this time. Local agents can usually give information upon this point. If not, the Director of the Summer School will supply the requisite information. REGISTRATION.—Thursday, June 18th, will be devoted to the registration of students. All students should register on this day: The Registrar's office on Thursday, June 18th, will be in the South East rooms of the Rotunda; thereafter, it will be in the entrance hall of Cabell Hall. The entire faculty of the Summer School will be in the adjoining room from 8.45 to 1.30 for counsel, on June 18th. Students should consult freely with members of the Faculty in case of difficulty in choosing courses. No certificate will be granted to students who fail to register before Wednesday, June 24th. The form of registration will be as follows: Each student upon application will receive from the Registrar, Professor Maphis, a card with space for name, and address, and for courses to be taken. This card should be filled out by the student, giving in full the catalogue number and title of each course desired. This card should be presented to the Registrar for purposes of filing. In exchange for it the student will receive a card for each course desired, each one signed by the Registrar. These cards should then be presented to the Bursar, Mr. Moran, together with the fee for each course. Mr. Moran will sign and return each of them to the student, who should present it to the professor of the course prescribed by the card. No student will be admitted to any course without the card of registration for that class, properly signed by the Registrar and the Bursar. A single registration card will admit to all the courses in the School of Methods. In the University School not more than three courses may be taken in any one summer, except by special permission of the Director. Each course requires a separate registration card. FEES.—No registration fee will be charged. The tuition fee will consist of $5.00 for each course taken, except in the School of Methods, where a fee of $5.00 admits the applicant to all courses. The Department of Public Instruction of Virginia has provided by donation that Virginia teachers shall be charged only $3.00 for the School of Methods. Further exception is made to the $5.00 fee in certain other courses where a special fee has been mentioned in connection with the outline in this catalogue. Before being enrolled in a class each student is required to register and to pay all fees. No reduction of fee will be allowed for late entrance or withdrawal. TIME AND PLACE OF RECITATIONS AND LECTURES.— On Thursday, June 18th, at 8 P. M. the Summer School will gather in Cabell Hall to hear the address of welcome by Dr. Alderman, President of the University of Virginia. Recitations will begin in all courses Friday, June, 19th, at 8:45 A. M. Students should present themselves at the first meeting of their classes with the required text-books and be prepared with tablets to take notes on introductory lectures. There will be no classes on Saturday, unless arranged for by individual instructors, except on Saturday, June 20th, when classes will meet at the usual hour. The length of recitation will be one hour, five minutes of which may be allowed for transfer from one class room to another. Thursday and Friday, July 30th and 31st, will be used for examinations; the determination being to provide for six full weeks of recitation over and above registration and examination days. Following the outline of each course in this announcement will be found the time and place of meeting for each class. Individual professors, may, upon consultation with the Director change the hours scheduled, in order to avoid conflicts. The Summer School lecture rooms are for the most part restricted to four buildings— Cabell Hall, the Rouss Physical Laboratory, the Engineering Building, and the Rotunda. FACULTY AND COURSES OF INSTRUCTION The attempt is made, and we believe it is attended with unusual success, to procure the most able specialists in their respective subjects as instructors. Few American summer schools will show a larger percentage of men of full professorial rank in their faculties. Especial attention is called to the strong faculties in the standard studies usually pursued in high schools and the first few years of college instruction. The following courses are offered: Agriculture (Two Courses). Art. Biology (Four Courses). Botany. Chemistry (Two Courses). Civil Government (Two Courses). Drawing (Six Courses). Domestic Science (Three Courses). Education (Five Courses). English (Seven Courses). French (Two Courses). Geography (Five Courses). German (Two Courses). Greek (Three Courses). History (Six Courses). Latin (Six Courses). Logic. Manual Training (Three Courses). Mathematics (Seven Courses). Music (Two Courses). Nature Study. Philosophy. Physics (Four Courses). Physiology (Two Courses). Physical Training (Two Courses). Primary School Work (Two Courses). Psychology. Reading. School Gardening. Story Telling (Two Courses). Teachers' Training Class. Writing. AGRICULTURE. Professor Davis. 1. Elementary Agriculture.—The following topics will be treated: Corn selection; production of good seed corn, 229, 272, 313; testing seeds for vitality, 25; butt, middle and tip kernels of seed corn; conditions for germination; treating soils for acidity, soils and their characteristics; the office of root hairs on plants; saving soil moisture, 266; poison in soils, 257; rotation of crops; study of nodules on legume roots, 278; renovation of worn-out soils, 245; clover and alfalfa seed, 194, 260, 306; alfalfa in the eastern states, 215; roots of the corn plants, 199; curing clover hay; weeds and how to kill them, 28; cotton seed and its products, 36; uses of soiling crops, 242; catch crops and cover crops, 278; cuttings for house plants, 157; layering and plant division, 157; budding peach trees; pruning a fruit tree, 181; the home garden, 255; the school garden question, 218; varieties of chickens, 51; breeds of cattle, 143, 106; breeds of swine, 205. Substitute lessons; Types of horses; gluten in flour; souring of milk, 29. Numbers refer to United States Farmers' Bulletin. Lessons are subject to change. Daily, from 2:30 to 3:30. West Range Laboratory. 2. Agriculture for High Schools.—The following topics will be treated: The farmers' interest in good seed, 111; corn judging (with score card); doubling the cotton crop, 285, 302; soil moisture and dust mulch, 266; enemies of cotton, 209, 211, 212, 216, 217, 290; the coddling moth, 171, 247; the plum curcullo; scale insects; uses of insecticides, 243; making Bordeaux Mixture, 127; prevention of potato scab; prevention of grain smut, 250; pruning a grape vine, 118, 156; a collection of economic seeds for school use; nutritive value of foods; 142; plant food in bones; value of wood ashes for soils; testing soils for fertility; experiments to show capillarity in different soils; some principles of drainage, 187; plowing under green crops, 278; inoculation of legumes, 240, 315; legumes as food, 121; testing milk and cream for butter fat; improving dairy herds by culling; winter forage crops, 147; testing for tuberculosis; poultry raising on the farm, 141; winter production of eggs; eggs and their uses as food; hog raising, 100; fundamental principles of forestry, 173, 228. Numbers at right refer to United States Farmers' Bulletins. Lessons subject to change. Daily, from 9:45 to 10:45. West Range Laboratory. BIOLOGY. Professor Tuttle. Professor Kepner. General Statement.—The summer work in Biology at present offered makes provision for the study of each of the great divisions of the organic world: separate courses being offered in Botany and in Zoology. The object in either case is, first of all, to familiarize the student with the methods involved in the systematic study of the organization of plants or of animals; and to give such opportunity for individual work by such methods on the part of each student, under the guidance of the teacher, as will enable him or her to carry on similar work elsewhere independently with confidence and accuracy. A second object of equal importance is to give to the student a clear conception of the vegetable or the animal kingdom (as the case may be) as a whole, in such manner as to impart a clear idea of the relations and significance of any particular group that may be at any time the subject of special interest. These ends are sought in each case by the presentation in the laboratory of a series of representative forms, each of which is in turn made the subject of careful study as to its organization, activities, and life-history: and by accompanying lectures, in which the results of the work in the laboratory are explained and supplemented, and the relations of the organism in question to the other forms studied and discussed. While the lecture and laboratory courses may be taken separately, they will in each case be most profitably taken together, and the examinations at the close of the session in either Botany or Zoology will cover both the lectures and the laboratory work in the subject in question. The Biological Laboratory is admirably equipped with simple and compound microscopes, microtomes and other appliances for cutting, staining, and mounting sections for microscopic study, etc.; and while the prime object of the course given will be to teach students to observe accurately, to record their observations with precision, and to make correct inferences therefrom, care will be taken to make them familiar in large measure with the principles of microscopical and other biological technic. 1. Structural Botany: Use of the microscope; simpler microscopical technic. Practical study of: A Seed-plant—anatomy, histology, development from the seed; Fern-like plants—a fern, an equisetum, a clubmoss; moss-like plants— a liverwort, a true moss; Plant-cells— structure, growth, modification, the methods of cell-division; Algae—a representative brown alga, a red alga, green algae, especially the more abundant fresh water forms; Fungi—a mushroom, a cup-fungus, the more important parasitic fungi, moulds and mildews, yeast; Fission plants: the fission algae, the bacteria. Work in the laboratory will at times be replaced by the field work in which the class will be taught to locate and identify the types studied. Laboratory work will be followed by a half hour quiz. Daily, from 10:15 to 12:15. Professor Tuttle. Cabell Hall, Room 12. 2. Systematic Botany: A synoptical course of lectures upon the vegetable kingdom, parallel with the laboratory course above outlined, and dealing largely with the lower plants not usually fully discussed in the text-books and the other literature commonly accessible. Daily, from 8:45 to 9:45. Professor Tuttle. Cabell Hall, Room 12. 3. Structural Zoology: Use of the microscope; simple microscopical technic. Practical study of: Protozoa—amoeba, paramecium; Coelenterates,—hydra and others; Flatworms: Threadworms, animal parasitism; annelids—earth-worms, nereis; mollusks—mussel or clam; Echinoderms—starfish, sea urchin; Crustacea—"water fleas," shrimps, crayfish, crabs; Insects—grasshopper, beetle, bee; Vertebrates—amphioxus, dogfish, frog; the fundamental tissues of animals— the animal cell, cell-division, maturation of the ovum, segmentation and development. Work in the laboratory will sometimes be replaced as indicated under course 1A. Daily, from 3:30 to 5:30. Professor Kepner. Cabell Hall, Room, 12. 4. Systematic Zoology.—A synoptical course of lectures upon the animal kingdom, chiefly upon the invertebrates, parallel with laboratory course above outlined. Daily, from 2:30 to 3:30. Professor Kepner. Cabell Hall, Room 12. Credit.—A student who passes the examinations in the two courses in Botany and the two courses in Zoology either in the same or in consecutive sessions will, on complying with the requirements for admission to the University, be entitled to credit for Course 1B in Biology (See catalogue of the University of Virginia) or for the requirements in that subject for admission to the Department of Medicine. BOTANY. Professor Lambeth. The outline projected is intended to give to the student a systematized course of study, making it an easy and agreeable task for him to identify the various plant families in his locality and acquire methods of study by which children may identify and become familiar with the individual plants of their neighborhood. At the beginning of the course attention will ge given to plant morphology and physiology, but the course will be of a practical character and performed in the fields and forests near the University where the plant life is diversified and rich in both indigenous and imported varieties, furnishing exceptional opportunities for the purpose. During the term each student will, under direction, collect, identify, mount, and preserve, characteristic types, so that he will have commenced the accumulation of an herbarium for use in his teaching, and to which he can continually add specimens from his own locality or that in which he is teaching. The results of the work contemplated would be of great value to the State, not only for its educational influence, but also for its economic importance as well. It would be fair to assume that with the teachers followed by their pupils working out the plants of all parts of the Commonwealth, it would only be a brief period until, from the collaboration of these collections, a complete and systematic symposium of Virginia's Flora would be available, and the information now limited to a few, and possessing only scientific importance, would become common knowledge and acquire economic value, influencing agriculture, horticulture, and many important manufacturing industries. The hours for daily excursions will be arranged as far as possible so that they will not conflict with other courses taught in the Summer School. Daily, from 4:30 to 5:30. Rotunda, S. E. Text-Book.—Dana's Manual of Botany. CHEMISTRY. Professor Bird. Mr. Sloan. 1. Lectures.—Thirty lectures upon the principles of General Chemistry—Inorganic, Organic and Physical. This course will deal more with the nature and laws of chemical change in matter than with detailed descriptions of chemical compounds themselves. Chemical reactions are classified and discussed from the standpoint of the more recently accepted theories, and the modern trend of chemical thought and investigation is dwelt upon as far as occasion and time permit. Daily, from 8:45 to 9:45. Professor Bird. West Range Laboratory. Experimental.—The instruction in this course is suited to the individual needs or desires of the members, who may take course 1 or not as they see fit. It is offered to teachers of chemistry who desire coaching in experiments that are suitable for their lecture demonstration or the laboratory exercises of their pupils (they may use their own text-books or laboratory manuals); to candidates for admission to medical and other courses, offered here or elsewhere, requiring a laboratory course in General Chemistry; and to those who desire experience in the analytical methods used in industries they contemplate entering, or who are preparing for civil service examinations for chemical positions. Those who register as candidates for admission to medical courses, etc., will be required to attend the lecture course and spend four or five hours each day, including Saturday, in the laboratory. They will not be permitted to take any other courses offered in the Summer School. The laboratory will be open from 9:00 to 1:30 daily. It is new and thoroughly equipped to do all the work offered. In addition to the regular tuition, those who take courses 2 are charged a laboratory fee of five dollars ($5.00). Apparatus and chemicals are charged for at cost. For the benefit of teachers in high schools and academies there will be on exhibition the apparatus necessary for such courses, together with catalogue numbers, prices, etc. Daily, Prof. Bird and Mr. Sloan. Hours to be arranged. West Range Laboratory. Credit.—Students who have fulfilled the conditions stated on pages 9 and 10 and who have completed successfully thirty hours per week for six weeks in course 2 in Chemistry will be excused from the laboratory work in Chemistry 1 B of the University course, and need complete in the winter term only the lectures and examination to received full credit for Chemistry 1B. Course 1 above and thirty hours per week of course 2 successfully completed will meet the entrance requirements to the Medical School of the University. DOMESTIC SCIENCE. Miss Charlton. 1. Sanitation of Foods.—Comprising the following general subjects: Household bacteriology—Study of bacteria, yeasts and molds; sanitation—heating, ventilation and removing of wastes; physiology and hygiene—organization of the body, process of digestion and circulation, secretion and excretion, relation of food to disease, care of the skin, home nursing; foods and nutrition—composition of foods, principles of nutrition, adulteration and inspection, preservation, dietaries in health, sickness, old age and childhood, cookery—methods of cooking, preparation of food. Daily, from 3:30 to 4:30. Madison Hall. 2. Household Management and Home Decoration.—Building materials; arrangement of rooms; finishing woodwork, floors and walls; furnishing; care and selection of utensils, silver and china; carpets and rugs; library; labor saving devices in housework; household accounts; entertaining; household service; instruction to waitress. Daily, hours to be arranged. Madison Hall. 3. Sewing.—Textiles and fabrics; sewing methods; drafting for patterns for underwear and shirt waist, illustrating different stitches on plain garments; care and use of sewing machines. These courses will be made as practical as possible and in such a manner as to be of immediate use to the students attending the Summer School. Daily, 12:15 to 1:15. Madison Hall. DRAWING. Professor Augsburg. Professor Blair. 1. Drawing for High School.—Historic ornament and design; course in architecture; water color and wash drawing from nature. Informal talk each day on Art,—the great paintings of the world, the appreciation and enjoyment of pictures, etc. Daily, from 12:15 to 1:15. Professor Blair. Mechanical Laboratory. Materials.—Sketch book, drawing books, soft pencils, and art note book for lectures, etc. 2. Advanced Course.—To be arranged, according to demand. Daily, 3:30 to 4:30. Professor Augsburg and Assistant. Mechanical Building, Room 1. Remark.—Mechanical Drawing will be provided if there is a sufficient demand. Application should be made to Director of Summer School. EDUCATION. Professor Heatwole. Professor Rudiger. Professor Payne. 1. Educational Psychology.—This course will begin with a consideration of the function of education in the social organism but the major part of the time will be devoted to the application of the principles of psychology to teaching. Among the topics studied will be the fundamental instincts and capacities, individual differences, habit formation, apperception, inductive and deductive methods, fundamental types of lessons, moral training, motor training, formal discipline. Daily, from 10:45 to 11:45. Professor Ruediger. Cabell Hall, Room 3. Text-Books.—The course will be based primarily upon Thorndike's Principles of Teaching, but Bagley's The Educative Process and James's Talks to Teachers will also be extensively used. 2. School Management.—The course will cover the following topics: Brief sketch of the development of the American school system, American public school ideals, significance of life, the teacher, her function and growth; physical conditions—school buildings, grounds, lighting, heating, ventilation, sanitation, and hygiene; organization of school—classes, grading and promotion; government— school virtues, character and purpose of discipline, self-control, school incentive, the incorrigibles; the curriculum—daily program, number of classes, recitation and the study period, training to think, reviews and examinations; moral education, the school and the home, decoration in the school room, the library; affiliated interests—athletics, literary societies, clubs, school paper; relation of the teacher to the board of education and to the principal; school ethics; physical education—nervous strain, defects of sight and of hearing. Daily, from 9:45 to 10:45. Professor Heatwole. Cabell Hall, Room 3. Texts.—School Management, by Dutton. 3. High School Problems.—This course will begin with a brief outline of the history of the curriculum, organization, and administration of secondary education in America, followed by a consideration of the function of secondary education, recent tendencies in public high school, and adolescence. High school discipline, relation of High School work to Elementary School and College, especially College preparation and preparation for life will receive adequate discussion. The major portion of the time will be devoted to a detailed examination of the educational value and methods of presentation of the high school branches and to the organization of courses of study. Lectures, reports, and discussions. Daily, from 3:30 to 4:30. Professor Ruediger and Professor Payne. Cabell Hall, Room 5. Text-Books.—The N. E. A. Reports, periodical literature, Longman's American Teacher Series and courses of study will be drawn upon for material. Remark.—Education 5 is open to all registered students free of charge. ENGLISH. Professor Henneman. Professor Mims. Professor Kent. Professor Smith. Rhetoric and English Literature. A. For present or prospective High School Teachers. To meet the needs of this class, the course will not only cover the subject matter of a good text-book in Rhetoric and a good text-book in English Literature, but will also give outlines and exercises designed to suggest methods of teaching these subjects. B.—For Professional or Technical Students, Deficient in English. There are many students who enter upon their professional courses and later become convinced that their English training is so defective as to interfere greatly with the prospects of success in their chosen profession. This course will enable such students to strengthen materially their English training, and to procure some systematic practice, under careful instruction, in writing English. C.—For students Preparing for College Entrance Examinations. The increased entrance requirements at the University of Virginia will make it necessary for some students who wish to enter, to do some special work in preparation for these examinations. The pursuit of the courses offered in the University Summer School, and the completion satisfactorily of these courses will exempt the student from certain parts of the entrance examination. D.—For Students Conditioned on their Entrance Examinations, or at other institutions, in their College Courses. These courses in Rhetoric and English Literature afford an excellent opportunity for students who have conditions to make up at the fall examinations, or who in Curriculum Colleges, have fallen behind in their Freshman and Sophomore work, to make up these deficiencies. E.—For College Professors and Instructors. There are many college professors and instructors who, without needing a particular review of the subject matter of these courses, might be interested in learning the methods used in teaching these subjects in the University of Virginia. For such professors and instructors, this course, supplemented by full courses in reading which will be assigned as optional work along with the work required of the class, would prove distinctly beneficial. 1. Rhetoric.—The purpose of the course in Rhetoric will be threefold: first, to master as far as possible the subject matter of the textbook, and in doing this to emphasize particularly accuracy and correctness in writing; second, to indicate the best methods of teaching this subject in the schools, so as to interest the pupils and induce them to take advantage of local material and opportunities; third, to encourage good reading both for its own sake and specifically for the sake of mental discipline. There will be daily original exercises. Daily, 9:45 to 10:45. Professor Kent (two weeks) and Prof. Henneman (four weeks). Cabell Hall, Room 4. Text-Book.—Lamont's Rhetoric. 2. English Literature.—The course in English Literature is designed, first, to give a general and comprehensive oversight of the field of English Literature; second, to sub-divide it into periods for convenient study; third, to handle with reasonable completeness certain select authors; fourth, to acquaint the students with the salient facts in the development of English Literature; and fifth, to indicate some valuable methods of teaching English Literature so as to lend it liveliness and interest. Parallel reading will be assigned, and as far as the time allows, there will be made a special study of College Requirements. Daily, from 8:45 to 9:45. Professor Kent (two weeks) and Professor Mims (four weeks). Cabell Hall, Room 4. Text-Book.—Painter's Introduction to English Literature (Rev. 1906). 3. English Grammar.—Talks on English Grammar and composition, designed especially for high school teachers. No subjects in the high school curriculum are more unsettled than those of grammar and composition, both being in a transitive stage. The multiplication of high schools in the South has called attention afresh to the importance of English but there is still little uniformity in methods or standards. The members of the class are requested to bring with them any English grammars that they may be using. Daily, from 10:45 to 11:45. Professor Smith (two weeks,) Professor Henneman (four weeks). Cabell Hall, Room 4. Text-Book.—Smith's Our Language, and Studies in English Syntax. 4. American Literature.—After a discussion of the definition and a division into periods, the periods will be studied in turn, with special attention to nineteenth century authors. Daily, from 12:15 to 1:15. Professor Smith (two weeks) and Professor Mims (four weeks). Cabell Hall, Room 4. Text-Book.—Page's Chief American Poets; Houghton, Mifflin &amp; Co.), and Abernethy's History of American Literature. Credit.—Any student who fulfills the conditions set forth on pages 9 and 10 and who completes successfully the four courses in English outlined above will be credited with course 1 A in English Literature. Remark.—The two courses in story telling (See School of Methods) should be interesting to students of English. No charge is made for these courses. FRENCH. Professor Dey. 1. Elementary French.—Grammar, through the regular verbs; exercises and dictations; the principles of pronunciation are insisted upon; four hundred pages of modern French prose are read. Daily, from 10:45 to 11:45. Rotunda, Room 2. Text-Books.—Fraser and Squair's Grammar (Heath); Dumas,L'Evasion du Duc de Beaufort (Heath); Merimee, Columba (Holt); Malot, Sans Famille (Holt). 2. Advanced French.—Grammar: Syntax and irregular verbs. Oral and written exercises, and dictation. The French play will be interpreted; seven hundred pages will be read. Daily, from 12:15 to 1:15. Rotunda, Room 2. Text-Books.—Gasc's French Dictionary (Holt); Labiche and Martin, Poudre aux yeux (Heath); Meilhac et Halévy, L'Eté de la St.Martin (Heath); Pailleron, Le Monde où l'on S'ennuie (Heath); Musset, Trois comédies (Heath); Molière, Le bourgeois Gentilhomme (American Book Co.); Racine, Esther (Heath); Corneille, Le Cid (Holt). Credit.—Students having fulfilled the conditions on pages 9 and 10 and having completed both these courses and passed the corresponding examinations in each will be considered as having absolved the requirements of French 1A, and will be admitted to French 2B (See catalogue of the University of Virginia, page 117) of the University's college course. GEOGRAPHY. Professor Milledge. 3. Physical Geography.—Series of field lessons illustrating erosion, corrosion, valley development, river basins, sedimentation, etc. (Indispensable as insuring vitality to the course.) Physical relief of continents illustrated by chalk modeling and land maps: resultant continental drainage: volcanoes and earthquakes in connection with mountain building. Relation of the earth to the Sun. Brief synopsis of mathematical geography. Theory of the Winds, directly based on the preceding paragraph: regions of rainfall, deserts and belts of vegetation on the earth in connection with winds. The Ocean,—its currents, tides, etc. Glaciers,—Ice Age, with especial reference to North America. Daily, from 2:30 to 3:30. Rouss Laboratory, Room 3. Texts.—Any good manual, Davis' Elementary Physical Geography. preferred. Professor Milledge. 4. Commercial Geography.—Brief discussion of stages of man's growth from savagery through the pastoral and agricultural to the present age. Potamic and Tholassic civilizations compared. Historical review of the commerce of antiquity;—Babylonia, Phoenicia, Greece, Carthage, and Rome: Scene,—the Mediterranean, with Indian Ocean and enclosed seas of Western Europe. Commerce of Middle Ages,—Italian Republics and the Hanseatic League. Discovery of America and Ocean Route to the East. Era of colonization and rise of Spain and Portugal, later of Holland, England, and France. Entry of Germany and the United States upon the stage. Areas of production of the world's great staples, (a) Agricultural, (b) Mineral, (c) Forest Products, (d) Fisheries. Means of transportation, roads, rivers, canals, railroads, steamships, and sailing vessels: Discussion of freights. Significance of the Suez and Panama Canals. Manufacturing centers of the world;—discussion of the determining causes of development. Problems of the future, consequent upon exhaustion of old fields and the development of new. Daily, from 3:30 to 4:30. Rouss Laboratory, Room 3. GERMAN. Professor Faulkner. Two courses in German are offered, six hours lectures a week in each course. In the course for beginners no previous knowledge of German is required. In preparation for the advanced course, at least two years' high school work in German or its equivalent is necessary. As the work in both courses is arranged on the supposition that the student in either course will devote at least eighteen hours a week outside of lectures to the preparation for lectures and to parallel reading, students taking either course are strongly urged to enroll themselves for not more than one other course in the Summer School. Students attaining a grade of 75% in either course will be given a certificate of successful completion of the course in question. In computing this grade, class standing is based on a daily written test during the first fifteen minutes of the hour, covering the subject-matter of the preceding lecture, and the other written work of the class will be reckoned at 50%; and examination standing at 50%. Unexcused absences are graded as zero. Excused absences may be made up by taking in some other hour than that of the regular lecture a written class test covering the regular class test for the day on which the absence was recorded. 1. Course for Beginners.—Pronunciation, dictation exercises, elements of German grammar (eighteen hours); reading of simple German (prose and poetry)—conversation on matter read (eighteen hours); parallel reading to be assigned. Daily, from 8:45 to 9:45. Rotunda, S. W. Text-Books.—Bierwirth's Beginning German; Mueller and Wenckebach's Gluk Auf. 2. Advanced Course.—Geography and history of Germany; German folklore; selections from Goethe's lyrics and ballads, in chronological order; advanced exercises in pronunciation and dictation; grammar and prose composition; parallel reading to be assigned. Daily, from 9:45 to 10:45. Rotunda, S. W. Text-Books.—Schweitzer's Deutsches Lesebuch und Sprechuebungen, fuer Quarta und Tertia; or Stern's Geschichten von deutsch en Staedten; Von Klenze's Deutsche Gedichte; Bierwirth's Elements of German; Wells's Modern German Literature. Credit.—The Beginner's Course is exactly equivalent to the first term's work in German 1A in the regular session of the University, and corresponding credits will be granted therefore by the Dean of the University, to those students fulfilling the conditions set forth on pages 9 and 10. The advanced course in German is exactly equivalent in character and scope to the first term's work in German 2B in the regular session of the University, and has been approved as such by the Academic Faculty of the University. Corresponding credits therefore will be granted by the Academic Faculty to the students successfully completing this course, who have fulfilled conditions set forth on p. GREEK. Professor Montgomery. 1. Beginners Course.—Special comparison of forms with those of Latin for aid of teachers. Daily written exercises. Xenophon's Anabasis begun. Daily. Hours to be arranged. Prof. Montgomery. Cabell Hall, Room 1. Text-Book.—White's First Greek Book. 2. Xenophon's Anabasis, four books.—Review of forms. Grammar work. Prose exercise work based on text read. Parallel reading on kindred literary and historical topics. Daily. Hours to be arranged. Prof. Montgomery. Cabell Hall, Room 1. Text-Books.—White's Edition of Goodwin's Anabasis; Goodwin's Grammar. 3. Gospel of St. Luke and Acts of the Apostles.—New Testament grammar, with special attention to comparison of New Testament and Attic usages. Three hours per week, to be arranged. Prof. Montgomery. Cabell Hall, Room 1. No course in Greek will be given to less than five applicants. The fee for each course will be $10. HISTORY. Professor Mitchell. Professor Heatwole. Professor Page. 1. Ancient History.—The work in this course, after a brief notice of the oriental nations, will be concentrated upon Greece and Rome. In the former, a special study will be made of the Age of Pericles; in the latter, the corresponding Age of Augustus will be emphasized. Students who wish General History will be allowed to do advanced work in this course. Daily, from 3:30 to 4:30. Professor Heatwole. Cabell Hall, Room 6. 2. Medieval and Modern History.—After a brief survey of the Middle Ages, in which the papacy and the Holy Roman Empire will form the chief topics of discussion, the leading events in the modern world will be grouped around the Renaissance, the Reformation, and the French Revolution. Lectures, collateral reading and reports by members of the class. Daily, from 12:15 to 1:15. Professor Mitchell. Rotunda, Room 3. Text-Books.—Schwill's Political History of Modern Europe (Scribners). As a source-book, Robinson's Readings in European History will be invaluable to students in this course. A Source-Book for Medieval History, by Thatcher and McNeal, is likewise recommended. 3. English History.—While the social, economic, and intellectual factors in the development of the English people will receive attention, the main emphasis in this course will fall upon the origin and growth of Parliament, the parent of representatives assemblies in the modern world. Lectures, collateral readings and reports by members of class. Daily, from 10:45 to 11:45. Professor Mitchell. Rotunda, Room 3. Text-Books.—Tout's Advanced History of Great Britain (Longmans, Gree &amp; Co.); The following source-books may be recommended: Kendall's Source-Book for English History (Macmillan); Colby's Selections from the Sources of English History (Longman); and Lee's Source-Book of English History. 4. History of the United States.—This course is intended to cover the general history of the United States. The lectures will deal in large measure with the economic and social growth of the nation; while the discussions and assigned readings will bear mainly on constitutional and political development. Daily, from 8:45 to 9:45. Professor Page. Rotunda, Room 3. Text-Book.—Student should bring Doub's History of the United States, or any modern text in history. 5. Civil Government in the United States.—In this course, students will be guided in a study of the structure and working of the Federal, State, and local governments in the United States. A special effort will be made to familiarize the student with the literature of political theories, the growth of political parties, and the present problems of American government. Instruction will be given by assigned readings, discussions, and lectures. Daily, from 9:45 to 10:45. Professor Page. Rotunda, Room 3. Text-Book.—Students should bring any modern text in government. LATIN. Professor Fitzhugh. Professor Montgomery. General Statement.—It will be the aim of the School of Latin to open to all teachers and students of Latin the advantages of University instruction in that subject. The study of Latin is the study of the language, literature, and life of the Romans. Every course will therefore have due regard to each of these interests. Course 1 is preparatory; thereafter the work is organized in all courses as follows: A. The Latin Language: Systematic study of Latin grammar, with oral and written exercises in prose composition. Two hours a week in each course. B. Latin Literature: Systematic study of the Latin authors in culture-historical sequence. Three hours a week in each course. C. Roman Life: Systematic study of Roman culture-history in English, in conjunction with the reading of the authors. Three hours a week in each course (coincident with B.). HIGH SCHOOL COURSES. Courses 1-4 are intended to illustrate the teaching of Latin in the Secondary school, and to offer to teachers in high schools and academies, and to students preparing for college, the opportunity of special instruction in the subjects taught in the four years of Latin preparation. The First Year of the High School. 1. Beginners' Course.—For teachers in high schools and academies, for college preparation, and for students of Latin at large. This course is devoted to the Beginner's Book in Latin and concludes with elementary Latin reading. It involves: the Roman pronunciation; careful study of accent and quantity; thorough drill in declensions and conjugations; the fundamental principles of the syntax of the cases, tenses, and moods; accusative and infinitive, relative and conditional sentences; the fundamental uses of the subjunctive; and the main laws of indirect discourse. These grammatical principles are illustrated in systematic exercises in translating easy detached sentences into Latin. Translation into English of simple Latin prose preparatory to Caesar. Daily, from 8:45 to 9:45. Professor Montgomery. Cabell Hall, Room 1. Text-Book.—Bennett's Foundations of Latin. The Second Year of the High School. 2. Caesar Course.—For teachers in high schools and academies, for college preparation, and for students of Latin at large. This course involves Caesar's Gallic War, Books I-IV, with collateral readings in Viri Romae, and the fundamental outlines of Roman culture-history; the study of the author will be not only grammatical but literary and culture-historical. Constant practice in sight reading. Systematic study of high school Latin Grammar, with accompanying prose composition based on Caesar. (a) Grammar and Prose Composition: High school grammar and accompanying exercises. Tuesday and Thursday. Professor Montgomery. (b) Literature and Life: Caesar, varied with Viri Romae; the broad outlines of Roman culture-history. Monday, Wednesday, and Friday. Professor Fitzhugh. Daily, from 3:30 to 4:30. Cabell Hall, Room 1. Text-Books.—Bennett's Latin Grammar and Preparatory Latin Writer; Caesar's Gallic War; Viri Romae; Abbott's Short History of Rome; Botsford's Story of Rome. The Third Year of the High School. 3. Cicero Course.—For teachers in high school and academies, for college preparation, and for students of Latin at large. This course involves Cicero's Four Orations against Catiline, the Manilian Law and Pro Archia, with collateral readings in Nepos' Lives; the private and public life of the Romans. The study of the author will be grammatical, literary, and culture-historical. Constant practice at sight reading. High School Latin grammar continued, with accompanying prose composition based on Cicero. (a) Grammar and Prose Composition: High school grammar and accompanying exercises. Tuesday and Thursday. Professor Montgomery. (b) Literature and Life: Cicero, varied with Nepos; the private and public life of the Romans. Monday, Wednesday, and Friday. Professor Fitzhugh. Daily, from 12:15 to 1:15. Cabell Hall, Room 1. Text-Books.—Bennett's Latin Grammar and Latin Composition; Cicero's Orations; Nepos' Lives; Johnston's Private Life of the Romans; Gow's Companion to School Classics, sections on the Public Life of the Romans. The Fourth Year of the High School. 4. Vergil Course.—For teachers in high schools and academies, for college preparation, and for students of Latin at large. This course involves Vergil's Aeneid, Books I-VI with collateral readings in Ovid's Metamorphoses; the principles of Latin versification with scansion of the dactylic hexameter; the mythology of the Greeks and Romans. The study of the author will be grammatical, literary and culture-historical. Constant practice in sight reading. High school grammar concluded, with accompanying prose composition. (a) Grammar and Prose Composition: High school grammar and prose composition. Tuesday and Thursday. Professor Montgomery. (b) Literature and Life: Vergil, varied with Ovid; the mythology of the Greeks and Romans. Monday, Wednesday, and Friday. Professor Fitzhugh. Daily, from 9:45 to 10:45. Cabell Hall, Room 1. Text-Books.—Bennett's Latin Grammar and Latin Composition; Vergil's Aeneid; Ovid's Metamorphoses (Miller); Fairbank's Mythology of Greece and Rome; Bulfinch's Age of Fable. COLLEGE COURSES. Courses 5 and 6, offered to as many as five applicants in each, are intended to open up to teachers and summer students the more important fields of college Latin. They are devoted to the broad cultural study of the language, literature, and life of the Romans. Roman civilization is the link between the Hellenic and the modern: the instruction will aim, therefore, to exhibit this relation, and so, to emphasize the unity and continuity of all human culture. The desirability of a knowledge of Greek and of at least one Romanic language is especially commended to all who would reap the full cultural and scientific benefit of the college course in Latin: the Greek illumines incomparably all parts of Latin study, which in turn bears fascinatingly upon the Romanic. 5. Livy Course (one third College course).—For teachers in colleges, for college students, and for students of Latin at large. This course is identical with that of the first term of 3B in the catalogue of the University of Virginia. It involves Livy's Hannibalic War, Books XXI-XXII, with collateral reading in Tacitus' Germania, and the private and public life of the Romans. The study of the author will be grammatical, literary, and culture-historical. Constant exercise in sight reading. College Latin grammar and exercises based on Livy. (a) Grammar and Prose Composition: College Latin grammar and prose composition (ten entire exercises in Nutting, beginning 6, 16, etc.). Wednesday and Friday. Professor Montgomery. (b) Literature and Life: Livy and Tacitus; the private and public life of the Romans. Tuesday, Thursday and Saturday. Professor Fitzhugh. Daily (except Monday), from 2:30 to 3:30. Cabell Hall, Room 1. Text-Books.—Gildersleeve-Lodge, Larger Latin Grammar and Nutting's Advanced Latin Composition; Livy's Hannibalic War, Books XXI-XXII; Tacitus' Germania; Johnston's Private Life of the Romans; Gow's Companion to School Classics, sections on the Public Life of the Romans. 6. Horace Course (One third College course).—For teachers in colleges, for college students, and for students of Latin at large. This course is identical with that of the second term of 3B in the University of Virginia catalogue. It involves Horace's Odes and Epodes and Vergil's Bucolics; the rythm of lyric and idyllic verse; the outlines of the art life of the Greeks and Romans; college grammar and prose composition. (a) Grammar and Prose Composition: College grammar and Latin prose composition (ten entire exercises in Gildersleeve-Lodge, beginning with 6, 18, etc. in Part I and with 72, 84, etc. in Part II). Wednesday and Friday. Professor Montgomery. (b) Literature and Life: Horace's Odes and Epodes; Vergil's Bucolics; the history of the Greek and Roman Art. Tuesday, Thursday and Saturday. Professor Fitzhugh. Daily, (except Monday) from 10:45 to 11:45. Cabell Hall, Room 1. Text-Books.—Gildersleeve-Lodge, Larger Latin Grammar and Latin Composition; Horace's Odes and Epodes; Vergil's Bucolics; Tarbell's History of Greek Art; Goodyear's Roman Art. Remark.—Any standard grammar or approved text will be adequate to the purposes of the work. For those who desire to purchase, special editions will be available at the University book stores. Credits.—Any student who fulfills the conditions set forth on pages 9 and 10 and who completes successfully courses 5 and 6 will be given credit for the first and second terms work respectively of Latin 3B (See Catalogue of University of Virginia). LOGIC. Professor Lefevre. After a brief survey of the history of the science of Logic, the class will be engaged with a study of either Deduction or Induction, according to the demand and need of the students electing the course. The lectures will deal also with the general character of the thinking process, its laws of development, and the methods by which thought actually proceeds to solve the problems presented to it. Special attention will be directed to the analysis of logical arguments and to the detection of fallacies in reasoning. Daily, from 9:45 to 10:45. Rotunda, S. E. Text-Book.—Creighton's Introductory Logic. Credit.—Any student who fulfills the conditions set forth on pages 9 and 10 and who completes successfully the summer course in Logic will receive credit for the corresponding term in Philosophy 1B. (See Catalogue of University of Virginia). MANUAL TRAINING. Professor Crawford. 2. Wood-working for High Schools.—A course employing a comprehensive set of bench tools, dealing with the principles of wood construction in a set of graded models; the action of cutting tools, their uses and care, and the application of wood finishes. Practical work, methods of presentation, and execution. Daily, hours to be arranged. Mechanical Laboratory. 3. Constructive Design.—An abridged course for the study of the principles of design with special reference to application in Handicraft. Problems are considered from the standpoint of function, structure, material, form, and decoration. Daily, hours to be arranged. Mechanical Laboratory. MATHEMATICS. Professor Page. Professor Echols. 1. Advanced Algebra.—The work begins with the Progressions and proceeds with the study of the Binomial Formula, Convergence and Divergence of Series, with special study of the Binomial, Exponential and Logarithmic Series. The study of Inequalities and Determinants prepares for the Theory of Equations with which the course is closed. Daily, from 9:45 to 10:45. Professor Page. Cabell Hall, Room 8. Text-Book.—Charles Smith's Treatise on Algebra. 2. Plane Geometry.—This course is designed for students wishing to review this subject or to repair deficiencies, for teachers and those who are preparing for college examinations. It is presumed that students attending the course have had a previous knowledge of the subject as a whole or in part. The lectures and quizzes will be framed therefore with the view of strengthening and harmonizing the knowledge of plane geometry. There will be discussed for historical development, the logical connection of the theorems and processes of elementary geometry; the definitions of the fundamental geometrical concepts; the axioms of geometry and the nature of geometrical proof; the systematic study of the original solution and methods of attack of geometrical problems; the theory of geometric graphical solution, and the problems of quadrature of the circle. Daily, from 10:45 to 11:45. Professor Echols. Cabell Hall, Room 8. 3. Solid Geometry.—The course presupposes a knowledge of Plane Geometry as given in the previous course and in the current text books. Especial attention is given to the logical development of the subject and to the dependent relationship between the propositions. The scientific and pedagogic aspects of the theory of limits will be treated in detail. The problems of geometrical mensuration for space are carefully worked out to conclusions. Daily, from 12:15 to 1:15. Professor Echols. Cabell Hall, Room 8. Text-Book.—Venable's Elements of Geometry. The method of presentation in the courses of both Plane Geometry and Solid Geometry will be by lectures and text references, with frequent quizzing and blackboard exercises by the student. Students are requested to bring with them such texts as they have studied and have used for teaching. A collection of modern texts in English and foreign languages will be used for purposes of comparison and in illustration of the different methods of presenting the subject in this and other countries. 4. Plane and Spherical Trigonometry.—The course in Plane Trigonometry begins with the definitions of the six trigonometric functions as ratios, and embraces all topics usually covered in the standard text-books,—including the use of logarithms. In Spherical Trigonometry, the course ends with the solution of oblique spherical triangles. Daily, from 8:45 to 9:45. Professor Page. Cabell Hall, Room 8. Text-Books.—Laney's Trigonometry, Part I; Murray's Spherical Trigonometry; Murray's Five-Place Tables. Credit.—Those students completing courses 1, 3 and 4 will be credited with course 1A given in the session; provided the conditions set forth on pages 9 and 10 have been fulfilled. MUSIC. Miss Hofer. Mrs. Starke. 1. Music for Upper Grades and High Schools.—Songs illustrating the more difficult problems of music and sight singing; two and three part music; bass singing. Advanced vocal training, treating of boy's voices; how to get most effective results from class and chorus work. Program making for festivals and entertainments; social and aesthetic uses of music; selected folk and national songs for illustrating literature, history, geography. Daily, (Hours to be arranged). Auditorium. Text-Books.—Modern Music Series, Books, II, III and IV. High School books. Games.—A short course in schoolroom games and exercises, singing games, folk games and dances for the playground will be offered to those interested in this work. Bibliography of games and exercises given. Printed outlines and lists of songs supplied. Remark.—Course 2, School of Music, (see School of Methods) is open to all students free of charge. PHILOSOPHY. Professor Lefevre. This course is designed as an introduction to the study of Philosophy to meet the needs of students who desire to learn the historical development of the problems and systems of modern philosophy. The lectures will follow the narrative of philosophical speculation from the Renaissance to the present time. The endeavor will be made to represent the various theories in their relation to the science and general civilization of the ages to which they belong, and to estimate their social, political and educational significance. Daily, from 10:45 to 11:45. Rotunda, S. E. Text-Books.—Roger's Students' History of Philosophy; Royce's Spirit of Modern Philosophy. Collateral reading to be assigned. Credit.—Any student who fulfills the conditions set forth on pages 9 and 10 and completes successfully this course will be given credit for one term's work in Philosophy 4C (see catalogue of University of Virginia) as an elective at large for the B. A. degree. PHYSICAL TRAINING. Mr. Peck. 1. Gymnastics for Men.—Course in Calisthenics and light gymnastics, for men. This course will involve free exercises without apparatus; exercise with bells, clubs, and wands arranged for concerted or individual action. Daily, from 5:30 to 6:30. Fayerweather Gymnasium. 2. Gymnastics for Women.—Same as course No. 1 for women. These two courses contain all that either sex needs for the perfect development of the body, and are adapted to public schools. Daily, from 4:30 to 5:30. Fayerweather Gymnasium. Remark.—No fees are charged for these courses. PHYSICS. Professor Clo. Professor Anderson. Four of the six courses outlined below will be given according to demand, and grouped in one of the following ways: (a) 1, 2, 3, 4; (b) 1, 2, 5, 6; (c) 3, 4, 5, 6. The student is expected to take them in pairs; either 1 and 2, 3 and 4, or 5 and 6. 1. Lecture Course.—This course is intended primarily for (a) those teachers who have been teaching physics or who intend to teach physics, and (b) those persons who wish to prepare themselves for more advanced work in the University. The instruction will consist of lectures along the line of some standard text. The splendid equipment of Rouss Physical Laboratory gives the student every opportunity to see thorough and comprehensive demonstrations of the phenomena of physics. In addition a study will be made of the simple and less expensive demonstration apparatus desirable for high school work. Opportunity will be given the student to ascertain the nature and cost of an equipment of a good high school course. This course includes mechanics, heat, sound, light, electricity, and magnetism. Preparation in trigonometry is not essential. Daily, from 8:45 to 9:45. Prof. Clo. Rouss Physical Laboratory, Room 1. 2. Laboratory Course.—To be taken with course 1. About sixty experiments will be performed by the student under the direct supervision of the instructor. The nature of these experiments will be fixed but no special laboratory text will be followed. Persons preparing to teach will be allowed to use the manual which they intend to adopt. Two or three hours daily, hours to be arranged. Prof. Clo. Rouss Physical Laboratory. 3. General Physics.—Covers the topics of Mechanics, Sound and Light. Lectures, experimental demonstrations and problems. Daily, 10:45 to 12:00. Prof. Anderson. Rouss Physical Laboratory. Text-Book.—Carhart's University Physics, Part I. 4. Laboratory work to accompany course 3. Daily, 2:30 to 5:30. Prof. Anderson. Rouss Physical Laboratory. Text-Book.—Ames and Bliss, Manual of Experiments in Physics. 5. General Physics.—Lectures, experimental demonstrations and problems covering the topics of Heat, Electricity, and Magnetism. Daily, Rouss Physical Laboratory. Text-Book.—Carhart's University Physics, Part II. 6. Laboratory work to accompany Course 5. Daily, Text-Book.—Ames and Bliss, Manual of Experiments in Physics. The number of hours daily required for Courses 3, 4, 5, 6, will depend somewhat upon maturity and previous training on the part of students. A knowledge of logarithms and of plane trigonometry through the right triangles is essential. Further, to take more than two courses, at one time, an additional previous training, both in a text-book on physics and in a laboratory is essential. Credit.—Courses 3, 4, 5, and 6, outlined above, will, when successfully completed in the aggregate, entitle the student who has fulfilled conditions stated on pages 9 and 10, to a credit for the college year's course in physics given in the University during the regular session, namely, Course 1B. PSYCHOLOGY. Professor Ruediger. General Psychology.—It will be the aim of this course to lead the student into a systematic knowledge of the chief facts and principles of psychology. Especial emphasis will be laid upon those phases of the science that bear on educational theory and practice. Experimental demonstrations and concrete illustrations will be freely introduced. Daily, 8:45 to 9:45. Rotunda, Room 1. Text-Books.—Thorndike's Elements of Psychology will be used as a text supplemented by references to other standard texts. It is suggested that students bring with them any psychological texts they may have. Credit.—Any student who fulfills the conditions set forth on pages 9 and 10 and who completes successfully this course will be given credit for one term's work in Philosophy 3B. THE UNIVERSITY SUMMER SCHOOL OF METHODS. Supt. E. C. Glass, Conductor. [The University considers itself fortunate to be able to continue this valuable school under the management of Professor E. C. Glass, Superintendent of the City Schools of Lynchburg, Virginia. Its record for the training of efficient teachers in Virginia is superior to that of any other Summer School. In fact, it is in a way the pioneer in the field. The number and efficiency of the teaching staff have been greatly increased for the present session. Especially is this true of the subject matter courses. Every subject taught in the primary and grammar grades will be taught in the School of Methods by instructors of great strength and ability. It is believed that no better opportunity exists in the South for the preparation of teachers for the State Board's examinations than is found in this school.] A fee of $3.00 for Virginia teachers and $5.00 for teachers outside of the State will pay for all the courses offered in the School of Methods, and teachers will not be restricted in the number of courses selected. Virginia teachers are given the reduced price on account of the Contribution by the State toward the expenses of this school. DRAWING. Professor Augsburg. Professor Blair. Miss Green. 3. Drawing for Primary Grades.—The following topics will be treated: Objects; still life; poses; Nature; creative imagination; plans, to be used in constructive work; analysis; composition; decoration; illustration. Two lessons each week will be given to construction work, basketry, and weaving. The three mediums in drawing,—pencil, crayons, and water colors, will be used in all classes. Daily, Hours to be arranged. Miss Green. 4. Drawing for Grammar Grades.—Free hand drawing with chalk, pencil, charcoal and pen and ink; practical drawing from nature especially adapted to schoolroom work; outdoor sketching; blackboard illustrating; map drawing. Daily, from 2.30 to 3.30. Professor Blair. Mechanical Laboratory. 5. Free Hand Drawing.—This course is fundamental in character and aims to show in a direct manner: How to draw; how to teach drawing; and how to use drawing. Special attention is given to blackboard drawing, chalk modeling, and how to draw nearly all common objects that are and can be used to advantage in the classroom. Primary and grammargrade drawing are special features of this course. Under these heads will be given drawing from memory and the imagination, action drawing, two-handed drawing; the drawing of trees, birds, animals, the human head and figure, as well as methods of teaching each one. Daily, from 9.45 to 10.45. Professor Augsburg, and Assistant. Mechanical Laboratory. 6. Color Work.—The course in water colors includes brush drawing and wash drawing. In general this subject will be divided into three lines of work: learning color; painting objects; picture making. (a) Learning Color.—The only way to learn color is to work in color—to use color. This is done systematically through a progressive series of washes which, in addition to the teaching of color, at the same time includes all the mechanical difficulties of working in color. (b) Painting objects is simply what the name implies, painting or making studies of the common objects which can be used in the class-room to the best advantage such as: Fruits,—apples, pears, plums, grapes and cherries; vegetables,—radishes, carrots, cucumbers, pumpkins and gourds; flowers,—sweet peas, poppy, marguerites, pansy, rose, daffodil, and violet; grasses,—clover, sorrel, flax, etc.; trees,—especially the oak, poplar; buds and leaves of the most simple and common kinds; pottery of simple form and bright colors; birds in the form of mounted specimens, also butterflies; bits of landscape, such as a stump, log, large stone, gate, etc. (c) Picture Making.—Under this head will be taken up: How to make pictures, the composition, light and shade, color values, shade values, and by keeping these separate, show, by actual demonstration, how each one may be represented. Daily, from 4.30 to 5.30. Professor Augsburg and Assistant. Cabell Hall, Room 4. EDUCATION. Professor Glass. Professor Payne. Professor Heatwole. 4. Theory and Practice of Teaching.—For teachers in elementary schools. The class will be required to select and arrange lessons from the various subjects taught in the public school. Plans of such subject matter will be made upon the principles discussed in class. These principles are such as interest, attention, correlation, the art of questioning, aims and methods of instruction in the various elementary school subjects; value of type-studies, written work, study periods, excursions; method of discipline; schoolroom activities. Special method in history, geography, arithmetic, and language will be developed. Daily, from 12.15 to 1.15. Professor Heatwole and Professor Payne. Cabell Hall, Room 3. Text-Books.—McMurry's Method of the Recitation; McMurry's Special Method in History, Geography, and Arithmetic; Dewey's School and Society. 5. Organization and Administration of Schools and School Systems (Round Table).—This course is intended for superintendents, principals, and for teachers of experience who desire to study the problems of grading, promotion, administration, etc., from a practical point of view. The work will be done by the instructor in charge, assisted by various members of the Faculty who have had experience in the various topics. The method will be that of the round table conference, opportunity for questions and discussions will be afforded. The powers, privileges, and relations of teachers, principals and superintendents will be discussed. The course of study in elementary and high schools, together with approved methods of school work and community work will receive attention. Daily, from 4.30 to 5.30. Professor Glass. Cabell Hall, Room 5. ELEMENTARY ENGLISH. Miss Andrews. 5. Intermediate Language Work.—This course is designed to give teachers in the elementary schools the essentials of matter and method for the language work of the four intermediate grades, third to sixth. The topics discussed will include the following: purpose and plan of language study; language environment; relation of language to other subjects; language and character; the teacher of language; importance of oral language; types of oral language lessons; conversation lessons, picture lessons, lessons on stories and poems, memorizing, lessons in usage, word study; the function of written work; incidental grammar of the intermediate grades. Teachers possessing several series of language books and professional works on teaching language, are advised to bring them for reference. Daily, from 8.45 to 9.45. Cabell Hall, Room 2. Text Book.—Hyde's Two-Book Course in English, Book I. 6. Elementary Grammar.—This course will cover the work of the seventh and eighth grades, aiming primarily at giving teachers a deeper, surer knowledge of the subject matter of grammar, with especial emphasis upon the more difficult points.—the abstract noun, the comparison of adjectives, the function of case, the personal pronoun, analysis, and, above all, the verb and the verbals. There will be, in addition, such discussions of methods as will prove most helpful to the class. Those expecting to take this course should bring all the good grammars in their possession for broader reference work. Daily, from 2.30 to 3.30. Cabell Hall, Room 2. Text-Book.—Hyde's Two-Book Course in English, Book II. GEOGRAPHY. Professor Milledge. Miss Haliburton. 1. Primary Geography.—Lessons on uses and forms of water—lesson on rain, study of brook in field work, springs, slopes, hills, and valleys, ponds and lakes, river basins in miniature, rills and gullies, soil—how made, erosion, transportation and sedimentation, deltas, flood-plains, forms of land and water in miniature, direction; weather observation and records—study of clouds, observation of path of sun, study of shadows cast by sun, observation of moon and stars; stories about Indians, Esquimaux, Chinese, Japanese, etc., describing homes, habits, dress, food, etc.; typical animals of the various heat belts; typical vegetation of the various heat belts; nature myths as correlated with geography. Daily, from 8.45 to 9.45. Professor Milledge and Miss Haliburton. Rouss Laboratory, Room 3. 2. Grammar Grade Geography.—General consideration of form and size of the Earth:—directions on earth, formation of soil (illustrated by field work), rainfall, streams and rivers, brook studied in nature, brook basins and divides, erosion and sedimentation observed on excursions, lakes, mountains and valleys, volcanoes, general division of ocean and seashore, general consideration of continents and their relief; latitude and longitude—change of seasons, zones, belts of winds, ocean currents; races of mankind and their distribution—religions of mankind, forms of government; zones of plant life; zones of animal life; North America studied carefully as to physiographic regions, climate, products, trade routes and political divisions; United States and colonies briefly studied similarly to North America; remaining continents briefly studied similarly to North America. The relation of cause and effect, the correlation of arithmetic with geography, the dependence of history upon geography will be especially emphasized. Sand maps will be used and their making illustrated. Chalk modeling of maps and rapid illustration with chalk used throughout. Several excursions for field work will be made, and the whole course will be practical. Daily, from 12.15 to 1.15. Professor Milledge. Rouss Laboratory. MANUAL TRAINING. Professor Crawford. 1. Hand Work for the Elementary Grades.—A comprehensive course in handwork especially adapted to the needs of the elementary grade teacher, or of the supervisor, with problems for each grade, embracing work in paper-weaving, cutting, and folding, native material basketry, clay modelling, pottery, loom construction and rug weaving, knife work, and bent iron. Daily. Mechanical Laboratory. MATHEMATICS. Professor Jenkins. 5. Arithmetic.—This course will treat the following topics: Foundations of arithmetic, history and development of arithmetic, mechanical work, thought work; primary method methods; a graded course; discussion of arithmetic texts; academic work in class; methods in arithmetic. Definite work in the subject will be assigned each day. Daily, from 8.45 to 9.45. Cabell Hall, Room 6. Text-Book.—Colaw and Elwood's Arithmetic. 6. Algebra.—This course will treat the following topics: Foundations of algebra, its bearing on arithmetic, algebraic language; treatment of simple equations, two and more unknown quantities; class work through quadratics. Daily, from 9.45 to 10.45. Cabell Hall, Room 6. Text-Books.—Well's Essentials of Algebra or any other good text. NATURE STUDY. Professor Davis. Miss King. The following topics will be treated in this course: Bird neighbors, 54; insectiverous birds; seed eating birds; birds of prey; the American toad, 196; collecting insects for school use; life in a terrarium; the cabbage butterfly; the grasshopper; the housefly; the tent caterpillar; life in an aquarium; June beetles; mosquitoes and health; honey bees; earth worms; the teeth of animals; osmosis; digestion and absorption; Nature's flying machines; how Nature prepares for winter; rock layers, and other rocks; how Nature forms soils; movements of soils; preserving plants for school use; how plants get up in the world; annual flowering plants, 195; storage of nourishment in seeds; the office of root-hairs on plants; struggles in a tree-top. Substitute lessons: Light relation; cross-pollenizing and self-pollenizing in flowers; relation of season to life history of plant; annual, biennials, and perennials; tasseling and silking of corn; useful weeds, 188; lessons from the strawberry plant, 198. Lessons subject to change. Numbers refer to United States Farmers' Bulletins. Daily, from 3.30 to 4.30. West Range Laboratory. School Gardens.—This course will be very practical, consisting of the actual work in a school garden by a class of children under the supervision of the instructor. Such topics as laying off a garden, with talks on how it should be dug and cultivated and fertilized, what vegetables and what flowers raised which will mature during the school session, the effect of certain insects on those plants for good or for bad, and the various interesting subjects that arise during the process of cultivation, will be treated. The school garden will be easily accessible to students and all are invited to observe the work done. PHYSIOLOGY AND HYGIENE. Professor Maphis. The following topics will be considered: the importance of the subject; the frame-work of the body; the muscles; the digestive apparatus; the circulation; the respiratory system; the skin, hair, nails, and their care; the nervous system; effects of narcotics, alcohol; the special senses; hygiene of the home; hygiene of the school. Daily (after June 29th), from 10.45 to 11.45. Cabell Hall, Room 6. PRIMARY SCHOOL WORK. Miss Haliburton. 1. Model Lessons.—Work with children just beginning school. A class of primary grade children will be organized for the purposes of this course. Lessons in reading, showing the use of the word and sentence method; lessons in phonics, showing, at first, exercises that are separate and distinct from reading; lessons in language, showing the use of Mother Goose melodies, rhymes, stories, etc., aided by dramatization, use of nature study correlated with language; lessons in number. This work with the model school is open for purposes of observation to all teachers in the School of Methods. Those observing should attend the discussions in course 2 outlined below. Daily, from 9.45 to 10.45. Cabell Hall, Room 2. 2. Primary Methods.—The subject matter and methods of teaching in reading, phonics, oral and written language, nature study, and number work will engage the attention in this class. Daily, from 10.45 to 11.45. Cabell Hall, Room 2. READING. 1. The Rational Method in Reading.—Sight reading; eye training; drill on the phonograms; ear training; drill on the blend; combined sight reading and phonetic reading; the uses and value of phonics in reading and spelling will be clearly demonstrated. Special attention will be given to the foundation work for beginners, feasible ways and means of carrying on the work and keeping it well balanced and along every line. Daily, First section from 10.45 to 11.45. Second section from 4.00 to 4.30. Miss Coleman. Cabell Hall, Room 3. Text-Book.—Ward's Rational Method of Reading. SCHOOL MUSIC. Miss Hofer. Mrs. Starke. The courses in this subject emphasize methods of teaching music, with special reference to the needs of kindergartens, primary teachers and those preparing for supervisory work. 2. Music for Kindergarten and Primary Grades.—Beginnings of music for children. The school song as a basis for musical training. (a)—Song as a means of self expression, interpretation and relation to language and phonetics. Training of voice and ear. Correlation with school subjects. Choice and classification. (b)—Expression through rythm; first, as developed in action through the dramatizing of songs, in school games and marches; second, as found in music,—the pulse, accent, analyzing of different time groups by clapping and marking. (c)—Relation of rote song to notation; rythm and pitch as discovered and pictured by the children; first steps in music—reading and writing, sight singing, the use of books. Daily, hours to be arranged. Auditorium. Text-Books.—Modern Music Series, Primer and Book I; song literature. STORY TELLING. Professor Wyche. 1. Classic Stories.—Some great classic tales and their place in education. Hiawatha; Beowulf; Seigfried; Ulysses; King Arthur; folk and fairy tales; Uncle Remus and Southern folk-lore; Bible stories. Daily, from 11.45 to 12.15 (June 19th to July 3d.) 2. The Art of Story Telling.—Origin of story telling and the story-sagaman and minstrel; the story in language, grammar, song, creative work, dramatization, etc.; the formal and expression of the spiritual. How to tell a tale—psychological principles. Daily, from 4.30 to 5.30 (June 19 to July 3d.) Remarks.—Story telling at twilight, on Monday, Wednesday, and Saturday, on North Rotunda steps. Local branch of the National Story Tellers' League will be organized. TEACHERS' TRAINING CLASS. Mrs. M. S. Moffet. Daily, from 8.45 to 1.15. Cabell Hall, Room 5. The purpose of this Class is to afford review work in subject matter to those teachers of elementary schools, preparing for examination. The work is essentially drill work. The instructor will be assisted from time to time by other instructors who are giving courses in similar subjects in the Summer School. 1. Arithmetic.—Cancellation: Review of Fractions: Percentage—three cases; Applications of percentage (profit and loss, trade discount, commission, simple interest); Taxes; Insurance Ratio and Proportion: Practical Problems in Mensaration: Extraction of Square Root. Problems will be assigned each day, to be solved by students. Class discussion of principle involved. 2. English.—Analysis of sentences; phrases; clauses; infinitive participles; use of a word to determine to which part of speech it belongs; combination of groups of sentences in one sentence; parsing. Model forms will be given for analysis of sentences, for diagrams, for parsing. 3. Geography.— (a)—Grand Divisions; correlation and comparison with North America based upon outline for North America. (b)—United States: typical state—Virginia; typical city—Richmond; typical river—James. (c)—General circulation of the air, and rainfall regions of the earth; plants and animals and their distribution; occupations and industries. 4. Civics.— (a)—Virginia Constitution: Fundamental principles of the Bill of Rights; the qualification of voters; the Legislature—its composition and powers; the Executive— qualifications, powers and duties of the Governor; the Judiciary—names of courts and jurisdiction of each; Finance—source of revenue, the levy, apportionment, assessment and collection of taxes, the taxes of corporations, property exempt from taxation; Education—purpose of providing schools, how expenses are met, officers, teachers, pupils. (b)—United States Constitution: Why formed; preamble; departments—legislative, executive, judicial. Method: Topical outlines; correlation and comparison with Virginia Constitution. 5. History.—Discovery and Exploration—conditions in Europe; reasons for establishment of colonies; relation of colonies to mother-country: Intercolonial Wars— French and Indian War especially: War for Independence: The Critical Period and Formation of the Government: Territorial Growth—Mexican War: Slavery and Civil War: Reconstruction Period: Great Inventions and Industrial Development. Method: Topical outlines of each. 6. Virginia History.—Early settlement; John Smith; Charters; Lord Delaware; Governor Dale; House of Burgesses; Growth of Colony; Governor Berkely; Virginia under the Commonwealth; Bacon's Rebellion; Negro Slavery; William and Mary College; Virginia's part in the American Revolution; Virginia' Contributions to the new nation; social and industrial conditions to 1860; Virginia in the Civil War; recent development and improvement. The course in Virginia History will be given in conjunction with the History of the United States. 7. Physiology and Hygiene.—The Framework—bones, shape, size, number, joints, use: Foods—sources, kinds, value, preparation, serving Digestion, teeth, salivary glands, stomach, gastric juice, intestines, juices, absorption, assimilation: Circulation— heart, cavities, valves, arteries, veins, capillaries, blood: Respiration—air passages, lungs, membrane, ventilation in the home and in the schoolroom: Muscles—composition, arrangement, fastenings, use, exercise: Skin—layers, glands, functions: Nervous System—brain, spinal cord, nerves, control of the body: Special senses—eye, shape socket, muscles, care of eye; ear, parts of ear, care of ear; smell, location, nerves, use; taste, use papillae of tongue, nerves of taste, by what affected; touch, common sense, where most delicate, why delicacy of touch is desired: Exercise—indoor forms, outdoor forms, necessity for exercise, proper time, adaptation to individuals and age, proper dress. WRITING. Miss Emens. The purpose of this course is to train the learner to write a free, easy, legible hand and at the same time to help teachers to teach writing well. Practical movement drills, figure drills and speed tests will be given throughout the course. Blackboard writing will receive special attention. The following topics will be discussed: How to interest children in writing; how to teach writing in rural schools; how to teach writing in primary, intermediate and grammar grades; what should be accomplished in each grade? Why teach writing in the grades? Daily, hours to be arranged. (June 18th to July 19th.) OTHER COURSES OPEN TO STUDENTS IN THE SCHOOL OF METHODS. The instruction in the School of Methods is intended to cover every subject required for a First Grade Certificate in Virginia. In order to prevent a duplication of work, those teachers preparing for examination for First Grade Certificate, will be permitted to take the following courses in the University Department without additional cost; First, any one of the following—Agriculture, 1, physics 1, or Geography 3, (Physical); second—History 3 (English); third—History 4 (United States); fourth—History 5 (Civil Government); fifth—Domestic Science 1, 2 and 3; sixth— Physical Training. THE VIRGINIA SUMMER SCHOOL OF ART. FIFTH SESSION. Ten weeks, June 22nd, to August 28 inclusive. F. Graham Cootes, M. A., Founder and Director. Duncan Smith, M. A., Instructor. The Object of this school is to furnish Southern students, at a minimum expense, practical instruction in drawing and painting, according to the methods of the very best New York and Parisian schools, with the additional great advantage of more personal attention than is given at any other art school. The Course is particularly designed for those desirous of making a profession of portrait, landscape and decorative painting, illustrating, cartooning and the designing of posters and advertisements. It will also be of great benefit to teachers and those who are interested in art for their own pleasure. Beginners will receive special attention. No previous experience will be required for entrance to the school. The instruction is entirely individual and adapted to the particular needs and advancement of the student. A Model in Costume poses every morning, except Saturday, in the large studio. The afternoons are devoted to landscape work. Mr. Smith, who conducted the classes most successfully during the session of 1907, has had a great deal of practical experience in Illustration, Portrait Painting, and Decoration, in addition to a long period of study in New York and abroad. For Prospectus giving full particulars and terms, address, F. GRAHAM COOTES, Broadway Arcade Studios, 1947 Broadway, New York, N. Y. SCHEDULE OF COURSES. 8.45-9.45: Biology 1B, C. H. 12. Chemistry 1, West Range Laboratory. English 2 (English Literature), C. H. 4. English 5 (Elementary), C. H. 2. German 1 (Elementary), R. 2. Geography 1 (Primary), R. L. 3. History 4 (United States), R. 3. Latin 1 (Beginners), C. H. 1. Manual Training 2, M. L. 2. Mathematics (Trigonometry), C. H. 8. Mathematics 5 (Arithmetic), C. H. 6. Physics 1, R. L. 1. Psychology, R. 1. 9.45-10.45: Agriculture 2 (High School), W. R. L. Biology 1A (2 hours), C. H. 12. Civil Government, R. 3. Drawing 5, M. L. 1. Education 2 (School Management) C. H. 3. English 1 (Rhetoric), C. H. 4. German 2 (Advanced), R. 2. Latin 4 (Virgil), C. H. 1. Logic, R. 1. Mathematics 1 (Advanced Algebra), C. H. 8. Mathematics 6 (Elementary Algebra), C. H. 6. Primary Work 1, C. H. 2. 10.45-11.45: Education 1 (Educational Psychology), C. H. 3. English 3 (Grammar), C. H. 4. French 1 (Elementary), R. 2. History 3 (English), R. 3. Latin 6 (Horace), C. H. 4. Mathematics 2 (Plane Geometry), C. H. 8. Physics 3, R. L. 1. Physiology, C. H. 6. Philosophy, R. 1. Primary Work 2, C. H. 2. Reading, C. H. 6. Story Telling 1. 11.45-12.15: General Assembly, C. H. Auditorium. 12.15-1.15: Domestic Science 3, M. H. Drawing 1, M. L. 1. Education 4 (Theory and Practice of Teaching), C. H. 3. English 4 (American Literature), C. H. 4. French (Advanced), R. 2. Geography 2 (Grammar Grade), R. L. 3. History 2 (Medieval and Modern), R. 3. Latin 3 (Cicero), C. H. 1. Manual Training 1 (Elementary), M. L. 2. Mathematics 3 (Solid Geometry), C. H. 8. 1.15-2.30: Recess. 2.30-3.30: Agriculture 1 (Elementary), W. R. L. Biology 2A, C. H. 12. Drawing 4, M. L. 1. English 6 (Elementary Grammar), C. H. 2. Geography 3 (Physical), R. L. 3. Latin 5 (Livy), C. H. 1. Manual Training 3, M. L. Physics 4. 3.30-4.30: Biology 2B (2 hours), C. H. 12. Domestic Science 1, M. H. Drawing 2, M. L. 1. Education 3 (High School Problems), C. H. 5. Geography 4 (Commercial), R. L. 3. History 2 (Ancient), C. H. 6. Latin 2 (Caesar), C. H. 1. Nature Study, W. R. L. Reading, C. H. 3. Story Telling 2. 4.30-5.30: Botany, R. Drawing 6, C. H. 4. Education 5 (Round Table Conference), C. H. 5. Gymnastics for Women, F. 5.30: Gymnastics for Men. *C. H.-Cabell Hall; F.-Fayerweather Gymnasium. M.-Mechanical Laboratory; R.-Rotunda; R. L.-Rouss Physical Laboratory; W. R. L.-West Range Laboratory; M. H.-Madison Hall.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INDEX Page. Art 35 Agriculture 12, 13 Biology 13, 14 Board 10, 39 Botany 14, 15 Chemistry 15 Civil Government 23, 34 Courses of Instruction 12 Credit for Work 8, 9, 10 Domestic Science 16 Drawing 16, 17, 30 Education 15, 31, 33 Elementary English 31 English 18, 19, 34 Excursions 7 Fees 11 French 19 General Assembly 7 Geography 20, 31, 32, 34 German 21 Greek 21, 22 High School Conference 8 History 22, 34 Laboratories 6 Latin 23, 24, 25 Lectures 8 Logic 26 Madison Hall 6 Manual Training 26, 32 Mathematics 26, 27, 32, 34 Music 27, 33 Nature Study 32 Philosophy 28 Physical Training 28 Physiology 33, 35 Primary School Work 33 Physics 28, 29 Psychology 29 Railroad Rates 10 Recreation 7 Registration 11 Rural School Week 8 Schedule 36, 37 School Games 28 School Gardens 32 Story Telling 34 Teacher's Training Class 34</field>
      <field name="fulltext">BOARDING HOUSES Below are given some of the names and addresses of persons who will take students to board during the Summer School. NAME ADDRESS No. men wanted No. women wanted Price per wk. 2 in room Price Per wk. 4 in room Price per wk. 1 in room Price per wk. board alone Price per wk. room alone Miss Virginia Bowcock Wertland St. 12 12 $4.00 $4.00 $3.25 Mrs. A. B. Brown 1009 Wertland St. 5.00 4.50 4.00 $2.00 Mrs. Sallie Blanton 1021 W. Main St. 4 16 5.00 4.50 4.00 Mrs. L. J. Carter 900 W. Main St. 12 15 4.00 3.50 3.50 Mrs. B. D. Chandler 1201 W. Main St. 1.50 to 2.00 Miss Pattie J. Daffan 852 W. Main St. 10 30 4.00 3.50 3.00 Miss Kate Douglas 1201 Wertland St. 15 22.50 mo. 25.00 mo. Misses Doswell Chancellor St. 10 or 10 1.50 to 2.00 Mrs. S. E. Gay 208 14th St. 12 15 4.00 3.50 3.50 Miss Kate Grymes 205 14th St. 18 4.50 3.75 4.00 Mrs. M. E. Irvine 1214 Univ. Ave. 8 5.00 4.00 Mrs. R. C. Jones 231 14th St. 6 1.25 to 2.50 Mrs. Thomas S. Jones 1212 Univ. Terrace 8 or 8 5.00 7.00 4.00 Jefferson Park Hotel Near University 30 30 7.00 5.50 8.00 Mrs. James G. Littig Very near University 4 4 7.50 8.00 3.00 Mrs. Jno. H. Moomaw Wertland Ave. 6 or 6 4.00 Miss M. E. McKennie 207 14th St. 10 or 10 1.50 to 3.00 Mrs. E. H. Offley 1122 Wertland St. 8 6 4.50 3.50 3.75 Mrs. E. M. Page Univ. Avenue 30 30 5.50 5 to 7 4.00 Mrs. N. Y. Patteson 1229 W. Main St. 10 20 4.00 3.50 3.50 Mrs. W. H. Perkinson Chancellor St. 18 or 18 6.00 7.00 4.50 Mrs. Thos. L. Preston Preston Heights 6 or 6 5.00 6.00 Mrs. R. L. Rodes 116 14th St. 30 or 30 5.00 4.00 4.00 Mrs. W. R. Reinhart Univ. Avenue 20 20 5.00 4.00 4.00 Mrs. Sam'l Saunders 214 14th St. 20 20 5.00 3.50 3.25 Mrs. W. H. Shields 1225 W. Main St. 40 or 40 4.50 3.25 3.00 Mrs. R. C. A. Sieburg 1106 W. Main St. 10 6 4.00 3.00 4.00 1.50 Mrs. John Stockton Chancellor St. 12 12 5.00 4.50 4.00 Miss B. H. Woodson 12th &amp; Wertland St. 8 17 4.00 3.50 4.00 2.00 Mrs. Wm. S. Woods Madison Lane 15 or 15 5.00 5.00 Mrs. V. T. Yager 228 14th St. 12 5.00 4.50 4.00 Arrangements have also been made to use the Randall building, which is the best dormitory of the University, and contains 50 rooms. This will be used for ladies only, or for married couples. The rooms will be furnished with everything except bed clothing, which must be furnished by the roomers themselves. For everything else including janitor's service, a charge of $3.00 to $4.00 for the term. This is a delightful place to room and the social feature makes it desirable also. The building is in the University grounds. Table board can be secured nearby. Application for rooms in this building should be promptly sent to the Registrar, Prof. Charles G. Maphis. Rooms on East and West Range can be secured for men at the same rates.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RETURN THIS If you expect to attend the University of Virginia Summer School, we shall esteem it a favor if you will fill out the form below and forward it to the "Director of the Summer School, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Virginia. This will not bind you to attend, of course, but it will merely express your present intention and enable us to estimate the probable attendance and make suitable arrangements for accommodation. 1. Name _________________________ 2. Address—Post Office _________________________ Street _________________________ County _________________________ State_________________________ 3. Present occupation _________________________ 4. Courses desired. (Give catalogue title and number). _________________________ _________________________ 5. Where Board is Desired_________________________ 6. What rate do you wish to pay per week for board? _________________________</field>
   </doc>
</add>