<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university of virginia</field>
      <field name="author_text">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2005_Q4_2/uvaBook/tei/z000000119.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240342</field>
      <field name="date_text"/>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:148890</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">A catalogue of the officers and students of the University of Virginia. Seventeenth session, 1840-1841</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">University of Virginia -- Periodicals</field>
      <field name="subject_text">University of Virginia -- Periodicals</field>
      <field name="title_display">A catalogue of the officers and students of the University of Virginia.  Seventeenth session, 1840-1841</field>
      <field name="title_facet">catalogue of the officers and students of the university of virginia</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">catalogue of the officers and students of the university of virginia</field>
      <field name="title_text">A catalogue of the officers and students of the University of Virginia.  Seventeenth session, 1840-1841</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1840</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:148890&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/bin/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:148890&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;serial volume&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;university of virginia&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;A catalogue of the officers and students of the University of Virginia. Seventeenth session, 1840-1841&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;catalogue of the officers and students of the university of virginia&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;A catalogue of the officers and students of the University of Virginia&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1840-1841&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Va.&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;The University&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa call number"&gt;LD5667&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;X004575773&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;o05654199&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;11 p. ; 18-23 cm.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;University of Virginia -- Periodicals&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;A catalogue of the officers and students of the University of Virginia&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1840-1841&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Va.&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2004&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2004 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 36 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">May 1st, 1880. Catalogues of the students attending the early sessions have never before been published. James F. Harrison, Chairman.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">BOARD OF VISITORS. CHAPMAN JOHNSON, Rector. JOSEPH C. CABELL, CHAPMAN JOHNSON, JOHN H. COCKE, THOMAS JEFF. RANDOLPH. JAMES M. MASON. WM. C. RIVES, SAMUEL TAYLOR. Secretary of the Board, FRANK CARR.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">FACULTY AND OFFICERS. Chairman of the Faculty. JOHN A. G. DAVIS (to Nov. 14, 1840.) GESSNER HARRISON. GESSNER HARRISON, Professor of Ancient Languages. GEO. W. BLÆTTERMANN, Professor of Modern Languages. J. J. SYLVESTER, Professor of Mathematics. WM. B. ROGERS, Professor of Natural Philosophy. JOHN P. EMMET, Professor of Chemistry and Mat. Med. GEORGE TUCKER, Professor of Moral Philosophy. HENRY HOWARD, Professor of Physiology, Medicine, Obstetrics and Medical Jurisprudence. JOHN A. G. DAVIS, NAT. P. HOWARD, Professors of Law. JAMES L. CABELL, Professor of Anatomy and Surgery. WILLIAM WERTENBAKER, Librarian and Secretary of the Faculty. WILLIS H. WOODLEY, Proctor. ALEXANDER GARRETT, Bursar. Rev. WM. S. WHITE, Chaplain.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CATALOGUE OF STUDENTS. SEVENTEENTH SESSION.—1840-1841. ABBREVIATIONS. A. L.— Ancient Languages. M. L.— Modern Languages. M.— Mathematics. N. P.— Natural Philosophy. C. E.— Civil Engineer. C.— Chemistry. M. P.— Moral Philosophy. MED.— Medicine. A. &amp;S.— Anatomy &amp;Surgery. NAMES. RESIDENCES. SCHOOLS ATTENDED. SES. Abell, George W. Albemarle co., Va. A L, C, M P, 2 Anderson, Wm. L. Charlottesville, Va. A L, N P, 1 Archer, F. H. Petersburg. Va. LAW, 1 Ashford, A. H. Alabama C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Ashton, Henry King George co., Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Atkinson, Geo. R. Smithfield, Va. M, N P, C, 2 Ayer, L. M., Jr. South Carolina N P, M P, LAW 2 Baldwin, B. J. Alabama A L, N P, 1 Baldwin, James W. Alabama A L, N P, 1 Bankhead, Smith P. Fredericksburg, Va. LAW, 2 Barksdale, Chas. H. Charlotte co., Va. C, M P, LAW, 4 Bagley, Wm. P. Accomack co., Va. LAW, 2 Beazley, Robert S. Greene co., Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Beazley, Wyatt S. Greene co., Va. A L, M, LAW, 1 Beirne, Geo. W. Monroe co., Va, C, MED, A &amp;S, 3 Bond, W. E. North Carolina N P, M P, LAW, 2 Brooke, Wm. H. Essex co., Va. M, C, M P, 2 Browder, James Dinwiddie co., Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Buchanan, Andrew H. North Carolina M L, M, N P, 1 Buckner, C. B. Lynchburg, Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Burnett, B. C. Essex co., Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Byars, William Tennessee C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Bynum, James South Carolina N P, M P, LAW, 1 Campbell, A. M. Amherst co., Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Carr, George Watson Albemarle co., Va. M L, M P, LAW, 2 Caskie, John S. Richmond, Va. A L, M J, M P, LAW, 3 Cazenove, Wm. G. Alexandria, Va. LAW, 1 Chambers, H. C. Alabama N P, A L, M, 2 Chambers, Josiah Louisiana M, N P, LAW, 1 Clarke, Wm. J. Richmond, Va. A L, M, N P, 1 Clay, H. Lawson Alabama N P, C, M P, 3 Clay, J. Withers Alabama N P, M P, LAW, 4 Cole, John Surry co., Va. C, M P, LAW, 1 Coleman, Richard H. Caroline co., Va. A L, M, N P, 1 Compton, John W. Louisiana M L, M, N P, M P, 1 Compton, Leonard G. Louisiana A L, M L, M, 1 Conrad, Lonis L. Philadelphia, Pa. M, C, M P, 1 Conway, George B. University of Va. A L, M, N P, 1 Cooke, Thomas J. Portsmouth, Va. A L, M, N P, 1 Cooke, Wm. M. Portsmouth, Va. A L, M, N P, 1 Cornick, Martin L. Pr. Anne co., Va. N P, C, A &amp;S, M P, 1 Cornick, William T. Pr. Anne co., Va. N P, C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Crouch, J. G. Richmond, Va. A L, M, N P, 1 Dabney, Robert L. Louisa co., Va. A L, M, M P, 2 Davis, Dabney, C. T. University of Va. A L, M, N P, 1 Davis, Eugene University of Va. LAW, 5 Davis, John Staige Univ. of Va. C, MED, A&amp;S, M P, LAW, 4 Dennard, Franklin Alabama LAW, 2 Donnally, A. F. Kanawha co. Va. LAW, 1 Dupré, Lucius L. Louisiana M, N P, M P, 2 Duval, John P. Florida A L, N P, C, 3 Early, J. R. Albemarle co., Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Emmet, C Temple New York C, MED, A &amp;S, 2 Eppes, Richard Pr. George co., Va. A L, M L, M, 1 Eubank, Thomas P. Essex co., Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Eversfield, Charles Pr. George co., Md. C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Flippo, Joseph A. Lancaster co., Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Forney, D. P. Alabama LAW, 2 Galt, Wm. R. Norfolk, Va. A L, M L, M, 1 Gayle, Rees D. Alabama A L, M, N P, 1 Gee, James T. Alabama C, MED, A &amp;S, M P, 3 Gilmer, George N. Alabama N P, C, M P, 2 Gooch, Edwin H. Albemarle co., Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Goss, Ebenezer Albemarle co., Va. M, C, M P, 1 Grantland, F. T. Georgia C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Gray, Charles D. Harrisonburg, Va. C, LAW, 1 Gray, Francis C. University of Va. A L, M L, M, N P, 2 Gray, William Essex co., Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, N P, M P, 1 Hamm, James S. Albemarle co., Va. A L, M, N P, C, 1 Hamner, Wyatt M. Buckingham co., Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 2 Harris, Clement R. Augusta co., Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Harrison, Matthew Loudoun co., Va. A L, M, C, 1 Heath, Richard M. Richmond, Va. A L, M, N P, 1 Hendren, John N. Augusta co., Va. M, N P, C, 2 Henry, Edwin W. Maryland C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Higginbotham, E. G. Albemarle co., Va. A L, M, C, 1 Holland, Joseph A. Georgia C, MED, A &amp;S, 3 Holmes, Martin South Carolina M, A L, M P, 2 Holman, J. B. Alabama M P, LAW, 1 Hope, Robert S. South Carolina M, N P, M P, 1 Howard, B. D. Mississippi LAW, 2 Howard, Hamilton P. University of Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Humphreys, J. C. Mississippi LAW, 1 Hundley, Richard T. Hanouer co., Va. A L, M, C, 1 Hunter, Henry St.G. Richmond, Va. M, N P, C, 1 I'Anson, Wm. H. Petersburg, Va. LAW, 3 Irving, Carter H. Buckingham co., Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Jenkins, William S. Kentucky M L, M, N P, C E, 1 Johnson, D. T. Louisa co., Va. A L, C, M P, C E, 1 Jones, James F. Frederick co., Va. A L, M, N P, M P, 2 Kincaid, William A. South Carolina N P, M P, LAW, 2 Laurens, John South Carolina M L, M, N P, 1 Lay, Henry C. Richmond, Va. A L, M, N P, 2 Leake, Elisha M. Tennessee C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Linton, John A. Washington, D. C. M L, N P, M P, 2 Logan, Henry C. Halifax co., Va. A L, M L, M, 1 McCaw, Robert G. South Carolina M, N P, M P, 1 McKennie, Marcellus University of Va. A L, M, N P, 2 Mann, N. B. Georgia C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Marshall, Hunter H. Charlotte co., Va. N P, C, M P, LAW, 4 Martin, D. W. Kentucky C, MED, A &amp;S, 2 Marye, John L., Jr. Fredericksburg, Va. A L, M, N P, 1 Mason, Lewis E. Southampton co., Va. A L, M, N P, 1 Maury, D. H. Fredericksburg, Va. N P, M P, LAW, 2 Maxwell, A. E. Alabama LAW, 4 Meerbach, F. W. Charlottesville, Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Meriwether, Evan W. Kentucky M, N P, LAW, 1 Michie, Theodore A. Albemarle co., Va. C, MLD, A &amp;S, 1 Michie, Thomas W. Albemarle co., Va. A L, N P, C, M J, 2 Miller, Warwick N. Charlottesville, Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 2 Moore, G. F. Alabama N P, C, M P, 1 Morancy, Francis E. Louisiana C, LAW, 4 Morris, J. C. Missouri LAW, 1 Mosby, Joseph Royal Louisa co., Va. C, M P, LAW, 1 Mullen, James L. North Carolina C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Neblett, William J. Lunenburg co., Va. C, M P, LAW, 3 Norris, Jesse W. South Carolina LAW, 2 Noland, Burr Powell Loudoun co., Va. M L, M, LAW, 1 Noland, R. W. N. Loudoun co., Va. M L, M, N P, 1 Nunn, John Mercer Louisa co., Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Oldham, Samuel Tennessee N P, M P, LAW, 2 O'Neal, William W. Georgia N P, LAW, 1 Orr, James L. South Carolina LAW, 2 Page, Francis W. Albemarle co., Va. M, C, M P, 2 Palmer, William P. Richmond, Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 3 2 Parkhill, Charles C. Florida M L, LAW, 1 Parkhill, John H. Florida M L, LAW, 1 Perret, Louis C. Louisiana C, LAW, M P, 2 Pope, J. W. Tennessee M P, LAW, 2 Preston, Francis Abingdon, Va. M L, N P, C, 1 Preston, Thos. W. Smythe co., Va. M L, LAW, 1 Prince, Joseph H. Sussex co., Va. LAW, 1 Reese, J. Meriwether Georgia M J, M P, LAW, 3 Rice, Benj. H. South Carolina C, LAW, 2 Rives, Francis R. Albemarle co., Va. M, C, LAW, 3 Rixey, J. H. Culpeper co., Va. LAW, 2 Rodes, Tyree Tennessee M, N P, C, 1 Rogers, William G. Albemarle co., Va. M, N P, C, 2 Rogers, William P. Albemarle co., Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Rutland, J. M. South Carolina LAW, 2 Sanders, Paul V. Louisa co., Va. A L, M, C, 2 Scott, Martin P. Fauquier co., Va. M, N P, C, 1 Seaton, Gales Washington, D. C. LAW, 2 Semmes, Joseph G. Washington, Ga. M, N P, C, 1 Shanklin, J. A. South Carolina M, M P, LAW, 3 Shelton, Thomas W. Albemarle co., Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Shepherd, Seth Mathews co., Va. A L, M, C, 1 Simms, William H. Halifax co., Va. M L, LAW, 1 Skinner, Charles H. Hartford, N. C. N P, C, LAW, 1 Somervill, R. B. Tennessee LAW, 1 Spencer, James T. Charlotte co., Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Staples, Samuel G. Patrick co., Va. A L, LAW, 1 Stark, Powhatan B. Norfolk, Va. M, C, M P, 2 Stewart, James D. Mississippi A L, N P, 1 Stewart, John E. Sussex co., Va. N P, C, C E, 2 Stokes, Henry Lunenburg co., Va. N P, M P, 2 Stokes, John W. South Carolina LAW, 3 Stubbs, W. W. South Carolina C, MED, A &amp;S, 2 Sutton, David King William co., Va. 2 Sydnor, Henry A. Pittsylvania co., Va. A L, M L, N P, 1 Tabb, John P. Gloucester co., Va. LAW, 3 Taliaferro, William F. Westmoreland co., Va. A L, M L, M, 1 Taylor, Charles S. Clarke co., Va. M, N P, C, M P, 1 Taylor, T. B. Florida C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Thompson, John R. Richmond, Va. A L, M, N P, 1 Thornton, James D. Cumberland co., Va. M, N P, M P, 3 Townes, Edward Danville, Va. N P, C, 2 Trent, William R. Richmond, Va. A L, M, N P, 1 Trice, James A. Richmond, Va. A L, M, N P, 1 Tutwiler, Thomas H. Fluvanna co., Va. M, M P, LAW, 1 Washington, John A. Mt. Vernon, Va. N P, C, LAW, 3 Watkins, John C. Nottoway co., Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 2 White, Benj. F. Missouri LAW, 1 Whitehead, A. P. Alabama A L, M L, M, C, 2 Whitmore, Samuel H. Petersburg, Va. A L, M, N P, 1 Wingfield, Marcus A. Georgia M, N P, C, 1 Wingfield, M. P. Georgia M, N P, C, 1 Withers, Robert E. Campbell co., Va. C, MED, A &amp;S, 1 Wright, George T. Essex co., Va. M, N P, M P, 1</field>
      <field name="fulltext">17 NUMBERS IN THE SEVERAL SCHOOLS. Ancient Languages 46 Modern Languages 21 Mathematics 66 Natural Philosophy 72 Chemistry 86 Medicine 45 Anatomy and Surgery 43 Moral Philosophy 46 Law 58 Civil Engineering 4</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RECAPITULATION. Virginia 109 Alabama 15 South Carolina 14 Georgia 8 Tennessee 6 Louisiana 6 North Carolina 4 Florida 4 Kentucky 3 Maryland 2 Missouri 2 Mississippi 2 District of Columbia 2 New York 1 Pennsylvania 1 179</field>
   </doc>
</add>