<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University of Virginia, Library</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University of Virginia, Library</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university of virginia library</field>
      <field name="author_text">University of Virginia, Library</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2006_01/uvaBook/tei/z000000538.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240342</field>
      <field name="date_text"/>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:181330</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">First Annual Report of the Archivist, Library of the University of Virginia, for the Year 1930-31. [Vol. 1</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Archives -- Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Manuscripts -- United States</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Virginia -- History -- Sources</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Archives -- Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Manuscripts -- United States</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Virginia -- History -- Sources</field>
      <field name="title_display">First Annual Report of the Archivist, Library of the University of Virginia, for the Year 1930-31.  [Vol. 1</field>
      <field name="title_facet">first annual report of the archivist library of the university of virginia for the year 193031</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">first annual report of the archivist library of the university of virginia for the year 1930 31</field>
      <field name="title_text">First Annual Report of the Archivist, Library of the University of Virginia, for the Year 1930-31.  [Vol. 1</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1930</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:181330&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:181330&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;serial volume&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;University of Virginia, Library&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;university of virginia, library&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;First Annual Report of the Archivist, Library of the University of Virginia, for the Year 1930-31. [Vol. 1&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;first annual report of the archivist, library of the university of virginia, for the year 1930-31&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia, Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;First Annual Report of the Archivist, Library of the University of Virginia, for the Year 1930-31&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="volume"&gt;[Vol. 1]&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="LC call number"&gt;CD3560 .V5 v.1-10 1930-1940 &amp;amp; Index v.1&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;X000450245&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;o04107376&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;16 p. : map ; 23 cm.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Archives -- Virginia&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Manuscripts -- United States&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Virginia -- History -- Sources&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covplace&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;United States&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covplace&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covplace&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covplace&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;First Annual Report of the Archivist, Library of the University of Virginia, for the Year 1930-31&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="volume"&gt;1&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2005&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2005 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 53 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">First Annual Report of the Archivist, Library of the University of Virginia, for the Year 1930-31 A YEAR ago, as a preliminary step to beginning the inventory of manuscript materials in Virginia, the newly appointed archivist interviewed a number of historians and librarians in the State to discuss the general situation regarding depositories, public and semipublic, and the possibility of gaining access to private collections. An outline of the various sources of historical materials was subsequently drawn up1 1. A copy of this outline, "State Survey of Historical Materials" is appended to this report, page 8. and submitted to these same individuals and others within and outside the State for criticism. Their comments were helpful and encouraging and it is gratifying to find that, at the end of the year's work, the outline, with a few additions, has measured up to actual conditions as found in widely separated counties in the State. The general plan of the first year's work and some account of progress during the first few months were presented in a paper2 2. "Survey and Collection of Manuscripts in Virginia," published in University of Virginia Alumni News, Mar.-Apr. 1931, pp. 151-154; appended to the present report, page 10. which the archivist read at the annual meeting of the American Historical Association, in Boston, Dec. 31, 1930. The substance of that paper may be used as the starting point for the present discussion. Emphasis is placed upon the survey rather than upon the collection of materials, since the former is more fundamental to the promotion of research in its larger aspects and the latter follows logically from the inventory. The collection of materials for the University Library, treated at the end of the report, is not to be minimized in importance, but it is believed that manuscript collecting, carried on in Santa Claus fashion without any direction of activity except accumulation, is neither scientific nor productive of the most beneficial results in promoting research. To carry on the survey by counties seemed to offer certain advantages of approach, and it was decided "to choose from each [geographic] section of the State . . . a county whose history, being of considerable note, has prompted some preservation of sources and some historical writing."3 3. "Survey and Collection of Manuscripts in Virginia," page 12. In pursuance of this plan the following counties were visited:4 4. See map on page 3. In the Piedmont—Albemarle County. In the Shenandoah Valley—Frederick County In Tidewater—Essex County. In Southside Virginia—Pittsylvania County. In Southwestern Virginia—Wythe County. On the Eastern Shore—Northampton. Two advantages were gained from this procedure: first, the satisfaction of sampling, as it were, the historical sources in various localities far removed and comparing their condition from the viewpoint of availability for research; second (equally important), the acquaintance of interested people in all sections of the State with this project of the University. Indeed, contacts with leading citizens in the counties have been of untold assistance in getting the desired information with a minimum of delay in dispersing the news of the work to neighboring communities. Inventories, in more or less detail, have already been made of material in county archives in a number of states, but in no case, it may be asserted, was the survey carried beyond the official government records. The present survey includes, in addition to county, city, and state archives, the manuscript records of such widely divergent organizations as business houses, lodges, hospitals, banks, social clubs, churches, etc.—representing every phase of economic and social life. In the first paper written on the project no limit was set to the historical period to be covered, but as the immense scope and complexity of the task have become more apparent, it has seemed advisable to restrict the survey, so far as private and unofficial public records are concerned, to the period before 1900. It is evident, however, that such a line should not be so arbitrary as to exclude manuscripts of especial significance on the 20th century. For recent records the problem is, in large measure, one of accessibility or of preservation by new organizations which seldom project their existence into the future with a view of appreciating what will some day be an interesting historical background worthy of authenticating by their original papers. The diversity of activities recorded in the files of the inventory is revealed in the list of Danville, Va. (excluding the city archives): American national bank &amp; trust co., Records, 1909-date. Averett college (Bapt.), Minutes of Board of trustees, 1860-99, 1900-04, 1904-21, etc.; Ledger, 1903-10, 1914-15, etc. The Bee (daily newspaper), 1900-15 (incompl.), 1915-31. Beth Sholem congregation, Proceedings, 1893-1903. B'nai B'rith. Randolph lodge, no. 304, I.O.B.B., Minutes, 1878-83, 1883-95. Carter, J. T., sons (foundry), Day book, 1908-09; Ledger, 1896-1900, etc. *Counties to be surveyed in 1931-32 are, in most cases, those from which several other counties were subsequently formed. Chamber of commerce, Records, 1920-31. Commercial bank &amp; trust co., Records, 1884-1931. Dan Valley (flour mills), Records, 1894-1931. Danville military institute, Minutes of Board of directors, 1922-31, etc. Danville tobacco association, Minutes, 1869-1931. Dibrell brothers (tobacco dealers), Records, 1873-1904 (incompl.); 1904-31. Epiphany, Church of the (Prot. Episc.), Vestry book of Camden parish, 18591931; Parish register, 1841-1931. First Baptist church, Minutes, 1834-52, 1852-69, 1887-1911, etc. First Presbyterian church, Session minutes, 1827-49, 1850-80, 1880-1912, etc. Freemasons. Euclid chapter, Royal arch masons, No. 15, Minutes, 1853-84, 1884date. Kaufman (J. J.) clothing co., Expense book, 1879-1913; Salary account book, 1899-1916. Ladies benevolent society, Minutes, 1884-92 (incl. Constitution of society); predecessor to Memorial hospital. Etc., etc. In almost every instance the records are kept at the headquarters of the organization, although frequently the secretary or a similar officer may have custody of the papers and neglect to take proper care of them. Of this, more will be said later in connection with the collection of manuscripts. In rural sections, which predominate in Virginia, the records are less diversified in character than those listed above, but the time required to locate them is considerably greater in amount. It happens that the counties visited this year include three cities with rather extensive records, viz., Charlottesville. Winchester, and Danville, which have added considerable detail to the compilation and have required more time than was originally expected. Similarly, the work in the State Archives Department, the bulk of which is completed, was retarded by crowded conditions, lack of any satisfactory catalogue, and want of a systematic arrangement of the manuscripts. Even with the aid of the Calendar5 5. J. P. Kennedy, Calendar of Transcripts, Including the Annual Report of the Department of Archives and History (Richmond, 1905). published in 1905, it is doubtful whether a wholly accurate list of this valuable material can be compiled. The same difficulty must be met when, at some later time, the manuscripts in the Virginia Historical Society and in the Confederate Museum are listed. Newspapers were, of course, included in the original plan of the survey and, as the excerpt from the Danville material implies, they are being listed under the city or town where they were published. To facilitate this phase of the work a questionnaire6 6. A copy of this questionnaire is appended to the present report, page 9. was sent to every newspaper editor in Virginia, to ascertain how complete are the files of each paper (and of any antedating the present journals) in the publisher's office. Enquiry was also made concerning old or duplicate files which the editor might be willing to place in the University or a similar depository, for research work. This questionnaire yielded about a thirty per cent return in replies, which, though none too large, was more than we expected. This information has reduced somewhat the task as a whole. Since our ultimate aim is to publish the entire inventory, we are considering the advisability of issuing, as a separate volume, the list of newspapers, indicating the location of the files and of single copies or scattered numbers. This volume could be prepared for publication long before the rest of the survey. In the course of the archivist's travels throughout the State he made a point of visiting the colleges en route in order to list their records and, at the same time, to interest the officials in the University's project. The additional publicity gained thereby will, it is hoped, instill into an increasing body of citizens a new appreciation for historical records. In a few cases, in fact, the custodians of school records have taken steps to put their own collections in such shape that they will be available for research as well as merely safe from destruction. As indicated above, the collection of manuscripts for the University Library goes hand in hand with the inventory and can be more satisfactorily accomplished thereby. The beginning of a systematic effort to build up a collection of original historical materials was described in the archivist's printed paper,7 7. "Survey and Collection of Manuscripts in Virginia," pages 13-14. and there is every reason to expect that research in the social sciences will be stimulated by this accumulation of manuscripts, more especially since they are catalogued and scientifically classified in the Virginia Room of the Library. In a sense this work gathers momentum as it proceeds, for the acquisition of one body of material frequently provides a clue to another, and some individuals who contribute their manuscripts find themselves interested in turning up others and acting as voluntary agents for the University. This situation is the more encouraging since the Library, with almost no funds for purchase, has depended largely upon the good will and generous support of the people. Some owners of manuscripts have been attracted by the proposal of placing their papers on deposit in the Library where they are safe and subject to recall by the owners at any time. Among the original materials acquired this year are several groups of farm account books, from both the ante bellum period and the latter decades of the nineteenth century. One set of these, for example, from Albemarle County, throws light upon the raising of thoroughbred horses after the Civil War. From several counties have come the record books of general country stores, one series of which covers most of the period since 1900 and is of special interest because this type of mercantile business is rapidly disappearing before the chain store and the large city establishments now serving the rural communities by truck. Records of business houses include also some scattered ledgers of a Danville hardware company, a Charlottesville newspaper, a Wytheville wagon and machinery repair shop, and the entire records (books, letter files, vouchers, etc.), of a wholesale produce company of southwestern Virginia, 1901-26. The John L. Hurt Papers from Pittsylvania County, consisting of several hundred letters, treat of some aspects of political and social life in the State since 1880, and contain several autographed letters of Virginia governors. Eighteenth century manuscript material still on the market or obtainable for the asking is quite rare, and the same may be said for early nineteenth century papers, a few of which have been collected. The only item of importance before 1800 acquired by the Library is a doctor's account book from Essex County for the year 1787. Even Civil War letters have ceased to be plentiful, except where a hitherto untouched collection of manuscripts may be brought to light. Ante bellum and Civil War newspapers are likewise at a premium. The questionnaire to newspaper editors8 8. See below, p. 9. resulted in the presentation of a few miscellaneous numbers to the Library; and gifts from other individuals have built up a fairly unbroken file of Richmond papers since the 'seventies.9 9. A recent purchase includes a file of a Staunton paper and one of the Central Presbyterian, organ of the Southern Presbyterian Church, during the 'sixties and 'seventies. Parenthetically it may be remarked that the opportunity to gather original published material, incident to the manuscripts, has not been overlooked. Annual reports of corporations and associations, catalogues of schools and colleges, city and county directories, are among the most valuable of these sources, nor have rare books and pamphlets, memoirs and historical sketches, been regarded as unimportant. When the initial steps of the project were taken and the suggestions of librarians in other institutions were sought, the desire of the University to promote a co-operative spirit in the collection of manuscripts was clearly expressed. With other libraries active in this work, the necessity of guarding against any harsh competition was strongly felt. The University has shown its good will by stressing first the preservation of historical materials regardless of where they are to be deposited. We have co-operated with the Virginia Baptist Historical Society by informing the librarian of the location of early minute books of Baptist congregations, while he in turn has facilitated the work of the archivist. The discovery that most of the Methodist congregations have neglected their records and that the church has no uniform policy regarding them, has prompted the archivist to discuss the question with a number of ministers and with Dr. Blackwell, President of Randolph-Macon College at Ashland, Va., with the hope that the church at its next annual conference may provide a depository (Randolph-Macon has been proposed) for the old records of Methodism in Virginia. During the time spent in Frederick County, several items discovered concerning the county and Winchester, the county seat, were directed into the collections of the new Winchester Historical Society. We are confident that in the long run this attitude of co-operation in collecting will encourage a wholesome atmosphere in the preservation of materials and will promote very decidedly our survey throughout the State. Obviously a year's work constitutes only a beginning in the development of this project, but we believe that the programme for the future is fairly definite. Enough has been done to justify in the minds of the University administration the support of the survey; and upon the recommendation of the late President Alderman and with the concurrence of Dr. Wilson Gee, Director of the Institute for Research in the Social Sciences, the Institute will finance the major part of the project during 1931-32, with the balance made up from the budget of the Library. It is hoped that in another year a regular appropriation can be secured to see the work to completion. Estimating that twelve counties can be completed per year (now that the work is well started) we are figuring on seven years more to finish. Of course, if the archivist can be given assistance, the time required will be shortened considerably. Questions of this nature, however, have not yet been discussed in detail. In conclusion, the archivist desires to express, on behalf of the University of Virginia, and particularly of the University Library and the Institute for Research in the Social Sciences, their appreciation for the grant from the Carnegie Corporation, made upon the recommendation of the joint committee of the American Council of Learned Societies and the Social Science Research Council. It is sincerely hoped that the present survey will be a real factor in furthering research in the social sciences in Virginia and in suggesting, perhaps, activity of a similar sort in other states. Lester J. Cappon, Archivist. 1 July, 1931.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Appendix A. State Survey of Historical Materials 1. Official manuscripts of the Commonwealth of Virginia. Materials in State Library (supplementary to calendars and checklists already published). Materials in various State departments. 2. Records in county court houses. Possibly in cooperation with work of State Archives Department; the accessibility and arrangement of this material, in many cases in wretched condition, will probably determine the extent of the survey. 3. Records in municipal buildings on Virginia cities. Little of this material has been published and its importance has doubtless been overshadowed by the historical precedence of county records and because urban development is comparatively recent. 4. Manuscript collections in colleges and universities. The desire of some institutions to publish their own lists may make it advisable to limit this survey to only a general record of what these libraries contain. 5. Manuscripts in public libraries. These are doubtless few in number but should not be overlooked. 6. Virginia manuscripts in the Library of Congress. This list may supplement what has already been published. 7. Collections of local societies. Such as the Virginia Historical Society; the Confederate Museum; Battle Abbey; the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities; the Fauquier Historical Society; Chambers of Commerce; local museums, etc. 8. Records of religious organizations, state and local. The secretary of the local or district organization usually has at least a partial record of the church for that area. Some churches have valuable records. 9. Newspapers of the State. The various newspaper companies keep files of their papers which in some cases may be better than those in libraries. The latter might be listed also. 10. Private collections of manuscripts (owned by individuals). These may be accessible to research students under certain conditions. 11. Manuscripts and records of business firms. 12. A bibliography of lists and calendars of Virginia materials already in existence.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Appendix B. 20 April, 1931. Dear Sir: The Library of the University of Virginia is making an inventory of original historical records throughout the State, to find out exactly what manuscripts and first-hand printed records have been preserved by public and private organizations and by individuals as well. The first problem in research work is the location of sources of information. Since newspaper files are among the most valuable of our historical materials, we are desirous of finding out to what extent they have been kept intact in newspaper offices and whether they may be made accessible there for research work. We should greatly appreciate your answering the following questions on this paper and returning the same to us at your earliest convenience: 1. What are the name and the date of founding of your newspaper? 2. How far back does your present file of the paper extend? Give exact date, if possible. 3. Is this file complete, or nearly complete, or relatively broken (with only scattered numbers)? 4. How many bound volumes are in this file and for what period? 5. Have you any files antedating your present paper? If so, state name of paper and dates covered, how complete, whether any bound volumes. 6. Are you willing to make your files accessible at your office for use by research students and scholars? 7. Would you be willing to place any of your old files or duplicates of recent issues in the University Library or in a similar depository where they would be safely kept and made readily available for historical research? Thanking you, I am Very truly yours, Lester J. Cappon, Archivist.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Appendix C. Survey and Collection of Manuscripts in Virginia The pride of Virginia in her more than three centuries of history is among the first impressions of the traveller who crosses her border, if, indeed, he has not been already apprised of the fact. The Virginian of today, whether his fund of historical information be profound or meager, retains an inborn devotion to the great men of his State; and, although he may have been educated in part from northern (perhaps even New England!) textbooks, his interest in the good ship Susan Constant and the settlement at Jamestown quite overshadows his regard for the Mayflower and events at Plymouth. And, one must admit, Jamestown was first! The preservation of Virginia's historical records has been an oft recurring theme. During the past hundred years there has been periodic activity of one kind and another in this direction. In the eighteen-thirties the Virginia Historical Society began to collect manuscripts and publish documents and papers in its Collections. The records of the colonial and state governments, after being moved from place to place and seriously depleted by fire and the ravages of war, were lodged in the Capitol, and from this accumulation was compiled the Calendar of Virginia State Papers, in eleven volumes, 1875-93. With the reorganization of the State Library in 1903, many of the state documents were transferred to the Archives Department, where they were made accessible for research. Meanwhile some of the colleges had begun to publish historical papers. In July, 1892, was issued the first number of the William and Mary Quarterly Historical Magazine, and the following year the Virginia Historical Society began to publish the Virginia Magazine of History and Biography, as a continuation of its earlier Collections. Through the "Public Archives Commission of the American Historical Association," W. G. Stanard made a report on Virginia archives in 1903, which directed attention in some detail to both state and county archives and to Virginia manuscripts in the Library of Congress. In 1905, with the aid of the Carnegie Institute in Washington, D. C., the State Library published a calendar of its transcripts from the British Public Record Office. This work included also a list of manuscript collections and a Catalogue of bound colonial and state papers in the State Archives Department and in the office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth. Until recent years, however, the interest in the preservation and publication of manuscripts in Virginia has been confined for the most part to official state records or to genealogy. Without minimizing the value and significance of the work done along these lines, it is obvious that these sources, from which former scholars wrote political history, fall short of the demands of the new school of economic and social historians who prize, in addition, the letters or diary of the every-day American, and such ephemeral stuff as the fragmentary minutes of a temperance society or the recipe of a housewife. The very nature of these records has led to a reemphasis of local history, crushed for years by its own weight of dull, unorganized chronology compiled by many an untrained antiquarian. While these secondary accounts are sometimes our only surviving sources of information, there is often a wealth of original material either untouched or in need of re-interpretation. Virginia as a part of the "New South", beset by new economic and social problems and deeply conscious of her tradition, has become an inviting field for historical and sociological research. As a result, the collecting of manuscripts is being promoted today by a number of southern universities and learned societies. The University of Virginia, while active in collecting, is giving primary consideration to a survey of manuscript materials and archives throughout the State. In consulting printed sources the present-day student may be said to enjoy the comforts of the "bibliographical age," so numerous are the comprehensive guides and finding-lists for a wide variety of subjects and collections of historical writings. In the field of manuscripts, however, he is limited to a few incomplete calendars or lists of papers in certain libraries or archives, while, for the most part, he must research haphazardly for a clue to the whereabouts of unpublished material on his particular subject. The time which he can ill afford to spend in tracking down the manuscripts means an appreciable loss in productive scholarship; nor is the situation ameliorated by the fact that as yet no satisfactory scientific method of classifying manuscripts has been developed beyond a chronological arrangement. The need, therefore, of a guide to manuscripts in Virginia, which was accentuated by the work of the Institute for Research in the Social Sciences of the University of Virginia during the past four years, led to the project of a detailed inventory of manuscript materials. Financed by the Carnegie Corporation, on the recommendation of a joint committee of the American Council of Learned Societies and the Social Science Research Council, the undertaking is sponsored by the University Library, which appointed the present writer to take charge of the project. In contrast to the collecting of manuscripts which has much of the fascination of detective work, including a baffling element of uncertainty, the survey is essentially a matter-of-fact inventory. No kind of material is excluded because it is not "historical" and no particular period of Virginia history is given preference. Anything up to the present may qualify. Nevertheless, like a bibliography, such an inventory must be primarily practical and usable. Therefore two fundamental questions are kept constantly in mind: (1) What material is extant? and (2) Is it accessible or will it be made accessible for research? The natural geographic divisions of Virginia suggested a plan of initiating the survey. This was to choose from each section of the state (viz., Tidewater, the Piedmont, the Shenandoah Valley, etc.) a county whose history, being of considerable note, has prompted some preservation of sources and some historical writing. Thus, for example, Albemarle County where the University is situated was chosen for the Piedmont region; Frederick County with its court at Winchester for the lower Shenandoah Valley. The simplest method of approach is to examine in detail the archives in the courthouse. These, in addition to the usual files of wills, deeds, and orders, invariably contain records no longer used in the daily business of the clerk and hence relegated to some obscure corner, but material of great value to the research student. A card index of all the archives is made so that their content and degree of completeness can be ascertained without delay. Similarly an inventory is prepared of city or town records in the county, a class of material only recently appreciated for its historical value because county functions have predominated during most of Virginia's development. Meanwhile, lists of business houses, churches and lodges, libraries and schools, banks, public utilities, and other organizations are drawn up. The responsible officer in each company or society is interviewed in order to learn whether the original records or books are preserved, what their substance is, what period they cover, and which ones will be made accessible for research. In this connection, it has been encouraging to find a general willingness to cooperate among a wide variety of individuals and organizations, even among business firms which might be expected to refuse because of conditions of competition. Experience has shown that this information must be obtained by personal contact with those concerned; correspondence nets only a small percentage of replies, most of which are unsatisfactory, and lessens the opportunity to follow up clues to other manuscript collections. Since newspapers are closely akin to manuscripts as original material, all files in the state are being listed, not only in libraries, but also in publishers' offices and those accessible in private hands as well. Historic houses and remains, in which Virginia abounds, are also listed by county. Their value as historical evidence is being increasingly recognized, and public feeling in behalf of th preservation of these "ancient landmarks" needs cultivation. The recording of these data is facilitated by the metal tablets which were set up along the highways a few years ago by the State Commission on Conservation and Development, to mark historic sites and buildings. Another large body of manuscript material is that in the State archives in Richmond, already mentioned. So far as the State Library is concerned, the problem of an inventory is relatively simple, for it consists chiefly in checking the archives against the Calendar published in 1905, in order to bring that record up to date. The absence of a catalogue of the private manuscripts in the Archives Department and the need of a guide to county records, original and photostat, recently acquired, complicate the task, but the difficulties are far from insuperable. Furthermore, all these manuscripts are accessible. However, under the control of such state offices as the treasurer, corporation commission, etc., there remain invaluable records, many of them stored in the capitol, their exact content unknown and their accessibility difficult. How they may be rendered usable is still undetermined. The question of an inventory of manuscripts in private hands is a delicate one. Assuming it were possible to compile a fairly complete list of individuals or families who possess such papers, one is confronted with the practical difficulty of accessibility. Few such manuscripts are arranged in any order for actual use and few are in any condition to withstand the wear and tear of handling. Even granting the willingness of the owner to allow the papers to be examined, there would be the inevitable embarrassment of exposure to requests at any time, because the existence of the papers was made public. It is this phase of the survey that is linked most intimately with the collecting of manuscripts, mentioned above, for deposit in archives and research libraries. Virginia has always had a considerable group of individuals deeply concerned with the preservation of her records. Yet, by and large, pride in the history of one's state does not necessarily produce a reverence for her historical memorials, and Virginians, like their compatriots in other states, need educating in this regard. Family papers, cherished by one member of the household and utterly unappreciated by another, are ever in danger of destruction or of dispersion within or outside the state; and the transitory character of such manuscripts renders an inventory of their whereabouts extremely inaccurate. Akin to this situation is the condition of many church records. Protestant churches in particular, and especially those with little centralized authority, neglect their records, which are frequently left in the hands of individual officers rather than being deposited in the church or in a fire-proof vault; and when that official passes on, chance alone determines the fate of the records. In the case of business firms, the practical difficulty of preserving the obsolete books in a safe place endangers their permanence. If they have been kept, sentimental reasons have probably prevailed and the books lie in some neglected corner. Business records of recent years have even less chance of survival because the loose-leaf files now in vogue are less conveniently preserved when removed from the file cases, and many firms keep only current files. The need of spirited activity in the collecting and preserving of manuscript in Virginia is unquestionably as great to-day as it was a generation or a century ago. As early as 1664 a legislative committee was appointed to report on the condition of the colonial archives, "since it appears that there hath been a great neglect in keeping the records in this country." This same spirit, intensified by the sale of "Virginiana" to outside collectors and dealers, was influential in establishing the Department of Archives and History in Richmond. A year ago the University of Virginia, having provided a specially equipped room for the safe-keeping and cataloguing of manuscripts, issued a broadside, offering "aid in the preservation, the study, the interpretation, and the publication of these memorials of Virginia's social, industrial, political, and intellectual life . . . to-day she can offer for these memorials a storehouse, fireproof and secure, a staff of eager and able young scholars from her faculty and graduate school prepared to classify, study, and interpret these materials for the cultural history of the Old Dominion. . . . Let [the owners of manuscripts] give if they can give outright; or else make our university the depository for safekeeping and scientific interpretation of this important material for historical research." The response from people throughout the State to this appeal has been most encouraging, and the promotion of this work along with the inventory will, it is hoped, aid materially in developing research in Virginia. Many persons prefer, of course, to keep their papers. The University is carrying on a sort of missionary work to prevail upon these individuals in any case to store their manuscripts in fireproof places. If the historical value of such records fails in its appeal to the average person, he may find in them even material satisfaction of the most surprising kind. Such was the experience of the owner of an abandoned mill and general store in the hill country of Albemarle County. Hearing that some of the old books of the establishment were still extant, the writer called on the owner to inquire about them. The man, with only a vague idea that some of the papers might be there, led the way to the old store and unlocked the door. From a confusion of worn out furniture, tools, and rubbish, he seized at random a rough box containing some account books and ledgers which we proceeded to examine. As I turned a few pages of one dated 1860-61, my eye lighted upon a ten-dollar greenback. "Probably old Confederate money," he remarked casually, but as I picked it up I found that not only was it United States currency, issued thirty to forty years ago, but that there were ten tens instead of one. "A hundred dollars," he half whispered, recounting the bills. "D'you suppose it's still good?" As I turned another page or two, there lay another hundred in tens. "Say, I guess we'd better look through all these old books pretty carefully," he exclaimed. The excitement was intensified when the next pages revealed yet another hundred in tens. His eyes fairly popped out of his head and he was so dumbfounded that he relied completely upon my count. The old book had proved so fruitful thus far that we almost expected more. And we were not disappointed, for well on towards the middle were hidden three more groups of one hundred each in tens and fives, and finally what might have been interpreted as incomplete, a pack of thirty dollars. You may be sure the other account books were examined with care and although they yielded no treasure, in one corner of the old box was a little green wad which proved to be another five, making a total of $635. The man, still rather dazed, with the pack of bills gripped in one hand, now proceeded to reproach his family for their carelessness and poor economy. Suddenly he looked at his bulging fist and exclaimed, "Say, was there 500 or 600 here? . . . Oh well, I guess a hundred more or less don't matter when it comes this way." Perhaps there is more than one moral to this tale. At any rate, to me it suggests that I might be warranted in charging a fair commission on all "deposit books" recovered! Since other libraries in Virginia, such as the College of William and Mary and the Winchester Historical Society, are also active in the collecting of manuscripts, the University is emphasizing the cooperative spirit which it desires to uphold in this enterprise. Competitive activity in advancing the cause of research is a questionable procedure at best, and already the advantage of co-operation is evident in the work in Virginia. The task is a large one, slow of development at first but destined, it would seem, to bear increasing fruit from year to year, as the work is extended from county to county. The collecting of material is certain to intensify the interest in southern as well as Virginia history, and the inventory should serve as a much needed guide to manuscripts actually available. Perhaps also, the project may suggest a method of procedure in the recording of manuscripts in other states. Lester J. Cappon, Archivist.</field>
   </doc>
</add>