<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University of Virginia, Library</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University of Virginia, Library</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university of virginia library</field>
      <field name="author_text">University of Virginia, Library</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1940's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2005_Q4_1/uvaBook/tei/b004123185.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240342</field>
      <field name="date_text">1945</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:126011</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">1828 Catalogue of the Library of the University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">University of Virginia. -- Library -- Catalogs</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Library catalogs -- Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_text">University of Virginia. -- Library -- Catalogs</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Library catalogs -- Virginia</field>
      <field name="title_display">1828 Catalogue of the Library of the University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="title_facet">1828 catalogue of the library of the university of virginia</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">1828 catalogue of the library of the university of virginia</field>
      <field name="title_text">1828 Catalogue of the Library of the University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="year_display">1945</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1945</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1945</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:126011&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:126011&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;University of Virginia, Library&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;university of virginia, library&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;1828 Catalogue of the Library of the University of Virginia&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;1828 catalogue of the library of the university of virginia&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1945&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1945&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia, Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="contributor" form="persname" role="Introduction"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Peden, William Harwood&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;1828 Catalogue of the Library of the University of Virginia&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Va.&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for the Alderman Library of the University of</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Virginia&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1945&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="LC call number"&gt;Z1009 .V57 no. 6&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;X004123185&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;o02714680&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;[2], vi, 114 p. ; 21 cm.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;University of Virginia. -- Library -- Catalogs&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Library catalogs -- Virginia&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;On spine: University of Virginia library catalogue--1828.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;"Lithoprinted."&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Facsimile has t.-p.: Catalogue of the library of the University of Virginia. Arranged alphabetically under different heads, with the number and size of the volumes of each work, and its edition specified. Also, a notice of such donations of books as have been made to the University. Charlottesville, Va., Gilmer, Davis &amp;amp; co., 1828.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covplace&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covplace&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;1828 Catalogue of the Library of the University of Virginia&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2005&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;©2005 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 599 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INTRODUCTION1 1 I wish to thank Mr. Jack Dalton, Miss Louise Savage, and Mr. Harry Clemons of the Alderman Library of the University of Virginia for their generous assistance. In the spring of 1824, Thomas Jefferson, then eighty-one years of age, began compiling the catalogue for the library of the University of Virginia which is the basis of this publication. The University, his long-cherished dream, was fast becoming an actuality, and Jefferson as Rector had gone so far as to announce publicly that his "bantling of forty years' growth and nursing" would open its doors to its first student body the following February. Jefferson, who had been enjoying an extremely active and fruitful retirement since his withdrawal from the "hated occupation" of politics, was well qualified for this task. From youth until extreme old age he had possessed almost a "canine appetite for reading" and could say, without exaggeration, "Books are indeed with me a necessary of life." For over half a century he had been a tireless book collector. He had gathered together a personal library described by a contemporary as being for "its selection, rarity, and intrinsic value . . . beyond all price."2 2 Jefferson had long desired to leave his University a great library, and his major collection had been gathered together with this end in view. The University of Virginia, however, never received this library. It was sold to Congress to replace the national library— itself to a large degree the result of Jefferson's efforts during the early years of his Presidency—destroyed in 1814 when British troops sacked Washington. Jefferson's first library had been destroyed by fire in 1770. His third and last was sold at public auction in 1829. And almost until the day of his death he remained a collector. Characteristically, the next to the last entry in his personal account book records the payment for a recently-acquired volume. But Jefferson was more than a collector and reader of books. Decades before beginning his catalogue for the University of Virginia, he had carefully catalogued his private library and had formulated a method of book classification (based on subject matter rather than size or alphabetical arrangement) successful enough to remain in use at the Library of Congress and at the University of Virginia for almost a century. It must have been with a feeling of pleasure and anticipation that the aged man began his labors, devoting to his catalogue from four hours to the entire day for many weeks. Yet the project proved to be onerous beyond his expectations. By August of 1824 he was weary of the task, "not yet in sight of the end," and asked aid from his old friend ex-President Madison, who obliged him by preparing the chapter on books of divinity.3 3 Among those who also assisted Jefferson by supplying data in specialized fields was George Ticknor. By late September, however, the work was completed, and on the twenty-fourth of that month Jefferson had the pleasure of sending Madison the catalogue of 6,860 volumes, "complete except the alphabet," calculated to cost $24,076. The whereabouts of this original manuscript is unknown; it seems logical, however, to assume that it was one of the casualties of the fire of October 27, 1895, which destroyed more than two-thirds of the University of Virginia collection. Fortunately, though, it is possible to reconstruct with considerable accuracy its scope and contents since it was described in an article written before the fire4 4 This article, "Our Library," was written by F. W. Page, University of Virginia librarian at the time of the fire. It is dated September 10, 1895, less than two months before the fire which destroyed the Rotunda, Jefferson-designed library building. Subsequent historians of the University such as P. A. Bruce and J. S. Patton discuss this manuscript but seem to be quoting from Page rather than from the manuscript itself. and because the University of Virginia possesses a manuscript copy of it apparently differing from the original only in minor and inconsequential details.5 5 "President Jefferson's Catalogue of Books For the University of Virginia Library 1825" is in the hand of Jefferson's granddaughter, Virginia Randolph, and is also dated by Jefferson, June 3, 1825. It adheres to the identical method of subdivision into forty-two chapters. In addition to occasional and minor differences in word order, this manuscript copy contains slight variations in some chapter titles. Chapter 14, for example, reads "Technical Arts" rather than the "Technics" of the original as recorded by Page. The original manuscript, like all the catalogues which Jefferson prepared, was based on Francis Bacon's system of classifying knowledge into the three major divisions of Memory, Reason, and Imagination.6 6 Perhaps the best single statement embodying Jefferson's ideas concerning book classification is his letter of May 7, 1815, to George Watterston, newly-appointed Librarian of Congress. Jefferson, of course, had evolved this method long before he explained it to Watterston. His library at Monticello had for years been arranged according to a similar classification scheme, and had been carefully catalogued by 1783. As Jefferson pointed out, the system was surprisingly elastic and could easily be modified or altered to suit the needs of each collector. These, subsequently, Jefferson applied to History, Philosophy, and Fine Arts. They, in turn, were subdivided into forty-two chapters. The first major division, that of History, consisted of sixteen chapters, one through five being classified as civil, and six through sixteen as physical, history. Philosophy included twelve chapters, subdivided as mathematical and moral philosophy. Fine Arts contained thirteen chapters ranging from architecture to criticism and philology. A forty-second chapter, "polygraphical," completed the group. This method of arranging his books according to subject rather than to size appealed to him, Jefferson said, "because of the peculiar satisfaction, when we wish to consider a particular [field], of seeing at a glance the books which have been written on it, and selecting those from which we effect most readily the information we seek."7 7 Jefferson's original manuscript also included eleven explanatory statements such as the following, setting forth the factors determining the books he had selected: "Nothing of mere amusement should lumber a public library." These statements do not appear in the manuscript copy by Virginia Randolph. Examination of any of Jefferson's catalogues makes immediately apparent the fact that — and herein lies a weakness in his plan — such an arrangement allows for too large a number of vague, uncertain, or haphazard classifications.8 8 For example, in the printed catalogue of Jefferson's library which was sold to Congress, chapter 15, "Technical Arts," numbers among its items Hayes's Modern Bookkeeping, The London and Country Brewer, Locke on Education, Hoyle's Games, Rice's Art of Reading, Calson's Specimens of Printing, and Parmentier's Resultats de la Fabrication des Sirops et des Conserves de Raisins. It is not remarkable that a library the size of the Library of Congress should ultimately be forced to abandon such a system. Rather, the striking point is that the system, despite its limitations, was as efficient and as practicable as it proved to be. It was not until several months after Jefferson's death that the Faculty of the University of Virginia instituted plans for revising and printing his catalogue. William Wertenbaker, who had succeeded the University's first librarian, John V. Kean, was engaged to prepare the catalogue for publication under the supervision of Professors Key and Dunglison. His was not an easy task. The proposed publication was intended to be an up-to-date catalogue of the University of Virginia rather than a mere copy of Jefferson's catalogue for the University of Virginia. At one time, the Faculty moved that whenever possible the original prices of the books be included; fulfilling this resolution proved to be infeasible and it was later discarded. Bibliographical data such as place and date of publication had to be supplied. The Faculty resolved that the titles of books in foreign languages be published in English "with suitable contractions which language they belong to." A list of the Library's donors had to be supplied, and all contributions or acquisitions not appearing in Jefferson's manuscript had to be included. The University's collection had to be carefully checked to see which books originally specified in Jefferson's catalogue had not as yet been obtained. It is hardly to be wondered at that at one time the Chairman of the Faculty moved to suspend temporarily the whole project. The professors and the librarian persevered, however, and early in 1828 the catalogue was ready for the printer, and was published in the same year by Gilmer, Davis, &amp; Co., in Charlottesville. In its printed form, this catalogue differs materially from the manuscript. Jefferson's division into three main classifications of History, Philosophy, and Fine Arts, though inherent, has been formally discarded. The original forty-two chapters are decreased to twenty-nine. The last chapter in the printed catalogue, headed "Miscellaneous, Including Poetry, Rhetoric, Education, etc.," takes the place of chapters thirty-one through forty-two in the manuscript. Similarly, other subjects are altered or expanded. For example, in the manuscript, the field of medicine is relegated to two chapters; in the printed form, these are expanded to eleven chapters. As revised for publication by William Wertenbaker, each of these reorganized chapters is alphabetically arranged. In Jefferson's manuscript, on the other hand, the chapter arrangement was not alphabetical but was "sometimes analytical, sometimes chronological, and sometimes a combination of both." This rearrangement simplifies the catalogue and makes it much more usable. Few people would dispute Jefferson's own remark, made several years earlier, "I think it possible that the alphabetical arrangement may be more convenient to readers generally." The printed and manuscript forms differ further in the amount of bibliographical data accompanying each entry. With minor exceptions, each item in the manuscript — as is true of all of Jefferson's manuscript catalogues — consisted of: name of author, last name first, but not alphabetically arranged; title; number of volumes; size of volumes; viz.: Price's review of the principal questions in morals—1 8.9 9 The place and date of publication frequently accompany entries in this catalogue or have been added to them, in one or two cases by Jefferson himself. In rare cases the language in which the book is printed is included. In the printed form, however, each entry usually consists of the following data: name of author, last name first, alphabetically arranged; title; abbreviation of language, if other than English, in which book is written; plàce of publication; date of publication; number of volumes; size of volumes; viz.: Carnot's theory of transversals, fr. paris, 1806, 1 4. Other differences exist. As recommended by the Faculty, titles of foreign books are translated and printed in English. A list of donors and their individual gifts is included, and the titles, in addition, are incorporated in the body of the catalogue. Occasionally, the catalogue is cross-indexed, and a supplement as well as a sketchy subject-index have been added. Finally, of course, not every item listed in Jefferson's manuscript appears in the printed version and, conversely, the latter contains frequent items not appearing in the original. Like Francis Bacon, whom he greatly admired, Thomas Jefferson was an intellectual whose mind had ranged widely and comprehended greatly. This catalogue of the library of the University of Virginia serves to illuminate our understanding both of the man and the times in which he lived.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CATALOGUE OF THE LIBRARY OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. ARRANGED ALPHABETICALLY UNDER DIFFERENT HEADS, WITH THE NUMBER AND SIZE OF THE VOLUMES OF EACH WORK, AND ITS EDITION SPECIFIED. ALSO, NOTICE OF SUCH DONATIONS OF BOOKS AS HAVE BEEN MADE TO THE UNIVERSITY. PUBLISHED BY GILMER, DAVIS, &amp; CO CHARLOTTESVILLE, VA. 1828.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCHOOL OF ANCIENT LANGUAGES. CHAPTER I. Vols. Size. Adelung's Mithridates, Ger. Berlin, 1806 to 1807. 5 8 Adelung's Mithridates, Ger. Berlin, 1806 to 1807. 4 8 Aelianus, Gr. Gronovius, Berlin, 3 4 Aeschylus in English by Potter, London, 1 8 Aeschylus in English by Butler, Cambridge, 1809. 8 8 Aeschylus in English by Schutz, Oxford, 1810. 2 8 Aeschines Socraticus, Gr. &amp; Lat. Clericus, Amsterdam, 1711. 1 8 Aesopus, Hauptmann, Gr. &amp; Lat. Leipsig, 1 8 Aesopus, Fables, Gr. Schneider, Leipsig, 1810, 1 8 Ainsworth's Lat. &amp; Eng. Dictionary, Carey, London, 1823. 1 4 Alciphron, Epistles, Wagner, Gr. Leipsig, 1798. 2 8 Ammianus Marcellinus, Ernestius, Lat. Leipsig, 1773, 1 8 Ammianus Marcellinus, Gronovius, Lat. Leyden, 1693, 1 4 Anacharsis' Travels, Eng. London, 1794, 7 8 Anacharsis' Maps, London, 1794. 1 4 Anacreon, Barnes, Gr. &amp; Lat. Cambridge, 1721. 1 8 Anecdota Grœca, Villoison, Gr. Venice, 1770. 1 4 Antient monuments of Italy, Italian, Florence, 1810, 1 f Antoninus in English, by Thompson, London, 1747, 1 8 Antoninus, Itinerary, Lat. Gale, London, 1709, 1 4 Antoninus' Works, Gr. &amp; Lat. Schultz, Sleswick, 1802, 1 8 Anthologia, Gr. Jacobs, Leipsig, 1794, 13 8 Appianus, Variorum, Gr. &amp; Lat. Amsterdam, 1670. 2 8 Apollodorus, Heyne, Gr. Gottingen, 1803, 2 8 Apollonius Rhodius, Shaw, Gr &amp; Lat. Oxford, 1779. 2 8 Apollonius, Epistles, Lubinus, 1 12 Apollonius, Lexicon Homeric, Paris, 1793, 1 4 Appuleius—Oudendorp, Lat. Paris, 1786, 1 4 Aratus, Phænomena—Buhle, Gr. &amp; Lat. 1793, 2 8 Arbuthnot on Ancient coins, London, 1754, 1 4 Aristophanes—Invernizius &amp; Beck, Gr. Leipsig, 1794, 11 8 Aristophanes in part translated by Mitchell, London, 1826. 2 8 Aristophanes in part translated by Brunck. Gr. Oxford, 1811, 4 8 Aristophanica, Porson, Dobree, Cambridge, 1820, 1 8 Aristophanes, Lexicon to, by Sanxay, Oxford, 1811, 1 8 Aristophanes, Clouds, Herman, Gr. Leipsig, 1799, 1 8 Aristoteles Works—Buhle, Gr. Bipont, 1791, 5 8 Aristoteles Politics—Schneider, Gr. Frankfort on the Oder, 2 8 Aristoteles Poetics—Eng. Twining, London, 1812, 2 8 Aristoteles Works, Gr. &amp; Lat. Paris, 1654, 4 f Aristoteles Ethics and Politics—Gillies, London, 1804, 2 8 Aristaenetus Abreschius, Gr. London, 1804, 1 8 Arrianus' Anabasis, Blancard, Gr. &amp; Lat. Amsterdam, 1668, 1 8 Arrianus' Tactica, Blancard, Gr. &amp; Lat. Amsterdam, 1683, 1 8 Athenæus, Casaubon, Gr. &amp; Lat. Leyden, 1612, 1 f Athenæus, Schweighaeuser, Gr. Strasburg, 1801, 14 8 Athenæus, Schaefer, Gr. Leipsig, 1796, 3 8 Athenian Letters, Hardwicke, 2 4 Athenian minor Orators, Bekker, Gr. Berlin, 1823, 3 8 Authors various, on the Latin Language, Lat. not. var. 1 4 Authors various, on the lives of the Emperors, Lat. Schrevelius, Leyden, 1661, 1 8 Ausonius' Variorum, Lat. Amsterdam, 1671, 1 8 Aurelius Victor, Arntzenius, Lat. 1733, 1 8 Aurelius Victor, Gruner, Lat. Erlangen, 1787, 1 12 Babrius Fables, Gr. Berger, Munich, 1816, 1 12 Bridault, customs of the Romans, Fr. Paris, 1754, 2 12 Brucker, History of Philosophy, 6 4 Budœus on the AS. Lat. 1 8 Budœus' commentary on the Greek Language, Lat. 1 f Buttmann's Greek Grammar, Everett, Boston, 1823, 1 8 Byzantine historians complete, Gr. Venice, 1729, 23 f Cæsar, Oudendorp, Lat. 1737, 2 4 Callimachus, Ernestius, Gr. Leipsig, 1774, 1 12 Callimachus, Spanlieim, Gr. &amp; Lat. Utrecht, 1697, 2 8 Calaber Quintus, De Pauw, Gr. Leyden, 1734, 1 f Calepinus Lat. Lexicon, 1 f Calpurnius, Beck, Leipsig, 1803, 1 12 Cambridge Classical Examinations, Cambridge, Eng. 1 8 Catullus, Tibullus and Propertius, Lat. Paris, 1685, 1 4 Cebes table of, Greek, Frankfort, 1807, 1 4 Chariton, Chœrea and Callirrhoe. Gr. Leipsig, 1780, 1 8 Chompre's Mythological Dictionary, Fr. Paris, 1801, 1 8 Cicero—Verburgius, Lat. 2 f Cicero—Brutus, Topica, &amp;c. Lat. 1 8 Cicero—Art of Oratory, Lat. Oxford, 1814, 1 8 Cicero—Letters by Melmorth, Edinburgh, 1808, 5 12 Cicero—Letters to Atticus, in Lat. and Fr. by Mongault Paris, 1803, 5 8 Cicero—Ad Familiares by Prevost, Lat. &amp; Fr. Paris, 1801, 7 8 Cicero's Life by Middleton, Boston, 1818, 3 8 Cicero's Otions, Eng. by Guthrie, London, 1778. 3 8 Cicero's Works, Ernestius, Lat. Boston, 1815, 20 8 Cicero's Notes on by Ernestius, Lat. Halle, 1816, 2 8 Cicero's Letters to by Atticus, Grœvius, Lat. Amsterdam, 1684, 6 8 Cicero's Orations—Grœvius, Amsterdam, 1695, 6 8 Cicero's De Officiis, Lat. 1 12 Cicero's Key to, yb Ernestius, Lat. Amsterdam, 1818, 1 8 Claudianus, Burmann, Lat. 1 4 Claudianus, Koenig, Lat. Gottingen, 1808. 1 8 Cleveland (Ch: D.) Epitome of Grecian Antiquities, Boston, 1827. 1 8 Cluverius' Italy and Germany, Lat. 2 f Cluverius' Introduction to Geography, Lat. Leyden, 1624, 1 4 Cluverius' Geography, Leovard, 1641, 1 4 Coluthus Lennep, Gr. Leovard, 1747, 1 8 Conciones, from Greek authors, Oxford, 1815 1 8 Conciones, from Latin authors, Oxford, 1820, 1 8 Conon and Parthenius, Kanne, Gr. Gottingen, 1798, 1 12 Constantinus Lexicon, Gr Lyons, 1637, 1 f Cooper's Latin and English Lexicon, London, 1578, 1 4 Cragius Ripensis, on the Lacedæmonian Republic, Lat. Leyden, 1670, 1 8 Curtius Quintus, Snakenborgius, Lat. Lyons, 1724, 1 4 Dammius, Lexicon to Homer and Pindar, Berlin, 1765, 1 4 Dammius, Lexicon to Homer and Pindar, Glasgow, 1824, 1 4 D'Anville, account of Ancient Gaul, Fr. Paris, 1760, 1 4 Demosthenes and Aeschines, Gr. &amp; Lat. Wolff, Francfort, 1604, 1 f Demosthenes &amp; Aeschines in Fr. by Auger, Paris, 1794, 6 8 Demosthenes in English, by Leland, London, 1802, 2 8 Decrees of the Romans in favor of the Jews, Lat. Leipsig, 1763, 1 8 Devarius on the particles of the Greek Language, Lat. Leipsig, 1793, 1 8 Dictys Cretensis, Delphin, Lat. Edinburgh, 1 4 Diodorus Siceliotes, Gr. &amp; Lat. Amsterdam, 1746, 2 f Diodorus Siceliotes, Gr. Bipont, 1807. 11 8 Dionysius Halicarnassensis, Gr. &amp; Lat. London 1704, 2 f Dionysius Halicarnassensis, Gr. Leipsig, 1774, 6 8 Dionysius Periegetes, Gr. &amp; Lat Oxford, 1710, 1 8 Dion Cassius, Epitome by Xiphilinus, Lat. Paris, 1551, 1 4 Dion Cassius, Stephens, Gr. &amp; Lat. 1 f Dogenes Laertius, Meibomius, Gr. &amp; Lat. Amsterdam. 2 4 Dornavius Ampitheatrum, Lat. 1 f Du Cange, Glosssary for the Greek writers of the middle and lower ages, Lyons 2 Eichhorn Ancient History, Lat. Leipsig, 1811, 2 8 Epicurus' life, by Gassendi, Lat. Leipsig, 1811, 1 4 Epictetus Gr. &amp; Lat. Berhelius, Leipsig, 1683, 1 8 Epictetus Cebes Porphyrius, Gr. &amp; Lat. Cambridge, 1655, 1 8 Epictetus in Eng. by Mrs. Carter, London, 1807, 2 8 Epictetus Schweighæuser, Gr. Leipsig, 1799, 6 8 Epictetus Heyne, Gr. Leipsig, 1783, 1 8 Erasmus, Apophthegms (see case E. 576) Lat. 1535 1 8 Erasmus, Dialogues, Lat. Variorum, Leyden, 1729, 1 8 Epigrams Gr. by Johnson, Eton, 1822, 1 12 Etymologicum Magnum, Sturgius, Gr. Leipsig, 1818, 1 4 Etymologicum Magnum, Sylburgius, Gr. Leipsig, 1816, 1 4 Euripides, Beck Gr. &amp; Lat. Leipsig, 1799, 3 4 Euripides, Hippolytus, Monk, Gr. Cambridge, 1813, 1 8 Euripides, Alcestis, Same Gr. Cambridge, 1816, 1 8 Euripides, in Eng. by Potter, Oxford, 1823, 2 8 Eutropius, Verhêyk, Lat. Leyden, 1761, 1 8 Eustathius, Ismenia and Ismene,—Teucherus Gr. &amp; Lat. Leipsig, 1792, 1 12 Faber, Thesaurus, Lat. Frankfort, 1749, 2 f Fabricius' Bibliotheca, Latina, or account of the Latin writers, Leipsig, 1773 2 8 Fabricius Bibliotheca Græca, or account of the Gr. writers Hamburg, 1705, 13 4 Fables Greek, author unknown, Hamburg, 1745, 1 8 Facciolati, Latin Lexicon, Padua, 1745, 4 f Ferguson's Rome, Edinburgh, 1799, 5 8 Flaccus Valerius, Lat. Burmann, Edinburgh, 1799. 1 4 Florus, Lat. Beger, 1 f Florus, Lat. Duker, Leyden, 1722, 1 8 Florus, Lat. Duker, Leyden, 1744, 1 8 Frontinus, Lat. Oudendorp, Leyden, 1731, 1 8 Fronto, edition of lately discovered writings, Maio, Frankfort, 1816, 1 8 Gellius Aulus, Gronovius, Lat. Frankfort, 1816, 1 4 Geopic writers (agriculture, &amp;c.) Gr. &amp; Lat. Niclas, Leipsig, 1781, 3 8 Gibbon's Roman Empire, Dublin, 1789, 6 8 Gibbon's Roman Empire, London, 1821, 12 8 Gildas Epistle, translated into Eng. London, 1638, 1 12 Gillies History of the World, London, 1807, 2 4 Gillies History of the World, Philadelphia, 1809, 3 8 Gillies History of Greece, New York, 1814, 4 8 Gradus ad Parnassum, Lat. London, 1819, 1 8 Greek Minor Poets, Gaisford, Oxford, 1814, 4 8 Grotius on the Goths and Vandals, Lat. Amsterdam, 1665, 1 8 Grammarians Latin, Putschius, Lat. Hanover, 1605, 2 4 Hachenberg's Gr. Grammar, Hartford, 1822, 1 8 Hecatæus &amp;c. Creuzer, Lat. Heidelberg, 1806, 1 8 Hederic Lexicon Greek, Leipsig, 1722, 1 8 Hederic Lexicon Greek, London, 1816, 1 4 Heliodorus—Coray, Gr. Paris, 1804, 2 8 Hermann on Greek metre, Glasgow, 1817, 1 8 Herodianus, Gr. &amp; Lat. Oxford, 1678, 1 8 Herodotus—Wesseling Gr. &amp; Lat. Amsterdam, 1763, 1 f Herodotus, Lexicon to Schweighæuser, London, 1824, 1 8 Hesiodus, Gr. Clericus, Amsterdam, 1701 1 8 Hesychius, Lexicon, Gr. Leipsig, 1792, 1 8 History, Universal, Ancient, London, 1799, 18 8 Hooke's Roman History, London, 1823 6 8 Homerus, Works, Gr. &amp; Lat. Bnes Cambridge, 1711, 2 4 Homerus, Ilias—Villoison, Gr. Venics 1788, 1 f Homerus, Works, Gr. &amp; Lat. 1606 1 8 Homerus, Life, by Blackwell, London, 1786, 1 8 Homerus, Ilias—Heyne, Gr. London, 1802 9 8 Homerus, same translated by Pope, London. 1817, 3 8 Homerus, Odyssey translated by Pope, London, 1817, 2 8 Homerus, Ilias—Clark, Gr. London, 1806, 2 8 Homerus, Complete Works, Lat. &amp; Gr. Clark &amp; Ernesti, Leipsig, 1759, 5 8 Homeric Poems, Gr. P. Knight, London, 1820, 1 4 Homeric Poems, description of the plain of Troy, Leipsig, 1814, 1 8 Hoogeven Doctrine of te Gr. Particles, Lat. Schutz, Glasgow, 1818, 1 8 Horatius—Bentley, Lat. Amsterdam, 1713, 1 4 Horatius—Bentley Lat. Reutlingen, 1814, 2 8 Horatius—Bond, Leyden, 1670, 1 8 Horatius—Lat. &amp; Fr. Dacier, Amsterdam, 1755, 8 12 Horatius—Minellius, Lat. Leyden, 1744, 1 12 Horatius—For the use of the Charter house school, London, 1822, 1 8 Horatius—Gesner, Lat. London, 1823, 1 8 Horatius—Delphin, Lat. London, 1823, 1 8 Horatius—Hunter, Lat. St. Andrews, 1797, 1 12 Humphrey's Montfaucon, London, 1721, 7 f Jacob's Greek Reader, Everett, Boston, 1825, 1 8 Jones' Eng. &amp; Gr. Lexicon, London, 1825, 1 8 Josephus translated by Whiston, London, 1820, 4 8 Isocrates, Gr. &amp; Lat. Rouen, 1652, 1 8 Isocrates. Gr. &amp; Lat. Battie, London, 1749, 2 8 Isocrates. Gr. &amp; Lat. Battie, Cambridge, 1729, 2 8 Isocrates. Gr. &amp; Lat. Battie, Paris, 1807, 2 8 Isocrates. in French by Auger, Paris, 1781, 3 8 Italy before the dominion of the Romans—Italian, by Micali, Florence, 1810, 4 8 Justinus, Delphin, Lat. Edinburgh, 1814, 1 8 Justinus, Lat. Variorum, Leyden, 1719, 1 8 Juvenalis, Lat. Henninius, Utrecht, 1685, 1 4 Juvenalis &amp; Persius in Eng. by Gifford, London, 1817, 2 8 Juvenalis and Persius, Lat Delphin, London, 1823, 1 8 Juvenalis and Persius, Lat Schrevelius, Leyden, 1674, 1 8 Kennets Roman Antiquities, Philadelphia, 1822, 1 8 Lambe Ancient history, Fr. Paris, 1757, 1 8 Lempriere's Classical Dictionary, (Anthon) New York, 1825, 1 8 Lennep, Greek Etymology, Lat. Nagel, Utrecht, 1808, 1 8 Libanius, Wolff, Gr. &amp; Lat. Amsterdam, 1738, 1 f Libanius, Reiske, Gr. Altenburgh, 1791, 3 8 Livius, Crevier, Lat. Paris, 1742, 6 4 Livius, Drakenborch, Lat. Oxford, 1800, 6 12 Livius Commentaries on by Rupert, Lat. Gottingen, 2 8 Longinus—Toup, Gr. Oxford, 1778, 1 8 Longinus—translated by Smith, London, 1819, 1 8 Lucretius Delphin, Lat. Paris, 1680, 1 4 Lucretius aylor, Lat. London, 1824, 1 4 Lucretius Fr. and Lat Paris, 1768. 2 8 Lucianus, Hemsterhusius, Gr. &amp; Lat. Amsterdam, 1743. 4 4 Lucianus, Dialogues in Fr. &amp; Gr. Gail, 1 4 Lucianus, Seheder Gr. Magdeburg, 1801, 2 8 Lucanus, Bentley, Lat. Glas 1816. 1 8 Lucanus Ocellus in Fr. by D'Argens, Utrecht, 1762. 1 12 Lycophron—Potter, Gr. and Lat. Oxford, 1697. 1 4 Lysias and Isocrates Eng. by Gillies. 1 4 Lysias Orations Gr. Taylor, London, 1739, 1 4 Lysias in French by Auger, Paris 1783, 1 8 Macrobius—Leyden, 1670, 1 8 Macquer, Roman History, Fr. Paris, 1 12 Manilius, Pome on Astronomy, Lat. Paris, 1786, Martialis. Delphin. Lat. Paris, 1680. 1 4 Martialis, Lat Bipont. 1784. 2 8 Matthiae's Greek Grammar, Bloomfield, London, 1784. 2 8 Matthiae's Greek Grammar, Abridged London, 1822 1 12 Maximus Tyrius in French translated from the Greek by Combes Dounous Paris, 802. 1 8 Maximus Valerius. Torrenius Lat. Lede, 1720. 1 4 Maximus Valerius, Helsrecht Lat. Lede. 1799, 1 8 Maltby's edition of Morell's Thesaurus, London, 1824. 1 4 Mela, Gronovius Lat. Leyden, 1722. 1 8 Menander and Philemon, Gr. Clericus, Amsterdam, 1709. 1 8 Meursius Glossary of corrupted and barbarous Greek words Leyden, 1614. 1 4 Micali see Italia. Millot, Antient History, Fr. Paris. 1819. 4 12 Milner's Greek Grammar London. 1819. 1 8 Minucius Felix, Lat. Gronovius Leyden, 1709, 1 8 B Mitford's History of Greece, Boston, 1823, 8 8 Moeris Atticista, Pierson, Gr. Leyden, 1759, 1 8 Mithridates. see Adelung. Nicephorus, Byzantine history—Petavius, Paris, 1616, 1 8 Nizolius, Lexicon for Cicero, 1795, 1 f Nepos Cornelius—Delphin, Lat. Paris, 1675. 1 4 Nepos Cornelius—Wetzel, Lat. Liegnitz, 1801, 1 12 Ocellus Lucanus, see Lucanus—(D. 427), Gr. &amp; Lat. Berlin, 1762. 1 12 Oppianus—Schneider, Gr. Leipsig; 1813. 1 8 Orations of Andocides, Lycurgus, &amp;c. Fr. by Auger, Paris, 1782, 1 8 Orellius, Collection of Epistles, Gr. 1 8 Orphic Poems—Hermann, Gr. Leipsig, 1805, 1 8 Orpheus—Gesner. Gr. &amp; Lat: Leipsig, 1746. 1 1 Ovidius—Burmann Lat. Amsterdam, 1727, 4 4 Ovidius—Burmann Metam, Delphin, Lat. London, 1825, 1 8 Ovidius—Burmann by Professor Joy of New York, 1823, 1 8 Ovidius—Burmann Minellius, Lat. Rotterdam, 1697, 1 18 Ovidius—Burmann Variorum, Lat. Amsterdam, 1702. 3 8 Paterculus—Burmann, Lat. Leyden, 1719, 1 8 Patavinus. Universal Geography, Lat. 1797, 1 4 Pausanias—Facius, Gr. Leipsig, 1794, 4 8 Pausanias—Kuhn, Gr. &amp; Lat, 1696. 1 f Perizonius, Ægyptian antiquities, Lat. Utrecht, 1736, 2 8 Perizonius, Babylonian antiquities, Lat. Utrecht, 1736, 2 8 Perizonius, Babylonian Lat. Leyden, 1711, 2 8 Petit. laws of Athens, Gr. &amp; Lat. Leyden, 1742, 1 f Persius—Koenig, Lat. gen, 1803, 1 8 Petronius Arbiter, Lat Bipont, 1790, 1 8 Phaedrus—Burmann, Gr. &amp; Lat. Utrecht, 1709, 1 4 Phaedrus—Burmann, Lat. Amsterdam, 1698, 1 1 Phalaris, Epistles, Lat. Lennep et Valcknaer, Groningen, 1717, 1 4 Philostratus, Gr. &amp; Lat. Leipsig, 1719, 1 f Photius, Lexicon—Porson, Gr. Cambridge, 1822, 2 8 Pindarus—Heyne, Gr. Gottingen, 1798, 3 8 Pindarus—Heyne, Gr. Gottingen, 1798, 3 8 Pindaric Lexicon—Dammius by Huntingford, London, 1814, 1 8 Plato's works, Gr. Bipont, 1781, 12 8 Plato's works, Gr. &amp; Lat. 1 f Plato, Scholia on, Gr. &amp; Lat. Ruhnken, Leyden, 1806, 1 8 Platonic Lexicon by Timœus—Rubnken, 1641, 1 8 Plautus, Pareus, Lat. Frankfort, 1641, 1 8 Plautus, Variorum, Lat. Leyden, 1664, 1 8 Plautus, Delphin, Lat. Paris, 1717, 2 4 Plinius, Epistles &amp; Panegyric, Gesnet Lat. Leipsig, 1805, 1 8 Plutarchus—Zosimadi, Gr. Paris, 1809—14, 6 8 Plutarchus in Eng. by Dryden, &amp;c. London, 1770, 8 12 Plutarchus in works, Gr. &amp; Lat. Paris, 1624, 2 f Poets, Minor Latin —Var. &amp; Burmann, Lede, 1731, 2 4 Pollux, Julius, Onomasticon, Hemsterhusius, Gr. &amp; Lat. Amsterdam, 1 f Pollux History, Gr. &amp; Lat. Leipsig, 1792, 1 8 Polybius—Folard, Fr. Amsterdam, 1753, 7 8 Polybius—Gronovius, Gr. &amp; Lat. 1670, 3 8 Polybius —in Eng. by Hampton, Oxford; 1823, 2 8 Polyænus—Casaubon, Gr. &amp; Lat. Leyden, 1791, 1 8 Polyænus—Zosimadi, Gr. Paris, 1809, 1 8 Porphyrius, on abstinence, Gr. &amp; Lat. Utrecht, 1767, 1 4 Port Royal, Lat. Grammar, London, 1816, 2 8 Porson's Adversaria, Gr. Cambridge, 1812, 1 8 Potter's Antiquities of Greece, Edinburgh, 1824, 2 8 Procopius, History, Lat. Lyons, 1624, 1 f Propertius—Lachmann, Lat. Leipsig, 1816, 1 8 Prudentius—Heinsius, Lat. Cologn, 1750, 1 8 Quintilianus—Burmann, Lat. Leyden, 1720, 3 4 Quintilianus—Guthrie, Eng. London, 1756, 2 8 Quintilianus—Institutions—Rollin, Lat. Paris, 1808, 2 12 Quintilianus—Institutions—Rollin, Lat. Paris, 1629, 1 8 Raleigh's History of the World—London, 1 f Raoul Rochette—Greek antiquities of the Cimmerian Bosporus, Paris 1812, 1 8 Richer, History of the Emperors, Fr. Paris, 1755, 2 12 Rollin, complete works, Fr. Paris, 1807, 60 8 Rollin, Atlas. 1 4 Roman minor historians, Eutropius, &amp;c. Bipont. 1 8 Russell's Ancient Europe, Philadelphia, 1801, 2 8 Rufus, Breviarium, Lat. Munich, 1815, 1 8 Sallustius—Cortius, Lat. Leipsig, 1744, 1 4 Sallustius—Delphin, Lat. 1770. 1 4 Sallustius —in Eng. by Murphy, London, 1807, 1 8 Sanctius' Minerva, Lat. Amsterdam, 1 8 Sappho's Poems, Gr. Volger, Leipsig, 1810, 1 8 Scapula, Gr. Lexicon, Bailey and Major, London, 1820, 1 4 Scapula, Lexicon, Basle, 1579, 1 f Scheller's Lat. Grammar—Walker, London, 1825, 2 8 Segur, Universal History, Fr. Paris, 1821, 10 8 Seneca's Works with notes of various commentators, Lat. 1652, 1 f Seneca's Works by Lagrange, Fr. Tours, 1795, 8 8 Seneca—Ruhkopf, Lat. Leipsig, 1797. 5 8 Seneca, Tragedies, Lat. Variorum, Leyden, 1651. 1 8 Seneca, L. Annæus and P. Syrus, wise sayings of, Gruter, Lat. Leyden, 1708. 1 8 Sibylline Oracles, Gr. &amp; Lat. Paris, 1599, 1 8 Silius Italicus—Drakenborch, Lat. Utrecht, 1 4 Silius Italicus—Ruperti and Heyne, Gottingen, 1795, 2 8 Socrates, Memoirs in Eng. by Fielding, 1767, 1 8 Solinus, Polyhistor, Lat. Bipont, 1794, 1 8 Sophocles, Antigone, Gr. Hermann, Leipsig, 1823, 1 8 Sophocles, Gr. Johnson, Eton, 1788, 2 8 Sophocles, in Eng. by Potter, London, 1820. 1 8 Sophocles, Gr. &amp; Lat. Brunck, Oxford, 1808, 2 8 Sophocles, Gr. &amp; Lat. Cambridge, 1669, 1 8 Sophocles, Erfurdt, Gr. Leipsig, 1802, 7 9 Stanley's lives of the Philosophers, London, 1701, 1 Stanyan's Grecian History, London, 1781, 2 8 Statius—Hackius, Lat. Leyden, 1671, 1 8 Statius—Hackius, Lat. Bipont, 1785, 1 8 Stephanus, Lat. Lexicon, London, 1734, 4 f Stephanus, Gr. London, 4 f Stephanus, Lexicon by Valpy, London, f Stobæus, Gr. Gaisford, Oxford, 1822, 4 8 Strabo, Gr. Coray, Paris 1815, 4 8 Strabo, Casaubon, Gr. &amp; Lat. Paris. 1620, 1 f Suetonius—Burmann, Lat. Amsterdam, 1736, 1 4 Suetonius— Wolff, Lat. Leipsig, 1802. 4 8 Suidas, Lexicon—Kuster. 3 f Sulpicius Severus—Hornius, Lat. Leyden, 1649, 1 8 Tacitus—Brotier, Lat. Edinburgh, 1796, 4 8 Tacitus—translated by Murphy, Boston, 1822, 6 8 Tacitus—translated by Gordon, London, 1817. 2 8 Tacitus—Ernesti and Obrlin, Lat. Leipsig, 1801 4 8 Tacitus—History, Barbou, Lat. Philadelphia 1808, 1 12 Tacitus—Commentary on, Ruperti, Lat. Gottingen, 1804, 1 8 Tatianus, Oration &amp;c. Gr. &amp; Lat. Oxford, 1700, 1 8 Tatius Achilles, Boden Gr. &amp; Lat. Leipsig, 1817, 1 8 Terentius, Phœdrus, &amp;c. Lat. Bentley, Cambridge, 1726, 1 4 Theophilus—Reitz, Gr. &amp; Lat. Hague, 1751, 2 4 Theocritus, Gr. &amp; Lat. Valcknaer, Leyden, 1779, 1 8 Theophrastus, Characters—Siebenkees, Gr. Nurnberg, 1798, 1 8 Thiersch, Gr. tables by Patton, Andover, 1822, 1 8 Thucydides, Gr. &amp; Lat. Duker, 1731, 1 f Thucydides, Gr. &amp; Lat. Duker, Bipont, 1788, 6 8 Thucydides, in Eng. by Smith, Philadelphia, 1818, 2 8 Valerius Flaccus, Lat. Burmann, (C. 46.) 1 4 Valerius Maximus, Lat. Helsrecht, (D. 407.) 1799, 1 8 Valerius Maximus, Torrenius, (E. 83,) Lede, 1720. 1 4 Vanierius, Lexicon to the Latin Poets, Lat. Lyons, 1 4 Vanierius, Rustic farm, Toulouse, 1706, 1 8 Vaninus, Amphitheatrum. Lat. Leyden, 1615, 1 8 Velleius Paterculus, Jani, Krause, Morgenstern and Herel, Lat: Leipsig, 1810, 1 8 Viger, on Greek Idioms, Lat. Hermann, Leipsig, 1802, 1 8 Vertot, Revolutions of Rome, Fr. Paris, 1778, 3 8 Virgilius—Douglas, Edinburgh, 1710, 1 4 Virgilius—Wakefield, Lat. London, 1796, 2 4 Virgilius—Lat. Delphin—Carey, London, 1822, 1 8 Virgilius—Lat. Minellius, Amsterdam, 1719, 1 8 Virgilius—Lat. Heyne, London, 1793, 4 8 Virgilius—Georgica, Eng. srtyn, Oxford, 1819, 1 8 Virgilius—Eclogæ, Eng. same, Oxford, 1820, 1 8 Ulpianus, Fragments, Lat. Berlin, 1811. 1 8 Vossius, on the Lat. Historians, Lat. Leyden, 1651, 1 4 Vossius, Etymological Lexicon of the Latin Language, Amsterdam, 1655, 1 f Wetstein on the pronunciation of the Greek language, Basle, 1686, 1 8 Wolff, Prolegomena, Lat. 1795, 1 8 Wolle, edition of Kuster on the Greek middle verb, Lat. Leipsig, 1752, 1 12 Xenophon's Works, Gr. &amp; Lat. Paris, 1625, 1 f Xenophon's History of Grecian affairs, Eng. by Smith, London, 1812, 1 8 Xenophon's Minor Works, Bachius, Gr. Leipsig, 1749, 1 8 Xenophon, Lexicon to, Sturzius, Leipsig, 1801, 4 8 Xenophon's Works—Thieme, Gr. Leipsig, 1801 4 8 Xenophon, life of Cyrus, by Poggio, Ital. 1 12 Xenophon, Apomnemoneumata, Schneider, Leipsig, 1816 1 8 Zonaras—Annals Gr. &amp; Lat. Paris, 2 f Zosimus, History—Heyne, Gr. Leipsig, 1784, 1 8 Greek writers of love stories, Mitscherlich, Bipont, 1792 4 8</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER II. MODERN HISTORY. Vols. Size. Adair's American Indians. London, 1775, 1 4 Adams' New England, 1799, 1 8 Alvarez, English Colonies, Sp. Madrid, 1778, 1 4 Annals of Queen Elizabeth, London, 1630, 1 f Annual Register 1758 to 1817, (see Miscell.) Anton's History of the German Nation, Ger. Leipsic, 1793, 1 8 Archenholtz's History of the Bucaniers, Fr. Paris, 1804. 1 8 Archenholtz's England and Italy, Ger. Leipsic, 1787, 5 12 Archenholtz's Seven years War, Ger. Berlin, 1 8 Archenholtz's Gustavus Vasa, Ger. Tubingen, 1801, 1 8 Archenholtz's Historical Works, Ger. Berlin. 1791, 1 12 Arnd's spirit of the times, Ger. 2 8 Ast's plan of Universal History, Ger. 1810, 1 8 Bacon's Henry VII. London, 641, 1 f Baines's History of the French Revolution, London, 1824 2 4 Baker's Chronicle. London, 1674, 1 f Baur's (Saml.) Historical, Biographical and Literarv Dictionary, Ulm 1807, 4 8 Baur's Biography of the remarkable persons of the 18th century, Ger. Leipsic 1820. 7 8 Baur's Gallery of Historical Pictures of the 18th century, Hoff. 1805. 6 8 Bayle's Historical and Critical Dictionary, London, 1733, 5 f Beck on the middle ages, Ger. Leipsic, 1812, 1 12 Belknap's New-Hampshire, 1812, 3 8 Belsham's Great-Britain, London, 1793, 14 8 Bembo, works of, It. Milan, 1808, 12 8 Bentivoglio, Hist. of the wars of Flanders, Paris, 1769, 4 8 Bentivoglio, Fr. by Leisan, Paris, 1769, 4 8 Bentivoglio, Works, It. Milan; 1806 5 8 Blair's Chronology, London, 1803, 1 f Blaquier's Greece, London, 1825, 2 8 Bolingbroke's Letters on History, 1788, 1 8 Borghini's Discourses, It. Florence, 1755, 2 4 Bosmand's aryland, Baltimore, 1811, 1 8 Botta's American War, Fr. by Sivilling, Paris, 1812, 4 8 Bougeant's History of the Treaty of Westphalia, Fr. Paris, 1767, 3 4 Bower's History of the Popes, London, 1750, 7 4 Brantome's Memoirs, Fr. Leyden, 1699. 9 12 Brodie's British Empire, Edinburgh, 1822, 4 8 Buckholz's Historical Pocket Book, Ger. Berlin, 1815, 11 12 Burk's History of Virginia, Petersburg. 1804, 4 8 Bunet's History of his own times, Oxford, 1823, 6 8 Bunet's History of the Reformation, Oxford, 1816, 6 8 Camden's Queen Elizabeth London, 1688, 1 f Camden's Britannia, London, 1806, 4 f Campbell's Naval History, London, 1813, 8 8 Campbell's Virginia, Philadelphia, 1813, 1 8 Catharine II, life of, London, 1799, 3 8 Census of 1820, Washington. Charlevoix's History of St. Domingo, Fr. Paris. 1730, 2 4 Charlevoix's History of France, Fr. Paris, 1764, 6 12 Chardin, voyages of, Atlas to, Paris, 1811, 1 f Chatham's Life, London, 1797, 3 8 Clarendon's Life, Oxford, 1761, 3 8 Clark on Coins, London, 1767. 1 f Colden's memoir of the celebration of the New-York Canal, New-York, 1824. 1 4 Collier's Historical Dictionary, London, 1701, 4 f Columbus, Memorials of, London, 1823, 1 8 Comine's Memoir of Louis XI, and Charles VIII, Fr. Paris, 1515. 1 f Coyer, History of Sobieski, Warsaw, 1761, 1 12 Dahler's manual of the Hist: of Literature, Ger. Jena, 1788, 1 8 Dalrymple's Memoirs, London, 1771. 2 4 Daniel, History of France, Fr. Paris, 1792, 10 4 D'Anville's Atlas, London, 1815, 1 f Davila's History of the Civil Wars, It. London, 1755, 2 4 Davila's History of the Civil Wars, It. London, 1801. 8 8 D'Aussy on the domestic Life of the French, by Roquefort, Fr. Paris, 1815, 3 8 De Thou—Universal History, with a continuation by Rigault, Fr. Hague, 1740, 11 4 D'Eve's Journal, London, 1682, 1 f Domesday Book, Lat. 1 f Domesday Book, Illustrated by Kelham, London, 1788, 1 8 Dictionry, Historical, Fr. Lyons, 1789, 9 8 Duhalde's History of China, London, 1736, 4 8 Dumont's Louisiana, Fr. Paris, 1735, 2 12 Eichhorn, History of Literature Ger. Gottingen, 1810, 6 8 Eichhorn, Literary, History, Gottingen, 1814. 2 8 Eichhorn, Universal History, Gottingen, 5 8 Eichhorn, History of the arts and sciences, Gottingen, 1796. 2 8 Eichhorn, History of the three last centuries Hanover, 1817. 6 8 Entick's Naval History, London, 1756. 1 f Entick's History of the War, London, 1763. 5 8 Europe, History of, from Charles the Great, Ger. Leipsi, 1810. 2 12 European Settlements in America, London, 1777, 2 8 Fabri's Encyclopædia of Historical knowledge, Ger. Erlangen, 1 8 Ferrera's History of Spain, Sp. Madrid. 1775, 17 4 Fauquiere's Memoirs, Fr. London, 1786, 4 12 Forbin's (le comte de) Memoirs, Fr. Marseilles, 1781, 2 12 Fox's James II. London. 1808, 1 4 Frederic II. King of Prussia, works of, London, 1789, 13 8 Frederic II. King of Prussia, By Holkroft, London, 1789, 13 8 Frederic II. life of, Fr. Paris, 1788, 4 8 Fleher's (Paul) Theatre of Learned men, Lat. Nuremberg, 1688, 1 f Fresnoy, method of studying History, Paris, 1729, 4 4 Gassendi's life of T. Brahe, Lat. Paris, 1654, 1 4 Goodwin's Henry V London, 1704. 1 f Goodwin's (Francis) annals of England during the reigns of Henry VIII, Edward VI. and Mary, Lat. London, 1628. 1 4 Gordon's United States, London, 1788, 4 8 Grotius, annals of, Lat. Amsterdam, 1608, 1 12 Grammont's Life of Frederic the Great, Fr. London, 1788. 1 8 Gurney's Saxon Chronicle, Norwich, 1818, 1 8 Guicciardini's History of Italy, Flarence 1818. 8 8 Guicciardini's History of Italy, Venice, 1738, 2 f Habington's Edward, IV. London, 1610, 1 f Hall's Chronicle of England, London, 1809, 1 4 Hallam's middle ages, Philadelphia, 1824, 2 8 Heath's memoirs; Boston, 1798, 1 8 Heeren's Biography of C. G. Heyne, Ger Gottingen, 4 8 Heeren's Miscellaneous Historical writings, Ger. Gottingen, 1821, 3 8 Heeren's Manual of History, Ger. Gottingen, 1822, 2 8 Herbert's Henry VIII, London, 1649, 1 f Herrera's General History, Sp. 1606, 3 4 Hewett's History of S. Carolina and Georgia, London, 1779 2 8 Henault's History of France, Fr. Paris, 1775, 5 12 Historical Register by Palmer, Philadelphia, 1814. 2 8 History, Universal. (Modern) London, 1780. 42 8 History (Secret) of the Court of Berlin, (Mirabeau) 2 8 Holmshed's Chronicles of England, Scotland, &amp;c. London 1807. 6 4 Holme's American Annals, Cambridge, 1805, 2 8 Horn's Tiberius, Ger. Leipsic, 1811, 1 12 Horn's Biography of Fred: Gedike, Ger. Berlin, 1808, 1 8 Horn's Nero, Ger. Leipsic, 1810, 1 12 Hume's and Smollet's Hist: of England, London, 1802, 13 8 Jenisch's Genius and Character of the 18th century, Ger. Berlin, 1800, 1 8 Jenisch's Hist: of Civilization in the 18th century, Ger. Berlin, 1801, 1 8 Johnson's Life of Greene, Charleston, 1822, 2 4 Jovtel, last voyage of M. de la Sale, in the Gulph of Mexico, Paris, 1712, 1 12 Justiniani, History of Venetian affairs, Latin, Venice, 1576. 1 f Kaempfer's History of Japan—Sheuchzer, London, 1728. 2 f Kennett's History of England, London, 1719. 3 f Komarzewski's Decline of Poland, Fr. Paris, 1807. 1 8 Kotzebue's Life, Ger. Leipsic, 1820, 1 12 Kotzebue's History of Prussia from the remotest times, Ger. Riga, 1808. 4 8 Kotzebue's History of the German Empire, Ger. Leipsic, 1804, 1 8 Labienus, History of German Literature, Ger. 1817, 4 8 Lacombe's History of the North, Fr. Paris, 1762, 2 12 Lacretelle's History of France, Fr. Paris, 10 8 Le Compte' Memoirs on the present state of China, Fr. Amsterdam, 1698. 2 12 Lee's Memoirs, New York, 1813. 1 12 Leland's History of Ireland, Dublin, 1773. 3 4 Lempriere's Biography, New York, 1810. 2 8 Lhuyd's Archaeologia Britannica, Oxford, 1707. 1 f Lingard's History of England, London. 10 8 Le Beau's History of the decline of the Roman Empire, Fr. Moestricht, 1780. 24 12 Lohe, on the Countries and Nations of the East, Ger. 1818 4 8 Lopez de Gomara, History of the West Indies, Fr. by M. Fumee, Paris, 1580, 1 12 Loskiel, mission to China, London, 1794. 1 8 Louis XIV. Letters of, by Morelly, Fr. Paris, 1755, 2 12 Louis XIV. Memoirs by himself, Fr. Paris, 1806. 1 8 Ludlow's Memoirs, London, 1771. 1 4 Lyttleton's King Henry II. London, 1760. 6 8 C Mably's Works Fr. Paris, 1797 12 8 Machiaveli's Works, 1818 5 8 Machiaveli's Works, Philadelphia, 1818 4 8 Machiaveli's Works, Florence, 1762 2 12 Macaulay's History of England, London 1764 5 8 Macquer's Chronological Hist: of the Jews Fr. Paris, 1759 1 12 Macquer's Chronological Hist: of Spain &amp; Portugal, Fr. Paris, 1765 2 12 Madox's History of the Exchequer London, 1769 2 f Maffei's History of the East Indies, It. Milan, 1806 3 8 Mallet's Northern Antiquities, Edinburgh, 1809 1 8 Mallet's History of Denmark, Fr. Geneea, 1789 9 12 Mangelsdorf's Hist: of European States, Ger. Halle, 1802 9 8 Marbois' Conspiracy of Arnold, Fr. Paris, 1816 1 8 Marshall's Life of Washington with Maps, Philadelphia 1804 5 8 Marmontel's Posthumous Works Fr. Paris 1805 2 12 Martmiere's Introduction to History, Fr. Amsterdam, 1738 2 8 Mazzei's Researches, Historical and Political on the United States, Fr. 1788 4 8 McCall's History of Georgia, Savannah, 1811 2 8 McPherson's Dissertations, (2 copies,) London, 1768 1 4 McPherson's Great Britain, London, 1776 2 4 Mehegan's Picture of Modern History, Fr. Lyons, 1782 3 12 Meiners' comparison of Antient and Modern Russia, Ger. Leip 1798 2 8 Meiners' Letters on Switzerland Ger. Tubingen 1791 2 12 Meiners' History of the inequality of conditions of men in the principal European Nations, Ger. Hanover, 1 12 Meiners' Historical Parallels of the state of things in the middle ages and those of our times, Ger. Hanover 1792 1 12 Meiners' Origin and progress of the Universities of Europe, Ger. Gottingen, 4 8 Meiners' History of the origin, progress and decline of science in Greece and Rome, Ger. Lemgo, 1781 2 8 Meiners' Biographies of the celebrated men since the revival of letters Ger. Zuerich. 1796 3 1 Mezeray's History of France. Fr. Amsterdam, 1688 7 12 Millot's History of France, Fr. Paris, 1814 4 12 Millot's Modern History, Fr. Paris, 1817 6 12 Military and Naval Letters, Washington, 1823 1 8 Minot's History of the Rebellion Boston, 1810 1 8 Moncada's expedition of the Catalans, &amp;c. Sp. Madrid, 1 8 Montecuculi's memoirs, Fr. Strasburg, 1735 2 12 Moreri's Historical Dictionary, Fr. Paris, 1769 10 f Morgan's Italy, New York, 1821 2 8 Morhofs Polyhistor, Lat. 1747 1 4 Moultrie's Memoirs, New York, 1802 2 8 Mudford's Memoirs of Eugene, London, 1811 1 8 Neal's New-England, London, 1720 2 8 Neubridgensis' English History, Lat. Oxford, 1719 2 8 Nicholson's Historical Libraries, London, 1776 1 4 Niemeyer's German Plutarch, 1823 2 8 Olaus Magnus, History, Lat. Antuerp, 1562 1 12 Olaus Ericus, History, Lat. Stockholm, 1554 1 12 Old field's History of England, London, 1816 6 8 Olmixions America, London, 1741 2 8 O'Meara's Napoleon, Boston, 1823 2 8 Orford's Memoirs, London, 1822 2 4 Paris's (Matthew) "Historia Major" (Watts,) Lat. Paris, 1644 1 f Peerage, New London, 1778 3 8 Pelloutier's History of the Celts, Fr. Paris, 1770 8 12 Perefixe's History of Henry the Great, Andrieaue Paris, 1822 1 8 Politz, Universal History, Ger. Leipsic, 1824 4 8 Politz, History of Saxony, Ger. Leipsic 1810 3 8 Politz, Historical Picture of 3 last centuries. Ger. Leipsic, 1816 1 8 Potherie, History of North America. Fr. Paris, 1722 4 12 Priestly on History, Birmingham, 1788 1 4 Priestly on History, London, 1793 2 8 Priestly's Biography, Philadelphia, 1803 1 8 Proud's History of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, 1777 2 8 Pouqueville's History of the Regeneration of Greece, Fr. Paris, 1825 4 8 Puffendorf's General History, continued by Martinier, Fr. Amsterdam, 1743 8 12 Purchas `His. Pilgrams," London, 1725 1 f Quinay's Military History of Louis the Great, Fr. Paris, 1726 7 4 Ramsay's History of M. Turenne, Fr. Paris, 1735 2 4 Ramsay's History of S. Carolina, Charleston, 1809 2 8 Rapin's History of England, in 15 vols. London, 1728 24 8 Continued by Tindall in 9 vols. London, 1761 24 8 Raynal's Philosophical and Political History, and Atlas, Paris, 1820 12 8 Retz, (J. F. Paul de Gondi,) Memoirs, Fr. Paris, 1819 4 8 Revolutions of Hungary, Fr. Hague, 1789 6 12 Robertson's History of Scotland, Albany, 1822 2 8 Robertson's History of America, Dublin, 1777 2 8 Robertson's History of Charles V. London 1792, 4 8 Roscoe's Lorenzo di Medici, Philadelphia, 1803 3 8 Roscoe's Leo X. Philadelphia, 1805 4 8 Royou's History of France Fr. Paris, 1819 6 8 Rulhier's Anarchy of Poland, Fr. Paris, 1819 4 8 Rushworth's Collections. London, 1659 8 f Russel's Modern Europe, Philadelphia, 1822 6 8 Rymer, "Acta publica," Lat. 1745 10 f Salmon's Moden History, London, 1744 3 f Salmon's History of Great Britain, London, 1726 2 8 Samme's Britain, London, 1676 1 f Sancho's Letters, London, 1803 1 8 Sartorius, Reign of the Ostro-Goths Ger. Hamburg, 1811 1 8 Sartorius, History of the Revolt in Germany, Ger. Hamburg, 1795 1 8 Sartorius, History of the Hanseatic League, Ger. Gottingen, 1802 3 8 Scott's Memoirs of Sir James Melvil, London, 1683 1 f Segur's Picture of Europe, Fr. Paris, 1810 3 8 Seriey's Chronological Tables, Fr. Paris 1806 1 12 Servetus, the Life of, London, 1724 1 8 St. Simon's Wars of the Alps, Fr. Amsterdam, 1788 1 4 Sismondi's History of the Italian Republics, Fr. Paris, 1818 8 8 Sismondi's History of the Italian Republics, Fr. Paris, 1818 6 8 Smith's History of New York, London, 1757 1 4 Smith's History of New York, Albany, 1814 1 8 Smith's History of Virginia, Richmond, 1819 2 8 Soltau's Letters on Russia, Ger. Berlin, 1811 1 8 Spelman's Life of Alfred. Hearne. Oxford, 1719 1 8 Speed's Great-Britain, London, 1631 1 f Stael's French Revolution, Fr. Paris, 1818 3 8 Stoddard's Louisiana, Philadelphia, 1812 1 8 Stow's Chronicle, Howes London, 1631 1 f Stada on the Belgic War, Lat Rome, 1648 2 12 Sullivan's History of Maine, Boston, 1724 1 8 Sully's Memoirs, Fr. Paris, 1822 6 8 Thuanus' History of his own time, Lat. London, 783 7 f Thierry's History of the Conquest of England by the Normands Fr. Paris, 1825 3 8 Tinour's Institutes written by himself, and translated into French by Langles, Paris, 1787 1 8 Timour, Bec. the History of, translated from the Persian into Fr. by La Croix, Paris, 1727 4 8 Troup (Robert) letter to Livingston, on Lake and Canal Policy Albany, 1822 1 8 Trumbull's History of Connecticut, New-Haven, 1818 2 8 Tudor's Life of Otis, Boston, 1823 1 8 Turner's Anglo-Saxons, London, 1823 3 8 Turner's History of England, London, 1700 5 f Verstigan's Antiquities, London, 1637 1 8 Vertot's Revolution of Portugal Fr. Arignor, 1806 1 12 Vertot's Origin of the Court of Rome, Fr. 1745 1 12 Virgillius' History of England Lat. Leyden, 1649 1 8 Volney's Lectures on History, Fr. Paris, 1822 1 8 Voltaire's History of Charles XII. Fr. Paris, 1817 1 8 Voltaire's Hist: of Russia, Fr. Paris, 1809 1 8 Voltaire's Age of Louis, XIV. Fr. Paris, 1808 3 8 oss Europe. Ger. Leipsic, 1802 1 12 oss Historical Picture of the 16th century Ger. Leipsic, 1792 4 12 oss History of the Stuart Family, Ger. Leipsic, 1794 4 12 oss Parallels, Ger. Amsterdam, 2 12 oss Historical Review of European Powers, Ger Halle, 1795 1 12 oss Manual of Modern European History, Ger. Halle 1794 1 12 oss On Modern European States, Ger. Halle, 1801 1 12 oss Aspect of the situation of Europe at the beginning of the War of 1803, Ger. Halle, 1804 1 8 Wachle manuel of the Hist: of Literature, Ger Frankfort, 1822 2 8 Waldegrave's Memoirs, London, 1821 1 4 Walshingham, Memoirs, Neustrix, 1 f Warner's Civil War in Ireland, London 1768 1 4 Warren's American Revolution, Boston 1805 3 8 Washington's Letters, Bost 1796 2 12 Watson's Philip II. London, 1812 3 8 Watson's Hist: of the N. York Canals, Albany, 1820 1 8 Wedekind's Chronological Manual of Mod: Hist: Ger. 1817 2 8 Williamson's Hist: of N. Carolina, Philadelphia, 1812 2 8 William's Hist: of Vermont, Berlington, 1809 2 8 Wilson's Expedition to Egypt, London, 1803 2 8 Winterbotham's Hist; of America London, 1795 4 8 Wirt's Life of P Heury, Philadelphia, 1818 1 8 Wood's Athenæ Oxonienses by Bliss, London, 1813 4 4 Wynne's Life of Jenkins, London, 1724 2 f Wyfleet's History of the Indians, Fr. 1607 1 4</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER III. MODERN GEOGRAPHY. Vols. Size Achaia &amp; Veji, by Schoockius, Lat. Utrecht, 1664 1 8 Africa, Leo Africanus, Lat. Leyden, 1632 1 18 Anson's voyage, by Waller, London, 1748 1 8 Arabia, Gabriel Sionita &amp;c. Lat. Amsterdam, 1635 1 18 Ayne's Universal Geographical Dictionary, Fr. Lyons, 1804 3 8 Bartram's Travels, Philadelphia, 1791 1 8 Belgium Confederated, De Lact, Lat. Leyden, 1630 1 18 Bohemia, by Strantryz, Lat. Leyden. 1643 1 18 Bossu's Travels, London, 1771 2 8 Brackenridge's view of Louisiana, Baltimore, 1817 1 8 Bruce's Travels with plates, Edinburgh, 1813 7 8 Busching's Geography, London, 1762 6 4 Chardin's Voyages by Langles, Fr. Paris, 1811 10 8 Chastillux's Voyages, Fr. Paris, 1788 2 8 Chappe d'Auteroche voyage to California, Fr. Paris, 1772 1 4 China, Lat. Leyden, 1639 1 18 Constantinople, Gyllius, Lat. Leyden, 1632 1 18 Denmark, Norway and Poland, Lat. Leyden, 1632 1 18 Dufrenoy's Geographical &amp; Historical description of the World, Fr. Paris, 1814 6 12 Ellicot's Journal, Philadelphia, 1803 1 4 England, Scotland and Ireland, Lat. De Lact, Leyden 1642 1 18 Frezier, relation of the South Sea Voyage, Fr. Paris, 1732 1 4 Gago's Voyage, Fr. Amsterdam, 1721 1 8 Gall, by De Lact, Leyden, 1629 1 18 Gall, the States, by C. Sellius, Lat. Leyden, 1626 1 18 Gell's Journey thro' the Morea, London, 1823 1 8 Germany, Lat. Leyden, 1634 1 18 Greece, Emius, Lat. Leyden, 1632 1 18 Grenet's Atlas, 1 4 Guthrie's Geography, Philadelphia, 1807 2 8 Hakluyt's Voyages, London, 1809 5 4 Harris' Voyages, London, 1744 3 1 Hawkesworth's Voyages, London, 1785 8 4 Hebrews, the Republic of Cunaeus, Lat. Leyden, 1632 1 18 Helvetia, by various Authors, Lat. Leyden, 1629 1 18 Hennepin's discovery of a very great country in America, Fr. Amsterdam, 1798 1 12 Herrera's Description of the West Indies, Sp. Madrid 1725 5 f Herrera's Description of the West Indies, Sp. Madrid 1730 4 f Holland, Hugo Grotius, Lat. Leyden, 1630 1 18 Japan, Various Authors, Amsterdam, 1640 1 18 Italy, Lat. Leyden, 1631 1 18 Kalm's Travels, by Foster, London, 1772 2 8 Labat's Voyages in America, Fr. Paris, 1792 6 12 Labat's Voyages in Guinea, Fr. Paris, 1730 4 12 La Croix's Geography, Fr. Paris, 1800 2 8 Lact's Description of the New World, Fr. Leyden, 1640 1 f Lafitan's manners of the American Savages, Fr. Paris, 1724 2 4 Lahontan's Voyages, Fr. Amsterdam, 1728 2 12 Lahontan's Continuation, Fr. Amsterdam, 1728 1 12 Las Casas, relation of Voyages, Fr. Amsterdam, 1628 1 8 Laval, voyage of Louisiana, Fr. Paris, 1728 1 4 Lewis and Clarke's Expedition, Allen, Philadelphia, 1814 2 8 Leyden, various Authors, Leyden, 1633 1 18 Long's Expedition to the Rocky Mountains, with Maps, &amp;c. Philadelphia, 1823 2 8 Mackenzie's Voyages London, 1807 1 4 Magnus Mogol, various authors, Lat. Leyden, 1631 1 18 Magellanique's Terres, Description of Fr. Lausanna, 1787 2 12 Meiners' Travels, Ger. Berlin, 1801 3 12 Morse's Gazetteer, New Haven, 1823 1 8 Moscovy, &amp;c. Lat Leyden, 1630 1 18 Moscovy, Geography Charleston, 1819 2 8 Muller on Geography, Ger. 1806 4 8 Murhard's description of the Archipelago, Ger. Berlin, 1807 2 12 Namur, Hanover &amp; Luxemburg, Lat. Leyden, 1630 1 18 Oleaurius, (Adam) relation of voyages in Moscovy &amp;c. translated into Fr. by Wicquefort, Paris, 1666 2 4 Ortelius, (Abraham,) `Theatrum orbis Terrarum' Lat. f Page's voyage around the World, Fr. Paris, 1782 2 12 Park's Travels, London, 1816 2 4 Persia, De Lact Lat. Leyden, 1649 1 18 Poland, Prussia &amp; Livonia varions authors, Lat. 1642 1 18 Portugal, Lat. Leyden, 1642 1 18 Phipp's Voyage, London, 1774 1 4 Pike's Expedition and Atlas, Philadelphia, 1810 1 8 Pinkerton's Geography, London, 1811 1 8 Ptolemy, (Claudius) Geographical relations, Lat. 1 f Rochfoucalt, (Liancourt,) voyage in the U. States, Fr. Paris. 8 8 Rome, Floccius, Lat. Leyden, 1642 1 18 Roman Germanic Empire, by Lampidius, Lat. Leyden, 1634 1 8 Savary Letters on Egypt, Fr. Paris, 1735 3 12 Savoy, Vander, Burchius, Lat. Leyden, 1 18 Scheffer description of Lapland, Lat. Frankfort, 1763 1 4 Shaw's Travels, Oxford, 1788 1 f Sleidanus on the four greatest Empires, Lat. Leyden, 1 8 Spafford's Gazetteer, Albany, 824 1 8 Spafford's Pocket Guide, New York, 1824 1 18 Spain, Campenella, Lat. Amsterdam, 633 1 18 Stedman's voyage to Surinam, with Plates, Fr. Paris, 1785 3 8 Stein's Geography, Ger. Leipsic, 1824 3 8 Sweden, Andreas Bureus, Lat. Leyden, 1633 1 18 Thrace, Antonius Gyllius. Lat. Leyden, 1632 1 18 Turkey, Montallanus, Lat. Leyden, 1634 1 18 Vancouver's Voyages, London, 1801 6 8 Valais, &amp;c. Simberus, Lat. Leyden, 1633 1 18 Venice, Lat. Leyden, 1631 1 18 Ulloa's Philosophical, Historical and Physical Memoirs on America, Sp. Madrid, 1792 1 4 Volney's description of the U. States, Fr. Paris, 1812 1 8 Volney's Voyage in Egypt &amp; Syria, Paris, 1822 2 8 Well's Ancient and Modern Maps, Oxford, 1700 1 f Young's six months' tour thro' he North of England, London, 1770 4 8</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER IV. MODERN PHILOLOGY AND LITERATURE. Vols. Size. Adelung's German Grammar 1 12 Anchoran he Gate of Tongues. Lat. Fr. &amp; Eng. London 1610 1 12 Alberti's Universal Dictionary, Italian, Lucca, 1797 3 4 Arnauld &amp; Lancelot, Port Royal Grammar, Fr. Paris 1810 1 8 Bailey's English Dictionary by Gordon &amp;c. London 1755 1 f Barnard's Polyglot Grammar, Philadelphia, 1825 8 Bauer's Grammar of the German Language German 1811 3 8 Birkman's German Grammar, Harrisburg, 1823 1 8 Boiste's French Dictionary, French, Paris, 1823 2 4 Boyer's French &amp; English Dictionary, London, 1797 1 8 Brockett's Glossary of North Country Words, New Castle, 825 1 8 Bullet's Memoirs on the Celti tongue, French, 1754, 3 f Buommatei on the Tuscan Language, Milan, 1807, 2 8 Calepin's (Ambrose) Dictionary of eight Languages, viz. Lat. Hebrew, Gr. Gal. Ital. Ger. Span. &amp; English by Lyons, 1681 f Campe's German Dictionary, 1807, 5 4 Con (M) Commentary on the Hebrew &amp; Anglo-Saxon Languages Latin, London, 1650, 12 Champollion on the vulgar Idioms of France, French, Paris, 1809, 1 12 Cinonio on the Italian Language, Italian, Milan, 1809. 4 8 Craven Dialect London, 1824 12 Dictionary of the Royal Spanish Academy, Spanish, Madrid, f Dictionary of the French Academy Fr. Paris, 1813 2 4 Dictionary Provincial French, Marscilles, 1785 2 4 Dictionary French &amp; German, Strasburg, 2 4 D Du Cange Glossary to the Latin writers of the middle and lower ages, Lat. Paris, 1733 6 f Du Cange Glossary 3vols. Latin, Paris 3 f Du Cange with supplements by Carpentier, 4vols. 4 f Dufief's French &amp; English Dictionary, Philadelphia 1810 3 8 Dufief's Nature Displayed, Fr. &amp; Eng. Philadelphia 1823 2 8 Eberhard (J. A.) on German Synonymes, Ger. Leipsic 6 8 Eberhard Pocket Dictionary of German Synonymes, German, Berlin, 821 1 12 Engelmann's method of facilitating the study of the Fr. Language, German, 1813 1 12 Erpenius's Rudiments of the Arabic Language, Leyden. 1628 1 12 Erpenius's Rudiments by Schultens, Leyden, 1770 1 4 Evans' Welch Dictionary, Carmarthen, 1812 2 8 Fick's Lexicon of the Ger. Language, Erlangen, 1823 2 8 Garner's Fr. &amp; Eng. Dictionary, Rouen, 1802 2 4 Gerault Duvivier, "Grammaire des Grammaires" Fr. Paris, 1822 2 8 Grammar of the Spanish Academy, Sp. Madrid, 1796 1 12 Grant's English Grammar, London, 1813 1 12 Grose's Provincial Glossary; London, 1811 1 8 Grose's Supplement to by Samuel Pegge, London. 1814 1 8 Guizot's Dictionary of Synonymes, Fr. Paris, 1809 1 8 Guizot's Dictionary of Synonymes, Fr. Paris, 1822 2 8 Harris, (James,) Hermes, London, 1825 1 8 Harris, Philological Enquiries, London, 1822 2 8 Heinsius, Theoretical &amp; Practical Grammar of the German Language, German, Berlin. 1817 5 8 Hickes, (George,) "Thesaurus Linguarum Veterum Septentrionalium," Latin, Oxford, 1705 3 f Hinrichsin's German Grammar, German, 1814 1 8 Jamieson's Dictionary of the Scottish Language, Edinburgh, 1808 2 4 Jamieson's Supplement, London, 1818 2 4 Ideler's Manual of the Italian Language, German. Berlin, 1822 2 8 Jenning's Dialects of the W. of Eng. Lon., 1825, 2 copies 1 12 Ihre's Swedish &amp; Gothic Glossary. 1769 1 f Ihre's Lapland Lexicon, Latin, Stockholm, 1780 1 4 Johnson's English Dictionary, Todd, London, 1818 4 4 Jonson's (Ben) English Grammar, 1640 1 4 Jones, Welsh &amp; English Dictionary 1 12 Jones, Origin of Language, London, 1764 1 8 Junius, "ymologicum Auglicum," Lye, Lat. Oxford, 1743 1 Kolbe on the copiousness of the German Language, German, Berlin 1818 3 8 Laveaux, Dictionary of Difficulties, French, Paris, 1822 2 8 Lacombe's Dictionary of the Old French Language, French, Paris 1766 2 8 Legonidec's "Grammaire Celto-Bretonne," Fr. Paris, 1807 1 Lequien's Treatise on the conjugation of Verbs, Fronch, Paris, 1811 1 12 Lescallier's vocabulary of Marine Terms, English and French, Paris 1 8 Levizac's Grammar, French, London, 1800 1 8 Macfarlane's English &amp;, Gaelic Vocabulary, Edinburgh 1815 1 8 Menage's Etymological Dictionary of the French Language, Paris, 1750 2 f Minshen's Dictionary or "Guide into Tongues" London, 1617 1 f Moritz, German Grammar, Berlin 1806 1 12 Mozin's French &amp; German Grammar, Stuttgart, 1813 1 8 Mozin's Dictionary, Fr. &amp; Ger. Stuttgart, 1817 2 12 Muratori. (L. A.) on the Antient Italian by Muratori, Italian, Naples, 1752 3 4 Nugent's French and English Dictionary, Paris, 1815 1 8 Orthography of the Castillian Language, Mudrid, 1782 1 12 Pegge's Anecdotes of the English Language, with a Supplement by Grose. London, 1814 1 8 Pfaff's Delineation of Germanic Languages, Nuremberg, 1817 1 12 Philip's English Dictionary, London, 1671 1 f Rynouard's "Grammaire Fr. Paris, 1821 1 8 Reinbeck's Manual of the knowledge of Languages, German, 1823 3 8 Reinbeck's German Grammar, Ger. Stuttgart, 1821 1 8 Richard's Introduction to the Welsh Language, Bristol 1753 1 8 Richelet's French Dictionary, Lyons, 1757 3 1 Roquefort, Glossary of the Roman Language, Paris 1808 2 8 Rouboud's French Synonymes, Paris, 1796 4 8 Schaefer's German Lexicon, 1800 1 8 Schlegel's Observations on the Provencial Language and Literature, French, Paris 1818 1 8 Schlegel's German Orthography, 1803 1 12 Sejournant's Spanish French and Latin Dictionary, Paris, 1785 2 4 Sennertus, Oriental Grammar, 1666 1 4 Sinclair's Scottish Dialect London, 1782 1 8 Skinner's "Etymologicon Linguæ Anglicanæ" London, 1671 1 4 Somnerus, Saxon, Latin and English Dictionary, Oxford, 1659 1 f Spelman's Glossary, Latin, London, 1687 1 f Steinheel, System of Instruction in the German Language, German, Stuttgart, 1822 1 8 Tim Bobbin's Works by Townley, London, 1818 1 12 Tytler on Translation, Edinburgh, 1813 1 8 Vallancey's Irish Grammar Dublin, 1792 1 8 Veneroni's Italian &amp; French Dictionary Paris, 1747 2 4 Vocabulary, Dlla Crusea Italian Naples 1746 5 f Wachterus, German Glossary, Latin Leipsic, 1737 1 f Wailley's Principles of the French Language, French, Paris 1 8 Walker's English Dictionary, New York, 1813 1 8 Willis' Grammar of the English Language, Latin. London, 1765 1 8 ANGLO-SAXON. Asserius Mnevensis, Anuals of Alfred the Great, Oxford, 1722 1 8 Baeda, See Religion. Bosworth's Anglo-Saxon Grammar, 2 copies, London, 1823 1 8 Estob's Anglo-Saxon Homily, London, 1719 1 8 Estob's Anglo-Saxon Grammar, London 1715 1 4 Gibson's Saxon Chronicle Oxford, 1692 1 4 Henshall on the Gospels, London, 707 1 8 Hickes' Anglo-Saxon Grammar, Latin, Oxford, 167 1 4 Jugram's Anglo-Saxon Chronicle, London, 1822 1 4 Junius, Gothic Glossary, Amsterdam. 1684 1 4 Junius &amp;c. Sec Religion. Lambarde's Topographical Dictionary. London, 1780 1 4 Works, 1638 2 8 Lye's Anglo-Saxon Dictionary, Manning, ondon 1772 1 f Somneus, Anglo-Saxon , , 1701 1 8 Walton's view of Hickes' Thesaurus, by Shelton, London, 1737 1 4</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER V. MATHEMATICS AND NATURAL PHILOSOPHY. Vols. Size Adams on the Microscope, London, 1781 1 8 Adams Geometrical &amp; Graphical Essays, Lon. 1813 2 8 Adams Astronomy &amp; Globes, Lon. 1812 1 8 Adams Essay on Vision, London, 1789 1 8 Adrain's Mathematical Diary. (Nos 1. 2 &amp; 3.) NewYork, 1825 Æpinus, Theory of Electricity and Magnetism, Latin, Petersbur?. 1759 1 4 American Philosophical Translations, Annals of Philosophy, Thomson, (See Miscell.) Annals of Mathematics, French Appollodorus Pergæius, Conics, Halley, Latin, 1 f Appollodorus Plane Surfaces, (R. Simson,) Latin, Glasgow, 1749 1 4 Arago &amp; Biot, Astronomical voyage, (See Biot,) Arbogast, "Calcul Derivations," French, Strasbourg, 1800 1 4 Archimedes' Greek &amp; Latin. (Torellus,) Oxford. 792 1 Archimedes' Arenarius, Greek &amp; Latin, See Wallis Archimedes' Dimensions of the Circle, See Wallis Aristarchus of the Magnitude &amp; Distance of the Sun &amp; Moon, see Wallis, Astronomical Tables by Bouvard. Burg and Delambre, French, Paris 1 4 Athæneus, See Veteres Mathematici Atwood on Arches. London, 1801 1 4 Azemar, Trisections of an Angle, See Garnier Babbage on Functional Equations, See Herschel Bacon's Works, See Miscell. Bailly's History of Antient Astronomy, Fr. Paris, 1781 1 4 Bailly's History of Indian Astronomy, Fr. Paris, 1787 1 4 Bailly's History of Modern Astronomy, Fr. Paris, 1779 3 4 Barlow on Magnetic Attraction, London, 1824 1 8 Barlow on Theory of Numbers, London, 18 1 8 Barlow on Mathematical Dtionary, London, 1814 1 8 Barlow on Mathematical Tables, London, 1814 1 8 Barrow's Euclid, See Euclid Beledor, Hydraulic Architecture, (Navier,) French, Paris, 1819 4 4 Beledor, Science of Engineers, (Navier) Fr. Paris, 1813 1 4 Bernoulli's (James) Works, Latin, Geneva, 1744 2 4 Bernoulli's (John) Works complete, Latin, Lausanne, 1742 4 4 Berthoud on Pendulums and Watches, Fr. Paris, 1805 1 12 Bezout's Arithmetic, French, Paris, 1822 1 8 Bezout's Geometry, French, Paris, 1814 1 8 Bezout's Mechanics, French, Paris, 1796 2 8 Bezout's Navigation, French, Paris, 1819 1 8 Bezout's Analytical Geometry, by Farrar, Cambridge, New-England, 1824 1 8 Bezout's Calculus by Farrar, 1824 1 8 Biot, Analytical Geometry, French, Paris, 1810 1 8 Biot, Precis de Physique, French, Paris, 1824 2 8 Biot, Physical Astronomy, French, Paris, 1810-11 3 8 Biot, Treatise of Physics, French, Paris, 1816 4 8 Biot &amp; Arago, Astronomical Voyage, Fr. Paris, 1821 1 4 Bito, See the Veteres Mathematici Bland's Algebraic Problems, Cambridge, 1816 1 8 Bland's Geometrical Problems, Cambridge, 1819 1 8 Bonnycastle's Arithmetic, London, 1810 1 8 Bonnycastle's Mensuration, London, 1823 1 12 Bonnycastle's Elements of Geometry, London, 1818 1 8 Bonnycastle's Algebra, London, 1820 1 8 Bonnycastle's Trigonometry, London, 1818 1 8 Bonnycastle's Astronomy, London, 1822 1 8 Boscovich, Optics &amp; Astronomy, Bassano, 1785 5 4 Bossut, History of Mathematics, Fr. Paris, 1810 2 8 Boucharlat's Analytical Geometry, Fr. Paris, 1810 1 8 Boucharlat's Diff. &amp; Intgral Calculus, Fr. Paris, 1 8 Boucharlat's Elements of Fr. Paris, 1815 1 8 Bouguer, Figure of the Earth, Fr. Paris, 1749 1 4 Bouguer, On the Manœuvring of Vessels, Fr. Paris, 1751 1 4 Bouguer, Optics, (Lacaille,) French, Paris, 1760 1 4 Bouroe de Villehuet, "Le Manoeuvrier" or Theory and Practice of the Movement of Ships Fr. Paris, 1769 1 8 Bourguet's Differential and Integral Calculus, French, Paris, 1810-11 2 8 Bourguet's Treatise on Navigation, Fr. Paris, 1808-14 1 4 Bouvard Tables of Jupiter &amp;c. Sec Astron. Tables Bowditch's Navigator, New York, 1821 1 8 Bridges' Trigonometry &amp; Algebra, London, 1810 1 8 Bridges' Conic Sections &amp; Equations, London, 1817 1 8 Bridges' Mechanics, London, 1814 1 8 Brinkley's Astronomy, Dublin, 1819 1 8 Bryennius Harmonics, Gr. &amp; Latin, See Wallis Budan, Resolution of Numetical Equations, French, Paris, 1807 1 4 Burg, Se Astronomical Tables Burckhardt Table of Divisors &amp;c. Fr. Paris, 1817 4 Burckhardt See Astron. Tables, Fr. Cagnoli's Trigonometry translated by Chompre, Fr. Paris, 1808 1 4 Cambridge Problems, Cambridge, 1821 1 8 Cardan, See Medicine Carnot's Geometry, (of Position,) Fr. Paris, 1803 1 4 Carnot's Relation between the distances of five points, French, Paris 1806 1 4 Carnot's Theory of Transversals, Fr. Paris, 1806 1 4 Carnot's Defence of Fortified Places Fr. Paris, 1812 1 4 Carnot's Correlativeness of the Figures of Geometry, French, Paris, 1801 1 8 Carnot's Reflexions on the etaphysics of the Infinitismal Calculus, French, Paris, 1813 1 8 Carnot's Mechanics, Calculus, French, 1803 1 8 Cavallo's Natural Philosophy, London, 1803 4 8 Cavallo's Treatise on Electricity, London, 1786 3 8 Charnock's History of Marine Architecture, Lon. 1801 3 4 Clairant's Elements of Arithmetic and Algebra, French, Paris, 1797 1 8 Clare, Motion of Flui London, 1747 1 8 Coddington's Optics, Cambridge 1 8 Coehorn's Fortification, Fr. Hague, 1741 1 8 Condamine, Measure of the three first Degrees of the Meridian, Fr. Paris, 1751 1 4 Condillac, Language of Calcukation Paris, 1798 1 8 Works, See Miscellaueous, Condorcet, Application of Analysis to Probability, Fr. Paris, 1785, 1 4 Condorcet, Means of learning to Count, Fr. Paris, 1800 1 12 Copernicus, Revolutions of Celestial Orbs, Latin, Bale, 1566 1 4 Cordier, Interior Navigation, French, Paris, 18 9-20 2 8 Cotes, (Roger,) `Harmonia Mensurarum," and Miscellaneous Works, Latin, Cambridge, 1722 1 4 Cotes, (Roger,) Lectures on Hydostatics &amp;c (Smith) Cambridge, 1747 1 8 Consin's Elements of Algebra, Fr. Paris, 1797 1 8 Consin's Diff. &amp; Int. Calculus, Fr. Paris, 1796 2 4 Creswell's Geometry, Creswell's Maxima and Minima Cambridge, 1817 1 8 Creswell's Spherics, Cambridge, 18 1 8 Creswell's Perspective, Cambridge, 18 1 8 Crozet's Geometry, New-York, 1821 1 8 Da Canha's ciples of Mathematics translated into French by breu, Paris, 1816 1 8 D'Alem Treatise on Dynamics, Fr. Paris, 1758 1 4 D'Alem Precession of the Equinoxes, Fr. Paris, 1749 1 4 D'Alem Nutation of the Earth's Axis, Fr. Paris, 1749 1 4 D'Alem Equlibrium and Movement of Fluids, Fr. Paris, 1744 1 4 D'Alem System of the World, Fr. Paris, 1754 1 4 D'Alem General cause of Winds. Fr. Paris, 1747 1 4 D'Alem Mathematical Works, Fr. Paris, 1761 8 4 Dalton's eteorological Observations, London, 1793 1 8 Dealtry's Fluxions, Cambridge, 1810 1 8 De Lambre's Abridgment of Astronomy, French, Paris, 1813 1 8 De Lambre's History of Modern Astronomy, French, Paris, De Lambre's History of Antient Astronomy, French, Paris, 1817 2 4 De Lambre's History of the Middle Age, French, Paris, 1819 1 4 De Lambre's Theoretical and Practical Astronomy, Fr. Paris, 1814 3 4 De Lambre's Determination of an Ar of the Meredian preded by a Memoir of Legendre upon the same subject, French, Paris, 1799 1 4 De Lambre's Ecliptic Tables of the Satellites of Jupiter, French Paris, 1817 1 4 De Lambre's Tables of the Sun, See Astron. Tables Deluc, Modification of the Atmosphere. French, Paris, 1784 4 8 Demoivre, "Miscellanea Analytica" Latin, London, 1730 1 4 Demoivre, Doctrine of Chances, 1756 Descartes, (See Miscellaneous) De Zach, Attraction of Mountains, Fr. Avignon, 1814 2 8 Doria's Mathematical Works, Italian Paris, 1722 1 4 Dubuat's Hydraulics &amp;c. French Paris, 186 3 8 Duhamel du Monceau, Transportation &amp;c. of Wood, French, Paris, 1767 1 4 Dupin's Developments of Geometry, Fr. Paris, 1813 1 4 Ecoles Normales, (see Miscell.) merson's Arithmetic London 1763 1 8 merson's Proportion, Arithmetic &amp; Geometry, London, 1763 1 8 merson's Combinations Chronology, Mensuration &amp; Surveying London, 1770 1 8 merson's Fluxions, London, 1743 1 8 merson's Arithmetic of Infinites, Conics, Curves, London, 1767 1 8 merson's Optics, London, 1768 1 8 merson's Astronomy, London, 1769 1 8 merson's Commentary on the Principia, London, 1770 1 8 merson's Mechanics, Projection, Centripetal Foreecs, London, 1793 1 8 merson's Miscellanies, London, 1776 1 8 merson's Algebra, London, 1764 1 8 merson's Geometry &amp; Dialling, London, 1770 1 8 merson's Elements of Trigonometry, London, 1749 1 8 merson's Mechanics, London, 1811 1 4 merson's Inerements London, 1763 1 4 Encyclopædia, Bitannica, See Miscellaneous Encyclopædia, Supplement to, Miscellaneous Encyclopædia, Miscellaneous Enfield's Institutes of Natural Philosophy, by Webber, Boston, 1824 1 4 E Euclid's Works, Complete, Greek &amp; Latin, (Gregorius) Oxford, 1703 2 f Euclid's Six first books, (Scheubelius) Lat. Bale, 1550 1 4 Euclid, by R. Simson, London, 1825 1 8 Euclid, by Whiston, Dublin, 1772 1 8 Euclid, by Tacquet, Latin, Amsterdam, 1725 1 8 Euclid, by Playfair, New-York, 1824 1 8 Euclid, by Horsley, Latin, Oxford, 1802 2 8 Euclid, by Barrow, London, 1660 1 12 Euclid, by Creswell. Euler's Mechanics, Latin, Petropolis, 1736 2 4 Euler's Naval Science, Latin, Petropolis, 1749 2 4 Euler's Theory of Music, Latin, Petropolis, 1739 1 4 Euler's "Opuscula Analytica," Lat. Petropolis, 1783-5 1 4 Euler's Dioptrics, Lat. Petropolis, 1770 3 4 Euler's Integral Calculus, Lat. Petropolis, 1768 3 4 Euler's Introduction to Analysis of Infinites. Latin, Sausanne, 1748, 1 4 Euler's Theory of the Motion of the Planets &amp; Comets, Latin, Berlin, 1744 1 4 Euler's Theory of the Motion of Solid Bodies &amp;c. Latin, Rostock, 1765 1 4 Euler's "Opuscula Varii Argumenti" Berlin, 1746 1 4 Euler's Elements of Algebra, by Farrar, Cambridge, New England, 1821 1 8 Euler's Elements of Algebra, French, (Garnier) Paris, 1807 2 8 Eytelwein, Hydraulic Ram, Fr Paris, 1822 1 4 Farrar's Application of Trigonometry, Cambridge, N. England, 1822 1 8 Ferguson's Astronomy, (Brewster,) Edinburgh, 1821 2 8 Ferguson's Mechanical Exercises, London, 1790 1 8 Fischer, Mechanical Physics, (Biot,) Fr. Paris, 1819 1 8 Flamsteed, Historia Cœlestis Brittannica, Lat. London, 1725 3 Flamsteed, Celestial Atlas, London, 1753 1 Fontaine, Memoirs not printed in their time, French, Paris, 1764 1 Forfait, Treatise on the Masting of Vessels, French, Paris, 1788 1 Francœur, Mathematics pure, French, Paris, 1819 2 Francœur, Statics, French, Paris, 1810 1 8 Francœur, Mechanics, French, Paris, 1825 1 8 Francœur, Astronomy; French, Paris, 1818 1 8 Frisius, on the Universal Gravitation of Bodies, Latin, Milan, 1768 1 4 Frisius, Mathematical Works, Latin, Milan, 1783 3 4 Galileo's Works, Italian, Florence, 718 3 4 Gallon, Machines and Inventions approved by the Royal Academy, French, Paris, 1734 0 4 Garnier's Arithmetic, French, Paris, 1808 8 Garnier's Reciprocals of Geometry, French, Paris, 1810 1 8 Garnier's Elements of Geometry, French, Paris, 1813 1 8 Garnier's Elements of Algebra, French, Paris, 1811 1 8 Garnier's Algebraic Analysis, French, Paris, 1814 1 8 Garnier's Analytical Geometry, French, Paris, 1813 1 8 Garnier's Trisection of an Angle, (Azeman,) French, Paris, 1806 1 8 Garnier's Statics, French, Paris, 1811 1 8 Garnier's Discussion of Roots &amp;c. French, Paris, 1813 1 8 Garnier's Differential Calculus, French, Paris, 1821 1 8 Garnier's Integral Calculus, French, 1812 1 8 Gassendi, Institutio Astronomica, Lat. Amsterdam, 1680 1 4 Gauss, Arithmetical Researches, translated by Poullet Delisle, French, Paris, 1807 1 4 Gaufthey, Construction of Bridges, French, Paris 1806 2 4 Gaufthey, Canals of Navigation, French, Paris 1826 1 4 Gibson's Surveying, (Ran,) Fr. New-York, 1821 1 8 Girard, Resistance of Solids, French, Paris, 1798 1 4 Goodacre's Astronomy, Richmond, 1824 1 12 Gregory's Mechanics, London, 1807 2 8 Gregory's Astronomy, London, 1802 1 8 Hachette, Elements of Algebraical Geometry, French, Paris, 1817 1 8 Hachette, Synthetical Geoetry, Fr. Paris, 1817 1 8 Hachette, Course of Physics, Fr. Paris, 189 1 8 Hachette, Treatise on Machines, Fr. Paris, 1819 1 4 alley's Astronomical Tables, Latin, London, 1749 1 4 Hamilton, (Sir W.) Observations on Mout euius, London, 1772 1 8 Harris' Effects of Lightning Floating Bodies, London, 1823 1 4 Hauy, Treatise of Phs, French, Paris, 1806 2 8 Hauy, Theory of Electricity &amp; Magnetism, Fr. See Theory Crystallography, Hero, See Veteres Mathematici, ershel Examples in Finite Differences; Cambridge, 1820 1 8 Hevelins "Selenographia," or description of the Moon, Latin, Dantzic, 1647 1 f Hooke's Works, (Waller,) London, 1705 1 2 Horrox, Posthumous Works, Latin, London, 1678 1 4 Horsley's Mathematics, Oxford, 1801 1 8 Horsley's Eucd. See Hustler's Conic Sections, Cambridge, 1818 1 8 Hutton's Philosophical and Mathematical Dictionary, London, 1825 2 4 Hutton's Logrithmc ables, London, 1794 1 8 Hutton's Mathematics, London, 1798 3 8 Hutton's Mathematical Tracts, London, 1812 3 8 Huggen's `Opera Varia,' Latin, Leyden, 1724 1 4 Huggen's `Opera Reliqua,' Latin, Amsterdam, 1788 1 4 Imison's Elements of Science &amp; Art, London, 1822 2 8 Journal de l'Ecole Polytechnique, See Miscell. Juan, Treatise of echaics applied to the Construction &amp; Movement of Ships &amp;c. Fr. Nantes, 1783 2 4 Keil, Astronomical Institutes, Fr. Paris, 1746 1 4 Keil, Lectures of Physics, Latin, London, 1719 1 8 Kramp's Analysis of Astronomical Refractions, French, 1799 1 4 Kramp's Elements of Geometry, Fr. Cologne, 1806 1 8 Labey, Elements of Mathematics, Fr. Paris, 1811 1 8 Lacaille, Foundations of Astronomy Latin, Paris, 1757 1 4 Lacaille, Mathematics Pure, French, Paris, 1795 1 8 Lacaille, Treatise on Optics, French, Paris, 1808 1 8 Lacaille, Mechanics, Fr. Augnon, 1781 1 8 Lacroix's Arithmetic, Fr. Paris, 1813 1 8 Lacroix's Compliment of Geometry, French, Paris, 1808 1 8 Lacroix's Arithmetic by Farrar, Cambridge, 1821 1 8 Lacroix's Algebra, French, Paris, 1811 1 8 Lacroix's Algebra, by Farrar, Cambridge, 1818 1 8 Lacroix's Geometry, Paris, 1810 1 8 Lacroix's Trigonometry and Analytical Geometry, Fr. Paris, 1810 1 8 Lacroix's Trigonometry, by Farrar, Cambridge, New-England 1820 1 8 Lacroix's Diff. &amp; Integral Calculus, Fr. Paris, 1806 1 8 Lacroix's Essay on Isrction in General, French, Paris, 1805 1 8 Lacroix's Diff. &amp; Int. Calculus, French, Paris, 1810 3 4 Ladies Diary, (Hutton,) London, 1775 6 12 Ladies Diary, (Leybourn) London, 1817 4 8 Lagrange, Calculus of Functions, French, Paris, 1806 1 8 Lagrange, Mechanics, (Analytic,) French, Paris, 1811 1 4 Lagrange, Resolution of Numerical Equations, Fr. 1798 1 4 La Hire, Treatise on Mechanics, French, Paris, 1695 1 12 La Hire, Mathematical Memoirs French, Paris, 1694 1 4 Lalande, Abridgment of Astronomy, French, Paris, 1795 1 8 Lalande, Logarithmic Tables, French, Paris, Lalande, See Reynaud, French, Lambert, Landen's Residual Analysis, ondon; 1779 1 4 Landen's Mathematical Memoirs, ondon; 1780 2 4 Laplace, Celestial Mechanics, Fr. Paris, 1799, 1805 2 4 Laplace, Theory of Probabilities, Paris, 1812 1 4 Laplace, System of the World, Paris, 1824 1 8 Le Clerc, Treatise of Geometry, Paris, 176 1 12 Legendre's Elements of Geometry and Trigonometry, French, Paris, 1813 1 8 Legendre's Geometry, by Faar; Cambridge, 1819 1 8 Legendre's Theory of Numbers, French, Paris, 1808 1 4 Legendre's Determination of the Orhits of the Comets, French, Paris, 1806 1 4 Legendre's Memoirs on the Determination of an A of the Meridian, See Delambre, Legendre's Exercises on the Integral Calculus, French, Paris, 811 3 4 Leibnitz, Works complete, See Miscell. Lemoine d'Essoies, Elements of Mathematics, French, Paris, 1789. 1 8 Le Monnier, Celestial History, French, Paris, 1741 1 4 Leslie's Elements of Geometry, Edinburgh, 1820 1 8 Leslie's Geometry of Curves, 1821 1 8 Leslie's Natural Philosophy, 1823 1 8 Leslie's On Heat, London, 1804 1 8 Leybourn's Mathematical Repository; Lond. 1806-14 3 8 L'Hopital, Conic Sections, French, Paris, 1707 1 4 L'Hopital, Infinitesimal Analysis, Fr. Avignon, 1768 1 8 L'Huillier, Exposition of the Diff. and Integral Calculus, Latin, Tubingen, 1759 1 4 Longitude of Washington, report on the, Washington, 1824 1 8 Ludlam's Elements of Mathematics, (Fryer,) Lon. 1809 1 Mackay's Longitude, London, 1810 2 8 Maclaurin's Algebra, London, 1796 1 8 Maclaurin's Treatise of Fluxions. Edinburgh, 1742 1 4 Maclaurin's Account of Newton's Discoveries, (Murdoch.) London, 1748 1 4 Maire &amp; Boscovich, Astronomical Voyage, French, Paris, 1770 1 4 Manfredi's Ephemerides, Latin, 1715 2 4 Macheroni's Problems of Surveying, Fr. Paris, 1803 1 8 Maskelyne's Astronomical Observations, London, 1776 4 f Mathematicians Antint, Apollodorus, Athenæus, Bito, Philo, Hero &amp;c. Greek &amp; Latin, Paris 1693 1 Mayer's (Tobias,) Unpublished Works, Latin, Gottingen, 1775 1 4 Mayniel, Experimental, Analytical and Practical Treatise on Fortification, Paris, 1808 1 4 Memoires de Physique &amp;c. de la Soiete Aeile, See Miscell. Memoires de L'Institut, See Miscell. Mendoza and Rios, Nautical Astronomy, French, London, 1797 1 4 Monge, Elements of Statics, Fr. Paris, 1820 1 8 Monge, Descriptive Geometry, (Brisson,) French, Paris, 1820 1 4 Monge, Application of Analysis to Geometry, French, Paris, 1809 1 4 Montucla, History of Mathematics, Fr. Paris, 1799 4 4 Mudge's Trigonometrical, Survey of Eng. and Wales, London, 1799 3 4 Murhard, Mathematical Bibliography, Lat. Leipsic; 1794 5 8 Mssebroe, Experimental &amp; Mathematial Physics, French, Paris, 1769 3 4 Newton, Amsterdam, 1791 1 4 Newton, Glasgow, 1822 3 8 Newton, Optics, Newton, Tables for Leases &amp; Interest, London, 1758 1 12 Nicholson's (P.) Architecture. London, 1809 3 8 Nicholson's Carpenter's Guide, London, 1823 1 4 Nicholson's Carpenter's Assistant, London, 1822 1 4 Nicholson's (W) Natural Philosophy, London, 1805 2 8 Nieuport's Mathematical Miscellanies, French, Brussels, 1794 2 4 Nolle, The Art of Experiments, Fr. Paris, 1770 3 12 Otto de Gueke, Amsterdam, 1672 1 2 Paoli, Supplement to the Elements of Geometry, aan, Pisa, 1804 1 4 ppus, Mathematical Collections, (Commandinus,) Latin, 1660 1 Pappus, Book 2d of Math. Frag. See Wallis, Peacock's (D. M.) Conic Sections, London, 1817 1 8 Peacock's Comparison of the Fluxional &amp; Differential Calculus, Cambridge, 1819 1 8 Peacock, (G.) Examples in Differential &amp; Integral Calculus, 1820 1 8 Pemberton's view of Newton's Philosophy, London, 1798 1 4 Philo, See Wallis, Philosophical Transactions, See Miscell. Pike's Arithmetic, Troy, N. Y. 1822 1 8 Pingre's History &amp; Theory of Comets, Paris, 1783 2 4 Playfair's Outlines of Nat. Philosophy, Edinburgh, 1816 2 8 Playfair's Euclid, See Euclid, Poisson's Treatise of Mechanics, Fr. Paris, 1811 2 8 Pommies, Manuel for the Engineer, by Reynaud, Paris, 1808 1 4 Porphyry, See Wallis, Potter's Mathematics with Lo Tables, London, 1753 1 8 Poullet Delisle Trigonometrical &amp; Analytical Geometry, French, Paris, 1809 1 8 Price on Annuities, (W Morgan,) London, 1812 2 8 Priestley's History of Electricity, London, 1769 1 4 Prony, Analytical Mechanics, French, Paris, 1810-15 1 4 Prony, Hydraulic Architecture, French, Paris, 1790 2 4 Ptolemy, (Claudi,) Magnæ Constructiones Lib. XIII, with the commentary of Theon, Greek, 1538 1 f Ptolemy, translated by Geo. Trapezuntino, Lat. 1541 1 f Ptolemy, Harmonic See Wallis Puissant, Treatise of Analytical Geometry, French, Paris, 1809 1 8 Puissant, Topography, Surveying &amp; Levelling, French, Paris, 1807 1 4 Puissant, Geodaesia, Paris, 1805 1 4 Reynaud's Treatise of Algebra. Fr. Paris, 1821 1 8 Reynaud's Plane &amp; Sheri Trigonometry, French, Paris, 1818 1 12 Rivard on the Sphere &amp;c. French, Paris, 1816 1 8 Robins on Gunnery, (Hutton,) London, 1805 1 8 Robins Mathematical Tracts, London, 1761 2 8 Robinson's Mechanical Philosophy (Brewster,) Edinburgh, 1822 4 8 Rondelet's Art of Building. Paris, 1812 6 4 Rondelet's Art of Building. Plates, Paris, 1812. 1 f Rowning's Philosophy, London, 1779. 2 8 Rutherford's Natural Philosophy, Cambridge 1748 2 4 Saunderson's Algebra, Cambridge, 1741 2 8 Saunderson's Fluxions, London, 1756 1 4 Saussure's Essays on the Hygrometer, French, Neuf-chatel, 1783 1 4 S. Gravesande's Ph. &amp; Mathem. Works, French, Amsterdam, 1774 1 4 Simpson's (T) Algebra, London, 1782 1 8 Simpson's (T) Plane and Spherical Trigonometry, London, 1779 1 8 Simpson's Elements of Geometry, London. 1821 1 8 Simpson's Fluxions. (Davis.) London. 1805 1 8 Simpson's Mathematical Exercises, (Hearding,) London, 1820 1 8 Simson's (R.) Conic Sections, Glasgow, 1 8 Simson's cd, See Euclid, Simson's Posthumus Works, Latin, Glasgow 17. 1 4 Singer's Elements of Electricity &amp; Galvanism an- ted by Thillaye, French, See Smith's Optics, Cambridge, 1738 2 4 St. Paul, Treatise on Fortification. Fr. Paris, 1799 2 5 Swden Van, Electricity and Magnetism, French, Hague, 1785 3 8 Tacquet's Euclid, See Eid Taylor's (M.) Tables of Logarithms, London, 1792 1 4 Tredgold's Elements of Carpentry, London, 1820 1 4 Turpin de Crissê, Art of War, Fr. Paris, 1754 2 4 Tycho Bahe, Tycho Bahe, Works Complete, Lat Frankfort, 1648 1 4 Vanban, Attack &amp; Defence of Fortified places French, Hague, 1737 2 4 Venturi, Motion of Fluids, Fr. Paris, 1797 1 8 Venturoli's Mechanics, (Creswell,) Cambridge, 1822 2 8 Vieta. Mathematical Works complete, (Schooten,) Ley den, 1647 1 f Vinces Conic Sections, Cambridge, 1810 1 8 Vinces Trigonometry, Plane and Spherical. Cambridge, 1820 1 8 Vinces Fluxions, Cambridge, 1812 1 8 Vinces Hydrostatics, Cambridge, 1812 1 8 Vinces Astronomy, Cambridge, 1810 1 8 Vlacq, Tables of Lines &amp;c. Francfort, 1778 1 8 Wallis' Works Complete, the third Volume contains the works of Ptolemy, Archimedes &amp;c. Latin and Greek, Oxford, 1795 3 f Whiston's Euclid, See Euclid Wolf, Course of Mathematics, French, Paris, 1757 3 8 Wood's Optics Cambridge, 1 8 Mechanics Cambridge, 1 8 Woodhouse's Astronomy, Cambridge, 1821-3 2 8 Worcester's Century of Inventions, London 1825 1 12 Wronski, Philosophy of Mathematics, French, Paris, 1811 1 4 Young's Natural Philosophy, London, 1806 2 4 Zach, Tables of Aberration, Latin, Gotha, 1806 2 4 Zach, Tables of the motions of the Sun, Latin, Gotha, 1792 1 4 Zach, Catalogue of the Fixed Sta Latin, Gotha, 1792 1 4</field>
      <field name="fulltext">F CHAPTER VI GENERAL NATURAL HISTORY. Vols. Size. Blumenbach's Manuel of Natural History, translated by Artand; French, Metz, 1803 2 8 Bonnet's Works French, 10 4 Buffon's Natural History, Fr. Paris, 127 8 Buffon's Natural Abridged London, 1792 2 8 Catesby, Natural History of Carolina. Florida &amp;c. Eng and French, London, 1771 2 f Domestic Portable Dictionary Fr. Paris, 1792 3 8 Dumeril's Natural History, Fr. Paris, 1807 2 8 Fourcroy's Elements of Natural History and Chemistry, French, Paris 1795 5 8 Gilibert's System of Nature French, Lyons, 1802 I 8 Horrebow's Natural History of Iceland, London, 165 1 f Humbolt's Picture of Nature, Fr. Paris, 1808 2 8 Leeuwenhock's Secrets of Nature, Latin, Leyden, 1708 1 8 Linnaeus, System of Nature, Latin Leipsic. 1788 9 8 Linnaeus, System of Nature, by Turton. London, 1806 7 8 Linnaeus, Amtates Academicae, Latin, Stockholm, 1749 10 8 Memoirs of the Linnæan Society Pallas, Travels in Russia, See Miscell. Piso on the Ntural and Medical productions of both the Indies, Latin, Amsterdam 1658 1 f Plinius, Natural History, Latin, Paris, 1727, 1 f Plinius, Natural History, Latin, Leipsic, 1778 10 8 Redi's Works, Italian Naples, 1791 3 4 Saussure, Voyage in the Alps, French, 1803 4 4 Shaw's Naturalist's Miscellany, London, 24 8 Smellie's Philosophy of Natural History, by Ware, Boston, 1824 1 8 Spectacle of Nature Fr. Paris, 1782 9 8 Swammerdam's Book of Nature, or History of Insects, Leyden. 1737 3 f Valmont de Bomar, Dictionary of Natural History, Fr. Lyons, 1800 15 8 Willich's Domestic Encyclopædia, French, Philadelphia, 1821 3 8</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER VII. AGRICULTURE AND HORTICULTURE. Vols. Size Abu Zacaria Ebn el Awam, Book of Agriculture, Arabic &amp; Spanish by Banqueri, Madrid, 1802 2 f Christ, on the Cultivation of the Vine, German, Frankfort, 1800 1 8 Complete Body of Husbandry, London, 1756 2 f Davy's Agricultural Chemistry. See Chem. Dickson's Agriculture, Edinburgh, 1770 2 8 Duhamel's Agriculture, Miller, London, 1764 2 8 Dundonald Treatise on Chem. &amp; Agricul. Lond. 1803 1 4 Fellemberg, Views relative to the Agriculture of Switzerland French, Geneva, 1808 1 8 Gauteron's Lette to Picket on Agriculture, French, Pamphlet Kalb on the Cultivation of the Vine, German, Stuttgart, 1816 1 12 Kirwan on Manures, London, 1796 1 8 Knight on the Culture of the Apple and the Pear, London, 1818 1 8 Memoirs of the Society of Agriculture of the Seine, Paris, 9 8 Muller on the Cultivation of the Vine in Germany, German, Leipsic, 1803 1 12 Ray Synopsis (Sterpium,) Latin, London, 1724 1 8 Serres, Theatre of Agriculture, by Gisors, French, Paris, 1802 4 8 Sichler's German Gardening, German, 3 8 Manual of Gardening, Ger. 1 8 Sinclair's Code of Agriculture, London, 1821 1 8 Taylor's Arator. Petersburg, 1818 1 8 Tull's Husbandry by Cobbett, London, 1822 1 8 Wheatly on Modern Gardening, London, 1777 1 8</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER VIII BOTANY. Vols. Size Acharius, Universal Lichenography, Lat Gottingen, 1810 1 4 Barton's Botany, Philadelphia. 1812 2 8 Barton's Medical Botany, See Med. Bigelow's Boston Flora Latin Boston, 1824 1 8 Bigelow's Medical Botany, See Med. Boerhaave, Index of Plants, Latin, Leyden. 1710 1 8 Boerhaave, History of Plants. Latin, Rome, 1727 2 12 Botanical Magazine, by Curtis. London, 31 8 Clayton, Vrginia Flora, Latin. Leyden, 1743 1 8 Curtis, London Flora, London, 1817 2 f Darwin's Botanic Garden. New-York, 1798 1 8 De Candolle, Theory of Botany, French, Paris, 819 1 8 De Candolle, Medical property of Plants, See Med. Desfontaines' Atlantic Flora, Lat. Paris. 1798 2 4 Desfontaines' Atlantic Plates, Fr. Paris. 1798 2 4 Dictionary, Botanical, French, Paris, 1817 2 8 Dutrochet, See Zoology, Elliott's Botany, Charleston, 1821 2 8 Evelyn's Sylva, by Hunter, York, 1812 2 4 St. Germain Manual of Vegetables, Fr. Paris, 1784 1 8 Greenway, Collection of Plants of Virginia, M. S. St. Hilaire, Exposition of Natural Families and of the germination of Plants, French, Paris, 1805 4 8 Hill's British Herbal, London, 1756 1 f Lamarck, French Flora, Fr. Paris, 1778 3 8 Linnæus, System of Vegetables, by Roemer &amp; Schultes, Latin, 1822 1 8 Linnæus, System of Vegetables, Lichfield, 1783 2 8 Linnæus, System of Veg. Latin 1817 7 8 Linnæus, Fundamenta Botanica, Gessner, Latin, 1747 1 8 Linnæus, Lapland Flora Smith, Latin, London, 1792 1 8 Linnæus, Botanical Philosophy, Sprengel, Latin, 1809 1 8 Michaux, History of the Oaks of America, French Paris, 1801 1 f Michaux, History of the Forest Trees of America, Fr. Paris, 1810 3 4 Michaux, North American Sylva, Paris, 181 2 4 Michaux, North American Flora, Latin, Paris, 1820 2 8 Miller's Gardener's Dictionary, Martin, London, 1807 4 f Monceau on Trees, Fr. Paris, 1758 2 4 Muhlenberg, Description of Herbs, Latin, Phil. 1817 1 8 Nuttall's Plants, Philadelphia, 1818 2 8 Persoon, Methodical Synopsis of Mushroom's, Latin, Gottingen, 1801 1 8 Pulteney's Botany, London, 1790 2 8 Saussure, Chemical Enquiries on Vegetation, French, Paris, 1804 1 8 Smith's English Flora, London, 1824 3 8 Smith's Introduction to Physiological and Systematical Botany, Bigelow, Philadelphia, 1814 1 8 Sprengel's Plants, London, 1807 1 8 Theophrastus History of Plants Latin, Amsterdam, 1644 1 f Theophrastus by Hill, Eng. London, 1746 1 8 Thornton's Philosophy of Botany, London, 1810 4 f Thornton's New Illustration of the Sexual System, London, 1807 1 f Torrey's Flora of the Northern United States, NewYork. 1824 1 8 Tournefort, Institutions, (Rei Herbariæ,) Lat. Par. 1799 4 8 Waterhouse, Botanist, Boston, 1811 1 8 Withering's Botanical Arrangement, London, 1818 4 8 Woodville's Medical Botany, See Med.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER IX. ZOOLOGY Vols. Size Aristotle's Natural History of Animals, Latin, Leipsic, 1811 4 8 Audebert, Natural History of Monkeys, &amp;c. French, Paris, 1810 1 f Brooke's Conchology, London, 1815 1 4 Buffon's Natural History of Birds, Fr. Paris, 1770 9 4 Camper's Works, French, Paris, 1803 3 8 Camper's Atlas, Paris. 1803 1 f Christ, Dictionary of the rearing of Bees, German, Francfort, 1805 4 Cuvier, Animal Kingdom, Fr. Paris, 1817 4 8 Du Costa, British Conchology, English and French, London, 1778 4 Donovan's Natural History of British Fishes, London, 1808 5 8 Donovan's Nat. Hist. of Insects, London. 1804 8 8 Dutrochet on the Structure of Animals and Vegetables, French, Paris 1824 8 Ellis's Zoophytes, by Solander, London, 1786 4 Fabricius, Entomology, Latin, London, 1792 4 8 Fabricius, Supplement, Latin, London, 1 8 Eleming's Philosophy of Zoology, Edinburgh, 1822, 2 8 Goffroy History of Insects, Fr. Paris, 1799 2 4 Grard upon the feet of Domestic Animals. French, Paris 1813 8 Grard Veterinary Anatomy, See Vet. Medicine Hooke's Micrography, London, 1645 1 f Home's Lectures on Comparative Anatomy, London, 1814 4 4 La Cepede. Natural History of Fishes, Fr. Paris, 1798 5 4 La Cepede. Natural History of Man, Fr. Paris, 1821 12 La Cepede. Natural History of Qnadrupeds, oviparous Animals &amp; Serpents, Fr. Paris, 1798 4 12 La marck, Natural History of Animals without Vertebræ, French, Paris, 1815 8 8 Latham's Natural History of Birds, London, 1781 8 4 Latham's Index, London, 1790 2 4 Latreille, General Considerations on the Natural order of Animals, Fr. Paris, 1810 1 8 Lawrence's Lectures on the Natural History of Man, London, 1823 1 8 Leach's Zoological Miscel. London, 1814 3 8 Pennant's History of Birds, London, 1781 1 4 Pennant's History of Quadrupeds, London, 1783 2 4 Pennant's British Zoology, London, 1812 4 8 Pennant's Arctic Zoology, London, 1784 2 4 Ray, (John) Methodical Synopsis of Animals of the Quadruped and Serpent kind. Latin, London, 693 8 Ray, (John) History of Insects, Latin, London, 1710 1 4 Reaumur, History of Insects, Fr. Paris, 1784 6 4 Recca, Complete Treatise on Bees Fr. Paris, 1790 3 8 Rudolphis, Natural History of Worms, Latin. Amsterdam, 1808 2 8 Salmasius, Plinianæ Exercitationes, Lat. Utrecht, 687 1 f Say's American Insects, Philadelphia, 1824 2 8 Say's Glossary, Philad, 1825 1 4 Shaw's Zoology, Engravings by Heath, London, 24 8 Swammerdam's History of Insects, Lond. 1758 1 f Virey, Natural History of the Human Species, French, Paris, 18. 2 8 Virey, On the Manners and Instinct of Animals, Fr. Paris, 1822 2 8 Willoughby's Ornithology, by Ray, London, 1678 1 f Wilson's American Ornithology, Phila, 1808 9 4 Zimmerman, Geographical Zoology, French, 1784 1 8</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER X. MINERALOGY AND GEOLOGY. Vols. Size. Annals, (des Mines) Brochant, Treatise on Mineralogy, Fr. Paris, 1808 2 8 Buffon, Epochs of Nature, Fr. Paris, 1778 1 4 Buffon, Natural History of Minerals, Fr. Paris, 1783 9 8 Burnet's Theory of the Earth, London, 1726 2 8 Cleaveland's Mineralogy &amp; Geology, Boston, 1822 2 8 Cronsted's Mineralogy, by Engesstorm and Maglelan, French, London, 1788 2 8 Fanjas, (de Saint Fond,) Essay on Geology, French, Paris, 1803 3 8 Greenough's Geology, London, 1819 1 8 Hay's Mineralogy French Paris, 1801 1 4 Hay's Treatise on Mineralogy, Paris, 1801 4 8 Hay's Crystallography, Paris, 1822 1 4 Crystallography, Paris, 1822 2 8 Chrystallography, Paris, 1809 1 8 Hay's Essay on the Structure of Crystals, F. 1784 1 8 Henslow, Syllabus of a Course of Lectures on Mineralogy, Cambridge, 1823 1 8 Jameson's Mineralogy, Edinburgh, 1820 3 8 Maclure on the Formation of Rocks, 8 Maclure Geology of the United States, Phil. 1817 1 8 Phillips &amp; Conybeares' Geology of England &amp; Wales, London 1822 1 8 Phillips' Mineralogy by Mitchell, New-York, 1818 1 8 Singer, Elements of Electricity and Galvanism, French Paris, 1817 1 8 Van Rensselaer, Geological survey of the Eric Canal, Albany, 1824 1 8 Werner on the Formation of Veins, Fr. Paris, 1802 1 8</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER XI. CHEMISTRY. Vols. Size. Annals (de Chimie et de Physique) Fr. Accum's Chemistry, Cooper, Philadelphia, 1814 2 8 Accum's Chemical Tests, London, 1820 1 8 Accum's Chemical Amusements, London 1817 8 Bancroft on Colours, Philadelphia, 1814 2 8 Baume's Experimental Chemistry, Fr. Paris, 1773 3 8 Berthollet, Elements of the Art of Painting French, Paris, 1804 2 8 Berthollet, Enquiries into the Laws of Affinity, French, Paris, 1806 1 8 Berzelius on the Blow-pipe, Children, London, 1822 1 8 Chaptal's Chemistry, applied to the Arts, Fr. Par, 1807 4 8 Chaptal's Elements of Chemistry, Fr. Par, 1803 3 8 Chevreul, Chemical Inquiries into several Fatty Substances, French, Paris, 1823 8 Chemical Lectures, Plan of, at Cambridge Pamphlet Children's Chemical Analysis, London, 1819 1 8 Complete Baker, French, Paris, 1778 1 8 Conversations on Chemistry Phila, 1818 2 8 Cossigny on Gun Powder, French, Paris, 1807 2 8 Crawford on Animal Heat, London, 1788 1 8 Davy s Chemical Philosophy; Phila, 1812 1 8 Davy s Agricultural Chemistry, Phila, 1821 8 Dundonald, See Agriculture Farish, Plan of a Course of Lectures on Arts and Manufactures, Pamphlet Fourcroy Elements of Natural History and Chemistry, French, Paris, 1793 5 8 Gay Lussac use of the Centesimal Alcohometer, Paris, 1824 1 12 Goham's Chemistry, Boston, 1819 2 6 Gurney's Letter to Brande, Pamphlet G Haüy, Theory of Electricity &amp; Magnetism, French, Paris, 1787 1 8 Henry's Chemistry, Silliman. Boston, 1814 2 8 Kraft's American Distiller, Philadelphia, 1804 1 8 La Taye on the Preparation of Lime; Fr. Paris, 1778 1 8 Lagrange, Manual of Chemistry, Fr. Paris, 1799 2 8 Lavoisier, Treatise on Chemistry, Fr. Paris, 1801 3 8 Leslie; on Heat, (See Nat. Philosophy,) Macneven, Exposition of the Atomic Theory, Pamphlet, 26 Nos. Macquer, Dictionary of Chemistry, Fr. Paris, 1778 4 8 Macquer, Elements of the Theory &amp; Practice of Chemistry, Edinburgh, 1768 3 8 Memoirs of the Society of Arcueil 3 8 Orfila, Elements of Chemistry, applied to Medicine and the Arts, French, Paris, 1824 2 8 Orfila, on Poisons, (See Medical Jurisprudence,) Parke's Chemical Essays, London, 1823 2 8 Patissier, Mineral Waters of France, Fr. Paris, 1 8 Priestley on Electricity, (See Nat. Philosophy) Saussure, Chemical Inquiries upon Vegetation, Franch, Paris, 1804 4 8 Scheele, Chemical Treatise on Air and Fire, by Bergmaun, French, Paris, 1787 1 8 Shaw's Chemistry, London, 1741 1 4 Singer's Elements of Electricity &amp; Galvanism, French, Paris, 1817 1 8 Stahl's Principles of Chemical Pharmacy, Latin, 1721 1 8 Swinden, Electricity and Magnetism, (See Natural Philosophy) Tabular view of the Nomenclature and System of Chemistry; New-York, 1821, 20 Nos. Thenard's Treatise on Chemistry, Fr. Paris, 1824 5 8 Thomson's Chemistry, London, 1817 4 8 Ure's Chemical Dictionary, London, 1823 1 8 Watson's Chemical Essays, London, 1793 5 12 Webster's Manual of Chemistry, Boston, 1826 1 8</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER XII. HISTORY OF MEDICINE AND MEDICAL BIOGRAPHY Vols. Size. Berard, Medical Doctrine of Montpellier, Fr Montpellier. 1819 1 8 Bontius, See Materia Medica, Briot, History of Military Surgery in France, French, Besancon, 1817 1 8 Cabanis, History of the Retorm of Medicine, French, Paris, 1822 1 8 Carcassonne, on the Medicine of the Hbrews, French, Montpellier, 1 8 Coster, Account of the New Italian Medical Doctne, French, Paris, 1825 1 8 Cross, Sketches of the Medical Schools of Paris, London, 1815 1 8 Dujardin, History of Surgery, Fr. Paris, 1774 2 4 Eloy, Medical Historical Dictionary, Fr. Mons, 1778 4 4 History of Surgery, French, Paris, 1749 1 4 Jackson, Eulogy on the Character of Dr. Warren, 1 8 Le Clerc, History of Medicine, Fr. La Haye, 1729 1 4 Mahon, History of Clinical Medicine by La Mauvre, French, Paris, 1807 1 8 Piso, C. (See Materia Medica,) Portal, History of Anatomy and Surgery, French, Paris, 1770 6 12 Regnault, on the state of Medicine in France, French, Paris, 1819 1 8 Roux, Medical Journey to London, Fr. Paris, 104 1 8 Tourtelle, History of Medicine, Fr. Paris, 1804 2 8 Valentin, Historical Notice of Jenner, Fr. Nancy, 1823 1 8</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER XIII. HYGIENE. Vols. Size. Armstrong, Art of Preserving Health, See Miscell, Finlayson, on the Preservation of the Health of Sailors, London, 1824 1 8 Fodéré, on Epïdemics &amp; Hygiene, Fr. Paris, 1822 4 8 Good, on the Treadwheel, London, 1824 1 8 Guyton Morveau, Means of disihfecting the Air, Paris, 1805 1 8 Hippesley on Prison Labour, London, 1823 1 8 Hutehinson, (B) on Prison Discipline, Newark, 1824 1 8 Haufeland, Art of prolonging life by Jourdon, French, Paris, 1824 8 Londe, Medical Gymnastics, Fr. Paris, 1821 1 8 Maclean, Evils of Quarantine Laws, London, 1824 1 8 Mercurialis, (H) on Gymnastics, Latin, Venice, 1573 1 4 Parent Duchatelet, Essay on Privies &amp;c. French, P ris, 1824 1 8 Persoon, on Eatable Mushrooms, Fr. Paris, 1818 1 8 Prison Labour, Nature and Effects of, London, 1824 1 8 Tourtelle, Elements of Hygiene by Brioheteau, French, Paris, 1823 2 3 Wallace, Instructions for the Preservation of Health in Indian Climates, London, 1824 1 8 Waterhouse, on the Effects of Smoking Cigars, Cambridge, 1812 1 8</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER XIV. MATERIA MEDICA AND PHARMACY. Vols. Size Barbier, Elementary Treatise on Materia Medica, Fr. Paris, 1819 Barton, Vegetable Materia Medica of the Unïted States, Philadelphia, 1817 2 4 Beaumé, Elements of Pharmacy, by Bouillon, French, Paris, 1818 2 8 Bigelow, American Medical Botany, Boston, 1817 3 4 Bird, on the Sanguinaria Canadensis 1 8 Boerhaave, on Materia Medica, Latin, Leyden, 1746 1 8 Bontius, Medicine of the Hindoos, Latin, Leyden, 1745 1 4 Bouillon-La Grange, Pharmaco, Chemical Dispensatory, French, Paris, 1813 1 8 Brande, on the Origin &amp;c. of Apothecaries Hall, in London, London, 1823 1 8 Brande, Manual of Pharmacy, London, 1825 1 8 Brugnatelli, General Pharmacopoeia, by Vlahe, Fr. Paris, 181 2 8 Chapman, Elements of Materia Medica &amp;c. Philadelphia, 1823 2 8 Churchill, on Acupuncturation, London, 1 12 Cloquet, (H.) on Animal Substances used in Medicine, French, Paris 1 8 Coxe, American Dispnsatory, Philadelphia, 1825 1 8 Cullen, Treatise on the Materia Medica, Edinburgh, 1789 2 4 De Candolle, Essay on the Properties of Plants, French, Paris, 1816 1 8 De Lonnes, Considerations on the Actual Cautry, Fr. Paris, 1812 1 8 Desptes &amp; Constancio, Conspectus of the Pharmacopoeias of London, Edinburgh, Dublin and Paris, Fr. Paris, 1820 1 12 Dunglison, Edition of Magendie's Formulary, See Magendie. Dunglison, Translation of Larrey on the Moxa, (See Larrey Ebrle, Treatise on the Materia Medica, Phila 1812 2 8 Formulary for Physicians, French Paris, 1783. 1 12 Fquet, on the Administration of Medicines, French, Paris, 1820 1 8 Gairdner, on the Effects of Iodine, London, 1824 1 8 Gales; on Sulphureous Fumigations, Fr. Paris, 1826 1 8 Geoffroy, Treatise on the Mataria Medica, French, Paris, 1757 11 8 Geoffroy, Supplement to, it by Nobleville and Salerne, French, 1756 6 8 Gray, Elements of Pharmacy, London, 1823 1 8 Green, on Fumigating Baths, London, 1823 1 8 Haden, on the Colhicum Autumnale, London, 1820 1 8 Hamilton, on Purgative Medicines, Edinburgh, 1809 1 8 Jourdan, Pharmaceutical Code of Paris, Fr. Paris, 182 1 8 Kapeler and Caventou, Manual for the Pharmacien &amp;c. French, Paris, 182 2 8 Larrey, on the Moxa, by Dunglison, London, 1822 1 8 Magendie, Formulary for new Remedies, by Haden and Dunglison, with appendix, London 1824 1 8 Magendie, on the Effect of Emetic Tartar, French, Paris, 1813 1 8 Martinet, on the use of Oil of Turpentine in Sciatica, French, Paris, 1823 1 8 Murray, (J.) Materia Medica, Edinburgh, 1822 2 8 Niel, on the preparations of Gold, by Chestien, Paris; 1821 1 8 Orfila, Chemistry applied to Medicine, See Chem. Paris, Pharmacologia, London, 1823 2 8 Pharmacopoeia of the United States, Boston, 1820 1 8 Pso, (C.) on the Res-medica of the Indies, Latin, See General Natural History. Pope, on Sarsaparilla, Conchonine, Quinine &amp;c, London 1823 1 8 Richard, Pocket Formulary, Fr. Paris, 1824 1 12 Stahl, Chemico Pharmaceutical "Fundamenta" See Chemistry Stocker, Alterations in the London Pharmacopoeia of 1824, London, 1824 1 8 Swediaur, Pharmacologia, Lat. Paris, 1803 2 12 Thornton, Family Herbal on Medical Properties of Plants, London, 1814 1 8 Wallace, on Chlorine in Diseases of the Liver, London, 1822 1 8 Woodville, Medical Botany, London, 1794 4</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER XV. MEDICAL JURISPRUDENCE AND TOXICOLOGY Vols. Size Beck, Medical Jurisprudence, Albany, 1823 2 8 Bertrand, Medico-legal Manual on Poisons, French, Paris, 1817 1 8 Briand, Legal Medicine, French, Paris, 1821 1 8 Capuron, on Legal Medicine as it relates to Midwifery, French, Paris, 1821 1 8 Chaussier, Legal Medicine Fr. Paris, 1824 1 8 Chaussier, on Antidotes, Fr. Paris, 1819 1 8 Dunglison, Syllabus of Lectures on Medical Jurisprudence, Charlottesville, 1827 1 8 Fodéré, Treaties on Legal Medicine, Fr. Paris, 1823 6 8 Fontana, on Poisons, &amp;c. Fr. Florence, 1781 2 4 Huard, Medico-legal Reflexions, Fr. Paris, 1819 1 8 Lecieux, &amp;c. on legal Medicine, Fr. Paris, 1819 1 8 Mahon, Legal Medicine by Fautrel, Fr. Paris, 1811 8 8 Manual of Legal Medicine, Fr. Paris, 1820 1 8 Montmahon, Manual of Poisons, Fr. Paris, 1824 1 12 Olivaud, on Infanticide, Fr. Paris, 1802 1 8 Orfila, Treatise on Poisons, Fr. Paris, 1818 2 8 Orfila, Treatise on Poisons, Fr. Paris, 1825 1 12 Orfila, Lectures on Legal Medicine, Fr. Paris, 1823 2 8 Plenck, Elements of Medical &amp; Surgical Jurisprudence, Lat. Leyden, 1786 1 8 Remer, Pharmaco-Chemical Judiciary Police, Fr. 1816 1 8 Webster, Essay on Medical Jurisprudence, Philadelphia, 1824 1 8 Zacohias, Medico-legal Questions, Lat Nuremburg, 1726 1 f</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER XVI ANATOMY, SOUND AND MORBID. Vols. Size. Albinus, Plates of the Bones, Muscles &amp;c. with descriptions, Lat. Leyden, 1747, large folio Antomarchi, Anatomical Plates, with descriptions, Fr. Paris, large folio Béclard, Elements of General Anatomy, French, Paris, 1823 1 8 Bell, (C.) Eugravings of Arteries, London, 1807 1 4 Bell, (C.) Anatomy of the Brain, London, 1802 1 4 Bell, (C.) Anatomy of the Bones &amp; Muscles, Lond. 1810 1 4 Bichat, (X.) General Anatomy, and on Life and Death, Fr. Paris, 1818 2 8 Bichat, (X.) General Anatomy, by Coffyn and Calvert, Eng. London, 1824 2 8 Pathological Anatomy, by Béclard &amp; Boisseau,, Paris, 1825 1 8 Bichat, Treatise on the Membres, by Husson, French, Paris, 1816 1 8 Blumenbach, Collections of Crania of different Nations, Latin, Gottingen, 1790 1 4 Bonetus, "Sepulchretum" of Anatomy, Latin, Geneva, 1700 2 f Cheselden, Anatomy of the Human Body, Boston, 1806 1 8 Clark, (Wm.) Analysis of a Course of Lectures on Anatomy and Physiology, Cambridge, 1822 1 8 Cloquet, on the Formation of the Skeleton, French, Paris, 1819 1 4 Cloquet, Plates of Human Anatomy, with descriptions, French, Paris, 1824, folio. Cruveilhier, Essay on Pathological Anatomy, French, Paris, 1806 2 8 Curtis, Map of the Ear Eustachius, Anatomical Tables, by Lancisi, Lat. 1717 1 f Eye, Map of the Fabricius ab Acquapendente, Anatomical and Physiological Works, Latin, Leyden, 1737 1 f Fyfe, Compendium of Anatomy, Edinburgh, 1823 2 8 Green, Dissector's Manual, London, 1820 1 8 Heister, Compendium of Anatomy, Latin, Amsterdam, 1748 1 8 Hooper, Plates of the Bones &amp; Muscles, London, 1818 1 12 Kirtland, Anatomical Plates of Bones and Muscles, London, 180 1 8 Kirtland, view of the principal Blood vessels of the Heart. Kirtland, view of &amp;c. of the Head Kirtland, the Arm Kirtland, Anterior and Psteoir views of the Blood vessels of the Thigh Lewis, views of the Muscles, London, 1820 1 4 Lieutaud, Anatomico—Medical Observations, Latin, Paris, 1767 2 4 Lizars, Anatoical Plates and Explanations, Edinburgh Lobstein on the Great Sympathetic, its structure, uses and diseases, Latin, Paris, 1823 1 4 Mackenzie, on the necessity of affording Bodies to the Schools of Anatomy, Glasgow, 1824 1 8 Marjolin, Manual of Anatomy, French Paris, 1815 2 8 Mascagni, Anatomy of the Human Body, (Prospectus.) Italian, sa, 1822 1 f Monre, Elements of Anatomy, Edinburgh, 1825 2 8 Outlines of Anatomy, 1813 4 8 Oribasius, Anatomical Observations, by Rasori &amp; Dundass, Latin, Leyden 1735 1 4 Prochaska, on the Structure of the Nerves, Latin, Vienna, 1789 1 8 Rayer, Abridged History of Pathological Anatomy, Fr. Paris, 81 1 8 Rose, Manual of Morbid Anatomy, by Marc, French, Paris, 1808 1 8 Scarpa, Anatomical Annotations, Lat. 1 4 Senac, on the Structure of the Heart, Fr. Paris, 1788 2 4 Shaw, Manual of Anatomy; London, 1822 2 8 Sue Elements of Anatomy for the use of Painters Fr. 1 4 Tedeann, Anatomy of the Brain, by Jourdan, French, Paris, 1825 1 8 Vieq d'Azyr, Plates of the Brain, Fr. Paris, 1813 1 4 Wenzel, Observations on the Cerebellum, French, Paris, 1811 1 8 Weber on the Nervous System, Latin, Leipsic, 1 8 Wilson, on the Bones &amp;c. London, 1820 1 8 Wilson, on the Urinary &amp; Genital Organs, 1821 1 8 Winslow, Anatomy of the Human Body, by Douglas, 1763 1 4</field>
      <field name="fulltext">H CHAPTER XVII. PHYSIOLOGY. Vols. Size Barthez, Elements of the Science of Man, French, Paris, 1806 2 8 Bell, (C.) Letter to, from Mr. Mayo, See Mayo Blumnbach, Physiological Institutes, Latin, Gottingen, 1810 1 8 Blumnbach, by Elliotson, Eng. London, 1817 1 8 Brachet, on the Functions of the Ganglionic System of Nerves, French, Paris &amp; Lyons. 1823 1 8 Cabanis, Connexion between the Mind and the Body, by Tracy, Paris, 1815 2 8 Crawford, on Animal Heat, See Chemistry Demangeon, on the power of the imagination on the Foetus in utero, Paris, 1807 1 8 Descartes, Treatise on Man, and on the formation of the Foetus, Latin, Amsterdam, 1686 1 4 Dumas, Principles of Physiology, Fr. Paris, 1806 4 8 Flourens, Experimental Researches on the Nervous system; Fr. Paris, 1824 1 8 Flourens, Supplement to do. Fr. Paris, 1825 1 8 Fodera, on Absorption and Exhalation, Fr. Paris, 1824 1 8 Foville and Pinel, on the Functions of the Nervous System, French, Paris, 1 8 Gall and Spurzheim, Researches on the Nervous System, French, Paris, 1826 1 8 Gall, on the Functions of the Brain, Fr. Paris, 1825 6 8 Georget, on the Physiology of the Nervous System, Fr. Paris, 1821 2 8 Haller, Elements of Physiology, Lat. 177 8 4 Hare, Physiological views on Digestion, 2d Edition, London. 1824 1 8 Lawrence, Lectres on Physiology, &amp;c. 1822 1 8 Lobstein, on the Nutrition of the Foetus, French, Strasburg. 1802 1 4 Lobstein, on the pre-eminence of the Nervous System, French, Strasburg, 1821 1 4 Magendie, on some discoveries relative to the Nervous System, French, Paris, 1823 1 4 Mayo's Anatomical and Physiological Commentaries, London, 1823-4 1 8 Mayo's Letter to Sir A. Cooper, on Mr. C. Bell's discoveries, Richerand, New Elements of Physiology, French, P ris, 1811 1 8 Richerand, New Elements by De Lys &amp; Copland, London, 1824 1 8 Serres, Researches on the Functions of the Corebellum, French, Paris, 1823 1 8 Spallanzani, Physical Opuscula, by Senebier, French, Paris, 1787 2 8 Spallanzani, on Generation, by Senebier, Fr. Paris 1 8 Spallanzani, on the Circulation &amp;c. by Tourdes, Geneva, 1 8 Spallanzani, on Respiration, by Senebier, Paris, 1803 1 8 Spurzheim, on Phrenology, Fr. Paris, 1803 1 8 Tiedemann &amp; Gmelin, on Absorption &amp;c. French, Paris, 1821 1 8 Virey, Natural History of Man, See Nat. History Warren, (J. C.) on the Sensorial and Nervous Systems of Man and Animals, Boston, 1822 1 8</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER XVIII PATHOLOGY AND THERAPEUTICS. Vols. Size. Alibert, Outlines of Diseases of the Skin, French, Paris, 1822 2 8 Alpinus (Proer,) on Prognosis, Lat. Leyden, 1738 1 4 Andral Junr. Clinical Medicine, Fr. Paris, 1823 2 8 Annesley, Sketches of the Diseases of India, London, 1825 1 8 Aretæus, on the causes and signs of Diseases, Latin, Vienna, 1790 1 8 Armstrong, on Typhus and other Febrile Diseases, London, 1818 1 8 Armstrong, on Scarlet Fever, Measles &amp;c. London, 1818 1 8 Astruc, on Venereal Diseases. London, 1754 1 4 Badeley, Case of Cure, by Prince Hohenlohe, London, 1823 1 8 Bally, Francois and Pariset, on the Yellow Fever of Spain, French, Paris, 1823 1 8 Barlow, on Pathology &amp;c. Bath. 1822 1 8 Bayle, on Chronic Arachnitis, Fr. Paris, 1822 1 4 Begin, Pathological Physiology, Fr. Paris, 1821 1 8 Begin, Physiological Doctrine, applied to Surgery, Fr. Paris, 1823 1 8 Bell. Treatise-on the Cow-Pox, Edinburgh, 1807 12 Boerhaave, See Van Swieten. Boerhaave, Letters to Bassand, Lat. Vienna, 1778 1 8 Boerhaave, Lectures on Lues Venre Latin, Frankfort, 71 1 8 Boerhaave, on the Institutes of Medicine, edited by Haller, Latin, Leyden, 1758 7 8 Boerhaave, Practice of Physic, Lat. Urcht, 1745 5 8 Boerhaave, Medical Institutes, Lat. Leyden, 1746 1 8 Boerhaave, Aphorisms for knowing and curing Diseases, Latin, Leyden, 1758 1 8 Boerhaave, on Lues Venerea, Latin, Leyden, 1751 1 8 Boerhaave, Lectures on Diseases of the Nerves, Latin, Leyden, 1761 2 8 Booth, on Hydrophobia, London, 1824 1 8 Boyer, on Surgical Diseases, Fr Paris, 1822 10 8 Boyle, on the Diseases of hot and cold Climates, London, 1823 1 12 Brown's Elements of Medicine, by Beddoes, London, 1795 2 8 Caffin, Physiological, Pathological, and Therapeutical Deductions, French, Paris, 1822 1 8 Campbell, on Epidemic Purpral Fever, Edinburgh, 1822 8 Capuron, Treatise on the diseases of Children, French, Paris, 1820 1 8 Capuron, on the diseases of Women, Fr. Paris, 1817 1 8 Celsus, on Medical Subjects, Lat. Paris, 1529 1 4 Celsus, Translated by Greive. Edinburgh, 1814 1 8 Chomel, Elements of General Pathology, French, Paris, 1826 1 8 Clericus, on the Tape Worm, Lat. Genera, 1715 1 4 Cooke, on Epilepsy, London, 1823 1 8 Cooke, Mr. W. Translation of Morgagni, See Morgagni, Cooke, Mr. W. on Hydrocephalus actus London, 1819 1 8 Cooper, Sir A. Lectures on Surgery, London, 1824 1 8 Corvisart, Essay on diseases of the Heart, French, Paris, 1818 1 8 Crichton, Sir A. on Pulmonary Consumption, London, 1823 1 8 Cullen's Practice of Physic, by Rotheram, New-York, 1806 2 8 Cullen's Methodical Synopsis of Diseases, Latin, Edinburgh, 1813 1 8 Delpech, on Surgical Diseases, Fr. Paris, 1816 6 8 Delpech, Clinical Surgery of Montpellier, Fr. Paris, 1823 1 4 Desportes, Treatise on Angina Pectoris, Fr. Paris, 181 1 8 Desault, Surgical Works, by Bichat, Fr. Paris, 83 3 8 Deveze, Treatise on the Yellow Fever, Fr. Paris, 1820 1 8 Dsruelles, Treatise on the Croup. Fr. Paris, 1824 1 8 Dorsey's Elements of Surgery, Philadelphia, 1823 2 8 Double, General Semeiology, Fr. Paris, 1811 3 8 Dunglison, on Diseases of the Stomach and Bowels of Children, London, 1824 1 8 Dunglison, Edition of Hooper's Surgeon's Vade mecum, See Hooper Falret, on Hypochondriasis &amp; Suicide, Fr. Paris, 1822 1 8 Fodre, Treatise on Goitre &amp; Cretinism, Fr. Paris, 1800 1 8 Foot, on Lus Venerea; London, 1820 1 8 Fothergill, Dr. S. on Ti Douloureux, London, 1804 1 12 Fouquet, Essay on the Pulse, French, Montpellier, 1818 1 8 Frank, on the cure of Diseases, Lat. Paris, 1807-13 8 8 Gaubius, Pathological Institutes. Lat. Leyden, 1763 1 8 Georget, on Insanity, French, Paris, 1820 1 8 Good, Study of Medicine, London, 1822 4 8 Gregory, Dr. G. Elements of the Theory and Practice of Physic, London, 1823 2 8 Hamilton, on the Diseases of Children, Edinburgh 1 8 Henke on Nervous Mastodynia, Lat. Berlin, 1 8 Hevin, Course of Surgical Pathology &amp; French Paris, 1793 2 8 Hooper, Physician's Vade mecum, London, 1823 1 12 Hooper, Surgeon's Vade mecum, London, 1824 1 12 Hutchinson, (Mr. B.) Cases of Neuralgia Spasmodica, London, 1822 1 8 Itard, Treatise on Diseases of the Ear, Fr. Paris, 1821 2 8 Jackson, Discourse on Fever, Boston, 1818 1 8 Jackson, Syllabus of Lectures on Practice of Physic, Boston 8 Jackson, Text Book of Lectures on Theory of Medicine, Boston, 1826 1 8 Janin, Memoirs on the Eye, French, Lyon and París, 1772 1 8 Johnson, on Tropical Diseases, London, 1818 1 8 Labonnardiere, on Hydrophobia, Fr. Paris, 1820 1 4 Lalouette, on Hydrophobia, Fr. Paris, 1812 1 8 Landr-Beauvais, Semeiology, Fr. Paris, 1818 1 8 Larrey, Military Surgery, Fr. Paris, 1812 4 8 Larrey, Surgical Memoirs, Fr. Paris, 1 8 Laire, Treatise on the Teeth, Fr. Paris, 1822 3 8 Lassus, Surgical Pathology, Fr. Paris, 1809 2 8 Lommius, Medical Observations, Latin, Amsterdam, 1745 1 8 Le Dran, Consultations in Surgery, Fr Paris, 1745 1 8 Louis, Surgical Works, Fr Paris, 1788 2 8 Macmichael, new view of the Infection of Scarlet Fever, London, 1822 1 8 Macilwain, on Stricture of the Urethra, London, 1824 1 8 Magendie, Researches on the Gravel, Fr. Paris, 1818 1 8 Martinet, Treatise on Chronic Diseases, Fr. Paris, 1808 1 8 Morgagni, on the seats aud causes of Diseases, abridged by Cooke, London, 1822 2 8 Newman, on Hydropic Diseases, Winchester 1822 1 8 Ollivier, Treatise on Traumatic Typhus, French, Paris, 1822 1 8 Olombel, on verminous Diseases, Fr. Paris, 1816 1 8 Ozanam, on Epidemic Diseases, French, Paris, and Lyon, 5 8 Palletta, Pathological Exercises, Lat. Milan, 1820 1 4 Parent-Duchatelet and Martinet, on Arachnitis, French, Paris, 1825 1 8 Pelletan, Clinical Surgery, Fr. Paris, 1810 3 8 Petit, on Hereditary Diseases, Fr. Paris, 1817 1 8 Petit, on Surgical Diseases, Fr. Paris, 1790 3 8 Percy, Surgical Pyrotechny, Fr. Paris, 1811 1 8 Philip, (Dr. A. P. W.) on Indigéstion, London, 1822 1 8 Pinel, Junr. on Diseases of the Brain, Fr. Paris, 1821 1 8 Pinel, Senr. on Mental Alienation, Fr. Paris, 1809 1 8 Pinel, Senr. on Clinical Medicine, Fr. Paris, 1815 1 8 Pinel, Senr. Philosophical Nosography, Fr. Paris, 1818 3 8 Plumbe, on Diseases of the Skin, London, 1824 1 8 Portal, on Dropsy, French, Paris, 1824 2 8 Pott, Surgical Works, London, 1783 3 8 Pring, Principles of Pathology, London, 1823 1 8 Pouteau, Surgical Memoirs, French, Lyon, 1760 1 8 Pringle, on Diseases of the Army, Philadelphia, 1810 1 8 Prost; Medicine improved by experience, French, Paris, 1804 2 8 Pujol, Works on practical Medicine, Fr. Paris, 1823 4 8 Puzos, on Hæmorrhage, Fr. Paris, 1801 1 8 Rasori, History of the Petechial Fever of Genoa, Fr. Paris, 1822 1 8 Rayer, Memoir on Inflammation, Fr. Paris, 1821 1 8 Rayer, Report on Yellow Fever, Fr. Paris, 1822 1 8 Redi, ou Animals inhabiting the Human Body, See Natural History, Richerand, Surgical Nosography, Fr. Paris, 1821 4 8 Richerand, Case of cutting out a Rib, Fr. Paris, 1818 1 8 Rochoux, Researches on Apoplexy, Fr. Paris, 1814 1 8 Rochoux, Researches on Yellow Fever, French, Paris, 1822 1 8 Rosen de Rosenstein, on the Diseases of Children, Fr. Paris, 1778 1 8 Rostan, on softening of the Brain. Fr. Paris, 1823 1 8 Rouppe, on the Diseases of Sailors, Lat. Leydn 1764 1 8 Roux, Surgical Melanges, Fr. Paris, 1809 1 8 Rouzet, Researches on Cancer, Fr. Paris, 1818 1 8 Rudolphi, on Intestinal Worms &amp;c. See Zoology. Rush, Medical Inquiries on Diseases of the Mind, Philadelphia, 1818 1 8 Rush, Observations on Diseases of the Army, See Pringle, Philadelphia, 1810 1 8 Rush, Medical Inquiries &amp;c. Philadelphia, 1818 2 8 Rush, Works of Sydenham, Philadelphia, 1809 1 8 Sacco, on Vaccination, by Daquin, Fr. Paris, 1813 1 8 Sahctoruis, on Medical Statics. Lat. Paris, 1775 2 8 St. Martin, Essay on Hydrophobia, Fr. Paris, 1823 1 8 Sauvages, Methodical Nosography, Latin, Amsterdam, 2 4 Scarpa, on the principal Diseases of the Eyes, Italian, Pavia, 1801 1 4 Scarpa, on the principal Diseases by Briggs, London, 1818 1 8 Scarpa, on Aneism, by Wishdrt, Edinburgh; 1819 1 8 Scarpa, on Heruia, by Wishdrt, Edinburgh; 1814 1 8 Scarpa, on Scirrhus &amp; Cancer, by Briggs, Lond. 1822 8 Sharp, Critical enquiry into the present state of Surgery, London, 1750 8 Shearman, on Chronic Debility, London, 1824 8 Shearman, on Water in the Brain, London, 1825 8 Stevenson, on Nature and symptoms of Cataract, London, 1824 8 Stoll, Practice of Medicine, Lat. Paris, 1777 1 8 Storck, Medico-practical precepts, Lat. Vienna, 1791 2 8 Swediaur, on Syphilitic Diseases, Fr. Paris, 1817 2 8 Tacheron, on Practical Medicine, Fr. Paris, 1823 3 8 Troilliet, on Hydrophobia, Fr. Lyon &amp; Paris, 1820 1 8 Underwood, Diseases of Children, Paris, 1795 1 8 Velpeau, on some affections of the Spinal Marrow, Fr. Paris, 1 8 Valentin, researches on Croup, Fr. Paris, 1812 1 8 Valentin, Treatise on the Yellow Fever, Fr. Paris, 1803 1 8 Van Swieten, Commentaries on Boerhaave's Aphoris, Latin, Turin, 1744 1 4 Vaughan, Essay on Headache, London, 1825 1 8 Venables, on Diabetes, London, 1825 8 Vassal, on the Transmission of the Venereal virus, Fr. Paais, 1807 1 8 Verney Du, Treatise on diseases of the Bnes, French, Paris, 1751 2 8 Waterhouse, Essay on the Whooping Cough, Boston, 1822 1 8 White, Doubts of Hydrophobia as a specific Disease, London, 1826 1 8 Wilson, on the Blood &amp;c. London, 181 1 8 Yates, on Neuralgia, London, 1822 8</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER XIX. OPERATIVE SURGERY. Vols. Size. Alcock, on Fractures of the Patella and Olecranon, London, 1823 8 Alcock, section of the leg after amputation Baslha, on the lateral operation of Lithotomy, French, Paris, 1804 1 8 Bell, C. Oprrative Surgery, Hartford, 1816 2 8 Bell, on injuries of the Spine and Thigh bone, London, 1824 4 Bowen, on the removal of Cataract, by Hyalonyxis, London, 1824 8 Clobury, review of Operations performed on the Eye, London, 1826 8 Coster, Manual of Surgical Operations, French, •Paris, 1825 4 8 Dlau, Memoir on the perforation of the Tympaum, French, Paris, 1822 1 8 Dionis, Course of Surgical Operations, Fr. Paris, 1782 2 8 Earle, Practical Observations on Surgery, London, 1823 1 8 Fabrioius ab acquapendente, Surgical Works, Latin, Leyden, 1723 1 f Heister, Surgical Institutes, Amsterdam, 1750 2 4 Key, C. on Lithy, London, 1824 1 4 Lithotomy, Method of Performing, 1779 1 8 Maingault, Treatise on Amputations, plates, French, Paris, 1822 f Roux, New Elements of Operative Surgery, French, Paris, 1813 2 8 Sabatier, Operative Surgery, Fr. Paris, 1822 4 8 Sanson, means of reaching the Bladder by the Rectum, French. Paris, 1821 1 8 Sarlandiere, Vade mcum of Military Surgery, French, Paris, 1823 1 8 Sleigh, on the posterior operation of Lithotomy, London, 1824 1 8 Vacca Berlinghieri, on Lithotomy, French, Geneva and Paris, 1828 1 8 For Works on Surgical Diseases, see Pathology</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I CHAPTER XX. OBSTETRICS. Vols. Size Baudelocque, Art of Midwifery, Fr. Paris, 1822 2 8 Blundell, Syllabus of Lectures on Midwifery, London, 1821 1 8 Capuron, Course of Midwifery, Fr. Paris, 1823 1 8 Conquest. on Obstetric Instruments, and on the use of Belladonna in Protracted Labour, Lond 1823 pamphlet Dewees, System of Midwifery. Philadelphia, 1824 1 8 Gardien, Treatise on Midwifery, Fr. Paris, 1824 4 8 Haighton and Blundell, Syllabus &amp;c. See Blundell Levret on Midwifery, Fr. Paris, 1777 1 8 Maygrier, Plates on Midwifery, with Descriptions, Fr. Paris, 1825 Mauriceau, on Midwifery, Fr. Paris, 1740 2 4 Powers, Treatise on Midwifery, 2d edit. London, 1823 1 8 Smellie, Treatise on Midwifery, Dublin, 1765 4 12</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER XXI. VETERINARY MEDICINE. Vols. Size Bourgelat, Elements of the Veterinary Art, Fr. Par. 1807 3 8 Giraud, on Veterinary Anatomy Fr. Par. 1819 3 8 Giraud, on the foot of Domestic Animals, Fr. Par. 1813 1 8</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER XXII. GENERAL MEDICINE. Vols. Size Aetius, Tetrabiblos, Latin Leyden, 1249 1 f Avicenna's Works, Latin. Vnic, 1608 2 f Baglivi Works, Latin, Leyden, 1710 1 4 Blane, Sir G. Select Dissertations on Medical Science, London, 1822 1 8 Blane, Sir G. Elements of Medical Logic, London, 1825 1 8 Boerhaave, Method of Teaching Medicine, Latin, Leyden, 1784 1 8 Cardan's Works, Latin, Leyden, 1663 10 f Clark's Medical Notes on Climate &amp;c. of. France, Italy and Switzerland, London, 1820 1 8 Derenzy, Enchiridion or Hand for the one Handed, London, 1822 8 Forestus Works, Latin, Rouen, 1653 2 f Fothergill, Dr. John, Works by Lettsom, London, 1784 1 4 Freind's Works, Latin, Leyden, 1650 1 f Galen's Works, Gr. &amp; Lat. Leipsic 10 8 Harvey's Works, Latin Leyden. 1737 1 4 Hippocrates, Works, Gr. &amp; Lat. Geneva, 1657 1 f Hippocrates, Vander-Linden, Gr. &amp; Lat. Leyd. 1765 1 f Hoffman's Works, Latin. Geneva. 1748 6 f Hooper. Examinations in Anatomy, Physiology &amp;c. London 1820 1 12 Hosack, Dr. D Medical Essays, New-York, 1824 2 8 Leeuenhoek, `Arcana Naturæ" See Nat. Hist. Legallois' Works, by Pariset, Fr. Paris, 1824 2 8 Liæus, Amœnitates Academicæ. See Nat. Hist. Malpighi, Posthumous Works, Lat. Amsterdam, 1700 1 4 Mead, Medical Works. Edinburgh, 1765 3 8 Morgagni's Works Latin, Bassano, 1765 2 f Morton's Works, Latin, Geneva, 1727 6 4 Paracelsus's Work, Latin, Geneva 2 f Ploucquet, Medical Literature Lat. Tubingen, 1808 Pouteau, Posthumous Works Fr. Lyons, 1783 3 8 Rufus Ephesius, Works, Lat. London, 1737 4 Sennertus's Works, Latin, Leyden, 1650 3 f Sutleffe, Mr. Medical and Surgical Cases, London, 1824 1 8 Sydenham's Works by Rush, Philadelphia, 1809 1 8 Vicq d'Azyr's Works, by Moreau, Fr. Paris, 1805 6 8 Vogel's Prælectiones Academicæ, Lat Lausannè, 1788 1 8 Young, Dr. Introduction to Medical Literature. London, 1823 1 8 MEDICAL TRANSACTIONS, DICTIONARIES, PERIODICALS, &amp;c Memoirs of the Royal Academy of Surgery, French, Paris, 1819 4 8 Prizes of the Royal Academy of Surgery, Fr. Paris, 1819 5 8 Memoirs of the Medical Society of Emulation, Paris, 8 8 Memoirs and Prizes of the Society of Medicine Paris, 1 8 Transactions of the Associated Apothecaries of England, and Wales, London, 1823 1 8 Transactions of the Medical Society of Lyons, reported by Gilibert, French Dictionary of Medical Sciences, Fr. Paris, 60 8 Castelli, Medical Lexicon, Lat. Geneva, 1766 1 4 Cooper's Surgical Dictionary, London, 1822 1 8 Hooper's Medical Dictionary, London, 1820 1 8 Nysten's Medical Dictionary, by Bricheteau, French, Paris, 1824 1 8 Par's Medical Dictionary, London, 1809 2 4 Anderson's Journal of the Medical Sciences, London, since 1824 Edinburgh Medical and Surgical Journal, Edinburgh, since 1824 Johnson's Medico-Chirurgical Journal and Review, London, since 1824 London Medical Intelligencer, for 1823, edited by Dr Dugliso London Medical and Physical Journal, since 1824 London Medical Repository, from the commencement. American Medical Recorder Philadelphia, since 1824 Philadelphia Journal of the Medical Sciences, 1824 North American Medical &amp; Surgical Journal, 1824 New-York Medical &amp; Physical Journal, New-York Review, (Medical) Fr. Paris, since 1824 Journal of Physiology, by Magendie. Fr. Paris, since 1824 Bulletin of the Medical Sciences, (Ferussac's) since 1824</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER XXIII. MENTAL PHILOSOPHY AND ETHICS. Vols. Size Antomnus Marcus, Moral Reflexions, by Dacier, Fr. 1778 2 8 Aristotle, See Antient Languages Aristotle, by Gillies. See Antient Languages Bacon's Works, London, 1765 5 4 Batteaux, History of First causes, Fr. Paris, 1767 1 8 Batteaux, Morals of Epicurus, See Epicurus in Antient History Berkeley's Works, See Miscell. Bouterwek, Æsthetics, German, Gottingen, 1815 1 12 Brown's Philosophy, Philadelphia, 1824 3 8 Bonnet's Works, See Natural History Cicero de Officiis. See Antient Languages Condillao's Works, French, Paris, 1822 16 8 Condorcet, Progress of the Mind, Fr. Paris, 1795 1 8 Des Cartes' Works, See Miscell. Latin, Amsterdam, 1692 9 4 Diderot's Works, See Miscell. Eberhard, (J. A.) Manual of Æsthetics, German, Hall, 1807 2 12 Epictetus, See Antient Languages Epicurus, See Batteaux Entield's History of Philosophy, London, 1819 2 8 Fichte, on the Duties of Learned Men, Ger. Berlin, 1806 1 12 Garve's Essays on Ethics, German, Breslow, 1819 5 12 Garve's on the Connexion of Ethics with Politics, German, Leipsig, 1798 1 12 Godwin's Political Justice, London, 1793 2 4 Gruber, on the Destination of Man, Ger. Zurich, 180 2 12 Hartley, on Man. London, 1791 3 8 Helvetius, on the Mind, French, London, 1776 2 8 on Man, French, London, 1775 2 8 Hobbes, Philosophical Works, Lat. Amsterdam. 1668 1 4 Hoffman, on the developement of the Human Faculties, German. Basle, 1805 1 8 Homes Art of Thinking, Glasgow. 1819 1 8 Hume's Essays, Edinburgh, 1800 2 8 Hutchinson, Inquiry into the original of four Ideas of Beauty, London, 1726 1 8 Hutcheson, System of Moral Philosophy, London, 1765 2 4 Leibnitz, Works complete Lat. Geneva, 1768 2 8 Locke's Works, See Miscell London, 1824 9 8 Locke's Essays, Boston. 1813 2 8 Logic, or the Art of Thinking, Fr. Paris, 1752 1 8 Lossius, Philosophical Lexicon, German, 1803 4 8 Lossius, Modern Philosophical Literature, German, Halle, 1778 3 8 Lossius, Instruction of Sound Reason, German, 1777 1 8 Meiners, Philosophical Writings, Ge Leipsic, 1775 3 12 Meiners, on the Mind, German, Gottingen, 1806 2 8 Moralists, French, See Miscell. Paley's Philosophy, London, 1788 2 8 Plato, See Antient Languages Plotinus, See Antient Languages, Supp. Poelitz, Æsthetics, German, Leipsic, 1807 1 8 Price, on Morals, London, 78 1 8 Reid's Works, Charleston, 1813 4 8 Renouard, Elements of Morals. Fr. Paris, 1824 1 8 Rochefoucault's Maxims &amp;c. See Miscell. Seneca. See Antient Langcages Sintenis, on the worth of Man, German, Leipsic, 1817 1 12 Smith, Theory of Moral Sentiments Boston 1817 1 8 Spalding, on the destination of Man, Boston 1817 1 12 Stewart, Elements of Moral Philosophy, Philadelphia, 1811 1 8 Tracy. (De Stutt) Elements of Ideology, Fr. Paris, 1818 1 8 Wagner, Ideal Philosophy, German, Fr. Paris, 1804 1 8 Wagner, Doctrine of Wisdom and Virtue, Fr. Paris, 1822 1 12 Whitby, (D.) Compendium of Ethios for the use of Schools, London. 1724 1 8</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER XXIV POLITICAL ECONOMY. Vols. Size Colquhoun, See Politics Everett, on Population, Boston, 1823 1 8 Jacobs, Science of Finances, Germau, Halle, 1821 2 8 Lauderdale, (Lord) on Public Wealth, Edinburgh, 1804 1 8 Malthus on Pouulation. Washington, 1809 2 8 Mirabeau, Theory of Import, Fr 1561 1 8 Petty's Survey of Ireland, London, 1719 1 8 Pryme's Lecture on Political Economy, Cambridge, 1823 1 8 Raymond, on Political Economy, Baltimore. 1820 1 8 Ricardo, on Political Economy, London, 1821 1 8 Seybert, Statistical Annals, Philadelphia, 1818 1 4 Say Political Economy, Paris, 1819 2 8 Smith, Wealth of Nations, London, 1812 3 8 Steuart, Political Economy, London, 1767 2 4 Turgot's Works, French, Paris, 1811 9 8</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER XXV POLITICS. Vols. Size Acts of the General Assembly of Virginia, from 1819 to 1827 Acts of 1st &amp; 2d Sessions of 18th Congress 2 8 Adams, Defence of the Constitution and Government of the United States, London, 1787 3 8 Adams, (John Quincy) on Weights and Measures, Philadelphia, 1821 1 8 American Remembrancer, Philadelphia, 1795 3 8 American Constitutions, New-York, 1820 1 18 Argenson. (Marquis d') Leisures of a Minister of State, French, Paris, 1787 1 8 Asby and White's Case, 1705 1 8 Bacon, Discourses on Government, London, 1760 1 4 Bentham, (J.) Treatise on Legislation, Dumont, French Paris, 1820 3 8 Bentham, (J.) Essay on Political Tactics, London, 1791 1 4 Bentham, (J.) King against Sir Charles Wolseley, London, 1820 1 8 Bentham, (J.) Truth vesus Asthurst, London, 1823 1 8 Bentham, (J.) Theory of Punishments, See Law, Bodin, Abridgment of the Republic of Fr. London, 1755 2 12 Brand, on the rights of Colonies, Latin, Leyden, 1820 1 8 Burgh, Political Disquisitions, ondon, 1774 3 8 Cardan's Political Arcana, Latin, Leyden, 1635 1 18 Cartwright, on the English Constitution. London, 1823 1 8 Castiglioni, The Courtier, Italian Milan, 1803 1 8 Chalmer's Treatise London, 1790 2 8 Chastellux, on Public Felicity, Fr. Bouillon, 1776 1 8 Code, (Civil) French, Paris, 1819 12 8 Code, (Civil) Conference of, Fr. Paris, 1805 8 8 Code, of Civil Procedure. Fr. 1808 2 8 Code, of Penal procedure, Fr. Paris, 1812 2 8 Code, of Criminal Institution, Fr. Paris, 1 8 Code, of Commerce, Fr. Paris, 1812 1 8 Colquhoun. Police of the Metropolis, London, 1800 1 8 Concilia Britannica, Wilkins, 446 ad 1717, Latin, London, 1737 4 f Convention, Federal Journals of, Boston, 1819 1 8 Cotton's Posthumous Works, by Stowel, London, 1672 1 8 Cujaius Works, Latin, Paris 8 f Debates in Massachusetts Convention, Boston, 1808 1 8 Debates in New-York Convention, Albany, 1821 1 8 Debates in relative to the affairs of Ireland, in the years 1763 and 1764, London, 1766 2 8 Debates in See Parliamentary History Debrett, State Papers, London. 1802 11 8 De Lolme, on the English Constitution, London, 1822 1 8 Dupin's Military Force of Great Britain, London, 1822 2 8 Dupin's Commercial Power, London, 1825 2 8 Commercial Plates, London, 1 8 Eton, Survey of the Turkish Empire, London, 1799 1 8 Everett's America. Philadelphia, 1827 1 8 Federalist, Halloicell, 1826 1 8 Ferguson, on Civil Society London. 1793 1 8 Fichte, on Civil Polity, German, Berlin, 1820 1 8 Filmer. on Government, London, 1679 1 12 Fortescue, Difference between an Absolute and Limited Monarchy, London. 1714 1 8 Gordon's History of Parliament; London, 1731 2 8 Harrington's Oceana, Toland, London, 1737 1 f Hazard's State Papers, Philadelphia, 1792 2 4 Heeren, Ideas of the Politics, &amp;c. of the Principal Nations of the antient World, German, Gottingen 4 8 Heineccius, Elements of Civil Law. Lat. Leyden, 1741 1 8 Heraldus, Daily Questions in Attic and Roman Law, Latin, Paris, 1550 1 f Hooker Works on Eccletical Polity; London, 1822 3 8 Jeanin, Negotiations of, Paris, 1659 2 12 Journals, Senate 5 8 Journals, Congress, 4 8 Journals, Secret, of Congress, 4 8 Journals, of the State Senate, Richmond, 1806, 1 f Journals. of the House of Delegates, 1777 to 1780 for 1792 and from 1810 to 1827 of the Convention of Virginia, 1778, Richmond, 1827 1 8 K La Riviere, Order of Societies, Fr. London, 1767 2 8 Le Trosne on Social Order, Fr. Puris, 1777 1 8 Louis XVI. Trial of, See Trial Memoirs of the Commissioners on the French &amp; English rights in America, Fr. Paris, 755 4 4 Miller, on English Government, London, 1803 4 8 Mirabeau the friend of Man,F Hague, 1758 7 12 Montesuieu Works, Fr. Amsterdam, 1765 6 12 Montesuieu Posthumous Works, Fr. Paris, 1798 1 12 Montesuieu Commentary on the Spirit of Laws, French, Paris, 1819 1 12 More's Eutopia, by Dibdin, London 1808 2 8 Normann's Manual of Statistics, German, Hamburgh, 1785 8 8 Ordonnance, relating to the Marine. Fr. Paris, 1786 1 4 Ordonnance, relating to the Fr. Marseillas, 1780 2 12 Parliamentary, History of England to 1660 24 8 Parliamentary, Lord's Debates, 1660-1743 8 8 Parliamentary, Grey's Debates of the Commons, 1667 to 1694 10 8 Parliamentary, Lord's Protests, 1742 to 1771 2 8 Parliamentary, Lord's Protests, 1668 to 1744 24 8 Parliamentary, Commons Debates, 1660-1778 32 1 Parliamentary, by Hansard, 1803 to 1820 41 8 Pfeffel Public Law of Germany, Fr. Paris, 1776 2 4 Plowden's Jura Anglorum, London, 1719 1 8 Precedents of Proceedings in the House of Commons, London, 1796 4 4 Priestley, on Government, London, 1776 4 8 Sharp's Rights of the People, London, 1775 1 8 Sidney on Government, New-York, 1805 3 8 Social System, London 1 8 Somers's Tracts, by Scott. London, 1806 13 f Spelman's Concilia, London, 1639 1 f State Papers, 8 8 Trial of Louis XVI. French, Paris, 1822 1 8 Vess on Civil Polity, German, Leipsic 1796 6 8 Vess spirit of the most remarkable Alliances of the 18th century, German, 1801 5 12 Vess on the Vicissitudes of the Constitution of the German Empire, German, Leipsic 1802 1 12 Vess Library of Civil Polity, German, Leipsic, 1793 2 8 Walsh's Appeal. Philadelphia, 1819 1 8 Woofall's Debates, London, 19 8</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER XXVI LAW. Vols Size. Abbott, on Shipping. London, 1801 1 8 Aherly Britanni Constitution, London, 1727 1 f Aleyn's Reports, London, 1790 1 f Ambler's Reports, London, 1790 1 f Anderson's Reports, London, 1661 1 f Andrew's Reports, London, 1792 1 8 Argumentum Anti-Normannicum, 162 1 8 Ashe's Tables, London, 1614 2 1 Akyn's Reports, London, 1781 3 8 Azuni, Maritii Law, Fr. Paris, 1798 2 8 Bacon's Abridgement, by Gwillam, London, 1807 7 8 Bacon's (Francis) Law Tracts, London, 1740 1 8 Barues's Notes, London, 1790 1 8 Baron and Feme, London, 1788 1 8 Barrington's Observations, London, 1796 1 1 Barton's Elements of Conveyaning London, 1810 5 8 Barton's Suit in Equity, London, 1796 1 8 Beaver's Translation of the Roman Law, by Ferrire 1721 1 8 Beawe's Lex Mercatoria, Chitty, London, 1813 2 1 Beller's Universal Law, London, 1750 1 f Benlow's Reports, London, 1689 1 f Benloc's Reports, London, 1660 1 f Blackstone's Reports, London, 1790 2 f Blackstone's Law Tracts, Oxford, 1771 1 4 Blackstone's Commentaries, Christian, London, 1793 4 8 Blackstone's Analysis, Oxford, 1758 1 8 Blackstone's (H.) Reports, London, 1781 2 8 Blount's Law Dictionary, by Nelson, London, 1717 1 f Bohem's English Lawyer, London, 1732 1 8 Bohem's Introduction to the study of the Laws of England, 1732 1 8 Bohem's Privileges of London, London 1723 1 8 Booth, on Real Actions, Hill, London 1811 1 8 Bosanquet &amp; Puller's Reports, London 1814 3 8 Bosanquet &amp; Piller's New Reports, London, 1806 2 8 Boucher, Maratie Law, French. Paris, 1803 1 4 Boucher, Commercial Institutions. Fr. Paris, 1801 4 Bracton, on Law, Latin, London, 1569 1 f Bridgman's Conveyances, London, 1725 1 f Bridgman's Reports, London, 1659 1 f Bridgman's Law of Charitable uses, London, 1803 1 8 Bridgman's Digest, by R O Bridgman, London, 1822 3 8 Brevium, Thesaurus of, Latin, London, 1689 1 f Brisson, on the Signification of Words which pertain to the Law, 1 f Brooke's Abridgement, London, 1776 1 4 Brownlow's &amp; Goldsborough's Reports, London, 1675 1 4 Brown's Reports, by Belt, London, 1820 4 8 Brown's (G.) Remarks, London, 1701 1 8 Browne's Civil Law, London, 1802 2 8 Bullet's Nisi Prius, by Bridgman, London, 1817 1 8 Bulstrode's Reports, London, 1657 1 4 Burlamaquo, Principles of Natural Law, French, Geneva, 1717 1 4 Burn's Justice, by hetwynd London, 1823 5 8 Burn's Elesiastical Law, London, 1824 4 8 Burr's Trial, by Robertson, Philadelphia, 1808 2 8 Burrow's Reports, London, 1790 5 8 Butler's Horae Juridicae, London, 1807 1 8 Butler's on the legality of impressing Seamen, London, 1778 1 8 Bynkershock's Works, Latin, Leyden, 1752 6 4 Bynkershock's Works, complete, Leyden, 1767 2 f Call's Reports, by Tate, Richmond, 1824 3 8 Calthrop's Reports, London, 1 12 Calvin, Juridical Lexicon, London, 1759 2 f Canon Law, Body of, Lancelotti, Latn Venice, 172 2 4 Cartlrew's Reports, London, 1741 1 f Carter's Reports, London, 1688 1 f Cary's Reports, London, 1820 1 12 Cave's British Liberties, London, 1766 1 8 Chancery Cases, London, 1735 1 f Chancery Cases, London, 1725 1 f Chancery, Practice in the Court of, 1694 3 8 Chitty's Law of Nations, London, 1812 1 8 Chitty's on Bills of Exchange, London, 1822 1 8 Chitty's on Pleading, London, 1825 3 8 Chetwynd Treatise on Fines, London, 1773 1 4 Clerk, Practice of the English Court of Admiralty. Latin, London, 1679 1 12 Clerk of the Peace, Duties of, 1726 1 8 Gobbett's State Trials by Herwell, See State Trials Code of Humanity, 1778 1 4 Code, Theodosian, Ritterus, Leipsic, 1736 6 f Code, See Polities, Coke's Entries, London, 1761 1 f Coke's Reports, by Wilson, London, 1776 7 8 Coke's upon Littleton, by Hargrave and Butler, London, 1794 6 8 Coke's Littleton, abridged by Hawkins, London, 1822 1 12 Coke's First Institute with Notes. by Hargrave and Thomas, London, 1818 3 8 Collectanea Juridica, Latin, London, 2 8 Collis's Parliamentary Cases, 1697 to 1709, Dublin, 1789 1 8 Collier's Law of Patents, London, 1803 1 8 Comberbach's Reports, London, 1724 1 f Complete, Arbitrator, London, 1744 1 8 Common Law, Treatise on London, 1720 1 8 Comyn's Digest, Hammond, London, 1822 8 8 Comyn's Reports, Rose London, 1792 2 8 Conset's Practice of the Law, London, 1700 1 8 Cooper's Justinian, Philadelphia, 1812 1 8 Cooper's (G.) Cases in Chancery, London, 1815 1 8 Custms of Normandy, 1537 1 f Cotton's Records, London, 1657 1 f Coswell's Interpreter, London, 1658 1 f Cowper's Reports, London, 1800 2 8 Cox's Cases in Equity, London, 1816 2 8 Craig's (Sir Thomas) Foedal Law, Ballie, Latin, Edinburgh, 1732 1 f Cranch's Reports, New-York, 1812 9 8 Croke's Reports, London, 1683 3 f Crown Circuit Companion, by Minehin and Herbert, London, 1820 1 8 Crown Laws, Latin, 1680 1 8 Cruis's Digest, London, 1824 6 8 Cumberland's Law of Nature, by Maxwell, London, 1 4 Cunningham's Reports, London, 1770 1 f Cunningham's Law Dictionary, London, 1783 2 f Cunningham's on Bills, London, 1778 1 8 Dallas's Reports, Philadelphia, 1806 4 8 Dalrymple's Feudal Tenures, London, 1759 1 8 Dalton's Country Justice, London, 1690 1 f Dalton's Sheriffs, London, 1700 1 f D'Anver's Abridgement, London, 1725 3 f Davy's Reports London, 1628 1 f Dicken's Reports, Wyatt, London, 1803 2 8 Doctrine of Pleading, London, 1677 1 4 Domat's Civil Law, London, 1757 1 f Dominion of the Sea, London, 1 4 Douglass' Reports Frere, London, 1818 2 8 Dumont, Theory of Punishments, Fr. Paris, 1818 2 8 Durnford's &amp; East's Reports, London, 1817 8 8 Dunco b's Trials, London, 1766 1 8 East's Pleas of the Crown, London, 1803 2 8 Eden's Philosophy of Jurisprudence, Oxford, 1744 1 4 Equity Cases, Abridged, London, 1793 Oxford, 1744 2 f English Liberties, by Care, London, 1719 1 8 Erskine's Rights of Juries by Blanchard, London, 1785 1 8 Erskine's Sphcs, See Miscell. Espinasse's Nisi Prius, London, 1812 2 8 Espinasse's Penal Statutes. London, 1813 1 8 Evans's Decisions of Mansfield, London, 2 4 Fearne's Posthumous Works, Shadwell, London, 1797 1 8 Fearne's Contingent Remainders, Butler, London, 1824 1 8 Fchte's (J. A.) Principles of the Law of Nature, German, Jna, 1796 1 8 Finch, on Law, Pickering London, 1759 1 8 Finch, Precedents in Chancery, London, 1786 1 8 Fitz-Gibbon's Reports, London, 1732 1 f Fitzherbert's Abridgement 1 f Fitzherbert's Justice of the Peace, London, 1617 1 8 Fleta, Selden, London, 1647 1 4 Fonblanque's Equity, London, 1820 2 8 Fortescue, on the English Laws, Lat. London, 1741 1 f Foster's Crown Law, Dodson, London, 1809 1 8 Freeman's Reports by Dixon, London, 1742 1 f Francis's Maxims, London, 1728 1 f Furneau's Letters to Blackstone, London, 1771 1 8 Geesi on the Penal Code of Romagnosi, See Romagnosi Gibson's Codex, Oxford, 1761 2 f Gilbert's Reports, 72 1 f Gilbert's Law of Executions, London, 1763 1 8 Gilbert's on Rents, London, 1768 1 8 Gilbert's Distresses, London, 1780 1 8 Gilbert's on Trusts by Sugden, London, 1811 1 8 Gilbert's Law of Evidence by Laftt, Dublin 1795 4 8 Gilbert's on Tenures, Watkins &amp; c. London, 18 1 8 Gilbert's Chancery, London, 1768 1 8 Gilbert's Exch London, 1 1 8 Gilbert, on Common Pleas, London, 1779 1 8 Gilbert, on Cases in Law and Equity, Londen, 1760 1 8 Gilbert, Devises, London, 1773 1 8 Glanville, by Beames. London, 1812 1 8 Godolphin, Orphan's Legacy, London, 1701 1 4 Gravina, Rise and Progress of the Civil Law, Leipsic, 1768 1 4 Green's Index, London, 1818 1 8 Grotius, on War and Peace, with notes, by Barbeyrae, London, 1738 1 f Grotius, on the Law of War, Fr. Amsterdam,, 1724 1 4 Grotius, Mare liberum Latin, Leyden, 1633 1 18 Hakervel on Parliaments, Leyden, 1659 1 12 Hale's Jurisdiction, London, 1796 1 4 Hale's Pleas of the Crown, Emlyn, Wilson and Dougherty, London, 1800 2 8 Hale's Pleas of the Crown, by Jacob, London; 1716 1 8 Hale's History of the Common Law, by Rennington, London, 1820 1 8 Hallifax's Analysis of the Roman and Civil Law, Cambridge, 1795 1 8 Hall's Digested Indèx, Richmond, 1825 1 8 Hammond's Nisi Prius, London, 1816 1 8 Hand's Chancery, London, 1809 1 8 Hand's Law of Patents, London, 1808 1 8 Hardres's, Reports, London, 1693 4 f Hargrave's Collection of Tracts, London, 1787 1 4 Hargrave's Juridical Arguments. London, 1797 2 4 Hening &amp; Munford's Reports, New-York, 4 8 Hening's Statutes at Large, (2 copies) Richmand, 13 8 Henry's Points in Manumission, London, 1817 1 8 Hetley's Reports, London, 1657 1 f Historical Law Tracts, Edinburgh; 1761 1 f Hobart's Reports, London, 1724 1 f Holt's Reports, London, 1738 1 f Holt's Law of Libels, London, 1816 1 8 Horne's Mirror of Justices, London, 1768 1 8 Hutton's Reports, London, 1556 1 f Jacob's Law Dictionary, by Tomlins, London, 17 7 2 4 Jenkins' Reports, by Barlow, London, 1771 1 f Jenkinson's Collection of Treaties, London, 8 8 Instructor Clericalis, London, 1721 7 8 Johnson's Ecclesiastical Law, London, 1720 2 8 Jones' (Sir W.) Reports, London, 1765 1 f Jones' (Sir Thomas) Reports, London, 178 1 f Jones, on Bailments, Nichols, London, 1823 1 f Jridal Writs, (See Officina Brevium) Ju-tian (See Pandeets) Ju-tian's Institutes, See Cooper, Theophilus, Vinnus, Kame's Equity, Edinburgh, 1825 1 8 Kebler's Reports, London, 1685 3 f Kelham's Norman Dictionary, London, 1825 1 8 Kelynge's Reports, London, 1764 1 f Kitchen, on Courts, Antrobus &amp; Impey, London, 1675 1 8 Lambard, concerning the Antient Laws of England, Latin and Saxon, London, 1564 1 4 Lambard, concerning the Antient &amp; c. Cambridge, 1644 1 f Lambard, Eirenarchia, or office of Justice of the Peace, London, 1614 1 8 Lancelotti, Body of Canon Law, See "Corpus Juris Canonici" Lane's Reports, London, 167 1 f Latch's Reports, London, 1661 1 f Law School of Harvard University, catalogue of, 1 8 Laws of the United States, 5 8 Laws of the United States, by Colvin, 1 8 Laws of Virginia, Richmond, 2 8 Laws relating to Travellers and travelling, London, 1819 1 8 Leach, on Crown Law, London, 1815 2 8 Lee, on Captures in War, London, 103 1 8 Leonard's Reports, Hughes, London, 1658 2 4 Levinz's Reports, London, 1722 f Lunlavns, on the, Græco-Roman Canon and Civil Law, Greek &amp; Latin, Francfort, 1596 1 f Ley's Reports, London, 1659 1 f Lilly's Reports, London, 1719 1 f Lilly's Practical Register, London, 17 2 f Lilly's Conveyancer, London, 1742 1 f Littleton's Reports, London, 1683 1 f Littleton's Tenures, Clarke, London, 1825 1 12 Lofft's Reports, London, 1776 1 f Lutwyche's Reports, London, 1704 2 f Mac Nally's Rules of Evidence, London, 1802 1 8 Madox's Firma Burgi, London, 1726 1 f Malyne's Law Merchant, London, 1686 1 f March's Reports, London, 1675 1 8 Marshall, on Insurance, London, 1808 2 8 Marshall's (C.) Reports, London, 1815 2 8 Marten's Law of Nations, Cobbett, Phila. 1795 1 8 Marten's on Pvateers, Horne, London, 1801 1 8 Maule &amp; Selwyn's Reports, London, 1814 5 8 Merivale's Reports, London, 1817 3 8 Modern Entries, Mallory, London, 1791 8 Modern Reports Leach London, 1793 12 8 y, on Maritime Law, Latin, London, 1778 2 8 Mollyneaux, The case of Ireland being bound by Acts of ariament, London, 1770 1 8 Moore's Reports, London, 118 6 8 Moore's Reports, London, 1688 1 f Muchall, Doctor and Student London, 1815 1 8 Muchall, Doctor and Student a very old edition, London, 1 12 Munford's Reports, New-York, 6 8 Nelson's Abridgement, London, 1725 3 f Newland on Contracts, London, 1806 1 8 New Retorna Brevium, London, 1728 1 8 Northingtons's Reports, by Eden, London, 1818 2 8 Noy's Maxims, by Thewood, London, 1821 1 12 Noy's Reports, London, 1656 1 f Oaths, Book of, London, 1715 1 12 O Brevium, London, 1679 1 f Od on Usury, London, 1809 1 8 Par's Reports, London, 1678 1 f Pands of Justian Pothier, Lat. Leyden, 1782 3 f Lex Parhamena, 1 8 Peake's Law of Evidence, London, 1813 1 8 Peltier's Trial, Adams, London, 1803 1 8 Perkins, Laws of England, London, 1757 1 8 Pettus, on Parliaments, London, 1680 1 8 Petty's Parliamentary Law, London, 1739 1 f Petty's Antient Rights of the Commons of England, London, 1680 1 8 Phillips Sheriff, London, 1808 1 8 Pleading, Rules fo Latin, 1694 1 8 Plowden's Reports London, 1779 1 f Pollexien's Reports, London, 1702 1 f Popham's Reports, London, 1656 1 f Postlethwayt's Dictionary of Trade and Commerce, London, 1766 2 f Pothier, on Obligations, Evans, London, 1806 2 8 Puffendorf, on the Duty of Man, Leyden, 1769 1 8 Puffendorf, Law of Nature by Barbeyrac, French, London, 174 3 4 Randolph's Reports, Richmond 4 8 Richmond 1823 2 8 Rastll's Entries London, 1670 1 f Rastll's Collection London, 1621 1 f Ray Reports, Bayley, London, 1790 3 8 Ray Reports, Bayley, Dublin, 1793 1 8 Rves's Two Tracts on Alien Laws, London, 1816 1 8 L Register of Briefs, Latin, London, 1687 1 f Rovisal, Code of 1819, Richmond, 1819 2 8 Richardson's (K. B.) Practice, London, 1776 2 8 Richardson's (C. P.) Practice, London, 1776 2 8 Roberts, on the Statutes of Fraud, London, 1805 8 Robinson's (C.) Admiralty Reports, London, 1812 8 Robinson, (Th.) on Gavelkind, Wilson, London, 1822 1 8 Rolle's Reports, London, 1675 Rolle's Abridgment, London, 1668 f Romagnosi, Italian, Milan, 1807 1 8 Roscoe's Penal Jurisprudence, London, 1819 1 8 Runnington's Ejectments, London, 1781 1 8 Rutherf?rd's Institutes, Philadelphia, 1799 2 8 Salkeld's Reports, Evans, London, 1795 3 8 Salmasius de Testamentis, Latin, 2 copies, Leyden, 1648 and 1633 1 12 Salmon's State Trials, L?ndon, 1738 1 f Savile's Reports, London, 1675 1 f Sayer's Reports, London, 1775 1 f Saunder's Reports, Williams &amp;c. London, 1824 3 8 Sayer's Law of Damages, London, 1770 8 Sayer's Law of Costs, London, 1777 8 Schlegel &amp; roks Swedish Convoy, London, 1800 1 8 Selden's Tracts, London, 1683 1 f Selden's Works, by Wilkins, Latin, London, 1726 3 f Selden's "Mare Clausum" Latin, London, 1635 1 f Selden, of the Jurisdíction in Parliaments, London, 1 8 Select Cases in chancer, London, 1740 1 f Selwyn's Nisi Prius, London, 1824 2 8 Sheppard's Abridgment, London, 1675 3 4 Shower's Cases in Parliament, London, 1698 1 f Shower's Reports, Leach, London, 1794 2 8 Siderfen's Reports, London, 1714 f Skinner's Reports, London, 1728 1 f Smith's Reports, London, 1806 3 8 Somner, on Gavelkind, London, 1675 1 4 Spelman's Concilia, Latin, London, 1639 4 Spelman's English Works, London, 1727 f Spelman's Anglo-Saxon Laws, Latin; London, 1724 f Spelman's Law Terms, London, 1684 12 State Trials, by Cobbett. 63 to 1817 London, 32 8 Statutes at Large, from 9 Henry III to 5 George IV. London, 41 8 Staundford's Pleas of the Crown, London, 1601 4 Stearns, on Real Actions, Boston, 1824 1 8 Strange's Reports, London. 1782 2 8 Student's Law Dictionary, London, 1740 8 Style's Practical Register, London, 1770 8 Style's Reports, London, 1658 Study of the Law, Treatise on, London, 797 8 Sullivan's Lectures on the Constitution and Laws of England, Stuart, London, 1776 1 4 Swanston's Reports, London, 1821 2 8 Swinburne, on Wills, London, 1803 3 8 Swinburne, on Marriage, London, 1686 1 4 Swinburne, on Wills, London, 1728 1 f Tauhton's Reports, London, 1814 8 8 Taylor, on Gavelkind, London, 1663 1 8 Termes of the Law, London, 1721 1 8 Theophilus, Paraphrase of the Justinian Institutes, Lat. Leyden, 1761 1 8 Tomlins, Juridical Repertory 1 f Tomlins, Law Dictionary, London, 1820 2 4 Tothill's Court of Chancery, London, 1820 1 12 Townshend's Judgments, London, 1659 1 8 Tremaine's Pleas of the Crown, London, 1723 1 f Vattel's Law of Nations, London, 1793 1 8 Vattel's Questions on Natural Law, Fr. Hague, 1763 1 8 Vaughan's Reports, London. 1677 1 4 Ventris's Reports, London. 1726 1 f Vernon's Reports, Raithby, London, 1806 3 8 Vesey's Reports, by Belt, London, 1818 2 8 cat, Law Vocabulary, Lat. Naples, 1760 2 8 Viner's Abridgement, London, 79 24 8 Viner's Supplement. London, 1799 6 8 Vinnius Commentary on the Imperial Institutes, Heineccius Latin, Leyden, 1767 2 4 Virginia Reports 1820-21, (2 copies) by Gilmer, Richmond, 1824 1 8 Virginia Cases, by Brockenbrough &amp; Holmes, Philadelphia, 1815 1 8 Ward's Law of Nations, London, 1795 2 8 Washington's Reprs, Philadelphia, 1823 2 8 Watson's Clergy-Man's Law, London, 1747 1 f Wentworth's Office of Executions, Wilson, London, 1774 1 8 William's (P.) Reports, by Cox, London, 1793 3 8 William's Cases in Equity, London, 1792 1 8 Willes's Reports, London, 1797 1 f Wickefort, the Ambassador and his Function, French, Amsterdam, 10 2 4 Wilson's Reports, Dublin, 1784 3 8 Wingate's Maxims, London. 1658 1 f Wingate's Britton, London. 1640 1 12 Wooddeson's Lectures on the Laws of Eng. Lond 1793 3 8 Wood's Institutes, London 1772 1 f Year. Books, London, 1678 8 f Yelverton's Reports, London, 1735 1 f Zouch's Juris et Judicii Fecialis, Lat. Oxford, 1650 1 4</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER XXVII RELIGION (CHRISTIAN, ETHNICK &amp;C.) AND ECCLESIASTICAL HISTORY. Vols. Size Adams's Dictionary of Religions, Boston, 1817 1 8 Addison's Evidences. by Purdy, London, 1807 1 8 Aeneas &amp; Zacharias. on the Immortality of the Soul, Greek and Latin, Leipsic. 1655 1 4 Ammonius Consonance of the Evangelists, Latin, Constance, 1782 1 12 Aquinas. (Thomas) Latin, Anerp, 1612 12 f Athanasius's Works, Latin, 1617 1 f Bæda, Ecesiastial History, Latin and Saxon, Cambridge, 1722 1 f Ba &amp;c. 1644 1 f Barclay's Apology, London, 1825 8 Barnabas &amp; Hermas. Epistles, Latin, Oxford, 1685 1 12 Baronius, Eeclesiastical Annals, Oxford, 160 12 f Baronius, continued, by Raynald, Oxford, 1693 7 f Baronius, continuation, by Spondanus, Lat. Leyden, 2 f Basilius, Works Complete, Latin, Paris, 1638 3 f Bate's Hebrew &amp; English Dictionary, London, 1767 1 4 Bible, by Thompson, Philadelphia, 1808 4 8 Bible, Hebrw 1720 2 8 Bible, Hungaric, 1765 1 8 Bible, Latin, 1703 1 8 Bible, "Sacra Vulgata" Vienna, 1813 3 8 Bible, in a Language of the American Indians, translated by Eliot 1 Bible, (Finnisch) 1 8 Bible, (Sclavonisch) 1 8 Bible, by Stt Boston, 6 4 Bible, Latin, Hamburg, 1723 1 8 Bible, Latin, 1663 1 Bibliotheca of the Polish Brethren. Latin. See Socinus, 1656 1 Blackbourne's Works, Cambridge, 1804 6 8 Blair's Sermons. London, 1802 5 8 ts Funeral Sermons. French, Paris, 1762 1 12 rdles Sermons, French, Paris, 1726 4 12 rdles Sermons, Aent, French, Paris, 16 12 rdles Sermons, Retreat, French, Paris, 1747 1 12 rdles Sermons, Mysteries, French, Paris, 1726 2 12 rdles Sermons, t, French, Paris, 176 3 12 rdles Sermons, Festivals of the Saints, Fr. Paris, 1723 5 12 rdles Sermons, hations, Saints, Fr. Paris, 17 2 12 rdles Sermons, Thoughts, Saints, Fr. Paris, 1774 3 12 Boyse's Pantheon, Cooke, London, 1787 1 12 Brenius, Annotations upon the Old and New Testament, Latin, Amsterdam 1664, 1 12 Bochart Sacred Geography, Latin, 1651 1 f Broughton's Dictionary of all Religions, London, 1745 f Brown's Dictionary of the Bible, London, 1820 2 8 Burnet's Exposition of the 39 Articles. London, 1819 1 8 Calmet's Dictionary of the Bible, Fr Geneva, 1730 4 4 Calvin's Christian Institution, Geneva, 1818. 8 Cave's Lives of the Fathers. London, 1683 1 f Chillingsworth's Works, London, 1742 1 f Chrysostom's Works complete, Lat. fort, 1679 4 f Clarke's Sermons London, 1732 10 8 Clarke's 17 Sermons. London, 1724 1 8 Clarke's on the Attributes of God, Glasgow, 1823 1 8 Clement's Works, Latin, 1629 1 f Concordia Evangelica, Latin. Paris. 1660 1 18 Cotelerius, Apostolic Fathers, Latin, Amsterdam, 1724 2 f Crellius, Works complete. Latin, 656 1 f Crellius, Works Lat. 656 1 f Cruden's Concordance, Brick, 1817 1 4 Cyrill's Sermons, Latin, Anrp, 1618 1 f Cyprianus, See Athanasus. Dll. concerning the right use of the Fathers, Latin, Geneva, 1655 1 4 Davanzati, Schism of England, Italian. Milan. 1807 1 8 Demoustier's Letters on Mythology, Fr. Paris, 1816 6 18 Duns Scotus, Works, Latin, Leyden, 1639 15 Dupuis, origin of all the modes of Worship, and Atlas, Paris, 1795 12 8 Dupuis, Analysis of, by Tracy, Fr. Paris, 1804 1 8 Dwight's Conquest of Canaan, Hartford, 1785 1 8 Eichhorn, Introduction to the Old Testament, German, Gottingen, 1823 5 8 Eichhorn, Introduction to the Apocryphal writings of the Old Testament, Ger. Leipsic, 1795 1 8 Eichhorn, Introduction to the New Testament, German, Leipsic, 1810 3 8 Eichhorn, History of the origin of the World, German, Nuremburg, 1790 3 12 Ellys, on Spiritual &amp; Temporal Liberty. London, 1765 1 4 Eusebius. Thesaurus Temporum. Lat. Amsterdam, 1658 1 f Eusebius. History of the Church, by Cousin, French Paris, 1686 6 12 Evagrius, See Theodoretus, Fathers, See Sacred Fathers, Foster's Sermons, London, 1745 4 12 Fox's Acts &amp; Monuinents, London, 1684 3 f Gesenius, Hebrew and English Lexicon, by Gibbs, Andover, 8 1 8 Grabe's Seint, Oxford, 1707 8 8 Gregory's Works complete, Latin, Paris, 1705 4 f Grotius, on the truth of the Christian Religion Clericus, Latin, Boston, 1809 1 8 Hermann's Pantheon, German, 1811 1 8 History of the X English Writers S. Monachus, J. Prior, R. Prior, A. Abbas, R. de Diceto, J. Brompton, G. Monachus, Th, Stubbs, W. Thorn, and H. Knighton, Latin, London, 1652 1 f Hodius, on the Texts of the Bible, Lat. Oxford. 1705 1 f Hone's Ancient Mysteries, London, 1823 1 8 Hone's Apocryphal. Testament, London, 1821, 2 copies, 1 8 Hottinger, Bibliothecarius Quadripartitus, Latin, 16 Huss, John and Jerome, of Prague, their history &amp;c. Lat. Nuremburg 1715 2 f Ignatius, Epistles, Latin, Geneva, 1623 1 4 Ignatius and Barnabas, Epistles, Vossius, Latin, Amsterdam, 1646 1 4 Jones, Canon of the New Testament, London 1726 2 8 ious Pelusiota. G. and Lat. Paris, 1638 1 f Junius and Mareschallus, four Evangelists, Gotc and Anglo-Saxon, 1 4 Kennicott's Old Testament, Hebrew, Oxford, 1776 2 f Leibnitz, Tentamina Theodicæae, Latin, Francfort, 1739 2 12 Leo the Great, Works of, Latin, Venice, 1753 3 f Lightfoot's Works London, 2 Lowth's Sacred Poetry of the Hebrews, Latin, Gtti- gen, 1770 1 12 Martin Luther, Works of, Latin. Witenburg, 1545 4 f Massillon's Works, French, Paris, 1820 2 Moiners, History of different Religions, German, ao- ver 1806 2 8 aso, Rev. Wm. See Miscell. Minue Philosopher, London, 1732 2 8 Mhei Ecclesiastical History, Maclaine, Charleston, 1810 6 8 Necker, on Religions Opinions, London, 1788 1 8 Newcomb's Harmony, Greek Andover, 1814 1 8 Newcomb's Harmony, Philadelphia, 1809 1 8 Newman's Concordance, London, 1658 1 f Nicephorus Callistius, Ecclesiastical History, Latin, Paris, 1630 2 f Origen, Hexapla, Hebrew, Greek and Latin, Montfaucon. 1713 1 f Origen, Hexapla, Bard &amp;c. Hebrew, Leipsic, 1769 2 8 Paley's Evidences of Christianity, Boston, 1810 1 8 Pamphilius Ecclesiastical History, 1779 1 8 Pascal's thoughts on Religion &amp;c. Fr. Paris, 1820 1 12 Pearson, on the Creed, London, 1 2 8 Philo Judaeus, Works, Latin &amp; Greek, Pfeiffer, Erlangen. 1785 5 8 Pilostatus, Gr. and Lat. Olearus, Leipsic, 1719 1 f Priestley's Harmony, London, 1777 1 4 Priestley's Corruptions of Christianity, Boston. 1797 2 8 Priestley's Institutes of Natural and Revealed Religion, Birmingham. 2 8 Priestley's History of early opinions concerning Christ, Birmingham, 1786 4 8 Priestley's Camparison, Northumband, 1804 1 8 Prideaux's Connexion, Charleston, 1815 Pazipcovius. Sacred Cogitations. Latin 1692 1 f Psalms of David, Gr. &amp; Lat nterp 1543 1 12 Sacred Fathers Works of, Lat. Wurzburg, 1780 13 8 Sacred Fathers Gr. &amp; Lat. Wurzburg, 1793 21 8 Sale's Koran, London, 1821 2 8 Schlevsnerus, Lexicon to the New Testament, Leipsic, 19 2 8 Scott's Bible, See Bible Scotus, See Duns Scotus, Sherlock, (W) on Divine Providence, Edinburgh, 1776 1 12 on Judgment, London, 1713 1 8 Sherlock's (Th.) Discourses, London, 50 4 8 Sike, Eanem nfan, Lat. ht, 1697 1 12 Sigonius, on the Republic of the Hebrews, Lat. lm- st, 1685 1 4 Shtinis, Posthumous Commentaries on the New Testament, Latin 1656 1 f Sos's Works, See Biblioth of the Polish Brethren Ste and Sozomen, Ecclesiastical History, Greek &amp; Latin by Valesius, 1677 1 f kouse's History of the Bible, London, 1742 2 f Sterne's Sermons London 1 6 12 lligt's Origines Sacrae, Cambridge, 1702 1 f Sbaus. Greek and Latin, 1549 1 f Strype's Annals of the Reformation, Oxford, 1824 7 8 art's Hebrew Grammar, Andover, 1823 1 8 Taylor's (Jeremy) Works, Heber, London, 1822 15 8 Taylor, (John) on Original Sin, London, 1 1 8 Taylor's Hebrew Goncordance, London, 17 2 f Testament New, Coptic and Latin, Oxford. 1716 1 4 Testament New, Beza, Gr. &amp; Lat. 16 1 8 Testament New, Fabricius. Lat. Hamburgh, 1743 1 8 Testament New, Greek, 1710 1 8 Testament New, Latin, all, 1776 1 8 Testament New, Gr and Lat. Montanus, Anrp. 1583 1 8 Testament New, Latin, Erasmus. tbrg, 1661 1 8 Testament New, Tartaric, 1 8 Testament New, Islandic, 1 8 Testament New, Syriac, Lewsden &amp; Shaef. ydn, 1717 2 4 Testament New, Greek, Matthæus, Wirtemburg, 1803 3 8 Testament New, Calmuck, 1 f Testament New, Mongol 1 f Testament New, Arabic, 1 4 Testament New, an improved Version of, Boston, 9 1 8 Testament New, Apochryphal Code of Fabricius, Gr. &amp; Latin, Hamburg, 1719 1 8 Theodoretus &amp; Evagrius, Ecclesiastical History, Latin, 1629 1 f Theodoretus, Words complete, Greek and Latin, Shulze, alle, 1769 6 8 Thompson's Four Gospels, Philadelphia, 1815 1 8 Thompson's Bible, See Bible, Tillemont's Ecclesiastical History Fr. Paris, 16 4 Tillotson's Works, London, 1728 3 f Tooke's Pantheon Baltimore, 1823 1 8 Trimmer's Scripture Catechism, London. 1818 2 12 Trimmer's Abridgement of Scrip Hist. London, 1811 1 12 Trommius, Greek Concordance, Gr. 1718 2 Ulfila, translation of the Evangelists in Gothic, with parallel versions in Islandic, Suethic and Latin, Stockholm, 1671 1 4 Van Dale, Dissertation upon Aristeas, Latin, Amsterdam 75 4 Warburton's Legation of Moses, London, 1755 4 8 Wesley, on Original Sin. Bristol. 177 1 8 Wharton's `Anglia Sacra" Latin London, 1691 2 f Whiston's Primitive Christianity, London, 1711 4 8 Whitby on the five points, London, 1817 1 8 Winer's Greek Grammar of the New Testament, by Stuart and Robinson Andover, 1825 1 8 Wolzogenius, Works. Latin. 1646 1 f Wollaston Wm. Religion of Nature delineated, London, 1726 1</field>
      <field name="fulltext">M CHAPTER, XXVIII ARCHITECTURE, DESIGNING, PAINTING SCULPTURE AND MUSIC. Vols. Size deen, Inquiry into Greia Architecture, London, 1822 1 12 Alick Elements of Architecture, Smyth, Oford, 1818 1 8 Annals of the Mus, and of the School of Fine Arts, Fr. Paris 17 8 Antiquities of Hrulanc, Engraved by David, with Explanations, by Mareschal, Fr. Paris. 1780 9 4 Antiquitios of Herculan, Engraved by Paroli, and published by F &amp; P. Piranesi, Fr. Paris, 1804 6 4 Arteaga, on Music, Italian, Bologna, 1783 2 8 Basan's Dictionary of Engravers, Fr. Paris, 1767 3 12 Burney's History of Music. London, 1787 4 4 Burney's An account of the Musical Performances in Commemorations of Handel, London, 1785 1 4 Chamber's Plans &amp;c. of the Gardens and Buildings at Kew, London, 1763 1 f Clarke, on the Greek Marbles, Cmbridg. 1809 1 4 Dati, Lives of the Antient Painters, Italian, Milan 1806 1 8 Desgotetz, Antique Edifices of Rome, Fr. Paris, 1729 1 f Durand, collection and comparison of Aient and Modern Edifices of all kinds Fr. Paris 1801 1 Eberhard's Theory of the Fine Arts, See Miscell. Felibien, Discourses on the Lives and Works of the most excellent Antient and Modern Painters, French, Treves, 1725 6 8 Garve's Treatise on the Fine Arts, See Miscell. Gibb's Architecture, London, 1728 1 f Handmaid to the Arts, London, 1764 2 8 Jones (Inigo,) Designs, 1 4 Kelsall, Phantasm of a University, London, 1814 1 f Landon, Landscapes &amp;c. Fr. Paris, 1805 4 8 Le Clerc, Treatise, on Architecture, F Paris, 1714 2 4 Le Grand, Galleries of Autiquities, F Paris, 1803 1 8 Le Roy, Antiquities of Greece, F Paris, 1758 1 f Lubersac, Discourso on Public Monuments, French, Pis 1775 1 f Major, (Thomas) the Ruins of Pæstum, Fr. London, 1768 1 f Maaual of the French Museum. Fr. Paris, 1802 5 8 Palladio, the five orders of Architecture, Italian, Rome, 1801 1 4 Patte Monuments of Los XV. Fr. Paris; 1765 1 f Perrault, See Vivius Perrault, on the five kinds of Columns, Fr. Paris, 1683 1 f Pilkington Dictionary of Painters, London, 1821 2 8 Seeley, description of the House and Gars of the Marquis of Buckingham, 1 Smato, Narrative of the Building, and a description of the construction of Edystone Lighthouse, Lond. 1813 1 f Spence's Polytis, London, 1813 1 f Sulzer's Theory of the Fine Arts, Ger. Lipsi, 1722 4 8 Sulzer's Theory Appendix. Arts, Ger. Lipsi, 1792 8 8 Sulzer's Theory Appendix, by Blandenburg, German, Lipsi, 1796 3 8 Visconti, on the Elgin Marbles, London, 1816 1 8 Vitvis, Architecture, by Perrault, Fr. Paris, 1684 1 f Wood, Ruins of Balbec, London, 1757 1 f Wood, Ruins of Palmyra, London, 1753 1 f</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHAPTER XXIX MISCELLANEOUS, INCLUDING POETRY, RHETORIC, EDUCATION, &amp;c. Vols Size Abelard and Heloisa, Life. Fr. Paris, 1728 2 8 Epistles, Paris, 1732 2 8 Adams's Lectures on Rhetoric &amp;c. Cambridge. New-England, 1810 2 8 Annual Register, from 1758 to 1817 61 8 Anthologia Persica Latin. icna, 1778 1 4 Antonio, (Nicholas) Bibliotheca Hispana Vetus, Latin, Madrid, 1788 4 f Ariosto, Orlando Frioso, Italian, Venice, 1772 4 4 Ariosto, Orlando Frioso, Italian, Milan. 1812 5 8 Armstrong's Art of preserving Health, London, 1803 1 12 Bacon's Works, London, 1765 5 4 Baggesen's Poems, German, Hamburg, 1803 1 12 Baldinuccis Works, Italian, Milan, 1808 14 8 Balow's Columbiad, Philadelphia, 1807 1 4 Bartas, (William de) See Sylvester Beaval German &amp; French Dialogues, German, Dresden, 1819 1 12 Beaumont &amp; Fletcher, Dramatic Works; London, 1778 10 8 Berkeley's Works, London, 1820, 3 8 Bitaube's Joseph, Fr. Geneva, 1777 1 8 Bibliotheca Btannin, Watt, Edinburg, 1824 4 4 Bibliotheca Arabica, ispana, 1760 2 Bibliography, Instructive, History Fr. Paris, 1768 3 8 Bibliography, Instructive, Belles-Lettres, Paris, 1765 2 8 Bibliography, Instructive, Theology, Paris, 1768 8 Bibliography, Instructive, Jurisprudence. &amp;c. French, Paris, 1764 1 8 Bibliotheque. Universal Fr, Amsterdam, 1702 25 12 Bibliotheque. Select, by Le Clerc, Fr. Amsterdam, 1712 28 12 Bibliotheque. Aucient and Modern. Fr. Amsterdam, 1714 27 12 Blair's Lectures on Rhetoric &amp;c. Philadelphia, 1798 2 8 Bland's Military Discipline, London, 1743 1 8 Blumauer's Works complete Ger. Lipsic, 1806 2 12 Bocaccio Theseide, Italian, Milan, 1819 1 8 Bocaccio Decameron. Italian; Floe, 1822. 2 8 Bohn's Catalogue, London, 1820 1 8 Bohn's Catalogue, part 2d London, 1823 1 8 Boilcan's Works. Fr Paris, 1819 3 8 Bolingbroke's Works, London, 1809 8 8 Borghini, Reposo, Italian, Milan, 1807 3 8 Bouilly, (J. N.) Tales for my Daughter, French, Paris, 1818 2 8 Bouilly, (J. N.) Advice for my Daughter, French, Paris, 1813 2 8 Burgers Works complete, German, Berlin, 1823 7 12 Burke's Speeches, London, 1816 4 8 Butler's udibras by Grey. London, 1799 2 8 Carter's (B. M.) Poems, London, 184 1 8 Catalogue of the Library of the Royal Institution, by Burney. 1 8 Catalogue of the Law School of the Harvard University, 1 8 Catalogue of the Leipsic Fair, of 1824 &amp; 1825, German Cato's Letters, London, 1733 4 12 Cervantes, Don Quixote, Spanish. Paris, 1814 7 8 Cervantes, Don Quixote, Eng. London, 1820 4 12 Cellini's (Benvenuto) Life, written by himself, Italian, notes by Carpani, Milan, 1806 3 8 Chaucer's Works, by Uy. London, 172 1 f Chaucer's Works, by Tyrwhitt, London, 1822 5 8 Chesterfield's Letters, London, 1774 4 8 Chesterfield's Miscellaneous Works, London, 1799 1 8 Chess, a Treatise on, London, 1787 1 8 Chubb's Practs, London, 1730 1 4 Clericuss Works, Latin, Amsterdam, 1710 2 12 Clias, on the Art of Swiming, ondon 1825 1 8 Collin's (J. R.) Works complete, Ger. Vienna, 1812 6 8 Collin's (M. R) Dramatical Poems, German, Leipsic, 1813 2 12 Colman's Catalogue New-York, 1825 1 8 Congreve's Works, London, 1774 2 8 Conversational Lon, Ger Leipsic, 1824 10 8 Corneille's Works, 1761 12 8 Cowley's Works, by Hurd, London, 1777 2 12 Co Correspondence, by Johnson, Boston, 1821 1 8 Cbi, on Italian Poetry, by Matthias, London, 1803 4 12 Cylodia, by Rees, Philadelphia, 41 4 Plates 6 4 D'Alembert, Melanges of Lit Hist. &amp;c. French, Amsterdam, 1760 5 12 Dante, Divine Comedy, by Portirelli, Italian, Milan, 1804 3 8 Derham's Astro-Theology, London, 1719 1 8 Descartes, Works, Amsterdam, 1692 9 4 Dialogues of the Dead, London, 1760 1 8 Dibdin's Library Companion, London, 1824 1 8 Dictionary of Trevoux Fr. &amp; Lat. Paris, 1771 8 f Dictionary, Neologick, Fr. Amsterdam, 1754 1 12 Bibliographic, Fr. Paris, 1790 4 8 Diderot's Works, Paris, 1821 22 8 Doddington's Dry, by Windham, London, 1823 1 8 Do's Illustrations of Shakespeare London, 123 1 8 Drake's (Natha,) Essays, London, 1803. 5 8 Dryden's Works, by Scott, Edinburgh, 1821 18 8 Dubos, Critical Reflexions on Poetry &amp;c. French, Paris, 1733 3 8 Eberhard, (J A.) Theory of the Fine Arts, German, Halle, 1790 1 12 Eberhard's (H. E.) collection of Tales, German, Leipsic, 1805 2 12 Eichhorn, Repertory of Literature, Ger. Leipsic, 1797 9 8 Eichhorn, Biblical Literature, 1787 10 8 Eastburn, Yanoyden, New-York, 1 8 Ecoles Normales, Lessons, Fr. Paris, 10 8 Ecoles Normales, Debates, Fr. Paris, 3 8 Eikon Basilike, London, 1821 1 18 Ellis's Early English Poets, London, 1811 3 8 Ellis's Early English Met. Romances, London, 1811 3 8 Encyclopædia, by Diderot &amp; D'Alembert, Fr 36 8 Encyclopædia, Plates, 3 4 Encyclopædia, See Rees Britannica, Edinburgh, 1823 20 4 Supplement 1823 1821 6 4 by Dobson Philadd 17 18 Encyclopædia, Supplement, 1803 3 4 Methodical, Fr. Paris, 1787 to 1816, comprising Agriculture comprising 6 4 Amusements of Sciences comprising 4 Anatomical System comprising 3 4 Anities comprising 5 4 Anities Plates comprising 2 4 Architecture comprising 2 4 Arts, Academical &amp;c. comprising 1 4 Art of Husbandry &amp;c. comprising 1 4 Art of Husbandry Plates, comprising 1 4 Art, Military, Supplement comprising 4 4 Arts &amp; Mechanical trades comprising 8 4 Fine Arts, comprising 2 4 Fine Arts, Plates, comprising 1 4 Botany comprising 8 4 Botany Supplement comprising 5 4 Botany Plates comprising 4 4 Chemistry comprising 6 4 Chemistry Plates comprising 1 4 Commerce comprising 3 4 Economy Political &amp;c. comprising 4 4 Encyclopedianna comprising 1 4 Fishes, comprising 1 4 Geography, Ancient comprising 3 4 Geography comprising 3 4 Geography Physical. comprising 4 4 Grammar &amp; Literature comprising 3 4 History, &amp; Supplement comprising 6 4 History, Natural comprising 9 4 Hunting, comprising 1 4 Jurispradence, comprising 10 4 Logic, Metaph. &amp; Morals comprising 4 4 Manufacture. comprising 3 4 Marine, comprising 3 4 Mathemat. Amusements comprising 1 4 Mathematics, comprising 3 4 Medicine, comprising 10 4 Music, comprising 2 4 Philosophy, comprising 3 4 Physics, comprising 4 4 Physics, Plates, comprising 1 4 Surgery, comprising 2 4 Theology, comprising 3 4 Theology, Plates, comprising 1 4 Plates, comprising 8 4 Atlas, comprising 2 4 Engel's Writings on various subjects, Germa, Berlin, 80 8 8 Engel's Elements of a Theory of Poetics, from German Models, German, Berlin, 1804 1 12 Eps Instruction of the Deaf &amp; Dumb, French, Paris, 1776 1 8 Erilla Arauana Spanish, Madrid, 1776 2 8 Erskine's Speeches, by Ridgeway, New-York; 1813 2 8 Evremond's (Charles St.). Works, Fr. 1753 12 12 Falk's Satirical Works, German, Leipsic, 1797 5 12 Fenelon. Dialogues on Eloquence, by Stevenson, Lendon, 180 1 8 Fenelon. Telmachus, Fr. Maestricht, 1793 2 8 Ficte (J. A.) Principles of the complete Dectrine of the Sciences, Jena, 1802 1 8 Fichte, on Learned Men, &amp;c. Ger. Berlin, 160 1 12 Fleury's Treatise of the Choice and Method of Study, French, Nises, 1784 1 12 Florian's Fables, Fr Paris, 1814 1 13 Fontenelle, Belles Lettres, Fr. Paris, 1813 2 8 Franklin's Works, Philadelphia, 1818 6 8 Frederick II. Reliqua, Schneider, Leipsic, 1788 1 4 Friedrich's Satirical Campaign, German, Berlin, 1817 3 12 Friedrich's Satirical Mirrour, Ger Leipsic, 1819 7 12 Garve on Society and Solitude, Ger. Bres, 1800 2 12 Garve on Fragments, Bres, 1798 2 12 Garve on Letters, Bres, 1802 2 12 Garve on Miscellanies, Bres, 1796 2 12 Garve on Treatise on the Fine Arts; German, Leipsic, 1802 2 12 Gay's Fables, 1 12 Glis, Theatre of Society, Fr. Paris, 1811 2 12 The young Exiles. Fr. Paris, 1812 2 12 Gentleman's Magazine, 1781 to 1820 128 8 Gentleman's Magazine, General Index 4 8 Gentleman's Magazine, List of Plates 1 8 Gessner's Works, German, Zurich, 1818 1 12 Gibbon's Miscellaneous Works, by Sheffield, London, 1796 2 4 Gleim's Works complete, German, albersadt 1811 7 8 Goldoni, Select Comedies, Italian, London, 1823 1 8 Godwin's Enquirer, London, 1823 1 8 Gothe's Works complete, Ger. Stuttgart, 1815 20 8 Gra Works, London, 1825 2 8 Gruber, Poetical Anthology of the Germans, German, Rudoldat, 1808 2 8 Guaran, by Chaers, London, 1832 2 8 Guarini The Faithful Shepherd, Italian. rna, 1785 1 4 Guiar (Mle) The school of Mas, French; Paris, 1725 2 4 Gymnastic Exercises, Paris, 1823 1 8 Harris's (John) Dictionary of Arts and Sciences, London. 1725 2 (J) three Treats on Art, Music, &amp;c London 1744 1 8 Harvard University, Report of the Committee of Over- sers of, Status, Laws, &amp;c. of, Haug's Epigrammatical Anthology, German, ih, 1807 5 12 Hawkins, on the English Dran, Oxford, 1773 3 8 Hazli's Lectur on Goc Writers, Phipa, 1819 1 8 Herder's Ideas on the Philosophy of the History of Mankind, German, Lp 1784 1 4 einsiu Grove of Bards, G B, 1823 3 8 Hockheimer's Technics, Ger ipsi, 1820 4 8 Hogarth's Analysis of Beauty, and plts, London, 1776 1 8 Holty's Poems, German, 1814 1 12 Home's Elements of Criticism. New-York, 1819 2 8 Horn, CarlGozz Dramatic Poetry, German, P- ig 83 1 12 Horn, Poetry, &amp;c of the ans, Ger. Berlin, 1808 1 8 Horn, delations for History &amp; Critioisn of the Belles-Lettres of Germany Ger. Berlin, 11 1 8 Horn, Lie. Science, Art, &amp; Religion, German, Berlin, 1807 1 8 Horn, on the French Drama, Ger. 1802 1 12 Howard's Lazare, Warrington, 1787 1 4 Howard's on Prisons. Warrington, 1784 1 4 Huber's Miscellaneous Works. Ger. Berlin. 1793 1 12 Huber's Danger of Systems, Ger. Leipsic, 1793 1 12 Huber's Collection of Tales, Ger. Tubing, 1810 8 8 erta Poetical Works. Spanish, Madrid, 1778 2 8 Hunter's aptiiy amongst the Indians, Lond. 182 1 8 Dramatical Works complete, German, Leipsic, 1 8 8 Ja, Syllg of Orieal Books; Lat: Cambridge, 1821 1 8 Jefferson's Notes on Virginia, Philadelphia, 1825 1 8 Je Works, by Cole, 1793 4 8 John, (J. tor St) Letters from an American Farmer, , ris, 1787 3 8 N Johnson's (Samuel) Works, by Murphy, London, 1810 12 8 Jones, (Sir Wm.) Works, London, 1807 13 8 Jonson's (Ben.) Works, by Gifford, London, 1816 9 8 Journal of the Polytechnic School, Fr. Paris, 1795 12 4 Jung's Dramatic Poems, Ger. Mentz, 1821 1 8 Jussieu, Simon of Nantua, Fr. Paris, 1818 1 8 Katchberg's Works complete, Ger. 1816 5 12 King's Origin of Evil, by Law, London, 1782 2 8 Kleit's Works, German, Berlin, 1803 1 8 Klinger's Works complete, Ger. Konigsberg, 1815 12 8 Knigge's Works, Ger. 3 8 Korner's Works, German, Vienna, 1819 3 12 Korner's The Lyre and the Sword, Ger. Berlin, 1814 1 12 Korner's Posthumous Works, Ger. Leipsic, 1813 1 12 Kotzebue's new Plays, German, Leipsic, 1823 12 12 Kotzebue's Novels, German, Leipsic, 1805 3 12 Kotzebue's Minor Works, German, Leipsic, 1792 2 12 Kotzebue's The Bee, German, Konigsberg, 1808 4 12 Kotzebue's The youngest Children of my Family, German, Leipsic, 1793 3 12 Kotzebue's Clio's Flower Basket, German, Darmstadt, 1811 3 12 Kotzebue's The Cricket, Ger. Konigsberg, 1801 3 12 Kotzebue's Leontina, Ger. Leipsic, 1808 2 12 Kotzebue's Plays, German, Leipsic, 1808 2 12 Kotzebue's The Oldenberg Family, Ger. Leipsic, 1792 1 12 Kotzebue's Philibert, Ger. Konigsberg, 1809 1 12 Kotzebue's The most remarkable years of my life, German, Berlin, 1803 1 12 Kotzebue's Reminisences from Paris, German, Berlin, 1804 1 12 Kotzebue's Louisa, Ger. Leipsic, 1800 1 12 Kotzebue's Dramatical Almanacs, from 1803 to 1820 21 12 Lacretelle, on the Prejudice regarding Infamous Punishments, French, Paris, 1784 1 8 La Fontaine's Fables, Fr. Paris, 1816 1 8 La Fontaine's Fables, with Commentaries of de Coste, Fr. Paris, 1810 1 8 La Harpe, Course of Literature, Fr. Paris, 1823 9 8 Lessing's Works complete, Ger. Berlin, 30 8 Lestrade, Translation of the Roman Nights at the Tomb of the Scipios, Fr. Paris, 1822 2 8 Levizac, Course of Literature, Fr. Paris, 1814 2 8 Locke's Works, London, 1824 9 8 London Magazine from 1732 to 1782, London, 51 8 London Magazine Index, London 1 8 Lyttleton's Letters, Troy, New-York, 1807 1 8 Martiniere's Geographical &amp; Critical Dictionary, Fr. Paris, 1768 6 f Mason's (Rev. Wm.) Works, London, 1811 4 8 Massinger's Plays, by Gifford, London, 1813 4 8 Matthisson's Lyrical Anthology, German, Zurich, 1803 10 8 Maupertius, Works, Fr. lyos, 1768 4 8 Meiners, History of the Female Sex, German, Hanover, 1800 2 12 Meiners, Constitution &amp;c. of German Universities, German, Gottingen, 1801 2 8 Memoirs of the Imperial Academy of St. Petersburg, from 1726 to 1746 14 4 from 1747 to 1765 9 4 Memoirs of the National Institute, from 1806 to 1822, Fr. Paris, 19 4 Memoirs Système Metrique Décimal, or, Measure of the ar of the Meridian, Paris, 3 4 Memoirs Ancient Literature, Paris, 4 4 Memoirs Literature &amp; Fine Arts, Paris, 5 4 Memoirs Mathematics &amp; Physics, Paris, 6 4 Memoirs Morals &amp; Politics, Paris, 5 4 Memoirs of Learned Foreigners, Paris, 2 4 Mercer, (C. F.) discose on Popular Education, 1826 1 8 Miller's Retrospect of the 18th Century, New-York, 1803 3 8 Milton's Prose Works, by Symmes, London, 186 6 4 Milton's Life, London, 1 4 Milton's Poetical Works, by Todd, London, 189 7 8 Milton's Paradise Lost, by Newton, London, 1770 2 8 Minner's Dialogues, Italian &amp; German, 1813 1 12 Minner's Dialogues, English &amp; German, 1813 1 12 Minner's Dialogues, Spanish &amp; Ger. 1813 1 12 Moliere's Works, Paris, 1823 6 8 Montagu's Works, London, 1817 5 8 Moralists, (French) a Collection of, by Duval, French, Paris, 1820 6 8 Moralists, 1820 2 8 Mozin, French &amp; German Dialogues, Stuttgart, 1813 1 8 Muhler's Poems, German, Berlin, 1805 1 12 Muhler's Poems, German, Berlin, 1813 1 8 Muhler's `Forget me not' Ger. 1815 3 Niebelungen, Song, German, Franfort, 1824 1 Onosander, on the Duties of the General of an Army, Greek &amp; French, 1 8 Pallas, Travels in Russia, translated from the German, by Gauthier, Fr. Paris, 1788 5 4 Pallas, Atlas, 1 4 Parmentier, Method of making Bread of Potatoes, Fr. Paris, 1779 1 8 Pauw, Philosophical Enquiries with regard to the Americans, Fr. Berlin, 1799 3 8 Perrin's Fables, London, 1820 1 8 Perchke, German, Leipsic, 1817 1 8 Petrarch's Poems, Italian, Milan, 1805 2 8 Lyons, 1551 1 12 Pfeffel, Essays in Prose, German, Tubingen, 1821 5 12 Pfeffel, Essays in Verse, German, Tubingen, 1816 5 12 Philidor, on the Game of Chess, Fr. Philadelphia, 1821 1 12 Philosophy of the Universe, Fr. Paris, 1796 1 8 Pilpay's Fables, London, 1818 1 12 Pindar's (Peter) Works, London, 1797 3 12 Plays, Old English London, 1814 6 8 Playfair's Works, Edinburgh, 1822 3 8 politz, on Education, German, Leipsic, 1824 4 8 Poggius, Works, Latin, Basle, 538 1 f Pombal, Anecdotes of, Fr. Warsaw, 1784 8 Pope's Works, by Roscoe, London, 1824 0 8 Preuss, Elegant Extracts, Ger. Berlin, 1821 1 8 Racine's Works, by Petitot, Fr. Paris, 1813 5 8 Rambler, London, 1820 2 12 Ramler's Poetical Works, Ger. Berlin, 1800 1 8 Ramsey's Travels of Cyrus, Fr. Paris, 1802 2 12 Radondonvilliers, Works, Fr. Paris, 1807 3 8 Raynouard, Selections from the Poetical Works of the Troubadours, Fr. Paris, 1816 6 8 Real, (Abbé de St.) Choice Works, Fr. London, 1778 4 18 Rebolledo, Works, Spanish, Madrid, 1788 4 8 Rees, See Cyclopædia, Repertory of the French Theatre, Fr. Paris, 181 51 8 Retrospective Review, London, 1820 11 8 Richter, (John Paul) Journey to Flactz, German, Tubingen, 1809 1 12 Richter, (John Paul) on Education, Ger. Stuttgart, 1814 3 12 Richter, Flower, Fruit and thor Paintings, German, Berlin, 1818 2 12 Richter, Hesperus, Ger. Berlin, 1819 4 12 Richter, Life of Quintus Fixlein, Ger. 1801 1 12 Richter, Titon, Ger. Leipsic, 1797 1 12 Richter, Titon, German, Berlin, 1800 3 12 Richter, Appendix to Titon, Ger. Berlin, 1800 1 12 Richter, Dr. Katzenberger's Journey to the Bath, German, Bresl, 1823 3 12 Richter, The Valley of Campania, or, the Immortality of the Soul, Ger. 1 12 Richter, Fibal's Life, Ger. Nuremberg, 1 12 Rochefoucalt's Maxims, &amp;c. Calais, 1797 1 8 Romances, (Greek) Translated in French, Paris, 1796 12 12 Roman nights at the Tomb of the Scipios, in manuscript, by B. M. Carter, 1 4 Rousseau's (J. J.) Works, Fr. Paris, 1817 8 8 Rowe's Works, London, 1792 2 8 Rudolphi's Poems, German, Leipsic, 1796 1 12 Runic Poetry, London, 1763 1 8 Salas, New Idea of Ancient Tragedy, Spanish, Madrid, 1778 1 8 Sales, Spanish ive, Sp. Boston, 1820 1 12 Sarrat, on the Game of Chess, London, 1822 1 8 Sauer, Prælections of the German Classics, German, Tubingen, 1816 1 12 Schiller's Works; German, Stuttgart, 1812 12 8 Schlegel's Works complete, German, Vienna, 1822 10 8 Schlegel's on the Language &amp; Wisdom of the Indians, Gmen, 1808 1 12 Schming's Fair Sibille, Ger. Dresden, 1810 2 12 Schming's The Good Office, German, Dresden, 1810 1 12 Schming's Tales, German, Dresden, 1811 2 12 Schming's Ignorance, German, Dresden, 1810 1 12 Schming's Trifles, German, Dresden, 1810 1 12 Schutz's Epigrammatical Anthology, German, allc, 1806 3 12 Seume's Poetry, German, 1810 1 8 Sevigne's Choice Letters, Fr. Paris, 1810 3 12 Selden's Works complete, Latin, London, 1726 6 f Shakspeare, 1 4 Shakspeare, Notes on, London, 1 4 Shakspeare, by Malone, London, 1821 21 8 Shakspeare, (3d vol. wanting.) London, 1800 12 8 Shakspeare, Index, by Twiss, London, 1805 2 8 Shakspeare, Index, by Ayscough, London, 1790 1 8 Shakspeare, Beauties of, by Todd, Edinburgh, 1821 1 12 Shakspeare, Illustrations of, See Douce, Shaftesbury's Characteristics, 1732 3 8 Sheridan's Lectures on the Art of Reading, London, 1765 1 8 Sismondi, on the Literature of the South of Europe, French, Paris, 1819 4 8 Spencer's Works, by Todd, London, 1805 8 8 Spectator, London, 1819 8 8 Spinola's Posthumous Works, Lat. 1677 1 4 Stael, Delphine, Paris, 1809 3 8 Swift's Works, by Scott, Edinburgh, 1824 19 8 Swift's Works, by Sheridan, London, 19 8 Sylvester's (Joshua) Works, See Bartas, Lond. 1633 1 f Tasso's Aminta, Italian, Leghorn, 1802 1 12 Tasso's Jerusalem Delivered, Italian, Milan, 1820 1 8 Tatler, by Chalmers, London, 1822 4 8 Temple's (Sir Wm.) Works, London, 1814 4 8 Theatre, Fr. See Repertory Thomson's Seasons, London, 1816 1 12 Thomson's Annals of Philosophy, London, 1821 9 8 Thomas, Essay on the Character &amp;c. of Females, Fr. Paris, 1773 1 8 Tiedge's Urania, German, Halle, 1819 1 12 Tiedge's Elegies, German, Halle, 1814 3 12 Tooke's Diversions of Purley, Philadelphia, 1806 2 8 Trevoux, See Dictionnaire Trident, or National Policy of Naval Celebration &amp;c. London, 1802 1 4 Tucker's Essays, Georgetown, D. C. 1822 1 8 Tudor's Letters on the Eastern States, 1 8 Vanbrugh's Plays, London, 1759 2 8 Villegas, Las Eroticas y Boecio, Spanish, Madrid, 1797 2 8 Volney's Ruins, Fr. Paris, 1817 1 8 Voltaire's Works complete, French, Paris, 1817 25 8 Voltaire's Essay on Manners, French, Paris, 1754 8 8 Voltaire's Collection of Letters, French, Paris, 1785 12 8 Voltaire's Collection of Letters of, and of D'Alembert, Fr. Paris, 1785 2 8 Voltaire's Collection of &amp;c. &amp; of the King of Prussia, Fr. Paris, 1785 3 8 Voltaire's Collection of &amp;c. and of the Empress of Russia, Fr. Paris, 1785 1 8 Voss, Essay on Education, German, Halle, 1799 2 12 Vossius, Works, Latin, Amsterdam, 1701 6 f Ward's System of Oratory, London, 1759 2 8 Warton's English Poetry, London, 1824 4 8 Wieland's Works, complete, German, Leipsic, 1818 25 8 Witt, (John de) Letters and Negotiations, French, Amsterdam, 1725 5 12 Wright's Translation of "A few days in Athens," NewYork, 1825 1 12 Young's (Edward) Works, London, 1762 4 12 Zimmerman, on Solitude, German, Leipsic, 1784 4 8 TRANSACTIONS OF SOCIETIES, PERIODICALS, &amp;c. Annals of Philosophy, London, from 1825 Annals of Natural Sciences, Fr. Paris, from 1825 Annals of National Industry, from 1825 Annual Register, See Chap. XXIX. Asiatic Journal, London, from 1825 Brewster's Philosophical Journal, Edinburgh, from 1825 Chemical Periodicals, See Chemistry Edinburgh Review, Edinburgh, from 1825 Ferussac's Bulletin of the Sciences, French, Paris, from 1825 Gentleman's Magazine, See Chap. XXIX. Geological Transactions, Periodicals, &amp;c. See Chap. X. Isis of Oken, German, Jena, from 1823 Jameson's Philosophical Journal, Edinburgh, from 1819 to 1822, and from 1825 Journal of General Literature, Ger. from 1825 London Magazine, See Chap. XXIX Memoirs of the Institute, Fr. Paris, from 1806 to 1822 Memoirs of the Imperial Academy of St. Petersburg, See Chap. XXIX. Medical Transactions, Periodicals, &amp;c. See Chap. XXII. Mineralogical Periodicals, &amp;c. See Chap. X New Monthly Magazine, London, No. 37 Niles's Weekly Register, from Sept. 1824 North American Review, from 1825 Pamphleteer, from 1825 Philosophical Magazine and Journal, from 1825 Philosophical Transactions, from 1766 to 1798 Phrenological Journal, from 1825 Quarterly Journal of Science &amp; Art, from 1825 Quarterly Review, from Dec. 1824 Retrospective Review, from 1826 Review (Encyclopedique.) from 1825 Repertory of Patent Inventions, from July 1826 Repertory of Arts and Manufactures, from 1825 Silliman's Journal of Arts and Sciences, from 1825 Transactions of the Literary and Philosophical Society of New York, Transactions of the Society for the encouragement of Arts, from Transactions of the Royal Society of Lond. 1766 to 1798 Transactions of the Royal Society of Edinburgh, from 1815 Westminster Review, from 185</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DONATIONS. [N. B. The Works are found distributed amongst the proper Chapters, in the body of the Catalogue.] Vols. Size By WILLIAM E. ALLEN. Lady Morgan's Italy, 2 8 By Mr. BARNARD. Barnard's Polyglot Grammar, 1 8 By THOMAS BARCLAY. Latin and English Dictionary 1 4 Elements of Euclid 1 8 Mc Pherson's Groat Britain 1 4 By Mr. JEREMY BENTHAM. Bentham, (Jeremy) Essay on Political Tactics, pamphlet Bentham, Truth versus Ashurst, pamphlet Bentham, King against Sir Charles Wolseley, pamph. By Dr. FRANK CARR. Sallust, a specimen of the earliest Stereotype, by William Ged By Mr. CLEVELAND. Cleveland (Chas. D.) Epitome of Grecian Antiquities By Mr. BERNARD M. CARTER. Hume's &amp; Smollet's England, London, 1802 13 Quintilian, by Guthrie, London, 1756 2 Ferguson's Rome, Edinburgh, 1799 5 Hume's Essays, Edinburgh, 1800 2 Chesterfield's Miscellaneous Works, London, 1772 4 Chesterfield's Letters, London, 1800 4 Leland's Demosthenes, London, 1802 2 Ferguson, on Civil Society, London, 1794 1 Life of Pitt, Earl of Chatham, London, 1797 3 Paley's Philosophy, London, 1788 2 Blair's Lectures on Rhetoric, Philadelphia, 1793 2 Cavallo, on Electricity, 3 Marshall's Life of Washington, and Atlas 6 Gibbon's Rome, Dublin, 1787 6 Robertson's Charles V. 1792 4 Robertson's America, Dublin, 1777 2 Darwin's Botanic Garden, New-York, 1798 2 Buffon's Natural History, abridged, 1792 2 Cicero's Orations, by Guthrie, 1778 3 Rowning's Natural Philosophy, 1779 3 Pindar's (Peter) Works, 1797 3 Rutherford's Institutes, 1799 2 Anacharsis's Travels, in 7 vols. &amp; Atlas, 1794 8 Plutarch's Lives, by Dryden, 1770 8 Johnson's (Samuel) Works, 1810 12 Lysias &amp; Isocrates, by Gillies, 1778 1 4 Gibbon's Miscellaneous Works, 1796 2 4 Voltaire's Age of Louis XIV. Fr. 1808 2 Hale's Pleas of the Crown, 1800 2 Tomlin's Law Dictionary, 1797 2 4 Coke upon Littleton, 1794 6 Blackstone's Commentaries, 1793 4 Williams's Reports, 1793 3 Vattel's Law of Nations, 1793 1 Cowper's Reports, 1800 2 Wooddeson's Vinerian Lectures on English Law, 1792 3 Burrow's Reports, 1790 5 Lacretelle's History of France, Fr. 1812 6 Botta, History of the War of the Independence of the United States, Fr. 1812 4 Stael Holstein, Mad. de Delphine, Fr. 1819 6 Genlis, Theatre of Society, Fr. 1811 2 Demoustier, Letters on Mythology, Fr. 1816 6 Dufrenoy's Tour of the World, Fr. 1814 6 La Fontaine, Fables, Fr. 1801 2 Bouilly, Tales for my Daughter, Fr. 1818 2 Bouilly, Advice to my Daughter, Fr. 1813 2 Sevigné's Choice Letters, Fr. 1800 3 Boyer's Fr. &amp; Eng. Dictionary, 1797 1 Genlis, The young Emigrants, Fr. 1812 2 Wailley's Principles of the French Language, Fr. 1820 1 Trimmer's Scripture Catechism, 1818 2 Trimmer's Scripture Hist. Abridged, 1811 1 Perrin's Fables, 1820 1 Florian's Fables, 1811 1 Rambler, 1820 2 Lequien, Conjugation of Verbs, Fr. 1811 1 Shakspeare's Plays, (3d wanting) 1800 11 Cicero's Letters, by Melmoth, 1808 5 Nugent's Fr. &amp; Eng. Dictionary, 1818 1 Roman Nights at the Tomb of the Scipios, 1819 2 Blair's Sermons, 1792 5 Repertory of the French Theatre, Fr. 1813 51 O Don Quixote, 1820 4 Rollin's Works complete, Fr. 1807 60 Russell's Ancient Europe, 1801 2 Pinkerton's Geography, 1811 1 Carter's (B. M.) Poems 1 Yamoyden, 1820 1 Dictionary of the French Academy 2 4 Edinburgh Review, No. 37 New Monthly Magazine, No. 37 New Instructive Games at Cards, Fr By Mr. JOSEPH COOLIDGE. Homerus, Iliad 2 Tacitus, Ernesti &amp; Oberlin 4 Guizot, Dictionary of Synonymes, Fr. 1 Linnaeus, System of Vegetables, Lat. 6 Linnaeus, Mantissa, Rœmer &amp; Schultes, Lat. 1 Pindarus, Heyne, Lat. 3 Buttman's Greek Grammar, by Everett, 1 Jacob's Greek Reader, 1 Thiersch, Greek Tables, by Patton, 1 Legendre, Elements of Geometry 1 Milner's Greek Grammar, 1 Gesenius, Hebrew Lexicon, by Gib 1 Stuart's Hebrew Grammar 1 Tacitus, History Lib. V. Barbou, 1 Livius, Drakenborch 6 Cicero's Works, Ernestius 20 Virgilius, Wakefield 2 Sallust, Delphin 1 4 Quintilianus, Institutions, by Rollin 2 Florula Bostoniensis, by Bigelow 1 Machiavel's Hist. of Florence 2 Genesi, on the Penal Code of Romagnosi 2 Bolingbroke's Letters on History 1 Playfair's Works, 4 Aldrich's Architecture, by Smith 1 Palladio, the five Orders of Architecture, Italian 1 4 Newton's Principia 3 Elementary Tieatise of Trigonometry 1 Bezout, First principles of Differentials, &amp;c. 1 Boileau's Works, Fr. 3 Euler's Elements of Algebra, by Farrar, 1 Lacroix's Elements of Algebra, by Farrar, 1 Lacroix's Trigonometry, by Farrar 1 Lacroix's Arithmetic, by Farrar 1 Cleveland's Mineralogy and Geology 2 Tudor's Life of James Otis 1 Tudor's Letters on the Eastern States 1 Horace, by Hunter 1 By Mr. CROZET. Crozet's Descriptive Geometry By MAJOR CARTWRIGHT. Cartwright, on the English Constitution 1 8 Trident 1 4 By Mrs. VIRGINIA CAREY Bayle's Historical &amp; Critical Dictionary, London. 1735 5 f Bishop Knnet's Hist of England, London, 1719 3 f Boyle's Works. London, 1772 6 4 The Doctor and Student, London, 1575 1 12 Philips, General English Dictionary, London, 1671 1 f By PROFESSOR DUNGLISON. Alcock's Section of the Leg after Amputation Clarke, on the Climate, Diseases &amp;c. of France, Italy, &amp;c. Surgeon's Vade mecum, edit. by Dunglison 1 12 Larrey, on Moxa, translated by Dunglison 1 8 Dunglison, on diseases of Stomach and Bowels of Children 1 8 Dunglison, Syllabus of Medical Jurisprudence 1 8 Haden's Formulary, by Dunglison 1 8 Medical Intelligencer, Nos. 29, 30, 31, 39, &amp; 48, by Dunglison Philadelphia Journal of Medical and Physical Sciences Historical Account of the discovery of the Cow-pox, pamphlet Surgical Memoirs, by Larrey By Mr. J. EVELYN DENISON, (Member of Parliament of Great Britain.) Supplement to Jamieson's Etymological Dictionary of the Scottish Language 2 4 Jenning's Dialects of the West of England 1 12 The Craven Dialect 1 12 By PROFESSOR EMMET. Exposition of the Atomic Teory of Chemistry, pamphlet, 30 cpies Tabular view of the Modern Nomenclature and system of Chemistry, 30 copies Instructions for the use of the Alcohometer, pamphlet By Mr. E. EVERETT, (n behalf of the Author.) America, by the Author of Europe 1 8 By Mr. GREENWAY. Greenway's collection of Plants of Virginia, M. S. 4 By Miss GURNEY, (England.) Anglo-Saxon Chronicle, translated, (extremely scarce) By GOVERNOR GILES. Pamphlet, containing Mr. Clay's Speech on the Tariff, Mr. Giles's Speech in reply to Mr. Clay, and his reply to Gen. Taylor, Richmond, 1827 1 8 By Mr. THEOD: HANSFORD. Epictetus, Cebes &amp; Porphyrus, Gr. &amp; Lat. 1 Cicero de Officiis 8 Ausonius, not. var. 1 Sophocles, Cambridge, 1669 1 Plautus, Paris, 1779 1 Plautus, Francfort, 1641 1 Quintilian's Institutions. &amp;c. Paris, 1629 1 Isocrates, Wolf, Gr. &amp; Lat. Roun, 1652 1 By Mr. WILLIAM WALLER HENNING. Henning's Statutes at Large 13 8 By Mr. HARRIS. Catalogue of the Library of the Royal Institution of Gr. Britain 1 8 By Mr. HARRIS, (of Plymouth, England.) Effects of Lightning on Floating Bodies, by Mr. Harris By Dr. JAMES JACKSON. James Jackson, Syllabus of Lectures delivered to the Medical Students at Harvard University James Jackson, Discourse on Fever James Jackson, Text Book of Lectures on the Theory and practice of Medicine James Jackson, Eulogy on the character of Dr. Warren By Mr. THOMAS JEFFERSON. (Independently of a Tstmnary Donation of his Library, not yet appropriated to the University.) American Philosophical Transactions, vol. 2, new series Josse's Spanish Grammar &amp; is 1 8 Sales, Spanish Hive, Spanish 1 12 By Mr. T. H. KEY. Key, C. on Lithotomy, London 1 4 Brewster's Philosophical Journal, a few numbers By GENERAL LA FAYETTE. Thierry, Conquest of England, by the Normands, Fr. 3 8 By Mr. LAMBERT. Lambert's Report on the Longitude of Washington City By Mr. WILLIAM MATTHEWS. Goldsmith, Citizen of the World, Philadelphia, 1804 2 12 By Mr. CHARLES F. MERCER. Mercer, (C. F.) Discourse on Popular Education By Mr. JAMES MADISON. Palladio's Architecture 1 4 Kelsall's Phantasm of a University 1 f Haler's Arithmetic 1 8 By WILLIAM Mc CLURE. Michaux, North American Sylva 2 4 Observation on the Geology of the United States, pamph let Essay on the Foundation of Rocks, pamphlet By THE CITY OF NEW-YORK. Colden's Memoir of the Celebration of the New-York Canal By Mr. OBADIAH RICH, (American Consul at Valencia.) Abu Zacaria Ebn el Awam, Agriculture, Arabic and Spanish 2 f Antonio, (N.) Bibliotheca Hispana Vetus 4 f Bibliotheca Arabic Hispana 2 f By Mr. LEWIS ROGERS. Stadius, Description, &amp;c. of Brazil 1 f By Col. THOMAS M. RANDOLPH. Shakspeare's Works, 1 vol. 4 to, printed at different times from 1600 to 1619 Il Petrarca, Lyons, 1557, with corrections in M. S. by the Inquisition, in the handwriting of their Officer By Mrs. RANDOLPH. Veneroni's Dictionary, Fr. &amp; It. 2 4 By Dr. RICE, (the Editor.) John Smith's Travels in Europe, Asia, Africa, &amp; America, Richmond, 1819 2 8 By Mr. SPAFFORD. Spafford's Gazetteer, Albany, 1824 Spafford's Pocket Guide for the Canal of New-York By NICHOLAS P. TRIST Hennipen's America, 1698 1 8 Smith's (W.) History of New-York, 1769 1 4 By PROFESSOR TUCKER. Tucker's Essays 1 8 Poetical Pamphlets, published in England 2 8 Darwin's Botanic Garden, plates, London 1 4 Milton's Works, by Newton, London 2 4 Bentham, (Jeremy) Panopticon, London 2 8 By Mr. ELKANAH WATSON. History of the New-York Canals 1 8 By Dr. WATERHOUSE. Waterhouse's Botanist 1 8 Waterhouse's Essay on Whooping Cough, &amp;c. 1 8 By Dr. WEBSTER. Webster, (John W.) Manual of Chemistry, Boston, 1827</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SUPPLEMENT. CHAP. I.—ANCIENT LANGUAGES. Vols. Size Agriculture, Latin writers on, including Varro, Cato, Columella, &amp;c. Antiquities, Gallery of, Fr. Paris 1 8 Antoninus Marcus, Moral Reflections, by Dacier, Bouillon, 1788 2 12 Architecture Grecian, by Lord Aberdeen, See Chapter XXVIII. London, 1822 Aristoteles, Treatise on Animals, See Chap. IX. Balbec, Antiqnities of, by Wood, See Chap. XXVIII Clarke, Greek Marbles, See Chap. XXVIII. Elgin Marbles, See Visconti, Chap. XXVIII. Eichhorn, Universal History, German, See Chap. II. Epicurus, Morals of, Batteaux, Fr. Paris, 1758 1 12 Galenus, Gr. See Chap. XXII. Greece, Antiquities of, See Chap. XXVIII. Greek, Love Stories, Translated into French, Paris, 1796 12 24 Heeren, on the Polity, Commerce, &amp;c. of the principal Nations of Antiquity, See Chap. XXV Heeren, Manual of Ancient History, Ger Gottingen 1 8 Herculanum, Antiquities of, See Chap. XXVIII. Hiibler, Synchronical Tables, 1st part, German, Freyburg, 1802 1 f Hippocrates, Greek, See Chap. XXII. History, Antient &amp; Modern, See Bibliotheque, Universal, Chap. XXIX. History, Universal, See Biblioth &amp;c. Literature, Ancient, See Memoirs of the French Institute, Chap. XXIX. Literature, and the Fine Arts, See Memoirs of, &amp;c. Manilius, Poem on Astronomy, Latin and French, Paris, 1786 2 8 Mathematicians, Ancient, Gr. &amp; Lat. See Chap. V. Meiners, on the Origin, Progress, and Decline of Philosophy in Greece and Rome, Ger. See Chap. II. Onosander, Strategics, Gr. &amp; Fr. 1 12 Paestum, Ruins of, See Chap. XXVIII Palmyra, Ruins of, Wood, See Chap. XXVIII. Polymetis, Spence, See Chap. XXVIII. Plinius, Natural History, See Chap. VI. Plinius, Letters by Mehnoth, Eng. Boston, 1809 2 8 Plotnus, Works. Gr. &amp; Lat. Basle, 1615 1 f Rome, Ancient Edifices of, See Chap. XXVIII. Salmasius, notes on Plinius, See Chap IX. Theophrastus, Characters of, by La Brnyère, French, Avignon, 1817 2 8 Theophrastus, ist. of Plants, with translation, See Chapter VIII Timaeus Locrensis, D'Argens, Greek and French, Berlin, 1763 1 12 Vitruvius, See Chapter XXVIII. CHAP. II—MODERN HISTORY: Annual Register, See Chap. XXIX. Gentleman's Magazine, See Chap. XXIX. Ginguené, Literary History of Italy, Fr. Paris, 1824 5 8 Hubler's Synchronical Tables, See Ant. Hist. Supp. Pauw, Philosophical Inquiries regarding the Americans, See Chap. XXIX. Riley's Narrative, New-York, 1818 1 8 Schlegel, on the History of Literature, Philad. 1818 2 8 CHAP. III—MODERN GEOGRAPAY. Jefferson's Notes, See Miscell. Kotzebue's Journey to Rome, Ger. Berlin, 1805 2 12 Martinière, See Chap. XX. Pallas, Travels in Russia, See Chap. I. Stadius, Description of Brazil, Lat. Francfort, 1592 1 f CHAP. IV—MODERN PHILOLOGY &amp; LITERATURE. Bouterwek's History of Modern Literature, German, Gottingen, 1810 12 8 Buchholz, Spanish Literature, Selections, German, Berlin, 1804 2 8 Tooke's Diversions of Purley, Philadelphia, 1806 2 8 Lossius, Modern Philosophical Literature, German, Halle, 1778 3 8 Siefort, Fragments of French Literature, German, Halle, 1822 2 8 Tiraboschi, Italian Literature, It. Florence, 1805 10 8 CHAP. VIII—BOTANY. Darwin's Botanic Garden, See Miscell. Supp. CHAP. XXIII—MENTAL PHILOSOPHY &amp; ETHICS. Cabanis, connexion between Mind and Body, See Chapter XXII Gall &amp; Spurzheim, on Phrenology, See Chap. XXII. Gall, Functions of the Brain, &amp;c. See Chap. XXII. Spurzheim, on Phrenology, See Chap. XXII. CHAP. XXV—POLITICS. Giles, (Gov.) Pamphlet containing Mr. Clays Speech on the Tariff, Mr. Giles's Speech in reply to Mr. Clay, and his reply to Gen. Taylor, Richmond, 1827 1 8 Political pamphlets, published in England 12 8 CHAP. XXIX—MISCELLANEOUS. Darwin's Botanic Garden, plates, London 1 4 Milton's Works, by Newton, London 2 4 Bentham, (Jeremy) Panopticon, London 2 8</field>
      <field name="fulltext">P INDEX. Chap. Page Agriculture 7 42 Anatomy, Sound and Morbid 16 55 Ancient Languages, Supp. to, p. 108 1 3 Antiquities, Chap. I. II. &amp; XXVIII. Architecture 28 89 Biography, See Antient Languages &amp; Modern History Botany, 8 43 Botany, Supp. to, page 112 Chemistry 11 48 Designing 28 89 Donations 103 Ecclesiastical History 27 83 Education 29 91 Ethics 23 68 Geography, Ancient, See Ancient Languages Geography, Modern 3 21 Geography, Modern Supp. to, page 111 Geology 10 47 History, Ancient, 1 3 History, Ecclesiastical 27 83 History, Medical 12 50 History, Modern 2 13 History, Modern Supp. to, page 111 Horticulture 7 42 Hygiene 13 51 Law 26 74 Literature Modern, 4 24 Literature Modern, Supp. to, page 111 Materia Medica 14 52 Mathematics 5 28 Medical Biography 12 50 Medical Jurisprudence 15 54 Medical Transactions, Dictionaries, Periodicals, &amp;c. 22 67 Medicine General, 22 66 Medicine History of, 12 50 Medicine Veterinary 21 65 Midwifery, See Obstetrics Mineralogy 10 47 Miscellaneous 29 91 Miscellaneous Supp. to, page 112 Music 28 89 Natural History, General 6 41 Obstetrics 20 65 Painting 28 9 Pathology 18 59 Periodicals, &amp;c. 29 102 Pharmacy 14 52 Philology Modern, 4 24 Philology Modern, Supp. to, page 111 Philosophy Mental, 23 68 Philosophy Mental, Supp. to, page 1I Philosophy Natural 5 28 Physiology 17 57 Poetry 29 91 Political Economy 24 70 Politics 25 71 Politics Supp. to, page 112 Religion, (Christian, Ethnick, &amp;c.) 27 83 Rhetoric 29 91 Sculpture 28 89 Supplement to the Catalogue, 1 Surgery Operative, 19 64 Surgery Pathological Works on, See Chap. XVIII. 18 59 Therapeutics 18 59 Toxicology 15 54 Transactions of Societies, Periodicals, &amp;c. 27 102 Veterinary Art, See Medicine Veterinary Voyages &amp; Travels, See Modern Geography &amp; Miscell. Zoology 9 45</field>
   </doc>
</add>