<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university of virginia</field>
      <field name="author_text">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2005_Q4_2/uvaBook/tei/z000000136.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240342</field>
      <field name="date_text"/>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:165655</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Catalogue of the University of Virginia. Session of 1858-'59</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">University of Virginia -- Periodicals</field>
      <field name="subject_text">University of Virginia -- Periodicals</field>
      <field name="title_display">Catalogue of the University of Virginia.  Session of 1858-'59</field>
      <field name="title_facet">catalogue of the university of virginia</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">catalogue of the university of virginia</field>
      <field name="title_text">Catalogue of the University of Virginia.  Session of 1858-'59</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1858</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:165655&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:165655&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;serial volume&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;university of virginia&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Catalogue of the University of Virginia. Session of 1858-'59&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;catalogue of the university of virginia&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Catalogue of the University of Virginia&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1858-1859&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Va.&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;The University&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa call number"&gt;LD5667&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;X004575773&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;o05654199&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;48 p. ; 18-23 cm.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;University of Virginia -- Periodicals&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Catalogue of the University of Virginia&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1858-1859&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Va.&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2004&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2004 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 166 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Board of Visitors. THOMAS JEFFERSON RANDOLPH, Rector. MUSCOE R. H. GARNETT, of Essex county. WILLIAM T. JOYNES, of Petersburg. WILLIAM J. ROBERTSON, of Albemarle county. JOHN R. EDMUNDS, of Halifax county. JOHN B. BALDWIN, of Augusta county. JOHN R. TUCKER, of Winchester. JAMES L. CARR, of Kanawha. JAMES NEESON, of Marion county. R. T. W. DUKE, Secretary. N. H. MASSIE, Commissioner of Accounts.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CATALOGUE. Faculty, Instructors and Officers. S. MAUPIN, M. D., Chairman. LITERARY AND SCIENTIFIC SCHOOLS: GESSNER HARRISON, M. D., LL. D., Professor of Latin. BASIL L. GILDERSLEEVE, PH. D., Professor of Greek and Hebrew. M. SCHELE DE VERE, LL. D., Professor of Modern Languages. ALBERT T. BLEDSOE, LL. D., Professor of Mathematics. FRANCIS H. SMITH, A. M., Professor of Natural Philosophy. S. MAUPIN, M. D., Professor of Chemistry. WM. H. McGUFFEY, D. D., LL. D., Professor of Moral Philosophy. GEORGE F. HOLMES, Professor of History and General Literature. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. A. von FISCHERZ, Assistant Instructor in German. G. BAILLARD, Assistant Instructor in French. G. LANZA, Assistant Instructor in Spanish and Italian. ROBERT T. MASSIE, AND JOHN M. STROTHER, A. M., Assistant Instructors in Mathematics. DAVID K. TUTTLE, PH. D., Assistant Instructor in Chemistry. MEDICAL SCHOOLS: HENRY HOWARD, M. D., Professor of Medicine. JAMES L. CABELL, M. D., Professor of Comparative Anatomy, Physiology and Surgery. S. MAUPIN, M. D., Professor of Chemistry and Pharmacy. JOHN S. DAVIS, M. D., Professor of Anatomy, Materia Medica, Therapeutics and Botany. B. W. ALLEN, M. D., Demonstrator of Anatomy. CATALOGUE. LAW SCHOOL: JOHN B. MINOR, LL. D., Professor of Common and Statute Law. JAMES P. HOLCOMBE, LL. D., Professor of Civil, Constitutional and International Law, Equity, and the Law Merchant. Rev. DABNEY CARR HARRISON, Chaplain. ROBERT R. PRENTIS, Proctor and Patron. WILLIAM A. BIBB, Bursar. WILLIAM WERTENBAKER, Secretary to the Faculty. THOMAS B. HOLCOMBE, Librarian. WILLIAM A. PRATT, Superintendent of Grounds and Buildings. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. HOTEL-KEEPERS WITHIN THE UNIVERSITY: Mrs. MARY S. ROSS, DANIEL WARD, WYATT W. HAMNER. WILLIAM WERTENBAKER, Post Master. [NAME OF POST-OFFICE: UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA.] Gymnastics are taught under the authority of the Faculty, by J. E. D'ALFONCE.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CATALOGUE. Catalogue of Students. THIRTY-FIFTH SESSION—1858-'59. ABBREVIATIONS. LAT.,Latin. M. L.,Modern Languages. GR.,Greek. N. P.,Natural Philosophy. MAT.,Mathematics. H. &amp; L.,History and Literature. CH.,Chemistry. MA. MED.,Materia Medica. P. &amp; S.Physiology and Surgery. MED.,Medicine. M. P.,Moral Philosophy. AN.,Anatomy. PHR.,Pharmacy. MED. JUS.,Medical Jurisprudence. BOT.,   Botany. Names. Residence. Schools Attended. No. of Sess. Adams, Charles L. Grenada, Miss. LAT., M. L. 1st. Allen, William J. Lunenburg, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN 1st. Allen, William Winchester, Va. GR, M. L., N. P. 2d. Allison, William H. Enon, Ala. MAT., N. P., CH. 1st. Alsop, George E. Fredericksburg, Va. CH., M. P., H. &amp; L. 2d. Amacker, O. P. Tangapaho, La. M. P., H. &amp; L. 1st. Armistead, Charles J. Cumberland, Va. LAT., MAT., CH., GR. 3d. Anderson, Edward C. jr. Savannah, Ga. N. P., H. &amp; L., LAW. 3d. Anderson, G. W. jr. Savannah, Ga. M. L., M. P., H. &amp; L. 1st. Anderson, Garrett King and Queen, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Anderson, Joseph W. Pattonsburg, Va. M. P., LAW. 1st. Anderson, Archer Richmond City, Va. LAW. 3d. Arnold, Philip M. King George, Va. LAW. 1st. Arnold, Thomas T. King George, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Arnold, A. J. Alexandria, Va. LAT., MAT., CH. 1st Arrington, S. L. Montgomery, Ala. N. P., M. P., H. &amp; L., MAT. 2d Baker, Thomas H. Hopkinsville, Ky. LAW. 2d. Baird, E. R. Essex, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Baldwin, W. H. Monroe, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Barber, Samuel B. Fauquier, Va. LAT., M. L., N. P., M. P., MAT. 1st Bardwell, Edward L. Columbus, Ga. N. P., CH., M. P. 3d UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. Bargamin, E. V. Richmond City, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT. 1st. Barnard, Thomas Natchez, Miss. LAT., M. L., MAT. 1st. Barrett, John Henry Henderson, Ky. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Baylor, Robert P. Essex, Va. LAT., M. L., GR. 2d. Beale, William R. Botetourt, Va. LAT., M. L., N. P. 1st. Beall, Samuel Lumpkin, Ga. N. P., M. P., H. &amp; L. 2d. Beauchamp, A. W. Lancaster, Va. LAW, MAT. 1st. Beckham, H. C. Culpeper C. H., Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Bedinger, George R. Jefferson, Va. LAT., M. L., H. &amp; L., MAT. 1st. Bell, L. R. Oxford, N. C. LAT., M. L., MAT. 1st. Berry, John S. Fredericksburg, Va. LAT., GR., MAT., N. P. 1st. Berry, L. L. G. Canton, Miss. LAT., M. L., CH., M. P. 2d. Bentley, J. Mordecai Danville, Ky. LAT., M. L., MAT. 1st. Bethea, Alfred Montgomery, Ala. LAT., MAT., M. P. 2d. Birchett, G. K, jr. Vicksburg, Miss. LAT., M. L., N. P. 3d. Bird, Mark, jr. Woodstock, Va. M. P., H. &amp; L., LAW. 3d. Bird, William Wallace Washington City, D. C. LAW. 6th. Blackford, Launcelot M. Lynchburg, Va. M. L., MAT., N. P. 4th. Blackford, Eugene Lynchburg, Va. LAT., GR., MAT., M. P. 2d. Blackburn, J. S. Charlestown, Va. LAT., MAT., M. P., H. &amp; L. 2d. Blair, Joseph A. Richmond City, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Bland, B. F. King and Queen, Va. LAT., M. L., MAT., M. P. 1st. Bledsoe, P. Fluvanna, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Boddie, N. V. Florence, Ala. LAT., M. L., M. P., H. &amp; L. 2d. Bondurant, George P. Buckingham, Va. LAT., M. L., M. P. 2d. Booton, William S. Rome, Ga. LAT., MAT., N. P. 2d. Bouldin, Thomas T. jr. Charlotte, Va. LAT., MAT., N. P. 1st. Bowie, Alexander Charleston, S. C. M. L., MAT., N. P. 1st. Bowie, Edwin Westmoreland, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Boyce, William M. Rapides, La. LAW, M. P. 1st. Boyd, E. Holmes Winchester, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 2d. Boyd, James M. Lynchburg, Va. GR., M. L., MAT., N. P., CH. 2d. Boykin, Anthony R. Isle of Wight, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Boykin, Robert James Portland, Ala. LAT., GR., N. P., M. P. 2d. Boykin, Frank Camden, S. C. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Bozeman, Joseph W. Louisville, Miss. LAT., GR., MAT., N. P. 1st. Bradford, Tipton Talladega, Ala. M. L., H. &amp; L. 1st. Bratton, John McK. Bath, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Breckinridge, Joseph C. Lexington, Ky. MAT., N. P., M. P. 1st. Briers, Henry H. Union Springs, Ala. LAW. 1st. Briggs, Charles A. New York City LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 2d. Brodwater, Jos. E. Accomac, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT. 1st. Bronaugh, F. L. Loudoun, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 2d. Brookes, John Venable Halifax, Va. M. L., N. P., CH. 3d. Brookes, Samuel Hunt Halifax, Va. LAT., M. L., M. P. 3d. Brown, George C. Nashville, Tenn. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Brown, John William Rappahannock, Va. LAT., M. L., MAT., M. P. 2d. Brown, John Peter Anderson, S. C. LAW. 1st. CATALOGUE. Bryan, James H. Bellevue, Ga. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Bryant, William H. Montgomery, Ala. LAW. 1st. Bryant, James F. Southampton, Va. LAT., GR., M. &amp; L., M. P. 1st. Butler, C. A. Everglades, Florida LAW. 3d. Butler, W. B. Orange Mills, Florida LAW. 3d. Butt, Josiah W. Norfolk County, Va. MAT., N. P., M. P., H. &amp; L. 2d. Byers, G. Newton Jefferson, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. Byrd, William M. jr. Selma, Ala. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Caine, J. E. Edgefield C. H., S. C. M. L., M. P. 1st. Cameron, J. H. Lexington, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Campbell, Henry B. Monroe, Va. MAT., N. P., CH. 1st. Cannon, D. C. Norfolk City, Va. GR. 5th. Carr, William C. Fauquier, Va. M. P., H. &amp; L. 3d. Carmichael, William Wye Mills, Md. M. L., MAT., M. P. 2d. Carrington, George W. Richmond City, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 2d. Carrington, W. C. P. Charlottesville, Va. LAW. 1st. Carter, Robert K. Frederick, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Caruthers, William Prince Edward, Va. M. L., MAT. 2d. Catterton, Finks Nortonsville, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Chaplain, W. W. Princ's Anne C. H., Va. LAT., M. L., MAT. 1st. Chapman, A. G. Port Tobacco, Md. M. P., LAW. 2d. Chester, W. Y. Lexington, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., M. P. 1st. Clark, Frank Peyton Winchester, Va. LAT., M. L., N. P. 2d. Clay, William H. Amelia, Va. CH., MA. MED. 3d. Clopton, T. J. Gloucester, Va. LAT., CH., H. &amp; L. 2d. Cochran, John L. Staunton, Va. LAT., MAT., N. P. 2d. Cochran, Howe Peyton Charlottesville, Va. MAT., H. &amp; L. 5th. Cocke, Charles L. Portsmouth, Va. LAW. 1st. Cocke, Thomas L. P. Cartersville, Va. MAT., N. P., CH. 1st. Coffman, Samuel J. Rockingham, Va. M. L., MAT., CH. 4th. Coffman, S. H. Garlandsville, Miss. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Coleman, John H. Athens, Ala. LAW. 1st. Coleman, Daniel Athens, Ala. LAW. 1st. Coleman, C. G. Louisa, Va. LAT., GR., MAT., CH. 1st. Coleman, Barry Louisville, Ky. MAT., CH., H. &amp; L. 1st. Coleman, B. F. Midway, Ala. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Collins, Robert M. Barton, Miss. N. P., P. &amp; S., H. &amp; L. 2d. Conner, Richard E. Natchez, Miss. LAT., M. P., H. &amp; L. 2d. Cooper, James D. Franklin, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Conrad, Holmes Winchester, Va. LAT., MAT., GR., CH. 1st. Conrad, H. Tucker Martinsburg, Va. LAT., M. L., N. P., M. P. 2d. Conrad, L. Lewis New Orleans, La. M. L., MAT., H. &amp; L. 3d. Cooke, J. C. Hanover, Va. MAT., CH., H. &amp; L. 1st. Corr, D. F. King and Queen, Va. LAT., M. L., MAT., N. P. 1st. Couper, Robert H. Darien, Ga. LAT., GR., MAT. 2d. Cowherd, Powell H. Albemarle, Va. N. P., CH., P. &amp; S. 3d. Cowin, J. H. Greensboro', Ala. CH., MED., P. S., AN., BOT. 1st. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. Cox, Joseph E. Chesterfield, Va. LAW. 6th. Cox, Joseph. Petersburg, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. Craven, P. H. Charlottesville, Va. LAT., M. L., MAT. 1st. Crawford, John D. Staunton, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Crisfield, Arthur Somerset, Md. LAT., M. L., MAT. 2d. Cross, Thomas H. Nansemond, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Cullingworth, J. N. Richmond City, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 2d Dandridge, E. P. Jefferson, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Dandridge, R. B. Henry, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Daniel, John S. Farmville, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 2d. Daniel, John M. University of Va. LAT., N. P., CH. 1st. Davis, Wilbur F. Murfreesboro', N. C. LAT., M. L., N. P., M. P. 2d. Davis, Samuel P. Liberty, Va. M. P., LAW. 2d. Day, John B. Charlottesville, Va. LAT., M. L., MAT. 2d. De Jarnette E. H. Spotsylvania, Va. LAT., M. L., MAT. 1st. Delahoussaye, C. Octave Jeanneretts, La. LAW. 3d. Deming, Joseph C. Norfolk City, Va. MAT., M. P., H. &amp; L. 1st. Dennis, Z. P. New Providence, Tenn. LAT., M. L., MAT. 1st. Deyerle, John S. Roanoke, Va. MED., P. &amp; S., AN., PHD. 2d. Dillard, W. H. Sussex, Va. M. L., CH., M. P. 1st. Dinwiddie, John C. Albemarle, Va. M. L., H. &amp; L. 3d. Dinwiddie, James L. Albemarle, Va. LAT., GR., MAT., M. P. 1st. Dobbin, Robert A. jr. Baltimore, Md. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Doby, Alfred E. Ridgeway, S. C. N. P., CH., H. &amp; L. 1st. Drewry, J. H. Southampton, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Du Bose, William P. Winnsboro', S. C. M. L., CH., H. &amp; L. 3d. Dubroca, Armand B. West Baton Rouge, La. N. P., CH., M. P. 2d. Dunlap, James C. Summerdean, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Durant, J. B. Brazoria, Texas LAW. 3d. Dwight, William M. Rantoules, S. C. CH., M. P., H. &amp; L. 2d. Earle, Richard T. jr. Centreville, Md. GR., M. L., MAT. 2d. Edwards, John R. Norfolk County, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Ehringhouse, William M. Seguin, Texas MAT., N. P. 1st. Elmore, Augusto Lima, Peru M. L., MAT., M. P. 2d. Elmore, Frederick Lima, Peru M. L., MAT., N. P., M. P. 2d. Emory, Thomas Washington City, D. C. LAT., M. L., MAT. 1st. English, William O. Westmoreland, Va. MAT., N. P. 5th. Estes, Robert T. Orange, Va. LAT., M. L., M. P. 3d. Estes, Joel H. Durhamsville, Tenn LAT., MAT. 1st. Estill, Charles P. Lexington, Va. GR., M. L., MAT., N. P. 3d. Estill, J. L. Lexington, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Ewing, Benjamin B. Satartia, Miss. M. L., N. P., M. P. 2d. Fail, William G. Camden, Ala. M. L., N. P., M. P., H. &amp; L. 2d. Fairfax, Julian Alexandria, Va. LAT., GR., MAT., N. P. 1st. Farquhar, Guy E. Pottsville, Pa. LAT, GR., MAT., M. P. 1st. CATALOGUE. Faulkner, J. K. Halifax, Va. LAT., GR., M. L. 1st. Faulkner, E. Boyd Martinsburg, Va. M. P., H. &amp; L., LAW. 1st. Fauntleroy, Thomas Middlesex, Va. LAT., GR., CH., M. P. 2d. Fauntleroy, A. M. Winchester, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT. 1st Featherston, J. C. Anderson, S. C. LAW. 2d Ferrell, A. C. Logan C. H., Va. LAW. 2d Ferguson, J. E. Danville, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT. 1st Ferneyhough, G. N. Albemarle, Va. LAT., CH., M. P. 2d. Field, William G. Culpeper C. H., Va. LAT., MAT., N. P., CH. 2d Field, John W. Accomac, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT. 1st. Fitz Gerald, N. Hampton, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st Fitzgerald, H. P. Nottoway, Va. LAT., M. L., MAT. 1st Fleming, F. N. Goochland, Va. LAW. 2d Fleming, Malcolm N. Hanover, Va. LAT., M. L., M. P. 1st. Flood, Thomas Walker Appomattox, Va. LAW. 1st. Flood, Joel Walker Appomattox, Va. MAT., N. P., H. &amp; L. 1st Flood, William M. Henry, Va. LAW. 2d. Fontaine, William M. Hanover, Va. M. L., CH., M. P., H. &amp; L. 3d Fontaine, Peter Hanover, Va. GR., M. L., N. P., M. P. 2d. Foreman, Columbus W. Norfolk County, Va. CH., M. P., H. &amp; L., MAT. 1st Forniss, G. McD. Prairie Bluff, Ala. CH., M. P., H. &amp; L. 1st Forrest, Douglas French Fairfax, Va. LAW. 1st Foster, C. B. Princess Anne, Va. LAT., M. L. 1st Fowlkes, Eusebius Montgomery, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Fox, William Fayette King William, Va. GR., M. L., MAT. 3d Fraser, James L. Beaufort, S. C. M. L., MAT., M. P., N. P. 1st. Frazier, D. S. Summerfield, N. C. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st Freeman, T. Major Frankfort, Ky LAW. 1st Fuller, N. B. Beaufort, S. C. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT. 2d Gachet, Charles Chunnennuggee, Ala. N. P., M. P., H. &amp; L. 2d Gaines, J. M. Culpeper, C. H., Va. MED., P. &amp; S., AN., PHR. 2d. Gandy, Darius F. Society Hill, S. C. LAT., MAT., CH. 1st Gardner, William H. Dresden, Tenn. MAT., M. P., H. &amp; L. 1st Gardner, William F. Alexandria, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., M. P. 2d Garlington, B. C. Laurens C. H., S. C. H. &amp; L., LAW. 2d Garner, C. H. Mobile, Ala. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st Garnett, W. F. G. jr. Richmond City, Va. LAW. 1st. Garnett, James M. Hanover, Va. M. L., N. P., CH., M. P. 2d. Garnett, C. L. Essex, Va. LAT., N. P., M. P. 1st Garrett, W. Robertson Williamsburg, Va. LAW. 1st. Gatewood, Thos. Henry Middlesex, Va. LAW. 1st Gayle, John H. Norfolk County, Va. LAW. 2d. Gee, George E. Non-Intervention, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st Gibbens, C. Mortimer Winchester, Va. GR., MAT., CH., M. P. 3d. Gignilliat, William R. jr. Darien, Ga. LAT., H. &amp; L., LAW. 1st. Gilbert, Thomas B. Vidalia, La. H. &amp; L., LAW. 3d. Gildersleeve, B. Richmond City, Va. N. P., CH. 1st UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. Gilmer, George H. Charlottesville, Va. N. P., CH., M. P. 1st. Glover, P. J. Demopolis, Ala. M. P., H. &amp; L., LAW. 3d. Godfrey, J. C. Laurens C. H., S. C. M. L., M. P., LAW. 2d. Godwin, J. Robinson Fincastle, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Godwin, Thomas V. Charlottesville, Va. MAT., N. P. 1st. Goodman, J. C. Gates, N. C. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Goodwin, F. L. B. Wythe County, Va. LAT., M. L., N. P., H. &amp; L. 2d. Goolrick, Peter, jr. Fredericksburg, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Gordon, John Ashwood, La. N. P., CH., M. P. 2d. Grady, C. Powell Loudoun, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Graham, Jos. D. Draper's Valley, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Graham, James McD. Lexington, Va. LAT., M. L., H. &amp; L. 2d. Grattan, George G. Rockingham, Va. LAW, H. &amp; L. 2d. Graves, A. G. jr. McKinney, Texas M. L., N. P., CH. 1st. Gray, H. V. Pattonsburg, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Gregg, Walter Mars Bluff, S. C. N. P., CH., M. P., H. &amp; L. 1st. Gregory, John M. jr. Richmond City, Va. LAT., GR., CH., M. P. 2d. Greenway, Gilbert C. Abingdon, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Griffin, J. Cullen Southampton, Va. LAT., M. L., MAT. 1st. Grigg, E. H. Buckingham, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Grills, Lycurgus Augusta, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. Grinnan, Oswald F. Culpeper C. H., Va. M. L., MAT., M. P. 2d. Guion, Lewis Parish Lafourche, Ia. M. P., LAW. 1st. Gwathmey, E. G. Hanover, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 2d. Haden, J. W. Botetourt, Va. LAW. 2d. Hall, George J. Gainesville, Ga. LAT., GR., H. &amp; L. 1st. Hall, Franklin S. Fredericksburg, Va. MAT., CH., N. P. 2d. Hall, R. H. Heathsville, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Hall, Lucien Lancaster, Va. LAT., GR., M. P. 1st. Hamner, William Palmer University of Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Hamner, Nimrod B. University of Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Hancock, Philip S. Chesterfield, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Harris, Jerry M. Louisa, Va. GR., M. L., N. P. 2d. Harris, Herbert H. Louisa, Va. M. L., MAT., N. P., M. P. 2d. Harrison, Edward T. University of Va. M. L., MAT., N. P. 5th. Harrison, P. G. University of Va. GR., M. L., MAT. 3d. Harrison, Edmund Amelia, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT., M. P. 3d. Hart, J. E. Canton, Miss. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Haskell, William T. Abbeville, S. C. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 3d. Hawthorn, J. R. Pine Apple, Ala. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Haxall, Philip Richmond City, Va. LAT., M. L., M. P. 1st. Heath, Horace M. Northampton, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT. 3d. Heiskell, Isaac P. Hardy, Va. LAT., GR., N. P., M. P. 1st. Henry, Patrick Fredericksburg, Va. LAT., GR., M. L. 1st. Henson, Hudson L. Fluvanna, Va. LAT., MAT., CH. 1st. Hereford, John B. West Baton Rouge, La MAT., N. P., CH. 2d. Herndon, John A. Pittsylvania, Va. LAW. 2d. CATALOGUE. Herring, William A. Faison's Depot, N. C. LAT., MAT., N. P. 1st. Herring, John A. Rockingham, Va. M. L., N. P. 2d Hiden, James C. Orange C. H., Va. LAT., GR., M. L., M. P. 1st. Hill, W. R. jr. Richmond, Va. LAT., GR., M. L. 1st. Hill, Robert G. King William, Va. LAT., M. L., MAT. 1st Hinton, John R. Rocheport, Mo. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT. 1st. Hinton, Drury A. Petersburg, Va. LAT., M. L., A. &amp; L. 1st Hitner, John K. Carlisle, Pa. LAT., MAT., M. P. 1st. Hodges, John J. Kossier, La. LAW. 1st. Hogg, Alexander Yorktown, Va. LAT., MAT., M. P. 2d. Holland, T. M. Franklin, Va. LAT., GR., M. P., MAT. 1st. Holladay, Waller Charlottesville, Va. MAT., GR., M. L., MAT., N. P. 2d. Holladay, Alexander Q. Richmond City, Va. M. L., M. P., LAW. 2d. Holliday, S. T. Winchester, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st Holliday, Titus T. West Point, Miss. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Holt, Bolling H. Columbus, Ga. LAT., MAT. 1st Hopkins, James Richland District, S. C. M. L., MAT., H. &amp; L. 2d. Hopkins, D. C. Richland District, S. C. N. P., CH., P. &amp; S. 2d Hopkins, English Richland District, S. C. LAT., M. L., MAT. 1st. Hopkins, William Leigh Mobile, Ala. LAT., M. L., MAT. 1st Hughes, J. F. Fluvanna, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st Hull, John Baltimore, Md. LAT., M. L., M. P. 2d Hume, Thomas, jr. Portsmouth, Va. GR., M. L., N. P. 3d. Hunter, Beverly B. Harrison, Texas CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT. 1st Hunter, R. M. T. jr. Essex, Va. M. L., N. P., CH., M. P. 2d. Hunter, John, jr. Louisa C. H., Va. LAT., GR., M. L., M. P. 2d. Hunter, Charles J. Danville, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st Hutchinson, R. R. St. Louis, Mo. LAW. 4th Hutton, William B. Gainesville, Ala. LAT., GR., M. L., H. &amp; L. 2d. Ingle, Edward H. Washington City, D. C. GR., MAT., M. L., M. P. 2d Ingle, Julian E. Washington City, D. C. LAT., GR., M. L. 2d Ingle, Osborne Washington City, D. C. CH., M. P., H. &amp; L. 3d. Jackson, G. A. Mecklenburg, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Jackson, B. H. Autauga County, Ala. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st James, John C. Goochland, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Jenkins, Melzar A. Southampton, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Jennings, William K. Rockingham, Va. LAT., GR., M. &amp; L., MAT. 1st Jennings, George B. Rockingham, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Jernigan, John H. Harrellsville, N. C. M. P., LAW. 1st. Johnson, John Charleston, S. C. M. L., N. P., P. &amp; S. 2d. Johnson, John Lipscomb. Orange Springs, Va. GR., MAT., N. P. 4th Jones, John K. Nottoway C. H., Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. Jones, James Leigh King William, Va. GR. 5th Jones, John Thomas Carrollton, Ala. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. Jones, W. C. Fluvanna, Va. M. P., H. &amp; L. 2d Jones, Philip B. jr. Culpeper, Va. H. &amp; L., LAW. 2d UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. Jones, John William Louisa C. H., Va. LAT., GR., CH., M. P. 4th. Jones, John Sheldon Yorktown, Va. LAT., GR., M. P. 1st. Judkins, J. H. jr. Cubahatchee, Ala. LAT., M. L., H. &amp; L. 1st. Kable, William H. Albemarle, Va. LAT., M. L., MAT. 1st. Kemp, W. Perrin Gloucester C. H., Va. LAT., M. L., N. P., H. &amp; L. 2d. Kemp, W B. Amité City, La. LAW. 1st. Kemper, Theophilus Cincinnati, Ohio LAT., GR., N. P., M. P., MAT. 1st. Kennedy, Nathan B. Sumterville, Ala. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 2d. Key, Joseph H. Leonardtown, Md. M. L., N. P., M. P. 2d. Kincheloe, W. James Fauquier, Va. LAW. 2d. King, Frank Montevallo, Ala. M. L., CH., M. P., H. &amp; L. 1st. King, J. Floyd St. Simon's Island, Ga. MAT., N. P.. H. &amp; L. 2d. Kuykendall, A. C. Romney, Va. LAT., GR., N. P., M. P. 1st. Lacy, B. W. New Kent, Va. LAT., M. L., MAT., M. P. 1st. Lackey, Samuel Lincoln county, Ky. LAT., MAT., M. P. 1st. Lackland, E. M. Charlestown, Va. M. L., MAT., N. P. 1st. Land, A. D. Shreveport, La. LAT., CH., H &amp; L. 2d. Lane, Thomas B. Matthews C. H., Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT. 1st. Larisey, J. Earle Walterboro', S. C. LAW. 2d. Latané, John Essex, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 2d. Lea, N. W. Holly Springs, Miss. LAT., M. L., CH. 3d. Leary, J. H. Colerain, N. C. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Lee, Hugh Holmes Clarksburg, Va. M. P., LAW. 3d. Lee, Charles D. Henry C. H., Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 2d. Leitch, Samuel G. Charlottesville, Va. LAT., GR., MAT., CH. 2d. Leslie, Samuel D., jr. Hillsboro', Va. MAT., N. P., M. P., H. &amp; L. 1st. Lewis, R. W., jr. Albemarle, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. Lewis, C. C. Berryville, Va. MAT., N. P., M. P. 1st. Lewis, Daniel W. Harrellsville, N. C. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Lewis, John S. Woodville, Miss. M. P., LAW. 3d. Lide, L. W. Darlington C. H., S. C. LAT., M. L., N. P. 2d. Lightner, S. M. Pocahontas, Va. LAT., GR., H. &amp; L. 1st. Lightner, J. M Huntersville, Va. LAW. 1st. Lindsay, C. A. C. Christian county, Ky. LAT., GR., MAT. 2d. Lipscomb, Wm. Henry Fredericksburg, Va. LAT., GR., CH. 3d. Lipscomb, Wm. Howell Gainesville, Ala. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Louthan, Wm. P. Berryville, Va. GR., MAT., N. P. 4th. Louthan, Carter M. Berryville, Va. N. P., H. &amp; L., LAW. 2d. Love, Wm. S. Natchez, Miss. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Love, Robert T. Fairfax C. H., Va. LAT., GR., M. L. 2d. Luckett, L. W. Loudoun, Va. LAT., GR., M. L. 1st. Luckett, C. D. Loudoun, Va. LAT., GR., M. L. 1st. Lyons, T. Barton Clinton, La. M. P., H. &amp; L. 1st. Mackoy, William H. Covington, Ky. LAT., MAT., N. P. 2d. Magruder, P. Wilson Woodstock, Va. N. P., CH., M. P. 2d. CATALOGUE. Magruder, J. W. Orange, Va. LAT., M. L., MAT. 2d. Magruder, John B. Albemarle, Va. GR., MAT., N. P. 3d. Marks, E. R. Prince George, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Marks, Spencer C. Montgomery, Ala. LAT., M. L., MAT. 2d. Marshall, James M. Fauquier, Va. LAT., M. L., MAT. 2d. Marshall, G. W. Abbeville, S. C. N. P., M. P., H. &amp; L. 1st. Martin, Edward L. Seaford, Del. LAW. 4th. Mason, Julian J. King George, Va. LAT., M. L., MAT. 1st. Mason, T. W. Brunswick, Va. M. P., LAW. 1st. Mason, J. M., jr. Winchester, Va. LAT., M. L., M. P. 1st. Massie, John L. Augusta, Va. LAW. 2d. Mathews, Alexander F. Lewisburg, Va. LAW. 4th. Mathews, Charles L. Cahaba, Ala. LAT., M. P., H. &amp; L. 3d. Mathews, J. E. Cahaba, Ala. LAT., M. L., MAT. 1st. Maury, Rich'd Launcelot Washington City, D. C. MAT., N. P., CH., M. P. 2d. May, Richard H. Lunenburg C. H., Va. M. P., H. &amp; L., LAW. 1st. McCall, William Thomas Marion District, S. C. LAT., CH., H. &amp; L. 3d. McCarty, D. W. Page Richmond City, Va. M. L., M. P., LAW. 2d. McCoy, Charles D. University of Va. LAT., GR., M. P., MAT. 4th. McDonald, D. A. Camden, Ala. N. P., M. P., H. &amp; L. 2d. McDonald, C. W. Winchester, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT., M. P. 2d. McDougald, W. A. Columbus, Ga. LAT., M. L., MAT. 1st. McGehee, Nathaniel M. Louisa, Va. LAT., M. L., M. P. 1st. McGehee, William F. Woodville, Miss. LAT., GR., MAT. 2d. McIlwaine, J. F. Petersburg, Va. M. P., LAW. 1st. McKay, J. Clay Warren, Va. LAW. 1st. McKeithen, A. S. Autauga County, Ala. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT. 1st. McLaurin, H. J. Statesburg, S. C. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT. 1st. Meade, Hugh E. Petersburg, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. Meade, William H. Charlottesville, Va. LAT., MAT., N. P., H. &amp; L. 2d. Meconkey, E. F. Westchester, Pa. LAT., GR., N. P., H. &amp; L. 1st. Meem, J. Lawrence Lynchburg, Va. M. L., M. P., H. &amp; L. 1st. Meredith, Wm. Bernard Richmond City, Va. M. P., LAW. 3d. Merritt, William T. Brunswick, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Meux, Thomas R. Haywood Co., Tenn. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT. 1st. Micou, A. R. Essex, Va. LAT., MAT., M. P. 2d. Miles, Adam C. Roachville, Md. LAT., MAT., M. P. 1st. Miller, Samuel Wildes Spartansburg, S. C. LAT., M. L., H. &amp; L. 1st. Miller, George Knox Memphis, Tenn. LAT., H. &amp; L. 1st. Miller, A. P. Lancaster, Ohio LAW, H. &amp; L. 2d. Minor, William W., jr. Albemarle, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 2d. Minor, Charles, jr. Albemarle, Va. LAT., GR, M. L., MAT. 2d. Moody, J. M., jr. Garysburg, N. C. LAW. 2d. Moore, James W. St. John's, N. C. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Moore, William Berryville, Va. GR., M. L., MAT., CH. 2d. Moore, James P. Greensboro', Ala. M. L., N. P., CH. 1st. Moore, Thomas J. Charlotte, N. C. M. L., MAT., H. &amp; L. 1st. Moncure, E. C. Hinds County, Miss. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. 3UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. Moncure, W. R. D. Fredericksburg, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 2d. Mordecai, J. B. Richmond City, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. Morgan, S. E. Richmond City, Va. LAW. 1st. Morris, William W. Henry, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Morris, John Goochland C. H., Va. LAT., GR., MAT., N. P. 1st. Morton, C. B. Culpeper, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Mosby, Leslie Lynchburg, Va. LAT., M. L., CH. 1st. Moseley, E. J. Powhatan, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT. 1st. Motley, B. H. Danville, Va. LAW. 1st. Murdoch, J. Campbell Baltimore, Md. M. L., MAT., N. P. 1st. Murray, John Southampton, Va. M. L., CH., M. P. 4th. Nardin, W. H. Anderson C. H., S. C. CH.,, MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Neblett, H. M. Lunenburg, Va. CH., H. &amp; L. 2d. Nelson, Kinloch Clarke, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. Nelson, G. W. Hanover, Va. LAT., GR., MAT., N. P. 1st. Newman, J. S. Orange, Va. N. P., CH., M. P., MAT. 3d. Nicholson, W. F. Shreveport, La. LAT., N. P., H. &amp; L. 2d. Nicolson, George D. Middlesex, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Niles, S. D. G. River Side, Tenn M. L., MAT., CH. 1st. Noel, H. R. Essex, Va. MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT., PHR. 3d. Nottingham, S. P. Eastville, Va. M. L., MAT., M. P. 2d. Oates, D. Dunlap Wacahoota, Florida CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Ogier, Wm. G. Charleston, S. C. LAT., M. L, CH., AN. 1st. Old, William W. Princess Anne, Va. LAT., GL., M. L., MAT. 1st. Opie, Thomas Staunton, Va. M. L., MAT., N. P. 1st. Orgain, George C. Lunenburg, Va. LAW. 2d. Orrick, Wm. P. Cumberland, Md. LAT., GR., M. L., N. P. 1st. Overbey, R. C. Mecklenburg, Va. MAT., N. P., CH. 2d. Page, Henry Somerset, Md. LAT., GR., MAT. 2d. Parker, Wilmer F. Snow Hill, Md. N. P., M. P. 3d. Parker, Carson Terebinthe, N. C. LAT., GR., N. P., H. &amp; L., M. P. 1st. Partlow, J. A. New Market, S. C. M. L., M. P., H. &amp; L. 1st. Patteson, Camm. Buckingham, Va. M. P., LAW. 1st. Payne, John M. Lynchburg, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Pearce, Robert S. Richmond City, Va. LAT., GR., MAT., CH. 2d. Peareson, Philip E. Matagorda, Texas LAT., GR., H. &amp; L. 1st. Pease, John B. Yazoo City, Miss. CH., H. &amp; L. 1st. Peck, Frederick Greensboro', Ala. LAT., M. L., MAT. 2d. Peeples, P. A. Carrollton, Miss. LAT., M. P., LAW. 2d. Pegues, Charles J. Dallas, Ala. LAT., GR., M. L. 2d. Peirce, Jos. C. Portsmouth, Va. LAT., M. L., MAT. 1st. Pelham, Charles T. Austin, Texas LAT., M. L., MAT. 1st. Pendleton, John R. Berryville, Va. LAT., M. L., MAT. 2d. Pendleton, Lewis S. Louisa C. H., Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Penn, F. R. Patrick, Va. LAT., M. P., H. &amp; L., CH. 1st. CATALOGUE. Perry, William G. Monroe, Va. M. L., MAT. 1st. Perry, William H., jr. Lunenburg, Va. LAW. 3d. Peterkin, George Wm. Richmond City, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Pickett, Charles Richmond City, Va. M. P., H. &amp; L. 2d. Polk, Lucius C. Baltimore, Md. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. Pollard, Joseph Montgomery, Ala. LAT., GR., M. L. 2d. Pollock, Thomas Gordon Fauquier, Va. LAW. 3d. Pollock, A. Anderson Scottsville, Va. LAW. 1st. Powell, James Henry Henderson, Ky. N. P., M. P., H. &amp; L. 3d. Pratt, George Julian University of Va. MAT., CH., H. &amp; L. 1st. Preston, Walter C. Lewisburg, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. Preston, John M, jr. Smythe, Va. LAT., M. L., MAT., CH. 2d. Price, Wm. M. Saline County, Mo. CH., M. P., H. &amp; L. 2d. Price, Thomas R., jr. Richmond City, Va. M. L., LAW. 3d. Prioleau, C. E. Charleston, S. C. N. P., CH. 2d. Pulliam, S. H. Richmond City, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. Purnell, G. W. Snow Hill, Md. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Quarles, J. W. Louisa, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Radford, William M. Montgomery, Va. GR., M. L., N. P., M. P. 2d. Ramsey, Henry K. Augusta, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Randle, E. T. Washington, Texas M. L., N. P., CH. 1st. Randolph, Thomas J., jr. Vicksburg, Miss. LAT., M. P., H. &amp; L. 2d. Randolph, M. L. Albemarle, Va. LAW. 5th. Randolph, F. C. Montgomery, Ala. LAT., GR., M. L. 2d. Randolph, A. S. Bayou Goula, La. LAT., M. L., MAT., CH. 1st. Rapley, W. F. Little Rock, Arkansas LAT., MAT., N. P. 1st. Ravenel, Edmund Charleston, S. C. M. L., N. P., CH. 2d. Read, N. M. Henry, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN 1st. Rector, William B. Campbell, Va. LAW. 1st. Redd, Samuel C. Hanover, Va. LAT., GR., M. P. 2d. Redmond, Charles P. Dubuque, Iowa LAW. 1st. Redwood, John M. Mobile, Ala. M. L., N. P., CH. 1st. Rhea, A. W. Jonesboro', Tenn. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT. 1st. Richardson, Robert H. Lynchburg, Va. LAT., GR., MAT., M. P. 2d. Richardson, O. P. Gravesburg, La. LAW. 1st. Riddick, James A. Lawrenceville, Va. LAT., M. L., M. P. 2d. Riddick, Edward T. Hertford, N. C. MAT., CH., M. P. 1st. Rives, Alexander, jr. Charlottesville, Va. MED., P. &amp; S., AN., PHR. 2d. Rives, Robert Charlottesville, Va. N. P., CH., M. P. 3d. Rives, Charles M. Charlottesville, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 2d. Roberts, Joseph K. Bladensburg, Md. M P., LAW, H. &amp; L. 1st. Robertson, Wm. B., jr. West Baton Rouge, La. LAT., MAT., N. P., M. P. 1st. Robertson, Thomas C. West Baton Rouge, La. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Robinson, J. Allen Botetourt, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT. 1st. Robinson, W. Leigh Washington City, D. C. LAT., N. P., M. P., H. &amp; L., LAW. 2d. Rodes, John William Albemarle, Va. LAT., M. P., CH. 2d. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. Rogers, J. T. Albemarle, Va. LAW. 1st. Rogers, Louis Magoon Accomac, Va. LAT., GR., M. L. 1st. Roper, S. B. Columbiana, Ala. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Routh, Job. Ashwood, La. LAW. 1st. Rowe, E. C. Fredericksburg, Va. LAW. 1st. Rowlett, A. E. Lunenburg, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. Royall, George K. Fauquier, Va. LAW. 2d. Russell, D. H. Equality, S. C. M. L., N. P., M. P. 1st. Rutledge, H. M. Charleston, S. C. N. P., CH., H. &amp; L. 1st. Saunders, John B. Paducah, Ky. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT. 1st. Scott, Thomas James Prince Edward, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Scott, Thomas James Montgomery, Ala. LAW. 2d. Scott, Philip H. Orange, Va. LAT., GR., M. L. 2d. Selph, C. McRae. Mobile, Ala. LAW. 4th. Semple, Richard B. Fredericksburg, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 2d. Semple, Robert B. Fredericksburg, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. Shackleford, Wm. C. Albemarle, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Shannonhouse, Wm. R. Hertford, N. C. CH., M. P., H. &amp; L. 1st. Sharp, Starkey, jr. Harrellsville, N. C. N. P., CH., M. P. 1st. Sharp, Thomas H. Harrellsville, N. C. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 2d. Sharp, William Harrellsville, N. C. N. P., LAW. 1st. Shaw, Horace T. Madison, Ga. LAT., GR., MAT., M. P. 1st. Sheffey, John P. Marion, Va. LAW. 1st. Shelton, Charles T. Louisa, Va. LAT., MAT., N. P. 2d. Shelton, Joseph L. Louisa, Va. LAT., MAT., M. P. 1st. Shepherd, R. B. H. St. James Parish, La. MAT., N. P., CH. 2d. Shepherd, Henry St. James Parish, La. LAT., M. L., MAT. 1st. Shewmake, V. P. Alexander, Ga. M. L., MAT., CH. 1st. Shields, William S. Memphis, Tenn. CH., BOT., M. P., H. &amp; L. 1st. Sims, T. Winter Clinton, Miss. LAW. 1st. Simmons, Thomas Edgar Brooklyn, New York LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Simpson, Edward W. Sparta, Ga. MAT., CH., M. P. 1st. Sinclair, John C. Charlottesville, Va. LAT., M. L., N. P. 2d. Skinker, Charles R. Richmond City, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT., N. P. 2d. Slaughter, A. E. Orange C. H., Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Sledge, Joshua A. Sumterville, Ala. LAW. 1st. Sloan, Samuel C. Palmyra, Mo. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Smith, William C. Pendleton, S. C. LAT., GR., N. P., M. P. 1st. Smith, Thomas W. Albemarle, Va. N. P., CH., M. P. 1st. Smith, Thomas King &amp; Queen, Va. LAT., M. L., GR. 2d. Smith, W. Breedlove New Orleans, La. LAT., M. L., MAT., M. P. 2d. Sneed, John C. Nelson, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., M. P. 3d. Solomon, J. H. Franklin, N. C. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Somerville, Walter, jr. Culpeper, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT. 1st. Sparrow, William E. Theo. Seminary, Va. GR., MAT., N. P., CH. 2d. Sparrow, Thomas W. Theo. Seminary, Va. LAT., M. L., MAT., N. P. 1st. Sparrow, Leonard K. Theo. Seminary, Va. GR., MAT., N., P. 2d. CATALOGUE. Stanton, J. C. Noxubee, Miss. M. L., N. P., H. &amp; L. 1st. Statham, William H. Carrollton, Miss. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. St. Clair, O. M. Selby, Mo. LAT., GR., M. L. 1st. Stephens, E. M. Newnan, Ga. M. P., H. &amp; L., MAT. 1st. Stephens, John A. Crawfordsville, Ga. LAW. 2d. Sterrett, Major Dowell Columbiana, Ala. M. L., MAT., H. &amp; L., M. P. 1st. Stevens, D. A. Charleston, S. C. M. P., CH., H. &amp; L. 2d. Stevens, Harry A. Harrisonburg, Va. LAW. 4th. Stone, Albert J. Iberville, La. N. P., CH., M. P. 2d. Stringfellow, Charles S. Hanover, Va. LAW. 2d. Stuart, G. W. Fairfax, Va. LAT., M. L., N. P, H. &amp; L. 2d. Sykes, Jos. H. M. Southampton, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Sykes, William H. H. Grenada, Miss. N. P., M. P., H. &amp; L. 1st. Taliaferro, J. Walker King William, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Taliaferro, F. W. Culpeper, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Taylor, E. P. Caroline, Va. N. P., CH., M. P. 1st. Taylor, Jefferson R. Albemarle, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Taylor, Bennett Albemarle, Va. LAW. 4th. Taylor, James B., jr. Richmond City, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. Tench, John W. Paris, Ga. M. L., H. &amp; L. 1st. Terrell, R. Morton Orange C. H., Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Thomas, R. S. Smithfield, Va. LAW. 3d. Thomas, J. Pinckney Augusta, Ga. N. P., M. P., H. &amp; L. 2d. Thompson, Willdridge P. Union Springs, Ala. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Thompson, B. M. Union Springs, Ala. LAW. 1st. Thurman, W. P. Bedford, Va. LAT., MAT., M. P. 2d. Thurmond, J. G. Salisbury, Tenn. GR., CH., M. P. 1st. Tice, D. W. Troy, Mo. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Timberlake, J. Henry Albemarle, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Todd, George T. Jefferson, Texas LAT., M. L., MAT., H. &amp; L. 1st. Todd, Thomas W. Nottoway, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. Towles, Wm. E. Bayou Sara, La. P. &amp; S., LAW. 5th. Towles, John T. Bayou Sara, La. GR., M. L., MAT., CH. 2d. Townes, S. Halcott Paris, Texas LAW. 1st. Trevilian, Charles B. Goochland, Va. MAT., N. P., CH. 1st. Trevilian, J. G. Goochland, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT. 1st. Trice, George W., jr. Louisa C. H., Va. CH., MED., AN. 2d. Tucker, B. St. George Williamsburg, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Turner, J. A. Greenesville, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. Turner, John P., jr. Kanawha, Va. LAT., M. L., M. P. 2d. Turner, Edmund P. New Kent, Va. GR., M. L., M. P. 4th. Turner, G. Kempton Lynchburg, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Vance, James Abingdon, Va. MAT., CH., N. P. 1st. Van De Graaff, Wm. J. Gainesville, Ala. LAW, MAT. 1st. Vaughan, George H. Osceola, Mo. LAT., N. P., M. P. 1st. Venable, Richard M. P. Edward C. H., Va. LAT., GR., MAT., N. P. 1st. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. Venable, McDowell R. P. Edward C. H., Va. H. &amp; L., LAW. 1st. Venable, Paul C. Farmville, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Waddell, James H. Waynesboro', Va. LAT., M. L., M. P. 1st. Walke, Richard, jr. Norfolk City, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 2d. Walker, Frank Scottsville, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Walker, A. Rhett Beaufort, S. C. GR., M. P., H. &amp; L. 3d. Waller, Samuel G. Henry, Va. LAW. 1st. Waller, J. H. Shelbyville, Ky. LAW, H. &amp; L. 1st. Waller, G. C. Shelbyville, Ky. LAT., GR. 1st. Warren, L. P. Edenton, N. C. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Washington, Robert J. Westmoreland, Va. LAT., M. L., MAT. 1st. Watkins, J. L. Atlanta, Ga. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Watkins, William M., jr. Halifax, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. Watts, Harrison Paducah, Ky. M. L., M. P., H. &amp; L. 2d. Watts, Thaddeus C. Montgomery, Ala. LAT., M. L., CH., H. &amp; L. 1st. Wayt, Newton Staunton, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Wellford, W. N., jr. Culpeper, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Wertenbaker, Thomas G. University of Va. GR., CH., M. P. 4th. West, John Thomas Norfolk County, Va. LAW. 1st. Wharton, J. A. Pearce Spotsylvania, Va. MAT., N. P., M. P. 2d. Wight, W. W. Goochland, Va. N. P., CH., BOT. 1st. Williams, W. C. Nanafalia, Ala. M. L., MAT., CH. 1st. Williams, W. K. Blue Sulph. Sp'gs, Va. LAT., MAT. 1st. Williams, J. Whitehead Greensboro', Ala. M. L., N. P., CH. 1st. Williams, R. L. F. Nansemond, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. Williams, L. E. Clark, Va. M. P., LAW. 1st. Williams, James W. University of Va. LAW. 2d. Wilson, Charles W. Norfolk City, Va. MAT., N. P., H. &amp; L. 1st. Wilson, William R. Amelia, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 2d. Wilson, Paca, jr. Brownsville, Tenn. LAT., MAT. 1st. Winston, Peter Chesterfield, Va. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN. 1st. Winston, James E. Lynchburg, Va. MAT., N. P., M. P. 2d. Winston, Joseph B. Lynchburg, Va. LAT., GR., MAT. 1st. Withers, William Greensboro', Ala. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 2d. Wood, John W. Hamburg, Ala. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT. 1st. Wood, Charles Charlottesville, Va. LAW. 5th. Wood, H. N. B. Albemarle, Va. MAT., N. P., CH. 5th. Wood, A. Jackson Albemarle, Va. LAW. 3d. Wooding, G. W. Danville, Va. LAW. 1st. Woodward, G. A. Talladega, Ala. LAT., N. P., M. P. 1st. Wrenn, Fenton E. Isle of Wight, Va. LAT., GR., MAT., N. P. 1st. Wright, D. Giraud Baltimore, Md. M. L., M. P., H. &amp; L. 2d. Wright, P. H. Goldsboro', N. C. CH., MED., P. &amp; S., AN., BOT. 1st. Yancey, Stephen D. Richmond City, Va. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. Young, S. C. Natchez, Miss. LAW. 1st. Young, W. R. Natchez, Miss. LAT., GR., M. L., MAT. 1st. Young, O. B. Spotsylvania, Va. LAT., MAT., N. P. 1st. CATALOGUE. RECAPITULATION. Schools. Students in Attendance. Latin, 263 Greek, 174 Modern Languages, 217 Mathematics, 247 Natural Philosophy, 131 Chemistry, 198 History and Literature, 101 Moral Philosophy, 170 Law, 109 Medicine, 99 Comparative Anatomy, Physiology and Surgery, 104 Anatomy, Materia Medica and Botany, 104 RESIDENCE OF STUDENTS: Virginia, 370 Alabama, 52 South Carolina, 35 Mississippi, 25 Louisiana, 25 North Carolina, 21 Georgia, 20 Maryland, 15 Kentucky, 14 Tennessee, 11 Texas, 9 District of Columbia, 7 Missouri, 7 Florida, 3 Pennsylvania, 3 New York, 2 Delaware, 1 Ohio, 2 Arkansas, 1 Iowa, 1 Peru, 2 Total, 625</field>
      <field name="fulltext">UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. A STATEMENT OF THE Course of Instruction, Expense, &amp;c., IN THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. MATRICULATION. To be admitted into the University, the student must be sixteen years of age; but the Faculty are authorized to dispense with this requisition in the case of application for admission by two brothers, one of whom is under the age of sixteen. If the applicant for admission has been a student at any other incorporated seminary, he cannot be received but on producing a certificate from such seminary, or other evidence satisfactory to the Faculty, testifying to his general good conduct. Every student is free to attend the schools of his choice, and no other than he chooses; with the condition that he shall attend at least three professors, unless he has the written authority of his parent or guardian, or the Faculty shall for good cause shown, allow him to attend less than three. Should he be twenty-one years of age, or more, he is exempt from this condition. COURSE OF INSTRUCTION. The session commences on the 1st of October, and continues without interruption until the 29th of June. The mode of instruction is by lectures and text-books, accompanied by daily and stated examinations. In each school there are three regular lectures a week, besides many others suited to the several subjects into which the school is divided. CATALOGUE. Literary and Scientific Schools: I.—LATIN. PROFESSOR HARRISON. The subjects of instruction are the Latin Language and the Roman History and Literature. It is endeavored to make the practical study of the language more thorough and more profitable, by connecting it with the scientific investigation of the doctrines of the grammar and of the etymology. The latter involves a regard to comparative etymology. To the Roman History and Literature, with the related subjects, so much attention is given as is found to be compatible with the duty, more urgent as yet, of meeting the actual wants of students in regard to the practical knowledge of the language, and to a just theory of it. They occupy, however, as heretofore they have done, one-third of the time allotted to the Senior Class. Text Books.—In the Junior Class: Zumpt's Latin Grammar, the Professor's Exposition, Arnold's Latin Prose Composition, Virgil, Horace, Terence, Cæsar's Commentarii, Cicero's Orations, and his Epistolæ ad Diversos, (Familiares,) Freund's Lexicon, abridged by Andrews, and Riddle's English Latin Lexicon. In the Senior Class: the same Grammar and Lexicons, the Professor's Exposition, Horace, Juvenal, Livy, Tacitus, and Cicero's Epistolæ ad Diversos, (Familiares.) Other authors, and parts of authors, are recommended to be read privately by the student, both for exercise in the language, and for the acquisition of the only knowledge of the literature that is comparatively of much profit; e. g. Cicero de Officiis, de Republica, &amp;c., Terence, Plautus, &amp;c. In the Roman History and Literature, Arnold's History of Rome, Niebuhr's Roman History, the History of Rome published by U. Kn. Soc., Long's Ancient Atlas, Smith's Dictionary of Greek and Roman Antiquities, (2d ed.,) and Browne's History of Roman Literature, are recommended. The students of both classes are required to furnish written exercises, chiefly translations from English into Latin. In the examination of candidates for degrees, the passages 4UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. given for the written translations are selected, not from the portions of authors which have been read and explained in the lecture-room, but from the classic writers at will. II.—GREEK. PROFESSOR GILDERSLEEVE. The subjects taught in this school, are: 1. The Greek language. 2. Greek literature. 3. History of Greece. The method of instruction comprises lectures, (systematic and exegetical,) examinations and written exercises. This school is divided into two classes—Junior and Senior. The classic authors read in the Senior Class, are principally: Thucydides, Sophocles, Euripides and Plato; in the Junior Class: Xenophon, Herodotus, Homer and Demosthenes. A private course of parallel and preparatory reading is also prescribed for each class. Works of reference.—For the lectures on the structure and syntax of the language, Kühner's Grammar. For the lectures on the History of Greece, (Senior Class,) Thirlwall's and Grote's History of Greece. The written exercises and the comments on the corrections constitute a prominent feature in the plan of instruction. 4. The Hebrew language. Text Books.—Biblia Hebraica, Rödiger's Gesenius' Hebrew Grammar, and Gesenius' Lexicon Manuale Hebraicum et Chaldaicum. III.—MODERN LANGUAGES. PROFESSOR SCHELE DE VERE. ASSISTANT INSTRUCTORS: A. VON FISCHERZ, G. BAILLARD, G. LANZA. The subjects taught in this school, are: 1. The French, Italian, Spanish and German Languages. 2. The Literature of these Languages, and the history of each idiom, embracing the general principles of the formation and growth of languages, and of Comparative Grammar and Philology. CATALOGUE. 3. The Anglo-Saxon Language, and, in connexion with it, the History and Laws of the English Language. It is a primary object of this school to teach the students not only to write, but to speak, and to converse easily in the living languages taught, and to this end the classes, in the hands of native teachers, are thoroughly drilled in sections. Two degrees in this school are required for the degree of A. M. IV.—MATHEMATICS. PROFESSOR BLEDSOE. ASSISTANT INSTRUCTORS: ROBERT T. MASSIE AND JAMES G. CLARK. In this school there are four classes: In the first, or Junior Class, the student commences with the study of Algebra; as he is supposed to have rendered himself familiar with the various rules of Arithmetic before he enters the University. After the first difficulties of Algebra are mastered, the subjects of Algebra and Geometry are alternately pursued, until they are completed. Trigonometry and Surveying are also taught to this class. In the second, or Intermediate Class, the subjects taught are: Nautical Astronomy, Navigation, Descriptive Geometry, with its application to Spherical Projections, Shades, Shadows, and Perspective, and Analytical Geometry. The Senior Class studies the Differential and Integral Calculus. To this class, a course of lectures is delivered on the History of Mathematics, and another course on the Philosophy of Mathematics. There is also a class of Mixed Mathematics, designed exclusively for such of the more advanced students as may desire to study the subjects taught therein. The course embraces the mathematical investigation of the general laws of equilibrium and motion, both of solids and fluids, with a variety of applications, especially to Physical Astronomy. The instruction in each class is conveyed partly by lectures, and partly by the systematic study of approved text-books, the student being assisted by full and frequent explanations from the Professor, and being constantly subjected to rigid examinations. The progress of the student in every class is also tested by his UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. being required to perform written exercises, in which the principles acquired are applied to the solution of particular problems. The text-books used are: For the Junior Class, Davies' Bourdon's Algebra, Legendre's Geometry and Trigonometry. For the Intermediate Class, Pierce's Trigonometry, Davies' Surveying, Descriptive Geometry and Analytical Geometry. For the Senior Class, Courtenay's Differential and Integral Calculus. For the Class of Mixed Mathematics, Pratt's Mechanical Philosophy. Any student entering the school has the privilege of attending all or any of the classes, as he may elect, and if prepared to enter an advanced class, may often find it highly advantageous to review his previous studies by attendance on a lower class also. V.—NATURAL PHILOSOPHY. PROFESSOR SMITH. This school embraces three classes. Instruction is given in each class by lectures and the study of text-books, accompanied by daily examinations. 1. The Junior Class meets three times each week. The object of the course of lectures to this class is to furnish the student with a comprehensive view of Modern Physics, and to make him familiar with its methods of investigation. With the design of laying a thoroughly scientific basis for the course, a large space is given, at the outset, to the discussion of the cardinal doctrines of motion and force. These doctrines are established, and their leading consequences traced without the use of technical or mathematical language. Their application to the equilibrium and motion of solids and fluids is fully presented. Under these heads a great variety of topics is introduced, embracing among others, the Centre of Gravity, Theory of Machinery, Friction, Pendulum and its uses, Figure of the Earth, Mean density of the Earth, Laws of Gravitation, Construction and uses of Barometer, Construction and action of Hydraulic, Pneumatic and Hydro-Pneumatic Engines, &amp;c. The subject of Molecular Physics, for which the student is now prepared, is next taken up and occupies the remainder of the session. The structure of matter, and the laws of molecular actions are explained in the light of experiment, and the atomic hypotheses of Newton, Boscovich, Mossotti and others are examined. The effects of the intermolecular forces are investigated, as they CATALOGUE. present themselves in capillary phenomena and in the osmose of liquids and gases. Their dynamical action in the phenomena of wave motion, both superficial and internal, is traced, Newton's rule for the wave velocity established, and the exceptions explained. The Lectures then proceed to the subject of sound, including its origin, mode of propagation, velocity in different media, reflection, refraction and interference, and the theory and sources of musical sounds. To this succeeds an extended discussion of Light, both common and polarized; embracing the propagation, reflection, single and double refraction, and interference of each kind of Light, and a full examination of the various theories of Light. The subject of Heat is then considered, commencing with Radiant Heat, its velocity, reflection, refraction, transmission and polarization: passing on to the physical effects of Heat, in Expansion, Liquefaction and Vaporization and including Thermometry and Calorimetry. In this connection, the theory and action of the Steam Engine are presented. Throughout this discussion, constant reference is had to the modern Mechanical theory of Heat. The course of lectures terminates with the subject of Electricity, Franklinian and Voltaic, connected with Magnetism, Dia Magnetism, Electro-Magnetism and Magneto-Electricity. Throughout the course, the applications of the science to Meteorology, Geology and Astronomy are noticed as they arise. This department possesses a large collection of drawings, and an ample cabinet of apparatus for the illustration of the lectures. Among the instruments lately procured, may be mentioned, Dubosc's collection of apparatus for exhibiting optical phenomena to a large assembly; Ruhmkorff's apparatus for Diamagnetic Experiments: Ritchie's Ruhmkorff's Coil, and a full set of Geissler's tubes for stratified electric light. Reference is made in this class to Rogers' Mechanical Philosophy and to Lardner's Hand-books. 2. The Senior Class meets twice a week. Here certain portions of the Junior course are more minutely discussed by the aid of the lower Mathematics. This class studies, in addition, the subject of Astronomy. Text Books in Astronomy.—Herschel, Norton, Loomis. MINERALOGY AND GEOLOGY. 3. These subjects are assigned to a separate class, which the members of the other classes in the school may attend at their UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. option. In this class, the lectures commence with General Mineralogy, which is treated with especial reference to Geology, to which it is designed to be an introduction. In the lectures on Geology, the specific identity of ancient and modern Geological causes is pointed out, the present action of these causes, whether atmospheric, aqueous or igneous considered, and their effects in the past history of our planet examined. The illustrations are drawn, as far as possible, from the Geological structure of our own country in general and Virginia in particular. The students have an opportunity of familiarizing themselves with the minerals, rocks and fossils exhibited in the lectures. Text Books.—Dana, Lyell, Jukes. VI.—CHEMISTRY. PROFESSOR MAUPIN. ASSISTANT INSTRUCTOR: DAVID K. TUTTLE. The course of lectures in this school commences with an exposition of the phenomena and laws of Heat, Light and Electricity, to the extent rendered necessary by their relations to Chemistry. The subject of Inorganic Chemistry is then taken up. The nomenclature, and chemical symbols and notation are explained, and the history of the non-metallic elements and their combinations with each other, very fully presented. Then follows a discussion of the general principles of Chemical Philosophy, including the Laws of Combination, the Atomic Theory and Theory of Volumes, and Simple and Current Affinity. The consideration of the Metals comes next in order. After preliminary notices of their general properties, the constitution and classification of Salts, &amp;c., they are taken up individually and very fully considered, together with their compounds with the non-metallic elements, and their saline combinations. The concluding part of the course is devoted to Organic Chemistry, embracing the consideration of organic Analysis; the Neutral Principles and their transformations by the action of ferments and other agencies; the Doctrine of Compound Radicals; the various series in which such radicals have been traced; the Vegetable Acids; the Alkaloids, &amp;c. The processes for detecting Poisons, and the means of counteracting their effects are presented in their proper connections: CATALOGUE. and throughout the course the applications of the facts and principles of the science to Medicine, Agriculture and the Arts, are duly noticed. Books recommended.—Fownes' Chemistry, as a text-book; Graham's Elements; Regnault's Elements, and Abel &amp; Bloxam's Hand-book of Chemistry for reference. DEPARTMENT OF PRACTICAL CHEMISTRY. In this department, under the charge of Dr. Tuttle, is given a systematic course of instruction in Qualitative and Quantitative Analysis; in the prosecution of which Mineral Assays, Metallurgy, Analysis of Mineral Waters, Soils, and Fertilizers, and Examination for Poisons, Pharmaceutical Preparations and the various determinations required in the practice of Medicine, receive a due share of attention. The Laboratory is kept open, and the Instructor gives his personal attention to the students therein, from 9 o'clock, A. M., to 5 o'clock, P. M., for five days in the week throughout the session. Text Books.—Will's Outlines of Chemical Analysis, Fresenius' Quantitative Analysis, Wöhler's Hand-book of Inorganic Analysis. VII.—MORAL PHILOSOPHY. PROFESSOR McGUFFEY. There are two classes in this school. The Senior Class studies Mental and Moral Philosophy, the first half of the session, Logic, Belles-Lettres and Criticisms, the second. Books requisite for the Senior Class: Mental Philosophy—Cousin, Reed and Hamilton. Moral Philosophy—Stewart, Jouffroy, Butler and Alexander. Logic—Whately and Mill. Belles-Lettres—Campbell, Kames. The Junior Class studies Political Economy. Books requisite for the Junior Class: Political Economy—Say and J. S. Mill. Four lectures each week are given to the Senior Class, and two to the Junior. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. VIII.—HISTORY AND GENERAL LITERATURE. PROFESSOR HOLMES. This School is divided into two distinct Classes, one of History, the other of Literature. To the former two lectures in the week are devoted; to the latter one; but exercises in literary composition are required from the members of the class. Either study may be pursued separately. A diploma will be granted for proficiency in both branches; a certificate of distinction for proficiency in one. HISTORY. In the Historical Class the successions, revolutions and various aspects of the principal nations of the world, are considered in such a manner as to afford a general view of the gradual and ever enlarging progress of political and social organizations, from the rude types of savage life to the complicated forms of modern freedom. Institutions and laws are discussed as the natural manifestations of the different phases of society; and an attempt is made to discover and elucidate the conditions of historical advancement, and to reduce the changes of nations and governments to the operation of regular principles. In the absence of appropriate text-books the following will be employed for study and reference: Schmitz's Manual of Ancient History; Smith's History of Greece; Schmitz's History of Rome; Gibbon abridged by Smith; Guizot's History of Civilization; Hume's History of England, abridged. For reference: Long's Ancient Atlas; Appleton's Atlas; Blair's Chronology, Bohn's edition. LITERATURE. In the Class of Literature attention is confined to the study of the English Language and its Literature. The origin, growth and philological peculiarities of the language will be considered; the various influences, domestic and external, by which it has been brought to its present condition will be explained; the lives of its most eminent authors will be studied in their historical order and connection; and the critical examination and appreciation CATALOGUE. of their principal productions will occupy the larger portion of the time. In addition to this, the Class will be required to practice literary composition. Text-books are more deficient in this branch of study, than even in History. The following will be used for the present: Spalding's History of English Literature; Shaw's Outlines of General Literature; Shakespeare; Aiken's British Poets. Medical Schools: IX.—MEDICINE. PROFESSOR HOWARD. In this school are taught the Principles and Practice of Medicine, Obstetrics and Medical Jurisprudence. To allow the medical student time to attain proficiency in Anatomy and Physiology, Chemistry and Materia Medica, before he is required to apply these branches in the study of the Principles and the Practice of Medicine, the course is opened with Medical Jurisprudence, which is followed by Obstetrics, and both are completed before the Principles or the Practice of Medicine are entered upon. MEDICAL JURISPRUDENCE. The lectures on this branch show the aid which legislation and the administration of the laws derive from medicine, and consist chiefly in the application of the Principles of Medical Science to the elucidation and administration of the laws, and the legal decisions in cases of insanity, every variety of mental impairment, crime, &amp;c., &amp;c. Text Books.—The Professor's Outlines, and Beck or Taylor. 5UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. OBSTETRICS. The lectures on this branch comprehend an account of all labors, natural, preternatural and instrumental; the professional assistance to be afforded in each, and the treatment of the female before, during and after delivery. The lectures are amply illustrated by specimens and plates; and all manual evolutions, and the application of instruments, are demonstrated on the improved phantom of Hebermehl. The students also practice manual and instrumental delivery on the manikin. Text Book.—The last edition of Meigs' Midwifery. THE PRINCIPLES OF MEDICINE. The Principles of Medicine, as taught in this school, comprise General Pathology, and a brief view of General Therapeutics; also Etiology, Nosology, Semeiology, Diagnosis and Prognosis. The nature and division of causes are first considered, which introduces the student to their effects—disease. Pathology proper is next considered under the two forms: Functional and Structural diseases. After the student thoroughly understands the nature of the causes of diseases, their divisions, modes of operation, and the resulting effects upon function and structure, a general view is given of the influences that can be brought to remove or counteract their effects. And the course on the Principles is then concluded by the consideration of Nosology, Semeiology, Diagnosis, Prognosis, and the Different Modes of Death. Text Books.—Wood's General Pathology and General Therapeutics, in the last edition of his Practice. PRACTICE OF MEDICINE, OR SPECIAL PATHOLOGY AND SPECIAL THERAPEUTICS. As the most natural and practically useful arrangement, all local diseases are classified and treated of according to their locality, or the organ or set of organs which they affect; whilst general diseases are arranged altogether pathologically. Much attention is given to Physical Diagnosis. Pathological Anatomy occupies a conspicuous place in the course, and is illustrated by Carswell's large and splendid colored plates, and, when practicable, by specimens. Text Book.—Wood's Practice of Medicine, last edition. CATALOGUE. X.—COMPARATIVE ANATOMY, PHYSIOLOGY AND SURGERY. PROFESSOR CABELL. The heading indicates the subjects taught in this school, and the order in which they are discussed. In the first part of the course, the Professor presents a general outline of the Animal Kingdom, by demonstrating such of the leading facts of Comparative Anatomy as may serve to indicate the natural affinities between the different members of the animal series, and to furnish a basis for a natural Zoological classification. In the second division of the course, which is mainly devoted to the study of Human Physiology, the peculiarities of structure of inferior animals are again noticed, with reference, especially, to the varieties of the same organ in different animals, in order to exhibit the simplest condition of structure essential to its office, and to indicate the uses of the superadded parts in the more complicated forms. The third portion of the course is exclusively devoted to the study of the Principles and Practice of Surgery. Text Books.—The Professor's "Syllabus of Lectures on Comparative Anatomy and Physiology;" Carpenter's Elements of Physiology; Kirke's and Paget's Human Physiology; Druitt's Modern Surgery; Paget's Surgical Pathology. XI.—CHEMISTRY. PROFESSOR MAUPIN. Medical students attend the course of Lectures on Chemistry, &amp;c., mentioned under "VI. Chemistry." A course of instruction in Pharmacy designed for the benefit of the students of Medicine, commences in March and continues until the close of the session. Text Book.—Parrish's Practical Pharmacy. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. XII.—ANATOMY, MATERIA MEDICA AND BOTANY. PROFESSOR DAVIS. ANATOMY. In this class are taught Special and Surgical Anatomy. The lectures are illustrated by fresh subjects, by wet and dry preparations, and by an extensive series of highly finished paintings. Text Book.—Wilson's Anatomy. MATERIA MEDICA. The course on this subject embraces: 1. General Therapeutics, or an account of the effects of the various classes of remedies on the organism, their modus operandi, and their applications to the relief of disease. 2. A detailed account of medicinal agents, in their commercial history, physical properties, chemical relations, pharmaceutical preparations, and effects on the system both in health and in disease. The means of illustration in Materia Medica consist of a superb cabinet of medicines, and a large collection of colored drawings of medical plants. Text Book.—Dunglison's Therapeutics and Materia Medica. BOTANY. The Natural History of the Vegetable Kingdom is taught in this class. It therefore treats of the Anatomy and Physiology of Plants—the principles of classification employed in arranging them according to the "Natural" and the "Artificial" methods, and the characteristics of the various groups. The applications of Botany to Materia Medica are constantly kept in view, and incidental reference is had to the relations which it sustains to Agriculture, Geology and Physical Geography. XIII.—DEPARTMENT OF PRACTICAL ANATOMY. Dr. B. W. ALLEN, DEMONSTRATOR. This department is abundantly provided with fresh subjects for the use of the members of the class; the afternoon is devoted to the dissections; and they are conducted under the constant guidance of the demonstrator. CATALOGUE. Law School. XIV.—COMMON AND STATUTE LAW. PROFESSOR MINOR. XV.—CIVIL, CONSTITUTIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL LAW, Etc. PROFESSOR HOLCOMBE. The object in this school is to acquaint the student familiarly and practically with the principles of his profession. With this view, instruction (which is designed to be as thorough as possible) is given partly through text-books and daily examinations upon the subjects taught, partly by comments intended to supply what is deficient and explain what is obscure in the text, and partly also by independent lectures. A Moot-Court is instituted in connection with the school, upon a plan which experience has shown to be well calculated to perfect the student in the details of practice. Under the immediate superintendence of the Professors, he is required to pronounce opinions upon supposed cases; to devise and to institute remedies, by suit or otherwise; to conduct suits at law and in chancery, from their inception, through all their stages; to draw wills, conveyances and other assurances; and, in short, to perform most of the functions of a practising lawyer. The school forms two Departments, each of which is divided into two classes, and the course of study therein is as follows: DEPARTMENT OF COMMON AND STATUTE LAW. PROFESSOR MINOR. Junior Class.—Blackstone's Commentaries, Chitty on Contracts. Senior Class.—Stephen on Pleading, Lomax's Digest of the Law of Real Property, Law of Executors, &amp;c. For Reference.—Virginia Code of 1849, Gordon's Digest of United States Statutes. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. DEPARTMENT OF EQUITY, MERCANTILE, INTERNATIONAL AND CONSTITUTIONAL LAW, AND GOVERNMENT, ETC. PROFESSOR HOLCOMBE. Junior Class.—Lectures on Government, Federalist, Duer's Outlines of the Constitution, Madison's Report 1799, Polson's Law of Nations, Select Chapters of Vattel's Law of Nations. Senior Class.—Smith's Mercantile Law, Greenleaf's Evidence, Barton's Suit in Equity, Adams's Equity. The degree of Bachelor of Laws is conferred upon those who, upon examination, manifest a familiar acquaintance with the subjects taught in all the classes; and to those who exhibit a competent knowledge of International and Constitutional Law and of the science of Government, a certificate of proficiency is awarded. ? All the books required can be procured at the book stores near the University on reasonable terms. LICENTIATES. Any person of unexceptionable character and habits, and of suitable capacity and attainments, may be licensed by the Faculty to form a class for private instruction, upon the subjects taught in any school of the University, in aid of and in conformity to the public teachings of the Professor. Licentiates are not authorized to receive pupils who are not members of the school or schools for which they are licensed, nor to give instruction upon subjects not embraced in the plan of the same. The employment of the licentiate is at the option of the student, and his compensation a matter of private arrangement. CATALOGUE. EXAMINATIONS. These are of three kinds: first, the daily examinations, which precede the lectures; second, the public examinations, two in number, held the one about the middle of the session, the other at its close; and third, the examination for graduation, held towards the end of the session. I.—DAILY EXAMINATIONS. In the daily examinations the student is questioned both upon the subject of the preceding lecture and such portions of the text-book as may have been designated by the Professor. His preparation thus tested is noted at the time of examination, and if the student shall exhibit material delinquency, the fact is communicated to his parent or guardian in the printed circular which is sent home at the close of every month. II.—PUBLIC EXAMINATIONS. The two public examinations, embracing respectively all the subjects treated of in the first half, and all those treated of in the second half of the session, are thus conducted: The Professor of the school prepares in writing a series of questions to be proposed to the class, and affixes to them numerical values, according to his estimate of their relative difficulty. On the assembling of the class for examination, these questions are for the first time presented to them; and they are required to answer in writing in a prescribed time, without communication with one another or with other persons, and without any reference to books. Their answers are subsequently carefully examined, and a value attached to each, not exceeding that of the corresponding question. In the schools of languages, subjects are also selected for oral examination, and the value of these exercises marked at the time. The students are then arranged into four divisions, according to the merit of their examination, as determined by the following UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. method: The numerical values attached to all the questions are added together, and also the values of the answers given by each student. If this last number amounts to three-fourths of the first, the student is ranked in the first division; if it be less than three-fourths, and as much as one-half, in the second; if less than one-half, and as much as a fourth, in the third; if less than a fourth, in the fourth division. The examinations are conducted and the results ascertained by a committee, consisting of the Professor of the school and two other Professors. The standing of the student at these examinations is communicated to his parent or guardian in the last circular of the session. Those who attain the first division receive, at the close of the session, a printed certificate of their distinction at one or both of the examinations, as the case may be, and their names are announced in the proceedings which terminate the course. These public examinations are sufficiently comprehensive and difficult to render it impossible for the student, without steady diligence, to secure a place in the first division. III.—EXAMINATIONS FOR GRADUATION. These are partly oral and partly in writing, and are conducted by the Professor of the school, in the presence of two other Professors, forming with him the committee of examination of the school. Here the student is subjected to searching interrogations upon the details and niceties, as well as the leading principles of the subject, and he is expected to be accurately versed in all the topics treated of in the lectures and the correlative texts. As a due acquaintance with our own language is made indispensable to the attainment of even the inferior honors of the University, all candidates for degrees are subjected to an examination, in order to test their qualifications in this respect. DEGREES. I.—THE ACADEMICAL DEGREES Are, first, that of Proficient in certain special departments of a school; second, that of Graduate in a school; third, that of CATALOGUE. Bachelor of Arts; and, fourth, that of Master of Arts of the University of Virginia. The degree of Proficient, conferred in a certificate of proficiency, applies only to those branches of some of the schools, which, by the regulations, the student is allowed to attend separately. These are Geology and Mineralogy, Medical Jurisprudence, Physiology, Botany, Political Economy, National Law, Constitutional Law and Government, and Anglo-Saxon. The degree of Graduate in a school embraces, in the schools of Ancient Languages, the Latin and Greek Languages; in the school of Modern Languages, any two of the languages taught therein, except Anglo-Saxon; in that of Mathematics, all the studies of the school, except the Mixed Mathematics; in that of Natural Philosophy the same, omitting Geology and Mineral gy: in that of Chemistry the same, omitting Pharmacy; in that of Moral Philosophy the same, omitting Political Economy. The degree of Graduate is also conferred in each of the Modern Languages separately, and in the Mixed Mathematics. None are admitted to these degrees who fail to give satisfactory evidence of their attainments at the public examinations and the examinations for graduation. II.—THE DEGREE OF BACHELOR OF ARTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. This degree is conferred upon such students as have become graduates in any two of the scientific schools, viz: Mathematics, Natural Philosophy or Chemistry; and in any two of the literary schools, viz: Ancient Languages (including Latin and Greek), Modern Languages or Moral Philosophy; and have also obtained distinctions at an intermediate and final examination of the Junior Classes of the two remaining Academic schools. The candidate for this degree must furthermore satisfy the Faculty of his general literary acquirements, by furnishing an appropriate essay, composed by himself, on some subject of literature or science, which essay he may be required to read on the Public Day. 6UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. III.—THE DEGREE OF MASTER OF ARTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. To merit this, the highest academical honor of the Institution, the student must have already become a graduate in the following schools: LATIN, GREEK, MODERN LANGUAGES, MATHEMATICS, NATURAL PHILOSOPHY, CHEMISTRY, MORAL PHILOSOPHY. He must, moreover, give proof of an accurate and comprehensive acquaintance with his entire course of studies, by an examination in the presence of the Faculty, on all the foregoing subjects, at the close of his academical career; and, lastly, he must prepare and submit to the Faculty an essay exhibiting a due degree of literary ability; and this he may be required to read on the Public Day. IV.—THE PROFESSIONAL DEGREES Are that of Doctor of Medicine, conferred on graduates in the Medical Department, and that of Bachelor of Laws, on graduates in the School of Law. To merit the degree of Doctor of Medicine, the student must prove by his examination that he has made satisfactory attainments in Anatomy, Surgery, Human and Comparative Physiology, Principles and Practice of Medicine, Obstetrics, Materia Medica, Chemistry, Pharmacy, and Medical Jurisprudence. To attain the degree of Bachelor of Laws, he must in the same manner give evidence of a due acquaintance with the Law of Nature and Nations, the Science of Government, Constitutional Law, Municipal Law, including the Common and Statute Law, the Principles of Equity and Commercial Law. Honorary degrees are forbidden by the laws of the University. CATALOGUE. THE PUBLIC DAY. On the closing day of the session, which, unless that day be Sunday, occurs on the 29th of June, the Visitors, Faculty, Officers and Students, and the Society of Alumni, assemble in the Public Hall, whither are also invited the friends of the students and the public generally. On this occasion, the results of the examinations are announced, the certificates and diplomas are awarded to the successful candidates, and addresses are delivered by the Bachelors and Masters of Arts. EXPENSES. The expenses for the session of nine months are as follows: 1. Fees.—If one Professor be attended, $50; if two, each $30; if more than two, each $25. Every student is required to attend three schools, unless, for special reasons, leave be given to attend but one or two. In the School of Law, the fee for the Senior class in either Department is $80, with the privilege of attending all the classes in both Departments. For the Junior class in either Department, the fee is $60, with the privilege of attending the Junior class in the other; but if the student attends only the class of Constitutional and International Law, and Government the fee is $25. Medical students are charged $105 for a full course, viz: $25 for each of four tickets, and a fee of $5 for dissecting material. For the class of Anglo-Saxon in the School of Modern Languages, of Geology and Mineralogy in the School of Natural Philosophy, of Physiology in the School of Comparative Anatomy, of Botany in the School of Anatomy and Botany, and of Medical Jurisprudence in the school of Medicine, the fee is $15 only. In the department of Practical Chemistry, the fee varies from $20 to $50, according to the number of days' instruction per week. The student in this department is also subject to charges for chemicals and apparatus, varying in amount, say from $10 to $30. 2. Fee for Matriculation, and use of the Library and Public Rooms, $20. The Infirmary Fee of $5 secures, in case of sickness, UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. gratuitous prescriptions at the Infirmary, and, if needed, nursing (by professional nurses), lodging, board and medical attendance by one of the Health Officers of the University, all free of charge. 3. Deposit to cover contingent charges and assessments $10. The residue of this deposit is credited to the student in the final settlement of his accounts. 4. Board, &amp;c.—At the hotels within the precints the charge for board is $130; for which sum, diet, bedding, room furniture, and attendance are furnished. Room Rent from $10 to 16. Washing may be had for $1 to $1.50 per month. Fuel and lights are furnished by the Patron at cost and five per cent. commission, and cost for each of two students, in the same dormitory, about $25 per session. The matriculation fee, Professors' fees, contingent deposit and one-third of the board are required to be paid in advance. The second instalment of board is required to be paid on the 1st of January, and the third and last on the 1st of April. A deposit of $20 is also required in advance to cover charges for fuel and lights. No abatement in the fees for matriculation, tuition and room rent is made on account of late entrance of the student; and no portion of the same is refunded, on account of withdrawal before the close of the session, unless the withdrawal be rendered necessary by ill-health, and occur before the 1st of February. KEEPING OF STUDENTS' FUNDS. Every student resident within the precincts is expected, on matriculating, to deposit with the Patron all the available funds which he shall have in his possession, or under his control, in any manner intended to defray his expenses while at the University, or on his return thence to his residence. In like manner he should deposit with the Patron all the funds received by him, during the session, for the purpose aforesaid. Students residing out of the precincts would do well to observe the same rule, as a security against accidental loss and improvident expenditure. The Patron will disburse the funds of students on general deposit, upon their order, for all legitimate purposes. CATALOGUE. PROHIBITION OF CREDIT. An act of the Legislature prohibits merchants and others, under severe penalties, from crediting students. The license to contract debts, which the chairman is authorized to grant, is confined (except where the parent or guardian otherwise, in writing, requests) to cases of urgent necessity; and these, it is hoped, parents and guardians will, as far as possible, prevent from arising, by the timely supply of the requisite funds. PRIVILEGED STUDENTS. Ministers of the Gospel and young men preparing for the ministry, bringing proper certificates from their congregations as to character and standing, may attend any of the schools of the University without payment of fees to the Professors. The Faculty, at their discretion, may allow any man of undoubted moral character, above the age of twenty-three years, to attend lectures in any of the schools of the University, and to reside out of the precincts, exempt from the rules and regulations prescribed for the government of students, except only that he shall pay the usual Professors' fees, and the usual compensation for the use of the public rooms, and shall observe all those laws of the Institution which enjoin respectful and orderly deportment. But the privilege so allowed may be withdrawn by the Faculty at any time, when, in their opinion, it has been used to the evil example of the students, or otherwise to the injury of the Institution. MONTHLY CIRCULAR. At the end of every month, a circular letter is addressed by the Chairman of the Faculty to the parent or guardian of each student, in which are stated his absences from lectures and examinations, and any other irregularity of which he may have been guilty, together with such further information as to the student's progress and conduct as it may he deemed proper to communicate. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. The object of such report being, on the one hand, to incite the student to steady diligence, by eliciting the commendation and encouragement of his friends; and, on the other, to restrain him from idleness and disorder, or to urge him to amendment by their admonition and advice; the usefulness of these circulars greatly depends upon the prompt and judicious attention they receive from those to whom they are addressed. Parents and guardians, therefore, cannot be too earnest in communicating such advice or encouragement as the monthly report may suggest. LIBRARY. The Library of the University, originally selected and arranged by Mr. Jefferson, has since been augmented by several valuable donations; among them the legacy of Mr. Madison, that of the late Christian Bohn, Esq., a generous and enlightened citizen of Richmond, and a donation presented by an unknown lady through the Rev. Dr. Alexander, of Princeton. Through such additions, and the annual increase by purchase, the Library now numbers nearly 30,000 volumes. Students are allowed the use of the books, under the usual restrictions, and the Librarian is present in the Library, for seven hours daily, to attend to their wants. SOCIETY OF ALUMNI. This association is composed of such former students of the University as, having finally left the Institution, have on nomination been elected members at the annual meetings. Its objects are the promotion of letters and general education, as well as the renewal from year to year of the pleasing associations of academic life. The Society holds its meetings at the close of the session. An orator or an essayist is annually appointed by the Society from among its members, and the oration or essay is delivered in the Public Hall on the day preceding the Public Day. CATALOGUE. LITERARY SOCIETIES. There are three Literary Societies formed by the students of the University, which meet weekly at their own public rooms for the purpose of cultivating debate and composition, and hold occasionally public exhibitions. They publish jointly a Monthly Magazine, under the title of "The Virginia University Magazine." RELIGIOUS EXERCISES. Divine service is performed in the chapel every Sunday morning and evening during the session, by the Chaplain of the University, who is appointed in turn from the principal religious denominations. Students also have the opportunity of attending, at their choice, daily morning service in the chapel, and, on Sundays, service at any of the churches in Charlottesville. STATE STUDENTS. To render education at the University available to meritorious young men of limited means, provision has been made for the admission of fifty students, (one from each senatorial district of the State,) without payment of Matriculation and Tuition fees, and rents. The advantage is meant to be restricted to those who are not themselves, and whose parents are not, in a situation to incur the expenses of their education. Their connection with the University is to continue two years, but for extraordinary proficiency the term may be prolonged. They stand, in all respects, except expense, on the same footing as other students, enjoying the same privileges, and subject to the same laws. By way of remuneration to the State for the assistance thus afforded, they are required to sign an engagement to teach in some public or private school or academy within the limits of Virginia, for two years after leaving the University. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. ? Persons interested will be pleased to observe the following particulars: 1. The applicant is requested to state his age, which must be over seventeen years, and to designate the several schools of the University he may wish to enter, observing that the enactments require him, if under the age of twenty-one years, to attend three, unless, for good cause, the Faculty permit him to attend a greater or less number. 2. In order to be admitted, the applicant must exhibit satisfactory testimonials—1st. Of irreproachable moral character. 2d. Of capacity, as well by partial cultivation as original vigor of mind, to profit by the instruction given at the University. 3d. If he desires to enter the school of Mathematics, or of Natural Philosophy, that he possesses a familiar acquaintance with all the branches of Numerical Arithmetic; and if he desires to enter the school of Latin or Greek, that he is qualified to commence the study of the higher Latin or Greek authors; and, 4th. That neither he nor his parents are in a situation to incur the expense of his education without aid. The following districts will be vacant at the close of the present session: DISTRICT. III. Norfolk county and Princess Anne. V. Sussex, Southampton and Greensville. VI. City of Petersburg and Prince George. VIII. Powhatan, Cumberland and Chesterfield. IX. Lunenburg, Nottoway and Prince Edward. XV. Campbell and Appomattox. XVI. City of Williamsburg, James City, Charles City, New Kent, York, Elizabeth City and Warwick. XVII. Hanover and Henrico. XXII. Caroline and Spotsylvania. XXIII. Stafford, King George and Prince William. XXVI. Fauquier and Rappahannock. XXVII. Madison, Culpeper, Orange and Greene. XXVIII. Albemarle. XXIX. Louisa, Goochland and Fluvanna. XXXII. Hampshire, Hardy and Morgan. CATALOGUE. XXXIII. Frederick, Clarke and Warren. XXXIV. Shenandoah and Page. XXXV. Rockingham and Pendleton. XXXVI. Augusta. XXXVII. Bath, Highland and Rockbridge. XXXVIII. Botetourt, Alleghany, Roanoke and Craig. XXXIX. Carroll, Floyd, Grayson, Montgomery and Pulaski. XL. Mercer, Monroe, Giles and Tazewell. XLI. Smythe, Wythe and Washington. XLII. Scott, Lee, Russell and Wise. XLIII. Logan, Boone, Kanawha, Putnam, Wyoming, Roane and Calhoun. XLV. Mason, Jackson, Cabell, Wayne and Wirt. XLVI. Ritchie, Doddridge, Harrison, Pleasants, and Wo d. XLVIII. Upshur, Barbour, Lewis, Gilmer, Randolph and Tucker. L. Brooke, Hancock and Ohio. Appointments to fill the foregoing vacancies will be made by the Faculty on the 1st of July. Applications for the same, addressed to the Chairman of the Faculty, should reach the University by the 25th of June.</field>
   </doc>
</add>