<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Patton, John S., (John Shelton), 1857-1932</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Patton, John S., (John Shelton), 1857-1932</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">patton john s john shelton 1857 1932</field>
      <field name="author_text">Patton, John S., (John Shelton), 1857-1932</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1900's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2005_Q4_1/uvaBook/tei/b006115014.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240342</field>
      <field name="date_text">c1900</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:152710</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The University of Virginia ; glimpses of its past and present /cPrepared by John S. Patton and Sallie J. Doswell</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_text">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="title_display">The University of Virginia ; glimpses of its past and present /cPrepared by John S. Patton and Sallie J. Doswell</field>
      <field name="title_facet">university of virginia</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">university of virginia</field>
      <field name="title_text">The University of Virginia ; glimpses of its past and present /cPrepared by John S. Patton and Sallie J. Doswell</field>
      <field name="year_display">c1900</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1900</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1900</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:152710&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:152710&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Patton, John S., (John Shelton), 1857-1932&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;patton john s john shelton 1857 1932&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The University of Virginia ; glimpses of its past and present /cPrepared by John S. Patton and Sallie J. Doswell&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;university of virginia&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;c1900&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1900&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Patton, John S., (John Shelton)&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1857&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1932&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="contributor" form="persname" role="[Author]"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Doswell, Sallie J.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1857&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1943&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The University of Virginia&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;glimpses of its past and present /cPrepared by John S. Patton and Sallie J. Doswell.&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;[Lynchburg, Va.]&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;J.P. Bell Company, Printers&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;c1900&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="LC call number"&gt;LD5679 .P3 1900&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;X006115014&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;o07332119&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;96 p. : ills., ports. ; 20 cm.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Advertising matter: p. 84-96.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Includes index.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The University of Virginia&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;Glimpses of Its Past and Present&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2005&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2005 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 235 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">LIBRARY OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THOMAS JEFFERSON The Founder Copyright 1900 JOHN S. PATTON AND SALLIE J. DOSWELL</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INTRODUCTION. The eminence of its founder, the new direction the institution gave to the university in America, the charm of its setting in a fair Virginia landscape, the adaptation of the architecture of a time when beauty was the ideal to the uses of an age demanding utility—all these and more have engaged the pen, and will continue to make the University of Virginia a subject attractive to those who write and illustrate books. Many of the sketches I have hitherto seen from writers whose talents and information entitled them to consideration have been in the nature of tributes of respect and affection; but the present volume, while not lacking this feature, is primarily designed to afford information. It serves the visitor as a not too garrulous cicerone, speaking only when information is wanted, and the alumnus as a companion to be called at any moment when his mood is to go back to his college days, and to be dismissed without offense when the mood has passed. Those who have prepared this book have had unusual opportunities to achieve good results, and an examination of the text before it was sent to the publisher convinced me they have made good use of them. Paul B. Barringer.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE NORTH FRONT OF THE ROTUNDA</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA: GLIMPSES OF ITS PAST AND PRESENT. An interesting story is that of how the University of Virginia grew out of the idea of one man and became an accomplished fact after more than fifty years of effort, which was often The Occasion and the Men. interrupted by the public cares this leader of thought and action sustained almost unintermittingly through his long life. It brings into view the personality of a young man recently returned from French and Italian universities to engage in some work that would be of service to his people. The occasion was at hand, and the right men for the task were met; for Jefferson, who had the idea, and had thought out all of the details, taking advantage in doing so of his unusual opportunities on both sides of the Atlantic, was well fitted to be the director of this bold movement, while Joseph Carrington Cabell, broadly educated and highly endowed, was the man of his time the best suited to enter the arena, champion the Jefferson idea, and secure statutory tangibleness for the splendid scheme. Albemarle Academy would The Early Professors. call for a passing thought, though it never existed, and Central College would require a word, though its academe never resounded with student voices. The first professors would afford an interesting hour, especially those who had come over sea when ocean voyaging was attended with danger and discomfort—Blaettermann, from "33 Castle street, Holborn," to quote Mr. Jefferson, "a German who was acquainted with our countrymen Ticknor and Preston, and was highly recommended by them;" George Long, the Oxford graduate, "a small, delicate-looking blonde It is the simple truth to say, without Joseph Carrington Cabell's persistent labors in the legislature, his self-sacrifice and indomitable courage, his wonderful political tact and unfailing diplomacy, Jefferson's idea would never have been realized, at least in his lifetime. It was once publicly stated in the Virginia Senate, in 1828, that in promoting "that monument of wisdom," the University, Cabell was "second only to Jefferson." —Dr. Herbert B. Adams. man," charming enough to catch a Virginia widow; and three others— Thomas Hewitt Key, Charles Bonnycastle and Robley Dunglison—who came over in the same vessel, the "Competitor." This voyage, requiring nearly four months—six weeks of which were spent in beating about the Channel—almost reached tragic consequences. The captain (Godby) was little better than a brute, who, Mr. Key said, deserved to be shot for cowardice. During the tedious winter voyage Key and Bonnycastle seem to have amused themselves at the expense of the stupid sailor. One day when they asked the mate for the latitude and longitude, he replied, "Well, gentlemen, the captain has ordered me not to tell you—but he didn't tell me not to chalk them up," which he proceeded to do. Thereupon Key and Bonnycastle covered a paper with a multitude of calculations or figures of no significance, and wound up by giving as a result the figures received through the mate, which they signed as showing the ship's place on such a date "as calculated by Dr. Barlow's new method." They left the paper on the table, and some time afterwards they found an entry in the ship's log in which the figures were given, with a note by the captain, "as calculated by me, by Dr. Barlow's new method." Another of the first faculty, Dr. John P. Emmet, though educated in this country, was a native of Great Britain, and a nephew of the Irish orator. There was only one Virginian in the faculty of 1825, and he first saw the light under a foreign flag. This was George Tucker (born of Virginia parents in the Bermudas), who was called from a seat in Congress, where he was one of the Old Dominion's representatives, to fill the chair of Moral Science in the University of Virginia. Among the successors of these learned men were many whose lives furnish interesting data for the college historian. The present sketch does not deal with the whole subject, but with glimpses and impres- In 1854, when Mr. Key was a candidate for the Latin professorship, then just constituted at Oxford, he told the writer in his room at Lincoln College, in May or June, that the sea was so tremendous during the voyage to America that he had been washed out of the ship by one wave and into it again by the next. Feeling rather staggered at this, I ventured to cross-examine Mr. Key, but I could not shake him; he only added, "I struck out," which, however, might have been done within board. —John Power Hicks. sions of the University which will recall to the minds of her sons fragments of her story and theirs which may have been forgotten. To many of us who return to renew, at this place, associations long since broken, around these old arcades voices instinct with the gladness of life's springtime "continually do cry." At every corner, and in the shadow of every arch and pillar here, memories meet us out of the years when life was alight with faith and hope, and death was only a dream. For us these dim old halls are tenanted with the countless ghosts of boyish ambitions that faded in the light of the world beyond. Here hope has sung for many a young poet his deathless song that never floated into speech—here for many an untried orator, with soul-compelling eloquence, have the senates of dreamland rung. —James Lindsay Gordon. A visitor to the University who comes impressed with its history will not be disappointed in the dignity of its architecture and the beauty of its surroundings. Its campus, which A Beautiful Place. bears the modest name of The Lawn, is of unsurpassed beauty, and the tourist will thread its Tuscan* * The covered way in front of the whole range of buildings is to be Tuscan, with columns of brick rough cast, their diameter sixteen inches, but in front of the pavilion to be arches, in order to support the columns of the portico above more solidly. —Jefferson. arcades and study its classic façades with an unexpected interest. On this Lawn three Presidents of the United States—Jefferson, Madison and Monroe—have conferred upon the issues of higher education in Virginia with the earnestness with which the great men of the earlier days of the century devoted themselves to the problems which faced them. Not the least interesting of the records of this institution is that thin, yellowed Record Book of the Board of Visitors in the days when Jefferson was Rector, and Madison and Monroe were fellow-members of that Board, the most of whose pages were written by the cramped fingers of the founder, then four score years of age. The last entry, penned in a good round hand in spite of the stiffened joints, and without any evidence of the tremulousness which the weight of years usually brings, was made by Mr. Jefferson three months before his death, which occurred July 4, 1826. You propose to me to write to half a dozen gentlemen on this subject. You do not know, my dear sir, how great is my physical inability to write. The joints of my right wrist and fingers, in consequence of an antient dislocation, are become so stiffened that I can write but at the pace of a snail. The copying our report, and my letter lately sent to the Governor, being seven pages only, employed me laboriously a whole week. The letter I am now writing you [three printed octavo pages] has taken me two days. I have been obliged, therefore, to withdraw from letter writing but in cases of the most indispensable urgency. A letter of a page or two costs me a day or two of labor, and of painful labor. —Jefferson to Cabell, 1822. * * * The University of Virginia is an ideal community. It has been described as a small republic, finding in itself all that is necessary in the way of government and the pursuit of hap- A College Republic. piness. It is democratic as far as its government goes, since the powers of control are distributed as far as possible. There is no president, but there is a chairman of the faculty who stands in somewhat the relation of other college presidents to the responsibilities of control and direction. He is not as nearly absolute as a college president. The faculty is his cabinet, and the faculty committees distribute the administration in a rather general way. Each member feels that he has a responsible share in all that is done, and the chairman gladly consults with this official body on all matters which involve a new policy. The The Professor In It. course once decided upon in a faculty meeting is carried into effect usually by the chairman, the chief executive officer, or is by him delegated to some special committee or some of his assistants. The system is entirely harmonious. There is probably no other institution in the country so dependent upon a broad and careful conduct of its business or wise decision as to its policies, but so eager are all of the professors and officers of the institution to further a policy which, in the first place, shall extend the influence and maintain the dignity of the University, and, in the second place, promote its success, that the thoughts of all, as well as their efforts, are employed unselfishly for the general good. Personal ambition has no place, and, if it should attempt to make one, the atmosphere would not be conducive to its growth. It is "team" work with the University authorities in the conduct of the schools, and class methods do not obtain. The professor feels the eternal pressure of personal responsibility to his colleagues and to the State, and there is no idling and no indifference. THE NEW DRIVEWAY (East of East Range). The noblest legacy they [the earlier professors] have left us is this—that the very genius of the place is work. No professor nor student of susceptible soul can establish himself here without feeling that there breathes through all the air this spirit of work—a noble rage for knowing and for teaching. —Dr. John A. Broadus. On the part of the students there is no curriculum, aided by time, to carry all alike forward to coveted degrees. Time is not an element in the winning of honors here. While there The Student In It. is an average period within which the average student may safely count upon winning his diplomas, the diploma comes at last as the reward of merit and earnest effort. So that, while this institution is not alone among places of learning in reckoning sound attainments as a pre-requisite for its honors, it maintains a just eminence in this matter, and the little republic cannot be attacked as having in any degree permitted its freedom to cheapen its glories. The students conduct various enterprises which prepare them for the greater fields to which they are destined. In literary matters, the students have forums for debate and literary disquisition. They publish an "Annual" which gives views of life among the students for the session near whose close it is issued. They publish also a monthly literary magazine, in which appear numerous articles in prose and verse, most of them original contributions, but with occasional translations from other literatures, and they maintain and disseminate a weekly in which the weighty matters of college politics, college society and college athletics receive more or less consideration. They have their secret societies, chiefly of the Greek-letter order, their school clubs, their german and dramatic clubs, and other organizations demanded by their social instincts and training. There are elections which, in a good-natured way, sometimes shake the college world as national political struggles stir the American people. The election of final president of one or the other of the literary societies is often attended with as much political skill and finesse as are devoted to the selection of a United States senator or the nomination of a president of the American republic. Then, there is a judiciary connected with the law department, and places on the bench are sought with whatever energy is permitted to those who must in such contests maintain a dignity compatible with the learned judges they aspire to be, the jurisdiction of whose courts, as far as the writer knows, is of unlimited imagination if of limited authority. To be the manager of the foot ball or base ball team, to hold in hand the destiny of the tennis courts, to be the man of chief influence in the athletic association, are honors coveted and well worth the wearing. The large place which the athletes of this institution have made for themselves in the amateur athletic world is well known to those who take interest in such matters, and need not be written of in this place. The atmosphere of this college world is ideal. Here a man's consequence is not determined by his wealth nor by his antecedents, but by his character, for which his antecedents have the The Student's Consequence In It. right to take some credit, and by his ability. There is absolute equality of opportunity, a thing necessary in an ideal republic, and the thing which was really demanded by the Declaration of Independence for the American republic. Class and caste exist inoffensively, not as the result of accident, but of the necessity growing out of differences in gifts and character which must be found in all large assemblages of men. So long, however, as equal opportunity is afforded no one can complain, and no one does complain. This atmosphere promotes robust manhood and rapid, healthful growth and love of integrity. The man who, while a student at the University, neglects his opportunities, so far as tuition is concerned, is still benefited beyond calculation by the views of life which are unfolded to him. There is here no method or manner which results in levity or frivolous idling with serious and important problems. The boy who enters this University is, in this respect, a man when he leaves it, and usually a man to be reckoned with. When University days are over and the student becomes an alumnus, it is found that he is well equipped, usually, for the difficulties of life. The men of this institution are the chief ones The Student's Consequence When He Leaves It. in their communities throughout the South, and their influence and position in the cities of their sections are conceded. In New York, and in other cities North, East and West, their talents and acquirements have brought them well to the front and made them useful. In Southern literature the University man has exercised a vast influence and won for himself fame, and for his Alma Mater, distinction. As a teacher, his charms and excellences are remembered by the alumni of scores of colleges and universities; as a lawyer, his voice has been potent with juries, and his learning and probity have added lustre to the judiciary; as a physician, he has ministered with surpassing skill in army and navy, and in general practice; as a clergyman, he has worn the cloth worthily in the highest, as in the humblest, fields; in politics, his name has been legion, and his influence for the better policies and doctrines of the republic; in war, "a paladin flaming in battle." To trace individually the men who, after leaving this University, have gained renown, would be an interesting but almost interminable task, although some have done this very worthily. Professor Trent has, in this way, produced some very pleasant pages. In concluding them he said: "It is highly interesting to watch the `rolling stones' of the University, many of whom, after trying three or more professions, finally wound up as `forty-niners' in California. One got into Garibaldi's service; one started from Virginia, was a member of the Texas Congress, then treasurer of Texas, then got a diplomatic appointment abroad, and finally settled down as a farmer in Maryland. One student from Peru became a professor of law in the University of Lima, was afterwards Secretary of Foreign Affairs, and then represented his government in China and Japan. But perhaps the entry which gave me most food for reflection was the following: Nathaniel Holt Clanton, of Augusta, Ga.; born 1847; student, Paris, France; pressed into service of Commune, and killed on barricades, 1872.' " I salute with reverence the splendid memories that gather about this illustrious University. The annals of your alma mater are rich with the records of service and bright with the inspiration of immortal names. . . . Out yonder your books are writ in the registry of a great alumni. Georgia has made her princely contribution to the roll. Alabama has lighted her torch of genius at this inspiring altar. South Carolina has sent her patriot sons for grand equipment here. Mississippi and Texas, and their sister States beyond the Potomac and the Ohio, joining their worthy youth to the steady stream from old Virginia, have moulded here the men who helped to make the republic great. —John Temple Graves. When Mr. Jefferson said that he "had sworn upon the altar of God eternal hostility to every form of tyranny over the mind of man," the sentence bore all the significance that it was Educational Freedom. possible to attribute to it. It was the vehicle of truth, and not framed merely for rhetorical effect. He believed in free government, and wrote its warrant in the Declaration of Independence. He believed in freedom of religious thought, and gave it lawful existence in the Virginia statute. He believed in free choice in the direction of educational achievement, and, in the University, gave the opportunity of election. Before the foundation had been laid in brick and mortar he had written to a young Bostonian, George Ticknor: "I am not fully informed of the practices at Harvard, but there is one from which we shall certainly vary, although it has been copied, I believe, by nearly every college and academy in the United States. That is, the holding the students all to one prescribed course of reading, and disallowing exclusive application to those branches only which are to qualify them for the particular vocations to which they are destined. We shall, on the contrary, allow them uncontrolled choice in the lectures they shall choose to attend, and require elementary qualification only, and sufficient age. Our institution will proceed on the principle of doing all the good it can, without consulting its own pride or ambition; of letting every one come and listen to whatever he thinks may improve the condition of his mind." For three-quarters of a century this system has been in vogue with results so satisfactory that it has commended itself to other important institutions of learning. The freedom which prevails in the selection of classes was extended at the very beginning to religious activity within the University. All sects were invited to come to the University and enjoy whatever advantages its courses afforded, the University to be free from any responsibility for the teaching of the seminaries, should they be established in nearness to the college, and, of course, the seminaries to have no connection whatever with the University. Religious investigation was not to be "precluded," but denominational views could not be taught, simply because the institution was a part of the State, and any propagandism whatever would be repugnant to the constitution. At this University the students are treated not only as men but as men of honor until, by their own conduct, they show themselves unworthy of this confidence. It rarely occurs that The Honor System. they prove unworthy. This confidence excites in them a reverence for things of good report, which has a vast influence upon their behavior as students and in their intercourse with men in after life. There is no espionage either within or without the class-room; perfect probity is conceded to every man, and his statement on any subject whatever is received without the attestation of an oath. In examinations they are free from surveillance, and when their papers are handed in they endorse above their signatures that they have neither received nor given assistance, and this pledge goes unquestioned. There are few instances on record where men have abused this confidence and tarnished their good name by dishonesty in the preparation of their examination papers, but the punishment was swift and effective. No meeting of the faculty was necessary in any of these cases; official action was forestalled by the voluntary action of the student body. The offence was not only one against the rules and regulations of the institution, but, in a large sense, a violence done the traditional honor of the student body, which it was their special privilege to avenge. In no case has the culprit been roughly handled. He was simply made aware of the existence of a strong public sentiment which makes it impossible for a man to stain his honor and remain a student of the University of Virginia. * * * Sunday, the 27th of October, 1895, will always be a memorable day in the University's annals. . . . About fifteen minutes past ten an alarm of fire was given by two young The Fire. men who, from the piazza of their boardinghouse, saw smoke issuing from the upper part of the northern end of the Annex. The fire was soon located at a point near the spring of the arch over the rostrum and, perhaps, between the ceiling of the Public Hall and the floor of the Instrument Room, in the northwest corner of the building. How it originated will, perhaps, never be known, as the most careful investigation and the most thorough examination of witnesses has failed to reveal its cause, though it has strengthened the probability that it was due to electric wires. Whenever or however it began, it had already got a good start, for the neighboring walls were hot, and from the Public Hall the flames could be seen eating their way down to the famous painting, "The School of Athens." The first impulse of those in the Public Hall was to cut or tear this picture from the wall, and, in fact, the bottom was torn loose. In great haste a ladder was brought, but it was too late. Not only was the smoke dense and stifling, but the arched ceiling over the rostrum was giving away. The picture could not be saved. Those who yearned for its rescue, forgetting even to snatch a bit of the burning canvas as a precious memento, looked longingly and with sorrow as the flames encroached upon the majestic figures. Baffled here, the eager-hearted rushed to other tasks. The fire was making rapid headway; the means of fighting it were inadequate. . . . The long flames lapped the Rotunda, just over the little room opening from the upper gallery. This room was filled with files of old papers, stacks of addresses and catalogues, unassorted engravings, and the Bohn collection of books. All of this inflammable material fed the fire, and the Rotunda roof was wrapped in flames. The ardor of students and friends knew no bounds. The Jefferson statue, which had been hoisted to its place by patient and slow processes, was lifted from its pedestal, drawn on a mattress through the room, safely eased down the curving stair and deposited upon the lawn. The sum total of the damage to it was a slight chipping of the edge of the drapery. The Minor bust, the pictures, the furniture and most of the books on the lower floor were saved. . . . The fire was spreading, and the buildings on the Lawn were threatened, for the "Old Chapel" on the one hand, and the "Students' Reading Room" on the other, connected the professors' houses to the burning Rotunda. All energies were now directed to saving the buildings on the Lawn. Bucket brigades were formed to aid in keeping the houses wet; the fire companies kept back the fire, and, under the leadership of Professor Echols, others tried to wreck the low buildings next to the Rotunda. A breeze blowing almost directly up the Lawn and full in the face of the Rotunda sprung up and turned the flames back. The danger of further destruction was over. Told merely in bare outline, the story may seem too long, but the whole chapter of unreckoned disaster had been crowded into a brief while. At a quarter past ten the faint indications of a small fire had been noticed. Mr. Jefferson's clock, the object of his care even upon his last bed, ticked on faithfully until its minute-hand climbed toward the hour-hand now pointing almost to twelve. The minute-hand reaches eleven, and then, at five minutes to twelve, the clock stops, the hands fall back and hang loosely down.* The story of the restoration is not attempted here in detail. The loss, what was restored, and what was added, will appear incidentally in what follows. * * * The new Quadrangle, or court, at the southern end of the Lawn, is three hundred feet wide and two hundred feet deep, and has been graded to a level about twenty feet below the The New Buildings. bottom step of the Rotunda portico. The Academic Building occupies its southern side, the Rouss Physical Laboratory the eastern, and the Mechanical Laboratory the western side. The Academic Building contains the public hall, seating nearly fifteen hundred; a general The Academic Building. assembly room, seating about three hundred; five large and six small lecture rooms, and the biological laboratory, fully equipped with instruments, apparatus and specimens for biological work. This building is entered by a handsome portico on the second floor, whence steps descend to the parquet and ascend to the gallery of the auditorium. This is arranged in amphitheatrical form, and seats about five hundred in each of the three sections—parquet, balcony and gallery. The grades have been so established that to an observer standing at the foot of the Rotunda steps the whole of the portico of this new building is visible, while the height of the structure is not so great as altogether to close the open vista, which has always constituted a charming feature of the outlook from the Lawn. In the lobby is a commemorative tablet in bronze, and a number of THE NEW QUADRANGLE Academic Building Physical Laboratory Mechanical Laboratory paintings in oil of scholars, statesmen and soldiers adorn the walls. The tablet reads: "E'en in our ashes live their wonted fires." This tablet commemorates the burning, on October 27th, 1895, of the Rotunda and Public Hall of the University of Virginia; and the restoration of the Rotunda, and the building of the Academical Hall, the Rouss Physical Laboratory, and the Mechanical Laboratory, during the years 1896, 1897, 1898, under the direction of W. C. N. Randolph, Rector; Armistead C. Gordon, Rector; William Gordon McCabe, Daniel Harmon, Legh R. Watts, Marshall McCormick, Thomas S. Martin, Rawley W. Martin, R. Tate Irvine, Joseph Bryan, Camm Patteson, William B. McIlwaine, of the Visitors; W. M. Thornton, W. H. Echols, of the Faculty; McKim, Mead &amp; White, Architects. 1898. Among the paintings is one of Thomas Jefferson as a young man, in regimental blue coat and buff vest, but the face is suggestive of Schiller rather than of the sage of Monticello. Portraits The portrait of Joseph C. Cabell should be mentioned in connection with the one last named. On the 15th of November, 1856, the faculty ordered the purchase at their expense of a painting of Mr. Cabell, "to give expression to their high regard" and "their grateful remembrance of his uniform courtesy and kindness towards them." "A thoughtful, kindly yet determined face has this Virginia scholar." Near the entrance to the Latin lecture room is a small portrait of William Wertenbaker, representing him as he appeared in the last years of his service in the Library. It was done by J. A. Elder, the distinguished artist, while he was on another work here. It was remarkable as being done at a sitting, as artists sometimes dash off a sketch; its fidelity is such as to conceal any defects of finish, if they exist. It is thought by many to be Elder's most successful work in our collection, in its striking and pleasing likeness to the original. The full length portrait of General Robert E. Lee would be conspicuous in any collection. The chieftain is in full uniform and looks every inch the knightly man he was. The artist, Elder, succeeded well with the head and face of the idol of the nation that "fell, pure of crime." J. E. B. Stuart is drawn life-size with his cavalry cloak thrown back from his left arm. His slouch hat, pressed down on his abundant hair, is ornamented with the cavalier plume. There is a twinkle in the blue eye of this dashing Confederate, and one has little difficulty in imagining him singing his favorite "If you want to have a good time Jine the cavalry." This canvas was presented to the University by W. A. Stuart, a brother of the cavalryman. THE ROUSS PHYSICAL LABORATORY—EAST SIDE OF QUADRANGLE Another soldierly man in the collection is Colonel Charles S. Venable, painted by Guillaume, many of whose works are to be found in this city and county. That with Colonel Venable the arts of peace followed the employment of arms appears from the collection of works on mathematics on which his left hand rests. The portrait of Dr. Gessner Harrison hangs at the left of the east door of the lobby. It was painted by his gifted granddaughter, Miss Lelia M. Smith, daughter of Professor F. H. Smith, and wife of Mr. Lucian Cocke, of Roanoke. The same artist painted the portrait of Professor S. O. Southall, "Old South," as he was called affectionately by his students. It was presented by the Law Class of 1882-3. Another professor's portrait is that of Dr. William B. Towles, painted by William G. Browne. Other portraits are of Col. Thomas Jefferson Randolph, A. H. H. Stuart, James H. Gilmore, and Governor William Smith. The walls of the interior of the Auditorium are graced with nine paintings, the subject of each having been in some way connected with this institution, and the full length portrait of Thomas Jefferson occupying the place of honor. This is the work of Andrews, of the Corcoran Art Gallery of Washington, and is a replica of the painting in the White House. It came to the University through Mr. William D. Cabell, of Washington. Dr. James L. Cabell was painted by Guerrant, a South Carolina artist. Students presented to the University the portrait of Professor John B. Minor, painted by Mrs. Cocke, who also executed the likeness of Professor N. K. Davis, which was presented by Dr. George B. Taylor, of Rome. This is not hung in public at present. The same artist painted the portrait of Professor W. B. Rogers, once professor, and always staunch friend of the University. It was the gift of Colonel Venable. The bust of Professor Rogers, in the Physical Laboratory, is the gift of his widow. The painting of Mr. Courtenay was executed after his death, from a daguerreotype, by Martin, a Richmond artist; that of Mr. Bonnycastle by Ford, a portrait painter of distinction in the thirties. The portrait of the late Leander J. McCormick was done by Elder, and was the gift of Mrs. McCormick. Elder also painted the large canvas of W. W. Corcoran, one of the most liberal of those who have given large sums to the University. The painting was executed at the White Sulphur Springs not a great while before Mr. Corcoran's death. The remaining picture in this collection within the Auditorium is a crayon of Edgar Allan Poe, the gift and work of Albert Bigelow Paine, of Kansas. The Lawn, once surrounded on three sides by University structures, is now entirely enclosed, the Academic Building and the Physical and the Mechanical Laboratories being the last The Lawn. of these erections. The Rotunda stands at the north end, and, with the offices of administration—the Chairman's Office and the Faculty Room, on the east side, and the Proctor's Office and the Board of Visitors' Room on the west— occupy the entire width. East Lawn, which consists of five pavilions, THE MECHANICAL LABORATORY—WEST SIDE OF QUADRANGLE or professors' residences, connected by students' dormitories, encloses the left side of the Lawn as it is viewed from the Rotunda, while West Lawn, made up of the same number of pavilions with connecting dormitories, encloses the right side. The width of the Lawn from arcade to arcade is two hundred feet, and its length from the Rotunda Portico to that of the Academic Building is one thousand feet. It is a gradual descent from the Rotunda steps to the Academic Building, the grade being distributed by five terraces. These pavilions and dormitories were ready for occupancy in 1823, having been erected in accordance with the architectural plans of Mr. Jefferson, derived chiefly from Palladio. The first pavilion on West Lawn, counting from the Rotunda end of the campus, the residence of Professor Tuttle, is an adaptation of the Doric of Diocletian's Baths; the pavilion next West Lawn. in order on the same side, now occupied by Colonel Carter, is the Corinthian of Palladio; Professor Smith's residence is Palladio's Ionic order with modillions; Professor Noah K. Davis lives in the fourth pavilion, which is Doric of Palladio. This building is the remains of old Central College, the nucleus about which Jefferson erected his more ambitious institution. For several years after the University was in operation this building was used as the Library, and was long referred to as the "Old Library." Its corner-stone was laid by Widow's Son Lodge, of Charlottesville, October 6, 1817, in the presence of Jefferson, Madison, Monroe, and many other distinguished people. This pavilion was probably not occupied as a professor's residence until after 1840. The "The Old Library" last pavilion on the west side is occupied by Professor Peters, and is Ionic of the Temple of Fortuna Virilis. Crossing the Lawn and ascending toward the Rotunda, the first pavilion—that so long occupied by Professor Minor, and now the home of Professor Lile—is Doric of the Theatre of East Lawn. Marcellus, while the Corinthian of the Baths of Diocletian was copied for the pavilion, now the home of Professor Echols. Following this is the old Holmes pavilion, now the residence of Professor Graves, in the Ionic of the Theatre of Marcellus; the Doric of Albano appears in the next pavilion, so long the home of Professor Schele De Vere, now occupied by Dr. Kent, while the Ionic of Fortuna Virilis is the order of the pavilion which stands at the head of East Lawn, completing the list, and now occupied by Professor J. A. Harrison. As planned, the Lawn was to be devoid of trees, so that nothing would interfere with the severely classic accessories, but at present two rows of handsome maples border each side. These are the successors of the double row of locust trees planted probably in the thirties. At first the space now occupied by the terrace wings of the south front of the Rotunda were open arcades designed as places for exercise in bad weather. The professors resident in the pavilions taught their classes in them and not, as at present and for many years, in lecture-rooms elsewhere. . . . . The English don (Professor Long) must have surprised the authorities by marrying a Virginia widow. Jefferson had imagined that his professors would remain single and live upstairs in the pavilions, leaving the ground floor for recitation-rooms; but professors' wives soon changed all that, and the classes were driven out doors. —Dr. Adams. In the basement of the pavilion in which Professor Noah K. Davis lives was the reading-room of the library. It was so dark that candles were sometimes necessary in the daytime. The library itself was in an upper room. Mr. Jefferson's last visit to the University was made to inspect and aid in classifying some books. This was in June, 1826, a month before his death. The Jefferson Literary Society at one time held its meetings in the basement room above referred to. East Range, a row of dormitories, with the Washington Society Hall at the north end, the old gymnasium, now used for students' rooms, at the south end, and the Alumni Hall The Ranges. in the centre, lies east of East Lawn. It faces east, while East Lawn faces west. The Wash. Hall and the other pavilions were originally hotels or "refectories." For a long time the central refectory was used as the residence of the Proctor, and the dormitory on the north side was his office and for a time, also, the postoffice. Before it became a residence, and probably while in use as a hotel, a Mons. Ferron had there a salle d'armes, and taught fencing and boxing (in the thirties). West Range, a series of many dormitories and, originally, three hotels, lies west of West Lawn. The central one of the old hotels is now, and has been for many years, the hall of the Jefferson Society. It seems that the Washington Society at one time held its meetings in this pavilion which, years afterwards, became the permanent home of the Jeff., while the Wash. has founded a temple at the north end of East Range. In this West Range pavilion Mons. Ferron's successor, Signor Penci, a Corsican, taught fencing. Penci went to Cuba to recuperate, and died there of consumption, about 1838. In West Range is the dormitory (No. 13) known as the Poe room. It is one of the traditions of the University, backed with some evidence, that the poet occupied this dormitory during a part of his stay here. His first room was on West Lawn, but a quarrel with his room-mate, Miles George, of Richmond, led to his moving to West Range. Between the Ranges and the Lawns lie the gardens and private WALK FROM THE ROTUNDA TO POSTOFFICE (Above Wash. Hall. Serpentine Wall) grounds attached to the pavilions on the Lawns. These are separated at intervals by narrow streets, enclosed between serpentine brick walls, which are a prominent and picturesque feature of the place. The two interior ranges [The Lawns] front upon a grassy lawn, shaded by trees, and about two hundred feet wide. They also consist of one-story dormitories for students, broken by the above mentioned alleys, communicating with the East and West Ranges respectively, and agreeably relieved by five houses in each range, the dwellings of as many professors, the fronts of which display considerable regard to architectural effect. In the front of the dormitories and of the professors' houses is a continuous colonnade of about twelve feet in width, taking the place of the arcade of the East and West Ranges, the arches being replaced by handsome columns which support a roof, nearly flat, over the paved walk below, the whole surmounted by an iron balustrade, and affording a communication in the upper story between the professors' houses on each side. —Dr. W. H. Ruffner. WEST LAWN ROTUNDA EAST LAWN Pavilion I. The Lawn. Pavilion II. Diocletian's Baths— Doric. Temple Fortuna Virilis—Ionic. Prof. Emmet. Prof. Johnson. Prof. Courtenay. Prof. Warner. Prof. Bledsoe. Prof. Cabell. Prof. Gildersleeve. Prof. Dabney, W. C. Prof. Page. Prof. Buckmaster. Prof. Tuttle. Prof. Harrison,J.A. Pavilion III. Pavilion IV. Palladio—Corinthian. Albano—Doric. Prof. Lomax. Prof. Blaettermann. Prof. Davis, J.A.G. Prof. Kraitsir. Prof. Magill. Prof. Schele DeVere Prof. Griffith. Prof. Kent. Prof. Howard. Prof. Peters. Prof. Harrison, J.F. Prof. Dabney, W.C. Prof. Garnett. Col. Carter, Proctor. Alley. Alley. Pavilion V. Pavilion VI. Palladio—Ionic, with Modillions. Theatre Marcellus— Ionic. Prof. Long. Prof. Key. Prof. Patterson. Prof. Harrison, G. Prof. Harrison, G. Prof. Rogers, W. B. Prof. Smith, F. H. Prof. Smith, F. H. Prof. Coleman. Prof. Holmes. Prof. Perkinson. Prof. Graves. Alley. Alley. Pavilion VII. Pavilion VIII. Palladio—Doric. Diocletian's Baths— Corinthian. Prof. Davis, J. S. Prof. Boeck. Prof. Bonnycastle. Prof. Davis, N. K. Prof. Rogers, R. E. Prof. Smith, J. L. Prof. Maupin. Prof. Davis, J. S. Prof. Venable. Prof. Echols. Alley. Alley. Pavilion IX. Pavilion X. Temple Fortuna Virilis—Ionic. Theatre Marcellus— Doric. Prof. Tucker, Geo. Prof. Dunglison. Prof. McGuffey. Prof. Davis, J.A.G. Prof. Peters. Prof. Tucker, H. St. G Prof. Minor, J. B. Prof. Lile. Although the central building of the University, the Rotunda was not the first erected. The ten pavilions and the dormitories on the Lawn, and the six hotels and the dormitories The Rotunda. comprising East and West Ranges, were ready for occupancy October, 1822. The erection of the Rotunda was begun in the spring of the following year, and by October its walls were ready to receive the roof. During the ensuing THE SOUTH OR LAWN FRONT OF THE ROTUNDA. year it was put under cover, but the portico was not finished until after the death of the Founder. At his last visit to the University, only a few weeks before his death, as I was informed by the late William Wertenbaker, he stood at the window in front of the Library Room, looking out upon the Lawn, until Mr. Wertenbaker brought him a chair from his own office, when he sat for twenty minutes or so, watching the lifting of the first marble capital to the top of its pillar, the one at the southwest corner. This concluded, he left the grounds and never returned. —Pro fessor Smith. The Rotunda was built to furnish, first of all, a place for religious worship. "The Apostle of Religious Freedom saw no inconsistency in applying public funds to the building of a chapel for unsectarian use." Another purpose, of course, was to afford room for the college library. Before the fire four rooms on what were then the first and second floors, were used as lecture rooms. The restoration has done away with two of these and the remaining ones are now used, one for the Schools of Moral Philosophy and Romance Languages, the other for the Library attached to the Law Department. By far the greater part of this building is devoted to the general Library and perhaps there is not anywhere a nobler library hall. Even before it was finished two or three notable events took place in this building. There, on Friday, November 5, 1824, the citizens of the county of Albemarle gave a dinner to Lafayette. Lafayette, after a parade, remarkable for that time, through the streets of the village of Charlottesville. In August of the following year the same distinguished man was banqueted by the professors and students of the first session of the institution. At three o'clock the General [Lafayette] was invited to a dinner prepared in the upper room of the rotunda, the whole size of the building. The tables were beautifully arranged in three concentric circles. Over the place assigned to the General was an arch of living laurel, beautifully entwined around two columns that supported the gallery. Mr. V. W. Southall presided, in the absence of Colonel Randolph—the General first on his right, then Mr. Jefferson and Mr. Madison. On his left, George W. Lafayette and his suite. —Charlottesville "Central Gazette," November 10, 1824. There, too, twenty-five years later, occurred the famous dinner of the Society of Alumni at the close of the session of 1859-60, which was followed by the famous oration in the Public Hall by the late Senator Voorhees of Indiana. Until the Fayerweather Gymnasium afforded a better dancing room, the Library was the scene of the Final Ball, which from time almost immemorial, has been the closing event of the Commencement season, when the students literally— Dance all night till the broad day light, And go home with the girls in the morning. And there, at the upper or northern end of the triangle, stands the Roman Pantheon, the temple of all the gods. Young people dance merrily under the stately dome at the end of the academic year. The young monks thus escape from their cells into the modern social world. How charmingly old Rome, mediæval Europe, and modern America blend together before the very eyes of young Virginia. —Dr. Adams. At first the Rotunda was divided into three stories, the first and second being given up to lecture rooms, the third, to the library. Entering from the portico, the visitor ascended one Changes in the Interior. flight of stairs to the library or dome room. As at present arranged, the library is entered directly from the portico. This addition of a story produces an effect far more impressive. Instead of two galleries as formerly there are now INTERIOR OF THE LIBRARY three. The light iron rail of the gallery has been replaced by an artificial parapet, the piers of which can serve as pedestals for a circle of life-size statues overlooking the space below. The dome ceiling is painted a sky blue, and decorated with twelve soaring eagles in white, their beaks and talons picked out in gold. The space between the circle of eagles and the central light is frescoed to represent floating clouds fading into the clear vision of the sky. The scheme of decorating was suggested by the use of the eagle in the hall ceiling of Monticello, and the model used for the design was a cast taken from that place. "It is well known that Mr. Jefferson took as the model of his chief building, with some modifications, the noblest edifice of ancient Rome, and one which fortunately remains in the most The Model. perfect preservation. It is that known in Catholic circles as the church Santa Maria Rotunda, but better known by its original name, Pantheon. Mr. Jefferson never saw it, for he was never in Italy. He was familar with it in the drawings of Palladio. . . . . Despite all this [the use of cheaper material], Mr. Jefferson's building was, in several respects, superior to the original. The latter was approached by five steps; Mr. Jefferson's by fourteen, giving an elevation to the handsome portico which contributes greatly to its imposing beauty. The Roman portico is one hundred and eight feet by forty-two, with sixteen columns thirty-nine feet high, and divided into three colonnades. Mr. Jefferson's portico is fifty feet by twenty-eight and a half, with ten columns twenty-eight and a half feet high, and its floor space is undivided, giving it a much lighter and more airy, as well as relatively loftier, aspect. Lastly, Mr. Jefferson raised the floor of the portico and thus increased the height of the cylindrical drum until it was equal to its diameter. The massive and ponderous original must have always from without have seemed somewhat dumpy."* * Professor Smith. * * * Mr. Jefferson's books did not from the nucleus of the library, as many suppose. The truth is, a large part of his collection was sold to Congress. The remainder he devised to the The Library. University, but his estate was involved, and his executor, the late Colonel Thomas Jefferson Randolph, disposed of his books to meet the claims of creditors. The real nucleus of the library were the books purchased according to "A Catalogue of Books forming the Body of a Library for the University," a manuscript prepared by Mr. Jefferson before the assembling of the faculty. These volumes probably cost the sum named in the Proctor's report of September 30th, 1826, as having been paid on account of library and apparatus, namely, $35,947.38. A large number of the books of the Library were destroyed in the fire. Such as were saved have been returned to the shelves. Valuable private libraries have been added by gift and Private Libraries Added. purchase. That of the late Governor Holliday, containing about five thousand handsomely bound books, constituting perhaps the handsomest private library in the State, occupies about one-half of the first gallery. In this same gallery is shelved the library of the late Professor George F. Holmes; and other recent additions include the collection purchased from Dr. Bruner and the books of the late Ballard Bruce, given by his daughter. Some other gifts of books: The Bohn library by Christian Bohn, a native of Germany, then (1840) residing in Richmond, Va.; largely German books and pamphlets. Library of President Madison, by will. There was some trouble and years of delay in securing this bequest, and the Faculty threatened suit. Many books were lost or otherwise disposed of, but about two thousand volumes were, in the end, placed in the Library. Mr. Madison also gave fifteen hundred dollars which was merged with a gift of thirty-five hundred by Mr. Douglas H. Gordon of Baltitimore (1883), and the income from this fund is devoted to the purchase of books. The library of the late Hon. Arthur W. Austin of Dedham, Mass., (1885), about five thousand volumes. The Low library (1868), purchased with the gift of money by Mr. A. A. Low of New York. The Gordon collection purchased with the gift of money by Mr. Thos. A. Gordon (1870). Mr. Gordon was a Scotchman living in New York. The Corcoran gift (1876) of five thousand dollars to be invested for the library. Mrs. Margaret Paul, widow of Mr. D'Arcy Paul of Baltimore, has recently given a thousand dollars to the Library, and the estate of the late Alfred Byrd, ten thousand dollars. The old library contained a number of portraits of scholars, philanthropists and soldiers. These have been removed to the Academical Building, only two or three paintings remain- Portraits in the Library. ing in the library, and these of recent execution. One, a miniature, represents Dr. Dunglison, another the poet, John R. Thompson, an alumnus, and still another, the late Alfred H. Byrd, of New York, also a son of the University, ten thousand dollars of whose estate has been given to the University to aid in the collection and preservation of works on Virginia history and literature. [It would be interesting to know more of Thompson's University life than can now be learned. He spent three sessions here, and during one of these, boarded at Miss Terrell's, in the Chancellor House, opposite the Brooks Museum. At that time the building was probably not more than half as large as now, for the late Dr. J. Edgar Chancellor added to it materially. Some of General Sheridan's officers made this house their headquarters on the visit of the Federals to Charlottesville.] In 1854 the General Assembly of Virginia appropriated ten thousand dollars, to secure a statue of Thomas Jefferson, and later on made an additional appropriation of five hundred Galt's Statue of Jefferson. dollars. Alexander Galt,* * Alexander Galt was born in Norfolk, January 26, 1827, the son of Dr. Alexander Galt and Mary Sylvester (Jeffery) Galt. His father died in the yellow fever epidemic of 1855. The sculptor studied art in Florence, Italty, from 1848, to 1853, and was in Italy again from 1856 to 1860, when he returned to Virginia and warmly espoused the Confederate cause. He was on Governor Letcher's staff, and contracted small-pox while on a visit to Stonewall Jackson's camp. He died on the 19th day of January, 1863, at Mrs. Crouch's, corner of Clay and Fourth streets, Richmond, Va. He was buried in Hollywood. The statue of Jefferson is only one of a large number of figures from his chisel. of Norfolk, Va., was engaged to produce a life-size figure in marble. The statue and pedestal reached the University at the beginning of the civil war, and were not unveiled until June, 1868, the address on that occasion being delivered by the Hon. Hugh Blair Grigsby. This piece of statuary was in the library when the great fire of 1895 took place, but the figure was saved from destruction by the prompt and intelligent efforts of some students who removed it to the lawn, from which place it was conveyed to the Brooks Museum, and subsequently returned to the library. The orignal pedestal was destroyed, but another was provided. It is said of the statue that it is a wonderfully truthful likeness, and that when the figure was put in place in the Rotunda, there were still living many who had been well acquainted with Mr. Jefferson, who all said "This statue is Jefferson himself." It (the statue) represents the great statesman in a costume modelled after that which he was accustomed to wear, the needful flowing drapery being supplied by a cloak flung over his shoulders. —Dr. W. H. Ruffner. A life-size bust in marble of Professor John B. Minor, by Valentine, the Richmond sculptor, is in the Library, The Minor Bust. to which it was presented by the Law Alumni in commemoration of the completion of fifty years incumbency of the Chair of Law (1845-1895). The pedestal is inscribed: 1845 He taught the Law And the Reason thereof 1895 The unveiling took place in the Public Hall (of the old Annex, destroyed the following October), June 12, 1895. The presentation address was made by Mr. J. B. Green, chairman of the Bust Committee, the address of acceptance by Professor W. M. Thornton, and the address on the part of the Alumni by Senator John W. Daniel. This noble protrait of a great teacher, supreme in the class-room, wise in counsel, fearless in danger, generous and kind and gentle, alluring men to the love of science by the gracious radiance of his own serene nature, tells the world how the alumni of this University have learned to value, not learning only, but the spirit of untarnished truth, the chastity of stainless honor, the blessed effluence of a pure and lofty life. —Prof. William M. Thornton. In the tall chair, covered with red leather, found in the Library, Jefferson sat as Vice-President of the United States. Its high perpendicular back and general lack of amplitude Vice-President's Chair. could hardly have made it a comfortable seat, but its rigid dignity is probably in keeping with that of the presiding officer of the old school. It was bought at a sale of government effects about 1870 by General William C. Preston, and by him presented to the University. There are two handsome bookcases or cabinets in this room. The one, a revolving case with four faces of plate-glass, and filled with books selected and given by the donor of the Cabinets. cabinet, is a tribute of Mr. John L. Williams, of Richmond, Virginia, to his Alma Mater. The other, of handsome dark oak, carved, was presented by Dr. James A. Harrison to the Poe Alcove, and is filled with volumes devoted to the poet's life and to reprints of his writings. In the Library, a section of which is devoted to Poe literature, is the Zolnay bust of Edgar Allen Poe. It was presented to the University by the Poe Memorial Association, a society The Poe Bust. consisting of professors and students, formed in 1897. The bust was unveiled in the Auditorium on the 7th day of October, 1899, the fiftieth anniversary of the poet's death; the principal address being delivered by Hamilton W. Mabie, of New York. The sculptor was George Julian Zolnay, a Hungarian, whose reputation is well established by achievements that show his genius to be bold, individual, and able to command results of the highest order in his works of art, among which is the allegorical illustration of the scriptural text, the University's motto, "Ye shall know the truth, and the truth shall make you free," which adorns the pediment of the Academic Building, and also a life-size figure for the tomb of Miss Winnie Davis. This bust must be regarded as his best achievement, since the difficulties overcome are the greatest, for he has succeeded in shaping in bronze the features of a man whose story is one of the most pathetic in the annals of American letters, and affording a vision of the soul and mind of the poet who has given to our literature its most notable, significant, and enduring part, as far as poetry is concerned. . . . . I had the pleasure of inspecting, with my colleague, Professor Woodberry, Mr. Zolnay's admirable work as it approached completion. We tested it by comparison with all the known likenesses of its subject, and after the sculptor's additional touches it seemed to us a somewhat idealized, but noble and not untruthful, portrait of your great Southern poet, critic, and romancer. Permit me, then, to congratulate your association upon the outcome of your loyal efforts to place a lasting and artistic memorial in the University to which the author of "The Haunted Palace," "The Raven," and "Ligeia," unquestionably owed so much, and which, in turn, justly finds increase of eminence from the growth and perpetuation of his fame. —Edmund Clarence Stedman. * * * In the more than three-quarters of a century of the existence of this institution there have been but seven librarians. John Vaughn Kean was the first. He was Librarians. a student of the session of 1825, and a native of Goochland. He was succeeded by William Wertenbaker, of Albemarle county, a student at the time of his appointment. He was postmaster at the University for forty-two years, and thrice Librarian. His first term began with his provisional appointment by Mr. Jefferson on the 30th day of January, 1826, and ended by resignation in 1831. Reappointed in 1835, he retired in 1857, and was again appointed in 1866. Ten years later Mr. F. W. Page was assigned as his assistant. Mr. Wertenbaker remained in active service until he was paralyzed, in 1879. In 1881, he was made emeritus librarian. He died in April, 1882. During his first administration the earliest catalogue of books was prepared (1828). When Mr. Wertenbaker resigned, in 1831, he was succeeded by William H. Brockenborough, who had entered the University as a student in 1828, and who continued his studies until the close of the session in 1834, when he was graduated with the degree of Bachelor of Law. He remained in office until 1835, when Mr. Wertenbaker's second term began. Mr. Brockenborough went to the then territory of Florida, influenced in the choice of a location by the fact that he was suffering from pulmonary consumption, and settled in Tallahassee, where he speedily won prominence. Under the territorial government he was senator from the western district, and at one time president of the Senate. He was Judge of the United States District Court, member of Congress, and several times a presidential elector. He died in 1850, at the age of thirty-seven. Thomas B. Holcombe, of Lynchburg, was appointed Librarian in 1857, and continued in office until 1861. He prepared a new author-catalogue in two volumes, folio. The war ended his service. He died in 1873, in New Orleans. Robert R. Prentis, of Nansemond, then proctor, was librarian pro tem. in the gap between Mr. Holcombe and Mr. Wertenbaker (1862-66). Mr. Wertenbaker's last term began in 1866, and, as already explained, continued until 1881. Frederick W. Page was elected in 1881. He had served as assistant during the previous five years. William A. Winston, of Hanover, succeeded him in 1882, and continued in office until 1886. James B. Baker, the present Secretary of the Faculty, was elected librarian that year, and continued in office until 1891. Mr. Page was appointed to his old office in 1891, and is at his post at this time, 1900. The north front of the Rotunda exhibits now something of the appearance which Jefferson intended it to present. Fifty years ago there was where the north portico now is The North Front a porch, reached by stairways leading up from each side. The stairs were removed when the Annex was built (1851-53). This long building, which terminated ONE OF THE COLONNADES in a Corinthian portico, occupied the site of the present esplanade and was connected with the Rotunda by a columned porch. It contained the Public Hall, a room that gained dignity from the copy of the School of Athens which hung above the rostrum. Over this public auditorium were the drawing and class rooms of the school of applied mathematics, and under it, various lecture rooms, notably for law, natural philosophy and modern languages. From this north face today extend two terrace rooms, the law class-room on the east opening on the colonnade, which is an extension of East Lawn arcade; the Y. M. C. A. Hall on the west, balancing the law room already mentioned and opening on the colonnade, which is an extension of West Lawn arcade. These terrace rooms, with those on the south, already described, and the connecting colonnades, carry a terrace promenade around the entire dominating structure of the University.* * The illustration facing page 5 shows the terrace rooms—the Y. M. C. A. hall on the right and the law lecture room on the left—with the terrace promenade above. In the Public Hall referred to (often called the Annex), hung an excellent copy of Raphael's School of Athens, made from the original in the Sala de Segnatura in the Vatican at School of Athens. Rome. On returning from that city in the summer of 1850, Mr. Daniel H. London of Richmond, Va., suggested that a copy of this painting should be presented to the University of Virginia by its alumni. Col. Thomas H. Ellis determined to carry out this suggestion. He associated with him Mr. John S. Caskie, Socrates Maupin, Benj. B. Minor and John R. Thompson, graduates of the University, and on the 17th of December, 1850, this committee published a circular, explaining their purpose and asking a contribution from those who had been students at this institution. In the following spring this committee requested Mr. London, then about to re-visit Europe, to order a copy of the painting and indicated Senor Mazzolini as copyist. Col. Ellis, Judge Caskie and Mr. Thompson made themselves financially responsible to the extent of $1,500, payable six months after date. Mazzolini was unable to undertake the commission and nothing was done until 1852, when Mr. London, while in Paris, conferred with Mons. Paul Balze, a noted historical painter, who had copied more than fifty of Raphael's paintings for the French government. The price asked was $2,500. The proposed selection of Balze was approved by Messrs. John S. Peyton, John R. Page, John G. Brodnax, A. Robert McKee and Edward G. Higginbotham, University alumni then in Paris. In December, 1852, a meeting was held in the Hall of the House of Delegates at Richmond, Va. Among those specially invited to be present were Judge William Daniel, Jr., of the Supreme Court of Appeals, Senator R. M. T. Hunter, Alexander H. H. Stuart, Secretary of the Interior, and Judge Alexander Rives, then member of the General Assembly— all University men. But the meeting was a failure, and it was not THE PUBLIC HALL OR ANNEX BURNED 1895 (Here Most of the Alumni Orations Have been Delivered) until 1854 that an agreement was effected with Mr. W. A. Pratt, of Richmond, Va., by which he became the agent of the alumni to be compensated by a percentage on the amounts collected for the fund. This arrangement resulted in a contract with Balze for the painting of the picture, which was received in 1856. After having been exhibited in London at the Royal Polytechnic Institute, and, in this country, at the Old Market Hall, Richmond, and the Library Hall, Petersburg, Va., it was hung in the Public Hall at the University, and opened to the public on the afternoon of April 13th, 1857, on which occasion an address was delivered by Major Preston of the Virginia Military Institute. This painting was lost in the fire. A new copy is being made for the Auditorium by Max Seeliger, instructor in mural painting in the Imperial Berlin Art School. He was selected as the choice of Professor Ludwig Korans, the great German artist, Dr. Ewald, regarded as the foremost authority on mural docoration, and Professor Andrews, Director of the Corcoran Art Gallery, Washington. Some friend, as yet unknown to the University, has furnished the money for this copy. * * * In his eighty-fourth year Mr. Jefferson gave, through Joseph Coolidge, Jr., of Boston, an order to Willard of that city, for a clock and a bell for the University. For each of these he sub- The Jefferson Bell and Clock. mitted directions dealing with the most minute details. He wanted a bell which could generally be heard at the distance of two miles "because this will insure its always being heard at Charlottesville." The bell was cast and duly hung, and served its purposes for sixty years. In the Spring of 1886, as it no longer rang out in the clear tones of its wont, the bell was examined and found to be cracked. McShane &amp; Co. of Baltimore cast its successor, which was put in place in the autum of 1886, and of course, was lost in the fire of 1895. The Jefferson bell was placed in the Brooks Museum, where it is still to be seen on the left of the entrance. The Board of Visitors authorized the Ladies' Aid Society to have it used in casting a bell for the Chapel, but its historic value was realized, and it was bought by the late Dr. Towles, Professor Stone and Dr. Tuttle, with the understanding that it was not to be removed from the University, but always to be preserved as a relic, and was finally presented to the Board of Visitors on the same condition. The Jefferson clock was also lost in the fire of 1895. In its place is a handsome time service presented by the Hon. Jefferson M. Levy, of New York, owner of Monticello, on the 13th day of April, 1899, the anniversary of the birth of the Founder. It consists of a regulator clock, from which is run a large thirty-inch dial in the library, two fifty-six-inch dials in the north and south pediments of the Rotunda, and a programme attachment for ringing the electric bells in all the lecture rooms. The dial in the library is of white marble, with raised Roman numerals, in black, and black hands. The outside dials are of steel, enamelled in white, with plain black Roman numerals and black hands. The regulator is guaranteed to run within thirty seconds a month. This is in the faculty room, THE CHAPEL and all the other movements are connected with it electrically, and keep exactly the same time. The system is so arranged also that clocks in the other public buildings, or in private residences, may be placed on the same electric circuit, and operated by the central regulator clock in exact synchronism. * * * On the 13th of November, 1883, during the chaplaincy of the Rev. Otis A. Glazebrook, a Ladies' Chapel Society was formed, and in seven years the Chapel which stands west of the Ro- The Chapel. tunda was finished. This society found a small chapel fund of five or six hundred dollars, which was the nucleus upon which was built one of $30,000, collected chiefly from alumni. The corner-stone was laid in 1885, the late Professor Schele De Vere delivering the address. The dedication sermon was preached by the Rev. Mr. Glazebrook in 1889. In addition to the $30,000 expended on the building, the organ-room, the gift of Mr. Glazebrook, cost $1,000, and the organ, the gift chiefly of Kentucky alumni, $1,900 more. While the architecture is out of harmony with the prevailing orders, considered without relation, the Chapel is a handsome and impressive church edifice, in the Gothic style with Norman arches. It contains memorial windows in honor of Dr. John A. G. Davis, Dr. John Staige Davis, Dr. James L. Cabell and Truxton Glazebrook, and memorial tablets to Dr. Addis Emmet and Dr. Gessner Harrison. This Association was the first organization of its kind in the world. It dates from the spring of 1857. John W. Johnson, Magazine medalist, final orator of the Jefferson Literary So- The Y. M. C. A. ciety, Engineer of Fort Sumter, historian of the defence of Charleston, and Episcopal minister, was the first president, while the first recording secretary was L. M. Blackford (M. A. 1859). The first corresponding secretary was Dr. Thomas Hume, now professor of English in the University of North Carolina. Other early members were H. H. Harris, John Murray, W. W. Old, James M. Garnett, Julian Fairfax, Jerry Malcom Harris, W. P. DuBose, James M. Boyd, John M. Strother, Thomas R. Price, William P. Louthan, James Dinwiddie, Robert Carter Berkley, William Allan, Howe P. Cochran, Richard W. Jones, Thomas U. Dudley, C. Powell Grady, A. S. Pendleton, and J. William Jones. From the foundation to the present time the membership aggregates more than three thousand. In 1856 there were several conferences concerning the matter, and, in the spring of 1857, a meeting was held which determined to organize, and appointed a committee to draft a constitution and by-laws. This committee reported at the beginning of the next session (October, 1857), and the organization was completed, but it is really entitled to date from the spring of 1857. —J. William Jones. Religious enterprises at the University antedated this organization many years. As early as 1828 the individual members of the Faculty arranged for services by the pastors then in Charlottesville. These were of the Episcopalian and the Presbyterian faiths. From 1833 to 1896, a period of sixty-three years, chaplains appointed by the Faculty were in charge of the religious work. The term of incumbency was one session each until 1848, when it was made two years. It will be seen from the following list of chaplains that the University has been served by many eminent divines. Presbyterian.— — Smith, 1829; Francis Bowman, no date given, but his term was at least one session between 1830 and 1833; Septimus Tuston, 1836-37; William S. White, 1840-41 Chaplains. and 1844-45; William H. Ruffner, 1849-51; Dabney C. Harrison, 1859-61; Thomas D. Witherspoon, 1871-73; Clement R. Vaughn, 1879-81; James M. Rawlings, 1887-89; A. R. Cocke, 1895-96; L. C. Vass, elected for 1896-98, but died September 28, 1898. He was the last chaplain, the office having been abolished, and other agencies substituted, as elsewhere explained. Episcopalian.— — Hatch, (probably) 1830-31; Nicholas H. Cobbs (Bishop of Alabama), 1834-35; Joseph P. B. Wilmer (Bishop of Louisiana), 1837-38; William M. Jackson, 1845-46; William Dent Hanson, 1853-55; Peter Tinsley, 1867-69; Robert J. McBryde, 1875-77; Otis A. Glazebrook, 1883-85; James L. Lancaster, 1891-93. Methodist. — William Hammett, 1833-34; David S. Doggett (Bishop), 1838-39; Leonidas Rosser, 1842-43; Jacob Manning and David Wood, 1846-47; W. W. Bennett and Ballard Gibson, 185153; John S. Lindsay, 1865-67; S. A. Steel, 1873-75; J. T. Whitley, 1881-83; Collins Denny, 1889-91. Baptist.—Robert Ryland, 1835-36; James B. Taylor, 1839-40 and 1869-71; E. G. Robinson, 1843-44; Jacob Scott, 1847-49; John A. Broadus, 1855-57; A. B. Woodfin, 1877-79; George B. Taylor, 1885-87; J. William Jones, 1893-95. John C. Granberry (Bishop), Methodist, was elected for the term of 1861-63, and John C. McCabe, Episcopalian, for the term of 186365, but neither officiated. The system was changed upon the death of Rev. L. C. Vass, in September, 1896, at the beginning of his chaplaincy. A secretary of the Young Men's Christian Association, latterly The System Changed. known as the University pastor, has had charge of religious work among the students, and eminent preachers from this and other cities are invited to deliver the sermons, a course which has proven very satisfactory and beneficial. The first secretary under this plan was W. I. McNair of Louisville, Kentucky, and the second, J. M. Brodnax of Mason. Tennessee, the present incumbent. The controlling body is the Religious Exercise Committee, composed of three members of the Faculty and three student members of the Young Men's Christian Association. The Rev. C. A. Young, Assistant Instructor in Hebrew, is rendering valuable service in the interest of religious teaching by courses of lectures on New and Old Testament subjects. He is making an earnest effort to secure endowment for an English Bible Lectureship. The day of his arrival at the University the new student is convinced that those who have declared the institution atheistical in foundation and purpose—a charge which is made ma- Religious Work for the Student. liciously to this day in some quarters—have not told the truth. He is soon made to understand that there is such a thing as religious enterprise at this institution, and that the matriculates bear a large part in its direction. He finds that he is expected to do his share, if he is so minded, but it is a matter of free choice with him, while he can scarcely escape the pervasive influence of the Young Men's Christian Association; and, if he has any bent toward Bible study and religious endeavor, he will find here abundant opportunity, more, perhaps, than at any other undenominational American college. * * * Early in 1876 Professor Henry A. Ward, of Rochester, N. Y., announced to Professor Smith that a gentleman of Rochester, an admirer of Mr. Jefferson and an earnest well- The Brooks Museum. wisher of the South, desired to establish at the University of Virginia a complete and costly museum of natural history, on the condition that other friends of the institution would pledge the sum of $12,000 to provide for the necessary cases, mounting, etc. The Board of Trustees of the Miller Agricultural Department furnished ten thousand of the required amount, and Professor W. B. Rogers and other alumni the remaining two thousand. It afterwards transpired that Mr. Lewis Brooks was the donor. The building was completed in July, 1877, and immediately afterwards a costly collection of specimens was assembled, to which valuable additions have since been made. Mr. Brooks's gifts aggregate about seventy thousand dollars. The building, constructed chiefly of brick, is after the Renaissance order, and is elaborately ornamented with the heads of various animals, carved in granite. The granite trimmings, which are rather too profuse, are carved with the names of eminent scientists, such as Cuvier, De Candolle, Audubon, Huxley and Pliny. The lower hall contains, on the floor, the geological collections, and, in galleries around the entire hall, the mineralogical specimens. The zoological exhibit is in the main part of the upper hall, while on the same floor is the botanical hall. The building contains a lecture room and laboratories. Mr. Jefferson selected the site of the present observatory and erected upon it a small building for astronomical purposes, perhaps the first observatory in America. This structure which was never devoted to the use intended, was pulled down in 1859. The McCormick Observatory. In 1881 the late Leander J. McCormick, of Chicago, gave $50,000 to establish an observatory, to which gift he afterward added largely; and W. H. Vanderbilt, THE McCORMICK OBSERVATORY of New York, contributed $25,000 to the same fund. The elevation is known as Mount Jefferson, and is about a mile southwest of the University. The site is a beautiful one and furnishes an unobstructed horizon. The principal building is a rotunda forty-five feet in diameter, and contains the great Clark refractor of twenty-six inches aperture. The computing rooms are adjoining and contain clock, chronograph, &amp;c., and a working library. In a smaller building are a three inch Fauth transit, and a four inch Kahler equatorial. Professor Ormond Stone is the Director. At its annual session in 1868 the Board of Visitors authorized the building and equipment of a chemical laboratory, which was done within the year, on a beautiful knoll west of Chemical Laboratory. West Range. The marble tablet on the face of the building gives the date of the foundation and this from Roger Bacon: "Naturae secreta et artis possibilia." It contains a large lecture-room with work and store-room adjacent, and a large room for analytical chemistry. The equipment and stock are extensive and of the most approved character. Medical Hall, one of the oldest erections in the University, stands between West Range and the Chemical Labora- Medical Hall. tory. It is devoted chiefly to lecture-rooms. This building was destroyed by fire in the late fall of 1886, and immediately rebuilt. The erection of the hospital was begun April 11th, 1900, in order to have it ready for use the ensuing session. The present erection is the central administration building, three stories in height, containing reception and consultation The Hospital. rooms, offices, accommodations for internes and nurses, etc. Attached to it is one of the best clinical amphitheatres in this country, with a convenient and well lighted operating room adjoining. On each side will be added one story wards with space for sixty beds. The plan admits of indefinite extension. The hospital is located in the open space east of East Range. The architect is Mr. Paul J. Pelz, of Washington, who is well known in connection with the Congressional Library, and the style will conform to the order of architecture which prevails here. The Randall Dormitory was built after plans furnished by Mr. Pelz. In 1859 six buildings, known as House A, House B, etc., arranged in the arc of a circle, were erected about two hundred yards southwest of West Range to accommodate the increasing Dawson's Row. number of students. The land upon which these buildings were erected had been purchased from a fund accruing from the sale of a tract of land devised to the University by Martin Dawson, hence the name of Dawson's Row. The series of dormitories known as Monroe Hill lies at the northwest end of Dawson's Row. The hill takes its name from the small building once occupied by President Monroe, Monroe Hill. which, much expanded and improved, is now the handsome home of Professor W. M. Thornton. The ex-President had his law office in a small building about a hundred feet southwest of the residence. This building is still standing. Temperance Hall, in which is the University postoffice, was built in 1855-56, the fund for the purpose being contributed by General John H. Cocke and other persons interested in Temperance Hall. the temperance movement. For many years the Sons of Temperance held their meetings in the upper hall of this building, as did later the Friends of Temperance, the organization which succeeded the Sons. Neither of these societies now exists. At the postoffice, at Chancellor's drug store, and across the street, at Anderson's and Olivier's bookstores, students congregate when the weather is fine, sing college songs, and eye the girls who pass in smart traps or stroll by on the way to "town." The name Carr's Hill belongs to the eminence north of the Rotunda and adjacent to the athletic practice grounds. It is derived from an early owner. A short time before the civil Carr's Hill. war, Judge Alexander Rives purchased it and presented it to the late Mrs. Dr. Schele De Vere, from whom the University purchased it immediately after the surrender. The original buildings, long since destroyed, were occupied as a private boarding-house. The present dormitories were erected several years after the war; and the mess-hall, still used as such, is of recent date. The Randall Dormitory, the handsome apartment house for students, architecturally in harmony with the other University buildings, was erected in 1899 out of a fund contributed Randall Dormitory. from the estate of W. J. and Belinda Randall, of Massachusetts. It is at the south end of East Range, with an imposing front looking toward the new quadrangle. * * * A few months after the opening of the University a literary association called the Patrick Henry Society was formed, composed of nearly all the students. Sixteen of its members, dis- Literary Societies. satisfied with the disorder which prevailed at its sessions, seceded and founded the Jefferson Society. The seceders held their preliminary meeting in No. 7 West Lawn on Thursday, July 14, 1825, and selected The Patrick Henry. a committee, consisting of Edgar Mason, of Charles county, Md., John H. Lee, of Fau- The Jefferson. quier county, Va., and William G. Minor, of Fredericksburg, Va., to draft a constitution which was reported and presumably adopted on the following Monday. JEFF. HALL WASH. HALL The Society met weekly at first; later, fornightly on "Monday evening at early candlelight." The first president (then called moderator), was Edgar Mason. The meetings were held in Pavilion I, and later, at the different pavilions on the Lawn. Jefferson, who was elected on the motion of Robert A. Thompson, of Kanawha county, Va., now West Virginia, declined honorary membership on account of his official connection with the University. Madison, Monroe and Lafayette accepted. John Randolph of Roanoke was black-balled because he was bitterly opposed to the election of Mr. Monroe, Jefferson's candidate for the presidency. Poe was elected an active member June 17, 1826, and soon after complied with the custom by reading an essay, his subject being "Heat and Cold." He participated in one or two debates and once acted as secretary pro tem. His autograph was cut from the minute book by some curio thief. This Society, in the earlier days, celebrated Jefferson's birthday by reading the Declaration of Independence and by addresses. FINAL PRESIDENTS. 1826—Chapman Johnson, Va. 1827—S. A. Townes, S. C. 1828—R. H. Brown, Va. 1829—Robert Toombs, Ga. 1830—William B. Napton, N. J. 1831—Benjamin F. Randolph, Va. 1832—Fairfax Catlett, Va. 1833—William D. Hodges, Va. 1834—E. Taliaferro, Va. 1835—G. W. Trueheart, Va. 1836—M. Carleton, Ala. 1837—W. G. Gray, Md. 1838—R. L. T. Beale, Va. 1839—J. A. Strother, Ala. 1840—J. H. Oliver, La. 1841—Robert L. Dabney, Va. 1842—Edmund Randolph, Va. 1843—J. F. Kunkel, Md. 1844—Tiberius G. Jones, Va. 1845—Roscoe B. Heath, Va. 1846—Robert J. Morrison, Va. 1847—V. E. Shepherd, Va. 1848—W. B. Woolridge, Va. 1849—John A. Broadus, Va. 1850—Richard H. Baker, Va. 1851—John D. Pennybacker, Va. 1852—George L. Gordon, Va. 1853—James William Morgan, Va. 1854—William R. Aylett, Va. 1855—James Taylor Jones, Ala. 1856—Creswell Garlington, S. C. 1857—Edward C. Preston, La. 1858—William G. Field, Va. 1859—W. Moultrie Dwight, S. C. 1860—P. J. Glover, Ala. 1861-66—None recorded. 1867—W. W. Foote, Tenn. 1868—J. B. Gantt, Ga. 1869—None recorded. 1870—S. P. Dendy, S. C. 1871—G. C. Hume, Md. 1872—Moses L. Wicks, Tenn. 1873—B. C. Wicks, Md. 1874—Frederick F. Reese, Md. 1875—Benjamin Fitzpatrick, Ala. 1876—H. H. Downing, Va. 1877—Joseph Allen Southall, Va. 1878—L. W. Gunther, Jr., Md. 1879—George D. Fawsett, Md. 1880—Pembroke Lea Thom, Md. 1881—Floyd Hughes, Va. 1882—William Corcoran Eustis, D. C. 1883—J. Hunter Pendleton, Va. 1884—Jefferson Randolph Anderson, Ga. 1885—R. C. Taylor, Md. 1886—None recorded. 1887—George Wayne Anderson, Ga. 1888—W. J. H. Bohannon, Va. 1889—George Gordon Battle, N. C. 1890—Raleigh C. Minor, Va. 1891—R. Spratt Cockrell, Fla. 1892—J. Gordon Leake, Va. 1893—Murray Mason McGuire, Va. 1894—Joseph A. Massey, Va. 1895—Hollins N. Randolph, Va. 1896—George Nelms Wise, Va. 1897—Walter Tansill Oliver, Va. 1898—Charles W. Miller, Ky. 1899—Joseph C. Taylor, Va. 1900—William T. Shannonhouse, N. C. In 1896 Professor James A. Harrison presented to the Jefferson and the Washington Literary societies a trophy to be won for the one or the other by excellence in debate, and to remain with the society winning it as long as it can successfully defend it. The Medals, Prizes and Trophies. trophy cost a hundred dollars, and was made by the Gorham Company of New York. It consists of a solid silver laurel wreath, encircling a scroll of copper, on which the names of the winning contestants are to be engraved. Each literary society offers two medals. The one for the best orator is presented by the society, but that for the best debater in each society is presented by the Rector and Visitors, and is known as the Rector and Visitors' medal. THE PATH ALONG EAST RANGE. It is not known when the Jefferson first offered a medal to its best debater; it was some time before a similar trophy was provided for the best orator. The records are imperfect; before the Jeff. Medalists. civil war almost none exists. It is known that in 1858 Mr. K. Kemper of Virginia was the orator at the intermediate celebration, that James Camp Turner of Alabama read the Declaration of Independence on the same occasion, and that Joseph Hodgson of Virginia was the orator at the commencement the same year. There is no record for 1859, but at the intermediate in 1860 Camm Patteson of Virginia was the orator and Robert Falligant of Georgia read the Declaration. At the final, William R. Berkeley of Virginia was the orator. It seems quite certain that none of these were medalists. The first medal recorded is that awarded to James M. Boyd of Lynchburg, Virginia, as the best debater. From this on there is no record of medalist, orator or reader until 1869, although the society was in active existence, and had been for two years at least (1867, 1868), with the usual quota of officers. In this year C. F. McKesson of North Carolina was intermediate orator and S. P. Luck reader. The list follows, beginning with 1871, there being no record for 1870: 1871—H. H. Martin, Va., debater; G. E. Nelson, Va., orator. 1872—Henry T. Kent, Va., debater; L. M. Elder, Tenn., orator. 1873—J. S. Williams, Tenn., debater. 1874—J. E. Powell, Mo., debater; M. W. Ransom, Jr., N. C., orator Roger Johnson, resigned). [This year efforts were made in the Jefferson as well as the Washington to abolish the medal system, it being alleged that to it was due the violent partisan spirit which often prevailed in the societies.] 1875—Leo N. Levi, Texas, debater; A. M. Robinson, Texas, orator (vice Lyon G. Tyler, Va., resigned). 1876—Bernard Peyton, Va., debater; A. P. Thom, Va., orator (vice Lyon G. Tyler, Va., resigned). 1877—A. G. Stuart, Va., debater; C. A. Culberson, Texas, orator. 1878—Dudley G. Wooten, Texas, debater; F. T. Glasgow, Va., orator. 1879—P. A. Bruce, Va., debater; Wyndham R. Meredith, Va., orator. 1880—William Cabell Bruce, Va., debater; Thomas Woodrow Wilson, N. C., orator. 1881—W. S. Lefevre, Md., debater; Robert W. Mallet, Va., orator. 1882—Charles W. Kent, Va., debater; William P. Trent, orator. 1883—M. C. Pope, debater; no orator's medal awarded. [Mr. Pope was called from the University before the commencement, leaving the society without a speaker for its celebration. William P. Trent and Robert W. Mallet filled the vacant places on the programme.] 1884—F. W. Gregory, Miss., debater; John B. Henneman, S. C., orator. 1885—W. B. Richards, Va., debater; F. R. Lassiter, Va., orator. 1886—G. W. Anderson, Ga., debater; C. A. Swanson, Va., orator. 1887—U. W. Muir, Ky., debater; M. S. Macon, La., orator. 1888—J. L. Kelley, Va., debater; J. G. Scott, Va., orator. 1889—Charles P. Fenner, La., debater; W. S. Hamilton, Ga., orator. 1890—P. H. C. Cabell, Jr., debater; E. L. Boyle, Tenn., orator. 1891—William G. Peterkin, W. Va., debater; Henry Lewis Smith, N. C., orator. 1892—No award of debater's medal; L. H. Machen, Va., orator. 1893—Lewis H. Machen, Va., debater; Benjamin Franklin Martin, Va., orator. 1894—No award of debater's medal; Hugh M. Dorsey, Ga., orator. 1895—No award of debater's medal; W. K. Allyn, Va., orator. 1896—Henry A. Hopkins, Texas, debater; W. S. Hancock, Va., orator. 1897—Albert Fink, Ark., and Walter T. Oliver, Va., debaters; Henry A. Hopkins, Texas, orator. 1898—H. W. Mayo, Va., debater; Joseph C. Taylor, Va., orator. 1899—E. Reinhold Rogers, Va., debater; George P. Bagby, Va., orator. 1900—S. E. Bradshaw, Ky., debater; Wm. C. Munroe, Fla., orator. * * * Little can be learned of the early history of the Washington Society. The date of its foundation is undetermined, but this association of students was in existence as early as Novem- The Washington Society. ber, 1835, for on that date an entry was made in the faculty minutes to this effect: "The chairman laid before the faculty the application of the Washington Society to be allowed the use of the old library room to hold its meetings." The request was granted. The Wash. celebrated the birthday of its patron saint, February 22, on which occasion it was the custom to read the farewell address. FINAL PRESIDENTS. 1844—J. F. Wooten, N. C. 1845—Presley C. Lane, Ala. 1846—George A. Hall, Ga. 1847—William H. F. Hall, Ga. 1848—J. F. Marshall, Miss. 1849—John L. Cockran, Va. 1850—Frederick Floyd, Va. 1851—Frank V. Winston, Va. 1852—J. F. Deloney, Ala. 1853—Edward S. Joynes, Va. 1854—George B. Taylor, Va. 1855—Virginius Dabney, Miss. 1856—John M. Bolling, Va. 1857—Algernon Sidney Epes, Va. 1858—Thomas U. Dudley, Va. 1859—Edward L. Martin, Del. 1860—C. W. Wilson, Va. 1861-66—None recorded. 1867—C. J. Faulkner, W. Va. 1868—W. O. Harris, W. Va. 1869—None recorded. 1870—J. C. McKennie, Va. 1871—Barnett Gibbs, Texas. 1872—Walter G. Charleton, Ga. 1873—Richard H. Maury, Miss. 1874—Thomas L. Raymond, La. 1875—Benjamin Johnson, Va. 1876—Frederick Elias Conway, Ark. 1877—Frank P. Farish, Va. 1878—V. M. Potter, Ky. 1879—None recorded. 1880—John F. B. Beckwith, Ga. 1881—S. J. Shepherd, Tenn. 1882—W. D. Toy, Va. 1883—W. T. Turnbull, Fla. 1884—James I. Van Meter, Ohio. 1885—C. H. Fauntleroy, Va. 1886—Lewis M. G. Baker, Va. 1887—W. E. Allen, Va. 1888—S. L. Kelley, Va. 1889—None recorded. 1890—Charles F. Coleman, Fla. 1891—George N. Conrad, Va. 1892—Robert Fulton Leach, Md. 1893—Allen P. Gilmour, Ky. 1894—J. Bernard Handlan, Va. 1895—Joseph T. Allyn, Va. 1896—Alexander Scott Bullitt, Ky. 1897—Frank Grey Newbill, Va. 1898—Charles N. Joyce, Md. 1899—Patrick H. Aylett, Va. 1900—E. H. Fulton, Va. There is little to be learned of the honor men of the Washington Society before the war. It is recorded briefly that in 1858 the oration at the intermediate celebration was deliv- Wash. Medalists. ered by Littleton J. Haley of Orange county, Va., and that Washington's farewell address was read by Thomas J. Wertenbaker of Charlottesville, Va. The orator at the final celebration was L. Southgate of Norfolk, Va. Two years later (1860) S. Taylor Martin of Richmond, Va., was orator at the intermediate; A. Jay Arnold of Alexandria, Va., reader; and, at the final, William F. Ogden of New Orleans, La., orator, and William Allen of Winchester, Va., was awarded the medal as the best debater. This is the first mention of a medal in connection with the Wash. The war came on, and no record exists, as far as the writers know, of the years until 1869. At the intermediate celebration that spring Richard S. Jefferies of Charlottesville was the orator, and J. G. Rogers of Maryland the reader. The final celebration is unnoted. In 1870 intermediate celebrations were discontinued. The following statement refers to honors awarded at the final celebrations of the society: 1870—Linden Kent, Va., debater. 1871—E. H. Farrar, La., debater; Barnett Gibbs, Miss., orator. 1872—H. A. McCollum, La., debater; C. A. Jenkins, Miss., orator. 1873—F. R. Graham, La., debater. 1874—John S. Brooks, Va., debater; R. S. Saulsbury, Ga., orator. 1875—C. E. Nicol, Md., debater, H. C. Stuart, Va., orator. 1876—T. E. Blakey, Va., debater; J. G. Colley, Ga., orator. 1877—J. F. Ellison, Va., debater; Junius Rochester, Ky., orator. 1878—Richard A. Jackson, Md., debater; Benjamin F. Long, N. C., orator. 1879—No award. 1880—No award. 1881—W. W. Wilkerson, Ala., debater; F. M. O. Fenn, Texas, orator. 1882—H. P. Lawther, Texas, debater; H. G. Peters, Va., orator. 1883—W. B. Eldridge, Tenn., debater; W. G. Winstock, Va., orator. 1884—L. H. Pugh, La., debater; B. H. Lee, Miss., orator. 1885—W. H. Bryant, Va., debater; W. J. Shelburne, Va., orator. 1886—R. G. Bickford, Va., debater; J. G. Covington, Ky., orator. 1887—J. B. Gibson, Miss., debater; T. E. Ryals, Ga., orator. 1888—L. G. M. Baker, Va., debater; F. Causey, Va., orator. 1889—J. A. Barclay, Ky., debater; F. W. Weaver, Va., orator. 1890—R. M. Banks, Jr., Miss., debater; G. N. Conrad, Va., orator. 1891—Charles F. Spencer, Ky., debater; Henry A. Etheridge, Ga., orator. 1892—Robert E. Cofer, Texas, debater; Harris L. Moss, Va., orator. 1893—John Henry Nininger, Va., debater; Algernon B. Chandler, Va., orator. 1894—Charles R. Frankum, Va., debater; Edward L. Greever, Va., orator. 1895—J. R. Rew, Va., debater; A. E. Strode, S. C., orator. 1896—G. W. Holland, Va., debater; Clyde W. Portlock, Tenn., orator. 1897—Preston W. Campbell, Va., debater; Charles N. Joyce, Md., orator. 1898—C. L. Kagey, Va., debater; D. S. Burleson, Va., orator. 1899—J. Douglass Mitchell, Va., debater; A. Leo Oberdorfer, Va., orator. 1900—Arthur J. Morris, Va., debater; Roscoe C. Nelson, Va., orator. WINNERS OF THE HARRISON TROPHY. 1896—The Washington Society. 1897—The Jefferson Society. 1898, 1899—The Washington Society. At least three other literary societies existed at the University. The Philomathean was founded in 1849 or earlier; the Parthenon in 1852. Judge Charles E. Fenner of New Other Literary Societies. Orleans and Thomas A. Malone (M. A. '54) of Alabama, now of Nashville, Tenn., were the first orators. Of the Columbian little is known beyond the fact that it once existed. At its intermedate celebration in 1858 its orator was William W. Bird of Washington, D. C., and at its final, the same year, George R. Culvert of Shenandoah county, Va., wore this honor. There is evidence that the literary societies were not always in high favor with the authorities. In the Editor's Table of the Collegian for July, 1839, the fact that the Board of Visitors Not Always in Favor. had, some two years before, passed a resolution prohibiting the celebration of anniversaries and the delivery of addresses in public by students is referred to with much feeling. "We are forbidden to speak," wrote the editors; "the tongue falters; the lips are closed, and the voice of vivid eloquence must ring through our Corinthian columns no more." The Philosophical Society, an organization of professors and students for original research, was founded in November, 1889. The presidents thus far have been: Dr. Mallet, Professor The Philosophical Society. Noah K. Davis, Professor F. H. Smith, Professor J. H. Gilmore, Dr. Tuttle, Professor Stone and Dr. Kent, in the order named; the secretaries, Professor Stone and Dr. W. J. Humphreys. * * * The first periodical published in the University was The Collegian. It was conducted by a committee elected by the students and printed by James Alexander of Charlottesville. The The College Press. first committee consisted of John S. Barbour of Culpeper, John Critcher of Westmoreland county, R. Barnes Gooch of Richmond, James P. Holcombe of Lynchburg, and Thomas H. Watts of Alabama, all of whom achieved distinction in after life. John S. Barbour died a United States Senator, after many years of active participation in public affairs; John Critcher was a leader in his section and a representative of his district in Congress; R. Barnes Gooch, a distinguished lawyer in Richmond, died before he had opportunity to manifest his full powers; James P. Holcombe distinguished himself both as teacher and as statesman, occupying a chair in this institution, and, at one time, a seat in Congress; and Thomas H. Watts, the Confederate States Attorney-General, was for more than a generation the great man of his native State, of which he was governor. The first number was issued in October, 1838, and its publication was continued until 1842, at least. The oldest of the existing periodicals is The University Magazine, whose first number appeared in December, 1856, under the auspices of the three literary societies of that The Magazine. time, the Jefferson, the Washington and the Columbian. There is nothing in the pages of its earlier issues to indicate who were its editors. The custom of printing their names was not introduced until the ninth number. This magazine has had among its contributors some of the brightest of the alumni of the institution. From it has been reprinted a volume of poems under the title "Arcade A GLIMPSE OF THE LAWN From East Terrace Looking toward West Lawn Echoes" which is now in its second edition. The first was edited by Thomas Longstreet Wood of Albermale county, Va., a student whose brilliant literary promise had entered upon its fulfillment when death claimed him; the second, by Mr. John W. Fishburne of Charlottesville. Six of its best stories have been printed in a richly bound and attractively illustrated volume, of which Dr. Charles W. Kent was the editor; the illustrator, Mr. Duncan Smith (M. A. 1897) of New York. The magazine is issued monthly during the session. College Topics was established in January, 1890, as a private enterprise, the societies refusing to take the financial risk involved. The founders and first board of editors were Legh R. Page of Richmond, Va., A. C. Carson of Riverton, Va., Stuart-Menteth Beard of Canandaigua, N. Y., Hunt Chipley of Pensacola, Fla., and John G. Tilton of Baltimore, Md. As the Magazine filled the literary field, Topics was projected as a medium of college news and college spirit. It was soon recognized as an exponent of athletic interests, and became the official organ of the General Athletic Association. It is published weekly by a staff of editors appointed by the Advisory Board of the above named Association.* * For a history of "College Topics" see "University Magazine," April, 1892, p. 478. Corks and Curls, an illustrated annual, is published by a board of editors appointed by the Greek letter fraternities, and was first issued in 1887. It is a handsome quarto, with a new design each year for the cover, done in the University colors. The above are student publications, and represent the interests of undergraduate life at this institution. The Alumni Bulletin, as its name implies, is provided to afford a means of communication between the University and its alumni. The first number was issued May, 1894, and since then it has been published quarterly. The Annals of Mathematics was established by Professor Stone in 1884, as a medium for the publication of the results of mathematical investigations of the highest class. Professor Echols was at one time associated with him as editor. Two prizes are given for excellence in composition in articles in the Magazine. The first is for the best contribution by a member of either society; the second is a prize of twenty dollars Literary Prizes. in gold for the best original poem published in the Magazine. This prize is offered by Professor James A. Harrison. Among the honors eagerly sought at the University is the Magazine medal. The names of the winners of this prize Magazine Medalists. and other interesting information are given in the following statement: 1858—John Johnson, Charleston, S. C., subject, "Drudgery and Leisure." 1859—James McDowell Graham, Lexington, Va., "The Worship of Nature." 1860—Leigh Robinson, Washington, D. C., "What Will He Do With It?" 1868—A. M. Miller, Petersburg, Va. Title of article unknown. 1870—Charles Wickliffe Yulee, Fernandina, Fla., "Michael Angelo." 1872—Thomas A. Seddon, Fredericksburg, Va., "The Ballad of the Ancient Mariner." 1873—R. T. W. Duke, Jr., Charlottesville, Va., "Old Letters." 1874—William W. Thum, Louisville, Ky., "The Death of Marlowe." 1875—Marcus B. Almond, Charlottesville, Va. (now of Louisville, Ky.), "Glendower." 1876—Leo N. Levi, Galveston, Texas, "Charles II and His Times." 1877—William P. Kent, Virginia, "The Moral Significance of the American Centennial." 1878—Dudley G. Wooten, Texas, "Uncrowned Heroes." 1879—Walter S. Lefevre, Maryland, "Queen Mab: A Study in Shelley." 1880—William Cabell Bruce, Virginia, "John Randolph." 1881—Samuel H. James, Louisiana, "Diogenes Teufelsdröckh." 1883—James Gazaway Ryals, Georgia, "Tennyson and The Idyls of the King. 1885—Blewitt H. Lee, Mississippi, "Shakespeare's Songs." 1886—John Singleton Mosby, Virginia, "The Story of the Nile." 1887—Frank E. Corbett, Texas, "Napoleon III." 1888—Ernest M. Stires, Virginia, "The Eastern Question." 1889—Thomas Longstreet Wood, Virginia, "Life in Shiflet's Hollow." 1890—H. Snowden Marshall, Maryland, "A Crusade by Turks." 1891—Stuart-Menteth Beard, Louisiana, "Essex and Bacon." 1892—Charles Trotter Lassiter, Virginia, "The Parliament of Man." 1893—Charles Hall Davis, Virginia, "The Chief of Women Poets." 1894—J. Spottiswood Taylor, Virginia, "An Unenterprising Fellow.' 1895—John Handy Hall, Virginia, "Marah." 1896—Schuyler Poitevent, Mississippi, "The Strange Music of Biloxi Bay." J. Pierce Bruns, Louisiana, Translation medal. 1897—Morris P. Tilley, Virginia, "Coffee Houses and Coffee Drinkers." Mayer L. Halff, Texas, Translation medal. J. Pierce Bruns, Louisiana, Original Verse medal. 1898—E. L. Grace, Virginia, "Sidney Lanier." L. P. Chamberlayne, Virginia, Translation medal. J. W. Rice, Texas, Original Verse medal. J. W. Rice, Texas (story), "A Sketcher of Skulls." 1899—Carroll M. Newman, Virginia, "Some Charms of Kipling." Philip F. DuPont, Delaware, Original Verse medal. Morris P. Tilley, Virginia (story), "The Body-Snatching of Mr. Peppers." From 1861 to 1867 no record can be found of the awarding of this medal, and it is quite likely it was not bestowed in that time. No award was made in 1869, 1871, 1882 and 1884. In 1882 William P. Trent and Charles W. Kent, both of Virginia, were honorably mentioned. * * * The Society of the Alumni was founded in 1838, but there exists only the briefest record of its transactions from the organization until after the civil war. Society of the Alumni. At a meeting of the Faculty in January, 1838, Professor Tucker, proposed that a committee should be appointed by the chairman to organize a society of alumni. The members of the committee were immediately appointed by Dr. Gessner Harrison, then chairman, and they were Professors George Tucker, J. A. G. Davis, M. D., and John P. Emmet, M. D. In the student publications—first the Collegian and then the Magazine — are occasional references to the addresses before the Society of Alumni on commencement occasions. The first oration of which there is any notice was the one by the Hon. R. M. T. Hunter, on the 9th of July, 1839, and it is quite probable this distinguished alumnus was the first of the long line of notable men who have accepted the invitation to return to the Alma Mater and speak to her children who have not gone forth, as well as to those who come back for the commencement season of reunion. In the library are two volumes of "Addresses and Memorials of the University of Virginia," made up chiefly of the orations delivered on such occasions. They contain several addresses that take rank with those of the great orators of the world. Certainly to this eminence rises the effort of the late Senator Daniel W. Voorhees, of Indiana. At the first meeting after the war, June 28, 1866, the secretary reported that during the occupation of Charlottesville by Gen. Sheridan, in March of the previous year, his desk containing all of the records and papers of the Society was carried off by the Federal soldiers, thus leaving the Society without written constitution, laws, or list of members. A committee consisting of N. H. Massie, Green Peyton, S. V. Southall, Eugene Davis and W. J. Robertson, prepared a constitution and by-laws, which were adopted in 1867. Of this committee Mr. Southall is the sole survivor. Since the reorganization the records are fairly complete. The following list of orators and presidents of the Society for the past third of a century are worth preserving: 1867—Marmaduke Johnson, of Virginia, orator; J. P. Holcombe, of Virginia, president. 1868—Charles Marshall, of Maryland, orator; J. P. Holcombe, of Virginia, president. 1869—William C. Rives, of Massachusetts, orator; A. H. H. Stuart, of Virginia, president. 1870—J. W. Stevenson, of Kentucky, orator; A. H. H. Stuart, of Virginia, president. 1871—W. B. Napton, of Missouri, orator; J. L. Marye, of Virginia, president. 1872—W. B. Quarles, of Tennessee, orator; J. L. Marye, of Virginia, president. 1873—Thomas Swann, of Maryland, orator; B. J. Barbour, of Virginia, president. 1874—J. H. Kennard, of Louisiana, orator; B. J. Barbour, of Virginia, president. 1875—R. M. T. Hunter, of Virginia, orator; D. B. Lucas (poem), of West Virginia; B. J. Barbour, of Virginia, president. 1876—F. W. M. Holliday, of Virginia, orator; B. J. Barbour, of Virginia, president. 1877—No orator; J. M. Hanger, of Virginia, president. 1878—J. C. Southall, of Virginia (opening of Brooks Museum), orator; J. M. Hanger, of Virginia, president. 1879—T. U. Dudley, Kentucky, orator; J. R. Tucker, of Virginia, president. 1880—J. H. Chamberlayne, of Virginia, orator; J. R. Tucker, of Virginia, president. 1881—J. O. Broadhead, of Missouri, orator; J. W. Stevenson, of Kentucky, president. 1882—H. Tutwiler, of Alabama, orator; J. W. Stevenson, of Kentucky, president. 1883—W. C. Rives, of Massachusetts, (W. B. Rogers, Memorial), orator; F. R. Rives, of New York, president. 1884—A. P. Humphrey, of Kentucky, orator; F. R. Rives, of New York, president. 1885—C. E. Stuart, of Virginia, orator; C. M. Blackford, of Virginia, president. 1886—C. E. Fenner, of Louisiana, orator; C. M. Blackford, of Virginia, president. 1887—H. A. Herbert, of Alabama, orator; H. E. Jackson, of Tennessee, president. 1888—W. Gordon McCabe, of Virginia, orator; H. E. Jackson, of Tennessee, president. 1889—H. T. Kent, of Missouri, orator; A. E. Richards, of Virginia, president. 1890—J. L. Gordon, of Virginia, orator; A. E. Richards, of Virginia, president. 1891—W. L. Wilson, of West Virginia, orator; Charles Marshall, of Maryland, president. 1892—L. S. Marye, of Virginia, orator; Charles Marshall, of Maryland, president. 1893—W. C. Bruce, of Maryland, orator; Joseph Bryan, of Virginia, president. 1894—Rev. John Johnson, D. D., of South Carolina, orator; Joseph Bryan, of Virginia, president. 1895—Woodrow Wilson, of New Jersey, orator; George Perkins, of Virginia, president. 1896—Rev. J. S. Lindsay, D. D., of Massachusetts, orator; George Perkins, of Virginia, president. 1897—W. R. Abbot, of Virginia, orator; Rev. Randolph H. McKim, D. D., of Washington, D. C., president. 1898—Rev. Randolph H. McKim, D. D., of Washington, D. C., orator; George Perkins, of Virginia, president. 1899—John Bassett Moore, of New York, orator; George Perkins, of Virginia, president. In 1899 a new constitution was adopted and since that event the Society has flourished more than at any other time in its history. The Board of Visitors, recognizing the obligation of the University to its graduates, has incorporated into the University system a scheme for alumni scholarships, the beneficiaries to be appointed, under certain conditions, by the local associations. In this way many bright young men are given the advantage of thorough university training who might otherwise be deprived of it. The Board has also set aside one of the University buildings for the accommodation of visiting alumni. This and other influences have led to the organization of many local alumni associations and the infusing of new life into the entire system. * * * Among the clubs are the German, the Dramatic, the Mandolin, and the Glee, together with State and School clubs. The fraternities are Greek letter and Ribbon societies. The follow- Fraternities and Clubs. ing Greek letter fraternities have chapters in the University: Phi Kappa Sigma, Delta Kappa Epsilon, Phi Kappa Psi, Beta Theta Pi, Chi Phi, Sigma Alpha Epsilon, Phi Gamma Delta, Delta Psi, Kappa Sigma, Sigma Chi, Alpha Tau Omega, Zeta Psi, Phi Delta Theta, Kappa Alpha, Delta Tau Delta, Mu Pi Lambda, Phi Delta Phi, Pi Mu, and Lambda Pi. The Ribbon societies are Eli Banana, T. I. L K. A., Z, and Thirteen Club. * * * In the first years of the University athletics took a military form, a military instructor training the students in the manual exercises, field evolutions, maneuvers, and so on. Attend- Athletics, ance was compulsory, obedience to the instructor enjoined by enactment, and a uniform was prescribed. The system became odious, and was abolished after being tried for several years. In 1852 a Mons. D'Alfonce became Physical Instructor and under him the exercises continued to be of semi-military character. His services in this department lasted until 1866. Back in the dark ages, when the University had no General Athletic Association and inter-collegiate ball games were as yet unknown, when our benighted forefathers were ignorant of "fouls" and "flukes," when "mass plays" and "curved balls" had not been invented, a pretty sight might have been seen from the foot of the Lawn. As the visitor reached the apex of the triangle, his eye would have rested on a great, circular framed building in the midst of the field below. Near it would have been seen a company of two or three hundred students, all in an easy uniform of blue blouse and grey trousers, drawn up in rank and file. At their head stood a lively Frenchman, an ex-soldier, issuing the word of command. And under his orders this regiment of college boys would go through a series of complex exercises, marching and counter marching, until well nigh every muscle of the body was brought into play—all out in the open air and under the smiling blue heavens. Or, entering the building at an earlier hour, he would have found these same boys turning upon bars, swinging upon ropes, brandishing broadswords or foils, dumbbells or clubs. And then, as the sun descended and before the great bell of the Rotunda rang out its evening summons, he would have heard the Frenchman, in his splendid baritone, raise the chant of the Marseillaise, or some other martial strain, and all the boys would join in, and the great chorus of manly voices would rise harmonious and float to the listening ear upon the fragrant air. The soldierly Frenchman was D'Alfonce, and the days were the days ere athletics had come in to rescue the University from swift and dreadful decadence. —Professor William M. Thornton. For ten years athletics received little attention. In 1876 the late Francis R. Rives of New York (M. A. 1840) gave a sum of money to found a boat club, and Mr. E. R. Squibbs, of the same city, furnished the money to equip a gymnasium. In 1888—twenty-two years after D'Alfonce—an instructor in physical culture was appointed. This was Ellery C. Huntington. His successor was Zelotes W. Coombs, who was followed by John S. Hitchcock, of Amherst, Mass., afterwards an alumnus of the Medical Department. All of these men were trained at Amherst College, and each held the office one year. Dr. William A. Lambeth (M. D. 1891), succeeded them, and still remains in office. THE FAYERWEATHER GYMNASIUM. Out of the Fayerweather gift the University built and equipped the Fayerweather Gymnasium. In addition to athletic appliances, it contains sponge and other baths, a swimming Fayerweather Gymnasium. pool, bowling alleys, ball cage, hundreds of lockers, etc. The architects were Carpenter &amp; Peebles, of Norfolk, Va., the latter an alumnus. The portico is Corinthian and of strict classic proportions, with graceful fluted columns and carved capitals of solid stone, carrying on worthily the Jeffersonian scheme of architecture at the University. The rich red of the bricks gives the prevailing tone of color, harmonizing perfectly with the sandstone trimmings, and making a pleasing contrast with the vivid greens in the grass and foliage which form the setting and background of the picture. And the esplanade, seen on the right, much foreshortened, is not only a pleasing architectural detail, but affords a charming outlook upon the campus at its foot, with its tennis courts, running track, and baseball ground, and the town beyond, and the wooded heights of Monticello in the horizon. —Professor William M. Thornton. Adjoining the gymnasium is the athletic campus, where football and baseball practice takes place and tennis is played. The golf links are between Monroe Hill and the Cemetery. The central athletic organization is known as the General Athletic Association of the University, which is chartered by the legislature. Every matriculated student and every alumnus of the University is a member. It is governed by an advisory board selected from students and resident alumni. The officers are a president, vice-president, secretary, treasurer, and a manager for the football and a manager for the baseball teams. Valuable prizes are offered each session in track and other athletics. The match games of football and baseball are played on the old athletic grounds, southwest of the University. Here many an exciting contest has been waged, while college songs—especially "the good old song of Wah-hoo-wah" (Air, Auld Lang Syne)—urged Virginia to her utmost achievement. The scene is an inspiring one when the rooters are in good voice. Then the academic quiet is shattered by hundreds of voices roaring the "Wah-hoo-wah" of the "long yell," the "Rah!—Rah!—Rah! of the "short," or vociferating in exasperating staccata, "Give 'em the ax, the ax, the ax!" The tumult is defiant or victorious as Virginia's fortunes in the arena at the moment demand. This rooting takes place on the west side of the field, while ladies on the grand-stand at the north end, or in traps on the east, wave Virginia's colors—orange and blue—and in every way display sympathy for her defenders on the gridiron or the diamond. The yells referred to are these: The Long Yell.—Wah-hoo-wah! Wah-hoo-wah! U-ni-v-Vir-gin-i-a! Hoo-rah-ray, Hoo-rah-ray, Ray-ray! U-V-a. The Short Yell.—Rah! Rah! Rah! Rah! Rah! Rah! Rah! Rah! Rah! Virginia, Virginia, Virginia! "The Axe."—Give 'em the axe, the axe, the axe, Give 'em the axe, the axe, the axe! Where? Right in the neck! Right in the neck! Right in the neck! Virginia! * * * Three companies of students were organized at the University at the beginning of the civil war. The first was known as the Southern Guard, and was commanded by Captain Edward Students in the Civil War. S. Hutter of Lynchburg. He afterwards became a major in the Confederate service. The second company was called the Sons of Liberty, Captain James T. Tosh of Roanoke county. Captain Tosh was killed April 7, 1894, by an explosion at Stevensburg, Virginia. The third company was organized in April or May, 1861, with James Parran Crane of Great Mills, Md., later of Leonardtown, in the same State, as captain, and William W. Old, of Norfolk, Va., as lieutenant. On the 4th of July, 1861, this company left the University for Wise's Legion, then operating in what is now West Virginia, and was attached to the Second regiment, commanded by Colonel Henningsen, the Nicaraguan filibuster. The company was disbanded by Secretary Benjamin to enable the members to join commands in their own States. The "Sons of Liberty" (named by Professor Holcombe) wore red shirts, trimmed with black velvet and well bespangled with brass buttons, black doeskin trousers, dark blue caps, and white cross-belts with huge brass buckles. The other company, "The Southern Guard," was distinguished by blue shirts and light blue caps. Arms were secured from Richmond, and consisted of very ancient flintlock muskets (minus the flints), cartridge-boxes (but no cartridges), and bayonet-scabbards. . . . . About dark the battalion marched to Charlottesville, where we found the "Monticello Guards" of that town under arms and awaiting a train from Staunton, on which came the "West Augusta Guards." . . . . As soon as the train arrived, we were loaded in box-cars, and were soon off for the war—sans rations, blankets, overcoats, haversacks, canteens and cartridges, not even a candle to break the total darkness—two car-loads of unprepared but unquenchable enthusiasm. Was there one of us that did not, during the stern trials that soon came to test us, recall with a smile, perhaps a tear, that first boyish rush to duty? —Frank S. Robertson. Nearly all of the alumni of this institution, not disqualified by age or disease, enlisted, and nearly five hundred were killed.* * The list contains the names of four hundred and sixty-three killed. Those who desire to look more closely into the war record of the alumni are referred to "The University Memorial," by the Rev. John Lipscomb Johnson, published by Turnbull Bros., of Baltimore, in 1871. The volume contains over seven hundred pages, and includes biographies of nearly two hundred University of Virginia men who took up arms for the Confederacy. "The list," says the author, "comparises not a few of those who achieved the highest honors of their Alma Mater: twelve masters of arts, two bachelors of arts, nine ALUMNI HALL, EAST RANGE bachelors of law, and two doctors of medicine are found in it, while the Literary Societies are represented by six valedictory orators, four readers, thirteen presidents, and five magazine editors." * * * The University was visited by the Federals under General Sheridan, reaching Charlottesville March 3, 1865, early in the afternoon. A part of the forces camped on Carr's Hill and Sheridan's Raid. in the vicinity, but the larger part around Charlottesville. Sheridan's headquarters were the house on the east corner of Park and High streets. The University requested protection and an official guard was promptly posted in and around the precincts. On the 6th of March the Federals left by way of the Scottsville and the Lynchburg roads. Before their arrival the silver and some other valuables of certain of the professors' families were confided to Henry Martin's care. He buried them in a box in the bell room where they escaped discovery. Some plundering was done—a few horses and all the provender were taken away, but on the whole little damage was inflicted. General Sheridan caused a search to be made at the University for arms which were reported to be concealed within the grounds, but none were found. In the mountains near by an old cannon, a six pounder, was discovered where it had been hidden some six months before. It was destroyed. * * * There is one little spot within the five hundred broad acres that surround the University which appeals pathetically to all lovers of the place. Lying to one side, down a pathway The Cemetery, overshadowed by noble oaks, over against a green, embowered wood, is a miniature God'sacre overrun with white and blue periwinkle, separated from the noisy highway where impatient feet pass all day long, and gathering to itself a solemn calm from the separation, most tranquilizing to the contemplative observer. Here, in its small enclosure, in sight of the gleaming copper dome of the Rotunda, under the shelter of the noble elevation from which rises the great McCormick observatory, exists apart and in charming seclusion the one spot to which old lovers of the University turn most lovingly, the resting-place of a little world of people once associated with all the light and laughter about the University. . . . . It is a little Westminster Abbey in the woods where men, famous in the annals of the University, sleep a perfect sleep among blossoming vines and ivied cedars, attended ever in their sleep by the loving ministrations of the living. Full it is of honored and distinguished names, yet the place itself is not larger than that which is covered by many a great European cathedral with its far-stretching aisles and apse, here represented only by the vaulting heavens and the vanishing distances of columned, overshadowing trees most full at times of mellifluous voices; full it is, too, of children's tombs and of unknown folk, and small snow-white bits of marble that seem to supplicate a glance from the passer-by. . . . . The reverent spectator will be struck on entering the burial ground with the simplicity of the monumental marbles. Simple crosses, the flamelike obelisk of granite or polished stone, columns surmounted by urns, rounded head-stones without symbols of any kind, three or four old English tombs with carven sides, and engraved horizontal slabs, bits of glimmering stone with children's names engraved; these are all. Nothing proud, little that is pretentious, desecrates this ivy-mantled THE WALK TO THE CEMETERY. sanctuary of the University dead who have stepped aside here for a brief rest till the resurrection-morn, like tired travellers sitting for a moment by the wayside, "pilgrims of eternity."* * Dr. James A. Harrison in Alumni Bulletin. Beside this embowered God's-acre is another of about equal extent. It is the silent bivouac of men who wore the grey—Georgia Volunteers, rebels from the Carolinas, Mississippi, The Soldier's Cemetery. Alabama and far Louisiana. Some of them fell mortally wounded at Chancellorsville and some at the Wilderness, and they all sleep literally under the sod and the dew and the great oaks, for the brick wall which separates the beds of these victims of a great political upheaval from the last resting places of dead professors and their congeners shuts out the periwinkle, the rose, the shrubbery and the trees which beautify the spot sacred to the repose of those who have yielded to mere mortality. But the rose is not always wanting in the Soldiers' Cemetery. The 30th of May, or some day about that time in spring, is dedicated to the memory of the fallen, and the people repair to this little cemetery at the foot of Mt. Jefferson to lay many a rose reverently above the ashes of the soldier dead. And in the center of the ground stands a monument to the heroes of 1861-65 (a testimonial as well to the noble women of this community who built it "for remembrance"), an heroic figure in bronze, by Buberl, nobly typifying the Confederate soldier. "Fate" says the inscription, "denied them victory, but crowned them with glorious immortality." * * * The "Calathump" in its worst form has probably no late counterpart in student life, and nothing approaching it happens anywhere except occasionally in some wild mining town The Calathump. on the frontier, where cowboys, "paid off," and, with a long period of enforced soberness behind them, get blind drunk, take the town in charge and "paint it red," to the music of their six-shooters in violent irruption. In the early years of the University, when disorder was frequent, the calathump was often resorted to as the easiest and safest means of annoying professors whose "walk and conversation" displeased. Masked students paraded the grounds, fired their revolvers, and made night hideous to those who remained indoors and dangerous to those who ventured out. It was during a calathump that Professor J. A. G. Davis, at the time chairman of the faculty, was killed by a student from whose face he had snatched the mask. The shooting occurred about ten o'clock on the night of November 12, 1840, where stands the large maple near the north column of Pavilion X, East Lawn, at present the home of Professor Lile. When life at the University settled down to a steadier existence the calathump became a thing of the past. It is said the last one of any moment was in 1856. Then Dr. Socrates Maupin addressed the college mob from the portico of the Rotunda, and it took his advice reluctantly and dispersed. The "Dyke," often spoken of as the same, was really a very different thing. The one was an exhibition, usually, of bad feeling, while the other was a characteristic ebulition The Dyke. of undergraduate spirits and a reigning terror to collegians who were "addicted to calico," as "going to see the girls" was and still is called. The practice was probably abused on some occasions, and in the end public sentiment prevailed against it. However, the purposes of dykers, while not conventionally benevolent, were not incompatible with a boisterous good humor, and the victim was never regarded with less favor, but rather more because of the distinction which had somewhat the value of a scar received by a German student in an affair of honor. The following is a truthful limning of a dyking scene:* * By Charles W. Coleman, Jr. Suddenly the still, crisp atmosphere was pierced with a hideous cry. Dyke! From the deep shadows beneath the arches, out of the alleys, and, in short, from every conceivable direction surged a crowd of students, shouting like mad, blowing tin horns and waving torches above their heads. A cold chill traversed my backbone with lightning rapidity, and my first impulse was to step back into my room, the door of which I had not yet closed, but Will and Walter held me firmly by the arm. Will chuckled softly. In an instant the cause of his heretofore unaccountable behavior flashed upon me. With a nervous grin and a ghastly effort at pleasantry I turned my face towards him and said, "Et tu, Brute!" He laughed and clutched my arm more securely than ever. By this time was collected before my door a screaming, hallooing, laughing mob, more hideous to a collegian in a swallow-tail coat than the Reign of Terror was to the royal family of France. There was nothing left for me to do but literally grin and endure it. Closely pinioned, a half dozen torch-bearers circling around me, the rest of the crowd gathered behind me, I was borne off along the centre of the lawn at a brisk trot. The torch-bearers went before, the players on instruments followed after; in the midst were the dykers playing with coal scuttles. And oh! those horns. The very bull of Bashan would have fled ignominiously before them. On we went, our ranks swelling every moment. I was marched to the Rotunda steps; six torch-bearers took their places in a line on either side of me; a double line of torchbearers formed from the porch to the foot of the steps. The muscles about my mouth were attacked with a twitching that was exceedingly unpleasant, not to say embarrassing. The order was given for silence and the removal of hats, and Walter, in a stentorian voice, announced me as the orator of the evening. With a sickening sensation about my chest, I made an effort to speak, WALK TO THE POSTOFFICE—Below Wash. Hall which only resulted in a great gulp. The din of horns, yells and coal scuttles, accompanied by a waving of torches which followed this attempt, gave me a moment's respite; and at the next pause I was able to articulate, "Gentlemen—" Again the deafening chorus arose. "It gives me great pleasure—" The loud and continued applause that ensued deprived me of the last vestige of self-possession, and I was only half-conscious of being rushed down the steps, along the arcades and being shoved pell-mell into the front door of the fair sender of my violet-scented, cream-tinted note. In the hall I encountered "papa and mama," who condoled with me upon my somewhat bedraggled condition, and the latter treated my opera hat, of which I had lately been so proud, to an application of the clothes-brush. With such assistance I was able to present a genteel appearance when my fair partner entered the room. * * * It is not easy to avoid some confusion in an endeavor to make a list of the professors and their assistants from the opening of the University to the present. This difficulty, which grows Schools and Professors. out of the development of the schools and the subdivision of some of them, has not prevented an attempt to accomplish a useful and interesting result. What follows is an effort to give all the schools that have ever been in existence in WILLIAM E. PETERS, LL. D. MILTON W. HUMPHREYS, M. A., PH. D., LL. D. this institution, the date of the establishment of each, and the professors and instructors who have taught in them: Ancient Languages (Latin and Greek—Established 1825)—Professors: George Long, 1825-28; Gessner Harrison, 1828-56. Assistants: John A. Broadus, 1851-53; Edward S. Joynes, 1853-56; William Dinwiddie, 1855-56; Thomas U. Dudley, 1860-61; James M. Boyd, 1867-68; Henry Clay Brock, 1870-71. Charles A. Young (Hebrew) since 1898. Latin (1856)—Gessner Harrison, 1856-59; Lewis M. Coleman, 1859-61; Basil L. Gildersleeve, 1861-65; and W. E. Peters, since 1865. Assistants: William J. Bingham, 1880-81; R. M. Smith, 1881-82; William H. Perkinson, 1882-83; James W. Kern, 188486; John Staige Davis, Jr., 1886-87; Robert S. Radford, 1887-93; James H. Paxton, 1893-96; C. C. Wright since 1896. Greek and Hebrew (1856) — Basil L. Gildersleeve, 1856-76; Thomas R. Price, 1876-82; W. H. Wheeler, 1882-87; M. W. Humphreys since 1887. Assistants: C. H. Fauntleroy, 1881-85; James JAMES A. HARRISON, L. H. D., LL. D. RICHARD H. WILSON, M. A., PH. D. W. Kern, 1885-86; John Staige Davis, Jr., 1886-87; Robert S. Radford, 1887-93; James H. Paxton, 1893-96. Modern Languages (1825) — George Blaettermann, 1825-40; Charles Kraitsir, 1841-44; M. Schele De Vere, 1844-95; Joachim Reinhard, acting professor of French and German, 1895-96; James WILLIAM H. ECHOLS, B. S., C. E. JAMES MORRIS PAGE, A. M., PH. D. A. Harrison (Romance Languages), 1895-96; English, French, and Spanish, 1896-98; Teutonic Languages, since 1898; William H. Perkinson, German and Italian, 1896-98; Richard H. Wilson, Romance Languages, since 1899. Assistants: Tutors: J. Hervé, 183133; Joseph Togno, 1840; Paul Piodal, 1840-41. Assistant instructors: Ernest Volger, 1851-53; S. E. W. Becker, 1853-56; Joseph Wall, 1856-57; A. von Fischerz, 1857-60; G. Baillard, 185859; Gaetano Lanza, 1856-61; William C. Grossman, 1872-73; Fred. M. Page, 1879-81; Julian Taylor, 1881-85; William H. Perkinson, 1885-89; J. Elliott Heath, 1891-92; Emerson H. George, 1892-93; R. E. Lee Dinwiddie, 1893-94; William H. Faulkner, 1894-95; Hugh M. Blain, English and French, 1897-98; F. H. Abbot, 1898-99. Mathematics (1825)—Thomas Hewitt Key, 1825-27; Charles Bonnycastle, 1827-40; J. J. Sylvester, 1840-41; Edward H. Courtenay, WILLIAM M. THORNTON, LL. D. FRANCIS H. SMITH. M. A., LL. D. 1842-53; Albert T. Bledsoe, 1854-63; Robert T. Massie, 1861-62; Francis H. Smith, 1863-65; Pike Powers was professor by temporary appointment from 1840 to 1841, and again from 1842 to 1843, and Alexander Nelson from 1853 to 1854; Charles S. Venable 186596 (now emeritus); W. H. Echols since 1896; James M. Page, adjunct, 1896-98, and associate since 1898. Assistants: Francis H. Smith, 1851-53; William Dinwiddie, 1853-55; Edward B. Smith, 1855-57; Robert T. Massie, 1857-59; James G. Clark, 1857-58; John M. Strother, 1858-61; Howe P. Cochran, 1859-61; Gaetano Lanza; Jr., 1869-71; William M. Thornton, 1871-73; Joshua W. Gore, 1881-82; R. D. Bohannon, 1884-87; James S. Miller, 188790; Harrison Randolph, 1890-95; Hopson O. Murfee, 1895-96; Edward O. Lovett, lecturer, 1896-97. Applied Mathematics (1867)—Leopold J. Boeck, 1867-75; William M. Thornton, adjunct, 1875-83, professor since 1883; William H. Echols, adjunct, 1891-96. Assistants: John W. C. Davis, 187072; Albert Folke, 1872-74; Henry Rose Carter, 1874-75; Julio R. Santos, 1875-77; Bernard R. Guest, 1884-88; John K. Peebles, 1888-90. Natural Philosophy (1825)—Charles Bonnycastle, 1825-28; Robert M. Patterson, 1828-35; William B. Rogers, 1835-53; Francis H. Smith since 1853. Chemistry (1825)—John P. Emmet, 1825-42; Robert E. Rogers, 1842-52; J. Lawrence Smith, 1852-53; Socrates Maupin, 1853-71; John W. Mallet since 1872. Assistant, David K. Tuttle, 1858-62. JOHN W. MALLET, M. D., PH. D., LL. D., F. R. S. FRANCIS P. DUNNINGTON, B. S. Chemical Technology and Agricultural Science (1867)—John W. Mallet, 1867-68. Analytical, Industrial and Agricultural Chemistry (1868)—John W. Mallet, 1868-72. General and Applied Chemistry (1872)—John W. Mallet, 187284; Frank P. Dunnington, acting, 1884-85. General and Industrial Chemistry (1885)—John W. Mallet since 1885. Analytical and Agricultural Chemistry (1885)—Frank P. Dunnington since 1885. Natural History and Agriculture (1872)—John R. Page, 1872-87. Natural History and Geology(1878)—William M. Fontaine since 1879. Moral Philosophy (1825)—George Tucker, 1825-45; William H. McGuffey, 1845-73; Noah K. Davis since 1873. NOAH K. DAVIS, PH. D., LL. D. WILLIAM M. FONTAINE, M. A. History and General Literature (1857)—George Frederick Holmes, 1857-82. Historical Science (1882)—George Frederick Holmes, 1882-97; RICHARD HEATH DABNEY, M. A., PH. D. CHARLES W. KENT, M. A., PH. D. Richard H. Dabney, assistant, 1889-90; adjunct, 1890-95; associate, 1895-97. Historical and Economical Science (1897)—Richard H. Dabney since 1897. English Language and Literature (1882)—James M. Garnett, 1882-93. English Literature (1892)—Charles W. Kent since 1893. English Language (1893)—James M. Garnett, 1893-96. ORMOND STONE, M. A. ALBERT H. TUTTLE, M. S. Practical Astronomy (1881)—Ormond Stone since 1882. Assistants: F. P. Leavenworth, 1882-88; Nicholas M. Parrish, 1888-93; E. O. Lovett, 1893-94; Gordon M. Buck, 1894-96; Herbert R. Morgan, 1896-99; Everett O. Eastwood, 1899—. AUGUSTUS H. BUCKMASTER, M. D. JOHN STAIGE DAVIS, M. A., M. D. Biology and Agriculture (1887)—Albert H. Tuttle since 1888. Medicine (1825)—Robley Dunglison, 1825-33; Alfred T. Magill, 1833-37; R. E. Griffith 1837-39; Henry Howard, 1839-67. Medicine and Obstetrics (1867)—James F. Harrison, 1867-79. Medicine, Obstetrics and Medical Jurisprudence (1879)—James F. Harrison, 1879-86; William C. Dabney, 1886-90. Obstetrics and Practice of Medicine (1890)—William C. Dabney, 1890-94; Augustus H. Buckmaster, acting, 1894-95; professor, 1895-96. Gynecology, Obstetrics and Practice of Medicine (1896)—Augustus H. Buckmaster since 1896. Pathology and Hygiene (1893)—John Staige Davis, instructor, 1893-94; adjunct, 1894-99; professor since 1899. Anatomy and Surgery (1827)—Thomas Johnson, demonstrator, 1827-31; professor, 1831-34; Augustus L. Warner, 1834-37; James L. Cabell, 183749; John Staige Davis (senior), demonstrator, 1845-49; lecturer and demonstrator, 1849-53; lecturer on Anatomy, Materia Medica and Therapeutics, 1853-56; B. W. Allen, demonstrator, 1853-65; J. Edgar Chancellor, demonstrator, 1865-72; William B. Towles, demonstrator, 1872-85; acting professor, 1885-86; professor, 188693; William G. Christian, demonstrator, 1889-93. WILLIAM G. CHRISTIAN, M. D. Comparative Anatomy, Physiology and Surgery (1849)—James L. Cabell, 1849-61. Anatomy, Materia Medica, Therapeutics and Botany (1856)—John Staige Davis, 1856-61; B. W. Allen, demonstrator, 1853-61. Anatomy and Materia Medica (1861)—John Staige Davis, 186185; William B. Towles, acting, 1885-86; professor, 1886-93; B. W. Allen, demonstrator, 1861-65; J. Edgar Chancellor, demonstrator, 1865-72; William B. Towles, demonstrator, 1872-85. Anatomy and Surgery (1893)—William G. Christian since 1893. Douglas Tardy, demonstrator, 1885-87; Richard H. Whitehead, 1887-89; William G. Christian, 1889-93; Halstead S. Hedges, 189397; Arlie C. Jones, 1897-99; James B. Bullitt since 1899. Physiology and Surgery (1861)—James L. Cabell, 1861-89; Paul B. Barringer, 1889-94. Physiology and Materia Medica (1894)—Paul B. Barringer since 1894. Law (1826)—John Tayloe Lomax, 1826-30; John A. G. Davis, 1830-40; N. P. Howard, 1840-41; H. St. George Tucker, 1841-45; WILLIAM MINOR LILE, B. L. RALEIGH C. MINOR, M. A., B. L. John B. Minor, 1845-95; James P. Holcombe, adjunct, 1851-54; professor, 1854-61; Stephen O. Southall, 1866-84; James H. Gilmore, 1885-96; William Minor Lile since 1893; John B. Minor, Jr., CHARLES A. GRAVES, M. A., LL. D. instructor, 1890-93; Raleigh C. Minor, instructor, 1893-95; adjunct, 1895-99; professor since 1899; Walter D. Dabney, professor, 189599; Charles A. Graves since 1899. Physical instructor, William A. Lambeth since 1891. Chairmen of the Faculty.—George Tucker, 1825, 1828, and 183233; Robley Dunglison, 1826 and 1828-30; John Tayloe Lomax 1827; Robert M. Patterson, 1830-32; Charles Bonnycastle 1833-35; John PAUL B. BARRINGER, M. D., LL. D., Present Chairman of the Faculty. A. G. Davis, 1835-37 and 1839-40; Gessner Harrison 1837-39, 1840-42 and 1847-54; H. St. George Tucker, 1842-44; William B. Rogers, 1844-45; Edward H. Courtenay, 1845-46; James L. Cabell, 1846-47; Socrates Maupin, 1854-70; Charles S. Venable, 1870-73 and 1886-88 (with William M. Thornton vice-chairman during this last term); James F. Harrison, 1873-86; William M. Thornton, 1888-96 and Paul B. Barringer since 1896. The chairmen for 1825, 1826, 1827 and 1828 were appointed by the Faculty; their successors, by the Board of Visitors. Secretaries to the Faculty.—Robley Dunglison, 1825; John P. Emmet, 1826; William Wertenbaker, 1826-31; Gessner Harrison, 183132; Thomas Johnson, 1832-34; Alfred T. Magill, 1834-36; William JAMES B. BAKER, Secretary of the Faculty. FREDERICK W. PAGE. Librarian. Wertenbaker, 1836-81; F. W. Page, 1881-82; William A. Winston, 1882-86; James B. Baker since 1886. * * * THOMAS H. CARTER, Proctor. In administrative capacities and in the lecture-room men of the first order of talent have served the University. Administration Officers. The list of her Rectors and Visitors is, in the main, a roll of great men, and it is recorded here with a pardonable feeling of pride. Rectors.—Thomas Jefferson, 1819-26; James Madison, 1826-34; Joseph C. Cabell, 1834-36 and again from 1845-56; Chapman Johnson, 1836-45; Andrew Stevenson, 1856-57; Thomas Jefferson Randolph, 1857-64; Thomas L. Preston, 1864-65; Alexander Rives, 1865-66; B. Johnson Barbour, 1866-72; R. G. H. Kean, 1872-75; A. H. H. Stuart, 1875-82; Wyatt M. Elliott, 1882-83; William Lamb (pro tem.), 1883-84; W. Roane Ruffin, 1884-86; A. H. H. Stuart, 1886-87; J. L. Marye, 1887-90; W. C. N. Randolph, 1890-97; Armistead C. Gordon, 1897 to February 28, 1898; Charles P. Jones from 1898. Visitors since 1819.—Thomas Jefferson, 1819-26; Joseph C. Cabell, 1819-56; James Madison, 1819-34; Chapman Johnson, 1819-45; Robert B. Taylor, 1819-22; James Breckinridge, 1819-33; John H. Cocke, 1819-52; George Loyall, 1822-28; James Monroe, 1826-31; William C. Rives, 1828-29 and 1834-49; Thomas Jefferson Randolph, 1829-53 and 1857-64; William H. Brodnax, 1831-34; James M. Mason, 1833-55; Samuel Taylor, 1834-45; Andrew Stevenson, 1845-57; R. M. T. Hunter, 1845-52; Thomas L. Preston, 1849-52 and 1864-65; William Lucas, 1852-56; John Y. Mason, 1852-53; Henry A. Wise, 1852-55; Andrew McDonald 1852-54; Fleming B. Miller, 1852-56; Robert A. Thompson, 1852-53; James Lawrence Carr, 1853-59; William J. Robertson, 1853-59; Harrison B. Tomlin, 1853-56; Sherrard Clemens, 1854-56; John R. Edmunds, 1856-64; William T. Joynes, 1856-59; Muscoe R. H. Garnett, 1855-59; John B. Baldwin, 1856-64; John Randolph Tucker, 1856-59; James Neeson, 1856-64; Roger A. Pryor, 1859-62; Patrick H. Aylett, 1859-64; William H. Terrell, 1860-64; George W. Summers, 1860-62; Franklin Minor, 1859-64; Allen T. Caperton, 1862-64; John M. Daniel, 1864-65; Douglas H. Gordon, 1862-64; Thomas S. Flournoy, 1864-65; George W. Randolph, 186465; R. H. Cunningham, 1864-65; F. W. M. Holliday, 1864-65; William Frazier, 1864-65; James W. Sheffey, 1864-65; John Brannon, 1864-65; Alexander Rives, 1865-66; B. Johnson Barbour, 1865-73; Thomas J. Pretlow, 1865-72; Marmaduke Johnson, 186572; Samuel H. Lewis, 1865-72; John R. Woods, 1865-72; Charles L. Mosby, 1865-67; R. W. Hughes, 1866-72; Samuel Watts, 186672; William E. M. Word, 1867-72; Joseph T. Campbell, 1872-76; Richard H. Baker, 1872-75; William H. Berkeley, 1872-76; Thomas Beckwith, 1872-76; R. G. H. Kean, 1872-76; E. H. Montague, 1872-76; Moses Walton, 1872-76; Micajah Woods, 1872-76; Isaac H. Carrington, 1873-76; G. P. Scarborough, 1875-76, A. H. H. Stuart, 1876-82 and '86; Thomas S. Bocock, 1876-82; Holmes Conrad, 1876-82 and '86; James H. Gilmore, 1876-82; John Goode, Jr., 1876-82; John Hart, 1876-80; W. C. N. Randolph, 1876-82 and '86; Paul Whitehead, 1876-82; John L. Marye, 1876-82 and 1886-93; John F. Lay, 1880-82; Wyatt M. Elliott, 1882-84; F. S. Blair, 1882-86; T. T. Fauntleroy, Jr., 1882-83; G. W. Hansborough, 1882-86; William Lamb, 1882-85; John Paul, 1882-84; W. Roane Ruffin, 1882-86; John W. Bell, 1882-86; Daniel Ruggles, 1882-85; Hugh M. Taylor, 1883-86: George T. Barbee, 1883-86; E. C. Burks, 1884-86; V. D. Groner, 1885-86; William Byrd, 1885-86; Holmes Conrad, 1886-90, and 1892-96; W. H. Payne, 1886-89, Burr P. Noland, 1887-89; W. H. Bolling, 1887-92; Mason Gordon, 1887-92; W. Gordon McCabe, 1887-96; Legh R. Watts, 1887-98; R. G. H. Kean, 1890-94; Camm Patteson, 1890-97; J. Marshall McCormick, 1890-98; Basil B. Gordon, 1892-96; Thomas S. Martin, 1892-96; Armistead C. Gordon, 1896-98; R. Tate Irvine since 1896; Henry T. Wickham, 1897-98; Joseph Bryan since 1898; Daniel Harmon since 1898; W. B. McIlwaine, 1898-99; M. Q. Holt, 1898-1900; Algernon B. Chandler since 1898: Henry H. Downing since 1898; Carter Glass since 1898: George W. Miles since 1898, and Walton R. Moore since February, 1900. Secretaries to the Board—Peter Minor, 1819—; Nicholas P. Trist, 1826-29; John A. G. Davis, 1829-30; Frank Carr, 1830-51; St. George Tucker, 1851-53; R. T. W. Duke, 1853-65; William Wertenbaker, 1865-70; James D. Jones, 1870-82; William A. Winston, 1882-86; James D. Jones since 1886. Proctors.—Arthur P. Brockenbrough, 1825-31; John A. Carr, 1831-32; William G. Pendleton, 1832-36; Willis H. Woodley 183645; George W. Spooner (pro tem.), 1845-46; William J. Kemper, 1846-53; Robert R. Prentis, 1853-65; John E. Johnson, 1866-67; Green Peyton, 1867-82; James K. Campbell, 1882-86; Green Peyton, 1886-97; Thomas H. Carter since 1897. William A. Pratt was the first Superintendent of Grounds, and served from 1858 to 1865. In the last named year the office was merged with that of Proctor. Alexander Garrett, whose portrait hangs in the court-room in Charlottesville, was bursar from 1849 to 1851, and William A. Bibb from 1851 to 1861. The office was then abolished. It was revived in 1882 and W. L. Maupin was bursar until 1884, when it was again abolished. * * * The commanding form of "Uncle Henry," the janitor, is one of the familiar figures at the University. He has rung the summons to lecture to two generations of students, his term Henry Martin. of service as full janitor having begun upon the death of "Doctor" Smith, who died after thirty-three years of service, full of years and such honors as the sincere regard and trust of his superiors, and lies buried in the University Cemetery, where he was laid in 1861, probably wrapped in his long blue coat, which was adorned with abundant brass buttons. Henry Martin's memory is marvelous, especially in recalling the names and faces of visitors who were once students at this institution. His manner is urbane and dignified and his probity perfect—in short, he is a fine old colored gentleman. He has been connected with the University since 1847, and his familiarity with the place and his knowledge of the persons who are still here, and of many who are gone, make him a pleasant cicerone to those who come sight-seeing. * * * In text and illustration attempt has been made to show the extent and beauty of "The Academic Village," while the spirit and compulsion of the student's environment have not been passed over. What is strongly felt by every man of impressionable soul who has studied here has not found adequate expression, of course. The influence and achievements of those who have gone forth cannot be estimated even by one who paces these studious precincts, but if any doubt that they have been of surpassing merit let him study the history, civil and military, of this country. For seventy-five years men have left these halls stronger in character and mental equipment than they entered them, taking increase to the sum of the moral and mental wealth which exalts a nation, and returning to the Alma Mater a generous tribute of prestige. The dignity of age is hers, while naught of the beauty and strength of her youth has departed. It is the firm conviction of her children that the coming years will add to without withering the infinite variety of her virtues.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INDEX. Alumni, 12; Association of, 57; orators, 58, 59; presidents, 58, 59. Ancient languages, 70. Annals of Mathematics, 55. Annex, the, 35. "Arcade Echoes," 54, 55. Athletics, 60-62. Auditorium, 16, 20. Brooks Museum, the, 42, 43. Bulletin, Alumni, 55. Bursars, 82. Bust, Minor, 32; Poe, 33. Cabell, Joseph C., 5. Calathump, the, 67. Carr's Hill, 45. Cemetery, Soldiers', 66; University, 65. Central College, 5. Chairmen of Faculty, 78. Chapel, the, 39, 40. Chaplains (1829-96), 41. Clock, Jefferson, 38, 39; Levy, 39. Clubs, 59, 60. College Topics, 55. Collegian, the, 53. Columbian Literary Society, 52. Corks and Curls, 55. Davis, J. A. G., assassinated, 67. Dawson's Row, 44. Dyke, the, 68. Fayerweather Gymnasium, 61, 62. Federals, visit of, 64, 65. Fire, the, of 1895, 14. Fraternities, Greek letter, 59, 60. Guard, the Southern, 63. Harrison Trophy, 47, 48. Honor System, 14. Hospital, 44. Jefferson, 26; statue of, 31. Jefferson Society, 46; Medalists, 48, 49, 50 final presidents, 47. Laboratory, Chemical, 44; Rouss, 16. Lafayette, visit to University, 27. Lawns, the, 21, 22, 24, 25. Liberty, Sons of, 63. Librarians (1825-1900) 33, 34. Library, 29; old, 22. Literary societies, 46, 52. Magazine, the University, 53. McCormick Observatory, 43. Medalists, Jeff., 49, 50; Magazine, 56, 57; Wash., 51, 52. Medals, 47, 49. Medical Hall, 44. Monroe Hill, 45. Observatory, the McCormick, 43. Parthenon Literary Society, 52. Philomathean Literary Society, 52. Philosophical Society, 53. Poe, 20, 24, 33. Portraits, 18, 30. Proctors (1820-1900), 81, 82. Professors, 70-77; early, 5. Quadrangle, the, 16. Randall Dormitory, 45. Ranges, 23. Rectors, 80. Religion at University, 40. Rotunda, the, 26, 28, 29. School of Athens, 35, 38. Schools and Professors, 70-77. Sheridan's raid, 64, 65. Societies, Literary, 46-49, 52; ribbon, etc., 59, 60. "Sons of Liberty," 63. Tablet, commemorative, 18. Temperance Hall, 45. Visitors, Board of, 80, 81. War, students in, 63, 64. Washington Society, 50, 52; final presidents, 50, 51; medalists, 51, 52. Yells, the, 62, 63. Y. M. C. A., 40; Hall, 36. "GOOD LUCK" is the only brand of BAKING POWDER sold in Solid car-load Lots. It is Wholesome, Healthful, and Highest in Leavening Power. More "GOOD LUCK" sold in the South than all other brands combined. Manufactured by THE SOUTHERN MANUFACTURING CO., Richmond, Va.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">S. C. Chancellor, Pharmacist and Druggist UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA. A full line of Drugs, Medicines, Chemicals, Mineral Waters and Students' Supplies. PHYSICIANS' PRESCRIPTIONS CAREFULLY COMPOUNDED. CHARLOTTESVILLE (VA.) WOOLEN MILLS MANUFACTURERS OF ALL KINDS OF SUPERIOR UNIFORM CLOTHS CONSISTING OF DARK AND SKY BLUE AND CADET GRAY KERSEYS, MELTONS AND DOESKINS FOR STREET CAR, RAILROAD, Letter Carrier, Band, POLICE, MILITARY AND SOCIETY EQUIPMENT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Anderson Bros. Booksellers AT . . . . ENTRANCE TO THE GROUNDS. To the University Of Virginia UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA CHARLOTTESVILLE, VA. IRVINE &amp; STEVENS CLOTHIERS MEN'S FURNISHERS TAILORS CHARLOTTESVILLE, VA. ESTABLISHED 1881. JAMES F. HARLAN Wholesale and Retail Grocer... 214 W. Main Street CHARLOTTESVILLE VIRGINIA</field>
      <field name="fulltext">?????? ..PANTOPS ACADEMY.. NEAR CHARLOTTESVILLE, VA. (P. O.) Prepares for College, University or Business. Beautifully situated on the eminence opposite Monticello. Ample tract of 373 acres; formerly owned by Thomas Jefferson and named by him from two Greek words—"All-Seeing." Purest air. Best sanitary arrangements. Full staff of superior teachers. Kindly home influence. Thoroughly equipped. Undenominational. Gymnasium and Bowling Alley. Telephonic and telegraphic communication. U. S. Suburban Delivery of Mail. Number of pupils limited. Also a Summer School. For Catalogue address JOHN R. SAMPSON, A. M., Principal. The Bank of Albemarle, CHARLOTTESVILLE, VA. DISCOUNT DAYS, TUESDAY AND FRIDAY. JAMES D. JONES, President, C. D. FISHBURNE, Cashier. S. V. SOUTHALL, Vice-President, R. T. Martin, Teller. T. P. CARVER, DEALER IN ...Fire Creek Coal, Best Lump Splint... AND Highest Grades of Anthracite, KINDLING AND SAWED WOOD. CHARLOTTESVILLE, VA. W. B. PALMER &amp; CO. FOREIGN STEAMSHIP AGENTS and Commission Merchants, 1321 CARY STREET, - - - RICHMOND, VA. AGENTS FOR International Navigation Company — AND — Atlantic Transport Company.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">J. B. &amp; W. H. WOOD CLOTHIERS, Tailors, Hatters and Gents' Furnishers. Suits Made to Order. CHARLOTTESVILLE, VIRGINIA. James Perley &amp; Sons, Student Furniture a specialty. THE LEADING FURNITURE AND UNDERTAKING ESTABLISHMENT, 101-108 West Main Street, CHARLOTTESVILLE, VA. LYNCHBURG OFFICE: 816 Main St. RICHMOND OFFICE: 914 E. Main St. J. P. Bell Company WHOLESALE STATIONERS, BLANK BOOK MAKERS AND PRINTERS, LYNCHBURG, VIRGINIA.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">LARGEST CAPITAL OF ANY BANK TRUST COMPANY IN THE SOUTH ATLANTIC STATES Richmond Trust and Safe Deposit Co. RICHMOND, VIRGINIA. CAPITAL__________$1,000,000 Does a General Trust Company Business. DEPOSITS RECEIVED AND INTEREST ALLOWED THEREON. President, JNO. SKELTON WILLIAMS. Vice-Presidents, JAS. H. DOOLEY. FRANK A. DAVENPORT. HENRY L. CABELL. Treasurer, LEWIS D. CRENSHAW, Jr. CORRESPONDENCE SOLICITED.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Norfolk and Carolina Chemical Company BRANCH VIRGINIA-CAROLINA CHEMICAL COMPANY HIGH-GRADE FERTILIZERS You cannot farm successfully without the use of Commercial Fertilizers. We make the best, and sell low enough to be within the reach of every farmer "STAR BRAND" and "OWL BRAND" SPECIAL TOBACCO FERTILIZERS "VIRGINIA" DARK LEAF TOBACCO GROWER AND OTHER STANDARD BRANDS FOR ALL CROPS. ADDRESS Norfolk &amp; Carolina Chemical Co. CRENSHAW WAREHOUSE, Richmond, Virginia.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">John P. Branch, President. John Kerr Branch, Vice-President. John F. Glenn, Cashier. Capital, $200,000 Surplus, $280,000 Undivided Profits, $62,000 UNITED STATES, CITY AND STATE DEPOSITORY. Merchants National Bank No. 1754. RICHMOND, VA. COMPARATIVE STATEMENT FOR THE FOLLOWING YEARS: ASSETS. CLOSE OF BUSINESS ON Dec. 31, 1879 Dec. 31, 1884 Dec. 31, 1889 Dec. 31, 1894 Dec. 30, 1899 Time and Demand Loans $346,862 73 $655,401 83 $743,704 72 $1,118,703 50 $1,176,070 00 Real Estate, Fixtures, &amp;c. 2,072 96 55,668 24 60,000 00 79,500 00 75,780 42 5 % Redempt'n Fund 9,000 00 9,000 00 2,700 00 8,220 00 6,165 00 United States Bonds 200,000 00 200,000 00 485,000 00 400,000 00 972,000 00 Premium U. S. Bonds 4,162 53 15,875 00 70,000 00 7,000 00 45,000 00 Miscellaneous Bonds 24,012 47 51,269 50 7,861 83 90,267 87 416,262 78 Due from Banks and Bankers 50,652 80 162,440 76 85,690 51 224,510 41 552,935 42 Cash 87,370 90 141,697 96 178,683 49 191,241 99 543,054 90 $724,134 39 $1,291,353 29 $1,633,640 55 $2,119,443 77 $3,787,268 52 LIABILITIES. CLOSE OF BUSINESS ON Dec. 31, 1879 Dec. 31, 1884 Dec. 31, 1889 Dec. 31, 1894 Dec. 30, 1899 Capital Stock $200,000 00 $200,000 00 $200,000 00 $200,000 00 $200,000 00 Surplus and Undivided Profits 17,247 81 90,198 39 130,509 06 228,275 07 342,647 83 Circulation 180,000 00 175,000 00 54,000 00 180,000 00 123,300 00 Deposits 326,886 58 826,154 90 1,249,131 49 1,511,168 70 3,121,320 69 $724,134 39 $1,291,353 29 $1,633,640 55 $2,119,443 77 $3,787,268 52 Business Paper Discounted for Customers on favorable terms. A specialty made of Collections in Virginia, West Virginia, Kentucky, Tennessee and North Carolina Daily and direct Communication with over three-fourths of the Banking Points in Virginia. Being the largest depository for banks between Baltimore and New Orleans, this Bank offers superior facilities for DIRECT AND QUICK COLLECTIONS. Correspondence solicited. We would like to have your business.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Seaboard Air Line .... RAILWAY .... JACKSONVILLE TAMPA HAVANA CUBA PORTO RICO NEW YORK ST. AUGUSTINE PALM BEACH MIAMI FLORIDA EAST COAST ATLANTA NEW ORLEANS ALL POINTS SOUTH and SOUTHWEST. E. ST. JOHN, Vice-President &amp; Gen'l Manager. H. W. B. GLOVER, Traffic Manager. L. S. ALLEN, General Pass. Agent.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Daily Times RICHMOND, VA. Subscription Rates, per Year, $5.00 For Nine Months, 3.75 For Six Months, 2.50 Per Month, .50 The next twelve months will cover the Presidential and Congressional Campaigns, and include the Inaugural of the President and the close of the second session of the Fifty-Sixth Congress. THE DAILY TIMES is peculiarly fitted to cover the entire field with its full Associated Press reports; its large staff of Special Correspondents throughout the State; and its Staff Correspondents at all the conventions and political gatherings. THE TIMES is independent, and its political news is not colored. The Times prints the news as it occurs, and the man who reads The Times gets all the news all the time, truthfully reported and unbiased in any particular. THE TIMES, first of all, is a newspaper, and its facilities for gathering and printing the news are unsurpassed in the South. Clear, concise, complete, just and impartial. THE TWICE-A-WEEK TIMES. Per Year, $1 00 Six Months, 50 Three Months, 25 PUBLISHED TUESDAY AND FRIDAY MORNINGS. IS PECULIARLY FITTED FOR THE BUSY MAN WHO DOES NOT RECEIVE A DAILY MAIL. Address: THE TIMES CO., RICHMOND, VA.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Security Bank, 1107 E. Main St., RICHMOND, VA. CAPITAL, $200,000 SURPLUS, 50,000 INTEREST PAID ON DEPOSITS. COLLECTIONS MADE ON ALL POINTS. SAVINGS AND BUSINESS ACCOUNTS SOLICITED. E. A. CATLIN, President. A. BEIRNE BLAIR, Cashier. New Ideas in School Books. The excellent text books recently issued by the B. F. Johnson Publishing Company mark a new era in the educational development of the country. Johnson's Readers, Lee's Histories, Manly's "Literature," and Curry's "South" especially are full of new ideas. If interested, send for catalogue and full description. FREE A charming booklet, "Revival of Interest in Southern Literature," "Literature in the South," by Chas. W. Kent and Hamilton W. Mabie, sent free on application. NEW BOOKS FOR THE GENERAL READER. "Uncle Isaac; or Old Days in the South"—by Dr. William Dudley Powers $1 0 Poems of James Barren Hope 1 25 "Heart Songs," by Josie Frazee Cappleman, of Mississippi 1 10 "Bobbie," a story by Kate Cairns 75 "Now That You Are Married" 50 Sent Postpaid on Receipt of Price. B. F. JOHNSON PUBLISHING CO., 901, 903, 905 E. Main St., RICHMOND, VA.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">S. T. MORGAN, President. S. W. TRAVERS, Treasurer. S. D. CRENSHAW, Secretary. E. T. ORGAIN, Auditor. VIRGINIA-CAROLINA CHEMICAL COMPANY RICHMOND, VIRGINIA. Being the largest manufacturers of Fertilizers, and having factories at the principal distributing points, are prepared to furnish Fertilizers of the best quality and lowest price consistent with the grade of goods. GENERAL SALES OFFICES: RICHMOND, VA. CHARLESTON, S. C. ATLANTA, GA. ORGANIZED 1865. Virginia State Insurance Co. 1001 East Main Street, RICHMOND, VA. Losses Paid Exceed $1,800,000.00 Assets Over 425,000.00 N. V. Randolph, President. Chas. K. Willis, Treasurer. Robert Lecky, Jr., Secretary.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">..VIRGINIA.. SECURITY ENDOWMENT COMPANY Merchants National Bank Building, RICHMOND, VIRGINIA Directors: M. B. ROSENBAUM, E. A. CATLIN, J. M. SWANSON, JNO. S. HARWOOD, WARNER MOORE, J. W. WHITEHURST, CHAS. T. O'FERRALL, JAMES VIRDIN. A short tontine investment contract desirable as to Security, Profits and Quick Returns. It is an old line life insurance contract with death clause eliminated, applying the principles of life insurance to stock, which enables the Company to mature it in a short time with large profits to the holder on absolutely safe basis. Organized October, 1899, and first redemption made April 1st, 1900, and will be made continuously each month hereafter, on a fixed and absolutely just basis. Redemption list, with name and address of holders, furnished on application. Correspondence solicited and testimonials furnished. Write to Company for information. McGuire's BOARDING AND DAY School, Opposite Monroe Park, RICHMOND, VA. THIRTY-FIFTH SESSION—September 20th, 1899, to June 20th, 1900. UNIVERSITY AND COLLEGE RECORD, Selected from Reports of Last Ten Years University of Virginia—1890-91—4 Degrees, 14 Diplomas; 1895-96—4 Degrees, 27 Diplomas, two of the five M. A.'s directly from this School; 1897-98, 2 Degrees, 5 Diplomas; 1898-99, 2 Degrees (1 Ph. D.). 34 Diplomas. Annapolis—Present Cadetship. West Point—Last competitive appointment. CORPS OF TEACHERS: John P. McGuire, Principal, E. W. Bosworth (U. of Va.), J. P. McGuire, Jr. (U. of Va.) E. H. Marstella (V. M. I.), J. G. Nelson, M. A., (U. of Va.), H. L. Roberts, M. A., Ph. D., (U. of Va.); Mrs. McGuire, with two Assistants, in "Lower School." Roll for Current Session—165. Catalogue for 1900-1901 issued June 30. Apply to the Principal, or to M. M. McGUIRE, Bus. Mgr., Room 33, Chamber of Commerce, Richmond, Va. B. T. WATKINS, WHOLESALE Railroad Ties, Lumber, Pine, Oak and Poplar Wood, No. 7 North 10th Street, RICHMOND, VA. References—The State Bank of Virginia, Security Bank of Richmond, Va., Metropolitan Bank of Richmond, Va., American National Bank, Richmond, Va. Correspondence Solicited.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Virginius Newton, President. J. B. Purcell, Vice-President. H. C. Burnett, Cashier. CAPITAL, $600,000. SURPLUS, $400,000. The First National Bank OF RICHMOND, VA. UNITED STATES, STATE AND CITY DEPOSITORY. Does a General Banking Business, Makes a Specialty of Collecting and Remitting at Lowest Rates. HAS FOR RENT IN ITS FIRE AND BURGLAR-PROOF VAULT PRIVATE BOXES AT AN ANNUAL RENTAL OF FROM $5 TO $20. ORGANIZED 1832. TESTED FOR SIXTY-SIX YEARS. ASSETS, $850,000. Virginia Fire and Marine Insurance Co. OF RICHMOND, VA. This Old Virginia Institution issues a Short and Comprehensive Policy, free from petty restrictions, and Liberal in its Terms and Conditions. INSURES AGAINST FIRE AND LIGHTNING. Wm. H. Palmer, President. W. H. McCarthy, Secretary.</field>
   </doc>
</add>