<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university of virginia</field>
      <field name="author_text">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1910's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2005_Q2_1/uvaBook/tei/z000000209.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240341</field>
      <field name="date_text">June, 1911</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:108267</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">University of Virginia record. Volume IV, No. 5, June, 1911</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">University of Virginia -- Periodicals</field>
      <field name="subject_text">University of Virginia -- Periodicals</field>
      <field name="title_display">University of Virginia record.  Volume IV, No. 5, June, 1911</field>
      <field name="title_facet">university of virginia record</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">university of virginia record</field>
      <field name="title_text">University of Virginia record.  Volume IV, No. 5, June, 1911</field>
      <field name="year_display">June, 1911</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1911-06</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1911</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:108267&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:108267&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;serial volume&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;university of virginia&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;University of Virginia record. Volume IV, No. 5, June, 1911&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;university of virginia record&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;June, 1911&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1911-06&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;University of Virginia record&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="volume"&gt;Volume IV&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="issue"&gt;No. 5&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;June, 1911&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Va.&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="LC call number"&gt;LD5667 .A43&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa call number"&gt;LD5667.2&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;X004490745&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;o07560180&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;10 p. ; 23 cm.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;University of Virginia -- Periodicals&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;University of Virginia Record&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="volume"&gt;4&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="issue"&gt;5&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1911-06&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2005&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2005 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 23 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">W. GORDON MERRICK</field>
      <field name="fulltext">[3] University of Virginia DEPARTMENT OF ENGINEERING General Plan of Study. At the University of Virginia engineering is studied as a learned profession, just as law or medicine. Care is taken in the first place to secure honest, thorough, and adequate preparation on the part of the entering student. This having been accomplished, a four year course has been organized, in which the student's whole time is devoted to his professional studies, including in these the fundamental sciences, which lie at the basis of all sound knowledge of engineering practice. No attempt has been made to create a place for courses in the humanistic branches—courses which in the majority of cases are fragmentary and ineffectual, arousing little interest in the student, and securing for him even less of benefit. On the other hand the scientific and technical courses are so taught as to make them true instruments of liberal culture; conceived on broad grounds, prosecuted to high ends, and followed in the right spirit, they develop competent engineers and not mere skilled craftsmen. Entrance Requirements. The standard for entrance has been fixed at the completion of the four year course of a first class high school. This course must include the full curriculum in mathematics (algebra, plane and solid geometry, and plane trigonometry). It must include at least three year's work in English (grammar, composition, rhetoric, and the normal course of reading in English prose and poetry). In addition to these 6½ prescribed units (3½ in mathematics and 3 in English) at least one unit in history is prescribed. The remaining 6½ units are elective, and may be offered in ancient or modern languages, or in history, or [4] in science, or in drawing or shop-work. In all cases the full requirement of 14 units must be met; only 2 conditions are allowed and they must be made up within twelve months after matriculation. Courses of Instruction. The work of every good school of engineering must be based on such entrance requirements as have been defined above, carefully formulated and rigidly observed. Inadequate preliminary training means always and everywhere inadequate and ineffectual work in the college course. An intelligent boy should be ready for the high school at the age of thirteen; four years later he should enter college. Earlier entrance upon a course of engineering studies is not desirable; the younger student has neither the maturity nor the steadiness of purpose demanded for success. The Freshman year in the University of Virginia is the same in all the engineering courses. Thereafter specialization begins, and the student's time is absorbed more and more each year by the technical studies needed in his chosen field for professional work. In addition to the prescribed studies the candidate for a degree must elect a certain number of engineering courses outside his special field. The young engineer obtains thus a broader conception of his professional work and an enlarged usefulness. Programme of Courses. To adequate preparation and studious diligence must be added expert teaching and a wisely formulated programme of courses. Every good engineering school must be the development of individual ideals and each one has its own accent, its own distinctive quality. The special character of the University of Virginia may best be shown by a comparison of its programme with that of one of the greatest and best known of the American schools of engineering, the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. The entrance requirements of these two schools are substantially identical. The amount of work demanded of the student is the same—eight hours a day for six days in the week. The course of study in each case extends over four years. At the University of Virginia the session is thirty-one weeks, exclusive of examination periods and holidays; at the Massachusetts Institute [5] of Technology it is thirty weeks. The general conditions are thus very nearly balanced. The tabulated statement below exhibits the distinctive features of the programme of each school, by showing the number of hours consumed in lecture, preparation, and practise for each of the four great groups of studies comprised in the courses of civil, mechanical, and electrical engineering: Programme of hours of work consumed in Engineering Studies at University of Virginia and Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Civil Engineering Mechanical Engineering Electrical Engineering Group A. Mathematics and Mechanics. Geometry, Algebra, Trigonometry, Analytical Geometry, Calculus, Statics, Dynamics. U. Va. M.I.T. U. Va. M.I.T. U. Va. M.I.T. 1116 795 1116 855 1116 855 Group B. Physical Sciences. Chemistry, Physics, and Geology; including in each case the laboratory courses. 1116 915 744 790 1006 770 Group C. Engineering Science. Applied Mechanics; and Civil, Mechanical, and Electrical Engineering. 2790 2765 2634 1940 2258 1920 Group D. Engineering Practice. Drawing, Shop-Work, Laboratory work in Engineering. 930 495 1474 1275 1570 1235 Group E. Humanistic Studies. English Literature, Modern Languages, History, Political Economy, and so on. 970 1080 1160 Grand Totals. 5952 5940 5952 5940 5952 5940 An examination of the tabulated figures shows that the M. I. T. consumes about one-sixth of the student's working time in humanistic studies. At the U. Va. his attention is concentrated [6] on the four other groups and the time thus saved is distributed in nearly equal parts among them. One other difference does not appear in this comparison. With its larger faculty the M. I. T. gives a larger percentage of the total time to class instruction than the U. Va. The result is that the student gets somewhat more direct teaching and does rather less individual work. That he is eventually benefited by this state of affairs does not appear. At the U. Va. out of each 16 hours he spends on an average 7 hours under the professor or instructor and 9 hours in independent work. This proportion seems liberal enough. Equipment. A modern school of engineering needs ample material equipment for the work of instruction. It must have not only laboratories of chemistry and physics and geology and mineralogy; but a sufficient outfit of field instruments; of shops and tools for work in wood and in metals; of testing machines for all sorts of structural materials; of apparatus for hydraulic measurements; of boilers and engines and appliances for testing the same; and of electric apparatus and dynamos and motors for both direct and alternating electric currents. In all those departments the University of Virginia is well furnished; richly furnished, indeed, in proportion to the number of its engineering students. Witness the large provision made in the tabulated programme above for work in engineering practise. The apparatus, instruments, and machines are new and of the best construction, and annual additions are made to the equipment. Crane Donation. Of the recent additions to this equipment the most important is the gift of Mr. Charles R. Crane, of Chicago. This gift is a collection of apparatus and machines for alternating current work in electrical engineering, so selected as to enlarge and complete the outfit already in use. Although serving actively as vice-president of the Crane Valve Company, an enormous business corporation, founded 55 years ago by his father, Mr. R. T. Crane, who is still its president, Mr. Charles R. Crane has many varied and vital interests outside his business. As president for many years of the Municipal Voters' League of Chicago he has [7] exerted a powerful influence for good government in an independent and non-partisan way. He was a close friend of the late President Harper, of Chicago University, and was associated with him in the heavy task of organizing that great modern school. He is deeply interested in biological research and has been for a long time the president of the Marine Biological Laboratory at Woods Hole. His summer home at Bridgeport, Conn., enables him to indulge on Buzzard's Bay and Vineyard Sound that love of the sea, which carried him as a lad on a voyage in a bark from New London to Java. Mr. Crane's permanent home is in Chicago, but his wide reading and deep study of American politics and world politics have brought him the friendship and acquaintance of many national leaders and have made him feel at home in many lands. He has long known the University of Virginia and his gift to the Department of Engineering is not the first of his discriminating acts of generosity to this school. Isabella Merrick Sampson Scholarship. Another noteworthy gift to the Department of Engineering recently received is a scholarship fund of $2,000. The donor was the late Mr. W. Gordon Merrick and the scholarship is named in honor of his sister. Mr. Merrick was born in Philadelphia, Oct. 28th, 1842. In 1867 he came to Virginia, bought a farm called Glendower, in the southern portion of Albemarle County, married a wife and settled down to the life of a country gentleman. Mr. Merrick at once took an active interest in county affairs, served as road commissioner and as justice of the peace for a number of years, and in the latter part of his life as county chairman of the Republican committee. In the fall of 1910 he gave up his country home because of ill-health, removed with his family to Charlottesville and died there January 3rd, 1911. In 1874 Mr. Merrick's sister left a fund, of which he was one of the trustees, to be used for education in the South. For several years the fund was used for the salaries of public school teachers in Albemarle County, and general public school purposes. In the last years of his life he became the sole trustee. He then determined to employ the residue of the fund for the [8] endowment of a scholarship in the Department of Engineering of the University of Virginia. Under the terms of the deed of gift the fund is placed in the hands of three trustees, two of whom are members of the University, while the third is a citizen of the county. These trustees constitute a self-perpetuating board. The management and investment of the fund and the appointment of the scholar is in their hands. The scholar must be a student in the Department of Engineering, and in the selection preference is to be given to a student from the county of Albemarle, if there be such a deserving student; and next to a student from the state of Virginia. If there be no deserving student either from Albemarle or from Virginia, then the trustees may award the scholarship to any other deserving student in the Department of Engineering. The annual income from the endowment is paid to this scholar, and he is eligible for annual reappointment as long as he remains a student of engineering in the University and justifies by his conduct and scholarship the expectations of the trustees. Persons desirous of fuller information as to the courses in engineering in the University of Virginia are invited to apply for catalogues to Howard Winston, Registrar; and for explanations and advice to address William M. Thornton, Dean. University of Virginia,July 1st, 1911.</field>
   </doc>
</add>