<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university of virginia</field>
      <field name="author_text">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1930's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2005_Q3_2/uvaBook/tei/z000000398.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240342</field>
      <field name="date_text">February 15, 1935</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:132590</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The University of Virginia record. New Series Vol. XXI, No. 4, February 15, 1935</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">University of Virginia -- Periodicals</field>
      <field name="subject_text">University of Virginia -- Periodicals</field>
      <field name="title_display">The University of Virginia record.  New Series Vol. XXI, No. 4, February 15, 1935</field>
      <field name="title_facet">university of virginia record</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">university of virginia record</field>
      <field name="title_text">The University of Virginia record.  New Series Vol. XXI, No. 4, February 15, 1935</field>
      <field name="year_display">February 15, 1935</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1935-02-15</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1935</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:132590&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:132590&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;serial volume&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;university of virginia&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The University of Virginia record. New Series Vol. XXI, No. 4, February 15, 1935&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;university of virginia record&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;February 15, 1935&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1935-02-15&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The University of Virginia record&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="volume"&gt;New Series Vol. XXI&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="issue"&gt;No. 4&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;February 15, 1935&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Va.&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="LC call number"&gt;LD5667 .A43&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa call number"&gt;LD5667.2&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;X004321690&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;o07560180&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;82 p. ; 23 cm.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;University of Virginia -- Periodicals&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The University of Virginia Record&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="volume"&gt;New Series, 21&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="issue"&gt;4&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1935-02-15&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2005&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2005 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 309 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PUBLICATIONS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA The University of Virginia Record: No. 1, January 15: The College of Arts and Sciences: Announcements. No. 2, February 1: Department of Engineering: Announcements. No. 3, February 1: Department of Law: Announcements. No. 4, February 15: Department of Graduate Studies: Announcements. No. 5, March 15: Catalogue Number of the Summer Quarter. No. 6, March 1: Department of Medicine: Announcements. No. 7, March 1: Department of Education: Announcements. No. 7-a, March 1: School of Nursing Education: Announcements. No. 8, April 1: General Catalogue Number. The University of Virginia Record, Extension Series, published ten times a year. The Virginia Quarterly Review, published four times a year. A national journal of discussion. The Alumni News, published by the Alumni Association twelve times a year. The Virginia High School Quarterly, published in November, February, May and August by the Department of Education. Bulletin of the University of Virginia Library, published at intervals, during the session. The Virginia Law Review, published by the Virginia Law Review Association, monthly from October to May. University of Virginia News Letter, published semi-monthly from October 1 through June by the School of Rural Social Economics.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA RECORD New Series, Vol. XXI, No. 4 February 15, 1935 Department of Graduate Studies ANNOUNCEMENTS 1935-1936 Entered as Second-Class Matter September 28, 1914, at the Post Office at Charlottesville, Virginia, under the Act of August 24, 1912.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">UNIVERSITY CALENDAR 1935 Thursday, January 3 Beginning of Second Term. Wednesday, March 13—Saturday, March 23 Second Term Academic Examinations. Monday, March 25 Beginning of Third Term. Saturday, April 13 Jefferson Day (Holiday). Wednesday, May 1 Doctors' Dissertations Due. Wednesday, May 15 Masters' Theses Due. Monday, May 27—Thursday, June 6 Final Academic Examinations. Monday, June 3—Saturday, June 8 Entrance Examinations. Sunday, June 9 Baccalaureate Sermon. Monday, June 10 Alumni Day. Meeting of the Rector and Visitors. Tuesday, June 11 Final Day. Monday, June 17 Opening of the Summer Quarter, First Term. Saturday, July 27 Closing of the Summer Quarter, First Term. Monday, July 29 Opening of the Summer Quarter, Second Term. Saturday, August 31 Closing of the Summer Quarter, Second Term. Monday, September 9—Saturday, September 14 Entrance Examinations. Thursday, September 12 Beginning of One Hundred Twelfth Session. Thursday, September 12—Saturday, September 14 Registration Days. Monday, September 16 Beginning of Lecture Courses. Tuesday, October 1 Applications for Collegiate Degrees Due. Wednesday, October 2 University Convocation. Thursday, November 28 Thanksgiving Day (Holiday). Tuesday, December 10—Friday, December 20 First Term Academic Examinations. Saturday, December 21—Thursday, January 2 Christmas Recess. 1936 Friday, January 3 Beginning of Second Term. Wednesday, March 11—Saturday, March 21 Second Term Academic Examinations Monday, March 23 Beginning of Third Term. Monday, April 13 Jefferson Day (Holiday). Friday, May 1 Doctors' Dissertations Due. Friday, May 15 Masters' Theses Due. Monday, May 25—Thursday, June 4 Final Academic Examinations. Monday, June 1—Saturday June 6 Entrance Examinations. Sunday, June 7 Baccalaureate Sermon. Monday, June 8 Alumni Day. Meeting of the Rector and Visitors Tuesday, June 9 Final Day.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES JOHN LLOYD NEWCOMB, B.A., C.E., Sc.D., LL.D. President of the University JOHN CALVIN METCALF, M.A., Litt.D., LL.D. Dean of the Department of Graduate Studies ADMINISTRATIVE COMMITTEE The Dean and Professors Manahan, Mitchell, Benton, Snavely, Balz, Jordan; for the Summer Quarter, The Dean and Professors Faulkner, Kepner, Snavely * * On the Carnegie Foundation. WILLIAM MYNN THORNTON, B.A., LL.D. Emeritus Professor of Applied Mathematics † † Died September 25, 1934. WILLIAM HOLDING ECHOLS, B.S., C.E. Professor of Mathematics RICHARD HEATH DABNEY, M.A., Ph.D. Corcoran Professor of History RICHARD HENRY WILSON, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Romanic Languages ROBERT MONTGOMERY BIRD, B.A., B.S., Ph.D. Professor of Chemistry WILLIAM MENTZEL FORREST, B.A. John B. Cary Memorial Professor of Biblical Literature WILLIAM HARRISON FAULKNER, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Germanic Languages HARVEY ERNEST JORDAN, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Histology and Embryology CHARLES GILMORE MAPHIS, Ped.D., LL.D. Professor of Education ROBERT HENNING WEBB, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Greek SAMUEL ALFRED MITCHELL, M.A., Ph.D., LL.D. Professor of Astronomy and Director of the Leander McCormick Observatory IVEY FOREMAN LEWIS, B.A., M.S., Ph.D. Miller Professor of Biology and Agriculture LLEWELLYN GRIFFITH HOXTON, B.S., B.A., M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Physics ROBERT BENNETT BEAN, B.S., M.D. Professor of Anatomy JOHN LEVI MANAHAN, B.S., M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Educational Administration JAMES ALEXANDER WADDELL, B.A., M.D. Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica and Toxicology WILLIAM ALLISON KEPNER, M.A., Ph.D., Sc.D. Professor of Biology JOHN CALVIN METCALF, M.A., Litt.D., LL.D. Linden Kent Memorial Professor of English Literature GEORGE OSCAR FERGUSON, Jr., M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Psychology and Education WILLIAM ROYAL SMITHEY, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Secondary Education JAMES SOUTHALL WILSON, M.A., Ph.D., LL.D. Edgar Allan Poe Professor of English ALBERT GEORGE ADAM BALZ, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Philosophy CARROLL MASON SPARROW, B.A., Ph.D. Professor of Physics ARTHUR FICKENSCHER, Diploma, Royal Conservatory of Munich Professor of Music JOHN JENNINGS LUCK, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Mathematics WILSON GEE, B.S., M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Rural Economics and Rural Sociology and Director of the Institute for Research in the Social Sciences TIPTON RAY SNAVELY, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Economics WILBUR ARMISTEAD NELSON, B.S., M.A., Corcoran Professor of Geology JAMES COOK BARDIN, M.D. Professor of Romanic Languages ALBERT JULIUS BARLOW, B.A., C.P.A. Professor of Commerce and Business Administration ABRAHAM BERGLUND, B.A., Ph.D. Professor of Commerce and Business Administration ATCHESON LAUGHLIN HENCH, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of English ELBERT ALVIS KINCAID, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Commerce and Business Administration ROBERT KENT GOOCH, M.A., D.Phil. (Oxon.) Professor of Political Science W. PATTON GRAHAM, M.A. Professor of Romanic Languages JOSEPH KENT ROBERTS, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Geology FLOYD NELSON HOUSE, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Sociology JOHN HOWE YOE, M.S., M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Chemistry EDMUND SCHUREMAN CAMPBELL, M.S. Professor of Art and Architecture and Curator of The Thomas H. Bayly Museum ORLAND EMILE WHITE, M.S., Sc.D. Professor of Agricultural Biology and Director of the Blandy Experimental Farm HARRY CLEMONS, M.A. Librarian ARTHUR FERGUSON BENTON, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Chemistry EDWIN PARTRIDGE LEHMAN, B.A., M.D. Professor of Surgery and Gynecology SIDNEY WILLIAM BRITTON, B.Sc., M.D., C.M. Professor of Physiology WALTER ALEXANDER MONTGOMERY, B.A., Ph.D. Professor of Latin KENNETH FULLER MAXCY, B.A., M.D., Dr.P.H. Professor of Preventive Medicine and Bacteriology ALFRED CHANUTIN, Ph.B., Ph.D. Professor of Biochemistry LINWOOD LEHMAN, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Latin FRANK STRINGFELLOW BARR, B.A., M.A., (Oxon.) Professor of History JESSE WAKEFIELD BEAMS, Jr., M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Physics SCOTT MILROSS BUCHANAN, B.A., Ph.D. Professor of Philosophy CARL CASKEY SPEIDEL, Ph.B., Ph.D. Professor of Anatomy JAMES ROBERT CASH, M.A., M.D. Walter Reed Professor of Pathology DUDLEY CROFFORD SMITH, B.S., M.D. Professor of Dermatology and Syphilology GORDON THOMAS WHYBURN, M.A., Ph.D. Professor of Mathematics HERMAN PATRICK JOHNSON, M.A., Ph.M. Associate Professor of English Literature JAMES ERNEST KINDRED, M.A., Ph.D. Associate Professor of Histology and Embryology FREDERICK LYONS BROWN, M.A., Ph.D. Associate Professor of Physics HARRY ROGERS PRATT Associate Professor of Music and Dramatic Art BEN-ZION LINFIELD, M.S., Ph.D., Sc.D. Associate Professor of Mathematics ARMISTEAD CHURCHILL GORDON, Jr., M.A., Ph.D. Associate Professor of English BRUCE DODSON REYNOLDS, B.S., Sc.D. Associate Professor of Zoölogy ARTHUR KYLE DAVIS, Jr., M.A., B.Litt. (Oxon.), Ph.D. Associate Professor of English GEORGE TALMADGE STARNES, M.A., Ph.D. Associate Professor of Commerce and Business Administration CHARLES NEWTON HULVEY, M.S., LL.B. Associate Professor of Commercial Law FRANK ARTHUR GELDARD, M.A., Ph.D. Associate Professor of Psychology THOMAS CARY JOHNSON, Jr., M.A. Associate Professor of History FRANK WILLIAM HOFFER, M.A., Ph.D. Associate Professor of Sociology ROBERT ELIOT LUTZ, M.S., Ph.D. Associate Professor of Chemistry LAUREN BLAKELY HITCHCOCK. S.M., Sc.D. Associate Professor of Chemical Engineering DAVID COLE WILSON, B.A., M.D. Associate Professor of Psychiatry and Neurology GEORGE WASHINGTON SPICER, B.A., Ph.D. Associate Professor of Political Science DUNCAN CLARK HYDE, M.A., Ph.D. Associate Professor of Economics EARL GODFREY MELLOR, M.A., Ph.D. Associate Professor of Romance Philology ARCHIBALD ANDERSON HILL, M.A., Ph.D. Associate Professor of English Philology FREDERIC TURNBULL WOOD, B.A., Ph.D. Associate Professor of Germanic Philology THOMAS PERKINS ABERNETHY, Ph.D. Richmond Alumni Associate Professor of History ALEXANDER DAVID FRASER, M.A., Ph.D. Associate Professor of Archaeology ORESTE RINETTI, Ph.D. Associate Professor of Italian * * Absent on leave, session 1934-35. MELVIN GARDNER DE CHAZEAU, M.A., Ph.D. Associate Professor of Commerce and Business Administration ROWLAND ANDREWS EGGER, M.A., Ph.D. Associate Professor of Political Science ALBERT EUGENE CASEY, B.A., M.D. Associate Professor of Pathology CHARLES HOWE ELLER, M.D., Sc.D., Dr.P.H. Associate Professor of Public Health ARTHUR AUGUST PEGAU, M.A., Ph.D. Assistant Professor of Geology EDWIN MORRIS BETTS, Ph.B., M.S., Ph.D. Assistant Professor of Biology FRANZ KARL MOHR, M.A., Dr. Jur. Assistant Professor of Germanic Languages HUGH MILLER SPENCER, B.A., M.S., Ph.D. Assistant Professor of Chemistry ALEXANDER VYSSOTSKY, Ph.D. Assistant Professor of Astronomy PETER VAN DE KAMP, Ph.D. Assistant Professor of Astronomy THADDEUS BRAXTON WOODY, M.A. Assistant Professor of Spanish ARCHIBALD BOLLING SHEPPERSON, M.A., Ph.D. Assistant Professor of English EDWARD LYMAN COREY, B.A., Ph.D. Assistant Professor of Physiology ORON JAMES HALE, M.A., Ph.D. Assistant Professor of History CHARLES KIDDER DAVENPORT, C.P.H., Ph.D. Assistant Professor of Philosophy WAYNE DENNIS, M.A., Ph.D. Assistant Professor of Psychology EVERETT FOGG DAVIS, B.S., Ph.D. Assistant Professor of Biology LESTER JESSE CAPPON, M.A., Ph.D. Acting Assistant Professor of History JAMES CECIL NELSON, M.A., Ph.D. Acting Assistant Professor of Commerce HISTORICAL STATEMENT While the original organization of the Academic Schools of the University by Jefferson contemplated instruction of graduate grade in each School, the first "post-graduate department" in the modern sense was instituted in 1859-60 by Basil L. Gildersleeve, then Professor of Greek in the institution. The degree of Master of Arts continued to be conferred upon graduates in all six Schools of the University. Professor Gildersleeve conducted graduate courses in the School of Greek; shortly after the Civil War a "post-graduate department" was announced for the School of Latin. Graduate courses were offered in individual Schools, but there was no general department organization for graduate study until 1904. In that year the Department of Graduate Studies was established as a regular co-ordinate division of the University, with definitely prescribed regulations corresponding to the requirements of the Association of American Universities, in which the University of Virginia was the first Southern university to hold membership. The degree of Doctor of Philosophy had, however, been offered by the University as far back as 1880, and the first doctor's degree was awarded in 1885. From 1885 to 1935 the degree of Doctor of Philosophy has been conferred upon two hundred and forty-eight persons. The present requirements for graduate degrees, with certain modifications, have been in force since 1922. THE GRADUATE HOUSE The Graduate House, administrative headquarters of the Department of Graduate Studies, is on West Lawn. Besides the Dean's office, this building contains one large lecture-room for graduate classes and four seminar rooms specially equipped for small groups of students and professors engaged in advanced graduate work. At present the class-rooms are used for certain advanced courses in the Schools of English and History. The Bruce Collection of books for the use of graduate students in English is in this building. This departmental library, endowed by the late Professor J. Douglas Bruce of the University of Tennessee, an alumnus of the University, contains valuable source material. LIBRARY FACILITIES The University Libraries altogether contained on July 1, 1934, a total of 232,014 volumes. Departmental libraries afford specialized collections in science, classics, English, the social sciences, and education. The Medical Library, now in the new Medical Buildings, is spacious and well equipped for graduate study. Graduate students may, through the office of the General Library, get certain books needed in research from other university libraries on the inter-library loan system. Nearness to Washington makes the Library of Congress and the Folger Shakespeare Library easily available for graduate students. GRADUATE CLUBS There are regular weekly or bi-weekly departmental conferences of graduate students and professors for discussion of topics connected with graduate study. In the various physical sciences, in medical science, in the social sciences, and in humanistic studies, graduate clubs, composed of students and professors, are actively engaged in stimulating investigation and publication in their respective fields. The scientific society of Sigma Xi is an important organization for the advancement of technical knowledge, while the Institute for Research in the Social Sciences furnishes a fruitful field of activity. The University Committee on Research, while not specifically an organization of the Department of Graduate Studies, is a valuable auxiliary of the Department. This committee administers an annual appropriation for promoting research in the various Departments of the University, especially in the matter of the publication of the results of original investigation, and so aids the general cause of advanced scholarship. An annual volume, "Publications and Research," containing summaries of contributions by professors and students of the Graduate Department, is issued by the University. A list of doctoral dissertations, with abstracts, is published each September for distribution among other universities. SCIENTIFIC LABORATORIES Each Scientific School occupies a separate building with an extensive laboratory and a select departmental library. Statements in regard to laboratories and general scientific equipment in the Schools of Astronomy, Biology, Chemistry, Geology, Physics, and the Department of Medicine may be found under the announcements of those Schools. More detailed information is contained in the General Catalogue. ORGANIZATION The immediate direction of the Department of Graduate Studies is vested in the Dean and an Administrative Committee of eight professors, appointed by the President. The Faculty of the Graduate Department consists of those professors in the Academic Schools and the Medical School who offer graduate courses. Courses marked C are for graduates and advanced under-graduates; those marked D are for graduates only, and usually for advanced graduate students, candidates for the Ph.D. degree. In the Department of Medicine the regular courses are evaluated as C courses; elective, special and research courses, and seminars as D courses. The prerequisites for each course are indicated, varying from 6 to 12 session-hours of college work. The various Schools, or departments, fall into four general divisions, or groups, as follows: Group I—Languages, Literature, Fine Arts and Music. English, French, German, Greek, Latin, Spanish, Italian, Portugese, Biblical Literature, Architecture, Music. Group II—Social and Philosophical Sciences. Commerce, Economics, Education, History, Philosophy, Psychology, Political Science, Sociology. Group III—Mathematical and Natural Sciences. Astronomy, Biology, Chemistry, Geology, Mathematics, Physics. Group IV—Medical Sciences. Anatomy and Anthropology, Bacteriology and Preventive Medicine, Biochemistry, Dermatology and Syphilology, Histology and Embryology, Neurology, Pathology, Pharmacology, Physiology, and Surgery. REGISTRATION Every graduate student, new or old, is required to register at the office of the Dean of the Department, Graduate House, West Lawn, after consultation with the head of his School. All women students must first register at the office of the Dean of Women, 22 East Lawn. The first three days of the session are devoted to registration. Every applicant for admission to the Graduate Department as a candidate for a degree must file with the Dean an official transcript of his college record. Admission to the Department does not necessarily imply acceptance for candidacy for a degree. All applications will be passed upon by the Committee on Rules and Courses of the Department of Graduate Studies early in the first term, and each applicant will be formally notified by the Dean of the tentative approval of his candidacy. The final approval of his candidacy will depend upon his record during the first term, or quarter, of his residence. ENTRANCE REQUIREMENTS Admission to the Department.—For admission to the Department of Graduate Studies a baccalaureate degree from a recognized institution of collegiate rank is required, for men and women alike. For students in the Medical Science Group, the M. D. degree will be accepted in lieu of a baccalaureate degree. In order to become a candidate for a degree, the student must be advanced to candidacy by the Committee on Rules and Courses upon formal application, as set forth below. Advancement to Candidacy for a Degree.—Any graduate student who wishes to become a candidate for a degree must file with the Dean of the Department his application on a blank form to be secured from the Dean's Secretary. This application must include a proposed program of work arranged in accordance with the requirements for the several degrees as stated below, and must be accompanied, in case the applicant does not hold an academic degree from this University, by an official transcript of the applicant's academic record made out by the Registrar of the institution from which the baccalaureate degree was received, and by a catalogue of that institution, marked to show the courses of study pursued. The application will be submitted by the Dean to the Committee on Rules and Courses, who will consider it in conference with the professors concerned. The Committee will have the right to require that the applicant add to his program any courses, undergraduate or graduate, considered necessary to supply his deficiencies, or to enable him to pursue with profit the courses he has selected. When the program has been finally approved, the Dean will report to the applicant his advancement to candidacy for a degree. It should be distinctly understood that graduate degrees are not conferred merely upon the basis of the number of courses passed, or of the length of time spent in resident or non-resident work, but upon the basis of the quality and scope of the candidate's knowledge, and his power of investigation in his chosen field of study. Candidates whose training and attainments are inferior cannot expect to secure a degree in the normal length of time estimated below for the respective degrees. As a prerequisite to full candidacy for a Master's degree, at least 6 collegiate session-hours, or 12 semester-hours, of foreign language (ancient or modern) credit are required. A reading knowledge of foreign languages may be attested by an examination. REQUIREMENTS FOR DEGREES Master of Arts.—The degree of Master of Arts will be conferred upon the holder of a degree of Bachelor of Arts who has fulfilled the following requirements: (1) The successful completion, in not less than one full year of resident graduate work, of the program of studies approved for the candidate by the Committee on Rules and Courses, as embodied in his formal application for advancement to candidacy. This application must be submitted early in the session in which it is expected that the degree will be conferred. The program must form a consistent plan of work, to be pursued with some definite aim, and grouped around some one subject to be known as the candidate's Major Subject, the name of which will be incorporated in the body of each diploma conferring the degree. The program should be arranged in consultation with the professors concerned, and must be approved in writing by a professor of the candidate's Major Subject, who shall be designated by the Dean of the Department of Graduate Studies, after consultation with the candidate. Ordinarily, courses aggregating 12 session-hours, or 24 semester-hours, are required of candidates for a Master's degree. (2) The preparation and submission of a thesis, to be accepted as satisfactory by at least two professors in the candidate's Major Subject. Two copies of the thesis, typewritten on paper of good quality, 8½ by 11 inches, and bound in stiff board or cloth covers, must be deposited in the office of the Dean of the Department of Graduate Studies not later than May 15 of the year in which it is expected that the degree will be conferred. The back of the cover must bear the title of the thesis and the writer's name, and the title page must carry the author's name, degree, and the subject of the thesis, followed by the words: A Thesis Presented to the Graduate Faculty of the University of Virginia in Candidacy for the Degree of Master of Arts. (3) A final comprehensive examination, oral or written, after the acceptance of the candidate's thesis, conducted by the candidate's major professor and two or more of his departmental colleagues. Master of Science.—The degree of Master of Science will be conferred upon the holder of a degree of Bachelor of Science who fulfills requirements corresponding to those stated above for the degree of Master of Arts. The degree of Master of Science, like that of Master of Arts, is regarded as a cultural rather than a professional degree and the prerequisites for candidacy, including a reading knowledge of foreign languages, are estimated accordingly. No extension or correspondence courses will be credited toward a Master's degree. Doctor of Philosophy.— The degree of Doctor of Philosophy will be conferred upon the holder of a baccalaureate degree who has fulfilled the following requirements. (1) A reading knowledge of French and German sufficient to enable the student to use these languages for purposes of research. This knowledge shall be attested by examinations in those languages set by the candidate's major professor, or by some one in his School designated by him. Examination papers shall be read and marked by professors in the Schools of French and German. The language examinations of candidates for the Ph.D. degree should be held by October 1 of the session preceding the final academic year of candidacy for the degree. Credit in this University for not less than 3 session-hours in B courses in either language may, on the approval of the School of the candidate's Major Subject, be accepted as satisfying the requirement in that language. Upon recommendation of the professor of the Major Subject, and at the discretion of the Graduate Committee, some other foreign language may be substituted for either French or German. (2) The successful completion, in not less than three full years of graduate work, of the program of studies approved for the candidate by the Graduate Committee as embodied in his formal application. The application for advancement to candidacy should be submitted to the Dean not later than October 15 of the session preceding the final year of candidacy for the degree, and must be submitted by October 15 of his final year. The program of studies must include a Major Subject, pursued for at least three years, and a Minor Subject, pursued for at least one year. The Minor Subject must be closely related to the Major Subject, and the program as a whole must contribute to the mastery of some definite field of knowledge as an object of study and research. The name of the Major Subject will be incorporated in the body of the diploma conferring the degree. At least one year of advanced graduate study, preferably the last, must be spent in residence. By special permission of the Graduate Committee the student may be allowed to complete his dissertation in absentia under the direction of his advisory professor. (3) A dissertation exhibiting independent research in the candidate's Major Subject, to be submitted in complete form to the Special Departmental Committee of which the candidate's advisory professor is chairman, not later than May 1 of the final year of candidacy. Three typewritten copies must be sent to the Dean's office, before the conferring of the degree. Two of these copies will be deposited in the General Library; one copy will, upon request, be turned over to the department or school in which the dissertation was prepared. The dissertation shall be typewritten upon paper of good quality, 8½ by 11 inches, and substantially bound in stiff covers; pasteboard covers are not acceptable. The cover shall bear the title of the dissertation with the author's full name and academic degree or degrees, and in addition the following words: A Dissertation Presented to the Graduate Faculty of the University of Virginia in Candidacy for the Degree of Doctor of Philosophy. The candidate is expected to arrange, at the earliest possible date, for the publication of the dissertation, either as a whole or in part, as the department or school concerned shall direct. Fifty-two copies of the printed dissertation shall be deposited in the University Library. Each dissertation, when finally submitted, must be accompanied by an abstract of from five hundred to a thousand words, to be approved by the department or school. This abstract, or summary, will be published in a bulletin for distribution among other universities. No dissertation will be accepted without this attached abstract. A fee of $25 toward the editing and publication of this annual bulletin of summaries must be paid by the candidate for the Ph.D. degree before the conferring of the degree. (4) A final examination, oral, written, or both, in addition to all examinations in course, upon such phases of the Major Subject and of allied subjects, as the Special Committee (described below) shall prescribe. Ordinarily no candidate may be admittted to the final examination until his dissertation has been accepted. Preliminary examinations may, in addition, be required by individual Schools, as stated under the announcements of these Schools. Upon approval of the dissertation, the Dean will appoint, upon nomination of the School concerned, a Special Committee of not less than three professors under the chairmanship of the professor of the candidate's Major Subject, and including a representative of the Graduate Committee. This Special Committee may, through its chairman, invite other members of the departmental faculty to take part in the examination of the candidate. It is recommended indeed that the doctoral examination be given before the entire professorial staff of the School concerned. The result of the examination should be promptly reported to the Registrar. Grade.—A graduate student's standing in a course is indicated by one of the following symbols: A, B+, B, C. A, B+, and B are passing grades: A is distinguished, B+ is very good, B is satisfactory, C is unsatisfactory. Failure to attain the grade of B on any one term will invalidate candidacy for the degree in the current session. Only graduate courses may be counted toward a graduate degree. Summer Session.—The Master's degree may be won by properly qualified persons in three full Summer Quarters. In no case will this degree be conferred without resident graduate study during three quarters, the equivalent in time of the long session. Not more than two graduate courses each term of the Summer Quarter will be credited toward the degree except by special permission of the Dean and the Committee concerned. At least 12 session-hours, or 24 semester-hours, of graduate courses are required for the Master's degree. A candidate for the Master's degree in the Summer Quarter must register with the Dean of the Graduate Department and submit a program of studies in accordance with the regulations prescribed for admission to candidacy for that degree in the long session. In addition to the preparation of a thesis, a final examination, written or oral, upon the program of study and acceptable to the professor of the candidate's Major Subject in the long session of the University, will be required. Candidates for degrees at the Summer Quarter Convocation must hand in their theses by August 1 and take their final comprehensive examinations as soon as their theses have been approved. Graduate Students in the Summer Quarter must complete the courses of study for their Masters' degrees within five summers after admission to full candidacy. Graduate students are strongly advised to continue their residence during one or more terms of the long session. Candidates for degrees at the Summer Quarter Convocation must notify the Graduate office of their intentions at the beginning of the Summer Quarter. Each candidate must submit for departmental approval to the chairman of the department concerned the subject of his thesis. APPROXIMATE SUMMARY OF NECESSARY EXPENSES The figures in the following tables may be taken as fairly accurate approximations of all necessary expenses for a session of nine months. As necessary expenses are reckoned here University, athletic, and tuition fees, laboratory fees, lodging, board, laundry, and books, but not clothing, traveling expenses, or pocket money. For each department three estimates are given—a low, an average, and a liberal estimate. The difference in the three depends on the difference of expenditure for board, lodging, books, and laundry—in other words, on the scale of living of the individual student. If a student shares a room with another student, and practices the strictest economy, he may possibly reduce his expenses below the low estimate. VIRGINIANS NON-VIRGINIANS Low Average Liberal Low Average Liberal University Fee $ 50.00 $ 50.00 $ 50.00 $ 60.00 $ 60.00 $ 60.00 Tuition Fee 40.00 40.00 40.00 90.00 90.00 90.00 Athletic Fee 15.00 15.00 15.00 15.00 15.00 15.00 Topics Fee 1.50 1.50 1.50 1.50 1.50 1.50 Laboratory Fees (average) 10.00 10.00 10.00 10.00 10.00 10.00 Room, Heat, Light, Furniture and Service 65.00 115.00 225.00 65.00 115.00 225.00 Board 200.00 225.00 270.00 200.00 225.00 270.00 Books 25.00 30.00 35.00 25.00 30.00 35.00 Laundry 25.00 35.00 50.00 25.00 35.00 50.00 Total for session of nine months $431.50 $521.50 $696.50 $491.50 $581.50 $756.50 A fee of $3.00 is required of all women students for the upkeep of the "Women Students' Association Rooms." For detailed information as to fees, rooms, and board, see the General Catalogue. FELLOWSHIPS The following fellowships are available for graduate students. Application for a fellowship should be made on a regular form which may be obtained from the Secretary to the Dean of the Department of Graduate Studies, Graduate House, West Lawn. The application, after being filled out by the applicant in accordance with directions, should be returned to the Secretary to the Dean not later than March 15. Fellowships will be awarded by the Fellowship Award Committee as soon thereafter as practicable and the successful applicants will be notified. Successful applicants for non-service fellowships must signify their acceptance of appointments by April 15. Attention is particularly called to this ruling in regard to fellowships by the Association of American Universities (of which the University of Virginia is a member): "Those who have accepted fellowships at a member institution shall not be eligible to appointment to a vacancy in another (member) institution except by consent of the former." Fellowship appointments are for a full academic year. What are known as Service Fellowships, that is, those entailing a certain amount of teaching or other assistance, are administered from the Office of the President of the University. Applications for such fellowships should be addressed to the professor in charge under whom the service is to be rendered. The College Fellowships: one for each of a list of colleges selected by the faculty; emolument, for Virginians, the remission of the University fee, $50; for non-Virginians, the remission of the tuition fee, $90. The holder must be a graduate of one of the designated colleges, and must enter the University the session following his graduation. Appointments are made upon the recommendation of these colleges. The Philip Francis du Pont Junior Fellowships (12): These fellowships carry a stipend of $250 for Virginians and $310 for non-Virginians. They are intended for students holding Bachelors' degrees who are entering the Graduate Department. A University and tuition fee of $90 for Virginians and $150 for non-Virginians is payable out of these fellowships. Junior Fellowships are not renewable. The Philip Francis du Pont Senior Fellowships (15): These fellowships carry a stipend of $400 for Virginians and $460 for non-Virginians. They are intended for students who have had at least one full year of graduate study and who have accomplished work equivalent to that required for the Master's degree. The University and tuition fee of $90 for Virginians and $150 for non-Virginians is payable out of the stipends. These fellowships may be renewed at the discretion of the Fellowship Award Committee. The Philip Francis du Pont Research Fellowships (12): These fellowships, with incomes varying from $600 to $750, are intended for advanced graduate students, candidates for the Ph. D. or holders of that degree, who must devote their time to research under the direction of the School concerned. The applicant is expected to submit a well defined project of research. Ordinarily, these Research Fellowships are not renewable. These fellowships are exempt from the University and tuition fees. The Bayly-Tiffany Fellowships (7): These fellowships carry stipends from $250 to $600, dependent upon the applicant's advancement. Most of these fellowships rank as Junior and Senior, but one or more may be Research Fellowships, if conditions warrant. The same regulations as to fees apply to these fellowships as to the duPont. Established in 1930 by a bequest of Mrs. Evelyn May Bayly Tiffany as a memorial to Thomas Henry Bayly and Evelyn and Louise McLean Tiffany. In making awards preference will be given, where practicable, to students from Northampton and Accomac Counties, Va. Vacancies may be filled by the Faculty Committee on Fellowships from applicants from other portions of Virginia or from the State of Maryland. The Blandy Fellowships in Biology: five; two with an income of $1,000 each, three with an income of $500 each, all with free tuition. For particulars, see the statement on page 25. Applications should be made to the Director of the Blandy Experimental Farm, University, Va., not later than March 15. The Elizabeth B. Garrett Fellowship: Founded in 1918 upon the bequest of Mrs. Elizabeth B. White, of Baltimore, Maryland. Emolument, $260. Appointments are made upon the recommendation of the Dean of the Department of Graduate Studies. The Bennett Wood Green Fellowships: two, with a maximum tenure of four years, and a yearly income of $600 each. Founded in 1914 upon the bequest of Dr. Bennett Wood Green, '55, of Warwick County, Va. The holder must have received one of the degrees mentioned below not more than four years previous to his application, and must spend the tenure of his scholarship in study abroad or wherever else the faculty may require. The holders are appointed upon the recommendation of the faculty. In making appointments, preference will be given: (1) to Doctors of Medicine of this University who are also Masters of Arts of the University; (2) to Masters of Arts of the University; (3) to Bachelors of Laws of the University who are also Masters of Arts of the University; and in all cases to native Virginians, and then to native residents of other Southern States. The Captain Craig Woodrow McDonald Memorial Fellowship, with an emolument of $225: Founded in 1930 by a bequest of his sister, Susan L. Stanard, of Charles Town, W. Va. Captain MacDonald was an alumnus of the University of Virginia, and was killed in the battle of Cold Harbor in the "War Between the States." In selecting the beneficiary, preference will be shown near or blood relative of the founder. Application should be made to the Dean of the Department of Graduate Studies. The John Y. Mason Fellowship, with an income of $325: Founded in 1892 upon the gift of Col. Archer Anderson, '58, of Richmond, Va. The holder must be a competent and deserving student, who was born in Virginia, in need of such assistance. The Phelps Stokes Fellowship in Sociology for the study of the Negro, with an income of $500: Founded in 1911, upon the gift of the Trustees of the Phelps-Stokes Fund. The holder must be a graduate student in residence at this University, and must plan his courses in accordance with certain specific requirements of the Phelps-Stokes Fellowship Committee. He must, furthermore, pursue research work concerning the negro in the South; encourage investigation and a wider general interest in the negro problem among the students of the University and of other colleges in Virginia; procure lectures upon negro topics for the University, to be delivered by lecturers approved in advance by the Committee; prepare a report embodying the results of his work during incumbency; and write a thesis upon some subject approved in advance by the Committee; which thesis must be submitted in completed form or in satisfactory abstract not later than May 15 of the year of the holder's incumbency. In awarding the fellowship, preference will be given to students in the Department of Graduate Studies, but applications from students in the professional departments will also be considered. The Rector and Visitors Fellowships in the Schools of English, English Literature, and Romanic Languages: three, with an income of $180 each, and the remission of fees. The holder must be a graduate student, and must devote a portion of his time to work connected with one of the designated Schools. Appointments are made upon the recommendation of the professors in charge. The William Cabell Rives Fellowship in History, with an income of $250, and the remission of fees: Founded in 1905, upon the gift of Dr. William Cabell Rives, of Washington, D. C., in honor of his grandfather, William Cabell Rives, the distinguished statesman. The holder must be a graduate student, and must devote a portion of his time to work connected with the School of History. Appointments are made upon the recommendation of the professors of History. The Service Fellowships in Biology: five, with an income of $250 to $750 each. Founded in 1929. The holder must have a baccalaureate degree from a college or university of recognized standing, and must have received a thorough under-graduate training in biology. He will pursue graduate work in Biology and related subjects, and devote not more than fifteen hours a week to instructional work. Appointments are made upon the recommendation of the School of Biology. The Service Fellowships in Chemistry: several, with an income of $450. Founded in 1919. The holder must have a baccalaureate degree from a college or university of recognized standing, and must have received a thorough undergraduate training in chemistry and physics. He will pursue graduate work in Chemistry and related subjects, and devote not more than fifteen hours a week to instructional work. Appointments are made upon the recommendation of the School of Chemistry. Applications should be sent to the Secretary of the Faculty of Chemistry. The Service Fellowships in Economics: two, with an income of $450 each. Founded in 1925. The holder must be a graduate student in Economics and related subjects, and must devote a portion of his time to instructional work in the Schools of Economics and Commerce. Appointments are made upon the recommendation of the School of Economics. The Service Fellowships in Physics: seven, with incomes varying from $200 to $500 each. The amount in any one case is determined by the special fitness of the applicant and is subject to a possible increase from year to year. The holder must have a baccalaureate degree and must pursue graduate studies with Physics for his Major Subject. Should he develop a special aptitude for research, his teaching duties will be lightened as much as possible. Applications should be sent to the Professor in charge, Rouss Physical Laboratory, University, Va. The Vanderbilt Fellowships in Astronomy: three, with an income of $350 each, and the remission of fees. Founded in 1896 in honor of William Henry Vanderbilt, of New York. The holder must be a graduate student taking Astronomy as his Major Subject, and must occupy a portion of his time in work connected with the observatory. Appointments are made upon the recommendation of the Director of the Observatory. LOAN FUNDS Applicants for loans, if not already registered as students in the University, must have complied with all the requirements for entrance. All inquiries concerning loans should be addressed to the Bursar. Lelia S. Bennett Loan Fund.—Established in 1926 by a bequest of $5,000 by Mrs. Lelia S. Bennett, of Albemarle County. Loans are made to deserving students in any department of the University. Francis Philip duPont Loan Fund.—Established in 1930 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia from surplus income, arising from the Philip Francis duPont bequest. Loans not exceeding $150 per session will be made from this fund to deserving students in any department of the University. Doctor Charles Hooks Harris Medical Student Loan Fund.—Established in 1923 by a gift of $100 per year for a period of ten years, from Dr. Seale Harris, of Birmingham, Ala., in memory of his father. In making awards from the fund preference will be given to applicants from Cedartown, Ga., upon the recommendation of the Superintendent and Principal of the Cedartown High School and Mr. J. C. Harris, Superintendent of the Georgia School for the Deaf, Cave Springs, Ga. If there be no applicant from Cedartown High School, then the award will be made by the President and Dean of the Department of Medicine of the University. Fairfax Harrison Loan Fund.—Established in 1915 by the gift of $200 from Fairfax Harrison, of Washington, D. C. Loans from this fund are made to deserving students in any department of the University. Harvard Loan Fund.—The Harvard Loan Fund was established in February, 1909, by an alumnus of Harvard University, who gave to the University of Virginia the sum of $5,000 as an evidence of the friendship and kindly relations existing between the two institutions. Loans from this fund will be made to needy and deserving students pursuing or intending to pursue studies in any department of the University, in amounts not to exceed $100 in any one session to a single student, at an annual rate of interest of four per cent. Kiwanis Club Loan Fund.—Established in 1922 by the gift of $100 annually from the Charlottesville, Va., Kiwanis Club. Loans are made to deserving Virginia students in any department of the University. Robert E. Lee Loan Fund.—In October, 1914, a gift of $10,000 was made to the University by a veteran of the Federal Army, who wished in this way to express his interest in this institution and his admiration for General Lee. Loans from this fund will be made to deserving students in any department who stand in need of such assistance. Lynchburg Alumni Chapter Loan Fund.—Established in 1915 by the gift of $200, with an approximately equal sum annually, to be loaned to students from Lynchburg and vicinity, upon the recommendation of the officers of the Chapter. Seven Society Loan Fund.—Established in June, 1915, by a gift of $500 from the Seven Society of the University. Loans are made to deserving students in any department of the University. The Henry Strong Educational Foundation.—From this fund established under the will of General Henry Strong, of Chicago, an annual allotment is made to the University of Virginia for loan scholarships, available for the use of young men and women students under the age of twenty-five years, preferably in the upper classes, to aid them in obtaining a "practical, literary, scientific, mechanical or business education." Virginia Students' Loan Fund.—The Virginia Students' Loan Fund was established by an act of the General Assembly of Virginia, approved March 14, 1908, and amounts each year to one per cent. of the annual appropriation made by the Legislature for the support of the University. In accordance with the terms of this act, loans will be made "to needy and deserving students of talent and character, from Virginia," in amounts not to exceed $150 in any one session to a single student, at an annual rate of interest of four per cent. Sarah E. Wright Memorial Loan Fund.—Established in 1915 by a gift of $750. Loans from this fund are made to deserving students in any department of the University. ANNOUNCEMENT OF COURSES SCHOOL OF ANCIENT LANGUAGES I. Greek Greek C1: Greek B1 and B2 prerequisite.—Aristophanes. Professor Webb. Greek C2: Greek B1 and B2 prerequisite.—Sophocles. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Professor Webb. Greek D1: Greek Literary Criticism: Aristotle, Longinus, Dionysius of Halicarnassus. Professor Webb. Greek D2: Greek Epigraphy: A study of the inscriptions of the ancient Greeks. Associate Professor Fraser. II. Latin Latin C: Both B courses prerequisite.—Courses leading to the degree of Master of Arts. The requirements lie only in the School of Ancient Languages. If the candidate's major work be in Latin, Greek B1 and B2 are the minimum requirements. Latin C1: Latin B1 and B2 prerequisite.—I. In Language: Advanced prose composition. II. In Literature: Tacitus, Annals; Pliny, Letters and Petronius, Satiricon; Juvenal, Satires and selections from other satirists. III. In Life: The economic life of the Romans. (M.A. credit, 3 session-hours.) Given in alternate years with Latin C3. Professor Lehman and Mr. Constantine. Latin C2: Latin B1 and B2 prerequisite. I. In Language: Advanced prose composition. II. In Literature: Tacitus, Histories; Seneca, Moral Essays and Tragedies; Lucretius, De Rerum Natura. III. In Life: The philosophical life of the Romans. (M.A. credit, 3 session-hours.) Given in alternate years with Latin C4. Professor Montgomery and Mr. Constantine. Latin C3: Latin B1 and B2 prerequisite.—I. In Language: Advanced prose composition. II. In Literature: Latin Literature from the fifth century on, with special emphasis on the Latin of the Middle Ages. III. In Life: The literary life of the Romans in the Silver Age. (M.A. credit, 3 session-hours.) Given in alternate years with Latin C1. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Professor Lehman and Mr. Constantine. Latin C4: Latin B1 and B2 prerequisite.—I. In Language: Advanced prose composition. II. In Literature: Selections from Patristic Literature from Tertullian to Gregory the Great. III. In Life: The literary life of the Romans through the Golden Age. (M.A. credit, 3 session-hours.) Given in alternate years with Latin C2. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Professor Montgomery and Mr. Constantine. Latin D: All C courses prerequisite.—A course leading to the degree of Doctor of Philosophy. The requirements lie only in the School of Ancient Languages. If the candidate's major work be in Greek, the completion of two courses in Latin C will be the minimum requirement. If in Latin, the completion of Greek C1 will be the minimum requirement. It is the purpose of this course to prepare the candidate for independent investigation of the sources of knowledge of the language, the monuments (literary and objective), and the life of the Romans. The following is an outline of the course: Latin D1: Early Roman Comedy, Plautus, and Terence: Two hours weekly, each term. Professor Montgomery. Latin D2: The History of Latin Satire, with Readings from Representative Authors: Two hours weekly, each term. Professor Lehman. Latin D3: The Roman Historians: Two hours weekly, each term. Professor Lehman. Latin D4: The Roman Epic: Two hours weekly, each term. Professor Montgomery. Latin D5: Latin Epigraphy: Three hours weekly, each term. Associate Professor Fraser. Latin D6: Latin Palaeography: One hour weekly, for two terms. Professor Lehman. Latin D7: Historical Latin Grammar and Vulgar Latin: Two hours weekly for one term, and one hour weekly for two terms. Professor Montgomery. Latin D8: Comparative Philology: Two hours weekly, for one term. Professor Lehman. Sandy's History of Classical Philology will be required throughout the entire D course. III. Archaeology Archaeology C1: Classical Sculpture: Prerequisite for undergraduates, Archaeology B2.—Advanced study in Greek and Roman sculpture. Given in alternate years with Archaeology C2. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Associate Professor Fraser. Archaeology C2: Greek Vases: Prerequisite for undergraduates, as for Archaeology C1.—Advanced study in Greek pottery. Given in alternate years with Archaeology C1. Associate Professor Fraser. Archaeology C3: The Homeric Age: Prerequisite for undergraduates, Greek A2 and Archaeology B1, B2, or B4.—A study of the geography and archaeology, and antiquities of the Homeric Age. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Associate Professor Fraser. Archaeology D1: The Topography and Monuments of Ancient Athens. Associate Professor Fraser. Archaeology D2: The Topography and Monuments of Ancient Rome. Associate Professor Fraser. SCHOOL OF ASTRONOMY Astronomy C1: Practical Astronomy: Astronomy B1 and Mathematics B2 prerequisite.—Astronomical observations and their reduction, theory of errors, application of statistical methods to astronomical problems. Assistant Professors Vyssotsky and van de Kamp. Astronomy C2: Celestial Mechanics: Astronomy B1 and Mathematics B2 prerequisite.—Problems of two, three and n bodies, perturbations, determination of a preliminary orbit. Assistant Professor Vyssotsky. Astronomy C3: Introduction to Astrophysics: Physics B2 and Mathematics B2 prerequisite.—One hour weekly. Assistant Professor van de Kamp. Astronomy D1: Advanced Practical Astronomy: Astronomy C1 prerequisite.—Determination of the position of fixed stars, use of transit instrument, equatorials and measuring machines. Professor Mitchell. Astronomy D2: Advanced Celestial Mechanics: Astronomy C2 prerequisite.—Determination of the position of an undisturbed body from known elements, determination of the elements of an undisturbed orbit, perturbations. Professor Mitchell. Astronomy D3: Astrophysics: Astronomy C1 prerequisite.—A discussion of astronomical problems. Professor Mitchell. Astronomy D4: Photographic Astronomy: Astronomy C1 prerequisite.— Theory and reduction of astronomical photographs, including spectrograms. Professor Mitchell. The Leander McCormick Observatory is situated upon Mount Jefferson, which furnishes an unobstructed horizon. The principal building is a rotunda forty-five feet in diameter, containing the Clark refractor of twenty-six inches aperture which was the largest in the world when constructed. The instrument and building are the gift of the late Leander J. McCormick, Esq., of Chicago. The telescope is fitted with micrometer, photometer, and plateholder for stellar photography. The offices adjoining contain clocks, chronograph, machines for measuring astronomical photographs and spectrograms, a microphometer, and an excellent working library. In detached buildings are: (1) a three-inch transit and a six-inch Clark equatorial with three photographic cameras; and (2) a ten-inch photographic telescope and objective prism. The members of the Visiting Committee of the Leander McCormick Observatory are: THE PRESIDENT OF THE UNIVERSITY. THE RECTOR OF THE UNIVERSITY. MR. ROBERT HALL McCORMICK. MR. LEANDER MCCORMICK-GOODHART. THE DIRECTOR OF THE HARVARD COLLEGE OBSERVATORY. THE DIRECTOR OF THE LEANDER MCCORMICK OBSERVATORY. For information in regard to the Vanderbilt Fellowships in astronomy, see page 16. JOHN B. CARY MEMORIAL SCHOOL OF BIBLICAL LITERATURE Biblical Literature C1: Any two courses from the English Group prerequisite.—Comparative literature. Ecclesiastes, Job, the Mosaic Law, and Ezekiel's Ideal State in comparison with related masterpieces in English Literature and translations into English. Professor Forrest. Biblical Literature C2: (Philosophy C34): Any two B courses in Biblical Literature or Philosophy prerequisite.—An investigation of the Jewish and Hellenistic elements entering into the theology of Christianity during the first two centuries. (But one course will be given, the selection being left to a majority of the class electing a course in this school.) Professor Forrest. MILLER SCHOOL OF BIOLOGY AND AGRICULTURE AND BLANDY EXPERIMENTAL FARM A fee is charged for each laboratory course at the rate of $10 for three terms, $7 for two terms, and $4 for one term. Any course may be withdrawn unless elected by at least four students. I. Biology and Agriculture Biology C1: Evolution and Heredity: Biology B1 prerequisite.—Evolution, the theory and its history; the principles of heredity and their application to human problems. Three hours of lecture per week. Professor Lewis. Biology C2: Genetics: Biology B1 prerequisite.—A study of the fundamental principles of heredity, with special emphasis on their various applications and on the origins and relations of characters. First and second terms only. Three hours of lecture and six hours of laboratory per week. Professor White. Biology C3: Economic Plants: Biology B1 prerequisite.—A study of the family groups of plants from the standpoint of their value to man. Lectures and demonstrations, three hours per week. First and second terms only. Professor White. Biology C4: Principles of Plant Physiology: Biology B1 and Chemistry B1 prerequisite.—Designed to emphasize the fundamental principles underlying the more important aspects of Plant Physiology. The course is intended especially for those who desire a basic, yet elementary point of view. Experiments will be performed dealing with such subjects as physiology of the living cell,— osmosis, permeability, metabolism, respiration, as well as other physico-chemical properties of protoplasm; physiology of the organism as a whole,—photosynthesis, mineral nutrition, water relations, growth, reproduction and environmental influences. Three hours of lecture and six hours of laboratory per week. First and second terms. Assistant Professor Davis. Biology D1: Advanced Work in Genetics: Each student will be expected to carry out original investigations bearing on problems in this field. Hours by appointment. This course includes an evening seminar, meeting once a week throughout the year. Professor White. Biology D2: Advanced Cellular Physiology: Biology B1, Chemistry B1, prerequisite; Chemistry B3, Physics B1, and Mathematics B2 recommended.— This course deals with the physiological mechanism of the living cell. Considerable attention will be paid to the physico-chemical nature of protoplasm, the biological significance of hydrogen-ion concentration, enzyme studies, plant and animal pigments, oxidation-reduction phenomena and other metabolic relations of cells and tissues. The physical and chemical facts and principles prerequisite to the treatment outlined above will be thoroughly discussed. Topics will be assigned individually referring to original literature. Three hours of lecture per week. Assistant Professor Davis. Biology D3: Plant Physiology Research: Original investigation in some of the lines mentioned above, more especially those enumerated under Biology D2, or problems associated with the filtrable virus diseases of plants. Hours by appointment. Assistant Professor Davis. II. Botany Botany C1: Plant Morphology: Biology B1 prerequisite.—The evolution of plants based on a morphological study of a series of types, which will represent the more important families of algae, fungi, liverworts, mosses, ferns, and seed plants. First and second terms only. Three hours of lecture and six hours of laboratory per week. Professor Lewis and Assistant Professor Betts. Botany C2: Taxonomy of the Flowering Plants: Biology B1 prerequisite. —Fresh and herbarium specimens will be used for study. Three hours of lecture and six hours of laboratory per week. Third term only. Assistant Professor Betts. Botany D1: Advanced work along some of the lines indicated above. The work will be varied to suit the needs of students applying for the course. Hours by appointment. Professor Lewis. III. Zoölogy. Zoölogy C1: Experimental Zoölogy: Biology B1 prerequisite.—A comparative study of the morphology and behavior of typical invertebrates. Three hours of lecture and six hours of laboratory per week. The work of the first two terms of this course is based upon the lower invertebrates and represents a complete course. Professor Kepner. Zoölogy C2: Parasitology: Biology B1 prerequisite.—A study of the parasitic protozoa, worms, and insects, with special emphasis on those which attack man. In each case some of the free-living forms will be studied as a basis for comparison. The scope of this work will include morphological studies, life-histories and the methods utilized by the parasites in getting from one host to another. Discussion of current literature by the students may be substituted for a lecture at any time. Three hours of lecture and six hours of laboratory per week. First and second terms only. Associate Professor Reynolds. Zoölogy C3: Medical Entomology: Biology B1 prerequisite.—A study of the parasitic arthropods, especially those that attack man. Three hours of lecture and six hours of laboratory per week. Third term only. Associate Professor Reynolds. Zoölogy C4: Comparative Vertebrate Anatomy: Biology B1 prerequisite. —This course is introduced by a general study of representative species of chordates. A comparative study is made of the various organic systems found in the different classes of vertebrates with special reference to their origin, structure and function. Ample opportunity is afforded for vertebrate dissection. Three hours of lecture and six hours of laboratory per week. First and second terms only. Dr. Gilbert. Zoölogy C5: Comparative Vertebrate Embryology: Biology B1 prerequisite.—A study of the development of vertebrate embryos, especially the frog, chick and pig. Some practice in embryological technique will be afforded. Three hours of lecture and six hours of laboratory per week. Third term only. Dr. Gilbert. Zoölogy D1: Advanced work along lines suggested by the student's interest and needs. Independent research will be demanded of each member of the class. Hours by appointment. Professor Kepner. Zoölogy D2: Research on the morphology, physiology, or genetics of protozoa. Hours by appointment. Associate Professor Reynolds. Seminar: Weekly meetings are held for the study of current literature and the discussion of research in progress. Attendance is required of all students in graduate courses. Note: Additional graduate courses are offered during the Summer Quarter at the Mountain Lake Biological Station. Further information may be obtained from the Secretary of the Summer Quarter, Box 1337, University, Virginia. The Biological Laboratory, completed in 1920, is provided freely with electricity, gas, and water. The equipment consists of compound microscopes of the best types, microtomes, paraffin ovens, incubators, sterilizers, and other apparatus required for general and advanced work. Special appartus will be provided as needed. The departmental library contains a working collection of biological texts and books of reference, as well as files of the more important journals, and a series of biological reprints. Affiliated with the Miller School of Biology is the Blandy Experimental Farm, established by bequest of the late Graham F. Blandy. The Director, Professor Orland E. White, is in residence at the University during the first two terms. During the third term and Summer Quarter he directs research of advanced students at the farm, which is in Clarke County, Virginia. For such students the farm serves as a field laboratory for experimental work. Fellowships: There are available five research fellowships in Genetics in connection with the Blandy Experimental Farm. These carry honorariums varying from $500 to $1,000. All five include free tuition. These fellowships present an opportunity for graduate study and research accompanied by a limited amount of instructional work involving not over one hundred hours. They cover a period of eleven months annually, and are designed to encourage investigational work leading towards advanced degrees. They are open to men and women with a bachelor's degree from a college or university of recognized standing, who have had special training in biological and agricultural subjects. The first two terms are spent at the University, the remainder of the time at the Blandy Experimental Farm. A limited number of General Education Board Research Fellowships are available, the emolument varying from $500 to $1,000 according to the training and qualification of the holders. Requirements for the Degree of Doctor of Philosophy: Students who select biology as their Major Subject, in addition to meeting the regular University requirements, must have a general knowledge of related sciences, such as chemistry, geology and physics; and a comprehensive knowledge of the various aspects of biology, as attested by the completion of prescribed courses and such examinations as may be imposed. Special attention is called to University requirements relating to French and German. The completion of residence requirements and class work does not guarantee a degree to any student. The preeminent qualifications are thoroughness, resourcefulness, initiative and ability to do creative work. SCHOOL OF CHEMISTRY A fee of $20.00 and a breakage deposit of $5.00 are required for each course involving laboratory work, and for research courses. Chemistry C1: Physical Chemistry: Chemistry B4, B6, B7, Physics B1, and some knowledge of calculus prerequisite.—An introductory study of atomic structure theory, kinetic theory and the principle of the conservation of energy form the foundations of the study of gases, liquids, solids, solutions and rates of reaction. A brief study of the direction of chemical change is then followed by the consideration of homogeneous and heterogeneous equilibria. Three hours of lecture and six hours of laboratory per week. Professor Benton, Assistant Professor Spencer and Assistant. Chemistry C2: Advanced Organic Chemistry: Chemistry B3 or B6 prerequisite, and C1 corequisite.—A systematic course of review and extension of the facts and theories of organic chemistry from an advanced viewpoint. Introductory discussions of special fields will be given. Particular emphasis will be laid on mechanism of reactions, structure, and stereochemistry. The laboratory work will consist of organic syntheses, quantitative and qualitative organic analysis, and an introduction to the methods of organic research. Three hours of lecture and six hours of laboratory per week. Associate Professor Lutz. Chemistry C3: Advanced Analytical Chemistry: Chemistry B4 prerequisite.—Lectures and recitations on special topics, including various physico-chemical methods of analysis and recent developments in analytical chemistry. The laboratory work varies from year to year and covers such subjects as Rock, Ore, Steel, Gas, Coal, and Water Analysis. One class hour and six laboratory hours per week. Professor Yoe. Chemistry C4: Applied Chemistry: Chemistry B6 and C1 prerequisite.— The lectures and recitations in this course are devoted to the study of fundamental principles underlying the more important phases of industrial chemistry, including both theoretical and economic problems. A considerable amount of collateral reading in descriptive industrial chemistry is assigned, and written reports involving use of the literature are required. Better appreciation of the quantitative relationships existing in the applications of chemistry is gained through problem work paralleling the lecture material. A number of plant inspection trips are arranged during the year. Lectures and recitations, three hours per week. Associate Professor Hitchcock. Chemistry C5: Thermodynamics and Chemistry: A systematic study of the application of thermodynamics in the solution of chemical problems. Three class hours per week. Assistant Professor Spencer. Chemistry C6: Micro Organic Analysis: Second or third term. Dr. Small. Chemistry D1: Atomic Structure: An introduction to the modern theory of atomic and molecular structure and its application in the study of the chemical and physical properties of matter. Radioactivity, crystal structure and an outline of the theory of atomic and molecular spectra are included. Three class hours per week. Professor Benton. Chemistry D2: Special Topics in Organic Chemistry: Chemistry C1, C2, and a reading knowledge of German prerequisite.—A course designed for graduate students specializing in Organic Chemistry. It includes discussion of such subjects as: Terpenes, molecular rearrangements, homo- and heterocyclics, carbohydrates, proteins, natural products, alkaloids, drugs, dyes, electronic concepts, and theories of reaction mechanism and valence. Individual study of original literature and occasional reports are required. Three hours per week. Associate Professor Lutz. Chemistry D3: The Kinetics of Chemical Reaction: A course designed for graduate students interested in the field of reaction kinetics and catalysis. Three class hours per week. Professor Benton. Chemistry D4: Selected Topics in Physical Chemistry: Conducted as a seminar for students specializing in Physical Chemistry. The topics chosen vary from year to year, and cover such fields as kinetic theory, photochemistry, phase rule, electrochemistry, etc. Three class hours per week. Professor Benton. Chemistry D5: Advanced Thermodynamics: A course designed for students specializing in Physical Chemistry, covering such topics as derivation of thermodynamic data from band spectra, systematic calculation of thermodynamic data of related substances, etc. Three class hours per week. Assistant Professor Spencer. Research Courses: Graduate students may undertake original investigation, under the direction of a member of the staff, in any of the branches of chemistry for which adequate facilities are available, as indicated below. In every case the student must satisfy the instructor that his preparation qualifies him to pursue research with profit. Hours will be arranged in conference with the instructor. In order that ample time may be available, no student will be permitted to elect more than one laboratory course in addition to research. Chemistry D20: Physical Chemistry, including Reaction Kinetics, Catalysis and Adsorption. Professor Benton. Chemistry D21: Physical Chemistry, including Thermodynamics and Electrochemistry. Assistant Professor Spencer. Chemistry D22: Organic Chemistry. Professor Bird. Chemistry D23: Organic Chemistry, including problems concerning synthesis, structure, reaction mechanism and oxidation-reduction potentials. Associate Professor Lutz and Dr. Small. Note: Unusual facilities for special research in the chemistry of alkaloids and drugs are offered in the alkaloid laboratory recently opened under the auspices of the National Research Council. Graduate students of exceptional ability may be admitted to this laboratory upon application to Dr. Small or to Dr. Mosettig. Chemistry D24: Analytical Chemistry, including Colorimetry and Nephelometry. Professor Yoe. Chemistry D25: Colloid Chemistry. Professor Yoe. The Chemical Journal Club will meet once a week (hour to be arranged) for the critical review and discussion of various topics of interest in current chemical literature and of such chemical researches as are in progress in the University. All members of the teaching staff and advanced students in chemistry are expected to participate in these meetings and to take part in the discussions. The Chemical Laboratory, recently completed, is of brick, fire-proof construction, and the three floors afford 45,000 square feet of space. The seven larger laboratories will accommodate 575 students, and in addition to these there are numerous smaller laboratories for the use of the staff and advanced students. There are also rooms for various special purposes, including three dark rooms. The equipment is satisfactory for purposes of both instruction and research. The laboratory maintains a working library containing about 5,000 volumes directly relating to chemistry, as well as complete files of the important periodicals. A gift to the School of Chemistry from Mrs. Hamilton Barksdale in memory of her husband, and from Delaware alumni and friends of the University, provides an annual income sufficient for the adequate maintenance of the library. Requirements for the Degree of Doctor of Philosophy: In addition to fulfilling the regular University requirements for the Degree of Doctor of Philosophy, candidates for this degree who select chemistry as their Major Subject must give evidence of thorough training in inorganic, organic, analytical, and physical chemistry, by passing written qualifying examinations in these subjects; these examinations to be passed not later than October 15th of the session in which it is expected that the degree will be conferred. Fellowships: There are available each session a number of Service Fellowships in Chemistry. These fellowships present the opportunity for graduate study and research in Chemistry, accompanied by a limited amount of instructional work. Holders of the fellowships will be expected to devote not more than fifteen hours a week to instruction, leaving ample time for research and work toward a graduate degree. On reappointment the required amount of instructional work may be reduced. The fellowships are open to men who have received a bachelor's degree from a college or university of recognized standing, and who have received thorough undergraduate training in chemistry and physics. Preference will be given to applicants who have studied calculus, German, and French. In addition to the Service Fellowships, a number of advanced Fellowships, requiring no instructional work, are also available to students who have already had graduate training in chemistry in this University or elsewhere. Applications for Fellowships should be made before March 1, on forms obtainable from the Secretary of the Chemistry Faculty. McINTIRE SCHOOL OF COMMERCE See James Wilson School of Economics for courses in economics not listed here. Economics C3: Advanced Accounting: Economics B4 and one other B course in the School of Economics or in the School of Commerce prerequisite.— The content of this course is based upon the content of Economics B9, but it is adapted to graduate students. Professor Barlow and Mr. Dandelake. Economics C4: Corporation Finance: Economics B1 and B4 prerequisite. —The course falls into two main divisions. (a) The financial policies of corporations with respect to the instruments of long term finance, the working capital position, the administration of income, the causes of failure and problems of reorganization. (b) The principles of investment. Professor Kincaid and Mr. Fitzell. Economics C5: Foreign Trade: Economics B1 and one other course in the School of Economics or School of Commerce prerequisite.—An analysis of the economic principles underlying foreign trade, commercial treaties and tariffs, financial settlements and foreign exchange. In the third term a study will be made of various problems in foreign trade including foreign markets, the gold standard, U. S. trade as a creditor nation, the American mercantile marine. Acting Assistant Professor Nelson. Economics C6: Labor Problems: Economics B1 and one other course in the School of Economics or School of Commerce prerequisite.—A study of the relations between employer and employee, agencies for the promotion of industrial peace including profit-sharing plans, bonus systems, co-operative enterprises, etc., a study of representative plans for the management of labor, copartnership and labor organizations. Associate Professor Starnes. Economics C7: Business Combinations: Economics B1 and one other course in the School of Economics or School of Commerce prerequisite.—A study of various kinds of business units and of the growth of large business organizations in this country and in Europe in recent times. Special emphasis is given to the causes of this growth, the forms, legal status and relations to business, efficiency of these combinations, and the social problems arising out of their formation. The organization of pools, cartels, holding companies, mergers, etc., is investigated particularly with reference to price policies. Professor Berglund and Mr. Hunsberger. Economics C10: Transportation: Economics B1 and one other course in the School of Economics or School of Commerce prerequisite.—A study of modern transportation systems, especially rail and water lines. Special attention is given to character of traffic, rate-making systems, recent governmental regulations and policies and problems of railroad and shipping finance. This course calls for advanced investigation of rate-making and traffic problems and of governmental policies. Professor Berglund and Mr. Holsinger. Economics C12: Regulation of Public Utilities: Economics B1 and one other course in the School of Economics or School of Commerce prerequisite.— A study of basic principles and trends in the regulation of public utilities in the United States with special emphasis upon the determination of the rate base, rates and rate structure of utilities other than railroads. In the third term special attention will be given to regulation as a phase of social planning. Acting Assistant Professor Nelson. JAMES WILSON SCHOOL OF ECONOMICS See McIntire School of Commerce for courses in economics not listed here. Economics C1: Public Finance: Economics B1 and one other B course in the School of Economics or School of Commerce prerequisite.—First and second terms: The general principles of public finance, with a detailed investigation of state and local taxation. Third term: The financial institution and methods of the federal government. Professor Snavely and Mr. Ellett. Economcs C2: Advanced Money and Banking: Economics B1 and one other B course in the School of Economics or School of Commerce prerequisite. —The course includes: (a) Money, bank credit and prices; (b) central banks and (c) business cycles. Professor Kincaid and Mr. Cain. Economics C8: Economic Evolution in Western Europe: Economics B1 and one other course in the School of Economics or School of Commerce prerequisite.—A treatment of the development of the economic basis of modern civilization will form the background for an investigation of the working of economic laws and a critical consideration of the actual problems that presented themselves for solution in ancient, medieval and modern times. Emphasis will be placed upon individual work and group discussion. Associate Professor Hyde. Economics C11: The Development of Economic Thought: Economics B1 and one other course in the School of Economics or School of Commerce prerequisite.—First and second terms: A study of the main currents of economic thought from the earliest times to the end of the nineteenth century. Third term: A critical study of current economic thought. Associate Professor Starnes. Economics D1: History of Economic Theory: First term. Economic Theory to the time of Adam Smith. Associate Professor Starnes. Second term: Adam Smith and his contemporaries. Professor Kincaid. Third term: Ricardo and Mill. Professor Snavely. Economics D2: Economic Theory Since the Middle of the Nineteenth Century: First and second terms: Neo-classical Economics. Professor Snavely. Third term: The Historical and Psychological Schools. Professor Berglund. Economics D3: Problems in Recent Economic Theory. Economics D4: Economic Research. Professors Snavely, Barlow, Berglund and Kincaid, Associate Professors Starnes, Hulvey, Hyde and Acting Assistant Professor Nelson. SCHOOL OF EDUCATION In 1920 the Curry Memorial School of Education was organized as a Department of the University, coördinate with the other professional Departments. The courses in Education, however, also count as Electives-at-Large and Major-Electives toward the degrees of Bachelor of Arts and Bachelor of Science in the College. The following is a list of the courses offered. A detailed statement of each course will be found under the announcement of the Curry Memorial Department of Education. Education C2: Problems in School Administration: Education B5 and Education B7 or B8 prerequisite.—To be given in alternate years with Education C3. Professor Manahan and Assistant Professor Jarman. Education C3: Problems in Elementary School Supervision: Education B5 and Education B7 or B8 prerequisite.—To be given in alternate years with Education C2. Professor Manahan and Assistant Professor Jarman. Education C4: Problems in High School Administration: Education B7 and Education B8 or B5 prerequisite.—To be given in alternate years with Education C5. Professor Smithey. Education C5: Problems in High School Supervision: Education B8 and one other B course in Education prerequisite.—To be given in alternate years with Education C4. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Professor Smithey. Education C6: Mental Measurement: Psychology B1 and one B course in Education prerequisite. Professor Ferguson. Education C7: Problems in Elementary Education: 6 session-hours in elementary education prerequisite. Professor Manahan and Assistant Professors Acker and McLester. Note: Psychology C3, Genetic Psychology, Psychology C4, Theoretical Psychology, Psychology C5, Systematic Psychology, Psychology C6, Special Topics in Genetic Pyschology, Psychology C7, History of Psychology, and Psychology C8, Statistical Method, may be offered toward meeting the requirements for graduate degrees in Education. See descriptions of these courses under School of Psychology. Education D1: Seminar in Educational Psychology: Hours by appointment. Professor Ferguson. Education D2: Seminar in School Administration: Hours by appointment. Professor Manahan. Education D3: Seminar in Secondary Educaton: Hours by appointment. Professor Smithey. Education D4: Seminar in Elementary Education: Hours to be arranged. Professor Manahan and Assistant Professors Acker, Jarman and McLester. SCHOOLS OF ENGLISH LANGUAGE AND LITERATURE Linden Kent Memorial School of English Literature Edgar Allan Poe School of English English C1: The Novel: Any two B courses in the Schools of English Language and Literature prerequisite.—1. The early English novel and its background. 2. The later nineteenth-century novel. 3. The contemporary English novel. Professor Wilson. English C2: The Drama, Elizabethan and Modern: Any two B courses in the Schools of English Language and Literature prerequisite.—1. The Elizabethan drama (exclusive of Shakespeare). 2. Restoration and eighteenth-century drama. 3. The modern British drama. Associate Professor Gordon. English C3: Literature and Thought in England, 1789-1832 (Romantic Period): Any two B courses in the Schools of English Language and Literature prerequisite.—Some acquaintance with the course of English history is presumed, but is not prerequisite. English literature of the earlier nineteenth century studied in relation to the history, literary biography, and thought of the period. The course will link the fields of history and literature. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Associate Professor Davis. English C4: Literature and Thought in England, 1832-1900 (Victorian Period): Any two B courses in the Schools of English Language and Literature prerequisite.—Some acquaintance with the course of English history is presumed, but is not prerequisite. English literature of the middle and later nineteenth century studied in relation to the history, literary biography, and thought of the period. The course will link the fields of history and literature. Associate Professor Davis. English C5: Chaucer: Any two B courses in the Schools of English Language and Literature prerequisite.—A study of Chaucer's writings and background. Professor Hench. English C6: Literary Composition: English B6 and one other B course prerequisite. This course is open only to those of proved aptitude in Composition who have obtained the consent of the professor in charge.—1. Essay writing and book-reviewing. 2. The writing of sketches and short stories. 3. Dramatic composition. Parallel reading in current periodical literature. By consent also, this course may be taken two years in succession. Conferences. Associate Professor Gordon. English C7: Old English: Any two B courses in the Schools of English Language and Literature prerequisite.—1. Old English prose. 2. Old English poetry; Beowulf. 3. Beowulf. Professor Hench. English C8: Middle English: Any two B courses in the Schools of English Language and Literature prerequisite.—Lyrics of the Thirteenth and Fourteenth centuries and representative Metrical Romances. Professor Hench. English C9: Eighteenth-Century Prose Fiction: Any two B courses in the Schools of English Language and Literature prerequisite.—The Eighteenth-Century Novel with considerable parallel reading and frequent reports. The English Novel is traced from earliest times through the eighteenth century. Assistant Professor Shepperson. English C10: The History of the English Language: English B8 and one other B course prerequisite.—A reading knowledge of Old English is desirable. 1. Old English and its pre-history. 2. Old English Dialects. 3. Middle English dialects to the development of a standard language. Lectures, reading of texts with interpretations of forms and constructions. Hours by appointment. Associate Professor Hill. English C11: Middle English: Two B courses prerequisite.—Prose and Middle English Didactic Poetry. Hours by appointment. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Associate Professor Hill. English C12: Spenser and Milton: Two B courses in English Literature prerequisite.—1. Spenser's Minor Poems. 2. The Fairie Queene. 3. The Poetry of Milton. Professor Metcalf. The following courses are for advanced graduate students. English D1: 1. Edgar Allan Poe. 2. Nathaniel Hawthorne. Hours by appointment. Professor Wilson. English D2: 1. The Early English Drama. 2. Elizabethan Prose Literature. Hours by appointment. Professor Metcalf. English D3: Shakespeare and his Times: Hours by appointment. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Professor Wilson. English D4: 1. The Elizabethan Lyric. A reading knowledge of French and Italian is desirable. 2. Seventeenth-century Prose Literature. Hours by appointment. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Professor Metcalf. English D5: The Renaissance in England: 1. A study of some of the persons and movements on the continent contributing to the renaissance in England. 2. Studies in the literature and thought of England in the fifteenth and early sixteenth centuries. Hours by appointment. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Professor Hench. English D6: Chaucer Seminar: English C5, or its equivalent prerequisite. —The complete works of Chaucer, with the exception of the prose, will be read, with special attention to literary, bibliographical and historical problems. Each student will be expected to give a term paper involving some research during the third term. The course will be divided as follows: 1. The Canterbury Tales. 2. Troilus and Cressida. 3. The Minor Poems. Hours by appointment. Offered in alternate years if two or more qualified students apply. Associate Professor Hill. English D7: Seminar in Modern English: English C10 prerequisite.— The problems of Early Modern English and the interpretation of written records. Associate Professor Hill. English D8: Advanced Phonetics and the Investigation of Spoken English: English C10, or its equivalent, prerequisite.—Careful ear-training and the use of the International Phonetic Alphabet. The methods and aims of investigation of living speech. Associate Professor Hill. English D9: Low German: English C10 and any other course in philology prerequisite.—Study of texts and grammar of Old Saxon and Old Frisian. Associate Professor Hill. Note: English D7, D8, D9 will be offered when one or more qualified students present themselves, but only two of the three courses will be offered in any one year. Germanics D1: Gothic: Open to Graduate Students in English.—Three hours a week, first term, by appointment. Associate Professor Wood. Germanics D2: Old Norse: Open to Graduate Students in English.—Three hours a week, by appointment. Associate Professor Wood. French D1: Old French: Open to Graduate Students in English.—1. The development of the French language in the early medieval period. 2. French literature from the beginnings down to the fourteenth century. Associate Professor Mellor. Note: Candidates for Masters' degrees in English are required to take at least one of the following session-courses: English C5, C7, C8, C10, C11. Candidates for the Ph. D. must have English C7 and such other courses in language and literature as their major professors advise. Thesis subjects must be submitted to the chairman of the department for faculty approval by November 15 of the final year of candidacy. Preliminary Examination for the Doctorate in English: A student who desires to become a candidate for the Doctor's degree in English should stand a preliminary examination in October of the session preceding his final year of candidacy, and must take this examination not later than October 1 of his last year. The examination may be written or oral, or both, at the discretion of the examiners. In case the examination is not satisfactory, the applicant may be allowed, by permission of the examiners, to present himself for a second trial after a lapse of at least one academic term. If this second trial is unsatisfactory, no further examination will be allowed. At the discretion of the professors concerned, in the case of a student who has received the Master's degree from this institution, an exceptionally high rating on the work for that degree, including the oral examination and thesis, may be accepted as the equivalent of the preliminary examination for the doctorate. Subjects of proposed dissertation should be submitted for faculty approval after consultation with major professors. McINTIRE SCHOOL OF FINE ARTS I. Art Art C1: Drawing B1 and B2, or equivalent, prerequisite.—Outdoor sketching in color in the first and third terms, studio class in the second term. (M.S. credit, 2 session-hours.) Professor Campbell. Art C2: Drawing B2, or equivalent, prerequisite.—The drawing and rendering of architectural compositions in color. (B.S. or M.S. credit, 1, 2 or 3 session-hours, according to amount of work accomplished.) Professor Campbell. II. Architecture Architectural Design C1: Architectural Design B3, or equivalent, prerequisite.—The Class A, and prize competitions of the Beaux-Arts Institute of Design, and a thesis design. Not less than two years' work for a candidate for M.S. (M.S. credit, 6 session-hours.) Professor Campbell. Colonial Archaeology C1: Architectural Design B3, or equivalent, prerequisite.—The historical study with measurements and the drawing of a work of Architecture in Virginia of the Colonial or Federal period. (M.S. credit, 3 session-hours.) Professor Campbell. Architectural Building and Equipment: The School of Art and Architecture is housed in Fayerweather Hall, formerly the old gymnasium. The main gymnasium floor has been converted into faculty offices and a large drafting room for instruction in architectural drawing and design. Over the offices is a balcony arranged for group criticisms, judgment of student drawings and small exhibitions. The ground floor is occupied by two studios for water-colour and freehand drawing work, the Fine Arts Library, a small classroom and business office, The large classes have their lectures and classroom exercises in other University buildings. The library contains three thousand books and bound periodicals on painting, sculpture, architecture and the related minor arts. Additional books on philosophy of art, archaeology, the theatrical and musical arts are in other school libraries. The best of American and European architectural and art periodicals are subscribed to. A well-selected collection of slides and photographs for History of Art lectures is available. The School owns an ample collection of plaster casts and still-life objects necessary for teaching freehand drawing and water-colour as well as equipment for instruction in various black and white mediums. A gift by John Barton Payne of etchings by masters is owned by the University. A permanent collection of architectural drawings and water-colours for student inspiration is exhibited on walls. All the printed documents relating to Virginia Colonial Architecture are on the library shelves and a rapidly increasing collection of photographs on the same subject is being formed. Opportunities for original research in Virginia Colonial and Classical Revival Architecture are afforded by the neighborhood surrounding Charlottesville. III. Music Music C1: Advanced Composition: Music B5 and B6 prerequisite.—Advanced Harmony and Counterpoint, Canon, Fugue, and the larger homophonic forms. Professor Fickenscher. Music C2: Music in the History of Western Europe: Prerequisites: Two B courses in the School of Music or the equivalent acquired through private instruction and study elsewhere. Open to graduates and undergraduates.—Development of the Music and Liturgy of the Catholic Church during the Middle Ages and Italian Renaissance. Guido, Saint Ambrose. Gregory the Great and the Gregorian Chant. The Netherlands School, Palestrina. The influence of the Papal Choir in European Music. The religious and secular composers of the Classic and Romantic Periods. Bach, Handel and their successors. Hours to be arranged. Associate Professor Pratt. Equipment: The work offered re-establishes the instruction outlined in the first curriculum of the University, 1818, the earliest proposal for instruction in art, architecture, and music in any American university. An unrivalled background is provided for it by the buildings and environment of Charlottesville; the University group, with its old buildings specially designed to furnish examples of the various orders "as specimens for the architectural lectures," its new buildings designed by Stanford White; the works of sculpture by Houdon, Ezekiel, Bitter, Borglum, Keck, Shrady, and Aitken; the concerts and exhibitions of paintings brought to the University with part of the income of the McIntire fund. For Music, the Carnegie foundation has recently presented the school with the "Carnegie Music Set," comprising a Capehart Phonograph, 900 records, several hundred orchestral, piano and vocal scores, and 300 books for the General Library covering the historical, biographical, technical and popular aspects of musical art. The school has also two concert grand pianos, an Ampico reproducing grand piano and several phonographs. The equipment for radio reception includes microphone and mechanism for making aluminum records of home performances. A set of band instruments purchased by the Alumni Association, double basses, kettle drums, and various other unusual instruments for the use of students in the orchestra, a comprehensive library of chamber music, orchestral scores and parts, operas and piano classics, as well as books of reference on musical subjects and collateral reading. There are also available for the Music School a three-manual Skinner organ in Cabell Hall and a three-manual Moeller organ, the gift of Paul Goodloe McIntire in connection with the McIntire Amphitheatre, and a two-manual practice organ in the University Chapel. The following gifts have been made to the musical library: by Mr. Iredell Jenkins, a valuable collection of operas, oratorios, light operas, piano music, first editions; by Professor Gardner Lloyd Carter, piano music and books on musical subjects; by Mr. Charles Orchard, a set of biographical works; by Mrs. W. H. Sage, a collection of piano music, violin and cello sonatas, trios, quartettes and quintettes. IV. Dramatic Art Dramatic Art C1: Advanced Playwriting: Dramatic Art B1 and one other B course prerequisite. Open only to those of proved aptitude in playwriting who have obtained the consent of the professor in charge.—Each student will be required to satisfactorily complete a full length play. Hours to be arranged. Associate Professor Pratt. CORCORAN AND ROGERS SCHOOLS OF GENERAL AND ECONOMIC GEOLOGY Geology C1: Economic Geology: Geology B1 prerequisite.—General principles dealing with the classification, origin, distribution, mining, and uses of metallic and non-metallic ores. Special emphasis is given field trips to the various mines of the State. Laboratory hours to be arranged. (B.A. or B.S. credit, 6 session-hours.) Professor Nelson. Geology C2: Petrology: Geology B4 prerequisite.—(a) Physical Crystallography. Determination of minerals and rocks in thin sections under the microscope. Optical and microscopical mineralogy with especial reference to the behavior of minerals as constituents of rock masses. (b) Petrography. The microscopic structures, mineralogical composition, genetic relations and distribution of igneous, sedimentary and metamorphic rocks. Lectures and laboratory to the amount of nine hours per week throughout the year, to be arranged. (B.A. or B.S. credit, 6 session-hours.) Assistant Professor Pegau. Geology C3: Invertebrate Paleontology: Geology B1 prerequisite.—A systematic course in invertebrate paleontology covering the ontogeny, phylogeny, morphology, and distribution of forms found in the geologic record with a certain amount of identification in the laboratory. Hours to be arranged. (B.A. or B.S. credit, 6 session-hours.) Professor Roberts. Geology C4: Stratigraphy: Geology B1 prerequisite.—General principles of stratigraphy dealing with its history and development in America and more important principles of sedimentation. Lecture and laboratory hours to be arranged. (B.A. or B.S. credit, 6 session-hours.) Given in alternate years with Geology D1. Professor Nelson. Geology D1: Structural Geology: Geology B1 and C4 prerequisite.—A study of the structure of the rocks with especial emphasis on those of sedimentary origin, the causes of various structures, and the structural relations of the southern Appalachians. Hours by appointment. Given in alternate years with Geology C4. Professors Nelson and Roberts. Geology D2: Advanced Mineralogy and Petrography: Geology B4 and C2 prerequisite.—Adapted to the needs of the individual student. Properly qualified students may pursue work directed along the line of crystallography or chemical mineralogy or petrographic research. Hours by appointment. Assistant Professor Pegau. Geology D3: Advanced Economic Geology: Geology B4 and C1 prerequisite.—Special topics for students in economic geology selected according to the needs of the individual student. Hours by appointment. Professor Nelson. Geology D4: Advanced General Geology: A more thorough treatment of the principles of geology as a science and its history. The character of the work depends upon the needs and preparation of the student and the prerequisites should be Geology B1, B4, and C3. Hours to be arranged. Professor Nelson. Geology D5: Stratigraphical Paleontology: Geology B1, B4, C2 and C3 prerequisite.—The application of paleontology to stratigraphy, and the value of fossils in correlations. The geology of the Virginias emphasized from the Cambrian to the Pleistocene, and the index fossils are studied and collections are made from the various horizons. Hours by appointment. Professor Roberts. Journal Club: The staff, assistants, graduate and advanced students meet on stated evenings during the session for the discussion of current investigations in stratigraphy, economic geology, mineralogy, petrology, and paleontology. During the year several visiting geologists discuss current problems at the Club, and such meetings are open to the public. The Lewis Brooks Museum contains collections illustrating the main subdivisions of natural history. Each of the collections is arranged so as to exemplify the principles of the science, and at the same time offers a large variety of subjects for advanced study. In geology the specimens show the different kinds of rocks, classified according to mineral character and the formations in which they occur. The collections of fossils, plaster casts, maps, etc., are exceptionally fine, and illustrate historical geology. In mineralogy, the principles of the science are made plain by well-chosen suits of specimens, models of crystals, etc. The general collection of minerals contains all the important species, and many of the rarer ones, in good specimens. In addition to the above, a beginning has been made of a collection to illustrate the geology and mineralogy of the State of Virginia, and this is being increased as rapidly as possible. SCHOOL OF GERMANIC LANGUAGES German C: German B2 or B3, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Of the following C courses two are given each session, the choice being determined by the plan of study of the undergraduates who wish to major in German, and of the graduates who are offering German as part of their work for the Master's or the Doctor's degree. Students are therefore requested to confer with Professor Faulkner not later than June 1 preceding the session in which they plan to enter the course. In all C courses in German collateral reading in the history of German Literature and in German biography is required. German C1: Goethe's Life and Works, with intensive study of Faust. Professor Faulkner. German C2: Given in German.—Der deutsche Roman von Goethe bis zur Gegenwart, with intensive study of selected novels. Professor Faulkner. German C3: Given in German.—Deutsche Lyrik, with intensive study of of Goethe's Egmont, Schiller's Wallenstein, and Lessing's Nathan der Weise. Associate Professor Wood. German C4: Given in German.—Deutsche Lyrik, with intensive study of the lyrics of Goethe and of Heine, and of selected lyrics since 1870. Associate Professor Wood. Facilities for Graduate Study: Special funds recently received have made possible extensive additions to the library in German literature and Germanic philology. Candidates for the Master's degree will be required to complete not less than two of the C courses, listed above, and Germanics D3, Old and Middle High German. Candidates for the Doctorate will in addition complete a program of study covering not less than two full sessions. Candidates for the Master's degree will be required to file certificates showing not less than 4 entrance-units in Latin. Candidates for the Doctorate must, in addition, have credit for not less than one year of Greek or take and pass a beginners' course in Greek in the College of Arts and Sciences. The following courses are offered for such candidates in 1935-36. Deutsches Colloquium: Open only to students taking German B2 or some higher course. Required of students majoring in German.—Two hours a week of practice in speaking German. (No session-hour credit.) Assistant Professor Mohr and Dr. Volm. Germanics D1: 1. Gothic: Open to Graduate Students in English or German.—Three hours a week, first term, by appointment. 2. History of the German Language: German B2, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Three hours a week, second and third terms, by appointment. Associate Professor Wood. Germanics D2: Old Norse: Open to Graduate Students in English or German.—Three hours a week, by appointment. (Given in 1933-34.) Associate Professor Wood. Germanics D3: Seminar: German B2, or the equivalent, prerequisite.— First Term: Old High German; Broune's Althochdeutsches Lesebuch. Second and third terms: Middle High German: Hartmann von Aue's Iwein; the Nibelungenlied. Hours by appointment. (Given in 1933-34.) Associate Professor Wood. CORCORAN SCHOOL OF HISTORY History C1: History of European Civilization including Science, Religion and Morals: Two B courses prerequisite. Professor Dabney. History C2: Social History of the United States, 1776-1865: Two B courses, including B3, prerequisite. (Offered in 1936-37.) Associate Professor Abernethy. History C3: The Old South, 1776-1865: Two B courses, including B3, prerequisite. Associate Professor Abernethy. History C4: American History Since 1865: Two B Courses, including B3, prerequisite. (Offered in 1936-37.) Acting Assisting Professor Cappon. History C5: The French Revolution: Two B courses, including B2, together with a reading knowledge of French, prerequisite. Professor Barr. History C6: Napoleon: Two B courses, including B2, together with a reading knowledge of French, prerequisite. (Offered in 1936-37.) Professor Barr. History C7: The Italian Risorgimento: Two B courses, including B4, together with a reading knowledge of Italian, prerequisite. (Offered in 1937-38.) Professor Barr. History C8: The Expansion of England: Two B courses, including B4, prerequisite. (Offered in 1936-37.) Associate Professor T. C. Johnson. History C9: Medieval England: Two B courses, including B4, prerequisite. Associate Professor T. C. Johnson. History C10: Tudor and Stuart England: Two B courses, including B4, prerequisite.—Lectures and reports on the intellectual, social and economic aspects of English life, and England's contacts with foreign countries through trade relations. Assistant Professor Hale. History C11: Medieval Civilization: Two B courses, including B1, prerequisite.—Lectures and reports on the institutional, economic, and intellectual life of the Middle Ages. (Offered in 1937-38.) Assistant Professor Hale. History C12: Europe Since 1814: Two B courses, including B2, prerequisite.—Lectures and discussions on the social and economic aspects of the period, the progress of social legislation, nationalism, imperialism, and the background of the World War. Assistant Professor Hale. History C13: History of the West: Two B courses, including B3, prerequisite. Acting Assistant Professor Cappon. History D1: Seminar in the History of Virginia: Hours by appointment. Associate Professor Abernethy. History D2: Seminar in the History of European Diplomacy, 1870-1914: A reading knowledge of French or German is required. (Offered in 1936-37.) Assistant Professor Hale. SCHOOL OF MATHEMATICS Mathematics C1: Advanced Calculus: Mathematics B3 prerequsite.—Elliptic functions and integrals. Legendre's polynomials and Bessel's functions and their application to problems in attraction, the Gamma function, calculus of variations, and other related subjects, including an introduction to difference equations and to integral equations. Given in alternate years with Mathematics C3. Associate Professor Linfield. Mathematics C2: Differential Geometry: Mathematics B3 and B4 prerequisite.—Metric differential properties of curves and surfaces in Euclidean space of three dimensions. Professor Luck. Mathematics C3: Higher Geometry: Mathematics B2 prerequisite.—Algebraic plane curves; circle and sphere geometry; line geometry, including differential line geometry and the use of tensors. Given in alternate years with Mathematics C1. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Associate Professor Linfield. Mathematics C4: Theory of Functions of a Real Variable: Mathematics B2 prerequisite.—The real number system; linear point sets; continuity and discontinuity of functions; differentiation and differentials, jacobians, integration: Riemann and Lebesgue theories; improper integrals. Infinite series: general convergence theories; power series; Fourier's series and integrals. Professor Whyburn. Mathematics C5: Theory of the Functions of a Complex Variable. Professor in Charge to be Announced Later. Mathematics C6: Introductory Topology: Mathematics B2 prerequisite.— Foundations of mathematics based on a set of axioms; metric spaces; convergence and connectivity properties of point sets; continua and continuous curves; the topology of the plane. Professor Whyburn. Mathematics C7: a. Foundations of Geometry. b. Non-Euclidean Geometry. Professor Whyburn. Mathematics D1: Set Theoretic Topology. Professor Whyburn. Mathematics D2: Combinatory Topology. Professor in Charge to be Announced Later. Mathematics D3: Analysis. Professor in Charge to be Announced Later. Mathematics D4: Analytic Sets and Abstract Spaces. Professor Whyburn. Mathematics D5: Application of Topology to Function. Professor in Charge to be Announced Later. The courses designated by C are fundamental in character and are designed to give the student a basic knowledge in most branches of mathematics and to provide a foundation for more advanced study in any field of mathematics the student may elect. The program of a candidate for the degree of M.A. or M.S. will consist of a limited number of these courses and candidates for the Ph.D. degree will normally take all of them. The courses designated by D are more advanced in character. They provide a thorough knowledge of Topology in its various phases and relation to other branches of mathematics and are intended to prepare the Ph.D. candidate to do research in the subject. The Echols Mathematics Club is composed of all officers of instruction in mathematics, and those undergraduates who show marked proficiency in this field. The club meets twice monthly for discussion of mathematical subjects. CORCORAN SCHOOL OF PHILOSOPHY AND PSYCHOLOGY I. Philosophy A certain number of the following courses will be given each session, in accordance with the needs of individual students. Prerequisite for all C courses in Philosophy: two B courses in Philosophy. Philosophy C21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, are open to undergraduates. Undergraduates will be admitted to Philosophy C11, 12, 13, 32, 33, 34 only after consultation with the instructor in charge. Students proposing to enter any C course in Philosophy are requested to confer with Professor Balz during the spring and fall registration periods. Reading Courses Philosophy C21: Plato. Assistant Professor Davenport and Professor Buchanan. Philosophy C22: Aristotle. Assistant Professor Davenport and Professor Buchanan. Philosophy C23: Thomas Aquinas. Professor Buchanan and Professor Balz. Philosophy C24: Descartes and Spinoza. Professor Balz and Mr. Weedon. Philosophy C25: Locke and Berkeley. Mr. Weedon and Professor Balz. Philosophy C26: Hume, Leibnitz, and Kant. Assistant Professor Davenport and Dr. Hammond. Philosophy C11: Modern Logical Theory. Assistant Professor Davenport. Philosophy C12: The Philosophy of Science. Assistant Professor Davenport. Philosophy C13: Mathematical and Physical Concepts. Professor Sparrow. Philosophy C31: The Theory of Value. Dr. Hammond. Philosophy C32: Political Philosophy. Dr. Hammond. Philosophy C33: Aesthetics. Mr. Weedon. Philosophy C34: (Biblical Literature C2.) Professor Forrest. Philosophy D1: Research. Special Requirements for the Master's Degree in Philosophy: The candidate must present evidence, not later than one year before the degree is conferred, that he possesses a reading knowledge of either French or German. The candidate must select, with the approval of the faculty in philosophy, two primary historical systems as the subject of a special examination, (oral, written, or both) to be taken in April or May of the session in which the candidate expects to secure the degree. Special Requirements for the Degree of Doctor of Philosophy: 1. Preliminary written examinations, designed to test the candidate's general equipment in the field of philosophy, must be taken before formal admission to candidacy. The examinations will be judged as a whole. They will cover the following subject-matters: (a) Logic. (b) Metaphysics or the Theory of Knowledge. (c) History of Philosophy. (d) Ethics. (e) A detailed examination on a primary historical system, to be selected by the candidate, subject to approval. 2. In addition to a reading knowledge of French and German, the candidate may be required to present evidence of a reading knowledge of Latin or Greek, or of both, if in the judgment of the faculty in Philosophy such reading knowledge is necessary for the preparation of the dissertation. II. Psychology Psychology C1: Advanced Experimental Psychology: Psychology B2 prerequisite.—A course in experimental methods designed primarily for advanced students. The entire resources of the laboratory will be available. One hour of lecture and four hours of laboratory weekly. Associate Professor Geldard. Psychology C2: Mental Measurement: Psychology B1 and any other B course listed in this School prerequisite.—A study of the more important mental tests and intelligence scales, of the statistical methods involved in their use, and of the results obtained. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Professor Ferguson. Psychology C3: Genetic Psychology: Psychology B1 and any other B course listed in this School prerequisite.—The development of psychological functions in the animal species and in the child will be traced as a genetic approach to adult human psychology. The topics to be considered include the senses, instinct, memory, learning and intelligence. During part of the year laboratory work will be included. Assistant Professor Dennis. Psychology C4: Theoretical Psychology: Psychology B1 and any other B course listed in this School prerequisite.—An examination of the more important positions in psychological theory, with special reference to the structural, functional, behavioristic and Gestalt points of view. To be given in alternate years with Psychology C5. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Associate Professor Geldard. Psychology C5: Systematic Psychology: Psychology B1 and any other B course listed in this School prerequisite.—A survey of the psychological literature pertaining to the special senses, feeling and emotion, and action. The course is designed to provide an understanding of fundamental methods of research as well as a knowledge of the status of basic problems. To be given in alternate years with Psychology C4. Associate Professor Geldard. Psychology C6: Special Topics in Genetic Psychology: Psychology B1 and any other B course listed in this School prerequisite.—A seminar course for advanced students in which the literature of special topics in child and animal psychology will be reviewed. Second and third terms only. To be given in alternate years with Psychology C7. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Assistant Professor Dennis. Psychology C7: History of Psychology: Psychology B1 and any other B course listed in this School prerequisite.—A survey of the historical development of modern psychology. Second and third terms only. To be given in alternate years with Psychology C6. Assistant Professor Dennis. Psychology C8: Statistical Method: Psychology B1 and any other B course listed in this School prerequisite.—An introduction to the statistical methods in current use in psychology and allied fields. First term only. Assistant Professor Dennis. Psychology D1: Research: Admission on approval of the professors in charge.—For candidates for graduate degrees. Professor Ferguson, Associate Professor Geldard and Assistant Professor Dennis. The Psychological Laboratory is provided with sufficient equipment to make possible thorough training in experimental psychology. Special apparatus for research has been acquired and new pieces will be added as the need arises. In addition to the general laboratory there has been instituted an animal laboratory with provision for work in comparative psychology. A shop with facilities for the construction of apparatus, two dark rooms, and individual research rooms are available. SCHOOL OF PHYSICS The prerequisite for the following C courses are Physics B1 and Mathematics B2. The student specializing in Physics is expected to utilize every opportunity to acquire laboratory technique as a preparation for experimental investigation. The C and the D courses are not necessarily offered each year. Some are offered in alternate years, some are offered once in three years, and others are offered as the needs of graduate students arise. On account of the rapid flux of thought in the Physics of the present day and the varying needs of the graduate students, the content of the advanced courses is varied from year to year. The effort is made to combine training in fundamental methods with securing contact with modern ideas. Physics C1: Mechanics: Three hours of lecture per week. Given as required. Professor Sparrow. Psysics C2: Electricity and Magnetism: Two hours of lecture and two hours of laboratory per week. Laboratory fee, $7.50. (Offered in 1935-36.) Professor Hoxton. Physics C3: Optics: Two hours of lecture and two hours of laboratory per week. Laboratory fee, $7.50. (Offered in 1935-36.) Associate Professor Brown. Physics C4: Heat and Thermodynamics: Two hours of lecture and two hours of laboratory per week. Laboratory fee, $7.50. (Given in 1934-35.) (Not offered in 1935-36.) Professor Hoxton. Physics C5: Precision of Measurements: Required of all graduate students in Physics. One lecture weekly. Given as required. Professor Sparrow. Physics C6: Introduction to Theoretical Physics: (Given in 1934-35.) Given as required. Professor Sparrow. Physics C7: Theory of Electrical Transients: (Given in 1934-35 and in alternate years.) Professor Beams. Physics C8: Differential Equations, Fourier's Series, Finite Differences, Theory of Probability, and Application to Physical Problems: Given annually. Professor Oglesby. Physcs D2: Advanced Theoretical Physics: Given as required. Professor Sparrow. Physics D3: Statistical Mechanics: (Given in 1933-34.) (Offered in 1936-37.) Professor Hoxton. Physics D4: Quantum Mechanics: (Given in 1934-35.) Given as required. Professor Sparrow. Physics D5: Spectroscopy: Given as required. Associate Professor Brown. Physics D7: Selected Topics in Modern Physics: Offered annually. Professor Beams. Physics D8: X-rays and Nuclear Physics: (Offered in 1935-36.) Professor Beams. Physics D9: Electrodynamics: Given as required. Professor Sparrow. Physics D10: Conduction of Electricity through Gases: (Given in 1933-34.) (Offered in 1936-37.) Professor Beams. Physics D12: Seminar: Preparation of papers on selected subjects. Required each year of all candidates for graduate degrees. Professor Beams. Research Courses: Original investigations required for graduate degrees each undertaken under the direction of one or more members of the staff. Physics D40: Research required for the Master's thesis. Physics D50: Research required for the Doctor's dissertation. Journal Meeting: The faculty and advanced students meet weekly for the presentation and discussion of recent work in the physical sciences. The Rouss Physical Laboratory: Facilities for research, which for a number of years have included an instrument shop and a departmental library in addition to a variety of apparatus, are now being rapidly augmented. They lie chiefly in the broad field of spectroscopy, in electro-optical phenomena, nuclear physics, electrical discharges, and to some extent in heat. Persons desiring detailed information about opportunities for graduate work may write to the Professor in charge, Rouss Physical Laboratory, University, Va. Fellowships: A number of Service Fellowships are available each session. During the session of 1934-35 there were seven of these carrying stipends of $280 to $550. With the exception of the athletic fee none of the University fees were charged. Opportunities thus are afforded for graduate study and research. Certain duties, mainly teaching, are required, not exceeding twelve hours a week in the laboratory and a possible average of three hours outside. Requests for application blanks and information may be made to the Professor in charge, Rouss Physical Laboratory, University, Va. All applications must be in on or before March 1. Additional opportunities are afforded by other fellowships not administered by the Physics Faculty. Information about these, particularly the Philip Francis duPont and Bayly-Tiffany Fellowships, will be found elsewhere in the catalogue. SCHOOL OF POLITICAL SCIENCE Government B1 and one other B course in Political Science are prerequisite to any C course. Note: The C courses listed are not all offered in any given year. Students who are interested should consult those in charge of the several courses. Government C1: United States Constitutional Law: A study of the American constitutional system through the case method. Associate Professor Spicer. Government C2: Political Theory: First term: The Theory of the State and of Government. Second term: The History of Ancient and Medieval Political Thought. Third term: Modern and Contemporary Political Thought. Professor Gooch. Government C3: Federalism: A study of the theory and practice of federalism together with an examination of the problems of centralization and decentralization. Professor Gooch. Government C4: The Principles of International and of Public Law. Government C5: The Theory and Practice of Public Administration. Associate Professor Spicer. Government C8: Municipal Administration: A study of the theory and principles of municipal organization, of departmentalization, of inter-departmental relations and of intra-departmental structure and methods. Alternates with Government C9. Associate Professor Egger. Government C9: Administrative Government: A study of the law of public officers and administrative commissions, of the adjudicatory power of administrative agencies in relation to constitutional doctrines and judicial supremacy, and of relief against administrative action. Alternates with Government C8. Associate Professor Egger. SCHOOL OF ROMANIC LANGUAGES French C1: Pascal, Rousseau, Voltaire: Their Influence: French B2, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Primarily a lecture course in French, each lecture being based on a passage in the original text that is first dictated to the class. Professor Wilson. French C3: The Non-Dramatic Literature of the Seventeenth Century in France: French B2, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Given in French. Special emphasis will be given to the works of Boileau, Bossuet and Fénelon. Offered in alternate years. (Offered in 1935-36.) Dr. Garlick. French C4: Drama and Lyric Poetry in the Nineteenth Century: French B2, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Given in French. Lectures, reading of texts, discussions, reports. Offered in alternate years. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Professor Graham, Associate Professor Mellor and Mr. Lee. French C5: Daudet: French C1 or French C2 prerequisite.—Here the principles of research are taken into consideration. Daudet material is collected, classified and shaped for presentation in French. Professor Wilson. French C6: French Drama of the Seventeenth Century: French B2, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Given in French. The greater part of the course will be devoted to Corneille, Molière and Racine. Offered in alternate years. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Dr. Garlick. French C7: The Short Story and Novel from 1715 to 1900: French B2, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Given in French. Lectures, reading of texts, discussion, reports. Offered in alternate years. (Offered in 1935-36.) Professor Graham, Associate Professor Mellor and Mr. Lee. Spanish C1: The Drama of the Golden Age: Spanish B2, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Given in Spanish. Studies in the works of Lope de Vega, Tirso de Molina, Ruiz de Alarcón and Calderón de la Barca, with extensive reading of supplementary materials. Professor Bardin. Spanish C2: Spanish Poets of the Romantic Period: Spanish C1 prerequisite.—Given in Spanish. The works of the chief poets of the period will be studied in detail. Offered in alternate years. (Offered in 1935-36.) Professor Bardin. Spanish C3: Modern Spanish Novelists (Group I): Spanish B2, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Given in Spanish. Studies in the novels of Pereda, Pérez Galdós and Pío Baroja, with extensive reading of supplementary materials. Offered in alternate years. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Professor Bardin. Spanish C4: Spanish Drama from Moratin to the Present: Spanish B2, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Given in Spanish. Lectures, reading of texts, discussion, reports. Offered in alternate years. (Offered in 1935-36.) Associate Professor Mellor, Assistant Professor Woody and Dr. Galbán. Spanish C5: Spanish-American Literature: Spanish B2, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Given in Spanish. A survey of the leading literary figures and movements in Spanish America since Colonial times. Offered in alternate years. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Professor Bardin. Spanish C6: Modern Spanish Novelists (Group II): Spanish C3 prerequsite.—Given in Spanish. Studies in the novels of Ricardo León, Pérez de Ayala, Palacio Valdés and Valle-Inclán. Offered in alternate years. (Offered in 1935-36.) Professor Bardin. Spanish C7: The Picaresque Novel and the Ballad: Spanish B2, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Given in Spanish. Lectures, reading of texts, discussion, reports. Offered in alternate years. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Associate Professor Mellor, Assistant Professor Woody and Dr. Galbán. Italian C1: Dante: Italian B2, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Given in Italian. The study of Dante's Italian works, with special reference to medieval thought. Associate Professor Rinetti. Italian C2: Ariosto, Machiavelli, Tasso: Italian B2, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Given in Italian. The outstanding features of epic and chivalric poetry and of political thought in the Rinascimento. Associate Professor Rinetti. Italian C3: Foscolo, Leopardi, Manzoni: Italian B2, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Given in Italian. Special attention will be paid to the contribution of these authors to the Risorgimento. Associate Professor Rinetti. Italian C4: Contemporary Italian Literature: Italian B2, or the equivalent, prerequisite.—Given in Italian. Associate Professor Rinetti. Note: Of Italian C1, C2, C3, C4 and D2, two are offered each session, the choice depending upon the plans of study of the advanced undergraduate and the graduate students in the School of Romanic Languages. The following courses are for advanced graduate students. French D1: Old French: French B2, or the equivalent and the permission of the instructor, prerequisite.—1. The development of the French language in the early medieval period. 2. French literature from the beginnings down to the fourteenth century. Associate Professor Mellor. Spanish D1: Old Spanish: Spanish B2, or the equivalent and the permission of the instructor, prerequisite.—1. The development of the Spanish language in the medieval period. 2. Spanish literature from the beginnings down to the fifteenth century. Associate Professor Mellor. Italian D1: Old Italian: Italian B2, or the equivalent and the permission of the instructor, prerequisite.—1. The development of the Italian language in the medieval period. 2. Italian literature from the beginnings down to the fourteenth century. Associate Professor Mellor. Note: Of Spanish D1 and Italian D1, one is given each session, the choice depending upon the plans of study of the graduate students in the School of Romanic Languages. It is expected that each of these courses will be given in alternate years. French D2: Balzac: The master's degree in Romanic Languages, or equivalent Romanic training, prerequisite.—A seminar devoted to the investigation of Balzac's method and material. Each year the seminar as a whole concentrates upon a single phase of investigation which is treated as exhaustively as local conditions permit. Professor Wilson. Spanish D2: Cervantes and His Epoch: Spanish C1 and one other C course in Spanish, prerequisite.—An exhaustive study of the works of Cervantes and his principal critics. Offered in alternate years. (Offered in 1935-36.) Professor Bardin. Italian D2: Petrarch: Italian C1 prerequisite.—Given in Italian. Petrarch's Italian and Latin works will be studied with special reference to their relation to Humanism. See Note following Italian C4. Associate Professor Rinetti. SCHOOL OF RURAL SOCIAL ECONOMICS Rural Social Economics C1: Advanced Economics of Agriculture: Rural Social Economics B1 and one other B course in either the School of Rural Social Economics, the School of Economics or the School of Commerce prerequisite.—An advanced course in agricultural economics, in which the primary emphasis is upon the principles of economics as applied to agriculture. (B.A. or B.S. credit, 3 session-hours.) Given in alternate years with C2. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Professor Gee. Rural Social Economics C2: Rural Social Problems: Rural Social Economics B1 and one other B course in either the School of Rural Social Economics or the School of Sociology prerequisite.—An advanced course in rural sociology. Lectures and seminar reports dealing with the more outstanding rural social problems, such as population, standards of living, environmental factors, rural institutions, community organization, and town-country relationships. (B.A. or B.S. credit, 3 session-hours.) Given in alternate years with C1. Professor Gee. Rural Social Economics D1: Research in Rural Problems: At the outset the course deals with research methods as they apply in the social sciences. After such intensive preliminary training, an original problem is selected for an investigation and these methods are applied in actual practice. (Hours and credit by special arrangement.) Professor Gee. SCHOOL OF SOCIOLOGY Sociology C1: Social Theory: Psychology B4 and one B course in Sociology, or two B courses in Sociology prerequisite.—Beginning in 1933-34, this course deals with the history or development of present-day sociological theories, methods, and problems. It should normally be taken in their first year by graduate students who have not had a similar course as undergraduates. Given every year. Professor House. Sociology C2: Collective Behavior: Psychology B4 and one B course in Sociology, or two B courses in Sociology prerequisite.—First term: Review of the fundamentals of social psychology, and general consideration of the theory of crowd and mob behavior, and mass movements. Second term: Public opinion and political behavior. Third term: The sociology of religion. Given in alternate years. Professor House. Sociology C3: Human Ecology: Psychology B4 and one B course in Sociology, or two B courses in Sociology prerequisite.—The scientific study of human society from a physical, geographic, and economic point of view; the spatial distribution and movements of population and institutions. Considerable time is devoted to laboratory exercises, and opportunities are provided for field studies. Given every second or third year. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Associate Professor Hoffer. Sociology C4: The Family: Psychology B4 and one B course in Sociology, or two B courses in Sociology prerequisite.—First term: The primitive family, the family in history, and the family as an institution. Second term: Family disorganization—divorce, desertion, marital discord, and the breakdown of the control of the family over its members. Third term: The modern family—the family in a changing world, the urban family, tendencies and proposals for the reconstruction of the family as a social institution. Given in alternate years. (Not offered in 1935-36.) Associate Professor Hoffer. Sociology C6: Criminology: Two B courses in Sociology prerequisite.— Throughout the year: lectures and discussions, assigned readings, laboratory and field work. The course deals with crime, juvenile delinquency, and other forms of conflict between individuals and the society around them. Special attention is paid to theories of crime and punishment, the causes of crime and delinquency, and the effects of various types of treatment of offenders. To be given every second or third year. Professor House. Sociology C7: The Development of Social Policies: Two B courses in Sociology prerequisite.—An examination of the major forms and tendencies assumed by efforts to promote the general welfare and provide for the needs of the underprivileged and maladjusted classes. The problems involved in the determination of social policies; and the processes by which such policies evolve. Social welfare conceived in terms of public and private benevolence, institutional care, personal guidance, state and national welfare organization, and national and international economic policy. Given in alternate years. Associate Professor Hoffer. Sociology D1: The Logic of the Social Sciences: A seminar course for graduate students only.—Throughout the year: Reports on individual assignments, discussions, and informal lectures, dealing with such topics as the classification of the sciences and the relation of the social sciences to each other and to other disciplines, fundamental methodological problems of the social sciences, and the conceptual determination of the object matter and research problems of the social sciences. Given every second or third year. Professor House. Sociology D3: Research Problems in Public Welfare and Social Adjustment: Permission of the instructor is required for all enrolments in this course. —Research projects, arranged and directed in individual conferences with the instructor. Amount of credit subject to determination in proportion to work accomplished. Associate Professor Hoffer. Sociology D4: Research Problems in Theoretic Sociology: Individual projects arranged as in D3. Professor House. Sociology D5: Research Problems in Human Ecology and Community Organization: To be arranged as in D3. Professor House and Associate Professor Hoffer. COURSES IN MEDICAL SCIENCE OFFERED IN THE DEPARTMENT OF MEDICINE FOR CANDIDATES FOR GRADUATE DEGREES HISTOLOGY AND EMBRYOLOGY Histology C1: Biology B1 prerequisite.—4 lectures or recitations and 10 hours of laboratory work weekly during the first term. This course aims to acquaint the student with the microscopic structure of tissues and organs. Cytogenesis and histogenesis are briefly considered in the case of many tissues studied. The relation of histology to physiology and pathology is constantly kept in view. The student is also given opportunity to acquaint himself with the principles and practice of histological technique. Dr. Jordan and Dr. Kindred. Embryology C1: Histology C1 prerequisite.—7 hours weekly during the second term. The laboratory work (5 hours weekly) with sections and dissections of mammalian embryos, is supplemented by lectures, recitations, and the study of models. The course aims to give the student a knowledge of developmental processes, in the light of which he may the better understand the more abstruse normal conditions of adult anatomy, as well as many anomalies and variations. Dr. Jordan and Dr. Kindred. Histology D1: The histology and embryology of the blood-forming tissues. Histology D2: The histology and embryology of the endocrine tissues. Histology D3: The histology and embryology of the reproductive organs. Histology D4: Cell physiology with special reference to blood corpuscles. Histology C1 and Embryology C1 prerequisite for the D courses.—9 hours weekly during third term. Dr. Jordan and Dr. Kindred. GROSS ANATOMY AND ANTHROPOLOGY Anatomy C1: Biology B1 prerequisite.—19 hours weekly during the first term and 12 hours weekly during the second term. This course begins with a systematic study of the bones, on the completion of which a part is assigned to each student for dissection and study. On the completion of this course each student has dissected a lateral half of the body. The student obtains his knowledge at first hand and by his own personal efforts. Dr. Bean, Dr. Speidel and Assistants. Anatomy C2: Biology B1 prerequisite.—6 hours weekly during the second term. This course consists of a laboratory study of the anatomy of the central nervous system carried out in considerable detail. The gross anatomy of the spinal cord and brain is first considered, on the completion of which sections of the more important regions are studied with the aid of the microscope. Fresh brains and series of sections of the cord and brain are thoroughly used. A reconstruction of the central nervous system showing the more important pathways is prepared by each student. Dr. Speidel. Anatomy D1: Anatomy C1 prerequisite.—8 hours weekly during the second term. Topographic and applied anatomy. Dr. Bean and Dr. Speidel. Anatomy D2: Anatomy C1 prerequisite.—Hours by arrangement. Special anatomical dissections. Dr. Bean and Dr. Speidel. Anatomy D3: Anatomy C1 prerequisite.—9 hours weekly during the second term. Physical anthropology. Dr. Bean. Anatomy D4: Anatomy C2 prerequisite.—Research in experimental anatomy. Opportunity for original investigation is afforded a small number of specially qualified students. Dr. Speidel. BACTERIOLOGY AND PREVENTIVE MEDICINE Bacteriology C1: Biology B1 prerequisite.—Lectures, conferences and laboratory work 12 hours weekly during the third term. The object of this course is to acquaint the student with the microörganisms which are of importance to man and his environment, the methods used in their study and identification. The fundamentals of infection and immunity are taught. So far as practicable the material studied is obtained from the environment, from the body surfaces, and excretions of normal individuals, and from the body surfaces, secretions and exudates of the person with various common pathological conditions. The student is thus introduced to the etiology of infectious disease and some of the factors involved in resistance. Through a consideration of selected bacteriologic and immunologic studies the basis is laid for the later study of epidemiology and preventive medicine. Dr. Maxcy and Assistants. Preventive Medicine and Epidemiology C1: Biology B1 prerequisite.—2 hours weekly during the first two terms.—The primary object of this course is to interest the student in the practice of preventive medicine. By lectures, clinics and demonstrations the epidemiology of each of the common communicable diseases is presented. The student is encouraged to consider these diseases not solely from the point of view of diagnosis and treatment in the individual case, but to understand the environmental factors and biologic conditions which are responsible for its maintenance and propagation in nature, and the possibilities of control or prevention, through the efforts of the private physician or the functioning of organized public health agencies. Dr. Maxcy and Dr. Eller. Immunology D1: Bacteriology C1 prerequisite.—This course is designed to amplify the introduction to immunology given in the regular course in Bacteriology during the first year. During the third and fourth years the student has become acquainted with clinical medicine. It is desirable to review the factors concerned with resistance to infection and the scientific background for the treatment of infectious diseases. By means of conferences and laboratory assignments the student is given an opportunity to perform and observe some of the characteristic phenomena in test tube and in the experimental animal. Special attention is given to those biologic reactions which are of value in the diagnosis or treatment of disease such as the Wasserman reaction, the Kahn reaction, agglutination technique, standardization of antitoxic sera, etc. 3 afternoons weekly for one trimester. Given in first and second trimester. Dr. Maxcy. BIOCHEMISTRY Biochemistry C1: Chemistry B3 prerequisite.—Lectures and laboratory 7 hours weekly during the second term and 14 hours weekly during the third term. Course comprises the chemistry of proteins, fats, and carbohydrates; digestion, intestinal putrefaction, feces; blood, milk, and bile; particular attention is devoted to the chemical physiology of digestion, secretion, excretion, internal secretion, intermediary metabolism, and nutrition. Laboratory work includes the study of carbohydrates, fats, proteins, purine compounds, etc.; gastric contents, blood, milk, and urine; the digestive enzymes and the digestion of foods; and extensive qualitative and quantitative work on urine. Dr. Chanutin and Dr. Ludewig. Biochemistry D1: Biochemistry C1 prerequisite.—This group meets twice a month at night for two hours throughout the session. A seminar course in the biochemistry of the diseases of nutrition and metabolism. Assignments in the literature are made and the student abstracts and reports on some phase of the topic to be discussed. An attempt is made to correlate recent advances in clinical biochemistry to disease. An informal discussion is led by the faculty members. The course is not given unless chosen by eight or more students. Drs. Chanutin, Mulholland and Blackford. Biochemistry D2: Biochemistry C1 prerequisite.—6 hours of laboratory work a week during the entire year. Biochemical preparations. Individual instruction is given in the separation, purification and identification of products of biochemical nature. Dr. Chanutin. Biochemistry D3: Biochemistry C1 prerequisite.—1 hour a week during the entire year. Physiology of nutrition. An attempt is made to cover the subject of nutrition in its broadest aspects. Various phases of digestion, respiratory, basal and intermediary metabolism are studied. Dr. Chanutin. Biochemistry D4: Biochemistry C1 prerequisite.—2 hours a week during the entire year. Biochemical seminar. Papers pertaining to Biochemistry and related subjects in the English, German and French literature are read by the participants. The student is enabled to keep in touch with the advances made in the subject. Dr. Chanutin. Biochemistry D5: Biochemistry D1 prerequisite.—For those students properly qualified the laboratory will be opened during the academic year and summer vacation. Biochemical research. Dr. Chanutin. PHYSIOLOGY Physiology C1: Histology C1 and Biochemistry C1 prerequisite.—Lectures, recitations, and demonstrations, 5 hours weekly during the first term and 4 hours during the second term; laboratory work, 7 hours weekly during the first term, 3 hours weekly during the second term. In the lecture course attention is drawn to the fundamental branches of the subject, and the more difficult aspects are thoroughly discussed. Recent important physiological contributions are evaluated, and the student is directed further to consult various monographs and original papers. The laboratory work consists of preliminary elemental experiments on the neuromuscular system, followed by intensive courses in mammalian and in human physiology. The latter are designed particularly to train students to observe and record, and to interpret and make deductions from their results. Suggestive outlines only are provided for the experimental studies. The course is particularly devised to stimulate and correlate the student's consideration of the activities of the organism as a whole. Emphasis is given to those branches of physiology which should prove valuable in later work in medicine. Dr. Britton, Dr. Corey and Assistants. Physiology D1: Physiology C1 prerequisite.—Application of physiology to medicine. Hours by arrangement. Dr. Britton. Physiology D2: Physiology C1 prerequisite.—The function of the alimentary tract and related organs. Hours by arrangement. Dr. Britton. Physiology D3: Physiology C1 prerequisite.—Comparative physiology of the internal secretions. Hours by arrangement. Dr. Corey. Physiology D4: Embryology C1 and Physiology C1 prerequisites.—Physiology of the fetus. Hours by arrangement. Dr. Corey. The above D courses require 6 hours weekly during the third term. Physiology D5: Physiology C1 prerequisite.—History of Physiology. Hours by arrangement. Dr. Silvette. Physiology D6: Physiology C1 prerequisite.—Advanced physiology. Part I, historical general physiology; neuromuscular system; Part II, metabolism; circulation; Part III, respiration, secretion; Part IV, central nervous system; special senses. Hours by arrangement. Dr. Britton and Dr. Corey. Physiology D7: Physiology C1 prerequisite..—Original investigation. Opportunity is afforded a limited number of qualified students to undertake investigative work at any time throughout the year in Physiology or nearly related sciences. Dr. Britton and Dr. Corey. PATHOLOGY Pathology C1: Anatomy C1 and Physiology C1 prerequisite.—4 hours weekly during the first term; 12 hours weekly during the second term, and 12 weekly during the third term. By a systematic series of lectures, combined with demonstrations of both gross and microscopic preparations, the various morbid conditions of the body are presented. In the laboratory, under supervision, the student personally examines all of the gross material and devotes considerable time to the study of the loan-collection of slides with which he is provided. In addition to this systematic portion of the course an attempt is made to acquaint the students with fresh tissues and disease as seen at the autopsy table. With this end in view the class is divided into small groups of students each of which assists at a limited number of autopsies. Fresh tissues are demonstrated during class hours and, whenever possible, autopsies are performed before the entire class. Dr. Cash, Dr. Casey, Dr. Scott and Dr. Shanklin. Pathology D1: Pathology C1 prerequisite.—An elective course in pathology is offered to all students of the fourth-year medical class 2 hours weekly throughout the session. The nature of this course will vary according to the number of students who apply for it. Regardless of the manner in which the course is conducted, its general purpose is to afford the student, who has already had considerable training in clinical medicine, a systematic review of the anatomical changes occurring in the commonly encountered diseases. The current pathological material is demonstrated to this group of students throughout the year. A limited number of students, who seem properly qualified, may undertake the study of special problems in which they may be interested. Hours by special arrangement. Dr. Cash. Pathology D2: Pathology C1 prerequisite.—An elective course in surgical pathology is offered to two students in the fourth-year medical class. The course will consist in an examination of the daily biopsy material from all clinical departments, including both gross and microscopic. Students taking the course will have access to the gross and microscopic material in the files of the Department of Pathology. The completion of some research problem will be encouraged. Dr. Casey. PHARMACOLOGY Pharmacology C1: Physiology C1 prerequisite.—Lectures, recitations and demonstrations 4 hours weekly and laboratory work 9 hours weekly, during the second term. The physical and chemical characteristics and the mode of action of representative drugs and other chemic agents are dealt with both in didactic and practical exercises. Special attention is given to analysing and interpreting the results obtained in the laboratory. Dr. J. A. Waddell, Dr. Saunders and Assistants. Pharmacology D1: The biological significance and pharmacological action of the compounds of certain metallic elements, particular attention being given to Ca, Fe, Mg, Mn, and Cu. Pharmacology D2: The influence of chemical structure on pharmacological action, the significance of the presence and position in the molecule of alkyl, hydroxl, carboxyl, and amino radicles being investigated. Pharmacology D3: The standardization of drugs, embracing a study of the most representative methods, chemical and biological. Pharmacology D4: The isolating and identification of poisons in tissues, vomitus and urine. Pharmacology C1 prerequisite for the D courses. Didactic, 2 hours a week and laboratory 4 hours a week during the first term. Dr. J. A. Waddell and Assistants. DERMATOLOGY AND SYPHILOLOGY Dermatology C1: Completion of second year of medical course prerequisite.—2 hours weekly of lectures during the third term, supplemented by clinics in the out-patient department. The importance, etiology, prophylaxis, pathology, clinical history, diagnosis and treatment of syphilis are discussed. After review of the anatomic and histologic structure and physiology of the skin the diseases commonly met with are discussed. The main object in this course is not to train specialists but to give all the students basic information regarding the diagnosis and treatment of the common skin diseases and syphilis. The relationship of these to other branches of medicine is emphasized. Dr. Smith and Assistants. Dermatology C2: Dermatology C1 prerequisite.—2 hours weekly of lectures during the first term. A total of 24 hours scheduled clinical work in the wards and out-patient department for each student. Dr. Smith and Assistants. Dermatology D1: Dermatology C1 and C2 prerequisite.—3 afternoons weekly for one trimester in the out-patient department. Clinical dermatology and syphilology. Dr. Smith and Assistants. Dermatology D2: 2 hours weekly during the entire year. Laboratory and clinical medical mycology. Dr. Smith and Assistants. NEUROLOGY Neurology C1: Completion of third year of medical course prerequisite.— 3 lectures weekly during the first term and 2 lectures weekly during the second term, supplemented by clinical demonstrations and ward rounds throughout the year. An effort is made primarily to present the fundamentals of neurology and psychiatry. In addition to the study of patients in the wards of the University Hospital, clinics are held at the several state hospitals for mental diseases. Dr. Wilson. Neurology D1: Neurology C1 is prerequisite.—3 hours weekly during the entire year, clinic 2 hours weekly and seminar 1 hour weekly. Mental Hygiene. Dr. Wilson. SURGERY Surgery D1: 2 hours weekly for the session. Limited to four students of the fourth year.—The daily material from the operating room and the collection of pathological material in the files of the laboratory are studied, with correlation between the pathological findings and the clinical history. The students are expected to examine all fresh material in the gross and to study the microscopic pathology. The view-point of the course is the interpretation of these observations as illustrating the development and progress of surgical disease. Dr. Lehman and Assistants. Surgery D2: Degree of M.D. and one year of interne service prerequisite.— The student is expected to spend his entire time for the year. Surgical pathology and research in the field of the biological sciences related to clinical surgery. The former portion of the course consists of study and reports on a large collection of surgical pathological material. The latter portion is to be arranged individually with the director. Dr. Lehman. SUMMER QUARTER In the Summer Quarter for 1934 the following graduate courses were offered: Biology, 12; Chemistry, 3; Economics, 6; Education, 16; English, 9; Government, 4; History, 7; Latin, 4; Medical Sciences, 12; Psychology, 5; Sociology, 4. Full details regarding these and other courses in the Summer Quarter may be found in the Summer Quarter Catalogue. The Summer Quarter consists of two terms each year. In 1935 the first term begins on June 17 and closes on July 27, with lectures five times a week; the second term begins on July 29 and closes on August 31, with lectures six times a week. RECIPIENTS OF DEGREES, DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES, JUNE 12, 1934 Masters of Science Brown, Thomas Dickinson, B.S., University of Virginia. Biology Charlottesville, Va. Thesis: Observations on the Morphology, Occurrence and Distribution of Manodistomum occultum Stafford, with a discussion of the genus manodi stomum. Brumfield, William Andrew, Jr., B.S., Virginia Polytechnic Institute; M.D., University of Virginia. Dermatology and Syphilology University, Va. Thesis: Psoriasis; with Special Reference to its Etiology. Cummings, Adison Gilmore, B.S., University of Virginia. Education Bedford, Va. Thesis: A Survey of Certain Aspects of the Public School System of Bedford County, Virginia. Daniel, Robert Howison, B.S. Com., University of Virginia. Economics Charlottesville, Va. Thesis: Financial Analysis with Special Reference to the Studebaker Corporation. Delman, Louis, B.S., College of the City of New York. Psychology Brooklyn, N. Y. Thesis: Stimulus-Response Relations in the Newborn. Dennis, Wilbert Chalmer, B.S., University of Virginia. Geology University, Va. Thesis: Igneous Rocks of the Valley of Virginia. Dollins, Elsie Mae, B.S. Ed., University of Virginia. Biology Charlottesville, Va. Thesis: Excretory System of Diplodiscus Temperatus Stafford 1905. Dulaney, Ben Bane, B.S., University of Virginia. Rural Social Economics Washington, D. C. Thesis: A Statistical Study of American Leaders in Education. Gentry, Fenton Allen Sevier, B.S., University of Virginia. Political Science Chattanooga, Tenn. Thesis: The Classification of Positions and Standardization of Pay in the Virginia Municipal Service. Happel, Ralph, B.S., University of Virginia. English Fredericksburg, Va. Thesis: Edward Lear, King of Nonsense. Jones, Juliet Armstrong, B.S., State Teachers College of Farmville. Education Churchville, Va. Thesis: An Evaluation of Recent General Science Texts and Courses of Study. Manne, Jack, B.S., University of Virginia. Sociology New York, N. Y. Thesis: A Study of Feeblemindedness in a Closely Inbred Mountain Family. Mustard, Robert Wall, B.S. Com., University of Virginia. Economics Cismont, Va. Thesis: An Analysis of the Seaboard Air Line Railroad 1922-1929. Schor, Irving Murray, B.S., New York University. Biology West New York, N. J. Thesis: Observations on the Cercariae Escaping from Pseudo-succinea Columella. Shelburne, Chester Claude, B.S. Ed., University of Virginia. Education Christiansburg, Va. Thesis: A Plan of Instruction for the High Schools of Montgomery County. Smith, Frances Crafton, B.S., Westhampton College. Biology Scottsville, Va. Thesis: A Local Dalyellia, Tentatively Proposed as a New Species. Stoddard, David Farnham, B.S. Arch., University of Virginia, Architecture New York, N. Y. Thesis: The Replanning of Certain Areas of Norfolk, Virginia. Strange, Louis Cleburne, B.S. Ed., University of Tennessee. Geology Guthrie, Ky. Thesis: Geology of the Patuxent Sandstone of Northeastern Virginia. Thomas, Hugh Rogers, B.S., Hampden-Sydney College. Chemistry Round Hill, Va. Thesis: A Study of the Colorimetric Determination of Gold. Tutwiler, Cameron Phillips, B.S., State Teachers College of Harrisonburg. Education Gloucester, Va. Thesis: Study of Fifth Grade Pupils in Five Consolidated Schools of Albemarle County. Winn, John Blanton, B.S., University of Virginia. French Versailles, Ky. Thesis: General Marquis Calmes. Wolcott, Gordon Bloomfield, B.S. Biol., University of Virginia. Biology Eatontown, N. J. Thesis: On the Cytology of Ipomoea. Master of Arts Arey, Hiram Cecil, B.A., Bridgewater College. History Bridgewater, Va. Thesis: The Public Career of Thomas Lewis. Belitt, Ben, B.A., University of Virginia. English Lynchburg, Va. Thesis: Katherine Mansfield: An Inquiry into the Nature and Derivation of her Art. Chenault, Marion Elizabeth,B.A., Randolph-Macon Woman's College. Latin Lynchburg, Va. Thesis: Vita Karoli of Einhard: A Study in Sources, Content and Diction. Cochran, Elizabeth Brooke, B.A., Wheaton College. Sociology Staunton, Va. Thesis: Staunton, A Social and Statistical Analysis. Curtler, Martin Stuart, B.A., University of Virginia. English Charlottesville, Va. Thesis: Lucian's Influence on the "Imaginary Voyage" in the Eighteenth Century in England. Downey, Marvin, B.A., University of Virginia. Political Science Washington, D. C. Thesis: The Democratic Movement in Colonial Maryland. Gravely, William Henry, Jr., B.A., College of William and Mary. English Martinsville, Va. Thesis: The Lunar Voyage in Literature from Lucian to Poe. Harwell, Marguerite Buchanan, B.A., Hollins College, Physics Petersburg, Va. Thesis: A Study of an Imperfect Grating. Jenkins, Iredell, B.A., University of Virginia, Philosophy Norfolk, Va. Thesis: A Study of Spinozistic Universals. Johnson, Henry Satterwhite, B.A., University of Richmond. Education Hylas, Va. Thesis: A Study of Physical Education in the Rural Elementary Schools of Virginia. Kerr, Mary Pinkerton, B.A., Sweet Briar College. Biology Spartanburg, S. C. Thesis: Some Species of Earthworms found in Virginia and South Carolina, with Notes on their Gregarine Sporozoa. Keyes, Raymond Stedman, Graduate of United States Naval Academy. History San Diego, Calif. Thesis: Greece, The Great Powers, and the Great War. Kinney, Laurence Forman, B.A., Hampden-Sydney College; B.D., Union Theological Seminary. Philosophy Charlottesville, Va. Thesis: Plato's Doctrine of Ideas as Exemplified in the Philebus. Langford, Gerald, B.A., University of Virginia. English Savannah, Ga. Thesis: Cyril Tourneur and the Revenge Play. Martin, Caroline Pierce, B.A., George Washington University. History Washington, D. C. Thesis: William Short, American Diplomat at Paris. Mason, William Leon, B.A., Randolph-Macon College. Education Bloxom, Va. Thesis: A Study of the Status of Motion Pictures in Education. Raine, Peter Woodward Allen, B.A., Hampden-Sydney College. Mathematics Richmond, Va. Thesis: A Vector Study of the Tetrahedron. Richardson, William Garland, B.A., University of Richmond. German Richmond, Va. Thesis: A Preliminary Study of Mood and Tense Sequence in Modern German Prose. Ritter, Eugene Kerfoot, B.A., University of Richmond. Mathematics Bowling Green, Va. Thesis: The Brocard Configuration in Circular Coordinates. Rodman, George Bush, B.A., Centre College. English Frankfort, Ky. Thesis: The Present-day Humanistic Attack upon the English Romantic Poets of the Early Nineteenth Century. Spiker, Franklin Armstrong, B.A., University of Virginia. History Strasburg, Va. Thesis: Thomas Jefferson as a Member of the Continental Congress, 1775-1776. Watson, George Carson, B.A., Randolph-Macon College. Mathematics Danville, Va. Thesis: The 2-Parameter Family of Cubics of the Polar Isologue. Doctors of Philosophy Armentrout, Mary Travers, B.S., State Teachers College of Harrisonburg; M.S., University of Virginia. History McGaheysville, Va. Dissertation: A Political Study of Virginia Finance 1781-1789. Barker, Robert Harvie, B.A., Furman University; M.A., Vanderbilt University. Sociology Danville, Va. Dissertation: A Social Study of Juvenile Delinquency in Charlottesville and Albemarle County, Virginia. Berelson, Louis Julius, B.A., Whitman College; M.A., University of California. Latin Portland, Ore. Dissertation: Old Age in Ancient Rome. Bodé, Donald Denby, B.S., Southwestern Presbyterian University; M.S., University of Virginia. Chemistry Memphis, Tenn. Dissertation: Soda Ash-Salt-Ammonia-Water under Pressure. Bradley, Charles Dunklin, B.S.E.E., Alabama Polytechnic Institute; M.S., University of Virginia. Physics Anniston, Ala. Dissertation: Ion Distribution during the Initial Stages of Spark Discharge. Davis, Roy Bryan, B.S., Wake Forest College. Chemistry Burgaw, N. C. Dissertation: A Study of the Saturated Cadmium Iodide-Silver Iodide Cell. Gilbert, Chauncey McLean, B.S., Massachusetts Agricultural College. Biology University, Va. Dissertation: A Comparative Study of Three New American Species of the Genus Phaenocora with Especial Reference to their Reproductive Organs and their Relationships with the other Described Forms of the Genus. Gilmer, Beverly von Haller, B.S., King College; M.S., University of Virginia. Psychology Draper, Va. Dissertation: The Sensitivity of the Skin to Mechanical Vibrations. Hess, Margaret, B.S. Ed., M.S., University of Virginia. Biology Richmond, Va. Dissertation: Edema and General Atrophy in Stenostomum Oesophagium Associated with Atrophy of the Protonephridium. Hodge, Ruth Patrick, B.S., Coker College; M.S., University of Virginia. Biology Kansas City, Mo. Dissertation: A Taxonomic and Distributional Study of Some Diatoms from Siam and the Federated Malay States. Hootman, James Albert, B.S., Randolph-Macon College; M.S., Mississippi A. and M. College. Physics Ashland, Va. Dissertation: Kerr's Law at High Field Strengths. Hunsberger, George Ephraim, B.A., M.A., Oberlin College. Economics Wadsworth, Ohio Dissertation: The Development of Tariff Policy in the Republican Party. Husted, Ladley, B.A., Oberlin College. Biology University, Va. Dissertation: Genetic and Cytological Studies on the Peanut, Arachis. Justice, John Lyttleton, B.S., University of Virginia. Chemistry University, Va. Dissertation: Equilibria in the Reduction of Certain Metallic Oxides by Carbon Monoxide. Lytton, Marion Randolph, B.S., Pennsylvania State College. Chemistry Norristown, Penna. Dissertation: A Study of the Oxidation-Reduction Potentials of Some Aryl Nitroso Compounds. Marshall, Alpheus Royall, B.A., Lynchburg College; M.A., University of Virginia. Economics Chatham, Va. Dissertation: The Federal Government and Labor Legislation. Nelson, James Cecil, B.A., University of Washington; M.A., Ohio State University. Economics Bickleton, Wash. Dissertation: The Extent and Status of Motor Transport Regulation in the United States. Orens, Irving Peary, B.S., University of Virginia; M.A., Columbia University. Philosophy Long Beach, N. Y. Dissertation: Foundations of Inductive Geometry. Palmer, Fred Shank, B.S. Chem., University of Virginia. Chemistry Middletown, Md. Dissertation: A Study of the Reduction of Conjugated Systems with Particular Reference to the Catalytic Hydrogenation of Dibenzoylethylene and Related Unsaturated 1,4-Diketones. Quarles, Gilford Godfrey, B.S.E., M.S., University of Virginia. Physics Charlottesville, Va. Dissertation: The Dispersion of the Electro-Optical Kerr Effect in Carbon Dioxide. Ryan, Lee Winfree, B.S., M.S., University of Virginia. French Lynchburg, Va. Dissertation: French Travelers in America between 1775 and 1800 with Special Reference to the Southern States. Silvette, Herbert, B.S., M.S., University of Virginia. Physiology University, Va. Dissertation: Chloride and Water Metabolism in Adrenal Insufficiency. Smith, Dudley Cozby, B.S., Charleston College; M.S., Union College. Chemistry Meggett, S. C. Dissertation: Absorption and Electrode Potential. Stump, Alexander Bell, B.S., M.S., University of Virginia. Biology Edgewood, Md. Dissertation: Observations on the Testacea. Threlkeld, William Logan, B.A., Georgetown College; M.A., University of Virginia. Biology Blacksburg, Va. Dissertation: The Life History of Ostertagia circumcincta (Stadelman, 1894) Ransom, 1907. Volm, Matthew, Graduate from Gymnasium Sigmaringen (Prussia). German Ivy, Va. Dissertation: Mörikes Balladen. Eine kritisch-analytische Untersuchung. Wilder, Frank Nahum, B.A., M.S., Emory University. Chemistry Atlanta, Ga. Dissertation: Some Further Studies on Unsaturated 1,4-Diketones and Related Substances. Wingfield, Robert Cornelius, Ph.B., University of Chicago; M.A., University of Virginia. Psychology University, Va. Dissertation: An Experimental Study of the Apparent Persistence of Auditory Sensations. Yuen, Kechee Chaoching, B.S., University of Nanking; M.S., University of Virginia. Chemistry Shanghai, China Dissertation: Synthetic Studies in the Morphine Series. RECIPIENTS OF DEGREES, DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATES STUDIES, AUGUST 31, 1934 Masters of Science Bell, Helen Purdum, B.S. Ed., University of Virginia. Biology Newport News, Va. Thesis: The Effect of Distilled Water on Division in Amoeba Proteus. Dickinson, Mary Waller, B.S., State Teachers College of Fredericksburg. English Orange, Va. Thesis: Analysis of Elizabeth Brownrigge as a Parody-Burlesque of Eugene Aram, a Discussion of Thackeray's Possible Authorship, and a Comparison of the Parody with His Later Works. Stone, Caleb Smith, Jr., B.S., University of Washington; M.D., Washington University. Surgery University, Va. Thesis: The Effect of Diet on the Liver Weight and Glycogen Concentration in the Partially Hepatectomized Rat. Worsley, Thomas Blanchard, B.S., University of Virginia. Economics Columbus, Ga. Thesis: Out of the Cotton Quandary. Masters of Arts Ballentine, Evelyn, B.A., Lenoir-Rhyne College. English Timberville, Va. Thesis: James Shirley's Relation to the Comedy of Manners. Barnwell, William Warren, B.A., Hampden-Sydney College. Latin Waynesboro, Va. Thesis: Women of the Last Years of the Republic as Portrayed by Cicero in His Letters. Commetti, Anita Teresa, B.A., Marshall College. English Bluefield, W. Va. Thesis: The Historical Romances of G. P. R. James: A Critical Study. Cometti, Elizabeth, B.A., Marshall College. History Bluefield, W. Va. Thesis: The Governorship of Thomas Jefferson. Dalton, Mary Gochnauer, B.A., Sweet Briar College. English Charlottesville, Va. Thesis: Andrew Marvell: A Study of His Non-Satirical Poems. Elmore, Harry Robert, B.A., University of Cincinnati. Education Tazewell, Va. Thesis: Survey of the Schools of Tazewell County. Harlan, Howard Harper, B.A., University of Richmond. Sociology Richmond, Va. Thesis: Zion Town: A Study in Human Ecology. Hook, Paul Garland, B.A., Elon College. Education Winchester, Va. Thesis: A Scientific Study of the Use of an Extensive Independent Versus an Intensive Method in the Teaching of Reading. Horn, Francis Henry, B.A., Dartmouth College. English Toledo, Ohio Thesis: The Plays of Peele, Greene, and Marlowe as an Expression of the English Renaissance. McKee, Alice Curtin, B.A., Hollins College. Biology Saltville, Va. Thesis: Morphology of the Transitional Zone of Photophyllum Peltatum. Mann, Lillian Kifer, B.A., Goucher College. Education Fork Union, Va. Thesis: The Determination of Some Specific Learning Difficulties in First Year Algebra. Myers, Ralph Garber, B.A., Bridgewater College. English Harrisonburg, Va. Thesis: The Small Town in the American Novel, 1870-1920. Oglesby, Roscoe Ralph, B.A., Georgetown College. Political Science Lynchburg, Va. Thesis: The Growth of Extradition Treaties. Oka, Hajime, B.A., Doshisha University. Economics Osaka, Japan Thesis: A Study of Limitation of Monopoly Which Is Obtained by Shipping Conference. Sanslow, Margaret Ann, B.A., University of Richmond. Biology Danville, Va. Thesis: Guppies on Experimental Diet. Trent, Eran Elliott, B.A., Randolph-Macon College. Education Troutville, Va. Thesis: Secondary Education in Botetourt County. Ward, John Cook, II, B.A., Dartmouth College. English Bridgeton, N. J. Thesis: Artemus Ward: Nineteenth-Century Critic and Humorist. Weston, Arvetta Talbott, B.A., Duke University. English North Garden, Va. Thesis: Alexander Smith: A Biographical and Critical Study. SUMMARY OF GRADUATE DEGREES—1934 June August Masters of Science 22 4 Masters of Arts 22 18 Doctors of Philosophy 29 Total 73 22 REGISTER OF STUDENTS, DEPARTMENT OF GRADUATE STUDIES, JANUARY 1, 1935 (Note.—The major subject of each student is indicated.) Alexander, James Charles, B.S., Wake Forest College. Chemistry Scotland Neck, N. C. Alleman, Benson Suesserott, B.A., Roanoke College; M.A., University of Virginia. English Chilhowie, Va. Anderson, James Francis, B.A., University of Virginia. Philosophy Dover, Del. Anger, Charles Leroy, B.S. Ed., M.S., University of Virginia. History Baltimore, Md. Atkins, Elizabeth Moseley, B.S. Ed., University of Virginia. Geology Charlottesville, Va. Ayre, Josephine, B.B.A., University of Chattanooga. Economics Guild, Tenn. Babb, Winston Chandler, B.A., Furman University. History Seneca, S. C. Baldwin, John Thomas, Jr., B.A., College of William and Mary. Biology Keysville, Va. Ballard, Edward Goodwin, B.A., College of William and Mary. English Williamsburg, Va. Ballard, Warren McElroy (Law), B.A., University of Virginia. Political Science Lynchburg, Va. Beatty, Alvin Von Erl, B.A., Oberlin College. Biology Bradner, Ohio Belitt, Ben, B.A., M.A., University of Virginia. English Lynchburg, Va. Bennett, Albert Luther, B.A., Washington and Lee University; M.A., University of Virginia; M. Ed., Harvard University. Education Charlottesville, Va. Bettis, Charles Eugene, B.S., Davidson College. Mathematics Morristown, Tenn. Black, Robert Kerr, B.A., M.A., Princeton University. English Upper Montclair, N. J. Blankinship, Leslie Charles, B.A., Lynchburg College. Education Gordonsville, Va. Blazer, Selma Halle, B.A., New York University. Physics Brooklyn, N. Y. Blincoe, James William, B.A., Randolph-Macon College; M.A., University of Virginia. Mathematics University, Va. Bonner, Oscar Trent, B.S., Birmingham-Southern College. Education Moneta, Va. Booth, Charles Edward, Jr., Graduate United States Naval Academy. History Painesville, Ohio Bowman, Raymond Palmer Garber, B.S., Bridgewater College; M.S., University of Virginia. Education Harrisonburg, Va. Boyle, Eldridge Roger, Jr., B.S., University of Virginia. Psychology University, Va. Bradley, Charles Dunklin, B.S.E.E., Alabama Polytechnic Institute; M.S., Ph.D., University of Virginia. Physics Charlottesville, Va. Breazeale, William McSwain, B.S.E.E., Rutgers University; M.S., Vanderbilt University. Physics Hendersonville, N. C. Brown, Joshua Robert Callaway, Jr., B.S., Randolph-Macon College. Chemistry Ashland, Va. Browning, George Landon, Jr., B.S., Virginia Military Institute. Chemistry Orange, Va. Burgess, Robert Miller, (cancelled), B.A., Bridgewater, College. French Mt. Crawford, Va. Bush, Elizabeth Loda, B.S., State Teachers College of Harrisonburg. Education Waynesboro, Va. Caffee, Nathaniel Montier, B.A., College of William and Mary; M.A., University of Virginia. English Norfolk, Va. Cain, Thomas Stith Malone, B.A., Vanderbilt University. Economics Nashville, Tenn. Carr, Ray de la Montanya, B.A., Davidson College; B.D., Th.M., Union Theological Seminary. Philosophy University, Va. Chapman, James Jeffries, Jr., B.S. Arch., University of Virginia. Architecture Gordonsville, Va. Childs, Christobel, B.S., State Teachers College of Harrisonburg. Education Orange, Va. Chiles, James Alburn, B.A., Wofford College; M.A., University of Virginia. Physics Spartanburg, S. C. Christian, Robert Murray, B.A., Davidson College; M.A., University of Virginia. History University, Va. Cocke, Virginia Webb, B.S. Ed., University of Virginia. Sociology Charlottesville, Va. Coe, Charles Autus, Jr., B.S. Ed., University of Virginia. Education Sacket Harbor, N. Y. Cohron, Joseph Wenger, B.A., College of William and Mary. Education Stuarts Draft, Va. Cole, James Webb, Jr., B.S. Chem., University of Virginia. Chemistry Virginia Beach, Va. Collins, Maurice Mackenzie, B.A., Otterbein College. Education Churchville, Va. Cook, Roland Eugene, B.A., Roanoke College. Education Salem, Va. Cope, Joseph Howard, B.A., Colgate University; M.A., University of Virginia. Physics Philadelphia, Pa. Cottrell, Stuart C., B.A., Lynchburg College. Education Lee, Va. Cox, Everett Englun, B.A., College of William and Mary. Education Stuarts Draft, Va. Crockett, Samuel Robert, Jr., B.A., Roanoke College. Education Lynchburg, Va. Crumpler, Thomas Bigelow, B.S., M.S., Virginia Polytechnic Institute. Chemistry Asheville, N. C. Cumming, Henry, B.S. (1935), University of Virginia. French University, Va. Cummings, Adison Gilmore, B.S. Ed., M.S., University of Virginia. Education Bedford, Va. Czerwin, Edward Peter, B.S., University of Illinois. Chemistry Berwyn, Ill. Dalgety-Kerr, Grace, B.S., State Teachers College of Harrisonburg. English University, Va. Dalton, Jack, B.S., University of Virginia. English University, Va. Dandelake, George Walter Francis, B.S., Mississippi State College. Economics Starkville, Miss. Davidson, David Nathaniel, B.A., University of Richmond. Education Rhoadesville, Va. Davis, Richard Beale, B.A., Randolph-Macon College; M.A., University of Virginia. English Salisbury, Md. Davis, Thomas, B.S.E., M.S., University of Virginia. Physics Norfolk, Va. Davison, Treadwell, B.A., University of Virginia. Rural Social Economics Richmond, Va. Day, Kathleen Maude, B.A., Dalhousie University. English Troy, N. Y. Delman, Louis, B.S., College of the City of New York; M.S., University of Virginia. Psychology Brooklyn, N. Y. Dickinson, Nella Virginia, (cancelled), B.S. Ed., University of Virginia. Biology Charlottesville, Va. Dodson, Norman Elmer, B.A., Berea College. Physics Berea, Ky. Downey, Marvin, B.A., M.A., University of Virginia. Political Science Washington, D. C. DuBose, John Pendleton, B.S., University of Virginia. Political Science Westbury, N. Y. Duke, Amy, B.A., Duke University. English Fort Valley, Ga. Duke, Francis Johnson, B.S. Arch., M.S., University of Virginia. French Richmond, Va. Duke, Helen Risdon, B.S., University of Virginia. English Charlottesville, Va. Dyer, Hugh Nelson, Jr., B.S., M.S., Virginia Polytechnic Institute. Chemistry Martinsville, Va. Ellett, Joseph Carlyle, B.A., University of Richmond; M.A., University of Virginia. Economics Pocahontas, Va. Ellis, Alice Elizabeth, B.A., Emory and Henry College. Biology Orange, Va. Ellis, Fendall Ragland, B.A., College of William and Mary. Education Richmond, Va. Evans, William Clarence, B.A., M.A., University of Arkansas. History Atkins, Ark. Farber, Herbert Rupert, B.S., University of Virginia. Biology Paterson, N. J. Faris, Burt Froment, B.S., Texas Christian University. Chemistry Fort Worth, Tex. Feinstein, Nathan Zigmund, B.S., University of Virginia. Biology Jersey City, N. J. Fell, Richard Royston, B.S.Ch.E., University of Delaware. Chemistry Elsmere, Del. Fentress, John Vernon, B.A., College of William and Mary. Education Waynesboro, Va. Ferguson, Frederick Ferdinand, B.A., M.S., University of Tennessee. Biology Knoxville, Tenn. Fink, Carl Keister, B.S.Ch.E., Grove City College. Chemistry Export, Penna. Finley, John Norville Gibson, B.A., Johns Hopkins University. History Baltimore, Md. Fitch, Frederic Brenton, B.A., Ph.D., Yale University. Philosophy Quoque, N. Y. Fitch, Howard Montgomery, B.S., Texas Christian University. Chemistry Fort Worth, Tex. Fitzell, Robert Gordon, B.S. Com., University of Virginia. Economics Baltimore, Md. Fitz-Hugh, John Rose, B.S. Chem., University of Virginia. Chemistry Vicksburg, Miss. Fitzhugh, Oscar Garth, B.S. Ed., M.S., University of Virginia. Physiology Lignum, Va. Flowers, John Wilson, B.S., Southwestern; M.S., University of Virginia. Physics Memphis, Tenn. Forbes, Henry Louis, Jr., B.S. Ch.E., University of South Carolina. Chemistry Columbia, S. C. Foster, Althea McClure, B.A., Converse College. Latin Spartanburg, S. C. Foster, Talmage DeWitte, B.S., M.A., College of William and Mary. Education Waverly, Va. Franklin, Francis Mack, B.A., University of Richmond. Philosophy Big Island, Va. Fray, John Joseph, B.S. Ed., Roanoke College. Education Rustburg, Va. Fry, Edward Merrick, B.A., Rice Institute. Chemistry Fort Worth, Tex. Fugate, Charles Hagan, B.A., Emory and Henry College. Psychology Snowflake, Va. Garman, Warren DeWitt, B.S., M.E., Pennsylvania State College. Physics Lewisburg, Penna. Gayle, Thomas Benton, B.S. Agric. Ed., Virginia Polytechnic Institute. Education Fredericksburg, Va. Gersoni, Charles S., B.S., University of Virginia. Psychology Brooklyn, N. Y. Gilmer, Thomas Edward, B.S., Hampden-Sydney College; M.S., University of Virginia. Physics Hampden-Sydney, Va. Givens, Emmett Edmonson, B.S., College of William and Mary. Education Martinsville, Va. Godbey, Stanley Taylor, B.A. M.A., Roanoke College; M.A., University of Virginia. Education Covington, Va. Gravely, William Henry, Jr., B.A., College of William and Mary; M.A., University of Virginia. English Martinsville, Va. Graves, Harry Brice, B. S. Com., M.S, University of Virginia, Economics University, Va. Greer, Callie Louise, B.A., Emory and Henry College; M.A., University of Virginia. English Abingdon, Va. Gregory, Walton Carlyle, B.A., Lynchburg College. Biology Amherst, Va. Gwathmey, Allan Talbott, B.S., Virginia Military Institute; S.B., Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Chemistry Richmond, Va. Hall, Dick Wick, B.S., University of Virginia. Mathematics Casanova, Va. Hall, Robert Turner, B.S., Virginia Military Institute; M.S., University of Virginia. Chemistry University, Va. Halstead, Frank Gedney, B.S., University of Virginia. Spanish Norwalk, Conn. Ham, William Taylor, Jr., B.S.E., M.S., University of Virginia. Physics Norfolk, Va. Harlan, Howard Harper, B.A., University of Richmond; M.A., University of Virginia. Sociology Richmond, Va. Harris, William Lile, B.S., University of Virginia. Education Cherokee, Ala. Hartman, John Henry, B.S. Com., University of Virginia. Economics University, Va. Hartmann, Maurice Milton, B.A., M.A., Washington University. English St. Louis, Mo. Hathaway, Charles Odbert, Jr., B.S., University of Virginia. Biology Hampton, Va. Haydon, Richard Challice, B.S. Ed., University of Virginia. Education Manassas, Va. Heins, Paul, B.S. Geol., University of Virginia. Geology Arlington, Va. Helm, James Thomas, Jr., B.S., State Teachers College of Fredericksburg. Education The Plains, Va. Hewson, Cecile Bolton, B.A., Bryn Mawr College; M.A., University of Virginia. Psychology University, Va. Hogan, Lucy Roberta, B.A., Transylvania University. Economics Lexington, Ky. Holsinger, Earl Chester, B.A., Bridgewater College; M.A., University of Virginia. Economics Broadway, Va. Holsinger, Justus Geil, B.A., Bridgewater College. Political Science Edom, Va. Honick, Leonard, B.S. Com., University of Virginia. Spanish Newport News, Va. Hootman, Willard Perry, B.A., Randolph-Macon College. Education Arvonia, Va. Hudson, Ruth Leigh, B.A., M.A., University of Texas. English Laramie, Wyo. Hunsberger, George Ephraim, B.A., M.A., Oberlin College; Ph.D., University of Virginia. Economics Wadsworth, Ohio Hutcherson, Dudley Robert, B.A., Emory and Henry College; M.A., University of Virginia. English Bluefield, W. Va. Hutcheson, John David, B.S. Ch.E., Georgia School of Technology. Chemistry Edinburg, Va. Janney, Werner Lutz, B.A., University of Virginia. English Lincoln, Va. Jarvis, Hilda Price, B.S. Ed., University of Virginia. Sociology University, Va. Jenkins, Iredell, B.A., M.A., University of Virginia. Philosophy Norfolk, Va. Jennings, Robert Cleveland, B.S., M.A., College of William and Mary. Education Waynesboro, Va. Johnson, Albert Edward, B.A., University of Virginia. English Merrick, N. Y. Johnson, Henry Satterwhite, B.A., University of Richmond; M.A., University of Virginia. Education Hylas, Va. Johnson, Jeannette, B.A., M.A., University of Alabama. French Montgomery, Ala. Joyner, Moses Butler, B.S., College of William and Mary. Education Dendron, Va. Kattsoff, Louis Osgood, B.A., M.A., Ph.D., University of Pennsylvania. Philosophy Philadelphia, Penna. Kean, Mattie Pendleton, B.S. Ed., M.S., University of Virginia. Sociology Trevilians, Va. Kean, Robert Hill, S.B.,S.M., Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Chemistry University, Va. Kearfott, Carl, B.S., University of Virginia. Geology Mamaroneck, N. Y. Kelly, Rachel Davidson, B.S. Biol., M.S., University of Virginia. Biology University, Va. Kennedy, Milton Boone, B.A., M.A., College of Charleston; M.A., Columbia University. English Charleston, S. C. Kinney, Laurence Forman, B.A., Hampden-Sydney College; B.D., Union Theological Seminary; M.A., University of Virginia. Philosophy University, Va. Kline, Leslie Duncan, B.S., Virginia Polytechnic Institute. Education Winchester, Va. Kohler, Charlotte, B.A., Vassar College; M.A., University of Virginia. English Richmond, Va. Krueger, John William, B.S. Biol., M.S., Bucknell University. Chemistry Chevy Chase, Md. Langford, Gerald, B.A., M.A., University of Virginia. English Savannah, Ga. Lankford, Francis Greenfield, Jr., B.S., Randolph-Macon College; M.S., University of Virginia. Education Charlottesville, Va. Lawson, Eric Wilfred, B.A., Emory and Henry College. Economics Cloverdale, Va. Lee, Katherine Rose, B.A., Western Reserve University. English Cleveland, Ohio Lillaston, John Bacon, B.S., Randolph-Macon College; B.A., Duke University. Economics Blackstone, Va. Lindamood, Jane Power, (cancelled), B.A., Mississippi State College for Women; B.J., University of Missouri. English Columbus, Miss. Lorz, Albert, B.A., Allegheny College. Biology Meadville, Penna. Lothery, Thomas Early, Jr., B.S., Davidson College. Physics Davidson, N. C. Luck, Calvin Kenley, B.S., Virginia Polytechnic Institute. Education Bedford, Va. Lukens, Isabella, B.A., Wellesley College; B.S., Drexel Institute. French University, Va. McCutchen, Kenneth Benson, B.A., Davidson College; B.D., Union Theological Seminary. English Charlottesville, Va. MacDonald, Edmund F., B.S. Com., University of Virginia. Economics Arlington, N. J. McEwen, Alfred Buffin, B.S., M.S., University of Virginia. English Richmond, Va. McGavock, Cecil Billups, Jr., B.S., University of Virginia. Geology Max Meadows, Va. McIlwaine, Thomas Jones, B.A., Hampden-Sydney College. Education Farmville, Va. McKeon, Charles King, B.A., Amherst College. Philosophy Paterson, N. J. MacLeod, Malcolm Lorimer, B.S., M.S., University of Virginia. English University, Va. McLeskey, Katherine O'Neal, B.A., Queens-Chicora College. English Charlotte, N. C. Mason, Mary Ruffin Jones, B.A., Westhampton College. Biology University, Va. May, Emery Ervin, B.A., Bridgewater College. Education New Hope, Va. May, Gladys Whitehead, B.S. Ed., University of Virginia. English Richmond, Va. May, John Benjamin, B.S., University of Virginia. Education Timberville, Va. Meade, Katherine Akers, B.A., Randolph-Macon Woman's College. Latin University, Va. Meade, Richard Andrew, B.A., Randolph-Macon College. Education Petersburg, Va. Merritt, Daniel Tatum, Jr., B.A. (1935) Duke University. Chemistry Charlottesville, Va. Miller, Clarence William, B.A., University of Richmond; M.A., University of Virginia. Education Crozet, Va. Miller, Edwin DeWitt, B.A., Bridgewater College; M.A., University of Virginia. Biology Bridgewater, Va. Miller, Frederick DeWolfe, B.A., Davidson College. English Surgoinsville, Tenn. Miller, George Tyler, B.S.E.E., Virginia Military Institute. Education Front Royal, Va. Molyneaux, Thérèse Denise, B.A., Seton Hill College, M.A., Columbia University. Sociology Charlottesville, Va. Moon, Sallie Gilman, B.A., Carleton College. English Boise, Idaho Moore, Dan Huston, B.A., M.A., Duke University. Physics Galax, Va. Murphey, Richard Rizer, (cancelled), B.A., Ohio University. French Lynchburg, Va. Musgrove, Beulah Mae, B.A., Randolph-Macon Woman's College. Sociology Roanoke, Va. Musselman, Robert Metcalfe, B.S., University of Virginia. English Keswick, Va. Mustard, Robert Wall, B.S. Com., M.S., University of Virginia. Economics Cismont, Va. Nash, Susie Watts, B.S. Ed., University of Virginia. Education Waynesboro, Va. Neff, Clarence Amos, Jr., B.A., University of Virginia. English Norfolk, Va. Newman, Ruth Carolyn, B.S., Rhode Island State College. Economics Kingston, R. I. O'Brien, Martha Anne, B.S., University of Virginia. Sociology Charlottesville, Va. Oliver, William Lewis, B.A., Randolph-Macon College. History University, Va. Painter, Hunter Monroe, B.A., Roanoke College; M.A., University of Virginia. Education Fincastle, Va. Parker, William Henry, M.D., University of Virginia. Surgery Covington, Va. Parks, Nathaniel Gorham, B.S., University of Virginia. Physics Lynnhaven, Va. Patterson, John McCready, B.A., University of Virginia. English University, Va. Pawley, Raymond, Jr., B.A., Colorado College. Economics University, Va. Payne, Grattan, B.A., University of Richmond; M.A., University of Virginia. Education Richmond, Va. Pearson, Harry Marvin, B.A., Maryville College; M.A., University of Virginia. Education Remington, Va. Peden, William Harwood, B.S., University of Virginia. English Freeport, N. Y. Pegram, Robert Baker, Jr., B.A., University of Virginia. Latin Richmond, Va. Phillips, Clayton Beverley, B.A., College of William and Mary; M.A., University of Virginia. Education Hickory, Va. Phillips, Howard Mitchell, B.S., M.A., Wake Forest College. Biology Lumberton, N. C. Pickels, Edward Greydon, B.S., University of Richmond; M.S., University of Virginia. Physics Richmond, Va. Powell, Marguerite Louise, B.S. Chem., University of Georgia. Chemistry Griffin, Ga. Price, Whitfield, B.A., Mississippi College. Chemistry Clinton, Miss. Puckett, William Thomas, Jr., B.S., Roanoke College; M.S., University of Virginia. Mathematics East Radford, Va. Quarles, Lawrence Reginald, B.S.E., University of Virginia. Physics Charlottesville, Va. Quarles, Richard Wingfield, B.S.E., University of Virginia. Chemistry Richmond, Va. Rambo, William Preston, B.S., University of Virginia. French Winter Park, Fla. Reid, Charles Gordon, Jr., B.S., M.S., University of Virginia. Spanish Charlottesville, Va. Reither, Joseph Oswald, Jr., B.S., University of Virginia. History Lynbrook, N. Y. Reno, Franklin Victor, B.A., University of Colorado. Astronomy Idaho Falls, Idaho Reuss, Carl Frederick, B.S., University of Virginia. Rural Social Economics Richmond, Va. Ritter, Eugene Kerfoot, B.A., University of Richmond; M.A., University of Virginia. Mathematics Bowling Green, Va. Roberts, Charles Pleasant, Jr., B.S.Ch.E., Georgia School of Technology. Chemistry Decatur, Ga. Robertson, Archer Frank, B.A., University of Richmond. Education Berryville, Va. Robinson, Marianna, (cancelled), B.S., State Teachers College of Farmville. Education Charlottesville, Va. Robinson, Richard Augustus, B.S., Mississippi State College. Chemistry Kilmichael, Miss. Rogers, Albert Alan, B.A., University of Richmond; M.A., University of Alabama. History Wilson, Va. Ropp, Philip Hortenstine, B.A., Hampden-Sydney College; M.A., Harvard University. English Roanoke, Va. Ross, Hugh Rudasill, B.S. Bus. Adm., University of Richmond. Education Criglersville, Va. Ruebush, Trenton Kieffer, B.A., Bridgewater College; M.A., University of Virginia. Biology Dayton, Va. Runk, Benjamin Franklin Dewees, B.S., M.S., University of Virginia. Biology Greenwich, Conn. Scarborough, William Acree, B.A., Randolph-Macon College; M.A., University of Pennsylvania. Education Carson, Va. Schoen, Zbyszko John, B.S. A.O., Ohio State University; M.A., University of Buffalo. Psychology Buffalo, N. Y. Schwinn, Julia Marie, B.A., Southwestern. English Memphis, Tenn. Scott, Margaret Phelan, B.A., Hollins College; M.A., Radcliffe College. History Richmond, Va. Secondi, Joseph William, B.A., University of Virginia. Greek New York, N. Y. Senn, Harold Archie, B.A., M.A., McMaster University. Biology Caledonia, Canada Shea, Anthony Vincent, Jr., B.S. Com., University of Virginia. Rural Social Economics Richmond, Va. Sinclair, Theodore Reid, B.S., Virginia Polytechnic Institute. Education Warm Springs, Va. Slaughter, Jane Chapman, B.A., M.A., College of William and Mary; M.A., University of Virginia. French University, Va. Smith, Benjamin Warfield, B.A., University of Virginia. Biology Baltimore, Md. Smith, Edward Jaquelin, B.A., University of Virginia. History Berryville, Va. Smith, Frances Crafton, B.S., Westhampton College; M.S., University of Virginia. Biology Scottsville, Va. Smith, Joseph Winfree, Jr., B.A., University of Virginia. History Fredericksburg, Va. Smith, Marshall Noble, B.S. Ed., University of Virginia. Education Scottsville, Va. Smith, William Elliott, B.S., Pennsylvania State College. Chemistry Philadelphia, Penna. Sollenberger, Richard Talbot, B.S., M.S., University of Virginia. Psychology Ivy, Va. Spicer, William Monroe, B.S., Randolph-Macon College. Chemistry Hanover, Va. Stirewalt, Margaret Amelia, B.A., Randolph-Macon Woman's College. Biology New Market, Va. Stone, Claire Watson, B.S., State Teachers College of Fredericksburg. Education Goshen, Va. Stuart, Alfred Herbert, B.S., Hampden-Sydney College. Chemistry Farmville, Va. Stump, Guy K., B.A., Bridgewater College. Education Waynesboro, Va. Sutherland, Mortimer Yates, Jr., B.S., University of Virginia. Geology North Garden, Va. Taliaferro, Robert Catesby, B.A., University of Virginia. Philosophy Richmond, Va. Tanner, Charles Allen, Jr., B.S., University of Virginia. Chemistry Gladys, Va. Taylor, William Pinkethman, B.A., Lynchburg College; M.A., University of Virginia. Sociology Phoebus, Va. Tennis, LeGrand, B.A., College of William and Mary; M.A., University of Virginia. French Phoebus, Va. Thatcher, Joseph Herbert, B.S., Franklin and Marshall College. English Lancaster, Penna. Thomas, Walter Henry, B.S., University of Maryland; M.A., University of Virginia. Education Warrenton, Va. Thompson, M. Evelyn, B.A., Lynchburg College. Education Unionville, Va. Thompson, Ralph Rudolph, B.A., M.A., University of Virginia. Latin University, Va. Tompkins, Charles William, B.A., Randolph-Macon College. Education Crozet, Va. Trotter, Herbert, Jr., B.S., Hampden-Sydney College; M.S., University of Virginia. Physics Woodstock, Va. Turnbull, Stockton Graeme, Jr., B.S. Chem., University of Virginia. Chemistry Arlington, N. J. Varner, John Grier, Jr., B.A., Austin College; M.A., University of Virginia. English University, Va. Wade, Catherine McIver, B.S. Math., University of Virginia. Mathematics Charlottesville, Va. Walker, James Thomas, B.A., College of William and Mary. Education Gordonsville, Va. Wallace, Leonard DeLong, B.A., University of Kentucky. English Athens, Ala. Wallace, Sebon Rains, Jr., B.S., University of Virginia. Psychology Chicago, Ill. Ward, James Edward, Jr., B.S., M.S., University of Virginia. Rural Social Economics Norfolk, Va. Ward, John Cook, II, B.A., Dartmouth College; M.A., University of Virginia. English Bridgeton, N. J. Washington, Marguerite Broadhead, B.S., State Teachers College of Harrisonburg. Education Crozet, Va. Watson, Fletcher Bangs, B.A., College of William and Mary. Education Chatham, Va. Watson, George Carson, B.A., Randolph-Macon College; M.A., University of Virginia. Mathematics Danville, Va. Weaver, Emily Adeline, B.S., University of Virginia. Spanish University, Va. Webb, David Barr, B.S. Ed., University of Virginia. Education Louisa, Va. Weber, Frederick Palmer, B.A., University of Virginia. Philosophy Smithfield, Va. Weedon, William Stone, B.S., M.S., University of Virginia; M.A., Harvard University. Philosophy Wilmington, Del. Wetmore, Donald Dawson, B.A., Acadia University. English Truro, Nova Scotia Wetsel, William Henry, B.S., Virginia Polytechnic Institute. Education Burnleys, Va. Wilcox, Samuel, B.A., University of Richmond. Economics Richmond, Va. Wilkinson, Gude Aylett, B.S., Hampden-Sydney College. Chemistry Newport News, Va. Williams, Francis Dudley, B.A., M.A., University of North Carolina. Physics Chapel Hill, N. C. Wilson, Aubrey Bennett, B.A., University of Richmond. Education Keysville, Va. Wilson, Robert Archer, Jr., B.S. Com., University of Virginia. Economics Toano, Va. Wolcott, Gordon Bloomfield, B.S. Biol., M.S., University of Virginia. Biology Eatontown, N. J. Wood, John Lewis, B.S., University of Illinois. Chemistry Homer, Ill. Yagel, Cameron Gayle, B.A., Bridgewater College. Education Arvonia, Va. Zimmerman, John Oakley, B.S., Hampden-Sydney College. Physics Lynchburg, Va. STATE SUMMARY Alabama 3 Arkansas 1 Connecticut 2 Delaware 3 District of Columbia 1 Florida 1 Georgia 4 Idaho 2 Illinois 3 Kentucky 2 Maryland 6 Mississippi 5 Missouri 1 New Jersey 8 New York 13 North Carolina 7 Ohio 4 Pennsylvania 7 Rhode Island 1 South Carolina 5 Tennessee 7 Texas 3 Virginia 180 West Virginia 1 Wyoming 1 Foreign: Canada 2 Total 273 Duplicate (Law) 1 Net Total 272 GRADUATE STUDENTS REGISTERED IN SUMMER QUARTER 1934 First Term 170 Second Term 137 Total 307 Less duplicates 82 Net Total 225 GRAND SUMMARY Net Total—Long Session 272 Net Total—Summer Quarter 225 Grand Total 497</field>
   </doc>
</add>