<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Royall Tyler</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Royall Tyler</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">royall tyler</field>
      <field name="author_text">Royall Tyler</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1970's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/modern_english/uvaGenText/tei/TylTaka.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240357</field>
      <field name="date_text">1978</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:476441</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Takasago</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="title_display">Takasago</field>
      <field name="title_facet">takasago</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">takasago</field>
      <field name="title_text">Takasago</field>
      <field name="year_display">1978</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1978</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1978</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:476441&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:476441&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Royall Tyler&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;royall tyler&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Takasago&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;takasago&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1978&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1978&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="contributor" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Royall Tyler&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Takasago&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="edition"&gt;1st Edition&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1978&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Ithaca, New York&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Cornell China-Japan Program&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1978&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="callNo"&gt;Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PL 782 .E5 p55 v.1&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;rj&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;pp. 27-40&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Copyright 1978 Royall Tyler. From Pining Wind: A Cycle of Noh</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Plays (English translation). Cornell East Asia Series no.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">17, 204 pp., 0-939657-17-1, $12 paper. East Asia Program, Cornell</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">University, 140 Uris Hall, Ithaca, NY 14853-7601 (ph. 607-255-6222;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">fax: 607-255-1388, kks3@cornell.edu).&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;CAUTION: Except for brief quotations in a review, no part of this</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">text may be reproduced or utilized in any form or by any means,</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">electronic or mechanical, including photocopying and recording, or by</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">any information storage or retrieval system, without permission in</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">writing from the author. Please address inquiries to Royall Tyler in</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">care of East Asia Program, Cornell University, 140 Uris Hall, Ithaca, NY</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">14853-7601.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Takasago&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1997&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 37 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Copyright 1978 Royall Tyler. Except for brief quotations in a review, no part of this</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">text may be reproduced or utilized in any form or by any means,</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">electronic or mechanical, including photocopying and recording, or by</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">any information storage or retrieval system, without permission in</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">writing from the author. Please address inquiries to Royall Tyler in</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">care of East Asia Program, Cornell University, 140 Uris Hall, Ithaca, NY</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">14853-7601.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TAKASAGO (A god play) Takasago, by Zeami, is perhaps the best loved of all the god plays. Its clear tone will endure, all but forgotten, until it is reaffirmed in a burst of energy at the close of the demon play—here The Watchmen's Mirror. Takasago actually means "dune." The area is now an industrial city on the Inland Sea, but the Takasago Shrine is still there. Takasago has been famous in poetry since ancient times, and famous especially for the Takasago Pine. This pine is said to be paired with the Suminoe Pine, but Sumiyoshi (Suminoe is simply an older form of the same name) is far to the east, in the neighboring province, and one wonders how the two pines really can be paired. The answer is that their perfect attunement frees them from space. Moreover, the Paired Pines are free of time as well, since one is the distant past and the other the present. N? plays often hint that past and present can be one. In Takasago, the past is called the time of the Man'y?sh?, a great anthology of the earliest Japanese poetry compiled in the eighth century; and the present is called the time of the Kokinsh?, another basic anthology compiled during the Engi era, in the early tenth century. It is tactful convention that makes the Engi era the present in Takasago; no never treats the historical present. There is much talk of poetry in Takasago, but in a very wide sense. The principal Japanese word for 'poem' is uta, which more generally means song. Thus we are told that "each sound of beings feeling and non-feeling, every last one, is a song." This is why "all living things to the Blessed Isles, they say, draw nigh." For Blessed Isles (a tentative translation of the name Shikishima) is an ancient name for the islands of Japan, and here stands for Shikishima no michi, the way of the Blessed Isles: this is simply a term for poetry. The true function of poetry in the Japanese tradition is communication. When all sound is heard as song, that is, as communication of essence, there are no barriers anywhere to understanding. (It is often specifically mentioned in god plays that all barriers, gates, and checkpoints stand open: the roads are free, communications are unimpeded.) When speech is coherent, as light can be coherent, truth is conveyed. The unfailing leaves of speech spoken of in Takasago are an everlasting flow of song that conveys the essence of man, and, in a wider sense, the endless hymn sung by all beings to that other singer, the one source of all being. In this antiphon, both beings and source are at one. Leaves of speech: one can hardly fail to think of leaves of grass. "Words" is all the term means, and "leaves of speech" (ha is a pine needle as well as a leaf) is an overtranslation. But the metaphor is so often followed up in n? that one must translate it, or mutilate whole passages. The fool tells the Sideman in Takasago that the Paired Pines hold divine converse through these pine boughs: each needle is, or sings, a word of their song. And since the pine is always green, the song is indeed endless. This endless vigor and life (the pine was said to flower ten times, once every thousand years) are actually seen in the pine's unchanging hue, and heard in the sound the wind makes as it blows through a pine tree. Pining Wind is a play about this sound. The climax of Takasago is the appearance and dance of the god pine himself, in the guise of the God of Sumiyoshi. The Sumiyoshi Shrine, near what is now the city of Osaka, is one of the greatest shrines in Japan, and the god there is the god of the sea. Perhaps sea and pine are one because the sea, too, is endlessly and murmurously alive. At any rate, the young and handsome god might well be nicknamed, like Henri IV of France, Le Vert Galant.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Takasago SHIN-NO-SHIDAI Sideman and Sideman's Second enter; they stand facing each other down front. SHIDAI on-str Sideman and Side Second Now do we first our travel wear now do we first our travel wear day by day it's bound afar we go! Sideman faces front NANORI off-sp Sideman I here present before you am Tomonari, a priest from the Aso Shrine in Kyushu. As I have not yet seen Miyako, I am starting on up there now; and I mean to take a look at famous spots all along the way. They face each other again. AGEUTA on-str Sideman and Side Second Travel wear, unfolding long Miyako Way unfolding long Miyako Way's cut out for us now waves touch shore and ship lanes lie calm the spring breeze how many days stretch on, ahead, behind, all's vague white clouds trail away, Sideman takes a few steps to show travel, then by the end of the passage returns to his place and faces front. why yes, Harima coast and Takasago shore is where we are Takasago shore is where we are. TSUKI-ZERIFU off-sp Sideman Hurrying along that way, we have come to Takasago shore in the land of Harima. Perhaps someone from nearby will be kind enough to show us the sights. Sideman and Sideman's Second retire to Sideman's spot. Second enters, followed by Doer. SHIN-NO-ISSEI They stop at first and third pines, respectively. Doer wears koujijo mask and carries a rake; Second wears the uba mask and carries a broom. They face each other. ISSEI off-str Doer, Second Takasago, through the High Dune pine spring breezes blow till sundown, Onoe the Hilltop bell gently tolls. Second faces front. Second Waves with light mists veiled from shore They face each other. Doer, Second sound us the salt tides' ebb and flow. They come onstage. Second stands at center, Doer at main spot, both facing front. SASHI off-str Doer 'Who then, who shall be friend to me? Takasago's very pine of old I never knew'; They face each other. Doer, Second as ages come, ages gone, bank snow on what snows we hoary cranes roost where lingers breaking dawn by spring nights of rime, work or rest, it's pining wind alone the ear takes in, while the heart's the friend I choose to open to. SAGEUTA on-str For callers, why, courting the pines come shore winds and fallen needles cloak now sleeve by sleeve, come, clear litter from beneath the tree come, clear litter from beneath the tree! AGEUTA on-str The place here, Takasago the place here, Takasago, and Hilltop Pine has grown old, ripples of age come wrinkling in, and all around under the tree fallen needles lie deep-piled, so enduring does life thrive, and how much longer yet? The Iki Pine, Doer moves to center as Second goes to mark post; they face front. why, there's another place of lasting fame why, there's another place of lasting fame. MONDO off-str* Sideman sp Just as I'm waiting for someone from the village, an old couple has arrived. Old people, I beg your pardon, but I have a question for you. Doer You're talking to us, sir? What is it? Sideman Which of these trees is the Takasago Pine? Doer Why, the one this old man is clearing around right now, that's the Takasago Pine. Sideman The Takasago Pine and the Pine of Suminoe are said to be 'paired,' yet Takasago and Sumiyoshi are a whole province apart. How is it they're called the Paired Pines? Doer The preface to the Kokinsh? says, 'The pines of Takasago and Suminoe are themselves reputed to be paired.' But this old man is from Sumiyoshi, in yonder land of Tsu. It's the old lady here who hails from Takasago. He turns to Second. If you know anything about this, do please tell it. Sideman s Astonishing! I see, old people, that you're together here, man and wife, yet far Suminoe and Takasago, by shore and mountain a whole land apart, you say are your homes. How can this be? Second Strange question! Though ten thousand leagues of hill and stream divide them, for lovers' hearts finely attuned, the way is never long. Doer sp Just reflect a little. Doer and Second face each other. Doer, Second s The Takasago, Suminoe pines, all insentient, do still bear the name of Paired: how much more we, then, living humans, with all the years we've gladly plied between here and Sumiyoshi— an old couple, who in the pines' own company have until now Doer presses toward Sideman. lived on, paired in age. KAKEAI off-str* Sideman s I hear you talk with greatest pleasure. Tell me then: the Paired Pines you spoke of now, do people here draw from them no moral? Doer sp In the old days, people said they mark a happy reign. Second sp Takasago means the ancient times of the Man'y?sh?; Doer sp and Sumiyoshi, His Majesty of Engi, who dwells in this present age. Second s Pine means unfailing leaves of speech Doer sp whose vigor endures now, as then, Doer, Second sp an image of praise to this reign. Sideman Most willingly I've heard you out, and how I thank you! Now in me no doubts spring sunny days Doer, Second with tempered brightness light the western sea, Sideman and yonder, Suminoe, Doer Takasago here Sideman pines gather hue, Doer presses toward Sideman. Doer the spring is mild, Doer faces front, while Second goes to stand before Chorus and Sideman sits at Sideman's spot. At 'rustles,' Doer advances a little and opens; after 'fortune,' he changes mood and goes to mark post, then turns left up to main spot; at 'of our Lord's,' turns to Sideman, then moves to center and sits. Second sits also. AGEUTA on-str Chorus the Four Seas calm, the Realm at peace; a timely breeze rustles no boughs in this sovereign reign! Well met indeed, the Paired Pines show good fortune! No, no praise is equal to the task, for such a reign brings to us, His subjects, full richness of our Lord's blessing, o the precious gift! of our Lord's blessing, o the precious gift! * off-sp Sideman But do tell me more about the happy meaning of the Takasago Pine. KURI off-str Chorus Now, plants and trees, they say, have no heart, yet flower and fruit never miss their time; filled with the power of surging spring, the southern boughs it is that blossom first. SASHI off-str Doer Yet this pine looks ever the same; the flowers and fruit distinguish no time. Chorus The four seasons pass, yet deep its millenial hue holds amid the snow; and the pine's very flowers bloom ten times, once in ten lives. Doer For such tidings one pine's boughs Chorus bear needles, leaves of speech aglow with dewdrop pearls: these in the heart seed polished grace, Doer till all living things Chorus to the Blessed Isles, they say, draw nigh. KUSE on-str For indeed, in Ch?n?'s words, 'Each sound of beings feeling and non-feeling, every last one, is a song.' Plants, trees, soil, sand, voice of the wind, water noises: even there's a heart to harbor all. Springtime woods moving to east wind, fall insects crying in northern dews: are not both song, our poetry? And the pine stands over all trees, in lordly guise, green through a thousand falls, and shows no hue of new or old: a tree worthy of that title, Marquis, the First Emperor gave it, so that in China and this Realm, all men accord it praise. Doer 'Takasago, the High Dunes' Hilltop bell rings; Doer stands, still holding his rake, and comes down front. Chorus through to dawn settles freezing rime,' yet pine boughs' needles stay the same deep green. Morning and night He mimes sweeping. I come to clean beneath the tree, but fallen needles never fail: for true it is, He gazes up as though at pine branches. pine needles do not all fall, their hue only grows and grows the masaki vine, sign of an enduring reign; and among all evergreens the Takasago Pine He turns to Sideman, then moves to center and sits. in this late age, paired still, signals blessing. RONGI on-str Yes, justly famed, boughs of this pine, yes, justly famed, boughs of this pine the old tree's past do tell, and now, pray, say your names! Doer, Second Then, what need we conceal? We, the spirits of the Paired Pines of Takasago and Suminoe, man and wife, stand before you. Chorus Astonishing! So, the renowned pines show a wonder, Doer, Second and though plants are without heart, Chorus so wise His rule Doer, Second that plants and trees, both, Chorus land that this is of our great Lord, aspire under His sovereign reign to dwell on and Doer turns to Sideman, then points his fan toward back of stage. on we'll go to Sumiyoshi now to wait for you, cry they beside He stands, goes to side, and stamps beat as though boarding a boat. the evening waves a fishing craft now board, and sail before the wind far, far away across the sea far, far away across the sea. Doer and Second exit. Now Sideman addresses Sideman's Second, and approximately the following dialogue ensues. MONDO off-sp Sideman I've a question to ask. Please see if anyone is nearby. Side Second Yes, sir. He goes to main spot. Hello! Is anyone around? The Fool, who some time ago slipped in to sit at Fool's spot, now stands. Fool Surely. What can I do for you? Side Second Would you mind coming with me? My master has a question he wishes to ask you. Fool By all means. Sideman's second goes before Sideman. Side Second Sir, here is someone who will answer your question. He goes to sit before Chorus. Fool sits at center. Sideman The Takasago Pine is famous indeed. But could you tell me about its connection with the Pine of Suminoe? Fool Well, I hardly know a thing about it, but I'll tell you what I've heard. KATARI off-sp They say the pines of Takasago and Suminoe stand for the Man'y?sh? and the Kokinsh?. One story has it that the God of Takasago and the God of Sumiyoshi were man and wife, and that when they called on each other they held divine converse through these pine boughs. That's why the pines are described as Paired. The glory of our own poetry, the vigor of courtship and marriage: for both of these we have the gods' divine power to thank. He goes on to cite various classic texts in support of his theme. By the way, didn't you meet an old man and an old woman cleaning around the base of the pine here? Sideman I did indeed. They spoke of the Paired Pines and of their fame, then suddenly stepped into a boat and set sail, they said, for Sumiyoshi. Fool Then no doubt that old couple were the spirits of the Takasago and Suminoe pines themselves. You really should go on pilgrimage to Sumiyoshi. Sideman But I have no boat. Fool In that case, please do this little craft, newly built as it is, the honor of being the first to sail it. It will take you safely to Sumiyoshi. See! A following breeze is blowing! Sideman Thank you very much indeed. Fool At your service. Fool retires to Fool's spot. He will slip out after the Doer's entrance. Sideman and Sideman's Second now face each other down front. AGEUTA on-str Sideman and Side Second Takasago! Our light craft under all sail our light craft under all sail slips out with the moon rising, the tide surge swells waves' salt foam, Awaji Isle looms and drops far thunders Naruo while skimming on swiftly to Suminoe borne we have put in swiftly to Suminoe borne we have put in. DEHA Sideman and Sideman's Second retire to Sideman's spot. Doer, who is now the God of Sumiyoshi, makes a vigorous entrance and stands facing front at first pine. He wears the kantan-otoko mask. SASHI off-str Doer 'Myself I've watched these long, long years on Sumiyoshi coast, the lady-pine— and she, what eons has she seen?' 'We're lovers: did my Lord not know? Within the Pristine Zone, Doer strikes full excitement pose, then stamps several beats. down long ages has the god endured; music and mime now play, night drums in rhythm beat, He sweeps his gaze over orchestra. soothe His heart now, ye of the Shrine! Now he goes to main spot. At 'rises,' he stamps several beats; at 'spring,' points around with fan, as though at a still snow-mantled landscape; at 'by the beach,' goes before drums, faces front, opens; at 'thousand,' stamps several beats; at 'break off,' comes down front, mimes the action described, then turns left back up to drums, takes left sleeve in right hand, gazes as though at petals clinging there. KAMI-NO-EI off-str Chorus Up from the western sea, wave furrows of Liveoak Plain, Doer rises now revealed the god pine, and it's spring! ISSEI off-str Lingering snows thin down Asaka strand Chorus and by the beach where sleek seaweed is cut and garnered, Doer but once draw nigh a pine's stout root, rub your hips there, Chorus and a thousand years' fresh green brims from your hands; Doer break off blossoming plum, set it in your hair, Chorus and snow of the second moon sprinkles your cloak.' KAMI-MAI At main spot now, Doer begins a vigorous but elegant dance. As text resumes, he withdraws to Doer post. RONGI on-str O precious vision! O precious vision! Clear shines the moon at Sumiyoshi sports the God: with what new joy we worship His own form divine! Doer is now facing front at main spot. Below, at 'the pine,' he gazes toward pines on bridgeway; then points with fan at his own image reflected in the sea down front; at 'For God,' goes to mark post, then sweeps left up to center; at 'pure,' glances at his own left sleeve, then turns right and up to flute; then strikes full excitement pose, as though sweeping away demons; then moves to center, mimes embracing something, stamps beat; at 'Thousand Autumns,' moves down front, pointing before him with fan, then rolls up the long, hanging length of his sleeves, then turns right and up to main spot; at first 'inspires,' opens toward front; then faces side and stamps final beat. Doer Yes, the varied dancing maidens' voices ring clear too, the pine of Suminoe mirrored shows in Blue Sea Waves is this, surely! Chorus For God, for Lord, straight lies the way, to Miyako in springtime go, Doer and the dance is Home to the Palace; Chorus endless fair years they bring, Doer the pure, festal robes: Chorus a darting hand sweeps demons hence, an arm drawn in clasps length of days and good fortune. A Thousand Autumns brings folk ease; Ten Thousand Years makes life long, so long the paired pining wind's hushed singing sound inspires tranquil joy hushed singing sound inspires tranquil joy.</field>
   </doc>
</add>