<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university of virginia</field>
      <field name="author_text">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1910's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2005_Q2_2/uvaBook/tei/z000000260.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240342</field>
      <field name="date_text">February, 1919</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:114806</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">University of Virginia record. New series Vol. V, No.3a, February, 1919</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">University of Virginia -- Periodicals</field>
      <field name="subject_text">University of Virginia -- Periodicals</field>
      <field name="title_display">University of Virginia record.  New series Vol. V, No.3a, February, 1919</field>
      <field name="title_facet">university of virginia record</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">university of virginia record</field>
      <field name="title_text">University of Virginia record.  New series Vol. V, No.3a, February, 1919</field>
      <field name="year_display">February, 1919</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1919-02</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1919</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:114806&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:114806&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;serial volume&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;university of virginia&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;University of Virginia record. New series Vol. V, No.3a, February, 1919&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;university of virginia record&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;February, 1919&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1919-02&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;University of Virginia record&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="volume"&gt;New series Vol. V&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="issue"&gt;No.3a&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;February, 1919&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Va.&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="LC call number"&gt;LD5667 .A43&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa call number"&gt;LD5667.2&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;X006131544&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;o07560180&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;29 p. ; 23 cm.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;University of Virginia -- Periodicals&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The University of Virginia Record&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="volume"&gt;New Series, 5&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="issue"&gt;3a&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1919-02&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2005&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2005 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 102 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">[2] Preliminary Announcement SUMMER SCHOOL OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA OFFICERS OF THE SUMMER SCHOOL. Aministrative Board. EDWIN ANDERSON ALDERMAN, D. C. L., LL. D., President of the University. CHARLES GILMORE MAPHIS, Professor of Secondary Education, Director of the Summer School. THOMAS FITZHUGH, M. A., Professor of Latin. JAMES MORRIS PAGE, M. A. Ph. D., Dean and Professor of Mathematics. JOHN LEVI MANAHAN, B. S., M. A., Professor of Education. MRS. S. S. MATTHEWS, Registrar. E. I. CARRUTHERS, Bursar. JAMES N. HILLMAN, Registrar for Department of Public Instruction. FRED M. ALEXANDER, Local Manager. MRS. M. P. HARRIS, Matron. SUMMER SCHOOL OF 1919. University, Virginia. First Term—June 23-Aug. 2. Second Term—Aug. 4-Sept. 6. ENROLLMENT BLANK. Please enroll me as a student of the Summer School of 1919 at University, Va. If I find that I have to withdraw before opening of the session I will notify you to that effect. Date_____1919 Name _______________ Home Address _______________ Have you attended the summer school at University before?_____ If you have attended University or elsewhere, please give dates of attendance_______________ I desire to attend _____ term (fill in first or second). SUMMER SCHOOL OF 1919. University, Virginia. First Term—June 23-Aug. 2. Second Term—Aug. 4-Sept. 6. DORMITORY BLANK. If you wish to room in the dormitories fill and return this blank with your Enrollment Blank and a place will be reserved for you. You will be notified if a place cannot be reserved for you. Date_____1919 Name _______________ Home Address _______________ Date on which you expect to arrive_______________ Room preferred _____ Term_____ Room-mate preferred _______________ Note.—The full summer school catalogue will be mailed only to those persons who are interested and will write for it. If, therefore, you wish a catalogue which will be ready the last of March, please write a postal giving the address to which you wish it sent. [3] FACULTY ORA HART AVERY Domestic Science (Instructor in Domestic Science, Athens, Ga., High School). THOMAS FAUNTLEROY BALL, B. S. Physics (Instructor in Physics, University of Virginia). ALBERT G. A. BALZ, M. A., Ph. D. Psychology and Philosophy (Associate Professor of Philosophy, University of Virginia). JAMES COOK BARDIN, M. D. Spanish (Adjunct Professor of Romanic Languages, University of Virginia). MARY R. BARNETTE Penmanship (Instruction in Writing, Hughes High School, Cincinnati). GEORGIA MAY BARRETT Primary Education (Director Training School, State Normal College, Valdosta, Ga.). ROBERT MONTGOMERY BIRD, B. A., B. S., Ph. D. Chemistry (Professor of Chemistry, University of Virginia). W. L. BRAGG Manual Training (Instructor in Manual Training, John Marshall High School, Richmond, Va.). WILLIAM EDWARD BRAY, B. A., M. D. School Physician (Adjunct Professor of Medicine, University of Virginia). EVERARD JOHN CALTHROP Vocal Production (Director of Vocal Department, Elizabeth College, Salem, Virginia). GARDNER L. CARTER, Ph. D. Chemistry (Associate Professor of Chemistry, University of Virginia). HARRY H. CLARK, M. A., LL. D. Education (Professor of Secondary Education, University of Tennessee). MARY LOUISE DINWIDDIE Library Methods (Assistant Librarian of the University of Virginia). J. E. DOBBINS, B. A. Education (Instructor Technical High School, Atlanta, Ga.). WILLIAM HOLDING ECHOLS, B. S., C. E. Mathematics (Professor of Mathematics, University of Virginia). MARY EISENBISE Manual Training (Assistant Supervisor of Drawing and Manual Arts, Columbus, Ohio). WILLIAM HARRISON FAULKNER, M. A., Ph. D. German (Professor of Germanic Languages, University of Virginia). ADEN L. FILLMORE Music (Director of Music and Supervisor of Music, in Pittsburg Public Schools). HENRY F. FUCHS, B. S. Music (Professor of Violin, Harmony and Appreciation, Hollins College). THOMAS FITZ-HUGH, M. A. Latin (Professor of Latin, University of Virginia). WILLIAM MENTZEL FORREST, B. A. Biblical Literature (John B. Cary Memorial Professor of Biblical History and Literature, University of Virginia). [4] EDNA GIFFIN Secretary, Y. W. C. A. (Member Field Student Staff Y. W. C. A.). WILLIAM P. GRAHAM, M. A. French (Adjunct Professor in French, University of Virginia). JAMES N. HILLMAN, B. A., Registrar for Department of Public Instruction (Supervisor of Teacher Training, Department of Public Instruction). JOSEPHINE HOLT, B. A. French and Spanish (Instructor Modern Languages, John Marshall High School, Richmond, Va.). JAMES GIBSON JOHNSON, M. A., Ph. D. Geography (Superintendent of Schools, Charlottesville, Virginia). FREDERICK JUCHHOFF, M. A., Ph. D. Finance and Accountancy (Professor of Accountancy, Toledo University). LOULIE C. KELLEY Geography (Instructor in Physical Geography, John Marshall High School, Richmond, Virginia). EVELYN KENDRICK, B. A. Physical Education (Assistant Department Physical Education, Mississippi Industrial Institute and College). WILLIAM ALLISON KEPNER, M. A., Ph. D. Biology (Professor of Biology, University of Virginia). HENRY C. KREBS, B. A. Education (Superintendent of Schools, Somerset County, New Jersey). WILLIAM ALEXANDER LAMBETH, M. D., Ph. D. Field Botany (Professor of Hygiene, University of Virginia). ALBERT LEFEVRE, B. A., Ph. D., LL. D. Philosophy (Professor of Philosophy, University of Virginia). RABBI DAVID LEFKOWITZ Jewish Education JOHN LEVI MANAHAN, Ph. D. Education (Professor of Educational Administration, University of Virginia). EDWIN MIMS, Ph. D. English (Professor of English, Vanderbilt University). J. MOORE McCONNELL, M. A., Ph. D. History (Professor of History and Economics, Davidson College). JAMES SUGARS McLEMORE, M. A., Ph. D. Latin (Adjunct Professor of Latin, University of Virginia). HOWARD MORGAN McMANAWAY, B. A. Education (Division Superintendent of Schools, Albemarle County). GRACE D. MASSENGALE, B. A. Physical Education (Assistant in Physical Education, Mississippi Industrial Institute and College). JOHN CALVIN METCALF, M. A., Litt. D. English (Professor of English, University of Virginia). JAMES NEWTON MICHIE, B. S. Mathematics (Assistant Professor of Mathematics, Agricultural and Mechanical College of Texas). GRACE ELDRIDGE MIX, B. S. Kindergarten Education (Supervisor of Kindergarten Education, State Normal School, Farmville, Va.). [5] WELDEN THOMAS MYERS, M. A., Ph. D. English (Professor of English, Converse College, Spartanburg, S. C.). JAMES MORRIS PAGE, M. A., Ph. D., LL. D. Mathematics (Dean and Professor of Mathematics, University of Virginia). JOHN SHELTON PATTON Library Methods (Librarian of the University of Virginia). EMMA ODY POHL Physical Education (Director Physical Education, Mississippi Industrial Institute and College). ANITA L. POLLITZER, B. S. Drawing (Late Assistant in Art, Horace Mann School). ERICH RATH Music (Director of Music, Hollins College). IDA EVANS ROGERS, B. A. Primary Education (Supervisor of Instruction, Mt. Vernon, N. Y.). EDWIN H. SCOTT, B. S., M. S. Agriculture (Professor of Agriculture and Biology, Georgia Normal and Industrial College). EDWIN FRANCIS SHEWMAKE, JR., M. A. English (Adjunct Professor of English, University of Virginia). YETTA SHONINGER, B. S. Elementary Education (Associate-Professor Elementary Education, George Peabody College for Teachers). EDWARD EHRLICH SMITH, M. A. Education (Assistant Superintendent of Schools, Richmond, Va.). BENJAMIN SLEDD, M. A., Ph. D. English (Professor of English, Wake Forest College, N. C.). T. R. SNAVELY, M. A. History and Sociology (Instructor in Economics, University of Virginia). ETHEL SUMMY, B. S. Primary Education (Primary Model Teacher, Washington, D. C.). ELIZABETH H. TENNANT Music (Supervisor of Music, West Chester Normal, Penn.). GEORGE A. WAUCHOPE, M. A., Ph. D. English (Professor of English, University of South Carolina). ROBERT FRANKLIN WEBB, B. C. S. Commercial Courses (Principal Commercial Department of City High School, Charlottesville, Virginia). CARL WHITLOCK Biology (Assistant in Biology, University of Virginia). DAISY WINGFIELD Music (Supervisor of Music, Roanoke Public Schools). Note.—This is not a complete faculty list. Other names will be added and published in the complete catalogue which will be mailed only on application. If interested, please write for it. It will be ready April first. [6] ANNOUNCEMENTS This is a preliminary announcement. The complete catalogue will be ready for distribution about April first. It will be mailed only to those who apply for it. If interested, write to Secretary Summer School, Box 149, University, Va. The University of Virginia Summer School is conducted for teachers and students in high schools, academies and colleges and for those who desire professional training for primary and grammar grade work. It also offers many courses for college credit, and others to meet the needs of students preparing for college entrance or who have conditions to absolve. It takes as its peculiar province, not the ordinary summer institute, but the solid and substantial training of high school teachers, college teachers, college students, and teachers of any grade who wish to procure professional work. LOCATION.—Charlottesville, the seat of the University of Virginia, is in a picturesque and healthful situation among the foot-hills of the Blue Ridge Mountains. It is at the junction of two great lines of railway, the Chesapeake and Ohio and the Southern, and is thus of easy access from every part of the country. The sanitary arrangements of the University are excellent. The climate is invigorating, healthful, and free from malarial conditions, the average elevation of the surrounding country being about six hundred and fifty feet above sea level; the water supply is pure, being drawn by gravity from a mountain reservoir six miles away; the system of drains and sewers is complete. The average monthly mean temperature from 1901 to 1911, taken from the records of the weather station at the University Observatory, was: June, 71.4; July, 76.8. There are three golf links, a well-conducted country club and many other attractions for summer visitors. EXCURSIONS.—Under the directorship of a competent guide, there will be excursions to neighboring points of interest such as Monticello, the home of Thomas Jefferson; the Natural Bridge; Luray Caverns; the Grottoes of the Shenandoah; the battle fields in Virginia; and any other points to which a sufficiently large number may care to go. The proximity to Washington and Richmond and Old Point Comfort (three hours' ride to each) should make a visit exceptionally interesting. On designated clear nights parties will leave Cabell Hall at 8 o'clock to visit the McCormick Astronomical Observatory, where they will be shown the stars through the large telescope in the Observatory. ENTERTAINMENTS, AND LECTURES.—A Musical Festival and other entertainments will be announced during the session of the Summer School. The Clifford B. Devereux Company will give three plays and The Players Club one or two plays. The whole course includes about twenty numbers and the price of a season ticket is $2.50 making the cost about the same as moving pictures. BOARD AND ROOMS.—Board and room may be had at prices ranging from $5.00 per week, where several stay in the same room, upward, according to accommodation and proximity to the University, the average being $5.00 to $6.00 per week. Most of the boarding houses immediately adjoin the University grounds. [7] One hundred single furnished rooms and one hundred and twenty-five furnished double rooms in the University dormitories will be reserved in the order of application. The price will be $6.00 for the full term of six weeks for a single room, and $9.00 for a double room. The price for the second term will be $3.50 for a single room, and $5.00 for a double room. All checks for rooms should be made payable to E. I. Carruthers, Bursar. Every double room must be occupied by two persons. No reduction will be made for parts of a term. Applications for rooms must be accompanied with the full amount of the fee, which will be returned for good reason and room released if application is made before June 10th. No rooms will be rented to any person who does not register and pay the fee in the Summer School. Rooms that are reserved will not be held later than July 1st. No room will be open for occupancy before June 21st. Roomers must provide themselves with necessary bed clothes, towels, etc. Rooms will be in charge of Mrs. M. P. Harris, an experienced matron and chaperon. Some members of the faculty will be located in each set of dormitories. No cooking allowed in rooms. The rooms on Dawson's Row will be reserved for men. The location of these dormitories in the University grounds and the social advantages resulting from bringing so many teachers close together make this arrangement a very desirable one and the rooms are eagerly sought. The University Commons, conducted by Mrs. S. I. Carter, will be open for summer students and will provide table board for three hundred and fifty persons at the very low price of $5.00 for a single week. $18.00 a month or $4.50 per week, if paid weekly, or $25.00 for the first term of forty-one days and $20.00 for the second term from August 2 to September 6th. A lunch counter will be run in connection with the Commons, open from 9:30 A. M. to 11 P. M. Application for dormitory rooms should be sent promptly with retaining fee. For list of boarding houses, rates, etc., see page —, or write to Secretary Summer School, Box 149, University, Virginia. FEES FOR VIRGINIA TEACHERS AND STUDENTS.—Tuition will be entirely free to all Virginia teachers in all the regular courses, both elementary and advanced, leading to the professional and first and second grade certificates. To meet local expenses the State Board of Education has fixed a registration fee of $1.50 for a six weeks' term for all of the Summer Schools of the State, and this fee will be charged here. There are a few special courses offered to meet certain demands but not necessary for certificate credit, for which fees will be charged to all who take them. The fee for each is designated in the catalogue. Small fees in laboratory courses will also be charged all students who register in them. Students from Virginia who are not teachers or preparing to teach next session will be charged the same tuition as non-Virginia students. Teachers whose residence is in Virginia but who are teaching outside of Virginia will be charged the same fee as non-Virginians. FEES FOR NON-VIRGINIA STUDENTS.—A single registration fee of fifteen dollars will be charged each student who registers from outside of Virginia. This fee will entitle the student to enter any of the courses outlined in the catalogue (except a few special courses which are so designated). No student, however, will be permitted to take more than three advanced courses or six elementary [8] courses without special permission in writing from the Director and without paying an extra fee of $5.00 for advanced courses, or $3.00 for elementary courses. Note.—Teachers outside of Virginia are not limited in the choice of their courses to the regulations under which Virginia certificates are issued, unless they desire to teach in Virginia and apply for a license issued in this State. In this case only State certificates from other states issued by a State Superintendent or a State Board of Examiners, and approved in advance by the Department of Public Instruction of Virginia, will be recognized as a proper basis for professional credit. Teachers from other states will receive credit for all work done at the University Summer School in accordance with the certificate regulations of those States from which they come. Medical Fee.—A small medical fee of 50 cents will be charged each person who registers in the Summer School, which will entitle him or her to free medical attendance by Dr. W. E. Bray, the Summer School Physician, hospital phone, 548; residence phone, 565; office hours at the hospital 11:30 to 12:30 and 4:00 to 5:00. Greatly reduced charges, if it should be necessary, will be given at the University Hospital, under the following regulations: Medical Attendance.—Any student who is temporarily ill from causes not due to his own misconduct, is entitled, without charge, to all necessary medical advice from the Summer School Physician; and, if necessary, to nursing in the University Hospital at a reasonable charge for the maintenance while there. This exemption from charge does not apply to cases requiring surgical operation, and for special treatment of the eye, ear, nose, and throat, or to constitutional disorders from which the student in question was suffering at the time of his coming to the University. Nor is the University responsible for the expense incurred through the employment of private nurses, necessitated by severe illness of students, or through the maintenance of quarantine precautions in contagious cases. Any student sent to the University Hospital by the advice and under the care of a physician other than the Summer School Physician will be required to pay the regular hospital charges for private patients. TIME AND PLACE OF RECITATIONS AND LECTURES.— Recitations will begin in all courses Tuesday, June 24th, at 8:30 a. m. There will be no classes on Saturdays except on June 28th, and July 5th and 12th, when classes will meet at the usual hours to make up for registration day and Fourth of July. The length of recitation periods will be one hour, ten minutes of which will be allowed for transfer from one room to another. DAILY GENERAL ASSEMBLY.—Daily from 11:30 to 12:15 there will be a period in which the students may have the privilege of attending a gathering of the entire body. At this time there will be devotional exercises, music, short addresses on timely topics by prominent speakers invited for this purpose, or some other interesting exercise. SUNDAY VESPER SERVICES.—Experience has shown that no Sunday service held here during the summer has been more attractive or more appreciated than what has sometimes been called the Sunset Service. Holding this service at this hour enables all the faculty and the students of the summer school to unite in one common [9] service without at all interfering with their attending the churches of their choice in the city. The service, which is always kept within one hour, begins at seven o'clock. When weather permits, the service is held out of doors on the North Rotunda steps. Otherwise in Cabell Hall. REGISTRATION.—Monday, June 23rd, will be devoted to the registration of students. All students who can possibly do so should register on this day. Those who fail to register before June 23rd will be permitted to attend classes and register as promptly as possible at other hours. The Registrar's office, located in Peabody Hall will be open continuously from 8:30 a. m. to 6:30 p. m. Students should consult freely with members of the Faculty in case of difficulty in choosing courses. No certificate will be granted to students who fail to register before Tuesday, July 1st, except a certificate of attendance. No student will be admitted to any course without a registration card naming the course in question and properly signed by the Registrar and the Bursar. THE GENERAL LIBRARY.—The General Library is open to the corps of instructors and the students of the Summer School from 9 a. m. to 1:30 p. m. 3 to 5, and from 7:30 to 10 p. m. The collection contains about seventy thousand volumes. All books withdrawn from the library must be charged at the desk. Usually books are lent for one week but there are exceptions, and the loan expires on the date stamped in the book. Prompt return not later than the date on which the loan expires is expected and borrowers will be fined ten cents for each day delinquent. Students are expected to give prompt attention to all communications from the librarian. REST AND STUDY ROOMS.—Madison Hall, the beautiful building of the Young Men's Christian Association, and during the summer session headquarters for the Y. W. C. A., will be open to students and Faculty of the Summer School from nine o'clock in the morning until ten at night. Students will have access to the current periodicals in the reading room. The other rooms will be used for rest, for study, for recreation, and for social gatherings. North of the building there are nineteen tennis courts which will be equipped for the use of the students. YOUNG WOMEN'S CHRISTIAN ASSOCIATION CLUB.— Open to every woman in the Summer School, this club is organized for the purpose of promoting a pleasant social atmosphere, giving an opportunity for social service and religious development, and for study of methods in club work and church work. The activities include "stunt parties," camp breakfast, Camp Fire Girls demonstrations, weekly meetings on religious and social questions and special lectures on rural life questions. A secretary devotes her entire time to the work and has charge of the club headquarters at Madison Hall. Her office hours are from 9 to 11 a. m. and from 2 to 3 p. m. STUDENTS' MAIL.—In order to insure safe and prompt delivery of mail, every student should have all mail directed to University, Virginia, giving always the street and number of his or her boarding place or the number and location of his or her room in the University. The local address should be filed at the post office promptly upon arrival. [10] TEACHERS' POSITIONS.—The University Appointment Committee receives demands for teachers each year. This committee would be glad to have well qualified teachers who are in attendance upon the Summer School leave their applications with the Registrar. THE SUMMER SCHOOL NEWS.—The News is a college newspaper, edited and managed by students of the Summer School. It contains all official and student organization announcements, campus news and notes, editorial comment, etc. Its object is to acquaint individuals with the life of the whole student body, and to unify the interests of all. RURAL LIFE WEEK.—The time between July 7 and 12 will be devoted to the study of rural life problems in general, and to the Community Centre in particular. A special effort will be made to secure a large attendance of farmers, and farmers' wives, and community leaders and distinguished speakers from all sections of the United States will participate in the Conferences. FOURTH OF JULY PAGEANT.—Each year an elaborate pageant is given in connection with the Fourth of July Celebration. An extensive celebration will be a feature this year. REGULATIONS CONCERNING CREDIT.—The instructor giving each course will keep the class grades, and attendance, hold the examination, and average the class grade with the examination grade, returning to the Director the general average grade of each student in each course. Absences or delayed entrance will be counted against the student. All examinations must be held under the Honor System. A certificate for each course completed with an average grade of 75 per cent will be signed by the instructor and the Director of the Summer chool, and mailed to the student. Credit Allowed by Other States than Virginia.—Application has been made to other Southern States for credit equal to that accorded by the Virginia Department of Public Instructions. Credits are now allowed toward the extension of the certificates by certain other States. All persons wishing to arrange for credits with their respective school authorities should correspond with the Director of the Summer School. University of Virginia College Credit.—Below are stated the conditions upon which credit in the University of Virginia may be granted for work done in the Summer School. (a) The student must satisfy the entrance requirements of the University of Virginia and matriculate before he can receive credit in the College for any work done in the University of Virginia Summer School. (b) The Dean of the College will accept the completion of the courses in the Summer School in lieu of the entrance examinations in the same subject, provided that in his judgment the courses are equivalent to those required for entrance to the University of Virginia, and provided, that the certificates of courses completed be approved by the University of Virginia professor concerned. (c) The Dean of the College will accept certificates of completion of summer courses in the University of Virginia, provided that such summer courses be approved by the University of Virginia professor concerned as the full equivalent in character and scope of the corresponding courses in the University. [11] All courses numbered from 1 to 100 in this catalogue have been approved by the professors concerned and will be accepted by the Dean for such credit as is indicated in the description of each course. (d) Students who satisfy entrance requirements will not only receive credit at the University of Virginia for college courses taken in the Summer School, but the summer school work is recognized by standard colleges everywhere, so that students have no difficulty in securing transfer of credits. Honor System.—All examinations are held under the honor system and the honor pledge required. VIRGINIA STATE CERTIFICATES. The Virginia certificates with which the courses of study at the University Summer School are immediately concerned are the following: First and Second Grade Certificates. The Elementary Professional Certificate for either Primary or Grammar Grades. The Special Certificate—For High School Teachers. The Collegiate Certificate—For High School Teachers. The Collegiate Professional Certificate—For High School Teachers. Courses will also be offered to meet the requirements of the Department of Public Instruction for High School graduates, who wish to obtain certificates. There will also be courses preparing for the State Examinations for first and second grade certificates and for extension of certificates. Observation work will be provided by a well organized vacation school. REQUIREMENTS FOR THE FIRST GRADE CERTIFICATE. The applicant must be at least nineteen years old, must have academic training equivalent to the first two years of high school work, must have taught successfully at least nine months, and must make a grade of not less than 85 per cent. on the state examination. The subjects required for the First Grade Certificate and value of each are as follows, the form for the applicant being included: Form giving information about applicant (writing and theory and practice) 15 Mathematics—arithmetic 10, elementary algebra to quadratics 5 15 English—grammar and composition 10, English classics 5 15 History—American and Virginian history 10, English history 5 15 Geography 5, civics 5 10 Science—Physical geography or general science 5, agriculture 5 10 Physiology and hygiene 5, spelling 5 10 Primary reading and methods 5, drawing 5 10 "This certificate is valid for five years and renewable for a similar period. It permits the holder to teach in the elementary grades. An applicant who makes first grade averages but has not the requisite experience or is not of required age, may receive a Second Grade Certificate convertible into the First Grade when the above requisites are met. [12] "REQUIREMENTS FOR THE SECOND GRADE CERTIFICATE. The applicant must be at least eighteen years old and must make a grade of not less than 75 per cent. on the State examination, consisting of the following subjects with the value of each: Form by applicant (writing and theory and practice) 15 Arithmetic 10 English grammar and composition 10 History—United States and Virginia 10 Geography 5, civics 5 10 Physiology and hygiene 5 Primary reading and methods 5, spelling 5 10 Drawing 5 The minimum grade for a second grade certificate is 75% of 75, or 56.25. "This certificate is valid for two years and renewable for two. The holder may teach in the elementary schools. "As before stated graduates of four-year standard high schools who have attended a summer normal or institute for six weeks must receive a Second Grade Certificate." PREPARATION FOR STATE EXAMINATIONS. Complete courses, covering all of the requirements for the first and second grade certificates, will be offered, beginning June 23rd and ending with the State examinations July 25th and 26th. The State Board of Education will renew the certificate of any teacher attending for five weeks taking three courses, two of which must be in Education. For several summers this work has been given at Midway School Building in Charlottesville, but this year all of the classes will be held in the University. SUMMER QUARTER. For the first time in its history the Summer School will this year continue for two terms; the first term beginning June 23rd and ending August 2nd, and the second term beginning August 4th and ending September 6th, making a full Summer Quarter. Students may enter for either one or both terms, the work of each term being arranged as a complete unit in itself. In each term all of the courses, leading to the elementary professional certificate, will be offered. Students may secure this certificate by attending the Summer School for three sessions of six weeks each, but those students who prefer to attend a summer session two quarters of twelve weeks in separate summers in lieu of the courses for three years, as outlined, may do so provided they secure teaching experience of, at least, seven months between the two summers. The work for the first summer of this arrangement will embrace the work of the first year of the three years' course, as outlined, plus six weeks of additional, related work and the work of the second summer will include the outlined courses required for the second and third summers of the regular three year course. Teachers who remain for the second term, which will continue five weeks with lectures six [13] times a week, can do so at less expense than during the first term. The following is the regulation of the State Board of Education in regard to elementary professional certificates. The elementary professional certificate is issued to applicants who complete one year of professional work at a standard normal school, based on a standard high school course or its equivalent, or who completed work required in summer courses at some university, college, or normal school, the summer courses of which are approved by the State Board of Education. CERTIFICATE FOR HIGH SCHOOL GRADUATES. Graduates of the standard four year high schools, who attend a summer normal for one term of six weeks each, taking five classes, three of which must deal with methods of teaching, may be granted a second grade certificate. Graduates of standard four year high schools who attend a summer normal for two terms of six weeks each shall be given a provisional first grade certificate to be converted into a regular first grade after seven months of successful experience, or in the event of required experience, shall be given at once a first grade certificate. Graduates of standard high schools who attend for three summers of six weeks each taking a prescribed course will be awarded the elementary professional certificate. The course may be taken at this school in either the first term or the second term this summer, the same credit be allowed in the second terms. REGULATIONS STATE BOARD OF EDUCATION. Outline for Primary Grades. First Year. Principles of Elementary Education—Education 129a, 2.30 30 periods Methods in Reading I—Education 132, 12:15 30 periods Songs and Games—Physical Education 193, 9:30 30 periods School Hygiene and Sanitation—Education 12 30 periods Methods in Language I—Education 142, 8:30 30 periods Second Year. Principles of Teaching and Studying, 12:15 30 periods Methods in Reading II—Education 133a, 8:30 to 10:30 and 133b, 9:30 30 periods Methods in Language and Spelling—Education 134, 10:30 30 periods Public School Music—Music 332, 8:30 30 periods Hygiene and Sanitation—Education 12, 12:15 30 periods Third Year. Methods and Management—Education 15, 2:30 30 periods Drawing 122a, 9:30; or 122b, 2:30 30 periods Nature Study and Home Geography—Education 110, 10:30 30 periods Primary Industrial Work—10:30 and 12:15; 2:30 to 4:30 30 periods Child Literature and History Stories—Education 111, 12:15 30 periods Observation, 8:30 to 10:30, Midway School 20 periods [14] Outline for Grammar Grades. First Year. Principles of Elementary Education—Education 129b, 10:30 30 periods Methods in Language and Spelling—Education 143, 9:30 30 periods School Hygiene and Sanitation, 4:30 30 periods Arithmetic and Methods—Education 137, 3:30 30 periods Songs and Games—Physical Education 192, 8:30 30 periods Second Year. Principles of Teaching and Studying—Education 17, 12:15 30 periods Methods in Language and Grammar—English 151, 10:30 30 periods Methods in Arithmetic II—Education 138, 9:30 30 periods Public School Music—Music 337 or 332, 8:30 30 periods Agriculture 106, 3:30 30 periods Third Year. Methods and Management—Education 15, 2:30 30 periods Methods in Literature and Reading—Education 144, 10:30 30 periods Methods in Geography—Education 130, 8:30 30 periods Drawing or Industrial Work or Home Economics, 3:30 to 5:30 60 periods Observation 8:30 to 10:30, Midway School 20 periods (If drawing or industrial work is taken in the third year an elective will also be required.) Summer School Professional Certificate—For High School Grades —Minimum Entrance Requirement.—The holder of a Virginia First Grade High School Diploma or the holder of a Virginia First Grade Certificate who presents satisfactory evidence of having completed the equivalent of a standard four-year high school course, shall be granted a Summer School Professional Certificate—For High School Grades, under the terms and conditions hereinafter stated. The certificate and other credentials which entitle the applicant to enter upon and pursue the course of study herein outlined must be presented to and approved by the director of the summer school before the applicant can be registered and admitted to classes. This certificate entitles the holder to teach only the high school branches named in the certificate. General Requirements.—The courses prescribed in any of the branches hereinafter stated for the Summer School Special Certificate—For High School Grades, must embrace no work unless it be of College Grade, requiring minimum recitation periods of sixty minutes each. These courses must be taken in a summer school at a registered college or university and must be completed within a period of three years from the date of beginning. The following "Content Table" gives the number of hours or recitation periods required in each branch, and in addition thereto the applicant must complete a course of thirty hours in Education. [15] CONTENT TABLE. Agriculture, 90 hours. Botany, 60 hours. Chemistry, 150 hours, of which 60 hours must be laboratory work. Drawing, 90 hours. English, 120 hours, including 30 hours in English Grammar, 30 hours in Rhetoric and Composition, and 60 hours in English and American Literature. Domestic Science, 90 hours. French, 90 hours. German, 90 hours. History, 120 hours, including 60 hours in General History, 30 hours in English History, and 30 hours in American History and Civics. Latin, 90 hours, including a review of Cæsar, Cicero and Virgil. Manual Training, 90 hours. Mathematics, 120 hours, including Algebra, Plane and Solid Geometry, and Plane Trigonometry. Music, 90 hours. Physics, 150 hours, of which 60 hours shall be laboratory work. Physical Geography, 60 hours. Spanish, 90 hours. Zoölogy, 60 hours. This certificate shall continue in force for seven years, and may be renewed for a similar period from time to time. N. B.—This course must not be given at any school in Virginia unless it is specially mentioned and advertised in its literature; no supposedly equal course at any other than a designated summer school will be recognized or accepted by the State Board of Education. [16] COURSES OF INSTRUCTION The following abbreviations used in connection with the courses indicate the buildings in which the classes are held: L. B.—Law Building (Minor Hall); C. H.—Cabell Hall; F. G.— Fayerweather Gymnasium; M. H.—Madison Hall; M. L.—Mechanical Laboratory; P. H.— Peabody Hall (Education Building); P. L.— Physical Laboratory (Rouss); O. L.—Organic Laboratory; R.—Rotunda; W. R. L.—West Range Laboratory; C. B.—Chemical Building. The Courses of Instructions are designated as follows: Courses numbered less than 100 may be credited toward the bachelor's degree in the University of Virginia. Courses numbered from 100 to 299 are courses for which college credit is recommended, though not given in the University of Virginia because corresponding work is not offered in this University during the regular session. These courses are, however, accepted by other standard colleges which offer similar work, and in which transfer of credit may be obtained. Courses numbered from 300 to 399 are courses for which degree credit is not recommended. The amount of credit for each course is indicated in connection with that course and is expressed in semester hours. Credit accepted by the University of Virginia is also expressed in session-hours, two semester hours being equivalent to one session-hour. Two hours of laboratory work, as a general rule, are equal to one hour of lecture or recitation. Courses which are credited by the Department of Public Instruction of Virginia toward certificates, will in addition to the numerals, be designated as follows: C—Courses credited toward Collegiate Professional or Collegiate Certificates, entitling the holder to teach high school subjects. E—Courses credited toward Elementary Professional Certificates, entitling the holder to teach in both primary and grammar grades. Note.—In this preliminary announcement the number and title of the courses are given only. A description of the content and a number of additional courses will be given in the complete catalogue. AGRICULTURE. Agriculture 106, 107, or the equivalent should be taken preliminary to or parallel with the more advanced courses, which may be taken in any order. Six pupils are required to form a class in the advanced courses. Agriculture 100. C. E. Laboratory Materials and Problems in Agriculture.—Credit, 2 hours. Agriculture 101. C. E. Soils and Fertilizers.—Credit, 2 hours. Agriculture 102. C. Horticulture.—Credit, 2 hours. Agriculture 104. C. Animal Husbandry.—Credit, 2 hours. Agriculture 106. E. General Agriculture.—Credit, 2 hours. Agriculture 107. E. Nature Study.—Credit, 2 hours. [17] ASTRONOMY. Astronomy 1. The Earth and the Moon.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Astronomy 2. The Sun and Practical Astronomy.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Astronomy 3. The Planets, Comets, Meteors and Stars.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). BIOLOGY. These courses have been so constructed as to meet the needs of teachers who are working in secondary schools, and to enable premedical students to fulfill the medical entrance requirements as prescribed by the American Medical Association. Pre-medical students must take Courses 4, 5 and 6 in order to meet their full entrance requirements. These three courses are equivalent to two terms' work of Biology B1, regular session. Biology 4. C. Botany.—Credit, 4 hours (2 session-hours). For teachers $1.00, for others $5.00. Mr. Kepner and Mr. Whitlock. Biology 5. C. Zoölogy.—Lecture 2:30; Laboratory 3:30 to 5:30; C. H. 12. Credit, 4 hours (2 session-hours). Laboratory fee for teachers $1.00, for others $5.00. Mr. Kepner and Mr. Whitlock. Biology 6. C. Experimental Biology.—11:30; C. H. 12. Laboratory fee $5.00 to those not registered in Biology 4 or 5. Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Mr. Kepner and Mr. Whitlock. Biology 112. C. High School Methods in Biology.—10:30; C. H. 12. Credit, 2 hours. Mr. Kepner. FIELD BOTANY. Field Botany 114. C. E.—Credit, 2 hours. CHEMISTRY. Chemistry 115. C. General Chemistry for High School Teachers.— Credit, 2 hours. Chemistry 116. C. Laboratory Course for High School Teachers. —Credit, 2 hours. Chemistry 7. C. The Principles of General Chemistry.—Chemistry 7 and 8 combined. Credit, 6 hours (3 session-hours). Chemistry 8. C. Laboratory Course.—Fee $10.00. Chemistry 117. C. Household Chemistry.—Credit, 2 hours. Chemistry 9. C. Organic Chemistry.—Credit, 4 hours (2 session-hours). Chemistry 120. Analytical Chemistry.—Credit, 2 hours. COMMERCIAL COURSES. Note.—These courses are not free to any teacher. A fee of $5 for any one course will be charged, or $10 for any two or more courses. Commerce 118. Money and Banking.—Credit, 2 hours. Commerce 119. Political Economy.—Credit, 2 hours. Commerce 305. Bookkeeping.—8:30. Commerce 306. Shorthand. Commerce 307. Typewriting. Commerce 308. Commercial Arithmetic. Commerce 309. Business Law.—Credit, 2 hours. Commerce 310. Accountancy.—10:30. Credit, 2 hours. Commerce 311. Principles and Methods of Commercial Education. Commerce 312. School of Accountancy. [18] DRAWING. Drawing 122. E. Section I, First to Fourth Grade.—Credit, 2 hours. Drawing 123. E. Fifth to Eighth Grades.—Credit, 2 hours. Drawing 124. For High School Teachers.—Credit, 2 hours. Drawing 125. E. Method of Supervision.—Credit, 2 hours. Drawing 127. H. Interior Decoration.—Credit, 2 hours. Drawing—Constructive Design. EDUCATION. Education 10. C. E. Methods in Modern Language Teaching. Credit, 2 hours. Education 12. C. E. Hygiene and Sanitation.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Education 13. C. School Administration.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Education 14. C. Educational Surveys and Tests.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Education 15. C. E. Methods and Management (Third Year Elementary Professional Course.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Education 16. C. E. Educational Psychology.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Education 17. C. E. Principles of Teaching and Studying. Second Year Grammar Grade Professional Course.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Education 19. C. History of Education.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Education 20. C. High School Administration.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Education 21. C. Matter and Method in the High School.—P. H. 4. Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Education 110. E. Nature Study and Home Geography. Third Year Primary Grade.—Credit, 2 hours. Education 111. E. Child Literature and History Stories. Third Year Primary Grades.—Credit, 2 hours. Education 144. E. Methods in Literature and Reading. Third Year Grammar Grade.—Credit, 2 hours. Education 129a. E. Principles of Elementary Education. First Year Primary Grade.—Credit, 2 hours. Education 129b. E. Principles of Elementary Education. First Year Grammar Grade.—Credit, 2 hours. Education 130. E. Methods in Geography. Third Year Grammar Grade.—Credit, 2 hours. Education 131. E. Child Study. Second Year Primary Grade.— Credit, 2 hours. Education 132. E. Methods in Reading 1. First Year Primary Grade.—Credit, 2 hours. Education 133a. E. Methods in Reading 2. Second Year Primary Grade.—Credit, 2 hours. Education 133b. E. The Teaching of Reading 2. Second Year Primary Grade.—Credit, 2 hours. Education 134. E. Methods in Languages and Spelling. Second Year Primary Grade.—P. H. 3. Credit, 2 hours. Education 135. E. Hygiene and Sanitation. Second Year Primary Grade.—Credit, 2 hours. [19] Education 136. E. Methods in History and Civics. First Year Grammar Grade.—Credit, 2 hours. Education 137. E. Grammar Grade Methods in Arithmetic 1. First Year Grammar Grade.—Credit, 2 hours. Education 138. E. Grammar Grade Methods in Arithmetic 2. Second Year Grammar Grade.—Credit, 2 hours. Education 139. E. Primary Grade Methods in Arithmetic 1. First Year Primary Grade.—Credit, 2 hours. Education 140. E. Kindergarten Observation.—Credit, 2 hours. Education 141. E. Handwork for Kindergarten and Primary Grades. Education 142. E. Methods in Language I. First Year Primary Grade.—Credit, 2 hours. Education 143. E. Methods in Language and Spelling. First Year Grammar Grade.—Credit, 2 hours. Education 331. Medical Inspection and First Aid. This course will be conducted by representatives from the State Board of Health, who are specialists in their respective fields, assisted by members of the Summer School Faculty. Vacation School and Demonstration Classes. A very important and helpful feature of the work in elementary education will be a regular vacation school for observation purposes. The city of Charlottesville will conduct a vacation school for work in all the grades, which will be in charge of trained expert teachers. Arrangements have been made for daily observation work, and classes have been scheduled to avoid conflict. The work will be done under the supervision of a critic teacher. Note.—A series of Round Table Conferences in Education will be arranged to meet once or twice a week. Separate conferences for high school teachers, grammar grade teachers and primary teachers will be held. ENGLISH. English 25. C. Rhetoric and Composition, I.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). English 26. C. Type Studies in English Prose and Poetry.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). English 27. C. Survey of English Literature, II.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). English 28. C. History of American Literature.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). English 29. C. English Narrative Poetry and Prose.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). English 30. The English Essay.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). English 31. C. Prose and Poetry of the Victorian Era.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). English 33. C. Contemporary English Drama.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). English 34. C. Shakespeare.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Mr. Sledd. English 35. H. A. Biblical Literature. The Origin, Characteristics, and Influence of the Bible as a Book of Literature.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). English 36. C. Survey of English Literature, III.—Credit, 2 hours (one-session hour). English 145. C. Advanced English Grammar.—Credit, 2 hours. English 146. C. The Teaching of High School Literature.—Credit, 2 hours. [20] English 147. C. Teaching of High School Composition.—Credit, 2 hours. English 148. C. High School Classics.—Credit, 2 hours. English 151. E. Methods in Language and Grammar. Second Year Summer School Professional Course, Grammar Grade.—Credit, 2 hours. English 332. Special Lectures on Literary Subjects.—P. H. 5; 4:30. English 333. Jewish Literature and History. FRENCH. French 155. C. Elementary French.—Credit, 2 hours. French 156. C. Intermediate French.—Credit, 2 hours. French 157. C. French Pronunciation.—Credit, 2 hours. French 158. C. Advanced French.—Credit, 2 hours. French 315. French Conversation. GEOGRAPHY. Geography 159. C. Physical Geography.—Credit, 2 hours. Geography 160. C. Industrial Geography.—Credit, 2 hours. Geography 161. C. Field and Laboratory Work. Geography. Methods in Geography. GERMAN. German 38. C. Methods of Modern Language Teaching.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). German 39. C. German C. Advanced.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). German 163. C. Elementary German A. and B.—Credit, 2 hours. HISTORY. History 40. C. Ancient History.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). History 41. C. The Modern Age (Course I).—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). History 165. C. The Middle Age.—Credit, 2 hours. History 166. C. Modern English History.—Credit, 2 hours. History 167. C. United States History and Civics.—Credit, 2 hours. History 168. C. The Modern Age (Course II).—Credit, 2 hours. Virginia History. Review of United States History. Review of English History. Methods in History and Civics. HOUSEHOLD ARTS. Note.—Each student should bring a white apron made by Butterick pattern 5162. It is recommended that students wishing to specialize in household economy take Hygiene and Chemistry as these courses are planned with special reference to the work in household economy. Teachers applying for a high school grade certificate in cooking or in sewing and the study of textiles must take two courses in each of these subjects. Household Arts 169a. E. C. Study of Foods.—Credit, 2 hours. Household Arts 169b. E. C. Study of Foods.—Credit, 2 hours. Household Arts 170. E. C. Home Management.—Credit, 2 hours. [21] Household Arts 171. E. C. Home Cooking and Table Service.— Credit, 2 hours. Household Arts 172a. E. C. Theory and Practice of Teaching Cooking.—Credit, 2 hours. Household Arts 172b. E. C. Theory and Practice of Teaching Sewing.—Credit, 2 hours. Household Arts 173. E. C. Dietetics.—Credit, 2 hours. Household Arts 174. E. C. Sewing and Study of Textiles, Elementary.—Credit, 2 hours. Household Arts 175. E. C. Sewing and Study of Textiles. Intermediate.—Credit, 2 hours. Household Arts 176. E. C. Sewing and Study of Textiles. Advanced.—Credit, 2 hours. Household Arts 177. E. C. Millinery.—Credit, 1 hour. Household Arts 217. Demonstration Work.—10:30 and 4:30; W. R. L. Miss Minard. LATIN. Latin 46. C. Sallust's Conspiracy of Catiline.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Latin 47. C. Livy's Hannibalic War.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Latin 48. C. Tacitus' Annals.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Latin 178. C. Teachers' High School Training Course.—Credit, 2 hours. Latin 318. C. Beginners' Latin. Latin 319. C. Cæsar. Latin 320. C. Cicero. Latin 321. C. Vergil I-VI. LIBRARY ECONOMY. The courses in Library Economy are designed especially for librarians of small libraries, persons wishing to prepare for library positions, and for teachers. Library Economy 179. C. Cataloguing, Classification, Administration.—Credit, 2 hours. Library Economy 180. C. Reference Work, Bibliography, Government Documents.—Credit, 2 hours. MANUAL AND INDUSTRIAL ARTS. Manual Arts 181. C. Wood-Working for High Schools.—Credit, 2 hours. Manual Arts 182. C. E. Constructive Design. Manual Arts 183. E. Upper Grade Work.—Credit, 2 hours. Manual Arts 184. E. Industrial Manual Training.—Credit, 2 hours. Manual Arts 185a. E. Primary Industrial Art.—Credit, 2 hours. Manual Arts 186. E. Advanced Course for Elementary Grade Teachers.—Credit, 2 hours. Manual Arts 187. C. E. Mechanical Drawing.—Credit, 2 hours. Manual Arts 322. Observation Class. Manual Arts 323. Agricultural Projects. [22] MATHEMATICS. Mathematics 50. C. Advanced Algebra.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Mathematics 51. C. Solid Geometry.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Mathematics 52. C. Plane and Spherical Trigonometry.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Mathematics 53. C. Analytical Geometry.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Mathematics 54. C. Differential Calculus.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Mathematics 55. C. Integral Calculus.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Mathematics 56. C. Coördinate Geometry.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Mathematics 188. C. Plane Geometry.—Credit, 2 hours. Mathematics 189. C. Plane Geometry—Review of High School Teachers. Mathematics 190. C. Solid Geometry. Mathematics 191. C. Differential Equations.—Credit, 2 hours. Mathematics 324. C. Review of High School Algebra. Mathematics 325. Elementary Algebra. Mathematics—Review of Arithmetic. Mathematics—Methods in Primary Arithmetic. Mathematics—Methods in Grammar Grade Arithmetic. MUSIC. Music 232. E. Material and Sight Singing—1A.—Credit, 2 hours. Music 233. E. Study of Tone and Rhythm—1B.—Credit, 2 hours. Music 234. E. Methods and Rote Songs—1C.—Credit, 2 hours. Music 235. E. Rudiments of Music and Melody Writing—1D.— Credit, 2 hours. Music 236. E. Music History and Current Musical Events—1E.— Credit, 2 hours. Music 237. E. Material and Sight Singing—2A.—Credit, 2 hours. Music 238. E. Study of Tone and Rhythm—2B.—Credit, 2 hours. Music 239. E. Methods and Practice Teaching—2C.—Credit, 2 hours. Music 240. E. Melody Writing and Elementary Harmony—2D.— Credit, 2 hours. Music 241. E. C. High and Normal School Music—F.—Credit, 2 hours. Music 242. Vocal Production—C. H. Music 243. Course in Piano Playing—C. H. Music 244. Course in Piano Technique and Interpretation. Music 245. Course in Sight Reading and Ensemble Playing. Music 246. Theoretical Course of Teaching Methods and Pedagogy. Music 247. Course in Practical Church Music. Music 248. Artistic Organ Playing. Music 249. Elementary Violin Playing. Music 250. Intermediate Violin Playing. Music 251. Advanced Violin Playing. Music 252. History and Appreciation of Music. Music 253. Ear-Training and Preparatory Harmony. Music 254. Advanced Harmony. [23] PHILOSOPHY. Philosophy 57. C. Deductive Logic.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Philosophy 58. C. Inductive Logic.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Philosophy 59. C. Logis.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). PHYSICAL EDUCATION. Physical Education 192. E. Grammar Grades.—Credit, 2 hours. Physical Education 193. E. Primary Grades.—Credit, 2 hours. Physical Education 194. E. C. High School.—Credit, 2 hours. Physical Education 195. E. C. Folk and Classic Dancing, Advanced. —Credit, 2 hours. Physical Education 232. Plays and Games on the Lawn. PHYSICS. Physics 60. C. Mechanics and Heat.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Physics 60a. C. Laboratory Course.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Physics 61. C. Sound and Light.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Physics 61a. C. Laboratory Course.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Physics 62. C. Magnetism and Electricity.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Physics 62a. C. Laboratory Course.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Physics 197. C. Mechanics and Heat for High School Teachers.— Credit, 2 hours. Physics 197a. C. Laboratory Course.—Credit, 2 hours. Physics 198. C. Magnetism, Electricity, Sound and Light for High School Teachers.—Credit, 2 hours. PSYCHOLOGY. Psychology 63. C. General Psychology.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Psychology 64. C. Introductory Course in Social Psychology.— Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Education Psychology. SPANISH. Spanish 65. C. Elementary Spanish.—Credit, 2 hours. Spanish 66. C. Conversational Spanish.—Credit, 2 hours. Spanish 67. C. Latin American Social Development.—Credit, 2 hours (one session-hour). Spanish 68. C. Spanish Translation.—Credit, 2 hours. WRITING. Writing 113a. G. P. Muscular Movement Writing. Section I. Locker Method.—Credit, 2 hours. Writing 113b. P. B. Muscular Movement Writing. Section II. Locker Method.—Credit, 2 hours. Writing 113c. G. P. Muscular Movement Writing. Section III. Palmer Method.—Credit, 2 hours. Writing 113d. G. P. Muscular Movement Writing. Section IV. Locker Method.—Credit, 2 hours.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Boarding Houses Below are given some of the names and addresses of persons who will take students to board during the Summer School. The Summer School is in no way responsible for any private boarding house, but publishes a list of such houses solely for the convenience of students. We shall be glad to assist any teacher in procuring satisfactory accommodations. Write to Secretary Summer School, Box 149, University, Virginia. Ladies Men Room and board 2 in room Room and board 4 in room Board alone Room only 2 or 3 in room Rooms only Mrs. Lucy Page Booker University, Va. 15 2.50 5.00 Miss Easten Duval Fry's Spring Road 8 2.50 Miss Virginia Bowcock University Terrace 40 20 6.50 6.00 5.25 Mrs. L. J. Carter 900 W. Main St. 20 10 6.50 5.50 5.00 Misses Cocke University, Va. 25 2.50 5.00 Mrs. Sally Hamilton Chancellor St. 20 2-2.50 3.00 Mrs. F. C. Hamilton Fry's Spring Road 20 or 20 7.00 1.50 Mrs. M. G. Hart Park Place 12 7.50 7.00 Mrs. J. L. Hines 14th St. 25 or 25 5.50 4.50 1.25 1.50 Mrs. Margaret H. Kable Jefferson Park Ave. 4 or 4 8.00 6.00 3.00 Mrs. W. W. Kelley University, Va. 50 20 2.00 3.00 Mrs. S. D. Kline 228-14th St. 12 or 12 1-1.50 1-1.50 Mrs. M. L. McPeak Madison Lane 50 or 50 7.00 6.50 6.00 Mrs. Nat Martin 112-14th St. 20 or 20 Mrs. E. M. Page University Ave. Mrs. Cora Pilkington Rugby Road 50 or 50 Mrs. J. E. Porter University Tea Room 20 14 7.00 2.50 Mrs. C. W. Richardson Delta Tau Delta 15 2-3.50 Mrs. R. L. Rodes 116-14th St. 50 or 50 5.50 5.25 4.50 1.50 Mrs. W. W. Sheppe 1102 University Ave 5 2.50 Mrs. R. C. S. Seiberg 1106 Main St. 40 or 40 5.50 Miss Lelia Smith Rugby Road 40 20 6.00 2.00 2.50 Mrs. J. E. B. Stuart Ellie Wood Ave. 17 2.00 University Commons 250 250 4.50 Mrs. J. D. Via. 503 W. Main 20 6.00 5.00 Mrs. J. H. Windsor 200-14th St. 20 or 10 6.50 6.00 5.00 Mrs. Va. T. Yager 216-14th St. 20</field>
   </doc>
</add>