<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Royall Tyler</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Royall Tyler</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">royall tyler</field>
      <field name="author_text">Royall Tyler</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1970's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/modern_english/uvaGenText/tei/TylSoto.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240357</field>
      <field name="date_text">1978</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:476440</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Komachi on the Gravepost (Sotoba Komachi: a fourth-category play</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="title_display">Komachi on the Gravepost (Sotoba Komachi: a fourth-category play</field>
      <field name="title_facet">komachi on the gravepost sotoba komachi a fourth category play</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">komachi on the gravepost sotoba komachi a fourth category play</field>
      <field name="title_text">Komachi on the Gravepost (Sotoba Komachi: a fourth-category play</field>
      <field name="year_display">1978</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1978</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1978</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:476440&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:476440&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Royall Tyler&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;royall tyler&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Komachi on the Gravepost (Sotoba Komachi: a fourth-category play&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;komachi on the gravepost sotoba komachi a fourth category play&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1978&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1978&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="contributor" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Royall Tyler&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Komachi on the Gravepost (Sotoba Komachi: a fourth-category play)&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="edition"&gt;1st Edition&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1978&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Ithaca, New York&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Cornell China-Japan Program&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1978&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="callNo"&gt;Print copy consulted: UVa Library call number PL 782 .E5 P55 v.2&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;rj&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;sa&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;pp. 105-116&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Copyright 1978 Royall Tyler. From Granny Mountains: A Second</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Cycle of Noh Plays (English translation), Cornell East Asia</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Series no. 18, 188 pp., 0-939657-18-X, $12 paper. East Asia Program,</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Cornell University, 140 Uris Hall, Ithaca, NY 14853-7601 (ph.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">607-255-6222; fax: 607-255-1388, kks3@cornell.edu).&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;CAUTION: Except for brief quotations in a review, no part of this</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">text may be reproduced or utilized in any form or by any means,</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">electronic or mechanical, including photocopying and recording, or by</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">any information storage or retrieval system, without permission in</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">writing from the author. Please address inquiries to Royall Tyler in</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">care of East Asia Program, Cornell University, 140 Uris Hall, Ithaca, NY</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">14853-7601.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Sotoba Komachi&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1997&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1997 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 33 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Copyright 1978 Royall Tyler. Except for brief quotations in a review, no part of this</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">text may be reproduced or utilized in any form or by any means,</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">electronic or mechanical, including photocopying and recording, or by</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">any information storage or retrieval system, without permission in</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">writing from the author. Please address inquiries to Royall Tyler in</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">care of East Asia Program, Cornell University, 140 Uris Hall, Ithaca, NY</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">14853-7601.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">KOMACHI ON THE GRAVEPOST (Sotoba Komachi: a fourth-category play) Komachi on the Gravepost is a play of such astonishing contrasts that one can feel hard put to make of them a whole. Komachi is here, as in Komachi at Gateway Temple, a hundred-year-old crone, but she still debates brilliantly with two monks from the Shingon center of Mount K?ya. Hardly has she triumphed, however, and confessed her name, when she is savagely possessed by the spirit of a former suitor who re-enacts, through her body, his fruitless courtship of her. At last the spirit leaves Komachi and she vows to enter the path of enlightenment (which, in the first half of the play, she seemed to have traveled to the end) by accumulating such countless little acts of devotion as are mentioned in the Lotus Sutra. This sutra says that even children who make sand towers (mud pies) in the name of the Buddha accumulate by this act incalculable merit. Thus, at the very end of Komachi on the Gravepost there is a hint of the innocence that pervades Komachi at Gateway Temple. Perhaps the whole play suggests that knowledge is nothing without love, and that humility is greater than pride. Perhaps when Komachi reminds the monks that 'Back links it is that lift one high' (for 'back link' and 'right links,' see Glossary), she is saying more than even she realizes at the time. Komachi's suitor is Shii no Sh?sh?, also known as Fukakusa no Sh?sh?, the 'Captain from Deepgrass.' According to legend, Komachi promised Sh?sh? she would yield to him if he would appear before her house each night for a hundred nights. He was to record his visit by cutting a notch on the shaft-rest there, the wooden support for the shafts of a carriage. Sh?sh? came faithfully, night after night; he even missed Toyo no Akari, the Harvest Vigil Festival that no courtier would normally dream of missing. But on the ninety-ninth night, one night short, he died. One is reminded on the imperfect magic rock bridge alluded to in The Boat Bridge, and also of the old saw, 'It's love that makes the world go round.' For not only has Sh?sh? kept Komachi bound to the wheel of birth-and-death, but it is desire's endless pursuit of ever elusive perfection that keeps the wheel turning. (In Granny Mountains, Granny Mountains herself is the desire and the turning wheel.) The wheel of Dharma is whole, but for incarnate beings it appears cut by a gap that can be bridged only by love, not by the flesh. The gravepost which is at issue in Komachi's triumphant debate is a sotoba, in Sanskrit st?pa. A st?pa is usually a mound consecrated to the Buddha, so that the mud pies mentioned above are a form of stupa. What Komachi sits on, though, is not a mound but a plank. A Shingon grave monument of this kind displays the symbolic shapes of the five elements or 'five wheels' which are the constituents of matter. Zeami attributes Komachi on the Graveposts to his father Kannami, although he says that the present version is his own condensation of what had been a very long n?.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Sotoba Komachi SHIDAI Sidemand and Sideman's Second enter. They stand facing each other down front. After opening verse, Sideman faces front. SHIDAI on-w Sideman and Side Second Shallow these hills yet conceal one shallow these hills yet conceal one very deep the heart! NANORI off-sp Sideman I am a monk from Mount Koya. I am just now on my way up to Miyako. SASHI off-w The Buddha of the past, now, is long gone; the Future Buddha comes not yet into the world. Sideman and Side Second face to face again Born are we into dream time between. What then shall we take for the Real? Human bodies, seldom won, are ours; the Tathagata's own Buddha-Teaching, hard to find, we've found, and this it is shall be seed of awakening vows the heart with purpose single black robes we've put on: AGEUTA on-w but know the self that's before birth but know the self that's before birth and parents there are none to cherish, and with no parents, no child either to detain the heart. The ten thousand leagues we go Sideman takes a few steps to show travel, returning to his place by second 'home.' He then faces front. are never long; on moors we lie and lodge in mountains, yes, these for us are the true home yes, these for us are the true home. TSUKI-ZERIFU off-sp Sideman Hurrying along that way, we've come to Abeno in the land of Tsu. Sideman and Sideman's Second retire to Sideman's spot. Stagehand places a stool at center, to serve as the gravepost. SHU-NO-SHIDAI Doer enters, wearing the r?jo, or Old Woman, mask. She is leaning on a staff and wears a broad, conical hat called kasa. She stops once on bridgeway as though to rest, then comes as far as main spot, where she faces back of stage. SHIDAI on-w Doer Pondweed adrift am I yet no stream stirs pondweed adrift am I yet no stream stirs to woo me: wherefore I grieve. SASHI off-w turning front Alas! In the old days my pride waxed very great. My hair, a black kingfisher-sheened, swayed supple, like willow fronds trailing down spring winds. My warbler tongue's sweet trill was lovelier far than fine bush clover flowers gorged with dew, at each whisper poised to drop; now even fishwives shrink from me, all see my shame. Joyless moons and suns have piled on me till I've turned hag, one hundred years old. SAGEUTA on-w In Miyako I fear men's eyes lest 'It's she!' they safe at nightfall AGEUTA on-w with the moon I sally forth with the moon I sally forth past Cloudloft the Hundredfold! The sentinel on Inmost Peak himself would never halt one so pitiful tree-hid, alas! She turns toward side, gazes into distance. the Lovers' Tomb of Toba, Autumn Hill, the moon's own Katsura river boats shooting shallows, and the rowers, who might they be, and the rowers, who might they be? TSUKI-ZERIFU off-sp I'm so exhausted I think I'll sit here on this rotten timber and rest. She takes her hat in her hand and sits on the stool. Sideman and Sideman's Second stand up. MONDO off-sp Sideman Oho, the sun's gone down, we'd better hurry. Look! The thing this beggar here is sitting on is a st?pa gravepost, there's no doubt about it. I'll enlighten her and get her to move. Side Second Right you are. Sideman's Second goes to mark post, passing behind Doer, thus leaving Sideman at Sideman's spot. MONDO off-sp Sideman You there! You beggar! Isn't what you're sitting on a st?pa gravepost, the very image of the Buddha-body, to which be reverence? Get off it and go rest somewhere else. Doer The very image of the Buddha-body, you say, most worthy of reverence. . . But I see no inscription to suggest that, no graven shapes. To me, it looks like just a rotten timber. KAKEAI off-w* Sideman s 'Dead and dry the tree may be deep in the hills, yet once in bloom a cherry's not to be hid'— sp a timber, then, graven as the Buddha-body, how should it make no impression? Doer s I too am a lowly buried timber, but if at heart I've still blossoms, why should they not do for offerings? Come, what makes you say it's the Buddha-body? Side Second Why, a gravepost, st?pa that it is, is Kong?satta briefly manifest, working his Samaya Shapes, his Vow-in-Action. Doer sp The shapes he works, what are they? Sideman s Earth, water, fire, air, and space. Doer The Five Great Ones, the Five Wheels, make man's own body; how is it you see a difference? Side Second Identical the shapes, but heart and virtue differ. Doer sp Then the gravepost st?pa's virtue? Sideman s 'Once spy a st?pa and forever leave the Three Evil Ways.' Doer 'One thought arouses the True Wisdom Mind.' There too, how am I the lesser? Side Second If True Wisdom Mind is yours, why don't you hate the sorry world? Doer As if it were one's mere appearance that might hate the world! No, it's the heart! Sideman No heart have you, and therefore knew not the Buddha-body. Doer sp I knew it, and therefore approached this gravepost. Side Second s Then why did you sit down and pay no homage? Doer Here it's lying, this gravepost—what's wrong with my resting too? Sideman It clashes with all right links. Doer sp Back links it is that lift one high. Side Second s Daiba's evil, Doer mercy of Kannon, Sideman Handoku's dullness, Doer Monju's wisdom, Side Second what's called Evil Doer is Good itself; Sideman what's called Torments, Doer Perfect Wisdom, Side Second and Perfect Wisdom's Doer no tree planted: Sideman the Clear Mirror Doer stands on no stand. AGEUTA on-w Chorus Yes, when 'Never has one thing been,' Buddha and Beings coincide. Sideman's Second goes back to sit at Sideman's spot. Ever a device to save dull, average man, it has been the thrust of the deep Vows; therefore, 'Back links it is that lift one high': when thus kindly she reminds them, Doer faces Sideman and assumes a commanding presence. 'Truly, an awakened outcaste!' they cry, the monks, Sideman, as though quelled, retreats two or three steps, goes down on one knee and reverently salutes Doer. Doer then turns front again. touching head to earth and doing homage thrice. But then, Doer Now my strength gathers, I give you this jesting song: SHIMO-NO-EI off-w My crime in Paradise most grave post it without quite free of every blame. Doer suddenly stands, turns her back on Sideman, and moves several steps toward main spot. UTA on-w Chorus You tiresome monks and your sermons! You tiresome monks and your sermons! * off-sp Sideman Come then! Who are you? Please, say your name! Doer turning to Sideman I'm ashamed; and yet I'll tell you my name. She comes back to center and sits facing front. NANORI-GURI off-w I am what is left of Ono no Komachi, daughter of Ono no Yoshizane, the governor of Dewa. SASHI off-w Sideman and Side Second Oh the pity! Komachi was years past a peerless beauty: blossom, her face shone, moon-laurel brows gleamed delicate, white-powdered was she ever; gauze and damask robes o'erflowed her Laurel Hall. Doer Native songs I made, and Chinese verse; Chorus 'Drink deep' urged my cup, from Heaven's Stream moon on my sleeve lay light, a lovely sight indeed.on And when did change AGEUTA on-w crown me with frosty weeds, sidelocks once fair clamp to skin in inky runs, moth brows once lilting lose hue of far hills? SAGEUTA on-w My hundred years lack wan these hairs hankerings do I no sooner dawn breaks than shame at my looks covers me. As she speaks these last words, Doer hides her face with hat, then stands and goes to main spot. RONGI on-w Chorus In the pouch hung round your neck, what is it you keep? Doer Though this day may be my last, against tomorrow's hunger it's parched beans and millet, mixed, I carry in my pouch. Chorus And in the bag you've slung behind? Doer Stained, filthy clothes. Chorus And in the basket on your arm? Doer Arrowheads white and black. Now she glances at the hat she holds. Below, she lowers her head as though to hide, and then at mention of sleeves, glances at her sleeves. Chorus Ragged cloak, Doer ragged hat, Chorus do little to hide the face; Doer and what of frost, snow, rain, and dew? Chorus Tears at least I'd wipe from sight but have no sleeves! She thrusts the hat before her, held upside down like a bowl, and goes toward mark post. Now I wander roads, beg from passersby; and when refused, She glares down into hat. rage and crazed wits seize me. My voice changes, ghastly. . . She drops her staff, thrusts hat out again, and presses toward Sideman. MONDO off Doer str Come on you, gimme something, you monk, come on! Sideman sp What's this? Doer Got to be going to Komachi's place. Come on! Sideman You're Komachi! What is this nonsense you're talking? Doer faces front. Below, at 'billets-doux,' glances hither and yon; at 'shower,' steps backwards; at 'reward,' lowers head as though containing agitation. Doer Oh no, Komachi, she's too much the lover: billets-doux here, proposals there str shower as sudden summer rains from skies empty comfort even gives she none, not one answer. w Now, just reward, she's touched one hundred years. Oh how I love her, how I love her! Sideman sp 'How I love her,' you say; then who has possessed you? Doer turning to Sideman Among the throng whose hearts were set on Komachi, turning front w specially captain Fourth Rank of Deepgrass, Shii no Sh?sh?'s UTA on-w Chorus bitterness thus manifold advancing toward Front has come full round: I'm bound for her shaft rest. Doer gazes toward bridgeway, the direction of the west; at 'moon's along,' turns front again; at 'gate guards,' goes to main spot, then withdraws to stagehand spot. AGEUTA on-w What time of day? Nightfall What time of day? Nightfall; the moon's by me down the road gate watchmen stand but they'll not stop me! Come, I'm off! MONO-GI-ASHIRAI Doer slips the outer garment, the mizugoromo, from her shoulders, puts on an eboshi court hat, and picks up a fan. She then comes out to main spot; glances at skirts and stamps beat; at 'wind-crease,' points to hat with fan; then moves toward mark post, drapes left sleeve over head and half hides face with fan; then at 'down my road,' turns left up to drums; at 'nights of rain,' faces front and gazes up into sky; at 'eaves,' comes down front, sweeps gaze around over head; at 'I go and come,' walks a few steps then returns to place; at 'one night,' stands facing front and counts on fingers of left hand; at 'Vigil,' turns right up to drums, then immediately comes down front; at 'notch,' stamps several beats; at 'ninety-ninth,' holds left hand out, gazes at little finger which has not yet counted a night. UTA on-w Doer Spotless white skirts I lift high spotless white skirts I lift high, Chorus wind-crease the tall court hat, hunting cloak sleeves pull about me, shrink from prying eyes along the way I go by moon, go in blackness, nights of rain, storm nights, leaf showers, deep the snow, * off-w Doer the eaves' bright drops drip quick drip quick Chorus I go and come and back again one night, two nights, three nights and four, seven, eight nights, nine nights attend the Harvest Vigil Feast I cannot, all alone cock-crow I never miss, each dawn notch the shaft-rest, bent on going the full hundred nights, and this the ninety-ninth— Doer steps backwards to center. Oh the pain! My eyes dim! Doer presses fan to breast, drops to one knee, then sits; at 'he of Deepgrass,' lowers head, absorbed. My chest bursts! cried he in agony and one night short died, he of Deepgrass, the Captain. His hate it is possesses me She briskly stands and, turning to Side man with a fierce air, stamps beat. and so turns me mad! Now she becomes perfectly calm and peaceful. At 'sand,' she holds out fan as though beckoning; at 'burnish,' turns right up to main spot, then holding fan like an offering, advances toward front; at 'start' folds fan and joins palms; then turns to side and remains motionless. KIRI on-w But for all that, my strong hope for life to come is very real: sand I'll pile into st?pas, burnish me skin of purest gold and, offering the Buddha flowers, set out on the road to awakening set out on the road to awakening.</field>
   </doc>
</add>