<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">William Brand</field>
      <field name="author_facet">William Brand</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">william brand</field>
      <field name="author_text">William Brand</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy_mss/uvaBook/tei/brand_letters/A9647.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">University of Virginia Civil War Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">University of Virginia Civil War Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">William Brand to Kate Armentrout, September 4, 1862</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:502809</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">William Brand to Kate Armentrout, September 4, 1862</field>
      <field name="note_display">Source copy consulted: William Brand Papers, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="note_display"/>
      <field name="note_text">Source copy consulted: William Brand Papers, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="note_text"/>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="heading_text">Miss Kate Armentrout Greenville Augusta County Va.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">September 4th /62 Camp Stonewall My dear friend,</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I recieved your letter yesterday, &amp; as we are laying still this morning I will try and write a few lines in answer. I know not when this will reach you as it is reported that a large Cavalry force has gone up the Valley in our rear. The Enimy have a large Cavalry force in the Valley &amp; our Cavalry being afraid of them buts us to a grate deal of trouble. We had to march last night untill twelve oclock through mud &amp; rain to meet an antisapated raid on Winchester. We are camped this morning near Winchester &amp; evry thing seems perfectly quiet. It will hardly remain so untill night.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I suppose you are aware before this of the fate of your Cousin R. our comp. is called to mourn the loss of one of our bravest youths who like a young flower was cut down in early manhood. We greatly mis him. All his comrads sympathise with his grief stricken parent &amp; relatives. I have been under the fire of the enimy twist since I wrote at Sheperdstown &amp; Smithfiel d . But by the mercies of a great &amp; good God I have been spared yet a while thare has been no regular engagement since I come down, only heavy skirmishing. We are ready for a fight almost evry day, as both armies are getting near each other. But I will pray &amp; live in hopes thare will be no more hard fighting in the Valley.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I am glad to hear that your Cousin L. is getting well but sorry to hear that your health is still declining hope ear this reaches you you may be enjoying the best of health. Thare has been a great many deaths in old Augusta since I left. I believe a desease cuts of as many as the sword. I recieved a letter from sister some time ago she said the Yanks ware in thirty miles of Uncles &amp; was fearfull thay ware going to make a raid through thare neighborhood. She wanted to know wether she ought to go a refugeeing or gird on the armer &amp; go forth to meet the foe. I give her the advise I would to all women stay at home. I got a letter yesterday from my friend John Sam he says if I ware at home now I could not but help having the blues as evry thing is so dull. I think differently I am sure thare is one whose company I could always enjoy let times be as thay please. Dear Kate you must have me to have been musing or my mind wandering on some imagina ry reflections. I was writing with two of three by my side &amp; intended sending other finishing, but never thought of it untill I had sealed it, but never thought you would be so strict as to follow my example. This is a beautiful day but our camp is not plesant we have no shades to keep the rays of the burning sun off our heads.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Did not know that it was Sunday untill I was informed this morning. We have been mooving nearly evry day last week &amp; the days slipt by unnumber ed by me. I hope before the cold blasts of winter sets in we may all be whare we can enjoy these blest of all days at home. My health is very good. I have no reasonable right at presant to complain of any thing. My kindest regards to all enquiring friends excuse this spoiled paper it got wet in my knapsack &amp; thare is none to be got hear . Your brother is enjoying fine health also the Company. I have not hurd from eather of Bro s since I came down. Remember me as one that loves you dearly &amp; wishes you nothing but pure happiness.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Write soon to your W.</field>
      <field name="heading_text">Envelope</field>
      <field name="title_display">William Brand to Kate Armentrout, September 4, 1862</field>
      <field name="title_facet">William Brand to Kate Armentrout, September 4, 1862</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">william brand to kate armentrout september 4 1862</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">William Brand to Kate Armentrout, September 4, 1862</field>
      <field name="year_display">1862-09-04</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1862</field>
   </doc>
</add>
