<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Case, Adelaide E.</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Case, Adelaide E.</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">case adelaide e</field>
      <field name="author_text">Case, Adelaide E.</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy_mss/uvaBook/tei/adelaide_case_letters/NA62e18.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, May 18, 1862</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:501539</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, May 18, 1862</field>
      <field name="note_display">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection, Department of Special Collections, Alderman Library, UVa.</field>
      <field name="note_display"/>
      <field name="note_text">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection, Department of Special Collections, Alderman Library, UVa.</field>
      <field name="note_text"/>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="heading_text">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, May 18, 1862</field>
      <field name="fulltext">East Claridon , May 18th '62. My darling Charlie,</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Few, very few are the days which I have spent equal to this. I am not happy to day, darling, far from it in fact. I am not well. A violent headache has clinnig to me all day, which added to the oppressiveness of the atmosphere makes me feel miserable.— Oh! what a refreshing breeze has just swept by — and then almost two weeks have passed since I recieved the letter that you wrote last. Dearest why do you not write ofterer would that you know how much happiness your darling letters brought; and how unhappy I feel when so long a time passes without recieving one. Do you hear that music Charlie? Grand isn't it? It is down stairs in the parlor. Who is it do you ask? Libbie Armstrong one of my scholars. (Did I mention that two families live in this house.) She has just played and sang, "Red, White, and Blue". I imagine I can see Charlie, my best and truest friend bearing that glorious flag on to liberty. Go on dear one , the prayers and blessings of Addie attend thee. Listen to those sweet strains another piece she is performing now, How quickly will music draw the heart to its gentle accents. What language is in music. Do you see the great tears which almost throws these lives into obscurity. It is not sorrow that brings them now, but it is the influence of that gentle music. Leibbie is not a good player neither is she a good singer but I am just far enough away to have it sound more like the chanting of angels than like the effect of a human being's voice and hands. I promised in my last to give you my experience in “boarding round” the second night. In my “experience” that I gave you last, I think in fact, I know I gave you the wrong date. It was the 1st and I gave you the 14th did I not? All for the sake of contrast here goes,</field>
      <field name="fulltext">May 14, A beautiful day this has been, pleasant both in and out of the schoolroom. My little “summer protoges”. (I know not what else to call them) have been very good. I can see that my school is dayly impro -ving. What implicit confidence they place in my Heavenly Father. sustain me and guide me in this duty, help me to lead them in the paths of right, All unexpecteded I came to mother Green's this evening. I came with Charlie Green, (one of my scholars) and found his mother absent; She had gone to the “Soldiers Aid,” After waiting perhaps fifteen minutes she came. A small lady she is with an intellectual and pleasant countinance. She did not exhibit any surprise upon seeing me but gave me a kind and pleasant welcome. How I thanked her for that she then invited me into the parlor and soon left me, I there had an opportunity of drawing contrasts, the room was not richly but tastefully furnished, every thing betakened an air of neatnesss. Choice books and pamphlets lay on a center table, looking so inviting and a vase of splendid flowers stood there by them lending an air of sweetness not often I took up a pamphlet documents hundred days in Missourian court busiest myself till commenced to tea , What a neat family group Husband, wife and child, constituted the family circle. After tea we conversed on various topics such as “war” , till — “conscience!” how fast time flew — half past ten, While conversing on the subject of war I learned that she had a brother who was in the engagements of Donilson and Pittsburgh Landing. She then read a portion of one of his letters written after viewing the battle field. He says, “I went out this morning to survey the battle ground of yesterday, Men died and dying lay there on that fearful field. A fearful sight it was sister but our hearts have become so callous that the sight of a dead man has little or no effect.” Heartless, wretch! I could have exclaimed, but I I forbore . I wonder if all soldiers feel so, I hope not but I must retire for it is late, what a pleasant room this is so cozy and nice and how tempting that bed does look?</field>
      <field name="fulltext">There Charlie, you have my second nights' experience. You can imagine which of the two which I have given you pleased me the most, but that racking pain in my head is so tedious that I will soon close. I wish you would write oftener darling, it is such hard work to wait in anxious expectation and then be disappointed.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">You must excuse my pencil marks for I had not a decent pen to write with and I have written in a hurry too. will not withhold her blessing from the</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Please write soon D, Addie . Evening 1 Charlie I wish you could seem us in our room Dora, Alma Leak Libbie and Ellen Armstrong and I, myself. we all occupy one room. Dora sends love. Al, says tell him, “she is happy,” she dont know who I am writing to I guess. Oh what comments upon my writing Dora recieved a letter from one of her army friends last eve. and she she seems quite happy. How I wish I could get one from Charlie, you Good night, my dear Charlie,</field>
      <field name="heading_text">Notes</field>
      <field name="fulltext">1 The postscript is written in the top margin of page 1.</field>
      <field name="title_display">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, May 18th 1862</field>
      <field name="title_facet">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, May 18th 1862</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">letter from adelaide e case to charles n tenney may 18 1862</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, May 18th 1862</field>
      <field name="year_display">1862-05-18</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1862</field>
   </doc>
</add>
