<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Case, Adelaide E.</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Case, Adelaide E.</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">case adelaide e</field>
      <field name="author_text">Case, Adelaide E.</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy_mss/uvaBook/tei/adelaide_case_letters/NA62e05.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, May 5, 1862</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:501536</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, May 5, 1862</field>
      <field name="note_display">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection, Department of Special Collections, Alderman Library, UVa.</field>
      <field name="note_display"/>
      <field name="note_text">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection, Department of Special Collections, Alderman Library, UVa.</field>
      <field name="note_text"/>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="heading_text">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, May 5, 1862</field>
      <field name="fulltext">East Claridon May 5th, 1962</field>
      <field name="fulltext">My darling Charlie .</field>
      <field name="fulltext">My "first day" in teaching has passed and here am I in my room at Mrs. Leslie's seated as quietly as you please giving my "soldier boy" the "perticelars" What a splendid landscape! I presume that even more beautiful are the scenes which you have witnessed within a year than are those on the banks of the little "Cuyahoga" but without any exceptions it is the lovliest place that I ever was in Oh! Charlie you must come home and draw a sketch of this romantic little place. Just as if I did not want you to come to see me. As I went to my "home" this morning. half a dozen little faces - although quite early - peeped out to get a sight of the new "school ma'am." What queer specimens of human nature! I could hard -ly keep back the laugh that made my side ache. (Bless me what language!) to hold [unclear] in. Some little fit of mischiviousness would seize hold of [unclear] one of them and they would turn to perform the act when lo! my eye would chance some how, to be looking right that way when oh! what a penitent reverential look the little fellow would cast at me . guess I couldn't give him a reprimand! Is not a school room the place to study human nature! I have some ladies as old as myself attending school. one Lillie Armstrong lives in the same house with Mrs Leslie . I have a class in algebra. I am real glad that my scholars are so far advanced for they may learn me something. Dora sits here by me. she has just recd a letter from one of her friends Miss Anna Williams . Why could not I receive a letter from Charlie. By the way darling three weeks [unclear] ago next friday was the last "happy day" that I have had. for you know that I am not truly happy only while hearing from you I can not censure you for not writing oftener for I know how the "blockade" interferes with my happiness. I have been teasing Dora to write to you but she is afraid it will not be acceptable. Oh: Charlie write Laura real often wont you my darling? She will be so lonesome now as Addie is not with her to drive off the blues. Charlie do you hear that noise? The frogs over in yonder millpond are having a regu -lar jubilee. I guess they dont know what fearful state our country is in. Oh: any thing but war. When men fight to quell a rebellion or to cease some awful wrong it is just but when they fight as some of the rebels seem to [unclear] only to kill it is horrible. What a strain of thoughts those disagreeable frogs have led me into. I will try to drive it away. I do not know of any news that has transpired in Mecca but that Jim Beebe has moved out of town strange to say he does not seem to be missed.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">But darling it is getting late and I must close or they will accuse me of being out "sparking." Sister used to say this was the next thing to it. But good night dearest. May heaven guard thee for Addie Please write soon direct East Claridon Geauga Co. Ohio</field>
      <field name="title_display">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, May 5th, 1862</field>
      <field name="title_facet">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, May 5th, 1862</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">letter from adelaide e case to charles n tenney may 5 1862</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, May 5th, 1862</field>
      <field name="year_display">1862-05-05</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1862</field>
   </doc>
</add>
