<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Chas. H. Cocke</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Chas. H. Cocke</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">chas h cocke</field>
      <field name="author_text">Chas. H. Cocke</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy_mss/uvaBook/tei/misc/CocLett.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">Letter from Chas. H. Cocke to M. Louise Cocke, Nov. 3, 1895 [a machine-readable transcription]</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:501806</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Letter from Chas. H. Cocke to M. Louise Cocke, Nov. 3, 1895 [a machine-readable transcription]</field>
      <field name="note_display"/>
      <field name="note_text"/>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="heading_text">Columbus Miss. 3 Nov 1895</field>
      <field name="fulltext">My dear Louise:</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I am very much obliged for your kind letter. The University fire was a great shock to me. It haunted me night &amp; day at first. I felt &amp; feel as though a temple had been profaned. No loyal alumnus can fail to feel a personal loss. If the alumni's ability equaled their inclinations, I feel sure the work of restoration would be but a matter of time, and that the shortest necessary. The limitations of poverty in such crises are most sorely felt. What a pleasure it would be to be able to give a million straight down at once to restore and re-equip the buildings, in such order and style as the authorities might deem best! As it is, while my heart was full and my purse empty, I had to force back the words that rushed forward for expression of my sympathy &amp; sorrow and content myself with sending Dr. Thornton a meagre declaration of my willingness to do anything in the power of an impecunious alumnus! I knew he would be deluged with telegrams &amp; letters, so I was brief.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Philip recd. a letter today from Bowdoin. He speaks of coming to Miss. on a hunt with some friend. Of course we will nab him if he passes this way. I am sorry you have no definite plans for Atlanta. We had hoped you would surely come and give us a few weeks. Cannot you still do this? It would give us great pleasure, although you would have a very quiet time. "Society" is unusually tame in Columbus this autumn, but we would enjoy you all the more for having you all to ourselves.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Our love to all. Write me or send me papers with plans of restoration when published. I shall be deeply interested in it all.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I am glad you made your mother take a holiday and delighted to hear of the improvement in her health. I have no doubt Fontaine will be delighted to spend his xmas holiday at the University, or with the boys if they go to Lower Bremo. Can you pack him away without inconvenience? The EHS has 98 students. .... Bowdoin met Miss Bell in Atlanta, so he writes. Phil has gone tonight to call on her, but he is very faithful to his N.O. girl. Write whenever you can. Present me cordially to Dr. Thornton. He must have his hands fuller than ever.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Very affectionately yours, Chas H Cocke</field>
      <field name="title_display">Letter from Chas. H. Cocke to M. Louise Cocke, Nov. 3, 1895.</field>
      <field name="title_facet">Letter from Chas. H. Cocke to M. Louise Cocke, Nov. 3, 1895.</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">letter from chas h cocke to m louise cocke nov 3 1895 a machine readable transcription</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">Letter from Chas. H. Cocke to M. Louise Cocke, Nov. 3, 1895.</field>
      <field name="year_display">1895</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1895</field>
   </doc>
</add>