<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Lydia Maria Child</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Lydia Maria Child</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">lydia maria child</field>
      <field name="author_text">Lydia Maria Child</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy_mss/uvaBook/tei/misc/ChiSpir.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">Letter to Mr. Higginson, 1859 July 4</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:501805</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Letter to Mr. Higginson, 1859 July 4</field>
      <field name="note_display">Additional handwriting across the top of the manuscript's first page appears to be a notation by a dealer or perhaps by Barrett: "r 91" "25.00/62" "Char[]"</field>
      <field name="note_text">Additional handwriting across the top of the manuscript's first page appears to be a notation by a dealer or perhaps by Barrett: "r 91" "25.00/62" "Char[]"</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Wayland, July 4'th, 1859. Dear Mr. Higginson,</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I am sorry I wrote to you about feeling lonely; for from what I hear, I judge that it troubled your kind heart. Now I beg leave to inform you that cheerfulness is my normal condition. I am too busy doing all sorts of things, to find much time to be lonely. Then my passion for cultivating flowers is so intense, and my interest in the habits of every little bird and beast is so amusing, that I seldom lack company.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I happened to be unusually desponding this Spring, because it brought round the anniversary of my friend Ellis Gray Loring's sudden departure; a loss greater to me, in every way, than any one but myself can understand. Another link of friendship had also been rudely shattered, about the time I wrote to you; and so it happened that I wrote disconsolately; a thing I very rarely do. As a general thing, I believe I am thought to have an unseemly degree of gayety, considering my venerable years.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Concerning my withdrawal from society, it had not been a matter of choice , my dear friend. I am by nature the most social of the social. But circumstances sometimes govern the strongest will . If I were chatting with you, I could explain in a few minutes. As it is, you must take my word for it, that I am social, and love my kind; and that I trust the way will open for me to indulge my inclinations, without neglect- -ing my duties. I am strong of heart, and feel as if God had some work yet for me to do in the world.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">My principal object in writing to you, at this time, is to remind you that you promised to send me your other pamphlet about Spiritualism. If I knew where to buy it, or by what name to ask for it, I would not trouble you. It is a subject that interests me extremely.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Mr. Garrison spent Sunday here a fortnight ago. How true and genial he is! But he is all reformer. In the Art-Temple, where I worship, he is a stranger.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Do you know Mrs. Darrah, the artist? She is a very charming person; thoroughly Anti Slavery, also. She was here last week, sketching some very pretty ponds in rear of the house.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">This is a dull little town; a real Sleepy Hollow. To day, I have heard Independence proclaimed only by two little boys with penny trumpets, and one boy beating a tin kettle, to the tune of Yankee Doodle.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Even that celebration seemed to me too good for such independence as ours.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I wonder what 1860 will bring forth? I have very little confidence in the Republican party; but their position is such that they can not advance their own interests, without doing some good to our cause. How I do wish the Southern States would take themselves off, as they are always threatening ! If we could only throw off that incubus, then we should have a republic, as is a republic. Gabriel, the great trumpeter, might be proud to celebrate its birth, and the Four and Twenty Elders think it no shame to tune their Golden Harps to Yankee Doodle. God speed the day!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Miss Parmenter told me she saw you in Worcester, and that you spoke affectionately of me. Thank you. I always think affectionately of you.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Very cordially your friend, L. Maria Child.</field>
      <field name="title_display">Letter to Mr. Higginson, 1859 July 4</field>
      <field name="title_facet">Letter to Mr. Higginson, 1859 July 4</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">letter to mr higginson 1859 july 4</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">Letter to Mr. Higginson, 1859 July 4</field>
      <field name="year_display">1859</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1859</field>
   </doc>
</add>