<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">John P. Lightner</field>
      <field name="author_facet">John P. Lightner</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">john p lightner</field>
      <field name="author_text">John P. Lightner</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy_mss/uvaBook/tei/brand_letters/A9621.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">University of Virginia Civil War Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">University of Virginia Civil War Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">John P. Lightner to Kate Armentrout, October 31, 1861</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:502783</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">John P. Lightner to Kate Armentrout, October 31, 1861</field>
      <field name="note_display">Source copy consulted: William Brand Papers, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="note_display"/>
      <field name="note_text">Source copy consulted: William Brand Papers, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="note_text"/>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="heading_text">Oct. 31 st 1861</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Oct. 31 st 1861 Centerville My Friend;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">It is with pleasure do I take my pen to answer your elaborate epistle, which I received through the hands of our soldier &amp; hero Mr J. Hayse. It need not be told you that it was received &amp; perused with great pleasure as I consider it a pleasure to read letters from all my friends, who manifest such a deep interest in the welfare &amp; safe return of our soldiers as you do. I am tolerable well at present, but not as well as I have been. I never had better health than I had two or three weeks ago. Have fattened so much you would hardly recognize me, if I were to meet anywhere away from home. I think you might come down &amp; see us all, while we are living in peace &amp; quietude. The indications for a battle are very faint; according to my way of judging. We will soon be strongly fortified here, and I hardly think the Yankees will attack us so strongly fortified, since they are afraid to "show us fight" in an open field. We had a grand display of the Va Vols yesterday evening. Gov. Lecher was present &amp; presented to each Va Regiment, the Virginia Colors, with a short speech exorting them to never let her be dishonored, while in their charge. All the Generals with in reach, were present on the memorable occasion.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Governor delivered his address, standing upon one of our newly erected forts.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Gov. is going to have a grand review of the troops this evening, I wish you could attend, it would be something romantic to you especially. I saw some ladies on the field yesterday evening, to see what was to be seen &amp; heard. This part of the country is nearly destitute of ladies &amp; citizens generally, some have united their destiny with that of the Yankees &amp; some with the Southerners.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I suppose you have heard that the Company to which I belong, has been detailed as a permanent guard at Gen. Smith's headquarters.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">We were detailed the 2 nd day of Oct. The time passes much more pleasantly in that position than it did when we were with the Regiment, withs notwithstanding our guard is very heavy.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I've gotten so used to Camp life, I feel as well contented here, and probably better than I would be if I were at home or College. One of my Classmates came down yesterday to see us all. From the news he gave of College I would not like to be there very much. Only one of my Class returned, Lacy from New Kent County. I hope he will have a big time of it. He graduates this year, if he studies pretty hard. You spoke to me something about W m Brand &amp; what I thought of him generally. I have not associated with him a great deal since he is in a separate Regt from myself, but from what I have seen of him or even heard, raised him in my estimation a great deal. His moral deportment without a reasonable doubt is impeachable . I have never seen or heard of his association with the gambler, swearer, or drunkard, or rather I should use participation instead of association, for we are all bound by necessity to associate with men of all ranks &amp; classes. To speak the truth, I have never heard of any action in his life, that would cast a shame &amp; reproach upon his professions. I don't know whether this will be satisfactory to you or not. I have asked no one with regards to him, but speak from my own observations.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">This war I believe is designed to bring out the characters of men, &amp; it certainly has brought out his by this time, &amp; I consider it a good one. I was very sorry to hear of the death of my old schoolmate Miss Sallie M c Cadden, and also others with whom I was acquainted, but speaking from your statement with regard to them, their parents &amp; friends loss was their eternal gain. That disease seems to have been more fatal this season, than I've ever known it to be. But all these things must needs be &amp; we should submit &amp; that, willingly. The suffering of our army in the west has certainly been very intense. But I still hope &amp; trust it will be all over by next Spring, at the same time I see the tide of war rising more fearful &amp; terr if ying than ever. I have no news to write to you that would interest you in the least.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I got some of the cake &amp; cheese you sent to your brother. It was very nice, &amp; accept of my thanks for it. Well I must close, give my love to any you choose, &amp; write to me soon again.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Remember me to be your ever true Friend &amp; Schoolmate Jno. P. Lightner Direct to Manassas Junction until further orders, would not be surprised if we did not go to the valley again.</field>
      <field name="heading_text">Envelope</field>
      <field name="title_display">John P. Lightner to Kate Armentrout, October 31, 1861</field>
      <field name="title_facet">John P. Lightner to Kate Armentrout, October 31, 1861</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">john p lightner to kate armentrout october 31 1861</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">John P. Lightner to Kate Armentrout, October 31, 1861</field>
      <field name="year_display">1861-10-31</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1861</field>
   </doc>
</add>
