<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Mark Twain, pseud. Samuel Langhorne Clemens</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Mark Twain, pseud. Samuel Langhorne Clemens</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">mark twain pseud samuel langhorne clemens</field>
      <field name="author_text">Mark Twain, pseud. Samuel Langhorne Clemens</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy_mss/uvaBook/tei/misc/Twa1Toa.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">The Regular Toast. Woman—God Bless Her [a machine-readable transcription]</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:501883</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English 
</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English 
</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English 
</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Regular Toast. Woman—God Bless Her [a machine-readable transcription]</field>
      <field name="note_display">Print copy consulted: Original manuscript in Special Collections, University of Virginia Library: Papers of Mark Twain 1862-1946, bulk 1872-1910; 6314; AMs 1891 May.</field>
      <field name="note_display">This toast was delivered at the Annual Dinner of the New England Society of New York, at Delmonico's, on 22 December 1882. Twain added the signature at the end of the manuscript, with the unusual complete use of Langhorne, almost ten years after giving this toast, presumably when he made a present of the manuscript to someone.</field>
      <field name="note_text">Print copy consulted: Original manuscript in Special Collections, University of Virginia Library: Papers of Mark Twain 1862-1946, bulk 1872-1910; 6314; AMs 1891 May.</field>
      <field name="note_text">This toast was delivered at the Annual Dinner of the New England Society of New York, at Delmonico's, on 22 December 1882. Twain added the signature at the end of the manuscript, with the unusual complete use of Langhorne, almost ten years after giving this toast, presumably when he made a present of the manuscript to someone.</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="heading_text">Delivered at New England Dinner Dec 20/82. — th Regular Toast. Woman — God bless her.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The toast includes the sex, universally: it is to Woman, comprehensively, wheresoever she may be found. Let us con- sider her ways. First, comes the matter of dress. This is a most important consideration, in a subject of this nature, &amp; must be disposed of before we can intelligently proceed to examine the profounder depths of the theme. For text, let us take the dress of two antipodal types — the savage woman of C entral Africa, &amp; the cultivated daughter of our high modern civilization. Among the Fans, a great negro tribe, a woman, when dressed for breakfast, or home, or to go to market, or go out a pick-up dinner, or to sit at home, or to go out calling, or to a simple or to take a simple tea with friends &amp; neighbors, or to go out calling, does not wear anything at all but just her complexion. That is all; that is her entire outfit. It is the lightest cos- tume in the world, but is made of the darkest material. It has often been mistaken for mourning. It is the trimmest, &amp; neatest, &amp; grace- fulest costume that is now in fashion; it wears well, is fast colors, doesn't show dirt; you don't have to send it down town to wash, &amp; have some of it come back scorched with the flat-iron, &amp; some of it with the buttons ironed off, &amp; some of it petrified with starch, &amp; some of it chewed by the calf, &amp; some of it rotted with acids, &amp; some of it exchanged for other customers' things that haven't any virtue but holiness, &amp; don't fit you anyhow, &amp; ten-twelfths of the pieces over- charged for, &amp; the rest of the dozen stolen "mislaid." And it always fits; it is the perfection of a fit. And it is the handiest dress in the whole realm of fashion. It is always ready, always "done up." When you call on a Fan lady &amp; send up your card, the hired girl never says, "Please take a seat, madam is dressing — she will be down in three-quarters of an hour." No, madam is always dressed, always ready to receive; &amp; before you can get the door-mat before your eyes, she is in your midst. And the hired girl never has to say to a lady visitor, "Please excuse madam, she is undressing;" &amp; even if she ever had to bring such an excuse at all, she wouldn't say it in that way: she would say, "Please excuse madam, she's skins, not herself!" Then again, the Fan ladies don't go to church to see what each other has got on; &amp; they don't go back home &amp; describe it &amp; slander it. The farthest they ever go is to say some little biting thing about the ultra fashionables</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Such is the dark child of savagery, as to every-day toilette; &amp; thus, curiously enough, she finds a point of contact with the fair daughter of civilization &amp; high fashion — who has often has "nothing to wear;" &amp; thus these widely separated types of the sex meet upon common ground. Yes, such is the Fan woman, as she appears in her simple, unostentatious every- day toilette. But on state occasions she is more dressy. much more dressy. At a banquet she wears wears bracelets; at a lecture she wears earrings &amp; a belt; at a ball she wears stockings — &amp; with the true feminine fondness for display, she wears them on her arms; at a funeral she wears a jacket of tar &amp; ashes; at a wed- ding the bride who can afford it puts on pantaloons. Thus the dark child of savagery &amp; the fair daughter of civilization meet once more upon com- mon ground; &amp; these two touches of nature make their whole world kin.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Now we will consider the dress of our other type. A large part of the daughter of civilization is her dress — as it should be. Some civilized women would lose half their charm without dress; &amp; some would lose all of it. The daughter of modern civilization, dressed at her utmost best, is a marvel of exquisite &amp; beautiful art, &amp; ex- pense. All the lands, all the climes, &amp; all the arts are laid under tribute to furnish her forth. Her linen is from Belfast, her robe is from Paris, her lace is from Venice, or Spain, or France; her feathers are from the remote regions of Southern Africa, her furs from the remoter home of the iceberg &amp; the au- rora; her fan from Japan, her diamonds from Brazil, her bracelets from California, her pearls from Ceylon, her cameos from Rome; she has glass gems &amp; trinkets from buried Pompeii; &amp; others that graced comely Egyptian forms that have been dust &amp; ashes, now, for forty centuries; her watch is from Geneva, her card-case is from China, her hair is from — from — I from the store, I believe. That I don't know where her hair is from; I never could find out. That is, her other hair — her public hair, her Sunday hair; I don't mean the hair she goes to bed with. Why, you ought to ought to know the hair I mean; it's that thing which she calls a switch, &amp; which resembles a switch as much as it resembles a brickbat, or a shotgun, or any other thing which you correct people with. It's that thing which she twists, &amp; then coils round &amp; round her head, beehive- fashion, &amp; then tucks the end in under the hive &amp; harpoons it with a hairpin. And that reminds me of a trifle: any time time you want to, you can glance around the carpet of a Pullman car &amp; go &amp; pick up a hairpin; but not to save your life can you get any woman in that car to acknowledge that hairpin. Now isn't that strange? But it's true. The woman who has never swerved from cast-iron veracity &amp; fi- delity in her whole life, will, when confronted with this crucial test, deny her hair- pin. She will deny that hairpin before a hundred witnesses. I have stupidly got into more trouble, &amp; more hot water trying to hunt up the owner of a hairpin in a Pullman car than by any other indiscre- tion of my life.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Well, you can see what the daugh- ter of civilization is, when she is dressed; &amp; you have seen what the daughter of savagery is when she isn't. Such is Woman, as to costume. I come, now, to consider her in her higher &amp; nobler aspects — as sister, mother, sweetheart, sister, daughter wife, widow, neighbor, poor relation grass-widow, mother- in-law, woman's-rights skir- misher, platform-reader, actress, hired girl, tele- graph operator, telephone helloer, store clerk, washer-woman, school- marm, queen, queen, book-agent, wet- nurse, step-mother, boss, pro- fessional fat woman, pro- fessional double-headed woman, professional beauty, &amp; so forth &amp; so on.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">We will simply discuss these few — let the rest of the sex wait tarry in Jericho till we come again. First in the list, of right, &amp; first in our gratitude, comes a woman who — why, without whom, I ask you, where would be those priceless treasures without which are all that make our lives worth the living. Yes, where would be our wives &amp; chil- dren if there hadn't been any mother-in-law? She — why, dear me, I've been talking three-quarters of an hour! I beg a thousand pardons. But you see, yourselves, that I had a large contract. I have accom- plished something, anyway: I have introduced my subject; &amp; if I had till next Forefather ' s' Day, I am satisfied that I could discuss it as adequately &amp; appreciatively as a so gracious &amp; noble a theme de- serves. But as the matter stands, now, let us finish as we began — &amp; say, without jesting, but with all sincerity, "Woman — God bless her!"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Mark Twain Samuel Langhorne Clemens Hartford, May 1891.</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Regular Toast. Woman—God Bless Her</field>
      <field name="title_facet">The Regular Toast. Woman—God Bless Her</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">regular toast woman god bless her a machine readable transcription</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">The Regular Toast. Woman—God Bless Her</field>
      <field name="year_display">1882</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1882</field>
   </doc>
</add>